Hi there Welcome to the
906 podcast brought to you by ggv capital on the show we interview movers and shakers
China's tech industry as well as Tech leaders who have a us China
Cross-border perspective on Stone, managing partner at ggv Capital and I've been working at startup
Invest in them in both the US and China for the past 20 years my name is
I meant investment analyst igb capital and a former journalist
Why is the show called 96 Chinese Founders have organically
Adopted that is 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
Cool us996 captures intensity Drive
In speed
Of Chinese internet companies many which are moving faster that even their American counterparts
On the show today we have David Lee or Leigh Shilling in Chinese
Who's the founder and CEO of YY one of the first live streaming Platforms in China
They went public on the NASDAQ in 2012 and is now a multi-billion-dollar company
YY also owns who are the leading game streaming platform in China which went public on New York Stock Exchange
Dismay
David is also the co-founder and CEO of the singapore-based
Bigo which is the leading live streaming platform is Southeast Asia
Four founding white in 2005
David served as an editor-in-chief and netease
And before that founded a website a provided a copyright trading platform for journalists and photographers
David received a bachelor's degree in Philosophy from Remy University of China
In 1997
Chili's lucky to Kauai as a performer company
In our Benson Potter Jamie Lee
I was on the border wife for 7 years
Height
Shooting David welcome to the show
Thank you
You and I have known each other for
More than
10 years
The first time I met you was March 2000
When I came
To visit
To talk to you about boy
And the through you as you met Beijing
I brought it up because
Of this past 10 year.
Many things have changed
In China
And you personal
So as you go by
The last
10 years
What are the things that struck up to you as Turning Point
In your life
And also in the revolution
Yeah I seem to the the most important changing point is from the
Why why is tablets
Before why why we
Weber Vista company
But where is the media
Yeah and if iyya launch till we are changing
Enchilada sauce or a basement company
And we are doing summer
Social platform
Anderson Community
Business
It's a total
Different kinds of business
I think
That very little company care
Change it from the website
Website company
Software company I drive time
As a media company there's not much technology
Is your not software technology
As a media company there's more of a sling app help
Many journalists and Mediacom the World by his friend looking for answer
How to grow
How did you decide that
Becoming
Technology-driven
Software
Platform infill social networking
Uniform of white
How did you come to that
Decision
And how did you make it
Because I do not make myself so that certain character
Yeah and before I established
Launch YY company I'm a journalist so
But after three years I abandon to
To be a Jedi
I never write article since they're okay yeah and I think I cannot
Alive
For all my whole life
So I created that
Yeah I do not write an article myself
Regret
The other ones live longer
Believer Levi
But after that begin to join the the evening out of company
I begin to think I will
Maribea added her again
But those are so who are netease
Yin sulfur
So I changed my mind job description
Yeah so I've heard that I never added
Evolve
When it was founded
I'm very professional.
Aprilaire Eliza very difficult
So when I leave the night is begin to
Launch the door so I think I will never
News business
Because the night is Ian Charter off of the opposable buses the mainly part of the polls
The news
But when I restart my business
We would do nothing
Related always nails
Yeah we are related to entertainment
But yeah
So when do I grow grow up as a wee wee wee touch the summer
Sitting we are sinking to change it to another kind of company I got time
When I when we decided to
Driving through the
Software
Santeria
Where have no engineer
I'll also be
Also rides
Java
Yeah we have no no wise understand C plus plus
Yeah
This is situation we decided
Change hour
Company into a brand new area
Yes. Time always separate on money
Wake me up about 2
10% of the money to the website business
90% off of
Remind me money in New business
Anyone dying wish will not help
Happy
How do you find the new Engineers Hollywood
Recruitment Nugent we recruit them brand-new engineer's
Two slobs a business
Yeah the only people
Move the from the other business to new business is myself
Oh yeah so I tried the new business and
Rick rule the people from The Arrow
I understand.
Bossip
Fortunately
Yeah to find a very good partner
His name is Angel and
Basalt
Because I Got High
He is
Working for five years for that is under
The right the soft surrounding the pawpaw
Papa is a second the law to the instant messenger in China
Battery different from each other
Sleo II Olajuwon tender
Chica cantando user
Is the 1 million
Budget
Papa was basing
Guangzhou
What kinda the same city
Yeah yes
Yeah so when I asked her to
Central to Jaja joyous yeah
Drive time
It is lucky so we joined together to start
The business
And that we we we recruited by Melvin a very very talented people at a time
Yeah it's very lucky because we know nothing about that
After 10 years
The list you'll be there
Faster people
You got there
.
How do you transform yourself from a writer or editor could you also did
Philosophy in college so very much in a Humanity Society to its success what internet entrepreneur and
Leading a tech company
I think because I start a philosophy in University
Yeah that's the best of scenes.
Is that a philosophy is that you
Cannot find a job
The first day I joined the University
They tell me you cannot find a job after I graduated
So you must help yourself to find the time away to survive
Right now I know why you're so argumentative
My wife
Because if you are you you want to survive
We are leaving
Philosophy
Yasso
The philosophies of what we are sorry but we are around to living
Where we are working for living we should learn something very different
Yeah
So how did you land your first job
Methods Java is accident
Philosophy major
Yeah it really a accident
Of a newspaper
Yeah I know what am I trying to the internet they tell me they will know they gave me a job chance
Yeah Justa internship
But when I was looking for that internship
I'm meeting some people from the other
Other newspaper
Yeah we we talked a lot and
Shay Shay tell me that's the way we need article
About King Saul
Do you want to ride article about King Saul
Yes I started a catalog
7000 word
Population population
As you know it's very difficult because of the newspaper do not have
So much
So I'm a traffic probably should I got to 300
Ohio Lottery
I forgot
Also no job
Offer for the fourth annual
It is about what we all graduated from July in China
It's a mad I just already met
Everybody
I did her off the newspaper
Call Ma
Friend if you don't have phone I asked you not to ask for a b b b b
Yasso
Job opportunity for me because
Someone quit
Computer types
What was the name of the newspaper again
Very famous newspaper
Everybody in the
The University of Redlands
Because
The guy article the article $40 us for
How long did it take you to write
So I got
How long does it take to write an article
Oh maybe one week
Are you the one with the weather
So
What made you decide
It was time to leave journalism and what was specifically attracted to you about the internet
Because I love technology very much in love
University
Because I do not have any job that chance so I I will find the truth
First timer in Tbilisi
Levi's
City University of helps the
Is that time all computer are very expensive
You are very special room
Yeah you know show to buy tickets
ORS ticket
But to to use it
Got it
That time you know that's a No-No services for the computer to
Lola likes
Let me hear you restart automatically
That's a no such function so
Many students
Trying to do things on the computer
Solis crash.
My computer crashed
How many miles to me
So I find the last chance I fix it to fall further
Teacher apps free
From that time and I learn lots of computers
Technology
And what led you to join Soho
The first internet job
I asked John to Soho only for
Full form of
Yes
Why
Because we're a drawing does the Soho they gave gave me a job
The two in charge of the
It Channel
Channel 4 News
We're about to the I find it that's how
Like I have a very
Palantir
Alright 18 that Chan
But yeah
So I promoted
Jim to
And when I find that I will
Re monster
I will be the first
Oppressive
Fastest route to home
What's the fastest growing
Yuan
Amazon all channels
Yeah
So I'm very lucky so I do not go to go work everyday
Realizing you're very good so they had to play games
So my boss finally is very very very strange that I do not to go go off
We women testosterone
The office Maybe
Walmart
They asked me what do you want to do because
Pistol
Walking my red hot
I said I find a very good person
Got it hunted the daddy
Hockey down
And not supposed to ask me what to do
Because I'm already the 1st at 1
Homemaker the Channel girls
Do you have two options
About me emoji
Good morning
So they say it's okay I will giving you a new channel
Yeah it is channel maybe it's okay
That's awful give you to give me a chance
Gave me once I might I'm sorry
I want to
That I don't know
The market
Yeah
So I ain't giving people
The final
I got time
So I fly to Guangzhou console to talk
Christina how about
Give me business
How
Cancel Hulu
Service
Services
Hyundai
Bath after Maybe
4 Farwell Street
Do you want to join that
Give all the possible control to you
Guitar portal
Eros
Easy way to college in Beijing
What is journalist for
Hobby 560
EBay
That you weren't so cool for 4 months
You just pick up your bags and move to Guangzhou just like that
Yes yes
What made you a box one box
You do you like me challenge
Imagine all the titles
I never lived before
But that didn't stop you
Yeah
By that time I have a car in Beijing do you know
I have a
Sea turtle
So well I'm boxed away with me to fly to Guangzhou to
To gather new job
Young
Jupiter
We're all quite famous
Monopoly
Who were the other three again
You are one of them
All generous
Yeah
Unfortunately
YMCA
Lee Orion
Okay.
So you give up on this
To leave Beijing
Center of universe
You tied up with internet
Lyndonville news
Route 2
Because it is I have a very big opportunity
So as even forgotten to talk about the salary
You just want the responsibility
So what am I drawing tonight is awful.
What's my salary
Icc's
Because it's
This year
Opportunity to get to the options
Sony jasticon cast
Accelerator
So I asked her how my cash
It's the same to you
More responsibility
Got it
Actually I got time I already found a business
I already told her payment
About to
25 *
Pronounce
About to
And now he's only gave me
I-15 south
So I lost the 10000
So how long did you work there
Lessons and takeaways
Experience
Oh I work for the night is full
3 years
Kahoot login
Oh I unhappy
Any joint
Netease Insignia in
Well not easily weinhofer
Lights on the three drawing
Laughter
Susanoo
Mets
July 2000
Free
And then the major
So
Almost
20 months
Were you a gamer yourself
Yes I play games very often because I have enough time
Study of The Who
What made you leave Daddy
Would you want to do
When I'm at least you can also know that because you not is Ivar walking
Funneh is my my Bosa
Give me
PBI
30%
Bruce
Yeah oh yeah
Yeah I got time I do not know what's mean the keep your ass
I never worked for English
What's up
Miles heizer I do not know
Caillou I cannot come like that that I keep you
Yeah but I will walk him out
Had to do that
After 1 year
Completed
A gross of Bowser 16 times
Well one six times
Off.
Love love love traffic
16 * 5
Yeah
Yes
Hardee's
Because I last time I seen
It's not a simple icing
Justina is a
The leading the leading Neosporin
Very serious or seriously
Yasso
We reposition ourselves into a
A news media more concerned that we all
Daily life
Official personality
You're fun
And you look at Alamo
Thanks
And so I can see.
Reflects your personality
Yes under eyes I time I decided
Make make a decision that
La carmencita aparts off news
Online users comments is a part of a noose
Not not not not not not
Different power off
So we combined all the comments and the News together
The first one
Even even today
Is
What's the deal
That that is
Lip reading the comments
Very well written
High quality ice quality
Let's begin like
When you started
Why why it was held to a wine right
And it was a
Online game web portal
Alphagamers for communication and community school for gamers
Sort of like Discord in the US so why did you pick this particular Market
Why the gamers
Because I got time II single weekend
We cannot see
We we can come up with an that n**** with Cena
That's very difficult to xidan Cena
Yeah
I seen that if we want to
Being a bigger media
That's enough for next the 5-year Swisher
We should
Do something different from sing
I got time to call Cena I always focus on media is Shelf
I see no I would rather not to focus on media is self I will
Focus on
Information business
So I plan the two
Ambassador
4 channels
As
Gaming real estate
Osmo mobile
And
Information technology
So I want to immerse the
40 frontal Channel and make this channel independent brand
Anda
We would provide those services
For the readers not news for the Raiders only
Yeah
The bus company they do now to love
Chance to persuade
Company to do that
So I want to tell them
I can't wait
With my own money
Not only because
The company you were asked to mount it was as business I want to look
Even if there's no no money I can use my own money
Amassment
That doesn't
So after that
Aleve
The company
Yeah 22 South Sahara
Gamers
Why did you choose that market
Because ask for for for twice
Yeah I haven't
Same time
So actual swan
Guinea
Release date
Wilson real estate give me a real estate
Auto
And the
Hiding from
Real estate
Auto
Is more
Duvall people doing it
Your personality
Fits to
Gaming
Burberry
And it'll help with the Bell Adrian Adrian
January
Recommend to do in France
Well he's a guy so
So we wait to give me Frost
Yeah
Did you guys meet each other at the tunnel.
We know Legion car wash
But it was after that
FBI website
Master
Are you guys excited
To work together
Tucson
Why did you call the accompany YY
Is the Chinese name is Tianjin
Wish means
Why why is the Frame of the Chinese
Ivory not as of yet
Okay
So I started out as a voice chat
Moisture has watched
And how did the product evolve
Overtime
Alpharetta is automatically yeah because all people in my office
Playing games afterwards and then we end our works at a 9 p.m.
And that way you can
To play games together to the midnight
So we are not talking to each other and the plains
Game together loll company play gaming together
Yeah so we find it at
Some people are on all the in the office
They are very difficult to
Communicative
We Finance be refunded that you guys
Accused
Yeah is also from the idea
Initialize that we do not want to only provide information
We want to provide services
Yeah
So we find it
You so very sheet
Huge demand for that service is so we change the from in the
News media are media into a services
Social Services
I remember all the people trying to do this
I speak
Executed
You went out at 4
End up being the most
Wait we move the very very earlier
But we we do not have a
Tagamet
We found the other other people a green virus
So we decided to move
90%
So how did you think about monetization
And if you were a consumer face
In the beginning
Text a lot of people worried that they're saying up at me.
The Westlake
Sword
Summit
Alibaba started
In mm
5ever
But
E-commerce
Virtual
Beach Chamber
What is your experience with virtual item
It's because I'm a journalist I write articles articles and
Iran media
Yeah I hate that you caused me to do two things
The first is a
Describes a user
Experience
And the second is
They want to change how I just hurry up principles
Yeah I think those two things is too bad
Yeah
And as I know
US is Colin Farrell from the I don't know
Department
An editorial
But I seen that do not want to do that kind of person
Yo-yo master
Have yourself into two parts
Good business
Bisimoto I want to channel the media space mode
Xcel Energy
So how did you make it virtual
Google
For voice
Messaging
Ace Hardware
People in the West
Imagine
By the time I do not want to build a business
Because we have many many men pets
Operated
Jamie Oliver
That's my plan media manager
They are repeated very very old business model the newspaper
Reason magazine
But how did you make virtual Goods
Work
For you
As among the states
It works it's not works I do not know that
Bisimoto
I know exactly apus mode off
I'm a gaming platform icon wrong
Gene Messer
So I can't get enough
Refuge
Revenue from Kimmy at that time
Yeah yeah
Publish new games
And some games are time-based
Charge fees for the
Or some of it
Within the games
Yeah we did wrong Damien business ourselves
So we do not get me out of attachment to other other company
Yeah if you want to get his money from
Promise on our platform
Ukvi
Game 212
We we we we were operated
As you know many many media manager that do not want to touch the
Real busy
With the operation
Newspaper
Operation operation
I want to because I know
Send volume of traffic
Baidu
How do I pass smog
I think it's only
Maybe I can
100 dollars
Spotify wrong
Gave me myself and I will get to
Is 5 *
Actually it's five
When you first start monetizing you were doing it from
Operating your own games
We're out
Then
How did you
Besides
Virtual
Good skiff
The gifting
What's 2 + how big
Whenever whenever thinking about that
Yeah because I decided that time many people are awesome songs uyy platform
They were singing songs
Yeah they seeing sounds
Wee Wee Sing
Can we
Rank
Athena
We do not know
Because people always find it at the bet her finger
How can we rent those cigarettes
So we
True why the fridge
Voting rights
Arie users
Why is voting right man vote
Vermont
So you want models you only got one ball
2 is free
Yokai only got one okay yeah and after Maybe
Two or three Montessori refund
Many many many people sell those photos
Under the table all prices in is
2.25 Yuan
Supervisor movie
Yeah
Yeah and it's very bad it's why our platform because there's many many
Trying to steal user account
Yeah Yeahs trying to use many ways to
Gather user accounts together
Yeah
And the
So
We want to
Compare the ways that hackers so I decided to sell the vote
On our own
Honda
Wait wait wait drop the money to 1y rmb
Sole they sell 2.5 rmb
Safeway
Yeah so
I thought Year we will we have a budget for
4 million RMB Revenue
From the sell-off of the boats
Yes but actually we call to
F****** mean
40 man tent house
Selling boats
Justice Alan Walker
Is there a limit on how many votes people can buy
Because of you feeling Limited
Livio
Stolen
What was the most amount of
Boats old
Naughty
Antarctica
40 minutes
Ms total
Per-user
Provide
What would you remember
Because we just along to
Make the
Make a
Hackley Bauer plus sizes
Sing is a very big as Revenue
Operation games
Today
Yeah
Dana how did you move from votes to gifting like virtual Goods
Like
Flower
Flowers
Race cars or
Ebenezer natural grocer
Because the people safe to vote I voted I want to see the singer see I have already voted
I called you for your vote
You be able to
What's the most expensive icon
Best diffuser ever bought a gift
I forgot
I don't care
How much is the race car
I do not know
That's just as much as I got a million rmb
Good spot
And gift it
1 million arm
Is what I've heard
I don't care about Revenue
Sew-in 27
Auntie NYY derive 92% of its revenue from
Live streaming
Could you talk about your view on the live streaming Market both in
China and the US
And how
Develop differently
I think the last streaming business is very huge in the future
If you cost
As you know
No TV
Interactive with a single person
Yeah
So is audience
Each Weaver's can you evolve into a program are you been
Yeah that's very important that's what a difference
From the
Computing computer to TV
Engaged
2 today
EZ Wheels steel go chlorine very fast
Why do you think the virtual Goods model
Really took off in China before I did in the US
Atlanta
I do not know is a bigot
Excuse
Business Revenue model
So how did you first meet Jenny
Legion introduced the Jenny to me
What to do tok
When you first met
Present time our Revenue
Growing out another narcissist uses green
On the way believe if we operate a game
Provide ourselves that we we
Gas Revenue finals
Medicine ball
It's emergency. Investing white and ucweb
IMessage xiaomi
So
Together we have
Empower portfolio
The best
Major Asian companies
Obviously ritual for Morningside has all
It's very true
As we all know any content of a media company in China has to
But here to Chinese government regulations
And
How much resources does Weis spend on regulating its content
To make sure
Ice Age
We are working very hard to try to
Titan management silicon
Tuna icing is very simple
Because
Yeah technology
Bruins
Very very fast are we doing Barrel Associates
But just to leave the machine to do that
NYY went public
In New York in 2012
There had been a decrease in Chinese IPOs in the US
So in 2010 there were
41 Chinese IPOs
In the US and in 2011 there were 12
I mean 2012 before while I went public they're happy only one which is Vip Shop
So why did you choose to go public at this particular time
Icing good for Google CEO
You should not focus on revenue is not focus on the market price
Yeah I seen but when we feel this company we just the
Want to provide a kinds of the
Information on a service
We want to provide information thesaurus
Waverton I want to make a money
Too much
Weight loss focus on making big money
Make money from Marshall gift we just want to provide a free world
Yeah so I think it for the most important things for me is to
Who decides
What should weight be
After maybe five years 10 years
How does this
Come back to today
And the state
What's the stats
The first step should I go
Totoro
You're one of them very very few
China Buffet
Start multiple
Companies and then have them
List
Now you start why why
Listen.
Spin-off puya
Both of them are out of
A golden dollar
USM
The Stuka
And you also spend off of
For selfies
We are War 4
China
Explain your strategy
Why these three
When I have all them
If one company
And in
What is your thoughts on
Joe profit
Ben Shapiro
Icing
Each
Cool companies
Smirnoff Manna business hours
Is a whale a craft business into a
Berry picking
Good company to get them all at the Vintage
Yeah but we waste being off the
Pico and we are
Is
Because of the way
Meet some problems
I look weird because we needed
Corporation wisdom
Yeah
Wait wait wait
Why why we're paying attention or attention
Yasso
Is very difficult
212 bus to carburetor
By the way is different
We find a way to
Spinoff
We are undone
Black we are to have a carburetor Winston said it's very important for the
Competition
How's the weather
This is different from the way
Depending on the content
You for the keeping company they do not a carburetor with us
Well very difficult
To to do things
Yeah
People who don't know why we are asked
Explain
What does a PR do
I think we are being hunted
Live streaming
Area
Yeah but after it's gross gross
Again
Responded
We will be a total solution
Esports
Online stopwatch
So when we find this week very very huge American
And presents a large
Just get publisher
I have an idea that's
Not the media other than Sports
Selective media
It's a media
Chilaquiles
Lesbians if you have newspaper
Maybe you'll cast apart of some kind of oil for the Swap Force
If you have a television
You can maybe supported get rights to Brock
Yes you'll cancel part of the stalker see you guys tomorrow
Newspaper maybe Newcastle part of the goal
Chess
Yeah
Zoso
Bieber the media make a difference
So icy
In the
Internet
Online unlikely me all all I'm broke costume
Will make a different kinds of
Popular
Yeah
After maybe five years we are they see
The lives live broadcast the office gaming is a a part of Kimmy
But you cannot separate the two things anymore
Kimmy on the Canadian broadcasting is combined together a better BP become a very cute
People with very good at playing games
Two-player games
I like to watch
With this chain and the tencent also say this
The basis for yes
Collaborate
Do it if we do not properly to
Who is tencent weibo fireworks
Yeah by the way we think we only got to the live abroad look at me bro costume
We we do not have the time to build up so much
Game
The prison have kittens he also need a Kimber custom II
Yeah so maybe seven people say is that
Maybe
Since I need a timer
I came in Broadcasting Company combined together as a casino
Hayneedle all the gaming company combined
Toby has similar business model
High School
Twitch
Is the market big enough
You have both the W end
We are
No I asking the finally finally situation is a tencent game
Combine lowest WF we are together as a whole
As one big company to company on this company wheel
Also to stewing to make famous and fasting
The NBA teams under your own ESPN
You'll make all those things together are you a very powerful ecosystem
Interesting
Yeah that that that's the real
That sucks
Just know that
That's how you feel
Exactly
Interesting fact
And just to give some contacts in Q4 2017
We are head 610000 monthly active
Streamers which was more than the 550000 at twitch had
And China is by far the largest gaming Esports marking the world with approximately
Over 200 million gamers in 2017
And the market is
Expected to reach
537 million Gamers spy 2022
And the market brought in over a hundred million dollars in Revenue last year
So going forward do you think the Esports Market will grow faster in China
Elsewhere in the world
I already see that
If you
To look at a single game company
It will never
You can see the skill
All for the gaming platform
Is Jackson lacazette
A single game can nozzle bigger than Steam
Butter icing
After this day
The
Jamie Brook hosting platform is actually the Next Generation off
Best choice
And possibly even
Yes yes
The Disco on the TV and they will combine together
Finally
Two tubular very very
Call Hector powerful
Entertainment Company
So internationalization
Global expansion
What was the motivation
Behind spitting up
Yes because we speaking of people because we want to provide free internet
But this is free now to call it we lost the too much money
I lost to
50 million US dollar in
Lumos
Tool to burn money that business we are already know it does that
That's really my money dependant dependent
But wait wait with me off 8th and the gas money from outside Lemaster
And the trying to print money
Angels Attic
Is a stove burn a lot of money today
No we we stop
Absolutely blooming
50 million US dollar
So how is
What is it doing now
We close at
The Pecos closed
Another phrase for business
It's Grove I regarded as you know in four months we grow from 02
Chameleon
Internet free
I'm free internet
Reenact
So what is it doing
Now that you don't have free internet calls to fast
The first day is
Oh wait to not have too much money
Yeah to Spanish
And we do not have time to build monetization
E. Business
4 miles
From 0 to 10 million
Daily active users
Is amazing
Yasso
What is it what is beagle do today
Free internet calls not offered any
What what is doing
After that business we closed the project yet
So we began what what should we do because of where we are already have. We still have
And maybe
30 million 40 million
Cashing hat
Yeah so
We change the intro
Aurora season
Live streaming
Is Carly
One of the top
10 apps in the social networking category on iOS
Not just seeing Southeast Asian countries but also Saudi Arabia Pakistan New Zealand
If we have are very familiar with lesbians
So are you familiar with those markets
So how did you
Go about
Oso company
If you do
Too much business about culture
You cannot expand it to the world so we do not touch anything
Related to culture
We adjusted to
Scenes
Related to truth
Very very hard on to provide all kinds of chores
What are the most popular forms of
Content
Orichalcos
Contact number
It is also
Weather like in Hawaii Fini
Talkin talkin show
Will you ever
Iyi choir beagle
Well I already have a option to buy deal
Wisdom
Two by 100% or just the control panel
Controllers
That you were that died
Beagle
IPL on Adam
Last time I maybe you one month later master
My self-employment
Omastar
70 minutes
Burning Man
Zoe
Will Debbie go eventually IPO on its own
Or would it be all Choir by
Why why later
I seen the baseball on the evaluation ice in sink Maybe
Why why not have an ability to
Maybe maybe
It is monetization
It's also through
Virtual
Gifting yes
That's
Oppressive
Asia
Whoopi Goldberg
Gold
For the rest of world
Like a lot America Europe
Another places
Already in
Middle East
Maribel Guillen
I think that you'll know China international market
I seen the China invented in TMNT the internet a concept wheel goes
Go overseas
Finally
So where you at just the one off
Now we're going to move on to the quick-fire round of questions the first one is who's at one printer you admire the most
And why
Atom model
I don't know his name
Whether I know what he hell yeah
The founder of Wikipedia
If you cost
Kate build a platform and this platform finally
Benefit
The human beings
Yeah I know he has the same idea with me
He also hate advertisement
Stately hefei food
Yeah yeah that's pissed Moto is very simple is Cash donations Maybe
Open definition
Lincoln
Did you feel you want to donate
We can video you show the way
Apus a beagle is very well design
I have seen many live stream
4 is a lot more variety
Fun things to do
Cya
What's something you read recently
That you
I read a lot of things about 2
Blockchain
Yeah I seen two maybe blotching
Real
Chanda.
Internet landscape
Even
Today is have a bad reputation off long time because all for the ink wrapped currency
Yeah
We we find it at 2
Based on blockchain you can build a brand new platform that's it
Belong to nobody
Wikipedia Wikipedia
No no one can control that no nobody can I own that
No one can get in their self benefit
Yeah so
Is icing good blockchain
Gave the internet new opportunity to build
Different perfume
That weight without working out or hot
What do you do for fun
I think that's a
Each people should
Have a
Long-term Hobby
Yeah because
If you can't do nothing you have a hobby
What's your hobby
I have many coffee
You look mean you gay I love driving motorcycles
So I will chat another one
So motorcycling
Do you like the outdoors
I like a motorcycle license to drive a climbing car
To climb mountains
I like fishing Alexa
I like it
Full show teen
Menacing
Okay
Thank you very much for coming thank you
Thanking him thank you
Airline flight 798
M996 multi-stage Venture Capital firm based in Silicon Valley
Play in Beijing we have been partnering with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past 18 years from seed to pre-ipo
With 6.2 billion dollars in capital under management across 13 funds CGV invest
Consumer new retail social Digital internet Enterprise cloud and Frontier Tech
GTB has invested over 290 companies with more than 45 companies valued at over a billion dollar
Dollars formula companies include Airbnb Alibaba
C trip Didi chuxing demo hashicorp hellobike cows keep
Black square toe towel wish soundtrue white white and others find out
Mouretsu gbc.com we also highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat group as lot Channel
Where we regular bichir insides events and job opportunities related to attack in China join these groups
96.3 gbc.com community
You have any feedback on this podcast or would like to recommend a gas please email us at 996
IGG bc.com