Princess Jasmine welcome to Abington
My dear
Welcome to the 9th at 6 podcast brought to you by ggv capital
On the show interview movers and shakers
China's tech industry
As was Tech leaders
Weather us China
Cross-border perspecta
My name is sandstone, managing partner at GTV capital and I've been working at startup
Investing in them in both the US and China for the past 20 years
My name is Sarah Jones an investment Analyst at ggv Capital and a former journalist
Why is the show called 96 schedule than any Chinese Founders have organically adopt
That is
9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
To us
996 captures intensity Drive
And speed
Of Chinese internet companies many of which
I'm moving faster
But even the American consul
On the show today we have Dora School a marketer and writer who has had an extremely interesting career across the u.s. in
Stars grew up in China and went to the US for
College
Where she attended Bard College in New York
She started her career at Unilever where she worked on brand development
And then join Michael
Courts in New York
Where she was the social Communications manager for 8
In 2015 she left
Michael Kors
To become the head of marketing operations at Ali pay us
Let's just Silicon Valley
In 2017 she returned to China to be
Become the CMO of
The Chinese startup
White closet or ERC
Which is often referred to as the
The Chinese version of Rent the Runway
Who recently left why closet to start her own marketing startup
Troy Alves
She has also been running a WeChat official
With around a hundred thousand followers
Call Doris
Wuxi blogs about the culture
Differences
Between us and China
She doesn't know I started it
China Peak
People pronounce her name
Doris
And by the way
Talk to you a little
I always found this name appropriate
Otter personality
Extremely Sharp
OnPoint
And insightful
Welcome to the show doors
Hi everyone
So you chose a very different
Career path
The vast majority of New Shanghai Chinese students
Study abroad
Most of my friends who won
College in the US
Phone jobs
Finance Consulting or engineering after
For graduation
But you went into fmcg and marketing
Why
A to be honest
One of the reason why it's
Akshay couldn't get
You know it's part, it's not like a big university like Harvard you know yell
So I wasn't really
Jessica School Bus you know famous for our and all of my friends are like really into philosophy
I don't want to be an artist when they graduate so we are not like one of those Target schools
That's actually the real reason and then the second reason is
You know when I was doing internship when I was in college I didn't even
Bother to go to one of those banking jobs
Because I just
Spell like that was rude
Boring to me
Because I asked you when to when
Consulting firms Rosenberg during my junior year and I
I did it with you know Julian Coco
Paperwork
Research on a glass industry
LOL another next year I was doing Coca-Cola internship and I compare the differences is really big
One is you know
Doing number and your crunchy number and you try to analyze industry
On the other hand when I was at Coca-Cola I do consumer research and I changed
The marketing campaigns
Achoo Iris
Peephole song
I feel like I really want to do some job apps
You know making a real
Vs2
Continue my personal Kenya
So that's why I
I chose to do my king
And I went Unilever
Indiana
So when you went to UNI lover you got to turn down a
Write how to do
Decision making
Yes when I decided to go to marketing the street I kind of did a research on what are the
Best companies to go to
Procter Gamble
Daphne
Cubase
Companies that like
Martin
School
So I apply for POC Again by China and the Unilever us
Because
Procter Gamble us couldn't sponsor
H1B for me but you don't leave her
At that time has this Innovative program
Call Shanghai management trainee program in which state
Chinese
People
2 years in us and another year they sent you to China to become a manager vs. inguinal
Tupac again will they just sent you back directly to Guangzhou
And inside debated rehab because
Papageno is my dream company at Unilever in US
That's really attractive
And then I taught you well enough to Unilever director and he gave me this point of view which is really helpful.
Jimmy
Even so now is that
He told me that you know practice Campbell hire like 30 marketers every year so till now they probably already have
Any leave it only hire 10
Chinese in the US to be
Cinemark Theaters in the US
Do you want to be when I would have
501 out of
Your uniqueness is going to Define how valuable you are
So that's why I was like oh yeah that sounds right
Turn down talk again
Heartbroken to turn
I went to
What a reason we have you on the show
Is that you had experience
Marketing
Which is fairly local
Jaja
Domingo
Both you and
So rare
Enough
In a second reason is that
You made it
Call me back
New China
Localizing
Quite a bit of time
Outside of China
So
On those two fronts
How easy is it
How much Leverage
Do you get from
The market
In the US
And then
How to do marketing Inc
How do you
Localizing
We integrate ourselves
Is that so
Great facilities like she asked me.
Actually you don't get a lot of lever
From
And lots of people after working out
Oh my God I should have left earlier
Sorry to be honest my path is a little bit you know I went you Unilever and then I
And then I went to the Chinese culture
That's when I came back to Beijing
2 years ago
What you doing Whitehall that I wasn't really that
You know culture shock
Unilever taught me a lot of you know the systemic structure thinking yours
How you calculated
Call fito.
But in China
The media dafran
Cuz you are so different
And then
The budget is there Frost
How to make videos
And I want to come to Y closet
Sorry
What is budget
Use your mind
So
I think that's the future friends so I really appreciate my
Experience
Us because I got to be
3D structural and as you know plant
Strategic
First in China you just need to be
A flexible and a unit you
Navigate around the resources to get things done so that's very different
So in 2015 you made the move from
New York to the Bay Area
To become the head of Market
Operations alipay us
I recently read the book I beat you to it which means
It's a book about the B2B
ESL team
Alibaba
Forest
Training
Message
An army life
Culture so
6 take away from the book is that this culture will probably be very difficult for
Internationally minded millennials
Because the company puts a lot of emphasis on culture and has a lot of practices are almost military in nature
And doesn't really promote
Sub Express
So what was your impression on the Alley
Culture after
Where were the most
Unexpected things as someone who just moved from
Khaleesi world of New York marketing
Yeah I think that was really memorable.
I'll never forget about that
I think it's great
It's great because the execution of
You know Alibaba is all doing so fast and smooth it's all because. Culture.
Cultivated but it's
It's really hard for me who has no hat the US education
Who has you know I have been trying really hard to
Try to express myself when I went to us
Add on to Alibaba it's like
Reverting back to us
IHOP
A couple of
Really
Memories like a really interesting memories when I was young
First thing is
When I was in New York you know the lifestyle high heels you're like
Head to toe dressed up and then you're like meeting celebrities that was my New York Life
Okay first thing is I went to Silicon Valley you know Silicon Valley New York that's already a big difference
Penske America
So I was like oh my God
Hangzhou
That was another hotel shot so basically have mountain in his teeth
Last second I was in high heels in York and next second I was doing double 12 campaign for hourly pay
And I was told that we were putting
Ribbons on my forehead
And then drinking alcohol and smashed the cups you don't Underground
Lots of drawers
A wall of math
Global map
Find my blood
Yeah and then we will bring the
Lionel slogan t-shirt
Yeah
Some other experiences.
To leave the closer
The market
New York
Too much on Ali
In the cut
Yeah because I think Alibaba is the future
And I'm still come value is also the future when I was saying Michael Kors
I think motor
Traditional marketing
Where is no you get a contact with a celebrity you make a
A fancy video with Palazzo budget behind it and then you
Have lots of
Stores opening
Where is you know I was reading like
From zero to one or growth hacker something like that
And I was seeing you know California are there are so many companies they just
Grow from zero to like
A million
Without any budget and all because
Growth hacking
I was like wow that's
So much difference in a name
And also seeing Alibaba yunnan China there are lots of
Crazy things happening like taobao alipay
So I feel like I shouldn't just you know
Throw myself into this fashion well which everything looks fancy but
I already
I don't eat
Steeda Business Point behind irocs
Sustainable
So I want to learn new things that's why
I went to Ali Baba in California so half the time I can learn growth hacking
From the USA and I have time I can learn the military style
A perfect fit
What was their biggest
Take away four
There are so many takeaways
The first foal I think the culture which you just mention Alibaba is
Really
Interesting like everyone in Alibaba is always super pumped
The Never
Slakoth
Something I never seen before I said I was always
Find you
Seagal how they did that
What's the HR System that you can motivate people like this
I literally remember one of my
Coworker
She just like you
First like a second ago the next I guess you don't think this is like something
Wow what kind of
You know it's hard to come support size
Opso
There's a saying in China
I don't know if
Still works right now it's bite
Pek
When was our marching it's more about
Spending money and how to create the brand awareness and an impression but
It's really about all right
How you make the most impact out of this budget so that's what I learned
Very good
Someone who is
Houston wasp
Welcome to
To go back
Come back to town
Internist
Yeah
I always wanted to go back since the day wasn't right so I made me stay in u.s.
Is because
I feel like us
Angels brand management and marketing
Is way ahead of timeout back then so I wanted to learn
The logistics of marketing
And an Oscar
Couple years on I feel like I already absorbed most
What part of the US
Marketing
On culture and lessons
I really want you
Do something.
You know
Like what I built
Industrial design Michael Kors the brain is already there and all y'all that's already there what I did is that I baste
The take
Make that bread and make it
A little bit better
Maybe
The white closet it's a fresh new idea and Brad nobody knows about it
And I kind of want to prove
Weather I really
You know Irene no marking or Not by
Maybe I should do something from 0 to 1 so I kind of want to
Show my muscle and
Hi-Chew challenge myself again
What is time now in a big
Like Unilever or Michael Kors or Alibaba
But in a platform that nobody knows about without any budget and see what I can achieve
Before you join y classes
So you hadn't been doing
Before
Is you working at
Audi that's doing
Us
And some China
Message
So do you
I think that because
Expressly Michael Kors
Mike Awesome
And because of your training
OtterBox
Help me to get a job
That's before you know
I'm sure that you can do Market
That's actually because my WeChat
I'm very real like I'm not even sure if I can do
Title marketing but
She trusts I can do that. Meyer the founder of my closet
Stella she read my blog I mean my WeChat
Account I was writing a lot about marketing and
Differences between China us how I did marketing
And all that
SUV has distracting me that she's
He's my potential
Hershey's like
Why don't you be mice
CMO and I trust you and she didn't even interview me.
She just say
Yeah come join me
So
I feel like she gave me the trust maybe I can do so
Something
You know big
Together so that's why I join
WeChat account unique
What word is
Things that you
You wrote that
Your followers
Respond to the most
I didn't chew things
A real experience how a Chinese working us
Looks like
The first post that made me popular is
When I rode
My job at my
Michael Kors and being a social Communications manager in New York City fashion wall and being Chinese
So that was like
How I experienced all the culture shock and how I
Struggle and I went past that
So that's really pop
I'm in a second thing is really comparing difference between China us so I wrote about
The difference
Machine
Bloggers
Beijing China us
How did
And how
I finished the first from China in yuan
And all that and right now I'm writing how Beauty bloggers differ from China and us
So I think when I was riding my articles all I was thinking is that what is minus points
People know Judy Place in u.s. on people no Big Lots in China but they don't know the difference
Trend on and how they
Different juices in different worlds I think being someone who is depressed of us and China
What I should bring to the table is sweetie
You'll see the difference and then you know inspired different worlds
How other people are doing the same business
So that's really popular on my
The Chinese world is all about finding what
What's the unique perspective
That you have
They're probably you're not the only Chinese
New York you're the only one who bother to write about it so
Writing
Great response just
Because other people resume
The most people just don't bother to write
Take me to make the effort in
Be disciplined
Keep writing
How to really reward
Yes yes
And then I was actually
When I was doing Michael Kors that was actually the rise of
The year of WeChat
Official plaque
So I really see
The Bennett
The benefit of writing a WeChat and how it got to my
Of course so I was thinking
If I write a blog
Under my name in about my Contin I could also benefit
So that's why it sweetie
Got me motivated to ride
I want one of those
Went when I want to put it out that against all right
Cursive
Do dinosaurs
Ocean shore Hip Hop
And I think
Like you said
If you were willing to
Something or
Do something
And it runs with all the people
Took advantage of
A New Path
Jessie merch
First Student
Also
You are where you are
Open jobs you Mickey
Take
To us
A lot of people don't
Do that they
Events in their career
And
Get better doing something
That he started
It doesn't want to
Track because that's how you get
Rimowa
But having different jobs different
Human require restarting
And we are just
In the long run
Much better Bridge
Right
Easy bread
I don't think so at all
You have to have enough
To be able to
Acrobatics
Redis
Albuquerque
Information is less in
Crate & Barrel
Right
I totally agree
What was the
Things that surprised you the most
There were things that was
Satisfied
Bob
Are you able to make
Well I was really surprised
So I didn't really know how
That's my first job
China
Dewey Martin
And also first time
In a startup
From anal
All before that it was read
So there were many shots so I'm not sure if it's
Is China or the starter
Everytime too many variables so I was shocked that
Lots of cistern are not build
I'm so we don't even have a
No solid
Data Tracking System
So
BCM
Close but they don't know where it comes from
And then
There's not a planning
So they're lost things like that but I really that I found its really, in China and small startups
Well what I really wanted to bill is really feeling
That you're bringing the
The maturity
Just coming from USB at the same time being flexible in China so not you
B2 american-style you still need to be Chinese style so
That was my shock and then
I was reap how because
As a someone who just came from America I was real
I managed to build my own team
And then also I grow the user base
10 *
Amope number user
And iiii
Actually built lots of
Successful campaigns that drive thru
Ross and also brought in the idea of
Growth hacking from the US
Combined with the Chinese style
Which is also called
Which is
Sufficient I don't have the Americans understand.
The witch has to stencil
I was really being able to combine the Western and the used
It turns out that sounds really something I
I think growth
China is
Usually
Heavier than the US
In the US people
Wait for people.
Come where is in China
Yeah I should have some really heavy meal or operation
So
Data in
Contact Improv
Where is in China is like human druid
So
Did you do a lot of
Dad
What do you think
Takeaways
You know the best
Operation standpoint
Frisch's employee I was doing lots of WeChat group management
That's like
Community-based and that's something we'd eat Chinese style is that
Yourbasin YouTube makeup
Poster and then putting the group so that people can make it viral and and inviting more people to
Join the group
Something like that
That's not
Existing in the US
But we also did
Like lots of pockets
In white closet where you refer friend about
50 Yuan or something like that
Or we just invented lots of
The incentive
Would like that you
Motivate
People to share
Where to
Use more
I don't think.
That's very common in us and us you just you don't you have to Rent the Runway you have lots of
Press on the platform and if you
China weihai
Something called Jack
It's like basically address
Coupon
If you have it you can rent one more dress
In your bag
And that's something that we created for Chinese
No budget
How do you say
Deal with that
How do you
Be Scrappy
Creative
Do things without
Oh yeah that's a good question so when I say
I don't have budget I actually me I have limited but it's not like I don't have any
So it's basically
How do you get the
Best Roi out of
So first thing is beauty how you
Get free traffic and then also make the most out of your traffic so for example I will talk to you
Crossword
Fry's employee pay
And then I know they have lots
Traffic and what they need and then
I just talked
To them about a collaboration between black
That's how we got.
Traffic to be honest
And the second thing is when you get the traffic you need to increase conversion rate so with a lot of a b testing
That's also, UF
To see how you really increase conversion rate
To not to waste at the other traffic and then the third thing is that
When people become a user we try
Heart to make them sure
What you refer
So you get the
What is fission
Go viral goes out of
Basic idea saying but just in Chinese system you need to
Use different tools
Incentive
And apply for MS2
I make.
Yeah I know so we made a very
Controversial
Video
Out of ordinary
What was it
How to workout
What's a lesson
Yes or the reason why we I did that is
So I did all the growth hacking
Feels like like I told you
But
Conversion rate is still very
Like limited because
Couple reasons
First of all
People don't want to
You know
Where to go to other people have already
They want it don't want to share
The first thing the second thing is
Nobody knows about
What is it like even icy
I can wear so many clothes in a mall
But I don't trust this platform solo brand awareness and Trust
Is there a thing is that
They just couldn't figure out how to run a call.
It's a lot of Education
Cost there
Seoul.
These zhuhai
No customer acquisition
So basically I figure out
The
The problem is, is marking issue
You to make people
Trust you be aware of
Yuan anole
What the hell you are
So that's why I
I really insist on making a video or a marketing campaign to make people be aware of
What causes and what benefits
It can actually bring to you so that's going to lower
The CAC later on
Right but then I want us to convince to see you like we need to make a video
Usually like when you say that
I need money to make videos
Theo's going to be very insecure like how much do you need and then what impact am I going to get out
This video
So I couldn't ask for a lot but I need you to make this video go viral and also at the same time
Really clearly communicate what the value of a
Positive
So
I thought about doing something.
Sweetie you know controversial to
Traeger
The bus and talk online no matter online
I just I want to make people talk about this
Concept sew-in needs to be something inside at
Sweety Sharp
I'm sorry
I did lots of
Oyster Bay on you know why closet and users and what Cajun they're using
Play Seether
So is that they all use y+ for what
Because an Insight behind at work
They feel
Really needed to
Dress
Desperately everyday
Otherwise
Especially in a city like Shanghai before going to laugh at you like oh my God you didn't change clothes again
So that's why they need a lot of
Draft and I took lots obligation hour can I see that
This is like the other deep motivation so that's why I made a video
About women at work and how they dress properly can
Yo
Eventually a force
Some I made a really dramatic and also.
Sweetie similar to one of the show TV show that
Population China
Just caught wind of song
Ghost Rider
So
That video eventually became so popular and viral in China there two sides
The people
Talking about once I was like oh my God this video is so
Funny
Three interesting animals such as you know Prada exist
Yellowstone
Oh my God you're talking about appearance
Career advancement
Do you even go to us okay that's not what I meant
Gucci Mane in China there's lots
Caucasian people don't trust
When you meet client
It's your like in gym clothes
But someone else were probably just can't actually get lots of
You know notice from clients so I made a really dramatic and I'll eat you lots of
Controversial
No matter which side they're on the all done with why call Dennis into the years are
But yeah I got lots
That.
Controversial video
How does it feel when you yourself
Popular car
Commercial
Of things that you know that's not
You are but
How to deal with
Yeah I had a
Huge struggle inside I was like
Hillgrove and your belief that's like oh my God which side right
Twilight kpi and Amaya
Make my job successful without budget I can make success happen and then the other sounds like
Yeah that's a little bit controversial that's not what I believe in PSI when I wanted to do the marketing I want
How to build a brand that's you know you know positive and make people feel
Feel better and now I'm making video that make people feel worse
So that was the first thing that's like a super shot to myself
Yeah so even to know I'm still thinking about it
Blog post
I wrote One
Yeah I wrote one back then to death
Fan or like to read itau
Why I'm making this video and
What I would message I wanted
But I didn't write about struggling dilemma after that
Yes
What would you have done the same thing
Do it again
I would do that video but then I'm going to create a second video after that
Yes so that video was going to create alderman
The controversy and Buzz and mystery and a secular is like revealing why she
She actually got the career
It's like an addiction to. Appearances order
Athlete resting she also worked very hard
So that's going to be, you know a serious video and then we can ask
She continued
But I didn't do
That's very good
Write very very very
What what could have been
6/2 company is self
Is referred to as the
The Chinese version of Rent the Runway
Why did he sing this
Small could work in
And China
The shared closet
Very new and
How about is soap
Powerful and work so well and stuff on it
It's so cheap
What was your opinion on this
Model
Yeah
That's actually
From my personal experience on table all I could buy.
Dog but not really so many dresses.
You know
Fit for me so I can you ask you have lots of
Good choices like you can go to
Zara are you to go to Michael Kors or there's lots of other boutiques
Store that's okay but in China
They're like
Low-cost level there are like look at your level
In between their nominee
Auction
If you go to Beijing I don't mean
Where can I go to shop
I don't even know which
Sliding door lock
Still opportunities in German
A fashion and apparel
All out there and then
I told you that
At work
Actually lost people have trouble
Wearing different
Everyday and in your closet is limit that your space is limited
How do I get to buy so many clothes I didn't.
The problem
The pinpoint is there
It's just
How you going to solve it
Elsa Matos
Strategic
Rotten tooth
Credit
Susan Garrett
I live and work in 9th
Embassy New York
Amongst my
S3rl
For you
What are you are
Observation
And how they
Different
And annies
And then
Do you see me song
Similarity or
New York is definitely my favorite city is
I think New York is fun because people there are they have this energy
They can go to work and very hard-working
Don't they still have a nightlife
Stan go to clubs or bar and then they go with you
Show
A gallery
Doing the weekend
Romantic relationship
There too many douchebags angel
But here's a message for guys Raiders doing solid
What where I see no Silicon Valley there lots of Tech Guys
That's truly trustworthy
That's why I find a boyfriend
I like Silicon Valley but different from my imagination I thought everyone's there's like startup Style
I don't know if I can now in the wrong
Foods that we talked about
Apartment investing stock rain turn right and I'm having two kids at home and which apartment
I'm going to buy in Palo Alto
Do you know what's that
House rice I just
I just don't think it's
Really cool
I came back to Beijing and Beijing is Beijing is like a combination of New York
Anna sedokova
Your friends are not
She not with me anymore what's wrong
You know someone grew up in Harris instead of in Silicon Valley has just very weird
I have to because I moved from Silicon Valley to Beijing I feel like fainting is on what
Every time my parents
Show me
Yeah my parents
They're like
Oh my God
Oh my God I can't stay here anymore so
That's really weird
In Shanghai it's like you know the restaurant
Celebrity style blogger Style
Lutheran North
Steelers
Luxury yeah I am at work
Teaholic so I don't really I'm not into those lifestyle things I I like Beijing more
Did you ever think about me on Saturday
Shanghai
Instead of envy
My my own shop
Yes still chose to stay in Beijing
Because I think the start of
The dynamic environment so much better
People are motivate
We talked a lot about girls
CNN
How to make roll happy
But in Shanghai they just asked me
How many pounds did you buy
In the western world
Is moron
Smoke City
Andaz
More of a
More likely to
Start up
Free
Gullah people
Startups
Chinese
Wachusett
Your own startup
In Beijing
Is a Sheikh
Yeah
I just feel like if I go by to Jean Ohio probably get off work at 6.
I'll go out
In terms of marketing
Go through the whole gamut
Fursuit
You marketed an American product to a Chinese
Set Michael Kors
And then
Chinese products
To an American Audio
And that your Market a Chinese product
Go to a Chinese audience
So why called
So out of these which one did you find the most
Most challenging and why
I didn't definitely white closet
I didn't you just want to smile
Michael Kors because it's such a big brown and it's fashion and
You're my king an American brand to Chinese is a bit easier because
In the past are nominee fashion the brands available in China
And then are you always such a big platform so although lots of
No us companies don't know about it I can just show them videos and
Press release and they're going to be
React like
Amazon
But why closet nobody knows about it
And then
People don't
Don't get that it's like a new brand new Prada and you concept and you pass
So I think that's the most
Pat and Jen
Part and also
Being the first
The job I got in China
Definitely the most challenge
Soaked
Maybe you can talk about your car in
What is a duet
What's your vision
Yasso
When I look at my past I feel like
All my interests are the products I was interesting are all forced female
You know cuz you're my pot as fast
Prada store
Like father that's no still apparel but in a tech company buyer
So
I always
I was
Vitas baidu
Women in China
Be more independent
Being just a friend and their needs are going to change
Vastly this year
Especially after that Viral
Controversial campaign
At Whitehall that which I made is that I realized
You know women are a different lady
Embarrassing
Thinking about the thing about different things so that's why I really want to focus on
No hurry calling me and then
Do research on it and how
You in a western world
How their GI protein
Economy Inn Holland China people are
Gene.
And what are the new products or
What are the new business
That we can get from this
Change
Somehow women think they're
So I'm doing this
Combination of marketing and media
On the media site I still write boss about
Different companies for example
Mary Docker with witches a top
Chinese cosmetics
Company how they did realtor marketing and then I compared Beauty blotters between China and us
Etsy what are the
Potential business idea that you could have have
And then
When
Unilock
Startup start doing that probably the most of the intrapreneurs are female there
You're not sure what
How to build a startup how to
And they're going to ask me
To help with them
So then I can use my
Growth hacking field in order
Experience to help with them so it's basically
I think it's going to be the future of
Chinese style
Consulting or media from is
You know you have a Content media platforms
To gain traffic to Gail the trust
Credibility and then people going to come to you for helper service
And even for FHA or
Consulting ideas or
Community groups and then
Study group
So I'm going to feel all that
To support
Huracan
NSU
Spend even Christy Moore
Do you find a
Woman exactly
Or
Founders
Have a chance to
Be themselves more or make
Speaker impact
Or less
Then there comes
I think Beverly in China
I think
Maya Moore in China
I definitely think the female leadership is going to
You know
China
Because of several reasons
First thing is
Biggest cemotap how I see lots of girls are raised
Like I
Likewise for myself
My parents never thought of me as a
They always
Treat me like I'm a boy I used to pay play basketball
What stores are all that
So I don't think I in any weaker than
The guys
Did I file a Spears like me
And the second thing is diet
The Chinese education system doesn't
Supports so much
Masculinity
10TV
Better I mean they can actually
Perform better than Western well you need to the guy
They need you
Do Sports and all that
Sakura
Intitle you just need to have a good school
And then
Auchan grocery
Akademiks
Academics rice or
That's why there's so many
You know
Axilla women out there right now
Rising
Starting is back in the history of
China history
Because of cultural revolution I think that's
It's called don't you right
Back in the days
And you don't
Say it's a female
Everyone
Equals
So I think
Women get you half more
Equality actually in China future
I definitely see that happening and I saw lots of female enter
Nurse already rising up
What other for example and then also the luck
Of a box
Lots of
Cosmetic
Companies already rise
So you are very dizzy
Connected to the
The land as well
Out of all the
Highways I know so
Do you have any
4 house
How to adapt
China quick
Will return from
The US
Cut down the number of
Time you use English
Thunder remix
I almost forgot to speak English and until you guys invited me today
Ellsworth also like
And that's actually the worst that make
Investor trust you more
She knows how do you style so that's what I usually teach people like you
Vocabulary
Before you come back
4nn second svdp open-minded
Don't feel sick
Teriyaki
I actually think people who never went abroad
There's so many of them are so much smarter than people who went to you as and then
Star there you know Elite
But yeah she naso
I just think you always until then more and be open-minded
So you're very prolific writer in Chinese
Articles on
WeChat
And some of my
He also
Topix
Michelle
One of these days are told me is that
Yo soy
Check roof
Mindset
Define your
Now husband
What does that mean and how would you apply what you learned to your private
Personal life
Reitzel
I always like to think about things and see whether there is some serious in common
Behind so when I was thinking about
Growth hacking in a Prada
You busy you find an MVP
P&i you do a b
We passed and then you find the first Narrows to test it and improve it
Until you find the PMI
I almost got married
Boyfriend
I should mention all this
I feel like oh my God what if I regret it later or is he going to be the best one
It's like is it is it PMS like that you don't even know it like
I just feel like I need to do some
How about we take a break and she's like I broke up with him
That's when I went to New York and I have
Some days with different style actually make notes like this
No western-style this is Chinese style
Ben-Hur style dispatch
I went out with them and see how I fell and I definitely know which are the types of guys I definitely
Don't like nope Automotive
Never
If they're still proud of
Open self
And then later I found out a car Velma Target
Audience look like Persona is like
Mick easterby
Not bad looking
Give me to be smart and then
She needs to like start up so we can talk a lot about that and I like
Good-looking guy to be honest that's very bad and then
He needs to be honest
Not like
Like like
So trust
So all of
These characteristic I found out that's probably a guy instead of combating doing tok
Patchogue
And then
I like what kind of companies
So that's a coincidence I went to Uber to
To do collaboration between IEP and Order Uber has all the tech
Actually call China Royal team in USA
Writings of in China because
They're All Dead
Data work
Data system is in USA cruden
Engineers in China and all this group is
Chinese
Smart
Tie dye
Interview with filtered already by Uber
Very talkative
I don't even think about that but when I went to Uber and I was doing this recap with them and meeting and then
My husband walked in fact that he was not my husband that he's like
Rihanna's and point out other mistakes he may wish information he should had and he's good-looking
I was like oh my god. The guy so that's how I knew my boyfriend and
Later I set up a
Celebration dinner
With Uber
I arranged like setting us up and he didn't actually know that
I said stop and then
B I got to know each other and then later we got married
That's my story and looking back I just made fun of it I was like that
That's just
Like growth hacker in a growth mindset
You shouldn't
You shouldn't you know
Just Married someone because your age is there and then you no regret afterwards you should
As many tests
Hospital right and then
Know what are the guys that you really think she would have got you should really
Not day and then
Just be happy with the guy
So that's
That's a very good story
Quick fire questions
What's a habitat using has
Has changed
I Rising
My high-school I write blogs
But that that that is not a pup
Public blog I just wright
Myself
Because everytime I'm angry
Frustrated and confused I always write down to
How to myself that that's a habit really changed my life
And what you do
Purposeful
I used to ride for fun but not right answer
What's something you read
Poor Charlie's almanack
You find that interesting
I just think it's very helpful found
To me I'm a marketer I never know investment that much and then
How people make decisions
And a lot of people talk to me about this book and says it's a really deep book
But you you should meet at
And I read it it's V intro
Because he
Talk about
You should always do things that's willing to keep it at
Bianchi
Keep it G and also
You no answer
Just studying marketing to do marketing you should study all other opt
Princess Jasmine
Physics
Finance investment
So that you can have a very how do you say robust
You know knowledge
Just tell him I definitely agree with that that's why I actually Jump Around
Brand management to Communications Choo Ops
To write out with me DIA
I think everything is related they have a
A similar system
You should always
Learn more
The last video
That's all the time we have for today and thank you so much
For making a tie
Time in this was really
Thank you thank you.
Airline flight 879 89.5
I-96
Ggv capital is a multi-stage venture capital firm based in Silicon Valley
Shanghai and Beijing with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past 18 years from seed
Capri IPO
With 6.2 billion dollars in capital under management across 13 funds
Ggv invests in consumer new retail
Social Digital internet Enterprise cloud and Frontier Tech
Gdb has invested over 290 companies
With more than 45 companies valued at over a billion dollars
Pergola companies include Airbnb Alibaba
C trip
Didi chuxing demo hashicorp
Hello by Adele
House Heat
Slack
Square
Hotel wish soundtrue white white and others find out more at Gigi bc.com
We also highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat group as last Channel
Where we regular share insights events and job opportunities related to attack in China
Join these groups at 96.3 jvc.com community
You have any feedback on this podcast
Or would like to recommend a gas please email us
I-96
IGG bc.com