Everyone before we begin I just wanted to remind you that we have created a WeChat group and a slack channel for you or
Our listeners
This is a community of people brought together by their shared interest in Tech in China
Through these groups are listeners have made friends recruited team members and found clients
We also organize regular offline meetups for this community
We had a meet-up in Beijing last month
And we'll be having another way in San Francisco on Thursday July 26th
Details for these meetups will be announced in a groups
To join the group's please go to 996. GG vici.com community and
Follow the instructions there
Once again that's 996. GG vici.com community
Vincent wrestler
Hi there welcome to the 9th at 6 Park
Brought to you by ggv capital on the show interview movers and shakers of China's tech industry
As was Tech leaders who have a us China cross-border perspective
Partner at ggv Capital it had been working at startup investment in them in both in us and China
For the past 20 years my name is Zahra Jones and investment analyst ggv capital and a former Journal
What is this show called 96 Chinese Founders have Oregon
Technically adopted that is 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
To us996 captures intensity Drive in speed of Chinese internet companies
Many of which are moving faster than even their American counterparts
Imma show today we have Erica and the founder and CEO of Zoom
Deleting video conference solution for Enterprise
Zoom is used by one-third of Fortune 500 companies
90%
The top 200 universities in the US
It is facing San Jose
Erica Rock I went to college in China
Bobby 997
Engine WebEx
When was still a very small company
2007 by Sisqo
And then Eric became Cisco corporate VP of engineering
Who was in charge of operation
Software
Eric's been 14 years in total eyewear backs and girls engineering team from 2010
2 / 2
Increases revenue from zero
2 / $800
11 + 20
Guns
Ggv are also happy Zoom customers
There's hardly a day when we're not using Zoom for some sort of investment meeting because we're such a global team and we investing Global Entry
So we literally cannot do our job without Zoom so thanks Eric
Thank you for having
So you were recently named a top seal on glass door with an approval rating of
99%
The average approval rate on Glassdoor is 69%
You were also the first person of color to leave that list
I wonder how do you think you did that and how did you
Feel when this was announced and what tips do you have for other CEOs
I would assist first of all
That's not a mile
That's our
Ichiza to me
Cuz it's Julia Providence
The culture that
Horchow
4 Hour
Reflecting our culprits
All for Havanese
Anacharis
So
Essentially
Mail for me as a
To see you my number one priority
To make sure I have agriculture
Beautiful song
Japanese
I really care about aliens
How to build a fire in Boise
If we are happy
Outkast
So I can let you know if you want to see you know
Water comes out for tips I would have seen
I'll Be Wild
Culture
Iron a mixture
Royal
Happy I think
Too much water
I'll do I'll try to do that it may not be as successful as you you you have been on your team have I've been doing it
What are some of the
Concrete things you have done that you things different or unique
On the other
Company cook.
I think Auntie what
I think this to myself off at 11 Cisco why should have
You my small office back then
Audi
Anna Stanley
Importance of
Coltrane
That's why we already be fun even on tymu just to myself
You know Ava comedy culture is
Japanese
I know the comments value is
Carrots Virizion
Do you know me
Caribbean
Can you care about it can you today cover a customer about a product
As well as care about yourself soup
We have worried about
Define a cult
And the volume Salon Devon or have
I know so you know summer
Alvin sings
Along the way before the girls are babies
So we
Beautiful song
Hardy Boys
Culture
Normally they don't look as those
Royce Grill Express greater in education background
Rita. Self motivation
I know mentality
And I think that's really important
A part of me want to hide you know up maybe see a height of a department
You want to try some vp-level from other companies
You wanted to hide those people who kangaroo themself along with
And I think those two things I really
Albatross
Enforcer RC
Wonderheart
The open invitation
Inora service that team
And ultimately be in
Number of go here as a team and I mean our executives
It's fabulous
Cost
Terraria
Royce
And our exactly
Entrust
Existed
I think
Start off
I see so sounds like
When you first started you had a group of co-founders
Imuscle founder
Then then your Nisha team will they all young people or Asian people for X College
Whom share your same cultural balance to
Start this with you
I will see that noted that young graduate
You know I'm the my offer 11 Cisco and the weather have monkey
Later
Engineers they all work
Nina with me for manager special
That's what I meant by co-founders
40 Engineers from Cisco followed you
Yeah
So
You decided to come to the u.s. in the mid-1990s because of the internet which you knew was the future but
It hasn't really taken out in China why were you so sure that you had to leave China and come to America 2
Capture that wave
Actually the first time I saw
I would have seen
I listening to
Eargasm
Speech in 90
Before in Japan
I was traveling
Japan Taxi
Accompany I woke up
All this time
Ball for me
Ally brazier
Happened to be the beer gas also was there in
To give a speech
Who's all running information Highway
I really I would have seen you know
How to put it on automatic skate Brothers
Sister visa application
Different world
Unlock code
And I have a sunburn I'm so sorry
Target customers
How to deliver and has a lot of the questions
China 1995
People
Understand that either
Why would Yahoo not Escape you know so powerful
I'm done
What about in comedy theater
To take a look Addison go back
However for whatever reason I did not look at it a Visa 1995
And I go to rejected
China however I bet Casino
Certified looking baggage
To practice my perseverance I think okay if I
I know Lisa I will try again
Add and that's attached
I think
I'm a successful but it took me
More than Wine Javier's
Is already 1997
Angela Kim here and I realized
Wow
Is a frontal wig
Offer internet
Revolution
I don't think I want to
Mrs.
So that's why I said it.
BuyBacks
To start writing
I cannot do any
Duckweb Sur small
And I even
Daughter speak language what should I do
I think a lot of people back then in China heard about the internal Revolution but not everyone like house to pack up and leave
Enjoy. So take a lot of grit to do that
Actually
Even if I
Came here to be honest
The ice at the time I thought about
Sister call me here take me to yours and then go back
Zaxby
My thoughts
And whoever you know when you start getting off something from worst more and
A lot of emotional connection
The pornographer BuyBacks
Is grated cheating
And the alarm always sort of
To go back home
Faded away
Anime near many Engineers from China I came here
And I've done pretty well inside the body
The minimum
Don't have the management experience
Or develop their leadership
Style
How did you do that
Engineering engineering had at the WebEx
I think we're seeing I think
I like a sitting a male
Is
Pretty open culture
Here so and the lotto
Over 6000 people
They would like to do
How are you
So you might really have assumed any mentors
Even
You know many many years ago
Rue21
Now that's why I also
Promoter step learning here
Zuma swap
Cuz I wanted to learn in also that's why I have so many mentors
Each of them I think they give me a lot of
What do I say
Hey what's your career aspiration what you should do next
I think a lot of them those were successful
All the entrepreneurs are leaders
You know that's why
Ice not only in old wife
Holding Ana to become an engineer but also I tried to
Practice in Osama in management
Skills
That's why I join a WebEx
DeWalt
What's whatever funding engineers
I gota
Promoted at 2
Manager senior manager director
At the Rapture all the way up
I'd offer to join the Cisco also got promoted
The carpet of APA
I think that I was the number one reason just a
Cell phone
I know Ashley
I want
How to do something
Yeah that's pretty much the shuffle TV
We sometimes hear of the term bamboo ceiling here in Silicon Valley where it's hard for engineers from mainland China
How to move up the ranks and the tech companies
Especially because of culture and language barriers so how did you overcome those
I do not send the language
Barbara is a factor
I was born send mmmforeign
China Wok
Exodus unirise swimming spots
Let me know Justin
You know a little bit
You know the culture you going to learn
Baidu by example
You know quite often for
You know many Chinese engineers
And the
You know giving their back on education you know quite often you have a new project
Need to know
I do not have this idea I just started
Why should I let my manager let other people know that
But he is very different and always Garden next we have open transparent
Communication
But wide open as long as all this is language various meaning I will see that
That is cute
And I was thinking about it why
In a few dollars would it cost
You achieve a lot of things and then you know
The others you know I will see you little bit promote
Some people say that asked
Why we sample the engineers have risen faster
In many of the tuxedos intra-matic today are of Indian descent
They also speak with heavy accent
How come there are not as many Chinese engineers
Risen to a level
The way you have
I think a community Beach NC like Chinese veteran engineers and engineers
Immediately
And also they are very smart
Biggest difference is dosa
You know a genius from India they have
Yes
Before I do anything I have a grade
No. It's like a PowerPoint service you in a why I wanted
Please have Arabic
So the idea for Zoom first came to you when you are a freshman in college in China right
Could you tell us that story
Yes or yeah I
That's a long story but anyways so
And I was fresh mine might my girlfriend
She's she was sophomore
Island 1987
You know she lives here
Another city I was born in
Mountain
High-end
New Providence
Beachin.
Sioux City versus city of sand in the city where I live is very far away
And every time
I want you to visit her
It would take
More than 10 hours
New Dragon Chinese
I know there I can probably
I forgot it
What's a problem that lost time
I took the train and there and then probably.
Play tonight you need to
And I know so I can watch
See her make it spicy
Are casino going to win
Winter break
Summer vacation
I ain't sorry I was I remember that actually
Someday
If I can have a smart and wise
And that's the one click I can talk with you can see you I think so.
And everyday I thought about that
But unless that resume
You know I studied
How to connect
Your technology is already but the idea or is there
Next
So you are on the founding team of
Cisco WebEx and you were there for 14 years what made you realize
That it was the right time to leave and start your own company
HUD
I saw the bod living
BuyBacks Austin
Cisco WebEx
Perseverate
Cuz I
I would say sitting in my lap
Is a starter
You better join a startup company
Do something
Find the soul Metacritic
Leaders really
Rycenga
In Sparta
Every time
Why I thought about leaving
Why bags
Emotional
How to go to that.
The bladder penis
What's the Galaxy
Is Rita Hart
Quite often sister Mickey lights
Stay for another year or not to year
I'm the woman that you like
I thought about leaving how it works
And it's doing all the food ready
But once you realize
Bags and everyday every morning when I woke up
I was not happy
Because I visited a website
Customer every time
I put some of the
I felt very embarrassed
Cuz I did not see a single
Happy rabbit
Why is that
Because you know one way beauty by bag
You know we wouldn't be folks the online usage
Values
Was that at
Happy you
Share the PowerPoint to share the best
Counting to be you and I in Oregon
440 or 40 years later lyrics some brand-new Pro
Like every business the god of
How to use multiple Solutions
They want to enable classroom
Devon How We Do conferencing and there have what unify the solution
The water table to have a club is to come from a solution he wanted to make sure no matter where that didn't you call me for
You also can't guarantee the good
You know a voice over IP polity
Yeah exactly
You gotta to realize
Cisco WhatsApp video to change
Shredded
I had no choice but to leave
Fix all those
Rebus problems
No that's why I finally see
Finally I decided I'm going to leave
I cannot stop
So that's enough
And when the 40 Engineers follow you how did Cisco react
First of all I managed more than 800 people
Small very small Pakistan
What's the weather
Meiosis
Siedah probably also saw
You know I have
No choice you know I'm so sorry I meaning
I have no way
In order to build a better solution
Is
Is the leader here I think it's a
You know is not meaning is nothing.
To do what you want to do
And I was yes
Nobody
Paid attention to what we were doing
So when you started Zoom the video conferencing Market was already pretty crowded so there were a lot of other Solutions
Like Skype Google Hangout
X FaceTime is that Aurora
What made you think that you can still come out and Market I think you said before that the biggest differentiation
Jefferson from the other Solutions it is that is it just works which I agree
So why does it work
Former
Customer from any user
Prospective cuz I
Chicago businessman costume
Literally
I did not see a single
Happy customer
Who
Would tell me hey
Really enjoyed you not answer
Show me all the solution or their back
I would have stayed
And you know nobody
Cosmo
What beautiful
None of them
The word beautiful in British
Cloud Beast
Video clip
So that's why I saw the opportunity
You know our philosophy was that
African beauty shops
Leather costumes
Enjoy
Using
I would say that the chance
You know that's a reason
Because quite often you know if you sing the market is
Stroopwafel
If you do not really understand
Appendicostomy
You sing if that's a game is over and you do not jump on that I would see
As you are going to Miss Dig
I just want so easy to use that you don't have to download the software
And remember login
Quick LinkedIn justworks
If it.
I make it so much easier
Add multiple level
Start using a product
Yes usability is reading important
I think a quarter to make
Easier
I know some
The qualities of rain
It is God
It works even when the service is not great
That's why we have
But focusing on optimizing
Our technology and reliable
Networks in China
Is awesome
Well versed
FaceTime audio
Works out quite well
But obviously we FaceTime video does not
How do you balance making sure that both audio and the video don't work well
So first of all a beauty in video and audio is orders to more important than lady
Like even if I can see you but if you're always hoping nobody is going to use that so easily
Innovate prioritize in audio traffic
Over a video
IND
You know given very very unreliable verlo banners
Hanover Foods on audio I know so we
Street light
55%
Which two country
So a lot of
I will see the
Flatware Hardware
Warrior first feel customers and how did you go about onboarding them
Oh we were very lucky our first to pay the customer
Was the Stanford
Continuing studies group
Oh okay yeah I was Solutions even not ready yet
Anna Diop
Yeah I said, remember that's a November or December in Tucson at 12
They were looking for us
Russian for the online
Learn on a teaching platform
University offer
Face
Cast of all the solution
Phantasm
Inequalities is better
Peter Costa
I really
What state is our confidence
And that's was our
Remember you also did a program in Stanford
Yeah that's the law like
I would like to see
Break
Guadalajara's
It was on a 6 for my
Emba
Approve app
Stafford
Cannabis
The whole summer
You have to stop brake but it didn't learn.
2012 supporting your cuz I was
That was when
The Mooks the online Edge basketball notification programs are starting to
Goodwill
So I seems like you popsugar right
Seckman the new cycling
You're very right actually beckson
And
We are we were like we're lucky together
Education sex
Oncologist
And therefore now you look at it
200 Nationwide
Universities that is
94%
That's a lot of benefit
Focusing on
Hi Ed
Guess what I've noticed you know
44 years later the origin of work
Boss Fender huge inference
You decide to focus on the Enterprise Market is that a consumer's
Consumer marketing
That is very different
Is Moto E no
Quite often
You got to have a free product
You know y'all
Monetization
It's ready they probably based on as you know I think
Inappropriate communication clappers
Rita Ora so for you and I'm a very important business meeting
I dunno singer in INXS to play ass
So and however there's a real tmall
Foreman
Knowledge workers
On those berries costume
I'm not looking for a new solution
That's why I think
From business model
Perspective
The penis song
Centuries
Will you ever have a consumer version
So that the younger version of you can talk to his girlfriend
Seriously I think that yeah well I think about that now
I think a cussing
Why was Young suffer from that I do not want any other stuff of that anymore
We might fall but for now
That's not our top priority.
WrestleMania SMB cost
Hughes Market
So we better
Full song
How to balance the needs of smbs versus the baker Enterprises big surprises you know I always ask for more
Security and more customization and so far
Soggy bottoms
That's good question so cuz we know in a dollar store we needed a balance
Speak to Nathan B and that's why I
Different
Strategy
You don't sow meaning
Even if we
SMB customer
We did
Add a lot of device which is already
Right now and I was
For the solution is already
Offer you know God less MB customers
You know sort of transition from SMB books to Enterprise
We knew that that's why I said you know what
From day one
From where you sit how do you see the future of work will evolve to thing teams will be
Become more and more distributed and juicing
People actually using videoconferencing to increasingly replace in person interactions
Absolutely
If you look at it right so first of all
Icing almost every
They have a modem all workers
Working remotely
What you
Noel
Why does my breath
You know if you have a what you t'ink you know you still needed to
Clarabridge In-A-Gadda-Da-Vida.
So you go to the house
Good
Buttitta, Spokane
I want to see when they fall
Why is the email another way
So do I use voice call
Bus Lines video
Email and chat I know I will see you know email
I do not think I use that you don't need an order for rude
You know Chad is so it's okay for the worse or composition
Is it hard to imagine I can fight people to talk about something for 1 hour
What is real-time Hoyle were in The Warriors or the problem is
Exhausting to attend it
I know but this one always multitasking
I also got to work through the window
Inn at Reading
As Reading part
Hinata singing out of tuna is
The blue character days
No Workforce
In the United States over one third of Workforce are millennials
Alarm
Video along with the phone
What if you give up.
Let them dog into the Audi car
Leaving all lights
No nobody wants
The Odyssey on the radio
Another
Trinis
Look at it at today's stop
You know I work at
Please
Never have a more than welcome
Less
If you
Visitor Facebook create account
Even a seal Mark Zuckerberg
Yes we're open space and that's why
You know where you have more than welcome group you go to Havasu do you go to have a cloud
Cloudy newborn
Weider Platinum Solution that's why
I think the video is going to play
Verbena prenatal
The Morgan
What
New Edition video I dunno messaging
How to become popular in the workplace
Was wislok it's cheaper folio in the US
Or Wizarding call from Alibaba in China or WeChat
You see more people
Using that
How do you see your solution work with severe messaging platforms
Hope it's very important I would I would call that a single vibration
Quite often and
Depresi like
Slack on me BMX
Some teams with introverted
It'll oil loss more like
Waterfall. The group
And all that conversation didn't know you. Real time
Baseball
And you still need a half of weed
Because you want to have a card MTG
You want to make a decision
I know especially if you want to talk with customers
The Potter Knows or demonstrated your sulfur you know and that you still need to have work
I'll be the closet
Kazoo Odyssey in like you know the combination.
Android ndk
Huge difference
Top of the morning
So how often do you go to China these days and do you pay attention to the tech developments there
What's for I wouldn't travel I need a bit of trouble I want to shower at the most twice a year
And I did that
4 years already
If I travel to very often
So that means
Product
And yeah I did not travel bags
China Bowl
Cerritos now
August
I want to go over there but Ohio or Everything Has Changed
Here I can get a visitor Visa cost
Commercial Auto
A toy what we using
In a video in on conversing
Zoom
I think you know I did not see this huge problem
Because every day
You know we
Obama
Are we do call
And I still can talk
What's the percentage of a percentage of Revenue
For you I'll send you a
North America probably around a 90%
Nike Nigeria
No arrests of 10% and most of them are
Australia UK English speaking countries
Sierra Leone
Yes
I receive that
Any growth coming from Southeast Asia match or are they developing markets
Because of Southeast Asia I would say still like a consumer-driven
Economy
Add a beauty B
Turn off sync
The Arctic
The real Winchester
Shuffle song.
America
An English-speaking country
That you replied
About India
Especially with all the cross-border
India because we have so many custom here almost there
And that we have so many users for
Your LinkedIn profile says delivering happiness who are users your happiness is my happiness
So I did not all COC delivering happen is this their mission and a lot of people would associate
Is in with efficiency or convenience
Not necessarily happiness what made you realize
That happiness is a key to your company's success
So yeah that's great question
Boston to my
Story customized gutter company
I was already 41 years old
Notre Dame
Elderberry young anymore
Butter flavor also I learned
How to lessen your custom
I'd really wanted a mess then
What's the purpose
Whenever I had a lot of question
I just
Don't have an ounce
Donatos
Is that
But along the way I really understand
You know the purpose of life
SuperSU
Is what happened
That's a really
Also during
How to
Cuz you
Happiness
Especially
Suppose you are so skinny
Under the former is
You going to make others
If you make others happy
Your happiness
Sustainable
So for me to build up. The company also
What to apply that if you don't
Who do the company Ward
The biggest word
We can make a costume happy
Isle Capri Buffet
That happy
Happiness
Let's light this is our company
Philosophy
You know you always had
I always
Communicate communicate with our employees
Storytime to mixer
Addison would be fine
Azealia Banks from successful in the US with BuyBacks and then Cisco and
Zuma scooter
Do you ever wonder given how fast time is growing
That you
Do even greater things
How do you choose to go back to China
There's a lot of our listeners
I've already compromising
Mainland Chinese Americans
Or Mainland Chinese in the US for a while
Should I stay
Where should we go by active antennas growing so fast
Yeah this is
Greater greater Quest
Also his cup
Birds
Again nothing is
Perfect
And the airport
I would G
And if you stay here
Squid in a startup ecosystem go to culture so many
Inno3d Json
Entrepreneur Sandy colors
So many things to avoid that was fired
You know that the back lawn
Loss of gritty Innovations I know a commie for
I'm the yeah there's somebody here also you know
The Baxter
The China you know the consumer-driven
Economy by over the past 20 years
Is once in your life
Trinity Keanu somatic
You get Alibaba on 10th
Even 50 and 20 years ago
Westminster Mall
Little 500 billion dollar company
I think that respect I think anybody would have said yes
599 6
The first wave of Internet
Got here
But that's why it's harder to see and the fold up very young I will see The Graduate
You know I would say
You know
We don't have a huge
Especially.
Consumer probably
Where is if you just to say hey
It won't discipulus on technology. True Innovation be happy
Lucy's Keys okay but also I will sink down the road as a more than more
I will see you know and that the company
Probably.
Absolutely
And I do not sing you go to sleep
Increasingly OB
Cross-border companies
Yes almost from day one
Hitler
So we're going to move on to the last
Art of the interview set of Center questions rapid-fire the first one is who is an entrepreneur are you
You admire the most and why
Entrepreneur or leaders
I think I would say
I really admire
Mark Zuckerberg
At a given
He's very young
The end of Utica
Agribusiness Facebook
Huge
Setopati
Pretty impressed
I look at a water heater cheap
What he did
And what more could be coming
Yeah I seen guys really
Abuelita
Leader singer I really admire a landlord form
He's Adidas
Edelweiss is a pharmacy you
Walmart
HD schedule
I know I single he's the wisdom of the wise
Trulicity
What
Think about
A lot of things
I could get it big wangs Emma like whatever your side of the
The first time
Will be misunderstood
Right
A lot of things like that
Words of wisdom
Thailand
I sold my name
Leadership
You know my leadership style
Why I sing I read it
With something you read recently that talk to you a lot or you recommend
Yeso
Baidu
Like reading a book
We also have a book
The club here by the way an employee
Whenever the
Buy a Bugatti
Myself or for their family member we all
Will always be
Casino
When you
Promoter step learning you got to do
Promoted and
Let the book I'm reading recently and I have a
Sarah Brooks
The Rebel kind
Almost done
Prism
From
At Bridgewater
In a global asset manager
Company
Wonderful
Leader
Great-uncle
Panera
Is awesome
Green China is obsessed with that book now
As wonderful book I highly recommend
What do you do for fun
I just
Enjoy
Yeah spending all the time is it
Does sometimes
In what year my song playing basketball
Send my daughter to dance school and that's my
You know probably every time
Why spend the time
No Escape
Obviously it's more like balance is very very important
But in China increasingly you see lot of worth
Work-life integration
People trying to simplify their life
Fit into the warranty
Truly be happy
Looking like that in your opinion
First of all
Dumbest thing about Autumn
Try to pursue a formula to balance
Look alive as long as you go without a direction you never
Can I have an ulcer
You know what
Because if you have a passion
You know
Kazuma Falcon
I just want to come to office I just want one.
Because I think this my life
I never think about that's worth
And if you always single a balance been working a lot so that means you stupid
Speed art
If you found the answer I think that you never will go back to ask how to balance
So thought that you like of work-life integration as well
Are the three degrees
Thank you so much for your time
My prayer
Airline flight 798
M996 by the way we also could use a weekly email newsletter in English also called
9 and 6 of the week's most important happenings in Tech in China subscribers
Informative and fun to read the new said also features original content and Analysis from
Star Academy subscribe at nine 6. GG bc.com
Is a multi-stage venture capital firm based in Silicon Valley Shanghai and Beijing we have been partnering with leading time
Entrepreneurs for the past 18 years from seed to pre-ipo with 3.8 billion dollars in cash
Anime smirk real estate funds to invest in globally-minded on spinners in consumer internet e-commerce
Frontier tag in Enterprise has invested over 280 companies with two
29 IPOs in 22 unicorn companies include Airbnb Alibaba
C trip Didi chuxing demo hashicorp Hello by cows keep
Black square toe towel wish soundtrue white white and others find out more
Borat Jew gbc.com we also highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat group as lot Channel where are we
Regular share insights events and job opportunities related to attack in China doing these groups at 9
96.3 tvc.com community
Or would like to recommend a gas please email us at 996 at gbc.com