Hi everyone
If you will be in Las Vegas for CES
The Consumer Electronics Show on January 8th
We would like to invite you to the 96 CS Meetup
20 GB capital r co-host Jenn fund
Global Founders and world-class leaders
Free evening of crossword and are working inside and fun
Our managing partner has song We'll have a fireside chat with exclusive VIP guess you won't want to miss
For more details and to register for the event
Please visit
CES. GG bc.com
And this is a reminder that all of our events and meet-ups are announcing 96 WeChat groups
Black community
I highly recommend joining these groups
By visiting
Night night 6.
Gvtc.com
Slash community
Vincent wrestler
Hi there welcome to the 9th at 6 Park
Brought to you by ggv capital on the show interview movers and shakers of China's tech industry
As well as Tech leaders who have a us China cross-border perspective on Stone
Partner at ggv Capital it had been working at startup investment in them in both in us and China
For the past 20 years
My name is Zahra Jones I'm an investment analyst ggv capital and a former journalist
The show called 96 schedule than any Chinese Founders have organically adopted
That is not a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
To us
996 captures intensity Drive in speed of Chinese internet companies many which
Are moving faster they even their American counterparts
On the show today we have George Yin or Yen Ching in Chinese
Who is the founder and CEO of clobotics
Exar Corporation
In Chinese
Dalian 2016 Club 86 a computer vision startup that's
6 to make traditional English
Trees more intelligent
Its headquarters in Shanghai in Seattle with offices in Beijing Dalian
And Singapore
I currently serves to Industry
Traditional retail and when energy
Climatic zones over 40
Send has raised
21 million dollars in BC
Defunding
GTA V with an early investor in 2017 and
Managing partner Jenny Lee is on the board
Prior to founding Cabarrus George Percy
16 years of Microsoft in the US and China
That's a vice president and general manager marketing and operations
For Microsoft Windows
You contribute to the double-digit growth for the regents
Freeburn dollar
But your business
Jenny and I have known him for over 10 years
He has also opened responsible for deception of Microsoft cloud business
El atomoxetine in lending Microsoft
Azure in Oskaloosa
In China with less than
10 months
Making Microsoft
First
Worldwide cloud service provider
290 service
Mainland China
Before Microsoft
George work at Goldman Sachs
Mackenzie in the US
Kiehl's mask
Green furniture
Is there any from Colombia
Welcome to the show George
Thank you thank you guys
So the majority of your career we're spending
Microsoft
I wonder what was it like to
To help are you as company run
How to operate
Somewhat less than
About how us companies
Can go to China
Great experience running the greater kind of team
Basically I am an engineer and I was born in
I'm having that engineer
Discipline and attention to details in the logic to applying to a business world I found myself able to transition into that
Tyrol preternatural
But the business is sold fast for Microsoft
The portfolio
It's not a problem to Consumer business to Hardware to services to Cloud
To licensing and Exedra
And that gives me a great
View of all aspects
Of the business
As well as how we would need to
Squeak different.
To make each one of the best
Successful so I found that
That have experience is super helpful to lay the ground for me to jump
And I wanted to dive into the details so how did you manage to launch Microsoft Azure and Office 365
5 in China within such a short period of time
And how did you do with the regulatory challenges
I think it's
It's with a lot of luck
To be honest it's a understanding the Microsoft ecosystem the business
Technology behind it on the engineering team in US
My boss me understood
How would engineering product needs to ship a self to be here in China
Spending more than 10 years in China
I have a good feel of what
What is the government or the regulars looking at
When a multinational like Microsoft wants without a service
As well as that was the right timing for
China getting a lot of weight behind
The cloud and infrastructure native that booming and wanting to have a multinational
Cloud provider here
To being a plane
So I think we are lucky that we're the right time the right place with the right people
And I want to be very level-headed
What's a government
About
You know what what is a take and how we can eat sushi bar technology and change your features and write out code differently in water
For the product to be localized and able to
Run operating
So could you talk about
Clobotics
That just give our listeners
Review of how it's helping
Time to transform
Traditional Inn
Other retail sites
We're focusing on digital tires
Products
So we think that offline retail today is
Unfairly
Challenged
Because it's really hard to connect to people with a product
In the retail store
And how would you go
And connect those dots is
Through the product in the middle
So recognizing the product is very hard problem
Is there any given one time there is hundreds of millions of different products are they in the mall
So how can a person go
The product so that we can have the interaction that
You have a soul naturally online we don't have it all flights
We believe that's a problem that we want to go
Digitizing the physical world starting with Rita
Stihl products
And once you do that at once you can build
Customer interaction or you can building to business interaction with
The product
That you have a very different model for her offline retail wood
Generate the revenue
So what what does your product look like
And who uses
So if you would going to a Walmart store even going to a
The mama Pop Shop store in Xi'an
Coca-Cola fridge you will see a iot device
We'll be sticking on the door
I'm basically two cameras looking in so they understand what are the products have been taken out of the Shelf
And we do local processing on the edge
So there's a small On The Edge chip that does deep learning algorithm to recognize what a product
I take it so it's only the bits that's changed gets
Sandbox
The cloud what the heck what are you able to see all the product movements
Over a million a million have
Coolers out in the market
So basically giving the headquarter that transparency and
Into Howdy's
Point of Sales devices are working
At them
So if it isn't retail in wind energy or two
Two very different
What's a commonality
Two of The Outlaws
To the field product
Service Pro
Which one the focus on
Depends very good question that's a question that keeps me open hats that wake at night
Essentially when we got into this business we see the fundamental technology blocks are the same
It's going to be hard where it's going to involve some type of software computer vision screening of automation
End
We are
We believe that these
Technology should be applicable in 3rd different.
We went into wind energy first
Because we had background
Draw a hardware
Computer vision
So that's
Entry into that
Space give us that natural barrier
And has a celebration that we need to be number one in the market
Stop the 2 years in this industry worship our first product and we are already the China leader
In doing autonomous inspection for the winter writing desk
When we look at
The Second Industrial we see the retail industry is
It's a trillion dollar industry with
Still very little technology
And we believe the technology that if we can provide for the offline retailers in the cpg companies
They wouldn't use that as tools and weapons
To actually have a fair fight against the guys like amazonics
We want to see how this industry would get shaped
In the future
But that takes a longer time for us to be there when that battle happens
We got to make sure that we can survive this Revenue stream we can be leader insurance place that we sure of
To look at wintermyers mobile device to play we look at more of the retail space is offensive acceleration
Template for the lawn
So what
Conner Industries Borger
Are you going tonight
We have
Plenty of things on our play for us to chew
Our goal is to be number one being those to feel that I think it's
It's going to be a while
Before we can ourselves
I say we are
So we're not looking at the third industry we think.
Our strategy is to have a
What's the fastest plane office play
And that's already
Complete I will just have to go super deep in these areas
To see how we can go help these Enterprises
To extrapolate
Better value and better potty
Do the wind energy companies have more money
To pay you
They do have
The pretty significant budget
For the operations and maintenance area
This is actually a 25 billion dollar market
Andaz 450000 turbine
It's worldwide
So if you do the math the average house to $65,000 they spend
Operations and maintenance alone
For a
Provide per year
And today we're only scratching the surface where is only getting $300 out of that 65
Thousand dollars that they're spending so there's a lot of Technology innovations that we can doing there to make sure that we can
That's a larger pie and also the pie South will get bigger
As the technology Innovations
So what's preventing you from
Just focus on.
It takes time for a commercial business
To really accelerate
And for us to do that part well we already taken the right set of a group
12 + 4
This is not a game of
You know if you have
10 people you can go to
Attend turbines if you drive a hundred people is 200 it's actually just a set of people that's turning I the customers
Besides I'm fixing boxing proven products Etc
So we're not increasing the team where is celery and make sure the product is better
And that time is not going to go away by adding people so
For us we know the trajectory is there and we will have to go deeper if I going deeper we'll just have to take that
So could you talk a little bit about your technology and how it
Appreciated from
The requirements for our technology
On the retail side
Is scale
Anybody today can take
10 or 20 pictures able to do some labeling and put it into a automl
Engine words from large companies
And Trent out at Freddy decent model that can
Get your nail 90 or 95
Inaccuracy
But that's not interest is great for devil but it doesn't work in a trillion Barb
We're talking about Millions
Of products that we have to recognize
And on the weekly basis their hundred thousand products
Update
So you think
To the platform that you
You provide
Able for you to capture those image
Way to label this image finder
She was that you're looking for them building the models are pushing a models
Universe small form factor
Into iot and into your devices
That's our bread-and-butter
And that's something that's really hard
To Chase or two
Bee frog
I always use an example of
On the things that we previously did I micro
I'm doing the search War
We have always thought that
With more money with more power with more talents were able to catch up with Google
But we found that that was not the case cuz that was a data game
They were in the market for
Exactly so it doesn't matter how much
You know Helendale, call where you at
We Believe for us today we saw this big problem
I'm at work in their first and we're capturing better will get better I was around it that gives a first-mover advantage
What's the temperature scale many many many years
Robotics is only around 2 years old but it already has offices in
Five cities
4 countries
Why do you want your business
Global firm
It's all about
Talent I think that Talent from multiple different backgrounds
Coming together
I will come up with
BARC
These are the insight
That dumb I want when we built it
Together
Running Global development teams for Microsoft
For many many years
That's just part of our DNA
That gives back
Unfair advantage
Quotes that having the best people in USA in Asia and in China except all come together
Working on the pieces that they're they're good at
Yo today
Machine learning API General
Music super hot Market
I'm able to tap into yuan
Other markets that haven't been
Watch to multiple times
I'm giving stuff on a resource economics
So
Speaking of talents
You guys have a
Killer engineering
A quarter of them
Hold a PhD
/ 84
Percent of the team overall
Masters to grow higher
Many
A team members
Prestigious Silicon Valley comp
Buy Microsoft Google Amazon
So what tips do you have
Have for recruiting
Technical Talent
When you pitch clobotics
Talons what do you use to convince
I seldom our Club Onyx
Dream
But in Chinese
I understand that we're about staying here but we can also
And the dream has to resume
I told the person to close his
Imagine that
Offline retail industry five years
If a person walks into a store
The stores no longer Isles after owls on rocks
After all it's more experience play
When you put on your AR class or when you looks to your mobile phone
Table in front of you with multiple products
Now suddenly start talk to
Start to give you more information
Start to tell you that there is alternative
Products that you can get as well by clicking it
You're getting more personalized information
Personal discount
That's what I see doll fine retail
And
Does that person wants to be
Departed I'd trade it does that person wants to tell his son and daughter that
His father or mother
Was a part of that Journey was part of that part of the mission that changed how retail industry worth
We Believe
Dancing resonates with a candidate
NY likes
Canada to join us
Almost 20 years
Recurring BC
I meant many
Professionals
With amazing background
In multinational
Most important us tennis team leader
And the ones working
Try not to bust a nut
Long time as well
So when you and your co-founders will come from
Being emotionless
For such a long time
Macomber gucciardo
What changed
For you
What was the thing that switch
Decide to do that take the rest
After all these years
And then as you start building a company that
No longer part of Microsoft's long apart of the big company now you have a
Sell yourself
And one brand
What are lessons
Quotes on positive and negative side
They'll be helpful to login
Yet I think the most important takeaways
Is 2 mi
Two and a half years
Startup world is
I started recognize
Is that I know nothing
And that's super super
Before present
Able to face himself and
Able to admit
That you know not
Extra large fishing too small pounds
You get into a position where
You think that you know everything you can you can't execute again do anything with your eyes closed
That's no longer in
So get yourself out of that comfort zone into a newer space cuz there's
Bigger world out there
Enjoy being a cop machine
Animal from Nagasaki what to do and
Get paid while doing it
Watching for you and your co-founders
I think words
Which is built differently there still be bass of these people that build different
Yo you look at your disposal see your saved a right I think it's just takes a special breed of people that become CEO
Everybody is fit for that role
And we're okay with that
We recruit a lot of people from multinational and sometimes they said you know I like my conference don't stay there
That's totally cool
But you go to find out of 10 people you talked to your friend a one or two person to have that spark
All you got to do is cut it given that knowledge that I need to leave that covers on Joyner
Next to in 3 years
It's going to be
Totally different
I give it to you
It is that you can recall
That changed for you
Personally
Yeah it's actually at the
Chichi vlp events
4 years ago I was sitting the back table
Looking up
I'm at the startup CEOs giving the speech
And you know some of those guys are great articulating their mission all those not so well right
But you can speak
Here we can feel the passion that they had
You not in the way that they're telling the story right and I look deep down myself to say okay am I
Am I just going to be a person who has a fast track to the Sea Suites in a large company
Or do I want to do something bigger
What is said that twice L fight I felt like
I also had a mission
I also had a vision why cats
Able to digitize the physical world I am willing to
Who converts the two together to have the
Tell without the tool that the people have to support
How's the world be able to make that happen
So why not take a plunge and try it next time
Georgians in the world
Demotivated
What was their biggest
List challenge
Came out of
Outside of a big hump
Picture yourself
Yeah I think it's about
Able to recognize that
Now without the Big Brand without the
Reputation
Peoples going to look at you
Nobita
And you have to be okay with that
The Pride
All the extra
Accessories that you had with a large company
All that stuff goes away
And today you have to build that rep
Teach me how to use both our heads roll up your sleeves
With your co-founder to do at Farm ground up
And
That realization was
A shot
Where you going to places where
Little People roll out the red carpet for you at
Time schedule for Exedra
And everything now you have to do it on your own
That shocked
5 Seconds
Right after that you know that you are in a different place
The battlefields different things
Do you have to be different
The agility of adjusting yourself
For the new environment I think
Any CEO startup CEO needs to have
How to quickly
So you have so many office
Lacrosse
Play geography
How do you divide up
Abilities across them in
And how do you minimize
Yeah to try to build this
Seems the group of frogs that are deep in certain areas
Fire around Toledo
For example the head of our us office
Is Avery on computer vision scientist
It has been
In the start of World as a CTO
So we build
Computer vision capabilities
You surround them
And you will see that
Because he has
Downtown the path previously
The amount of senior Talent
Send the June Attalla
And also the fresh hires in the interns
Can I start to come all together
Indicted
Pot
Apple support
If you're in China if you look at our China infrastructure
These guys are
Startup or exit a internet guys
So they know how to
Quickly roll out of
I form and scale to millions and millions
Services
Over very short a time so there's a fire around
Where that talent pool has a ride DNA built from
You haven't
Exposed
To be
When you guys
Thinking about
For robotics
What major
Decide to do this
I think in China.
Previous no internet on mobile internet
Has been a really
Rush
Of consumerization of all my spaces
To be honest
That's not something I'm very good at it's not in my DNA
Enterprise field for all of us
Keep on watching and waiting
I believe the next wave
Okay
Is going to happen on the to be side
And it is going to happen with
Deep technology companies
That can go help and push the business model
Working with a traditional Industries to
That's where my friend
You got to do something that you're good at
Yo in a place where all does all the cards are stacked against you
Its global
It's deep Technical and it's able to scale
Into services at other people
Knowing what you know now we look
Career Microsoft
What are the
MCU
Learn
Help you do what your do
And what are the skills as you wish
Should have learned
Either of your homeboys who else where
Never would have better
Where are you
Two for the road
Asperger question we're just talking about that in the team yesterday
I believe I stating the
Microsoft engineer X-Men Xavier
I believe I
Spend a little bit
I would cut down to about eight years
Learn how to build a product a couple of times
I know how to scale a product and I would leave that last
4 years
To go to a company like Alibaba
Because I believe in the earlier days
Of Alibaba the way that. Jellett afford to go trans ability for the pressure to be on a person to
I need to be versatile enough to being different roles
That type of pressure
Is what I'm experiencing today and I'm learning from scratch but if I had that
Does company where everybody had a similar values and it already has a similar
Movement I believe I'll be more prepared
I'll have a better preparation before where I'm at
Best bagel bites
Providence
Thank you
I looking at
Advice to you gif
To entrepreneurs who are debating whether they should go
Train at a bit
First
Or just you
Starting a comp
Yes my personal experience I think that
Printing large companies I look at Microsoft is awful
And this is a place where you can move into multiple roles that started with an engineer and I was in product manager
My daughter wanted large
Engineering team that I
Came to China that Iran China business
So large
Large organizations able to give you these multiple roles and for you to do any take selling these
If you think about it
It's actually very low-risk
Rights you really don't have much to lose by trying new things and large comfy
You don't have to worry about the 70-80 people that are with you have to worry about their paychecks if it's bicycle you're free
While but that you should try to get as much out of as you can while in these couple
You got to tell you yourself that once you're ready
Jump
Ayumi fewer you think they almost ready job
Because you going to have gravy seems like Gigi Viejas
Right to close the last mile to get you out of that door
Everybody
Sitting you know at the ggb bad
And sometimes you just have to look at straight into house I thought that's go
How did you know it was
Who is The Rifleman
After spending so many
It's actually a evolution of revolution
I've been preparing the same
For three years as was talking about
I believe that the market
The technology and my experience is not at the place where I think I'm ready
So it just becomes a natural progression
Of where I want to take my next
Career with the people that I can join
So when you left Microsoft
I did a lot of people
Come with you
Alpha record no
I think
You got to have your own
Once
I'm on the road once I'm
Telling people my vision
There's other people work for Microsoft other places that cool
New my reputation in the industry
And decided that they want to share that dream with me
Everybody has to take their own path that's going to a different time for
Remember we welcome anybody from multiple backgrounds will share the same dream to come in
Anytime to enjoying the journey
Amir advice to give people who work
Take risk is very
I love you with an going to be
The companies were they going to
Stay so we actually afraid of texting
Risk of losing their teeth
You think you realised
The training on
The practice
Sessions
Kakashi
If you have gout approachable
Different mentality
So you have service
Variety of
First 20 engineering side and
Going to the operational
Hillside and now this
So could you talk about your
Takeaways from
Various
Bistros
Are different but your fundamental principles how you approach and solve a problem or the same
A technical background
You always very logically
How to dissect
The problem
Play areas and doing trade-offs
We can show the logic
Supplies into the decision-making
Process
That's just built in
Intermi
And I've been trying to apply the same skills that's what I'm on a engineering running a product or
China
But I
Quickly found out that in a start of World
It's not always the
Therefore that actually have a
Circle
Axios or either CEOs that are currently serving today it's companies are small and you're bigger than me
We talk on a daily basis
Bounce ideas off each other
To make sure that I don't get blindsided by things that I'm
I've been avoiding overlook
I think that's critical
Again recognizing that you don't know anything
And build a bass tabs
Support supporting system around you
For those guys to
Give you ID and a bison
Challenge
I'm your strategy
I found out to be bear
BSU assembly in your Coke on me
How did you think about
And what role did
How do you come home
Actually didn't do any recruiting
Most of us work together for the past
8 to 10 years
So we knew each other
When you do that
These Punk hold on a team come together
We were able to have a good chance of achieving some
So it was a natural progression
And once you took the first step
Everybody said we want to go take the same steps that wasn't very natural
El Paso get there
I didn't
That's probably one of the benefits
For a
Older person like us
Is that we had that it
Experience in the large company so you have a TracFone
And a truck lifted means
So I advise I will give it to the younger guys I'm making sure that you really cherish your reputation and your track
If I could spend whatever
Cuz all that stuff is going to
Add up and
You run
Across border
You are sunshine
How do you deal with
Cultural
Differences in
And how do you make sure every
Such a diverse
Write it down
LA Times
Mytalking
Things gets messed
A person's not there gets messed up by bypassing words back and forth
I want you to write it down
It's on the paper
You will quickly realize when you write things down you actually what haven't you been more structure thoughts Luna things that
You thought me the stats didn't make sense on paper
Moore I'm to make it make sure that ideas or solid so we have a writing
We use Yelp
OneNote
So everybody can contribute to the the same
Service
That we can see
How our company of her ideas professional
Stop.
Topcoder Will Rock You
Did you think people work
Same hours
Lacrosse
Different offices associate
Bob
I think the hours are
Different
People are constantly thinking about the problem at work
We don't have office hours we don't have Punch Cards
We don't try call A Long Walk off a short people work
You can see through the
Activities on words on WeChat
WhatsApp for a new email
You and the people are constantly trying to solve
A problem
The problem is not going to go away
So whenever you feel like you're rested whenever you feel like you're ready when we feel like the timing is right
Start up as a self motivating a self-driven
Services
It's not
You get a paycheck to paycheck that we give for the things that we give them today
Any of these guys can walk out of here and go to a cone company
They're not here for that
That vision
The faster that we can go cheaper the better prepare we can get that the better it is
Some people do we have in the US
Let's hope people in the US
None of those guys are pretty seniors are very seasoned guys
To be honest those guys also have less
Financial burden
This is well so you don't these guys if they bleed in your vision
They want to spend time their productivity.
Come out it's just going to be
How many people do you have in China
We have over 60 some people in China
And it spread some sales marketing operations
And Engineering assets app
So
What we have seen so far
Summer engineering China 10 to 1
Get going
And it
He said
It doesn't work if
Either way to go
The Architects in the US
In general show something within the seed
Need more plan give NSYNC
Tested
The product
Before they rolled out
More deliberate how do you reconcile the difference
Cancel that you can be
Cookies
Yes it's very good
We have something called the Prototype Google
Rex the Prototype grooves
Basically it helps me or helps people really put together that vision
You can see it
You know 6-10 month down the road what that looks like
Fortunate that our business is a scale
It's not something that
You can just ride and give it out and
Give me feedback
You can do today
But how do you descale that service
All about deep engineering infrastructure
Social work and that part actually is going to take time and this is where the US
Oh you know the guys without experience even our CTO West done this for you know Bing search comes in
So the infrastructure that we built today can scale to millions and billions
List of SKU that we have
Have to go recognize
Customers are multinational
So their expectation of our services are a Salazar super high when customers are putting he
Chi-Town yuutousei
The stuff that you give us
Saw that we want to do the right thing so we don't want to turn out that
Need a wasting engineering resources to rebuild MBR
Fortunately is very fitting to our
Stop
What advice do you have for us
Tech companies for
Thinking about entering
The Chinese market
It's going to be challenged
To be honest
And I can tell you
The multinationals haven't
Figure that out yet
And it does take
A special breed of people
Not only look straight
Please but understand a China environment
Understand local culture here
I know is how the US operation works
And able to
Learn quickly adapt
The local environment here
That takes a special
Or special group
Up to four people to deliver
So take your
Time entering through China
It's not a place we stick a flag so where in China are you going to get
Slaughtered
So take your time find their Vitality even groom that's holiday
If you have to but this is a325 your journey
And by the way this is going
If somebody found a secret formula should go
Sell that to Microsoft or Amazon anybody else right cuz they haven't really forgot to tell you
You in Peru
Microsoft
Knowing what you know now
What would you have recommended to the men's
I do it differently
City Market mosques us
Ventana Enterprise size or on the
Consumer site with that
Ouch ouch
Look. I think all the other consumer side
Timing wasn't right.
The team had a different agenda it was
The different DNA
So that part was
It was not going to happen
But on the Enterprise side
If
In a large corporation would
Truly truly
Call route
Engineering team
Dedicated for China
And made that China leader to be responsible
Not only for sales and marketing
Before engineering for research
For investment
You make that a true CEO for China I believe the Dynamics will be very
And that's still something that not any of the multinational CEOs
Maybe some
KFC
Then what kind of person
Would have succeeded
As a Microsoft China
CEO
In charge of the entire Opera
Encoding engine
Review were in sitting at Redmond
And you had to pick someone
The first Microsoft
What would he
He look like
I think I'm a very good
Choice what is about you that really should have seen
Okay as the things I was saying previous
Nissan of Santa products
Spell all times
Understand
How business were Rhonda
Understand that
Cease of government
And also regulation policy
You know what I left Microsoft
But having
Don't do that two or three years the starter
I thought the door so much I've seen so many things
Underground lab
I would say that much better prepared
Then I was 4 years
Manchester
Exactly
So now it jumps to the final
Part of the interview which is around
Rapid fire
Questions
The first one is
Who is that
When are you admired
I'll give you two
Chairman Mao and George Washington
There becomes a virtual
OK Google
I think
I think Chairman Mao is a great entrepreneur right he
He had a great idea
He had
I was a mediocre
People right
She had very little tools
And he's able to go attacking this area where he bleed in
And turn around
And use whatever the resource that took a long game into creating what is
Kind of look like today
Right so I think the entrepreneur spear if you read his writing
It's always a part of his DNA he's me
Pricing so I respect the person for
Able to take that
Plunged
We're changing our industry
He changed the world
George Washington
Rite-Way comes into and say hey we don't do something great
Again a great ideology
But very mediocre
Very little tools all the cards are stacked against
But you take the wrong real time Bill what is United States of America today
I believe these guys
Your Love
I'm a history buff
What a weed
Things about how they pee comment
Account end
I'll be able to conquer these difficulties
It makes me think that
The things I'm doing
What's in a book or article that you
I read recently
BBQ on recommending the principal
So principles of grey book
Because you're basically destihl
All of
These learnings are all of these things that you said
I wish that I can write those things down
Put together in a book and share with you so
This is not a book that you re wants to put on a bookshelf to something to carry with you all the time and just flip through chapter
And there's going to be these aha moments
Cindy's Choppers you said
If I took a different path I look at a person differently
If we had
But you that person's background I might behave a little bit differently in Tulsa
All these things are so resonating and
So useful
It's it's something that should be a pocketbook size that carry with
All the CEOs order
So what do you think about when you get up in the morning
What motivates you to get out
In the morning everyday
And also what are the things
Keep you awake
Indict
The thing that motivates me or that
Today Eddie some people and
Yo
Sometimes later will be a hundred a thousand people that share the same vision
And it wants to go help
The traditional Enterprises and help them to digitize the
And if that dream spots around
I believe
The day the world will be very different than we see today but
The waiver changes that we can experience or going to be bigger
Data Internet wave
It's gonna be bigger than a mobile internet
It's going to be bigger than
The cloud way that we have seen
The physical world is the ultimate game where you
Bring all the talents all that collectively all the weasels together
To shape
How we going to see things differently 5 to 10
And what keeps you up at night
It's going to take a long time to get there
Call Lindsay by resource
The right customers are right product to serve the customer all kind of comes
Together
It's a long journey
Gotg via likes to back me up and make sure that we all catch you that drink together
What types of roles are you hiring for a how can people read
Reach out if there
I think in a startup
Little People define the role
I actually don't have their clear job description
Hive engineering
I've self-supporting guys I've operation guy
And when a person comes in he looks at when we doing and he tells me
How did job do
Prescription Shop
That's how it work
If you are looking at a job description I can get you on
Www.microsoft.com this whole bunch of jobs listed
Last question what do you do for fun
I don't know how much time before these days
I murdered a saltwater aquarium
Fanatics
And I have a saltwater tank at home
It's a ecosystem on its own it has
You don't lpsf
Yeah she has
You know live corals has
You don't need Lori has the order
Things that you can't imagine to see I have it in my
And it's delicate because you're basically shrinking the Steve
Into your living room
And the right chemical balance and write tweets that you have
Are there Bright the right bells and whistles alerts that
You have to mix it up
Potassium and calcium are all correct in the right level schedule
And that's something that I can focus on take my mind off
What I do in a startup world
And it calms me down when look at the
Official snail swimming in the water you see the starfish in
You excuse you see the crawl style waving back and forth
What's that gives me into a different environment where I can distill
NSYNC
And process
And be better prepared
Whatever your
Hours at Michaels
Witching hour
It wasn't working hours now
I would say the working hours are not different
Microsoft
I also looked at that for me at least it was a it was my own entrepreneur
If you look at me coming to China at the first person worked on us
I must look at me going from engineering to
Stop smoking working at Cloud which
Jumping into seal
All these things
I'm taking out his entrepreneurial experience just trying with a lot of risk
Lights off the hours at putting is not your regular
I work 6 days a week
Whenever there's a customer call I'm there I spent all the time with a cell is going to a customer
To see how we would
Close a deal and how we will go structure deal how we will get government on our side exedra
So that experience continues into start of World
It was more careful
George thank you so much for being a no-show
Thank you
Airline flight 879 89.5
I-96 ggv capital is a multi-stage venture capital firm based in Silicon Valley
Shanghai and Beijing with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past 18 years from seed
Capri IPO
With 6.2 billion dollars in capital under management across 13 funds ggv invests in costume
Smyrna retail social Digital internet Enterprise cloud and Frontier Tech
GTB has invested over 290 companies with more than 45 companies valued at over a billion.
Dollars
Pergola companies include Airbnb Alibaba C trip Didi chuxing
Domo hashicorp hellobike cows keep Slack square-toed
Wish soundtrue white white and others find out more at 2 jvc.com
I also highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat group as lot Channel where we regular share insights event
And job opportunities related to attack and try to join these groups at 9 96.3 GVC
Ebay.com community
You have any feedback on this podcast or would like to recommend the gas please email us I-96
IGG bc.com