Hi everyone for those on the East Coast we have to a Saturday events for you coming up in York City and Boston
First on this Saturday April 13th
Hanson I will be hosting the first 96 meet up in New York City at 11 a.m. to 1 p.m. in Midtown West
Come join us for brunch meet other 96 followers in New York and enjoy a special life podcasting session
Where we interview with Howard director of the highly acclaimed documentary People's Republic of Desire of film about
China's live streaming phenomenon
Space is limited so please register at 9:06. Gbc.com NYC
Specific location will be included in the confirmation email
Also for those who will be in Boston this weekend
Hanson I'll be hosting a fireside chat on the latest trends in Tech in China
All Sunday April 14th
I should have 4 p.m. at Harvard Business School
Cakes from Lydia will be provided as refreshments
You can RSVP for the events at 9:06. Abc.com Austin
Intervention
Airport
Hi there welcome to the 96 podcast
Brought to you by Gigi capital on the show went to the movers and shakers of China's tech industry and discuss
Call Founders from around the world can draw lessons from China Tech ecosystem my name is Hans home
Igtv capital and I've been working at and investing in startups across the u.s. China and other emerging
Markets for the last 20 years
My name is original and the marketing manager at ggv Capital and a former journalist why is this show called 96
96 is the work schedule that many Chinese Founders have organically adopted that is 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6
Days a week intensity drive and speed internet companies
Miracles over last decade
Channel where you can connect with like-minded people interested in Tech in China we organize regular offline events across the world
Wells Fargo followers you can join these by visiting 96. Ggvc. Com
Hi everyone
Before we jump into Today's Show I highly recommend checking out the last episode of the 906 podcast if you haven't already
During the last episode hunts and I discussed the challenges and opportunities that high always were Chinese overseas returnees
Space as they come back to China
That episode has very useful background information that will help you make sense of this episode
So on Today Show you hear from a few of our ggv fellows
What is jujube fellows
It is a program that we lost this year which was designed for sea turtles or Chinese overseas returnees
To get re-acclimated
To the Chinese startup ecosystem in business environment
Juniper program 34 Global - young leaders came to Beijing and completed a while week intensive training on Tech
Premiership in China
R34 fellows were carefully selected
I'm over 400 qualified applicants
They come from Top institutions around the world
The most well-represented schools are Stanford Harvard MIT and Berkeley
And many are currently working at Silicon Valley Tech companies
Such as Google Facebook Uber Apple Etc
All of them are native speakers of Chinese or equivalent
And are fascinated by the meteoric rise of China's internet sector over the past decade
Among the first class of the fellows
Two-thirds were professionals and 1/3 or in school
Their ages range from early 20s to late 30s
They represent a diverse range of talent and skill sets including engineering product business and marketing
During a program the fellows visit at the headquarters of 8 Chinese unicorn internet companies
And heard from a total of 21 Founders or executives
Bouchette lessons on what it's like
To start and run companies in China's business environment
Our speakers came from some of the most valuable tech companies in China
Including by dance DD xiaomi
Chancel choir show faceplusplus
Thalia bong
Keep hello to sing and others
During these closed-door sessions the speakers shared not just tips for success
But also candidate stories of failures and pitfalls that they ran into a loner start of Journey
The program is designed to resemble a light with MBA on all things related to China startup ecosystem
And by the way if you're interested in learning why we organize the program
We actually have a blog post
In which we discuss the rationale for starting to be a fellow's
You can read the blog post by following the link in the show notes
So now you will hear a few interviews with RGB fellows on their life stories what brought them to the program and what they took away
Away from it
Hi everyone
Today I went to view one of our TV fellows Davidson
Or since you weigh
In Chinese
Davis currently a data scientist at Apple
Cupertino
Is originally from Suzhou China
In attend college
Germany
Jacobs University Bremen
Before heading to the Bristol Pennsylvania
A PhD degree in ee electrical and system engineering
Welcome to the show David
Thank you hands massager
So how was the Apollo space
Well
I guess you're asking about program but first of all I think the fellows were absolutely amazing
In my inaugural class the Fleming self I sing
It's frankly
Amazing is now Cyril
Personally for me I
What expect
But when I was in Beijing it was a week off
Path schedule
Coastal conversations
Executives and founders of the hottest startups
In China
An officer
It was eye-opening
I mean to be there how many minutes per day rough
We're joking towards the end of the program everyone almost near the burning out.
And it's almost like a 96 Jaguar having a diff
License roughly 10
9 meetings at least
Add a birthday and we're doing lunch meetings and we're eating in the bus
And were
Hurry up
To use the bathroom at the next company we arrived
Fodera and Erica Fisher is Hialeah great job
Scheduling
Are you guys a lot
Yeah I think not only carefully curated this program and all of the
Conversations and visits
Restart ism
We jokingly say is an immersive
Boot camp for ain't going to do that
And how many of you
What's on the Strip together
Roughly 36 of us I believe
Out of Africa pulled over
400sel
You guys all very lucky and well-deserved
Definition is what I felt when we thought about this program then
We didn't expect to be seeing this many applicants
On top of that
Most of the 400
Plus albicans
A very firm resume
So very hard for us
Juice wrld
Flattering bearing press
I'm glad.
Communities forming and
Yeah I think the team did a good job in terms of marketing and
I'm so sitting up
Applications
Chain Reaction refer at least
Three or four of their best friends and I personally actually referred a number friends and I personally feel guilty about them not being
Affected
Uber support
My next question is
This is Sheriff bit more about yourself and 3 life expectancy
I noticed that you have lived in
8 different cities
So loved her more about it I personally need 9
So I know what that has done to me is I love to hear what
SWA
Sure
Laugh
Full Germany when I was 16 for college
And why was Andromeda number of internships
Bowser's backpacking
A random chip
Locations
And after that I'm up
States Refugee studies
And what's up what you doing College in
In Germany in German and you have there when you were 16 or 18
A1660
You start school early
I used to be in the program Car special class will give the young celebrity program with
Potomac High School
And the University of Science and Technology in China had a lot of Managua
The 1st of August
Tenure professor at Harvard
But at a time when I was 15
I look around in Enfield
Something was wrong I always felt I was rushing myself
And this accelerated pace of study
A person who failed or something more
July Stone
And it was one of the only
Animation
One that many people
Respect
Addition to actually go into the word instead of
Not going to college in Madison Beer
Basically prepare for the past
And in ritual perspective
I think you definitely are
Being
Open
Camping traveling
Across different
Countries at young age
In
The face in Michigan
Really helps to shape
A global mindset
And the building of this open-mindedness
I believe critical
And navigating through an Ever more increasingly
Call Blythewood sure and is nationally I feel that way helps me to understand
And appreciate and respect
Diversity and differences in cultures
Believes
And Society
Why did you pick Germany
Phone number places and then
Most of my friends in the states for grad school off of work
If I couldn't
Be the best
I like to be a little bit different
And I was a petrol head and everything two cars
Famoso Germany
Got it
And after
Germany
Lobotomy
What were the most
Play something about your money
That you didn't know
Before a discover we were there
And what were the things that impress you the most
I think there's one thing that impressed me most about Germany is
Time management
And dedication
They're almost
Same thing
Urban legends on China social media about how Germans are
Carefully curating managing and documenting everything
First of all
When I was imprisoned Jeremy Idaho
I really don't like mobile phone
Tavares
Normally
They actually have the lowest
Penetration penetration and also phone usage
And always CD country spell out here to get up by red on the economist
They would flaunt their friend and say
Believable
In September
The winter is coming should we grab tea together
On the second Sunday of November
Let me check my calendar to take out the little book
Find a date and going to be like
I'm available and let's meet for tea at 2 p.m. at your house and we never saw each other again I'm just show up
Incredibles so
Quaker time when I was a pain everybody's like
I've never laid and then berkeleytime 15 minutes late and in Germany in time is time
Managing of documentation I went skiing
And it was
Holiday season
Give me a prescription runtime
And then out of Despair I found
Optical Shop
Where I had my glasses
It's about 3 years ago
I gave them just my first and last name of course that's a record
And they have my record and emailed me over again
I like 10 minutes and I think this kind of dedication
Odoo documentation
Anti management
Made the Country Store efficient because you think in terms of building an a
Actual physical object
So many
Peace movement
You just have to be so meticulous and precise
So that's the takeaway
I wasn't very
Organized before
Honda oil change for you
As a big change for me and really helped shape
Make me feel better
Okay good
Yuan to the US
Square piston
Yes
Motion price in Philadelphia
When I first I was leaving my consulting job
Active mg when I was moving for
Costco Hunter Ashley comes on farewell party and email me the first week I was in space
Lima title sad
Hello David
How is
United States email sad
Is it really fun just like in the movies and really frankly when I first got into
The station
We actually had somebody
Renting house for house in Wilson West
I'm not sure it's basically Chicago
Slightly better
Or you could call 911 people come out
An hour because police demand
I don't want to be in danger
So
It was a huge shock for me because it's quite alright
From Europe in general and also quite different from the movie Tyson about States of America
Pie and friends and
Other things
Edison interesting parents
To see
How
The Landscaping of environment
In a different continent
And also in a
Play call system
And I wanted
Stay here for the record
10 is the one of the safest school we have a lot of
Security personnel
Yeah and then I take the retake care of everybody
TD Bank
I've been to UPenn couple times
Enjoy both experience
When I was there
So what prompted
Drawing app
And how long have you been an apple and
Do you ever get the
Bernard
Should bug
Did you something
That's a lot of questions I answer first why did I join in the first place
So my first show up to a grad school
I was at the Pinnacle
The Legacy branch of
I monitor
But which took care of all the Ever US agency
Public opinion monitoring
Consulting
On I did for about a year and I realize
Nice is not quite
Sing for me
Icing I enjoy problem solving and critical thinking
And quantitative things
Golden
My make mimosa
Especially in the public opinion talking about
And that was the end of
2017 I got a call from the cooter
At a point inside
Doing something cool
Intelligence
And I basically
PhD degree in electrical engineering
To public
Opinion consult
So if my picture section systems engineering
And my concentration
Is on human behavior modeling
So when we do is apply quantitative modeling
And the computer simulations
But to understand
And predict human behavior
My lab back in 80s now he's dead this
Profiling
Old world leaders
Unpredicted
Tripe
This week
Based on public speeches extracted
And formulated
Nazi models
And I personally wish my pissy work we actually published
How to predict a model
Coalition Dynamics in regions of conflict like Syria military factions Audiology claims
How they form
Call Esurance
Will see you tomorrow to do us election
Eye testing in 2008 and were able to achieve
A very highly accurate
Models
Appaddict
Zip code
How collectively people to vote for update
Appendix based on ideology
And that was
Interesting
Ideology
So basically if you look hot the US elections
There are published positions of those candidates
There also
The Annenberg national election survey of largest
Panel composed of
That was hosted by managed by the time
So
What they do is they ask
About
What are your positions on
The top
Six or eight issues
Slipknot art
Commercial
Including
Taxation welfare immigration
Uninterested
Curling
Pro-life and pro-choice
Corinth Topix
And I'm based on those
Questionnaire responses
You can basically place an individual
High-dimensional
Space
And then there also the
Ancient Enlightenment was
The published statements
Of the illegal Canada
And I know you can see you
Which candidate would give them a higher perceived utility
Invigilator noises and people are irrational or misinformed
Collectible noises
Cancel
Out form in your purse
Behavior
In terms of making
The better choice
Play for themselves
Fascinating
So from there with his go next
So from there I was one day given this report on Syria
About to friend Ida logical group
UPS in Syria
SF State Department for office use on it
And I traced back to the author of that document
Turn on Pandora.
Practice was an alumni
And so with a minor present
Once I reach home
It's pretty cool
Happened to work on this
The Intern
Antitoxin
What did The Internship
Meet you to tell them to go full-time offer Nashville
And I joined the firm
Being one of the first
The scientist
I love you technology
Help them to
Extract people is
The medical narratives
Anan
Tracing public opinion
Encore social issues
For a number of pi
Signs from your stomach
Unnecessary
Agency
And
The general customer
Horoscope from there too
I think it would help me to build a lot of more solid engineering
Technical skills
And I felt
It was this insufficiency for me personally
In terms of
And actually have a couple of offers
At the same time
I wanted them I still remember when
Br
Content strategy
She manager for Coursera
Deciding what Rotondo
How many products
Understudies
But my argument myself is that
I think it's easier to
Go with the technical track and Adrian track
When you're younger because
Everything faster in the morning verses
If I go for managerial Consulting tracking
Do an MBA I think it's
Much more difficult to
Come back to
Mechanical field because the pace of
Innovation
Ana peso
Change in the type what is just so fast
And I want to stay tuned
Until I'm ready
So you were in school at UPenn a retile operating about his research
And ends up working for monitor
And so does the internet become full-time
Then how did you go from monitor to
Swear words what city were you in for monitors lanzhou
There's three are former
Kumon
Pinterest
Okay
And then nothing for the barrier then how'd it go for monitor 2
I realized that
I would
Not sufficiently trained
And and Technical and Engineering background
For me I basically Middleton
Concord has to be better
A young age
To concentrate
On a technical track until I'm ready to mate
The jump entirely
Tube strategy
Look for Tech firms in
I wasn't looking
At a time
Until the end of Seventeen
And I got a call from recruiter
And I'll point
Ugly Heart
This really cool thing going on here
And where
Ending
A secret
AI project
Until you
October 1st
Phone conversation
Would you like to do the interview with us
And I didn't exactly
Is Fallout 4
What are you doing an apple now
Now you can share
I think for the OSHA tagline I am developing
Shiny hunting
Natural language
Understanding capability
Of Siri
And
That's all I'm allowed to say
Truck.
If you feel that by doing this theme
Prove your technical background and experience
I think it does
And I think one of the things I did not realize
I joined his dad
There's an inherent
Advantage
Two large Tech firm
It's a scale that
So when I was a monitor
Our clients are we looking at
Police auctions record the million half a million
Sizes of data and asking out
Wyan
This kind of probing questions
But an apple whenever we doubled neighbors and relatives
Future
We're serving in hundreds of millions a day
So I think that's really valuable
Burns and then also really helps you in and almost
Fortitude
To sing
And sing at a difference
And then when you are at Applebee's you ever
See anyone around you do a startup
How did you come to know about innovation in a
Explorer
Sure I think
SO2 colic departing
1-4
Self-driving the other one
Why don't you do ico's
Late for him to
But anyways
As an entrepreneurship I have always
In a firm believer
Startup life
In order to
To do great things
And I would say for anyone
With a mission
To realize their dreams they should
Try to work for themselves
Commander life
Or at least appear to Fairlife
To at least
To build something they believe in
And that's my
Personal credle so to speak
And I've always been seeking opportunities to do so
I have done
One side of back
When I was in grad school
And my last social apps that after you start funding
But in the same time I realized
Dongguan
Fashion
And we had a very competitive
Competitor
By the time we launched and didn't go quite well
Persisted to me
Truckin personally for me at this stage
I think I'm trying to be
Much
Technical background as I can but and also
Nepeta important actions
That will become you
When I do decide
And find out what I meant
I say you can race
$5000000
What will be your
Startup idea
That you will
Tailspin
I think there are two considerations hours
When I want to do start
1 East Howe
Confident I am
To realize
And secondly how
Image of a possum
I
I've always been
Actually don't be thinking about
In the area of
Strong
In general
Halogens
And language understanding
I think this will be
Critical trend
The next
4 reasons
That almost obvious
Number one there will be a new form and much more efficient
A natural form
Of human computer interfacing
So wouldn't using clicking and typing as major form of making with computer systems
Ever since the invention of
Mustafa Centre now
But
Don't cut program to
Just use our fingers going
Natural form of communication for anyone as we're doing right now
Aswetalk
And this really requires
This computer system
How to say
Capability
To fully understand and take in
What's our intent are
A language system would help bridge the gap
And I think it has two very important applications for 1
If you think in terms of human
Computer interface
This will help
To bring
Technology so much more personal
And Incredibly easy to use
Even people who have no computer skills at all
And now I believe there are plenty
And secondly their massive shows of data
Existing
In the anticipation
In a broader public domain
Star in text
And and not
In any other form
Anhui country of still doing
Streamwood matching
Define information and we have hummus reading analyst reading through
Pages of Shopkins from Prospectors
To due diligence documents to files and in Shreveport
To get maybe one or two
Useful pieces animation right
But what if the computer had
Speakability
To read
Thomas 10
To summarize
And also to
Do the Cure
In
An ear or superhuman
Level
I think there have been some sort of stew in the area
And some vertical Industries during this already but I think it's still a relatively underdeveloped field
That is inherently challenging
Ana procedure
Like challenging
Is natural language processing a very specific domain
Vertical use
People pay a premium for it
The benefits
Garden rakes
That's a good idea
So now you're at Apple Cupertino in the new campus amazing
Is very easy to
Just working for the rest of your life
Never leave
It's so beautiful and so self-sufficient
What prompt you to decide to apply for today
Movie Palace
The first of all about apples
Campuses in
Amazing
But
In terms of why I wanted
Apply for Lowe's
Obviously I do have
The dreaming long-term
To do something
And to be good at it
And make an impact
That's very tangible and personal
I don't believe
You can quite do that
And I normally
Organization
In any
Elevation Church
Secondly
I think we study current economic
Google trend
China is taking an Advil increasingly important bro
On what stage
Economically
It'll be a natural thing to do
To be in those environment
Just like an old-time she would have wanted
Venice
Florence
Milano to be a merchant I think they want to do a start of anyone
Adventure
You want to go to
Friendly and also the overall Society
Providing
Good foundation
And I'm cold
One thing I
Wired about
Repulsive
Steve Jobs
And he's finally it's going to
Intercede
The construction site
She appeared very
Upset
What is fellow man
Why
Aren't you happy about
He said he just realized
Everything
Not to bring this
Antidepressant comparison
Overall
For every single
And they will always be
The next big thing
It's important for those individuals
This weekend
To take the leap of faith
And commit
Twitter believe in
Opium
Eventually.
And I hope I
Along the way
It seems like you are also impressed by
Peter Thiel
I think you said
Marvelous
Brave
Intelligent
Person
He's almost
Contrarian
In a way
Awkward
And I've already spoken almost
Every single
Executive
Insomnia
Find China
Db-tour
Was talking about there is one
And talk about process of being something
Sing out of nothing.
Very helpful
Informative
The Writing Center
Salon
So I must
One week trip
In China
What you fellas
Who was the actual life speaker that you heard
That impress you
Besides people quoting Peter Thiel
I think it's
It's lingering the chief of staff Denver garage
Oyster
Social network site
4 video clip sharing
It's a very controversial service
And why did Chris
Search for
But some people
I think there are
Sharing
Distasteful
Boring or
Lowbrow hunting from tier 3 4 5 6
Yasso
Icing
That's the perception almost everybody in the class had before him come in and I think everybody else
I took a lot of you in there like
I'm through with gossiping and if you want to ask him very sweaty question
I know you all have this
Perception of these
Infamous company I work for but
Here's our mission
So he should have a love question
Which I really I could withstand without doing the wrong day that's why I stopped
Recording
Everyone
Faithfully
He said they're sweet sayings
Good in life
The truthful
The kind
And the Beautiful
If you think about Instagram and then there's two
The word for donations are the kind
And the question is the
Spectrum Business
To the artist
Composing a chimichanga with with a famous painting
I think a lot of stuff Working Class People
And for those who don't know it
It's like realism
Some paintings in French
19th century French
Los Arcos
Depicting the life of
Orchids
So basically is arguing that it's
Is a modem version
Of
Art
That is strictly recording the Daylights of people
Cool in a precautionary area
Worst employee
Emitted in history
My ass is kind of venal
Almond
An Eureka moment
Wow
This is what you're doing this is kind of eye-opening and really this astonishing
For everybody
We didn't know you were doing charity work
And I think to a certain time
It is
They were talking about Universal values were talking about
How was your
Everybody's looking at you to share I could have access to a
Very meaningful and deep conversation that was something
The most unexpected
Turn up volume
For attending
And I personally was very tough
Bye
Is kindness
And also their vision
At least there are other types of vision
As well as just
How open he was going to share a business
Regulatory hurdles
Question was facing when going so fast
So now what
Good
Any
Big takeaway
After 1 week
The things you learned
Or things that you feel
You can take away and help you
To do something
Dallas news
I think without a doubt it would be
Realism
Not quite shows
Style but I really think the sense that I think
A lot of us
I'm going to
Elite institutions
Looking at Big tech company
AR
Living in a bubble Sprite I wouldn't quite had
Choke grounding
In Market
Outside
Silicon Valley outside
Getting a real check
Stout
Slightly painful
Elizabeth discomforting
Fundamentally reassuring me personally I think
A lot of my friends and me personally had
Over romanticized
The idea of doing a startup
And really almost
Ignore menticide bones to extensive fantasizing
Catching exorbitant evaluations
After 6 months after 6 months after C Class
Of doing this marvelous younique
And reality when when we whittled companies
And talk to him
Read learn from all this founders
XNXX
Is odd
I think the idealism is there
Passion and
Urban legends some of them are truly real
But the
Amount of effort
Dedication
And the firmness
Of your face and bleed
Actually execute
And being persistent leader
Takes a lot of
A lot of
Perseverance
And he's like
I think night when there was a lot of curiosity and I came back with
I love respect
Hours of thunder
Twice
Well companies didn't do that well
But it is the hardest job on
TPS Honduras
Eoin
Meet your
Something
So
Smecu things that
No matter how hard I work this easier job
And like you said
We all have a lot
Respect
Yeah and then what
Kind of thing
Do you have any plans to return
China to work
In the future
And how would this what you learned
From this program
Impact youth makeup
Golang for
I think
Sociable in the long run
As I said earlier
The economy trends
Are really going towards
In favor of China
And in Asia and a lot of memory
Economy's
Pussy
Next
Send
It is natural thing to
To be there
To be on the ground
Anthem
You sent a woman
Fighting the battle
What to do today
This way helped me the program itself
Really helped me
Enjoy one
As I'm getting a reality check
To fully understand
And have that kind of breadth and depth
In such a short period of time
Is simply incredible in a parallel
And secondly also help
Salata social program
Boys are fellows
Turning Point
OK Google
Might come up
I feel this
Quit program that way healthy
Define duress
And and to make more informed choice
If you have any suggestions
For next year
How can we do it better
Make the next class will Conor
In terms of size of the class
I still think 36
What's good what do you think should be more
Wallace
I think it's about right
If any launcher
Italy
Difficult to build a cohort
Sense of camaraderie
In such a short period
I was 6:30
240 PP
Is brown rice a
Do you feel got to know almost everyone
I try to be a socialist I could
Not only I would say hi
Relativity
Three quarters
Then the last question
A fun question
It you got 10 days for vacation
This year
Where would you want to go
I'll go to Israel
Is Rose the other Silicon Valley other than Johnson
Candy and actual Silicon Valley
And I was almost going to go on the climb trip
Now at the beginning of 7:10
Then there was a terrorist attack
Buy the farm
So
Everlog racing
Whenever I go
I read
Israel
My Promised Land
About the
Hold on is it
And the moment the returning batteries
What's right now
And I would want
Thank you very much
Go beyond our podcast
Professional thank you hands and thanks everyone
Fraternizing
Digikala
Thank you
Now you will hear an interview with another of rggb fellow
Oh hun or hon baoding in Chinese
Went to Harvard for his undergraduate studies and graduated in 2014
And has worked as an engineer at Google as well as at a startup in La before returning to China last year
Sobo
Could you tell us more about your background where you're from and why you're here
Sure yeah I was born in Beijing
In 1992 and then when I was three
We move to Hawaii
And I lived in Hawaii for about 7 years
9 move to Connecticut my first stop in the mainland live there for a year
And I went to middle school and high school in Indiana
I went to college at Harvard
And then lived in San Francisco and Los Angeles
And then last year in
July I came back to Beijing
Why so I'm a co-founder and CTO at a tech startup with my cousin
And we're focusing on English education for the 0 to 6 age range
And currently most of our development happens on WeChat specifically WeChat mini programs or Sceptile
Why did you apply to Jadoo fellows
So before most of my life and work experience has been in the US
So I thought it was a really good opportunity to learn more about Chinese Tech
And also previously listened to the GV
Podcast a lot
Got a lot of that
I think you're quite special because I have a lot of friends
Who spend the vast majority of
Their life in the US even though they were born in China and they identify with the term ABC
American Born Chinese even though they were born in China
And they may not even
Speak Chinese
Even though you left China at H3 you're still extremely connected with
Chinese language and culture and still identify as like a Chinese person so
Could you talk about why that's
The case yes I think
Most of us are very influenced by our parents
Then my parents I think are pretty different from most
You know ABCs parents they study the humanities so my dad is a history professor
My mom study Chinese in college
So
From a very young age they really cared about me learning about Chinese history in Chinese language
I remember as a kid my mom pretty much everyday wood
Read
Like the Yuan like textbooks
With me
Even though it was at a slower Pace than
Black eye normal
What Chinese
Kid
But I think even
With all of that
After coming to China
I've had to downgrade my
Sense of my own Chinese ability so before in the US out consider myself like a
Supposed native speaker coming to China I feel like
I'm more of
At most like a middle school
A level Chinese
I think you're extremely fluent but I think a lot of it is
Not language but the
The nuances of the culture
Society
You can't get
In textbooks
Also the tongue use their married if so how has the adjustment
How long have you been
Been here so I've been here for about half a year
Yeah I think the adjustment has been
Free easy
I think mostly it comes down to the attitude where I'm very interested in Chinese culture and Chinese Tech
Changes that have been happening
In society
I think living in the US for so long I
I'm just so familiar with
Us society and US culture
That it's just really interesting to learn more about
A different culture but also
I feel like it's my own culture so out of connecting with my own
Roots
So can you talk about your experience with
Did you get fellows like
After you came and lower your expectations and how did the program
Yasso
I think
Even before ggv fellows I felt slightly overwhelmed because
In the group chat you sent like five or six different books in Chinese enough heck
I read like this
Book list
I started
I started reading a one of them
It's like
An overview of like 2008 to 2000
And then I started kind of timing myself so you know I've read one chapter like how long would it take for
Finish this book
That I realize that I couldn't actually finish the five or six flags
I meant I didn't actually finish that book by the time the event started
But I think after
Going into like going into the event
I realize that you know I could follow along and then
Everyday was really action-packed
But it was kind of like a fire hose of just fire hose style learning really just got to
Overview of a lot of different Industries and then also companies at various stages even though
I think the
Early stage company was still pretty large like series series
Possibly
The companies we interact with Warrior course but there were a few that were morally
Yeah
So what was something I left
The most impressionable
Yes I think there's two aspects one is the
The actual companies
That we learned about so I think
One of the really interesting companies for me was mocha
The co-founder
He left China I think I was
Dahlia
So he went to Berkeley for college and then most of his work experience was also in the US but he came back to China
I know I think when he was like 23 or 24 something like that
And he decided to go into the 2v industries
I thought was really
Interesting
Given that he didn't have a prior experience but it seems like he has a really good attitude toward
Like learning
Just talking
A lot of different
People I think that's a really good
Skill set to
So why did you identify with
I think his Outlook is very
Like Silicon Valley
Inspired I think it's just inspiring how he managed to build a company
Even though he didn't have like
Prior experience
Area or
In China
So you have worked in Google in Mountain View and also a startup in
La
How would you compare what you saw in the
Us like the text-based there verses
We're seeing here what are the
Major
Difference
Both just people's attitude and work
So I do think in general
People
Well there's there's two aspects to it so one aspect was listening to the ggv podcast I got the impression that
Every company was very
996 all the time all the employees were nine and six
Had a little bit like Sweatshop like
But I think after visiting the company's I've gotten a little more nuanced understanding or like to gvr
Not judging you but not in sex is more of like a
Mindset where
People are
Thinking about
Work more often then
People evaluate I think that stuff
Play true especially
Within like
Co-founders Earl
Like higher level
Companies
They're kind of constantly thinking about
You know how to run their company and I think
Part of that possibly stems from the amount of competition that exist in China
We're like
Once you have someone success for
Seemingly successful business model you'll have a lot of
Competition
That comes in and it seems less the case in soccer
Valley
So what will be our biggest
Rough couple takeaways
From Judith
What are the interesting takeaways was
The other fellows who would have very good job opportunities in the US there very seriously considering quitting
China
I think that really contrasts with
A lot of the
People who immigrated to the US in the
In the early 90s
Mason Lake
Basically my parents generation
I think the mindset back down was if you
You could stay in the US
Say I think
I think that's a really good sign
Yuan for China that
It's able to attract
These people back
Even better sinus
If you're able to attract
Completely
Like completely different immigrants right think that's a sign of
The health of a cup
For you
Do you feel
You're welcome in China do you feel like it belongs
Yeah I think so
Although the funny thing is in Beijing a lot of people
Ask me like are you Japanese all right. Cuz they listen to my Chinese and they think it's like a little bit off
But I haven't actually experienced that in southern China maybe it's because
It's like you just have a different accent
Yeah
And I think the more someone has spent time in the US interacting with ABC's
The more they're impressed with my level of
Chinese
And then the more someone is actually like completely native Chinese the less they're impressed
Your Special K is for our fellow so almost everyone is what we call a highway or overseas return
Cool probably left China from like 16 to 20 something
To attend
Palo Duro High School or grad school in the US or other countries
And then they may have worked in the US for a couple years and now considering coming back but you laughed at it really
So when you were speaking with the other fellows did you feel like
You had a different perspective on certain things
Then the rest of them
I think so I mean I think for me even though I don't purposefully try to do it and I think so
Consciously a lot of my thinking is still impacted by kind of American or like Western
Ways of thinking
But I think
Having grown up in a Chinese household as well a lot of the I can understand
And sympathize with a lot of like Chinese ways of thinking
As well
Things that came up that was interesting to me was when we visited face plus plus
Yeah so I think
There was
Or there were two
Other Americans in the group so Fisher and bench and I think they brought up a 7
Like privacy issues
And
I think listening to them talk about like privacy issues I could release some thighs with that as an America
At the same time
As a Chinese I could predict the Chinese response because I I think I live through that
Yeah yeah yeah
I really think that's a gift
I think most people
Can only lift their life and
B1 now the other but where
Living in an age where you can actually
Peoples
Sympathize or empathize with
Both sides of the story end
Identify with
A larger
Set of people that was really one of the biggest
Takeaways from living in Indiana
So previously when I was living in the US in Hawaii like
Hawaii is a very Asian state so like if you're Chinese you're just kind of part of the majority
Culture
And then after moving to Indiana I think
Even though I
Grew up as an American people saw me as a Chinese so then I ended up you know having to explain
A lot of like Chinese culture and like
People would have preconceived notions of like what Chinese people are
And then also like when the 2008 Olympics happened they would ask me oh yeah did you know like the Chinese gymnasts
Taking their interview stuff like what do you think about that
So yeah I think living in
The Midwest actually really shaped my identity as well as a Chinese person I think it really reinforced
My sense of
Okay maybe I'm not completely American-made maybe if someone grew up in
San Jose or the bay area where everyone else is an immigrant
That maybe their understanding of what an American is would be very kind of emigrated
So was it a difficult
Decision for you to
To move
To Beijing because you have not left
Care for life
Over a decade
No it wasn't it wasn't difficult at all
I think
What really helps was the fact that
My parents had moved back to
Or they move to Hong Kong in 2012
So I no longer had any family are in the US
And then also coming to Beijing
I'm working on my startup with my cousin so I think just having that family support
Crossword help
That also when I was working in the Barrios
And La I was pretty Frugal so I like saved up some money so I think that helped with the risk
Terrace Park
And you see yourself here in
At least a few more
Yeah yeah as long as I think you know
Funding doesn't tryouts that's why
Could you talk a little bit about the startup
Yes so we're targeting a026 age range
What's the name
Oh yeah it's called your mama
Archery
And
So we're focused on the 0 to 6
Age range
And mostly developing mini programs that foe
Focus on content
And then also
Games that center around that contest
So trying to
Expose
Chinese kids still like
English content and then trying
Air Force
The concepts
And you say you're mostly baoding
The product around which how many
Any program
So that's quite different from what you're used to work on the states did you have to learn everything
Again
I think
The fundamental programming aspects are
Pretty much the same no matter what new framework
Comes up
But definitely the details of implementation are
Are different I had to go through a lot of
Documentation in Chinese
Which
Involved like looking up a lot of
Words and then also going through like differ
Tutorials and then also learning how developers in China kind of
Works where do they go when they have questions
News about bugs
How to how to
It's not something
So as long as you're good smart engineer and you can read Chinese it's not a
That difficult adjustment
Because I think
Fundamentally most programmers are
Lazy which is a good thing so
Whenever you hear this new completely new framework it's usually built around something that kind of exists
Already because it it doesn't make sense to reinvent the wheel
So like
WeChat mini program it
Kind of sounds like completely new but it's actually built on
You know JavaScript
Wxml which is similar to HTML
And then also W
Access
As switches like CSS
So like if you know if you're familiar with web programming it actually
Is pretty familiar
Cool so
Is there any last words you want to say maybe
To either or audience or perspective
Gdb fellows applicants
Yes I think given my background I really want to
Encourage other
You know Chinese Americans are
Members of the Chinese diaspora to really
Keep in touch with China you don't understand
History especially recent history maybe like why your ancestors decided to go abroad
I think that's really interesting
I also think from a practical perspective it's really important to learn Chinese
Yeah there's a lot of
Unexpected
Opportunities that you can get just from that
Language ability
I think like
When I was in high school
Never would have expected the Chinese tech industry to have grown
This level and back then I would never have been able to predict that right now I would be in China like working
In China it's possible because you
Okay cool thank you
So that's all we have for today's episode and if you're interested in applying to attend the next batch of ggv fellows
Program in January 2020
Please join the 906 WeChat group in slack Channel
We're all related announcements will be posted
You can join these groups by visiting 96.2 gbc.com community
Airline flight 879 89.5
Listening to this episode
960 is a multi-stage venture capital firm based in Silicon Valley Shanghai and Beijing
We have been partnering with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past 18 years from seed to pre-ipo
With 6.2 billion dollars in capital under management across 13 funds tgv invest in calcium
Humor new retail internet Enterprise cloud and Frontier Tech
GTB has invested over 290 companies with more than 45 companies valued at over a billion.
Dollars
Formula companies include Airbnb Alibaba C trip
Didi chuxing Domo hashicorp hellobike cows keep Slack
Square Hotel wish soundtrue white white and others find out more at G G
Qvc.com we also highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat group as La China where we regular
Play Cher inside events and job opportunities related to attack in China join these groups at 9
Text. G gbc.com community
Recommended gas please email us at 996 at gbc.com