Hi everyone we're excited to announce a new program
Ggv fellows
Designed to help sea turtles or a highway
Chinese students studying overseas
You got to know the Chinese entrepreneurial landscape better
As a sea turtle myself I know that many of those worried that were not CD cheat enough
Go back to China
Like a local network
We're worried whether we can survive in a fiercely competitive market
Where most people work 9 9 6 if not 007
This program is designed to address those concerns
If you were Chinese student or professional who is studying or working overseas
Or have done so in the past
This is a program designed for you
Is Wigwam program in January 2019
In Beijing
During most u.s. colleges winter break
You will be able to learn from Executives as some of China's most available to come
And visit some of their offices
You will also participate in mixers with students at top Chinese universities like chinqua and beta
To build a local network
Please visit
Stellos. GG abc.com
For the application link and for more information
Once again that's fellows. Ggvc. Com
Vincent wrestler
Hi dear
Welcome to the nine at six podcast brought to you by ggv capital
On the show interview movers and shakers
China's tech industry as well as Tech leaders who have a us China
Cross-border perspective, managing partner at ggv Capital and I've been working at startup
Investing in them in both the US and China for the past 20 years
My name is Zahra Jones I'm an investment analyst ggv capital and a former journalist
Why is the show called 98696 is the work schedule than any Chinese Founders have organically it
Adopted that is
9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
To us
996 captures intensity Drive
In speed
Of Chinese internet companies many which
Are moving faster they even their American counterparts
Hi everyone
On the show today we have Grant horsfield
Who is Chinese name is Colton Chung
Very ambitious name
Grant is the founder of the luxuries work company naked group
And the co-working space
Make it hot
Grand is from South Africa and first came to China in 2005
In 2007 Grand started naked group
With his wife Delphine rural properties in China for rental and tourism
And its Flagship Resort is located I'm organization a beautiful mountain 30 minute drive from Hangzhou.
Prioritizes sustainability and Design
Anika Resorts visitors can immerse themselves in nature and enjoy being away from City Life
Take a sleeping Farm Stables ride horses climb mountains
And the environment encourages them to retreat and their themselves to Nature
Naked group Pioneer the concept of Yeshua in China
Which translates into wild luxury
A concept of combining Renee Trawick luxury hospitality
In 2015
Granny Delphine start of the Cold War contain
Make it pop
Which also focus on Environmental
Sustainability
And stripped-down architecture
Make it hot offers several services
Open Office
Private office
Hot desk
And I'll have
10000 members
Across 24 hours locations
Built-in shelf haidian Beijing
And Isis pendant Australia Hong Kong to Vietnam
April 2018
A month ago github
And we weren't announced that they would join forces to support business in China
If Roy's
Welcome to the show
Thanks thanks guys
Happy to be here
So that start with your personal story
Why did you move to China in 2006 instantly
My family and I movie time so I can fly
Around the same time
But you were from South Africa
You were successful entrepreneur
Why did you decide to come to China
So
Yeah could question
I've done an MBA and it
Teacher electric give me a story about China which really
Caught my attention
It was a
A crazy entrepreneurs story where the guy wind up
Bringing chicken
Making a whole bunch of money in 6 weeks
Height of 6 month
And it was
So you did the good people here if anybody just went by the pear
The thing about the story was interesting is that it was about selling to
And nobody in that time was thinking about that
Everyone
About buying from
So I came here thinking will let me let me come in and
Blow this place
And maybe something will catch
And when I was here I was searching constantly searching for
That's what I thought it was I thought it was something from
Forget that I was going to bring to China
And author of
You're in the hall
Where is xur
What company invests buy Knotts pass
Investor in tencent yes exactly
I realize that what was missing here was lifestyle
It's difficult to explain to people
What you don't know you don't know
When the people here
Donuts great City but they just didn't know
Having a couple of small tank
Howard University
Cape Town hit business and quechan it's real lifestyle set
Front where people genuinely live life more than they were
What is the opposite of China
Yeah
Baseball 30 years ago no one thought of it when we when we
What I was really trying to do was
So the problem of myself
Give me something else to do rotting.
2 bars and restaurants and stuff
And I live like a little
But that experience
I guess
Was what we ended up importing
So we didn't importapart
Hijabi bribe Delphine to move with you
Wife to move to China
2002 design Xin Tian Di
Original
So she was more successful that you
If I had none
How successful she was I would have been too nervous to
You know I saw a pretty girl like exactly exactly
But just as a as a heads up Delphine was always involved with me but she said she remained as an architect in a separate company for men
NES whilst I started
Naked
But I must say
I could never have done any of this without her she's the
I see the the
The drowning that I need in life
And then so I have to credit
Fort Parkway those who haven't been to China
Cindy Woods
Is the place to go to in Shanghai and go to the bike
The first modern
Plaza
With money from from Hong Kong
Yeah that's right
Grand I wonder what about like the environment you grew up in inspired your interest in nature
Everyone's influence body back
I was very very placed I grew up in a in a little town called knizner witch
I think it's probably one of the most beautiful corners of South Africa I went to a school it was
In the bush
Let me know.
It's just
The country song
And I was there from 5 is oldest
Scion you in Hunter X yet
I didn't know the city or towns ionian HIV you learn
We did survival camping from
9 years old
Will you just dumped
In the bush with no parents no pictures no nothing
Like for me I'm formal come to always say to Delphine like when we in the countryside
I can never get you anywhere but put me in a shopping center
You know I think that
1 background influences you and in Africa
I don't know what I sent to find
African people tend to have a
An affinity to love and care for nature
So this is something at
It's very important to me now
In my life about
Not only what we've contributed to China and the way we build sustainable and operates
Sustainably but now getting food
How we can perhaps use our influence
To help
Save some of the animal problems that we're having
Yeah I think your background
Always comes back to
How you draw a pig
If you done
If you can
If you experience that your whole life and then you come to some way with it isn't essentially any night chat
It's kind of obvious in stock
How difficult was
Set free to start naked Resort
In China
Wow at ya mean
The stories go on and on I mean it was never easy no businesses
Was it
Easy to to do what I did
I think there was a element of
Look for me in the fact that I was at
African and a farmer
When you go out to
The countryside uniform is anywhere in the world are the same
But
I meant for me just dealing with
The farmers in Morgan Saint was
It's no different from dealing with a farmer's where I drop
So I don't have a great
Set of ego to Woodside
Maybe I have a big ego no Krishna
That looks like your Chinese name
I didn't give myself at night
The dead man was an air conditioner change my name
No
The thing is
It it Chinese real people
As long as you come down to
They label
Drink baijiu
Get to know them
B
Genuine with them
They fall in love with you
You just like any other
Rural people
So that was my
That was my
Benefit that other people didn't have
But having said that
What is go funding
UltraStar
Well that was interesting song permit
Yeah
Look
So we start small in China I think that's my advice to anyone get you grounding office result wasn't
Very big was 21 room
Skip
So we just needed a few million dollars it wasn't
That expensive
We did use some friends
To help
Envestnet First Resort
Animus
Tell you that was the first time I realize that I never want other
People's money I knew straight away like
They kept asking me like
So how's it going with the performance you going to give me a report and I said no
It's going fine and that's good enough
And then soon very soon I was like I don't want anything to do that so when we build
Naked Stables Witcher
She's a huge
Ambitious
Just talk
I decided not to toot
To get any investors IU
Used it
As the primary source of money
And I know it was the greatest thing I ever did because always see naked Stables we got a massive
Unlock
We don't but I took a massive game
Very very
Into
Of course
Away from me that actually was in my account
You didn't use it
But anyway
How did you survive through that
Sneezy had a heart attack
Sears item by myocardial infarction
And I think
Women entrepreneur
Wind things
The worst
Is that defines
Who you are and
I need money
What's up
Nothing else was going to solve my problem
So
I've been searching and I found two people that were willing to
Blenders
Loan shark money
I mean
Crazy stuff
I need it in a month
And they trusted they they looked me listen
You look
Trustworthy trustworthy I never had nothing to Leverage
Other than you know my smile
And I bet they help me out and Buzz
Desperately wanted equity
Buzzfest
And then and then I made it through in it
I wish music
If I ever got the product finished
It would work
I proved that with the 21 RoomPlace 21 room place with David make money
Island
Later in business in hotel business
That scale is
Very very much
And them
So I knew it would work I just had
To get that I have to just
Survive long enough
Always been my mentor
To being an entrepreneur
Stay alive
As long as you can
And if you stay alive
Ultimately
Come out of
I also wonder what people thought of your idea that time because
That concept of combining nature and luxury was pretty much unheard of in China
Luxury was like an oxymoron because
People Associated the Wilderness was like hardships and like peasants and it's there really think of that as what
Like people with
The middle class would do right
Show me Rhapsody ride at least two sides like this my friends and mine best isn't they thought I was mad
Everybody was a
Ron seriously what were you cannot gun for that amount of money
In the middle of nowhere
No one's going
End
It was a lot of that
To be honest I don't think they was
It was maybe one or two
People that
Even gave me the
Slices
They just wrote me off
And said this guy's nuts
If I didn't have much
Unlike today
Sinuses is regarded as Resource Center
It was nothing any
You must know that
In my heart I knew that
People would need lifestyle but they would need to enjoy
But coming back to the
Consider that the idea of trying to keep
The natural
Environmentally friendly and stuff like that
That wasn't
Creative
Marketing
Idea that was just because that's who Delphine and I are
If we have to build anything
It would be that way
So we can talk just to give you a context and when I took Delphine on honeymoon
It was in the Land Rover where we slept on the roof
Land Rover driving through Africa six countries in Africa
Sleeping
With the Lions
Amazing
And her parents
Come home, that was very very very upset with us
Lego like
This is ridiculous
I don't think people understood in China but
But I did realize that I'll name
The Chinese name Luis
That's
Helped every
Because in a way
No one at put those two characters
Heather before and when we did that occur
It kind of made a new word
And it ended link tonight Channel with pure and I was just
Authentic and people fell in love and I kind of it was just a day I remember it so clearly it was like
The result
Just was full
And I was like
All right
Everything's going to be fine
And if our listeners who don't speak Chinese voice in me is naked heart
How did you come up with his name
So
I have to take credit non-chinese speaking person but I did we got lots of
Import from bears
People different names
And there was a friend of ours you ask
He gave us those two characters
Is together
I'm about to
We did a survey across all company and no one liked it
Except me
Anna and I
I said that's the name and no other that's where we going
They would like not as terrible idea
To be fair she was
She was
She was ambivalent
To the idea she was like okay.
It's okay it's not okay but whatever you say will do that sir
So I have to take care of his cooling that as the name that we're going to be a long time.
Are the company in 2007
Actually finally hit on lotion in 2009
So it wasn't something it was
From day one
So when when you first have to go out as the brand
We had to find the first custom customer feedback
What was it
Exit
Instant
Like almost like we would like some
Sage
What's up
Buddhist Plaquemine
Okocim
You like DP spiritual person
That's so
I am I too but we know that
But it was cool and and today
Poetry about a girl
Copious
Number
All the time
Frenchman's
And is losing everything
Everywhere
And always trying to use out trademark but
I guess that's been
We should be proud of that.
Or do I have it
And stuff
When I got here cuz my name is Grand I was given this name Kellen turn on speak any Chinese I was trying to learn Chinese
The time
And
And that allows what you mean
And we looked up this like billboard where the air conditioning company writing galenta is it that that's my name
Best color change immediately
So into the HR and I said
Can you come up with the name
I think that would
They must be having ships and giggles
I didn't know
Personality so they figure you can live up there
Yes I'll given this name but
In moments and nobody knows Grand
Holtsville know any English
Yeah it's like Anyway logo
I don't even know that
Started building that place I wasn't even City
I know but in a way I didn't deserve
That at that time I should be doing
How much to drink in Asia
Oh I'm a king abijah I have consumed every buy Jabra
Friend and
Huge quantity
Pizza by George
But remember that
By Joe in those days was was it wasn't for me
It wasn't a scary thing it was like a necessity
The sum of those house with soap
Cold in winter
My feet would be
Frozen and if I wasn't drinking goodbye Joe we would survive
The body was a full moon
Fuel to stay alive but
I got to know
Old families
Getting
Horribly drunk and doing stupid things like shaving each other's hair off
One night I'll tell you a story I've been having this mess
Altercation with Lamar
And llama eyes
The stone Manor
The Villages he was
Kind of like a
Lily said the alpha male
And me and him at Walmart
Kyle little
Different from Jack Ma
Skinny but strong
We started drinking and then
I realize that it was a ghost
Everyone
Sites like hidden away
In the forest
I said to him come you and me we're going to go to sleep
Just the Two of Us
And you would like
Scrapy
See you scared if I could get him there
We would resolve out
He would have to tell me show me it's fear or I would be able to look
You know like
Give him comfort and we might fight
As long as I get into the ghost
Damn you
Define let about like I don't know
1 in the morning
Kilauea family
We make a little fight inside the house in the middle of the house with no chimney
1 bit
And was broken
And I said you can have the bed I'll
I was drunk song
Animal lookup
See installed sitting on the bed
Couldn't sleep
He was terrified
And I should have said
You want to go back home
CJ's liquor
And I was at we were self
From then on we're best friends he thought I was a hero and I will probably tell you
That I'm I'm a Rockstar so that's how we solved our problems
Getting drunk and doing silly
So that's a great lessons for anybody from us
Was expanded
Do wasps bite you'll go to a ghost the haunted house
Before you talk about a naked have one more question
Back then
Going to Mohegan Sun is like
Picking out Las Vegas in the middle of nowhere
Why won't
30 miles outside of
Ya Abdullah people things
This is like some
Decision was looking for was a place that was
Quiet
Even more detailed
I'm looking for a place at the end of a road
So where they wouldn't be
Sidibe
It's not a transient place
It's a place that you go to Anna
So my wife and I and my cicatriz
Diamond and various people
I used to go on these like trips
Outside Shanghai just looking
A quiet place
To get off the main roads
All the signage and everything was in
In-N-Out
Chinese Chinese characters
Beijing Jeep
So you know
It was quite
Trying to get off the Beaten Track
Was never that easy
I'm so one of these trips actually took a bicycle
With a group called birdy bikes
And fortunately the guy was useless
And when we got lost we actually stumbled across this little village
Sanju which is on the Morgan Channel and I was like
The whole village
Pretty much desert
Did they was 12 old
And I just fell in love and I said this is it
I found it
And actually signed the lease that day
What's a lanai
Who is husband just passed away but
She was so happy that I was coming into
Shell House with it
Anderson
Business was just lonely sport elec
Amazon on Old buildings
Later on we ended up buying
The Landing
Jesse Melanson wasn't like some
And I'm like I win detail research on a slope for a quiet place
Nantucket whale
Heartbroken
Traction did you gather for Nick a resort like I heard like the rooms are booked out all the time what kind
Have people go there
Yes
92% of all customers of Chinese
People don't realize that that mean we talked about naked knowing that you know is the word naked only lotion is really what is
Famous
In China and that was always on
Emission put in the early early days
Publix Gateway
Yeah my friends mine
Network somos Foreigner
No I've always believed no matter what you do
If you make a good product
Anyways good restaurant if you make good food
Yukon felt good food bodies really important
People mistake that
Resort
It's about the experience
So it isn't about the room it isn't about
The food it's about
The actual experience
People sometimes forget that
Pulteney place in China
I don't think the
That we have that good
At what we do
You think that everyone else is that bad
And because no one is actually bugs
Stop trying to back that nobody was trying to
But still today even
People voting results all the time
Connecting something to
Famous
The part about like sex League
Experiences
They just build
Hotels in the mountains
This Is Random
But I think that that's going to make money
So let's talk about naked hot which is your co-working space
What motivated you to go into this space in the first place
Transitioning from luxury resort to a co-working
Yes I think the shed economy is something
It's always intrigued me I people don't realize but our results are actually
Like very much part of the shared economy
Very unusual from any Resort you'll see anywhere in the world
Naked Stables
This is at
81 of 121 rooms are actually shared villas with multi
Ballroom
Meaning that people traveled as families
Groups of friends
And people are actually sharing it
Something that
A lot of society
Forget stuff
We used to do hundreds of years ago
Site to desktop
How people lived evil Georgia
People's homes Bo
Travelin Man
And spend time with you
So that's kind of gone
And Donnie time we get together with people today seems to be in restaurant
But so when we did that it was kind of bringing people
Together and that intrigued me so
I wish I realized that
You know we could scale this business.
The coworking business very fast a tile design
Ideas my wife and I had we could
Maybe be more creative
And what we have more chance
Do things end
To be very very Frank
Like
Co-working office Texas
3 months
To build
There was one
It's kind of like
Struggle with like getting satisfaction United like this feeling of like a
Oh yeah that's beautiful we've done it
It takes so long
Give this this is like
Just right where we going to get
Real insta
Satisfaction instant gratification
People also thought I was crazy
Being so aggressive
In the early stages
But
We saw immediately that
The future was
Was this
This idea but I didn't actually know the business that well
I just got jumped into it and then alone
On the job could you first heard about it elsewhere
And don't say we can do better
Yes
A friend of mine
She said I should we should do it and
But I really didn't explore what it was all about we just kind of played with one or two and then
Very quickly and people
And we enjoy doing it so it was
I could process
At that time where there a lot of other co-working spaces in China already
No and they still on
Because I don't believe most of the people of dream coworker
But no they were they were I think 3Q Hadfield one play
That was pretty much
So does pretty early on
Bahamas
Call my mom
Flipping jug just for
Passaic City
This is
I think
Coaching at San Vicente
Just so Random
The people think
It's spacing
And already lost in space
Is so far from
Space
That
But no one in
China seems to get that
Which is
Kind of random for me
And I
Even though I talk about it all the time and I've done interviews about it all the time Adam Newman speaks about it all the time.
Continue just to
To treat this is a
Likely strain Space Marines.
TCU what are the
Five things
What three things
That you had to get a ride to make your
A lot more popular
The most and alphabetics.
So the most
Is being able
Let your members
Connect with each other
Without being invasive
I do that
True physicals
So you'll designing of the
How do you trade
The common area
Where people feel
Comfortable to come together and meet each other
And that's really important
Essentially
Trying to break down the barriers
Jean company the more that companies can interact with each other more businesslike
Which of the most successful
Standing up to smaller they can keep the company
Search by using other companies
To solve some of the problems
An end we see today
Like so many more smaller companies operating
This is the future is no question
Physical space the second part was the technology to allow p
Outside of the
How can I promote my business How can I
Promoted William How can I
I connect with other people in members Etc
And that was the technology platform which Nobody Does by the way
Yeah we work an acre
Being in a very
Effective way we spend a lot of energy on that
And I think that the sad part is
Scale
Realizing that
That you can run this as a moment pop operation joint like a hood
Credit union network
Exactly so
Yunnan Hotel
If you don't have enough rooms you'll never make money unless you are a home operated like
The mom and pop breakfast exactly
So this is the same
If you really want
The sexy Gap have
Huge ambitious
To change and then realize that you are a solution
Orlando
You are not renting from them
But you have to do
Just like a hotel no one's going to sign a management agreement with you if you haven't done it before
So you have to invest to earn money
Spices and then the landlord realized we don't have to
To be compared that we can work together so that's what happens today
We just find manager
But you have to prove
That's what
I read these stories in the internet constantly like you know
Aren't you
Exposed
HELOC what happens if the rental market changes in
You know suddenly you know
Global rent
When that hurt you
But it wouldn't
Be significant because most of the deals we do on linked
Yunnan
Liability of rent
Reckon partner
Fight between
Sucks those are the factors that really
Most
I'll praise Duncan
And you have to be a good part at the same time
People the Wonder Man
If you are eight
You clearly a guy was just in
For the short-term
Big landlords
No you're not.
So for you did you take out some money this time
Your descale cooker
Will Sonny this I didn't choose random
I'm so firstly we invested heavily by self
We've had some law
I'll positive cash flow
Antutu running this business
And then in
We did Abby wrong
I would have pushed I'm by the way I've never done
Equity fundraising round in my life
And I might
Repotted
But in the beer and we did a
Convertible
Note right eye with the go capital and
Trustbridge
And another company email
And
And so these guys
We were imminently about to close I'll see round which was in
Was was finally
Inequity like finally
How to use a big round it was
Big valuation in
That's when we work stepped in
And so the guys that were in the beer and they had the opportunity to convert
Just an hour before the transaction
Husband
So is effectively speaking you can say that that be round was a
Account
Only for one hour
You know that
I am old-fashioned
But I really don't like the idea that entrepreneurs
The throne money
I buy in distance I think it's
Afloat
Thing
It's work for a lot of company
Lots of cameras
I think entrepreneur
Should have
More skin in the game
I think the other one profitable business
They should come with a LifeStraw
You know really
Black feel what it's like
Imminently bankrupt
That's what I want to see more entrepreneurs like today in China
Disguising
Get other people
Anyway that's
I'm old-fashioned
Got it
And I know I'd I can honestly now I don't need to do fuse other people's money so it's fine
So I'm good I'm done with
It's holy
Using alipay
But I thought you were in a race around and expand
So you know technically yeah with the mudra I am no longer executively involved
Didn't make it home
I'm on the board my wife and I
Will continue to advise
And we are hoping on this
Fundraising round.
But it's not my company Tinashe holder
I'm just not.
I'm not the alpha male anymore
I know one has to listen to me I can bring
You know advice
On the direction
So what punk music
Do Duster
Look
Operating that there is only good at projecting the division in the
The bread.
Yeah what you doing
Look
This business
We were going to what competing on two fronts
We compete
Appropriate position
So where we making these deals with various landlords
And that hurts on the one side
And with we fighting for the same custom
You know
Normal competition is healthy
Between companies
When you competing literally on
Two friends
The same company
And that company
Has a lot of other people's money
I knew that they really
Didn't care about how much they lose you heard me
And I've seen enough story
China news
Scene
I also
I had a good connection with Adam we met
He made a big
He should have
Taking me out two years
A whole bunch of uber as well
And so
He
You know I like where you was going and honestly we work had the same
Ideas of
Yes really you guys are very like we just
Let the money making on the real estate wanted to figure out
How to solve a bigger penis
Hillsborough clerk
So
You know we had a very very strong
Technology team hair design team in
Hospitality Street things we were
It didn't happened
Nnnn
Realized
Hospitality as much
So we brought that hospital to take ideas
We haven't
And just good partnership and I'm very very
I think we did
Exactly the right thing
For the success
The bug company
Do you not stay in operation V clearly with their balance
I'm not employable
Will end in inches everyone will be unhappy
I see the Moda or just some of it will just not worry about yourself
I knew this many many many years ago that's why I became an entrepreneur
Go back to school
I need anyone to tell me anything
Maybe I should just say hey Grant would you please go and do that I just wanted to tell me
So I was like okay I'm really bad at
Being told what to do.
I know that that one work but
I still have a big role to play and we were
And I don't know
What exactly that's going to be and how that's going to happen but
I believe in this industry
And I really believe in what we doing
So you know I will find a way to something besides Resorts and co-working space
What will be a surprise
Yeah.
I am very passionate about something
A big big problem
Huge problem
That I want to solve
Which is on
Which is the fact
The teachers the worst
Until I Bean
Exploring this a lot
I've been thinking about this a lot I spend most of my awake I was thinking about this problem
I tell people
Sometimes that
50 years ago when you went to University didn't go to university
Because it was the name of the University
Hobbits
You went there was a professor that you wanted to study under
Yep and
You know when you
When you let her go
Fishing it was someone he told you fishing off
Riding a bicycle cost
Everything was about teachers
Lost
Today they are the whisper people
So I'm we have this concept kuebler
Which is
The idea of it is trying to reverse that and make teachers
Fundamentally don't
Revista
And make the University
Hiya
The teachers on
Consulting basis employment
And if I can find a way to make
Good teacher
Just go up to the top and go down to the bottom system
I believe we can
We can make
The most wealth
In the world this is obviously potential Global business
What would face one look
So we've already tested face
We tested in a very small narrow area and Wellness
Yoga teacher
That was an area where I could
Explore the idea of simple and narrow and Edibles amazing control
Teacher to make 20 times more money than they can
20 time
Electricity in China in Shanghai
Russia we never said that's the area of microcosm built the soft they rolled it up
Bulla
And the teacher that used to work for
Wine glass
Studio
That on our platform
Let make 20 times more
20 times more money
Tulsa possible what's simple
The institutions of today make all the money I mean by the institution is
The Hobbit
Not the school
The Wine Place
Peach the OnePlus
Studio
Someone had the money
To rent
Space just put it out make it pretty
I need used and abused
The teachers who actually the hero
And why the teacher isn't the hero
No one remembers that teaches Toyota have co-working Space 2
Co-working space
Do help having that space
Espaces everywhere you just don't realize it
So we found
Spaces
Think think
Hotels
The gems and
Restaurant so you need a technology platform that allows the booking of those things
Exactly
It's so much space
Investor in a company
Yeah you do
When I get to Round Rock
I really believe it needs a lot more thinking and I'm
I'm I really want to figure out
Quesadillas
A small at the beginning now I think
I can really disrupt
Everything
Can you have Juno help
Deep teaching.
The key Things Are
The space and hyperspace you got to have a $2
You got to have the industry relationship
EasyBib
So now I have for anyone else
That is not easy yeah I have a lot of space around the week
Second largest
Can we water on have more more services
They don't want to speed in renting space
Exactly
That they're my company
How are you spending your time these days how do you split your time between this
MS project
We are naked harbin naked
Yeah so we still have this integration going on between the two companies not an emergency Z
Yeah this is a challenging time
We're in a lot of emotions happen if
People feel nervous and
Stop saw so I'm still playing an active role there
Supporting a little bit on wework
I'm doing this fundraising round way I can help
I
I am well quite a new number of new resorts on the development so I spend
A fair amount of time on that I'm still the only person that can me and my wife but
On the monster planning side
With only people that can do that
Looking at
How the result
Will XD
And I look like so we still involved in that
And then I'm spending a lot of time thinking about bullying
And I'm building a team
So we had a meeting in La last week in fact I wear I flew in a whole bunch of people
Tumi
And yeah it will be building the software out of that most opt out of Vietnam so it's going to be a real gold
Makes the laws
Why did you pick la
That's the place cuz that's where most of the it was a really good teachers who party
Actually Wednesday cuz one of my great friends good one go
He he he came
His first project
That was like his big thing and my big thing is building a hotel to suck
I wanted to go see his one
Because we've been friends for number of years
Stay at the Roosevelt
The triangle United
Yeah I mean
I think
The
Laa London
And Shanghai all
Impudent
It is one of the owners that I need to
Atlas
The New York
I don't know how I'm gonna
But I know that
That's what I'm good at. I'm good at navigating
The things that other people don't know how to do
So we have for investments in LA
Isaac rubbing
My mother still lives there
Battalion
Good for lifestyle message
Brands
Media
Ecommerce Resort in Napa
Cold naked mapa
And
Coming soon
What's the space
We trying to pick up some of that
Cheap land that was burned
Bring it back
Sounds good
I've been to the naked hub
Headquarters in Shanghai I felt like it was kind of very different from other co-working spaces of
Been to there a lot of, areas like event spaces where people can get together there's like a food court
Turn on the first floor
For listeners who haven't been could you like give like
Dislike a visual description of what naked hops look like and how
They're different
Yeah so I think the one area we we had the confidence in the carriage was
To create that common space will it shed space
Essentially a co-working
Environment should
Triple five
Functions that you share
When is the kitchen
You know Siri
Coffee area the other one is the living room
We call a meeting rooms or Workshop spaces
Hotels
And then in the wellness
Spaces
These
We end up
Using about 30% of all
GFA
Of the total area of a building
Inputting into sheds by stats
About double what must I do
Chinese Club leader
But in order to do that you have to have the belief that you can sell
Nothing like a hot day is productive and that we have another protocol naked agar
Where people will be willing to to to pay increments small increments
Money on you
People to use this
And that's what we proved and we were very successful at that and
I think the future will look more and more like that respect cuz it's so much more fish
Yusuf
Space
And people don't realize but commercial Office Space
Is
The most inefficient
Thing in the world
We normal office will use
20 square meters
Per person
I will use about 5 so we can reduce a file
75% reduction on on space and think of how much less construction you have
How much less space would be
Actually being used meeting rooms in traditional office
I'll just so inefficient like you'd like
9%
Of the month the room is being
But that's not all
That's not good use of space is not environment
Friendly's
So I think naked was always trying to
To figure out these
Set of environmental questions
At the core of what we were trying to do
And through that you have to have
Courage
Conviction
To to make that s*** space
I'm very interested in new product that you are offering naked Hub go
Hot dads step can be rented by the hours so users can see the available locations on a WeChat Mini
Programs just like how they can view available bikes
On a bike sharing app
And they can pay by the hour and then enjoy free coffee
I personally think there's a lot of demand for a flexible spaces like this
Because people are always struggling to find suitable places to do a couple of hours of work in between meetings in the city
So how did you come up with this
Idea
Yes
Very much a product person that's how I think every day but it's by the minute by the way not by the hour
And the idea
Random space
But for me it was more of a an Enterprise solution
So companies especially large multinational
They
They trap they they will have offices with your inherent in one
Location in the city and the city is a big place and get commuting around the city can take you out
Open amount of time
LOL hope
Who is that
Multinationals will be able to do Society offices
Bible
And then start to use a platform like this would have
You know that
50 different offices in one city
I'm
The idea really stems from
What we see today in consumerism where people are buying
Things on smoking
Just buy what I need
End
A novice T-Mobile can and the bike sharing apps
Excellent. But so was Airbnb
Subways
Didi and Uber
And what we've learned is that
Technology
Define essential
Became a new tool for us to be able to do singers
And without that
We couldn't do this
And the thing is just no one realized that this was
Nothing that could be done
We love it
Become hugely successful with literally in pay the face
Beta testing area balance
It's like going through the roof
I think we sign
More
Naked Hub go members and react
He have
Real members
And then we did that in
But not not not surprised it is it is insanely cool obviously we will
Extremely lucky
Do you have a
Done the steelbook
If I had done the deal little bit late I could have got even more because naked hub goes
Sex faces is God real
Real traction
And when you roll that out across
The globe on on the Wii with platform
It will be massive
That's how you get people into the system and then you start
Did you arrive out of revenue streams truck the real estate is never the future
Betty
Entry point
The landlord collect the money on the register
How to make a revenue stream
Not utilized
And there's so many service in Lyon top executive designer
And and we always say this to develop is like we don't want to be in competition with you
You guys are good at what you do but you carry on doing that
And I will get there
Buy wework
Kentucky naked and so
These kind of products
Will make people
Pokemon Mall
More concert to UCB we're rolling out making up go to other places absolutely
Shanghai is going to be at 8
A testing ground for Lord of new products.
We developed
And then they were all in my
On the way with platform
So we we've got
50 60 70 Engineers not working here in Shanghai in Rowena scale-up mm
Engineers
Focusing on product development
You know how we can bring more
Solutions
To the general
Person on the street
And by the way
The first 15 minutes of
Free when you walk in the naked hub
You scan like and you get
So you can let you get a taste of it
They're going to have a beer in a coffee and walk out and pay nothing
And I figured out that if you're a good be a consumer
Then you can do the make a you can get drunk really quickly
Without meaning to pay much money
So students are highly recommended
What will be your top advice for other non-chinese entrepreneurs who want to start businesses in China
I think
Most of the same things that you tell
Entrepreneurs anywhere in the world
Butts
The most of the best advice but no one Chinese yeah okay I would say respect
And learn from
Do not have the arrogance
Thing that you know more that you know more
Just so common for me
Just seen foreigners do that
The last 15 years
And it's just so dumb cuz I just don't listen they don't take the time to actually try and understand what the the local guys are trying to
I think that that
What's the right word
Presumptuous surrounding
Bikes
Do you know more
I'm here
I think that's my great
Like icon think I'm better than anyone so would like at the lowest rung of like the low wrong things
So yeah and learn from China and
Enjoy it embrace it
I actually really
Localizer
So many foreigners
I'll do that that if you don't get it in the first you need done localized just leave
Cuz you never gain
Paw Patrol
As you know in China new retail is a buzzword started in
January 2017
And you also see a lot of
Amanda
Snack shelves convenience stores a lot of stuff
What's on my who's believer in the share economy and human connection
How do you feel about that
Trend that supposedly have
I think it's the start of another
I don't think that is exactly the
Dissolution
Going to see is going
But it's going to be the thing that helps us learn
Call retailer
Is in a major major
The whole
And pure online is known as
Walmart
And this kind of unmanned retail is also not
Perfect solution
Aimbot
We are consumers
Human beings
Consumers
Annie's to be a
We just need to learn what it looks like shopping malls where are not at High Street stores at High Street
Shops.on not at bat
You know
I think this
New
Retail idea is
Is a stepping
Stone in the direction
If you're not drunk
And you like the
Industry I think it's
To think more about it
I think it's going to be a lot more innovation
In that area
Me personally
Phantom retail so
I'm not thinking about
But I think about services
You think about experiences exactly
For my children to my children children
It's just wrong if I the worst place
Looking for the worst people in the world
They're going to be the worst
In the bathroom
Really bad there for society and you even for to spend time and doing something that's impactful that's something
Do you believe in God
Exactly and Retail
Buying stuff I kind of done
That fat thing I'm from Africa
I don't know how to explain it
Shopping game
List of things to want to go and do
We're going to end this interview with a
Roundup quick fire questions so just tell us the first thing that comes to your mind
The first one is who's at one printer that you admire the most and why
To Richard Branson
Elon Musk
Richard Branson just cuz
I love
His Mantra is
What about the brand living the brand
Actually
Being the brand
Lisa from you is all what
Regulated industry
Crazy and wild lime and then I love the end and remember that there's a similarity
Between virgin and naked but I've always told if we put those two companies together we could have
A real Finance Company
I'm buying an Alexa sidelines
I use my country money is a South African
I love the fact that he doesn't give a shitt
And I think I'll II
I ascribe to that I despise
You know when I read media
Is rice rubbish
The and I trust me I read the international media about China
It's like
Hello
Are you even being to China
At the moment I don't like media that much I have that in common with Elon
Really don't like
Intermediate
The media habits
ABC's
Either elong my stability and courage
To just
Startling
Like this okay Lisa
This will new idea
Taking a big challenge
Can you claim yourself
And I'm and I think my teacher problems a challenge
I think
Sold it but I know it's going to be a big deal
What's something you read recently
That touch you a lot
So yeah
Outlook
Will Hurd
Hertz
It is a
Environment. Just a couple of days ago well
You know
He came on the beach
Mina full of plastic
The rhino
Population beijing
Decimated
You know I read a lot about this
It hurts me I just think that
Human beings
So idiotic
The way we keep killing an animal
Stop shooting up and having sex
Yeah that's I read too much of that
I'm stopping reading Weston like
Mail and stuff because I need
The newspapers cuz they all just full of such horrible
Stories
Faulty emotional
What do you do for fun
Wakeboard with my daughters in golf
Golf and wakeboarding
Boating sailing
How did you die in China
I go so far to build a golf simulator room in my house so I can play any golf course in my house
But don't ask me how and why I build things
I'm going to bed stuff right
And then I have but we have a yacht
Get one in in in in Hong Kong when we go to the boat
We we wait for tomorrow
What IL does is 7 and she's rough start wakeboarding already
So you know we love being on the ocean
And that we love being in nature
Cicadas
Get on a boat and sail away for fun
Thank you so much for your time and we enjoy our less we encourage our listeners to visit naked help when they can
Can you snake a tub go this is really cool product
Thanks guys that was a lot of fun
Just about to
Airline flight 879 89.5
I-96
By the way we also produce a weekly email newsletter in English also called 9 + 6
Roundup of the week's most important happenings in Tech in China
Subscriber some told us it is from formative and fun to read the new site also features original content
An analysis from Zara MI
Stripe at nine 6. GG bc.com
Venture Capital firm based in Silicon Valley
Shanghai and Beijing with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past 18 years from seed
2p IPO with 3.8 billion dollars in capital under management across state funds
GTA V invest in globally-minded entrepreneurs in consumer new retail
Social intranet Enterprise cloud and Frontier Tech has invested over to him
90 companies with more than 45 companies valued at over a billion dollars
Pergola companies include Airbnb Alibaba
C trip
Didi chuxing demo hashicorp hellobike cows keep slat
Square
Hotel wish
Soundtrue white white and others find out more at gbc.com we also highly recommend
Joining our listeners WeChat group es la China where we regular share insights events and job opportunities
Face related to talk in China join these groups at 96.3 gbc.com
Flash community
You have any feedback on this podcast or would like to recommend the gas please email us I-96
IGG bc.com