Vincent wrestler
Hi there
Welcome to the -6 podcast
Brought to you by Gigi Capital under show
Wintergreen movers and shakers
China's tech industry
And discuss how I found her
From around the world can draw
I'm fine Aztec ecosystem
My name is Khan song
I'm a managing partner at ggv capital
And I've been working at and investing in startups
Across the US
China and other Emerging Markets
Play last 20 years my name is Emma marketing manager at ggv Capital and a former journalist
Why is the show called 96
96 is the work schedule and many Chinese Founders that organically adopted
That is 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
Genesis captures Lane tensity Drive
Speed of Chinese internet companies
Booty growth Miracles over last decade
Also I highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat group in slack Channel
Where you can connect with like-minded people interested in Tech in China we organize regular offline events across the world for Apollo
You can join these by visiting 96. Ggvc. Com
Imma show today we have or will how in Chinese
Is American
Producer
And Rider in your opinion
Super Start in Tacoma
Originally trained as a molecular biologist
Before becoming full-time filmmaker
He held various
Position to Quality Companies in Kuna, Idaho
Yahoo China
And Ali Baba
Composer Satie
He was a China country manager for TripAdvisor
As his career progressed
So his passion anymore tistic
Accretive
Pursuits
April 12th documentary filmmaking
Full-time
Is there
What's the subject of our show today
Is a documentary called
People's Republic
Desire
Is a journey into livestreaming industry in China
Warehouse
NYY
The document their lives behind the scene
The film has won
The grand jury award at the 2018
South by Southwest
Anime
Mini Opera War
And has green an over 40 film
New York Times Coco film
Hypercharge
What Allie X
Seth is in a really surprising
An Everlast
If you haven't watched the film
Is Vivillon
BMO iTunes Amazon and Google Play
Does visit
Desert. Film4 links
How has Bruce to
Glorifying
And nowhere to call home
How is a bachelor's degree in biology from University of Sciences
Technology in China
Degree in molecular and cell biology from Brandeis University
An MBA from University of Michigan Ross School of Business
Welcome to the show House
Thank you
Glad to be here
So I wonder how did it come soon
Choose a topic of this
And why did you choose to focus on why why out of all the live streaming platform
Yasso back in 2014 in the summer time I went back to China to
Start researching my new film Project actually broke
Es6 project ideas in mind
I do some research filming in China
And then just randomly one of my friend who has a financial analyst at that time asked me
Since you're working tap for so many years
Have you heard of this company called why why
It's listed on NASDAQ
Acmarket that back then was over
3 $4 already
How to make money
So I was intrigued because for many years
As possible saying I work in
Beijing China Alibaba and TripAdvisor China
I'm button
I asked around my friends in Beijing or Shanghai
You're not.
It's about these Gamers addicted to gaming this is the kill time online
How can company that even tech people in the big city
Know about it get listed on NASDAQ
So that was my first impetus to start researching
And then
I luckily swear in Dutch
Connection
China's internet industry
And I was introduced to the Shell in the founder of YY
And Alicia Linda introduced me to YYC marketing department
Eyeshadow as the live stream
In China did you some event
There was like wow this is so fascinating
You see all these live streamers who
Because whether my can we have mixers there there's this sounds much better
And then they attract money
And then as soon as I realized
There are a lot of too hot
You know
Rich
And as well as the the losers all getting together in the showroom
And every night when they do their shows
It's 2252 even 100,000 people watching simultaneously I was like wow
This is fascinating because
The rich and the poor that don't get together
Community
The altogether
And they actually talk to each other the wish of each other
So that was so fast maybe I decided to
Make You Feel My
And how long did it take you to make
The film and what were your biggest challenge
So
I started filming in summer 2014 before live streaming really explode in China
If you guys follow developments in industry in China unit watching will explode into mainstream Consciousness in 2016
Because I need to have a
Why why every year
Hazardous
Annual competition
I was like wow that's going to be a cool so I followed my
Life's humorous as
Prepare
To go to this competition to win
Kotoko the idol title
And that can be fun to watch
And then
Next year I can come back and feeling a little bit about the personal stories
I got it in the Buda
More typical three a structure
But then
Very quickly soon after I finish filming the first competition
Where one of the livestreamer Wong laws
Be the girl the female
She had a plastic surgery
And she moved
So I can like
Film her personal life title cut it in
Before the competition
To cheat to build a 3X talk to animals
The film the next
Competition
I feel all the way into 2016 as a witness the explosion of Life streaming
In China and then
So that's almost like two years of filming production and then the editing took a long time to get a year-and-a-half
Because
Such a complex ecosystem
The business rules
How to replicate
The social
Status the luxury cars that
And
How
The agency Worx trying to
Komodo life shimmers to manage
So the business rules as well as
Different levels of relationship is so complex
So to me a long time to arrive trying to streamline the story
Enough so obvious cook
Potentially understanding but in the same time
Retained
Complexity
Because that to me was what's fascinating about this weekend
In this fantasy world
Simplicity and complexity between
Portraying this
Virtual community
The counter
Stories how the characters are feeling
As the flame goes up and down
As all intros
Trash dump
About the relationship with their families
Real life relationships
I be impacted
As they're all Einstein grow
It feels like a mixture of Hollywood
Netflix
Snapchat
Kind of Hall combine
Take me to Arden Mall
Yeah I mean when I was making the film
Futurama Black Mirror
I so so the overall feeling is the film is very sci-fi ish because I feel like China is already
Compared to the US
Is coming in the future already
So I decided cautiously to make the
This film feel more like a sci-fi film
Is selfies very
Black Mirror
Yes your film is Black Mirror
I'm seeing a white wife
It's system
Reminds me of online
Hollywood
And Netflix
Snapchat
Go out that's that's absolutely correct
So I love your title
Republic of Zaire
I found a very thoughtful
Can you explain the logic
Yeah I mean what's the logic
Because you wanted you want to convey this film is about China obvious
People's Republic
Something
But then something
So what is this why why or
Virtual
Community about
It's about
Indiana
People ask me to explain
Why do these poor people spend money on
Why do they switch people spend money on
It's so hard to explain the
Each row in an online community
Multifaceted
It's not simple to summarize
So Indiana just decided like desire
Desire
Is
Is this longing is this aspiration but it's
This emotion
Brodie knob
Places like money
The film characters all have
They all leave
Pretty deep impression on the viewer from the two wall homes
In her celebrities who devote their whole life to live streaming
A white white widow to how The super-rich Who lavished
Virtual gifts on their favorite streamers to the Dallas Zoo who are the migrant workers searching for cheap entertainment
I always wonder how did you find it
How do you
Get them to agree to
So I was lucky as a mission
Is conscious about
PR
Does a temperate on a company you'll be different
Not as evil
So the marketing team was really really nice to me
Introduce me to the the Marisol said can you help introduce me to this one
And then they will do that
At first the Maca team definitely
Try to put satellite humor to me
Br
Am I becoming baby no no
It's what why wanderlife Gmail
The Host
Some of them can be boring
And so that's one thing
Secondly some of them actually tell a different story
You know one of them
I'm not going to name names.
She's putting herself
Online but you realize just
29 year old teacher married with kids
I can I can poetry about her
And
Ecology
Every last human has to have some
I need that
They need money
So their fans can support
Most of the channel that make up a story
I lie about who they really are
In the beginning the last summer were confused based thought I was making a cover video for why
So I can show up
Documentary
I don't like
I don't know that India can we just hang out
Sew in
With the guys is easier with the Michael Walker
Really easy to open up to me because I'm a guy
We can just hang on head beer they'll hang out but we Somoza very difficult because she's a girl she live stream
She flirts and talk sometimes dirty jokes to her pictures
With me a guy
And she feel really uncomfortable so far. Of time
Chapters that you cannot come
Dollar fly bath bomb
New York
Because I'm very sick
Scanned and
Light included when they're like Friday
Really
How do you get them
How to be comfortable in
I think the keys are you just have to show up
What's a show-off holding the camera in front of them
Loreena McKennitt forget
Is there anyway so
So I'm anyview reviewers have called the film
Provocative and unsettled
Terrifying
It was at
Part of your intestine
How to do
For it to be that way or was that
I didn't know different types of filmmakers
Different types of documentary film
Some documentary filmmakers just
Want to give the impression
Observing life
You know I'll always the filmmaker
But I'm
The kind of like I want to tell ghost story
I want to find the most romantic moment
Telugu story
To keep a strong impression on my audio
My aunt is trying to figure out what the message is
So
Obviously I followed them for two years I have like 700 hours of footage
Which I shot
As well as hundreds and hundreds of
Hours of recordings of their live streaming shows
It's up to me to pick the right moment
So yes I
Intentionally
Really push for some
Traumatic or provocative
Portage in
Koepsell footage in the film
Because you know even when I explain live streaming to a Chinese artist who made
Uniquely Chinese
Complex
An astonishing
I also asked honest because
Any given night
So yes I think
The part of what the reality is it is released
We think that
They'll be other forms of life
Streaming of any merger
What is the southeast
Where I
Latin America
When I look at why why
Wow when I'm at college
It feels like
A bit of
Pro wrestling
And so proper
During the day in
In the US
Professional sports all combined
So this is very intense feeling
That even the
The most girls
Users
Mura Masa
Can participate
And see you later part of a movement
2 Chainz
On order where you're champion
The person you
Support to end up winning it all
You feel like you did it
Sports sports
So popular
That's why why why and other major path election in plantando I have competition though I have a annual competition
Most of the competition was sometimes weekly competition because
Do you want to encourage livestreamer
Live streamers fast
The patrons and the poor thing as all get together to support and give him or her to win win the number one
For the vanity for the reports for the fame
So where is soccer popular
I think this
People Are People
Garfield is there a great team
Get that Auto
I wonder if you got different reception
From Chinese audience
Versus
Very different I think I think
Usher
In developed World Rochester New York
When people watch this film they were like
Wow
Can this be real
This is so crazy
And
I think I think they look at it almost really like a black man because several reviewers
Mission
Great dystopian
Near future Carlos story but I think for Chinese people
It's real because first of all will have heard of
Lie to me if you not haven't been a fan of Lie to Me
Secondly
In terms of the motivation is a llama understandable for
For Chinese people to understand why the rich want to show off
By throwing money Ally
So awesome
So we're saying we have actually been seeing LifeStream kind of slowing down
Where is 4 video is rising fast
Become the go-to medium for
Entertainment for the vast majority of Chinese mobile internet users
Like going and I'm quite sure also
Did you see this trend
Call me when you were
I know I was so busy I didn't get my phone
You know I saw that taking a lot of this
That the buzz
Phone for live streaming
So what you think
Anchovy
Every night watching
I saw the Elsa population
A short video show videos
Kind of funny
You can you can spell however much time you want
No longer is like show video
Right now.
The popularity I think overshadow
Where is shareholder in
So we know how they're doing
I will guess the puppy. Overlap
Queen why are you
And quite so
Asbury
Different
Entertainment body wash
Yolanda / live streamers I follow actually went and started taking off their all yours in Christ
What impression have been getting working us China cross-border tag is that there's General sense
Amount of people in China that Tech is a Force for good
Where is the opposite of
Do you agree with
Media impressions
Honestly I feel like
In the US
We tend to live in our own media Bubba right depends on which meter would follow
Which Twitter
You know celebrities will follow
I feel like such a lot of the film coming out
About America
Oversee the majority of the internet consumers
Not as concerned as some of the media Elites about
Kotoko the dangerous
Technology
Even though yes I'm the older mainstream media right now while talking about the Facebook privacy or
Nature of Technology
Mainstream media
You know you can watch
American meme Netflix
Instagram search
Watch cam girls you can watch
Like I recently talked to
Reporter who is doing a story writing a book about
America's largest Indian Premier luncheon topics
I think it's the same thing that you talked
Show users
Their day-to-day they are not thinking as much about
But I definitely do agree
In the mainstream traditional media
In the US there's a lawn mower
Pause and reflection
About the compass rose technology
Can play in this society as compared to what's happening in China today
Bingo Wing China filming
Do you feel this
Morristown restaurants
People in Tennessee
Can make their life
We'll make the world
Better absolutely I think I think China
You know this child is being discussed elsewhere. We don't have as much of a concern
That's not to say everybody don't
Care about public General
And as I also like we are
More
Open to embrace the latest the newest
Technology and I think
Even right now right I mean
Chinese people still believe in technology
Either like a i to hear this
Almost a bad name
Inside of a superlative
What the Chinese going through is very some of your
Founders Inn
General consumers
In
Southeast Asia
Latin American
In developing
Dolphin world
Sufficient
You feel like texting
Exchanging
In development
Lookout
I want to talk about your very in
Find career path
You were trained as a biologist
The wedding to Tech
So could you talk about
How you make
What guy that you are
Well okay so
What else going up in China
Either
Middle school and college I was always interested in the humanities
Chinese song over traditional Chinese
Yeah your parents would
Expectation, not you
Never push me
Not you introduced
Stand by you
Something better
Something stable
With a better is a better future so that's why
I decided to do biology
The science
And then button does not satisfy a lot size
Emotionally satisfying
Bill I didn't know what else to do Chinese immigrants
You do either
Business law or medicine
So I picked
Business because this is the most flexible
I asked you to Love talk I lost it I started off as a product manager
Excite at home
What products edible
No I stayed
And so and then I work my way up in
So I can part of management to General management
IHOP alibaba's long sorry Mama
So the farm and I guess I was always have this
To express myself more
I like
You know you work with the Pillow People
To do it
I feel like I'm getting farther and farther away from the creative
I love to get my hands dirty
And I will always being doing some writing also make you on the side
Where you at
2007/2008
Oh okay yeah that's right after the murders was Yahoo
That's right
So yeah I've been
Certain point
I just have to ask my question
Entrepreneur launch my company become a multi-millionaire first before I do what I like or do I want to do what I like
Right now so it took a while for me to
It's okay Ford
Tilapia
Chengdu art
That's where I am right now
When you went to Alibaba was that
Like first time you were back in
Probably.
So initially I was managing
Technology transfer of
Yahoo's advertising technology
Into the
Ali Alibaba group I was managing the technology
Operation
No I mean
I took a year off during filmmaking and then I join that you coming
Start up
And I didn't go anywhere so and then
Because I really wanted
People were already talking about
Chinese internet company because the first wave the Baidu and the Soul who
You can always argue do coffee
It's copy to China by the body
Wanted to understand the culture
What makes Alibaba
Crop
Oyster takeaway
I don't think
The only culture is so strong
I personally don't think
It's right for everyone but
I mean I consider myself still
Loco loco loco
The culture what are talking about does the clothes camaraderie
Essex
So I like that
Everybody was battling Giacomo is the general right
We are trying to
You guys are the truths that's all
To the battle
Abaddon some other people
Different
TripAdvisor
So that was
Great different intensive basically
Disadvantage of a typical Western internet company trying to expand in China
Whereas you have a lot of
Great industry know how
You have a suck very successful business model in the US
How to adapter
Indo China Market
Where is
Fat movies
Do you want to replicate the success story
In a different Market
Or do you want to create something that was always something we struggle
It was
Great learning experience but
Challenger
Cushing and Chino
Falcon
I think if I could change
Was that party
Yeah
Competing I mean it was hard
China back then
The two biggest comfortable look that was
Sitrep because it has both hotel booking as well as Council reviews
As well as
Qunar
Hotel beta at the hotel room
Hi sweetie ice Adele
Simple analysis
Chinese founder
Who stole
First Auto
Workout for year 2
Hated
This is so slow
And not fast-moving enough
Have they come out and do their next order
The successful startup
Super hot
You should have told me that because I was thinking through your startup
So are you still playing with you
No because
Whenever I travel back to China out to the US that you'll equation always say welcome
Welcome back to the US
Like whenever I say I'm a filmmaker I feel always feel like I'm the Frog
You know I like
I feel like I can say I'm a film
So what's the next
So we can expect
What are you working
Netflix original
Sure it's a 39 minutes
It's called family
It's about me having kids through surrogacy
In the US
And take my kids
Kotoko Modern Family back to China
Essays my traditional Chinese pirate
Watch on leaves early film
Wedding Banquet is kind of similar to guys a comedy with a lot
I saw your own
Stop my old stories
So you will see me
You'll hear my voice
Do you finally essay
Inspiration the model
Or something
Obviously
Castes
Truly
Chinese buy also has Universal appeal because
You focus so much on the human emotion
With nowhere near
But is this
The same color
We're really appreciative of
People who can tell the China story
In English to the greater World in a way that's
Authentic
True to
So in that way I think 9
Sex and what you're doing or
Our kind of
Thank you
So as someone who have
Had a lot of dramatic
Careershift
I wonder how you develop
The self-knowledge
Uno
What you're good at and what you should be doing because I think a lot of her audience
Are younger people trying to figure out
What their next steps
Springfield
What did you do
Help you find your
That's a tough one
A lot of times you have to be
Almost stupid
To stop burn.
I mean despite what everybody else tells you you're going to fail you have to have that
Strong
If I put in a bad word
Start doing
Rather than thinking about it like when I
Star
Wanted
What is a mixer um I just
Start writing screenplay
Read some books and started making
Short films
I watch a lot of the old title loan in that way
I did it
Like I said earlier
Long time
Before
I had my last film which is
Is the road to fame
That
When I saw the film was not permitted on the festival
Cause I knew
I could do this
I knew my next one will be even better
So you need to be able to get your hands dirty to
Before you know
You can be
Do this for time
So
How have you figured out if
4 documentary
No it's very hard because
When I first started doing documentary full-time every once awhile put my business hat on
I'll be thinking about
The ROI of all the hours and put it in for my cat
Optimize this process
To make it faster
I mean
If you think about it documentary film by Nature has limited market up here
Just like
Certain types of writing
So there's no business model per say I'm not doing this
Right now
How to really try to make a lot of money
Ideally
What's you making nothing on me happy enough reputation all the people
Will commission what to do filmed
HBO
And Netflix and then that's how you can make a decent living
Kind of in transition
I'm thinking about
On the other way
Document
China commercial
Talking to me right now I miss her
So hands I know you're really enjoyed
Hear from your perspective
What do you like about it
Barclays personal
Because he was ugly
Pennywise
Just seeing the story being
Play It Again
And see how the characters are in it
Different but familiar
This is something
Easy for me for me to relate
Secondly I think
Amazing job
Of showing the
Plexaderm
Struggling
Explain to the westerners
How it works
Yeah with a film is every
I'm so alive
I think if we have more time will probably want to go into how it is
It's very similar
Professional sports in other form of payment work in the western world
What developer around the country
Around the world how there's a lot of similarities
I would love to
Odyssey
Wow
Go through some of that
Later
The other format
To show how he sees a 2
Guess it's just a lot of things I saw in a film
Baby unique
Play Chinese for the value so extremely Universal
Denso Universal aspect that's not as obvious to
Westerners who watches
For the first time
It was so shocked by the details
That lady
Forget
That there is a universal connection
As well and not something that I think.
I am sure will Howard tomorrow West 2nd of topic material
You lived in China on the ground 480
This reminds you of
Like what you saw
Tennyson point where is a country with a rising middle class but also
Are Creepypastas kind of Left Behind as well
And they wanted to see a part of this progress and movement
And my pretties we know why why he gives them a chance to do that however little money they make
They using that in a way that give us a lift themselves their life a lot more meaning
And the part about connection is
Is Grambling University
Specifically Chinese
But the desired
It was a great way great work
These are to be connected to be meaningful
Prepartum movement
Extremely
And become popular in the US I said you were to have its call you to
I mean the login never took off in China phone virus reason
Took the Roses login in China
Into the celebrities on YouTube the type of content
They produce
How do we lie on
Stouts controversy to generate popular in China
YouTube
Almost
Fail
Amortization
Should the weight of whiteheads
If you have other set interesting broadcasters on YouTube
Advertising
I see you was wrong around the world who willing
Google pay
For additional evaluation services
It just that
Did not
Do as good a job
At the courthouse
And one thing that will be
Hopefully
They learned about that both us and China
MPL companies go by services
That we can go truly
Between
More classical
So the concept of nine
XSP
Snooze alarm
96 ICU
Jack Ma.
I just released the article
About what he thinks about the phenomena so I was wondering if someone who lived
In both us
China
Deeply what's your
Perspective on
Idaho
I don't know if we should call it ours or
Mentality
This phenomenon
Do you work done at 6
Around the Clock
I do not have sex
I think the reality is that most startups are doing
Right
Whether you're the startups are in the US or in China
If you want your starter to succeed or anybody was doing anything this will truly passionate about
NSX
I remember when I was working Alibaba what it was lunch in Sugar bizarre China
We were all working on it
Nobody complained about it
A part of something great
You want to work 9
I think right now what China discussion
Is Bali in China
10 from 2
The true reason why we're having discussion in China
What is
I don't
Potential know the younger generation I don't feel that the younger generation
That's one
Set Ali is
A lot of the internet companies in China
In the house
Alibaba tencent
Established companies already
Establish company
Country is hard to call today the startup culture.
Cohesiveness submission definition
Get people excited
Observing Seneca Valley as well right
I think well in instead of trying to enforce or ask
I need the HR to do a better job in Tennessee
Buying to the punch of the working
Mickey's fun for people wanting to do it
Want to do
Company
I've worked in
Probably six or seven different companies in my in my car
UMBC alone
CVS Medford
Parlor
In
I think a lot of people think that they're
Just working in order to live
So
About work-life balance
Complete Arsenal
But when I
For the things I do
I don't just do it for mine
Employer
I'm doing for myself
And I feel I'm sure you can
Set to do filmmaking for yourself
You'll get a story you want to tell this mission one achieve
Personal growth
You want to get to
Is a Personal Agenda and viewpoints
You want to come
And for all of us who are Multicultural with living multiple cities
How do you tell something
That's uniquely you
Quite a bit of Chinese elements
Yet at the same time if you want to make a universal sound people get it don't see you're weird
I think that wow
There's something deeper
Is something I can learn from
Sukhumi is never about work-life balance
Is always about work-life
Cuz I don't treat work as work
A cheetah work as my life calling
What is a life calling
Why would you be bounced away from
Retreat at the jobs to make money
You don't bite me meaning what you do
Quite frankly you should be doing at all
You should do something that you truly truly truly
So you don't find it something that you have to fight against
So would that want to remove
To the last
Part of the interview which is around a
Quick fire questions you can just say the first thing that comes
Remind
The first one is whose entrepreneur you admire the most
Ponemah
Professionally
Well mannered
Internet company in China
As someone who worked at Alibaba
Alibaba
This is what it's hard to replicate
Lyric Harris Summer charismatic leader Like Jagger
We were so we know
He is
All about wouldn't happen
The second one is what's something you read recently that
I just finished reading
The latest issue of foreign policy talking about nationalism
I find that fascinating
Why is that
It's not a book about it
What's a habit you have that you think has
What's a happy to have
In order to get better I have
Have to do actual work
That's why my parents keep on telling me
You know a lot of the political discussion in this country is the bathroom is like
If you want to get better
Will Carter
What do you do for fun
I watch film on Netflix
Western
Netflix
May 3rd
So everyone please
Go watch that on May 3rd
Thank you so much for
I really enjoyed
Good afternoon
7989 * 4
Thanks for listening to this episode of 996
Venture Capital firm based in Silicon Valley Shanghai and Beijing we have been partnering with leading technology entrepreneurs
Iceberg has 18 years from seed to pre IPO
With 6.2 billion dollars in capital under management across 13 funds CGV invests income
Zoomer new retail
Social Digital internet Enterprise cloud and Frontier Tech
GTB has invested over 290 companies with more than 45 companies valued at over a billion dollar
Pergola companies include
Airbnb
Alibaba
C trip Didi chuxing demo hashicorp Hello by cows keep
Black Square
Hotel wish soundtrue white white and others find out more at 2 gbc.com
We also highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat group as lot Channel where we regular share inside
Events and job opportunities related to attack in China
Join these groups at 9 96.3 jvc.com community
You have any feedback on this podcast
The recommended gas please email us at 996 at gbc.com