Recent wrestler
Tampa Airport
Hi there
Welcome to the -6 podcast
Brought to you by GE Capital
Went to the movers and shakers
China's tech industry and discuss how Founders from around the world can draw
I'm fine Aztec ecosystem
I'm a managing partner at GTB capital and I've been working at and investing in startups
Across the US
China and other emerging markets for the last 20 years
And a former journalist
Why is the show called 96
96 is the work schedule and many Chinese Founders that organically adopted
That is 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
Chinese internet companies that produce many growth Miracles over last decade
Also I highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat group in slack Channel
Where you can connect with like-minded people interested in Tech in China we organize regular offline events across the world for Apollo
You can join these by visiting 96. Ggvc. Com
On the show today we have Jing Sun
Or Cynthia in Chinese
She's the CEO of C trip the largest island top of iPhone in China
Which is listed on the NASDAQ
Is Kerman cabs around the 20
3 billion dollars US
She has being a secret
I'm 13 years
Parts become CEO in November 2016
GameStop the CEO of Secret for four years and before that CFO for 7 years
Before children C trip
Jane work at Applied Materials
In the US
The head of sec
And external reporting division
Prior to that she worked with
KPMG
As an automatic during silicone body for 5 years
Can we see her bachelors
Degree from the prison
The score of the University of Florida
From the Peking University Law School
Just yesterday C trip analysis Financial results for the fourth quarter
And for year ended December 2018
Never Avenue for 2018 was 4.5 billion US dollars at 16% year-on-year increase
Intoto DMV for 2018 was 105
Feeling US dollars
Which is around a 30% year-on-year in
Welcome to the show Jane
Thank you
So most of our audience is already familiar with shrimp
And you have a part of the company for over a decade
Could you share with us three things you're most proud of about C trip that most people may not know
Yes
First of all it's the growth of the company
When I joined a company we only had about 500 million market cap
And today we're exceeding 20 billion
In the past 30 years
So I'm extremely proud of
Olive Grove
And secondly is our expansion into Global spaces
When I joined a company C trip is only
Are there a small Chinese online travel company
And now
Intime self at gamer we're already at the largest in the global space
So I mix
Extremely proud
All of the achievements
Our team has made
And lastly is our
Initiation
Are in terms of the
I'll protect you in the female leadership
Because I'm the
There were a few CEO in a major
Internet companies
Also we put a lot of emphasis
Helping female leaders
Nurture them and to make sure they survive in our company
I read recently in one of your interview that you actually provide the option to pay for some of your female employee
Plays to freezer X
In case
They want to
Preserve the option of working
And having a child Edison
Yes
Very Progressive company policy and we're the only company who offer this
Benefits
Chihuahua female employees
And employees really a very excited to have this
Protection
All for their career path
I'm going to take the interview to earlier age
Earlier point in time
When you went to us
You've already in college
In China
Why did Stella go to us for business
You start with the law school first
And then you went to us
Business School
Why did you decide to do that
And also said go to us for
Yeah when I first came to the United States I was a sophomore in Peking University Law School
Indict
Chinese system law school integrated system
States
Law school is accredited school
So my original plan was to go to the business school first
And then go to law school next and get my Ph.D to set up the third step
But right after I graduate
I can't be good Chinese
Graduate student wants to make her parents proud
Yes absolutely
Betty Mae 30-year of business school in University of Florida
I interviewed with the big four accounting firm and they give the offer
So I feel it to all let me make some money to save enough money so I can go to the mosque
Degree
So that's why you know I started to work he was kicking G Silicon Valley office right off.
Graduate from University of Florida
And then opportunity comes when my husband became
The first to see Kyoto of Alibaba
Mm
And all aboard
Asked me to join secret SPCA full of secrets
So we moved our family our back to China
Take on these challenges
Jumping to Yahoo
Yahoo
Southern rock
Somebody as well
Without your first
Exposure to internet
Yeah we are very blessed for the opportunity because when we went to school
The cultural revolution ended
And when we went to
College in Champaign open the door
So both of us were able to go to the USA to study
When we finish the school
Silicon Valley
Sojong joint Yahoo
When there was only 46 employees in a company
And then
4 years
We got the phone call was very good friend of ours
The joint
Invite him to join a very small company
Call Daddy Papa
And that friend is Jack Ma so
You know last Yahoo
When the stock price was about 200 USD to 300 USD
The enjoying the small a company called Alibaba
I always feel both of us a very very blessed for the opportunity
So I command has responsibility to
Bring up at the next generation of the readership and give them
As good an opportunity as possible going forward
Right space when he first suggests to you that
You must go from there
A company Yahoo
Which was a star at that time to join this little small company you have drill bit of nowhere
What was your immediate reaction
Yeah we have no Jack for a couple of years
So even before challenge joined Alibaba
Whenever we came back
China
You always talk to the engineers to Alibaba I try to help out
As much as possible
And we
Always see Jack as a very good friends of ours
I tried to be helpful
And I remember one day
John Carter phone call from Jack
And said oh you already
Finish your 40 year with Yahoo
And I got VC money SoftBank invested 20 million
Yeah you got that you have to join us
So
Believe in the vision
Jack hat
I only had my first baby
She was born she was born in March 2000
Angel joined Alibaba in May 2000
But I thought to be a good wife I always should be very supportive of him
ISO key joint Alibaba
And it was during a very difficult stage of Alibaba because
Self banking St 220 million in a company
So when y'all joined he told me
Alcohol only had $5 left in the bank
So
Yes it has been a long way and we're extremely proud of
Achievement
Alibaba team has achieved
And how big was sitra when you joined and what made you believe in
The ski trip vision
Yeah I also asked myself
Well first of all I ask
History questions
A force of 4
Should I
Invest my youth
United States in China
And at that time USA the GDP growth rate was about
2%
And China was growing anywhere between 8 to 10%
So when the economy is growing so fast
It presents a lot of opportunities
For the unemployed
So when I joint secret pie become one of the youngest CFO in the market
So that's the first question
Should you
Remain to be in the USA or do you want to go back to
China
The second question is
If you want to invest in China
Which industry
I will give you a very good opportunity
Squirrel
And
I always tell myself if I join
Company
Alcohol
You can make a lot of money
But in a way it's not very healthy
Reitzel
I tried to tell myself that I need to join a company
That is
Fairway healthy
A Dairy Queen
Happiness to the peephole so I believe
Kabul
I'm not only a great happiness
Stream videos to family
Let young kids learn
It also brings Global p
When we travel around the world
So I choose
Invest my
Time and energy in my used
Bolinas
And DeSoto question is if you want to invest yourself
Travel industry
Which company has
The best opportunity to win
It'll when I talk to I like him
I feel very
Strong that this company is very humble down to earth
Hard-working
And they have the best opportunity to weigh
And so these are the three things I considered
When I
Decide
Two Joints each other as the CFO of the
So it has been
A very good day
Pack
Phony
What was it like to transition from
CFO to CEO and then
CEO
What kind of lessons did you learn about how these leadership function
Can work together
Yeah
When I was a CFO of the company was very small
But grow very fast
So whatever
That is not taken care of by
Elevation of teams I would have just too jumpy and a fix
A couple of years
Our board
Feels that I already was doing this year olds position
So they promoted me to be a clo
And then three years ago when James talk to me
And he wanted me to take on more responsibility as the CEO of the company
And I told him that we just finished two major deals
When was Elio when was Chennai
And I thought our team this
Stabilized
The finished
The mergers and acquisitions
Before I took responsibility so I waited for year
And then two years ago we made a very smooth transition
To see your position
Shuffle me micros track
Istat
I already see what else needs to be done
And without the title I was already doing a lot of
Oddities
So far away yeah
Adidas Team my advice to them is always
Costco
And invest
You have time and energy in the next level
And then
Us-10 out
So my title my scope is never a limit
On what I do
Whatever is good for the company I would just jumping and look at it.
People outside of China have
Stereotype
Of how Chinese
Women
And yet you were among the very first
The runs
Major Chinese
Internet come
In the major internet company worldwide.
What
Kind of challenge
Did you have to overcome
In order to be
Come
In such apus
Opportunities
To prove yourself
To show that you can
I think it's a female leader
I tried
To be authentic
I think a female as themselves has lots of
Stress
You don't have to act
SML
Be successful
ISO
A couple of our strengths so we have is that Forza 4
We always put the team first
I never
Very welding to make
Personal sacrifice
In order for the team to
And I think that's so great strength
Will you become
High level
Executive
Cocina company
The second thing is
Females are also very good ways
Putting yourself in others shoes
So when I mean that you go Shay Shay
I always try to see
For this deal
What
We can brain to the other side
If I were the other side
What they would like to have
Right
So if you
To your selfie
People shoes
It's very good for you to make a deal
That is when we rather than I kill you or you kill me
Coincide
And the food thing I feel female reader that's very strong
Is the communication
And Computing skills
So a lot of times
Weather sensitive
We understand what
The teams need
Instead of
I just focusing on Wednesday we try to
Bring to the table
A comprehensive solution
So that
The team's career path
Company's interest
Shareholders interests
Our customers interest
I will take
So I think a female leaders
Have inherited
Strength
And we have to
Are use our strengths to be successful in the business world
What is it like to run a public company listed in New York
China what is your typical day like
Yeah the schedule is very demanding so I tried
To get to the office
At around 7
To 7:30
So I finished all my
Homework
In my direct report if I eat to have while on with my director poet
Normally I invited for breakfast meeting at 8
Ephraim 9 my
Schedule is back to back
Half an hour for meeting
He's back to back
All the way until
Maybe 6 to 7
And in the evening I tried to
Show the work papers I need to read
And bring it home if I'm not traveling
I tried to have dinner with
My family
I want a kiss like young I tried to help them with the homework
I know they're old enough
So when I'm working there doing their homework
And from 9
12 a.m. or 1 a.m.
I schedule my overseas
Europe was United
Space with NASA
Etc
So
That's how I try to
To balance my work
And life
Do you work 5 days a week
Or more than
More than that
China in 96
Meeting from 9 to 9
Time 6
Bass
A lot of them is a lot of
7-Eleven 7
The 7:00 to 11 p.m. 7 days
So some of the listeners
Like to ask a question
How can you be efficient when you work long hours
So implied in that question
You can either be
Efficient
Or
You're being efficient
In your mind
How to tell
Menards
Become efficient
Insta
Yeah I think efficiency is very poor
So I tried to
Run
Half marathon on the weekend
Every year my husband and I tried to join two marathons a year
So
Healthy is staring
The second thing is also
To train your team so that they can be
A sufficient Sur
Understood lay is a range of time
Otherwise
So when I'm in the car
I tried to
Listen to a book
I when I'm in the office I try to
You know arranged in BTS
So there is no more than to waste
Could you tell us about the baby tiger program as C trip to encourage internal initiatives and how do you make sure
Your overarching goals of the company are effectively communicated to all your employees
Yes it's a company is growing bigger and bigger
We consistently think about what is the best
That's the way
To energize the company
So when
Initiative so we took is the baby tiger
So basically our employees are encouraged
To bring new ideas new business plan
To us
And we'll give them fundings
Personnel Resources
And then let them to innovate
So for example when not their employees
She is very young
Right now he is only 26 years old
And he is the CEO of gesine which is
It's a cream
Business unit
I'm so we give him you know he wants to do
Eustis business unit anchor
And then at your tickets
To attend
At hotel business
He's only 26 years old
So
When we ask
How much money
How long
He needs and he says you know I need
2 million RMB 6-6
People to improve
I'm successful not
It's not you
Closeout
And it only took
What nice
To prove that the volume exceeded 10000 per day
Last year they delivered a billion dollars to the
Tavares
Successful Young
People there each other
Smart
Analeigh tip
And we want to encourage our young employees
To step up
Take on more responsibility
But in the last 40 years
Message of Jonah company
You have helped to
Increase the value of a company
What is sukiyaki
You're very successful
Extreme articulate
What's your drive why you still working this hard
Personally
6 7 days a week
Yeah a couple of things I think
Forza 4
I have
Two young kids
And I think
Mothers
Are the best role models for their children
I cannot
Tell them
To study hard
To be independent
And meanwhile
I'm relying
My husband
Not to where I can watch MTV
So I think
Few
Watch your children
How to grow up petrol on them self
How to be independent
Fathers and mothers
The best role models
For them
Secondly I think I'm
So so blessed
Pasta for the opportunity as we discussed
My grandmother was very smart
Age
China was in the world that the Second World War
The escape from Boise
And my mother
It was awesome he's also very smart
She was a chemistry engineer but they suffered from
The cultural revolution
And when I went to
The school the cultural revolution ended
When I went to the
College they shall pay open the door
When I finish college
In the United States
Internet
And when the internet
Dana Silicon Valley
Chinatown
Every step we made
Extremely blessed
Our generation is extremely blessed
Sofubi everyday
I'm
Sucre
School
My professors for my
Parents for everything we have
So for me the only way you can return
Disfavor
Is working hard
And create the opportunities
For the new generation
So they can be
Very successful
They can step on your shoulder
And create a new
Ida Price
That becomes
10x
As big as
Today's hits
So you feel that is
This is your calling
Strong sense of
Sabine.
So
Tigres made money
Switching basketball
Into
Very startup
In China and outside
Including busting
Did you prefer go to ja
Merging
Did we go to Nar
And many other
How do you say no problem
He also invested
Companies that just make my trip India
As well as boom supersonic
In the US
Can you talk about
Examples of
Obscenities that he hoped
The cheap
Holy smokes Batman
And how did you
Decide that you want to make
Investments
Beyond
China
That what you look for in these startups
When you
Vancomycin
Yeah we heard very high standard
Chippewa
Acquisition Target
Are there was three principles we adhere to
The first one is if needs to closely related
To trouble in this
There are a lot of opportunities
Outside
Humble but we are very
A much focused on the Travel industry
The second thing is we only I interested to a making investment in the Winger's
Number one or number two in each row
So how do we make
Tin Anniversary Inn
Zoe Massey winners
And the sad thing is
No matter how good a company is
Evaluation needs to make sense
So it's very difficult for us to make a move because we are looking for another
YouTube
Are ridiculous
So if you look at our investment wing on which is the number one Travel Agency in Hong Kong
6 years
To finally close the deal
It was during the financial crisis
When we took the opportunity and made it
If you look at our investment Inc
Again it was during the financial
Crisis in 208 and 209.
So a lot of company if they're so good
We need to be
Sarah patience
We need to be confident
That one plus one equals five Thai Palace
Synergy
Sissy trip is a travel company the business
Is inherently global
So in the fourth quarter of 2018 revenue generated from international business accounted for a 30 to 35%
One of the company's total revenue
What do you hope that number to be in
Five years in which region would you prioritize as you go global
Yes in 5 years I hope the
Pie will be 50% to domestic at 50%.
We move to the global places very methodically
So at the beginning
We only do Chinese people travel with in China
And the second is that P is
Chinese people
Trouble with eating
The Great China area
And a soda step
Is Chinese people
To Asia
And then the rest
So we pretty much finished
The Chinese people album
The layout
For Chinese people album
Now we're looking at
The flooring people
Travel to China
Because I won't even tour in China is very strong
Product offering is Farrakhan
Comprehensive
And the last
Step
Probably will be
Ford Ranger forum
So
Offering person
Safariland
I so we will make our move
Very massage
Every year
To achieve the
Best
Successful
Willow China outbound travel
I'm going to wrap up
/ 140 million
Well travel Over
Let's collect
We spent over hard
20 billion dollar
Us total
Harvard inventory from China is
Much smaller
Only 30 million
It only a fifth of those
Stuff from outside
China
How important do you think
Inbound tourism
And what kind of
Efforts
That makes sense
To help China
Is your desk
I think China offers a great offering
For the following friends
So we work very closely with the government try to increase and attract
The amount of customers
There are a couple of things
We can do with stuff
Element
Perciful we need to make
Visa application
So you know have an app
Mobile
Maybe will be much better
Captain heading to foreign friends
Lining up
In the embassy
Encompasses
How are you
So that's a first date
The second thing is The Rock
From
San Francisco
Go to China from linden tree
The sad thing is
Having a China welcome program
So well
People enter into China
We need to make sure there are English signs
People feel they are very welcome
And I think that if we focus
Which would interest the four in France
I will be able to make
Make a great mood
What is your advice to younger people with cross cultural backgrounds who have lived across both us in
I'm trying to adjust like yourself
I always tell my children that you
You would have to be
Successful they need to look at
Christopher
What's they are passionate
You can be a lawyer
You can be here cutter but whatever you do
You need to feel passionate
And try to be the best
Your verdict
Please send me your city
Passion is very poor
The second is he is what they're good at
So if you have
Eileen go by
Cultural background
That's for real
I think it is
Kids will have very good opportunities
Doing business
English speaking
Countries as well as Chinese Peking
So that's very good
The third one is also need to ride on the way
So for example
Right now
Internet
Is there a
Mobile
AI
Dizziness Trace obvious
Great
Job opportunities for the young people
The manufactory
Trouble but it's not
Fast growing as the other
Mining industry is not as fast
To write on the way pesos
As you grow your International
The demand for talent that's
Multi culture
Also Gray
What type of
Employees do you look for
Yeah
We
Try to look for furcifer bilingual bicultural people so we have a Global Leadership
Program
Hairy student
Chihuahua from China
Originally
Study of living at work
Silicon Valley New York
Lau no xcetera OU
And then I will arrange
To come back again
George
I think cookies
People Warehouse
A derecho
Remind him of them a listeners
The Power 96
Yeah that's what
Encourage you to
Because everyone was in
To apply
Last day of last you a bit more
Controversial
Which is that some of the
I will listen
Watching
DCI make the claim
That is
Not easy to find a Chinese company
Treated in the US
I knew exactly
Change or NASDAQ
That's cool
Completely transparent
Making sure
Even working papers
Accounting
With a
As You Wish Bakery
Is it this is a tricky
Touchy subject
With them
Chinese government
What's the best way for a
Chinese company
The overseas
To navigate
Yeah I think
China is growing so fast
Analogy
Hero professor
Used
Was very good
Chinese like
Yao Ming when he was 10
He was already much taller than anybody else
Right so if you expect
Teenager y'all means behave like an adult
It's a little bit tighter
Took for him
But he is learning
My Chinese learning Chinese culture is a little bit more reserved
Then the American culture
A little teeny kids
In the United States
Learn how to do PPT how to do presentation very well in China
What's green China we haven't done any presentation.
Should learn to be a global citizen very fast
Because
Much is given much is expected
As the second largest economy in the world
Are the government the community to schools
And Enterprises Lexie trip to take on the responsibility
To grow our young people to grow up
A company to be able to
I manage that
Expectation
But on the other hand
Africa
Dealzon
Need to learn China a little bit better
Millions of
Dance from China
Very interested in learning
EBay United States
If Trump issued a Visa I'm sure there will be more Chinese students
Going to study in the USA
Yet I still very few students
From the United States
Germany
O UK coming to
Study in China
The cast of
Mutual Way
Chinese people needs to invest more in the stands the US
Rules and regulation understand the culture in West
Country
But the
Oso
Missing us a little bit more try to understand
Mm a years of confusion setting
Then I think
A lot of misunderstanding yba-11
And I'm very
Blessed by the APA
Eternity
To have
The opportunity to study in a reverse Queen China and also to study and work in the USA
And I very much like to be a good Bridge 40
I think travel also plays a big
Rolin
Enhancing. Neutron
We just launched a new product
Today
Quote that Romeo
Mini
Lost
The summer my husband and I took our children
To visit Italy
So when we were in Rome we taught them about the Roman history
How to kids
So with the Wolfpack
The city
And then we took them to the
Sinsemilla the middle evil times
And we put them about the reform in a religion
Flores
And we taught them about the Renaissance
So when I come back
The kids just to learn so much
Along the way
So the Confucius teachings
It is better
To travel 10000 Mi Venturi
Pencils in a book
Came back
I talked to our products
And I thought
Did they were so much
Education
All we can do along the way
So we launched a product
And we will have
Professors experts
Destination
And before we send it to his children wear
Let them read these books
And then let them touch it when they come back they can share their stories
What they see the pictures
And I think they would never
Catabolic
And these kids will be
Such a good Global citizen rather than
Having the only
View from China to the world
Now they will know wow outside of China
There were so many people similar
Two Chinese people yet so different
I'm very positive.
Travel will enhance
The International Exchange and promote Global Peace
Now it's up to a final round of quick fire questions who's that you admire the most and why
There are many
People I admire I think Bill Gates full most
I think he
Buda such a successful
Company yet
Time
He
Contribute so much to Africa
I took the rest of the world
And I have very high admiration for him
What's something you read recently that you wreck
I enjoy
A lot there were many books
Looks like
I recommend
Are the classic book is
From good to great
YouTube
Skip Collins
And then being Enterprises
From zero to one
Explanation Enterprises
Addenda
The record book I enjoy to read
What is the
Better angel of
Kennedy
Talking about confidence
Battle Islands
Decrease
Angela racist
Progressed
What is your favorite travel desk
Oh I have so many natural
Seen I love Africa
It's just
So beautiful I think
Humans
Migrated from Africa
Ice Africa s'wonderful and we climb up
Mount Kilimanjaro in 24
And in terms of History
I love Egypt and we just went to Israel Jordan
And I think
The history of
There is just so amazing
So I got high lyrics
Recommend
She's a liar
Pier table
What you do for fun
I have many hobbies
Athletics
Are we
Ski in the winter dies in the summer
On the weekend if we run marathon and
Anything that is
Aventuras en Barranquilla
RJ that's all we have for today and thank you so much for your time
Repeat every time thank you
Thank you so much for having me
Sony
You're going to hear a short interview with our managing partner to shameful
Pelagius investment in chunar and online travel company that merged with C trip in 2015
In a deal that was bad about close to 10 billion dollars
Could you please tell us about how you first met soon are and how you came to invest in them
It's kind of a long story
And
You know I first met Fritz back in 2005 mm
Beijing China World hotel
And cons
You know a lot of us have our meetings in China Wall back then
That's right and so I met Fritz
Demopolis
Abeka no 506 bike
Beef roast
Carrying his briefcase
Telling me about this medicine
Play and travel set
And I thought it was an interesting story
But I wasn't at
Paying a lot of attention
Because at that time
B5 Baidu just went public
I thought that Jesus such as such right that's a
Big search company already just got out and
Couple billion dollars at that time
And why would that be a Marketplace for a vertical search so I wasn't paying a lot of attention to it
Until they did the series
Sirius B
I still have questions on
The value of
Hey buddy go olmeca
But during the process I got to know Cece drawing the co-founder
I also got to No Frills and the two of them really well so it was a / 3 to 4 year.
And by 2000 and
7 + 2008
I saw that they were doing something
Right
Quite right
Because how
Flight information got democratize because he
Is digitized
And tickets became e-tickets
What is physical
Tickets so that were watching TV at that time for them
To actually help
Consumers acquire
The cheaper possible
So that was back in 07 or wait
My first meeting done with frizz was
80506 and
When I saw that
The search
Yeah search for flight prices
She started to take off
The whole momentum
Because of
The
Change in the market as well back in 07 to 8
If you recall if the whole financial crisis
Action consumer becomes more price-sensitive
Sochi Nike
Quite a bit off
Post in terms of geography
One because of the market to
Because of
But digitization
Off the ticket
I can operate
Another perspective
Where Trina is
Anti portfolio
I feel that I missed
And I could tell you why I missed it
I'd like to shoot and I also met the company in mm
But only two websites
Canada travel
What is a genome
Yellow one is Secret
So why do you need a price comparison
Website that didn't even work most of the time
Can you have two
Go to two sites look for everything
And what most people also
Fresas
Even though he's an old China hand
You still not local local back
And you worried that if I see Yo is from localizing bully in bed
Into all the SMB server companies that sell ticket
In China
And then thoroughly
Chinese government in Chinese SOS
The move in trouble soccer move very slowly
When will the airline have e-ticket
Long time
And they don't they don't move.
So those are three things that most people
Applesauce
Imposter I think what you think the well was I
The sector was changing
Chinese government and the
Major airlines
In China what you shouldn't you take too much faster than anybody thought
What's possible
In Atmore travel agents
Would getting a line and want to be online
So and not dependent on them to travel sites
With all the
Price information
A competitive tuna was acquired by Foreign company
Don't shoot out was kind of left alone be able to focus on
Dominator China Market
And not be distracted
So I think you should get a ride called made on Batman bed
Welcome to BC Pasadena
Nursing home
Condition to say no about she changed
You can go back
Because this action
Oportun
Right actually
That were despite the investment that I made that was the
Question and overhang on the question
You know
Fritz and Cece and you know together can they truly
Grow a company from
You know 60 people too few hundred to a few thousand so the organizational complexity
Grows as organization complexity grows can they
That's a combination of
A foreigner versus a logo
Can they really run the organization I think that question continues to be
Be there
And I think the other line
Thing for me which
Later brought to the involvement of Baidu
What's that
The metasearch service itself it's actually a fairly thin layer in terms
Soft the value because you are providing a vertical eyes
You know comparison engine
Force very specific sector
On the front end
You still have to Baidu
Which is the start of the
Global search engine
And now you have to OTAs that kind of laying veloso y'all really playing the Arbitrage between the
Robot search
And OTAs
And that value is always
A little bit of that overhang for me so as a company evolve into 2011
I realized
By that time
That hate you know what they
Something has to happen
Is he there
Because if you look at what happened very close to Dan kayak and sites that post-merger was also silt
To Priceline
Until we knew at some point that the value of this company is
Canby cab
And so
The one thing I have to do is to figure out how to make
The company grade
Until we actually had started conversation we baidu ants eat rib and so on
And so
The involvement of Baidu
Into the company was strategically important because if actively made
Chino
Starting in 2011 the de-facto Gateway for all travel
That positioning
Houses to transform itself Beyond just a meta-search play to a OTA
And
That 4 in 2011 through 2013 Parts IPO
She not win on this
Crusade
To go from flight to
Hotel
To order multiple travel services
Transforming itself
How to become more of a multi-platform
Better than just a media platform
So that's a very important transformational change
The allow it
To grow
From a five 600 billion dollar valuation company went by the first
Got involved invested
Post-ipo of Freefall billion dollar company
Also that was a second mouse
Obviously
As a company
A photo evolve into this huge battle with C trip
And the eventual Mojo with C trip
What's in the outfit of all given how intense the company
Station wagon
And that is facilitated by both
You know by do and I'll cells
Dave & Buster's
In association with the manager
So before they became a tree lotia it was
More differentiated
From C trip in terms of Pi
Right
But you can think of the relationship kind of lie
Bible verses
Alibaba taobao right cuz if you automatic search and you
I wanted to say at some point
They the conflict
Will be there if you become the dominant player and the other is
The Dominos
Multiplayer
Because each has
While they're playing a different role
And a value chain but
Competing for value
So that competition got intense so we have to take certain sites
We took sight we baidu earlier
And then I'll
Obviously we
Did the modulator with c
I just put into perspective I think when
But Jason said when
He got Baidu
In
2 notches
Thunderman dollars
Kayak in the US
Didn't have any
Investment from Google search engine
It was sold to Priceline the number-one OTA in the US
China
42 billion dollars
Tocayos
Global companies over 2 billion
Enchinar was only 500 600 million dollars
In China is a
Only play
Doing exactly the same thing
That would by Justin Bowman
The ends up
Increasing the duration of a company
But keeping up with a number to search engine in China to become
4 billion
So
Shoot shoot important deal
To make changes about Alicia in
Complexion
Of the Netscape
That's right
I think as we
Go to Hunts Point
You no answer your investor
And some sort of a partner to entrepreneurs
Open times
You know
The entrepreneurial Drive
Yeah business on a day-to-day operationally I'll guess you didn't know that
The understand the landscape quite well.
The drive to
I did develop the strategy execute on it
But for the most part I think water in grasses have is that we have this
Globo
Landscape
Particularly our team here at GTV so we understand a lot of the Dynamics this going on Underground
You looking into that
Future
Where do we create value
The creation of valleys not just for ourselves
The creation values of audience
So and often times we hope that we could offer
A value-added advice
And hopefully
Positioning the company
4 greatest
Could you talk about
The role that you played in the sea trip to Nara merger and how long did it take and what were the biggest challenges
Well
It took a long time
I had long conversations with all sides
Including
Seatrade Baidu
And for lack of a better way to describe it it was
Pretty intense
And the intensity
Oh that's a lot of
So we have to realize one thing
Nothing right now.
Complexity comes from the fact that you have two companies do management that have fought
Over a few years and many years
And
That is a missing element
Which is true
And so it's up
And so how do you
Established
Understanding
And Trust
What the eventual
Not so much as in the value of the
DeSoto acquisition rerouted value for both
Call Juan
It's also the fact that was the eventual management going to look like
And so
That transitional management that's the big part of the conversation
Can you fight I spend so much more time
Talking food ad
Going to every single option
And that sticks a lot of time
Atticus
That is obviously emotions involve and entrepreneurs and managers needs time to digest
A lot of these options at compass
But having said that I think we
Finally came to
I didn't
It took time to Camp come to terms and typically
If you reflect
If I reflect on
The some of the parties I've done including to wqs Extra
Most of these deal
Easily take 6 months to 1 year
That's the kind of timeframe you have to
IPad 4
Are you still pacing
Throw this process
Easy hive
Objections
Easy have
When people say no or not right now
How do you get people to events
If you say yes
And how do you come up with a method to
It's Life of Pi so that every
They feel they got something that's
Either tolerable or
Acceptable or something that's
WhatsApp moving phone
Well perhaps that patience is inevitable cussing
You just you have to live with it and it's not something that you
You need to pay
Thanks for that matter you have to appreciate evolve
Aldi
Energy emotion the
The The Sweat The Tears that entrepreneur put in into building
These companies and so is not easy
And so we
Naturally have to
Appreciate and empathize
Cancel that's very important
Number one number two I think
Having said that
Entrepreneurs house arrest
That's a rational part of that understanding the value of those outcomes
So numbers that make a difference
So
Rationalizing Trudeau's numbers
And
Also
Typically that is a premium for the exit party
And so how do you rationalize Trudeau's premium
For both to buy the cell site to a
To come to terms with
And and having some sort of a
Santa Madonna
I think
That process the number of processes
This is so important because his
Is a full realization of value
A team
Obviously
If I called the
Quora to buy side
Device ID
Typically got the upside
The future value
Where is the
The cell site
Biggest dove
The value
That is premium today so so a premium to the car value so that's a bit of a working model if you go and
And rationalization to
. they call the mix of it and that
Typically for entrepreneurs that quite rational I mean you know at the end of the day
They worked out hot air
Work so hard and sweat and tears behind in that that had be a meaningful reward for them
Curious because you said that because that's competition between Sutro to Nara was becoming so intense it became inevitable
For them to merge
Is this a China specific
Phenomenal because in the US there also a lot of
Intense competitions but there doesn't
Listen to BS
Much
Murders of rival
Yeah
So
I think the
The competition in the BB look competition that us is not
YES Prep in China
And you know Zara
You've been
China over the
This few years and you see me
All intense competition is and how ruthless
So ruthless they are the mall
Delta fight
And more intense
If you look at Uber versus
Love and you compatible
DD vs quiet
It's a different level of intensity
Sometimes in China there a literal fight like between delivery men
So it's it's fairly intense and given that the
That it drives
Photo
Drai's to NASA City
Do I cheat, puto
On the stadium
What is the state
Not the CD state in some cases
If you look at some markets in some cases they come to terms
In what day is the online video landscape that's to compact that's to competition
All if you look at the
A food takeout landscape Loyola my versus made
Become so steady state
What is stop
Intensity at the start raising
Daisy stop the subsidy and start raising soda
The Tick rate
So that uses the
X ready
Discount
80 State and set them all just cannot happen for beerus
Reasons
But otherwise
Weather
Investors continue to fund it
And a neat Capital the need for Capital At You drives
Big pot of
The Mojo
You also see the founders getting diluted every time they breathe
My money
If they're bored that's in
Pop-up with more Refresher
Because the battle just sew in
Intense and it's hard to figure out who's going to win
Then
It makes a
Harder for the Thunder
The keep on raising
Abusive couple competition so intense
But you know the other guy is not going away
So you really want to do this for another 2-3 years or do you want to figure out weight results
The like Optical
9 + 6
9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 this week
What sometimes
Oo7 all the time 7 days a week
You do.
Did I kinda want to do this anymore
Gazeta
A life is going to get any better
Verses about stopping off
Boyer's too much more willing
To figure out a way to get out of the
The stomach
I think that's the kind of conversation
Often times we have to have with
Rationalizing
2D
Options ahead
The risk for sister
Reward the downside versus the outside
Like I said I think
Entrepreneurs desert emotional part of them where I'll be OCD
Add as a conviction and drive that make them who they are by the same time that's very rational part
Understand
Some of these Reis robotics
So with that that's all we have for this episode infection for a Time
Thank you thank you
798 beijing
Who does episode of 996 is a multi-stage venture capital firm based in Silicon Valley
Shanghai and Beijing with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past 18 years from seed
Capri IPO
What's 6.2 billion dollars in capital under management across 13 funds ggv invests in consumer
Retail social Digital internet Enterprise cloud and Frontier Tech
GTB has invested over 290 companies with more than 45 companies valued at over a billion dollar
Colors
Pergola companies include
Airbnb Alibaba
C trip Didi chuxing demo hashicorp Hello by cows keep
Black Square
Hotel wish soundtrue white white and others find out more at ggvc.
We also highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat group as lot Channel where we regular share inside
Events in job opportunities related to tok in China
Join these groups at 9 96.3 jvc.com community
You have any feedback on this podcast
Or would like to recommend the gas please email us at 996 at gbc.com