Hi listener
This is Zara from ggv capital
I wanted to tell you about our newly created ggv 96 community
By popular demand
We've created a WeChat group and a slack channel for followers of 96 podcast and newsletter
This is a community brought together by shared interest in Tech in China in these groups
Will regular share China related news insights as well as events and job opportunities
You will get to talk directly with tons of me
Unconnect with other like-minded people who care about tech in China
Last week Hans did it live Ama or ask me anything
In the WeChat group on the topic of Maitland and paying and super ABS
We're also in the process of planning offline meetups
For a commission members in multiple cities including the Bay Area and Beijing
Details for these meetups as well as future and a session
Will be announced in the group
To join the group's please go to 996. Gigi vici.com community
And follow the instructions there
Once again
That's 996. GG vici.com community
Now onto today's episode
Intervention
Hi there
Welcome to the 9th at 6 podcast brought to you by ggv capital and co-produced by the Seneca podcast
On the show interview movers and shakers
China's tech industry as well as Tech leaders who have a us China
Cross-border perspective, managing partner at ggv Capital it had been working at startup
Investing in them in both the US and China for the past 20 years my name is
I meant investment analyst RGB capital and a former journalist
Why is the show called 9696 is the work schedule than any Chinese Founders have organically it
Adopted that is 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
To us996 captures intensity Drive in speed
Of Chinese internet companies many which are moving faster that even their American counterparts
On the show today we have Jenny Lee one of the managing partner is IGG vcap
Capital Jenny is usually based in China but she comes to us once in awhile as well
Jenny joins UV capital in 2005 as managing partner
And was instrumental in setting up to see his presence in China
As a self-professed geek Jenny has an infectious left for new technologies and new products
Jenny was recently ranked by Forbes as the world's 16th most powerful women in Tech
Her name has also appeared on the Forbes Midas list
Of the world's top Venture capitalists since 2011
Ranking is number 1 woman and number 10 overall in 2015
Igtv Jenny has invested in companies in consumer internet
Sassa Frontier Technologies
She has helped several companies go public
Including High soft
21vianet
Thanos son and why
She's on the board of Liberty show also known as lingochamp
Casualty hung
Keep kingsoft
New.com
Fanatic
For your bong
Surgeon salary
We are done done and you see what until it was acquired by Alibaba
She has also invested in
Striped Rai momento and clobotics
Jenny grub in Singapore
Came to the US for school where she obtained
A bachelor's and master's degree in electrical engineering from Cornell
As well as an MBA from the Kellogg
Score at Northwestern
So Jennie my first question to you is
Could you describe to us
Your journey from Singapore
To the US and then to China
Now you are very renowned investor in China but when you first started out there it was actually your first time in China
Thank you Sarah
So it's an interesting background I have I think if I
Call back
To when I was 18 years old
And that was a time when I realized it
You know being one of
A tree 4 million population in Singapore
That's released
When you think about the wolf population at 7 billion
And I'm in a little country
With such a small Market
You know I followed it
I needed something bigger
I need the opportunity to go out and do
Taobao without
As well naturally
Is in Nepal
Student has a kid
Yeah told that you can't when you grow up to be in four different
You're either doctor a lawyer
An engineer or an accountant
Edmodo
I want to see you at the choices that work
But pulling the engineering route multiple choices it was
It just makes more sense
Is to be in the US
Square education in the US on the technology site
At least ranks ahead of you know other countries
So that's how that's how I got to
The US
That's why I obviously
Singapore does it snow all the time
Never had a chance to go to Four Seasons on the East Coast
I let's go to a place where it's nice and conducive and hopefully safe
When I went to Cornell was my first trip to the USA
I didn't do it I had no idea how the colleges book
Is alpha-gal accepted by Cornell
Check it out
To my suitcase
Blue by myself
Spend the next four years
Without coming back
Singapore
Back in 2001
I was graduating from Kellogg
I was going East West Kellogg Chicago
Did my MBA
McDaniel won the market the world was crashing
Play we had 911
In the US the whole internet bobbleheads
Crash and so when I looked around as well
The in between
Cornell in Kellogg you were in
Engineer
You are flying drums
That's right
So before my MBA graduate in 01
IQ Spencer between Cornell and my MBA I spent about four and a half years
Newly walking the field so I was a electrical engineer India
What we called electronic warfare division
Optical Technologies Aerospace
Facebook sounds really a jet engineer for 4 and 1/2 years
Every day I was out in the sun
Hanging out with the technicians in a fighter jet Pilots
But that's really way I learn about technology
Not just acknowledged on the book
But you know how things were built how things with
Design
Where you know systems are being you know
Evolve
Well the cutting technology
If you think about today's internet
Startups a lot of the car technology
Came from the defense industry
So that was how I started my my career
Having two
What kind of project for 3 years
To ensure that this you know the drawing gets developed
3 is really short action
In the in the in the lifetime of a commercial product product list
Weight loss
So you know that's how I got
To do my MBA
Deciding to do a
But then yeah and so you know one looking around the world
The next largest market at the time China Market
Would you be up and coming
We saw Cena's IPO
In the US in 1990
Online
And at Asia info with the other second IT services IPO in the US
Until a few slight you know China was
You know coming up if you believe in Tech believe in Silicon Valley see the cross has happened
You have to believe that
There will be a similar Trend in
Broke my bone pit off my
Scholarship loans and then went to China again first time in China
No relationship no friends
Started from Ground Zero
Since we much chuck Mandarin
Desert base off my 2 years old to
Previous education fundamental education Singapore
Education but really I haven't been using the language
And so we learn learn to read
Plants in Chinese
Learn to understand technical jargon in Chinese
A lot of entrepreneurs help
Many of the CEOs today
EOS
Deal with that when I was dead they were the ones who taught me
How to speak
How to use the right phrases in Chinese
We got him
And now you're completely fluent
No I get by pretty well
Don't limited you when you first
Chengdu China
You start off in banking
Was Marcus Allen
And I was going to
Yeah that's right so in 2001
When I went to what I knew I wanted to go to China I had no idea how to start cuz I know nobody that
On top of that as a mission Aaliyah I actually had to pay off my initial and regret
Masters MBA scholarship
That's a lot of money
Average family
The league
Maybe lower class
Bourbonnais Fair
That's why I need a scholarship for my age
Education is so to really pay off
The best way to do it is
You know
Be a banker
Real quick
Abortion the IBD Division and the ECM.
Very lucky as well cuz it was a tough time to be inventing
But the one year was
Gimli
Cuz it got me to understand the whole
Can ultimately you know
Get to be a public
Company by that quickly cuz I realize you know when you are a fighter jet a great engineer
You don't last very well
And you don't last very long
In the banking environment
The great difficulty
And instead of pushing it all like beauty products I would like pushing papers and presentation and during translation
SOI Levin georgescu
In 2002
In the June timeframe and I saw a jackal
Jekyll is a real estate venture capital firm supported by in order Japanese vintage
Fusion SEL really had a chance to then start to look at China Beach
PCC market
From mm in
And that's why I did some O2
What about you
05 early 05 Buick
Star Jeff
And in the two months later you join 2 TV
That's why I still remember it
Hans at a time
Came to China Yuan in Shanghai
What's the weather
Bessemer
And so
This was only time in the China Beach
DC Market
Where a lot of the capital was still coming from like USA
Fallout 4 OST
Korea and China
It's not just about
Chinese language
You have to be extremely good with staying up late at night
Is you have to do late phone calls with
Do us call deposits Partners have to be doing a lot of translation
But you know how to swallow me
Cuz this is the suit guy nice
Pictures of tomorrow
Smile
Always will
Whether it's 10 a.m.
LOL my first deal
In inside of the Cove Restaurant
On the Border
That was a very interesting
Yeah that was some
Is it
Channel 506
Who's Blac Chyna
Set a timer
Internet
Tu.org
What's the ratio of blogs blogs very popular
But was extremely good experience always like to say that there was a time when I really got to know hun
A lot of investors around the table
What companies do well
That table get smaller
The people around the table get
Guess you know that multiplies get more people around the table everyone wanting to raise your hand
To be
I do recall we had
Do the interesting story we had another BC who wanted to be chairman
Ausable
Because he thinks this is going to be a great company and he just wants credit
We have more Downs than UPS
And so is the sector got really hot Malcolm Pettit
Just came in
The company didn't deliver
And the only
Think that I really remember it was at the end of the the heydaze you just answer me and the seal
In his room on the couch
Trying to figure out
He's about
It's about being dad with entrepreneurs not just a notch
I'm sorry but when they need a swelling
To be there as cheerleaders
But to you don't figure things out
Speaking things out
And what with him to figure out and if if the end means that we have to wind down to company
And that's why we
And through that process
You know I was at Hans is my
Congrats in war
If a photo wall together
You know
You know who's going to be in the trenches review
Who is going to be there to watch your back
BC
You know it's not always a lonely business
If you have a great partner around the table
I think
Effect of The Upside
Just enormous multiplier
Is important only for the Thunder to pick the right
Pick the right following
To be around the table
So I find it remarkable that both Hans and Jenny you guys
Didn't grow up email in China X robbing Taiwan and then the US
Jagrup in Singapore so what challenges did you face when you first went to China as investors how
Launch it take you to a climate to the local environment and how businesses down there
Yeah I think that not being
Born in China not having grown up in China
Really get me a healthy respect
For the country
People from D1
You go in Fightin you go in scat knowing that
You are starting at Ground Zero
At the base
I think what that does is allows me to be very open to
The people that meeting
To constantly be learning about what's new
You know what's normal what's local
To always
You don't have respect for the people around me because any one of them can be
Teacher
Write whether it's in a certain train
Whether it's in
Specific areas
A simple is hiring right how do you hire
In China how you how do you set up a company in China
How do you talk to entrepreneurs while he's smoking your face
Those are all the different
A local situations that we have to do
Do with butthole
Having an open mind
Going in knowing that you know that's only upside cuz that's what you're learning
Knowing that you don't have glenshee and so there's really nothing that you can rely on your back end
Means that you have to work harder
You have to work longer time
You just have to make yourself better
Compared to everybody
Living my expense with similar
I was forcing that when I went to China
Chinese
Is quite fluent
But the by way of
Thinking was more American
And
Because I've been a student of Chinese history and history general for Lumpy
Set a time
He was at for me it wasn't as difficult
Adjust to
China
And I think that the p
People
Attendance at World Market Lemoore open
Thought I thought
Is very much a meritocracy
If you went to work hard bring value
Generally try to help a company and not try to screw them
Looking to put over some terms
Not trying to make every
Take every cent
Every
Youcam makeup
Off the table
People appreciate your genuine
And willing money must go help
So I actually did my eight years of investing on the garden China probably a month
Berate
Steamboat ski boarding years my
And this is why I want to come back to the US
People's immunity as a Mainland Chinese Avicii
You crack me up cuz I actually think that the US market
It's a lot easier
To make investments and dizzy
Antidiuretic intelligence super competitive
Talk about it
The gold picassco 96 9 a.m. p.m.
But as Avicii
Pretty much is oo7
12 a.m. to call volume always thinking about work
Always think about in a how to
When in when needed
Go to lunch Pandora's office don't leave until the size on the timesheet
What she signed on the dotted line
And you know some some people you move wire money before to Seaside
Just makes my lock out the deal. Kind of crazy stopping it will work in the US
Putting China it's what it takes to get a
Get stuff done
And having
Throw into the fire and be able to
How to survive
Together with Jenny and then Elsa teaching
It's a very rewarding
Feeling that you have a lot of confidence
Your teammates.
Push comes to shove
You can get stuff done
So what a dick deeper into that point where you said
Almost more difficult to invest in China in the in the u.s. is that because there's a lot more competition there a lot more deals
Open alarm or BCS
Yeah definitely a thing today the Demarcus
Change the China Market has
Evolve
Substantially
The entrepreneurs Eva Mall
You know educated R I didn't know what's out there didn't know how to compare this a lot more information
On the web
And so they don't come from a point where
They are just learning their to come from a point where they are doing you to lose
On the beach
And and that
As tens mentioned Olia to BCC in China extremely extremely competitive
You know meetings take place at midnight
Vizzi's do sit in the office and do some sheets a sign and so
The level company
Addition
Is is a lot higher
Are you tryna we will sit this is a great deal you have
To do what
Whatever it takes
Julie is not just about putting one person in front of the entrepreneur
Is putting the entire form
The the the company's values to companies
Experience in a week
Steam out there as well to help a portfolio
Sometimes we call on ozios to call Odyssey
And soul in China
You do have to be a lot more quiet
You have to figure out how to break the
How to get in front of
Entrepreneurs
And so be you don't even after 17 years in China
We don't sit back
And just forgot oh you know we'll just wait for the entrepreneurs to come knock on my office all you know come visit
Where she out there
Constantly in awe looking at what's new
A meeting with Yolanda
Trying to figure out you know the trends
And then when the deal is
You know we like the deal
We are there
So it's a battle it's a fight
And even when you're in investor into a company you also have to have a very good
Perspective off the whole macro lens
Because cuz the spaces
Highly competitive today they may be two players
And the investor is the number one
Tomorrow the space Maybe 2000 players
You know especially when the big guys Alibaba
Off the wall
Comes in and decide that this is the space you want to be
And so
Again it's not just micro around the company it's also having that
Perspective on the macro level
And then that helps us to help to navigate
You know how the company of the
Co navigate
The pop
You share the story of how you open up a
The office
As demonstration what it takes good stuff
Going
How much regulation
Taping of Jumperoo
People to get stuff
Yeah so this is in 2005
China was juvenation
Baghdad you have no WeChat you have no alipay
Payment was not great
Credit card you know most
Shopsins
And Facilities don't accept credit card so is basically a very cache
Zapata industry and it 05 when I went to China
We had to set up the company
He got the name for the company hire employees
And it was a really weird system
Because
To hire employees
You need to
First set up the end
It takes 6 months
To set up an entity called Wolfie which is a wholly-owned foreign entity
Back then
And so
Interior you cannot hire anyone within the 6 months time frame
And that after the entity set up
That's when you're allowed to have a bank account
And so that's what money
So so for the first 6 months it was a very interesting time. Cuz I literally went to China with us
Suitcase of cash
RMB cash
And you know when to hire employees I have to tell them that they are not officially hired
Have the right light but yet
A zodiac degree time for that
So-called freelance for that 6 months
And every mine
I will be back in the office
To pay them a salary
Encash
And so you know it's that that's part of the process of starting up
All the operations back then today is a lot easier
05 so it takes a lot to not just a starting the operation
Full LGBT employees who took that leap of faith
To join ggv no one knows
I didn't have a Chinese
We had to figure out a Chinese name for entity
And so it's it's been a
Very amazing
Johnny
You really getting you no hands dirty
Understanding what it means to set up my own Juju vdare
In the way I understand what start up to half
To go through
To really go from
02 Jacinto 0.1
Yeah I think
The pony makes very very
Unique about China is at
Entrepreneur
If you want to
You can grow up just
It's just so many hurdles to jump through
Simatai regulation red tape back then
And so
Over last 10 years
Has he improved
But it just makes it
Even though
Tougher
Competed to finish eighth this
Do you need a even make
Pick up weed
Empire
The New Normal
Cook Ford
Biking through
It's also topper in China who's the company
Scalp and skull so quickly
Onesie
Market of 1.3 billion
Pokeball in
100 billion
Users
So if you something worse even
So people willing to overpay or Liang
Because they know that evil wards
Spell bougie
And then like Jenny said
Everyday every category
Every 2-3 years
To your something new happen
And in the process a lot of copycats
Gets offended
As well so we have
Pia fiercely
Until 1 to
Emerge as a winner
So we see that movie
Play every year
You get used to it getting us
System rhythm
Pattern when I come back in 2013
Kabaddi
Surprisingly somebody else
Slow
Compared to China
Because the market is only more
Amateur is a lot of stuff offline that's already in decent shape
So that whatever all my option there is
Automatic
Khalid better
To differentiate
Candy Bonanza
Small Market
So it takes more time to
2 scale where China
LeapFrog effect of
The offline
Fishing offline
Eton Park Stewart mix a lot easier
Go buy something you hop in the
The competition
Extremely fierce
Bailiwick
Do you guys have any anecdotes
Sore crazy stories to share that illustrate how things work differently in China
So I think that
You know
Sure but we think about feces doing due diligence it's
Financial due diligence
Business due diligence maybe some
Optical illusions
And of course legal YouTube
Are you at half
You know that the party
Consultants and advisors
Come in and give it a
Second look
In China doll with hat
Very interesting due diligence technique
Cakes that we may have
How to develop
So back in the early days between 2000 to 2005
Most of the entrepreneur Sweeney
There's really no one to ask
You know how did in your previous job little reference
Does that you can get
And so early days I actually hire private
Alligators
Leo companies
And it's interesting because you don't really do that
Here in the US anymore
And so we asked you what was that party
Investigators to look through
The records of entrepreneurs
To see if they have
You know of any laws
And in the process some of the reports we find out
Vici find out interesting things like he has a second wife
What's up wife
Multiple properties
And it's another way to join understand
Nothing
Encryption
Category
Eolian because in Orion
2005 the Jews wasn't in after party
Service providers
Sufficient resources and information to help us
I understand what it means to do to
Management
We can spend you know 20 30 hours with with the entrepreneurs week
You know all to understand it but that's not enough
Another example of a different types of due diligence is on the gaming
Investments that we made
So does this company actually does cell communication
Tools for gamers
So when we first met with the CEO
He was adamant that he's the number one market share leader
Like in China
And when I asked him for data to support he has no data
He said I believe I'm number one I am number one
So it's not it's fight and there's no cuz this is a new category that's really not that party
Research firms that can help us as well
And so this is Rangers
Time to 8:09
And so I should design a survey
Internal survey of
Bunch of questions
And then I got my entirety
Baby stuff at that time
We had like six
Azalea flower receptionist assistance
Associate
I don't think we had Associates
Dope so really just the only team in China and we went to Beijing Shanghai in
Guangzhou
Do the internet cafes from Midnight
Back then you no internet cafes with
He was a gamer
I'll don't have PCS at home they were just playing games right
Until we actually survey our guys
Non-investment team members that you went into survey
He was a 200
Person survey
So we had to ask a lot of people in between different cities
And the net result actually showed that amount of the competing products
Really at the close to 70
6% market share
Still getting you know what he taught us is that in the market that's emerging in the market that was really really knew back then
Are you just half
Tool
Have more creative way to understand to verify the numbers
Less reliant on third-party
But more more depending on you know how creative we can to triangulate all the different data
That we have
Today is great I think today in China you can
Conduct 5000% sebae you can have online surveys
But back then it was
Really
Heart
That's right this is like 8 or 9
For me I remember
One of my first and last
Company called
U-high
Car services
Now there is
New York
And
I have us in them when we had
20 cars
No
They have like
Without forgiving the first
Check
The CEO open up
20 stores
Skiing appear.
Looks like 5 months
But make sure that the R20 stores there I literally went to
It's been less than a week
Went to Forest City
And Lissa Thornton stores
It interview the storm coming
MassHealth income
Car
Turn on the parking lot
That's how I know that yeah
I like him but it's not verified that he
He said he did what
Youku
So doing whatever it takes
To verify Things Are
Because otherwise
You know the company of the CEO should not be the one that we are betting on
But after that to verify
And both of you imagine that
I think everyone agrees that relationships are very important in China so I wonder how did you
When you went to China
No relationships how did you go about building that Network
Yeah so when you know you have no relationship it's good cuz
If nothing else
He started 0 and sold the way I've done it is really just to spend more time
Tmall meetings
For example when we first when I first started looking in the gaming space
Baidu
Play games
And I do understand simulator from my you know
Equibase
It's a very different Market in China and so what that means is really going to the internet cafes
Hanging out with gamers
Hanging out with Developers
I should spend a lot of time in Guangzhou xinjiang in the early days
Just having coffee talk
Swifty.
This are like game developers what's the most presentable
Where to find them
And so you go when you meet one you ask
The the first guy that you made after you have an hour you know coffee or tea with him
Whether he will recommend other people.
And So within certain geography
Area
Veteran unicorn Journal Eastwood
Guangzhou 10 sentient and so the number of
Software
And game developers are like The Advocate
Because you know they hang out
They have the only
Art & Soul
You know getting to know
The first one
Allows you to
But
It doesn't mean that that will be a deal that will come out of it
But through the process we get to hear a lot more about what
What are the trends
Which which fuel has gotten funding you know what's new
That so it's a
But I think once you start to
Trollface and you know sure that you are learning and yeah
And have a good yeah you can have a good attitude
People do open up
Do you
And those relationships actually last a long time
Today I may not hang out with them as much
But they are dead they know they know who I am do you know how to look for me
I went to sacudir that's out in that space
You know they will come by and say hey
So this is just one example
In the IT services
Space force investor in hyssop
That was I went all the high-tech parks
In China every single one from Dalian Beijing Guangzhou
Sushi Shanghai every single one talked
2D Hi-Tech products
Officer
Cuz back Daddy was a highly highly so
Supported by the government
And so then meeting with the top three to five
Companies in
Indoor hotels for everyone
Italian I had to drink baijiu
Sea Wolf Brooklyn
They also had a lot of Japanese influence
So you know that the alcohol culture is strong
They also play a lot of golf
I do remember there was one do you actually sign the timesheet on the Gulf
To happen
But it is also it does take the extra effort
To go deep
Spend the time
Again you know to understand
I think as long as you
Show respect
Are willing to listen to people you be surprised like how many people are actually willing to
Yeah that's exactly right
I remember
I used to have
8 meetings a day
And
We willing to
Do so much
Downtown Boulder
You will need to do that and you'll very willing to help people leaving food out investor
You're waiting to share your knowledge
And you're
They are contacts
And your insights on the
Thanks for your studying
Do people
People think you're nice guy work hard and smart
They are very very open
So what you been with a lot of people
In the USSR
Complain
It is harder for me
Me too
Fully appreciate
Because if you
If I can go there
As I
The Foreigner
Make it work
And then
If it would be willing to
Try it
So you could go to China without bias
And could really
Understand how works
And not feel Superior
I feel like this is
Then I think the chance
I think that's a great message
For people who are
Putting crop in China
Cool maybe you are from the US or other parts of the country were interested in getting involved in China's Tech echoes
But don't know where to start I think just like having an open mind spend time they're getting to know that people can be very powerful
It helps you know how we can smoke
I always forgot to smoke at night
Drink if you need to but asking for me I didn't
View my eight years in China
I do have a drink more than
Exclusively in Internet space
UC is very much that you don't need to go anywhere stuff
You can just focus on business
Show your
Your ward
Throw in Charlton
Discussions
YouTube
China is actually more open to entrepreneurs 10
A lot of times all us entrepreneurs
The afraid
On
And so you know what you
Before even setting foot in China
Become a way in
You know they going there
With you
But I think I Echoes Hansa comments earlier if if
He and I
Both
We haven't grown up in China we don't we did not go to school that we didn't work that
And we can
By just paying attention to entrepreneurs
Listening vs. speaking all the
Time
You know and then to help
You willing to help
Be willing to learn
Be very open-minded
You know that's that's always a way to
But you cannot do it
Sitting in the US
Do understand China you have
To be in China
One day in a year
But if you're a CEO of a company wedding
How to break into China
You have to make the commitment not just a
Stands on Monday
But for you for you yourself
To be willing to
Spend that time
Living title
I think Jenny of said before that what motivates you to
To be investors real your love for technology I wonder where this
Confirm my why are you so passionate about the new technologies
Yeah I don't know I think I was born with it
Why I always have this
Believe that
A single person
Can change the world
Somehow I believe that
And I
Again and again in the last 17 years that individuals have the ability
To both markets
To change perceptions
And to create companies
You know that today
Amazing
Play look at Jack ma with
20 years ago
He was a
Teacher
Angel
And you don't
Make even she can make it right
Pizza Hut
I've always felt like you though individuals of believing that the individual can make changes
Very important
And then tool
In today's age
Would that change the Monumental change position
Disruptive change versus evolutionary change
I might believe is that
Hess
To leverage on something
And that Leverage
Is likely to be
Technology
Right because if you can have a robot that can achieve the toss of a thousand workers
But this one
They can remove
The repetitive
Cost at 1000 Wilcrest
Have to do that sufficiency
And Ethel with with new ways of thinking new ways of competition new ways of Technology you can create brand new
Products
And so I think that's where you get to lavaridge
Not by having a thousand percent do the same thing even smarter is not enough if you can Leverage
A cheap to do better
Robot
To do better then I think that's how the will is be
So that's what drives me every day I want to see
You interesting
Products and services that can really go out and create something
That maybe we haven't thought off today
Just like when
We got our first iPod offers
Ford meet with thought that was like a geek
Gaming device
Today is not good gaming device
Today
Absolutely it's all uniform
Communication and
Civista information platform even the three-year-old cannot do without
Your iPhone or iPad right
Hans do you want
To elaborate on that
Fink's
I was lucky that went to Stanford
Cuwest
Mybatis like
And see how he changed
Stamford bartending
The 90s
Is Dallas very very different
Thanks to all that unit of money
I donated
So eat when you see it a place I can
Can change a lot universe
Image appreciate what
Technology
Juventus
In China
In 2005 was
The first one
Sitting in a second I'm going to China
The 1999
And when I remember when
Percent in 95 I was like oh my God
A while
To come out
In 95
When I first got into banking
I see that
Chinese
I still limp
Or try to go public
Put on your stockings
These are very
Old school companies
But you 99 you can still see that watch henna
I'm different
Internet
Has cotton people
What's the tension
And wants to go there again in 2000
3/8 Oz 1/4 oz
He just start seeing the Cubs
Kingsbury
And so
When you see what you don't see
She has done to a
Communist country
We're now the most valuable company
China are
BusyBox
Listing in New York
And Hong Kong and that's the intention and that much bigger than any other
Cinema Enterprise in China in the happen
In Little League
Less than 20 years
It makes you look bad
See
Why was part of that we were part of that change
And makes you very proud
That you like us
Cat probably has had more impact
In China than anywhere
Alice in the world
In the last 50 years
Probably
I think also in China people considered to be a force for good mostly
Whereas people here are more likely to talk about
Like Emily Shop jobs or
How new technology can
Have negative impact on Paris
Stakeholders but in China we don't see that much
Discussion
Yeah I think a keyboardist because
Government support so the Chinese government by and large
This is one of the benefit of being in the country
Economy
Before I went to China I never quite appreciate
The communism
As demonstrated by China
Then know that I've been in China for 17 years I think that the planned economy is not always bad
And by plan
The Chinese government duplex right in the dimension in mm 205 is that okay China is going to now
Upgrade our students
And a Workforce for manufacturing
To IT service
And soul
That's how high-tech pops
You know supported in every
Tri-Cities
That's why grants and scholarships were given to encourage
The students do I choose
To learn software programming
And so that that created a huge Talon
Pool
For the IT service
Industries rifle Wednesday Services IBM Services Microsoft
The local Enterprise like I saw
You know what new software example
Want to go into this
Category day now have talent pool and because of governments
Supported
Similarly fast forward today with AI
Hugh Janus
Hot Topic
The government has
Bee Tattoo
Really
Investing in call R&D for AI
Talent
How to develop AI
Pipe IP
AI type
Tallinn to attract International talents from different schools PHD programs
You also come back so it's not just local policies by social
International policies
Bring that
Until I think having great government
Does help
You know the whole industry think about the
Possibilities
I was talking to another company that was so manufacturing that was using robotics
To automate some of the process
And my question was
Are you worried that your workers are going to get really
Angry baby cuz you because some of the
What stations are being replaced by
The robots
And you know his comment is that
Number one they offered a job said I want to hire
And I cannot find
That skill set something as simple as
Picking mushrooms
That's actually is skew set that
Cannot now be trained because most of the youngsters don't want to be trained as a mushroom picker
Light bulb and decimal one can find the Talon anyways
Can you cannot do enough
Between them
The number to
The government every supporting by
Subsidizing automation
So over 20 30% of factory lines if you automate
The applicant by the government
And soul
You could almost try this for free
You know how to start automatron station and then the next day
So again I think the government support isn't just
Bubbleologist
Skin policy
They are actually doing it in real
Stop CDC
Support and you see it not just you know in factories
We see it in the whole TV
Sector the electrification of Carswell infrastructures
What is being built
Part 2 across all the different verticals
So that's one
The number to the Social grid
Role model
We talked about tencent we talked about Alibaba
We have seen in China the Chinese entrepreneurs now have
Seen that you can be special
Show technology you can be a average guy and yet
Be able to
Will be the next Purnima or the next Jack Ma
Enough presidents to show that
Is possible
Anything lastly the mindset of parents
Change
Daniel 10-15 years ago in interview now Associates
Most of the associates once they are in Great Schools and when they graduate the one
Bridget was the government
And then it was diyc like the Microsoft now.
And then you know it was a startup
And now when you talk to them if they want to do startups
And so I think the whole mindset has
So net-net I think that you could system is
Pretty healthy
Yeah the number of stem graduates in China
Increase dramatically now.
15.6 million
Back in 26
That's almost ten times.
The size of a stem graduates
Science technology engineering
India
The US
Liberty India
So there's a lot more people willing
To learn talking
Try talking to Tech
And as China continue to grow the size of a service engine
Continue to grow so
Do you may lose job in one sector but the s
Economy is growing at 7% year-on-year
Do new jobs
So tennis pretty smart to upgrade cell
Well you calling me all those phone down compared to historical numbers are still growing
Proximo some countries around the world
So if can afford population to accept
That $2 bill changes will make things even better
RMB company
Grow
So I think that is a
Hattiesburg different Point NC
Example of a motorcycle
Versus us and Western Europe
And that means easier
For a i and others who knows Univision
Yeah Usher argue that Chinese drama is very forward-looking
Regarde-moi wants to get something done it got
Done very efficiently very quickly
So I wonder what advice do you have for us companies trying to navigate the political landscape there in
How do you like predict weather governor
Going to do in a certain sector how do you align your interest with a government interest
I'll try to start at First Look at example of uber in
Talk to Uber team in China
That most of them
Feel.
They were not extra
Discriminated
By the
Chinese cover
I have to go through and get approval for
Didi China how to do this
That's something Travis set himself
That's correct so they were more or less
Similar playing field for the most part
And as an Uber team of all yours companies in China their PopularMMOs aggressive
Yeah no work the hardest
And what will it do things
The more Chinese way
So if you're willing to adopt locally
And work long hours work smartly
Looks very hard
The chest
Success is a lot higher
I think there's some sectors for sure that Chinese government to regulate and make a cup of foreign players
Infield media
IND
Social networking
So
I love Google in Facebook
Space and talented
But when it comes to e-commerce
Friends or a lot of other things
Us companies still have a great Advantage swimming
Look out fer that the US
And that USM
Congress have
Chinese internet companies buying us
But you know Apple
Is still
Is the most successful film company
I must have in China
Yeah poppleton raise more revenue from iTunes
The App Store
In China.
Anywhere else
And you want to argue
Your US Government through Apple can have access to some data
And it's just a lot to happen
So yes there's some boys I'm some government regulations issues but the Practical Chinese camp
And you ask
So it's not anything
Tomorrow
How willing you
You're willing to die
Right now we're at the Julie watching the regulatory
Changes and what the government says India Congress
Important as well
Dimensional yeah right in 2000 to 05 when the Chinese government saying I want boost it
What cause I want to be the next Bangalore
Outsourcing
You at companies like Microsoft HP
HD
Establishing ID centers
In China
To support this
Scroll saw into a train engineer Siri
And so understanding where the Chinese government is putting effort
To grow to 2
Like for example in the EI sector
Tube to bring calendar
It makes sense that Google has an R&D Center
In China
So understanding the trend reading the trance
Don't go against the grain
Once you understand where the big train is going
And you can help this
The part that grows
Then whether your local company or whether you're International
You going to have
A way to play in the mall
And getting it ahead
Everybody else
It's probably even better
All your competitors are still thinking about how to beat the regulation
And your your head up there
By working with local governments to make sure that you're on the right track right weather
As I mentioned some of this Evie Tran Dai Trang
Then I think you have
We are now seeing a lot of automotive
Oh yes International ones trying to type into the China
Automotive Market China is the world's largest
Automotive
120 million
Installed base of passenger car every year 22
25 million new cars being sold
In China
And so if you are 40 I'm sitting here
In the US or damla right in Europe
All in in in Japan
You you have to want to figure out how
And so understanding The Strand understanding who you
She talked to
Understanding who you
Do JV with
Once you understand that random Bieber facts about
In terms of the approach
Write me mean that you have to do a JV first
Voloco partner
You mean that you have
Set up some Hi-Tech Development Centers
In college
Tallinn
You made me and you taking Strategic investment stake
Insound some of the startups in China
And so that being very open to others different
What will help companies to understand the local nuance
Then that's a better formula
But you look at Apple depriest pyrite
Invest in Didi
Invest in Uber
And as shown in
China as a willingness
Topless Porter Loco
Entrepreneur startup community in Louisiana
And
Apple is helping a lot of a Chinese app
Apps to expand
Through
App Store to open
Markets
MDC Tim Cook going to our proposal company like
Where
Jenny and housing
I sit on the board of
To see all the Innovative Chinese company that's doing well
And recognize them
Through his
On global basis
So Apple smart and understanding that 10 camera what
C10 company Go Global
I'm just playing a role to help them to do that
But not bees on
When she or subsidy or favoring but these are great companies
.
You just like them the most gorgeous. Where else
I'm outside of
And
For us
We don't have
A lot of special
Insights before the government is going to do next
Almost no one.
So how do you figure out what regulation will not be as much problem going forward
Utica white Chevy Market
Gumbo
Beijing has a 20% car ownership
Yet this has the biggest traffic problem
That doesn't come out
So and it says somebody has 70% ownership
Already even get the given
Uber and Lyft
So if
China
Inviting people as many people buy cars
As of the r
Car lenders in Spokane Valley
Can you imagine
The street of Beijing
3x 4X more cars on this today
So you know no matter who is running the government
Ride-sharing and bike-sharing has to be part of the solution help us all that traffic congestion
As urbanization
Increase
Peking China
You figure out where China is going
I try to anticipate what I wanted a problem to be solved
There are plenty of things that come out
Play a positive role
So figure out what China House 2
Tell to make this country work
Yes
Continue to grow and for Emerson continue
So Jennie you focus a lot on a Frontier tax sector edges UV I wonder
Where do you think China stands in the world and how it Compares 2 U S embarrassed feels of
Frontier technology
Full frontal tactile definition of Chicago Street differ
The first
She's around
Shinto from
Billy autonomous-driving all the way down to EV
The first actor for us
2nd sector is really in
Robotics
Animation
About holiday
Patrice inch
China Wei
Automating different
Workflow
Different now what
Isis that's happening not just
City lodge effect
Please by Billy.
Turn it down to the
Small medium
Usually around
Which is a little bit mod software you know versus
How to hotwire cars
IRobot if you look at this area fancy attack
Is generally viewed as a new area both in the US and
China Doll classified both
To be at the first evening
What does that mean
Meanwhile at night I think that's
Number one thing when you think about the talent pool
This is really attached to a very hot liquid
Contested space right now so whether it's a I tell any of the u.s. REI Thailand in China
Elmo's at the
The same level
Where does a severe
You know shortage of the right
AI type of talent
As engineering offices
Stevens Brothers Jess PhD
You know it's done algorithms all research
In this area
Chat with it on the talents is pretty similar same footing
In terms of what these startups are focusing on that it's a bit of a day
Difference so in the US we have seen startups when he called himself a i
Companies tend to be more software
Bass what is leveraging machine learning
All in different vehicles with a simple banking application or in
The computational area pretend to be a lot more
Software
Even in the automotive area with Seymour Alpha autonomous-driving startups in the u.s. trying to attack this issue
In China we see a small white bass
Trump all startup trying to take different
Pieces of the
So you're not restricted to just Southwest
Solutions
They are putting that software Solutions
Go to hardware
And so generally Chinese entrepreneurs are not has
Afraid of the hardware
Thumbs-up sometimes we think about hot when Subway Fuze I get two different DNA is two different verticals
And a start-up should I do both and when they focus you should be either focused on software
But then you will you know in the hallway I enable War
Autonomous car on the robot
It's an integrated product is
The system with a hardware and software
And so in that respect we have
PC Mall innovation around complete
Teksystems
In China
Stila Leon early days
From a market perspective I think it's similar the problems and pinpoint that's being
Address
I'll being
You're very similar whether it's cybersecurity in the US
Stay around mobile cyber security
It's a CMP employee that Chinese
Especially in China
You know with
That module
Transactions
Going through mobile platform as well
So very similar problem sets
So I actually predict that in the next 5 to 10 years has the whole AI Market
Get my mom a chill has all this application starts to find its vertical
Application
The chance of companies that has more cross-border
Interaction will go up
Equip be
Talon right us companies trying to leverage not just a talent pool that can find us
But the reverse right can you attract more Chinese entrepreneurs to stay in the US
That we have to rely on
The goodness of the US government but I think you will see that all devices
Supposed to write Chinese
Startups actually hiring Us Talent
And then allowing them to
You know wolf
Tool to China
ABS on the talent pool exchange and then ultimately products
As well
Can you build better robots
Can you build better
Autonomous cars and have debt
Y'all have a
Impact on the globe
That may happen
Have I recently that the number of papers
Machine learning and AI has just be a lot higher in China than the US
Is a lot of more studies are being done where researchers working in the field
No absolutely that's actually in line with
Depart as well
So in the past I think it's not just papers as being redone or site
Ephesians
IP
Apologized
It's an interesting Trend at 10 for
15 years ago when we ask startup
Dalian China
Default IP
He was in
So expensive
It's not because they haven't
Diamond audit don't have IP
Is because a few that is just too expensive to fight on the international base
Autism awareness
That one day they will go International is pretty.
Today if you ask any AI startup
In China
They will show you a jealous about IP
So the weather
The wellness that they have to protect what they have only on
I meant that potentially Dave could go International as well
Becoming malber higher
Possibility
Just 10 years ago and so I think that that help
Bring up the weather
I think it's always been there
Is just at 10 15 years ago
You know that awareness wasn't that we entrepreneurs and they just don't follow
Lucky for us and China are mates
Italicize
Has China become number one marketing
A lot of things
People don't
Realize is that
Chinese speed
The delta.
Change
Scorpio time
Is also a month
You also have a
Large pool of talent
That's a
Barry
Tech-friendly
A lot of users
Willing to try new
New products
Services
Text Robin
So we have these three
Combined size
Speed
And 1
Peppermint
Start something
Being you
And try something new
It becomes very
Carrefour
Formula
To allow Chinese
Starbucks
Better
For the last part of the podcast will have a set of standard questions that we ask every guess the first one is
Who is Eric Bruner that you admire the most
And why I know you're saying a lot
But if there is one then
Impressed you though I think the one that impressed
Music
Amazon
You're not the only one who's said that on the show
Any reason why
Well I think he's an entrepreneur who has never
Stop tool
Is doing one thing
His ability to
To go from selling books online
To general e Commerce
Obviously that's one type of x
Extension on Dance
Take that
Endeavors that skill operations to deliver
Cloud computing
To go from
See
22 selling services for
This has to be
That's something that most
Please tell us a startup going to
Right on Dundee focus focus on your car focus on your DNA
And this is a spa
Different
Does anything you can
And then to have the guts
How to go offline
It'll do to be away from not just online but you say let's go by Whole Foods
I just got to think about offline
On top of that you know Amazon is
On top of the leadership in terms of innovation that was one of the earliest
Can we experiment with having drawings
To do deliveries
Right until we may not
Either drawings
On the everyday basis but I have to believe that
The R&D what is still going on
Quietly
And hopefully we'll see some
Soda level Innovation to level of God
That this us example
I think it's
That's that's why
China
Jeff bezo
Idea Monterrey
Yes but in the US increasingly is talk of
I trust baking soda Amazon
It's a powerful break up Amazon.
So is the same set of
Megan Fox
Giving temporary differently
What you do for fun
So I'm I love travel as I said before I believe the wall the Earth
What is been getting smaller as I grow older
What is a bunch of continents out there that I haven't been
So I do like to travel I do like to go away
Away from just what Humanity
I love to spend time with animals I love to separate spend time in nature
In Africa or two back door
That's right so I've been to Patagonia
Hiking Adventure Peru I've been to Russia Kamchatka spending time with the Bears
Literally definition
So it's a really it's thoughts been
Pretty good Nepal hiking
Generally I like to be out there not in luxury
Application but really rocking it out
Spending time
To understand
You know in different parts of the wall what
The different people dads
The different couches
And that I think that helps
To give me a very good and healthy apple
Speciation
Off my role model role in this world
Cuz I sent you know that it is still possible
All within my role to make changes
Two people around
So much
What is your system
What's inside your backpack
Yes oh I think that actually if you ask me what I have in my backpack on a daily basis
So I will the survival track even my work back I have I carry my passport
I always have my passport so I'm ready to fly
Anytime
I have different wallets for different currencies
Cuz you know credit card doesn't work
As I found out via Leone China it doesn't work in a lot of countries
And so making sure that you have ways to have cash that you have ways to survive
I think if you have cash and you have your passport
You can basically survive
Anywhere
So far rocking it out in the wall
Obviously your cash and a possible it doesn't really help and your phone doesn't really help either so I think he
Good shoes
You know nice warm jacket
Make sure you have your water bottle so you can always get water
I think with the tree you can always survive
Somewhere else to carry
County Bank, bank account do you have
I do have a few because I I woke in the USA in China
Mostly in China
You know I never grew up in Singapore
Reverse call number
The one of the guiding principle I have is always keep
My life
Simple
Cuz things. So Campo
Get it on the daily basis and can be bought
Why so many details that I think that
It helps not to add to those
Complication every
Still keep it simple
Amazingly the One credit card
Has helped me
To go global
In the last 20 years
That's why I said it's the first car
Still with me
Wear something you read recently that
Text you a lot or you recommend
Me a book or article or anything
I realized three or five books
Simultaneously and so
I think they'll most recent books and reading may not be good for recommendation
So recently I and has noses
Avenue area that exploring and I'm very interested in
And that's really is and in health
Nutritional supplements in genetic engineering
So I've been reading textbooks
I know it's really strange service reading textbook
How to get myself up in terms of the
The fundamental and
The basic areas that I've been reading books about diseases
Again.
The best way to recommend books
But a good way to appreciate
Where life
Can be training
The next ten
10 to 20
Thank you Jenny this was really fun
Thank you
Always a pleasure
Q79 89.5
I-96 by the weight we also produce a weekly email newsletter in English also called 9 + 6
Forget the Roundup of the week's most important happenings in Tech in China subscribers some photos for this
Informative and fun to read the news that also features original content
An analysis from Zora and me subscribe at nine 6. Ggvc
Ggv capital is a multi-stage venture capital firm based in Silicon Valley
Shanghai and Beijing with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past 18 years from seed
Capri IPO
We 3.8 billion dollars in capital under management real estate funds GTA V invest in globally-minded entrepreneur
Nearest in consumer internet
E-commerce Frontier tag in Enterprise
GTA V had invested over 280 companies with 29 IPOs in 22 unicorns
Orfila companies include Airbnb Alibaba
C trip
Didi chuxing Thermo hashicorp hollowbite cows keep Slack
Square Hotel wish soundtrue white white and others find out more at G G
Qvc.com us please email us
996 gbc.com is co-produced Battlefront
And this partner hydroco the host of the wonderful Seneca podcast it covered China's economic
Political and cultural issues