Hi there
Welcome to the night at six podcast
Brought to you by ggv capital
And co-produced
Pacifica podcast
On the show interview movers and shakers
China's tech industry
As well as Tech leaders
Weather us
China
Cross-border perspective
My name is Khan song
I'm a managing partner at ggv Capital
And I've been working at startup investing in them in both in US
A China
For the past 20 years
My name is Sarah Jeong
I meant investment analyst igb capital
Jennifer Moore journalist
Why is the show called 96
Texas to work schedule that many Chinese Founders have organically adopted
That is 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
To us
996 captures intensity
Drive
In speed
Of Chinese internet
Many of which
I'm moving faster
But even the American counterpart
On the show today we have Jerry and the co-founder and former CEO of Yahoo and the founding partner of America
Cloud Ventures
Which focuses on C2 later-stage companies booting infrastructure invalid chains around data
Jerry was a Pioneer in a consumer in an industry and icon of Silicon Valley
It has been an inspiration to both engineers and entrepreneurs worldwide
Jerry also orchestrated one of the most famous and lucrative deals in Tech History anywhere in the world
12 + 5
Earrings for Yahoo to invest
1 billion dollars in cash
Plus that sell Yahoo China
Exige for a 40% stake
A small but fast-growing Chinese company
By the name of Ali Baba
Which happened to be a GB profolio already backed
Post-money valuation of a deal
What's for 5 billion dollars
The deal was considered by many as being
Expensive
In Risky
It was awesome largest foreign investment ever made in China tech industry
Today 12 years later
What about this was close to 500 billion dollars or have a trillion
And for the return of 100x
In 10 years
For y'all
Jarrett remains active on the US China cross-border technology scene
He's on the board of Alibaba and Lenovo
Speaks frequently at various events
Advises US tech companies looking to go to China
As well as Chinese second base
Trying to expand into the US
Welcome to the show Jerry
Thanks thanks for having me so great way to
Kick-off 2018
During a first visit China in 1997
Let's go by I can chat about
Contact
He was a government official assigned
To you to be a translator in
How to get around on the Great Wall
And that time what was your impression of him
And back then did you have any inkling at all
He was going to do something big on the next
Do decades
Back then you were
The king of Internet
Yahoo whistle
Highest volume
In a company in tire world
What struck you about China
Well I know I was born and raised in Taiwan as you all know Hans and and it was since I came to the
U.s. I never went back to Asia very often and so being able to go back to China for the first time in 1990s
7 was a thrill
And you know meeting Jack then was very interesting because I was immediately
Struck by how inquisitive and how curious he was about the internet and internet was not very big and it in China
Jack spoke grade English you never spend time outside of China so he learned it in China which was also very unusual back then
But it was clear that he was an entrepreneur at heart even from 1997 now of course I had no idea what he
He would go on to do
He may not have had any idea what he was going to go on today and if so what
7 million that users. He was very very small and internet connections were terrible and
And so this was very much an early days kind of a
Time so I would say that overtime obviously
Country embraced internet but at that time
Is really
Kind of early days
Backwaters
Did you guys talk about the internet at all
He was very inquisitive he asked about the web he asked about
The internet and he asked about
All the
Information part of it I think he had some experience building
Directories are or things like that for telecommunication at Yellow Pages yasso
So he was very knowledgeable about a lot of aspects of a Yahoo was that sandwich was a large directory in a search engine
So we did talk a lot about that and he
Clearly was
Not your typical
Government person
Back then
Ultra Asian people were trying to figure out what internet is what in MN
And I think that I've got time
The market leaders in Taiwan
China
Or Hong Kong Japan
Or just starting
What was your impression of
Asus potential
Internet
Market
Well in 1997 when I visited China and it first met Jack this was on the heels of the previous year
Your 1996 started Yahoo Japan with
SoftBank in in La Sushi song so
Tommasi as he is now is very much a Visionary he pushes and must be 10 or 20 years ahead of
Where the trend is and he saw the opportunity he was one of our First Investors in Yahoo in the last day
Public but also his condition was to
Start Yahoo Japan and I think
We were in no position
Back then we were a young company I think we have less than 50 people and we were too busy in the US but
But he was so persistent and forceful as author is still today
That we agreed to launch Yahoo Japan and probably some sort of the record time he supplied
All the labor he put some of his best executive even put his younger brother ties already as one of our big Surfers
So we had launched Yahoo Japan the previous year and it was
Difficult to get it launched but then we saw the early successes of having been first-to-market there is so
To your question I think there is this very palpable energy around Asia not only in Japan
When did Korea exactly Korea was really just
It's beginning to take off and then obviously China wasn't far behind
Since Yahoo Japan work out so well over time
Will you think I would do something similar
Evener solely as then
For other parts of Asia
Yeah we try to do the same model elsewhere we try to do Yahoo Korea it did not work out as well and I see
I think there was some very strong incumbent competitors in Korea that has turned out to be
Huge Dom and neighbor in the windows guys
Any China we knew we had to plant a flag early and try to get some things going
But also ultimately
We need a partners
To survive in China given not only to Market which is usually the driving
Dr. Bhatt
China yells I have
Did the government
And the regulatory side of it that made it very unique
As you know it's not easy for US tech company to operate in China what do you think are some of
The most common challenges faced by us companies when they try to go to China
Well I think number one is really understanding
What is the goal and how do you fix it what do you define success
And
And part of
The early days of the internet in China in the late 90s and early 2000s
The challenge word
Really that the regulatory side was just also growing up
So they were trying to figure out how to
Regulate the internet industry at the same time all these companies were coming up some companies were
Less regulated and others and
And I think now there is more less
More clear roadmap for for companies that want to be in China
And I think
The last 20 years have shown the government also has been
They've been open on some ways and clothes and other ways about letting company is in and I think part of it is
Having
Partners or having investors
Maybe like
GDB yourselves
Who understands sort of the
The highs and lows of the rise and fall of different
Sensibilities within the Chinese culture in the Chinese government
On the topic of local partners
How do you pick
A local printer that fits your company culture and how do you make sure that they're actually empowered
Oh yeah that's a good question
We were very lucky in Japan to have
SoftBank is our local partner who
Put all their way behind us Japan is notoriously difficult as a market
And and for us
To have had mosses
Support and
I'm backing was really critical but but it was also one where we
You know he is he had
Majority of equity in yoga pants
Case where he had
More of the stake of the company for us to 2
That in order for us to be successful there
In other places I think it just depends it really if you can find a great local team
Command local manager
A lot of times
That's the key ingredient whether you find a partner or not
And it depends on what kind of company because if it's a large Fish Company and
And there isn't so much local Innovation or or or product
Localization is required
That's one formula in and you we seen a lot of us companies that basically used
The market as more of a sales and marketing Market
Where is
A lot of our companies today especially our Venture companies in portfolio companies
Do require not only product rollout but also
Some indigenous
Localization or innovation that needs to happen
And there you need more talented executive team
Stand just your standard sales and marketing section
So it really kind of depends on it but ultimately comes down to running the business you know people
It's stuck on running finding Equity partners of government Partners or
Capital you know but ultimately
It's who's running the business day today on the ground and
Goleta Marketplace and
Are successful examples tend to be people who
Are great getting the product out into the market that
Fits the Chinese market
And I think that's a that's a secret sauce that's hard to come by and and
It helps to have other backing and other Capital Partners but usually
It's much more about the people on the ground
Right you had a
If you attempt
Status in China yes
Obviously the most recent one the final one look extremely well yeah
Investing
My car to the Yahoo ever did
After the initial Inception
But
Before that. Boy you work with that don't we appreciate someone extremely controversial figure
How did you decide to pick him in the first place
Over someone like a robin lior
Or what anyone else in China
In and was insisting on having a hundred percent ownership
Reacquisition
Or
What you did the second time with Jack
A poncho
But material steak
I will not be a better strategy for our us company
Looking at
Funny vagina
Well we realized that in China that we needed a local operating person
As I said being in China
Running a product set
Without
Local
Exactly team was very very difficult
And this is still before the regulatory side was clear about what Yahoo is allowed to do what is not allowed to do so
We did a choir 371 and really used a position to buy the management team which is stronger
End
And his team only is as you know he's very Scrappy
He's bald he's got to complain about a Russian Roulette well he doesn't really believe he really just sees himself
Desert room ever again specialty Neil this is almost 20 years ago he was really a Maverick and so I would say that
Challenged from the standpoint of him being a subsidiary within a large US company at what time
But his approach to the Chinese market is sort of
Ability to kind of come up with
Things that really can disrupt the market to this day he has done that
I actually learned a lot from him
And you know our episode in China
The challenge was and is now kind of a
A seminal moment if you will was meeting with the government officials and
And them in
None
Not so uncertain term saying that you know Yahoo really you shouldn't shouldn't be operating in China and
Or even what was the way they said that you know we have this regulation that's coming up
Next year that will make
What you guys are doing the illegal in
Courses in regulation I think the never got past but you kind of get the idea that you down they really
Suggested that we don't operate in the media and
Information business in China so
That was when we got the hint and we said well you know if we're going to
Pull out of China we want to put our efforts with somebody that we think of you winner
3721 acquisition already yes this is supposed to be 71
Because we all did 100%
And
And the government
Was
Not really
Keen on having
A foreign-owned entity that has potential
Information to Media
Presents so
So we we knew we had to get out a coffee you would have
Part of the debate was you know if we're going to
Leave China we should parlay hour
Alcester
Into something else
And that's when we went down this investment path
And and I'll be asleep by that time we've reconnected with Jack but also more importantly the
That e-commerce
This was not an area that was subject to
Foreign investment
And so we thought that if we can
Translate hour
Holdings in China or operations in China into
Investment in a minority investment the government will be fine with that in and obviously too
Area B Commerce I was I was fine so
So that's how we ended up
At least
Sequentially get there
1 billion cash
Plus Yahoo
Will China yes for 40% stake in
It's so
They seem to bother you so model of a afterwards with a 5 billion side billing pus-y yeah
That was pretty
But I remember I mean
That what this was
Done in 2005
Summit
In Pebble Beach
And bananas nouns in June or July
Earth-shattering cuz he was on the kilobyte or going public
Bye Felicia
Quadruple post
Listing to about 5 billion
And you have to fight being dollar company what when Prophet pocket when private in China
Abraham said they had these coming had no business being out on my chin
The design of Justified
How did you how were you able to make that
Decision
To do this
And how are you without you as a CEO this deal will never have gotten I wasn't the CEO at Terry Semel was a CEO in
The Terry was
You're with me in China that moment when the government told us that we
Couldn't be in China anymore
Terry was
Extremely positive about China and quite frankly
Doesn't get enough credit for all the things
We
Yell in my mind and thinking back about it it was a very obvious
Things to do
Dylan and I think a lot of people
Say this about decisions that you feel good about right decisions that you don't really
Think of all the difficulties but I think in retrospect you're right it is
A huge
Investment
For a company
Like Yahoo to use how much of our cash to bet on that kind of valuation on that market
Improving Market obviously
Guidance guidepost one is you know we saw the success in Japan
Where we were in the auction business and commerce business so we saw you know betting on
The disorder of the
Betting on the on the leader
Even though there's not a lot of tech you know there is
A lot of marketplace Dynamics are already starting to take
And the second thing
Which I've talked about publicly is that
During the time we were running Yahoo China weather is
Sorority more with
Cojones
We try to establish our e-commerce business
Using the same Playbook
That we did in Japan and
We were just
Getting killed in completely annihilated by taobao
And
And we knew how Fierce and how
Smart & house for teacher
Yelp
Comic-Con the grand level but also on the Tactical level
Jack and his team was and I think that we threw that competition We Believe
I called his caterpillar
So so it was It was kind of in the
Humbling experience of having competed with Jack that we realized we'd rather partner with him then
The tide compete with them
And I think Jack
And then I'll probably benefited from that investment as well they really like you said you know
Put them on the map as a sort of the leading internet company in China
It's so it was the right time clearly we were
Besides a
Jack ma Ali Baba
Hopi language
Working with someone like a robin Li and Baidu or
Ponemah in pain sent to you by
Well I I think I your choice well I don't know if we had a choice
The clearly
There are great entrepreneurs and they they are
Proving you know if you look at Pony
You know I'm with you and me a WeChat you know that position WeChat
Turn out to be one of those
Salmon oil to we try to come on yeah it's unbelievable
And anyway we can talk about their history and how they made multiple transitions just in business models in India
But I always say that the simple answer is that while they're great entrepreneurs
For Yahoo to be involved
And
Search
Which is Baidu or in
QQ wechat Communications
The messaging would have been difficult
And I think
I think e-commerce was the
The obvious safe place for us to be
Government
So that was a factor
Famous earlier about
Getting very
Clear
Understanding from times government what you could do cannot do in China
Twice a day with clear but it was never clear that you could do something so
So
Sew-in in. Contacts
Do you think that switching to talk a little bit
Travis Uber decide to do a deal with Ed which was a
Did you prepare for Leo
Silver China
2dd in exchange for stake in DD and IBD have
Mistaken buber in the US
As well
Do you think that was
A similar context
10 years later
You know I'm an observer
On the board for DD and
But I don't really know the details of
That transaction might my guess is that there was some government
It certainly
Agreement for them to
There has to be some sort of government approval for DD and yd
Commercial previously
And then when Deedee and hoober resolved their competition in China
The government hats at least
Let it happen
Because they were sexually
The last two players left so whether there was
Significant
Issues
With Uber being a US company
In China
You certainly can speculate that you know it's you
Have
Massive amounts of data around transfer
Petition in routes
Some people's
Moving patterns that that could be construed as something that's sensitive and so
What the weather that really was a factor or not who knows
Looks at me I wasn't part of the
Let's discuss the truck driver has shared internal struggles that
His understanding
From Chinese government was
Subsidy
In this case
Cookie ends up being illegal soon
Uber and obviously they think twice about what
Yeah
It's um
Yahoo welcome to
Welcome to China
Not another thing happened here as well in the US
Where Alabama's most recent the interest inquiring a payment processor in the US
Whiskey night in this is even after
Jacket already famously met with President Trump
And had a great conversation
If a person from Praise Him
Afterwards
So seems like this is just a lot up
Politics
And
Polarization
Around us China business dealing
You know wait that's kind of
Not really a line with end-of-line business
Economics
Yeah I think it's one of our
Givenchy GV
Interested in a lot of our investment
Commonalities is
RBC cross-border in icing
The US China cross-border
Issues are getting more complex rather than lust
And as tech companies become bigger bigger
If you look
Ali Baba
Or Amazon or
You know obviously you're
You're faang stocks and companies
There are
Enormous complexities now
ATL
With regards to
Aldi's deals are evaluated or proposed deals in
It's not even just internet deals right I mean if you look at all the semiconductor deals in the last
Couple years
The regulatory body
The US which
Cepheus is
It is it
This is largely a political
Body so I think it becomes much more difficult
4/3 of these bigger companies to do deals
That may of touch on other people so you can imagine it's not maybe just a government that don't want certain deals
What happened like the one you're talking about
Maybe other companies I don't want that
And they were popular
Yeah so I think it's a politicized issue right now between the two countries we certainly hope that that environment atmosphere which
Change over time
As I think the best outcome is for
More free-flowing of products and ideas
And then capabilities markets
But for now it seems like we're entering more of a more
Cautious
Time between the two
I know that for example from the perspective of visa and master
They're extremely worried about ipe
Turn up volume of body paint
Together
Is becoming closer and closer to what
I'm beside myself
Also in China
So
It's like you said there's notches
Political issue but also for other place in the market
People just wary of
Deify suspension.
Chinese companies hire
In general
Retin-A with Chinese tourists being the
Fast-growing outbound
Traffic anywhere
Empowered that you put on top of that
Is it makes any
Existing playing any
Boston Market
Weary
What could happen
So it's almost as if
This may not be the perfect analogy
Nut
The Chinese company in the US company are going out to different parts of the world
We see that
You probably have seen as well
Us companies do better in Western Europe
Canada
Australia New Zealand
America
And
Executives with NFL
Indian descent
In emerging companies have
Show me I didn't do well in India as well
Where is a Chinese company to battery in Southeast Asia including onesia
The Muslim countries in the Middle East and
North Africa
Eastern Europe
Seems like the world is almost divided into half
A look at a Chinese Hall fees
1 Belair Road
Expanding into
Middle East
Give me different parts of Europe in North
And Africa in general
That the world is
Coming more more
Yeah and it's not clear how
The weather is really two camps or not it I think eyes to us
Current policy tends to be
Yeah retrenching from a lot of Art
Even being a longtime allies it's
It's unclear why leave in the US influence
Sinfar Marcus Wu
Will continue but I do think
And having us as most Dino
Inadvertently or IR or
I think he wrote it yesterday or today that
The US has helped make China great
Nnic part of it Florida go yeah I think I think part of it
It is as you said that that the government policy of 1,000 Road is
Taking a lot of
Government
Resources
To build infrastructure.
Ties development into Southeast Asia
Sir the Indochina independent in Indonesia
And then you know sort of
Westward it through the Stans in
And into Africa
It won't be surprising I think
To see Chinese companies also
The private sector being taken advantage of the sort of the
The Tailwind that the government is
So if you had the chance
To do it again would you have tried
Operator in China from day one or would you have picked a local
Or invest in a little coat
Company from day one
I am always those are hard questions because
I think I think
With
Our experience
It was a moment in time
You know
Today if you were to
Try to start
Yeah you wouldn't start what we started back has because the rules are more clear than more players than
Marcus Montebello
It is you know we would have to find another kind of a Greenfield early-stage
Endeavour. To have a question but
But I would say that
Having
Spent the time of China operate in China
Have you spent a time through Acquisitions and trying to acquire Chinese company
Having spent her Time competed
With Carbone Alibaba
You know he led us to this very
As I said, so natural
An obvious decision to invest in Alibaba
Which I don't think we would have done
Have we gone in there turning dust
Yo ass up here investors because we didn't have the skill set of being an investor
Or
Or trying to find a partner and believe me we try to find Partners but
The finding a JV partner something else would have been
I think also break
Palazzo
I'm so envious because you know it's it's almost
Like the old saying goes you know every every step we took was for a reason
And
Now we we never imagined I never imagined that fine dusting Alibaba 2005 we would end up having
Alibaba being nearly half a billion dollar company
But but certainly we felt like they were our best chance
Successful
In China
Through their hard work and their
What kind of advice
Do you give to us companies
For seek your advice as they try to go to China and what do you think that companies like
Facebook or Airbnb should do as they approached Chinese
Well I think
I told a lot of our companies to try to go early
Not necessarily to set up a very inflexible joint venture or anything like that but go early to explore more
How to get to know people build relationships
Understand the market and understand their product Market fit it really is two different worlds now
Lighting the Chinese market especially
Almost every Market B2B b2c
Is I think that's different
In China is in anywhere else from The Uso
So there is no sort of hey we can do what we did in the US and it working
China more the other way around these days
It will get to that song
So that's that's one thing is to just
Did understand China early a meet people early
And the same thing is if there really is an ambition to China there has to be a plan
But also you have to probably go in there before
Too big
And I think there is
Some weariness by
The multiple different factions within China weather is the government
Or the private sector or
Whoever to say Hey you know if your large large company like Airbnb or Facebook
Time in the China
There's more worried about them coming in and going against what a government
Policy is real government agenda is
I think Airbnb probably has had more success than safe Facebook
But over time I think all these
All these things will work
Play out in the way.
It really depends on I think with the market would accept in China and the government works
But I think by going somewhere early
Helps companies
Not have that big
Serta company syndrome
Can you put on them
It's much tougher on the company cuz they're not big
But I think it's a really do China as a core Market
They should do that
Soonerride
Has the lesson is that it's never too early to
Two-factor China into a girl's plan and hire people
It could be a
Yo I think if you run a company or used to run companies
You know you think about
Energy markets in
1224 maybe you know and I'll set 36 months and I think in China you just have to take much longer term
It may take you five years
To get anywhere
May take you 10 years and we know plenty of companies
I've been there for a long time and still have very little market share but there
Continue to work
And trying to cultivate a relationship
China I say this with a lot of Arkham
China
It's not a place for transaction
China's really play
Play relationships and if you viewed as a transaction to say Hill going to start as a vegan
Not this off of our checklist
I'm going to move on to the next country
It's not what chances are he's not going to go well and
Whereas I think it's those people who really
Sustained, Capital large wants to companies to go to there
Country and do something for them
You know their China now try try this is
20 years ago self
So the China status is also changed so I think it really
It really takes a different kind of attitude
And long-term View
It's not just
Another Market
It seems like
Any founding team in the US
I don't have someone
Who's from
China origin
I need to send
It makes a lot hotter
We're both in Welsh
In
Peterson pastor
And also having Denny was a co-founder
It was from China
Easier
I wish to figure out how to Leverage
Well yeah and then I think these are all generations right I think right now there are
Example you're exactly right having somebody that understood
China in Chinese
I can go back there and function there
Which is not all the Chinese kill can I I can't go back and function there but but Danny can and I think
That's critical but I think over time
As China becomes a market that
Everybody has to be able to
Expose himself to
Because it's probably
You know it right now is still the US and maybe Western Europe but pretty soon China
Is the top one or two Market that you have to
Be successful at if you're building a company so so that that that may or may not be
Exclusively.
Dimaio's people who are Chinese I mean
But so far it has been that you really takes a while to to really understand China and
And you being an expat there is not the easiest
Thing to do know in a very very Dynamic competitive and I mean your show is called
I-96 right I mean not to
A very shocking kind of thing for people who visit there
But I'm still down at 2 p.m.
United States in China
If you look at
Two set of data points
Looking about edition of Amazon worth
Probably somewhere
Arguably
Call China Inn
Parts of Southeast Asia
Amazon has
Walmart
China
I've got to get about Alicia
Is
Bakehouse
You look at DD
Versus
Uber do you start a 4 years after Uber
You're not an observer
They are
Primarily a Chinese company
Investments LLC
Uber has been all around the world with minority stake in China
Yet
Bobby some to company
Arabic symbols wechat
So
The Chinese market has just been
For the right
Mobile internet company who has the right product Market fit
Who do walk 9
Computer company install a much faster
That anybody else
Has never happened
What does that mean and how is going to impact silicone body
I noticed some of the smartest
Product people
Instagram Maui
Are increasingly paying attention to what's happening China Buffet
WeChat
With alipay
And so forth
And I change the way they see my building products
Neu us
Infor
Other markets
Is that a growing trend
Okay or is it just more of anomaly
Still
Prediction 5
Special 10 years old
How would the teacher
Nissan
GOI it's a really good question and I think
Part of the reality is that
The volume
That you know the companies that you talked about whether it's
You know Alibaba tencent or
DD
The volume they do everyday
Astound
Real people who don't spend time there
You know so
It's it's adding another zero sometimes to zero the one you talk about
Scully China whether its mate while I'm doing deliveries or either doing
The number transactions in
Denali pay in tencent Tempe
Or the number is a TD kids
Get some
It is so there is a
Scale factor that is
Extremely important
I think in
When people develop new products
In China is set
Necessarily need the fanciest
Technologist
Bodega
Handle the kind of scale that's much much much higher
Right and be stable
There's a
So there's an element of
And as those companies growing as those companies scale
Hey you think they can they can take that advantage of stability and scale
Elsewhere that us companies we have to read
Do to get the kind of scale elsewhere
Especially
So that's one one element the other element I think is that
There is still a
A lot of more fundamental Innovation here in Silicon Valley it is still the Melting Pot of
The world
Dustin
Apparently all we have on froze you and I both by have on Forest Home every
Country has a very diverse
Set of entrepreneurs and I think in China is still relatively mono in a monolithic in terms of their most
Chinese butt
But you're starting to see Innovation that is
Really for China Market sick
It really indigenous and really local
And using business models developed
You're saying because of the scale and
Can you sing
The density of the population
Allow certain things to happen in China that won't happen in Uso
We're saying business model differences right not just technology a product
Differences but really starting to
Whiskey Business
And I think that's what's going to happen in 5 to 10 years where you going to have business models that really hard Innovative and different in China then
Then the US
A little closer to Ali Baba but you know the new retail that the Ali Baba is
Is advancing
Yo yeah it's really hard to do here in the US but he really works in the in China
So did that I think you're just beginning to see
China going from the early days of the internet being sort of a copycat culture
Two more indigenous development
For local market products
Which is now graduated to eat more indigenous business models innovation
And we have all those things really working it's kind of like a flywheel right
Sing
Not only
Alibaba tencent Baidu being
Large players in oral mucosa
Systems in terms of Hindustan
An m&a
You're saying there next Generation in ddn
Mate1
And those people are now very aggressive
Faster than Eminem
As well so
Did the relay
Creating their own sort of ecosystem there
I think part of the reason sings scale so fast in China is due to the leapfrogging effect
So sure how to skip credit cards into mobile
Cement skipped on-premise software
Get landline to mobile
How much do you think
The growth can be attributed to the Sea facts and
How can companies continue to
Scale once this low-hanging fruits are already paid
It's a great coach I do think the Frost has been a great benefit to China but
You also have to remember
India could have done the same LeapFrog
And
By most measures there
Most developed countries could all have the power
Rhysand and so so I think there is
Far behind in China when they
Could have arguably been about the same starting point
The mid-90s
He's right so
So I do think that the LeapFrog is something that China as a country
We're very conscious
Trying to take advantage of and this probably lot of it is
The government leadership and put the put a lot of it is I think the entrepreneurial spirit
To say hey
You know we're going to solve a problem
And we're going to solve a problem with
No existing
Yes it and whether it's Logistics which they didn't have vassalage
Network like
FedEx
Whatever
Or
Like you said landline
Mobile phones or
A number of other ways in which China develop faster than
I think e-commerce is one of them
Right I mean
For awhile retail e-commerce coexisted but but it's
Clear that you Commerce
Has more benefit without having to go build
Stores
So I think I think there is a conscious effort
For China to do these leapfrogging move
Looks now but I think
Overtime
Yo
Sting scale
It's harder and harder to leave froggy can't really leave frog
Existing
Scaled infrastructure so
That may slow down
Growth at some point which
It has to slow down
But that the question really is is
Is there new areas
Pecan Grove
Just as fast
From LeapFrog
Is and that's
You mentioned
Cloud and SAS I think
I think there's actually
An argument to be made that
Assassin China is still very
Must do everyday
There's not a very
Yes all the cloud is Big player AWS
Just getting started their butt
But it's not like here where
You know major major major business
There are still a lot of room to grow I think in digital
Media in China
And I think that's an area where
There's still a lot of opportunity so so
My guess is that
Azaria mature they need to keep
Can you define leapfrogging out
Unity Sand
And it's not surprising that a lot of these
Large
Internet companies in China are starting to look outside of China
You know Indonesia being a
Key Battleground for a lot of companies
But it's going to happen elsewhere
It seems like
And look up question.
Supposed
A lot of smart
Journalist in The Wire
Your times were
Masonry caulk
A similar question
Thinking that
Chana benefit
Behind in
LeapFrog dog
It's easier somehow
Implies easy
Weebly you look at the
Florist
Portal days
Gaming dice to the
Search messaging e-commerce days
Now to the mobile internet days
The quality of Engineers continue to go up
And for one reason or the other
A lot of be smart people
May have been educated
Or working us
Weather stupid glass ceiling or other factors
It was
He kind of made it easier for them to
Not easier but can of pumpkin to
Try to go back to town and we can walk there and be here to do it
And not something like that this into a China India comparison
But
A lot of Indian
Executives who may have been interrupted in India
Interrupting beanbags successful in the valley
And in in Boston in Seattle and so forth
The town that would have to compare what time they may have been able to prevail
India to the next level
Ends up staying here any us
Where is the same level
Quality of talent and took going back to China
Installed a whole new internet suck
It obviously government played a part in
Allowing that to happen and not try to Uber regulator too much
And so
One thing I also notice is on
For the Chinese
Intrapreneurs nobody's for Generations
In some sense
We are there and we are lucky
Was the time
That this week and a half
In the spirit of any number two possible
If you come up with new ways to increase efficiency
Intuit ecosystem
Which
I mean who would have thought.
10 years ago
What are the most valuable companies in China will be none government-owned
Ram 2500
He was China petrochemical mobile it was ICBC Bank
These days
That that that you had number one number two most powerful company in China being completely Private Eyes
And run by Angela Norris
Induction cook celery
Open next
10 years
Ben that's something that no one with all possible
10 years ago
So something about internet something that fit
Chinese Innovation and Entrepreneurship
That kind of Defense each other to
Make the screen
Change
In China
The question is
Could that be exported
Indonesia Middle East
Do other countries wear
One belt One roemmich play a factor
And somehow
This model can be a interesting
Develop
Teen model
For other emerging market
That didn't have
May not be able to do that on their own
But now could be affecting my check
It's a great question Hans in the end I think
Yo just to go back on something you said I I think there's a little bit of
There's not another perspective with regards to
Chinese entrepreneurs
I think that
As the China Market has
Taking off and then started Rising quite frankly they were probably more opportunities for
Them to go back
I'ma career in
And contribution stamp points and staying here in the USA I don't know if there's really a glass ceiling
Get into that
Privacy glass going for
Indian tech executives
And a number of other ethnicities
So it may just be that opportunity China is much bigger and you can party argue that
You know for Indian
Global Executive to go back to India
What are they going to do there
Alright so
So it really does speak to the the rise of China's
Economy in the rise
Anna's development
To attract
The make that
Makemake coming back
Fort Lauderdale
Oversea-chinese to be attractive
If not all of them have been successful but I think that there continues to be a massive
Tallinn China
And so there is no question that has you think about
Yeah we highlighted you highlighted a number of great entrepreneurs and show
But you don't
You need hundreds of thousands of
Skilled
Techworkers
Programmers and coders and developers and now you know Big Data
Today I capable
Engineer
These are
Extreme shortage
Did China even know they're trying to crank
Come outside
To me it's more the opportunity back
In the market that they
That they have the Heritage from rather than
Danny Nelson
To that point the question is can Chinese companies
Stand outside
China or help countries markets that have not been developed outside China
I think that's the next
Big question in the mixpix phase for China's
Gross
Everybody's trying to do a little differently I think governments are getting smarter post Uber and post
Aldi's
Companies come in and in so
It's going to be less straightforward I think then
The past 20 years regulations
Going to deal with local
People
Probably they won
Especially if your large company and Sully's become sort of
Upfront
Negotiated
Political government deals
Many instances
And
And end and so I think it takes a different skill-set to do Maneuvers in
All these different countries
Who all have Tiffany's
Being able to contact create not only a
Sustainable Market but also develop Talent locally
Because it's hard to export bunch
Chinese managers into
Country for very very long time
Hussein kind of Japan try to do that
Didn't work in the eighties and nineties
So it's got to be a different way we nobody knows what it is yet but I think it's going to it's going to be the next big challenge for lotto
Rebecca Webb Alabama
Export in Chinese
Manager
We also have seen
Up companies
Building up sizable press
In Middle East
Is also a
Area B Commerce
Curated
Morning
T-Mobile
Markets
The Muslim country
And they're growing extremely fast
You can tell that then the consumers in Muslim country
Did I used to getting diskin flux up Goods at
Such cheap
Affordable prices
In Soca quality at great prices
Rate formula flea market
And so
It is seems like
The Chinese companies even with
Too much government
Overtly supporting them
Are fighting weight expending
So
And the old man have sex
If not talk till 7
So
It seems like
One could also guess that the
Local executives
India Muslim countries
The work any Chinese companies
Eventually maybe their own
Yeah Jerry Yang and Jack Ma
In those countries
So
Guess my question is that
Us by not letting Chinese in
Missing out getting these
Cedar Point
Know what's going on around the world
Ensure for short-term
You prevented a Chinese company from coming into the US
Footlocker.com
You're missing all what's potentially
Possible
Not making that
Nestor changes hit you need
Global basis
Earlier
Yeah well I think any barrier
You know I'm a globalist so I think any barrier is generally negative
You could argue that
The us being more
Protectionist now than before
Yes
Missing out on some
Trends that could be happening elsewhere in the world in
And I think
China has been criticized
Last 20 years were not
Open brightness setting from the great things I may become
Companies like Google and
Facebook are doing so
So you know I think it's easy to point out that these barriers tend to have a negative effect but also
Overtime I think
Yelp
It remains to be seen how how these different
Marcus would develop because if
Markets that China now Dustin
And I'm more like China there is
And it's not just the market dynamics but it
The way to a government-to-government think about it and in the trade and everything else so
I think the stakes are much higher
And I'll come back to that same a couple times but I think the stakes are much higher in
And whoever wants to
To win in these markets now how to
Go in with much more at
I wonder out of the Chinese Tech Giants
Which one do you think is best equipped
To go Global in this is a question for both hands and Jerry
Wow
Face on Face Off
You know it
I I think
My
Original business was it was an internet
Portal or search
Reformation business and so I think
I think of information businesses as a little bit easier to move around and I would say you know
Tencent is probably in that
Camp
They have
Unbelievable acid in WeChat and
And if the capabilities on WeChat is offered
You know in other markets
In its full capacity
I think it'd be very very difficult for others
Some people compete
And
Yesterday
There is what happened
Lions line in
I think I have them all but you know but but I do think that the power of the network and
Power software is very easy to go out now
Alibaba
Clearly is the other one that
House payment
Special way of entering markets and their e commerce is
Is once they establish it is very very very powerful as well soap in terms of being a the mood quickly I would imagine
Moving a messaging app around is probably
Liberty zrn
Does a soap or hasn't demonstrated
Sea level commitment
Dot Alabama
Yeah
That's a great question I don't know I don't know
I think they're happy to let the Chinese diaspora
Spread that WeChat for now
Got it
What are you what do you think
I noticed that the Alibaba tencent Generation Y
Chorus pedal be over 45
I'm over 50
And that's a generation
Uncle Rob still treating the West
As you know where a lot of innovation happening
It's a very healthy dose
The Interpreter was seeing
Not our
Chainsaw race
30 and 40 Grand Pointe Chinese internet Market
Start to grow fast
They do respect the us but there's a lot more ambition in their part
Show. They're always better why
That look at the camera
DD or timing at that hotel
Or at the one singing at the
Which one all of them
Show more question
Globalization
And even the younger into
Penora's
In Hangzhou
Not alright
Used to things David cross border
Are building companies are in suits
Focusing on China album
In there
A question is even stronger than detention or Audi
To do that
So I think you would be extremely interested in the next 10 years
I do like you think that everything's become a lot more politicized
So
A Chinese company I'm more likely to do well in
Countries. Org
Politically friendly
And hence
The Muslim countries
So you'll be injured
C2C
What happened
I like your answer you're basically saying I'm old and you're young
That's why we're all doing this
Picture of young people I think
Your story of meeting Jack
Confirmed she says that and I've always felt this way that we should judge people not just by who they are today about
Also by
Who did Kobe coming
10-20 years
Now you're an investor how much of investing do you think is
Judging people and like their future trajectory
And how much of it is
Your business
Well I ate it's really good question I think
If you are investing at the stage
That we are at AMA
It really is early-stage sometimes
Two Founders in a garage in
Just with an idea and so
How's it anyting pre-series younossi door or late seed even some series a companies
You're really
80% investing on the team
I think where they want to go to the market it matters I think this sort of
The product idea matter is obviously
But it's very different than later stage investing you if you look at a series Bo gross then it doesn't matter where you're spending
Capitals go to market but it before you go to market really is about
The ideas behind the entrepreneur and
Johanns knows this but the sum of our
Some of my most
2 + 1
Public companies
Have started the company under one premise
And now they're doing something
I almost a hundred eighty degrees
And
And I think you can only explain that by
Having busted in people who are you know doggedly persistent in
In solving problems in Falling weather
Gut instinct
What advice do you have for people who are trying to develop this good judgment
Other people
Honestly The more I've done this and you know what coming up on six years here as an investor
Demarcus hackett's luck you know it it really is I mean obviously
I said I jokingly but I do think that
If you look at our successful entrepreneurs
There are people who are very experienced their people who are first time
You look at
Some of entrepreneurs who failed multiple times
You know someone very experienced in somewhere are
And and we all know
I believe that's the case for me personally that
Building Company starting companies
You got to work really hard to have
Prepare all your life to do it you have to really
Do it will help all all commitment at full passion
But
Luck has a huge part to do with
And for me to have started Yahoo when we did
It was really
I think the good timing more than anything else
Put me to meet you back as somebody that you know what does mon my first DUI made in China is it
Is blind Luxo
I think you you have to work hard and you have to prepare yourself but I think luck is a huge part of
Making success and I think
In our now if I had an algorithm to pick
That would be worth selling but I think
You look at cryptocurrency right I mean four years ago
Yeah it would have bet on it right so
So I think you really and then remains to be seen so I think it really it really comes down to at least in my mind
Understanding the rationale
How they are different things how they
The water they motivations are
How they plan to deal with adversity
How they tell their stories sometimes just listen to Somebody's pitch
Changes your
Opinion about
Sometimes you eat look like
Slide inside my goddess
Granny hearing aid
Andy in the office
Be true to self car
So to me it's it's really a seal game and it's not about numbers
I don't know what I would say is hardest for investing because you just
You just never know
You really you're really rolling the dice
Another person you met really all his muscle
Amazon Yoshi sign of self
South Bank
What do you think of
Vision Spa
And how that's changing
Well you know
I think Massa
Yo from the first day I met him
What's the different than what I was going to say he know he is the most persistent
Tireless
You know he keeps
Pushing himself and pushing people around him
You know he has and he's
Emacs
He makes big butts
And people remember a lot of his
Successes Yahoo fortunately was one of his early
Successes but he's also have plenty of failures
But you never less the failures.
Guitar hymn
He just goes back in
And fight harder and I think
What the vision fund has done is allow him
Achieve something that I think he's always wanted to do which is
Brothers being an investor that has some influence but not passive income
Like most investors are quite frankly even odds for the all week
You can pound the table and a note sound spinner doesn't want to listen
But in his case because of the checkbook and because
Of the platform he has a very clear platform that he wants to build around
Ai and around iot and around
The emergence of cloud that he feels like he can use that power of the capitol
To create a next-generation platform
Perform a car at 2
Modernized
The correct notion but I think any of you sing the the beginnings of that with Didi and Uber in
Transportation
Betting big on on a Ahi
Is big believer in Singularity
I think he's very purpose
And I think she wants to do more than just being a passive investor in the ready
Couple of companies grow up in
Sell it
God wants to influence them you want to drive a certain direction
And it's a big bold that and that's
Best Masa
Just take a look at it the ride sharing Market
Amuse investor in Cloudy the sense of being
Mercy into DD
So nevermind China already his master in grab nanachi
Profolio
Number one in Southeast Asia
Is investor in Orlando in India
And by investing all these Uber competitors
In the biggest markets
Outside of us
Eaton sub
Indirectly or directly car you
2 tribella virus remover
Now he can you message Uber much more sacrifices
In
He may be easier to replicate at the Uber China DDO in Southeast Asia and India
To have the local number one player buyout
Uber prices locally
Little Burgundy Baltimore that resource pack home driving for example
Uber Eats you out of my shirt on the other business more profitable in more interesting and more
Disruptive in
So in some sense he trying to
Using the resources you have
To rationalize their the the market
Deformed baby carrots
As you said you know that to the extent that
People compete and
And cooperate
In different regions on the Rideshare as a market for example
You know it's a it's a win-win-win right I mean nobody's subsidizing and losing money in burning car
And then for him
That
Drives up his investment Bassett Valley
So he's he's got a very clear view of how
These things could be made to be
Be successful
But he still got
You still got a lot to prove
In terms of being able to really realize some of these things over
But I think he sees
That's a mistake
Are we what are like Yahoo like Alibaba is going to make
Baltimore
That's that's that's a plan
Yahoo's investment in Alibaba has been called
The best invest
An American company has ever made in a Chinese
Which investment do you think has been a second
Look I I think it's an American company but
Open asper yunnan
And we went in at what beat
2039 Dolley Madison it's incredible
And they almost 35% 34
Whatever it is
So there is there the stories that
That I think seem incredible now but
But I think
It's what makes
This whole Venture business so interesting is that
Joey doesn't
Brian to start WhatsApp
And
Have 50 people on Cell to Facebook
But for $19
Is is those kinds of Silicon Valley stories or Beijing
Stories you know that that makes every entrepreneur want to
To do this but
But I also think
You know we may be coming into the area where we might see more of those kinds of invest
Commence by the Lots.
The skills a lot bigger than the scales a lot
And
Now there's disproportionate
Kind of
Dynamics in the marketplace for
Winners
And so I think that's the that's the
That's going to be the big thing is who's the next winter in a very big space and
Argue
That died today sign ups
Cons of big players
Time in the US
18 China
Well I think
He's always you look at investors right
And you guys are one of them
And in most investors
Invest
Thinking that
You know on the upside
They will be the next B8
Whatever but on the downside they can sell it to one of these guys
Smite right and you've had plenty companies we have plenty of companies that always come to this Crossroad where
I can go raise
Alamo money
Or I can sell a company
Yeah
A lot of companies
Even if not for those may or may not want to sell it
Company lot of investors will take
They take the opposition
So I think
I don't think it's so much that startups are pawns I think the investment community
And by the way I think the large companies are much
Wasabi now
And the
Capital is coming not just from the traditional
Venture capital
Farmstead also
A lot of corporate money and a lot of other money that's in the in the in the mix
So, Sovereign wealth
Cansado wealth funds really starting to play a role
Because you know they have to get the return somewhere
So I think it's more complex than just saying companies are ponds
Did I think Realty investors
Stop pushing for certain outcomes
In most cases
Delta rational and sell
Sweetheart by companies on wannabe
Completely irrational for very very very long time and maybe some things like magic leap
Or something
Could do that but
But is very very difficult for I think for a large number of
Small startups to
Be able to maintain than race cars
With their investors
If there's a
Alternative to sell at ocado try to actually argue that
In the older days
If you're at you remember in 10 years ago
Most most of the Chinese Zodiac
Run the risk of being clone by the big boy
Voice record
Petite these days
Does the competition among themselves are so fierce
You almost have the issue of balance of power that
Baby brother by volume
To save them self time to compete against each other
Shut that she argues that
Better.
Than ever before
Yeah and I think we all were saying a little bit of that in the US where
You know I would say
5 years ago
The big internet companies in the US work what much more quizzes
And recently I would say that you know
They're they're much less so they're still Acquisitions here and there but they're more discipline their their lot less alcohol
There is a lot less of the unit billion-dollar outcomes
Fuel injector
So
And I suspect that China will go through that same phase at some point
You been done to me these are just cyclist things right and so
Startups
In some ways I think it's a much more rational world
Here in Silicon Valley now you have to you can't count on getting a choir 2 years from now
Yo you you have to come up with something that
Stainable and cause you said to become
Companies here are building everything, Google
You know is
Is
Is building
Everything from
YOLO autonomous driving to
Solving aging
Activities are typically maybe Resort may be reserved for the startups
Can years ago now the big companies are doing it
Periodically so is your startup and you getting venture capital
You have to come up with something that a big companies aren't going to do and I think that's also its shift
11 yo you have to solve problems at the big guys
Either don't want to solve or we don't have time
Before I left that
If they won't get to
And oh. That's a totally different challenge
So looking forward do you think the US
And trying to take ecosys
Systems will become more
Integrado or more separate and ink
Cuz I feel like for every app in the US or is that equivalent in China
And both ecosystems are just very surprised
People are at the people are separated in
Countries
I know I think I think today if you
Can I can't even name one
Really that
App that you would use in the US
You know to high-frequency that you would go to China and use
Maybe you can come up to 1 but
But I do think that's been
You know two to ecosystem in that and then we talked about this I think
The evolution of lost 15-20 years from copycat to indigenous product Innovation to know indigenous
Innovation in China
That is really playing out
But they're alright I think they are
Ways in which
Companies with attack ecosystems
Can be more integrated
Eventually things that run on the cloud here should run on the cloud there and vice versa or whether it's
You know sort of the B2B world or enterprise software world
Logic that you don't really need
2 salesforce's
Dot-com
Torrentday.com
There's no real you're managing
Yeah your Enterprise probably is the same
From a product
Respect cross-border
Producing from a consumer standpoint
Did the consumer behaviors in the language and cultures are different enough that
You probably will see
A separate ecosystem
And some of the basics like mail messaging and maps
Search they're already fully developed in
So I think
It's hard to say those things will revert back to them
The two countries so
And to me it is no longer just about politics and saying the
Companies the country somewhere work with
If that's not the case
Marcus already developed
Nicole Troy NY
The only ones I can think of them more
Airbnb URL
You can see
It's not as big in China
Tiara baidu
That's why you pay Ali Baba's partner
Yeah
And also
It seems like
Json
Pointy made
The earlier about
This is probably Innovations in
In China
It just seems that e-commerce
Virtual item sale
Anything less than advertised
How are you said you was are paid up his model
Becoming such a
Speaker in phone
Which is not a case here
And.
Companies that know how to do that well scan user
I want to pay for things
Are better at emerging-market
Cats in general
Amazing General get ice developed
You're absolutely right I
You know advertising is
Has you know really boost a Google and Facebook here
In the US
And probably you know obviously Western Europe
But
Advertising as a business model
This is very small purse
Countries including China
Enchiladas
So
People pay for poor performance
And also
User pay for
Sam's auction
Yan
It's hard to imagine 10 years ago.
Chinese music
The growth of body intensity
It's incredible
Last question I wanted to ask his own
Super apps
So actually just last week
WeChat launch their mini games and also made their many programs
More powerful and
I feel like we tried it's just becoming closer and closer to an operating so
So far Chinese people it doesn't really matter if you have
IPhone or Android
Silver time that
And with Yahoo as well that vertically integrated
Large platforms tend to get a
Attacked by more
Category Focus
Players
Do you think
Super apps like Facebook and we each had our
Sustainable
It's it it's a great question I think
It is
The case that
If you are
Smart
You can
Continue to Leverage
Traffic in the eyeballs you have
In two more more particle appliques
And so it's
Not surprising
I think you forgot my face book has always
Worried that if
They weren't
They have their own
Phone or that if and only wants to
Cut them out because they're not an operating system
But I think if you developed enough
Critical application
Within
The same umbrella and it's interesting to see them
Embed some functionality of impella Facebooking on Facebook
Pap and then they they split off messenger and
If kept on Instagram
WhatsApp separate so
It's a multi-app strategy
Brighten Facebook's case
In WeChat I am not seeing them go
Multi bird house all one they really going to really put it in one
And wishing dangers that I best in the company where try to do all things to all people
You run out of
You are so how
How companies can navigate that kind of
Growth is really tricky from a product design standpoint from user perspective
Yeah I cook the Calera gelato machine learning and AI to do that but
Ultimately I think
You know it it depends on whether
They are
Getting more back from creating these particles rather than
Sprite if you hear
Creating a vertical and then you
Getting less traffic back then
Something's wrong so
I I know the WeChat team little bit I think they're really really really smart but but I things are your gift
Well taken in that that could be one of their challenges is
They have to continue to
Messaging while the continuum
Be able to do a lot of these
Poli payments well but
Do they get into every little thing there is
And and that means there's going to be room for others to
Either partner will come up with their own
Hotel East
Very interesting.
Case study right I mean
There should be no reason Telltale beer if you have to have been existed at all and then for them
Is really an opportunity that
That that Esau
When we were coming over question
Interview
Did you swipe question was something that fascinated us
Guess I you uke argue that Yahoo is for some reason
What did everything
You did more work than
Google ever did in the
Early days the internet that was so needed
And then that you have a Facebook and and WeChat
Dot.
Doesn't need to do everything themselves anymore
APA format other app
Plugged into it
Is there any enough other ass around
1020 years later
And so if you look at the model and you look at
What someone total has done
Is take
An app that
News aggregation.
Reporter has something like that
As somehow
Madoff popular enough and
Frequently using
Power another assortment of
Michonne from video app
So
It is going to be interesting
How hot are you
What are the other ways to spell something.
Somehow deep voice not going to notice in front of them
Is something there
Kind of familiar with
But
If you don't know how to do that
Then you could be argument be a part of the big company but if you can get that right
Yeah you can always win
Pick your battles but also I think there is an underlying user need or demand that they
Fulfilled
And I think that's
Cuz you know you're absolutely right hands in describing what
Somebody needs to create but this sounds like
I'm missing parts on Haystack in Mission Impossible but
But for those people who end up doing it they listen to the customer
And they
Learn from their customers
And it still happens every day and that's why it's so fun to do what we're doing
But we might last question is around Apple
In in China
When Apple first went to China
Whistle
IPhone
That the government doesn't know what it is
Interesting
Got another phone
Thumbs up
All Commodities no problem
After 10 plus years
It is no longer just a phone is a computer it has a
Lotto since the beta
That any government would
What I want to know more about
What what
If you have to make a prediction
What does Apple need to do over next 10 years
Continue to do what they do
Wow is almost an anomaly
Compared to Yahoo
Compared to Facebook
Apus always been cited as the most successful American company in China
Today and that nobody talks about it and
I think part of it is
That they have
I understand
Don't know them very well but I understand
Tim Cook personally
Before UCLA
NetSpend
It goes back to sort of what we talked about building a relationship understanding the culture
Really finding the value add for
The country of China and make that value proposition
Unique enough that
But it's not I don't think it's a one way street I think there is some checking balances in China wear
You can't just
Arbitrarily decide Apple goes out
Can you imagine the Uproar so
So there is there is a process and an apple has spent a lot time investing
Not just money but also
Lot of relationships in the lotto
Valleyride bus manufacturing and otherwise
Look at me
I think the next 10 years
Is
It's going to be very different
Especially given
Given that that
Now this is like you said it's not just a handset is
It's more of a software company
How do you spell retainer companies in
Never before
And as China
Works through their own thinking about cloud and
How
Cloudworks
In China
And I would argue that's an area where they're still fairly early and thinking through hell
Data regulations regimes
Yes I would Apple I would
Spend the time to think through how they can be added to that process like they've done and so
So is there smart and do the right thing say they will
Continue to be viewed as a valued
Player in China
And if they
Arbutus Athen they will have problems just like everybody else
Heading
Their role in the whole world
Did the Uber thing
Is not as publicized
Dakota messenger Uber in devising DD
And I made a huge difference in outcome
And also
UC temp spend a lot of time
Visiting Chinese startup
I've started develop locally in China
And doing well on Apple a store in the US and in China
But many of them have ambition to grow Beyond Time
And to extend the Apple
What could be a facilitator
Of attendance
What system
Exporting the outside of China
It kind of fits what the oppressor
She is trying to do
Extending China soft power beyond China
And it so
You can talk to him
Working very hard
Mice out of your house many others but it certainly looks
Like they
They
They have a plan that is executed you know for well over decade
Right so far last part of the
Podcast we have a
Quick fire questions
Okay
Who is an entrepreneur that you admire the most
And why
Besides
Yuan besides Jack who else
Well I think we talked about I mean the ones that I'm really impressed by in China is Chun-Li
Engine jingle accommodation is a DD is really unreliable and
In some way to me is
One of the most
Yessir TJ but
A bike rounded entrepreneurs
I've met and so
It's not it's not a
Surprised that he's
Where he's at today
And by the way I think he is
12 by 12 by
7 is never a time that he's not working and
It's incredible
I might sure of
Fortunate working with
I think somebody is probably the
Fastest
Growing
Executive order Last 5 Years
From where you was before you where is now
Is the biggest lie by
I've ever seen
I just absolutely is.
End
A lot of people say that he doesn't speak English but I think he is
I he must understand at all because you show intuitively strategic it's incredible so
Yeah
What's the best and worst
Decision you've ever
Resizing
OC keep saying that
Obviously investing Alibaba was turned out to be the best decision but you know
Probably times he will say that was the worst
Decision
But I will say that it's always
Your toughest decisions are the ones that people will say it's your pastor worse than
Only time will tell
Which one is which
What motivates you to wake up
Each one of these days
What's tell keep you up at night
NYSEG
Doing a podcast with Hans
What you look like I feel like
Is that the energy that I see from a lot of entrepreneurs
Where a lot of them are moonshot ideas
You know it that's the business I'm into turn invested in things I might change the world
Maybe it's one-in-a-billion chance but
And and that kiss me up in the
Turn O2 to know who I'm going to see you and hear their ideas
A lot of it is also getting helping them navigate through building the company but I think
There
Passion and energy is
This is
He's really inspiring and kind of feets
So we said earlier it keeps us Young
And keeps us
Xiamen for friend of
What's possible that I think as human beings that's really
That's really your very life yeah
End and yes I think
Making returns is is part of the score carding
But in my case I feel like
Benefiting from
Tomorrow and forever
It's been a real toy
Now when they run into trouble that's what that's that's what keeps me up at night so
That comes with the territory
Thank you so much for joining us Jerry it was great to have you
But several years now and has been
Very interesting ride together
So look forward to have more or thanks for having me
Thank you for coming
Good afternoon
Thanks for listening
Who does episode of 996
By the way
We also use a weekly email newsletter in English
Also called 96
Who does a Roundup of the week's most important happenings
Inside in China
Subscribers some photos for this
Formative
And you said also features original content
An analysis
From Sarah MI
Stripe at 96
Ggbc
Ggv capital is a multi-stage venture capital firm based in Silicon Valley Shanghai and Beijing
We have been partnering with leading technology entrepreneurs for the last 17 years
From seed to pre IPO
With 3.8 billion dollars in capital under management across 8 months
GTA V invest in globally-minded entrepreneurs in consumer internet e-commerce
Frontier Tech in Enterprise
GTA V has invested in over 200 companies including Airbnb
Alibaba
Z-Trip DD
Hello bike
House
Keep
Slack
Square
Toutiao
Wish
Soho social
Why white and others with 29 IPOs and 17 unicorns to date
Find out more at gbc.com
If you have any feedback on the
Does podcast or would like to recommend a gas
Bisimoto
I-96
IGG bc.com
This podcast is co-produced
Bow friend and business partner
Kaiser kuo
The host of the wonderful sinica podcast
It cover China's economic
Political
A cultural issue