Hi everyone we're excited to announce a new program
Ggv fellows
Designed to help sea turtles or a highway
Chinese students studying overseas
You got to know the Chinese entrepreneurial landscape better
As a sea turtle myself I know that many of those worried that were not CDT enough
Go back to China
Like a local network
We're worried whether we can survive in a fiercely competitive market
Where most people work 9 9 6 7 8 0 0 7
This program is designed to address those concerns
If you were Chinese student or professional who is studying or working overseas
Or have done so in the past
This is a program designed for you
Is Wigwam program in January 2019
In Beijing
During most u.s. colleges winter break
You will be able to learn from Executives at some of China's most available to come
And visit some of their offices
You will also participate in mixers with students at top Chinese universities like chinqua and Bay.
To build a local network
Please visit
Stellos. GG vici.com
For the application link and for more information
Once again that's fellows. Ggvc. Com
Recent arrest Monroe County
My dear
Welcome to the nine at six podcast brought to you by ggv capital
On the show interview movers and shakers
China's tech industry as well as Tech leaders who have a us China
Cross-border perspective, managing partner at ggv Capital and I've been working at startup
Investing in them in both the US and China for the past 20 years
My name is Zahra Jones I'm an investment analyst ggv capital and a former journalist
Why is the show called 9696 is the work schedule than any Chinese Founders have organically it
Adopted that is
9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
To us
996 captures intensity Drive
Wind speed
Of Chinese internet companies many which
I'm moving faster they even their American counterparts
On the show today we have tissue in food
Managing partner at ggv Capital based in China
Tissue enjoying ggv in 2006 and has more than 20 years of experience in Venture Capital investing
He focuses on travel and transportation social media and commerce
As well as Enterprise services in China
T-shirt has led Jujubes investments in Troon Redd
Yoko's without ucweb
What was your militia
Mediavue food truck Alliance or Amendment
Maytag and currently serves on the boards of Expo Motors hello bike
Twitter
Charles Schwab & Co
Issue played a critical role in many key strategic mergers and Acquisitions in China
Such as those of you quote without by the ocean or sitrep China and what would you marry for
Ever since his early investment in Baidu in system by the border by due for more than 8 years
Dude has been recognized by Forbes China as one of the best way to topple US every year
Since 2006
And frequently appears on the folk model X or Y
Price with UFC fighter just to let the Investment Group under the finance and investment division of the National Science and Technology board
Board of Singapore
Wichita tennis TV
In his work in the articulation of Hewlett-Packard
Distance from Singapore and graduate from National University of Singapore
With the first class honours degree in engineering
As well as master
A management technology from University graduate school business
Welcome to the show.
Thank you
So I wanted to start with you earlier career how did you end up in venture capital
Well it's
Bit of a Twist and Turn
You know I started to have the idea of being a bunch of capital when I was in Hewlett-Packard
Sr R&D engineer
My spend some time in the US spend some time to Valley spend some time in Corvallis Oregon
Looking at or the
Innovations and I was still
Sakes
And Corvallis Oregon
Corvallis Oregon
It's
It's where a HP has a star Pinhead division
So it's interesting how a lot of the Technology Innovation actually happens in
In the US
And even though I was an R&D engineer at Hewlett-Packard
It was more of a localization effort
Reformatting the printer if you will in different sizes and shapes to fit the different market segments
That was where I I said well
You know Asia at some point
Innovation has to take all we have to
Have our old product
Technology Innovation capability
Until
You know I figured out whether I wanted to be an entrepreneur you know be an ambassador so that's where I really had the ID
But really that wasn't a lot of
Startups that wasn't a lot of
Venture capital and I thought the only good stepping stone will be to join some Veggie Capital then
There were a few like water and advertise and so on
But when I rode my CVS and nobody really bought his call back
So that was then so the stepping stone for me was really an STD where I went in and
Stop debating cubatur
And I did that for about 4-5 years
You know that's part of the government initiative I what year was this
96 to mm
So there was a time where
I wrote papers and
Y'all and I I went around it will actually
I went to Israel Iran to
Ireland I look at
Also so
Innovation initiative London cambridge's Acura
So I think it opened up my eyes a bit and then the dog really came when in mm
Idfg
Stockton expansion this whole
You know Tim Draper has this Vision looking at venture capital and growing Venture Capital Beyond
The 20 mile radius
Off Silicon Valley show
And started
You have to eat planet and you know that's why I joined give je plan and that was my
Extend into the industry
What if the deals you did at DFW Planet wisp I do could you talk about how your first met Robin Lee the founder
And why did you think it was a
Idea to invest in
About to be
To be honest I think when
At a time that word is waves of returnees from us back to China
And
Through The BFG not what which is a pretty powerful now weather
Strong Affiliated not world end
You know I was referred to Robin
I remember my first contact with Robin was over a video call
True the Singapore office with a Skype call
We had a video call
Where's with Robin
And so that was when I first met Robin an hour rate was found it interesting
And I went to Beijing visited the office at 2 invited at that time
Is a NICU remember was this very
Pretty run-down place is called me. So you got bingo
There were very few people they had like 13-14 people than I'm so
Why invest in looking at the environment looking at
These guy coming back the I mean leaving your family behind and coming back to
Strive and make a difference in the market that they believe is growing it's you know it's just
Barry feel the passion
And that really kind of like
Give me the
Have you got hey you know this guy could do it so that's on the people side
S2000
That's mm
Meet 2008 about your research
Honestly was more a lot more desktop I got time and say okay you know
And there was no Google it was really comparing within to me and asked my into me was doing the
Is search engine for Yahoo and was powering the number of the portals
And then you also buy to have the same model
And service provider and I still remember that was the
Yeah
Definition of the thesis I wrote in a mammal
Partners
And so that was a thesis but I think I'm the line yet
That was this
View
That as information grow and that's more
Svss more websites and small content
It'll pull to put away portals is organizing the information to a directory is not enough
I'm so search has to be eventually a gateway
Now I wouldn't have predicted business model at that time
I just predicted the knee and predicted the guy.
And then obviously Baidu
Pivoted to a beauty model
Was it yeah it was it really 2001
How difficult was it get to that
Decision it was it was not a it was not a straightforward decision
At that time
That was a robin
So we had Cena so who natys we had all the major portals by the way
As our customers right
So
Pink customer site okay
But really we're not really making a lot of money is like
200000 us what a year and so it's it's a fundamental questions of where the value
When we go to capture the value
Obviously going to see setting up your own portal you're competing with
Your customers
And so that's
That's a I know that really puts a Barbie doll to True a lot of conversations like
Are we sure we going to do this I think one Robin was very determined and
Because he feels like
Is heated SRU guide like
No is that desno
There's no outcome there's no Market there's no value yes you can get
Some business right
But there's not a big business
So I didn't.
Determination he had at that time was really really important
And so the reference that we have what we do not Google I mean Google was in
Thalia
In 2001
So it was really goto.com
Goto.com with a company that actually bfj in basket
As well
That had to model for people performing
The acquired
First five placements on
All the search results in all the major portals and and they basically but they do Albatross business they they don't really own
Massage
So
Both Robin and nose in some ways of Google as well figure that hate that's the model that they could money
Overtime
Goto.com
Approving a business model
So you grab in Singapore when is school there in
Works there in the beginning of your career when did you come across the idea
Singapore my specific
So
I grew up in Singapore Joe Iowa
Mike my dad my
My mom that book to the both of Chinese Peking they were both teachers and I grew up in a very
Chinese speaking family my
My dad had monster in Chinese history so
So I had the
Affiliation or Affinity to China even when I was
Young
I think a lot of it is
The fact that I grew up in a family that you know gives me the confidence and
Some level of understanding
Aon
Affinity to China
Until when opportunity comes along
I was like okay you know I should go spend some time
My first trip to China was
Back in
In the second year
University
So
At that time you know I I I did a
Exchange program in Hong Kong University
And then I
I added a trip to China
It was quite an experience One China was to
Very good I was 19
You wasn't about 1990
So
The country is due a very close country is still limited by resources and
Open up in 1992
With the storm
Hey Ya
It was very only
And I took a train through Hong Kong
I from Sunshine all the way up to about how large is north of Beijing
And
I still remember when I tried tried to cross that border deal with people who say
Hey you know can you
Does this job so it's still a plan economy
So that's this coupon that you can
If you can bring across and got a stamp
They would actually be able to
You know cat the produce across the rug which is the television without those taxation
Without the
The import tax
And so I tried to do that
I was a student I can make a mule some money
And I was caught at the immigration I was brought into the immigration room
And I was questioned and
You know initially I'll show you this.
It was quite an experience
So it it's in the process of traveling through China
You see the different faces of China
And that the important thing is that over the years you see how I think what's important for people to know
All about China
Is not a ball
What you see at an instant
He's about the change that you see in the process
Because that changes
The one that is
Power
The change. Jessie ended
Does the simple change in infrastructure
But it's also the change in the people the my side
I think that was something that actually caught me in
And say this is a country that
Come up
I really agree
When I'm in school here I go back around once a year and every time I go back I don't recognize the country
Yeah and I think right now like I don't go back for more than 3 months
Completely
Well you know just the kids that we talked to
Yesterday I mean do you know what
That's what I was like conversation is like
I mean these kids are
Amazing I mean
The power they know what they want
I mean if you compare two
This I guess the same group of kids their parents in the end and the generation before then it got very different but the change
Going through and the inter like that
It's Alicia
In this country
Is the one that
That's really amazing for
This generation Z is going up with a lot more confidence about half lot more information
That anyone else beforehand
Ryan isn't probably see them
Carrabba's lentil rice
So how did you first come across to TV
Elementary
Gbwhats actually founded by four Founders how many seeing Joe Kalman
We have hanging out and Scott Bond him as well
I am the one Thomas and Joel Thomas Wilson
My college
At at
So he
He ran a
I find it that timing on Dennis TV called TV
DanTDM related
Became Pediatrician on TV of China became hippies
So anyway that's a little bit
History dare
So Thomas and I goes kind of way by and I knew him since that he say
After I joined the fji idea to leave the FJ
We started to have conversation
You know about last name saying
You know he really want that
Me to comment
Nail spend time with gdb
And actually help set up 2GB in China
Set a time that was so so Jenny 2005 is 2005 and
So you know she
I do remember so Thomas
That time you know got his team we spend time together
And then we also went to this Alibaba big event in the Westlake in 2005
That's why I spent quite a bit of time with Haney with Jenny and so the idea was kind of coming together
I had the
Option of say hey ghost.
Fun Zone files
Or Johnny apothem and I figured that
Partnership is actually not that easy
You want to join a group that
That you have some affinity
And so you
You may not be a like but at least you have some
Cultural connection you have some
A common understanding you have some common
Friends in common
Browns and so you can you can go a long way
Sold out
Big part of my consideration when I drawn ggb was the fact that I know Thomas for a long time
What was different about you versus the other us Farm cuz I remember
Baidu Harrah
Back in 2000
234 had a tough time raising money from Sandhill Road everybody in the whole world could have seen
Baidu Baidu and could have invested everyone pass
So what was about you TV that make you feel comfortable that is
Does not like another
ABC women's China
Ford GT vs
Gdb actually I think
Thomas beard
Haney and
God and Joel
I didn't get the group and we we we started off with this
Very fundamental view of
The cross-border
We believe that
That's a lot of intellectual average that we can get
Across us and China by being on both sides
We
I I saw how the team spend time together in fact
I meant that more than once I met him in
The whole team in Singapore I met whole team in Beijing and made the whole team in
The valley
So you can see how
They are spending time together
To interconnect
A lot of the
Views of the views and ideas
And two today I think that's the
Approach that we continue to take
Gdb
Across is punishable we spend time across
Both both region
Having all sides but it is in
DUIs are in China
And being on the ground
Asking what's happening it's important
So I think for many of the
Silicon Valley.
You know where I was the FJ
To be fair I think
Tim Draper someone really.
Spend time
Traveling around
Most people would not
Maybe they'll do it once in
A long time ago
One year two year three years but not frequently
You know how many times a year
So
So that's that's the engagement I think only when you
Hot and feel and not just reading
Materials
An articles that you can make a better connection and F4 you can bake a better
Inform judge
On what you're investing
You have that many of the
Largest m&a
Yeah in history of Chinese internet sector starting with Joe Caputo which was the first ever multibillion-dollar dealer that got done
Internet in China
Read about it I was extremely impressed inspired
The way you did and what else is possible
I thought I was coming who can be a different era
Starting with that deal with more to come
How did you think about the idea of structuring the deal
And how did not get you to do more things like that
/ lost
Yasso
It alright
I as I spend time on tudor
And I spend time with Gabrielle
Look at how this company has
It is a
Interesting I mean it with a first-mover
In the market
Caught on video online video the
Obviously
It started with more little bit of a beetle parked cars and then it evolves right
Andy become more mainstream content
And
So as it becomes more mainstream content
Y'all
Oh that's
A lot more content
Acquisition and cost
Escalate so it's not just use acquisition
Costas contact
So as you look at this
Particle
The competition start to get intense and
Where's the cost of content escalating as much as
5 to 10
Display
It's it was like hundred to two hundred thousand
Rmb / episode 2
A million to 2 million
Rmb
Any shot of Everclear
So that was this
The first
Dang it I mean
Looking at a market
And
Looking at and then
Look ggv are we had quite a bit of money in there we actually brought our
We also brought audit investors
I feel really real
O'Reilly's 405 it was 10% off of fun
Also that the question is really
You know what
Was nice and
You know that
Doodle
At with all the
We bought a $10 house
It did go IPO and
Murad ipoe
Waipio Valley weather
About to the market also reacted to a point where I get home devaluation came down Hymn for her
100 million in
You don't we have
200 million cash but that's why I took 200 million cash
Will last about
Tough monster
That's Gary
That's really scary like wet wild can you raise capital
Drink
So
He my mind
Consolidation
Has to happen
This Market
Has we got consolidated
So and I went around talking to
The people
Gary I spoke with Victor I spoke with Roku
Victor youku
I spoke with Kanye from I touch your body if I do
So I thought that talking to Dom
They hate this kind of
Obviously I'm coming from a position
Where
Yunnan
You're not looking at $2 and I told to Gary this
I said
If consolidation is going to happen
You want
Because you captured the most valued by being the kingmaker
Right
That was a thing that really try to get him to think about his number 3
Number one
He was I mean in terms of traffic it was kind of
Two so it one two three but in that ballpark are not that far apart
But you can really be the key make
In that instant bright
NBA players that PDP players
And so I do
Which a lot more traffic
So we knew something has to have
So that that for
Biplane got hand I was able to you know
Get the attention
No problem
Well I didn't when I talk to the CEOs
Everybody knew that
The biggest issue is Trust
Life
How can we do this
Like because to have a MMA
You have to
Open up the kimono
Like everybody has to say okay this is
This is what I have open up some gas so you have to open
And
And that's one
2 is
You have to feed all the manager
So
Let me know
Deck that can be
D2L
Alright so somebody
Has to step aside
And what do we do with the match many Star just one person
Is that one team
So that's always the the
Ski park
In MMA
So I think
I was able to figure that out
That was in
One12 12 2012 when
I remember it was
Chinese New Year and
I had a call with Eric leave from Shumway Venture and then
So now after we had multiple calls out the dad hand
We brought everybody to a neutral ground
We had to re everybody to neutral ground which is
Hong Kong 4 and we had a closed-door session
Kioku into town between you and to the whole one day one it's almost one full day
All through the night and we had a handshake
How we took a bow
Just about three weeks
From that point on
To iron out
Mejor Crema
But I can be announced
Obviously
Taobao listed company
The whole completion of the transaction
Take time
I'm going to be a little naughty and ask obviously you're very Closer by do and you know both Robin and also
Gucci
Hook up by the woods on the water LIC was in the white numbers
Well you have to ask that
When he saw the news was
It was a little bit
Wow shop with them as well
About to be fair
It all
What we're friends but
I will lay the opportunity
Down for you but if we
If I want to get the dude on reading speed
And certainty certainty is important
So that that that driving conviction and
Determination to want
Galveston Veterinary
Victor
So
Do in terms of
At exits to thing
I'm pretty sure start thinking about that from day one and have a clear idea of how their come
Exidor
I think
No I think you have to stop it I Dear Dad
Well if you if you want to go and build something
You don't build something to say
I built a Sal around I think you want to build and say I want to build something
Now the outcome is really hot
I would say that
You know I've been in this business for a loss
18 years
In-N-Out China
And
I didn't first ten years most people would say.
IPO is the
The way to go
Because
First of all that wasn't Manny
Super unicorns
Unicorns that actually can make
Logic
Right
So
You know
From 2010 to now heading over the last 8 years
Now we have
We are
These ginormous companies like
Aliante concern and baidu
JDJ
So they have
They now have the
Market
Market cap
Uwell 2
How to make Lodge acquisition
Interesting outcomes
So I think the market has
Change so Eminem
Just ice
In the US will be
Become a
Could be a very interesting Isaac in some ways it can be a better exit
How if you have to complete looking at liquidity part of you yet
Bubble of entrepreneurs and Anubis
But I think a lot of people don't realize that up until that you'll go to the murderer
IPO with
Primarily the only way
That's right people to get AIDS
In the US where is 80% lemonade
Was all IPO up Adele.
Engineer fu
Few more prominent big-name M&S
I didn't next one was Vikings investments into chunara
With controlling stake
That was another unusual
Move
What had a controlling stake but also
The company was able to go
Public only two deals I was done at all time when it was so who
And their game company
And then I was with what you did with by doing too.
So how did that work and once again how do you generate rust on both side
To have
Both sides agreed that yes one will have control mistake but no to the amazement has control operationally
Yeah well I think the
The story was that you know chunar
That was back in 2011
So in 2011 shootout
Started off as a meta-search play
And
Yeah you were competing with
Cucina
Initially and but
Overtime
You know if we want to take
True not with you level so you was more like a kayak and sites that in the US
And
It if you want to take schunard to a bigger
Company
That business model is not enough
So it has to
It has to evolve into more Beyond a Media Company be and become a OT
Call order I mean
How do you become a o t a i mean really dead
That whole supply chain is being controlled by both sitra Bandito
So
Two so that two outcomes one is
We sell the company at that time we had the option of selling the company say
600 700 million to
OCC Tribble
The lights
Or
We want we continue to grow that company
But we need some
Ammunition
So
And so the idea that time I had was
If we can have Baidu to invest
And if I do can
You know
We can make sure not become the de facto
Gateway
Fall travel search
You'll be a very pompous
So at least I control
The supply I mean
50 Monaghan
And then I can work on the supply chain
So that was the idea
And so I brought the Baidu team
Abroad
CCI prison
So together and and have a conversation
And I was able to work out a deal
With them
Obviously d
It was complex because Baidu
Definitely wanted control
So we negotiated the
The control State you know
How to 60%
And
We wanted to maintain Independence oh
We we have
7 boat seats
I'll preach Baidu
At 4
But that's a 4-seat that the appointment
Remember so
A sort of the Divide
So that was how we
Restructured the
Deal
And we went pretty well
Soda company continue to grow that business in 2013 we IPO to come
But competition
Continue to
It becomes
In Tad's right way
Wave sea travel
ISO Alibaba and so
By 2015 we forget the funeral James Leon came back to see Trey band
Airsoft at the conversation alkmaar consolidation then
So we did we did that m&a with
Shinar
Back in 25th
Team
And it was a great outcome for us
It really priced
Tonight at 7 to 8 billion so you was at a Next Step Up
From producing Bessemer
It wasn't
Step up from Baidu investment because
Baidu investment web
Radiator that's how about you we have sold the company
Would have been
2015 combo
How do you negotiate a deal
Deal that's acceptable
To everyone
Especially a lot of the time
People may have different
Intros and
One player might be more dominant than the other so how do you make sure everyone
A set of terms and
Except
First of all you have we have to understand what
Each body wash
So Baidu has
This strategy
That time
If you look at it
It was run relative
They had a strategy that. Somebody goals Dede wood
I won a majority
As much of a stake as possible but they are very willing
Spell to have that
Management and
Xiamen
Given to
To the team
Depron step business
So that that was you know
Baidu
Onesite
Okay I want to own that body
5 minute IQ
Run it
Vincent has a similar Style
10010 has
Today at
Samosa by tencent doesn't require that lot ownership
I do at that Minority
That's what I might do is more majority type
Arrange
You have to figure out what the
One that's why
And whether in the management what do they want
So I think for the management team as well for cc but the club
Who would want to step up as a CEO
You know because
You know he will lavish on that
To build
You will be able to take this company
You know just from Media company to a OTA camp
That's what really he wanted
So he's willing to give out that ownership
Set time to 2
To do that
So I think it's a question of just
Making those needs
Matt
And you know
I'm building a Arrangement equating arrangement.
Allow precise to
To get what you want
With the recent merger of
Humana and culture about
Which are the largest
Top trucking companies
The angel investor one guy actually became
Ciccio
Adding that on that deal, say that there's a lot of that's a lot of investors and wet Wild
Route the few minority shareholder off you my mind
I will give a lot of
A lot of the credit to one column
I remember one thing is last year in August I was
Traveling in Europe
Wangjing caught me and say hey
Deal you know
I'm going to do this and I'm going to
He and he was still alive
He was mine he was an angel investors it was positioning himself and invested but he was the one who really negotiating
Shockwave WhatsApp
What's a bonnet
Alliance
So he told me he's going to get it done in
2 weeks
Hi babe
Do I got a few things.
I told him was like that's not going to work
Because they are very comfortable in size
And I think that
That's no one
Management that can
Say
I don't know how to say this in English like
Bhutan rights
What size is saying that
Okay you know I
I I gave up you you are you're better than me
I don't think so at that time
The
The the management team leadership the leadership of the management team
It's not that clear
So I said you know
I think ini I post this to Wonka I said
If you want to do this the fasting
The right thing for you to do
Become the CEO
If you become the CEO of the company
Everybody will follow everybody will
Will follow you
The leadership
Annies
He's X Alibaba your has a operator experience
He has
The credential office investor indeed investor DDC
He has that cloud
So anyway it the whole deal took months actually
In
I didn't want to be the tremendous job off
You know
Talking to the various investors on both sides
And including the government
That the supported
No both sides in order to prospective government
Still to come pick us as Lotto
Disadvantage
So I think he managed to
Will all these things
Together and
And cut a deal work so so
By mistake my hat off to him and he's done a fantastic
Even
STD bronchitis
Or didi and Uber
Just
After that you'll who to delete everyone
I'm a lot more used to
Doing MMA
Joseph put inmate Huntingdon
Excetera excetera
What do you think are there
External factors
And I made a lot more possible to have MMA after 2011
What were the two factors involving with Audubon Pennsylvania made a possible easier to have
Honda deals
Well I think that
Does a lot more MMA I think that's
An accidental Factory is ready
These Market
China the pace of change
An innovation is
Accelerator
The market adoption
Consumers education everything is
Add a salary.
You look at how I weezing evolve you look at how payment evolve in China
A lot of that has
Capital
That's a lot
Capital being
Pumping to subsidiary
The program that is subsidies and so hot
2 2
To drive adoption
I'm on hand you have
Rapid adoption
Janina Market
Which is driven a lot by capital
But yeah.
On the other hand
A dry scalp
Titian
At different levels which also requires a lot of Kappa
Thrift store
It all it does a limit to how much Capital you can race
Despite whether you are TD or York yd
That's a limit to how much valuation people are willing to pay and so
Hiding capital
A factor that
Actually drives those MMA
Because you can no longer race
Mall Cop
Enough for you to Bard
So you have to pick out while snacks and sold that forces a lot of consolidation
I think it stopped it really with online video
Inanity boss into the out of oracle's like
You know EDM quality by sharing and Uber China and the ride sharing space and then we have
Measuring by Sherri Webb
May Tuan and Kim King
Which is more deep
Takeout business
So you just consult will you continue to see this happen
Because
The market
SMB capital
Market can no longer
Take those
Financial subsidies in finance
Consolidation
So I think that's a big
Factor
The other thing is just I think with the yucutu doe case it's also a mindset shift
People understand what that means
And entrepreneurs who have
You know
Y'all bet the guys was sold that business are you know to mm850 Exeter
They
DXE the Army good with with with
I mean big they got up with pot of gold
I think
When you when you see that it's also important
All the entrepreneurship the alpha down hard work is it paid for
If not
It's not the little just walk away without anything
So I think that outcome also helps
So
So I think it's a
2 factors
You've let a lot of Jujubes invest
Shenzhen mobility in
Including
Ride-sharing companies like Didi and grab
Bike sharing
Hello bike
Trucking company in my mind and also connected car company
Expo Motors or shop on seashore
I wonder what makes you excited about mobility and you are mine
In 10 years how will people be
Yeah so I think that's a pieces that
Affirm
I woke
Wave hands at work with Jenny so we
We we we talked quite a bit about
You know I do remember
So when we first started
This whole thing is just a concept
Porsche economy right
But ride-sharing in
I'm so
Professing faster in grab it and a dog
We caught up with Ed
I didn't hold
The whole tracking service
Chris Paul
I didn't want is
If you look at it all business model
They all wear
What is on the consumer and business and
It's it's not easy to connect
Demand and supply
So that's a fundamental issue which Mobility I
She creates because it's
Location
So that technology
Mobility solution actually
Makes a connection work
And then along with that I think that's the first time
And
We we we done went on from
Connecting people
Because
The guy providing the sub is a drivers do a person
How to connecting with an object
Which is a car or bike to stop
So I think that
The mobility solution will evolve
The
D Supply on
Which is the vehicle
Ghost from the bike
Christmas elf drawing
South right to
A car which can be bought on Amazon
What time
Is
The connection will be caught will change
Towaco from
People to object
And so that will be a lot more technology that needs to go in there
How to make the car more intelligent
Autonomous over
What time
So I think
If you see the evolution of this actor
And
Wake me think that
These things going to
Convert
The car company
And the right sharing
Platforms
It's going to come by
He my mind out of the food truck Alliance now is called
It's going to
He has to think about how to
How to build trucks that is
Eponymous
Overtime
Espada 1
So that connection will ship all the time and so
I didn't put ugb is
We have to
We ambassador
We invest ahead so we
These are pieces of Jigsaw somehow
Now that maybe
Working independently as different companies and still
Collaborate with each other or they may
Much with each other
At some point
We don't know
But
I think it is a
Directions
That market is high
That
Car
The supply and will become more and more
Collagen will be
Become more a man if you will
All on this side it just
Become more intelligent
Telling you the kind of service
You can ride a bike
If you're just going for a
Want to 3 kilometer or 1 2 3 miles
How are you can
Got a car
So in that same app
You you should have all the transportation service that you know
Versus having like multiple apps
So I think that will be more
Consolidation that could happen in disc
So what investment that was not as obvious
Is from day one was
The bike sharing
Hello by Adele
So
When
When you met them
The second was already very heated with
A lot of investors money going into ammo bicondova
And that the vendor markets in China was pretty saturated Allred
Yeah
And they failed
And the founder was very young so what makes you believe
That it was a good idea to invest in demand
Obviously it's a very prescient decision because they're the number one
Independent by sharing
Player in China
I love you but don't know.
Production by Alibaba
Yeah
Well when I first look at this
Bike sharing space
I was trying to
Figo light how do you make
How big is
It was
Funeral
You can predict that you don't even need to pay to write to to try to get a ride bro
How do you make money from a ride-sharing
Service that that was mine
First question
And
So
So we we met
We might mobike or we not owe for that time
And
Find out what different questions that we
We had it on my about both companies
This
Otho had a very
Simple
Bike
Religious a bike with a lock
Like a mechanical lock
And I will work
So
And and when I look at the model is 200 RMB a by the cost of operating the 200 by
Towanda R&B by a lot
Is quite High
I mean
At that time David
Debbie Wade
The co
So hat is
Had his model and I was looking at a model I said
You can never really
Take tomorrow cuz I think the cost of operation
Co-op
The rights
Robot robot
The number of rice per day could shift
As you go from Summer to Winter
Things like that so so when I look at tomorrow it wasn't quite making
And mobile
Similar and
So when
@brenda Halo by came to me and so it was already out
Portfolio is they had a service
For parking. Time in
What's not going very far and this is his
Second Venture and
And then you know and then he tried to any'tizers tried to tell me to ask him to do this which is
Stuck in the shade so
Why should I believe you and so I think when he tried to do that
But he threw his first to graduate he has a
Accumulated
A lot of operating know how
He understand a lot of the issues
Around
Bike operation
A product
Prada issues and how to make
Operationally efficient
The service operation
Play fishing
So I thought that victim of Engineers
It was a good team of Engineers and
So it'd be the one interesting thing is
Initially I
Completely convinced I say
Well what are you going to do
What are some trials threatened in some selected cities that he did he went to two cities and he did some trials he came
The numbers
And and then
He sought to open my mind
About what disc
Grandma one I think
The the number of
Rice actually
This this is a big mark
So just from a frequency of Engagement
Is far higher than the TDM
So at that time I kind of we did a bag
So tobacco
The envelope
So as to Major list for China
That these rights but they could get to
That's a big number
In terms of using
Well that's one thing that caught me
The second thing is
Yeah he was telling me that
Hey you know I'm not just doing bikes
I'm going to do
Electric Power
But has a lot more product and Technology
Emo music
That you need to deal with light charging
Bison
Prices wireless charging on charging stations and blah blah blah
Those are issues that he hasn't
I figured out yet but he said hate directionally this
Xiamen to do
I'm going to increase my
Not only the frequency of Engagement but
The distance for
Travel
But
That statue God got me
Interested
So I brought you haunted
Wake up at 3:54 how did you get over by that
The concern that
Via subsidy will still be there
In art what the capital of
Christopher Wilde
Do you feel that give me a passage with all the
Consolidation
That won't last forever
Then we already a year 2 years into it
So the
So
So I honestly do I bet on this guy become
Number one right from the inside not really
I was like okay what's my wand
The other thing about Vice sharing is that
China has closed
400 series
Wave
More than a million million people
And so
This
And in a mobile and even at that time or buy a no-fault alarm me in Tijuana
Fairfield City to get dad's room for them to grow
Said that's one thought
The second thought is that
No because even after this
Given to all this because I haven't been amazed
The worst case scenario
How to get console
Odyssey that's value
So that's how I thought about initially
I hate you
If they do there's any
To do this right
In the West cast
So that's why I know
Will you be I got you and Jenny we spent
Sometime in between
We put in the first 5 million and
II
Free melon so we continue to finance him until Chang we came along and and Financial
Taking the long way.
And today they are
By far the largest player
Friday
They are more than 25 minutes a day
Yeah
You know the aggregate
Aggregate also go for a mobile
Understand because
That way his team had to buy clothes not as quick intelligent
But what do you think is the reason that I hope I can overtake even mobike
Number one for lunch
Mike Meyer Weiner mobiles
Not so much on.
Product
My Rio mobile was just
My understanding of
What's happening with the mange
Richmond
So
The
Not Unified
Not as
Yeah not as Unified
So I think that
But you should die
Roi
I hear from afar
Which
I think
So that was the thing that I
I think eventually
Octagon itself
Presently being he's gay
He's the
He's a real founder
Hi mobile
He's the chairman but
He is really doing
Yellow wheels
At Broadway and where he has hundreds of Millions.
Bonnie Wright
Orion TV company
So what
That's a TV company and so
Wet weather cset right where does he stand
So it's a different so I think that
Evil entrepreneur has haiku
Conviction in
You know go all in on one one thing
The chance of snow
Size of just hire
GDP was not a major investment Automotive sector in the
Between 2000-2010
There were other investors who rushed into a space Cocina automotives a huge sector
That's why she called me
In China
Poverty line
60 years
Most realistic
E46 years
MTV has become a major investor in the space lab IU with invest
17dd and Edna Halo bike and
And
Norfolk Airlines
So within a very few years
Become a major investor in the space.
What does a
Elvis first move Advantage. Important
Or you wait for the right signals
In order to decide how to double down on a
I think when you invest you learn
And so I didn't the initial investments in graph
Gives you
Vantage point
I still hate what's happening
Find a ride sharing space
Nidd
And then Hello by
Nauc Hall
People are thinking
About last night
So
I think a lot of it is
Evolution
Offices
Mitra
How to say okay I know exactly
5 years
You're sounding Road
It's really a process of
Talking to these entrepreneurs and say okay this is how I see my biz
Evolving
And you got bikes along the way
N
I think the
Dog from
Didi and grab
And
You know food truck Alliance they have a common theme
Which is
Is Asmara connectivity
Just and
Simplifying the connection and making the
The supply-demand more efficient
That's the fundamental right
Then along then beyond that is really
Howdy
DIY Vaseline
Evie's is a different my
Already it's
It's really
Dad
The when goes to Halo by is a the object
The car
The Disturbed
Does the vehicle has to be
Become more intelligent
So hello by Kiss Me.
Scentsy
That
The object
You know with AI with
We've also sensory
Technology
Will become more and more intelligent
And I believe that you know in the next 3 to 5 years or 5
After 10 years
Car will be
And has it all why I
Santa talking looking at
Space and
Talking to Shopko and say hey if you want to do this
You should go RN and go
Ezypay
When you see white and it was at the
So endia and I are look at this category
Just as Tesla was founded by you
If not many people
Normani on
Cuz you need
Almost
You need us Iran
People who have done it before
It's so hard suck big supply chain
That you you have to sample talent that believes in you
You and I left you have done it before is like why you write and
You have to have two Financial Muscle help yourself to say that this is why I wanted to do an
Investors want to follow you
So
You know leaping from you actually you know he puts in hundreds of Millions
Exponent
I got you. Did the same I mean he did they put in where the
Money wedding
How many players who can do this right
And how
As a big category
China sells 26 million UK server
Your
Huge Market
So what
If some if he can capture it will be
Huge
What does it mean for a long time and you when we see young PCS
Trying to break into the
Industry
Fight over a video
And get worried videos projected but I see didn't get approval
And then
Sometimes it worry about price or they don't worry about price you want to pay any price to get into it.
What advice can you give them
How to be patient and methodical
Orthomatic
One categorical
Did he look at what she has done in
E-commerce versus retail with investor initial investment about by now has
Good morning
Shunyi beijing
E-commerce space
When your retail space
Simple to use in China
Look at auto transportation space
Futaba in there
With
In tune are and then also we did Airbnb in the US
And then Auto investments in
Sharing in my
Any luck at El Frontier Tech with Jenny
Sector ice overtime gets
White
Well cover
With keto teaching Bass
What kind of ice can give through UMBC
Think before they act
And not
Crepe on the neck
Octane
Courtesy Inn
Your old you don't get it in
Well there's always new stuff
Well that's too bad Yelp
D4 Young
New ideas innovation
Providing
New drivers
Robot
Driver's world
Disruption
So that's
Great now
The thing here is that
With with ideas no
You could look bad Amazon you know
Mm in
Raise a ton of money
You know it's some puppy
When was crazy today
Amazon is
A ginormous Company soap
You
First of all you have to do
Appreciate
And take time to appreciate it
What you believe
And get
Get the opportunity
And I'm sure you know I G I think I did
Many other firms will
Give you the opportunity to
YouTube
Advise and
Deep dive
And spend time do I have to understand the fundamental
A lot of
The stop.
About
My view I mean
Talk about things
That should be at a very high level
What
He can be but
But there are a lot of
Things That Go
Can go wrong
And when things goes wrong
Is it really going wrong or is it just a moment
But I'll see if you can understand that
You could dance
Make the best of it and capitalized
So I think
You don't from my early investments in Baidu like
I want to say that
For the first three years I just don't know where the light is like
You don't know if this company can be
Because
Whatever they do why would they make stupid
Pioneer Steel
So small
People don't talk about it
We don't know
Yasso
After the Baba Buzz thing seems to fall into
The black hole
So you have to
Believe that
Search will become
But
You is just
How does it get there
It takes time
So likewise I think weather is
Write Shayari
With cryptocurrency with
AR with VR with AI all the later stuff
Can you imagine
It will come
That question is
Waze app
Vacation
That will
Staraptor Smogon
Will gives it that
That power to
Explode
Explosive growth
We're going to move on to the last
Part of the show witches
Around a quick question
Phrases whose entrepreneurial admire the most
That's always a tough question
The entrepreneurs that I
Walkway
And that they all have different trades brother is Robin leave from Baidu or CC drawing from Shannara
Shop home now
We are becoming a sea right
I respect entrepreneurial
For the
You know Drive
And passion
And for some of them is
Like passion the passion goes Beyonce I want to make
The passion goes into
Making things possible making a change
Possible
It all fall short poem I mean
To be fired
The guy is
Retirement
He can she can retire on
On a boat on a plane or whatever right I mean he's
He's kisise OUC wife a couple Bella doll
And so
Wanting to have that
And outdrive to say. Something
And now he's like
Having eight meetings a daytime meetings a day while looking through weekends and so long is
It goes beyond money
That passion so I respected
So many entrepreneurs Iris
Percent
What do you do for fun
What do I do it for fun I
Actually I I love
Sport I attended recently and I broke it
I brought my lab Achilles tendon recently and I broke my
Right one
6 years ago 7 years ago
So anyway
Actually I love
I love sports I love to play sports I I love to challenge myself
Self
I love team sports
The smile because is a good way to
Social
You know my wife is now telling me he's a
You know maybe you shouldn't ski anymore should have play badminton anymore as like
No I don't know I don't know
Stop I started skiing on the
Bye love the challenge
It's my Auto Falls I love the challenge of
Yo
Going through that process
And you know eventually
Beanie Boos
Be better in bed
So
I love the challenge
Myself and I
Well thank you for your time thank you
798 beijing
Listening to this episode
996 by the way we also produce a weekly email newsletter English also called 9 + 6
Who's at the Roundup of the week's most important happenings
Intec in China subscribers formative and fun to read the new Siddhartha features
Original content
An analysis from Zara me
Stripe at nine 6. GG bc.com
Friendbase in Silicon Valley on high and Beijing we have been partnering with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past
18 years from seed to pre IPO
With 3.8 billion dollars in capital under management across state funds GTA V invest in globally my
Find entrepreneurs in consumer new retail social internet Enterprise cloud and Frontier Tech
Gdb has in Boston over 290 companies
With more than 45 companies valued at over a billion dollars
Pergola companies include
Airbnb Alibaba C trip Didi chuxing Domo hashicorp Hello by
Cows keep Slack
Square
Hotel wish soundtrue white white and others find out more at ggvc. Com
We also highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat group in slack Channel
Where we regular share insights events and job opportunities related to attack in China joined a screw
Bridgesat 96.3 gbc.com community
Do you have any feedback on this podcast
Or would like to recommend a gas please email us at 996 at gbc.com