Intervention
Airport
Hi there
Welcome to the 96 podcast
Brought to you by Gigi capital on the show wings of the movers and shakers of China's tech industry
I just got home Founders from around the world can draw lessons
Ecosystem
My name is Khan song
I'm a managing partner at ggv capital
And I've been working at and investing in startups
Across the US
China and other emerging markets for the last 20 years
My name is Rita young I'm the marketing manager at ggv Capital
Why does show cut 96
96 is the work schedule many Chinese funders organically adopted
What is 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
To us996 captures the intensity
Drive and speed of being an entrepreneur in fast-growing Market
From Beijing to Bangalore Jakarta to New York
I highly recommend you joining our WeChat group and slack Channel where you can connect with like-minded people
We organize regular offline events across the world for all listeners you can join this by visiting 9/9
6. GG vici.com
Lea Michele we have Josh Luber
The co-founder of stockx
Sarcoidosis the world
First online stock market
Barhyte Medical
Consumer gets let me speakers
Hi back
Streetwear in watches
I'm a popcorn fart
Play
Stellas place
It would have been asked me different action happens
Automatically
The detroit-based
Startup was launched in 20
Mx922 Europe
Balances first authentication Center in London
Sarcastic
People falling
Before launching stockx
Josh have built three out of
Nice and worked at IBM as a strategy
Consultant for almost
5 years
He holds a JD and MBA from the Emory University
None of this is as impressive at
The fact that he started collecting sneakers from 10 years old
And has more than 350 pairs of sneakers
Annie's home
Welcome to the show Josh
Thanks for having me
First question I wanted to ask exactly Four Hands
Cuz I know you're a big
Basketball fan but you're not really a sneakerhead yourself
Can you tell us the story how did you meet
Josh and what about stockx
Kind of excited
Jor-el colleague Robin
Was tracking
Consumer spending
And this trend
Are people buying
Charlotte weather radar
In an obviously there were two companies in the space in the US
Wingstop
And I'm when we met
Through
It was battery Ventures
Who put us in touch
Rocker battery
It was a GoFundMe
Put us in touch with Greg
And Josh
It was a it was very obvious that
There's a lot of stuff with
Any process of
Didn't know Greg and Josh
Another friend of Stevie Scott
Adopt my sugar alcohol radar and we caught up in
I guess we can rejoin the stockist
Ssfcu
So he just all came
Together the fiction
Do you remember the first time you've met Josh are there any interesting anecdote you can share
Yeah first my Greg and then Greg connector
Meet with Josh
So we met at given.up on office
Gdb and we were
On the way to China or just back
And so there was a lot of stuff to talk about China
It is extremely refreshing to see a company
From us
That were
Sew in
Sticking what's happening in China and recognized what channel can do
That you can have
The best Supply in the world by being the US
And you have other relationship the brands but being the US
We have the US pop culture is leading the world in what's fashionable
Yet there's a
Huge huge huge Marketing in China
That's number one in the world.
You can somehow married at 2
You can go to unbelievable
Helping us
In China before in fact
Before I ever met you don't Rodger who is on our board
Connected us the Highlands
When we were
Greg Schwartz is our CEO and co-founder
We're Greg and I were coming to China
And how does it help set up that trip
Before before he died
Gmat before and it was when we got back
That we actually got the meats
The first time in person and then
You know this relation
Almost all of the investors that we have
DC
Otherwise
We're all people that were actually
Helping
Before that doesn't
So why were you interested in China or coming into China
In the first place
Yeah I mean
Is the right it's one of those mosto
Questions in in a lot of
Categories would certainly for us when we sell
Denver super fortunate to be able
What is Saltillo tile
Are products in the world
It's Nike Lube
Baton Rolex
Supreme are the products really he's held himself we built a mark
Build a model
That has been able
Go to grow very rapidly and build a lot of
Supply and then
If the demand has been here
And China has become 15% of our business
Almost without us
Doing anything
Yet totah really localized release
I'm going to grow that market
Defrost
It's on right now.
Testing a bit more about what you were doing
Before stock
Yes so I started run
Three other stars
Before the snow that meant anything to do with sneakers almost intentionally
It's almost like intentionally separating business
Some pleasure in my life but the the business that that would have been chubby
Comstock expose a company with
Call Campus
In campus
Was a price guide for
12 2013-2014
We are analyzing
EBay data
To figure out what her shoe tax
To create some idea of a true market value
Sneakers
And we were just fortunate I guess to be the only people doing real analytics around the secondary Market
Sneakers at the time and end as this
The core data layer or understanding of market value
Would eventually become
The foundation
Stock X has the market play
Which is the market place built on market value
How stock market
Chantix work but understanding the true market value of any asset
A consumer good like that the real you
Any part of the store
You got to understand the numbers for a Saturday night on the field
Jobs for people who actually don't get
Sneakers for sports
Can you help us understand likewise
And I know you have a question about is
Sneakers closer to
Drops or two starts
I found that question fast
Yeah at the corner here that me this is supplied.
This is econ 101 added
That's very very most basic and most pure even props
More pure than the stock market
Get itself done the stock market itself
The market price of a
Overstock
Ultimately actually of Funk
Function of of what
People think
That company is going to do what they
The performance is going to be
Stickers
Just supply and demand
Do you have these products
At the brand
Complete your Nike and Adidas and Jordan
Really leopard scarcity in order to put out less product
Then there is demand for
Plus products
And by
Basic economics
If something is available
Then people who want it
Then that price
I will go up
And that's what's happened to your neck used to doing this for
34 years dating back to 1985 and
The first Air Jordan
But it was always a very
Local underground sort of thing and then in the last
Osteophyte
6 years really on the back
Social media in
Instagram
You know the sneaker mark
Begin a lot more means
Extreme as more people one acts
And that's really really really with
Stockx about
Access
And creating access
Search for product
That have really high demand
That's hard to get
It's hard to understand
Where to get it what's real what's a fair price for it
And that's really that
The Corvette you know the question around the stocks for drugs it is
Was one of the most popular articles that we wrote back in the day when we were just
Just a price guide when I camp
And was this idea of actually looking at the data around sneakers to
To see that the the mechanics of essentially the
Supply and demand
And how people were buying
Selling sneakers
Looks frankville a lot like the way that people buy and sell boats.
End drugs
But you know
Places support much more League
So you are a sneakerhead yourself
Also
Update on Earth
As well as a serial entrepreneur
All of the sweet things
Which roaches
I think is actually the fundation of
Stockx it's definitely data
We have
Super fortunate that we have been able to grow and become
One of the largest sneaker marketplace in the world
It's almost a red herring
Sneakers are
It was called stocking
Text not sneaker exit
It really is about the model in really is about
Did the economics and the data
Of upgrading Marketplace that's built on
On those stock
Mechanics
Sneakers release
Just put in the first category
And look if all that that for General kid knows is that we sell sneakers made by the next pair of sneakers from us
The we appreciate that and we appreciate that business but it really is about the big idea which is why I get to
To come here to Hong Kong that does speak it rise
Speak around the world and explain the people that this is about
A new form of Commerce that is
For lack of less cliche way of saying it
Truly
Like this generally doesn't exist outside the ACT
Actual stock market
And that
Thank so back to the question that
Try to answer
Are you here to talk
Is
Sneakers more like soccer.
The interactions of the
Participants in the market is a lot more like drugs
When you see people that are buying three pairs in order
Where to fund their
Collection and pay for one right if I can get ahold of three and sell to I can afford
The data and the the supply and demand an understanding why
Shoe sales for a certain price
Is actually a lot more like stocks
Where you have
Is pure supply and demand and you and we then have built marketplace around that but that idea that is really just about how
How many people won Everest how many
Paris Roxanne
So it's both
Write the data is more like stocks are the
This behavior is more like drug
Pictures of a sneaker
Is part of what you
You guys do
Wouldn't treat me
Apartment in Ewing
Crack that is very obviously
Minneapolis
Beyond
Sneakers
Explain a lot
Yet we didn't make anything
Hit like the stock market
It has been the most efficient form of Commerce for a hundred
50 years
An understanding supply and demand
Has been
Everybody would have
Would have loved to
To understand supply and demand
Any product
They sell but demand is always been a really
Hard things under
We don't have any widgets that there the brand create
But the man has been a forecast
Projection off of last year sales
You know what I hope or wish her or percentage of markings
And whatever it is
Put in the stock market
Demand is real
You know exactly how many people are willing to buy Nike
Stockx
Price
You know in NY time
And so by applying that same model
Any consumer good
By understanding demand for any consumer good
You can just create a more efficient Marketplace
And so
Any any product any consumer good that you would ask a question
What is this worth what should I pay for
That is a question
Best answer
Goodbye supply and demand
Until some of the other cat
Is that we sell today
Watches
Handbag
Streetwear collectibles
You know these are these are products that are inherently worth more
Then they're often
Released for and they become more valuable
Because they're collectors because
There there
Are scarce because of because brands
Panjiayuan market
Also works
Downside also works on discounting right so
You know we're hearing in Hong Kong and is
News quite hot
Show all winter jackets are 40% off on nike.com or whatever they are righteous some discount
Because we're off season
Why is it 40% off
If we understood demand for winter jacket
Here in Hong Kong in July
Well some people might be a temper
You can have
True variable pricing if you understood demand
And then all the sudden that that is just a more efficient way to be able to it to price those pretty
Are products in this particular
It's about this is variable
Still the market actually
Create I am thinking are there like proof
Fashionable sneakers
Speculators now do people like do this.
Just to make a living
The questionnaire implies
It's about fresh inspector is implied
It's about necessary buying a
And selling
You don't when we say the stockx
Today stock market
The things
Immediately people think about investment
Stock market
That's not necessarily the case right at the core were consumer goods
We are an evolution
All we do is connect by
Business hours for the purple
Price of buying and selling
Consumer good
Absolutely professional
Sellers
The same way that their professional sellers on eBay and some of those are your one guy
And in the basement or
Isb companies
Now the cons
Buying and selling in order to
To speculate
Make money
The evolution of the business
Is is not only allowing two people
Day trade sneakers to buy and sell sneakers
The same way that we buy and sell oil
I really do sit in a warehouse
Like that is
The logic
Extension of what we're doing
Besides crack your other co-founder you have a circle phone
Dan Gilbert
Cleveland Cavaliers
How did the three of you guys be
Idea to
What it is today
You know what Greg Schwartz is the CEO and co-founder
Who runs the business with media today has been doing
Finish last 3 years
Starting to run three other starts before
We never had a billionaire co-founder of an idea and
Attraction is quickly
But the short version of was a long story with how'd and I got together was that
Essentially dance I had the exact
See my dear indepen
And I never met him I never been in
Detroit
Cavs game
I believe this idea around the stock market
For sneakers and for me it was very ground up I got the sneakers on my life
And I had this
The campus that was around
The value of
Sneakers
Dan was sort of coming out from the office
Candle which was the stock market
Dance over for years and I literally can't get him to wear sneakers right
But that's okay right Janet seen this sort of this idea from the stock market side and enter
You know what a Fantasy fishing
Markesan said wolf
Why can't we buy consumer goods
The same way that we buy or sell
And then he saw a 15 year old son buying and selling
Speakers on eBay in 2015 like every other fifteen-year-old kid took a closer look at that so you know what that's a pretty crappy market leader
Would that be a perfect
Start stockmar
Greg was running another startup Within danzico
System in Detroit
And Dan Gregor
Danipro scratches inhalers and I had this idea let's create a stock market
Sneakers in
Will those guys to know anything
What sneakers but if
Dan Gilbert
Build a business together then you don't take that call
Those guys
Started that business they get a week into it relies will man we need a sticker guy
Who's the sneaker guys
Sneaker stock market
Do some research they found campus they found
My work around
Docker data
We got together and
And then we realize that you don't
Also trying to build
Start a three other companies that work Friday and it wasn't random guy so
It was a pretty crazy in the serendipitous way that that we got together but it's been a pretty great
Situation for Greg and I
To to just sit there and have somebody that really understood the bigger idea and and I have the resources
They want to just
Just run the business
It's not worried about the rest of it
And then
How old is Scott
Cutler your new CEO
It's in the bag
We lost this
On February 8th 20
That's when we start working on December before February
916 stock
X goes live
February 10th
16 I got a email through Linkedin
From a guy named Scott Cutler
Who at the time was the co-star
EBay own StubHub
The time eBay was our largest matter
The time eBay was the largest market
I like man
But you did come after us
This quickly like what is going on
But the reality was he before Scott was at StubHub
He was
One of the leaders of the New York Stock
Just got email bases Hey listen you know I'm at StubHub
You understand marketplaces I was at the New York Stock Exchange in a sentence
I get what you're doing I understand why
A stock
Things is a better model I would love to help I'd love to be involved
But we bet it's got to no end cuz we're Wireless
Why is he no like
He was really understand about an honest
He has like the exact his background is exactly what we are and then he end up going and working eBay but like
Like fuel Marketplace ticketing
You know that whole wide world and then that the stock
Market so
Stop behaving investor in the very first round and became for Greg and I one of our closest advisers over the past
Couple years
In and just helping
Think through the business and we never
Bracket we never really thought that we would be this
Biggest quickly that we could
We can get someone likes
Scott m winscott
I was thinking about leaving eBay a couple months ago
I said hold on hold on don't go do anything else like let's talk about this
Then let's figure it out it was
Is very not unlike MTG gain a very sort of serendipitous opportunity came out we weren't looking for a new CEO
But it was sort of the perfect marriage and so you'll be announced everything a couple weeks ago and it's been pretty awesome too
It happened here movie
Borden
Frankly I mean
I I take nine other CEOs none of the people like Scotty
800 in
20 some people and it's
Still Desir everybody's still doing 7 Jobs still like when were you know three guys in the garage and end
And that's the fun part of it also
It it's all about great people so it's exciting have Scott here to move forward
Everyone is based in Detroit
And I just started operation
In Europe
What's it like to do buildings
Global business
Troydan
I was at first convention
With Europe
What's Oxbridge
It will look at as you know as well as anyone right to be a global
Company produces Global Marketplace in 2018 you need to get
Action of local market
Susannah collection local is
So
When we turned on the website in in February 20th
16 everyone in the world
Most places walking by yourself
From stockx
We have local operations local
Teams local marketing logo
Customer service local
Shipping
And so we
Put our first team on the ground in London and Q4 of 2018
And I have been slowly building that team
There's a close to 30 people now in London including both it
A-Team
Visiting but also an operation
Facility where we authenticate all the products
Local payment methods
Look marketing local
Operations log
Local shipping
We just rolled out
Italian or first local language about 2 weeks ago and we'll start your other European languages
And then we get to do more local payment methods and then behind local look by sight
Then it's localized marketing look like customer service and everything else because
You don't get to work for
When to sell the products everybody wants what we need to go to
The crate that you know very easy local experience so that everyone can buy it
How they want to buy products and get products
Forecaster in
And more efficiently and more economical
So in other words you have a very
Google
Customer base
I would assume
Yeah one of those interesting things as we've been traveling the world in and you know we have a team now in Tokyo and then
And we've been super Fortune
Can we get to do a lot of press
One of the first
First questions in almost every reporter ask
Me and I'm in any local market is
What are the differences in taste
Is your weather differences in products
Send n the answer is at the top
Nothing
It's it's all the same it's Nike Louis Vuitton Yeezys
Supreme your Rolex off white
At the top now you have a long tail with different tastes in different markets
It's but like for what we sell nose product
It is all the
Club lit
And so then we get to be the ones
The figure out how do you take that global
Supply
And make it available locally official
Why is that
Who are the two
This is yo it's Michael Jordan it's kinda it's
It's Virgil abloh is it you don't even like we're going to get we get to draft on
On the back of the most iconic brands
In the world
And you know that's just really a function of the
The products that we sell
And the brands are created scarce around these products
And let you know if there's one word for stockx it's about
It's about creating apps
For consumers who either
Didn't know where to buy this product
Or
Or knew where to buy it but when asleep outside of sneaker store for 3 days
Or you know
Didn't know how to Wade through eBay or knew how to use eBay but didn't know it was real or newest real within the what a fair price was all these things
Which made buying these products
Inherently difficult and a lot of friction
We provide
Just pay taxes for those products
That people want and so
It's great I love the fact that you know
Louis Vuitton and Nike do our marketing for us
Stockx started
With only snake
And now entering
Handbag streetwear and watches
It comes with a layer of
Protection and validity by its verification model that is necessary
Today given the
Prevalent prevalent
So how do you balance scaling up the volume
In your platform at the same time provide the verification process
Yeah I love that we didn't start with authentication because
It is
We got a lot of value
Out of all time
There's no question
Every single product that we sell
Pastor one of our now five
Detroit Tempe Arizona New York London and end now I know that in the Netherlands
I'm sure we'll have a
At least one or two in Asia very soon probably have another one in the US
And there's a massive amount of body that because there are a lot of fake products out there and if you're 14 year old kid and you could care less what a bitter and ask
Kaiser what's means you know you're never going to get a fake pair of Yeezys
There's Mass
Asset value there
But you're not on like sneakers being somewhat of a red herring because we're about a lot more than sneakers
Authentication really just is
Facilitate the larger model it's almost just the ante to play
It at this point
Set about the stock market model
What about this
This model built on how the stock market works
And if someone isn't 100% certain that what they're going to get his real it changed their perception
Value
If your seller
You think you're going to get a scam chargeback
Did someone said you saw today
It changes how much you want to sell some
Nike stock on the New York Stock
Change your voice
Like if you thought you were going to fix your stock like it would change everything
For us it's just part of of the larger model
And look even when Nike and Adidas have a chip every shoe and every kid with a napkin authenticate every
Product
We will still stay
Stan Mill that transaction we will
Still run that same process
Because it's about the law
It would be easier quicker
Refers to do that
Speaking of
A few big names
Eminem
Mark Wahlberg
And others
No parking private company is
Chevrolet what's it like to get a move on
And
That's not help your business
Yet you not unlike you know how it how you and I first met
We created
A venue for some of those folks to invest because they were already helping us
We never
Never started this business thinking we were going to go out and get the most famous people in the world involvement in this
Business
It happens
Soup organically the first one was was Mark with Mark Wahlberg
We're in a meeting really early on with Dan and it somehow just randomly came out that Mark Wahlberg wears a lot of Air Jordan
And that is why I don't bark
An hour later on email chain with Dan and Mark 2 days later in Calif
Tony at Mark's house going through a sneaker closet he's like oh we should put these on stockx
And then you know a couple weeks later something very similar happened around with Eminem and Eminem's manager Paul Rosa
Bergen you know they're both from Detroit and Paul was in the office
Working with with people in in on Detroit things
And it was also a very organic thing that that we came in contact
And they were helping us so we created that first round
I know we could get those guys
Uno the Great
Diary
You know a $10,000 check to Eminem doesn't really you don't move the needle
So that was the beginning of it and then it was a sort of organic growth around as we
Came to contact with other people and dumb and we've been super fortunate we get a lot of people that are interested
Because the product
Because of Dan because the NBA
But we get
How to choose those people that are generally in it for the right reason and who can have your value
Eminem
Coach you are you look like
You know the first person
That ever told me that
The first person that ever told me I look like I was Eminem
Which was really funny there's that
Is a scene in this video that that we shot
Where I say you know I'm here with Eminem to pick up shoes for the charity auction and
Eminem goes
I'm here
Person asking when I met
Josh of the First Tee of
This is the first time
I actually would be
Streetwear is
Less
Globo and
More local because of the ink
If you think about
Search who are in the US
You know what people are
Chasing after braces
In China
It's quite individualized
So what do you say
Get so
Streetwear just gets the long tail lock
Supreme like Supreme is the Nike of streetwear right and so at the top everybody wants Supreme
Underneath that there's a couple other brands that aren't aren't nearly as big but have you know babe
Which is a bathing Ape from Japan
And then there's a few other brand Palace
I meant it just gets the long tail a lot lot lot
But very top
Like that's just that it's just
The clear leader it is
I I forgot about the time I had the exact number but it is overwhelming majority of our street our business
Terms of dollars
And units
Suspended Supreme
It in China
Pretty obvious
That do a nice ass
And several others
While trying to be in the space
And you can tell what it is a
Growing fan base
Sports for speakers
The consumer level and it's much bigger
Annies
So much because people thought because
The end result of this
Is
Actually
A convergence
The primary and secondary Market
Together to just be one market
Right and we always people always ask what's the resale Market how big is it us we think it's maybe
Around 2 billion
Probably maybe it's 7 8 billion and growing
The global retail Market is 100 billion +
It's the whole thing
And for our growth is
Is about like that next customer that retail
Customers about their last
Footlocker nike.com
That never would have tried to wait
EBay 3 years ago
Because you got walking to Footlocker and there's
300 400 pairs of shoes on the wall
A6000 differ
Track shoes on stockx
Just be you know a hundred dollar shoe that's a
Colorway
It's on the wall at Footlocker and it's selling on stockx for 110 or or 95 right
25% of our business
Actually left
Then retail price
And it's that it's that long tail of just abs
Product is out there
And that's why it's a convergence of all of this that are real
For sneak and this is just sneakers
And it's not too bad
Illinois
Four singers that the brands
Most of our base
Designer started in the US
What kind of
What relationship do you
4C
With them
Open up the sneaker brands in and even you know the streetwear brands and and Luxury Inn and everywhere else
All converging the same place which is you know
Ultimately two to work together
The best example of where this all goes is what happened
So
10-15 years ago
Teams and leagues were wrecked
Ticket scalpers
Ticket websites today official resale Marketplace in Major League Baseball
Other teams in other leagues
You know when other taking website started to pair up in and now step up as
Primary ticket
Got the Sixers the Yankees and a few other teams Naruto what they've done is they've basically created one market
One Market that's what the stock market
Enterprise
That's the evolution
Is to work with Nike to work with Adidas to work with
You know the street or Brands to release product directly into the
To literally
IPO products
Initial
We've done some of these and and stay tuned like in the next
Three to four months
Another half-a-dozen IPOs coming
With brandy
Including some really big sneaker brands
This where you get to a point where
Disappear this line between read
Tell Reese other just one market about those brands
You're engaging with us and with the secondary Market saheila
You know you guys have
Wework website traffic
Foot Locker
We have more customers than than most any Sneaker Boutique or sneaker retailer so it's an evolution and na
Inevitable Evolution that we all end up
Working together global
And lumps globally
The other side of the equation
Emissions
So overtime how would the
Online
Commerce
Interact with
Offline
Store
Just so you know we just opened our first brick-and-mortar location in SoHo in New York about two blocks south of
Love Supreme on Lafayette and
I was careful to say brick-and-mortar not retail cuz we don't sell anything
Whereoware Market
The primary purpose of that Loki
Station is for seller drop off
4 Cellars who've already sold
Something on stockx to come in and drop it off we authenticate in the back of the sea
Store so someone can get paid out much quicker
And then we can have that product can get it
Okay but the evolution of that
Beijing sanlitun
We've done pop-up locations in
London la
Chicago Atlanta and will continue to do more in
More permanent
Devolution it's about bread
But having a
The brand experience on the ground in these locations
And where you know sneaker culture to our culture and our
Customers are
Really
Favorable situation to beware
I don't have to rely on on
Brick-and-mortar sales
In order to to pay the bills
And once you do that
And think about it from a brand standpoint and you can be more creative you can take rest you can have it all a lot more fun in in
I'm doing that knowing that
The Core Business
Is it online
This is how you
Movies I've seen in
Japan Inn
Korea Taiwan
China
It's how you can go to offline store
Use QR code
Skyrim buy something
You don't have to
Take it with you
Ship your house
Later so you don't have to touch anything
The scan
Haywood Mobile Wallet
Extremely
Easy in French
Also it's a
Phenomenal
Example of consumer Behavior because
Because for us what happens is
Open the first pop up
Yeah we only had people that were
Working the pop-up authenticators intake
Not very quickly realize
Did the most valuable people to have on-site
Uber customer service
And a half people there that could answer those questions that we used to come in via email or chat
And if you would explain it so that I could buy
And that
What is massively powerful cuz it leads to exactly what you do
You sit there in the shop on their phone or otherwise had questions and had friction around using the product
And now I can do that in the prodigal show up at their house y'all in a couple days
Exhaust
Why eBay isn't
Yeah I mean
EBay
Great and will always be great for that like long tail product
Right you want to find some unique one-of-a-kind item eBay has as
What's the scale for that put the eBay model
Is is antiquated
Right I mean Thursday there's no catalog bases there's no structure data
And they can't
To implement this
Is 4 even just a core reason right if you will look for that the shoes I'm wearing right now on eBay you will get
Zen music
Have to figure out
This person that personalizes
600 yd
800 yuan how many views has person have visor cap
All that stuff is nonsense
Is confusing you go on stockx
There's one
Product
That promise you will buy share of Nike stock there's one ticker symbol for Nike stock and everything happens at the
That one place
Is this the standardization to be able to have
You don't single product page
Catalog base
Experience
That eBay would literally have to
How to create an entire new
Rebuild an entire site
To do that so
You know we're not connect
Concerned about someone like eBay coming in
Replicating what we're doing as much as we would be more concerned about someone building something
Scratch
And then competing with us somewhere that were not with it at
Geographical your dick
Products
Every single thing that we've done
Is infiltration of that model
In and how we handle payments and how we handle shipping
Indica
Experience
And the man with great is
Is it taking a while
But every one of those things builds moat around the business because like you have to
To be fully committed to that model
In every way that you go the product to be able
Actually do that and so
Got reaction
Intent to that question
Like you know eBay is probably the last
Can replicate
NBA
Book off
Ground Zero
New China 2
What is today
It's not hard with sassy stock
Doing well in China
What are you playing
That we got in China
You already have
If 15% of your boy
Coming from China
So it's early indicator
Something big
Yet there are also local competitors
Players
RV sites
So how do you think
Chinese market
Yeah yeah this is
It is the price of the most
Important question for us right now
In terms of our short and medium-term strategy
China is
Is maybe the only
Sing the We don't know exactly what
What we're doing and we're still exploring a lot of different options because there are
Very formidable you know marketplaces on the ground in China
First sneakers
But we have this
Supply and there's a really unique
Distinction between
You got that what what has
What happened in the past
Marketplaces in in US companies coming to China
Versus this scenario where we have the supply that
Because most
It comes in the market
For sellers are
Pentofrost we have some some big decisions to make
Quickly around
Who do we partner with
Could we try to compete with
And where do we set up those
Those teams in those operations
I mentioned earlier
100% of a bottleneck
Every part of this
Just people
Here's here as well right
We still need to hire you know great leader for
For China but also for it for all of us
And build a local team in weather that local
What team sits in Hong Kong or Singapore or mainland China
And then where is the operations team sit when we authenticate products that sit
And either those food three places or somewhere else like those the key question
Oceans and then it's at the function of you who do you work with here do you work with one of the existing sneaker marketplaces
And partner with them
Do you compete with them do you work with one of the big players the Baba's rjd's
And so those are the all the different order
Decision points that were in the middle of of determine right now
I mean like I said everywhere else that we were really Clear Vision of of Haddix
Did you do this
In the short medium term and manager
Show me different option
For how we can do this knowing that 15% of our business is already
Here
There was a couple weeks ago
Christopher Ward shoe and all the sudden it was the biggest shoe on stockx
The impact
So so clean
You know over Chinese New Year
There was a shoe this is the best story there was a shoe it's called
Air Jordan 1 mid
This is a shoe that is
Discount
Nobody
Us where is it
But there was a black
Gold colorway of the Jordan 1 mid
Did during Chinese New Year
We can the number one selling shoe on stockx
For like 2 weeks
Because it was black and gold it was because it was during Chinese New Year
And some celebrities born in all the sudden
And all the US Dollars figured out they were all going to finish line
Buying it on sale I mean
It is so clear the impact
At the China and so we really you know it's important for us to
How to figure out the right way to do it
I was on YouTube last night and there's actually
A tutorial on how to buy
Sneakers from stockx
YouTube
Sandy has
We don't like we don't have local language
We just rolled out of town and I will continue to roll out European languages but obviously
Located
What is your local payment methods we have to do in a process
I'm doing it then the biggest
Questions around who do you partner
Figure it out but yeah
So what do you say to sneakerheads
Who's this to you
Having a stock market
For something that we love is
Kind of ruining
The fun
Define destiny
Yeah it is
So is right like this idea that you can like go fine like great sneakers for like a d or like this
Cover them like you just it it doesn't exist anymore
In the midnight
And he's there was a guy whose name is bobbito Garcia and he wrote a book
Games where the Seminole Sneakerhead Bible
In the midnight
In the title of the book was
Where'd you get those
Where'd you get those that used to be the seminal Quest
Nobody asked
A question anymore we have the internet we know where to get everything we know when everything's coming out and where is being released now
Can we get it can we physically be able to get it no because we're not willing to sleep outside of a sneaker store for 3 days
We don't know the manager of the store but it's
All the game
Like that idea
Vigo yeah there's a community we could all
I like that doesn't exist anymore until we've done is just we've created access
Grandparents year-round would it become
A very fragmented
Aiden and Messi
Did it just hard for anyone to be able to play unless they really really have you know that
Inside baseball opportunity
And I
AHS
So another words sneaker has nowadays actually really appreciate what you're doing
Yeah well
They certainly have voted with their
Wallets right
I mean we are PS4 again
Yeah
Yeah I mean
That way between FBS scoreboard
Just that dumbass
Growthwright like what
About awareness
Right
This just an easier way to be able to buy any product
And that's also attended a what
What someone what what
What consumers want
I really
Interesting conversation last night at dinner with a woman who said listen
Sustainability
But
For consumer goods
People on SOA vote with their
With their wallets
Sustainability voter on
Access price
Yelizaveta purchase
And like that's what
The stock market model creates for
So as a serial
Do you have
You know one piece of advice that you want to
Pass it on to other
Yeah so I have two related please advise that I sort of always using here and there the most basic
But they're like
It's so important to the first is his talk to everybody
Don't think someone's going to steal your idea or show up with an NDA.
To talk to someone like
The refinement of those ideas and find those people to work with like it's just important get out there and just talked to everybody
But everything
And then secondly is like
I just do something
Like that the idea that you have to have this perfect idea or perfect plan you know is is Judge
Is completely like a lot
I could never in a million years have
Predicted or planned
To meet
You know one of the most successful busy
People in the world Dan Gilbert and that he would have the exact
Name ideas
And like I didn't know that
The one I was creating campus when I was like going through like millions of rows of Excel spreadsheet to it to clean all this eBay Dayton Builder
Guy or something there we had to be just be doing something
Push that Ford
Those
Those things going to ultimately you
Put me in a position to meet the Anna be able to do that until it's you don't talk to everybody about everything and then and just do some
Credit-wise
I'm so we're going to jump into the last part of the podcast which is about Rhonda
Quick fire questions
Okay just say the first thing
Reminder
Can you give us some Pro tips for shopping on stockx
Insider
Have been
DMVs are by far the most
Daiwa parts of the whole
System almost everything I buy on stockx is I have a
Bit out there that's a beacon to the world let someone know that I'm on
The buy this
Prada
Enzo by understanding how to use bids like that
That just so much data to someone different parts of
The product of business
But the Holy Grail evolve it is bit
Who's the entrepreneur you admire them
Oh man
You know what I'm not going to answer
I don't want to
Put a spotlight on
Person but I've met multiple
A different people different times that really inspired me and help me you know along the way I've never had really like
One Mentor
Different people at different
Different times of help in a where I was and that and that is almost always been
So much more that has been
234 steps ahead in my journey it's not
Me to Steve Jobs at City
Who's the guy that they built
The company that was had
You know
Three times too much track
My company's balance those are the people that have been most helpful
Brenna
What's something that you have read recently that you would recommend
Have read
The only thing I read anymore is my email
But I'm in the process of actually listening on audiobook
220 Bobby hundreds book
Which is called this is not a T-shirt and Bobby
Hundreds was one of the founders of the streetwear brand the hundreds in one of these really
Should have like OG original streetwear brands
It started you don't back
Back in like the early
Mm mm
Three I think so
To be around 6
15 years in that game
And it's a really good story of
The evolution of
The culture of our customer
And the culture of supply and demand
And an end streetwear and how it's all grown
And
Yeah so anyway that that's what I'm currently listening to and it's awesome and it's you know it's just a really really great story
A really successful business that was ever a billionaire
Business but it
Been going on for 16 years in an industry that it didn't
And so
I'm a big fan of
Of what
What he wrote
What's a habit that you have
That you think changed your life
Eden essay change your life in a good way right
Is that open for purple
I'll tell you what it what really it is and it it cuts both ways which is
I don't really sleep
How much anymore
Usually about 4 hours a night I usually go to bed between 6
Yeah yeah yeah
Yeah what happened is a bigger the company
Became the more what was going on
The last time you have to do any real work during the day until I come home
My kids bad my wife go to bed
And from 10 p.m. to 2 a.m. from 10 p.m. to 3 a.m.
And like to work
And all the sudden like my my suit sketch
It was pretty horrible so it's it's
It's My Life positively in the business
Certainly not necessarily healthy and at some point we'll have to figure out to get more sleep but you never
Plan that you just stay at 5 minutes
Later every night and then all the sudden
Yeah you're going to bed at
For I am but it's because
There's just so much like amazing
What to do when it's just so
You know you're running
We're Global business
On this side of the world
Is so much harder just
It would like by the time I'm trying to go to bed then emails and everything else but yeah
Hans can tell you how to
Asleep on the plane about that
Sit on a plane and you know whatever
Yes I'm sitting here
With Katie run PR forever stockx
Is Austin very embarrassed for the different places I can still sleep
So what do you do when your stress
I don't know I don't act like I don't really feel like stress as much as like
Frustration frustration with with
Your inability to be able to you know control certain things right
I like I'm just not worried about like I'm just not worried about failure I'm not worried about that you know like my my stresses
My frustration really comes around
You know like not being home
For my kids in the end that's where
Stop right so
Yeah you deal with that in different ways whether it's FaceTime or whether it's cancel
Sing a trip to be home in like those is where things
Like that that's the flip side of evolved
Strike witches
Yeah my daughter is almost 7 my son is 4
And then it's amazing to be able to have these.
To travel around the world
But then the flip side
What would you like to meet the LeBron James foot
You know I don't really have the best
So as far as
Yet so
It took a minute for LeBron
Two seat
Through you know that I wasn't sure just like dance guy in stockx
You got that end
But we have done this
Where
Temperature
And we did a release with Nike
He gave us
LeBron James
First retro sneakers
Create a sneaker box
Out of wood from the Cavaliers
Championship Court
Caught up the court
And I mean clear my search thing I remember
Championship ring in the Box the first time ever met LeBron when
Act that it already
What happened
And then
His like it was like
This is knit reaction
Was you know
Good morning positive
But then he's like always like you did that with the bike that was great and we talked about the project for a while and then
Country the project
What's your favorite pair of sneakers
Did changes everyday but the
The shoe that I have the most of is
She called The Air Jordan 1
Lance Mountain white is a collaboration
Skateboard Lance Mountain end in Air Jordan
And I have seven pairs
I think I almost died
The math of it that would
Have you ever met
Michael Jordan
I have never met Michael Jordan in person but I have been on now
Conference calls
With him all three of which have been me
Pitching
Stockx to him as
You know that the leader of Jordan
And I know both of his sons really well
I think it helped that it was on a conference call and not in person right
He was
Super fashionable knowledgeable of like what we're doing and all that but
Beethoven said
Thanks for being on the show Josh we really enjoyed it
Airline flight 798
M996 is a multi-stage venture capital firm based in Silicon Valley
Singapore Shanghai and Beijing
We have been partnering with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past 18 years from seed to.
What's 6.2 billion dollars in capital in our management across certain funds
Ggb invest in consumer new retail social digital and internet Enterprise cloud
Loud and from to attack
Ggb has invested in / 290 companies with more than 45 valued at over a billion
$10 include Airbnb Alibaba
Bident to trip Didi chuxing hashicorp Hollow Pike house
Keep slack Square
Wish shopping shoe white and others find out more at ggvc. Com
Any feedback on this podcast or would like to recommend a gas please email us at 996 at GGC