Everyone before we begin I just wanted to remind you that we have
Create a WeChat group
Blac Chyna
For you are list
This is a community of P
People brought together by their shared entry
In China
Through this group
What's our listeners have made friends
Recruited team members
And found clients
We also organize regular offline meetups for this
We had a meet-up in Beijing last month
And we'll be having another way in summer
Cisco on Thursday July
Details for the
Please meetups
Will be announced in a
To join the group
Please go to 996
. GGG
Si.com
Slash coming
And follow the
Again that's 996.
Ggbc
Jd.com
Splash coming
Welcome to the 9s sixpack
Brought to you by Gigi
BB capital
On the show
We interview movers and shakers
China's tech industry
As well as Tech leaders
Weather us
China
Cross-border first
My name is Khan song
I'm a managing partner at
Gdb capital
And I've been working at startup
Invest
Emblem in Boston USA
A China for
My name is Sarah Jeong
I meant investment analyst igb capital
And a former journalist
Why is the show called 96
6 is the work schedule that many Chinese Founders have organically adopted
That is
9 a.m. to 9 p.m.
6 days a week
To us
Intensity
Drive
Wind speed
Of Chinese internet
Mannywood
I'm moving fast
But even their Mercy
Counterparts
Imma show today
We have Justin call
He co-founded Justin. TV
The website allow anyone to broadcast video online
In 2011
Justin TV
Spell of its gaming division
Ostrich
Which as many people that went on to become the leading
Live streaming platform
Computer games
Any us any else
Which was acquired by Amazon 2014 41 billion dollars
More recently dusting cliff on the atrium LTS
NLCS stands for legal
Neurology services
It is startup that's building technology
To revolutionize
30 Gordon Street
Ngdv fortunately is a
A buster
Justin is a true started veteran
In addition to starting multiple companies of his own
He's also work with hundreds of them as a partner at y combinator
And has also personally enjoy invested in many of them
Justin Grubb in Seattle as a Chinese American
Graduated from Yale with degrees in physics and philosophy
Welcome to the show Justin
Thanks for having me guys
I am
Excited
So I start with live streaming
I think your ears sort of the original livestream ru
What make holiday in 2007 you and your partner started
Justin. TV or 24/7 live video feed off your life
Broadcast via webcam attached to your head
And your lack housing lost about eight months in a trifle out of attention
So what inspired you to broadcast your live at a time when this concept didn't even exist
It was just a crazy idea
A random
Pretty bad idea actually at the time although I think we're onto a nugget of something popular
Yo Justin.tv was before Twitter or in
Instagram or Facebook being you know popular
That it was before
The Kardashians
Yeah there was before Instagram celebrity so
The result is a bachelor and that kind of show
Yeah there was a reality but there was no like
Real reality like
I'm taking you along on my life and we thought
That would be interesting
Tried taking someone Along on this
Journey of your life
Could be interesting and then
The attention could make somebody a celebrity
Unfortunately
I am not very entertaining
Until I was a very poor Teske's right you know we should have gotten
Probably someone was more of an actor played some more attractive than me maybe someone
The musician
Some with some talents but instead when people came to Justin TV which was a 24/7
Live show about
Myself and my co-founders
They saw four guys sitting in apartment
Programming
Did you change my name to do more like entertainment stuff but it really fell back into like mostly trying to keep our website up
And so
Literally
Programming is not interesting
Watch it cuz
Watching someone
Program it looks a lot like watching someone write an essay or watching someone
Yeah like
Budget YouTube video play video game play Starcraft so it was entertaining right the video of the person itself
Was not that into
We tried to run around the city
Unfortunately there's a lot of downtime technology wasn't quite there yet it was like right on the border
There's no iPhone
We tried to launch it so it was the end of it so fast
A mobile internet connection so actually
We headed Upstream together multiple modems
From a different providers
Under one computer and then
Sending the video
Multiplexing it over multiple
Cell phone connect
And that's how we
I were able to create this life
Extreme back in 2000
What was the phone
The first thing that
What was the first product Market fit.
Right so what happened was we launched the show and we thought we were like so cool
Bunch of people came because of
They thought
This is like a real life
Truman Show at HEB
Udo now of course it would be so we're back that before like why do you want to put video on the internet tonight Cavalier life that is soup
Super weird
So is this big media phenomenon and then we got interviewed by the
Today Show on MTV
People, that you're on a computer like this boring
What are you doing
And then luckily they would come and they would ask us like how are you making a livestream on the internet presence is not
Technology that existed
So we built a platform like YouTube for live video
And that
Is one we would want that about
6 months later
You know we had a lot to show and then
That's when it really took off
That's the product I used
Right see how they use that TV back then right
A lot of people thought I was just
In TV live
But no is named after a guy found out that way
Yourself
It was going to go out and become so big
Launch a whole category or
Did you just do it for
Okay so for the show itself
We thought
They could be a crazy idea maybe we'll be back who knows you have no idea how big it would be
But for the site
YouTube for live video
We thought that could be big I mean YouTube had already sold for in a 1.6 or 1.7 billion dollars you like that. So
There was an idea that video online could be valuable
Rights
So it wasn't that
Sweet. It to be applied
Yeah couple years we were like 20 million Mau
All that popcorn
Can you tell us a story of how twitch became a spin-off of Justin. TV
Shirt so you don't fast for Leo
October 2007
You know her Ray and technically it was
A pretty big achievement for us because we had figured out how to you
Nothing worth back then the flash media server like tinworth like streaming was very much more difficult
Do I install plug-in stuff like that
As we watch this site
Atlantic
Cut cigar for the next couple years between 2000
Ana 2007
Do the early 2008 all the way through
Hot rod 2010
It done really well and
Celebrity started live streaming there is other content on your people like
Also different content Sports entertainment
Talk shows
And
Then it just stopped growing
Because it turns out
Actually not all content is
Good life only a very few kinds of content are good lighting most content you want is like a VOD rather video
So then we were like we need to figure something out because anything that's not growing on the Internet is
Is about to fall off a cliff
Breaks the internet
So we decided
Okay let's
Go back to the drawing board and figure out something that we think we can invest in that could
Potentially be
Bigger than what we have right now
And so we looked at what we're doing and there were a couple ideas we had one was around mobile video
I like Periscope actually but
Several years earlier than her scope
4 years earlier
And then
The other was
The gaming channel there was like a small gaming
Section right on our site like
3% of the sideways people watching other people play video game
And we were like
Why are people doing this
Actually be interesting thing was back when we had our own show
3 years earlier
Maybe three and a half years earlier
We had plugged in at one point I remember I was
Reminder to this
But my friend Steve Hopper
When is a co-founder Reddit
Steve and I have been hanging out
You know the early days of the showing
Plugged in the camera
We like an analog cameras we have to plug it into the Xbox
And we were like broadcasting ourselves playing Xbox
Locksmith and people like that
Unfortunately we didn't figure it out until like way later
But you know back then mm
10 what happened with people start streaming
Gaming content and we
Decided let's go with this
And try to make this a thing
We think this can be bigger than
Existing site
Because it seemed like engagement was high one of my co-founders
Emmett is the
See your Twitch today really thought
This could be something it was
Is the temperature
If you liked
And so
Weed
Decided to build stops him around it
Focusing on the product
What's your address again that
And so
Long story short after about
Six months of working on it we said hey is really working
It's called the Jets
TV gaming
Channel 11 weather
Change name in twitch
And then wash it as a
So excited that
I just start taking off
Put was the
Rite soda
We were debating on the name
I remember I really like
Some like four letter acronym no smell like ESPN right hardwood pad like X
Rge
TV or something like that
How do you remember what it was actually
And it would like
There's absolutely no way we're going to do that and then he had
This idea of calling it
Zarf
What is X x a r t h
On the way
Your purchase of a lightning rod for like
Couple thousand dollars
And then
That was the name of the place holder name
Without the process secret project name or whatever is Rita's on the signs up and sew
He's going to call it.
And then
A few days
Before launch
He found
The site
Twitch.tv
And he was like the twitch like I like fast twitch muscles you know twitch nip
Sounded like gaming like any other like we going with switch
Dell at that point
Everyone had argued so much I think
You just like
Okay what am I whenever you want how are you making money for your
Original live
Streaming products
Yeah so the original Justin.tv was very advertising
Supported and it was all
Got pre-rolls the wheels had this cool thing that were like
Midrolls that the broadcaster could trigger
So if you were doing Up Your Life podcast
Something to take a bathroom break
The trigger advertisement
And I go to the bathroom
Bryson tiller
We thought that was like
What is a huge innovation
Which was at the time actually
And
Install thing today at twitch
But not true
Which is more more kind of like the
Eaton sites like the Chinese
User donations is
Virtual Goods
You guys have for co-founders
That's right
Oracle founder
Ryan to how do you figure out how to make this a
That's a great question
We made decisions incredibly poorly
That sounds like a joke but it's not a joke that sounds like a joke but it
It's really not a joke
The funny thing is that you
Probably lots of talk about an hour
Affected
Mike subsequent companies or like Atrium today we had a lot of co-founders but
Back then we didn't know anything I mean you're talking about
These are for 22 year old guys
Who started the company when they let you know
We didn't we didn't know anything about me
Nobody had ever work at a real job.
Michael
Who was the first
CEO had actually worked at a job but it was a political campaign and you can imagine that they don't have the
Best management structure or training right Sophia for guys and we got together and
We were just like okay what we made all the important Decisions by arguing
Who is
It was a CTO Kyle was the VP engineering
Michael was the CEO and I was the like I had a product basically that she
Product officer
But
We kind of made every important
Decision together
That is
Not a good way to do things you need to trust
I need to delegate
People have the right
But we didn't do that because I think we didn't really figure out how to
Do that until we really pivoted
Twitch
And we also incubated this other project also can we couldn't even decide what to do. We don't want to put it on Friday we put it into two things
Socialcam
And which eventually spun out we sold it
Do Autodesk
460 million dollars
But that is a defies All Odds for type of thing right through all the mistakes you made
I mean
Two of them but
This is not a good way to run things everybody going off on their own in order to
Have their own domain right
Which is sad because I think we were right inside a lot of
Always great team but it's not sad because everybody is well and
Cobra Kai lined up starting a company with my brother yeah
Cruise automation that
Is doing self-driving cars and
I met him before
Was a bit too early for like little cows interesting
But that they were too smart for her own good that's amazing
That's amazing
Seoul Sausage
And then you don't I don't know if you saw that
2 billion dollars Airsoft
EXO incredible story
So truly there was a lot of talent and is one organization town
But
Took a little time to mature
Right until like leadership I would
So why why did you still have so many co-founders before your current company if that didn't work out before
It did work out
It didn't work out but now I have there's a lot more
Delegation and ownership of specific role soap
Yeah we've co-founders
2ct oval hazard
I'd like to really in charge attack I'm not like
Micromanagement
Do this technical
Decision of this product
We are co-founders in charge of the legal side
Really in charge of the legal I'm not
I don't actually even know
Certain things about our legal like who our clients are not managing at that level
It's much more about
Creating
Actual metrics of accountability and then say hey go get these metrics right and I'm going to trust and I'm going to give feedback on the resource to you
If you need feedback on your plan
But I'm going to trust
That you are handling this
Domain
Same goes where are we have a co-founder of the operation side and then one
Also out on the market
Tell me more detail
Still on Twitch I know immensely CEO
When you guys
Decide to sell the comfy
Looking Back in Time
Is amazing
Did you ever look back
And look at how
The sectors involving China and however Trident becomes
Great way to monetize
Did you ever think about how
The site could have been more
Then what it is today so I'll tell you two things
Suicide obviously could
Be more in as
Become more ripe
Because when we sold it we were 55 million Mau
And does a lot
Mike's butt
At the same time
At that level it was very hard for us to raise capital
Because you know most of the time
Did not understand
If we had talked to more probably Chinese investors actually they would have understood it
And in fact we had money from
Chinese
But comparative Sandhill investors you know they did not understand
This industry one year later they they're all work investing
Any sports or whatever
Nobody nobody understood it so we thought
970 million dollars
Tremendous amount
Because earlier that you're actually about a month ago I tried to
Sell some secondary for
At 200 million
Got a lot of decline
So we thought it was
Really good
And then afterwards obviously it's become a much
Greater success since that right so
In the year following
The acquisition all the metrics doubled
The company is like gone too and I never released I don't think very much recently answers are metrics
The company has gone to you
Almost 1500
People I believe
Now it's
San Francisco you know they're opening up there all night
Story building
It's like a tremendous
Success
And I was just looking at
Alexa
The first time in years
Number 12 website in America
So
Obviously there was a lot of Headroom unfortunately I don't think we were able to
Really convinced
Capital sources
The funding isn't
Independent company
But you know you can't be too sorry about that one interesting conversation we're having a remember during that process
Selling in 2014 over the summer
I'd like a conference call on all the board members
And everybody was like yes cell right now I think we should sell this is a great deal
And I remember
One of our board members Chris Pike formerly of driving now doing his own
Rumors
He was like no don't sell
I remember
We were all silent
On the call and I was like
Why
What do you think it could be worse
You don't because you think that this Market as like not that big of a market or maybe not
We don't know but you know it
How big could it be
And he was like I don't know 3/4 billion more
Everybody was just kind of like are you not Island they're just wanted to be like you were crazy
You are crazy but everyone was just
Everyone was just silent on the call and
And then we just start talking about something you know when you're out
I hope he listens to this I mean he was the only one who is right
Like oh we should be
It was fun though such an amazing adventure
Investor duties investor on my colleague was on the board of why
Yesterday was a
Game
Commenting
Site back in 2000
Insects
And today is a 10 billion dollar
Mobile video
Site for gamers
And it's just a
Fitness spinner
Something that's live streaming
For gaming
Dollar
Martin cab company in Baltimore
It's hard imagine
In 2006 that
For 8
As a game commenting site
It's like $39
Yeah and it's
I just so hard to believe by then.
Could be a mainstream
You can see today that
You could be bigger than
Most of the sports
Absolutely
Because everyone's playing video games
Scott there everyone's playing video games
Everyone is
My dog biting her daughter's on all the time she spent a lot more time on gaming then
I overdid on Sports when I was
Courage
Don't you see the time spent it just
Almost number one activity
For kids
Yeah that's probably not good but this could be a good programmer
Designer later
This is maybe there's something analytical writing to get gaming helps with the analytical reasoning and stuff like that so you know I definitely think it
For me when I was
The kid
Yeah teamwork there is a hardcore gamer
I was probably I was playing Counter-Strike and World of Warcraft when I went in Warcraft
3 when I was in college
Probably spent a little bit too much time playing
We still going to yell so give me all about yeah that was once I got it so I can do whatever
Drywall I can play these games you don't like I'm just exactly
So it was a
I actually did lose a lot of time
Two-player games
Justin.tv actually went down a lot cuz
I don't know what you know
I'm sure you guys expresses like it's
Business
End and start of
So interesting it's kind of like its own game
Yeah very stressful horrible game to play sometimes but but
What was they like to sell a company to Amazon
What was that process
Dislike for you
Well I didn't really do mosto
The work is that it by the time it's 2 Cor
Just on the board
And
I think for them is very stressful for any acquisition process
Is very stressful but I think he's like one of that
Actually most dis
Upland in Silicon Valley
Yeah I think a lot of other
Companies
Bigot
Caught up
Hype you know they're like
They get really caught up in like
We need this for strategic reasons
Getting Amazon out of all the
Companies
I kind of seen or like
Investments were sold whatever
He's like the most
Discipline
Mean that they won't overpay
Facebook acquired Instagram and WhatsApp because it works out it's a lot bigger
Yelp
Yeah absolutely I think that it doesn't matter how much you pay
There's two types of
Companies that are like
Good
And the ones that are like true least
Strategic
A10 like
Nnn Visionary right there making his Visionary bats
Google Facebook
And then there's like the type that are more like
Really
Disappointed
I think the people who'll really
Drug are the ones in the middle
Our kind of half and half
Ana de Luz
Important deals because they were too tight or or they are
Exactly
I forget that we're at
About 3 billion
Internet users worldwide now
If something does work
You will be my
And if it doesn't
It doesn't matter how much you pay cuz you wasted already
Mimosa glasses
Absolutely riding the world
Biggest wave. Right so
So report last year found that there is now a bigger audience for game video than audiences of HBO Netflix yes
ESPN Hulu combine
Which is kind of
Crazy to think about it
Did you imagine this will happen or were you surprised
Game streaming took off
I think we were so
Surprised how fast
Was growing the game streaming
In the early years
I doesn't surprise me though because I mean
Back in 2007 the gaming addict
Mystery past
The movie industry
I don't know if you remember that but that was like a big thing
People like
All these like entertainment people
We're like what the f*** you didn't like nobody saw that coming
Okay well you know when you do MTV Cribs
You see like every athlete has an Xbox Aerosmith that makes sense to me and so
Exactly so so I just I think it was pretty obvious that gaming videos going to be a huge thing it is already the number to category on
On YouTube by the time I started to itch and then like
One or two years and it was like the number one category on YouTube
It was not a big surprise
It's actually wouldn't be surprised if it
You know that it wouldn't happen early
In China
Gaming was already the number one monetization
Method
Big Commerce
Shut down in that he's both of those turning out games and then pissing got into it
10 years later you see tencent everywhere
From riot games
Still for that
Amazing
See how big a
So what was it like to have this whole start of Journey as an Asian-American ihoa where were you
You off your identity and did that
Change things for you anyway
That's a good question
Seattle
Speak Chinese at home
Bhai Most Wanted
School I want to price my private school
High School
Mostly white white kid
University Preparatory Academy
So I didn't feel I never like really thought that much about like identity
And like it
Ethnic identity
And then
In Silicon Valley
Adele uddo I will head that join the Chinese American students
Association are like the club
And
Uibe school
But I think is a little bit different from like a lot of people grow up in
In California the Bay Area
Something wear this like a lot
33% of something Asian-American
Chinese
And so
I think is a little different
In the industry I didn't think that there were
It didn't feel like
You know with my YC Network or whatever that there were like not that many
Asian American Founders although I think actually if you look at assets
Statistically there was that message
Translate 10% to Wifey but it felt like it was like 30% of icma or something like that so
Whatever I did I didn't I didn't believe
Feel like it
Change things very much
Stop motion first reaction
When you went to China
Well so the for the last time I went to China
It was
So when I went to China 2000
About to open the
The biggest damn right
The Three Gorges Dam and I was I was like did the cruise down the thing and it was like rule
I was like China is like
Best farming world
Super early and then I went back last
Year in December or not last year 2016
Oh my God oh my God this is crazy
This is different world altogether
And I feel that way a little bit because I'm not taking that many frequent trips to Asia
Probably going once a year but two different place you know so I'll go
To Jakarta or
Singapore
And
It's amazing how all these places are I'd like
Garufa structure than America
Better
Play taller building Saigon more buildings like
It's crazy
Worst traffic
But yeah they like world's changed so much
I think it's super interesting
What's the climate nature were better at removing
London when throwing knives
Tokyo went through 1960s it'll get better but it takes.
It's all blown away
And
Blown away also by the work ethic
Can an innovation that's happening in anyone
Yeah I think it's pretty obvious now I guess
2016 I think
People
There's a little bit of questions but like
If you came to America
And that's one like a lot of
Chinese investors start investing in
In Silicon Valley
Like what what is this money coming from what's going on or whatever
But if you told you as an investors are founders like The Innovation design
Play coming in from China
Feel so you got me
Yeah exactly
You got to be kidding me now
You see obviously like the dockless
Transportation models
Coming here
You don't like a lot of innovation is happening in in
In China is just so much
Like I didn't
Kind of balance of innovation to shift
Pretty rapidly
Should be pretty scary if you are
An American
You know who is Patriot and you should be a little scared
At the same time you know we're making it
We will be taking a lot of things for Grant
I think we take like immigration of skilled
Labor rate for Grants
Like we should be trying to
Get every single
Engineer from around the world
Want to live here to stay here
We should be giving taco
Exactly
You know because we're talking about you just look at the numbers right the bell curves of the populations might look the same but China's 1.3 billion people Americas
It's just not competitive
Numbers
Stem glass
Sierra 4.7 billion for China
Mm
2004 us
Arby's quality matters
But over there
You people are
Smart
Twice as hard
And they're a lot more of them
Yeah exactly
You don't have to be a math major to draw the
Rest of the Curves in like where they Henderson
And so
I don't know I just feel like
Real people are going to be very surprised at how fast
It happens
Especially like
Kind of global balance
What's the power
Couple things one
Competition is good
When there is real competition
That's when did the true color comes out
Do you read one of them from computer and get better
What do you want to sit around and bitching try to keep him down
Decision
We as a country
The US has
Secondly is at
You look at
The way that chainsaw to start it it's very
They tried to turn it into a math problem when steering pump
What is angle
Where we at
How to go from A to B
Took the time it takes to scale is actually faster in China
Cody Vine
They'll probably got start with Justin
TV and twitch
Products made in China
Got something
Is malama creative
Did anything could happen but takes bottle
Absolutely
I think this
Your merits about siding
And you probably want to figure out ways that you can go by and
I want to do this podcast review as the first
Chinese americans on the show
Is to share more of different ways to scale to come up with her
That problem
Does 2 2 2 solve
How to get the right part of my
Youfit
So that both sides can learn from each other
Equivalent faster
Compost sites
Absolutely but I mean even if you think about
You can even say you know this I think a lot of the criticism
But I started
Insulting value back in 2006
Throwing up 2010 what's their mm
12 is like
What Chinese
Just cloning every
Nothing right
Even if you think and now I think people are clearly like oh that's not
That's not the only thing I like
But even if you think that Chinese people because culturally or whatever are less was taking with less innovative
They're still four times as many people so you could be 1/4 as in
Yeah like there to be like
American person right and then you would still be competitive
Yunnan people should think about
How do
Grow from someone who's very creative and
Corn like hacking culture in
Just trying to build things into a manager or
Someone who can run a t
You want to company
That's a really good question I mean
When I was young
I felt like
Experience was like worth
And I ain't know I was like oh we can just rethink you know because Silicon Valley has his mrs. Legend of like
Are we just get a bunch of young people smarter than people smart young people locked in their sleeping in like a
10 in their living room and I just like make some immigrants
Exactly but
But the reality is
Like there's a lot of you look great example look at like the scaling on Twitter like you know this growth is massively stunted by like the down
Downtime in life
You know what for years and years
And
What I realized overtime getting expenses hey
Expresscopy really value
Brightest restaurant management stuff we don't have to
Insulted the thing that people
I think that I didn't realize when I was younger was
Silicon Valley I thought you had to rethink everything or like rebuild everything from Fresh Prince
Even if
Elon Musk
Mostly
You just need to innovate on one or two things really well and get a 10x on one or two axes for any of the rest of stuff you should just do
Do the best practice whatever whatever they did at Google or Facebook or whatever
Yeah you don't have to innovate
On your on your recruiting just need to do the bat like the top level or what
Right front, and so
I feel like that's something that I didn't really realize it's like you can hire
People who have it
Experience
And bring them in to do
2 x 100
Nmd do that at which actually
Years later eye twitch
You don't 6 years later I'm sorry
We brought in guys like
This is Jonathan
Had built
Eyes are Ciara like
And
He had built gaming ad sales teams before for IGN is a co-founder by genright
So he knew what to do and he just
Plug-and-play boom calorie high
Sales team and then Saran Wrap
We started learning how you can hire these like
Leaders who have
Experience who could ask
Cute and I think that's a big thing to realize
Just like
If you're young
You might have like really fresh
Innovative ideas that changed culture
But you can have other people have more experience help you exit
It's kind of figured that one out early and be able
I don't know
And if you figure out early that's how you be
Become super powerful right like that's how you become like
Evan from Snapchat
Hours Aqua
Oh yeah that most people like
Think they struggle with it and then
They get like a middle out
You've seen and advised Hunters of startups
What's the most common mistake that you see in Founders and what do tell them
Most common mistake
ICN Founders I mean number one
Is probably
The not focused enough
You know I think that companies always need to focus as much as possible
I think that's
Super hard to do I understand the Temptation I'm always tempted to like go as bright as possible
I think think Focus
This is really important
Second thing is probably
Give up on him way too easily
Yosemite now that starts I like
In fashion
A job you know that kind of a career
The people try it
Anime just give up after a year whatever
Go to something else
Exactly
How you know I don't think that great companies are made that way
Does almost everybody there oportun
Too high
Yes but in the Bay Area are insane to drop
Maybe High
Maybe actually High
Other mistakes that people make
It depends
Transamerica company you want and how much
Risk you're willing to take
But a lot of people want something is working
They go too slow
Yeah they don't hire the best exactly can you help
Open scale they don't even mention earlier to let go of things
They're scared to overspend you know which
Is reasonable in some ways
But it also can limit
Your growth
I notice a lot of Thunders underestimate
How important
What is to have
Their Drive their passion
To be like guiding
For some culture
In the front
That was moonrise a heart
Experienced
Their PCS were replaced on
What's up
Bike sprints
And what a lot
People see us Farmers don't know is a
Yocan Hive experienced hires but they would never have the vision
The passion YouTube
200 Expendables
So if you just focus on doing that well
Pushing me
Circles you higher
Absolute
Like you must learn to manage right and you must learn the scale because
You can't
Very quickly after your team is probably more than 5 feet
People the marginal effort of your work
York direct individual contributor work like
You programming you doing sales whatever it is
Is very low-light is like
Now it's like 20% of the company or five people anything above that
If you're up you have a tick team of 25 people
Is 4%
And so you can spend your time on like
Like if it's all of your effort in the entire year is 4% of a
The company if you just spend
Your time affect
Can people's work on if you only have to make people more than 4% more productive
Superior management
In order to like
Equal your
You don't know how much individual contributor work either you've needed doing lights
So your ability to manage people is your Leverage
And I think
People go into that mode
Slowly
Repentance something works
Should we move on to talk about
Atrium which is your
Current temperature
Italians more about what
The company does
Short story trim came from my problems mites
Experiences as a founder
Elwood Leo
And I was a power user why I should say as an involuntary power Reserve corporate Legal Services
It always spend money every time you want to do any major business transaction in America
You pay lawyers right and so for when you're raising funds if you're doing m&a and we did Big Amedeo
Litigation
All of this
You need to hire lawyers and I loved
The lawyers that I had who
Basically give me expert advice
Based on their extra knowledge
But there are a lot of experience
This is where I felt like it
Cookie cutters.
Turn it crank turning work
And I was like why are they using more software to deliver certain automated
But to automate things
To streamline the flow of information
I leave Law Firms out there they don't even in America you know they don't even use
Project management soft
You know they don't use
Like Trello or Asana
They don't use
CRM software for their clients and I sat down with an attorney
And I've been a client of their firm for
6 years
Which Wich
She didn't even know who you are
Yeah so that's weird because this is a 700 million dollar year business
And you didn't even know that you know I was at client like that's
That's weird
Because the level of
Professionalism
Enterprise sales organization is just not there but
There's a bunch of reasons in that that the industry's like that I don't need to go into those reasons but our goal with atrium
Was to
Archie's Island
And we're making it better for founders
We're making it better for
Attorneys in Pearland
By making it so that
Basically we want to make
Regal streamlined
Effective is like we re
Are top-tier
Technology-enabled Law Firm
That delivers legal services to Founders
And we make it streamlined make it faster
Making more transparent
Are we making
Pricing much more
A front right so you can know what you're going to pay
I left for our attorneys and paralegals
Our goal is to make things
Easier for them
To automate all the lights
Low-level work so they can focus on the high-level advisor
Which is what people want to do right you didn't go to law school
To like crank out
Signature maker
But bite or two like
Put together the first version of like a boilerplate.
And on top of that
The Lord is Noah cappe
Every time you do a fundraiser
You can wait
For sure to be secure yes unit stuff
But I need a Theodora snow
Exactly what's going on
Pilot superpower
You can imagine other services
Rendered
Absolutely absolutely so
What we're doing is really think about that
That we were building as a platform where we take
Legal
Structured data
And then we'd like me
You know so we can for example
Understand
Who is the owners of your company and then
There we can do things like
Reduce
Android
I'm or we can make that accept data accessible in other ways back
That's why I think that's this
Super valuable thing
And
Brickside about it now it's it's only been a year I was just saying it's a
We launched in June of 2000
17 North Bend
Exactly a year
And things are going pretty good so far
So last year you guys raised $2000000 new series a from over 90 investors and Gigi bb1
Why did you decide to do such a party around with so many Buster's
Ever I just want to see the biggest party biggest party round
It's a party round you know is it in Silicon Valley it's like kind of what happens now I think the same is true in China where someone will go and no
Play over there raise money from the dozens of investors
The OU's angels and maybe parts
The funds for their class
Cbrown
We chose to do that
Because we wanted our
Investors to funnel us
Portfolio company
Domino's Pizza
S works pretty well so far
So I'm pretty happy with the
The results in
And we also another thing is we wanted in vest
This is not to say hey
You don't legal is something that people don't actually want to take risk and right so we didn't want to invest
How to say hey don't
Don't try this
Service
Yeah exactly or even if they just
Familiarize
So what has been the progress so far until
Terms of
Providing the actual services
Yeah progress so far we going
I don't work for over 240 clients so far
I was out this client raised over four hundred million dollars
Last year
That's pretty cool call you then
So we do a couple things we can
Is he do the legal around
Financing
We also have
Boot camp called hm scale where we teach people how to fundraise
And I think the cool thing about that is
A lot of found is only one thing we realized the course of of operating a trim is that
A lot of founders
Just come in and they want help with
With the process
VCU.
Kind of
You and I are very spiritual experience
Guys are coming in and they just like don't know what to do you know you seem or more technology comes from outside the
The cost of living is so higher
But they don't have the connections they don't know what to do so we put together program
That's out today long boot camp
For Founders to teach them hate here's how you
Raise money and then we help them work on there
Deck in the narrative and
I welcome
Are most of your clients first-time founders
I know many of them are a multiple-time Founders or are we have clients or later Stage Company is your 200-person company and stuff like that
But we do have a lot of
Garceau there's an education component 2
Yeah absolutely I think that really want one thing I learned from Vice
Seawright is YC how to how do I see scale they built a lot around
Education around
Free content out there in the market events
Community right
And I think that one of the things that we can do here
For Adrian being a platform for
Companies write how do we
If I think about our missions Mission it's really the help
Fastline com
And I have to provide them with services and
An application to help them grow
Right and so
How do we do that while I take
Your education and
Community and like teaching people how to run companies
Information that they need
Hazel weight
Chucky
Was it get funded
Welcome to each ramp
Poison Netflix
Face in their course
Absolutely I would love to be able to help
So I spent 10 years since you started Justin.tv is there
Thousand sixteen You knew when you were just sort out
Knowing what you know today
Knowing what I know today I would have just sold it to Facebook in 2006
Besides that
I think that
You know when you have something that is a market
Category leader in a growing category any benefits as it don't sell it
I think I think we could have been much more effective if we had implemented actual management
In the early days of Justin TV and going through twitch
And and done a couple like basic things may be hired senior leaders I know it sounds so cliche to be like oh just hired you know
You got the gray hairs or whatever but you don't having some more senior leadership
Structure in the company where there's more division of labor among the co-founders
I wish we had more clear metrics-driven with gold rim and we never were like on okay ours or anything like that
Hunting putting in
Would like somebody's management
Tools to having workshops around that
Yeah will be helpful for your
Founders
I should do that for a rage and we should have an okay hours were
Workshop because I think it's super important
Understanding that management isn't
It's not a job right it's not a
It's not something that
Supposed to make your life.
Fun store.
A tool for you to be more
Successful
It's a collection of tools that for you
Right but I always thought that your management was kind of like a dirty word in
Yelp
Exactly we're supposed to like
We were supposed to just
Like hack on something until it was like Facebook
Whatever you know but
We didn't really realize I like
The world working or worse and I think that's the benefit of actually having a job
Before you start a company
We never had
I'm curious on your perspective on what Justin said about like if you are a category
Earlier you should hold on to a do thing that applies in China too or is that a different story
I think in China most people know that lesson from early on just so many sectors got disrupted
So that
If you have a cuddle leader they never never never saw
What has changed in China is now you see industry consolidate
So number one number two player fight for
Three years as hard as they can
Racism much
Money as they can they figure out who's Ash better
I forgot we depart
Yeah so that they can own more of the world end
The one who sold out and some become great and investor
Joe now you have Best of Both Worlds are more investors are more professional
Experience come through that
Does cutting Springs in also have a much bigger outcome
In the original article
So it's what
Absolute
Originally Saul mobile
Be acquired by
Great one
And sometimes
I asked the business it's just hard to
To be a standalone best depending on what you're doing it can be hard to be a stand-alone business
Nvidia look at you after while you figure out that
It's hard to be strong alone
Then if that's the case then
Finding the right comfortable be great we were messing musically
Help me save to figure out a way to scale and then
Encourage them to
When they want to merge into someone else
Find a Graco mean by dance
She move on to the
Rapid fire questions
Was it entrepreneur you admire the most and why
Who's the author
Leader I admire the most
And why don't my who's older
That's all I was younger
That's a good one older and younger
Everybody probably says Elon Musk Elon Musk
I think I admire because
He's always look so
Stressed out and he has so much pain right I'd like to keep doing it despite the pain.
That is a guy who
Is not enjoying his life
I know exactly I respect that because he's doing it for the
Humanity even at the sacrifice of the self in that is truly
Do Psychopaths have seen how you think this ice cream
Fun to eat ice cream
Yep that's
That's right I hope that's okay
But maybe the other the person I would say actually then
If I can't choose elong would be
Brian chesky
Hi Brian. Someone I known
Their entire long time journey through through Airbnb
And they used to come by our office
Across the street I remember in the early days.
Cuz we were like one step ahead a lot along of course of then they rapidly
Eclipse
But I just need to get in twitch
But I like to I admire rhyme because he always
Just learning he's only trying to level up
From somebody who's
A couple steps ahead
And finding mentors gift and I think that is as inspired
Me here at Atrium actually I'm always
I'm trying to like how do I level myself up you know that's the last
Kind of
The thing for me like the reason I start a trim is like I want to
Bill the company bigger than twitch
Which is a very high bar in order to do that I'm going to have to
I continue to like
Be self-aware and level myself up and figure out what I
I'm good at indranagar out and work on
You know improving my strengths and maybe complimenting my
But and so
Really a lot of that since bye bye bye
I have a lot of respect for
For what he's done
How to build his company
Are younger founder I respect immensely
What is two is obvious one in a non-op
1 1st Ave
Patrick Collison
Stripe
He's acting like such a genuine good person
I mean I
You can't respect that right everybody's also very curious
And as others
You know I think his
Is curiosity drives him to
Really Blake Building Company that embodies I do know I can
Ticket with with stripes
Feels like there's so much on the
The technical axle inside and
I'm really investigating the
Technology side that
Eureka College
It's like that
In the Spear of the compass
And obviously hot that has driven massive success
Maybe the not obvious side
It's my really admire is
Daniel gross
Co-founder of a company called Q
I whistled Apple
Before
Years ago now I think
And maybe is 545 years ago
So he was very young when I met him you. Maybe
18 years old or something like that
And
Daniel
Was I just like this guy is one of the smartest
People I've ever met
So smart and not just smart on the
Outside of
Cousins
Intelligence and
And Technology but it's also very
Connected in Silicon Valley
Emotional intelligence
This is been able to like building
Amazing that work here in
Silicon Valley
Now is a partner at y combinator
It's raining is AI program is well at AI grant program
And I always
Feel like when I talk to Daniel I'll learn something
I need someone
It's funny because I would go to him and I'll go to him and I do 4-H him and I asked him
Be back in advice on life
My business ideas in plant and there's not that many people in
It's including many of the
Many investors who I'm like
That's a guy want to talk to you
You know how I'm
Younger than me
8 years younger than
That's amazing
What's something you read recently that talk to you a lot
Read recently that I think was really great his book called
The elephant in the brain
Bye
Scott Robin Hanson
The Economist
And another I got to the guy from Silicon Valley a programmer
And this book is all about the hidden with motivation
Human behavior that we don't ask
Do you want to talk about
I like
One of the things
I remember from the book I was discussing with Emmett Mike
Got switch go powder
How was that
Yo advertising actually works
I'm not just
Because it is of the bright light brand advertising worth
Because it
Your brand advertising and
And you see it so you have that exposure
But it's also because
When you know other
People have seen it
So so like BMW advertising as a luxury brand networks because not just
Because
UCB wnec looks like cool that or whatever you like of a BMW cool but because you know other people have seen that
So you know that like
BMW has a luxury place in their mind
And so that means that you can like basically if you buy BMW then you get that value of like
Other people
I think it's luxury right
So I thought that was like an interesting jobs
Actually
And you know I think I was coming at you you haven't thought about the book is filled with examples kind of that
That was pretty fast
What do you do for fun
What do I do
4fun great great question
What if I have fun while I'm not fat I'm a gun full
Elon Musk yet
But I
I am
I have the place up
In Sea Ranch California
And on the telephone
TV surrounding
Like throw throw axes and Dawn high taxes
Outside outdoor outdoor Sofia
Alright thank you so much for your time this was fun
Alright thanks for having me
Volume four
Thanks for listening
Buddhist episode of 996
By the way
We also produce a weekly email newsletter in English
Also called 96
Progesterone.
Of the week's most important happening
Inside in China
Subscribers
Component speakers
Informative
And you said also features original content
Analysis
From Zara me
Tripe
At 96
Ggbc
Ggv capital is a multi-stage venture capital firm based in Silicon Valley on high in Beijing
We have been partnering with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past 18 years
Proceed to pre IPO
We 3.8 billion dollars in capital under management real estate funds
GTA V invest in gold we minded entrepreneurs in consumer internet
E-commerce
Frontier tag
An Enterprise
GTA V has invested over 280 companies
With 29 IPOs in 22 unicorn
Pergola companies include
Airbnb
Alibaba
C trip
Didi chuxing
Domo
Hashicorp
Hello byte
Cows
Cheap
Slack
Square
Hotel
Wish
Soundtrue
White white and others
Find out more at G G bc.com
We also highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat group as lot Channel
Where we regular share insights
Events in job opportunities
Related to attack in China
20 scrubs at 96.3 tvc.com community
Do you have any feedback on this podcast
Or would like to recommend a gas
Bisimoto
I-96
A gbc.com