Welcome to the nine at six podcast
Brought to you by GDP capita
Echo produced
What is citic
On the show we interview movers and shakers
China's tech industry
As was Tech leaders
Weather us
China
Cross-border perspective
My name is sun stone, managing partner at GTB
Capital it has been working at startup
Investing in them
In both in us and China
Forecast 20
My name is Sarah Jeong
I meant investment analyst igb capital
Jennifer Moore journalist
Why is the show called 96
96 is the work schedule that many Chinese Founders have organically adopted
That is
9 a.m. to 9 p.m.
6 days a week
To us
Captures intensity
Drive
10 speed
Of Chinese internet
Many of which
I'm moving faster
But even their Mercy
King Auto Parts
On the show today we have daughter Kai fuli
Who is the founding president of Google China and a renowned computer scientist known for his work in artificial intelligence
Hifu is the founder and CEO of sinon Beach
Adventures
Early-stage VC Fund in China
Messi started in 2009
Is born in Taiwan
And emigrated to you as a young age
Just work as an executive at Apple SGI Microsoft than Google
He played a critical part in establishing virus
China
Would you like to come back without research
For all of Asia
And I was a
Game-changing event
In the field of tech
Billy became the founding president of Google China
And then a few years later in 2009 he left to go to start it
Is a non busy fun Columbia University where he gave a commencement speech this summer
And a PhD in computer science from Carnegie Mellon
Besides being a private investor an advocate for artificial intelligence
Is also well known in China as skyflower shorty track iPhone
Career coach an influencer with over 50 million followers on weibo as well as his official account
And he has published five bucks and frequently gives speeches at universities across China
Welcome to the show.
Thank you thank you for inviting me
The first questions I would start with the OD States part of your life
Can you tell us when did you leave timeline what prompted
In
What kind of expertise
When you first went to the US
Was there any adjustment.
Oh okay yeah it was I thinking early 70s when my brother was a PhD in
Us went to visit my parents
Family
After many years
Absent
And he saw that
Why the large gap that us had
Education cess
And compared to
All of Asia
And he said why don't you come live with us
So so I did late 72
A lot older
So he was out in Oak Ridge at Oak Ridge National Labs Gulfport Mississippi
Which I went to and lived in
It was all really quite an experience because I wouldn't give me some
The only
Chinese student in high school which is probably something
English back then
I didn't speak any English when I went but I think with typical southern hospitality
Welcome with open arms
Can you fax the oak ridger
Newspaper of the small town of Oakridge recently had a three-part series
Interviewing with me so I really treasure the days
And I think the people are very warm and wonderful
The teachers were very patience
Look it up to speak with the language
Did you encounter any difficulty at all
Well of course they're always you know some people unfamiliar with
Asian boy Oregon
A lot of people cutting
Occasionally when someone picks on me
And I didn't really know they were picking on me always be some other warm student will come to my
Has so I never had any real
I seriously
A 6 years
6 years yeah middle school and high school
For your Chinese amazing
So how do you
How to compute people search death
United basketball
Yeah so I went when I first went to the u.s. my mother said that I have a 2 wishes to things you must
If I let you go
First you have to marry a Chinese wife
Which I did not comment
I did that situation
The second was she said you need to write me a letter every week
And then she corrected every mistake on the letter
At the time phone calls were expensive there was no email
So it was all based on this one letter from me to her
She wrote the letter back
Correcting my previous letter
And then that help me keep up
My mother moved in with me
So they were have to write anything to her
Walmart my family
Got it
And then you went to New York
I did very different City
That would prompt you to choose Cumbia
Well Colombia is a very
Famous school for and I apply to a bunch of famous schools
And it was
I mean
Peking Chinese restaurant 1st and you go to the highest-ranked one that except
New York
No New York was a positive factor but I think I was still very much a Chinese mentality
How do you go to the ranks and say okay
Columbia's rank whatever number 7
Did you know you were going to study computer science when you went there
I did not
I enjoy computer science a lot in high school actually got exposed to it in high school but
I did yes IBM.
Equivalent to 360
So when I went to Columbia I was going to study math
Because in Tennessee I was State winner in mathematics I thought I was really good
But it turned out in a Tennessee was a small state
I did not I did not do that well I was placed in the most advanced math class for 7 people
That was probably number 7 in the class
You get an A- just forever
Pretty good at it but then I also discovered that computer science
Which was a lot of fun than I thought that was a lot
Remember the first time you came across a computer
First time it was at the University of Chicago
High School sophomore year I went to there to study number Theory
Special master
The class and then they gave me an account
Barely knew how to program I mostly play games on it
It was a lot of fun
But your brother didn't show you how to
Program computer no no he didn't have or know how to program one
Well he was he was a biochemist
Okay
Lemon juice
Helena IR
Columbia
Quantum dots
I went to Carnegie Mellon
To school straight to school to the PHD program
Yeah I was fortunate to have had a professor John Kender
Who was the CMU grad
And teaching at
Columbia
And
He liked me a lot and recommended
I got into CMU
The best school and I was
So when was the first time you should
Sure the term artificial intelligence
It was in my sophomore year at Columbia
Darling
It was in a course are called natural language processing
I was taught by a professor who was a student of Roger schank
Was one of the early
Cognitive science based natural language
Experts
So
So we build systems using lisp
How to understand understand
I froze a dialogue system
It's light is what you would call we would call
A chatbot
Sowak would build a chatbot for my 19
80 + 81
What it was
Intelligence
Nose in the
Late 80s
Fields medal
I'm fine
Yazawa for breakthrough
Siri
Who knows
Come to reality
Teens what are the
The critical Factor
Change
Popular and so prevalent
Right I think the biggest factor is really the maturation of
Even though
Are there were multiple ups and downs
There are times when neuron that works real hard.
Hidden Markov models for my PhD thesis which way the same class of neural Nets
Butter
And then they kept improving
And even though they were. If I don't I
Deep learning reinforcement learning those algorithmic improvements
And the people will continually work
That's the most important
Boxer
Of course the author almost as important factor
Is the availability of
Huge amount
Yeah because
The internet company
Exactly a lot of people think it's all algorithms but actually
You need to have a
Training with large amounts of data
And you need to tune your hours and based on the amount of data you have
Do you get more day that you improve your hours in better you get more data improve it better
And then. It already cycle
Is what I drove today and as you said
Who has the most day that was the internet companies
So the US is suck Google
Facebook Amazon China is Baidu Alibaba
So when you finish your PhD are you planning a career in a cup
Gmail
I was
I stayed at honeydew melon
They made me
Assistant professor
Yes yes I was
I research scientist and an assistant professor
Skip the postdoc
You really made an exception because my PhD at a time
What's considered an important breakthrough in speech recognition
Golf course in hangzhou
It really wasn't anything
Close to good enough
But but I stayed and talked
And what led you from there
To work
Call Tacos El Bebe
Academia
L'accademia really wasn't quite for me
So I felt
All the work you need to do to get
Grand get students was a lot of busy work
Without the corresponding aha moment
When you can get to do exciting research
Exciting
And actually more importantly University wasn't a great place to make things happen
Write papers it's still kind of Ivory Tower
Still academic
I wanted to
Change the world
And of course it was Apple that called
And it was
A similar style recruiting that said look do you want to spend your life
Writing useless papers or do you want to essentially the same things that job Steve
Jobs at the John sculley sugar water but useless paper
How big was Apple when you
Gosh I think was about
Suite 3000 I think it's been a long time I think
And what do you say was your proudest The Chew
When you are at
Call my proudest achievement
Was getting on Wall Street Journal and Good Morning America
When we demonstrated our speech recognition
Which still again did not work but it was fun.
Close to working system because
We had a great team of Engineers
Tell my PhD algorithms a real time
It was really really fast faster than anybody else
But it wears wasn't good enough
Butts up whenever the last Wall Street Journal cover did the stock went up a few points
And then I go
It was in 1990
392 92-93
That's when I first remember you
Caring about you
I'm reading the newspaper
I'm sorry I didn't work as well
If you are looking forward to buy a map to get to the market
Is it was not a failure but it was not not a success
Honolulu Airport
You look familiar
I was a pineapple for 6 years
And then towards the last two or three years it was discontinued around the playoff
I think from career development
You know I learned a lot in adversity
Console people
Managing teams in good times and bad also got a bunch of promotions because my boss is skipped
Getting fired or so from being a manager to
Tovp Injustice I think about
Two and a half
So it's it gave me a chance for Accelerated growth
I wanted also argue it was not too fast
I had to go back and relearn in another company's but
Ultimately
The iterative rounds of layoffs
Southwest is too much
SGI
Resolve I thought wow that's a
That was an exciting company and little did I know I was
Jumping out of the Boiling Pot Into the Fire
Hallelujah SEI number
Paula Stephan there
Justice 2 years
We we actually build the first set of web servers so I went to a totally different business
It was I with a profit-and-loss
3D technology for the web and then we fell down
Web servers
What service were a big success
I'll make a few hundred million dollars
And then the 3D for the web was too early
It was called vrml virtual reality in 1996
And if I'm there you went to Microsoft
Yes and the time
I was actually ready to go out
Ice Outlook
Every company I went to it ended up getting killed by winter
Because winter was the windows in Endowment for them
Guerrilla
Facing the market share issue and then Apple couldn't deal with it
Entailment our products are almost as good much cheaper and STI the same thing
Market solution
People eating out
Yeah at first SGI workstation road with only things you can use for
Cobb movie animation but later
Wenzhou beginner yoga
And I sold so that's a
Calls me to say okay I'm just going to have
After work for either Microsoft or Intel
But if that's the Wintel duopoly
So I interviewed at Microsoft
Intel got two job offers
And the chosen
What women do to stop Microsoft
Well I thought
Oh yes it was changed
Both companies offered me to had their research lab in China
And I think it was really my roots
Insoft
Where is that I really didn't know much about semiconductors
I felt I want to work in a company where my expertise is at the
The core of the company
As opposed to ascending peripheral
ISO Microsoft with a software company
I saw that was trapped
Austin Hardware companies
Apple NSG eyewear
Software was evaluated purely as
And to help yourself Hardware
And that Microsoft was maybe a first chance I could do so
How come both those companies were thinking about setting up
Honda Center
Incheon
Going on up
I held it management team
Think about that
I am guessing that one of them decided to do it first and the other herd
I suspect Microsoft shows first
And then I think Intel said hey Microsoft doing we should do
Go to Microsoft
Honey RV Center
India at a time
No no no
He was actually research incorp your fundamental research and both companies are doing that
And there certainly were no strong indication China would be an academic power attitude
Yeah that's what's so surprising
Microsoft only had Redmond and Cambridge
That's Cambridgeshire UK and China Beijing with the desert
Did you expect that you will be working in China doing the
Oh yes yes yes it was specifically for that position
And I felt you know China
I met a lot of great Chinese employees fellow students
At Carnegie Mellon an apple
I saw that the people in China
We're incredibly hard-working very smart very motivated
Maybe not as good education as you ask but I felt
Microsoft
Could do something
If a brand is was strong and we could hire the smartest people
Being a Taiwanese election
Hesitation
To work in Beijing
I know it was actually one of my father is
Wishes on
On his Deathbed
I would spend time in
I saw my parents and emigrated from mainland China to
Emigrated move from a move
Check exactly
So my father has always wanted to
I hope the move back himself
Witchwood
Wouldn't be materialized in his lifetime
But he thought I should
How is your adjustment process when you first started working in the mail
Cuz you haven't really
Yeah but it was very open environment I think all the universities academic academic
We're very very curious they were wondering the same price as you are
Why would you pick Giant
What do you hope to do what
And then we showed no we really want to bring the smartest students
So we brought back from the US top researcher
A lot of people
Very famous
Yeah yeah we're very fortunate there was just a wave of Chinese
Yes ma'am in China right I would say probably Hong Kong University of Science and Technology
What are the first grader China waved but largely not Mainland but definitely msra
Typically phds in their early mid-30s
Who are rising stars
I'm almost all of them
Born in
Yeah about other senior people or maybe yeah
80% point in mainland China
The junior people are 100%
Guava juice
And how did you first meet his car into a recent TV show
The account they said that you met Eric Schmidt on the golf course
Yes I did well I actually went back to Microsoft headquarters
And then when I heard that Google was starting
It's on us
Google China presence
I thought I had the right combination because
The school wanted to R&D
They wanted someone who understood China
Communicate
What's Silicon Valley culture
So actually volunteered myself and send an email to Eric Schmidt
And then we were arranged to meet
I mostly because
There were too many Microsoft people interviewing
And they
Saltado
I would prefer not to be seen by a lot of Microsoft?
Google what tips do you have for
People who are
Trying to attract owls
Join their company
Well I think you have to find people with the right cultural fit
And you have to have a very high bar
And you have to show
The people's Iraq map
In your company
And iiii
I think you want to find people
The people who the rights culture and the background
Will generally find it to be
Because people will want to work with people
Quora similar minded equally smart
And they can learn from
And in a culture that nurturing
And also
Consistent with the values that they believe in
So I think part of it is you got to pick up
Who to Target
And then and it happening
Incredibly important original nucleus of people who are themselves
And then attract more people
Over the top
Crew
People
Google give me
Yeah what's Microsoft's the top reasons were
This is the
Only place
Statscan do fundamental research with the freedom
And you will
Be helped with the team
Super smart young people
Incredibly hard-working you remember how it was for you
And then Microsoft as a brand
Offer Google it was some this was a chance to really build up
A business
That's could be
Phenomenal
And that combined business engineering everything we happy empowerment
After headquarters
Second is the Google brand itself.
Add the time Google was
Clear and by far
The most attractive company to Europe
Exactly
Workforce
And then the third would be all the wonderful
Actually not so important but
Incredibly important
Recruiting the wonderful the benefit
I thought we had a
Executive chef
Lobster for lunch at
All kind of benefits
In the US there was
Doing yard
Laundry for you and all the other good stuff
So all those benefits
Actually did work
In attacking people
Even though I don't think they work or
As far as the long-term
How would you define the culture
Google China
We wanted to really have an independent mindset
That because I felt the only way Google China could succeed
Was to
Delete this is your own company
And go after it
And in order to do that we wanted to
Have the Google values
But have the freedom
To really I roll out new product features
And
Iterate and show numbers in terms of
Market growth and
And also advertising Revenue growth
So it was a probably
Almost like a startup within the compass
When do you think you had the first
Claim that Google my name
I need to leave
I I didn't
I didn't
I think the Google business so went up for the first 3 years
That I was there the market share went up significantly
Revenues were almost a billion dollars that search share went up
Sure sure was about to Triple
My tenure
But the last year
I think there were
Some difficulties
I think
Hardly just do to Google
Feeling that okay time to build one
One Google
And not have this you know
Difference
Everything being different
Because all the products features a lot of code was for
And people were questioning Hey look
Google now has expanded successfully throughout the world then maybe China should you
Just be like any other country
So I didn't have as much freedom
Has asked
Before and also I think they are
It was the one year when Google's Financial numbers were not
The greatest last numbers
The last budget
As far as to attract
Traffic and usage in marketing
So those those were the
Some of the challenges we faced
But also I think I would
More I left Google because not because of the challenges
But because I saw the opportunity
I saw that mobile was going to be a huge deal
Harley being in Google I saw the power of Android
And then I saw that the entrepreneurial energy the entrepreneurs and the BCS were growing in China
But there was a gap in the
Early seed-stage funding
So I thought feeling. Gap
What's v my technical background
And also be a lot of fun to help young people
Car companies
So that was really the
Started with A and Q
Beijing model
That's right right
Right now
As you evolve them Auto
Alaska
70 years
What were some of the
The biggest
Lessons
Takeaways
Right so our model today is
Basically a VC model
It's Wheaton Aston series A and B
We still do angel deals when we can
We rarely we don't incubate but I don't want any more investing early stage
Stop ta deal sweat when one comes along
I think we pride ourselves on being very
Technically
Knowledgeable
Picking the right trans
And we
We we still have a lot of the early spirit that we love our
Entrepreneurs we have a very strong service team
To help in terms of marketing PR
Oanda
Finance legal and so on so we have a big team
That's continues to help the entrepreneurs even though it's series A&B
What is a service mentality the
Prawn entrepreneur mentality
Yeah and then we have now in a Eye Institute
Which is now
Implementing AI
But also helping RVC is that deal referral and judgment
That's maybe a little bit like you know Greylock and Benchmark in the technical
Type little bit like Andreessen Horowitz Enterprise Services operations
And maybe a little bit like a Google Ventures and happy are all engineers
So we're trying to make
Make this model work.
The fund is doing well
But in retrospect you asking me what things out I learned that were maybe not quite as I originally expected
I think it is
Is probably obvious to you hun that many people in DC now
And then myself too but at the time
I thought a nurturing incubation environment
Could help a lot of people
Philips there areas in which there not strong
And increase your chance of
However I think in retrospect
I think the strongest
Finally successful entrepreneurs
Are so strong and you're so confident
I think they feel
An entity like an incubus
Or someone who for the watches over them like a teacher or even a boss is something that's highly on
Undesirable
The great entrepreneurs want to be independent
They want to be
Funded they want to give
Be given import
But they need to be their own boss
And they're big and strong and powerful and confident they'll make mistakes
Comes from learning from the mistakes
Not from a teacher
Who guides them along the way so that's how we made our roll ships
The one that I think is more
Complimentary
2 people who are off
It's a typo
Strong
I just hope I can
Older
Yeah. Yes space changes a lot because in the early stages were doing mobile
It was very young
Because the money is because
At that time PC people wear in the mid-thirties
And they couldn't change their mindset so he's one General
And so we back young people lights very Lean Startup very low small amounts of money
And a very small amount of money was enough
Because it was a three engineers
But now as we going to heavier Styles where you have to
You know I think about new retail new house
I think about new education you actually have to
A big customer acquisition
You may have even offline activities
And also the Chinese competition evolve differently from the US
Having us continues to feel
Light startup is good life isn't always good
Mark Zuckerberg exactly but in China
The competition is so fierce
That's if you have a light model someone might copy you or do to
Ride the next wave
So you have to really build very big deep Moats
And the most often have to do with
Ugly offline and the expensive
Capital expenditure or summer
Experience experience
Ricer Miata
Exactly something so the amount of money we put in has to be a lot more even though series and the people tend to be
The older more experienced
I will start running larger
So what advice do you have for a US company
A sweet one
Inter China is
She giving you a
Google Tim Cook salary
Recently that you can change the
From the sidelines
What he was defending apples moved
Comply with Beijing
Regulation
Yeah oh I'm more to the question
Wenzhou have done well
Going to be
Morton
Starbucks
The internet guy
Yeah
I I think
Foreign companies will have a tougher time than beef
On the one hand China is a big lucrative Market everyone should try to enter in
Participate
But said the good days when Procter & Gamble could comment
Just take it all is done
Starbucks
Public was one of the
Last entrance yes that will have
Kind of
Mindshare they have
Finding the next one will happen
Be tougher because the
Chinese brand builders are getting better
Minang traditional
I think it's
American company shouldn't take it
Internet companies have it maybe it'll even harder
Apple is the one example of success but you could argue
Did not have internet company
So an American Technology Company I would have
Have to advise
I want is if possible get a Chinese partner
And
I want to be part of this summer I've also try to get deceased
Find a local entrepreneur that's another model
If you are
If you are in a
Press certain areas may be a state-owned company or a bank
It all depends
Internet company maybe bat was good but
So so I think you have to evaluate but having someone who knows local
Yep that's core
And that that's important
Who buys I have is if you have a
Very strong technology differentiation
Consider selling the technology
Consider license
Because that's another way
That's you
China is now very much much better in respecting IP I think
Technology licensing to be a very good and easy business you don't have to deal with the complexities of all the
Local market and running
So
What would you saying is the most successful us
Apple would certainly be one of them they're doing okay so far although I think they're facing some challenges
As well
There's not not not to be growing but
I think
They
Carolina
I think
Actually some traditional companies are still
I build a strong enough roots
They're still doing okay IBM being one example.
They have a very strong brand very strong local partnership ecosystem
Those are probably two
Styles to consider
But they're also Hardware companies like Intel and video I think they're also doing
Because they're kind of a
Lap dance
That infrastructure
It's a little bit easier to
It's a little bit like Licensing hours
What do you think
Yahoo
Adult
Uber
In a while to realize
Yes you more of a
15 motivate
Yes
I think so
I think so I think
Are there Uber deal was
A very shrewd to be down there where the time it that that they did
And I think the Alibaba Yahoo maybe a little bit of luck
Because the time it was hard to Envision the way things will play out
But nevertheless I think Jerry saw Jack
As an amazing amazing God
That's right so I think it is
Maybe you well informed from the people angle but the business side garage different did not see it play out this way
It was great
Who recently wrote a piece for the economist about a phenomenal as a lamo or Alzheimer's with offline
Do you think
So the boundary between all my offline
Is being lured you think China is ahead of it
In which area of application are you most excited
Price online merges with offline is when you can capture everything in the physical world
Digitize it and upload it and combine with online
So it when you're shopping
Actually
The fact you picked up some products are bought some product that's captured and combine with your online pattern
That could be done with your sister
Online payments you could also be done with a video camera or other are there sensors and mechanisms
The entire o m o is
Is is huge in China because we see it hitting
A lot of areas including retail
Including
Public transportation including education
And also
If you look at the amount of digital activity
Best happening in offline
China Islam
Away passing the US
Online wise
Yunnan China
Mobile users is maybe three or four times
Us
But in terms of online
Payment
He is so much bigger online
Especially offline Mobile payment is off the chart
Is over over 50 x
And then that's enabling
So in China I think the
Biggest enabler
How much is as much as we love a i&o mo
We think a huge enabler that's already happened
Is the
Mobile payment
Now in China over 600 million people
Can do a peer-to-peer
Micropayments
And almost frictionless almost without Commission
Exchanges to each other and that will empower
Many times of applications
So are investments
T-Mobile
You know that some of the live streaming
And
Food delivery that's all taken off because Mobile payment will be the enabler
That will make everything happen a lot faster
So I think the offline
Payment
I will unlock
Alana song gross
An accelerated ways even faster than beef
Before
So you know if you asked me to predict future of AI as possible China are you as well be ahead
But if you ask about the future poema
About the mobile payment driven
Online offline merging creating value
There's no doubt
China will be the leader in
Normal asked questions.
When you get a Microsoft
Once you had a
Open letters
Concussion
A lot of the Chinese
Also
Buku lineup
Coming
The future president
Baidu answer
Ciccio's on 10th and and and and
What made you capable of
Pretty August
In the first place
And what do you think someone like me
For any other one
Well I think
There is a place and time for everything
There was a time when Microsoft brand was the most amazing
There's a time when Google was a most amazing
And there are times NBA team
And now I think the age of entrepreneurs
So I think it's hard to
Fight against the trend
I think actually the entrepreneurial trend is the most powerful
Including the government's support for the mass entrepreneur and innovation
Campaign
As well as I think the
The parents and the
The young people themselves
I thinking differently
So I think it's hard to watch with somebody's mind and force them to
Still think some companies hot when it's not
I think right now
If you want to follow the trend
People want to be entrepreneurs
They want to learn how to be entrepreneur
And I think we're in the fortunate position as Avicii
To be able to connect to those people
And find a way to fulfill the dream
My last question
What you and I have
Using that
City phone number
What do you think of someone a mod
Well I I think the
I think the China model is very hard to reply
I actually don't think it will
Can be replicated at anything close to China scale
Partly is because I think China have all the things happening at the same time
Very hard-working Industrial
Industrious
Population
Plenty of capital coming in
The willingness to take risks and
All of those things at the right time and the
The ride Revolution came along with the internet's mobile now ai
So it was almost a perfect storm
Design perfect square for China to go from
A poor country to manufacturing now into tap
That cannot necessarily be replicated for other countries because
Are the initial step of
Using cheap labor
To gain a strong ground hold in the world is may not be doable because
He's taking a lot of those jobs
So it's not clear
Having more
Unskilled laborers is a benefit to large population
Country anymore that's the number one reason
The other thing is those are perfect storm elements
Are just hard to realign for another country
So I think what's most likely to happen is
China and US War each become a very strong
Powerful corner
The Otherworld
With its software Technologies know-how and
Going into other countries
Write a Chinese camp
An American Cup
Right so that will happen in many different ways you know Google is used to Facebook are used to expanding their own presence
Subsidiaries
In Chinese companies maybe be here
Or even tell me
Write in China some of those companies are expanding himself like xiaomi
Some companies are doing Investments like
Some companies are doing startups
But still not leaving China
But like the you know Tokyo copycat
Two different countries
And the live streaming CopyCats in the bicycle copycats
Those are necessarily biome
Xiaomi or
So older models
Chinese Laundry wedge sandals
Yes I think in the end
China and us will really play very big role
The other countries were obviously the ones with bigger markets and more
Advanced infrastructure will still enjoy
Good growth
But it's hard to really a replication that you admire the most
The entrepreneur I think
Would have to be Steve Jobs
I think he has the boldness to dream The Impossible
And also
Learning to become a better leader
Now he's obviously had a lot of issues and faults
And had to leave and come back
But I think God he is in thought they inimitable
What's up
And work
Best decision
Probably
I think I have to say marry my wife but professionally my moving to China
Yeah I think the
Worst decision
Is probably
Just generally believing
Speech recognition could work in the 90
Michelle's Corley
Continuously trying.
Without learning
From the previous lesson but eventually I learned
What's a habit that you're glad
Reading
Thank you so much for your time and now it's
The pleasure to have you
Thank you thank you
Okay
Good afternoon
Thanks for listening
Who does episode of 996
By the way
We also produces weekly email newsletter in English
Also called 96
The rundown of the week's most important happenings
Inside in China
Subscriber some photos for the formative and fun to read
And you said also features original content
An analysis
From Sarah me
Stripe at 96
Ggbc
Ggv capital is a multi-stage venture capital firm based in Silicon Valley Shanghai and Beijing
We have been partnering with leading technology entrepreneurs for the last 17 years from seed to pre-ipo
What's 3.8 billion dollars in capital under management across age funds
GTA V invest in globally-minded entrepreneurs in consumer internet e-commerce
Frontier Tech in Enterprise
Gdb has invested in over 200 companies including Airbnb
Alibaba
The trip DVD
Hello bike
House
Keep
Slack
Square
Toutiao
Wish
Soho social
Why white and others with 29 IPOs and 17 unicorns to date
Find out more at gbc.com
Do you have any feedback on this podcast or would like to recommend a gas
Bisimoto
I-96
Igbc.
This podcast is co-produced
Bow friend and business partner
Kaiser kuo
The host of the wonderful sinica podcast
It covers China's economic
Political
And culture