Recent arrest Monroe County
Airport
Hi dear
Welcome to the 96 podcast brought to you by tgb capital and co-produced by the Seneca podcast
On the show interview movers and shakers
China's tech industry
That's was Tech leaders who have a us China
Cross-border perspective
My name is Sunstone, managing partner at GTB Capital it has been working at startup investing in them
In both the US and China for the past 20 years
My name is Zahra Jones I'm an investment Analyst at ggv Capital and a former journalist
Why is the show called 9696 is the work schedule that many Chinese Founders have organically adopt
That is 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
To us996 captures intensity Drive
In speed
Of Chinese internet companies many which
I'm moving faster
But even their American counterparts
How much do today we have limping
Who's the co-founder and had a mobile phone xiaomi
We're having this conversation at a very exciting time
Both for being himself
As well as for xiaomi
Xiaomi one of the most valuable private companies in the world
Is last round robin Easton was 46 billion dollars
And reportedly is going public
Later on this year
Good himself with his name had a mobile for xiaomi a couple months ago
And many of the products are hitting the market
Recently
Show me how to unprecedented
Come back here in 2017
It was the fourth largest smartphone seller in the world by shipment in
4th quarter last year
And in January this year it was one of the top three Cellars in the world
Instrument last quarter was almost 100-year on your increase
Beyond China sell me is the number one smartphone seller in India
Which is the second largest smartphone market in the world
And top 5 in 16 other countries
Probably show me you work at Microsoft for 11 years and then I Google
Four more years
E-service Indian director of Microsoft research Asia in Beijing working with
Dr. hefley who appeared on the show
Are podcasts earlier
You are also the vice president of Google China
Instruments nearing and then the engine driver Google global
When I first met you while you are Google yeah just decided to co-found xiaomi
In late 2009
Audi 2010
Willie G
KK
Audi intent other top-notch Chinese Tech veterans
What a journey it has been
So handsome Ben both of you mad Legion the founder of xiaomi pretty early on
I wonder how did you eat meet him so I'm at Lejeune back into something tonight I would say
Because at that time they didn't have already retired from kingsoft
And you have started to enjoy investing into a moving companies
Usiu siwa
And that was a cool go in charge of all the Google mobile products and
Business Development one of the key partners with Google
In China was ucweb
And it's a pretty straightforward collaborations Amino Google just put the search bar on UC Browser
When Agents of S.H.I.E.L.D Co-op
Prenatal for the two of us to meet
We started to entertain the idea of starting xiaomi together 2009
Iowa State
And
It took us a good
Six months maybe even more than that
Eventually came to how we would like to come to eat
Already put together
And what product
It's a lot of discussions I was here late night discussion strings
Coffee's and Prince Charming
DNN smoking yes
Was it his idea first and then you
It was mainly his idea
But there was a discussions and ideas change also evolve over time
Both of us has a really you know I me as part of my job at Google working with
Have a small team building Android system
It was part of my job to evangelize the Android
Is a open source operating system for the Next Generation
Cinepolis
And then himself has a deep interest in Mobile at that time
So when I met him he has a bag of phones back then was you know what's my fault
Enterprise iPhone at that time also and also
And I myself also had a bag of full with me
Is that it was my job to carry all these hoes and use them
Especially USD Google service Google Maps Google search
Odyssey headphones and also Andreas
How's the weather
So we both had him read adventures and stuff like that
And it's pretty natural 4C Venturi saying hey maybe there's a way that we can
We can put together company and build that the Next Generation smartphones
Fortunate
What did you think this was like a
Crazy idea at that time because there were so many large players in the smartphone world
I Claudius right there's a lot of big players back then
Samsung S5
And of course a poem
Beijing China
There are many players and at the time Nokia's dominant but the opportunity really is
Will be this back then was
It wasn't really about future from what's the snowfall
It was
Finger smartphone is a computer
Annie's a computer that allows you to process
And the Ant us
You can do it yeah it's a computer
Anything that PCS can do
Back in the old days
Eventually smartphones
And although
And more
So that was a really exciting idea
So we haven't thought much about all competition licensing
We just saying hey
There's an opportunity we can together pill company that builds this next generation
Phone sent that people will
Places opportunity that we talk.
Well I first met Beijing a bit earlier in 2008
Back then she had a thesis around three drivers
For internet growth in China
And they were similar to mine
Social networking was the first
E-commerce was sucking
IMobile
Wireless internet
What's the third
Can I try to collaborate on social networking around casing lo1
That wasn't a successful so we hope to be
Then we try to Calabria run
E commerce company at Brand call Bangkok
Funko
Tempting
Which grow fast for a few years but eventually turn off
Is there a project that we try to work out together and make it work cuz he mobile
And not what size xiaomi
I remember the first time
I heard that ID about xiaomi from Beijing
And if I'm been
I thought
They were completely nuts
He's in history of phone companies in the world
No stop has ever been successful
And some even predicted
When I first invest in xiaomi 2010
That the only way
Xiaomi can be big in China
Is it Motorola
Ericsson
And Nokia in back the Nokia was extreme dick was
Everywhere in China
All three had to fail
Pastrami
To have a chance to secede
Get out of the habit
The more I heard about
Beijing and been talking about xiaomi
The more you can see how they hire they may have a chance
He's the only team in China
I had experiencing e-commerce
In Brimfield
In software engineering
In
Internet services for gaming
And
Home Design exterior
No one else had all five skills Under One Roof
And this is why I saw they have a they may have a chance
To do something very special not no one else has ever done
Another person in that was key in the show me the history was Hugo Barra
I'm asking it was you being that
Convince him to join xiaomi
And he is now at Oculus at Facebook and actually at the recent CS
Aqueous announced that it will form a partnership with xiaomi to take his VR headset to try no
So how did you first meet you go and how did you convince him to join a Chinese company
That was so fast growing but little know outside of China so the first time I met Hugo
Actually
Back in 2007
Are you outside on Google
I was in charge of the pieces for the China Market
And then you go join a he was the product manager for the
Google mobile app global
So you and I could join him and I was out of the way
Recklessly
He was face at UK and I was Beijing Beijing with me
But I will travel around the world a lot and back amount of Aladdin you know every month or every other month
We met and talked about you know how we feel great products together for Google and
And I would really take the FedEx Mobile products Euro to the market
At the Google time and when we saw the xiaomi Hugo is one of the person who pay a lot of
Attention enough cause interest in to watch I miss doing cuz what we are doing actually building Android phone
Is closely related to what Google history
With Andy Rubin in the mobile access by Google
Tell him and I keep a very close connections and discussions and then conversations and beatings even outside Salvation Army
In
As we
Launch the first song
I was a decent successful about the 2nd of August
Msv started to look at
Expanding beyond the China Market
You know he'll go
Is Sunny the person that comes to my mind that we could work quickly
Que Malaysian we talked a lot about
Yahoo be the best guy to have a starter International
And obviously
YouTube
Squinting of anybody better than Hugo Hogan DDS
I remember the first time I met Hugo
That was in 2006
He came to China with a mutual friend Robin check and that was the first time
They ever come to China
Google was extremely impressive
And impressed
By what was happening in China
Announce before he joined Google in Android
And once you join Google Android
I think the rest is his Sports history
So how long was Hugo at Shelby in
How do you say keep in touch with him
Yes yes of course he's
You don't show me in I was so late 2013
And he left and returned to us
In March April 2000
So he's been with us for over 3 years
I was just reading
And I have to stay at Javier's yet
Huge contributions to International
Especially including Beauty out
Starting
The team-building out
The operations Inc
Gorgeous
The biggest OSU
Forecast today
Yes we do keep records contact with sugar and this last weekend given I met that
CSI Vegas
And I'm in a hehehe all station launched the Oculus products
I miss that lunch events by few hours because of my
Call Fat's anyway
Singapore right after that then
I was at USA
Give me a number mean by we're crossing over
I think China definitely changed
Hugo
To go is now very used to working 9 to 6 if not 7 days a week
Before you join xiaomi
I can tell he wasn't sure what he should join a china-based startup
Even though from the numbers he saw the Android
Xiaomi what's a definite growing fast if not a fascist
I'm on Android phone for a while
But I think China was such a unique situation
That it took him some time to think and decide that
Xiaomi was a perfect opportunity for him to tie China
Cuz he had all the friends and metal Amor people that's comfortable with
Insight shop
And I think are not definitely made a indelible mark on him
So even though he's not back into somebody I think there's a quite a bit of China in him
Yeah and speak some really good Chinese
This guy has got over
Coastal media
In Arleta
Once you guys assemble a team
It's impressive how you make xiaomi war
I know you guys went through a few iterations and also changing working Style
Be in the beginning but more 95
9 to 6 would you doing Innovative work
And then
Very quickly you guys change your time at 6
If not oo7
9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 this week
Or even midnight to midnight seven days a week
I remember the first lunch party but she'll me one that I went to those back on August 16th 2011
Don't forget our date
About two dozen people showed up
And after they drink went through the introduction of the phone
You finally got to the the highlight of the of the show
Kebab lunch party which was the price of the phone
He was a 1999 Hemi be
Or around $310 us
And I assumed he announced the magical figure of 1999
R&B everybody stood up and the clap
He was the first smartphone that was price for the mass Market
With the world-class pek
Anywhere else
You know why you don't find it
Are there after we shall see the whole phenomena around me fence
How good is holding come about
How could
This crate happened so quickly
In a market
As competitive as
China I was probably trace it back to the
Time in v
How about starting a company
Who is able to build
Read highest rated high quality phone
And I'll fight
Viatera Channel
E-commerce wechat
Fantastic road bike India 2010-2011
So direct current customers and allow customers in China to buy a really high-paying quality phone
Smartphones Android
At a price that they have never seen
Pectin all the smartphone
Windows Mobile in Apple iPhone way up there
And also
A couple of free high-spec
Android phone with all price ads for 5000 RMB
MLB able to come up with side smartphone
Respects equal or even higher than some of the high-end phones in the market
And at a Sub-2000 Army range
Yashow customers is it
Physical creation
And the reason that were able to do this is just because of the way. Stopping Ambien
His mother is really around 7 thread customer where you, of course is the most efficient channel that
Established
And everything are not only selling on so proud of you,
But I also
Mlb.com
So it was something that the no other smartphone company
And this is really the Tipping Point
And also remember who was first found
That it's hard to sell online
Back in 2011
That didn't work out very well
It happened right before shot
But it turns out that becomes a person wasn't as simple as to set up a website about a product
Selling so there's a lot of attention shoes operation
Really making the website
Primacoustic shipping warehousing customers
A whole Spectrum
Also remember within the first 34 hours
You got something like 450
1000 phones ordered
Online
He was amazing
Besides a iPhone
I never anything anything like
It was exciting moment but you're also very stressful moment
Turn around
Lightsaber
People call you got what you got to do any more Teen Hunger marketing or see you again sell
That you purposely starve a customers and not giving the phone quickly now
Yeah that was the most stressful things that vampire
Cuz one of the aspect of my business model is two thing of smartphones has
Test the internet customer
Internet users
Who uses the van Econoline
And Frankly Speaking if we can sell a lot more than what we able to produce
You've asked any night companies like Google or Facebook today is it hey would you like to have
An extra 10 million users to use your service they would
Assess that young small startup
We just unable to read the cable on demand
This react
And and then ask about your sister is also.
Improved
Faster
As investor in the previous board member in xiaomi
Back in 2011 I predicted that in your first year
You guys can probably sell 200,000 films
And even do that I would have been extremely impressed
Amber by the end of 2011
You got soul something like over a million phones for the first generation the you are we launching August 16th
Hands that you said 2011
And
For the whole cycle of Maven be sewed
7.1 and 7.2
2012 is great
2013 was even better
2014 was absolutely amazing
Instincts are the plateau in 2015 and 2016 was a tough year
But somehow as a team you guys manage come back in 2017
And I was also impressed sitting in the phone industry
What is your monkey was opened up here we are for sure
I think he's actually a really good. For us to read to it eventually
I think in 2015 and 16 we are running into a couple of challenges
One Challenge
Which I mentioned the previously about the business model of xiaomi
And apparently e-commerce growth
After the first few years in audit 2010-11 tarvish
Reedy high double-digit growth e-commerce growth in China
CNN is not a sauce but the whole entire commas
You, is the holy Spectrum
China
Especially in smartphone
Yes we are seeing
Some amazing
Hi GG
Digit you in trouble did you grow and it's slowing down to becoming a myth
Double digit and then
Load up
So you got musk rose has already passed out
So that's that's one of the one of the big change we seeing
The second change was Seattle's we're seeing is
Often people bought the first generation folks
Smartphone
Mom and a son already
Aware the spec
Performance and enjoy the reading comprising the
That's due to
Part of it due to the xiaomi to pay more attention on the phone
The look and feel you know what material
How beautiful the Foley house in the fullness X-ray camera
Camera pictures
Videos
Idaho Spectrum experience
People to asking much more than this
Oh you know hi spec
You know they can't lullaby
Yeah that the whole special mix
Everything I mentioned passport
So we are learning the changes of the Consumer Electronics
You know where where we haven't haven't seen
And then it's at. Where we started the other sounds like
For xiaomi to Reedy
Keep innovating and out Univision competitors work
We need to do
It'll be okay Integrity structures
How many people we have
How many resources we should be investing
Including out this great components and Technologies
That has edges over
So these are the these are. Where
Although it's still realize he misses up and you're one of my messages
Play eternity I think it's actually a cold in two years.
How we can become stronger
Housing copies the change of a business models Avenue, Sylvania, slowing down not what we should be doing to recover
And then
What we should be doing the capture the next one
You're next
Big Rock
So those are the two year period
Get us to think deeply into
Making xiaomi stronger
Unplugging ovation
I'm resource investing in 90s
And I'm catching the next big
So that was something that we
So show me has an ecosystem approach
When you go into a xiaomi store you not only can buy phones and computers but also
Air purifiers ricecookers headphones umbrellas
How does could you explain how the Seacoast
System works and how do you ensure a quality control of these products
They shall me invest in because they obviously have an impact on your brand
So
This is something that came up
About two or three years after we launched the first phone
And the discussions internet between the founder of Scientology myself and cabal the founders was
If you look at the success of our model on smartphone
You can generalize it and say okay
What we're doing is not asphalt but
We can
Take consumer electronics we get to coyotes
You know s Topeka opportunity
They can we apply what we have done you know it's my fault
Including settings are the customers really commas
And how can we take these and generalized
Adam Pugh
Bigger business
That cuz you might really
So this is what the ecosystem here comes out
And of course you know there's a way that discovered a discussion in trying to say whether we should be doing beauty products on sale
Or whether we should be leveraging
Bestar phenomenon
China
And read it to me in a way where we can use the investment at 11
And Legend being a really really great and reinvested himself and also instrumental for 9mm self
He told me you got a chest and he himself has Led Zeppelin
To do that used to leverage that you masked man
Sa-2
Tokyo this ecosystem
And this becomes relief active
The way we do it
Is we have a team of Rita talented product managers
Each are responsible for some keravada products
And the Parliament is just Wilbur crocifissa ecosystem company
To build
And design the Box
Starting mr. This feature design
And I will come together to say okay what features we would like to have
What will be the look and feel
I thought we would like to have in the car
We like them to have
I sent you her the same design philosophies
Yesterday you look back and look at all the
What if we have fires in an air purifier is a scooters
I will rice cookers they all look the same
Driven you know by audio engineering
You know they would do that manufacture Supply Chain management
And then we have them to launch their products to the market
We do the tech what we do the CO2 Market
Marketing sales
We put them in a store in the way where we designer store S1 store
Because the Milwaukee and they will be able to see in a phone's being the center and then
L'Occitane products
You are on the phone
It's being put together right right next to each other
The farm
You know
What team is OAR
You know how I feel
So those are those are that the general idea
And you become so reflective because you not only motivate
The eagle system companies to redo great products because they are and we met that that that intrapreneurs write their own picture
We had a small shower
But you don't show me green and motivate a team because we had we don't have over a hundred teams in repeating these different products
Any gifts
A really really good spectrum of products
On our website
That's how you know the customers
Any loss.
You know what happened was going to walk in and look at all the products
I will keep
What's amazing to me is that when you guys first start trying to
Gilmore products Beyond phones
Whereas he took
Samsung and Sony
To do everything in-house
You guys develop ecosystem
An ecosystem had a network of very hungry Chinese entrepreneurs
Who are with very willing to learn from xiaomi
You did everything that I can
The focus on their core products what carrier Neshaminy brand
11 to the xiaomi ecosystem of suppliers
To help him descale
As a result
You have so many new offerings for users everyday every week
Every month from your ecosystem of portfolio companies
Both online and offline retail store
So that leaves days when we sent out of the xiaomi store at Seaport walk in
Big frequency of store visits
It just a lot higher
The ne
Store for other phone companies
In the world
And is also one of the
Learnings we had in the last couple
Challenges
And let me see the father of
Bahamas
And it was okay well
How to optimize a business model
Fed up doing everything
You know we realize
The most powerful pieces mother of show me wasn't only to see,
It was Sarah and I was a kid
Set the right means because I was sunny, is much more efficient so I can schedule the customers
But
Let me have a store
It's if it's a hydrogen ion store that doesn't attract and plus the store what allows customers to her
Atarax
Looking like direct interaction with the product
You know any given day out there taking the penis and watch a movie
Hey you look show me how they can try it and they can decide whether to
But as long as distorted as an operator bios
Xiaomi designs
Everything is
Xiaomi where we can offer the products
At the same price as those being offered online
Take us to the most
When did they have an experience of the product store
So it's a shelter up becomes optimize speed
Online off
Do you ever see guys carry any products does not Brennan show me inside of stores or on your websites Wheatley do
Reduce some of the
But the products are
Where can fleas live
End
All the products today that are selling in the mist or are being built by that you can still come in
Yeah most of them are carrying the Migra
Some of it
Doesn't carry to be home brand but you has the same Quality Bar
Hysterectomy Home Products
Xiaomi products and also they are all be with
Burrito Company
That believes in the same pieces
During a past speech Legend was compare xiaomi to Muji
Which is very interesting to me because Muji is kind of like the exemplification of
New retail where there is
High quality beautiful design
Relatively affordable
Cost
And everytime I go inside
Emoji store end up buying something even though I
Don't have I don't need anything and I think it's the same with xiaomi
When I go to China always go to a salvage yard and I always end up buying something
So
How how fast are those xiaomi Jazz expanding in China how many stores are there how many cities
Are you guys in
So
Today we had 287 stores
It took us two years to get together this number
I was fully in charge of telemarketing from 2014 to
Just coming back
I want to change my door again back to the ID field
And one of the major task when I was three sets of marketing was to be all this week
Cuz we're seeing more clear
A customer trends
China
That all customers
The only shopping online
But they will be they will take that families you know kids
My husband's wife
Spend time machine shopping mall during weekends
Watch a movie have a good night
KOHLER stores including which stores
Verizon
And I'm in a unicorn memory distortion
Appointment
A lot of customers
They know everything smart
But they didn't know we have so many
Cuz you made it honey products
So very common expression
Show me a show me a pot and it is not spending time to to look at every single products
And then they become they become really super super interesting and some of these products
Cuz iPod products Spectrum
Goes from a product that sells for at least a couple
RMB
10000 Yuan
You know more expensive products
Like we are sweet we have 750 in
Projector as TV set-top box plus speaker
Here for the images and even those products
In the marketplace
That
Acai weed high-quality and sale at such a low
Set alarm at 10:15
34e size
So it generate is really high interest for customers to
Spend time in browser on the products and eventually there's a okay
Taking a bye
Italia MVP
Then hey they remember seeing those products in xiaomi home and Israelites
So this with her presence really gives customers a deep impression on
You know xiaomi is not
That's my phone
Swaffle puss
Manything
Coyotes schedule
Basically from generation to grab a smartphone
Those who are born after 1985 or 1990
Show me how to become the brand for them to go to when they first don't have their first apartment
First job
And first time they be on their own outside of college
Cuz everything I wanted
You haven't from xiaomi and your speaker system of companies
And it all fit the budget
The products of beautiful design
And of high-quality
Well that's a go get there someday
Along the lines of new retail in Brooklyn they came first
When did Japan in late 2000s
Look at Mucci
Uniqlo
I think back then it was already the seed
DaVinci gossip Hildebran that'll be the national bird for Chinese consumers with many products
How did you think about going International
And replicate your Nissan model
Xi'an China
Yep so that's also the opportunity right and if I
The last two-and-a-half years
We started by Indian business back in 2000
What's the first time in Hugo and I went out to eat
Who is a general manager
4 Hour Fitness
And then we built at 2 tomorrow morning
And now
Azshara missionaria number one smartphone
And as we are spending on
Business in India mostly really,
We also at about the same time
Maybe a slightly
After we started that
The Whitney retard
Operation in China
Reset at the beauty of a retard
And it wasn't
We know how to buy a hundred stores but the Indus already smarter
Guess it doesn't have the number of products that we have
But the retail presence in Europe
Midas stores are selling anywhere between
Ford 4000
Even pretty shoes number for
A store that's about
Six seven
And so the business is growing is growing in a way that way
We just don't
I'll individuals that you wet rule over 6
In 2017
And we believe
The growth
I will continue
Probably not success again
But I think this year we should be able to
Achieve another
If you're looking to launch more ecosystem products
India
What are the planets away accidentally
Is I know whether we should be launching at
Smart TV
Which Bollywood
Directions
Air purifier
Does largest product I should wear suitable for developing
So we see these this whole opportunity in international developing countries where
Use my phone if some of industry is about couple of years your boss 3 4 years behind China
So you right at the verge of taking
And people are starting to Caroline about
So the owl keeper eyes.
Also I have a apple
So going forward would you consider it I'm expanding show me into the more developed markets
For example by working with
Telecom carriers especially with the recent
Huawei AT&T deal which was
Killed by political pressure in the US
How do you think
Xiaomi
If I end when will xiaomi ever have a product in the US so we we have a head
In the last couple years working on
Indian markets Indonesia baggage
Officially entered
Back 2 months ago
And also southeast Asia countries
As far as Eastern Europe we are number three in Russia
Now we are
And also I Ukraine I think we are also in between your
So all these
Eastern countries and developing countries are
Just a few years behind China
So this is the market that
Enjoying Pascal's we we have already have our hands for it
40 world countries
Just about
Two two weeks ago we open the first door in Spain
Is a store that is open by us and our Distributors and so far the stores doing great
It was a it was really a small trial
NNU seems to be
It seems to us that customers are really anticipating the Sham Apartments
Developed countries
So it's a good result so far all the way short
Beat up to it to give it a little more time to see how customers are reacting to our custom
My phone says when somebody gets them
But if this continues to go well I think developed country is Within Reach
I was suddenly faced a starting with the Western Europe countries
That that we were looking at
And follow probably by
North America
18 maybe sometime
I think one of the reasons xiaomi has become so so
Successful is because it has a very unique approach to marketing
Could you share with us what is a me fan or Misa in Chinese
At what about xiaomi mix
Those magnificent so enthusiastic
It's almost like you're being done online
Especially nowadays
Wendy's forum
What will we fill out at the
At the very beginning of xiaomi
What people are mostly getting on to the forums to
This to
Try the ladies version of me why
Salvation Army
Off the Android
System and I can download MIUI in Elantra
Jackson on the forums
It is help us
Got the first group of greedy Royal use
And as we start launching
Devices
And
From this Farm we expand into a lot of the online social media
You know we leverage way bar
And followed by a WeChat you know friends in circles
And follow by cheat codes on
Belarus a lot of these social media platforms to do a marketing in
And it's
It's mostly of
Between my friends and customers
Starting biking 1011 S&M
We keep doing this
Map of Alaska
A lot of those even today
Today for instance like
We have these events where we call a popcorn Yuan
We haven't all my popcorn events
In different cities
You know animals video maybe every few weeks
And then me fencing each of the Cities
Together and they would share their feedback
How to use satin xiaomi products
Especially a scrap I promise like spending Beyond smartphone
Dariush
Passionate about some of the new
Now
At the last two years as we're spilling out retail stores
This a slightly change
Skills for every single retail stores that will open a new city
The movie fences that City would come join us
In the opening ceremony and I myself as well
Key mapping out the store
I've been to many minutes
An actual person to pick many of the location of the stores by self
I'm and out there you know
Opening stores
I'll doing some weekend
Search events
I'll meet friends to come along
You know they will see this as an opportunity to get to know us more personally SOS getting to know Adam Eva
So he becomes a sort of a platform for me
Get us each other and get to know each other and also get to know a lot more about tell me about
And we also started to see
Similar things happening in India
Asia
And also in Spanish
And one of the reason we pixpaint open the first door
Country was because
Be found at in Spain behalf
A lot more
So I'm spending a business in different countries
This is going to be stupid
What marketing
Events
Events in the US
Ice machine go to the media
May not understand
Most of the things you just said
So is easy for him to say that xiaomi is a copycat of Apple
When you hear this
How do you deal with it
How do you try to get them to see that it is different
Okay so I'm from several aspects first of all I think that's it comes to a question with Pope
I would mostly be
Intact
Everything show cattle
Every year from the ndk
From software hotline
We happy
They're having
Fighting
2 / yellow
Delphi / 6000
Over half of these are
Despicable
Becomes a shoot acid for xiaomi
Solaria nishitetsu yuan originated
IRS office
How is Ally Commerce
Second Use when you look at the way we push innovation
A lot of the population
Initiative
A spec in mm
August 20th
June 25th
We launched chamonix
When velocity mmx4
The whole media including vessel media
They look at the camera phone
Jesus
This is exactly what they were
Expecting
You know my name
Xiaomi who came up with this phone
That has no face
Top
And Anacortes Mix phone was pretty revolutionary
We won't be sake suppliers
9 genius
How many of these is Innovations actually on engine repair
And this this Mixed Martial cat
Pretty prestigious Hawaii
So
All these are something that being
Built-in table
And you can look at the product offering off the xiaomi the whole hotel me mother
We have
Are Labrada products
Mix in all you couldn't
TVs and laptops
Air purifier
Wearables
I'm over a thousand
And these are these apartments is that
Opium design and driven by
Xiaomi
Designers
Ecosystem
All together
So I would say we are probably to The Other Extreme of
The Embrace openness
A lot
Android phones
Play it's all open
You know we have these iot
A protocol
Where are we
Encourage all the iot companies to build in
And understand Us shopping open
So any other
Companies for brooding
Gadgets or
Appliances are more than welcome to
Turd
Modules and imbue into their products
Any becomes all connected device
It's a open standings
I love your pussy
So
I myself as anything that
Is that all
Being like apple I think that's a stop
Right unn this will probably take some adjustment and also for people who don't know us
If they are able to come back and look at a store
So you guys launched the remix to it's a day before Apple launch iPhone 10
How do you think it went
And what was the rationale for doing that
I mean you could do it again would you have done anything differently
I think the date is probably just coincidence because we use it has to set the alarm stay
Fuel Metallica
Just a lock
How to make stories
Is it again
Another EDM
We tok mix 1
Which is really in the way
Henry SF we can do to make
The mix more practical to Reedy
Allow people to buy is what makes one
Is
Because it's so hot
And
Hopefully the whole cycle
We just couldn't keep up
And they becomes a shoes complaint for
I'm in the absence of Light how can we make
Mix 2
Better than this one in yet
No alarm
So so he's been lot of
Time in engineering
Field
I'm and it's also pretty well received device
And we also improve a couple
User experience
Including
Price of one of the complaints that people have
What is a mix 1
The back camera it doesn't take video
It takes good
Good images
So I mix to reading room
Camera XP
And you compare the Imaging
You have an excuse
That any other phone company World iPhone
Apple included
Because your ecosystem products
It's just so comprehensive
Some people would say xiaomi is already number one
Internet of things or iot company in the world
What is the iot strategy
And are you working on your Alexa
What would I look like okay so we just launched while a few months back
We just wants our first smart speaker
It's called Cheyenne jobs
And that speaker is able to
Drive
You know we are Chinese
DIYs
Almost all out
You can ask the council turn on and off
TVs
You can ask
So I can clean it to suction your lips
So it's a very natural fit
Biote
What are we going to be like Alexa systems
We have discussed that in
I actually got
Assistant
Enchiladas
And now with over 80 million Connecticut
Show me Island
Remix
We also commissioning not only the smart speakers but
How can how can we more effectively control all this
Well-managed
And be stupid
There's a scenario where you were
My speakers at home
Places when you are way
How do you really control
So are these are something that we have been
Working on
And one of the angle and looking eye with your promises
As I having all these connected devices
Either with you
Or at home
I like what
It'll provide a very unique opportunity for us to do a lot of
Data mining
Based on the data that is already promised.
And of course we put privacy I have everything
But with you sad content
We like we are but a towel in on a bigger scale
You know how air quality looks like
In all
Major big and small cities
You know how I would have pollution landscape look like
In spaghetti squash
Amino
What city
What was the population are more inclined to exercise
Well with the amoeba information and also does Moscow information you will be the CEO you know it looks like this
You know China people I'm waiting time to exercise and run then another problem
Does desiderata
A data mining opportunities
And this is why the AI
Artificial intelligence
Algorithms
And I believe this is actually where the future
Show me recently launched a partnership with Baidu in Ai and iot
Why did you choose to partner with Baidu could you explain more about the thinking behind the partnership
I wasn't person in charge of this partnership but I think in general we are partnering with many companies on
And by Dosa and he's one of the companies that have it you may as well have it in
Annie's a very natural part Partnerships
And I think in the future AI was Sunday coming play
Setting the smartphone has anybody that's my phone it would be the
Biggest python for AI
Imagine your phone can lolitas
A communication device
What is device by
You can listen
And you can watch
You know thinking great images and photo
And it
Is a device that always with you
So this is a problem that we believe will be one of the few sharpshooter
And of course you know where your home Oklahoma OT devices
I wish the gadgets
People ready
Can people catch a lot about
You know
Exercising
Vivid
Healthy Lifestyles
All these opportunities way I can come
How many people in the US have the impression that
Shelby's main differentiation point is affordability
Do you think that's still the case
Today probably but as we are we are coming closer to
Launching a product in USA I think it would
Change a lot of customers
Perceptions
Some of some of my friends in us when they
Why they got a Hands-On some well products
You know Dad
They did love it so much and it's not
Cuz we are not sending any of these in US
Products you know it.
I still remember one time I I brought Mascoutah
Mi scooter
Yes over to Boston
Students in the classroom
And if they love it
Is a scooter on Android
But you can actually control it with a remote control
You didn't even have his follow you you know whenever you go
I'm anemic smile turns left and right
Following your about 2 feet away from you right
You can even have it
You know I carry Goods
Around
Where will you go
Is really a cool piece of and of course when they hit when they
At the very last I told him like using only cost $400
They like crazy
But he was really that you know dieta products out that way.
So then how would you describe Sammy's company culture
And what are some unique management practices that you
Have seen or started a xiaomi that's different
From Western companies you've been with
I'm in are there any practices you brought yourself me from either Google or Microsoft
Nnn over a lot of a lot of my city
Not that Michael's having Google engine it didn't work out of date they washable
Yunnan
I founded this company together with leaking out of co-founders
And
Chinese Peking I think the last 70 years
I was able to find a way to fit my life in the
Yeah I don't know how
3D
Makes any sense
Kid there's no one like that and tomato paste to fit your life
Yes and tells her that a lot of US dollars in China
I will achieve
Some cut some of us a test
And and also and smartphone last
Most of you probably know it's really competitive
I'm in one product
So you really have to really push
The Innovation and not just yourself but also
DanTDM
Operational
Person
Not even being in a store
Just thinking how can we build a store
Different from and better than any other
And that's how
I'm pretty sure. All the founders anime
Happy monkey
Nothing at that actually very similar to mini of the city
Cuz I I Know Tab know a lot of them you know what Google used to be Sodom and still a second company
And I think innovation
It is in the blood
This is what
Champion
Companies house
I remember the first time I took huc
To meet you guys back in the summer of 2010
They walked away thinking that you guys are us
Talented
And knowledgeable
Aswad innovative
Has any Silicon Valley company we have ever met
And may not have a lot of HTC engineers
Barbara Palvin
So on a more fun note
You are a success story of an engineer turned manager and founder
You change a row a few times but it's not always easy for engineers to
Make it managers are founders
What advice do you have for a Chinese engineers in the US or China
Who may want to start their own company
What kind of things do they need to watch out for
I'll be happy to share some money
Myself
I think one of the big running is
It's not a choice
To say oh I would rather do
IND
Products
And I don't I just don't want to do
Cuz you have no choice
Company
You just have to do whatever his name
Commissioner
You know you've asked me if I have been doing engineering
I myself and
Joint pain
Centrelink references
Is what I have been
But when it comes to
Xiaomi this is the company that I have found it
When
Assassin operational marketing is
The job.
You have to take over
Uses of pickle
And then you just have to find a way to
Make yourself
Enjoy it and personally I am not
Like
I don't like
Spending time in shopping mall
Before Ayatollah marketing job in
I will be with my family and I will be sitting
How much are waiting for
The family of sha'ban
And have no interest at all in in retail
But I'm
Havana realize
Xiaomi we have to be at the retail presence
You know I force myself to
To stop
Learning return
And that
Actually travel over to the Tokyo Tower
Hong Kong too many places and you and you are sometimes when we enter the soil stop looking at
Oh why do they design the
The bazaar
Why do they use these types
What the lion looks like
What's a material that they use to build a table
You know how did they design the store so that people walk in
Maximize the outcome
And then it was interesting right the first
At the first few months it was
You know I have no idea how to build
But as I stop eating out the first or the second store and then I see the
The turnout the store
Improving
The stove
Team is actually become sexually funk
And anything for any people who
Who wants to do a startup
This is something that you just have to
Whatever it takes
I don't think it's it's any of ice but it is a learning that I have
So if you've something to remember I even the earlier days when
When we don't have any
And have You Met My remember that
You don't have any CFOs
I do about few years back
Penny delivery
Holidays in the first year we don't have any friends
Religion and I said hey we need to talk to
SMU masters of
Apology message xiamen and one of them
Go put together
Pieces forecast
I've no idea and how to do a piece of work at it
Look up some books
So I didn't talk to my wife
A test that my wife actually had a small business
She had a small business back in the US
So she has some experience putting together
You know something you know the finance forecast so she give me the sex especially
Spectiv
What's your present course or Saturday with your rent yours is not right and that's it so I took that
And then I feel the very first
A company forecast vs forecast
On that success
There are a lot of great Chinese engineers in the US
Increasingly even the PM's are doing well
In Silicon Valley
Many Chinese internet companies have set of R&D centers in the US
Ben do you see show me doing that or do you have more in the u.s. in the future
Exorcist
Yes we have our first office in San Diego told you what's going on with us
Be not I think enough
I'm at and I think we should ask as we spending more business hours
China
Expression you getting close to enter
American
Does Ashley's having pool and symptomatic
1970 typing
So for the last part of this podcast will have a bunch of Rapid Fire questions
The first one is
What was the best and worst decision that you have ever made
Decisions I might have made some bad decisions but I don't know how to wait
Wait at the bust
What were the best decisions I would certainly say that this decision.
Kicking back
It's probably
Pathogen
My life
What motivates you to wake up each morning and what keeps you up at night
What are you excited and worried about
I think the part that keeps me really motivating everyday
I done got a half
Lenny the latest Technologies
But it's the learning
Comes with
My
Operational jobs in sales
That I know how to redeem your gravy
That I know how to do a
Living campaign
Running from
Punished
You know suppliers
I am also learning from
And how did I know you know
I'm pretty sure you know it's the business of Jamaica growing
What I worry I think that's all I think that at that award on a daily basis
Today I asked my role changes again at 2 months
IPhones
Laughing a lot of
Wedding version
How can we fit in
And what customers would like
Next Generation
To all these
Questions.
And thinking
Even
I am I even dream of something
A lot of things I actually
Operational
And he's also what comes with the way
It's on a daily basis
It's a
No you don't feel that
You don't really feel excitement
But you would have the
Your day today
Obituary
Operation
Hitting you
And you said
And be optimistic Turtle to encourage yourself
What's something you read recently that touched you a lot whether it's a bug or
Article
Yes oh so I read a lot of books when I have time
And I like that
I like the bred
The latest when I finish this
Should I
The hittite related
Racing xiamen
Astana company
Play all the details
Like how you feel
Operational issues
Challenges
Sounds so familiar
It was quite a few years
Yeah so you can recommend me some new books has
Okay thank you so much pain it's a pleasure to have you here
Hu7989
San Jose International listening to this episode
By the way we also produces weekly email newsletter English also called 9 + 6
Roundup of the week's most important happenings
Intec in China subscribers informative and fun to read the news
Original content and Analysis from Zara and me
Describe at nine 6. GG bc.com
Play stage Venture Capital firm based in Silicon Valley on high in Beijing we have been partnering with leading technology
Entrepreneurs for the past 18 years from seed to pre IPO with 3.8 billion dollars in cash
Reminds my prostate funds GTA V invest in gold we minded entrepreneurs in consumer internet e-commerce
Frontier tag in Enterprise
GTA V has invested over 280 companies with 29 IPOs in 22 unicorns
Orfila companies include
Airbnb Alibaba C trip Didi chuxing Domo hashicorp Hello by
House keep
Slack Square Hotel
Wish social white white and others find out more at 2 gvtc.com
Do you have any feedback on this podcast
Or would like to recommend a gas please email us at 996 at Gigi bc.com
This podcast is co-produced Battlefront and business partner
Kaiser kuo the host of the wonderful Seneca podcast it covered China economic political
And cultural issues