Sound the alarm at 9 in the evening
Hi there
Welcome to the nine at six podcast
Brought to you by ggv capital and co-produced by the Seneca podcast
On the show interview movers and shakers
China's tech industry
As well as Tech leaders
Weather us China
Cross-border perspective
My name is Sunstone and the managing partner at ggv Capital
And I've been working at startup investment in them in both in us and China for the past 20 years
My name is Zahra Jones an investment Analyst at ggv Capital
Jennifer Moore journalist
Why is the show called 96
6 is the work schedule that many Chinese Founders have organically adopted
That is 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
To us
996 captures intensity
Drive
In speed
Of Chinese internet companies
Many of which are moving faster
But even their American counterparts
On the show today we have gin deal
Senior Vice-President I bite is one of the fastest-growing Chinese Tech Giants that has made a lot of news
Both literally and figuratively
Most people know by Diaz buys Flagship product Sierra Tokyo
Unused aggregation app that uses artificial intelligence to recommend content to his millions of users
1 average spent 74 minutes per day on the app
The Guidance also owns four out of the top six short video apps in China
And has also demonstrated its overseas ambition
With the acquisition of the US for a video app Flipagram
And most recently merging with musically
The top-ranking short video app in many countries with hundreds of millions of users
And also with ggv portfolio company
Should you be cold on musically cisb
And see
And I've been on board of the company
Since 2015
About the fight dance musically merger
Tgv has become a shareholder in by dance as well
On the Shelf we'll talk about significant this deal
As well as how others got to know each other
And why we think that hotel
Maybe
Best position
Chinese startups
To go global
Welcome to the show thank you for inviting me really my pleasure
Thank you you've had a very interesting career you grew up in China went to study abroad in New Hampshire during High School
And I came back to China for college and then attending law school at Berkeley
And it worked at a Silicon Valley lawyer and then come pick him back to Asia for work
Before taking a leading position at Woodbridge China and most recently joining bytedance
So that start with your first formative experience when you first came to the us as
Houston
High School
You went to
Interest-only
A predominantly white town in New Hampshire
What was your biggest takeaway from that experience and white. Particular state
I think it's
For me I was 17 you know what I want to
Compare New Hampshire I went to a local high school
Who stayed with English-speaking host families at situation family for the entire year they have switches I think they're louder
I think the entire this when you experience is really eye-opening
Change poem
Decided to take a gap year
I guess
You don't want to look back I guess the biggest takeaway is
I was able to learn the other side of the
Sorry
Antiviral aih
I give examples
You know I still remember that when I went to
Learn history
I was a senior yeah that was a senior year I went to
At school and at 2 pastry class
And what I learned about Chinese history
What I learned when I was in China right now
Remember that I even got into a huge debate with my classmates and teachers
WhatsApp
It is wrong
And I said why and that actually
Couldn't you know English wasn't very good I couldn't really articulate the reasons but what I found out that they said one sentence
I remembered
Today that they said
You said that because you were taught that
I think that's very important
Is just
You don't you know I am fortunate enough to involved in a very small community and tripping or community
That you don't come see us a lot of established
Entrepreneurs of tech companies in one of the topics at today
We spend alot of time all actually is about AI artificial intelligence in education
Education conference
This afternoon and then eating our CEO and founder would have a conversation fireside chat
Connor rental
And in that group we discussed
What a I going to change to education
What topics going to be replaced
What skills are subjects
Better actually
Not really
A2000 forward-looking as technology develops
So I think education is very important
And Anna and I think there were few people
Who actually had the opportunity
To learn Chinese history in China and then also had
Same exposure in the US what they say about Shang Dynasty
The Chinese history
Ymml strong supportive
Having kids
To expose what emerged
In-N-Out only multi-language but also you don't want that Rose
Emoji
Culture educational system
So that not only it's not about the language is about the information Avenue and the channels of
How you receive information
I think that's very important so
I always wanted to hear other side of the story
To be able to form my own argument to have them work
Objective
Veal
I think that's
Very important and I think about
I think a lot of us who study abroad at an early age also resume with that
The feeling that our opinions are shaped by how we grew up and how we were taught
Yeah so you studied law and wondering
Cuz you said before that you like risks and Ventures below is a pretty risk-averse
Career so how how why did you choose study law and become a lawyer
Was actually a lawyer a patent lawyer that was
Vietnam very renowned patent lawyer in China
And if you look at he's you know that's all you have to take borrow and get a
Allow certificated and be able to practice his license and the Hues Chinese license number is
Number two
Anyone ever lawyer
Yeah he's a patent lawyer and he started he's
Law career
Inches
50 years old and he actually want to hang
I started a patent firm
And in his seventies he started the first
Limited partnership
Law Firm
In China
Spell independent
Community
So I guess and he is to me you know he's just not
He's not
Those typical lawyers.
You see that you know a lot of
Deed execution you notice
Follow whatever the
Patent lawyer in China
He is a lawyer with
Chihuahua intrapreneurship
Amy my interval naturally
You know I was learning from
I think he now you know
My own is also lawyer on Patchen and my
Younger youngest cousin
The other one too
Rental law school in the state
A lot of our family members actually wanted to become a lawyer but not traditional
Cuz you know you know
We magic legal aid lawyer profession is never the flower with big suitcase
And paperwork
Attract will mad at everything
Kind of a lawyer it's to me is that smile
Impression of being a lawyer
So when you first
What was your field
And how did you change from that
Going to pack
I think
I was very lucky that I went to law school in California
Yeah Berkeley so you know that's a very intrapreneur
Chevy Malibu
Diane and I want to let you know the phones that work that are all those
Typical Santa Maria law firms on the East Coast that they even have
Comedian vest
Lennar at the ambassador of the clients fail to pay
Cashier
SOI was interesting that I was
Very much involved I was a corporate lawyer so I represent clients
Synoptic company
Go to the board meeting
Can help them sideways
And help them enter into China
Took them public in the US
Tsmma and also took them private
Add a couple years I started my career at Wilson sonsini as a corporate
Robin Carmen Chan
In mm
And I still remember that most of our clients back then were
VC funding
In the US are trying to adjust
I think she started just started and we hope to quit us
Making sure it's a good China and representer
It is a look over kind of the portfolio company they decided to invest in
And then later we
Represent antreprenor School study MBA students phones Denver
Eater Charleston
Second-handed cars come to the office to help
And later on we started representing
Those Chinese intrapreneurs
Cool
Study abroad actually starting receiving
Funding's
Local VC
Chinese music Chinese
Or maybe
I would say
A China arm of USBC but have a
Stronger China present
Black Nike ID to yours
Idg
Quiet
You know a tendon in his one of them as well
DCM China and although
And then later on we started representing intrapreneurs
That's also kind of a conscience
Option
But for a law firm said we wanted to go
Grow with the company
And then we started companies
That was even some some Chinese Chinese Reese's intrapreneurs started
Have an interesting more diverse
Background some of them
Never study
Just grabbing some of them can barely speak
So that you see the changes
Very very entry
Kissing that you go to the sport meetings first
Do you know the board meetings of very rigid
Incorporate governor
I just like typical us companies you have a very sound headboard
He go through the routine
And then you have to
A little bit relax
Board environment
I don't they sometimes the board would hold a meeting on WeChat
All the changes you think is
Very very true
Dizzy all the time
Felices
We sing it Versace more companies
From China
That has a mixed management
To be a
As well as hog weight
Baltimore comes to going out
And it sucks when you have people who
Bicultural
Multi culture
Do you see that as a sustaining Triton
Would we see more of those companies
Or do you think of Music musically invite dad's arm or Ally
I would definitely think that
All the management team today at
Especially in Texas
Stackers whatever
More diverse
What members in Altamonte
That people have different background
And also have to say that just being in kind of the intrapreneur side
That have seeing you know
Intrapreneurs leaders actually unconsciously
A wanting to diversify their management
Someone to talk to me
Yeah yeah it took a little gap between my TD and vitodens and they can talk to
And did you notice that while we just wanted to really that works of our management team
You know what they do have this implanted
In the mind.
Because people given back today even today that we hire a lot of people
Very interesting facts
You never know what they got a boy
I probably some of that
I'm one of them and we do have a couple weiner management team
Bad we recently hired that I think a very you know they're not dating
Not have technology background
And some of them not even family like China but they come in and they boys
Very interesting different perspectives when we discussed
Things and I think that's very important
And that's very healthy Trend that you see
As a company to become immortal
You moved from the legal career to Tech
I'm wondering what was that learning curve like for you cuz it's
A very different profession
I guess is
Depends on what type of lawyer
Thought you were if you are corporate lawyer you know most of the time
To some extent you were more like
Acting
General counsel
And I was
Is actually bald
All the two
Yucas tacos
I don't 6 months
I remember that I was pregnant with my first child
I stayed in haidian tonight
Commute every day
Fragment you know until they find a replacement I was there at
Tubing ball with you
Operation
Yes
So and I think as
Service provider
That you want me to
Just south of
If you hadn't chosen the UC Berkeley
Would you end up being worth
Have you gone to a different Law School
What does any of the album
East Coast
Was you end up being with
I think probably not
I think the location matters
You know sometimes I ask my husband actually went to Carnegie Mellon
And then he worked
Chad Bloomberg New York
Sometimes you know that's the same question himself
What TV you don't end up at on what street or somewhere it's going to be
Variegated
Sweating location matters and I do think that
That you don't because I want you
Explain the four that you want to be the one making the decision and not just advising
People how to make decisions at what point did you realize
That's what you wanted
I was actually preparing last night I Was preparing my speech that I going to give
Do graduate students at chinois tomorrow afternoon
It's all about entropy
Panache a vital part of
Teenager Pandora as the owner not a renter
And I think everyone not everyone can become
A founder of account
Bedeviled why should
Have
The central partnership
When they work at a fast growing type
Apartments that you need to
Take as much ownership as you could
And if you are you know you have
Auctions you a part of the company
So you are making decisions and you are responsible
For moving things forward
I think this mentality
Not only to me I think to everyone who works at by dad
That they should feel that they're making the dish
Decisions
And they're moving things forward
And they are taking responsibility or liability
You know to bear the consequences
It is been a couple years at
Uber what made you
To decide to
Make.
2 or 4
Reform camp
Pennywise
Discuss as you know
In the history of Silicon Valley companies no internet company
Succeeded in China
So what
Make this one
To be the one
For you too
Welcome back
I think
Uber
You know those
Type companies fast-growing
Startups
Uber
Is
The most
A Chinese Chinese
I think I'm with vitodens and I do think my dad's
Tumi
And you know I pay scale
And down
And in size I think it's definitely the most Silicon Valley
In China
Intersection of the two wolves
Yeah yeah in both cases
So I think it's very you know I know so we don't I know a lot of people
Yoart before my work sad it was also advising providing legal advice to Uber
And we know, investors
Wait we just knowing best Rivers
Uber
And down
And I think I met Travis
Him and I think Wilbur is
Just very intrigued
That they
Very believer
Kwelitv
An original
So if you look at you know all the Uber China Inn
Collies
China time
Dad they all have very interest
Auditing firm
Interesting
But I think they all have sure that they
Compassion
An intrapreneur
And they wanted to originated
Earthquake
As opposed to just
It'll borrow things where what where
Row by row experience
Something are so that's why you know
You see a lot of creativity
Stop
The idea was in
How did your first meet Travis
We have, fans and I think they were in China
Anonib
Talking to
The winter of
So introduced through mutual friends
Yeah introduce food
Peter said before that one of your probably the shipment that we were was being able to cultivate a very amazing team of
Employees
Wondering like how did you find
The team members and where are they now the ex Uber China employees
People answer though I had to
Cuz I'm in a Uber in us has
Share of controversies
That's not a topic
Pocket podcast of some of that are questionable and incredible
But after the Didi Uber China deal
We actually gvsu hosted events
Featuring some of the team members from Uber Tennessee
And we were
I'm very impressed
What a quality
And the
Integrity of the
I was working by saying Deedee was very proud of DD as well obviously
Amazing
But it was very interesting to see a collection of talent
In a Silicon Valley
China King kind of
Originality inability
Decisions
Dare to be great
So
This is my dog's question for this
This one's very into
How was your day going
Put the team together
Gables building
The works
China Study
You know I maybe I can share one instance that I never really shared with other people
That's what I want to hear
Is that so I remember that one
One travel
Was he in the Beijing
How to announce a merger
Piano 2 hours
Have white rhino
And when did they
That I
Andy Ruiz
We are all very proud
Ubers
Maliweb
And out
What if
Jayden Realty
Support
You are such a
And I'm
And Travis
Pofu William
Appreciate
And learn.
Do becoming part of
White wine
Adidas reflection
Actually pull out the
Because Sherwood
Copper wire you know principal
Haitian
It'll be a owner not a renter
Make magic
Meritocracy and tone stepping
Optimistic leadership
Always be hustling
Super Pawn
Let Builders build
Baseball bats
Customer obsession
And at Champions mice
You know those are very deeply implant
Into every single
Vagina
And the very part of you know they asked actually the executed
But ya didn't God
Tyga that everybody's father
Some of them you know some of them actually join a bike sharing business
Concession about that right
But I think they definitely carried all those spirits
So how did you first meet evening
CEO of Vikings
I started about you know
Eating personality a little bad and I might leave me alone time ago you know what night I think me and I went to
I was with Uber and we went to speak at the same conference
A teeming actually which had at me and I didn't know where he got my WeChat
Not really searchable can we talk before after
I think it's kind of out of nowhere I I didn't
Try that again Seattle what year was this
2015 presidency
The first time we met and then
China
WeChat at me
I might I didn't remember I think I
Chetak
He's speech is before me
You know I do to remember the details
Best thing about me is very
Give me an introvert
Indian by tweeting
You're not very social and he doesn't like
So we out and socialize with other people
When it comes to a cootie
Leesburg Christian
Aggressive persistent I don't know how many times he comes to you
This little cafe you near where I live near my apartment in Beijing you know the east side I should also
Play side of where the company is where he lives
He's very persistent
Remember after the merger I think the second aliens with music can we meet
MSN log people will say hey
You know how I take care to give you some
You know I think that's interesting you can always come to recruiting has a even today has persisted
Become very social
And he is actually very open-minded
To embrace people with different culture Edition back
You know I would be impressed with that
So what what what was the reason that he used to convince you or what were you persuaded by
Have to admit that I didn't know much about
The product I'm acting
I'm a user actually I'm going to another one
No I was using over
Yeah
And I was using my mom used to joke that you know that you love
He likes to see me joined Hotel because
That provides all hit her daughter's information
Oh that is actually personalized
Anyway so
I think I was just very impressed by
Paintings
Ambition
Attitude
And also I think he has very high tolerance
Of people with diverse background
But I think that's very important
And I am enough quotes and I know kind of roughly you know.
Company and also I also said that I didn't want that that was a very quick decision for me
I didn't want to join another company that is burning money
And for our listeners who may not be as familiar with Vikings could you give an overview of its products
Sure happy to
President has a variety of products
That are counted platform
A powered by Machine learning
So Daddy
People can it's really Discovery platform that provide personalized compass
Two olives
And its Flagship product is called sociology Naruto with y'all
Which you know what has
It over a hundred million users
In China daily active users in China
And II Buckhead after products
Are we caught UBC products
Micheladas
Chinese people
A familiar way those short video products historian
Horsham
And then they had one
Data more focused on interactions
Overcomes personalized,
The three packets of products overseas products
Including this
It'll musically we just recently announced the merger
Musically is really a great platform that is covers
Us and Europe most of their users
And this is rhodium agents that we didn't have too much coverage before
So I think there are definitely Synergy about musically and
Going forward
In terms of
Tiger lady
Global Mart
How would you summarize the mission of ideas
It wasn't
In one sentence or two
Bank is I wanted to tell you know why
You know this content platform was
Found it in the first place you know the company's 5 years ago
And 5 years ago
Ambulate 2011/2012
That is
Beaming realize that the information
Information agent
Atwoods transforming from PC and newspaper
To mobile
So at an accompanied by the development of machine learning and AI technology
Yeah but those are all based on PC
Netease
We're eating a yeah but yeah but then you take into consideration of that weed the first app way /
It's called a lance is actually
A very simple content platform that Focus sound
Apple biting joke
Similar to Reddit with less political content
But at the very beginning that you mean was Ashley using machine learning the key features
Lentils jokes
So I think we're really the first one who use my s*** applied machine learning technology to contact YouTube
Discovery breakthrough
Innovation
And then we applied us
Technology to all the products we have today
That make us you know different from other
Add approach
When it comes to contemplate musically
I decided to
Merchandise
Mumbai dance
One reason why I was in favor of it
Did this is a very unique capability
Can boost almost any company you work
Most people haven't had the opportunity
What do you
The chance
To develop the algorithm
Also machine learning
You guys have something that can be applied
Across multiple
How many Engineers does spiders have
We now have about 3000
Ngos and data scientist
Wishes I can go bare access
We applaud that we have today in China
Which is also
You now easy access to find today
I'll let you know very
And I know that recruiting many top talents in machine learning and AI algorithms
I think it is everywhere you know from the valley
What what are the top reasons that you use to convince people to join by tens
What would you tell them
Edo
I think part of
Because I was with Uber which is very operational driven company
And is very
Very technology
Product
Type of company
So guess different types
Funniest would have filled a different way
Quitting
Style
I think for any operational
Operation driven companies what iPhone is that there
Birthday they're really storyteller
Inspirational
Yeah
That fart at company's Allosaurus style is
You know
It's very you.
Eating is always say that we do not want to raise
Hikes by Tatian for candidates
But that's you know that you should pull up I mean that's how you feel
We should definitely going to really boost
Recruiting strategy lessons
I really sell almost all the people join Uber China
And 2K what month are doctors salaries
Aldo's
Play the song You Know by dance is very down-to-earth
Company
B&N
And they really just tell her that
I think the most
Inspiration slogan I heard it will be
Join the company work with inter
Fixing people do interesting.
Ghetto engineering recruiting
Send it can be very very
Data-driven
To be in the
And den
MGK bath Market
And if you ask the evening was kind of the big track of recording Collins Brody with the conversation recipe
So Uber want to change the world it was inspirational
Bytedance is very solid reliable and looking at interesting products
How did the evening who is very solid and reliable
You find out he not
You know I would want to go global
We want expand Beyond China
What
Prompt him in a company
And you guys
To make that decision
We started our International expansion in mm
Another company was
Steel for your a little bit more than two years old
So is Barry Williams that he started and decided to go
Globo
I know you don't and I do see this in many
Entrepreneurs in his generation
That they stink globally
And they never intended to be
A chine account
Norton mid-to-late 30s
Yes
And they say and also I think I'll come check in space
You know I'm sure online content media social media space
Do I think this is
Just so you know this is just the right thinking
That you couldn't think of you can't really
Continuous selfie White Ranger
From Prada
Users
Perspective
This is the platform business
So I think they never really intended to
You know where global company to headquarter happened to be in Beijing
I sent you personally also worked on a lot of
Totalis recent deals with
Companies outside of China how was this process of negotiating with non chine
Chinese companies
And because
I guess brand name is very strong in China but overseas
Not many people have used its products or they use it but don't know is part of by chance
I think the most with or without answer is trust me is much easier than Hugo shading waves label companies
Music deals
Switch positions we are doing more votes Wicked Ways has been side we do seed
The products Energy Engineering or talents energy that we feel that we can help the company
So when whenever we approach and then Chinese
Ice Company
And which are most founded by product people
Engineering
Dizzy very easier for us because we could have really have a camera
To show you know
Interesting you know one of the companies we talk to you after we
Replay Zendaya.
10 slice
Dad you know the Airways stop when we got in we can improve on their products
And the founders smile
They showed me the reason for the Temptation twist board
6 identical
We just we really think alike
I think it's as kind of it is much easier than
I was a negotiating with
Business
Finance
Yunnan people
Musically is also you know we we had to come is treated as a builder as a
Products people
So I think it's
Sweet forward
And then you have to come in
Play when you speak the same language
So Hans would you like to come in more unlike the significance of the musically tote real deal
But I think when we messing musically the it was the first
Company
How many Beijing Shanghai
With a very
China dominated team
Pencil Building Products that become mainstream in the US
And I was
Extremely hard to do and never did no one ever did that before
That was interesting
And then over the last few years
You can tell that
Musically has something amazing
But it could use extra help
To to get fulfilled a true vision
Well as possible for them to pick American partner
I think collectively as a board and shareholders
We all felt that going with someone like Tokyo if you'll be something quite special
And offer a lot more upset
And I think the
The culture
Are so similar in both Farms
Both do 9 and 6 9 a.m. to 9 p.m.
62 week
Cardinals schedule
You can improve car. Product screaming tuna
And and I'm not even for a for a few years even before I don't you
6 years ago
It's amazing to see how much he has matured
Like there's sunset
Amazing
And then
I know that for us
Get a deal done
That you may have to figure out a way to work with futon at Cheetah Mobile
And then
The evening plus I was able to
Who sell that and make that happen
So you was not an easy deal I don't think I don't think anyone else
Could have really done it that is not many people can
Are you guys getting gotten extremely efficient
So far all of a sudden music
We boycotting
How to be seized is IG and teaming then
Acrylic wall
Depressed
Having no content company in the world has been able to succeed both inside and outside of China soon. Send
It's okay
It's a milestone
Yeah thank you
Thank you
Auburn Bay pollution optimistic
Thinking like a champion and let you guys do more even though in a lot of markets
Thank you
I mean the two teams just sound so you know that music team
Versace men RTS or integrated
And
Ai weiwei ready for
Holiday season
The holiday season is a very important tee
Accounting products
Who would you say is the target audience
Four by Genesis products
Both in and outside of China
I think in China you know because of the large user base
So I think the demography
Kind of evil
Is a disability
Smartphone
And in 4 UTC products
CW have
I think China pek
Is a huge disparity between
The first-tier cities
4th and 5th
In the countryside
The city and Countryside
So you know we have other products audc
Fetal products
That amore
Calgary at 2
Give me weight of the different Generations
I'm at the Wynn
Which is
Did the Chinese
Virgin of musically as lot of audience
Dad in in the younger generation
90s
Swage
Squids
And outside tryna I think
We have a product called tick tock
Which ranks number one consistently for the past week
In Japan
So we think
Japan Korean
Southeast Asia Indian
You asked your about all our target audience now we have given products
Cover different wages
But the bike and recommendation engine
And it's
Without engines almost
Anybody but I'm more
Apple products
And you have lover
Tokyo is a great
Way to
Market other products
Public Tokyo
But also have
Epicene
Do both
The first time
Yeah I think the back end cuz all the engineers and product people are based
Airbase in China so we share the same
Backend and also we do Qualls
Product marketing as you said that we will be able to promote
Other products
Inflection
And outside China I think music
The top priorities
That we will
Apple emoji annoying to come in yours
Skin in other regions
Not the Way You Are
Hotel to become the
Platform
I think one of the Stars show the
It is a monster
Top five or six
Most awfully use
What has the most
Reading time
Above all apps
China
How how did you guys
Get to the
Achievement
I made that possible in such a
Too short.
Yeah I think I think now and some
I think someone just did a
Statistics that we are about in terms of waiting time media content consumption time worry about 6
.6
Percent
You know I'll say
The aggregate
Call Desert Tire on mobile phone
I go by what number 5
Each daily active user now spends
/ 17 minutes
I mean you know in China on Tokyo map
I think this very low engagement
Wade comes from
UniFirst, supply-side you definitely had more diverse
Accountant
How you know ranging from traditional to take
Counted
Immunization
Where would partner away probably
All the major media
Outlets in China
When you come that
2 PC professional decorated accountants
And ugc user
And also what you never variety of formats
You have text
News
Blog
Pictures
Question and answer
Video how about that
The time
Half of 270
Venice panel watching videos
So we definitely see video saree
Becoming
You're definitely
EBay timeshare
And you also we also lost the Twitter type of way what type of
We told you
Feature
It also we don't encourage users
Quaid content directly
I'm so if you look at the rage format an advertisement it's just another form of counting
Will you do personalized as product my way well
And you can invite it in the park where it is itself actually account
So
I think the reach content
And also better this way you'll have
Udo variety of which continent
Format and you disability
Play the algorithm that were able to build
Distribution
I think you definitely
Engaged
Earwigs out in
It's a bit more
That's why the time
What issue that many media platforms are both in and outside of China struggle with its meditation
Could you talk a little bit about how
Iden's makes money do you know where ER advertisement Revenue
Model business
I think it's different
Social
Media platform hosts
Publix
An advertisement you think about it
This man is really just one of the puppet
That's why you know what about you
Monetize
Is actually better to monetize
Public content
Dan is the man
Search
Dantos
Social content
So I think
This is so you know what the news feed by say
Advertisement I think it was
And in this area wasn't really
Wasn't built in a lot of Vig and big companies didn't pay a lot of attention to this area
Montecito
Weekly woman
Moving Giver discuss.
On this one to two
But you tried monetization on the UTC
The short-form mobile video app
Will you be looking at different ways to monetize Beyond
Flooring.
But I think you know when
You know I think being I think we're exploring that but I think is important to realize
The power
And potential office
Is one stop come from
That not only because I'm going to technology-wise you would be able to
Morito you use
User Behavior watching videos recommended
Advertisement
Questions
Pictures in others it may be recommended
Interesting
Celebrities
To those all it is
Are you able to really
You know don't they release energy is among those
Reading behaviors on different formats
Are you can monetize a so I think a One-Stop platform has a lot of potential
Where at is how did you discover
Awesome stand-alone
In my uniform of mine ization perspective
I understand where you're kidding
Okay what are the biggest lessons that you've learned from your family
You know I think my my mom actually is very
Career I want a dead woman and she's very sick
And she always encouraged me to
How to find a step forward
Andy Mohr model
Sometimes when I was
Kind of struggling or deciding between
Attending my kids school emails or are you going to go on this business web
She is always the one encouraging me to go on a business trip
She said well enough kids going to forget about that which is the truth
So I think this is very important that I I was actually said to a
Boarding kindergarten
3 years old
Come home on week
And I love my Paradise I had to wear my parents I just you know I feel like
So I guess you know my mom is very encouraging me
I'm taking more
Beijing
Interesting boarding
Boarding and even had a little Hospital inside
That I remember website
Fever and
I sure did Ivana that you have to call my mom for some reason they just put me in this
Outside Hospital
And I stay through the entire week what did your mother do as
Docker career
My mom works at a time
I like it all all women China Federation
Show me the interesting somewhere so he cheats by when creating a tab just so you know
Small takeaway ask my husband is out also you know interesting you know why I've you are
As more partnership as opposed to traditional husband and wife
Can we share equally and in some of
The kids.
He's better than me
And some of them
Is better than Han so we share equally
Intensiva
I think that's also very helpful that you have a very
Strong family support
And you are also able to
Leverage all the resources you have
That's important
Now I have work both in the valley
That's why I was here
These days do you see much difference
In Spotify
Aggressiveness
What's up
Pace
Or XY
Between 9 to Pandora
Tourism
Holy definition that Chinese companies
Vanessa Moore
Aggressive
We come we
We have this nice
Schedule
But not as a not at we work every other son
I think about you know we have about
Every other Sunday
So 96 on top of that every other day
Weather Sunday
So it is 10 to 10
And I think when you think about you know
A lot of we started at 5 yards
So that people come
Until today
That we still here Williams so which is
Pretty well
WeatherTech
And and here is all the trainings in all the meetings on Sunday when I talk about working Sunday
Meaning for 5 hours
The entire working
I'll be there look at you know our schedule is
The meeting some morning to you that night
Alabama 4 weeks ago actually asked
The Department's cuz I'm response
Pacifier lot of things
Overseas
You don't come to moderation team is out also going to wait in my
Skull bandana
Prgr eagle
Forecast
So I asked my Adidas lvsa you know I'm okay if you
Decided to opt out
It's illegal to leave one side as actually didn't come on Sunday
Say I am okay if you opt out
The majority of responses are
A lot of meetings
They also feel that if the company is
Growing very fast paced
I feel a little bit left behind
Yeah and she said that she didn't want to come outside but is ended up that
Elmo see you know every other Sunday because of the work.
And meetings that we require
So as a woman in the family
You probably get a lot of people asking you like how do you do it all
That's probably one of the most
What does it take to be able to do a lot of
Chugalug
Extremely fast moving
Always involved
I think to be able to kind of jungle
You know that's workload
And having two very young
I think the most important
How much weight
Play time you high
And are you feel excited
About your own
What's your mom's name
I think it's very very important
To be able to
To do something for your own to make yourself happy and energetic
Then nothing you can take on more challenges
And two to be able to accommodate more
I think that's a boy
I think
Anyone who can take care of themselves
Especially women you know man I guess you don't
Always take care of themselves are selfish
I should definitely
Blossomtime parade
Yeah
Are you feeling happy
You are
And you have feelings
Madhur
The most
I think
I think you have to understand that you manage them you know what they care the most
At what you care the least
That's very true
You want to do it well
You have to go to give up. Go
So you don't ya and and work that way we always say that we were
I wanted to make magic
Achieve
Perfection
But I home you know
I I care less
There's really a lot of things sad
I feel.
III character list
You know what kind of
Close my kids
I swear we could have milk
You know
Are there dressing properly for school you know
Attending every school
You know there was just at 8
Started actually education about this
You know I can go half
I can not go the other half.
You know if Daddy can go if
You know what Daddy can go but if not that's fine
Let's all fights
How do you prioritize
Reply lessons you learned in worked for to your family
Yes or no the other profession side yet
If both parents was in the valley I think it's
It's
Is more likely to be able to do that
Sear
Them over there
Yes or no I think in the valley I don't know you but but I definitely see some family so I vote
Go to
Also
So beautiful
Some similar
Domestic system
Somebody saying the body cuz you just go to Whole Food and buy a lot of
I'm outside it is easier that you don't really look for
I think in
In about a year
In New York
Somebody's place
You have
The mother is somehow expected
Spend more time
Attending the
MySchoolBucks
Buckets
Yeah I think that you have to educate their children that what are the conventional truth is
And you shouldn't always follow the conventional truth
How do you hatch a billionaire mindset
To be honest as also thing you know Silicon Valley moms
Returning to work
Because they wanted to demonstrate to their children specialist
Dad daughter
Yes
That you don't women swallow is not only defined
To do the math
But also can take a role just as their daddy is
EIC definitely this
Need
You know from children side
No pressure even from education side
455 stay at home mom to return to the
Coincidence
When
The debate is on
In the US after you get married
Almost all
Women are more expected
To change last name
Qufu map
Previous lost
To the husband
I don't ever see that in
China or
Parts of Asia
But in USA
Almost expected
And
Psychologically
It's its edges
It's it was
It was eye-opening for me
Cuz
It's not what I'm used to
You know what
In Asia women
Keep a lost thing
If you married and still you know
Your own person
But in the US
Is Ura
Socially
Expect to change
So is this a small thing but
Different
Don't expect
An interesting cuz I'm in charge of booking you know
All the family trips
And my family or my husband is responsible
Before executing yet that I mean try to
So whenever we travel to a hotel
To always call my husband mr. Leo
Iveco master ball from time to time as well
So you know he's fine I think I think it is I think it's more of a cultural and Hayes
Hey sweet thing in the western world
Even yes
They change to their husband
I don't mind
Italy
The confidence
So move on to the last part of the podcast is so round
Quick fire questions that you admire the most and why
Other than Travis and evening
I guess my grandfather and my uncle
I talk about why it leopard a little
You don't go inside there was just this you know you know
Generation you know the phone near the founder of patent Chinese patent law
My uncle you know
Inner mongolia
Uniform had lenovo and it and now the chairman of lyca group
And just I I think I might hear him as definitely a business leader
As well as
Kind of a big
Family
John Fay
His older brother of my dad and and two sisters real sisters
We definitely owe him you know as most respectful
Family member and always comes again
If I have
Questions concerns
Breitbart
Or travel
What's one piece of most memorable advice that your uncle has given you
You know I think
TS
A very very good at tackling conflict
Yeah complicated as in because you know to be able to become a business later in history
Generation
Continue.
Today that
He has
Encountered a lot of complicated
Issues
He teaches us really by
Hiding those weight example
I think it's hard to to say when count conclusive
Why do a sentence
Brody.
It'll all those complicated issues and he always ask
In what situation is different problem would have different bound
And when the boundary changes
You got using you
Oatmeal solution to Southside
There is no Universal
Problem Solutions there is no Universal solution
So he's very good at listening
Anna tackling those complicated
What do you think is the best and worst decision that you've ever made
So there was always
The other side of
You don't have
Consequences after making a decision I don't see there is
The so-called best or worst
But if speaking of requests
I can definitely do
Spend less time on being a lawyer
Carmen's amazing mentor
I think that's something that I feel that you know if I were able to
Choose again
I think I would
Stop sooner
Morning
What's a habit that you're glad you have
I think very good at multitasking
You know sometimes I do conference
Pause while I was
I can tell you knows not obvious that when you're talking to me you're awesome
Dating someone have a conversation
Are you really good at it
I feel bad
You know cuz cuz I'm busy and I do want it and I'm a very fast
Axecutioner
Siid wanted to reduce
Fusion
Ass wipe
You know I'm so that makes me sometimes Anita mall
He has a lot of
It was really fun to have you and thank you so much for your time
As well as the collaboration we had
Earlier this year I'll be around
Yeah partnership
798 beijing
San Jose International listening to this episode
By the way we also could use a weekly email newsletter English also called 96
Roundup of the week's most important happenings
Inside in China
Subscribers some photos for the informative and fun to read
And you said also features original content and Analysis from Zara MI
Striped at nine 6. GG bc.com
Play stage Venture Capital firm based in Silicon Valley Shanghai and Beijing we have been partnering with leading technology on
Nurse for the last 17 years from seed to pre-ipo
What's 3.8 billion dollars in capital under management across age funds
GTA V invest in globally-minded entrepreneurs and consumer internet e-commerce Frontier Tech in
Enterprise GTA V has invested in over 200 companies including Airbnb Alibaba
Z-Trip
DD hellobike house
Keep slack Square Hotel wish cell phone show YY and other
What 29th IPOs and 17 unicorns to date find out more at gbc.com
Do you have any feedback on this podcast
The recommended gas please email us I-96 at Gigi bc.com
This podcast is co-produced Battlefront and business partner Kaiser kuo the host of the
Wonderful sinica podcast it cover China's economic
Political and cultural issues