Hey 986 listeners this is Zara from ggv capital
I have a special announcement this week
Hans and I will be doing a live show in San Francisco on March 21st
We'll be interviewing Airbnb co-founder Chief strategy officer and chairman of China
Natal chart
Airbnb's headquarters in San Francisco
Will be discussing how Airbnb has expanded into China
One of its most important International Market
And the company's China strategy going forward
The show will be at 7 p.m. on Wednesday March 21st at airbnb's headquarters
8999 Brannan Street San Francisco
If you're in the Bay Area
We love to see you there
Tickets are required for attending and they're selling fast
Grab yours today at 96.2 gbc.com
Slash live
Again that
996. Ggvc cam live
Hi there
Welcome to the nine at six podcast
Brought to you by ggv capital
Echo produced by the Seneca podcast
On the show interview movers and shakers
China's tech industry
That's was Tech leaders
Weather us
China
Cross-border perspective
My name is sandstone, managing partner at GTV capital
And I've been working at startup investment in them in both in us and China
Quarter past 20 years
My name is Sarah Jeong
I need investment analyst igb capital
Jennifer Moore journalist
Why is the show called 96
96 is the work schedule than any Chinese Founders have organically adopted
That is 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
To us
996 captures intensity
Drive
In speed
Of Chinese internet companies
Many of which
I'm moving faster
But even the American consul
On today's show we have the co-founder of shell home shoe
Orenda Chu
So sure which literally means Little Red Book in Chinese
Is the world's largest lifestyle platform that integrates community and content with e-commerce
Over 75 million users use the app to follow influencers
Create and consume in
Accountant
And buy everything from Fashion to Cosmetics to Lifestyle products
4 bills overseas
Enter Mexico Chinese brands
Socialista ggv portfolio company
Is really one of the pioneers of the concept known as
Dogo
Guided purchase
It's also one of my personal favorite shopping flask
Because when I feel like shopping but don't know what to buy
Josh Wisconsin and influencers can always give me inspiration
And the numerous
High-quality reviews and tutorials posted by users can also help me with product selection
Miranda is one of the two co-founders of yahushua
Would you like to share with us a bit up your background in a why did you decide to Star shopping
Actually we all Machado and I started selling shoes for years ago
Long time friends with
Kind of bag for over 10 years
4 years ago when we wanted
To do something
Internet
We found that
They're interesting that Chinese people are traveling overseas
For shopping
This is something that we didn't expect
Earlier
There isn't any
Application that tackled this Market
For Chinese shopping overseas
But this is an opportunity we see and it will quickly
Gather some information abdominal platform to
Teach people how to shop overseas
Then
Quickly trying to a social platform
People can share information about
On what they buy and how they make the decision and the where to buy
Travel company
Or was it a
Social networking company
Showing
Shopping tips
It's very interesting when we first launched in our store app store travel category 4
A long time
Why you are you how old are you are kind of like a shopping
Return to shopping category and you know the other apps
Ask ask
Kind of liking trouble
I would say it's a combination
Actually tackle the problem the shopping problem
Wild air travel
Best I feel good dip that why people
Spell all the time
Shopping while they shooting join you know the Beautiful Things overseas
It's because it's
Veritiv
Fordham to baidu
Saint to get those information
That's why
We think that they need a social community
To share the information to get more knowledge about what you buy
Where to buy that's why you're called Little Red Book
You're like a guidebook for people to know where to find things
The comedy
Yes and do no wrong in China is a very Chinese color
It's very easy to remember and
Bookcase not only a travel book that it's also the rich between something you know when something
Thing you didn't know
We will always consider ourselves that's kind of like
Was something that you don't know
You can discover more last out there
Remember when I first met you guys
About the startup
It was
You got started
Or just over you
At all
Yes
Damaged a lot of
Incontinent
Regenerated
How did you guys think about
Focusing on contouring
Versus Commerce
Early on
Why did you start
Come first and not touch Commerce
We started was very light
Countenance
Because that with incontinence important is because we think that it's the first.
For people to discover the neulasta
You should gather information and then come up with the problem that how to get things
So it's
It's very
Natural
For users
They have to discover that things they would like
And then they would think that how to get
So that's why we start this accountant platform
Truly based on kind of
To solve users problem to take OST
It's not that kind of something that we want
At the end of 2014
I do not receive a lot of complaining about it you know we see a lot of beautiful things everyday baby
Where to buy them
Exactly
Look at this despite rain for those overseas items is there it's hard to buy them in China
They're either too expensive in a shopping War
Something's dead
The lost things that are not in China yet
And the other things do you know
Carousel by individual salads
What you don't know where
Take out them you don't know whether it's fake or what is to expenses
So
What's a wow that's a child
And the end of that year does so kind of new policy issued by Chinese government
It's called the cross-border
E-commerce
And there comes out of town
Because you know at a time in China Tea, sis
Already a very
Competitive
When something new come up you know everybody's that was the same level
So
We decided to jumping the
Crossword lady,
Sorry to be a commercial company
Remember in 2039 bussing West
Peking Duck
Chinese Goods
Chinese Mirch
Celebrity
Giselle
Zhuhai
China
And then. 2014
Ghana maybe time
For import
So I met
About 10 other companies
Aldi quadsport
Commerce in Oconto
You were the only one that comes out before
And you're the one
Your tuna with the least amount of Commerce experience
We start investing you
Sears bikes
Thinking that
So hard you could come to
Serbia stronk
Competitive advantage
Worried at any point in time that people will come to your place
Read the content
Discover tips
Then go somewhere else
Toy shop
And not come
Conduction
And how do you overcome that fear
What concern
Yes I think we will Vera work as first but you know
Taurus
Not something that we do
Also they are very
List file
I do remember that when we first launched one product
In our at our path warm is
It was so loud like in 10 seconds
Identify my damn we launched kind of like 10 products
It's kind of like very step-by-step thing
I still remember Ella at a January of 2016 are mostly gianvi is around 1
Chameleon
We
Kind of like 100 million
That was only half a year so I think all confidence
For PewDiePie users
People are pay more and more all platforms because they really wanted
Yes
So
I think Lori bed to worry it makes no sense so what would
What does pry
Do you think that
People will only pay
The higher price
Toy shop you're on your platform
When you face
Spending our looks
Forty malt
I think
Generally I think we're very reasonable price
Because I want all the team was very difficult to identify whether
This products
Is Frank City Pops hours
They can be lazy
And I think to help our uses
You offer convenience
So I think that's why they started shabab platform
And another thing that we think it's really important
Is the coffee
Because we started
It's a community and they don't already know I said we can take no ass
Every continent
Yahushua
True
It's kind of like written by all users with no kind of like benefits
So they really process platform
That's the trastes transfer from Community to e-commerce
So did you
We also something did you start a fire
I think so very long period of time
90% of all items are sold out
Within 24 hours
Sulphur V have review we would just try to just look for more items
So
That was the first stage of are you
Building process data
We asked you to place
Remember to
Conversion
Was as high as
2% which I'm never seen anywhere else
So it's you
Build out the app
Create account
And I share a lot of good
Free
You don't pay them any
How do you get them
I think just so you know
Especially for women to share what to buy
Is a neat
Previously they made a shirt on waist
And then people will say okay kind of election food that people will say some negative words
It's about it
So they actually need somewhere to show their lifestyle
And to find
Yes exactly so I think to create a
Friendly
I'm mister and greater kind of like a very friendly
Environment is
There is a report
I would take another example you know
Everyday we will you kind of like
Took a lot of pictures and the place them all all moment
In this case there's a trend
I'm people
Every national holiday people are kind of sharing their power packs
WeChat moments
Don't pay them anything and
There's not an activity called
Place your
Hubble pics
Kind of like environment
I'm always doing that
Horseshoe way always
Put a lot of kind of
Product average
Shaquille environment
Do chip.
People 2 still Luton
To share more
So I think that's what we
For those who may not be as familiar with the product itself
I'm actually a very seamless integration between the social and the
Community in the Commerce so you can follow influencers and then
See the pictures they share and that you can see
The clothes are wearing tack by brand and then you can click into those brand origin
EBay Quake on The Closer where I can buy them
From the app
So I think is a very powerful
Way to
Convert social traffic into actually Commerce
Transaction
Amanda tomorrow that we seen
Which Sandlot in China and it's only starting out in the US
So I guess we can shift the topic to talk the more about your personal background so
What made you want to start this Venture with your co-founder shower and how did you meet him
Sorry I actually
Boston
Brass and we actually met at the mall called maze it's okay
It's a true story that
You are just shopping there
Yes exactly at a shopping place and that's a Time both of us were universities
Woodward
On the same trip to kind of like
Alfa Romeo Harvard
You know I do
Met him before because
There was so many in Chinese
And I are both from I heard someone saying the local dialect
Kind of calling.
Power and son is saying something about shopping and that's
My first impression was very appropriate that you met in the mall yeah I've been and never imagined than one
Do something about overseas shopping
We first started the we started with some kind of like shopping guys you know
Add a shower and I personally wrote
How to shop in USA
And that was for our very first
Very interesting
Fuel
Life is always come around
How did you come up with this
Idea in the first place
We actually didn't come up with this idea
UniFirst play I still remember
First PowerPoint is called China rent a Runway China
Runaway China
Weebles
Love
Traveling is so we really want to do the travel app
With the kind of us
Shopping Guide written by Towing in the planet
Shopping yes exactly and I still remember
Rachel Ames comments
It's no sex at all and then we give you so much money and you did the PDF
Because I still remember at 2013 now is Richard Lane Estero member of China
Are you that's a lot of money
Two tribes Frankie mobile at the we actually started as a PDF
It was kind of
Crazy
There was just quickly turns you okay
And their social class
Are you a big fan of shopping yourself and how much shopping do you do
Before and after your foundation holschuh
I'm a big shopping center sold us showing
You can see that we met at a shopping place
I think it's
It's really something that we both lost and weed everyday I
You know what you open a tattoo shop
Yahushua is supposed a word
Panda personal Hobbit
So I chop up really a lot
Harvard
In Chinese New Year
I think I did time we
. we want to see the outside world
It's all post photos showing anime it's our first trip to you as ever
And what year were you guys in college we the same to you or different
And I think
Towing
We were born the same year that the towing is when
Year
Yes
OTB of course he said he did at Yalta when the granite is Stanford GSB
So he's very very Talent
Yes I think that because
My parents wanted me to start earlier you know you ain't in Chinese
Burnsville
Can you use study journalism you school do you think that helped you at all with word entrepreneurship Journey
Please write the first draft of the blind
Say that a generalist is someone that collected information and distributor
I think that's
Kind of like what's your horseshoe doing
Show newest or social platform and you can say
Likeable media major
Also it helps people to get information kind of like
Awesome journalism has to kind of like the same logic behind
So where it where the top countries that you Source your products from
Nowadays
Japan to Korea apples Ferry
Pop's right you know
Taqueria
The Korean pop Star has a very popular in China the movies the TV series
I think the current temperature
Is very popular in China that gives an olive
Laws of tuna to 2
Have more exposure about their friends and
And the second reason for that is suno
When people in the Chinese people are more
They look alike
Explorer
US market you know
If worse the trash
Is there a different sizes and the very different sets
Sold
Korean most popular and another one is Japan
No dependas
Famous boys quality
And they has a lot of
Smaller brains with kind of like a thousand years of History
But I think that's
What people are buying right now for the college
I know you mentioned recently that the proportion of overseas products on sale home she was actually at the
Declining and people are willing to buy
The message Chinese brand
For the last 2 or 3 years why did crossword, sista populist
Because that mean China
Interesting new brands
I don't think
They just want to buy two items
In China
Before but they just one
Quality Prada
Yes exactly
I think it right now there is a lot of new emerging brands in China that people love
CVS photo cards
So it's a shoe brand that also has its own Cafe where you can
Have afternoon tea and shop for high heels at the same time
Yes
So
I do think it's because the right of both the consumer
Any more receptive to local Brands and also
Domestic brands
Rising
At the same time
I think I'm actually the younger generation
Have no buyers
About whether this brand zizo vs always domestic
Suck their domestic friends now
Put more focus on brand building
Rather than owning the kind of
I think previously they put
Are too much emphasis on
Two on the production butter than the brand Beauty
All right now
They know how to do it
How to tell the story
And it helps a lot
Jeffers
Google profile
Popular user
How old
And
What part of the country
Average spending
4 year old
I would say that all uses are
Dairy
Young
Eight is Enough female
Choose to further
Elaborated We're Young I think I'm the ages between us 717-0018
Two around 40
I think I'll pour some of them by the college
Before the year
Other half I think they're
The field area they still look for
Good quality lives they spend a lot of time on discovering new things rather than 2
Tick tubes
What did no
Takes a 30 years
Would you say more you
Above 30 years in age or under 3
I think more uses on their survey
To the one
3 2 1
Let me give an example
This year
70% of all new users at war after 1995
Yeah
Will be around the half of the abuse or stop Warren after 99
Okay
Young and have my money
What store apps pending
Baidu
Is Time Warner
I think it's very difficult to say
Especially for us
First of all we're sociopaths for
Actually don't have their
Purchase records
That's what those School shop on sale Home shoe
I would not say Derek richer than
The previous generation I think their purchasing Behavior
And the concept have changed a lot
Play Master P I college students better Happy
And there
The one spend money
I think
Four very different age group that spending is still very very very different
Brinley
There's some kind of like what
Which is really popular Rats on it's called whole life
The average
Pies for Whole Life Ace round 40 RMB for lipstick
This really chip but it's really popular among the young students
Staffers file walking tooth kind of Life cosmetic word for squirrel
4/6
You know it.
Fake brands
Like AC Lawler cppi still the kind of life
Purchase Behavior
It's there a different right now
The younger generation love new brands
Didn't have that much to spend
Bedford Square over today yesterday
Still look for something they know maybe there is some new brands of swell bed
Mostly the price of higher selling items
Angelica
I think we're very strong
Cosmetics
Austin care
On fashion
Belstaff
Apparel
Yes
So
Just still so young for most
Just anything that young females would like
I sent the second you would be kind of the mavic air
Moddedzone
Martha mother and baby
Home
Home window repair
Home decoration
Because snow Furnishing there's something while walking to
And also we have on others
Things as well
Genesis is similar to apparel
What's Allison's
Eyes kind of like
Digital products
Like what do sour iPhone x
Yes exactly
No no
Different categories
Babe
And isn't that the are used to buy in their life
Hollywood Style hair
Because they have just very
Ostrong kind of like
Quest
Rather than they will search elsewhere
On average
For those who shop on shopping
How many
Rensselaer
Statistics
We just launched the membership
What one of our members
There was kind of light on
425 * 7
40 *
Yes
But I've seen
I think they're
Who shot more frequent
Yeah yeah
Definitely
I think you did the end of lost you. I'll use a base is still kind of liking it is 30 million
Close to it
80 minutes are you supposed
Yes and
Danuser
For fun times
Yes.
So I think you guys have made a conscious decision not to use advertising as you remain
Source of Revenue could you talk about that decision because I think in the US a lot of
Internet companies especially those that have community and content still rely on Advertising as their main
Meditation mode
West I discuss this with
A friend
My friend has a very interesting conclusion that
Because they think that
You can be very lazy you know
You don't have to do all that you know how they say
Logistics name
Exactly because everyone
Running to therapists so
It's kind of love holds value chain
Beijing China most big companies
Do everything
If you take penicillin
So
Does
Is there a good opportunity because you know we have such large population that's very easy for you to
And also
We think it's the best
For the company to grow
Accident
Yunnan
What speed
We also offer the best music
Experience
Exactly
What was the film lucky never going to the other side
The register-herald
Morehouse
Yeah exactly and gradually becomes
The entry barrier
Because people
They make the shopping decisions here
And they can directly by here to don't have to jump to
Either he comes pass from 2 to look for things
Stacy
Yesterday a friend Chamois a date
14 percenters
Users who have seen
I mostly fashion apparel shoes back
14 Ulster
How about users after they see items
They will log on
Tus Ojos YouTube
To find more reviews
I don't know
Eventually picture
I think just
Find a place to make the shop decision become more and more important and there I believe there are a lot of them
Turn into song
That is very dangerous
I remember when I first moved back to California in 2013
The one of the first thing I noticed
Suicide
Companies like Pinterest Inspire this
Whole social sharing
Movement
Just want to touch Commerce at all
Just want to do ask
Get everybody in China from
Are investment in British language
Turn into ottoman
Does every
Received housing of Commerce first
What is transactional route
What's the score good score for second round
Virtual items
This is why when we
We might
70D
We hiding her Jutsu
To do Commerce but we know that you're always a comfort
Company First Commerce is an extension of the
Value provide
I sent you first start e-commerce really provide all uses a good experience that help them to
I'm standing platform the right now we're kind of like open platform
We do you, spend we warlike eCommerce platform
Because we have so much content and users
So they lost new brands they want to sell hair
So they can't open the kind of shop themselves rather than that we have to do a lot of heavy things
I think that's going to be the future
But still kind of like
The battle xian logistic
I'm provide kind of regular AR help the kind of you know always has
Smaller Brands to transport those items from overseas to China to individual
Another thing is to provide the best customer experience
That's why we have one office
21st soccer in Commerce your
Stop calling inventory for the most
Best selling products
Yes
Sakura supplies
To sell to users
The overtime you evolve that you sent into a moth
Walk us through how you guys made.
Position
Only and also
Operational
How do you spell excuse
First of all I think we started to become as we know that this day will come
Because you know
Are Spencer's countenance
Social platform
There's over 1 billion exposure
Of notes
Discount has already but we can take him
Yes so what
First started
Just that we sell to uses
Reddit into
Marketplace but last year on Marketplace a Psalm a strategy
The wizard it was kind of like
To help
Telus
From what island
Are we integrate those platform to
Provide more items so that when people see contents there more things to buy
An indoor kind of like
Now that's the lovers
Because
When does start to sell on cell phone shoe
They feel that this even more traffic
To their stores because
Yahushua is the place they go and they discover things
And that's the rest of the deferred sentence
Does the first date but this year we walking to
Kind of like more open
Chores
There can be more new brands on Chaco shoes
Australia
If you think
You fit all user profile
You helped us here and we'll have a lot of
Tools to help you
But of course we'll have all the rules
Cosmic spirits
Will see you there will be a lot of the new brands new emerging brands are social sooner or later
That's interesting.
We do think that sounds the place to discover
You think so but over time
It's even more powerful when user
Discover new things elsewhere
What come to Kalamazoo for
Additional research verification
Knowledge and tips
And then you mentioned maybe you can just stay inside with you and buy it from
Yes exactly is so now that's what pill has a dancercise on the chores to organize the information I think that's
That's very sensual and the Vets variable
How much do users use your search function
Cuz they do a lot of Discovery right
Do they still search for things like in a targeted way
Yes I'm just a scent that has mentioned
Nowadays like more situation light
Discover all right you know
A WeChat
Call Cole
We're kind of a platform that has a lock
Reviews reviews in the comments
Which are generated by users
And there
Very trustworthy
That's why uses words eventually come to the platform and to discover more information and actually
Most of them I made the most of the Mets shop decisions here that's what
I think that's what matters most
What do you use the Technologies in algorithms to recommend in personalized content
For users
Based on their interest
Yeah I'm definitely
I think that's
Main focus
For last year
Because you know
Wait user kind of like Adam although you can only cater for
One kind of
Users
When we use Ai and they use the machine to start
Chualar about users
Not everybody see things different
So that's all
E-commerce
Launch this a strategy
So now everyday sis
Does the different things
So is you in corporate world person
Recent
Recommendation
Algorithm
How do you balance
Put some summer young user
Based on what
She buys
You can tell that she's a
And you can get a sense of her budget
How much is spent on
Don't you order so how do you balance between
Pushing other stuff that she
Ford Pharmacy
Bring something that she would
Aspire to one of
Inspired by
How do you pronounce
Switch
Products you
Leprosy first
Okay
The first of all
Interesting thing about our data is cemented we use it's not coming from the purchase Behavior
From the content
What they see and what they like
I may can only invite kind of like 40 R&B lipstick but I want to see the 301
So
The data source is kind of like the French
And another thing is the mother has exchanging everyday which is
Simple Alive new kind of like
You waste
Cubase you sour Cafe
So
Right now
We don't have a kind of. The best model is improving everyday
The one question we asked every one of our guests
Sister working schedule
This podcast is caught 96 as we are recording this at 10 p.m. on a Friday
Just wanted to ask typical hours I shall Horseshoe Inn
As a startup and how has
Has it changed
Florida Gators
At first we walked
Kind of like
6 days now what artist
5 working days
We started
Add a the company's that at the Town clock in the morning and I think
Nowadays
A lot of teams around
Near the end of year do you still have to work very hard to about 10 or 9 to 10
Best for something
I think they they can't get up earlier
Is busier During certain Seasons like double 11
Yeah shopping
We're still very kind of like a very startup company
I wish
People that
Crazy for
The things they wanted
So they would
Care about
Related to working hours
Accomplish
Recently in the US we have Black Friday
Michelle Hunter also has red Friday
Kohl's
Could you talk about this year's
Red Friday
What are some how did it go
Is he
It went very well of course
Red Friday is kind of the festival that we
Crave for
Those who love
Tissot vs
Products
I think this year is a bit different because this year we are venturing to ww11 for the first time
Time
Souldoll uses
Have dislike to festivals
November
So
Did you know that we saw a lot of reviews ads on that very haphazard
Enjoy like a whole month celebration
By purchasing a lot of things
As a esposa e, Dennis social
Platform
What would you think how do you define success for a child tropical success can mean different things
I asked for
Social platform is usually usually measured by engagement and number of Mau
E-commerce is usually measured by gmv so how would you balance those
I think we'll just stage main focus
I'm a sociopath
Define this.
Arwen
The Chinese the young people they won't discover more lifestyle
The first brand jumping Utah has it
Deseret Book
I think that's the kind of a
Fasting
We watch it
Because I always
Think of yourself online Disneyland
You know just and then represent
Loving
And a lot of traffic
That you don't from the very you know
The richest in China we caught by fumi
To some somebody who's had to travel to
Who is traveling to Shanghai for the Space Place
Go to Disneyland
Offline
Bed actually at the ticket
It's not the Memphis model you know what they have restaurants that have shops that have long things inside
Exactly I think I'll community-based at Disneyland
So our main Focus ST YouTube
I think I will keep you the restaurants or shops you know
Right now with what you have
Not that many shops and restaurant and
There's not many things you can do all of you can consume
Sweating
Doing that but that's all main focus is stupid a larger than
So that more people can go here and they related
Discovered
As you can you expand your
Goddess Alexa
So fast
That's all
A couple years ago
And then
Not sure
Start a business
A cheaper version of
How do you guys think about your
How do you plant
And
I think this about their
Scalable business time
I still sing weathergard different we're social
Nightstand
Really not
Kind of a purely eCommerce platform
For private label I would think that's
Every company has very different strategy
Because she'll chew is the label itself
When you think of cell phone through you think of quality live using useful life itself
Talking to this Market we want to do something about Brandon
Something about the sign something about Google
Call of Duty
Rhododendron is kind of like
Cheaper version or it's kind of like hot China custom job
Within
Bring it to some friends
Some friends that
Reasonable price
Betty on people love
So it's going to the final part of
The podcast with Chase quick fire around
The first question is what motivates you to wake up each morning at work
Keeps you up at night
While I was say to really make the world a better place through
Social and yes now we're around
When you feel very heavy responsibility
What was the most
Inspiring
Story
I still remember that
Very early days
When they did
We received some
Hometown for Harvard
And you know one of our user has written
So long the letter
Send his I remember most at
You made a sea otter
I really want to send you that is because you made us
See more possibilities
$10
So that
She wants to kind of like a b or better herself
I think that's very touching you know you have
Change someone's life
This kind of story songs Yahoo
And that really gives us a lot of motivation to work harder
Help women
Exactly
To find a confidence and the gradually build model
And what keeps you up at night
What would you worry about
I think
There's sometimes I don't know whether I'm growing fast
Keep up with the path of the company
That's
I think first of all personally
If I stop growing
That might be the chance that the company will grow slower
I always wanted to know
To know what I don't know
I think that really helped the company to go
What do you do for
To ensure that your growing constantly personally
Reading and talking with a lot of
Bee pollen
Yes at 2
Jingdong is kind of like
Community created by tens and it's like 50 startup CEOs
That we went a lot of classes and a trip together
Really helped a lot that made a lot of friends and
Another thing is that read books
I think I've
Over 20 books last year
Yeah
I think when I have a question you know now that sells lot of ways to learn to you can read a book you can listen
Since you pull test
There's a lot of ways to Elara
Once you have the problem you always have to
Can talk to a person then you can love me by yourself
So out of those books which one was your favorite
Very interesting
I realized recently I read two books
Leadership
Management
You know this year the team is going very fast
The anxiety of
Not mention
After reading this to can I have more
About the management
So I think that's
I like
And another book is very interesting
Sheryl Sandberg
Laying
Also they're old
It is this year at tsinghua
How many miles I have the opportunity to do a rat talk with shows them book so I got to review this book again
And I found
Does similar sayings
On the book
Belated
Shoe wrap up
So I thought I have a lot of personal feeling
I remember Sherry Road that's on
When they
When she was thinking about joining Facebook
She
She's
She could be.
CEO of Lincoln
The CEO of Festus
Toto
If you are offered
Seat on a rocket place
Yes
Just cake it
A lot of people when they join your ad
They have the
A question about the package about titles
That's a sentence out with toddler
What is something
Others may not
I think I'm just very optimistic person I always
Play with that
Sing the same
It's not something that ever
What what is the
Like Louis
Experience
Throughout your journey
Like what motivated
I think
Mostly the people I work with
And I have been kind of like longtime friends and also watching the match
The end
That's why I was kind of like people who have followers
The journey when every time I talk to my real friends
You know what they have
Feebas really a lot of time and has made a lot of sacrifices you made rat
What so far is so
I think when I think of done everyday
I think
I have to just so you know
Skip Hop.
West across
If you're ignored Executives that you admire
USAC service number
I think
Ponemah
Blossom
Kind of like one months ago you know Charity Dinner
Spend the laws of personal efforts on that theater
To put someone to sell. The WeChat moments ass
Getting more money for kids you know for me it's still
There is difficult for those you know
Delray
Skiing in Cobra Kai
Disturbed
Fast War
Kind of like
But their High position bed
He's so humble and he's really made a loud person after you know to try to shake people's hands
See if they donate any money
Come alive when you're stupid
Play auctions
I think I really received
You know that after this very little Alfred
He still making me every little thing
I think it's really touching
Well thank you so much for joining us and now wish you all the best way she'll horseshoe
Thank you you're the best is yet to come
Sure it will be
Q79
Thanks for listening to this episode of 996
By the way
We also produce a weekly email newsletter in English
Also called 96
Who does the Roundup of the week's most important happenings
Intec in China
Subscriber simplest form
And you said also features original content
An analysis
From Zara me
Stripe at nine 6
. ggbc
Ggv capital is a multi-stage venture capital firm based in Silicon Valley
Shanghai and Beijing with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past 18 years
Proceed to pre IPO 3.8 billion dollars in capital under management real estate funds
GTA V invest in globally minded entrepreneurs in consumer internet
E-commerce
Frontier tax in Enterprise
GTA V has invested over 280 companies
With 29 IPOs in 22 unicorns
Pergola companies include
Airbnb
Alibaba
C trip
Didi chuxing
Domo
Hashicorp
Hello bike
House
Keep
Slack
Square
Hotel
Wish
Soundtrue
White white and others find out more at Gigi bc.com
Do you have any feedback on this podcast
Or would like to recommend the gas
Bisimoto
I-96
A gbc.com
This podcast is
Co-produced
Balfron
Abyss partner
Kaiser kuo
The host of the wonderful sinica podcast
It, China's economic
Political
And cultural issues