Vincent wrestler
Airport
Hi there welcome to the 9th at 6 podcast
Brought to you by ggv capital and co-produced by the Seneca podcast
On the show interview movers and shakers of China's tech industry as well as Tech leaders who have a u
China cross-border perspective and the managing partner at GTV capital
Working at startup investing in them in both the US and China for the past 20 years
Is there a jang I'm an investment analyst IG capital and a former journalist why is this show called
96 96 is the work schedule than any Chinese Founders have organically adopted that is not
I am to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
True us996 captures intensity drive and speed of Chinese internet companies
Many of which are moving faster that even their American counterparts
Hi everyone welcome to their first live show of the 96 podcast
First I'd like to thank everyone for their support for 96
We lost the show almost exactly two months ago and have gotten a lot of really positive response
This is from listeners across the world
We were ranked as one of the top shows
Technology category on iTunes
And some
Blisters that told us that this is a show that they wish had a success
On the show today we have Nathan blush Isaac
Who is Airbnb co-founder Chief strategy officer and most recently chairman of Airbnb China
Nate has played a key role in helping Airbnb expand globally and formally help establish airbnb's engineering
Data science and marketing teams
Nature has become a entrepreneur when he was in high school when he launched a business as sole to over 20 countries
Nick graduated from Harvard with a degree in computer science
He has stayed in hundreds of Airbnb homes and also has his own Airbnb homie services
Welcome to the show Nate
Thanks for having me
Certainly has already beaten the Mark Zuckerberg and Bill Gates
By graduating from Harvard
We have no Nate
Https apartment only for a long time
Since I think I sodi as early as 2010
We didn't end up being a master then
But fortunately for years later we became one has been quite interesting Journey
Working with
Now we on their baby itself but also on the
China
So you have recently been appointed
As a chairman of a Airbnb China
But he had been involved with China on all four for a while
Numbers from the very beginning
Take us through. Journey how did you guys start thinking about
China and what the process engineer you took to get to where you are today
Yeah well as a founder
Been thinking about China since we first got involved in the story goes that
I'm going to go way back so we made our first real International push outside of the US in 2011 and 2012
And the focus then was on Europe that's what we're facing lot of competition at the time
But by 2013 European really settle down and we're looking towards Asia
And in 2014 we basically one of our four strategic initiatives for 2014 was what we called when
Asia
And very quickly going into that we had a realization that
That China was going to drive a lot of the network effects in Asia
That's all the Travelers are coming from China around the world but also in Asia has a huge huge percentage of the in
About travel at these other countries
We actually at the time
Had an otherwise contemplated really focusing on China we have heard all the stories about how challenging is
Enter the market
How what western companies tech companies are often not successful
It's a we were actually focused on places like Japan
Korea
But it was to that realization that all the inbound Travelers may be coming from China that we realized that
Okay China
A critical part of this equation
And
Then the question became
How do we do this in a way that we think we can beat
Successful because my
Our starting assumption was after hearing all these stories
That the default is to be unsuccessful
Do we have to have a pretty strong rationale for 4/4 kind of how we're going to approach this in
You have to be
Choiceful
And so
R R Us
We realize our unfair Advantage is there
Global Network
That we have the fact that we have today
4 1/2 million homes in 191 different country
And we thought okay
We're really the only company in the world that can provide an outbound travel solution to Chinese
Travelers
Let's just focus on that
In other words we're not focused on the domestic
China
And we're very explicit about
That really shaped
The first
Probably two or three years of our China story
Starting in basically mid-2014
Initially the focus was all on
Really product
Actually there's a lot of product and simply didn't work in China
I do too
Restrictions we had a lot of dependencies on
On Facebook on Google
Question Alaska for load
It said we had to basically pull out those dependencies
How to find other Solutions
In a lot of stuff just wasn't relevant to in terms of like social network integration so we had to
Connected to local app stores local social networks
Local payments
So this is actually
You know if they're not at work.
It is still ongoing but I say the first
Year
You're in a half was really dominated by just fixing the Prada
The basic
Make it work
Which of course made
Remarkable difference
What's the products aren't working
Growth really did start to take off
I would say
Parallel to that we were exploring setting up a local
And that took a lot of time I think
Going into the market
Yeah we had heard all the stories and then people ask you all these questions that are
A little bit daunting like you know how do you think about
Data privacy in corporate structure in
Yeah there's all these things that as a newcomer
You know you don't really have a strong perspective on or any instincts
And so
And I think at the time we definitely
Basically asked every company that experience why did China ask them
How they approach these things
He's really learning
A lot
It took a while to get through that
Yeah it wasn't really until probably two years and that we really had a
Look like to be up and running
That was properly licensed and everything like that and that's when we started to hiring
The team
Sew-in not basically
Mid-2015
We started building the team
It was quite small for a while will pass worth it today
We have a hundred fifty people in Beijing
It's going pretty quickly
Started 2017 with around 30
And
And we saw a big
Transition about a year-and-a-half ago which is
Although the initial Focus was on outbound travel
What happened in China what just happened elsewhere to is
Travel Store Broad and they have a good experience on Airbnb
Then they come home
PlayStation hey maybe I can do it at home
And so organically a lot of people are signing up to host who had previously been Travelers
In China
And so today we have about a hundred seventy-five thousand
Homes in China
That have largely materialized organically over the last 2 years
And we spent actually very little money
To create this domestic business
Eisenhower domestic is actually a very important part of the strategy to but I think we'll get more into that later
I remember in one of our first meeting with you
You ask a Glen
Fishing
And myself
A question that I asked you
Which is should you have the server in China
Or outside
Do you have HIV or not
Investor from killing bats in the parent company
What supplements every Chinese
How do you guys work
Through
Those issues
What were the summer
Useful advice you got
During the process
Stop learning
Heading is a lot of started looking at China from us
And they're going through
Stop this in public
So you went through
Quicken 2014
Summertime
But you just need to ask a lot of questions
And so we
Would make us to China and we would go visit
All the companies we could both Chinese companies and Western companies in China
And sit-down with management
Really get their perspective get their advice I mean I think you
Going into any country but especially China you have to be
Student of the mark
And I think you have to go into it assuming
You know not
So having that blank slate is important
You get you hear a lot of things
Appetite has conflicting
If I Stay
Xiamen
We Are One
Tubidy
The classic one is United
You need a JV partner to enter the market
I'm in here
Christelle
Which in our business is really hard to break apart One Market from another again because of the global Network effects common
Tech platform
Yeah it really isn't a
Separate business
Uber
That's right
That's right so we were
Resistant that idea
But yeah so many people tell you even today
That it without a local partner
Who has a
Majority share
You're that that's kind of a recipe for not being
Successful
JV or
How to stay together
And at the end
We give it all by Sia
I'd say also that you don't have to make all these
At once
And so are we. Like parallel process
The products work
Could Happen immediately
Setting up the local ID
A lot of time
Getting lice
Took a lot of time hiring to lot of time
Yeah in the meantime you could still
Visit China talking too many members
Meanwhile your business is growing and you're just learning
They tell me that's also
I think Q2 informative it's just
Look what's happening organically
Aside from what you are manually
And you can learn so much
So you're recently it be
China
I wonder what has been like four
How often do you go to church
It's very exciting for me because
I've been a part of it
Kind of decision-making on the bigger things from the beginning I was a huge
Advocate of taking asleep
Focusing on China
Incel
Yeah it is great to be able to see the story through
The difference now is that I'm in a more operational capacity
So I get to try to keep that about every decision
I n
Understand more of the contacts
And I think that's really fascinating because China is such a different Market
That
You need to do a lot of learning
And we are what you
What you read about is it just so different than here
That
Yeah it
It would be less interesting ever
Easy
So the fact that it's hard
Make it really interest
Teen challenge for me
How often do I go there I would say basically monthly right now I'll be going there on Sunday
Are you learning Chinese at all
And I learning Chinese
About a year-and-a-half ago I started
Doing a podcast series to learn Chinese
After about a month after I had to stop
The tones are just
Too much it just doesn't stick in my head
I guess
Also people have proven that it's not
Extremely nice
Language but it really high
Sounds like a challenge
So I wonder what is airbnb's trying to team working on now you mentioned there over a hundred people there
I say we have a 154 times at the moment
About
From a functional perspective
60a say about of those people
60 are working on the product
And we intend to grow that never quite a lot
How we think product is
Probably the biggest sleeper in general for the business
And it is very measurable and
The second largest
Yeah contention would be able to host Community operations
Really
Enmarket on the ground feet on the street type thing
Where where
Hosting meetups
Inspecting property
Things of that nature
There's probably easily
40 people in that group
And then I say every function has at least
That 10 to 25 people
It's a complex business
And so you know we have a
Very build-out marketing team
That
Yeah
I will be putting out a variety of home-grown campaigns throughout the year
In other words not leveraging Global assets but everything kind of original from the ground up
Even the concept
Public policy horse has a big deal for us
And so that varies
Save-A-Lot municipality by municipality and so
That also requires a lot of people
So
There's quite a lot going on
I will say that part of our precious
China has been to build up
I'm at autonomous a team as possible which
Largely comes down to making sure that
All the resources needed to ask
You are actually in China
And we've really tried to cut all the execution
From San Francisco
Possible
John the early days a lot of product working and other work is getting done here or out of the Singapore
And we've really gotten quite strict about that
I mean despite the fact that there are others in the company you want to help out we've really
Push all the EX
Sakura shocked that China
It's all happening in the same office
Badaling Beijing
But if we take
Separate
Cannabis antutu
And talk about album
First
That's where the
Linkable Network
Artifact is the strongest
He has said repeatedly in many conferences
China's largest outbound tourism marketing
And grab the largest was a busy
44u
How do you plan a skill that business
Does it require a separate team to manage
All the inventory worldwide
Cater to the Chinese
Tuscaloosa
It does not really require that much of a separate approach
Especially on the supply home side
The homes that Chinese Travelers are booking are no different than anyone else around the world
Thus far
And
That doesn't seem to have slowed us down
I do think there's a question on my mind which is as we
Become more mainstream and we move Beyond Tier 1
Tr2 tr3
You know what
How did the requirements change
I'd say a lot of our travels right now
Have some comfort level of English
And of course that's not representative of the market
And so
Yeah we have experiment thought about you know how can we better match Chinese Travelers with Chinese hosts abroad but
How can we
Help translate user-generated content
I think of that nature but by and large dust by we having
Gone that way yet
I'd say
On the domestic front
You know we've got a lot of things
Totally naked China
Free sample
We have a much bigger emphasis on quality
Making sure that
Philosophical
Philosophically want to make sure that
We don't have what we call a two-tier system
We want to shut that the quality of the product in China is of equal quality to that
Globally
And it's a little bit challenging at different prices
What's peanuts drastically there's just a far lower price point
And there's also an abundance of
Home Inventory
Make it home
In China
You get a lot of inbound homes.
Are kind of empty shells
Yeah that doesn't doesn't happen that aren't actually lived in
And so
We have actually prioritize quality over growth
And we actually
I routinely taking down properties in China
That we feel don't best represent the brand
I'd say if we let the business grow completely organically in China
It might tend towards
Kind of service department
A little bit more professional
And
Yeah we have is this brand image
All about
Unique local authentic travel on its very aspirational brand want to make sure we preserve that
Hi in China and so
Some of the operational things to do
Support that
On the ground photography
Brassy doing in person
Inspections on homes in certain cases
Everything that gets posted on a cyclist reviewed at least online
And often results in a phone call where we coach and we talked about how to
Make this host even more successful
It's all just a lot more Hands-On in China
Then we've done anywhere else
Speaking of the brand in the lower-tier cities
Are they white issued a lot of Western companies face when they expand into China
Is that their brand is perceived to be very Western and it's hard for them to connect with the grassroot users
Many of the Miranda lower-tier cities
So is perceived to be podc or not connected with
Energy of the land
I wonder if that is that something behind
The decision to name Airbnb I being in Chinese
Which means welcome each other with love in Chinese
What efforts have been made to make sure the brand is
Perceived as more grass
Absolutely. That's one star Chinese
Brand name
Ciara go now
And so they're actually a few years that we eat when we had Airbnb
And that
Yeah I don't
There's no evidence that that was slowing us down
That being said as we thought about becoming more mainstream
Yeah there is a hypothesis
Just that we needed a local
Name
I would say 1 year in
I think we are correct about that
Sada latest kind of marker
Getting surveys
I wish definitely showed that I'd being is
Resonating a lot more and more memorable than Airbnb
Did I'm sure it's very difficult for a local person to
Just to say I remember since
Has nothing to do with the language
So I think
I think that was a good choice for us but if you look at our history at starting about that it wasn't really necessary on day one
I think it's more nicer now everything about growing the domestic business
And branching out
Her2 Q3 study
So when you enter China than the market was in a blank slate like there were quite a few
Other company domestic companies that were doing home rental or Home Sharing
How confident were you that you were going
To be able to carve out a meaningful Market
How do you perceive Local Company
Well
I was always very confident about the outbound p
It's because I knew that something that we could do uniquely well it'll be a long time before local companies
Build an outbound business
And so that part I think was always
Pretty clear in and honestly that was our only aspiration
Begin with
Maybe there was an assumption that the mess
Business
What's likely going to be too hard
And so
We explicitly did not focus on that for
Two to three years
It was until we saw that organic growth that we started getting a little bit more ambitious
Looking at
The competition which there's been a lot I think at one point there was about a dozen companies
In the earlier days now.
Just a few
There's been a lot of consolidation in the meantime
We've kind of seen some of the story in other countries
As well I mean it certainly has been a lot of Airbnb
Clowns in Europe
And I'll swear
And
Yeah I think there's a few learnings that we
Seen elsewhere which is that
Airbnb is a Marketplace
Airbnb's of C2C Marketplace consumer-to-consumer
It's a community
And it's built on
Trust
And often through use a referral
And that
Growing that kind of business takes
Time
And what we seen with
Competition
Around the world
Is that
They look at us and they say that's a successful model
I'm going to raise a bunch of money
I try to speak
Quickly
I think that is a common mistake
Because
To build
The kind of business we built we purposely have kind of gone slow
And it's been built through word-of-mouth
And use our testimony and Trust
Building
And not through direct sales
And so what we've seen in other countries
Not specifically, but other countries is
People raise a hundred million dollars
Hirevue sales team
And it really becomes hard like a Beetle seat
Model almost right off the bat
And if it starts out that way it's really hard to then back into a C2C model
The minute
All your homes feel like the professionals
Suddenly the average person doesn't feel like they belong
In that commit
And so
Oh that's one generalization I would make
You know the other thing is that
We've been nothing
Very honest with ourselves which is to recognize that
We will never move as fast as it truly local come
We will try to
But I think
I think you have to be honest about you know what your strengths and weaknesses are
And so you know the weaknesses that
We will
Never move as fast as local company and will probably never have the appetite
To spend as much
Money as a local company would be wild
I mean it is truly
Eye-opening
How much are oil companies willing to spend spend spend
With very little Revenue
But based on the idea that you know it's kind of winner-take-all
And
And I think that works
Floor companies
As an outside I can do that just something that
It's not going to work for us
Why did that would work as the outbound
So that has been kind of our focus and I think what has
Say that despite the other 200
So just leave is also investor into. Which some people have called the Airbnb of China
High School to explain what Twitter is and how
Maybe it's different from Airbnb
Picture
To tok a starter
With the help of a c trip
Partial these days are HomeAway
Growing in the US and also Airbnb
So the idea was to give them quite a bit of money
Seedling grow fast
And inside humidity getting to
Going out to look more professional
Managed serviced apartments type
So you have some more of a Beat
Because he filled ncdc for sure
Anna
If captures. Segment of the population in China which
Definition need for
And we also saw in the market that there is a shout out to
Nothing more but much more quiet my price point than the both Airbnb into jaw
And that one's phone to buy lot of local money varby money
And it's going after the more value consumers as young students
At like 10 bucks 15 bucks a night
Type of accommodation
And so
China Hustle
4 tier cities and at least in this Eichmann
3tier competitors
Ichiban house, 424
But obviously we think that the market is big enough you can come in multiple 1
Did the way I was
Describe the difference between say aramid touche
And it goes back to what I said earlier about how they
How to bootstrap your business
Immediately went after at Sunset apartment buildings that had 20 vacant units at a time
Yeah sometimes even hotels
Network service
Apartments
And so they brought on a lot of
Inventory lot of homes
Apartments very quickly
But they're all fairly generic
And they didn't have the same above character
That are individually owned
Homer Park
At what
And so there is a large quantity of inventory but it didn't necessarily stand out as being
I think
That much
More unique or cool relative to a hotel
And so I think it was hard to build a
Interesting consumer brand around that
I think they've done a very good job and having a lot of supply
I think they've had a much harder job
Building Supply
Consumers I think part of that is
Because there isn't as much of a brand
I'm around 2
Respect in China
I've grown
Expendable
And so
Unlike in the US where
Go to one of the
Big hotel chains in the US
Most of that building
All rooms haven't been
Refurnish
Where
Upgraded in the last 10 years
Internal audit new hotels coming
So to be to win against the hotel business
You need to have something that could differentiate
Are BBQ to do it through
Community Building
And
Pooja choose to do with her professionally managed
Stop
That's why they make that
Love you seem more places than
Hotels Canby
So it's it's a it's a different way stock market for sure
Jerry yang founder of Yahoo has said on her show that
China is not a place for transaction
Training supplies for relationship
I wonder what has your experience
Spinlife Beauty relationships
Especially as someone else
Didn't grow up there
I totally agree with that
Again I going into the market I mindset has always been to be the student
Don't assume anything and
Ask all the questions
There's no dumb question
I'm really thankful.
You know when I go to China people are been very generous
To take meeting
Very generous with their time and very generous with their advice
And I just say I like those casual interaction
Open all the doors
And expose you to a lot of warnings that that make you more
Successful
I would also say that you know it's very easy to not know what's going on as an outsider
Like when you don't understand the language of the customs
I think it's very easy to get the wrong impression
So when you hiccup more transactional approach you think you're on the same page about self
You think something went well
Because you had some quick Exchange
And you thought you took away the right message
Do you have to get it
And so I think it's only when you
Spend
Atlanta
Hours with somebody
That you really kind of
Truly get honest
Same page and I kind of have an understanding
United exhaust
Did a culture
And this is from an outsider's perspective
Buy it
It just values relationship the fact that you everyone always has a gift for you
When when they come to visit or are you visit them even
I think
Is a sign of valuing
Relationships
And putting an emphasis on that
Forza run efficiently so we have gifts
Forney
How to do want to share your experience on that
You also didn't grab email in China
I think China's open the market has very merry tok
Oxycodone
If you go into the market with the attitude that
You going to learn a lot
Contribute
Sometimes
Contribute before you get anything back
It's it's a country where a lot of people of were willing to
I'm work with you
Because of your willingness to
To do something good and positive
Earlier this evening
We had another talk
In which an Enterprise from Singapore
It's trying to sell
Their service pin to both us and China
And now she found out China more welcoming
Yeah I sold the product worked
The the customers like Alibaba intention willing to fast-track them
Giving more resources to help him to build a product
Roanoke
Quickest sooner
Because they know the customers know that they can use the solution and help him win
And that woman was not openness
I also work tonight 6 to get stuff done
Is almost very difficult to find anywhere in the world
Even with
Government relations I think it's
The super elevator
Which is to say going to the conferences
Talking about the topics
That are important
The officials
Get out grabbing the meetings telling the story
Signing the memorandum of understanding
You all these
Things go a long way and I'd say are you a fairly unique
The China some of its Asian more Broadway
But I say in China
These
Things have really open doors
Brusque
Where you guys we have taken care of the western approach
I think we would be kind of
Shut up
And so
And I think
I wouldn't have known any of this
Without having a local tea
And I think that's another part of like our approach
Has been to
Build a local team in Beijing
Really Empower them
Make sure that
All the execution happen to that
They basically guide me
How to trade these walk-in clinic
Destructive relationships
Versus taking
What would otherwise be probably can I eat with thrush
Randall you have
About Honda 50
People in China
In August is a huge Market
You can easily see
10x if not hundreds
Nice ice
How do you plan to
Rollatini China over
Well in general with our model it is relatively operationally light
I will say one of the unique things about China is
The cost of Labor can be laughing so enables a lot more operational model
How did you see us a lot of the Shanghai to make
NY China economy so successful in China
The fact that
There's so much labor available to assist in making the transaction goes smooth
That being
Said
And I think
We're still going to take a relatively disciplined approach
Tuacahn
How we grow
Bad can't have a growth class like I said earlier
I acknowledge that we probably will never be willing to spend as much
At the competitors
But we will definitely spend more than we do another country is in fridge that but we're doing a China
Having under 50 people on the ground we've done nowhere else
And it is our only product
Team outside of the US
And so
We're definitely willing to think different
I do think
Look at that
The discipline can also be good
How much does a reflection of how we approach the market
There's a fine balance between
High conviction and paranoia
And I think you need both
I think we went to the market
Having done a lot of reflection on her strategy but we've also could have stuck to a gun to that strategy
At the same time
I'm constantly paranoid about
What are we missing
How are we doing
Are we falling behind we're getting ahead
And I think
It's a fine balance between conviction and paranoid because when you're paranoid
You can easily question your conviction and change direction
Which if you do that too many times this big problem
At the same time if you have so much conviction
That
You know you're kind of have a
You got your kind of overly confident
That's a big problem
So I think that's
Been critical as we think about
Yeah do we do things like we do here do we do things like
We see others doing in China
It's definitely a both
And
I think finding that middle ground and sticking with it
While also being very reflective is critical
Travels inherently a very Network driven business
That the bigger you are the more dependents you have
The network is that it's going to be worth more
One of the simple math we did
Before investing you guys in 2014
Was that the Priceline of that point in time whiskey billion dollars and they didn't crack China
Fast forward 3 or 4 years later
Their bodies and no 90 billion
Infantino grow
But you have something that's harder for them to replicate
In China the taking a more indirect approach that you know
Lately investing super early on
And most recently they invest in meituan
Is this daily activity encourage
Agoda and other assets they have to go to China to partner with a lot of people in China go out for the Alabama Market
After using the indirect approach
Is a
Feasible approach
I do think that by strategically investing other companies in China
That it is a productive work out for them
Mary Scully after the album Market
I think it's certainly is it's a safe approach
And
It's
Somewhat of an incremental
I think
That can be a very smart way to
Start
And based on what they weren't that experiences
They might decide to lean into it more
Which I think they have over
4 time
And it's not unlike us
Right where we started off making
Basically a product decision to invest and resources and fix
Tena products
Then we decide to set up a local entity but really still
Limit our involvement out battles
A lightweight and Deborah
The now it's a full-fledged
Fully
Staffed
For each function
Team focusing on domestic
In addition to outbound
And so there's been a progression there as we've learned
And I think
The decisions they've made in
Play doubt
It's basically
Allowing them to work as they go
So you don't basically
Jump
Too far to something you don't understand
And an n
For them
Domestic otm marketing channels very different
Gazelle
Etsy Tramadol authority of Versailles
Oxygen Bar
Buffalo China
You Got Served
You going to China
Yeah she can compete against local players in the in the
In the long run
How do you want to grow the Potomac business in what segment of the
The populist do on the focus on
I should have mentioned this
The earlier one of the questions but you're the reason why we
We
How to expand it in bishan
To include domestic wasn't simply because it was organically taking off
I mean that was
That gave us confidence
I think from a strategic perspective lights
Actually really critical that were successful
What's a domestic
Is that
Domestic is more frequent
And it's relevant to a larger part of the population
And so we have a concern that if we're not successful at domestic
Then somebody else would I find what Home Sharing is
China and it won't be Airbnb
And so as
As outbound travel becomes more common
Those outbound Travelers will already be customer
Hours of The Local Company
And end
It will not be natural for them to now come to Airbnb
Until I actually think our success domestically is
Is a little bit of a race
To educate the market and build a relationship
That will hopefully blossom into an outbound
Travel
The other kind of
Codependency between domestic and outbound is that
There's a very different
Adra dr's average daily rate
Especially the price people are willing to pay per night
This one Chinese Travelers go brought they pay
Going
International rate
Which is your more on the order of
90 hundred bucks tonight
Domestic travel
Is that a much lower APR because there are a lot of inexpensive hotels
And say yeah you're talking more in the $40
Somewhere in there
And so
What that means though is it
Is very different economics what is your class structure isn't really that different
In other words
We justify a lot of our expenses
Based off of outbound wrapping
A lot of those Investments actually benefit our domestic
Big business
Where is the local companies they only have domestic Revenue
So they actually have a
Much smaller Revenue pool which to justify
Their cost that are willing
Burn a lot more money than we are
And so
They still spend
A lot even if they have less Revenue
Shuffle my business model perspective we can sustain
Our business
In a much more healthy terms
Because of this
Duel Dino
They're coming back to you like
The importance of domestic and how we compete
You know I think it's really about
Continuing to draft off are outbound business
The Graduate domestic
Focus on quality because that's something that requires extra
For effort and work doing things in China we dumped
Do elsewhere
But
Don't
Spend money against just a domestic
Everything we spend money on
Also
Especially from me
Consumer demand perspective
Has relevancy for the outbound business
As well
And so the air like you just vibe
Troy on the outbound and it just so happens that it also grows
To know this point
13 years ago Jack ma made a decision
2 * 14
Tok Mommy
Listen to StarTalk
If he was worried that the Alibaba. Compass
Which is the outbound
Tree business for Chinese
Supplies was hung
Stuff worldwide
Maybe under attack
EBay Crocs de Messi
E-commerce business in China
So you have to start elbow
Do nothing else is defensive measure to make sure that people who could
Start selling the
If I'm the one
Will be selling on the top of the master bathroom
40 Celtics
Customers overseas
And the second one that is over important for listen to know is that
In China we really value
Frequency music
In the US a lot in this us we've been MBA textbook
You spell awesome learning about having high margin
Evens low-frequency it's okay but make sure you next time is good every order
You do is high-margin as is Great Britain
Those pens most likely end up being Manish
And so in in China we learn how you have hive
Highest frequency of usage look at WeChat
Look at table out you have high frequency of usage
The chance are you can spell that into
Other business overtime
Without a high frequency of usage
Having a user
You don't have any Leverage
Start other business
That's why I'm a tendon pain which started off as
Groupon food ordering now it's
Expanding into
Ride-hailing movie tickets
Travel and everything
I think also with different China it is is the mobile option
Extremely high
You see all the activity on mobile in in with different mobile is
People only work with so many apps
We only have so many accents
And so I think there's kind of natural 10
To gravitate towards those same trusted providers that have your payment information on file that are already installed on your phone
Versus venturing out and in trying something
New endeavor
Could you walk us through how Airbnb approaches localization how is your
Chinese
Customer-facing product different from
That the one we used to and I heard that half of the booking in China
Through alipay now
So what what what are other examples of
Changes you've made to the product to suit
The tastes and habits of Chinese
Consumers
So there's the front end and the backend
The backend exec
She's quite expensive and I'll get that
On the front end
There's the obvious stuff
You know in terms of
The maps in The Social Network Integrations and
Mobile app store in the alley.
And by the way
Something like alipay when he added that
Is like a business
Increase 15% overnight
As you said it's now more than half the transactions by far
You have a hotspot feature and had the business jump
Double-digit percentage overnight so I was
Pretty cool
So that was very packable other things we do that
Less noticeable
The homepage is slightly different
In China
So I called the product
White Pages
Set up the pages to profile pages that display the homes
It's different
They basically lay out the information differently prioritize different things
A funny enough
The changes that the China team came up with they then tested globally and actually work
Well Global Excel
Iced Out
We took some lessons out of China in
Next part of the
I would say a lot though is
Similar in other words we made a decision
From the start not to Forfeit codebase
Not to create a separate app
And so
The byproduct of that is
80%
85%
Pretty similar
On the back end
There is a lot of
Complexity
That can easily go under-appreciated
And that complexity is
To deal with
The kind of data storage laws
Site performance
214 Compton
We know we're not at social networks so that's not
Not as big a hurdle for us of course
There's that
I would say fraud
In China is quite sophisticated and the fraud we see coming out in China
Oh yes it is very different than fried we see elsewhere until we actually have a
Chinese Tech fraud Justice
I said yeah and it's at least another thing is there's a lot of like
Credit scoring Innovations coming out in session
And these are good input
Into our trust
Tasty
Answer these other things that we've invested a lot in the back and that you don't answer
It is very important lesson
Volodymyr
To realize
Yes I did in just a moment on that I'll say that you can look at your numbers I feel really good
But I think you really have to stand a check your numbers
Sendai
Not get too excited too fast
Because so often you realize that you know
5 15% of whatever you're saying
Might not be for real
But and so
I think that's another lesson
From China is that
You have to have a dedicated team
He just like that you can't Take Your Eye Off the Ball
And you can easily find yourself in a place where you thought your business was doing really great
But it was actually
All artificial activity
So in China Millennials now account for over half of the travel Market
And they're known for their taste for adventure and there are more open-minded
I think Milano's now account for over 80% of Airbnb trying to Airbnb China Market which is a high proportion.
The other countries
Do you make any special efforts to appeal to Chinese millennials
I think it's a little bit less of what we do and it's more about what we don't do that has caused this and in other words
Chinese Millennials are materially different than their
Parents
Which of course it's
Does every country by an in China it's it's very start
You have a different
Comfort with language with
International travel
Especially around organized tours
Versus
The free independent Tech planning
With technology
And so you know we just see young Travelers
Having the ability and appetite
To embrace Airbnb
In a way that older Travelers
Are prepared to take that leap
We've also like not invested in
Working with tour operators
So we haven't netsilik gone after the
The order
Market
And
Contrast that with other countries
You know in China is 80%
Millennial on the traveler side another countries that would be 50
2%
By comparison
I think on the host side there's also a difference
I don't know the official number but certainly
From my anecdotal experience
First month's rent
He'll definitely see
A lot of the house being younger typically
They've come at it because they they traveled on Airbnb for
Cesar from that angle where as in
Other countries
Typically the hosts are older property owners
Empty nesters
I want to listen to what you said on this podcast
If there's a way for you to
Dumor China
Album business with Millennials who may not be as fluent in English
And there should be more of them than those who are
English
Even when you can crack that
That should be a huge right before your domestic business overtime
As well
Absolutely
Absolutely I think your dad's
That's going to be hot
Maybe the next big challenge for us
In terms of
Yeah we've accomplished a lot
I think you're one cities
Where networks are ubiquitous and extremely song
Your presence here too but
Yeah that's
That's
The really big part of the market
M&M can weed
Do as well there I think that will be interesting on the next year
In preparation for this podcast was look at something
Basic Chinese authorization stats
They are
I can cover like as Europe in US
There are 14 cities in the US
That has over a million
Resume
Heather 3 in the California here to San Diego San Jose and LA
The three alone in Texas
San Antonio Houston and Dallas
There are
Just under 40
Of such cities with over a million people each in
Europe
Including turkey
Putting China number is 160
The number is going to double
The next 10 to 15 years
So when we look at 162 360
With all these a million people each that's a huge Market
For Airbnb to tok
Yeah and I think I may have much rather
Be popular with millennials
Because yeah they're going to
Grow older and and and you're going to try to go with them but I also think
As millennials
Go off at families they want to afford
Larger homes
In urban areas which they have an affinity for
I think we can be apart
Of that Journey meaning I think
We can help them
To buy a bigger home to ever hire lifestyle and be that. That's what we seen elsewhere
And so I think you know
This is this
In China this move towards urbanization
And when you look at these Urban centers are growing so quickly but also becoming so expensive
The affordability is actually becoming quite low
Especially in the new development which I think a lot of the
Young Millennials aspire
To live in
I think we can actually be a part of the
Dissolution that they're already familiar with
And help them to afford
A big arrest
Valentina's precise astrology
Government
Is that a top 26
B2xpress of 11
So the other
140 cities
Are organized enough
That connect the high-speed rail and then more Subway
Do bees eat
For Millennials to move to
So you can see that
You guys are moving along
Calculator
I think partly because of urbanization others
Also a booming share economy there
There's so many startups that describe themselves as Airbnb for this or Airbnb for that
So there are startups
That allow you to share bicycles
Clothing basketball phone chargers
Umbrellas luxury handbags
I'm in the Chinese government actually
Expects to grow the transaction of the Sherry County by forty percent
Percent year-on-year over an ex
Skewers
And by 2020 is expected to account for over 10% of China's GDP
Why doesn't the sharing economy has
Take a note
In China is your thing this Grill this sustainable going forward
But I think the the urban density
And share scale the market
Helps a lot
Detroit liquidity between
Spider-Man
I also think that the
Low labor costs
Allow
A bit of hand-holding in terms of making
Can transactions
Workwell
In other words
Aladdin Marketplace in China are not
QRC to see there's usually a component
Of hand-holding
To facilitate the transaction at 11 that you wouldn't
The elsewhere
Usually as offline kind of runners
Will help with the deliver AR
Quality control taking inventory
Stuff that we're Franklin
Not cost effective in
San Francisco
By arguing and in alot of pain
Other countries
So I think that's why we're seeing so much Innovation I'd also say like the government as
Made a pretty strong message that like
Innovation is welcome
And for me it's such a different conversation when I go to China and
The general Outlook of policy-makers are
What's the new models
To them are opportunist
And there should be rules around his opportunities but they generally say new models are a good thing
Let's do that
But like left we're on our way into it and take steps together
Other countries
Basically policymaker say
Wow that sounds really cool
But I have all my existing constituents running on old model
And so we really need to
Be cautious
And basically do optimize for the incumbent
In the industry
And
Kind of star from that mindset
As opposed to seeing
Everything new as a big opportunity
It's so you know I think
That helped some of these ideas
To thrive Ematic bike sharing is a great example to
Where are you bike sharing in China has been a little bit of a free-for-all
And that's generally been accepted in a way that in the US at least
Then I think other
Western world countries
People said no you like you just going to be a lot of ground rules about where you can discard your bike
And frankly needing to be
License
Before you can even
Try this idea
Has do you want to come in John
I think a runny semen our show is quite unexpected is China actually has less regulations or
People face
Less regular tree
Push pop when they
Start new things in China that allowed to go find some
People don't know that you know 10 years ago the most
Valuable
Probably try to come
What is in China or China
Mobile tunnel
Control of petroleum
And
ICBC largest bank
And 10 years later the most valuable
Highest market cap companies
All of china's tencent Alibaba
2vz Bike Company
With US dollar funds
And this is also
So for a
Country
Run by Chinese
Comes party
That. Just something that you
You cannot imagine
Was even possible
Bullfighting music
In the same time you look at the speed of adoption
Take picture example
It doesn't come so fast so soon
Partially because the government knows that
Dry sherry in Visalia
Part of the solution to deal with traffic problem
So is needed
And Annie speed sort of
Hard to figure out
How helpful you can be when I pee
And regulate accordingly after
And so what happens is that you see new Dollar Tree in news
Susan being try more quickly in China
That you just met you are
TV on top of that you think of China as a country that has 4.7 million
Stem graduates
Every year
Verses only less than 700 thousand
In the US
Ensure more people going to be more equipped
Try and
Design and enrolled on new product
Faster pace
Almost anywhere else in the world
If politically stable and continue for the next 10 years
It's an is hard imagine
Airbnb not have a much bigger market share
Norcross
That it is today
So it is imperative for American Stout
Figure out
How to crack China
Deception Point Market
Ignoring me
And I say this is coming back to the topic of relationships with
Came up earlier
Yeah this is where I think the mindset in China is
Yes you can do this
But
In the butt is we're going to kind of code about the regulation
Together
It's very much based on the relationship
I think you need to establish dialogue early
And kind of give the heads-up about your intentions
And there can be a lot of back-channel conversation and collaboration
That you just don't see elsewhere
Yeah that's where things can I come to a head
Unfortunately and then there's a lack of progress
In China I think is a lot of conversation
On the back end
About your how we going to navigate this
And doing that a Cooperative manner
Not too late or MVB on the spot bed
We went to in this investment
Thinking that everybody's popular most likely
US Cellular
Text out of a 6 seat
In China the best
I want people look at Uber as
Example that
Failte chine
We actually just
State chemical burn 2 billion dollars in town if you can 2014
Butt. Tube in dollars. They clinical burned
Ends up being a steak
In
DD
Which is 2 years later is now Worth close to and I'm doing.
For any mistakes I could be
4X in 2 years
Have you asked very good
Obviously how they've done that earlier in 2013 when I broke the first meeting could have the same state Foley 20 min.
But that was a true story
But I think I think that we really think that
Glennys teaching myself we all think.
Did you do that
Are babies unique people
Prabhas Global Network
You are running a
That are big
Be quite different
In China
Versus what other
There's Donuts in the US
So if we were
We want to make sure that
Thought I really appreciated your support. Thank you hun
We're going to move to the last part of the show witches around a rapid fire questions
The first one is what is the most memorable Airbnb home that you
Either in China or
Around the world
Nicest home was one and in Maui recently it's actually I got to be part of our new luxury products are launching
But most memorable I would say it was a treehouse in Bali
Which was all made of bamboo in the jungle it was like three stories three bathrooms but it again
Treehouse
So that was pretty cool
Two hundred bucks tonight oh my God
Yeah I was probably $18 a night and in tilapia
I put out three different stories to say that like you know
Many different price points and many different
Types of experiences all good you can have but also very different that's the beauty of Airbnb
Who is an entrepreneur you admire the most and why
How is it right now Elon Musk
Simply because he's just taking on like these
Amazon mega ball challenge Mission Impossible over
At the same time you just like
How is it possible that you can just
Take such a bully
So confidently and actually
Bring results
Sure y'all feel the same
What do you do for fun
If you have simplified
Haworth one right
It is honestly but that aside I have a family so I have two kids so they can be quite busy and
Pure joy
Aside from family
Go to the gym
I don't know what's so funny about that
Buy Peloton to get do it from the comfort of your home
Digital portfolio
But I actually I I think I think
Staying healthy is really important when you're working hard
Especially even just
Yeah distressing it
Working out whatever that van that takes
Has enough throughout all my endeavors
Starting at
How much younger age
Has helped me a lot
To kind of stay focused and get
Get stuff done and be productive
Aside from that
Travel course
Bicycling skiing
What's something you read recently that you recommend or that cost you a lot
Right now I'm reading something called out seven powers
Book about basically strategy and it talks about
The difference between
Strategies that really enduring trait enduring power
First is what my traits assessment short-term
NN basically the book says that
Everything of how to be boiled down to
Strategies
It's Academy
Thing to see something so simple
The story behind Tony.
Successful companies
I want to hear
Thank you so much for your time this was really fun
Thanks for having me
And thank you for coming
Hu7989
San Jose International listening to this episode
996 by the way we also produces weekly email newsletter in English also called 9 + 6
Who does the runner-up of the week's most important happenings in Tech in China subscribers some photos for this
Informative and fun to read and you said also features original content and Analysis from Zara
Stripe at nine 6. GG bc.com TTV capital is a multi-stage venture capital
Friendbase in Silicon Valley on high and Beijing we have been partnering with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past
18 years from seed Trooper IPO with 3.8 billion dollars in capital under management real estate fund
GTA V invest in gold we minded entrepreneurs in consumer internet e-commerce Frontier tag
An Enterprise GTA V has invested over 280 companies with 29 IPOs in 22
Unicorn orfila companies include Airbnb Alibaba C trip
Domo hashicorp hellobike cows keep plaque Square
Hotel wish soundtrue white white and others find out more at ggvc.
You have any feedback on this podcast or would like to recommend a gas please email us at 996
A gbc.com this podcast is co-produced Battlefront and business partner
Kaiser kuo the host of the wonderful sinica podcast it cover China's economic political
And cultural issues