Hi listeners
For today's episode we have a crossover show with our sister podcast
Founder real talk
Which is hosted by Armitage
Can partner Glenn Solomon based in Menlo Park
Glenn has left many of Jujubes Investments Enterprise SAS comp
It's in the US
Found a real talk is a bi-weekly podcast where clay interviews Founders and start-up Executives about the challenges that they say
And how they've grown from Top experiences
This episode is an interview with Orion gel or a chold one
Who is the founder of mocha
Which gland and I recorded in Beijing
Also we've had two very fun 96 Community meetups in the last
Why in Beijing where we had over 200 attendees
And one in Shanghai where we had dinner with 40 of our less
We frequently host offline events
Where you can meet not just members of the GB team but also other like-minded folks swearinger
Attack in China
All of these events are announced in our listeners WeChat groups in
Slash Channel
You can join these at 96.3 gbc.com
Enjoy the show
Hi there
Welcome to the night at six podcast brought to you by ggv capital on the show we interview movers and shakers
China's tech industry as well as Tech leaders who have a US
China cross-border perspective on the managing partner at ggv Capital
And I've been working at startup investing in them in both in US
In China for the past 20 years
My name is Zahra Jones I'm an investment analyst ggv capital and a former journalist
Why is the show called 96
6 is the work schedule than any Chinese Founders have organically adopted that is
KTM 6 days a week
To us
996 captures intensity Drive
In speed of Chinese internet companies many which are moving faster than even the American counterpart
Hi everybody
I'm excited today to have
Orion
Zhao
Hazard gas
And we also have Mike
Colleagues origin
As our guest host
So Ryan is the founder and CEO of
Mocha
What is a fast-growing
MyHR SAS startup
Happy China
Ngtv invested in Orion
Company in the
Capri around in late 2000s
The company has been growing faster
Mocha house companies
Increase
The efficiency of their hiring process
By providing a CRM software
It currently
Has hundreds of costume
China Inn
Including the likes of xiaomi
Burger King Levi's and many other
Recognize
I'm also really excited
Because this is the first time
A china-based
Founder CEO
Profound Realty
In fact
You're recording this
In Beijing
Orion is arising from China but graduated
Convert mm
13 Souls
He's now returning to China
He spent close
2 years after his
For turo
In the Bay Area
Before returning to China in 2000
Start mocha
What is co-founder who's also
Attorney from
Tell rhyme welcome sound real talk
Thanks thanks having me
So first question for you
Starbucks
What about the compass
Tell us about me
NYU
Cool
First came back to China actually had no idea what else
I was like thinking about maybe joining a company or like a coup start a company
Looking for opportunities
And because I was working at or else we do a lot alike and have Frost
So I was looking at and financial which does a lot alike
Credit analyzing insta
And I realize that they don't
Could a lot of Versailles on their recruiting
Site like Curry side
So that got me interested because in the US
Call me they all have like a really fancy career site
I went out to her to like talk with Bunkhouse HRT Post in China
And I realize they have some real pinpoints like besides a career page
Such a slack collaboration between HR and their hiring managers and the interviewees
And also they have problem like liking all the talent back
And lastly they have problem analyzing their recruiting data
So I found those pain points are real and then I looked at the market there's not like Rudy koopor I Solutions all there
So I decided to build while myself
So has it always been your plan to return to China or did it happen organically
I think more organically it was not life
Swirl defended I think
Overall I think I was thinking about like come back to China documentary about life
I still haven't Wells like feeling old I feel like I learned a bit like in the US already
Like come back and see what's going on
I guess not like Rudy planet
So when you decide to start mocha you already come back
China
This problem that you
You just mentioned it wasn't like
Understood that problem why you were in the US
Yeah so I was anxious in the US I see all of financing happening
I know the market
Is Rihanna
But I just don't know what's going on there
And how this
Fear of missing out I feel like om light in San Francisco everything's going well
I just don't know what are the opportunities in China I'm like trying to understand in the US but never seen the
Darling just so different so I decided to take a leap of faith
Not knowing anything and come back
And then like looks
Simple problems to solve
Originally actually gave myself 6 months
How to discover what you do
Actually only took me like two months to fund ideomotor
Oh wow
The same feeling I think that fomo is universal to all Chinese students who study abroad these days
Read out a news on your WeChat moments in like all your friends doing interesting things
Yes
So what were some of the challenges you
Effaced coming back
Attorney
Did you
You know feel like
The time away
Actually
Cookie further away from what
What's going on in China and really understand the market or were there that you could bring back
More positive or negative
It's a really good question I think there's positive and I think there's some also like a non- but like I guess things that
I need to improve more I guess I'll start with the things that learning LOL that help me in the US
I think the one thing that I learned in college was sort of not working
I think I was
Lucky to join
Business attorney in Berkeley Hills, Dallas ins Inc
Supervisor in Siler no not working
Actually really important that I think I'd learn some of the
Excuse
So help me to know how to network and that goes to the downside of being a sort of sea turtle were returning
Is because I have no connection
I don't know who to call about to discover problem
But I do have the skills to not work
Childlike ask my friend okay I'll make this intro or like okay talk to this person and then get that person to introduce me to
To another person
So do you have the skills budget
Cuz I don't have that resource
But I feel like
My education in the US really help me that I have asked you to learn how this feel to not work those things are
More valuable and ghost longer-term
The resource heart rate hinders me
Recruiting
So I have no connection in China
I don't know who are the reliable
Coworkers or colleagues
To hire Sebastian
Florida
In the beginning which was really hard to like recruit as I gradually to view my network now I think I know more
China
So you eventually could over
Overcome that challenge just by working
Hard at it
But it wasn't easy
It was not easy at first
Year of mocha
I probably interviewed 500 HR
I will go on to the recruiting website as send my resume
And they will ask me to
Come interview for positions and they all say oh actually
Ideas to have this pain points and then start the car
Workstation that way
About creative
Yeah
Call Sol
If you look at
The market in China
Force a sand cloud
How would you
Define
What stage of the market
We're in in China
And you've seen the US
So how do you contrast
U.s. I think in China the South Marcus really early
I mean in China
It's been that way like there software companies
Are there mostly on premise
The sauce babe I think it just started in
I guess
Mm
14 or 15 years so it's Rudy
I think it's rude in you in early
Whenever I go back to the US and also going to introduce me to like those 80s companies who are in the
Similar space to us
And I talked to them I feel like the 80s which stands for applicant tracking system
And that's what we do
I feel like 80s in the u.s. is like a commodity like everybody use it like and they understand the value of
But now in China
How to educate people and even for senior-level
Like when we talked to some CEOs they won't even
I understand the battery behind a soft
And it would take time oh like
You can really increase the efficiency you can really collect all your data and do your business in a more data-driven way
Doesn't the Marcus barrier
What kind of challenges
Has that presented given
Flea market
You're in an early Market
You can't just rely on the fact that
Your customers going to
What you doing
Budget Suites
You sell how you deal with that
Esl couple challenges I think it goes three ways
The first challenge would be
IRacing forum
Most of the Masters in China they have never have sex
Embossing Enterprise
Companies
So most of them don't see Darkseid or they don't think it's a big opportunity
No reason found
It's challenging in Enterprise space ordinance a space
Plus number one
Who is recruiting Talent
Because there's no successful SAS business in China
Like in the US you can say all of their Salesforce there
Workday
In China there's no search
Big companies
Intolerance will not come to us
Brother they will go through like
Alibaba or they will go to like tencent weibo a WeChat whatever
So the Second Challenge will be Talent
I guess La so you will be acquiring customer
It takes time to meditate
And also the willingness to
Pay for them is relatively low but I mean
In the market and we see it
Growing tremendous
So those are the three
So who was your first customer
And how did you find them and convince
So there's a really cool story about this
I was not even ready to launch the Porter Airline Commercial Way
So it was April 2000
I got a call from a recruiter
Who was saying okay try the portal gun for like a week
By and later on I was like we were in beta
How did you discover us
It was actually
We were posting a recruiting post
Politechnika
Discussion board
How to recruit people on that technique award
PCO according to the description of the company this is something you should do that I want you
So he called me up and then like you ask me
Porta introduction like PPT warlike stuff
Nothing like I have no life introduction stuff and then I made that were nine and send to him
And then after mom's with clothes deal that's our first customer
That's awesome and also probably gave you an indication like
Okay there's a mark
Yes def
Tara Strong
Okay now you mention one of your big challenges
Recruiting a team
Yeah
But you're over a hundred people today
Yasso
When we invested you were 20 or 30 people you've grown by over a hundred head since
If we invested
Do you eventually overcome that issue
Have you done that
And what are some of the tactics you've used
To get the best people
When you're competing with the likes of
Ali Baba & Company
Still Remains challenging but I think
Some techniques
That I can share
I guess one thing is ask for reference
So I guess you read this
Color blocking
Some Like Us block or like maybe quora
So you ask someone you think it's very smart
Ask
Who would be the person who
Kiwi refer
And then talk to that person
And then ask for another referral
And that person will probably be pretty good
So I used that technique
All the time through my network
And also I guess one thing is to just be very prejudiced
Youjizz
Option 1
Find a talent that's really good you just
Stay in touch and always try
He will feel oh you are very sincere about it and also you are very persistent about
So over the time as the common growing in a positive way
He will eventually even though it in the early days it
It's really risky and later on you'll see the program
Okay sounds like for you recruiting has been very person
Yeah you are out there you're
Yourself
Hand to hand combat training
Candidates
How about this time hundred and thirty people 150
AP poll
You know our experiences
It gets harder for
Baidu CEO
Or founder
In this case
To be centrally involved
Every new
I'm coming in so
How you going to scale that
That's a very good question
Two ways to solve that orlick not like
Entirety but like to help
The situation the first one I guess is
You have to have a rude astrology chart
It's really important to have recruiters who are dedicated on
Recruiting
Especially when you're growing your booty
So we have this mistake
Earlier this year in the first
Half of this year
We had only one recruiters
And we didn't know how
Heart it will be like a recruiter
Shooting
We saw one person will be nice
Banal like we realized that's not the case and we not have like four weeks
Liquid Rainbow the team and now it's really helping us
To move the funnel and like move the needle
The first answer will be having a really strong HR team and recruiting team
I guess the second part is
Culturally by example
I would go out of my way to hire mydirect
And very persistent
Shows a good example to the other hiring managers they will go out of their way to her there.
A lasting having that sort of Paddy and culture in The Colony
The Harry is not only the recruiters
Problems but also the hiring manager
Job is Rudy critical
And I'm guessing you use your own product as well right
That must help totally I think it helped a lot and I chew we were successful to
ReDiscover some of the calendar we interviewed earlier
Have them onboard
Because when we were only like about like 30 people people are like scared of drawing
Early startup
But we still keep their record in the system and we have all the
Interview comments
Some recruiter join us they would look into our system see all earlier
Why don't we
Team against
And we actually close to
The talents
Do you hire a lot of Chinese overseas
Attorneys or do you prefer more Loco
We actually don't have
Too many overseer attorneys
We do we have a preference we only look at the skill sets
But I guess I'm the manager level I personally I guess
Referral to have like Little Tokyo
Because we have
Easier for them to recruit their team
Rather than like us we have
Do the not working
All over again
No eyes you're even going out your
You team have you hired some
Senior level folks
Stoli
What's the market like in
In China for
Super senior
Talent in art
Using the same techniques to find those p
People as well or do you have to
Do certain
What kind of executive searches
Or or this kind
Define the right
I think the techniques
Are the same but I guess one singing I guess I noticed it's different from the u.s. to Telemark the senior Italian Market
It is
In the US as a senior talent to care about Act
Understand
Don't understand that much
And I think the reason behind it was
Because not many people have made money
Equity
They were mostly just earning cash
Sew in
Chinatown Market
Senior leaders
I think have a
Relatively
Before understanding
Alexia
Actually like last night I was trying to escape
Play my offer to a senior leadership like technical it leadership role
I am Beijing even though
He has been working for I think more than 10 years
And he still cannot really understand how I actually works how fast can work
Well
And it's a technical leader yeah I think that's
Actually there's some similarities
He's with us equities
Is a difficult concept
To convey value
Chicken day
Engineering
Yeah but there is
There's more of a culture of people knowing that you can make a lot of money if your company does well in your neck
So
That piece
Yeah in China
So as you
Think about your own
Life
So far
We talked a little
What about the fact that
You were in the US
Came back to China do you think that's making you a better leader
And
If you had to do it all over again with
Make the same decisions or
Try something different
To the first question I sing you didn't make me a better leader in a lot of ways and I'll come back to that later
August 2nd car show make a different Choice that's hard to say maybe I will stay a little bit of
Do just what I'll have more I guess more management skills
STI guest Coral growing bigger and have gas more experience my help
Real life looking backwards but it's hard to say whether I will make the same decision
I guess
To the first question like Hall
Does my experience in the USA, Education sort of made me a better leader
I guess in the US
People value innovation lot
And people trying to sing about long-term how do we create value
Yeah
So have you had turnover in your company or have most of
Date who you want
We did have some time
So why do you think that's happening in China One thing I
Observe is that
The war for talent
As severe as it is in the US Maybe
Even more
And so you do CP
People picking up and leaving
Is the fomo thing by
I'm trying to find the next great
How do you put
Prevent your
Employee based from thinking about their next job and focusing on what they need
Help help mocha
Yeah that's a really tough question and I think probably a lot of Founders have that same challenges
Couple techniques
That I think it's important first
Higher leaders that's really charming and that they know how to lead the team they can leave
Have the folks under them
Watching
Car the same time but also feeling like they are learning new stuff
Leaders who are softball about like training people making people grow
Bus number 1
Have like really good managers
And I guess the number 2
Thing to do is
You have to swap a swirl mark
Surprise to them
We have seen that presents growing and he's making contributions
I'll make sure she's also compensated
So
Those are probably the only two things that sink
To help the sea
How about culture
You guys intentionally build your culture at MOCA and if so like
What is youku
Important
I think that is to
Attracting great talent
Retaining that I think that that's a really important
We really care about culture in the
Very early days
Me and my co-founder we would
Right on like what's a cock
Overtime will actually come back to
I see how is that still write how sure that we want
Animoca we have six
Es6 items
First its ownership
Second act
Sword will be be open sync different
And customer-centric and lastly will be tended as
Is critical to maintain people in the company
Wechat
Who likes rock
Would you buy with buy with real hands
And I feel like
The younger generation of Chinese Talent they would enjoy that lie because our company's really transparent
And they don't find that somewhere else
So that definitely helps us to retain Talent
Because our, states very transparent people get loud soldiers
They feel safe they know like what's going on they know how much money are left in Bank
They know what the revenue is growing really fast so that's
I think that's a
Nike outlet does that make it unique in China to have
All hands
Frequently and
A lot of transparent
Ncn
In theory it sounds good but have you ended up having some unintended consequences
Stop being so.
Transparent open
Do people leave cuz they get scared cuz they have too much info
Some people got scared first but then they got used to
That's something that I found very fascinating is
The power of coffee
So I have a du-rag
Poor who is Boris m1978 Associates
40 years old still a lot of habits are really stubborn
She is not that open mind
After joining the company for half a year
She started real life
She is changing online
To ask me alright like it's been like
A year in motor and I am like so I lost
I feel like I'm changed but I don't know why there is positive or negative
Because you're becoming more old
You talk with your husband more over a you talk with your colleagues moreover
You just become more happier than your last job
Because in her last job
People are not supposed to say things Pub
They're supposed to say goose in him publicly but not basking
And so
Chuhai some of negative emotions which makes
For supper I say
So I felt like the power of culture is really strong
You're actually part of the
Post 90
Generation of Founders are those born after 1990 so I wonder how do you manage people who are older the
That's a good question I think one thing I learned there's some principles in management that I enjoyed
A summarizing time to
One principal I really like is
There's only one way to lead is lead by example
So I act the way that I want my leaders to
So I would like use the same standard to them as well
Legis another thing to manage them or like so I'll leave them as
Personal caring
I do like wow wow a lot
I think some Chinese companies that don't do what I want
But I feel like one was really personal time that you can show you care that person Alot Like personally or their fan
Xiaomi
Heard lights
Career growth and stuff
So those are some techniques
That sounds great
Yeah
Okay so I get to see you in the US pretty frequently you definitely come to the US quite a bit and I can see your network
Working skills at work
You do a good job of
Building out you know kind of a
Broad
Cast a wide net
Have people that you've gotten to
Danelle
Who are in one way or another helpful
Why have you done that
Why you spend time in the US what do you get out of that and
Is it something you recommend other
Other founders
Here in China
I totally would recommend I think it's actually in sauce
The business librarian we're just like years behind the US March
So those Founders were senior leaders who in the SAS business in the US they have seen
All over they know where the pitfalls they know where they should emphasize where they should spend their money where
You should focus
So like talking was them really helps me like a voice on pfos
So I definitely recommend
Anakin like maybe gave one
Concrete example
It's like recently we were thinking about life food in pasta
And the Sioux talking with senior leaders are like service like platform-as-a-service
Service because they tore down the row like when we serve Enterprise they will have customisation
So when cop with senior leaders at workday servicenow SLC
Do you understand how they do their pasta
And that would help us
Astro Boy sound
Define the people are generally pretty open when you
I think so I think so
So when you first started the company did you model yourself after any American company or it was a
More of an idea that came
Do you
I think it's a deer came to me like a mansion like how that you came I didn't really play it but like after that
I'll be okay my daddy look into the US market to co house market in the US
Is it like a viable
So I did, he's like Greenhouse lever who are really hot compress back there like 2015 when I started more
So those are so I'll be coming that way we're very similar
So thinking a little bit about mocha longer
Termite you guys are growing
Super fast
Which were really happy about is a shareholder
How do you keep that going
And
What were some of the
Concerns you have the
Keep you up at night
That really fast
Yeah I think how do I keep
Fast rolls I think it's Italian
I think Thailand's really really important
I think we do have a good strategy going up to the market
Because the Chinese market
Has a huge demand for
HR software
But the thing is peutinger HR software is not easy job
Biggest challenge or what keeps me up
Tinnitus
The palace
How do you spell icing like
62/70 time recording my life senior leaders
So that will be
MocoSpace
Challenge am I
And you know it as you think forward right if
If you're able to continue to grow effective
What is success
How will you know when you can tell I've done what I wanted to do
Yeah I guess
The division of the companies to empower companies
Through a chart
Doggy and we are going to roll out more and more offerings
After recording we're going to probably do onboarding
Organization management
And the payroll and all that
Performance and stuff
So similar to like work days off
Midterm Milestone will be like Sorel 4-year will heat a scale that we are able to IPO in the US
Blessing for years
I guess that's just a small step
Are you for years and later on we're just going to continue to growing
Add more product offerings
To the
Teleport
Have you guys added new products yet
I'm your man 80s
Strikeline so we haven't added like
Holding you like suit yet but we did a delay I like Fisher Witchwood priest robot
Black pretty big
Honda Talon release
So how hard is it
How to add a new product
I think it's pretty hard especially icing in China
Cuz I think.
One thing that's different from the US and China is
In China will you have really
Have no good life chords
Enterprise portal
In China because there's no successful
Products like Enterprise
A porta
So it's really hard to get talents we have to train our talent
We will have to tell them how do you think long-term
How do you say no to customization needs
Right yeah
Adidas the challenge
Unlike video enterprise software
Have you thought about trying to
Bringing
Being a product managers who have
Experience in the US Navy
Armoire
Used to that kind of environment
Or
I don't know how you yourself may be trying to
Get some more
Connections to
2 product
Really smart product
People in the US
Yeah definitely I think that would definitely help end
That sucks you want the reason why all that was in the US 2 months ago was trying to recruit
Technical leaders
I think that would help. It just
It's really hard to recruit people
From the US
Because normally those senior leaders they will have already have families
Yeah and it's really hard for them to move back to China now when they are
Translate stable
Situation
It will be helpful and we will look forward to have some like
Senior leadership
Or like maybe just Junior people
From the US to join
Import I in engineering
When and how will you go global
That's a tough question we've been thinking about it we sing the US Marcus very interested
But I think our products do not at the stage of maturity
I still like it raining very fast
So maybe
325 years
Hey sweetheart
The loud house
Sales team marketing team will be
Big Challenge
I have to
I guess how the China Market thong first and then maybe singing bother you
Global
Okay so for now it's focus on the China Market in China
Yes
Okay I need that.
That makes a lot of sense
It's hard enough for companies
Mature markets
And you're really in a
In a market that
Sounds like you have a lot of work
Keep growing it
The good news is
So yuan
Can get very big
Just focusing
China Inn
Expanded
New products that
Give you the opportunity
He really likes me
Quite a bit,
Yeah so you guys
That the metrics
Companies use in the US
Serta mattresses
Both internally and
And for like the financial Market
Investors
Pretty well-known
And you guys have adopted a lot of
Do you think that that makes you unique in China
Or you know decent Chinese company
Caught on
To what USS markets
Metrics
I think it does make me sort of unique I think.
Also one thing that GV definitely helped us a lot
I don't think a lot of Founders in the China Market that they understand how those metrics
So I think ggv
Having the global view Daphne helped us
To know what measure like for example NPS
Example IKR for example like retention Church LTV CAC
All of those things a measure
Yeah we do they like rigorously
Soulfly
We are quite unique to the investors in China they rarely see this
Kind of like
Very detailed very rigorous mattress
So you're teaching them versus the Missouri River
Okay
Ryan has been awesome we're at the stage of the the episode we're going to go to the hots
Tsar and I are going to fire
Questions that you just say the first
Comes to mind
Okay first one
Tell us about an entrepreneur or a founder
You have respect
I think Bill Gates
He gave me the inspiration for entrepreneurship by saying
Okay great
What's a buck or another
Piece of content that you in
Enjoy reading that you recommend
Two other found
I think high output management
IND group
Oh yeah that's
The great one
That's a great one oldie but a goodie okay for those listeners who may be coming to China someday what's
What's a good place you recommend
Come visit
Apart from the mocha headquarters
Will be a recommendation
I think the Forbidden City
I think that's very cool place to visit
Okay so in Beijing
Okay
What types of roles are you hiring for a mocha and how can people reach out if they're in
Oh thanks
On the port side supported managers
And also engineers
And also designers
And if they're interested they can just reach us at hello & mocha hr.com
Awesome and if you
You apply to that you're going to be in the mocha 80s
Yes
Okay well
Ryan thank you so much for spending time with us on found a real talk this a great episode and I really
Great wafer listeners
The China Market
Thank you
Airline flight 879 89.5
I-96
Ggv capital is a multi-stage venture capital firm based in Silicon Valley
Shanghai and Beijing with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past 18 years from seed
QP IPO
With 6.2 billion dollars in capital under management across 13 funds ggv invests in concert
Zoomer new retail social internet Enterprise cloud and Frontier Tech
GTB has invested over 290 companies with more than 45 companies valued at over a billion dollar
Pergola companies include Airbnb Alibaba C trip Didi chuxing
Domo hashicorp hellobike cows keep splat
Square
Hotel wish soundtrue white white and others find out more at Gigi bc.com
We also highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat group a slack Channel
Where we regular share insights events and job opportunities related to attack and try to join this group
Bridgesat 96.3 gbc.com community
If you have any feedback on this podcast
Or would like to recommend a gas please email us at 996 at gbc.com