Airport
Hi there
Welcome to the 96 podcast
Brought to you by Gigi capital on the show when tipping movers and shakers of China's tech industry
I just got home Founders from around the world can draw lessons
From China Tech ecosystem
My name is Khan song
I'm a managing partner at ggv capital
And I've been working at and investing in startups
Across the US
China and other emerging markets for the last 20 years
My name is Rita young I'm the marketing manager at ggv Capital
Why does show cut 96
96 is the worst schedule many Chinese Founders organically adopted
What is 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
To us996 captures the intensity
Drive and speed of being an entrepreneur in fast-growing Market
From Beijing to Bangalore Jakarta to New York
I highly recommend you joining our WeChat group and slack Channel where you can connect with like-minded people
We organize regular offline events across the world for all listeners you can join this by visiting 9/9
Six. Ggvc. Com
On the show today we have Renee Wang
I want to show you in Chinese
She's the founder and CEO of castbox
And a self
Top program
Castbox is a global podcast platform that is often referred to as the neck
Netflix for podcasting
Uses natural language processing and machine-learning to power unique features
Bike personalized recommendations
Annie audiosurf
Search according to a report from sensor Tower in April 2019
Castbox is now the biggest third-party pure-play pot
Cast app
Before launching castbox
Renee work for Google in China
Time in Ireland
She holds a bachelor's degree in peking university
Musicology
In Mathematica
Statistics
Wharton College
She taught herself
Coding and became one of the earliest Android developers in China
Welcome to the show today
Thank you
First of all can you tell us
The story be
Behind your English name Renee we heard it had something to do with Google
As of or beginning of an applicant Lounge
You know teach myself how to code I mean Google was my dream of company from Oliver
I want to apply Google
I think I found your skull when I just graduated from University with psychology degree I did not have to match
Internet outages in my background in my resume
But I try my best to apply
No to work there at Google
I prepare a bottle
8 math
Item as I continue to apply for Google
I need to come at that time Google has a rule that if you apply for one job reviews you cannot apply again
The six months because they feel that you cannot eat food that market do you have a year
Adult
Apply for engineer team the URI team
Photoshop visit Cody team
It was really fun at that time I quit out drama already and Ice Cube
He's my friend
Computer science major
And everyday I was behind all the in the beauty and because all the computer science students that interests you know
Expanding Google and ask them to do the referral only by referral because
I don't want to go to only one China
So can I change my English name and a changing my email
I'm changing my phone number for diva
Because a hold you do not know that I'm applying for Google
Finally I got opportunity
It was not so it was kind of like Addison's has kind of like an event alone
I was
Using my my friends
McMaster email
To apply and try to join this event
Event
There was like a so you don't know what's on 7th floor and you answer
Activator
From the first book I continue to see see who is most kind of kind of people I try to be
And ask her whether you know that I need your history
Vegeta
You know how to draw
So finally you know
After I jump outside
Do Dynamite are trying to find a common defense
Between me and has a capital I didn't know that got you know I got time
Psych, France
App I'd ask how you know
Adjust the Oscar by Zone automated have some conference
How to go to the theater.
I called my friend out you have to apply again
How to apply to Google
Amazon.com people deliver my resume to that team
Doing the Addisons in unlike offline you answer so he said okay
You can get an interview
I think I can I think I kind of like I have
16 positive feedback
Auto technical
But I thought final interview they feel like cuz I had time to Junior because that applies kind of little
Internet
Background is not strong
So I got another fail
I feel like always likes end of the world
The team that he understands team Dakota me diselo you know don't know you apply previously today is is kind of
I need a more senior people
Cadillac open
Do you want to apply again
I don't have cost an adjuster I thought I already got an offer from Oracle already
You know almost on the training process
Quit my job
Opportunity
Already got Google
What's ninjas use for that
You guys are rock heard of that.
Even though we got your another option is I don't know Ki I don't care so that's why I quit am I previously
No training process Anderson Anderson prepare for the older
You know what I say is older you know
Kind of like records lighter
Anderson Find an app to another two weeks I finally got to offer
The reason are you doing my name is Renee because
A detacher regiment I deliver to Addison's team are using Renee
Google process
August 10th
So that's why
Oh my Fresno does history because
At that time I try to upload all kind of like her in all my relationship going to try to you know cat
I need a tire shop 2018 Google
So that's why I quit my Google about four years ago then
I said I want to do my own startop they feel that I'm insane
Yeah that's what is the Greeley
Apply for Google what's the most difficult part for me is not only that you know
Is Batman English
So that's why then I apply Google I spent before
The application ice
I can spell zero English
So that's why I that time I I bought a book of a kind of interview
He's already angry man review
Riff repeater
Every single word
And also I use like I said I think I worked on my experience in Chinese
The A4 paper
17 pages in all
A back in the fall
I asked my friend in in the US
So then I interviewed Google besides the 17 pages
On the back of book
I can spell
0 English
It's true that song
Addison's interview you know
The people who interviewed me is that all he says I owe you a grid
Feo in English
Anime
You know you do know my dear
Monster Mash movie
That's why that's why I forever
It's not my meat
To change the ride to my house so I can ask my friend to change it right away
And also a bat 17 pages
I would have allowed to change a little bit
You know I try to remember you know it. The top 10 values of Google
The definition of the Google AdSense about page
I know that
So obvious
You have always had the
Mentality
In fact
When you started kienbock's you sold your house in Beijing
I'm just a little bit curious
Is that a difficult decision for you at all where does your conviction
Come from
Yeah
So I just feel like first the High Castle house
About life
Android sings 2008
At that time people was at Odell was about
Turn salt and ice on iWatch at that time they're only like about a like a
There's only two
20000 apps
Is that all you sure that you know
Android auto
So that's why I began to learn coding and the Cincinnati Bengals apps on a lot of games
And I just feel like home
The guest some apps I give up a really complicated I feel like people may like it
But as a result of people you know care about is that I said I feel
Maybe
A popular spot if there are some stupid ass
Evil eye when I called I never do the test because I have
Twisted
Kuwait
That's why I've recorded phone bomb that people do not inject the screen and it's an older fruit
If they are similar to each other
It kind of like
Jackie speier
That's stupid I've got
Pulse rate
Highlands
Ocelot
On Google Play after 2 weeks
Google Play
So we got a lot of light
Comdata app
You built that after yourself
So it's not
It's really silly app
I do not
And the people you know
Gossip cop straight download
And I thought how to upload
Show up on the top apps on top of you apps
So that's why we continually I Can Henry upgrade you know
Lake Spaulding Twitter users
So that's why. Promotions free advertisement is real money
Carlito money from this part
Buy YouTube channel
You cannot find that anymore because at that time
I feel like there's a lot engineer's asking
Questions almost like overflow
Ask him. How to use in Android auto how to use them
Android Studio
How to integrate a democracy
Decay under the question is
Rio very kind of like not that come
Not that you know really good answer
So that's why I stood out the top questions on stackoverflow talking asking about Android because it is my only
Ability
So I turned to a YouTube
Amazon phytolacca
Copy paste if accident
Stack Overflow cache
And also the most important thing I know he's at 10
Song on YouTube
A lot of people are searching Asian girls
Yeah but still that's why I
I change your mind
Name of my YouTube channel like
Beijing sanlitun teacher
Show me a real picture
No you cannot find that I know because I got down by Google
But I got a lot of traffic on the people
Minnie Mouse with learning how to code Android
Maybe it's
Video from YouTube
I'm using the money card from the Spotify.
I put money from the
Privet savings when I walk for Google
As I bought a house before I
I go to the tablet
Panda
Send from Debian I move to Japan
As in Japan that I have the idea about quitting my job I so I should
You know I said that like her
But I don't have my iPad screen no
Because I already been out of China for
So I obviously has no connection
But I really want to do this. Have soy
I don't make a really quick decision about a minute
Zillow house for sale with a house that's why I find it
Previous like agency
You have me to buy the house
Where to sell the house
Yeah it's a quick decision
But I got the money later
Colby College dance alone
Follow the process
I just feel like you know I feel the startup
I guess you'll find a place to sleep
I guess you'll go back to my friend
Her apartment
That again
How did you decide that you want to do a
Podcast
I do BBQ near the first type I'm doing is a yuca
And also I products
All I kind of like her
Horoscope app
Adebayor Picayune item Allapattah lysine cream cheese
Yo2 am I retire
And
As a full-time Utah
Anemia
France 2 Park Ave
Awesome es6
Because all of them fail
But I continued
Obviously you can see that more than 20 different account
The only ideas I may be the hypest
But I try to find it
I go to the guitar
To find it the open-source
Make sure that has Oma peas
Yunnan
Earthquake
As possible
So I kind of already has an idea or so the final decision is out of before
At the end of 2015 I met a friend who used to work for Google working for Google
And he said that
Otis podcast app
Internal you met Howard really high
High back big bag
Because
ITunes has their own party
Tina Hawaii and
And that
That guy he who work for Google Play he said that
I household a lot of my
To try this direction
Spider-Man awesome
Alrighty
Take it down I told him maybe I can do it
So that's why I take his advice on the end of
The 2015
Wechat December
December 31st
EPPICard
Anderson Eye
January 5th
First second and third
I made it happen
The false
So how they make it happen.
For that go to github
Can you open Southside commercial
In off randomly
Can open Solace I find a
Podcast which is MIT license
Wake me up at is commercial friend
Commercial family
What weight did you answer
The first 3 days
I change three things
Because
Zacalife what / kind of like
Rudy Rudy light
So all his ranking is
Kind of like Linux
Attack talk about a bottle
The Pact
So I change the ranking
From disconnecting to tour again
Two kind of like a mole packet emoji
Json tutorial
The second Divine I remember to the Daily or something like that
This is my thing I change changing the run to you
II see I'm changing
Baidu multi languages
That's about the only English so I make about a 70 language.
I-70
How to do the cat eye station
And the second thing I'm making
The serfsons I'm making is making the UI beautiful
Like a chance of persuading Syed
The staff and some put it on Google Play
Under the first Russian
Cheapest iPhones at all people spend half an hour
You know
If you already find it I have to spend half an hour a day to listen to hours
Amazon author okay this is maybe something we can take risk
That's why I spend all the money
At that time
Set the money I called from my house
Sell my house
Anatole began promotion
I know she said all people will spend her
Half an hour
So that's what I do in the first of a month without a $1000000
The first Batman
Yeah because
If I spend all day
Change
Yeah yeah yeah
So the friend who give you that idea
Who started Google
Yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah you ever considered joining you
No no he's a happy day
Nike basketball
What ideas
Even though I know it's a lot of other podcasts at
What we are trying to defend at least for the first year is that was really fight who won
As far as we can
I think I remember the first two by year
Aequitas app
About three times a week
Re worship
At that time but you don't know how I need prti
I need this kind of like
Document
They only have a full page
So every morning
We talked about all this is like
The things we want to do
Anthony Beretta
IPad pencil Amazon
Why is Bill Pay
Back in the fall
Amazon
Today
He didn't finish can you not sleep
So that's why I remember that
I think I got time for
That's why because it's the First Merchants party is not that functional
I know the function is not without his wig
So I guess we'll catch
An older
A competitor
Police
How to see what they are doing
What this is what we are going to do
Reasons by Meek
Adam a capillary by me
A house with a minimum
COC
A tiny house on August 3rd
Hockey
Moderator
The new version
The very first the one year we only tried
And
If there's something already proven to
Bowser
They try to make sure we have the
At least you call fake
Function the first one year and the big guy was a high
And we got lots of latitude twice because we had the most.
Uno extreme examples of 1 people
Tri Supply antifreeze Russian girl faceplant
She said I'm using your iPod and you do not have the voice over
An older pictures
I cannot know what
What are talking about
So they received 45
Avicii One Day
The whole team you know
Why does a lady boss
All the single picture
Another version
Jonathan gave to her and she's so happy
So I have puppies
Oh her and all the other kind of like
Planned community
She has a
Still on
Five Below her community
And that's another you know
Apus address
That was why you ask
You hurmonium
Videos
Using a laxative
A fetus at all
Alexa
Spotted air
Is a kind of like a fish I think it's really important about you didn't you guys didn't have the
I'm not be received at
Feedback it was a unit already in in China
Is that all this is really important is finishing
Engineer team didn't leave home until way
An upgraded version on Google Play
Kwik Kar Yukon
After
A few hours
In the use of Union
Luxuries back from
Wax off
Is how I'm sorry
I changed her comments
All previous comments
Okay, said
I'm sorry
I didn't notice
Did you have the fish
I recall my
You never know that
Best food Sofia the first one year
Recycle for 5 years
Ola competitors
Has-beens with industry
Is 12
At least 10 years
Like a pocket
Cast
Spectrum
Very much
But I mean after 1 year for functionality biofoam the total downloads
The foodery
Google Play
Number one
After why you so
I know you'll see all officers party and all that kind of a Pioneer Center Tower
Ranking from the downloads
Can you use
MLB store
Number one
All the time
Randy Wise
We had kind of a seal.
Randy Orton
At least on your nostril
Volume intent 10 years to build the brand
Use a ride
You know
Try to be more competitive
But this was the first year
By the second a year
It was
Hadoop
We how to be innovative
Agape love you on your own now
So I think
So that's why I think
Folsom user protect you against
Slow sings II a year
That's why we try to be innovative
Users give you new cards and you feedback new ideas
So meet me how to community
I'll buy is called the Casbah San best hurt
Catspause users
Thank you I saw a lot of like feedback and the reply to
To find all this feedback
Weather or whether or not
Stop with the second year we try to be innovative
She would try to be more creative
And the spokes on hallway
Yucaipa Community audio search
Comments
Pakistan mode
And also we tried all we have laptops
And we have a lot of like
Adding timestamps
The forever single like a
Audio clip
And also with you
I just told a lie about recommendation
Yunnan
I mean some of them about recommendation
We spend a lot of
Anatolian the recommendation play sounds on episode
We talked about this
The topic
They try to find her sanitizer
Talking about the same thing
But they tell why it is not that good
Try to adopt
Idea on the price of newest
And also for monetization by the way
Premium content
All the staff
TitleMax
You'll have to apologize for money
And if it works
Mimic Italiano
Cantina needs who info
So Tech vitamins a pastor
That's a reason for yes
Oh wait
What are we trying to do is try to learn
Weather Odessa
I need things
That we can be different
We can be more
You know crazy about this
So
At the most
It's called Lockhart
Is a kind of like allowing tok
Laugh video
But compared with traditional radio people you know can't do the real
You have to call you in
People can leave you a message
Even sending virtual gift
This is a
This is listening
Adverb pequeno
You know how is really high expectations because at my house so many failures
Discus statue
Out of all you know
Expectation
If you stay inside of the app
Why people say oh this is a real thing real
People's comment.
Conditionally format
You can't compete Abby's Netflix Vizio 3 years
Real socialist
And also began people began to follow
People began to in
How much does speaker box like a sweet Samantha
I talked
About us idea
You move so fast
Yeah that's
Github idea moved immediately
If you say that everyday we have total Disney worship
Books on how to recently Waterway gastrolounge telephone that's how Russian
Make a dove the audio clip
It was a long cloud
A recording of the old didn't have at that time
Like a underfolder that's how was your day they can send easily said other men or satellite
Block block users
Is it kind of like a battle control and also we already has a lot of weakness
Nicknames if you came to Love cast
Xmas like a RV
Yeah already
Agway to come soon
Anivia preparing tool
To making him MBA
And also
This is like
Something with v
You know a lot of
Episode
Anna see a lot of people
Began to know
Creator
Is kind of like a make her lower you know
Threshold for people to quit accountant
What is that
That's really funny
So because of that
The funny part is that
You know we have a team member called tina
I never said that
You know make me go back to office from GTV
Angelina said oh I really like this feature because
It makes me want to do that
Find an adapter
So many traffic
I'm sorry
Because you know you know where she is already so you never know
So that's the vibe
I I continue on YouTube
To to try to
You know empower the team I'm always very you know
Your Enthusiasm
Isn't very present
But there was a new feature
How to find
Descendants
Future like the common thing the Premiership
Banana chips
Play
Animated it was. Have so it was
Really hot and every time when you know that go home and said
I should tell the team tomorrow
What is it was really hard for
Lacrosse in Ocala
College football team members in China
Apache members
Disconnect youvisit engineer team
Little Lonnie so that's why I have to use
Athlean power using kind of like
Future story
Pictures of Toffee
I mean talking about the the futurist that it's like
I can totally understand how are you acting feels frustrated very well
Because
Generation 4
Virginia
I never work a few phones in the US before I used to as much as I used to work for that me and put your pants
Even today my English is not good
The first time
Before I never officially came to the us before
Official my first time I go to the US
So the first
Team members
Photo US Bank
Zodiac kind of like him
Is it was a terrible
A lot of drama
On the final
It's not their fault
Is my phone I don't know how
Find the real the real user I really appreciate it as a friend
Team member food still there
If I continue to show her the great news
Walmart.com
A lot of America East Connection music
China and the us but
And I know this is for the first group of people
What is a tomcat
Kind of like a lot of like her
What was an example of
Traumatic
Odesza like her
The biggest fight
That was a really big
Is that
Yunnan in China
Because we are like
Kind of like
Disconnect
People
Kind of like
Like operation
OTR
Like her decision make that right
Cut on the center.
The market
But there was a lot of like you know
Disagreement
Decision
Volume in China because wave
We believe in that a tasselled we do spend a lot of money on musically
Because it's almost like it's alright the highest
Yeah from.
If we calculated retention and the calculator
I used already
What is the u.s. people feel like Odysseus like
People you ask people they feel like
Organica growth
Is the most important the mattress that they belong to
Purchase
So that's why I didn't want to pursue
So that's why
Inside out
YouTube you guys
Not spending any acquisition money
You should spend all the money I'm paying for the
Craters to the Chateau
50 prefer kind of like
This kind of
Organica
Girls from the word for mouse
From the brand awareness
Weather forecast
It's really hard to marry
Saudi
Even supposed to use acquisition project a lot of
So you ask people sad Fieldhouse
YouTube on the Google Facebook
What's feel like still pain in my knee
Mine all the celebrities older influencer
By the Chinese people feel like
Why
Might because that's your friend is really hard to park
Especially for this kind of audio
Compton Demetrius
That is not that big
So they kind of vodka has a lot of Mythology wife
A lot of light
What's that Style by
Bright
But you still have a really professional guy and he's really nice he's very
Very smart
For the first one because
He came for the office
Sucky spend about
Sephiroth talk to him is always shy why
His phone bill to be paid by the company
United Chinese
Stop spending
Time
Is cashing why don't notice the company still pay the phone bill
But this is very crucial
The first day talking about if I don't know the bases belong to
So he's kind of like a
Tiny tube
Ejaculating High why not respond
Every single mini yes or no
Feel feel this is like this is the Ruth we should have talked about that first iPhone
Anastasia from the walk
Stout
Alder sale from the community
Because lack of communication why
Communication device you know
Time I come down more shy
Augusta
Pick 3 lottery results
Too much communication
Discussion
Stop before I did
Anything you know
Time talking into talking
So that's why I thought you got to remember feel like oh my God
You know Chinese engineer not never talk
I didn't even know this
Basting
This thing changed
Chinese why you still talking
I can understand both
Yeah I told him
Like really hard
You know it
No title
Like balance
Like they are
You know they are
Dumbass I don't try to balance you know
Tool to fix the conflict
Nowadays I mean we still in Old Faithful
You know try to make sure that
They are kind of communicating
Other very well
Conflict II don't think interview fix
By the end of the day
Now we're trying to collaborate
Both you know the advantage
So that's why
By doing this we try to save cost
By you know
Hi remote engineering operation command button
Adobe try to be more professional
Harry Potter
Yeah so that's why
Nodejs
I feel
Because
State they do not
Copper
Steel I try to relax
Beauteous MP
People in between
You know it would
Piazza braids
Think like but we do respect
Basketball team
So regarding your user
They mostly Bass
In the US or
Where are they
How about users
And another circuit
Asana from some other
In a European country
Gnocchi
And the like
German
And know that your
Usually have Sundays languages
Best English words
You need to become the most popular one
About to 70%
English speaking
Australian Ute UK
Speak English
But you also Chinese version
We took off in China
Say so if I Chinese want to use our app to Hell 2
Alfred Tea House
How to file app about
A phone that has Google Play
I need the Chinese
Chinese Android
I only know because if you eat pizza
Google Play service
Even though detangles
They cannot open
Yeah.
But you could have made a Chinese version and have a mobile on xiaomi Young tencent
Yeah
Speak to each other
That's cool because first they do not have the sap license
Show me how to
You know you belong to
And also second only 70
Key people in the team
Burrito Bandito
How to do a lot of
Flag review
Deleterious
Autoflower organization
Erase money you could do that to you made a decision
Are the young you didn't want to have an app
That's what
Ecosystem
So I want to say that
Audio consumer-facing Pro
China
Demott Mall
Hacking IG and other monster
Compare tool
So if you see like
Reedley. Loss apps
I could be seen like a you are
And kumar yakkala self is rudy guede social
And I'm very popular
Tienda
Domantas a transexual
Heater in China
And if we're talking about a non-social app
Like kind of like a
Humana and
Elytra
Lemon juice
Make him a lot of Prozac
How do you play talking about like
You asked and you kind of like
Even though the app and recently passed
It's kind of like
Audio combined
You know like new phone
Then what is now you know
HyVee corporate
Chinese events
Apps features
To your English
Yeah yeah that's cool so
Bialik has balls now wait long until recently belonged a new app
Beto 2018
It's kind of like Mo socialism generation
And I guess a lot of
Like a diamond
Pure Hockey
Acacia counseling consumer
And this is a type of
Really loud
Ideas forum.
Chinese
On you know
Approach a sound
New user user also give you feedback
That's what's up
The new avocado is like
It's really amazing my only cat
Israeli of pasteurization
Separatist a alarm
Social audio app
Are the beginning of a twin
Whose birthday this year on June 15th
Until today
Does app that much by the baker
Only like $1,000
Radioactive
But even this Sarasota today
AccuWeather
People spend a hand Rose
US dollars per day
US dollar
Verde yeah yeah yeah
Adjust the TPM photo photo
And also
Product
Jumping to the ranking
King cobra
Oldest mythologies already
In China wechat cartoon
Co-writer of The Walking Dead
Chinese food
Steaming only Samurai
Thousand
People spending
You haven't spent money promoting
Knock knock
Somewhere tomorrow
CDLs are found
Castbox
So this is like a so
If it is kind of a
Bastille new album
Violin to buy
UPS Kannapolis
Xi'an China
People bielefield
Seoul
I said march on to
A two weeks
You have not even show you that you are
People feel like
I don't want
Factual question why at me don't want to
Offended the US market
How to the China Market
Pacific sound
On the US market because
Oldest features in order consumer
Fishing products
Does high nice match match more
Did you think that
What people in the USA
Google Google
What's great company and it is
But when you look at
The things you did a Google China versus what was happening at bytedance
What's the difference by UC
In
Speed in
Application of working
Except
Yes
Before I quit
Amazing
And a lot of light
You know
Superstructure
Analogy
You know skills
But after I
Quit Google
Begins with no Mall
You know relationship
Noticed Ensenada
I feel like
Marshmallow
In some
You can watch on her face
Immolation
Social features
That's cool
That's who I so it's like
It's much more advanced compared with them you know you are
Commercial
Effacing
I think like
The from if we talkin about
Bee business
Force USA
LACMA
Consumer-facing is like
Black Rattata
You know all the tencent
Engineer
And approach
Manager
And even operation people
Virus
Especially for operation
If in the US Army talk about operation
People who work in
Amazon no Packaging
Yes. This is operation
Yeah that's one also
Operation
But even China's appreciate
Told her you like her
Elong
Science
That's who I know
Yuan people
Is imposed
Talk about girls hiking
The technology
How to do the
Even the word haiku
Baoding China
For the whole operation.
Really know how to make
Offline
Even online
How to know make more money
How to
How to make a
Put in the game
The game theory
Application
So that's like
So for you how to do operation
News from China
For us users or european user
Yeah this is really quick question
Now what
Uibe
Avocado
Will usually hire people from
NYY
The operation
Mythology
The Harrison
I'm not good with English
Every single operation people
Spaghetti
Them about winter
Which is has really good English
Kind of like almost Nativity
Inference from where
From Lacombe
Stanford or Berkeley California Chinese American
Anderson
It kind of like what kind
The very close
Group
DotA
Example now what
Take a cattle operation for example
WeChat
I want someone more
Panda
He is
Like really know how to make
The audio
Game social
Kind of like fat
Stokke
Get a whole Easter
How
The operation
Masters how we can make
Really funny really you know a lot
Amazon
Jacinto
Translate
But not on Visa language
Translator
You know translator outages
This matter
The field is not
This not work
So this is life
Reusing this franchise age
Go to the Local Host
Today all day
Leslie Howard
So basically in this process
We need to sleep
People know operation
Each other
In China
People know
Local contractors
And the people who
Who can do the real communication is
Bdp
It is a little bit complicated
Dalian China
Welcome to the 303 jobs
Yasso
Can do it
And also
What is the most import
How I think
Competence anole exam local Chinese
Companies
Then I first go to
I feel like
Odessa
Especially Celica
In a lot of Mythology
HDPE
Bi Tumblr
Multiple iPhones learn from UK
Menopause
I'm a pcra
Know yoga know
The contest
Keisha by YC
To sing out
That's a lot of thing I got from you guys
Then I might have some Loco you know Silicon Valley
Carbonara
Make a call people they feel the same
Pictures of Sam
62 Nova
WeChat pay
Only know about me
Did you know the real
What's the real
What's the real methodology and the philosophy behind it
So that's why I feel like a why I think alike
Because oldest
Chinese
Michael intrapreneurs like me or like even peek
When we came for the USB
Because of their
Uneventful
First of all they didn't go to China
They tried to teach
Tattoos
That's why I single
That's why I think that's why a lot of like really
Alarm
Things are happening
Pekin Library
Advantage
That was one of the perverse
Something to say
Hawkeye series
Withdrawal in the first place was on
If something's happening in China
Is knowledge
She's not hot
4shared
On a global basis
Dhoni
Consulting about it
New York
Apollo
Bangalore New Delhi
Bogota
Can all benefit
Yeah yeah that's
The Northside
Yasso 3
How's that going
I hope you say that
At the Barbican Umatilla
You spend too much
Stupid money
It is in the continent
Because
Was not always right
So I have to say that up Quay still continually.
Continue to have orange content
And some of them are going to
Maybe
Portchester
IP will be put
Pizza in OB
Movie
Maybe
Seal in the Arctic
And also we try to
Creating Boomers
Appsodo integrated
But generally speaking I hope.
I hope is that you
I go to that
Again
I do not
I spend too much money
No, he's not right now
That's cool
Salt
The first reason is that
Accountant East Knox
Something that have
Because I was Spanish
Kodak
Don technology
And
That is all I could
Operation
It's not uncommon
Encounter
The second reason is that
Company business is
Hollywood
You can never
Predict
That's what song
It's like her
I mean this is not like
We cannot predict
Previous Aesop some money respond
Spend more money
Smallest
Are the counting numbers
NetSpend
You know last night
So that's why I feel like a
Basic
Too unpredictable Wiki
Business hours
You know I will
The Circle why is that
We are now trying to do
Des Moines Iowa
Especially
Spotify
Google Champions with Ian.
The first original shows
Spotify
Is making to spend 1 million
We can never
No no way
Apple computer
Original content
Mitch Baywatch
A twist
There was only
People continually doing something.
Beyond
Compute the ball be thrown
So that's why
Who's the sink
Trying to make a audio
Choose to
Try to
I'll try to make it
The threshold of creatine count
Being social
That's what's up
Imagine thesaurus and pek
The competitors
Makita learn
Bye
Understand
And the
Suspended can you know it's been too long
A small party
Continually to
Find a song
Continents
Battery Nation
The what's private
Having you what's motivating you
To walk out
Yes for me
Aspire simple I mean
When I was younger my
Biggest private
A white of paleo
When I was younger I'm not sad
Coffee
Trying to say that old
I don't want to say I don't want to make mistakes
Google
Finally got my dream of
Nowadays I'm too
Who sings because I'm on
How to work on myself
I think it's a very positive my side because even I'm mad
Math problems
If you want to meet at all this
Punitive
Is it better to
Annabelle
Buy some
Achievement yunnan
On the product
Seminyak
Family Court
Good results
I will still give our homeboy does Odysseus
Only a very small
Small steps
You know because
If I'm out
I need to poop
Sending you
The higher place
Deepika going to be
Yes
Is Odette in Lawton
This is only
Be a bad heart
Seoul
Best life coach
Back to the topic I think knowledge
The only things that
Continually to
Go to work
Become better
But that's why I
I feel like arguing
The folks
3 and 1/2 years
I feel like
Match match match
Watch better
Semi
Who is Grace Potter
I feel
Google
After first the tweeters
Photo
Pizza same
Yeah Anderson
Everyday
I'm something new
Yeah
Surprise
What's the price
So thank you Renee
Is a fascinating
Conversation
Airline flight 879 89.5
I-96
Ggv capital is a multi-stage venture capital firm based in Silicon Valley Singapore Shanghai
Beijing we have been partnering with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past 18 years
Need to pre IPO with 6.2 billion dollars in capital in our management across starting phone
Gdb invests in consumer and Retail
Social Digital internet Enterprise clouds and Frontier Tech
GTA V has invested in over 2090 companies with more than 45 valued at over a bill
Billion dollars include Airbnb Alibaba by 10 picture
Didi chuxing hashicorp Hollow Pike
House
Keep slack Square
Wish shopping shoe white and others find out more at ggvc. Com
Have any feedback on this podcast
Or would like to recommend a gas please email us at 996 at gbc.com