Hi everyone for those in a Bay Area hunts and I will be hosting a 906 anniversary party on Friday March 8th
San Francisco
The event will take the form of a China Tech trivia night
You get to test your knowledge of China's tech industry by answering trivia questions and teams
The winners will be awarded attractive prizes
Such as a bundle of the books that are past speakers have recommended on a 96 podcast
At the event you also get to meet and hear from some of our jujube fellows on what they learned during their intensive 1 week program
Time in Beijing
This anniversary parties open to all followers of the 96 podcast and friends in the Bay Area who follow Tech in China
The event will be at 7:30 p.m. on Friday March 8th
In Soma San Francisco
The exact location will be included in the confirmation email
You can sign up for the events by following a link in the show notes or visiting 996. Ggvc
SF
It'll be a fun night and I hope to see you there
We'd like to thank our sponsor and partner one piece for their support for this event
Also here's a tip if you want to win at this trivia night I highly recommend we listening to previous episodes of the nine
Es6 podcast
Since many of the answers to the questions can be found in our show
Recent wrestler intervention
986 by there
Welcome to the 96 podcast
Brought to you by Gigi capital on the show went to the movers and shakers
China's tech industry
And discuss how Founders from around the world can draw Dustin's
I'm fine Aztec ecosystem
I'm a managing partner at GTB capital and I've been working at and investing in startups
Across the US
China and other Emerging Markets
The last 20 years my name is Sarah Jeong
I'm a marketing manager at ggv Capital and a former journalist why is this show called 96
96 is the work schedule that many Chinese Founders have organically adopted that is 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6.
Days a week intensity
Speed of Chinese internet companies which have produced many growth Miracles over the last decade
Also I highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat groups in slack Channel
Where you can connect with like-minded people interested in Tech in China we organize regular offline events across the world for a while
Followers you can join these by visiting 96.2 gbc.com
On the show today we have Simon John or John cemo in Chinese
The founder and CEO of growing IO a data analytics startup in China that helps product managers and Market
Analyze mobile apps and websites without adding
Tracking codes
Growing IO now counts over 6000 companies as its customers
Including the likes of DD Walmart tortilla and others
Previously xiamen wasena director business Analytics
At Lincoln
In Silicon Valley headquarters
Before that she worked as a senior manager of Psych
EBay
In 2015 he left a decathlon career in Silicon Valley
Pandas return
China has started his current started growing up
Prior to all this summer work as a brain surgeon in China
Nanjing
He also played in NBA from the Baldwin Wallace College in Ohio
Time is also the author of the Chinese book show season 1
Chief growth officer
And it's a thought leader in the field dinner for the growth
In China
Welcome to the show sign
Thank you for having me here
Handsome
So how did you know Simon for a long time do you remember how you first met
Yes
I think
I met Simon we were still at Lincoln
Or about to
Leave Lincoln
To explore the possibility
Abusing someone in China even though he has been away for so long
He was freaking out
Consumer Cellular
Or something with Enterprise oriented
And the trailer was out in China back then
Customer setup is the only thing that matter in the Internet space
There's no not a lot of proven Enterprise examples that worked out well
Yeah that's his Arabic
He's so he's figuring out should you work with someone who started one
With no other success or
Bet the farm on the Enterprise will be a big train in China
That's exactly right I remember
Lyrics are let you know that I talk with hands
He shared a tiny bit about United China Market on US market doing to be to be in China now
If it's not easy
That's right
You started your career as a brain surgeon at what point did you realize this man up
Be what you want to do for the rest of your life
Send White
When did you find your passion and data
I think this is a almost a two questions
The first one
I started my career in the medical in University
Shandong cancer hospital
I think I dropped her six were nine months you know I figure out that's exactly not her
What have you in my life
And then you know I I totally know the chief of that department
Let me know I need to leave
Because I going to be on talk to her
Actually it's
It's very
I would say
You're serious you know so on
Career
I need to leave that thing out space for someone really loud
But not me just a being okay with
Stop
I know so
Personal day
I strongly believe we know
Anyone
Everyone
I need to enjoy whatever he or she is doing
The dance that we all in or motivating out this person
Becomes a bat
In a few
So I got a moment
Acheulean
Thank you note
I didn't have the passion
I'll be in the pasture Dr arena in the world
So
That's the reason a lot
You know
Opterra
I think roughly speaking a year
Wheeze on anyone's notice
Storm leave
Stay in the apartment for
Tweaks
Mommy
This location
Quiet data
White Acura is linked to a computer
You know it was not about to
It was about about the computer
Why was the very very young you know and that was my toy
I really enjoy it
You know end
Starting from the playing video games
And then starting you know the shift into that computer games
And then ship tattoo
You know internity Navarro early-stage I remember a lot of water with 80s
Enit
Not this modern
How to connect to internet
Lacoste
Very early the most powerful
Nothing ever happens in my life
And I like it
I enjoyed and then I want to know
Who sings in this field
That was a 1990
Aid
NikeiD
Beginning very early
Tipping Point for
Chinese internet
Remember 97
China Hut Destin
A million internet users
Yeah yeah
China and had a picture taken with Jack Ma on the
Great Wall
The very earliest
New China Buffet
Yeah I remember that part
View house before I suppose.
+ 386
44806 Cimino
Computer models
And that was the first computer I had
And you my life
Yeah
And then I
I need to do something in this
And you came to the US in
2000 in
What prompted the
So you know because of that I was very young you know I I like you know American movies
And video games
Nobles books
Cutting a lot of things I finally converted into
Why American
Are such a
Free TV no
Country right now
So many amazing people in
Turquoise so many
Amazing Stories in the movies
Spartak Technologies
I just feel you know this country must have some
Sing significant Depending on time
What a new
I done the moment I want to learn from them
You know and that motivated mean
Tool
Come to us
I think that's the
End
How did you find your way into the field of data analytics
I think the whole world is in a hyper-connected
Behind the scene
So you not because those taking a personal Hobby
Movies in American whatever
And then I had a moment
Give me Commerce right but I filled out this e-commerce is so fascinating you no end
It's kind of interconnected the whole world about using
Internet but also can sell things
I couldn't open my more personal video game stores than was a
Student you know I found out this is the best way I can sell things
I want to do e-commerce
Reason I start
You not doing some research into how to do you convert how to build a website
Ottawa
If you want everything you know together
And I figure out and I learn
And then you know
You seen I shifted my focus from just a computer internet
2 e-commerce but funny conversation need to understand the data in the database
Why don't you know everything
So I learn
And
Yeah and then I start to
Working on this field
And that's how you got in Dublin
Yes because I want to do e-commerce e-commerce eBay and Amazon
Yeah yeah yeah
EBay Worcester
The largest animal
Soenda I
I joined them
Odesza
Why did you join a LinkedIn after that
So and that's alright
What kind of eBay
I really learned a lot
Amazing
Department
They use in they tattoo
Fully operated
Site in order business
You know and then
The manager who recruited me enough for that the eBay position
He told me silence is a Silicon Valley
Writing
I feel you should have.
Are smaller
EBay
Had the employees or something
And
And his name is Paxton
He said he's great guy
And that he told me you Simon that usually go to summer Mall
I didn't understand what he was talking about
I told him
Academy
I was just a look at my promotion
I don't hate
You didn't understand what I mean
You should really go somewhere you're not you're not growing in a smaller
He strongly believe I could do better
Are you not in those smaller
No more do more
And then he recommended me to
A couple places you know
Yeah he's friends
Run
And then I just
I got a couple offers
Which is very small back then
Breakfast Mall
Color keyboard
More than
Yeah definitely something like that
So you are there
For almost 5 years
You let him build the Analytics.
To support their companies monetization
Talk about why analytics was in
Import into LinkedIn and what kind of impact
Did your team have
Is the
I think the great the greatest question
Lincoln really respect the data right
It is part of the
The company strategy
You know or is it
Part of the company culture
I was just joining LinkedIn
I remember
Ross Drive data Data Drive money money by Rick Ross
Clear
And the second piece is you know so I think Lincoln really in power
Employees
How to use the data
He's not that I could do this this
That right
You just say hey we want some driving December result what are you guys can do
And we did a lot of our creative you know and projects
You know a prophecy
Lincoln
But I think that you know six months ago and I read
Hoffman reached out to publish a book
Cut the
Please
Yeah you know that's the case of engine case
Use
What's the project we deliver
I think that's the
Internal cross engine to boost a LinkedIn Revenue growth
That is call that part of the Marlin
Internally
I think it's increase efficiency
See by sweetie
Sometimes
Walter Knoll
I don't know who you are
Daddy
I'm making me upgrade my
Provocation
I'll just stay home because you are working out my family not go to Hawaii
Announce what what exactly have done to
Assigning a used to close one deal for months just to work you guys did
I can close 3DS in a week
The contact
Yeah what's the mom and seen a relay
Make me super super happy
And then the whole team have
I think that's the ultimate
The power to
So what was the exact reason that the conversion
Increase
Is it because of better targeting
Better targeting you know
Batter
Indochino fit
Better messaging
Better positioning
The most part is the
The automation
Writing a salesperson
Lompoc prison while you want to talk about
Seriously speaking you just need to click three buttons
To generate a PowerPoint
Slides
A slice of pecan
Ggv yttv need LinkedIn
Wellington Park fits under
Who can recommend the war
You know that's a
Cole Haans
Pitch deck
P stock
We should really really push the productivity
Toby's repair one
By the way not to be home in three minutes and I'll prepare one
So that I can be
Sunday
I remember in video semino internal
You know they are tracking
We found that there were
500000 PowerPoint stack
Something like that
A year so we could translate into almost 2,000 data analyst work
If we do this manually
And that
And everything's a customized uniform
Or custom
That's just the beginning
But also you know I'll be upstairs working on connected
And then
Fundamentally changed the way
Lincoln Square
And this really really make me
Personal fuel
Providence
Yes I can change
The lights
So you were making a
Quick difference
Insidetheville again
Yet many people
And I
I can relate to this
Cuz I bought them for 798
China.
My neighbor said that there's a ceiling
4 Chinese in
The most most Asian
Employees Indians may be an exception most handsome place
The ceiling
Ben Harper
Two leadership roles at meteor
Hirelevel
So
What kind of examples for lessons
Both positive and negative
While working at Lincoln is one of
A performer
I will start with a positive
I think I will end up with
The positive as well
In a piece of everything is two side of story
But number one is
I think you know the company culture is very important
Better than YouTube recent results and that you're performing
Right
And that leadership team country colonized AR
How many grapes can a peephole
You need to grow them
I think Lincoln
At least what I was there in a WhatsApp
Beijinger
In harmony I give me the opportunity to grow
You know I
I think that's very important for any employee no
Olivia NASA comedy
Panda
Space
Space is not the the free ride in or free vehicle to bring you your not to the next level
I think person speaking now we need to really work hard and that deliver
Better
Apartments
Decide
Feel
The seating seating problem
So I'll try came back in Little China
I understood that this a little bit more than that I was there I was there I talked about all this just a complication you chills
It's just a
In our Chinese a can of Ira Silo that you know not to uniting much
Right now I don't feel that way you know anymore or I don't feel much about that anymore
I feel you in the are Chinese you know like the engineers
Number one
So I think you spend too much time in the
At Sparta in this
View we forgot he know we need to grow our leadership skills
Corazon Bonito Crowell management skills we need to grow our business skills
A part of marketing sells you know
Everything on the customer and Market
If we don't have those skills
It's about hard for a person to become the the leader for the company because I
He or she will not have the
General you know how to manage the whole business
I think that's the
A very important learning I have
The second part is I feel
If you want to grow leadership skills
Those kind of
Excuse
That's not right at umich term
Learnable
Bring me to
Learn.
However if we only learn from our only
Securence we won't become a very fixed man
Massage person
But we have to
Intentionally to expand our an orphan O'Leary
That you already know I need someone
Really good in this field
Coach osprey
What does sometimes in life
Myself writing essay
7 or 80 years ago
I didn't have the awareness writing a someone can
Colquitt County
Butter in that view
Is Annapolis a certain stage
When someone try to leave
Guide me
Tell me
Something I really do the piano
I
Star Trek refusing me now.
To lessen.
Not to mention we got high
Donna Stewart
So I think in this area
Could it be expanded
A much more open-minded
The man's side
Someone Cuda guide on the mentor
This person
I feel right now it's in somebody in our Chinese community
Exact 2
How do you spell people
If we couldn't run today walk together
We want enough
Much better
But not just
Simoniz floor by himself or run them they right now
Just keep learning from practice
Learning from practice results of anyone
Nicole tour guide
It's kind of a
Alaska Fusion
I think the last
Is the our education system
I'm not blaming our education system
So
We didn't the teacher module about a methodology
Off of how to learn
Talk too much about
How to be right on the final results
So my feeling you know right now I think there's some change you know
Will happen
In the past several years
Are Chinese Engineers were in or
A que hora es stay in the Sonoma Valley
We need to learn the fundamental methodology
But not just that
How to get the results
So the Kitchen System Unity
Talk to Matt about the results
Not
How to learn
Learning
And finally
I would say
You and you asking though we have to get a green card we haven't got H-1B we have got there
Milton Harrison
Those kind of limiting on people's ambitious and
Yunnan
How to say
Is a desire
Being more creative I love you more
So if
I clean right now
If I look back
I just had too much fear
You know
EBay in LinkedIn everyday lose my job
So exactly end
However
I strongly believe you know us culture
Real encouraging you have your independent thinking you know right
Being creative
Being
Customer-centric for Sandpoint
It's okay not to speak up
You know it's okay to express yourself
Clearly
And then you know we Scots
And that's what I learn how to link him after 9 months in my life
We have to be extremely honest and then
Brutally Honest by telling the truth
You know however I done Monday status care what were the fear
I had in my mind that's blocked me
Off of being batter
So that's just my personal I said I'm not
Apply to everyone
But I
I recommend you know
Other
I don't
I don't know what you know you
You have the same you no problem
And that
I think
I would recommend
So when we looking at
You're calling score of Indonesia
The / last stand
Decades
They have done amazing job
Auto variable
What are the lessons that we can learn from
Now you see
A lot of them were
I seen exactly
At Harbor and other places in just truly Market
Though I look at it you know the you know the top five
Fortune 500 writing us out especially for tech companies
Hominy Indian exactive
Are managing you know
Taobao
Yeah business
I would say
Complication adjusting apart up there
Very shallow in a surface you know
Harbor I think deeply
Cultural bias in a writing though I think he knows how they teaching a businessman are almost across the
All the levels and the second is he not a teacher how people collaborate abuse others that's very important
I almost forgot
Operation is one of the most important thing in Ark
Cracks are also a leader
I think of India employees they know how to collaborate
How to be collaborative
How do you know
Keeping your independent thinking
But also can compromise in the final
Find the solution
Also they know how to build an app
That's very important skills
Because if you like me now
Agree on Samsung
You have to I leave the lobby you know everywhere right now
Underneath
And the final Ain't Enough
Agreement
So
I think I have a lot of thing to learn I know so
My feeling is he not so
They understand you know so the letter
A lot better than
Chinese import
Chinese employees of sometimes and they feel if they work
A hard enough
Fat people recognizing out there
Actually no no that's wrong
You know and you do your work it's almost like a product-market right
So you only feel that great a product result people know
That's a fader you have to email promoters Parker in the right Channel right now
You need to have right now
No it's not that
It's on the house
Stop playing politics
Is the hall
We make a great idea
Become a virgin
So I would have recommended
Chinese
Learn.
That's very important on basic skills
Anyone
Want to be successful in the company
Search for Chinese
Folks in
But it's gray less
Anyone
Young 22
Can I move up in the corporate ladder and do more make more impact life
Arby's in Lawton then I move back to the Bay Area in 2013 was felt like you
I learned a lot from being on the court of a Battlefield
In China for 8 years
You see so much and see that this is a TI something this
Toughest Marquis Memorial
Do
Have you see where or even goes.
I thought you were getting a second
Sorry I didn't on the podcast
Not even a little bit
He's dachshunds are sassy
Naches tennis Pacific
The great lessons
Then it's probably the motivation of doing nine at six podcast
Is that they're not there maybe
Starting to China contact
But the implication
Application is actually quite Global Beyonce
I think another reason for that phenomena is a self-selection bias
So a lot of enterprising Chinese
People at Silicon Valley Tech companies actually moved
Back to China to either join or start companies like you did
So
There's kind of
Seal of officer at LinkedIn
Would you still have come back to China
Heart attack
And this is a part of town is that India has is that you have so many Graces us with Indian exact
Eclipse in the US
What day
Be able to give her up
Justin bubak
To India
If I were already on the fourth minus list 5 years in a row
Mus what I give up
To go to China
Not so easy but interesting is that by
Both places
The things you will learn
Become quite powerful
Anyway that you wouldn't have
You've just staying one place
That's exactly right
You know that's almost like
The story you shared it with me your hands remember
You're sure it was me
You did a lot of research on the Japan history
You learn a lot
My feeling is you know when you told me that story at the moment I connected
So if I stay in Silicon Valley
Advice on my career
I would have never learned this new language
Even though we talk Chinese
I am in Chinese I came back to the China Market
I just learned so much
It's almost like a new world that's my 20s know that I learned
And then you know so you know I IRA flag out this is
China Market
For me it's almost like
Japanese
I was learning taina
He really enjoy learning history
I think that's enough to teach me
Afghanistan batter
Customer
You decide to come back to
China Warriors go
And you decided
Do
Take a punch in the edifice
When was not clear
What took yours Kardashian make
I feel something Enterprise
Seoul local market
Adidas right Against All Odds
Viable business today
What are the some of the early challenges he have to
Too Faced and how did you end up solving them with
You can pick two or three
I would have say naso coming back to China you know building a startup
Building enterprise software
You not being a startup person
All this for me
What's the computer new
You know I think that the reason because
Do this in the sunlight
You know because of whole
You know
The personal
A or B
I look back
I would have say I should have a better understanding of
Part of my cassette
Right I should understand in a different state you know
WhatsApp
Nor should they sit first time light bill
Starbucks
So we made a lot of mistakes
I think the most important one is
Under the market
But not just
Book song
The technology be
Or the technology dream of you
We had in a full-time customer on the market
This is in the first lesson I would like to share with anyone
Wang computer startup you know you're any Market the second part is you know
Lesson
I learned a little bit
It's a virus that leave it to earlier too much money a little bit too much money
You not doing the Cersei or you know early stage
That's actually clowder
A lot of things
Because we can do marketing we can do a lot of things
Early signal
If I had the less money
I would have to do is like a different
I recommend you no other
You just one of my
Bee folk song
No marking
Early-stage
Completed Fox on customers and then make sure our part I can feed our customer need an early state
And then make sure everything new
Become smooth
Add appointment
Service
Transino check
You know it's kind of a
I don't know that I even did not know that
Supposed to be the forecast
Even someone told me
Enough about 2 because it's not resonating always me at the moment
Then I made a lot of mistakes so high
Other entrepreneurs
They should agree.
Or State Park
Exodus lessons
Enterprise Sheridan
A lot of books
Yeah
You don't know
We don't know
And that's why tweeting of each that's right
I think a lot of founders of us especially in China sees fundraising as a signal for a 6S
But as long as we close around evaluations High we are successful company
Pressure and like you said Can dilute your focus
So there could be a downside
To that as well
Different type of culture
American Thunder
Here
Art in China
Startender
Donut
Every
Press what media expert
Will want their Founders not to
Talk about valuation and money race too much
Is reporters are so jaded
But they don't want none
Report IU makes a lot of money
And we want to know like what kind of.
You Really Got Me
ORS notice of me to company
So that's a lesson that mr. Peter knots in China but also in
Not America southeast Asia India Emerging Markets very easy
Boogie with a pallet
Good chest when they just raise a large
It takes more maturity or
Expensive bongs
Concerto
I'm just leaving
4shared
Anyway
So what what recommendations do you have
Chinese employees at Silicon Valley
Tech companies were interested in
Coming back to China
Baby found
Startups
Two different type of award
Right Honda
You know it's depends on what they
Really want
You know and I would have say
Here in China
This is acid
Significant
Historical points
You know people can come back
To become someone memorable
You know you human history
So this is the
The place
The Next Generation
Greatest Enterprises
So I would have say
Someone in Silicon Valley
Young
They are you know how does ambitious
Now they really want to do something about it being
I'm creative
Is the market in Elkin North Shore the greatest
No entrepreneur
I think that you know
In the next 5 or 10 years
So this opportunity
Really
Make sure to come back
I think some of them.
They might make me regret
You know this.
A lifetime opportunity enough for a lot of work
Young Smart well-educated engineer azure
Writing on Chinese
Noah Fox
The two sinks
Coming back
If I say
I've heard a
It got to become a VP
He already come some scenery rakiraki or whatever
Golden chance and also kids family houses your car
It's harder and harder for them to come back
Right now I think it's the opportunity for them to
Play in this stuff
Nephew
They have nothing to lose
Right
I almost you know
What are three or 45 years old
Yeah
They are much younger than me
They have nothing to lose
So
Again
Eva
The process would be very painful
I would ever come and lean on them too
The Comeback that's the story I told it
Some of the employees in The Green Mile
I told him you know just a lifetime you know you haven't
By heart
This is the place you know for people to
Become better
And yeah
And also
Analyze the environment right thing about the crashing
Has just asked me you know this
Other
Country is exactly manager
Think about it if you want to grow your marketing you on The Fun Song lyrics
Isalita
Competition
You want some
Chinese people who stay in Silicon Valley
But I mean here in China
I would have
A lot of people
Are trying to figure out the timing issue
How long should I stay in the US before coming back cuz if you stay too short
The premium of what you can bring back his limited but if you stay too long you get settled
Keyboard also worried about the economic uncertainties facing China right now
You don't disagree crashing you know
Is there anything you know about the outside
You know what
Best
That's come out
For my part personal point of view
I would say timing isn't the most important
Every single sobcon choir
If your wife think improves and we can learn anything
Harmon Auto
Because everything
Having an environment
Requirements
It's much more efficient than
Doing something
I would say this the place this battlefield
Learn in the battlefield
Right now
Better schools
And you know
Just being in that environment
I think that the question is our rates are very legitimate and we hear that from a lot of
Folks who listen to 96
What comes out relaxed
Who else will hear from a lot of people who made that confession box it.
The first thing you do is
It's not worried about
That you were Superior
You cannot think that you know me
You have to be more humble and learn
To sit in here in China Mall
So if that's the case
It is much harder for someone woke
Acquire that
Domain expertise
Bought something when you come back
Is most the time it doesn't
Either you're AI or machine learning specialist are you going to come back and stay
IAAI enrichment specialist
You can acquire expertise in the US and come back
When you have achieved it
The chance of you becoming a business leader
And do your startup in China
It's not going to be high
Because your mentality is always
He's already like IMAX Park
So penny aprima for BMX
You choose
To come back here
Counter in pieces leader
So sure you would expiration date on Linux
Allah Allah Muslim
At all different person in the last 4 years
Newark to New York today
What made you decide to do.
In what specific lesson you had to learn
Cucumber tea
Shaped
Leader
Expert in
Did I make
Text me one of the best in the world
I learned from the peoples of criticism
You know so
Because you know but I just came back
Exactly like it was a hands just described
I thought I was one of the best
In that field
Then the part I built
Would it be the best in the industry over then the company I would have built it will be that the bats right
Denver tomorrow
Work with me
Omani male what a horrible person
I wouldn't say no so
I learned enough
Crisis
You know I think the whole team learn from that
The freezing point
T shaped
The number one
Problem
Is he
How to build a
We used to be at Hawthorne Theater
Rosanna Rent-A-Car Union TWP Ardis Delaware.
A fundamental we found this not working anymore because we need to be
Who delivers
The Mini 2
Have the operation
Organization online
I think the hardest in the lesson I learn
Nobody really need
How to build a crate
Equate organization writing
See you always not just so you know
Home Depot Hutto
Computer parts
But I also understand customer understand the people
Olympia weather
Translation
I did not
Notice that
It used to be just a lot of terms
In my mind
In Huntington Park
Hi wire Gose kind of like that
Stopping at a field
Result of my knowledge at the moment I just live with it
Cracking up right now we need to be with that
We made all the mistakes
We beefin about the license
Italian policeman told me a sign that you're wrong
This.
I thought I was not wrong
And she will throw up
Bucky no
You know and I said, analyze
Hey
Why
And she told me I was wrong writing that why I couldn't understand
What's he mean
And then I also live in a different about people
It told me I didn't have that problem with her
Only you have that a problem with her okay then let me think about that.
The problem is you know so
I didn t know
Aware
The problem
I had
Frases Amor Papa
I have to change myself
So I think you know after coming back to
Go to China
I become a little bit more
I wish I could be more open
People give me a feedback
You know open mind
Nintendo myself
So I think that's the
The largest
Alarm
I still have a lot of
Learn react
The more I understand you know what
I should do
Amor
I feel
A criticism
And the people are self
I think that the second part is
In business
The are so many great and knowledge in
Ingenerate
In the history
Because we are
Seoul
How to say
Not recognized
The definition of CEO
Salt
We made a lot of
Cost
Based on
Personal.
These are the facts
So I mean we have to learn from the
We have to learn from them
We have to learn from
Making mistakes
I need to be quick
Keep on making the same mistake
For five years
I think that company
Diner for sure
Bena Landfill fire
And keep them
What one of my theories that assume that
Everybody
Simile smart
To get the right answer
You have to go through
Similar number of
Mistakes
You could be Chinese
Indians or Chinese or American Xenoverse Martha's matters resume
Some number of
At 6 to get there
Used to be that somebody go to the process and a second-team can
Copy and clone and take shortcut
It's so you
You get over it quickly
You didn't have to go through some numbers
But as
Marvimon Visa countries
Are The Cutting Edge what they do
You still have to go back to figure out whether the missing the steaks
They got me going to get a ride
So having said that
Do you feel that
We'll look at China vs. US have been working both places
Which Market is faster
At your rating
Making those mistakes
You want to get to the if I don't answer
Soonercare
Of course I think you know
Because I'm in this market
I think Chinese you know I'm reading learnsoft
Lieutenant Stone plan
They just shoot first aim later
We just see the breaker and it just really partigyle before it's ready
So he
Think about this way I will call this is a crazy with you
Writing.
The speed of her
Innovation
Because Foster & Foster
We cannot just set out the process
Before
Rihanna Style
What a customer reading eat
And I would say that's part of the the univation
Chinese way in Arena of course going to spend the pussy.
The funding
Fiverr I think the competition is
Botsford then
We crazy
Yunnan creating the series
Freezing moo
Pizza or engineering the whole industrializing Oxfordshire
That's not V enough for this enough
Twine
But of course there are some fundamental things
LTV
Adesa fundamentally sound
Sure thing
Stop
You know stabbing to that appeal.
Ross
Another common criticism of Johnny stems from
That's a big lottery is that
Yeah there's no work life
Dallas
Innovation for a long time
And if we want to see
Stay creative stay fresh
Unipig timeout
Think about things to yourself healthy and so far
Is very legitimate
In China what do you say
And what do you practice
Do you worry about life
Work-life balance here
And you can see teams work 9:16 a.m. to 9 p.m.
This week's events
Deport efficient and
Car proven
The same time what do you have to choose
We were just a creative Innovative for them.
This is a great question
Why wasn't working in the valley I was working very hard
You know come carries my
Colleagues or my peers
I think that was one reason you know
I could
Get promoted faster than normal
How to remove back
I found
Every single company you know in China almost
You know
From
Baidu tencent
You know everyone's
Zohar
You know writing us all
Prism clean out recently be harder
A summer coming in
I don't know annual I knew parties right
Last chance will 96 and tomorrow something I got you know you speeding I recently
Butter
My feeling is Tina so
Having a clear goal
CPAP delivery
It's very important
You know he's any Market
Right if your competitors you know they doing much more working out then
Do you want ya and I-55 and I have a company
I would have said this company would
So in China market near you have to
Harder than us company
Who survived in this market
Even Alibaba you know the building is just
Couple blocks
From my room
You know you could have see at 11 or 10 p.m.
The whole building is almost there
The dancer
Peer pressure
I would say
Around the other side
I definitely think you know how to keep a certain level of
You know space
4 people tent
I'm too deep thinking you know
Cool effects on work
But not jesting Buy hours
How many hours we were
Steel
Country song believer
But there should be some balance
You asked me depression
The first time I move back
China
We walk almost there
Oo7
Almost 7 7 days a week
We won the home around in Oswego 4 a.m. in the morning
We came back around 9 to 10 a.m. in the morning in morning
Lbb
We just have all faced under
I think I almost nine months I'll be feeling we could enter
Evo
Think it's not
997 bus 7 days a half day we can talk all we can take off
Steal your fill out this is so exhausted and then we have to learn ballet
I was a tree company sure that she like that Tina and balancing point
Butter to a certain level
So what is your schedule now
I recommend a national founders
Antidepressant
Because I've been day
Go somewhere else
Right now
Computer shutdown
The Our Father
Become a clear
And before
Right when they occupied today's
Is far harder to make the right decision
That's the recommendation I've been given by my friends and my pierced sometimes in my
The unit on the couch
So I learn
A lot better than before
So I would say there is a balance
What is the schedule
Still
96x
I go to the office Elizabeth Sunday
Quieter
I can think of
Maybe you know
But the reason why I start managing you
19 out of the bathroom but your share with me right now
Funny story
I think I need to learn a little bit how other people
Always occupied by myself by my old house
I don't change
I'm also fascinated in Japanese sweetheart
Some of them some of them can achieve
Be able to think
Reflect
And still be able to
Aggressively inquicker
As needed
How can you do both well
Insult me
I've never questions
Juice
Efficient and
X
Or you were
Then I 607
And you're not
See that you have to choose
I think there's a way to do both
And that's a higher form
I'm working in the quiver can do that
Will be the most effective
I wanted to ship the topic to gross you wrote a book
Call Chief growth officer
In Chinese
Which for many Chinese people was their first exposure to the
The concept of data-driven
Gross
About time gross as a term was already
Frequently heard in the valley but still relatively novel in China
So what do you think are the
Major differences
Is between Chinese dog growth and Silicon Valley stop
I think Chinese Worsham braless
Some more like the numbers right number so users you know
Number off of unity MVR
Number Alpha
I think not symptomatic Rose which means you use a science use data
To grow efficiently
I know you mad at your
What part of life cycle you know smart play
Percy of Fox on the Run maybe you and Eve he apologized become the part of my tooth
If it stays you know finally retention
Adeste to you should not
The booster you know the number of Ross
You know you'll figure out the channel fit
And thank you
You are saturated
Across almost exactly what Lincoln did
In the past 15 years right
Stage by stage
And harbin China
Like it was answering the question he asked me
Play
Depot
De nada
Time
Do this is so classic
I would have Saginaw Chinese market the folk song
By using what I wrote it
Right at the moment you said I'm the other bees them all.
You know
So
A lot of great companies you know
That is something you know
But recently I think they start changing
Is the market as a whole
It's not expending about you
So you have to be at work
Efficient train
How to survive a small dog door
Normal day
I would have said there's a changing underneath
ESI economia everything you don't Democritus Tarkington Avenue
I will not say which ones right which ones are wrong
But I just say I'm just saying you know right now
It's time for
Many many companies
Tumblr
How to run business efficiently
This is the fundamental
Computer long lasting
Enterprises
It's not just two years old
You like you all done
No
Actually able to upgrade company
Should have a lot of patient education
It's a long-term Journey
Then I would have stayed
Walter Theory
Loading dock
We brought the market
Could help a lot of companies entrepreneurs
Become
Long lasting
So I can
It sounds like that
Bodes well for
Enterprise SAS
At the sector
Yeah
Anamosa to CR
The consumer company's attitude
Bastille
Bring us some companies are boost by
Replay
You know Terminal Market
I wasn't being crazy is always right
Being fat
Doesn't matter you know
Mature Market
Or a
In a fast-growing Market
Being fast
United States
Yeah it doesn't matter
Where We Are
That you don't need to ask
For here
Caribbean Shore
Short shorts for my cycle
Being fought Mancino's
Everything we need
Terminate
And this is not a
Popular
Thinking in circles
Everybody's favorite emoji
But if somehow you could do
Angular
Think
On your feet
Cic
The same time you see whatever else. Movie
That's great I learned
Have a war like men
Mentality like
No matter what you scrap DeLand Sheriff first
And then figure out what to
Do later
I think over time
You got to be able to bow
But you know how to play
Why are you on the go
So you must have had
Fascinating
How you learn is very important
I think one of things I I picked up
There's a train coming by or xiamen
They figure out how to learn
Faster quicker
Then there
Competitor and that's how they
Now we still on the Journey of learning how to do
How to learn
Rate
So movie onto the quick fire questions
Won't you know I learned a lot from different genotype entrepreneurs
I would have stay
At the
You know who's building yunnan Pixar
Heat Tucson
Sumatra
Reading I mean in science
How to
Hope you had a creative culture
How to learn faster
How to become
Nicole Wright
Can within the company
I admire him meaning
A lot
I read a book actually the book who was recommended by the CFO on top
Picabo Co-op
Esau Simon you can read that in a creative ink
You know that's
He recommended you know to me
A couple years ago
I read a book
I learned a lot
It's a fascinating item at him about the twist going
Guilin China
Yeah he presented
I think you could do better
He she shared a little bit
And I admire him
Right
Had a dream
You know Alpha
Beauty
Something really unbelievable
Not at the moment
And then deliver
Figure out
Dream is not the
He did it right
Kemah building dreams
You know and the
Hsf
These are my recent you know
Right End
Also another culture
Everything
And also
I like her
What's something you read recently that you recommend
I would recommend Allahu Akbar old books in a store
And I have one book
I like the recommended
Any not Bernardo
Read it was a very old one
I think it's called the
At the discipline of a mark
Leader
What's up
Funny story
I brought the book you know last year
Inca
Summer or something you know Amazon a ship not my friend who live in asymptomatic
Josiah boss embossing
He always in a broad back
And then he brought it back and it's going to be another year almost November
Iran
Start a reading a book
Does Grace know a lot about you no more
Public park
Service
And the you know you questions
At the funny part is that in the book
I saw a note
APA
The Fowler
Bashar assad hate
The book I'm selling it
Is always 5 to 20 years old
On my shelf
Eastside
Congratulations
Your boss you're brought the oldest books you know ever on my shelf Facebook was 24 years old
Michelle
And
The book talk about you know how to become a market leader
You know
The focus
The folk song
Booking service
Efficiency
Analyze
Panda
Napa, CA area
25 were almost 30 years ago
Army
Brand new information
I learned a lot a lot of questions that I had
3 years ago but I wasn't Building Company answered
Talk about it
Optimize
Every single Factor
You have to choose whether you choose what a situation this creative personality
Right
However 1300
Residence Inn Vista across
Furious
By the well
Brighton forecast
Typical a
Alfred Morris or founders
I could grab a large amount
Everything you know is right
For whatever reason
Titusville
I would recommend
What do you do for fun
Jeff type of fun
Go to work
I think that's the fun part 2 the office yesterday
Ben today
Anyway I would
I want to say beside the work
Panda
I like to play video games
I used to be a barracuda video game player
Recent I just if I have stressed out play video games the reason my son
He's better than me
From here
Hebron soccer cleaner than myself
Right I just feel
Yeah
That's all we have for today thank you so much
Thank you so much
Airline flight 879 89.5
I-96
Ggv capital is a multi-stage venture capital firm based in Silicon Valley
Shanghai and Beijing with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past 18 years from seed
Capri IPO
With 6.2 billion dollars in capital enter Manish Motocross 13 funds ggv invests in coleslaw
Sumer new retail social internet Enterprise cloud and Frontier Tech
GTB has invested over 290 companies with more than 45 companies valued at over a billion dollar
Pergola companies include Airbnb Alibaba C trip Didi chuxing
Domo hashicorp hellobike cows keep slat
Square
Hotel wish someone true white white and others find out more at Gigi bc.com
We also highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat group as slack Channel
Where we regular share insights events and job opportunities related to attack and try to join this group
Bridgesat 96.3 tvc.com community
You have any feedback on this podcast
Or would like to recommend a gas please email us at 996 at gbc.com