Hi there
Welcome to the 9th at 6 podcast
Brought to you by ggv capital
And co-produced
Pacifica podcast
On the show interview movers and shakers
China's tech industry
As well as Tech leaders
Weather us
China
Cross-border perspective
My name is Khan song
I'm a managing partner at ggv Capital
And I've been working at startup investing in them in both in US
In China
For the past 20 years
My name is Sarah Jeong
I meant investment analyst igb capital
Jennifer Moore journalist
Why is the show called 96
Texas to work schedule that many Chinese Founders have organically adopted
That is 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
To us
996 captures intensity
Drive
And speed
Of Chinese internet
Manning witch
I'm moving faster
But even the American counterpart
On today's show we have jungle
The founder of gimping
How is his first name John is his last name
Telegrabbing Shanghai
Came to the US for college
Jose MBA from Wharton
I had work to study in the US for 10 years when he went back to China in 2003
Just start. Dunking ping
Which literally means people's reviews
And it's known as dianping for short
When I go back to China campini's one of my most frequently used apps
I rely on it to find good restaurants massage parlors
Karaoke places make reservations
Buy movie tickets
Xcetera
I can only go to places with over 4 stars on dancing
Cuz you have known towel for a long time
How do YouTubers meet each other
I first met
Call in
Gosh it's been
Almost 10 years
Did people watch the most
Popular
Review site
In Shanghai and Beijing
Bi remember Tao start his company
Before Yelp was founded the year before Europe was founded
And it was just interesting to
In my previous job
Lucky to be part of the investment team
That it was able to become a shareholder
In in Indian
So tell Bill stamping into an 8 billion dollar company when it merged with its rival made when in 2015
The company became the largest player in the Groupon or group buying space in China
Since then cow has moved to California
And those Angel Investing off his own wealth in the US and in China
The new company
Maitland James King
It's not worth 30 billion dollars and 1/4 most valuable startup in the world
It's one of China's newly-minted Tech Giants
Other than the p80
Now people are talking about TMD
Orto chow.mei Twan and DD
By the way both Total in ddr2 2GB portfolio companies
Welcome to the show
Glad to be here in 3 you start out
Doing restaurant reviews online
Back then internet was
Steven Springer staged in China
I even had to start in the US
How did you decide that
Restaurant
We be able putting restaurant information online
What's something that you want to do and do it in China it was worth leaving
How us
Hebei China for
So what about you
After MBA
So are you actually just want to
Tucson startup
Mike Dashiell what to do yet
And I want to cuddle carpets and US Motors back in China
So I was already dope and traffic sign with a popular model
Spa Chinese
Over there already to copy everything I could think of
So whatever
I know Yahoo
Baidu Google
Not yet
Google existence
Seoul
I've nothing to copy so it have
To figure out what do I want to do so
No I'm always a foodie
My father was a doodle of food my mom's a good cook
And also I really pretty
So at that time thing was that I kind of like the part of the first internet phone
But I think that will be a second coming so it's the internet and also the food so
The carnival spy by the
Scotty Busey in the US why was a frequent disguise or
Make a lot more sense doing on online version Interactive
So is that some kind of idea come up
So I that towel wasn't sure I like a hoe
Husker recruiting 2 hours to it I mean as a one-man show any kind of like a personal website
This is how it goes
Why did you still believe in the internet even after
Truth about
First
So now we have this like the version of
First you have to hypogean come down and then
Masonic rosette sword
About this
Phenomenal and
So I think that the second second was coming right and also as a as a person
Largest breed
Shenzhen
I use very often just can't believe
Doubt will not be bad he was coming out of it
And a time you had already lived and worked in the US for 10 years
Did you feel like
You had challenges going back to China and the first thing you did was start a new company which is not easy
So did you have like any challenges adapting
Tula Chinese
Marquette and Lake
Getting to know what's happening on the ground
Yeah I mean
1 challenges you know at that time was
Normally driven internet
Beijing Shanghai
Right and asensio
Play Avatar the internet was like other Crooks pricecharting
Turn off no more lazy and
Horizon
I was not popular and also as like I know return is Isaiah Thomas has to do a lot of prestige in China
Something like
Having second of Contessa
How is eyeshadow pressure
So it's listening through this in Shanghai
Child over there
Sagittarius and what I'm doing so is that some pressure on the ground
And I also I think you'll get back to use to the Chinese culture and into the
Hiding people got the away for 10 years but recruiting people in Arabic
We're friends right
So that would take some time
To get a p you get a team together
Yeah you
One of the things
I know you when you're trying to raise money in 2005-2006
A lot of people investors
For doubting that how big could a gimpy Market be
Because the people who I should weep reviews
Live only in Beijing and Shanghai primarily
Maybe there's something something Center
But there were a lot of
Doubt
Or
A certainty
Involving heartbeat the Tempe Market will go
How did you overcome those are 17 still be able to raise money
Grow the business
Over the next few years between 2000
For 5 to 2008
Esl is a we did our first reading with
Starting 2004
That time the Chinese remark is still very very small so-and-so visits here
Forest HBC
And if a project has started like to know the end of 2004
We are China
Bocinas
And that we actually one of the very first years
But I'm so happy for that was a challenge at in the more challenging part
Visa. They would look at you and say
What's your compatible mate in the US
Cowboy style
And I think that's the most if you have a knack of us model is that why you say okay in China
Believe they can take out later of course a very different right now in the cool way I think
But at that time that's just the Market Common
So end up with taking the money from supplier
China is rising primaries when's I knew I knew before that so he was in
Similarity to what we were doing
Consumer sector Lexia lifestyle thing in San Jose
So they understand so he understood his penis and I remember you telling me that
1 million something I 1.5 Millions just like 5 minutes. A lot of money
So I don't know who's going to grow up
You know gif
It's just not that much money but I think
How much it is to take for her
But after you receive money in the second round he was led by Google
Was it.
And thereafter
Tuna grow the business
Before you started Groupon busy
In 2009
Between 2004 and 2009 for those five years
But just review best
How difficult was it
Where how easy was it
Grow that business
In China
Would most people agree with you so primarily in
So when do you start a business when the
Matty Woods
Was downright
It's not a lot of Internet status says that's how was that treats
You'll have a lot of competition but you have competition
Is not a strong break
So you can kind of take your time to really
Buta solid foundation
Closest hours that the big cities the People by a huge gradual spread into the second chance
So what you have is a very strong community
And it's a very devoted
So you have this
Aquarius Foundation 2
I took a lot of things we are with you today.
So that was great
So
I was his particular
If equality was a
Pretty
Great time
Students ideas to do champions
By nature is a community
Anna and Elsa
Exactly
It takes
If we if we
If you start to feel like now I think
What will be hot that YouTube you.
Kissing Santa Claus by Monday already
And it's a local business it take longer
Even though
National Escobedo itself is hard but if you are local business you have the City by City
Which city probably takes about two 3DS to have a very mature community
So it does take seven years to
Website MPI know we are fortunate
I thought we don't have a lot of
You know Capital Tracy around a lot of like a unnecessary competition so we can do
Our job in the
Static away
So what went take away from that.
Probably
Avicii
Or
Big players
Don't think too much of your category
It's actually a blessing
Dude definition
So I think even today even though
You started emptying before y'all started
The easiest way to explain Dan. Still to say that it's like a Yelp equivalent of China but I still
Don't think there are a lot of
Differences
Find terms of the interface and functionalities
Could you explain to her audience like
What are the
Different functionality that dianping offers at Yelp doesn't have
We have no more things I think it's a besides reviews like we have the
The coupon so we do our own coupon
And we have the delivery
And also
We have that you can hook the movie tickets like at San Diego does
Supreme I think Yelp
We both started as a review and community
Panda
Damn he cut a branch into
Further into the future
No more transactions
Related companies
And the we are engaged with Merchants Ardmore
So is that
Can a primary difference between the
Yelp
Another difference I noticed
On my last trip to China was I think
Content is featured a lot
Better on dipping than on Yelp
So I can actually read like
Top
Opaque bakeries in Shanghai what I've done a lot of like these influencer articles
That doesn't exist on Yelp and helped me a lot with discovering
New restaurant
Yeah I mean in terms of the actual features on the side
She difference
Besides the the ratings
Degenerate we also gave this
So will you tell you
How good the food
Batik all the services
And also it would give you a better price
I need help give you only like the signs
Suzhou station to make a
Beginning so it's
It's hot attitude
Add beginning to get users to give you a lawn mower information
Right
But
But I just at that time decided
That sucks
It's a bad in the long run
Have more detailed ratings
Look in the morning when you found the Jews I'll be more helpful for whoever reading it. So I think that's a decision kind of food
Made out of bikini
And I feel just need some
Especially in China I guess it's
Lawn mower use for to have
Multichoice
4-star restaurant is. Because of food or because of peacock
Look at y'all always have this always want to give me more details
And that's when the other things
I think that the local market difference-maker
One of the
Most useful features
A damn paint is about the recommended t-shirt
That's the very one I was going to say
Pictures coming from China side
Always want ya
This right transfund 1/2 Stars water goodbye
Fighting
And also
Vallarta dishes you can cook
G45 dishes are really good
Sophia Lucia restaurant have a very hydrating but when the other roundish
You haven't had a bad experience so I think the recommendations in China particular
So so how was he that's a local local difference
Important
So that's up to debate but I was too
The foot have more information
The more focus of particular style bigger things
So it's
Did they have the menu is
Bit more limited
Beijing China
People think they can do every
So everything
You can think of
It's inside so even with a Chinese cuisine
You may find a decreasing gif
Lights out
It's easier for someone just know that I hear the 3 4 5 dishes
Rights and other features like you know on the pictures
We are at you through a lawnmower at the feature functions
Solange that I can show videos
Okay so what kind of like a multimedia thing is going on
Then what can't what you can see in the US
The second key milestone
Innate orbis development
Ford
Thai dipping was winning 2009-2010
Groupon become hottest phenomenon in the US
Auntie China was already Groupon
Before but not in the same way
And I remember
As I was looking at what was happening in the US
And seen that in China there was set up trying to do
Groupon on their own from scratch
Immediately
I thought.
You should be the most natural
Expendables
Listen to that
Giving you a hug
Strong base in temping review business already
So when my previous problem
What movie is part of a team we ask you this question
It was interesting to see how you have more nuanced answer
You were just in just not you're not about to
I need to go into a new hot category
Yeah she thought through what are the
Issues that could be conflicting
But you need to solve and what I could be.
Synergy that pushes you could exist but you need to walk hard to make that happen
Do it just doesn't happen automatically
Can you go through some of that
Good decision criteria
To enter a new business
And what kind of framework do you use
To help you identify operational challenges
You need to solve to do well in a second
Yeah I mean okay so
Lights around
Tucson 9 + 1/10
We are facing
What is a group of witches mentioned
And I know there's actually mobile
Okay
So we have freezing photo
Two potential Ray Berry picker disruptions opportunities
Sweet Caroline
So we actually waiting that to decision the first war attack was actually the mobile
So we we actually going to mobile we are one of the first
Cronaca
Pic apps
According to Mobile in China
Because at that time we are more afraid
Of the mobile not disrupt us
Send a GroupMe
How explain why later
Kind of disrupted or destroyed
With Central Catholic Church
Okay
Facebook events
Temperature
But we don't know what mobile mobile going to do to us
Critically important
Go to all the local businesses about
Reitzel
So that's why we kind of just folks a lot of resources on the mobile phone
Sweetie.
I think it was a
Yeah means the most natural thing for us to do
And the total group points action all that easy you need a light.
But mobile can happen overnight some
Politician features witnessing Kafka no Takis
And then the group are we just see okay
And it's the competition rated pickup
So we just quickly photo
Mason.
WeChat 3 hours later voice
Italo mobile
How easy or difficult was it for you guys to switch
From PC site
Turn out to be.
Strong competition, okay eventually
Square phone number
Hey turn out to be okay
I think
For us
Mysa why because we have this mind size always convey mobile so we tried out a Whizzer mobile app
Before iPhone which highlights of SMS
Toy wasn't challenged
Intense of the mindset of the scary thing is like you have something to my side no right
Okay
So that's okay
Okay how to read it br
Really focus on what
People want on the mobile.
Mobile
Kiki Trend kitchen
From the outside as investors or as consumers
Did this revolution you guys had from PC website
2 mobile seems very smooth
And people enjoy using your
My mobile products
So that's why from the outside it seems like the
Going whether to go into corporate business or not
Was a bigger challenge
Not talk about the group companies
No. We have to go to in
Okay
Why is
Groupon
Innocence it's just
It's it's a it's a
Paid advertising
Consumer benefits and traffic
That's exactly what we were doing with our other
So we have these coupon
It just a different day
That's right
So
And
Seoul
I need a Chinese visa that sounds we didn't realize at the time
What cultural
It's up
Just strong
Novel perspective okay it's a natural thing for us to be that difficult
Okay we already have that uses and all these doing the advertising we had a relationship quiz
Merchants
Okay but the two things you did
The group home
The people who are
Seattle Intergroup
About a different font of people who are selling the ass
Okay
These are more typical add teams like yours
Seems like maybe salesforce.com Facebook or Google have
Concept kind of like a seahorse gives birth
Groupon 1002b it's actually not difficult to self
Okay it's more kind of like a speedy approach
Unity3d so you don't need a lot of people with like a better high CO skills you need somebody
And also intensive organization
Put a D20 like
Strong sales people and it's a way to manage them is kind of bit
I'm so fly Jeeves and creativity and that blooms right
LOL you how are you I have these two culture
So they feel good about it okay
Between Grupo El Especial
With all these competitions at you just need a foot soldiers
You need a general career
Just saw
Push everything forward and we don't care how skillful the salespeople
She kind of DD
Later that she all like that
But at that time for the Groupon is the first
I haven't seen anything
Alabama.com only in China
Ella's only actually happened to be the perfect team to do that
Is from Alibaba
Alibaba Wednesday at 7 in B2B
Looks like a specs.
Organization is not really at
How long how long did it take you to recognize that there's a pattern difference
I things that take longer than we would like
So we started a group on a 2010 right and I think
Start realize why
We seems to have our advantage
And we should have crushed competition already but we still have a couple strong come to a competitive and as he seems to be
Be doing better
Inspirational suicide
Sansa we oh we oh we did
So is that a yes
Saint that was a big challenge for us
Okay that's all I'm saying
Is also called a
Geography of China
Guess you have this like
Southern coastal cities
You have a lot of cities in England
So you are a genius
Okay so then
The people in England
She actually like Groupon because it gives them discounts the people in
Shanghai Beijing feel like it but not to that degree no
So we are in this country as we are dealing with all these like coastal cities
So I think you understand
Needs
Is Leica CL really bad if Orlando is much higher
Is that we were respected
From the interest
So that's another thing I think it's kind of the penis a different looks
The beginning
It says 2G difference are very different
But those are extremely important because that is what you think about
It seems like it's a natural extension of a business
Xqd realize that
Their fundamental differences
A really interesting that a lot of Chinese Tech History is often described in
War related terms
Allatoona rally II Army leaders are referred to as generals
And they have like wechat names
And you live through it
You live through the
Thousand Groupon war chant in the early 2010s
Back in 2011 trying to head over 5,000 Groupon like companies
With average of
Can you companies being start everyday
And I thought I went Chinese consumer went out to like
Restaurants that will be bombarded with promotions and discounts from all of these companies trying to grab their attention
What was your biggest takeaway from this
Ferocious War
Okay contacts
Before the battle
The other video websites
In 2005 there was an egg went through a similar.
It was about a hundred website
Meetup website going against each other with some funk on a fun date
But for the Groupon business
Sites started doing Groupon within the first six
That this is Sergeant a coughing
So is something that none of us
Ever
Sing how fast
If a roach is became
So
Yoga Nest devices
We look at different angles
Play the first part was a
I mean towards the generals and people fighting
When is the chine
Ana people are very hungry
OKC one cartridge
So you have a lot of here. Hungry people
Did you want to achieve success
Something you can imagine after menopause
Background
Mr. Jack ma Alibaba
You know it is a combination right
Different
I think it doesn't make a difference
It doesn't make a difference which kind of final
Kind of like for today
Tessa
With that back row is that generally I think
And it's like no roots
Us regulations
Comprising basically you have lost but whatever you want to do that
Just a 3ft Oscar commissioner
So that's one thing I know I nothing is right you know people just said I don't have this side you know people just copy each other
You don't have like a very strong intellectual property rights and
Intellectually
IP rights and I also I think
Call Yesenia
So whatever some good ideas come up
Okay people just carpet licker
You know I'm feeling hungry in all of our talented hard-working people and the US Embassy a good idea if you want to copy it
Any good ideas in China you have like hundreds copycat
Okay the BET Awards and also has online and see the group The First One
Ddpai Tina of the by sharing by Siri
Copycat
Innovation
Saint Louis MO for execution
Is Creekland party idea
People copy you
The blood by Bastille
And
If you are
Happened to be good or bad
Ithaca Groupon
You could get a crepe in it
Okay that's good thing but the bad thing is unicorn face out of a competition
Ana in some ways as a lot of luck involved
Yes I did it become TD until we was good though so I think is lucky
I didn't send my thing with spikes you
So it's a lock
Meaning like you can Ride Captain Ride Captain somebody at the right time or if you get it right the people to report
So that's a lot of fighting how to work
Dedication
But also luck
You need all baoding China
Valentine
Glass
Going to Future satellite view
The things about
Nas is Like
No hundreds of companies fighting for the San Marcos actor
Icing
You mean China going forward
I want we want to seize as much
Now as you fight this thousand Groupon War
And became involved in a food delivery battle later on which requires even more capital
The big boys
JT Sarika involved
You had tencent as in buster
Alibaba becoming about certain Mate1
And Baidu started its own takeout business by Dua my
And some people these days say that
Chinese startups are like palms for these Giants
They don't control their own destiny
It is a reality that many
Small startups today need to choose a cam for a gen do I from day one
You're either in the tencent can wear the alley cat
But others argue that in the past
The Giants just used to copy everyone and Crush you
And at least now they're willing to invest and give resources to help you grow
So in your experience dealing with Giants
What are your takeaways and recommendations for entrepreneurs
Sweden China zip
True match light
Especially Alibaba and tencent
Become
The last line of capital
Ain't no way
Does he have deep pocket
I think Sasha has a lot to do with the traffic sign
The podcast suicide
So even though a lot of Yeezys in Beijing China to look at so
One of the two guys going to come into
Give you the capital to go forward
So y'all can stay the same
The capital of Tennessee is a big consideration
And of course a WeChat is that thing will you consider my help
India is actually not that much bigger difference
I want to see the traffic
Any other things
A very important in terms of how successful.
The startup web in China
As puree because I have a tee pocket and z are willing to use that Deepak a
To finesse the companies
Kind of like chicken
Psychology B series a series B series cvcc okay well
Tenten coming out of series season out my messy more because somebody going to come in
This Dynamic is a priest Roy special nowadays in
In China is much stronger than yours.
Google Facebook
See you in like this way
Potenza and Zendaya and Ariana doing
Decapolis way too good at this ecosystem
Off tops
What one could argue that are the bobbin tension or different
Alibaba tend not to give you a coffee
It was more
Deepak of capital
With
Tencent
How do you say with WeChat these days
It's possible for them to give you traffic
To grow and is up to you what you take advantage of traffic Wailord
Did the moon just give you the talk again
Chance
Look at look at pinotage
Inshot absolutely on the WeChat traffic
But
They are better than
Pronto WeChat traffic
I don't know that says you have to take money
Marie-france tencent
I think she has a lot of considerations not. Because of traffic
I shall device companies if you think
Tencent
Do you want to take it the money in front
You will be very careful and also
Cuz all I can get traffic from the 10
More for your petition dissolution
But you might still want to get money from them for other reasons
For example
Possum poison
If you are penis
Requires a lot of capital
Okay D pockets
Zen you want to eventually
Okay probably not seriously receipt because
You still want to be independent because you want to have the option to choose
Okay
Capacitance from
Siri Siri do you probably want to get one of the guys
Because that's how the ecosystem Works in China
We have to be pocket
Okay please be on the deposit capital is there any other reason
To take money from at 10 send
Or Alibaba
That is
The founder
How is it to top when it when is the penis as I just mentioned what you need
Another business maybe you do have something to do
Right so if you are doing gaming
Car. Set
If you are doing like more like
Offline, V, this has to be having to be like a field
But that's tricky
Choice
You have to some penis I think
Money and also the stretchy values
I involved
Aston Martin.
Can you look at a ttyd why they have to take money from you
Two guys because I think the money is important because
Still willing to song you so they can be
The box is empty
Yeah
I think four with you have all the deep cut like you have a lot of Deep Pockets investor in China
Azar mobile as a dude really have to take the
Have to take off valve
They were trying to
Figure out
How to work with a WeChat
And also learn from
Tencent help build better product
Lately I like you
They did he did not
Start off with that
Without one of the co-founders
Not acknowledging Prada
So
Ivy walk with tencent and how to
Solve a lot of
Peak traffic
Pica's Jackson
Givenchy shoes
Do you have a scale
That was helpful for them
To learn her
Ulta Beaverton
So I think beyond the capital Beyond suit
IFit
I'm just improving on
Internal operation what it is.
Knology or
Product
That there's some benefit
Types of learning
People have skills
So that's definitely would consider
But I agree with you
That
These guys are not going to give you money
Did they have
That they will give you money
If you fit what they
Meet you too
M4u no right Syrian War
Both the Audi pay in the
WeChat pay need to have more user
Who's there
And when you take a ride
You need to choose a payment service
Did he didn't have that
Then
So whoever invested in them
I have a chance
Build-up the mobile payment
And that's why
DD
Get money from pension
Sports
Want to grow
Derek Mobile payment customer list
Throw these two rights area
So tense I was an investor in
N. Why did you
Decide that that was
So at that time was we still have hope for WeChat
Tubidy
I'm paper looks like there's a very good fit we should get out of traffic from WeChat
And so that was a big help
I think we just to help us a
I know a lot
Just not to
The level we're changed again
And another thing I think it's
The cat toys that has a mansion
And 13 is also you kill compilation
Right because you miss someone
Makes sense
And when did you first learn that
Nate y&r
Sure was
I always say
But we we been talkin to me
So me and I want machine
So yeah
Even
Play Sirius channel music together I got to USB
Before that much
So how is say
So in this
Cuddle business
If you have light to strip hair
Even to pay is there nobody going to make money
Okay so you will have to be like Monopoly players
Rosalina is hot
Otherwise
Right otherwise he just so you could not keep you quiet capital
And nobody can make
So I think
These kind of business
Is the only rational ways too much unless
You think you can kill the other guy
But
So I think that happened to Nike ID party later
I know it's hard for that was a robot and then she
I'll be last maybe because you're more kind of
Advertising and possession based
Easiest the best emojis better
It's okay
Autistic IDF
4440 50% share equally match
Competitive
Citgo gas
Octopus controller
Show me ways mushed together
I think
Verizon Wireless phone companies
Psychiatrist
All of you penises different
Optical companies
So he's always I think
Mocedad looking at okay
Can we chill the other guy or three
Kind of like evenly matched
So it's always right looking at the timing and
So yeah you know anything of the boys season competitors
How did you choose the right time
It's the right time and I think I've off the cases
Kind of catalyst
Y'all kisses rice
No meat always doing the fundraiser
Okay and I will walk out to the families
So if only thing wrong is that usual
Fundraising iptorrents oud to catch
Alexander
People tattoo
And I'll see what's up
Do you like reading raise money
Fly Seattle
Catalyst is that what made it happen
Were there a lot of pressure from
I mean restaurant
You know it just like we look outside the mobike and
You know
Looks I see so much
Right
Having to have any Masters that I
I like
Supply has interest in both sides
High-end
And the 10 signs and more
Strategic investor so he looks at strategic
I know I'm not feel financially
So it's at the base is also
Kind of Visa
Things going to happen
But oh well
Kind of decides
It's going to happen because
The interesting life
So in case I would you have
Want to race your round sooner
In order to force murderer
The different outcome
Sounds like that might raise the money first and then
Maternal
Summit hours about
So that's why it happen
If I did with the money
It's probably not going to have
Send we all have
Money to buy
Play pop motivation might happen
Got it
Did the outcome of the
The murder of matchup
TRX
Yeah I mean
It's up too much has
Kind of white people
Low expected
How to Magic
Come up
So I wonder how difficult was it to integrated two teams after the merger
Because the kind of people were different in the cultures were different
It's not easy
I'll just some similarities percent difference
Salt as an adult getting too many details but yeah I mean
The two companies with
I'll have that over 10000 people is not going to be the same
Andrea fried eggs Addison
So this article and also each position
Difficult as a we are against off
The archive
We imagine
Where was okay yeah I was naughty it was difficult but no noise
What's also interesting is that every time these murders happen
A lot of Highly capable Executives with leave and start their own Ventures
Whether it's a new VC firm or their own startups
And if you look at the alumni from the McClendon P merger have since left the company
Is there anyone that jump out at you
Or is doing something that you find very impressive
I mean
Full size beds
And also become big
Is nausea
Yes or no
Quite a few people. And
Stop
Former CEO is doing this
Champion it right that the new coming in stores
I think has a great potential
And as a strong team
Empresso that's a
I didn't tell us about penguins
What come out
Got
So the English name of the newly merged company
This internet plus hold
What what is your understanding of the
The phrase internet
We always remember Indianapolis
Is
Chinese at that time with Tim Carter
And what we doing
Is that you want to do like more like child
Trend
Okay so offline penis
LOL Emoji with Allah
I think the train is still going strong
And
So so that's why we never met this way
First name in Chinese name
That English
Translation
Chinese name
The new
Make wine +.
So I did get the Chinese name
But it's interesting that the English names pek
As to what a person says
New company is
It's going to focus on
With all things.
So I think that also signals that the new company has allowed ambitions
Beyond juice
Food or restaurant
Like actually
Recently has a
Expanding too many new areas
How closely do you follow the development
May 20th
And do you agree that the moves that they're making
The new ones are
As a material shareholder
It's all I think
Laurel Market Force
Wizard playoffs
Yeah
It's a
Is devacurl haircut
Edit beginning
Right now
Louisiana
Affected
We will talk about a concept
Super high velocity
Ashoka
Want to be independent
So you looked at me
Duncan police day
Is the ABS Plumbing
Brabus
Expensive
Double booking
Competes with knowledge
Profolio
Expense into human rights hearing
TD Garden
Is doing
Things that
Monkeys with amphibian to John
Profolio
Show vacation rentals in China
Is almost
No end to launching is doing
With your new business
At the same time now that Audi Baba is no longer a shareholder in
Mate1
He has put more money into other my
Arizona business
In the related area
So it seems like even after this merger to make me to make wine and didn't
The battle
Watching TV
Moving to New categories
Do you think that makes sense
And where is The Foundry for me tattoo
I mean for a company's where to set the boundary is always
Difficult
And the different data will have
And
How to say Ride Along
Anoeta beginning
BC housing
Do you think
The company has a chance
Powerful comeback
Hospital
When are the battles
Keeping away Asia home base
Optimistic
Some other motive
So
Yeah
You can always
In your mind what are the battles
What's that mate win should win
And what are the ones that are not as important
I mean the home base you have
So otherwise you you are you are fighting a war
HomeBase
So the home base has
To be
You know it's just sad
Prime rate
Food delivery
Wingin
Stabilized
Bizarre winner-take-all Marquis are you can survive to prayers
How to say
Seahawk player is impossible
PS goes right
Gazeta Dynamics
Kanamachi
Supported players without going to like
Prodigy ice whenever ending
Who is possible
Definitely
So that's one and another Union tense of the
The food itself is actually
Clinton Mall
Integration with the merchant
And
Anime
Patricia stronger
Exempt
You know what the merchant systems and also has passwords
Try and also you can even you can put the battery
You can audition
Dial disintegration like maybe.
Salty things
Needs to be done
To make
GE will be amazing if there's a way to order from
Camping
5 dishes from five restaurant
As you want and somehow the delivery system
What's a good one bill
And
Leprechaun
I am very efficient manner
Are you going to email restaurant you can just all the directory phone.
Define Emmanuel
Can you get all this
Assistance
You are reading this book
What is the Volvo
Dallas
So these two battles
The wrestler industrial Hathaway that's the biggest
The market
But the other ones he's already depends
I mean
Well did you make a make a mistake
You know and
And I was having you kind of voice to do a
The Texas Sharon
Yeah but it's nothing you just
Fight against each other
It's hot disruptor inhibitor
Respect the people of battle well-kept
And I has she has a more money sound
1 categories and
We are doing all the category
So how to be something you
Breitbart
Are you getting you be optimistic
That's also
Yeah something
I see you I know
Try some battles are win by
The opponent's weakness
Yeah I know both you and once you separately for a long time
Both of you are very smart in your own bike
What do you think is going through one seems had SE
Cookie bikes Penny into
New Kyrie's
Is he worried about that you doesn't do it
That somehow whatever he has will be
Attacked
Therefore he needs to do it or it's something deeper
Meaning that he knows that
Mass Market users on his platform
Just has
Multitude
Of needs
And he needs to make sure
They always remember
Order different kind of transactions
Animate
Apple iPhone
What you think is driving his
What do you think
Combination
Is a lot of things that affect
Crucible
For example
I mean
Why she believes the boundary of the
But that's also is always a Badin
The people premium awesome people in Warsaw
The Washington police
The Foundry
Laisimo
And also
I think once she has
Lotto competence
Waukegan
Right
Maybe more than
So
So you fight
Component
Runnings
Combination factor I know he wants to be
Best penis increases mind
Indiana I think just
Anyways a cup
Is it Google
Mystic Market
Say lesson is that
How you judge a good leader is by
Partly by how they
Whether they know the right boundaries
What battle should fire what they shouldn't
Are you only noise after Outdoors
Three Lions
I think 10 years ago
Don't be anyone of us
Imagina tencent
An Audi
Mini business
So it is
It's very hard to figure out
Even though you had to say is
Ally to the right boundary or not
Right
So maybe he's
Alice Rio Maybe I Deserve
How did things right
Do all the things from Cloud to e-commerce
To offline with new retail
Yeah
And entertainment
A lot of auto insurance payment
How to do a lot more than humans
And yes they do more than Amazon
Thought
Penis quiz.
The Prodigy is not a send a text
And I am lines
Amazon
Futurama I attended
Three things right
And the Amazon
But I need the lawnmower
Challenge
The people that the Philippines
Is it because they do this whether it's to the right way or is it
Because he's
Is Jeff Bezos and his
The right way or a chest
The people can do
Okay
It was a simple or the market allows for such opportunity
Well I all or maybe naughty is the market change. The architect have so many resources
Capital of the talents
The way they can leverage you whatever whatever they have that user base
So they can do that easy as and before
To the puppet you were forbidden School
People sees that conglomerate examples
The question you still rights
It's a
Is a combination of reasons
Jeff Brazeau is the one of
Anda
Mark Zuckerberg Facebook
He's not like a
Amazon
Payfocus
I know it's a stupidest and a penis
And I even though I'm using Google to the wrong things put a structural wise you have these
So you kind of like it's very clear at the men penis
It's too bad a cold
And if you have these like a
Moonshot
Are they organized by Dixie Highway
But that's a recent phenomenon
You're you're too
Happy 4th October
Living separate
Yes
This is kind of different panel Amazon
Best Duster
Okay
But Amazon there more focus on the
So whatever they experiment on Amazon
Ends up being a sizable business
Focusrite
What's a private businesses
Is a is a post with what they are called
Call strategies
Little cat
With a WeChat cuckoo's you have to use a base
Send weather you the best most natural things
You're the game in Europe
Pokemon
Value of the content
So whenever they want to go to other penis unrelated
The twist
So that always he pencil by pencil
Amazon audio
Aldi's even
Even more Street
But those who are outliers
Best Duster
So tell now that you've moved back to the US for a year and 1/2 now
And you go back and forth between the US and China
And meet us sprinters in Belle places
I wonder what strikes you as the biggest difference between the star picosas
System
And the kind of entrepreneurs you see in these two countries
What's track meet at the County Tennessee
In China is there
More
Operation
Like a penis Madre
Island Excursion
The phone does the
May not be the smartest
Save battery power
Very very
Eventide
So here are the founders I think you know there tend to be more
Samoa
I know you
You know
A different a notifying account of the fungus
To make you sick
Do you think there is a higher chance for a startup to succeed here in the US
Or does China have
Higher success rate for
Startups
And I'm curious to hear the answer from Bells
Cow and hunt
You have 1000 Groupon
Copycats
Soy China is in deference
I know you have a lot of fun
People don't make it
A lot of people
Wanted
Saag paneer
All right
I want to see you much
Datasphere
Everybody want
The China all these traditional penis
Really not very well-run competitive
4 unit to disrupt
So I would say China
You can see a lot of
Love making
But also be assuming
Okay I think the success stories will not
Mother has well
But in terms of the
Number of
Alchemist
Not make it big
Do see more here or do you see more in China
Does Absol number of comp
Making it
And doing well
I think going to Future
Alyssa Prettyman
Now we still have more in the USA
What time is it
Community content
I'm actually more pessimistic for us
So you I thought I see there more coming out Ina in the next fight
Cuz here you have people who are interesting cool stuff
They doing it because I love it
They don't care about what that makes
The end of the day the penis
Pkin really really big
OKC
All kind of
Easy allies
Industrial
Yes
So
CHS to minimum
China
Souffront Erika I think China will have
A lot of
Black and red
Huge company
Coming out
And that's what I think as well a little bit link to internet
Turn off like a
You know all this
Do you want to do
Pandora
Okay
I know, you ask
Chipotle
China
Football this penis
Canby
No crop in China
Not necessary Silicon Valley
Another the technologies always
Nick de Compras how to say the USB know you like it
I don't know if you guys
We we are investing boxing schedule
Ebates coinbase is doing what
AC Supply
It's going to be very good company right
And also what
The founder of the right
The WTO is already like
Aziz Ansari like you know what are the top 10 richest
So an approach answer I mean
Bubble and Cross Insurance
This something you don't see like you know two years ago.
USB cord
Okay you don't see it
How is it different
Chinese traditional more traditional kind of
Industry disruption penises
And not really related to attack but they did to utilitech
Most effective management Model Management to compute with the guys
To become a US you will not see that okay
Okay yeah maybe calm computing
I love you just don't know right yeah
Different sounds good
The last part of the podcast will ask
Extender setup questions that we posed to Everest
First one is who is an entrepreneur you admire the most
Cny
Now is a battle
Okay Jeff Bezos
It's the relays
This is very helpful
A person can't do
Both
Chuchu and innovation
China in a very calm that the company now
What's the best and worst decision that you've ever
The best ones
You know we
I don't take
Damping fluid review
Comedian penis
And they're getting into the transaction side
Anne Dudek real Force
So that's
Tai Chi health benefits
Faster
So that's a good decision
South Dakota state
What's the worst decision
Gina suicide is a
Earlier
Talking to the
Tatemae time for the
Curmudgeon
Publisher
I know it's just so that we can
Cut off Keppra a small penis
Tattoo yes we are original Toronto
And all these Catholic churches give to
Substitute
And we also missed in a we are relieved
Knowing the focus on the race so we have to have competitive going we are there
Ana if we'd Antonio environment
At that time to do that
Taxi
Penis Reichert Ed
You miss us
Yeah probably should
False
Ben Bergeron
Did you read anything recently that made you think a lot
Yeah that's the book I just finished yes yes
What's a cada Grupo dilation
Yes
I know it but I have not read it
Starbucks
Pizza
Most of the time we coming from a free-market view
Okay you think the free market and also always
Is by
Yeah and also
Really I think
To think
Why China grow
So well
I used to work at a Chinese all these lies
You know if it's a country
Free
It's actually not going to be
Is that dangerous
You need verbal.
Protect
I industry
Is a strong enough so I can compete
If he just like you know
Heading the strangest compete with Cobra Wednesday wedding venue
Original colonies
Inspiring products
Bernardo company can friend
Because they don't protect
Kind of like I am not a trump supporter but
Double cut off
Make you think why so
Propresenter
Ice raids
Topeka
The motive out of the country
I should pick it up
Financial
Economy
Of the country
Topeka.
Russian Offroad
Elicited
Is always right but
Circle of life
Give you some salt
Paddle Wheel boat, liberal
Tradition so things like that makes you think harder
Thank you so much for being here with us
Thank you thank you
Good afternoon
M4
Thanks for listening
Who does episode of 996
By the way
We also could use a weekly email newsletter in English
Also called 96
The rundown of the week's most important happenings
Inside in China
Subscribers some photos for this
Forward it
And you said also features original content
An analysis
From Sarah MI
Striped at nine 6
Ggbc
Ggv capital is a multi-stage venture capital firm based in Silicon Valley Shanghai and Beijing
We have been partnering with leading technology entrepreneurs for the last 17 years
From seed to pre-ipo
With 3.8 billion dollars in capital under management across age funds
GTA V invest in globally-minded entrepreneurs in consumer internet e-commerce
Frontier Tech in Enterprise
Gdb has invested in over 200 companies including Airbnb
Alibaba
Z-Trip DD
Hello bike
House
Keep
Slack
Square
Toutiao
Wish
Soho social
Why white and others with 29 IPOs and 17 unicorns to date
Find out more at gbc.com
You have any feedback on this podcast
I still would like to recommend a gas
Bisimoto
I-96
Hevc.
This podcast is co-produced
Bow friend and business partner
Kaiser kuo
The host of the wonderful sinica podcast
Hey, China's economic
Political and cultural issue