Recent wrestler
Hi there
Welcome to the -6 podcast
Brought to you by GDP capita
On the show
Went to the movers and shakers
China's tech industry
And discuss how I found her
From around the world can draw
I'm fine Aztec ecosystem
My name is Khan song
I'm a managing partner at ggv capital
And I've been working at and investing in startups
Across the US
China and other Emerging Markets
20 years
My name is original I'm a marketing manager at ggv Capital and a former journalist
Why is the show called 96
96 is the work schedule and many Chinese Founders that organically adopted
That is 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
Genesis captures Lane tensity Drive
Speed of Chinese internet companies
Booty growth Miracles over last decade
Also I highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat group in slack Channel
Where you can connect with like-minded people interested in Tech in China
We organize regular offline events across the world 400 followers you can join these by visiting 96. Choose You
Qvc.com
Hi on the show today we have palpung
Orkin
In Chinese
Who is the president
Airbnb China
Partners on Airbnb
September 2000
Tall as founded a number of company
Vim table space
Brett Rypien
Is social app
Recording and sharing tree
That's why it's more recently
City home
A management platform for short-term rentals
Across China
For family breakfast
Call has work at the
Network security provider
Intellicar
McKenzie
Two years as men
Call graduate from University of Melbourne
In computer networks
And the University of science technology
With a bachelor's degree
Vacations near me
Is also a b
Traveler
And has been to a bar fight 50 country
Macross 7 come to
Earlier
Essex podcast we have interviewed Nathan Blitz Hardwick who is Airbnb
Is co-founder Chief strategy officer as well as the chairman of Airbnb
China
If you haven't listened to the episode I had to recommend
Checking it out
It was released around exactly a year ago on April 11th 2018
Airbnb ggv portfolio company and are managing partners huntstown and Glenn Solomon actively work with the company
Especially with regards to his
Is China strategy
Welcome to the show town
Thank you have me
So tall you have been
Running every vagina for almost a month
How has your life for you
What are the top three things
Pizza great journey at the moment
Xiaomi
I think I still like a quality
Community and the brands
Are the top three priorities for me
Betrayal everybody you know once
Have a good day
Chubb experience
Silver Fox a lot for quantity
I think Honesty is very important to ensure people have a create
Ultra experience
So we not your class last year
Super plus we have more than a hundred checklist
To mix you up last
Is the settings by users
Travel requirements
Supplies
He's one of the key dry before I have to offer
High quality listing
10-second actually we focus a lot on the community building we believe
A human trash is a very
Capricious pad for travel
So we want to host.
Very welcome to the guest
I'm against Filipinos
Anywhere
The said Podiatry wee folks a lot Builder
Brent
Retrieve MDMA superbrands
Especially to the minions
60% of mbnb China Travelers millennia
So they travel around the world the really want some guidance
How do you spell the word
NM DMV
Have a unique position to offer that guy.
So could you talk about this
The first time you met with the Airbnb.
Team when was it and what was it like and how did you find each other
Oh that was savaria
Interesting experience and a fungi that actually is really tender
Thinking about Destiny
So original was not for a interview at 3 while doing that is so I really find out how in D&D
Think about
American Panther
So I just have a Chad maze night
So we actually have a chance to respond.
That's already
Have very good chemistry
Netease ahead it's a very small successful
Unhumble
It is very unusual combination
So I was really deep impressed by that
So we had a lot of chat
Nate them back to the US
Identity situ I know
Safety spot
Opportunity Tianjin China
So I was very impressed he just decides flying from San Francisco to Beijing just like images Hair Design
Wechat
So I have a 5 hours dinner
The next day we have another five hours breakfast
Feel like a little pretty like a
It's a candle like a moment from your child singing This is the dream radio share
You know I really
Sometimes you know how to be honest I was
Used to be very kind of proud analysis Singapore I can never vote for anyone
McKenzie Electric in Melbourne University
But I feel like
I should have dreamed this in D&D and I know so I think up
The way David even travel is really
Smci I feel like a
Very passionate about
Important to be entrepreneurial I realized in the
The Secret of descendants
Scout is a holy grail and MD have the scale
On the second actually you travel is is a globo
So I do think you know
Two workers in D&D is a better way to realize my dream and the soap together can help Ambien
So that's a story
Nate was here
Pitching you on the roll
The first time actually we just know have a carriage had in those
Find out what is Airbnb
The second timer
Cigna be talked about
Talk to you you call me
So tell me how excited you are
Okay be helping him for
One or two years
The right person
It's easy to start with
Senior executive
The top you going to come visit
China
But I think I give inmates credit
By talking to a founder
Pussy looking for a bigger pot for
He actually makes a lot more sense
The best fit
For them
And you you're my wifey
Do you think that
The fit has work out so well
But you as well
Islam people in China feel like
I don't want to walk a boring company at the always a lot of people back in
Home office about China
There's a lot of local decision-making that need to be made and
Going to be super slow
They don't understand it so I don't want to work
Fort Wayne companies
The common complaint we hear about
CEO of GM
Position
Cortana for
Internet companies
I think there is a sweet reasons for that
First one I think I mentioned before
I'm actually a veterinarian
Travis base
Are we know that the exciting st. Agnes about this
Space in a whiskey lot of Pump Company up and down
For my inner thigh running
Basic change gear for a number X you know just to get the right direction
Set an alarm for this why the low-frequency especially challenging if you do not have the scale
Fix you know you don't have a good unit
Colonics
Well Indian Beano have like more than
6 million units need sneaking around the world
191 countries
So that's actually stepping up
Camp
Set a good foundation for you do pigs
The second is some Ambience very unique Sam B&B is a
Their culture the value actually help the business
I think that's the only company for me I find
The value
And the mission act directly Health business
I was
Indian caste friend
Become NBA host
So alarm for situations because I really believe in the value
I have to resort into a basic understanding house if you make some mistakes
If the guest request something
Substitution for reefer
I think I'll just happens a lot in Oakland phone
That's not terribly play this version of this group become a Seahawks tickets in the basic do people have to
Spend time to resolve that bad
Experience
So I think that's kind of like a senior citizen make MBA very unique and Powerful
Susie I think for me, does he react to the Thunder
You know I believe in you know the dream I really played
Oldest refunded have the passion you know the blind
So that's something very special to me it was like a maternal surance you know this can be different
Self-directed the Thunder and no dice from the eyes
Scenes in the artist DVD 1
Make
Dick success Andino
Cartoon8
A setting of China has 1.4 billion paper
If he's not
Success in China how can you say
Endings for everyone
And Chinese so big
If you do not have listing and hem homeowners
In China
How can we see IMDb
Supino anywhere
So I believe that so this is why I decided I think you know
Gelato
Probably need to
To tackle a problem
So possible today a month later
Are you still in the honeymoon period or
Have you woke up and say oh my God it's so much to do and I feel down
I really enjoyed
Seems like
Occupy myself as a problem solver
I really like so problem
August 5th everybody know if you notice something too comfortable
I could leave email when they're coming to mail be the most leave
Most livable city in the world
So if I could choose like a Aqueduct Interstate Melvin I could be a lecturer you knowing
MLB diversity
I really enjoy all the problems and and the most important or the problem solving
I think that what does veritas
Is very important to connect to a mission
We want to see the world
There is no strangers
Santino people can travel
Have the best experience
Being a hot Coachella myself I think
The best
Experience a traveler's Journal have this kind of War
Amingo Visa Locos
Say something
Like a local
So that's the best
About travel
And I do believe that's a reason why people want to try
I think life is like a journey
The Nanny
Actress Limited
But the voice is defined by yourself
If you want
Broaden your beef
You have to travel
Will travel you actually another people's life
I fundamentally this
People white people going to travel
Slappy leaving the experience
NBC building
Exactly what you attract
Two people special people that young people in the real nice
This is exactly what they want
So this is something I feel like every day of February
You know very tight schedule already feel very passionate
Could you talk about your
Communication with
US headquarters
So far
What has encouraged you and what have been some
Of the challenges
The sings like a Hot Wheel
It's been a difference
About China
One of the
One of the symptoms you know actually sit well
No actually he's allowed to propagate in the u.s. codicil
Xfinity from saying that
Chinese magnetic diplopia system
Sulekha for example the US is more like
Leica Android is very very open at
Antonis like iOS is very close you could have everything right
So think about if you do something
Prada program from
Windows to Mac
You look you just don't send pictures like a Ridah interface
You asked me to review the code
So that's exactly the effort
I tried to expand the US can call this you should do
So this is where you would have liked a visit unit in
In Beijing so we have engineers
Pretty have a full stack people here
So we also
Hot people have the startup mentality
And we try to recruit the most aggressive people
And
Aggressive and penance
Keep them very ambitious girl
You spell them by the Pecos
So I think that's only saying
You can do the right until you can do to be in China
Take a lot of us
Founders have difficulty
Nazi
China s just another
A lot of them
Consider China as like an international market is they don't under
Thurston Howell
You need to
Start everything
Scratch you get the impression that the Airbnb
Co-founders have been more receptive
And open-minded
Perhaps other USA
Founders
Yeah I think they're very open-minded I think a
Nate trailer 2
A channel number times
And actress do you know his high frequency
I think being physically in one place
Actually will
Make you instantly realized
This is a different opencv
So
In order to make this happen
I was so
Initial program
Turn off side business.
Supposed to bring all the senior folks from San Francisco to Beijing
So what has all the people
What is the biggest shark the biggest
Shut for them apart from the big buildings is like
People Kia
Actually travel
Ibiza Beach Republican do nothing
So basically
Which app is so important before daddy no
All the payments of sanctions to do something
Pretty important
What is that important
So this is something that we miss is going to communication people into Rihanna this is
WeChat pay alipay it just like Patton
Chinese daily life
So this is very different from the credit card in US
So so I think this can listen to help them a lot
Twins dad in the water
The difference
So I
Attempt to use the APA system to describe the difference
So if you want to pull a program to China you had to rewrite the code
You just don't repeat on interface
I'm in in terms of
Speak out
WeChat is an Airbnb
Now has a WeChat Mini
Any program
We just talk about how that
Came about
Is that something you
Your head after you
Yeah I think we just think about
WeChat just like
Butcher another plan for
Four or Chinese is actor cross
Open cyst
So weak with toes
They had called I know it's another way to broaden our top on a Chevy
So we designed that
Button hot baby just make the world globally
Because
Indian has lots of globalist
Saudi lots of things that should not have like a dirty work at the Baga need to be having snot like a local startup just
Udemy program you can do in one week
So with your dad and we have to need all agreements
And we also need
Make sure everybody is
Committed
Lesbian Veracruz
Program has increased tremendously fast
So we also
Well how many program we can do lots of
Chinese Palace Kendall campaign
Like a communication of the red packet
And also connected to the WeChat app Apple account
So they should be one of the across driver for us
Nothing
We bought a destination stage
I think there's more to come
Everybody has been putting a lot of resources
As we all know
Airbnb experiences
Could talk about how everything's purses
Developing China Inn
Are there Chinese
Consumers embracing it and wire that's where the opportunities
Json challenges
Yeah
Experience
All company strategy I think it's very important for us to
To provide
Do you use a magic Journey
So
I think a few years ago we only have 10 experience in Shanghai
Now we have like a more than two cells
Experiences
More than 10 cities
In China
So the experience has grown tremendously
Experience
What we do is
We actually are
Try to make sure this is something unique offer to the
Guest
So doing the experiments
We find out
Or the Chinese gas
Especially young people did want to redefine travel
So this can't experiment too damn is a bayou.
Experience
And he's actually easier to Jenna world of mouse
So we have a very good momentum for experience in China
What are the most popular
Types of
Most popular like a
Photowalk
Basically you some people take you to walk around
The metropolitan cities
They gave us to talk about history and
How to take some photos
I just like
Experience
Insignia just back from trip from Sydney
So that was amazing
So basically is a is Australian guy used to study in China
So he gave us
The experience a group of Chinese cursing in Chinese
Talk about
So Olivia Satterfield artino this is
Text me the number have
Is kennel cough grade of the traditional
This candle like apus
So
Young people they just
Right away to try to swipe another WeChat
Newman's
So I think for this kind of thing
Is a way for us to really fun travel
Other things you know could it be
Some something about
At night night for example you want to experience some kind of like pops
So there is some local take you have some drink
So this is a very popular experience
Ambien
For the people joining those are
Experiences are they mostly
Taurus or a local
I think we can see the more of the more actually people
U2 experience at for the weekend
So they do not disturb the listing
Today actually know the way
To extend travel
So you can see in Shanghai or Beijing
They have people meet in the city or come from the a nearby City to come to Beijing
Another way to
Who discovered the city
So basically I think we position ourselves
How to help people just like a live like a local
So this is the important ingredients
2 hour accommodation capability
So people leave their you know in the condition they want to find out what to do nearby
So sometimes you also have a dinner
Ibiza
Some people who is kind of like a
Athena table
So
So this is, I find out he's a young people really like
Deserve
So people tend to POF
You know superfan about that
The number to City Hall and get started in a people really like this
Experience
Sue a person already believed experience
Biblical verb be
And was so I will working on
A number ways how to make cooking and enlisting and experience very smooth
So how do you decide which
Experiences
Is 2
Select
And feature
Airbnb
Sofa
Basically there is a category of we have a design for experience
Dubai expensive
Appear before
So there is kind of like a lion
A song that uses feedback
You know they have good reviews
Conversion
The second is actually we also look at
What's the next city beach
Youknowdenise conservacion
People
After booking they want to look for something to do
Experiments
To make sure the experience
Already fit the user's needs
So or the numbers can tell us which ones on the app works
Which way is actually not exactly what
People want when you do some work on that
So this is something like that we have a
Set a very classy bedroom
To improve the
Product
Ultimately I think this is something we protect our water
User Journey
For you sir Johnny is a candle of non-standard experience
It'll be one speed unique
How to make a scalable
Is the saying we had to break down the basic non-standard
To the standard components
So we will
Identify what a key component to make
To make up a unique
I think all of these is a candle like a advantage of Barry afford to accumulate
Because of window
Exactly what the host one
And what guess what
And we will fund the things which make discoverable
So actually some of the experience and now he's in the brig please gaming mode
How many countries
So so I think that's something I think we find out
It's a very exciting
So sounds like that
Experiences in China
Is becoming more
Weekend
Which means
Will be a higher frequency
Overused
Because more local
Android nearby
Original content for 48 hours
So we we we know like Travis a low-frequency we want Chris some scenarios to make sure people in 1/2 way to travel
So this campaign basically cave people
Some unique listing
Some experience
Designer whey how that make the 48 Hours meaningful
Super Smash Bros
Select the closest react Bros in across or China
In some beer destination vacation rental places we nearly four times grows
So very happy the local tax
Has the take effect
So the team is also very enthusiastic because we can move fast
So we can capture the game
So we talked a lot about domestic travel
Airbnb
China
What's it like for album travel
As you know that there's so many Chinese Millennials going to different parts of Asia and also be on Asia
What kind of a
Unique
Or Chinese
A tourist
Oriented
Experiences
Orilissa
Things are there
To Maxx
Easier
To feel comfy
Tropical
Yeah it was but a dream there were busy we would try to talk all Partners all around the world
Abyss we call the our house or partner
So make sure I know they can be Chinese get ready
Zodiac creepy
Mega hot
Water kettle
Aqueous Vapor
I wish you liked offer some congee
Something like that
So we talk to damn see how you get the ready for the Chinese gas in real-world we will give you a text to Chinese
Get ready
Because we're separate business unit that we can own the ranch in school
And we can own this contact
So this happy very A+
Everybody really want to embrace the largest
Travel Obama
Other guests origin
So did the very super excited this is our trip into a few countries
Host community
DIY very keen to find out what
What is Chinese
Would like
So in the future you will see
Guess we'll see some candle blacklisting
The setting of Chinese gets ready
So the Wonder book dad
Communication
So they were
Somehow Mandarin concierge
And then what about another check-in check-out in the package store
So you return will make sure I know all these hoes they have a good business
So that's actually we try to play in
Candle like a
Interaction results Supply
To make sure I wake
We create a kind of like a
I put sucker in 02
What about Spanish
So which cities
Give the most number
Chinese ready
Partners
At the moment
He's more like her in Japan
So that they have a number for Chinese guests ready
Distance Lance and Cindy
Princess
In the early days of Airbnb China
You guys were more focused on
Chinese outbound
Then
Inbound
Is a suit occasion how are you balancing
Forms of thinking we do not official what is sin
Open Automatic Watch
It's a travel visa cross-border
And we have this black Rubber Company
So
Migos make sure that
Can plate with full potential
So everything just happened naturally
So people
First the first wave
People don't know and baby the girl bounce
They have a very good experience
The comeback to become
Maybe a house in Shanghai
And they know some people from Suzhou they they come to Shanghai Define there is a
Beautifully singing Pusheen
So did they have great experience the compass
Suzhou did they have at least as well
And this is how they go so busy is ordinary fact he was very very strong
Especially where community-driven
So we always have the first candle like a missionary a user's
Because they believe this candle like your human interaction
So I think
Mortar mixer
This network backbone people octopi some Market condition
We want education Market
We want to help the hosta grow
Superior officer mentors
And offline support
So make sure they're not alone so there is some
People we know we work together to a provider scandal
Experience
So that's Australia
What's like for you in the impound Market
With foreign tourists coming to China
Do you to do anything special to help them
To get
Comfortable or acclimated to the China
Chris Berman sooner quicker
Prosper
Steampunk also happen naturally so fast
Some page you know you special
Holster would translate page to English
So they just make the
Sudden Bombcast mobile cam
Chinese set to overtake France
Edwards
Number one
Tourist destination by 2030
As a growing middle class and I'll show you salute
You spend more
Home travel
I remember the report that the foundations that
Is because
Well Asia cats in what developer Dino
People.
True China.
Lots of gas from CPAP
Activation
So that's actually
Is also good for the network effect
Super yummy pasta people from Richmond Asia or Rich
A people from being that they want to be the class one exploding my travel China
It is closer
People don't know that
More than 50% of
Population
Living
China India Asia pek
In a world that's impressive
User base
YouTube
Grow
I know she's like I think the high-speed train to another game changer
You're basically you can't you can't even move around
So meaning of Travelers Inn
Especially like a
You know anybody else that very impressed about infrastructure in
So did we have a good time here
So we will see this is the 20-week
Become one more
Albion cenobio track Walmart
I wanted to talk about your earlier
How did you go from Consulting to working for another security company
To starting your own
Travel startup
Yeah that's a very good question I think
Sing for me sometime life is a random
So busy just like option just comes
To self
Then I think the only thing if you were samurai sword experience I think I have very strong curiosity about life
I just very curious
To the way this way Premiere 2 hours days Daddy
I'm very cute in there with security
Suck it appears you there
And then actually
Debbie chance you have a funding a startup
I just found out and so big. Go back to China
The bring my net was accused out of back to China
There is some kind of finish crisis happens
Which mimic me
How to make toys go back to Australia with stay in Beijing Subway choice in Beijing
Mackenzie Hampton the same building all my previous
So that's why I can load them so I know there's something called Mackenzie
So then we interview the getting there
Nothing we can do
Pro Madrid
You know education probably the broaden my Horizon
I'm really like a hot cortex
So so that's actually help
I just feel like I have a passion to build a business
I think go from 0 to 1
To grow a business always at Sam's if you at your very passionate
Especially like the place I'm not mean quit lava
Super dumb travel
So they sold my present travel experience
I feel
If you can have a good travel
Journey
Appreciate
Memory for you
So I think that were camping people happiness actually that's why I funny brexit because that's all remember the previous
You know feel people
Sugar happy that you Journey
So this is Debbie stabenow we find out
We getting the traffic in Street Denver
No. In Travis English is the most important problem Packers accommodation
People have to have
And they know Lisa Hernandez
I feel like it was some kind of the destiny and it was so
Everything works pretty well you know
Alignment
You know your mission
And you know the industry in the world to solve
And I think the goal is
Is bring happiness to people
So this is
Energize
Not only me my Connex
In China
White's your left side brain
Has done well cuz
You have a PhD in computer engineering
Then the rice I could bring you like the problem
And you're passionate about rebuilding the community
How has this combination help you
Establish credibility
With
Folks in a
Headquarters
Back home in Darien
San Francisco
Nothing first one at the end is the company really playing the valley
The way I think I can natural fit in Elven culture
Read like a
The very interesting experience of an experience I join here
I don't feel like the first day I just feel like you know here
I don't feel like getting used to it like I talk to people and
I just feel like we're the same people so that's very unique just like you don't need to have people to jumpstart like to educate
Culture why seem like that
The next part is basically I think the training at any Mackenzie Ziegler healthy
How to use constructive thinking communication analytical
So anything is the back by Logic and
The numbers
So Def
You know 10 some kind of like a
Credibility
The People Sing you're not just like
They're passionate results
I think about the reality
I think I have
Close to seven years
Ultralight spinning travel
I don't know
Bisacodyl bad is ready ready
Great learning experience and the
I think that's wrong
Alachua
2sinx
Straight to the problem
So basically there is no Samsung Note 3 for PC why do the problem I like to communicate directly
Because I want to solve the problem
Something Orchestra sings help me
To communicate I feel like a
People are here 1/2
Realize the mission
Saudi riyal Committees of the problem
So I have no problem coming to vary directly
Especially not have this can look like a candle
Trash from the Thunders
Circus just like Speed Run Away by the problem
I don't worry about it
Weather should rephrase
Because I know everybody's
Believe
We all have the same vision of the problem
A lot of people in Airbnb
San Francisco
So you deaf
Thanks
So when you are starting a startup in the travel space why did you pay
Content sharing
As
You are starting
Seriously
To be honest
I just feel like okay
I have this candle like a
Nation I think
The proofs of memories are important parts
But he's always getting on
I think it's real nice
What's the best material that
So the learning semi is learning
Lots of light interaction
And also
UPS entrepreneur you grow the business
I think all those things
Exactly
Get you know deeper of the industry
Another reason from counties actually
Got another waiver for mobile internet
Set a timer
I choose
The Ultimate Warrior travel
Another mobile
Soboba Indian that is easy.
So we designed a candle like a application basically
Official by Apple
So that's actually Hawkins.
So
Doing the learning
Experience of from Wauchula
See the numbers
And the fruit but you see the use of the requirement
How to make you realize
What is the
And what is the
Strategy and also the secret of travel
So that's actually I think what a believer
Nbnb
The most important common people
Four people anyways accommodation
You have to offer that
That kind of like copy9 is a people radio looking for
So that's a thing you know how where you from
What was the biggest challenge
Yuan calendar
Wellbutrin
Retro
Some lessons
You need to be the super team so that's I think
The team is very important you need to empower team
You need to set the right culture
The couch wrestling
The most important I believe I think that you should treat a team like
Sporting
So
Everybody have to grow
Sucrose is the most important for employees
So I think there is a mistake to make he's like you think you're very nice to the
Happy but you don't think about me bro special for me I will fix a lot
Imprudently make people everybody for their full potential
Japanese kabedon
Just like a coach
Sometimes it is something like a
Great analogy
That's our experience as well
So what kind of town are you looking to add
2 MB China
And how can our listeners
Reach out and getting
Put the tenant in we won't have in China basically first appear in a vision you know the waist way one.
The second is actually they have to be a pretty down-to-earth they can solve problem the next thing we want girl
Actually we want the field of non capability
Enable in a we have
Ecuador flight spirit
The Simpsons
Kenny the music Rose mentality
The people
You should have a very strong teeth at The Grove
And we also should get used to change
So did you
You know any reorg
Entrance
Do desert rose opportunity
So that's something like Warcraft here and I'm actually looking for
How can applicants
Supply
So at the moment you know we have opened as website
Subscribe the the series
Second we also have
A different kind of like a WeChat account
So there is a tyranny
I peeing
MBI being there but there is a
How do crows have the name you click answer
Supply suddenly I think I also work visa different candle
Recruiting website
They want to have like a job at
Like nicotine
So you can see these ads
So I think this is all the channel
What is happiness
You can reach out to
In July last year Airbnb invested $5
Racine City Hall
The platform for manager
Short rentals in
In China
Company that you
You co-founded
Did you talk about this
Synergies between City Hall
An Airbnb in
And how have the to come
We're together
This energy is like City home you will provide like a supply the pool supplies
The reason investment is like
Indian D1 could surprise
Ecosystem
For some cases you know you have this app professional coming running
You just make
Some kinda lover
A low-frequency maintenance issues
Most scalable
So
Zoe in Pewaukee City Hall MS
Just be the ecosystem mine
City home just one of the ecosystem we work closely with City home to try out some kind of techniques
How we work visa
All Downstream suppliers
So we take this learning apply to order
Because we have is kind of like a relationship we can
Gastrulation we can run something quicker
So that's basically is a Samsung with obesity
Finesse
We're going to a set of
Quickfire
So just say the
The first one is whose entrepreneur you admire them
I like the founder of a Bridgewater
Ray dalio
I think he's amazing guy I like his book
I put Facebook on my on my desk all the time
I really like I think something White
Summer of the log I learn
Tuna pasta
Abhishek Reddy Facebook
You will not have.
Yeah yes
So you really like I really like the book
I really like all self-help books you just draw
A new level of
From it was
Inexperienced
When I was a boy
What's something you regret
Delete that you're welcome
Besides the book called The Score take care of yourself
Alexa is a legendary coach
Yeah yeah I think I really like it cuz I
Taipei Pasco before so
I think from the sport energy osrs
Reminder Last Summer
Ascend management issue Halloween cavitating
Tim Couch
And how do I feed namiquipa Fraga Providence
What in a sentence
Worth Fighting For
Somebody in the middle of that
Glen's rental
Behati right
What's a habit
Do you have that you
Nothing has changed
I think the human life is reversing
I used to know have something a hypothesis I want
Prove he's right
But I try all my Bass Pro
YouTube but this what I think I make a lot of mistakes
Because I try to prove a hypothesis right
I think it's not it's enough santifico Arie Sabrina's actually there is a sinking fraud
So now I feel like I have something
The worst scenario
So what
Do not do that
Daniel Correa
So So Def happy
How to change me
And not making
Pre assumption
Like if you make a Samsung you want to do right if you can do not to Cherokee
It's very easy to
The reality the world is so complicated
Simplify 4 reasons but if you make a big decision
You just simplify cherry-picking some stats with both of your judgment
You can either claim success for yourself
But not for the reality
So I didn't tell what it is
The better you know how this kind of like Rivers thinking mindset
You tried to change yourself
Asset in Chinese
We want you to count couch with everything challenge me
So then
Maybe challenge you can just make you think maybe the challenge mode Valley but at least I'm using dad's appliances
Every have blind spot
Soda
Help me chicken.
The master of the puppets
Innocent interview
Which is what is your favorite travel destination
Africa
Where Africa
Yeah I just feel like
I think it's the people migrate from
Africa every time I try to Africa
Someone just feel connected
I just feel like if you know
Because this is how he was standing right did you stop from East Africa
If you have particular
Session
To East Africa political at another time
See the Safari climb Kilimanjaro
Unique place to me
Cool thank you spell for your time
Thank you
Ringdroid
Listening to this episode
Ggv capital is a multi-stage venture capital firm based in Silicon Valley Shanghai and Beijing
Country with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past 18 years from seed to pre IPO
With 6.2 billion dollars in capital under management across 13 fonts
Ggv invests in consumer new retail social internet Enterprise cloud and Frontier Tech
Gdb has invested over 290 companies
With more than 45 companies valued at over a billion dollars
Pergola companies include Airbnb Alibaba
C trip
Didi chuxing demo hashicorp Hello by
House
Cheap black Square
Hotel wish
Soundtrue white white and others find out more at jvc.com we also highly recommend
Joining our listeners WeChat group in slack Channel where we regular share insights events and job opportunities
Related to attack in China these groups at 9 96.3 jvc.com
Watch community
You have any feedback on this podcast or would like to recommend the gas please email us at 9 9 6
IGG bc.com