Hey everyone
For those of you who are in Silicon Valley
You're invited to join our next 96 Community meet up on September 27th
Which is a Thursday
At 7 to 9 p.m. on Stanford campus
You will be able to meet handsome me in person and also mingle with other like-minded people who care about tech and China
We have held these meetups in for City so far
And always impressed by how global-minded and talented or audiences
Repeat the event will be on September 27th at 7 to 9 p.m. at Stanford
And the specific location will be included in a confirmation email that you receive upon registration
You can register for the events at night 6. Gigi vici.com Stanford
Once again that's 96. GG vici.com Stanford
And as a reminder that 96 Community is open to all and you can join the committee via WeChat or Slack
At 96. GG vici.com community
Recent arrest Monroe County
Airport
Hi dear
Welcome to the nine at six podcast brought to you by ggv capital
On the show interview movers and shakers
China's tech industry as well as Tech leaders who have a us China
Cross-border perspective on Stone and the managing partner at ggv Capital it had been working at startup
Investing in them in both the US and China for the past 20 years
My name is Zara Jones I'm an investment analyst ggv capital and a former journalist
Why is the show called 96 schedule that many Chinese Founders have organically it
Adopted that is
9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
To us
996 captures intensity Drive
In speed
Of Chinese internet companies many which
Are moving faster they even their American counterparts
On the show today we have Tobias when the co-founder of lime
HGTV portfolio company that's disrupting Last Mile transportation in the US
And Beyond
A few months ago we had Brad Bell the other co-founder on the show
Back when the company was still call limebike
About time limes operation was still pedal bikes only
A lot has changed since then in a short span of a
A few months
Limebike has become lime added other Transportation modes including e-bikes
E Scooters to his services
Expanded into
20 Marcus
If we're countries
Announce the 335
Million dollar funding round LED by juvie
With participation from Uber which will become lime strategic partner in the electric scooter space
Lime is currently working with Uber to co-branded scooters and make them available in the Uber app
So we thought we would have lime on the show again and this time with Toby
To discuss the company's recent progress in the hot topic of the day scooters
So congrats Toby and welcome to the show
Thanks for having me
With me to
Journey
Since you start this process at the end of 2016
Actually technically early
We
Incorporated the company in January 3rd 2000
I think about in qvar
Am I seriously in this
Yardley f2017
And obviously the first year throughout 2017 year mostly in
Dockless Bike Share
In what pump you guys can make this change
Or a starter evolution
I am in the shepherd pivot into
Scooters
Yelp
It's actually interesting if you look at our original plan from day one
We never position
The company as a bike showing
O'melveny
Rice always starting
With spikes
Can we name the company as limebike just to be more focused
Starting from day one if you
Talk to some of our friends and even our investors
We have bigger vision
Text my cell
Yeah I would believe slime is
In the long run a brand that same power
It does empowering the urban living
Starting from Pike
And I will adding new product and services
You know along the way
To fulfill a different user needs
So
I would rather call I'm a user Center company rather than the bike Shield
Chair Company
With that sad
You know
Because we have a bigger Vision to create
Michael McCarthy platform
To serve people move people from 8
Bikers the starting point
And we're also constantly no evaluating innovating different products but like ebike
Scooter
Laminas de Frozen
Only company in the world that has
Dockless Bike Share.
E-bike shenzhen
Super sharing
Myself
What matters to us is sweetie finding
What did users need what the city's needs
And I get no customizable
Solid you
Coral testing
Deciding.
E Bike and scooter
The next product you should be offering in
Audi 2018
So electric product is
Has very very strong power
And we've seen that you know from a lot of user
Research
End user feedback that we collected from the field
The electric product has been in the world map
Starting from day one so we actually started our innovation
Auntie bikes in Q2 2017
And then I'll Q3 we started to look into scooter sharing
Started to you know deciding what
What was Marcus was and also was the right you know
Paula mix
To enter a different Market
Palace of USA
Myself
You know it's still ongoing discussion internally while so what we proud of
Because we
Ambition to create
The platform that we can constantly
Innovative Hardware products
Makes it enable us
You know in Nevada
Either way
So in your from your perspective and it did you see
What are the common
Usage case for bike
E-bike
And the scooter
And what sort of penne unique nomics will pay back
Period 4
For this
Yeah
So
Did this replies have
Braid different out use case
For scooter sharing we've seen very very strong use usage
In high-density area
And people use that
You know
To get from 8 to be much faster and also the fun factors you know
Catana
Is the one you write in
Two people smiling weather while when they were riding scooters
And if you'd like we've seen people using. For longer this is
So for example for scooter the average distance is Rob the amount for
Device is actually 1.5 pack
What's 1 * 2
What's the distance
August
Scooter
And we see people taking device notches
You no longer this is but also climbing the hill I solve for example in Seattle
People are choosing e-bikes
For getting around a lot of the hilly Terrain
You know a lot often.
The other you don't modality
Enforce the pedal bike
A lot of cities like that and also a lot of communities like that because it's more affordable
All the people who want to get a little more exercise
This deal pek to August you choose to use pedal bike so
I would say you know three product
Actually serves
So it goes very interesting some people write it for really long because I use that
That's what
And some people use that for short-distance have a mile or you know one point
Play so anywhere between. I was kind of similar to
Scooter so I'll never about them all
So I would say you know
Pedal bike video service
Kind of deer mom
The equity
Dental program that would provide a lot of
Yes it is and also allowed
Uses want to Dua Lipa mwah
Jenna economic wise
Of course you know all the you Paula is a lot better
Because people are willing to pay side a more
Dodge to have that better products.
ISell
But the costs associated with that is also slightly higher
Because we need to
Change the battery will charge
Scooters
You know
Maintaining
So what's a slightly higher banal
You know I don't f*** with Adidas
I remember when scooters first take over San Francisco everyone started talking about it it became like
Is Oliver news all the time
And I'm every time at the Caltrain station
You'll see the scooters
Why do things scooters work so well in the
And do you think it can be replicated in other markets like China
Yeah so funny enough we
Will also see a lot of kind of quick
Turn around you know using scooters
I'll sometimes you know our operational team can't even
Scooters
Touch the grass
So before I touch the ground people are driving
Amazing you know what you guys Asian and then the passion that we see from the users
Stop
And we're passing about
What we've seen so far
Because we see in a scooter could be ever interesting way
Commode
Excite
To embrace
Autonomous alternative
Mobility right other than
Just driving around
That pie thing is going and also
Back to a question I think is
A very
Interesting culture
All related products
Riesel a lot of people going going out in the US
Riding your razor scooters
Push scooters white outdoor sectional
Culture and as fun as fact
Rise and people are doing that from a circuit
That's great and also speaking about International
We've seen
Some of the European Marcus house very strong
Has similar
Have you scared
I got
We're not just in us we just launched Paris about 3 weeks ago about to Launch
You know if your mark Marcus soon in Europe
Are we seeing equally Goods you know you know usage
Do you think it will ever work in China at all given the
Cultural differences in how
Just a condition
China is
China is a wild card that was a special for a scooter I'm not sure but if I were to gas
I would say it will be
Utilize too well but would that be
God of a few Acts
Better than bike
Right so I think bike is already to win
Bodega job already
Play So High.
In general culture wisest
You know a good thing for bike sharing
So I think in order to get that marginal Improvement
Anton euthanization
And economics
Scooter
By investing
Alarm World operational
Charging maintenance
Not sure if.
A wise
Go to market
Prada
But I think it will be also you guys while he's just a bikers
Bissell popular already and there's
Lots of vaginal reason
Forever people
To the extent that you can share code
Talk about the Unicorn almox
Scooters
Send the payback period and as compared to bikes
Sunday Bikes
So unfortunately we can't stress too much
I would say you know in some of the markets
We are with profitable in many markets
And the companies are financially
Wonder Bible
You know we are
Expanding too many markets and then we're seeing
On the part of the market become profitable
With our again
Operation
Deficiency
Burberry
Obviously when it comes about
Woman talks about scooter sharing in the US
Another name that pops up is a bird
From your perspective
How well do you think they're doing and
What differentiates the two services
And ultimately using this
Uber vs. Lyft situation or
What what time do something quite that differ
I think the race was around
$400 in
Lesson in less than 6 months
Are supposed to batteries in about 2 billion
So it's a fast-rising
Respectful
Competitive
Why so I think
From our perspective we welcome competition
I think that's something.
The only get us better push-ups to improve in
It also helped educate a market that we can boast you know grow
Ultimate goal
Samurai
Just to bring more people off the car
And I embrace the
Lime green
Transportation
Thank you
Everything you know
Anybody who is doing this is
Disrespected
And how this Market will be
I'm kind of payout in differentially I don't have an answer I think
Two companies competing could be an option
Palazzo
A market
And space that require loto
Different
USA
Skillstat
Capabilities
For example
Supply chain Hardware
Depression caused from
Out of those one supply chain Hardware been able to
Scalar product
With low cost in a high quality
Restless Heart
Ioc
Many teams out there
That's why I meant to see the relationship
Right so we take this pain very seriously
Starting from day one
You know we set the alarm
What kind of strategy to Reedy what was the city
Now we're in over 70 markets already
Across four countries
Airport Primary in the US for now
But everything go market that we go into
And we operating now we have
Either agreement
Or SLA or you no mo you so
We really going to whoop
Closer with the city
To develop something that we can
Localizing customized
I'm not just going rogue
Rock the Boat
I think it's super important for us
Established
Relationship I think
Consideration should be in the long run
Well
Apus
When you know
Bigger
And the third thing is sweetie operational efficient
We
We have two interesting tomatoes to operate one is
Dr Joseph Hogan
Which we
Call Celesta people to
Mansion cards
And also we have our own operational team right
And.
But you don't report them for us to maintain our
Higher level of
Courtyard
Operation
That people see weight loss
Miss Parking
Bible is
Organelle
Problematic
Bikes or scooters in the market
Buses out
So
I think the boy is
And I will quote
We just need to again
Focus on the most important thing in
Pencil in China
You got some much better operating
Imagine. Piece
Has charging been in
A challenge and how are you guys resolving
Your charging is exciting times for me
Because
This is that you should never been solved drywall
Across the
EV charging
If you look at
Some of the shared Mobility which were
Supply Electric
You know
Power
Is it
Never been software well
Now we've seen very very
You know
Powerful two word using work out a form using our juicer program
Alarm people
Like you love me just
You know go out clogged
A fuel scooters every night
I'm going to
Where's our personal cars
How to get that done
SOS very very scalable and Ivory
No I think it is a very exciting and interesting challenge.
Alaska cities and then I will Mobility is
Are getting more and more likes
We're kind of leading the way to
Soft hours
Cutting unique platform
Operational
Effort
Spousal I discuss your recently announced partnership with Uber select Uber CEO
Madara has said that a number of occasions
Indicating that Wilbur wants to be a transportation super app
So besides a partnership with you guys they also announced a partnership with
Cargo just
The mobile convenience store
M&f Fortune brainstorm Tech he said cars to us or what books are to Amazon
So they started with a premium service were black and they exchanged over a square pool
And then food delivery ubereats
And then partner with
Jumper bikes in and out you guys first squares
So and
Because I going forward that will have bus and natural cyst
Show up a brass wall
So how do you envision this partnership layout
Yeah we're super excited about the apprenticeship
Uber
We will be going to call breathing in
In the market that we have
John
Joanns
Brandin John's Landing
Scooters
And I will also integrate our
Scooters in an hour
Tinder app
We see our service very very complimentary
Uber
Especially for the short distance is
Always better
China Wok
Or use a bike or scooter
Try to get around
Is more affordable
All right so I think we're uniquely positioned to do something
That's
Serving a lot of
The user's we both have
And
Yeah I think we
We will look forward to you
Pushing that screw together with
And also
The other thing we're super excited about
About hubris punishable
Around International
Silver has very
Yellowstone International
Open and we look forward to
Expanding quickly
International
Super Ivar's concept people connected
To WeChat
But what I don't know is that
Give me channel was inspired by
Facebook
Facebook connect
It's a super website
Back in 2008 or 2009
And then now you can see Wilbur
Barring the superyacht concept from
WeChat at work
What's in China
And to lesser degree DD
Supercut
The Eagles know about us and China Market
Extremely Wild
In What scenario can you imagine
Mine be a super app
Yeah that's it
A very interesting idea and we've seen
You know it
Especially the Chinese company's what Chinese app has done
A lot of things.
Way faster
Tactical really really sorry
And that there is a space
That's something that we
I always
Inspired
As we're going our live
I think for the new term with you want to make sure that we are completing and I owning this
Michael Mobility
Hospice
And
Moving forward
I think what matters to us is sweetie
What user really
And what user
Can naturally use our app
I think
We'll leave that for users and I got us
To move to in immortality
I mean we have seen coming home again used to come up with ideas for the additional body Well Services
Respond quickly
That will break out at BB&T new things
What are your thoughts on other verticals you could expand into such as delivering
We don't know yet so I think a lot of areas are very very
Exciting and then big markets and then also
Highly correlated to people still alive
Very close to
You know
The way that people are using hours
Definitely you would want to carefully
Annalise was
What's needed out there what's not being software wall
And then what we can do better
I'm personally very excited for food delivery on bikes cuz how that's how it works in China and is 12 fast
Because
Cars got stuck
In traffic all the time
Yeah and plus we have a big basket
Solana by Cindy bikes
If it's
A grocery bag
So
I could be a good fit
But what are your thoughts in terms of how
The movie destroy the future for Last Mile
Transportation
Imagine what
Like 5 years
Converse driving
BMO problems
Society
What kind of a last mile transportation
Solution could it be album
Multimodal
Cut it cut it.
I would say for Michael Mobility shorter sense
Will be either bikes or Scooters or something else
Who will be more personalized
I can fit one or two people write mostly one
And then I'm very flexible
I saw you can Busy Bee hop-on hop-off
Opossum
Yeah or yah
And it should be very
Affordable by yourself
If you don't want to pay
More than $5
$4
Anything that fits depth
Criteria
I think could have a very very good
That's one and then for longer-distance
Thanks
Steal cars
Will be around for a long time
The current
Current has given by people or a Thomas driving range I think for the longer this is
The car will be will be around for a long time but
What we care about is you know
Other than car
And what we can do
What can we do
Bikes
Scooters are what we are
Starting now
Also you know if there's other
Foremost
Transportation that's also solving this more efficiently and more affordable
Made with local
The local space
What does you guys or like OfferUp
Local Commerce
It just seems a lot of things that can be done
Overtime having stuff
Deliver to you locally have
Pay for
And in a mobile home
Escort service
Make a lot of sense
So
I think you guys are at a cusp
Doing something
Quite interesting
Starting with the transportation space for this lawn mower roof
Of course yeah we see the value and also we're open for partnership
So I think
Having Punisher of not just like
Independent variable other
Local LDS today's service
Now that you've been running
The business for awhile now
Has your vision of what the company could be evolve
How has it beaten or Master expectations when you started out as a surprise
Yeah is a good question I would say
Surprising but also expect
When we first started
We know that
This area is
This is
Nadja spend all industry but also potentially trillion-dollar
Because we're touching people
You know most
Frequent
Highest frequency in Wales
Getting around
If you think about
The way that you get around everyday right counting all of the walking
Acid
I mean the territory that we are tapping into is
Possibly 80%
Your daddy
Tips including walking
That's exciting we know it's going to be big
And we know
The solution that we provide
Is
Something
The current alternatives or not
It works
You know
Providing as your motivation
Way to two
That's what people to get around so we're pretty
Confident about our products
In the market
And also we're proud of the team
Also putting all this together I would say things I expected
Going badly
Fast
Somewhat surprising to me.
The cities
Are also embracing this a lot fast
Some of the Technology Innovation
Hit the market
Let me talk to the cities
All cities little respect are skeptical
But primarily around
How does a 3D carousel
Our problem right
So we act differently
Bike-sharing versus
Scooter sharing bikes
Yeah it's definitely part 2
Different so bike sure is
A familiar area
Mercedes they know how it's working
Just we just need you to educate educate them
How dockless bikes
Ogden that how is it working how can we do today
Does some of the other players
In this industry
What scooter is brand new
So it requires little more education but I think
Reputation of managing this while it's important
That's why that we we spent a lot of time and effort
What was the city's making sure the operation sensing
Cachet
So that we can
You don't surf
When was it is
Joshua Project thank you notes
Have the
The ravenous in the data.
Bump city is
A lot better
And we thought I think they're welcoming
Anything does reducing congest
Dancing Dan
Reducing Diablo
That's surprisingly
Timeout
Here in San Francisco we've seen a lot of
Changes
With regards to
Policies
What do you think
Wait weekend
Expect golang
I'm bored
Especially with regards
Two scooters
Some Cisco is working on
A permitting program
We are we're closing with
Looking West
At the city
We don't know the exact time what we've heard so far as
Anytime
August
We are
Australians
Continuously work with the city to make that happen
ASAP because
San Cisco al-taweel launch
About three or four months ago right so it's
Very rapidly
Became
One of the very best
Big Market
All we've seen huge adoption is people love it and then
Also
The behavior
UR parking
Right OS generally very positive
We we've seen weight loss
You know vandalism and Dad
Car parking issue
I'm liking some Cisco we've done almost a hundred
We've had almost a hundred
Thousand users
Within just
Llcu
Weak spot amazing given only has
200000 people
Fs17 salt
Population
You will Rick and Morty but we really working hard
To get back to some
Summer in the city seems to be more open
San Diego San Diego
What are some of the general pattern
That exists
With the cities. How much
More open
It's hard to generalize
I would say it so it's really city-by-city
And sometimes this time
From time to time
Appraisal
Portfolio sample Seattle when we talk to it
The city
Initial reaction was
To push back
Hey
We like this program we think this
Husband can be really powerful.
Best way to little bit because we just had the
Get off a lot
Dog base program
Want to figure out what's that
And now we wait for about
2 months and then continue to work with the city charge
How to convince time
You know how we can do things
And all of a sudden
Open it up I think the city also are
They have the incentive
To look for better options
To solve the problem
So that's one
Extreme case Raise Hell push back
Making us feel like always going to take forever but event
Turn turn out to be
Goodbye quickly
Some of the markets are generally very openly
Like Dallas and San Diego
They don't have
A cap
And also the one I chose
You know that's it now and I'll see how it goes
Without signing a lot of limitation I think if I if there's one thing that we can
Generalize
This pattern I think
They all come from.
Southern part of the country
Is Walnut a lot of tourist
Baltimore traffic traffic and then they just eager to find a way
On a personal level what is it like to build an American company in the rug relatively regulated sector
As a first generation
10 pennies
Interesting question
It's definitely not easy but
But also
I think to me is finding that
Sweet spot right so I think
Not many things.
That's good for me or fit as a good fit for me
One thing I really like what hands has measured
House is about 12
Stay behind the scenes
Particular industry
I'm so proud that I
Can serve as a bridge between us and China
Empower to
Technology in Prada West
Supply chain Hardware capabilities are we have in China and also you know
Couple by the knowledge
The iPad
You know by leaving in the u.s. work in the US in the past
Many years
How to customize a program
From operational perspective
Chiapas bag
To make that work
So having that place Boulder
Perspective
Fidelity
I think that's something I can offer for this business
And I think that's also a 1
Key differentiation
What's wind nausea for short eyebrows
So that's something as a founder
And first-generation Chinese founder dies
We have said repeatedly on the show
Alice podcast
Politics are local
The fusion technology Biz model idea Talon capitals very gloomy
So you are
Your knowledge of what's happening in china's bike-sharing definitely
I'll give you a call in analyzing potential the US market
And they're quite a big difference
Come to Market
As it turns out that
You know it is screen sharing is more popular in the US in an e-bike
Brother in the original pedal bike sharing
But
You guys made a lot of changes
In localization to make that work in US
As you expand to Europe and
Other regions Beyond us
What are the things you look out for
And how do you make sure that you can continue to localize
2 needs of local consumers inevitable
There two things I think Matt has a lot but we're thinking about International
1 is
The market
Right is it
Kind of similar to
The US market
All intensive the
Social economics
And then the waiting list
Hey and then
Enchanted
Costco open
Open minded
Bob adoption around by Sharon Den
If there is a room I think
That's a good fit for us that's why we're thinking about Europe
And some of the
Which we can add more value
Yo by leveraging what we've learned in US
Around Market
And then the other thing is really about
The chi Trice out
One thing that we
Things that we do right
Or I think we position relatively well
It. Will you set up a local team
In the US and also in any Market
And we trust
The local team we give them a lot of autonomy by
Dual
Enabling dumb
Our Essential Knowledge
Enable with the local
P.m.
And local hires
How to make the right decision
Was cuz we just
We can't understand everything
I think you know
Making sure that we mobilize the team
I'll remote remotely with the right incentive
With the right Focus
Do you envision or City
Change
As
How we get around
Changes so like maybe scooters an device requires only infer
Do you think
Cities watch
Adapt our environment
How we're getting it
I do believe in that
And we have seen that
Nowadays
We've seen cities
Using hours
Show data
To identify where people are writing more scooters and bikes
And they are using that
To make their own infrastructure
Decision
The past is really a
Unknown area
I'll for them to
Design a bike rack
Now they have the data in that I like
Seattle we know they're working
Also for bike and scooter park
In the past
Is Regions around bike rack
Redbuds
Dockless bike sharing
School District does not require any
Station any physical location
The one provides
Flexibility
What people do
Pocket but also craisin challenge
How to
Make sure that people can follow the rules
With all them although we actually work with the city to come up with a lot of
White
Wideline
You know just
Halandia sidewalk where people work cities are in beijing Burger Limited
Capital
Put your orders
How to fight like a street parking
Whitestone
For our bikes and scooters we seen that in
South Bend Indiana Lucy night in Austin and then also Seattle
And we also spreading all this
Best pract
Does around the country
Cityside Towing.
Feel baby
And also the way that we're changing people's life now is
Philip house in the US people
When people are going out there
Can I walk
Can I drive
Or maybe sometimes can I take a Subway
If you live in
The city in New York
Christ words
Chicago
And the future we really want people to think
Bike or scooter were others
Greener transportation
First if they feel
Walking is not an option
Is that all
Starting
The starting whiskey
If you obviously have mature become
Bear success
What's the 2 years
As a fundraiser
I feel so very happy and glad
You look at sort of
Your own background
What made you
Papa Pear you
For to do well in this opportunity
And and what were some of the biggest lesson that you learn
I'm on the job
Over the last two years that you think will be
Great useful for young founders
To learn from your first time to Euros
Would love to share more so I had
I started my career as
Drysol
What's a marketing manager at
Popsicle
Back to the days
I wore I was born and brought up in China
I would thin popsicle China for about 6 years
ILauncher gator in China manage 7UP
Pensacola I think.
Consumer product training is super helpful
I got a chance yeah I got a chance to work on operation product Innovation I work on.
Average formula and then package
Innovation right so that's
How similar to
You know what the way that we innovate the bike
Designers Law School
Stephanie helped a lot
And then
And I'll take him to the US finishing my MBA
I spend a little bit of time and consulting which is great get me a lot of work
Different industry and also I spend four years as a VC before
Starting a line
W2 Express
Is definitely very rewarding Grande.
Trap me further
Flip to completely open My Verizon
I saw got a chance to look at you know so many interesting consumer-facing internet companies
Should my betta fish at night so I love
Consumer product I love
Quitting and working on Paula to touch people's life multiple times
Everyday
And
As Avicii I got a chance to work with the founders and then you know
3D
Continue.
Journey but I've never thought about
Yourself
Time ice I want to create my business PS4
The amazing people out there who want to start their business I would say two things one
Be patient rise though don't set a set a goal for yourself
Set a goal for yourself to learn to you know really I need to do this
By what time it was this way right but I think
As the founder of
Start a business
Timing and then everything that you
Accumulated in
From knowledge
Will get you a long way so
Biggest lies
But secondly I think
Keep
Keep that is open right now and then
I always think about what excites you the most
Bye
Looking broadly
What's out there you will find the
So what excites you now
Making lime the amazing
Consumer brands for the US and globally
Yai
I think it's exciting to
To start lime with Mobility Service First
Play Soul but in the future I really want people
Can see the lime as
A brand that they Trust
A brand that can help them get things done
Abandoned
Touch their life multiple times and then they feel very excited about whenever they
They talk about life
Hello.
Something that I want
How many employees do you have in the US now and how many do you have in China
Yeah we
We have a couple thousands of employees in China
We have
Close to 300
Employees around the globe
About you know one
Onforce
Are in China
But we're expanding very fast where
What hiring
Across the globe
Text to support alipay International expansion
Product Innovation engineering work
Camila oceanship operation super excited
A lot of our listeners are
Potential employees is the
China markers really well so how can the reach out if their interests
Yeah so first I'll go download the app ride the line
Sanya bikes I just
You know the child Fallout 4
This thing may not be a good fit for you right so I think you know
I would love people to love the father in The Lobster
Problem solving
And then I think about if there's an
Any of that but we're well then will you know
Just log onto our website slime
Destiny website images
I know we have
Patio opening
Sildenafil
For adequate peep
As you know what are shows going on at 6
Because we are impressed
By the efficiency
18. Does a 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. six days a week Kentucky
What's what kind of work schedule do you guys keep
Did you notice any difference among the different
Collies in different countries
Yeah
For me I'm 24 7
Yeah so people can reach me pretty much any
Explanation for the people who work at lime
I think you're more
Night night Texas Stephanie something died
I'm super impressed by
Tocado para Zord
You know the founders
Startups in China
I think that's also something
Our team in China so doing
Without telling them to do voluntarily doing that now right and also does
The people's
Deception
In our organ the US
Seeing I was Chinese
Pallet bars working so hard
I'm still very efficient and very efficient and then generating a lot of outcomes
Because we bounce
I mean us colleagues also working
Their ass
Really really hard-working
We
I think sex is
Symbolic time I think people are
Working on something.
They're super
Excited
Everyday no matter is
No matter
If it's
Early or late riser
I think
The the philosophy behind it is
Basically
Book online azure
That's right
It has to be some kind of mission-driven
For people who want to spend the most time into an enjoying
We also notice I'd there
Some of the other
Chinese bike sharing company
That's come to the US early
Like mobile
Seems to
Run into some issues
Shuffle has said they will pull out
In the in the US
From your perspective what are the things that they have done
Right and what are the areas that could have done better
18.20
Yeah hopefully mobike we went other company while we respect them as well as
I think you know both companies have
I've done tremendous
Great works
Around the globe right especially in China
You know they pioneered industry
Something that inspired us
Start a business
Snus
And
Also the way it ended the speed that they're executing is really fast
A few things I think it's being
Quite challenging put down also we try to avoid
Some of the
Pitbull
What's the weather like
Number one thing having the local Focus
And then the local team really focusing on the market
Aetna provider support
For the local market tool
Either way
It's that simple
What's the number one thing
And immature I think really you finding the right fit
Or expanding globally
No I think
Is that all
Assuming
Everything will work
Similarly as it is in China maybe 211 movie
Research and Dan Hyland
Small-scale razel sometimes
It's okay to start
Yep that's what we've done
The first one
Come up with
Bikes
When are the first one to launch a bike
When are the first one to do
Scooter
But we took
Of course once we'd
That's why so funny
Eunos
Think through everything
Thanks for the most important things
And Dad
Status
You don't have to be the first
As you know when investing Hello by cazwell
In
The China now that they came from behind
Now the number one so execution is much more more more important
When does rush tomorrow
The marathon
So we're going to the last part of the
Podcast vs. Rauner quickfire
Questions for Tuesday the 1st
That comes to your mind the first one is who the entrepreneurial admire the most and why
Steve Jobs
Grades
Innovator
Has
A Very Brady
Kind of unique and extreme level of
Prada
Perfection
Grady jobs
What's something you read recently that you recommend
I don't have much time to read but
There's a bug Mei always like
You know from
From good to
Great
I was reading the Chinese version
That's a good book and I think is
Always getting
Buy a lot of.
The things
What do you do for fun
What are used to do for fun I used to
I used to
Oh wow the professionally I talk to the founders a lot right side
As a Visa really enjoy me I mean it. Whenever I talk to DS Dallas and then I just love to
The passion download talking to the
Found it
I like you alot yeah thank you and
I used to play golf and I used to play soccer but now
These are all the time-consuming so I say that so
Now I will say you know in my
Spare time I do
You know I was some drama just to get myself going to relax
And then Budgetel
The Chinese Bob American Drama Korean drama
Running you know
Once once in awhile I think it's too important to Cuba
Kobe Bryant is a famous saying that you know
I got the kids up for the morning
In Twain's 20 years
Triangle
I want the hard work that is make another sacrifice
But he says
Ice cream
Yep that's something he enjoys
How do you feel how do you have Raffi about what you do
Yeah
I said speak about Brad buy things
He probably feel the same
I think it's
Movie about finding
Your passion and then finding the things that you can add value
End
Sometimes it's just really one or two things in your life
Riesel
Yeah they can be Hughes
That can be super super meaning for that
Your wedding knot
You're putting money right
Were you you're waiting to bring you our time and even you are
Is is one of the opportunity that I feel super excited and then
I feel that I can evaluate
Give me future
Yep
Well Toby thank you so much for your time and we can't wait to see where land will go next
Thank you so much
7989 Blanco
Listening to this episode
I-96 by the weight we also produces weekly email newsletter English also called 9 + 6
Hotels around up of the week's most important happenings in Tech in China subscribers some photos for this
Informative and fun to read the new said also features original content and Analysis from Zara
Subscribe at nine 6. GG bc.com
Did Venture Capital firm based in Silicon Valley
Shanghai and Beijing with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past 18 years from seed
Capri IPO 3.8 billion dollars in capital under management across state funds GTA V invest
Globally minded on foreigners in consumer new retail social internet Enterprise cloud and
In Frontier Tech TV has in Boston over 290 companies with more than 45 companies.
Valued at over a billion dollars for Villa companies include Airbnb Alibaba C trip
Didi chuxing Thermo hashicorp hollowbite cows keep Slack
Square Hotel wish soundtrue white white and others find out more at
Qvc.com we also highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat group as La China where we regular
Share insights events and job opportunities related to attack and try to join these groups at 9
TxDOT ggv c.com community
Sumter will talk it is a biweekly show that it's real with Thunders about the challenges that Founders and so
Startup executive space
And also how they have grown from Top experience it shows hosted by my fellow managing partner at EDB capital
Glenn Solomon office again on ultrasound versus boss
House episodes of the show include Stewart Butterfield from slack Sarah Friar from square and Netflix
Live from Airbnb you can take a listen by searching founder real talk and any podcast app
On this podcast or would like to recommend the gas please email us at 996 at Gigi bc.com