Hi there welcome
To the 9th at 6 podcast brought to you by tgb capital on the show interview movers and shakers of China
When is tech industry as well as Tech leaders who have a us China
Cross-border perspective on Stone, managing partner at ggv Capital and I've been working at startup
Invest in them in both the US and China for the past 20 years my name is
I meant investment analyst RGB capital and a former journalist
Why is the show called 96 Chinese Founders have organically it
Adopted that is 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
Intensity Drive in speed
Of Chinese internet companies many of which are moving faster that even their American counterparts
On the show today we have none other than Tony fadell
Who needs no introduction
But just for the sake of formality
Tony is the inventor of the iPod
Co-inventor of the iPhone
Founder and former CEO of Nest the company that pioneered The Internet of Things
And currently the principal at Future shape
And investment and advisory firm coaching deep Tech startups
Tony was the SVP of
Apple's iPod Division and led the team that created the first 18 generations of the iPod
And the first three generations of the iPhone
Throughout his career Tony has authored more than 300 patents
It may 2016
Time named The Nest learning thermostat the iPod and the iPhone
S3 of the 50 most influential gadgets of all time
Today has been a longtime friend of gdb
It'll probably Jenny
What we have is guest house
I Michelle today
Welcome to the show Tony
And
Great it's great to be here
It's great to see you all here in in Beijing welcome to Beijing
Thank you
Wonderful
So you have been a prolific coach and investors since you left us in 2016 could you share with us what excites
Do these days
Well I think
You know
The first thing that's exciting is that Innovations happening everywhere
You know there's always been great ideas all around the world
But
After really the
IPhone in and smartphone Revolution happen
We unlock the DNA test for people around the world to to make revolutionary technology
Easter open source through Communications Network
Master the internet
And now you can see innovation
And and creation of new
Businesses new technologies new product
All around the world
So to me it's
Engaging the entire global
Set of brains
And not just ones in Silicon Valley or in the east coast of the US but literally the whole world can now innovate
Incredible World Class levels
And to me that's really exciting because that means we can get to
Solve big problems fast
Which is really
Are there any particular parts of the world that you're especially excited about
Well I'm definitely excited
By what I've seen in China
Since
You know coming I started coming here in
With the very first time with the iPod
And then
And seeing how much it's changed
This is the first time I've been back in about 5 years
And to see how much
You know
Not just
You know copycatting in a lot of ways that you thought
But it's literally innovating in all new ways that we've never seen before and and
Because
You know I think of
First-mover advantages
I'll all the time when I when I invest
But I also think of last mover advantage
Truck right and if you think about China when you didn't have credit cards and there wasn't a lot of consumer credit and there was wasn't a lot
I have a lot of things here
And you get to use the best
Technology
And actually make it yourself
And create things that the world has never seen before
That's really exciting
Because we're not just taking old systems and innovate
For creating new things and new species of fish
Things that have never been seen
So Jennie you've known Tony for a long time could you talk about how you first met
Well yeah I still remember Non-24 about 5 years and she probably 5 years exactly
To this day
But then pants and I were attending a party in the valley at the Venice house
And I was
The first question that I ask entrepreneurs
Weather entrepreneur time it would be who's the coolest guy who's the coolest guy in the room that I got to know
Just in case I have feel the been sitting next to me Xeo off Evan oil and then on my right was Aaron Levy
PO box and the opposite to the guy across the table for me
Can you play back then is that while you know he has a new company and you cool products you should just get to know him now
And so that's how we met and went out to Tony and he was busy introducing his cool Nest protect
But I that time that was about to be launched
Oh that's how we met and I think also that was just
Hit it off
It's always great to buy entrepreneurs whom you can talk talk about
Cool can you know if you lie
Give me the straight by this is. This is not good this thing is
Not real
Idol with always kept in touch and it's it's been a very interesting and a very engaging interaction
We've invested a lot of things together
Can we talk all the time about running boards together
So it's really great and fun to see how things have developed over the last 5 years
But you know when we met we instantly hit it off as you said you know
No BS
You tell it like it is I tell it like it is
And when you speak it when you meet people like that regardless of wherever they're at
You just
Resonate with them you like okay this is someone I can get along with that was it was clear after our first
Do you know one or two conversations is like
Okay
We're going to get to know each other a lot more and we've actually talked a lot
And she's very busy hours
We talked a lot Hans as well we talked many times
And continue to find great entrepreneurs to back around the world
The hunt tonight
After that first meeting I came in second meeting to go pay a visit to NASA and 22
Trying to see if we can invest in that
We were too late later than you
And so you know we would love to find more ways to work together as partners this time
Not just you know you best entrepreneurs
So Tony you have close to 250
Investments now
Most of them since being attacked at least in the US and Europe
What do you look for when you invest in founders
And what excite you
Well
You know
Tumi
You know there's lots of money out there
And there's a lot of entrepreneurs doing a lot of
Interesting things
But for me
What I want to be able to do
Is not just
Make money
My job is not to make money I'm not investing other
People's money
I'm investing my time
More so than money
And what I want to do is I want to really be able to
Help entrepreneurs who are doing very hard things
Which are usually in deep technology
Things that don't have revenues for a while
But take many years to develop
Before they can become really disruptive in an Indus
Help those entrepreneurs and Mentor them
With not just myself but our team
To help them get their dream to become reality to affect the world as fast as possible
For the most amount of good
So for me
I was
A young entrepreneur when I went to Silicon Valley in 1991 and Beyond and I had lots of people who helped
Helped me cuz they saw something in me and they said I want to help this kid and it wasn't always about money
And so now that I'm older you know almost you know 25 Going on 30 years later since going to Silicon Valley in the fur
First place
Now I think it's my time
To be able to do what other people did for me
And help those Innovations grow and now they we can do them
A lot of places and do many more meaningful things that we
We could have 30 years
So for me that's what
So exciting and it's not just about
Consumer Hardware
Building you know the next iPod or something or nest
It's really about
Technology be applied to new spaces
The things that
We know when we created our last 30 years
Is not about you can innovate that shirt
But it's about bringing that and that democratization of those those Technologies
To agriculture
To food
Two medicine
Ted Automotive
If we look at it there's so many things that now need to be
Either revolutionized by the software and Hardware evolution
Or they need to actually
Be created new things that we've never seen before to be created
That's what's interesting to me
Because I don't want to keep doing the same thing you know I left Apple because after
18 Generations the iPod or whatever
The 19th one you know it's pretty pretty predictable I think you can pretty much predict what the next cell phone waves
Smartphone always going to look like or the one after that
That's not what you want to do is be on The Cutting Edge
Create something that's totally changing
Hopefully like I've been able to do
In my career now do it with
200 other companies in different things that I don't know anything about
And that's what the best thing is you going to do something
You don't know anything about to come fresh dive you go
Why don't they do it that way this is the way we've always done it so it's never going to change has come and go
That doesn't make much sense what's the rethinking
That's what's fun
Is rethinking
Old Industries
I was thinking of new things no one's ever thought of
To me that keeps me young
And I get to work with lots of young people
Nn
Hopefully help them Reach their dream
So how do you tell if a team
Science
Versus someone who actually have a chance to
Grow and learn evolve into something truly revolutionary
Hansa grade question
You asked them what their mission
You ask them what they're really trying to do if they're trying to just trying to find more money to continue the researching from car
College from University
It's very clear it's like all I just want to do this and they don't think about the business implications they don't
They just want to keep having fun doing what they're doing
When they say
I have this technology and it can change the world in these dramatic areas
And then they can state
Maybe not the right but I some kind of business
Is there some kind of Market case
And they're trying to
Get other people to help them understand and build a business
That's when you know it's something
Interesting
You know
We see a lot of great demos and nothing wrong with robotics you know when those cool AI robots
Running around but then I keep saying
What meat are we feeling what are we actually really
Fixing
Right
You can create and that's fun
But what are you doing
White in 10 years when you wake up
What
Are you going to have on your resume to show that you've done some build something great
And all the people on your team to do something great and not something great is
Not just another product or another demo
But a business
Something that will last beyond
Your time at the camp
Right so if I think about it
My time at Apple
It still has the iPhone
And I feel relieved that
With something we are building that really was important and it still continues to
Nest continues to go on and create new products
And we created a culture in a business
To create more products
That's the kind of thing you want to talk to an entrepreneur about
Not just this one idea and getting it to the market
What is their big vision
Where does it need to go in even if they don't know what it is they have to have like
Wow I want to change the world in this way for the right reasons for these kind of business reasons
Make sure it's sustainable
It's not just
Bring the technology to the world
I also think a large part of being a successful entrepreneur is solving nearby problem in the right time
So the timing is also important so what do you consider to be at the right problem at this current age
Well timing is every
Sometimes a failure is based on execution that other failures are based on time
You always want to be a little bit sooner
Bennett needs to be
In the nest was just a little bit
Too soon
But it worked out
Right it was just a little bit cutting everybody's doing
Right now each market something in China that's a great idea that might not be a great idea in North America
May not be a great idea in
Europe
So you have to think about timing
Not Justa
What people are talking about in
The Press
But what are customer saying that
Just because you have a great idea
And you're not
Close enough to the market
Need
And it'll take a really big gap or leap
For them to understand what it is
If it takes more than
2 minutes to sell your idea
You're probably not
Doing a good job either explaining it or you're too far Advanced from where they're thinking
Redemptive
Buyer purchase
Sitting somewhere
So I think about you know my time at General Magic
General Magic
Most people don't know what it is but we are basically creating the iPhone
In 1991 to 1994
We had the best team in the best ever we had downloadable apps
We hadn't
Games we had an email Wireless email me at everything
That's what used today it took us 15 years to get there any of the smartest people
And so we were a total failure we obviously
It showed up 15 years
Later
But we had the right idea
So
What is going on here in China
And when I look at startups and thinking about the timing
There's things that the market needs now
And things that'll get funded
And there's something that usually
Something pressing for like made in China 2025
If you're doing something that needs to be done right now you're probably not innovatively
You need to be building something that is going to be a hit
In 45 years
When the market wakes up
Because that means you're starting before anyone elses
But you can't be so close
That
Everyone else is doing it or it's pretty simple. Implement
But you also can't be 10 years out
Because then business isn't happening
Do you have to really be in if you're doing anything important I always say is it takes 10 years or
To see full
Fruition
You know to come to full
Ripeness in a way right
10 years are really realize a business
A product
A good product
Is usually 3
4 years
Write good businesses
And so
You should always be thinking in those kinds of her eyes
Obviously you want to ship something in a year or year-and-a-half
Something from the time you start
It was that kind of Windows I see
In business but you got to make sure
That what you're pitching
Close enough
To what the need is or Annie that you discovered that they didn't know they need
So that they can convert or they'll actually put their
Signature on a contra
In some way or puts
Portfolio what will be there
Top three
Products that fit that description.
It could be something
Quite game-changing
It's stupid early if was time but is closed
Well I think I really break up we're starting to see a breakout almost happening an impossible foe
Impossible Foods is
Is basically meat without a Col Rite Aid or so it's a burger that's
Vegetable based
But it has
Almost all the same or Better Properties than regular meat
Right
There's a lack of protein in the world
We are unsustainably farming
Cows and cattle today and it's killing the planet is killing us it's a totally inefficient
And we're just at the point where
Meat eaters Argo
I'll actually try that and they like it and it's not
Crazy GMO technology but it's right on the verge
And it's going
Multi
Continent
Right
Suzhou Chapel
What is it Underground
We've been working on it and you can have the team has
I've been working with them for a while
The teams are working on
6 years now and we're finally there and it's going to be in total
Brightness as a full business in in the next
Two to three years because it'll be everywhere
It's taking a long time so that's
Kind of I think hopefully an example of what I you know
What I mean
Let's see another one
I think transfer
Asportation
Is a big one so if you look
At
You know we've been talked about self Drive
We all want it to happen all understand this
Site he's not ready for
The technology
Everybody's been saying it's coming in 2019
20/20
You know we have automaker saying we have full self-driving or we're going to have a software upgrade for full self-driving
No we're not
The stuff isn't ready
It's not even nearly ready
I think
Just like
People
We have to learn to
Crawl
Before we walk
How to walk
Before we were
And you know and run before we Sprint
Cars are going to be the same way
And it's not just the tip
Cars are all about
You know different speeds in different location
At different times of day on
Under different Environmental
We are going to do the same thing
To think we're going to all of a sudden making a highway vehicle that's going to work
Tremendously well in cities
No today we have some
Self-driving capability
On highways in very controlled
Digital situation
If we look at countries around the world
There are driving modalities that are
Very analog not digital the US for the most part 2 digital transportation
Emerging Markets Emerging Markets
China is in between cities that are digital and there's other ones that
To think that we're going to be able to address all of this in version 1.0 or even 5.0
Actually insane
And I eat
When I see people investing
Like craziness is over going to have
Self-driving taxis
They're going to be the worst taxis in the world
You're not going to want them
They're nice
Mobility stuff with the bikes in the scooters in
And other transportation
But self-driving
I like self-driving in
Campuses
I'm slow speeds where you can you know where you want to do this
Highly controlled it's highly digital
It only has to work under certain environment to still at the steering wheel in a thing so someone has to get in to keep it running during the day
We're going to have those kinds of on-ramp
Text for people to say that
It's going to be autonomous driving
In 3 years
We all have a dip
We all have different expectations
It's all marketing
All kind of crazy
It's not
What realities
Just like
The iPhone we had it in 1994 with General Magic
People that understand the need we understand
But the technology is not right
Basically we don't we don't have the technology
The all the and the regulations and all the other things
That is much too early
Now that's a you shouldn't invest
No
But you have to invest smart
And you have to understand what can be deployed when
And not think that
You know now we're talkin about
People are talking about
Fleet Mobility Management Solutions software solution for autonomous vehicles
I'm like
Oh my God that's going to be 20-30 by the time we need 2027 or something like that
We can't even make a car
An Eevee based car that runs won't rent long-range enough without all the
All the computers and they're still already too expensive
So much to go
So that's an example of something that happened today
If you smartly to find it yes it will happen
But the way it's being defined and being built
It's so far out there
That we all want it cuz it's cool science fiction My Name happened
It's on Mark it's all driven by
Marketing and shareholders and
In and people think they're going to make a ton of money right now
And they're just
You know they're chasing a dollar they don't understand
All the social implications governmental up
And the technologic
How about vertigo indoor farming
Another thing that I think is
Very interesting
But you have to look at the biz
You have to go back and go
How much
Is it costing
To produce these vets
For these fruits
In which location what are the alternative
Sounds sexy and it's interesting for a marketing thing
But when you come down to the business aspects
You know some of these vertical
1000 containers
It's cuz everyone's trying one
Right I always said that
If we put anything on Indiegogo or anything
You can sell
Between 10000 and 100000 of anything
To anyone cuz there's enough early adopter
But they're just demoing
To say it's going to truly be a business
We're so far away from that
Now do we have to try absolutely
But the valuations a lot of these things are getting well out of hand
And they just seem cool and it was like that sounds cool
But
The reality is we have to look at the egg
Economics
Because
It's not going to be carbon-based because we're going to be getting rid of you know Logistics services and
There's all these other elements that have to happen to incentivize to make these things more
And they're not today
And
It's you have to really look at the numbers has anyone about all kinds of certain things
But I always go back to not the sales numbers but the real hard unit economics
You understand what are we really solving
What are you betting on
If you can't get the economics right
Regardless of the kids you can't scale
Nnnn I always look at the economics from a scale point of view
Not just like it's going to be hard really making a thousand of them so it's really expensive so we'll never get to 100,000 likes
Solar panels
4 years
From the 70s but it's finally taking off
In the last 10 years
Right
Because everyone's like we'll never scale I'm not worried about scale anymore
If we figure out the unaka economics
China or another he's going to go off and figure out how to make
Custom the cost out happens so much more quickly
What's the what's the real fundamental reason why something should exist
Look at that
Look at those.
Which of the following in indoor vertical farming that could be different
Wish I was talking to you about that later
Okay I can't wait to hear more
Maybe Switching gears a little bit so it's when you've been a very successful entrepreneurs for 25 years and Los Angeles McKinney
How do you strike
The right balance
Between you know
Taking on the role of a coach
To the founder of the say Hey you know this is something
Getting rid of the issues within that I don't know David is trying to catch the guy to get it in the unit
Well you know I've
I and you probably seen it.
You know sometimes you have to bite your tongue
The first time just like you can ask them questions
Nuna
You can either see in some entrepreneurs use like
Why did you do it that way
Did you ever consider this
Or did you ever think of that
And neither
Do you know kind of a bit flips in their brain
And literally within hours or days a week
Or it's like
Next month
9 months a year later it still hasn't like
Sunken
I have all the ideas or anything
But at least coming back to you
With a
I thought about that and here's why I don't think it's going to work
Right
Or
You know or we rule it out right then and there like yeah I already thought about it
Yeah that's not going to work
So you can really understand in and I like to do that in the process of when
We're thinking about making the investment
And challenging their to see if they're mensurable sure at the time of the investment
Roll your roll the dice then and you have no Leverage
In a way
And so you always want to have that kind of
Too many times I
Because I'm not worried about missing the next deal
This is about fun and Indian meetings where it's about working with great people who really want to work together
Write a lot of
Investors are like they want to have their best fit
Put forward they want to say I'm entrepreneur friendly and I'm not going to challenge
To a certain extent
For me I gota
180 degrees out
I challenge you from day one I'll send him a hundred questions.
And I want to see how far until a break
Not that I'm trying to like but it's there I want to see how far they're going to go and how deep and how fast they're going to respond
Detailed response
Because that's going to tell you what their normal
Kind of way they think about problems or how they communicate or whatever
And if they can do that
Then it's a great litmus test for what I think's going to happen over time
I never thought about that
No we haven't gotten there
As opposed to someone who always says oh yeah we thought about that or
Yeah we're going to do that too
They just have to say no we didn't think about
And Hugo okay
I know that they're real because they said
Right exactly
So yeah so it's that kind of thing
So do you get moments where you feel like this problem is
Attractive enough that
You want to do it yourself
Nephew
There a few moments
You know from me
Did everyone that's ever going to get back in the game one day you're going to go back
I was going to get back to it and Nest was something bad
I thought of
And I couldn't let it go it took nine months
For me
To find leak
To doing
Cuz
I had to look at it from every angle
Cuz I really wanted it to be right
I had been at that point
Over 20 years
Of
You know multiple startups that
Failed or were marginally successful
You nope
Years and years at Apple running like crazy
So to throw yourself into it again when you didn't have to you already financially on lsf
To throw yourself into it you have to make sure all the variables there and let you know
You don't not that I'm risk-averse
But I like to risk mitigation
But make sure I really understand what the real
Opportunities but what are the real risks
Before diving into
And so when I look at these other businesses
I have different calculus I use for when I'm going to be the CEO
Verses when other people are the CEO and I think I can help them
And investing get them around certain obstacles cuz I've been there before and I think it's a good business
But is it something good enough that I would want to
You know
Tear myself away from my family and all I said since I already had been doing it for
I effectively now
25 to 30 years depending on how you count
So it's very hard for me to want to engage and say how I wish I could do that cuz I know how
End
I have to tell you it's a Young Person's game
The real you have to be in your 30s you know 20 year olds
Videos there are some of them but they're usually not successful
Sometimes I get lucky but most of time it's in your mid-30s
Early forties is where you're really sick
So you really figured out you failed enough times you've learned
Right
And so
I'm not in that category
You know that's where I can come back to Mentor so so my calculus for me to do something is very different
So I
So when I see something I can oh my God
If I was 30 again would I be there
Cuz I get to go have a fun ride with that entrepreneur
And helping them
With their board and their investors everything else I get to be in a list
I can have a lot of fun
And and I get to be young again at the same time I get to help them
And I get to almost be CEO without being CEO
Cemeteries wife Kitty and I like
BBC
You know it's some point everyone has a different reason for when they going to get involved with the risk level you knowing
I'd much rather take my time and help 200 on sugar
Rights and then just one company with a lot of people but
It's tough
You know how it is
You know I always would love to go back to college or High School inside
YouTube
OK Google
Exactly
Self do you your face in Paris is traveling through Asia
When you see go to different markets
What are the differences
I'm similarities among the founders you choose to back
Frosty geography
In what kind of lens do you use to look at investment
Indifferent geography
Oh yeah okay
Well I think
Looking at the investment is very different than looking at the
Human nature that I found throughout all our travel
Is the same everywhere
Everybody wants to care for their families everybody cares about their
Communities
For the mall on their governments are
Even care about themselves
Human nature is the same
So entrepreneurs it's very easy to go and find entrepreneurial Talent
That's very similar
They have their mission-based they work hard there
They're proactive that you know they can communicate well and you can find that on every Khan
When it comes to Investments
A very different calculus
And how you
Choose to invest
Na
Company
China
Versus the US
Versus Europe
Because each of them are a different
Stages
You know
One thing we learned way back when
During
During the time
Apple we did the iPod
Right in the
An apple wasn't doing well it's time and iPod came out
And it was
A
Critical in someone
Success in the first year 2 years
But it was all Apple Focus so you can only have a Mac
Brighten an iPod
It said use an iPod
So what you had to do was
We could only marketed to more or less you do you SRT
Little bit of Japan nobody was really in Europe using Apple Mac
Work that we modified in all that
And by your three we made it work with a piece
So
When we took it to Europe
Because I could work with a PC and we took it to the rest of the world's people are starting all I want
That first time we hit the European Shores
Or the Asian Shores
With it
We use the marketing as if
We were still Marketing in the US after 3 years
We forgot that the markets themselves
Didn't really know what an iPod was they really didn't know what 10,000 songs in your pocket but they didn't know all the
So the first 6 months when we launched it in these other countries
We didn't Taylor the marketing
To understand the market
We tailored it based on what we've done in the US in copy
We had to bring those people up to
It's a what is this long way of saying you know
What it is
You got to understand the Dynamics of each mark
To understand it
Investment is really make
In the US
You know
You had to
Day
I'm fundamentally deep.
And that detective is coming out of research institutions
It's it's
That's where I like to invest
It's not about social mobile that's over now there's certain things that are old
Adipex really hot
In Europe
Deepak is just starting
It's mostly
Kind of the US
223 years ago
You know business process Automation and and alternative business models and that's
An innovating
In that Mark
In China Chinese much more about
You know
Scale
It's not about the technology
Azide
But it's about taking something where you have a good
Market that you figured out that unit economics you figured out it
And pressing the button to get the capital and scaling it up to billions of people
Right
And so it's all about execution
It's all about
Customer acquisition cost about how do you submit vat
Kind of thing
Do you have to look under that
At some point
That calculus is going to move to the US again
Right
And then it's going to move to the you know to Europe
So these things are always out of phase each of these regions are out of phase
If you look at Southeast Asia
Very different than all of those again
So
Entrepreneurs
Easy to determine
Weather option or has a business that investable and then makes a lot of sense
Is very
Locally driven and you need to have great partner
In each of those areas to help you do the do
Due diligence to under
Stand it
And so
You know and it's great to learn about these things
It's hard to sometimes pull the trigger when
You don't really have all the data
To make the investor
And so you like the way you would is if
You are investing in the US
10 years or 20 years and that's what's so great about ggv is that
Are you guys been here
And now you're going even further into other mark
Ripe
And investing ahead of the Curve
Bright and learning that's
Just like you should be
Creating startups
Ahead of the Curve
Right and that's
Investment is all about seeing the next Horizon entrepreneurs are all about seeing the next Horizon
And then finding those things
And emailing it
And so it really takes people on the ground
Great understanding
Cuz you just can't cook
Key cutter and copy
From Play Store
It doesn't work that way
I know all of these NBC firms try to globalize when it was way too early to do so
I have to go to be treated
I think 440g for us
Play friends with benefit from the
Country simplification of iPhones and Android phone
When you have some of the smartphone penetration in a lot of markets
Easier to scale the business model has worked
In one country
Other
Especially in
Emerging Markets versus the high degree of organization and Rising middle class
It is Market pantry
Oh absolutely. There's a lot of similarities you can do
And now that we ate like
Finally there's 4G in India you're finally there's 40 everywhere and it's cheap enough
And it's cheap enough right and so
And then you have to look at you know the arpu
And figure out what is really the discretionary Capital that each of these families has and where
Deployed or for that matter the it budgets for each of these
They all everybody around the world has to digital
Right
I'm Families 2
The question is is
What's the cycle where are they
Where's the acceptance just like when I was coming back to the iPod
You got it just the timing is critical in each of the
When everybody just says that they can move their model their business model from one continent
To the next really easily
You know that's right and that's the kind of the entrepreneur who you know sometimes they need to be mentored
And other times they just say that because they're selling it trying to prop up there you know there
Valuation
And I'm like forget it just like
Smattering a on every single present form of social
Mobile or whatever is Uber of
Yeah you know I'm the aif leads like no
Sorry Akon
Fit right
Allege that she got to be much more
The thoughtful.
Do you think would be entrepreneurship first train at big companies or should I jump straight into entrepreneurship
You yourself has been awesome big companies
Yeah I have some real Lessons Learned on that
If you're going to be a great entrepreneur
You better know what sales and marketing is not just what engineering is or operations are fine
You need to know
Pretty well
What each
Function does and how they kind of in a relay
At a massive company Corporation are you going to learn that
No way
You're going to be a cog in the machine
At a startup
A five people are 10 people are going to know that
Absolutely not
What I'm
What I'm 4 is so small
800 Polaris 850 person startup
Will you can go in in the first two years
You can watch it grow what it means to
What kind of stress goes on in the environment when they're like growing a 20 people per quarter 10 people per quarter
When you can go and have lunch with a marketing person and learn what they're talking about Earth science
And you can start to get
Some sense if I could not learn this stuff in school no bitoku
Right you're not going to tell you about the failures going to hear about the successes and the real big failures and then
The knot wanted Dynamic and it's really happening in case study
You got to be there you got to learn
You got to learn by doing
And Learn by doing means learn by doing with others
Who are knowledgeable and experienced with a good enough team
If you just
Got to school
And this is what happened to me I start my own company
I didn't know what I didn't know
Right and that's what was so great about me going to General magic I got to see everything
Wasn't
I wasn't maybe that's awful is best
But that's what I was number 30 at this company
But we grew. 200 in the very short. Time you got to meet and learn
Become part of
Mini
Piece of the organization
Industrial pH
You know I can't when everyone says I PhD
It's not a PhD in art
Frontier realism
It's not a ph meter
It's a very near thing
That doesn't help you
Create a company
You got to really be able to speak the language of all these different divisions in different types of
Some people know how to
No enough when you need something
Not that you know who the best
Experienced professional Hazard how to do that
Start to understand
And you can only do that by
When working in Azusa Sears b or a c company
Das Racist
Two or three rounds of financing
Exactly small enough that you can
Tok almost everyone
But big enough. You have given functions you merge
Exactly and
And
You're going to go through some failures
If it's not going to be about maintenance mode
Oh yeah we just need to have this is like real
You know
Yeah a real fighting to try to win the market
Fix this problem or whatever and it's really
Ugly and gory
Cuz that's where you going to learn
It's fun it's bassinet
You know
So yeah so
Do not go to big company
Huge what do not go to little tiny one
Go to something there you can really
Add value but they're going to teach you probably more than you're going to be able to bring
Go to the Jacob
Yep
I remember you said before that nests would have never happened if I didn't get out of the echo chamber of Silicon Valley
So how did this happen and why did you move to Paris in 2009
Okay
What are the biggest reasons why I'm here
Here in China while I'm traveling throughout the world to Southeast Asia
Why we're living in Paris
Is that
You don't know about other people's problems
Unless
You lived
And you know a lot of people say oh yeah I can go and you know
I can from Silicon Valley or whatever else
Everything looks
Like
It's all solvable
It's absolutely not
The reason why
You start
A startup
You know
Do you know
Get created in Europe and then they got shipped over the us when the US started in
Everybody has different problems
With different needs
And different ways of being
And even though you might think o that cars the same as that car over there
There's a regulation differences Galore between the two different cars
Here in China that you know a Buick here's a Buick in the US
There's so many differences
That
You need
Be able to live there
The other thing is
You have obituary
In other words you get used to your environment
So after being in Silicon Valley for at that point 20 years
You got to see everything is the same
They're all shades of the same thing you see the same problems you see everything else
Do when you get outside that
And you go to a different place
Where
Fundamentally everything's different
It knocks you off your thing and you have to re-evaluate everything and relearn how to live and learn how other people and why did they do
Do it that way
We did it that way is it smarter
I always thought
That's the way it's always done this like a big company
That's the way we've always done if you continue to do it that way
The US political system was really smart
When mute living in France
And seeing how they elect the president
Oh my God I'm like
This is genius compared to the US
And so
When you have that kind of experience
Angular wait a second
They're smart people all around the
They may not be Market in the media might not be focused on
Mosto
Times people like
Come eat with me and move your startup near me
Cuz I know better
No no no you got to go the other way
And go meet with people because
Technologies vent democratize
Communications Bank
All the specimen democratized everyone can get access
Now it's about going to the market
And making them
Those markets
And so that's
If I wouldn't have done that I would not have seen the problems I would have continued to solve
What everybody else. Where the
What I love is you know what the other thing that happened when I was
Cuz this was in Paris in 2009
When we were there
But that went to different museums
And when your Paris
There's hundreds of Museum
And you start see a pattern
And the pattern emerges where
If you looked at Picasso
Michelangelo
Or any of the great artist
You start going wait a second
They lived in this city for a while
Then they took a bunch of a little bit of time off and they lived in this city for a while
And then they lived in that City with
I'm a different inspiration in new our new things that they were working on
And it was all about refreshing and pressing reset on your brain to get new Inspirations new ways
I'm looking at the world
To come up with new ideas and Creative Solutions or ideas
And so you're like
I'm in Paris I see this TRS they did this on my
Duh of course I got to do the same thing
Came back to build it now traveling the world
Other things
And I got some really cool things that I want to do now
Being
You know traveling in this area of the world as well as in Europe
I'm going
We got to build some of these other companies I'm trying to find Investments around that stuff because it's
I would have never seen it in Silicon Valley
Or
Frankly in Paris cuz that's
Getting worried
Any in Europe
Unless you travel to the place where they jump
For example
You know we were talking about this earlier which is if you think about Southeast Asia
Southeast Asia
Is very much like Europe
Was before
That ain't you right before the European Union
There's different currencies
People are traveling around middle class is now being established and its traveling around Commerce is
Happening within aside a block and things need to move more quickly
So what technology
What things need to be built for that region
That trading region
It's not all going to come in and out of China
Amongst themselves what needs to be built in
What's inside of that
And to make it more fluid reduce the friction
Because
I don't think given this whole
Wave up
Populist Behavior
There's going to be another EU created anytime soon
There might be trading blocs but there's not going to be a new kind of political political system put on
So given that
How are our business is going to adapt to that what business that can be started in
And that could be really
Wild an interesting to watch
And it's just
Now getting there
As you see things like
Gojak
Grab and other wood starting to go
The multiple countries
Check right
Pretty interested
DDS
So we're now sitting in Beijing end
What has surprised you or impressed you the most about your current trip to China with her overall impression of the China
Ecosystem
China
It's underestimated
I think a lot of people want to continue to
Oh
The China 15 years ago
It's the
An incredible opportunity or any credible threat depending on how you look
And
You know
I hope that
While there has to be the right Reckoning and balance between
Superpowers in the world and trading blocs and
All that stuff's got to get yourself worked out
We still need to cooperate we still need to work together
And we still need
Information to flow and
The knowledge of
All different people
Flow
Freely between each eye
Because it's really important because we live on one play
And
We cannot be hunkering down
Especially when you look at the IPC
See report from last week saying global climate change is going to affect us in 12 years none
30 years
We're going to have to be working together
And
I would rather see countries compete
To make the world better
Dental
Off each other and then we starve each other of the innovation
I know that's bae
But
China
Is an incredible opportunity for the world because it can set the standards and help
To bring scale
To the lot of these industries that are going to need it
Help us with climate
Just like we did with solar panel
Rightly or wrongly forget solar panel dumping and all the others
If people play the game right
And they play by the rules Within
And we don't have a
Global Currency meltdown because of currency War
We can help the planet go much more quickly
Together than apart
If we have
Global Currency Wars
And global trade Wars
We're going to slow down
Tremendously
The revolution we need to get to a CO2
Les
Otherwise we can lose 10 or 20 years on our way
Because we're being or sticking their head in the ground
Did US is awesome we're going to do it our way we can't do it someone planet
There's no Mars sorry
There's no moon
There's no space
We got it we got to solve it we got to solve it together and so for me China
He's going to be a
Huge win especially as more cities are developed
The rest of the world at least in the you-know-what
Some people consider the modern world China is very modern
The US and Europe
North America in Europe
There's not new city been created
Should have been created and you can use the new technology to create
And you can figure out new ways of being and do that more so than the Middle East
Write more so than Africa
Could you have all the pieces
So I hope that
The technology that's going to be created in the cities that occurred going to be model to help us get out of this because
We're going to need it
The population growth is slowing around the world but it's not selling fast enough
No not going to solve it
We're going to need experimental cities and a lot of different innovation
But his DNA to mutate enough time to find our way out of this
Which one is the best bicycle
Chinese incredible opportunity
The help
Save the world even though yes
If there do need to be reformed
But
This is where
Everyone can leave together
And not
Be divided
So I think we talked about how the world is changing
Entrepreneurship is changing is getting more global
Capital as well as getting more Global absolutely
So many interactions
It's with investors in us and Europe
In Asia as well any import advice
For folks like us
Well
The dirt
You know
Look
In the world they're good people they're bad
They're good businesses and bad breath
Good leaders
Badly
In the world of capitalism
Two same thing
At the end of the day
Entrepreneurs
Should only take money
From people they respect
From people who can add value
Not just a brand name
It's about a person to person relations
Bright
Or mentor
It's not just the firm
It's the person you're going to have on your board
It's going to be about
The
Hopefully a person you can call in the middle of night
When your
When
You're an utter panic
To get advice and that you trust and they're not going to use it as a weapon against you
That is a trusted partner
Write someone you want to go have
Lunch or dinner with that you wouldn't
Your mind having your families get together and at some point
Obviously there's always business
But at the end of the day
It's got to have a personal
Relationship because it's all about trust
And it's two ways word
You know when you get
An investment from someone they're trusting you
To return that
But you're also trusting that they're going to
Believe in you
It's not just a business right
Transact
Because
You know with all the failed
Startups out there cuz there's still going to be tons more
This is about a long-term relationship
Right and so
Even if a startup doesn't work out
There are so many entrepreneurs that I back again
Because I saw him in the tough times
Swipe right
Through the hard times
Cuz that's when you really know a person who is when weather's on the investor side or on the entrepreneur side when it's tough times
That you can push each other you're there for each other
And
You know in 20 years you going to call each other go
Remember I'm here and you know
Wouldn't when it was top you were there for me I'm there for you whatever it is
No matter how much we read in the media and all the BS and you know social networks
You know you know taking people down everything about that relation
At the end of the day not what the media says or what
The latest thing on Twitter
And so
The reason why I'm successful is because of the relationship that hope I've invested in until this is not about trains
What about relations
And so and it's a two-way street cuz you're getting married look
Investors getting married to a
A entrepreneur if it's good and an entrepreneur is getting married to a partner not a VC firm
And a VC firm is made up of really good partners if they're really good
So yeah there's Bad actors out there and bad forms
You got to be much smarter
As an entrepreneur and you got to be much smarter than vestra to make sure
That it's not just that I'm putting my money into something cuz it's a
Oh my God it's the next next
Hottest thing
It's because you really believe it
And at the end of the day it it's not about who
Gives you the biggest pre-money valuation
Whatever you're going to see it in the terms you going to see them how fast they work together how fast they get back to you how much value they can
Any
Requires both side because an entrepreneur with too much ego
Aunt Anna Vissi who thinks that there is a new CEO you don't want that either
So
Look take capital from good Folk
Right
And only invest in
The cuz
Look
It's inevitably lot of things are going to go south it's not going to work out like we all wanted to
You know you get one in five one in 10 is a great home run
We don't hear about all the failures
But
They do happen
You got to be there for that
And
Let's just remember it's about people
And relationships not about transactions in money
So we're going to proceed to the final part of the interview which is around a rapid fire questions
Admire the most and why
Right now
The best
Visionary operator
All around
Kind of businessman
Quiet
Smart
Everything
Jeff Bezos
Jeff without a doubt
You know I watched
Two side go up to the first time I think it was in 1994
And
To see
The long-term thinking
The Abyssal long-term thinking there
You know very Chinese like
I'm glad you said it that's how we feel
The ability to keep rolling the dice and saying
I'm not going to give back
The money and buy shares back from shareholders I'm going to continue to invest in myself
That's
An amazing
And of course now he's got a huge
Responsibility to the world
To not just
You know show how business is done right
But the show how to be
Done in a socially
Conscious manner
You know is a homely face for them
Because
They can make a lot of
Great changes for the world
And in many directions
And. So I'm looking forward to
Sing the next phase of
Jeff and Mary
But what he's done in the last
20 years
Amazing
Absolutely.
Dino hats off
Undeniable
But you don't have an answer this question or if you do we'll have to
Broadcast
But all he will think that or call Elon Musk
The next Steve Jobs
What do you think about that
I think they're two totally buried if
I know I
I met and spent time with you on and it's been a lot of time
They're very good
Tulsa
We just leave it at that
Okay thanks
What's something you read recently that you would recommend
Whether it's a book or article
Well you know they're too older books
So I can some people might think they're older but they're
Absolutely
I think about them on almost a daily basis
And a third book as well
From a design purse
But
There's from Daniel Kahneman that
Thinking Fast
Consuelo
And the other one
Kasabian
That's a good book
Sapiens
Just rock my world
So those two books
It's a lot of it
Sapiens
So much about
Society
And thinking fast and so is so much about the individual and when you combine the thoughts and both of those books
And where we're going with societies where we're going with you individually and where we're going with the
Individual as a computer
You put those together and it's it's a synthesis for
Helping you
Understand the world in a better way
To help you make better decisions as a leader for where we need
To go
I'm as a society people and us
Society of people that co-evolved with
So I take
The third book
That I'd recommend in this is only from a
Seeing things in a different way
And
Seeing things
To get out your space if you can't move to go see things differently
Is a book called In Praise of Shadows
I don't know if you know it
But it's only a
60 or 70
Page Plus
And it's by a Japanese author in 19
30 poo
Wrote down all
Of his comparisons of
The old Asian Japanese world
To the more Western modernize world when things were becoming Electra
And machines lights and everything we're coming to Japan
And the difference is between them two and you can then see like oh my God there's a different way of living
And maybe the way we're living today isn't the most effective way there might be some older things are some different ways
So makes you
Rethink your surroundings
And help you tune into that
Kind of
What is it that I perpetuate
That I kind of suppress
That I need to go look at
Again and rethink of in the new light
To get your mind
In a flowing again
For Creative juices
What do you do for fun
What to do for fun
I love to bike
I love to run
Yoga
So do yoga live
Music
Without a doubt I'm going I can't I can't get enough music music music music music music music music concerts
Going a lot of cons
Now I'm watching my what's also fun now for me is no watching my kids grow
And going out surfing when I know the kids can surf better than me
I try but they're already like well past it
And so so fun for me is watching them grow
And then the other one is
In and our family grow but the other thing that's fun is
Watching the startup
And watching
You know they're all little kids
In a way I'm watching them mature and watching the leaders
Not just the entrepreneur the founder but the watching the management team
And seeing them
Go through different phase in your life
Wow
It's really amazed
So those are all fun things for me and I'm only doing the things I like
In my life
Because they're fun
Cuz I don't have to
You answer me another question which is
A lot of people who do well
Morcheeba lot in life
Are quite intense
An operator faster
Sure going to try to manage a large organization
Operative
Saudi reconcile how do you reconcile that to get every move in the right direction
Without burning a lot of them with his $0.11
Well it's a really great question but it's all relative
Right
Sometimes you can push too hard
Because that's what you want
You also have to remember that
Good decisions don't just happen
Fast sure does take some time
Analysis paralysis
Would you also can't make
Knee-jerk reactions
Based on gut
Like there is there are
There are
Backbase decisions and opinion-based
And leaders need to know the difference
Opinion-based ones should be made by a core team or one person and continued that right
And fact-based ones as long as you don't get in that now is paralysis
It should be fast and so they make a good enough decision you know and you know what the bassist was making
Undo it if the assumption
So
There's there's a
If you're working
100 hours a week
120 hours a week
No way
Look it's not going to happen it's not sustainable
That's what happen when I was in my 20s and I
I had to reboot my life because
I think Elon Musk is learning that right
Write the can't work that
It just
Do not get to make
So your organization needs to move fast
You need to
Have them you set up the main goals they set up the sub goals
And then they get back to you the tasks and the work product
You know that they're going to be in the deliverables in the timing
And then you can negotiate over there
Right and you push
And when hourly happens is is
One team says I can move this fast the other team says I can move that fast and they have to work together cuz I don't teams
Do they normally push you pull me kind of experience as long as you have it laid out
See you but you have to agree on what the parameters are in
And those things up front
It sucks
Not hat it's not fun and things change all the time
But until people understand that relationship in that bonding
And that they each have to work with each other
And under some kind of
You know
Schedule of deliverables
That's when the home thing gets moving
It's your job as a leader to set the mission and set the major goals
Let them come back
With the details
And make sure you all agree
But then each team's going to push each other and as soon as it comes up
You know it's like
You want me to get involved I can help him push him along if you want and I will
And if it happens enough times then you'll know you need to replace the fur
Or sometimes they rise to the challenge
But typically
I see if you pired well enough
People will rise to the challenge
As long as you're not number one
Overdoing it like going too fast
Right you can explain your decisions
And that you set up some framework for a scheduling so that everybody understands their interdependencies
So everything can Loop
Right
So you got to have
Good tools to make that
But if they all have two relatively be on the same page
If not
You're going to find out very quickly
To trim off those
Those people
And then the other one is when you're
At a certain enough sizes you make sure you have mentoring
Inside the
So that the mentor
Third party method
I just not internal third-party Metra comes in
And then came then
You know
Be that
Advocate for whichever party
Is moving too fast or moving too slow and whatever
To help you normalize what's really going on because I would get a lot of people
Appointing each other
And the more times
You know I get people blaming I always say look
You can come in
Complain to me as much as you want
Cable TV show up in my office
I'm going to make a decision
The neither of you can only like
So you guys figured out before you get in
The meeting should never be about the arguments inside the meeting unless something new happened
After planting or who knows what it is
Ghosting should be all worked out just like a great Board of meeting
A great Rapport building goes really smoothly because all of us individual issues got worked out well before the board meeting in the board meeting
Music for Molly
Large
Team meetings are also the same
All those little things we talked about the big thing
And we get through the big decisions
Not the little stopper squabbling
So
You know I'm at
Stats about being a perv
Nnn learning that end
Having a mentor there
Help those people learn that because you really a lot of young teams
They start
Daniel pointing
They don't understand what it means to be over
So that's just a
You know
Lack of experience
But that can be learned quickly if you have the right tools
As a follow-up question
BBQ in the valley
I was bleeding work-life balance
And
And also thought they had that you can we innovate you work the Chinese
At least not at 6
What's the name of this podcast
Because we
That's impossible they think that
To do innovation
Indicted Armin
Between the two kind of arguments
So what would you think truth lies
How could something move fast
Work hard in Stoughton
Well first they have to understand what
Their true value in differentiate
If you understand what your true differentiation is
Anna value
Then you work really hard on that
And you have to work double time to build it till I get
Okay
You can't
There's certain crunch periods when it's a week or two weeks were people all we're all shipping something or something's got to happen
Yes there's going to be extra time and yeah I could be 996
Chicopee 997
Whatever it takes
They can't be that all the time
Ripe
Because again
Just like you can be in the
Echo chamber of a Spate of a
City
Orab
Industry
You can be the echo chamber of a
What company and you can never get to see what reality is like outside
And know what real problems are cuz all you're doing a 7 coming for us you need to remember what your own problems
Everybody needs time to process
I always say sometimes
You need to slow down
Speed up
And that means having the proper checkpoints product development checkpoints right proper board means the proper communication
Patience doesn't mean it needs to be this you know
Lots of red tape and tons of you know
Processing
But you gotta slow down and you got
Taking some cases
To be able to go faster so that you don't make
And that's about
You know
Again experience manager
As opposed to just work faster and harder and we'll get it solved
It doesn't work
Because you're going to do that and like you said you're going to end up burning
It's just not
Just not going to work in
You know I've seen that a lot in
Startups and young managers I associate a lot in
You know where I
Been in various places in China
You know it's
It's not thoughtful
You got it you got to have you step on the gas
The step on the brakes
Sometimes
And you know what
Frankly my some of my best ideas and best solutions to problems that happen
When I'm away from you
Jennifer just even a few hours when I go for that run
Don't go for a run and have music
Don't go for whatever you know in
And be distracted cuz you're sitting there walking and you're still on your phone like
You got to have a shutdown
Sleep
It doesn't mean you having another meeting and I was literally
I called Tony time
You know I'd be nice just like okay
And I'm not thinking about it but all the sudden boom
The solution the problem shows up in your brain
People think that
Working harder is going to solve it
It's Not Over
Most the time
The world's increasing need swimming global
Do you worry about
The mindset of Silicon Valley
As being the hungry now
Not not not be aware enough
What's going on
I think that
People
Ra
Product of the
And
Just like
I needed to get out of
Silicon Valley
After 25 years it's great and nothing wrong with it but I get to learn new ways
I think that each person should
Understand that there's great things
About all kinds of play
Places and there's not so great things
Nowadays
Because of the democratization of
You should go to different places and see how they ended
And see how they build Ark
And how they get along
That thing you got to do much but you got to have more than one data point
To know the right way.
And a lot of people now ask me who are in Silicon Valley phone number
What would you do
Right now if you were me
And I said
You're in your 20s
I said go somewhere
Go somewhere go to China go to Korea
Go to your go somewhere else
For 3 months
Just go live there go
See what it's all about building that work outside
Do you get a new baselining
Of what's going on around the world to come back with fresh ideas and your valuable to someone
Even if you have to go back for whatever reason
You're valuable because you have
A different perspective than what everyone else has and as we know great startups
Ingrate
You know what to call it
Colleges look for
They look for people who are differentiated
Differentiate yourself it ain't going to happen when you're in the same place all day
Go differentiate yourself and go challenge yourself somewhere else
And go learn about a place or learn about a new sector alert about anything
Do you come back and you're more valuable for yourself and more valuable for other people around you
Tony thank you so much for your time
Lot of fun
9960 is a multi-stage venture capital firm based in Silicon Valley on high in Beijing
We have been partnering with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past 18 years from seed to pre-ipo
With 6.2 billion dollars in capital under management across 13 funds ggv invests in consumer
Bernie retail social Digital internet Enterprise cloud and Frontier Tech
GTB has invested over 290 companies with more than 45 companies valued at over a billion
$10 for solar companies include Airbnb Alibaba C trip
Didi chuxing demo hashicorp hellobyte cows keep Slack
Square Hotel wish soundtrue white white and others find out more at ggvc
Si.com we also highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat group as lot Channel where we regular share
Inside events and job opportunities related to attack in China join these groups at 996.
Ggb c.com community
If you have any feedback on this podcast or would like to recommend a gas please email us at 996 at
Bbc.com