Hi everyone I'm going to tell you about our sister podcast
Thunder
Real talk
It is a biweekly show that gets real with under
About the challenges that founders
In startup Executives face
And also how they have grown from Top experience
The show's host by my fellow managing partner at ggv Capital
Glenn Solomon
Albany Park office
Produce pericolic Fisher again Ann Arbor San Francisco office
Past episodes of the showings
Food Stewart Butterfield
From slack Sarah Friar from
Square and Nate blue Charizard from Airbnb
You can take a listen by searching founder real talk
Can any podcast app
Airport
Hi there
Welcome to the 9th at 6 podcast brought to you by ggv capital
On the show interview movers and shakers
China's tech industry as well as Tech leaders who have a us China
Cross-border perspective, managing partner at GTV capital and I've been working at startup
Investing in them in both the US and China for the past 20 years
My name is Zahra Jones an investment Analyst at ggv Capital and a former journalist
Why is the show called 96
6 is the work schedule that many Chinese Founders have organically adopted that is 9 a.m.
5 p.m. 6 days a week
To us
996 captures intensity Drive
And speed
Of Chinese internet companies many which are moving faster that even their American counterparts
Eyeless nurse
Starting from this episode we like to try something new
Instead of having a guest
Hans and I will have a dialogue about a current event or Hot Topic
Internist
Seen today
On this episode we're going to talk about shammys IPO which took place in Hong Kong
On July 9th
House is one of the earliest investors in xiaomi as well as a former board member of the
So hum these two weeks have been a world when for you you are in Hong Kong for a Siamese IPL
And appeared on TV four times in a single day
What was that day like for you
Oh I think that's amazing milestone
For the management
And his board members
Who I participate
In the closet company from the
It's amazing that this company started
Years ago
Yeah
Somebody remarks
Back in 2010 that the only way show me where when
And become big
Is it the Motorola Ericsson Nokia out all day
Go away
Adam back in 2010 everybody in tunnels using Nokia or Motorola
So it was
Pretty remarkable how the war has
Drink a lot
Air in the ears
And xiaomi
I'm through with
Cheer accounts that moment
When Legend first told you about
The idea of
Xiaomi
I remember it was so cold winter night in Beijing 2010
That's right it was in late January 2010
Allegiant called out by Richelieu yo Ching from Morningside first
How to
I think
Westlake
6 hour discussion
WhatsApp from 6 hours
Taco hours
The amazing incredible
I spend I was
Second person to call in the same week
And I met with him in person because I was
Flipping beijing at a time
To talk to him
And remember in the first
Half an hour I was just
Shock
Of what he wants
To do the Hulk there's no
In history
Textile apps
No
From
2tb 2.5 g and 3G
No startup has ever
Seated
From scratch
Stepping up
So he was trying to do with something that was
Has never been done before
The first 30 minutes
Autism shock
Next one hour I have decided that this
Makes sense
And they probably have the best thing to do it
Because
Just a few things that you said
The first thing you said was that
In 10 years
By 2020
Smartphone will replace laptop as the
Most valuable and most commonly used
Computing device
That people carry along with them every single day
And the second thing he said was
Went in this market
The winner has to figure out how to build a brand online
And sell online
And listen
Consumers feedback
Online
And be able to get away fast
Beijing
Consumers. Feedback
He expect on this point by saying that
All the great phones for Motorola Nokia even Android or iPhone
HTC
Phone companies don't listen to consumer
Steve Jobs famous for saying that
Consumers dont know what they want
Let me know what they need
So it's takes a genius to come up with the amazing product in this category
And they took the opposite of entire approach
We just that you'll come up with something that's
Solid
Decent is good
He welcomes user feedback
So they can get a ride
Screw up crossword
And that's
I think that's the second revolution idea.
He came up with
That was interesting
The third idea was
What's the fact that to wedding
Apply for Math League
You know you have to be working side Hardware
Have the best
What's my fashion manufacturer
How to be able to build up some kind of android-based OS
So you have a chance to do a UI.
Taylor Swift needs
Of the local consumers starting with China
And the first thing you need to do is
Be able to monetize through internet service
And now through horror
The harbor has to be as
That cheap as possible
That's low-margin possible to get to the heads of the office many users
As possible
To make a to make it work
Those are the three things he said
That I thought were extremely a revolutionary
That no one else in China had a similar thought
I.
Point point in time
Yeah it was designed to be
More customer-friendly
Then the existing Hardware player at the time
And also
More
Internet Service Company in China was willing to
To what to do
The people who want to do software only solution
But not many want to do
Combination of all three
I think I'm the second point about show me listening to his users
My thing is
Pretty revolutionary in that late really really want
How to befriend
So
Xiaomi always says like
They trade their users as friends as equal
And they're not
Saying all you do
I'm going to make a product
You're going to like it
There's a bug I really recommend called Tyga
Was just sent of party
Inspection by Shelby co-founder
Yuan Chang
Bush talks about how xiaomi
Customer marketing
It's really impressive how they were able to
Is it their philosophy is
Is to build loyalty first before
Same if they want to have a really deep relationship with their core users before going big
Crucial to it
Definitely
And I think the
People overlook this xiaomi had co-founders from Google Microsoft and kingsoft
And Africans are other Chinese internet companies
And a lot of the tactics that work
King from
Co-founders with experience
Operating in China what is from big company or Chinese camp
Nothing in this area Richelieu by Moines Iowa
Face Mart in putting out
That hot how you matched
23 Giffin
Company culture
Unique xiaomi culture
Will be the key determinant
To decide whether xiaomi can be back on
And I think they can see that that's the most serious thing
That he did
Once you started
You make sure that people function well
As a team and spend a lot of time listen to
Customer feedback
And astrology Stephanie panel
After first year of Howard
I think what convinced me to invest in tell me what's that
Leaving his team was the only team in China
That had to be
Sulphur Springs from King Saul
The internet service
Give me experience
Wingstop
At the unemployed building Springs from Bangkok
India
Almighty Commerce
Prince from
Jojo
Even though it was nobody with strong Harbor experience
Lincoln was able to recruit them build a team overtime to overcome diet
No one else in China had all five
So I thought I'd let you have the best shot
With four out of five attributes
To a wedding
Is definitely not an easy decision
Or obvious
I think all the people who pass on xiaomi or Leon
Possible autological Right Weezer
Either the prices
Too expensive
Or they wasn't enough
Datapoints show this condition
Can definitely make it
And Hardware is a difficult
Business
214 C
Sustainable.
So for all the people who pass on xiaomi it is
Absolutely
I can complete weasel mow the lawn
It is not the puppet show me what does he look at all the
Make a unicorn stuff coming out of China
The next few months for IPL whether it is a
Make wine or a
Single door
Or what
Patricia coming out later in the form of a bike dance
And
TD every single one of them for
Most of the Rams
To pass on them are extremely logical indivisible annual argue
So
To make you suffer from calls
And make those spots
Why you have to believe that founder has a right Vision the right direction next
Into that the market is changing
The favorite a new way of doing
And then three remaining cases
Iskcon players must not get it
And not be able to adjust
To give newcomers to the opportunity
To make this rock
Destruction happened possible
The lava comes out to judgment because you know the founder
And Wellness
Carmen. He was she has a right attributes
To take advantage
Market opportunities
And I didn't date you cannot doesn't take off
If you don't like doesn't make enough impact in China
In the awesome world
It is not possible these Apple
Bridget loves can make a war
Till now we have a saying this.
Because we're betting on China is going to be
Different
Because we're not betting on internet is going to change China improve China
Therefore you should bet on Founders
Who has the most
Audacity
Biggest change pasa
Guess that the few of them that can make it work
We'll have to check and see how come
I think they can get a calculation on
Personiv xiaomi the window
But you're a little late at night and I participated
The first one investment xiaomi at IPO
Not sweet
Yielded 866 tax return
So don't take that risk
With the dishes are found early on
It's not possible
To make stock return if you're very rational and reasonable
The room for return on Fortune Wheel
So you have appeared in the present number of times talking about xiaomi and I've noticed
One question that a lot of us reporters asses
How does xiaomi compare to Apple
I guess they always try to find a xiaomi equivalent
Us in a closes
Stay single visible because of the smartphone does
So what
Why do you think people should
Stop comparing xiaomi
If not Appleton
Which company do thing is
The closest
When will the
Question I've heard from you
American Audio
Obviously
You're very smart investors in general
Investing in Taco Bell
Decades
When the first question I heard was that
So
Xiaomi a has a party system so how is it compatible to Android
Show me all the last
The years
It is amazing how
Even smart investors
Like to use
Eno
And put on top of
Companies from Emerging Markets
And think.
What is
Similar to the other
It's very difficult for any investor to fully understand
Xiaomi model witch
Uniquely Chinese
Besides that listen to Consumers and therefore not presume they know what consumers want
Quick weekend getaways
Meet and exceed
Exploitation of consumers
I like people look at xiaomi Revenue source
Some things I hate 7% come from the hallway
Another 10% come from Smart Home Appliances
An opportunist seems to be growing in 2018
Baby stuff for 3 months
So it's a hardware company
Two people for people who haven't tracked xiaomi that's a very easy
Unfortunately most of the smart investor
What is in Hong Kong or us or elsewhere
Have not come through
Rise of middle-class
Or upgrade
Consumption
Assumption in in in China or two
Japan
Or even in Taiwan
Whenever people and large middle class
Rice
And going through ovulation in one
Resume the end up buying Brands they Trust
And I grow up
What is with Uniqlo and in Japan in the 90s
Or some some throughout the 90s and 200s
Mm
In
In the US
Whether it is HEC in Taiwan
You got people end up
Growing up at what are you mainly in the u.s. in the 80s with with gap
And then most recent last 10-15 years with Zara and H&M
Consumers Cooperative
The end up buying more from now brand
Muji is not a good example, out of Japan
So what's wrong he has done is
Is becoming a brand.
Customer first light
Pics of a phone
That ends up liking experience spent a lot of time on the internet
Through the xiaomi phone
Stand up and show me TV and other smart home appliances from xiaomi
WinCo's Wasabi story we're going to a
Outlet mall
You stop buying can help with overtime to submit a new pot to come out each month
I probably xiaomi ecosystem company
I'm going there often and as such
And don't spend more time out xiaomi app
The most popular example public show me a video
So when that happens
UFC of liking effect
Faster growth
Hardware first
What comes later in each cohort
You some more users will end up spending time my shopping app
Thereafter
They sound very good at building an application app
Not take the best of
Content Pro
Related areas and put under the platform and build a business around it
Is so. Internet service impact will come later
Any needs have user use multiple camionera products
To to to get them to want to use those
So what what the
Public buses haven't had a chance to see
Is the lagging effect that will happen with more crap from internet services
The only time will tell
The proof that this is right
Is what we see from looking at a core data
But I think over time
Smart pop investors will learn
That is a different kind of company that what they're used to
I was right
One of the xiaomi co-founders
Let's compare xiaomi's business model to that of a small restaurant
So they sell food that's kind of
The smartphone but they really make the money for
Vim tips
Fish comes from
Crack and a lot of people forget that
For any pure internet service companies
People have the growth hack
Meaning that you got to figure out ways to grow user base
Through mechanism
That you have to spend money on
Calculate LTV versus cock
To figure out what is a good way to scale your user base
It's a painful user show me Ashley
Gets paid at least 5% gross margin if not more
Off to hot where to get users
So there in that Services actually has a
Has a negative cock
Is it a positive pack
To grow users by getting paid for it
Is it a hundred people use
It's a very different model than almost any other internet service companies out there
So if if this is sustainable
And there to make sure it is symbol is through having a lot more Harbor products out there
Study middle class
Consumer family can buy
In in in in the US.
Froyo of horror device
To get paid for crying users
Solana unit services
Siskin Steel
Are there after
So it's a very different model 1 people you eard their people used to
Investing overtime people see if
If it doesn't work out
Was some of us
Would you compare xiaomi
Emoji
Given
View of a shelf
And how it's more
Adopting the concept of
New retail
Stephanie elements armuchee in Uniqlo
In a different field in the 4 for xiaomi
There's definitely elements of
Costco model of basically
Description
Plus very low cost
To make sure no more
Products are affordable
By the rising
The defin elements of Amazon in there as a papa
Myself
Many many Pollocks
Bielenberg Focus
At delivering Superior experience
Tuatara music
So what they doing
, in a team have come up with
Is a mixture of different models
The itis
Core
Is figuring out how to
Beat a customer's best friend in
Olympics first
Exceed a consumer
Expectation
And I think in his
7 words
Internet
Prodigy
A being focus of being
Focus on delivering Superior experiences
By focusing on
Delivering water mouth
Possum Word of Mouth impact and being extremely fast
These four terms
Michelada
I think the lesson here is that
It's not possible to take a shortcut and
Find a US equivalent
Live forever
In China or every emerging market
A lot of times
There is no cumpli equivalent and
We just need to take the time to understand the
How they really were
And I only have a Chinese company also
About any company with new business
Facebook IPO was
At $30 a share and
Within the first 6 months after IPL you went down to $19
And I'll today is over $300 this year
Sew-in for years people learn that it is very different model than what they used
I remember back in 2008 2009
Who put on Facebook
I think that is a company is given us why put out out
Is not as profitable as Google and never will be as popular
That's Google
Therefore it's a very easy even for a smart investor in the world to miss
Of something that's
And the fact that xiaomi
The primary Market is in Asia
Makes it harder for a US investor
William Hung Ambassador
To truly understand
The only time can show
That it is say yes Superior a model
But when you look at how China has expanded over the last few years
Now there I'm on the top phones not only in China but also number one India in n673 other come
Self
The penetration is a lot faster
And deeper than we all thought it was possible
If we look at number of interviews
Xiaomi online
The next 1.5 billion users
Becoming online between now and 20
20:30
Most of that growth
What come from the
74 countries that xiaomi is
Skin already
So I'm
I love you ask me about what a Chinese come to the US or not
I think
Completely missed the point
Not the crow is coming from
Existing countries
The song He's already
Show me causes Salva internet
Allow people are scam
Article of that term
Why what how would you convince
People that show me isn't internet
Could you elaborate on some of
Internet services
Show me has a prospectus Dimension that has over
18 Oz
With each of them with the monthly active users
50 million
Elsa has about
Import a 38 Oz
Each of them has
Over 10 million in monthly ad
Beneath these are amazing numbers
Any aggregate
He did over 1.5 billion
RMB
Internet Subs Revenue in 2017 which Audi placement
As a top 25 internet service only
A company in the world
I think the most popular when people know
It's probably xiaomi
Tommy video
Tell me video has
Has an interesting way of becoming application services
He doesn't license content from anyone
What it does is
Abacus counting from
I see from your coochie. From
All the top Chinese video out of Eastwood
About E license
The content
Yeah and
Whenever I use a click
On a video
In xiaomi video it takes you to the content from
Its partners
But within the app itself
So that you can have more
Immigrant experience
EMP charges advertising Revenue
And also
From the user
So it makes money in multiple ways from different stakeholders
And it should I Revenue with some with his Partners to provide the original a video content
So you can focus on providing the most
Comprehensive
Collection of content
To that user
At the same time
So far they don't have to spend much money on the card in the content themselves
If we go way to coexist
Without a content
Producers
So is a good way to build build a ecosystem
To provide better service in
People can make
They're sure of the
Of the money as well
Does a very good way to
Duke to outgrow business
And they're playing a philosophy
In other categories as well not just the outside of China
In the process of doing so we also become switching ambassador
NBC service provider so they work with
In situ xiaomi invested early
And so it was able to grow with Chachi
As well and they're doing that not just in China but also in Benny of the
Other 73 countries are there in
So
Again
Parting bastard haven't seen this ghost
System approach
And from our experience of investing in China since the 2000
We know that
If a country take off an internet makes an impact
Many of the top in the compass in the country will have tremendous growth
So show me what when multiple ways
As we stopped up the investing and building an ecosystem
Egypt country
So I wanted to talk about the IPO is
Myself and devaluation
The pricing
So if there were a lot of fluctuations on
On the first day and
Do you think
Xiaomi was
Had a reasonable pricing and
What would you expect
I think over the last two weeks has shown that xiaomi stock price has steadily risen
Now surround party 21
I think
Whatever the short-term fluctuations was the first day or so
Heading all black
2 weeks
That's totally fine end up being the high enough
Heading about pricing at the Lord of the Rings
Makes it easier for investors to believe in the in the in the end of the story
Inn at Reading volume a lot
To show that
Nonis the volume
Reasonable
Stock price also
But I think we should be looking at a longer-term
How strongly will continue to grow based on the
The twins that I mentioned earlier
So
We always think that IPO
It's just a blip or a mouse
I need a day
You got to be
Can you look up the business at UW
Oprah larger
Continue to grow in
And looking out of Facebook on Google and Apple
In
Alibaba and tencent
All the great companies out there
Show. So that's the way to
Crave audio
Overlocker.
What's one question about xiaomi that you wish you were asked
But you're never
I think a lot of people don't understand
What some ecosystem means
Boating terms of
Highway code
And then
Internet service
People don't know they have it
Correct and think I think going back in China
Over last decade
Wer
The fortune of beat having a front-row seat
Does ecosystem form in China
What is in the form of tencent invest in gaming companies around the world
And
E-commerce players in
China
Or Alibaba
Ambassador
Incompetence in the ultra-space
And I pardoned some of them
Or
Companies like make why not become a super app
Implementing
And WeChat
Do we not doing this and see how we became the same
Let a lot of content providers
Nice to be on top of their popcorn
This kind of ecosystem were
Seems that * company learned and tried
Through four generations of 14 regions of Entrepreneurship in in China
I just realized
10 13 years
And we are very fortunate to see that happen
And getting up
Perspective
So when we start investing
In Southeast Asia in
Yeah us or even like a marathon in Europe maybe down the road
The perspective of a building
Assistant company I think 10
Replicated expended
Where is it happening with
Uber learning from
B20 do you want to be a super app
What transportation services and be willing to invest
Income is like a line
And others
And that does services
Ecosystem
I think more companies should learn from that
And have a better chance of
Becoming a bigger company not on their own but also help other countries grow with them
In over last 10-15 years
Web snap extremely profitable
Inbody creating for
Chinese
So those are great lessons I hope.
Are are willing to consider and we'll be happy to help
Sing the best way to appreciate your music
By visiting
Xiaomi store
UCI notches phones
Laptops in TVs for also
Rice cookers
Air purifiers
Segway headphones
Bags umbrellas
Etcetera
These are all products made by companies I shall be invested and it helps that late when used to be an angel
Yes
I just want to see the hundred plus different kind of products inside each shopping store
It's amazing that xiaomi itself only makes three products
The phone to the TV
Laptop
Everything else is made by another company
That Shelby has invested
And help this guy
And when you have not many
About 80 plus
Companies
Now you can work with
Each month somebody has it was some
Epsom
That will get the
Customers want to go back to
Distorting just hacked what's going on
So the foot traffic to repeat repeatability
And frequency of the foot traffic is much higher for xiaomi than any other
Company company
After that's one of the key differences between Apple and show me is I would never go to Apple Store
It's like once a month just to chat with new cuz there's nothing new
I know it's the only go there when my phone is broken but I would go to a xiaomi store
Whenever I feel like shopping and browsing cuz there's always something new it was always
Pleasant surprise wedding
And that's the appeal to a rising middle class and then
Increasingly over nice environment
Do you want to do that many people are starting to have their first apartment in first house
For the first time in your life
And starting a family so
There a lot of needs
That could be fulfilled by a trust
Strong and robust
Ecosystem and you're right
New Lexington
Work for 3 years
As a angel investor
Surprise yourself xiaomi
He will not have come up with yet
Idea of
Building that
Iko Iko
I think those of us who
Invest with him
When he was a angel investor or very fortunate to have a chance to
Participate
And something else
As big as this
Cool so that's all we have for today
Thanks for listening I would love to hear your thoughts on this new format
We can reach Hanson I directly by joining our listeners WeChat groups in slack Channel and then is 6. Ggv
Abc.com coming
Community has grown into over a thousand people within the last couple months
And I think that's a testament to the growing interest
Skin tag in chine
Thank you
Airline flight 798 9.4
And it's listening to this episode
I-96
By the way we also produce a weekly email newsletter in English also called 9 + 6
Roundup of the week's most important happenings
Intec in China
Subscriber some tortoise videos from formative and fun to read and you said also features original content
An analysis from Zara MI
Describe at nine 6. GG bc.com
Venture Capital firm based in Silicon Valley Shanghai and Beijing we have been partnering with leading technology entrepreneurs
Ford has 18 years from seed to pre-ipo with 3.8 billion dollars in capital under management across
State funds GTA V invest in globally minded on spinners in consumer internet
E-commerce Frontier tag in Enterprise
GTA V has invested over 280 companies with 29 IPOs in 22 unicorns
Pergola companies include
Airbnb Alibaba
C trip
Didi chuxing demo hashicorp hellobike cows keep plaque
Square
Hotel wish soundtrue white white and others find out more at ggvc.
We also highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat group as slack Channel
Where we regular share insights events and job opportunities related to Tech in China
20 screws at 96.3 tvc.com community
Do you have any feedback on this podcast
Or would like to recommend a gas please email us at 996 at gbc.com