Hi everyone will be doing a special Ama or ask me anything episode where are managing partner Hons telling Michael
Co host on 96
What answer any questions from you I want a future episode of the show
You can submit questions to him beforehand by filling out the form at 9:06. Ggvc. Com
Slash Ama
You can ask about anything such as investing philosophy China's internet ecosystem career choices tips for
Founders questions about specific companies with invested in and so on
Once again you can submit your question at 96.2 gvtc.com Ama
The link is also in the show notes
Recent arrest Monroe County Probation
Hi there
Welcome to the 96 podcast
Brought to you by GE Capital
On the show went to the movers and shakers of China's tech industry
I just got called Founders from around the world can draw lessons
I'm fine Aztec ecosystem
I'm a managing partner H-E-B capital and I've been working at and investing in startups
Across the US China and other emerging markets for the last 20 years
My name is Orajel and the marketing manager at ggv Capital and a former journalist why is this show called 96
96 is the work schedule that many Chinese Founders have organically adopted
That is 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
Drive-In speed with china's internet companies
Growth Miracles over last decade
Also I highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat group in slack Channel
Where you can connect with like-minded people interested in Tech in China we organize regular offline events across the world for a while
Followers you can join these by visiting 96.2 gbc.com
On the show today we have won the co-founder and CEO of Penta
China's leading dating app
Santa is a social app that helps young people in China connect with one another
It has a slight left
Slide right interface
Only one two users both slight right on each other can they start a conversation
Company was founded in 2014 and has helped users makeover 10 billion matches to date
In 2018 time was acquired by Walmart for around 735 meal in u.s. dollars
For those who are unfamiliar Momo is a top location-based social networking platform in China that helps people meet strange
Fingers around them is also one of the leading live streaming Platforms in China
It's a public company on the NASDAQ and its current market cap is around
6.8 billion dollars
What year was born in Beijing
Nico Robin Sweden
Deals to master's degree
When a computer science
In a sec 1 Industrial economics
In 2007
China and started his first business
P1
A fashion Community which I see I remember
Before caulking tight end in 2014
Welcome to the show
Thank you
Hi everyone this is you is great to be here
So you were born in China but move to Sweden at 8
7 could you tell us about the move like why you
Movies are at what was it like for you
So because my father was doing research
And he was invited to Sweden to Be Our Guest
Researcher
And after he was in them
So after 2 years there we decided to move there
The whole family
So we moved in 88
So very big dipper
The back in those days
The world that sign you through
Still
In the early they self open up in Belton
China
Lights off
All our furniture
Didn't belong to us we belong to
The people that.
Did they kind of like
Roundy's II
I used to and the first
10 years or so
Lived in two difference
Switch
Is probably quite different than the Sweden people people could imagine
Rights because
We had one Suite in the whole test
What kind of like nominations
I got to get in touch with all sorts
Different cultures so that was very
Secondary School
Because I was
Interested in
I'm so
I went into the city 2
Go to a school with a special matthan
Science class
And that was more like the
How do you say
The canal
Elite part of
I'll sweeten the difference between immigrant area
Call drink
Most central part of Stockholm
I would say that's almost as you know ask difference
Between China and Sweden
Very big
Tasha's of you know
How to look at the world
Which I think has
Serve me a lot
How so you get to your 4th base with you look at the world
But
And it's often traffic today
And each one has their own reasoning
Which makes sense from their own
Perspectives and narrative
And did you get to
Early Autumn
Get acquainted with the whole
Notion of narrative
Rights because there's a whole history behind
Why you think is right
So
You stop
Looking at things in terms of black and white
Number to Newton Center Simsbury
On our show and she talked about her experience of
Gahr High School in the US
In 2007
You decide to move back to
The China
I was in China I live in China work in China but in 2006
And 2013
What prompted you to move back China
So
Right
Queen College
And
I'm starting to work I work for a while after Cincinnati
I started to have a lot of business
And I think it started when because I was doing
VoIP work
Sony Ericsson
And my manager there wanted me to
Join the Zone company
To do
Pyp for solving
Between countries
And I came up with this idea of how to reduce to cause significant
Please review IP
So basically it's a solution where
Before you go on the airplane
You transfer your number
URI directory number to our server locally
Safe
Is Eufaula from Stockholm to Beijing
Can you transfer it to the stock on AR stock number
And when you arrive in Beijing you buy a new SIM card and then you
Send SMS
Telling us with your new SIM card number is
And all
Calls to your sweetest number it will gets brought it to your Chinese number
So you pay to level two
When you want to call out
If you call a Swedish Swedish number just call from as good as normal Swedish
Did you call a Chinese number or anything
Afford number
You called our local server in soccer
And then you pay to local fees again
So you can start paying
Somewhere between 6 and 12 R&B per minute
Becomes like less than one
And another one
To this day that I think has a solution
Although I mean room is much less of a problem just cause has been reducing the
Butts back in those days this would Bieber in you and would solve the problem
So if we file for a pittance
We wanted to do this
Company and the manager went as far as to offer me a CTO position
Waze
Its 20% stake in the company
Anfernee was like okay so it wasn't hard in this
Did the whole situation took me like
A week or so to a map
So I started coming like
Something snapped
And I couldn't understood that
For any business what you need to do
Especially if you can like Norma Morales aviane
Intertek
Define the pinpoint
Yunnan people complain about
Stuff all the time so you fine
Anything people to complain about stuff to paint
You solve it with technology and you find a way
Charge money
And that's the desert
So you know it business ideas what's coming up
Everyday
In every conversation
So it sounds like
I was bound to start
I wanted to go back to China because I even though I was
Quite comfortable with the Swedish culture
A lot of friends
Horseweed
But I still felt
More Chinese
The volume song
And I like China more
So I wanted to go back to China want to start a company
And I think of the Chinese people in Stockholm there's not definition
I think me and Sophia were the only ones I knew of that those wanted to start a company and wanted to go back
China
So we naturally kind of started to
Look for business idea
That's why I did it
And I remember P1
Back then he was a very
Cool
Fashion website
It was a first website in China
That has a black
Aqua color
And it was still cool
But I never reach out to contact you cuz I thought
Well maybe it's too early for its time
Users in China
Grassroots Market
People who can appreciate piwine will be very nice and only in Beijing shanghai
What were your lessons
From
Why did you do this particular concept and this user interface
What did you learn after doing it
So the reason we did P1 us
The major reason was that
We saw that
Sensui
Sophia had been away from China for worth
4 years
The time in I hardly ever lived in
China Red Sea
We thought that if we would just
Nina flat-out competes with
Play the Grassroots entrepreneurs in China we would
So we would have to come up with something different
And back in those days
I mean
Hikes in Seville
A lot of business ideas were
Borrowed from
The US
So our stuff we're coming from Sweden
We were pretty sure no one has seen anything like
Even if they saw our
But they wouldn't
I understand you describe the product a little bit
So it was like a high-end
Community
Assassin community
And it was invitation-only that's why it was kept
Spotify.
And we have a lot of street style photographers
Who would Scouts for people who are really stylish
In and outside of
I am shopping mall
They were just
Exploding all the time
Then they would ask
If the person wanted to get the
And we were so picky
.
People really wanted to a lot of people dressed up just to get
Stop
I want to take the picture we took their contact info and invited
And the only if they sign up to P2P one would they be able to
Get the picture
Sol commercial rates were super high
What's like 80%
And The photographers were
Paid for each qualified user the actual generated so it was not based on the working time or two photos
Amount of users we got
So is requisition cost was around
15 RMB
60 R&B
4 attack
Qualitative user was actually pretty pretty sure
Is very good so we got millions of users
And to give an example of the quality of the user's right so
At 1 points
I often even said they wanted some fashion people
So they asked us to my 30 user
And we didn't think too much of it so
We sent out emails
2 random users and we got 30
Not even one of them bought a car
The quality
Because I think about this people who went to
I like 1 hour and see in the 2020s right word
The day had a lot of money purchase power
So
Even though we didn't have so much traffic
All the luxury Brands we're out of Kaiser at work Pines gas
So we we degenerates
Significant CPI numbers
It was like over a thousand rmb
We have you know at the max I think we have like $20,000 you
Big business
Three main messages
From the whole endeavor
No we tried for seven eight years
With all sorts of different pivot
If you want to try to get it to work
We just couldn't
Rights and did the three main lessons was
Wine with tuna
But like I said
We thought that you know even though this is a nice markets but China has so many peoples that they still a big
China internet
You want to get
Because that's the value of Chinese internet
So we can like
Big.
That's one but the second part it is
Probably more important and that's the pain point
Is not very strong thing.
But fashion socializing if something
You can live without
So
If they don't have a problem it doesn't matter how good the solution is
And the sad part is that since you don't
The product was too heavy
Since we didn't have a killer feature
We tried to compensate that but I didn't work pictures
And that's not a good way
To to try to succeed with internet startup
So when we stopped going to town town where you wanted water tube
Nocatee
These mistakes right
So we wanted to go for a super strong pain
The witches
We spend a lot of time trying to Define.
Right and our positioning is like solving
Singles have a lack of China Smithfield
That's art.
It's neither for hookups
Or for getting married
Because those are actually kind of like
Sub portions of the market
What small portion
Took him to be frank because
Even though all four guys there's a you know
Quite high level of
Acceptance for hookups
Four girls still in China in Asia
You know it's it's not as pronounced
So we're talking about 5 to 10% of the
The female Market
Heavily limits how big you can be
But if you define it as
You know
Meeting
If you're a single
That's something everyone
So by doing that
You open up the whole Market space
A lot
By the dodo
So that's a hard isn't it how we defined or the dipen points
It's obviously a Big Mac market
And the sad part is that the product is very simple
Are the products even though being simple
Fits the Asian and especially the Chinese
Culture very well
I think much better than it does
For the Westin
And and that's because
Chinese people
Don't have
Acertijos
Solve the problem
Let me for most of the day for most of the people in China
It's indecent to approach someone you don't know
It's still like that in the culture
Having a lot of girlfriends boyfriends before you get married that's totally fine
Getting in touch that first step it's very awkward
So that's why
There are hardly any
Hardee's
Rights in college
And
Most people don't go to top Soundbars
Rides and if you meet someone on the subway where in the mall is on you
Talk to them
That's a hottie
But that's one issue did the second issue is that
Mosto
Chinese young people are not in their hometown
That's quite unique
So there is either in a different city to study with work
And they're much more lonely
Because
They don't have the family and friends are
And no one to introduce
So it's usually just go to work
Sleep alone
Everyday
So it's super lonely
And the 10
Even though being very simple
Spitz this
This problem 512
You never need to flirt
You never need to
Take the first step
Because when you swipe someone
When you when you slide someone left or right
That person doesn't know
But they only know
If you like each other
And then both take the take the first step of the same time
And for the guy
You never expose yourself you never get rejected
Issue
And if you get if you do get mad
Talking to the girl is
You're very confident
You know that she's interested
She doesn't get the grass this is it doesn't bother and standby a lot of guys
And the girl also has a super Heights accessory
Because
Portage our numbers
60% of the guys
Es6
Girls like 6
X device
So
For the girls
It's almost like in the short match
If they like someone
So they feel like you don't like the
Emperor II parts
The search for girls is that they can be proactive
Usually socially rights
Female demon in the West
They're waiting for the guys to approach that right
They can be proactive ride so it's completely
How do you say even playing field
So they can choose who they like
And that's something that you speak
Bytes of data people approaching approaching them in real life
Are awesome not the ones they like
And
In something once they like pastel like a 60% chance of matching with
So the experience is very good
So even though as far as the service employees division just flip some cars and and you know
I solved this initiating the first Contact
Which I think is much bigger problem in China
But that's how we have been many dating websites and then apps
In China as was outside the China
When you were doing tan-tan
What were the features
That you were thinking of that's
Different
From everything that's out there
And what are the features that are distinctive Chinese
That a Western Ave
Won't be able to
Satisfy
So
I don't think it's so much
About
What features do you have
Supposed to
Like how you operates the whole service
What kind of values do you have
While doing that
So I think there were like a hundred products doing more of the same product
And they all failed
And they sell not because
We were doing a good job and I'll containing them
And even though I don't sing to this day that it's
Really
Difficult
It becomes very difficult if you don't have the proper experience
And we only gained experience by basically
Sailing with p1478 ears
So we basically made all the mistakes
You could make
We succeeded
By not feeding them
And for a new startup
For new entrepreneurs
Who haven't made those mistakes
I think you would need to have a lot of luck
To avoid
For us specifically rights
In this kind of service
First off
You decide
Is everyone going to see each other only one
Fort Worth or are you going to like
Repeat
Other people you see
Since you don't have too many users in the beginning Wright's most
Startup choose to repeat
That's a bad idea
Because
If you like someone
Just waiting for them to like you back
Right
So if you see them again this is waste of your time
If you don't like someone
What's up
What you want to optimize for its time its efficiency right
Amount of time you spend versus
Getting a someone you can meet all flying that likes
Right
That's a proper person
That's what you want
So you only see which which person won
The second is that we want to see fresh people you don't want to see people who raps like 3 months ago
And that's also a big issue
For a
New service since you don't have
How many users
In many of the other services you see people who are
After 3 months ago and then you feel like he's a ghost town
So we decided early on you can only see people crafted maximum within like
48 hours
But did you have to be active within 48 48 hours
Those two restrictions
Then you have to
Can understand what you're doing and I don't think
Hardly any of the competitors would we have
Realize this right so
Ringtones on each person slides
200 Parts on average
Verde
Nuzlocke
Change
If each person slides
Donut cards
You only see the first one
I want to see fresh user
What does it mean for new service
It means that locally within the city
You have to grow by 200200 girls a day
For this to be sustainable
Bratz
But at the same time if you do grow by 200 guys Wonder Girls a day
No one will hit the bottom of the stack
Because most users are aren't active every day thereafter I'm not average maybe every second day
And if you don't hit the bottom of the style
They don't care if there's one card left for a Million Parts
So you're
Essentially
Operating as if you were dominating Market already in terms of use Experian
So you can you can very early on give you sore
Stop music.
And since we had this offline
Street style
Acquisition
Experience
WeChat
Get good looking guys and girls
Offline
We just skip the whole Street South Park we just use
Male and female models
Male Hollister with the fact good looking girls
Attract
Does the concept of being or a price
Yes
So it's so you could get
Park rides
You get the city to live
I don't think any of the competitors
Smash dude
So we first
Did that in Beijing and any changes
It didn't work in Shanghai
That's very interesting people don't
Dirt
They're just not going to work
Awesome
Pretzel that supposed to earn experience in in Beijing for some to get some matches
You talked to all those 10 girls
Maybe 5 will dancer
Should get some matches if you don't say anything five of the girls will talk to you
That that's how big of a difference is there is
So why want to get Beijing Zoo to work we had this problem like how do we have the right there Manga
If you have 2 offline get each City to work that's a massive investment
It doesn't
Feel like it's going to Skilled
Right
So something we try this very interesting what's that
We changed
The maximum distance
From
100 km
100 + means infinite's bus the single biggest
Optimization we have done in the history of time
Like just that single change
Made everyone laugh
So in a small City before you can maybe slip
Clyde Carson
Right now we can slip those five cars and people in the other surrounding cities and if those were not enough you could see people
Score super happy users
Even if you were not so happy as long as you interact with this happy users
People tended to not care so much about location
Muffaletta sandwich
So immediately we got the whole China 2bs acted more lesson temperature retention the song
Is Beijing in chengdu
So we could just do it
Atmosphere of the Hulk
What's up left the maximum distance is it a hundred plus kilometers
Is Asheville I think like $2,000
Has China
Rustic 1200 miles
There's a lot of people close by
You don't notice that
No limits
It's only when there's not people around but that you noticed
How do you date
Live far away from you
Oh yes I mean they were early on they were
Took a plane to me through this I mean it's insane the first day
Says you can only use each person once right
We had one of our own the female workers employees
Who ran downstairs like what's up what's up
So she bought a new SIM card to register new number new account because she miss
Swiped
A die
So she wants to sweat that guy yet
Within the first month we had the first
Married couple
Rotisserie thank you email
That's how I fishing rods
So it's quite amazing
Persepolis look like
Western Dental
They usually connect to Facebook
So by doing that
They get the lot for free
I guess Facebook profiles are very good
Wright State the first of all
Almost
At least in the West
It's almost always of the real person
Right
I saw the real person in the
It's not
Trying to look good
It's not better than the profile pictures upload for then
That's one the second is a lot of
They get their contacts for free to get Sturm Facebook fretrest for free so they know who their friends are
They also get their profile information
So the only thing you need to do is if he's right there with descriptionari sell everything else that you get for free
Also you get much higher conversion rate from down on the after signing up
Because it's like a one button press
So in China obviously can't do that
And
Send
The Western Ave scannable
Odoo success because
Of this connection to Facebook
If you want to get this to work in China
You have to find a way to emulate
That success
Pretzel
So from the first day
WeedMaps
Not moderated all user profiles
So we remove all profiles
Who did not have a proper
Which is like 40%
Because that's how China is
And you obviously can't use WeChat because WeChat is it won't even worse than like 40
So we would ever use it when you sign up you actually invisible
No one can see if you can spot the other user
But what is quite efficient
And if you passed and people start seeing you don't listen that you don't need to know
If you didn't have motivation you'll get the phone saying hey you can use this
And you have to change your profile picture
So we did that from day one
So there has never been a system automatically pings user as the S8 become more active
They need to contribute more to their own profile
But is also like
Tan-tan no one has ever been seen
That has not been manually past moderation
Okay
So that's very
Big sacrifice
Take a self I think we have probably killed off
Like 80 million accounts
Enough
Power to do that manual
Monterey
I mean we have hundreds of people doing now
This makes sense for you because like you said most user and upload look at 200 photos
Yeah
So you want to make sure that these are high-quality to under photos
Right so I mean if you do that your excitement goes down a lot
But it's also we have to do that then we have to develop like a profile information system
For users to fill in the profile
They need to feel more alive so it's all
We have profile tags
And I think that's like 85% of the user
Filling out tax
That's always also
Quite Vegas assassin
And then since I sign up with their phone numbers
We used to foam mattress
Instead of the Facebook
So what we do there is that
We blocked all your phone contacts
It's like almost everyone
They don't want to see their color
What About Us
What they want
Right
We push people who are secondary
The friends of friends are actually okay
Got it
So that's how we used to call
Are you sign up and they automatically paying your whole contact list
That's what I mean you can call it features but I think it's more like it
You know operational Rockford IL
Exactly how you operate
Are you Union
And you got everything through
The useless
Cases
Make sure that user experience is optimized
For your moderation do you use automation like machine learning
We're looking at that for now but
So far is Alden Iowa
And that's the thing with China is quite cheap
So I said the funny thing is that we looked at some external
AI Solutions right for doing this
At which everyone else uses
More expensive Facebook
Popular
So it took you don't even automate this you don't need to
Operation it
In China you can
So you have to be able to do that
So do people just moves
How do you prevent people from just moving the conversation to WeChat
Wednesday meat on Santa we want to maximize use experience so we don't want to print
I mean that's a natural need
I mean would we prevent them from exchanging phone numbers
. that's silly
Which has is probably more convenient than phone numbers
At this point
So where did what's the problem we saw like I said is 4
Singles to meet people
We're not falling the hole
Keep in touch with your friends part because that would be just directly competing with each other
Yep
A WeChat is not good for meeting new people
No no no no that's intentional use their biggest issue is that it's getting diluted right
Dating is a heavy that neuter of the French reference
So they don't want that is very weak.
And another thing is that even
If they change WeChat
Does the conversations tend to be quite short clip
Because it's not a friend
This is a potential
Girlfriend voice
Is it works out then that's one person that you got if it doesn't work out you never talked to the right
So it doesn't really matter if that thing happens on
Countdown for WeChat because it's not like a long-term
Relationship
Could you discuss the monetization strategy for 10:10 and would you monetize the same way if it was a western
Product
Tim Short Term I think our Revenue
Strategy is very similar to how we would do it in the West
Right now it's kind of subscription-based
It's like buddy out of service
You pay a monthly fee
For a
Different sorts of
A premium features
What is a premium product right you can use it there's no
Can use it very well as a free user
But if you
Buy a subscription
It's much better
So that's what we're doing and actually
Butts
One of the things with China versus the West I think
Is that
The median arcuate
Tend to be lower
But you can definitely get the average are put to be higher
Salar outliers mostly about the top 1%
If you find Revenue models were there's no limits on how much you can spend because the subscription obviously if you want to spend more
There is healing right
But if you find
Irelia model such a sin
Games or live streaming rights where you can spend as much as he wants
The pool house
Yeah and then there's people spending tens of millions amount
Brighton
Those are at like 1% of the revenues
And you use a significant increase the
The average RP
So those are things we are going to look at
Ecobee4
But there's no need for us to be too aggressive about it yet because
We're still melted in a gross
So it's not mushy
If you look at the
Profiles of the most active users on 1010
Are there all
Just young users or are they
Different
Profiles different
Kinds of user
Nowadays since we have reached a certain scale we used to be very much about
Miriam Makeba
What is canopy in expanding
So is it
It's more
Expanding towards all sorts of people
But it's
More of a focus around young people
Now it's like 25
Interesting used to be in college
Nose people helping
Out of college and working for a lot of surge of users were like 35 buses
And for the loss of War 35
Or even older
What has attracted them
To come
But the thing is like I said there are really knows alternative
Looks like neither online or offline
So if you want to meet someone
Which
If you're like a single or the divorced person or something
I mean
That's like a
Kung Fu right that's it like a super
You have to
So as long as they know about us they're going to try it.
How do you think the dating culture is Tianjin do you think 10th and contributed to that change
Only hope we have contributed
I think the Revolutionary service was really cute
So they can alike
Open up this whole
Web friends
Kind of notion
It's kind of like
Facebook
Which had an order this world about dating
And they were smart about it so this quickly switch over to friends management
Which is much larger
Frosty
WeChat already owns that market that doesn't really make sense
See that's how they did it
It was all about
Strangers
Don't have any friends
That's so
I mean people my age that I know of
Drop in China
I mean half of the MetLife.
Throughout
That's how big I think
So
I think the whole you know online Romancing
Revolutionize
Widely accepted among the population for use
So that's nothing
Made any difference
I think what were you kinda like
Hopefully contributed to is that
We made it easy
In recent
Biggest reasons your sister
Has not been too many good solution
And I wouldn't say we are
That's awesome
Either
Butts
We're definitely better than most of the competitors
So
That's why even though I think we have
Big room for improvements
We're still
Better so.
Significant
A matches like over ten billion matches today send each matches like over the two people right so it's like
20 billion experiences
And even like a we don't know how many people
You know got together because of this
But even like a very conservative
Estimate is tens of Millions
With n
There is like
300 million singles word you know people who could
Be counted in that category
So tell him
Quite significant
Witness with any dating app
Idiopathic effect measures
Not prevent frost and harassment so far
Especially for the production of the women use
What are the things that you have done
That your products that work well
And what are the other new measures you may want to add
Overtime Timothy music
Express even better and safer
So
I can't talk
In Broad Strokes about
What we have done we can't I can't go into details because
It's Secret
It's like a
Charter anti-hacker can obtain
I'd like
Ever continuous prices also
That the spammers and Salon they tend to operate in
Did they have a huge like
Supply chain
That's all there is there are people who are specialized in terms of
Trading accounts
People who are specialized in terms of
Getting matches
34A specialized in terms of getting those matches to add other accounts on WeChat
And then there is another group of people who taught Chats on WeChat to get their business.
Assembly line
Old fourth Parsons operated by different people
And it's quite professionally operated
What I think we even know the office
And I by now I think there's only like one or two players left that still are able to do anything
Because we busy
The barrier text barrier of getting
Is today being able to do anything
So big now
Most people just can't do it
So it is all about this kind of like
Pacioretty how to hack your account
Game
You
Prevent them from being able to do each of these four steps
Lights
You have to do it in a way where
Even if they know what you do
They can't do anything about it
He cannot be baseball all strategies
If they don't know what we're doing
Then it works if they know then you can just recommend it
Beds for sample if they build a certain type of profiles and we we
Find certain keyword
And we we we we Banda Ms on a TV
Then it's very easy for the day because
And you just remove the keyboard
By doing this what we did is that we educated
So we made them better we made them
Create
Profiles in the future that look more like a real person
Which is really bad you don't want you want you don't want. It's right there
If you reach write essay in Indian you can
Cast metal
So it's kind of like an enigma
You can never use the information you get from ending
You have to get there you have to
Kill them with other means
Because the whole thing is that you don't you don't you can't let them know that you know
So it's quite complicated but but in the end you have to
Use methods were
Even if they know what you do there's just no way around it
It's like a hard block
Whosampled the day by Bunches of love
Phone numbers like 10000.
Sequential phone numbers right
So if you see
Certain patterns are in infinity band or 10000
Becomes much more expensive than by those numbers
Stuff like that
I didn't we have problems mental
Thousands of different goals
And it isn't a i formulas for 404 how to cash them
Difficult
ShopRite like a Spam account in Samsung
I think we have probably done this
Better than any other player in the social sphere and I include all the friends management
Services Selter
I mean we talked to two people managing and dispatch on WeChat they were scared of
Like
How high we set the bar
80% of people we kill off are not even
Define that's timers
So
The result is that you don't have to see that many spammers on
At least compared to most other services.
So in 2018 we all win this this so-called phone call or Pete for social apps in China with a lot
Water companies launching new chat apps or social networks and investors pouring a lot of money into these products
But it's
, we agree that it's still very difficult to challenge the dominant position that WeChat has in all Chinese people social
Do you think startups
In the field should
Seek to challenge at all or should they just work with WeChat
I think like
Social is a pretty Broad
Concept
But this phone call what we're referring to I think
Part of its with where we talk about you know
Socializing with strangers. Kind of adopted because of our acquisition
I think
People people
Succeed with social app
Exit opportunities
So.
I think more than half
And then the other part which is people doing you don't like the friends management part trying to challenge WeChat
And I think it's smashed if more difficult
I wouldn't say that it's impossible
I think there's definitely
Opportunities out there because
To the two days there is not been a proper
Implementation of something like
Instagram
Or
Snapchat
In China
People failed
4 years
We doing Facebook
In China
Yogi hot Tyson
God's favor
Facebook
It went with the whole friends feet something that works at all in China
And obviously
Right so is it is it is not about
If the concept works or not this is just about
If you are able to operate
Correctly like I said
Send it
Socialism
Quite difficult you have to really get into the minds of users
And then you have to implement a simple today
So I think you need a lot of experience
You know a lot like birds
I think
Entrepreneurs like that
So I think
If I'm seen with tried something like that he would have a pretty good track
He was come out right on
He knows his stuff work with social but there's not
478 years
It's not that people work without experience
Become a master at Social
So I think the biggest block
So that combination just hasn't really happened yet
Only very few
Can do it maybe you can or do it again or someone like Alex true or lie
Lewis from
Musically if it come out
Let's do it again baby
There's not a lot of people
And you need a lot of luck and I mean which I think is much more dominant than Facebook it says follow
Because they have the whole i m park
And I am I think it's even more important than friends feat
Earlier you mentioned
That that when it comes to our proof of Chinese users
The median
Arpu is low
But the average the mean could be high because of the whales
Of the Hyatt
Yes so
Ization He also mentioned maybe gaming or
Live streaming are better ways to
Capture the whales
Getting to spend
Without much upper limit
Don't when it comes to motivation for you
Why did you choose not to build a towel yourself
Instead
Decide to sell
Who was pretty good answers to areas
And we were thinking about selling
Besides mom or did you think of anyone else by
Tencent
We also
Has capability
MS2 areas
So did the thing with Mama on
We were not looking for a
In a position we were racing around
And it was going
Exceptionally well
So I think like two weeks after we open up the round
We already had term sheet
It's an unfinished
So
We would have been able to close the ear out
But at that point
Momo approached us to R&S advisor China Renaissance
And we have never met
Tanya before
So are we expecting was funny quotes
Interesting idea to meet meet up and we did it
And we hit it off quite well
Body of Sonic ice
Yeah I mean like I said it's quite
Difficult to succeed in in the social sphere
Right
So
You noticed that
A lot of the philosophies are actually quite similar similar
I mean mom has gotten a lot of
You know from media and also before I know how smart he is
Andy Anderson
So that was feeling
Installed where they with monetization
You know what to expect
But nowadays since we have
Succeeded quite well with its already we are
Quiet confidence right
Just a year ago but we had
Less than ten times of what we haven't tried so
Weed in Reno
What will happen
And for us to keep growing we would need to spend much more in Athens Market
We will need to significantly increase our marketing budget
So the risks were definitely
I thought that
On the stock exchange their market cap so companies were
A little bit too high
So very big chance of like a big drop
And now I know it's because of this
Something ride the bus
Anything else could also have
You made it happen then you could have even worse
So if that happened and we would stand having you spend our money on marketing
Revenues to grow
We will be in that pretty.
Stop so we definitely had that
Risks to
And the second part is that
Working
Along with mama tambien
I mean if look at us today we are we are running the company
Quiet in the Tennessee
In terms of the product
And operationally
So
Price difference
Getting acquired versus racing after you know around
It's actually not that the Earth
The feeling is quite
Scimitar and we're getting a lot of help
From a stronger
Morris.
Text
Weihai
A lot of different strengths in terms of how we operate our products
So by saying the strength
It's
It's quite helpful for both sides
You know together we Morris own the Hallmark
And the value of that versus you know just
You know competing is I think is much better
Yes
Stop. That's how we thought about it
And iiii don't forget it's even though we have managed to get some Revenue swans
In
No more I like you I think
Audi
Or tencent approach you as well
Alibaba was investor in Toronto
Ashley
And tencent is someone we have spoken with for a long time
And the issue there is
It's like I said you know
Shoot challenge is the delusion
So it's hard to see how we can significantly
Contribution tg2 2 to mm
Regardless how well
We do is more like a financial a message for them
So that's why I did
The date they want to focus more on you know it's a teachable
If we
You know properties with $0.10
In the way we do
We would not get as much
You know how them priority as we're getting
And the Synergy would be quite different
WeChat is not there
But as soon as you can wear with QQ
Could
But
It will be very different conversation
Yes and QQ is like a monster into like those who fought at the end the end the organization rights
Toyota at Mama
Yeah I mean this is really been a pleasure
Has your day today changed
Too much I mean we do try to extract it as much energy as possible but
We both think it's better to operate small end table
Streaming and gaming operations
Do you plan to
Leverage their know-how
And I do more on your own platform
We're just going to leverage their know-how
It's more that we're trying to find ways to get inspired by Gaming and live streaming
Degenerative
You know models that are similar
Masses are exactly the same
And if we do something like live streaming but I wanted to be
A little bit more
Kind of like how
Trifle dessert
Craigslist
Probably like the biggest live streaming
Player out there and you could also say that they are like a live streaming company
But you definitely don't feel that they're alive streaming how products
It's a lot more social
So that's
If we do something like that that's how I wanted to feel like
And that's the challenge but there's no urgency either
So so
It's more and more about girls
I think a lot of Founders in Chinese specially the younger Founders tend to have is attachment
To what they built and they're less
Open to
M&a ideas
What is your advice to Founders like
At what point should you say
I built this but it's probably better off
As part of you know another company
Yeah I don't know how
How blunt I can be
Just completely blondes
If you do not feel
As the founder
You don't get quite far from seeing the money
But that's a major difference
Yeah you got a lot of faith
And I don't know if you're doing if you're doing a starter for face work for it
Money in the long run I think most people
For the money
This week in a basketball forum
But the Detroit is find someone who can be a partner
If you went out that your garage
Then you pretty much giving up your baby in take a shower in
You won't have much control the product afterwards anymore
Exactly
So for this episode we experimented with
Crowdsourcing questions from our listeners community in a couple questions from our listeners
And by the way here's a message for our listeners if you want to contribute questions
The haunted house on the show please join our listeners which a group of slack Channel at 9 and 6. Gbc.com
So here's a question from Jenny was a co-founder of walk the chat a WeChat marketing agency what is the
Chris Astoria managing
Data in China what kind of regulatory difficulties have you encountered with
Regard to data on your platform for example users my post
Revealing photos of themselves and how do you make full use of data other than for optimizing a product
Okay so
Tom Thumb we try to be a very data-driven
P1 for many years
And with this
Is it a sin all sources
Wrong way
But I think in a long
Run
We felt everything we saw from Facebook made
So much sense
So we wanted to operate the products
Run a T Test
Don't try to be to top-down driven
Don't rely on genius theaters
Did anyone with the bright ideas to try out their stuff and it did if datawise it's good
If it's not you drop
And sales tax
Sailor Lee
You know release early and its rates
That that sort of
Thinking right
And aside from that in terms of data obviously
So I'll wear them
And for us
I mean
The people you see is
Is based on
An algorithm
So that's like
The key part of our product
So that's obviously a big
Carter Harvey news
Data
To try to optimize the user experience report for users
But
Think of that ass
Having any
Privacy plication
Because no one
I was looking at it it's just like machine learning
In terms of other other parts
Like I said we manually moderate
So
All explicit content
Are filtered out
So I don't think you have
Ever you would ever see anything bad on them
That's been the culture for so long now
People don't upload explicit content
How do you spell flight like
It's less than
0.1% of our content
That actually is bad
It's not
A person that just like a shoe or something
In the dust of the biggest issue
So expressive, and stuff like that is actually not a big issue
And like I said spammers evens to do something
Because we have so strict
Monitoring of every like automatic
So they did they cancel
So
Even people saying bad words
It's a
Super small percentage of
Hobbs architects
Here's the next question from json Liu
A software engineer at Google
How did you validate your product market fit
And get that first round
Active users
And what a mess
Actress do you use
Help you to do part of the interracial
Yeah so
I think I went through muscle.
One part was this offline
Acquisition of users
One part was that we invited all uses on p12 Jun-hyung
And that's like an unique as if no one else has
Because that
Basically the best-looking guys and girls you can find in China
Rats
We don't get too many people to sign up with like 20,000
Interval scale didn't make a big difference between X alexiad users
You just can't get anything better
So so so so that's one part and then
And the rest I can describe in terms of like the philosophy and the end of operation rationale
Who won the 2000 starter
Underestimate
How much learning
One has to have the patience
Just two people
Without doing pee while you are never
Handmade thinking work
The idea could be exactly the same
Far out wrong in like so many seals of our philosophies
Ouija 1
At the front
Time points
You know it would just be laughable experience from a big company what is a human attention
Orali
Or Google may help somewhat
But unless you make your fair share of mistakes and learn from them
It's not enough
Exactly I mean
One example
The first two three years AP1
We are not products ribbon nortek driven
We were Grand River
So all was about building this
High and ran people with
But that's not how you succeed with scaling internet
But with all that experience you wouldn't have the initial users
Oh no
Exactly
I mean I just know why you can succeed without trying to do it brand ribbon this is no way
And also feels like
No matter what you want to do you have to do something to you personally
Passionately believe in
So that even if the real you talk is different from other people's wrote
Overtime
You learn and adjust
Everything you did before becoming used for
For the next venture
Definitely
You have finally a question from eating you along a business developing professionally Hong Kong with also Swedish Chinese
What are the skill sets and valleys from Sweden that has helped you
Imbued are startup in China what are the advantages and disadvantages of being sweaters Chinese
So internship first disadvantages I knew very little about China
And the problem was that
I was I was so bad I didn't understand how bad it was
That's that's a like a common issue I think with most things I've seen many employees as well
Or or competitors
They're just
You're not good enough to understand how bad you are
It took me seven years
To realize that okay I don't understand this job
That's very honest
I tried to compensate for that
Only took a year to starting to understand more, better
That's a bit of a mess you see the problem is hard to solve
Like I said
Having seen many perspectives of different things
I think you have the much open mind
About them everything
And Sweden is a very
Communistic
I think it's even a communist level
It is a cultural issue tried so
Is everyone is married
That I think keeps employees happy
I'd say it's easier to
To to interact with people
Well
You don't have this body bossy attitude
So I think that's one of the things that have
We have had going for us
We have pretty happy employees generally
But you mentioned that you don't believe in having a genius boss
So everybody can have the idea and you stayed at to test it tested that's good
If you look at Facebook most of the stuff that actually made in words
We're not
From something
What's something
So the genius of Zuckerberg is trying
To build a platform that
Purchases
Brides and what makes it very easy
Back in the days where they were doing just PHP in web websites
They could babysit single lines and colors
I mean I don't think anyone has ever
I also think because of your experience living
The Western Society you know how dating could be different
And how
The ways people meet each other could be different
Because of you
Robin China all you see is how the Chinese
Way of interacting
And also we have a lot of information from Western companies
Right and I think it's quite hard to understand them
Without having my
Experience my sweetheart
Which should I open ask one more question before
Zara cosita quickfire
Session
Which is like you said not many founders
I've experienced
Living and working overseas
In addition to making something work in China
A lot of Chinese models
Can be exported
The other Emerging Markets
Other world
The next new 1 billion
Users will come from outside of us and China
So what do you think of companies like bytedance trying to expand
In four markets
And for you personally
You feel that either inside 10 times
Or more or
Something new are you home later
Do you want to do something that's more global
In the next ten
Frontier
Justice symbol
Yes definitely
I mean
Once in a time in T1 we
Try to Define our core values
They didn't help at all
I mean for what it's worth one of them was like a Global Perspective
So I think that's one of the things that makes it
Different than other companies
So we're definitely have a global Outlook
Everything we do but we have to focus on China
And we have a good shot
You know those
Expanding
In two different areas in Social
In China and also if you know but we've been dating and social about abroad
So that's something we have already started doing
You know some working but it's not
The highest priority yet
I think that's a Subaru
Impress company that that's
They're probably did the one in China has implemented this whole
Can a Facebook
Type of operation
Data-driven
A b testing town like
Open up everyone can try different sorts of things
Culture
I am going to like your faucet
Did they are very aggressive
Brett
Maybe to Abra
So if there's any
If there's anything.
You know
Wood
B22 there a disadvantage it's my feeder aggressiveness
That's also their strength
So we will see how it goes
But it's definitely
Exciting company
And one-of-a-kind I think in the world
There's no one
The apps I've seen the in the west who are
You know Jose to their level of rest.
We do see a lot of Founders from Latin America from Southeast Asia
India
Beginning not just want to learn from us
Breaking Christian learn from what fungus in China have done as well
It is super exciting for us
To be in the middle of everything and help Founders learn from each other
We we think. I'm building a Global
Community Global product this is much more interesting way to live
So next we'll jump into Irondequoit fire questions so we can just say the first thing that comes to your mind
Admire the most and why
Assistant jobs
And it's just as good as he has been
Able to
Absopure visions of what series
What what is doing in
Haven't
So well
And have been able to get this whole team to
You know
How do you say race
The whole standard
To his level and get it to get them. Shift
The stuff
On time
And I think that's also came from
His
Misfortune
He would never have been able to do that do it if everything is well
Desperately
What's a book you read recently that you recommend
Have not read too many books recently
I was not too impressed by the first book
And then I was
And even less impressed by the
Beginning of the second book but
From the second part of a second blog on Tumblr
The whole of a circle
The Sci-Fi Park
Wow
Really I think the people interruptions could be better but I mean Certain Justice I park
Awesome
Lastly what do you do for fun
I just came from Boston
So I've been doing Auto. Boxing
Trainers with cats
I need to lose weight so so so so this is super good for that
Aside from
I don't know what's the movies
Play some games
Bisbee bought every game you can buy but
I have not said anything
Really
Sense
Miss college days
I used to be like
Elite Quake play
Play Quake 4 like
Call Doris Day for 4 years
So I was like top 10 in the world
Airport
Equate one
But then I
Took too much time is allowed
And having pretty
Pick up games
What do you see yourself doing in 10 years
10 years
I have a pretty strong entrepreneurial
Spirit soul
I'm probably going to be
Entrepreneurial project
I'm sure you will
Great global
Thank you for your time and we really enjoyed this conversation
Thank you
Airline flight 798
San Jose
996 Venture Capital firm based in Silicon Valley Shanghai
Why in Beijing we have been partnering with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past eighteen years from seed through.
With 6.2 billion dollars in capital under management across 13 funds ggv in bus
In consumer new retail social Digital internet Enterprise cloud and Frontier Tech
GTB has invested over 290 companies with more than 45 companies valued at over a billion.
Dollars
Formula companies include Airbnb Alibaba
C trip
Didi chuxing demo hashicorp hellobike cows keep slat
Square Hotel wish soundtrue white white and others find out more at
Qvc.com we also highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat group as La China where we regular
Fish are inside events and job opportunities related to attack in China join these groups at 9
TxDOT ggv c.com community
You have any feedback on this podcast or would like to recommend the gas please email us I-96
IGG bc.com