My dear
Welcome to the 9th at 6 podcast brought to you by ggv capital
On the show interview movers and shakers
China's tech industry
As was Tech leaders
Weather us China
Cross-border perspecta
My name is Khan song, managing partner at GTV capital and I've been working at startup
Investing in them in both the US and China for the past 20 years
My name is Zahra Jones an investment analyst RGB capital and a former journalist
Why is the show called 96:6 is the work schedule than any Chinese Founders have organically adopt
That is
9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
To us
996 captures intensity Drive
In speed
Of Chinese internet companies many which
I'm moving faster
But even the American consul
Higher One
On the show today we'll continue with our new series to wear instead of having a guest
Hans and I will talk about a particular topic that self-interest are listeners
On today's episode we're going to talk about why we invested in yellow
So we at GTB recently announced the major investment and yellow a leading micro Mobility platform based in Brazil
Which has raised 63 million dollars in series a led by Juvia capital
Yellow laws Brazil's first dockless bike sharing service in Sao Paulo in August
Is also become Paladin e-scooters and developing e-bikes
To provide a comprehensive micro Mobility solution
Toozers in Brazil and Beyond
Additionally yellow also offers digital payments
There is yellow pee platform
So it might be sinking why are we talkin about
A Brazilian startup on 96 a show about tech in China
Because our decision to invest and yellow is very much informed by our experience of investment in China
Soe hunts could you share more about this linkage and why you make this decision
Sure
Zara
I think my being
Global BC fire
We have data points
From multiple regions
Before we
Decide to make this
The best bunny yellow
And Brazil
Aiming line entire Latin America
I'll partner teaching
Jenny with a number in bus
Cinemability
Whether it's a
Didi in China
Hello byte
In China
Grab
Southeast Asia
I like how are you
In line in the US
And their number other investor
Not debating
Category
We are
Chuck realize that
Urban Mobility
He is a global phone
That given organization
In traffic
Congestion
Pollution
It just itches more solution needed
Subwoofer
Problems in Excel problems.
Not just in Beijing now
Prison sentence but also in
Mumbai in in Bangalore
In Jakarta
In
KL Singapore
Also in New York San Francisco Highway that's why I was in some Paulo and
We look at
Apollo it's the 4th
Congested
Most congested city in the world
He has a
Subway system
Take care of
8 million
Riders a day
Convertible to Tokyo
Just under 9 a.m. for 4 Beijing
Yeah traffic
Congestion still a major problem
Suburbanization
So it is a problem that we
Nodejs global
Solution will be
Global
Secondly
When we look at this team this team
Very impressive
The CEO
Musa
Edward Olmos
Has Manufacturing
He built up a largest bike manufacturing company
In
Brazil
Is familiar with supply chain in China
And he sold his company successfully
To a Canadian player
A couple years
And then that that is to other co-founders
The head of product
Head of
Both came from 99
For those who have Tri quad
DD has done
Worldwide
Didi invest in 99
Largest at local
Rice & Company
Brazil
AutoZone Palo about two years ago and then acquired it
End of last year beginning of the this year
And so
Are people who decide to leave 99 due to their own thing
And thanks to Carlo from
Monashees
One of the top
Maturity stage winter fun in Brazil
Is co-founder Ariel
Android auto
So it was
Different timing
China looking at how
Mobike
Lenovo Mahalo bike
I start to
Take over China with a bike sharing
And so
It it's it's not on the Visas are having global dances
You got the founders themselves are increasingly more gullible
Looking for ideas and inspiration the solution nachos from the us anymore
But also from increasingly from China as well
So having the duopoly of datapoint
Please lot easier
Avicii in the founders
Dubus III
Dupaco
Next
So a lot of problems that people are facing today are
Global in nature
Then you can find solution in
Racing
Thoroughly
We we like this
Yellow because nausea
This is interesting for me
Micro Mobility standpoint they have bikes
Scooters and bikes
And other things
But in addition
Because
Over 80% of a population
In Latin America
Heartland Bank
Meaning that they don't have a pension with a
Deposit you don't have
Saving or checking account
So a lot of people carry cash
Witham
And how do you get
People who only have cash
To participate
T-Mobile payment
Participate
E-commerce
To pay for a service
Coming up with a QR code face
Solution
Alipay
Which has some simple
Was to a WeChat pay makes a ton of
If the
If I'm the 919
IDE not working
King Dedede
After that
The acquisition
I'm not seeing what was happening in China
It probably will have taken
A longer time
You coming with us
So the fact that
Did the
Almost two companies into one makes it and with experience team now they have a successful
Subway
Made a lot of easier
Would make a bat in the new reach
Bus
Why is it so significant that
Founder and CEO Eduardo Musa has a background in manufacture
2 question
I think for lawsuit
Who's we are corrupt or worked in or invested in
China
China has a unique Advantage because either the manufacturing center or factual the world
So it's very easy to get there any hardware product
Prototype curated
And manufacture a maskil
Extremely quickly
Pitea
To do that from us 44 you're from Europe
Is Reykjavik
This is why you
You see in a dream space TGI
Is the PopularMMOs
Competitive
Most aggressive
At launching new products
Quickly overcome
A lot of competitors worldwide
In this market
And so
For bike sharing scooter sharing
We also thought that given the tariffs
That exists barriers
Is this not America
Imports will always cost more
You'll take more time unless you are there
WeChat
Which increase
Cost and if you can manufacture locally
Then near the spare parts
Scuba cycle and is more environmentally friendly and also cost
Sufficient so for variety of reason
Hobby and more
Vertically integrated approach
In America
Special on America
And Siri
Makes a lot of sense
The challenge
Is a find a team
That has
Starting to disciplinary
Mean that they're people who understand offline World Manufacturing
Production
As well as understand internet
Product iteration
Entomology a pack in skillet
So this team
Having have the best possible worlds was very rare
Exciting Force
What's really exciting for me as well as I'm
Zhangjiajie becoming more and more global
Everyday and
I should we just went on a trip to Southeast Asia a month ago where we went to a Singapore in Jakarta and met with
Local entrepreneurs and VCS
I'm and really saw the energy of the entrepreneurial landscape there
So how do you think Latin America as a region
Going forward cuz a lot of people still have
Reservations about like the boys abilities or macro factors
Are you at all worried about these issues in
How do you think about
The future of the region
I live through the Asian financial crisis
In the
Late night
I was working in Singapore
Sowa. It's about happening in the
In the region
Even some who lived
In the US for almost 20 years
America over the last
20-30 years
You see that functions rates have show
Economic welfare also
The key lesson that we learned
Omnibus in China
Is that when you have enough of a internet penetration
Weather is
Through PC desktop
Or
ABC order
Throughout
Smartphone
You have a chance to have a foundation
Technology
Make changes
In society and bring about if you can
Ambassador in Alabama since 2003
Did Ubisoft pforzheim
Call Jack ma brought about a hole
E-commerce era
Into China out of nothingness
Because of he
PetSmart Culebra
That's that's
Bicicleta beneficios
Internet penetration
And use.
How to build a table out
And then.
TiVo
When you see when we see in there enough of
A swamp in fishing
Livermore internet
Coupled with urbanization
Trends
You started
See a middle-class forming
You spell see you then
They operate in a more efficient manner because
Is the benefit of Technology
Tax benefit of The Proven business models
T-Mobile
So when that happens will feel the a new economy while you merch
And in it will grow at a faster
Toothpaste that economy
So
The society
Become more stable
Overtime
More fungus will be able to make impact
With
I think the learn
From both us and China
So that's how
Hypothesis
That was seeing somebody some of the happening
Indonesia
Southeast Asia and North America ready
The telephone number of unicorns
Indonesia now you have tokopedia
Pokemon pack
Traveloka
As well as Go Jack
And grab
So they are five or six
Y******
In Indonesia already
A country that has almost 300 million people
And it's cheaper Capital roughly around $3,000 us
In a similar to watch Hannah Wes
About that
10 years ago
And you look at. America also see a number of unicorn snot what is the 99 soul
Or is it
Mobile
Hosparus
Or whether it's a rocky
And we have a puppy tray to mercadolibre
So you have you have number of public and private unicorns
For me in love my car ready
Because smoke penetration rate
In Brazil's now 50%
In Mexico is a 1/3
So
You start to see
Early indicators
America even notice a
Quite a bit disparity between
Overall GDP per capita is roughly around $10,000
You asking some of the major countries
So you still seeing that in both regions were
Go to Southeast Asia or South America
Birthing side that fathers can learn
From us and China
And this where
In those selected areas were quitting or existing investors mobile
Could be helpful
To them we're willing to consider
What mix is best when
And help them to
I found a really interesting that these days entrepreneurs in Emerging Markets are not just learning from Silicon Valley but
Also learning from China a lot
They they call themselves like the mate one of
Southeast Asia artist of Latin America or whatever so
Silicon Valley is no longer
The only place where they can take inspiration
Yeah you know back when
Jesus found 18 years ago
The world had
Roughly less than
A few hundred million internet users
And most of them were in the in the US
So
It's very easy
Before whatever works is it
Also works at everywhere else
I'm over last 18 years you see China emerging now
Almost
Just admitting unicorns
As IUS.
In China as a developing country
As450
Frontier City
And in this 450R cities
Each one has different
Macabre
So you look at that
Argue
If you discount the language barrier
China has seen any kind of issue at least most of the issue
Emerging Markets
Country has to go through
In one of those
New York cities
So
Whatever problems you are trying to solve your own
Home Country developing
Market
Somebody in China has
Uncomfort
Something similar
And it has
Figure out some way to deal with it
So are the minimum earning what channel
Has done is
Is a
Higher starting point
To make it easier to figure out
What is what kind of localization and they will be a lot of position
That's still to be needed
In your home country
But at a minimum
Having both us
A place to learn makes a lot of
Easier to try
Skip
Thinks that that may not work
And be able to resume stopped after this
It could work
Massive lot of time in
And one of the areas we investing is called too high or a Chinese founders
Is targeting
Are there a merge
Markets around the world
I wonder how do you think about
How do you think the Chinese entrepreneurs
Compare with Loco on
Foreigners when it comes to
These new markets are they
Because of their experience of scaling companies in China are they
Advantageous when it comes to going to these markets or with a Locos
When the day is the end
That's the one. Dog question
I think that you would like like to ask
Cuz we're both of us in China
Were there more Chinese company come to the US
Working US starts ever crack
China I think that's a common question the media and other folks like to ask this
But what we actually are seeing
Over last several years
Is that
The US companies
Startups
Do better in the a.m.
America
Especially North America in
Parts
Of Western northern Europe
And then
Traditional Australian music
Some of the larger
Casinos companies
From the US
Art
Expanding into
India
Leveraging the high quality of Indian executives
It's already working this
Do something else
In the home country
As well so that's where the US companies
Extendo table spend time
And Welton
And for the Chinese company
Call me after greater China and then sausage
Maybe India maybe not
But the Middle East
Eastern Europe
Even Africa
Art
Very nice
Adidas popular view exception are in Brazil
In xiaomi if I were you
Some of the new entrance
Star in Mexico
So you do see each other's company
Compete better in the developing world
And leveraging what they have
Tested in De
So the question is will the local startup
In developed
Countries do a good job of
Meeting The Challenge from Chinese company
What do they collaborate
Or would they learn very quickly
And be able to leverage their lesson
From us in China
And therefore apply localization as needed by quickly
Indigo country
Weeks to see Daddy Chinese food
What is Alibaba
Or it what u d
Xiaomi
Becoming more open
These local country
And follow my tedium by dance and others as well
I think that you will see a lot more
Investment from China
With the the fast racing
Local startups
So that there's a way to work together and for the local Starbucks
Livermore
The Chinese partners
I think that's probably the most common
Cooperation
Also season comes that shopee
That took money from tencent
And then are building their own company
Home businesses
In Southeast Asia
Many of their
Executive
Bob spent a portion of their life
In in the Southeast Asia
Does this kind of high protein
They could be some
But may not be a majority
Overtime they could be more of them
But with weave
We think that it cloudy should be some Chinese companies
And look.
What happened more
The Archimedes like everybody else that have Bob Lazar exam station they are
Off reading
People sent from
Dd7
Consuming people from Beijing
To a lot America
You meant to be seen that the
The team from
China with all much Yuan exact experience
Stop to local market
And that's something that will closely closely monitor
All the founders with Matt in both Latin America and Indonesia are very fluent in English
Yeah that's what that's one thing that even caught our attention
Where in post office takes a lot of America
I think the
It's very interesting for us
CDs founders.
Arlen quickly on what's happening in US
But increasing willing to learn from
Looks like ourselves but what's happened
In China and even those with China on their own
Through their alumni work
So as long there more Chinese people
Start studying southeast Asia and not America
It makes it easier to Foster
Collaboration
Between startups in those regions
With with China this makes it easier for the local founder
How to go to China
Through the
People to learn what else
Week we think.
The world be a much safer
Better place
Willis and want knowledge sharing
Understanding each other and benefit from
Trump's knowledge
Yeah in like 96 itself has a very low body
Actually have a pretty sizable audience in
Police is like southeast Asia and Latin America lie we were kind of surprised how it caught on quickly
With this Global Market
I think that's because
People around the world are increasingly realizing the importance of learning from China no matter
Where they are
I also wanted to touch on the topic of payment because part of yellows
Product they not only do
Transportation Mobility but they're also
Launching yellow pay platform which is similar to a leap in WeChat pay in China
It's QR code-based so
Allows user to transform cash into digital credit for a yellow services
So through a network of certified
For sale such as convenience stores New Stand and bakeries
Users can buy yellow credits in cash by scanning a QR code
And then apply those credits to yellow rice
And we've seen the power of QR code
Face
Mobile
In China where are the mobile payment Market is
10 times larger than that of the US
And just like how Alibaba incubated alipay
Groton Connecticut
We believe that yellow pee also presents
Agree opportunity in the region
So
Missing payment is such a huge effort
Why does a yellow has a chance to make that happen
In China
Alipay
Unpopular
Partial because
Creek Apartments
A lot of merchants
Don't want to spend money
Took to have a terminal
Process credit cards
And then one smartphone
Become
Quite popular becoming popular
In China
WeChat pay was born
It made a lot easier
To tip the merchants
Or buy stuff on Merchants or
Pay your friends
For money you owe them
Or just say
Lobster Chinese New Year
Morning cursive
People to
Answer to a pulse
Triplebyte information knowledge
So you chop a really took off in China and now
I'm everywhere you go there they are a lot of interested or even want to
Take cash only
Accept WeChat pay
And it's so
How fast is Rose
A Mesa
No looking at
Post office in
America
Where the person
High prison population
I don't give a
My bank
Account
In China with
Wechat WeChat pay
You can link your
WeChat pay were already paid
To a debit card
If some of these
Countries
Emerging Markets
Most people don't even have it
So
Baby frog
I'm from a casket Society
To a cure
Code based
Screamin we sing there's a
High chance that could happen
If those Country RV have
Tight enough
Of smartphone penetration
So that's our hypothesis
This is how about that came up with
That we think will be very popular
And we'll see on the neck
Next five years what does our bare bear fruit or not
But it definitely makes so exciting
Experiment
And financial is worth more than Goldman Sachs
It's party imagine
We have a lot of respect for Goldman Sachs
What Investment Bank
But it's impressive that last over a decade or so
So you what you took a trip to Brazil
Couple weeks ago yourself
What was your impression
What did you see
What is going to Jakarta or to some Paulo
It is impressive
See the face
Pace of urbanization
Have you seen markets
And also
You see that there's just a lot of
Activity Auto founder
Who are
Impressive
And well as
Educated in softball
And want to do something
For their country
Weather is the founders we met in
Jakarta or
Looks like yellow in some Paulo
Every one of them
Trying to figure out how can you Leverage
Archaeology
Elsewhere
To help their country
Become more prosperous
Safer
And
Facilitate the growth of new economy
That would be more efficient
Secret society
Benefits to more
The mask
Market the unbanked population
And I think that is
Extremely synonym
And for something to be big
Alibaba
How to get big in China
For WeChat and
Peking Beijing China
They haven't we something
That's useful to society
To bring analogy
Democratizing
Inbreeding benefits
To the mass Market
You don't do that
Then the Piston will have more niche
And doctors
It's not going to BSB
So
Seymour Thunder
What will you do that makes it our job
Exciting
And interesting every single day and makes our life
Some meaning
So my last question is I think
All of this is true and
Saying it is easy but having a gut
Tibet on a brand-new region and a significant amount of funding
Into a region
That is pretty new to us
Takes a lot of
Courage
So what was
The Tipping Point for you and you realize this is something I really want to
That what was that decision process like
For you
I think talking to both
Adorno
And his team
Ariel
Android auto
What's important
Also speaking to
Other PCS
In a company what is Carlo from Moana
Teaching are they from FaceTime
And other side class 5
Grishin robotics
It's as you can tell there
This is a group of
People what does VC offenders
Want to make a huge difference
In there in there in the region
And a very willing
Going to cooperate
Chanel Chen
Take notes
From other regions
Iqos USA
Super 8 News
Foremost
These were quite some of even travel to China already
If I look at the website for modishshe
Singapore languages
Portuguese Spanish
Chinese Inn
English
So when you see other people or not share more than 96 body
Much more collaborative
Global
It makes it a lot easier for us to feel that we're on the right side
History
Azaria done amazing job of functions podcast
And also recognized that the meetups
Everywhere we go
We see people who have lived
In at least five cities
Woodbury Commons Outlet in five cities
Somebody
Even the content like myself
And you see people who have travel around the world and
Receipt more things
In the mirror of the fast
Connecting the dots
I want to be helpful
That just gives us
A lot of Hope
And in
Remind us what we saw in
In China
About
1518 years
So
ABC is in the business of recognizing patterns
That that's smart
2000 BC
End up seeing a pattern
Asuna niedenfuer date of Constitution
And hopefully
That our hypothesis
Depends on what we have seen elsewhere
That will be right about Southeast Asia
And a lot of America I think we are very focused on investing that are words we know
We don't want to experience in many other things
So we
He will be focus on twins everything a problem in nature and 1/2
To share what we know
USA channel
To be helpful to others
Quotes
Thanks for listening and if you have any feedback or 1A Ridge hunts and I directly you can join our listeners committee
A WeChat or slack at 96. Ggvc. Com
Community
Tankathon
Buddhist episode of 996
Ggv capital is a multi-stage venture capital firm based in Silicon Valley
Shanghai and Beijing partnering with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past 18 years from seed
2p IPO with 3.8 billion dollars in capital under management across age funds
GTA V invest in globally-minded entrepreneurs in consumer new retail social internet
Enterprise cloud and Frontier Tech
GTB has invested over 290 companies with more than 45 companies valued at over a billion dollar
Hours for Phila companies include Airbnb Alibaba
C trip Didi chuxing demo hashicorp
Hello by Adele
House keep
Slack
Square Hotel
Wish soundtrue white white and others find out more at Gigi bc.com we also
So highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat group as last Channel
Where we regular share insights events and job opportunities related to attack in China
Join these groups at 96.3 jvc.com community
I'm going to tell you about our sister podcast
Founder real talk
It is a biweekly show that gets real with under
About the challenges that Founders in startup Executives face
And also how they have grown
From Papa
Experience
The show's host by my fellow managing partner at ggv Capital Glenn Solomon
Audubon Park office
Pretty flower called Fisher again
Past episodes of the show include Stewart Butterfield from slack Sarah Friar from Square
Handmade guitars at from Airbnb
You can take a listen by searching founder real talk and any podcast app
Do you have any feedback on this podcast or would like to recommend the gas please email us at 9 9 6
IGG bc.com