Hi there welcome
To the 9th at 6 podcast brought to you by tgb capital on the show interview movers and shakers
China's tech industry as well as Tech leaders who have a us China
Cross-border perspective on Stone, managing partner at GTV capital and I've been working at startup
Invest in them in both in us and China for the past 20 years my name is
I meant investment analyst igb capital and a former journalist
Why is the show called 96 Chinese Founders have organically
Adopted that is 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
To us996 captures intensity Drive in speed
Of Chinese internet companies many of which are moving faster that even their American counterparts
On the show today we are extremely excited to have yummy
Token
Co-founders of Neil
O'Neill Jim Croce
In Chinese
Nail designs and manufactures smart
Infra perform select
Is currently the largest
Lithium ion battery powered e School
And a leader in Europe as well
As of June 30 this year
New had sold more than 430,000 Smarties
China
Europe
In other countries
Use vision is to become the number one brand for urban Mobility
Power by Design and Technology
Before Neo smart electric two wheel Vehicles didn't exist in
And two wheel Vehicles were perceived low and
The company has changed our perception with their smart E Scooters
Premium bread
No just went public on the NASDAQ
October this year
Did you mean that no serious a back in 20
And Jenny Lee Alcala join the board
We're back the company ever around since then all the way through its IPO
It is now the largest
Shareholding
In a company
We are very excited to have yen
Token
With us today
Almost fresh off a plane from New York
Congrats rapo and welcome to the show
Hi thanks Anne Sentara we are very honored
To be on the show
Yeah actually
CGV happiness
Lot specialist
They like yesterday I introduce my product
To my God
Yeah I did I say you were going to 524 Delphine on time
So how does it feel like
To take a company public
What was your most memorable moment
For your New York
Very exciting very exciting I think it's the most memorable moment for me and token is actually
You know way
That one I waited realize NASDAQ Bell is that your digital now
Literally I mean it's so we were holding hands together pushing that button
What I think
Most Marvel flask
If I may I just too exciting I just forgot talking
You have a background in private equity and also work
Backyard Buffet
Fortuno
Can you talk about your transition
Pharma investment
To install exact
I think it was a very interesting I kick heroin with the kicker Capstone it's the operation of KKR so which way
We are are dropping to the portfolio companies to invest in and the become a sort of a you know a food high map
Part-time exactly was in the
Accompany
And I didn't use the company that has the most technology and most exciting work I have ever take
MLK carry Mei Mezmur traditional companies like call Farms or
Hog farm sending as well as you know liquor companies
Enzo when I got a chance that he actually
You know which an extended offer to musee to join you be part of the new family will I look at this
Is the most high tech company most cool product I was super excited
It was just that excitement at last
The last 4 years
How did she got to meet Jenny
Well it's a ho-3 introduction that I have heard of Jenny and the tgv
In the past so I heard
Introduction to other VCC
Sit on the board and then
Dirty remarks remember I met Jenny at Starbucks in Shanghai so headed to our chat
Was a very interesting on the very very sight
So
Who are your cousin
And why do you think they're buying
Yeah actually 3rb
Big data analysis
All the information we got
Users
Dislike
More like telecommute
And you we're not doing a toy
Cizzorz age
Between 25
Do you like 35
How much are they offering customers and also in our database
We can cisa
Your daily travels around 20km
Animosity trip is
302 350
Which means to say or telecommute vehicle in real life
We are pi to helping them
Things like a boy all the traffic jams other like
City
Movements
Happy to see we
Literally changing your life from
Super rash
City traffic to Lake Health freedom
Just to come on that I think we appear to Young user setting up at ya
Idleman
I think you know he was 25 35 I think hands are already out
That picture
Sola products
I love your products the guy I will have a young mentality
Scooters
Bastille
Help me out
To remind
What the freedom is
In the city I think that's a part of
Emotions
We try to bring tok
It's not a reason why you get so
Lifestyle
Product and brand
In China
It's not a reason that but it I think it's
The lifestyle represent I think we are the first lifestyle-prod in China
I think this two wheeler
Market Linda we hope to actually become Lifestyle brand
In urban Mobility Market
I'm acting weird we're on the way to being that assessor part of that
Amazing accessories.
Mobility of breath it's not only about your major product
Is so buting the environment
Fence for your users
For your daily life
And not only about
Also about
Bugatti Life lyrics
Sell your brand philosophy
And right now we have really strong fruit
Alucard
We have a three different
Calibrate switches to reading girasol the brand
Apparis for exempt one
Leticia I'm going today is the really hot and you never
Community also
B12
Hyper-light
Full life circle
I wrote a review
And just advertising
His own self
Www.com
How are users
Got new accessories
Example
Existing like e-scooter
Brazi wants you have fighting ever since
But please think about exchanging next
Westfield years
But after he purchased our accessories
Immediately become new Rider
Got it in terms of geography
Where are they are they
First-tier cities are lowered
Oui oui cover of a white range wearing a hundred fifty
China I meant I know so 23 countries
Honey Smacks
And so
Yeah how are users leaving
Solace Urban Mobility should we seek traffic conditions not only
First Years
He's wasting the tr3
Steerforth
CDs as well
So it's actually
That
Able to our product able to
To solve users paint
I think that is what
He's a lot to penetrate
China's well
The last week I think you being nosey
You know the most stylish
Scooter out there
They also add a excitement point about users
Is it riding scooter is not
Just your daily commute
It is actually a demonstration of your
Personality demonstration help you or your belief
I think this is regardless where you live
People on
You only love comes only for 5
5 years old
How do you cast
Figure out weight
Enter
And pantry
So many different Market
I think a few things
First walking the Prada is you
To be honest I think
You know if you've been deleting iron-based battery
Scooter it said it's your lithium batteries very light is actually portable for YouTube
Emergency food
People to take at home to charge
How to solve a big boy
And the design is unique
Goodnight I think Nina RM series was the first product
Well first
Mobility product that every 107 International major award
Holly tree house design
Find the product
This is the last 20 years
I'm making examples
I said the usaid award right now
We were the sewer metal
The Bronx was a BMW 5 Series
First we got the silver
But then we thought okay BMW
Okay at least we feel a little better
And it's it is about Services I think we know what how about you know
Well that 570 source
Hi in China now I'm Global you had like 700 sales points is actually what a serious is Carriage to carry us through the
You know this attempt to penetrate that year for tier 5 cities
Because when people buy those scooters
They need
Good after sales services
We have Brenda stores
Provide that service
I think.
Make people feel like they got a
Experience not only the product
But actually through the
Entire usage cycle
How far products
I think that's what we try to use
So tell can what is the design philosophy
Behind
Actually I always have discretion I talked about Ibiza Tony yesterday they give me
Really
Goodspeed back images
The design should be have
Pilots
And right now I lock companies talking about
Should be through all the savjz Brooks group and everything
I've been
Peking Consulting industry
Manny years
Best things to sell
You got
Is sap Define a product should be from your life
The sinks are alike R&D team
The management team
The full monty guy
Finger scooter
Right now they're riding scooter everyday
Eat your
The first-hand user and
Ready
Design products
For yourself
You solve your own problems is better than you
Interpreted something next
Some money
A huge difference
This is Sam Houston
Keith
Secret sauce
Could you also talk about your background
And how you come to join
Yeah my background
High school jobs
The first job I got this
Dishes
In the restaurant
Everything
How to be a highschool dropout
Cool
Betoken magnitude
Like English people to drop off earlier because
Yeah they're lucky
We are we are just
Things through the whole internet's industry growing super fast and learning from internet
And eventually
2007 how to go to Microsoft
Not the words that jump to the top companies call from
Design
Do the languages we just learning
They're like
4 years
Literally I learning my language also my all the professional skill at my work
And the sink sea salt
Is Chi-Chi
Then I make live for me
Bizuayehu spec 24000mah
Founder of iPod
How do you meet
Actually I'm the guy have the idea
Universe bikini
And first-year just
Does seller pay all the time and
Myself
As there is a huge
Products
It's not only about design
An R&D
Issue do you think about the manufacturer the marketing of the sales office Alice is everything
Visualized I'm not the right guy to holding the Hulk
Because I know I truly know myself
Good at something
Anything else
I can learn
Meat saw the guy who introduced me to his friend which is Alicia
It does the founder of the
Auto hold you
And he introduced heesa
Fran history
Call Mimi
And then but then the ventures
That's great
Define albeit
Possibility
Future line here obviously
You know it's your line here this is sitting next to me
Show about creativity of a product
Buck technology
That's all there
The end
Yeah this I will be all about numbers or about how to get the product to the users got to make sure users a status
Spiderwebs out services
Executions into my business
If you take a picture is
Hahaha exactly what we're wearing today
So there's so many things you could
Design the world what especially about scooters
Excite you
The first idea how is it
Shoe selling
Nigh
And doing a Time
I'm leaving Shanghai
From my apartment to the office 4 p.m.
Is a lacrosse
Media
Viral
What your name means
No chance. Taxi
And they're waiting for like five or six buses I cannot lie
Squeezing
Yes and I have my motorcycle butt everyday like
All the gears everything
And also I'm I try to
But wants you off
Sweating office
My boss is
Pizza
I saw my own Solutions
I'll look around I think solder the e-scooters is good Solutions
But doing the time there
Bad quality
And Design
NSYNC I'm the monster
Doing the products for all the
Blacktop 500
Companies
Meaning no reason for them
Maybe I can just do it for myself
This is star
Is the truly
Solve my own problem why did the first scooters
All my friends
Sayoc
Come on I need one
The guy seesaw
Creative director from the
Shoes like
How do I tighten company
The weepy of sow
Tech company I just saw okay
Lil Skies where we never think about
Please riding a scooter
Really cool stuff
Makes sense
So we all know that Hardware is hard
So how do you
Deal with
The whole
Supply chain
Manage
Like this huge operation
A lot of Opera
Well first of all we don't want to take the entire cry.
I think yesterday
HGTV
Event
She told me I should Tony Fidelis at Asbury Park
Earthquake
Where you know he actually Envy
Chinese
Because here in China
They are
A very good set of manufacturing base
And Howard
Manufacturers
Where in the USA live
That's exactly what happened
But we know what we're looking at China Market
It's about
Annually there about
30 million
New electric scooters Mosel asset but still I mean
Scooters sold their so
Nostrum Supply chains there a lot of manufacturing
Suppliers to provide
Components
And also for Mamaki compounds the DTM battery
That manufacturing is also tender in China
Driven by electric vehicles
So it would be benefiting from those
But I'm having said that
We did trying to wait but have to spend a lot of effort into upgrading
Are the quality of RC
Suppliers
Because those supplies used to be providing
Ask partner part 2
You know traditional as a scooters most doesn't have that high-quality
Requirements
So we have to have a very strong
Basically the supplier quality management team
You actually sitting in our suppliers manufacturer
To actually
Inspect air quality
To the helps him to improve
And that was it was
Litter the effort we put in so it wasn't about shortage of Manpower shortage of
Materials
It was a shortage of
High quality stuff
Brightening awareness
The team will hire what you know are entirely
You guys manage our
Supply chain
You know wait wait wait higher from
You know from Huawei from
Letter fonts
Something from automobile
Amazon Prime cancel music
Consumer electronics manager quality
Used to be run
How is bucolic I-4
Like a high-precision
I like a meter
How to say crippling
I think about that he's thinking that closet you know standard
Scooter industry
So that was basically
How we got our
Play Spotify Gabby to be standard
And also the stand
Next time
He always has really good manufacture
All the
Difference industry we have a really
Like diversify supply chain
The some of them from a motorcycle
Kind of cheetah mobile phone
SUV using all the ships we got the benefit from it like
Smart watch
Business because we have accused
Quantity of Buzz
All those chips they have super mature Manufacturing
How to sync the Wii
And you we're not designing all the chips
I think they saw we always say Technologies pretty cold
Our job is to integrate every code
Acknowledge
To have warm
Experience delivery driver user
That's a keeper
Sewing to sell some juice
Originally you were selling
E Scooters
Online
E-commerce company
And then
Switched
Evolve and adapt
What stores as well
What was the thinking
The doing that
And how did you quickly
Pet stores in
Something different
I think it's a great question I think it wasn't driven by sales a was actually driven by services
Because when we initially so unlike what were big hit
Hunting 2015 with wafer stood on that JD crowdfunding so actually
I broke the shadycroft any record in China
72 million RMB sales in 15 days
What record not ranked number 6
How is it being very hot
But what would happen when our user got a scooter because it is
It's not a toy so that the use of databases when you use those things on daily basis you will need to guess
Service that you know you made got a flat tire or the things
And that time our service network
Party
Knoxville home service network
Hulu user feel like little dizzy got a high-end product
How do we receive a service A1 Tree Service
And they were complaints of Chinese users
I mean
Is there a variable
Brenda service naturally evolved become
Cellsense wall
So that's how the decision was made
How is spread out in China and the globally was
Distributors ask Distributors what do even call them Distributors we call them City partners
Will even make you know she'll new name cards for them will be like a new technology
You know Hangzhou City
Partner
We carefully select those
Northeast Pewter City partners and what do we call them
Select the right person
Basically the people who actually really believe in her car
I really believe in that window
Join this path
They also you know they can change the way how
In their City how people travel over
So yes we we got some really serious people who really love the boss that's how you know Dino you see like
Beijing 1900 oldest big cities that means we got City Partners come in and stop UTI stores
Yes I mean the end of day they will actually enjoying the economic benefit but initially
When they sign up the economic benefit was was not first intention because
Wright's Whitworth, those people a let's open up
A store like an Apple Store Furnitures everything Elvis there's a fire
Evolve
Then
That you know provide service to our users
They want you cannot come in and say Hey you will make money
The great idea you know to actually carry this uni product
True
The user's inner-city I think they they just love that concept
That helped us
Also some really interesting
Salat offer
There are not in this business
Before they become new user first
They enjoy your visit community
Need to come by the store owner
The service is for your friend
It's not only for the customer
It's a huge differ
EBenefits
Free pets
Maybe you could touch on the new
A lot of our listeners
Chinese soda
Newest spell NIU
Which means
Chinese but also has other me
Banana starting this
We want to
Do an internet
Can we select a lot of wars
Asda pronounce difference
The new in China is a
Small boob
You also can pronounce
Is the new new
Something new
As something new
We are just like rasp or but also weird
Create new
Industry for a new way forward
Reverse
Just a little touch on that I think it's the news in Chinese little boy
That's a very good
Implantation on it's not like you're super proud
But you are little bit proud of the achievement that you have done
Through the effort
Kind of a connotation
I think that's what we try to build into our user-specific by writing out
Scooters
You feel that you know that you are little bit
Proud hopefully traffic you can use to
You know accelera career somehow
Vanessa
The second the first vice news a second ties in your pee
So in the first half of this year around 13% of your net revenue was derived from sales outside of
So could you talk about how
You plan to go Global I know you're already in Europe so what are some other markets that you're excited about
Where are you
Excited
Target
Be honest
Static wearing your first
Because
That was back in 2006
Teen when Okinawa
You know that time we were still very young
With deliver a product
A few months after we get our product what's up
Okay I think we had that live ambition
Tooth fur Prada Acoma
ICICI meizhou largest Twitter
Worldwide Milan every year
BMW
See whether we have it
Bands that were staged
But we got a lot of increase in in
I from you're doing that, I know we were not even on the menu in the main exhibition
Where in the
What it was it will rain today
Spare parts
Because of us
Really big trafficking in your area
So that should give us
The confidence that he
You know we got a chance in Europe and then
They are Distributors from America there.
How to say shh
Closest post office
I think it's all about you know
How we
Basically
Planar used to National Expansion
Not graduating you step-by-step fashion
Also I can remember is
The day we are
The first time, if you ask me
La la la
From Japan
Chinese China
That's annoying China LeBrons
Registry
Yeah but
We are proud
That's a Chinese company
I just switched up a little bit and talk about your IPO
The copper market right now is not very good
Some argue
You could be the last company that
Republic
In the US
This way
What are some of your lessons
Dora bikes
So you can share with us
Our audience
About what you went
Google IPO
What I mean is about what it takes to go
Public
I think the advice number one is
Make sure to TVs on your voice
Is it truly inside
Let's Nacho
It is this not a joke I think it's very appreciated throughout the process
Jenny's amazing
Devices that you know
Really
Looking back I think nobody can control the timing right when we start the process
The time you look much better dress
Daiso
Yeah so it's I think I know they wasn't even Marcus
Wasn't good
Then there's nothing you can do about it
They prepare quickly prepare early and then the whole thing was actually is
The more I won't talk about his actions after that I feel I think
Why do both of us actually feel that excitement but just
The twin Society will push the button
Bender
Can the pressure come in then you realize
You know that yesterday was a trust from
Private investors
Not as the trust from public investors
Is then we feel like everyone who actually on my list
Even just widest year of our stock
With you
Responsible responsible because we want to make sure we could not deliver value to them
You know in your long-term fashion that means we need to work harder we need to basically
Do what we do the best
Keep rolling a better product those are things
And then
Is never stop
This game never stops when I was a private
I'm the product
Bio Life
Valley weight loss event
In Paris this year and IPL
I feel more proud forever product launch seriously
The things he sucks
This year we're allowed to protect Paris Negron
First time
Introduce our products
Europe
And to the global
Alex
Much more
Like like pressure for me
Because we should be
Really think about around the world what's the next 3 or 5 years about our
Products to sculpt
Really deep to the other Technologies are the designs to helping people global
Where the first I'm not sure where the first Mobility company that launched product
But the first two wheel Mobility
The definition
Chinese Mobility company like four languages
Because it it will have 500K
Italian German French and Spanish
How many words are so lucky the Swedish guys actually speak pretty good English
Felicia
Hey
Green German
The users
Cuz I had to do that
Yes
Did you talk about
What a lot of people will come gradually
Can you go public
What does that
Give you more pressure and going forward
You mentioned you actually sleep better or private
So
What are you most excited and most worried about
Most excited part for me is actually in a big list
The public
Put us really
Spot
Globally
I-80 ino80 soda set
Hey a testimony say
Hate we have accomplished from 0 to 1
We start as a
It is Chinese startup
But now
We are AAA puppy
The company that has a chance
To global market share
Reciting.
Vicky busted window opportunity I think that's what
Excites me about it
What worse me about
It's the same thing as
No
We're giving a chance
Weather
Are we can actually grass
I think
Our team the entire team
I have to deliver
Has to work hard
Panda
Wayward
I think I was
To myself you actually
At the end
Yeah you just a few
Texas like that
Yeah yeah yeah yeah
1 cm
Timer
The whistle that window
Opportunity
No it's actually you already had
How to say we need to get that
I said that
Where the huge
Pressure coming
Actually for
Myself
Play song
That's when the IPO is a pressure
That's it's not the most
Pressure part because I'm always the self pressure prison
And also the thing you saw
Author up the day we got IPO
Really like freezing
Because okay I got Time come back to my product side
I think it was talking to see where he got most nervous it was invalid or show was about yesterday meeting
Tony fadell
Google press up with everything
So you know if you can type you obviously was not an easy Journey
Both you reflect back
To what have
What were some of the most memorable moments
YouTube that you experience or
Your team Express
That's what's showing
For me
Is y a vowel
Xiaomi IPO
Lamesa
After that
Open Vail
We see all of it
It's like that
Literally you
Broadcasting your products
You are a vision
Also your
You're like
Efficient
2 Iraq war by taking picture
There
And then
Maybe like
Eyes exist
Probably changed my life
Because it's more
Responsibility
Plastics assembly moments for me
Looking back I think it's the old so moment for token but he's actually in that picture so he could remember
I was actually when I needed a couple until the first time we got the first product prototype
This guy was that you look at tokens face
You couldn't tell whether he's smiling or his
Quiet
That was a it was like a
Freeze up moment right
Then there were times when we first after we do today the crowdfunding
We knew going to break a record on the 15th day
When you aren't they want because if they want was so the number was huge
The midnight if they won when will the results came in because everybody
Inlet
In the office
There's nobody leaves because
Broadcast TV yelling for the numbers
That moment is like finally got something because of the initial the product was a concept
Can you put on the stage where
Real money
They are people buying.
For the current funding the most
Memorable
Who sings this song
They didn't see this product in real life
Missing in real life
Call pictures
Like one videos
Love your purse
Also
Go to the last part of the interview which is surrounded
Quick-fire question
The first one is who is the entrepreneur you admire the most
And why
Besides
Personally
Is this guy is crazy
This guy is
Overby Auto every bus
Everybody's
The thinking
Instead of
Like pasta
Speed Stacks Steven Barton comp
I really like his fire Kong
Dreaming about snow
Jimmy
I think since tokens
Flight 24
Steve Jobs
It was about building a product I think he do the product but yeah I should do degree
And if you the long lasting
Something with Luca
I'm livid cliche waiting that I didn't know Apple
Post listing
Look how Apple grow after
After the listing
You know you look at her Steve Jobs I think
Biography
Resume
Summer movies
Even the guys driving crazy on the product but that guy has
Is great business sense a great company
I mean he does it all
How that happened
And they changed the entire industry
Teresa wood we're hoping we got a chance to change
Change Urban Mobility
Sorry yeah I have to
Crack to you
Steve Jobs not clear brand
Who created religion
Lassitude
What's something you can read recent
Now you're welcome
Actually
Is a book
My wife
History about
Kitty Hawk
As you know I'm not like
Reading Rainbow Guy
I'm ready most of things it's not about
It's not about
Finance
I'm getting box
Laura is
Ora Ora
Sort off
But see smart more like
You're fighting
With your brothers
Ricci was friends
Achieve what I miss you
How's that actually looking at my
I think I can say audible try so yes
So I'm not saying I'm nothing as far as
ISO exactly
What I'm listening now it's a skull powerful building a culture of Freedom response
Spotify
By Patty McCoy
Hi Stacey. I think she would say
It was a HR ahead
Netflix
And because we as we're Beauty our company with Luca Ashley
Is a culture super important
Netflix has
PPT
I kind of picture of sheep
BtoB debut
Culture hiring right people
So I think that got me interested in then
You know she came up with a book and is that
Icy Hot how they actually feel down they
Suraci the first-hand experience
Any we always think that it's actually
Even to have a long-lasting company I think
At the end it's about people it's about a culture
We still have much to learn
I think that is
I shoot up okay rock
What do you do for fun
Me
Writing
Handwriting
Tampa Tribune
Is my
My life
There's another part tokens going to do for fun better
Laughing the kids to Young self
Like memorizing yourself
I got my first daughter
And activate I go
Oh wow
Everything
Just haven't
Same to you
I mean
I think right now besides work I think the rest of the time I asked
Mojave Road
Should I take it you are
You know you yeah you can gauge a interesting conversation with her
But I never can convince her to do things that she doesn't want to do
Daiso
I am the Seal of a new scooter literally I think that's the fun part was
Because might my wife that is afraid of taking her out on the scooter
So I'm well actually
Have the owner
So little during the weekend
It's how you know that
She was just like that what you know
You take me out a new scooter
That was that
40 minutes Drive
Physical therapy
The last question what type of Rose are you guys hiring for
And how can people reach out
Know where we're hiring
Osuna
From India
From marketing
From sales
That I think it's a
I hope we can
I think what we were able to
Attract good talent
But now
Since we're public
I think hopefully that will a lot to attract more Talent
Will Alaska be
As competitive
As you know baidu xiaomi
Obviously
Scooter sharing is becoming very popular
Nus
Add lime and bird
In-N-Out
Spread to about America
Eva Halo
China is wrong
Do you ever think about
Coming with product for that
That's not
For some
We actually have that
I already
So we we are supporting
Scooter share operations in Europe
I think they're their company
There's company
Scooter using our scooter shave in pesos
There's also company called mooville
I'm OVO
Using our scooter sharing in Madrid
And there's also, Corbett using our scooters
Words for sharing
And in Vienna
Solder scooter star
I wish I
We provide open API
So that they can link to the back back and management system
Is a physical
Scooter
It provides
The other flight management
Are the API or the cloud services
We at the package
We went over for a couple
Never enough
So what motivates you
To wake up each morning
Anna
Keep you up at night
Token
Always empty
Wake up in the morning
Because
I'm really good
Sleeper
The first thing you wake up you feel great
I'm wearing my my digital watch everyday
Some people like
We have a really light sleeping and then going to sleep
And then
L for me
The first of five minutes 20
And always be
Through my makeup
That what keeps you up at night
At 9
Always thinking about
Not productive
Is more like floss
Is it like
What problem
Chainsaw
It's not only about
Lividity
About
People leave
And the
Obviously
Like there is a fire then and then
London
Thinking guy
Always jump jump
My daughter wake up
Fighting dirty
So it's not about what
It's cool so she wakes me up
Everything in the morning Russian tomorrow
We're still asleep
DeSoto convention
Future because I mean she goes to bed at 8
So that's how I expect
She's always energetic
Actually I have a
So this is this is one part of that I'd like to share a
Weather app not sure where this
True or not
But based on token me I think might be true I think to be a good entrepreneur
You need to be a good sleeper
They're so really I asked
Blueberry song
Panda
No matter
What's out there how to make the pressure
Driving to the weather, tips
Very quickly
Acting you have to let it go
Is a necessity they're always going to so many things out there
Next day
Tea to prepare for that so that I make sure I got a good sleep doesn't matter is a 4 hours or 6 hours
Bastrop
Tolkien doesn't sleep
Esme and I
Geissele rail DWP
Carl
Anne's elwy Tagalog
R&D team
And one guy called Chris is that really early let employee
Yeah Randy Team USA okay
We know why not
Not able to be entrepreneur
Because
It's literally me and cars
Sleep like 3 or 4 hours
Everyday everyday anymore
Because if they're like at the at least
5 / 6
Really important
So what keeps you up
A night
Nothing right because
But not keep smell
I do have a habit plan out for the next day
So before I go to sleep High
Do Spanish
What I do
Things to do
Who I'm going to have
Tomorrow
Panda
Yeah I don't do magic
Everyday I do that once a week
But I do think sometimes makes sense
Anyway, I should have got more free time
Two step back
Rethink the whole thing I think one of us
My user device
Every Wednesday
You do it that a job is the daily operation job everything
I need you got something
What were
Actually
About to step back and reflect the actual matter
Because I know that you know when looking back I should maybe just a three or four things actually really matters
At the end
But
When you were in the job
You sometimes you lost that big picture
So you some sense I think what actually keeps him up
At night is
I need to constantly remind myself saying hey
I need to step back and just got back to look at what matters because I'm so afraid that
I will get lost into
Episode of The Daily
You know
Needy greedy details
Where you forgot to pay picture
I think that that is
What I worry
I travel a lot as you guys because you guys knowing
Sleep very well
Heading old days the good generals can do that as well but they're fighting on the battlefield
Otherwise
You yourself comfortable pressure and worry
Yeah it's okay thank you so much for being here with us and we can't wait to see where it new will go now
Thank you thank you thank you for having us
7989 Bank
Listening to this episode
996 ggv capital is a multi-stage venture capital firm based in Silicon Valley Shanghai and Beijing
We have been partnering with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past 18 years from seed to pre-ipo
With 6.2 billion dollars in capital under management across 13 funds ggv invests in consumer
Bernie retail social Digital internet Enterprise cloud and Frontier Tech
GTB has invested over 290 companies with more than 45 companies valued at over a billion
$10
Formula companies include Airbnb Alibaba C trip Didi chuxing Domo
Hashicorp hellobike cows keep slack Square
Hotel wish soundtrue white white and others find out more at 2 jvc.com
We also highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat group as lot Channel where we regular share inside
Events and job opportunities related to attack in China join these groups at 996. Street
Cbc.com community
You have any feedback on this podcast
Or would like to recommend the gas please email us at 996 at gbc.com