Vincent wrestler
Hi there welcome to the 96 podcast
Brought to you by ggv capital and co-produced by the Seneca podcast
On the show interview movers and shakers of China's tech industry as well as Tech leaders who have a u
Us China
Cross-border perspective, managing partner at ggv Capital it has been working at startup
Investing in them in both the US and China for the past 20 years
My name is Zahra Jones I'm an investment Analyst at ggv Capital and a former journalist
Why is the show called 98696 is the work schedule that many Chinese Founders have organically it
Adopted that is 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
To us996 captures intensity Drive in speed
Of Chinese internet companies many which are moving faster that even their American counterparts
Welcome everyone into this strange gdb 96th and Seneca podcast Library
According
I'm sorry. I'm joined by my 96 ho-hos Hans Tung managing partner igb capital
I'm by Kaiser cool host of a Seneca podcast and producer up in 96 podcast
Please join me in welcoming our special guest Professor irrational Quan
We're delighted to have Professor Quan with us today
He is the international program professor in Chinese economy and business and professor of global economics and management
At the MIT Sloan School of Management
And he's the founder and head of the China left and the angel at MIT
Such a pleasure talking to you for Seneca last year in San Francisco
Your straight talk in your practice is always quite the breath
A fresh air
So look like what's the deal with the elephant
In the room
Trade War are we we've seen volleys in both directions now first the steel and aluminum tariff and in the face of dude
Chinese response
Then he had the 60 billion dollars punitively over the 301
Twgok
Then China's announcements
And and now just on Thursday this week 8
Thread of an even larger Tariff of 100 billion
Bite by Trump
Administration relief
Is fixed as opposed
To one particular Target of all this time I mean it it's
China's new tech focused industrial policy that's called made in China 2025
America has
Basically always opposed Industrial Park
Call Meechie and in Japan in the 1980s which is a target of American Iron
What is it that they object so much too in
Made in China 2025 end end is there
Is there actually something to objective is there as or something it's deliberately quite unfair
Okay thank you Kaiser and very good to share the podium with
Hanson Zara as well
Yeah this is a big elephant in the room
And I think
The
The possibility is a real one that things can get all of the country
Might you have an escalation of the conflict
And the more you ask if I ate
It's more difficult to
Walk down
Farm.
High position that you have made very clear and so is your specific
A question about what the US is its objective
Through this
The power of action
I guess there
Three things and
Falling into categories why is
Macroeconomics
Which has to do with the trade imbalances and their different calculations about
Exactly what is the what is the right number
Byron Lars there is a
Decent consensus that us has a persistent
Pray
The deficit with China maybe the
Size is not as big as
They say
Complication
AR
Norman
How do you Account Processing trade
So that's one that's on them or macroeconomics side
On the more so the microeconomics
This has to do with the issue of IP
So Trump actually use that term which is IP theft
And you know what type of debate whether or not straight out of
Is the right remedy to deal with that
I don't think it's alright instrumental deal with even the macroeconomic issue but
Formica
Long instrument
And then there's the political officer of security
Issue
Which has to do with
How a
Incompetent established
Power
Do you swear
A rising power
That has such a fundamentally different
Play deep all you can all make right social, institutions and violet was right
And that's unprecedented multi-dimensional
Western Union with kind of always knew their weakness
That's right the great ballet but what consumer products
There's nothing to be a trivia about
Right there
Basketball
Imitation Russian accent
Severe severe
Biology and chemistry
The fundamental difference is WeChat
They didn't have that
That's true
Bye-bye neither of China at that time
Appointment
But the fundamental difference is that
Sylvia's never use their signs
But you can call me
And so there was a god
Regina Hall
Advance the science was
Which was mostly geared toward
Defense
It was never really apply to Economic Development
Tsume Yuki
Horrible
Where's the country I actually had you know
Established scientist
That's a great book by the way written by a historian
The title of it is a lonely ideas
The book is about
How old is Sylvia
Invested heavily in signs
Antec maybe technology heavily in science
But never came
Benefit from this is a huge difference between
So I think the
Fear on the part of the United State let this sort of separate two issues why is whether we should fear
Interview
The other is
Whether or not
Superficially there is a subjective reason
For a average
Person in the United States
To say wow look at that country that has a
Is sort of a normal a communist
Assistant
One-party system in all of that
Plus signs Plus technology plus hands
Right song
You know
Boston Silicon Valley
You need three things
Scientist
Scientists technologists
Entrepreneurs
And
Reitzel
No we can debate about the quality and the quantity is impressive
China now
In terms of
You probably have more data than than I do quantity has a quality all its own
So so
Size Matters
Right so so
Well I mean sometimes you do have but the thing is
Let me put it this way if
You don't have a big
Signs of establishment vegvisir established
The probability of having Stellar signs
InStyler investment exactly the law
You kind of need a size because precisely the probability is low you need a size
To make the actual number
And this is really in terms of
Country to Country comparison
It is the absolute number that matter
It's not so much the ratio to Chinese
You know
Success raised in
If you can use the
The success of x's and maybe
That can be low in China
But as long as the numbers large
Who the other country
That's significant
So sometimes we would need to establish our benchmarks more clearly
So you think that this is what's bruising anxiety around industrial policy
In terms of industrial policy
It is true that
If you look at
Silicon Valley Boston
There was
Lesson 4 / industrial policy
Explaining the development of
Silicon Valley and
Band Boston
But let's face it right so
Amenity
Benefited tremendously
It's not
Bissell a design to
Increase the price of plus this is where the mercantilism comes in
And the mercantilism is an idea that
First you use the government
Directly explicitly to Advance economic goals
A second that you focus on train
China has the flavor of
Both
And that worries
People here
This is for me it's surprisingly
Bishop people
In the US, talking about
Chinese government's role
Something Auto Suisse
Funding of those
Put all his money
To work as of that made a huge difference
If I look at that the actual facts
Of how to send out of a leprechaun
Amazon most valuable company in the world
We have very little egg
This much government
Is it
Can do well
If a government doesn't bother that
Internet companies were founded by people who are either Americanized or actually had been in the United
Long time like Barbara leave for absolutely and you know with American men
Capital listing on American
Emotional for making money from tencent and Baidu and
How to apply skins for Americans in people
Preaching to the choir
Yeah I do want to ask you about Trump says 500 billion
I think that the real number you know the nominal numbers 350 maybe but then
I think
Focus on me
That number is
Is it
What is 500 / 300
The reason is that
Fundamentally the trade imbalances
With China are driven by the difference in savings
Exactly
If you would throw incurve 500 billion or 300 million dollars of
Trade imbalances
The China
Then you'll have to do that with somebody else if you want to borrow that money if you want to see if you want people to show up in your Treasury
You you consume a lot right relative to your savings rate
That means by definition that you have to
Sort of borrow and then
Deficit
Difference between the capital account which is
Importing them on a phone the rest of the world
And the trade account which
Is the deficit
China has exactly the
If China does not have a huge
Everything else being equal I'd is current level if China doesn't have this huge tray
United States
Then
The savings investment and consumption ratios are stars
That it has to have
A train stops
Which is
The description is really about
Why you need to have such a
Big surprise a surplus in the first month
Vadadent whether or not this is the right way to
To do with it
So that is from the house of the weather
The consumption Valor contemporary issues and maybe you're investing too much
Maybe you're not consuming enough
The Texans running back
We're actually actually fun companies
The r
Riding the consumption upgrading China
I want to see
Customer comes to Mark not just locally
So it's so it's so that's a that's a
Both analytical
Write discussion to have
As well as a economically meaningful
Relatives in China
I I wish that they could consume more
So that is what is constraining their consumption
And why their savings rate
Is so high
And that's a
Atacama social safety net
But that's a discussion.
That's a
About domestic
Policy issues rather than about cross-border politician
Country the country that typically don't have those
Even though I mean it I think it's interesting to note that
If you are going to slap a bunch of times
Is it really going to hurt China so much words
Just an accelerator the rebalance Hyatt my own view is that it is hurting China more than it is
Resorts in the US
Write this is strictly
And you can all midterm
So if you think about
What the US is
What kind of
Products that are important
These are from Chinese
Industries
That are competing with us
That so essentially
China sort of
Economics distinguish between absolute advantage and comparative
China has a comparative advantage
Light Industry labor intensive industry
But it is producing these
You know
AI companies drone company that DJI and
Leather caning in terms of absolute advantages vis-a-vis the US
Cell companies
So the US is targeting those guy
And those are competing with the US companies
Where's the Chinese
Imports one that you are
Are basically complimentary
Weather
Chinese
Society in Chinese
Now we're talkin about
Soil
Into
That's hopeful I guess that's
Is that one of the application that maybe other applicants
Essentially sorbian is the Upstream product
Inside of air handler
So that's one so it is it is it is it is complementary and the other
Effect on China is
Agriculture is a part of the
The core inflation
So
China
Henna
Afford to have
You know inflation right right
So it really does hurt us have more of an impact on the Chinese macroeconomic situation
Then it does on the United States
China
Depends on the US
In terms of the
Much more than the other way around
So if you're just
No us is losing 150 billion dollars
China is losing you know whatever y500 write something like that
So it does have a bigger effect on China than it does
Yeah I'm such a
Play I think
Lot of times trade war is about Paula
So basically who is going to bring
So there I don't really have a very good way of reading the situation
So they sent that I have to
Say something about it I will say the following which is
With everything
Democratic societies are more vulnerable
Politico
Because
Businesses people
Speak up
People who are losing fur trade Wars
You know authoritarian Society you don't you don't have that
So typically we say that a democratic
Country a has a lower tolerance
Spore
So there's actually research that shows that democracies don't go to war with
In part because they have a low tolerance
We just got the witch witches
One of the reasons is
It support
Where's your sense of your sense of that even if you have pain you don't express it
In this particular situation.
I'm not so sure this manifest
It's there when you go to the grocery store when you go to the end consumer products
At least for now
He's targeting Industrial Park
Feed on each side
Pork
Corn that's directly affecting the consumers rights
IR tolerance will
Write one word
Imagine that it is going to be the US
Who's going to Blink
First
It's getting interest
Us businesses
Unlike
Arnold split
So before
10 years ago
The US business community
Was almost
Unify
In terms of
Supporting
China trade with China
Open the mfn most favored nation trading status
All of that
And not going after China in the aftermath of
South Tama
Us business Community Awards
Unified
Engage Chinatown
So essentially what is Noah's engagement
McClinton
The Clinton administration
Because China has increased
To become more
Buy Local
You have to sign in in in in in China
Heart overlay
Talk to me
For foreign companies do more business
Apple's doing well in Starbucks doing well and
Now in general Pepsi that they are exceptional doing well
Troubleshooting Microsoft
Asenapine
Affected by a Chinese government wants to
Bible
You going to argue that the Trump trade War
Damascus
Situation is making China think harder
About being a global citizen
Send info in some sense
And it has received synonym
You want to have to come power score companies were countries
Got to compete with each other to keep each other honest
You don't have to be nice
They have to respect and fear each other
To do the right thing
I respect
We don't mind that but but hands
It can get all the liquor
And
It could have that kind of effect that you you want
Increase a lot 100
Ben 10
So how do you if you walk down
If you walk down from 50 billion
No even as I'm at the professor I know something about math
You go down to 25
Now it's 100
UE Central a frame that sits by the higher level
Once you friend that is Carson dellosa
This is something that I have no taste in China
Xian Chinese
The young Chinese in China
More nausea
Then when I was
Young Chinese
We're all naturalistic back during the founding of that
Shortcoming of a system back then
Assistant with her bad thing
The current generation you know they play games that they don't really know what the heck
I think they have this
Certified
Longview about what city
Chi Minh
Seoul
It's not the size of the GDP is
May 2nd
In the world
What per capita GDP
AP
Is right in the middle
Of 198 countries in the world
Middle East
Canova country
India is per capita GDP
It's not the aggregate you did not know right so
And just speaking from personal experience I think
Chinese rest of my generation
Come to you as to study
Ashley want to go back
He stays piercings actually work in China they want to
Contribute
All they wanna
Make a lot of money there
More up to it he's there it's hard to get a US Visa now so they're not so
Words that are pulling them back home and I think part of the reason
That the reason why Chinese tech companies can't grow so fast is because they can attract all these
What's redis
I think that's a very good thing and and I
Celebrate
Shenyang people
Aspirations in
I just I just
Want to say that
Sometimes we need to be
More cool headed about being cautious
Yeah I bought these macro issues right so I think don't translate the macroeconomic
Amazon
So blindly into macroeconomics
China still has lot of children in the countryside
Nothing is
Behind children
The country
What time is it
So I just think that
And I would
Argue with that
If the young technologist
From China
Think about making money that's great
But what's to think about how to use technology
To solve these social problems
That would be awesome
I want to ask you a couple questions I I mean first I want to ask you about Americans likely react
Add about Chinese people react
Directions to the burgeoning trade War
United States in the United States or China is obviously targeted
Not just red States not just
Bullying is not in a red state
Craigslist
Alcorn gensley beans and end
And pork
These dotart
She should have been treated
Ashley Pro Trump
Is it smart
Strategy let me know where is this going to fart
Is it possible I
Is it going to look like God playing near meddling in American polity
How are Americans likely to respond to
Meme
China
You picked a
I'll give you two blocks
I think so.
The one issue is what is the alternative
Right so
I think this is us a smart
Strategy
As you can play
Idris Elba
Under the Sycamore
Does and
But I
I have a feeling that I may be wrong
Open do you know
I have a feeling that it may not
Trump is not a conventional politic
His supporters
They may be some here but I don't know about his supporters are already up.
Sometimes are not
Super clear about their true economic interest
And you know
Many of their supporters what
Have a lotto game from Obamacare
He's the one
Promise to demolish
Obamacare
Are you, calculations may not work this time
I was going to finish my
Earlier
Example about
The political capacity to a beer
I actually think Tom
Has a quite a bit of
Evidently he look at his
Will the Mueller investigation
What's wrong with offending 1.4 billion people right away
And and also if you look at his approval
Rating
Is a Pool of Radiance
Right in the middle of the tree
Console
And the business Community is more split than before
And there is more of a
Bipartisan bipartisan consensus
About
This particular
Issue
Then there was before
Even the Democrats
Support some of the
Paris for a cocktail tonight and we have to decide between a Moscow Mule
Or a Dark and Stormy Daniels maybe a white Rush
Russian interference
Edinburg solid objects my little brother from Facebook
The ordinary people in China
Are they
Rally around the flagon
Vicodin
What's a hashtag that I keep saying no
What was just out of
What is it
We didn't we didn't grow Chinese
So
It's a you know
More
When do you know to give us more
Yeah bring it on Reno
Bring it
Like that
Again that's Kaiser
I think
My only again
I'm a professor
I can say these things
Which is that
I think the
Biggest fear is the lack of
And
I think China
So if you look at Chinese you can all make
Growlithe
Right if you look at a Chinese macroeconomic picture
We're talkin about a Yukon the maid that is through heavily
Dependent on investment driven
Consumption household consumption GDP ratio is about 40 39%
Which is actually very loyal compared with major UConn amazing the world
USMC
So so
So to have more sustainable growth
You need to decrease investment
You need to increase the consumption
And you need to have a healthy
Export
Outgrow
EXO
If you
Cartel
Export now
To keep
The growth rate as it is in a 6.5 diesel
The only
Nothing available to the policymakers is to increasing vitamin
More Fai
And then that means more Bank
How long will it take that I have driven growth
Moore printing over the money
The two parts of the economy that are healthy
The house will consumption
And the X
We need both of them
Right at home
I would you know
Again
Professor I will just swallow the
Bitterness whatever I was just
You say Okay so let's just have a
Have a compromise and rather than sort of playing on this a psychological nationalist
Sentiment
I think that's very very dangerous
Nationalism
Has never
Been a friend for you Konami
From where we said
Kind of kind of
I see that
Changing
Opposition
Cuz he always do stuff
Don't expect
There's a possibility that he was ejected
You look at China
Pékin change somewhat
But not too much
Okay
What's most likely happen
AR View
Mike personal
Is that things are getting nastier
For a while
And see which talking
Pick up more
And make a test
Accordingly and nuts the mixer hosting a lot
Whiskey
Than ever before
But we could see this
Pronoun for I
What do you think this whole episode will go down in history as a hiccup in the
More
Then a bigger trend of globalization or do you think globalization is actually stoppable by
Individual leader
Globalization has been stopped
Buy individual leader
Firefighter Brown policy choices
If you look at lines about the smoot-hawley Tariff smooth and if you look at the suit of the cross
Border investment
As a share worldwide GDP
The world reach
APK
Just before.
The first World War
Write a note for the next 50 years and 6 years I went down the hill
So so you know maybe with hands around the things will be different.
But I'm not a lion if you make
Policy decisions
You can really go down when I pass
That you regret
Later so
Interview question whether or not this is a short-term hiccup or not
I actually don't think this is
And I think
Sometimes we distinguish
15 structural
Component and cyclical component
In the past
The US China relationship has been governed by
Cyclical up and down
For the structure it was moving in the positive
Did you know that
It's moving in the right direction
I'm not so sure
Precisely because I see more evidence of
Bipartisan consensus
Getting
Harsher on China
Trump obviously but also business community.
Right
And from the Chinese side more nationalism
Strong leadership
But you know
Country also
In my own vehicle
Is not implemented you cannot marry forms
Ida Ida Ida
Response
Larry Market open market liberalization
If you look at FBI as a as a measure of some sort of a civilization that has been 3
So
The more worrisome is the component of the total FDI inflow
In the early 1990s to the mid-1990s march of the Chinese
IPI
Was Amanda coming from Hong Kong
Like that and then it went down because
Euro
Now we're coming back
Put the situation in the early 1990s
The Hong Kong Investments are outpacing Japanese Investments
Us investment
And your opinion
I have nothing against the Hong Kong investment
But I would argue with that the US investment
European vitamins Japanese Investments brains vagina
Technology
Management
Anyway I don't think Hong Kong about
Right there more indicative of
Brought a global integration for China is
We all hoped China would
Do more than ever before
It helps to have a c
Superworld when it's more balanced
But what the science we do see
Is that instead of being milked to to be to be more militaristic and be more antagonistic
Versus economic Forum disaster route which is
I want Beltline Road Coppell
Depending on us for export
When we sell more of our services model and goods
To Southeast Asia to India to Central Asia to Eastern Europe to Africa
Latin america
I think over the next 10-20 Years you'll see a lot more push
Buy Chinese government aligning with a Chinese internet company
To export and
Introduce other developing
That's why the chance of more tennis company coming to
Us
It's less
Good morning Chinese in a company going out
2DS other developing Market marching world will increase dramatically
How's this is felt very cynical let's let's move this more than I-96 territory and talk more about
Tech investor
The time to shift it into that
Supposed to do that
Can you spend a lot of time studying
Chinese
And you start with looking at soe early
And then Starship into
The private Enterprise
And then even with the channel app look at the
As UC ship
From soest
Department of ice
Internet companies
Do you see the
Quality management team
Piazza
Does the kishin of a
Apus systems
Anthea
Growth
Change party
Is it commensurate with the
The change in
So so so this is an excellent
Equestrian
So I found it in China la banda Lobby
And since then.
It has been
I 10 years we have worked
About 300
Chinese companies now
About 70 Indian companies
So
As an academic
It's actually extremely hard to study management because we don't have faith
The work I did in China
I did
Texas Lotto
Chinese entrepreneur company
The shift
Toms River
10 years ago
If you look at the type of projects we are doing invisible he's the type of projects we were doing 10 years ago
10 years ago most of the projects we were doing
War about
Marketing
Marketing overseas
I have a product I want to sell to Japan I want to sell it
Do you ask
You will have a team please help us
No come up with a marketing plan and
How to tell over
Increasingly
The projects
Are about
Management in Covina
Human resource
Management
Financial reporting controls
Devising kpi
Things like that
There is a dramatic shift
From the external orientation of these company
Two internal capacity-building
On the part of the companies we work with
I think
You know this is not a systemic peace update
To tell me that the Chinese entrepreneurial companies now
Put more volume or premium
Management
Right so
Also before if you look at Chinese private sector companies
That is simple structure
1 boss everybody was a management
I would say 20 years ago
It was irrational
AT-AT walker
They don't want to be a worker
And I can't be the boss
So what the boss is doing everything by himself or herself
Now you have
A
More sophisticated
Managerial
System
You have top management middle management
Applying management
And I think this is
Really reflecting
The dynamism
And and
Ryzen quality
Chinese privacy
The part of it is
I think part of it is
When the economy is
More competitive
Right you can't just rely on
Connections
Government connection
You cannot just rely on that
You have to rely on management know-how
What was the technology
Right technology is playing more and more important role
In art an alarm projects in the last 3 three years I would say
The ratio of the planets share of the technology project
70%
Not surprised
Interrelated
Internet-related
Art
I have a piece of
Technology
So I think definitely
At that level
Chinese economy is I-10
GDP
And all of that
I actually think that
These microeconomic indicate
Are a more reliable indicator
Healthier
A hole
Chinese economy is getting high
That's what you smell outside looking in India and of course you run the NBA live as well I'm really curious about you
Either disorder
Qualitative or
From head work without the China lab media lab
Absolut Vodka shipping some compared
Now.
Engineering Style
Dial TV
Yucca root
Yaso India
IPad
5 years ago 10 years ago
I went China live in India. Began
Mostly with high Indian students doing Indian
Chinese students are in China
Now it's just the office
The tiniest in Islam
The Indians
They they they are more curious about each other
And
And by the way I got interested in India
A long time ago
That was criticized
Well being
Optimistic about India
But I think that you know
India has
Breathing the huge constraints it is facing has
Dunwell
Well right song
It is now able to grow 7%.
There's a term called that Hindu right of the growth
Conferences if you say all this country is growing at the rate of growth
It doesn't have to be about India I can be about
Country
If your on everything else that had all k
1%
7% we're talkin about eustachian growth
Meso
Weather savings right about half of the Chinese savings rate
Whether you guys smell right
How about Chinese in Bessemer
80% of the Chinese
I take responsibility for this I did ask him to be Politically Incorrect and then he
You obliged versus the Hindu
Call Kaiser
Small investor
Into Indian
What is a
When is number one number two Indian
And when that when I look at them especially Snapdeal
NSC even other Indian B
Leading Tech
There's just been a lot
I'm coming to town
I am meeting with Chinese
He's meeting with Chinese
Actively want to learn
In knowledge
What has happened in China
Italy filled a lot of
Big umbrella from problems are there trying to solve in India
Somebody in China
I saw the symbol of
And now the local adaptation will be very different for sure
Badolato principles
Jackson storm
I should be quite body
Remind me how the
Chinese New
Come to Silicon Valley and ride right right of your your portfolio companies
Alibaba
But are they looking at it
Learn manager
Just got to be some reason why
So many more Indians
Okay I think the end of the Chinese company are looking India as a
The market Express
I think that's mean that they are more Indian exactly
Silicon Valley
Not make me never change
At least not for now for a while
But what they sing what is partially because
Mosto
A successful a lot of success
A lot of successful
Promising Chinese
Engineers or apartments
End up going back to China
It's something you're stuck
And they're done for the Indian executives
Being here has been a payoff
Upington
But as India Pro
You could change and what's interesting about India's
More more Americans actors who have done well in
Us in psychology
Are more willing
To invest heavily
Into India
Amazon
Is investing in India in a way that it never went there too
To try and waste, waste money and be irrational for China they look at the market cap of jd.com
80 90 billion
That's what
Amazon PO box
Are not being
So we see a lot more competition Indiana
Between American companies
Indian local sawdust in Chinese
Beyond India do you think the other emerging markets around the world will look more like China or more like
The USS
They develop and how optimistic are you about
Did we have Chinese companies
Ways to expand into those markets
Southeast Asia Eastern Europe and Asia Middle East
North Africa
Not as a
Shut the fertile hands
I think I think
They the Chinese companies
10 to
I know a little bit more about Chinese companies in the US than I do about
Chinese companies in Indonesia
So the Chinese companies unlike Japanese companies
Which came to the US in the 1980s
The Chinese companies
Kanto has a
Separate operation
Indian Idol
As compared with their home operations in
The management team is separate
The typically have a American
The head of the US operation like
Son, Daisy
I'm not like that but
Pineapple
And they don't quite impose
Chinese managerial method
On their us operation
Where is if you compare that with Japan
North Korea
Taqueria right
Is Japan lean manufacturing zero inventory and
They imposed even the
Hugo Minnesota
Ramona Flowers
Emagine Ohio
The Honda open expanding Ohio
In 1987
Imagine in Ohio 1987
Where the Americans there
Bowling in 02 the boss
Factory
Chinese companies don't do that so
Enter that 996 nonsense
Angela's 99 6 days a week
So I think
They're the Chinese
Managerial
Poage
Is quite different right so
It is
You know I
What time they serve on the board of attorneys Investment Company
Much less
The company alone
Rather than exercising active
Managerial voice
We can debate whether that's the right thing to do about but that's what I say
Right so maybe when I go to Indonesia
Be more handsome
But I do know that Alibaba is investing in India paytm
Patreon and
Wikipedia
I don't really know how
Interventionist
Alibaba is
Willis auto
Inquire
The both are happening
How how do you think the relationship
Swaintech and governor
Different
Between us in
I kind of feel like in the US
Washington DC is often at loggerheads with Silicon Valley
Whereas in China the interests of
Tak and the Garmin seems to be more aligned
To agree with
Well I think in the US
Weather Logan Heights is the right word to use II
I don't know but there is a
A distance
Between
Pride
In the fact that it is not
Located on East
But now they
Are no more realistic now they have
Washington the Air Buddies office in New York
Because because because the government is going to regulate what happens at Facebook and
And so if you don't work with the government the government will come to you
And so I think
Even the tech sector in the US has to be realistic about
The role of the government the government
Is not going to go
I think you know whether that's good or bad that's a separate discussion the government is not going to go
It could be even more active right it's always talk about
The current
Wave of
A technology
Producing
Potentially producing
Shoes winners
Adopt would be widened
The governor has two player
In China
I think
Know if you look at Alibaba maybe this is the old story now about Alibaba tencent Baidu
It is absolutely true as hands pointed out when they first developed
They didn't really have any meaningful
Relationship would I have
So there is a lava was backed by SoftBank
Tencent was backed by a.
I'm about to South Africa
Yeah
Sotalol
The question is now they're getting so big
Now they're getting so big
You know Alibaba nanjing finance and all these areas
Whether or not the government is going to get more
Right there is evidence that the government is getting more interesting
Then how do you structure that relationship
Is going to be
Definitely don't want to get involved
So far to kill them
Hainan
They are doing so many things
The government has to
Certification
So that's one kind of involvement the other kind of involvement that I see
Moral
China then I do
In the United States
Is is
Government loan venture capital
The Fonz
Invite
Very aggressively
Stage
Startups
You don't see that
Indian
You have in a one CIA
CIA
Oh okay
Seoul
Publix
Happening
The US Department of energy has Loan program
Different from equity
Investment
Weixin China
Shenzhen Capital right
And and
I actually think
If you look at that Moto
That model is closer to the Eastfield Mall
Then to the US mother
Israel
In the 1970s
This Is How They
Invested in the early start
JumpStart
Jump starter pack industry in Israel
Government as an investor for the key differences
Maybe the difference is not as big
But the commute
The difference is that in the case of Israel
The government was a more of a
Passive
Investor
Has relied on the judgment
All of the
Of the
Took a backseat
Where's in China maybe the government is more active I'm not sure
But also to be if I look at
The playing field
Apostle top 50 beaches in China
I would say probably 30 of
Are us back
Back by USA limited partnership with the LPS us USMLE
Probably 20 the ratio probably 20 of
RMB funds are doing well
I'm almost twenty I was a lesson
Less than
Some kind of government
I said okay but I also think
It is not the wrong thing
To do for the government
Go back meme
Startups
Adidas iPhone
That the reason is that
So it so
We talked about
Eternal 20
Law of the industry in China wants to develop
Rconnect
Pickle manufacturer
No
Energy these are huge
I actually wish to see more of that in the US
Exactly in the US right so what you see is
Law of investments in
Internet related things maybe an AI now
Unlike signs
Anything in between actually doesn't attract
Auto V it takes to get money from
Government official
Using
Is a different skill set
From designing
Best product
Designing
Abesco
Customer service
Designing
So
I want I want to see
Government
Invest in
In my heart heart
I still like to see
Or insurance
Pincher bug
What university
Play more
I could broken the way.
Yu-Gi-Oh
So I actually think
I agree with
Everything.
DJI drones
The US from
I didn't go to us don't lose out
Is not that there was no Capital funding
Putting them to fight against
Did you like the TV
In China I think what
Difference
Us
Is locking that manufacture
The sectors are manufactured spending
To to do better
So I actually think this is
One of the huge advantages
China House
Exactly Nicole location between technology and manufacture
So if you look at alarm Boston where do you see Manufacturing
Actually if you look around Silicon Valley
You don't seem a lot of that
It is
La Covenant Factory is okay for particular kind of Technology
Maybe lifesigns I'm not sure what right but
But yeah
Energy Capital Equipment and
You really need
Both large-scale Manufacturing
Biggest biotech I mean it's true that mean
Social search engine there's no reason why
MLB
A manufacturing version of
Call Silicon Valley
So
There's a book by actually MIT graduate
Bunny Farm
About
Heartware
Innovations in Shenzhen
Has a famous Hardware hacker really real
Sendai
We tend to think about and I was just copying
What he says is that it's much more than
Is incremental innovation incremental Innovations
On top of it basic model and they make it
Thousand times better
That margin of improvement
Is all that because of
Miss incredible
I'm having a lot of Technology
Involved
La Nova menu
Manufacturers evolve
Another consumer
10 started with
Barring other
We'll talk a little bit about the impact of the so-called
Fourth
Industrial Revolution
In the United States and in China
I mean if you look at all the major technologies that are obviously going to be disrupted by move already mention
Beauties yashow Advanced robotics
Xai
I'd genomics it and especially Gene editing
RCA 9
The two countries that are really at the Forefront
Are China and the United States and its
It's the private sectors of both
They don't seem to really be talking to one of
And these are really important things were interoperability
Standards
Ethics issues really needed to be
I am in
Autonomous driving things like that all these things are going to be really important
How
Musician area where you were going to see
Divergence and it in a lack of of interoperability or art do you think that this is a
Potential area
4 bottle cooperation
Or does it even even matter
I hope so
If you look at a i
There's some
Profound
Socio-economic implications
The arrival of
IAAI
You mentioned privacy
Transmission parts
Looking back on labor right
That kind of thing
Can be countries
Chinese value privacy as much as
Does American
Effect on labor
No China is still a AAA in the 1.4 billion people and lot of laborious
And there are still farmers and
So if you're just sort of think about
How you make this transition from low-income
A middle-income to high-income
You still need
Conventional industrialization why you have
Employment
So
Failure to talk to each other
I think and to think long-term about
The rise of
One of the things that I
That I read
About
Uno China 2025
No the division as you read about the Visions read about the industries reader
About the money
All these things
IP
Strategy
Financing strategy
What are you doing
Is
The implication
On society
Locations of Labor
This is remarkable to me right so if you read Marvin Minsky
Work on
From AI
He was MIT professor.
Going back to the 96 days
Father of AI
She began to talk about these things back in.
And
I do believe that lack of that conversation but by the way I might eat now has a
To study the effect of AI
Labor market
On that committee
And
It's a good
Except me
The disciplines that committee represents
Systematic effort try to understand and anticipate
I just don't see any of that in China
I was just as I remember when Amazon go
The amend convenience store by Amazon opened
Every article mentions how many cashier jobs will be lost
Where else went Bingo box or purple a company in China open there and then coming into and they have
300 of those now
No none of those articles
In China talks about Nation evenly
Like the word of
Cashier jobs
It's just less
I think we would use planes that Cavalier attitude
How much does a Cavalier is that s a
As a as a country
There's a lot more
Keepall for optimist
Stick on
Talk technology growth in China will narrow the gap
Bachata
Us
Give me a funny reason to believe that I mean they've they've only seen life in
Improve
As Technologies in a perfect correlation between
These two things
So far that's the case
Mexico continues to happen
What will the government do a decent job.
I'll probably solve that
Anaconda
Keep whatever's not working hush hush
And
It's is easier to have that position under authoritarian
You could argue
Dot-dot can happen
Faster
People get used to it
Authoritarianism
But I also think that I agree with pants on this couch Road
When I first came to the US
I was the
Pies to see movies
What's a Blade Runner
Which portrays this
Jesse Black Mirror
So there's a 3% in Western societies I don't really know
Why I should
Invest time in learning about that
Was Frankenstein more spiteful
Trying to destroy the world and others lot of
That in the western culture
What was the Renaissance
Both kind of
Both respect and
I'm recent and distrust philosopher who used
Sofia at NYU in Shanghai names and a green smash you with a book called Shanghai future
At the 1937 World's Fair and at the 2010 Expo
GM
Pavilions one was GM another
A book for General Motors twins both of them were about future cities
And
You know that
It was called
Futurama
In the time since Futurama his busy is a byword just for cheesie's or where's my Jetpack
Spiral Towers
In in in China is there still an earnest
Erase of this idea
Futurity
Technologically driven it is a betterment of
It's really interesting Scar from the Opium War from mother
Things that happened in the 19th century
Number people
I feel like $10 is good without technology we will be defeated again
And that kind of inference
It's true
We're still embarrassed about the boxers
But I think that is more gentle than
It's actually more gentle baby young technology
In the western culture there is always
Session
Look at what lawyers do
Star City right solder
Trade off
You always want to think about that
The downside
And then devise
Institution democracy is actually to guard against
Volume
Yeah where is he
The Chinese culture there's not
Similar
Forward Thinking about the dance
This will cover for kitchen about unification
I thought about hate this government is back
Or did the king is back just make sure he doesn't
Adversely impact us too much
That is very different
The sentiment goes like this
Okay this king is bad the next king will be great
Olympics in Beijing
Summer Olympics 2008 opening ceremony
I might do. I wouldn't want to show that for the rest of world
Brainwashing
Chinese reporters life back I know they look.
It is very different ethos very different
Absolute
So I think we should have a
Broderick
No the privacy issues
How we think about technology
How we think about all these
Collectivism
Yeah we don't have enough of
Conversation
Brother Paul you did a lot of research on the relationship
Talent and economic development I wonder
There a lot of light nutrition like me who
Come back and became Highway
Sea turtles
I'm enjoying Thai companies are started
What what do you think are factors that make them
Because not all of them are
They have a lot of adjustments to go through
After they go back
What's up I don't know the individual cases
Right so I think that's a cohort
The
The highway cohort
Is going to
Very important
China
So I think but the key thing is
I think
People like you Zara have to make a decision
Right
How
Local do you go
Do you go all the way to
The local
Things
And lose your
Sort of Iceland
Global
Argue with that China needs more of a globalist
Perspective
And ideas
Then
More MIT students more Harvard students going back
Play mobile games rise of China is not short of local
People right vagina is short of global perspective
Gomorrah of the attorneys
In US markets meeting the better things
And then totally agreeing with
Red soles
Occasionally
Guagua in Chengdu with your shirt off on a hot summer day
As always I do but but
Good but don't live that life
Let me try that next time I'll take you
Thank you so much for joining us and Kaiser is always fun to have you
And thank you so much to everyone in the audience for being here with us on a Saturday night
Thank you
Airline flight 798
San Jose International listening
M996
By the way we also produce a weekly email newsletter in English also called 9 + 6
Roundup of the week's most important happenings
Intec in China subscribers formative and fun to read the news.
Original content and Analysis from Zara and me
Stripe at nine 6. GG bc.com
Venture Capital firm based in Silicon Valley shanghai and Beijing with leading technology entrepreneurs
Ford has 18 years from seed to pre IPO with 3.8 billion dollars in Capitan dramatic Motocross
State funds GTA V invest in gold we minded entrepreneurs in consumer internet e-commerce Frontier
Tax in Enterprise
GTA V has invested over 280 companies with 29 IPOs in 22 unicorns
Pergola companies include
Airbnb Alibaba C trip Didi chuxing Domo hashicorp Hello by
Cows keep splat Square
Hotel wish someone true white white and others find out more at Gigi bc.com
You have any feedback on this podcast
Or would like to recommend a gas please email us at 996 at Gigi bc.com
This podcast is co-produced Battlefront and business partner
Kaiser kuo the host of the wonderful sinica podcast it covered China's economic political
And cultural issues