Sound the alarm at 6 in the evening
Hi there
Welcome to the 96 podcast
Brought to you by ggv capital and co-produced by the Seneca podcast
On the show interview movers and shakers
China's tech industry
As was Tech leaders
Weather us
China
Cross-border perspective
My name is Khan song I'm a managing partner at ggv Capital
And I've been working at startup investment in them in both in us and China for the past 20 years
My name is Sarah Jeong
I meant investment analyst igb capital
Jennifer Moore journalist
Why is the show called 96
96 is the work schedule that many Chinese Founders have organically adopted
That is 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
To us
996 captures intensity
Drive
In speed
Of Chinese internet companies
Many of which are moving faster
But even the American counterpart
Where does Tina come from
His name is Dan
Her name is Tina
She comes from China
Hi everyone this is Zara from gdb Castle
What you just heard is an app called also known as lingojam that's changing how millions of
Chinese people learn English today
Using speech recognition and artificial intelligence technology
I first heard of a Daily Show from my mom actually
Like many Chinese people she learn English in school when she was young
But when she was preparing for her first trip to the US to attend my graduation
She still panicked about her ability to communicate with actual Americans
So she told me she now uses an app called Duty short everyday
Where she speaks English sentences into her phone and is scored on her pronunciation
The app works like a game where you must
Pass a certain score before proceeding to the next level just like Angry Birds
Glitter addicted to the app now and sometimes even with my help was just stuck at a certain level
And her spoken English actually improved a lot and she was able to make some conversations with Americans when she came to visit
Is LG TV is actually one of the earliest investors in goalie schwa
Hudson are super excited to be interviewing founder and CEO of Lily Shaw
Here in Beijing hgtv's evolving lifestyle events a huge conference that gather as many of Chinese chop Hunter
Printers in a Buster's where he was a speaker
You might hear cars honking as we're close to the street and this is Beijing
We're super excited to have you join us today
Well thank you so much for having me in Santa Clara
So let's start with your products
If I'm someone who's trying to learn English as a Chinese person how would you describe Julie Shaw in
Three sentences
It's a
It's an AI English teacher on a mobile phone that can't have
You
Learn English more effectively than the conventional methods
How many users do you have
So far we've got over 50 million registered users across the
Quote mostly in China with also
Over under 75
About 50 million
A lot of them are paying right as of this July we've got over
A paying customer
And the more interesting way
Over 80% of them were paying for the very first time
How much on average does
Hey
Between 60 to $80
Are you
Go out that's how much they pay for it
The first time
But but
A year it cost about $150
IC
Take how many years does it take to get
250 million
Register users
Let's see what the app was first launched I got in time table 2013
2013 Ford F150
So now Jenny first talk to me about this investor
You just started
That's right that's why we were actually literally I think
Ggbs
Earliest investment as of
Maybe May of 2013 took Jenny was
Was saying hey you should take $1000000 at least from us that's
Are the smallest
Well we can put in
You know I'm thinking about even last year that was a funny Act
Yeah
Black first two months since you launched you you roast her number one in the Apple App Store
Free paid apps
In China right it's also very interesting kind of a historical events because
The time in April of
13 earthquake
Inkster trying ain't got nevermind
Yeah before then we were a free app
That we said okay what time you get paid
And we going to donate all the revenue
How much
It was going to be but all the revenue
To Charlie to 2in
Go to the
People who are in the earthquake zone
So we did that and quickly
Rose
To the top 10 of the
China Market
And then you know
I stayed there for three weeks at the peak was number to across-the-board it just right
What was it Temple Run
Then we were near the top of the leaderboard for for a while then
August
Top 2013 when we launched the Android version we decide to
And make everything
Free so
To sort of spiritual growth
We went from there
So I think that's incredible because learning English is
Many people considered to be a boring task
Learning takes a lot of effort and for Education app to rolls to the top of the App Store is quite incredible
What do you think about Louis show that makes it so
Appealing to people and it literally addictive
Yeah but that's one of the questions that we thought
A lot about when we were starting out because
Traditional learning is kind of boring
And especially English many people hate it sometimes because they run into a really bad
LCD display
My whole life
But you know what we're starting out we saw the need
That's something you know you reading didn't
Think up whale
When you're in the US right now so so that's something you know highest
Got got off the plane and the started you know
Really deserving the local market will result in need without okay
Mobile surgeon
Time chart of time travel
Tell you are in 20
Funny 12.12 ain't tryna you saw this karaoke app named Tombaugh
Deputies searching
The first I thought
Stupid right who would be saying to yourself
People that age group remember you know this this built-in microphone thing
It's really unique
It could change people's behavior so we're okay
You are so interesting into that cell phones maybe the class B practice English
How can we make them stick
Rice always thought okay now you know Angry Birds
You know
Very popular at the time
Can we give advice
But you know what would be the key element of gamification can use
Okay so maybe some feedback on their pronunciation
Raikou
Indication of how good their pronunciation is
That at that time I I caught my
College buddy linkway who was a research scientist at Google in Mountain View back then these rationalizing speech
Conditioned air Miami
Can you do this
Yeah course
Okay so why don't we
So that was really very International without okay that's build a very simple
Utility
Push something you content
People everyday give me fighting 11
Games you know
Feedback
I see if they stick
Sweetie at the first day she will think about the hey you know can we make it you know simple but easy to use
So that we can
Accumulate the uses and keep growing right
So just like you know
The founder of iuc hush up and was talking about on stage at the first station
So that's what we did and it within the first week
One day
What we were looking at that are traffic at just
Shut off
Then we realized
That within a few hours people are sending us
Screenshots of
Happy Feet shirt
Apple's App Store in mainland China Hong Kong company in Japan
So that sucks whatever
Our first big wave of uses
Because apples
So I think you are at your company became profitable this February
Do you have any tips on
Entrepreneurs with regards to monetization and how you started thinking about it
Early on
Yeah I mean you no looking back I think we did
I can share.
More about our sort of
Guelph history and
Key decisions we made it on the way
Of reading
Before we decided to enter this Market we ask few questions
We thought okay we going to do something
Customer-facing
And we saw
Big needle Chinese
Even with
Very ineffective
Conventional methods
People are partying like
$5,000 or more a year
Into the Traditional brick-and-mortar School Supply
So we like okay
This is clearly they're not getting much in return
Statistics
Shows
That you know half of the people
Who paid that much money
Never go back again to the school after 2 months
I said remember they pay like 24 at 12:20 to 24 months
And altogether
I just stopped going even though they still have money man I was talking to one of them
You know owners of a very big branch
The supermodel
You said yes
They're probably I'm like okay so
I see a big gap in
The data exchange how much people are paying and how much they're getting
Return
So
ICP Market
IC
Huge
Efficiency in a system
Then we got excited
Because
You should just pick up in about exchange on the
It deficiency
Technology can come in and
Healthy food that's very gracious to us we are all three co-founders
I'm just company we were engineers by training so we with this will figure something we can do is
We can use technology and products
To improve efficiency
Some cysts
And we can get Daddy out of
So what role does air play Spa
Specifically
And what can what kind of dish no service
Can you provide
Exactly
So
I'm going to talk about AI into Xbox One S Automotive user value expect
The other is solid business
Model S
From the use of an expectorant we realize
There are two major Tran
I think
Like the
The theme of the
Lights out
Introduced
You know if they're popular
Terminology
Talk about lot in recent years called
Salvation
We see
2 keywords in consumption
What is
That the quality of
Backup. Which
Oftentimes translate into more personalized service
The other is for the time or efficiency aspect
Teapot Chinese
Pay money to get to save the time so that we have wasted our time on the things they love right so these are the two
And these two Trends are
Nowhere to be seen
It's very expensive
What's what makes it more expensive is the only
Amount but doesn't leave this thing you spend time together results pre-season get this right
So we thought what if
We can reduce
The price they pay
And make them reach their learning goals
Faster
So that will be a
They're comparing
So we thought
What's the future of learning
Look like
We literally close our eyes we would dream about it for quite a while
We thought
Towards
Personalization
And high
So we thought
What can make it possible
Now we realize
You can only go so far
By throwing
Human teachers
And weeping
Default
What time is it
We see a lot of one of my models both online off
But that they can go so only go so far and they by the way they do
They have really bad that you cannot
So we thought okay what was that
Without okay
It should be something like
The that the Baymax
The Disney movie paintings
You have some intelligence
Virtual
Understands you really well
I understand you you're learning better than yourself let any human teacher possible because of the interaction
Does product knowledge more
Exactly
Hundreds of thousands and millions of users
By the way
This is I'm going to throw this out at 2 to review to get your input. I think this is
Higher level
Of shared economy
We talked on share economy with
Talk about the show me about physical
We are able to hire the best of the educator
AI scientist did that designers
Across-the-board and they do whenever go to Kasam to teach because they thought that's going to be a waste of their time but
Now they're dumping took the knowledge X
What is into this engine right and that the
It's negligible
This is a whole new model of really
Pushing the boundary of human learning
Forward so we can learn from
The engine room
Radio we think as time goes by
The brain
Is AI teacher
Going to be more powerful in a really surpassed most
And we've already demonstrated that
Even before we launched this AIX teacher in July of 2016 with you tattoo Matt experiment
Wzts
Took which test as a benchmark because
Ticketmaster the comedy paint framework which is a conical level system of
Proficiency
The result can be very interesting late in the users using a learning from Rai teacher on their cell phone
We're able to get up one level
And there's
System
With only about 36.5 hours of study within two months.
And recommended at least 100 hours of study to
To get up.
That level so we
Chipotle learning
Efficiency
So we think this is just
Stony Point
3D owl
We know are probably has a lot of
Eres Tu in
Direction
So ask someone from China was studying overseas a lot of my friends went to English schools like sheen on Fallon and others
Do you think that with
Absolutely Shore
Do you think you guys can replace those schools and replace actual teachers or do you think they still have a roll
Play in this new world of AI
Yeah I got that question a lot I think we've shown in the past year or so
Who is that
For adults
Definitely we think
Can't do most of the word if
Today we are uses on average do they spend over 5 hours a week
And I've been getting very noticeable Improvement
How are you this way
3D
Exceed their expectations We Didn't Start you know
You know with
$15 a month
Monthly subscription model they can't get this kind of improvement
But you know and if you go down there the age group
If you're talking about teenagers leaving kids
I think human interaction is still needed but the AI
Can really help a lot
Let me give you another
Cervix during example
We did a social responsibility project in the highlands Chiang Rai Highlands in rural China of a Tibetan Avenue School
Last year
They don't have
And so we donate
Smartphones and we made our paid a t-shirt a product for free for them
At 9 months
Using this product
Two to three times
A week
Each time for 45 minutes
There are how many students did this
They are about a hundred a hundred and
Not 9th grade
Their average score score improved for in English
By almost 20 points
On a hundred point scale
Improvement
Yes it's it's pretty remarkable.
Should be told that their starting point starting over isn't that high but still very impressed
So that's extreme
I I don't Envision that our teenagers with ob only
Starting studying for tomorrow
But still
We actually have a lot of things teachers as an app as our users
On my time you know is a sign you know
Assignments
For my students to do to practice listening speaking
And so so I think
It really is not about
Replacing the teachers Robitussin actually
Alleviating some of them and help them
Pandora
Precious time
The other more sort of the motivation the purple character and the
The other aspect
Education
Redeemer well-rounded
Human being
I think that that's a very valuable aspect of Education as well as that I think that's going to take a longer time for AI
How to play a significant role
Start an email
Maybe you some of the that us audience didn't I know this but think some of the
China Celeste about heroes by Queen on Providence a 70% of the
Primary schools and the secondary schools
Latin
The number is 50
That's really huge deficit
1.3 billion people in China find German people live in the city
So it's not an 800 million people
Mosam don't have ass
English teacher
Or just in general quality you know teacher
Espresso
Yeah it's a huge problem we think
In English
You can also teach other subjects or Chinese
Later as well
But I think so yes so I think the general argument
Hose farewell you know
Across-the-board we think
Artificial intelligence in body
User-friendly Services can really go a long way there
They can't help equalize
The fields pretzel
People with different socioeconomic
Quite education on and they can really bring down the car
And improve the efficiency
Think about that you know a lot of the
Sixth-grade students
They go to bed at
11 p.m.
Too much homework
Do a lot of them go into waste
People know that
So a lot of the problems
Tempe salt
Improve efficiency green. The cost and also equal access I think
We didn't think about AI this term
Particularly we thought about technology
Prada getting people's
Mass
Some experts
Norwich ND
Bacon to the product and that it can't evolve evolve
Shy one level you have English
Chinese and others
Academic stop
That people would
You can teach in school
Another way of looking at
Another level
Is that
They could be more professional usage
Tweening
For the set episode
Can you share more about that
Access
What can learn new things that could be done with this report
Yes let me give you a couple examples we work with
They're well-known education Sports name that last night was he lives in San Francisco open in the past
To oppress US GDP spending almost half
Time in Shanghai
He's learning theory which we use
Extensively in a product called rhr
Recursive hurricane
It's just one of many many see what you can find
Right but it's very unique one
He told me one
Football
Club Soccer Club
Belgium
Was using his
Tony Siri
2 train
The players
And
And I'm more of a human-centered way
Breaking down the movements
The players
Get better faster
We were talking about
You can definitely imagine
Some kind of product
You know what you maybe even with
Yao Yai
To read help
Professional sports team
With replacing
The human coaching at
Give me five
Product
And another aspect
One of my friends who was doing
The training of car mechanic
She actually
Coddington
In-depth chat with me the other day
Asking me
Hey can I use AI to really revamp
Michael
Now it's very
Labor intensive
Takes a long time and depending on that the trainer's quality did the outcome of that the cost
There is
Parliament
So
Now if we started talking about
The huge Market
Professional training China and also
Call r e d a i
And other Technologies
Reedy
Soda Princeton
Why complicate
How how do you use AI
Universal teacher
To guide them through
All the questions
I think you can start from something relatively simple
We were talking about for some check up procedures or some something that you would
Normally required
Memorizing a pretty thick manual or something
You can't actually make them some kind of game
And
Cup and remember
Small bites
Okay and it can really use your of your appointment time and you know you can just
If you have 5 minutes you can't fire which one took challenges and you remember something and that time you just pick up from there
Breaking down
Monolithic
Horse and Rider small pieces and use them to sort of Stitch the elements together
Individualized
Also obviously across different domains and subjects we need that Doma export
Commander
That's why you know we are increasingly more and more you know content-heavy company as well you know
A lot of pictures he professional
Generator exactly we have we have we had a community that seem more ugc than we had PGC so that's
Topic is there and I talked about in relief
Epicenter company
Build up
The curtain designs
It's really about
Looking at
Using East
And with your product and service around
Give you feedback that's ugc
But when the professional content creators
I hope you do
Roberto Conte
Leprechaun PGC
That's why I wasn't very volleyball
Pole
Is an armada
Not only the professionals generique on
The uses action feed up to us
Decree lockdown
You don't get that bad individual
That's a very unique
OK Google
But I really had told me earlier that
You can learn English for a while but if you need to use English
To get a job in a job interview situation
Is a different kind of application English skills
And of course more practice in
Your fine amount of time to Ace an interview
You'll be nice if their module
Miss America
Can go through
Yes we have that kind of Rogers and we literally have examples of a security guard at an office building
Training are out for half a year and got a office job
It really recorded huge pay raise like we have
Lot of different samples like that
And we have funeral
Grandpa's are retired
Deeply worried about not being able to talk to his grandson leaving San Francisco starting user app and
His next visit
Finally be able to communicate
English be self-sufficient and just go round
Everything so
Yeah so when you when users first open the app date
Debrief survey
22 indicator interest
Why do you want to learn English by its weather if you want to study abroad shop abroad
Me to be able to talk to foreigners or get a job if pass yes
212 Warwick Ave
That's right that's right we tried Reedy to personalize the content for them and I'll also they can explore but yeah we WeChat
To make it relevant
EDC that exciting things you can do after you hit you
Have you one of the most powerful motivation
I want to switch
Papik tumor
Or personal let's talk about your background and Hangzhou City
East York College interest
Right and then you went to a Chihuahua and then you went to Princeton for graduate school
So you speak perfect English now but I remember you said before that when you first came to the US for Princeton
Your first news at McDonald's and you had difficulty
Communicating with
The counter help at McDonald's
I wish it was very simple English and that made you think about
Why diets
The case so can you share more about that experience and white why do you think
Even though you got top scores in English test in China
It was still difficult for you to come in and see where the actual American
Yeah so it's quite sciatica
Going to be in my life life like memory now that was
September 1st
And I was at Anna McDonald's near the Newark Airport
I was trying to just pick out a few items but
Not that way I didn't understand I finally
You know I said okay number 2
Picked up stepmill
No remember that I
I got almost perfect score in my TOEFL exam
Missing 10 points
Mexican scale
But I think
At a time
I was
Mostly doing draws on my grandma you know maybe
Riding
My Melissa peking
Didn't get that much
Exposure effect
So when I met
My late advisor at Princeton I was
Most worried about
Speak speak
Can I really
You'll follow and have a beautiful conversation and discussion about me recent copy
But then I I
Maybe spend an entire year
Watching the news talking to my America
In a fellow students and sauce was getting
All the practices that I could
Verity health
So I
It's really about
Not just getting your your language at
Education from the books and from the unit doing drills
3D
Use it in practice and practice makes perfect ID
Price bear Wild
A scale
Type subject
I like language
Unfortunately even today that the whole
Education system and the setup of Tanks running course and in China is more like a luxury
The teeth the teachers take the center
Stagehand
Preaching way Mariah
Said that that's that's really I think concentrate
If so when we started out
A building to stop
I have many of my
Fellow classmates in my mind on my
Is it would travel back in time and they use my app what
What they need what would I need
The most
So we really think a lot of Allison speaker
Practices
Imports and
Annapolis
And also really help them get access to authentic
Lime juice
Dialogues
Spicer we we we hired
Very talented writers to write authentic.
We have
Top tier voice actor
Actresses house
Report
The
Recordings
Yeah we we try to give people
As authentic
Yeah it's alright
Transporting native English speakers
2 people who may not otherwise have access
Living in
Exactly exactly
You had that... We think both
Helps in the learning setting and also
Also I found my motivation
So you were here before
That's right I remember for most of the last decade
And Stucky being a returnee a sea turtle
Coming back to China
Internet start
Is nice
Muggsy Bogues
Grassroot
Enough
Hello Kitty cheat
That's right you know what's going on
But that seems like with what you're doing now
You'll return the background Ashley is a huge
Plus for you yeah I think I did a couple things right looking back
The first thing is I took my time
Before coming back to China and even after coming back to China
To really observe
Allure
And I saw a lot of examples of techies Chinese Takkies with some kind of Technology coming back really use
Use that as a dog looking for the nails to get off price
The results weren't good
I do think the Ops
I had a
US Patent no
Virtual Router migration in space you know I could have raised a huge amount back then
Studer House of rats
Sephora software-defined networking could just do a startup
I didn't do that I thought okay
Recondition myself and the final unimarket find out what Missouri where am I
PM hat on and build a solution
The Haven at p.m. background is Ashley
Yes I think so yes now I think.
Startups in this
Related field
It starts before my startup and did they didn't
So that while because
Have only single founder
Tech background
Virginia
And they come back with us going to hammer starting to build privacy
To see if they can stay
So I think yes having great co-founders is great process and also having a product respect Andre
Reading you know
If I weren't doing this startup
With this approach
I was not going to be place
Co-founder and he would probably other successful
Research scientist I call you something else
App identify the user need
And probably first and then as you build the solution you use
And also if you look at a spectrum are approaches pretty Silicon Valley
Yes okay we use a very
Approach
So I think really you know find the right problem to solve and find the right
People and 2 is reading important
If I were to do the moron
I don't think I'm going to be the best counter for like bikes
Right so just find the right right problem right space and you pick the right approach
I think you are
Experis
Including your overseas experience can be reduced by
Would you say the other Shore as more product driven or technology
Honestly I item make that distinction
I think people don't consume technology
The oldest of the only consumers
So good product
Technology will be embodied in a product
Pink Tesla
As an example
Can you talk about some of the situations that you've been through with the product and
The major decisions you've made along the way and things you've learned
Utility app that people wanted
And then that's
A practice
Practice to revolves
Into
As largest
Nationalist community
We realize okay people have the needs
The used
App daily
It would be italicized I just paid 5000
Dollars to that.
High School
Why don't we offer
A systematic solution
People don't pay
Hateful this piecemeal
Corroncho toys
But they would pay for
Somatic
So we we we we
We went out
Talking to the top publishers
Pearson's
First Cambridge of the world
And try to license
All the famous
Text books
What design for the offline custom teaching environment they worth it
Someone lying there in their caucino studying in the solo mode on a cell phone
With okay why don't we go there from scratch
Did the perfect solution we envision it does exist today
So now we've assembled at work
Stephen not easy and we find out where us and China experts
It started doing that
So the stuff is really you know
Going from I just just a utility app and the community into
A full flash
Honey technology company
And with
Asystematic
Leveled
You guys are not having a project manager experience was important
So you don't just
Take your tongue out and look for
From the Seoul
How did you
Qingdao product management
Experience
Hi Google
Especially in Silicon Valley
The shortest answer is really follow your heart
Back when I was doing my PhD in computer science at Princeton I remember I
Didn't even know
There was this
Position hot
Park management
Yeah you don't have the spec Tech back on but ice also
Try the product manager role
Bridgeport
So interesting I'm back on before
Not NBA I ain't
You know I wasn't
Got an offer at McKinsey
That's right you know about appropriation War preparation for my
The interview
I actually read 18 month Wall Street Journal
And I died I literally
That's one of the really good
Operation and so many case study yes I did
I was interning at Cisco do you know riding my agromin to the big fat routers but
I would I would not go back to my apartment
Drove down the busy Central to to Stanford campus interview practice with my photo studio
No friends at Stanford
Yes we did that for the whole summer always knew that you were
You didn't just want to be an engineer you wanted to be in the business
This what I think I think I see a lot of
Country House
Beautiful Technologies right but I also see you
Anal fistula
The weather
Great businesses
They could be even better.
You know how to use it
Lack of
Bridge spa temperature
I can do that. I actually was the only time he's got an offer
McKenzie
As a consultant
But that is now and I got the offer from Google
Yeah
You know if I could
Learn how to
Build up rocks on Google
That's probably the best of
You can get it if you want to become Mexico
That's why I went
We see a lot of Engineers
Obvious including Chinese
That don't have that business.
So there corn Cole
Stuck
Doing just acknowledging
Refining algorithms
And it's harder over Pier time of 5-10 years
To then become an entrepreneur
You don't have the
That a comprehensive in a background
I'm a business to the complement of Technology
Yeah I can totally relate to what you said
Examples of inspiration
Hdb to figure out how to help
Engineers want to have in Abyss.
Yeah practice so you at your expense
Yeah but you know honestly I see a lot of
Ingenious whether they are Chinese or other background
If you just give them the right exposure
Doraemon a date they can grow in
When two or more well-rounded
Uno founder
Yeah that's
Did you always know that you were going to
Return to China or did you also consider staying
Honestly I always know
But I'm still remember very clearly you know when we bought that little condo in Sunnyvale with my wife and we were talking about
Who is such a great company we work
At least want that flight for 5 years
That I left everything
Alabama center for 5 years
I didn't I didn't know
Sweetie I think
I kind of sensed the growth my personal growth is started to a plateau
A little bit
And also when I visit Becca
Back to China I see
Just Energy
Okay you can see it but you feel it too
Okay so that
So the both factors are my
Interesting
Wow how did your lifestyle change
When you first
Return to China from
Google
Do you think our podcast
I
I no longer own a car
I I took the very crowded Subway
I ought to try to save money action I sleep with my
College buddy who was also a returning from Harvard doing start
We we share an apartment
Did I had a 1-hour emoni Subway commute right with two transfers at the beginning
Laura where's obviously it was great
I was watching people
Using their cell phones
Exactly you you would buy the same kind of breakfast by at
Convenience store
And you just just really live
The way they left
And watch
Honestly I didn't have the time to watch so much TV but I would talk with them over lunch and my my chair
Tennessee
Tell me about weather wash
I would just listen to your conversations
Actually
Did the first Spark
Came from my lunch conversation with my colleague I did in the starting my call me right away I joined at China which is one of the leading
My yellow card Eastwood
Should we be watching more American TV shows more movies
Poopy so much Soul into different language in school
If you pee so much and now you ask me any more TV shows movies
Then I started to look into smart
I see Houston man I see how
The current we wasn't your first product actually I thought about that
Thought about
Can we do something with better
Christian agradan to a funeral TV
Leave me alone movie Bittersweet stremio something or or Enterprise
Finalize resuming electroneum mobile
Because I see a huge Muse and eat and us that
IC
Clear growth
Mobile in general
So would you say you decided to start a company and then went out to identify to find
No problem in a market or was it
You saw the problem first
I
I clearly told myself you know it's the right time to leave Google and then do something
And I had
Four choices
I cooked
What state in the Bay Area and I
I was getting a lot of you know LinkedIn
Private messages from recruiter sweat till you can't come join us a small start-up you could do it on your own in the Bay Area
Animated Hobbit episode
So I would just go back to China
Brandon
I said okay
Now you already back in China
There's actually
Not that
Big of a hurry
You should take your tie
Really learned
The Marquis that are really finding the right user need first
Google recently launched the new headset that can
Automatically translate everything you here in a few languages
What is the name of that product ends you think in this age
With these products will people still need to learn foreign languages in the future
I really want to try that
Something later this month when I visit us I'll try to get a pair of that
Yeah I think that if that works well I think it's going to
House off
Some of the problems
Like my parents when they travel abroad maybe you can
I hate you.
But I don't think that's going to be completely eliminated that I share in a market in fact I
Unimaginable with
Technology like that you know you would at the school system would eliminate English as a subject
3D I think that the natural way
4 people
Communicate
It is through there
Traditional conversation, Mather
People that do that
And also
Process
Learning a language
Is also a
Process of
Understanding that culture
And also it's a process of
Celcom
We see that comment a lot warmer uses in a let me know the grammar and vocabulary don't have a conference
Exactly when they actually are Beyond
How to communicate to the people there entry
I think it's it's it's
It's alert
It's a learning experience and that
Appoint
You know you able to
Do the things that you weren't able to do before so I think so
I don't like that
Right wing
When Jenny first told me about your team
I was surprised that no one on your team had any teaching background
Teaching English has been in ICU said done for over a decade
There a lot of academic study on it and what's the best approach and so far
Now those two different schools when I have the
Ability to innovate
But they understood some of the theory behind
Dot teaching English
What teaching General
So how did you initially develop.
Pro tyre products
And handle this iteration send it shortly
Not having that background
Get to some kind of product Market
Dad the darkness answer is
We just did what we feel is
As users up
Exactly as I could learn English
The hard way
Okay we thought okay and we weren't trying to build the Silver Bullet
At the beginning
I don't think
I still don't think we have the Silver Bullet
Voting process
Okay at the park is never finished
Let's just push baby 1 dialogue
Office of higher level in interest per day
And it's interesting to them they can practice Kathy back that's good enough
That doesn't require that much of universal curriculum
Go to research
But now we believe that there was a design team at the at the end
How big is a tuna
About 40 people
So I actually don't think you don't mess hat
All the you know mechanics
When he started out
Riesel at you know you bring the right people at the right time if we were
To get the best
You know
Kitchen design expert
Back in 2013
So I think it's just
Soto the team along the way.
Can you talk about the geographical spread of
Louis R Us users and what kind of users they are they students were white collar workers West
Breakdown
Yeah so we have one third of of uses being a K-12
So they're underage
And weep
About
Weather little bit less than 1/3
Are you just being
College students
More than 1/3
And you have students outside of China
Yes we have
Now I think we have less than 10%
How about you just being a brat
Mosto
In China
Because you would need to be able to read Chinese
The app is only in Chinese
But yes I ain't tryna we we are
Buy Auto
We have flour uses ain't
First day of cities Balto II
Port Huron
Countryside
And you mentioned that your
Your company can serve as a force for equalizing
Nation within China
People ain't too bad may not have access
Was too good English
That's correct. That's why we did we see huge potential there and
This year we have set up
A dedicated team working on social
Working with ngos
Improving
Access to
Quality Inn
We are hoping
Dodgers score
Would you consider expanding two languages other than English
It's always on a road map
Weather for Lake.
What are three new things that you Zurich
Expect in the neck
Steer
Betsy
They would definitely
Cm
More
Efficient
Teacher
Cell phone
Number two they will see you some
Very cool
First
In the world kind of Technology
Ready to lunch and learn
I think there will also see you some our new
Exciting
Fox
Yeah
This this mean
I think Alicia also has the world's largest database of
Chinese people
Pronunciation
In English what you do with all that
We punch the data and the we keep improving our language assessment
Today we have
Other worlds
What would you need
The most
Accurate
Speech
Ignition engine
Thanks to that
Cutest
And also we Beauty on top of that dataset
Now our engine
Was not only able to
Actually gif
If you back on
Peoples
But also on
Grandma
Vocabulary
Flynn Center
Coherence hbase get all major asset
Backed up
People speech
We even also
Develop
Assessment
Writing
Yeah so so we we've been building up
Full stack
AI engine
To help people
How to learn Unity
Yashow is easy to tell
People when they're wrong
I think it might
Baby harder to teach them what is right
XY so that's an area we being
Making a lot of Investments
We have
Recently set up
Small office in San Mateo
Oh okay
Former CIA
Scientist
Stop on Facebook
And the Weeping hiring event aggressively balding
China and the US
To read it got the best people
Excited about what we do and if we can
I also can't you build with that Talent
To build
The next generation of Technology Pro and cons
I think both
These are the three pillars
To solve the problem
You mentioned
How big is your us
I know it's a few people we we we hope to
Got to
By the end of this year
But we have very high SED how do you say
That's really exciting
So
I wanted to talk a bit more about Monica
Position has allowed
Westers may have the impression that Chinese users are less willing
Pay for knowledge
Incontinent
I think that's been changing dress
Tickling the past few years
Projects like the dollar or smile at where people pay subscription fees to access knowledge
I think Alicia is another reflection of that do you find a surprising that Chinese people are paying so much
Foreknowledge
Yeah totally I think it's an unstoppable Chan
In all thanks to the surge of easy access
Quality content as well as
Mobile payments
On top of what you smashing these are these are real examples but
I would want
One thing which is
Education
You know parents are so much exactly in Chinese
Morning
Or anything else
Prioritizing spending
You know
Percent of
Total spending on
Freezing a
Child Inc
It also
That's that's
My bogging figure figure
Another education
That's been making a lot of waves
Vipkid
Do you think they are
Compare Dulce the Mystic
Competitor
How do you think
Hair product compare
View them as a competitor because number one day Focus mostly on kids
And so far are paying customers are mostly adults all y'all young young
Young adults
Number to we take
Different approach
You know they are trying to bridge human teachers and students
They're more like
We think we are on a different
Quote unquote Innovation curve
We think we are trying to do what human teachers can do
Oro do it much better than human teeth
So are we build AI
So I think
The approaches are different
And companies are also guard
I think both have have
Their sweet spot
Will be our top advice for
New Shanghai
Overseas returnees
Chinese students who study abroad and 1/2
Start new company in Troy
Call gdb
Yes number one call ggv talk 2GB
Honestly I think I we were very fortunate
To have DTV hazard
Their first semester
And the bee our continuing supporter
GBS
The unique
Perspective
Both of you at Market in China and also
It's understanding in both technology and
Commerce I think it really is
Quite made mix
Veronique
By the way it has really good reputation Cross of both markets are doing
Secondly I think it's really
About
Finding your
Calling you if you are a just hot core in all Technologies
Oig Orban
Youku made
Have a different
A decision-making process that is someone who
I'm just glad you
Identify your Bureau and what you owe you
Aspired to become and then but regardless I think really find if you think China
Viator Greece
Not really
Take the time
Understand the market
Even if you your role
Will still be the CTO but you still want to understand
In the past
18 Monticello
You see a huge wave of new AI startups
Technologist with their golden Hammer looking for problems they don't have a good
End-user usage case
Have a rita
It'll get that did the order straight
Identify the problem first
Stan Phillips
Solve it
The other way can be
As you go through this stinking and Analysis process
It's also very good way to find the right people
I would
Strongly advise against to be a single founder
I think having a good team is
Half of 6
Footings optimal mix initially
Two or three people
8202 i3
I think
And you didn't jump straight in
I can buy you worked at a online advertising
And that helped you
2K activator
Proud to have you leave for my McKenzie interview and you know it.
Asia at Princeton
I took only one class which way
What's a high-tech
Icy Hot by their experience veteran and that he used to teach at HBS brand we use it
HBS case studies
That really help
Pet my
But then
I'm coming back to your question you know
I joined at China not because of its technology
Because of its
Reputation ink
Marketing
Operation
These are the things I know right
To a Google and Valley and I know I would need
If I'm going to be the CEO of a nuke
That's so
You are well prepared before you get this
I tried jumping to the quick fire questions
The first one is an entrepreneur that you admire the most and why
Admire
Quite a few people
But if I had to pick one
I would say Jeff Bezos
I don't know him
Personal yet
But I know he's a prince hello
Which Beatle enter
The key thing is I think
She's better vision
He started from building a lalala bookstore
But I think she always had
A very big
Habesha skulduggery weather
You don't you don't read a lot about
Come come on this beach
But you just
Cheap
Plugging away
Once you sort of build a reputation track record
Even
Wall Street
Kind of understand
He swept
You know the valuation of whatever it's just a sign
People's confidence in Kiss approachable
Thought that I read
So I and also
I will always
It'll make this
Analogy that most 99% education companies went offline
Today
On the market
The more of the Walmart
Did the core competency is in operation efficiency
Who try really hard to squeeze out maybe living profitability
Ending
The employee
Large wolf
If they throw morva
People
A problem
But we are definitely more of an Amazon model
In our core competency is technology part in data that's also a very end
You know once we hit
Prophet
Trinity which we did back in this past February you have a much nice North Margin
Justina
The Unicorn
That model
Even the scale the size of the company
Amazon is Stephanie
Their nipples
Traditional
And then she was very hard even though they're very big already
Exactly you know you know BB focus on the most impactful problem to solve
Everything we do is we we got him out of the car that
Share with us something you read recently
That inspired you a lot
Could be reason or a while back
Inspire you
Yes
But if you think some of them are in Chinese people
May not resonate and in the US but I will say you know I recently reread the
Books from Ben Horowitz
The hard thing about hard things
Irie locked up
Yeah I just
I always enjoy
Reading especially
The first four chapters
For me that's
Very relaxing
His problem
What
At the same time yeah I'm kind of traveling and I'm putting myself in his shoes I'm traveling through time
I'm and I'm like
Yes what would I be
What position would I make
Had I been
I'm like yeah so what's Ohio's jaw strength
Who's suffering
Problems back then
Tell this to my colleagues I'm like
Look
Things are never easy if you want
Make something
Keep on your way
What keeps you up at night and one more
Should you to get up in the morning
Asleep
I sleep pretty well
What's a thing that you worry about
But yes I think
At this stage what
Think about the most is
Really
How to build
That the best team
Really
Make
Did the future
Learning
A reality
Because I my partner tonight
We have a deep conviction that
Educational battle where is learning is
Is definitely long overdue for a remap
End of the first three industrial revolution steel industry
I think the 4th
Revolution Star Staffing
Change that
And it's
Both exciting and also challenging
Stephanie interdisciplinary Africa
So that's why now we have
Professor nichter pre-season
Expert
Cognitive neuroscience
We have
The Kylie in
Computer science from Princeton as of
We have
Professor Dan Schwartz the dean of the school of education at Stanford
Hazard device
What getting
Experts from
Different discipline
To work with us
3D
Pink OtterBox how the future learning should look like
Weekend
Then make it happen
This is very exciting but
I think you're really getting the right
People
Together
And
Astilbe
And protect
I am making progress is
Is it
Different
Including my advisor.
So when you wake up in the morning what gets you excited
Sweetie just thinking about
How lucky myself and my
Team is in the history of
I was reading the other day Prosperity. As I was reading
You know of brief history of tomorrow
Lookbook
Yasso
Ryan Switzer
They're lucky
Being born trailer
At this age and also had this background you know going overseas really open your eyes and see what
Also and also
Which host
We have technology
Keto Market
It is in China right
Everything's starting
Really I think almost all the stars are aligned already
That's really keeps me at all so I give as well
Not very very lucky
Yeah
One last question what is one thing you believe in
And that other people
Maybe
5 to 10 years
Majority
Update
Subjects
People learn
Can be augmented
Buy artificial intelligence in a major way
You know that the scope is definitely not limited
Tucson a skill-based
Sis
Brasa Pisco
If that happens it could be the single most important factor to change the
Inequality in access to good teachers
Exactly I think technology
Or more specifically artificial intelligence powered learning products
Will be the biggest game-changer for edging
Android on very cheap smartphones
He's going to be sold in
The Raconteurs
That's
Super
Excited
All right we're very excited to
To see where the we sure will grow in the next five
And yours and thank you so much for joining us
Bank of America
Now you were here a short interview with Jenny Lee
Managing partner at ggv Capital who drives or investment effort in AI in Frontier Tech
I would make her want to invest in lillieshall
Hi Jenny thanks for joining us you let us get event investment in really short could you share a bit more about why
Company
When I first met you almost four years ago this was when he first started
The company formerly called lingojam
At that time the company was busy Hangzhou just do three of them
And you're still trying to encourage one of your co-founder from Google
To come back and join them he's really the
NLP expert
Behind The Voice
I think what's really attractive about them
Is the small door that time was
You know why you was thinking about revamping or disrupting the whole Edge
Sector by combining gamification
Elements
Tilly's product as well as leveraging
You know
Really deep voice engine
The ultimate
The process and you know that's why I'm removing the ReliaCard
A Reliance on
Having extra teeth
Peaches
Keisha English
The mobile phone is excellent platform for the interaction
And when I first took a look at the product
You know I was I was pretty impressed and I used to look at
Gaming Investments as well and I think
That that combination of making learning language fun
Kilkenny fication using the mobile phone is Toledo
So that was a long long time ago 4 years ago
That when I was talking about AI
Today at ring in after the last
All years of Hot Wheel
The team has really feel great
Product demo sabila big
Great.
Negotiating from no globally
Can you ask for
China
In NLP
So very excited
James Dean Butler team itself
Backtrack of you
I know you like the product goes up what about the team himself
Yeah this team is a very interesting
All he saw the co-founder abandon who you both have elements of
I'm global
You know education their pet
Experience working overseas
But being Chinese the understand
You know the pin point
That Chinese have
When you're learning a new
Nn
And so the right complementary background Windows 10
Technology
Product sense
Speciation
For the sudden eat and pinpointed English
It is a very aggressive
Yes you know
Learning CEO
You never cease to amaze me
Universal we will really see the best friend
Investment
And
You can tell that you know why you believe
He's one that
Has his own views by the same time in areas where he's not
Show all he doesn't mix
Experiencing
100 ICP
If it has a thousand guys to ask you out from getting input from people
Experiencing himself
He's not going to just say you know take what you give him but that he would
Talk to another hundred guys
And you know but when when he thinks you're right
He will change very fast
So I think the bed is as much
I'm not just on the product on the sector but also
Light Ivory vs
Youngest CEO
What's the biggest
Pain GIFs
Scene in Hempstead
The investment
Yes oh I think that over the last 4 years definitely has grown
Pectin she was learning how to hire
When to fire
How to incentivize I think over the last four years a definitely is getting a lot more experienced having
Sinemet so many
A people so as a CEO I think
This
This critical right assessing a hiring the right management team my thing is done.
Julie over the four years really matured and so he's assessment and now
Pic of a management team members to join him his
Gotten better and better
I'll most recent hire
Is in our view a super CFO
Always part of the GTA V ghost
System that he managed to convince her
To come out retirement to join him
Together you know in this in this group
Going forward so I think that's one
Learning
Managing
Finding the right tile
And then the second part that is really matured
Really focusing saying no
In this new category with Education Plus AI
Target the kids you
Target key to 12
You can also change the product from learning English to learning Chinese
You can learn Japanese in Korean
Self-deception
Very flexible
But knowing when to do what I think
Important
And so he has
Oso buddy Years love to say no
The Cara project
To leave them for later
To develop and and really focus on
What's call
On which right now is the China market for English learning for adults
We may go up and down each group
But I think that China by itself
Extremely picky
So we should take out
You know we do have all the building blocks in the back end
Technology
260 engine to mod
Multiple languages
Even when they decide to
I think on that front
It so it's never easy for you to say no to things
Billy Merchant
DC the product be able to
Teach other subject matters besides languages down the road
Well I think the way the engine is here for is
Spec sheet for language right now
Oh my thing to go from language to
The teachings of physics and chemistry and math is a little hard
Show up a little bit more far off
But I think if you look at the demographic itself
The business isn't just about Educational Learning a language
It's also evolving into lifetime
Our knowledge and learning education learning learning is much
Betta business
Much longer time in terms of LTE
So I think that you are a big opportunity
What kind of advice have you given
Yeah so you don't always given that we were so early C investor
Dimension you know we help him interview candidates we help him think through
Packages you know fall like how how you should incentivize how you should hire people
When to fire I think the whole ESOP setup boy sexually
Something to help with photosynthesis
Steam
One of the battle at the we help to get here from coming off the road
The other aspects is that you know the company over the four years also had very good
Successful fundraising rounds
Louis Padres when you don't need the capital and he is always
And so in that sense with also help him the thing true financing went
To have financing which of the partnership
Choose from
I believe that we have oh so you don't feel very good complimentary shareholding in basketball
Time for that
Thank you Jenny
Good afternoon
49 Airline flight SQ 798
San Jose International
Thanks for listening
Buddhist episode of 996
By the way
We also produce a weekly email newsletter in English also called 96
Hotels around up of the week's most important happenings
Intec in China
Subscriber some photos for the informative and fun to read
And you said also features original content
Analysis
From Sarah MI
Striped at nine 6
. ggbc
Ggv capital is a multi-stage venture capital firm based in Silicon Valley Shanghai and Beijing
We have been partnering with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past 18 years
Proceed to pre IPO
We 3.8 billion dollars in capital under management real estate funds
GTA V invest in gold we minded entrepreneurs in consumer internet
E-commerce
Frontier tax in Enterprise
GTA V has invested over 280 companies
With 29 IPOs in 22 unicorn companies include
Airbnb Alibaba C trip
Didi chuxing Domo hashicorp
Hello by Adele
House Heat
Slack
Square
Hotel wish
Soundtrue white white and others find out more at ggvc. Com
Podcast or would like to recommend a gas
Bisimoto
I-96 at GGC.
This podcast is co-produced
Bow friend and business partner
Kaiser kuo the host of the wonderful sinica podcast
Hey, China's economic
Political and cultural issue