Vincent wrestler
Airport
Hi there welcome to the nine at six podcast brought to you by
GTB capital and co-produced by the sinica podcast
On the show interview movers and shakers of China's tech industry as well as Tech leaders who have a u
China cross-border perspective and the managing partner at GTV capital
Working at startup investing in them in both the US and China for the past 20 years
My name is Zahra Jones an investment Analyst at ggv Capital and a former journalist
Why is the show called 98696 is the work schedule that many Chinese Founders have organically it
Adopted that is 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
To us996 captures intensity Drive in speed of Chinese internet companies
Many of which are moving faster that even their American counterparts
On the show today we have in dencia and found you
Or singing a new song in Chinese
Article founders of data visor
Assertive here in Silicon Valley that provides big data security analytics for consumer-facing website
Synapse
His customers include some of the largest companies in the world
Such as Alibaba
Camping Pinterest Yelp
Phytosaur toutiao
Among others
Both England and Fang have Decades of experience the Internet Security
Specifically on Friday large-scale attacks to all I services
Such as fraudulent online payments
Spanning user hijacking
Search result poisoning Etc
They're both senior researchers at Microsoft
For many years
Before starting televisor in 2013
NFL overtime
Providence
I first met both of them in 2014
You have come a long way
Humana receive her PhD in computer science from CMU
And a bachelor's degree from
Peking University
Fan holds a PhD in computer science from Berkeley right here
In a box
If I'm up
Welcome to the show
Thank you hun
Dussehra
My pleasure to join thank you
First of all could you give our audience an overview of what datavisor does
In layman terms
And describe how you're helping some of your most important clients
Sure I would be happy to
So did Isaiah is a company that leverages
Adelita Technologies which is AI machine learning in Big Data
To protect
Consumer-facing companies from a variety
Fraudulent abusive and money laundry activities
And That's Amore Pizza on pull off those at tax
Including for example what do we have
Is it that the fake account
That's the witches of the
Reason to kind of very hot topic and they could introduce Pammy like some content
Fake content
Joker be like so fragile listings and scabs
These are the familiar
I'll go song
Operating China
At what worse than all time in China
Western audio
Why are these
So so many fraudulent
Listing
And accounts
What's the purpose
So I'm
As for example like sort of a we everything going online when we have this fear of going to the
Kind of Internet a mobile app like so the Eero
And the opportunity of directly touching a large number of users from app
Perspective
Is significant the in-house
Expanded and that's Channel some also at the same time be quickly noticed by the
Attack person being Channel
That to facilitate all these
Kind of illicit activities we saw
And those incredible example which we talked about
Milestone spammy content and fake listings
+ 4
In this case he's a professional attackers not just for one off
Thanks Lisa actually coordinated organized crime rings that have strong financial incentives
And other
So they're plenty of action waste a cashier monetized
Craigslist
Voice example
I'm the cash set up song fake listing to
Attract normal user so that they can chase
I make money scams it says
Afterwards
Or more often they also set up a business for example they can trick some
Small businesses I can promote your business and you pay me this much and I can
Help you find a lot of
Offense I can help you write reviews and
And then they can also do a lot of other things
Example Day Camp
I tried to hijacking some existing peoples
Accounts
Can put up the fake listing there and answer that
Lmpeople
Click those things they castrate download malware so they can monetize further to other
Channels
So a lot of CR customers are consumer internet
Like Alibaba
Dimming the ones I mentioned
Do you see more of those attacks
In China or in the US and how are your client's knees difference
Different in these two mark
So these attacks we see a comment
Kind of the issue actually crossbows China
I swear
Datavisor
Common challenges
And we talked about that what we talked
Talk about these fake
What is one example
Protect
It is a broader category of
Attack
For example you need cream for
Atlanta
Conduction
Which is
Maybe more, Sam Elliott
The credit car likes
The twin the day that got leaked
And someone else obtain this information that's hackers
Then they just use this
Credit card
To issue a payment transaction
I know without owner
Actually
Convert injection
Which result
The
Typically what we call the chargeback
Attacks it to emergency
Depends
And also other type of
Ataxic as fraudulent in stores
Fraudulent marketing words
Anno domini apps
Natural looking
To expand their user base
Fifo example
Crying like users
Different Channel such as what
Facebook a Google intern many other channels
Where they could apply uses as well
And in such kind of different kind of channels
Sometimes they're also add Network dress up channels in subnetwork
And there could be
Places
Weather for Campo
Lighting stores
Purchase actually fraudulent meaning
They never existed
These are not real user in stores
And the Beast another example
Off the fraudulent activity that we see very common
The other type of use cases we also talked about
Doctor is more like we do FMLA today of identity theft
I want sensitive information
Credit card information
And I
Social Security
Social Security numbers or credit card information address information
Thomas identity can potentially be abused
By someone else that we don't know about the use this information
Apply for new credit card
And also for example to
Open new bank account
Without actually
The
The real user actually knowing about the existence
And that when they have these like a new credit card new accounts
Then they cut
Further performance examples
Are transactions other type of illicit activity we talked about
And now I'm so
These are different forms
Off the attacks that we
Saw that actually post
Like a China I could consumer-facing
Applications online service as well as those in the US
Face comment
And that obviously is for titan smite
Different cycling to Regions
But
It is a common challenge
This is
Something that happened
When oldies online services
Actually
Quickly increasing in a we all act
Removing
If I'm offline in Europe
To the online
And it just makes
Bees attack
Idiot
And these are the problems that they'd of Isaiah is
Address
How did you two first meet each other
Yeah we met each other at the Microsoft
Research when we first
Join Microsoft we agree to have to join the same Mouse
Microsoft
Watch Silicon Valley love
And then we seem collaborative
Think with each other ever since year was that
It was
Okay so it's been 12 years
Microsoft for almost
10 years
Did you guys work on projects together while you were there
Yes
We closely Clarity with each other as you since the very beginning
Many of the projects in the security like a broad security area
So was it a difficult decision to leave Microsoft
When did you know it was the right time to make
I can talk about it so it's actually
So I want to say
From that time I saw the one we to like says make a decision that Wheatley to a kind of
I know in the Silicon Valley law people thinking of startup
A lot of the times
Oh God you actually didn't occur to us
For very long time but
When the idea occurred to us
It actually is relatively
Quick and easy for us to decide that Samsung
Yes we are very interesting doing that is something exciting and we wanted to go out go about
So I would say it's a, decision Prospect
David wasn't really hard
So I remember Harry Shum from Microsoft was the one who
Connected us
You got a ride already left
Microsoft
Stop doing this
How do you guys know Harry and
How did you get him
I believe in you
Yeah yeah so hurry actually he's
I came from CMU in both my
Husband and I
And how is legendary one right and that is the kind of alarm 9
Very senior alumni role model
Coming from CMU what you socially the
De facto CTO iMac
Microsoft Word
He I think he's hungry are the CTO of AI
He has the role model
Before I saw likes
CMU graduate
Angus area of AI machine learning excetera
And
So hurry and ask God to know each other like so that actually
Microsoft time when
My husband I actually graduated
Lhasa from CMU
He was trying to actually recruit us
2 after Microsoft the Asia
That was kind of the route of the daughters of the early days.
That's right
So
So from that perspective like so from that time
He's being like a a mentor to us and roll mod on plus like a mentor
To ask
So I'm
When we two actually kind of a laptop Microsoft
Actually we we actually
When should I saw Tahari
Talk about this
No idea what we wanted
Do and he gave us a lot of encouragement and how bad that I actually
Brainstorming this and talk about this
We've been kept in touch from time to time overtime and
Got a lot of advice from him
How did you guess
Besides that this
Problem
Yes we have the actual working this area for a long time ever
Testing soil pH
PST time
I was working on network
Intrusion detection
And the email West
Honda
The forensic analysis so we're always in that I can.
Security Outfield
Andy Microsoft where I live it higher because we don't do network-level and stuff a lot in my
Microsoft Microsoft we work with so many product groups all the way up
Research we work with
Christine we will quit
Hotmail
Forefront and the air like a sky face extra so we work with many internal team
A Microsoft we develop a lot
System to help design tunnel
Fights virus type of attack dogs
And in the techniques with the dead that was
More like very focused
So when you have one problem
I have at one specific solution for a problem we have another brand new solution for
After 7 years we feel huh
Everything I do
Surface very different but the other Bluetooth connected
Instead of actually chasing them off to the other whether you located at what their behavior change them
It's already late
Tomorrow maybe I can convince
So I'm there all connected underground that's why we feel
We want to leave Microsoft computer generic solution
Melania project
Not chasing after what the heck things happened when we talk to different people
And then we also see that opportunity because most people even today
What their solution is there actually after the fact that she attacked they feuding rules
Is she attacking they have labels that Cheney models are always very active
We want to be a we want to do something proactively
Carlton looking at things automatically
Discover new patent
That's the idea we feel we actually have idea how to ask if you that
That's why we
We shall we want to be Microsoft to give a try
Got it
What's the easy
Warhawk difficult was it to do your own salad
Having been the comfort
Microsoft
Gazelle
It's not easy even though there's an idea and makes sense this
Officially a part of Market fit
Just take that first jump Lee Buffet to leave a comfort job coaches
Khushi believe I wear comfortable successful career
In a Safe Company to come out and do this
It's not easy decision so
What was it like after you make.
So I think of the decision perspective
We were talking about that is
Actually seems that
Ratatouille easy decision for the journey was not enough
Play ever want to go by your journey as it can be to
Talk about why the decision seems easy is I think after
Kind of be in this area long time post office
Passion
We want to do something big
Black and
You see all the all the unicorns that you don't
Morton the research
Word Microsoft research at a time
Kind of focusing out and vomiting
The state of all that's what we two
Actually are doing
And we very good at it. At the same time
We see this gap between research and Industry and the True Value
Proposition severitus
And I'm So at the same time it's very difficult to get
Ross
Particularly in the security likes out of area
So we too are very excited about
Coming from research to say can we bring this
Kind of a new ideas and latest technology whatever would come up
Quickly to production
And that's something brand new in sounds really exciting and we think
Also the time in that time works very well because the mega timing
Is everything moving online
And I made attack a lot easier and everybody's a needle such solution the four
The other we can come machine learning AI Solutions with big data
Is a technologist being involved
The state where it's more mature
The product Isaiah to Anna bring to the market
So we were very excited about that possibility
Leaving the comfort zone
Definitely
A Samsung
A lot of people was a question but I think that in this case we to have some advantage of being ladies because
You feel maybe the family burden a lot more
The family
Kind of meals we probably both very thankful to Allah
Aspen at that time
They both stopped working
Mercer
Facebook my Microsoft I'm not leaving
Bring up the idea and
We always have this joke I went to my husband and told him about this and say
Well why don't you like some other cheat
Me as a housewife except I don't do housewife
What you would know houses
I guess that also is that is another factor to some extent
Shield
Kind of Tourism advantage in to stay with the family support and being kind of ladies we feel
Not like that is kind of
That
Possible
Tell me what you see conversation
Supportive young children when you started a company right
Barrie Ontario
Yeah.
Children
Oh I have nannies so that they actually gave me a lot of help
The Palm Neon
I am still still open
Husband
My parents and in-laws
Nanny's especially nearby to
Is my mom here
Nearby I know yes
I think we got the the whole family
Support
Actually want to
My parents
Gave me tremendous
They stayed with us
Support
And also
That's why we
Very thankful for
Family
I think of anybody
Hoodoo star double weather
Kind of love
Ladies will guys that you need have any
Support use your schedule
Very long
Always at work
So you need someone
Saudi decision was easy and a support was there
What's the journey like
After you start a startup
How difficult is it to get stuff off the ground
Hire people and then
Try to convince people join you this database didn't have any brand at all
You you two hadn't had any success
So how easy was I want to go watch
Set to get their project
APA running head
So I will also didn't talk about the name Justine
Elsia and the one we to actually looking at this Riley said decision was easy
And nausea also pops because
We didn't read it now
Play essay like before we make the decisions actually
To get likes
Calling
Sartre like
Talking about this and the day working as good advice to say
Here are the first important for nausea should talk to to really learn
Are you ready
Is there something you want to do to make sure and that before you jump into this and said oh it's is not what we want
So with that we did we actually talked to a few
Folks have been doing startups
And say what does it take
To do a startup
I think after that we came back and
So we will ask what do you feel
When we too had that consist now so
We don't think we have ready
I think I want to do it there is always
Somewhere
To get started
And now we have to start somewhere
Animate the first step is to quit a job
Stop the beauty where can I buy
So it said like this other
Truly like draw lost things we not ready for
And the alarms things to feel on all the way
But that we decided to do it and then that's that's where we get started
I won't say the journey is is
Definitely
Hot lava hotter
Then I would say when we started
Initially pass because he initially we don't have any expectation what's it's going to look like to play with no expect
Patient and but it was actually not easy you talked about so example recruiting right
And
My husband's working like saw the Microsoft to and then bleeding a lot
Team as well
And everybody's complaining recordings very hot and competitive
How old is Val Like Son of the heart
When your install.
That's one thing
Where your equal one Microsoft recruiting on at 41st Street
So how did you guys get the initial hires
Good people
The first two or three High
Text join YouTube leaving you
Yeah I think that the first few
People actually that someone that way
We know I never found
The previous.
And then
We are we grab those
You have to stop at
And then I'm moving on
As many
Actually start to have
The referrals
She going on that way
Including and
Stop
Program
Weihai internal recruiters
She says you're so then
Actually get the ball rolling
Extjs call the company
Strong discipline and initially
That does mean we grow actually
Slower
But one thing we did what I told all about
Recruiting
And that I think it was overtime is paid off because
We do kind of said a stronger team when you have a face
It actually made the further down recruiting site at UCF
Temperature
How many people do you have
We have already I think I over 80 people
Today and quickly
Obsessed
So both of you grab in China went to college there and then came to the US for grad school
So you still have a very strong connection there
Current customers are based in China so have you thought about starting this company in China and why did you choose to start a
Natural ant
Started yet because
We actually work
Microsoft Live all I'm home
And also it's Silicon Valley rights
The place of innovation so we actually
Didn't think off of Akshay at starting
China
Until that the reactor
They have a good customer base and react
I just thought of China branch
Particular we working the Technology field rice Silicon Valley is this field
For both star math must fear and
Zhuhai technology
So it didn't occur to us
We have a startup
Find different places
Stop door datavisor when we started
The idea is it
The technology
Tostada
Did you send out
Do you have engineers in China
Crudos engineers
US company in a cell
Sea turtle
I would say actually initially we thought we have the silica Maddie angle and it must be someone
Attractive but actually
Successful companies already in China so far
I think they grow really fast as well
It's also
Very difficult to recruiting there
In a consumer company
Is that Enterprise
So, sometimes go even faster
So be attractive store Enterprise company
Dashiell especially comparison
So makes it even harder so how did you overcome that
Did you go through
The Microsoft connection
To be more people that. Know you
Devil believe
To try and join you how did you get
What was your hook
Because the first few engineers in China
First of all we had one of our early founding members and now who actually let the
He went to China relocated that's actually fake a step and if someone
Being there
And living
People relocate
He wasn't
Us actually for a few years but a few years already
Yeah probably
And not going to China so that
Pic first app
And we do actually locally get help
Perform
I would invest us
There are two helpless that I had
These are actually
Early Anchor Point
Some of the clients some of them
And that's why I remind myself you
Yeah
And I told the later stage when we want to also
Have the product development in China
We also had
He likes other very capable team members when they
Us
Who wanted to relocate back to
Actually. I actually help with the team tremendously
Stay here for too long
There were similar kind of work to here
Well sometimes yes and then decided not too long
And also to my son we find that opportunity
Attractive to them as well
So who was your first customer in
What was the process like
Attracting women on boarding
Customer
We will actually just
Closing the the first founding Ron and then we met and mimosa
Saunders I should buy asking so I know if I like a friend
Who actually on
Helped them to around Google and they actually introduced
Because they did talk to them asked what's your biggest problem and they had to spend problem
So we said all that I want all file friends actually having a start-up at that time so we we talk to them
At the I wish I still remember that was actually at a Starbucks
Sidemen clothing
Stanford at the night and then we
So talking about all that the product refuting and the initial put the times that we have and and then
I actually got pretty
Excited about our solution
At that time small cheap
I think we have to help them
Softer Spanish
Then we actually go back to do a
POC with them and then
POC results was very good
Quickly move on board
So that was actually the first class was actually very lucky we happened
Meet him actually
It is
Is memorial paying client to
Doesn't receive almost Market cabin back then
Is a few billion dollars
Like Yelp
Do you think you'll be that easy
To get into Yelp
To give people more contacts mama is sort of like the tender of China social networking app
Mostly anonymous
Social networking for people to me
People
Maybe outside of basketball
Comparable to Snapchat
So can you imagine
Meeting Snapchat anybody seniors
Snapchat
Having a few our conversation
Did they give you the steel
Who is the west of the POC so it's not giving us it's just giving us opportunity
This lucky part is also
Something reflecting today's word the particular for China
That grow really fast
Three and half years
So they grow phenomena such a fastest speed in their team is also
Relativity, as well as a young team going up quickly
Expand province
Off.
Kale it becomes
A key issue that they have to solve for them to go to the next step
I think that's a reflection just to say there are many companies in China
A face similar challenges
That's really fast gross
In relativity
Kind of younger and experienced team of handling
A really large scale issues that is very detrimental to post user experience in business growth
Anywhere I want
Teas could help
So I would say we were lucky to get that boom by the first time
But that's also like strengthen
Sum of all belief of going to China
As I walk the major markets as well because y'all many more companies like
Benefit from
From our expense investing
So many consumers
Did the market is so big
And the
Growth is so fast
Not they know they're having issues
Salt
And
Like you said not as many of them
Scale
Therefore they very open-minded
Anything
Bicknell makes sense
Salisbury Marathon
Instead of a lot of hurdles and
Who you know
Have you had it all the references
Have you are you at
Complying to this regulation derivation
This much
Fuel hurdles
Enterprise company
Penetrate the Chinese market
Can trust you in soap
Throw a little bit more like I'll be able to risk attacking and embracing new technology
How to try out new things
And I think that's also that kind of spirit to help them
Medic Rolex
The part of the growing fast I think.
When they were all kinds they have not gone IPO yet afterwards
On the spam problem
Not such like sort of an issue that they have to
Become greedy headache about
I think.
Then be able to focus on their Core Business
Start inviting you to come to
Sparkasse
Also.
We wanted a lot of sass companies
Security service
Roofing companies in
Us to know that
Telemachus Ashley
Gray Market
But you don't have anybody on
Your team.
From China
It help you to penetrate.
At 8
You think that is very difficult
Tacoma takes a long time
But for those
Yahoo. Both China and us
Matthew Thomas
Even better mark
The Kraken
I think of China definitely sees very promising large Market
Price of a monkey sizes
So many opportunities
A lot of life
Internet services
In a traditional companies and moving
To online
3 day fast
And that was another thing I mentioned in notice
Is really their willingness
To adopt new technology and new solutions
To help them grow faster
Doctor general lights
Sentimental
Mus is all of us
The cut cost
In China is helping to make more money and grow faster
Very different motivation
And people usually move faster when can help
So today how many percent of your clients are in China versus
Does the US
I think we have about
So
When we enter into China
Omaha flights
Jacqueline
I'm here and today we definitely see you like
Maki grow fast
The number of customized statue
Growing at the fastest
US map
5 scale bigger
And that's
Who sing with other
Company that selling both
Into us and China
Comparison
Chinese market Chinese
Klein's archery
More open mobile
Try new things
Grow faster pace
Alipay USA
South Africa
SAS company
Who don't have a telemarketer
Benchmark
So you guys have a very bicultural.
Team like a lot of team members
Have Chinese background have an office in Beijing
Is it
Difficult to run a bicultural team like both
In both countries at the same time
Do you think that's a long-term competitive
I think the song probably want to comment on the
Lingala culture particles
Heard from the technology perspective
The customer
You'll wish that they today issues like a everyday
I think that there's definitely
Culture differ
Patina Chinese
Customer
Hazmat
Chinese
Customers usually move out of crib
And I'm there
Quickly prepare theme
Quickly as well
The same time they ask
She have a lot more requests
NWS
I said they want
More requests
I'm supporting boss
USA
China is that
So we have actually us
Support team and also
Even you can have all developed
The support you actually need to have
Pueblo CO
Face to face time with a customized
Number one
Important city in China
So we do actually work with
The China
Remote
The looming Tower
What causes thatch
But in the meanwhile I think of Technology
Very good
Accor
With a custom always always
Noah members
China Inn
I should also come
Very easy day
To all the
Of course
People standing
To go
Kristin Fontana
The time Factor
I think the remote
Collaboration
Casspi actually work
I will say reasonable
Play well
So you have a lot of calls
A night here
7 body type
And morning with newt
It's ammonia noon timing
Just about time you get up in the morning China
Certificate
Sometimes we talk
Morning time as well but it's only four
But that usually Sawa like
I'm sum of all
That company meetings will be
The late of
Accommodated
Go to McDowell
Encourage likes
Location of crossbows teams
So we will have
Coming to visit
USS Titan
To come over
And then we also
Members from
I'm here going to China
Do Charles to work with them together
So I am now
The China teams
Probably about 30 people today by
How quickly growing
To actually more than double their now
It's really
How many people do you have
Here by comparison
What do we have is about the 50 people
Sakuku have more in China
Yuan to
Probably 50-50
And are more people almost people in China in Beijing or
Are we first open the Beijing off
Staffing 2000
And now we have
Quite some time
So that's why we
Show houses lately
That's why
Chloe
I'm looking for support
It support
For sale shenzhen
We are hiring a few
We feel also from
Like some of the
Is back to write
And giving the child not culture we want
I want to be with the customer listen to them that helps was this I'm off to the developer
As well we also have R&D team
Locating post
And the reason is a that they were able to
Bead directory
Like get to know the business values
My voice and the
So be able to
Perform
At the support
And then the other
I think it also makes it recruiting slightly easier because the
As we talked about the recruiting in China
Is also difficult as well cuz he couldn't Beijing and 9th
Think I had a
Presence
Different locations also enable us
The best pasta
Sure
So how does your approach to fraud detection and prevention differ from the traditional
What will differentiate your technology
I think I'll main differentiation
We are called
Supervisor
Which
As I mentioned before that most of a solution
Concurrently
Small react
You see something bad you rather rules are you
You see something values.
Machine learning
Solutions that should work well
When the things asked
Staples
The mission all I can image recognition Mozart
People ashy
What people look like don't change
Weather in fraud scenario
That actually changes very quickly
Waupaca evolve sometime overnight over a few hours that could change
If you're always like a writing rules to start even I can machine learning Solutions
2 start training
It's actually very
Slow and always react
That's why we did not put something brand-new we called it an unsupervised machine learning solution that a table
Tudi taxing
Bad things on the Fly and look at the things that you real time
Protecting you from a patent
That's what differentiates us from all the other Solutions
And it seems we actually
Just thought it was a social off you
We actually few 2
Skill
So we had we can actually process succulents off of your van so very quickly in our
Distributor engine
And that's also the main differentiation
Competitors
Do you hope to expand into new areas going forward
Yeah so I'm currently we started with the socials
So that's where we actually
Different land Memorial
Social network
Can we see a lava axe
She abdomens we're still going pretty strong
Sector
I know we move into the gaming sack
Picture of in the middle
Because a lot of people actually
Have a huge Mark Hedges $1000000 to mocking.
To buy new users in gaming
And many of those sacks you're faking stall speed
They are only limited source of a good insult. They are such
Channels
So the gaming company Ortega on the whoever we need to buy New Uses and upper having a party
Wasted their marketing dollar so
We help with them trash you've added all the advice and help
Get three phones for those and avoid those are bad
Install
That's a second Market that we asked
Doing pretty strong
And we also are doing a moving to the financial markets
I know we are free
Temple wework
With some of the largest
Clyde Jackson money transfers
Banks is that true
Because there are a lot of issues in a financial institution as well for example
In us it's a lot of things
Extra credit face
But it was credit bureaus information leak
Anybody cash
To pretend to be me to apply a credit card online
And he can get the credit card and starting
A lot of
Coordinated attack
We also see a lot of
Synergies between.
Different sectors
Because many of the attackers will playground in the social
Oh I have a success
Here and I can launch lives
Attack
What about tomorrow I start attacking financial industry that actually give me much higher
Higher all ice
A nostalgic place so that's what we
We actually shifting there as well talk to you how
Jack manual
Finesse remix
2 Chainz
Different type of
Do you actually see overtime C
Cheese similar
Players Saints
That's very similar patterns and it sometimes
They're always think of attack is always evolving they actually very Advanced and they change very quickly
But the way that we
Traditionally people think
Financial institutions
It's actually have different attack
Havana Social sector
Damn is that she eats
Tempeh bacon
Even not even a penny right now
But financial institution you get a one card that you actually able to have a lava
Like a revenue-generating
But in English in now
That these actually cast actually
Because they can't use a launch large-scale attack they was just try to
To see whatever they
So far I know you seen a lot of
Interesting fraud cases can you tell me an anecdote
Yeso
It's Rudy
See some of the fraud patterns nowadays
It actually
So one of the cases
Police officer
Lost
A big heo attack
Cancel account takeover
Account takeover
Usually before recession much smaller
Skip this attack
12 minutes of accounts
Compromise
And the pot is actually making the very different font
Traditional
It's Quickly evolve
It's actually change super fast
And if you took a tummy ATO attack they was just what credential stuffing and I try to login and then
And they do some similar things
But for this particular hu attack
Dashie
So that you love each iot device all over the world
Switch IP address
Have only very very little
Activities and each one coming from varidesk
Distributed the world
And then logging to this
Accounts
Their attack patterns very quickly change
The first time they actually logging Dash
Pretend to be not good
Yashow very Quest
If they login to stop twitching bad things immediately
And in the bathroom seat Dewey media 2K
You can write a rule that
You logging you made it to a lot of bad things
This is actually the second
That type of behavior
Captured
And then they change it to Vera
Delsey weight limit themselves
Very quickly
And and they are they do only one thing at a time and then another thing at a time and they have a very long as randomization
And this change is only a night
A few days today I changed
And then when they see this thing that she doesn't go well they switched quickly switch to another patch
Which is the only login it don't do much things at all
And they run them so you can see the the whole like a week off
What time when they actually conducting this attack first to use very sophisticated message over
Iot devices
They pretend to be iPhone which is the most
Most popular devices there
And then they did quickly change patent
And this
Attack pattern changes
Is something that we
See very popular
Amount all the attacks
These days
And for some of the client
Received that they actually attack
Section very patient initially they were actually created many different
Like
Master
Distilled account
2 attack
And then when they see that
It's not very
Thomas Ian
Solutions architect
Then they will say I register call that a dude. Don't do anything
And I I just wait
Well I like I feel like a monster
And I don't do anything that I starts with X
By that time most of the Ruby
Justin watching this is older, this is actually a good account
The Nostalgia attack
And then at some point today also see
If I actually become
Very socially well connected to my profile looks good
Then it actually might the chance of miso
Accessing
They're sold that in that case
They could slip you the connections among that go to users among themselves
And look at it very good profile pictures and I have a long letter and things about themselves
And it attacked that way
And even though this at all the solutions actually able to
Capturing
Then they were actually moved to Old heo attacks and and compromise the old user account
The conductive
Activity there
So the
The things that we are trained to react
Seeing that
A lot of ass
Changes
The different behaviors
If you're the solution is always like
You see that behavior and you have something deploy
They are always
Chasing after what day
Conducted
Always react
That's why I think we have a lot of
Access into checking this
Bayer Advanced
And the distributed attack
Using all the time
So
Has mentioned it was actually easier for you because you were a woman like starting a business
At times where you thought it was harder because you were a woman
And have you
Encounters
Instances where people were treating you differently
I could definitely lighter as woman like
AccuWeather app
Silicon Valley where do exams
No particularly
Rainberry technical field
See different views in different
Perspective
Is coming up
And that
That's
Perhaps I think it said it said it a normal thing
Phenomenal
Weather today
And that's just reality
These different views perspectives
And I would talk about OverWatch I think we to probably see you kind of lucky because
On my way
And
Owl
Masters in France
How old is super supportive
Despite the fact that the two of us by two co-founders that I've always liked so the female co-founders
Anna nobody actually
Serious questions because of that
Particular combination factor to question
Weather is going to be successful not week are tremendous
Support along from the people around us
But definitely draw occasions
I would to talk about that maybe a couple of examples where it would be did to feel like sense
A different example of a common theme was B
We going to maybe parties
Posted
Somewhere those are kind of
The
Sometimes in life
People to call
When do a lot of attendees
Likes of a guys and being female
End of the people you don't know about
Yeah sometimes it's difficult to start a conversation because the tenderness is
The guys like to talk to guys today
Dot. Sometimes we sell laxatives
And
Where
Joe likes of the week we'd love to see more like Southern
Gmail
Turn off being there
Back machine there like you there's a community
Ana support
And I also I think it before
Going to be laughing my ass off every Mission we talked to
People likes out of
But introduction of fans Etc
About at the start of Journey and
So we've talked to folks on pole light
Example like Southern gaster
Just just as a casual conversation
And the idea media restarting
Oh seems to Charming ladies want to have asada
Facebook.com
The conscious bring to us
Is there's a question is that going to be stuck until Friday right are they serious about it
But both of you also have very strong technical records
Careers before you did this so
I guess
When people see that they're like okay they're serious
So I would say
Such thing exists but I think of most part
The place to
Does the people surrounding us
Xcetera
Fairies
So what advice do you have for other female founders
Quanta services
So I encourage like
Female
Female likes turn off
If you have
Dreams
To golf
Assuage
And that
So for the two of us
Even though I sell the Wii word to FEMA
So we went ahead and did
And I really am
Encourage others
To do the same and
So
After all I think
I really think
It should not be relevant to the gender from the perspective by
When we two are lucky anthem
This
We are knocking
Considering
Because we're having a
Technology startup
And
Because we're two
Female cofounders
We shouldn't do it never occurred to us
But I also encourage others
To hold the same view
To actually move
Forwarding
Doing it
I also likes other
Wheat or lucky like
Ricardo Lawson
Support
And I would also hope likes of the
I think I Community also give more support
Two other
Like female
Kind of
Potential cofounders like us
Dad to give them enough support
So that they could move forward
And the disappointing
Sometimes comes from family Tramadol family
Import
You wouldn't be able to do it
And was friends supporting his investors
Support Jewish
Needs to be a lot of snow
Support
For this to happen
I read
Before I talk
Around the time maybe
We too are thinking about startup
I rather Sheryl Sandberg spark healthy.
A lot of
Courage I get home
Samurai
So
As you this kind of
Stromedy
Experience like Mentor Oman on the role model
Yeah I know that could also in French
Address
Do you think China or in the US
Deers
China auctions
Feels less about this gender actually yeah
Actually
China Tucson
Because I asked
The same question
People ask the same questions
And the maybe this is incorrect
Reception and I feel like
China
Gender likes other
Bias
Seems the last
The problem that pee
Alot definition
You see people talk about it less
Yummy exist
Talk about it
Some statistics shows in China women leaders actually
The percentages
Greater
Yeah I've seen the same
I think that's really a few yeah yeah
But I don't remember the details
I've read some stuff maybe when we actually
I'm going up
More point
Kingsoft
But here I think we have
Allowed
LC9 engine
Wayne Thompson
Bahari
Do not consider
And we have actually a lot of a gray tiger
Female engineer
Small company actually our gender balance
Dairy Queen
I will say hi
But I dislike
Just very good by Silicon Valley
Solo
We are now in the final section
Apple podcast
Quickfire
Give us the first answer
Tell us an entrepreneur you admire the most
Could be the US from China
So I don't many entrepreneurs actually add my does so many great entrepreneurs
Cats that the landscaper I would say
Dairy Queen admira hero mask
And that he's not just one entrepreneur is Syria on
Turn off many different companies in the my most
Is the wild idea he has
And the reading to pursue them really 2 challenges
The boundary of Technology
Enough for the US to become from technology to that is really inspiring
It's actually very interesting to see email I actually have the same picture
Together
I'm very big and also the tension
The details
Joshua
3DX
She something that we read
I want to
Follow
Is there something you read recently that you recommend
Guy redboxrecorders think fast
Something slow
And I like that book
Guys talking about how human brain
World's End
Where you develop
Fire
Play cautious
Lights
Decision
And
And then quite a bit of even a thing
Think of some of the concept of applying today like a
Kind of
Business ronning pot
About voicemail
The concept of marketing
And I can reflect
To those blocks
2 +
Really recommend
And UPS so I rather not so
When you book
That's actually
Athenia Mason
Just thought of his the hard journey but I see other people
Alarm
Gizmos used for after
Already encountered some of the things you talk
Things he talked about
I know like when I read it I know that I will make the same mistakes
Cuz I just haven't done it yet
What do you do for fun
Country we don't have a lot of time to me I have time I like to travel with my family
Extended time
I like them know
I always enjoy reading 5 time quiet time I can
The dog that Interruption like a Wells maybe some tea and excetera
And that's luxury
Usually eat with wings
Bookstore Chinese books
I revolver
What I will be in
So for trying Chinese books actually
I love to read that
What we talked about is the
The Source MacBook
I don't know if you're not like that
So I think you know
Maven to test if there's a new
China's new type of volcano
Particular recently
Doll like a set of several new ones
About a girl.
Talking about
And so I left those because
They are there is a again it's
School of imagination
One can do and really to
You the best
Stopwatch
And
I like a lot of it also the characters
There are two of different words like how you essentially is imported the reality into a different word
And
Then you suddenly
Some of the things you learn from that word
And you can take
To apply the reality in thinking of
Different away and I interpret that as another book we read read before
A Game of Thrones
What's the popular show there I think the complications there
Sartre
So
The part that.
Enjoy
Do you have time to watch any
Video
Netflix
Amazon
Not a lot but it's surprising all the video I watched
With my kids all the kids movies
Kissing movies
How are you
Try to like Southern find a time to do a little bit of exercise and at the same time
Like maybe watch some
And that
But what I watch
Shan
Very widely
Something more serious documentaries
Sasha
Just for fun
Relaxing
Panda
View that time
As a time I'm
Winding down everyday and the from the
Part of the world can you little bit time to wind down to exercise
And then afterwards I feel like I
I think better
Got got to tell you should watch videos
When I watch
My wife
Do you believe that
American one
Like a walking dead or something come out of you
Watching by myself
I like to watch more than
Chinese
Videos
Yeah so whatever is the hottest newest
From
From CCTV or something
The major production
Historical
Irene
Enjoy watch
I've watched the reason when function is really popular
And I also like that movie
Is this fun people watched
Radio
Show some
Thank you so much for being here with us
Thanks for having us
Thank you it was very fun
Good afternoon
Airline flight 798 9.4
Thanks for listening to this episode of 996 by the weight
We also produce a weekly email newsletter in English also called 9 + 6
Hotels around up of the week's most important happenings
Inside in China subscribers formative and fun to read the news that also features
Original content
An analysis from Zara me
Stripe at nine 6. GG bc.com TTV capital is a multi-stage venture capital
Turn based in Silicon Valley
Shanghai and Beijing we have been partnering with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past 18 years from seed
Capri IPO
We 3.8 billion dollars in capital under management real estate funds GTA V invest in gold Lee minded entrepreneur
Nursing consumer internet
E-commerce Frontier tag in Enterprise
GTA V has invested over 280 companies with 29 IPOs in 22 unicorns
Orfila companies include Airbnb Alibaba
C trip
Didi chuxing demo hashicorp hellobike cows keep plaque
Square Hotel wish soundtrue white white and others find out more at 2.
Qvc.com please email us
996tt bc.com this podcast is co-produced Battlefront
Abyss partner hydroco the host of the wonderful Seneca podcast it cover China's economic
Political and cultural issues