Hi everyone we wanted to get to know you are listeners better
So that we can serve you better
Please visit 96.3 cvc.com
Survey
To fill out a very brief questionnaire the survey chosen to appear on the 96 pot
Cast as a guest host and ask her own questions to our gas as well as
Resume on an episode of the show
If you're looking to join a startup
We can also help recommend opportunities to you
Based on your response
I look forward to hearing from you at Nene 6.
Ggbc. Com survey
Also I wanted to tell you that one of my favorite podcasts
Acquired
A show about tech Acquisitions and IPOs
On the show
Host David Rosenthal and Dan Gilbert go behind the scenes of these acids
Every episode is full of great history lessons and insights into some of the most important companies in the world
It's my goal to show during my commute then I highly recommend checking it out
If you're into Tech or business in general
On the latest episode
Acquired covered xiaomi IPO
And hunson I appeared on the show SKS
You can check out the episode by visiting acquired. FM
Or searching acquired in any podcast app
Hi there welcome to the nine at six podcast brought to you by ggv capital on the show
Interview movers and shakers of China's tech industry as well as Tech leaders who have a us China
Cross-border perspective on Stone
I'm a managing partner at GTV Capital it had been working at startup investment in them in both in USA
China for past 20 years
My name is Zahra Jones an investment Analyst at ggv Capital and a former journalist
Why is the show called 9696 is the work schedule than any Chinese Founders have organically
Adopted that is 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
Cool us996 captures intensity drive and speed of Chinese internet companies
Many of which are moving faster than even their American counterparts
On the show today we have Celine Chen founder and CEO of bingobox China's first scalable
24-hour unmanned convenience store
It's a small lightweight box-like shop where you can purchase pretty much everything that you may fly at a 7-Eleven
But unlike traditional convenience stores
No human staff is required inside
Bento box
You must scan a QR code
To register on this website
Did you check out you place the items on the counter
Scan a QR code
And then pay with WeChat pay with hourly pay
Boost Mobile payment
As you head out as soon as her at a door can automatically detect any unpaid items
The door will only unlock
What's all the items
Happy
Is a Pioneer in a phenomenon known as new retail in China
Commonly understood as using technology to transform offline retail
Bingobox was launched the public in August 2016
And now has over 300 boxes in almost 30 cities in China
GTV live bingo boxes series a investment in July 2017
The company raised another $80 in series speed is January
Would you be also participated in
Titling thank you and welcome to the show
Hi hi
About your background
Before you found a bigger box
What motive a YouTube
You decide to solve this particular problem
What do you think
Convenience stores
Have a future in China and how is it different
Publix produce moments like Family Mart
7-Eleven in Seoul
Well before I found it in the boss I was
Looking
Ovary
I was smoking in
Heisman
And I helped my
To solve marketing problems
Send
Help them to
Sell products to
Because you might roll
I organized
Channel problem
And I'm at a time I know that the trailer was
Very important
How to grind
So I'm earlier in 2013
I think
In the future I will
I hope I can
Develop a new 1004 price that they can deliver their product
Hi Tiff accentuate
Lost ending
And can you search in I stop and go fresh
Is a
E-commerce
Setting
Fruit
Suviche
Popular
Application in China
Yes and then after 1 years effort
We will build up our family Network
South China
I did I stop
Bingo fresh is a online an e-commerce platform selling
Fruits online delivery to customer
Nv200 logistic teams
Top business books
Quite well and erase our appreciate Finance
On August 2015
Apparate financing
Sudan
The business
It's not
Is Pacho
Co-op really fast because we are
Leading
Leading company in China
And then also in the same time I I was thinking about how can I
Lower third
Delivery course
For my own business
Fortnite for the e-commerce business because
At a time delivery cost
Already available
I want to be
Extremely Loud
Make finger fries
Outstanding compete about
Cleaning companies
Vodafone
I want to raise another round of Finance
So
The time I
I know an idea is to put a refrigerator
Inside a community
Put refrigerator
Downstairs of our consumers
I deliver our fruit
In the
That's what refrigerators and they
Go downstairs to pick up the fruit
Get to lower my jewelry cost
Is it inbetween a pilot
Why not why not to sell some
Something that is easy to easy
To stall
Half-life
South Asia Flags brother Andrew
Sell those front live
Coke
Dicen.
Handsome biscuit
To get more
Because
And then
Cost
And when I come up there idealizing
Since I have I want I want to sell things I sell products in depth refrigerator
Why not just Baker
And make a convenience store that
That is the initial idea of bingo balls
And then
Different
Shenzhen Family Mart
7-Eleven
Which are located pretty close
Is anyway
Aldo in China
East community may have 20
52 hours
Tower has me
Maybe
Ace Hardware has Maybe
So
You can find Family Morrow 7-Eleven outside.
Community
What makes
Your salute
More fishing
Because you know
We are more closer
Soda consumed attend 7-Eleven
Penny Mart outside
Also outside
Yes because I was
Downstairs
You don't get to walk out the residential area Community
And then
Nexus smaller
So you can
Put inside
Be a community
That's not the most important thing the key thing is that
You only hand put a machine
Insider community
Do you want to become a machine
Not pay any rent
Yes communities
Yes that's the trick but vidapay our rental
We just pay that One X update
The only real
We have no staff also we have an extremely long
The next hour
Total cost is where it is much lower I mean that is 115 soft
Traditional operational cross outside
Baby heart defects
Baby height
And delivery cost will be cheaper that e-commerce
Deliver by order
To the machines
No you have
Xfinity on the delivery cost as well
Omission
Now come with information that be
What king
Yeah
Looking show
Has the
Societies which help efficient
To make this happen
So
On the next one
Which is you were in advertising
Executive for this wine has a lisp
Model
Showbox has a conology angle
Google something
Amend
How did you
Emma wiggle
How do you find a partner
To work with you
Come up with that
Technological
How to say I have some it back on
Even though I'm not
Yokai but I
I partially agree
I was I am a dick
Because I had you know I
University I
Twitter coding myself
I know most most of the technical
And I know it
How that works
Did I find the solution
It's in my mind for years I know I just baby
Kind of Technologies
Baby mature and icing
I know they disappear book so I chose
Pick up some
Images of baby creative
Guys
In my TV
And I told him
The direction
So then we we just walk it out
I have to say the team is ready in baby
Creative and the Heart
They have Sunday play that way
So if I have a lot of solutions are talk to a lot of
The Dead the Xbox in dinner in this industry
And use our Internet line to come come by all this
To save the first version of bingo balls is only.
Innovation of
Application that level is not I don't think we are
The technical
In the technical point of view is not
Baby baby Hi-Tech
Hi-Tech
Recreate that
MVP minimum viable product
That's because why I can do that
Because I have a
Send a team
We have survived
Press in Python
They track me
And a trustee
Chastise
Directions
The team the team is Remy I have to say
The team is very good
I have to go
What team
So obviously Amazon also has its own version of
The unmanned convenience store caught Amazon go
And they opened a store in Seattle and which open to the public is January
And many people
Refer to bingo box as the Amazon go of China so I was wondering when you started bingobox did you have
Amazon go in mind at all or
How how do you think about this
Like different version of what you're doing
If you notice of the the last time you
You should know that I wear I bring
Do the bingo balls
At 2016 stat
Your dad
The video of amazing goal is Eastwood on December 5th
At that time our first bank about us
Has already operates
I'm a single
When we get better ping
Nothing about actually icing
You my point of view
We are very different
From amazing goal
I mean
From the
From the beginning very beginning
We are aiming to the stove different problem
Flamingo boss we are creating a new channel a more efficient
Hire a fixer
Channel
Create a new at a new shop and you are our environment
Consumers
A new a new way
For YouTube icing
Dubai
Products
Amazon go is
Beehive day fixing to
Tufted chair
Shopping environment
Old traditional
Shopping mall and they are not
Ameristar 3 car rack
Disappear
A cashier free Soul Auto have people
Total merchandising
So
For my understanding Amazon go is true
Is try to solve that problem in that you in the United States
The kashia is very high pay
And the other way to Wild pinpoint that
Easter pic time and lows
Got no time
And then when
They take a lot of rental for 4:44.
Store
At the peak time
The wait for
Play Kidz Bop because I have a lot of
Many choices that I can
I can drive to another store
Appliance stores very very very developed in
Because you lost a lot of choices to
To go to another store
They tried would solve his problem
So that if you can
No line for check how is baby
They take a safe to save a lot of rental
That's so
I think in that way
When is the Kesha free model Pembroke
And also the course
When the cost
Reasonable
Will baby panda sneeze a lot
For the old traditional channels
Different directions
The pockets
How is the target
Who do you target
I know I don't mean to type that
Actually actually we are convenience store and our Target is
All kinds of people
Yeah you have knees
Technical Boss video
New offer
So S7
Person team
On the back end can watch 45 stores at the same time
4 Bingo box
PSV we have a 7 pack steam can can Ben 10
Lower 48
So what
Actually we have
Terrific Services is
Getting higher now
And in the future
I-77 past team can maintain
50 60 70 80 boxes
That's our plan
So could you walk us through it a technology that you used to
Track items in your store
I think it started out with
Radio frequency identification or RFID
Which uses a tad that contains electronically stored information
But later on you also integrated computer vision
How did you make these particular choices and in this particular order how much are you spending on RN
How much resources are expanding rnt
Disorder is not
It's not a choice
Is the accessory
That yes yes because
At beginning we have no
Research
Power
Restart computer vision
Need a lot of money to fall for you
But the research
So
We just stood up we use RFID
Chipper and
And mature technology to build up our a man
Convenience store station
Alliant SSL
Total solution
Product recognition is only the first
Step off the amend kunming install operating
. we need to recognize the product and then we need to
Do the payment and after that
In the back end we have
Maintenance operational system
Twitter POTUS
You can see the results
I7 opposing team
Command j-45
Bingo Bash
I mean that.
The product recognition is
Web the very first app
And then we used to have baby
On highest we can find a life ID
Aztec
Levi ecss
Technology to do that and I know
Ma
The large scale usage iPad is not very
No chip enough because you do need to pay
Harry
Ivy Tech
Attack on
The labor cost
Patek cost so
Is definitely the computer computer vision is the future
So at the same time we use ibid to build hours
Our entire system and
True
Get
Hellas 2
Understanding of the office
Business model
And lay her in the same time we have
Invest a lot of money I am in need of US dollars
True to the research
You have
Naugahyde
We have our team of 100 100 research engineer
To do that, Theresa.
I know a product is called
Self on fire
Use computer vision to to the recognition of the product that will get rid of a body
So our operational calls is
30% lower
That means we are now
Already
For the last K-Love
Replication
What is the accuracy rate
Of your computer vision solution
Technically
Activate Straight
Should be over 99%
Night night night night
Now
Franklin
Now we have no Death Note such off technology that can achieve a 100%
By now
So I mean baby is already very reliable I have to save it
Who is very important
In the payment
Is more important
The time
People don't want to save
1 more minutes
What they want
Security security
The feeling of security
When you
Pace Auto
Products on the go
Cassia oil cassia
99%
The product list
Is correct
The one
Percent unit to unit 2
Move
Move the product and to do the do the adjustment after that
Tattly
Sophie
Correct
Okay
He was not accurate for whatever reason
And
Customer connect
Going to go fix it through moving the item
What happened
What do they do
Can I call someone to help
Yes they can call to help we have I-20
7 by 24
Vishal
Service
Soft 24 by 7
So you can easily put push a button on the cashier on cashier
Then you can see our customer service
FaceTime video call
Conference system
Ambassador
That is a likely will happen when you move the product
That you
Still doesn't
Unlikely happen
Another difficult
Saying about a man coming towards how do you make sure people pay so what is the shrinkage
Straight
For Bingo boss or percentage of goods are stolen
Pay effort
Tractor
Consumers auto detailing
Do you know
Inside bingo balls
No
That's very very
Less people who steal in Siberia boss Because You Love
When walking bingo balls
You are under
Is recorded recorded and we also have
Our our our
All camera is
Empower by our action
Behavior recognition
When you behave
Your behavior is
Samsung tablet
Behavior has happened
That's our car alarm
So the bad guys of his service
So is
TeamViewer
You can immediately see the see What's happenin surviving a boss and then they can take over.
Statistic about how
Heartland Dental
We we don't suggest you lock the door
So they can take over
When they put the pussy bottom in back
They can call me to talk to the bank about
Talk to the person presents in July so you can see I can see the screen
You know
What is is extremely extreme situations
So Extreme Measures we we we don't we don't suggest
Cattle USA but we have disc
We have to equip a of this message
So you know what the descendants ways baby love
You almost two years of operations operations you have
Encounter
3 * all of this
Steals by Kiss
Because they use the app that pair with pair with phone
To open the door.
SMS Pro
Today's date
Most of the apartments View
Will bill pay online of course
You know people still sings that
The interest rate is not
They have no money to buy all these things
Because
Icing to initiate is the
Mygov
Brooke
Flocknote
Attack
So David David David behave yourself you know people walk-in Bingo Ball State
Tenchu
China
Behavior
So you can see inside the cab of a one-week if you don't you don't need to
Dipping versus baby clean
So this is all of your imagination. People tend to sing
Especially in TLC to use for cities
We have all this thing about Cynthia faucet
Invo area
Peabody
They don't
Damaged product
Oh I remember Jason Mata
Take his 5 years old
The boy
Keep pulling down all products
On frog
End
Every time
It will pick up all the Prada
Potato bug
5 to 6
Times and then after
Duke and impaired
February
She's just a baby
Rainier Behavioral
So you guys have a
7 person team
7 + 45 + 1
White.
Ratio
Because now
The display's are we going up you go up because now
Competitive
Because it has a team they have no different function like
You need to have one
Mount Pleasant
In the warehouse to two
How to get for the preparation for each Boss 2 2
So you need you need to
Light White
Prepare sole stick out
To do that
The preparation and 1%
You need to deliver the product
True.
Source
A manager
Manager
Tea menu for
For 4
Area
Light
Run manager
Ofo 100 process soap
DeFranco position
So you also need that back end
Talk about the monitor
That's up to 7
Tickle tickle 45 store
7 + RV can take take care of 80
Okay.
Can you talk about that unit economics of the box like how much does it cost to send a box up how much
How much does it make on a typical day
What's the payback period if you're open to sharing
Actually weed
Average
Income
Petit four boxes different in different cities because the boss
When located in some
High population densities area
So
Ohio
So now in an hour
OS 300 salt at our original
A sarong
Is around 800
Today
We can
We have now
Cartoon salsa
UKC Beijing is
It is higher than
Cos it is higher than two two cities
Turn photos
Beijing
Sanlitun beijing
We can expect now we have everything we have
Payback a VIP back. Will be at 10 months
Okay
And you chose
Residential communities
For the your entry point
Or a lot of bingo boxes are in this gated residential communities
Why did you choose that particular setting
Because you know
In the future I thinking about
When you locate bingo balls
Outside residential area
You can very easy
Location of life
Because the price is
Transparent
Is a market Behavior
It's baby
The price of is
Open to everyone
Inside Westchester area
Now at this moment
We are the only business partners Fiesta west west end so
The only toys
We are pricing
We aren't doing the price
So
You know
That's why I'll rent always solo
Because
Property management team
Do not have
A second choice
Icing
When we enter
Community now
Reluctant
Block this business
We are the only choice inside this area
And son
Original site explosive Sahara
How to prevent household household
Get past password if you sign exclusive
Now we are we tend to
Do not sign
The sign that exclusive because
Is naturally your beauty
Only one
Because of property management
They don't have to initiate to introduce a new competitors
Inside the same area at the same community
Because
Introduce and second one
The owners
The Papa John's owner to not allow because
We are doing the service for them
For the
For the property owners
Just one
24-hour convenience store they don't need
Because we are
Bishop office twister
Vista Property Management
And they when they when they introduce a new one
Talking Tom
Death in the opposite way they need to pay
Heimo korth
Navigate to
Socialism
To supply supplies
So they do not owe that sings
The last last thing is
Our competitors
Debut novel
Fairview North
Compute
Resorts in San Juan
Community School
Wntk
Now China you have
Selenium
The old Ford 400000 communities in China
Guess a lot
This Market is very big is extremely back so I
Industry in the field in the near
325 years
We will not
We will not that the computer you not
It's not baby strong
Are the prices of the goods in bingo balls comparable to those in 7-Eleven
Are they the same or a little
Incompatible
A pricing
A price strategy is
5% lower than the
Tendon normal convenience stores
5%
It's always cheaper
Landmark convenience
Is Tripper
Many of them are even more efficient busy
Yeah obviously speed extreme baoding China
Across-the-board
PO Box already has around what 300 stores
So
How did you
Turn bingo balls in
Into a fast-moving
Company in
What vitamins do
Still
Senior employees
Do you see
Any other copy cats come into the
Space
Yeah and
Do something sooner
Actually I don't think we
Real fasteners
Even though yet
Sweetheart just starting out in this rain
Have a baby
A more
Democracy expand pan
In the factory SVG
React wings
Foundation
We have developed our own
Technology
Centos
I have to say that
Stop the most experience
Americhem list of operators
In the world
We have a lot
Practice
In this industry and now we are ready
Fort Lewis fast
Belfast expand
Adele comes to the copycats I don't care about
I don't worry about any car
That's because from the table because I know
It's definitely you V
You have CopyCats in China makeup
Well
Then you are a good model
Equip business in China
Why what's up
Got a lot of
Cobra cast
And I even I don't
Sing any I don't have any
Half of thought I don't try to stop anyone
Entering this field because
The Beast
The market so big
The back is so bad you know that is 6.8 million
Mom and pop stores
In China
So the body is so is so bad
And I also sing
Because this category is Sonu
And you need
Enough compassion
The painting in this field that to f11
The market
I embraced competitors
And also all the copycats is I know I noticed now
They don't know the size of this business stay out there they just
To just want to
Some of them are
Pocket to make fast money
They just copy
The shape of finger Boston but they don't know
Put an effort
Toyota MR2 do the
Tekken
Goodbye so
Icing competitor is liquid
Is good
For all the order
Participant
What's in this field
Please go to everyone
The top two internet Giants in China Alibaba
Tencent
I'll be regressive
Expand into new regions
All about to do it
By themselves
Cousin you should do it
What is your thought
Working with them or
Competing against
My Philosophy to co-op
Race
Soda
Good Resort
Show me Alibaba and resources
But at this moment I don't
I don't want to sell bingo balls to anybody
That's why I do what
And I will welcome for order
Quick resources
Full cooperation like if testimony
You miss me
You must me I'm open to that interested market price
Houston metal market price but
Just like the one from a 10-7 OtterBox
Some group will listen cuz podcast
You know it's settings open for business
So right now for a bingo box
Shoppers still need to plays everything on a counter
To check out even though it doesn't involve
Human cashiers is still takes a bit of time
Whereas for Amazon go user just take everything and leave
So are you aiming for that day when you can
Realize
That vision and how far are we from there
Okay just about chicken goal
So
Bachelder
Point of view II just been zombie
People don't like icing Icing
Related when we talked about
Making a payment
What is more important
Double liability
Is more important than the
In a tie
In fact loud
Do you speak about casciato to do the payment
It's already very iffy
Do Tesla 10
Seconds
10 seconds
I don't think that's what this
Just disappear
Acceptable to I need to to a consumers
Kmart
10 seconds more than you can get laid
Feeling of security
I think this
What it
Was it for the extra 10 seconds
So
I think that
Bingo balls
Consuming Spirits POS in Singapore
Is
Somehow better than
What technical experience icing is
Mall
More acceptable for the
For the low price
Photo
Like you do
When's Halloween
Can you guys do know
You know it's baby pee
But when you making a big amount payments a live
You need to check the people before you
You do make a payment
Actually I know
Pick N Go
Angle
Maybe in the future sometime
Lupita mainstream
My my my policy is
Where can human eat it
Offer it
Have you seen a consumer demand for that yet
Rocky Mountain
Most of consumer taste
The Hulk
To experience that kind of
Nice beautiful
Wenzhou
Verizon store San Jose
You know
Where are you
Launch this kind of
Ron's Chicken Go
I have to say when the the cause
Is low enough
Is reasonable
Singapore Singapore
By this time by now even Amazon Amazon go
They need to
Did system
The cost million dollars
So intent
Not even can do a bunch of passing accuracy
So icing is not a chip
This technology is not mature enough
Inow
So there's only one store
You have 300
I think I can go
The Chicken Go technology is not released
Now
So I think
Also a huge difference between the China and between China and the US is in China Mobile payment is
As such high penetration rate
So everyone it has WeChat pay were all they pay on their phones
And bingobox leverages on those forms of payment
So you don't need to do a lot of user education
For them to know how to use the bus whereas in the US
There's no like
Mass adopted
Mobile payment methods
So I might take a lot of the more time for users
You actually
Become used to pain with her mobile phones
Actually
Now I have no plans
Tool
Locate pickleball scene
North America
So I
I really don't care about yes but I was just commenting on the fact that
Probably this this idea is probably more Bible in China because of how
Widely-adopted Mobile payment
The sewer
Obviously
That is Mobile in China
Genovia
We are launching a new box in Korea and also in Malaysia
Popular
China
So we we we also provide another another ways of payment
Traditional credit card
What is the party's kind of payment
I have to
I have to say that's not the efficient that are not essential
Barrier
It's not barrier the payment is not the barrier
Because you know
Tested
Denise top consumers
Dismounted
Is the weather
Picture
Chikka for them to use bingo balls because you know
Venti iced Epix
Snow storm outside
Take a lift out there you can buy all the things you need
That's the chicken
Also in the US
I noticed that all the newspaper articles about Amazon go mentioned the loss of cashier jobs
Where at in China
Rarely mentioned in the news
I think people in China generally have a more
Buoyant
Attitude towards AI in new technology
Library on the positive impacts rather than negative ones
So what why do you think that's the case
I Sing Because
Chinese people nowadays
Educated by the
Internet
How many years
We are now in a
Interchanging
Area
Hng Aurora in China
Everyday is different
You know you're nasty
Stay sizing
Cheetah chasing not so fast as yet
Is China that pencil
And also people that
Because they are
How to say
WB develop
Two societies
Set it up
People that
Do you care about that
Escapability
Status quo
They don't
They don't like change
I think it's reasonable
Also there a lot of existence
Existing constituents
Any two
Persuade
For any new
Changes to happen and that takes time
So
You recently launched a new product called Bingo box Mini
Can you tell us more about what that is and how it works
15 products
And I like it very much
It's a very low-cost viso
Riso recognition
Solution for
Traditional convenience store
Now we should be
Regis
Neat 707000 rmb
For each product
4-H Bingo bus Mini
Is pack n play
I put it in the store
And
Keep your first job
SKU what is
After three days
You can
You can start to sell these products toe-tapping boss miniview recognize all your products
So
You can say focaccia
So that's like it looks like an oven right the size is about the size of an oven
And you can basically
Re outfit a traditional mom-and-pop store into a
Saimai bingobox
Yeah so that can be very powerful because that do Mission China has hundreds of thousands of these
Traditional mom and pop stores
Yes so by doing that you extend your impact beyond your own Bingo boxes and into these
More traditional
Existing source
Yes yes
I am expecting so how many of those have you sold how many stores are using
Okay
We just have some
Muffin song
So what's now doing
Cool and then
Define ai or cell phone is your
Initiative
For enhancing the accuracy of the
Computer vision
Recognition of
Your products
In the stores
How is that going
Is not only
Is not only the computer vision communication
Is a total solution
Including the
Computer community service
Epi
I mean the business intelligence
We have Empower Empower it as a
The division aviso capability and in the future
She will be
Communication skills
Like it's a i
Is an AI Sol
In the future
Sapphire
Can talk to you
And she will know you
Better than yourself
Pachet station
Oil
Records
She knows soaps you know your preference
NFL sizing
She would do something
Recommendation
Pollo en
And give you
Exclusive promotion
So I think
Self Rai stock has a baby with
We have a big plans
So is she like Alexa like she can talk to you when you're in the store
Okay
Cool I'm really excited for the future
I jump to the final part of the interview which is around of quick fire questions
The first one is who is an entrepreneur that you admire the most and why
How to say
It's pretty chilly say that I like
Steve Jobs
I hate the most
That because
I think he
Where is Del Rio
He don't care about others judgement and
Insist
The pursuit of perfection I think it's very difficult
Did you know
When you when you run your company.
Can you sister
You love your
The pursuit
So I think you stupid
What motivates you to wake up each morning and what keeps you up at night
A rake's app is
The truth
The gym.
Look at the bay
UKC
Bingo boss everywhere
And we can we can make
Order I have a lot of
Imagination in hat and all this
Imagination 10:2
That made me really excited
This baby happy
So what is your dream what's her vision for
Retail in China how many Bingo boxes is enough for you
My dream is
With that
I die I don't want to set a
Elise
That hundreds of thousands
Something about China
Also in the in the world
Exercising now baby high efficiency
Send hi if you can
Channel
Icing is too
It's good for the society
Yep so
The gym
Vicksburg wakes me up
Good morning
At the job that works.
Everyday
Yes
A lot of meetings and Josh
So what do you do for fun
I like Bots
I like to sing
Alex Boss
Exposed
Especially
American Idiot
Nobu stalker
Pool table
And also I like driving
Driving driving driving
I like I like
The things that
Make me
Excited
That's how I
Music
Off-road driving
That's the way of the
To release my pressure
Okay
Ice expand across China
You have to do you have to deal with the local government
And how does that work
Do you need a permit
Or any kind of
Permission from them
Yeah she definitely we need to do basic almond and now the government job is
The most
One of the most important things of us
So because you know Bingo buses in new is a new saying
Tether China the Dominate don't know how to
Benjamin
So we are we are now working close with the government to have the permit
Kind of beer is now a practice is to science
Fage
Corporation agreement
They will
Officially
Allow us
Cho
Total running is kind of back inside
Community
So
Auto Glass now
Tattoo
Working with the government
East Water standard the standard
Participating in this
Police rules
Local government one by one
Or is
Is it
Special level or at
Central level
Now we just only
Retreat we just can't do it by my work
So now what
15 / 1/2
We heart rate because a permit
I did the permit form
14 cities
Jason China
And then
You had probably
How many ABCs
For as he is
The round.
A lot of pictures
Are the hot dogs
Unlock
PicsArt
Baby casinos
Dismiss
Send
I think that's cabbage
31 he he he made me and he
Lyrics
Set downstairs to heat
Text me in WeChat
He he he he told me that
Long time no see
I haven't seen such an exciting feeling a long time yes
Yes test
What he said to me
You know
Information information from this season
The cottage
Encouragement
Yeah so I think I would give me a lot of
Thank you so much for being here and we look forward to working with bingobox going forward
Okay thank you
Now you are here short interview with Eric Shute managing partner at ggv Capital in the China office
Letter investment in Bingo box
So you have been gdb Sunspot early 2017
Yes and you haven't done a lot of very interesting the new weed combust
Megabox Bonneville
What's the irrational food
Spend time new retail
And what's particularly interest you
About megabox
Yes so
Before I talk about that people pass away so wants to know that paint
So far the traditional
E-commerce market and also the
Pinpoint
Photos of Lionel Richie
So the pain point for the traditional e-commerce
Started
First you have to require a lot of person
Uses for y'all
E-commerce things
And actually cause to search
These days
So normally so maybe
So if I'm 5 years ago so you'll have
To purchase a used to purchase in your cell where is like 10 rmb
Today is such attitude
200-300 events
Mm
Smartphone penetration is gonna band size is not growing as much
Yes so actually I think short there's no try to search a certain traffic.
For today
It was my fault and he just bought we used to to install every application
I wished I was stalked
So you may want to install one or two
Monthly you don't have to install
Another words the consumer has already got used to several application
Already.
The second up employee is that possible Castaways eCommerce
So even though you need to purchase one bottle of water you still get delivered to the company
Get to the home so it will cost you almost the same as the price of the good
So this is two major pain Point weigh station
Toys R Us Mall
Robinson cost
Under a very competitive
Situation in China
So are you have to do this
Price of cost
Okay so true major pain Point ways to traditional retail
At yes. The first one is to
Ship the goods to the retail Point s consolidation
So you have more economy of the skillport ordered
Right you just shipped out the total
Chester take away Tan on himself
So fill for the traditional why is also the same so I like the first one that number one point is that
The rental
Pentecost was usually High very high so as we all knows that if we want to open when
Retail store in China like Shanghai Beijing and a console
So the average daily Break Even Point Es as high as
And the car be the lowest to normally
We will see like a 10000 13,000.
For the break-even point
So where's the new retail
You can
Virtually pay valid
Cost sometimes you up you put some
What are the boxes to into the middle of nowhere and you are charged for free
So the second one for the retail
Traditional retail is dead
At the stocking cost
So structure
Avocado total cost but you still have to pay attention
And you have to
Imply like a suite of five persons and Alyssa true person at the same time
Install service training course training time and also leakage
You don't worry about things
Saudia some catch-up time for the for the new staff and do you have to pay more attention to the Staffing and
If they have potential and stick to the general principle yourself photo
So these are those major Fame points at 240v Commerce and 240 and a tradition
Retail level
The new Ritz hotel at the South Pole
So full for the first one that you don't have to pay
Check why use a speaker the buckets just nearby
When did consumers just walk around they found that doesn't need it they just walking and
Purchase it
Second death note
Because
Just like I said so.
Pay attention and take it away and you may be consumed immediately like a Coca-Cola
Is Dad
Construction communities
There's just no rental costume
Robbie's not right now
Enforces Staffing card
Do you have to
Check data entry
Play like a what's a what's a day or twice a day
The most but you don't have
Hopstop Stop Standing There and
Provider
Immediate service
So there are a lot of companies in the new retail space is being a buzzword in China in the past 2 years
A lot of companies in the unmanned space especially so what
About bingobox stood out to you
Yes of course I'll fall yesterday
So
When we invested early so we considered the founder of the team has the most valuable
We are looking for
So at least I spend a lot of time we still have found it before we met
Make a final decision
Provided he can proof of everything he
Statues to take to your answer final
Finalize
This is very important
The second one is that
They have amateur
Solution
Like I carted mature solution to where we come to the business world will have to provide a service
To be stable
So a lot of guys come to me Erica I can provide a image processing
Image recognition solution to to you at this is
Final
Avulsion of the new retail
We found the accuracy
I mean transform maybe 50 50% to 97 +
You going to waste a ninety-five 97% accurate right
Askew
Estufa
Top-ranked
Being stable wasted no operation in the real world
So
Fit solution actually it's not so advanced
Compared with the image recognition why
But as the first generation
Do you want to go out the business so quickly and wanted the business to be stable
So when we talk about it future astronaut
Doing is he is doing with the second generation which is also waster
Most advanced to image processing
Solutions
So this is a different major difference between
I think a box and the other players
What is your definition of new retail we've talked a lot about this term but I think
Different people have different meanings to it I think it was first proposed by Jack ma few years back
Yes I seen the first first and important
The definition for new Naruto is hot
Be smart
Sew a lot
Parasol investor day inviting some new deals, new retail but they are they
Do not use Smart Camino
So you don't know who I am
What they are buying
Who are the founder of
So
They are not a trend.
The future of the the new retail
Second one yes.
What's the new ritual you have to stop for pain points
Wow wow semi photo traditional semi 40
When you can solve all the pain points
All the problem and the using the small machines model solution and noodle noodle uses
And have a database
444 foot to be used in the future
With the batter
Possible I mean solution business model
So that will be ideal
Make sense
How has the bingobox and sleigh and the team grown since you first met them
Oh yes oh a function level so the team level
But they have changed
Kitchen Magic
So I mean
They have to do a lot of good ass
Not only operation lava but also I like hella Halal HR
And also strategic and
A most important today is ID
The most recent today are recruited the head of the IRA in Intel
Hi in China
Turn down
290 always encouraged
Image processing
Solution
Icicle
So
Chinese New Rochelle
Investments
Take the
Best Heller from IT world
Could not doing enough SmartThings or Internet
But the technology you know how is Ashley there
Does a great marriage of up resources
And opportunity
Right right
So
It this is very important to
And the second one is dodgy business operation so as you guys know they are the first runner in this space
And they have certain dividends not only
For the business but also found
The government so they have developed exclusive
Collaboration with more intensity is government
Hopefully to to run the business
Graduate
And
When we inviting the carpet
The company only up for the five boxes
Electricity and now the company runs more than 300
Cities
Sorry it's over
Temperature City
And possibly they were wrong Spanish into
2000 final this year
Yes fast
Silento. You texted him right after a meeting that Bingo boxes the most exciting deal you've seen
In a long time
So we look forward to seeing the company grow and our partnership
Thank you
Eric that was very informative
Thank you very much
7989 Bank
San Jose
I-96 by the weight we also produces weekly email newsletter in English also called 96
Who does the Roundup of the week's most important happenings
Impact in China subscribers formative and fun to read the new Siddhartha features
Original content analysis from Zora and me
Stripe at nine 6. GG bc.com
Turn based in Silicon Valley
Shanghai and Beijing with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past 18 years from seed
Capri IPO 3.8 billion dollars in capital under management across age funds GTA V invest
Best in globally-minded on foreigners in consumer new retail social internet Enterprise cloud
And Frontier Tech GTB has invested over 290 companies with more than 45 companies.
Valued at over a billion dollars for companies include Airbnb Alibaba C trip
Didi chuxing demo hashicorp hellobike cows keep Slack
Square Hotel wish soundtrue white white and others find out more at ggv
Macy.com we also highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat group as lot Channel where we Regular Show
Hear inside events and job opportunities related to attack in China join these groups at 996
Stop GG vici.com community
Do you have any feedback on this podcast or would like to recommend a gas please email us I-96
IGG bc.com