What you're about to hear is part 3
A multi-part series on the first World War
If you're one of those individual that likes to know the story before the story you might want to catch up on those if you missed either
One of them
Although some of you probably don't mind just being dropped into the middle of a story like you arrived in the time machine and yet to figure things out
If you're one of those kind of individuals
And who cares about those earlier to shows why don't you just Jump On In
And join the horror in Prague
Grass
We blueprint for Armageddon
Part 3
December 7th 1941
A date which will live
In infamy
Eats history
The events
The figure it out
Call nist time and place I take pride in the words ich bin ein Berliner
Mr. Gorbachev tear down this wall
Welcome this kind of examination because people have got to know
Whether or not their President should question
We are not descended from fearful men
It's hardcore history
The very same WeChat
The first world war breaks out
August
A British Expedition
Leaves British Waters and heads for the South
Walpole
Antarctica
Led by guy named Ernest shot
Shackleton is one of the people that's normally associated with the very tail end
What called the age of Discovery the age of exploration
And you know what the tail end because
You don't like guys like Christopher Columbus Shackleton and his crew have camera
1914 you bring a camera with you
And he's able to document in photographs
Real clear interesting photographs this ordeal that he's about to experience
As he's on his way to
He's keeping tabs on this war that's broken out right when you left mean
This is the first real. Of globalization in the world and he can keep track via Telegraph of the
Minnesota major events that are going on
And like everyone
Shackleton is appalled by the scale
You can't believe the amount of casualties the number of people with challenges involved in logistics
It feels like this flame that is burning at an unbelievable intensity
So everybody just assumed that couldn't
Continue
Better than the Assumption even before the war
Broke out the Kaiser family says to his departing troops you be home before the leaves fall
When the French military leader Joseph Shaffer is told that his troops should be issued metal helmets to replace those cloth
At their starting the war with
He said don't bother
You'll never reach the
For the war is over
But there's a real feeling that
Something that's
Operating at that level of intensity can't continue for very long
Before Shackleton get to find out how the whole thing is though
Ian has
Ship and his crew get trapped in the ice
In the Antarctic
And again photos
It's wonderful
You get to watch the ship as it's crushed by the ice and Shackled get out and basically live
On the ice floes while they wait to be rescued
Which is not happening fast enough
And you can see that his people are going to die out there
If somebody doesn't do the Really Brave thing and take one of the little boats another 20-25 foot
Turn off the big boat
Amounting to almost an open rowboat not quite but almost
And he had a few crew members get in it
And head out
Into the Arctic
Waters
Looking for land
It's insane you think about it and it's insane that he survived
Anime 1916 Henley's couple of guys that he set out
You know into the Arctic
With amazing stories of of towering waves and all these things
Stumble into
Isolated
Whaling station
South Georgia Island
Which normally most of us would think is penguin territory it must have seemed positively balmy to
Shackleton and his crew
Who by this time look like
Bigfoot
Or something like a missing link
Totally sunburned
The Beards on their faces Frozen and
Icicles hanging off them
They were originally wearing animal skins but those skins did not like the saltwater very much ahead molted and marotta
Smelled and
Falling off of them I mean
The first thing they do when they get to this whaling station to scare the heck out of two boys
Couple of 12 year old or something see them first and
Go off running and who could blame them
Eventually though the adults Come Running
Shackleton identifies himself he's taken into be sort of restored given water
And I guess you could
It's a debrief
We're told one of the first questions he asks
Is benefactor
It's for an update on whatever happened with the war he was following
Inches tell me
When was the world
And in one of the more famous
Responses you'll ever get about this cuz it says so much in a couple of sentences and that's why I've gone down
In history the benefactor supposed to have answered his when was the war over question with
The war is over
Millions are dead
Europe is mad
The world is Matt
Shackleton react to this news
With horrified disbelief
And he's just catching up
The rest of the world
Because no one can believe
At the level of intensity that this conflict displays from minute one
Can be sustained
Remember this war starts very differently than the Second World War
The second world war kind of ramps up slowly
The first world war is like someone pulling the pin on a grenade and everything explodes at once
Everyone attacks it
There are a lot more people
Killed in the first month of the first World War
In the first month of the sack
In fact so many people are killed
But the people living through this. Have nothing to compare this to
The numbers are off the charts
I mean look at what
They were looking at is normal casual
By the way this is considered to be horrible could be bad it could be like the russo-japanese war
On steroids couldn't it
That war happened two decades before the first World War
Lasted 18 months
Is seen as sort of the testing ground for a lot of the weapons intact
Fixing everything that would be used in the next War
An 18-month 265000 people are killed it's horrible
165000 people are killed in a week or two
In the first World War
20 mm Frenchman die in a day
In August 1914
There are no metrics
For that
Are you American history
Fans out there
What's the worst war in American history
The US Civil War right
Because everyone who dies is an American
Casualty
Last 4 years
It was between 600000 and 700000 Americans killed
That's how many people you lose killed roughly
In the first month
Of the first World War
Everyone is done
And it's not just
Generals and world leaders and everything that say that this war can't last you have some of the top economic mines in the world
Singapore economic reasons that can't continue
John Maynard Keynes
The guy who will later be the father of Keynesian economics
Sajan 1914 that the world won't Last a year
As soon as the financial liquidity dries up he says
All the belligerents will be forced
To come to terms and make peace
It could have been more wrong
Countries will ditch the gold standard almost immediately they'll inflate their currency
Dell open up lines of credit will start borrowing
Lord Horatio Kitchener britons
Warminster one of the few people who understood how
Along this world would really in the last said quote
No Financial pressure has ever stopped a war in progress
And quote
Kitchener understood
But many of these people who should have understood better didn't
And that's that we had entered the era where nation-states could really take a punch
We talked about that in an earlier episode as a mixed blessing
It means
That you don't
Succumb to the enemies attacks right away but it means you also last longer
When you last longer you see your human and your financial capital
Ground into powder
There are a lot of
People who Wonder
Whether it was actually a benefit
For the French and the British to win the battle of the Marne
That's where we left off the last program
The battle of the Marne at the time was seen as
You know the savior of France
The Germans with their pre-war battle plans with her meticulous Precision planning that it had decades to come up with
The perfecting this plan
Stage fail
At the Battle of the Marne when
When by the time the other than the crowning moment happens where everything rests on what the Germans are doing
What sides are like a couple of Punch-Drunk Prizefighter
When using that
Analogy for this whole conflict because it works so well
And up until
You know the French and British victory at the Marne
The Germans have been the one really dishing out the heavy blows
But everyone is so tired and at the end of their rope by the time tomorrow and happens only a month into the conflict
Did you get the feeling like
The end of the first round of the both Fighters have given everything they have in there so tired that if anybody could just Land once
Solid blow on either side Italy over
In the French and the British land that blow
And the Germans are
Forced
Backward
Air Force backward
So that they can
Reorganize their life
Sand close up
This dangerous hole
In Airline
That was exploited by French and British troops as Churchill famously said is only he can
Those troops were
Probing their way into the German liver
And it's a
Classic maneuver to try to pull your troops back and reorganize your line when it's also a dangerous
And it also means
That the Germans have given up on the silk
Call Schlieffen Plan
I find it interesting sometimes when you read
Some of the histories
The first World War
You will find yourself in a very similar situation
Did the commanders on both sides
Of the western what will become the Western Front
And that is
You'll be studying this as though you're playing around with
Toy soldiers
I mean I'll read stuff with Hillside in this division did this and pulled back to here and then you're totally losing track
Of the human element
And the problem with that is if you don't understand the condition of the people on the ground
You're going to create all sorts of plans
It don't take into account what they can actually carry out
I mean for example
The general staff
Of all these armies
Are tens of miles behind where the fighting is I mean
Most of them the German general staff example are sitting in wonderful French chateau
With roaring fireplaces drinking wine out of crystal
Glasses and playing with maps and little protractors trying to decide where to move people and what to do with them
And the British and the French commanders are often doing the same thing
The problem is is that these little
Protractors in these armies that they're moving around on maps
Bear no resemblance
To what the human beings on the ground or dealing with
The human beings on the ground or spent
Both sides
Have worn themselves down to the nub
I can hardly function anymore I mean this is the point in the war once the German start retreating after the battle of the Marne
Where the British and French commanders think they've got them on the Run
Sir John French the British commander
Thanks but he's going to be in Berlin in 6 weeks it's going to be over will unleash the Cavalry will launch this massive Pursuit will just
Who are the enemy whose routing and it'll be all over
The problem is a Sir John French's troops are in no condition to do that
In fact
Every side is finding out
Another one of the new realities of Modern Warfare
And that's that they use ammunition at a pace
But nobody was prepared for
At this point in the conflict
Everybody is actually rationing
The
Artillery
We can't even use the guns the way they want to because they don't have enough Sheldon take the Russians as a perfect example
At this point in the war
The Russians are producing
35000 artillery shells a month
Sounds great doesn't it
Can you realize that once the fighting actually starts
They're using 45,000 shells
A day
Making 35000 a month
Shooting off 45000 shells a day
Now all these armies went into the conflict with nice reserves the shells
The buy a month-and-a-half into it
They're down to almost nothing and even the French and the British
You know as they pursued the German Army's at the German Army's Retreat from the Marne
They can't
Function the way that they're
Trained and ready to do so they have to ration everything and so does the German
And everybody's just at the end of their rope
And you lose the human element when you study the history of things from the very highest levels in the moving of armies around
On maps when you see arrows and
Calvary armies in all these kinds of things when the people on the ground
How many
Keep me different situation
Here's how
Ryder GJ Meyer describes
In the situation after the Marne quote
The French and British so jubilant at and in many cases astonished by the German withdrawal from the Marne
We're badly battered
Worn out
I'm running low on a Central Equipment
Many were almost too exhausted to move
He's quoting an English Soldier now
Quote after 5 days and nights of fighting
1 English Soldier Road
Decimated spent and hungry
We are lying on the bare Earth with only one desire in our hearts
To get ourselves killed
Meijer continue
And they were short of shells for their artillery
It is one measure of the sustained intensity of this new kind of warfare that the French faced critical shortages of Amy
Ignition for their 75 mm Cannon their most effective field artillery piece
Because only ten thousand rounds were being produced per day
That was barely 20% of the knee
He continues
For any number of such reasons the armies of the entendre
The allies
Failed to close with the retreating Germans
Or exploit the huge gap that had prompted there withdrawal they did not attack in force until the German first second and third eye
Armies had settled into fortified position
On High Ground north of the Ain
The next East-West River North of the Marne
By then it was too late
And quote
The Germans themselves were not horrible
German Soldier
Julia skoczen writes about the retreat from the Marne
Quote
The streets were badly worn
Abandoned vehicles were lying on the sides of the road
We began to move at 3 in the morning and before we were fully aware of what was happening we found ourselves with the rear
Guard regiments of Infantry
Shot to Pieces arrived in a pitiful condition
Stay at Castaway their knapsacks and all unnecessary impediments
And we're trying to get along as fast as possible
Soon after the first shrapnel of the enemy began to burst above our heads
Which caused us to accelerate our March continually
The road we could also been used during the advance
Was still marked by Deep shell holes that were filled with water to the very edge for it rained without interruption
It was pitch dark and every now and then someone would fall into one of those shell holes
We were all wet through but continue to press on
Some would stumble over something in the dark but nobody paid any attention
The great thing was to get along
Dead horses in men lay in the middle of the road but nobody took the trouble to remove the obstacle
And quote
Lest we forget about the human element remember that these Germans
Are moving through country that was formerly occupied by civilians
Where the heck are they
Well
In a lot of cases
They're still there
In very great Danger
Here's what coaching
About that quote
The road was covered with the equipment the soldiers that thrown away
We too would long ago cast aside all unnecessary ballast
Dust we were marching when we passed a wood densely packed with refugees
Does hunted people have stretch blankets between the trees
So it's to protect themselves from the rain
There they were lying in the greatest conceivable misery
All in the jumble
Men and women
Children and greybeards
Their Camp reached as far as the road and one could observe the terrible hours that they lived through had left
Deep furrows in their faces
They looked at us with weary tired eyes
The children begged us to give them some bread
But we had nothing whatsoever left
And wear ourselves tormented by hunger
The enemy shrapnel was still accompanying us and we have scarcely left the wood when shrapnel began to explode
They're which caused the refugees now exposed to the fire to crowd into the field in an attempt to reach
Beach safety
Many of them joined us but before long they were forbidden to use the road because they competed The Retreat of the troops
That's all of them were driven Without Pity into the fields soaked by the rain
And quote
As German soldiers like Julius or usually escutcheon are
Retreating
Back the way they came
They're being closely pursued by their French and British officer
One of whom is the Irish Soldier fighting in the British expeditionary force that we talked about earlier John Lucy
Right about this time quote
Advanced continued steadily as the Germans were driven back from the Marne
The rear guard showed some resistance everyday
And occasionally we picked up stragglers and wounded from the enemy Army
Although we took our turn in our Brigade at Advanced Garden Outpost duties
Our Battalion did not really Crossed Swords With the Enemy again until the 14th of September
On that day
And on the few days preceding it rain fell
And we were not very comfortable either in big Wacker on the line of March the weather began to get cold
On the evening of 13th September at British airplane
One of the few the British army possessed
Approached from the German side
And Wheeling around a lighted in a field to the right of our marching columns
The flying officer climb slowly out of his machine
And coming stumbling towards us in his heavy kit
Did not wait to find an officer
But shouted to us all
There they are waiting for you up there thousands of them
Anyway just right arm toward the wooded Heights across the river Ames I'm 3 miles away
And quote
The riveraine
Was right by
The highest
Elevated point in this whole area
On the front
Now it's not very high
In terms of the grand scheme of geography around the planet but in the very flat area near the French and Belgian border
It was 500 ft tall and some places
And that gave a commanding View
Of all the flat country around it
This is the point that the German soldiers have been told
To turn back around
And face their pursuers
And Dig Inn
And stop
This has been one of the last commands made
By the former German Commander the one whose job it was to carry out the Schlieffen Plan
Helmuth Von moltke the younger
Totally collapsed from his nervous breakdown
After his plan failed
He's replaced by one of his critics
A controversial choice that the Kaiser
InnoTab
The guy name
General Eric
I'm talking High
Now one thing that becomes clear
When you look at the high command of all these arms
Is the generals have outrageous egos most of the time
And they often are jealous
And a snipe at their peers
Ameren falkenhayn is named it angers among other people Erich ludendorff this
Young wunderkind who's been doing great things for the Germans on the Eastern front and who will say of
Vulcan Hines
Appointment
I'm only capable of love
And Hate
I hate General falkenhayn
Valkenhayn was critical of
Minolta
Before the battle of the Marne even starts
Valkenhayn looks at what Von molcas doing and thinks he's lost his mind
And rights
On September 5th 1914 quote
Our general staff is completely lost its head
Sleeping's notes do not help any further and so molcas wits come to an end
And quote
All the Kaiser must have read that and decided
It's in Van molka couldn't
Pull this off
Maybe one of his critics can
Falkenhayn
Turns his troops around tell them to dig in and begins looking for replacements for the people who died
Because the German Army is a fraction of what it was
Just a couple of weeks before
They aren't the only ones
The British and the French armies have a similar problem
Are all decimate
The difference is Britain and France have colonies
And Dominion
A commonwealth Nations
Who the minute the war starts are basically told to get people over there and their arriving everyday
The British have Indian troops from India arrived in Canadian show up very quickly
The Scots
From Scotland are always a part of the British forces and they arrive in kilts
And this is where they will get their famous nickname which some people wonder if it even happened this way
But it's too good of a nickname to
You're not mentioned
The Germans supposedly call them the ladies from hell
Because of the Kilts they were
Where and they're all showing up every day in greater numbers and taking their place in the line
To replace the dead in the wounded
The French are bringing troops from North Africa
From Morocco and Algeria and troops from
Central Africa and places like Senegal so you have
Dark skinned black Africans in the French army
Something that the Germans won are not accustomed to
And to a little dismayed about because they think about all of the black Africans left in Africa
That maybe could be brought
To fight against them to
When the Germans try to reinforce their own
Torn open ranks
They have to do it with German
Now they have a bunch of them
People who demand that the war was declared signed up
I join the forces and we're in training this whole time the problem is that the war is only about 6 weeks old
None of these people have had enough training to make them anywhere near as good as the soldier they're trying to replace
The falkenhayn calls them up anyway
The situation is desperate the war could be lost right here right now
And every man is needed
And all these troops are going to be thrown into the Bloodbath
Amir the French and Belgian border
It's at that spot where the Germans have turned around
Halted the retreat
That has been going on ever since the battle of the Marne
Taking the Heights on the other side of the river Ain
And began to dig in
Fortify
Re-equip reinforce
And are waiting for their pursuers to show up
Are French and British pursuers
Assume that they are going after a bunch of Rowdy German
They're not expecting to run into heavily fortified positions in a very very strong spot
Remember John Lucy in the bef are Marching toward that area
When the airplane lands in the field in the pilot goes running up to the British March column saying
They're waiting for you thousands of them on the other side of the river
I'm a night of September 13th 1914
The French and the British try cross that River
And dislodge the Germans from the height
I need to design
The British do this Crossing At Night
In heavy fog
Pontoon boats for the most part
I get to the other side
A side that has no natural covering its facing Unifour to 500 Foothills in the distance
Heavily wooded
And the sun comes up
And burns off the fog
Leaving the British troops totally exposed
And the Germans slaughtered
Artillery machine guns even from the flank
The British stagger back across the river
And their Commander Sir John French orders them to dig in
And face the Germans were dug in on the other side of the river
This is the main thing your history books will tell you
Did the first battle of the aisne is known for its supposedly the time
When trench warfare was initiated
This will be the most iconic and memorable part of the first World War
But it's a misnomer to suggest the trench warfare just started here
Because given the technology of the day
Trench warfare begins organically it's a natural human response to the fact
The air above ground level is filled with so much steel and Lead
But it's suicide
To be out in the open
Across the entire front
Stretching all the way from the
Swiss border
Across the entire franco-german border up through Luxembourg up into Belgium
More than 400 miles in millions of men on both sides long
Human beings have done the most natural thing
Possible
They've gone to ground
And they've tried to get as low as possible to escape
What aren't General will call the storm of Steel
Later in the war
In addition to digging down there throw up things called breastwork
Switches
Putting stuff in front of your position to
Stop the bullets
If you're lucky it's sandbags if you're not lucky is anything you can get your hands on
The combination of digging in the Earth
And putting up barriers in front of you begins to fortify the entire line on both sides and in some spots.
Germans in the French
Are only a couple hundred yards from each other
The fortification of the entire line
Changes this war
In ways that the generals on either side or unprepared for they don't know what to do
So they go back to the
In training
What would you say
Find a flight
Turn the flank
Attack in the rear
The problem is is that there's only one tiny little area of this more than 400 Mile Line
We're in heaven calcified into an almost seizure like situation
And that's the area be
Between
In this battle at the river and that is just happened
And the ocean
To the north
It's not very big
Zone
And both the British and the French on one side and the Germans on the other
Begin a
Crab like
Dance of Death
As one historian
Describes it
Trying to probe their way towards Open Country
For a very long time
This was known as the race to the Sea
But historians have come to hate that term because
He gives the false idea that somehow
Reaching the sea is the goal
All about the sides with in fact
If both sides reach the sea
It means that there are no flanks anymore
And there will be several
Big battles between
The armies as they collide
In their attempt to find an open flame to turn
Now
It's worth pointing out here that won't worry about experiences the most complicated War
I've ever studied
And it's a very unusual conflict because in many cases
The battlefield is not going to change
This area up near the franco-belgian border for example is going to become
One of the worst
Killing ground extended Killing Grounds in all human history
Later in the war
Troops marching up to this Battle Ground will be able to smell it
Before they actually get there
In addition
When one side attacks the other side will often counter-attack so if you look at the battle on a map
It makes no sense at all I've got 400 page books that deal with just single encounters
Between the two sides and it's impossible to make heads or tails of it
Even with maps even if you're an expert
I'm part of the reason why because the nature of battle has changed
Armies are staying in contact with each other
That's very different than through most of human history through most of human history Armies come together there's a short Sharp
Clash and then they
Break contact and move in opposite directions again
Battles that last more than one day are extremely rare
Up until this time.
All of a sudden
These armies aren't going to break
They're going to stay
On opposite sides of a short little no man's land and hold each other by the
The throat
Even on so-called
Quiet parts of the front hundreds or thousands of men can be killed every day
Now this is not unheard of
Near the
End stages of the US Civil War
Ulysses S Grant a northern General
Will have a similar strategy where he maintains contact with the Enemy grab them by the throat doesn't let them go
Island grinds them down the strategy of attrition
But that's new
The European experience
And neither side's giving up yet they're going to try
Define that blank until there is no flying anymore
That race to the Sea will involve several more big battles including one that involves
You know what's left of the poor Belgian Army
Remember the Belgian Army was what the Germans thought we're going to be a bunch of chocolate soldiers
And instead they put up this heroic
Doom resistance to them
Enough fighting and being pushed backwards every step of the way
Once the Germans
Replay on their lines at the riveraine
Their entire
Blank is threatened by the parts of Belgium that haven't fallen to them yet
Including the Giant and vital Port City of Antwerp
So this is when the Germans go take all that
A pound and work with those same enormous guns that they destroyed the Belgian forts with at the beginning of the war
And they pushed the Belgian Army all the ways that the belgians are sitting there with their backs to the ocean
There's no place left to run
And the Belgian King is with them and at one point he orders his officers to stand behind the trenches and shoot anybody
Belgian soldiers that their run away and they stay there being pounded by the artillery
Until they can't
Stop
The Germans
They realized
If they don't hold that area
The Germans are going to be the one who find that open flanken the turn the British and the French in this is
You the part of the war where it looks like the Germans might actually reverse the entire Battle of the Marne results
And went anyway
To the belgians do
Something that is
Are there nuclear option
Huntington
It's a sacrifice that might have saved the war for the allies
Remember Belgium is one of those areas of Europe it is actually
For the most part this part of Flanders that were talking about in Belgium
Below sea level
And the reason that it even exists because
In Forever the belgians have been pumping out water and building dikes
And things like that to keep the ocean out
In the Belgian When Things become desperate to the point of Doomsday
Blows up the dikes
The Belgian King makes the decision to let the sea water in
October 22nd
It's a true sacrifice because he's not just flooding one of the more fertile parts of his country
He's plotting it with seawater
And the saltwater will do terrible damage to the fertility of the region remember the Roman supposedly
Would so salt into the ground
Of the territory of their very worst enemies
So that nothing would ever grow there again
The belgians have done this to themselves
Voluntarily
To protect
The very end
End of the Allied line and keep the Germans from breaking through and perhaps taking the channel
The Germans have no idea what's going on at the water level rises
But within a couple of days
There's a five mile wide shoulder deep lake
Separating them
And the Belgian forces and the belgians will stay behind that like 4 years
That essentially shuts off.
Part of the front
Bad news for the other Allied Forces
Is it now that the Germans didn't need those troops to try to
Deal with the belgians they turn them around
And threw them into the developing battle at a place called Ypres
Which on October 22nd breaks out big-time
And
You tried to come to this point where
The true
Futility
Of the wasting of life
Is so aptly
Because of course war is all about spending live
To achieve a goal
The tragedy happens when you spend lies for no good reason
Eat Pray you begin to see the kinds of
Tragic level
That this will reach
A large number of the troops
The Germans had called up
Inwood very little training
We're Young
Students
Whose teachers had indoctrinated them into the idea of
This is what you do when you fight for Germany and what a great honor it's going to be you know when they would all join up together as students with
Fraternity Badges and all these things in
After very little training they were thrown into this combat
That was developing around the city of Ypres and the surrounding area
And one of the really tragic
Parts of
Conflict
The students would run up against
What was left
Some of the greatest military units in the world
The old British professional Army
Which has been
Ground down new ever since the war started but still had some of its best units intact
These
Badly trained
16 17 and 18 year old kids
Would be Massacre
For no good reason
As author Winston groom right
Lights quote
On the front of nearly 20 miles
Tens of thousands of men came to grips and did their best to murder each other in the cold tank
Misty Hills surrounding April
In many places the fighting was hand-to-hand
That morning
Divisions of the German 4th Army
Consisting in large part of students
Attacked the British line such as it was
In a fitted binary and frenzy the German students came on arm and arm
Are waving their rifles in the air singing
And with their spikes
Pickle halba helmet
Festooned with flowers
By the thousands they were shot down
Even though they outnumber the British at times 6 to 1 that morning they face the most professional
Elite regiments of the British army
If not the world
The black watch
Coldstream guards
Scotchgard
Cameron
Grenadier guards
Irish guards
Stafford
Gordon Highlanders
Green Howards
Royal Scots fusiliers
Welsh fusiliers and others almost too numerous to mention including the huszar's and dragoons of the Cavalry Court
When was all over the British official history estimated
At least half of these youthful Teutonic Warriors
100000 of them have been shot down
The Germans name the battle the massacre of the Innocents
And quote
In German it was the kindermourn
And after the war
Parents of some of these children
Would put a poignant Monument
Over there Mass grave
Showing a weeping father and mother
Looking out over the mass Graves festooned
With the fraternity pin
Of these young kids
Who thought War
What's going to be a romantic hero I could venture
I'm not going to focus
On Battle after
The battle after
The Battle of point
What's conflict
Story
It's a complicated
And
Detailed enough conflict did you kind of have to pick your battles
Pardon the pun
And it's a human side of this affair
Taiwan
Focus on what the people who were living through it
Woodforest to expiry
For example
20 year old
Herbert sulzbach
A gunner who joined up as the war starts
I was getting his first taste of battle
As the Battle of Ypres
Begins
Lights quote
Change of position
We pull forward
Get our first glimpse of this battle
And have to get used to the terrible scenes in impressions
Corpses corpses and more Corp
Rubble in the remains of a captured Village
Trenches hastily dug by the British or full of bodies
We get driven out of this position by infantry and artillery fire
We stand beside the guns with the horses in a dreadful night
Comes down on
We've seen too many horrible things all at once
They make a very strong impression on us
Barely twenty years old as we are
But these things also Harden us up
What's going to come
And quote
He's not the only one
Another German
Rights to his sweetheart
With care for her sensibilities and understanding of what military censorship might do to his letter
About with the reality of what he's experiencing is like
He writes
During these battles
In Flanders
Quote
My dear Maria
I feel so terrible I'd really rather not write to you
That doesn't mean I've forgotten you though every day spent here makes it clear to me how beautiful home is
What a crowd of feelings that word home
Brings out in me
I've lived through such horror recently
No words can describe it
The tragedy all around me
Everyday the fighting gets fiercer and there's no end in sight
Our blood is flowing in Torrance
When I think of our 247th regiment
My eyes swim with tears
The first and second battalions have only 250 to 300 men left
Some more than half are gone
Today only a few of my comrades will be still standing
My company Commander
Lieutenant Moss power
I've been at the front for one hour when he was shot through the head
Pale and close to death
He was carried past me
Today
Sunday
I started this modest grave and joined in prayer
That's how it is
All around me the most gruesome devastation
Dead and wounded soldiers
Dead and dying animals horse cadavers burnt-out houses dug up fields
Cars clothes weaponry
All this is scattered around me
A real mess
I didn't think War would be like this
We can't sleep for all the noise
At least 30 shells exploded once the whole time
We called for backup yesterday and today
I hope they make it
There are only a few of us left to tackle the English
I managed to wash myself properly yesterday for a change
My beard is getting ever longer
Otherwise I'm feeling fine as you can see all this noise is not going to rough on my werdenberg car
And quote
German soldier named Paul who
This war
Brings out
The extremes of humanity
And even the most
Monsters human beings that you can take out throughout history
Exhibit some of that Humanity through their writing
Hugo Reid one of the most monstrous human beings who's ever lived
Chronicles of this combat
Even he
Seems somewhat Human by the whole thing
Adolf Hitler was there
In Flanders
In 1914 at these battles
It was his first encounter with combat
I wrote about it in his
Book mine comp
Quote
That last a day came when we left Munich
To begin the Fulfillment of our duty
For the first time I saw the Rhine
As we rode Westward along that's quiet water to defend it
The German stream of streams
From the greed of the old enemy
Went through the tender veil of the Early Morning Mist
The niederwald monument gleam down upon us in the gentle rays of the Sun
The old watch on the Rhine roared out of the Endless transport train into the morning sky
And I felt as though my heart would burst
And then came a damp cold night in Flanders
Through which we marched in silence
And when the day began to emerge from the Mist
Suddenly an iron greeting came whizzing out us over our heads
I'm going to Sharp report
Santa little pellets flying between our ranks
Ripping up the wet ground
But even before the little clouded path
From 200 throats
The first hurrah Rose to meet the first messengers of death
Then a crackling in a roaring in a singing in a howling began
And with feverish I teach one of us was drawn forward
Faster and faster until suddenly past Turner Field and hedges
The fight began
The fight of man against man
And from the distance
The strains of a song reached our ears
Coming closer and closer leaving from company to company just as death plunge too busy hand into our ranks
The song reached out to and we passed it along
Deutschland Deutschland Uber Alles Uber Alles in Deerfield
4 days later we came back
Even our stepdad chain
17 year old boy now look like men
The volunteers of the list regiment may not have learned to fight properly
But I knew how to die like soldiers
This was the beginning
You said that it went on year after year
But the romance of battle have been replaced by horror
The enthusiasm gradually cool
I need you to enjoy was stifled by mortal fear
The time came when every man had to struggle
Between the Instinct of self-preservation and the admonitions of Duty
I too was not spared by the struggle
Always when death was on the hunt of vague something tried to revolt
Strove to represent itself to the weak body as reason
It was only cowardice
Which in such disguises tries to ensnare the individual
A grave tugging and warning set in
And often it was only The Last Remnant of conscience which decided the issue
Yet the more this voice admonished wanted to caution
The louder and more insistent explores the sharper resistance group
Until at last after a long inner struggle
Consciousness of Duty emerge Victorious
By the winter of 1915 1916 he rides
This struggle has been for me decided
Unlock my wheel was Undisputed master
If in the first days I went over the top with rejoicing and laughter
I was now calm and determined
And this was enduring
Now Faith could bring on the ultimate test without my nerves shattering are my reason failing
The young volunteer had become an old Soldier
And this transformation had occurred in the whole Army
It issued hard and old from the Eternal battles
And for those who could not stand up under the storm
Well they were broke
And quote
Hitler would actually
Leap out into no man's land under a hail of bullets
And try to rescue a
Commanding officer
By putting them on his back and carrying him back to
The German lines
It will be decorated by the Kaiser for this
Even though the man he rescue died
What Hitler is talking about in this personal struggle but he has to go through to try to make himself do something
The entire urges of humanity inside a human being
You argue against
Is something that
Every soldier in the war
I was going to face this kind of Carnage needs to
And deal with at one point or another
Sometimes they don't even have control over what has
People will be affected by
The storm of Steel is
Ernst Junger will call it later in the war
In different ways sometimes consciously but sometimes
In a way that defies even what they want to do
Can one of the things that The Human Side of
The first World War
Requires us to look at
Is how and why were these people doing these things
Intelligent human beings
From the modern era look at what our grandfathers and great-grandfathers did in this conflict
And can understand how and why they did it
Part of it is the romance in the heroism in the ID of Duty and what's expected of them
And some of that is what motivates soldiers to continue to
Press forward in unbelievable situations in combat even today
But there were other
Elements in play
Less savory
We were dealing with modern nation-state
Who had ways of compelling a certain level of behavior
There were a lot of people
We're not brave in this Combat on all sides or
Whose body is simply would not do what their mind told them to do
Those people
Often had to be sacrificed
As an example to others
In 1914
A British Brigadier General named e l Spears
Wrote about one of those methods that the modern state
And really States had for some time before this
Used to compel their troops
To be brave and to do their Duty
Any road quote
Generally my day had just been roused from sleep on the straw of the shed and was standing in the street
When a little group of unmistakable purport
Came around the corner
12 soldiers in an NCO
A firing party
A couple of John darms in between them and unarmed Soldier
My heart sank
And a feeling of horror overcame me
An execution was about to take place
Generally my day took a look
And then held up his hand so that the party halted
And with the characteristic Quick-Step
Went up to the doomed man
He asked what are you been condemned for
It was for abandoning his post
The general then began to talk to the man
Quite simply he explain discipline to him
Abandon your post was letting down your pals
More
It was letting down your country
It look to you to defend her
He spoke of the necessity of example
How someone could do their Duty without prompting
But others
Less strong
How to know when understand the Supreme cost of failure
He told The Condemned man that his crime was not venal not low
How many Must Die is an example so that others should not fail
Surprisingly
The wretch agreed
Nodding his head
The burden of infamy was lifted from his shoulders
He saw a glimmer of something
Redemption in his own eyes
A real hope
Though he knew he was going to die
The general went on
Carrying the man with him to comprehension
There any sacrifice was worthwhile if it helped France ever so little
What did anything matter if he knew this
Finally the general held out his hand
Meaning to Shake The Condemned person
Pand
Yours is also a way of dying for France he said
The procession started again
But now the victim was a willing one
The sound of a volley in the distance announced that all was over
General d-mate wipe the beads of perspiration from his brow
And for the first time perhaps
His hand trembled as he lived his pipe
And quote
That's something
That all sides will do in this war
The way of saying yes you may face certain death
If you walk into the storm that is Modern Combat
But you'll also face certain death
If you don't
Very important build a bear in mind
The fact that these soldiers who failed in their Duty somehow or exposed
To capital punishment
Does not mean that that's why Soldier
That's something that has been present in most armies throughout history
Since ancient
At the Romans if your unit fart badly
Would make the men
Draw Lots
And one out of every ten soldiers in a unit would be killed that was called decimation
And to add insult to injury
The Romans would make their comrades killed
So that's a standard part of warfare throughout most of History
Most of these soldiers were fighting for much
Higher values
Things that you do more cynical 21st century mind
Sometimes almost sound like
In a military recruiting marketing slogan
But they meant something to these people
I mean something to soldiers today
Duty
Honor
Country
Sovereign
God
And what's more once these soldiers get into combat
A responsibility to your comrade
Nonetheless
The first World War
Is able to take
One of the most extreme activities humans ever take part in
Warfare
And make it worse
Instart for example
With what trench warfare means for the soldiers on the ground in terms of day-to-day living
Go out in your backyard
Dig yourself a hole
Sit down in it
In the rain
And just living
Day after day
Without any bombs
Guns
Bullets
Or murderous combat
And it's horrible
50 seoul
Most of them in Flanders one of the rainiest parts of Europe
They live in the mud
And they can't quite get their mind around how that changes this
Romantic idea
Of adventurous combat
It's so many of them signed up for take for example some of the most elite units
In France's military men who were in The French Foreign Legion and who find themselves in holes in the ground
Ground
Alan Seeger
I will die
On the Western Front in 1916
Righteousness trench warfare is getting started
Quote
This style of trench warfare is extremely modern
And for the artillerymen is doubtless very interesting
But for the poor common Soldier it is anything but romantic
His role is to Simply dig himself a hole in the ground and keep hidden in it as tightly as possible
Continually under the fire of the opposing batteries he is yet never allowed to get a glimpse of the enemy
Exposed to all the dangers of War but none of its enthusiasms or Splendid lawn
He is condemned to sit like an animal in its burrow
And hear the shells whistle over his head
And take your little daily toll from his comrades
His feet are numb
Is canteen Frozen
But he's not allowed to make a fire
He's not even permitted to light a candle
He must hold himself up in his blanket and lie down cramped in the dirty straw to sleep as best as he may
How different from the popular notion of the evening campfire
The song
And the good cheer
And quote
It's after the battles up in Flanders
On the Ain
Eat bread
When is trench warfare sets in the German Soldier
Rudolf binder tries to explain what's happening in 1914 when he writes quote
The war is got stuck into a gigantic Siege on both sides
The whole front is one endless fortified Trench
Neither side has the force to make a decisive push
Everyone seemed settled on a winter campaign
But as far as I can judge
There's no possibility of an early finish
We are still stuck here for perfectly good reason
One might as well say for perfectly bad reason
This business May last for a long time
And quote
Now
It's important to remember that most of the people who are finding themselves stuck in this business in 19
Aren't really Soldier
Soldiers might be expected to deal with this kind of
Incredible experience but most of the troops in these uniforms and carrying weapons which
For all intents and purposes appear to be so
Six or eight weeks ago were civilians
They were shopkeeper
A delivery boy
And students and insurance salesman and teachers
All of a sudden find themselves
In circumstances that they just can't make sense of
Horrible situations
Many of these people have never seen a dead body in their lives
And then all of a sudden find themselves
In situations like this German soldier in 1914 describing
This new phenomenon of trench life
Day-to-day living in a hole in the ground
We combat going on all around you he writes quote
The dangers of trench life may be realized
When I say that often neither the dead nor wounded can be removed
If you put up as much as a little finger above the edge of the trench
The bullets come whizzing around immediately
The dead bodies must therefore be allowed to remain in the trench
That is to say the dead man is got rid of by digging a grave for him in the floor of the
French a few days ago a soldier was so badly hit by a shell that he was cutting too
His shattered body could not be removed without risk to the survivors
And was therefore allowed to remain
But presently he gave rise to a horrible stench
And whatever they did the men could not get away from the mutilated black and features
Sometimes arms and legs torn away from the body are allowed to lie about the bottom of the trench until someone can bury the
One gets hardened in time
And quote
Getting hardened in time
Is what's happening
During this period in 1914 once the fighting
Abby's major first battle died down because this is when the reinforcements arrive
And the reinforcements are not part of the regular army these are the civilians
From a short time ago
Thrown into uniform and sent into this hell of combat
Little bit different for the veterans especially the profession
The British professional Army
Yeah that existed before the war started the so-called old contemptibles
Are being as we said
Whittled down to
You're practically nothing but there's a few of them laugh
And you're trying to integrate these former civilians into their ranks
Without getting killed in the process because those people don't know the ropes yet
And they're doing things that scare the regular
John Lucy one of the old contemptibles in the Irish guards
In the bef rights quote
We stood to win the wet shell holes and crumbling trenches under the Thunder and Blasting flashes of German hike
Explosives
There is no need to describe this bombardment except to say that it was the worst of my experience
A few of our fellows broke under
And 1 porkchop entirely lost his head and ran back out of his trench
He had not a chance in the open
The Earth was vomiting all around us
Any tumbled over in a few yard
Better to have kept to the trench
No trained soldier would leave that
Hey Corporal a Burly fellow
Spell near me with a shrapnel bullet in his head
He lay unconscious all the day
Nodding his hold had is if suffering only from some slight irritation
And did not become still until evening
Earlier in the day one youngster said
What about putting him out of his misery
I'm more experienced man explained that there was no pain
The smallest earrings a little moans
Came from a man who was then already as good as dead
Another Soldier
Lucy says
Had his belly ripped open
And stop supporting his back against a trench while he gazed with fascinated eyes at large coils of his own
Guts which he held in both hands
This was almost too ghastly a site I saw
It sequel was better
The man Central had not been penetrated
He got safe out of the trench
Was washed
Tucked in and mended well in hospital
Maned Men passed crouching and crawling behind me leaving trails of Blood on the ground
On their way to a Ditch Witch LED back into the woods behind
Some of them were moaning too loud
Unlike our old man he means the better
1 young militia man in particular
Came by roaring in seeking sympathy for a broken arm from everyone he met
Lance corporal told him that for God's sake to put a sock in it
And if you were really badly wounded he would have no breath left to howl
That's topped hysterics
I should say that the noncoms of the old army had the worst time of all
Trying in circumstances like these to keep inexperienced men in hand
Some of these men could not even fire a rifle properly
And at times our hearts quailed for our safety and theirs
And quote
This experience
Was so unlike with the soldiers of the day were accustomed to
The minister of War
And war hero himself Lord Horatio Kitchener in Britain
Famously said when seeing what this whole deal was like
This is not war
Maybe you hadn't been
But this was sort of a way of
Telling everyone in this generation
Welcome to the 20th century
This is how it's going to be 4
These battles in Flanders
What you do
Shatter
Many of the leaders
Confident and what's going on
Remember when the war starts they have a plan for winning the war that's been
In a worked out over years but once that fails
All these generals have to improvise
They have to
Create new offensives in new ways to win the war from where things stand
And after these battles in Flanders die down and you have this trench warfare setting in General von falkenhayn in German
Money runs the numbers
And they're horrible
I'm in the Battle of Ypres
All sides combined
You're talking about another 250000 casualties in a few weeks
That brings a German totals on the Western Front since the war started
Which is August
2 more than 750 thousand
The French you're topping a million
The British and for all intents and purposes lost
They are professional Army the greatest in the world small but the greatest in the world
It's down to dozens of men in units that had hundreds of men
You know a very short time ago
And in Britain there trying to scrape up replacements
And you can see how how bad it is by how quickly their changing the requirement
Because when the war starts you have to be 5 foot 8 inches tall
To be in the British army
In October they lower that to 5
Foot five inches tall
A single month later in November they'll or that the five foot
3 in tall
The Germans
Are having a similar problem they learned a very
Hard lesson in these battles in Flanders
You must
Let the troops finish their training cuz they threw away a ton of Lies with people who weren't ready to fight
But Duncan Hines got a more difficult situation
Because the British and the French as we said have dominions and Commonwealth Nations I mean the Canadians alone in a fit
Patriotism are sending more than 30,000 fresh troops
Across the Atlantic
In the largest
Transportation of
Troops
When the history of the world across the large ocean
I'm talkin I have two accounts
He goes and he tells the civilian leadership
Did the war in the west camp B1
He tells them that they have to come to some sort of an arrangement
And He suggests making
Peace with somebody
Maybe the Russian
Because if you make peace with the Russians maybe the French will lose heart
He says all of these other nations are simply weapons in the hands of the arch in
Which is English
And they have to be at the British have to be the ones
That the Germans focus on and we have to get these other countries
Which are merely sword in the hand of perfidious Albion he says
Need to get them out of the war
Now this is going to be very hard to do because way back in September all the allies
Chinese agreement saying nobody will make A Separate Peace
Nonetheless falkenhayn hopes
But he can make his War aims
You no longer Victory but shattering some of these Powers they leave the war
The civilian leadership in Germany the politicians like bethmann-hollweg
Are appalled by what
They can't figure out a way to do this because
The Germans just like all these other countries are so appalled by the casualties in the blood that's been spilled
The nobody is willing
To give up anything
You've already lost too many people
One thing if you lose all those people in a victory
Do nothing if you lose all those people in a loss
Besides
Batman holding just a couple of months ago was writing up
Plans for what the victory conditions in the war going to be in he got these grandiose
Schemes where we're going to push the Russians back we're going to keep the French down forever we're going to all these vassal States and now his Chi
Military leader is saying listen we can't win the war
Now
Don't forget Hines Rivals guys like ludendorff in the East who already hate him
Viscerally
Say that his attitude you know this early in the war is tantamount to treason
I basically insinuating and no one certain terms that I change and Military leadership my change all these sorts of things
Valkenhayn is told
But there's no way
That we're ending the war
He tells his troops on the Western Front
To hold on to what you have
Never Surrender a square foot of what you one if you do counter-attack immediately and retake it
Because they take invaluable territory valuable Farmland valuable resources valuable industrial Land from the French
And if he can't get the war
Stop from the political leadership he's going to hold on to what he had
He tells the troops in the west to deepen their fortification
Instead of just one line of trenches
He wants multiple line
He and all the other leaders
On both sides begin to use
This wonderful weapon which doesn't seem like a weapon at all of barbed wire
Something it was first invented
A generation before to keep
Title pending in the American West
And in the last couple of Wars since then it been used
You know sparingly and soda experiment Lee
Now all sides take this wire with all these sharp edges and begin to use it as a fortification
This will be another one of these
Iconic things on the Western Front and you don't even think that
Something like wire with little tiny barbs on will make that much of a difference but it proved to be one of the
You know most
Important
Elements of the of the war on the Western Front you can even make a case
Did they will invent weapon systems which still dominate militaries today
Simply overcome the barrier
Created by things like
Like barbed wire
Now it's not all bad
For the Central Powers in Germany is 19141
Shore General von falkenhayn has decided that he can't see a way to Victory on the Western Front
But there's fighting going on on other friends too
Is main adversaries in Germany's High command
The ever more powerful team of Hindenburg and ludendorff
Believers that you can win the war by beating the Russians they will become part of the
Group of German generals that will be known as Eastern
Rich people to think you can win the war
By being victorious in the East Falcon Hines one of these guys who
Is part of the cabal known as the westerners
Believers that any real victory in the war will come on the Western Front
Newfronts opening up is 1914 wines down strange front Stu
We haven't even mentioned that there's fighting going on
In the Pacific because it really is a sidebar to this story
Japan for exam
Once the war breaks out quickly throws in their lot
With Britain and France and Russia in the eye
They do so for purely opportunistic Ruiz
The Germans have some territories in the Pacific
The Japan can easily snap up it won't be much fighting it won't be much trouble
And if the Allies somehow lose the war
There's not much Germany and Austria-Hungary and stuff can do to Japan way over in the Pacific anyway
There's no downside
So the Japanese snap up some of these Drummond Island possessions in the
Pacific to take some German territories
On the Asian mainland
And the most important part of all of those
Actions
Will be the fact that some of those places will be
The Battlegrounds in the second world
And also that Japan's
Taking a German possessions on the Asian mainland help
Precipitate later war between Japan and China which will help create the conditions where the Japanese are part of the Pacific War in the
The Second World War I mean it's more of a long-term situation
I mean it's more of a long-term
Cancerous situation but
Japan's been in the war since the beginning it's part of what makes this a world
Buddy November 1914 turkey at
And this is a very different
First of all
The Turks are not United on the idea at all
Some of the more aggressive
Members of the government
For now called The Young Turks
Sort of precipitate
In a way that leaves the rest of the government out of the decision
They in some Germans working together decide to Shell
Some Russian Port facilities in the Black Sea
Without getting the rest of the government's position
And then of course Russia declares war on turkey and boom there in
The Germans have been trying to set this up for a long time
They wanted turkey on their side
Which is strange
Because turkey is one of those Powers that's really having a hard time right now
And the Germans already have one of those
Allied to Austria-Hungary
Which yunnan for 5 months of War already look
Doughton
The Germans will take the saying
About their Austrian allies
That they are fettered to a corpse
Well now they're adding another corpse I mean you really have to admire how well Germany doesn this war considering
Did they have two of the weakest powers in Europe
Not just on their side
But requiring a lot of their help
But the Turks provide
An interesting
Are you
To the journey
It's not that they have an Army and Navy that's going to be real helpful
But the Turks control a nice
Trunk of what today we would call the Middle East
And by simply deciding to get into the war
Dayforce
The British and the French who have a lot of possessions in that area
To defend them
They've expanded
The battlefield
To include a whole bunch of areas
But nobody was fighting over before turkey
He got into the war
What's more
Turkey's historic
Anime
Is Russia
A Russia that is putting all their Manpower
The dealing with the Germans in the austro-hungarian then all of a sudden
South of all that fighting
They now have their historic enemy turkey in the war
Again it's not that they're so afraid of the Turk
It's they're afraid of taking any troops away from the main Battlefront
To defend that area at all
Same thing with the British and the French now they have to take troops away
From places where they're using them against the Germans
And use them elsewhere
So the Germans aren't really getting the Turkish armies help as much as they're getting
The fact that the people they're fighting
How to fight
Somewhere else
Now
For our purposes there's a wonderful little
Moment right at the beginning of turkeys involvement where
The highest-ranking figure in the Muslim World religious
Proclaims a Jihad
Against the allies
Britain France Russia Serbia
And this is an era where the Muslim world was was more united in a religious sense of me nowadays
It's more like
The Protestant version of Christianity where there's a lot of different religious leaders who
Kind of all have equal standing
At this time.
The guy who was running the religion from Turkey
Had
Not total
Control over their religion
3 carried a lot of weight and when the war breaks out on November 14th
He proclaims a holy war against
Britain France Serbia Russia
And this is big because
Britain France
And Russia all have
Huge
Muslim population
Germany's ambassador
To Turkey
Says that now
You know the British are going to burn up in Jihad
Whether or not that's what really happens
If your Britain and your friends and your Russia
You need to be concerned about that and now you need to divert forces
From other crucial fronts
To deal with this new dilemma
Turkey is
And has been for more than a hundred years known as the sick man of Europe
They've just bought
Two Wars before the first world war breaks out the first and second Balkan War
I'm lost
Most of those European possession
Penniless
It's a disaster they just bought two battleships
Which they had to ask their
Citizens
To essentially donate the money for they purchased them from Britain
And then when the war broke out Britain kept on
Which was another reason the church were not too happy with the Ally
Nonetheless
The fact that turkey is going to be in the war
Means that the British
Who am I
Controlled Egypt for some time now
Have to worry about it
Have to worry about the Suez Canal
Also
This is the era
Where oil is
Finally becoming important
In a right before the first world war breaks out of prison lays down its first ships that are going to burn oil
Instead of
Cole
And everybody is starting to see
Did not only is oil important
But the Middle East is a place that has a lot of
And now the Middle East is going up in flames
Some of those planes probably would have been very welcome
On the Eastern front at this
Point where the Russians and the Germans in the austro-hungarian they're locked in Mortal Kombat because it begins to free
At the end of the year as one might expect
They may be dealing with
In a rain and historic
Cold one of the coldest winters on memory on the Western Front
What's the coldest winters
In memory on the Western Front were pretty darn average on the Eastern
And the weather conditions slow everyone down
The Eastern commanders and Hindenburg and ludendorff also don't have enough troops to do anything truly MoMA
Meant to say
Begging falkenhayn in the Kaiser for them and they keep
Getting rebuff
The Russians
AR
Inapt
When they're attacking but they're very tough when they're defending so things tend to slow down and the Russians tend to go
Go on the defensive
The austro-hungarians are already almost done
In a 5 months into the war and they're fighting the last defensive that they will launch independently in the whole War
They already have
A giant Fortress with 150000 austro-hungarian troops in it
Surrounded by the Russians it's a bad situation
The weather slows everything down
And if you actually try to follow
The various battles going on
You'll notice that there is
Ate a rhythm to them that makes it difficult
For anything to ever be solved I mean one side moves forward the other side moves back and then you know they were verse course
Historian Peter Hart does a pretty good
Rundown of the rhythm of the Eastern front at this time
And sums up the way the
Infirst
Six months of War end
You know in
Delizia
And Poland and places like that
He writes quote
The Seesaw nature of the fighting in the east
Two steps forward three steps back
One step forward
What's becoming increasingly apparent to all along the line
In the north for all their efforts
The Russians only managed to hold onto a token sliver of East Prussia
In contrast they lost much of Russia and Poland to the German advance
What's the Strategic drawback of occupying this territory was such
It was not a particular disadvantage in the broader scheme of things
It was in the South against the austrians
That the Russians have made their biggest gains
Are they had overrun nearly all of Austrian Galicia
Justice on the Western Front
The scale of the forces involved have been incredible
By the end of the year 143 Russian divisions
Face 53 Austrian and 38 German division
Losses on all sides have been simply breathtaking
By the end of 1914 up to 750,000 Russian soldiers
500000 austro-hungarian and 140000 German to become casual
All this in just five frantic months of mayhem
And quote
It will await
A change in weather conditions
For that front heats up
Throughout this
Most inhumane of conf
There are tons of stories of
Prisoners being killed
And horrible things being done all over me when you have millions and millions of men involved in
Warfare
There are going to be
Stories
You know that run the gamut
The ones though that sort of
Reinforce
Know your connection
To humanity
Are there too and they deserve to be pointed out sometimes there on an individual level
Is a story from the West
Confronted I like right around the time of
He pray about a British soldier named Willie Frazier
Is wounded in the shoulder
Duck you know in place as the Germans overrun his position
And the stories recounted by author
Winston groom
Here's groom talking about
Frasier
Injured
On the bottle
Quote
His shoulder have been Shattered by shrapnel
There was fighting and killing all around and the Germans captured him
Having studied German in Frankfurt in 1909 he was astonished to hear a German Sergeant yell out an order
Where to shoot him
Willie yell to a German officer
How many officers spoke
Willie recognized his accent
How do you ask if he was from Frankfurt
When the officer replied that he was
Willie asked him in German
Don't you wish you were there now
The two men exchanged forced grins
And the officer ordered his men not to harm
And quote
You can find stories like that all throughout
People who shoemanity shines through on an individual
In a base on all sides by the way
No one had a monopoly on that
But there were times
When the humanity sort of jest
Burst
Fourth
And math
Spontaneously
None more famous
Maybe overrated some people say but I don't see how it
Can be overrated
Then what happened
It on Christmas Eve
Especially on the west
The conditions are horrible
It's freezing
You know your feet are
Stocking gruul mudwater
But you think can't get any worse and then it all freezes and you're stuck out there in the cold
And all the sudden the people on the Western Front
See something
Relatively unbelievable in a conflict where you have shells going on every second snipers picking off any
You want raises his head above the trench and then all the sudden
Soldiers reported
Hearing singing
And seeing
Weird
Colored light
The colored lights were off and coming
From the German trenches
Soldier
Julia skoczen
Was in one of those trenches
Opposite
The French
China conditions were horrible
Put on Christmas Eve
This is what
Quote
Christmas in the trenches
It was bitterly cold
We procure to Pinetree for there were no fir trees to be had
We decorated the tree with candles and cookies
We had imitated the snow with wadding
Christmas trees were burning everywhere in the trenches in at midnight
All the trees were lifted onto the parapet
With your burning candle
And along the whole line German soldiers began to sing Christmas songs in chorus
Old owl blissful
Holdout joyous
Mercy bringing Christmas time
Hundreds of men he writes were singing the song in that fearful wood
Not a shot was fired
The French had ceased firing along the whole line
That night I was with a company that was only Five Paces away from the enemy
The Christmas candles were Burning Brightly
And were renewed again and again
For the first time we heard no shots
From everywhere throughout the forest he writes
One could hear powerful Carol's come floating over
Peace on Earth
The Frenchie says left their trenches
And stood on the parapet without any fear
There they stood quite overpowered by emotion
And all of them with cap in hand
We too had issued from our trenches
We exchange gifts with the French
Chocolate cigarettes Etc they were all laughing and so where we
Why we did not know
Then everybody went back to his trench and incessantly
The Carroll resounded
Evermore solemnly Evermore longingly o thou Bliss
And quote
Private William
Quinton
In the trenches
On Christmas Eve
On the British side
Wrote about a similar situation farther down the line
Quote
All around us lay about 3 in of snow a typical picture postcard Christmas
Things were very quiet
That peace and goodwill to all men feeling seem to be in the air
We could hear the German still strafing of Ypres way but the next night Christmas Eve
Even up there with much quieter
Something in the direction of the German lines caused us to rub our eyes and look again
Here and there
Showing just above their parapet
We could see very faintly would look like very small colored lights
What was this
What did some prearranged signal and the Forerunner of an attack
Was it to make us curious
And that's expose ourselves to a sudden breaking of machine-gun Fire
We were very suspicious and we were discussing the strange move of the enemy
When something even stranger happen
The Germans were actually singing
Not very loud
But there was no mistaking it
We began to get interest
The enemy at least we're going to enjoy themselves as much as the circumstances would permit
Suddenly
Across the snow-clad no man's land
A strong clear voice rang out
Singing the opening lines of Annie Laurie
It was sung in perfect English and we were spelled out
No other sound but this unknown singers voice
To us it seemed like the war had suddenly stopped
Stop to listen to this song from one of the enemy
Not a sound from Friend or Foe and is the last notes died away
A spontaneous Outburst of clapping a rose from our trenches encore
Poodle French
And quote
All along the line
The two sides
To have this interesting moment where they
Began to emerge From The Trenches little by little
You know a place where they couldn't stick a finger up
Without having a shot off
Just hours before
Everybody must have been so incredibly Brave to try
But once I would raise themselves up a little bit in the other side with raised themselves up a little bit more
Until both sides
In this hellish environment where nobody could go anywhere near
In the open-air
We're standing apart from each other
Gazing
Right at the enemy in no man's land
Find on Chris
Private William Quinton
Quote
Has daylight trapped in
We were surprised to see the Germans waist-high out of their trenches
Gazing across at us with impunity
Imagine the position
Where is yesterday the mere sight of a bit of field gray uniform would have caused a dozen British rifles to crack
He was the enemy
In full view of us gazing serenely across no-man's-land at us
And we had him
To wash in the front line the whole world to change
We could take stock of our surroundings at our leisure
At 9 precisely the German burying party climbed From The Trenches shovels and picks on their shoulders
Advanced about 10 yards in our Direction and waited expectantly
A word from our company officer
And our party were soon out
The officers looked on
Apparently conversing
The digging party soon lost interest in their task and before long were busy fraternizing
Cigarettes were being exchanged
And they seem to be enjoying themselves immensely
Needless to say before very long we in the trenches were soon out on top
Sauntering about the snow
But keeping this side of our wire entanglement
Likewise the Germans
For the whole of that day and for many days to come
Friend and foe mixed freely out on no man's land
Except for the fact that a few of the enemy could speak a little English we found the language difficulty of bar to conversation
But we may do with signs and gestures
I remember distinctly German holding out an open box of chocolates for me to take one
The Germans wanted to play as a football match on no man's land
But our officers would not allow it
And quote
There are reports.
British and German troops engaging in soccer matches
Up and down the line
It was an amazing spontaneous
Outburst of
Humanity
And it's so appalled
The higher leadership
But they made sure
In future Christmases
Nothing like this would ever be allowed again
If you thought the war was bad
It's about to get worse
And I'll let Winston Churchill
He
In a leadership position during the
As part of the war
Set up 1915
Time when he says
Man lost control
The conflict
And forces took over
He wrote quote
The year 1915 was fated to be disastrous to the cause of the allies
And of the whole world
Spider mistakes of this year the opportunity was lost of confining the conflagration within limits
Wichita with normous we're not on control
There after the fire roared on till it burned itself out
Thereafter events past very largely outside the scope of conscious choice
Governments and individuals conformed to the rhythm of the tragedy
And swayed and staggered forward and helpless viola
Slaughtering and squandering on ever-increasing scales
Till injuries were Rod to the structure human society which a century will not face
And which may conceivably prove fatal to the present civilization
13 January 1915
The terrific Affair was still not unmanageable
It could have been grasping human hands
And brought to rest in righteous and fruitful victory
Before the world was exhausted
Before the nations were broken
Before the empires were shattered to pieces
Before Europe was ruined
It was not to be
He writes
Mankind was not to escape so easily from the catastrophe in which it involved itself
Pride was everywhere to be humbled
And nowhere to receive its satisfaction
No Splendid Harmony was to Crown the wonderful achievements
No prize to reward the sacrifices of the combatant
Victory was to be bought so dear as to be almost indistinguishable from defeat
It was not to give even security to the victors
There never was to be the silence following the great words of peace
To the convulsions of the struggle must exceed the impotent turmoil of the aftermath
Noble hopes
Hi comradeship Inglorious during rain every nation Toledo only to disappointment
Dissolution
And prostration
The sufferings and impoverishment of people's might arrest their Warfare the collapse of the defeated might still the
Cannonade
But their hatreds continue on a PS
And their quarrels are still on set
The most complete Victory ever gained in arms
Espanol to solve the European problem
How to remove the dangers which produce the war
And quote
The war was entering a new phase
Buffets
A stalemate
What do you do to break the stalemate
That was the main challenge facing commanders on all sides
At 1915 rolls around
And you know later in the war
The Allied generals especially will get labeled
It was butchers
Blockhead
Some people who can't think their way out of a paper bag
And in some of that's Justified later in the conflict but we have to cut them quite a lot of slack early on because
Leave Western Front in the trench warfare and everything begins to solidify all of these generals on all sides
You're confronted with circumstances that there are no metrics for
There is no data on how you deal with this
They have to learn they have to experiment and then they have to look at the data afterwards the problem is
Is in this conflict
Any experimentation in the military Laboratory
Human beings are the lab rats
And you learn at the
Of human Carnage
Now
The Allies are more willing to do this they have more Lab Rats to play with in this becomes
Huge feature in the early part of 1915 because
If you are Sir John French the British
Or if you are
Justice shop
The French Commander
You know that if this thing has devolved from a wild swinging boxing encounter in the first round just something that small
More like a wrestling match where both combatants are
Holding each other in a death grip
But that works in your favor
You're the stronger comeback
You have more man you are more industrial power you control the Seas
If it's going to go that way you're going to win
That you may not want to have to be as hurt as you may have to be to make that work
Worst case scenario long-term
You're going to win that in cash
It's the German commands
Sanders that are forced to think outside the box
Because they're not
The problem is
Is the box that they have to think outside of
Is the one that was worked on for decades before the first world war came out
To create
Laws of war
Humanitarian restrictions on what you could do
Ways to pray
Protect civilians non-combatants and even combatants from
Your things that were considered to be
Unsportsmanlike or
Extra horrific more horrific than it needed to be
Remember in the first episode we talked about things like The Hague
Conference
Ways to make war
Conform to international law
The problem was
The Germans in the Central Powers were now in that
Position that everyone kind of knew was going to happen
You know when you wrote those laws of war which is
They have to decide whether or not
Adhering to international law
Is worth losing a war
Can you begin to see
Both sides
Try to use
Asymmetrical Warfare and new technology to break the stalemate and a lot of what use are the very things
Prohibited
Annie's pre-war agreement
A perfect example starts in late 1914 when German warships
Open fire
On British coastal town
Kill more than a hundred
British citizens
Becomes a wonderful propaganda tool
For the Allies to cite the baby killers of Germany
But that's nothing compared to what's coming in 1950
The first thing that happens is a
Absolute benchmark
Arkin
Warfare
When in January
The German start
Really
Trying to get involved in what we call today strategic bomb
No aircraft have been in use since the very moment the war started
One of these
Excuses that the Germans used
For attacking France was they said that some plane had come from France and bombs nurenberg at the very moment that the Warsaw
Started
Which is probably nonsense
But it shows that there were airplanes involved in the conflict from the very beginning but anyways.
Really didn't involve the laws of war
All of the Air Force's put together in the world when the war started had less than 500 plane
What planes they did have
Turned out to be wonderfully valuable tools for reconnaissance which
Was what
Air power has been used for
Earlier than this time even in the American Civil War there were hot air balloons
That they would use to see what the enemy was doing in the distance
Planes were wonderful for that
They also turned out to be fantastic in the more technologically sophisticated armies
It was known as artillery spot
And that allowed Your Guns to shoot at Targets that the Gunners couldn't see
And you could shoot for example
In a Faraway over a hill and if it was an airplane there they could tell you what was happening and that was
Interesting enough to trying to explain without radios and everything what was happening but they could tell you that your shot.
Tell short or long or was too far to the left or too far to the right
And this gave a huge Advantage the armies that can make that work
Less sophisticated armies like the Russians couldn't
And hence were relegated to shooting at things they could own
Only see you at
But this early on in the fighting you can see how primitive Things Are
Because early on when aircraft
Wooden counter enemy aircraft
Didn't have any way to do anything about
And they were
Taking handgun
These Pilots up in the plane with them
And trying to take potshots with their pistols at the enemy air pilot
Let me know
Sophisticated things are at this stage in the war
It's only when
The Germans run up against the in a trench warfare in the Western Front and they're forced to start looking for things
That might help them your break the stalemate
They noticed they have the greatest Zeppelin
Fleet in the world
Zeppelins of course are lighter than air
Blimps dirigibles those kinds of things
And before the war the Germans have built 10 or 12 of them
And had them sort of sitting aside when the war started which scared
Their enemies
Probably more than they should have they sort of had a fleet in being role where
People like Churchill and Britain at the beach
And worried about
What are the German Zeppelin
Mike the German Zeppelin
That was probably out of all proportion to what the German Zeppelins could do
The Germans try to use them at the beginning of the war for example
Renovated
Belgium and had to try to deal with those forts a couple of zeppelins
Play Wolverine trying to drop some bombs
When the stalemate on the Western Front reaches its real
Uno
Calcification moment
The German start looking for ways to use these tools that they have
And there is no metrics
Just like to run any metrics on the Western Front to try to figure out how to break that Stanley there's no metrics that will tell you what these Zeppelin
Will do if a bomb
Targets in another country
Was a British theorist
Who suggested that the very power
S&S
The people
You don't need another country in their home country feel when the enemy is able to with impunity
Fly over your territory and bomb you
He suggested that if they bombed the civilians with confetti
It wouldn't make any difference it would still
Damage their morale terribly because it's a feeling like you can't be defended even at home
The place that most people tend to feel safe at this stage in military history
They were people arguing
The German High command saying
For all we know these Zeppelins could win the war
And before the war at these
In a big conferences that were part of trying to come up with International laws of war
You're there were rules discussed about how bombing should work I mean should you have to give the city that you're going to vomit
Chance to surrender before we bombed them
And
Lest you think only the Germans were doing this both the British and the French were sending
In a small bombing raids over into Germany
And Germany was sending small bombing raids with aircraft that were holding little hand bombs out of the open-top
Pits and dropping them but nothing significant
Nothing like sending large
Numbers of Zeppelin
All together
Embalming
January 1915 the Germans launched
The first one of those
They go after
Comport
Facilities
Britain
The problem with this is the same problem they're going to have any early second world war which is you may say you're trying to hit military
Target but the accuracy is so terrible you're lucky to fly over a city the size of London
And be able to hit it
Buddy's Port facilities end up being
An example of an early example of when civilians get hit
With these weapons will start bombing London in May 19th
And of course it becomes a propaganda Victory right away for the allies
Again label the Germans baby killers
Which make the Germans defensive as you might imagine there's a wonderful letter from a German Zeppelin leader
To his mother
Trying to
Explain to her what apparently he's already tried to
Explain to her before
But this isn't
The evil stop that this is Modern Warfare and yes it's not like you know knights fighting a duel
But at the same time the Situation's different than win tonight
It's fought duels
People in the homefront are no longer innocent
In Modern Warfare
They are the ones who make the weapons
That the soldiers require
To fight if the soldiers can't break through on the Western Front what if you could
Prevent one side from building the shelves necessary to keep the war going
This is where the idea
Of the home phone
First really take
6 hole
And it becomes the justification for attack
Packing civilians in other country
There's a letter that the German Zeppelin leader writes to his mother
Trying to make his
Action City apparently feels guilty over himself
Sound morally okay
Quote
We who strike the enemy where his heart beats
I've been slandered as baby killer
And murderers of women
What we do is repugnant even to us
Necessary
Very necessary
Nowadays there's no such animal is a non-combat
Modern Warfare is total warfare
A soldier cannot function at the front without the factory worker
The farmer and all the other providers behind him
You and I mother have discussed this subject
And I know you understand what I say
My man are brave and honorable
Their causes holy
How can they send while doing their Duty
Is what we do is fight
They may frightfulness be Germany's salvation
And quote
This
Same attitude
Will be applied
To the other
Hearts of warfare the
Rear their ugly head in 1915
Because of the needs of the situation I mean flamethrowers are one of the technological weapons
UniFirst appear in 1950 and again using science
In ways to try to
Create opening
Weather actively on the battlefield or strategically in the war itself
Another perfect example of this from the first World War
Has to do with another one of these new Weapons Systems
Challenged
Angel theories in Orthodoxy
One of them had to do
With rules concerning Naval blockade
When the first world war breaks out the British and the French navy literally sweep the Seas clean of German ship
Military & merchant ship
Disordered Naval blockade was
One of the main things that Britain could offer early in the war they certainly were going to offer millions and millions of troops they didn't have millions
The troops to have the greatest Navy in the world
And just like in Napoleon's time
On a strong Continental power takes hold you shut down their merchant ship and you close their ports you don't allow them to get any
Materials resources anything from anyone else if you can help it
Another word
International laws concerning what you were allowed to keep from
Combatants you weren't supposed to keep
Food stops are the
The needs of everyday life you can keep weapons in those kind of things but the British and the French pushed those rules way past abound
Common sense
And work
In a classifying things like cotton Fabrics is war necessary material they weren't really going to allow anything through
Now
For all of human history
There's been sort of a of a
Calculus you could count on
And that's that the weaker Naval power
Cannot blockade the stronger Naval Power by sea
How could you write
Your ships try to blockade a country like Great Britain they'll just send their Navy out to sweep your ships off the sea
What if your ships aren't
On the sea
What is the ships that are trying to blockade
And island nation like Britain nienstedt
Under the sea
The Germans had summary
This is not a brand new invention
When did finally reached a stage of Effectiveness where
The British were to find out
At the old Naval orthodoxies about what a weaker Naval power could and couldn't do
A change
There was no answer at this point in history
To the submarine
Surface vessels could not detect them unless the submarine
Surface they couldn't destroy them
Germany had a lot less submarines than Britain and France but here's the thing
Britain and France couldn't do anything with their submarines
They couldn't use their
Submarines against German Merchant shipping because there wasn't any German Merchant shipping about five minutes after the war breaks
The surface fleets of France and Britain thought of that
But Germany surface lead which is one of the
Things that have precipitated the war one of the many causes it's always cited is the naval arms race between
Britain and Germany
State import for the most part
Knight of the British know the Germans were willing to risk
He's enormously expensive
And hard to replace surface ships that were they would have called capital
Battleships
Unbelievably expensive ones mean for example the British had just commissioned the class of ships known as the Queen Elizabeth class battleship
Which was so good in the first world war they still be very effective units in the Second World War
But if a cheap Little Submarine could sink one of those ships with a torpedo
That's nothing to any Naval commanders are willing to
Risk and so all of a sudden everybody's being so careful with their big ships that it leaves openings for The Little Ships to make
Everyone thought at the beginning of the war
But these submarines would be used in the military sense against other warships
By February 1915
The Germans are now using them against Merchant
Shipping and all of a sudden the greatest Navy in the world finds that they can't defend their merchant shipping
Because of a new technological creation
Or a weaker Naval power has the potential to turn the tables
On the best weapon
Did the great Naval Powers have
Blockading weaker Navy
Powers
And the British were doing a very good job of keeping goods and
Weapons from flowing into Germany by sea
Are finding out that the Germans had the capability to do the same thing back to them
Now the big issue
Will surface if you'll pardon the pun
Around whether or not
The Warfare should follow the old famous rules of the sea or not
The old famous rules of the sea
Where did you didn't destroy
Merchant shipping non-military vessels without letting them know
That piracy
You basically are supposed to
Give them a message and say we're seizing your ship let them
Take their people off the ship on lifeboats and stuff and then you can either sink the vessel that you
You know more after or you can take it as a prize and capture it
The problem is when a submarine to try to do this
It open the damn up
To being destroyed and the British played this up they started putting guns on all these Merchant ships
So if the Germans came up and did what they were supposed to do
Tell the merchant ship captured your prize of War now get your lifeboats out get your people off the ship and will sink it
They'd often pull the canvas off a gun and start shooting at the now vulnerable submarine cuz it had to surface in order to
Comply with the international laws of war right
Did the Germans were having these debates
In 1915
About whether or not they should do that at all
Maybe they should just sink these vessels
Without surfacing or warning them or anything
But this again would look like the Germans were
You know the ones outside international law
We're the ones who were the bad guy
And worse
Then that
They risk alienating neutral powers the most important of which was the United States which was a very
A maritime power
Huge in the trade and by the way at this point in the war if you wanted to say who is gaining from the first World War
It's the United States because
One of the things that all these powers do
When they find out they can't produce enough shells and weapons and War materials to keep the war going
Is borrow money from the United States
And then turn around and spend that borrowed money
On stopping production from the United States
Often called the Great neutral
The United States just wants to be able to keep delivering your stuff word has to go
They're already getting tents with the British
In a searching their ships and saying that this ship for that ship can't dock at this point of that port
When the German start
Sinking Merchant vessels
Sometimes those Merchant vessels have Americans
On them
In early 1915
One of those vessels was called the Lusitania
The Lusitania if you want to think of it
Inner to conceptualize what we're talking about here
Is very much like the Titanic
An extremely large ocean liner
A passenger ship this is how people got from the old world to the new world and back again across the Atlantic in the day
He's before transatlantic Air flight
Now
Controversy has raged ever since
The German submarine
Which open fire on the loose
Betania sank that ship
On whether or not it was a legitimate Target of War
It have munitions
If it did
Supposedly they could sink it
Is a lot of evidence that suggested did and some conspiracy theories out there that suggests that people like Winston Churchill
Assured that it did
So that it would be another
In nail in the coffin he was starting to construct that would eventually get the United States into the war more than a hundred Americans
Turn on the Lusitania.
At various times in the war
The Germans would start up what was called unrestricted
Submarine warfare
With a shot of anything that looked like an enemy ship of any
And other times where they would stop
Because there was a huge debate within the halls of German leadership
Over whether or not they gained more or lost more when they did this
If the United States comes into the war it's a huge loss
But it's one of the few ways that
In 1915
Vacancy
But they can bring Britain
To its knees
They can starve thataylaa
In ways that the British never could have imagined before the war
Because before the war they thought you had to have a bigger Navy to do that
Technology and turn the table
On the greatest naval power in history
Perhaps
The most iconic
Asymmetrical Warfare
Of this.
Has to do with something that was a big worry at the Hague conferences in the late 1800s and early 1900s
Something that
New shows the desperation of the Germans at this stage in the war that they would Resort
Involves the use
What the Hague conference call
Asphyxiating
Gases
Everyone is realized by the late 1800s
That the modern chemical industry as we would recognize it today it come of age
Meaning we're all sort of explosive gunpowder's and everything
They were so much more explosive than
You know I've been the case in Napoleon
Time less than a century before hand so everyone was aware of the possibilities
Gunpowder and explosives were just more powerful versions of weapons that have been used for a very long time
The chemical industry made possible the use of weapons
3 never been used
No one knew
And what the effects if they were used would be and so at the Hayden conference in 1899
The issue was addressed
The conference outlawed the use of quote
Poison or poisoned weapons
Arms
Projectiles or material calculated to cause unnecessary suffering
And projectile design for the diffusion of asphyxiating
Or deleterious gases
And quote
Buddy 1915
Germany's looking at all these laws of war
Completely different land
As we said the trade-off
Between
Follow international law
Or lose the war
What's more they're dealing with this front as we said on the Western Front that had solidified an interesting way
You said you have a
Continuous trench system
From the Swiss border all the way
You know up to the
Ocean
And the interesting part is
A lot of that territory is not really good fighting ground
A lot of its to Marshall a lot of us to Forest did a lot of it
The Germans are in such an amazingly strong position you'd be an idiot to challenge them
Which leaves the same few spots as good areas to launch offensive
Your campaign
Which means
That those areas but
Become the most horrific battlefields
In human history
Because they basically don't move very much for the entire War
And
The same ground is
Cloud up by artillery shells over and over again
People that died
In some of these places are never buried
And so you have
A Charnel House of Horrors
Of people who just been killed the other day
People that were killed a month ago people that were killed a year ago all in the same spot and you was the soldier have to leave in the
This environment
Kinetochores ignores
The more mundane aspects which is if you are trapped in a trench
And you can't move without being shot
What do you go to the bathroom
Early on in the combat
British soldiers were talking about taking
The German helmets with the spikes on them as souvenirs for the war but quickly realized that the best thing you can do with those things
Is use them as a receptacle
For the call of Nature and then toss it as far away from the trenches possible so that the smell of thousands of men doing this
In a confined space over
Years
Doesn't overwhelm you was reset certain Battlegrounds like Ypres
Will become famous
For their smile and you will be able to smell them before you get anywhere near them
Canadians are arriving in early 1915 in numbers
And they take over some of these battlefields
You know where
Nothing has changed I mean no one's going out and buried anybody that was one of the things by the way during the Christmas Truce has
That we talked about
It was the number one thing both sides tried to do which tells you how crazy
The smell in the situation and I'll horrifying must have been but
They jump out of these trenches and start to try to bury these bodies that have been out there for months
Canadian soldier on the Western Front arriving at the trenches of Ypres
Early 1950
Trenches that have been occupied by
In a Gurkha forces from around India
Anna Canadian Sergeant name
SV Britain
Describes
His
In welcome
To the Western Front
In suitably horrific
Terms
He says quote
Left at 6:30 p.m. for Reserve trenches
And reached our Reserve dugouts VST Julia
Just rathole
One hell of an accommodation
Got to the trenches as a fatigue party with steak and sandbags
I know there were Reserve trenches
They were so rotten
No trench is it all in Parts just isolated mount
Found Germans feet sticking up through the ground
The gurk is it actually used human bodies instead of sandbags
Right beside the stream where we were working with a bodies of two dead since November last
1 face downward in full marching order with his kid on his back
He died game
Stench something awful and dead all around
Water rats and made a home of their decomposed bodies
Visiting the barbed wire with Ray ordinary wire strung across
Quit about 1 a.m.
Came back to our Dugout and found them on fire
Add to Market St Julien
And put up in a roofless house
Not a roof left on anything in the whole place
Found our sack of food have been stolen and we were family
Certainly a most unlucky day for I lost my cherished pipe
Bad at 4 a.m.
And quote
Call the Canadian start the battlefield
And the traditional aspects of what war had already come to be by that time
Where's bad as it was going to get
They were frightfully mistake
Can fight this battle that will be called the Second Battle of Ypres
Is the first time
That the major gas attack happen
And the Canadians will be the
Reason that it doesn't
Turn out to be a huge tragedy for the Allied cause
The other reason will be that the Germans had no idea
That their attack was going to be this successful in this becomes a pattern with all this new technology
Very often
The Commanders
Are trying to figure out whether this new technology is going to be something that's effective and useful
So they try it out on a small scale not really expecting to make good use of it
And because of the sheer shock of the new stuff
It proved wonderfully effective
But it can't be exploited because the generals who authorized it to use hadn't planned to explode if they were hoping to test
Get out a little bit and then if it was good they'll use it later
But by the time later comes around the other side has figured out countermeasure
Gas work exactly like the
And before it was used
The German High command just as they did with submarine warfare
Debated whether or not this was a good thing intensely
As we said
There were all these
Laws of the Hague conference it set down saying you couldn't use the stuff
And some of the German leaders that said we sign these papers and others had found little loopholes like legal loopholes it said
Couldn't use shells
But nothing said anything about
Just taking the lids off of
In a containers
But had chlorine gas in them
Historian Eric dhoombros rights
Quote
The same kind of murderously cold wartime mentality that would terminate 1200 civilians
Aboard the Lusitania two weeks later
Did not allow however
Perspective international law
German legal experts advise General falkenhayn that the attack could be justified because the gas was released
From containers
In fact
Just to save artillery shells
And not from projectiles
On the other side of the debate
Duke Albrecht averton Berg commander of the 6th Army
Argue that unleashing this new weapon would not only be immoral
But also dubious military value
For the allies with the wind normally at their backs would probably send 10 times as much gas on the germ
German positions
Karl Von einem of the third Army agreed
And then Express additional worries over the quote
Tremendous Scandal and the quote that would compromise and disgrace Germany in the eyes of the world
Quote War has nothing to do with chivalry anymore he wrote
The higher civilization Rises the more vile man becomes
And quote
If anybody still had
Any of those old
19th century truly going back to ancient times
Versions of the Romantic glorious heroic duel that they've been raised to believe that war was
Operation
Disinfectant
Will cure them
I'm such a little
That will be the German name for the
The program
And the code word
To start the operation
Will be God punish England
The operation balls
Almost sick
Mm cylinder
Containing chlorine gas a by-product
Of the German die manufacturing industry that the Germans are planted in the soil carefully overtime around the battlefield at E3
In August 1915
They took the tops off the container
When the wind was right
A letter
Chlorine gas
Blow across the battlefield toward the Allied trenches
Which were occupied
By french-algerian forces which involved
French troops
And Algerian troops
And also the newly-arrived Canadian
I didn't know what to make
But they figured out pretty quickly
It was
Hell on Earth
As one Indian soldier would ride his face
Father after work
This isn't War
This is the end of the world
The end of the world
To some of these p
People at the Second Battle of Ypres
Look like a cloud
Greenish-yellow gas
It was floating across the battlefield so slowly
You could actually walk ahead of it
Because the soldiers didn't know what they were looking at most of them didn't move
Until I hit them
Again historian
Eric Dorn brose
Stretching 6000m along opposing line
And bellowing high up into the air I think ghastly looking green yellow cloud of gas moved eerily and
Threateningly with the breeze across no-man's-land
The gaseous monstrosity took on a pinkish Hue from certain angles as the descending Western Sun show
I'm through it
To compound the shock and Terror German heavy artillery began to lay down a pounding barrage
Two French Colonial divisions
And a Canadian division were caught completely unaware
Quote
Take a look at this
Said one Canadian artillery Observer to his Superior as he stared through binoculars it was coming towards them
There's something funny going on
Any dough for cover from the incoming shells
But just then the wind shifted
Compressing the gas cloud over the Algerian
Whose forward units were in golf
The soldiers grab their throats
Choking and writhing in excruciating pain from the Searing chlorine gas
In minutes
Many hundreds lay drowning in fluids given off by the lungs
Seeing this
Others panic
Drop their rifles and ran
Leaving a 6 kilometer Gap in the line
And quote
Private William Quinton
A British soldier
Experienced his first gas attack
Only about a week after the first time it has been used
That Affair had caused
The high command
To tell the troops to soak
Flannel in water and just put it over their noses is a
Cheap easy attempt to try to forestall the gas
But none of these soldiers knew what they were facing until they actually
I had a gas attack hit them
Which Clinton had hit him on May 1st
Quote
Suddenly over the top of our Frontline
We saw what look like clouds of thin gray smoke
Rolling slowly along with a slight wind
It's under the ground reaching to the height of eight or nine feet and approached
So slowly that a man walking could have kept ahead of it
Gas
The word quickly passed around
Even though it had no Terror for us
For we had not yet tasted it
From our haversacks
We hastily drew the flannel belts
Soak them in water and tie them around our mouths and noses
Suddenly through the communication trench came rushing a few khaki clad figures
Your eyes glaring out of their heads
Their hands tearing at their throats as they came on
Some stumbled and fell in Lay writhing at the bottom of the trench
Choking and gasping whilst those following trampled over them
If ever man were raving mad with Terror these men were
What was left of our section still crouched at the support into the communication Trench
Are Frontline judging from the number of men who just come from it had been abandoned
And we not waited for the first Russian German
But they did not
Come see our biggest enemy was now within a few yards of us
And in the form of a cloud of gas
We caught our first whiff of it
No words of mine can ever describe my feelings as we inhaled the first mouth
WeChat
Spit and cough
My lungs felt as though they were being burnt out
But they were going to burst
Red hot needles were being thrust into my eyes
The first impulse was to run
We just seen men running just certain death and new it
Rather than stay and be choked into a slow and agonizing death
It was one of those occasions when you do not know what you were doing
The man who stayed with no braver than the man who ran away
We crouched there terrified
Stupify
A large shell burst on the parapet
Just where we were sheltered
We were almost buried beneath the falling Earth
Young Addington a chap about my own age
Was screaming at the top of his voice and trying to free his buried legs
He got free and before we could stop him he rushed off god-knows-where
We then saw the reason for his screen
His left arm was blown off above the elbow
He left a trail of blood over my tunic is he climbed over me in a mad rush to get away
And quote
Clinton and his unit of Canadians
Will block
Heroic
Play the hole that develops in the line keeping the Germans from breaking through
German hadn't expected to break through the entire reason for this gas attack was to experiment with the gas
And to cover the fact that the Germans were removing troops for use on the Eastern Front
The German High command had no idea it was going to be this successful
And no one had any idea how horrifying
Private William Quinton in this unit will move up to the front line
Animal experience
The aftermath
Of what the gas attack today
The people who first encounter cat
Hero quote
Black in the face their tunics and shirt-fronts torn open at the NEX in their last desperate fight for breath
Many of them quite still
While others were still wriggling and kicking in the agonies of the most awful death I've ever seen
Some were wounded in the bargain
And there gaping wounds lay open
Blood still oozing from them
One poor devil was tearing at his throat with his hands
I doubt if you knew or felt
Did he had only one hand
And the other was just a stump where the hand should have been
This Stumpy worked around his throat as if his hand was still there
In the blood from it was streaming over his bluish black face and neck
A few minutes later he was still
Except for occasional shutters as he breathed his last
And quote
As I've said before in this program and I think I will say many times more
This is the most horrifying sustained
Situation
Terrible
I've ever seen soldiers forced to endure
And millions
Millions of people will get to experience this before the end of
Conflict
My own grandfather
Bagasse
On the Western Front
And he was never the same after
The use of poison gas
Is a defining moment
Quentin Nesconset
One that puts
The Final End stamp
19th century Victorian romantic ideals
You can't pretend anymore when human beings are being treated
Either way you would treat
Ants with a can of raid or some other insect
Decide
Even before gas is used
The times of London the great paper in Britain
In November 1914 will run
An article
Which
Seems amazing by modern standards but of course we're in a post
First and second World War era now
Those people were coming into this conflict with certain ideals and understandings of what war was going to be like
And the trenches
And the
Continual death for no apparent gain
Head shaking their whole view of what war was all about
In November 1914 the times ran this
Peace quote
All the spectacular side of the war has gone
Never to reappear
Trenches and always trenches
And within range of the concealed guns invisibility the supreme law
Day after day The Butchery of the Unknown by the Unseen
War has become stupid
The screen on the Infantry is tremendous
And it is endless
At the cost of thousands of lives a few hundred yards maybe gain
But rarely indeed does even the most brilliant attack produce anything
Fresh troops brought up under cover of a tremendous artillery fire which opens up by surprise me effective
Breech but only with heavy loss can such an attack be carried through
And quote
That little
Run-down about how War has become stupid now
Accurately describes
What the entire year of 1915 on the Western Front will be like
Nobody is going to move
At all
An amazing numbers of people are going to die
In efforts to gain
Now in the defense of the generals who ordered these efforts to gain nothing
They have to figure out how to do things including experimentation
To our minds
You would think you would stop after a while but these people had to figure out how to win the warm and they didn't even know for example
How to get through
The ever-expanding fields and barbed wire that crop up between the two enemy trench line
You have to have battles to Simply see what kind of artillery blows up enough of the wire to create a pack
Have for your troops to attack through
This is lessons being learned
At an Incredible cost but there's really no other way to do it
It's fascinating to look at pictures already in 1915
Six to eight months after the war has started
And see how this. Has become sort of an estuary
Between the 19th and 20th Century
Will you see the combination of the two centuries blending I mean
When the war starts you a Cavalry that is indistinguishable from Napoleon's
Cuirassier is going off to war with gleaming breastplates and horsehair
Helmets and Sabers and
Heel spurs and white gloves
And now you have gas and soon you're going to have
You know German Cavalry Lancers for example as soon as 1916 rolls around they start having the same helmet that the Germans were
Using the second world war the Stahl helm
And you have no Cavalry with lances and a Stahl Helm and a gas mask and it's the perfect example
All of the two errors
Blending
So like I said a historical estuary
Hugo from
Let Napoleonic
Feeling of war with French soldier going off into the conflict with bright red pants
You know in 6 to 8 months later we have gas we have flamethrowers
We have hundreds of guns at a time firing on Battlefield we have trenches barbed wire snipers every
Freeware
This is not what anybody thought was going to happen
Anna Begins
To unhinge a lot of people
Which is something that
Is new to The Human Experience
At least
As far as
The modern
European armies are concerned
People begin to go insane
To lose their mind to have their nerve shadow
This is something that I said no just War
Does something that seems
Unbelievable
The ability to take
One of the most stressful situations human beings ever find themselves in
And make it worse
Is all war
Psychologically challenging isn't it
Made the first World War
More difficult
Then almost any other major conflict you can think of
It's not just the changes in Warfare although that significant
How long the soldiers
We're forced
To deal with it
Take one of the worst battles in human history to be a soldier in
The famous
Second Punic War battle of cannae Right Where
Hannibal and his carthaginians famously surround maybe 80000 Romans
And then spend the entire afternoon
And slaughtering them by hand
Cutting their way into the center of this
Crowd of doomed men who have to wait all day
In the most unbelievably
Disorienting environment you can think of they can't hear anything they can't see anything there's dust everywhere but they know what's coming
You're told by the ancient writer that's so terrible
It when the carthaginians cut their way into the center of this mass of doomed men
They will find that some Roman soldiers
Back so tightly that they couldn't even raise their hands in the crowd of people
Just sunk to their knees
Dug a little hole with their hands put their head in the hole and covered it up
Committing suicide
Because either they had lost their mind
Or they come to the conclusion
Why wait
That's that's supposed to show you how terrible the situation is
In the first World War
You begin to see very quickly
People who are
Unhinged
These soldiers
Trapped at the Battle of cannae we're having a historic
Bad day
But it was one day
A week or two before that battle they were in relatively little danger
If they survived a week or two after that battle same thing
The soldiers in the Great War
Had no such luxury
They had to deal with these circumstances
Day after day
And after this war military psychologist looking into the phenomenon of what will later be known as shell shock
Will determine
Under the conditions the soldiers were fighting in it doesn't matter how Brave you were
Eventually
A WeChat a different
Threshold we could stand but eventually anyone would lose
Think about what's involved
And you begin to understand why first
Take
The shelling itself
Which is
Something that
Is it really impossible for any of us to understand there are very few people living that have ever
Been through the kinds of shelling that these World War 1 soldiers routinely had to deal with
And it's
Very hard to describe
One of the traditional kinds of shelling in that war was something that came to be known as Drum Fire
Drumfire
Is so named because it sounds like a drum roll
I'm instead of you just hearing the drum being tapped at that speed each one of those things represent the shell going off
How quickly the shelter Landing
Ernst Junger
Don't we quota. The author of the storm is still one of the most unusual Soldier by the way in the first world war because
He kind of like
The Wharf
Any kind of saw in a positive benefits to it you know so it's really uplifting side of War
And he was about as Brave as any Soldier you will ever find lost his composure
Under artillery fire
Explains a situation
Ray comes Under Fire
And just loses his mind temporarily you know this again one of the strongest
People mentally in the first world war that we know about and younger says quote
We fell out in extended order and lay down expectedly in a series of flattish depressions
Did some predecessors of ours had scooped out of the ground
Powerball conversations were suddenly cut off
Buy a marrow freezing cry
20 yards behind us
Clumps of Earth World up out of a white cloud and smacked into the BIOS
The crash echo through the woods
Stricken eyes look at each other
Bodies press themselves into the ground with a humbling sensation of powerlessness
To do anything else
Explosion followed explosion
Choking gases drifted over the undergrowth
Smoke obscured the Treetops
Trees and branches Came Crashing to the ground screams
We leaped up and ran blindly
Chased by lightning and crushing air pressure from tree to tree
Looking for cover
Skirting around giant tree trunks like frightened game
A Dugout where many men have taken shelter
And which I too was running towards took a direct hit that ripped up the planking and sent heavy Timber spinning through the air
Like a couple of squirrels having Stones thrown at them the NCO and I dodged panting around a huge beech tree
Quite mechanically and spurred on by further explosions I ran after my Superior
Who sometimes turned around and stared at me wild I yelling what in God's name are those things
What are they
Suddenly there was a flash among the root work and a blow on the left Fife lonely to the ground
I thought I've been struck by a clump of Earth but the warm trickle of blood indicated that I've been wounded
Later I saw that a needle sharp piece of shrapnel had given me a flesh wound
Don't my wallet had taken the brunt of it
Define cut
Which before slicing into the muscle head split no fewer than nine thicknesses of stout leather looked as though it might have been
Administered by scalp
He continued
I threw down my haversack and ran toward the trench weed come from
From all sides wounded men were making tracks towards it from the shelter Woods
The trench was appalling
Choked with seriously wounded and dying man
I figure stripped to the waist with a ripped open back leaned against the parapet
Another with a triangular flap hanging off the back of his skull emitted short high-pitched screams
This was the home of the great God pain
And for the first time I looked through a devilish Cinque into the depths of his realm
And fresh shells came down all the time
I lost my head completely
Ruthlessly I barged past everyone on my path
Before finally having fallen back a few times in my haste
Climbing out of the hellish Crush of the trench to move more freely above like a bolting horse I rushed through the dense under
Growth across passing clearings
Till I Collapse in the cops by The Grand tranchi
And quote
This
One of the most suicidally brave Soldiers of the Great War
If it can happen to him
Could happen to anyone
And I'm constantly amazed
At the immense
Bravery
And an almost carelessness of death that are grandparents and great
Grandparents showed consistently in this conflict
And I always wonder about how
Baidu
Am I generation would do in the same situation
The owner tries later on
To explain what the
Feeling of being in an artillery barrage is like
It's difficult because we have nothing to compare it to
Have you ever been on an airplane for example when it's in heavy turbulence and it takes one of those horrible drops in your stomach just
I mean it
I can't even describe that feeling
And that's nothing
Younger
Write this
In one of the greatest descriptions I've ever heard of what
Feels like he was trying to explain it to people who never experienced it
He wrote this
Quote
It's an easier matter to describe these sounds
Then to endure them
Because one cannot put associate every single sound of flying steel with the idea of death
And so I had told in my hole in the ground with my hand in front of my face imagining all the possible there
Variance of being hit
I think I found a comparison the captures the situation in which I
And all the other soldiers who took part in this war
So often found ourselves
You must have imagined that you were securely tied to a post
Being menaced by a man swinging a heavy hammer
Now the hammer has been taken back over his head ready to be swung
Now it's clearing the air towards you
On the point of touching your skull
Then it struck the post
And the splinters are flying
That's what it's like to experience heavy shelling in an exposed position
And quote
Now when you can
Take cover in the trench and press yourself up against the Earth
And dig your head into the soil and try to just
Weather the storm that's hard enough
But there are a lot of times in this conflict a lot of times
When your job
Easter run through
The Drum Fire in the Halo shells
To do everything your body
Tells you not to do if I'm stronger than get carried away by the shell fire you know what help do
Regular old shows like yours truly have right
Yulia scotching is in one of those situations
That soldiers all through the war will be and we know some officer blows a whistle and says time to jump out of the trench
Run-pass the gunfire
And he writes
The feeling you have when it's your turn
Quote
Weird approach the firing line a little more than two miles when we got Within Reach of the enemies curtain of Fire
A terrific Halo shells with plowing up every foot of ground
Thousands of corpses of German soldiers
Were witnesses to the immense losses the Germans had suffered in bringing up all available Reserves
The French try their utmost to prevent the Germans from bringing in their reserves and increase their artillery fire
To an unheard-of viola
It seemed impossible for us to break through that barricade of Fire
Hundreds of shells were bursting every minute
We were ordered to pass that he'll
Singly and that her running pace
We were lying on the ground and observed how the first of our men tried to get through
Some ran forward like mad
Not heating the shells that were bursting around them and got through
Others were entirely buried by the dirt dug up by the shells
Torn to Pieces by shell splinters
Two man had scarcely reached the line when they were struck by a bullseye
IE the heavy shell exploded at their feet
Leaving nothing of
You can imagine what we were feeling during these harrowing minutes as we laid crouching on the ground
Not quite a hundred feet away
Seeing everything
And only waiting for our turn to come
One-hit entangled oneself in a maze of thoughts
Certainly one of the officers would cry
The next one
That was I
Just as if we're out of a bad dream
I jumped up
And race away like mad
Holding the rifle in my right hand
And the bayonet in my left
I jump aside a few steps in front of to bursting shells and running to two others which are bursting at the same time
I leapt back several times run forward again race about wildly to find a gap through which to escape
Fire and iron everywhere
Like a hunted Beast one seeks some opening to save oneself
How was in front of me and behind me the officers revolver
Kept ready to shoot
The lumps of Steel fall down like a heavy shower from high above hell and Damnation
I blindly run and run and run until someone gets me by my coat where there someone Roars into my ear
Stop
Are you wounded
Have a look
Perhaps you are when you don't know it
Here I am trembling all over
Sit down
The other person says you'll feel better
We tremble to
And quote
How many of us could do that
And think about the mentality
And how these people were raised
You know what was involved that allowed them
To do this I mean I have a feeling that my generation would just turn around at the office or holding a gun to watch to get
Get us to do that and figure like I can't take us all out we're not going into that
We did a history show Once about
The question of whether the older generation raised in a different time we're tougher than we were
And of course there's no way to really come to any conclusions about that
When you read this and you see
What are grandparents and great-grandparents did
It boggles the mind
And if those shells won't drive you insane
The Carnage that they create that you have to live around everyday
Just met
As I said one of the terrible things about this battle that's different from most of the second World War
Is in the second World War
You have What's called the moving front Gwynne Dyer his
Famous peace War talk about the continuous front
Duty calls
The first world war initiated
In the second world war The Continuous front mu
Blitzkrieg
And the people are continually changing location
What makes the battlefields of the first World War we said earlier so particularly horrifying
Isn't it doesn't change
You get to live around the Carnage
From years past even in the Second World War
Eugene Sledge writing
You know from the US Marine talking about fighting in the Pacific will talk about his particularly
Horrified feeling
As he watched
Flies
It were feeding on dead bodies right near him
Fly-Rite
To the edge of his coffee
And land in his coffee
These are the little
Horrifying things that you would think after why we just drive you out of your mind
Philip Gibbs
Is absolutely
The groundbreaking work now it can be told
Was a journalist on the scene as we said earlier and unable to write about the reality of
The war until afterwards
He describes
One of these situations
Just how
Incredible it was to have to live in this
It's worse than the Charnel house
He describes
An area called
Couch
That was so terrible
Near the Ypres Battlefield
Just quote
The worst school of War for the sons of gentleman was in those days in for long afterwards
Couch
This was the Devil's Playground
And his chamber of Horrors wherein he devised Mary tortures for young Christian men
It was not far out of Ypres
To the left of the Mendon Road into the north of is Wildwood and Sanctuary wood
For a time there was a chateau there called the white chateau
With excellent stable and good accommodation for one of our Brigade staff
Until one of our generals was killed and others wounded by a shell which broke up their conference
Afterwards that was no chateau
But only a rubble of bricks backed up with sandbags and deep mine craters filled with stinking water
Swapping over from the Belvedere Lake
And low-lying pools
Bodies and bits of bodies and clots of blood and green metallic looking slime
Made by explosive gases were floating on the surface of that water below the crater Banks when I first pass that way
And so it was always
Are men live there and died there within a few yards of the enemy
Crouch below the sandbag
And pasted into the mud bag
If they dug to get deeper cover
Their shovels went into the softness of dead bodies who have been their comrade
Scraps of Flash
Booted legs
Black and tans eyeless heads came falling over them when the enemy trench more their position
I blew up a new Mineshaft
And quote
How would that not drive anybody crazy
Daddy is
War
Made worse
That's you living in Zombieland
And being shelled at the same time it's
It is as I said many times and will continue to say this is the worst experience or soldiers in Warfare I've ever seen on a map
Scale
Even in Stalingrad in the Second World War
Widely considered one of the worst places to be in the world
That just equal
The experience that many men on the Western Front got to experience routinely
How did they deal with it
In ways
That are
Some sort of a wonderful
Testament to Human Nature
They often joked about
Adopted a sort of gallows humor at times
That reminds you of police officers
Or fireman
Or be honest journalist
And soldiers and people who see this horrible stuff
And their way of coping with it
Is humor
The journalist Philip Gibbs
Experience this and took part in it
And this was his theory on the
Whole thing quote
It was astonishing how loudly one laugh to Tales of gruesome things
Awards brutality
I with the rest of them
I think it's a bottom of it was a sense of the ironical contract
Between the normal ways of civilian life
And this hark back to the caveman code
It made all of our old philosophy of life monstrously
It played the hat trick
With the gentility of modern manners
Men who have been brought up to Christian virtues
Would prattle dear little prayers at their mother's knees
Would grown up to love poetry
Painting
Music The Gentle Arts
Over sensitized to the subtleties of halftones
Delicate scales of emotion
Fastidious in their choice of words
In their sense of beauty
Found themselves compelled to live and act like eight men
And it was abominably funny
They laughed the most frightful episode which revealed this contrast between civilized ethics
Any old Beast law
The more revolting it was
The more sometimes they shouted with laughter
Especially in reminiscence
When the tale was told of the Gilded Salon of the French chateau
Or at the mess table
It was I think he writes
The laughter of Mortals
That's a trick which have been played on them by Anna ronico fate
They have been taught to believe that the whole object of life
What's to reach out to Beauty in love
And that mankind and its progress to Perfection had killed the Beast instinct
Cruelty
Bloodlust
The primitive
Savage laws of Survival by tooth and Claw and Club aynax
Allpoetry
All art all religion had preached this gospel in this promise
Now that ideal had broken like a China base - 2 hard ground
The contrast between that
And this
Was
And quote
The stories that they told
We're both funny
And revealing in a horrified way like The Gallows humor you see from police officers and soldiers and whatnot
One of the ones
Is this one
Quote
In one section of trenches the men made a habit of betting upon those who would be wounded first
It had all the uncertainty of the roulette table
One day when the German Gunners were putting over a special dose of hate
A sergeant kept coming to one dugout
To inquire about a quote and quote new Chum
Who would come up with the draft
Is private Smith alright he asked
Yes Sergeant he's alright answer the man crouching in the dark hole
Private Smithers and wounded yet
Master sergeant again five minutes later no sergeant
Private Smith was touched by this interest in his well-being
And said
That's Sergeant seems a very kind man said the boy
Seems to love me like a father
A yell of laughter answered him
You poor bleeding fools and one of his comrades
Each drawing you in a lottery
How to do win if you've been hurt
And quote
Another example
Of this
Amazing ability of human beings to adapt in these kinds of situations
With the tools given to us including humor which again you you look at survivors
Of Auschwitz
And Treblinka and the death camps of the Nazis
The Jews were using humor even there
Hope
Gibbs tells the story
Quote
In digging new trenches and New dugouts
Bodies and bits of bodies were on Earth
And putting the sand bags with the soil
It was sent back down the line of men concealing their work from German eyes waiting for any new activity in our ditches
Bitter Bill said the leading man putting in the leg
Another bit of Bill he said unearthing a hand
Bill's ugly mug
He said at a later stage in the operation when the head was found
Gibb says quote has told afterwards that little episode in the trenches seemed immensely comic
Generals charcoal.
Chaplin's Treasury
And quote
All the coping mechanisms in the world.
We're not enough to help
Things got to a really critical
Echostage
Every human being has a breaking
And
What in the first World War was called shell shocked
We mentioned it earlier would later be updated to battle fatigue
As soon as
The experts realized it was an imprecise term because you didn't have to be exposed to artillery in the shells at all to get it
Now we would call it post-traumatic stress disorder u-see-it in soldiers today
It's pretty common
No
I'm not
Just not his story and I'm not a psychology
Just either so take this with the gray
But this is something that appears to be what they call a spectrum disorder
Meaning
You can have a severity scale
Golf like 1 to 10
And not to minimize anything
Current veterans go through
They'll often come back from these wars
It was Nightmare
Or an inability to sleep or
Eat properly
For the we integrate into society and they've obviously suffered some trauma and damage
In the first world war though
Those people would often be shot
If you couldn't see visible evidence and often times even if you could
The people in that are especially
Early in the war
Didn't look at this as some sort of a legitimate problem to them this was just another manifestation of cowardice
Punishable by Death
Take for example
Phillip Gibbs his account and he has a bunch of them because this was one of the things that upset him the most
He would go to the front
Report on what the soldiers had to endure
And then once they were damaged by what they had to endure report on how
The completely clueless militaries of the day
You'll then punish them again for something they were already victimized once for he tells one story for example
I'm an officer that he's meeting with who comes back
To the meeting with him from a court-martial hearing he just been
To where
They'd sentenced one of these people who
He had his mind blown by his experience
To death
He says quote
Going up the camel one day I had to wait in Battalion headquarters for the officer I'd gone to see
He was attending a court-martial
Presently he came into the wooden Hut with a flushed face
Sorry I had to keep you you said tomorrow there will be once wine Less in the world
A death sentence game said he nodded
A damn coward
Eddie didn't mind rifle fire but couldn't stand shells
Admitted he left his post
He doesn't mind rifle fire well
Tomorrow morning the officer laughed grimly and then listen for a second
There was some heavy crump's falling over camelhill rather close it seem to our wooden Hut
He's talking about artillery shells falling
Nearby
Damn those German Gunner said the officer
Why can't they give us a little piece
Return to his papers
But several times while I talk with him he jerked his head up and listen to a heavy crash
On the way back
I saw a man on foot
Walking in front of a mountain man passed the old Hill love the shepherd bird
Who are the village of Lockport
It was something in the way he walked in his attitude
The head hunched forward a little
In his arms behind his back
Would make me turn to look at it
He was manacled
And Tied by a rope to the mountain man
I caught one glimpse of his face and then turned away cold and sick
It was Doom written on his face
And in his eyes a captured look
He was walking to his wall
And quote
I mean the wall where he was going to
He put up again
And Shop
By his compare
Gibbs later quotes another General saying
But anyone who comes down with these symptoms is a damn coward and he have them all shot
Now
Early in the war this is how they thought
Because they didn't deal with this routinely
They're doing a little talk of this during the russo-japanese war a decade before this where the Russians were encountering this kind of
No problem
But this was a new experience this idea
Combat fatigue battle fatigue shellshock this would be stuff by the way that all the major militaries of the world
Would study after the first World War
Any would incorporate what they learned
Into training procedures and how you
Dealt with combat in the next War to try to minimize these problem
Even later in the first World War
The generals would learn
If you need to rotate your troops away from the front lines
Regular intervals you can't leave them up there indefinitely
Or they're all going to go
So you'll see these times where
For a week or two
The troops will have to live in the mud in 3 feet of standing water under shell firing all the time
But then they'll take him to the back to the rear areas that are safer
Can let them recover
And then slowly moving back toward the front this rotation
Was intended to keep them fresh and key
Keep them from becoming psychological casualty
And
These are people
Who are foaming at the mouth
Sometime
When they were brought back from the line these are people who are saying I just can't handle it anymore General although sometimes
That's what you encounter
These are people whose limbs have turned to Rigamortis
Or War so palsy
They can't walk
For the epileptic seizures
Or seizure-like things you're seeing you can actually go see this by the way because after the war
People didn't heal they never heal
40 years later there still
I'm taking up Hospital space in some of these countries
And there are films that the doctors made showing you these people symptoms in their online you can view them
Some of these symptoms are so physical in nature
That this is kind of how the term Shell Shock first became
Fashion Nova
Because there were theories that maybe the concussion in the change in air pressure that the shells nearby
Exploding
Actually did brain damage or nerve damage to these people
Because when you actually see some of these cases and how they were affected
That looks like physical damage it doesn't look like mental
Again that did not prevent the military's
I'm treating this as cowardice
Especially early on
And dishing out
The capital punishment penalty for
That having been said
Still fascinating to me how
You actually
Had to BX
Executed for this
Sometimes you can read books with a British
These cells
The 1970s 1970s
And it's just as outraged
No end and you looking and 330
People are executed or something for
Running away in combat abandon your post desertion those kind of things
And I think to myself I think my generation if we were forced to go through with those people had to go through
That's how many people they shoot in a month
Because what's happening in 1915 and you can sum up the entire Western Front in 1950 you don't have to
To deal with any of the battles
Is that the situation is
Is degenerating into
What we understand the first World War
Trenches
And defenses that are becoming ever more sophisticated
We are now getting beyond the error we are talking about
China One Long trench on one side and one long trench on the other and maybe
Sophistication here in there
A little barbed wire between
And we are entering into a phase now
We're
On the Western Front
You begin to have to fortification
And you're not talking now about
Successful attacks
Going after people you're trying to batter down
Defenses that goes sometimes mile
Backward
Astoria
Thorne Bros
Describe the
Deepening 1915
Fortifications like this
Quote
When the Allies attacked in May 1915
The Trenches were shielded by two belts of barbed wire
Each five feet high and 30 m deep
Behind the wire lay a trench Network
Consisting of three lines 100 m apart
At regular intervals each trench had a zigzag or dogleg Traverse
The Shield Defenders from shells Landing nearby
And prevent attackers from firing machine guns down the entire length of the trench
Dish Network of trenches was supported 1000 back
Buy concrete machine gun pillboxes
Thermodown enemy soldiers who pierce the forward position
Those
Already formidable sounding defenses were increased
During the summer
Brose continues quote
During the summer a second double belt of barbed wire went into place 1000 meters behind the rear pill boxes
The first train system
Then came a second triple line of trenches also backed by machine gun emplacement
The Defenders also burrowed ever more deeply into the ground
To make the system work optimally monthly outputs of machine guns that increase nearly 12 volt
Both the first and second trim systems were linked by communication trenches for moving up reinforcements are retreating
Underground telephone cables connected the first line with the second as well as with the artillery far to the rear
General falkenhayn well-designed
Kilometers deep
Double killing zones amounted to a massive engineering and construction project
But it was carried out before the Allies attacked again into
September
And quote
That's attacking a fort
Now if the Allies were also deepening and making the trenches more sophisticated
But not to the same degree the Germans were because the Allies attitude is why would we waste that much effort
When were hoping the next attack of the next attack breaks us through would be out of these trenches will be in their Trench
The Germans have a much more defensive attitude on the Western Front at this time
They plan on staying awake
They dig deeper into the Earth and build these bunk houses with you Timber overhead in a big trees laid down
Log cabin-style with Earth on top of that sometimes they have carpeting on the floor wallpaper on the walls show
Shelving I mean
It's
In some ways
A giant
You know Roman Empire kind of
Hadrian's Wall up and down the line mini belt
The Deep
Peter insane Fordham
Application who in their right mind would think you want to slam human beings up against that over and over again
Well
Franklin
British military leadership on the cob
France's military leaders also jafra
Have an attitude of just get them out
They're on the sacred soil of France it's also important resource in industrial territory
Chopper will waste if necessary an entire generation of young Frenchman to eject
The Haunting from Francis oil
Propaganda
Nickname for the Germans
Andy
British commander of British forces in France
Confusingly and ironically named as we said before Sir John French
Agrees with shop or just give us more troops
Where the bigger boxer in this price by who cares if we get there
Elbows in there
Risks in their bones
They're going down eventually just give us more truth will pound these fortifications down
And the way they did this by the way
What did Morgan
1915 is not just the beginning of the heavy duty trench warfare it's the beginning of the attempt to deal with the heavy duty
Trench warfare
And you do this with ever-increasing amounts of guns
A bigger caliber
And
Using them for longer.
What time
In just one of these
Double headed battle that will be fought in the middle of 1915
Jean French figures out the way to break through these kinds of fortifications
Is with many many hours
A mini mini guns
Shooting in a confined area
Stockpiles 5.2 million shells
Start using this
A1 double-headed offensive
Are you going to pound these fortifications and then you going to send men into the Gap to occupied and that's what I
Friendship the tencent
Artillery conquers the ground
Can you send the man in afterwards to occupy
The 1915 Stratus
He's also called
Buy some commanders bite and hole
Tony's General ideas with
Can you grab an area
Get your grab it with artillery you take it over with people when all the other side killed by the artillery and then you start for Define
Why don't you turn that into your little castle and now you just moved
Your side's fortifications more toward their side
It's a giant moving War
Trenches in sea
Fortification the moon one side take
A new area
The other side
Goes and attack them right away before they can fortify
Again
Possible to follow these battles
1915 look like
Evermore big guns
Evermore wasted opportunities Evermore futility
And the most forward-thinkers amongst the Allied
Leaders in
Decision makers
I'm looking at this already at the end of 1914 and they can see it in the distance and they thinking to themself
Must we go there
French think you're supposed to have
Floated the idea first Bluetooth picked up most famously by Winston Churchill
An idea of finding a flying
In another fighting
Theater
Why do we have to
Throw more troops into the meat grinder
Did the British Empire
It's just starting to produce a decent number of people
They got some
Building up of troops happening
These volunteers that first joined up at the very beginning of the war now
Gone through their training.
And I could be thrown in early like
General falkenhayn did with those poor
Student soldiers are going to be husband in for just the right time they're green
But they're trained
Must we throw these precious
Intrude
Into the meat grinder
More Empire troops by the way are also showing up the
Canadians as we said the Indians were already there
But other troops
Really from Dominion I think we should
Commonwealth earlier
And although the term was in use it's not officially the right
Term until between the two Wars when
Commonwealth status is branded to some of these places
Let's just call them to minions
Troops from
New Zealand and Australia
Raised up again in patriotic fervor
For the cause and large numbers of people relative to the total population D places
They're on the way
Are you really going to sacrifice all these troops into
Hacking
Deepwater vacations
For the commanders on the western
Front French and British war
You know of the
Opinion that every person should be thrown into the Western
Confront stay would argue that
It's only a meat grinder on the Western Front cuz we don't have enough men yet
To overrun that me
You give us enough people we will end this war fast in a lot less people will die
There was as I mentioned earlier
Kind of cabal
Bankers
Food come to the conclusion
But that sort of thinking was mistaken
And it surely there are better ideas out the
Then to throw
Are more and more human beings into the teeth of the enemy's defenses
Decabol had some famous members
Winston Churchill
For example maybe the most famous
Call the Lord Horatio Kitchener the war minister not far behind
And these people
Were of the opinion I guess you could
Compare it to
Set up a predator
They have been trying to take down
The nastiest animal in the herd
4 months now and they gotten Gordon the process
The Germans had done damage to every
Major
Member of the Allies by this time
And there were
The great Lions of France and Britain and Russia looking around and take you to themselves
Why don't we just follow the traditional
Predatory
Son of a protein go after the week
Anosike
Any ol
Instead of going after the strong and young and dangerous
And there was a country in the war now that met all three
Of those key classifications of the guy like Churchill would have made
Country
The week
Is more than a country
What's an Empire
Dying
I've been calling a turkey
Throughout this whole show because that's the proper name for the first world war but there's another proper name 2
Conjures up a whole different set of images than the perhaps modern sounding name of Turkey
What's the Ottoman Empire
And that conjures up images of salt
Janissary
Harem
And being on the gates of Vienna almost over running into
Central Europe at one point at the height of their history
Of knocking down
The walls of Constantinople
Formerly known as Byzantium to the Greek
Constantinople to the Romans
And then
After the sultan
And got through that historic barrier in Concord the city he renamed it
Eastham
As sort of a momento
And giant Monument
For what his
Ottomans had achieved
That was when the Ottomans were young
The Ottomans were old
And they were losing territory
Over the
Decades like nobody's business
They were seen as a carcass to be picked
The sick man of Europe they were called
And someone like
Churchill
Looked at
Turkey just sitting there they come into the war in November several months after the war officially start
And they're surrounded by water
And there
Maybe not even a second-rate power they have the territory of a big second-rate Power lots of
Places trying to get out of turkey but still stuck in Turkey
Hello neighbor might look at it a record might look at it or an Armenian might look at it
None the less without them mean to sort of
Territory named one of their main reasons there been a war called the
Crimean War
In the middle of the 19th century
Is because
Turkey was so weak and yet soul
Filled with territory you could take
Did the British and the French had to get involved to keep the Russians from snapping up too much of it
So this appeared to be the easy animal in the herd to take down
And a crucial place that might have all sorts of impact on the war if you did take him down
Take for example
All the countries that hadn't decided whose side they were going to fight on yet
Turkey enters the war as we said
A headache for the Allies cuz they open up an entire new theater
Of operations really there might have been in a little stuff on the side going on but when turkey gets in the war in November 1914
The Middle East is now in
India maybe in
Southern rushes in play North African Egyptian play the Balkans is in play
Balkans
Is territory that when the ottoman Turks were young and Powerful
They own
They'd fought two wars in the past couple of years
With the former territories that they used to own and watch them in a shake off the Ottoman Empire
Serbia Bulgaria Romania Greece all these places have been pulling themselves away
From ottoman influence for some time now
And none of them had decided
Which side they were going to fight on in this war yet and it's fascinating and you talk about watching open diplomacy in a way
Like watching horse trading going on is watching the Allies on one side and the central powers on the other side
Try to
Convince a country to go their way I mean with Italy for example
It's almost open auction time
I mean one Alliance will walk in the front door and say well if we win the war on you join us you can have this province from the enemy in that prob
Believe in any other door comes together Alliance it something is that all they promised you what if we win you can have this.
And this was going on with all these countries in the Balkans and Greece
Revamp on the Aegean
The number two thing they were all concerned with his what were they going to get
They got in the war
What are you promising me and you know going to the highest bidder
What's the number one thing they were all concerned
Who is going to win
These countries knew that they were absolutely like roadkill if they picked the wrong
Inside
But in early 1915
No clear-cut
Dominant side head emerged
Wenzhou Churchill and his compatriots had this idea that
They could strike a big blow in that theater right in that part of the world
Even if they didn't knock anybody out with it it might convince a lot of these Powers while you can save
Britney's going to win France going to win let's join them
Write change the course of the war that way
So all these good arguments
Starting to accrue for
Cabal of people like Winston Churchill
When all of a sudden something intervenes to bring the whole thing to a head
Put it on the front burner and make the government consider whether or not it's a good idea that one thing to have a good idea to another thing
You really be thinking about a case of Scooby-Doo
And a request from the Russians
Change this from a theoretical question to one that they're debating
In early January 9th
The Russians are asking for him
They're facing
The Turks down near there
In a border the
Turks in the Russian
Territory touch
Far away from where Russian forces were fighting the Germans in the austro-hungarian
Because of the distance
The Russians have pretty much taken their troops in
They're fighting for their lives against the Germans and use them up north
And now the Turks are attached
Lacking in strength
Down south
The situation will get
Critical and late
December 1 on December 29th
The Turkish forces up against the Russians on their Mutual border
Start the Battle of Sarah,
And try to attack
The Russian Defenders
From multiple sides
Tutte
Very optimistic during Napoleonic in concept
Plan
Led by a civilian strategy
I will take a hundred and twenty thousand men a good Turkish Army
And ruin it
Because he's Russian
A smaller Force than the Turks attacking them
Are ensconced
In the natural Fortress that is the Caucasus Mountain
In the middle of winter
All this fighting is going to happen
Elevation
P1065
Turkish soldiers are going to be fighting
As though they're dressed for the lowlands
The logistics of this
120000 man army are going to be
Carried up into these mountains on tiny little windy mountain roads and is not even many of them
And it's snowing like you can't believe we're told of
In a multiple days of 14-hour marches through
In a waist-deep snow by the time these poor Turkish troops get to the Russians
Their darn near defeated that
Some of them surrender ride with several cords Just Surrender that you and you just get this image of these starving
You know units that are just falling apart and at the end of their rope
Some fight bravely and almost fanatically anyway and then the next part of the story that's famous is the retreat
Of this Turkish Army
Back to Turkey they lose about half their strength
We're told that of the
People that do make it back
Is turkey a third of them are so badly wounded that they'll have some part of their body and face
And the stories themselves and
Amazing how
A like they are booked a book
But they make they create the sort of mental image of like Napoleon
Retreating from Moscow in the winter harried the whole way back
With these
Soldiers that were freezing on the March cuz it was so cold in the mountain passes in the middle of winter
And the Army is supposed to be followed by
Through these
It almost Bram Stoker
Schleich train
And taking the Frozen soldiers as they freezer is it become too wounded to defend themselves it's a horrifying story
And the church will be very bitter
And affected by the
This battle
The Russians will be though too
Because even though they technically Win It
For all they know the church could do this in another three weeks or another month and they're not ready for this again
The Turkish attack down here
Prove that this is not a quiet safe front
And you better be ready for more
They're not ready for
More
This is why they are
For help
And they asked for some diversion to be made
Will draw some of these Turkish troops away from them
And maybe something that will
Open up
The supply lines again
Because the Turks control
One of the most
Strategically important
Spots
Not just in the world but in world history
When you take Constantinople in the 15th century like the Turks did
The Dardanelles come with it
The Dardanelles
Are the actual separation
And this is a geographic feature that goes back to
Forever
Between
Asia and Europe
You look at it on
Satellite images it looks like a rather large river
But it really is only a mile apart in some
Spotting
This is the Waterway the
It takes you from
You know the Aegean Sea which is connected to the Mediterranean Sea we just connected to the rest of the world
And get you from there
To the black
Which is not connect
Get to the rest of the world
Unless you're using the Dardanelles
It's a straight
Extreme importance
And the church control
They are fortresses on both sides of this
Glorified River
With Canon
They've got mines in the water way to prevent people from getting through that they don't want to get through and once they get in the war in
M1914 they don't want the Russians to get through
And they don't want the British to get through
And the French to get through and this is a huge problem for Russia because they don't have a lot of places
You know where people can trade with them via the ocean
Especially
You know if it's anywhere near the winter months
If it's near the winter months
You need
Dysport open
Find the Black Sea port
Now the trucks are closed it
The Russians are in such bad Straits
They are sending soldiers
Into battle
With a rifle
And then another Soldier whose job it is to Shadow the first Soldier
And when the first Soldier dies pick up his rifle and use it because the second person didn't get it right
The Russian industry cannot keep up with the military need
So they're having problems like that so you can see how important it is for them to be able to trade with Britain and France and maybe I'll
Outside powers
If just to get rifles to arm their troops with and now the trucks are closed off
An important area
And Winston Churchill things he can open it
He gets an idea
That will involve any ground troops at all he continually point this out in his book by the way
Use this book for
For the show but not of the history book
It's not the kind of
Do you want to use
Define historical
Truth
It's the kind of book you want to look
Define
The truth as Churchill saw it and Justified it after
Which is a very different thing
Churchill's fingerprints are all over this thing
This thing is going to go south
He does what almost any other person with any responsibility for World War in their postwar
Memoirs
He defends himself
Answers his critics justifies this
Explains that and
You no different than the German generals
What not
In that respect
But his point is
When he thought of this idea
It didn't involve any land troops
Since its land troops are going to be a huge part of
Tragedy that this unfolds into he basically says he washed his hands of the whole plan once
That situation changed
Churchill's plan
What's the take
The largest most powerful Fleet ever assembled in world history
And force the straight
Simply
Sail through them
Wiping out any Fort you know this anywhere nearby with Naval gunfire and go from one side to the
And then once you're on the other side you're right next to
Formerly Constantinople now Istanbul and you have a giant megalopolis
Underneath the guns of the greatest
Fleet ever assembled
Sent to war
It's an idea that looks
Great
On paper
And then by the
Time events go from a all the way through the alphabet to Z though
You see who rules the alpha
When it comes to getting
Something from the
Leafy erratic
Full stage 2 the reality
Beijing that's Murphy's Law
And Murphy's Law grabs hold of these events
And quickly turns this whole Affair into something
No one had ever thought
What's the right thing to
Told you how people can get
Swamped by events sometimes in Churchill spends a good part of his book on this subject
Trying to point out that he was one of the victims of what happen
He's often been portrayed
As the architect
If you ever want to see
Frustrating
History
Can be sometime
Look at Churchill's thinking of
Because when you examine it it's so logical he's doing exactly what
Any of us would help somebody in a position of power we do in terms of
I'm going down the arguments and the risks and benefits logically
And it still turns out
Horribly
What's the weather
Lesson is that teaching to the other commanders were saying
Yeah just keep smashing against the wall
Oh my goodness doesn't scene
To matter whether you think outside the box we do the same darn stupid pointless thing again and again
The first world war equalizes the results of both of that
And you're darned if you think and you're darned if you don't
Church of the basic assumption
Was it the British Empire was sitting on an enormously powerful Fleet
That was used
The part that was useless is so useless you can't even use it if the enemy Fleet comes out
The fight is a whole bunch of British ships
It were made obsolete only in 1906 remember
1940-1950
What happened in 1906
A brand new type of battle
Became the name of the initial ship names dreadnought
And that becomes the name for that entire
Type of vessel
A dreadnought
Class name now that's
Because that's how revolutionary this ship was
The problem is
Is the instant it arrives on the scene
It makes obsolete
Fleets of
Hugely expensive vessels dozens and dozens and dozens of the Dead have been built up over a lifetime makes them obsolete overnight
And of course the British being the greatest Navy in the world they had the most of these
Battleship
The older boy
The ones that in 1905 or the greatest force of float
The 1906 are ready for the scrap Heap
That's what Churchill said all these ships were heading for
What are we saving them for they just going to be scrapped after the war he said that the Admirals had these
Emotional attachments to these ships
Because they've served on the Moor
They remember the day when these were the most powerful warships afloat in Churchill
Attitude is these are assets to be used up for a gain
We can use him in the Dardanelles and if we lose him we don't lose any
Winston Churchill's plan of using
The fleet in a lightning attack that the Turks weren't ready for with massive Force I could just force The Straits before anyone
Could respond to it
Turns into something totally different
Over the next several weeks
And Churchill has always claimed
Did the events were completely out of his control
What are uses as an argument the line
He was told that there were no troops available
So any plan he came up with pretty much had to have
A tiny little group of Marines to run on Shore and knock out a gun if necessary
But nothing else so he says basically he can't be responsible
Sponsible for this land disaster that's about to happen
He never assumed there be any troops anyway here's what he said
Quote
At the evening meeting of the war council on January 28th
When the final decision to adopt the plan was taken Lord Kitchener repeated quote
We have at present no troops to spare
It was on that Foundation alone that all our decisions in favor of a purely Naval attack have been taken
But henceforward a series of new facts and pressures came into play
Which gradually but unceasingly change the character
An enormously extended the scale of the Enterprise
Under these influences in less than 2 months the naval attack
With its lack of certainty but with its limited costs and risks
Became subsidiary
And in its place there arose a military development of great magnitude
Over this new plan the admiralty had no responsible control
Our advice did not Prevail our criticisms were not welcomed and even inquiries became a matter of
Delicacy intact
Nonetheless
By the results of this military operation
We had to stand or fall
And quote
I know you don't need translation from me
But isn't that the same as saying hey that wasn't my idea you changed it but I still have to be responsible for it
You see a lot of post World War 1 map
Martin sound like that
Nonetheless
It adequately explains how
Out of control the process seen once Churchill and his cabal had taken their little private idea
And had adopted by not just one government but the Allies as
The plan
Of course in the final analysis
The people with the most control over your plan
If your wisdom Church
Are the ones on the scene
Actually have to make it work
The military can
In this case the Admiral
On February
17th a couple of those Admirals are leading the most powerful Fleet that's ever gone to war
Bleeding a little
Who poker the most powerful Fleet in the world is the British Fleet sitting
I'll be in scapa flow up in Scotland waiting for the German Fleet to come out
Play
But that bleeds never done any
They're waiting for their chance
What's the largest most powerful Fleet that ever gone to war and try to do something so far
This one
18 or so battleships most of the British summer in French
Most of these the old battleships
That were made obsolete a decade before but also including
The newest Super dreadnought
Queen Elizabeth with 15 inch guns
At 12 or so Cruisers 30 destroyers a couple hundred transports
This Fleet might not have lasted very long again
Crack
German Fleet
But in this part of the world it's the most powerful
Uniforce afloat
And would have been the greatest thing in the world a decade
It arrives in off the coast
Turkey and begins
Selling those
Straits
On February 19th
And things starts
Slowing down
Plan is to battle your way through destroy all these fortresses as you continue to move.
Deeper and deeper into this
A river like
Piece of geography
But you know the weather gets bad
Sweet Retreats
Into a safe distance
And then it comes up and they shall come forth and then something else goes wrong and Church of the sitting back in Britain going crazy pulling his hair out
Sending messages after messages basically saying
Hurry hurry hurry the whole plan requires you to hurry
Because the longer they take
The more you lose this whole idea that there's some surprise to it
The catches the Turks off guard
And so the Turks have already figured out when you see the largest Fleet than it ever going to war
Show the British are doing something down here the good news is that does take away troops fighting the Russians and take some pressure off
He asked for help
The first place
The bad news is instead of the British advancing against a totally
I'm ready fo you know when taking advantage of surprise
They're sitting there giving the whole basic idea way
Vermont
On the 18th of March
The fleet decide to try again in a big way Churchill's back there prodding and get to work it out there do a big attack
And the 18 battleships in the whole Fleet goes in start selling the Ford
Submarines are
Detached and sent on land to go take some of these sports that are particularly troublesome
And then
A ship hits a mine
French battleship
Range Rover
Really quick
About 700 people died
Kaboom
Before anyone's had time to digest.
Another one
And then another one and by the way on the scene they don't know that these are mine
Mine's are one of the things I thought about Torpedoes or another all they know is big expensive important ships
At least in the old
They are starting
Sink and list and
Explode and the commanders pull everything back and by the time
They get away from The Straits
They've lost
Or seen
Triple six
Now what Winston Churchill would say and what he did say is who cares
These are old battleships are not of any use to us at all
So using to take the straight but at least take the straight
He said the Admirals had a whole different opinion
They didn't see this as an asset to be used
They saw it as
A
Charge to protect
Pajamas he said had an emotional attachment to these ships they walk their decks back when they were young officers in
Chinese ships were the
Queens of the Seas and he says now they had this
Attachment they didn't want to lose them and the whole point was they were there cuz they were losable
Again what's so terrible about what follows is Churchill's attitude was that the sleep was totally expendable
Put in order to protect this
Expendable Fleet the high command decides the ground troops how to
Be sent in
They pull the fleet back
I begin assembling these 80000 men that they're going to attack
This area within the plan is
To overwhelm this peninsula called the Gallipoli Peninsula that's right next to the Dardanelles
And take over all those Forts and all those gun positions with your ground troops
Then those guns won't fire on your little teeny minesweepers were clearing the Straits of the mines
And then your big battleships won't get mine
But it's the tail
Wagging the dog here
And Churchill and others have said ever since the war was over
That this was a disaster
Waiting to happen because the whole point of this
Plan is to use strategic surprise to catch the enemy off guard
How's it going to be going to be caught off-guard when it takes
Weeks after the battleships pull back
To get the ground forces on the beach
The Turks are commanded
My German Jen
Case
A very competent guy named liman Von Sanders who supposedly says
If the Allies will just give him eight days he can put together a defense he's desperate for time
In 5 weeks
By the time the landings take place
In late April early May 1915
To say that the Turks are ready maybe is a little bit presumptuous
But they're waiting
And you get a chance to see
What the worst nightmares of Allied planners
We're planning for D-Day in the second world war you know the attack
Across the beaches
Across the English Channel Landing
Allied troops on the occupied French Coastline so you can see what their nightmares must have been like because they were young men when they
They got to see how something like an amphibious assault could go wrong
Have they saw it on the
Beaches of
First of all
It was a nightmare
Improvisation
These troops were trained
For war not trained for amphibious assault
They landed sometimes on the wrong Beach
They have completely somehow gotten the train all wrong even with aerial surveillance
I mean the poor Australians are landed in a
Mile from where they were supposed to land
It's like a reverse Amphitheater
A historian John Keegan who visited the sites of the one thing that overwhelms you when you go there
I needed it this
I need little coal and you drop a ton of Australians there with The High Ground all around them like an Amphitheater
And just leave them
I'm some of these beaches
The Allies are able to land route relatively easily and try to capture The High Ground
Another Beaches they landed on sure what to do on a couple of these
Beaches the Turks are waiting for them
And massacres
She would have won
The Allies had taken a a
Transport ship
And cut out a hole in it so that they can drive it right up on the beach in the soldiers could just
Jump out and be ready to fight
The troops trained machine gun
On the door
I'm in the door opened and all these troops jumped out they were machine-gunned one by one by one as they hit the
Less than
25 of them
Several hundred
Even when the Allied Forces at Great cost sometimes take these beaches
They're not only sure what to do next
They have no idea how things are going on the beach next to them
They don't know if the ships know where they are the ships don't know where they are there's no coordination going on
And you really get a wonderful object lesson in which you're also getting on the Western Front
Concerning what weapon system is really missing
War
Unit exist but not in the way where it's coordinated not in the way that you'll see it come of age in the next World War
It's one of those things that when you
Considerate in a vacuum it doesn't even sound like a weapon it's like barbed wire you don't think of Barbed wires weapon you don't think of Ray
Radio communications as a weapon either
Pin the missing ingredient in so many of these missed opportunities in this war
If only the troops that broke through knew they broke through if only they could change were the artillery with shootings if only we could
Bring up reinforcements this happens all the time on the Western Front
Now it's happening
Gallipoli
Sometimes these troops land
Imma just noticed and they don't know what they're supposed to do next or they take the first position that the plans ahead of time called for them to take
And they stop there
What would you expect them to do they don't know what's going on
Have to be careful of their own artillery going to Shell them
The problem is is once again
It allows the Turks
And you will see a lot of fighting going on
For the high ground bees areas
That Overlook the beaches
You know this whole time still might have work if the Turks had turned out to be a soft
Anime
You know if they turned out to be as weak
And is decadent and his
The unmotivated is Allied planner sort of assumed that they would be
Instead they fought like a lion
Which of the Turks are capable of the Turks are very dangerous Soldiers the ethnic Turks especially
And they'll be an incident at one of the top
Chubbies Heights
Where Allied Forces
Are fighting with Turkish forces led by a guy named Mustafa Kemal
Go after the war will become one of the most important figures in post-war turkey
35 years old
And he sees the Allied Forces in his area reaching the heights everybody knows that these Heights are going to be important
And he ordered his troops there
Out of ammunition
To hold them off and he says
These famous
In a lines that have gone down in Turkish history
I don't order you to attack I order you to die
In the time which passes until we die
Other troops and commanders can take our place
And quote
What about the opposite reaction what the Allies were expecting the resistance to be like
The Allied resistance
Is just a spirit
The Australians and new zealanders
To be honest will prove themselves some of the best if not
The best
Fighters in the war on these beaches
But they're completely hamstrung by the
Screw up
On the situation
And in almost no time
The Gallipoli campaign
Turns into a Mediterranean version
Eastern Front
And it's got all the same
Tragic Hallmarks that the Western Front has
Barbed wire
Artillery
No man's land
Trenches the whole thing
And a military historian would point out that of course it does
It's the same situation the same things and conditions that created the need to have people dig into the Earth
Anna created
The power of the defensive over the offense if it's just as present in the Mediterranean in the Aegean is it is on the Western Front
The Australians find out about this
Firsthand I grew up next to it
Air Force Colonel Isaac you fought in the Second World War
I used to ask him who the toughest soldiers were
8 that was an interesting question to me
And I always wanted to hear something like
Germans and I remember he surprised me once by saying the British in general
And the Australian and New Zealand troops specifically
I said why and he said be
Because you would find yourself in these horrible situations
And they would be like
Joke
They said that's
Indicative of a
I'm a level of bravery that you don't normally see
But it doesn't always help you
There's a story
I'm an Australian corporate who wrote about being pinned down on one of these beaches when they land and the Turks have The High Ground there shoe
Shooting down before Australian
For trying to get their act together get organized figure out what we do next while they're under Fire
And while their friends are dying
And yes
For a little while
Some of them are laughing
Rights quote
Golling fire rained on us from the left where they were high Cliffs
One man drop down alongside me laughing
I broke the news to him gently
You got yourself into the hottest Corner you'll ever strike
I showed him where the enemy were
He fired a few shots
And again I heard the sickening thought of a bullet
I look at him in horror
The bullet-head fearfully mashed his face and gone down his throat rendering him dumb
What is eyes were Dreadful to behold
How he squirmed in agony
There was nothing I could do for him but pray that he might die swiftly
It took him about 20 minutes to accomplish this
And by that time he tangled up his legs in pain and stiffened
I saw the waxy color creepover his cheek
And breathe easier
And quote
Amazing to think about this one person who's got to consider his own life which is under attack
How he deals with Tru to need him and
He gets to watch that going on
20 minutes to
If I tend to focus on the horror in the story they didn't tell me it's because that's what gets to me
Any history you read on any subject is going to
By its very nature
The person telling a story usually historian but then sometimes you
Is going to focus on the things
Intrigue or interest them for me
It's what these people had to go through on all sides
And it's the horror
Did I constantly try to imagine myself experiencing and it's mind-blowing to me
And I think I
Anime shows
The ones who stayed with me listening like you
There's got to be something that touches you too
Gallipoli
You have the same
Charnel house
Situation where dead bodies
Are a part of your life
And living amongst them
Is part of the horror that enough that your life is always at stake that you watch all this death and destruction
But you live with Corpses
Corpses of
People you often know or knew
This is a remembrance by British soldier
Leonard Thompson who arrives
Are the Dardanelles right after the
Major Landing
Quote
We arrived at the Dardanelles and saw the guns flashing and heard the rifle fire
They heaved our ship the river Clyde right up to the shore
They've cut a hole in it and made a little peer so we were able to walk straight off and on to the beach
We all sat there
On the hellespont
Waiting for it to get light
The first things we saw our big wreck
Turkish guns
The second a big Marquee
You didn't make me think of the military but of the village vets
Other people must have thought like this too because I remember how we all rushed up to it like boys getting into a circus
And then found it all laced up
We on laced it and rushed in
It was full of corpse
Englishmen
Lines and lines of them with their eyes wide open
We all stop talking
I never seen a dead man before
And here I was looking at two or three hundred of them
It was our first fear
Nobody had mentioned that
I was very shocked
And I thought of Suffolk
And how it seemed a happy place for the first time
We set to work to bury people
We pushed them into the sides of the trench
The bits of them kept getting uncovered in sticking out
But people in the badly made bed
Hands were the worst
They would escape from the sand
Pointing begging even waving
It was one which We All Shook when we passed by
Saying good morning in a posh voice
Everybody did it
The bottom of the trench with springy like a mattress because of all the bodies underneath
At night
When the stench was worse
We tied crepe around our mouths and noses
Describe have been given to us because it was supposed to prevent us from being gassed
The Flies enter the trenches at night
And lined them completely
With a density which was like moving claw
We killed millions of them by slapping are spades along the trench walls
But the next night it would be just as bad
We were all lousy and we couldn't stop shiting because we caught dysentery
We wept
Not because we were frightened
Because we were so dirty
And quote
And like a bad movie
The Gallipoli campaign which was supposed to
Do an end-around
The suffering of the Western Front
An end more quickly by striking
Another week joint
In the enemy's Alliance
Just extended that suffering to a new phone
The entire
Affair will get continually worse
As generals and Admirals who don't want to admit
Defeat keep pouring more and more reinforcements into it
The Turk do the same thing I just becomes
This ongoing hell
Is on going to hell
Will eventually cost Winston Churchill his job
Back to British government
Essentially have to reorganize after create a coalition government in Churchill's the one left out
He will leave the admiralty were told
After being shot
With tears in his eyes certain
But his career is over
Talk about one of the
Great
Mistakes of all-time obviously had a great career ahead of him
Pictures of weird guy
I always have to watch myself with him
Because I like him
I think a lot of us like you
As a historical figure he's quite likeable
Teddy
That's the same way
But you have to remember
These guys have qualities
That make them somewhat unusual
It's hard to factor those qualities into the man
Churchill toad
One of his best friends in February 1950
The time when he's planning this whole Gallipoli thing
Something that's relatively shocking to hear when the whole world is stunned by the Carnage
Of the worst
War in human history
He told his friend this
Quote
I think a curse should rest on me
Because I love this war
I know it's smashing and shattering the lives of thousands every moment and yet
I can't help it
I enjoy every second.
And quote
Imagine if
People whose loved ones were over there fighting and dying and heard Churchill admit that
And one of the things that happens when you use Churchill's account
Of these events that he played an important role in
Did you get all his excuses and you get his point of view
And you get
Very one-sided account of these Affairs were Churchill is the hero he was right all along and only people would listen to him if only the
You have screwed up his plans at all would have
Ingrate
Historian Peter Hart and Brittany I find B
Very fair
He had this to say he's not on the
Churchill was right
Wrote about the Hogle
Quote
Apologists for the Gallipoli campaign have long tried to boast of what could have been
With a heavy emphasis on if only
This fails to recognize that the Allies bought the campaign with levels of Naval and Military Support that will consider
Acceptable
Until the Turks defeated them
Time and time again Hamilton promise success again and again he failed
Gallipoli was one of a series of military
Easterner Adventures
Launch without proper analysis of the global strategic situation without consideration of the local Tactical
Ignoring logistical realities under estimating the strength of the opposition
And predicted are hugely optimistic assessment of the military capabilities of their own troops
Not for nothing is hubris regarded as the English disease
The Gallipoli campaign was a serious matter
Vital resources have been drawn away from where it really matter
The Turks were all but helpless if left on their own
They tried to launch an ambitious attack across the Sinai desert on the Suez Canal but have been easily thwarted
Gallipoli achieve nothing
But you provide the Turks with the opportunity to slaughter British and French troops and copious numbers
In a situation in which everything was in The Defenders favor
Meanwhile back on the Western Front was the Real Enemy
The German Empire
And quote
The ends by saying the Gallipoli
He was a tragic sideshow
And blaming Churchill in large part
The disaster
All the tragic sideshow
What's going on
Another horrible disaster was as well
This is a console
After all full of horrible disasters
But this one was somewhat different
From soldiers fighting it out on bottle
This one involved
Entire
Several
In fact
And it is
Perhaps the most
Argued about
Case of genocide
In world history
In order to understand the
Need to recall how much of a role
Did of ethnic self-determination
In leading up to
Did the conditions that create the first World War
End of the first World War
Shelf
Remember there are a bunch of
Centuries-old
Free 20th century Empire
Let's go to stumble into the 20th century
Carrying all sorts of baggage from previous eras with
Baggage that is in part
Tearing them up
And a lot of this baggage
Just ethnic
Take the
Austro-hungarian
Pirate a perfect
Example of a multi-ethnic Empire
With a ton of different ethnicities in it
Are presided over by a German Hungarian Elite
On paper all these people are
Equal austro-hungarian subject
But if you happen to not be German or Hungarian off and you don't feel very equal
And during this time. Many different ethnic groups
Are either looking to create their own
States
For themselves
Or they're looking to
Join
With ethnic Brethren of there that have already done this
When the first World War II Fletcher College
Touched off by a Serb National
Someone the Slavs
You probably look at it
Patriot
But the austro-hungarians looked at him as a terrorist
And looked at any of their own people that wanted to join
With Serbia a not that old
What country created by the ethnic serbs
Anyone want to do that it was an austro-hungarian subject was now treason
An insurrection
And a rebel
If you're actually in a war with that country
Your fifth columnist
Or 8
Cancer
On your knees
And there's
No question that there are a bunch
Of Empires that are dealing with these problems in their a bunch that are sort of put those problems off
Even the winners in the first
World War II Britain and France were only going to push these questions farther down the road
And after the next World War the British will be dealing with similar situations in India
And the French will be dealing with it in North Africa and Indochina
The austro-hungarians
And the Russians and the Ottoman Empire deal with it now
And it creates huge problems
And it does so in a realm that is historically extremely violence inducing
Tanacon
Annie's old Empires were
Poor people have very long memories
And everybody has
Atrocities that the other side is committed over the centuries that they can point to as
A justification for what they are going to do now
Modern
For example
All the situation in the Middle East right now and how
To sit down with anyone who's involved in a
Close at hand with those conflicts
The first thing you find out if everyone has
A ton of bad things that they can
Pinpoint to the other side did
And after a while your head just spins because you don't even know where to start everyone's got such long memories
And there were so many bad things that have happened that they point to the other side is
Being responsible for
That you just don't even know how to solve
Back problem and untied gordian knot
But that's not
Compared to the ethnic
Memories
People in Europe
And anyone who remembers that
Breakup of the former Yugoslavia in the middle 1990s
Remember
That's a perfect example of how deep
Desatnick tensions go
You know we were all under the impression
That whole ethnic
Animosity between groups in those
Areas had been tamed and that those fires have been completely put out
Little did we know that
Heat under the ashes
Smoldering the whole time that all it took was a little gasoline poured on them
In a smoldering Heat
Flare up
And horrible things to be done and then when you went and questioned anyone
For example a Serb
Or acrylic or a Bosnian Muslim about it
They would point to the other side and talk about hundreds of years of awful things that they had done to them
You don't even know where to begin with
The worst situation of this
Happens in the first world war although it happens in a lot of places
I forget during the 1915 retreat
The Russians did a lot of terrible things to poles and Jews when these things get
Pale dog
In history book by comparison with what happened to the
Christian minorities in the Ottoman Empire
For example
The Greeks
Corbin inhabiting the
The Anatolian
Plain of Asia Minor
Since the Bronze Age
Or the Assyrian p
All the Christian Assyrian minority
In what's now
Kind of Northern Iraq
And who
Claim to be the descendants of the ancient
That's true
That's a weird horrible
Karmic wheel genocide coming around to hit them because
After all.
Biblical Assyrians are one of the
Very early confirmable
You know
Instigators of ethnic cleansing and genocide you can find
And of course
The most famous of all
The Armenia
The Armenians are in
Ancient
Who inhabit an area
During the first world war is kind of around where the borders of Russia
And the Ottoman Empire come together
To hiss
Historic arch enemy
The Armenians are caught in the middle
And they always have been
Certain periods in history they've been able to form their own independent state
For example when Rome and Persia were little week they could do that and then as soon as Roman Persian
The ancient world got their act together from this while in a brownie
Armenia was the first official Christian state
Which did not particularly make the Ottomans enthusiastic
It's kind of part of the reasons
With the Armenians
In the Ottoman Empire had always been treated as second
Citizen
And they remind one
Of the Jews in Russia where
Periodically youku
Have these
Pogrom
Incidence of violence break out
Calling men women and children would just be slaughtered I mean there were
1895 1896
The sultan Ahmed
Did awful things in from 50,000 to 3
Hundred thousand Armenians
Died in just that one in there was another one a couple years later another one a couple years after that 1909 there was another one
And the Armenians
Between a rock and a hard place because part of them live in what
The Ottoman Empire
A part of their territory and ethnic group extends up into Southern Russia
An area by the way that Russia had been taking over over
For the past Century
So it's sort of a Battle Ground area
And you take this people that the ottoman Turks and never been that enthusiastic about anyway
And then you start this war remember the Russians in the church start fighting in late 1914 early 1950 and the Turks get
Defeated by the
They have that Napoleonic retreat with the Wolves reading all the Frozen people
And a lot of that army
Defeat the Turks in that battle
Who composed of Armenia
Armenians
From the Russian song
Date of the Border
A bunch of the Ottoman troops
In the defeated Army
We're also Armenians
And to make matters even more complicated
There were some Armenian Rebels
We're trying to create some sort of a state of Their Own
And who can blame them for wanting the wrong state after so much persecution for so long
But the way the Ottoman Empire Beauty
People
You know what the best of times was unreliable
Once the Russians win the important battle in late 1914 or early 1950s and the Turks feel their back up against the wall
Now they begin to worry that the Armenians on their side of the Border are positively dangerous
You know the ones who are loyal
Are potentially vulnerable to subversion or propaganda
Or maybe even having to do Guerrilla groups
You coerced them into cooperation through agile practices
Like killing collaborators as it's called
That's the best-case scenario worst case scenario you Armenian subjects are just loyal to the Core
And are hoping waiting and actively working behind the scenes
To help the Russians
To the Turkish government this is treason
They are
Feeling like you're either about to be or are being stabbed in the back and their government
As we said never all that enthused about Armenians anyway
Decide that a solution has to be found in their solution is to get rid of the Armenia
If you believe the official Turkish line
Getting rid of the Armenians Medrol okay
If you believe what
Majority of historians obviously Armenians believe
Getting rid of the men killing
The process when it began with systemic
One Village
After another
It was done with a certain amount of
Understanding
That it would be bad publicity
The
Christian Towers
Russia mainly but also Britain and France
Had often times used
Persecution against the Armenians and other Christian groups as an excuse to
Intervene in the internal affairs of the Ottoman Empire that's the way the Ottoman Empire was it got it
So then there was all the reason in the world not to publicize that you were doing this and not make a big deal out of
Official line of the Turkish government is the during
These efforts to move the Armenian people away from the trouble spot
It won't be a problem if you moving to say Syria
A lot on.
Through starvation
Do disease
Through hostile ethnic groups that never like the like the Kurds decided to take advantage and swoop in and killed a man in right there
Women in all the horrible things
But there's so much ever
That this was done
In the same sort of fashion that any one of us would recognize
Genocide being iffy
It was the Holocaust or Rwanda or it really reminds one of the former Yugoslavia a lot
And the trucks are very sensitive
Any Armenians are very angry that they won't admit it
You know this is where I get a little upset with this whole
The idea of genocide as an official
International crime
Only a rose in the
Middle 1940
And since that time
That word has become a legal High
Where it would if someone were actually
Convicted of genocide
I trigger all sorts of real-world ramifications
And so everybody does everything they can for the most part unless it's a pariah state
To find anything except genocide
Welts
Hundreds of thousands of people died
But it's merely a crime against humanity cuz there was no intent mean
Become a legalistic word where all these different things have to be mad at the
Big deal with disabled
Countries can find
Themselves
You dealing with sanction
Calls for reparations or issues with alliances or train deals
And turkey didn't want that nobody want
Even in countries
Did acknowledge
Their genocidal practices at one time
They were a group that have Arisen in the more trying to get that overturned in Japan there are right-wing nationalist now we're trying to now
Cover up and down play
Japanese genocide activities against China during the second World War
The most normal thing in the world
But we've all done it
That's why it's hard for me to understand
The Turkish
Attitude the decisive blow to their pride somehow
If they hadn't committed the genocide they be
Like one of the only people on the planet of any consequence it hadn't
Part of the shared Human Experience a sad is that sound
Go look at the Old Testament of the Bible
A book that Jews
Christians and Muslims all hold sacred
The god of the Old Testament orders
Genocide
After genocide
Chill
Everyone
Put the man
Women children and all the animals to the sword
The reason it's in the Old Testament
Is because that was such
Common behavior that those people at the time would have understood it
I've often said about slavery that we all have slave blood running through our ancestral veins
Somewhere
Same is true for
Genocide
We've all
Had ancestors
Who were the victims of genocidal attacks
And we've all had ancestors somewhere down the family tree
Who are the ones committing the
In their book why not kill them
Mall
Professor Daniel Sherrod and Clark McCauley right
The one of the downsides of this whole thing
Is that we act as though
That bad man
Or that bad people committed this unusual act when in reality as they say
Quote
Given the right circumstances
Normal human beings are all too ready to
He killed my cat
And quote
He will often hear the Turks in their own defense
When accused of
The Armenian Genocide saywell
Look at what was happening
To Muslims
And Turkish Folk
Who were in the Balkans
And we're being treated by those
Countries that had thrown off the Turkish yoke
Enough to rape and murder and all these horrible things and displacement
All that is totally true
But it doesn't alleviate Turkish Guild
Open the Armenian situation it just adds more people to the court docket
What happened to the Armenians
And other Christians in the Ottoman Empire during the
Time including Greeks
And Assyrians
WhatsApp
Between 500000 and 1.5 million
In Armenian
Women
Children
Men old people
Lots of rape
Horrible stories
Sounds like the einsatzgruppen under the Nazis
Sounds like Rwanda
Sounds like indonesi sounds most like
The former Yugoslavia in the 1990s on steroids
But I don't blame the Turks anymore than I blame the rest
Sport that human behavior
And what's interesting is
The Armenian Genocide actually overshadows something similar to it involving
The Russians retreating in 1915 from a German offensive in Poland
And at gunpoint taking hundreds of thousands of poles and Jews out
And a lot of those people never return
They were seen in the same way that the Armenians were seen by the Turks is unreliable disloyal elements likely to see
Side with the Germans
And interstingly enough in a wonderful sort of karmic way
A lot of the reports that are considered to be the most reliable
About what the Armenians were going
True
Come from the
Turks allies
The Germans
German advisors in military
An embosser
For telling their own government
The terrible things that are
Happening
To the Armenians
In that country
And then within a generation
Those story
Germany
That's how
Endemic
Whole idea
Chilling
Your enemies down to the last
Qunar
Terrible as this is
That's the way we are
Human being
And killing
Your enemies down to the last person
Is not just
Beginning to look like the equation in these horrible
Criminal
Genocides
Starting to look like the equation
In that algebra
Problem
If you're one of the military commanders in this convo
How you win the war
Not killing every man woman and child just killing
Every Soldier
You're on the other side
You know after
Another horrible battle on the Western Front
1915 when the Allies lose
Town of people to gain literally not an inch of territory
The French General Patton becomes one of the first Allied Commander to openly say
If this war is not going to be one by some miraculous
Breakthrough
Or some tactical or strategic
Bit of Brilliance that opens up
You know flying for a breakthrough
Going to be one by killing more of the enemy
Then we lose ourselves
The war's turning into a war
Attrition
And while that might sound like an ultimate Allied victory
Because if everybody kills
You know one person on the other side until there's no one left the Allies have a lot more people than the central
The problem with that
Little bit of mathematics
Set the Central Powers
Are killing
More Allied troops in a losing themselves
And will do so ever
Single month
Until almost the end of the war
So that mathematical equation is as yet
Unsolved
And I'm predict
But of course
Modern Nations
Pac-Man
At some point
They cry on
Which in this conflict has been ruled out by the Allies signing those treaty saying no one will make A Separate Peace
Which means they'll fight
Until
The political system
Were the armies
Or
The will of the soldiers to resist collapsing
By the end of 19
There's a couple of countries that look in real danger having that happen and even the countries that look quite a bit safer than off
Austria-Hungary
Oar Russia look
Even they are showing
Democrat
Vulnerability
Please can this war
Really go on
For another year
Pokemon longer than that
But not everyone's going to make
Don't forget you can now buy the classic
Hardcore History shows directly from iTunes
Just type in Dan Carlin in
The search window
And if you want you can still purchase osho's from Dan Carlin
One.com
Would you like to help us out
Help the podcast
Show
It's all we ask
Go to dancarlin.com for information on how to donate to the show
Like
Alice
Susie salmon
That's what
The child prodigy and genius Musical
Composer
Emotes artist
Supposed to answer when someone said how do you come up with your composition
Indy start with
The piano and then build off the battery start
Destruction and fill in the middle or
And he's supposed to say
But it comes to him
Like
The same time
All together
And that phrase keeps popping into my head because that's the biggest challenge
In telling this first world war story
The second biggest challenges the ungodly amount
Material
It is produced from many different
Countries in viewpoints
About the story I've never been so overwhelmed with material as I have been for this
And it's all controversial so you really need to read a bunch of different
In authors and viewpoints tutu
Get a sort of a nice
Broadview some of these
But the stories can't even be compartmentalize because they affect each other
What's going on in the Eastern front affects outcomes on the Western Front which affect outcomes in the Mediterranean theater and
So you can't even tell the stories
Separately they all have to
The kind of weave together and it's really easy with this much going on
To lose track of the story
So I thought we would have a rare
Little Rico
As to where we are right now so the broad Trends to get us up to speed
And a few thoughts
From the last show that I'd like to do
Just throw in a little extra
Love here at the end no extra charge
Just bring us up to speed make sure I cover
I have a list of things I want to make sure I
I hate to get through this whole show Tayo I left
That out
A quick recap
Can be done relatively soon
The war breaks out
In August 9th
A bunch of these countries have been ready for predicting yet they mobilize quickly it's all on a time scale and everybody
Launches their pre-war battle plan
Switch for the Germans is most famously called the Schlieffen
Advance through Belgium in a wide Arc
Smashed the French armies on the head while you're
Keeping them occupied to the front as well
That doesn't go too well
It does for a while
I mean the armies clash in the first month of the wars
Commonly referred to as the battle of the Frontiers
When you get these 19th century tactics
Running into twentieth-century mechanized Warfare
Which leads to the worst single month in terms of casualties that you're going to get in the whole War
Because you're not going to see
A lot of
Cavalry Charges against machine guns and artillery
Prepositions
After the first
That's when
The really
Mind-blowingly shocking things mean guys with armor and swords and white gloves and red pants and
A bayonet charging prepared positions I mean the whole thing is is Cookie and that last for bottom
The next month is what happens after the Germans
Lose the battle of the Marne
And they're sleeping play
Is broken
As of the second month of the wars then basically running away from there earlier position
Trying to find a place to regroup
Finding a really good place to regroup on the other side of the river rain
And digging it
And the Allies following them
Unable to take those
Wonderful positions on the other side of the river rain and digging in themselves
Inaugurating
Officially trench warfare
And you have the so-called race to the Sea
When the Germans and the French and the British you don't want to run into each other's prepare defenses anymore start trying to find a flank in the only
A open party
Of the battle line left
From the riveraine up north towards the sea
Both sides reach the sea before they find a flag
They have a couple of terrible battles including the first battle of Ypres up there and then
We settled down to the 1915 Warfare basically
Which is going to involve
Both sides launching offenses that don't do
And that City read the book sometimes they can make him exciting oh they almost broke through and all of their only been modern communication
But the bottom line is the bottom line
You have a bunch of battles during 1915 on the Western Front
Nothing changes
On the Eastern Front
Nothing changes either
But a lot of movement happen
Why do people die a lot of movement happens
The overall strategic situation Remains the Same
Because when the Russians and the Germans Clash right at the war start the Russians get crushed in a couple of big battles
Tannenberg masurian Lakes
Then they beat the austro-hungarians
The serbians be the austro-hungarian whole bunch of stuff happens when you turn around
And subtract all the deaths and all the movement everything else the situation is the same
The Russians are there
They're not defeated they can replace all their losses
And if you really want to chase them they'll run all the way back to Moscow like they did against Napoleon and like they'll do against Hitler
How do you really want to follow them all the way back there
So they don't have trench warfare they have movement Warfare
The movements not ending anything
And then of course
Because the Russians and the Turks start getting into it down in the south
The Russians at the Allies for help which leads to Winston Churchill's cabal
Having yet another good argument to argue that maybe we should take the Dardanelles with all these pre Dreadnought battleships
And then the Dardanelles happen
Here's what we can kind of
Add the Flop I was just promising you because
Remember one of the sidebar hope
With this Dardanelles campaign is that it might influence some of those countries down in that region
The head and decided which side to join yet but it was obvious that they were sort of taking bids
Italy most among them
They like the Allied been better
They saw the Dardanelles campaign looking pretty strong back in May 1915 you know when they were Landings and true
Assaulting the heights everyday and want to look like
Britain and France were strong
The Italians join the war
They instantly attacked the austro-hungarians
At really the only good spot on their border to do that
Because the rest of their borders basically the Alps
And basically the austro-hungarian have The High Ground although they find and have found recently
Almost like something out of the old Captain America comic books
In which Captain America Frozen in the snow except
Of course he was alive when they
Defrosted them
These poor Austrian
And Italian soldiers that their finding with these glaciers melting up in the Alps
In these caves and I mean they look
Perfect like they were frozen yesterday their uniforms their weapons
Their facial characteristics everything I mean it's crazy it's like a time capsule of the most
Grotesque kind
Nevertheless the one area that's good for fighting
At least compared to the Alps
It's on the river re songs
The Italians attacked the austro-hungarians right away at the river is Alonzo
And lose
So then they attack again on the River Song so this will be called the Second Battle of the river so I'm gonna lose again
They do it again third bottle
Riverssance all they do it again the 4th.
River sounds
By the last year of the war there on the 12th
Battle of the river isonzo
And hundreds of thousands have died
And in fact
In only 6 months of warfare the Italians will have 200,000 casualties and are quickly
Playing catch up
With the rest of
The power I should point out something by casualty
Please do we keep using that term in its worth to finding it
Casualties of the military term in many of you know
And it simply refers to the loss of battle
Your general and it's your army were talking about
Casualties simply means
The number of people you don't have available to fight
Those who've been killed those who've been wounded those who've been captured and those who are missing
So when I say casualties
That's what it means all the missing in this war usually means
Dad if I say Dad well
That means killed in action
Tell the Italians 200000 casualties within six months
The other power that gets into the war does so in October
And it's the bulgarians another one of these Powers at Churchill and his friends at home
To convince
To join the Allied side when they saw how the Dardanelles campaign was going but by October the Dardanelles campaign is really going poor
Morley and the Bulgarian have been promising good land and they don't like the serbs anyway so they joined with the Germans in the
The austro-hungarians all three of them promptly attacks Serbia
And knock them out of the war
Nobi the story this harrowing story of
Serbian Army
I'm going all the way through Albanian
Mountain passes like a bunch of
REITs starving until they reach the C&O be evacuated by French British warship to fight another day
One thing I wasn't sure if I mentioned in the story you know we talked about the Second Battle of Ypres where the Germans use
Poison gas for the first time
In a successful way was used on the
Eastern front in a weird way once
But after the Second Battle leave for the Allies start using gas to and by the end of 1915
The standard mix of shells is you want some high explosive in your mix
And you want some shrapnel shells in your mix which are like giant balls filled with tiny little babies when they explode is like a
Giant hand grenade going off
And then the last shells you want mixed into your little Triad
Infrared Fitness are your gas shells
SO gas high explosive shrapnel you shoot it all the same time
It makes a nasty little cock
For the poor troops
The ground
Everyone got gas and everybody wearing gas masks now
And you end up with these images that are still to my mind
The greatest images of
The first world war cuz they say the most
When you'll see for example I love the one that shows
A German
Cavalry
Lancer
In 1916 or 1917
Who's wearing
The Stahl Helm which will come into Vogue in 1916 which is basically the same basic design you'll see the
German Army have in the second World War II is wearing like a German wehrmacht Helmet
Little Lamb
On a horse
And wearing a gas mask
He's like half medieval Knight
And half Stormtrooper from Star Wars
And that to me encapsulate what this war is these meetings of the modern world with the pre-modern world
Like a historical Estuary like I said
And in fact
You know what seat is Uber modern because really there hasn't been a major war fought with gas
Since this
Time. I mean there been incidents
Of chemical weapons and gas use
But you've never had the major mean the second world war there was no
Also it should be obvious that there have been several theaters that have not gotten much or perhaps
Any attention
From yours truly and it's not because I don't find them interesting and I think you could do a whole
Podcast just
On
The African experience in the first World War
But it's not important to the out
Come of the first world war when you have to chop in places for
4 time these are long enough already
You naturally look at the Pacific in the first World War
Or Africa because it didn't affect the outcome
What had more of an effect on the outcome
Are the soldiers from those two areas that were trucked into places like the Western Front and who fought the
Lots of North Ave
Lots of sub-Saharan
Lots of people from the Far East fought on the Western Front
And places like the Dardanelles
And eventually at Salonika and places like that
In the funny way
The place where
Africans and Asians had the most impact on the war going one way or the other
Was the same Western Front that
We normally think of as being a British
French Canadian
Soda preserving
Down the road and American Way
So by the end of 1915
You basically have a static situation
Western Front
Stays unchanged
Eastern Front keeps moving around
But everybody still standing there facing each other
Dalian Turkey
The war's been extended to down there but it's just stable
Turn of the reasons this is called the year of
Stalemate in the first World War
If you want to talk about something new that has happened
Helmets
Just started right
We mentioned the German stahlhelm a minute ago the first one is the French help
But then the British metal helmet than the German one appears
And it's one of those things that doesn't seem like a big deal but all of those helmet designs will be the basic design
That the second world war helmets
They'll all look very familiar and being
Vogue for quite a while at least in their basic
Look the German one change
Oil change
But also
Because it boggles the mind
And a little bit
Doesn't it
If you don't get your first metal helmet really till late 1915 which means all these people have been
Fighting the most artillery intensive war in human history by far
With cloth
Hats
On their head
Digging holes in the ground where the only thing that's exposed to fire
Is the top of your head and it's
Covered by a hat
And forget the obvious thing about like shrapnel exploding in the air and just you know hitting you in the head
So many of these shells don't come all that close to you they just blow.
Tons of rocks and stuff up in the air that then come down and land on your
Had
How many
Casualties
From the first
Where the war could you a tribute
The fact that none of these troops
Had metal helmet
It's crazy to think about head crazy to think that it took him a year to come up with that
More than
Finally
And I think this
Firmly belongs in the casualty area when we're discussing
10 casualties
Modern medicine
Change the situation
If you were studying military history
You'll notice a very interesting
Change
In the way the casualty death to wounded figure
Show up in the
Normally
The number of people wounded and the number of people who die are pretty close together and take the Crimean War
What happened in the 1800
More people died
From disease
Then from combat-related wounds that might have been a little extreme but not that far off the norm
By the first World War
That changes immensely
It's because
The medical situation has been Revolution
Modern
Military medicine really begins in
A lot of these doctors especially on the Western Front
Are doctors from private practice who have been drafted or
Joined and volunteered for the war effort they're often doing surgeries right near the front
These are people who live in the modern era when medicine is starting to be pretty darn good
And it completely changes the game I mean these people are not just able to save lives
And this is sort of a mixed by
I guess if you're a soldier
But they will be able for the nation-states that they work
Work to send a lot of these
Damaged soldiers
Back to fight again another day and sometimes multiple times
That ends up
Increasing
Ability of many of these states to keep fighting pass
Where they otherwise would have been able to
We don't have to do for example is look at the burn rate on some of these armies
By the end of
1950 by October 1915
The Russians are losing
235000 man
Every
Month
By the end of 1915 17 months into the war
The total Russian casualties were over 2 million man
I even though they could
Replace the human beings
What they can't do is
Replace
The morale
The capital
These are tells his French and British
Counterparts the end of 1915.
The population has turned
Pacifistic
An anti Ally
Meanwhile
The Western allies are having their own prom
The soldiers in the trenches starting to get a little uppity
About their willingness
The continued suicidal attack
Endlessly
That's not a good sign
Commander of the German forces
Is creating strategy
Is deciding that if they're really in a war of attrition why not designed the Battle 2
Who killed the most people instead of having breaks
Teresa maneuver isn't
All that
And Erich von falkenhayn
Create
Killing grass
To invite
The French Nation to bleed itself white in
The big fleets
Finally come out
How to play
And new technologies debut
Whose job it is to break this Log Jam
I'll trenches
Machine guns
Barbed wire
And gas
The year 1916 is sometimes called the breaker of Nations
It's going to be some Nations that suffer some Mortal wounds
Before that years old
Overall that
And more
Part 4
A blueprint for