Stay tuned at the end of today's program for information on where you can get more free hardcore history audio
Today Show is sponsored by Audible
Get a free audiobook with a 30-day trial membership if you sign up with audible today go to audible.com hardcore history
War
Text Hardcore History all one word
2500 - 500 to get started
December 7th 1941
A date which will live
It's hardcore history
The blitz Edition
I'm very interested
In pain
Not a masochistic Carissa District way
I'm interested in pain and suffering
For much the same reason that
Virtually All of You Are
Look at the entertainment you consume
Take out all of the physical and mental pain and suffering what do you have left
It's a source of Art and always has been
Because it's
Speaks to us on a human level
Does it matter how many things are different
With human beings Through the Ages and how much the culture changes us
How much the technology makes us different from our forebears
We can all understand pain
I think about it a lot
I say that I'm interested in the extremes of The Human Experience what does that mean
Sometimes I break it down I think it just means pain
Mental and physical
You start to wonder about being so interested in that by James Baldwin the writer
Wonderfully I thought when he pointed out that this connects us to each other
Any road quote
You think your pain and your heartbreak are unprecedented in the history of the world
But then you read
It was books that taught me that the things that tormented me most with a very things that connected me with all the people who were
Oral I've never been alive
And quote
It's such a strange thing this pain right this
Evolutionary
Adaptation that's probably saved more human lives than anything fear and pain together especially
The same time
Think of the loophole
I think it's a loophole that I wouldn't want to fight say that it's an evolutionary feature
Think of the
Loophole that the infliction of pain the ability to turn your own senses against U2
Hurt you
Think about what a huge role that's played in history
Going from a place where the pain is so useful to tell you you just put your hand on a hot stove
To a place where somebody else can put your hand on a hot stove
To hurt you deliberately for one reason or another then all of a sudden
Those sensors that keep you safe
Are the very
Weapon used to hurt you
To torment you and to compel you to do things against your will
Strange thing this
Sense
My reaction to other people's pain and suffering fascinating to isn't it
You can sort of run the gamut
Anywhere from
Empathy and sympathy
Two kind of
Amusement or enjoyment
Or
Maybe even you could say emotional voyeurism
But in our defense
Most of the time the kind of
Pain and suffering we're enjoying is
Back pain
Theatrical pain storytelling pain Hollywood pain and suffering
And no one getting hurt for real
But
The more real something seems
The more emotionally intense it can be and that can be more satisfied
My kids have been watching
Live performances of plays on television and they make a big deal about how it's live and in front of you in more real that way
And I thought what if they did
Action
Films or maybe not even the action film just the trailers the promos that run
Before the movie that you go to see assuming you still go to see movies
What is a
Did a live performance in front of an audience of that in a real car crashes
Real bullets in the real guns
What would be a horror show wouldn't it
I think they go quickly off-script is the bodies piled up at
No person in there
Decent sensibilities would go to watch people killed in public for entertainment
But of course we all know
The people have done that
Which is the normal behavior
The one that says oh my God torturing and killing people in public for entertainment is barbaric
For the people that say
As someone from a time. Where this was common and approved of behavior might say
Hey wait a minute
You just put a thin veil
Between what you like
And what we like
We both like the same thing
He just like yours to be faked
Whatever part of the brain is enjoying it maybe the same part is being titillated one way or the other
I'd like to warn those who might be squeamish
But this particular story is going to be very graphic indeed even by our standards
But the fact
That we need to issue such a warning
Because we might be too sensitive about this
Is it self fascinating
Because once upon a time there were people
Who would appreciate a warning also about this kind of stuff at the warning that they wanted was the one that it was going to happen
So they made sure they got there and didn't miss the live version
And in fact for a lot of them
So that they can get the jump on the high ticket prices that we're going to be charged for the rooms close enough for you to actually Witness
Smell see and hear
Tortures and executions done live
There's a lot of fascinating things about us I think
In the story I want to talk about today but it all revolves around
The question of pain one way or the other end in the lot of the stories that we talked about the pain is everywhere in the
StoryBots
Interspersed
And melded together with the topic in this story it is Center Stage
Once Upon a Time
Not that long ago
Human beings went to public executions were torture was a huge part of the event
In order to watch and enjoy it
What the heck is that
Well we never promised answer is around here cuz there's no one qualified to give them
Questions about what this might say about us either today or back then
Or
In perpetuity
Pretty fascinating to but as I said
Not for the squeamish and if you want the people who can't handle this good for you
Some of us
Are still fascinated by this
Reasons
That I like to think are
High-minded and educational interesting I hope it's just not a
Historical voyeuristic
Trip through time to do the equivalent of virtually sitting in the seat next to that
Spectator at the Roman Colosseum where he watches people devoured by lions
One of the things I have to keep reminding myself
Is that if I were born in a different place
In different time if you took a baby as I've always said from now in a time machine back to
This Roman era for example
You or your kid might be sitting down next to the guy eating the equivalent to popcorn while you watched wild beasts of
Flower people for your pleasure
It's obvious isn't it that there's a huge cultural influence on what's going on here
What's not obvious maybe at least not to me
Is which direction the cultural influences operating
Is it bloodthirsty times like the era of the Roman games in the Colosseum and whatnot
Creating
Bloodthirsty human beings that like this stuff or is it
Catering to
An innate need I mean this question gets
Really deep when you ask
What's the default human setting
Or whether or not you enjoy watching others pain and suffering For Your Entertainment
Because the really uncomfortable question is to say that yes cultural influences are playing a huge role in whether or not people like this stuff
It's modern-day culture
Just making that stuff not as popular that used to be in other words
The default setting of humankind is to enjoy the stuff in the Roman Colosseum and it's only modern
Enlightened
Thinking and rationality and empathy with other human beings that is
Sort of blunted that natural enjoyment
As we said a minute ago
The people from another time. Might argue if we started wagging are finger what they enjoyed
That we both enjoy the same thing
We just like our version to be fake
The human equivalent of that little
Disclaimer you get at some movies where they'll point out that no animals were actually injured in the making of This film
Well these days we feel the same way about people that have for quite some time no people were actually injured in the making
This piece of entertainment
But there are people who are purists
It would say wash
I don't go in for that kind of fakery
Make my
Torture violence and what not real
I'm not even sure
That that's true to be honest
Depends on
You know what side of the bed I woke up
In the morning I'll senecal I'm feeling but
It does occur to me from time to time
But it's an untested unproven sort of an assertion that we in the modern develop
Enlightened posted like the world that we like our violence fake when were the
When were the public ever given the equivalent of a blind taste test on this
If we released two movies very similar to each other on the opening Blockbuster Summer movie Seasons first day
And they have to compete head-to-head
And one is a traditional full of movie Magic in the actors all get-out
You know just doing fine so the film
Has to go head-to-head against a groundbreaking new piece of performance art
It is so unusual that several of your favorite actor did not survive the production of this film everything you see and it is real
Who do you think wins
You know after one week of ticket-buying you know how many people go to one film over the other what are the reviews
But I bet it's a hit
That would be weird when it is hard to imagine
So what if we imagine something that's just as weird but you could see it happening
Imagine some tin-plated
Dictator in some poor impoverished countries already executing
Everyone he thinks is a criminal anyway probably publicly to
How is own people and keep his regime afloat
What if he just decided listen
There's a demand for this I could treat it like
One of those restaurants that serves endangered species on the menu where people would pay $10,000 a plate just to taste something
That you never tasted before no one will ever taste again
How many people have seen a public execution we did they pay to go
Be interesting to think about list
Famous celebrities that might sign up for something like that just to say they went
Selfie from the
Live execution
I'd be interested just from the human experiment and data research soda
View of course
If the guy just inflated dictator decided to do it all Pay-Per-View globally
Esl
5995 get to see the execution will be some preliminaries with staging this for entertainment
Fire Winnie Stacy's big boxing tournaments righteous are you going to have opening acts
Walkout fighting is a whole bunch of things that go into keeping the public happy enough to want to buy this again
We don't get to be the dictator even of a chain plated
In a little country somewhere else without having a few
And bits of understanding how to play the crowd
I'd be very interested the day after
Something like that occurred
To look at the statistics of which countries which regions which peoples
Body to the pay-per-view more or less when did be interesting to see which country shunned it or hardly bought at all
Which is which countries
Really bought more than their share
I think that would be some interesting human data
Then I suppose we would have to hope that something like that when the numbers didn't show up
But they didn't show it was some sort of hit
Can you imagine how that would
Blow open the door to incentivizing any number of cash-starved tin-plated dictators
To Elbow their way into the
Lucrative in a virtual execution tourism Market
But even if something like that happened there is a layer of emotional protection mean you're not there
Just like there's a layer of emotional protection
Between you know a live 5995 pay-per-view execution and what a lot of people look at online right now
You can go see
Historic footage of assassination attempts and executions heck you can go watch
Some of the Nazis hung for their war crimes not the
Big people in Orangeburg that there were lots of other
A punishment down the line and some of them are online and I don't think you were statist if you view it not at all
There's something different is it that happened a long time ago
There's some Detachment and it being a two-dimensional image maybe even a black-and-white certainly grainy whatever
Takes you
More and more away from the scene and there's
You said yourself this is like watching a boxing match 35 years ago
I know the outcome and no one's hurting right now so somebody got hurt in that fight it's long over
But if you're watching it live it's not
Let me just contemplate for a minute the idea of watching an execution live I mean if the laws change where you live in all of us
This became possible and they were going to have one
In the nearest good-sized city near you
How many of your friends and neighbors do you think would show up to watch
Do you think there be a difference between
You know people who make a lot of money and people who don't make alot of money people have one religious Faith or people have no religious Faith or another
You see what I'm saying would be interesting to see
Who showed up and why just has a
Mass Humanity psychological experiment
Would you go
If you did
What do you think would be the motivation curiosity
Or
The idea that listen this isn't some stage thing like
You binge-watch on TV Anything could happen right you don't know what's going to go on one of these things
And if it was weird the first time that it happened how long
Do you think how many of these things would it take before people became comfortable with
If they ever became come
People with it
Let me blow your mind for a minute if you don't already know about
This
Let's talk about an execution
That occurred
Not in the Middle Ages although you would think it was from there when you hear it
Execution occurred in Paris
Not all that long ago as a matter of fact to give you an idea of context
George Washington is a full grown adult and is already
Been through a war and commanded troops in battle for the British
It involves a guy who tried to kill the king of France in
B1750
And in March 1757
He was going to pay for that crime
And hundreds of
Thousands of people
Flocked into Paris
To make sure they had a chance to see it
And according to historian Paul Friedland
The people of Paris
Love
Execution
He said that he italicized the word love
He had said that the
Sovereign like all Sovereign throughout the history of the world that want to tell their people to stay in line that they were hoping that these
Public executions would terrify the population and
You know enhance the political sovereignty of the ruler but as Friedland points out
That's not always why the people were there and that's not always what they got out of it he says in the preface to his book
Seeing Justice Done
Quote
But I hope to make clear in this book however
Spectators of executions in early modern France did not tend to see the penal spectacle as a manifest
Station of political sovereignty
Neither were they terrified
In fact I loved attending execution
From the 16th to the middle of the 18th century
Public executions in France
Extraordinarily popular with Spectators from all social class
Many of whom were so desperate to watch that they rented out windows overlooking the place of execution at exorbitant
Dim sum
Or staked out Prime viewing spots near the scaffold run nearby rooftops off and days in advance
And quote
And what was the mood of this crowd that
Stormed into Paris that day to watch this event
Friedland wrightson
Please excuse my traditional mangling of the French language when I
Disgusting
Traditional execution site in Paris
Quote
Every credible primary source give the impression that the people who own the plaza to grab that day
Could barely contain their excitement
Is the Fateful hour near
Terror could not have been further from their minds
Unless of course we count the terror of missing even a minute of the spectacular show that was about to take place
And quote
He then talks about
A guy
Colette
Is his name would like to go to these executions
And how he showed up
Quote on that special day he arrived bright and early to see the show
Friedland rights
And brought along with in the 18th century equivalent of movie popcorn
Now quoting from
Galette
Writings
Quote
I showed up at 7 in the morning
And found a good many of the windows of the rooms on the graph already filled with Spectators of both sexes
I was placed by Madame Superior The Establishment had a window on the first floor
And I had as companions and curiosity three gentlemen
I added my little store of Provisions to theirs and around noon We Dine together with a fineapple
Appetite
And quote
Ladies and gentlemen
Batman 2 describing an 18th century version of a tailgate party
And it will be hours before the event itself takes place he people are partying it up in anticipation of this
Guide event
And this giant event
Is gruesome
Any extreme
And what were these people so excited to watch
Well
The most
Spectacular and that's the words of many different people not me
Execution of that age and it was spectacular cuz it was unusual cuz they hadn't done one of these
Really nasty ones in a while so everyone wanted to see it
What's so nasty about it
Well it was published ahead of time what was going to happen to this guy
He notices so that people would know what they were coming to watch
And so they would know exactly what happened to people who tried to
Sticking knife between the Kings ribs
The Prisoner was sentenced to have big chunks of his flesh torn out of his breasts
Arms thighs and calves
His right hand
Which is held the knife this is very symbolic
What's to be burned it said by fire and sulfur
And then all the places where he had the flesh torn out of his
Body would have and I'm quoting here
Molten lead boiling oil burning resin
Wax and sulfur melted together
Poured right into the womb
And then his body was to be dismembered by four horses
Can we gain this Bears some
Delving down into what we're talking about here in this is gruesome but I'm sorry but
This is juxtapositioning
What weird
Seeing here with these human beings who want to go watch it
And the more horrible it is
For many of us the harder it is to understand the desire to be there
Involved in the process
But an enormous crowd of people turned out to do just that
And a very famous book called discipline and Punishment
The officer of the watch this executions account was reprinted
This is a primary source
Pairs with
The crowd saw
Quote
The sulfur was lit but the flame was so poor that only the top speed of the hand was burnt and that
Only slightly
Denny executioner his sleeves rolled up
Took steel pincers
What you been especially made for the occasion
And which were about a foot-and-a-half long
And pulled first at the calf of the right leg
When is the thigh
And from there
At 2 fleshy parts of the right arm
Then at the breast
There was strong sturdy fellow this executioner found it so difficult to tear away the pieces of Flesh
But he said about the same spot two or three times
Twisting the pincers that he did so
Emily took away form did each part of wound about the size of a 6 lb Crown piece
After these pairings with the pincers
Damian Who Cried Out profusely the without swearing The Source says
Raise his head and looked at himself
The same executioner dipped in Iron spoon in the pot containing the boiling potion Witchiepoo
Poured liberally overreach wound
At each torment
He cried out as the Damned in hell are supposed to cry out
And now he's saying what The Condemned is screaming
Pardon my God pardon Lord
Despite all the pain The Source says
He raised his head from time to time and looked at himself boldly
And quote
Some have theorized that this condemned victim was mentally ill
And that
He committed this crime and then paid this punishment and these days would have been seen as psychologically unbalanced
The fact
That the crowd could watch all this though and not be made psychologically unbalanced is interesting
The AC control in the Hanging Tree
Points out
That you do not have a bunch of people watching
Those proceedings we just described
Vomiting or anything
How many people could come back
From our time period now be placed in the crowd to watch this thing live
And not vomit
It's strange to think of something that seems like an
Automatic uncontrollable response
Being something that's actually
In a culturally influenced by control points out that crying is laughing is what you find
You know I'm using is I mean all these things that may seem to be
Hardwired into what are cultural distinctions including whether or not you vomit
While watching a horrible torture execution or maybe
Whether or not you like it
Storing Garrett G Fagan
Recants the Great
Rake
Casanova who is there
And walk Casanova was appalled
He looked at other people
And not only weren't the Apollo they were liking it
He says this is fake and writing quote
Casanova who considered the spectacle quote and offense against our common humanity and quote
Reports that he several times closed his eyes
And blocked his ears to the atrocity
But that his companions were riveted by the spectacle and never once diverted their gaze
They felt no compassion for Danielle and they said due to the enormity of his crime
Casanova's friend to redis
Even had surreptitious sex with one of the women while the ghastly execution proceeded
Other eyewitnesses describe members of the crowd especially the ladies watching with detached disinterest
Reven chattering and laughing
And quote
I should point out that this was a particularly extra nasty execution
The these people enjoyed
Because The Executioner's really didn't know what they were doing
Been done one of these executions in a while
And when things didn't go as planned they had to improvise for example when they were trying to tear this person apart with four
Horses pulling in different directions
He didn't tear apart
They had to work
You know by cutting the joints and seeing if that would help with that didn't help the head to start pulling the limbs in different directions
And people
Would have considered this because they were looking for novelty and the unexpected perhaps
An added
The reason this is so interesting
Is how many of us could have gone
I seen that
What's different about us
And people only a couple hundred years ago
Who has I said didn't just go and watch this and endure it
Let's sacrifice and paid a lot for the privilege
Are we the more normal example of
People on the default setting when it comes to watching
Other people suffering
Or they
Or maybe that's too cut-and-dried a distinction
Maybe it depends
On who's the pain and suffering is being experienced by
What if the person
Who is providing the entertainment the person being torn apart the hapless victim
Is not in fact
So hapless
And maybe has a lot of victims themselves every what if you are doing this to a horrible
Murderous dictator
You think you're bad people from history
I always throw Hitler in there because he sort of my quintessential example but you can fill in the blanks write you have some terrible terrible person
Go Saddam Hussein maybe in a rock and let the Shiites in Iraq
Watching being torn limb to limb
Does that take an attitude which if it was anyone else you would be horrified that you were enjoying watching this
Spectacle because it's that
Demonic individual
You going to enjoy every last shriek
Now the actual idea
For this
Talk today this discussion came to me
After re-reading a book that's very interesting it's the
It's a book about the diary of
An executioner
Lived in the
In 15 1600 in that.
And it was fascinating because
It reminds us that there are multiple shall we say
Viewpoint
In all of these Affairs that we were just discussing these tortures terrible execution will obviously
We've been focusing on the audience the people that would like to watch this stuff and isn't that sick
Or
Maybe not depending on what
Really
Human
But there are other angles
They're just as fascinating that book on the Executioner
It was fascinating to think about the person tasks
Would you doing this I was bad as it is to watch it
What about the person who molested
Carry out the actual things
The modern sensibilities would suggest even watching should make you sick
So that became
The Germ of an idea to look at this for multiple Vantage points because you have
The crowd
The Executioner and of course the vantage point
Of the victim
If you want to
Wonder about what goes on in the minds of people in extreme situations
What is it like to mount that scaffold
Haven't had plenty of time to think about what you're about to face
Get up there and look out
A crowd of thousands of people that have come to watch you go through with your about to go through
And then begin to go through it
Bit by bit
Sometimes
For hours on end
If you want the understatement of the century there's a quote attributed to
Robert Francois
As he's let out to go begin his ordeal that would take hours and end up with him in pieces
He just said
Rumor Has It Anyway
It's going to be a hard day
I wonder if there was a way to add up all the people in human history
The found themselves in that same position that
It's going to be a hard day
So the position execution victims since the dawn of time
I wonder how many of those people there were
I mean public executions have pretty much been going on since history has been
Written down right we all understand
But it's not
Ubiquitous it's not everywhere all the time but my goodness
You know the amount of
Cultures over the arrows that utilize public executions
He is far more common than not
As we said earlier it's an obvious purpose for the state doesn't it
It's a message
And the Assyrians
In one of the earliest people to carve this message in stone showing what they did to people who broke their
Biggest laws
That's a way of making sure that even if you weren't there to watch it live you can still get the message
Herodotus the so-called father of History so that's how far back we're going here
Tells the story which may or may not be true
That one of the early Kings of Persia can't Pisces II
Force the Nobles of Egypt
To convene in a public place to watch 2000 of their children killed in front of them
That's not for entertainment value because you can't imagine a more horrifying seeing if that were true right away
What is that sound like
But it sends a message doesn't it from the ruler Persian all the people in Egypt
Interstate Concord
Or this will happen again
The Chinese having been around essentially forever is a civilization also
Very familiar with the use of public executions
As a tool of
Of enforcing state power and sovereignty
And they've been around so long they've been able to
Live through many different eras
Where are the ideas of legal reform and capital punishment will change
Some more liberal some quite Draconian indeed
The Chinese are one of the very early civilizations
To attempt to deal with crime
In a way that sometimes comes into Vogue
This idea that
What if you just punished every little teeny crime in the most severe way
Wouldn't that just deter everything
Moron that later
In the new world of course there are plenty of examples the Aztecs with their
Tearing of the beating heart out of the sacrificial victims were there war captives or not
In the northeast of the United States famously other tribes there used to torture people to death in the tri would gather round and
Take part in it including
Allegedly children to
In the Warrior wood
You know who is being tortured or the woman who is being tortured or what have you would defiantly
You know
Resist the torture is me could go on for days
All these things someone who probably point out
Have a religious element to the
There's a huge ritual involve so maybe it's not so much
You know that these humans are getting a kick out of watching this thing
There are other deeper questions involve which is true but one wonders how much it alleviates
The fact that people may have been having a good time watching this you can't tell for example
You look back on the Assyrian reliefs the carvings were they show
But they are impaling their victims on Stakes
You can't tell if there's a crowd there and there be no way to tell if they were having a good time
You first start seeing that phenomenon
In Rome
Bright
Famously
At the gladiatorial games
And people showing up the way you would go
To a pro wrestling match today
If the wrestlers were fully armed
And left a lot of dead people at the end of the show on the ground
And animals by the way
This is where you clearly can see because the records are so good
And the
Connection between enjoyment
And horrific
Torture and
Suffering
Is so obvious
Mean you can write it off 900 different ways but at the end of the day
These people are enjoying themselves and going to Great Lengths
To make sure they don't miss
In these horrific
Murderous encounters that will play out in front of them in real time
So let's look at Rome for a minute
As part of an evolution or maybe you could call it like you don't really like to grasp history
If you had a wonderful graph like a stock market graph for periods in time we're human beings overtly wanted to
You do this more for whatever reason including
A culture that might really encourage it
The Roman gladiatorial game era
Maybe the high watermark in history on that graph because it's hard to find anything
White so
Brazen
About the commercialization
Marketing
And
Staging
Of
Torture and death
As a spectator event
When it's fascinated people for a long time
I mean cuz it's so obviously an interesting question about
Humanity and Human Nature
Rome's Arenas and the violence that was perpetrated in them in the
The almost modern marketing of
The understanding of what the customer wanted and how things should be advertised in the order that it is
When should happening
As I said a minute ago stage
And also many of the modern media
So the Dynamics were also implied the need to continually for example
Provide new and novel and more inventive and grandeur
Spectacles to keep the people coming back
And there's all sorts of theories on how this developing
There's this linear progression from in a very early Roman things and then layer-by-layer new things get added three
Example when Rome becomes Morgan Empire
It starts conquering more far-flung places you begin to see
The importation of exotic animals from strange locale
And this becomes part of the van right when an animal show the local arena
And the people can come and look at the animals but somehow that turned into
People can come and look at the animals kill each other and have men kill the animals that animals kill the men in
Listen to the scale of what we're talking about this becoming eventually
And bear in mind this idea that once upon a time
It'll probably advertising that you had a giraffe and a monkey and an elephant might be enough to bring the people into the seats
But eventually you got to go
Two extremes
Will Durant writing a long time ago
Says quote
The simplest event in the amphitheater was an exhibition of exotic animal
Gathered from All the known world
Elephants
Lions tigers crocodile
Hippopotami lynxes
Apes
Panthers
Boars
Bears
Wolves
Giraffes
Ostriches
Leopard
Antelopes and rare birds were kept in the Zoological Gardens of Emperors and Richmond
And we're trained to skillful exploits
Or marry prank
Apes were taught to ride dogs
Drive chariot
We're acting plays
Bulls let boys dance on their backs
Sea lions were conditioned to bark an answer to their individual names
Elephants
Dance to symbols
Struck by other elephants
Where they walked on a rope
Or sat down to table
Or Rhodes Greek or Latin letters
And quote
Sounds like something you take your kid to at this point doesn't it
Durant then continue
Quote
Animals might be merely paraded in brighter humorous costume
Usually however they were made to fight one another
Or with men
Where they were hunted to death with arrows and javelins
In one day under Nero 400 tigers
Fought with balls and elephant
On another day under Caligula 400 bears were slain
At the dedication of the Colosseum 5000 animals died
Is the animals wish to compromise
Meaning not fight each other
They were stung to combat by lashes darts and Hot Irons
Claudius made a division of the praetorian Guard fight Panthers
Nero made them fight 400 bears and 300 lions
And quote
Now let's just stop for a minute and think about this
Can you imagine what that looks like we talked about some of the greatest show men in the modern era and the
Sorts of exploits they pulled off
Who's the promoter that comes up with the idea of let's have
Hundreds of the royal guard fight hundreds of lions
And what does that look like
Here's the thing though
We might do a movie
Today
With the concept of a war between
Human armies in Lion Army 300 praetorian guard against 300 lions
But it involves a lot of CGI and stuff like that when did a lot of Graphics maybe your computer and all that the Romans
Don't mess with any that they didn't have the ability obviously but at the same time you know maybe they didn't like their
Wild crazy fantasy stories fake
Do you want to see human armies against
Lion armies don't turn it into a Lord of the Rings movie
Do it live
On the stage in front of an audience
It's an absolutely
Crazy seem to imagine though isn't it
No matter how you break it down
That is so weird
Would you watch it if it were on
Available from some video site right now
Would you watch it live
Now here's the thing
That falls in the weird category to me more than it falls into the
Terrific stuff
Well that's a terrible thing to say but but I mean in terms of just raw human cruelty
There's almost a sporting element to the other if you really sort of sick
The Lions might win
For the people might win the mean
In one of the injector stand about the Roman too many if you've course already do is they will bet on anything
And just because we're pointing out the really Bloodsport aspect of what they loved they loved it all
Horse races chariot races sporting events that were bloodless I mean all of it
And a good day at one of the Arenas like one of the good ones in Rome rooms like the New York City in the Broadway of
Of these sorts of shows bigger better and
All the highest caliber performers are in Rome
The other Arenas are some of the Off-Broadway people
But a full good day at a place like the Forum involves all sorts of stuff with the violence be
Being just one element in a good promoter and somebody staging this thing the right way knows how to make
Some performances Maybe by your favorite singers with some good stuff in between some religious messages here or there for the kid
What's a whole bunch of stuff and if you were really good
Lunch time at lunch time you run down to the bottom of the Coliseum and everybody would get lunch at the same time but of course you know
You still got to have something for the people who are coming back with their lunch a little early you can't have
Nothing on stay so that was when
You know the pure executions would often take place
Lunch time
The Roman writer say they're usually less people in the stands but because of the empty seats
Those people
You don't have more of a chance or so the influence the way things went naked yell stuff out and
People would do what they said sometimes another words to please the crowd if you had some person that you were slowly
Putting to death in front of the people that have come out of the food quarterly
And they had a good suggestion you do it for him write anything to keep their folks happy and coming back next week
And once again you can't help but sit there and go
Who else ever did that
Some of these histories I've been reading make it plain that
You're normally and I tend to fall into this category to you think everything has happened before somewhere
In history right there's nothing new Under the Sun is the old saying goes
But you'd be hard-pressed to find
Any widespread
Similarity anywhere else to what the Romans were doing
In these games except for these territories that the Romans took over and spread the Games 2
One of the
Interesting arguments used against those who suggest that this is a particularly Roman thing
Is how popular these games were
When they sprouted up in places that have never had them before in the locals found that they like them
Quite a lot to
But this
Ability to actually control what was done to the victim
The giving the mob essentially the people with the loudest voices are the highest paying customers
The right
To control the action is like a god-like power
Think about
The virtual reality video game
Element that I just been added to a real
Situation in real time
It's registering Gary Chief egg and rice
Lights quote
The execution phase of Arena spectacles
Cannot have been anything other than viscerally brutal
This was sheer murder
The disposal of what was considered human garbage
While the Roman writer
Seneca
Was repelled by what he saw during the lunch time break
He recorded various comments that the people shouted out is The Butchery proceeded
They demanded various types of action
Seneca adds a further noteworthy detail often-overlooked
All of this happened when the arena was practically empty
Pure Butchery apparently was not to everyone's taste
And quote
Eden points out that Seneca trying to make a point about how we know
Crowds are bad for your morals and attend
Go down to the lowest common denominator essentially in a crowd
But then he says quote
Seneca's account reveal something of the spectators mental state
During execution
Their ability to direct the course of action on the sand would have strengthened an already formidable sense of him
Empowerment
Indeed the ultimate sense of empowerment
Over life and death itself
This was one of the clearest manifestations of the crowd as Domini
Lords of the Arena
The crowd nearly called out its wishes to see them enacted
And quote
It's at this point I had to take three steps back for a sec
That is such a wickedly weird
Concept
If you think about it I mean if you really go
What the heck was that like
To have a person
Walking to the arena
Is Dermatology Kyle describes the missing you naked or nearly naked
With a placard eater
Held with them around their neck
Explaining what their crimes are in their sentence
Is and then tying them to a
Steak
Or he says
Alternatively
Just leaving them in the arena alone unarmed
To face the Fate
Davis sentenced fate that they're supposed to face but as
Astorian
Garrett G Fagan pointed out
It might be open to interpretation depending with the crowd one that you want to burn somebody there's fire there you want
Rip pieces of the map Arthur's implements available
You want to pour something hot molten metal of some sort on then we got some right here
As I said before I am fascinated by the extremes of
The Human Experience
And I'm not sure
There's anything far greater in terms of extremes and being a condemned
Imprisoner is going to die
The execution
If you had a scale of like
Easiest way to be executed and hardest way to be executed I think these days we do it about as easily
As we can make it Lethal Injections and stuff like that
Our sensibilities are different than the sensibilities of these earlier eras
Where
People dying execution wasn't
The goal
It was a byproduct
Did the goal goal was the suffering and in the case of Rome the suffering wasn't just to pay for the crime
It was to entertain the crowd
I'm hard-pressed to find a situation
In terms of being executed and putting yourself in the position of the condemned
It would frighten or scare me or drive me out of my mind as I thought about what was going to happen as much as
The situation
You know in the Roman Arena
But this may be personality Bass
Can you go to some of these other cultures the Japanese thought about every way that they can
Possibly kill convicts and prisoners and people they don't like for example
Maybe they'll boil you
Does it help if you know that's what they're going to do tomorrow morning you're going to get boiled
It was a history I was reading
Connected to this and I'm going from memory here
But they've been talking about someone who's going to be beheaded in the morning and then the question was how does one prepare
Hair themselves
For that
The night before
What's going through your head
What are the mental and physical preparations I mean it's not the kind of thing that most people
Throughout history have had to think about right although
We all know is I think I said earlier if you added up all the people throughout history that have been in this position it's a sizable number
If you're someone like
Yourstruly though
And someone says you have a choice between knowing what they're going to do to you tomorrow or not knowing what they're going to do tomorrow
Banality wants to know
For whatever reason
So for me the idea that you could go into this Arena ostensibly to be lit on fire and burned to death but
But you know if the crowd has a better idea we may go with that that would frighten me more
Then having someone's everything to tear you apart tomorrow with Tom
At least I can sort of mentally
Prepare myself how would someone
Prepare themselves to be beheaded in the morning
It would sure help to know that that's what was coming at least
Is my personality is sort of organized
Now what might they do to you
Well
The sky's the limit in terms of the inventiveness of man of try to figure out ways
Not just ways to
You know add a little
Variety to the situation but ways that would even
Entertain the crowd
If you go down the list of things
Crucifixions on their butt crucifixion slow
So they often would combine
Donald G Kyle says
Crucifixion with some other punishment that they like
Fire was used a lot they like fire in the arena
But you know and it surprised me to actually read this I didn't know this
The Kyle says that the number one way people died in the arena
Do to Beast
In a wild animal
And while I knew that that was big in the arena I had no idea
But it might be the number one cause of
Death to the people they were dragging out of there
I dunno and Kyle has something in his notes about it where he says
That there was quite an emphasis
On finding these animals
For the arena by the way just like there was a big emphasis on finding the people for the Arena 2
It's very strange to think about this but here in the New Media world we always talk about needing content
To keep the audience satisfied will
If you think about it that way and they did
The content that was needed
At these games and not just the ones that wrong but all the Off-Broadway areas to
Worthy
People
Who's going to die in the arena while we got some slaves and
This is actually true they have
New accounts where they try to figure out okay we got some slaves from this Uprising in
Are you there
Okay let's parcel them out they need them for games here they needed for games here I mean literally it is providing content for these shows
And as I said there's other things that the show the performers in magicians and jugglers all kinds of fun things
But if you were to look at the
Posters that they put up all over the city announcing
But these are coming
The violent parts are often
What are the main events
And in terms of animals to get back to the Beast
Question
Kyle says that they wanted
Real wild ones I didn't want anything raised in captivity they didn't want anything that have been in captivity very long because
After all if you're selling we have a lot of wild Lions on your little posters all around your City to get people to come to the show
You don't want them to get there and find out that the Lions don't do much cuz they just waiting for you to throw their typical meat lunch to them
You want something that's going to go after these people you've tied to the crosses
And I should point out
But I don't want to go there because there's a lot of controversy
At the how far you can take
What was going on in the arena because there's accounts that
May or may not
Try to overhype some of this stuff
But there are stuff and it again I don't want to get into it
I mean there's stuff about women are going to come in here and be forcibly raped by Bulls before their
Put to death any whether or not these things happen the thought that that would even be thrown out there
Buy some inventive mind is something that people would like to see
Is extremely disturbing
For modern person
And this is perhaps a sexist way of thinking but I think it's ingrained in some of us
The idea of watching women die in the arena
Is more upsetting than watching the men but it didn't seem to bother the crowd at all
Watching women ripped apart by Beast was going to be just as fun as watching Men ripped apart by bees
It's hard
For we modern people to get our minds around this especially since to me this is so different than say the Gladiator fights
Which maybe we could conceive to something
It's
A much more push to the edge version of things we already like
Ever been to a big boxing fight
In Las Vegas or something
I mean this is a violent sporting event
The buzz amongst the crowd and there's almost nothing I've ever experienced like it you think yourself well
Listen to It's very barbaric but you could see the same sort of interplay going on in terms of whatever parts of our brain are being
Stimulated
It's boxing
Plus
It's pro wrestling with weapons for real
And
As all sporting events
You don't know who's going to win training may come into it coaching strategy tactics I mean sports fans could get into something like
I got you bet on it I could see it
To me these executions that were different
And even if most of the crowd didn't go in for The Butchery
Like a professor Fagan had said
Certainly a number of people did
I'm reminded of another quote by Seneca
Talking about the games and it was like a throwaway line but it was something about how
He was insinuating you couldn't allow even a dull moment
Between acts in a call so that the crowd or something could be affected called for some throat-cutting in the meaning
In time so that they wouldn't get bored
Again throwaway line but the horrific nice of the actual imagery if you imagine it
Is sobering
Why did the Romans like it
And how did they just
I don't think you seem like
The most logical follow-up questions
The why they liked it part we're going to continue to talk about cuz it's really sort of the focus here
I mean the obvious things that come to mind right away is curiosity
But any of these Seneca and you came for all the other stuff
And you just got grossed out by the violence probably not but maybe
Or maybe you're curious you want to see what this looks like
One of the other
Things that's talked about in events like these is even if you've been to many of them before this is not scripted Conte
This is like a live sporting event in the sense that you don't want to DVR it and hear what happened later you have to be there cuz
Something weird could happen and sometimes.
This curiosity
There is sheer sadism and sadism the weird thing I think in my opinion until
Totally non-academic an unqualified but
But doesn't it seem like some of the tendencies
They're more unusual on an individual level become more common on a crowd level so whereas it might be
Rather rare to meet someone who's a sadist in a crowd of people
As a crowd of people I think we're more sadistic
The whole is greater than the sum of its parts Maybe
Got a Thang
I guess for how the Romans Justified this cuz let's remember
By our modern standards they are harsh and brutal and strict even in this. Where it's at
Off their High these to be stricter there
Loosening up a little by our standards they're still very strong
The Romans were into things like Lavo and reason and all these sorts of deals
How did they look at this kind of stuff
And say to themselves well listen this serves a good purpose
The swell Hotel
Our old friend riding many decades ago will Durant
But it's a nice succinct
Description
Quote
Most Romans defended the gladiatorial games on the ground
That the victims had been condemned to death for serious crime
That the sufferings they endured acted as a deterrent to others
That the courage with which the doomed men were trained to face wounds and death
Inspired the people to Spartan virtues
And that the frequent site of blood and battle a custom Romans to the demands of sacrifices of War
And quote
He then
Mentioned several famous Roman writers and how they basically supported
The idea of the games
And then get to Cicero
The lawyer writer
The one-time console
Famous at the end of the Republican.
And even though Cicero
Would make comments approving of the games sometimes
He also said this which is a pretty
Humanist sort of thing for a Roman writer to put pen to paper about
Durant says about Cicero in the games quote
Cicero was revolted by the slaughter
Quote
This is Cicero what entertainment can possibly arise to a refined and human eyes spirit
From seeing the noble Beast struck to the Heart by its merciless Hunter
For one of our own week species cruelly mangled by an animal of far greater strength
And quote
As we said earlier trying to figure out
Why the people in Rome enjoyed this
These violent
Entertainments is something that's been interesting to people for a very long time and Crosses into that Territory between a couple of distant
Ones like
Psychology and history
Has so many variables that it's not surprising
But you don't have
Widespread agreement on what this is I mean people arguing
The prevailing Theory tends to change every decade or so
There are some commonalities the things you run into
I generally most of the time and the number one
Commonality something it won't surprise any of us
When we ask how
These ancient people could watch other human being treated this way it's easy if you don't consider them to be human
And the dehumanization of the victims here
Is Obby
Samina
Everyone you'll read points out
The vast majority of these people who are dying in the arena
Are slaves one way or the other
They may not have been slaves their whole life if you capture somebody on the battlefield to make them prisoners they can be slaves the next day
A lot of these people who died in the arena by the way workout
Prisoners
Sometimes made to fight
Other prisoners
For the enjoyment of the crowd
Going to let the idea that we expect some sort of empathy and sympathy from the crowd
Might be flawed if the crowd sees these people as
Well with the Nazis would have called the intervention right
These are subhumans these are slaves are people with no rights and their people that are widely reviled in the society especially
Actually the ones at the lowest level especially the ones that have broken Roman law
We said earlier
How many people would be
Appalled at the idea of watching some horrific torture execution today
And how many would change their mind if you said yes but it's this horrible dictator is a Hitler
Or Saddam Hussein or somebody we're doing two how many people would go out well in that case Count Me In
Well for a lot of the Roman crowd
I was reading stuff
By several different authors Kyle among them who are suggesting that
You know a big part of the Roman desire to watch this stuff comes
From seeing the victims in a similar light to that
Right they're deserving of this
Therefore
You know why not get a little bit of enjoyment from their death while at the same time making it so horrible
That other people who might think of doing this or just waited
Now before we leave
The Roman example
There's one element it's worth bringing up
Because it's a
What's an estuary if you will have to cross over
Between
The modern
Violent entertainment
And the ancient entertaining violence
It has to do with something to some historians call
The Fatal charade
The Fatal charade is something that you can easily
Imagine developing
Because you need to have more novel a new things to bring in the crowds and remember at the Coliseum they were having
Naval battles take place for the crowd with water
The spectacles are amazing so you can imagine how
The Dynamics of it all mean that you know these grown unimaginable proportions a little bit like history
Got to become 6 hours long
How do you spell charades
Involved using The Condemned criminals
In
Play
Comedy
Dramarama anything like addressing the Muppets characters putting in assets up
And having them reenact
What went on in the story but the stories they pick are often homicidal
Anaval maimings and so what they did then was they did it for real
You said earlier what if you
Made one of those
Previews they show the movie theater for an action film that use real bullets and had real people get really hurt
And what would that be like
Maybe like these
In a fatal charades in Rome
Astorian Donald G Kyle in his notes
Quoting several other historians
Wrote about the Fatal charade
Quote
The combination of theater and execution in the amphitheater was not theater proper
But rather bartsch says
A violation of the theatrical by the actual
Or rather
A conflation of the two
Not a representation but a replication
As she notes
The actual death in the charades
Fulfilled the requirements of both the plot
And the penal code
And quote
That's a crazy line
That the deaths
In these fatal plays
Met the needs of both the plot
And the penal code
That it wasn't a
Representation like a movie would be today
It was a replication
Like doing
A story on the Manson family murders
But re-enacting them rather than replicating them on film
And what makes it so different as it's right in your face
There's no doubt
The people are really enjoying this where is in all the other situations that come to mind
That would involve other ancient peoples that you can find
It's so hard to disentangle
The religion
From the ritual
And
You know the lack of sources to tell you specifically the people were having a good time
To figure out as we said whether or not the Aztecs are enjoying watching the ceremony involve
Human soccer
Or whether it's all part of some giant
In a religious ritual
That sort of overlays the entire question that explains it in a way that's a lot less
Denigrating towards the human species than the simplistic
You know attitude of well they're having a good time watching
Penis person suffering.
The Roman exam
Is the most
I can find
That forces you to look into a mirror
And if you're trying to make the case that human beings are inherently good
Inherently empathetic and inherently
With a sense of Brotherhood and Sisterhood toward their fellow man
You know you have to hold this is
Exhibit a and say well then
How do you explain this
So then of course the question arises
Briefly
And not without controversy
If these things were so popular why the heck did they disappear
And the answers of course are less simplistic and more argued about than they used to be
I still think most of the historians
That you'll look at
Will
Acknowledge that there's a role in the
Change and Sensibility shall we call them
Between a
Minority Christian Roman one that was increasing in
Importance in that Society Wright the ethics were changing
And the views on things like the
Arena and how moral something like that was what we're also changing now let's be honest
Even if it wasn't for ethical reasons connected to their faith
You could understand why Christians might think the game suck to me look at how many Christians went there and
In these Arenas her
Well let's be honest there countrymens entertainment
In many cases
There's an interesting Twist on this by the way this idea that
Christianity may have helped kill the games but it hasn't
Anything to do with a growth in refinement of sensibilities and all that
It has to do with
Maybe
You can call it 8
Scheduling golf
I mean for example
The games themselves were
Happening a couple of times a year like many Olympics
And that just happens to be the time when you had
You know some of the more serious
Holiday.
Christians
And so maybe we're talking
Got something here that has to do with a quest
Scheduling conflicts as I said
Leading to a reduction in consumer demand Maybe
There's another theory that these things that only existed as long as they had because the emperors
Gave
Them all the support because it helped
The whole bread and circuses thing will these are the circus is right they play a role for the emperor they play at mystical roll the can
Connect the emperor to the subject, there's a whole lot of theories about this
Once it stops doing that to the same degree there's no reason for the emperor to go to those great expenses and all that other trouble
Have a nice Cherry race and call it good
I should point out to the
Are these Roman tradition where they have these games these go way back in their history and actually evolved other Italian people like
Stand lights in a truck engine and people who would have sometimes at funerals and whatnot these duels and Duels are not.
Baton
Common throughout history
He was just Roman as we said layering we talked about the animals with layered on all the different levels of
Performance
And attraction and
I mean these things as we said we're like a variety show
With the violence as sort of the headliner Act
But I read that they didn't die out all at once in that
Even quite a bit of time later after Emperor's and whatnot had tried to get rid of them they were still popping up here or there
So
Maybe not quite getting the ratings that used to get
But still bopping around you know the Off-Broadway circuit and
In a pulling into locals every now and then for a little
Nigori equivalent
Old fashioned dinner theater
Maybe
Now this worry program dealing with
Executions
Criminal law
Criminal justice or the penal system or anything like that there be a lot of examples to go into
Where you're seeing public executions all over the world all the time it's just
Is depressingly
Familiar
But what you don't have is the kind of evidence that Rome provided of what the mentality of the crowd watching was
I know where else do you really see such raw enjoyment for example
It's very possible that those Japanese
People
Living nearby would it be
Person to convict being boiled to death
Happen if you did that might be unusual and you might want to go watching so
Are you pick up a few friends and you go get some food you go down to the beach to have some fun
Certainly might have happened in my cynical way of looking at things sometimes I imagine it probably did but I don't have the written sources
In English
To prove it
The next place that I can prove it
Or at least make it
Logical case with some evidence
Is a lot nearer to our own time than Rome was
Perhaps a little bit more of an indictment
It's one thing to try to say
At those ancient people living thousands of years ago
We're almost a different species from us but it's much harder to claim that
When you're talking about a time. Say as we said when George Washington is a young adults
Robert Francois Damien
Is being torn apart over four hours
In front of tens
Thousands of early modern
Inspect
Raiders
George Washington's life
Actually not
Bad historical
Marker for this conversation
Because over his life
Span
These sorts of
Spectacular
Grotesquely medieval torture executions
Will go out of fashion
Washington course
30s
Hi.
Costco 19th
December 1799
Lived during a period
Often
Labeled in your high school history textbook says the enlightenment of the Age of Reason
Those kinds of executions don't sound very light
Do they
And they were passing away during this era
Her bunch of interesting reasons but the reason
That we can use it to examine our question of
Yunnan people
And violence
And the extremes of The Human Experience as we get these
Source Israeli Annex
Explosion in store
Starting at around
The 16th century
Japan 1500 to 1800
You can really see this
This entire question from multiple viewpoints in ways you've never been able to
And I think that's why if you buy
Reading material in English on this subject it is inordinately concentrated
On the period from 1500 to the early 1800s sanding Western Europe
Because the sources
Plaintiff
And from multiple viewpoints take for example
One of the most interest
There is nothing
From the Roman era
They gives you the perspective of the person whose job it was
To execute people
What the guy who had to do all these horrible things to The Condemned
Think right
Would know
But we have
The equivalent of a diary kept
By an executioner in Germany in the 16th century
How amazing is it to have that point of view to add
To try to three dimension lies this
And what about
The Condemned
Themselves again nothing from the Roman Arena on how that poor
Individual felt before they went through what they went through
But in the air were talking about The Condemned could speak sometime
And what they said
Was written down and transmitted and then of course we have an audience
That you can examine now from multiple viewpoints over multiple Century in multiple countries
So if you want to examine this fascination with
The spectacular Ade of death in people's interest in it
This is perhaps the best laboratory we can work within
Because there's a lot of data to synthesize now
The problem in talking about this is there is a lot of variation
Region region
Arrinera
And so any generalize statements are bound to be false in some way so I hope
I can count on your Indulgence on this
Try to
Get us to where we have to be to have a discussion about this we're going to General
But if you want to understand
What happened that allowed
Modern people
You know from the Louis XIV era of the Enlightenment to go to these torture executions and enjoy themselves
You have to kind of understand how it got that way we have to have some contacts
There's a bridge to maybe take us backward
For some
I was thinking of
That a couple of rulers
News during George Washington's life
Implement
But they were secret reform
We just kind of Interest
For example
Frederick the great of Prussia was considered one of the Enlightenment rulers
A guy who didn't just
I read people like Voltaire the famous
Enlightenment thinkers
He was a pen pal
One of these people that implemented changes that
Part of all this stuff that
Broadly call the enlightened
The Age of Reason
And one of the things that
Frederick the great tables were formed the Legal Sea
In the 1740s
Now we did away with a couple of
Medieval type
Executions I mean I think he got rid of burning for example couldn't burn somebody alive anymore I think
But I know
But he kept
Stuff like
Breaking with the wheel
But his Secret order his reform dictated
That the person who was going to be subjected to this ordeal
Be strangled beforehand
That's not the interesting part per se
The interesting part is that Frederick
Mandated that this strangling be done in such a way
Did the crowd would know it
As far as the crowd was concerned
They were still watching a person being
Broken apart in the most horrific medieval fashion possible
But Frederick
Any Executioner's would know
But the person actually felt no pain
What's going on there
And before we think of it as an isolated exam
Maria Theresa
The Habsburg Empire a couple decades
Later issued a similar sort of order and her point
Was that listen
The person is dead anyway
That's what we're really doing here
Here trying to
You deprive that person of his life why
Heater prolong the stop
But then why keep the string
Angling Secret
Texas
To the rationale Behind These
Spectacular
Public executions from this
Bizarrely modern era
Why do they do them at all
The point of all this was to create a
Shockingly Freight
Prospective
A deterrent warning
And for the purposes of
The warning
It really wouldn't matter whether or not The Condemned was actually feeling the pain that the audience thought they
They were feeling
The most important part of the equation was that the audience did indeed think they were feeling
The pain and suffering and when you consider with the really nasty
Executions that a guy in
Frederick the Great's time would have had available to him
They're frightfully need I mean burning for those of you who find that particularly horrible
Others might choose it was a personal
Question
As their most horrible most to be avoided
Potential execution method
Breaking on the Wheel
He mentioned a little early what the heck is breaking on the Wheel
Storing Garrett Fagan
As a horrific description
When you can see after you hear it
Why strangling somebody ahead of time would have been an act of considerable Mercy he writes quote
Particularly unpleasant was Wheeling
Also called braiding
Or breaking on the wheel in France
Or breaking with the wheel in Germany
The procedure he writes
Took many forms
And was employed in numerous countries across the European continent and in foreign colonies
The usual method
Was for the victim to be tied to a scaffold
Board laid out on the ground with wooden struts to raise the limb
And a wagon wheel
Or a hammer iron bar or club
Used to break them
Special execution Wheels were manufactured
With projecting flanges for atom-smashing power
Alternatively
Victims to be run over repeatedly by heavy wagons
The traditional
The word means
End of the ceremony
What's for The Condemned to have their ruined limbs threaded through the spokes of another Wagon Wheel
The braiding part of the action which was then hoisted on the pole for display
They are the victim if not dead already
Could linger for days
Hey heroin eyewitness account from a 1607 execution reports how the victim was transformed
Quote into a sort of huge screaming puppet
Writhing in rivulets of blood
A puppet with four tentacles
Like a sea monster of raw slimy and shapeless flesh
Mixed with the splinters of smashed bone
And quote
This takes us back
To the reasons for the spectacular punishment the justifications and
When you go back to how it all started
The water becomes very muddy indeed
For example
Remember us wondering about
Many other peoples in history and whether or not
The fact that there are heavy religious overtones the what's going on whether or not that means you can determine if they were there
Cuz they wanted to see the violence and meet at the Aztec crowd
Is witnessing the human sacrifice ceremony
Is this fun
Or is this a form of piety right
Hard to tell the waters are very muddy
In the Europe
Proceeding. We're talking about here the same thing is true
And big disclaimer that's not to say that there aren't religious overtones in the
Roman arena there were
And that's not to say there aren't religious overtones at Robert Francois Damien's execution there were
But it's pretty obvious from those two examples that it's not the number one thing in Rome the number one thing is the amusement of the crowd
Endymion case the number one thing is demonstrating the authority of the state
The fact that people are enjoying watching the authority of the state being demonstrated
That's a different question that's more human
In the period that leads up though
To these relatively secular
Pursuits in the mid 1700 do you have very religious execution
So once again
Is the crowd there for fun
Or is this something
Larger
We compared the Roman Arena
To a kind of
Theater sword
Theater where the violence was real
But maybe touching some of the same parts of your mind
Or psyche that enjoys watching the fake version now
Entertainment as I said was the goal though
Pride what's the what's the what's the form of execution here that will be most novel and interesting to watch
In the case of the executions
In the Europe of the Middle Ages
The ones that are the
Precursors to be later examples we've been going over
These are also
Like a form of theater
But it's more like a morality
Fashion
One of these
Message oriented displays when there's going to be
A lot of drama
Is going to be quite a bit of horrific viola
But if it all goes off the way these executions in the Middle Ages were supposed to go off in a lot of these
Cases
Again exceptions exist and there are
Local variations
It would be a happy ending at the end
The person who suffered the most
Pain and violence during the experience
Will find themselves
If they conduct themselves properly of course
In heaven
God in the saint
In the crowd
Will it X if these historians are to be believed
Seem almost jealous of
Just out of curiosity
What would have to happen what would it take
To make you
Jealous
Or envious
Someone who is just indoor DeLong
Drawn out
Painful public torture execution
I don't remember
Ever seeing eniac
Counts from the Roman era of people
Spectators in the arena
Feeling a whole lot of
Envy for the person being eaten by wild animals as part of their in death sentence in front of them
Now if you had told me I had overlooked something I wouldn't be surprised
If you'd said that there were accounts of the Christian martyrs
Wood witnessed their Brethren dying in the arena and wish that they could
That happened to them too I wouldn't be surprised
You see accounts like this all over the world at various times very
Devout people
Who have a completely different set of logical priority
When's that are not based on here and now
What are focused more on a long term for ever afterwards venue
It changes your rational calculation right if you're much more worried about
An eternity in heaven
Rather than the momentary
In a logical pros and cons that way into the situation you might be facing here
Now fast-forward
A few centuries and as we all know
Did Christians go from A persecuted sect in Rome 2 running the joint
When it comes to Western Europe
I'm on the Western Roman Empire goes away and leaves all the successor States and its wake
The vast majority of Christian in the ones that aren't will be
This is the
How do you spell to say if you go from ugly lady antiquity
The Age of Reason begins
This is Europe at its most
Intense
Religiosity right there their most fervent
This is the area where
And it encompasses the Crusades and encompasses all the religious wars that happened because of
The Schism between another Protestants in the Catholic to me there's a lot that go into this
And a ton of people will Diamond witches inquisitions it's all during this era
There's a line and I'm going from memory that
I once read a historian said
That they said in this era
The most vicious procedures
Inflicted
On devout Christian
I even more devout
Christian
You have near Universal
Catholicism in these country
Freeze until the
The great schism with Martin Luther
Their enclaves
Jews
There's actually a lot of folks in some places and there's a bunch of heretical Christian sects
Whether Christian or not of courses
Is the main issue that are being wiped out and persecuted
But there's a worldview now in place
Bright
A reality that in some ways is like our own
If you drop an apple
Gravity does what gravity does right it does now it did then
But there are other elements of reality
That are believed
To be a hundred percent valid by almost everybody
The influences everything
Take for example
The near unanimity of the idea
But there is a heaven
Hell and a god watching over everything and that everything is divinely ordained
Now we have people of course we believe
That today
But it's one of many different belief systems out there in fact
One of the great things about living in a free society and a free part of the world
Is it you're free to pick and choose your own reality either within limits I mean you still have to ignore
Gravity
But otherwise
I mean you can
Treated like a
In a buffet if you will take I'm going to take a little bit of it
Eastern mysticism
Mix it with
Catholic doctor in at a little bit of you know hard science and some UFO ology cuz I like that
Pause Massage Envy
21st
Century
In philosophical smoothie if you want
But I think we have to recognize that that the freedom
That did not exist in most times and Mo's place
Is there are
Course
Terrorism places where did by and large
The belief system with a lot more constrained
Both legally
And obviously in terms of
Religion and faith
But also because of the old garbage in garbage out
Element of what were the people even being exposed to take for example
An illiterate person in the middle of Europe in oh I don't know we'll say
The 10th century
What do you know you know
Probably the religious texts
That will read to you by somebody else
And anything you personally experienced
Well that's going to limit your world you right there and if there's 100% belief in the religious texts
And everyone else feels the same way
Will that help
Playing
The accounts of some of the executions that have come down to us
From this era
Which artist Bazaar
As anything I've ever seen
But without the face explanation it doesn't make any sense
So first of all when we talk about
Executions in the Middle Ages
What do we mean
Astoria Paul Friedland
Point out by the way that there are far fewer resources and accounts of execution from this era than you would think considering Symphony
In terms of torture and execution montavon mutilations during this time. Right
Very eye for an eye
And you can lose a hand if you receive lot of that kind of stuff
In his book The Lure of the Arena
Is reindeer Chief Pagan rites quote
Passing Beyond antiquity
Our sources for the Dark Age punitive practices are not good
What's rotten Middle Ages in Continental Europe it is clear that many forms of aggravated execution in public
Torture were employed
Including burning
Boiling alive in oil feet first
Decapitation
Burial alive
Drawing and quartering branding flogging and miscellaneous forms of Mutilation
For those guilty of multiple offenses
Cumulative punishment could be applied
I'd is stipulated by the court
In this way lethal and non-lethal punishments were often combined
So that torture preceded execution
Or mutilation of the body was carried out postmortem
Desoxyn Spiegel
He continues and illuminated German legal code of 12:20 to 12:35
Shows beheading
Hanging
Hacking the birching and shearing of women tied to a stake
And mutilation
It is not evident from the Saxon Spiegel however
But these punishments attracted crowds
But there is no reason to think that they did not
And quote
If he's executions in the Middle Ages
And the Renaissance dd&d draw crowds and I don't see why they wouldn't
Are the crowds there for
What was the draw expect to have happened what did they hope to have happen
This is why we should have set up their religious stuff
Up till now because
That's what twists in the unique way because
If I told you that the legal system wanted
An exemplary deterrent
Going to deter people from committing crimes and that's why they hung up bodies and pieces of bodies and heads on Stakes at the bridge
Bridges and all that that would surprise you with it
Injustice is always headed to turn two-factor
And we've been a lot of theories about that this
Nothing new in that in that question
Is the religious side that to the modern mind is harder to understand
What if you went to this execution
Instead of feeling
The mindset of stereotype in our minds
Of how these executions go with the crowd
Providence cheering and throwing refuse and heaping abuse on The Condemned they make it our way to the
Apple
Gallows
Ravenstone
And then when they're up there just about to die the crowded during at them in all this and while this didn't happen
The source of State depends on
What the bad person did and how they comported themselves during the whole process but
More often than not in this. We're talking about right now
The crowd felt
The connection
To The Condemned
Compassion
And if the whole thing went off well
The historians often described
This is being a spiritually
Moving event one of them use the word maybe two of them use the word
Potentially
Beautiful
Now let's remind ourselves for a second
But what this beautiful event might be
And then ask ourselves again
What it would take
For you
Over me
To watch this live
And describe it afterwards
Is beautiful
So in his book rituals of Retribution historian Richard Evans
Recounts
The tale of an Englishman named John Taylor
Who lived in the early 1600s and did a little traveling
And wrote about what he saw
One of the things he saw
Is while he was visiting the contents he got to see one of those executions that they weren't doing much where he was from anymore in England.
I said earlier I think
English of a penchant for hanging
That we'll talk about in a little bit but
It didn't mean I didn't do other things that just meant it was a little bit more unusual sewing
John Taylor goes to
You know the continent and sees an opportunity to go to an execution where they're breaking someone with the wheel
He describes it in his language from that time. This way
Quote
Monday the 19th of August
About the hour of 12 at noon
The people of the town in great multitude
To the place of execution
We just half a mile English meaning distance
Without the gates built more like a sconce than a Gala
Griswold Inn ditched about with a drawbridge and the Prisoner came on foot
With a Divine with him
Being a priest a religious
Figure
All the way exhorting him to repentance
And because death should not terrify him
They are giving him any Rouses into Rouses of wine and beer
British the custom there
To make such poor wretches drunk
Whereby they may be senseless either of God's mercy
For their own misery
But being prayed for by others
They themselves me directions lutely
Or to be feared desperate
And quote
Then Taylor describes the execution which would have been maybe unusual for him to seize his quote
The Prisoner mounted on a mound of Earth built high on purpose that the people without
Macy the execution a quarter of a mile roundabout
Four of The Hangman's men
Takes each of them a small halter
And by the hands and the feet they hold the prisoners
Extended all the broad laying on his back
Veni Arch hangman or the master of this Mighty business
Took up a wheel
Much about the bigness of one of the four wheels of a coach
And 1st
Having put off his doublet his hat
And being in his shirt as if he meant to play at tennis
He took up the wheel
And set it on the edge
And turned it with one hand like a top or a whirligig
And then you took it by the spokes
It looked it up with a mighty stroke
He beat one of the poor wretches legs in pieces
The bones I mean
Witchy roared grievously
Then after a little pause he breaks the other leg in the same manner
And consequently breaks his arm
And then he stroke for five main blows on his breast
And burst all his belt in chest and shivers
Last week he smelled his neck
And missing
Burst his chin and jaw autom amex
Lenny took the broken mangled corpse
And spread it on the Wheel
And thrust a great poster pile into the neighbor hold of the wheel and then fix the post into the Earth some
Being in height above the ground
Some 10 or 12 foot
And there the carcass must lie until it be consumed by all-consuming time
Or ravening foul
And quote
This was part of the exemplary deterrence
And the idea of the. Right
You not only have to have the execution be like this
But you have to have pieces of the body lying around to remind people
You got to put them in gibbets in cages and you got to cut him up in pieces and put the pieces in different places
And you got to leave the people who died on The Gallows hang in there till they fall off by themselves
As an example to others
So now considering
This englishman's
Description of this rather unusual execution by his standards
If you had witnessed it live you think you would have
Called it
Beautiful
Would have been some Sublime spiritual experience for you
I said earlier
Some of the stuff so he's executions are so bizarre if you don't have the faith element
You can't even get your mind around it's hard enough to get your mind around it with the faith element
Freeland gives another example in his book and I would quote it
From the original Source accepted there's too much Latin in it it's hard to follow
But essentially it talks about
One of these breaking on the wheels that happens
In the original source is talking about how
As the
Condemned is being killed you know it is if they're being broken on the Wheel
They are
Singing or shouting religious verses
And the crowd is picking up
You know where The Condemned leaves off so he'll do the first verse deal do the second in unison he'll do the third they'll do the fourth it's
Call
And response
While he's being killed
What's more
According to this Source he's talking to the guy who's killing in the Executioner
And I guess the only way to put it is he's
Making requests right tell the crowd I want the next verse in Latin
Then all this kind of stuff
Completely bizarre to the modern mind
But as Friedman says this is the kind of thing that the people
In that era would have seen as potentially beautiful
A wonderful lesson for the kids write a morality lesson here here's what can happen to you if you go wrong but if you continue to
Believe in God and you sincerely seek
Redemption through repentance you too can make it to Heaven I mean
There is all
There's an element of Faith involved here that's understandable
The modern people of faith
But because this isn't modern
Feh this is a
Medieval version of Italy Renaissance version of it
The part that's hard to understand
Did the people in the crowd very well may have seen
The violence being done to the malefactors
Body
As necessary
To get to the Heavenly goal and if that's the case
What was being done to that malefactors body
Was it good thing
And because it was being done
Someone soul is going to be saved
And if you actually watch that
I did pretty good crazy entertaining show with a good message at the end and a feel-good
Minnesota an attitude when you get home you're all run out the emotions have been totally in play
I mean I guess what I'm saying is there's an entertainment
That isn't there
At the same time
It is so formalizar when you read the rules by me to have it written down.
You know who stands where and what the formations in line is supposed to be who comes first and
This is a celebration of
Both religious and secular Authority
But it's so ritualize would be hard to make a case
Edit anything but that
So if you say people are enjoying what they're seeing and they go home glad they came and there's a huge draw for the next execution
I don't think there's any arguing about that
But it's not the same thing as what's going on in the Roman arena is it
Friedland
Says quote
Prior to the middle of the 16th century those who attended executions I will resist calling them spectators
Did so largely out of a sincere desire to participate in the ceremony
That held profound personal meaning for them
And not because they wanted to talk from a distance at the suffering of others
These were less
Spectacles he writes in the way that we understand the word today
Then they were rituals
In which those who attended saw themselves as full participants rather than onlookers
When asked was usually the case The Condemned participated fully in the ritual of repentance
Seeking forgiveness from Divine and Earthly authorities
Witnesses usually Bridge the physical distance
Between themselves
And the patient meaning The Condemned
Through prayers
Tears and empathy
The public transformation of The Condemned criminal into a repentant sinner enable the entire community.
Undergo a kind of feeling that may be experienced as profoundly beautiful and uplifting
And quote
Don't also had a lot of other ritual important elements to it
The key though as
Historian Richard Evans points out the whole affair
Requires an absolute consensus on the part of everyone involved executioner
State authorities condemned audience
That there is the possibility of an afterlife
Evans rights quote
Eternal life was indeed what the malefactor sought
And with the ritual meaning of execution was designed to provide
Almost without exception The Condemned gave the impression of being penitent Christian
Who went straight to heaven
After making a quote and quote
Good day
It was a sacred ritual
It depended on the acceptance of all concerned of the possibility of an afterlife
The good death of the malefactor
Purge the community of its blood guilt
I'm canceled out
The bad death
The sudden unprepared and bereft of the opportunity to make peace with God in the world of the malefactors murder
Victim
Assured the community that the spirit of the executed would not return to haunt the survivors
Asthma so often believed to be the case with the Restless Souls of the suddenly Departed
He guaranteed the Peace of society
By ensuring a grateful Corp
And it reassured those would witnessed it that they have done a good deed
They paved the way to eternal life for a soul seemingly Beyond Redemption
And quote
There's a certain irony isn't there that modern people
Instantly recognized in a situation like this
That Europe in its most
Religiously Fanatic. In its history
Are treating their Outkast
Malefactors
And lawbreakers
In exactly the same fashion as the individual at the center of their religion was treated
Jesus Christ of course perhaps the most famous
Victim
Of a hideous
Public
Torture execution
On a cross by the way
Which is just how some of these European execution victims were killed two
By their Christian Executioner's
And while historians point out that sometimes the crowd could make the connection between the similarities between the
Condemned having to make their way to the scaffold and Jesus having to make his way
Enough to where he was going to be nailed to the cross
No one seems to make the next obvious connection which is wait a minute
If our Saviour died in one of these hideous public torture executions
Should we really be doing this to other people
Nonetheless this is kind of what makes history fun
And we as people interesting
You just can't make this stuff up
So I think it's pretty fair to say
That while we won't give the people in this era a get-out-of-jail-free card to totally be absolved
From the charge that they might have been going to these Affairs for you know she or entertainment and enjoyment
We will say that like all those other cases we mentioned you know the northeastern
Native American tribes for example we don't know the water is too muddy to say cuz there's obviously ritual
And religious elements involved
It's only when you strip away those Elliman
That may be the potential get-out-of-jail-free card religious
Side of this
Ceases to protect
The society from charges
That they're just watching this stuff to get a kick out of it
And the reasons by the way that this will happen over the period for about 1500 to 1800 R complex
They're arguing about they're also interwoven so it's very difficult to say
You have to pay a lot of attention to this element what's going on because it's hard to quantify how much that matters compared to some other element is going on
And how they interact
Take for example one of the theories
Which I love I love this thing because it
There's an element with it just touches some hardcore history little nerve of mine
One of the ideas behind
How these executions go from these religious experiences with a crowd of The Condemned are working together to get a soul to heaven
More theories on how this changes Friedland
Subscribe to this I guess I think
And that's at the Lutheran
Change this a bit
You know there's this great schism right we all understand the Protestant
Reformation the big revolution Martin Luther kicks off and by the way the Protestants as it is
Overall entity didn't seem to have a problem with executions
Luther
Was quoted as saying was famous quote.
The hands of the Executioner the hands of God or something like that
But when these Lutheran's begin to be early on executed as Heretics
They're a curiosity for the crowd
And one of the reasons they were curiosity
Friedland another's right is that
They will go to the execution
Happy
Glad handing
Patient and ready
And
The thing about them that's so difficult is that when the the confessors are dealing with them or the priests are dealing with them with your throat
You're dealing with them or the crowd is trying to deal with them
There's almost a like who's out christening huella
You can call them Heretics all you want but when they're
Screaming
In pain during the execution there screaming out the name of Jesus Christ
What are we saying earlier that vine I like
During this. The most horrible procedures were done on devout Christians by even more devout Christians
The Freeland and others point out that
This may have short-circuited
This entire ritual we talked about earlier right the one
Whereas on Peter sparenberg says he says this requires the cooperation of The Condemned for it to work right
Are you go home after watching one of these events feeling
Satisfied
And like you did a good thing and like all is right in the world everything has to go as planned but what if the criminals
As you would have seen them these Heretics
What is they don't repent
What if they don't say they were wrong
What if they don't play the role
That they're supposed to play well it doesn't number of thing but the one thing it certainly does as pointed out over and over by several different people
Is it short-circuits the script
The one thing these events don't have a lot of
Is uncertainty at the very formalized Affair we just described these executions in the Middle Ages and afterwards
The fact that these Lutheran's could do anything
Adds an element of uncertainty
Are they going to recant their faith right before they're about to be burned alive
Sometimes they did sometimes he didn't
It creates a
Level of uncertainty
It is not that dissimilar pardon me for saying so
To a sporting event
When you don't know the outcome
Freedom quotes historian David Nichols
Who said that people were quote drawn to the burning of Heretics by curiosity
They were Novelties and people wish to see how this new kind of criminal face death
And quote
Apparently this
Curiosity about
Protestant Heritage won't last very long
But some historians think that this
Plays a role in breaking down the barriers if you will separating people were going to these things for ritual reasons
People are going to these things for spectacles
Now that said before there's disagreement on a lot of this stuff a lot of the question we're getting into now you will find the app
Experts I've noticed
Disagree not that this is a factor but how much weight you give each fact
You're so we just mentioned the Curiosity factor with Protestants Heretics
Import news.
Different people disagree
There are other elements in play here
That should be mentioned that are interesting that are
Part of the
Reality of the times if you will
How about the fact that this is the. Where people really start
Examining
And
Medically
Dissecting human bodies
So it'll be like a theater sometimes they'll open up a person and they'll be a crowd watching from above of disinterested science
Who will see y'all at the ligaments work and there is the aorta I needed that kind of stuff
And they get these bodies by the way
Usually from execution victims
And it's
Considered to be one of the parts of the sentence that the judge wants to make it extra bad he'll say not only are going to break you on the Wheel
But afterwards we're going to give you to the doctors to
It was called anatomize you'll be an atomizer
Now you and me we may say who cares we're already dead but you're talkin about people have a very different belief system and being an atomizer
Is not only something that might mess you up
In heaven question
It's darn
Shameful
And another thing you'll notice of these executions were modern people will go away. Who cares it's part of shame in the
Individual and maybe their family and certainly anyone who might want to do what they did
The by far the greatest amount of agreement you will see when you read from
Years ago to now the experts on the subject of
And these kinds of executions and what's involved
The elephant in the living room is state power
State Authority
You mentioned earlier and if you look at the fall of the Western Roman Empire
And the development of states in the history of all that afterwards you famously will get to the
Treaty of Westphalia in the 17th century where they will talk about the nation-state being the highest form of four
Political organization all that kind of stuff
It's during this period that these nation-states these budding
Infant nation-states are beginning to create the sort of bureaucracy and power and all that stuff that we associate with them
Now the number one thing you have to do by the way
We secure a monopoly of force
You can't run
A modern nation-state and have a bunch of War Lords and Barons and other people able to have their own private armies and
Messing with you
Job one get rid of them and there's only one Authority and they're in the Capitol you begin to get these
The so-called absolutist
States of the earth Louis XIV era
There's a lot of reason this is important as I may be the number one most important part
Let's start with the fact that it's the main reason you can't follow the story chronologically
Because depending on how advanced
The authority of the state is in any given region
The execution procedures and all that stuff will be at different phases so for example
Places like London
A country like England
Which establishes a monopoly of force
A relatively early compared to the rest of the states in Europe
You will see the executions take on a different form
You will see the goal of the state being different you will see the reaction of the crowd watching differently
Paris will do something similar
But you could go out in the Hinterlands go to some small
Place in Bavaria Maybe
And you'll find it a long time after they stop doing the whole religious connection with The Condemned and all that
Hiding places like London and Paris they're still doing it in the Backwoods of Bavaria
So this is all happening at different time
Noesis we said
You lose the get-out-of-jail-free card when your ritual turns into a spectacle
How much do you blame
The power of the state for this well let's understand what they do right
They begin to have a problem
With the religious side of this whole deal
Because the state's interest in these public executions
Is four things to be as absolutely horrifying as possible to the crowd to send a message
Write this is deterrence at work
But what if through
All those religious ceremonies that we've been talking about
The religious side of things turns this Condemned criminal who the public should hate
And be repelled by and not admire at all with that turns them into and almost fainted figure
She began to see these complain to me if there is going hey
We can't have this right
We don't want the crowd
To feel
In any certain admiration we want them to feel
Scoring for the speakers of the begin to have problems with
What they want out of these executions conflicting with what the religious
Side of the
Budding nation-state
With the execution
The goals of the clergy and the state Aurora.
Just by the way
Correspond to the same. Where a bunch of the Elites in these most civilized society
He's right here in London or Paris or what not the really civilized Elites are not so religious as they
They used to be
Again it would be stupid to say that they're not religious compared to now
But compared to the so-called unit
Superstitious
High water mark
The Dark Ages
The darkest we now know but you know
I mean
This is a whole different animal these rationalist of the budding pre Enlightenment era
And they're often the ones
Who are pushing this idea that hey these religious people
Are screwing up the goal of this thing we just to make these criminals the worst people on Earth and you never want to be one
Historian Richard Evans in rituals of Retribution
Writes about this new
So I've been lighting Montera that's budding and let's not pretend that it's budding among the rank-and-file in the population it's Buddy
Cream of the inteligencia
They have an infant
Here's what
Women's rights quote
The new rationalistic concentration on public punishment is a theatrical demonstration designed to make the
The Publican w**** the criminal
Was part
In other words
Have a broader concentration
Only educated in deterrent function of punishment
It is easy to see that this concept of penal policy
Ran counter to the religious and crypto materialist rituals
Which played such a major part in capital punishment in the early modern period
And which before the 18th century were accepted in the elite as well as popular culture
And quote
So this is an example of one of the arguments being made by someone Evans
Identifies as one of the rationalists pamphleteers
Of his day
Listen to the arguments against
The religious side of this hole
What do we call it earlier Sublime beautiful experience
Evan says quote
The purpose of the public execution Thunder the rationalist pamphleteer was being completely undermined by this
Contradiction
It was unfortunately true he declared
According to
Pamphleteer from that era
Set the rebel is not motivated by the desire to hear something good and that's be moved and uplifted
Amelie by the wish to see something new
Ella satisfy his curiosity
Even on many occasions at the cost of human feelings
The ultimate purpose of public punishment is largely frustrated if the malefactor dies in circumstances that arouse
The kind of admiration and respect
Infanticidal woman
Clothing adorned purely and white
Going joyfully to her spiritual wedding accompanied by the preacher is a very dangerous site for other people
Call in the conduct of their daily life
I'm a murderer he continues
Going to his death accompanied by the size prayers and admonitions of the preacher and by the singing of inspire
Hiring funeral hymns
Open has the deleterious effect
Of causing Weeknd Melancholy Nature's to desire for themselves a form of Extinction
Which is they think
Allows them to meet their end more peacefully indeed more joyfully they're on their deathbed after a lengthy illness
And quote
Evans then point out that this doesn't mean that these people thought The Condemned should have no religious consolation but that he should occur in private
Will heal their souls privately but don't let it
Soften the crowds attitude toward them in other words
The idea that this should be something
Were you see this person
As going off to some wonderful destination in part because you are sending them there
That screws up the whole reason the state wants this guy dead
Woman dead
Now there are other things
They get thrown into the mix as reasons why
The attitudes of the spectators change from ritualistic to voyeuristic
Take broadsheet
For example in the rise of broadsheets
Huaraches by the way a term still used
For the oversized newspapers today
It was a kind of newspaper I guess you could
Say a booklet of pamphlet sometimes it was just one big piece of paper
But think about something that looked like Ben Franklin did it on his home printing press and that's not a bad mental
Often times it was mostly illustrations because you know who knows how many people in the audience could actual
Read
The text would often explain what was in the pictures and sometimes it almost look like a comic book where you would see several different panels
Showing events in chronological order
When these things first started to appear either late 1500 maybe maybe even earlier
What they were showing was often sold of a cautionary tale a moralistic cautionary tales
First
Pain in the comic book shows the person being born
Everything looks
Great
And then the next painting shows the person that adolescents and still going good everything's right
And in the third pain lady shows the
Pivotal moment in their life
When you decide to
Killing Rob this person
The next pain shows to being judged by the authorities and expand shows the being executed
The last pain maybe just shows them
You know hanging on a
Deserted Gallows while the buzzards you know
Circle above
Of course the message to be absorbed by the
Little kitties at night when you show it to them is
You know I stay on the straight and narrow or this could happen to you
Overtime these broadsheets begin to become more
Let's just say lascivious
Salacious
Mushroom or something we would recognize today in fact
If you said tabloid ask
That might not be too far
Off the mark this coincides with a. And again there's a chicken in an egg albumin
How much is this is encouraged by the broadsheets and how much of it is
In what societies doing in the broadsheets are just
You're playing into the trend of it
An increased interest in
Crime
Punishments
And
We would say today gossip I just read one
History were the historian was saying that one of the Prime things language has been used for since language
Began was gossiping
Depending on how you
Define that term but
But in a sense these broadsheets
It's began showing
Real things when they were talk about these executions which kind of help with the drawer right the people knew that these were real events but then
The people doing the broadsheets
Wood
Embellish them and dramatize them they make the crimes more salacious and they usually be about unspeakable
Cool things with your course if you're gossiping the best thing to speaker
And they would
Then in lurid detail your talk about the execution
And there would be a lot of focus on the dramatic last moment the climactic
You know last speech maybe from The Gallows or the Ravenstone
Paul Friedland talked about one of these famous people think about son of a Matt drudge of their day just knowing exactly what sort of
What the mood of the public really was
Signifying right what buttons do you have to push to release a lot of these broadsheets
And he says
The titillating short stories had subjects like
Murderer
Incest
Parricide rape sodomy
And sorcery
No confirmation yet that one of the most called hardcore history
But you begin to see
A change in what the people want
And it's difficult to untangle how much of that is because the people were changing
And how much of the fact that the people were changing was due to the fact that they were reading more of these broadsheets and it was interesting the more
Good morning True Crime and what was going on in these people who were dying on The Gallows and
As one
Historian said it was a tragic
Spectacle
But these people were selling these broadsheet publishers
But it helped change the focus and some unquantifiable way from a religious oriented ritual
To something that was much more based on
Curiosity
And salaciousness
And maybe even
Voyeuristic enjoyment of somebody else's suffering in this is where we get to the next and he's broadsheets
We're existing at the same time and were intertwined with these people
Who like to go to the executions now for Less religious
More fun
Historian Paul Friedland says that he was in the 16th century that you first saw the beginnings of these people who would show up
What are the executions more for
Fun
Baby funds not the right where they they were almost like a rarefied group of hobbyist
It seems like for a while till it became a mass thing
You know these people used to be in on it years before the trend started in August to see these guys all the time an Executor Khan
These cuties people start to purchase
You know select seats so that they could be
At the execution but not right down in the mosh pit
If I Freeland says that to those folks
The people ride around the scaffold or the Ravenstone to The Gallows those people are actually characters in The Great tragic
Spectacle 2
Do you want to be able to
Take the whole scene in from a really good Vantage Point preferably
Elevated preferably with cocktail server Bowl end
Snacks
Freeland call these people penal voyeurs
Lawyers of the penal system in action
And he says
That they are
Perhaps analogous
The same in a similar way to these people who are now enjoying the broadsheets as they get more and more pop life you know 19
50s comic book e
Salacious mean this is like steam pulp
Maybe you could say
And if there is a connection between the two perhaps maybe one helps
Create the demand
Well they got it right you read a few broadsheet than you think. Maybe I should see one of these things live
Prelim rights quote
In many respects we might think of rosettes readers hemans friends while they were set maybe the Matt drudge of his
Day in terms of broadsheets
We might think of rough sex readers as analogous to the new penal voyeurs
Who are gathering in Windows overlooking the scaffold
And precisely the time when he was writing his tragic stories
Recette tragic realism made readers feel as if they were almost there at the scene of the execution
What was the relative freedom to experience their emotions as if they weren't
To forget themselves in SOB with the light in private
In a way he writes
The new penal voyeurs experienced a similar sense of being almost there
From behind their windows at a considerable distance from the scaffold
They can gaze out at the real-life drama unfolding beneath them
And they could take it all in
The suffering of the patient
The Compassion of the crowd
As if they were all characters in a magnificent spectacle
To which they themselves were not participants
The spectators
They were beginning in other words
To process the execution scenes played out before them almost as if they were watching one of Pierre corneille
Neil's tragic heroes or heroines deliver a monologue prior to execution
Peeking in on the most intimate moments of another person's life
And death
Outside the traditional framework of participation and compassion
They were free to feel a sense of tragic Delight
We're free to feel nothing at all
For them the crowd gathered around the scaffold have become a kind of Greek chorus
Reacting to the suffering of The Condemned and expressing The Compassion that they
Seated up above the windows no longer felt
And quote
Now I'm relying on a small number of sources he was smaller than I like because believe it or not there's not a lot
Especially in the stuff we're talking about here but I think friedland's wonderful
Facebook is wonderful
And he tries to get his mind around
These really interesting questions he does as good of a job as any I've ever read on the subject
He helps us understand this transition which is difficult because
As we said earlier the transitions will happen at different times in different places you can't follow this chronologically
And that's true is Need for any of these in a great so-called periods of history in your history books the Renaissance the enlightenment
The Renaissance comes to Italy a lot earlier than it comes to
England
Right
So we all understand
Changing sensibilities changing cultural attitudes changing ways of life all this stuff
Happens much more slowly
Then sometimes the histories make it out to be we don't change we people like
Light switching on a light bulb ride
But in this era were talking about here
There's an interesting little twist to it all you know someone wants told me
When we were talking about how many listeners
Someone had
For their show
And he said it's not always how many people are listening sometimes it's who those people are
Well what if you manage to create a religion
And you convert
One person
In another country
But that person is the absolute ruler of that country
How many individuals is that worth
This day in age in our modern
Democracies all around the world you got a co-op
A significant chunk of the population for any big movement in any direction
What if you just had to convert one person
We mentioned Frederick the great earlier
The ruler of Prussia so often associated with the enlightenment
This is a guy who for all intents and purposes has done what a lot of other things around history of done convert to a new relay
Religion and then sort of impose that on his country with his religion for lack of a better word
He's reason
And the Age of Enlightenment values I mean is we said earlier this was not a guy who was just reading Voltaire he was corresponding with
Vim as a penpal
He was all in his will
The Enlightenment ideas
And he wanted to create a country that represented this right that didn't have
Torture is Barbara's torture executions going on all the time I mean one of the first things he did when he took the throne and got rid of the penalty of
Burning sodomites
Those of you
Frederick the great fans on
Understand that there might be some interest
Irony there
He also would eliminate execution for a ton of crimes mean you no longer cut the thieves hands off of me he's doing these are all
Things that
And he can do by himself as the ruler you don't have to convince a whole lot of people in the country that this is the way to go you can just do it
And in Reading Richard Evans is
Book on this fabulous book on the subject
It's fascinating to note that in this era
If you were going to have for example a less
Medieval like I'm sorry that historians are cringing every time I use that word I mean it as an adjective of horrible torture
Who is barbaric sort of system in a more enlightened age
Reform was going to have to come from the absolute rulers because
It doesn't sound like the people they ruled over had a lot of trouble with it at all they were enjoying it they were snapping up the broadsheet
They were still going in large numbers and more and more people reviewing it doesn't event
So if you'd actually told your people listen we're going to get rid of this breaking on the wheel thing they might have been upset about it if you actually said
Said something like we're going to
Strangle them first they don't feel any pain but don't worry we're still going to go through with the execution they wouldn't like that either this is how you
Explain the idea
Find secret strangling
Why did Frederick the Great
Tell his authorities to kill the execution victim before they went through the horrible execution but
Make sure that the crowd didn't see it
Because the crowd wanted to see it
Why did Frederick the great care at all
This is a little bit more interesting
As I said this is
Maybe
A person whose illegitimate convert thinking
And why must this person suffer any more than is necessary and this gets to the whole idea behind the enlightened
Write this
This change in viewing things
In such religious terms
And you start to see a very modern isn't it
A focus more on life
Here and Now
And not as much of an emphasis on the Hereafter for example we said earlier that in the earlier eras to punish
Chinese executions was often viewed as the pain and suffering you went through
The death was the byproduct
People like Frederick the greater from a much more modern era where they look at the
Punishment in the execution
As being the deprivation of any more life or you don't get to live anymore your life ends now
That's your punishment
If that's the case
Why don't you cut your head off why do we have to go through all the rigmarole
Oh yeah because we need to send a message to the
Krowd
So strangle that guy
But don't tell him
Fascinate
But why listen to me and we can have a next
Mike Richard Evans explain it to us
He quotes the law code that Frederick is working on
Which enunciate this new rational is the way of viewing things like the penal system and says that these executions in the point of them
Annie's quote
Not to torment the criminal but rather to make a frightful example of him
In order to arouse repugnance in other
And quote
And then
Batman says
About that
Quote
Nothing could express more clearly the monarchs understanding of the purpose of punishment
It did not matter in the least the malefactor was actually dead when the sentence was carried out
Where did it deliberate deception was being played on the public
The rationalistic Frederick II
The execution was a kind of pedagogical theater
Drawing its purposes and its methods from the model of broke tragedy
Its purpose was not to inflict suffering but you deter by making an example of the offender
And it had to awaken feelings of revulsion in the onlooker
Anything that seemed likely to frustrate this purpose was to be avoided
This included the infliction of pain to such a degree that the sympathy of the crowd by bia vote
Apart from this obvious political purpose it is also important to note that Frederick did in the end considered a text
Excessive suffering was if possible to be avoided
The degree of pain with to be calculated precisely in rational terms
And quote
I love
That this chapter in Evans book is entitled
A rational degree of pain
In other words these Enlightenment rulers had no problem at all
With inflicting a ton of pain on people and suffering
But only if it could be justified as practically useful
This may look horrible to us today but it was a huge improvement over the previous conditions
Another huge Improvement and other Enlightenment execution reform
It doesn't seem like such a huge Improvement to our modern years
Was the increasing
Use of
Decapitation
As an execution method
Used to be something in most of these countries
It was reserved for the nobility back in the old days cuz it's considered to be an easy death when you think about the
The alternatives
Well over this are right in the more Progressive European Continental
All states
The
Practice of beheading the victim becomes
More
Common and you see more and more people that wouldn't have qualified for it half a century before
Being
Either with a sword or an axe
Cutting too at the neck
And before you think about this is
Just the most gruesome thing you can think of let's point out
But when you think about your options what would you choose
As long as everything goes well execution by the swords pretty quick right take it over
Breaking on the wheel taking over strangulation death
At The Gallows I mean what would you rather have right
Of course the problem is
That little phrase
Executed well
This requires some skill
On the part of the execution or a skill which is only sometimes there are those of you out there who actually practice with a C
Sword
Know that
Actually
Cutting something
Efficiently is not as easy as it looks
There's some skill
And hopefully you want to be relatively sober when carrying out the app
And sometimes neither of those things
Can be present at an execution
And then you have something really nasty
In front of you
But here's the thing if you want the crowd
Once again this is part of the attraction now
You don't know how this is going to go even this has its own draw
Because there's a lot of gossip and how these things go I mean you can go look at the French history where they're talking about
In letters to each other these decapitations
And the ones that don't go well or extra
Gossipy
More interesting little bit more juicy pardon
Adjectives Arrow
Another thing that has become somewhat of a draw to the crowd
Is the fact that the way The Condemned person behaves right before they die
Not as predictable as it used to be
Remember
There was a metaphysical carrot
Involved here that helped Ensure
Did The Condemned criminal
Would play their part in this ritual this script is sort of a fair right there
Penitent Christian for example
Undergoing the good death
But what if they weren't
Pennington what if they weren't even acting like they were Christian
What if they were complaining about the authorities
What if they were abusing the religious figures that were there
What is they were
Clowning around for the crowd to get the crowds
Approval
And what if they were just going to their death like Clint Eastwood
Absolutely fearless and cool
And the crowd looked at them
And
Thought it was
Awesome
Badass
I mean
None of that
Is
What the enlightenment
Rulers who are
Orchestrating these new specs
Nicole's that's not what they're trying to achieve
I remember
These are people that are a lot more concerned than people from the earlier era
About effectiveness
Can you take away
This idea that the
Person is going to go right to heaven
And if this is all a religious ritual and their souls going to be saying everything's going to be wonderful afterwards if they cooperate
You take away a big reason for them to cooperate
Add to that the fact that most of these again more progress
I say that because there was always
Nasty activities continuing back in the backwood
The places that are leading the edge of the satellite in Madera
They're not torturing people much anymore either which was the other thing you could do
If The Condemned criminal wasn't
In the following the proper script right
Apollo the scripture will take you back and you know tripaneer offer
Take another pinch out of your skin with the glowing hot
Tong's but if you're not doing blowing hot tongs anymore
And if the person doesn't think they're going straight to heaven as long as they cooperate
I don't cooperate as much the other thing that happens
Is the people who are
Absolutely out of their minds terrified
I'm more of a problem to
And that's not good if your Enlightenment ruler trying to send a message to the crowd
Because when they see terrified people who is one author said
Clearly understand the implications of both what they have done
And what they're about to have done to them
The crowd tends to become more sympathetic
Annies Enlightenment rulers want
You do not want the crowd sympathizing
Or going to the side of the condemned
That's a complete
Slap in the face
In what the whole point of these executions were right but if you have a poor
Woman convicted of infanticide
Who no longer be sure that she's going to heaven and has no one telling her that that's everything that's going to happen
A person who make beats
Falling Up
Heart as they're executing her emotionally
I mean
The crowd can be vicious and want to see blood
But part of why they're going for this event
Is it it is an amazing human drama
It's not just watching people
Be killed
It's watching everything as we quoted from the Freeland piece of me in the most intimate moments of someone's life and death
And you having an emotional
High and low roller coaster rides throughout this whole thing is Again part of the attraction what will you ever find
It is this deep
And real
Facebook on English executions historian vac gatrell
Quotes Edmund Burke
You know one of the Enlightenment writers from the. Famous guy
Talking about the draw
Of these sorts of things these executions in
You know sort of where they speak
To humanity in their soul
And as quoted by
Kittrell
Burke rights quote
Choose a day on which to represent the most Sublime and affecting tragedy we have
Take the most favorite actors
Spare no cost upon the scenes and decorations
Unite the greatest efforts of poetry
Painting and music
And when you have collected your audience
Just at the moment when their minds are wrecked with expectation
Let it be reported to the state criminal of high rank is on the point of being executed in the adjoining Square
In the moment
The Emptiness of the theater would demonstrate the comparative weakness
The imitative Arts
And proclaim the Triumph of real simple
And quote
Comparative weakness
The imitative art
The Triumph of
True sympathy I mean isn't this
What we asked earlier if you made two films
In one show the pretend
Pain and suffering that we normally do in our movies in another show the real thing with real bullets real guns real
What used to say
Might depend on
The specific individual in question right are you the kind of person that would go see a movie or movie be
Remind me of Charles dickens's explanation
Why people go to these public executions and what they get out of it he said
It is in our secret nature
To have a dark and Dreadful interest in the subject
I need that sort of rings true least to my sensibilities
Makes you wonder what else is in our
Secret nature
Are we all
In a wired the same way do we all have that secret nature or some people different than other some people choose the real violence movie
Others would never think of going to that they want to go see
The imitative
Because after all
It provides
A buffer that allows you to enjoy violence where if you knew it was real You couldn't possibly have fun
Knowing that that person was suffering
Did your thing to me that for other human beings
That's exactly what makes it more exciting and worth watching
Then they pretend stop right people really are suffering the Triumph is Burke said of real sympathy
Now both Charles Dickens in Edinburgh are specifically referring to the English
Xperia it's not really British yet although often times when you say English in this. Includes whales
This is one of the most
Intensely studied
Versions of the public execution experience when we have these questions
And you are reading in the English language
The majority of the sources you're going to have are from England and it's
Use the whole thing because the English experience is somewhat different than the continent for example we mentioned earlier a penchant for hanging
As we all know right hanging has been around since before recorded history
Maybe the cheapest the dirtiest way to execute somebody you can think of right
No muss no fuss as long as you don't care about the suffering of the victim
It's about as easy as you can get it's also sort of banal
From a spectacle standpoint
You know if you were actually crafting this for the
You know the spectacle itself you'd say hanging really come on
Where is the
The English we should point out
I pretty much enjoyed most every type of execution at one time or another they take a backseat to no one
One on the continent
And during various reins
They would boil you they bring it in love to burn Heretics but then who doesn't
Journeys R Us
But the English experience has really color the whole
Your question of public executions in the way the crowd behaves
It's colored all of us in English speaking countries cuz the predominant
Amount of evidence comes from England
Colors
Experience in other ways because the English are
Ahead of their time I guess you can say
In terms of the development of things that influences the public
Execution so
If you're one of those historians that wants to make
State Authority
Number one reason for these executions being the way they are
Or the English r
Ahead of most of the rest of the world and state formation modern Post westphalian State formation
Right to their head of the game on
Do you see the trends
Showing up earlier there
If you want to talk about the religious ritual side of the executions and how when that was eliminated because the absolute
Just rulers
Didn't think it was helping them deter crime
Again
The English were ahead of the game on that one too if for no other reason than
And unlike the absolutist regimes of the. On the continent in England it's not an absolutist Virginia
You have a king but you have Parliament that mean it's all pretty
Famous Riley
English system different than the continent but interesting lead a whole group of historians will say well that's why the
English execution situation so different
How is it different
Well
Certainly it fits The Stereotype that we often think of all these executions a lot more because the stereotype itself is of the
English experience the whole Carnival Atmos
Sphere
At the public execution
Very English
The
Bravado and the almost a joking nature that some of the condemned will show with the crowd
You're the famous line
If they would make the executions go through a very long soda procession on the way to the execution spot
And they were bars on the way and one of the execution victims famous Leanna
Go to the bar and get the drink or has it brought out them says I'll pay you on the way back and you're the crowd loves that right a little bravado on the way to
Your death
The English example is also unusual because they go through one of these periods where they sort of Troy
Try to deter crime the way we talked about at the very beginning of the story
But in certain areas the
Legal system will get it through their head that the best way to
Deter crime is to have maximum penalties for even minuscule cry
Lots of
There's a whole Chinese dynasty for example these other areas where
And you steal something you're gone
Any little crime you're gone
In England is known now as the bloody code
Which was a series of legal measures very class oriented by the way very skewed against the lower classes
It started making
Almost anything you can think of
At least on the law books
Punishable by Death
You pickpocket somebody
4 more than 12
Pence twelve pence nothing right 12 Pence of value boom
Eligible for the death penalty
You wore disguise in the forest boom eligible for the death penalty
How many got to beat like crazy
I mean if you go and look at the law codes
In England in the 1650s there
Probably half a hundred
Offenses that can get you the death penalty
How do you write it in this is an era not that far from the Middle Ages and been on 50 things or what and I'll get you the death penalty
Amir Century later
It's like 200
Offenses will get you the death
And as I said many of them very small to very famous.
In English History
Now we should point out
That there's lots of Pardons and
Acts of mercy and all these things that the ruler in the church and whatnot can provide so that a lot of these people sentenced to death don't
I'm actually go to The Gallows
About a 35000
Death sentences
BAC control says
Only 7000 executions happened
But the executions were often
Have people very much like the poor people who came to watch the execution
And the crimes they were being killed for
We're things that many in the crowd didn't consider all that bad
You take a woman who starved her child
And bring her up on the Gallows in England as
Did happen
And the women in the crowd will yell and scream horrible things at the red
Did you bring a little petty pickpocket
Or somebody who is Maybe
Poaching the king's deer in the forest or something like that up there
And then they make a jaunty Brave speech and maybe talk to her
Pretty girl in the audience right before their executed
And the crowd could find themselves very much
On the side of the condemned
Wow
It's hard to imagine some of the more absolutist machines in Europe putting up with say
Anti-government
Screens on The Gallows from there condemned
Criminals in England gatrell says they have a long-standing custom of allowing
The Condemned to say some stuff
Before they die even if it gets the dishes
Letter said earlier the English usually like to hang
They're condemned criminals
And while this might seem like a more merciful sentence than some of the things we've been talking about
Going on in Germany in the Netherlands and France and places like that
Good trail reminds us that
You know it's not as
Sweet and nice as you may think I mean if you're thinking of judicial hangings today
Those should be called neck
Would be a more
Accurate
Because they're
Scientifically designed in most cases
To break the neck
Of the execution victim
Which is theoretically quick
And theoretically painless
Before the modern era though
If somebody's neck broke that was a side byproduct that wasn't the goal
They were often using ropes that
12 in Long
I'm turning people off
Lottery
That's not neck-breaking
That's good old-fashioned strangulation
And gatrell reminds us
That they are much nastier than the thin veneer of respectability
It is often used with euphemisms another ways to disguise the horribleness of it
He says when you when you get right back down to Basics you were talking about
He says the choking
And the pissing and the screaming
And that is often hidden in the sources
The people who went and watched it live
You damn well what they were saying and getting as
He also points out and just blew my mind when I read it I'm going to quote it verbatim
He said quote
Late eighteenth and early nineteenth century English people were very familiar with the grimy business of hanging
This is so large a social fact
Separating that era from our own
That although it is not the most obvious way of defining modern times
It must be one of them
And quote
In other words
Defining modern times if you want to look at it that way
It's the age where we are not
Familiar
With public executions
Where the idea
But you might see a human body hanging
Somewhere near you
And not think of that as something out of the ordinary
Is what separates modern times from shall we say
Early modern
X
I will say
That the English rationale the way that the English defend
Their massive amount of executions compared to
Places like Prussia and the Netherlands that are starting to really really really decline their execution
Is the English do it in sort of
We Americans would say with a liberty argument
They claim that the only way to deter crime in their system
Is by making sure that if they catch you
You will receive maximum punishment because the chances of catching you are tiny
Because the English do not want to live in a police state
History palfrey lucente frenchify
Police state like those absolutist regimes in the price you pay
We're not having that surveillance to deter crime in advance
Is allowing that they're going to be that crime
But if the authorities catch you
You will receive a
Enormous penis
And it supposed to have
Just like the executions on the European continent a deterrent effect
As a famous Axiom from the time
Said
In Britain that men are not hanged for stealing horses
But that horses may not be stolen
Bright
Control quotes in minister of parliament writing in the middle 1800s
Who said that the question was not quote one of softening the heart
Or saving the souls of murderers
Butter preventing the Queen's subjects from being murdered
And quote
And he also points out
The hanging isn't
Something that was chosen because
It's particularly easy necessarily even though it is
But because it was particularly appalling in terms of sending a message he says no one who lived in
That era was under the illusion
The hanging was anything other than a horrible way to die
It's also a very dishonorable way to die
And this is not the sort of things
That we would pay much attention to when we look back we're focused on the pain in the suffering of the actual execution are
But if you could bring back someone from that era
And watch one of these executions on television
Together
They would notice things that maybe we wouldn't
And they would be able to determine whether or not the
The court that sentence this
Malefactor had considered
You know that they should be extra harsh or extra lenient I mean for example where they dragged into the scaffold to The Gallows or
The Ravenstone
In a freshly skinned
Ox-hide
They were it's more dishonorable
Is a whole bunch of
Things that we would call symbolic today that don't matter much to off that would have been
To some of these people more important than the fact that they were dying
I was fascinated to read some of these things where
Yeah they're really trying to
Alter their sentence these people who are being sentenced to who committed these crimes one way or the other
But you're not trying to get out of dying either they're trying to die in a more honorable way
Where they're trying to reduce the number of dishonorable things that have to happen to them on the way to their death
Once again
Hard for us to understand today cuz their status in their society means nothing to us of course
A shame and dishonor plays its role in the state's effort to use these Affairs to deter other pee
People from committing these crimes right in that sense the people in England
We'd better be called British somewhere in the middle of the story
Are not in any way different
Then their neighbors on the continent during this time. And in fact not very different from you know people conducting next week
Fusions all throughout history I mean isn't that the overwhelming reason you do them
Naughty
Only but it's right stop people from committing those kind of crimes
But of course as we said
You everyone in Europe during this time. In the West End during this era where
The ritual side of things the religious side of things soda fading more into the background leaving people that are more concerned with effective
Deterrence is what you're after
Amor Amor the public intellectuals in these countries start asking
Legitimate questions about
Well is that what we're getting
Are we getting determined effects for these horrible spectacular executions in there was a lively debate
You would think that exhibit a
For anyone making the argument these executions were tutoring people would be the fact that the audience is enjoying themselves
Right there not
Terrified and awed by the Majesty of the Law & Justice
You're more likely to be worried that they didn't pack enough snacks in case the pregame festivities for this little event run long
She got this disconnect between what you're after what you're getting and then you have this third big elephant in the living room and we've already
Alluded to this earlier it's
Sometimes just called the change in Sensibility
As with everything in this happens at different times in different places and there's a trickle-down
Will start sometimes
Other times it will become some of the litterick Latin to be a trickle-down overtime
Some of these changes and sensibilities will never reach
The lowest class
The people
I'm trying to explain the so-called change and sensibilities is as difficult as trying to explain something like
Why did the 1960s happen
Right I mean it's going to be
Is zeitgeist
As sometimes reality can be referred to
And playing into the Zeitgeist going to be all different kinds of friends and forces and whatnot I mean to just give you one little teeny strand
As an example of how
How many things are playing in with the growth of the popularity of novels
In this period from about 1500
People reading more these things
With characters and storylines designed to get them to
Feel
And be sensitive and care
And have empathy for the people in the story right
I read one historian who suggested that there's a cause and effects paying back and forth between the culture in these novels but then Essentia
Actually they were training
People
To have empathy now again who's reading novels in these societies right the literate people to begin with so
It's not a broad-based change in sensibilities
What is the change in sensibilities amongst
Shall we call the class of people
The most folk want to emulate
Many of these countries
You now have middle-class people
And a certain amount of Mobility that didn't exist in
In the classes before
And one of the ways you Associated yourself with the better classes to emulate their attitudes
And if they were starting to think
The public executions were Goshen
And if there was something inhuman about them
And barbaric
Well then those are the kinds of attitudes that began to
You infuse your class overtime right as I said the trickle-down effect
Now here's the thing
Why would these executions be considered
Anything other than great entertainment wasn't at these hobbyist from the upper classes that were first going and enjoying them spectacles to be
Begin with
Well here's the way
Astoria Paul Friedland explains it
You brought brushing when you talk about the intellectuals of the Enlightenment because there were different opinions from the intellectual
Rules of the Enlightenment
But one of them was that man
For lack of a better word
Is basically good
And it would basically sympathetic and basically empathetic
And if you're in a situation where a lot of people aren't that way than they've got screws loose right there the outline
That's not normal human behavior that's abnormal human behavior the problem isn't that when these people are writing this
That's the way their societies are behaving Paul Friedman rights quote
The growing public fascination with
And curiosity about executions
We're on a collision course with contemporary piano Theory
Which regarded exemplary deterrence is the very reason for punishment
I change the French
He continues
Quote while the new penal voyeurism was still restricted to the relatively privileged members of society
You seem to take notice of the discrepancy between the intent of the punishment
And the way in which it was being perceived by The Spectator
What is this new way of watching made its way down the social ladder
Alarm Bells were sounded
And quote
He then points out the
The praying and weeping crowds from the religious ritual era
It probably never really been terrified by executions the way the state wanted
This was
Kind of getting
Ctrl e then points out
But there's a third element involved this elephant in the living room this Revolution and Sensibility
She said quote
At the same time another cultural crisis was looming on the horizon
Over the course of the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries
A revolution and sensibilities would sweep over both sides of the channel
Human beings would be reimagined as naturally benevolent and compassionate
The eager anticipation of amateurs
To watch executions as if they were a dramatic performance
For perhaps even worse
The callous indifference of those in the windows
Who watched and felt nothing
Would be difficult to square with the new view of human nature
As instinctively compassionate
And quote
He then goes on to say
Did you have this growing conflict between Spectators desperate
To watch people die on the scaffold
Penal theory that is built around the idea that people won't be able to watch that kind of thing without being terrified
And he said the culture of sensibility that insist that people can't watch this stuff without being horrified
Because if they are horrified
The kind of inhuman
The reactions of the crowds
A lot of these cases
Vexing Boethiah
Authorities
And a lot of the intellectual class
It would not reacting the way that they were supposed to
Not as the target audience for these spectacles of Justice
Not as human beings watching cruelty to other human being
I read in one of the things I was researching to this program
An account where they were talking about watching somebody burning alive in front of you today
And they said it's impossible for most people
To watch something like that up close without feeling almost physical pain themselves
And then it's not a mental respond
It's not like you actually process it all its instantaneous
That's right you almost feel the physical pain for the person who suffering in front of you
Just like a drama saying about people not vomiting at the horrible executions
A people like Damian right there not vomiting we would today in large numbers why
It's not a process thing it's something that's so ingrained in US
Did it justice become physical somehow the
Does the cultural Elements by Cantrell said that you cry based on what your culture tells you you should be crying at
In the fact that you couldn't watch somebody burning alive today
Without feeling physical pain and somebody before this Revolution and sensibilities happened
Could
Is an interesting difference in US isn't it
I still can't
Make myself believe
That we're not empathetic creatures may just be
Discriminatory and pathetic creatures I mean if you're watching someone broken on the wheel you may or may not care about
Bottom if it's your child
I think you're going to feel every blow as if it's happening to you personally
Maybe you feel that way if it was your first cousin
Maybe you feel that way if it was your second cousin twice removed your neighbor from down the street
But maybe it's some point
You no longer feel quite the same you're not quite feeling the blows like it's your own child
As we said about the Roman Arena how did these Romans watch these people
In a massacred in front of them in horribly painful ways and enjoyed they didn't see them as human Maybe
I just laid it's a Christian to visit to that not human not the same not my kid
I said earlier that I want to do this from
A couple of different hang
Simply taking that approach seems to be a perfect example of something we do in the post
Revolution and sensibilities age that maybe would not have been such an obvious way to do it before
It's an effort to try to
Walk a mile in the moccasins of the people in this story write
An effort to gain a little empathy for what they were going through a little sympathy
It's kind of strange because of course
And there are so many different things how would you be able to gain any real empathy
And some of these questions have no answers but
There's something human in this that wants to ask them anyway I mean take for example
Trying to have a little empathy
With someone who's going to get their head cut off
I asked you
How would anybody know what that felt
Doesn't keep us from wondering though does it
I imagine you'd Wonder a hell of a lot more in a lot more intensely
If this be heading that we're
Theorizing about what about to happen
To you
If it's me
I have to break this entire
Experience down into two halves
The obvious have
What's it like walking up to that scaffold and dealing with the execution
But then there's a whole other half
Which is easy to forget about when we're just discussing this order from a high-minded
Now
What's it like to live with this hanging over your head
4 days
4 weeks
Iran account by app
Boxing trainer
Famous guy who said the minute the fight was signed
Is boxer instantly started Living with
The fear no matter how tough and strong and
Badass Leeward of their opponent any live with it every night they would wake up in a cold sweat and ever dream about
Just up all the time
What's it like living instead of
Knowing you're going to face Joe Louis on the 25th of August
You're going to get your head cut off on the
25th of August
You got to believe that there were people that actually seen some writings
The Condemned or basically just over it by this point they're doing this is prolonging the agony let's just get the whole thing over with
Prolonging the agony is part of the whole deal
When we make a transition by the way from
From the religious figure sincerely trying to save the soul to an Era where
The authorities are looking at the religious figures in the much less devout way and seeing them as just another way to break down the condemned
Bright
This whole situation breaks people down so I can Lodge
Doesn't it
What's worse
Horrific agonies you put yourself
Through mentally before
The event or the event itself
Depends on what
Going to happen to you
You right
In your head if you're thinking you got off easy
That breaking on the wheel charge that you could have been convicted of has been commuted to a nice honorable quick
Decapitation I'm sure in your head you're thinking of the stories were you for those things
Things go wrong right
Take the one
The. Joel Harrington in his book The faithful executioner accounts
A woman in Nuremberg
Convicted of infanticide this is as you will know already probably by listening to me
Pretty pretty common charge in this era
I'm sure today we would
Chalk a bunch of that up
Postpartum depression
Nonetheless
Lot of women going to their deaths in this era
For killing their newborns
Woman named Margarita boeglin
In 1641 an extremely beautiful person of 19 years
She's describing the sources
Most to be decapitated
She was sat in the chair
She was made ready by The Executioner's
Assistance
Make sure that the neck is
Get exposed in the right area
And in this particular kind of execution By The Sword you swing it like a baseball bat more than you swing it like a chopping
Instrument
Do you want a nice level swing
And you didn't always get
According to 1 Chronicle reprinted by Harrington
Quote
This poor child was very ill and weak so that she had to be carried and brought to the Gallows or Ravenstone
How much is sat down on the chair Meister Valentin he's the Executioner
By the way
Circled around her
Like a calf around a Manger
And with the sword
Struck a span of wood in a piece of skin as big as a coin from her head
Knocking her under the chair
And since he hadn't heard her body and since she fell so bravely the crowd asked that she be released
No such luck though Harrington says
In from underneath the chair he says the victim now wounded
Cried out this 19 year old girl
Quote Oh help me for God's sake what she said often and repeated
Then The Executioner's assistant grabbed her and set her back on the chair
Whereupon the Executioner delivered a second blow
And this time hacked in the neck behind her head
At what she however fell from the chair
Still alive again shouting God have mercy
After this the hangman hacked and cut her head on the ground
And quote
There's another account
In another book of a hangman in
Greeting hangman in northern France
The required more than 20 blows of the sword
To cut off the head
Of his bick
I'm a
Four Swordsmen
That might even be a
Generous description
But I can't imagine taking
20 Strokes of the sword
Wrapped in human neck
It should be pointed out that legally most of the time these executions were allowed three strikes it's a little late
All right three strikes and you're out
And help meant the crowd to pick up stones and throw them at you
Not legally of course the king never said what you can kill my executioner
He doesn't do in three Strokes
You know there's an Unwritten rules to baseball and
Decapitations in this era to
And even if you sat there and wondered about how quickly a decapitation went if it went well
Maybe you would worry that it might not
Unless if it did go well
Wouldn't you choose
This method if it were
You up to you although there are different ones right I mean as we said earlier
I think you know if you're going to go through
An execution during this era
You know what is your choice of method of dying because there's no Lethal Injections
I don't need a whole lot of accounts of
Hemlock drinking since Socrates back in ancient Athens
And believe it or not we modern people
Obviously think of shooting is a
Potential
Method to get out of this
Relatively painlessly
And yet that seems to be something that was confined to
How soldierwood
To be treated rather than someone in civilian life you don't hear a lot of shootings
As a civilian form of execution
When is Sarah starts though
It's coming
Ricky cuz it starts off with sort of the biblical approach
Two execution methods write us with an eye for an eye Mosaic law kind of thing
And so for example of a murderer in the latter part of the Middle Ages maybe into the Renaissance
With a hammer he might be executed
You don't want to scaffold by an executioner holding a hammer
I've heard all different kinds of accounts what what the ritual was in there
Religious elements to it but it even goes back to pre-christian Superstition canceling out the evil of the deed
You hit your murder victim with a hammer that we hit you with
With one
And even when the era of actually dispatching people that way
You know starting to go away
In some places usually once again outside the big cities when you get to the superstitions Countryside
They would still include the eye for an eye thing even if it was only symbolic
So we might strangle the person
Who was the hammer murderer
But then after they were dead hit him with a hammer few times as what you know
Symbolic Act
So the ways in which people were killed in this early. Though often mirrored what they did if you were an arsonist a burn you
They drowned a lot of people for a lot of crime scene
Drowning believe it or not an actual form of execution widely practiced during this era
And you decapitate you break you on the wheel any number of things
Right
The other thing that could happen to you
Course is it they could do damage to you on the way to being executed
So if just dying isn't enough for you in this early. You might be tortured on the way to death and one of the ways that was pretty popular
Involve those famous red-hot tongs
We alluded to them earlier I think it's got giant pincers
That are glowing
Orange
And then what they do is they take what we're called usually nips
Out of you
They would take the glowing pincers take it to a piece of skin maybe your breasts maybe your arm
And take him and burn and rip a chunk out
More than three nips
I ready
Considered to be fatal
And nobody wanted to give anybody more than
The goal was to have someone suffering not to have them die before they died where they
We're supposed to win the way they were suppose
I'm still
But there's broadsheets and carvings in artwork showing the Executioner riding in the cart with the victim
You know giving him the prescribed court-mandated number of nips on the way to the
Scaffold
Facebook seeing Justice Done starring Paul Friedland
Quotes a primary source someone who witnessed one of these executions this one in December
Involving
The pre-execution nastiness
Furosemide
Psychologically torture you as you thought about it
4 days or maybe weeks
Ahead of time
He writes
Quote
The guilty party
After having made a full confession
Was condemned to be
Executed
After the reading of the Judgment the Executioner had him getting into a cart
And he was placed on the knees of The Executioner's wife
The Executioner then began to torture him
With red hot pincers until they reach the house of the cannon who he had murdered
They're the Executioner cut off both his hands
Upon A chopping block
That have been placed for this purpose on the cart
The Executioner's wife blindfolded him
And her husband cut off a hand
She would place the stump
From which a spurt of blood was escaping into a kind of cone
Witches solidly tied up to stop the hemorrhaging
He was then led to the core debayle where he was decapitated and cut up into four pieces
Which were then hung from olive trees outside the city walls
And quote
Now again one of the ritualize aspects of this that was also popular in the earlier. What can go
Go to the scene of the crime
To carry out the act of Justice right so we cut this guy's hands off
Outside the home of the person those hand killed
This is another aspect that may have kept the size of the crowds down at earlier executions because there was no set spot
For the right if you had to have them
At important ritualize places connected to the crime itself they were in different spots all the time
Once you have a raven stone or a Gallows that's in the same place all the time probably in a pretty high traffic
Bigspot
Well then everybody knows where the execution is going to be
Usaw corresponding growth in
Crowd size
In fact historian Richard Evans says crowd sizes showing up these public X
Executions in Germany will continue to rise
And will be at their very highest when the practice
Is done away with
You never really lost its draw
And it's draw
Once you know you start getting
The numbers of real reason you don't have a lot of the information before this. Is it wasn't recorded
Once you start getting the numbers
It's already a lot of people showing up to these
Garrett Fagan says that win
The sources begin to pay attention he says to The Spectators in the 18th century
The crowds emerge as substantial to enormous
Evans and rituals of Retribution right specifically about the German experience quote
Although contemporary estimates must be taken with a pinch of salt
It is clear that the crowds at these events were frequently very large
It was said that 20,000 people attended an execution in the thuringia in town of Klingon in 1788
For example
And the same number the last public burning
Eldon eisenach in 1804
Welding 1771 the night before the execution of Matthias klostermeyer the town of Munich
Nick was
Now he's quoting a primary source from that era
Quote
Already so filled with Outsiders that they could barely be accommodated anymore in private houses
That's the next day's Dawn had scarcely broken when a wave of people came flooding through all the streets and alleys
And while one part of the crowd pressed onto the town hall
The other hastened over the Danube Ridge to the place of execution
Where the mass is Multiplied more and more
Evans continues quote
In the Saxon capital of Dresden at the execution of the Bandit
Lips tullian in four of his companions in crime on the 8th of March 1715
More than 20000 people
144 carriages and some 300 horses looked on according to a contemporary report
On the 19th of February 1807
Now quoting from a contemporary report
Thousands of Spectators surrounded the high Market in Vienna where The Condemned man got onto the wag
With the two preachers
Thousands of people filled the streets
And many thousands of spectators
Turn around in a circle at the place of execution
Eden quotes a person who remembered
The entire population turned out in the town he was from during an execution in the streets and houses away from
From the execution Square were completely devoid of life
Victor gatrell says that in
England London you could sometimes have crowds of 100000 people or more
Let's remember all these numbers come from
Times and places where the populations were a lot smaller than they are now
Some of these towns that had 20000 people show up for
Executions may not have had 20000 people living in the nearby vicinity
And this was an ERA when it was a lot harder to get from place
Play some 20000 people showing up at a village execution is a lot of people
100000 people showing up to an execution in London
Is a large execution even though that's a big city
After all
100000 people is a large
Spectator crowd at a major sporting event now
With population transportation and everything up to Modern standards
So good luck finding anything
The Drew is many people in this time.
Aziz executions did
As large as some of the battles of the.
Another reason this plays into walking a mile in the moccasins of The Condemned here
Is because they literally sometimes had to do that
On the way to the x
Execution site
Conditions were different everywhere
But a lot of the more famous sites there were long for sessions that took you
You know to the place where you were going to die
And there were a lot of people
Who viewed you and screamed at you
Or supported you as the case may be along the way
In fact
It's probably not too much of a conjecture to wonder if The Condemned person had ever seen a crowd as large as the
The one that shows up to watch them die
The
Place where you're dying May determine
And how the crowd reacts the time. May also and of course the nature of your crime
Sometimes they were
All over you in a terrible way making your experience that much worse
Sometimes they were sort of in your Camp praying for you hoping for you
Or maybe just a little bit sympathetic it in the later. To your roguish courage that you're showing on the scaffold or whatever it might be
It's interesting to note that when they will finally do away with the
In a public execution hear some of the people who were critical of that said that your
Depriving The Condemned of the of the only support they have in this moment where they're going to die right to cry
Crowds on their side but sometimes it's not
There's a lot of stories about
Especially you know the crowd in England could be particularly nasty if they didn't like you
And things thrown in an epic that's her old and all kinds of things
Think about how much that plays into the experience though
Of the terribleness of it if you're The Condemned having to see all these people
I just your your senses absolutely must have been overwhelmed
By the amount of sensory input coming your way
There's several accounts where
The I really just figured you were writing these accounts say that The Condemned all along the procession
Kept her eyes focused a couple of inches from their face
Add a crucifix
Fix it was being held out going to just kind of trying to tunnel vision this thing and not think about another thing about the not thinking about it
If you're trying to walk
A mile in the other man's moccasins or woman's moccasins as the case may be
Is it that person
Sober
And if it was your situation you were dealing with here would you be
Earlier we quoted that British Observer who watched a breaking on the wheel in Germany are breaking with the wheel
And he was critical of the idea that these people wouldn't go to The Gallows
Ravenstone is we said
So intoxicated that they really didn't know what was going on that it kept them from making their most important last piece
So what have we got in the world in the whole thing what you want to kind of have your wits about you when you do that cuz it's really important
He mentioned that the crowds would have took that job
For him so that maybe The Condemned could be out of it
In in many of these different areas that are chronicled
There are
Shall we call them alcohol
Injection opportunities along the way and some of its built into the ritual right some of these places
These Bars along the famous execution router known for any stop here you bring the condemned in here and he gets
A glass of wine from Austin
It's gentle
Contribution to the public do it or whatever it might be
Cottrell points out over and over how many of these people going to the Gallows were
Dead drop
Practically now here's the thing again
Who wants to broad-brush cuz let's say
You're going to be beheaded on the continent one of those
Lucky people who get the decapitation is your sentence
You don't want to be drunk I would think I mean you might want to be so you don't know what's going on but if you don't know what's going on you
Might move
The number one reason that people didn't have successful decapitations is cuz they moved
So you don't want to be swaying around drunkenly
Having who knows maybe a slightly drunken executioner trying to
Figure out how to
Time the wobble
What
Experience might be when The Condemned finally reaches the scaffold looks out
Cease that crowd
Look at a fear of public speaking imagine what that's like
Although some of these
People in the places that let them speak would speak their usually be
Awesome religious stuff that would go on the scaffold and during the ritual religious. Quite a bit sometimes
And then the execution with command
Do you feel
Anything in a decapitation that goes off well do you have any Consciousness at all
The tablet
Why do people feel right about this is a famous and I'm sure totally discredited so don't even bother
I'll say it's probably just credited at the outside of people
Some men are doctors during the time. Working in the era when the guillotine was in
Heavy use you know that Blade the drops
Mechanically separated
Head from their body
They have some I guess if I'm going to remember you're had some discussions with The Condemned basically saying listen
Bridges experiment
Your dad so
You know what you feel anything blink you know things like that
Slapping the face of the recently
Decapitated head and
Trying to get the eye to focus on them
Let's just say it's been interesting to wonder even with the spinal cord severed
How long any amount of Consciousness might exist I mean
2 seconds
3 seconds
No seconds
That brings me to one of the interesting lines about hanging
That I looked up when I was trying to figure out a cave
If that's what decapitations like what is hanging
And hangings weird and I want to be careful here because while I was researching and I was shocked to find
A lot of comments from people who had relatives who would hang themselves and we're not so happy that
The various sites I was looking at we're giving detailed information about it I thought maybe you didn't able these horrible
Family tragedies in there so
Thousand apologies in advance that's not what I'm trying to do here but when you try to get into the minds of people
Lunch is going to go through this
But who are going to ruminate on what it's like to go through this for a long time before they actually do
You know what's that like an and I have to say that there is I've searched and searched I find no common agreement
On what it's like in terms of painful vs. Painful
Whole lot of different
Accounts
Some of which state very painful other account saying that they were out the minute it happened let's remember something though in this. As we say
Set earlier
This is not the
Modern kind of hanging where the goal is to try
To break the neck
Of The Condemned person through it
Particularly long drop
And a jerk in a specific direction that supposed to separate the spinal cord
Right considered to be again a quick death
No one's quite sure how long
In this era as I said earlier you would often see people hung on very short rope
It were like
12in long I mean if you go look at the
Artwork
From the.
It almost looks like they did it wrong like to Modern are you going with ropes not long enough they must have had to shorten it for that
To get it into the whole frame artistically speaking know that's how they did it
It look like somebody basically was hanging by
A really really 6in short rope
But that means you're strangled
By Design
And often times they would simply take you up on a ladder
Turn the ladder sideways
Have I said
And turn you off
It's called
In England before they got all fancy with the
The trapdoor stuff that used to just
Take several people sometimes on the back of a cart
In a hook him up to a Gallows which was often just
A
Piece of woods
Lay between two trees
And just drive off and leave those people as it was said dancing in the air
Those things by the way can go bad too
Because people would
Other lots of stories
Actually about
Family members and Friends definitely executioner sometimes
Having to run up and
You hold on and pull on the legs of their loved one
To try to speed this process up
I read several accounts are from people that all said that you get this really loud roaring in your ears
You're probably from the blood being constrained
And ones who survived said that when the Rope was removed
You know how it feels when your foot falls asleep and it's really painful when it starts to have pins and needles
They had that in their head and they said it was so bad you you halfway want to go back and be executed rather not have to deal with
I'm tempted to say after the research I've done that
The experience is heavily based on any number of variables
I could range
Across a wide spectrum of
And you were out one minute after they put the Rope around your neck to 15 minutes later you're still choking strangle
And
And convulsing
And the crowds watching that in taking note by the way this is all something we're
You are the entertainment
And one wonders
You know if you know
For any period of time
What's going on
You know mean your performance as its perceived by the audience for example
And it's like a contemporary can from the 1700 by Doctor Who's living in an area where they are executing people
By hanging a lot so we have a lot of time
You do research on this
And he says that there's a certain period of time with those being hanged
No they're hanging
Control quotes a doctor Alexander Monroe professor of anatomy Edinburgh
In 1774
Telling a guy named James Boswell vet quote
The man who was hanged suffers a great deal
Videos not once stupefied by the shop
Amana suffocated by hanging in a rope
Justice by having his respirations.
By having a pillow pressed on the face
For some time after a man is thrown over he is sensible
It is conscious that he is hanging
Ndk
There are lots of accounts of the Rope
Breaking
The malefactor falling to the ground and someone
Recovering and sometimes the crowd gets on their side that day
This is like a sign from God and they should be reprieved or later on in the nonce not so religious.
But it's not fair to try to kill somebody twice nonetheless they're often hanged again
But they give us some story sometimes about what it was like
You know what they perceived and again stories are variable so it
It's likely that it's
Independent heavily dependent on conditions and variables like where the Rope ends up for example around your neck
Is it around your windpipe or your carotid arteries things like
In fact a lot of these variable
What's the time
And
We talked about where to place the news and how to position
The Condemned
Svac
Trump wants out
Route 8 made little difference
And he'll mention the names of a bunch of different people that went to their death
On The Gallows here
Bill also
Caught a lot of primary sources so if you hear me say quote within the quote it's a primary source
He writes about these precautions
To position the Rope well to limit the suffering quote
These precautions did little good however
It was a common pattern in what ensued
As an early nineteenth-century broadside representatively declared
The news of one man's halter quote
Having slipped to the back part of his neck
It was a full 10 minutes before he was dead and quote
So too with the very last tyburn hanging in 1783
Quote
The news of the halter having slipped to the back part of his neck
It was longer than usual before he was dead and quote
Hatfields news
Slipped twice Cottrell says
And when he did drop it was only 18 in so his death was prolonged and noisy
Is
Struggled on the end of his rope for five minutes before he was still
Hartley quote
Was much convulsed
And struggled for 10 minutes after the drop fell
And quote
The not having slipped behind his neck Governor wall in 1802
Took 15 minutes to die in agony
So the hangman pulled on his legs
In 1804 and Harold was driven to a scaffold erected in the widest part of the Old Bailey
The regular dropping out of commission for a while
When the cart Drew away
Meaning when the cart
She was standing on Drew way and left her hanging
By her neck with nothing underneath her when the car Drew away quote
She gave a faint scream
And for two or three minutes after she was suspended appeared to be in great agony
Moving her hands up and down frequently
And quote
Control continues quote
Hanging glass go in 1824 treason James Wilson quote died with difficulty
And after it hung about 20 minutes
Blood was seen on his cap opposite the ears
In 1829 Thomas birmingham's rope
Slipped and quote
Prolong his sufferings to a considerable extent
He breathed in agony for nearly 5 minutes
Shouts and screams From the Mob cause the Executioner
To hang on his legs until life was extinct
And quote
And it could get wild and once again if you were in the crowd
Perhaps that's what keeps bringing you back you never know what's going to happen
Control continu
Is quote
Got a 1797 hanging the scaffold platform gave way
Precipitating clergyman and executioner to the ground
There was no time to hood the two prisoners
So they quote
Sworn off with their distorted features exposed to the view of the distressed spectators
And quote
An arsonist
Charles White
Struggled incessantly to escape his bond
He kicked at the Executioner
And the ordinary meaning the religious faith
I just lodging the cap hiding his face
The crowd yelled in excitement
Partly suspended destruggle still
Reaching the platform with his feet
Frida's hands and held onto the Rope
The Executioner had to force him from the platform
And pulling his leg
Does he choke
The crowd saw his distended tongue
And I'm covered in distorted features and they shriek
And quote
So even though there are accounts of hangings that make it sound
Like The Condemned
Seem to die almost instantly
And those definitely are throughout the historical record
Obviously they have these other kinds of incidents as well
Then there's stuff like burn
Which once again conjures up
The worst of the worst
Terrorist groups
Today in the
Deliberately medieval again as an adjective but also denoting a time. From long time ago work
You used to do this kind of Mosaic law stuff
Conjures up the worst of those kinds of groups
It's right when you talk about burning people to death but
They were still doing this up until the early 1800s
Again
After George Washington has died of old age
Women got it a lot more than men
And it was often viewed as an alternative so
Whereas we started to get much more enlightened
Breaking women on the wheel you wouldn't want to do that to a woman if you spare them the breaking on the wheel you burn them things like that
We mentioned earlier the
People who were burned on witchcraft charges
And United States that we usually hang but in Europe
Lots of burning
Some estimates as high as a hundred thousand people
Burned for witchcraft crimes in Germany alone
During this
Broad.
It wasn't just women although usually was
We can be all high and mighty about
You're not understanding our forebears for why they did that because we have the unique advantage of
Well
Most of us
Not believing in sorcery and Witchcraft and not thinking it's a problem in our community and not believing that they live amongst us
And not believing that the only thing that really fixes the problem is burning them to death
Checkr
Buy us right at the door on that one
If we were talking about something like terrorism that we did believe in and it was a hundred percent agreement that the only way you stopped that was through burning Terror
Or maybe even suspected terrorist to death
I imagine we have a future
Proponent to that
Even now
Nonetheless what was it like
To go through that burning experience
Well that depends also
And there's a lot of famous ones you know Joan of Arc comes to mind
Right
I read some accounts that talked about
The likelihood that the smoke it
Stealth would render a person unconscious
During the later. When they're still doing this into the 17 hundreds in Britain for example
They're doing the same version of secret strangling that they're doing in places like pressure but they're doing it
Openly like in one of the particularly horrific
More recent burnings
They were executing a woman for killing her
They call that petty treason by the
Major treason was like crimes against the state
Petty treason was a wife killing her husband
Nonetheless they had the
Strangulation thing rigged
If the wood cuttings I've seen are
Correct
Sort of on a chain
And it was around her neck on the steak and then somebody would hold this change well 15 feet away
Away from the faggots of wood that were burning
And strangled them just before the Flames reach them
But this time we were told that the chain got too hot
And the guy whose job it was to strangle the
The woman so she didn't have to suffer burning in the enlightenment.
In a word course you wouldn't
The burning will you didn't strangle
I had to let go with the chain
And everything got very old-fashioned very quickly
The woman's name by the way was Catherine Hayes
Who is burned alive
In London in 1726 this account comes from public executions the Nigel
Hawthorne book
And he takes an account
Sounds like a near primary source but maybe not from the Newgate calendar sound like a newspaper
And it says quote
He's received the sacrament
How much drag on a sledge to the place appointed for her execution
When The Wretched woman had finished her devotions
In pursuance of her sentence
An iron chain with put around your waist
With which she was attached to the stake
When women were burned for petty treason it was usual to strangle them by means of a rope
Passed around the neck and pulled by the Executioner
So that they were willfully insensible to the heat of the flame
But this woman literally burned alive
The Executioner let go of the Rope too soon and consequence of having his hand burnt by the flame
The Flames burn fiercely around her
And The Spectator beheld Catherine Hayes
Pushing away the fagets while she rent the air with cries and Lamentations
Other faggets were instantly piled on her but she survived amidst the Flames for a considerable time
And her body was not perfectly reduced to ashes until 3 hours later
And quote
So you have this image of a person
Struggling to kick away the burning
In a f****** of wood around her and they just keep piling moron
She doesn't sound like she's dying from smoke inhalation to me
And one of the things by the way that you will read about a little color here
In these later burnings the Executioner will sometimes hang on
Hello bagra pouch around the neck
Of the person
Manacled to the stake
And that pouch contains gunpowder
And I hope it is
That when things get hot enough that will explode putting you out of your misery so you don't have to be burned to death
And is the. Goes on your Reed
More more counts of
Like when noblemen have to be killed in a rarely but when noblemen have to be killed like that dildo be having whole bladder
Is filled with this gunpowder hoping for the best
And while that does by the way look a little like the secret strangling thing which enlightened ruler is trying to limit the suffering of The Condemned
There's also a practical
Way to look at this I mean this is insurance
Isn't it
So that you won't have another one of these incidents that gives the state of black I like some woman
Manacle to a post screaming to the crowd and kicking away the wood as fast as you can pile it back on that doesn't look good for
Little pouch in gunpowder around the neck might save us all a lot of trouble neck
Next time
And one thing I don't think we have pointed out that's worth mentioning
Is that a lot of these people being executed are bad people
Who committed bad crime
Write things we would
Treat severely today murder rape robbery all those kinds of things
So let's not make Angels out of these people that don't deserve it although I doubt no matter how bad you are we want you burned alive
That having been said let's remember
That in a lot of these places England for example we mentioned already
They are executing people for crimes that no modern stay whenever exit
Do people for
And
Even with all of our modern techniques
Justice system and everything we have going for us now we still make mistakes
And convictions right
What was the failure rate like you can only imagine
In this time. Cuz right before this time. When they're doing like
You know trial by ordeal
I'm going to throw you in the river in a few hours
Think you're innocent if you float you're guilty I mean in the world a little ways out of that. So
Imagine a bunch of these people being executed or bad people
Imagine a bunch of a mark
And if we're going to walk a mile in their moccasins and try to wonder how they must have felt don't you think
Afraid
Has to be like the most dominant
Emotion that's just overwhelming them psychologically breaking them
There were these Rogues and
People who went to their deaths almost
Carefree there were some others who went
With an almost hinge of Madness or perhaps neither one of those people
Has affected by fear as
The average
Joe or Jane
Back
Trailpoint out
That
And almost
Stupefying level of fear affected most people
He writes
Quote
Most people would Mount the scaffold
Now quoting primary source
Quote
Trembling in a very extraordinary manner
Their whole frame violently convulse
Their minds bordering on stupid vacation
Having to be supported by officials
He continued
Elizabeth Godfrey hang for murder in 1807 went to the scaffold in a state of frenzy
Green Acre in 1837 refused the attentions of the ordinary of Newgate bravely enough
What is the scaffold he was quote
Totally unmanned
All his fortitude had left him
He was unable to speak
And the officer was applied to support him or he would have fallen
End quote
He mentioned several other examples and then continues quote
An 18 year old girl had to be dragged to the scaffold at Bristol by half-a-dozen men in 18-49
The clergyman vainly asking her to walk quietly
My 1868
He writes
The images were seared in memory
Quote
Have fainting riches
Sometimes supported between warders and chaplain sometimes struggling fiercely with the Executioner
To plunge and shriek and kit
Until the lumbering dropped Falls
Sometimes sinking into pitiable syncope to be hanged sprawling over a chair
And quote
Cottrell says that for many
The fear they felt inside with betrayed by their bodies
Losing control of their bladder or bowels he says even Marie Antoinette had to squat on the cobblestones
Sr bowels gave away when she saw the cart that was going to transport her to the waiting guillotine
And it's not really the time or the place but there have been long debates about
Whether or not the culture the people in the past lived in
Made their fear less than ours would be today or even made there
Sensitivity to physical pain less than we would feel today
Without going too deeply into it
Most of the more modern things that I've been reading
Went
Out of their way
To contradict those earlier ideas but as I said another topic for another time
Let's just point out that when these women for example
In England went to the stake to be burned to death
The fire probably felt as hot as it would be for you or for me
Of course there's no way to prove it and with different person to person but I imagine that
In these times of of
Paralyzing fear those with extra strong religious believes might have had
A higher level of comfort
The most heartbreaking
Primary source accounts I ran into
Have to do with a
German arsonist woman who was I assume burned because during this period they often burned arsonists
But she was burned I think it's a steak but
The source
Chronicler whose writing this for religious purposes so understand that going into it
Point out that as she is
Being
Executed
She is calling out to Jesus basically saying don't go anywhere I'll be there in a minute I'm coming I'm on my way
I mean here's what
Historian Richard
Evans chronicling this in
Rituals of reprobation Rights he says quote
The last words of Anna to blur an arsonist executed in Spiller in Silesia on 6th November
Number 1744 we're very similar
To someone else
Quote
Lord Jesus she cried
I'm here Lord Jesus I'm coming now
Lord Jesus take my soul up to heaven
And quote
You can hear can't you
The
Desperation
Right make sure you hear me I'm coming right now
Found myself
And greatly moved by
And I can only imagine that those
Of lesser faith that found themselves in the same position might have been just a little bit jealous
Karl Marx
Famous quote
About religion being the Opium of the masses
Well if you're about to be burned at the stake don't you think a little opium
Or a lot of opium is just what the doctor ordered
In fact
If it's me we're probably medicating from the time
The most
Insane moment in the whole Affair happens again as a modern person we would think that moment is
The moment when the Flames are lit right in front of you is your change of the steak
Are the people in this era
If I'm reading the sources correctly
The insane moment one that would be on their life stop 5
You know most impactful moments in my life if they were
Catalog in something like that at the very end you'd have to say that you know somewhere on the top 5 list is that moment
The Executioner actually touched me
Because the touch of the Executioner
Is an inch
Saying saying you have to talk about the Executioner to set up a little bit about how someone back then
Might have felt about
We've been looking at this from the point of view for a little while now the person doomed to die in this X
Situation really when you think
The star of the show
There's another star of the show maybe call them the supporting a
Actor
And their role in this
If we're looking at the question of you
Streams of The Human Experience is
Just as Extreme as the person who's dying up there for the entertainment of the crowd
It's his job to kill them for the entertainment of the crowd
And whereas The Condemned only have to go through this situation once
And then he's out of their misery
The person
On the other end of the story the best supporting actor if he does a good job in this Tale
Have to do it over and over again it's the way he makes a living if the way he feeds his family
And they have to think about it at night
Then you have to clean his equipment the next day I mean
This is a psychological challenge that in modern times
Terrible regimes have had a hard time dealing with a mean
There are stories you can read about
The German government during the Nazi years trying to figure out how you get around the problem of
The people that you get to shoot all these Jews that you lying a pit with
Army psychological problem
There's only so much liquor you can ply someone with
And yet they managed
These Executioner's back in Europe during the day
And it's more difficult to do that maybe even
Then a modern person might think
Because the tendency is to think something like well
You wouldn't have gone into that trade if there wasn't something you liked about it
Either you like the job
Will you like the pay in the benefits and you don't mind the job
We can think of any number of reasons why a person might choose or not choose to go into such a trade
The modern bias at work there though when I start to think like that
Is I forget that in many periods in human history people have no choice in this kind of thing
When I was growing up it was one of the things you would say about these unfree governments
In many parts of the world they're going to tell you what you do for a living in Americans and Western European wheat all shut it right
Make a basic human Freedom doesn't it
But in this era as in many other areas in places
The class
System is not very Mobile in fact
What we call class in a lot of these eras
Would be better called casts
And there is no Mobility between them and you can be born into a place in society where you have limited or no
Choices for example
Was your dad
Is an executioner
Guess what you're doing for a living in all probability
You're going to be executing people too and if you turn out to be one of those people of us
Artistic
Sensitive disposition
Really not the killer kind of person
Do you want to feed your family
You're going to learn the trade and figure out a way to make it work for you
Because the society in these areas wasn't going to let you do
Much more than that see here's the thing right away
That confronts our mental image are stereotypical image of the Executioner in this.
The hooded executioner and whatnot
That's more by the way something that happened in England than the continent but the reason wasn't because the Executioner
I wanted everyone to see their face and to be proud of the situation necessarily
Some of them may have chosen to obscure their features
But everybody else who lived in the town where the execution was happening
They damn well wanted to know
Where the Executioner was
And they wanted him to stand out of the crowd
Because they didn't want to accidentally come in contact with him in any way shape or form because he was
As Paul Friedland rights
An extraordinary being
Both extraordinary
Blessed in some ways with special powers
But also undeniably cursed with a lot of others
Including the ability to turn you from a
Honorable person
Into a dishonorable person in your heavily class base
Nae cast
Based almost
Society
Simply by touching you
And by the way this touching doesn't just mean
In a while they are performing their duties as executioner it means running into them even accidentally at the marketplace Avenue
Brush against them
You can be that innocuous
This is why
The authorities and the citizens want the Executioner dressed at all times in clothing that clearly marks out the fact you're the
The Executioner
And some places they have to carry like special staff that are certain colors so that
The crowd knows wait a minute
There's a guy who kills and tortures for money and if I touch him even accidentally I'm just honored
I imagine that you in the most crowded Marketplace there must have been a nice
Buffer zone of no people
Around this guy and his close family members
And I have to confess the more I read about The Executioner's of this era
It's it's probably fair to call them the X
The cutioner
Laugh
Of Central and Western Europe in this era
The more fascinated I am by them
That's not very much
On them
Surprising is that mites
To 21st century audiences and it's remark upon by some of the historians
Who say that the
Role of the Executioner was sort of downplay they were seen as more of a cog in the machine
As opposed to
How do you appear more now in the histories which could be compared to say a ringmaster at a circus a deadly
What's the person who's
Orchestrating
Conducting the entire Spectrum
If it works
This is the person who in a place like Germany will go up to the magistrate's afterwards and hold the sword up and said my Lord you know did I do well
You wait for his
You did exactly what you were supposed to do kind of response that's all formalized in
And everything
But if that guy screws up
Will Justice get the black guy whose fault is that right
And before we go any farther let's understand
That the ramifications for screwing up an execution
Could be a lot worse than losing your job
People throw stones
When things like that happens and executioners have been killed
Interesting me enough
One of the historians point out
That I read that they
Refrain from touching them though anyway
Why we're still not going to touch him even if we want to kill him or throw things at him cuz if we touch him
Then we get this out of right like leprosy another problem in the.
And it could spread
You don't even want to be near
You know somebody who could get you sick and well this is a different kind of sick
It's the
In early modern
Sickness known as dishonor and if you don't already have it
You don't want to get it
The idea of them as extraordinary beings is fascinating to me
And yet when I read the historian kind of go down the list of why
Do they might be called
Different kinds of beans to teacher singing and even on a genetic level because what ends up happening is this infamy
But these people have
Make them
Unmarriable for example
So the people that they end up marrying or often women who are from families of executioners also
So they sort of double down the stories they on their weirdness because they don't get to live with other people either
They're marrying into their own kind of
Class if you willing into distant relatives and mixing these families
And then over Generations you get these great executioner families
But they're a little strange because they're a bunch of people
Live in this world of executioners on both sides down many generations
And they don't get to mingle with anyone else
Historian Richard Benjamin
Points out
Quote
Because of his dishonorable occupation the Executioner lived outside the community
Which only served to heighten his Sinister image
He could only marry within his own Circle
So that a succession of execution was involved
The Executioner had to distinguish himself by wearing special clothes
Which generally different from his black or red Robes of office
Attempts to secure a special status by dress inconspicuously
Failed on account of the rigid dress regulations for the Executioner
You're a good wages and got uncomfortably
But he had to live outside respectable Society
Sit alone in a separate place in church and was required to eat and drink on his own at the end
And quote
And it's affected everyone in this family too
Condolences quote
The social implications of Dishonor we're suffered not only by the Executioner
At least had an occupation
But also by his children
Who were forbidden to learn and honorable crafts
Town Craftsman in particular ostracized the Executioner
And quote
The Paul Friedland really blew my mind when he talked about how this
Dishonorable
Taint
Turned all these people into people that could only
You'll hang out and intermarry with each other which overtime creates
Well dynasties an Executioner's related to each other
But also people who been
Intermarrying in a small circle for a long time genetically
Closer to each other
Then did any of the outside population he writes quote
How are we to explain the rise of this closely interrelated cast of people who gradually came to occupy
Time most of the official posts of executioner in the cities and towns of northern France
The Netherlands and german-speaking Northern and Central Europe
Perhaps the androgyny of executioners was itself the cause of the opprobrium
As practitioners of this very problematic profession came to be quite literally a separate
Tribal race of people
Most likely being dodging me and the revulsion attached to the profession were mutually reinforcing
Has Executioner's became more reviled they increasingly marry their own kind
Intern making them seem even stranger
And quote
It's reading who says that they became an extraordinary being
So profane
At the Executioner could not come into contact with other people or objects without profoundly altering them
In other words
A something kind of magical
And at the same time
An untouchable
The better ones also seem to be part
Psychologist or psychiatrist
Because they had to think about this
Instrument they had to Shepherd
Human beings
From life
To death
The mostest
Stream emotional and stressful moment of their lies right
And in these
Executions that we're almost always these
Carefully stage drama these spectacles of Justice
You had to go a certain way
Route to come off without a hitch
The Executioner needs the cooperation of The Condemned
They need to work together
To pull this thing off
I know that sounds weird
But it's in everyone's interest I mean we mentioned earlier that there's a journal and Joel Harrington's book on the faithful executioner
Wonderful
But unfortunately for we moderns the book does not address the things we want to dress The Executioner's name is French
Germany
He doesn't say here's how I live with myself and all these things we wanted
Every time you seem to be
Thinking about the victim too much he switches to what they did
And what made
Them end up in this position in the first place the horribleness with their crimes
By the way of something a lot
A lot of people would do today
Focus on the crimes not the justice
None the less hair even have a great
Color throughout the book and explains the context of all this stuff
He's just friend Schmidt executed 394 people
Over his career
And tortured and
Dished out corporal punishment the hundred more
Think about that for a minute
If a guy like that comes up to me
For the last drink right I mean we said earlier the one of the moments that might be the most impactful of your life is the moment.
Executioner touches you
Another might be when you're in the
Poor Sinners parlor as it was sometimes called
You know saying your goodbyes and talking with the religious figures and all that stuff and then the announcement comes in as it often did in the
German states especially
The Executioner is at hand
And this person shows up Frenchman showed up in his best Robes of office
Came with a drink
And share the famous last drink
With a condemned there also in many places with a famous line
Neil sometimes called The Hangman's meal
And this is supremely weird
I think was Richard Evans you pointed out for a lot of these poor
Convicted German criminals during this era
This lavish meal that they gave the right before they died was probably the greatest meal that they never had and
Far above anything that ever even seen
And often times the people who judge you
And the religious figures and even the Executioner will eat with you at this meal and you might be required to wear your own bear
Burial shrouds of the whole thing's not weird not at all right
It's part of the psychological breakdown I mean
I mean my burial shroud and having the best meal I've ever had to meet with the guy is going to kill me
But if a guy with 394 kills on his record come to me
And says listen
I know what I'm doing here I've done this a lot of times let me tell you how it's going to go easy as for you and easy as for me I think I'm
Going to listen to him after all
If I squirm around too much and don't do what this guy wants
He's going to take more than one shot at my head if this is a decapitation for example and should be pointed at
The historian had a great lie you said listen these people are under enough pressure anyway they have a reputation not
Totally
Without reason of drinking too much what would you do again your job to kill people how you going to handle that
But if these guys take too many strokes to do the job
It might be open season on them and violence is a Richard Evans print out violence against executioners who botched
The job
What the sources are abundant
But that'll make him even more nervous right so you really want this condemned to sit still work with you
And you'll all get out of here as easy as possible Right
I'm going to listen to the experts in this case if he explains to me
The best way to hold my head to make this go fast
I'm going to be broken on the wheel or broken with the wheel the directions might be a little bit more complex
Just to throw this in there cuz I think it's also interesting another reason these people are so dishonorable as they often had a lot of side gigs
Is in the community that we're also sort of untouchability things
Like cleaning the latrines and
Picking up dead animals and all the stuff people don't want to do right the unclean kind of stuff
But it's kind of interesting because they could often make a really good living
Almost to the point where they're rich
And one source pointed out how interesting it was good we modern people think that money is the great equalizer
And his point was not at all in the earlier you can be as rich as Midas but if you're at a certain level of society I mean if your reach is mine
Trains
Nobody cares
When did real well with all their side games and they were knackers and all these other things but
Nobody wanted to eat with him anyway
Another weird thing about him is it at the same time they are these dishonorable beans that you don't want touching you
They also were kind of thought it was magical Healers
Obviously they know a little bit about Anatomy
They also
Practice torture and keeping people alive to be executed in fact they probably had pretty darn good amateur
Knowledge it's kind of tough to have the person do what they need to do
In a way that doesn't dishonor you but people went to them as Healers
They also had another side business and this
One of the weird
Parts of the era left over from the Middle Ages
They could sometimes sell a little Blood on the side
The blood of The Condemned was often thought to have magical properties
Especially for epileptics
And a lot of these executions people rushed
Scaffold to get ahold of some blood
And the
Smart are more entrepreneurial Executioner's usually had the resistance
Already in advance ready to go basically saying something like that they get one they get one I mean
Son of a Dracula sidegig someone's blood but
In supply and demand and all that
Supply and demand is not a bad way
To describe
Some of the process that led to the decline of these Master Executioner's these Master Craftsman
Because of the 1700s
No go on
You get to the ladder part of them
These executions become rarer and rarer I mean the numbers are actually public
Rushing record
What are the records in the Netherlands the records in Paris
And you're seeing single digits in some places it sometimes right there
No reason to have a full-time executioner on staff and there's no reason to have a lot of them until they start declining in number
Amazon probably making professional
You know what Champs at the side gigs to make those work full-time but
You wind up with fewer these people
And as time goes on
They're getting older
One of the
History's I read had a letter
From one of these old Executioner's
Trying to assure a potential employer that he still got it
Right
Essentially was said something like you know I know I'm old I know the sword is heavy but you know it's like riding a bike
But it's a sign
If you were if you were these people are even around the ones that are around are getting old and they're not exactly
Are they saying boxing to rest is to rust their rusting
It's part of the reason you seem more and more botched
Decapitations during this period
Which was a significant problem
And as we know being people
If you have a significant problem we're going to try to invent ways
Two eliminated and that's what the guillotine was
You know the blade that drops down the scaffolding and separates a person
From life to death in the blink of an eye literally
Attempt to cut out
The human equation believe it or not as bad as that looks to us now
It was a step forward in
So the man's progress towards
Becoming more humanitarian
It took away the infamy associated with being touched by the Executioner that would spread to your family in the old days now
You know this was all about a rational penal system
You have to die but it doesn't have to be any more painful
Then this there's no
Infamy attached to with The execution is no longer this
Infamous figure that scares the heck out of people he's just a guy who's a technician
And as much as the guillotine is associated with these
Bloodthirsty crowd they come to watch the execution like it's something special because we're using the guillotine
We should remember in context everything we've been discussing right
These people the guillotine was to be shortchanged
There's no show you can hardly see it it's over in the blink of an eye you can go watch executions of the guillotine
Official
Judicial ones there's one famous one from France I think it was like shot in the 1930s or something
It's in slow motion the entire thing because even then it's
I mean they run the prison right boom boom it happened so fast you can't believe it if you came all day
And tailgated in expectation of that
That's like you know when I used to buy pay-per-view boxing matches
And somebody would walk out and boom it's over with once you know
That's a good way to feel cheated as an audience
At least one of the histories I was reading made
Sound like
People really would have preferred to go back to the more spectacular execution simply for entertainment value alone
Some people
Not all people
And this brings us back around to the third viewpoint
Here I wanted to examine
Things from
Did The Condemned who did the X
Did you sniff how about the audio
The audience is really been the question through
Throughout this entire conversation has ended
How the audience is reacting and
During this period this is when it kind of gets fascinating
The aspect of okay so we human beings like this stuff they've been watching it okay so we're maybe not surprised if we're real cynical
So why did it end
And how did it
Stop
Definition process is there a roadmap there
Or you can say Okay weave
We inoculated our self against that once before and here's how we did it
During this period
When the sensibilities as we said earlier begin to change among some people in some classes
The audience going to be executions begins to in some
Manner of speaking
Look at itself
And not like what it says
Pierce. Bergin his
The spectacle of suffering
Gives a primary source account a dramatized one he points out
From a person who was
Shall we say on The Cutting Edge of these new sensibilities wouldn't even want to see one of these public executions but stumbled into one
Remember the positive gravity
Execution site
Fight in Paris
Quote
We were proceeding toward the plaza graph
It was late and we thought the execution over
But the gaping mob proclaimed the contrary
The man was broken on the wheel as where his two companions
I could not endure the sight of that execution
I moved away
His friend
Watched it all stoically
I turned to look at something else
While the victim suffered
I studied The Spectator
They chattered and laughed as if they were watching a farce
But what revolted me most
What's a very pretty young girl
Lysol with what appeared to be her lover
She uttered peals of laughter
Suggested about the miserable man's expressions and screams
I could not believe it!
I looked at her five or six times
Finally without thinking of the consequences I said to her
Mademoiselle
You must have the heart of a monster
At the judge by what I see of you today I believe you're capable of any tribe
If I Had The Misfortune to be your lover I would shun you forever
As she was no fish wife
He writes she stood mute
! again
I expected some unpleasant retort from her lover
He said not a word
Then a few steps away I saw another young girl drenched in tears
She came to me leaned upon my arm hiding her face and she said
This is an honorable man
Who feels pity for those in anguish
! again
And quote
Those comments also emphasized
Another key thing it was making some in the crowd judge others in the crowd harshly for their way that they were reacting
Women
Women were
Staples at these executions pretty much every source
Suggest from the get-go
Some sources suggest that women and boys traditionally made up the majority of the crowd
It hadn't been a problem before this era but this is the error remember that has certain built-in assumptions amongst Allah
A lot of the inteligencia
About human nature
And one of those assumptions have to do with Womanhood
And how women are naturally
The more compassionate sex is one primary source quote are red it's a basically something like they're scared of spiders
But they can go to these executions and watch intently and enjoy it
So the reality of women that these executions
Was clashing with the inteligencia view of what Womanhood was in their minds in their writings in there was
Assumptions once again
If woman who does really like this ideal compassionate
In a mothering State than what we're seeing when we see women go to these executions are
Twisted people
People with a screw loose in other words they are establishing a new Baseline for normalcy
One that is
Idealistic perhaps at least
For some people in their times and then what they're seeing on the ground
The Ground Zero
Clashes with their ideal
But it is fascinating as a modern person to read some of these letters that are published in the histories
There are upper class women in
France free sample in their letters are in Freeland
As wonderful as I said
And you can see that there is an element of the soap opera
Going on here
Some executions are
Horrible others are wonderful others are beautiful the people are all huge part of the draw I mean you have likes
Celebrity executions imagine simatai
Most famous
People who have tons of cosmetic line the reality show them to getting into trouble and then the public execution where
Their former popularity
Plays into the draw the crowd later I mean if you love this person in this nut film would you love to see them their final
On the scaffold
Freeland actually uses some of these letters as a way to
Try to make his case
That it wasn't
Class that determined whether or not you had feeling for these people who died on the scaffold because a lot of these
Women
Compare Asian high society for example
Went to watch executions of people they knew
Wow
And enjoy them
Prelim relates the story of
Madam
Two cats execution in 1699
He says that Spectators of every class crowded the Streets between
Prison in the execution ground in Paris
He says all the windows overlooking the scaffold have been rented out well in advance
And then he writes about
A letter written by
A woman named Uno her
Talkin about the execution he says quote
Despite having been personally acquainted with Madame to cat
Denoyers account of the execution dwells far-less
I'm whatever emotion she might have experienced at the sight of watching her friend die
Then on the feelings of excitement she felt at watching the spectacle of the execution
At times you know are compares
Two cats
Performance in quotation marks
Did the experience of watching a dramatic production
We're calling receipts blurring of the theatrical in the real in his particular brand of tragic realism
This is
Madame De Niro writing about watching her friend died
Quote
I was in the windows of the hotel-de-ville and I saw poor Madame to cat arrive
Around 5 in the evening
Dressed in white
One would have said that she had studied her role
Because she kissed The Chopping Block
And attended do all the other particulars as if they were simply a matter of performing in a play
In the end
One had never seen such self-possession
Anicura saint-sulpice and then she died a true heroine
The hangman was so moved that he missed her head
And had to repeat his job five times before he managed to behead
Descended the beautiful Madame to cat
Who was the ornament of all Paris
And quote
Again it sounds like a soap opera
And Friedland notes it was only for a brief moment in the letter
That
This woman looked at herself and wondered about her own emotions as a spectator
She writes quote
One never saw anything as beautiful as her head when it has been separated from her body
They left it for a Time on the scaffold so the people could see it
Her face was turned in the direction of the hotel-de-ville and I assure you that I was dazzled by a
In the end I was so touched by her death
But it took me more than 6 months to recover from
I need this with pain that I now recall these thought
And quote
Freeland has another letter
He quotes from
Pie Society
Parisian woman who was talking about
Case of murder case involving a woman at the center of it
Obsessed Paris like
A great gossip story in a 4 months
They followed the trial
And then eventually
The woman has to go up on the scaffold and be
Executed in the Nae throw her body on a fire and burn it up
Sending the ashes up into the small caparison the letter writer says
But you know for months
All of Paris lived and breathed this story of the trial is going on
And now all the Paris was a literally breathing this person in
Everytime they inhale
Now this heading cause any sort of fuss
For a long time by the 1690s you were starting to get the very earliest
In a complaint and Rumblings about women
John Holland seemingly it was it they might enjoy this kind of stuff and they were having the same problem with boys kids
In the ritualistic religious are you could have choirs of kids singing and humming during the
Worst of the executions
Considered to be
A good lesson hold them up on
The shoulder of the father so that they could see better
Take him to the Gallows afterwards let him see what happens to malefactors take him to the gibbet showing the dead bodies rotting inside
The better classes started looking at that and thinking that there was something wrong with that child abuse we would say today
Or at least the stirrings of people who began to think that way
And for anyone who didn't there was beginning to be
Public pressure in the culture on them
And it's interesting that it was only directed at the so-called better
People for example V AC control in his book The Hanging Tree
Talked about Sir Joshua Reynolds
One of these so-called better people
Who in 1790 decided to go to water hanging you know no big deal
It was starting to become important
Which p
And he was
Appalled to find the newspapers criticizing him the next day for going
They basically said that the man he went with
Someone lower on the social strata we would expect those kind of
People to go but not somebody like sir Joshua Reynolds
And Reynolds was kind of confused
Should have caught off guard by the change in sensibilities if you will and so we wrote a letter
To his friend Boswell who we went to the execution with afterwards kind of saying
What's wrong with going do an execution right here here's the defense if you will
For enjoying
The hanging a good hanging hanging well carried out and I should point out that he went to the hanging to watch
Will five people being hanged but one of them was
Aeon servant-girl for somebody he knew
And a servant girl
New him
She recognized him right before the news with put around your neck and bowed to him in front of this giant crowd
She by the way was being hanged for a little theft
Such was the bloody code right
But Reynolds says the whole thing went well what's the problem he wrote to his friend Boswell about the criticism he received
Even the newspapers for going
And said quote
I am convinced it is a vulgar error
The opinion that hanging is so terrible spectacle
Heard it in any way implies a Hardness of Heart or cruelty of disposition
Any more than such a disposition is implied in the seeking Delight
And the representations of a tragedy
Let me stop here he means like a drama or a play
He continued
Such an execution as we saw where there was no torture of the body or expression of Agony of the Mind
Who were the criminals on the contrary
Cured perfectly composed
Without the leaf trembling
Ready to speak in answer with Civility and attention to any question that was proposed
Neither in a state of torpidity or insensibility
A grave and composed
I consider it is natural to desire to see such sights
And if I may venture to take Delight in them
You know that your sister and interest the mine
To give it some emotion
Is moderate exercise is necessary for the body
If the criminals had expressed great Agony of mine The Spectators must infallibly sympathize
But so far was the fact from it
You regard with admiration the serenity of their countenances
And hold apartment
And quote
This is clearly a guy
Who doesn't feel the physical pain of the
Victims that he's watching otherwise he might have approached
The way you described this differently
But 30 Years be
Before this guy right
That
Adam Smith
Author of The Wealth of Nations
Wrote something else
Called the theory of moral sentiments in 1759
Where he basically implied
But it's natural when watching someone burn to death as we've been saying to feel the physical pain of the Vic
Heroes quote
By the imagination we place ourselves
In his the sufferers
Situation
We conceive ourselves enduring all the same torments
We enter as it were into his body
And becoming some measure the same person with him
Infants form some idea of his sensation
And quote
Again these thinkers are implying that this is the way we are
So then what does that make pee
People who aren't that way
Like poor sir Joshua Reynolds
Right
It makes him someone liable to be
Be criticized by the
Cultural
Critics of his day
It also shows a change in the mood and these historians will
Go over letters and comments and editorials and all sorts of things to show that the mood is changing at this change of sensibility
Now we told you like when we were talking about how you
Try to quantify all the different
Friends that play into any zeitgeist
The 1960s for example
Well how much value to place on this change in sensibilities among some classes in some places
And how much weight to put on the fact
That the authorities are not liking some of the main things involved in these executions anymore
Is sort of all
You know what tomato or tomahto thing if you're an expert I mean this is the kind of things they have debates over no one argues that they all Play-Doh
What did you argue over how much of a role
The people out there that are Ground Zero Cenex
Will point out the listen
There was never
A real change in the attendance rates at these executions and unless you want to say that they continually grow
Is Richard Evans points out
The high-water mark for attendance of public executions in Western Europe are right before they're taken behind
You know the jail walls and made private
Showing that there's no drop-off in demand
People who put a great amount of importance on this particular angle
Will point out that people never
Grew out of public executions because of a change in sensibilities they had the public execution in the spectacle taken
Away from them
By the authority
There are lots of reasons the authorities seem to be
Less than satisfied with these public executions the first thing is is that slowly but surely
A consensus was developing that they weren't doing what you wanted to do not just because people weren't terrified
Because they weren't deterring crime
Voltaire and other in a public intellectuals that argued that the
You know death penalty for almost anything or these spectacular ones actually made certain kinds of crimes worse
So the authorities during this big are of penal reform in the 1700 especially were trying to get down to a Bedrock Prince
About what works
The other thing that was happening in the 1700 if you remember your history
Is the always present fear of the mob amongst the European
Autocratic rulers
Exploded
Intensity
Right around the 1790s
That wonderful party known as the French Revolution happened
Which would spread some of these ideas like an intellectual contagion all over Europe
And all of a sudden the most dangerous thing if you are a ruler of one of these countries that you can think of
Is a large crowd of your people together in one place
Especially if a lot of them are perhaps partying
Especially if they're very wound up about something
I mean worst case scenario imagine at the public execution that you are staging to draw all these people into one of your main cities
To watch and get all drunk and excited about
Is somebody who's
Crime was political
Against you the regime
The hundreds of course will be the era of revolution in Western Europe 1848
Crown Jewel year
But all of a sudden the idea of getting a lot of
The masses in one place at one time
I want a sudden sounding very
BAC Cantrell says
That it was the authorities that imposed emotional restraint
On the crowd by taking away their public execution
Cuz it wasn't serving the needs of the state and you have some German sources that talk about the execution itself
I think I'm quoting here but from memory
Brutalizing
The Spectator
So you can't argue that they're enjoying what they're singing
What you're arguing that it's the exposure to these kinds of spectacles that are making you enjoy right to become
Palace used to it
Numb
And there is a ton of
Class animosity in the sources where the dumbasses who go to these executions are portrayed
You know increasingly is lower and lower class more and more brutal
And Jennifer example the Prussian nobility Justice
Completely disconnected from the Richard Evans
They sneer the masses and think of them as bloodthirsty and low in terms of culture
By the middle 1800s
Most of these major states are doing away with public executions changing them in ways to make the crowds
Very small for example they will still execute people publicly in Paris
Till 19th of 1930
What they'll do it in a way that minimizes crowd size
Chinese Publix pek
Vehicles will go from being encouraged and staged
To being discouraged
Deterred
And eventually simply taken away
From the public
The best quick rundown
To describe the process that we did in this whole particular section of this conversation this
Case study if you will from the early modern era
Is
Why not
Richard J Evans rituals of Retribution
Where he says
About
The ending of public executions and he goes down a list of what year they happened in all these different states 1850
I just ate did it 1856 this state did it
And then he says of the ending of the public executions in Germany quote
The predominant immediate motive for this change was official fear of the mob
Public executions attracted huge crowds
Any emotions which they were thought to arouse wenzhou considered dangerously unpredictable
Evans Ben says that what happened was you had this religious ritual
But the state of NC took their religion out of destabilizing the whole thing and basically leaving nothing left
For people to enjoy it
Virtuosity reasons
Or sadistic reasons or fill in the blank reasons he writes quote
Decades of official attempts to secularize the execution ritual remove it from the arena of popular
Culture and Krypto materialist religion and converted into a solemn expression of state power head only
Only succeeded in destabilizing it
The transition from a status bound Society
Tawana growing class antagonism between bourgeoisie and proletariat
And broken asunder the synthesis
Estate in community ritual that had created the early modern public execution
The educated middle-class has now found the crowd Behavior repugnant
While it's deliberate desacralization at the hands of the authorities and gradually stripped it of its mean
Meanings for the common people
The dismantling of Guild Privileges and other aspects of the urban hierarchy
Through the political reforms and social changes of the first half of the 19th century
I destroyed the structured crowd
And replaced it in the eyes of the authorities with a formless volatile Ma
And quote
So this idea that public executions went away because they were no longer serving the interest of the authorities
He's a popular one off and heavily weighted when people
Trying to
Weigh the importance of this or that element playing into the zeitgeist
Modern sensibilities
State not liking executions anymore there's a bunch of other little
In private life I mean
You can find a lot of little variable that
Play wonder why things are unfolding the way they do but what's
Clear and interesting is that it happens very quickly
Control quotes people
Writing in the 1850
Who can't believe
But in the 1830s they were doing what they were doing
I mean that's a
Quick Change
In the wave
Some people
Anyway right which peep
Would be a good question to ask
My history books when I was on high
High School made a kind of sound like
The arrow we just talked about was the
The time where humankind in the better parts
The world grew up
In a moral
Became more Humane threw off the shackles
Leftover medieval ism
And into the Modern Age when it comes to moral sensibilities write the Modern Age where you could come up with
Human rights in Concepts like
War crimes and all these sorts
The things
And I actually think there's a pretty strong case for that
If we're talking about humankind
Collectively
All of us together
What if we're just talking instead of humankind my food just talking about human
Then you might have
Say
Well that differs on a case-to-case basis
I mean most of our societies no longer impose
The sort of cruel and unusual public
Punishment on criminals
But that doesn't mean their people wouldn't turn out to see it
I mean many societies have examples
Let's call it extrajudicial justice that have happened since the early modern era that Drew huge crowds
When in the United States to take for example
Lynching
Lynching is annex
Extrajudicial
Something carried out often
And by a mob or by vigilantes
In the United States
A lot of black
American males have been the victim of lynchings between 1890 and 1929 330 I think the
Cut off was
More than 3000 estimated
Black males lynched
And racism obviously a huge part of The Americans
Experience including
Trying to keep people down
After reconstruction and the Jim Crow laws
All that was going
And yet
The United States of America has our citizens turned out for lynching involving white folks to
And there are photos of them at lynchings of black folks
Smiling next to tortured
A charred corpses of The Condemned
The victims would be a better word
And there are also photos of them smiling next
Do the hanging
In some cases partially stripped
Corpses
Of the white criminals taken out of jail
And strung up illegal
In other words
If we're doing it
Experiment on whether or not
People
Would still come out to a public execution if they were ever brought back
In the
20th century
The datapoint suggest
But the answer would be yes in fact United States didn't even stop public executions until the middle 1930s and I believe 20,000 peep
People showed up for the last one
The difference though it was a kind of what would you say simple hanging out
Take offense at that statement
But at least it was
The punishment prescribed by the enlightened of 20th century Society
Of the time
One of the really
Interesting comparison points when were talking about the lynchings in the United States is
You are not constrained by
The law that said you can't have cruel and unusual punishment you off and we're going for cruel and unusual punishments in the air
Actual accounts of diesel engines are terrifyingly horrible
You think blowtorches is that enough for you
Many of them were done in private by small groups of people
And that's part of the history of the ACT but that doesn't really concern us here for what we're talking about the ones that are interesting is sort of day
Data points if you will
Are the ones that
Drew huge crowds
Because you can write off small groups of people
Twisted
Malcontent
Unusual outliers
A lot harder when the sampling
Is of an entire town
Like Waco Texas
In 1916 and I don't mean to single out Waco it's just the most famous
Case
Those of you
Know your history of lynching
No I'm going to speak for a minute about the Jesse Washington case
And Washington's a good example because I had people come up to me and try to
Downplay
Play the stuff and one of the arguments they'll often uses yeah well of course I'm innocent people
We're Lynch but most of these people did bad things as though that would somehow be okay
Remember if Jesse Washington had faced legal justice
For the crimes he supposed to have committed he would have been hanged
A simple hanging right
But he wasn't
Historian Amy Louise wood describes the Jesse Washington situation this way
Quote
The 1916 lynching of Jesse Washington in Waco Texas
Stan's is one of the most widely known and scrutinized lynching
Because it in many ways
Typified the grotesque excess of spectacle lynching
Just over two months after The Birth of a Nation played in Waco
An estimated 10000 people watched
As a mob mutilated
Strangled and burned Washington to death
On the grounds of the city hall
The mayor she writes
And the chief of police
Watched from a window above
And quote
Washington she writes was a 17 year old African American
He was charged with
Killing a woman and maybe raping the woman
The jury deliberated for 4 minutes
Before convicting him
But Justice
As I said which would have been a simple hanging never had a chance to
In a run its course because as woodwright
Quote
Just moments after the jury which has deliberated for only 4 minutes
Reddit's guilty verdict
The crowd in the courtroom surged forward and seized Washington
Local businesses promptly close their doors
Spectators men women and children
Swarmed the city center
Climbing trees and standing on rooftop to get a better View
Local photographer Fred Gildersleeve who have been notified that Washington would be lynched
Capture the events on film from a window in City Hall
Afterwards his images were sold on the streets of the city
Along with body parts
And other Grizzly Remnant from the day's events
And quote
Folks this is not really modern
France which is shocking enough
This is 20th century
In the Main Street America
And if you go look at the photos
Which were taken of this lynching in progress
You can see why they turned out to be so
Galvanizing in the anti-lynching movement
Because you look at it and you are
Staring into a time machine
They're dressed differently
But that's a photograph
That gives you a pretty good idea
What these early modern executions must have look like two
The scenery changes the costumes evolve
But those people wearing those clothes
That's the same species as it always was
We are the lab rats
Experiment
Which wonder is about how we react
To this
And by the way the things that they did to Washington as
What's the case in a bunch of these lynchings
Are every bit as nasty as the stuff that went on
In those executions in early modern Europe we talk
Bottoming chopping off fingers
Burning people Jesse Washington was raised and lowered over fire for at least an hour or some sources say two
He tried to climb up the chain that was suspending him over the fire
But apparently was unable to because he lacked fingers which has been chopped off along with his genitals
This Is Not Unusual
Crowd of people watch this
Participated in it
Enjoyed it
Send postcards to other people later one is famous and says something to the effect
Quoting from memory here
You missed the BBQ
Q
We missed
Good Barbie
This is cruelty
Mask
Plain and simple
My dictionary de
Callous indifference to or pleasure in causing pain and suffering
Clearly.
And it's not a few outliers
People with Twisted evil minds
It's a wide cross-section of an early 20th century American city
It's tempting to label something like the Jesse Washington lynching as
Involving inhuman cruelty
But it looks all too human
After you
Leaf through
If you chapter 7
Your history book
Probably safe to say that this
His cruelty element is
Is a universal part of The Human Experience
Uncomfortable questions start coming into
Play
If you ask
Why
For now by the way and I think I have that
There is no agreement
Over this way
My issue
Why people are violent why they would enjoy watching violence
There are theories there are ideas
There are debates
There are studies at
Crosses many disciplines
I think storytellers have always understood
Unconsciously
But there are these buttons they can push
That
Trigger emotional responses in us that may be chemically related maybe they know how to push the dopamine or serotonin button
Every three pages of your script to make sure you get whatever
You need
To keep reading the story and be interested maybe it's a gunfight
Maybe it's a little sexual activity
Maybe it's some sort of Twisted
In a scene that makes you laugh
Or freaked out
But somebody knows that that's a button that will work for you why does it work
Do you want over the eras of
In evolutionary adaptations built on evolutionary adaptations
Is that
Flying into Isabel don't like playing into a jungle cats inability to not follow something
It looks like it's running away from it I mean is there something deep in our souls
It was once upon a time very useful
That's just left over like an appendix
We don't need this cruelty or this desire to see cruelty anymore
So what you still doing there do we need to get rid of it because
You know we haven't needed it in a long time and it causes a whole lot of side effects as we all know
Tncompass
Question that always the Wonder
If that's not the case if we still need it somehow
If it's a standard part of Who We Are
And along with all the obvious negative signs to it has some positive benefits I like to
Sometimes uses an analogy and you knew I was
Going to go here
Star Trek app
Captain Kirk
Explaining to the
The two halves of his personality I guess you could say
Politically call them
The positive and negative half a good the bad half
The one with the most celebrated positive human qualities in the one
Another sort of shows us that are most
Will seven deadly sins oriented best maybe you could
Throughout most of the episode
You know there's a good in the bad one of the bad ones doing all these bad things and getting into trouble that Goodwin is worried about
The moral of the story is there comes a point where
You're hardcore decisions that affect life and death and all these kinds of things comes into play
And the half that doesn't have the negative qualities is ill-equipped
There's something about those negative qualities that help
Round this person out
So that they have what they need in different situations most of the time maybe you don't need that cruelty Jean
To come into play
But maybe sometimes you do
That's a weird thing to think about
Right and maybe let's suggest
It has to do with
Chances what if it's like fire
And if you don't have it at all you freeze to death but
Maybe in a place like ancient Rome were there watching people die in the arena let's remember
The Romans
Is Will Durant pointed out with
Argue that the arena was good for their people
In their day right
Made you less of Shia blood made you a better Soldier made you tougher to watch this kind of stuff or so they thought
And maybe for their own time that's the level of Cruelty that those people needed to thrive maybe we don't need that level of cruel
How much less
Cruel Society
Then the neck
Next uncomfortable question that arises from that one is so how much cruelty do we need
Perhaps the follow-up uncomfortable question after that is even if you decide how much cruelty you need
What is X Change
Of course all implies that you can control cruelty like a
Temperature gauge
It is strange to think of
And we've been talkin bout a revolution sensibilities the idea that you could have a counter-revolution in sensibilities
People can become
Potentially more brutal depending on how you measure it more cruel than their parents or grandparents
Understand
Our parents and grandparents maybe the high-water mark of
Empathetic
Human development I mean
It's pretty recent
It's impossible to imagine today though
Play Jesse Washington type lynching happening in a small American city
In 21st century America in front of all those people can't even imagine it's a we call that progress right
Might we ever slide back in the other direction I mean I can't imagine
You never see something like that again
But maybe you could say that in 20 years do the whole bunch of different modern influences
If you took a pinion Polo 20% more of the survey people would say that what was done to the victim
Was correct
See what I'm saying that would be back
Sliding wooden it
And yet there's this weird dichotomy
Between what
I guess without study or thinking about it what one would think should be happening to society now
Versus what you see
Because what you see is a very empathetic Society some have suggested that the pendulum has even swung too far in that
Empathetic
Too weepy
Bright overly so may
Which then of course begs the question you know just
The pendulum swing backwards
The fire naturally
Note to self correct to the right amount of heat for the tenor of the times
Maybe something
Like a 911 happens and all of a sudden you need to change the cruelty level on the thermostat to allow for more
Darkside Captain Kirk activities necessary
You dial it back too often though into shorter. Of time you might find the room uncomfortably cold
The weird dichotomy
Is that in this era this Uber sensitive Uber empathetic error
We have more influences on us
That theoretically should have worked us
According to the experts that when I was a kid were telling me
That the number of simulated murders that I have seen on television is my brain was developing
You know something in the 14000 whatever they used to throw the number of the average American Child by the time they're fourteen years old is she and 14th
Does Rachel whatever it was the slogan
The implication was
And I don't blame him this was all pretty new stuff you got a 1960's television
Those hardly even counted murders by 1970 standards and those hardly counted murders by
Our standards today in terms of how came they are
Nonetheless there was ample worrying
But the accumulated effect of all this simulated violence would do something nasty to my generation when we got older and we're old
Weather now
What happened
The problem of course we all faced as we are immersed in the modern Zeitgeist we can't tell
If we've been warped
You got to bring somebody back from another era and instantly say hey notice anything weird about us
Weird funny to you
Bring back Captain America I love this about the Captain America character by the way he's a 1940's ERA American instantly transfer
Folded into the now
And you get to see his reactions to all the changes
But he didn't get to go through slowly like
The rest of society did
Pay 1940s American
Do we look warped
Do you
But
Tumi living in the milieu as I am
I don't see that we have been
Terribly affected in a nasty way
And if you would gone to the people the 1970s and show them the kind of violence we would see simulated today
Hey the realism level of it
I can't imagine what they would have said I mean the movies that you can go see the day and lots of the R-rated ones meet this crime
Criteria we've been rated X when I was a kid
X by the way traditionally what you labeled hardcore pornography
And kids Once Upon a Time
By the scale of today
It was a lot more tightly controlled in places like the United States
So they have your non-pornographic movie
Labeled X for violence with a huge deal right you basically wouldn't be making your movie we got lots of movie
Movies like that now
Again
So what
Society seems to be standing and the problem in trying to figure out if you can see long-term damage
Do do I see more and more simulated violence but more more real
Is the Zeitgeist thing again
How do you differentiate
In all the strands of reality and try to quantify that we have more school shootings with youngsters than we used to maybe it's violent video game
How would you know
$15,000 variables acting on those kids as well
But Society still standing right
When you think about what we were exposed to it a little bit shocking
Take for example this is what occurred to me
How many people have seen the images of the terrorists who are
Is slitting the throats with the knives of the people in the orange jumpsuits at their feet was on like every magazine cover at one point
The videos are all over the internet been viewed a bazillion times
That's more graphic than anything 99% of the population of the western world would have seen when
When I was a kid
The kind of stuff you'd only see if you were in combat
Or a first responder or a journalist or somebody who looked at autopsy photos I mean that's
That would have shocked America in 1974
Now
How many things like that have we seen
Does it do anything to us at all if you watch a hundred real chilling forget about the simulated stuff they were worried about
Black kids watching the 1970s
If you watched a hundred real killings online in a 24 hour period Does he do anyting
Here's the funny part
If it does something
I find that really interesting if it doesn't do anything I find a Justice interesting
Experiment right
Of course it would be if we had kept
The variables the same I mean if you'd shown
American children 1970s level television violence for a hundred years and then looked at the results
But it would be one thing but we haven't done that obviously
Deepened and intensified
The experience a lot since I was a
The kid
We just mentioned the
More realistic fake violence there is the real violence now online to contend with
The assassination and execution videos all that stuff you could see
But there's a
Temperature
Element now that wasn't involved back in the day
Yeah I just asking how watching the stuff affects people
Now you can ask how participating in it does in a virtual sense right
The first person shooter games come to mind but there's a lots of things out there
But do similar sorts of things in terms of immersing you in a fantasy world
And allowing you to behave in ways you would never behave
In the real world
And I don't think there's anything wrong with that
I know what these people think time should remain static and how would you have prevented this this is the experiment
People are affected by this
And so far I'd say
You know we're doing pretty well but it's such a short term Horizon I mean what's the
Computer error been like 20 years since that really took off
Thirty years I mean this is short-term Horizon stuff
Call me in a hundred years right
When we will have the ability to put you
Into any of these situations
We talked about that are really extreme
In an almost real sent to me how long until that's the case
Again
I don't see anything wrong with that either
And this is an extension of Storytelling
And its existence of the very beginning of Storytelling which was oral a long time before anybody ever wrote anything down
Pushing the same buttons in a more intense and realistic way
It is always been pushed
All you storytellers out there understand the pain raises the emotional stakes in the story
Human beings right
Whether we talked about emotional physical or even the kind of pain
That is The Fountainhead of Comedy
The great poker game of life is
Played with chip
The human pain and misery
And it is interest
Peking compelling
Tencent very dramatic
To watch somebody playing a high-stakes game even if you're not sitting in on it
Isn't that
Reading about
Dramatic character
Wild situations Reven historical figures
In the past I mean we're watching them play
Their poker game of life
And risking their chips
Pain
And you can't look away can you
And I don't think there's anything wrong with that either unless you find yourself
You know continually routing
For that person to lose
Just like I don't think there's anything wrong
With finding something like the Jesse Washington lynching situation from a hundred years ago fascinating and reading
Snap-on all you can on it
I really think he gets weird
If you say something like wow this is so interesting I really love
To see one of those
Could a revolution in sensibilities
Truly back
Track
That much
Another thought occurs to me
And that's what we talked about a long time ago on this day
Discussion that you know there's never been any blind taste test on this
In terms of making these statements about
What might happen Generations from now
It is slow poison of portrayed or real violence
Seeps into the body politic over several Generations in thaxted
Maybe we're already we're we're worried we might get to
If you say if we're not careful Generations from now they want to watch
Public executions who says we wouldn't now
I we mentioned earlier one of the theories on this whole thing is that
They never went out of fashion these public execution that this was a free market capitalistic content-related decision
And the audience got to decide
It never would have gone away maybe
Bounce that we were going to have the first
Public execution in the United
State since the 1930s
Put it in the sun
Centralized
Bigspot
Some scaffold in the middle of Las Vegas
Right near all the hotel
Do you think you'd be able to get a ringside seat
Can you be able to rent one of those rooms with a picture window of you down on the scaffold and one of the nearby hotels
I wonder
And
You know I think that there's a breakdown
Age that would have
I've been where you tap this first execution it be this groundbreaking event and everybody would be appalled and just
Outrage in there be a lot of public shaming you be sir Joshua Reynolds all over again in the media would be there but of course only to cover
You know the human depravity of the people that showed up to watch this acting are there any famous ones
What happens
With the next one in a war on public execution number three since the government reinstated public X
Vacations
I bet by then things start to
Melo
And once the public pressure relaxes cuz these things are much more common I bet the entire
Media
Approach shifts and we're not
Looking at
The crowd any longer in
Shaming them to the rest of the country we are in fact playing to that crowd
And I doing some man on the street interviews
You so did you know the person who's being broken on the wheel today here in Vegas
I realize that example sounds more like a dystopian
Movie script than it does any sort of reality but then I have to keep reminding myself listen
We can get
Hundreds of people in the world like 500 people died
It showed up to Ted Bundy's
Execution when he was put in the electric chair
Hundreds of people will show up to these things
When they're happening behind Prison Walls
Any can't see anything
Imagine how many more would show up if they could if the
Person conducting the execution said this guy is so bad that just has one time
We're going to move the execution back out in public
Can you imagine in the modern era how quickly that would spread on social media
Do you think you can get that 500 people that were there
To see an execution that they couldn't see
You think that would
Suelto something keeps could you beat the 20000 people that showed up
To the last public execution in the United States
And if you could
What does that tell you in terms of Trends right we could still pack of moon just as well as we could have in the 1930
What's it going to be an interesting human experiment
I tend to think and again my
Opinion on this
Just simply personal
I tend to think that
Maybe some of us are hardwired definitively one way or the other right give me my
Eye pain and suffering fictionalized cuz that's how I take it best
And other people that they know I want to see it real here I wanted to be real when I read my history books and no
But yes this historical figure suffered this way or I wanted Reno like I want to see it live I think there are people who are hardwired
One way the other than that I think there's a lot of us there probably
You know could go either way
Much more likely to be influenced by the culture we grow up in the times and what not I mean
You might not be hardwired to like watching animals chew people up in the arena but hey if everybody's going anyway
And I like the food there it's kind of fun and I have fun life I mean I think there's a lot of people that you know go along with
The crowd
So whereas we
In this particular era are going along with the crowd by being naturally empathetic
If the crowd changed or the times changed
I think it's a lot of people in the mushy middle that could go either way
And people that would never be caught dead in a live public execution today how gauche
Might change their minds if you know
You got trendy again
Leica
Bell Bottom Jeans
Do you want a good stuff that was left on The Cutting Room floor
Floor
Can we put that
Show together
Is amazing
Because there's just so much stuff that when you're reading it
Your eyes just get
WYD
About the topic
It's a wacky weird
Crazy topic
Getting it
If you were one of those people that I'm sure are out there
Who wanted to hear more from the
Executioners Viewpoint we mention
Called
The faithful X
Did you hear about Joel Harrington
That was one of the things that prompted me to even
Do this subject
Is a topic in that book is available if
From Audible
And you'll get it
As an audio
The podcast live
I don't have to
To tell you
The value in being able to
Consume your
Entertainment
Educational material
Information
In a form that allows you to still use
Your hands
Eyes
The tasks
Automotive in a long time
Traditionally offer a free audiobook with a 30-day trial membership
Membership includes a lot of things including a free audiobook
Book a month
30%
Off all regularly priced audiobooks
They have an unmatched
Selection of
Topics and genres
Choices
I mean if you have the faithful executioner
Well you're kind of reaching into the abyss
Your topics a little bit aren't you
Thereon
Able to
One of the things I really like about it is
Did it works across a wide variety of devices
And picks up where you left off so you can go from like your tablet to your car to you
Your phone to your Echo and all these things will pick up the
And if you're in mid-sentence boom Unity
Keep on listening
Very cool and they have
Free apps for your iPhone or iPad or Android or Windows phone
You can listen
On an iOS device in Android
Fire tablet Windows phones
You own your books this isn't a streaming thing and he
You cancel your membership you still on
And you get something called the Great listen guarantee if you didn't like the audiobook you bought
You can swap
There's a lot of other great features we've been talkin about Audible for years
And if I said
Yeah they've been supporting a shelf for a long
Time and I like them because I love
Selling book
If you go to audible.com hardcore history
Or
Text Hardcore History all one word
2500 - 500 you can get started today
A Bunker show is all we ask
Please go to dancarlin.com for information on how to donate to the show
Be sure to follow us on Twitter the address
Is at hardcore history
For years we've been trying to figure out a way to give more hardcore history audio to the Hardcore History audience that would be you
You folks and it has been
Difficult
We have found out through brutal experience you do not want anything but what you think you're expecting on the regular feed
And so the only answer we finally came up with was to have
Another fee
Another Hardcore History podcast
Toyota this one exists only so we don't screw up the one you like already so
The standard Hardcore History feed this one will give you the so-called Epic shows when we can get them to you which is
6 month sometimes now we just too long to be out of touch
The other feed
A chance to stay in touch in between long
A chance to deal with
Things that you folks don't want in place of your epic stuff so we're providing it in addition to that
Interviews answered questions
Interesting angle shorter bitumen for example we have two things in the can as they say
At the time of this recording loan is an interview with Mike Duncan famous History podcast
Expert on Rome
And author of the new book The Storm before the storm will talk about
The storm before the storm the earthquake that shook the Roman Republic
The foundations that eventually led to the Julius Caesar guy we all know about
Do you like Rome
We talkin about it in one of the show's already up on the new
Feed
The other is me answering all at once a question I've answered from any of you individually for a long time
Based on something I said once people want to know
Weather I think the first of the second world war German military was the superior of the two
Well that's the very first show
On our feet
Call Hardcore History addendum you can get it on our website and get it on iTunes subscribe to it hope you like it
And it should keep us
You know in touch more often than once every five or six months