What you're about to hear is part 5
The multi-part series on the first World War
If you haven't caught the earlier episodes and you want to know what's going on it might be worth your time to go back in this
Listen to them
You've already heard them or you don't care about
I got them please
Join us for
Part 5
Blueprint for Armageddon
December 7th
A date which will live
In infamy
Leo events
Call nist time and place I take pride in the words ich bin ein Berliner
Instagram
This kind of examination because people have got to know whether or not their president question
If we dig deep in our history and our document and remember that we are not descended from fearful men
It's hardcore history
Earlier in the story
We brought up the often
Quoted phrase
Is that one man's terrorist
Is another man's freedom
We brought it up in relation to the man actually
Launched
The incident.
Spark the first World War
Serbian nationalist gavrilo princip
Killed
The heir to the austro-hungarian throne the Archduke Franz Ferdinand
Thereby precipitating the crisis
That actually started the war
The austro-hungarian saw print ship
Unequivocally
The terrorist
Is Serbian nationalist
Brethren
Revered him
In fact not that long ago a statue was unveiled in Sarajevo where the assassination happened
Honoring
The Assassin
So you review
Of the
Motives of these
People really depends on
Who's doing the viewing at the time
Friendship is far from the only figure in the story
Who falls into a similar category
The United States is dealing with one themselves
Elves
In 19
For example in January 1916 just has the German military is putting the finishing touches
On what will become
The quintessentially horrible Battle of Verdun the quintessentially 20th century style battle
The killing field created by Mac
Artillery the meat grinder
It will be for done
The United States is attention is taken off European Affairs by events going on in Northern Mexico
Mexico has been
Convulsed by Revolution since1910
Northern Mexico often becomes one of these
Hotbeds of unrest and instability
And in January 1916 gunmen waylay
A train
In northern Mexico
Now
This is at the
Tail end of the era where train robberies are not uncommon but these gunmen aren't there to rob the train in fact if they go up
Up and down the aisles
They leave
The Mexican national the locals alone
But they pull off
Every American from the train that they fine
They find 16 to 18
Workers
Employees of a US Corporation operating in northern Mexico
They take these Americans off the train line them up
In front of the track
Forced them to strip
And then execute
We know this because one of The Americans
Feigned death and got away and told his story
I believe he said that the bodies were also mutilate
This very well may have been
An attempt to provoke a response on the part of the US government and if so the mutilation is just part of adding fuel to
To the fire
A little something to make the US government even angrier
At this event
And things have been escalating to this point in northern Mexico for sometime groups affiliated with the same gunman had been
Hacking isolated Americans and murder here and murder their rape here were there but this was
Upping the ante significantly
None the less
The maneuver accomplished
Nothing
Concrete
Note
So a couple of months later
In March
This group of
Gunman or Outlaws or revolutionaries
If you're looking at it from another point of view
Up the ante again
Across
The US map
Mexican border
In strength
More than a hundred
Go after
American interest on the US side of the Border
Culminating in net in an attack on a US city
Columbus New Mexico
In the middle of the night
They Roar through this town
Shooting looting killing and burning
18 Americans will be
Kill the town will be burned down
And the
Bandits
Or
Terrorist
Or revolutionary depending on your point of view
Will escape back into Mexico
Now is a side note then as now Americans are heavily armed people
And those Bandits paid a high price
Forearm what they did to that town many more of them died
Then Americans died
None the less the idea that you were safe and protected
Within the confines of the US borders with shatter
In a way that hadn't happened
Since the Apache Wars in that region attended 30 years previous
The attackers of Columbus New Mex
Chicago were affiliated
With a Mexican revolutionary leader
Known to history not his
Actual name is Pancho Villa
Navia almost certainly wasn't in Columbus New Mexico he'd been hurt not that long before
But these gunmen
We're part of
In his man
And if you look at this superficially
There's a lot of similarity
Between Pancho Villa
And Osama bin Laden
This is not said to insult
Mexican folks who still in some cases Revere
Pancho Villa's memory but it's hard to avoid that at least from the American side of things
There are rough
Analogies that you can
No point to free sample
Like bin Laden
Via had Once Upon a Time been a friend to the United
Someone we thought we could work with
The news
An armed and trained in hell
In fact
After
Bat attack in Columbus New Mexico when it was obvious the
Some response had to be put together
President Woodrow Wilson
American leader
Launches an expedition
A military Expedition into northern Mexico
Since about five thousand men
Across the border
There was a a an official leader but he wasn't the guy who actually LED things on the ground that I know that things on the ground
Was an American General named
John Pershing
Whose nickname by the way was blackjack
And a year before to show you how close
The United States have been DaVita at one time the year before
Pershing launches this expedition to go capture this terrorist Pancho Villa
He loses his whole family
Terrible house
Parson's wife
His little girls they were
Little children
Died in the fire
And
As he was
Wallowing in
Almost Soul crushing grief
Amongst the condolence letters he received
Was one from this
Pancho Villa
Person
That he would be chasing
About a year later
There are a lot of interesting things
That this Expedition
Cross the border
Shows not just
Mexicans
Not just Americans
But European observers everywhere who all throughout this war
I wondered
What do United States is going to do
And what their capabilities are
All of a sudden they have a US military force in the field to have a look at and measure up against the standards of
Early 20th century War
Be honest
American Endeavor look
Looks like a disaster
It doesn't look a whole lot different
Then efforts 30 years ago to the year
That were launched
To go after the last Apache leader to
You break off the US reservation system with 40 Warriors
I'm going to some of the same country that via and his men were hiding in
Looks like a very similar Army just add some motor cars which is what the US
Military
Was employing to give them some Mobility
And some airplanes that look like they were invented by the Wright brothers themselves in fact
The pilots were trained in some cases by Orville and Wilbur Wright that's how recent
You know airplane development is and the US planes are so rickety
And so new and none of them survive
The first week or two
Of operation down
One of the more interesting
Aspects to the US operations in northern Mexico to go get Pancho via is the US doesn't know Northern Mexico in there
Maps are all wrong
And so they have leading their army as Scouts
Apache
Chinese Apache
Include allegedly some
Apache Scouts who were amongst the Apache Scouts
The hunted down Geronimo 30 years before
In fact there's quite a connection to a lot of these people involved in this conflict
John General John Blackjack Pershing
Was a junior officer
Trailing Geronimo
30 years
Before these event
It's believed the Pancho via wanted to
Get the US to attack northern Mexico and bog them down in this insane
Saying country to fight
Insane Terrain insane weather conditions
And thereby raise his standing among several revolutionary leaders
Vying for control
Of the instability in Mexico that have been going on since the 1910 Revolution
Began
But if Europeans already had a stereo
Typical View
Of the United States is a nation of cowboys and an army mired in an almost old west
Sort of approach
The Expedition into northern Mexico to capture Pancho Villa
Did nothing
To disabuse them
Of that stereotype
Too many European Observers
It wasn't just a frontier Army
The United States of America look like they possess
It's kind of a frontier mentality to go along with it
One of the things that was really hard for European planners has been
On both sides of the war by the way
Is it a beginning to look more and more like the United States are going to play this huge role in the war
What did that even mean
Can I say to never sent over lots of men to go fight in some European War
It was alien to the American Experience or what they actually do that
There were a lot of European Observer that thought that even if us got into the war they wouldn't send troops
Americans don't do that
And that's
Part of what makes that pre first world war United States of America
Hard for modern Americans to understand
If you know your grandpa
If you're lucky enough to Adventure Grandpa
Explain
You begin to get a real feel
Bring what they're about even if they're very different than you are
But they're real
You can relate to
United States of 1916 is like a great great great great
You can read all about it you want those people are different from you and you don't understand and you never knew
You never knew anyone like
The modern United States
Of America is the most
Interventionist great power in the world
In 1916
It was the office
And it had a long mythology connected to its very founding
It reinforced the idea
But that's the way American forum
Policy should be
Before the United States could involve itself in the first World War
It had to somehow deal with this lasting Legacy
Dating all the way back to
Pre-revolutionary days but why don't you just start with the
Farewell speech of the first American President George Washington
The speech that was really read aloud
Once a year
Patriotic fervor
Beach the told Americans
To stay out of Europe's Wars
In the middle of his
Goodbye speech to the American people in his resigning from public life he said quote
The Great rule of conduct for us
In regard to foreign Nations is in extending our commercial relations
To have with them as little political connection as possum
So far as we've already formed engagements
Let them be fulfilled with perfect good faith
Here
Let us stop
Europe has a set of primary interests
Which to us have none or very remote relation
Hence
She must be engaged in frequent controversies
The causes of which are essentially foreign to our concerns
Hence therefore it must be unwise enough to implicate ourselves by artificial ties in the ordinary
Vicissitudes of her politics were the ordinary combinations in collisions of her friendship
Or enmity
Our detached and distant situation invites
And enables us to pursue a different course
If we remain one people under an efficient government
The. Is not far off when we made the five material injury from external annoying
When we met take such an attitude and will cause the neutrality we met at anytime resolved upon to be
Scrupulously respected
When belligerent Nations under the impossibility of making Acquisitions upon us
Will not likely Hazard the giving us provocation
Which we may choose peace or War Hazard interest
Guided by Justice shall Council
Why forego the advantages of so peculiar situation
Why quit our own to stand upon foreign ground
Why by interweaving our destiny with that of any part of Europe
Entangle our peace
And prosperity in the toils of European ambition
Rivalship interest
Humor
Caprice
Is our true policy to steer clear of permanent alliances
With any portion of the foreign world
And quote
When Americans review those people like demigod
And that's peaches reread to America's schoolchildren and reread publicly once a year on the anniversary
You can see
But if you were an American who thought the United States should enter the first World War
You have a lot of Mythology to overcome
A lot of ingrained ideological training
And lest you think that those are revolutionary sentiments from the beginning of a Nation a lot of times people are very
Emotional and sentimental in Loft
Idealistic when a nation is founded
Cools over time
45 years after Washington gave that speech the current president of the United States
A second-generation guy like a
George W bush kind of
John Quincy Adams
Give another one of these
Chinese foreign policy
Coining a famous phrase that Americans would use every since you're going abroad in search of monsters to slay
The very
Antithesis of the idea that the United States government is going to use
As the slogan
To get the United States into the first world war John Quincy Adams in the middle of Warren his speech just dealing with
What the country's foreign policy should be 45 years after Washington
Gave his speech said quote
Speaking about the United States here in the feminine pronoun
White quote
Wherever the standard of freedom and Independence has been or shall be unfurled
There will her heart her benedictions and her prayers be
But she goes not abroad in search of monsters to destroy
She is the well-wisher to the freedom and Independence of all
She's the champion and Vindicator only of her own
She will recommend the general cause
By the countenance of her voice
And the benignant sympathy of her example
She well knows that by once enlisting under other banners than her own where they even the banners of 4 in in
Independence
She would involve herself
Beyond the power of extrication in all the wars of interest and intrigue
Have individual avarice Envy and ambition
Which assumed the colors
Can you strip the standard of freedom
The fundamental maxims of her policy would insensibly change from Liberty
Divorce
The front light upon her brows with no longer being with the ineffable Splendora freedom and Independence
But in its stead would soon be substituted and Imperial diadem
Flashing in false and tarnish luster the murky Radiance of dominion and Power
She might become the dictatress of the world
She would be no longer the ruler of her own spirit
And quote
This kind of
Historical Legacy of idealism this mythology if you will that Americans
You know had reinforced all the time provided a natural counterweight
4patriots
To choose a side that seem to be
Do opposite of what patriotism normally
Implied anura patriotism
Was a key part of nationalism it's the and grabbing of the flag sometimes and pushing your Nations glory and and and
And borders farther
That was true in the United States to
Everybody's human the same sorts of
In a rallying cries off and work on Americans that work on other people
But you also had this refuge for people who were patriotic and who could take an anti-interventionist position
And couch it as much in the flag as those were suggesting the real Patriot
You know joined up and fought the Spanish in Cuba for example
As Theodore Roosevelt
The former president of the United States and and
Volunteer for that Spanish
American War
You know kept taking the opposite viewpoint
Going to the United States of America lived in a different time than those founding fathers
And it real patriotism in real man
Would be ready to join the first world war in the United States is
I'm looking like a
Powered by not being involved
The Theodore Roosevelt is not the president in 1916
But he's needling the guy who is
A guy from the other party a Democrat named Woodrow Wilson
One of the most
Enigmatic and hard to get your mind around figures
In the story
And part of the reason that Wilson is so hard
To figure out is because the historians don't agree
The majority of historians have always taken Wilson sort of at face value
And portray him as
One of the most if not the most idealistic president in American history
A guy who is so peace-loving he's virtually gone DS
And a man who did everything he could
To keep the United States out of War
And the fight for this
Wonderful just fair peace after
That's the
Sort of the Goodwill Goodwill send in the evil Woodrow
Wilson Insurance
Have some historians see them
The other historical campus smaller but very vociferous very loud and growing
And those are the people who for a lot of domestic reasons it should be pointed I don't like Woodrow Wilson at all
And often
You know escribe Sinister or Vino motives for him doing what he was doing
And the Sea man
Who wanted to get involved with the allies
Who sought peace for his own vainglorious reasons
Who was
A
Schemer and a person who hid behind a mask that promised
You know idealism in peace and they were German generals for example
Or never
Falling for that story that Wilson was some Bambi deer in the Headlights
On the world stage and always thought that was just a really good mask
It is Machiavellian scheming hid behind making him even more.
His disguise was better
Unless I'm not going to wait as a fan of History into which Wilson I believe with the real Wilson but look at how it adds to the
Uncertainty of the whole thing
What is the sky all about
Now I personally think that the air of mystery that surrounds Woodrow Wilson
Make some more interesting character and he's a giant
Enigma that's quickly becoming perhaps the most important single individual
In the story by the end of 1916
But you know I didn't have to live with them
The people in this tale he's not a character he's a world leader
And what the United States does in this war might decide to conflict
So the stakes couldn't be higher
Winston Churchill
Writing after the first World War
She's got a very interesting view on Wilson it's hard to describe you can see he's he's walking on eggshells sometime
But he says this guy we didn't know anything about it when he comes out of Academia basically
Age is only in the American system
Do you get these people that can come from totally outside
Politics
A complete unknown Eagles in Britain
Such a prime minister would have spent years in the in the House of Commons or what-have-you you know working their way up there would be in the pub
Buckeye the whole time they would be an unknown quantity by the time they got the top job
He Marvels at the fact that Woodrow Wilson is an unknown
You know the most powerful man
In the United States
And quickly becoming the most important single figure
In the war Churchill writes about Wilson quote
In all his strength
And in all his weakness in his nobility and in his foibles he was
In spite of his long academic record in brief governorship
An unknown
And I'm measured quantity to the mighty people who made him their ruler in 1912
Still more was he a mystery To The World At Large
Writing with every sense of respect
It seems no exaggeration to pronounce
The action of the United States
With its repercussions on the history of the world
Depended during the awful. Of Armageddon upon the workings of this man's mind and spirit
To the exclusion of almost every other Factor
And then he played a part in the fate of nations in comparably more direct and personal than any other man
And quote
That's why we're talking about
The United States so much in this afternoon
And if one of the other
Parts of the Wilson story that are interesting is when you get
Human beings in positions of great power and authority
Often times their little quirks
Or idiosyncrasies
Or characteristics
Can make-or-break history
I mean we all have little
Things about us that might be quirky or idiosyncratic
Because we're not in positions of power and authority they don't really make much of a difference if
If I don't Hitler leave the military after the first World War II decorated Corp
And goes and opens up a sausage shop in Munich
Is corks
And idiosyncrasies and characteristics
Don't make a big difference on the world
You probably never hear about them they only affect
In other people he have contact
But you take that same figure and you making the iron-fisted dictator of one of the Great
20th century Nations on the planet
And all of a sudden that man's quirks and idiosyncrasies and characteristics
Can create a deadly Holocaust
Now Wilson didn't have those kind
The characteristics at least
I haven't heard that even from the evil witch
But he did have characteristics that impacted this whole situation one was
He was almost always convinced that he was right
The paraphrasing here we said something to the effect of one that he felt pity
4 people who had different opinions than him play knew they were wrong
You can watch the way he operates in government and he's a supremely gifted politician
But what time those people are unwilling to let other men
Carry out
You know their policies and end their programs
Because they know they could do it better and you can see that from Wilson to
After the war
The man is going to become the British prime minister game David Lloyd George
We'll have to sit by the French military leader on one side
And the president of the United States on the other and he said it was like sitting between Napoleon on one side and that was the French leader
Jesus
On the other
That was Woodrow Wilson
And Jesus was probably more the way Wilson saw himself
George was trying to convey
And the way others
Negotiating
With the savior
Can require a debt
And Wilson's demeanor
And so the professorial air of superiority and that I'm always right
Kind of Savior are about him sometimes
Robbed
Some people the wrong way and certainly influence the way
That Wilson handled things
And there were several big challenges to American neutrality
It Wilson had to deal with an all were especially acute
In 1960
One involved American lives
The other involved American money
And the last involved
An American election
Start with
Perhaps the number one most obvious
Thing sucking United States into the whirlpool The Vortex of the first World War
And it was something that was so obviously doing that you can feel
The momentum even now reading the history books about this sort of slide into a war because
The Germans use of this Thoroughly Modern science fiction almost weapon the submarine
I have a submarine with creating conditions where
A couple of Americans here and there every now and then we're dying on ships
Every now and then it was worse than that
When the Lusitania went down
Which was a Titanic like
Liner
To a submarine torpedo
More than a hundred Americans went down with that ship
How long
Any Nation put up with that
The problem is is that the US would complain
And work something out with the Germans
Tensions with drop and then a month later
Month-and-a-half later boom it happens again
It's like a sore
Kept getting poked with a needle before it was
Able to heal
And yet
Wilson kept making the conditions more and more
Impossible to fulfill so those
Anti wilsonian historian to say no no you misunderstand Wilson was trying to create the conditions that the Germans couldn't help
Violate and then get the United States into the war
And then claim it was forced upon the America
For example Wilson at one point his administration
Which high-minded rhetoric and speeches was defending the right
Of an American passenger
Remember Americans could travel on
American ships
Neutral ships in certain times the Germans have sworn they wouldn't go after those
Wilson was defending the right of an American to travel
On a British ship
Aura French ship right a belligerent ship
And defending their right
Travel on a belligerent ship even if it was carrying munitions
And defending their right to travel on a belligerent ship carrying munitions
It also was carrying defensive guns on it they could hurt us every
When the Germans
Throw up their hands
And say
That's a damn Wilson didn't look like it
That's the kind of guy you going to trust with peas
I mean look heated head and their attitude
He doesn't hold the British to any of these same
Rules he's trying to hold up to the British blockade going to use submarines that use mine
They would mind the North Sea they create the zones where they would stop every line if they could get their hands on make it go to a British port
Search it in a decided with contraband
And Wilson and his administration were pretty darn quiet about that
Occasional protests and nothing more to the Germans just look like rank Hip Hop
And to anti wilsonian historian to them it looks like a perfect
Example to show
Really these ideals
That Wilson professed
We're very conveniently ignored when they ran against what he wanted
There were other complications that affected what he wanted to
One had to do with perhaps
The most ancient of motivations
I've all economically
The United States
Was making a killing on the first world war by 1916 pardon the pun
And it began to affect
It's entire Outlook toward the conflict
It's one of the longest term impact by the way of the first World War
The results of which we live with everyday in our modern world
But it's sort of sinks
Beneath the radar it's a lot easier to understand the submarine warfare question
And it is the economic transfer of wealth
From Europe
To the United States
This war
Was so total in it
Steaks
That these that the sides fighting it found no good reason
Not to spend every bit of capital they had to win
When Britain started this war in 1914 she was the richest country in the world
It was not long after the era where the phrase the Sun never sets on the British Empire was in Vogue
The British Empire Control directly or indirectly about a third of the planet
She was wealthy and she's been sucking up a lot of the wealth of Europe for a hundred years
During Europe's most dominant time.
On the world stage the era
Penal colonies in and post-napoleonic Splendor right the Victorian age
And yet when 1914 started the British didn't just have their own bills to pay in this most expensive of all human conflict
The underrot their Dominion
The candidacy Australia the New Zealand
The underworld countries like
Italy and paid for almost all their costs during the war the Russians to a lot of other small powers
The amounts of money that were changing hands I've seen so many different
Attempts to come up with it all you have to know though is
It's ungodly
At one point it was like 75 million dollars a week
In 19
16 money
When is it incredible wealth transfer when Britain started buying stuff from places like the United States When The War started
Use cash
And goals
We talkin about credit
Debt
And if you wanted to think of New York is being like a giant vacuum cleaner
With the sucking hose end in London just sucking out a hundred years
A civilizational wealth
Acquirement
It's not a bad image
In 4 years the center of world banking as we send another episode
Is transferring
From London to New York
Same thing for the center of World Trade
And all of a sudden by 1916
Wilson is acquiring a huge amount of power
Because the United States is the banker
And these people are beginning to owe it money
The British realize it at the same time
History Injustice
Don'key rights
About Wilson's new ability
Because he controls the purse strings of the Allied side in this war
To dictate any sort of outcome he might want
Donkey rights quote
If Wilson desire to force the Allies to the peace table the opportunity had come
And he knew it
On October 3rd 1960
Hey British interdepartmental conference noted the nation's utter dependence upon American munitions
Steel
Foodstuffs
Oil wheat
Cotton and lubricants
Where do United States to engage in economic reprisals
Britain's war effort with practically stop
Of the five million Pounds Sterling needed to prosecute the war reported to government economist
John Maynard Keynes later that week 2 million must come from North America
Quotes in a few months time claimed the treasury official the American public will be in a position to dictate
Hey to this country on matters that affect us more nearly than that
And quote
The author continues quote
Reginald McKenna Chancellor of the exchequer concurrent with cane
Telling the cabinet in late October quote
My next June or earlier the president of the American Republic will be in a position if he wishes
To dictate his own terms to us
And quote the author says at the end of December McKenna told an American journalist that Wilson could quote
Force the Allies to their knees anytime in a moment
And quote
United States in late 1916 is like a bank
And Europe and especially great
Britain was the financial underwriter in the whole Allied war effort basically
Always the bank money
I give the bank a lot of power
But there's an old
Lying in bed
And if you owe the bank a little bit of money it's the bank who has
If you owe a bank a lot of money
That power goes back
To the person that was the money because the bank now has a vested interest in seeing that that person survives
So that they can pay them back
The United States is beginning to worry about what happens
If we can't sell this war material any
Or we can get paid for the credit we're loaning out
The US has had a very uncomfortable
Sort of prosperity to send on it in the past 2 years
In 1914 the first world war breaks out the American economy is not doing well at all
My 1916 halfway through the year the American economy is
Coming along nicely thank you
Some historians have actually called the United States
He nation of War profiteers at this point if if Wilson was successful in creating a negotiated peace at the end of May
1916 somehow and you wanted it at that point declare the winner
In the first World War
Do you know which two Powers I nominate
I nominate Japan
In the United States and the Japanese hardly fought in the War doll and by the end of 1916 the United States had
Fought in the War.
Those are the victors the Japanese get involved in 1914 for purely
Opportunistic reasons
They can take over all the German Holdings in their neck of the woods and the Germans can't do anything
To get all this territory
For basically nothing
The United States
Is selling
Amazing about
Both sides need everything in the Americans will sell to anybody but they can't get their stuff to Germany
They still made loans and tried to get stuff to them but by and large the British blockaded shut that down
But you could still trade with the British and we did
And the idea
That that trade might somehow go away
Began to filter into the halls of government
The prosperity that this war brought the United States created another vested interest
And there are economic historians intend
Storing to look more at
Economic motivation for white countries do things that pointed this is the most important
Undercurrent of why the war was really going the way it was
That is another reason to and this is very pedestrian
But Woodrow Wilson in 1916 was an American president faced an election campaign
And this is where the
The real uniqueness of the American situation is demonstrate
What is the president do
Who's running for re-election
And the big elephant in the living room situation is this war in Europe
When he's facing an electorate made up
Immigrant
A people
On both sides of that conflict in the old world
Historian David Stevenson does a great job
Breaking down
Are the ethnic makeup of the United States and showing you
All these weird problems that the United States would have if it got into this conflict
That other nations wouldn't
For example he points out
That large chunks of the United States is made up of immigrants are some of these countries
The two main groups that are that are
Problematic
For anyone who wants to talk about siding with the Allies in this first World War
Are German Americans
An Irishman
Google Stevenson rice
Quote
Support for American neutrality was strongest in the interior
And especially the middle west
Where the German Americans were concentrated
I'm home only an insignificant minority favored intervention on the side of the Central Powers
US population in 1910 of 92 million he writes
Two and a half million have been born in Germany
And 5.78 million had one or two german-born Para
In 1917
522 German language newspapers and journals were published in the United States
German Americans were the largest ethnic group
In Baltimore
Pittsburgh
Chicago Detroit Los Angeles and San Francisco
And quote
He then goes on to talk about Irish Americans
Who and we didn't even get into this
This is as a person
A partly Irish American descent
I would have just gone off on on the whole Irish
Uprising the Easter Uprising what happened
During the conflict of which the Germans may have had a role
The British considered this and especially nasty stab in the bank
Backstabbing during wartime reacted by killing a lot of Irish unit
Killing Irish leaders in the uprising
Infuriating Americans of Irish descent of which there were a ton
That's what your politicians like Woodrow Wilson
You have to deal with the fact that you have a ton of Voters who are the only people that can keep you in power
Who are really interested in not
Joining the side
Of the Allies maybe or anyone
The slogan for the 1916 campaign that's most remembered
On the Woodrow Wilson side
Is the one that said quote
He kept us out of War
And quote
That was a slogan that appealed
2 most America
Wilson's peace oriented
Secretary of State William Jennings Bryan
Had said at one point that New York
And the major newspapers want war
The rest of the country one
Wants peace
If you're an American planner
It's interesting how many times you can open up the history books and see references to
The uncertainty of what these large immigrant
Descendant populations would do if the US
Join the Allied side in the war
2.5 million Americans born in Germany
What are they going to do when War breaks out of potential terrorists
And so it became
Real interesting issue before the
Conflict involved the United States as to whether or not
Do United States was unified in the idea that it would go fight on any side in the
Now what do you do if you're one of these American figures
Perhaps one of the top politicians
Who want the United States to get into the first World War
What's your strategy for dealing with these Americans
Who don't want to go
Want to stay neutral
You may be a huge majority of the country during this time.
If you're a politician in your used to sort of putting your finger in the wind and going in the direction that people want to go but they don't want to go
Go in the direction you want to go
And what's your strategy for dealing with that
The strategy of several of the top political figures in this. What to play the super Payton
Accused
Americans
Who disagreed with the idea of getting into the war
As being
Disloyal
Intake for example the former President Theodore Roosevelt
In 1916
Roosevelt is not running for
But he's campaigning and helping
The guy who is from his own party that the Republican that's challenging Woodrow Wilson in the November 1916 election
Now Roosevelt is in an interesting position here
Desperately wants to get into the first World War
You think it's cowardly that the US is staying out
He's publicly
Slamming Woodrow Wilson from pillar-to-post for not wanting to get involved in the con
He Compares him on the campaign Trail
To Pontius Pilate in Jesus Wilson's neutrality
Is worse than Pontius Pilate
Remember Pontius Pilate
He's the Roman official
Who in the Bible sentences Jesus to be crucified
That's a pretty good political
Swam with the president isn't it
But then
Roosevelt makes a point to go after what if the time were referred to as hyphenated American
You know people who have a hyphen
Between there
Description of your nationality
German
-
Irish
Jewish
Hyphen American
And it was a
Feeling amongst a lot of Americans that these people weren't real America
That they had conflicted loyalties
And it was also this idea that you had to have 100%
Loyalty
To the United States
And any consideration with what the ancestral home might want what's equivalent in Roosevelt's on words
Used to being immoral Trader
So how do you deal
With the fact that you want the United States to do something that most Americans don't want to do
You slam is traitorous
Those who opposed it
Now
Wilson was in a bit of a different position because not only
Many historians think they did not want to get in the war maybe but he certainly had a public Persona of not wanting to get in
The war
But Wilson didn't like anyone
Who disagreed with
And you can see
Wilson's attitude about those who would oppose his policies even in peacetime
In his response to a telegram he received from an irish-american there's of hyphenation right Irish
Hyphen American
Leader
In September 1916 the guy name
Jeremiah O'Leary
Ann O'Leary was telling Wilson something that's that's
Perfectly logical he's explaining to him that all of these moves that seem to lean toward the Allied side of the war going to be
Issues in the campaign right there's nothing controversial about that
O'Leary's cable said quote
Your foreign policy is your failure to secure compliance with all American Rights
Your leniency with the British Empire your approval of War loans the ammunition traffic RAC
Is in this campaign
And quote
Most American political figures would understand that's just
Someone from the opposition explaining if that's how the American political system works is nothing wrong with that especially not in peacetime
Wilson Road back to Jeremiah O'Leary quote
Your telegram received
I would feel deeply mortified to have you or anybody like you vote for me
Since you have access to many disloyal Americans and I have not
I will ask you to convey this message to them
And quote
In other words
Just simply opposed Woodrow Wilson's policies in peacetime
Doesn't make you part of the loyal opposition
It makes you disloyal
What is a president who feels
The peacetime opposition to peacetime policies is disloyal what's a guy like that going to do
When it's no longer
Well here's a little preview to think
We still have laws on the books that we're currently enforcing and using in the war on terror
Their President Wilson's response to critics
Put dress him negatively
In Wartime
Unless you think that this isn't over reaction there may be misplaced
Priorities
It's worth noticing that in late 1916
There are several belligerents in this war
Who are most threatened not by Foreign armies defeating their armies
On the battlefield
By their own populations
Collapsing from within
Morally
Or in terms of their unity and support for the government
In an era where more and more
Of the armies of these modern twentieth-century States could take a punch and stay on the battlefield fighting
Year after year
The chink in the National armor for some of these states was proving to be
The homefront
And nowhere by the way
Do you see a better example
I'm just sweeping away of the 19th century mentality
When and how the homefront is viewed
The homefront of course is a shorthand word for the people back
Living their civilian lives and supporting the war economy
Helping to make Munitions and all the stuff that helps support those troops at the front
In the 19th century in Europe some more genteels
Rivera there were all sorts of Peace conventions in
And laws of war meetings to do to help
Spare civilians and keep them as far away from the suffering of War as possible that was considered to be a civilization advanced
It's interesting and end
Telling I think
To watch that sort of genteel peacetime mentality
Crash into the rocks of reality that are the 20th century
We're all of those
Rules look like rainbows and unicorns
I mean from another time with gas in each other with univ insecticide Humane Society said that you meant to say
Something you use to spray on human beings
Like their aunts
Are there golden 19th century genteal conventions right there
In the same applied to civilians we have the Germans
Using Zeppelin raids to drop bombs on on
British cities I mean there goes those nineteenth-century conventions right there and the German bombers who do it
Insight this idea that everyone is a combatant
If the homefront is a legitimate Target
In Total War
Then so are the civilians going about their daily lives in places like Germany and Austria-Hungary
When the British cut off trade to those places they begin to do the
Put an entire nation or an entire Alliance
Dance under sea
And one British official actually said you know
What's the difference between putting a city under siege which has been done throughout history in the civilian population in that pussy
Mid-City always suffers
Inputting a nation
Under Siege
The British clampdown this blockade at the beginning of the war
By the middle and latter part of 1916
At long-term Anaconda likes
Strategy really begins to bite
And
Part of the reason why is the societies are already straining
To the maximum to just keep their militaries
In the field
And I think it's easy to forget exactly
What does strain on these societies Nawaz because you look at the we know we've often compared
The size of these are modern armies to what Alexander the Great conquered the known world with back in the end of the 330 SB
BCE
Alexander the Great is a
Core
In one of these modern armies
Listen to What a German Army Corps of which they had dozens in the army
Requires to sustain itself
Imagine an ancient economy
Me trying to
Provide this
This is from Hozier
Herve
And his book on the first World War
Quote
The Army consumed copious amounts of food and fodder
A single core of 35000 soldiers monthly
Devoured 1 million pounds of meat
600000 loaves of bread
189000 lb of fat
Or he says 242000 lb of canned meat and 121000 lb of marmalade
And he says 73000 lb of coffee
It's horses
Perfect size
Needed 7 million pounds of oats and more than 4 million pounds of hay
We 18th Army Corps he says for example estimated that it needed 1,000 wagons extending
49 miles to Halt its monthly allotment of bread
It's butchers Slaughter 1320 cows 1100 hog
And 4158 sheep every month
Taken as a whole he says the German Army weekly
Demolished
60 million pounds of bread
131 million pounds of potatoes and 17 million pounds of meat
No one in the government or the general staff he writes
Had given serious considerations to such a mammoth needs for a. Of 4 years
And quote
No no one saw that coming
Someone from the ancient world I mean
This could never have been sustained
Before the modern era
But sustaining it
Tok
All of those
Necessary
Foodstuffs
Out of the civilian populations mouth
And they were beginning
2 *
Because of it
The winter of 1960 and 1917 will be remembered by Germans forever as the turn up
And that's the winter where the hunger blockade
Really big
Astorian
Eric Thornburg
That's 1916 turn to 1917
Caloric intake
Wechat already begun to fall in late 1914
Play do about a third of pre-war consumption levels
Money connections and the black market help the lucky ones but even the Upper Crust
Suffered
Now quoting a noble
Woman we are all gaunt and bony now
We have dark shadows around our eyes
And I thought your chiefly taken up with wondering where our next meal will be
Brose continues quote
Poor kid almost disappeared from dinner tables and restaurants where Crow was now serve
Milk was reserved almost exclusively for young children
Butter and sugar could be purchased only in very small quantities
Eggs were rationed to 2 per person per month
And turnips and rutabagas had begun to replace potatoes
And quote
Brothers goes into a couple of
Reminisces
From Germans about what those taste
Liking then says quote
Inevitably as nutrition level spell bodies to come to a variety available
Like Ricky
Scurvy
Dysentery tuberculosis and influenza
Estimates place the number of blockade related deaths by Wars end at 730000
Which makes popular outrage understand
Now as with everything in the first world war there are historical dissenters who will
Challenge
Every aspect of
What's known as the hunger blockade affecting the Central Powers
But nonetheless
Important thing to understand is that it
It creates a dynamic in this conflict
Forces
German side
To do something
They're the ones
Continually getting less food
Their adversaries the British and the French do not have a food insecurity problem
That Dynamic forces the Germans to do something to change their situation or they'll just strangle
I mean if you're already living through
What Germans are calling the turnip winter in 1916 and 1917
What are they going to call the next winner of 1917-1918
You don't have to be a genius to see
That you now have to do something
To change the state of
Affairs
German public opinion begins to demand.
Now I should point out that that just pretty much makes them the equal of all the other
Populations of all the other belligerent seemingly
Doesn't seem like anyone
Particularly happy with the way their government is Prosecuting the war
Regardless of which country you're talking about at least amongst the majors
In Britain
At the end of 1960 in their government Falls
And the new prime minister who Rises
Is
The very embodiment
What voters would vote for if they wanted to shake things up and get somebody different in there
His name is David Lloyd George
Usually just called Lloyd Georgia
Feisty
Welshman of a much more working-class background than you normally see in these
Positions
Might be exactly what in the average dissatisfied with the way the Warriors going British to this and wanted
Now it is a little interesting that only a couple of weeks
It's before Lloyd George gets the job
He's recorded as having said about the Allies in Britain
We lost this war
Now he's
In charge of Britain's war effort it's also interesting to note that you could
How how up in the air the outcome of the first world war is in 1916 where you can find leading figures on both
Side who think their side has lost the war
Nonetheless
The French also get into the game 1960s been a terrible year for them to just as a
Has been for the British
And they finally find the courage
To get rid of their longtime military leader
The legend
Joseph joffre
He's been living off the
The fumes of his reputation from the Battle of the Marne a long time I think it's safe to say been underperforming
And the French finally they can't fire and he's too much of a legend but they finally so
Kick him upstairs and promote him to a ceremony opposed to replace him
With the First new French leader since the war started the guy name
The Russian population in public
Which isn't really supposed to have much of a sway
Supposedly cuz they live in a
In a strange sort of autocracy with a part-time legislature
But they're making their feelings known to more on that in a minute
And in Germany
The population just wants a way out of this trap
Some people would like to see
Efforts made towards
Figuring out a way out of the War Witch
They have people who say this in all the belligerent countries but you have to be careful
A little while ago we talked about Woodrow Wilson
Suggesting that people who might oppose his policies were just loyal
You could get you thrown in the
Jails in a lot of these belligerent
If you appear to be disloyal so too much peace talk could get you in a lot of trouble
Nonetheless there was a body of German public opinion
It was pushing for another route
They wanted their government to take the gloves off
Stop playing nice
With the adversary
They wanted their government
To unleash the submarines and to heck with what the Americans would do
Germans the American policy look to be a very conniving way to Simply deny Germany
The use of the submarines if you make the rules too restrictive
And then the Americans case the rule basically was
Then an American traveling on some ship gives it some magical protection simply by stepping on board you can't think that she
Now there's an American on it
That pretty much nullifies the submarine for Germany
At all but if that's the only way
You see a chance to end the war with a German victory over the British
What is that mean
Can you let the Americans hamstring you like that
Add to that the fact that a lot of Germans don't really see the Americans all that neutral already
And think that maybe Britain could be defeated in for 6 months before the Americans have a chance to do much of anything
Add to that the fact that when public opinion beers in that direction
There are Germans in the military High command a majority of them that were already thinking that themselves now they have public opinion
The submarine
The Americans come in the war
There were German leaders though that didn't like this choice
Wanted to find another option rather than
You know use the sub to get the United States into the war
Chief among them was a chance
Germany the top lid
Pickle guy's name was bethmann-hollweg
Can we discuss him before
This is all by the way very controversial very complicated very convoluted you're getting the Dan Carlin
Condensed
Potentially unreliable version of this
But it's a fascinating time in the conflict because
The politicians
Blood by holding think they find a way to throw a monkey wrench
Into that terrible choice that the allies of sort of voice did the Germans on with the hunger blockade and everything that they got to make a move
So
They make a very
Unexpected
December 12th 1916
Bethmann hollweg
And the Germans
Announce
That they are prepared
To enter into negotiations
Twin the war
Now it should be pointed out that such
Calls for peace in discussions about peace and going on since the war started
Woodrow Wilson had stepped up
Pretty much right at the beginning and said
I'll meet you at anytime you want
They were attempts by both sides in the war to try to make A Separate Peace with somebody else and maybe get
In one of the Allies above your enemy to drop out of the war but those are peace terms
Just to get an edge in the conflict are not peace terms to end the war
The Germans were making the first
Apparently serious
Certainly public
Offer
To sit down
And start talking about the issues that kept the conflict going
This was
Huge
Shock
Not exactly to the Wilson Administration they've been getting some information fed through some back channels that the Germans might be ready to
To do this but the Americans felt that they were going to unleash this being peace proposal
When the Germans do what they preempt Woodrow Wilson's version and he have to rush his out you know
About a week later
A little bit miffed that the Germans stole his Thunder a little bit but all of a sudden in December 1916 after this horrible
Here
There were peace proposals on the table
And it puts everybody in a really uncomfortable position
German to taking a real chance by the way
By trying this proposal route
If this is a high-stakes card game and I often think of the warden in terms like that
The Germans because of the hunger block and everything else are forced to play a card and everyone thinks they're going to play that really high-risk high-reward
More dangerous car they have
The unrestricted submarine warfare card
Instead they play a potentially equally
Perilous card
The one that no one's expecting they play the peace card
The peace card can blow up in your face if you don't play it deaf
Case in point
What are your enemies going to think when you become the first power to come forward and start talking about stopping the war
They're going to think you need to
What's more
Is it danger your own people might think that too and you spend a lot of effort in this War 2
Stiffen their backbone and keep their resolve in place
How much are you going to undercut it if you become the first power to seek
Peace
So this whole thing has to be worded very careful
And it is but almost
In such a way to give your
To give you whiplash as you're moving your neck between
The humanitarian side of the German Chancellor's proposals
And the side is filled with overwhelming hubris
The Germans talk about what this war is doing the civilization
And how they be willing to get into conversations about ending it but they're still invincible and they're going to win the war and they don't need to do this
And what would the terms be on the other side maybe you could say that
Allies
Historians have argued about
The motives behind this
Ever since but the truth of the matter is if you look at this like a card game
There were some good reasons for the Germans to play that piece card
Whether or not it was realistic
And whether or not the other side except
And some historians say this was
What it was intended to do the whole time
Provide some diplomatic cover
For the start of the unleashing of the submarine
To go and say hey we'll talk about peace
Then when it's rejected be able to turn around
To your own people
And say you know you better give up those hopes of an easy piece we just tried they won't do it this is a fight to the end stiffen yourself
And also to show the world including the neutrals and including the people on the other side of the wards population that we're not the ones
Keeping this Carnage going
We could have been over but your side wants to keep fighting
Most especially
Is an attempt to maybe
Influence public opinion in the neutral countries especially the most important neutral country the United States
Which has so many german-americans in it
That they were more than 520 German language newspapers as we said
What do you think the editorials are going to be
In those newspapers
After Germany makes a peace proposal and the Allies SWAT it down
That's going to put some pressure
On the US government to stay out of the war and that's going to influence American public opinion over who the bad guys and who the good guys are
That may have been the overriding intention
Others German peace efforts but nobody knows
It may have been
A
Serious attempt to at least start negotiations going
And to take a position that didn't make you seem too vulnerable at the outset the Germans pick the right time to do it it was right after
The capital of Romania fell to the central powers are there
Negotiating from a position of strength here
And the Allies SWAT it down
They have to
The problem with asking these powers to State publicly what their War aims are in order to create a piece
Used to show that the war aims of these Powers have gotten so out of hand
That they bear no resemblance to anything that could be negotiate
Historian Gwynne Dyer
Rodan
As we may have cooled it already on this program
Quotes
What the governments of Europe who found themselves trapped in the first Total War discovered
To their dismay was it at the means used to fight the war total
And so must be the end
It was almost impossible to stop short of total victory for one side
And unconditional surrender for the other
And quote
The old
Territorial exchanges and the paying of reparations
And the
Giving up or acquiring of colonies
Was a nineteenth-century sort of Warrant
It sounded out of place
In the twentieth century of the British or the French or the Germans or anyone
Had said that their War aims involved a little change of territory
A little reparations money or what have you it would have seemed so out of
Portion to the cost
There would be real Danger
That the public would think that's what the country was fighting for wasn't worth what the public was paying for
In addition to that occur
Course
There were some craving territorial
Ambitions involved in no one wanted to State those in fact
Outside
Promised other people territories
Two allies of theirs
For example
The Italians were promised
Territory from the austro-hungarian Empire once the war was over
The British couldn't very well say that was a Warframe
And still not look like
Cynical
Games been in this war when everyone by the way
On all these sides
Is a cynical games with but you can't show that to the public what's more
The idea of War aims that stopped short of defeating the enemy unconditionally
Clash with your propaganda
This is a war that using such 20th century ideas
As a war to end all wars
And a war to make the world safe for democracy
It's not a war to acquire a few colonies on the Mediterranean and some oil in the Middle East
Based on the breakup of
The austro-hungarian empire
It's a war for these high-minded ideals the problem is is if your propaganda portrays the Germans as the second coming of the month
Ingles
Well actually the Huns is the word the propaganda use
And their baby killers
And nurse
Executioners and none rappers and all the things that propaganda makes them out to be
How can you possibly sit down and sign a piece of paper to compromise
That's what them and have peace again
When the Vatican
Was I at this time trying to
Help create the conditions were peace could happen
The Vatican kept telling the powers to live up to those pre-war agreements to make war
Less horrible
And they were saying that they were favoring this not because
They were
Idealistic
Because
If these powers kept doing everything in there
Edomite to destroy one another they were going to hate each other so much that there was going to be no space Andres mutual respect left
To carve out a piece lighter
The Germans were no happier by the way
Estate their warframes Pub
For the exact same reason
There was an implied threat in
Included when the Germans came forward with this attempt
To get negotiations started
An implied threat was
If negotiations didn't happen in Warren fruitful
They would play the unrestricted submarine warfare
The peace negotiations
Are over by the end of January
Weary
In the middle of January actually on January 20th
Wilson makes a famous speech
A vase
Speech where he calls for peace without victory
And your so-called peace without victory speech
On the 22nd of January when essentially he already knew
It wasn't going to happen Wilson lays down the kind of P
Peace that Europe will have to broker to end the first World War
If it's to be a lasting
You can't be one of those pieces
You know where the knife is turned in one side is left hating the other
When you think about how the first world war ended and how it's sold the seeds for the Second World War
Wilson sounds like Nostradamus with some
In this part of the speech where he talks about you know having to have this
Kind of peace
He says quote
I'm speaking only to face reality
Add to FaceTime without soft concealment
Victory would mean peace forced upon the loser
A Victor's terms imposed upon the vanquished
It would be accepted in humiliation
Under duress
Add an intolerable sacrifice
And would leave a sting
A resentment
A bitter memory upon which terms of Peace would rest
Not permanently but only as upon quicksand
Only a peace between equals can last
Only a piece the very principle of witches equality
And a common participation in a common benefit
The right State of Mind the right feeling between nations
It is as necessary for a lasting peace
As is a just settlement of vexed questions of territory
National Allegiance
And quote
So you not only calling
Peace
Where nobody can claim a victory we just stop fighting
And begin negotiating
For a postwar world
In which Wilson and envisions
A new international Global structure
To enforce
Global Peace and harmony
So that we never have a first world war again as I said for those historians who suggested
Wilson
Is out to make Wilson the biggest historical figure he can
That would be a heck of a leg
I can see if he can pull that
But instead
Within a couple of months
The United States will be in the war
And from the Allied perspective
Not a moment too soon
The end of 1916
Early 1970
We've been spending quite a bit of time
Setting
This.
In the war up
But this. In the war is probably the most important 6 months in the last
Hundred years
People talk about the first world war this transformative moment
And the after effects that we're living with
No even now all around us
But the most transformative moment in that conflict
What's about to happen now
And
You know
I can't help it find some sort of metaphor analogy approach to looking at it but I mean it
It's like we have this tree
And they've been shopping at it
For two years and at the end of 1960
Falls over
Winston Churchill says three ingredients acting together
Create what he calls the second climax
Of the war
In the spirit
We dealt with two of those ingredients
The Americans
And the submarine
3-ingredient
Involves Russia
Dealing with what you could
Safely call the first rate
The countries that were at the top of every
When The War started
The rich powerful cohesive Unified
In a top-of-the-line States the Frances the Britain
The Germany's
But if they are worn down by
You know this
Many years
This war
To this point
To where they are now where the Germans are undernourished
For lack of a more provocative term
What must be the situation that the countries that weren't for 3
Great powers in the war started the ones that had challenges and were struggling in various areas
How are two years war treating them
Will the Italians
Have open disagreements about peace
In there
Government
Been in the trenches there are pamphlets distributed by
Socialist that say
Next winter
Not another man in the trenches
The generals are not
Please with Outlets hard to blame
They're unlikely
Your 10th or 11th Battle of the isonzo river
Fighting over this
Torturous mountainous terrain with create an environment
You know it's a little teeny horrible war in and of itself with all these unique things I mean just to give you one example
In the mountain war that the Italians are fighting the austro-hungarian when shells hit their all carved into rock mean instead of
Trench is a lot of times
They've blown out like
Chasms for
Cover but when the shells hit the Rocks the Rocks just
Winter
Creating like a secondary amount of shrapnel that's just horrifying and then when you get wounded
Your way up
Six seven thousand feet you got to be brought down through the mountainous alpine conditions to the nearest weigh station.
They still find Frozen things up there even today
The horrible conflict
And by 1916 the Italians are unlike their 10th or 11th
Version of it and all they have to show for this more more dead people they wouldn't be human
If they weren't starting to get a little fed up with this in fact
That just puts them on
Car with how it seems
The populations of all the belligerent country
Preacher doing
The house Austria-Hungary doing remember they're the ones that
You know kind of over at Ground Zero when this whole War got started they're the ones who had the Archduke that got himself assassin
They're the ones that
Hino sent that uncompromising letter to the serbians they're the ones that sparked this war how they doing
Well I bet they wish they hadn't
They're in terrible shape
The venerable emperor that ruled there for so long
The benign face of stability and finally died
To be
Succeeded by
The next Emperor was a much younger man and look at his country and says that the Germans this war has to end in nineteen
In Austria-Hungary is worse than done
This new emperor during this coming year will go behind the Germans back to the Allies reportedly
And try to sew to sell them out
And the Germans find out about it and then they never going to take their eyes off Austria-Hungary gain all the sudden
Annie's brothers in arms don't trust each other anymore
It was very interesting move that a lot of pee
People talked about
It's almost like World War version of Rudolph Hess flying to Great Britain you know to make A Separate Peace for
Nazi Germany in the second world war just this weird little Endeavor and all it does is
Learn Austria-Hungary Germany's mistrust
And then you have
The Russians
Are the Russians from the very start of this
This war even before this war for a very long time
Have been this contradiction in power
In one sense they are massively
Powerful in a military sense theoretically they are terrifying
And yet they are at the same time
So fatally flawed in the underpinning
Anything Rush is doing in this world he seems to be like riding some real or we're walking a tightrope and and Design
Blaster wounded any moment just
It was an unsteady
So the situation
There's a story that sort of shows this
This contradiction in terms
The military leader the Russian military leader Bruce seal
You'll have
Inoffensive named after him in 1916 we talked about it nowhere near as much as it deserves
In the last program
This once again puts the Russians out there
In a good light shows you what they can do when they get that their act together and they are
Devastating
750000 casualties in the austro-hungarian Army mortally wounded it is
Frightening
What the Russians can do
You know when things go the right way
A Priscilla tells a story that shows you just how
Bailey
You compromised everything is you how Rodney insides are he says
At the height of this offensive when everything's going so well he's receiving unsigned
Letters
From his own soldiers
Telling him that if the fighting doesn't stop soon
They're going to kill him
Russia's been
Having internal problems
Decade
The currents are
Nicholas II
Bizarre Bazaar emperor of the old name that goes back hundreds of years but they still call
Call Nat because that's essentially what the office still is
In his name is official long title it says he's the article
And
Even if the Russian Duma has been given
1% in the
Dodge Dart 99% of the power
He's a and an example of the old world
At its most Royal
And yet he knows
How
Rightfully fragili underpinnings are
When he was a mere adolescent
He saw his grandfather
Carried into the Royal Palace
With his legs
Orangish red
His groin gone his stomach ripped out
A Spaceman gold and he's bleeding out on the Royal carp
Pretend and the royal family including
Nicholas
The second the man who will be Nicholas II watch their grandfather died
15 minutes
Even killed
In an assassination
Another one of these stories where
You know there's always out in his bullet-proof
Sled
And I can a bomber throws a bomb it sounds a little like the whole Sarajevo thing the kicked out the first World War II bomber throws a bomb to bomb
Goes off kills people who are not the target
The target comes out in this case is our comes out to look around
And there's another bomber in the crowd
Supposedly the Tsar at the time it said something about enough thank God
But nothing happened in the other assassin that he's throwing the bomb and I'm saying it's a little too early to thank God
Boom
Any bleeds out in the Royal Palace floor
While the Czar who will be commanding Russia as the autocrat
In the first World War
As a 13 or 14 year old boy watches he knows how dangerous the job is
He knows that there's
A violin
Current
Rottenness
That opposes his sister
He's dealing with it all the time
One of the things that makes this story so interesting that was when you're dealing with one person
With almost
Total power
As we said earlier
Their little idiosyncrasies
Make a big impact on history
In the case of Nicholas II
The autocrat of all the Russians right
His idiosyncrasies involve
Some things that
I think most
People out there who have children can at least relate to a little bit of
It's interesting that there's a
Judas story
The chest has a
Personal
Tragedy
Wrapped up in it
This is an example why you
Can't reduce history
Some sort of mathematics
Or some sort of
Predictable set of rules are there human beings involved
In the case of the Tsar
It's a fascinating story
Play The Man
Just so you know I mean this is how you were wise this is the Old Europe is being destroyed
He's the first or second cousin with everybody
He's the first cousin with the King of England he's the second cousin with the Emperor of Germany I mean he's related to every
Everybody and his wife
Is the first cousin
Of the king of England I mean
A little incestuous Maybe
But that explains why
The czar
And his wife mourn her in a second
Who only have one son
Give birth to a son
Who's a hemophiliac
It runs in the family
Queen Victoria who sort of the the the descended that all these people can trace their Heritage back you said that this did not run
And her family
But it seemed to
Victoria of course was German in her roots
So was the czar's wife is Irina
Alexandra
Both of them
Lovage
And I say this because you know you would think today would of course they did
Listen this is an era where especially amongst nobility
You often had three political marriages you also have these very old-fashioned things that were very common back then with a husband and wife really didn't love me
Each other the husband was out
You know with all the girls all it wasn't like that
With Nicholas and Alexandra this is what this was a lobster
Really why
And not just between the two of them
But with their children too
They love their children the way we think of
Every modern person loving their children all the way they should
And that is not to say that people in the past didn't
Although you find a lot of examples in the royal family throughout history with the father hardly sees the Sunday. It's not like that with
They take an active day today roll
In their parenting and they wrote letters to each other
Constantly Road in English
But they both spoke well
The tsarina was German but but
She spoke Russian she spoke English the Czar spoke everything
And they communicated in more than a thousand letters with each other will you get a real feel for the
I'm one of the things
They are absolutely terrified
Is there Sun who's got haemophilia
He's their only son he's the next
Zar
And he is almost certainly going to die young from this
I just so you know haemophilia is a disease where your blood.
Not to get too technical cuz I couldn't explain it anyway
But but basically
Any little cut or bruise has the potential to spiral out of control
The normal
In a rough-and-tumble of a of a young child's life
Will kill you
And in this era especially
Parents just assumed almost Adesa
And these two
Parents as any parent we would think of today probably
Could hardly handle
I thought
And they were looking around for cures and trying to find them
And eventually they found someone
Who seem to be able to
Fix their son
And because of the little idiosyncrasy connected to who this person tended to be
World history completely halt
And in the funny part about it is and I know it
If it is a tragic story that it's an interesting story to bring human story
But there are elements to it that would make a good
In a sitcom
Or a good movie premise
As I walked
2 in to talk about this today I remember the movie that was kind of based on the premise
Nick Nolte and Eddie was called Down and Out in Beverly Hills
And the story is about a vagrant kind of homeless kind of guy who by hooker by crook ends up
You know he's living with a rich family in Beverly Hills
Really fabulously Rich family
And of course because of the dichotomy and their lifestyles in the way they view the world hilarity ensues right
That's kind of what happened
What does r
And his wife and their hemophiliac son
When they found somebody who seem to be able to heal him
That somebody was basically the equivalent of the vagrant
In Down and Out in Beverly Hills
They were bringing
A peasant
In
To have a look at their six son
Hasn't name is Gregorio
And history has always been I mean he's a hardcore history personality if you've ever found one
And the fact
That this government was run
99% by one guy and his wife
Opens up the door
Tua Grigori Rasputin being able to have the effect on his
Historian Peter Hart does a good job of
A framing all the various things that seem to be going on at once including what I just talked about
The way Russia is sort of a giant
Hamstrung by the
Ancient system of theirs
So the guy like Rasputin could make a difference in the idiosyncrasies of a single individual or two
Could come to the fore he writes quote
The Russian Homefront was gradually collapsing under the Intolerable strain of War
The czarist government did not have the flexibility necessary to cope with the plague of economically
Political and social problems that affected the land
The Tsar himself received any form of democracy is a threat to his regime
And rather than introducing an increase measure of liberalism with more attracted to the idea of a total disillusion
I've even the tokenistic Duma
Appointments to positions of considerable Authority
We routinely assigned by the Tsar on the grounds of either naked favoritism or the authoritarian creden
Angels of the candidate
Spy scares rage through Society with particular suspicion falling on any Russian general unfortunate
Enough to have a dramatic name
Meanwhile incompetence and Corruption blossomed unfettered
Wanted to Center the Czar was publicly embarrassed by the adherence of the tsarina Alexandra
To the Ludacris Cult of Rasputin
An unhinged religious Mystic
With a penchant for irreligious Pursuit
The whole despotic system of government
Was resting on just a few weak individuals
Russia was being hollowed out from within
And the vacuum at the center with creating dangerous instability
And quote
Know everything that Peter heart says
Could have applied to several other countries in this
Everything except
One thing
Depart dealing with
Grigori Rasputin's agrate wildcard
The story in a quintessentially Russian figure
I mean it's hard to imagine him anywhere else and he is
Outrageous and Larger than Life
Peter Hart is great historian as he sounds a little bit like
He can't understand
Another czarina the wife of the czar
Kind of falling for this guy and he's stick he calls it the Ludacris Rasputin cult
I mean if you two had her here to ask her she would probably said you but I saw him do it
Multiple times
Do what
Save my son's life
If you saw somebody save your kid's life multiple times
Don't you think it would be hard to have your
Logic override what you think you saw
I've seen
Cold-hearted
Total real estate
Turn into people seeking quack remedies
These when they were dying of cancer
They were looking for hope
If your kid is dying you're looking for help what if somebody asks
He comes through
I mean what is that
Quack treatment
Fourier
Relatives
Terminal cancer
Cure the cancer
That's the weirdness in the
Story
The royal family the emperor and his wife
Run into this guy Grigori Rasputin first
A1905
About 10 years
Time.
We are in the story
And there's an entry by the Czar and his diary we met a man of God today
And so starts this relationship
Between
This person who was born a poor peasant in Siberia
An uneducated everything
And his relationship
With two of the most Royal figures in the world
I mean the king and queen of England that's the level were talking about with the tsar and tsarina imagine today's queen of
No power at all picking up some
Person off the street who's almost homeless and not even the London homeless person someone from the sticks up in the north of England somewhere some
Small town bringing them in the palace
And having them live with you for a while instead of questioning them
On the state of things
What are the people saying
And oh yeah letting the minister medicinally to your child
It's a crazy story
And the only reason Rasputin becomes important you can hardly imagine important
In most of the other systems of government
Because Russia is so autocratic
If you capture the czar
You capture the country
Rasputin made the Royal Family
Emotional hostages
Whether that was intentional or otherwise is debatable historians disagree
There's some historians who think this is a person who stalks
It was a blast
Man of God with the special powers to do
You know religious oriented things that other say he's a charlatan and he knew he had
The royal couple sort of emotionally blackmail but there was nothing anyone can do about it there's a great quote from the Tsar
You're in the middle of the story with Rasputin wear
One of his advisors says something to the effect that you got to get rid of this guy
And the answer is there's nothing I can do about
And a lot of historians have always interpreted that
To mean that the Tsar is basically saying he can't stand up to his wife
You know that she wants him and there's nothing that the zarkin do you won't stand up to his wife
But you know some historians have come out recently and said you know it could easily mean there's nothing he can do about it
Because there's only one person who can save their son's life the heir to the throne by the
If you really believe that
Disputing God got you in a weird position
Between 1905 when the song Rasputin first meet
And where we are in the story right now
Late 19c
Rasputin has been worming his way into the czar's family
Pretty consistent
Not a circle of friends his family does Ry these get together sometimes we would
His wife
And his kids and Rasputin
Now there are back step
Sometimes the relationship goes sour for a while usually cuz Rasputin who is a Serial misbehavior
Does something particularly outrageous
Either embarrassing is are so much that
That that he does with his underlings are continually telling him to do and
And sends Rasputin away
Or legitimately upsetting him
Nonetheless everytime he manages to break the relay break up
I guess you could say with Rasputin
Inevitably Alexi his son the heir to the throne
Will get sick again
Necessitating a return
Rasputin
He's like a cigarette habit
You can't kick
Now this Rasputin characters
On so many levels
You know you have to think you were dealt some interesting card by faith
To be able to Parlay
Your gifts
From his upbringing as a
As an uneducated peasant with no money in the middle of nowhere
To where you are in
The royal
And when you see a picture of him
You see a little bit
I mean he was 5 foot 9 inches tall
Pretty normal
He had dark black oily
Hair
Parted in the middle
Unkempt mustache unkempt beard interesting way of dressing I mean if you if you would Photoshop his picture
Going to the back
How many number of 1970s heavy metal album
I don't think I would be able to look at the band's photo on the back
And know that you did that he would have been perfectly as the basis of any number band
Back then
Heck if you were a lead singer and you named the band after him
It would fit in on any lineup you could think of it as a heavy metal festival when did I mean you know this weekend only blacks
Sabbath Iron Maiden Motorhead and Rescue
Most amazing
And you can tell because normally
You can't tell from photos a hundred years ago
In a certain qualities of individuals it just gets lost
True the layers of
Fuzziness in black and white and all that but if you catch the right photo arrest
You need to be caught just the right time
You can see
What the eyes were
Cuz they jump out of the black and white photo from a hundred years ago at you even now
The whites of his eyes were said by witnesses to be extra White
And again it kind of looks that way in summer
Is eye color Dazzle people to the point when we get multiple descriptions that all countries
Some people say blue some people say brown some people say gray some people say multi
When you read about his sort of
Tick like weigh
Of walking moving his nervous habits the way he wouldn't talk for a while then all of a sudden you get this
This
Stream of sometimes unrelated conversation spiced with sexual innuendos
I mean there's a part of you think of an I just read a book on the late writer Hunter Thompson
They sound like
In a room together they would look like they were impersonating each other
Rasputin is a combination
A person who looks to be a very devout
Religious figure
From
Russia's Christianity in orthodox
Christian
And a drunken hour
Apparently that's not
That unusual in in the Russian tradition especially in the Siberian tradition where Rasputin's from
Directions
Offshoot some sex
Cults
Who have these interesting beliefs and I don't understand him I wouldn't wouldn't try to explain them but apparently
It involves needing to send sometimes in order to get the right kind of
I repentance working for you
And and
There are rumors of orgies that take place as part of the rights for these religions an end some historians not mode
But some have tied
Rasputin some of those
Strange sex in strange beliefs
I would make sense in one in one sense. Because there's no
Conversations
That have been recorded with his wife and yes he was married
You know when she would walk past him and in the middle of a town with other women and they would all see him having sex in the open with some towns
Woman
She would say something to the effect of well that's just his cross to bear
He's got to do that you don't even like
Piedmont to judge
He has to do
He's helping us
I'm sure if I was Rasputin I would want to sell it.
That way let's put it that way
Gossip
Column type
Offenses that he's always hard with
RR extreme drunkenness
And sexual outrageousness
And usually
In combination
The rape charges
That are brought to the tsar and tsarina is attention with a household staff is accusing him of going after them he's absolutely
Brazen he will sit down next to a figure from the royal family and put his arm around her at a party with all the
Aristocrats Erin start moving in honor
There are stories that you have to know that the tsar and tsarina knew he was this way because had these family gatherings I mentioned earlier witherall
All sitting there and it's just him in the family he'll sit next to the princesses were all adolescent girls during this time.
And they will jump up like they've been
In a product with a hot
Needle because he's goosing them
Feeling them
In front of the Czar and czarina
And yet at the same time
Some of this stuff is passed off as just part of his rustic peasant charm isn't it cute
But he doesn't know how inappropriate that is
Like I said some of these people in Russian aristocracy
Hated him
But those who didn't
Kind of had a reaction like he was some sort of exotic
At the zoo brought in and you have to make allowances for what he doesn't understand
He might not know you can't just walk up and touch some Noble woman's breast at dinner and how how funny and interesting it is at
Is the outrageous you know that kind of an attitude
But he was fun and historian Joseph Furman has written two books on recipe
Eaton points that out
Quote
Rasputin was fun
It was a pleasure to be in his company
He gave people nicknames
And they were often cutting and quite appropriate
He might double woman
Hotstar
Boss lady
Sexy girl or good looking
What a man would be called Fancy Pants
Big britches
Long hair
Poor fella
People accepted this is a Charming characteristic
The humor of a peasant who meant no disrespect
And quote
Tell the people that didn't hate recipe
Would often
Can Overlook his outrageousness and consider that part of
You know his charm
Is rustic peasant chart
Nonetheless sometimes
It was a little too much even for those are there famous into this and they all end up in the local media Believe It or Not Russia had
A tabloid media during this time.
And Rasputin was one of their
Staple
Minifigures I mean back in my day
Every one of them had to have it Elizabeth Taylor story or Michael Jackson story or something like that
Kim Kardashian probably today
Back then in Russia if you didn't have a rescue the story
You know every so often
I mean you were worried about circulation drop
I just when you think there be no new news to get roaring drunk in it
You know highfalutin restaurant in the capital city starts yelling about how he knows the tsar and then pulls his pants down and
In which his genitals out the restaurant
Word like that gets around
Tabloids eat it up at one point the Tsar had to tell the Tabloid that they couldn't mention his name anymore
So they just started referring to him
At the guy who lives on so-and-so street whatever street he lived on
And everyone in the public just knew who they meant
There were cartoons
That made the round
Showing Rasputin with his hand on the naked breasts of the tsarina
Implying what a lot of people wondered about this relationship although it's almost certainly not true
If Rasputin's going around town sleeping with everything that moves from peasants to Royal
Women as well
What you doing with the czarina
There are even whisperings and one public charge made
That the
Heir-to-the-throne the czar's son
Is really Rasputin son
Almost certainly not true but the more gossip circulating but that kind of talk the more it undermined
In a people's trust in
The tsar and tsarina remember this arena is already German at a time when
The Russian people are hounding Russian generals who just have German last names
What happens if you are German
And the czar's not around and this strange Russian peasant who seems like a spin golly is
I mean there were protests in 1915 where the people were saying down with Rasputin down with
Alexandra
He's not an unknown quantity everyone realizes he's almost a public figure
They debate him in the legislature
And the powers-that-be want him gone
There's a story during the
Time.
One of the ways they tried
Did you get them out
It's a famous story
1 day rescue in here to knock on his door
Go to the door in the man standing there with a pack
Is Rasputin the packaging Rasputin open the pack
And it's full of photo
Rasputin looks at the photos and they are photos of
Vim
Unconscious
Insensible do to drink
And there are naked women all around
Nice boat
The man at the door gave the package says either you leave town and go back to where you
You came from a stop
Talking and influencing the czar
We're going to get these pictures
It was an extortionist
And I'm one of the nights apparently that
Rasputin and passed out from drink
Is enemies have hired prostitutes and position them around him naked and started taking photos to Black
In typical unexpected fashion Rasputin
Took the photos straight to the Czar and sort of
Throw himself on the mercy of the Court
I know a lot of the time
Rasputin's able to skate away with no real repercussions
Sometimes he's not
Wechat occasional wrists with
Between his arm
One of them for example that went on in 1912 is a perfect example of how
How hard it was for this artist
Stay away
Rasputin
The 1912 to have one of these disagreements on the Tsar sends Rasputin back to Siberia the royal family goes on
Vacations
September 1912 to their country Palace
They're playing around in the young heir to the throne Lexi jumps in a boat
About 7 or 8 years old
Not Unusual Not Unusual for seven or eight-year-old to land wrong and hurt themselves
But most of the seven or eight year olds
Hemophiliac so it instantly becomes a problem there's a giant hematoma in his lower abdomen they take him back to
The palace and I have a terrible
It gets very ill
Very bad
Takes about a month for him to start to recover
Genesis just starting to turn the corner and I've never understood this his mother does Arena think should be great to take him a little carriage
Dried and it's a bumpy road and they hit some bump and he cries out in pain and Something's Happened inside him they take him back
Back to the Palace
And now they have
One of the most horrific periods of their life starting
Because this kid starts to die
It takes a while it's very painful and the parents are watching
The kids fever skyrockets
The pain become so terrible he's delirious and slipping in and out of Consciousness I read somewhere
That are opium is used in the past sometimes your people in the
Heir-to-the-throne condition but they didn't use it for him
And the screens are so terrible that we're told
Palace staff has to stuff cotton in their ears to walk around to deal with it
The parents like I said loving
Real Hands-On parents
Their turn
At his bedside
And he's begging for help you
He saying Lord have mercy on me
Was one of the things recorded over and over and over again and my mom helped me the pain
And
We're told that
When the parents shifted the bedside was over they would walk
Out of the room just burst into two
Zar said that
A certain point the doctors run out of things
To do
They tell the parents there's nothing more they can do it becomes apparent to the parents and to the patient
But he's dying and he starts
Talking about those things
That destroy Paris
You never want to hear your little kid
Kid saying he's
He sang When I die will the pain be gone to his mother
Yasmin
After he dies they build this little Shrine in the woods for milestones
And then the reality of the situation sets in and they start putting together a public statement to tell the Russian people
That the heir to the throne has died
The last
Rights
Are performed
And
While at a meeting
The Czar gets a hand scroll note from his wife saying
Come quickly I think it's time
The boys about to die
At the last minute
The czarina
Pens note2 rasputin off in siberia essentially saying help
And she get the cable the next morning
Hit the famous cable
And it lets a little air out of the tires that it's not as good a Cody.
Historian Joseph Furman
As we always thought it was
The cable was always thought to say
God has seen your tears and heard your prayers
Do not grieve
The little one will not die
Do not allow the doctors to bother him too much
Watch & Co
Russian store in Alexandria VA
Apparently says there were
There were two notes but the one that was Miss quoted really said quote
Fear nothing the illness is not as dangerous as they're saying
She's at the doctors do not bother him
And quote
By that afternoon
The boy is out of pain and is able to sleep in the fever starts dropping
The doctors are
Done that it should be pointed out they
8 respect
But they were forced to move several of them quoted in that
In Fuhrman's latest book He's written two books on Rasputin
And they're just
They don't know what to even make of it and it wasn't just this time they would be trying to stop the boy from bleeding and pass incident
And in Rasputin would come up and they would watch him stop it
And historians been trying to find
Explanation
Ever since
I mean I've heard everything from
Hypnosis
To the power of suggestion to drugs to one theory is that
That they were giving the Young's are aspirin which was like the new wonder drug back then and that of course would have been the worst thing to give
Rasputin says don't let the doctors bother him too much they stop giving him the aspirin
Some people have suggested that there was some
Ocean rescue
Add disorder kept the boy
You know in a bad state anytime he wanted to
Can pressure on the royal family that's all kinds of theories
Arena
And you've already seen Rasputin save your son's life several times and he just pulled in back
From the brink of death by Telegram
Don't you think you'd stop caring
About the wherefores in the what-ifs and just not want this guy to leave your side
If the tsar of Russia was in the process of
Kicking his Rasputin habit he fell off the wagon
After that 1912
Pull your son back from the brink of death
Here's the thing
Rasputin
Wasn't the problem
Because he kept feeling
The Heirs
If he had stuck to that
Probably we don't even
Talk about him very
Of course the reason we do talk about in the reasons a famous figure the reason half of Russia wants him dead is because he's not stick
Fixing the air he's meddling in Polish
In a funny way to I can see how that have
I'm not so appalled I mean if you if you if you look at this from the tsar and tsarina is bandage
And you think this guy has some
Does Ariana think he's a man of God and that God favors him and only
Prophetic
And if you'd seen what she's seen when you think so maybe two and if you thought that
Wouldn't you want to use this guy like a Magic 8 Ball
Especially with the stakes as high as they are for the Czar at this time I mean when the first world war breaks out when the Romanov
Dynasty is threatened
When millions of lives hinge on the decision is our makes
How tempting would it be
Now to just sort of
Rasputin what he thought about
Appointment through that idea
Should I go to the front end command from the Frontline source
And that's the event by the way
The Tsar going to commanded
The frontlines
Which opens up the door to turbocharge
Rasputin's influence
And really ushering Russia into the terminal phase of the end of the Romanov Dynasty cuz what happens is
End of the terrible losses against the
Central powers that the Russians had suffered
Bizarre thought
The people might need a scapegoat and he
Altruistically offered himself up as a sacrificial lamb you think he's going to go to the front his advisers think this is a tear
Terrible idea with lots of downsides
But Rasputin likes the ID
Therefore by the way those are real
The idea that one points desires wavering and think maybe he shouldn't do in Rasputin
In a bolster his confidence that it's a good idea
Cancel the Tsar leaves the capital and goes to kind of clothes
Frontline
A little something is Irene is left in charge of the day-to-day activities and she is using Rasputin like a match
She gave ball like you wouldn't believe
You can read it in the letters back and forth between the Czar and his wife
Because she'll inform him what's going on she calls Rasputin our friend
Code name
And she'll say to those are our friend thinks we should do this our friend doesn't like that legislator
Heartburn things that appointment job to go to this person
Until debated back and forth and
Rasputin is
Making huge decisions for Russia's future in Wartime when things are deteriorating bad
Italian bread riots are happening in
Satisfaction is is palpably on the rise and demonstrations are occurring and he's drinking 12 bottles of
Wine a day at Waco
Don't think the belligerent powers
Of the other countries aren't aware of it either the British secret service is monitoring according to
A story like Joseph Furman
Is monitoring
Rescue
I have a nickname for him a code name they call him.
Forces
And
Many things about Rasputin trouble than they're not sure he's not a German agent
They think he's unstable certainly
They think he is
In favor of some sort of peace deal to get Russia out of the war the whole lot of reasons they don't kind of like him
But this problem is becoming acute
And
Some noblemen apparently
We take it upon themselves
To rid Russia of this
Cancer
Which is the way they see Rasputin
They decide to kill him
When we reach this point
We're actually caught up
With the storytime
Find again
December 1916
Where we left off before our little Russian digression
You know that
Time with the submarine
Turn the peace deals on the table in the questions about the US getting into the war or not
In December 1960
Rumors are flying
The capital
That Rasputin's going to be killed
And they're so pervasive
Rasputin here's the
Allegedly his children hear them doing they hide his clothes so he can't go out
Nonetheless
Even with those rumors flying he can't resist and this is the traditional stories Kennedy assassination
And good luck finding the truth I'm just giving you the the most common story here
Apparently a nobleman
Offers his wife
To rest butan
You know a nice little clandestine Arrangement o after party
Or something like that
Rasputin takes the guy up on the offer he's a nobleman Felix yusupov
What is his name I think he's so rich he has more money than the ruling Dynasty
And working with a bunch of other men it's a true conspiracy nobody knows how deeply there are some who think the British secret service
Was even in on it
The majority don't
Yusupov
Meet
Rasputin kind of his door bring him down into the basement
Yankee Doodle to Titus
Story together
Wonderful
Is playing on the phonograph upstairs that they can hear
So you got this little American Tune playing in the story as a Russia
It reaches the terminal phase here in the Romanov Dynasty
There food on the table there's wine
The Rendezvous is a little pushback you stop off says they sit there and they eat the food they drink the wine
And after a while you sup off begins to freak out
Because he's laced all these things with cyanide
And this guy is not dying
He says he's a
What's bothering me a little stomach bothering him a little but he's he's sitting there
Drinking more eating more and asking you some pop to sing for him I like your singing voice
Yusupov excuses himself goes upstairs to where the other conspirators are and freaks out what are we going to do
Finally one of them decides
They should shoot him and do some pumps got a pistol. Of goes down there tells
Refuting look at something on the wall over there and then when Rasputin turns around the pistols pointed at him you sell pops
Says he said you don't say your prayers or something like that shot him in the chest he Springs me falls down on the
Rod frothing-at-the-mouth convulsions dies
The assassins all come downstairs have a look at the body the blood everything
Go upstairs to commiserate about it for a while and then we're told that the Assassin yourself off
Wants to have another look at the body
And so he goes downstairs
Anne. Joseph Roman historian quoting some original sources in his quote
Talks about what happened when you step off went down there to just make sure
That nothing was amiss
Women rights quotes
He found Rasputin lying in the same position on the floor
Overcome with a terrible inner rage
Usafa grabbed Rasputin by the shoulders and shook him
As he stared into Rasputin space
First one eye and then the other suddenly opened
In the story she's quoting his green Asian snake eyes
They fix the prince with an expression of satanic hatred
Rasputin stumble to his feet
Foaming at the mouth
Roaring and angrily wildly clawing at the air as you rushed towards yourself off
Blood dripping from his mouth he grabbed the prince by the shoulder
Weeping in a pallet from his uniform
Rasputin was reportedly growling his tormentors name in a low guttural voice
And quote
It's like a zombie
And Usopp office
Screaming everybody runs downstairs when they hear the struggle going on and you stop at the screaming about the time everybody gets downstairs
Mutant have lurched into the snowbound courtyard in his running away and he's yelling
Yusupov first name who's also
Spruce yourself up
Felix Felix Hotel the Sarita everything
Annie's going to tattle
On the prince for trying to kill him
And people open fire the prince among others
At Rasputin as he flees misses him a couple times then hits them somewhere in the back
And then they run up to the
Anybody that's on the ground and they put a bullet through his forehead
Then were told they wrap them up and tie them up then wrap them up in a carpet then go to a nearby River where there's ice and
Controlling through a hole on the icing
In a Hopi
Flights to Finland
Of course he does
They find him in a few days
They dragged the body out and end the myth of this story and again so much better with the myth
Is that during the autopsy
They found water in his lungs and his body untied is ohia freedom self
And only at the end round so they Cyanide and imaging work they shot him multiple times it didn't work they threw them in the river
Turn it almost didn't work
Historians say that
Shop to his forehead
Almost certainly
We killed him it's right in the middle of
And it's possible that the cyanide was old or the Never
Forgot put in his drinks
Or who knows but it adds to the legend of Rasputin
There's a warning before he dies that he gives to the royal family supposed
That also add
Add to his Legend
You know another one of these prophecies that are sometimes uncannily correctly supposed to have said
To the royal couple quotes
If I die or you desert me
You will lose your son and your crown in 6 months
Rasputin is
Write again
From Beyond the Grave
This. In the first World War
Timeline
About the time. Rasputin die
You take a couple of months before he was assassinated a couple of months afterwards
That really is the first world wars crowded hour
Roosevelt called his combat
In the Spanish-American War
He was trying to describe these
Large number of events.
Crammed into a short period of time he said it was his crowded hour
If you're referring about
November 1916 to April 1917 is the first world war was crowded
Huge number of events compressed in a short period Of time
These events are all connected though to the various teams we've examined individually so far
The United States
And United States involvement
In Mexico
The submarine
The high-level diplomatic activity in maneuvering
And the
Trainwreck that's about to happen with Russia
This all comes to a head as we said
January
Late January 1917 Woodrow Wilson gives his peace without victory
While he's doing that
The Germans are already
Behind the scenes
Prepping
For their February 1st resumption
Of unrestricted Warfare they pulled the trigger on that because they had given
The high-level politicians in Germany
The
Go ahead to try some peace maneuvering
Of course they were told at the peace maneuvering doesn't win we let the submarines go
The submarines are slated to go
February 1st
Now because Germany was reasonably sure as was everyone else
Pretty much that
If they started shooting at every ship on the high seas
The United States was going to get Dragged In
End of the war the Americans with diet
American ships would go down it was pretty much inevitable so the Germans started working on some contingency
In January
1917 you know again right around the same time Wilson's proposing peace for all men and all the time minded sentiments
The Germans are sending
A telegram
To their Ambassador in Mecca
Chicago
Giving their Ambassador in Mexico some instructions
On what to do
Just in case the United States comes into the war
It starts fighting Germany
The telegram
From the German
Foreign
Secretary a guy name
Arthur Zimmermann
To the ambassador of Mexico
Says this
Quote
We intend to begin on the first of February unrestricted submarine warfare
We shall Endeavor in spite of this to keep the United States of America neutral
Any event of this not succeeding
We make Mexico a proposal of Alliance
On the following basis
Make war together
Make peace together
Generous financial support and understanding on our part
That Mexico is to reconquer the Lost territory in Texas New Mexico and Arizona
The settlement in detail is left to you
You will inform the president of the above
Most secretly as soon as the outbreak of war with the United States of America is certain
And at the suggestion that he should on his own initiative
Invite Japan to immediate adherence
And at the same time mediate between Japan and ourselves
Please call the president's attention to the fact that the ruthless employment of our submarines now offers the prospect
Compelling England in a few months
To make peace
And quote
So there's a note
Suggesting that Mexico go to war
As part of the Central Powers against the United States if United States gets into the war
What's more
They talked about getting Japan on board to that was one of the United States is great worries by the way the Japanese have to
Are the Americas all these theories from American planner that maybe they could either go take the Panama Canal and come up through Mexico mean
When is All This Is War playing kind of fantasies
But the idea that
Japan to be brought in
And flipped cuz they're on the Allied side the Germans are talk about flipping the Japanese making them on the Central Powers to having a
Japanese attacked the Americans the Mexicans attack the Americans
If nothing else
That keeps the Americans busy so they're not over there fighting Germans in Europe
If you're playing a board game here of risk or something that's not a bad idea going to the game called The Plum
If you're playing the game called diplomacy
There's all kinds of variables in real life
Not taking into account in the game of diplomacy one of them is
But your enemies might be tapping into the cable that you use to send a secret message like that
From Germany to Mexico
The British got it
Snatched it right off of the American
Atlantic Cable
Which they were tapping
I think we mentioned in an earlier episode
The British may be the the best Espionage codebreaker
People of all time
When the war starts they cut the German
Transatlantic cable to Germany can't send Telegraph messages across the Atlantic
So they work out deals to borrow other people's cable sometimes
Do United States let them use
The US cable for just messages Woodrow Wilson thought with
Would maybe
Masterpiece Riley wants to the Germans have an open channel to him
Did the Germans use the American cable to send a message to Mexico offering some
American states to them if they come in the war
By attacking United States little Iraq
The British have a problem
They can't tell the Americans about this cable right away
Because then you're going to get all these embarrassing questions like how do you get the cable
And then the British would have to say if they were going to be truthful well we tapped into your cable and we've been reading your message
I just for the whole War
Can't quite
Say that too easily
So by hooker by crook it's a great story Barbara tuchman wrote a whole book on it
The British figure out a way
To sort of hide the source of
You know how they got this cable
They give it to the Americans
Woodrow Wilson in Stockton
And understand the contact right
This is the very month January 1917
Did American military forces are finally withdrawing
From the Pancho Villa Expedition right this attempt to go get this
Terrorist
Us settlers in Arizona New Mexico
Texas would have called him
Mnusports kind of comes back with their tail between their legs it didn't get Pancho via that killed a bunch of his man but
Despite you know
Hi public
Praising of everything involved General John Blackjack Pershing says it wasn't a very memorable. In American history
Nonetheless it made the Mexicans
Mad as hell and in the US almost went to war with Mexico twice in two years
In 1914 US troops occupy the city of Veracruz in about 200 people died in that little Endeavor may be closer to 300
Nearly
Call the war between the US and Mexico the end
And then in this Pancho Villa expedition to us crosses the Border goes after a guy who is also the enemy
Mexico's leader
But it's so upset the Mexicans to have US troops in their country for any reason at that almost led to war
And so just as you're getting your troops the very month you're getting your troops out of Mexico
The Germans are sending him a telegram saying hey
Want to go to war against United States I'll give you three Fates
Will help you
It struck a nerve
For Americans
When Woodrow Wilson release that letter
Publicly
When the American public first heard about
Germany's offer to Mex
The reaction was one that I think would Woodmere the reaction of the American public in a similar situation today
A large number of them thought that
The telegram was a forgery
The British intelligence was behind
Did this was an attempt to trick the American government
And to affect American public opinion and make them more Angry Germany more pro-war
Speculate how much
You know that's what a perception would have stayed that way if the German foreign secretary Arthur Zimmermann
Haven't done something in early March 1917 that looks
Inexplicable
He admit it
That the telegram had been sent and that it was genuine
Twice
The second time
He said he hoped the American people would understand that this was only
To come into effect if war broke out between Germany and United States
As a way of saying you know you understand that right
American people wouldn't
The confirmation that the Zimmerman Telegram was indeed an official
Secret proposal from the German government to the Mexican Government
Outside of town of America
An undercut the cause of german-americans and irish-americans were hoping to keep the United States neutral
Was another
Nail in the coffin of neutrality and a huge German missed appt
In fact
The whole decision
To unleash the sub
When they did was a bad decision by
Germany
If they had only waited a little while longer
Longer events would have
Happened
That would have made that move unless
Terry
And if that's the move that gets the United States into the war that it would have made that event unnecessary
Winston Churchill points out
That the
Timing of the event
What happened in
March and April
In his mind show the hand of Destiny at
Here's how he framed
What's about to happen what's about to happen latest in German that will screw up everything
In here
You know set the stage for our modern world as much as the United States getting into this conflict will set the stage for the modern world
Russia has its Revel
Churchill says
The beginning of 1917
Was marked by three stupendous events
The German Declaration of unlimited U-Boat War the intervention of the United States
And the Russian Revolution
Taken together these events constitute the Second Great climax of the war
The order in which they were placed was decisive
Hit the Russian Revolution that occurred in January
Instead of in March
Wharf alternatively that the Germans had waited to declare unlimited U-Boat War until the summer they would have been no one
Limited U-Boat War
And consequently no intervention of the United States
Hit the Allies have been left to face the collapse of Russia
Without being sustained by the intervention of the United States
It seems certain that France could not have survived the year
And the war would have ended in the Peace by negotiation
Or in other words a German victory
Did Russia lasted two months less
Germany refrained for 2 months more
The whole course of events would have been revolutionized
In this sequence
We discern the footprints of Destiny
Either Russian endurance
Or German impatience was required to secure the entry of the United States
And both were 4th
And quote
As we mentioned already the situation in Russia had been seething and simmering
For quite some time
The straw that broke the camel's back
Was an almost complete break
Brushes transfer
Which has been withering since the war started
And that had suffered
Terribly in the winter that just happened
Russia almost
Couldn't handle is transportation needs in peacetime
After several years of war
They were whole cities
We're not receiving enough food
One of them was the Kappa
Metrograph
Petrograd used to be called Saint Peters
But when the war started that's
Sounds a little to German
So they changed it
To petrograd this is a city that we
Will change its name all the
During the Communist years it will be known as Leningrad now St Petersburg
Broke again
Nonetheless it's the big Metropolis
And it doesn't have enough food
You take a bunch of people who were angry already add the War Admiral food
It's not surprising they were marching they've been doing it all throughout 19-7
Irish historian William Mullen
Points out
From the beginning of 1917 there was a wave of strikes
Concentrated in petrograd
On the 7th of March
30000 workers were locked out of the feudal of armaments plants in the city
The following day international women's day women gathered in the vyborg working-class district
Protest against hybrid prices
They marched past Finland station
Nevsky prospekt by which time the strikers number 200000
Down with the war
Down with the High Cost of Living down with Hunger bread for the workers they cried as they marched through the city
The protesters connected their experience of war with much broader political claims
Although the Crux of their complaints was the food supply crisis
This material experience of War had political implications including the overthrow of the czarist regime and then.
The war it was possible in theory
That the food supply system could be reformed
But the Striker's new the czarist regime could no longer reform itself
And quote
British General Sir Henry Wilson
Went to Russia during this time.
And came back and
Is Piers
You know concerning how the people in Russia felt towards the tsar and tsarina
And told them quote
It seems a certain there's anything can be that the emperor and Empress are riding for a fall
Everyone
Officers Merchants ladies talk openly of the absolute necessity of doing away with them
They lost their people their nobles and now their army and I see no hope for them
There will be terrible trouble one day
There are open to
Discussions amongst
Some of the higher levels of Russian Society
The terror attack should be made against
Someone stands up at the Duma and important person
Later in the story
And says that the Tsar needs to be removed by terrorist means if necessary
Now
It would be foolish to say that the
Uniroyal Court did not have their so
They did
And they had people who didn't have a problem with
You know when Emperor but they had a problem with Nicholas II
So they were all stripes in this idea
That the Czar needed to go
And no consensus at all about what would take its place or how to get from here to there
Russian knew how to have protest
To revolt
About a dozen years before this time. They had the famous 1905 rap
We could also come
After
In a Russian
Problems in a war
That Revolution broke out
It got so serious the Tsar
Supposedly
Rode out his application letter he didn't deliver it but it was ready to go
In that particular Revolution the crowd marched on The Winter Palace with Hazard was to a line of troops to open fire
Fire on them killing hundreds of them
It's always Bloody Sunday
Bizarre had received intelligence reports a few months
Before this event
Saying that
Quote
Recently the conviction has been expressed without exception that we are on the eve of great events and comparison
Which 1905 was but a toy
And quote
That was for my police report
Bizarre received
Months before these demonstrations in March Breakout
But here's the thing
You know as with many historical events
They can be seemingly inevitable for the longest time and still come as a surprise when they actually show up
The people who are out in the streets March 7th March 8th which was International women's day they didn't know that this is
Is the revolution
In fact the people on the scene point out that that's one of the Tipping moments in this situation when people understand wait a minute
This just isn't another demonstration
We've been having
This is the chance to topple the government that's the big Turning Point
And the actual moment of the turning point
He's one of those really interesting almost turning point in history moments revolutionaries like Leon Trotsky
Who certainly see it that we spend a lot of time talking about that moment the Tipping Point in the revolution
This is seven days
7 days
For a 300 year-old Dynasty to fall
Then it starts off with some Factory Strikers
On March 7th
By the way this is our calendar these events in Russia happening on on the old calendar in February so it's often called the
Very Revolution and it makes the dating
Confusing as hell
For someone like
Me
None the last March
7th by our calendar 1917
There's an industrial strike
March 8th is international women's day the women go out
And strike and protest about the lack of bread in all this
Seems to be key and so many people talk about it
Write the fact that the women
Are doing this a lot of these women of the wives of soldiers at the front
Which gives them a huge amount of credibility as you might imagine
Without their soldiers
And they're out on International women's day on the 8th
On the 9th the women come back out bring more people
And go to factories and shops and businesses and grab the workers out and have them join the strike of the crowd swelled with
At least twice what it was the day before
By the next day
The industry of Russia's capital is
Paralyzed
And to show you how out-of-touch the tsarina is with all this
She writes in her diary on March
Tent
About
The troubles in the capital and she's basically in charge of the capital quote
This is a hooligan movement
Young people run and Shout that there is no bread simply to create excitement
How long would the workers who prevent others from working
If the weather was very cold they would probably all stay at home
But all this will pass and become, if only the Duma will behave itself
And quote
The Duma is a Russian legislature which
I think I said earlier had about 1% of the power in this system in the Tsar has about 99% and the tsarina is complaining that the
Misusing at 1% sort of
Russian revolutionary Leon Trotsky
Compares her pretty convincingly to Marie Antoinette
Before the French Revolution that said let them eat cake state
And she and the Czar and before he died Rasputin like this one Russian Minister a guy
Guy named protopapa
And so
He begins to sort of act as the tsarina's minister in all this
Situation and according to some of the scene it's anger at him
That prompts a lot of this activity
The events that are happening
Starting really on March 8th and then March 9th are large enough to be a big news story
Any International media is there
There are magazine journalists there a newspaper reporters for
Brittany France places like that telling the folks back home what's going on
In the Russian capital
One is a British newspaper man
Name John Paul
And he writes about the women
Protest
He writes in this is about March 8th
And my apology
She's for my Russian pronunciation
Quote
The rioting was so far confined to the viberg size
The cheap workman's quarter of petrograd
Put in the center of the Tramway service had already become a regular
On the 9th the rioters stop the trams across the river
Terrorizing the drivers and throwing parts of the mechanism away
So that the service crew still more intermittent
Visits were paid to all the factories in the hands were called out in sympathetic strike against the sudden food shortage
On this day to a prefect of police who threatened the crowd was killed
Strong Cossack squadrons Patrol petrograd and there was a collision on the nevsky
In which the Cossacks use their whips
But they told the crowd that they would not shoot
So long as they only asked for bread
Alarm that the attitude of the Cossacks the authorities on the 10th
Brought troops of the line into the streets to support the police
Posted machine guns on the nevsky and stop traffic across it at many point
And quote
John Pollock then points out
It sounds like a rumor but what what the Russian Minister working for the tsarina is supposed to have said
When his methods for dealing with this Uprising are being questioned here's what Pollock rights he says quote
Protopopov approached by one who endeavored to convince him of The Madness of his methods only answered
Do you know how splendidly machine guns work from the roof
And quote
Pollock says
That the first serious Bloodshed happens on March 10th when police open fire
On a group of protesters and killer wound V
The Tsar is now told about problems
At the Capitol remember he's off kind of at the front
Not in this
Capitol Hill he's letting his wife so to run the show with the spreader Popoff guy
How does our finds out about it they tell him things are bad
He issues an order that basically says make it stop
That order appears on lampposts and all over the city the next morning when the riot
Sanders and protesters
Master 2
Protest for the day they see this message from the head
Petrograd
Military Garrett
Quote
During the last days
Disorders have taken place in petrograd
Followed by force and assaults on the lives of soldiers and members of the police
I forbid every kind of assembly in the streets
I won the population of petrograd the commands have been issued and repeated to the Troops
To use their arms
And not to stop short of anything in order to assure Tranquility in the capital
And quote
John Pollock is out in the streets. Day
NT Wright quote
Sunday March 11th began nervously
There Were Soldiers everywhere in the streets and strong bodies held in reserve in Port yards
By now the trams at all. It was hardly possible to find a car
No newspapers appeared
About 3:30 p.m. the troops begin to clear the streets around the nevsky at the Bayonet Point
And soon afterwards
The police turn their machine guns onto a crowd at the same place as the day before
But with more deadly effect
A Caucasian officer who is nearby
Estimating the number of dead at 300
At the same time heavy firing took place further down the nevsky
An opposite the Kazan Cathedral
Several score more people were killed
The crowd here retaliated with pistol shots
Another prefix in a kernel of the police besides policeman the various innocent passers-by being killed
It was significant he right
It's soldiers were seen among the crowd firing on the police
And the number of man in some 14 officers are different attachments
Were arrested for refusing to support the police with arm
Almost same afternoon a drunken officer of the volume ski regiment named loss cabbage
Ordered his men to fire on the crowd
They refuse
Polish cabbage Sports one of the soldiers to obey
His shot killed a woman
And quote
The hurting of women
As I said seems to be an important part of this affair cuz it's mentioned by everyone
Trotsky says the rumor that was going around
Was that a police officer struck a woman
With a clock
And that this was witnessed by the Cossacks who were sort of
Sitting by neutral
Are there two kind of
Add some muscle to the mick but the armies kind of standing by while the hated police
And the public face off
And
Trotsky's is whether or not it really happened everybody believed that a woman had been assaulted in front of the Cossacks in the car
Call Saks drove the police away who did it
Now one of the things that if you watched
Recent revolutions you'll notice that
Often times some incident will happen
That the
Demonstrators and protesters and rioters will sort of
Clean to some sort of symbol
Generally from the event
It becomes almost like a high sign that protesters use and that they rally around
According to Trotsky
What it was in this Revolution was a Cossack
Calvarymen
Lincoln to the crowd
And that this wink became sort of a
Symbol
Of what was going on here's the way
Trotsky explained it and remember trotsky's a revolutionary for him this is a hugely heroic tale and that's the way he
He tells it
And I think we're all colored
At least those of us who know what's coming
Buy what's coming
This revolution is going to devolve into something very terrible
And
A lot of us look back on this event thinking that that's how we should View
Bee removal of what came before communism
And yet there was a. After this revolution
Where Russia was on the road to becoming something more like the United States
And so getting rid
Of a czarist regime that these people seem to hate like a Saddam Hussein
Was initially viewed
As a plus
And the reporter on the scene for example for the British press
He's thoroughly in favor
Oh something replacing this regime
The United States is too by the way one of the problems the United States has with joining the Allies are being
Associated with the Allies is not Britain and France would they feel very close to in a lot of ways
It's Russia
To them Russia is the same kind of
Militant autocracy that
Do us propaganda paint the Germans ass
The ideas are going away to be replaced by some sort of constitutional government
Makes a lot of people in the Allied camps it up and
Cheer for the protesters
Now in the story by Trotsky of the Winking Cossack
He explains that the officers of the Cossacks kind of force them to charge into the crowd at one point
But as soon as the officers pass by in Scatter the crowd
The regular Cossacks are very careful moving through with their horses not to hurt anyone
And
Trotsky right
It's quote
Behind them filling the whole width of the prospect Gallop the Cossack
Decisive moment
What's a Horseman
Cautiously in a long ribbon Road through the corridor just made by the officers
Some of them smile
E-courts app
Protester
Caillou referee calls
And one of them gave the workers a good wing
This wink
Karate size
Was not without meaning
The workers wearing Bolden with a friendly not hostile kind of assurance
And slightly infected the contacts with it
The one who went found imitators
In spite of renewed efforts from the officers
The Cossacks without openly breaking discipline failed to force the crowd to disperse
Flowed through it in the Stream
This was repeated three or four times and brought the two sides even closer together individual cost X began to
Reply to the workers question
And even to enter into momentary conversations with them
I'm disciplined there remained but a thin transparent shelf that threatened to break through any second
The officers hasten to separate their patrol from the workers and abandon the idea of dispersing them
Lines the Cossacks out across the street as a barrier to prevent the demonstrators from getting to the center
And quote
He then told the story about how these Concepts will allow themselves to be used as a mounted barrier
But they don't stop
The protesters from diving under the horses bellies
The fact that the Cossacks traditionally thesaurus
Crowd control mechanism
Appear
Less than enthusiastic about carrying out their traditional role
Convinces the government that they have to bring in the
The Garrison of petrograd is like a hundred 50 hundred six
Thousand men
They've got the people
And they call the man in March 11th is the key day because that's the day that elements of one famous unit of training Squad
It's called open fire and kill those people that the British reporter was talking
Now
The people of petrograd
Are appealing
To the Troops as you heard earlier mingling with them talking to them they are walking up to the line of Bayonetta troops
You know in in ones and twos and saying Brothers you're not really going to side with the police and kill us are you
The women again taking the lead in this whole thing are walking right up the line of banded troops and
Grabbing their rifles with the band that's on them in wrestling with them and saying join us
I did a lot of that going on
After the
Shootings in the street on March 11th
Citizens were told workers go up to
Members of one of these storage units
And tell them
The people in your unit open fire yesterday against the people of the city and told him what happened
And then those troops went back to their barracks and on the evening of March 11th
Morning of March 12th
They had one of those
Moral crisis moments
He instant in any Revolution a guy like
Leon Trotsky would say
And he describes it with almost
Heroic
Mattones
This this moment where this
Storage unit
Confront the reality that they shot a bunch of those poor people that have been besieging them not to shoot
The day
Before and they were going to have to go out and do it again
Today yours with Trotsky
Quote
The soldiers had no more time for hesitation
They were compelled to shoot yesterday
And they would be again today
The workers will not surrender or retreat
Under-fire they're still holding their own
I'm with them their wives
Mother's sister sweetheart
Yes and this is the very hour that they had so whispered about
If only we could all get together
Chucky saying that all these people
Thought about
Could these are be overthrown if only we could all get together that would happen and now these soldiers
We're not taking part in that they were taking part in crushing that
If only we could all get together trustee rights
And then at that moment of supreme agony
Indian bearable fear of the coming day the choking hatred of those were imposing upon than the X
Schnur's roll
The ring out in the Barrack room the first voices of open indignation
And in those voices
To be forever nameless
The whole army with relief and Rapture recognizes itself
Bust down upon the Earth
The day of destruction of the Romanov monarchy
And quote
The soldier shot their officer
Ran out into the streets cheering enjoined
The people of petrograd
Trying to overthrow the czar
Encourage other military units
To follow
Most of which by the end of March
12th and done so
The Garrison was melting away in joining
The antivirus
Rioters
They ransacked
The artillery Depot then they go to the Arsenal and break into it and take all the weapons
Then they burn down the court of justice and a bunch of other government buildings
And for March 12th on you have open battles in the Streets between the people in the army
And the very large police forces
And we would call them today the secret police and all these police agencies that have set up machine guns
At intersection
At this point
The big question is what the heck is the Czar doing
The first thing is our try to do is just get rid of the Duma
And when the head of this
Powerless for all intents and purposes Russian legislature received the order that the Duma is to disband he says
And most of the Duma joins him in the street
Joining the rebels
Next bizarre gets on a train
On the 13th of March and heads back toward the capitol from the fighting friend where he is
In one of his typically strange moves
He takes a lot longer to get there than he should have because he says he doesn't want to disrupt any of the
War traffic heading to the front so his train takes over the long way around
And it ends up getting stopped on the way to petrograd because the revolution is spreading to other cities now
And one of these train stops the revolutionaries are stopping the train
We are told that the czar's advisors
Are bringing him telegrams
Power Brokers including
For example
His cousin
And others that he
He needs to give up
The crown
And what sort of interesting
About Nicholas is that he almost seems willing
Going to do it there's a whole line of thinking
You know if you read a lot of the primary sources he sometimes portrayed as this drunken tyrant
You know when
But when you read more modern-day history he's a much more pitiable figure
Churchill likes
Patricia would like
What does great things about in this poor misunderstood person of course he wasn't a great man just a good man and he talks about him like that
What does orange soda
Seems to be relieved
How to prospect
Giving up the car
At first there's like five minutes of talk about giving it to his hemophiliac son but the Tsar doesn't want that
Any interesting neatly enough in the application note
To his people
The Tsar specifically mentions not wanting to be parted
From
In the Sun at your door
Once again you get that feeling of Nicholas and Alexandra at these kind of
Your parents were just
Adore their children
Whether or not this is some sort of smokescreen to cover something all the evidence seems to point out to a guy
Who cared more about his family in some ways than beings are
There was a quote to the guy
Who will take over
The What's called the provisional government
The country in the near future his name is Alexander
The kerensky
And he met the Tsar after the Czar been taken into sort of custody
And he said quote
As I studied his face
I seem to see behind a smile and Charming eyes
A stiff
Proper mask of utter loneliness and desolation
When I began to know this living mask I understood why it has been so easy to overthrow his power
He did not wish to fight
And it's simply fell from his hand
And quote
The things that this is are we going to have to do to keep power
He seemed
Unwilling
To do his wife may have wanted him to She Wrote letters
Telling him he needs to be tougher and stronger
He seemed to care more about the fact that all his children while all this is going on
Have a bad case of the measles which
Are you serious
Back then
And is as concerned seemingly for them as he is of giving up
In his power
All over Russia
Begin to break into government buildings
And teardown
Paintings of bizarre
And the aftermath of this revolution sounds like the aftermath
The fall of Saddam Hussein again when
All these
Figures that were part of the government that work for the Tsar are being arrested and held in custody by people in armed
Weapons
2 PowerBlock
Forum
In the wake of all this cuz remember there is no plan the real revolutionaries have been working for this for years what kind of caught off guard
Guard-one It app
So there's no competing groups for power one group is the people that used to be the almost powerless
Duma
All of a sudden they have power and they're mostly liberals and and Miles socialist and people who want to cry
Create they end up writing United States by the way in June saying that they want to create a constitutional government they want to use maybe they do not
But competing
With that
Particular entity for power
Is power too much lower-level groups that
Especially revolutionaries
Forming
Council
Rules of workers
Send soldiers together
And
They form this rough weird
Partnership with the
Provisional government is to
It's called the former Duma
And they kind of work with each other sometimes but they come to
Disagreements over other things
But when push comes to shove
The Soviet
As they're called these
You elected groups of people
Soldiers and workers councils
Seems to win
The first thing that they win
Is a rule that says that anything involving the military
Is under the control
The Sobe
And this is the key issue for the other
Countries in the war
Germany wants Russia out of the war
They've been paying
Agitators for a long time to hopefully make that happen now you have this situation with his arms gone what are they
The Russians going to do militarily
The British and the French feel the same way
Along with the Americans they're not that upset that the czar's gone but they're very concerned that Russia is going to pull out of the war
This
Provisional government will be known as the kerensky government
At a certain point
They tell the Allies that they're going to continue fighting a committed to continue fighting the Allies start pouring
Money and stuff into Russia even at a greater pace and they were before
How do you continue to hold off Germany in the Central Powers with your army
While you're 300 year old
Monarchy is busy collapsing all the structures
That have been you know hanging by a string
Start falling apart
What are the soldiers at the front going to do this became the key question
And it's not answered right away
Churchill as only he can
Saw the whole thing is an unmitigated disaster looking back on it from the late 1920s again now he can see
Where all this is going to go
Communism in the future so his ideas are probably
He said the tragedy of Russia was and I'm quoting here that her ship went down within sight of
Port
Meaning we were just going to win this war
And then Russia doesn't get to share in the spoils
And he says of Russia quote
With victory in her grasp
She fell upon the Earth
Devoured alive like Herod of old by worm
But not in vain her Valiant Deeds
The giant mortally stricken had just time with her dying strength to pass the torch Eastwood
Across the ocean to a new Titan
Long sunken doubt
Hunan l'rose and began ponderously the arm
The Russian Empire fell on March 16th
On April 6th
The United States enter the war
And quote
It's been an interesting two months for the United States
Since Germany
Decided to unleash the submarines
In the first 20 days
Is Robin Leach into submarines the Germans sink
Merchants
40 Newton
Amongst
There are us shipping companies
In the month of February when this all starts that start losing a million dollars 1917 value money by the way
A week
The next month March 1917 those numbers will double
And all of a sudden
We begin to see what the first
Real
Competent
Use
Involving
At least a minimum number of submarines is liking world has
The Germans have been perfecting that you do with these new
Weapon systems like submarines the science fiction type weapons what do you how do you use them at the beginning of the war they're kind of going after
Warships and whatnot and then they they work on short little bursts going after neutrals and Merchant ships and now by 19
1017 the Germans know what they want to do with these things
And they have enough ships to make
Their plan work minimum number but enough
They Unleashed them to go after everything which is what their strategy has told them you have to do to really maximize this weapon system
And there
Thinking enough ships
So that Britain is for the first time in the war in real danger itself of going under
What are the advantages of being an island nation is it you got the strongest Navy
You don't have to have the same kind of fears that are Russia have
Auray France
The Germans aren't going to be able to break you directly cuz they can't reach you
This is the first time in the war that the British faced any serious threat
Of the Germans in one way or another reaching them affecting them personally
Forcing them perhaps
To knuckle under
Just some sort of peace deal
In April
The month
The United States gets into the war
The Germans sink 400
Almost 805
1000 tons of ship
The British Empire
I cannot stay
Those kind of losses
The submarine war
It eventually brings the United
States in
If for no other reason
Venice
Disrupting
Operations in the country
The president is under a lot of pressure on a day-to-day increasing basis because once he starts thinking all these ships US ship stop leak
They begin to congregate
And clogged up and cause traffic jams outside the major ports on the Eastern seaboard
And then all of the Commodities and food and perishables that we're going to be loaded onto those ships begin backing up
You got this
Terrible
Clogged all the ports on the eastern coast of material this rotting and degrading because the ships won't cross the Atlantic
Because they are afraid of the submarine
At one point
Wilson wants the army ships
Change the situation
Watch provide Assurance of the taken
Norcross
But this is like a ticking Time Bomb for Wilson he's got to do something this situation is only going to get worse
The Zimmerman Telegram happens in late February to a mean
All these things that just increase a situation that's bad
And make it worse
But there's no
Instant moment where the line has been crossed
And there never will be
At some point
By March 1917 at the latest then probably around the same time the Russian Revolution is happening
The Wilson Administration decides
They've had enough
5 us ships go down in March 1917
Twosome in the Wilson Administration this is confirmation that the US is already at War
War with Germany
It doesn't have to be some big Lusitania 911 moment
To cross over this invisible line it's happening every day and on April 2nd Wilson Gibbs
Is most famous beach one of the most important speeches in American history
Concerning
The situation
That he see
The United States is at war with
Germany
The interesting part about the speech if you dissected it
Monumental on so many levels
He's so crappy way it's put together he never says that the Congress
Declare war on Germany you know so that we'll be at war with Germany he says we are at war with Germany and I invite you to
To confirm that fact
He had no time gives Congress
The impression that they have any control over this decision at all
Luckily for him they went along with him big
Time but what if they hadn't
Part of Wilson's speech focuses on the specific reason we're at this point talked about the submarine warfare Compares Germans
Do pirates and all these kinds of things
Take some time out of the speech to say
That we're not at war with the German people we have no quarrel with
It's their government we don't
Liking this is a big change by the way
In in the way
That much of the United States government will
Craft
Another way that they frame relationships with other countries to
Got nothing against the people
It's the government of Wilson point of view is
Is the people aren't running the government like in a democracy or Republic
Within the people aren't responsible
For what their government decisions are they may be the victims of it and we might have to hurt you
In order to overthrow your government but we're not mad at you
Is really high-minded sentiments
Forever known afterwards as wilsonian principles
The talk about things like the need to make the world safe for democracy I'll give you a taste of that in the second
But more interesting
And again one of the more groundbreaking parts of the speech is that Wilson takes on the US
Tradition
Of non-involvement in European affairs
Head on
And he basically said
That was the way it was
Times of change
Here's the exact phrasing
Nikki Gibbs
What is a sea change
In American
Foreign policy in the way the government of the United States approaches
The conflict involvement with the rest of the world and that course changes one we are still living with today
In the modern world
In the middle of his speech
Telling Congress that a war exists right now with Germany Wilson says quote
Our object now as then is to vindicate the principles of peace and Justice in the life of the world
As against selfish and autocratic power
And a set up amongst the really free and self-governed peoples of the world
Such a concert of purpose and of action as will henceforth ensure the observance of those principles
Neutrality is no longer feasible or desirable
Where the Peace of the world is involved
And the freedom of its people
And the Menace to that Peace and Freedom lies in the existence of autocratic governments
Back by organized Force
Which is controlled Holy by there will not by the will of their people
We have seen the last of neutrality
In such circumstances we're at the beginning of an age where it will be insisted that the same standards of Conduct in a person
Possibility for wrong done
She'll be observed among nations and their governments
That are observed among the individual citizens of civilized States
And quote
Having a national policy
Connected to the idea of not going abroad in search of monsters
Display
Just started to sound really low
Old fashioned
But at least
Wilson's
Got some really good
Arguments to justify the historic
These are the ideas
I'm wilsonia
And here's
How Wilson enunciate
Just some of them
Quote
It is a distressing and oppressive Duty Gentlemen of the Congress
Which I have performed in this addressing you
There are it may be many months of fiery trial and sacrifice ahead of us
It is a fearful thing to lead this great peaceful people into war into the most terrible and disastrous of all
Towards civilization itself seeming to be in the ballet
But the right is more precious than peace
And we shall fight for the things which we have always carried nearest our hearts
For democracy
For the right of those who submit to authority to have a voice in their own government
Are the rights and Liberties of small Nations
Universal Dominion of right
Why such a concert of free peoples I shall bring peace and safety to All Nations
And make the world itself at last free
Just such a task we can dedicate our lives and our fortunes everything that we are and everything that we have
With the pride of those who know that the day has come when America is privileged
To spend her blood and her might for the principles that gave her birth
And happiness and the peace which she is treasured
God helping her she can do no other
And quote
One wonders what John Quincy Adams
Would reply to that
Nonetheless
Guys like Theodore Roosevelt who been saying he was going to
Skin Wilson alive if Wilson didn't go to war
Like the speech a lot
It's interesting to note by the way
That the one American political figure that the Europeans
Really respect in this whole question is Theodore Roosevelt
Because Theodore Roosevelt is really one of the early what will be called Atlantis
People who believe
For example in locking arms with country like Great Britain in and doing great things with them
TR was an interventionist
Before his time
And in the United States he's thought of as an extremist the Republican candidate for
Tell him to stop campaigning for him because he's so bellicose it's working against the Republican Party write your
Letting Wilson in the opposition for traces warmongers
That's the guy though that appeared to be ahead of
The curve when it came to figuring out
The Germany needed to be dealt with
Again from the British point of view
There's a lot of this that you can look at and say the very things the Germans are being
In Slam for doing
Are things that they were kind of forced into doing by what their opponents were up
Up to
The first world war is not the
The clear-cut Good and Evil
Separation at the Second World War
He mentioned that
Nonetheless if you're on one side of it it certainly is
The Prime Minister of Great Britain for about a couple of months when Wilson makes his
Historic speeches Lloyd George
In his Memoirs Lloyd George writing after the war can't help
Take a shot
At Wilson
Not because of what he did but because of how long it took him
Speaking about Wilson speech now
George writes quote
These principles were excellent and excellently expressed
DIY democracies of France in the British Commonwealth
Penn already borne the burden they've been scorched by the heat of a thousand days
In the battle with this natural photo to Liberty
Stealing water wheel
Blind from his
Speech they rejoiced George does
At the Advent of this powerful help from the greatest democracy in the world at a time when troubles were multiplying
They perhaps might be excused for thinking that issues so clear now to President Wilson ought to have been apparent early
Clear to his eyes
They felt grateful in their hearts to the Great America
Theodore Roosevelt
Whose Vision was so undimmed
And whose sympathies were so sure from the outset of this Grim struggle for international right
And quote
Winston Churchill sounded almost the exact
Same way what took you so long
Speaking of Wilson
Peace out
Quote
He had behind his policy a reasoned explanation and massive
And all must respect the motives of a Statesman who seeks to spare his country the waste in horrors of War
But nothing Churchill rights
Can reconcile what he said after March 1917
With the guidance he had given before
What he did in April 1917 could have been done in May 1950
And if done then
What abridgment of the slaughter
What's pairing of the agony what ruined what catastrophes would have been prevented
And how many million homes would an empty chair be occupied today
How different would be the shattered World in which Victors and vanquished alike are condemned to live
And quote
Writing from the late 1920
And seeing
The mortally wounded and terribly scarred
Continent
Which Winston Churchill remembers as being the height of World Civilization
To him the US taking this long to get into the war
Looks like something that
Cost you the world you knew
A couple days after the president
Gives his famous speech
The Congress vote to support him
And take the nation to war
Don't wasn't close by the way in the House of Representatives it was something like 374
375 2
And as much as a Wipeout is that sounds
I read somewhere that that's the
The second most opposition the Congress has ever shown the president in a war vote the War of 1812 being the
The most
Nonetheless
Seems pretty clear that most of those people voting
Punisher about
What voting for going to war was going to mean
The future mayor of New York.
LaGuardia was
Congressman win this vote
He said that 60% is a 30 years after the war that 60% of his Brethren were pretty sure this wasn't going to mean troops
The Westin send armies overseas
The fight in on Europeans way they thought it was going to be like financial aid and Naval help
Mabel help is the one thing that us can do right away
Military help in an army
That's a problem
Because the US really doesn't
In April 1917 the US Army's rank
Largest
In the world
Doesn't have any flamethrowers or any tanks or any gas masks or mortars
No grenades
Aircraft are these rickety strange
Beast
The dino
The right look like the planes the Wright brothers kind of
Put together they don't look modern at all
There's not enough artillery
Shells for the guns to shoot more than a few minutes by Western Front
In a standard
Astoria
Justice don'key says
That the US relatively speaking have been better prepared
For the American Revolution in the War of 1812
Then they were
Pairing for the first word
World War
I disagree with him about that but his point is well taken
The United States if it's going to be any help to Europe
You're just going to have to survive while it waits for this help to be accumulated the only place the US
Can help right away as with money which they were kind of doing already going to lower interest rates and give better deals but
It's a continuation of what was already happening
And the use of the Navy
The thing the Navy can do right away
Is help against the submarines cuz we said in April 1917 the submarines take more than 400
Merchant ships
Britain's problem isn't it doesn't have to stop all the sinking have to stop the rate which is so much more than what it can reveal
If it loses less ships and it can build a month it's doing well if it loses more ships than they can build a month it's in trouble
Height of the submarine war will be
February 1917 when unrestricted Warfare is declared
And the next date
This is when Britain
Lives or dies
I thought of the steaks and Lloyd George and Churchill them all these guys go out of their way to talk about the almost a lot
Farm is the word Lloyd George Lloyd George says
But there are some of the most
Cautious people in his cabinet that are starting to Muse out loud about maybe we better make peace while we still have some ships afloat
He says the Germans were getting gleeful
But at times they just had these reports coming and it made all the pro submarine people seem to be perfectly
They were all of a sudden going to win the war Churchill said we went from being you know the side that had time on our side
Why do we can just wait this out and everyday the Germans were losing the war little bit more to having the tables flipping out I'm was on the German side
And the British had to come up with countermeasures
Or lose the war fast
They not only did
But it was the civilian leadership
The pushed for the answer that turned out to make the biggest
This is sort of one of these early indications of something is changing
For years the military men have had almost unquestioned Authority
To choose whatever path for Fighting the War they wanted to know matter what happened
But now
How many people have died in so many disasters in so much of the same tactic seeming to
You know equal the same results except more body stacking higher and higher that there was push back now from civilian leaders
Lloyd George and Britain is one of these guys who
Who says openly that my job is to protect the soldier in the field
And to the soldier in the field of General his biggest enemy sometime
And you could hear all this talk about the stupidity of the military leaders even Churchill kind of goes out of his way to say that the
Military experts were all against
The solution that ended up solving the subproblem
It was a civilian leaders for the most part that pushed the idea that one the day
The idea was both breathtakingly simple
And Incredibly complex
The idea was Convoy
The grouping of ships into large
Formation
Surrounding them with warships and escorts and sending these large bodies of ships across
Organize times and schedules
The military man off and believe that this was just going to group your targets
For the submarine
Make it even easier to line ships up like in the shooting gallery
When it was experimented on again the civilian leaders pushing to experiment with this
The results were fantastic
Almost right away
But you about that approach these kinds of formations often got sunk
The idea that it was going to be easier to spot
Fifty or sixty ships on the water rather than a single ship turned out to not be true in the in the vast spaces of the Ocean Beach
Eagle convoys got
Swallowed up to and is Churchill said
When these convoys made it across the water and slipped through the blockade instead of having one ship make it through the German blockade you had 40
5460 ships do
By October 1917 of 99 convoys heading to Great Britain
With more than 1500 ships in them
Only 10
We're still part of the Convoy we're song
14 more
It's training.
Lottery
Those are
Easily replaceable losses
And by October 1917 it was clear
The Germans were no longer going to be able
The sink
More shipping
The new British
Could replace
What's more
They now have us ship
We aren't helping to replace the
As you might imagine
The whole decision on
Germany
To engage in this
Can a submarine
Walker is one of the most if not the most criticized
Decision
The German leadership ever
Understandable
You know what kind of once again puts the lie to
The stereotype
Have the Germans as sort of a
Applauding methodical sort of
Conservative sort of leadership style
Because in both world wars
The Germans would prove to be great
Creek Camp
They just weren't lucky
But they were willing many times or so to throw caution to the wind and try these things
Innocence though it's a defense mechanism when you are the weaker party
Mean to me the analogy that works best in that in the war
That that we have going right now is to weight-lift
Are competing against each other and one of these weightlifters is bigger and stronger than the other
One which is obviously a huge advantage in weight lifting
But it isn't everything
And the weaker weightlifter has to
Try
You need to make up for it with technique
And training
And will to win
And maybe
Give me some chances
That's Germany strategy for the
This war
And you know you're seeing so many aspects
I've changed
From the 19th century to the 20th century that you
Can point you in the story because that's really the theme when you look at
You in a big picture
Germany has transformed
In the recent
1916 the year before this time we're in now
I'm really in a old style
Monarchy with legislative in a balancing out to something that looks much more like a 20th century military dick
That doesn't happen overnight and it almost kind of happens because it needs to
The only way Germany has a chance in this war is to be
The technique man
And have the greater will to win all those things I said about the smaller weightlifter
Germany has to organize it
It's Society
More efficiently
Then the more powerful
Allied temp
If it's going to stand a chance in one of the things that happens is
When you get Hindenburg and ludendorff in there remember the 2 German Commanders
We talked about
This military team but
It's really only one day
Ludendorff
He takes on more and more the powers that in the twentieth century we see over and over again
In regions where you have one strong man who started his dictatorial control in the German start to try to organize their society
To make it more efficient
Like
You're being able to tell workers where they're going to work
In a controlling people down to that level because
As one
The German leader said
The goal is to turn Germany into one vast Munitions fact
To do that requires a sort of single-minded
Fitness and in a lot of power concentrated in one person
At this stage in the war that person is ludent
Hindenburg took over 1916
And the first thing they did was sort of doing an audit
Of how the war is going and what we're doing to fight it in the condition
And the first condition you notice when you take over the entire War
Is on the Western Front
You have about two and a half million men
Manning the barricades
The other side has a mouth
4 million man
And their numbers are increasing every month how do those trends
You have food riot
It's at home women
Fighting with police officers in the streets
Because they can't get the food they need you have
Strikes in a bunch of the major firms in a bunch of the cities and they get so bad sometimes the Army has to be called in
To disperse the strikers
So the government is now going in and sending strike leaders to the front to get him out of the way mean the society is under
Severe stress and we already talked about the food
I mean there's a quote
From Ice glaciers
Sums it up when he talks about this
Is Pure Eatery now he quit he says quote
Soon alluded ham thrilled us more than the fall of Bucharest or some apparent success elsewhere
And quote
These people's knees are shrunk down to the most basic human survival level
Yeah great we took Bucharest but did you see that ham we have in the cellar that we found I mean you know
Something any of us could understand
The star
The pressure is on Germany's military leaders
Get to do something you can't very well launch an offensive on the Western Front when you're outnumbered the way you are you going to be lucky to survive at all
1916 was terrible for the Germans on the Western Front
So you launch the submarines
That becomes
Your chance to win the war without having to
Do the Imposter
On the Western Front
Now ludendorff
Is a very strange
Is Commander Germany you'll sort of in more everyday
In the story
Hindenburg is partner with the Charisma guy
He's a old man he really if he have been great at one time in his life
He's in his dotage now
He's he's the revered public-facing is governed by ludendorff the guy behind the scenes
And we talked about him and he's the one who way back in 1914 got that City in Belgium
To surrender by banging on the front doors with the hilt of his sword
You know when he easily could have been killed walk right up to the front door
Loan guide I mean that he's an interesting guy
He's flawed in a lot of ways and
Depending on what your story and you grab you're going to hear that
The bumbling psychologically fragile ludendorff or you're going to see this this great Gambler who
Who was who was fantastic at certain things and remember all these generals are 19th century man
They're adapting Under Fire
At a quick Pace to all these new conditions
And just when you think they're getting it
Some new develop
And comes around maybe you're starting to understand the physics of land Warfare a year or two into the first world war of your general
And then tanks appear and then gas appears every what do you do with all this airplane start having a real impact
You don't just have to learn you have to be flexible to continue to evolve as these generals
Nobody's greater
Endorse not bad
Ludendorff changes
The basic strategy
The guy
Who came before
Von falkenhayn strategy was
Basically defend every inch of territory
Ludendorff is perfectly willing to give up territory in exchange for killing
He'll pull off things like operation Albury
Right about this time period start in late February 1917
Or he will
Holdback
Troops that are that are in an egg
Bose Lupin the line the line is a straight because of fighting here in there it's bulging out in some places lyrics
Kingston
And he begins in early 1917 to pull troops back there
Their way out there in no man's land and straighten up his line he'll cut off like 25 miles
From the Western Front by doing this
Freeing up 13 or 14 division is basically a German army
To be used elsewhere
Not too complicated maneuver
But his strategy in 1917 as far as he's concerned is going to be defense
So he's going to line things up and prepare for that and it gives him all kinds of advantage of this
Is one area
It'll be called the Hindenburg line
He puts together
It is hard to imagine making the defenses of 1916 deeper and stronger and more
Impenetrable but that's what they do in 90
June 17th the Hindenburg line is an example of
Who endorsed idea of Defense in depth
And what that means is it the German defenses go back
Jack Ma
And they're designed to act like a rubber band so that when something runs into them
He just stretches and stretches and stretches in the farther it stretches the more resistance you find
And then eventually just snaps back
Devious
The way it's designed and I don't need to get into all the details it's the machine guns on the barbed wire and the pill boxes and all these things but they
Just go far back into the distance and there's no more trenches anywhere near the front line
Because those are too easy to pick out and and she'll everybody just sort of sits in holes in the ground in a sort of a random Pat
There's no lie
In fact there's hardly any Germans when you first get to it
It's just a few Germans holding you up and taking casualties and then as soon as they can't keep you at Bay anymore they were three facts
The next line and then to the next line
And every step of the way the defenses are a little bit stronger and the Germans are a little bit more numerous
As the British or the French were attacking them are getting less
And less numerous
And then is there getting more tired of me I thought to myself
Some of these
Defenses go back 9:10 Mi it would kill me without any resistance
Imagine trying to do it
With machine guns
And rifle fire at
Grenades
Artillery I may just
You just can't imagine
Having much left if you even get the nine or ten miles to the end of the defenses and then waiting for you there
Are German army
We're going to counter attack anything that the last
That makes it all the way through these defenses
It is absolutely almost impenetrable and devious if you only have 2 and 1/2 2.8 million men
To fight four or four and a half million men on the other side
This is a good way to equalize the odd
This is a weightlifter who figured out a way to lift more
Denny's
Bigger opponent
My favorite
Part of the Hindenburg
Red line defense
Military history
Is that they build a giant
Moat
In front of it I mean there's no other way to
Pray that it's an absolutely perpendicular walls
Trench
That is between 9 and 10 ft deep
And 12 feet across
It's meant to stop every
Define tanks especially Amino fall into the air and won't be able to climb up the perpendicular side
But it's not an easy job
4 troops either end behind this
Giant
Mold as you might imagine our machine gun positions and all kinds of defenses and more wire and all these sorts of things
It is crazy to think about having to attack something like
And what's more when ludendorff has
People
Retreat
SWTOR the Hindenburg line and give up these positions
The hundreds
Thousands of Germans who died
Contesting over the last couple of years
He has soldiers destroyed
Everything
You know as they go
Creating a dead zone from the old front line to the new one
Scorched-earth policy
Something which by the way upset
Crown Prince Rupert
Who was the field-marshal commanding some of the troops you had to do this destruction
He was so upset he almost resigned over it
And complained about it how this was Germany's reputation and in that discussion you basically ca19
18th century a figure with 19 century standard Crown Prince Rupert
Break the member of the Bavarian
Royalty and
Ludendorff a thoroughly
20th century Total War kind of guy
It's a clash of cultures
The 20th century 1 ludendorff got his way
And the troops of the German Army in a very old
School style
Began creating a dead zone
In this part of France in front of the Hindenburg line and a dead zone that extended in some places 20 mi
German Soldier Ernst Junger
Was there watching the destruction take place
And he Compares it to a kind of lunacy
Image
It's funny because if you think about people doing this in the second world war you think about them using mostly explosives and there were explosives used
To create this dead zone but Germany needed her
And so a lot of this stuff was done by hand
And younger says it had a bad effect on the troops and he also blame some of it on
What he calls
Economic Times we live in
Or something like that and what he really means by that is this
Total War 20th century sort of mentality
Younger rights
About passing through this dead zone
Being created by the German Army as it moved
Backwards
Towards its main line
And quote
The villages we passed through on our way had to look a vast lunatic asylum
Whole companies were set to Knocking or pulling down walls
We're sitting on rooftop
Uprooting the tiles
Trees were cut down
Windows smashed
Wherever you looked clouds of smoke and dust Rose from Bath piles of debris
We saw men dashing about wearing suits and dresses left behind by the inhabit
With top hats on their head
With destructive cunning they found the roof trees of the houses
Fixed ropes to them and then with concerted shouts
Hold until they all came tumbling down
Others were swinging pile driving hammers
And went around smashing everything that got in their way
From the flower pots on the window sills two-hole ornate Conservatory
As far back as the siegfried line that's what the Germans called the Hindenburg
Every village was reduced to Rubble
Every tree chopped down every road undermine every well poisoned every basement blown up orb
Booby-trapped
Every rail unscrewed every telephone wire rolled up everything burnable burned in a word
We were turning the country that are advancing opponents would occupy
Into a wasteland
As I said he writes
The scenes were reminiscent of a madhouse
And the effect on the men with similar
Half bunny half repellent
They were all so we can see right away
Bad for the men's morale and honor
Here for the first time I witnessed wanton destruction that I was later in life to see 2xs
This is something that is unhealthily bound up with the economic thinking of our age
But it does more harm than good to the destroyer and dishonors the soldier
And quote
And it should be remembered that this isn't a war damage
Country this this area that they're pulling apart now in creating a dead zone was an idyllic part of France it wasn't touched
By The Wharf you weren't right on the front in the first world war especially in the Western Front
Things were great behind
One of the complaints French soldiers on leave happy as you can get
20 or 30 miles behind the front line and everything is like there's not even a war going on
You know they see men with their sweethearts prowling around going to restaurants for dinner
In a town 30 miles from the front and it's like it's another world
So they're tearing down these beautiful
Parts of France
To create this dead zone they're destroying every
And then
They're leaving booby traps
Because when the Germans give up their position
They're going to retreat as I said sometimes 20 miles in this one area
All the way back to the main line
The
Allies are going to follow them when they follow them they're going to run into these town when they run into these towns
They're going to run into and younger talked about it earlier booby
Traps here's what he said quote
Among the surprises we prepared for our successors
Horsham truly malicious inventions
Very fine wires almost invisible
We're stretched across the entrance of buildings and shelters
Which set off explosive charges at the faintest touch
In some places near Road ditches were dug across roads
And shells hidden in them
They were then covered over by a large
Plank and Earth
Screen over them
A nail has been driven into the plank only just above the shelf
The space was measured so that marching troops could pass over the spot safely
But the moment the first trucker field gun rumbled up the board would give in the nail which off the shell
Where there were spiteful Timebomb
They were buried in the basements of undamaged building
They consisted of two sections with a metal partition going down the middle in one part was explosive
Any other asset
After these Devils eggs
He called them have been primed in Hidden the acid slowly over weeks
Eroded the metal partition and then set off the bomb
And quote
British reporter Phil
Untrue some of these towns right after younger and his men and vacated them
And Allied Forces moved in
And give talks about all those same kinds of
Booby trap
And then says this quote
Only a few of our men were killed or blinded by these monkey tricks
Are Engineers found most of them before they were touched off
But one went down dugouts are into ruin houses with a sense of imminent danger
All through the devastated region one walked with an uncanny feeling of an evil spirit left behind by the
The masses of men whose bodies have gone away
Exuded from scraps of old clothing
He was in the stench of the dugouts and in the ruins that they have made
And quote
Booby-trapped
Dead zone
Ludendorff is a fully
20th century
Total War
Commander
And this is a big mood this is pulling a big rabbit out of a hat and it's
You know if you were military history fan like I am
What makes ludendorff so interesting
Not a lot of generals would pull disc
Kind of stunt
It was a game-changer in many respects I mean that hold dead zone for example
Proved to be a huge problem
For British and French forces to try to overcome
They move into this
Cratered
Destroy denuded area where even the wells have been poisoned how do you even
Supply that
The Germans on the other hand and move to sites they been working on
4 months
Some parts of the Hindenburg line of had a half a million workers working on it for months and months and months
And building a new Frontline from scratch like building a new home it was now move in ready they move back
I can do it and there are railroads bringing supplies up to the back
What ludendorff
Was wrong foot
The Allies he stole the night Marchi
Seize the initiative he changed
Their plans
It's for 1917 without knowing what their plans were
Assembly figured if I do this all the planning they've been doing for months
Will be obsolete
They're planning to have mito
20 miles
Closer to Paris than I am
If you were an Allied General how would you deal with it
And if you said you don't want to deal with this problem at this looks like an impenetrable nightmare that just puts you in League
With those military thinkers at the time who were known as Eastern
These people who thought
Hacking on the Western Front was insane
Look at the defenses who would do that
Prime minister Britain Lloyd George is one of these guys
Here's the thing though
You can always find generals and Military Commanders
Who no matter how
Impossible the military task looks
Will be optimistic about explaining to you how their play
Plan will overcome
After all
People don't get those jobs by explaining how they
Hantover
Here come the enemies
Defenses
We told you earlier that
The French soccer
Their military leader that they've had since the beginning of the war Joseph chakra
Any sort of going to kick him upstairs
And before they do they have another one of those yearly meetings were all the allies
Russians in the British in the French and all the other allies they get together they have this meeting and they try to coordinate next
Deers military plan
So that when
The British in the French attack on the Western Front the Russians at the same time attack on the east in the Italians attack in the South and everybody's pushing in
Multiple directions all at once portion the Germans to
You know
Maybe break some
I mean the Central Powers at this point of liking
Eggs
And as soon as you can break into any one of their sides east west north south I mean you feel like the war
Will be over
But they're all holding steady
The most commanders are looking at the Western Front and say but nothing is a steady is that
Must we attack it
The friend should always believe yes you must
Course they're a little biased because the Germans are on their soil and they would like to
Does he even pushed off
When Joseph jafra
Is Aspen Lake 1916 at the big meeting
What are we going to do in 1917 what's the plan Jennifer tells him his plan is a repetition of the song the battle that was
Just wrapping up the battle that was so horrible for British and even for French forces
Going to wear the Germans down in in in a several months long battle that forces them to throw in the last of their resources
French politicians were horrified
The last thing they wanted is about a like that because as far as they were concerned
How did anybody know that it wouldn't be the French Nation
The true in all their resources in men
This is part of the reason is I forgot
Kicked upstairs
Different politicians
Just like British politician
They were starting to do the unthinkable
In terms of 19th century attitude
They were starting to interfere with military decisions because they were losing faith that
The people making the military decisions
How to write priority
The politicians
Wer
Worried
About the casualty
One of the big criticisms especially from the soldiers in the field
Is it the generals weren't
The guy who gets the job is the main allied military commander 1970 we mentioned earlier
Is a guy named Robert nivelle
Annabelle gets this job because he's the guy out there
Optimistic about victory
Remember generals do not get hired
Promising to not overcome the enemies
Fences so there's an ingrown bias in the whole process
The Robyn Adele
Tells the French leadership
When he takes over that you don't have to have another bottle of the song you don't have to have a grinding months-long battle
You can have a lightning bolt
Hammer stroke
It just ends the war
In
48 hours
Now it sounds crazy doesn't know where a bunch of French
General some of whom
Nouvelle leapfrogged over
How they were guys who probably deserve the job at least 3 maybe 4
More than development eval was this
He's a
Charmer
He's he's one of these people that can win anyone over
He's not winning over these jealous General he leapfrogged but there's a lot of politicians that are sold
When your bowel
And some of them aren't even French
Novelle has this great advantage over the other French
Military leaders
He speaks English
Repeat perfectly speak sit without an accent
Is Mother's Day
So he's a charmer to begin with
Kind of a Salesman but people like him he doesn't feel slimy or sleazy
He sort of an optimist
And he goes over to Brittany wins over even the
Archie Sterner
Lloyd George
It was in there and explain to the British exactly how this
Plan to rupture the Enemy Lines will work
And it involves creating a reserve
2728 divisions that are going to be like the spider in the web
And as soon as the Germans are held in certain places and weekend and then this 27 divisions will go get him and it's going to take
48 hours
And
Like any good salesman offering some of the money back guarantee
There's a guarantee guarantee that nibbled tells everybody
Is if it doesn't work in 48 hours will call it off.
Now that's a promise to get rid of the part of these battles that's most troubling to people who care about dead people
A lot of the Dead
Unless you have just tragic first day is like the battle of the Somme fought in the battle of the Frontiers
A lot of the deaths
Happened because he's battled one for months and you could end up after 48 hours if you had a chance to see is it working or not working call it off it's now
Not working that takes a lot of the risk out of it and you can see why politicians would like that plan a lot more than Joseph opera singer
Let's have another
For 5 months long battle
The problem is
In hindsight is everyone knows
Nouvel was working on a on an idea
It might not have been tenable
Annabelle made his name at the Battle of Verdun at the very last stages of
When the Germans were being pushed back in the other direction
There's a lot of historical debate over whether or not anything
Novelle did
Was effective
But even if it was affected it was effective at a very very low-level to all the sudden be the military leader in charge of not yet
All of France's forces
What kind of Britain's forces to who he will Clash developer clash with Britain's Commander Douglas Haig
They do not like each other the egos of generals are proverbial anyway
At least you guys were fighting about
Will create problems between Britain and France's allies
MLS novellas the most powerful
Military commander on the Western Front he's never come in at 4
Is first real problem happens
When the Germans pull this
Operation outbreak end
Disappear
Remind me a little of the British getting away at Gallipoli
And fooling the Turks at the Turks didn't know that they'd laugh
David Yurman
Is kind of pulled back
From this Giants aliens and wait for
For the British to find out they're gone
And I love the way it starts by the way starts with
With the British looking out over there trenches and seeing the German trenches
Beanshell
And then coming to the realization that the German trenches and that they'd get there
Facing off against there being shelled by German
And it's a German artillery
Blowing up the trenches in destroying everything of value in it and then destroying the trenches so the British can't move up into the menus
And then of course
Probing
It must have been Erie
There were like single Germans left behind a shooter rifle off every now and then it just keep the Allied armies from pursuing to claw
Mostly
But once it was
What year that the Germans were pulling back into miles an miles church I said like 50 miles every place I rented more like 20 at the
The farthest
But nonetheless
To pull back that far means your military maps are all different
The place
Let the hammer blow in nipples offensive was going to fall
Is the place ludendorff just make hate it
Okay so as ludendorff probably intended
You got to change your plans don't you
You mean conditions on the ground a chain
Ennavale said I don't have to change my plans this all helps
What's my goal
And this is where everything starts to fall apart in this
Plan and yet at the same time you can see
How
These are such
Huge Affairs involving so many months of preparation so much momentum
But even if you find out
Near the beginning of the of the battle that things have changed
There's a momentum that you can't really even
Stop in this case everything starts going wrong for me Bell before the whole Battle Star
None of us before Nemo part of the battle
Starts
The campaign
It's sort of a diversionary campaign designed to
Make the Germans move away from where niveles going to attack
Start that's the part of this campaign
It involves
The British
And the Dominion Force
It happens
I'm next to the French position at a place called
Iris
And at this battle for at least
A few days
Everyone gets a chance to
Sissy
Exactly how you would go about
Striking defenses as Invincible as the Germans
And it looks a lot
Like world
World War II
And you know several history is it pointed out that by the end of the first
For the armies are Proto
Second world
War armies
There are certain battles know during the war where you can say aha
There is a big step for
Forward towards that second World War
20th century
In a style of fighting
That's what the Battle of arras is known
In the grand scheme of things as we said
This is the spring offensive this is what the Allies do every year right the weather gets good in Spring we launch an offensive
The British and the French launched one together with a launch one in tandem the Italians do as we said many launching everywhere the Russians
This is the Big Spring offensive
The British part is the sort of diversion as we said and yet they're going to pull this off
Initially
So well
They're going to show everyone
What 20th century combined arms
Warfare looks like including Eric
The amount of
Coordination no
Have to come off
Correctly to make this work
And it can't be maintained
But for the short period of time they're able to make it work
The British show you that
Modern combined-arms Warfare
Can devastate the static
Defenses
Here's a way historian Peter
Describes
The many things that were starting to come together that could be Unleashed at at rosson house scientific and modern 20th century
This profession of arms is really becoming
He writes quote
Many lessons have been learned from the song
An artillery was at the heart of the plan
And the Royal artillery and come a long way since 1915
The thousands upon thousands of new recruit to learn their trade well
The gun detached
The layers the NCO the officers were all now wedded into efficient batteries
They were capable of increasingly sophisticated and complex bombardment
The guns themselves without plaintiff
Anywhere vast numbers of medium and heavy artillery pieces joining the masses of ordinary 18-pounder and
4 1/2 inch Howitzer field artillery
Advances in technology and science
Also combined to give a greater understanding of the mechanics of a shell in flight
And the measurable adjustments caused by different meteorological conditions
Accuracy was improved
And the Advent of the 106 fuse
Mented shells would burst instantaneously on the slightest contact
Switchmate clearing barbed wire in great deal simpler
Smoke shells were also now routinely incorporated into the barrages to try to mass be attacking infantry from
German Defenders
Gas shells were a key part of the garage
And they were less visually dramatic than the clouds of gas released from cylinders
But they were far easier to deploy
And much more predictable in their effects
Progress in the linked tasks of photographic reconnaissance and artillery observation allowed targets to be
He identified and then destroyed by indirect fire
New techniques are flash spotting and sound ranging also assisted in locating the exact positions of German
Batteries
And quote
Demond coordination of
Come off correctly to make the stop work
Is astounding and it shouldn't be surprising that it usually does
What makes a Roth difference is that in some cases it did
Paper example
The creeping barrage
The creeping barrage is a fantastic
Military Innovation and they've been trying to make it work before
Dispatch
In this battle they got it right
In this battle they were able for a while to create
Protective
Explosive force field
Around British troops
The way it work as you would get
Town of guns anywhere from several hundred to more than a thousand
Firing
Giant
Cannonades
In front of your advancing forces
Creating a wall of explosions in front of them
And you have it coordinated everybody would have their
Winner watches synchronized in the troops will be told okay in the first
20 minutes you are to move
You know a hundred yards forward
And at this time the barrage will shift another hundred yards in front of you so this is all worked out so that
You know the protective barrage supposed to keep the troops safely and as they Advance toward the enemy
And the very last step of course is the barrage will land right on the enemy
And then it will lift at the last second in the enemy will look up in the British forces will be right there standing in front of them
Having March the whole way
With a giant explosive force field protecting
As you might imagine
Coordination is critical
You screw this up in one of two things happen
The better thing
Is that the garage gets way ahead of the troops and they're exposed to all the machine-gun fire and all the stuff the garage was supposed to protect them
That's the good part that's the best outcome
The worst outcome is that the garage is short
And that giant explosive wall That's supposed to protect you from the enemy instead
Decimate
When it works
It's fantastic
The Battle of arras it works
Initially
Tell me a bunch of Innovations
Another one again
It's been tried before but never quite like this is whole batteries
Submachine gun
Will be used
What's called indirect
Fire meaning they Point them up to the sky
So that the bullet end up falling
You know right straight down on targets you can shoot over Hills
Not even seeing what you're shooting at is one historian
Explain it apply hosing down
An important piece of
In ground they would have
Thousands of machine gun bullets
Falling every second on some of these
Important Road
Crossings and whatnot
All through this
What are the important elements at the start of the battle
Is that
So many of the troops that are going to initially rushed
The German side are underground
At the start of the
There's a lot of Chucky ground in this part of France and like a lot of these battles
There will be a ton of digging
In fact for months the Germans and the British on both sides of had sort of a
Tunneling War
And occasionally in a British tunnels toward the German front
Run into German tunnelers going the other way and they had these terrible gunfights in the dark underground you know like
Troglodyte
Some sources say that the moment the actual Ground Battle
Adam Ross started
Some of these tunnels have gone up all the way to the German lines but just
Couple of feet
Separated them
From the German trench lines and that
At the Second Battle started exploded
Charges in those those
Little walls of dirt blew down in the Canadiens
Storm32 breaches it doesn't matter what
Exactly happened
The Canadian storm. Vimy Ridge now and took it
On the first day
Arrange that
Untold numbers are Frenchmen had died trying to take
Back in 1950
It's a huge Canadian
And the Germans were in terrible trouble for a short while
At the Battle of arras by the way it's not you they get a lot of credit and deservedly so
But there were Scotsman for example up on the same Hill
Dealing with all kinds of problems
And yet
For the first 24 hours
It looked like Douglas hang the British commander
Was going to have on his hands the long-awaited much
Fantasized about in his head breakthrough
Ludendorff writes in his diaries that it was a
A dangerous moment and then and then lamented the fact
The here this brand-new defense-in-depth system he come up with with all this working all this money spent was apparently useful
Against these new British combined arms tactics
That was until he figured out
His commander on the scene a guy named Falcon housing
70 something year old guy
Hadn't quite figured out
What he was supposed to do
With these new tax
If they were still way too new
And he had done a bunch of things that were part of the old tactics he put all his guys for the most part way up front
Where they could be
You're taken by the artillery more than two and a half million British shells by the way if fired
In a shorter time than the battle of the Somme
And then he put his reserve That was supposed to be there to plug any holes
15 miles back too far to do anything in for a short. Of time it look like the British were going to break through at this battle
And then just like
All these other battles
It slows down
Once the troops Advance Beyond where their gunfire can help them
Then the guns behind them have to move to
And that takes
Time and everybody gets
Tired and I begin to wear out and while they're resting and rejuvenating cells for the next pushed the Germans arbre
Bringing up their Reserves
And the Battle of arras with this wonderful first day in his capture this important
Vimy Ridge
Turned into just another one of these battles
By the time it's over more than a month later
You have like a hundred and fifty thousand British casualties at like a hundred and thirty thousand German ones and by the way I found it
Interesting that the newer histories numbers of the casualties these battles is significantly higher than the older
I have some that say that 75000 British
Died at this battle
That's a big discrepancy in the number
The traditional numbers
Turn out today are well over a hundred thousand
All sides
The Joy over
Beanie was short-lived
And what happened at this battle what happened
And a bunch of other
First World War
It shows the difference between how well the first
Stay usually the first 24 maybe 36 hours of these
Minutely exquisitely planned encounters go
The part that's all been rehearsed
And trained for 4 months and months and months goes great and you're able to make the coordination work
But then the next jump
And wherever you are in these battles is a part that becomes much more improvisational
Much more ad hoc
You can't have a plan
In a month in advance for what you do on the second day of the battle cuz you're not really sure where you're going to be the second day
You may have some
But that doesn't mean that's what you're going to do when and as many historians point out when you look at the next
Jumps
In any of these offences they are so much more haphazard and all that coordination falls apart
But you don't see the wonderful results that that months of preparation gave you for 24 or 30
6 hours and yet you can't break through these kinds of deep defenses
In that short of a period of time you would have to have
The combined arms activity work as well as it did for the first 24 hours at a Ross
And be able to carry it through for a week or two
Nevertheless it was a near run thing
Gone down in history as a as a
Heroic encounter mostly for the Canadians the largest in Denver they participated in yet on the Western Front
And I always have to remind myself
You know you look at this in an almost
A field Marshal type fashion when you study this for military history you see it the way the General's office
These advancements on these Maps what worked and what didn't another coordination question that the technical side of War
Do we have to remember that when I was try to remind myself
Do the people on the ground this is not so technical
Philip Gibbs
Was there
He was in the tunnels
With the troops as they came back
From these encounters up on Vimy Ridge and places
Like that
Gives gives you a real
A feel for what it was like
He writes quote
There were tunnels beneath the roster which are men advance to the German lines
And I went along the one one line of men was going into battle and another was coming back
Wounded
Some of them blind
Bloody
Vomiting with the fumes of gas in their lungs
Their steel hats clinking as they grow past one another
Involves on each side of these passages Men played cards on Barrel to the light of candles stuck in bong
I slept until their turn to fight
With gas mask for their pillow
This is outside the Citadel meaning of the city
There were long queues of wounded men taking their turn to the surgeon
Who were working in a deep
Crypt with a high vaulted roof
One day there were three thousand of them
Silent
Patient muddy blood-stained
Blind Boys are men with smashed faces swapped and bloody Rags groped forward to the dark Passage
Just leading to the vault
Led by comrade
On the grass outside lay men with leg wounds and stomach wounds
And quote
Norman Collins
Is an officer with the
Scottish forth
Seaforth Highlanders
There they are two
And Collins just tells the
Stories that
Remind you of
The very strange moral position
These kinds of
Put you in
Collins talks about
The fact that they were actually shown
How to
Kill
One of their own men on the battlefield
Because of the
Pain and suffering that they were enduring
And this isn't specific to this battle
This happened on the battlefield
Throughout the first World War
In basically every Army
And I got caught in these conditions he's our human problems the physics of humankind on the 20th century battlefields
The results are
Predictable
Horrifying
And
Pitiable
Collins rights quote
After such an intense fighting you always had men lying out in no man's land
Probably with their testicles blown off and crying in agony and laying out there all night long in the dark in the rain
Most would never have survived
But you had a choice
They could die in agony or you could shoot them
You were showing how to do the thing very cleanly
You would take your 45 revolver and talk to the man
And you behind him and whilst you were talkin pull the trigger
Put a bullet through the back of his head and immediately the whole front skull came away and they were dead instantly
There was no pain about it
But I can honestly say this
But I never had the courage because that's what it took
I never had the courage myself to shoot a wounded soldier
I carried out the operation many times afterwards on animals
I could kill a pet dog far better than a vet could
But I was never able to shoot a wounded soldier
I probably should have
My friend Auto Marie Dixon was wounded in the stomach
Can the IRS attack in April he was in great Agony from what I was told
The kindest thing would have been to shoot him on the battlefield
Instead of that they took him back to the hospital when he died days later
It's a tremendous thing to shoot a friend
Even though he's in agony and I just didn't have the courage to do it
Most of them died overnight
And of course they didn't thank you for it I'm sure
And quote
There are battles coming up
Were the numbers of pi
People
Who are either shot by their own men
Or beg to be
Will Skyrim
Nonetheless
This battle
Was tough enough
The initial stage is a relation to take
Vimy Ridge
Became
Nightmarish as the month when Dawn
And
The casualties piled up
Before long the British were suffering 4000k
Please add a
I was getting to the morale
The troops
Games tales of
The story
About arriving on a scene
Right after a bunch of men just behind the front have been blown up in their bath together
Weather in the bathroom
Stream with body parts in Blood and he
And a soldier he knows sits down to talk about
You know how things are going
And the soldier is clearly at the end of his rope as far as what he's willing to put up with
He writes quote
A few minutes before our meeting a shell had crashed into a bath close to their Hut women were washing themselves
The explosion filled the bath with blood and bits of Flesh
The younger officers stared at me under the Tilt forward of his steel hat and said hello Gibbs
I play chess with him a groom's Cafe in Fleet Street in days before the war
I went back to his hot and had tea with him
Close to that back
Hoping we should not get cut up with the cake
And quote
Now
This battle is I said he's known for how wonderfully competent
The integration of all the different elements were to make this battle so effective
That's not how the guy on the ground sees it though
Gabe says that his friend he's
Having tea with says quote
I had heard before some harsh words about our generalship and staff work
But never anything so passionate
So violent is from that Gunner officer
His view of the business was summed up in the word murder
He raged Against The Impossible order sent down from headquarters
Against the brutality with which men were left in the line week after week
Head against the Monstrous
Abominable futility of all our so-called strategy
His nerves were in rags as I could see by the way in which his hands shook
When you lighted one cigarette after another
His Spirit was in a flame of revolt
Against the misery of his sleeplessness
Bill and imminent Peril of death
And quote
British reporter Philip Gibbs
Thinks that that's a high level of disc
Content and perhaps in the British army it is
You want to see what's going on
French army
At about the same time
In France a great drama
Is unfolding
During this time
Because right before these offences are scheduled to start
The French government
And new political leaders take
President a new war minister all the civilian leaders of change
Any civilian leaders have a very different attitude towards this offensive that's about to start
And the people they see
Succeeded
This causes huge problems the first thing is they're not big fans of nivelle
I joined the club there a lot of people have wonder why this
This guy got the top
Job when there were several
In a superior figures really August people
Who could have gotten a p'tan Falls people like that we're sitting in the wings and they gave it to a much more Junior
Person but but for political reasons
Keep it that last government
Anyways that we're good for that last government but now that last government was gone in the new one that comes into power
Would have rather had any one of those other
What's more they don't like is playing
Is ideal for this great Thunderbolt assault with all this artillery that's going to end the war in 48 hours they're not buying it
Lot of people are by the way a lot of people are drinking
The Robert nivelle Kool-Aid
And getting into this optimistic mood about this Thunderbolt ending the war
But the new government
Pretty sure that that's not what's going to happen
And they've got some people who Oughta Know sending the messages
Warning
There are other military commanders in France were saying call this thing off
Going to be a disaster
Some of them are people who are actually subordinate to Nevada and who have
Jobs to do
In this coming offensive
That's scaring the government as you might imagine
This is all part of this
Growing
Interference
Politicians in the Affairs of generals in this is one of those times
Were there sort of a Faceoff
The meeting is called
Between the new war minister and Novelle
In late March in the new war minister wants to convince the Bell to call this whole offensive off
Almost impossible thing to do is we said earlier about
The stages where you're just
Finishing the last touches
Ready to go it's taken months and months the training in the rehearsals in the money spent
And all this stuff and now the government the civilian leaders who don't know anything about war
Any general
Want to call it off
My reputation
Remind me to get a lot of personal motives
And the war minister has some good argue
He tried to tell him look
Everything's changed
Since you first formulated
To reevaluate
German
Hold back
From
Their old positions to be new position on the Siegfried line another place is right
There's one big change
But not just that
The war minister tries to make the case
All of these
Big events are happening right now these Trends coming together everything we talked about
On this day
Program up to date
Are coming
The four
At the same time
In late March when the war minister talking to the veil about this
The United States is just about to get in the war and everyone knows
The Russian Revolution has just happen
The submarines
Are about to
Enter into the month with a sink 840000 tons of Allied Shipping
There's alot going on
And Frances war minister
Surprise to tell
No one's going to hold you I mean Everything's changed maybe we should re-evaluate Annabelle says no
The government gets even more desperate as the
Offencive nears
And
Precious him and he
Polls to take away car
He says to the government either you back me on this ride resign
And everything I've read says that this is a crisis
The French
For all sorts of internal reasons
It was likely to bring the government down if they
They fired the veil right before his offensive was supposed to take hold
And everyone bought into the optimism and drank the Kool-Aid
That almost no choice in this confrontation
Politicians and Generals
And the government back down
But it was even worse than the government knew
Because the Germans knew
All about
Novella
Plans in detail
Two major incidents
I want involving captured documents that never should have been anywhere near the front lines that the Germans got their hands on it
Andrade
And the officer that they captured were able to find out more the Germans knew all about
The French plan
When they were going to take place and what was going to happen
And they had known in general 4 months
Air reconnaissance
And told him I mean these giant Affairs are like giant Supply dump that go on for miles and miles and miles it's very difficult to keep
Keep the enemy from finding out about it
And in January the Germans had about nine divisions opposite
Niveles
Armies
By the time the bells about to launch his attack
The Germans have 48
And they're waiting
And it's a disease
Storing hold you heard that right
Lights quote
After several delays due to foul-weather Novelle on 16th April unleashes artillery for 9 days
And then mounted is infantry charge in driving rain
Reports from agents in French pows
I chipped the Germans off to the coming offensive
Given the news of the offensive in the difficulty of the terrain
The Germans were able to Halt the main attack
Before Agape on their first line
Where is Novelle had forecast a penetration of seven or eight miles on the opening day the French rarely advance
More than one or two MI
Bosses were horrendous
Whereas navale head coldly predicted 10000 casualties for the first day the number was 10 x braids
After the war the historical service of the French general staff placed casualties for the first 4 days of the offense
At 30000 killed
100000 wounded
And 4000 missing
And quote
The story of what
Is a wonderful
Demonstration
How many things can go wrong when you're trying to synchronize everything so carefully
Start with the weather
Just like a Terraza week before the weather was bad
You know who has snow during a spring offense
But that's what the french face sleet snow rain
Creating mod
Slow the progress of the Infantry which has been calculated precisely to keep up with the
Explosive force field of the creeping barrage which this guy in the valid pioneered back in Verdun
But never on this kind of scale and in this case
The
Memorize the forcefield got way ahead of the troops
Exposing the truth
To just
Unbelievable amounts of machine gun
Fire there's one part of this front
Where the French have to
Travel forever
To take this
You know height in the distance in an in this Ridge they
Determined
Cut all these little holes into the side of it
To add to The Ravines and the gorgeous and everything that are already in it and stuff machine guns into every hole
Did you can fit into this Hillside
It got about 4
Thousand of them trained on this French infantry trying to
You crossed this space
At arras and here
You know when you read the history books
They sound like relatively productive First World War battles cuz
The soldiers actually take quite a bit more ground than they did in the earlier battles but that's sort of deceiving
Because this is all part of the new German strategy
This defense-in-depth where the Germans aren't supposed to fight to the death ball up on the front lines now and not giving into brownish supposed to fight
Two reasonable degree and then retire to the next line
So they're letting the enemy have more ground they're just killing more of them while they retreat
The French actually Stumble Inn
To these
First-line areas and think that they're winning cuz they're just not finding that many German
And then the Germans open up on them from the second
As you might imagine
A government that has been assured
That they'll call this thing off in 48 hours
And I was going to try to
Cash in on that guarantee
They actually gave Novelle an extra day on his 48-hour
Promise here's how writer Gigi Meyer
Scribes
A situation where the
Politicians come to the general
And tell him to call the whole thing off now
You guaranteed it wasn't going to be another song you guaranteed we're going to win the war with this Thunderbolt
And here's what my rights
Quote
On April 19th
3 days out
Attack starts
The war minister intervene
Trying to get nivelle to stop
The general who in demanding approval of his grand plan had promised to call it off if a breakthrough were not achieved Within
In 48 hours refuse
The very next day he found a histogram however that he had no choice but to pause
The divisions at the front we're breaking down
Both their morale and their supplies of ammunition dangerously low
Late on the day after that April 21st a new phenomenon appear
And quote
John Keegan among other
Historians
Going to Great Lengths to point out
How there's an accordion like backup
The begins
Once the timetable isn't held to strictly when the when the front elements of these French forces get bogged
Down everything behind it gets traffic jam
Recorded Louie Bartos of friendship Corporal in the story several times
And Bartos is at this battle but he never sees anything he gets stuck in one of these traffic jams and as far as
You know something's going on a mile or two in front of him but he doesn't ever get there to find out what it is
The soldiers who find out what it is though
Begin to
React as one might imagine from the horror and in this case the tip of the
Spear in one of these areas
Are French Colonial
The story of what hap
A2 British
Celeste Philip
Rights quote
Talking about the French
Gibbs talked about how the French were lured into
The lightly defended
First Zone
Only be attacked by the Germans in the second Zone
Rights quote
They were to be allowed an easy walk through to their death trap
That is what
The French infantry advancing with masses of black troops in the colonial core in the Frontline of assault
All exultant and inspired by a belief and Victory
Sweat through the forward zone of the German defenses
Astonished and then disconcerted by the scarcity of German
Until the Nile rating barrage fire dropped upon them and smash their human waves
From French officers and nurses I heard appalling Tales of this tragic
The death way of the black troops
Froze the blood of the Frenchman with horror
Their own losses were immense in a bloody shambles
And quote
The French Colonial Soldier
Which have been thrown into this
Disaster
Ran screaming back towards
Is there online
Yelling
Peace
Down with the war
Death to those who are responsible
And all of a sudden
The French army
Began to collapse
Traditionally
The nivelle offensive is seen as the straw that breaks the camel's back
French military
And it's ironic that it would be that way cuz if it's just judged
In relation to all the other French battles
NFL offensive is not terrible
The casualty bill is horrifying but pretty normal for these big battles and remember there's people being killed every day on
So-called quiet fronts
The British
Casualties every week to what they call wasted
Just living on the Western Front with snipers and bombs and
French braids and all that is 5000 people a week
So even between the big battles is horrible but in the big battle the numbers are astronomical by that standard
No sense is not that bad and they did gain
In a pretty decent amount of ground
3 miles and some places
But this was sold
In a completely different way the salesman Robert nivelle
So this is the Thunderbolt that wins the war everybody got to have this last push of optimism it and strength Andre
Resources in and gumption
To end the war and then we can all go home in the sufferings over
A lot of people drink the Kool-Aid and the crash after they drink the Kool-Aid was worse than if they never
Kool-Aid at all
All that optimism Boomerang back on the Val
Who started to try to recast the marketing just being 24 hours into the conflict was no longer talking about war winning
Thunderbolt he was talking about hey it's going very well
Modest gains in the sector in the sector and no one was buying the re-crafting of the marketing strategy
The French government now has a wonderful little drama on a tan
We're trying to get rid of novalis he won't go quietly
They put pathan
He was very competent
We talked about him earlier
In the Bells all job and they have a Face-Off and you see this wonderful again changing the guard between
Politicians kind of trying to
Assert their authority over the generals in this pushing tag on who's going to be the ultimate Authority
The one thing that the politicians have in their favor is that they're concerned about casualties and the generals appear to not be
He concerned about casualties and the people who are rising up in French units
Up and down the Western Front
Are very concerned about casual
NFL offensive
Traditionally
Is what kicks off water called
The 1917 mutinies with music
That's a weird charm and it makes it sound
Like one unit rebelles and then the rebellions eunos
Transfers like wildfire up and down the front and all these units are acting simultaneously if that it happened the war would have been over
What do you do to stop a rebellion or revolution when it's the Army that's rebelling about it happened it would have been all over end
The French government knew it and acted accordingly
Instead
You have to imagine a burning roof with the Embers
Everywhere you know going off into the wind and Landing all over the dry grass on the lawn
And you you know the French government is running around stamping out fires as they catch hold I mean as many as six of these units a day
Wer
Involved in as I said what the French called acts of collective and discipline which meant the whole wide range of thing
Sometimes it meant getting drunk as an entire unit and that was the end of that we're not going anywhere
Other times they just refuse to go up to the front
1in 1/4 decided to march on Paris and was talked out of that at the last minute
And a lot of this was
Tied to the Russian Revolution going on simultaneously
The French in the field
Saw that all of a sudden Russian soldiers maybe we're going to get out of fighting this war cuz they've somehow with the people acted together
Go after the people that were as Louie Bartels explained it enslaving them
Polly Barton
Who's the Socialist who would have used these happenings in petrograd in Russia
With great
Enthusiasm
Wrote this
Right around the Times the
Outbreaks of
Collective in discipline are happening in his army
Quote
But this time the Russian Revolution broke out
Those Slavic soldiers Only Yesterday enslaved and bent double under the weight of iron discipline
Unknowingly marched off to massacres like resign slaves had thrown off their yoke
Proclaim their Liberty and imposed
Peace on their masters there hangman
The whole world was stupefied
Petrified by this revolution this collapse
I'll be immense Empire the czars
These events had repercussions on the Western Front into route the French ranks
A wind of Revolt blue across almost all the regimen
And quote
Because I said it was an uneven sort of an affair
Sometimes it involved
Whole units large numbers of troops other times it was a decision made by single individuals alone
That they just weren't going to have their lives thrown into a meat grinder anymore
Historian Eric Dorn brose
Tried to give you a sense
The feeling when he write
Lights quote
Already on day 2 of The novella offensive 17 soldiers of one regiment left their post and went to the
The rear and then in May 30,000 infantrymen abandon the line
A junior officer recorded the scene at 1 Train Station receiving man who'd been rotated out of the line
Not roses quoting
And I Witness
And the eyewitness to the Troops
Getting away from the front
During this rebellious times as quote
As soon as the train enters
With what you would say a horde of savages all the doors open on both sides and Men flood out on the platform
Shout insults
And threats fly in all directions
Death to the sugars at-home murderers and pigs that they are long live the revolution down with the
War is peace we want Etc
Ambrose pics
Quote
The trouble spread the 68 of 112 divisions in the French army in June
He's reporting 125 mutinous incidents but no killing of officers
The rank-and-file demanded an end to further attacks
Better pay and living conditions
And more furloughs
And quote
John Keegan and a couple of other historians have an interesting way
Of describing this
This act of rebellion that was breaking out almost spontaneously although influenced by other breakouts all across and
Up and down the Western Front
He said it's like a labor strike
But the soldiers had just decided
That they weren't going to do certain things anymore
He said it wasn't defeatism it was defense ism
Meaning these soldiers were not going to let the Germans coming invade France they weren't going to abandon the line and they wouldn't stop
Fighting but they weren't going to be involved in any more of these offensives
Where a hundred thirty hundred forty hundred fifty thousand of them we're going to become casualties in a hopeless cause
Let's also remember that it didn't get to this point
Until the French army had suffered in three and a half years
About his many killed at the United
States has suffered in all its Wars put together
How would the United States
Today
A nation of 300 million France at about 39 or 40
Deal with 1.5 or 1.7 Million Dead in 4 years
Adjusted for population size I be more like seven seven and a half million somewhere around there
Can you imagine
Would you expect us to be hangover
Free for the rest of the century in terms of military affairs
The French had some lingering damage
Because of this
First World War
Anyone else would
It's amazing they got
Back on their feet at all
It's also sort of a Wonder for the Allied cause that the Germans are unaware of the
That somehow it's it's funny you have been developments of that everybody in Germany like talking about in the streets it's so well-known and yet
The French army starts falling apart and rebelling in the Germans don't know
If you were the French High command and you got your army
You know starting to catch fire like a bunch of
Rooftop Amber's that are falling on dry grass what do you do to stop that
You got to be very careful don't you
You give up too much it becomes like what the Russians are dealing with where you can't even have the troops
In order to round when they start electing their own little governing groups and they do what they want can't have that but if you cry
Crackdown to get all tough on them
You might spread the revolution it's a Daft
And
Terrible tightrope for the French government to walk
This new military leader that takes over for nouvelle pathan is considered to be sort of a soldier General so that helps
And you famously go around all these units
Speaking to them and actually promising and delivering some of the reforms they want
For example reforms on home leave
Food drink I mean there's a bunch of things that he can manage to
Perk-up in and take care of that help the troops
Piping on the front
At the same time
He has to show who still in charge this is still the military
Laws are broken
Discipline must be maintained
The French
Start a Crackdown in July 1917 they will court-martial almost 24,000 sold
Collective
LSU about 500 death sentences
They will actually carry out
But there's one thing to Tomcat
He cannot make this Army capable or willing or trustworthy
To go on another major offense
This is an army that have to regroup
Be rebuilt refortified Vuitton's going to do a historically famous Java this but it's going to take time and in the meantime
The number one thing that he gives to his troops that they were asking for cuz he's got no choice
Is it they're not going to be thrown into
Murderous hopeless offensives
Anytime soon
This leaves
The Western Front in any sort of offensive activity on it for the rest of 1917
To the British alone
The British commander Douglas Haig is fine with that
Cuz he has a plan
And you wanted to carry it out for some time and now that the French are not in his way
He cast
His
How much is a
On Ypres and the Belgian port
Yet again
Douglas Haig the British military leader
Once the British to launch an attack on the German defenses
Indulge
A titre
Where there's already been two battles
Sleep right in this war
You're already
Now hague's got a great Army to do this
British Army
In late 1917 mid 1917 is maybe the best Army in the war at this
It's taken years for the British
In a traditionally a c power to build up a land power
Goodbye July August 1917 they've done a great job of doing just that and its Millions
Strong
Anybody try to boot
Teague Army
When this war started very very fine and professional and volunteers but
But the boutique
What they have in 1917 are a bunch of mostly conscripts unfollows you to mostly conscripts they don't
Sing on their way to and from Battle anymore like in 1914 after the song that all stop these are a bunch of Grimm
Professional
Cooperate when
Deadly efficiency
I have a sort of a
I'm a real that's hard to do
Describe and they suffered a terrible
An ordeal the year before the battle of the Somme terrible lost a lot of fantastic people but came back with even more are
Artillery pieces here in 1917
In the hands of Hague and Hayden wants to use it in Belgium against the Germans
But there are people that think that's a stupid idea
And after several years of war when you've watched
You know the same thing happened over and over again in all these battles there are people that are going to push back they're starting to see some of these for
Political leader start
Question what the military is doing open
To their face
You know when we mentioned this earlier I don't want to insinuate that this never happens I mean Abraham Lincoln for example
Famously would argue with a Civil War General
But in some countries like Germany
Politicians in Germany
Do not interfere in military strategy
I need only
Just started doing that in France
With the collapse of the novella fences
Right it was in development of this would have brought them into
Saying are you sure we want to do something like this
Again
In Britain
I would think as a modern person reading the story and I think many of you probably thought the same thing
You're wondering why it took this long how many times can you lose hundreds of thousands of people
In what appeared to the non-military I to be very similar kinds of attacks
Maybe a little strange if there were more people questioning this in Britain there are
Led by the prime minister
Lowell George
Now George to be fair
Is viewed by history very similarly to the way Woodrow Wilson
It's almost as though
There's a good Lord George
And there's an evil Lloyd
Different histories will portray him differently
But taken at face value
Lloyd George presents himself
As the person who defends the soldiers
From The General
He says during this whole lead in
To whether or not he gets to have his Belgian defensive quote
The cabinet must regard themselves
As Trustees for the fine fellows that constitute our army
They're willing to face any danger
And they do so without complaint
But they trusted the leaders of the nation to see that their lives are not needlessly thrown away
Another not sacrifice John Muir gambles
Witcher resorted to merely because those who are directing the war
Can think of nothing better to do with the men under their command
It is therefore imperative
Before we Embark upon a gigantic attack
Which must necessarily hentel the loss of scores of thousands of valuable lives and produce that sense of discovery
Which might very well Rush Nations into premature peace
That we should feel the fair confidence
But such an attack has a reasonable chance of succeeding
Amir gamble would be both a Folly and a crime
And quote
I must confess
The to the modern Observer having just witnessed the several years previous of this war
You think yourself when you hear something like that
About damn time
But many modern historians Wonder
They wonder if Hague
Didn't have a pretty good feel for this thing
And that these politicians were barking up the wrong tree maybe for their own political purposes
Hagstrom makes it look like Lloyd George doesn't know what he's talking about
When he
Opens up an operation
On June 7th 1917
To take this
High Ground
But you need to take before you can have his Ypres.
It's called Messina rich
And the British had since 1915
Been tunneling under this 8 miles of Ridgeline
And planting explosives underneath
The incredibly deep and complicated German defenses up there who they were impenetrable
The British went underneath them
And the Germans knew they were doing some of this cuz they found one of them
But on June 7th 1917 when he decides he's going to take this High Ground
He starts off his attack
By blowing up
That 8 miles of Ridge lines with these munitions
There's more than a million pounds of explosives underneath those Hills
And when they blow up all within 28 seconds of each other
Supposedly
You could hear it in London
I've heard some people say it was heard
In iron
Thought to be the biggest man-made explosion before nuclear weapon
A vaporizer
10000 Germans insta
The second those
Minds are blown up
Thousands of British artillery pieces on the horizon open fire on the same line of ridges
And
The British
80000 of them who come out of their trenches and end March toward that High Ground have a pretty darn easy.
Time taking it
I first world war standard
I got always throw that in because
To the naked eye it still looks like a lot of people died but
My first world war standards that's a pretty darn good attack and once again it seems to show that the British have found the secret sauce
The magic formula of how the tanks in the artillery the aircraft and all work together perfectly and boom Messina Ridge taken
Not that much loss of life
Seems like he knows what he's doing
But before he gets approval for this battle Ade prelims pulling up the guns he's getting ready
Boy George and Company take him into a back room and make him kind of do a PowerPoint presentation
Britain civilian leader in Hague sort of grits his teeth and does it
Explains why it'll be a good thing
Your wife why we should be doing this and why it should be a walkover did you see that wonderful battle we just bought and took Messina Ridge
Hague will end up getting other generals and
Admirals
Just want to side with him against the political leadership there were always politicians who sided with them
Military professionals who leave things to them
Four guys like Churchill
Or Lloyd George who were the ones
Questioning military leadership they were very tough position can you imagine what risk they would have run
If they had overruled all their military professionals and then 200,000 guys get killed
In a battle
Which by the way is almost the default result of a lot of these battles
So you could pretty much be assured that that would happen if it happened to the generals oh well it just happened again.
General but if Lloyd George overruled all their generals and it happened because of him you can be sure
He would have been roasted
So predictably
Douglas he gets his offencive
He starts by
Starting a military bombardment of the area right around July 15th July 20th
Before the ground attack starts the British will shoot almost
4 million shell to just show you how the progression is going a year ago with the psalm we were all
Call saucer-eyed and so was the rest of the world at the time
When the British shut off a million shells before they started
Bad battle for this when they're shooting off almost 4 million you can see why Germany is concerned
With
Finding a way to turn the entire country into a Munitions Factory
The goal
On July 31st
The Ypres offensive
Very soon afterwards
So is the rain
It will be the rain that will give this battle
It's Unique standout Carey
And there are so many battles in the first World War
Sound the same
It only a few standout and it's always for some particular reason they become associated with something special you know an offer if
Take away the most casual
The most shells
I mean everyone knows
Verdun is the grade artillery meat grinder offense
The song is that
Horrible
Tragic
Situation would maybe tragic encompass
Brusilov offensive in the East is known for its scope
Passchendaele
Show me the British name for 30 / is known for its mod
And my doesn't sound like too terrible thing but when you think about living outdoors and fighting
Mud makeup
Terrible situation
And I don't want to suggest that just because this is probably the worst mud anyone has ever fought in the first World War
That mud has not been a problem for soldiers on other fronts and another battles
It's been sort of the bane of the existence for people especially in trenches
But nowhere is the mod like it is in flan
The soldiers fighting and it described it as having a consistency of porridge
Torchy's
There is no bottom
And you stink in it slowly
As you would in quicksand
There are a lot of people
Who died in the first two battles of Ypres by drowning
In addition
There is a complex
Very fragile system of dikes and other water and flood control measures
That have been implemented in that area over the centuries to keep the water from taking it over
The artillery has done great damage to that before 30 price
Now with this wonderful barrage of 4 million shells that the British launched into this area
Destroyed whatever was left in that sis
But it's when the rain starts that he gets horrifying because you taken already
Horrifying first world war Western Front Battlefield of the sort we've described with the giant trenches everywhere the veggie tray
Haitian all gone except for the little twigs and sticks that used to be giant trees
Is horrific hell Mordor like
A landscape and you flood it
Now we had battles like the song where there will be rain and you will have moments of flooding but it isn't like this
This battlefield will start the flood and it will stay that way
There will only be three dry days in the month of August
In fact they get double
The normal rainfall
And this turns the area
Into swamp
Swamp of quicksand
And very quickly with all of the
No casualties that start cropping up you get the same kind of situation we talked about at the Somme
Where if the shell holes with your everywhere filled with water become like toxic dumps with
Human bodies decaying in them in the remnants of
Poison gas and trash
And
The results of the music these things is latrines and it is being most sickening stuff you can think of as a matter of fact one of the problems can
Fronting the British
At this battle
Is
They don't have water for the truth they have water everywhere they have water coming out their ears but none to drink
Can you show holes in the mud
Will form as nasty and enemy to the soldiers fighting in this
As they are
You know opposition and I don't want to suggest it wasn't bad for the Germans either that maybe the Overlook side of passchendaele it's so
Horrible in this is seared into British Consciousness then it's so horrible for British troops
Which let's remember and not just English folks
And Welsh
Scotch Irish Newfoundland Indian Australia New Zealand Canadian and I'm leaving some out
They're all their suffering
But the Germans are suffering too
The rain is so bad
Dead Within
Just a few days
He has to call a halt to operations the guns are sinking
You know what's the horses are syncing up to their chip the people
Are sinking what makes this battle particularly horrifying
Is that in no other battle in the first world war do you routinely see the soldiers putting that unbelievable situation
Equation that we quoted Norman Cousins that
Scottish Soldier
He was saying he was given the tools to
Kill his fellow man if they were badly wounded on the battlefield
What if they're slowly sinking in mud
Because that's what was happening
When we talk about battles it's carnation
What do we mean by
Well in the first World War
Hundreds of thousands sometimes millions of men would go through these terrible places
Passchendaele one
You know we're done with another the song was another
The brusilov offensive I mean these people who go through these horrible experiences
Number in the hundreds of thousands or millions of those survivors then go home permanently changed
How many human beings have to go home
Permanently change
For that to Ripple across their entire Society
Passchendaele did just that and part of the reason why would because what these people saw
Troy Dam
I mean the most widely
You know lampooned poetic line
Is Wylie Lampoon because it became so associated with the
This battle Siegfried Sassoon wrote
I died in hell
They called it passchendaele
You can see pictures by the way of this battle
On the battlefield to try to keep soldiers from getting stuck in the mud
They laid down duct board
And so you have and you have to imagine go look at pictures it is amazing you have a battlefield that looks like
The moon if the moon had been turned too much
And then
On the mud to try to keep people from sinking into it as though it's quicksand they put these little teeny planks in
Nmama
Make them look like
Hats in for where people need to go but what this does it means that the soldiers have to actually walk on those a machine gun
Understand just Target them
And these duckboards are blown up every night by the artillery and every night to get Royal Engineers coming rebuilding for the
Next day
Under Fire
Peter Hart and his wonderful book on the first world war the Great War
Quote private Norman Cliff a British soldier in the first Grenadier guards
Describing
In what was happening and it happened to thousands of soldiers
Quote
The approach to the ridge was a desolate swamp
Over which brooded an evil menacing atmosphere that seem to defy encroachment
Far more treacherous than the visible surface defenses
With which we were familiar such as barbed wire
Deep devouring mud
Spread deadly traps in all directions
We splashed and slithered and dragged our feet from the pull of an invisible enemy determined to suck us into its death
Every few steps someone would slide and stumble and weighed down by rifle and equipment
Rapidly sink into the squelching mess
Those nearest
Grab his arms
Struggled against being themselves engulfed in a few Min Lee possible dragged him out
When helpers floundered in as well and doubled the task
It became hope
All this training efforts fail in the swamps swallowed it's screaming victims and we had to be ordered to plot on 2G
Dejectedly and fight this Relentless enemy has stubbornly as we did those we could see
It happened at one of those leading us was Lieutenant Chamberlain
And so distraught that he become at the spectacle of men drowning in mud
And the desperate attempts to rescue them that suddenly he began hysterically belaboring the shoulders of a sinking man
Swagger stick
We were horror-struck
Does he does most compassionate officer so one strong is to resort to brutality
Are allowed protest Fortune to desist
The man was rescued
But some could not be
And they sent shrieking with fear and agony
To be order to go ahead
And leave a comrade to such a fate was the hardest experience one could be asked to endure
What the objective had to be reached
And we plunge Dawn
Bitter anger against the evil forces prevailing piled on door exasperation
This was as near to hell as I ever want to be
And quote
And Brian Cooper the ironclads of cumbrae
Quotes of soldiers
Depressing quotes
One of our men was unfortunate enough to step out of line
And fell into one of these mud hole
We managed to Loop a rope securely under his armpit
But it was useless
The poor fellow now knew he was beyond all Aid and begged me to shoot him
Rather than leave him to die a miserable death by suffocation
I am not afraid to say therefore
That I shot this man at his own urgent request
And quote
Any account is clear
Did this particular mode of dying affected the soldiers
In a worse than most of the other ones this is the the true extra horror
Of passchendaele third Ypres
Writer Adam hochschild in his book
To end all wars
Coach of British major
At 34
Who says quote
A party of a company man passing up to the front line
Found a man bald
2 above the knees
Dog with mud
What he means
He says quote
The United efforts of four of them
With rifles beneath his armpits
Made not the slightest impression and to dig even if shovels had been available would be impossible for there was
No foothold
Judy compelled them to move on up to the line
And when two days later they passed down that way The Wretched fellow was still there
But only his head was now visible
He was raving mad
And quote
And just like most of the other bad World War 1 battles
The other people stuck out in no man's land
That you couldn't go get
Drove the men in the trenches their comrades
Just almost insane
With powerlessness
Historian John Keegan quotes pretty Soldier Edwin Vaughn
Who's at the third Ypres
And who described
How the rain takes a known horrific situation the people stuck in no man's land and the sufferer
The date went through and the suffering that they've been transmitted to they're powerless comrades in the trenches
And made it worse
By just adding water
Soldier Von talks about
Being in a shell hole and then says quote
From other shell holes
From the darkness on all sides came the groans and wails of wounded men
Faint long sobbing moans of Agony into sparing shriek
It was too horribly obvious that dozens of men with serious wounds
Must have crawled for safety into New Shell holes
And now the water was Rising about them and Powerless to move they were slowly drowning
Horrible Visions came to me with those cries
Of men lying meme doubt they're trusting that their Pals would find them
And now dying terribly alone amongst the dead in the inky Darkness
And we could do nothing to help them
Dunham was crying quietly beside me and all the men were affected by the piteous cry
And quote
Lieutenant Edwin Vaughn and his man are relieved a couple hours later
Is there walking back
Down the line
He notices quote
The cries of the Wounded have been much diminished now
And as we staggered down the road the reason was only too apparent
For the water was right over the tops of the shell holes
And grow
Now if you wanted to look at this battle which went on for months
In military terms and you wanted to look at it positively as some
Modern historians do
You could say
Very killed between 220 and 350000 more Germans nothing wrong with that in war
Depression right
Course if you're the British political command you you'll know that it killed
About the same number of
British soldier
Detained
A few miles and some places that Canadians heroically capture the
Town of passchendaele Against All Odds and through much
You're suffering and persevering
What again
It's not
Quite apparent
How this really pushed the end of the war any closer
It definitely pushed a lot of soldiers though
Closer to a transformation
That they would eventually if they lived
To make it home
Transfer to the entire Society
Pretty Soldier Ronald skirt
Forever transformed
His experiences
In Flanders 1917 Edward so many others
It crushed the underpinnings of so much of his worldview
He writes about
The battle quote
I said the men's morale was breaking I suppose I should have included myself
I had long since lost any desire to continue as a fighting Soldier
Idealists and coward art of much use on a battlefield and I was a bit of both
At nineteen I found my standards of conduct obsolete
My ideal shattered
I've lost all faith in institutional religion
My church at authorize me to break the 6th commandment in the name of patriotism
And quote
He continues quote
Eventually I worked it all out
At least for myself
God was all right
It was we who were wrong
Why the hell should he care what happened to us a lot
We had brought this war evil into existence not God
The reason evil and ugliness were triumphing over goodness and beauty
Why pity and compassion were considered weaknesses and ruthlessness and cruelty regarded as Noble
The reason for all this was the wickedness in ourselves
And not the indifference of God
That's why the more murders you committed the bigger the hero you became
That's what made your Superior officer slap you on the back and say
When did old chap jolly good shooting when your shells are destroyed in minutes
The beauty which Craftsmen had toiled lifetime to create
Disillusion is very very bitter when you're young thoughtful imaginative and sensitive
And quote
In the post
Script to his memoir
Mars writing in the third person
Skirt says
Quote
Before 1917 ended
Json belligerent sensitive youth
Head escape death by inches a dozen times
Had seen his comrades die in Dreadful agony
Had seen and heard man who should have been dead
Men broken
P***
Limbless
Disemboweled
Screaming for anyone with a loaded rifle to end their unbearable suffering
And watched his friends and others
Slowly choking froth is poison gas suffocated them
Could not believe it possible until his own eyes told him it was
But half a man
Could leave for what seemed to him hours
And by the time he was rendered unconscious himself
Had come to realize that every friend he'd made
Every man he'd worked with had become cannon fodder
For years afterwards
Memories of these Horrors haunted his dreams
I Disturbed your sleep
Yet awake he could never bring himself to talk of
Emily thought of those wounded man and the comrades he been with when they were killed he always came to the same conclusion
It must never happen again
Never
And quote
There were hundreds
Thousands
All survivors
Like
This young man
They went home
Greatly influence
Their home societies
Mean there are literary historians
It will point to the influence these people had in the writings of the 1920s
And 1930s
Everywhere
War artist Paul Nash with another one
Permanently affected by passchendaele
He'd been to other areas and thought the war quite nice and then went to passchendaele
And had his entire world turned upside down
This is as related by
David Reynolds in his spine history the long shadow
He starts off by saying
Nash enjoyed all these other areas of the war
And then rides quote
But when Nash returns in November to the rain and mud of passchendaele
He was transfixed by quote the most frightful nightmare of a country
Moore concede by Dante arpo than by Nature with no glimmer of God's hand to be seen
Anywhere sunrise and sunset are blasphemies Reynolds says he explained
Quote
They are mockeries to man
And quote
Reynolds writes that the scene he says was gilded with the colors of hell
Yellow stinking mud
Shell holes filled with green white water black dying trees and unceasing shells that
Churned up the land into a graveyard
Quote
Gordon Nash now
I am no longer an artist
Interested in curious
I am a messenger who will bring back word from the men who are fighting
Do those who want the war to go on forever
Beabull inarticulate will be my message
But it will have a bitter truth and make it burn their lousy Souls
And quote
British war correspondent Philip Gibbs was there
Is all over that Battlefield
And
He had a true admiration for
Not just
The English troops but all the Dominion troops to and what they accomplished their goal of a doomed heroism
And Gibbs was just blown away
By what human beings and in these Gallant soldiers were able to achieve
And nothing upsetting more than to hear later
Did Sir Douglas Haig the British commander
Had proclaimed reports of the battlefield at passchendaele as being
Exaggerating
This is how a very angry Gibbs respond
Quote
Sir Douglas Haig thinks that some of the descriptions of that six months horror were quote-unquote exaggerated
Has a man who knows something of the value of words and we saw many of those battle scenes in Flanders and went out from Egypt
When many times during those months and then you names all the places that he been
A ninja by saying and Beyond to polygon wood and passchendaele where his dad lay meaning
The dead that
Haig was responsible for
Where his dad lay in the swamps and round the pill boxes and where tanks that are followed into the mire were shot in Tucson
Scrap iron by German gunfire and where our own guns were being flung up by the harassing fire of heavy shells
I say now that nothing that has been written
He's more than a pale image of the abomination of those battlefields
And it no pain or brush has yet achieved the picture of that Armageddon in which so many of our men Parish
And quote
Many people began to doubt British military leadership
Just because they would think you should ever fighting conditions that were that bad
There's a story and some people doubt it ever happened at used to be something that was mentioned by almost everyone writing about passchendaele
His book in Flanders Fields Leon Wolff
Tell the story his way and says
Quote
The following day
Lieutenant general sir lancelot kiggell
Paid his first visit to the fighting Zone
As a staff car lurched through the swamp land and near the Battleground he became more and more agitated
Finally he burst into tears and muttered
Good god did we really send men to fight in that
The man beside him who had been through the campaign replied tonelessly
It's worse further on up
And quote
Some say it would be
She was to think that these military folks have not been out to the field and seeing the conditions are known what they were like
I'm not going to take a position on that
All I will suggest is
But there were a lot of people
Who look at the conditions of passchendaele
And wondered
And what was going on in the heads of Britain's military leaders
Passchendaele
Is one of the most often cited nightmares of this war
To Britain
Along with the song
And just like the song
It did terrible damage
Britain's Army
British military historian John Keegan who's definitely in the anti Hague
Camp Road quote
On the song he had sent the flower of British youth
To death or mutilation
At passchendaele he had tipped the survivors into the slough of despond
And quote
For those in Britain's political class
That wished the generals would pay more attention to casualties they would get their wish
But not for an entire generation
The junior officers at places like passchendaele would be permanently affected by the
That bottle
British military Rider Brigadier Peter Young Road
Quote
The memory of this battle affected British leadership in the Second World War
Causing many commanders to go to extreme to try to avoid casualty
And quote
This attitude will
Become a generation too late
For leaders like
Lloyd George
He and his allies had tried to call off
Passchendaele campaign after the first sort of
An impetus was spent
Only to fail once again up against the military leadership
It was hard to say
Lawton mod
Blood and mud they can think of nothing better
Should be sad
Even though the British
You're suffering he's kind of cash
Tissot with a German
And their soldiers are being
Tragically
Affected by this
Fighting
As the British soldier
The German general Hermann Von Kuhl
Wrote in his report
About the troops fighting in Flanders
Quote
The sufferings probation and exertions which the soldiers had to bear
Or indescribable
Terrible was the spiritual burden on the lonely man in the Shell hole
Sportwrench
And terrible The Strain on the nerves during the British bombardment
Which continue day and night
The hell of Verdun in the psalm was exceeded by flying
The battle to hold Flanders has been the greatest martyrdom of the war
And looking back
It seems that what was born here was superhuman
Stop perhaps it may still prove
To be too great
A courageous Act
And quote
Well what
General cool didn't know in December 19th 7
Canteen
Was that
Something was taking root
That would end up leading
To the German military commanders getting their hands on between 500000
And a million
Fresh
Veteran
Rested
Soldiers
Faith is about to put the dice
The iron dice
Back into the hands of Germany's
Leadership
It's well-known
They're already inveterate gamblers
And the chance
To try to throw
A knockout
In a war where both sides look like badly beat up and permanently damage Fighters
Be irresistible
Seems like no matter what
Floyd Joy does
There's more blood mod
What in the world's future
In 99
Be sure to follow us on Twitter the address
Is at hardcore his
Get more hardcore history at dancarlin.com
If you think the show you just heard is worth a dollar
Dan and Ben would love to have
Abacus
It's all we ask
Go to dancarlin.com for information on how to donate to the show
I'd like to apologize
A couple of things right off
The first thing is for
Silly little
Persnickety mistakes
You can probably tell special if you wait for these programs to be released as we make
But I'm a bit of a
Not when it comes to detail
And yet the people around me keep telling me that there's a certain failure rate that should be expected I'm not really good at accepting that is
Especially when I catch the errors before the show gets out
Nonetheless
This one will go out with me saying the word trenches
To describe
The
Kind of fortification
That the British Orion
Passchendaele end-of-course
NoHo
To be a much
Closer term I think trenches to those British soldiers would have been a luxury on
Nonetheless
Those are the piddly little things
It slipped through our strainer here even when we catch them so that these shows come out more than once a year which we are just
Barely beating that
Think right now heading toward once a year at this pace
So I apologize for the piddly little errors in the past the ones in this show any in the future
We try hard
We're not
The other thing I'd like to apologize for is for perhaps ignoring your favorite part of the story
Whatever that might be
Favorite region favorite Army a favor
People favorite event
Picking a topic like this
Is humbling
And you know it once again shows you some of the potential downsides with our leap
Before we look
Topic picking policy here on the program
Nonetheless I will forgive in advance from now on I promise I've learned my lesson
Every historian and author
Who talks too much about the Western Front at the
Expensive other areas of the first world war because you start to realize why that becomes important
This is a very confusing
There's alot going on
It would be so easy to go off in the weeds and lose everybody I have
But I'm worried about losing myself in the story you end up sticking to the Western Front and Russia and the United States
As a sort of an anchor to keep the story
You know
Clinging to some sort of structure
In some ways I think it's probably the week hosts
Answer to the problem on the other hand
Every time you introduce another theater
Another peep
And another
Norwegian and more names and individual
You make the story more and more confusing
The first world war is a giant
What's your getting here and I say this about all of our prayer
You're getting the Dan Carlin version
Of the first World War
And unfortunately that's leaving a lot of things out but I tell you what
As a
Friend of mine once said
Perhaps we should look at it as
Is just leaving
A lot more potential future Hardcore History topics available
Forest to handle
Down the road
Show
I'm going to make up some of the deaf
The things we haven't talked about and make up for some lost time in the Middle East
Are there are many things going on that
Create
In the beginnings of the modern world in the
Region including important foundational
Events
The lay the groundwork for the modern Recreation
The ancient state of Israel
In Russia we get to see
What an intellectual contagion that might be a good
How to describe it
Drop down into the middle of the very fertile petri dish that is provisional government Russia
Can do to a country like that is an answer to the question will perhaps arise as to whether or not an army can ask
Actually function
If the soldiers get to vote on whether they want to follow orders
And finally
Will get to see
The arrival of
US troops in large numbers
On the European continent for the first time ever
If I'm lucky and get what I want
We will get to
To delve a little bit into air power
How WeChat
Three-dimensional lysing battlefields in Al
That technological race
Is a little like
No Steve Jobs and Bill Gates and those guys were involved
And Technology back in 1960-1970 they might very well be in Airplane development
Geeks
These
Pilots in these planes are
You know
Have technological geek in half
Medieval Knight
We'll talk a bit about that if I get lucky and
I can make the time
And finally
We'll talk certainly
About the difference
When both sides are exhausted on the Western Front
That half a million to a million fresh troops can make and I'm not talking about American troops
I'm talking about the German soldiers
That arrived from the Eastern front to the Western Front
Can make on tired French and British armies
Before the Americans arrived in enough numbers
To make a difference
The last year of the war
Alyssa price
All that
And more
Compartes
A blueprint for a