What you're about to hear is the six
And Final
Part of a six-part
Series on the first World War
Traditionally we suggest people listen to them in order but I realize not everyone
Additional
And there may be a few
Historical dyslexia
6 out there and if that's the case
It might not matter to you
You listening
If that's the case please feel free to Jump Right In
Those of you who've heard the previous episodes welcome back
Two-part
Sex
He said the final
Part not counting next
Picture Show
Blueprint for Armageddon
December 7th 1941
A date which will live
In infamy
Leo events
Call nist time and place I take pride in the words ich bin ein Berliner
Mister barber shop
I welcome this kind of examination
Whether or not their president
We are not descended from fearful men
It's hardcore history
What's the most dangerous weapon in the world
I've had this discussion many times
With many people
And I seen it Go all over the
But generally you focus on nuclear war
Because that's an obvious thing to put
You don't win the number 1 spot for most dangerous weapon in the world
But there are some that are little bit more Insidious and potentially worse
Take for example
Biological
Think about some of the worst
Plagues that if ever
Infested mankind now imagine human Ingenuity in a laboratory used to make
Such plagues worse
And now imagine releasing those upon your
Anime
The reason they're so extra dangerous
Is because of the way they spread
And the fact that once you open the Pandora's box of biological warfare
You generally lose the ability to shut the box again
You may exchange a few nuclear weapons with an opponent and decide to stop
Once you open up that box and unleash
Super smallpox or what have you
You can't turn that off again
Another reason is very dangerous is that super smallpox
Doesn't differentiate between the people you targeted
And everyone else that it may spread to
It's a bit of a doomsday device when you think about how something like that could backfire
On the very people who decide to use it
It's a little light to siding
To get rid of your next-door neighbor in your apartment complex by burning down his place
This potential for the fire to hurt you
Is very real
But sometimes if you run out of options gambling like that might make sense
In late 1917
Where we are in the store even though we've been using sliding time scale that's about where we are
In late 1917 the Germans are desperate enough to
Try
All sorts of things
Including the equivalent of biological warfare
But instead of using some sort of contagious
Disease
They're using contagious ideas
But you might be able to make a case
But in this situation
An actual disease would have been prefer
Whenever I think about this idea I think about Napoleon
The famous French emperor of late 1700 early 1800
It was such a force in Europe
Napoleon was someone who spread
An intellectual Contagion
Remember professors in college
Suggesting that this was the thing that scared
The Kings and czars and Emperors of Europe the most about Nepal
Because Napoleon arose in the wake of the French Revolution
The era where Frenchmen were infused with these ideas
Rebelution
Equality of republicanism
All these things that seem
A relatively moderate
The people today even beneficial
But those with the scariest things on earth to people who were Kings and Emperors and czars
And many of them figured
That they would eventually be able to throw the French out of these territories
And get their Thrones back
But they were less sure about their ability to cleanse their population of these dangerous radical ideas
The French occupying troops had spread to the
In fact many
Historians believe
At the famous
Revolutionary period in the middle 1800s
Was the blossoming of seeds that were planted
By Napoleon's troops
As they
Occupied all these countries talk to the locals and spread
The equivalent of an intellectual Contagion
Of course if you're one of those types who would View
The ideas of the American Revolution or the French Revolution or the ideas of the thinkers who helped
Prompto's Revolution
As a negative thing
Then perhaps you would view the 1800's as an example not a seed flowering into some wonderful plant
What is a virus beginning to more
And mutate
And evolve into new and maybe more dangerous form
The eighteen-hundreds is
Up until that time.
Almost certainly the greatest. For
Intellectual examination of forms of government that ever existed
And part of it is because of the increase in communication and how people all over Europe can begin to have conferences and discussions
Magazines and newspapers that each other reads and have
All sorts of attempts at trying to apply
Rationality
And logic
To the idea of government
Because most of the government's in a place like you're up at this time.
Are things that have existed in
One form or another for centuries
Someone in the distant past was a great military leader who establishes a dynasty
Who rules for hundreds of years and no one ever really asks
Whether or not that's the right thing to do for whether or not as smart or anything else
In the 1800 people began to think
Along with
Any changes in science and all kinds of different things that maybe
People could come up with smarter approach
But it was wide disagreement though I'm what that smart approach might be
And some of the great figures of the 1800s
Who played roles in this
Will become extremely important figures
In the 19
In fact
Someone who is involved in trying to come up
With a system that seem to be an improvement over what Europe was living with in the 1800's
Explodes in importance
In 1917
Exactly where we are in this first world war story
He was
Renowned in his own Day within his own Circle but he certainly wasn't a household name
He becomes a historical superstar in 1970
And there's a little bit of iron needed that because in 1917
This week has been dead 34 35 years
One of the best
One of the worst
Aspects
Have an idea depending on whether you consider it good or dangerous
Is the fact that it doesn't die
With the originator
In 1917
All of a sudden everybody starts hearing the name Karl Marx
Marx is often credited with being the
Originator of
Modern communism Marxism
But I think that's probably giving him a little too much credit after all
Very few people
Come up with ideas out of nowhere and Mark
Like most people
Stood on the shoulders of giants with his ideas
He was reading guys like the German philosopher Hegel and a lot of other people
What if a guy like hagel's an example of
The intellectual Contagion
Denmark is an example of someone
Cool
Mutated it
Farther
Of course perhaps the ironic tragedy of marks
Is that Mark
Didn't get to be the implementer of his ideas
His ideas
Wer
Adapted
And more
In two different
Like many figures from history if you could go back and show
Karl Marx
How he's treated in the history books in the things he's associated with
I think you might jump off a bridge
There's a lot of figure
Or remembered for things
That are almost 180 degrees different
Then what they devoted their lives to working for
Mark study was doing good
And yet today we think about his role
In the deaths of tens of millions of people
And the creation of some of the worst
Slave states in all human history
If you read Marx
And find out what he was all about
That's exactly what he was hoping to
Prevent and stop
Eliminate
You can bring Karl Marx back from the dead and have him analyzed where things went wrong
I wouldn't be surprised at all
If he blamed
A botched
Implementation
For the way things turned out
We might argue that Marx's ideas from the get-go we're poor
But I think he would probably say that you never got a chance to see what he wanted
Because he wasn't the guy
Built the house he was the architect maybe or maybe the last guy to design blueprint
The guy who actually built the
Dwelling
Was a guy named Vladimir Lenin
And i'm reminded of a quote by the writer aldous Huxley
About how ideas
End up influencing
People and it's not so much a question always
How many people
But who they are
Huxley Road quote
It is possible to argue that the really influential book is not that which converts 10 millions of casual
Will readers
But rather that which converts the very few
At any given moment
Succeed in seizing power
Marks and Sorrel have been influential in the modern world
Not so much because they were best sellers
Stop because among their few readers
We're two men called respectively Lenin and Mussolini
And quote
Vladimir Lenin is the hinge point
Between Theory
An application
When it comes to modern-day communes
Easy implement
Marx is the originator
And Lenin is the implementer
He's a figure
The combines
Some rather
Unusual qualities in one human being
Often times the intellectual in the deep thinker in the philosopher
Is a different sort of human being
Then the person of action
Raichu for the man of action
And often times are two different kinds of people linen is one of these strange individual
The possesses the qualities of both an intellectual
And a person of action
Annie's dynamic
Abilities
We recognize even by the people
Who were his opponent
Take for example the description
Elora Gorge
The man who is the prime minister of Britain during really the second half of the first World War
George will write his Memoirs in the 1930s and he will say this
Vladimir Lenin
Quote
He was a communist
But whilst fanaticism does not always endowed with possessor with great administrative ability
It is not incompatible with a genius for government
And no one can doubt that Lennon was one of the greatest leaders of men ever thrown up in any yet
And quote
He then goes on to compare him
What he calls
Plague bacillus
Lenin was certainly up
Most revolutionaries are
People who tend to not see Too Many Shades of Grey things tend to be black and white
Winston Churchill famously defined the Fanatic is
Someone who can't change their mind
And won't change the subject
Churchill had his own opinion of Lenin and once again
It evoked this idea of an intellectual contagion he also compared Lennon to some sort of bacteria
And he blamed the Germans
For unleashing it
On your
Playing an active role
In
Implementing a form of germ warfare
It would have
Horrible effects down the road
Churchill Road quote
Lenin was sent into Russia by the Germans
In the same way that you might send a file containing a culture of typhoid
For cholera
To be poured in the water supply of a great City
And it worked with amazing accuracy
And quote
That brings us to the third person who is very important
In
Implementing
This
Intellectual contagion Warfare kind of approach
The facilitator
If March is the originator
And linen is the implementer
Lennon needed some help
To get to the point where he could in fact
If you will
Anyone
In the beginning of 1917 Vladimir Lenin
Is an exile
He's living in Switzerland
Next to a sausage back
On the second floor of a rented flat with his wife
Trying to make a living
In what you might call
The professional revolutionary
I'd like to get back to Russia in 1917 because it's apparent that
Huge things are happening in Russia the Tsar has been overthrown a provisional government is taking over
But Lennon can't get from where he is
To Russia
There's a war going on and there's a lot of territory in between Switzerland and Russia to deal with
And then he get
Somehow
From the facility
The leader of Germany's military
And for the most part by this time civilian government
Erich ludendorff
Ludendorff in the Germans have long been
Associated with Lenin's rise to
Power
The exact amount
Responsibility
The Germany
Manhattan that story is debatable and has been debated since 1917
One of the reasons
Historians
Have a hard time nailing down to finitive answers
Is because it's
One of those things that falls into the category
Of what we would call today
Covert operation
Or Black Ops
Tzatziki
Stop both sides in the war
We're trying to undermine the cohesiveness
And the stability
Of their Epona
A potentially wonderful way to do that was to give money
Or arms or sometimes military advisors
Two revolutionaries
Insurrectionist
And Breakaway group
An ethnic separatist
And people who lived in countries that were colonies of some of the great Powers but who wanted their independence and both sides as I said we're doing
There's
A lot of alligators
Things about German involvement for example
In the famous Easter rising in 1916 in Ireland
How much Germans support
That's questionable 2 and part of the reason why is
Nobody was exactly advertising
Chevy's top secret affairs
Most of the stories Trace German involvement
At least as far back as 1915
Most of the story suggest that it was
Contacts with leftist individuals who pointed out to the German government
That there were shared goals
On the part of Germany
And some of these Russian revolutionaries
Take for example Lennon and his particular offshoot of the communist
In a mainstream known as the Bolshevik
One of the things Lenin was calling for
Was peace
That's exactly what the Germans wanted from the Russian
By 1917
They wanted the Russians out of the war
The Russians were tying down
Millions of German troops on the Eastern Front
That the Germans would love to be able to switch over to the Western Front
To fight the exhausted French and British before the Americans arrived in any sort of decisive numbers
Now the big gamble here
Of course
Is that the Bolsheviks while they may share a common goal and getting Russia to leave the war
I'm not Germany's friend
Ludendorff deciding to use them as a tool
Is a Cantu adding another Boxer into the World War 1 boxing match
We use that analogy throughout the series the idea of two boxers fighting each other
Part of ludendorff gamble here
Is he talking about introducing a third boxer into the ring
One that wants to fight both the other two boxers
But ludendorff has a pretty good idea that he'll go after
The one ludendorff on the Germans are fighting first
The Bolsheviks and Lenin are preaching the equivalent of a global
Civil War
If the American President Woodrow Wilson
Is calling the first world war the war to end all wars
Lenin has his own idea
The war to end all wars is Irish historian William Mulligan points out
Lenin's idea
Of the war to end all wars
Is revolutionary
War
The Bolsheviks are calling for
The poor
And working classes
Of all Nations to rise up and over
Germany is only a little less vulnerable to that sort of message then Russia is
This is why I ludendorff
Is playing with fire or in this case
Play
He stands a really good chance of getting burned
By this very same weapon
That he in 1917 decides to help
Use against Russia
The actual mean
To get Lenin from
Switzerland back to Russia is provided
By the Germans in April 1917 so we're going backwards a little bit in the story
The Germans provide a single
Seal
Train car
For Lenin and his cowboy
Historians have
Disagreed over
Who demanded that it be sealed
Some say the Germans wanted this train car sealed so that when Lenin and his cohorts are going through Germany they don't intellectually in Fair
The Germans on the way through
How do you say it was Lenin in the Bolsheviks who demanded it
The last thing that they wanted was to have
People in Russia find out that they were accepting help from the country Russia was fighting oh yeah and a people who have
I happened to be capitalist 2
Nonetheless whomever it was who made the decision
As the train car goes through Germany there's a famous incident where Lennon or one of his cohorts looks out the window
And happens to notice
That there are no mature men
Anywhere to be seen
It's children
And women
And old people
Germany's mature male population is either
Dead
When did
Or at the front
Lenin and his party then we'll have to board a ferry and go by
Boat for a little bit then I'll get back on another train the train will then arrive
In petrograd formerly St Petersburg the Russian Capital just before midnight
On April 16th 1917
There will be a crowd
Waiting to welcome him because like many other
Dangerous ride
Kohl's
Lenin is coming home from exile
The Tsar for decades have been exiling all these
Barry
Formidable intellectual contagions at those are the ones he wasn't executing by the way Lenin's brother have
Been executed by the czar
Now all these people were coming back to Russia
At roughly the same time creating a seditious
Soup
Politically speaking in Russia during this time.
And believe me rush it was ready for
There in this precarious situation after the Tsar Falls where you have
Short of a moderate government
Known as the provisional government sharing power
With these
Groups of soldiers and peasants and workers who have gotten together and elected leaders
And we're shooting
Trying to lead from the bottom and they're sharing power in and not very comfortable sort of an arrangement with the provision
It is absolutely a setup for problems
And yet you kind of
You have to feel a little bit for them
I mean think about what these people are trying to do
They are trying
To run a country
After toppling the regime that have been in power for centuries
This is a tough thing to do in the best of time
But this isn't the best
The time
The equivalent of a bus passenger
Try to get ahold of the wheel in the bus is already careening off a cliff
And then you get a guy like linen arriving
And he gets off the platform
At a little before midnight and tells us enthusiastic crowd of supporters quote
The piratical imperialist war is the beginning of a civil war throughout Europe
The worldwide socialist revolution has already gone
Germany is seething
Any day now the whole of European capitalism a crash
Sailors
Comrade
We have to fight for a socialist Revolution
The fight until the proletariat wins full directory
Long live the worldwide socialist Revolution
And quote
Even
Lenin's friends
Thought this way to optimist
In fact
At that very moment the current
Russian government power-sharing Arrangement was trying to put together
An offensive against the Germans
Schedule for July 1st
With an army that was sketchy
At best at this point
If you are Russia's provisional government
You are between a rock and a hard place in 1970
You are barely holding on to power
You have strikes you have on rest you have all kinds of problems and now you haven't been in here taking the already
Kind of extreme Bolsheviks and pushing them into greater
Extremism
He's calling for three main things that are impossible for the provisional government to really contend with
He's calling for peace
Bread
And land
A triple threat of a message that would be effective across much of Europe in nineteen
I have to provisional government
Hose
It has to prove to the British in the French that it's still a viable partner in this war they're funneling tons of
Subsidies to this government
In fact they need to
Convince the Germans in the Central Powers of the same
But you can't just assume we're done in the best way to do that is to launch an attack
The problem is is that this Army
Might have been willing to stay and defend
Mother Russia soil
But most of them are not willing to go on the offensive and run into the machine guns in the artillery barrage Isabel
The Germans
They may not give a hoot about
Bolshevism or communism or any of that but they understand peace bread and land
On July 1st
The kerensky offensive is it sometimes called at the July offensive lead by the great Russian general Brazil
Launches an attack on a wide front against
The Germans in the austro-hungarian
It becomes
A disaster
This is the way historian Peter hard disk
Quote
After a two-day bombardment
The second brusilov offensive attack began with a flourish
With the attack of the Russian 7th and 11th armies on the Southwest Front
When the Infantry went over the top on 1st July early results were promising
But then everything started to go wrong
The best and most loyal units have been chosen as the assault troops
While the follow-up and Reserve formations were far less committed
Indeed
When it came to moving forwards
Many regiments simply refuse
The attack petered out an ignominious
And further planned attacks reader cancelled or abandon
Then a vigorous austro-hungarian counteroffensive was launched at ternopil in glitzy on 19th July
The Russians broke and retreated in chaos
This Disaster triggered the replacement of brusilov as commander-in-chief by General coronal off on the 1st of August
The Russian army was falling apart
And such a taxes had been carried out only serve to call the few remaining loyalists unit still willing to act
Did we prosecute the war
The vast majority of Russian soldiers wear now content to be passive observers at best
Indeed
Periotome it was estimated that some 2000000 had deserted
In quote
For a while
The German High command in the austro-hungarian high command encourage their troops to fraternize with Russian troops
To sort of undermine
Their willingness to fight
They stop doing that
When they found out that the Russian troops were spreading socialist and Bolshevik propaganda back
To the German and austro-hungarian
Nonetheless
What that
Disaster
At the kerensky offensive did
What's essentially prove that Russia's Army was done
And open the door even more
To the Bolshevik
Message
Calling for
4 piece
Writer GJ Meyer describes
A letter
From
Rudolph
Hatsune the next
World War will be one of Hitler's henchmen
Writing back to his parents
About what the Russians are doing
Opposite the German lines
They're basically fighting amongst themselves
He writes quote
Yesterday we saw heavy fighting
But only among the Russians themselves
A Russian officer came over and gave himself up he spoke perfect German
He was born in Baden
What is a Russian citizen
He told us that whole battles are going on behind their lines
Their officers are shooting each other
And the soldiers are doing the same
He found it all too ridiculous
They can all get lost
As far as he's concerned
We invited them to eat with us anything
Pa-12 and drink plenty of tea before going off
There was a lot of noise coming from the Russian side yesterday
They were fighting each other in the trenches
We also heard shots coming from their infantry but they were firing at each other
Charming
And quote
Lennon said
That the Russian soldiers were voting for peace with their feet
The failure of the July offensive was another nail in the coffin
For the provisional government
An added to the support of Lenin and the Bolsheviks to
Were able to portray themselves as the
Real alternative
The provisional government the one party that didn't have any responsibility and what was going on
And the more Russians didn't like what was going on
The more the only choice to change that seem to be the Bolsheviks and over the months
Between the February Revolution the top of the czar
And just about November the Bolsheviks increase their support
In these
Councils
Peasants and soldiers and workers known as the Soviet
I don't November 7th 1917
They move
In a Triumph
AB Superior organization
They were able to take over
The most important government buildings in the Russian capital
In a coup
That most Russians awoke to find a fait accompli
Already finished
And
The most radical government in power in a major state
Since the French Revolution
All the sudden Lenin and the Bolsheviks
Or in charge
Of Russia
And
Marc's
And the other 19th
Century thinkers
We're about to have their ideas
Updated evolve morfin changed
Put into practice in what was about to become a giant
Human experiment
But you're most of Old Europe This looked like a human experiment conducted by a mad scientist
Too damn it look like
The second coming of the French Revolution did Lenin and the Bolsheviks might as well have been Jacobin
How long before The Guillotines are brought out and everyone starts getting their head shot
Within 24 or so hours of taking power
Lenin starts to make good on some of his promises
Understand the Lenin's promises had attacked
Medical purpose in mind
They would end up
In his mind helping to spread
Revolution.
Water Country
The fire caused
Buy German general ludendorff attempt to burn down his neighbor's apartment
We're beginning to Fan the Flames to degree
When many other countries were likely to get burned
Lenin's decree on land said among other things
Quote
Private ownership of land shall be abolished forever
All land shall become the property of the whole people
I'm passing to the use of those who cultivate it
And quote
Ben Lennon started
Spreading
The sort of propaganda the most horrifying
The powers who have been fighting the first world war for more than 3 years by this point
He said quote
We shall offer peace for the peoples of all the belligerent countries upon the basis of the Soviet turn
No annexations no indemnities and the right of self-determination of peoples
At the same time according to our promise we shall publishing repudiate the secret treaties
And quote
Secret treaties
Were the treaties amongst
The Allied powers that were in the files of The Winter Palace at the Bolsheviks had just taken over
By making
What was in those files public
The Bolsheviks were pulling the
Wikileaks maneuver
Or the Edward Snowden disclosure of their day
By the way another
Similarity
To the release of the secret treaties
And the Wikileaks Edward Snowden
Revelations of of the more modern era
The newspaper in Britain that released the information to British readers
It was the Manchester Guardian
That published in Britain
The
Secret treaty information that Leon Trotsky and the Bolsheviks released of the world
That's the same newspaper in Britain that took the lead almost a hundred years later
In revealing the Edward Snowden Revelations
Historians Michael nyberg and David Jordan right in their history of the Eastern front in the first World War
Quote
The Bolshevik leaders had little interest in working with the capitalist Western allies
They soon publish the text of the secret treaties and diplomatic understanding that they found in the Winter Palace
And the government archives
These agreements showed French and British support for Russian territorial gain
Especially a turkey's expense with regard to Constantinople
This seemingly revealed with the Bolsheviks have been arguing all along
Namely that the war had been fought for Imperial interests
Not out of self-defense
The publication of these terms embarrassed Allied diplomat
Put claimed in public that no such agreements existed
This also angered The Americans
Who would advocated a peace without annexations
And quote
The new
Bolshevik government
Began to
Tell generals along the entire front with the Germans and austro-hungarian turksat they should start making
Local peace treaties that called
For an armistice
430 days along the entire front
All of a sudden
Russia was in the process of dropping out of the war
Lenin is supposed to have said
A famous quote
Aptly describes the situation in November 1917 he said quote
There are decades when nothing have
And there are weeks when decades happen
And quote
And look at the change in Fortune for him
Personally
Six or seven months ago he's living in a rented
Flat
On the second floor
Next to a Sausage Factory in Switzerland
Now by November 1917
He's basically the guy in charge of the largest Nation on Earth
But this leadership
Is not uncontested a Russian Civil War starts almost immediately
With the people who
Opposed Lenin in the Bolsheviks and it will go on for several years and be terribly bloody and draw in the great Powers as well
It also will not include
50 million or more people who are counted as the citizens of old Russia
As some of these territories begin to break away from Russia
Again one of the really
Dangerous things that the new Bolshevik government
Professor
This is a belief in self determination
Well there are lots of different people who didn't want to be a part of the Russian government
The fins
Polls
The ukrainians and others
Who were starting to think maybe they would just leave
They were far from the only peoples
Who were members of larger State entities around the world
Who thought that they would like a crack itself
Determination
All these European countries that had colonies were in the same position
And there was no message more dangerous than the idea
The time it come to perhaps allow all these people to decide for themselves
Whether they wanted to stay colony
Already
The plague bacillus
What's begins to spread
And threaten not just the Allies in the Anton powers
But soon the power that made it possible for linen to get back and start the fire in Russia to begin with
This is the point in the story
Where
Russia
And communism
Veer off into their own tail
A very long complex Tale
It impacts the rest of the 20th century you can easily make the case
The perhaps the most important
Long term effect of the first World War
Is the collapse of the Russian czar
An eventual replacement
By the Bolshevik
It will eventually lead to Joseph Stalin
And the horrors of the gulag
And the Cold War
There was a wonderfully prophetic line
Around the time of Karl Marx so you can see how long
Before this time.
Bed
Revolutionary thinkers like bakunin were saying
Quote
If you took the most Ardent revolutionary
Vested him and absolute power within a year he would be worse than the Tsar himself
And quote
And for all his high-minded rhetoric
Very quickly
Vladimir Lenin
Was proving a coonan
Right
Play late 1917 early 1918
That side of the Bolsheviks and the Communist Regime in Russia
Was still
Debatable
An unknown
If you actually read their public pronouncements
They look like an almost an ending in hindsight this sounds terrible. Almost a refer
Flexing
Group of idealist who refused to play by the old cynical hard-bitten
In the rules of the European powers
And to get an idea of how difficult it is to figure out you know what's going on there and what these people are like you can look
Diaries written during the time. Where people try to make sense of what they're seeing in Russia take for example
Evelyn princess
Lucia and we talked about her before she's in English
White
I'm in German nobleman living in Germany she kept a diary that's often referred to
To give sort of an impression
Of what's going on in Germany in the feelings of they having she writes about this new government in Russia
While the peace negotiations to end the war in the East or going on
Those negotiations will end up with
One of the most one-sided treaties in all history
Call brest-litovsk
And the only reason it's so one-sided is that the Bolsheviks were in such danger of getting overthrown before they hit him
Consolidated power
Did eventually they just agree to one of the worst deals of all time assuming that the Communist Revolution is soon
Going to come and sweep all these Western European governments in central European governments away anyway
So who cares what they agree to
During the negotiations Leon Trotsky
I mean we've also quoted earlier key figure in the Bolshevik
Government
Is negotiating this deal
Andalusia writes in her diary in January 1918 quote
The brest-litovsk negotiations seem likely to come to nothing
As Trotsky seems to be playing a double part
And people say he's only toying with the central powers to be better able to sow the seeds of sedition
And Rebellion amongst the West European people
They say that already the German prisoners have been set free in Russia
Common soldiers are being placed in command over their former officers
She continues quote
There are many different opinions about Trotsky hear some calling him a dreamer
And ideally
Others abusing him as a bloodthirsty tyrant
Whilst there was a whole class of admirers who declare him to be the greatest man since Christ lived upon the Earth
And the prophet of a new religion which is to regenerate Mankind and create a new Paradise after the deluge
Loser of the war
Who knows what part this man may be going to play in the future fates of Europe
Some 120 years ago people were saying almost the same things
I'm a certain unknown little officer
Who are the reign of terror and bloodshed developed into the vampire Emperor who almost succeeded in
Draining the blood of all Europe
And quote
She of course is referencing Napoleon who grew out of the French Revolution
Two people at the time. That's what the Revolution in Russia kind of resembled
And her quite a few similarities they're pointed out by various historian between the French Revolution
And the Napoleonic era
And the arrow in the Bolshevik
Take charge in Russia
Take for example
One of the stipulations that the Bolsheviks were making during the peace negotiations at brest-litovsk
They wanted their troops to have the right during the negotiations
To fraternize
With the German and austro-hungarian Soldiers on the other side of no-man's-land
Why did they want that
Because they felt that just like Napoleon's troops spreading the ideas the intellectual contagion the sedition
Of the French revolutionary ideas
To the lands of the Kings and emperors
In the eighteenth and early nineteenth century Europe
The Bolsheviks assumed that their troops would do the same thing to the Germans in the austro-hungarian
In early 20th century
Combine that with the impact that the release of the secret treaty agreements was having
And the Russian government the new Russian government the idealistic at least on the surface new Russian government
Was doing
Amazing damage to the Allied war effort by undercutting all the propaganda
And they had help by the way
The other really idealistic power that was starting to have an impact on the world scene
What's across the Atlantic
It was the United States
Into the hard-bitten
Cynical
Bismarckian realpolitik Europe of that day
It would have been hard for them to decide who was more idealistic
The new Russian Bolshevik government
Or the American government of Woodrow Wilson
In a sense though
It's hard to blame
Britain and France annie's other European powers for the fact
That they had gone into the war
Making agreements with each other and their allies for carving up this territory or exchanging that tear
Territory that was standard operating procedure
When the war started and had been
You know forever the 19th century was full of those kinds of
The problem is in just a couple of years
Things have changed
In so many ways
The first world war at the transitionary. From the 19th to the 20th century and that includes
Things like
B
Proper
And moral justifications for war
I'm part of the problem is
Dip for 3 years now
DIYs
To name just one example the Central Powers were doing similar things
Had made the warframes out to be these
High-minded ideals right
The war to end all wars
I'm making the world safe for democracy
For fighting if you know German militarism I mean there were all these very high-minded ideals
So when you sell people on those ideas
When they find out that really what those soldiers are dying for is much more pedestrian
It's hard to square
Those two realities
In fact
There were Nations involved in the first world war that essentially head
Join sides with
You know the the alliance that promised them the best outcome
Italy Bulgaria Romania to name just three countries got into this war for no other reason than
In one side of the other promise them some territorial gain that was more than the other side promised
That was a very common reality from the 19th century
Part of what change that animated
Unacceptable
What's the price that Europe was being forced to pay for these territorial Act
Positions
I mean a perfect example is 20 years before this time. Where we are now
Instead of 1917 8-19-17 imagineering 1898
And you're the British army
I'm in an area that's going to become part of you know your
Colonial the territories that you have direct or indirect control over in
The Modern Nation of Sudan
There's a very big battle called alderman
Bought in 1898 Winston Churchill was there as a very young man his first real exposure to
Peking duck
Battle
Underarm German had about 8000 or so British troops and then they had
The bunch of Ally
Size of theirs from Egypt
Places like that
Natives
Work as you think of like
Tribesmen butt butt butt troops from
Egypt
And they were fighting people who were kind of tribesmen a bunch of Sudanese
Under Armour leader in that country more than 50,000 of them show up to this battle against the small group of
British and British Isles
And using modern Weaponry including
Basically machine guns modern rifles I mean it's essentially in a beta version of the first World War army that Britain
Go to war with and they're fighting guys who have like muskets price
And in one afternoon
Inflict some 30000 or more casualties on the tribesmen and
Folks that they're facing
10000 dead
5000 capture the rest wounded
And the British lose 45
British soldier
In the Endeavor
Then they just demolish this native
We are only losing that number of people
For such great games
Sometimes you don't
Always
Think too much about the deeper questions involved in the cost of the cost isn't that great
And let's be honest in this era
If those British soldiers have been wiping out
Frenchman
Or Germans or swedes or people like themselves
There might have been more of an outrage
It was an ERA where sometimes
The killing of native peoples in other places was not given the same sort of
A sense of horror and outrage that
Killing people who look like
Yourself
Mike
Engender we all understand how that might work
And so instead of a battle of omdurman where
The changing of territory with a relatively
Small affair with relatively few casualties
You don't like 1917 the Germans in the British in just one battle in this war
You know suffer between 200 and 500 thousand casualties each
You think of deeper
Different more fundamental questions
When you not only suffer
4 casualties light
But you do so over and over and over again
Again
With no appreciable change nothing certainly worth all that
He began asking fundamental questions about these treaties you wrote and then earlier time in this war
How many Frenchmen
Is it worth losing
To regain the Lost territories of Alsace and Lorraine
How many German young people is it worth
To hold on to Belgium
How many austro-hungarian troops are conversely Italian troops
You know is that particular
Area
Near Trieste
Morris
How many
Dominion lies in Indian lives in British lives
Is post war British involvement in the Middle East worth
Well if it's the Battle of omdurman and were talking tiny numbers it certainly worth
There's a number that you're going to get to
When it's not
The first world war challenges a lot of people to ask
Those kinds of questions
And the people that were operating under the same sort of mentality that would have been present at the Battle of omdurman
Are red-faced when these treaty show up showing that that's just what they're like
They have
Changed yet and the treaties are going to have to be fulfilled anyway
Meanwhile if you didn't feel bad enough
In late 1917 when the Bolsheviks released this information
In January 1918 in part because the Bolsheviks did release this information
President Woodrow Wilson in the United States release something called
The Fourteen Points
Number 14 points
What is the Bolshevik
Move
It makes the rest of the world look like a bunch of capitalist warmongers is like a left hook
The American move in 1918 in January it's like a right cross right after work
To all these European old Power cuz the United States hitting from
From the other side of the idealism scale
AR
Suggesting that you should have a war based on things like mutual respect
Woodrow Wilson says nice things for example about the Germans about the Americans in the rest of the world do not begrudge
The Germans are shot at German greatness and all this kind of stuff another word conciliatory stuff if you're trying to have a deal and make every
Everybody come to the table
Feeling like yes we can work together
But if you're the French and you've already suffered more than a million casualties against these people
You had a war against them a generation in the past mean you're not really in the mood to be very conciliatory
And then Wilson starts talking about stuff that's as idealistic as anything the Bolsheviks are putting out and a lot
I have it sounds very similar for example
Here's how Wilson leads into his 14 points and notice how often he talks about
A change
In
You know
What we can maybe call today
Global public opinion
Or International morality and values
He says from the beginning of his statement
Turn down
In history of the Fourteen Points
Quote
It will be our wish and purpose
That the processes of peace
When they are be gone
Shall be absolutely open
Initial involving permit henceforth no secret understandings of any kind
The day of conquest and aggrandizement is gone by
So is also the day of secret Covenants
Entered into in the interest of particular government
And likely at some unlooked-for moment to upset the Peace of the world
It is this happy fact
Now clear to the view of every public man whose thoughts you're not still linger in an age that is dead and gone
Which makes it possible for every nation whose purposes are consistent with Justice in the Peace of the world
To avow
Nor any other time the object it has in view
An event goes into
You know the kinds of things he's talking about here
That will make a difference in the postwar world of it everybody should start to agree to
He says
As the number 114
Your number one point in the Fourteen Points quote
Open covenants of peace
Openly arrived at after which there shall be no private International understandings of any kind
But diplomacy shall proceed always
Frankly and in the public View
And quote
Can you imagine
Even the governments of our world today
Even talking about doing that
The idea that you should have treaties with other countries and all the agreement should be public and open to everyone. I mean
That's radical stuff even today
It sounded every bit like what the Bolsheviks were calling for
And all of a sudden you have Old Europe
The three for five years ago was sitting at the height of its Fame everything was fine
And now they've got this on both sides of them
Powerful Nations
It's a real change in Attitude
As I said though
It's not going to be allowed to
2 Chainz
Agreements that countries have between each other
And the juiciest stuff that came out of the secret treaty released
The Edward Snowden like dump
The Manchester Guardian another's
Was the
Treaties that have been
Sign some of them as late as 1916 the most famous is known as
The sykes-picot agreement but there are others
Catalog the great Powers plan for ripping apart the Ottoman Empire the great powers on the owl
Allied side won the war
They were going to go totally Imperial
The old Empire
Meijer
The Russians were going to finally after hundreds of years of wanting it to get
Constantinople
Istanbul later
Byzantium Once Upon a Time
This great City that controls
Are the Dardanelles and the Bosphorus and the
You know the access to the Black Sea would be a huge to
The Russians were prevented from doing this by the very British and French
That they were now negotiating with to get it
In the 1850s in the Crimean War
Which propped up the Ottoman Empire for another generation but now the Russians were on the same side as the French and the British they had all the
Decided that the Ottomans had to go and they were all going to agree on what pieces they got
Now the payoff for the Russians getting Constantinople the regions around that
Was that the French and the British we get to carve up much of what is now the modern middle
I just don't write me to email I know that even saying the term Middle East
Is a reference to their colonial past in that region
Because really if you were going to announce it properly should call it West Asia
Or something like that but that doesn't really didn't know the exact area you're talking about you can get into the
The area's I bet you could take the Levant or Anatolia for Mesopotamia but those are all just pieces of
The term Middle East and Compasses so I apologize I know it's not the right phrase
Nonetheless we all know what we mean and certainly if we're going to talk about the era where Middle East becomes the colonial term for the era
Why not start with the arrow where it becomes a colonial possession
4 non-islamic powers
The sykes-picot agreement and others have France carving up large chunks of the modern Arab world
And the British
Taking Northern Iraq
And I mean
They're breathtaking
They really are and when
The Bolsheviks release the secret treaties and the ottoman government reads the secret treaties to their own
In a group of
Knoebels is the wrong word but governmental ministers
Eugene Rogan says in his book
That there's this audible gasp as they here
The plans that France and Britain and Russia have
You know for the future of the Ottoman
It's not going to be a slap-on-the-wrist it's going to be dismemberment
And the dismemberment of the Ottoman Empire is what creates the modern Middle Eastern world
It is still such a part of our lives today
I said earlier that the Bolshevik Revolution was probably the top
Your long lasting
Aftershock in the first world war but maybe
It's better to say that there's a list of three or four
Possible
Lehman's to the throne if you will and maybe another one is
The changes that
Are created in the Middle East because the Ottoman Empire is broken up
Let's remember this is a 6
Hundred
Year old
Hard to
Overstate how long
Structures
And the type of rule by the ottoman impacted that area
First of all it was a large area that was under
Muslim control with a caliphate on paper at least and the leader of the religion at least the soon
Any branch of it in Turkey
The Turks ruled that region with an iron fist
And yet at the same time
It was
In the process of having huge debates over modernization and keeping up with the rest of the world
And they were just a few years from finding out that they sat atop some of the Worlds
Greatest deposits of oil on the planet
Which some more
Conspiratorial historians
Will will weave into the story and point out that it wasn't an accident that the French and the British for example word aside
Adding that it was worth tearing up the Ottoman Empire at this point
But if they hadn't
And somehow the Ottoman Empire existed another 10 or 20 years
Think about
The Inheritance it was about to come into
As a giant
Multi-ethnic
Islamic State
With oil wealth
Coming into the tummy it's fascinating to ponder how different the world might be
But if you remember of the government of Ottoman turkey when you hear the news about how you're going to be dismembered
As part of the secret agreements to become public
You're getting that information
About a week maybe even a little less
Then a week
On the heels of some other information that sort of should have warned you that this was coming because everybody
Awoke
To a declaration that was published on November 2nd 1917
It appears in the bunch of newspapers and kind of went viral like
You can say by the standards of the early 20th century
And the statement said this
Quote
His Majesty's government view with favour the establishment in Palestine of a national home
For the Jewish people
And will use their best endeavours to facilitate the achievement of this object
It being clearly understood that nothing shall be done which may Prejudice the civil and religious rights of existing now
Non Jewish communities in Palestine
For the rights and political status enjoyed by Jews in any other countries
And quote
She gets out of November 2nd
You got the news on the 8th of 9th
You know about the sykes-picot agreement in the others that that don't just tear up
Your Empire and give it to the Victorious Powers if they're going to be victorious that's still up in the air
But also
Gives it to people who are currently
In your Empire now most notably
Arab people
In a very similar move to what the Germans have done when they sent
Vladimir Lenin
To go into Russia and destabilize that country the British have been working with
Subjects of the Ottoman Empire and encouraging them to Rebel
There were a couple of important Arab tribal leaders
They were already sort of thinking along those lines and may have had contact with the British even before war broke out
Who buy 1950-1960 we're convinced
To rebel against the ottoman Overlord
They had a lot of British help
They eventually went from a bunch of ragtag gorillas
To a relatively nasty gorilla forest in the region although the impact that they had on the war has been hard
Target about forever with historian
It's a very colorful story involves
This person is called Lawrence of Arabia they made a movie about him but there's a lot more to that including the most important
People which released to tribal families
The British were able to convince
Rebelled against the Ottomans
Both of whom were important 1 control.
The area around Mecca
The other had a name that
Now Graces the front of the country that occupies the Arabian Peninsula Saudi
Any other family
Put Kings on the Thrones of multiple
Post World War 1 Middle Eastern Nations
The kings of a rock came from this family
The kings of places like Jordan the current king of Jordan is a descendant of this family
And that power emanated
From this first world war throwing their lot in
With the allies
And then
You're reaping the reward now it should be pointed out
That's the reward
Was not with a plan in the British after the war
Found themselves in a rather uncomfortable position
When they realize that they had promised multiple things
To multiple people
And often times it was the same stuff
This will lead to some embarrassing moments after the war
Over questions about fine printed what was really said and meant
Sir Henry Wilson who is the chief
Of the Imperial general staff in 1919 will tell another
British general
Quote
We've made so many promises to everybody in a contradictory sense
That I cannot for the life of me see how we can get out of our present mess without breaking our word to somebody
And quote
And it's easy to see
Why the Arabs have been promised things and what what it was hope that they would do the Rebellion
What's been more argued about in his more interesting for his stories of trying to figure out
You know what was
What was to be achieved by the Balfour Declaration
Duration
And there were so many different rationales that have been put forward that could be a study and interesting show in and of itself
I didn't run the gamut to from people who are suggesting that
The reason the British throw their weight behind
You know what Jewish homeland in Palestine have to do a personal relationship with a Jewish guy who helped
You know make it easier to create
A weapon
There's another theory that it was hope that they could have ate that the British wanted a friendly people to occupy this important area
Just want to help guard Britain's Imperial possessions in places like India
But my favorite of the many many theories out there for Wylie
Balfour Declaration this important
Benchmark moment in the history of modern Zionism happened
My favorite is the anti-Semitic
Reason that it might have happened if some people put forward
Which is that there were both a combination of real anti-semites out there
And people who were pretty educated in pretty sure
It was just a Canard
When people said that Jews ruled the world
But just in case it wasn't
Wouldn't it be worth it just to be on the safe side
If we made sure that Jewish public interest the world over
Was on our side
In Factory
British were even worried about rumors
That the Germans were going to offer the Jews a Homeland if Jews sort of signed on with the German cause
And so in an effort to make sure that if the Jews control the world they were on our side
That we were going to have
A statement made that said we supported
A return
To Palestine for Jewish folks I love that without. Just
That's the most perverse of all the excuses but none the less
What is did
What's a c
That later on we all understand will grow into
In the modern Middle East that we have today
There's also that one other
Little
Element
Of course
Frasier role in this
Story week
Mentioned it a little bit ago
The turns this region from
You know what you easily could have
Suggested might be a Backwater in the middle of nowhere after the war was over with some
Important religious
Sacred sites and whatnot but not much going on the way resources were value or anything where the great powers on the world
Old Stage with care much for this area
And instead trance
Forms this region
Into perhaps
The most strategically valuable spot on the
It's because all of a sudden
The world realizes
The importance that
Oil
Petroleum
Who's going to play in the 20th century world
And everybody sort of realize it at the
The same time
It's one of my favorite parts of the
More storage so hard to figure out
What people knew when
There had been vision
Is all throughout the development
Of the twentieth century realization that oil was going to be
Be huge
When they start pumping this stuff
In the 1840s and 1850s 1860s and a bunch of different places
And refining it in the main reason it's important in the 1800 remember the 1800
Is part of the Industrial Revolution the Industrial Revolution was a revolution that functioned
Mostly with cold
Is the energy source although steam was also use
The people that are
Making the decisions in the first world war going to be men in age groups who grew up
In the world
Powered by
Coal and steam
Oil was becoming quite valuable but for different reasons than
Energy
Well I guess you could still say was energy was it was in the illumination Source in a lot of places that used it
4 light
They also used it for lubrication and oil
But people did not foresee
What maybe youku
Tikal
The vehicular Revolution
That the first world war was so plainly
So to put on steroids it was coming anyway but you know how Wharton
Technological
The progress
Because
Well it's life or death
One of the famous stories of the first World War Z the famous battle of the Marne the story of the taxi cabs
Paris
Lining up to
Ferry troops to the very hot
Spot on the Battlefront that was in near danger of breaking this is all a romantic story that
Helps illustrate
One of the really early Trans in the first world war the use of
Vehicle
How to change the situation on the battlefield
We're all human history men have either been walking themselves or utilizing
Are natural animal power
In this battle they were starting to use things that were powered by gasoline
And you would go from
Cars in taxi cab
Two trucks
Two tanks
You have aircraft
Try to imagine and I'm sure Leonardo DaVinci could do a great sketch of it in the Renaissance
Try to imagine
Aircraft
That work
Cole
Or steam power
You kind of needed this
Dance
Portable energy source that became part of internal combustion engines
And all this stuff sort of happened
During the war
The Visionaries
I've been people like Churchill who it said
Convert the British Fleet
2 oil burning instead of coal
He was ahead of his time
In like 1908 the British government was making deals with
Oil Company in Iran for the anglo-persian oil company was very powerful and very important for a long time but once again
Indian shows
That some people were on top of this
Or
Play some historians who suggested
They may have just been doing this for the lubrication and illumination value they may not have foreseen the vehicular Revolution either
Once it
Strikes
You know even people who are doll that Visionary can see oh my gosh
Peanut oil is the coal of the 20th century
And I often think to myself you know
If you found the oil of the 21st century some clean-burning
Immensely wonderful replacement to oil they could do all these fantastic things but it only appeared
In a few separate isolated regions around the globe
What do you think
The governments of the world would do today about that
I mean here I've been critical of the great powers
For some of the horse Trading
That was apparent in all their War
I have probably overemphasized
Not to agree considering how much geopolitics
Did play a role in
Economics did play Roll
The first world war had a lot of reasons and the reasons that countries got into it had a lot of different causes a nuances as well
What is the horse
Trading nature of territories
It seems to stand out
So much to Modern sensibilities
It does make me think however
But if that 21st century version of oil
We're found tomorrow
But in limited
Amounting in limited areas
I do wonder whether our governments would act any
Differently in terms of the way they would approach it then that first world war leadership
If anything
I would imagine that what they learn from the first world war is not what to do or what
What not to do
But perhaps have a better sense of how you justify
Why what you do
In the first World War II our modern sensibilities into the changing sensibilities of the time
It all seemed a little too naked sometime
Once it was exposed to the light of day
And yet it's hard to blame any of these
Powers
For doing whatever it took
To see to it that you could get yourself
Some of this new
20th century version of
Cole
Because it could literally be a matter of
Life or death
In terms of remaining a great power
And as normally happens in the lottery for natural resources
Some places were blessed with lots of this stuff
And other places with almost nine
The United States is one of the first places where
The first great
Minister Saudi Arabia
The first great oil boom in the United States they fighted
Pennsylvania initially
And then in a ton of other
The United States is one of the great oil-producing nations of all time
And they really come into their own right when the oil really takes
Very very late 1800 early 90
Russia also has some wonderful reserves that have been underdeveloped
From very early on in Baku and places in what's now
Parts of Azerbaijan
And the problem they were having a course of this Bolshevik Revolution a lot of these
I'm out of the way places on the Russian periphery we're deciding maybe to go
On their own
And take the oil with them so
Temporary problems
Are the Russians in Baku but what that does is create
A situation where there's a giant wonderful
Supply of oil
Sitting there with no big government controlling it temporarily cuz the Bolsheviks
Allow their whole thing is in disorder and they're trying to get a handle on things in there
Preaching self-determination people are taking them up on the offer
Baku was all of a sudden you going to break away and become part of some maybe azerbaijani state
That is just too much of a
Temptation for a bunch of great powers that look at it and think
I bet I could get there with an army
If I tried hard enough and what if we could seize
The oil fields of Baku
The only other good source
Anywhere around Europe was in Romania
And about 1917 all the great Powers realize we got to get ourselves some oil
And the British and the French and the Germans 3 of The Great powers on the world stage when the first World War started
Some have good access to large
Amount of oil
It's hard
To suggest that there is any
Bigger National Security concern for those Nations at this point
Then to secure themselves a supply
Of this centuries
Great
Energy source in the one that's needed to power
The most cutting-edge weapons that you need to win any War
Easy to be critical
Are these people pursuing these kinds of policies
Look at what the stakes are
And from a purely realpolitik
Down and dirty
Standard
The arguments for imperialism in this case make a certain kind of sense
I mean what they're saying for example
Amongst British politician some of whom do not want to go in
And control these areas
Is the prime minister before the current prime minister in 1917 Herbert Asquith
And he didn't want anything to do with this region and all of his problems and factionalism I mean the Arab tribes that were fighting
Fighting on Britain's side as part of the Arab revolt
We're only part of the Arabs out there they were a lot of other air was it were very loyal to the ottoman government you had
Sunni and Shiite
Issues to deal with a mean to to a square that looks like a hornet
But he had a hard time fighting against the people on the other side of the argument
Who are making the point
That you were then going to Simply
Feed
Whatever could be taken from the Ottomans once they were gone
To your great power rivals
When the French will go in there and take the oil perhaps and then
They're strengthened while you are weakened and you don't have any access to the
Cole of the 20th century
As Asquith eventually said you know he said quote if we were to leave the other nations to scramble
For turkey without taking anything ourselves
We should not be doing our duty
And quote
Well if
Not having access to your own oil
I meant that your country would
Ball
To a second-class status
I think there would have been a lot of
People in Britain
A democratic government
Who would have said that it was their politicians Duty
To see that that didn't happen
Now the last time we checked in with the story
In the Middle East and all that area concerning the Ottomans fighting against the British in the French and the British Dominion troops
Places like India
At South Africa and Australia and New Zealand and places like that
Did the war hadn't been going particularly well
The Turks were tough they put up a pretty darn good resistance for a country that was supposed to be basically done
Having just bought a couple of Wars previously economics were in the disaster in everything
And instead the Turks put up a pretty darn
Spirit of resistance they've got the Germans in there helping them to
You're modernize a little here and there and the British simply were not prepared and who could be for the logistic
Nicole challenges
The trying to maintain large armies
Which the British did intend to maintain in the field anyway throughout their history
In the middle of the desert
The challenges were huge the church were tough
The British
Essentially had to retreat from Gallipoli that got trapped in a place called cook like we told you
In an earlier episode and had to surrender
It was not exactly their finest hour but in their defense
Most of their effort is in the meat grinder area on the Western Front
This is an area that
Some people referred to as a sideshow
And this gets back to the argument we
Mentioned earlier
Are between those in the Allied camp
They called themselves were called westerners
And the others who were called Easter
People whose idea said that the Western Front the meat grinders is the focal point of the war it's going to be the side
I did there
So taking troops and sending them to any other part of the war
Is
To work against what you need to be doing which is breaking through at the key point
The other group The easterners believed that throwing troops into the meat grinder where things were stalemated was
Calais waste of lives
When there were vulnerable points all on the rest of the map that could be exploited
Easier places to go
Winston Churchill in the second world war was always looking for the soft underbelly of Europe
What's the weight of phrase was turned in the first world war there were easterners looking for the soft underbelly of Europe
And
Best argument I ever heard for who was right
Because I was looking at Lloyd George's Memoir the other day end
20 years after the war he still justifying and wagging a finger in the face of the western you're saying we were right
And the westerners are saying that they were right
The German general
Ludendorff it pointed out that yes
The west and the Western Front meat grinder was where the war would be decided
But if there was a kid
Astrophe on any of the other fronts in the war
That that would impact German power on the Western Front leading to a loss there
So that they were interconnected
All these non Western Front battles are sideshows
Unless those fronts
And then it's a disaster
In 1917 the British who have changed generals
And who have now put a meticulous effort into
Just
Slowly but surely building up the infrastructure that you need to maintain an Army in the field every just think of the
Pipelines of water
Did they build from miles upon miles of her miles to go out to where the troops are going to have to be in Trench
Give me the amount of effort that's required the buildup of troops and everything else but by 1917
They begin to push the Turks back every way
Do your 1917 and especially the latter half of the year
Cease multiple victories
On the part of the British LED Allied Forces in
Places like Mesopotamia and Palestine
Lots of
Outflanking some wonderfully
Clever
Spy Maneuvers and some
Fantastic
Bravery in audacity on the part of
Some of these Dominion mounted infantry forces for example
End up creating a situation where
The British High command can see Jerusalem
The holy city of holy cities right sacred to at least three major
Religions Islam
Christianity and Judaism thinking see Jerusalem within range and they know that they're going to take it if this
Your momentum continues
But after
Dealing with passchendaele in the mud in the blood of the shock in the sense of never-ending War which just wraps up in me
Mid November
Boy George ass
British general Allenby
If you can manage to capture the holy city by Christmas
Says it will be a great Christmas present
A little pick-me-up
If you will
After all of the horrible
Lloyd George gets his wish granted
On December 11th
With the British and Allied Forces already in the city
They receive a surrender notice from the Turkish representative
Who writes quote
Due to the severity of the siege of the city and the suffering that this peaceful country has endured from your heavy
Guns and for fear that these deadly bombs will hit the holy places
We are forced to hand over to you the city
True saying Al hussaini the mayor of Jerusalem
Hoping that you will protect Jerusalem
The way we have protected it for more than 500 years
And quote
Doesn't that note
Sort of Bring It All home in terms of
The immense age of some of these
Nation-states that we're dealing with here
There's a ton of irony and symbolism
When the Allied Forces captured Jerusalem
Start with the fact
That Christians and captured Jerusalem before
In 1099 during the First Crusade
Was a very big deal at the time
Followed by a terrible Massacre but the Christians managed
To hold the city for a couple hundred years
Islamic General Saladin the Great
Record by the way
Will retake the city during the third crusade in the late 1200
There will be a major crusade in the Middle Ages launched against these very ottomans
You know when there are a lot
Younger and more vigorous of an m
And now Christian forces
For once again moving into this city
Propaganda
Possibilities of an event like this are huge
But it also has some real-world post-war implications you know that old line that
Possession is 9/10 of the law
Well that will certainly be the case after the war
When the British are involved in
Not always wonderfully nice negotiations with the French
And people who are locals in that region over who gets what
There have been some agreements during the war that
Palestine and Jerusalem should be internationalized
The British didn't like that idea as much after the war and since they were the ones governing
There since December 1917
Gave them a unique ability to decide how things were going to go so important in a real-world sense to
The entire affair
And its importance of the entry into this
Holiest of cities was understood and Stage managed to degree
The British government had some
Ideas on the way we would say today the Optics
With a visual should go
In 1898 the German Emperor the Kaiser had visited
Jerusalem again with lots of visuals and Optics and lots of photographs and lots of propaganda
Benefits for doing so and he
Kind of
Offended some of the religious Folks by not really seeming humble enough in the face of evil such intense sacred
Vesper
Yeah three of them
Top religions on the planet
It was even a story that the Turks had to destroy a part of the ancient old
You know Israeli part of the walls
To make room for the Kaiser's car so we so we can bring the car in whether or not that
True it certainly made him look bad and before Allenby
Becomes the first Christian conqueror in more than 500 years to walk into Jerusalem
He gets a little advice from British general
Robertson
Who tells him in a telegram quote
In the event of Jerusalem being occupied it would be a considerable political importance if you want to
Officially entering the city
Dismount at The City Gate
And enter on foot
German Emperor Road in Ennis and went around a better man than he walked
Advantage of contrasting conduct will be obvious
And quote
By December 1917
It looks as though it won't take a whole lot for the British in the French and the Dominion forces
To strike
At the Turks and just sort of
Push the entire house of cards over
In some ways the Turks are.
Doing themselves any good because when the Russians pull out of the war
It leaves a ton of territories that have lots of Turks in it
The open for Turkish conquest and the Turks are sending armies that might be better used against the British in the French
Into this territory were places like Armenia and Azerbaijan and all those places are
In order to get new territory while they're losing old territory
Nonetheless whether or not the French and the British can just
Pushover the house of cards now becomes a bit of a moot point
Because very early in 2-19-18
When the finishing touches on any idea to do that would have to be in play
All of a sudden
Everything
Is
Needed back on the Western Front
Allen bees going to have his forces his best forces ripped from him and no reinforcements or extra forces added
Because all of a sudden
Just when everything look like
The United States was going to come in and turn the tide of the war
The Germans attempt to turn the tide of the war first
And we mentioned before
The real differences in sodas
The feeling the ebb and the flow in the Rhythm
Of the two World Wars
The first and the second world
In the Second World War
There was a certain point where
Where the outcome of the war was no longer in doubt
But it was quite a ways
Between that moment and the end of the war
It's probably safe to say like
Late 1943
Everyone knows that the Germans in their side or not winning that
No one knows how many people are going to have to dive
Before the outcome is finally settled
But everyone knows what the outcome going to be you can concoct some
Real real long shot scenarios where the Germans for example get Atomic weapons first or something like that and changed the course of history
But by and large
It was a moot point
Past a certain age
Probably 843
I said
The first Wars Rhythm was completely unlike that
There were
Yeah if you wanted to say
Who had the advantage most of the time it was the Allied on Time force if you don't continually putting their weight on the
The other side wearing them down
But the other side led by Germany would strike out and lash out at certain times with huge blows
End of the easily could have knocked the other side
The last of these Germany throws
In early 1918 even the members of German easy to Upper military castricone
The last
Card
Now I have to set a few things up before we understand about this lab
Card situation
The first is understanding with the Warriors
Germany's got some good stuff happening and some bad stuff
We just mentioned one of the bad things
The situation with their Turkish Ally in the Middle East is starting to turn for the worst
Write the latter part of 1917 not so great
But that is offset by good things would have been happy
In that same time. We said is so important October November December 1917
The German send actually not that much but it made a big difference some help to their austro-hungarian allies you been
Fighting Italians
Forever
In the region of the river is Sansa
They have had 11 battle
Girls of the isonzo to this point in the war
So you can tell how much things are moving
Right at the stalemate
Is Alpine peach in their cutting
Hideout into the ice it's this crazy Alpine War they're fighting
Both sides are really tired in the Italian troops are really tired of of the guy who's been running the show for
Dollar General in charge of
Of their effort he's really sort of
A stickler and they've had it with him and they've been they've been
Like their austro-hungarian enemies
Putting up with a lot for years
There's a lot of Senseless death certificate has been terrible
And then all of a sudden the German send
You know seven or eight divisions there to act as sort of The Cutting Edge of another offencive
The 12th
I songs o
But it gets
Known by a different name because it stands out from the other eleven battles of the isonzo it's often called The Battle of corporate
The reason that stands out from the other
Battles of the isonzo
Is because this time something decisive have
The Italian
Get smashed
And who can blame them the Germans are
Once again using an even more perfected version of new tact
And new artillery methods
And we said before what you're quickly watching occur in the four years of the first Warrior watching these armies transfer
Form from something more like
You know the franco-prussian war in the 1870s
Just something more like
The Second World War
And you can see it
As the tactics develop year after year from stupidly walking in the machine gun fire in order Rose of men to wear
Infiltration tactics are taking over and you're beginning to see a lot of the same methods being employed by
These armies for the very first time
Did every army in the world still uses today involve
Fire and movement the mutual support
Bypassing strong point
From the Germans do this
To the poor Italians
And the Italians get
I mean 300 thousand people surrender
That's how bad it is
And yet
The Italians are able to move like 60 miles back reform their lines
Keep from falling apart totally and await helping the British in the French you have to take
You know troops again from the Western Front
To bolster the other area but what it means is
By the end of 1917
The Germans have not
Out a bunch of their opponents in this war when you look at how they started the war with all these enemies against them
Look at what they've done
1959 knockout Serbia
In 1916 they knockout Romania
In 1917 they just knocked out Russia
From the war
And given
Italy such a bloody lip that nothing is going to happen down there for
While
But now in early 1918
For the first time in the war
The Germans face
The British and the French
Without
A whole lot of distractions
They don't have the Russians on the other side
And
They have
A small window of opportunity
Before millions of Americans
Start arriving in Europe
The swamp
This is the way Winston Churchill
Describes
The situation
Set up
Will say and then I'm going to contrast that with the way out of Hitler
And remember that both of these people are writing to specific audio
Churchill's writing two people
Who are
In the especially British and American audiences in and really
Super patriotic romantic sort of an approach
Hitler is writing
This material for a bunch of
Bitter War veterans
Who
Still ache over what they
Experienced an endless feeling of betrayal
And end the bitterness
Since the war ended so they have different audiences their writing for
What contrasting their Styles in the way they set this up is intrigued
Churchill describes
The situation in the number and remember
The end of 1917 the British were still in shock
From the battle that they still call passchendaele
Churchill says quote
As the passchendaele struggled died away in the storms in mud of winter
The military rulers of Germany address themselves to a new situation
The collapse of Russia had enabled them to transport a million men
And 3000 guns from the Eastern to the Western Front
For the first time therefore since the invasion
They found themselves possessed of a definite superiority over the Allies in France
But this superiority was fleeting
The United States declared war and was Army but have not yet arrived
Once the great masses of American manhood could be trained and equipped
Transported have brought into the line of battle all the numerical Advantage Germany had gained from the destruction of
Russia would be more than counterbalanced
At the same time the German Main Headquarters new the grave losses the British army had suffered at passchendaele
And felt themselves entitled to count Upon A Marked Decline and its strength and fighting quality
Lastly the amazing character of the German Austrian victory over the Italians at corporate
Glitter temptingly
And quote
He then goes on to say
It would have been a great time for the Germans to open negotiations with us
Instead they chose to attack
Before we get to Hitler's view of the situation it's worth asking
You know what were the Germans fighting
What did they hope
To achieve what was the best case scenario in any sort of ends of the war
And this is another difference between the first and the Second World War
In the second world war as soon as the Americans had said that
Unconditional surrender
You know what's supposed to be the
Victory conditions
It made the war one of those conflicts where you're going to get with call the carthaginian
In a reminiscent of how the Romans in the third
Punic Wars treated the city of Carthage total Destruction
Right total occupation
Total submission in Domination
Unconditional surrender are the
In the first world war like so much of the stuff that went on during this time.
The surrender was going to
Everyone presumed could it be some sort of a negotiated a fair going to be a bargaining session
And both sides are fighting to be the superior person at the bargaining table
Write the one who can in
Cyst
On better terms
As general ludendorff the German military leader points out what they're fighting for and why they have to keep attack
He says quote
Germany could only make the enemy incline to Peace by fighting
It was first of all necessary to shake the position of Lloyd George
And clemenceau by a military victory
Before that was done peace was not to be thought
And quote
Now let's remember what ludendorff means
Is it he needs US military Victory to get the kind of
If he wants
Write a piece that for example give Germany
Either director de facto control of places like Belgian for exam
That's his bargaining position in any sort of agreement that ended the war
That's what they're fighting for and the other side is too
Although more and more one of the conditions that the Americans and the British and the French were insisting on is it the German
Form of government has to change
They can't be a monarchy anymore
Well
That may leave Germany still alive but it means if you are the Emperor of Germany or any of these high-ranking people that are
Part of the German monarchy
It might as well be total war against you
Germany may live on but you're not going
Adolf Hitler
Is a
Soldier
In the first world war as we had mentioned earlier
His book Mein Kampf which is written for this
German veterinarian
House were rotting so we mentioned a little earlier
He talks about the
Sculptures in the shirkers and all these people
That are beginning to sort of
The German Army in the back from the homefront that's the way it's portrayed and when you read ludendorff
I'll Memoirs to written during a similar time.
He has the same thing going where
You know that the reason that the German troops are in danger is not because
The enemy will hurt them because they're sort of this Victorious entity on the battlefield it's because the homefront will let them down
Before
You know Hitler sums up the situation that we're facing right here at the beginning of 1918 he goes off
On
Some strikes that are taking place during this time. In Germany
There's a Naval Strike that happens in 1917 that that's disconcerting
And then several hundred thousand Munitions workers go on strike right at the beginning of the new year in 1918
And then again when the German government punishes the ringleaders of the strike they send them to the front as punishment but that
It means that they're infiltrating Audi's military units
And they're infiltrating them
With these ideas with ludendorff and Hitler
Thai right to Bolsheviks
Hitler ties bolshevism by the way the Jews
So right there you even begin to see the origins
Of the stab-in-the-back
And here's the way Hitler
In his in his
Well what are you going to say best-selling book mine comp
Describe the situation the Germans found themselves in
After they giving the Italians a bloody nose a corporative after they've knocked all these other people out of the war and after finding out
You know that they're going to attack
Quote
Toward the end of 1917
The low point of the Army's dejection seems to have passed
The whole Army took fresh hope and fresh courage after the Russian collapse
The conviction that the war would end with the Victory of Germany after all began to seize the troops more and more
Again singing could be heard
And the Calamity Janes became rarer
Again people believed in the future of the father
And quote
The Calamity Janes are these sculptures in sherpas and people who say
Anti-patriotic things were
Or negative things about the war effort
He says quote
Especially the Italian collapse of autumn 1917 that had the most wonderful effect
In this Victory we saw proof of the possibility of breaking through the front
Even aside from the Russian theater of war
A glorious Faith float again into the hearts of the millions enable them to await spring 1918
With relief
I'm confident
The photo was visibly depressed
In this winter he remained quieter than usual
This was the lull before the storm
And quote
Did Hitler sums up
His view of this moment
And what the Allies were facing now with a sort of Germany Unleashed he says quote
In the winter of 1917 to 1918
Dark clouds appeared for the first time in the firmament of the Allied world
For nearly four years they have been a sailing the German Warrior and had been unable to Encompass his downfall
And all this while the German had only his shield arm free for defense
Baba sword was obliged to strike
Now we may eat
Now in the south
But now it last the Giants back was free
Streams of blood flown before he administered final defeat to one of his foes
Now in the West
His shield was going to be joined by his sword
Up till then the enemy had been unable to break his defense
And now he himself was facing attack
The enemy feared him and trembled for their Victor
And quote
Now in one sense this is a post first world war Hitler
Putting a Rosy picture on this thing you know what here we were going to defeat them and then we got stabbed in the back by the
Jews and Bolsheviks right
But at the same time
There's some truth to a couple of these things one
The Bolsheviks were having any
Influence on German
And that attempt by
Ludendorff
To get rid of his next door neighbor in the apartment complex by burning his apartment down is big
Beginning to change Germany little bit and ludendorff writes about this in his Memoirs in a way remember writing years
Later so we can pretend to have hindsight
He basically acts like he understood the risk was dangerous he thought they could contain your the Bolshevik
Intellectual contagion but he knew that there was a chance it wouldn't work out that way
And there's something to that in terms of
Why the Germans were all of a sudden beginning to
Start the show real
Cracks in the facade of the home
And some of these people should be pointed out that a guy like ludendorff or Hitler thinks are Bolsheviks
Are probably more like
Social Democrat
Frappuccino mild socialists
I like ludendorff anyone who's thinking that the war might have gone on too long
Or that Germany instead of an emperor might do better with a representative democracy or a republic or something
That to them is traitor
Radicals
You might as well be a Bolshevik
None the less think about what these people
We're going through four years of war all these countries in a sentence
Sacrificing their future
What each generation of youngsters
That they call up and throw into the mall
Inter sacrificing their path
Two sticks
Cannibalizing
Their countries
Historical in long-term asset
Recorded the English wife of a German nobleman princess blue shirt
Evelyn blue sure writing in her diary
She told this story that is just heartbreaking about
You know the fact that the Germans don't have enough ammunition anymore and they're starting to go into the society and intake things
To melt down
One historian I read said that during this. More than 10,000 Church
Or melted down
Princess blue shirt tells a story
She says quote
There are other signs to pathetic in their way of the increasing scarcity of metal
Breviary where the old church bells and even the organ pipes
Are being dragged from the churches and turned into ammunition
Whilst owing to the scarcity of oil the sanctuary lamp
Such a dear familiar sight in Catholic churches May no longer shed
Tender light before the Tabernacle
In a small town near here
A sad little ceremony took place the other day
The ancient church bell which should run the people from The Cradle to the Grave for 300 years and more was
Requisitioned by the military Authority
The grief felt by the inhabitants
Was so great that they determined to do their ancient friend all the honor they could
And after having performed the regular funeral service for the dead over it
A procession was for
Headed by the priest
In his vestments headed acolyte
Swinging their incense
Any inhabitant
Following the Bell
Which was covered with wreaths and flowers and hand it over to the military authorities under tears and protestations
And quote
I look at that story is kind of symbolic
The greatness of Old Europe at the height
And the high-water marks of its wealth in
And civilization
And you hundreds of years
Glorious path behind those with a
Girding the whole society
Being ripped apart and thrown into the mall on the furnace
To provide the implements that are needed
To fight the war
It is destroying
It's high place on the world stage
This is a sort of tragic irony
But isn't confined to Germany by the way this is how Britain and France and Russia and all these old line Powers kind of feel they're trapped in this car
Sounds like now
It is chewing up their wealth
Destabilizing the structures of their society in once again
Taking the next class of draftees who reached
18 years old
And throwing them into the meat grinder to
Think of the
On these people who are commanding all these armies on
On both sides
And ludendorff you can't help but think about this guy cuz he's the one who gets
Decide
How you play Germany's last car
Central Powers last card think of the people that are counting on him
I'm a completely human except
Paramed imagine
The stress and responsibility that falls on this one guy shoulders more than anyone else on that side obviously
Help and staffs
In other people to consult and what-have-you but basically the number one person's responsibility is
His
He's got to plan
The biggest battle in world history
And the stakes
AR
Everything
Wow
This is the biggest encounter between
The cutting-edge militaries of the world that has ever happen
And that's what ludendorff
Is planning
And it's an immensely complicated
Affair with
Detail beyond belief
Ludendorff
We'll start moving
Troops from the Eastern Front have been fighting the Russians
On trains all the way over to the West before the Russians even sign a peace treaty
By the spring of 1918 he's moved a million German soldiers who had been fighting the Russians
Over to the west where they can now be used against the French and the British
The German Army in the west numbers over 3 million
Soldiers
By Spring 1918
And ludendorff has a plan that he's going to
And put into place that that involves
Throwing multiple punches
At the French and the British like a 5 punch combination
Annie's going to use about a million soldiers
Perform V
Michael named after Saint Michael is the first of these
Punches but the entire Affair will sometimes be called
The 1918 spring offensive
The German soldiers referred to as
Sometimes it just a great battle in France that shows you how big it's going to be
One part of it is sometimes referred to as the peace offencive
And sometimes the entire Affair is called
The kaiserschlacht
The emperor
Historians have been fascinated by
ID series about
Ever since we're a couple of Major Reese
What is the scope
And the other other state
This is the largest
Battle the world
Never seen the complexity is unbelievable
It's very hard battle to follow or explain or talk about
It in the front will be miles long it will involve millions of men
The complexity
In terms of trying to plan and arrange and get ready
For one of these big offensives in five or six months which is your planning window
Is perhaps the most
Complex
Task human beings have ever attempted to
I think you could say that there are bigger things like Friday
Creating a global society which were in the process of doing right now that's a very high
But you can do that overtime and build on the achievements of previous generations and sort of involved towards a solution
Complex problems
These people have a Time window and it short
Get the kaiserschlacht done within 5 months booms got to be ready on the 21st of March get it done I mean
Just the attempts to
Cheap the Allies in the dark about where it's coming
How can plexus help
Neither will move troops and equipment at night
They will cover up the artillery gun Wheels with cloth so you can't hear the
Staples roust out the civilian population in all the towns in March around all directions to confuse
You know Allied Observers
They will scramble and use false radio messages and just because you know this is sort of a transition. In history
Just to cover all their bases they will also pull out the carrier pigeon
Including carrier pigeons
Captured from the other side
Put false notes in the little compartment
You know in their leg and send them off
Call covering all your bases isn't it
But think of the plan again complexity in all the work that goes on
The other
Fascinating aspect historians are the stakes
When do you have
Takes like this
Biggest war in human history
And is one historian put it ludendorff and the Germans have six
Months
To change the course of the war here
After that the
Numerical Advantage the Americans will provide will be overwhelming
Do you have this window of opportunity
And it's an all-or-nothing thing
Some historians have argued that the Germans should have just
Going on the defensive here Duggan
And made the Allied Forces fight until 1920 or 1921
Before the
The mounting losses would force them into some sort of a favorable peace but that kind of ignores how bad things are on the home front
The German Army can withstand
These Allied attacks are going to lose the people back in what homework
A year past the infamous turnip winter
What happens when the turnip winter is the good old days right
Diluting open the Germans don't just put this attack together
They're excited about it
The German troops are almost
Ecstatic the morale is sky-high they want a chance to win the war
This is why this first punch operation Michael is so important
Because this is the punch where all the optimism is employ
Place right everybody's drinking the Kool-Aid
Ludendorff decides to
You know up his
Gamble Auntie little bit more not only see gambling with this attack but he's going to
You know essentially pull out the rocket fuel
From
The great mass of troops he goes through and calms his army for the best man write the healthiest the strongest
That one's of the highest morale the veterans who weren't cynical yet all these people
For better than the rest of the herd
Bird and pull them out
Put them in the special units and give them the best weapons again pulled away from the great mass of people
And the special training
What they called special training in the first world war today we would call
Standard
They called them Stormtrooper tactics we called them
Fire and move tactics and every army in the world uses
Now
Nonetheless what ludendorff is done here has created initial
Advantage
Jennifer himself
Because his best troops are going to go up against the great mass of French and British troops that they run into
They will give out the Lion's Share of casualty
Did the French and the British in the allies
But they will also take the Lion's Share
This is a gamble because
When ludendorff uses these best troop she's going to use them up and if they haven't won by that point
He's going to be left
With the not best
Troops
The leftover
People who had their best weapon stripped from them and given to the other guys people who haven't been trained in the latest tactics
People who it's expected are going to Simply move up
And occupy the trenches that have already been conquered
It's a Campbell
And on March 21st
It's not a gamble lutador us to worry about
Because he's got
I'll be Stormtrooper and assault unit
Waiting for
The moment
To jump off
Synchronizing their watches and waiting for what will be the largest
Cannonade in history
To kick-off
March 21st
Operation Michael
The first punch of the German multi punch combination
Aim primarily at the British
Some 10000 artillery piece
Uses will open fire
At about Dawn somewhere in the four
Shower
They will only fire only
Forever if you're under Fire the lonely fire 4 about
4 hours
It's what's called a hurricane bombard
Very different than what the Allies were doing through most of the war
Where they will bombard for weeks on end some
It's right at the song
In 1916 the big artillery battle vellfire 1.7 million shells in the first week and it's famous
Oh my gosh
But every first world war major offensives out does the earlier ones in this one
They fire
Becomes a contest
Like a statistic in the
Guinness Book of World Records but they fire 1.1 million shells in 4
And it's conducted like a symphony
Death
The Germans have brought in
All of their big
I guess you could call the military stars to this battle
One of them is this artillery conductor
Georg
Brooklyn
His name is but his nickname is
Breakthrough Muller
We have a whole Theory ended even perfecting how to use these artillery barrage
And part of his theory involves
The idea that you don't need to destroyed
The enemy positions which is what's always been done all you need to do is neutralize
All you need to do with that Machine Gun Nest to stop them from shooting long enough
So that the Infantry doesn't get killed on the way to taking out the Machine Gun Nest themselves
So use it a lot more gas
First of all
And
He has a hole
Order that all this come to the meat first he shoots the gas
That doesn't kill you but it's like tear gas that makes you gag and vomit and it makes you rip off your gas
But then he hit you with the phosgene gas but if you're not wearing your gas mask kills you
Can also use mustard gas which is
A long life
So it's like spraying that
The ant spray that will still kill the ants a week later even though it's dried up
The mustard gas is shot of all these important Crossroads in areas and Heights and observation post
Either
You get out
We are so covered up in gas masks and everything you can hardly function and the Germans just want you to be impeded
Right you just have to be not functioning long enough
For the waves of German soldiers to be free and clear
To overrun your position
It also has the added benefit of not making
The terrain in front of your dancing
Look like
The cratered surface
The Moon
Large shell craters and
Become a barrier all
What's owning previous battles
In this one the German archery was going to minimize that
Keep the way open for
Quicken shocking advance
The artillery opens fire on March
21st
You know it's strange to say that they're surprised cuz everyone knew this was coming but the surprise is in the intensity in the locations and what
The Kaiser
The Emperor of Germany and the face of the German military Hindenburg are reportedly at the battle
The Kaiser was known to have this wooden tower that sort of like a ranger station at wreck
We could try to see
A battle
What you something
In the night
Strange people came out
With picnic basket
First major battle
US Civil War to watch
Anna Kaiser and Hindenburg
We're supposedly at this battle to watch it unfold
Winston Churchill was also there when the cannonade opened up
And you get this feeling
These are jelly like figure that you just not going to miss any big historical event if he can
Avoid that and he was at this battle too and he gives one of the
Original and much quoted account of what it was like you said you know just walking around the room was waiting for something to happen
He woke up from his sleep somewhere in the 4-Hour and is relatively silent
And then
Quote
Suddenly after what seemed about a half an hour
The silence was broken by six or seven very loud and very heavy explosion several miles away
I thought they were our 12-inch guns
But they were probably mine
And then exactly is a Pianist runs his hand across the keyboard from treble to Bass
There Rose in less than one minute
The most tremendous cannonade I shall ever hear
And quote
You said that quote
The weight and intensity of the bombardment surpassed anything
Which anyone had ever known before
And quote
Ernst Junger the German Soldier we talked about
Sometimes in the story is also at this battle
He's on the opposite side of the shelling rights and not even the side that's being shelled and he says
Tell made every other event he been to in this war look like a tea party
And he was at many of the big battles
Right
Petit Park
He said that the shelling
Sing to suspend the laws of nature
Couldn't light a match or anything because the shockwaves even as far away as
The German troops were
Would love it right out he says that if you looked over the Enemy Lines all you saw is rolling clouds of flame
And it looked like the way the desert looks when you look in the distance and the heat is shimmering and makes you almost see mirages
She said that that's what it looks
On the side of the people being shallow
The effect
On the British troops
Is almost like being Punch-Drunk
A private in the 1st West Yorkshire regiment
Who was there
I explained it this way quote
Nobody could stand more than three hours of sustained shelling before they started feeling sleepy and numb
You're hammered after
3 hours
And you're there for the picking when he comes over
It's a bit like being under an anesthetic
You can't put a lot of resistance up
On the other front side been on there been so much of our resistance that whenever Jerry opened up our artillery open
Quieted him down
But there was no retaliation this time
He had a free do with us
And quote
I should point out that the Germans called the British Tommy
And the British called the Germans Jerry
Offensive that's how that have
Historian Alexander Watson quotes
A German battalion.
Ernst
Determine
Who recorded that men reacted to shelling quote
For the most part with the feeling of enormous sleepiness
And then said that you get both emotional and physical change
In men who are being shell
Also think about the people on the receiving end
I was about to be in ground attack
After they've experienced something that does this to
Wiedermann says quote
The eyes pop out of their socket
The expression becomes fixed in glass
The facial skin loses all of its red color
The skin becomes yellow
The cheek bones protrude
The lips are shut tight and sticky spittle tax up the tongue to the roof of the mouth
The heart Works in short convulsive Beats
Breathing becomes slower
From time to time a cold shudder runs through the body in the teeth chatter
Every spoken word
Spelt is agony
And quote
Watson goes to point out that
Surveys have shown that
The troops were particularly scared
An unsettled
He writes quote
Not only did artillery cause more casualties than any other weapon on the Western Front
But those injuries that it didn't inflict wear off in Grievous
Contemporary psychiatrist agreed that men's primary fear was not death
Mutilation
Wounds to the stomach jaw and eyes were particularly dreaded
It is not significant that artillery fire was more likely than any other weapon to cause head wounds
Moreover
Shells were terrifying because it Lieutenant Saint leg or somewhat coyly observed they could quote make such
A mess of 1
And quote
Watching continue
Quote the weapon eviscerate
Maimed and disfigured
Body part could be scattered over wide distances
And legs and arms blown into trees by the force of explosion
Such sites were obviously extremely disturbing
Especially when the victims were friends or comrade
As Lieutenant yoxall remark quote
When you seen the she'll fall into the midst of six men and packed three of them away in a sandbag
One wonders whether anything matters
And quote
This is when you realize though
These people are veterans
What's in this combat in that this makes a huge difference
These people have been hardened
To their current
State by degrees
I seen many horrible things in the path and living through
Situations that while they might not be as Extreme as what they're about to go through
AR
Smaller versions on the way there
It's like lifting a smaller amount of weight on your way up to lifting a greater amount of weight not like taking
A week civilian Like Yours Truly and throwing him into the kaiserschlacht
Tomorrow
And then expecting him to endure under shellfire
And while there are certainly people
That fell apart under shellfire broke and ran under shellfire lost their minds
In at the Shell Shocked me a lot of those kinds of things The Amazing Story here and I think this is what happened made people
Throughout history since it happened
Is it the bat bat vast majority people stayed there
In those
Positions
Having a logical
Part of their brain
And self-control somehow overriding their animal instincts that must have been
Screaming at them to Simply flee
But as I said these
People
I've been hard
I wish they'd seen before
The very day before March 21st before this artillery barrage happens
Ernst Junger
Is in
A shell hole
In
A relatively safe part of the line
Henan officer are in one and a whole bunch of men are in the Big Shell hole next to his it's like an Amphitheater he
He says
And they're sort of having a meeting everybody stack their weapons and if comp
And there she'll fire going on and all of a sudden so if a random stray shell falls into that
Big crater that's built like an Amphitheater
It had a hundred men in it
It's maybe the most gruesome upsetting part
Of youngers gruesome and upsetting story and he says
After the explosion it's so freaked him out and this is Ernst Junger we don't want to take one of the veterans veterans
Eagles tearing off running in a sort of a panic before eventually he'll stop himself and realizes he should go back and try to help someone
But then that same Ernst Junger
You know that next morning whatever it is 12:15 hours afterwards is going to be sitting
Annies jumping off point
Synchronizing his watch watching this artillery drop on the British and getting ready to go over the top and attack
What's amazing is when he does so
He does so
In an almost
Getty fashion
Hard to describe that the mood that these soldiers going over the top
You're not suggesting this battle I mean there's not necessarily representative but he says everybody else we're sort of
Kind of on the edge of Sanity almost
Berserk but at the same time
He said that they would talk to each other and it would only come out in little fragments or sentences and he said anybody who was observing us would think we were
Incredibly happy
At the same time he's talking about this rage that's coming over him and he squeezes his eyes and the tears are coming out and he's
Ready to hurt somebody
What's funny when you read it
Is
It kind of reminds you something that maybe in the back of your head you knew already
I think
When you look at these modern soldiers coming from nice backgrounds like ourselves
In a well trained and educated in all these kinds of things
We somehow assumed that the very tendencies that we will freely admit that ancient be
Peoples had and Vikings had and all these kinds of people that could get up into a berserk rage
You know when kill a victim and stand up and celebrating it and enjoy being a warrior that somehow because we have
The aircraft in artillery and machine guns and a nice that it's all gone
And in some people it is
It's putting some people it's not
An astronaut goes looking for someone to kill
When he jumps out of these
Jumping off point after the artillery barrage lifts in the German Army attacks on March 21st
The big sweep
An operation Mike
It's foggy
By the way
This will be one of the things that ludendorff will get lucky with a couple of times in his multi-punch combination
Fog is not great for the German attackers it makes it difficult but it's in the night
Mayor for the Defenders
The Germans are using water sometimes called infiltration tactics and if it's foggy
Infiltration tactics are a lot more
Affect
Pretty sure set up all these Defense Zone
With Crossing machine gun firing all these things were all these
All these different defense readouts can help each other
But because of the fog they can't see anything
And then all of a sudden
The
Germans are jumping into the trenches where the British soldiers are
Catching them totally off guard
Historian Peter Hart
Quote Captain Charles Miller who was on the line at the Germans approach for their initial attack you know
Before 9 a.m. in the morning of the 21st through the fog and says quote
The first attackers were into the trench long before the Mist lifted
I was so occupied with the flanks that I barely saw them
Before they appeared out of the Mist and lip down into the trench
In a moment we were all mixed up in hand-to-hand fighting
I had two men coming at me with your bayonet
One of them I think I shot with my revolver while I Sergeant standing just behind me. The other at Point Blank
Range with his rifle barrel over my shoulder
Almost at the same second a German stick bomb came whistling into the trench from the parapet
Right into the bunch of us
And killed or wounded practically the whole lot of us
English and German alike
Weather was actually this bomb or a band that stabbed that gave me the wound in my neck I don't know
It might have been either
For a moment we were clear
But there was a nasty little shambles around us
Sergeant Adcock would just saved my life
Having his head blown off
I felt awfully we can discover the river of blood was flowing from my neck
I tried to bandage it but the bandage wouldn't hold
Before they attacked us again they brought up some trench mortar
And knock Seven Bells out of us
Then swarmed into the trench
By that time there were only a handful of us left on our feet
And all I suppose wounded
I got another wound from a stick bomb would you put a bit of metal into MiFi
Before I Collapse
I tried to give the surrender signal and hoped I succeeded they're buying saving a few lies
We've done our best
What are the things that happens with these modern battles
Is that they really turn into
Hundreds of smaller encounter that when you add them up together equal this big thing going on over 40 miles
But when you read the accounts of these battles they all sound like
You know
Me and 10 guys took that Machine Gun Nest a hundred yards away and it took us three hours we lost two men and we can
Killed everybody Machine Gun Nest and then we continue to move on
That's an encounter in this war right
So every time you read what it sounds like an isolated little incident in fact
Younger when he comes upon the first enemy soldier he sees on March 21st
If the
Private encounter this moment where Yonkers
In this
Almost berserk mood that he just talked about giddy they've been drinking alcohol their Punch-Drunk from
All the artillery images of sensory overload
Macy's the Santa me
Annie sez
Quote
Then I saw my first enemy
A figurine Brown uniform wounded apparent
Crouch 20 Paces away in the middle of the battered path
With his hands propped on the ground
I turned the corner and we caught sight of each other
I saw him jump as I approached and stare at me with gaping eyes
Walleye with my face behind my pistol stocked up to him slowly and coldly
A bloody scene with no Witnesses was about to happen
It was a relief to me finally to have the photo in front of me within reach
I set the mouth of the pistol at the man's Temple
He was too frightened to move
What my other fish grabbed hold of his tunic
Feeling medals and badges of rank
An officer
He must have held some Command Post in these Trench
With a plaintive sound he reached into his pocket
Not to pull out a weapon
What a photograph
Which she held up to me
I saw him on it
Surrounded by numerous family
What you all standing on a Terrace
It was a plea from another world
Later I thought it was blind chance that I let him go and plunged on Word
That one man of all often appeared in my dream
I hope that meant he got to see his homeland
And quote
So even
In the blind rage
Of the berserk moment that younger had described earlier
He was able to pull himself from the brink and answer that plea from another world
I let that Soldier live
Mercy could be a dangerous commodity on the battlefield
Like this
Very normal for soldiers
Going past
Something like a bunker that might have enemy troops in it to just simply throw grenades
Down the stairs into the bunker
Not worried about it just keep on moving
They were also
Killings
In hot blood a lot of
It was normal for example of troops kept firing at you all the way up till you were almost on top of them and then tried to
Surrender good luck with that
It was killing In Cold Blood to on all sides
Buying large when they could
Both sides like to take prisoners
None of these Army surrendered in large numbers that was quite unusual
But a mark of what
A great first day out
Operation Michael has
Is that it sees
A huge amount of British troops surrender
Numbers that you never see
First day
17000 of these people have been casualties
Do do that for our initial bombardment
So you can see how their nerves
Shopkin some
But they're infected by all those physical
Symptoms
Earlier
And they're just stunned
Historian John Keegan tells a story of a British
Machine gunner who must have been pretty representative of this day it was mowing down German soldiers like
As the approaches machine gun position
And Keegan
Coach the soldier
A saying
Quote
I thought we'd stop them
When I felt a bump in the back
I turned around and it was a German officer with a revolver in my back
Come along Tommy you've done enough
I turned around and then said
Thank you very much sir
I know what I would have done if I'd been held up by a machine gunner and had that revolver in my hand
I have finished them off
He must have been a real gentleman
It was 20 past 10
I know the minute because I looked at my watch
And quote
And if you actually had to surrender to Germans
You know why this event it was going on
It could be a very near run thing
British private Alfred Roshes captured on the 22nd
So the next day
With a boy as he describes him but a soldier none-the-less whose badly hit in the head
Eyes bleeding
Andros rights
Quote
The area we cross is swept by rifle and machine-gun Fire
We crawl and escaping
The boy is in pain and crying
Presently he jumps up
Do they come he cries
I pulled him down who I asked
Jerry he said
I look cautiously up
Theory is right enough the first wave almost on top
And quote
Groceries account continue
Quote
Leave it to me boy we're done we're prisoners now
Do whatever I tell you
I wait a second and then
I say
And take your helmet off
We do so
The German in front of me says
Raises his rifle and take same
I mutter to myself I hope to God he won't pull that trigger
For 10 seconds we remain so
When he lowers his rifle
And says what I take to be wounded
I nod and say yes yes
He beckons when we approach
We still have our equipment on and the Germans other shouts pointing to it
Flip it off bike ride of the boy doing it myself
The German has spared us
When we have spared him under the circumstances
God knows
Perhaps not
And quote
But that same sort of gallantry you see on the German side
In cases like this is present on the French side
And the British side and the Russian side I mean this is this is a human
Element coming forth in the midst of all this evil and of course
Just as something to juxtaposition the whole thing
You see the
Killing of prisoners
By all sides as well
Ian passingham calls March 21st
The day
The opening of the Michael offensive the first punch in the multi-punch combination right that the Germans in the throat
One of the most dramatic days in the hole
And he says
Quote
In the event that despite numerous Tales of heroic last stands and derring-do
21st of March was a disastrous day for hague's bef
Mina British Force
It was the bloodiest day of the first World War
They were over 78000 casualties
Almost 40000 on each side
Though the storm troops and advanced in one or two places up to 10 miles by the end of the day in the south
Overall 21st of March was a day of great sacrifice and confusion
And quote
78000 casualties in one day
That your new world record
You're right there
The horrible Battle of Waterloo a hundred years previously
Obscene maybe 60
Mm casual
On the first day
But there was no second day at the Battle of Waterloo
Operation Michael
Play the 78,000 casualties on the first day of the first punch of a multi punch combination
That would go on for months
Randall gray who wrote a piece on the Kaiser slot said
It was quote the greatest and most intense battle ever fought by the British army
And quote
He also said
Quote it's certainly represented the most awful non-nuclear
But chemical
Fighting ordeal undergone by 20th century Soldiers with the possible exception of some 1940 119
45 Eastern Front battles
Any rain Iraq War
And
I always try to remind myself
That what these soldiers went through
True at these
Scarred them forever
You know there's a difference we should understand that there are a lot of people who go to war who never see any
Who deal with paperwork
ProLogistix are Supply in the wrong very important but the
The people who come home after this war
And change the psyche of the world
The writers
The thinkers
It's just the everyday people whose attitudes have been shocked into a different paradigm
At what age
Experience in this combat
Go through things
I was particularly moved in one of these Kaiser slots battles at a German soldier
Under artillery barrage
Talked about what happened to him
And when you think about him having to live with his memory the rest of his life
And how would alter him on a personal
And then imagine millions of people
Who had seen equally scarring events in their lives who went on to help create this postwar world
And you can see how this war dug deeply in
Psyche
20th century civilization gouged out a permanent
The soldiers under French
Artillery fire
Aaron one of these bad
He writes quote
French shells began to hit to the right and left of us
Leaving human forms writhing in agony
Or Advanced came to a stop
And after hesitating a few minutes we drew back while the artillery fire followed
Ripping large gashes in our formation
Soon the French Drum Fire engulfed us
The air was filled with gas and flying pieces of Steel
We automatically mounted the machine gun for action
And then like animals we borrowed into the Earth as if trying to find protection deep in its bosom
Something struck my back where I carry my gas mask but I did not pay attention to it
A steel Splinter broke the handle of my spayed
And another knock the remains out of my hand
I kept digging with my bare hands
Ducking my head everytime a shell exploded nearby
A boy to my side was hit in the arm
And tried out for help I crawled over to him
Rip the sleeves of his coat and shirt open and started to bind the bleeding part
The gas was now so sick that I can hardly discern what I was doing
My eyes began to water and I felt as if I would choke
I reach for my gas mask
Pulling it out of its container
And then notice to my horror that is Splinter had gone through it leaving a large hole
I had seen death thousands of times
Stared at in the face
But never experienced the fear I felt then
Immediately I reverted to the Primitive
I felt like an animal cornered by hunters
With the Instinct of self-preservation uppermost my eyes fell on the boy whose arm bandage
Somehow he managed to put the gas mask on his face with his one good arm
I left Adam in the next moment had ripped the gas mask from his face
With a feeble gesture he tried to wrench it from my grass
Then fell back exhausted
The last thing I saw before putting on the mask with his pleading eyes
And quote
That's related in Peter Hearts Wonder the book The Great War he has such a way of finding
Those incidents that when you read about them
They they Boggle your mind and then you can go forget about them
But imagine the guy who has to live without the rest of his life
Those kinds of moments that
The extremes of Human Experience where these moral choices are thrust in your face like that
Ernst Junger do I shoot this guy before he shows me the picture of his family
It's kind of what makes these wars fascinating is how do people behave
When
You know they are under this kind of
Intense pressure and strange extreme circumstance
This is what's happening at the ground level
The Big Picture level
This last card played by the Germans here
Has been shockingly effective
The British 5th Army which let's be honest was in no position to be taking on a German Force like this at the moment they
I've been recovering from a previous battle they were holding two large apart of the front
They had
Infrastructure and defenses that needed some work
And then they get hit
With this force in this in this violence
And it immediately shoves them back
The Germans penetrate the first line of their defenses in an hour or two
13 to the second line of their defenses by lunchtime
This causes
The first of several of what I call Soil your underpants moments
Better part of
The kaiserschlacht
The multi-punch combination of luden
By the second day of the battle
Historian hold your hurting says
Did the fighting is intent hand-to-hand it's closed
Combat with grenade and it's brutal
And he writes
Quote
After two days
Ludendorff mobile and attack divisions had decimated Gulfs
5th Army
Had driven the British almost 40 miles behind the song and the crows at Canal
Hey get lost 200000 killed and wounded
90000 prisoners of war and 1300 guns
Most importantly his defenses have been ruptured a 50-mile gap driven through his line
Open field
Lay ahead of the German
And quote
This initial advance
Has morale skyrocketing amongst the Kaiser
And some around him
Hold your sails quote
Wilhelm II rushed congratulations to the Troops
And admonish them to push on
This is the Kaiser talking now
Quote much has been accomplished
Much more Still Remains to be conquered and quote
Kirby continue
The Kaiser ordered schools closed in Germany to Mark the victory
In quotes
He presented Hindenburg
With the iron cross with golden rays
Last given to Prince blue shirt for reading Prussia of Napoleon
And Wilhelm II inform his Entourage over champagne that quote
If an English delegation came to sue for peace
It must kneel before the German standard
It was a question here of a victory of the monarchy
Over democracy
And quote
Ludendorff for sure just Kaiser that the British army had been defeated
But many in the upper echelons of Germany's military
We're much more sober about what was happening here
And realized it at the pace they were getting chewed up
He was going to be a problem
The question is
Who is going to break first
This is like
This boxing match we've compared this entire War II throughout this entire series we have too exhausted Fighters hero
The German High command is kind of thinking you know we really don't have that much laugh
I mean some of the German High command or countering with
Yeah but neither do that
V army will be forced
To pull back
When they pull back the Army next to them has to pull back the third Army otherwise they'll lose contact
With each other
The problem is is that both these armies are attached
To a French army
And this is the first
Crisis that erupts
There's
A breach about to open up between the British and the French armies splitting those armies would be huge
This brings us
To what the heck
Is ludendorff trying to do right what's his plan here in disguise
Whelmed
It's one of the big controversies of the war
Theoretically
He wants to punch a hole in the line surround the British
Push the British up like a bunch of falling dominoes all the way back up to the English Channel
There by changing the entire complexion of the war
Buddy's flexible
He has the saying that is often been quoted afterwards cuz this is one of the things ludendorff gets the most critiqued about
Where he says
In terms of the strategy and tactics for this big multi punch combination quote
We will punch a hole
And then we will see
We did it that way in Russia
And quote
And he and Hindenburg didn't do that when they were commanding Eastern Front they go in there they punch a hold and roll up a Russian army
Brazilian casualties do that long enough and eventually a rickety
Russian State falls apart but this is France and Britain
Are you really
Gambling that you're going to open up this hole and they're just going to fall apart
Well ludendorff attitude is
That I'm not going to fall for the mistakes of my predecessors
Those people who
You don't have this one place they want to attack and they run into a brick wall and they just keep throwing more troops into the meat grinder in front of that brick wall we're not go
Going to do that when we break through somewhere we going to reinforce success
This is supposed to be
The part of the latest German ideas about the
What happens if the Breakthrough comes at a spot
When there's not that much of War winning quality
Unum goals anywhere nearby
Because the Bulge
Some even call it a breakthrough that the Germans have against the British 5th Army
Happens in a place where there's not anything close by that's going to win you the war
All those places have been you know extra specially defended by the best troops in the best defenses
The reason that the Germans break through here is because
It wasn't some very important
Object nearby
But the Germans are moving so far
It eventually they run into one
The place where the roads and Railways all come together a French city name I mean yeah
And it's at this point that something that's been an issue for the entire War
Comes to a
And almost fatal head
And that is the fact
That there is no
Coordinated Allied leadership at all
Because at this point
Douglas Haig the British military commander on the scene would like help from the French in this crisis situation please send me true
Epson historians have argued about whether or not they did some historians nowadays said they not only did they did it
Before they were even asked and they did it in larger numbers
How they were British historians Adam always said
Stingy with extra troops in
Put Hagen a situation where the worst possible thing could happen I mean a soil your underpants moment
Indeed
But he was asking for
Troops from a guy named pathan who had his own worry he was worried he got an intelligence that the Germans had another fist
It was poised
To attack near Paris and as far as potassium was concerned that was his number one concern
There's a meeting on March 26th
And some historians have described
Haig's mood at this point
As near panda
As he runs up against this brick wall where he's not getting the kind of help he feels like he needs and he's in a crisis situation
Eric Thorn bro says
Quote
Gaps also opened between the British and the French across the Lewis River
Sending Hagen to near panic
As he ordered trenches dug to protect the channel ports
Shifted six divisions from his northern Army including three from the Frontline
Unemployed pattan to rush 20 division
Always quoting the head of the general staff the British general staff Sir Henry Wilson quote
Ted Wilson on March 25th
Quote he said that unless the whole of the French army came up
We were beaten
And it would be better to make peace on any terms we could
And quote
The seriousness of the situation
Finally leads the Allied on Tom Powers
Disregard questions of sovereignty and jealous guarding of
I'm rights and privileges at all that and finally decide to
Nominate and finally approve somebody whose job is going to be
Not so much to be the boss but to be the guy that Courtney
This honor goes to the French military leader Ferdinand sauce
We had talked about him
In an earlier
Very aggressive
Energetic
Brave
The first thing she'll do
Is issue an order that says
That there will be no retreat from this
Important French
City that ludendorff
I'm going to go after now
I mean
The people have to die where they stand basically not one step back
And he will Dole out the reinforcements as he sees fit but he's going to be very stingy in the desert
Generals like Haig
Will think that he's stingy
Lloyd George the British prime minister writes in his Memoirs of the
If Josh was being a gambler and that's what generals often has to be how often it we said that ludendorff the gambler
Is gambling on is it he can be stingy with these reserves and that these generals can me
Manage without them or manage without what they really want
Heads up said he can't get 20 divisions 20 divisions is a huge Force
No wonder you can't get 20 division boss just trying to
Safeguard
And stock
Pile
A reserve force people that can just stay back
Stay in good health ready-to-go chomping at the bit
And then unleash a Counterattack when the German offensive is like the way that washes up on the beach and lose
Loses its momentum right before it
You'll sink back into the surf that's when you want to launch a counteroffensive with fresh troops in the enemy's exhaust
What's Foxy's
In this multi-punch
Combination of ludendorff is an opportunity to win the war
Let the German punch themselves out here
And then take it to him with a fresh horse once they're exhausted
But the first person only be built by being stingy with reserved when people like hey you're worried that he's about to be pushed into the sea
In the French and the British were about to lose contact in the
In the middle of middle part of this front
There is desperate
You know I mean heroic when you talk about some of the fighting of this battle if it's the kind of thing where you know you have the last four guys
Guys with the gun over run fighting to the last man to
And I'll give the rest of the army you another hour safety while they we move back to
Reserve positions I mean it's really frantic heroic stuff in the Germans are striving they know this is
The war winning or losing moment and they are giving it their all in the casualties
Are outrageous
I want to people talk about this time.
As the end of trench warfare in the beginning of open Warfare again which hasn't existed on the Western Front since the war started at me
He had like six months of it
And the casualties were terrible and then everything went down underground into the trenches cuz it was the only way to
Stay alive with all that
LED flying up above
In a ground level
And now it had reverted to open Warfare again in the troupe seemed
Happy to be moving
But this is also much more dangerous cuz those trenches were there for a reason they protected you from the kind of casualties
That you're starting to see right here at Kaiserslautern
With the resumption of open Warfare again
Comes a kind of casualties
And we haven't seen for a while
Something happens on March 23rd
That it is hard to put it in a proper context
What happens is
People in Paris
Start seeing and hearing explosion
I don't know why
Decent sized explosion
And in an interesting sort of twist
The explosion comes with no sound of any shell or anything there's just nothing and then boom
You know something goes up in smoke
And it's puzzling
For a while the people in Paris can't figure out what's going on and they were there books that talk about this where people will be in cafes speculating
What's causing the explosions in
An aircraft is what everybody was thinking but that the skies were clear and there were no air
And then one of the theories floated
Buy some of these people in cafes that were quoted was that the Germans had somehow smuggled in artillery
You secretly hiding it in some force or something within range of
Cuz he was so obviously artillery piece or a bomb
Finally
What the french will figure out
Is that they are being shell
From Cannon
Firing from the German side of the line
But the German side of the line is
Way farther
Then the range of any other gun that anyone's ever heard of
Turns out
The Paris is not being shot by one gun
I probably multiple gun but they're called the Paris gun
And they're being shelled
From a distance of 75 MI
The gun can reportedly shoot 81 MI
And to give you an idea how long that is
One of the longer-range guns you will ever run into are the 16-inch guns on the American
Iowa-class battleship
Making shoot if I
Recall career
Directly between 25 and 30 mile
So you're talking about a gun that shoots
Twice as far
Easily
It's got a barrel that is 100 ft
Long
They have to have a special crane like device
Sits over the gun and holds the barrel up and keeps it from drooping
The shell that it shoots
I am told
Is the first
Thing that humans ever launched into the stratosphere
And the distances were so long that the Gunners had to reportedly account for the rotation of the Earth
First in their calculations
But their calculations couldn't be that
Targeted I mean these people could only shoot its cities
Turn that accounts for why the shells would have landed
Randomly
The worst occasion is a much-talked-about
Still
Incident during a holiday when people were in church in one of these shells Came Crashing through the roof exploded in the
The church and killed
Like 80 or 9
90 people it was awful
But over the course
The conflict
It would only dish out a little more than 800 casualties and less than 300 gas which you know isn't wonderful
But if you have a giant artillery piece shelling your city I think you
Would assume were
After a while
But some historians say this is all part of a concerted effort
What the what the Germans are trying to do
With their armies shocked the allies
Into a pro-german piece and shelling Paris is away
Of of
I'm working the other
Flank sort of on
I'm pushing you British armies back I'm shelling Paris and and believe me it certainly makes clear to the French the stakes involved
The Germans are close enough to be shelling Paris
The key to this battle is going to be
How the generals utilize the reserves that they have not to get too technical but
But in this level of Warfare when troops are fighting each other in Modern Combat they're wearing each other down
And whittling away their strength
And so generals have at their disposal troops that they're holding back
And where they decide to commit those troops as part of the art of generalship it's part of it wins or loses battle
And it's part of what the generals are so concerned about
When they launched these offenses
At least happy offences have to punch is ludendorff will throw
In Kaiserslautern
Are nothing but
Efforts to divert
Reserves from where he really wants to punch
What was decided to do is to throw
You know some of these vital and The Limited
Reserves which are all these wonderful Stormtroopers
These
Ernst Junger says they're all kind of young long-haired sort of wild man is opposed to this with a buzz-cut German
It's interesting to talk about Stormtrooper culture I had understood them to be
Members of the of the best and brightest simply pulled out but
Younger makes him sound like some sort of
Ultra-cool set of long-haired German Viking youngsters or something
Unless you don't have a ton of them
So where you going to use them ludendorff decides to throw them into where the British army V army in the third Army where they're bulging back like
40 miles
And see if you can smash through to this important Railway junk
But he runs into the same problems
That the British and the French could have warned him about
Duffy's first world war armies run into
When they try to launch offensives and continue them day after day after day
Assembly breakdown
Any breakdown on multiple love
First of all the logistical and Supply problems are immense
And it remains for the armies that still have
A lot of good stuff like the British and the French to the Germans were down to like
You know horses that are underfed and not even enough of them to try to move Supply up
These battles are
Huge chine
At one point some of these really important German armies
Instead of ironic end up
Conquering and pushing into the territory that they had deliberately
Destroyed in a scorched-earth policy to hamper their opponents
And now they had to try to operate in it
The German Army right next door to the army that moved through the scorched-earth territory ended up going through the old Somme Battlefield with all the
Craters and barbed wire and
You know the graveyards of the dead and all this I mean
So both these armies were kind of been bad to rain now they're attacking and more and more
The Allies are resisting heroically
And the supply is
Huge
The German Army is starving
In some case
And you know when you read like The Memoirs of ludendorff he'll say something like well Supply didn't keep up or some little comment like that
As a reason why you know these battles bog down but when you actually read accounts of what these troops were desperately
We trying to get the
The guns and the bullets but more importantly even the food to these people who are at buffets called the tip
Tip of the spear or the head of the snake
The combat troops are actually fighting
They're being shelled and shot at while they they try to overcome
Supply difficulties
That once you hear the music there and go white it's a miracle they got as far as they did
Historian
Alexander Watson
As a reminiscence by
One of these German Supply troops
Realizes that winning or losing the war requires that they get their stuff up to the front but listen to what they have to
Contend with
And then magnify this
Crossing entire
40 or 50 mile front as they try to move forward and continue to keep this momentum
As the supply lines get stretched longer
And the
German says quote
I have the feeling that we've been marching in the wrong direction
We asked on several occasions but don't receive any useful information and in the meantime Tommy
Dear pet name
For the British work
Begins to shoot and not at all badly
I just ride on ahead and come upon to recently shot up carts into dead horses
Through a miracle the driver remains unhurt
They warned us that we should not drive past
Greenfront is hell
What can you do
Therefore
Four words
Now however the way begins to get bad
Thick mud makes forward progress difficult
Assume we have a supply column stuck fast in front of us
A Saxon mobile bridging unit cannot go any further
It approaches us and gets stuck
We therefore harness the horses
Porsche make room
Unload the bridging unit Stuff Etc all in the deepest darkness and with the least possible noise
In addition the shells crash around
That one no longer worries about that
After much effort the wagons are got back on the road and we think
Now the comrade in his column
Who missed their way can go on but no
Just then a Narrow Gauge train comes rushing along
You responsible chaps afro Munitions on the rails
One jolt in the train has derailed
On exactly that street along which we have to pass
What to do
With unspeakable effort
The Munitions Witcher jammed the front door removed
The derailed carriages lifted by means of a winch
And then the route is free
Now the vehicles can get through when they start up again
We then come to the worst part of the road
Bickley allows us to go forward only gradually
And every moment
A wagon and its driver gets stuck
Reserved teams are sent forward
Bridges over streams are especially difficult across and on top of that we're under heavy fire
And quote
But the fact that
Troops aren't getting supplies
Becomes part of the reason why they can't continue to push on at the pace that
The German High command wants them to push on the pace that they're going to have to push on that they want to achieve these
Objectives
Princess Evelyn blue sheer the
English wife of the German nobleman Hulu
Hold a few times before
As a story
About letters that their family was receiving from family members who were in these battle
And when you read them
You hear about an army that is literally
Starving
And exhaust
She writes quote
They say that no words can describe the horrors of what they've been through
They write that they're almost dying of starvation
They say they Advanced so rapidly that no Provisions could reach them and their division was 5 days and nights fighting
Incessantly without food
Or even sleep at all
And those of their companies who were not killed her wounded died of exhaustion
And it is only by a miracle that they themselves are left to tell the tale
Their letter ends with the significant words quote
Send us some food somehow as quickly as you can
For we also shall die
And quote
Heathen
Comments about
The situation in this little village where she lives quote
The Peasants and Village People received the news that sometimes one sometimes even two of their sons have been killed
On the same day
It has been wholesale Slaughter of late
And quote
Given that situation
It's not hard to understand
Once these troops
Began to push forward
Into Allied controlled area
And see the supply dumps
Anta stores
And all these things that the Allied troops have it's funny if you read their account they think they were suffering
Right I mean I remember reading one where the guy said that
British soldiers were eating dog biscuits were practically starving
But these Germans come across with these British
Forces have
And they just stopped in some cases
GJ Meyer quotes of famous piece
About a soldier
Investigating why the advance wasn't moving forward
A German
Captain
Writing about events on March 26th
Quote
Today the advance of our infantry stop near Albury
Nobody could understand why
Our Airmen had reported no enemy between a bear and I mean
The enemy's guns were only firing now and again on the very edge of Affairs
Our way seemed entirely clear I jumped into a car with orders to find out what was causing the stoppage of the front
As soon as I got near the town I began to see curious sight
Strange figures who look very little like soldiers
And certainly showed no signs of advancing we're making their way back
There were men driving cows before the Mundelein
Others who carried a hand under one arm and a box of notepaper under the other
Man carrying a bottle of wine under their arm and another one open in their hand
Men who have torn a silk drawing room curtain off its rod and we're dragging it to the rear is a useful piece of
Men with writing paper and color notebooks evidently
They'd found it desirable to osaka station or shop
Men dressed up in comic disguise
Men with top hats on their head
Men's staggering
Men who could hardly walk
When I got into the town the streets were running with wine
I have a seller, Lieutenant of the 2nd Marine Division
Helpless and in despair
I asked him
What is going to happen
It was essential for them to get forward immediately
He replied solemnly and emphatically
I cannot get my men out of the cellar without bloodshed
And quote
But in addition to the logistical and Supply exhaustion is another kind of exhausting it plays into all these World War 1 offenses
It's the part where human beings
Simply come
To the end of their limit
You know when you can fight a battle the way you want to you rotate people out
So after a unit is so tired they are not useful anymore
Replacing by fresh troops but in these battles and especially on the German side
It was very difficult to do
And I didn't
The same troops are fighting for days and they're dropping with a stand mean
If you believe the princess blue shirt letter they're dying
Exhaustion
But if you think about how
Being this tired effects
Your ability to resist and your willingness to
Continue onward
I mean we're
Sitting in the comfort of our
Recording studio here
Overwhelmed by these people's ability to put up with the
Yelling
And the conditions in the dead bodies and all that stuff
But that's when you think of them having a full belly and a good night's
Sleep imagine it
When you haven't slept in days and you're starving to death
In the second world war some of these armies will sometimes you do things like amphetamines to prolong the amount of time
People could
Endure before they hit the exhaustion point
I've seen it blamed by some historians for some of the more Infamous massacres
Your troops that have been up for 12 days straight using speed
They might not be as rational
Or as
Collected as they might have been 12 days previously
I'm part of why these exhausted soldiers
Are they able to force anything to a conclusion if they're they're moving forward
They've been successful they've been reinforced
But they don't have any Mobility
Throughout all of human history Cavalry it's would have played the role
Of what they needed now someone that could
Rush forward in Attack retreating or
Troops were at least pulling back really so
He knows all sorts of Chaos in the enemy rear
The Germans need tanks
I need armored personnel carriers
They won't have it for another world war
Their opponents do have these things
The unveiled the tank a year before this time.
And they become better and are getting continually better at figuring out how to use it
Initially the German High command hits
Stopped at this whole tank idea but they're taking it more seriously as time
Time goes on
They wish they had some tanks now I bet because he's exhausted soldiers
Only able to march forward
Strange on Serene considers this to have been almost Criminal
But the German High command
Launch is these offensives to win the war
But don't give the troops any way to exploit them
3 he said quote
As the year would show the days of Cavalry is an arm of exploitation on a modern Battlefield were over
Yet people as it was the Cavalry was the only exploiting arm that existed
For the Germans to launch an offensive intended to win the war with none at all
Was not just foolish
It was Criminal
And quote
And it would allow the enemy to move
Reserves and help in the French of Unleashed
Divisions of troops that come to the A2 and the resistance
Of the Allies will stiffen heroically you know in front of this important Railway juncture
And the Germans would run out of gas essentially
It would be like that wave
Lost the momentum at the end of the beach
And ludendorff
Years later writing his memoirs about what he knows is this important moment in his history German
Chinese history world history in that he's been
Criticized for a ton
And here's the way he puts
In his memoir
Forest quote
The enemy's line was now becoming denser
Any places they were even attacking themselves
While our armies were no longer strong enough to overcome them unaided
The ammunition was not sufficient
Penn Supply became difficult
The repair of roads and Railways was taking too long in spite of all of our preparation
He then goes on to say
It was an established fact that the enemy's resistance was beyond our star
And quote
On April 5th
Ludendorff
Calls off
Operation Mike
He's inflicted 178000 casualties on the British band
In 15 days
77000 on the French
Are you suffered between 230 and 250 thousand casualties himself
For a man who launched this whole attack
Out of a fear that American reinforcements were going to come and swamp the Germans through sheer numbers
You can't trade lives at this rate in survive
Ludendorff knows that
But he's going to continue to punch because that's his plan
He's hoping to land a clean shot somewhere
The problem is is that there was so much invested
These offenses that have been planned for months always do the best
Troops morale was always at its highest
The failure was disheartened
And the dad on the German side come disproportionately
From the very best hand-picked troops
Can you decide to
You know use most of the rocket fuel in the very first punch you don't have a ton left for subsequent punch
And at this point
Ludendorff starts getting really pointed not-so-nice questions from subordinates about what's he thinking here
What we going to do
Some of
Ludendorff staff is turning against him
They're openly questioning his decision making in these situations
At least one of ludendorff responses to his
Rebellious staff members made it into the history books he supposed to have said and one historian described it
Acidly
Quote
What is the purpose of your croaking
What do you want from me
Am I now to conclude peace at any price
And quote
Wilhelm Von leeb
Who will be a field Marshal in the next World War is openly critical of lewd
Indoor
And then says
That on March 31st he quote totally lost his nerve
And quote
This is sort of the way they described
A nervous breakdown
And if ludendorff it had one
Here
He may have had
Another one or he may have had the first one later there is going to be an increasingly stressful. Had flu
And he's already showing signs of cracking if he'd had one
Then that would just
Put him as the second
German military leader in this war
To have a nervous breakdown the original architect you had to carry out the plan to win the war the brace started the war Von moltke
Also
Lost his nerves
How do you say yourself who cares
Why does it matter
But if ludendorff is still basically the guy making all these decisions on what to do with all these punches and how to re
React when opportunities or crises erupt his State of Mind is
And if it doesn't clear
Houses decision making going to be
He gets questioned increasingly as we continue one or the second punch arrives on April 9th
So right after Michael is called off
They launched Georgette
Each of these punches arrested has its own name George it was supposed to be George but now it's been scaled back hands
Georgette
Because of the huge losses
The first punch
Cost of germ
Georgette is launched in the North in Flanders
Against
In a really strong defenses where they've been fighting for years
These defenses have been weakened somewhat though because when the Germans were busy throwing their first punch
Hagen the British were rushing every unit that they could spare down to where the fighting was in a bunch of those units have been up here in flight
A lot of what ludendorff is going to do with these punches
As we said
Is the creator version
Video equipment in a boxing match of throwing a punch at someone's body to get them to pull their hands down opening up their head
Another punch
This is where ludendorff really wants to win the war though
Because up
In the north here in Flanders his goal
Are the channel
These ports right on the other side of the English Channel from Great Britain that are supplying everything the entire British Army and info
Back all of the stuff that they're bringing in
You know to share with the French and everything else
It's a key area everybody knows it
And when Georgette strikes
Once again ludendorff got foggy weather helping him out
And once again he somehow strikes units that are just
Shouldn't be in the line
They were actually moved
What was thought was a quiet part of the line
And then boom you have another German hurricane bombardment you have
Still some Stormtroopers left we're pursuing through this fog
A poor Portuguese division
This is truly becoming a World War now
It was supposed to be leaving
The front that day gets just
Disintegrate
Artillery fire a British unit pulls back and you have a very similar situation to exactly how Michael started
Does German penetration another soil your underpants moments
When Hague once again pleads for
You help from the French and he gets some
But its source
Stingy
In his mind how much you got to remember
Bashas squirreling away troops for this Counterattack he wants to launch when the Germans are totally punched out
What do you have to gamble
That he can be stingy with troops and not have hate fold up
No one knows whether or not that can happen Hague issues one of his
Most
Famous
Speeches or proclamations I guess you would say it's called The Backs to the wall
Proclamation images literally one of those stand or die orders to the Troops
Very famous very
Stirring rousing when the situation is grim quote
Many amongst us are now tired
To those I would say the victory will belong to the side which holds out the longest
The French army is moving rapidly and in great force to our support
There is no other course open to watch but to fight it out
Every position must be held to the last man
There must be no retire
With our backs to the wall and believing in the Justice of our cause each one of us must fight on to the end
The safety of our homes and the freedom of mankind of light depend upon the conduct
Of each one of us at this critical moment
And quote
Nonetheless
Again do do roaches resistant I mean you have to think of both sides is absolutely straining to the max
The British and the French are able to hold once again
The logistical supplies in the human exhaustion and the casualty levels
You don't destroy the momentum of the German attack again it's it's
A mirror image
It's the same thing that the Allies it had to face the last couple years when they tried to launch a fences and then continue to maintain them all
Madam
Georgette gets to within 5 miles
Chucky
You know jective
And both sides by the way oh yeah
It's going to be mine I'm in Suffern another hundred and ten thousand casualties each
It's hard to get your mind around the numbers I always think
Can you figure 50 to 60 thousand people fill up your average Sports Stadium
So you're a hundred and ten thousand number is
In a couple of sports stadiums in Georgia by the way is small
That's why it's named George
The big
Encounters are giving you
In a multi hundreds of thousands of
The people
On May 27th
Almost a month later
Ludendorff Row the Third punch
I'm at the month later because it took that long to
Is a refit
And reorganize
And send Replacements and have people in the hospital that didn't have major wounds get sent back to the front
Meet the exhaustion with such that it took a month to recover so that they could launch another
One of these punches and it's called operation blue shirt
And within a couple of days
The French are discussing abandoned in Paris
Moving the government to Bordeaux
The British
Arpanet
But if the French fold up here and it's a real
Possibility that they will
That the British army will be trapped
On the continent on French soil they will be hostages
In the mines
Are some of these people that were
Discussing coming up with a plan to get the troops
In out of France
Hostages
2A an arm twisting German Pisa green
Right before the Americans
Can cumming
Saviour up with their massive numbers of people
The British would have had to
Knuckle under after the French were defeated in their army
It's hundreds of thousands
For low Millions
Be held by the Germans
For leverage
Wishing happen here is a replay of what we saw in both Michael and Georgette where the Germans again have an initial breakthrough
The shocking
And unlike
Operation Michael were the Germans broke through and there really wasn't any super fantastic goal that they could strike
This time when they break through
It's near Paris
The French cap
Ludendorff decides to reinforce this attack
Cavium pathakam labels him and I think it's a pretty good label
For him he says he's ever the opportunist
Never the strategist
But that can be taken kind of is a compliment
Tattoo ludendorff
Thanks for the idea of
Hitting yourself down one
Standard recipe or set of rules or objective
In a decreases flexibility he makes a move toward Paris and we have this crisis again another story of your underpants moment
Ferdinand Forest provides as many troops as he can without totally destroying his opportunity to have a counter attack in the near future
Future
The Americans unready untrained
Get thrown into the mix because of the desperation of the times
The fighter a small encounter at chateau-thierry it's called and then they'll fight
A famous battle in American military history called Beetle wood
The Americans when they get into combat
The first time
They fight like the Europeans fought in 1914
No they're not particularly enamored with with
European Warfare of what they've seen and what they've been a friendship tried to train them and stuff
Stater Brothers storm up San Juan Hill in and simply take these things why are we being so
You know
Conniving about it and why are we here just come up and a little Dash a little American aggressiveness and you'll clear out these
Strangers in the Germans would be on the Run
Because of this
The Americans are taking
1914 level casualty
Minnesota 10000 casualties at belleau wood boom
Welcome to the war
Initial German Reports say that the Americans are almost suicidally Brave
Very good Marksman but clumsily lead
Pan American artillery
Which is mostly stuff they borrowed from the French they don't have any of their own heavy artillery
Doesn't know how to do basic things that the European armies do all the time that like a creeping barrage that sort of level of cooperate
Duration
And I'm sophistication isn't yet
Part of the American Arsenal
But it makes it hard to conduct battles
The way the Europeans do
At this point ludendorff says his biggest fear
About the Americans
Is that they can go and take over
Quiet parts of the line from the French and British soldiers that are currently they're allowing those soldiers to be moved
Linda positions where they can fight the Germans
But there are 10000 Americans a day
Arriving
In France
There are almost 300 thousand by this time in the story
And there will be
250000 every month
For the foreseeable future
Is the Emperor in great military leader Napoleon said about troops
Quantity has a quality
All its own
And what ludendorff is going to find out
Is it the Americans make damn good soldier
The Canadians
And the Australians do to and several historians John Keegan among them
Have started saying that by this point in the war
The Canadian and Australian divisions are the shock Army
Of the British army
The British had lost a ton of their own unit
In 1916 at the Somme at at this point
The Canadians and the Australians are healthier bigger
Stronger you're still getting sort of The Pick of the litter
Whereas these British
Formations involve a lot more people that
If you had your druthers
Should be back in civilian life yunnan with kids or
Still finishing up school or whatever it might be
On the Canadians and Australians are so important at this point in the war that the German intelligence pays attention to where they are
And
I read somewhere that said that if the German intelligence saw that the Canadians in the Australian
A division for right by each other they knew that some offensive was going to happen right there
1 German Soldier quoted
After being captured by the Canadians
Head had been shocked because he said we thought you were up north
You know they think they've monitored where they were
When the Germans captured the Americans
What had so impress them was a combination of how
You're strong and healthy the Americans were compared to
You know the way
The soldiers that they were either encountering or living with work and also that the equipment was so
Nice
And Christine and they marveled at the quality of the leather
And the belt buckles and all those things I mean to the German army stuff at this point is
Will trash there kit
Call them is tracked and guns and whatnot are still good but in terms of clothing and what not
The German Army is looking pretty ragged
It'll be two incidents that are celebrated in American history that show the attitude of the Americans as we vote we celebrate
One comes
During a one of these really battle that involve Americans we're going into action with the French in the end there's a moment in time where the French decide to
To call a tactical retreat
Cuz sometimes that's the right move to make you know from the from the Playbook
And they advised the American captain the Marine Captain I believe that
He can do the same thing and he famously says
Retreat
How we only just got here
And then there's another famous incident
Has gone down into American military law
From these early battles where the Americans do to their impetuosity and and suicidal bravery is
The German
Commander might say
I'll get themselves in trouble Under Fire and Tallgrass the machine gun painting them down and mowing people down
And at a certain point one of their officers an old Marine who had been at all the classic preview first world war marine and count
Recently have
Open from the Spanish-American War to the Philippines to Central America and all that kind of stuff supposed to have stood up
Started walking forward firing his weapon from the hip and yelling at all the soldiers that were on their stomachs in the tall grass
Come on you sons of b****** do you want to live forever
Once again
The ending is a mirror image of the other part
Conscious
Physical
Human exhaustion combined with logistical and Supply nightmares combined with
Heroic
Resistance again I can't emphasize enough
These battles on both sides are fought with the ultimate
In a sort of
Frenzied striving I can't describe it any other way
The Germans are starting to get
As we said they burned their Rock
They're down to people that they had
Planned
To be the troops that you put in the trenches that the better troops had already conquered
To serve in the rear and just kind of be the last line of defense and had a lot of their best weapons were taken and given to the other troops
They never been trained in the new Fire and movement the stormtroop tactics
And these are the people now who have to make the last few of these punches work
When the batter troops
At a higher state of morale
At a better time couldn't make it happen
The 4th punches thrown June 9th
Called gneisenau
And this time
You don't see that initial.
Where the Germans are able to
You don't make great progress
For their stop here they're just stop
By this time the kaiserschlacht has cost the German Army between half-a-million and 750000 casual
Remember
This punch of theirs
But they were going to throw
Was about a million 2300000 man fist
And now
It's condition is a little like what
The condition of your fists would be
If you would been throwing it multiple times into a heart
First it gets nicked
Let me get sliced up in
It starts to bleed
And then it starts to
And if
That wasn't enough there are two other things impacting the ability of the German army
To continue to fight
One is perhaps
The worst disease in human history certainly top 5 on anyone's list in terms of
Nasty epidemics
The history of the Spanish Flu
And it
Probably
Chilled
Between 50
+ 100 million
At a time when the population was less than 2 billion
Some 500 million people will come down with
China in June and July right at the
The time and all these encounters are taking place a half million German soldiers have
In addition to
An actual Contagion
They're dealing in the German Army Now with an intellectual
The fire that ludendorff it started in his next door neighbor's apartment
Is now
Coming home to roost
And as we said it is so hard to figure out from the memoirs
How much of these people are actually Bolsheviks
How much is a mar much more moderate socialists and how much of it are just people that have decided that the war should be over
Guys like ludendorff and Hitler they put them all in the same category
Dubai 1918 is The Replacements
Are coming to these German units when they need reinforcements from home
They are people
That have been
Touched shall we say
By the intellectual Contagion
Let loose in Russia by the German High command to undermine their willingness to continue the war
And now they're part
Amuse German unit
Author Adam Hall
Child
Writes some stuff on the Americans and then shift gears
Towards this
Intellectual contagion issue
The ludendorff is sort of in a car make sort of since beginning to read
Your rights quote
In addition to confronting Americans eager for battle
The German High command found danger in another Court
The impact of the Russian Revolution was beginning to Ripple through the German army
Has its divisions of Eastern Front troops were transported to France and Belgium
The general discovered
Revolutionary ideas that come with them
Having read German language newspapers distributed by the Bolsheviks
Or fraternize with soldiers from the fastest all been Russian army
Many had lost all ardour for combat
Quote
Our Victorious Army on the Eastern Front became rotten with bolshevism
A senior German general told an American newspaper
After the war
Quote we got to the point where we did not dare transfer certain of our Eastern divisions to the West
And quote
Hochschild continues quote
Soldier ship to the Western Front
Turn rowdy
Firing shots from train windows
I from one troop train in May 1918 carrying 631 men
83 deserted along the way
Cynical troops chalked
Battle for Flanders
On the side of the Railway cars
Taking them West
And in half-a-dozen German cities underground Network
Work spring up
To a deserter
Leftist sympathisers provided men with shelter
Money
Forged papers and ration cards
And instructions on the best spots to slip across the border into neutral holla
And quote
A little over a month
Laughter
The fourth German punch gneisenau is halted quickly
Ludendorff
Carlos V
And by the way he's planning on 1/6
Pawn shop in Flanders again
Where Georgette JustFab
The first is V punch maybe to draw reserves away from Flanders
And to who knows you know punch a hole and see what happens
It's known to history as the Second Battle of the Marne
The reason why people remember this name
So well is because
Instead of the Germans breaking through and having this early success
At the Second Battle of the Marne
They get hammered back
They launch a pincer movement at a head
A couple of French cities and one side of the pincer is immediately stop the other side
You know goes on for a couple of days slow grinding advance and then it stopped
And then
The French military leader the generalissimo now the Allied on tan forces Ferdinand phone
Launches
The counter
Now historians disagree over whether or not this Counterattack counts as the beginning of b-big counter-attack
Bosch has been saving up for some say it does
How do you say
The Discounters attack is more something designed to stop
This battle
Nginx counter-attack is the beginning of
Porsche
Nonetheless
Within two days
Of the Second Battle of the Marne being launched by ludendorff
The Allies are counter
And they're doing it using
Essentially Second World War
They hit the Germans in the fly
They hit a part of the Salient that
A rear area essentially in the Germans are there trying to cut down some weed
That they've just Advanced into
Cuz they're starving
And then with no warning at all
An artillery barrage just
Starts
And instead of it
You know hitting various positions all over the place
The shells instantly
Come together to form
One of those
Creeping barrage is those walls of explosions
And then the creeping barrage instantly starts moving forward
Like a giant
Moving hurricane
Heading towards German troops
Behind this hurricane of shells this wall of explosions
Is a giant smoke screen
And charging out of a forest where they've been hiding
Are hundreds of light tanks
Followed by infants
And with aircraft swooping down
Conducting what we call now ground attack missions
Which is something that did not even exist three years preview
These tanks didn't either
Not only are these tanks and in hundreds of them in one place is very uncommon
These are a new kind of tank a light tank
But even ludendorff has to acknowledge in his memoirs
Made a big difference
Because they're fast
Well
They can move at the speed of a jogging man where the heavy tanks which are the size of a school bus and have 15 to 20 people
On the move
Atmore the speed of a walking man
Hundreds of the tanks at once make a huge difference as well
And what their job is
Is the goat take out the things
That are so damaging to the Infantry
Thereby making it safe for the Infantry to advance remember what the first world war did
Was combined a bunch of new weapon systems together the changed everything
Two of the most important of them were
Machine guns and barbed wire
The first thing to do is crushed the barbed wire and go after the machine guns machine guns can't hurt
And what they basically do they often don't even use their guns they often just drive right over
The Machine Gun Nest in either crush the people inside or force them to flee
But this opens up
The battlefield for the Infantry who are following close behind
Ludendorff also mentions in his memoirs
French are using he calls them tanks
That hold Infantry
He said this infantry drives up in the tank
Onto the battlefield
Dismount setup a Machine Gun Nest and the tank goes back to pick up more Infantry
He's basically describing armored personnel carrier
These generals throughout this war
Have been accused of being unimaginative butchers
Are figuring out how to overcome
Challenges of early 20th century Warfare
The Germans on their side have some very forward-thinking generals were good at this the Allies due to one of them is a Canadian guy another
Australian General
Korean Monash
And they're coming up with a new tactic
The French General who are coming up with a new tactic in together
They are overcoming the traditional things that slow down an offense
You might call it a form of Proto Blitzkrieg
American Soldier
Elton e Mackin was at
This Counterattack and I've been told that there wouldn't be a preliminary Barrage at this
Wall of
Feel this Moving Wall of Steel would just appear instantly and in the Infantry would Russian afterwards and he just
Describe the situation like this
Quote
One instant there was silence
And then the world went mad and a smashing burst of sound
Men caught off-balance were hurled to the Earth
Which joke against the guns
Mainz Stupify refused all function for a moment and reel
Everything within a hundred yards was nodding bitter touring bikes
Men in trees and wire
The stately Forest melted beneath the raging storm of fire and steel
Heavy branches and tree trunks crush the life out for men who coward among the routes for shelter
One heard of furious awful screaming
At the Shell fire rolled away
Then mad waves of charging infantry came after it mopping up
And quote
This Allied counteroffensive
Put it in
To all those punches
The German Army have been throwing
Ludendorff will very quickly cancel
That Punchy was thinking about
Throwing up in Flanders again
And you put the German Army on the defensive
And the German Army has now reached a point in this war
That is
You you seen a lot of Wars actually what it's that it's that point when
You're not defeated
But you can no longer win
How you play that
Card when you're dealt it is very in
And once again
Makes us wonder about
You know how sound
The mind
Of the man who's going to play this
Card is
During this time period Ludendorff
Spotted by subordinates cry
At one point they will
Carefully
Convince him to go see a psychiatrist
Any exchanges actually almost a little comical I mean you know these are human beings
And we could have some sympathy but at the same time that
The psychiatrist is saying things like you never get out
You never smell the air when was the last time you had some good food you know
It's just whatever you never think about yourself and ludendorff is going yes yes
Altru
What can I do
And then later says
But the war has taken
Everything
In one sense
Exaggerate
Soon after the German
Michael Oher
Offensive starts ludendorff
Motors into territory that has been recently conquered
By the Germans
Some of this ground contained Gray
And ludendorff pulls up in the car The Story Goes
Have them dig up the remains in one of the graves
And he identifies his son
Also named
Eric luden
Now this is a stepson actually
But supposedly he was
Close to them
Biologic
This was the Second Son
But he'd lost
In this war
Also the second pilot
And you know what you eating disorder compare and contrast
This is the last war where you see a lot
A famous powerful important people lose their children
In the war
I can't think of another time. After this week's been anything quite like this
I mean not only did ludendorff lose
Two step sons but just off the top of my head
The Prime Minister who Britain
You know went through the first two or so years of the war with Herbert Asquith he lots of sun
Ferdinand Fox the generalissimo of the Allies he lost a son
And famously when he have been told the news he was busy in the middle of an offensive and doing stuff he was told the news he gave himself
Half hour
To grieve
Compose himself and got back to work
Theodore Roosevelt's famous Adventure Junkie
Encourages kids to get involved and then lost
Pilot also
It's hard to know how much
Losing his second son in this war affected ludendorff
Attempted to feel like
It's just one more straw
Weighing down the camel's back
And he's in one of these positions you know I'm always fascinated by the
Stream
Human situations
Ludendorff in one of those positions now in history there's a lot of people have been in the more they're under this extreme crushing Strasser
And is there a limit that everyone has her could you plug
Some other person with some other personality type in the situation ludendorff saying and have them do better
Me looking at off Hitler in the last 4 months of the second world war he's under this crushing
The Sword of Damocles pressure
Annie's this
Halsey dress
Can you put someone else in that role and have them do much better I don't know where the limits of
Human endurance are
Juno
It's a question
It's valid across-the-board you don't just want to ask about the people at the top of the food chain like the ludendorff
You also want to ask
About the soldiers collectively in the fight how long can they endure
And also about the Pea
People back home remember
One of the things that this war really inaugurate
The idea of Total War
Although you can go back
Other times in history
When you see it but in the modern era
Total War means the involvement of the West called the home phone
All the people are needed
In this endeavor because they produce if nothing else
You know all the Munitions and everything the troops at the front need to keep fighting
What hap
It is when they reach the limits of daring
How to slide part of the war
In the last couple of months will be known as the hundred days
Is one of those it's not a heavily study part of the war because it's not
Like the
Trench warfare part of the first World War
But it's one of those occurrences that that when you read it
It brings strange emotions
The four
Because what you watching
Is a sort of a doomed effort
And the cost of the doomed
Effort
Beyond belief
So as you watch it you don't know what to think because there's something
Unbelievably
Admirable
About the people in the stories willingness to sacrifice all
For whatever we
The part of you just screams out at what appears to a person not in that situation and let's be honest
Raised on much more cynical modern values
What appears to be
Frankly not that smart
Why did you think that the war is over and you were looking at it from the early 21st century as we
We are
And you watch these people go through unbelievable things
To prolong it
In a one second longer or something you can't help but feel
Like you want to scream out against the collective waste of it all right
You know if you know that this is done why let this continue
And it's a strange emotion as I said
There's something
Heroic
About the last several months of the war
And one side of the heroism
And is it again for people in the 21st century it's it's
It's a little strange because we have the second world war intervening in the way we think about things in the second world war really had a good and evil
Fealty
The first World War was sold as a good and evil war in the people at the time. Kind of treated it that way but a hundred years
Later as we are now you can look back on it and see
It's really not a good evil War
It's really more of a
Old lining of power politics international relations
It's pretty representative
In a much larger scale the kind of Wars people of always
And once you do that
Begin to see
Everyone sacrifice in a certain light and that I said
In a strange way the light
These people sacrifice
Really takes on in the last several months of the war is is
Heroism
The very old
Grand Spencer
The term and maybe a sort of a doomed Herald
As we said before you know there's a very
Tolkien-esque
Feeling
Did the first world war and many people will say that that's not an accident token as we mentioned in an earlier episode
Was in this war as a soldier
Started writings the stuff that would become things like the Lord of the Rings
You know in this conflict base certain scenes of The Lord of the Rings on things he'd seen in this war
And the way
The tokens would have under
Kansas hold Lord of the Rings
Story
Is a last Alliance
Of the grand old peoples that used to be so powerful
To take down the dark power
And then
In a one or two things can happen either they can lose to the dark power and everything will be covered in darkness
Or they can beat the dark power but in so doing
Will so damage themselves that their
You know high water mark on the world stage will also be over it's a doomed
Victory and that's kind of
What we're watching in these last
Couple of months of the war
Where are you
Rightfully high amount of damage is being done to all sides
In this effort to bring what's now a foregone conclusion to an end
These people are dying
Overtime
Maybe
You know can we kill enough of the enemy to make them give us a little more leeway on this point in a p
That's what these people are really
But they're dying in such large numbers
But these will be
Mortal wounds really to the British and the French Empires any from not mortal wounds in terms of replaceability cuz Adventure
You can replace those people may be mortal wounds
On an imperial site
Whose cost was now appearing to be
Unsustainable
On August 8th
The Allied
Powers law
The long-awaited
The punch
Against the exhausted German for
In the hopes
That you can
Snap back like a rubber band everything that they had
Taken in the past couple of my
They have washed up to the top of the beach as we said the tide that had run out of momentum
And on August 8th
They were hit
With such
Extreme violence
In in several places
That ludendorff will call it
The black day of the German army
History of this
Can you call it that
Not so much because the Germans
Were smashed and pushed backward but they were
But because it seemed to be
The first real confirmation
That the morale limit
Had been reached
At least for some of these Souls
There were a ton of surrenders for
Which is what has happened
A couple weeks before when the French at launch that battle with all those light tanks a lot of German surrender now they did again here at
Are they didn't surrender
In ones or twos
You guys that have been cornered in Shell holes
They came in groups
Heavily armed man led by Junior officers
I would surrender to the first Allied officer they ran into
3050 75 men at a time
It was it was a sign of something different cuz the Germans didn't do this
It was a sign
That we were reaching the limits of endurance at least for some of these
The Army had become brittle
And on August 8th you see that because some elements of the army held firm
We are trying to keep a solid line
If it gives away anywhere the enemy streams through that and then surrounds all the other position turning them into little Ila
Amongst the enemy
And one of my favorite stories from August 8th
Because it really brings forward the sense of confusion
Is of an officer in the second line of defense was in a bunker on a telephone trying to get news
What the heck's going on here stop
It's foggy that day which is kind of like mother nature
I decided to equal the yard cuz it has been foggy through so many of the punches the Germans and recently thrown in
Their 1918 spring offensive it seems only fair
It would be foggy
Another day the allies counter-attack and it is in that bunker Commander says you can't even see ten feet out there
And then as he's on the phone trying to figure out what's going on in Eid coming down the stairs and
And says that the lines are broken in the enemy is
Has has Pez bypass this
Read out as if is behind them
And he says that before the person speaking even get the whole message out
The grenades are rolling down his
Staircase into his bunker
The enemies are already
Throwing grenades
So is sums up how
August 8th looked in the Allies in the north of it I mean yeah
The British were using the Canadian to Australian Cypress episode of shock armies
Used 500 + 10
And most of them are the big heavy ones that
They're like school buses
And have the aircraft come in and do the ground attack missions
I am the Infantry come out that use the
The wall of shells but no preliminary bombardment
And German units just break in front of
The French have success
You know when there's that they launched a couple hours later
And the Allies are pushing through German lines and making what
Buy first world war standards
Is great progress here's how historian Nick Floyd described
The Day quote
8 dog is would be one of the most remarkable days of the war
Although the position of all units was not known
The Allied assault and driven between 6 and 8 mi into German line
Shattering the second Army and unhinging the flank of the 18th Army on its left
German casualties have been staggering
The official history estimated that they were as high as 48000 men
Including 33000 missing or taken prisoner
400 guns have been lost
As well as hundreds of machine guns and trench mortar
4 the battalions in the Frontline
Often only small groups of survivors remain
He then continued
Misquote
Numerous Frontline battalions have been reduced to the size of companies
All that remained were clusters of shell-shocked men
There will utterly broken
Their faces grimy their eyes glasses
Staring straight ahead
Their stories were always the same
Horrifying accounts of iron monsters clanking out of The Mists
Towards them
Of mass infantry attack
A being cut off and surrounded
Waiting for counter-attacks that never came
Some did not or perhaps could not
Say anything at all
Ludendorff worst nightmare was
It seemed
Coming through
And quote
In his Memoirs his very suspect and take it with a grain of salt memoirs
Ludendorff claims to have sent an observer to go and check out the scene
What are these
Units were breaking
He says the Observer came back and said
That the troops at the front line
Were yelling at the reserves they came up to take their place
Black legs
Strikebreakers
You're prolonging the war
And ludendorff
Pointed out
That there was no way to hide now
You know the changes in the fighting efficiency is he called it of the troops
They become brittle you couldn't depend on some of them
Ludendorff said of course that I warned you about this all the time it's the motion isn't taking hold he wanted to
Shoot more of them maybe is a
Way to stiffen the defense
But then he says
The dis convinced him that the war
Had to be in
And then some history say
Did the Kaiser a day or two later comes to the conclusion after talking with them that the war had to be ended in than other histories
Say other things
I don't even know how to describe all of the uncertainties as people try to figure out what really happened
And is opposed to what ended up in the history book
There's a lot of evidence that suggested ludendorff was more of a
Hardliner and held out until much later
But when you see how
Again the sacrifice that's going to be made because he maybe drags his feet on peace.
Negotiations for example
That's a hard thing to justify after the war if a decision like that cost an extra hundred or two hundred thousand casualties
How do you look your countrymen in the eye 20-30 years later right
I think if I were in ludendorff shoes I might try after the war to shade things in the best light to
One of the tragedies during this. They'll be a
German general who is
Looking at the incoming list of 18 year olds in entire
Age group now being called up again to be
Thrown into the mall
Love this war when it's already decided and
Jose
Too bad about the Young Blood
If one of those
Members of that new crop
Youngbloodz was your son and you lost him in that war
Afterwards reading ludendorff Memoirs you might not be
You pleased either
Nonetheless
After the black day of the German Army on August 8th
The Allies will launch a series of regular Hammer blow
The Germans and they're all pretty darn awful in between them there's tons of
Fighting going on you the taking of this Machine Gun Nest e moving into this Valley it's pretty much constant somewhere up a
Turn down the line pressure on the German army
In the casualties because now we've reverted back to open Warfare again people are not hiding in trenches which let's be on
Are safer than being up above the trenches which is why you had trenches to begin with
And the casualties just go through the roof again
At a point in the war
We're really
They're fighting for
Improved
Terms of an armistice
Right and ludendorff not exactly moving all that fast supposedly the Kaiser want to open up negotiations with the Netherlands
But it's not
We taking off so fast and you're thinking
In your head is you look back on this tragedy everyday
In all these people dying just want them to hurry rush there's a time limit here right everyday
You get a little closer to Armageddon
Armageddon
Exactly what historian Peter Hart
Call Des.
Did the war
The. Aft
Black day of the German Army August 8th when multiple punches keep knocking the Germans backward eventually knocking them back
I can do those prepare defenses
That they had
And I move forward from months ago and everybody takes up their positions again in the Allies smash through that
Heart says quote
The Allied armies
British French American and Belgian moved forward along most of the Western Front
They were winning all right
The casualties were still high
This was a truly murderous form of warfare
It's a sobering statistic that of the 1.2 million men serving in the British expeditionary Force
Between August and November 1918
Some 360000 of them became casual
This was unsustainable
The bef was being consumed
The French and Americans were also suffering this was Armageddon
And quote
Again it remind you of an almost tolkien-esque
Situation
We're the good guys even if they win are going to be a shadow of their former selves
But if it was bad for the allies with least knew that they were
Going to win the situation
Think about what it was like
The people who are enduring
With the knowledge that whatever they were fighting for
Is already a mood
In passing
Quote
Most of the Kaiser's men wear now utterly resigned to the prospect of defeat and despair
But they fought on in places with such tenacity and in such good order never ceases to impress animes many that either
Witnessed it then or consider it today
But it was also a truly awful experience
Soldiers bemoaned their plate
He quotes a German soldier
During these
Last hundred days of the war
Quote
Our artillery is fired out
We have too few horses
Are fresh troops are anaemic Boys in need of rest who cannot carry a pack
But merely know how to die
They understand nothing about Warfare they simply go and let themselves be shot down
The summer of 1918 has been the most bloody and the most terrible
Every man here knows we are losing the war
Still the campaign goes on
The dying goes on
Again that's another guy
You might not want to read ludendorff Memoirs after the war
After the war the great German historian militaries during Hans Dale Brook will be a scathing critique of ludendorff
And with the same kind of Rage that anyone might have from that generation
And even that side of the war when you realize that maybe
Several hundred thousand casualties were unnecessary
As we said the weird
Human emotion that comes into play though
Is that when you look at the sacrifices in the endurance of these people
You can't help but notice the heroism in it right
It's a strange thing
Lloyd George knows it though the British prime minister in his Memoirs in a
Art that you can't release pin
Goes out of his way to just talk about how amazing
The whole thing was he says quote
The ceaseless body blows delivered with increasing Power by the Allied Forces left the German army
Breathless and helpless
But it is fair to acknowledge
That they retreated fighting for every kilometer that they ultimately had to concede
He was not a Chase
And hardly a Pursuit
Starved
Decimated despairing the German soldiers fought on
Making us pay a heavy price for every mile we wrestled from them
Throughout the whole War the Germans had shown themselves Dowdy Fighters but there was nothing finer in their record then
The pluck with which they continue to withstand Us in the hour of their defeat
They could not but know that they were beaten at home their families were starving
Yet in the month of October the last whole month of the War the British forces in France suffered over a hundred and
20000 battle casualties
As evidence of the resistance they encountered
Between July 1st and the conclusion of hostilities the British battle casualties in fighting a beat info
Nfo that knew he was beating on every front
Total 430000 in killed wounded prisoners and missing
Doing practically the same. The French lost 530 1000 men
How many Americans over 200000
Let us do honor to a brave people with whom we've had but one deadly Coral
They fought to the end with desperate Valor
End call
American historian Scott Stevenson
Rote
Quote
To be a German defender in the path of a major Allied attack laid in the war was to experience the whole
Tours of Dante's Inferno
And quote
And truthfully when you read the stories
They sound like they could come from any part of
This nightmare
The worst tragedy here is
Did you get the feeling like
Like all of this is
They're coming after the time when this conflict should be ended already
If the whole thing is already tragic this is the
Historian Nick Lloyd talks about a German Gunner name Ernst
Killmeyer's
Who recorded in his diary about the fighting going on in Layton
September early October
He writes about his experience of coming under sustained British artillery
Bombardment including a direct
He talks about three men and says that they were quote
Torn apart beyond recognition
May said oh Lord what a Monday morning
And said quote
I'm firing on gun number for all day
In between we picked up the pieces of bone and flesh and put them in a box
I marked them with a red pencil my companion at all times
So that the cemetery official will know
Has there metal plates with names and ranks could not be found
Try to pick up three heads
Six arms and feet and whatever else there is left from your friends
And then the historian Nick Lloyd Wright's
Quote
Killmonger was understandably traumatized by his experiences
Quote if that's how three of us died he wrote I hope their families will never find out
And quote
And it came as we done earlier in this
Peace I want to emphasize
These are the survivors
To go home and make the post first world war world
These are water in their memory bank
These are what they carry with them these are what influence their politics
Their standards
Their expectations
And influences what they want
The bitterness
That is part of what
Adolf Hitler is trying to touch in his audience reading his book mine comp
Is the sort of bitterness
That experiences like this General
And I do so in an entire generation
The British and the French
Also have the
They're poets and their writers
And if thinkers and their politics
And when one wonders why they
Seems so willing to do whatever it took before the second World War
Even if
It involved will be call today appeasement
Look at what were in those people's memory banks
Doing all those negotiations
The vast majority of the people that will be in decision-making positions militarily and politically
Were people who were in the fur
World War
Look at what they went
And think of how it changed
As Autumn was beginning to turn to November in 1980
18th Optimist were beginning to think that this war could be won in 1919
Paschima still pointed out maybe 1920 was more realistic
If the Germans began a step-by-step dog and defense they could hold out for a long time
It's worth pointing out to cuz it's kind of important of the Germans
Art on German soil get their retreating but they're still on conquered territory
Something that they would continually tell themselves was
In a sign that they were never defeated
And something politicians after the war will play up to write the never defeated German Army always on conquer territory but there be
Being battered pillared
The post
During this last hundred days offensive
They will retreat at one point
To the old Hindenburg line these great defenses they going to make a stand will never break the Hindenburg line and then American and French
Forces break through the Hindenburg line
Ironically though considering all of the debate the Allied
Commanders and politicians have been having for years the eastern or western or debate where you put the troops where do you win the war Western Front
Country someplace else it's someplace else that collapses first
In this case
It's What's called the Balkan
And for years the Allies have been slowly but surely building up forces in a place called Salonika in Greece and doing nothing with
The mainly
The British especially joked that they were the gardeners
Salonika
Cuz they were just sitting around
Agregar me eventually joins the French and British Army that's their the army of Serbia remember Serbia has been conquered
Taking over out of the worn-out for a couple of years but their army fled with the king at the head
And they've been reconstituted here at Salonika
But more people are dying from malaria there than any military fighting and then all of a sudden September 1918
The Allies strike there against a bunch of bulgarians
Who are poorly supplied poorly motivated and certainly not ready to be hit by what is now more than
Allied troops
And they collapse
Dissing perils ever
And it's funny because if you read the Western history is written by the British and the French in the Americans
It's clear that to them this is a sideshow thing it could barely get to mention sometime
But if you read German
Accounts
This is a catastrophe
They get their oil
A lot of their food from this area
This will certainly
It'll be the last card for the austro-hungarians were teetering anyway
Cuz this is right by them
The Ottoman Empire you know was one second away from collapsing to this is sort of a final straw
Between Bulgaria dropped out of the war in September 29th
That ludendorff finally breaks down
No ifs ands or buts about it
He goes to the Kaiser
And says that the war must be ended right away we need an Armistice right now if I can't guarantee that the Army will be able to stand another
24 hours
The German Government contact Woodrow Wilson hoping that they can get a nice deal from the Americans were at the British and the French are not feeling.
Charitable
Wilson still has house
Is idealistic 14 points out there and maybe the Germans can get that deal now looks a lot better to them while they're retreating
Going to do while they were dancing
Andaz German military historian Hans delbruck
Writing this is
The most
Painful
Event he's ever lived
And he writes this at the time
To the German public and is the
Editor of the book points out this is something that would have been censored 3 weeks before he wrote
Right it was so anti-war or defeatist or whatever you want to say but now at this point in the war
He's allowed to openly say something like
This
Quote
The same day I completed the previous volume
The most terrible fate we feared overcame us
Are Southeast front in the Balkans broke completely open
The bulgarians were defeated their King abdicated and the army of the untalented so long defended Solana
What's on the march to the Danube River
Is Siri of the English not only fought but destroyed the Turkish Army and took Damascus
In Constantinople the German Allied Turkish government of Everett Talent is gone
It will not be long before the English fleet has free access to the Black Sea
Austria-Hungary is also in full dissolution
On the Western Front our hope that the enemy offensive would not pass through our Siegfried line is unfulfilled
Under heavy losses of prisoners and material are army Retreats from one place to another
The superiority of our combined enemies not only in men
But also in material airplanes tanks and Munitions far exceed expectations and calculations
When we remember how strong we looked at the world this past spring and our Battlefield successes from the 21st
First of March through June
Are sudden reverse is hard to believe
And quote
On October 30th the ottoman
Drop out of the war
On November 3rd
The ostrich
While all this is going on you have this very weird almost month long period
Where negotiations are opening and going on behind-the-scenes and everybody begins to get the impression that things are happy
I mean the mood is quickening the Warriors
He's winding to some sort of a conclusion but people are still dying in Mass numbers
Summon the higher-ups of the German Navy
Decide that if the wars going to end like this
The German Navy is going to go out
Heroic
And they
Come up with an idea for an Imperial Navy death
Sally out with everything you have take on the British Fleet
You know when a giant head-to-head battle and go down fighting and take as many of them with you as you can
Which towns
Heroic and wonderful if you're some Admiral somewhere when news that this is what's going on reaches the same
Sailors in the fleet though
Who can also see that the war is winding down everybody's going to get to go home it's terrible but it's over
And then they find out they get to be part of some death ride to save some honor for a fleet
That isn't going to be around
Weather
Death ride happens or not
In a month's time
They say no
Annie begin
Rebelle
Riot is not too strong of a word first
They have mutineers mutineers a captured
Then the rest of the fleet
Sailors get upset about the mutineers and
Long story short they end up
In a running through the streets taking over the naval city of Kiel
And then they send out runners
Two other nearby cities and they begin to spread
An idea not that dissimilar from ideas that were being spread in Russia
The year before
Here is
The fire
From ludendorff Neighbors apartment finally taking flame in German
And there's been a lot of analysis as to how Bolshevik oriented some of this is
And the truth is most of it isn't
The left in Germany runs the gamut from mild social Democrats all the way to hardcore what are Cults partisan
And everything in between
And part of what'll happen over the next six months in Germany will happen because there's no agreement on the left at all
As to watch it happen
Except that they're pretty darn unified about one thing
The war shouldn't happen anymore
Anesthesia
People spread to other locations city after City
Ghost revolutionary
The great journalist Philip Gibbs was with the Allied on Tommy's as they
As they battled the Germans back towards Germany
And thinks of everything they've been through these years of war he writes quote
The thought of all the losses on the way
And of all the futility of this strife
Molded ones heart
What fools the Germans have been
What tragic fools
What a madvillainy there had been among rival dynasties and powers and politicians and people to lead to this
This massacre
41 gained out of it all
Nothing except ruin
Nothing except great death and poverty and remorse and Revolt
And quote
I'm at the German armies are collapsing
Gibbs points out that it's not a moment
Too soon
Your rights quote
The British army could not have gone much farther after November 11th
When the Armistice brought us to a halt
For three months our troops had fought incessantly
Storming many villages strongly garrisoned with machine gunners
Crossing mini canals under heavy fire
Losing many comrades all along the way
The pace could not have been kept up
There was a limit even to the Valor of British troops and for a time we had reached that limit
There were not many divisions who could have staggered onto new attacks
Without rest and relief
The French and the Americans
And then says quote
Before them the German troops were in Revolt
At last
Against the bloody
Futile sacrifices of their manhood in people
A blinding light had come to them revealing the criminality of their Warlords in this great Swindle again
Their race
It was defeat and Agony which enlightened them as most people even ourselves or enlightened only by suffer
Disillusionment
I never by successes
And quote
If you read mine comp
This moment in the war
Is The Crucible of Hitler's life
And he says basically what Gibson
You know when he finds out
About what's going on he is recovering from a gas attack
In the hospital
Annie finds out that
This war is essentially winding down to an Armistice in the German government and the allies and especially Woodrow Wilson on it
Getting back and forth as people died and Hitler freaks out
And then he writes about it in mine comp
In a way
That is
Tactically brilliant
I mean Hitler is a demagogue of the highest order
And knows exactly you know what buttons to push in his body
And he knows that this audience
10 years
15 years after the war not even that long in some cases
AR
Still in shock
In denial and disbelief and in the bitterness that they are drowning in thinking of
What was lost and who they knew who is lost and in the limbs that they had lost in the lives that they changed
He knew
Hit those buttons were right
For exploiting
And yet at the same time demagogue
A manipulator though he was Hitler understood those buttons really well
Because those were actually the same buttons that he was so effect
Feisty wrote this in mine comp
Remember imagine reading this
Has one of those
People sitting there without an alarm
15 years after the war
Tortured by
That experience still
Hitler says
Quote
And so it all been in vain
In vain all the sacrifices and privations
In vain the hunger and thirst of months
Which were often endless
In Vein the hours in which with Mortal fear clutching our hearts we nevertheless did our duty
And in vain the deaths of two millions who died
Would not the graves of all the hundreds of thousands open the graves of those with faith in the Fatherland
Add March 4th never to return
Would they not open and send the silent mud and blood covered Heroes back as spirits of Vengeance to the
Homeland
Muchachitas done with such mockery of the highest sacrifices
Which a man can make to his people in this world
Are they died for this
The soldiers of August and September 1914
Was it for this
In the Autumn of the same year that the volunteer regiments marched out after their old comrades
Was it for this that the boys of 17 sank into the Earth of Flanders
Was this the meaning of the sacrifice which the German mother
Mage of the Fatherland with sore heart as she let her best-loved boys March off
Never to see them again
Did all this happen
Only show the gang of wretched criminals could lay hands on the Fatherland
And quote
This bitterness was not just
On the side of the Central Powers who lost this war though
Corporal louis barthas in the French army
Is
If nothing else
Almost
In sympathy
With the German vet
Many of these people felt cheated by the whole thing
Disillusion by the whole thing exploited Eva
Barta sounds like he feels more sympathy for his German enemy
Then he does for the people
You know that in his mind anyway Bartos is a socialist and believes that the
The people running the world
He writes quote
Meanwhile the great drama was reaching its conclusion
Alone against 20 Nations being after her in a fantastic clamor
Germany
So proud in 1914 now on its knees ask for mercy
Ask for armistice
But this way of fleeing the war didn't appeal to the striped sleeves
Who didn't have their fill of crosses
Metal Stars Stripes ribbons honors and Glory
For these folks
Warhead the end with total disaster for the German army
Against which
Jenna Waterloo and Saddam would be mere skirmishes
Thousands of captured Cannon
Hundreds of thousands of captured Bashas
Shattered enemy forces streaming back across the Rhine Bridges
Pursued with bayonets at their backs by our soldiers
Our regiments entering the great cities beyond the Rhine
Flags fluttering bands playing here was the apothecus dreamed of not only by our great warriors
By the government
Almost all the Press
Almost all the embassies and back in the rear all those who had nothing more to lose
For who had more to gain by continuing the war what did a hundred thousand
200000 more cadavers matter a few more months of unimaginable suffering to bear
Did that matter for those who were far from the slugfest
Assassin to accomplish this monster history in the so-called Allied government sought to delay for as long as possible
The hour of the last Cannon shot
By requiring Germany to repeat its demands for Armistice several times
Four simple questions of form and formula
He says during that time
In an orgy of murder bloodletting and burning the whole front was in flames
From Egypt to bail for without exception all the regiments were thrown into the assault on the German machine guns
He says the German Army's been back on all the point of contact without letting their line be broken
And their Retreat didn't turn into a route
And quote
What you hear there is admiration
From a soldier to a soldier
And sort of a shared understanding
It when it came right down to it
You know
Truces could be called and they could go in the middle of no-man's-land and share tobacco and chocolate with each other
But the people that
As Bartow said said earlier in the work
Force them to fight
Each other against their will
We continue the conflict until things were just the way they wanted
And people will die
Until the absolute last minute
On this conflict in fact they will die for decades after
The Germans will finally work out a deal
Was Woodrow Wilson and the Allies in the aunt aunt they have to get rid of their form of government
And transition to a republic
Ludendorff
Officers resignation
You know what the last couple of days of October it's
Accepted
Dons a disguise and flees the country
The Kaiser is told
He has to abdicate
And save lives in the end the war and he tries not to
But it's kind of pizza stabbed in the back too and kind of forced to in
And he flees to the Netherlands and now this new German government which has been sort of Left Behind
As a landmine by guys like ludendorff ludendorff famously said again blaming the Socialists and the people
Go back home if you know that they did this stab-in-the-back so let them pick up the pieces and let them get blamed by signing
Call the surrender an Armistice papers and
That's kind of the way ludendorff started spinning this whole thing from minute one
Hitler picked up on that
An entire German political movement will playoff this idea
That these people who signed the peace agreement the traitors
Hours of November
We're the ones who lost the war
And it was never lost it
The front by the soldier
This will set the stage
For the next
Conflict
And when the actual
Peace agreement is signed sealed and delivered
Which won't happen for quite a while to be long negotiate
Patient into 1919
The results are so punitive
The people will realize forward thinkers will realize I must say at the time
This does nothing but delay
The decision
And that they will be so many embittered elements after this treaty assign the one that will actually end the first World War
Will be a series of
Trees actually
But you're guaranteeing another world war in the near future
Yet one can't help
But think of all the men in uniform
Especially those in
Combat you
Gorgeous
Glad
That they were going to have
And at the eleventh hour
The 11th day
11th month
11 a.m. November 11th 19
On many different fronts
Soldiers
Greeted this moment this agreed moment it's a little strange When The War would end in advance
Astorian Soldier
Politician John buck
One part of the
Infinity War end
Here's what he wrote
Quote
Got 2 minutes to 11 opposite the South African Brigade at the easternmost Point reached by the British army
A German machine gunner
After firing off a belt without a pause
What Sheen to stand up
Take off his helmet
Bow
And then walk slowly to the rear
There came a second of expectant silo
And then a curious Rippling sound
Which observers far behind the front
Lichens to the noise of a light wind
It was the sound of man
Cheering
From the village to the Sea
And quote
The future may have been
Poison
But at least
These people would
Where to see it
November 11th
Will be celebrated
Is Armistice Day
And will be celebrated with a wide
Find range of a motor
The war however
Had taken the geopolitical
Colchester map of the world that have been basically in place
Since Napoleon's
Defeat a hundred years
Before
Throw it up in the air
Andaz
The pieces fell back down to earth in
People try to reconstruct
A new world religious countries have been totally removed from the map
A lot of people were going
Suffer
Part of the reason that the
The first World War
It's so important to our modern time
Is that
It's a little like a giant
Bundle of Fire
That when you light It Off
Nice big chunks of firecrackers blow off in the distance and continue to work
Explode sometimes with more violence than the original
That's what II
Direct
Successor
Bolshevism in Russia tweets to the Cold War
The situation in the Middle East in the
Oil and the
Colonial Empire
Sing about the first world war is that it wasn't
Quite Armageddon yet
The very things that probably were needed to create
An absolute
Global Holocaust
And yet
Entered into the picture things like nuclear weapons for example
I think you can safely say looking at it
What's the first world war was
What's a blueprint
Armageddon
If This Were A book this one
So to be the post
Script section I guess
But one of the most interesting a
Aspects of the first World War
Is what
Right afterwards so divisive results
Change so much
So the Catalyst for change itself is interesting but the change in Usher's In this passage
Start with the fact
That all of a sudden
The map of Europe the great geopolitical chessboard that had existed forever was thrown up in the air
Totally scattering all of a sudden pieces fell down that hadn't existed
In a long time all of a sudden Poland
Napoleon
Looking for quite some time
All the sudden there was going to be in a like a Czechoslovakia I mean these are
Places that used to be part of larger Empires but those Empires were smashed by this war
Austria-Hungary alone when you break that if you get a bunch of Nuka
You break the Ottoman Empire up you get the modern Middle East
Hebraic Germany up
And you get them
Arguments
For the second world war right to get Danzig and you get the sudetenland
What's
Also Apparent at the end of the first World War
Did you get this
.
People who are trying to play the game the way it's always been played and maybe
You can make an argument always will be
And people who are trying to
Utilize the flip side of bitterness I guess you could say to
Create a better world
We talked earlier about Woodrow Wilson
Idealism or
Fake IDs
Realism depends on
Woodrow Wilson
But nonetheless
When you sell a war on the idea that is a war to end all wars
Sometimes that becomes powerful hype that you have to at least make a good argument around if you want to play things
The old-fashioned way
The British and the french fries and Apple
Make out like
Winners
In the war
It comes to
The territory that they acquired when when the Ottoman Empire broke up
All those new countries didn't really get full Independence most of them
How to sort of a compromise sovereignty is that a good way to put it
With the French or the British Empire
Ensure
The 20th century version
Kool thing oil
The British will
Miraculously end
The Americans another's
Pushed ideas like
Self-determination in the British and soda mouth at 2 and they kind of believed it to a minute it's one of those things where is the
Prime minister had said he kind of would have been
Remiss if you didn't grab some of that area just like the French have it none the less they all kind of realized
It didn't look that great
With the new set of values
Play what's self-determination became this weird thing to
You know who deserve their own place and
And how can you use self determination as a weapon Hitler would use it against one of those territories that was created out of hole
Old cloth
Buy the World War 1 peace of green
A place called check
Slovakia
We didn't that place was a territory that had a majority of German
Havasu dating
And Hitler would turn the arguments of
Idealism and self-determination on their head when you said hey of self-determination what you really believe in
Those Germans in the sudetenland
Be allowed
To come back to Germany and bring their land with them
This would turn out to be a big problem in what are called
The interwar years
It would hamstring
An entity that was truly idealistic like the League of Nations
Set up after the first World War
By the people who were as I said on the flipside sort of the global bipolar mood instead of being bitter
Their attitude about the first world war was a sort of a never again
Attitude
Things like the League of Nations and collective security
We're going to ensure that the world never had a tragedy like that happen again
We emphasize the bittern
At the end of the lot program because the bitterness helps play into the next War
But there were a lot of people that weren't bitter
And it's only fair to point that out first of all you had people
A lot of times these were officers to its
Interesting to note
Who are so proud of their War service and what happened
And justifiably so look what these people endure
Wouldn't take anything away from any
Some people straight up
Enjoy the expiry
Ernst Junger has a piece in his book
Read us something
That I think many people throughout history of dumb when they're at Giant historical event when you're the great battle and you know
You're watching history unfold
Sometimes there's a powerful feeling
In that and especially when you think you're playing a part in it
On the
50th anniversary of the Normandy Landing
I remember there was a
Newspaper article published by an army
Psychiatrist
Who was talking about
These kinds of moments in soldiers lives and said
For many of the men
You know who were at
D-Day in the Second World War
The greatest experience of their lives the greatest event they would take
Harden
History Niall Ferguson in his book
Pity of War
Describes
The remembrances of a couple of soldiers
For probably representative of a whole lot of these Souls
Windsor Canadian private talking about
And what the first World War
Stanley said it was quote The Greatest Adventure of my life
The memories of which will remain with me for the remainder of my days and I would not have missed it for anything
And quote
It also had
This sort of momentous feeling it was sometimes tough to
Andre captured
Private life
Ferguson also quoted
Another soldier that said
Quote
Everything that happened after the war was an anti-climax
And quote
In some ways the war was in
So many people went
To fight
Based on ideas like
The war to end all wars
And yet people who were rather farsighted but there were plenty
Before the Smoke Head even
Cleared
We're predicting the Second World War I mean the generalissimo
Of the Allied Anton forces Ferdinand Foster
And said when he saw
The Versailles Peace Treaty
This is not peace
This is a 20-year armistice
By the way was almost 20 years exactly
Play 21
It look to the British and the French like they made out well with territories that they were able to take over
But they were both
In terms of their great
Power status
Mortally wounded
The eventual cost of this war especially falls on Brittain shoulders more than any other they were sort of the banker
LTI lightside
And
They are still are or were recently I don't know if they're still outstanding loans but it was only in the last few months
That they paid off one of the outstanding first world war deaths
We're still out there
We had said in the show the
Center of World Trade and banking
Transferred from London to New York
During this conflict and as a result of the financial
Transfer of wealth from the old world to the new world that this conflict required
As we had said about Tolkien this is
This is the
You know people's of me the free peoples of Middle-earth
Destroying themselves to take down the darklord right he's gone
Imperial German he's no threat to anyone anymore
But France and Britain
To name just two countries I mean not even to go into Russia's backyard and mentioned them France and Britain will never
Be what they
The Russians needless to say
Aren't going to be what they are they're going to be living under
Communist
Regime
For decades
The Czar and his family in the middle of 1918
Will be executed by the Bolsheviks every last one of them and the cook
United
States
Comes out of the war well
Actually they're there
On the receiving end of all that old world wealth
Sample
But for Americans it was quite a change
How to change the head really started
With the Spanish-American War
In 20 or so years before the first world war when the United States started going abroad
And involving themselves more overseas the first world war solidified that Trend and even though after the war
Or they would be the smooth
We're not doing that again you could tell that it's
It was sort of like virginity
AAA barrier have been Frost
And you really just
Couldn't go back to the way things were weave
Find that out as a mirror
Africans in the Second World War
Americans also got to experience other
Things that would not be uncommon in Europe things like
Sedition and Espionage Act
Imposed by the Wilson Administration things to prevent criticism of the war
Anti-war activities criminalized
Laws that are still on the books and still used
Today
That most people look back on and still think
But those words
Extreme overreaches a presidential
Authority
Nonetheless
You know it was
The first World War
The threat was there
Japan
As I said it would be the United States or Japan that I would nominate for the big pictures in these wars
Japan had a relatively easy run if it took over anything that was over in their territory that was German
And then started moving in more to the Asian mainland
Already in charge
Have a lot of Korean folk they started
Taking over territory that would eventually morph into what some historians now considered to be the really early
Early stages of the second World War
Because by the time
The second world war breaks out the Japanese have been involved in fighting with the Chinese for years and
Some fighting with the Russians to
Turkey will continue to have problems with violence
And ethnic conflict and
Modernism
The fighting will never release
Stop overing in Anatolia
And that country will continue to strive towards a more
National statehood they'll go through.
Under Kemal Ataturk Mustafa Kemal
But that's important in their history
They'll also have to begin to
Live down some of the things that were done during the first world war and famously to Armenia
But also to people
Assyrian Christians
Greeks
The Turks had an ethnic problem
That they dealt with sometimes in a very heavy-handed manner
The austro-hungarians also had
An ethnic problem
They along with the Habsburg rulers that have been in power for centuries were wiped away as a result of the
This war
And the idea
Of self-determination that Hitler would be able to use
About the sudetenland and whatnot would begin to raise
Ugly sort of questions
In places like India
Controlled by the British
But not necessarily because the Indian
Trying to
To clean up after the war
Is one of the Great
Efforts of modern times
First you have
The bodies to deal with
Then you have
The damage to the battlefield and then you have the cleanup
It happens
You know in in the collective
Populations of all the
These countries the emotional clean up
Bewilder getting past
All of these societies
That were heavily involved in the first world war will have a lot of disabled veterans around
It will be a very visible reminder
Nobody gets
Put this
Behind them
And walk away unscathed
There's a story
Adam Hawk
Child in his book relates
The dates from the time of these last German offensive
Big Lots
Card being played
That is a perfect example of what was going on
Hundreds of thousands of homes when there's no question it was that many I'm just playing that number safe
Hauschild talks about these
Cards that the
Officers would send to family members
Informing them
That they are
Child
Orlov one was dead or missing
And he says quote
The cards float out in the ceaseless stream
But when it came to Stephen hubhaus his younger brother his parents
Like so many others
Simply received word that in the new German offensive
The 23-year old Paul was quote
Missing presumed killed
And quote
You've been seen fighting
Then falling
When is units position was overrun
Several months later the family's hopes were raised when a fellow officer passed on a rumor that Paul was wounded
And a prisoner in Germany
With male going through contacts in neutral countries
Steven got in touch with a pacifist Committee in Berlin
Quote
I was very glad to be able to set on foot by this means
Inserts for my brother Paul
Alas
No trace of him could be found
My poor mother for over 6 months
Persisted in the van to believe that Paul would return
And quote
Hochschild continue
During that time Margaret hobhouse never cease to write letters to her son
Although they eventually came back Mark
Undeliverable
Return to Sender
Paul's body was never found
And quote
Lots and lots of other
I'm still being
You know you don't know
How much
Are the really nasty stuff
How to get into on a program like this
Because you don't want to be gratuitous
What you do want to be able to do
Is in your mind's eye
See what these people are seeing
Right as we always so you can experience or understand what
They're going through but you can try
To have the tiniest little bit of
Emotional sympathy
But you kind of have to see things through their eyes and what they're seeing is
Permanently scarring
The people who have to clean up after this war
Or sometimes is traumatized the people that have to fight it
After these last big German offensive
That that
Last Story dealt with
The boy missing and presumed killed
The people who were killed had to be picked up by somebody
An American soldier named Robert Hoffman
In August 1918 was one of those somebody is one day
He writes quote
Did you ever smell a dead mouse
That will give you about as much idea of what a group of long-dead soldiers smells like
As will one grain of sand give you an idea of Atlantic City's beaches
A group of men were sent to Hill 204 to make a reconnaissance
To report on conditions there
As well as to bury the dead
The story was a very pathetic
He says
The men were still lying there nearly two weeks later just as they'd Fallen
I knew all of these man intimately
And it was indeed painful to learn of their condition
Some had apparently lived for some time
I tried to dress their own wounds or their comrade to dress them but later they died there
I was especially pleased that the capture of the German soldiers that made it possible to bring back all the wounded in our sector
Many of the men have been pumped full of machine gun bullets
Shot almost beyond recognition
A hundred or so bullets
Even in a dead man's body is not a pretty sight
One of our men was lying with a German bayonet through it
Not unlike a pin through a large beetle
Bayonets are hard to remove when once they've been caught between the ribs
Especially the Sawtooth bayonets many of the Germans carried
To dislodge them it's usually necessary to shoot once or more to loosen the bayonet
This German had not waited but left his gun and passed on
The little Italian boy was lying on the barbed wire his eyes open and his helmet hanging back on his head
There been so much shrapnel in some of the bodies were torn beyond recognition
This was the first experience of handling in burying the dead for many of our men
It was a trying experience as I was to personally find somewhere later
He then goes on to say
There's nothing more pitiful than a battlefield after a bat
My pitiful yes
Dangerous
Is another term we might use because
This cleanup is ongoing even now
There's a good side in the downside
For the cleanup process with having a war that doesn't move
The great mass of Europe and places elsewhere were spared
The total sort of ruin this war that the second world war brought to so many areas
But the place is where the war was actually fought we're devastated and not just devastated permanently scarred maybe Park
Permanently ruin
Certainly for
Several foreseeable life
Author Donovan Webster wrote a whole book
On the state of those battlefields in earlier Wars today and the most
Polluted
Most
Dangerous most impossible to imagine them ever cleaning up her all these ones that the first world war fought on the western
Turn front
In these places where things didn't move for years
Because the shells
Bury themselves in the ground
I don't remember what the exact percentage that they that they estimated
The number of Duds British versus the number of good shells were
But since 1946
French
Specialist
Remove
18 million
Shells
And they estimate that there's another 12 million
Just around Verdun
The biggest shells like those Paris gun shells the Duds from those
Are so deep in the earth they won't even make their way to the surface for 60 year
Hundreds and hundreds of these people who go and try to clean up these areas die
They're been Farmers killed her like 35 killed in one year when their tractors were hitting shells and some of these shells as you
You might imagine
Are chemical weapons
The problems that these people have trying to reclaim the areas are so bad that they just have cordoned off the area since the war
And millions upon millions of Acres of France and part of Belgium are just shut down
Too dangerous
Don't like the world's biggest garbage dump
Which human beings all ground up through it
And then it's littered with booby-trapped explosives and chemical weapons
Good luck cleaning that moonscapes
The Germans have thought
That they were signing
Something more like an Armistice more like a secession of hostilities
More like somebody along the lines of what they thought Woodrow Wilson was talking about in the 14 points
What they ended up with was more like a Saran
And truly given their military condition that's probably what they should have been doing
But even
As the war was winding down ludendorff changed his mind at the last minute
I wanted to restart the conflict right before the Armistice actually took effect
Would not have been a interesting what if scenario
Nonetheless his army was ready to go home and in a lot of cases
Was going home by the end of the gym at least a million people that they stopped thought were shirking
Or not listening to orders or simply refusing to fight anymore
The deal at the end of the war
And the difference that the Germans thought they were getting versus what they actually got was one of the seeds
Fatso's the future bitterness
The German Navy manages to sort of give the middle finger
The Allies you know the year after the war's over when they're transferring their Fleet
To Britain as
Part of the mandated things that they had to do
You know with the peace treaty
And they intentionally sink a bunch of the ship
So they may have rioted against their own officers at the end of the war
But that didn't mean they wanted the former enemy
To end up in possession of their
Vessels
I also like to quickly mention
Something that I think you're aware of this been throughout this whole program.
The ripples
The these wars and all these debts and meanings and sufferings caused
The number of people
In a relating to the soldier or civilian who experienced the horribleness
And how that just radiates across Society
You can go read the
The artist
So this post-war generation
And and sometimes it's just so incredibly haunting I mean you'll still talk about for example.
Are all these women who sweethearts
Or betrothal people that
You know they maybe would have married somewhere down the road didn't exist cuz they died in the war so they ended up spinsters
Me just decades
Of pain
In a Rippling through
The society
A sense of loss
And often times in some of these
Nationstates plagued by chaos
You know what they tried to find there and their New Path I mean Germany's are perfect
Example Rush has an even better one
People were often confused
And
Sometimes
Caught up in the wheels
Of things
That they had no control
How'd you like to be some civilian living in a country that went fascist
Or Bolshevik
Fell apart
I'd like to point out
That
The problem with the story
That we did here is the same problem you often run into it
If you read or speak in the English language
Which one you want to
Get a hold of something about the first World War
I've often said that doing these programs
Has given me
The most
Sympathy for the people who actually write these books
And create the materials that we use this as sources for this program for example
Because once you try to do even a pale imitation of what they're trying to do you instantly
All your questions answered right away why didn't they do this and then you start to
Do this, show yourself and you go oh my God how am I ever going to include this without
Screwing something up
I mean
If there's anybody who got really shafted in this story I mean I can think of numerous
Who deserve to ton more time
But I think we alluded to it earlier the french-owned enormous part of the story I didn't even get to clemenceau that's inexcusable right
How do you even get away with that Carlin
All I can say is
Look how long this series is now
I mean
I left out tons of stuff to get it down to this enormous like this isn't that terrible what about the people in the Balkan
This is where the whole war begins
Those are the people who had an amazing history right before
The first world war are finding themselves in their national identity and Consciousness is all coming together and then it's a fantastic
Caustically
Both traumatic and dramatic time of change I mean it
It's colorful it's interesting
The situation in the Middle East with the Ottomans and
An end in the modern Middle East beginning to form
Africa got totally shafted in the story
Could have been a whole podcast series on the first world war in Africa
And the Far East is busy setting the stage for the Pacific War in the Second World War
And we dealt with it minimal
As a point of explanation though I might point out
The Lac
Good
English
Work
On this subject
We have a lot of quotes from Germans a lot of quotes from British folks and their dominions a lot of cool to the United States
There are not a ton of good books even on the French
Will you get a lot of first-hand accounts from soldiers or their experience
I found one really good one I'm with used in the show but that guy wasn't at the Battle you're talking about
All of a sudden the sources are hard to come by
Love to have more from the Russian side
The Balkans the Ottomans
Africa would be great to
Finally
There were some subjects we could have gone into more deeply that I know a lot of you want
I mean some of you people
Geek out about the military side of History's I do
We did do some discussions on airplanes that didn't make it into the show we did some deeper stuff
Honda
Warships
It didn't make it into another show those are all be rolled together with
Some other potpourri I put
Put together any extra show whenever we get that out and I'm not promising when that happens I got another one
The real
A regular history shows to start working on right away cuz you folks have been patient with me
This one took longer than any we've ever had in the past and will I get
Cy go look at the reading
Be nice to do a subject that is not as well documented
Next time
Thank you for everything
If you think the show you just heard is worth a dollar
Dan and Ben would love to have it
Abacus show it's all we ask