I need is a fascinating example
How we human beings can be molded and stretched and
Trimmed and shaped like a bonsai tree
by the cultural influences into many different
Diverse versions of ours
Ourselves
Anyone who's a fan of National Geographic for example
Seize the many different colorful cultures and subcultures all over the world write the extreme
Differences of humankind
And how wonderfully pliable we are to the cultural influences
that, you know, determine
How we like to dress what we think is attractive little marks of status all kinds of thing
Now magnify that
by all the eras humankind's ever been around right so not just a diversity of exotic different places all over the world
But all of those places is all throughout history and you can see that we've
Well probably tried just about everything is this species wouldn't you thinking and we seen all kinds of different extreme versions of what we can become, I mean, take the physical version
I'm a fan of the people of the Eurasian(欧亚的) steppe(干草原) in those tribes as many of you know
Some of those tribes from time-to-time used to like to practice
Something on his head binding
It's one of the Counterpoint
Foot binding in China
Which was popular in some circle at sometimes
To keep the feet small and to have them developed a certain way
Will same thing with head
You see this in other parts of the world to and sometimes cradles for example certain Native American tribes had cradles that we
Shape the head a certain way to.
The point is is that when the skull is pliable when the person is young, you can shape that heads
And so like a bonsai tree if you will
And the Romans used to complain that the Huns(匈奴人) look monstrous to them
I remember growing up thinking while these Romans are really sensitive seeing some people who maybe have slightly Asian features
You're thinking about monstrous
Well now we have skulls that have come out of the ground some of these tombs some of these kurgans were they buried some of these Huns
And some of these Huns have skulls
that look like they are
Taken right out of an alien movie
Big elongated(加长的) skulls that go way far to the back you wonder what they must have look like with hair and skin
The point is is if you were a Roman looking at them you might have thought that they look monstrous
However if you were a young calmly Huntik noblewoman
You might have thought that guy looked hot so it's all a question right of
Are the cultural carrots Dixon White Sometimes it's not things
There are so visible on the outside
we are recognized the vast majority of our makeup in terms of our attitudes
And the way we think and the way we organize reality is probably going to be culturally
Determined
Now I am a fan of extreme situations in history
In the country
that produce guys like Hiro Onoda
Workstream
And the cultural carrots and sticks were designed
To take many
Of the In a Civic attitudes that most societies considered to be positives
And turn them up to such a high level on the dial of intensity
That they took a bunch of things that might be considered good
And in another context that made them dangerous
How can your culture
Impact things
Like
Duty
And honor
Patriots
And willingness to sacrificing lay down
One's life
For the greater good mean these are all things that most societies
You know what figure out
All sorts of cultural ways to encourage
How about just recognize
And take for example
A metal
Ceremony
It might happen in the United States written award citation
Somebody was extra Brave or extra heroic or did something out of the ordinary and maybe you get a medal and when you get the metal
The person giving the award will say something like you know for
Heroism or bravery or sacrifice above and beyond the Call of Duty
Above and beyond the Call of Duty
That right there was a recognition right that there are limits
To what normal people can be asked to do in normal times right
And if you exceed those expectations
Go above and beyond the Call of Duty you get a medal
What is the cultural heritage
Sticks in a given Society
Have evolved in such a way
So that there's almost nothing
That is above and beyond call of duty
Where the culture expects
Encourages
And only approves
A level of sacrifice on the part of every man woman and child in that Society
The most other cultures Reserve
For their most elite military unit
Welcome to the world that famed Japanese holdout
Hiroo onoda was raised in
When another got back to Japan in 1974
Ghost written book of his
Remembrances
Was created
It's called No Surrender my thirty-year war and energy describes
The Japan he was raised in he says quote
At that time if a soldier who had been taken prisoner
Later managed to return to Japan he was subject to a court-martial in a possible death penalty
Even if a penalty was not carried out
He was so thoroughly ostracized by others
Then you might as well have been dead
Soldiers were supposed to give their lives for the cause
Not groveling enemy prison camps
General Hideki tojo's instructions for the military CID explicitly
He's not quoting
The instructions quote
He who would not disgrace himself must be strong
You must remember always the honor of his family and his community
Animas dry fervently to live up to their trust in him
Do not live in shame as a prisoner
Die and leave no ignominious crime behind you
And quote
When he leaves to go off to war one of the things he takes with him as a family dagger that his mother says
If your capture use this to kill yourself with
And I tried to think of any other
Mother
Sending her son off to war in any other major power in the Second World War
With that kind of advice
Interesting is a very distinctive different culture
Got some might have a counter on
I meant to this point
That the reason these Japanese holdouts were continuing to hold out was her duty honor country the emperor that sort of thing by pointing out
A bunch of these people said they didn't know the war was over
So maybe it's more of a sense of being isolated and not getting the news
But the counter argument to that has to do
With the fact that
These people were often told explicitly in many different ways that the war was over
And he chose not to believe it and they chose not to believe it because it clot with their
Elemental indoctrination into all this I mean for example
Hiroo onoda
He had family members flown in at high expense to the Japanese government because
Hiro Nakamura still chilling
In the Philippines
After the war right he's not just sitting up there in the mountains by himself not bothering anybody killed 20 to 30 Filipinos
So that makes you want to tell this
This person in no uncertain terms and spend a little money to make it happen
Hey you're killing people in the war is over
Believe that they left the newspapers here's how he puts it
In the book written
With him
Quote
The search party Left Behind newspapers and magazines
Most of them were recent and a lot of them contained articles
About the crown Prince's marriage
The newspapers which covered a period of about four months
Made a stack nearly 2 feet high
We we need to two other holdouts with him
We thought they were reprints of real Japanese newspapers doctored up by the American Secret Service
In such a way as to eliminate any news that the Americans did not want us to
Sissy
This was all we could think so long as we believe
The greater East Asia war was still going on
And in the way he writes
The newspaper has confirmed that the war was still going on
Because they told a lot about life in Japan
If Japan is really lost the war there should not be any life in Japan
Everybody should be dead
When I arrived in the Philippines in 1944 the war was going badly for Japan he writes
And in the Homeland the phrase 100 million Souls dying for Honor was on everybody
These lips this phrase meant literally
That the population of Japan would die to a man before surrendering
I took this at face value and I am sure many other young Japanese men my age did
He says I sincerely believed that Japan would not surrender so long as anyone Japanese remained alive
Conversely if one Japanese were left alive
Japan would not have surrendered
He continues
After all this is what we Japanese at all vowed to each other
We had sworn that we would resist the American and English Devil's until the last single one of us was dead
If necessary the women and children would resist with bamboo sticks
Trying to kill as many enemy troops as they could before being killed themselves
The wartime newspapers all played this idea up in the strongest possible language
According some of the slogan
One was
Another was
The Empire must be protected at any cost
Another one was 100 million dying for the call
He says quote
I was virtually brought up on this kind of talk
end quote
When Onoda got back to Japan
Some of the things that I read in some of his later actions indicate
But he was less than happy
With .. what had become of Japan after the war was over in terms of their National values their intensity level in what
Now I can
Speaker experience but in the 1970s
The rest of the world thought the Japan
Was still a very distinctive culture
And very committed to
Shall we call it the above and beyond the Call of Duty ethics
They seem very intense about that always
Something that they took very seriously they were known for in fact
Other people really
Like things like Japanese products because you knew that they were going to be intense about
You're getting it done right but to a guy raised by the standards of all known Azera
This was not good at they lost something and let me tell you what they probably lost and the rest of the world would consider this to be a good thing and I think
Modern Japanese wood for the most part 2
They weren't all prepared
Every man woman and child
To sacrifice themselves anymore to the level of your the world's greatest
Military units right
Act like Spartan hoplite die on command of the emperor like Spartan hoplites these people in the
Modern Japanese war were much more sensible
But in here all notice world
There's a level of insanity the
It's starting to happen in it
It's really complicated but it kind of explains why
The Japanese are this very distinctive different major power in the SEC
The world war
And why they're certain unique elements to the Pacific War against Japan that just wasn't present in the other theaters
Because I reset the Japanese word
Quick little run-down mighty
Explain some important things and by the way
Japanese cult
Culture is much debated as you would expect extremely complicated and definitely a place to be left
But let's just say
It was some pretty obvious things that we should take note of
That might help explain how you get such a
Distinctive
People and let me use the word here that I like I like the wording.
I will point out my stepfather's generation and he fought in the Second World War
He believed that this regime and this
Government in the society that turned out a guy like he wrote on Lota with turning out fanatic
Another word that was much used amongst
They are
Automatize near robot
And I should point out that
Wartime propaganda played into this but
Americans kind of had this image of both the
German opponent in the second world war and the Japanese opponent as robot
But different kind of robot
The German robot was like
The vision in The Avengers
Cold robotic mathematical deficient precise and deadly because
There's a coldness in a logical nature there
The Japanese is the other side of the robot specs
They're like foaming at the mouth crazy robot
They don't stop you have to
Did Littlefinger will come after you if you leave that alone and ready to die for the emperor excited to die for the emperor
Dora cartoon character that's extremely dangerous
The word fanatic is a wonderful way
To avoid having to look beneath the surface at any of the human motivations that might be bald red fanatic is just an A to B
Sony jerk
In terms of
You know the depth that they need to be examined
Real people
That might be extremely motivated or
Feel extreme pressure in societal and cultural coercion to do something for example fly
An aircraft piloted by then suicidally into an enemy ship
Those people might have
Some really interesting motivations to see
Interesting
Points of view
Where they think they're doing
What sort of a range of options and choices do they think they have
This becomes a much more human story when we realize two things one
Any of us could have been born there
Is a certain randomness
Even if you believe
In Uno a DD selecting everything about you they could have selected that you end up in Japan in the 1920s
Go to school with Heroin OD
Besides that
There's a certain understanding
At what happened in Japan
Can happen again it will happen differently it never looks the same
But look at the elements involved
And wonder if you can't imagine them being filtered instead of three Japanese cultural filter the cultural filter of
Of your Society
But use the same way and turn to the same kind of uses
And maybe turning out the same kind of
Intensity
Did the Japanese really seem to exude all throughout the story telling me point out there's a wonderful phrase
That was used by a rabbi to describe
The Jewish people
Once but I love it
Because I think it's a wonderful shorthand phrase that applies to a bunch of different very distinctive people on the planet and the shopping
These are certainly one of those
Substitute the word
Choose
Would Japanese
The rabbi said
The Japanese are like anyone else
Only more so
Don't know if I got the exact wording correct with its but the line is perfect because it did notes
A level of intensity right they have all the same human qualities as you do they just have them at a higher intensity
You think you are a good Gardener and your garden looks down when you're done in a raking and taking care of it will go look at a Japanese
He's guarding you feel like you didn't do anything
Intensity with which state
They pay attention even to the little lines in the dirt I mean
What happens if you take this in
Density too far
Dial it up to high
Even if we're talking about being intense about are things that you normally
Considered to be positive today
Unless intense level mean your patriotism you got Duty. Love of country sacrifice for the Statham
All these things that so many people today we consider positives
How high do you have to
Turn the dial up on the intensity level though
I know we already have
I Want superhero run
They should have just happened in it but I got another one only cuz
The Japanese holdouts to me
Isn't that sort of like a Japanese version of the Captain America backstory
Right he goes he's a second world war person from the 40s gets put to sleep essentially get awakened
In the modern world and is continually contrasting in the last thing he should have remembered what in his mind
Like last week he was in the forties with the whirly finds now in the values and all these modern different thing
All these holdouts were like gone for decades aren't they all like Captain Japan's in that sense
I need the Japan of the 1970s.
Despite the rock music
The blue jeans in the longer hair
It would have been
On display for this Japanese war veteran
But the Japanese of the 1970s were still
Like everyone else only more so
But in the eyes of someone like oh nah that seems his attitude was not more so enough
Boston College a few things right away the first thing is it's one of the oldest
Tropes
In history
The people look back in
And pine away for golden age that they missed the really never existed and old people do this anyway
She probably got some of that go
Going on
Let me also say that I know from personal experience cuz it's the era I grew up in
But in 1974 there were a lot of World War II veterans from the United States of America that didn't look too fondly of
The direction American culture was going
Or think
The intensity level of Devotion to ideals like Duty and honor and patriotism self-sacrifice
Was strong enough in the American culture of those days
So in a funny way
These bitter opponents in the second world war the Japanese Imperial Army
And the US
In the military
We had something in common if they were reminiscing about the kids today
Give me the early
Timmy 1970s
And you're on the surface there does seem to be a little something different
Doesn't there
From the Japanese to the Allied perspective if you're pining away for the Golden Age
On the Allied side
You're pining away for the things that brought you victory
Right at the kids today
Mi amor
Honor patriotism Love & Country let you know what we could do great things remember we did in the war we won the war but the Japanese didn't win the war
The war was a tragedy for them on so many levels
So why would you look back on the values
The kind of made you the kind of country you were that you can fight a war like that
If that's what it led to
Well perhaps the devil's
Counter argument here
Is it yes while
These specific values and the intensity of the era on a scale of one to ten ten being most intense the
I need during the era hero another growing up in our a1011 and yes that got them into trouble eventually and led to
Japan's downfall is a great power
The counter argument that can be made is Japan never would have been a great
Had it not been for
The very specific
Active nature of the Japanese and let's understand
This is a people
Not quite unique but darn near unique in the.
Of colonial Domination by the colonial powers of the western world
It managed to avoid that
They did not avoid it because anybody was going soft on anyone else or because Japan wasn't day
Tempting targets
Snap up
They avoided it because they created the kind of society and Military
It made it impossible for somebody to snap
And they did this
Well coming from way behind in the technological race
You know most Miracle like fashion that I think and remember you are getting my little toe
For good or ill
The intensity of the Japanese character
Is in large part I think
A factor in this
You start talking about like National characteristics it gets very easily bleeds are usually in a weird
Racism
Stop but it's not
A Japanese
Racial thing that accounts for the way they are to cultural
Carrots and sticks but by the way full disclaimer here
It's going to be a lot of Race 2
Not because it matters to me or because I think it's important
Because it matters to the people in this story and they think it's important
The late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries one of the high water
What's College Global racism
And the pseudoscience
Stop it and it will impact this story to give you just one example without going to depleted when they will be cases where
I will just take
White
Western Society don't use the terms that are popular with the time. Because that's going to keep
We use the terms of use
Contemporaneously
But they will be white
Military powers
That will get
Badly hurt
From Miss judging the capabilities of a non-white power simply because in racial terms they considered them
Kind of subhuman we don't have to worry about
About those people because
I mean listen we're White
In there
I think the word that you
Used for monkeys
And the payback for that car make lie
Is to get your rear end
Handed to you by a bunch of people
And we that you underrated because of some weird
Construct
A racial superiority
It warm
Your perception of reality
Of course you know what perception of real
Eventually
Meets the real reality in
There was some payback there more on that in a little bit
My point is we'll get to the racism thing and we'll talk about race cuz it matters in the story
It's very multi-racial
In an era that's very race
In this case though
How do you
Figure out you know who the Japanese are and why they are the way they are well first of all this is a subject for expert job
Obviously Japanese culture has been much debated even in the United
State
I remember the kid when they started
I'm selling a so much on cars
A fascination with this Japanese
Corporate culture in the way they did things
This is a much-talked-about thing
Per person like yours truly
I can only hit the big boys there are some obvious things that you can look at and go wow that must have effect
Did the story
I don't know how I don't know to what degree I don't know what mixes with the other factors but boy you can't ignore
Is a couple of those I want to get into
You're going to help explain how we get to where we are
Every society in the world right is a blend
I'm old and new
In the case of Japan
The proportion of old to new includes a lot more old than most places
This is by Design
And their history kind of consciously shows not just
Ave
Preserve this distinctive way of life
But how trying to preserve their distinctive
Culture
Can get them in trouble where they then need those qualities of intensity and everything we were talking about before 2.
Dig them out of a hole of their own creation is this interesting dynamic between
Are the Japanese wanted to remain distinctive that that causes problems that then their distinct tivity
Require them to help them get out of
Without going too depleted
Let me explain
A little of
The background
Big events
Raven
Reading
Japan for dummies
Hope you understand first of all we all get the idea
The geographically speaking
Japan has the opportunity to be different just because
There an island nation or in
Series about
Having that
Little bit of water that cuts you off from the mainland allows you at times sometimes depending on the situation
In a long time to keep
The Ebbs and flows and tides and sometimes the storms raging on the big continent away from your shirt
Now the fact that you are an island does not
Determine
In any way shape and form how you develop their lots of different ways you could go for lots of different reason to me take a look at something on a map
Theoretically should be pretty simple
Take a look at Japan on the map of them take a look at the British Isles
Theoretically these places should be somewhat
Now I guess your name
And yet
The Japanese will have
Periods in their history where they as much as possible try to limit contact with the outside world.
That's just the way they wanted to go for reasons that are
Understandable once we get in
And the
English and British
In a larger sense or just the opposite I would going country might be a good way to put it so outgoing
Dubai the time
And we're setting up the story we're getting into now
They directly or indirectly control a huge chunk of the globe
The Japanese culture is a
Of course ancient
Dates back to
Really early time
And the relationship
That probably has meant the most
In Japanese history to the development of that island nation is the one that they've had long-term
With China
Jupiter
Review stage if you ask a Chinese person they might say it's the Sun
Not a necessarily impossible to justify point of view either if you think about
In a China basically being the superpower of East Asia
Throughout most of human history except for certain period of time when it
Reaches certain low point
Boynton power when does the civilization stock market dips for the Chinese stock
But most of the time in China
Of the world is at least as powerful as today's modern day China is
Things so stable