[Music]
Stealth technology, the Internet, GPS in
the palm of your hand, Autonomous operation
Technology is a driver of our times
since its founding in 1958 in the midst
of the cold war. DARPA the Defense
Advanced Research Projects Agency has
been a driver of technology.
Welcome to voices from DARPA, a window
onto the history people and
accomplishments that have earned DARPA a place among the most admired
institutions and cultures of innovation.
My name is Ivan Amato and I'm your DARPA host.
In this episode of Voices from DARPA we will hear from some of the
stakeholders in an institutional
five-year experiment called the embedded
entrepreneurship program EEI for short
the vision of EEI now in its second year
is to help entrepreneurs survive the
unavoidable and harrowing(令人悲伤的) phase of
startup and entrepreneurial culture
often referred to as the valley of death
that's when anything insufficient funding, poor cost projections,
missed deadlines supply chain issues inability to scale up from a prototype phase
intellectual property disputes market fluctuations a federal policy change or
any number of other hazards can kill off even the best of technology ideas like
the origin of any innovative technology
this innovative institutional concept
EEI began as a glimmer(微光) in people's eyes
including those of Kacy Gerst, DARPA's Chief of Commercial Strategy
the embedded entrepreneurship initiative
is you know like anything else at DARPA
it's a
it's an experiment we have specific metrics that we have to hit and
you know every year we'll continue to measure its value, we'll continue to
iterate and learn to optimize this model for impact
and at the end of the fifth year then
whoever the director is at that time
we'll we'll take a look at it and see if it's really helping us achieve the DARPA
mission of creating new capabilities
that are in the hands of the warfighter and national security end users
It's that last bit that part about getting technologies beyond
the valley of death and into the hands of war fighters and national security users
that EEI is designed to make happen more
often than it has in the past. There are
plenty of business and technology
accelerator models out there Tech
Transfer Offices at Universities try to
help faculty license patents or get startups going for one there are various
business boot camps that promise to turn
technical teams into business wizards in
three to six week programs venture
capital firms bet on winners and feed
those chosen companies various levels of
funding and sometimes business expertise
to help move concepts toward commercial products and services
Gerst says DARPA poses unique challenges
when it comes to accelerating development
in the innovation ecosystem
DARPA is
very early stage you know we're taking
things from
idea often to you know proof of
principle or
first prototype and really understanding
what performance can be gained and that
in business terms that's pre-seed stage
So it's unique in that it's very early
DARPA is
unique in that most of its portfolio
focuses on the
hard tech, deep tech space that you know
materials science, biotechnology,
microelectronics that take
a long time to mature.
A lot of the original business accelerators were designed for software
and not hardware and definitely not material science.
and and then the last reason why it's
unique is that it's very
high risk but potentially high impact
and so
the result of that you know in my world
is that you don't see
many straightforward business models
where DARPA has you know developed a
technology that's just slightly
incrementally better from what's out
there today and it it nicely fits within
to the existing system
you know the existing market system and
the existing supply chain often DARPA is
going after things that have off the
charts performance that have the
potential to to really upend the
existing market structure
that require new thinking around
business models and partnerships
sometimes DARPA develops some really
unique things where we're thinking oh
this could create an entirely new space
a new industry and that needs to be from
a commercialization standpoint supported
in an entirely different way and so
we designed this program to uniquely fit
the DARPA model EEI came out of the
gates in a mad sprint
following a pilot stage the initiative
began ramping up to full-scale status in
october 2020 in what is initially
planned as a five-year institutional
experiment already EEI is engaged with
more than 50 research teams each one
with big big plans we have
54 research teams some of them are still
thinking about if they should become a
company
some of them are in a corporate research
lab and they're you know investigating
the hypothesis that there's a compelling
business case here and trying to
determine if they should spin it out or
license it but
54 unique technologies that we're
helping plan the path forward for a
typical EEI effort begins when a DARPA
program manager a pm approaches Gerst
and her colleagues at DARPA about a
research team of scientists and
engineers that the pm is working with
and that has a great idea that might not
make it through the valley of death
without the sort of help EEI can offer
the central pillar of EEI's model girth
says is to provide funding in the
quarter million dollar range for
embedding a seasoned and vetted
entrepreneur into a technical team for a
year or even two years the embedded
entrepreneur adds crucial sober business
and commercialization insight and acumen
to the optimistic and often idealistic
technical mindset that the researchers
bring into the mix it takes both to get
promising technology into practical
shape manufactured and into the hands of end users
here's how Gerst explains EEI's special sauce
one thing we're doing differently from
the typical business boot camps that are
out there is we're providing longer term
entrepreneurial support
a lot of the business accelerators today
are you know three weeks to six week
programs
which didn't align well with our timeline
the 2nd thing that we're doing
that's really unique is we're running
this in parallel with the research so
what our scientific teams are learning when
they're going out and they're doing
customer discovery
you know they're understanding what the
market values what features make sense
what performance envelopes are required
they're taking that learning and they're
bringing it back and they're modifying
their research so their end prototype
the end result
is a lot closer to what the market would
value and pay for.
Running that work in parallel
speeds things up significantly that was
a big problem when I first came in.
Program managers were coming to me like
when they had a month left on the
research program and the prototype had
already been built and then we'd go out
and find out like
it's vastly more expensive than what
anyone will pay for or
this uh
this
feature that you focused most of the
research effort on they don't value but
this
sub feature that could really be
optimized further they do value and so a
lot of these teams were having to go
back
uh rebuild a prototype to make it look
more like a minimum viable(切实可行的) product and
that's really costly and it takes time
the final thing that we did differently
from
others is we
it it sounds uninteresting but it's
actually the biggest impact thing is we
have paid expert mentors
paid expert business mentors
most programs have volunteer mentors
when I was you know after grad school at MIT
I worked at a MIT spin out and we had
these great volunteer mentors that
helped us like one hour a quarter and [hehehe]
they had these phenomenal experts and
gave amazing advice that ended up making
the difference for us but we definitely
didn't have access to enough of their time.
This is where a foundational component
of EEI a partnership with In-Q-Tel
Emerge comes in.
In-Q-Tel emerge is a
subsidiary of In-Q-Tel a more than
20-year-old non-profit venture capital
firm with roots in the intelligence
community. It now has established itself
as a unique place at the intersection of
venture capital, government, national
security and the startup community
Scott Cunningham of In-Q-Tel emerge
works with Gerst and her EEI team at
DARPA and with DARPA program managers
and their research performers those are
the Principal Investigators, PIs and
other research team members that PMs
contract with to investigate new
technological ideas and territories.
DARPA is absolutely fantastic at
coaching new technologies into being
many of these new technologies are so
new that they go into new markets
and if you know anything about getting
technology to market when you have a new
technology and a new market. It's tough.
There's a dramatic
need for capital it's highly risky on
both the technology and market side and
that's a classic valley of death story
So what we
try to do with all of our performers and
with our PMs is take the the PM's needs
and the Department of Defense's needs
identify the risk elements in the
commercialization piece
not the technical the PM and the and the
Principal Investor have that but in the
commercialization piece
and help our colleagues reduce that
uncertainty which makes it much more
attractive to
american investors.
so if you have a new widget or even a
new vaccine type or a new way to get a vaccine
or a new way to interfere in a supply chain
or cook something out of a supply chain
there's an element of risk it
doesn't match up and you have to [..] is that
it just drop into the current supply chain
or is it very different
to the extent it's different you need somebody
to think through all the different
pieces the regulatory piece the
logistics the infrastructure the waste
all that sort of stuff so we work with
performers and work with the program managers
to identify those elements and
work on them.
That includes things like
intellectual property strategies,
market segmentations finding people to
put together the right pitch deck for
them and then actually matching up with
people who have money.
Those business (经验丰富的) savvy people Cunningham refers to
constitute primary ingredients of what
Gerst and her EEI colleagues hope will
become their lasting contribution to
DARPA's track record of delivering new
technologies to warfighters and not
infrequently to the public at large
these are not people employed at all by
In-Q-Tel or by DARPA. These are people
that we intend to embed so that all
their work products become the work
product on and owned by and and are the
confidential information of the company itself
So where we find these people? We make
suggestions the performers if they can
find them make suggestions there are
some performers in certain locations
San Francisco Bay Area, Boston
that there's a good environment around
for entrepreneurs and it's easier to find people
folks that we support in more remote locations which don't have that ecosystem
we go out and find individuals that they
could consider and they do the
interviewing, they do the hiring and then
we simply provide a non-object to make
sure that the people that are being hired
are actually capable and and competent(有能力的)
at doing the elements of our work statement
that we're encouraging to do.
We are talking DARPA here so that means
we are talking about visionary defense
technologies or at least technologies
that are very hard to realize so the
portfolio that Gerst, Cunningham and
their EEI colleagues is hoping to usher(引领)
into field operation and commercial
reality sounds like a technophiles(技术狂热者) wonderland
Many of them are involved in war fighter performance
everything from sleep to
vaccines to making sure our guys
if they end up in a far away place and
get exposed to
unusual things that we can detect it
that we can actually make sure their
bodies are are capable of responding to
it in unique ways we are working with
operational biotech supporting our
troops in physical structures
Can we
create novel structures to as you land a
helicopter to decrease the dust in the
air using biologicals some nutrients
that coalesce(合并, 烧结的结) the sand underneath the
helicopter and keep dust down
can we create artificial reefs to both
land on and protect against global warming
Can we
make bricks
in faraway places without cement and
lower carbon footprints and creating
coalesce aggregate materials and low carbon ways
of doing this
each of these is a specific company and
a specific
embedded entrepreneur that we have
supported
In addition,
some things that your listeners may find
slightly odd.
We support individuals who are
bringing materials to
agricultural uses
in the conversion of materials that are
contaminated(被污染的) with such things as
mycotoxin(毒枝菌素) into
high quality ingredients(成分) by feeding
through insects(昆虫)
One company that has scored some of the
earliest successes with its
participation in EEI is Embody, a biotech
firm based in Norfolk, Virginia. In 2020
the company launched its FDA-approved
orthopedic(整形手术) surgery product called
Tapestry. Already in more than 200
patients, the technology is showing
promise for greatly improving the repair
of tendon(筋,腱) and ligament(韧带) injuries which
are common in both athletes and
warfighters.
Let me tell you about
Embody's, kind of, technological approach
That's Jeffrey Conroy, Embody's Chief
Executive Officer, which makes him the
company's number one storyteller.
He says the company's partnership with
DARPA began when it was selected in 2015
as a performer for the atoms to product
program a typically ambitious program in
the agency's Defense Sciences Office.
The program ran from 2015 to 2020 as the
program's name suggests it was all about
building things with atomic level fabrication control.
Here's how Conroy
explains the basic technology behind the
company's new orthopedic surgery product
When we were funded under the Atoms to
Products(A2P) program from DARPA it was
basically a molecular level additive
manufacturing program so we were
effectively funded to innovate in
manufacturing methods
using materials at the molecular level
to build structures.
In our case it just so happens that we
chose to use
a biologic molecule collagen(胶原蛋白) as our substrate(底物)
and develop a manufacturing method to
engineer(设计)
surgical implants that would cause your
own cells to grow new tendon and ligament tissue
over a surgical repair.
and so
We use clinical grade collagen.
We combine it with another polymer(聚合物)
we create a copolymer
in a benign solvent(良心溶剂) chemistry and then
we developed kind of a modified
electrospinning(电纺丝), pneumatic(气动) spinning(纺丝)
technology where we reinvented the
physical structure of the system
the solvent chemistry
the material science in terms of
everything we could have understood
in terms of
possible combinations of polymers and
collagen until we found the right
tunable characteristics to engineer
fibers that allowed us to build this
surgical implant that really mimics(模仿) the
native microarchitecture of your own
tendon tissue (肌腱组织)
and so we used manufacturing technology
and a biologic material and biomaterials
to engineer these structures which
harness your own body's power and your
own cells power to grow new tendon tissue.
In other words typical DARPA super cool
technology helping companies prove an
audacious concept is what DARPA programs
like the Atoms to Product program are
all about.
But Conrad notes that small
companies like his not only have to
traverse(穿越) a technological valley of death
but to be fully successful a
translational and commercialization
valley of death as well
EEI was presented to us as an opportunity to get
an additional resource was the $250,000
that we were able to use to support the
hiring of a Chief Commercial Officer and
at a point in time 18 months before a
product launch where that person could
have a tremendous multiplier effect
in terms of
preparing to be commercial
building early relationships
building clinical relationships
building all of the framework
for commercial success that you don't think about.
customer service, how do we take orders
how do we, how do we do training, how do
we service and support customers
well beyond the positioning and the
differentiation what I can tell you is
that it turned into
one of the best decisions we made as a
team here in our six year history
because
we needed to refine the story we needed
to get our tentacles(触手) into the
marketplace. We needed to engage surgeons
earlier the result was not only was able
to bring seasoned executive Rob Brown
who's our Chief Commercial Officer, I was
able to recruit
a real high performance executive and at
the same time we were able to discover
new opportunities for a business
Now there are plenty of companies with
great ideas and an abundance(丰富) of science
and engineering talent but that still
lack the knowledge skill set and
relevant experience to get all of that
brilliance to the finish line whether
that be a new way to make missile fuel
or an autonomous naval vessel or in
Embody's case a new FDA-approved
biomaterial-based implant for in effect
getting damaged tendons and ligaments to
repair themselves.
Conroy says the boots on the ground, data
from surgeons and their patients since
the product's launch in late 2020 is
heartening(令人振奋的)
We've had a tremendous response after
launching the product at the end of 2020.
Now we've completed our first 200
patients we'll do just about 500
patients this year and
we're able to demonstrate that in 30 to
50 weeks our implant is gone and the
patient is left with new aligned
connective tissue and that is expressing
native collagen in place.
So we've created a mechanism to
stimulate
new natural tissue growth that thickens
a surgical repair and over time what we
hope to prove is that we've reduced the
patient's risk of re-injury and we've
accelerated the opportunity to return to
normal activity. That's kind of the the
background on the
technology that was funded by DARPA and
how we translated that investment
into producing FDA-regulated medical devices,
really for the benefit of sports medicine patients
Conroy credits his young company's
partnership with the Embedded
Entrepreneurship Initiative as
accelerating the launch of Tapestry and
opening the way for other products
we came in contact with Kacy's EEI program
and
that office had a very clear mandate
from the start which was
okay, we're a funding mechanism we fund
moonshot technologies, we're great at that,
we are trying to look a little bit
closer to the market and understand what
else do these companies need to be able
to get commercial. So what what are the
indications of success early that will
lead to commercial translation.
and
EEI came out of research and engagement
that Kacy's office and Scott Cunningham
had had started
our early EEI work was
they helped us develop a very detailed
market model to understand what adoption
would look like what we could expect
what our pricing models might look like
what our revenue forecast might look
like, it was really detailed as as you
would expect from DARPA analytical tool
that is
eerily tracking reality as we get
commercial here so we're really happy
fundamentally for me DARPA has been
if not anything
one of the most important relationships
in the creation of this company
and that means that not only were they a
formative validating partner in the
technology and bringing a product
through FDA but they recognized that
okay now the next set of challenges are
commercial challenges. yes you've got to
have great tech but now you've got to
have market needs that are attainable(可达到的)
you've got to have markets that you can
1) get your fair share then figure out
how to get more than your fair share
and EEI specifically
helped us go from kind of a consultative
discussion where we got
input on forecasts and input on
commercial models
2) okay now we're willing to put some
resources directly into the company so
that you can augment your team with
skill sets you don't have
their skills that you need we're going
to enable them coming into the company
18 months or at least 12 months before
we would have been able to afford them
ourselves
and it was transformational it really
helped us create a framework for
external success
not just how do you hit a project milestone
but now how do you hit the hot buttons of your customer
and how do you start to generate the evidence
that's going to help you scale and
generate a long-term successful
sustainable business. So it's been uh
it's been a great experience to be a
part of it and I'm really thankful for
Kacy's team and
John Mayne and the Atoms to Products team
and everyone at DARPA.
Embody is just one of the earliest
adopters of the EEI model there are more
than 50 others and Gerst says the target
number of partner research teams by year
5 of EEI is 150.
She notes that the collective portfolio
of these technologies already is
reflecting the broad spectrum of
technology development that mothership
DARPA is known for.
We have software to
identify deep fakes, we have design tools
to increase the speed of designing
integrated circuits, we have Covid19
diagnostics medical devices,
quantum sensors,
so it covers a pretty broad area.
Another key metric that EEI values is
how much investor capital for EEI
partner companies the initiative is
helping to attract especially from U.S
investors rather than foreign ones
the biggest win for the program is that all
of the funding that we've helped these teams
raise a hundred percent has been with
U.S investors rather than foreign
investors and you know one of the main
challenges that the embedded
entrepreneurship initiative was stood up
to address was that
because of that valley of death because
we had a lot of teams standing up and giving
entirely technical pitches that didn't
garner(获得) any investor interest. There was a
lot of foreign interest and foreign
funding offers into those companies and
so our initial hypothesis(假说) was
hey if if we can help them build up a
compelling business plan, go to market
strategy, then they will be able to
attract U.S investment
And after the
first year of running the program -- we've
just concluded our first year -- we've
helped our EEI teams raise 20x
what the government has put in through
the EEI program
in all U.S funding
from U.S investors right now it's at
like 244 million dollars
but wait
there's more
as of the end of november EEI had helped
participant teams spin out more than a
dozen new companies stand up nine
manufacturing sites and close 17
development agreements with larger
companies
Gerst knows DARPA too well to go on the
record saying that EEI itself will make
it past its own valley of death this
five-year experiment in which it has to
show it actually helps DARPA succeed in
its mission.
But DARPA is future oriented and
optimistic and so is Kacy
so I hope that when
our whole team the whole EEI founding
team when we look back
you know we're old and
we're looking back on our lives I hope
we can say
yeah
that made a huge difference and there
already are several
companies that have come out of this
where we can say
that wouldn't exist without this
resource
and what we did was really important
thinking through this new model or that
would probably exist but it would be
owned by one of our adversaries and now
it's it's based in the U.S
Thanks listeners for sharing this time
with me I hope you join us again for the
next Voices from DARPA
for more information about DARPA and the
many breakthrough technologies in its
portfolio visit DARPA.mil
and for links that enable you to
download this podcast go to the voices
from DARPA page on DARPA's website