Support for this podcast
Send the following message
Did come from
Struggling to find a purpose
Vacation home
VRBO does the hard work for you
Matching you to the perfect place to stay
Every time
Download VRBO
Go in the App Store
Let Virgo find a home
That matches
From NPR WBEZ Chicago
Wait don't tell me the NPR news
Quiz
Thom Yorke
Twin
Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown Chicago
Actor Kate Mulgrew
Joining us later on she of course played Captain Janeway
On Orange Is the New Black
You may have heard this
It is true Illinois
Republican lawmaker
Have put forth a resolution to
Project Chicago
Our city
From the state because quote the city no longer fits the values
Of the state that's fine
What cool amicable divorce we can do that but look if you do a check Chicago
Can you please put us somewhere where it isn't winter 11 months a year
The moment that we are still here
Ready to take your call the number is 10008 wait wait that's 18892
To 48924
That's my first listener contestant how you are on wait wait don't tell me
Hello this is
Grandma Kim
I'm calling from
Comfort Texas
Is it a comfortable place Comfort Texas
Right now
Pretty hot
What are you doing
Comfort
Cool camping
Or your Chef in a can
Okay this is a weird question for me on YouTube but do you serve the kids
Bug juice
No no
I'm sorry cuz we were served bug juice and I'm desperate to know what that really was
What what time do I show Grand let me introduce you to our panel this week
First it's comedian whose book your dad stole my rake another family dilemmas just came out in paperback
Welcome back
Tom Papa
950 contributor to CBS Sunday Morning in the host of The One
Wondery podcast OnePlus One it up
Finally the comedian performing at hilarities comedy club
In Cleveland June 20th
Through the 23rd
Alonzo bodden
I bet you knew this but you're going to play who's Bill
All this time Bill Kurtis
Of course is going to recreate for you three quotations
Things we found in the week's news your job correctly identify
Explain that do that
Two times at a 311 R price
You ready to go
Here is your first quote
Was extremely
Call
Hello somebody going to Great Lengths to him since he wasn't upset no he wasn't upset
When he stormed out of a meeting with Nancy Pelosi and Chuck Schumer
Who was it
That would be
Would be president
On Wednesday President Trump
Stomped into a meeting he had called
With Nancy Pelosi and Chuck show
Yelled at them for
Trying to impeach him
And stomped right out
Now we have never identified with Donald Trump more
Then this moment
Because we are also always trying to get out of meetings
Now the president then after he stomped out of the meeting
3 minutes after you walk in went out to the Rose Garden to make a spontaneous
Appearance before the Press
A spontaneous
Disappearance they had scheduled
Before the meeting began
And for what
Staff had printed up a big
Posters
Always has a spare selection
Just posters just in case the president
Needs to rent
I know the same way you always carry plastic bags
Can you take your dog
It was true
Yeah I guess so
Is walking around the perimeter while till he's finished
Getting to the Garden every day
Mississippi map
CMS
She said something about
Pray for the president president president after the country
Smart away
What's weird is that President Trump
Presumably is angry and
People OC because Nancy
Pelosi wants
To impeach him
Or as he likes to put it
The I word
And
And what's crazy is he says that but Nancy Pelosi but Nancy Nancy Pelosi famously is very reddish
About moving toward in
She says
That he the president wants us
To impeach him so therefore we shouldn't do it
He thinks
True
She thinks
What to do at the fire
What is base for the real reason is that he thinks
Is being impeached
Means you get to have sex
Sex with an intern
All right we're moving on
Here
Is your next quote
Lactose again
Tolerance
That's the rallying Cry of a protest movement growing in Britain calling for more people to throw what
At politicians they don't like
Close enough
Milkshake
The latest type of political
Protest is throwing milkshakes
Two politicians began with a protester
Was confronted on the street by the far-right politicians
Tommy Robinson and he had a milkshake and he spontaneously
You just took off the cap and threw it on
Ndk
Spread widely much like a milkshake down a politician suit
Right-wing brexit are Nigel farage has gotten so many milkshakes
Promoted him
Venom McDonald's near one of the
Speeches was asked by Scotland Yard
Not to sell them
So ecstatic milkshaking
We all got to see what it was like to be
Filet of fish
So can faraj say
He's shaking
Not so he doesn't have to whip
Was trapped in his campaign bus
Because people are outside all holding milkshakes
Imaginext
Just waking up
Wookie
It's so funny how different our culture
Shoes are like over there
Can insult again
With a milkshake
Vignette are present
Showers
What does seek
Secret Service have to dive
In front of him and takes the shape
Yo
McDonald's
Burger King this is truth advertising
Twitter hey we're selling milkshakes
King in the UK is Prince
Charles cuz that's the only time he ever gets to really wear crown
Set server closing you need to leave
You can keep the crown
But look how small my head is
Next to the mask
All right you're last quote is the title of an episode of Arthur that's of course of popular anime
Mr. Ratburn
Endless
Special someone
What episode was not broadcast in the state of Alabama because they
The special someone that mr. Ratburn married
Was what
Well yes another man
Another man are technically he married a male aardvark and I don't know why people are upset about two males marrying each other
Rather than a rat Marrying an aardvark of course the real reason
YouTube and show his you don't want to give people the idea it's okay to bring kids to wedding
Or maybe I would
Has problem with two men getting married as there's nobody in that couple they can forced to have a baby
I just would have loved
Sit in that meeting
When it like
The aardvarks marry in the rat
Not Northstate yeah these people just have
What that nothing else to do but apparently
They worry about the past
What's with the Teletubby
Marymount man
It's weird
Did the standard way of Alabama public television is still fine with
The Dora the
Explorer but that's only because they don't know that the thing that Dora is a
Exploring is polyamory
Just wait till they find out that everyone on Sesame Street
The furry
Spell hologram doing AR quiz
Congratulation man
We want to remind everyone they can join his most weeks right here at the chase
Chase Bank Auditorium in Downtown Chicago Illinois
Get some more information just go over to WV
Easy. Org
Guitar website
Let's wait wait. NPR
It is time for you to answer some questions about this week's news
Faith parenting is a full-time job through bonobo
We learned this week
Are heavily involved in finding their son
We know that bonobos are
Randy that's true right so I would
Think they're involved in find
Telling their son's mate that's exactly right
Supernovas are also
Vampire Knight
Yeah they came from bonobo with when they made partner
Bonobo moms aggressively help their sons findmate they check they chase away competition
Either their sons straight to potential partners and then
Explain to the feeble bonobos
How wonderful their son is once you get to know him
Classic Helicopter parents so who else is going to be at the party
And are they ovulating
And then this is true once
The kids actually hook up
With a fertile female
The mother will stand guard
Nothing in hands
It's a sexual performance like Mom
So this this behavior is actually
Sleep more proof that we have the
Descended oh yeah
Trump
Do that all the time
That's not good enough
My mother was more like taking
Relevant
She my mother never got involved
In and who I would date people would even ask her like this
Does it bother you that
Not married.
And she was like
I don't have to live with him
Yeah she later I'm rid of him I don't care who
Would you ever marry an aardvark
Coming up get out the Ambien is an insomniac Bluff The Listener game calling AAA wait wait to play
Will be back in a minute with more wait wait don't tell me
From NPR
Support for this podcast and the following message
Comes from
Trader Joe's
Were you never have to wait till
Discover delicious
Just foods and beverages from around the world
Speaking of waiting you don't have to wait for more episodes of Trader Joe's original podcast series inside Trader Joe's
Filled with fresh takes on everything from Frozen Foods to flour
Find a new episodes on Apple podcasts or wherever you get your pocket
Moret traderjoes.com and at Trader Joe's
On Instagram
And Pinterest
James Reid was fatally be
Soma Street
Death with galvanized
Put in a court room 9 months later
A not guilty
In episode 2
Trial in the birth
Mmpr it's White Lies
Listen
Drive now
Chicago
Wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news
I'm Bill Kurtis
We're playing this week with Alonzo bodden
Papa
Saline
And here I got is your house
Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown Chicago
Thank you everybody if you are listening on the radio
Kind of sad that you'll never be able to
Cherish this moment again well
Then just download the
The show with a podcast to listen to it again and again
You'll get all the quest
Eventually but right now it's time for the wait wait don't tell me Bluff The Listener game
Call 1aaa wait wait
Two-player game in the air how you are on wait wait don't tell me
Hides from Norwich New York
In the middle of nowhere
And what do you do there in the middle of nowhere
Baby quotes for Daniel little
Quilted like a particular designs they can be recognized
I actually know they're just
Get sewn together and
Richard it's nice to have you with us
You're going to play a game on what you must read to tell truth from fiction Phil what is Richard
Topic don't let the bedbugs
Nothing's worse than when you can't sleep
And even medication or PBS can't help
This week
We're out of someone being kept up
For a surprising
Reason
Are panels are going to tell you about it pick one is telling the truth you want a prize
The voice of your choice in your voicemail you ready to play
Yes alright first let's hear
Tom Papa
Asleep was couple in the historic Southern
City of Granada
In Andalusia
Have been troubled by
Strange incest
Buzzing noise
In their house
They called the police
Nothing
The cop firefighter
Still
Nothing
On a whim
They called their beak
Keep her friend Guerrero
Who enter the house
And discovered that it was
Was filled
Whitby
Course what else
With a beekeeper going to
One can only imagine the Carnage
The Beekeeper found a hive with around 80,000 bees behind a bedroom wall
Guerrero said he was
Surprise butt
Human inhabitants
Have been able to share a house
Noisy neighbors
Especially
As the highway
Was so big it must have been there for years
But as is common with a lot of Mary
Couples
Is it good chance
They both thought the other one and left the bat
Turn fan on
And refused to turn it off out of
Spite
With the B's remove the couple Canal look forward to even more sleepless nights as they return to listening to
To each other
Snore
And getting up to use the bathroom
A couple in Spain find 80000 bees in the wall that's in Tom Papa
Your next insomnia story comes from
Faith salie
New parents will try everything
Take out their babies
Nina bacon
Swansea Wales
Also gave all the mums
Co-sleeping
Support group
A gift of a
Sleep sheep
A fuzzy stuffed animal made
With real local lamb
Camphor that has a white noise
An embedded in
Turn it on
Cheap
You'll drift right off
But as soon as Nina started
Using it she started weight
Waking up in the middle of
The night screaming in a cold sweat along side
Her partner Nigel
Smite
Who's likewise
Speak watching her and hyperventilate
All this while their daughter merch
Curry bacon
Kept sleeping like
Like a baby
Her mom friends and their Partners were having the same
Problem night time
Terrors
No one knew why
One night
After baby
Mercury was extra fussy
Cartullo herself Act
Sleep Inn
Turn the Sleep sheep
Up to 11
As she sat listen
To the switch
Uterus
The sounds
She heard a deep male voice
Or did she
If she listens
Super duper closely chic
I can barely make out the sheets
Singing in a Barrett
The tune was like a
Soothing Nursery
Nursery rhyme with horrifying lyrics about devouring a baby
It was sung in this really cool
Creepy voicemail
When he got to the part about the baby
Beto's in earlobes
Sing like Welsh rabbit
That's when I gasp
Did Nigel sat bolt upright
An investigation revealed that while a worker on The Late Shift
Was making the white noise
Recordings the microphone
Him up while he was
Was rehearsing in a
Acoustic love song
Who's girlfriend
Relieved to learn this but still shaking
Nina says
I guess
He means well but he
Really needs to work on his metaphor
Jeep turns out to be a wolf
Infliction
Clothing because of
Hidden recording of an original song your last story of sleeplessness comes from Alonzo
Boden
Shannon Arthur Murray thought they found
Perfect retirement
In the town of ravello off the code
Coast of Italy
And they had
Until the 3rd night
It started at midnight
Crying weep
Screaming
In Italian
As if somebody was being
Torture
Whimpers grunts
Leaving deep bumps
Like bodies were being dropped on the ground
What was it did they live below a serial killer
Couldn't be
At that rate the time would be
Depopulated in a month
After whole Sleepless month is staring at
Interpret the ceiling they called
The police
And found someone
Unspoken nothing
English to understand their
Point
The crazy person living above us
I think you need
Helps Ensure
Oh no that's not a crazy person
That's just
Vlad Guerrero
He's the most famous
Italian painter's
Mr. Carrero known as a painter of joy
ASL million
Names of Prince and post
His favorite subject
Big eyed adorable
Kittens
Playing kittens
Hunting kittens cuddling
Everything but
In sleeping because then you could
And see that wonderful
How big I
Signore Carrero
Who's studio is on
Top floor to build
Heard about
Complaint and came to apologize
He explained that he was only able
The paint the happy kit
After you first
Spell dolly
Ozone rays
Legion anger
So that the only thing he had left the
To put on the canvas
Was inner peace
It's a loud process
She said through the
Translator buddy
It's made me really really rich
Alright get somebody
For a while until it was
Discovered was it from Tom Papa
Bees in a house
In Spain
From Faith Sealy
Bad original song secretly recorded onto a sleep sheep in Wales
Port from Alonso age
Screaming artist upstairs in Italy which of these are the real story
Of unintentional insomnia
Have to go with
A
They're going to pick a Tom's story Walter E the correct answer we spoke to someone
Familiar with it
Guy came in to evaluate the house info
80000 bees in their bedroom wall
Ryder talking about of course the discovery of this enormous number of bees inside the house
Congratulations Richard you got it right well.
Thank you so much for playing are in 2.4 Tom just for being honest
1R price
The voice of anyone you might see
Thank you so much bye bye
And now the game where we reward a lifetime of achievement by offering a few minutes of a pale imitation of it
But we call it not my job
In the Far Far Future of Star Trek humans have created a paradise of equal opportunity
Been weirdly
It still took them 30 years to find a woman to Captain a Starship
That was Kathryn Janeway played by Kate Mulgrew she also started as red in Orange is the New Black
How much is a new memoir
She joins us now
Welcome to wait wait don't tell me
Thank you it's very rare for
For an actor to play one iconic character on television you've done
What do you get recognized most for when you're walking them
Captain Janeway
Yeah I bet
I bet that's very closely by
Red and sometimes I get the double whammy which is an absolute next with
Captain Janeway Janeway red
And I'm freaking out a very interesting Venn diagram intersection but I'm sure they find you
I myself in the Star Trek nerd so I'm going to start by asking you about that was
When you were offered
That roll
Oh Captain Janeway in Star Trek
Trek Voyager
Did you know what you were in for
Did you know
I had no clue
Really had no idea that it was going to be as life-changing as it was
Normal life is
Typically ambitious
Forward-leaning young actress in Hollywood raising my Tucson
Intently I'm starting technobabble which is
Absolutely like learning Greek
Overnight
Sure working 18 hours a day in four and a half inch heel
Wait a minute I can't remember seeing your feet they made you wear
Are heels on the bridge of the Starship
Really
And if I had not had those heels I would have looks like a little cartoon character
They could have made you decided you were just a particularly
A short kind of alien
Did you how have you found I'm sure it continues to this day your interaction with the
I think the fans
Star Trek fans have the best fans
In the world but you never had a moment but it was represented by that classics
Night Live sketch with a Bill Shatner get a life
If you've never
And it's been cornered by these people arguing with you about the way
My hand stopped off and save it
I made it so rude and I said that to Bill
Really
What did he say that these people have given you your career
It's no big secret
And it works both ways
You lectured William Shatner about Hinata
So then a while ago you
Recast as read
Who is the
The chef in the kitchen in a powerful
What's the cook in the beginning
Did she change
What did you
I mean I imagine there's not a lot of research
You can do
To be a Starship captain
But did you actually have to do like the
The classic like actor research
Words to play that one
They gave me a very
It's small
A piece of paper on which was written this is Galina red reznikov
He's been in prison for some time
She's a blessing
We only want you to tap
Cockroaches looking for this place
Flavor
Right of of of Russia
But that is what came out of my mouth
I want to talk about your new book how to forget
Which is quite a remarkable book I've been reading it all week
First of all you really
All right I'm going to tell you the truth
Finally I can make the sign of the cross is not going to make much difference
Seriously the truth of the matter is is that a lot of the people we write we have in the show him written book
Make an attempt
To read their book
In your case I actually got quite involved in it
It's beautifully written and the story is I'm not going to say
Entertain
Beaming as much as as
Deeply involving
The book is about the death of your parents
Correct
I am told that your book how to forget
Is the number one best
Seller on Amazon
Under the category Dysfunctional Family
Congratulations
That's wonderful to know there's a lot of very intense stuff about you
Your family about your father your mother
I know your parents are no longer with us because
As I said I read the book but
In the book have they still been living
Obvious
Do they live long enough
How to understand and appreciate
Successful
You became
He never saw me
Never
He never watched
Play on television
She's pretty much a guy
That just confused
Right
He seemed to be absolutely perplexed by the what the hell are you doing up
Where are you
I just go get the vodka
Forget about it
I'm just going to ask you one but one more thing the
The your first book you're more autobiographical memory is called born with teeth
Cuz you were born with teeth
IWatch
What does it mean if a baby is born with a full set of
That she's awake
Oh
Are you a witch
I'm kind
Which sure
Cuz I've always wanted to say this
And now I can ready
We are you a good witch
I've always wanted to say that to you
I'll get you my
Well Kate Mulgrew we are delighted to talk to you we've invited you here to play a game we're calling
Red in Orange is the New Black
Meet the rest of this
Spectrum
So we want to explain the scene we were noticed a lot of color in your recent work so we thought we'd ask you about some other colors
That didn't show up
In your TV show
The three questions and you win our prize for one of our listeners
The voice of their choice on their voicemail
Bill who is Kate Mulgrew playing for
Sebastian
Fall River Massachusetts
Alright ready to do that I think you're ready to do this I got that
The nomadic
Tuareg people of the Sahara don't have a word for the
The Color Purple
Which has
Resulted in some interesting quirks
Such as which of these a
When Tuareg filmmakers did a remake of Prince's Purple Rain
They had to call it rain the color of blue with a little red in it
B instead of saying a turn purple with rage they say chewing on ones own toes
Or see they refer to purple jelly beans as the ones that are at least better than the black one
Definitely be
It was actually a
I know it was
You know what yeah
This was actually true is reported on NPR these Twilight filmmakers made their own remake of purple
The color blue with a little red in it and apparently it's not bad
Alright your next question
Pantone
Is the technical name for a brownish
Color
That has what
Distinction a dog's adore it which is why all dog food is that color
Be it is the color of everything Once you turn the lights off
Or see it is the very worst
Color in the world
You're right
That's what happened
What happened was an Australian marketing company did a survey they found out that this
Shade of brown
When is the least appealing color in the world
Unless they've been used it for cigarette
Okay last question you may think you know all the colors but you don't
Which of these is a real
Color
A fall of us
B Gamboa
Orsi's smaragdine
I'll bet it today but I'm going to go with B
Veganburg
Yeah you're right but they're all real colors
Call Miss can be described as a brownish-yellow gamboge is a transparent mustard in
Smaragdine is a kind of green
What do you mean how can it be mustard if it's transparent well
Color but it's like a lighter
Do we have
The colors are refinished
Why finish where only finished when built
Give the score so Bill
How did Kate Moseley doing a quiz well-proven Cambogia is the New Black
Emoji stars as Red on Orange Is the New Black is a
The former Starfleet captain on board Voyager
It's called how
To forget Kate Mulgrew what a pleasure to talk to you thank you so much
Bye-bye
It just a minute
Bill orders the beef tongue extra rare if you know what I mean it's the listener Limerick challenge
Wait wait don't tell me
From NPR
Support for this podcast and the following message comes from
ZipRecruiter
Hiring used to be hard multiple job sites
Facts of resumes but today
Hiring can be easy
And you only have to go to one place to get it done
ZipRecruiter
ZipRecruiter sends your job to offer 100 of the web's leading job boards
Then ZipRecruiter scanned thousands of resumes
Define people with the right experience and invite them to apply
Do your job
Try for free
Ziprecruiter.com
Slash weight
How many candidates are running
Presidents
Maybe more to come
What does a lot
Keep track of
Which is why the NPR politics
Podcast
Hitting the road
Introduced
All the people running for
Join us on the campaign Trail as we interview the candidate
Ask why they are the best
Pick for president
Follow along this spring and summer
Subscribing to the NPR politics
NPR WBEZ Chicago
This is wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz I'm Bill Kurtis
We're playing this week with Tom Papa
Faith's alien Alonzo
Zobo
That's a Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown
Gyro in just a minute Bill write his first
Op-ed for the New York Rhymes and oldy listener limerick challenge
If you like to play give us a call in one AAA wait wait
That's 18089 to 48924
Rhino panels more questions for you from the week's news
Tom Amazon is testing a new method to increase productivity
Improving their boring warehouse jobs by converting those tasks into a what
Video game
Exactly right
Basically the boxes you move in real life correspond to objects in video games and he's little
Scream there's a
Space game
My castle game and of course
Grand Theft Bezos
The Washington Post called it's Tetris but with real boxes
You're pitted against other workers and other
Departments and it's fun
Because if you win you might get to keep your health insurance
Are you avoiding anything are you running over
I don't know I myself have not played it
But you are actually visit by physically moving things in the world you are.
If I can leave the game
It's a huge Improvement
Over Amazon's previous game for warehouse workers who can go the longest without
It's just a nefarious way to track employees and increase
Deficiency but others say the same thing cuz that's obviously what it is
In a statement Amazon said no workers had experienced a side effects of mushrooms to eat to make it possible for them to jump
Do you play
Play a video
Play video
No I always want
But I have a life
Alonzo Alonzo this week a long-standing debate about space travel
Was finally resolved we now know that you
You cannot achieve
Propulsion in space using
What
You can't treat propose
Explosive
Any more personal propulsion around the space station
Oh you mean gas
Yeah
We say this
Nice gas
Expelled from a
That's exactly right
Or as we call it here on Earth
Farts
Trying to keep it classy
Have you have you not listened to the show true I've been here for a while
So so
Again this is this
This whole episode is
Is just having me Quest
Scientist you know you think there's
So
Willian and it's
Intimidate
Yeah and they're sitting around saying hey
Fart my way around the space station
Then you're like
Open the pod bay door how they're at least open a window
But I know for a fact
That my
Frenkie
That his farts
Light on
Fire
Corefact
And
I also know for a fact
If the flames
Too close to him while you're doing the
Experiment
His
Yeah jeans will light on
Dawnfire you don't even have to be in space
If you could just be in a base
New Jersey
Yeah we gathered that
Coming up the game where you have to listen
For the ride
If you'd like to plan are call and leave a message at 1 AAA
That's 180 date night
244 klickly contact us link on our website wait wait. Npr.org
You can find out about attending our weekly live shows right here
Route to Chase Bank
Time in Chicago
The Mann Center in Philadelphia
Her first ever show at the beautiful Blossom Music Center
Located within Cuyahoga National Park
Park in Northern Ohio
That's July 8th
Be sure to check out this week
Wait wait
Quiz on your Alexa or Google home device
Just say open the wait wait quiz
And Bill and I will hang out with you ask
Ask you questions listen to your words and if that's not have enough you could also win any one of her voices for your voicemail
How you going to wait wait don't tell me
Stephanie Carl's
Formerly of Yakima Washington
I just moved to Cheshire Connecticut
Well I've been to both
Hello
And what
Why did you do that and how have you found the transition
We love.
The New England is amazing
It feels like we're in another country East Coasters are
Something else really
To the last word or phrase missing for me
If you can fill in that last word or phrase correctly into the Olympics will be a
When are you ready to play
Here is your first
Limerick
From celebrity armpit
Sedney
I harvest their micro
With ease
It is culture
I'm fine
As I
2 On The Run
From their essence
I make
Wheels of
Cheese
If you like how cheese is made out of bacteria mold and hard old milk
The wish it had one more gross twist
A cheese maker in London is making cheese with bacteria starters made from swab celebrity
Skin
If you're not a list enough to be made into a cheese then you'll just be made into
Sea salt
Just think of how much closer you'll feel to your favorite celebs as soon as you eat their bellybutton remnants on a cracker
Imagine tonight celebrity cheese board a little Monterey Hugh Jackman
Some lady
Gorgonzola
And of course
Brie Larson
Alright here is your neck
Limerick the austrians
Raise in Ark
Brow
It seems odd that
You won't
Find the frow
Is a bovine baidu
So it's hashtag
Mimu
It's not safe
To be kissing me
Austria
Has faced an epidemic of people sneaking into pastors and kissing cows
After a startup offer to donate money to charity for every cow kiss
The challenge has proved so popular that Health officials released
Statement of begging people
To stop
Kissing cows
Look one side you need to stop doing what you're doing is if you put yourself in a situation in which ecoli is now a nest
STD
To kiss on the lips
Apparently
Kathakali
Because they braces
Alright here is your last
Limerick
From my lunch I feel abscess
4 days
News about Jenna Haze
Down the stairs
The truth doors
Listen past 3 minotaurs
Their bathroom seems a lot
Sienna
Ono well Minotaur is a kind of
Can't because where would you find the Minotaur in the middle of a
What's a minute
Pretty much
Reporting in a crisis in New York restaurant
Restrooms that are way way too hard to find
The Crosby Street Hotel restaurant requires you to go down a flight of
Upstairs and find your way through
25 doors
Before getting to the restroom
Diners have called finding the bathroom at Augustine quote like a game of
Flu
By the way whoever said that
Do not play
Clue with them
Restaurants in New York are considering fixing the problem by installing a Starbucks in the middle of the dining room
The problem came about because more and more restaurants are being built in
Reclaim faces that were never designed
D restaurant
The lone exception is the hot news
Spago
Turn on the old men's room
Port Authority
Bill how did Stephen
Can you do an AR quiz
She got it all right
Congratulations thank you bye bye
This message comes from NPR
Sponsor the Illinois office
Prism who would like to ask
Ask if you're up
4 amazing
From Chicago to Lincoln Springfield from Shawnee National Forest to Main Street Galena
There's a lot
To see in Illinois
Some might even say it
Amazing but we won't because
That's really up to you
Visit enjoy illinois.com and see if you're up for what some people
My call amazing
Support also comes from
VRBO
Finding the perfect vacation home is hard
Startup looking for the beach house big enough
Sex and wind up watching videos
Observing.
Verbos Got You cover
Matching you to the perfect place to stay
For your getaway
Every time
Download the VRBO app
VRBO
And put it into frustrating vacation search
Discover everything from condos and cabins to villas
Castles
Let's go find a home
That matches you
Now onto my final game lightning fill in the blank each of our players will have 60 Seconds
The answer is many fill-in-the-blank questions is he or she can
Each correct answer is worth 2 points
Can you give us a Discord
Faith your third-place Europe first the clock
Will start when I begin the first question
On Tuesday former White House counsel blank
A divided house
Judiciary
Miguel write several Film Production to stop filming in Georgia and protested
The state news
Blank law
Ord
Yeah boy
This week lawmakers in New York approved the bill
They would let Congress
See Trump
Blank text
Right on Thursday John Walker lindh the American who joined the blank in Afghanistan was released
Prison
Write this week a fugitive in Connecticut
Has agreed to turn himself in if blank
He gets 15000 likes
For his wanted poster that's exactly right
A new study released Wednesday warns that Rising blank levels could displace
200 million people are the
Next 80 years
Yassi levels yes
On Monday the Golden State Warriors
Swept Deportes
On the Trail Blazers
To dance with the black
Finals again
NBA
Celebrity Chef Jose Andres shared his newest recipe with the world
Potatoes roasted on a pan with blank
Or picture
No
Potatoes and roasted on a pan of compost
The chef's new recipe combines potatoes with soft coffee grounds and quote a scrap
That's from your compost bin
The instructions say use
Pre-heat your oven to 450 and surf
Potatoes sprinkle with coffee grounds add garbage to taste
And then order repeat
Bill how did faith
Do on AR quiz
She sets a High Mark she got 7 write 14 more points
When's total of 16 and Aleve
Congratulations what will you flip the coin in the back handle on
Heads or tails
Hit it is heads Alonzo you want to go second
Get it out of the way let's go right now
On Sunday President Trump told Fox News that he was doing everything he could to avoid a war with blank
The Rock
On Thursday WikiLeaks founder blank was charged with violating the Espionage
A song like this week Federal prosecutors accuse Michael avenatti
Stealing over $300,000
Transformer
Blank Stormy Daniels would be delayed Harriet Tubman
Make a group of firefighters in Arizona got more than they bargained for
A house that was blank
Fire know that was to be expected the surprise was it was also filled with snakes
Will giving the commencement address at Morehouse College billionaire Robert
Smith Blanc
OU Creed
To pay their student loans off he paid off everyone's student loans
Happy beating the San Jose Sharks in
In six games
St Louis Blues advance to the blank
NHL Stanley Cup
Right after being pulled over in Nebraska man
But they didn't believe him because he was black
He gave a woman's name is a man
No
Didn't believe
His fake name because he was also wearing a name tag
Call the guy over cuz his car matched the description of one owned by a fugitive named Markel counter but
When questioned the man said that his name was DeAngelo town
The name Frida
Police would have left it there if the man was also wearing a name tag that very clearly said
Hi my name is
Is markelle Towner
The man was arrested and is plead not guilty
But that was before police found a piece of paper in his pocket titled a list of all the crimes that I mark
Bill how did Alonzo doing our clothes he got 6 write 12 more points 50
How many times does Tom need to win 7
This really game Tom fill in the blank on Monday Michael Cohen said that he was
Instructed to lie to Congress about negotiations to build the Trump Tower in
Blank
Moscow Russia
Early results from India's national election show blank winning
A second term
Modi yes this week and judge ruled that the
Does peanut for blanks Wrecker
Secrets of Deutsche Bank
Could proceed
Trump right after a string of violent protests reacting to the re-election of Joko Widodo Authority
In blank
Restricted social media use
Used throughout the
New Jersey Endo Indonesia after trying unsuccessfully
Return an item to Amazon for x a woman in San Francisco blank
Yelled it
Siri no
One went to Amazon
Shareholder meeting and try to
To return it directly to Jeff Bezos
Hilarious on Sunday the series finale of blank said
Ewing records
HBL
Game of
Yes
A Massachusetts man called nine-one-one to say someone had broken into his home and blank
Liz farts on fire
No
Blind
Man and the man and his child got home discovered the back door open
What did expecting the place to be ransacked and in fact in fact found it to be a lot
Weiner
Then it was
When they had left that morning somebody had come in tidied up
Clean they actually they smelled all the cleaning stuff to clean the floors and everything and best of all
Included a little origami rose
Tide on top
Of the brand new toilet paper roll
Wow
That is the creepy
BS story I've ever heard
Spell did Tom do well enough to win
He's in there for ride eight more points a total of 11
He's
Not a winner
So who is our champion
You're just a minute
We're going to ask us after all the Arthur drama what would be the next time a cartoon who makes headline
Thank you to stock and Ledger for providing a family cookout style meal without actually having to spend time with their family
NPR WBEZ Chicago Association Productions in Bremen the benevolent
Overlord
Are public address announcer is Paul Friedman our house manager
Tyler green
Assisted by Simon Tran and married to Olio
Our brand new interns are penny Navid and Lila
Francis
Are web Guru is better
Novi BJ leiderman composed our team has produced by Jennifer Mills miles
The billion
Winner winner Peter Gwinn
Technical writer business and office managers Colin Miller
An executive producer of wait wait don't tell me
Now panel
What would be the next cartoon to make the news Tom Papa
Me to shows up at toys
Story
No one will work with a character named
Woody
Jake Sully
Paw Patrol cakes
Amazon anti
D-backs parents
With a rabies outbreak for a series finale
Bart Simpson is 30
6 years old
He is old enough and he will
I'll be running for president in
20/20
Iran wait wait
And thanks to all of you for Alyssa
We will see you next week
This
Is NPR