Support for NPR
In the following message
Did come from servicenow
Making the world of work
Work better for me
They're cloud-based
Platform and solutions
Deliver digital workflow
Spell create
Great experi
And unlock productivity for your Holcomb
More at servicenow.com
Hey thanks for listening to wait wait
Don't tell me before we get started we'd like to better understand
Who's listening
And how you are using pods
You can help us out by completing a short
Anonymous survey
Npr.org
Slash podcast survey
It takes less than 10 minutes and it really helped
Support the show
That's npr.org
Podcast
On the wait wait podcast you are about to listen
You'll be able to hear
Emily
But we can't hear you
But it doesn't
I have to be there
With the new wait wait quiz for your smart
Who will ask you a question
And
Be able to hear your answers
Imagine that
A little back and forth between the three of us oh what a
Gloria's age we're living in
Just ask you
Alexa or Google home
Do open the wait wait
To try it out
If you do well enough
You could win my voice on your voicemail
That's right
Get these pipes
Without
Aplomb
Give it a try
From NPR and WBEZ Chicago
Wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
Hey EDM fans
Get ready for it
Villa
I'm Bill Kurtis
That's a Chase Bank in downtown Chicago thank you Bill thank you everybody
Legends
Best of country music
Steve Earle
Now Steve is not one of those pretty guys and a cowboy hat and no
He is the real deal
Among other things he's been married
7 time
That you might call 6 divorces assign a personal issues
In country music they call that research
Let me know you have problems too and we just want you to call us
And play our games maybe when our prize the voice of your choice on your voicemail the number is 1 AAA
Wait wait that's 188-892-4890
2/4 now let's welcome our first listener contestant how you were on wait wait don't tell me
Hi
This is Michelle Nolan and I'm calling
Plymouth New Hampshire
Plymouth New Hampshire we know that tell me what you do there in Plymouth
Ironman Middle School teacher oh my gosh
You are a braver woman than I could ever be because Middle School is truly hell is it not
Colorful
Let me introduce you to our panel this week. It's a writer and
Performer you can see in the upcoming
Final season
A Veep
Computer drops
Hi welcome Mexican teacher writer for the
Style section of the Washington Post
It's Roxanne Roberts and finally a serious man with Siri
Serious things to say but none of them here
Play who's Bill this time Bill Kurtis is going to read your three quotations on the week's news your job
Correctly identify
Or explain two of them do that you would surprise you know what it is the voice of your choice
Are you ready to play
I am
Here is your
Your first quote
He's just extremely flirtatious
Completely safe
Now
That was Mika Brzezinski
Defending a prominent Democrat was being criticized for
The way he lays
His hands
On the lady who is it
It is Joe Biden Vice President Joe Biden Tuesday
About to enter the presidential race was hit with accusation
Nations that he's been
Weirdly creepy with women
Not exactly man-bites-dog more like man gives dog unwanted back rub
Came forward this last week to describe an incident 5 years ago and which biting to put his hands
And on her shoulders
And she
He says quote inhaled her hair
You must have liked to brand of shampoo because he then quote
Put a big
Slow kiss on the back of her head
Unquote
Now one problem
Is that is overly familiar another is that he doesn't know which side of the head is the kissing song
Yeah he's a little
Clumsy it's kind of like
Lenny Bruce
Oh my God
Can see how that would be
Be a belittling but I mean like I do that too baby head
Semi love V
Imma unembarrassed baby head
Mela baby's head and then this
Just like you just want them
They smell so good
People like how many months are you
The person is buying dip was he put out a statement he said
Not once did I believe I acted inappropriately while he also believes he was born with those teeth but it doesn't make
Heathen
I had to put out a video
In in which
He doesn't quite apologize
But he explained that things used to be different back
When when he
He started
Impala
Joe Biden
I'm not just creepy I'm also very old that
He should have just
Just apologize like I don't know why it's like what is it that so
Hard of four about policy
Apologizing
Because I'm sorry but I don't know
Play that whole video was like
I was like you were waiting and waiting and waiting and it and then like
He wanted you to think that he had said
Thinks he did anything wrong
I think Joseph
He's a guy that
This is like hey you know I'm a hugger
And
Get your hands off today
Can I marry there's plenty of times I don't think I did anything wrong but I still apologize
Michelle here is your next
Quote
That was presidential lawyer Rudolph Giuliani
Getting a little angry
This week
At the authors of what
The Mueller report report
Do you remember that's why I remember last week when the Attorney General said
The mother reports which only he had seen exonerated the president
It also said he didn't obstruct Justice
And also not only does the president really weigh 230 lb where is
Does long ties just to keep
From intimidating all of us with his rock hard abs
Well turns out
Maybe not
Members of Mueller's team are reportedly very upset because there were a lot of things in the report that made the president look really really
Bad
And somehow they didn't get mentioned
The team even had a list
True prepare to their own
Summaries
Of the different sections of the
Report to be released to the public
Summaries with titles like
Like Lollapalooza but with
Collusion
And I can't believe it's not obstruction of justice
Because it totally is
The molar teeth
Was
Legendary
For not giving
Bring up any
Until you if
Is raining outside
Standing next
Them
You said
Rite Aid
Indigo
Because the reason why we have like
Council regulations that we do
Do now that there is this like check of going
Attorney General
Because
Kent Starplex
Mass printed and like
Broke broke the internet for the first time 20 years ago would like
He released like
Every single word in every
Piece of evidence
And I wish we didn't have that one other wish we had
We could the country could live without like the blue dress and all those
But I would like to know
About like
Don Jr like calling up
Some Russian on his cell phone to be like hi this is the son of the president
Can you collude with me
Your last quote is from an article in the Washington Post
Describing a downward
Trend
That people are experiencing
There are a lot more things to do now.
That was one of the reasons that people might be doing what a lot less
Sleeping
Nowell
Metaphorically Maybe
Can you repeat
Well I have a hint for you
Okay I would never hear I was trying to avoid this
Well like chicken tenders
Their nights are boneless
Yeah Michelle do you know it now
What is
Yes I'm glad somebody around here up in class yes
Have sex is answered more Americans
Then ever before about 25 per
Percent reported not having any sex at all
During the last year 2018
Well if you don't count
Joe Biden
Sniffing their hair
And they don't
Because
There are more things
To do
There are
What's surprising about this is
That
Part of the reason is that people get older
And people get older their rate of sexual activity tents
The decline
Although they still have it which
Probably why the red
The jokes are getting a little harder for me to tell him to tell you about it
But
But what's different is that young people
Are also
Saying not this year deer
Given to believe that song
That when
The young folk with tax
Want to Netflix
Chinchilla
A metaphor for
Impeach
Actually Netflix and chill because that of course is the other
Explanation
Is that there are so many things to do including all this
Streaming entertainment
So you know it
He looks like
Yeah honey I'll come to bed as soon as I finished watching all of Nets
Many months later
Where did
How did Michelle do an AR quiz
If you got a ball right
Congratulations
Bring up panel time for you to answer some questions about this
Tom
Researchers at
Australia we're interested in making the roads safer for cyclists
As result of their study they have
Have suggested
That we ban
What
Spandex
I'm just tossing out ideas here
I need a hint
Well
This is true
They're suggesting instead
Rephrase
People who
Recycle
Stop calling us exactly right
Just like objectifying
You have figured it out
There you are that's exactly right you may think of cyclists is a neutral term like violinist
Best oral sex
But according to the authors
Bible study in the Journal of traffic psychology and behavior cyclist is a dehumanizing
Like caca
And it makes it easier for drivers
Is two sides
Swipe them feel aggressive even
Throwthings Anthony
As in I threw a beer bottle that a person is cycles and boy does that satisfy
But you have to
To say a person
Who drives
Threw a beer bottle at a
Person who Cycles
You have to say a person who drives through a
Bottle that beer
Coming up if you think lying is annoying wait until you hear this week's Bluff can call 1aaa way to play will be back in a minute with
Good morning wait wait don't tell me
Play from NPR
Support for this podcast and the following message
Which come from Stanford Children's
What are the scariest things are
American Hero
Mom look
Because the next words are usual
Billy can fly or
Joey riding the dog
Or a crayon stuck in Valerie's nose
Here's something you might
Want to hear
With over 20 pediatric office
Stanford Pediatrics
Oceans are all over the Bay Area
Not Justa
In Palo Alto
Find a Stanford pediatric
At Stanford Children's
. org
Hey Sophie reisenberg host of NPR's ask me another and I'm here to let you know that every Friday in April
We're bringing you an episode.
Spotlights
Women in comedy
You'll hear from redis
The star of NBC's parks
To Recreation
And I'll talk to Russian doll actor Greta Lee and co-creator leslye headland
And many more listen now
NPR
WBEZ Chicago
Quiz
I'm here playing this week with Peter Gross
Roxanne Roberts and Tom bodett
Is your host at the Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown Chicago PD
Thank you girl right now it's time for the wait wait don't tell me
The Listener game don't want to play a game in the air how you were on wait wait don't tell me
From Burlington Vermont from Burlington how are you
I'm great how are you
Talk to you
Turn right
Very popular here Jimmy like inside
Add a friend a couple years ago
Through the woods
Ask him on the trail the other way was Bernie Sanders
Well maybe it's nice to have you with us
You to play the game and what you must try to tell truth from fiction Bill what is Nate's
Topic you're under arrest
Isn't it crazy how standing in the moving sidewalk at the airport isn't illegal but murdering someone who stands on the moving sidewalk
This week I read about something that was once just annoying
Now being against the law or panelist going to tell you about it pick the one who's telling the truth mean when our prize
The wait waiter of your choice on your voicemail you ready to play
Oh yeah
Alright here we go out your first
Story of an annoyance made illegal
Comes from
Tom bodett
When Carol Domino San Diego discovered the CVS
Receipt draped across the
Kitchen counter
You couldn't resist pulling out or tape measure
Her husband had purchased one single Pearl
Prescription yet the receipt
She discovered stretched out at an astonishing
4 ft
8 in the height of Olympic champion gymnast
Simone biles it's also the width of an Antwan truffle reclining loveseat
Longer than the legal Harvest limit for alligators in Georgia
And about the size of a good number of other random everyday objects you don't think about very much
This receipt is ridiculous and unnecessary Diamond tweeted calling for the scrapping of
Give paper receipts for emailed version
Leaping into action at The Ting of a tweet
Democratic assemblyman Phil Ting of San Francisco introduced
The bill that would make email.
Receipts the law for businesses
Is grossing more than $1000000 a year
Rule-breakers could be
Define $25 a day and up to
$300
Is he here
Which if you're grossing more than a million is like
Nothing
State already banned single-use plastic bags and mandated that plastic
Straws be available by request only
If the ease receipt bill pass
California would want
Once again become the first in the nation
The Crackdown on another hidden
Hazard of our Modern Life
Their wasteful and their toxic
King said about the receipts
Their lack of recyclability really makes them problematic
Strong words from a mildly influential man
Rest easy California
California attempt to make those horrible long drug store receipts finally legal
Your nectar of something vexing being verboten
Comes from Roxanne
The Millionaires and billionaires in Palm Beach
Used to getting anything
Things they want
But on this
Florida Island
And the one thing they can't find
Is parking
The shortage of Pablo
Book spaces has been
The problem for years
But things came to a head last November when the least
Swagger
A descendant of the island
Is founder
Susie Herman
Third wife of a hen
Billionaire
Got into a fight on
Tony Worth Avenue
Elise Pollard
The front of her rolls
Into an open space
It's just as soon as
He backed her Jag
The same space
And neither would
The ensuing brouhaha
Resulted in
Disorderly conduct arrest
Add a new law passed last month
Reports the Palm Beach
Daily News
City officials debated various solution
But finally settled on
Two cars arrive
Same spot
At the same time
The older driver
Space
And only if he or she produce
Chooses their driver's
License as proof
Of age
But the Real Genius of this
Is that they know any
Any self-respect
Seeking trophy wife
Will drive away
Before ever revealing their real
31st Ave bend over
Further Enterprise in Palm Beach and legal solution
10 ^ 2
Two people vying for the same
Parking
Space your next story of a
Keeping prohibited comes from Peter Gross
What 75 year old Wanda crowns
Johnson ran for mayor Baker City Oregon it was on a pledge to
To quote restore fiscal responsibility old-fashioned values
Used and good grammar
That's right
Grammar
Miss Cranston
She's known to three generations
The Baker City children
With an English teacher at South Baker Middle School
For 45 years in
Passionately
During her campaign about how
Improper grammar amongst millennials
Does emblematic
Societies
Overall decline
After she easily won election last fall she had the clap
City Council
Pasty
Getting ready to affirm momentous modifications about recitation act or
Grammar Act
Which one into effect this week making the following conversational crime
Actual crime
Using LOL or other internet jargon in conversation
Using like anywhere in a sentence other than
When to indicate approval and using the word literally literally anywhere except
Literally
Violators will be forced
$5
Anagrammer jar a giant 6-foot tall mason jar that has been installed outside City Hall
This law is like
So stupid 26 year-old cafeteria being until the Baker City Herald
So what this town is going to have to take insane
At which point police grabbed Bethany copter and dragged her off to the grammar jar
Has she disappeared out of sight Bethany Was Heard calling out help I literally being
Tortured
One of these things is now subject to the full weight of the law or will be is it from Tomball
That was annoying long
CVS and Walgreens
Receipts and apparently they're like those received what can I tell you
Is it from Roxanne Roberts parking place disputes
Are now going to be adjudicated in Palm Beach by age
Or from Peter Gross
Actual laws
Against poor grammar in a
Small town
Which of these is the real story of laws about what is annoying
I'm in. I'm sorry about the long way
You're evil tomstar everything wrong receipts being made illegal perhaps
In California
Well
We are very excited about this
Because to bring you the correct answer we actually spoke
Did the person
Who was behind
This cracked
UC
People coming out of stores with receipts that are five
We wonder why the wasting so much paper
10 of California's 19th Assembly District talking about the receipt building introduced
Into the state
Assembly congratulations that you got it right thank you so much
Congratulations you earned a point for Tom for something telling me
The truth
I hope you feel good about that time
Thank you so much
And now the game where we invite people to join us
We're just about as long as we expect them to want
To be here
Steve Earle is the singer songwriter that other singer-songwriters
Want to be he came out of a Honky Tonks and Texas and then to Nashville where he wrote
Classic country-western Tunes like Hillbilly Highway in the devil's right hand
To know this is not easy listening
He has a new album out now Steve Earle welcome to wait wait don't tell me
Country is that your genre is that accurate I've been called
Country singer
Country rock singer and Folk
Singer in the New York Times
I'm in there like my dad thought I'd finally made it when I made
New York
Crossword puzzle
Congratulations
You you got your start really early
You just you knew what you wanted to do from very young
I didn't finish school because
I regret that now but but
I just didn't see how they were impeached
Then where that what I wanted to do then
But my parents were incredibly supportive I finally dropped out when I 16
That's I start playing coffee as an adult
Guys have been playing folk music for a lot longer than I had that's where I first heard of Townes Van Zandt
I got clock in my new record is a record of songs
Written by
Guy Clark because I made a record
Thrift Town songs
10 years ago and I do not want to run in
The guy on the other
Riverside having made
You are such a fan or
Townes Van Zandt that you actually like
Went where he was and tracked him down at the same time with guy with downtown Houston
He turns up at my gigs about four people there
Get out including towns
And the second set when I go down for my set you're the first at the most eventful thing was
The club Owners dog fell in love right in front
II said I finally come down and here's Town sitting in the front row
I drank a little
Pretty lit and he was sitting there and he did not make a sound while I was actually
Cut between every song Hit leave acne
Play the Wabash Cannonball
I don't like side play another song
Great I'm being heckled by my hero
I get a treasure longing to get to
Play the Wabash Cannonball finally had to admit I don't know the way
And he's in he's so you call yourself a folk singer and you don't know the Wabash Cannonball
Play the song called Miss
Mr. Mudd and mr. gold
What song has that has
About a million words
Anthony shut up
And he became a teacher
You've been through a lot
I mean I find out I mean like for example you played a recovering addict
In The Wire
I did and it apparently
It was it was not a stretch for you is it
The word for me too because I was offered acting roles when I was a lot younger and better-looking than
I am now and I hated it when I
Just made a record so I just always turned them down and
Then think about something I want to do with David's big music
Fan and heater
Call my manager because I've got this character
I think she could do it
What do you like to
Read what I read for it on me now just don't know
Meditating
In a studio
And you know it was
Play by play the redneck recovering addicts and like you said I didn't have to
I really accept New York and the most amazing
In New York are yoga and Broadway music
Georgia was just a
The thing that was sort of
Fish with a fly rod
And I get that travel places
Fun to do and I fell in a river for
For the first time
You know I was
Just getting back in the bug floating down to the neck
Ispot talking to a friend of mine
And I just said man my core strength is
Going
10 and he said well you're not been taking you got to go
Couple times a week ago
I spend money on dumb stuff
It started
Is that
Dealing with a physical issue
But I'm on the way I'm
Still here is 12
You know that's
It's a spiritual program and what do you think you're supposed to do is entrust
Is get to a place
Free pray or meditate everyday and that was the only thing that I didn't do
And I'm kind of an Old Hippie anyway and so I'm done about these things all my life
But through that Association I'm a yoga teacher in New York
Anna
Started studying with her
I'm on blocks and
You know why the cheating
You've you've been married
6 * 7 *
6 * 7 * 2
Six Wives right
So independent
I have to correct them
For the record seven divorces
Excuse me
Now
When people when people talk about people been married a lot
We often joke about you know hope over experience
Insignia they just think this time it's going to work out we talked about people's optimism
What I was thinking about in your case is
Is how do you if you meet a woman and the woman knows you've been married say let's
Pick middle 5 times before
How do you convince her like no
Really
We'll wait a minute. That like to hear it here is to hit the real question
You've been married
6 *
Have you made a woman
Willing to marry that's what I mean
What you know it says yeah that should give you
Pause and
I'm finally starting to get it
Yeah
Okay so
Let me ask question
Elizabeth Taylor
Was married to my X
Do you like to be
Married do you like being married
I played 200 shows
Best shows
That's not what I asked
I'm so
Whoever was married to me probably didn't like it all that much
Because I was gone but I have the time and I didn't really know what
Really being married was like the way the
I got my own room
Well Steve Earle we've invited you here to play a game we're calling Steve Earle
Steve Urkel
Hahaha
Do you remember you've been around
Yeah
Uber nerd Steve Urkel, popular TV characters in the 1990s in the show Family Matters
I'm guessing you didn't have a lot of time to watch TV and then I do know what I think I don't think I've ever seen a complete
That's great that you're not supposed to know anything
Going to ask you three questions about that icon in
On the Fly pants
Suspenders
Did you get to write you want a price one of her listeners the voice of their choice in their answering machine
Who is Steve Earle playing
Brian Hines
Of Pleasant View Tennessee
Now the popularity of the character of Steve Urkel was great for the actor in the TV show but bad for whom
A
The actual Steve Urkel For Whom the character was named who spent a decade and during jokes and
Disappointment
That he didn't talk funny
Be the belt industry as Urkel suspenders cause a 40% decrease in sales
Mercy speech therapist would deal with people trying
To talk
Like Urkel
Oh wow
What's a b
Do different be the belt industry.
Because that offenders are so sexy
That was actually the real Steve Urkel real scissors are the character's name for and he did not enjoy it after
Next question merkel's popularity led to a number of branded products including which of these
Hey Steve Urkel nerd glasses with masking tape
Pre-applied
Beer close breakfast
Cereal
We're seeing automated chess player called the mechanical
Breakfast cereal I guess
All the marbles
Jaleel White the actor who played Oracle went on to have the usual struggles of an actor
Associated with one roll
He tried appearing on Dancing With the Stars but what happened a ask to dance
Syn flood high pants and suspenders
You swore and stomped off the set
Behave yourself noxious the other participants became known as jerk off
Or see he insisted on doing his own choreography for the Jitterbug section and broke a hip
Oh
Let's see
Be it is be here by the way he deny the rumors that he was on
Unpopular and said he got along great with everybody he was still voted off the show
How did Steve Earle do
Smart guy
Steve earle's new album is called guy is out now wherever you listen
Listen to music Steve Earle thank you so much for doing with your life
Lily Pad is rocking don't come knocking in the listener Limerick challenge
Wait wait to join us on the air will be back in a minute wait don't tell me
Stream NPR
Support for this podcast and the following message
Come from Stanford Children's
What are the scariest things are
American Hero
Mom look
Because the next words are usual
Billy can fly or
Joey riding the dog
Or a crayon stuck in Valerie's nose
Here's something you might
Want to hear
With over 20 pediatric offices
Stamford Pediatrics
Are all over the Bay Area
Not Justa
In Palo Alto
Find a Stanford pediatric
At Stanford children
Stop. Org
El swiping on Tinder one
When she discovered the problem
I was literally giving
White faces
A chance I was not given
Black
This week
Invisibilia follows
One woman's Quest
To get rid of her racial
From NPR
WBEZ Chicago this is wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Kurtis
We're playing this week
With Peter Gross
And Roxanne Roberts in the area
That's a Chase Bank Auditorium
Downtown
Chicago PD
Bill sings his favorite song by Ronnie Anna Grande
Would you like to play
It's called one +888-888-924-8924
Rena panels more questions for you for the week
Week's news
Peter many of this year's 1700
Democratic candidates for president
Many of them have of course created Spanish
Best versions of their campaign websites right
What a recent report in Politico showed that many of them actually made those websites by doing what
Yes
Using Google Translate
That's all I did
It's it's very economical or as Beto O'Rourke
Spanish site might say I'm very talk Spanish
Went out in the rain to eat
Democratic candidates
Spanish language websites Cory Booker and Kamala Harris
Prescott AZ
Amy Klobuchar though got a C4 mixing up the Spanish
Fish words for fork
And comb
Is entirely done through Google Translate
Resulting in this
Truth Club shark holding her own mother a dude
We went over in his spanish-language side Bernie Sanders just added to everyone
The millionaire
I feel their pain.
Rita's my wife
What is a native Spanish
Speaker
And sometimes to impress her like I want to write
Thing really romantic and
An anniversary card
Or something
I'll go to
Google Translate
And put my sentiments into
Spanish into talk
What does
Peter safety officials in New York are cracking down on one side
Specific type of business that they say is not providing enough exits
And in many cases trapping customers inside
What is the best
Escape room exactly right
Designed to trap people inside
Back in February New York rate of the task force to investigate all 22 of the Cities Escape rooms
For safety violation
They went to the first one and haven't been seen
The task Force's findings twenty one of the 22 Escape rooms have exit that are not clearly marked
And the other one has been shut down for being rude
Ridiculously easy
It is like a weird
Phenomenon
People are like put me in danger as I take it out and then
No I did one with my my whole family in my in my mother
Father-in-law
Was in New Jersey
But it was really hard
Scratching at the
Bleeding was one of the ones like a zombie and a chain with a
It's one of those
Theme there was a lot of
Sea mythology
Involved
Play like Tara is there somebody in there
You Must Escape the other Wonder ship is it that
Peter Comfort is the number one factor and underwear purchases
Which is why One Clothing Company
Is making underwear out of what
Old t-shirt
Snow
Ironic about the country
Oh my God I saw this
Gene
Jessie Jean panties jayanti
If you wish you could feel like you were riding a horse naked
On a saddle made of sandpaper
Have we got underwear for you is high-waisted underwear made of
Denim complete with rivets and Pockets called
Janties
JD's of course Spring up scratches
If you think
Is a combination of the word panties and Jesus Christ you're not going out
Hey sorry to bug you about the
I'm really insecure
I need validation
Please help us out by completing our survey
Npr.org
/ podcasts
Thanks
Coming up lightning fill in the blank the first it's a game we have to listen for the rhyme if you like to play on air call and leave a message at 1 triple
Wait wait
That's one 888-924-8924 you
The contact us link on our website wait wait. Npr.org
You can find out about attending our weekly live shows here
Chase Bank Auditorium in
Chicago
Are upcoming show in St Louis Missouri on May 9th
And if you love to experience
The throat without going anywhere
Check out our new interactive quiz
If your smart speaker
You're just hoping the wait wait quiz and you can talk directly to bill in myself
And we will talk back
You could even win the voice of your choice for your voicemail playing
Are you are on wait wait don't tell me
Hi Peter is Tillery Jericho from
Chicago Illinois
Do here in the finest city in the world
Pediatric gastroenterologist
Chicago Comer Children's Hospital
What's good work
Can you live that in you live down there in
In Hyde Park
We actually live in the South Loop pretty close to Soldier Field
Okay
So you can
Watch all the drunk people leaving that's exciting
I hope I wasn't singing
Well
Welcome to the show Hillary
To the last word or phrase missing for me to
If you can fill in that last word or phrase correctly to the limits will be a winner you ready to play
I am alright here's your first
Too ruthless
Blood-sucking Banditos
We humans are just
Big Burrito
Play the Messiah
And they will not drill a
It kills food and sex
Mosquito DJ Skrillex is apparently a real Buzz
Skill according to researchers
Skrillex's EDM tracks
Scary Monsters and Nice Sprites
Has been linked
Two declined mosquito mating rates
The song which if you haven't heard it
And let's be honest
None of you have
Aces high or low frequencies
Distracting mosquitoes from the usual Hobbies of blood-sucking
King and getting it off
It isn't that they hate
Skrillex music that's the thing it's not like it's driving them away and they love it
Get there quote
Entertained by it
Which means they attacked hosts less often
Then those in a dubstep
Free environment unquote
Mosquitoes are having
Exactly.
All right Hillary
Here is your next
Limerick since moon rocks are easy to scoop
Old ways
We will try to recoup
We're paying the piper by bringing home diapers
Will go back
To pick up our
Hoopa perfect LED for gastroenterologist
Foxy Apollo 11
Left 96 bags of human waste
A stop on the moon
Now we know why there's a dark side
Side of the Moon
Humans have been blasting things that the space for years now
Liked songs by Mozart
Boc photographs
Apparently our poop
I just want to go back
To pick up the moon poop
Do research how living microbes have
Beard in space
Over the last 45
Buzz Aldrin
The first people on the moon
Himself tweeted this week I sure feel bad for whoever finds my bag
Really I mean after like 4 days of
Pang
Yeah
90s
Six pack
Alright Hillary here's your last limerick
It's quite enough beat
Epilogue
They found me a mate
In a bog
I've got an amphibian reason to live again
I'm no longer the lonely is
Back in January you told you all about Romeo the so-called world
Frog vodka
To be the last
Has water frog you lived in isolation
For 10 years
But an expedition to Bolivia found Romeo his Juliet
Nice another frog
Secret to poison them
Makes it seem like your dad when you're really not but I'm sure nothing bad will
Do frogs have hit it off to now
Living together
They're even trying to mate
The Romeo quote needs more practice
It's understandable they might have some trouble giving that Romeo is going to loan for 10 years and also there's a little bit of
Pressure all the signs
Does the staring at them going
Hey guys start doing it of your species will die out of it
Bill how the hell are you doing
Hillary is very good very smart
She got all three right
Congratulations
Support for this podcast
Send the following message
Message come from Stanford children
One of the
Scariest things
Mom look
Because the next word
Are usually
Billy can fly
Or Joey riding the dog
Or a crayon stuck in Valerie's nose
Here's something you might want
With over 20
The pediatric office
Stanford pediatric
Kids are all over
The Bay Area
Not just in Palo Alto
Find a Stanford
At Stanford Children's.
Support also come
Comes from feather
Weather moving to a new city
Or moving down.
Feather believe
You start with life
Your furniture
I should be able to
Change with you
Become a feather men
And get access to over 150 pieces of
High quality
With the option to add
Swap buy or return
When life or taste
Change
See how easy it can be
Delivery app
The burdens of
Furniture owner
Available in LA
Orange County
New York and San Francisco
Feather
Furniture that
Changes with
Now on to our final game lightning fill in the blank each of our players will have 60 seconds must answer as many fill in the blank
Is Hershey candies correct
Cancer net worth
Bill can you give us a
Tom and Peter each have three
Roxanne has to
Alright Rock You are in third place or up first fill in the blank
On Wednesday Theresa May once again requested an extension for the blank deal
Right on Sunday the state department announced
Plants
To cut Aid
Two three countries in blank
Central America this week a parent in California became the first person to
Plead guilty in the blank and Mission
The college bribery
Overwhelming Victory Lori Lightfoot was elected blank
First black
Female mayor
Mayoral race
Write an interest from visiting Komodo Island because
Cuz people keep blinking the Komodo dragons
They keeps
Feeling that's right on Sunday Yukon Advanced to their 12th
Straight final four appearance in the one in the blank turn on
Ncaas on Thursday electric car company blank reported record low sales in a 10% dip in
In stock value
Peppa police he was shot while protecting an asset during a secret mission was actually blank
He and his buddy
We're shooting each other to
To try out there bullet
That's exactly what we do
Took himself to ER
The police got there he told him I mysterious assailant attacked him while he was protecting an asset
Man's wife was not amused by this nonsense and blew his cover
Man insists he will be exonerated once the full Mueller report is released
Bill
Actually well and i r l a r e
She leaves
With a total of 82 coin Peter has elected to go next so Peter Phillips
On Sunday a whistleblower revealed that 25 people in the White House were granted blank
Despite significant red flag
A security
Right on Thursday President Trump walked back his
Close the blank
Featherboard
The price this week Mitch McConnell use the so-called blank
Option
Advance a handful of press
Trump judicial nominees
Nuclear Strike this week the CEO of blank said the company took full responsibility
37 Mack
Waynesboro
Right saying he wanted
To celebrate
His team's big win with his granddad
Add a soccer fan in Argentina
Flew his grandfather to Argent
No he rushed to the graveyard to dig up his Grandpa's skull
Put you at a higher risk for death and son Blanket
Smoking on Tuesday farmer bro blank
Solitary
It was revealed he was running his business from prison
Shkreli ride in what experts are calling the most
Swedish arrest ever an officer in Stockholm apprehended a man
While they were both blinking
Making meatballs wearing bikinis and acting as a muppet
The Great Gatsby
Bill how did Peter doing our quiz
Got five right
Total of 13 which means
Roxana
Still in the lead Lorelei
So I'm guessing that in order to win Tom has to be perfect
He has to get the full boat
Here We Go Thomas
Listen for the game from the blank
On Wednesday the White House Began their ninth round of trade talks
With blank
Vagina right on Sunday a woman carrying a USB drive full of malware was arrested by the sea
Secret service at blank
Mar a lago house Ways and Means Committee asked the IRS for
6 years of blank stacks
Stop President Trump state of blank was indicted on bribery
Three charges North Carolina
This week a Maryland man was extradited to
The Florida on charges that he had a blank
While on vacation there
He does dress
Chinese woman and snuck a malware
Tackled a pelican
On Thursday
I think I do
Just lost pelican pelican on did me on Thursday
$18 an hour
Beginning weight
According to a new study cats are able to recognize their own blanks
You like this
It's like news it's their name
But they just don't care
Dang it, the company created the new alarm clock that uses the
The soothing sound of
Blank
Oh yeah I know
This is a cat coughing up a hairball
You know I'm going to give it to you
Seriously
The answer we have is a puking dog
He's got Patsy I'm here the Catalan alarm is an app with a variety of climates
Beijing sounds ranging from
Atom smoke alarm
Do dog barfing and your bad I'm sure they have cat coughing up hairballs in there
But if that doesn't work there's always the premium membership
Which is a real dog
And I guarantee she'll never sleep past 6:30 ever again I don't think so
Close he got
14 more points total of 17 with lost
Kalahari Park
Surprising Revelation in the mall of report when we finally get
To see it
Special thanks this week
Stock and Ledger
Perfidious
Wait wait don't tell me the productive NPR WBEZ Chicago in association with the Urgent haircut Productions
Doug Berman benevolent overlord
Warehouse managers Tyler Green Assisted by Simon Tran and married to Aaliyah
Are interns or Alex McCone
The Clapper
BJ leiderman composer I seen my program is produced by Jennifer Mills miles dornbos
And Lillian King
Our love language
Is Peter Quinn
Directions to y&r business on off managers call another rapper that can coordinators Robert
Executive producer of wait wait don't tell me is my
What will be the big shocker
In the Mueller report
One entire page will be
Redacted except for 3
Scattered words
Duck
Parade
Sphincter
Investigations in Sioux
Roxanne Roberts
We'll find out the body of Jimmy Hoffa is buried in New Jersey
Under the 18th
Hole at Trump Golf
There's a reason that you've never seen the two of them in the same room
Steve Earle
Steve Urkel
Are actually the same
That happens will ask you about it
I'll see you next week from San Antonio Texas
This
Is NPR
Support for this podcast
And the following message come from Madewell
Where the model
Good day start with
Straight jeans
Madewell offer
Apus premium denim styles
For seriously
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com