Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Park
The newest Resort
In the center of the Las Vegas Strip
Enjoy Powerhouse artist
Dislike Lady Gaga
And indulge and inspired cuisine
From pacemakers like Roy Choi
His new restaurant best
Bill Kurtis here
On the wait wait podcast you are about to listen
You'll be able to hear Peter
Emily
But
We can't hear you
But it doesn't have to be that
With the new wait wait quiz for your smart
Speaker will ask you
And
Be able to hear you
Dancers imagine that
A little back and forth between the three of us
Soho what a guy
Gloria's age we're living
Just ask
Alexa or Google home
To open the way
Weight quiz
To try it out
If you do well enough
You could win my voice on your voice
That's right
Get these pipes
Without
A plumber
Give it a try
From NPR and WBEZ Chicago this
Wait wait don't tell me
Play NPR news
DeNiro get a load of me
Raging bill
Chase Bank
Auditorium in Chicago Peter Sagal everybody
Birds are chirping and it's time to take a moment
To enjoy this
Spring because pretty soon the only Seasons we will have will be summer
Summer 2
Mega summer
And everything is on fire
So while we can
You still go outside without
What's putting on
Fiat 500 sunscreen
We're breathing in some fresh air
Taking a week off from the news
Instead
We're going to listen back to some segments
We love
Let's read with an interview with my
Second favor
William Shatner
Who joined us back in December
Peter tried not to
Geek out
And failed
So when I was a kid I loved Star Trek
The original
I loved it so much
That I used to dream
Crewmember
The Enterprise
Sure guys they got
The trouble with a blue shirt maybe even a yellow shirt
And I will get it
I have ambition but that's my job
This isn't how I thought it would go but I dreamed in those days that I would someday get to talk to Kathy
Dunkirk himself
Will now find out if that's
As good as I dreamed it would be because William Shatner
Has a new album
Christmas songs out in
And he joins us now
Where are water playground
I'm really excited to be on because I've got to tell you
Listen to the program over the years
It's one of my favorites driving somewhere on the Saturday afternoon
Wait wait don't tell me I can't tell you what it means to me to know that you
Listen to me
After I spent so many happy
Towers Watson
Yes but I didn't know it was you all right
You become quite a recording
Sorry I have I've got the two records it to albums out this year
A country music album and this Christmas album that we've called Shatner Claus
Now you're singing career if I may be so
So bald
Begin with the record that you put out when you're playing captain
Back in the six
Pants for men
I've listened to the whole thing
Wow cities where you did that that eventually
The infamous version
Lucy in the Sky with Diamonds
As I'm sure you know this
Became
Shall we put it
A novelty song
After a while
Ends and subjective of much amused
I believe the word derision is
And was that hard
For you to deal with with that became like a
Hilariously funny thing
We sharing back
It does
Cinder the area of the perception of silly
But as the singing William Shatner
We all know the famous sketch you did on Saturday Night Live where you're at
Star Trek
Express
Some shall we say in page
Witty remark
Was that reflecting your experience
No it was meant as a joke and I'm sorry
Did you took it too seriously that you moved out of your parents apartment
It's all right
I was going to talk to my mother
I know that there has been
There's been so many
Versions of Star Trek
The best one
That a lot of people spend their time arguing over which Captain was better I
To me believe it was
I don't know what the argument is about actually
Direct development directions I get together with the other actors
Whatever hash this out
Yes
Several blows
I think everybody thinks that the best tonight I just leave them in
There
Quandary I don't want to disturb you there
Metal
Stability
That so many people have done over the years
Is they do their William Shatner
Yes I have done
Can't how can I change the face of the
In the face of the Earth
By popular demand you're being requested to do the invitation
Are the only thing I can think of to do
Is the episode
Where are you
Enterprise
Ends up
On the
The planet where the
Becomes our findings
Fighting the yang
If you remember this
Captain Kirk
Enterprise
Save them by introducing
Sing the US
Well Bakery
We
People
Wait a minute wait a minute
The worst imitation
Well William Shatner as you can tell we're all pretty delighted
To talk to you but we must
Do our business we have invited you here to play a game we're calling
Film Festival
So one of the greatest moments we would agree
Was you shouting Khan in Star Trek 2
The Wrath of Khan
But a different kind of the khans film fest
Sibling friends answer
Two out of three right you win our prize for one of my list
The voice of anyone that they like
Bill who is William Shatner playing for
Breast
Wow Columbus Ohio
I know him
Here is your
First
Question
Martin Scorsese
70s
Who had the best
Relationship with
The press record
Swarmed
In 1978
Target Express you decided to stop all the interviews
Is why
Hey he ran out of cocaine
Saying no more coke no more interviews
Be he called the police on a reporter who asked
Kim how tall are you
Are you anyway
Or see he snapped and
Responded to a question by shouting you talking to me
You talking to me
It's got to be dirty snap
He did
He snapped and started shouting you thought you were talking to me you talking to me
It was the cocaine you know
Of the 70s
Different time
Alright next question, is famous for the film company
But also for elaborate the Blissey
Surrounded
Such as when one company
Once did
Swarmed the celebrities on the red carpet
The 200 fake zombies
Resulting in three actors getting bit
Be poison to the food at
The party's Buffet just
To entice partygoers
A visit from porta potties
Recovered with ads
Orsi's storming the famous hotel
Du cap-eden-roc
Fake terrorist
Dressed like Isis
That's a good thing they would do
Glass that's what they did
It was supposed to promote this company's Broadband services
Is it did not help
Last question if you get this right you win
And my life has meaning
The festival
Can be dangerous
As in which of these
Hey over the years at least 14 women and 4 men have
I fainted
From being crammed
Too tight outfits
For the runway
Be when the actress Simone Silva took off her top in a photoshoot
With co-star Robert Mitchum
Two photographers suffered broken bones and
Yuan Crush
Or see the sound of all the cameras going off attracts hordes of wild dogs
Known
SLS Chien du Cinema
I love the picture of of Mitcham standing by
Well the lady just robes and people that crushed
That's when you got to go with your right
The ensuing photograph
In which mission is kind of using his hands as it makes you
That picture is actually what I'm most famous images
Tanacon
Bill how did William Shatner do in Ark
3 +
Congratulation
William Shatner
There's new Christmas album Shatner Claus is out now William Shatner
Piers in unaired moment from one of our past
Helen with more and more States legalizing pot
The hot new trend
Cuz I'm sure
You all know
New trend is
Cannabis drinks
A problem
Cannabis
String
You drink one and then you fall
Fall asleep
They don't really sell a lot of them no that's not the problem
Well you may not notice by the third one
It takes awhile for it to hit so
You're just
Believe
No that's not the problem that's my club basic problem two people selling beverages
You
Heave
Weed out
Every single answer you've given is the right answer
No problem
We will see a lot of sophisticated stoners
Serta picking one up holding their nose and then
Thanks
I told you you were in fact
Kefla
Exactly like you
Actually they do taste terrible they have flavor is described as quote oily grass and having notes and quote
Dish soap and urine I know I think you're thinking of Zima
It really gives a new meaning to this buds
For you
Repeat that
Shake It Up
Candice Bergen that's in a minute on wait wait don't tell me
From NPR
Support for this podcast
Then the following message come from UCLA Anderson School of May
Who teaches the next generation of leaders their values
Stop sharing success
Thinking fearlessly
And driving
Anderson offers globally ranked MBA program
As well as master of financial engineering
Master of science in business Analytics
And doctoral and Executive Education
Tailor to sew that graduates
Create a positive impact
On businesses and communities
Morten Andersen
PennDOT ucla.edu
High of your eyes over here host of NPR's hour of puzzles word games and trivia ask me another
This month we're celebrating women in comedy
And this week we're joined by Retta
You may know her from her role on NBC's Parks and Recreation or her new series good girls
Listen And subscribe now
From NPR and
WBEZ Chicago this is wait wait don't tell me
Play NPR news
News quiz
Here's your host at the chase
Chicago
Peter Sagal this week we're taking a break from the news going outside
Binge watching the world go by
Have you seen the show called the
Clouds
Special effects
Amazing
Apply sunscreen let's keep listening to our favorite segments from the last
He is a Resa
Bluff game that
Michael Holbert
And I'm calling from Shelburne Falls
House Massachusetts
Shelburne Falls Mass
I thought I knew message
As well but I have no idea where the
That is
It's a little bit Western
All right
Are you just making up town name to fart right now cuz I've never heard of Greenfield either
What do you do there
I am a musician and performer in a small theater company called the
Agile Rascal bicycle touring theater
Bicycle touring
Yes we
Perform original Works in theater and we tore them
On bicycles and we perform for free
The theater
It's not hard enough let
Let's make sure that when we show up
MLB sweaty
Are we going to break into the Shelbyville mark
You make it in Shelbyville then you can move over to Greentown
Unser hello Michael
We're going to play our game and what you must try to tell truth from fiction Bill what is the time
Bullseye
That's the game we play in bars mostly because that's definitely the time to be picking up sharp objects
Throwing them
But what's a Pastime here is a
Port in Great Britain and in fact
There was a big
Controversy
As they say over there
At this year
Grand slam of darts
Tournament are panelist or each
Pick that one winner prize
The voice of your choice
On your voicemail
Are you ready to play
Yes I am I first let's hear from Matawan
The world of professional.
What's like any other hype
Performance Sports
Has its fair share of gamesmanship
From well X coughing Jag
Exaggerated sniffling
Daughter seen and heard it too
But
Cuz it smells it
Things escalated this month following allegations of an ill wind
Specifically one emanating from the behind
A Scottish darts player Gary The Flying Scotsman
In a post-match debrief
After being
Blown out in a match 10 to
Wesley
Sparky harms Anderson
Dutch rival
Accuse the two-time PDC world champion of releasing something a little stronger
That his signature smooth
Throw
All to gain the upper hand on.
Anderson stonetree deny the allegation instead turning the accusation back
On his wife
I swear on my children's lives
You said it was not
My fault he said
Even breezily relied on the classic he who smelt it
Delta defense
Anderson the winner went on to describe the smell as
Eggs
Rotten egg
But he insisted the stink hadn't come from him
I water expense came from it'll take awhile to
How to dispose
Tom's presumably supposing a mean stink eye
Told Dutch TV channel all cl7
It'll take me two nights
Delete the smell from my nose
A gaseous controversy
Between two players at the Grand Slam of darts
You're next
Story of the dark
Debacle
Everyone at the international darts
Championship
Was impressed by one of
The first American women
Doctor Shreveport
Agricultural
Is Professor from the University of Nebraska
Who was competing while wearing a classic
The Cornhuskers
Farmer's overalls
And plaid shirt
With farm girl
The British tabloids called her doctor
Pippy long.
The semi-final round started like any other
Dr. gertsen and her Challenger
Charles cook walked out
And shook hands
By the second round Charles cook was
Visibly sweating
And also whispering to
Each dark before you through the
His last
Sixth Rose mist
The target entirely
Things look good for the America
But then her behavior also became erratic
Stargazing annies
Dark
Turn them around
Touching the point with her thumb and then
Theme surprise
It's time that
Hayward shark
Finally the match
Was called on account of both
Contestants not being able
Finally the disorientated dr. guertin and minutes
She laid her hands and hallucinogenic
Frogg Toggs
She made in the lab in order to get an edge on her opponent
Sadly the antidote she created for
Herself didn't work
Xfinity home
In her last statement
Before being disqualified
An ordered off of Venus
He said
Sometimes dark go on the target
Sometimes it's hard to come to you
Sometimes I can
Can hear my own
Smell go Cornhuskers
In America
Tried to use frog or toad toxins
To defeat a republic but it backfired your last story of some Bullseye be asked
Tom Papa
B28
18 Grand
Slam of darts
Text was not without controversy
For the first time in
Storied history
The games with a focus
Animal rights protest
Who are contending
The Dart Association
Is promoting animal cruelty
By continuing
To use the term
Bullseye
A crowd of protesters heckled attendees are they entered the building
Holding up signs that read
Stick a dart in your own eye
What did the bull do to you
And Trump suck
A spokesman for safe
The save animals from exploitation organization
Set a time for the community to stop using the defenseless
Has its place
We went for the fox Hunters
We're eliminating the bullseye and we're coming after the flea circus neck
Jonathan haskel the head of the National Guard Association seemed genuinely
Perplexed by the protest
We've had complaints before but mainly about our drinking and our hygiene
This is a new one to me
Alright what event is happening at a major darts tournament
Was it
Bim adewunmi one competitor
Saying that the guy who beat him got a
Unfair advantage
From Brian Babylon how an American competitor tried to use toad box
To hallucinate
Her way to Victory
Or
From Tom Papa How are animal rights
Protesters
Is disrupted the event
And because they protested
The term Bullseye which of these is real story of Nevada
The big dark
Well I think I'm going to go with
Why why are you choosing
Farts are hilarious
Story and to bring you the real story what happened in
The darts tournament
We spoke to a Jenny
There was a really strong fellow
Fart in the air while he's inside with Larry so I can get my chainsaw
Steelers Sports
Reporter for the Washington Post
With great seriousness
About
The Dark Spark
You got it right you are correct
The voice on your voicemail
Bye-bye
Long before the fictional newscasters on
On Fox News
There is a fictional newscast
Esther Murphy Brown
The Incredibles Candice Bergen
Brought Murphy Brown to life for 11
7 seasons and she joined us on stage at Carnegie Hall
Back into
The show would never have been brought back
If
The election had turned out the way we want
Ribs if Hillary Clinton
President we would never have brought the show back
So what do you know Donald Trump created a job
That's right
Murphy Brown is not very happy with
With the current president
Oh well we got it really isn't the man
Is a gift
Everyday
It is a gift
It really is
I don't know how many
People who are fans of you now know this
But you were in fact
An extraordinary famous child
Because your father was one of the most famous Americans alive
Edgar Bergen
I don't think it was that
Famous but he was
I think it's
But your father again for those who don't know was the world's most famous and successful ventriloquy
They had a dummy Charlie McCarthy
And he was also a famous ventriloquist on radio
Yes
I've seen archival film of
Your father doing is acting just like people say I have a face for radio he was a ventriloquist 2 rating
Did you grow up
Really in there in your early years thinking that you were Charlie McCarthy
Sister
Oh yes
I was always
Call Charlie McCarthy
Sister
But but he was Far More Than A
My brother he was
We was like ahead of
Space in our house
And yellow room next to mine
And every now and then my father would bring him out and we would just kind of sits and
Once I mean a man wants we would have been the breakfast room he would put
Charlie on one knee and me on the other end
When he would
Squeeze my neck it meant that I should move my mouth
He would put you on a me and treat you as if
If you were another ventriloquist dummy
That's correct gif
In the 90s
Who starred in Murphy Brown
Which is much as any other sort of Sycamore TV show exemplified the nine
Is it would like The Dominic Show and of course
It became quite political when Dan Quayle famously went to
Not you but your
Character
Did he know
Did it was a fictional character never seen the show
But he was savvy
Lately his handlers
Had taken the line about Murphy out of his speech
And he
Reinserted at end
Did the speech
And that's all anybody talked about
I remember the entire 6 months
What's of the campaign
It was on
On the front page of every paper was in every
Political cartoon every editorial
It just didn't let up
Time for
You want in the original run
5 +
Yeah lead actress in a
In a comedy
Is that yourself
Is it true that
You said please don't nominate me anymore
He turned it down
I didn't say please don't I just didn't
Submit myself for nomination
I didn't
Like go in
Please don't know
No no no
Amy's home and then
Charlie McCarthy
RC with them
Where is terminal
Charlie
Yuan The Muppet Show
What was that like
Was that like
Trippy
Let's just say
It was a medium I was very comfortable
Well
Candice Bergen we can talk to you all day but all right
But we have invited you here to play a game we're calling
Murphy Brown Murphy's Law
Murphy's Law of course as I'm sure you know the law of the universe that anything that can go wrong will go wrong
We're going to ask you three questions about examples
Murphy's Law in effect
Did you get to write you want a prize one of my list
The voice of their choice on their voicemail
Billy was Candice Bergen playing
Dylan
New York
McDonald's
Corporate web page
To help with employees eat better
But they had to take it down after what
Inevitably
Happened a
The employees all gained an average of 20 pounds over 6 months
Beat It
Illustrated the concept of poor nutrition with a picture
Of a McDonald's meal
Or see it encourage people to go out and eat
At Burger King
I would say this because they gained
McDonald's gave its employees
Nutrition advice and they all followed it and they all ballooned like
Will duct isn't that what happen
Not in this case what happened was
They live the webpage they commissioned to illustrate good eating habits use the picture of the McDonald's
Cheeseburger in french fries
Kill the McDonald's corporation
It's not a problem here Bill Hillman was gored by a bull in Spain bad enough but
But it happened shortly after he did what
Hey was arrested for 27 different incidents
A cow tipping
B wrote a book called How to Survive the Bulls of Pamplona
Percy put on his new bright red cape
That's what happened you didn't read his own book alright last one if you get this right you win
A big game hunter in Zimbabwe was killed last year
When what happens if a zebra caught sight of a zebra print bikini briefs and thought he was alive on mail
Be one of his fellow Hunters mistook him for a quote balding lion
Horsey he shot an elephant and the Elephant
Fell on him
I guess the elephant fell on
At least one of them died happy
How did Candice Bergen do on AR quiz
Somewhere in the Smithsonian institution a wooden dummy just went
Damn
Candice Bergen stars as Murphy Brown on the show Murphy Brown back after a short Hiatus a tears
Thursday nights on CBS
She was just nominated for a Golden Globe for the park
When we come back
Two very tall man Conan O'Brien and NBA star Aaron Gordon
What is a
Is good at basketball
Find out which one in a minute from wait wait don't tell me
On NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor
The ridge wallet
Looking for a Father's Day gift
The ridge is the wallet rematch
Its innovative design music
Is premium materials like Taipei
Titanium and carbon fiber
And has over 30000
Send 5 Star reviews
The ridge wallet comes with a lifetime warranty
If you love it
And free returns
Find the perfect guy
Gift at ridge.com
NPR
And get 10% off
With code and
NPR
Summer movie series
Is here and pop culture happy hour has you
Forgot
Do the Blockbusters you know about Anna
Surprise bright spot
You might not we'll tell you what we are looking forward to what
Secretly dreading and what might
Sneak up on
Listen now answer
From NPR and WBEZ Chicago
I'm Bill Kurtis
Just at the Chase Bank Auditorium in
Chicago
Thank you so much we are taking the week off to me
We're getting outside and we're enjoying some
Some fresh air
Fresh Air View heard Terry gross's interview with Conan O'Brien
So much better than ours
Wow that is definitely true we still had a pretty good time with us back in January
Let's listen
I was a young writer turn alive
And I was the writer that was kind of known
To sort of perform my sketches
Three other writers and I perform them
For people when I get them laughing
I think Lorne Michaels notice that I left on a live I went onto the
The Simpsons
And I work there for a
About a year-and-a-half
2 years
When
Lorne Michaels was charged with
Who's the new guy is going to replace Letterman
End
He said you know I was just
Conan
He's got something
And
They looked into it and it turns out I really
We didn't have any
But I fooled them and here we are all these years later
It must have been crazy those first years
Because you know you weren't a stand-up you didn't
The following is
Performing you were thrown
You going to be in National Television
ResCare you're nervous
I was diluted
There's nothing like delusion
There's nothing like
If you think you can't do something convinced yourself that you can and I did have a few drinks and go do it
MOHAI
Mow how dare you speak to me directly right now
Bill would you ask Conan late night show hosts
When they get home a lot of time
Remember who was a guest earlier that day at the taping
How many shows did you ask him about that can you remember the guests
The show that night
Oh that's a relief
Yes. You know what's funny to most points
No
You do the show and it becomes
You're feeling the moment when you're doing it and I like in the hole
Experience and I'm actually not eat
Even kidding about this
I think everyone's
Probably
Familiarity
Famous toy the Etch-a-Sketch
Yesware
You turn the knobs
To create
Picture you
Create something and then you just shake it and it's gone and you start again
Everyday I come in
And I learn everything I can
That I need to know
For that show
And I learned it to the best that I can and I can
And tell you everything
Think about the cats
Play everything about the comedy
The minute it's over
I shake
Beatrice catch
And all of it's gone
And I go home and I
I don't know what
I've done 4000 hours
Of Broadcasting
9 of it quite good
Yeah what color is it talk to you if we have asked you to play a game where call
Team Coco
Meet hot
Coco
Your supporters fans are known as
Team Coco
What what do you know about actual Coco
The tasty hot chocolate pepper
I know everything
Really that's a bold statement
There's not a thing you can ask
About hot cocoa
But I do not know well I am interested in what's going to happen now because we have in fact prepared three questions for you
About hot
Coco
You want a price one of our listeners
Is the voice of their choice
On their voicemail
Are you ready to do this
I was born ready who is Conan O'Brien playing for Raleigh North Carolina
All right
Chris Kresser
You think it's just what kids drink instead of coffee but hot cocoa
Can change your life
As it did for whom a Bernie Madoff
Who after he was convicted and imprisoned for
Defraud quote
Corner to the prison Market
On Swiss Miss hot chocolate
Be Jeff Bezos who's first internet business was delivering steaming cups of hot chocolate
The people suffering through the Seattle winter
Orsi Eric McMillan who was inspired to invent
The kids ball pit
By looking at mini marshmallows
Floating in his
Hot chocolate
You're very
Peter
I want to say this one more time
It was actually a was Bernie Madoff
I'd like to
Noah apparently you Noah born trailer is born trailer and is apparently made of made very well for himself in
Prison
With the Swiss Miss
Hot chocolate
Yeah you know why I got that one wrong
Believe
In our penal reform system and I don't poop
I'm shocked that they would let Bernie Madoff do that so in a way I'm counting that answer is
I like your company
People really really love Coco
A lot so much of it at one time
People were doing what
Amex
Protein powder in
End of Coco
So it would be the only thing that ever happened
Be snorting lines of cocoa powder like Coke
Orsi's trying to have a trans
Infused into their body instead of blood
Answer is
Snorting
Cocaine
Will cocoa as cocaine
Sorry I slept there
Yeah I heart
Answer is be snorting cocoa
Snorting chocolate was championed by a Belgian
Chocolate who invented a little device that
Cocoa powder
I know that engineer and I work with him
Have you tried the snorting coke
I guess I have it's fantastic there's an incredible High
It lasts for about 20 minutes
And then you have to cough out the marshmallows but
The wonderful experience
When you wake up you're wearing German shorts I don't know why
All right let's go so you can get this right
For True chocolate lovers there's a pill created by a French scientist
Which Resort
$13 a bottle
Will do what
Hey make anything you eat including meat
Taste like
B make your farts
Smell like
4C it gives you chocolate dandruff
Instead of dry skin you shed chocolate
The answer is a
Your answer is a that makes anything you eat
Sweet like chocolate
Yes
Chocolate chocolate chocolate
It's B
I'm sorry
But yes
The idea is
It's a little pill and you take it
If you take it
Your farts smell like chocolate option
You know what I'm going to tell you something I didn't go for that
Because it's scatological I don't work blue I didn't realize this was
Is that kind of show
But I guess it's all about farts now
With you and I hope you're proud of yourself
How did Conan O'Brien
Do
On our show will you throw the score out because he's the only guest we've had when
Are they saying he says is right
Conan
Good King
Thank you
Who is the host of So Many shows including the new podcast Conan O'Brien needs a friend you can also
On Conan Without Borders on Netflix
And on Conan
TBS Conan O'Brien what a pleasure to finally have you on thank you so much
This message,
From NPR
Ridge wallet
Looking for a Father's Day gift
The ridge
If the wallet Ria Mae
Its innovative design used
Is premium materials like type
Titanium and carbon fiber
It has over 30000 5 star review
The ridge wallet comes with a lifetime warranty if you love
And free returns
Find the perfect
At ridge.com
And get 10% off
With code
NPR
And here's some more previously unaired material never been heard before
Jesse a wealthy New York real estate developer went through a bitter expensive divorce with his wife in 50 years
It let his ex-wife know he's better off with his new younger brother this week he put his wedding photos
Where
In the New York Times wedding section not big enough for him
Times Square
Close it's not far from there
But he put it on a
Put it on the side of a building
Lake Theater
Himself and his new wife
42 ft High each of them
Rebuilding loans in New York
Harry macklowe is now divorced and happily remarried and what better way to celebrate than rub it in everybody's face
What they found out that he's not legally allowed to rub things in other people's faces
Photos of himself and his bride
On the sides of one of his Park Avenue buildings
He said quote since I wasn't getting married during the summer in the Hamptons it wasn't able to hire an airplane with a banner to go up and down
Down the shore line
The Hamptons losses are game the pictures are big enough
So you can see the realization in the new mrs. Mac close eyes that this maybe wasn't a good idea
What sounds like he's definitely over is at
Support for NPR comes from Newman's Own founder
Working for no reason
The common good
By donating all profits
It's from Newman's Own food
Ducks to charitable organizations
That seek to make the world
A better place
More information
Is available
Newman's Own Foundation. Org
We have time for one more segments as we take the week off to play outside so let's hear from someone who spends most of his time playing inside
Orlando Magic star Aaron Gordon
Join this on stage
When we went down to Orlando in November
Peter Looks So Thai
Tiny neck
Converse of the like the basketball stuff
How is it that someone
The size of the
The Statue of Liberty
Is a small forward
I would like to think of myself as a
The powerful small forward of a mixture of
A couple of
Yeah yeah
I was kind of like a lot of
Maybe a hyphen
Is the power forward more of a ball hog
It sounds like a small forward as nice
When it comes to rebounding yes
Ball hog
It says you like to be
Apparently your father play
San Diego State
And I
Hey brother plays pro ball
He played pro ball over
Juventus
He plays in them
Who played at
Harvard
To the Harbormaster
Fire in aqua so I imagine your friendly games are out
Hayward
Gruesome
Forest View trash talk
Alright tell me something
It's kind of like the
Saying I'm the younger
Right so
Just by Nature on the most annoying
Yeah
I mean just
Do you like it leave your NBA contract out
The table
Oh some money fell out of my pocket
For your enthusiasm for the slam dunk
Yes yes
You did you did a slam dunk and what you vaulted
On top of and then over
The mascot
And you just you just going to stand there and I'm going to jump up
Put my hands on your head and go over you and
You're going to hold up the ball and
The mascot was like
Is actually
It is really funny
Because
What stuff the Magic Dragon
He's a great mascot mascot
Just like green dragon he has he's a
Stars on the top of
Who is head
And
When I was practice
Who sang I couldn't get the grip of
The ball right
Songs like
Stuff
Buddy you might need to take the Stars off your head
And he's really going to take one for the team music player
We did it and I got the dunk
The sadness
Friends Day
Will Aaron Gordon we have invited you here
Play a game we're calling
Play for the Orlando Magic
Real magic
Magic shows
React to three questions about great magicians answer
Two two of them correctly and you will win our prize one of our listeners the voice of their choice
Bill who is Aaron playing
Tampa Florida
Okay portable
One of the great magicians of the late 19th century was
Harry
Color
How did Keller learn to do his greatest trick
The levitating woman was it a
If he was a practicing
Buddhist wheel
Enlightenment
Was given control over gravity
Be he tired of the woman to a thousand trained fleas who
The flu or upward
4C he walked up on stage while another magician was doing
The Trek ran around back to
To see what was done
And then ran away
I'm going to go with the latter
Pretty daring how you get to be a legend of magic
Alright second as well another great Magician of that Golden Era of magic was
Was Carter the Great
And one of his
Famous tricks
Was which of these
The magical divorce
A trick in which he made his own wife this
Sapir
Be the disappearing theater
How much the entire audio
And found itself
Suddenly vacant lot sitting on their butts
4C the vaguely disquieting meal
In which Carter age
An ear of corn
Raw
I think I'm going to go with B
It would be the disappearing theater all the sudden everybody was out there sitting in there about 2.
That's the one that's the one
Skip it
I'm sadly he missed his shot now I'm afraid
It was actually the magical divorce
He made his wife disappear
His wife eventually
Decided that wasn't funny
Check to the Phantom bride
Did you get this right you win
Okay
To use their skills in real life such as
In which of these
Doug Henry used to skip out on dinner checks by making himself
Disappear during Desert
Angela
3 years has made himself look
Like he's lost
By constantly surrounding myself with trick mirrors
4C David Copperfield
Disappear while he was being mugged
I'm going to go with Copper Fit
David Copperfield
Performing some guy came up tried to mug him and you made it
Watch wallet
How did Aaron do it
Graduation
That's it for our little break from the news we back next week refreshed and ready to go
Wait wait don't tell me the production of NPR WBEZ Chicago and association with urgent haircut Productions Doug Berman
Overlord house managers Tyler green
Assisted by Simon Tran and married to Olean
Our interns are Alex McCone and Rachel Club
Iwebtv Elizabeth
BJ leiderman composer theme our program is produced by Jennifer Mills miles dorenbos
Lillian King
Are Spirit Animals Peter Quinn technical to Hawaii
Public address announcer that's Paul Friedman
Are master of operation
Does Colin Miller a production coordinator is Robert Newhouse our senior producer
Is Ian chill out an executive producer wait wait don't
Is Mike Danforth thanks to Bill Kurtis
To all the panelists you heard all of us another contestant it all our special guests
And we're bosses for letting us take a week off on Peter Sagal we will see you next week
This is NPR