Support for wait wait don't tell me
And the following message come from rocket mortgage by Quicken Loans
With award-winning service throughout the home buying process
A rocket mortgage.com
Slash weight
Equal Housing
Licensing office
50 states
Nmls
Consumer access
That's a bad word
Number 3030
Wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
It's all right
Motus
Your Saved by the Bell
Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown Chicago Peter
Everybody
Later on
The first Orchestra conductor we've ever had on our show the legendary Marin alsop
I'm going to ask her how she can get a bunch of emotional
Fragile ego maniacs
To do what they're told just by waving
In her arms
Because frankly that's never work
Search for me
The first one here your soul
Give us a call
The number is 18881
That's 180-889-2489
Let's welcome our first listen
Contestant High
You are on wait wait don't tell me
Chicago
Chicago Chicago
But you're not far are you far from us right now where are you
I'm in the summer house
Oh okay
The restaurant
Are you come on down
To the show Travis let me introduce you to our panel this week
First up at the comedian performing with CD Robbins
September 5th
To the 7th
At the Arlington Drafthouse
House in Arlington Virginia
I'm going to hope that was a dog of some kind and not coming back
Alright we'll try that again
What is going on
Be quiet but then these cars are driving by
Oh my God
Thrift Shop
It's a comedian performing with Cindy Robbins
What's the temperature
To the 7th
At the Arlington Drafthouse in
The Virginian
It pita bread
Netty contributor to CBS Sunday Morning
Facebook
Bailey Hey Kevin
To the podcast nobody listens
Dover to Travis as I'm sure you enter
Dissipated you're going to play who is Bill this time Bill Kurtis
From the week's news if you can correctly identify or explain two
You still have them
You'll win our prize
Any voice from our show you choose in your voicemail
Ready to go
I ready
All right
Here is your
That is
Is outside my purview
That was the answer that somebody gave all about a hundred times on Wednesday
Done with every question he was asked
Who was it
So
You know that moment at the beginning of
Willy Wonka
The factory when Gene Wilder comes out in
Wiki Old Man and everybody is
Appointed and sad
Somersault
Everybody
Cheers
Well imagine that
But instead of the summer so he just kind of daughters around for 8 hours
Was Wednesday
Former special counsel Robert Mueller appeared before a two house committees
With the energy and enthusiasm
Have a man facing his annual prostate exam
Which might explain why he answered certain point
Did questions by just turning his head and
And coughing
Everybody said it was boring but I was kind of breathless
Because I was
Know something is going to happen
You didn't want to miss the one moment and yet nothing did I was so disappointed
How many Democrats and liberals
Because liberals had been building him up for
For two years
As this
Clint Eastwood
Going to come in and
Kick-Ass
And take names
And in the end he was just like
Clint Eastwood
Who right now is 89 years old
Define I am the movie
9 success
The president in the movie Clint Eastwood says I don't want to do that I'm not going to go in there but then he goes in there
There was none of that
And instead of Clint Eastwood we got like
Sam the eagle
From The Muppets
Or maybe you know he also kill termites
Give me of those what are those
The Easter Island
1 heads what are they called
Biggest drones
Moa
Samoa
Reported
It was a perfectly nice
It was an ice age
King relative
Alright Travis here's your next quote
I will disprove the doubters
The Doomsday
And the Gloom says that was somebody taking office as the new British prime minister
Who is enemy evolve Gloom
Boris Johnson
Johnson or
As or Bojo is we hope everybody starts calling
Imagine what it would be like
To have your formally powerful and
Sirius country
Taken over by inning
Incompetent womanizer with terrible
Bars to do isn't it well
Boris Johnson
Became prime minister
Look
How far
The Empire has fallen they are so broken the good news is they're ripe
Decolonize
Time for payback India
What has happened where
People who were clowns are now in charge of everything
And I wish they were actual clown
Because those people at least have timing
Is is most famous at least here in the US
For being at the mayor of London during the 2012 Olympics during which
He tried to do a zip line stunts
Promoted
And famously got
Stuck
Dangling from a rope
Remember this 50 feet above the ground
Maybe that's why he was
Finally elected
The handle brexit
He knows what it's like
To be just
Stuck there not being able to
Get out
Looking like an idiot
Interesting
Bloke but he struck me
And maybe this
Just cuz I'm reading the Harry Potter series
The first time
With my children
Super Slither IO
Tries to throw you off with
With this Hufflepuff hair
I'm just going to say this and you may not get this yet
They will
He's not so much Slytherin as he's Peter Pettigrew
Wow
Peter down the nerd hold on transforming back from a rat
Halfway all right
Your last quote is from the governor of
Puerto Rico
I have not resigned
That was an official statement made just one day before he did what
Governor Ricardo rossello Puerto Rico survive this Mass
The financial crisis
Terrible hurricane but the one thing
He could not survive with his own
Text
In the leaked messages the governor mock
What is enemies in
Disaster victims
People of the disabled
Which is all bad
But then he went after Puerto Rican
Icon Ricky Martin
And that will not stand
Did he really really did and it in the end
As you probably saw tens of thousands of people
Took to the streets
Pics of San Juan
To demand disaster
Lead
By Ricky Martin
Yeah yeah yeah
This is it really is
Sarika
Defend himself rosello said he
He was just blowing off steam in the pek
Text that were leaked
Shouldn't be taken seriously
Which is what all of us would say if
If the terrible terrible thing
Can we email our friends ever got out
Oh my Lord the protest
Sumas in the streets were like March
Catching ball still erasing all their email from there
How would you guys fair if all the private message
Did you accept your
Got outfit
I would never be allowed to be governor of Puerto Rico again
I'd be even more unemployed
Only good part
The Scandal has shown
That Puerto Rico is so full of corruption
Shouldn't racism and misogyny
The maybe now President Trump will recognize it
It is part of the United States
Puerto Rico
Congratulations Travis
We want to remind everybody they can join his most weeks right here at the Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown
Chicago Illinois for tickets
And more information.
Stroller Webster 4/2 wbez.org or you can find a look at our website wait wait
. NPR
Rhino panel it is time for you to answer
Some questions about this week
Petey the owners of a giant replica of Noah's Ark in
Kentucky have filed a lawsuit against
For failing to cover damage caused
To the ark
By what
Water
Exactly right
Even worse
It was rain
The 510
Footlong replica Ark
Is part of Kentucky's
Noah's Ark
Encounter theme park
What are the perfect vacation getaway for families
Who find Knott's Berry Farm to be a little too
Gracie the owner say they were in
Inspire to build a replica when God's voice told
Come to gather up
Two of every animal
And charge them $75 each
Permission
The park opened in 2016 but was forced
Close for a few days right then when the ark and its surrounding area
Was damaged by and I quote
Slightly above-average
Rain
Apparently they skip the part of the Book of Genesis where God tells Noah to
Spring for the undercoating
Do you happen to know Peter what other
Experiences they offer
Noah's Ark Adventure I'd I have I can't say that I've been face I can't say that I've been
I do believe this is a creation
Primary creation
So doesn't have a two figures of a unicorn
On a nearby Hillside
You should have made it a water park
That's true
Coming up with a yellow Jersey
Wait wait don't tell me
From NPR
Support for NPR in the following netty
Message comes from
NPR wine club
Discover hand-selected wines from award-winning Vineyards around the world
Learn the stories behind each one and enjoy a unique bottles inspired by your favorite NPR shows
But without having to leave the house
The clubs welcome offer includes a bottle of the delightful all grey
Eggs considered Pinot Noir
If you're 21 years or older uncork the fun
NPR wine club.
It has already been uneventful summer in
Yeah between the 2020 debate
And the president's battle over immigration
There's a lot
And when there's news you need to know about the NPR politics podcast
Is there to tell you
Not to mention
So you can meet all of it
Ompl is going to drive me completely crazy
The NPR politics
Subscribe
From NPR
The WBEZ Chicago this is
Wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz I'm Bill Kurtis
We're playing this week with ptdi bro
And Adam
At the Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown Chicago
Peter Sagan you so much right now
Feliciter game call 1aaa wait wait
Two-player game in the
How you are
Hey this is John Daly from New Brunswick New Jersey New Brunswick New Jersey
I'm from New Jersey what are you do there
I'm a chemical engineer working at L'Oreal
L'Oreal
The skincare products company
That would be a
I'm going to ask you a
And I and I want you to tell me the truth
I see ads
Especially for
Skin care
And I usually maggie's
Amazingly elaborate about
How this amazing product
Is anti-aging and is going to make you look like this supermodel
Supermodel
Is going to solve all your problems
Are any of those claims
True
I mean only only if you buy L'Oreal products
Especially Sarah
Absolutely
Glad to know we heard it from the side
Well
Welcome to our show John you're going to play the game but you must try to tell truth from fiction
Bill what is John Scott
I'm just here for the Chaffee
There's so much
Casual fans don't know about the
The Tour de France
For example did you know
Tour de France is France
Tour of
But not all of the
Stars of that bike race are on the bike
Our panelists are going to tell you about it
Unsung hero somebody who works in the back row
Of that great race
Pick the real one
Emanuel Wynne AR price
The waiter of your choice on your voice
Ready to play
Yes sir
From Faith sale
Old black-and-white photos of Tour de France Riders show them
Smoking cigarettes
On their bikes
Darlene Kelly
Cheeks inhaling the smoke they believed open the lungs
It was only 2002 when the tour officially outlawed cigarettes within a hundred meters of the root
But do you think this has
Stopped toulemonde from smoking oh no no my friend
This is France
Enter
GTA
His job his metal
Is official cigarette
Extinguisher of the Tour de France
He's a stone-cold man in a beret
Stocks the crowd looking for
For smokers
When he sees a lit cigarette
Casually places his thumb and index finger in his mouth
Covers them with
Spit
And douses the burning stick with a Sizzle as he
Swans by
Earning him the nickname
Mesilla
Mister Magic
And you can't miss him
To travel with that or he rides his 1964
Joe motor scooter a contraption that
So terrific
Quickly loud
It warned smokers he's coming and therefore leaves a wake of hastily cast off cigarettes
Didier celebrates his work every night
With a nice Pernod
Single gas wall
Problem
He says
Nothing holding with a little smoke as long as it's away from zika
The official cigarette extinguisher of the Moto you're next
Story of a tour helper comes
From Adam
Felber
The cycling world was stunned last week by the Revelation that
The devil Tour de France
Is Rick
Know the winner is
Predetermined but now we've learned that the loser
Is
In fact for the past 10 years
Tour officials paid an hour
Actor to come in last
As a means of encouraging
Lower razor to maybe thinking of giving up
Now if this sounds like evidence of an overweening everyone gets a trophy Nanny think culture run amok let me assure
Sure you
Exactly what this is
It's a good job and actor Leon Christ who is just exposes this year
8 loser
You don't have to try this hard you can have a pint or two
How do you make friends with a lot of wonderful funny people whose only sin is being helpless wankers when it come
Comes to cycling
But now that the Jig Is up Christ knows that the gig is over and we can all rest assured that next year's last place finisher
Will be a real loser
For his part Grace expects he'll return to acting and maybe someday the cycling quotes
Now that I'm coming
It'd be fun to see if I can improve on that or
Baby just doing what I did this year but for free and with more training and
No drink
In fact nevermind
Leon draisaitl designated loser of the Tour de France always comes in last July
A story of the wind beneath
The Tour de France has wings
News comes from pita bread
One of the great traditions of the Tour de France is fans rioting
Encouraging messages for cyclist
Ghost on the road
Stuff like golang
Miguel
You don't even need those training wheels from
How many fans write bad burn
Profane pictures
Which the tour doesn't want showing up on the TV
Broadcast
It's hard enough to keep people watching ever since
Play Crackdown
On drugs and all the cyclist walking their bikes up there
So the tour has higher to Man Who Sold job is
Describe the course every day in
Repaint over those dirty mess
They're called officially
Erasers
People draw genitals
I have no idea why
Because it's fun
Multi the erasers just paint over the image
But they also let their artistic side show
According to the Wall Street Journal one of the erasers
Renderings of the male anatomy into butterflies or owl
By the way
Now you know the backstory of everyone you meet
Who has the butter
All right
Topolino in France
He's helped along
Buy one of these three p
People is it from
Faith the official cigarette extinguisher guy who
Rides on the Corson
Take the cigarettes out of the mouth
Are the people who might dare to smoke them near the Riders
From Adam felber Leon Grice the man whose job it is to ride and come in last so nobody else has
Or from PD
The stories of the guy who goal on the course and erase the obscene messages that people might have left
For the writers they don't appear on TV
Which of these are the real story
Of the Tour de France is Little Helper
I really wish with all them but I'm going to go with number 3
Alright then
To bring the real answer you somebody who knows a lot about
The Tour de France
The most inappropriate graffiti
You see out on the road to the Tour de France's you spell genitalia wouldn't be a favorite
Robinson he is the European sports reporter for the Wall Street Journal
Who wrote about the official Tour de France erasers and what they have to do congratulations you got it right
You are being honest and you have one arm
Has the voice of anyone you might
Congratulations
Thank you so much thank you
And now the game will be asked
Pioneers to go discover something completely uninteresting it's still not my job
Marin alsop discovered her passion for music
In an early age
Juilliard wouldn't admit her to their conducting program
So she just started her own damn Arkestra Nextdoor presumably
To drown them out
2000 music director of the Baltimore Symphony and the South Paulo State Symphony we are delighted to have her with us Marin
Stop welcome to wait wait don't tell me
Thank you
Musical Geniuses like yourself were you like a musical
Prodigy did you have to be forced
Rihanna where did you love
I was born with a job my parents were
Professional musicians wear
My dad was a violinist and my mom a cellist and so
They needed a Pianist
And so they said all let's make one
So I was born
With a job and
Really hated the piano
I hated it I retired when I was sick
From Gallup
That was because you didn't like the piano or because you just resented your parents
This is why you were
How much time do we have
You know for every kid there is
Is there is a right instrument playing the violin
It was very close because they said
They said you want to go to summer camp
You know I'm so I already had an archetypal image of summer camp you know was sailing and
And horseback riding somehow horse
Just got in there and I forgot to tell you you might have to
How to play the violin
And
Is this campus called Meadow Mountain
Finally called the concentration camp
App for violin
So that's why when you got there they just put you in your little salad
So you're going to price
What is from
Until 1 everyday 5 hours
Luckily I was 7 I had no real sense of
What time
7 years old and they made you practice your violin 5 hours a day and that was supposedly for pleasure
Camp right I mean there's so many things to say
Swallow
The only sport we are allowed to do
Ping pong
I am
Awesome at ping putter loft
Is it true we read that you decided at some point you wanted to be reckoned
Well what happened was it after
After practicing for 5 hours from now
I played in the orchestra which I loved it
They got some complaints
Is that somebody was trying to lead the whole Arkansas
Picture from the back of the second violin
And so
Where is the orchestra
From the second vial
I think the problem was I was having a really good
Good time was really cute back there and I was having fun
And you know I was
Moving and everybody else was
Do you know already like
Stonehenge and I was busy
And then luckily my dad took me to a concert and I
I saw the conductor he came out and he started talking to me I talk into the audience talking to me
And you know he was really excited and then he started jumping around and conducting and I thought
Nobody's yelling at this guy I could do that
He is doing the yelling
Exactly
And he was sweating and spitting in
In-N-Out in that was Leonard
Oh wow
And I should say so much famous
Became of I I guess
Student ism
His protege
And I did luckily
Yeah that was a
Highlight of my
How does one become a protege of a conductor like I'm thinking
Karate Kid
You know like and is there a lot of work with the
Switch of the arm
There's a lot of that yes
Really under the question is
Every kid
Jugos
Sia concert
Thinks he or she can be a conductor
Write the actual the actual movement that you make
Forgive me
Looks
So what is it
That goes in
Conducting
Oh my God that
These questions you said they're going to be
Listen you know it's true it is a lot of it I think about who we are as
Human beings
That creates a different sound
And and elicits a different response
It's all about body language
Not only that
How to see you work
Something I noticed most people can't see this
The conductor has their back
The audience
But because music is playing
Can I shout instruct
You must indicate
What you'd like to meet
Facial expression
You have to have a wide range
Dirty looks
Encourage
Looks or you're not really going to play it that way are you
Also you know you have to anticipate
Sometimes people are about to
To play at the wrong moment you know you have
Anticipate
Preventive conducting I call it you know
Don't do that
You have a good conductor
But are you a super
We have heard I've seen
At musical conducting but what other kind of conducting
Conducting a lie
Electricity
We're going to ask you three questions about that other kind of conducting
Did you get to write you would apprise for one of my listeners the voice of anyone they might like
On their voicemail
Bill who is Marin alsop playing
Lucinda Watson of Chattanooga Tennessee
Who was this month
The winter of our smarts
Quiz
You could be a winner to just ask you
Smart speaker
Do open the wait wait quiz
Alright ready to do this
Here we go
Lightning rods were all the rage after they were invented in the late 18th century so much so that they
Turned up where
A attached
Two race horses
Just hoping they give them an ex
The Kik
Beyond cannonballs in the hope that it would attract lightning onto someone's enemies
Orsi
On top of ladies hats
Because they looked
Cool
Oh
Pixie
We got that horse back
Do you have the
Or ladies hats
Because they looked so
Yeah but that would hurt wouldn't it the ladies that that could be
That could be really dangerous
Well ladies inordinate sacrifice
Sephora fashion
We're going with the hat
Yeah okay we're going with the hat
It's amazing by the way how you got them off of work
Our next question Electric
Fences
Are excellent conduct
Of course
But they're not just
Pepper Farm someone
Once seriously suggest
Using an electrified fence
For which of these uses
This is a surrounding a mixed martial arts Fighters at the first
UFC bout
Beekeeping the political press from harassing senator
Foreseeing managing the line
It gets quite extraordinary at Franklin's Barbecue in Austin
Austin Texas
Okay I'm going to go with the barbecue because the electric in the barbecue it sounds kind of
No it wasn't the barbecue it was mixed martial arts but I just want to say that I'm glad
That you mention the barbecue cuz the only reason I put it in here was that they would hear it and send us some barbecue
Appreciate the help
Get this last one right you win
Your last question is about superconductors these are the remarkable materials that conduct electricity with
Industry in science
In 2010 a group of Japanese scientists made an incredible discovery
About superconductor
How did it happen
Was it a one of them was picking out ham at the grocery store freezer sex
Noticed it was colder than the frozen chicken
That led to the discovery that
Hammock
An excellent superconductor
Be an incompetent lab assistant made contact with two electrical leads and
The current pass through his body
Deficiency without harming it
So he now works as a
A professional superconductor
Dunked a superconductor in booze and discovered that red wine increase its conductivity 62%
All right we're going with see I'm trusting them
And I got amazing results red wine
Increases conductivity of the substance they were using 60
80%
Bill how did Marin alsop do
She's a winner in our body
Music director of the Baltimore Symphony Orchestra
Can see her at this summer at the Ravinia Music Festival
Weather Chicago
Dayton Moore at Marin alsop. Com
In just a minute
Listener lyrics
Wait wait wait wait don't tell me
From NPR
Support for wait wait don't tell me in the following
Message comes from rocket mortgage by Quicken Loans
Imagine how it feels to have an award-winning team of mortgage
Make the home buying process
Smoother for you
The history of industry-leading online lending technology
Rocket mortgage is
Changing the game
Visit rocket
Mortgage.com weight
Equal Housing lender licensed in all 50 states
NMLS consumer access.org number 3030
Rocket mortgage
My Quicken Loans
Push button
Get mortgage
Bitcoin music
Huge amount of Electra
Need to power to camp
And that is created some very unique money making offer
Cities in different parts of
Is also causing some governments
Listen
Subscribe to the
Indicator from NPR
From NPR
WBEZ Chicago this is wait wait don't tell me the NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Kurtis
We're playing this week with Petey Pablo
Faith salie
Saint Adam
And he'll get at your house that Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown Chicago
If you're lost and you look
You will find Ville
Rhyme
After rhyme
Play give us a call at 1 AAA wait wait that's 1889 to 48924 right now panel somewhere questions
Snooze
This week a reporter Spencer
4 days until this resource is getting to the bottom of a mystery that
Protracted fever
Media attention
From across the country
How a mysterious
What
Ended up
Is this an animal
It is not in there
Although sometimes it comes animal style
An in-and-out
Burger
A pristine
Uneaten
Perfectly wrapped in and out burger was found in the middle
Street in Queens on Monday
That is
Thousands of miles away
From the nearest
In-N-Out
Burger restaurant
It's global warming its migration
New York found a strange An Inconvenient way to pack
Was Tara portal to a parallel
Superior dimension image in and out was available every
And how did survive worth
3 minutes without being eaten
That's a pretty good burger
Who cares about street meat
What did we discover well in NYPD put out an
Amber
Girl alert
Anyway
Investigative reporters
4 days on the problem
And she was able to track down
The sixteen-year-old
Queensryche
Who had picked up
3 In and Out Burgers on a trip to San Diego people love them so much they fly to California they get burgers to bring him home
Somehow she kept them in pristine condition
The whole way back didn't eat them but what you got home
She was rushing to catch a bus the bag burst open and one of them felt
To the ground
Did a burglar
Steal it
The Hamburglar know what happened
Like a lot of
People or things that come to the Arkansas to could finally be a star so it ran away
And will be appearing with Andy Cohen
Next Monday night on watch what we found on the street live
Adam online dating may actually now become a thing of the past
Because there's a new kind of matchmaking where you try to get a date
I simply asking your friends
Do what for you
Find you a date
Yes
But using what
Technique
On their dating
It's like putting your profile like I'm by the way I have a friend
No not at all
I'll give you a hint here on Slide
The three you can see that you know PowerPoint
Your friends to create a
PowerPoint slide deck all about you
That's great helping you move used to be the worst thing you could ask a friend to do
It's a new dating
Trying to give you the opportunity to say the sentence hey can you whip up a PowerPoint to help me get lucky
The event is called date my friend
Docker PPT
Oh the office rounds know that
And it gives your friends a chance to pitch in the other singles at this big presentation using PowerPoint
Wow it combines all the fun of a work meeting with the people who know all your worst
And if your friend's name is Ted
You can say thank
Thank you for coming to my TED Talk exactly
So
Okay
Don't do people
It is in the bed
Why did you you go to this event
Either you're a seller or buyer exactly like any other kind of business
Investment thing or
Sales pitch
You come in your buyer you sit down in the cellars come up and say that let me introduce you to my friend Ted
And they show you a PowerPoint
Including and this is a real one such
Such a
The positive points you know it's
It'll be a little bullet point list
Starwipe
If you know
Has in unit washer and dryer
Are there conflict
The two you want to feel like you're getting the whole
Package
That's not helping with about
Yeah I mean
What is a commercial
How can I move in
Opportunity
I need some tender loving care
Exactly
Coming up with lightning fill in the blank refers it's a game where you have to listen for the rhyme
If you'd like to plan are call and leave a message at 1 AAA wait wait
1889 to 48924
Or click the contact us link on our website wait wait. Npr.org
So you can find out about attending our weekly live shows right here at the Chase Bank Auditorium in
In Chicago
Are upcoming shows August
29th and 30th
At Wolf Trap outside of washing
September 12th at the New Jersey
The Performing Arts
Weather in Newark
New Jersey
Heidrun wait wait don't tell me
Hello hello
Who is this
This is Serena from Austin Tech
Texas
What are you doing here in Austin
I am an X-ray tech in the house
Hospital
You're an X-ray tech at a hospital
Okay I know you probably get
What is question of law
I apologize but I'm genuinely
What is the weirdest thing you found inside a human
I don't know.
Appropriate for public radio
Say more
Welcome
Serena
Of course complete the rhyme
Bill Kurtis
Is going to read for you 3 news with Adam emmerich
Text but it's not going to
Your job provide that last
Rephrase do that
2 * 8
After you when I pray
Price ready to play
I'm ready
Here we go here's your first limerick
Mike heard
Leaves along
Slimy Trail
I'm a farmer
But on a small scale
A cream from their slime
Turn back
What's the time
And that's why I
Nail yeah it's as if
Address of Oak milk
Gross enough there now milking snail
Do snails have nipples
We're talkin about
Snail mucus cream that are being used as cosmetics
People pay hundreds of dollars for this although for half the cost I will send you what just came up for my stomach
As I started to talk about this apparently snail slime as a moisturizing agent with many benefits collagen
Production
Heals acne scars and more people complimenting your wet
Sticky face
Someone just sneeze on you in the subway
Character next limerick
In their shells
They don't have beaks
Snorlax
But for gossip
They are
Powder
Kegs
With vibrations of sound lots of nose goes
What's around
There is Chatter amongst
All the
Change the nest it turns out cuz talk to each other they do this by vibrate
Getting their shells an incredible Discovery in an efficient way to
We're making
It is believed that these vibrations of egg to egg act as a warning call to thread as detector
And it's not safe to
To hatch
But also can trick the mama bird in
Taking her cell phone is going off
What creatures are in the wild donate eggs
Well apparently
I'm just tell me what the signs are tall.
Amanda Nagy
All scientists know is that they noticed that when I say I see y'all say
Makes a
Distinct
Distress call
They do warning call
All the eggs start vibrating
When is it there
Telling each other
Halo
Maybe it's also like that kind of
Unication halfway
Restore like do
This is not a good day to talk to Mom
But if I should say this only applies to
Wild fertile egg
Eggs in the nest
Don't worry about the eggs in the fridge
Talking about
To the second you closed
Here is your last look at
4mybaby I'm changer
And wiper
But it's false alerts
Sometimes when there's stink
It's less full than you
So I get text alerts
From
Diaper
Pampers
Has created a new line of electronics
PetSmart diapers
Which send data to your phone
Alerting you when the diaper is
Is dry
Using wefi
Exactly
That's a strong signal
Let you know I like how your baby doing it let you know if the diaper is
Dry wet
Very wet and you'd be better off putting her up for adoption
Think of it as a nappy app
That's cold
Your nose
Well
This is
And I speak to you as a fellow parent
Supposed to help you avoid the
We've all seen it
We've all done it
Pulling the diaper bag
Smelling it worse
Sticking your finger down there to find out
Even you wouldn't do that but the idea is like Italy
What is tell you it's like you know I see I don't have to do any of those gross things my phone tells me that my baby has just wet herself
Wherever she is I have no idea I'm staring at my phone
Bill
How did Serena do an AR quiz
Bring it up graduation Serena thank you so much
Support for NPR
Comes from Newman's Own Foundation
Working for nourish the common good by donating all profit
It's from Newman's Own
Food products
Charitable organization
To make the world a better place
More information
When is available
Well at Newman's Own Foundation. Org
Support for this podcast
And the following message come from the Walton
Thun Family Foundation
Where opportunity
Route information is available
At Walton Family Foundation
. org
Now it's time for a final game lightning fill in the blank each of our players when I have 60 Seconds
The answer is many fill in the blank
Directions to see if she can
Each correct answer net worth
So can you give us this
BT and Adam each have three faith has to oh my gosh
Alright face you are in third place Europe
First fill in the blank
On Wednesday the Department of Justice in
Announced it would not prosecute
Attorney General
Define
A congressional
Subpoena
On Monday the White House
Congressional negotiators
Agreed on a two-year blank deal
Budget
Chapter 5 months delay
Samsung announced the release of the first ever
Foldable
Right after being found injured in jail while awaiting a
Is trial the space billionaire
Blank was reportedly put
On suicide
Yes please in Australia
Made it the world's easiest drug busts
That's what a man driving with 140 million dollars worth
The drugs
Drove
N-tuple
Exactly right
On Monday India successfully launched the unmanned mission to the far side of the blank
Right according to a new study people without history
3 heart disease should not take
Prevent heart attack
Aspirin right after being arrested by local police on a minor charge of Duckman blank after being released
Children
No he sent the officers
Flowers
The flowers which arrived at the station shortly after the man was released came with a note that said quote and thanks for the good service definitely
Five star
Really how often do the police get that
But police did get the end of the note which said can't wait to do business with you all again very very soon
I think faith
If you're pretty well-built what do you think
14 more points Cutler's
Okay will you flip the coin and Adam has elected
Indigo nexo Adam film
On Wednesday a federal judge blocked
The White House's new policy blocking blank
Time Central
Asylum right on Sunday mass
Man attacked
Anti-government protesters at a train station
Chenin Blanc
Amsterdam Hong Kong
This week or officials reported that blank fired
Two short-range missiles in
Into the ocean North Korea right on Tuesday the Senate voted to indefinitely extended
Compensation fund
For the
Survivors of blank 911 after being re-released into theaters blank beat to become the highest-grossing
Film in his
That would be that Avengers
Movie
All the cakes you order for her two-year-old daughter didn't say happy birthday lizard but
Instead said the blank
Happy birthday lizard
No it said happy birthday
It loser
Mom is hoping to get her daughter Elizabeth the cake with her nickname lizard
But thanks for the rush conversation with the bakery she instead got a cake
Declaring happy birthday loser
Fortunately Elizabeth is only 2 and can't read
What a loser
It second place
It's all right
How many need to win this is for the game fill in the blank on Wednesday President Trump
The vetoed three resolutions that would have blocked his arms deal with black
Russia Saudi Arabia on Tuesday the Senate voted 92 8
Confirm Mark esper as the latest blank
By defense secretary this week the White House announced that the federal government would be resuming blank
After two decades
Capital
Very good a woman in Idaho is in trouble with police after calling 911
Ask the police to stop chasing her during a high-speed
Pursuit according according to their Ministry of Health over 19 people died in blank
Hank from drinking tainted alcohol
Costa Rica following a huge different prophets automaker blank said it will cut 12000 jobs
Yes very good police in the UK investigating a number of suspicious symbols drawn on sidewalk
In a small town have determined that they were blank
No they determined
Buy a little boy drawings
Drawings appeared mysteriously all over the town of wait for it
Ramsbottom
Weather for concerned with this some sort of weird mystical markings of some cult
The Mystery of the Unabomber was solved
What a woman posted on Facebook
My son
Was given talking school today in the way home he took the drawing bums every 20 yards
Sorry
He says in the ballgame
4 more
And a total of
What's the weather
Robert Mueller is finally done with his special counsel probe what we do with the rest
Office summer vacation
Special thanks
Stock and Ledger restaurant here in downtown
Chicago 4
Feeding us wait wait don't tell me
Is rectiv NPR WBEZ Chicago and association with urgent haircut Productions.
Benevolent overlord
Mxr public address announcer is Paul
Friedman or house manager
Is Tyler Green Assisted by Simon Tran
Are interdependent of Edie and Liza Francis rweb Peru is best
BJ leiderman composed and produced by Jennifer Mills miles during boss
And Lillian King this week
The rhombus
MK Villa
Is the spot where we used to mention
Your Gwen
But we don't anymore
Technical director is Colin Miller a production coordinator
Executive producer
Wait wait don't tell me is my
Robert Mueller
Peter Gabriel
He's probably going to find someone with no phone service so people
Can't call it
He's going sailing he's going to buy a yacht and name it
Purview
So he can actually say I can get into that that's my purview
Adam
G4S bags
The Cool Ranch Doritos
Welcome to Walmart
When will I see you about it on way
Wait wait don't tell me
Netflix
Is NPR