Support for this podcast
And the following message come from Tito's Handmade Vodka
Do you know how many
Flavors Tito's Handmade Vodka makes
The answer is
Suggest one
Vodka flavored vodka
80 proof
Tito's Handmade Vodka
Fifth generation Incorporated
Distilled and bottled in Austin Texas
From NPR and WBEZ Chicago
Oh this is
Does wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
Forget about
LeBron
You've got trouble
I'm so sad
In Cuyahoga Valley National Park
Peter's everybody
It is wonderful to be here at Blossom a music venue founded back in 90
68 by the Beloved Mayim Bialik sitcom for which it is named
Later on we're going to be talking to Piper Kerman the author of Orange Is the New Black was now
Teaching writing in prison
I'm here in Ohio
But first the New York Times published an amazing expose this way
We close to a heart
With a shocking conclusion we have reach
Quote
Peak
Podcast
That's right
Single person in America
Now
Has a podcast
So from here on podcast
Will slowly decline
Until there are none left
And people will stop committing unsolved murders out of a lack of inch
Didn't want to bother starting a podcast but still want to hear your voice on one give us
Call
The number is 1 AAA wait wait
That's 18892
Now that's welcome my first listener.
Contested how you run wait wait don't tell me
Hey this is David David where you calling from
Little Falls
Minnesota Little Falls Minnesota now I lived in Minnesota but he never came across Little Falls
Smack dab in the hearts of Minnesota right in the middle
What do you do there in the middle of
My wife and I want to bite you
Will you do
Thought that if I truly wanted to give up everything else
Happy happy
I would want to buy
Am I right
In this assumption
I would be right now
David let me introduce your panel this week first up a comedian
You can listen to on the new
Smirnoff vodka.
It's Alonzo bodden
Hello David
Aliens of extraordinary ability is out now on Audible
It's Maeve Higgins
And finally the host of them obituaries podcast his MO bituary is a live show will be at the house of Independents in Asbury
New Jersey on August 21st and Stage 1
Fairfield
42nd
It's Mo Rocca
David welcome to the show
Three quotations from this week's news
If you can correctly identify or explain two of them you will win our prize
Any voice from our show you my choosing
Voicemail you ready to fly
I am thrilled to playbill here we go
Your first quote is from the president of the United
Steaks
Those tweets are not
Race
He was talking about some tweets
He said earlier
That were totally what
Yeah totally racist
The country have been arguing for some years of the president
Is Ray sister just you know recently charged
Or races
Curious
Or merely you know
Racy
It all started when Trump told for congresswoman
To go back
To their countries
He was just testing it
If it worked he try it on Melania
Hey
You laugh
It's it's cheaper than what he had to do to the last two
Zoosk
This go back to your country saying was so
Unvarnished
That many news organization
Just threw up their hands and just called it racist
Even NPR
Which stands for know please don't say racist
NPR This is an organization that is so even-handed
It covers a kick To The Cross by talkin both to the crotch
In the foot
The thing is is that
Three of the women
We're born in the eye
Today they were I mean Ayanna Pressley
Wuxi represents Massachusetts but she was actually
Born in Cincinnati and I realized
This Crowd
Cinco Baptist
Cincinnati is like going back to a hellhole
Different Cleveland
Rallies on Wednesday night
This whole thing went
Toronto Marlies
Herb accent
Send her back
That was really ugly.
The fact is
You got to get the president this
He's really good at coming up with chants
Like lock her up
Send her back
Democrats
Keep trying it it doesn't work with their program
Free college tuition but only a public university
Qualifying applicants with a limit of family income and 220
Alright your next quote is from NBA star DeMar DeRozan reacting to
Photo of himself
But somebody posted using some
Something called face
Whoever started this Atman
Yo message
People's life
The Rosen was upset that face app made him
Like it does to everybody who you
Is it look
What
They look that's exactly right they look old it's 20 years
Took over the Internet this week and gives you a picture of what you would look like
When you are 30 years old
The images were all a
Springerle realistic
They could replace
The previous technology
For finding out
Look like old
Looking at you
Your parents
What does it mean if you run the photo through the app
And you just get back up
Picture of a coffin
What I like your cuz I want to marry a guy who's like 30 years older than me.
So I'm going to upload all my faceapp photos onto my dating profile so he'll be like oh nice old lady just like me
Because that's an old guys like
I don't know how to do it
But here's the thing
And you might have heard this too
It turns out the app was made by
Russian programmer
The Democrats led by Chuck Schumer advise people to delete the app immediately and make sense
The Dems need
To stop it
The Russians use that old face technology and Joe Biden
It'll just be a picture of a handful of dust
And sadly they already got to Bernie
Your last quote
Is about a big shake-up
Buy movies
Who cares if it's a woman
As long as she still drinks martinis
Kills bad guys
And have sex
With lots of
Did lots of women
Jesse McLaren
The news that what movie icon will be played by a woman
Nginx
Film
James Bond David a woman will be the next
James Bond or technically agents oo7 but that doesn't matter because
Cuz no one cares less
About distinctions like that
When fans of popular movie franchise
Also easy going
According to reports British actress
Lashana Lynch
Kobe playing agents oo7
British MI6
The first woman ever to do so
James Bonzo will still be around in the film
Please play bye
Daniel Craig again
But now he's retired
We all know what happened to Bon
Once he got me tood
You know that right you were calling this woman pussy
Seagull or her name is Deborah
I usually bond to send to go see a manicure and now we had to go ch
HR
Uncle figure what was unclear
We hope
That a female oo7 means there will be Bond boys
Just as ridiculously objectified
As all the Bond girls have been so it's like seven and seven
Your mission is to link up with an informant
The 22 year old Surfer named
Octo dong
You talk about bees
Bands I mean the ones
Imagine
Who lost their mind
Over a black Little Mermaid
Yeah I know
When they get
Oo7
It's a black woman they probably
Who just died in their base
It was just too much and they just killed over
Bill how did David doing our quiz David nailed it all free
Congratulations David thank you so much for playing
Rhino panel is time for you to answer some questions about this
News
May this week the House of Representatives ordered an investigation
Discovery Institute
Pentagon
Really tried
To make what
Weapon
I can tell you first of all with pentagon
That's very good man
Is it something to do with the weather
Can you give me a clue.
I love the smell of a Lyme disease
In the morning it smells like
Victory
It's the creature that you get lice
Slug thing
What sound does a clock
Hexagon program thank you to the panels for that
DirecTV now
Is ordered an investigation into whether this happened
There's evidence
To suggest that the
The Department of Defense
May have experimented with
Military weapon
Because the wars of the
The future will not be one
Wood bullets
Will be won by
Convincing the enemy
Me to run through
The tall grass
With shorts on
It really makes me
It just makes me wonder how much
Free time
Can military
Investigators have that you would actually listen
This week we need a report we need to
Didn't know if they were invest
Instigating using
Ticks
Back in the
60s
I would sit at my computer and play games and just make it up yeah
But when they were trying to get gastrodin they do all stars
Yeah I think they sent
Fisher something like like
Progressive
They said Sheba
Aggressive
Distance to Cuba
Exactly
Made
What you just started another investigation
Coming up
Or wait wait don't tell me
From NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor SimpliSafe Home Security
SimpliSafe believes fear has no place
In a place like home
That's why they made a completely wireless home security system
They can be self-installed and under
An hour
Their sensors are built to protect every point of access
To your home
Plus SimpliSafe has no long-term contract
More than 3 million people of already Protected Their home
What SimpliSafe
Get free shipping and a 60-day money-back guarantee
SimpliSafe
Dot-com
Slash weight
We spend millions of hours and billions of dollars on video games
Put in console still compete with
The next level of streaming and subscriber services
I'm Joshua Johnson
Subscribe to 1A on NPR as we consider the
The future of Gaming
Play NPR WBEZ Chicago
The NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Kurtis we are playing this week with Mo Rocca
Maeve Higgins and Alonzo bodden then.
It's a Blossom Music Center in Cuyahoga Valley National Park
Everybody right now it is time for the wait wait don't tell me
Listener game call one
AAA wait wait
Twoplayergames
Hi you are on wait wait don't tell me
Hello this is Jeremy Simms in Whittier North Carolina
What's Whittier
Looks to the Smoky Mountain National Park
Cherokee
I'm a winerip and a musician
You're a wine rep what's the wine
What seemed like
In North Carolina
I fit in the summertime when it's
Taurus season
And speaking of which NPR NASA
Angiographic and all you guys or your wine club
Weiner Lane
Really professional NPR wine
Addition wind sounds
So sad
Jeremy is going to play our game but you must register
Tell truth from fiction
Bill what is Jeremy's topic
Director of the Iowa Department of Human Services
You're fired
I love the state were New York Mayor Bill de Blasio lives
Just fired the 66-year old director of it
Department of Human Services why
Arcane list
Going to tell you
Tell me one of them is telling the truth pick that one
And you won a prize the waiter of you
Your choice on your voice
Ready to play I'm ready
Let's first hear from
Maeve Higgins
It's not where you been it's where you're at
A cool saying but not one that applies to Jerry foxhoven
The director of the Iowa Department of Human Services who has recently asked to resign from his post
The shocking reason for his resignation
And it's only the
Becoming care no
He does not live in Iowa
Nor it turns out has he ever even being there
It began when Mr foxhoven was at a meeting in DC and refer to Iowa as
That lovely place by the
When jimin Olympus in Iowa housing official hurt his colleague saying that he quizzed him
Asking what their state was famous
Mister foxhoven replied in a shaky voice
Well as you know Iowa
The Lone Star State
How about those Iowa Buckeyes
Next year we win
All of the football game
That's what the newspapers picked up on this
One report to reach mr. foxhoven on the phone and asked him some basic question
But anybody who lives in iOS should know
In response
Answer the question
Where is Sioux City
He answers
I haven't seen you in years
What a great girl
Now that he's being fired his former employees at connecting the dots
When it came to having team meeting
He would always video conferencing
Even when the meeting is happening just down the hall from his office
Contacted by reporters
Some staff mentioned seeing a surfboard in the background
A nosing that in hindsight it was unlikely he was using
To surf
Springfield
Jerry foxhoven problem he had never actually been to Iowa
Your next story of the pink
Slip comes
Mo Rocca
Until June 17th
It's your old Jerry foxhoven was Iowa
Director of him
Turn Services
That was the day after he sent an email to 40
300 agency employee
Praising the music of the late rapper
Tupac Shakur
Foxhoven
Formerly known as The Notorious
DHS director
Isn't just a fan of
Tupac Shakur
He was hosting weekly
Tupac Friday
Play his music in the office
Aerozone birthday foxhoven served
Tupac theme
Cluding one decorator
With the words
Fog lights
During his two years he sent
52 Poppin emails to employees
When Governor Kim Reynolds ask
How to resign was
One week after foxhoven sent an agency-wide email
Reminding employees to Mark Tupac's birthday
If I playing one of his songs
Anyone think that is
6 year old Island loving rap is
Funny bear in mind
Set the Barre
First rap
Was heard in the opening
Of the greatest American Musical which was set in Iowa
The Music Man
Cash for the fancy Goods cast for the soft goods cast for the nagas in the Pickens in the freaking cats
You can talk you can talk you can picture you can talk you can talk all you want but it's different
Jerry foxhoven fired from job in the Iowa state government because apparently I have his overly enthusiastic capricia
Creation of Tupac Shakur
Your last story of a dishonorable discharge comes from Alonzo
Boden
Jerry foxhoven loves Iowa
He Loves Us State cities
Town
The fields the highways
He loves I was human
And he loves providing them
Services
Which is good because
Is the Iowa state director of
Human Services
But there was one problem
Jerry foxhoven
Heat score
It started with a Facebook page
Recalled corn
What is a devil's brain
Jerry posted all the reason
Since he hates corn it gets caught in your teeth
It's hard to the Jets
Corn on the cob is a
Sloppy mess on your finger
The page grew in popularity
What other haters
Chiming in
An unpopped popcorn cracked my tooth
If I want to know what I ate the night with
Before I keep a diary
It even. Political with a tax on ethanol fuel subsidies or the corn lobbies influences on Congo
The problem with this is Facebook
Is public
And when corn Farmers saw the page they went straight to the governor
You can't be coming over the corn state in Havasu
Senior point
I hate corn
Rebecca Shields a reporter from the Iowa Gazette
Asphalt Tobin
Why the hatred
Corn
Beethoven said
Can you eat corn everyday is a
Child in
I just got so sick of it
He thought it would be funny to
After that
Sportage join
When is Paige
Became a real thing and it
Spun out of his car
Control
He sighed
I guess in the end
Korn one
All right
It really is a guy named Jerry foxhoven really is 56 years old and he really
Weather this week
The head of Human Services for the state of Iowa
Why
Was he fired was it because
From maid he didn't actually live in or at ever been to Iowa
From Morocco
Overt
And perhaps over enthusiasm for the rapper
Tupac Shakur
Or
From
Alonzo
He just
Heated corn too much
Which of these are the real reasons
We Believe
For his termination
I'll have to be more raucous
Story story of the complete Yasmin for Tupac Shakur
Alright you picked his now it's amazing because we were able to get in touch
With the gentleman
In question
Himself
My favorite song by Tupac
That was Jerry foxhoven he loves Tupac Shakur
Almost as much as he used to love Iowa state bureaucracy
Congratulations you got it right
Always telling the truth including about Meredith Wilson inventing Hip Hop
So you have won our prize the voice of your choice in your voicemail congratulations
Alright thank you
And now the game where we ask people who've been through a lot
To go through
Thing else
Not my job Piper Kerman was a happy-go-lucky young woman when she just happened
Happily go to Europe
Put some drug money
And got unlucky
Ended up serving a year in a women's prison but you know all that
Because she wrote a book about her experience
It's called Orange is the New Black which was adapted into the hit next
Flick series
Can I spend more time in prison here in Ohio teaching writing to inmates
Piper Kerman welcome to wait wait don't tell me
Have you put away is it is it all is it all right that we tell people that you're here in Ohio are you still on the Run
I mean I don't know what your status
I am not on the lam and I yeah I've been living
When you're in Ohio for all
5 years
Fantastic and end
Believe everybody knows your
Story but maybe not
You were a young woman living in Soviet a fancy free
This is back in the early 90s
And you had a friend
Who asked you to do this are into bringing some money
Which was ill-gotten
She asked me to carry a bag of money from
Chicago to Brussels
Write what you did yes I did and and just to be clear you knew this was not like
Legit
And you did that
And then you extricated yourself
From that delicious Japan that life but then some years later there was a knock on your door
Many years later the sundress
It was actually.
As a metaphor
All right
And to make a long and ultimately profit
You are ended up
Pleading guilty to charges
What is money laundering
And went off to Danbury State Prison
Yes Federal
Federal Prison
The book obviously is in
Is a memoir
It's nonfiction
They took some liberties
The book is a true story and the
The show takes the book
Put in a blender and put the
A lot of other
Yeah that isn't that fantastic
Fan of the
Michelle
Okay where and all the people all the wonderful
Back in prison
Although now you were doing it as an instructor
And so what are you doing
It
Teach a true story
Braiding class
A class
Commanding right
True stories from their own life as
Flea memoir
And and
Where are you doing
I do that at the Ohio State
Reformatory for women
Which is right smack-dab in the
Middle of the state
And then at the Marion Correctional
From that
Liberty to the mende of your famous prison recipes
They were very interest
Cheesecake recipe actually at the men's
Facility the women all knew how to
Do it
Cooking with
Which I did not think was the thing that happened
In prison
Turns out the food in the chow hall
Pretty bad
Skills of the
Prisoners are much better
Other materials are kind of rough
To work
Exercise was
What are the few things youku
Could you to spend your time you ended up at least
The first looking pretty great
I ran a half-marathon when I was in
That's really boring
Where do you how do you run a half marathon
You run a half marathon around 1/4 Mile gravel track
Wow
So you but as you said
Chat with the food Hall was terrible so you started cooking for yourself how do you make a
Good cheesecake
To make a cheesecake in prison
Unidays
Tupperware bowl
You have to have that after
The commissary or borrowing
You make a cross out of
Smashed up graham crackers
Or Oreo.
You need some margarine that
You've stolen
From the chow hall
That is the only
Stolen ingredients
In this recipe which makes it novel and notable
And then for the filling
You take those
Cheeses that don't
Refrigerated
You need about a half a cup of pudding
You can usually get
And
User to beat those things
Viciously together
Shoulder cream
And then you get a beating on it down on the pudding and cheese
And you also start to add an inch
Tire thing of
Kimora
About yay tall I'm making I'm putting my hands about 8
10 more is the
Powdered powder substitute
You put that in there the whole can
Container you try not to think about what
What's going at what's in there right and you mix and you mix and then it actually what you have is kind of
Yes yes well
Then you take
The Plastics
Squeezed lemon
And you put I would
Is really most
Cast of The Lemon
Squeeze that in
What is a mix
And it tightens up I attribute whatever
Mysterious things are
Contained in
But
Remarkably like the tech
Picture of
A New York
Cheesecake
So it seems if you're in prison
You've got to get a Food Network show
Well Piper Kerman it is a pleasure to talk to you we have invited you here
Play a game that we're calling
Blunder
Do you busted and as we discussed serve time for money one
Wondering which made us wonder how much you know about the mortar
What kind of laundry
Questions about
What they call
Clothing laundering
They might like on our show on their voicemail
Bill who is Piper Kerman playing for
Sofia Carson
Ohio
Who's here with her family today
Who's the first question American Pioneers had to bring invented way of dealing with dirty
He closed what was it a
Sticking them in the old face
Geyser in Yellowstone
And waiting for it to erupt
Be shooting their laundry
Tree with quotes
Soap shop
Or see just standing there a buffalo and blaming the animal
I'm going to go with Old Faithful you're exactly right
Direct flights for as they say they were to stick their laundry in the guys or wait for it to go up the laundry with blowout in the air they pick it up
That's what I was just absolutely
While he was writing Walden
Henry David Thoreau of course shot himself off
Civilization
That made
80s clothes
Kleen Def
What clever technique
Did Thoreau used
To get his clothes
Queen
During his year living at
Coat his clothes
Is in honey
Let the
The Bears
Lick them clean
He used his philosophical insights to
To convince the clothes
To turn away
From dirt
Or see he walked the mile into town and had his mom do it for
This is so easy
Walden isn't that far out of town they also brought food for
All right last question nowadays things of course in laundry as with everything else it's all high-tech
Astronauts on the international
Small space station
Do their laundry how
Buy laser
Be hanging them on a line outside
Or see loading their dirty laundry into a cargo spaceship and letting it burn up on
On re-entry
I think it's basically a virgin
Disposable underwear I'm going to go
You're exactly right there's no water up there it's much easier to bring up Fremont
Cargo ship hit the old laundry in the ship and let it burn up on me
You're exactly right
Billie Piper doing our quiz
She got all free right and that is right
Piper Kerman is the author of the book Orange is the New Black the adaptation
Of the book
Is on Netflix
Its final season drops in July 20th
Piper Kerman thank you so much thank you so much
Take a deep breath
Be back in a minute with more wait wait don't tell me from NPR
Support for this podcast and the following message comes from
MailChimp
So you want to grow your business
No one
Male chimps all-in-one marketing platform that's what
It has all the marketing stuff you need all in one place
So you can save time and money
Edit powered by a marketing CRM so you can collect organize and understand your audience data
All to help you Market smarter and grow fast
Learn more at MailChimp
Dot-com
Well you're sleeping
A whole bunch of news is happening around the
Up first is the NPR news podcast
She caught up on the big news
In a small amount of time
Spend about 10 minutes with a
First on weekday mornings for men
NPR news
NPR WBEZ Chicago this is wait wait don't tell me
NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Curtis Ware playing this week with Alonzo bodden
Mo Rocca
Maeve Higgins
Pepsi Warehouse
At the Blossom Music Center in Cuyahoga Valley National Park
Everybody thank you girl it just a minute Bill tries to find a friend on
Grindr
And I listener limerick challenge game
If you like to play give us a call at 1 Triple 8 weight
188-892-4894 right now panel some more questions
For you for the week news this week researchers
Publish the translation
Hefei historic
Earliest known
Communication
Between Christians outside of the Bible
The date from 2:30 ad
And it's a letter
From one brother to another
Which the writer
Please
With his brother
For what
Is this
3rd century
You saying
When are you going to be
Done
What's Leviticus I want to read it now
I love dietary
Directions
Give me a clue I shall we don't know if the
The phrase used
Translate to catch a
Mayo or A1
So it's one brother
Tell him about a great new
Condiment
Who discovered asking for a concept that he's asking for
Sauce pick up
Pick up the song zactly The Letter begins greetings my Lord my incomparable brother paulus and it goes on
Please bring back.
Saw psylocke
It's basically a primitive form of texting somebody to pick up dinner on the way home
The brother offer
Reimburse policy
How to be a venmo
Those days that was the name of the cow bladder you kept
Your coins in
What's the sauce in question is a fish
Liver sauce
Which sounds gross but when the entree every night is Larks tongues you want to drown it
Of course it probably wasn't real fish liver sauce
You know is just laying
And where was this discovered lizards discovered and it was a Papyrus that originally
Egypt is it
Been sitting for
Decades
And somebody's archiving
I love a fast
Food Rosetta
Slab
Maybe it was a menu with a drive-thru
We're all out of fish liver sauce
Mets
Babe this week the website Lifehacker posted their advice for avoiding stress while fly
We all need that
Their number one tip is what
Don't fit in the window
Really
Because
Did I do know that I was just air ticket
I did not know that it is the worst
Because it changes your voice
And this thing happened to me where I was sick and then I said to
Child sitting beside me I was stuck in the window so I said
I felt like I would
To be sick
As I said to the child
Give me can you just
Go to the
Interrelated
And then they took so long
With their iPad and their headphones
And then I turned to the times that I said
Who is that
On the kids on the front on my says somehow on the kids
Parents sitting behind me
I was really you know it was extraordinary I was almost
Charming
So what do you love
The question was what is the number one thing
Prey lovely relaxing easy
Don't eat pasta
Tempesto before you get it
Imma give you a hint this just doesn't sound crazy it's only crazy to anybody who's ever done
The third visor
I'll take a red-eye cigarette
School give it to whoever said it
11 p.m. gets in at 5 a.m.
Security lines
Shorter the tickets are cheaper
Play the more likely to be empty
But that's because no one else is stupid enough to take the red off
The main argument that was that you'll sleep better
Would make sense
Except for the fact
50 flight is named
After what happened
To you when you do not sleep that's why it's called that guy over right eye
Absolutely I think the thing to do is find out what flight made
Amazon at 9
Coming off its lightning fill in the blank refers is the game where you have to listen for the ride if you like to play on their caller leave a message
1-aaa wait wait
That's one 880-892-4892
Before higher on wait wait don't tell me
Hi
Regular
From Salem Ohio to Salem Ohio forgive me for not knowing this and how far
Far is Salem from where we are in Cleveland
It's like an hour
An hour away what do you do there in two
Well I work as a Forester but the dream is to be a stay-at-home mom
You work as a Forester
Isn't it usually the other way around the people that home with their cats wish they could be out in the forest
Maybe that might have to
Danny welcome to the show Bill Kurtis is going to be a few 3 News related literature the last word or phrase
Missing from you
Can fill in that last
Word or phrase
Correctly
To be a winner
Here's your first love
Pay attention
Come close
Take good care
Now what do you see
Nothing there
H2O
CO2 and cement
ZzzQuil do
We have whipped up some
Food from
Are there
I finished
Company claim they can make an edible protein
Using only carbon dioxide Water and Light
A product currently known in the US as like what
The food
This food made of thin air has a consistency
They say similar to weed
Wheat flour
Which means you can finally Gorge yourself
On all the dry wheat flour
You want feel free
Eating
The ideas they say we can actually make food
From Air
Using electricity
Somehow creating edible protein
That gives you
Yeah
I can't be weird if that were the case you'd be like what are you trying to go to diet breathing for me today thanks trying to lose it
That's what it sounds like it sounds like anuel AA.
Alright here's your neck slimmer
This avian trend
Like Hitchcock
Is fluck
Has been spurred
They dive bomb for fun
While I'm
I don't know run
I have just been
Attack by a
Birds are going crazy this summer dive-bombing it's
Food of the people's hands
Red-winged blackbirds of the biggest aggressors attack
Can anyone who comes near their habitats
That will leave the tax myteen random it is breeding season the birds are really just saying hey
Knock next time
Or they shouldn't hang a necktie on there
Desk knobs
They take time out of there
You know love making two
Bomb a person
Because the babysitter
All the babies are made already
Alright Jamie here is your last
Limit
Has Pottery Barn in lakes
Immense
Phillies ref
Will Dow pay dividends
2 annual all run across
Chairs from
Rachel and Ross
Resale furniture
Picture
On
Friends friends friends inspired
Shoreline from Pottery Barn UK
Spruce up your space with iconic living room pieces from the sitcom
And get yourself
Mugs
Do you have Rachel's coffee table
You can have a bunch of lazy people lying around you somehow don't need jobs
Friends as you all know is a television show that ended about 15 years ago
People still watch it
Because of the hilarious antics
Rachael Ross
Niles rosin
Frasier
There's a lot of this going around a lot of
Stuff
Sponsored by TV shows Pottery Barn
Is doing friends unfortunately
Sears
The Chernobyl
Not for not so long
Tornado Orange
Black furniture
How did Jamie do an AR quiz
Jamie's been waiting for it all her life and it paid off for the perfect score
Cricinfo
This message comes to you from NPR sponsor Capital One
Capital One Knows life doesn't alert you about your credit card
That's why they created Dino
The Capital One assistant
The catches things that might look wrong with your credit card like overtipping
Duplicate charges or potential fraud then sends an alert to your phone and help you fix it
It's another way Capital One is watching us
For your money when you're not
Capital One
What's in Uruguay
To capitalone.com
For details
Support also comes
Something
Protein bars
I think I can
Will remember the story of that little engine who thought she could
And didn't stop until she reached the mount
With 20 grams
The protein 0 grams
Sugar and no artificial flavors
Pink bars
Provide the same inspired energy to
Fuel your goals
So what are you hope to pop out a few more reps at the gym or simply power through the afternoon after missing lunch
Think knows you can
Get 25% off with code wait
Think products
Dot-com
No wonder why final game let me fill in the blank you should buy players with that 60 seconds wood
What's the answer as many fill in the blank
Does he or she can expect answer
She's not worth to phone
Bill can you give us
The score is five
Points
Maeve has one
Alonzo has
All right major in third place you're up first the clock will start when you begin your first question
Fill in the blank
On Wednesday the house voted to hold attorney general blank in
Contempt of court
Fefferman
Looking for his name man looking for his attorney general
William Barr
On Wednesday Rand Paul block the senate for
Approving a compensation fund
For the victims of blank
Right 911 this week
The DNC announced the 20 president
Qualified
Round of televised
Yes on Monday India
On Monday Indian scrubber they're playing the mission to blank just minutes before
For takeoff
Their mission to blank their mission to the Moon yes very good
During a routine traffic stop in Oklahoma Police found blank blank and blank inside a man's vehicle
I used to think of three different words
Crazy sexy
Be cool if I'm an open bottle of whiskey alive rattlesnake in a canister of
View raining on Wednesday World Health Organization declared the blank outbreak
Can the Congo a global health
Ebola right on Sunday
Novak Djokovic
Defeated blanked
He played his second straight Wimbledon title
Another tennis
Arby's is dead
They would not be adding The vegetable-based Impossible Burger to their menu but they would be adding
Blank bacon
No
A carrot
Made of meat
It's so much easier to be a vegetarian now that there is a carrot
Fruit vegetable exactly the new item from Arby's is made
Turkey which is then flavored like a carrot so it is everything you love about me
Except the taste
Because the product launch was the first time somebody said I want to show you all my meat
Garrett
It has not been arrested
Bill how did Maeve doing AR quiz
5 write 10 more points a total of 11
And you're in the league alright Alonzo
Alonzo drop next fill in the blank on Monday the White House issued new rules effectively barring migrant
From Central America from requesting black
Asylum right on Thursday the US Navy said it destroyed a drone from blank
In the Strait of Hormuz
The Ron Rice on Wednesday the house voted to block president
Saudi Arabia right after spending months
Tending to an watering his girlfriend's new house plan
Man in Australia discovered blank
Her boyfriend
No
Discovered that it was made of plastic on Wednesday streaming service on Wednesday streaming service blank
Announce
Its first major loss
If us subscribers
Domination
Game of Thrones leave the pack
For the 2019 blank award
Write this week police in Alabama
Warned that criminals flushing drugs down the toilet could lead
Black
Highly
Kid alligator
You're exactly right the police referred to the bearded teachers
Gators
Drug dealers in Alabama if you keep flushing your stash down the toilet you may end up creating a race
They say
Of meth addicted Gators
Roaming the streets
Looking for a fix
That sounds way worse than a normal Gator doesn't meth make your teeth fall out
Problem solved
No I think Alonzo did pretty well what do you think they got 612
All right
How many event does MO need to win
When Tony's five the way we can do that
Fill in the blank
On Wednesday the house voted to block a call from representative Al Green
Start a blank proceeding
Against Pres
Write following the publication of a trophy
Offensive text messages
The governor of blank has said he will not be stuff
Puerto Rico
The Trump Administration
Informatica citizenship questions
The blank
Right on Tuesday former Supreme Court Justice flank passed away at the age of 99
That he was out of famous baseball game
The gamer Babe Ruth
Supposedly called
ShopRite
This week a correctional facility in the UK announced the new program where well-behaved prisoners will be given blank
No
Keys to the prison a year after declaring bankruptcy toy store chain
Blanket
Athens opening two new stores for the holidays
Apartment complex
Can Colorado residents a note informing them that blank was no longer allowed
People
Live loud laughter
MMOs residents to only use Library level voices and stated that quote
Loud laughter in conversation with people to relax
Singing their homes is a noose
Regardless
Of the time of day
In order to heal after tooth absolute minimum of the building managers have
Install radios that will play NPR
Department
Whitman Peter
Colorado
Legalize marijuana
Bill how did Moe do did he do well enough to win
You got that five that he needed
So he wins with 15 the graduation tomorrow thank you very much thank you
After face off what will be the next big app
Everyone will get excited about
Wait Wait don't Tell Me NPR WB
G-Eazy Chicago association with the Urgent haircut Productions at Doug Berman benevolent overlord
A public address announcer is Paul Friedman and Lila Francis rweb crew is better
BJ leiderman composer theme is produced by Jennifer Miller
Miles dornbos
And Lillian King
Technical directions from Lorna white her business and off managers Colin Miller
Executive producer Michael
Danforth now panel what will be the next big app everybody
It's called faith
And it makes you look like Nicolas Cage
Alonzo bodden there's going to be an app with no filters No Effects you'll take a picture
Currency what you act
Flea look like
Call The Rum Tum Tugger app
It tells you what
Can you be in the music
Cats even though I already know that I would
Skimbleshanks the railway cat
Alonzo bodden
Wcpn ideastream and everyone asks you
Opossum
Is NPR