This message comes from
NPR sponsor
Fitbit with a Father's Day gift from fit
Your dad will get used.
It's about his body and how
Visit Fitbit.
Slash weight
To save up to $30
Stores with free next-day shipping
From June 2nd
The June 15
From NPR and WBEZ Chicago
NPR news quiz
Hey
Steph Curry
Chronic spinning old basket
Finger
Adam Curtis
We have worked
On this
Show all week
And frankly I
Going to pay off
Later on we're going to be talking to Olivia Wilde the well-known actress
DirecTV
Is about to young woman
Who at the last minute realize they've spent their entire High School careers
Studying
Forgot
To have any
Fun
Alternative title for this film
Public radio host
Present at the creation
Fun by giving us a call the number is 1 AAA wait wait that's 188-892-4892
Two forks let's welcome our first listener contestant how you're on wait wait don't tell me
Hi this is
Grace I'm calling from Montreal
If you have a ride
We do they are crazy
Perhaps you're just not used to rock
Enthusiasm in Canada
Welcome to our show let me introduce you to our panel this week first
The comedian will be at the
The Houston Improv June 13th to the 15th
And you can hear his new podcast back to school with Maz jobrani
Alright
Spotify in anywhere podcast
I found its Maz jobrani
Hi Great Neck the comedian performing at the Firehouse Grill in Devon
Princeton Illinois June 13th and headlining the
The Comedy Barn
Chicago July 5th
Do the 7th at the atom
Burklow Gray
Welcome a comedian whose Netflix
Special produced by
Tiffany haddish and Wanda Sykes
Comes out this summer zaida Rodriguez
Bill this time Bill Kurtis is going to redo three quotations from this week's news if you can correctly identify
Explain two of them you will win our prize
Any voice commercial you might like for your voicemail are you ready to play
Your first quote is from the president
There were thousands of people on the streets cheering
There were definitely not thousands of the people in the streets cheering for the president
Where
This week
I'm going to say yes London England very good
Commemorates the 75th anniversary of D-Day and while you might say that's a solemn occasion
Can you recognize the sacrifice of our nation and our allies
The trumps a family vacation
Having such a good
Time Don Jr and Eric went for a
Pub crawl
But everybody waited until the 5th
Pub
To tell them that you
You don't actually
Crawl and this is true excitedly tweeted quote
In route to The Hague
Yeah you are Ivanka
You are
Piers Morgan
Was in
Interviewing Donald Trump and I think that's a great mom
Because that's two other people that don't have to
To talk to either Piers Morgan
For dogs
Send them off
Sort of like the iran-iraq war to talk to each other
I do like
Just understand President Trump I don't think actually likes being president
Doing the job
Given the meetings
He likes the pumpkin
So he loved this state
Dinner they threw for a mother
Queen of the Royal Family
And we saw those pictures of him
Wearing
That
White tie and Tails outfit
It was weird
Did it fit so poorly cuz it was perfectly tailored for
230 lb guy
I tell you what I did love
Come to your house if they're so bad you like
They can stay for dinner
They can't spend the night
Visit Upstate at Buckingham Palace is no no it's under renovation
They have a 130 bedroom
Alright Grace your next quote is someone on Twitter reacting
Recent scientific news
Thank God
That was a reaction to news that what
Will end
By 2050
Oggi's
It's not so much that climate change will end it's that climate change will end the something else
Population growth
Yeah yeah yeah. I'm going to give it to you because basically
Everything will be over
By 2050 the whole world
You may have missed this because everybody was
Distracted by that hilarious video of the rescue
Hiker spinning underneath the helicopter wasn't that great
But according to a study out of Australia there is an excellent chance
The human civilization will be over by 2050
Which is silly cuz
Human civilization already ended
We started using Fried Chicken as bread for sandwiches
Wondering how the scientist
We're dead serious by the way
Can be so specific at the world end
Precisely in 2050
That's because research has shown the world warranty expires
In 2049
Did you guys see this did you guys notice this in the in the
Yeah I got a reaction
Twitter cuz my response
Good
Yeah I know I feel like I'm in a real
Sam's right now we need to reboot
All the game
Thrones Fantasy Life
The news that the world would end in 2050 came out the same week as Joe Biden a noun
His plan to reduce
Is carbon emissions and this is true by
He might need
To massage back a bit
What didn't he get
In trouble for that
The plagiarism
Sing write something again
They said that they date
The Basic Talk
The verbiage
From other climate
Research has ended
Inside Edition
Just put it into the sea
Thanks it was doing it
Basically
Just
Copied and pasted
He stole his climate plan from
In the Book of Revelation
Michelle Obama's at home like I'm up
I'm so tired of these people
Vibratory plow
Hahaha thanks a lot this is Obama
Alright Grace
Here is your last quote
If the FBI says it's near here
I guess that's it
For now that was a man
Name Peter Byrne is 93 years old and
Is best known among the
His peers
As one of these
The Four Horsemen of
Of Sasquatch
He was talking to the Washington Post this week after the FBI finally released
Their top secret files
On what
Wow I have no idea
You never heard of
Sasquatch also known as
What is the answer back in the day as I'm sure you know the FBI
Surveillance files and
All kinds of public
Here's why not Bigfoot
Factors one theory that Bigfoot never revealed himself
Because he was afraid
J Edgar Hoover wood
Reveal that he's been wearing an enormous
Back to back
But for decades there has been
Rumors
Does the FBI
I tested the first saint
Temple found in Oregon
Discovered it was not
Any animal known to man
But this week they finally release
Is the file in it
Turns out that
True as long as the man were talking about
I never heard
Of a deer
Because that's what it is
He waited
40 years
And it was like
The answer is no
Please like this for a minute be like
You were right it was Bigfoot
Adidas like yes and I was just kidding
8 years
Taipei guide
Address
Goodwin Matthew
Pallbearer
First job at the FBI
Bigfoot tape
Canada did very well graduation
Right now panel it is time for you to answer some questions about this week
News
By the saying that they're hoping to appeal to people that just hate to go shopping
Sherman
The toilet paper
Has introduced a new product what is
Did they improve the toilet paper
This is sort of an improvement
Paper towels
No
I know this guy
You mad
It is
It's it's the product
But what
Wow giving Clues
Oh no
Mama don't let Adam take it if you know it
Xiamen forever
Giant
Rowland scherman
It's a roll of Charmin
So large
It is designed to last
Two three months
Where do you keep it
Well
Funny that task
Because it's an enormous roll of toilet paper
Will not fit in
Your standard dispensary
By 1 it comes like a little
Stand paper you buy this you will not run out
For three months imagine
Like a small
Car tire
Pain after your toilet but you do realize you can like on Amazon and get us
Subscription I have one
Toilet paper comes every few months
And we use it
I don't need toilet paper
Pile up on red like your New Yorkers
Subscription boxes
Netflix
I'm still on the toilet
Coming up stand clear of the closing doors please at the computer seems left
A game called will be back in a minute with more
Don't tell me
From NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Fitbit
Fitbit want everyone to know their body
Better even your dad
You probably doesn't know how much deep sleep you get
Katsur bet his heart
Beats faster at the smell of barbecue ribs
Were there any burn 500 calories on the back nine
Get the incredible dad in your life
The gift of finally knowing
Everything
Shop now at fitbit.com weight
And save up to
The $30
Free next-day shipping
Due June 15
After more than 50 years of lies and
Witnessed
Finally
I need to know what they going to get off or not
But I'm glad when they did
Even though they will give 290 they'll give him they knew that would
It's White Lies
Listen
Subscribe now
Wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Kurtis what you're playing this week without him
Jabroni
Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown Chicago Peter
Thank you very much.
Everybody
Hey you want to remind you
That you can also hear our show is a podcast wherever you get your podcast
That's right finally
We got to the bottom of who murdered Maz jobrani
Oh I'm sorry
Spoiler
Wait wait don't tell me Bluff The Listener game
Two-player game in the air hot you're on wait wait don't tell me
Cedar house
Are you doing
Where you calling from
Sumter South Carolina Sumter South Carolina okay what are you doing
I'm a trucker
Our
We sometimes hear from public radio
Get some company on the road is that the case
It is I like your show and when Bartaco
That really gave me
Good chuckle
God
That's why we're here
Text
2 hours a week what do you do to pass the rest of the time
Call Ralph
First thing you should ask
Interesting person
So you don't mind all that time alone in the cab because you've got
You with you
What's up
Welcome to the show you're going to play the game and what you should have to tell truth from fiction
Bill what is Sean's top
Get out of the way Grandma the commute
The thing you don't like to do to get you to the place
You don't want to be
This week we read about someone trying to improve
Your commute
For you are pandas going to tell you about it
51a telling the truth you win our prize The Voice
The wait waiter
Of your choice on your voice
Smelly ready to play Sean
Sure
Okay here we go
First letter from Adam
Burke
Straphangers of the world know the Pains of public transit
Amputation particularly in summertime
What is
Quite literally the pets
Across the globe commuters are crossed into Dental
Sleep act composite
Face to face with a stranger's underarms.
It's being insufficient
Charlie perfume
Now it's Tacoma base
Consulting firm think they
Adult currently conducting tests
From the subway Network
In Seoul South Korea
It's very simple concept
What explains lead engineer sarachan
No one wants to cause a scene by calling someone out for their sin
So our solution is both effective
And more importantly anonymous
Each strap and handles on a
Train car
Is equipped with a special mechanism
Which when activated by a subtle
Twist and pull motion
Dispenses a present
Fragrant
Which deodorizer
Is the area immediately around
The all Factor Ali affected passing
Wallet anti be made to alleviate
Train station
The path
This is the first
2B passenger operator
Original design had
The spray aim directly at the problem area
Plainchant
What height difference
Some people were getting deodorized right
In the face
The pilot program is going well
We're calling it axilla
Says Chen
Partially because that's the scientific name for armpit
But mainly because axilla sounds like
A giant
Lizard made of body
Spray
What are pressors installed at armpit height
They can be activated
Play anyone who needs
On the trains your next Story the commute improve
Comes from Ida Rodriguez
There's a new way to get to work
And it is taking the city by the
It's a new
New startup called
Prkr
That's parkour
With no vowels
Parkour of course
What's the news for today
From place to place
Urban and bye
Like Aphrodite
Without a serger
Pandora
Prkr
Provide you with
You're very old park
Who will show up at your home
Designate
Johnston
Klein and somersault your way to work
It stopped
Entirely by out of
Former circus
Because
Is there any other kind
Owner Bigsby Daniel says quote
People complain that the sidewalks
Too crowded
The walls are
All of a sudden
My boring commute was an exciting life and death at
Set prkr Klein
Lovely dance
Do does my clavicle heal
I'm going to upgrade to Spider-Man rooftop jump
Package
Parkour in New York City
Your life story the commute in good repute to come from Maz jobrani
If you live in a big city you've certainly seen rental Electric
Scooter zipping hipsters around
Town being left haphazardly on sidewalks and annoying the hell out of
Well in an effort to improve the local communiques.
A Swedish company called kangaroo is
Introducing an alternative ride-sharing option
Kangaroo start with a c as a pogo stick sharing company
Yes pogo stick
Texas Tech companies are always looking for new innovative ways
To do business
No matter how stupid it sounds
Kangaroo has decided that bouncing from your lunch meeting
Into your personal trainer to your dinner date is what we all need in our lives
CEO and co-founder Adam Mickelson stays
We've been following some micro Mobility market and Slenderman
We also making a statement and contributing to something Beyond
Taking you from point A to point B
Emphasizing the sustainability in
Fitness aspect of the pogo sticks
Like most trans this one will probably catch on for a little while until someone bounces off a pogo stick
On the sidewalk
And into the hospital
Seen this movie before knows that kangaroo can go wrong
Alright Sean let me review choices for you
One of these stories of a way to make your commute more interesting if not quicker
Is
True from adam buerk installing spray deodorant
Dispensers in Subway that you can
Spread some right of the offending armpit
Remind me to commuting bike
Parkour in New York City
Informasi
Rental Pogo
Styx
Just like those scooters but bouncier
Which of these are the real story the new trance
Interpretation
Well
I like the first one
Where are you get this
Spritz
Pain in the armpit
Okay so your choice
Is Adam story
The little devices that allow you to
Spritz offending people riding their armpit hopefully without their knowledge
On smelly subway car
Right
All right
Well
Bring the correct answer we spoke to
To the person who is actually
In charge of this way of improving your
Of course we're not that delusional if we believe that told to fix her saying things you can do for preschoolers
That was Adam Nicholson he is the found
And CEO of kangaroo
The company behind the pogo stick share program and before we go further we just have to admit
Mod nails
I thought it was you again
Pick it up Sean because
You realize this and in fact Adam was lying it was Maz who had the unbelievable true story
Of the rent a pogo sticks I'm sorry you did not win however
You've earned a point for Adam for I think his lovely idea of dealing with the problem of subways in
In the summer thank you so much for listening Sean thank you so much for calling
I can play
And now the game where we ask
Can somebody cool
To do something
Lame
Olivia Wilde became well known as an actor in TV shows like the OC and house
Movies like Tron legacy
And Cowboys and Aliens and now
She's behind the
If we working out well her debut film
Booksmart
Is one of the best reviewed film
Songs of 2019
Olivia Wilde welcome to wait wait don't tell me
Thank you
So you done so much in a relatively recent is there isn't one thing for which
Do you think you're most well-known when people see you in the
I think it is probably house but you never know there's there's Tron fans everywhere they come out of the woodwork you know
I do there more of the nerdy variety
Is there also the most awesome I love
Everywhere but I have to say
Drinking buddies is a movie I shot in Chicago
Add yes and I love it very much and I have
Give it up for the Chicago microbrews
Being witches
Really awesome
This is great because obviously as we mentioned you've done some
Pretty serious Hollywood project
And Joe Swanberg filmmaker here in Chicago he's famous for shooting Ultra low-budget movies
He doesn't script
He just says hey guys
Is your character sit here and turning the camera go
Yeah yeah and did you enjoy working that way
Oh my God I love it especially cuz we were drunk 100% of the time
I tried to emulate it with booksmart with less beer because we had Young
This is your first
Future witch
Is very exciting
Yeah I'm one of the things I've read is that it
It's very intimidating to be a movie director
Cuz even a low-budget movie there's a lot of money this Allah
A lot of people they're all looking to you too
To be the leader
Did you have to struggle with that was that tough for you did you fall Nat
Actually End of the Roll
I thought we naturally into it because I've been on sets for 17 years
I was ready to take the rain
You know I was ready to be the boss
Listen to Heart I enjoyed that part have you been onsets doing all those other projects you've been doing sitting there the whole time going
Damn it I should be
Increasingly yes.
This movie book smart
It's about
Two young women they're about to graduate high school
It's also very contemporary if I'm not mistaken it takes place right now
The spring of 2019
Yes that's right
You are to me a very young person but you're not that young
So did you have to learn stuff about like what high school kids are like now and how they were different
When you were graduating ice
Yeah basically they're just a lot better now
Smarter there much cooler there much more evolved
How much more fluid
And then I had to learn some of their cool lingo that I am
100000 years old and I had to kind of catch up on how they
For the longest time I didn't know what they meant when they were like Brad Pitt lives
Batman's outfit so I passed out on
The word
Brad Pitt
Bad Batman
Yeah
Did ever tell you anything that made you think they were just pulling your leg
They were at the whole time but
They were very very kind
Give me a call I have to ask you this is a movie
As is giving away by the title about to rather brainy girls
In high school
Woohoo in fact the side at one point they haven't had enough fun they've been
Been so brainy and
Was that what you were like
In in high school
I went to like the ultimate nerd High School just the nerdiest
The nerd and I was one of them and I'm proud
We didn't have
Fun party
I just wasn't made aware but
The movie about it in order to go to the party
The movie has come out it's gotten great reviews I hope
A lot of people see it let's assume that it is the success that it seems
Tubidy know what you want to do next or going to
Try to do one of those big superhero movies
Usual progression
We've done those big movies you can
Handle it
I can handle it I can handle it as long as I have you no good snacks and
Loud music I can make it happen
You know I will say
The statistics are pretty Grim for female filmmakers so I say that all of us ladies should step up and
Start telling stories as much
Could we possibly
Well Olivia Wilde we haven't
Fact
Nice to hear to play a game that we're calling
Olivia Wilde
Have some Wild Wings
That's right we're going to ask you about Buffalo Wild Wings
What's the casual-dining franchise that was named in your honor by some drunk guys were really into cowboys and alien
Answer two out of three questions correctly on your win our prize for one of our listeners the wait waiter of their choice during their voicemail Bill who is
Who is Olivia Wilde
Playing for
Denver Colorado
All right
Here's your first question
Though the star of the menu at Buffalo Wild Wings Dezavala
Obviously
The wings
That's not all they have to offer you could also order which of these at one of their rest
AAA 1 gallon bag of fountain soda for only
Only 799
Be a cocktail called the gin and tonic and ranch dressing
Orsi
Chicken forearm
Oh my God
I am just Airi
Really
Hope it's
What was the back of a bag of salt and soda
That's what it is
You're right Olivia that's the right one very good
Good for parties
Yes that question you can catch it with any sport you want on the many TVs at your local Buffalo Wild Wings but at 1
Ocean in Alabama
You can also do what a attend a church service
B Hunt game
Very big backyard
Orsi's have paintball fights with other cusps
Oh wow
Oh my gosh
I'm going to go with church
You're absolutely right Olivia yes
Of course the church service at this particular Buffalo Wild Wings begins Buffet
For the restaurant opens you can't have beer and wings
Service however
They encourage you to stick around and enjoy it at
The communion wine also come in a bag
Perfect in this as you have been in so many other things
Who's your last question March Madness is the busiest time at Buffalo Wild Wings right
To the restaurant
Is always looking for
Four ways to make the customers experience even more enjoyable
Including which of these
Hey they set up boots
With sports bookies to help you drop your brackets
Being on site therapist for those
Suffering from actual clinical March Madness
4C the jewel stool a cool bar stool for men who got
Vasectomy so they could skip work and watch more game
I love all of us so much
What are the booths with sports
It was actually the jewel stool what does truth and it isn't even
Genius many men
Schedule vasectomies around March Madness
This is true so they can enjoy the enforced rest in front of the TV
So why not entice them down to Wild Wings
Right marketing
Bill how did Olivia Wilde do an AR quiz
That's a big one play
So good about this
I feel great do I get a lifetime
Mywings I'm hoping
I think you should go into your nearest Buffalo Wild Wings
And say hello I'm Olivia Wilde
I would like some wings
And see what happens
You should go do it
Olivia Wilde's new film book-smart is in theaters now go see it it's charming and funny as all get-out Olivia Wilde
Thank you so much for joining us on waitlist my time
In just a minute
AAA 24
Wait wait don't tell me
From n
PR
If you want to hear more about Olivia Wilde in her new movie book-smart
Then check out last Friday's episode of Pop
Culture happy hour
Were you can get a twice-weekly low down
The latest in TV
Support for NPR
This podcast comes from
Choiceology
Unoriginal podcast
Charles Schwab
Choiceology examines the forces that affect our perceptions
Indecision
Like why we underestimate
How long a project will take
We're thinking outcome was obvious
In hindsight
Who's Katy milkman
Explorers question
Xen share strategies for making better
Choices in life
Download the latest episode and subscribe
Schwab.com podcast
Wherever you go
Human behavior doesn't always make a
What kind of sans
At least on the surface
I said would you mind if I give the dogs
Little piece of cracker
With some hot sauce on
Without and see what they choose
Hidden brain
A spicy podcast about science
Psychology
And why people do what they do
WBEZ Chicago
Wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
Angela Curtis Ware playing this week with
Ida Rodriguez
Maz jobrani and Edinburgh in the hearing
Patsy Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown
Chicago PD
Hugging emoticon
Control and I listen to a limerick challenge game if you like to play give us a call
At 1 AAA wait wait
That's 18889
To 48924
Rhino panel some more questions for you from the week's news
Adam wall The Finnish people rank
Look at the top of the world in terms of Life Span education and wealth
Off the Wall Street Journal reports
That they are at the bottom
In one Katha
Aghori what
Humor
Almost
I'll give you a hint it's like
Nice
Weather we are having
Huh
Julie Maz jobrani
Asian doctor Strangelove
Small talk
Maybe the top of the world and all these other important things but they're near the bottom and chatting with the stranger next
USD RBI
Hahaha
And this is true of many schools in Finland are now offering Small Talk classes
The help film
Engage with people from other countries
Enjoy small talk
Feels like that the student gets up before the class and
Who says I like your shirt
Where did you get it
In the student stands are like totally frozen for 20 seconds
Before saying fine thanks
How are you what's up....... Please tell me there's a place
In the world
Shut up
That's why it's called but trailer called finish
Moss as some countries
Turn to solar wind power hour Department of energy
He is still all in on fossil fuels
In fact
In a recent press releases
Referred to fossil fuels as
What essential
No
It's a little bit like you may remember this back during the Iraq
Where were they decided they didn't
Want to call French
Enterprise
So it was
Freedom fuel
Close enough
They called it molecules
Of freedom
Oh no
Eye Quotes
The government
Of the United States
The department of energy is doing what it can to promote an efficient regulatory system
That allows for molecules of us freedom
To be exported to the world
This was this is a press release about exporting Natural Gas
Or as they called it
And I promise you again I am not kidding
Freedom gas
What happened
We do not need to wait to
220 v
Is there any way we can hurry
Molecules of Freedom sounds like
Is invented by
Atoms of asshat
I can't wait to be
Free from the owners bird
Breathing
Twenty50 by the way
I had a question for you
Adam if you've ever gone to CVS and wondered what it would be like to lay down on
On the floor good news
As part of the company's
Expanded focus on Health Care deal
I'll soon be offering customers
In-store yoga Lake
Exactly right wow to CVS Pharmacy
When is expanding to focus on
Wellness
My offering in store
Yoga class
Encouraging deep breathing exercises
Shoe sizes in the place everyone goes when they have a cold
Velocity offering a selection of eight
Footlong receipts
As yoga mat
How does that work to be like downward dog aisle 5
I've been standing in line at a taxi
CVS with people Icon
And spreading all over me I was.
Yoga for
The one thing
Coming up it's lightning fill in the blank but first it's the game where you have to listen for the ride if you like to play on are called and leave a message
AAA wait wait
That's 180 date night
Click the contact us link
Qunar website
Wait wait.
Npr.org
That you can find out about
Attending our weekly live shows right here at
Go to Troy Ave in Chicago
Upcoming shows ready
June 27
At the Mann Center
In Philadelphia
July 18th
At the Blossom Music
6 center near Cleveland locate
Cuyahoga
Park and
Forget Moss be your own panelist
Smart speaker quiz
He's probably dead soon anyway
Answer questions about the news and you may win a prize just say open the wait wait
Quiz to your Alexa or Google home devices
You're on wait wait don't tell me
Josh Asheville North Carolina I love Asheville and I have not been there in too long what do you do there in Asheville
Diamond contractor
What's your selling the stuff that the contractors
Used to do their stuff
Stop is that good work
Yes most the time it is
Yeah yeah I know you do any Contracting building yourself
Yes I understand.
Welcome to our show Josh Bill Curtis is going to reach your 3 News related limerick
With the last word or phrase missing from each if you can fill in that last word or phrase
Is correctly into the limericks will be a winner you ready to play
Alright here's your first lemon
Core values this game will dislodge all
Quit throwing so hard
Pet my crotch
Y'all
Sportsman Lake humble
This makes the world crumble
Let's Spanish
The Savage game
Dodgeball yes very good a team of Canaan
Indian sociology
Clearly enjoy Junior High School
Say dodgeball is a quote
Tool of Oppression that quote
Encourages students
To aggressively single others out for dominance
And to enjoy that
Exclusion and dominance as a Victor
Which is also how you win
Inn at dodgeball
They argue the DodgeBall is morally flawed and harmful to the Social Development of children what they fail to mention
Ocean is that if
He throw the ball at the right angle about the right in front of the guy cross me into the perfect crotch shot
10 points for
Gryffindor
Show me tell these people who always
I talked about getting rid of a graph
Competition in
School don't they always sound like alien
They're trying to take over
The world in 20
Peaceful
Dear Josh is your neck slimmer
We got tired of cafes that have cats
We think
Are better for chats
Over whiskies and beers they lend whiskers
And ears
Heart bar
Let you drink with
That's not bad
No wings
Best rap bars new bar in San Francisco that offers customers
What's the drink with live rats
And it's definitely not just a bar that had a rat infestation and had to come up with an excuse
San Francisco
You can touch and hold
And hold
What a deal
It's right next to cockroaches tacos
Here's your last limerick
Good for underwear lying
Vigilantes
They were once made for Grammys
Not
Anti seize
These high waisted briefs
Seemed a little messy
But the kids now all we're Grammy
Do you like your panties like you like your grandma high-waisted and hanging out at Walgreens then you will love
The Season's hottest lingerie Trend granny panties
He probably Underpants
Exploded in popularity when a photo of Rihanna wearing them
Went viral
Young women flocked to buy the cabin
What others paid
Actually waited for Grandma to die and hope 7 and arrow
Fathers who have
Squatting the full granny panties include JLo
Kendall Jenner and Angela Lansbury
Ironically your actual grandma is now sporting a gospel song
It wasn't
Those darn rats
Congratulations thank you so much
Support for this podcast in the following message comes from ABC
Presenting the new game show Press Your Luck
Have to take big risks to win big buck
And be sure to avoid
Round for round contestants answer questions to earn spins in the morning
Spend some more chance
Do they get to Banks
Are they land on the whammy
Steel
Elizabeth Banks
The fun and thrilling Press Your Luck
Premiering Wednesday June 12
On ABC
Now on to our final the game lightning fill in the blank each of our players with at 62nd
The answer as many film
Each correct answer net worth
Can you give us
Is too and I got doesn't have any
So that means that I thought you were up first
Begin your first question fill in the blank
This weekend accident at blank Military Academy
Because one fatality in over 20 injuries
Yes very good
On Monday Apple announced that it was disc
Continuing
Blank
Morality
No iTunes what cutting into the cake at her daughter's graduation party
A woman in Texas
Was disappointed
You discovered the bakery had given her blank
Gluten
A cake made entirely of Styrofoam
On Wednesday
It was the display cake
See they sent it over
On Wednesday video streaming site
Blanket
They were removing a
Thousands of videos
Expressing quote hateful ideology
Right on Monday the governor of Texas
Signed a bill banning all a blank
Cameras
Phone camera
No red light cameras after being awoken by a loud sound is entryway
Australian man was able to scare off a home Invader by blanket
Streaking
You know what I'm going to give it to you by stripping naked and chasing him with a didgeridoo
Is that what they call it
Startled awake around 4 in the morning and surprised to find a thief try to
Sneak out at front door with stolen goods
But he probably wasn't as surprised as
Steve was when a man stripped off his clothes picked up his didgeridoo
And started chasing him around the house
Bill how did Ida do on Ark
Why doesn't the game she got three right
Pics of six more points
Turtle dove
Very well. You are up next on the blank on Tuesday the
The house passed a bill offering a path
The citizenship for blanks
DACA
Dreamers former White House communications director
Your blank agreed to provide
The congress with some documents related
Hope Hicks
This week at the CDC reported that the outbreak of blank has surpassed
1000 case
The measles right according to a new report The 20/20 blank
Under couch
Whats the US population
Census write a principal of a school in West Virginia has apologized after accusations
Replayed your eyes his graduation
From blank
Oprah
Ashton Kutcher's acceptance
Speech at the 2013 Nickelodeon
Teen Choice Awards
On Wednesday Oakland became the
The Second City
Decriminalize
Is blank
Oh mushrooms yes magic mushrooms
This week the world is celebrated as a baby in England became one of the first to ever to be born with blank
Wings
The answer is frosted tips
Frosted tips or one of the trendiest hairstyles in the 90s and were perfect for anyone who wanted to have one more thing to regret about their High School
The 90s Are Back In a big way it's proven by Daisy Evans baby born with completely natural frosted tips
Daisy's parents think
It's adorable
But it's definitely going to be overshadowed 20 years from now when Daisy gives birth to a baby that
Comes out of the womb
Vaping
How did Maz doing AR quiz
Bi-Rite 10 more points in a total of
Well. All right then how many atom need to win
Port at I-5
All right
I'm you ready to do this
This is for the game
On Monday a federal judge rejected house Democrats lawsuit against Trump over blank
Military
The Bono border wall
Well this week marks the 30th Anniversary the pro-democracy
Protest
At Tiananmen Square in
China
Beijing on Friday the 2019 Women's World Cup
Kicked off in
Blank
Acotar no in France
The men's World got actress Jenny slate
With announces akumetsu
Speaker for cuttyhunk
Middle School wish list
Speak to a room filled with black
At 1
Student gets exactly one single graduating 8th grader
On Monday blank came to an end after 32
New game
Yes ride sharing app Uber announced they be offering blancride
JFK Airport starting next month
Unicycle
Helicopter despite the best efforts of locksmith
Blacksmith
A 100 year-old safe on display at a museum
Canada remain locked until blank
Until a visitor came along
And opened it
That's exactly right
It's on the first try
30 years of despite their best efforts and no one's been able to open it
That was the case until a tourist came in and guessed the right combination
On the very first try sadly the only thing the mystery safe was it
A few papers in a pile of dust
The museum has invited the man
The tries lock in the bank vault
Next door to see if there's anything more exciting
Bill
Did Adam do well enough
He did very very well for write 8 more points
Total 212
Which means
We're going to ask us to predict now that we know the truth about Bigfoot what will be the next surprising FBI file
Thanks to stock and Ledger restaurant here in Chicago for filling our bellies
With joy and Falafel wait wait don't tell me
NPR WBEZ Chicago in association with urgent haircut Productions
Benevolent overlord
Route manager is Tyler Green Assisted by Simon Tran
Returns are Pnina Beatty and Leila Francis
BJ leiderman composer Theme by program is produced by Jennifer Mills miles dornbos and Lillian
Are designated Survivor
Is Peter Quinn
A business and office manager
A production coordinator
What file will the FBI reveal neck
They will reveal dito Sama Bin Laden still alive and working at a coffee shop
Brooklyn making Osama bin Laden
Ida Rodriguez
The FBI's will be releasing a file
Stating that
The FBI actually
We stand for
Full blooded Italians
Adam Burke
Signs of aliens will be overjoyed when they released nothing
Files
But the a file
Because that town alphabetized
Well if any of that happens we're going to ask you about it son wait wait don't tell me
Working today
This
Is NPR