Support for this podcast
In the following message
Come from Duckhorn
Napa California
Duckhorn Vineyards has been
Crafting classic Napa Valley Wine
Ants with a sense of place
For more than 40 years
Learn more
Or at Duckhorn. Com
NPR
From NPR WBEZ Chicago
This is wait wait don't tell me
NPR news
Filling in for the legend
Barry Bill Kurtis
I'm one of the legendary boy
Voices of the NPR credit
Keoke Inc
And here's your host
The Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown Chicago
Peter Sagal
Did Mike D'Antoni the coach of the
The Houston Rockets of the NBA the first as you have figured out Bill Curtis
Is taking the week off
Off to maintain that
Baso4 fundo he has to rest his voice once
Every 40 years
We are delighted to welcome schielke I Anson to the judge and scorekeeper
See you may know him as
The guy
Who voices NPR's funding credit
Like so
Support for NP
NPR station and support for Peter Sagal
Will styes come
Pick up how we do things here pretty quickly if you give us a call the number
Is 1 AAA wait wait that's 18889
Let's welcome our first listener contestant High you are on wait wait don't tell me
I am Caitlyn from Birmingham Alabama
Hello Caitlin how are you
I'm quite well a
Thank you I'm glad
You don't sound like you're from Birmingham
Am I right
Yeah I know I'm from
Pensacola Florida Pensacola and how did you arrive in Burma
Which is meant for
Yeah
Long journey let's just say
About 8 years ago just
Popped up
Were you kidnapped
Birmingham
Will Kaitlyn welcome
2 hours
Door panel this week
First up
It's a feature reporter for the style section of the Washington
Composed it's Roxanne Roberts
Happy New Year and that's just the host of the confessional podcast
Tbtl
And the public radio variety show Livewire which will be at the triple door in Seattle in February
And the comedian performing in Houston Texas next
Tweak January 18th at the Wortham Center
The host of the new weekly podcast nobody lives
DePaula found
Is Paula Poundstone
Did the show you are going to start us off our first show of 2019
Started
But this time we're calling it
Who is chiaki
This time
Dancing feeling if your bill is going to read your three quotations
The week's news
If you can correctly identify or explain just two of them you would our prize
Any voice from our show you might choose on your voicemail you ready to go
Your first code is of course from
The presidents
Of these United
I may do it
Probably I will do
I would almost say
Definitely
The president
What's expressing concern unshakeable resolve
To declare a national emergency
Then say so he can do what
Oh I don't know me
Maybe Build That Wall Build That Wall Build That Wall week
President Trump hinted he might
Declare a National Emergency to get the money for his wall Maybe
He's not sure
The whole point of an emergency is that it
It's fairly obvious you need to do something about it
Nobody stands in front of a house on fire
For 3 days
Might be an emergency I don't know it looks pretty Bernie
Basically Trump declares an emergency only when he wants something and he can't get it any
The other way like oh no the White House kitchen is out of coke emergency
Oh no my wife turned 30
Speaking of the White House kitchen being out of Coke
Did you see how much you weigh
What's sniffing during the
The TV address
But not nearly as weird
As Chuck Schumer and Nancy Pelosi seems to be
Giving the
Respond to two of them
Crammed together behind a single podium
First Pelosi spoke and Schumer just
Paradise silence
Unblinking
Is it the muscles
Controlling his eyelids were also furloughed from the governor
Stood there and stared at us looking like the owners of
That old Motel where all the guests
Keep disappearing but if you seen their wax museum down in the basement
This was
Jose
Shout out a very nuanced
Shout out to American Gods
Okay the only thing that was missing was the Pitchfork it had a very we're not mad at you were just a
Appointed in you
Is Caitlyn your next quote is a bit of a
Understand
About somebody who announced that he was about to become a single
He's a cat
He's not a loser that was famous Matchmaker Patti strangers assessment
The newest eligible bachelor in the scene what rich man announced his
Divorce this week
Oh
That shiny bald men
Favorite
I don't know what has to do with it
Jeff Bezos the richest man in the world and splitting from his wife can you imagine how obnoxious you have
Have to be
When somebody doesn't want to be married to you even though you're worth more than a hundred billion dollars
Statement mr. and mrs. Bezos
Say their parting is friends and that even if they knew that it would end in divorce
25 years ago they would
Have gotten married
That's very sweet
What is Jeff Bezos
Of course credits his wife for all the Lovin
Unsupportive received over the decades
Mackenzie Bezos
Ended up with 60
85 billion dollars
Yeah which means she can go to Whole Foods
Twice doesn't she get some kind of discount
Then the National Enquirer unveiled
This investigative report they said they've been following bases around for 6 months
They found out he
He was having an affair
They even found love notes
He wrote to his
Hey since you looked at my face
You might also like
What's in my pants
Beyond Amazon
I actually did reveal the actual text
She allegedly sent
Metrocenter a little
Little odd jerky can you read a couple these are all real
I want to smell you
I will show you what
My body
And my lips
And my eyes
Very soon
I love you
Alivegirl
Girl that really gets you really. You can see why he
So entranced by her she's alive
No
They have that
Email now it's
This horrible
Where
Get an email and then it gives
Picture or you know I'll see you then. I love you alive girl
Yeah what if he weird about
I mean I don't know what will happen with his
Current time
His girlfriend if he ends up dating as the rich
Would that be okay
You know I mean
How do you dating a
Otherwise
I mean how do you make sure the people are just interested in you and not in your billions of
Split the bill
Yell at somebody who lives on it
Public radio salary
People liking you
For you is overrated bring it on people who are wanted to come after me for my bill yet
Alright Caitlin your last
Quote
Is from the world of literature a revelation we heard about just this
We need to talk
About wizard
That was a headline
Does a headline from Jezebel commenting on the recent and shocking revelation
In about what literary universe
Oh wizard
Oh Harry Potter Harry Potter
This was all the rage
Literary characters JK Rowling the author of the Harry Potter novels
Occasionally writes more about them
Various for
Including this website
Pottermore
And she wrote this
Sam mentioned in passing
It's in the way that you
That it wasn't until modern times that the Wizards in her books in
Installed bath
Bathrooms at Hogwarts
Because you
Quote hitherto
They simply relieved themselves wherever they stood
And vanished
The evidence
Fun quotes
Gazelle Dumbledore got his
Miss rolling can be sliced you might have meant this as a joke
The people went nuts especially parents with bought their kids wizard costumes that were dry clean only
That's really gross idea committed
Is privately
Hermione just
Class yeah
There's a certain sort of
Too much information quality
Pizza did anybody needs
To know
You know because there's this
Insatiable hunger for
Grimoire wizard
Many ways on.
Damai Beach
She's like you want more information
Here you go
I was just thinking though
The wizard
Would never have to suffer empathy
Because because if we don't ask that question she'll never answer it that's why
Do I have to do it why is that
Paula
Magic wands
Yes yes
Liftopia jokey how did Kaitlyn do on Ark
Wingardium Leviosa making her a winner
Right now panel it is time for you to answer some questions about this week
Snooze
Paula members of a once prestigious organization Erica
Complaining that the group has become nothing more than a place
Hard-drinking
And partying what is this
The White House Down
I'll give you head
When these people are boozing it up
It's a literal Genius Bar
Mensa Mensa yeah
Insects really Mendoza
Smart people get together and drink that's what they're doing they're going for a header going to party like it's the square root of 3000900
Said one member quoted in the Wall Street Journal these are wonderful loving playful people
They also drink more than anyone I've ever seen
That's right these nerds are out here to raise the roof and I know exactly how many foot pounds of force will be required to do it
We're going to Dubai in our Bluff The Listener game call 1aaa wait wait to play will be back in a minute with me
Stream NPR
Support also
Comes from the all-new
3 row Subaru ascent
There's room for a 7 or 8 passenger
And a choice of 2nd row captains
Chairs or bench seat
The ascent also features standard symmetrical all-wheel drive
Brad compher
Pantanal weather
The Subaru ascent
Love Is Now bigger than ever
Learn more
Borat subaru.com
Start Shepard
Thought you knew her
But then one day
A stranger called at home
The phone
In my ear and he's saying your father's a crook
Did you know that
The story of a Fallen Hero
And the mysterious
Obsession that drove in four decades
This week
On hidden brain
From NPR and WBEZ Chicago
This is wait wait don't tell me
NPR news
Filling in for Bill Kurtis imco key Inc
One of the voices of
NPR credits
And the voice of all your
NPR fan
We're playing this week
Meet with Paula Poundstone
Luke Burbank
And Roxanne Roberts
And here again is your hose
At the Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown Chicago
Peter Sagal
Two-player game in the air
Wait wait don't tell me
Yes I am
URL
This is Dean Winchester I'm in Mount Pleasant Michigan
Central Michigan University in
No I'm retired but I take classes
Each year
Oh that's right what are two things you interested in learning
Anything that looks interesting and I don't have to do the work and I don't get paid for it so it's
Gene welcome to the show you going to play our game but you must try to tell truth
Fanfiction Chucky what is
Jeans
Topic you've got Dubai problems
The city of Dubai gets its name from the fact that no matter how expensive something is people there Dubai
Also in Dubai that joke would be punishable by Death
Anyway
All that comes with the price our panels are going to tell you that
Three stories
The problem
Specific
To Dubai
Pick the one who's telling the truth even when our prize the wait waiter of your choice on your voicemail
Ready to play
First let's hear from
Luke Burbank
Verma is a 29 year old social media celebrity
I'm Dubai who got very rich
And Famous
Just for being
Well rich and famous
He was one of his nation's first reality tea
Three stars
Think of him sort of as
Kim Kardashian
Of the United Arab Emirates
So you might say it somewhat ironic that it was a social
Media-related
Stunts that landed in the hospital this
Has the khaleej times
Reporting Verma was just
The latest High earner
In the UAE
To injure himself taking part
And something called
The Scrooge McDuck challenge
We're very rich people
Let's be honest very rich guys
Women would never be stupid enough
Do this
Liquidate their entire Fortune
Into gold silver and diamond
Incident Philly swimming pool with the treasure and then
Dive In
The problem as Verma at
A surprisingly High number of other dudes
Dubai have learned
Do personal experience
Is that Scrooge McDuck
Is a cartoon character
And in the real world
Where we all live
The treasurer's though individually small come together to form an impenetrable solid Mass
A mass that broke both of his wrists
Kaze
Compression fracture of his
Spine ant lift
With no actual memory of
The event
Last thing I remember I was at the bank
He told the newspaper
And then I was waking up in a hospital bed and they were telling me I might
The vision in my right eye because
I got in a Doubloon stuck
Doctors do expect his memory to return eventually in his wrist
And back should heal
Just fine to
Division damage though in his eye that might be
The permanent
Jumping Vernon
In-stride worst case scenario he said from
Women's hospital room
I'll have to wear a monocle
Just like my new hero
Scrooge McDuck
The Scrooge McDuck challenge in which dumb young rich guy jumps into all this
Money and badly hurt himself you next story of the Dubai don't
Roxanne Roberts
There's gold in them thar
Chicken nuggets
Yes behold the gold rush in the United Arab
Emirates
Where there's a race
See who can put the most
Edible gold on the
The most unlikely
Free food
Gold flake
Pizza
French fries
Cocktails and course
Desserts including red velvet
Cake with gold frosting
And ice
I'm wrapped in
Karat gold
Gold Leaf
The gold dust
Can add to the
Pace Bus
Looks great on in
Instagram
Not so much in person though
Quote I had gold all over my teeth
In mouth
Roger alien Prado
Who told the wall
Trying at 7
$25
Gold cap
Chino
That hasn't stopped
People from ordering $45 gold
Chicken nuggets
$99
Gold hamburgers and for $340
A 14 oz
Sirloin steak wrapped
In gold
Explain the general manager of the Four Seasons quote
Absolutely
Excessive
An absolute
Wii Dubai
Too much gold in the food
Your last
The story of Mo Money Mo Problems
Comes
From Paula Patton
Many residents of Dubai struggle to find uses
For their money
And more importantly
Uses for their money to highlight the fact that they have so much
The peacock company is there to help
Peacocks
Art to the
Peacock company
What elect
Scooters are
To the bird company
Like the scooter users
Peacock users
Can use the peacock app
Define
Where there was a peacock to rent
Nearest
And the company provides
Thousands or they may just trip over 1
On the street
And use their app to pay to rent
The peacocks are Tethered to docks that have been
Install drop
City of the
Overly indulged
Why weren't a peacock
Because you can't
And people do a peacock Fanning its glorious
Tail feathers
Is like the user Fanning out of fat
Cash
It's a status symbol that
Peacocks are also noisy
The burden is most notice
Isabel in elevator
Dubai price itself in high-rise building
And peacock renters have discovered that the birds are afraid of heights
Peacocks fly but they don't go very high on an elevator they pass out at about the
Floor
But not before they lose their lunch at the 5th
All right one of these is a problem
The people I've encountered of the ultra-rich
Golf
City of
Dubai
Is it
From
Luke Burbank
Scrooge McDuck challenge in which of these one
Wealthy idiot
Injured himself by converting all his
Money into cash and trying to
The dive into
From Roxanne Roberts
What's the story of how it's impossible to find anything to eat in Dubai that isn't covered with gold for prom
Paula Poundstone
The rent a peacock app
Which has resulted
In just too many peacocks
In the city of Dubai which of these is the real story of
Troubles in that paradise
I think because of
Stupid
I'm going to go with
Number to the gold
Recovered
Food
Too much
Food covered in too much gold he doesn't Roxanne story cuz it sounds stupid enough to do
Well we spoke to somebody who reported on this
Desposar phenom
Boston have any real Chase restaurants I will
Servu
Gold flakes
Instead of Parmesan cheese and gold
That was Michael am in the walkthrough journals Deputy bureau chief for the Middle East and North Africa who wrote the story about
Gold
Taking over the dining
And scene in Dubai congratulation
Jean you got it right
You earned a point for Roxanne Roberts
You want a prize the voice of your choice in your voicemail congratulate thank you so much for playing yesterday
And now the game we're successful people find out what it's like to not know why you're even
Play It's called
Not my job
Mike D'Antoni
Is a former NBA player
Star in the Italian basketball league
16 years a head coach
In the NBA with the Phoenix Suns LA Lakers New York Knicks and now
The Houston Rock
He was the 2017
NBA coach of the year
Enjoy this now
Coach Mike welcome to wait wait don't tell me
Rockets doing are you satisfied with how the season is going
We're doing better now we had a rough start a lot of injuries and
Problems but another ship is going pretty good right now
I'm glad to hear it. Are you a guy who
Feels
The progress of your team emotionally do you get upset when it
It's going poorly do you feel
Dilated when it's going well
Yeah but you know I think we're all in this business
Especially because we want to
Competing
Do you get emotionally invested in the players and the fans and
I've been in the fetal position lifetimes on the couch
Not an adventure that would be funny if they Pander to you there
What's it like getting to watch James Harden play every night
Special
The real deal
You know he's better than what most people think he's about something
For people who don't know James Harden is known for his extraordinary offensive play and also for his amazing beard
Yeah
Have you ever had to talk to me about the beard like
Do nobody can see your uniform number
You need to
No most diamonds like you know you got to get there or you got
Part of your duties as head coach
He seemed pretty serious are you allowed
Tease him about his beard
Very carefully
When did you
Figure out that you could be a coach
I'm 39 years old now retire from playing and I'm looking around and going now watch
It's like
United really good teams in Europe I got lucky and like anybody else is just
Speed at the right spot at the right time and
When back and started coaching the NBA
Psychologic
Nicole
Techniques
Did you use
That would mean that I would have to be and
The players have to be smart so we're not messenger
Tempo Style
Do players like playing
Sing for you because of that or is it
Exhaust
Diet
There's been something to have enlightened obviously I've been to different cities
I've been fired a few times so
Don't like that
No no
Don't like being fired then like when you get four
No
They get me fired
Coaching
Incredibly well-paid
Incredibly talented athlete
Who have been at the
The Pinnacle of their sport
For probably retire
Everybody in the NBA
For the Superstar
How do you
Handle people like that
Who are the stars of The League
Well
There's a lot of groveling and begging and
A bleeding exam that you need to have some
Psychological
James Harden say or Chris Paul both Superstar
If you want them to do something they're not doing or you want them to do something better or differ
How do you do that
We work together and get my experience in there and we
We're very athletic base now so a lot of it is
Data
Driven where they can see that it makes sense
Give me an example of a
What time were the problem
Is soft by data
Will you have a player that shoots primarily two-point shots and says 3-point shot so I'm not going to
Get too technical but
I can show him some the data that
Shooting that shot there is not his
Effective shooting
3 points you have to change your text
They don't know that
3 points is 20 years for the
Wait a minute
I Monday at YMCA men's
Recalled that
Dusklight shards you probably heard of us
I didn't name the team
We have Scouts their most tonight we lost a game this week by 49 points
Do you have any
Advice
It's for us is how to be a better
Start score more points with three points more than two points
The biggest cliche of every sports movie
Any of us have ever seen
It is the half
Halftime motivation
Like I said they're giving me some space
Well coach it is
It's great to have you with us we've invited here today
To play our game and we call it
Mike D'Antoni
Meet Mike
Dan
Tony since your name is built out of three first names
But like a Transformer
Mike D'Antoni
We thought we'd ask you one question each about a mic
Add an
Panettone
You get to write it down in mic
Could you Tony and Dan
Could be a Tony in Mike
You do any of those you win our price one of our listeners the voice of their choice
From art show
Chucky who is coach Mike D'Antoni playing for
Jim Hogan of June
Are you ready
First
Michael Jordan you may have heard of him he remains the world's most famous Mike
He was so famous during his heyday
That you can find which of these
He's a a shrine to him in the
The Palace of North Korean dictator Kim Jong ill
Be a mega church in Lebanon the believe
He was the man
Messiah
Or see the be like Mike
Diet book which recommended you consume only Gatorade and
Expensive cigar
I'm probably going with this run in North Korea just cuz
Dennis Rodman stop. Problem
You're right you're exactly right
That guy Kim Jones
Got his love of the great Bulls teams of yesteryear from his father Kim Jong-il so Kim Jong-il
The Dictator
Had a shrine to Michael Jordan
All right makeup is
Dan one of the most famous dance in American history was vice president
Dan Quayle
He's remembered now mostly for misspelling the word potato and for not
Being Jack Kennedy butt
He also said many memorable things during his time
In the public light
Including which of these
Hey
Quote
I have made good judgments in the past
I have made good judgements in the future
Bee quote I believe we are on an irreversible trend
Towards more freedom and democracy
But that could change
Orsi
Quote the Holocaust was an obscene. In our nation's history
Not our nation
But in World War I mean
We all lived in this Century I didn't live in this entry
Centuries history
Unquote
Do you have D All the Above
He said all of those guns
The last stop is Tony
So one of the most famous Tony's of course is Tony the Tiger
Tony the Tiger the cereal spokes animal has fans around the world
Then get a little out of hand those such as when which of these actually happened today
A group of people started raising money to save tigers
From they said being harvested to make Frost
Did flakes
Big Tony the Tiger went on Twitter to ask
Furries
Please stop sending him anthropomorphic erotica
Or see somebody invented a language called
Tony talk
Which is English but you girl every are
Samuel McBee
You're exactly right
A couple years ago tweeting inappropriate things that Tony the Tiger so he tweeted quote
I'm all for showing your stripes feathers Etc
But let's keep things great and family-friendly if you could
Cubs could be watching
How to cook Mike D'Antoni do it on quiz
Nothing but Nets
Might got three out of three graduation
Houston Rockets coach Mike thank you so much for joining us
Bicycle inner listener Limerick challenge game
I want you to wait wait wait
To join us on the air
We will be back in a minute with more wait wait don't tell me
From NPR
Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Park
The newest Resort
In the center of the Las Vegas Strip
It's where Lady Gaga Bruno Mars and Aerosmith
Bring down the house
In the intimacy of the park
It's where La Chef Roy Choi
Mashes up Korean flavors at his new restaurant best
Be inspired
At Eataly mark
Enjoy your spin on
Fine dining
Home address
And let it all go
At on the record
Biggest his first speaker
Park MGM
Intimate moments
Big spear
Hey it's guy raazi
Here and on the next how I built this
How to win
With no background
Fitness
Set up some stationary bikes
Dim the lights
Did the music
Is it a cult following
In a multimillion-dollar business
Call SoulCycle
You can find how I built this
Whatever you listen
From NPR
And WBEZ Chicago
This is wait wait don't tell me
Play NPR news
Filling in for Bill Carter
I'm going
One of the voices
NPR credit
And if you haven't guessed by now
Contractually obligated
We're playing this week with Paula Poundstone
Roxanne Roberts and Luke bourbon
Here again is your host at the
The Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown Chicago Peter Sagal
The best actor Golden Globe to Ramey Malik
Qunar listener Limerick challenge game
If you like to play give us a call in one AAA way to that's one 889-2489
Do for right now panels more questions
Just for you from the week's news
Paula the big technology shows
CES is on right now in one of the gadgets make
Splashes
New 18
$100 treadmill from
Korean company
Specifically design
To help you lose weight
Cats exam
Did you know that
No
Why did you guess
Because I just thinking of a need that
Little cat
Can you start by setting a weight Target
If your cat but don't go crazy
You could stand to lose
10 pounds
That would make your cat this
Disappear
Then the treadmill plays messages like here kitty kitty
And when you become physically fit
Humans will become your prey
So fat
That she couldn't have done a treadmill
Because
Just walking across the floor She was like
Because she was so fat that it hurt her leg
Oyster cell
What was I to do I mean
Michael run over here
I would absolutely watch a t
TV network that's only
Only show was cats on treadmills
Roxanne this week somebody got in trouble for accidentally calling 911
Where was this person
And I'm going to
I need a hint
Hi my emergency is that I'm
Like 8 miles above the Earth
An astronaut astronaut yes
Space station is where they were
Is this a butt dial
So apparently just like in your office
To dial out at the space station you have to dial 9
Wow and one particular astronaut
Dial 9 and then hit one and one
Where is the emergency
And it's like
I'm in space
No one can hear me
Scream
That where you spray Sports
I love the idea that there's a
Phone
On there like does it have a super long cord so that the the teenage astronaut can go around into a different
Part of the space station and talk to her friends
Roxanne this week one woman in
In China woke up with a very rare condition
She can no longer hear what
Not quite know
For many women wouldn't be so much a hearing problem as a hearing
Absolution
She couldn't hear her
You couldn't hear any men at all
Identified in the news reported missing
Christian went to bed nauseous she woke up feeling much better
With a calm stomach
And a complete inability to hear her boyfriend
Speak
Chandler to the hospital and met with a specialist
Explain quote she was able to hear me when I spoke to her
Good money young male page
Walked in she couldn't hear him at all
That's right
The doctor was a woman
Chad apparently lost the ability to hear low frequency
Ketone so she won't be able to hear guys or they're sick beats
She recovers
We hope she enjoys her recovery we have no idea I was going to go through life
Stabbing man telling her how Bitcoin works
Wait
Without having been tell her how everything works exactly
Coming up with lighting fill in the blank the first is the game where you have to listen for the rhyme if you like to play on air call and leave a message
Did it one Triple Eight wait wait
That's one 889-2489
24 orkla
Alexa contact us
On our website wait wait. Npr.org
Do you can find out about attending our weekly live shows right here at the Chase Bank Auditorium in
Chicago upcoming shows in Savannah Georgia on February 7th
In San Diego
California
How you run wait wait don't tell me
Time in San Diego California
What you been up to I just said we're just going there in a couple months what do we know about San Diego
I don't know I always
Hang out at the drop zone
You hang out at the drop zone
Yeah I work there and how much got ever
Okoye to skydive
Really yeah
Good enough in here I am
Yeah
You just professionally but
4fun
You don't want a hobbyist parachute
Right here is making his debut
As a professional Limerick reciter he's going to recite few 3 limericks but he's not going to say
The last word that's up to you East limerick
What about tonight
Fox News
Complete the lyrics
Two times at a 3 you win our prize ready to play
Alright here's your first
My helmet I don't really like
Lycra spandex
Foot clips
Psyched
And my soul is a flame
For that ultralight
Brain
I'm deeply in love
With my
Fight very good research out here treats that cyclists have an emotional can
Into their bikes
Forming bonds akin to that of a
Spouse or child
They give their bikes names they nurture them
They kiss them I mean
They fix the fake fix
Their bicycles
Researchers say the bond is formed through shared experiences the bike is such
The huge part of your daily routine you start to think of it as a friend
Instead of a means of chance
Application
In the strange friendship hey I'm going to Bar do you mind standing outside
For 7 hours
I had a
Bee sweet Thunder
That was a hand-me-down that I think I had caught feelings for
12 / 13
I can see someone
A guy having a
Feelings for a huffy
Sweet Thunder
It was it was a hand-me-down from what like what
Some extended family member
It was pink
Have flowers on it was not technically at that time
Big guys bike
Yeah
Thunder
Here is your next
Limerick
French diners find it
Crude
To have bare breasts
And thighs
With their food
It was only natural
But the meal
Didn't sell
So they'll
No longer eat
In the
Nude
The Peruvian restaurant is closing its doors after launching is Francis
Premier nude restaurant 27
They just couldn't get enough butts in the seats
In addition to its lack of customers the restaurant I couldn't keep up with its costly here not expenses all the cooks needed to
Did you intentionally say hair nut
At no point in the experience
Does this sound like
A good idea
Just the injuries from
Gravy
Yeah it's dangerous
Boy when you drop your knife your jump back
Alright here is your last limerick
The Bluefin came in on a schooner
Brought down by a gold
Tooth harpoon
It's a rare taste
Is why the
The price is so high
I've been 3 million
Bucks on a
4.4 million-dollar tuna
What's the difference between a man in Japan
113 pound bluefin tuna for we thought $3000000
People wondered
What the man was planning to do with the tuna got their answer
When he bought five cases of cream of mushroom soup
Tuna hotdish baby
Chucky how did Doug do
Doug at 3 out of
If I don't have to pay for beer can I give a shout out to her and everybody at her work
Apparently everybody in her shoplift
The Raytheon serum shop in Bagram Afghanistan
Background will go ahead say it loud everybody
It's all right hey all of you guys Contracting over there at the floral first afsbn in Bagram Afghanistan
Hey how's it going
Thank you so much for playing
Thank you
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Sagemcom from Park Inn
The newest Resort
In the center of the Las Vegas
It's where Lady Gaga Bruno Mars and Aerosmith
Bring down the house
In the intimacy of
The Park theater
It's where La Chef Roy Choi
Mashes up Korean flavors at his new restaurant best
Be inspired
Eataly Market
Enjoy your spin on
Fine dining
And let it all go
At on the record
Biggest hits
First speaker
Park MGM
Intimate moments
Big Xperia
This message comes from NPR Spa
Goldman Sachs
Four insights from leading thinkers at Goldman Sachs
Under state of Mark
It's Industries and the globally
Listen to their podcast
Exchanges at Goldman
You'll hear a range of topics
From the tech IPO landscape
Two China's economic Outlook
And much
That's exchanges at Goldman Sachs
Available on Apple podcast
Spotify
Stitcher SoundCloud and Google Play
Play and it gs.com pot
Now it's time for a final game lightning fill in the blank each of our players
Will have 60 seconds in which to answer as many fill-in-the-blank questions
Does he or she can
Each correct answer is not worth
Chucky can you give us the
Roxanne has four
Luke and Paula are tied with
All right
We flip the coin Paul has elected to go second
Cancel look that means you are up first
The clock will start from the beginning first question fill in the blank this week the US
Resumed its ongoing trade talks
Blank
China this week Deputy attorney general blank said he would
Wood step down after
Mueller finishes his investigation
Hot rod Rosenstein police in Ontario have issued a statement about the proper use of 911
After a woman called the police
To report
Call
To report that her
Timbits 4
From Tim Hortons
Were cold
No she called
That you did not like
Her daughter's friend
This week this week more than 1 million felons in blank regained their rights
To vote Florida right on Monday blank beat Alabama to claim their second
Can college football title
3 years
Write a woman in Virginia was surprised
The discovery that the Christmas tree she bought also came with blank
Inside of it
A war on Christmas
No
The Christmas tree came with thousands of praying mantises
Bow Wow
When Malik Rose brought her tree home she didn't notice the walnut-sized brown a case under one of the branches
Whoever she didn't notice
A few hours later when you're living room was swarmed with dozens and dozens of baby praying mantises
Finally someone is putting the Christ look at all those praying mantises
She's rescue the mantises and is feeding them rather than
Doing the obvious thing leaving the house in never ever returning and that's why
Chucky I usually do a lot better I just want you to know
He got four right for 8 more point
A total of 10
And he's
In the lead
Alright Paula. Next fill in the blank after undergoing surgery for lung cancer
Blank missed oral arguments
For the first time
Something named spree
Ruth Bader Ginsburg
During his trip to China it was reported that blank had reaffirmed
What is commitment
To denuclearization
Kim Jong-un
Right on Sunday French president Emmanuel macron accused the show called blank protest
Pictures of using a
Extreme violence
Oh yeah this weekend Uber driver went viral after he was filmed trash-talking the LA Chargers by his passenger
Who was blank
One of the elect
Yes the running back in fact according to a new set of us play Commission
Spiked in 2018
Yes
Following damage to trees caused by visitors blank National Park in California
Anise plant
Closed for the duration
The shutdown
Yes please in Australia responding to reports of a man in the house
Screaming why won't you die over and over again
Broke down the door and found blank
Well something's still alive
Profound
He found a man trying to kill a spider
According to police reports several passers-by called nine-one-one after hearing threats being shouted from a nearby house
Worried that someone might be in danger officers were dispatched to the neighborhood with their Sirens blaring
Only to find a man trying and failing to
To kill a spider
The man is now resting comfortably at home
And assure the one that size 8 case looking thing and it's Christmas tree
There's nothing to worry about
Chucky how did
Pollock at 6 right
412 more
A total of 14
Impala is now
And how many vendors Roxanne need to win which you being new here you might not
Not know she will inevitably do rocks and needs
5 to Thai
+ 6
She's going to win here we go Roxanne
This is for the game fill in the blank during an interview with 60 Minutes Democratic representative blank said quote there is no question
The present
Is racist
Mispronounce your name Alexandra
Yes you got it all most romantic ocasio-cortez
This week military official said they would capture the US
ESPN fighting
4 blank
Interia
Price Is Right on Wednesday President Trump said that he had ordered FEMA
Stop sending Aid
Three areas of California affected by blanks
The Wildfire has filed suit against search giant blank
Drawstring pants
Executive
Accused of sex
Sexual harassment
Google drive this week Gleason Ohio managed to find a man's drug stash
Despite the fact that he hated in blank
PlayStation
He hid his drugs in a box labeled not
Drugs on Tuesday the chairman of departments are blank and
Announce the new 5 billion dollar bid
To save the retailer
Siri Bohemian Rhapsody in green book
What is the Prize winners
Of the 76th annual blank awards called Rider this weekend woman in Oklahoma who shot a deer offseason got busted
When she blank
Was this the person that
Confessed that there was a woman there
Shot and then they
I confess that the dating app and
And the guy was a
It was a game where
Okay because she bragged about it on a dating app to a game warden
Has anyone skilled in the art of online dating knows
The best possible pickup line is Hi how are you I just shot at
Deer
Exactly what this Oklahoma woman texted her new match
Completely unaware that he was a game warden and it work
He was interested
He wrote back asking flirty follow-up questions like
Did you use a bow and
Do you have a DMP permit for Zone 36 or 34
Did Roxanne enough to win
Just as you predict
At 7 right
So with 18 points
Roxanne is this week
Champion
We're going to ask us now that we know far too much about Harry Potter what will be the next
Next shocking Revelation from the world of literature but first let me tell you
Special thanks this week to Farmhouse Tavern in
In Chicago for feeding us again
Carrot spectacular
Wait wait don't tell me on NPR WBEZ Chicago and Association
Urgent haircut Productions Doug Berman benevolent overlord
Writer the mixer public address announcer
Paul Friedman
Warehouse managers Tyler green
List of assignment random
A brand new engines just out of the box
Alec McCowen and Rachel Clapper
I went through is Beth Novey
BJ leiderman composer has produced
By Jennifer Mills
Miles dornbos and Lily and King are Open Bracket Credit close bracket is
Peter Gwen
Technical director similar to white our business and ops manager is calling Miller
Is the executive producer of wait wait don't tell me
Is Mike what is that smell
Danforth
Val Peta what will be the next big Revelation from the world
Luke Burbank
Holden Caulfield father secretly funneled millions of untaxed dollars to him over the years
Roxanne Roberts
Draegast
Speed was never great or even
Good his wife says he was kind of mess
Paula Poundstone
Tom Sawyer and huckleberry
Didn't use a rap that use Ski-Doos
Freeze dried food on the island
And if any of that happens panel will ask you about it on wait wait
Don't tell me
Daniel Fairbanks
Next week
This
Is NPR