Support for this podcast
Send the following message
Did come from VRBO
Struggling to find a purpose
Vacation home
VRBO does the hard work for you
Matching you to the perfect place to stay
Every time
Download VRBO
Go in the App Store
Let Virgo find a home
That matches
From NPR and wbez chicago
Chicago this is
Wait wait don't tell me it again
NPR news quiz
Forget about Bill Barr
Come to the bar with me Bill Kurtis
Fox Theater in St Louis
A few weeks ago we along with the rest of the internet
Learned how you people hear slice your big
Horizontally like normal people
Or Jews
But in Low Places
Like a little round loaf of bread
We're here because we wanted to come and ask you
In person what
The hell is wrong with you
Later on we're going to be talking to one of the greatest St Louis Cardinals
To ever play The Wizard of Oz him
I'm self Aziz
Smith is going to be right here if you want to see if you can handle our slowly
Roller so give us a call the number is 10008 wait wait
That's one 888-9248
It's time to welcome our first listen to contested how you are wrong wait wait don't
Hey there
Is Courtney Moran calling from New Orleans
Play Courtney how are you I love you I learned you were lucky to live there what are you doing
I am an event manager at a
Historic venue here now I know is that a challenge
Because I know
People from New Orleans really like to party a lot
It can definitely be a challenge
It's the end of prom
Season right now which I'm happy about
Because hundreds of children in New Orleans
Her party
It's not as much fun
I think it would be I don't think it would be fun at all
Would you open container laws and all welcome to the show Courtney
Let me introduce you to our panel first of the comedian whose debut Comedy album Babylon Ball Z is screaming everywhere
You can see him June 24th at the moth Grand Slam in
Chicago it's Brian Babylon
Max the syndicated advice columnist behind ask
Amy and the author of
Strangers 10
To tell me
Amy Dickinson
Hey Courtney
And he's a man for all seasons most especially
Springetts Tom bodett
Hello Courtney Courtney welcome to the show
Who's Bill this time Bill Kurtis
This is going to be two three quotation
If you can correctly identify
Explain two of them you'll win our prize any voice from
My shelf you might choose in your
Ready to play
Yes all right
Your first quote took up most of the
The space in a birth announcement
Archie Harrison mountbatten-windsor
That was the name that is longer right now than the person it was given to who is it
The new royal baby royal baby
Yes according to the
United Nations
1 million
Different species of life on Earth are going extinct
But at least
We were able to
To save
The rare
Useless baby Royal
This is the first child of Prince Harry and his
His wife Meghan
The baby is
You sure you want to know
7th in line to
Did the throne after
His grandfather
Is Uncle an
And his cousins
So he'd better get to killing it
Now
Yeah that was Game of Thrones he's like next
So I'm nearly now you nearly next yeah
Really better than American term that's like being the the secretary of agriculture
So probably not going to happen but you're allowed to dream about
Have a question about his name a couple of questions.
His name is really Archie not Archibald
Yeah I was hoping a lot of people
A lot of people say we're too obsessed
For the Royals
Ward and not have to be obsessed with
The Royals
But
Come on
It's just so exciting
After the last couple of years
To see a
RipStik
Successfully exit
Sumter
Wow
Currently
You know this is Megan's first baby sometimes that's hard it was
The challenging labor
But interested Me by tradition the OBGYN who finally pulled the baby out is now the right
King of England
Well isn't I mean I don't know
British history
Thoroughly but
Is this the first
Royals with American
Colonial
Apparently there was somebody way back when but certainly is
What is the first one
Yeah yeah
I don't know why I saw a CNN did some
Horrible tagline
How old will you be black on black
How do you
How do you raise a British black purse
All African-American I thought I died
I don't know if you saw the video of Prince Harry
Coming out he was so excited
He said the baby was close to amazing
His wife was quote amazing
And the birth itself was quote wait for it amazing
But you know what he also said something that men I've never heard a man say
He said I don't know how women do it
I have never heard a man say that I'm sure men
What kind of man do you hang around
I thought that was so endearing he was so delighted with everything he was frankly
Hey just so happy f
Happiest day they didn't have feathers
Alright your next quote is new
Gingrich
Speaking on Fox News
You didn't lose a billion dollars
He had a billion dollars
Mr. Gingrich was explaining why
Despite news of this
Astounding laws who's still really is a wonderful business
It could be Trump Donald Trump our president
The New York Times reported this week
That Donald Trump lost one
Billion dollars
Between around 1985
A 1994
He lost money running a casino hotels Airlines a football team on one occasion
He left 300 million dollar bills
In the pockets of his pants that he ran through the walk
Honestly
We should have figured out he really wasn't that good at business when
He tried to pay off Stormy Daniels
With a Groupon
Peter got to say one thing
Change your name Brian
People need to realize
He lost a billion dollars back
A billion dollars worth
The billion.
Free internet
So you couldn't have a lot of billionaires prancing around that's back when you had to
Destroy people's lives
To get a billion dollars
He lost a billion dollars
Vent
Literally nothing about business and I don't know if I could I couldn't ask
Accidentally lose that much money I would have to do it
Purposely
Sports
You can find a child who owns
Eliminate
Did Stan and they would make better dividend
The Donald Trump
Alright your next quote
Wasn't official
Statement from the
PR department
Of HBO
This was a mistake
Daenerys had ordered an herbal tea
That was the official explanation from HBO
About how what appeared by mistake
Inosine
In Game of Thrones
Starbucks
It was a Starbucks it was in fact a Starbucks cup
Well it was a to-go coffee cup is unclear as to whether it was a Starbucks cup Starbucks
Stop
Last week's episode of Game of Thrones obsessive fans
Also known as
People with enemies
Real talk
Keep either live
Spotted a Starbucks
Coffee cup sitting on a table in this
Supposedly medieval fantasy
Disney kingdom
Fans of course
We're outraged because in the book
The nearest drink
Only Dunkin
You know what I'm tripping
I thought it was
Supposed to be there cuz
Time machine
Play No Effects on my own dragons
So you know like why couldn't there be a starting why on dragons they can't go to a Starbucks drive-thru Ryan the dragon I mean where do we stop
I have a question how long was this cup in the shot was it
Second is like one shot and you don't I mean I have you noticed I did not but I can
Eli
If I could be got a little kids like you're not surprised to see a Lego anywhere you know
Your underwear drawer
Largest and that's the way Starbucks cups are like you don't even
Seether
It's true I'm sure you're right nobody noticed it
Bill how did Courtney do inertia
Bring It On
What a smart guy congratulations thank you Courtney hope you get some rest before the next
Farting
Bring up panel time for you to answer
Some questions about this
Week's news
A former Tech exec
Now once
Disrupt the beverage in
What is new product
Liquid
Death
Premium price
Tallboy can
What got to be kombucha
Nope
The name is perf
Tricked out
Liquid
Death liquid that it's Red Bull and yogurt
Nope
Okay I need to hear
It puts
The dye in dihydrate
Hydrogen monoxide
Chemistry class was a long time ago
It's
Oh it's
Two molecules of water
It's
Twice the water water water water
Ojani hydrogen dioxide
200 it's an old joke anyway moving on
Liquid death
Is the name of this product
The guy who's come up with is already raised more than
$2000000
Hours for his venture
It is a tall can of
Just tap water
With a skull on it
It is targeted directly to
The quote extreme straight edge Punk crowd
Because nothing says
Punk rock
Like a $2 can
Of tap water
The water is designed to quote
Murder your thirst
And according
Maybe that's the secret
There it is according to its inventor it offers Punk's a quote water brand that spoke to them first of all if your water
Start speaking
To you you're not a punk
You're a stoner
And if you wanted to sell canned water to real Punk
Try telling him to freeze it
And then hit themselves in the
The head with it
Record some new fans in our Bluff The Listener game call 1aaa
Wait wait wait wait don't tell me
From NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor squares
Squarespace allow small businesses to
Design and build their own website
Using customizable Lake
And features including e-commerce functionality
The and mobile app
Squarespace also offers
Built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online price
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website
Or domain
This is Kenny Malone from plant
I know maybe you've heard there is a new Jeopardy champion
James Holt
He's been racking up
Record De Lima
He is also
Sort of my brother-in-law
On Planet Money
We are going to ask what makes Jamie so
What is James doing
That makes him so much better than ever
Subscribe and download planet
NPR
WBEZ Chicago this is
Wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz on Bill Kurtis we're playing this week with Tom bodett Amy Dickens
Brian Babylon
Shut the f***
Theater in St Louis Missouri Peter Sagal
Hey thanks everybody and listen if you are just tuning in
You like all know I missed it or maybe you just want to hear it all again so you
You can pretend you have a
Impress your friends by knowing all the answers
All you need to do
Is download the wait wait podcast
The same show you love on the radio
It's for mattress companies
And stamps
Right now it is time to play The Wait Wait Don't Tell Me Bluff The Listener game call 1aaa tway to play
Games on the air
I'm having at one time from Lummi Bay washing
Evan from Lummi Bay
Washington welder
I think they had a girl's name figured out but not a guy's name figure it out
Night I got stuck with the family name do you know what the girl's name was
Let me ask you a question
Given what you've been through
Would you
Prefer to be named Emily
We are here to play our game
But you must try to tell truth
Conviction Bill Evans topic
I'm your biggest fan
Celebrities
Have long found
Fans the traditional ways
In purchasing Twitter followers
Drama Chinese boss 4
But this week we heard about a new way that a
Fan
Found the person or people their fans
Are pandas going to tell you about a pick the one who's telling the truth
You'll win the wait waiter of you
Your choice on your voice
Ready to play
Alright first let's hear from Tom bodett
The lyrics to A Horse With No Name blue my mind
SED Lollapalooza organizer Mason Ford
Ford who is 16 years old discovered early 70s soft rock bands like America and bread
When his dad erased his Spotify playlist of hip-hop favorites
And replaced it with what he thought would be the genre from hell
I couldn't
Stand the f words and whole cap and emanating from his room and earbuds another day said the Elder Ford
I wanted to punish him with some diamond girl in Muskrat Love
I thought he needed understand what obnoxious
Just feels like
Instead
He loves it
What I realized
Explain for the younger
Is that hip hop is not chill music
All me and my friends want to do is chill and hang out
This weird sound is so chill it almost doesn't make sense
I mean Baby I'ma want you says that and with that Googly sounding
Guitar thing in the background it's
S*** I love it
After two or three songs you can't move
The ball a palooza will be no firefest promises
Ford referring to the famous concert
Goodfellas Last Summer
It's more of a warming drawer fast
Surviving members of America Along with Dan Fogelberg will headline the event to be held this August in
In a closed Walmart parking lot
Springfield Iowa
Father Ford will not be attending
I live through the 70s once he said a day of this might kill me
A young man becomes a fan of 70 soft rock to a cruel prank from his father
Your neck story of a celeb making a new fans comes
From Brian
Babylon
UPenn volleyball player list
Zloty was
Running late for practice
Philly
The pressure was on
Cuz she had to park her 19th
Key for Pontiac
GTO
I have enough for my grandpa
To a parking space barely big enough for an enormous lanyard
I hate this car
I said why
As soon as I land my Pro
Beach volleyball contract I'm by myself a Honda Fit
She tried a Time
East times
Scraping or bump in the car in front of her
I'm going up on the curb
With drivers behind her honking their horns and go
Complaining
Finally she was
Ready to give up in
I keep driving
But then a gentleman
Computer window
And said may I assist
She was very angry about this
Ben Platt sexy
But got out and let him in
And the most amazing display of driving hat
He hopped in
And in the most amazing display of driving
She had ever seen
He whip that 20 feet of it
Detroit Steel
Villa parking space
With just a few turns of the wheel
She wrote his name down to send him a nice things
And then when she
TV show The Neighborhood
Teammate the teammate said Jimmy Johnson
The NASCAR driver
No fat Elizabeth I think he had a Toyota car some
Some kind
But it was never
48 himself
Seven-time NASCAR champion who was in town for
No parents
Elizabeth
Of course had to watch him race
Instantly became a
The fan
Self confidence
Africa on the tracks
She says
And if you think he's good at racing
Theme park
A Nascar fan is made with Jimmy Johnson himself steps into
2 Parkhurst
Car
Your last story of a famous person convincing someone to like them comes from
Amy Dixon
When they heard that Lyle Lovett their favorite singer was coming to Austin
17 women from 3 generation
Chance of one
Big Texas family decided to
To call it a Girls Gone Wild Weekend
Beloved love is mighty strong in the Walker
Clan
So Belinda
From El Paso rallied her gal Pals
From all over the country
Sisters cousins
Her mother
And even her 85 year old grandmother
And told them
Pack up your Spangler cowboy boots
Tencent bota boxes
Chardonnay lady cuz we're going to see Lyle Lovett
Tickets drop off
The event was coming up
When Walker sister figured out that the Lovett coming to Austin
Was not
The Texas native
And rectangle face
Grammy award-winning singer Lyle Lovett
No
This love it
Was John Ira Lovett of Connecticut
A former Obama speechwriter bringing his
Popular Progressive politics podcast
Love it or leave it too often for a live taping
The Lyle Lovett loving ladies decided to go ahead with their Girls Gone Wild Weekend
It turns out
Having to watch a politics lecture from a guy who can't sing and was never even briefly married to Julia Roberts
Roberts
Was just about right for these girls
Gone mild
Alright to hear your choices somebody made a fan
In an unusual way was it from Tom bodett 70 soft rock
Get a fan when a kid is punked by his own father
Justice playlist
Was it from Brian Babylon Jimmy Johnson
Credit One new Nascar fan
He graciously
Parked her car for her
Or from Amy Dickinson
The political pundit and podcaster Jon Lovett
Got a whole bunch of Texas woman to come see him because they thought
He was Lyle Lovett
Which of these is the real story
Unexpected
Meeting
Fan and Idol in the
Well I'll tell you what
I live for 12 years
In Texas and there ain't no way in God's green earth I'm picking any other story but that one
17 women who want to see Lyle Lovett and ended up hearing
An interesting political comedy from Jon Lovett
Got to be alright
Well
We actually
Spoke
To one of the fans
One of my cousins looked and
Jon Lovett
My sister like no no no I got life
Belinda Walker
Practically an entire female side of the family went to see Lyle Lovett and got John instead it's okay they like
Call Jim
Congratulations you got it right even you have won our prize by taking any story and you want to fly
Well done sir
Bye-bye
And now the game were amazing people talk about
A pretty ordinary thing
Things we call it not mine
Everybody in St Louis love the Cardinals and there is no Cardinal more beloved than Hall of Famer Ozzie
The Smith winner of 13 Gold Glove Awards
The claim that the best shortstop ever to play the game and known around these parts as The Wizard of Oz or simply the
The wizard
Go crazy Saint Louis hits Ozzie Smith
The Ozzy you came here to steal
Louis to join us from where you live now that you're retired which is
Right here you little retard from the game back in the 90s
You never left st. Louis
And this is why I know why would I leave I always wondered about that because there's a there's a
Kind of cliche
Sports that
When somebody
You know
Does something amazing for the local team likes they hit
It's a homer to win the national league champions
They say that guy will never pay for a beer in this town again
So is it true that you can't pay for your own beer in this town again
Call Ryan Lovett
Just say you know I'll have a beer and just wait
Just stand there
I bet not
Do you still follow the game sometimes I understand
Retired players at camp
Enjoy it because they not playing
Yes I follow the game I go to spring training
Yep and I usually go with
Yeah I did with the guys for like
10 days and then
When they start playing games I get out of
Can you do any like Eli construction of the shortstop's you like wall you need to do
Is Leap 30
Sideways get the ball
Jump 10 feet over the head of the guy coming in the second base and throw to first
Do they come up to you and asks
Well how do you get into the floor
Do you know when the one thing that I always like
Explain to people
Yolanda Sanchez
What's in motion stays in motion
Right so the one thing that you don't want to do
Princess Anne middle infield
Is be stagnating
Yeah there has to be some type of movement that allows you
You go left to right
And that that probably is the one thing
When I talk to her when I try
Trying to teach a guy
Is to have some type of movement
Cuz that's what allows you
Never flat-footed it's interesting because you mentioned you know laws of physics cuz I was watching
Quinceanera highlights and that was physically impossible
Couldn't be done
I always ask
Question of of elite athletes like yourself how young were you when you knew that you were good
You know I don't know if you ever really know exactly when that
But when I was a kid I used to throw the ball light where to pick fruit
I used to throw the ball up
On one side of the roof
And run around to the other side
In hopes
Yeah of catching it
Forget the ground
And people are sitting here wondering now
Yeah
Did you ever get there did you
Did you do it
I never did I never I never did but it was that type of
Determination
Yeah
That made me
Oh I understand that again
Can you play it's just me
Pure Magic
Pikachu seems like
Natural ability that
You could leap up in the air
Both feet 3 feet off the ground
Pegla first baseman without hardly look
Let me say this here
Pikeville
I'm standing back there and I listening to
Bill did you just
You just talk.
I just thought
It just comes out
To do with the gift is you
You try and maintain it as long as
Share it with as many people
You possibly can and
Never take anything
Marseille
Is growing up in Chicago watch
Channel 9
I was always amazing how you were
So cool
24/7
Even right now you like to
Help me understand help me be a better person
How do you keep that level of cool but still
Meet at that intense
Brian awadis
You just just be yourself
You know okay when your mom's friends is easy
IMAX about
35 was just being myself
Would a 230 lb guide
Trying to kill me with his feet
I would pee my pants that would be honest being myself
Never let them see you sweat
Well as a Smith we've invited you here to play a game that this time we're calling
We're off to see the wizard
When you play it is The Wizard of Oz
Just a wizard
For your magic
Who plays at shortstop so we thought we'd ask you about
The original Wizard of Oz
The classic
Movie
Answer two out of three questions correctly you win a prize one of my list
Who is the voice of their choice in their voicemail
Bill who is the great Ozzie Smith
Richardson St Louis Missouri
All right all right
People say they don't make them like they used to and it's
It's true The Wizard of Oz is
Proof of that which of these
Is a real reason that the Wizard of Oz as it was made
Could not be made
Today
Hey the actors who
Who played the munchkins were all paid a fracture
Action of regular wages
Due to an old
Pay by height
Be the wicked witches broomstick
The scarecrow's outfit in all of the
The fake snow we're made of a
Bestest
Or see the 1994 Religious Freedom Act
Which prevents witches
Or wiccans
From being presented in negative light
Call
Idiocracy
Can I tell an anecdote
So I read that you know the Tin Man
With all the silver
Bet that makeup was so toxic
That it sent the original actor
To the hospital
Genesis
That scene in the poppy field Arrow sleeping
And all the snow falls on their faces and wasted
Alright next question The Wizard of Oz has been of course
The pop culture treasure since it's
Releasing 39
Sometimes
Things from the movie pop up in unexpected places
As in which of these
Hey after Margaret Thatcher died in 2013
The song Ding Dong The Witch
His dad re-entered
British music charts at number two
B Popeye's restaurant once offered something called the gizzard of Oz
Or see Garth Brooks 2003 man behind the curtain tour in which
He sang his entire set
In a booming voice from behind a curtain
Just like the wizard did
They said they say what are you saying that you're right that's what happened
All right
Let's see if you can be as perfect in this as you were in just about everything else
There was a fair amount of acrimony of the said it was
Wizard of Oz with a lot of the hate folks
Because I'm one of the performers who was it
Was it a
Scarecrow actor Ray Bolger
Who walked around the set saying actually I'm very smart
And mansplaining
B-flat Ami roskopf a Russian method actor
Who played the lead flying monkey and weld
Decided to act like a monkey on
On the set if you know what I mean
Orsi Perry
Who played Toto the dog
I hated more per week than most of the human actors
He work
What's total play
You're right it was me
Terry the dog who played Tuttle brought down like a hundred fifty bucks a week which of the time is
The equivalent
$2,000
What is today so you
Wallpaper
Bill was Ozzy
As perfect as he was here as he wasn't
Score Ozzie Smith
Apartments Legend president of the Gateway PGA reach Foundation
10th Annual Gala and golf tournament September 22nd and 21st
The plague
In just a minute Bill asked for Ashmere in our listener line
AAA wait wait to join us in the air
From NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimum
Apps that can be open from anywhere in 5 min
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Na
What would you do if you found out a story that have shaped your identity was a lie
NPR's new podcast
White Lies investigates murder in Selma Alabama from 1965 and exposes the
Experiencing the captain on
Until now
White Lies start listening to
From NPR and WBEZ Chicago this is
Wait wait don't tell me
We are playing this week
Aaron's her house that's at Fox Theater St Louis
Peter Sagan in just a minute bill
Is gremlin after midnight
In our listener there more College if you like to play give us a call
Edwin AAA wait wait
That's 18894
Right now panel
Some more questions for you from the weeks
Amy The Wall Street Journal reported on the new celebrity
Fitness a guy named Brad
Who managed to make himself
Famous
By doing what
Okay I know this
If this guy is so it's a
The Peloton
The stationary bike that all the rich
People
Brag about having
So there's this class
In New York that live streams
And this dude
Brad
Keeps like photobombing
The class
He sits right next to the instructor and it's like
Richard Simmons
Dancing and
Exercise height
He's like a
Middle-aged
Dude in a bad t-shirt
Who wants to get on camera
One thing about the Peloton is it
Always have
Very nice
Like the solarium
Tokyo in your base
I'm just like everybody else
Feel I should add this
Before the conversation goes on too long
That's right
Yeah I was very into this
$2,000 to buy this high-tech exercise bike
Screen on it so they can live stream classes
In at least once a day next to the insanely hot inspirational
Contractor there's this guy named Brad going
Hey
Imagine if all the Peloton users were paying a lot of money to have this
Experience just love it
One said quote I try not to watch him
Oh gosh my blood pressure spike one woman figured out that since he's always in the same space
On The View
That you can just put a Post-It note right there and never have to look at him
Tell me a Peloton that whole sub
The Priceline
$2,000
I don't know man
Almost
Get one of those
Out-of-work millennium
Around maybe Brian contrary to the point
But it would be fun
Amy if you want to do something nice for your washing
Machine good news we now found out
You can buy
Your very own washing machine
What wonderful
Is it
Is it a
This is a blank keep some kind of Gadget a cover
Cover
Apparently a washing machine covers a very popular
But apparently
1 Winfred
BBK notice this week that's for sale and everybody went
Crazy cuz it looks
It's very much like what
Like
The Mona Lisa
Victoria's Secret turns out to be the spin
It looks like lingerie lingerie for your washing machine
Make it sexy
Exactly it's true this is an item for sale
Dust cover if your washing machine that looks exactly like a classic
Lacey
Negligee
Washing machine
Then say
I don't know does this make me look fat
Use that you know I have two teenage boys whenever I
Ask me I'll go put the
Wash
And it's a which one is the washer
Ghost put that in the dryer all your wet
Sled stuff
They said which one is
Is the dryer if I had an extra
Anyone with the Underpants
If the washing machine is rocking
Valentine needs to be repaired
Coming up it's lightning fill in the blank but first it's the game where you have to listen
For the ride
Do you like to play on are called and leave a message
At 1 AAA wait wait
That's one 880-892-4892
24 or click
The contact us link
On our website wait wait. Npr.org
You can find out about a
Weekly live shows back
Chase Bank
Auditorium in Chicago upcoming shows
What the man said
Philadelphia
Pennsylvania July 18th at the Blossom Music
Cuyahoga Falls Ohio
And if you haven't already play our new smart speaker quiz just say open the wait wait quiz
Senior Alexa
Go home and if you get for question
She's right you might want a prize
This week you can hear bill sing his favorite
Little man sex song
Hi you're on wait wait don't tell me
Buy beer
This is Sarah calling from New York New York
Oh they're wonderful I love it here
I love everybody who lives in New York does cuz otherwise they wouldn't put up with
What do you do there in New York
I work in publishing what are you doing
I am booked for Emirates manager at a literary agency
OIC
So you're you're you're jobs
To get those books out there
Okay so what do you do when you're not selling book
But I like Freedom my free time of course
So you you read all day what a tough day reading
Boy let's go home and read some more
Welcome to the show Sarah
Bill Kurtis is going to be a few 3 News related them right for the last word or phrase missing
Sing for me GIF you can fill in that last word
Rephrase correct
On two of the limericks you'll be a winner
Ready to play
I was born ready
There we go
Here is your first love
I'll take tea with a big goldfish
Please
It makes froth
The columns
Supreme
That glossy veneer
Is it gas consumption beer
I am drunk
Glob
Cream cheese
You are literate
Cream cheese in New York
Of course
The streets flow with me
Cream cheese
Is the newest food trends
In China
Yeah I did your dirty
Can you get a big sort of
Live cream cheese
Floating on top
Bristol's advised drinking at an angle that allows you to grab some tea
Invite cream cheese at
It's called The Tea macchiato and if you think that's
That's gross try ordering it
With locks
Alright here is your next
MyYearbook
Has few intramural
But it's filled with pus
Tails
Oldest without twirl
The tree-dwelling rodent
Is having a
Is Mammoth
We're making a yearbook
Squirrel
Are University of Texas alarm is putting together a yearbook for the campuses
200 residence
Because
When you're crazy you don't realize your
Hahaha
It'll be so fun
To see you know that
The superlatives who got the most popular
Most likely to see
Succeeded giving you real
Ni Hao Facebook
Start I believe so is all started yes Mark Zuckerberg was reading the squirrels at Harvard
Yearbook features pictures of the
Tiny yardrat
Graduation gowns and hats
No
Is each
All of the squirrels get a senior
Your quote
Be the change you want to
I hope that person
Sims parents are getting the basement ready
Because yeah
That's right
Here
Is your last
Fun times
Best reward
Too bad there
I feel a strong pull
To the times that are dull
And one third of my life
I feel
Bored bored
Polls show the average American
Is Bored 131 days a year
That's a third of the Year coincidentally this very weekend is the hundred and thirty first day of this
Jay's been bored since January get ready the rest of the year is
It's going to be awesome
I don't give a
I don't get bored
I guess I do but maybe I have enough
Control over my life I don't put myself
Situations
Is it bore me that
No, I say this in solidarity not
Aspersion
Yeah true. Sunday is one where there still some yogurt
People being bored
Endlessly stream TV shows but on the other hand
We can also endlessly stream podcast so it makes sense
Bill how to start doing work which he did very well
Blitzstars
Three of the graduation
This message comes from NPR spawn
Capital One
Is reimagining Bank
I offering account
With no fees or minimum
I'm Stickin be open from anywhere in
5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Na
Skyrise
Creator of how I built this in
We're returning to San Francisco for the second the how I built this Summit
Supported by America
Express
I'll be joining there by founders
Companies like Instagram
Whack away Bliss JetBlue and many many more
Visit Summit
Npr.org
More and
To see you there
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Did you come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solution
Strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org
Now onto my final game lightning fill in the blank each of our players with a 60 Seconds
Which the answer is many fill in the blank
Is as they can
Each correct answer net worth
Bill can you give us
Amy has three Brian has three
Tom has 200k
Tom that means
You are
Up
First
The clock will start when it begin the first question fill in the blank
On Thursday a house panel
Voted to hold a
Attorney general blank
Built bar right according to a un report released on Monday
For 1 million species
She's a plants and animals face
Extinct
Should write this week FBI director
Actor Chris Ray denied
Spying done
Campaign
Trump campaign right following several days of violent
Live in the Gaza Strip Israel in
Blank
Declared deceased
The Palestinian
So the time
Write Burger King announced a competitor to McDonald's Happy Meals
Easter 2019
Deep quotes
Blink
See it's not the Happy Meal it's always the board meal cuz people are bored like a third of the time
Close it's the pissed me off because when they're not bored they're angry
In an effort to get
Higher wages in healthcare thousand
The drivers from Uber and Lyft
Blanked on
When are they
Yes after officers in Florida at the woman he
He pulled over and she had anything on her person they should know about
She reached into her yoga pants and pulled out
Hoof
There's not much you can keep in your yoga pants it's
She pulls out
Get out of
Beard
Gecko
Orbach Geico it was in the right animal family it was a 1 foot long alligator
Silver after running a stop sign and told officers
What you been up to collect
Do frogs and snakes
And also had a backpack stuff
With 43
So far
A totally routine traffic
Stop
Florida
But that was before the woman who pulled a foot long alligator from her pants
And responsibly slip cigars
Celebrated the birth of Archie Harris and alligator Windsor
Wait a minute
Maybe those 1 million species aren't going extinct maybe that lady just has them all
Alright we flip the coin and Amy has elect
Lego nexo Amy fill in the blank
Under direction of the White House former White House counsel
Blank defied
A congressional
Not McCann
Again I'll 500R 500 Days in prison
Two journalist from Reuters arrested
Sit in Black released
Wizard Philippine Myanmar
This week President Trump signed an executive order imposing new sang
Oceans on blank
Venezuela Iran
An unidentified projectile from a t
North Korea
This weekend in Florida was charged with drunk driving after he crashed
Is blank into a blank
Peloton
Into
A lingerie clad
Washing machine
I know I got it nailed it his lawnmower into a
Police car
Just two weeks after release the latest movie in the blank franchise became too fast
Fastest movie to make
2 billion dollars
Avengers
I'm coming in the UK was Furious when she ordered a candle in the shape with the number five for her daughters
5th birthday
And instead received
Blank
Five number one candles you're so close she got tutus and A1
The woman ordered the candle from local super
Online delivery store
But they're apparently all out of you no candle shaped like a V so thanks to one for filming specialist quick-thinking and
Map skills
Woman is representative five roll with a cake
Celebrating her
221st birthday
Spell how did Amy doing our quiz if you got 3 write 6 more points
She has a total of 9
But Tom still leaves
Is 12 all right
So how many event does Brian need to win to win Ryan
Okay ready for the king ready to do this yeah here we go fill in the blank on Monday former Trump lawyer blank
Started his three-year Prince
Michael
That's right this week the Senate intelligence committee
Subpoenaed blanked
Answer more questions
Write this week law enforcement officials in La seized over 1000 blanks
From a Bel Air mansion
Fresh Prince
Look out hippies The Wall Street Journal is warning you that homemade blank could
Flowed
Kombucha on Wednesday Denver effectively decriminalize blank
Wait to speculation aircraft maker blank admitted to knowing that there's
737 Max plane had a problem
Boeing kazoo in Germany had trouble with its raccoon exhibit when it was invaded by blank
Morricone
Exactly right
It was invaded by a wild raccoon
Zookeepers at the Heidelberg zoo in Germany
Recently discovered this bonus raccoon while cleaning out the exhibit
And do the EU rules around invasive animals that can't kick him out so they've named him
Fred this is true
I will provide him with
Free room and board
And castration
Fight
Congratulations
In just a minute we're going to ask our panelists
To predict what will be the next
Expected thing to show up
In the last episodes of Game OF
The first let me tell you
Wait wait don't tell me they're productive NPR WBEZ Chicago and association with the Urgent haircut production
Doug Berman benevolent overlord
Are interns are out
McCowen and Rachel Clapper rweb Guru is
Beth Novi
Special thanks to the staff and crew at the Fab you
BJ's
By Jennifer Mills miles run Boston Lily and King are Nights in White Satin is Peter Gwen
Technical directions to Lord of white hair business on office managers Colin Miller
A production coordinator is Robert Newhouse producer and executive producer
Of wait wait don't tell me
Is Mike Danforth now pending what will be the next unexpected thing to show up
On Game of Thrones
Before it's all over
More black people
Amy Dickinson
Chew episodes
From Sunday seriously will be
Da'shawn hand feeding
Pet dragon craft
Mac and cheese
Bedtime bodak
Jon Snow is 23andMe results
Hey if any of that happens will ask you about it here
On wait wait don't tell me
St Louis Public Radio
River in st. Louis Missouri
Sitting at home next week
This
Is NPR