From NPR and WBEZ Chicago this is
Wait wait don't tell me the NPR news
You'll never take down this
Billionaire
And here is your hostess
Chase Bank Auditorium
Chicago
It's that time of the year when everybody goes wait a minute Summer's almost over and then they don't run around like maniacs
Pack as much fun as they can into the short time remaining
That's what we're doing in the shower
We're packing in
So many memorable moments
Android conversation
Well by the time we're done you'll be ready to go back to work
Just to get a break
From all the joy
First
When I was growing up I loved Jacque Cousteau the famous
Oceanex
Explorer
More sense because Jack
What is father
Gusto joined us in June of last year Peter asked him
How he was introduced
To the undersea world
But until my fourth birthday it's slightly different I actually went to the bottom of the pool with a family friend who is
Reading the newspaper while I was Buddy breathing with him everything is when you're sort of sharing one respirator
Back and forth
Star Trek and
He's reading a newspaper at the bottom of a pool
Yeah I guess he was bored but there's not much to see at the bottom of the boot into any fish in there I understand
Did you always want to go into what I guess
This is the family biz
The coastal family
I was actually
I never pressured to be in the family business I was always encouraged
To forge my own path
But at the pass always ended up turning back towards what we do with the family
Because I grew up watching
Your grandfather TV
It will the jacuzzi
And I mean
To me what I
Remember as much
What is the film of the fish
Is your father's
The grandfather amazing French accent
I'm talking to you and I can tell it if you did not speak
Really elaborate right exit I will not take you
You seriously
Jordan time when I was 7
Your specialty is
Sharks right I saw a film review diving with sharks
Inside
Well I don't know how to do
Describe it it's a big artificial shark
You hiding
Shark shaped submersible yes
I always wanted to approach great white sharks in a different way than the ugly bubbling creatures in the cage Thor
At these wild animals
The best way to go and learn a little bit more about them is to become a shark so that became reality and
M6 2007
Rebuild a shark shaped submersible little did I know that
Doing such a thing was more challenging and I ended up on the bottom more than I did with the sharks
Really so it would just like you to go down there
And you be like hello fellow sharks
And you just
Continue the sink right now
So you know it was it was meant to be a polymorphic sharp where you could do
Male and female in Fortune got so complicated we left the male parts
Behind in
A female shark that was hoping that hey maybe this is going to attract a shark and we'll have mating behavior
Female shark Parts on
Immersible
Shark parts
But they weren't
Detachable
Male sharks have two penises or clasp
So they're lucky
Unfortunately
Twice the maintenance.
One more question
Witches
Accurate was Finding Nemo
Can my child hard
Well Fabian Cousteau it is a pleasure to talk to you we can talk to you all day about the ocean
But we have in fact
Ask you to play a game of this and this time we're calling it
Man just get cool with the flow of the jam
Man
A lot of fish
Personally
What do you know about the band Phish
Legendary
Some Grateful Dead fans find a little to Mandarin
Answer to out of these three questions right you win a prize what if I listen to the voice of anyone they might like on our show on their voice
Bill who is Fabian Castillo playing for
Robert loving them Los Angeles
What's California
Alright ready to do this
Let's go for it I just first question
How fish got its name
PH
Is HP
How fish got its name has been a subject of Interest
Fans for decades
Which of these is a possible explanation for
Permasand quoted in Newsweek
Hey that's what the bandleader Trey Anastasio says and said
The cursing
BSN acronym meaning
Psychedelic hypnotic
Instrumental sounds are
Happening
Dorsia to take on the sound that comes out when you're filling a balloon
Do nitrous oxide
At a party
In Vermont
My love Sia
I won't say that I've done that
Before
Question
The acronym meaning
Psychedelic
Hypnotic instrumental
I
I'm guessing that knows answer the nitrous oxide
Is the river that never come out in
I actually listen to a lot of fish music and I'm
I'm guessing it was the nitrous
Lead singer Trey Anastasio was
Expelled from the University of Vermont for a prank that he is never described in public
But according to Phish fans it was
One of these
A
Stealing a human heart and hand from a biology lab
And sending them to a friend with a note heard you could use a hand
Be getting the gig
Playing The Star Spangled Banner at a UV football game and keeping it going for 18 minutes
Orosi pot brownies at a Dean's reception
Cheese
If I were in his shoes I would have done this
Sick twisted humor of the of the hand a
Whether you're right that's what he did at Corydon stablish story
About to get this right you win
Fish has a fair amount of celebrity fans
Including
Which of these is a
Morning Edition host Steve inskeep
Who says he starts every day at 3 a.m. with quote
A spliff in my fish
Bootlegs on 12th
B the musician Rob Zombie who says he plays
Fish music to quote go to my happy
Horsey actor Abe Vigoda who played Detective fish
And the old Barney Miller TV show
Who wants to join the band on stage dressed as a wombat when he was 90
82 years old
See I'm going to go with be on that one
Yes
Why do you think it's definitely not
What was your reasoning
But 92 I leave you never know
It's not true something what somebody had to make that up
I think they'll want you to go into the
All right let's go with this
Halloween concert
Raichu value
I'm actually friends
With Rob Zombie
And I hate my stand-up specials that I can
Until you
Perfact
He has no happy
Rob Zombie
From directing House of a Thousand Corpses
To your stand up special
And I killed
How did Big Ang puso doing
Fabian did well out of the water as well as in the water you got two out of three
Congratulations
If somebody wanted to know more about what you do down there how would they find out
All go do I Fabian
Gusto.com that's easiest way or follow me on social media
An oceanographer
And the founder of the Fabian
Cousteau ocean Learning Center pleasure to talk to you
Thank you so much for joining us
This Summer's been
Pretty full
Snowfall in fact that we had to edit out
Part of it
Here's a question we asked Roy Blount Jr
A couple of months ago that we
Didn't have
Have time to Broadway
Right we've had an intense tornado season but so far
Meteorological technology is allowed p
Be warned in time
One problem though residents of tornado-prone areas are
Complaining that
The tornado
Rings are doing what
Carrying the chicken
No
Scaring the
Kalifano
Gering NE livestock at all
I had a lot several other livestock
The tornado warnings are interfering with
With Rush Limbaugh
You're so you're so close
I'm going to give it to you
They're interrupting dirt
TV shows
Start a couple of weeks ago
What is station in Ohio interrupt
The Bachelorette to warn people to
You forgot sake take cover
And tell those people contacted the TV station
Not to thank them for saving their lives
But to tell them to stop with the warnings until we find out which of these identical asshats is going home with her
Also my TV is flying away can you do anything about that thing
Here's the question was that done in the middle of a
Rose ceremony in
Yeah I know let's get real you know you're holding
Five rows
What is a new six of them like
Do not
Give me the weather app
But if you're wondering why there so many tornadoes
I got called into a Pennsylvania weather station
Can any had the
The other solution is
Because of all the roundabouts
The traffic circle
Cars going in circles
Just next time you see around about
Save the country drive straight YouTube
What are we
Go back to the Beastie Boys
Girl Lindy West will be back in a minute
Good morning wait wait don't tell me
From NPR
Support for wait wait don't tell me in the following message
It comes from rocket mortgage by Quicken Loan
Imagine how much
Feels to have an award-winning team of mortgage
Jack birds make the home-buying process
Smoother for you
The history of industry-leading online lending technology
Rocket mortgage is
Changing the game
Visit Rocky
Goodmortgage.com
Weight Equal Housing lender
Licensed in all 50
Estate nmlsconsumeraccess org number 3030
Rocket mortgage
My Quicken Loans
Push button
Get mortgage
What place of games everybody I hope your Eisenberg host of NPR's ask me another
Are you looking for the answer to life
Funny or questions
Zamboni
That is correct
Every week we Blain comedy
+ 8
Special celebrity interview
Jim Gaffigan
I've always done acting I just have never gotten
Rolls
Listen and tell your friends
This is
Wait wait don't tell me the NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Kurtis and here is your host at the Chase Bank Auditorium in Chicago
Peter Sagal
Find a cram in as much fun as we can in the last moments of summer time is short
So I recommend listening to this while playing beach volleyball while ziplining at a music festival
Multitask people
Earlier this year pillow released a show called
Shrill
Based on the Memoir by Seattle journalist Lindy West
We interviewed mrs. West herself
Spin Seattle in December
So you grew up here in Seattle
Will Seattle
Where is my parents and I all went to the
Not at the same time
I've been reading your book
Which is a great book hilariously funny
And you were a very different person growing
Then you are now
Yes I was very shy
And
Weird and I just wanted to hide
Israel under a blanket and never talk to anyone
What I was
8 or something I
Just peed in my
The chair cuz I was afraid to ask the teacher but he go to the bath
First day of school it was like I've been there for months
French was really nice
Let's just put this
Briefly you're not like that anymore
Menstruation test
Yeah we would love to the
The Red Tent
Ceremony
It was just
It was just a bunch of
Ladies sitting in a
Pink Panther
They made a pillow fort
Inside a community center
And then we sat on
The floor is like 8 Hershey bars
Oh that sounds fun
That would be great
You're not welcome
You wrote here in
In Seattle for the
The Stranger and
You wrote for Jezebel the feminine
This website
And you
What is that
Do you have like we're at
Tweed jacket with patches
Yeah
The feeling year
The feeling
It is
Terrifying
So I built my
Personal brand
On like
All caps
And like fart
Horrible vulgarity
And I can't do any of that
I want to know did they did it when they when they brought
Bring your voice two times
But there's a
New rules around here
They didn't even give me that talk I think they were like
Come on
If you have dignity
I know you find it cuz you of course famously were trolled a lot on Twitter
Engage one of your
Would rape this American life story
In the chapter
Do you find that the trolling that you get
New York Times is
Yeah but what I get from New York
Dellavedova comments
But I
Do get like
10000 word emails from
You know
70 year old man explaining to me my father I'm sorry
It'll be like there's a few things you need to know about
Women's lib
It's actually very Charming in a way
It's instead of like a thousand points a day I get like
Once a week I get a couple
TDS email
Yes
It's a different life
It's a new
World for me
I am reborn I know
TDM instead of
Vicious
Misogyny
Well Lindy West it is a prism
A pleasure for me to be
The fan
But we even fact ask you to play a game we're calling
Use
Christ
So
You are a Lindy West
I see where this is going
What I saw that coming at you two questions correctly about the man who gets to wake up to Kim Kardashian
Almost everyday and you won a prize one of our listeners
The voice of their favorite wait wait
Person on their voicemail
Bill who is Lindy West playing for
Carrie Lapidus
Of Everett washington
Don't we were looking into this and I actually found a column that you wrote I think
Jezebel about
God
What if
Okay but maybe you're a huge fan
And you like no other
The stuff incorrect
No
Play Duel of Kanye
Quite a bit
I am wouldn't say that I know
But I will find out here is your first question
Kanye West Houston tour
Star global
Fanbase
How is Santa Claus
What's the club in Beijing
Fans call him
Kanye
Obvious but it just so happen
That in
The Beijing dialect of
Chinese Kanye
Means
What a quote
Guy who steals your noodles
With his chops
Be quote someone who brags a lot
With no action
Instafollow it up
4C quote
Essentially
TMI
Okay I'm going to go with
See
Ctmi nose actually be
Kanye is an idiomatic phrase meaning someone who brags a lot
Before Kanye West
2008 Kanye went to
Jail
Briefly
Destroying a paparazzis camera
Booty call
Classic one phone call
John McCain mistakenly thinking he been elected president
It might be able to help him
Be the paparazzi
If you got a good photo of him coming for the camera
Morrissey he used his one phone call to order Chinese food delivery
Rita Jail
I'm going to go with
Be going to go with bead
Paparazzo
Attack
Everyone sins
To be yelling at me
Not something you're not used to
I feel nothing
We get it right
Everything
Everything you win if you get this right
Terrible things that last question
Kanye recently
Was quoted by his own wife
Saying that something
Doesn't get enough credit
What was
A
Pollinating in
Insects
Be Art Garfunkel
Or see his own wife
I need you guys to be unified in your mermaid
Okay
Reincarnation would be
Because come on come on Jayla
That's what they talk
Seriously
HP
Kim told GQ
Even though I'm an ass girl
Kanye always says my boobs don't get as much credit as they deserve
Unquote
She got two out of three
The weather
I'm old enough to have lived through a number of Revolutions in pop music and I pretty much missed all of them while listening to me
My scratched up original Broadway cast album
Pippin
Why doesn't Vegas Peter is utterly oblivious to was
Rise of the Beastie Boys the new york-based Trio
Who helped to
Who popularized Hip Hop
With their album
From the 80s and 90s
So when I talked to Mike D and ad-rock
The Beastie Boys the main thing I wanted
Janelle was
What were their parents thinking
It seem like your parents and this was back in the 70s
Would basically let you guys do whatever you wanted
To do it was like when you were like 14 or 15 your parents like are you ghosts
See what is Black Flag concert to have whatever you want
Just be back by morning
There wasn't that much of a discussion
Yeah pretty much different type of parenting you know
You know the details
Flag Show versus
Like a bad brain Show versus a treacherous P I don't think she wanted that kind of fine print
And
One of the other things that I
I do not seem like you guys constantly
Had great Strokes of luck
For example you form the punk band The Beastie Boys originally hardcore band
And you did a you did a song called
Cookie Puss
British Airways
Stole it for a commercial
And give you lots of money
Which is fine
That that had happened yeah yeah
Does that strike you like an amazing Stroke of Luck cuz then you had money to like
You no pay rent and buy that first drum machine
Yeah it was pretty awesome to go from 0 to we got it we got a bunch of money was pretty nice
I've never had cash like that
I was at a friend's house and I heard our song playing from the TV set
Animals like it was one of those things that make You Go Hmmm
And then like I don't know how long after your first hip hop track
You were opening for Madonna
Yeah crazy right you guys are like 19
You didn't have your first album out
And you were
Opening for Madonna on her first national tour
Blowing up on MTV and then she becomes
Madonna that is
In terms of just public Consciousness like the biggest pop star
On a planet she likes shut up to
Michael Jackson
And you were like her opening act when this happen
I don't even know opening act
What is the right
Any word
Assault on
Poor unfortunate
Suspecting 12 year old girls
You guys are on the way up and you keep writing about your books how you
At this point before License to Ill came out and people would hate you
Which is kind of fun for you to write about was it fun to live
Kinda I mean nothing was definitely funny that
You know children were crying watching us
Interesting seeing how angry their parents were
One last question about the book the book has got some amazing stories in it about things you did and things that you saw
Was there anything that was like two crazy
For you to put in the bucket like now we can't tell people that story
Yeah
Would you be willing to share it with us to space
Well
Adam and Mike we are delighted to talk to you and
We have invited you here today to play a game we're calling
Beastie Boys
Meet the yeast
Steve Boyd
But what about people who make
Bread
That's what we were thinking when I ask you three questions
About the yeastie boys
Patriots
Correctly
I know
It's both dumb and on brand okay
Are Adam and Mike and Beastie Boys playing for
Fruity Riots of Washington DC
All right
Here's your first question in feel free to collaborate argue whatever you like
Bread is really important to the French
I'm sure you know so much of the French government once did what a
Created an award called LaCroix
Dapat or the cross of dough
Be passed a law preventing Baker's from taking vacation
4C they sent in certain violent criminals to eating only American bread
Definitely
Be because
Vacations are essential
French people at the Crossing Doe
Yes it was actually be the one about taking vacation
Because the problem is French
Bakers were not allowed to take vacations but then they
Modify the rules another Baker's of France
Can either take vacations in July or August
But that way there will always be some Bakers around
They did
Here we go
These days most people are more excited about baking cakes and bread making
Celebrities that have people like
Buddy the cake boss valastro
He wants
Tried to get out of a DUI arrest by telling
The arresting officer what
A quote you see your way to letting me go there's a sacher torte in it
Because I'm a soccer tour
Thank you
That's why they're a good team
Bae quotes
He said I'm sorry officer but do you know what happens if you let Palm don't overcook
Or see he said quote you can't arrest me
I'm the Cake Boss
I'm going to see Mike how do you feel about that
You're right it was in fact
Sexy yeah
Stand when you're baking cookies at home and you realize you don't have enough eggs but not to worry according it to something called The Organic Authority
What makes a great egg
Is it a blood
Bee sugar or see sex Magic
That's a good question
Wow
Interesting
I mean I'm going to have to go to sanitary B
Yammy yammy
Clearly a culinary
Do you really think
That the protein
Of eggs would be sufficient
Chili substitute
Before by the pure carbohydrates
Table sugar
I do not
All right
Blood
Remember not saying you should do this we're saying you can do
I feel like a blood the blood would be thick enough to replace it
Rotting Flesh Blood
MDC should be happy
If you're choosing a blood
Bill how did I can make dinner quick a fan of the Beastie Boys
Congratulations
Mighty and ad-rock are the Beastie Boys their new books of Beastie Boys book is out now it is
Fantastic great for fans or even if you're not Mike and Adam thank you so much for joining
When we come back
Smith from Doctor Who in somebody else talks to Retta from Parks and Recreation
That's in a minute
On wait wait don't tell me
NPR
Support for this NPR
Cast of the following message
Message comes from tapestry collection by Hilton
An independent group of neighborhood Centric Hotel each with their own vibe
Whether it's the sound hotel in the heart of Seattle
For the Rose Hotel in Chicago
Each location is
Is probably connect
Get to the local fabric of the community
So whether you decide to take in the modern art
It's inside the rose or visit the Space Needle
At the sound
Staying at tapestry collection by Hilton Hotel
That's as unique As You Are
Visit hilton.com wait wait
Well you're sleeping
A whole bunch of news is happening around the world
Up first is the NPR news podcast
Get you caught up on the big news
In a small amount of time
Spend about 10 minutes with a first
On weekday mornings from NPR news
Don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
I don't tradition here is your host
The Chase Bank Auditorium in Chicago
We are trying to make up for all the lovely summer days we waste
Staring at our phones
But we visiting some great moments in the recent past
Which we were only able to
To experience first time because our phone
We're debt
Parks and Recreation became
The cult hit
Sitcom
Stars rela
I called hiroto's families of the show
Last year
Guest host Helen Hong
Ask her about her role on the
The show
And her new book
So the title of your
Buck called
So close to being the
Y'all don't even know
Be honest
Did you call it that just to watch interviewers
Squirm when they had to say it on the air
Little bit little bit
Save a title right the other people have to say it
Generally I don't but I do like Santa
What's what's the most creative any interviewer has
Has come up with
Say the title
Usually they say
Becca to be in the blank
But Kelly Ripa said so close to being the s
Show the app
Clever
Clever girl
I know your real name is Marietta sirleaf
Sound so Noble I feel like I should
Bow when I'm saying it
You should
I just did Marietta sirleaf
Why do you just go by one name Retta
What up when I was in college
I hooked up with this guy from Georgia
And they pronounce
Marietta Georgia May weather
Oh and
He started calling me rather as if I allowed it
And my friend thought it was
Hilarious and so they insisted on calling me that and then so when I first
Doing stand-up
I between an open mic in the MC came out and said
What other actress writer and that's how I got rid of four
Because you didn't have the patience to go over your actual name with him
No I was like if this is too challenging with six of the easy stuff
One neighbor which I think is
Is boss me Cher Bono
I heard you were back
Pursue medicine before moving to LA to become a
The comedian
How did that work
I was I was pretty mad I was
All about the book
Growing up
I
I was taking a year off after college
Which is the first time I ever lived alone
Brake just before I went into medical school
And I used to it and I was giving myself so my TV was my roommate
And after a while I feel like I can do this
I can do this
But I decided that I wanted to have my own which is why
I started doing stand-up because I saw that so many
Sitcoms where
Headed by stand-up comedian so
Stand up
Imma stand up
Comedian I still haven't gotten
Oh awkward
How don't you come from
Don't you come from an immigrant
Emily rata
I do my parents are Liberian
How did
How does your immigrant myself coming from an immigrant family when I told him I was
Become a stand-up comedian there like what
So how did yours
Because you were actually like on your way to Medical
Why did they take that
They're actually pretty good about it my mother
Said no you carry around your father's last name which is why I don't use my last
My dad's big thing was like
Just get health insurance
Seven habits that we can take care of you
Speaking of your dad's last name I heard that you're actually
Venise
Lavalife
Liberian former president
Yeah
Ellen johnson-sirleaf was married to
My Dad's cousin
So you come from not only an immigrant family but an
Family
It's like like that
Was really high up
Yeah I guess I version of royalty over there
Because she won a Nobel Peace Prize
That's right, homie
What better than a Nobel
It's Friday I got more calls about her being on Oprah then her winning the Nobel Prize
Your biggest
What does Donna on Parks and Recreation
Can I just tell you I was
A guest star on one episode
Parks and
For literally 42
2 seconds
And I have had
People Acosta
The street so I can imagine what you
You must be dealing with
But having been on like a series regular on it
Oh yeah like there's not a day that I walk out of the house and go to a tree
Treat yourself
Please open the floodgates
Here
Reddit we have invited you here to play a game we are calling that's a good boy
You're currently starring on a show called Good Girls
So naturally we want to ask you about good boys
Evan doggies
We're going to ask you three questions about dogs
To have been very good boys
Get two of them right and you'll win a prize for one of our listeners
Any voice from our show on their voicemail
Bill who is Retta playing for
Daniel Emami
Of Houston Texas
Beretta
Are you ready
Yes okay here's your first question
A dog in England has been on a tighter leash since its owner discovered it had been doing what
Licking all the freshly washed
She's in the house
B
Traveling by bus
Twice a week
Take to a local pub where he was
Which bed sauce
Messages
Orsi attempting to mate with the neighbors
Cat
Which it must
Happy sad with a very doggishly
I
I want to go with
Yeah
Okay I'm
Sorry the answer was B
Traveling by bus twice me he was fat sausages
The funniest part is apparently he
I could catch the bus there but like
Couldn't catch the bus
He always had to be driven out
Hilarious
Read I hear your next question it's okay you have two more guesses left so
Here's your next question
After being robbed several times
Tire shop in Texas
Decided to enlist the help of a guard dog
What happened next
Baby owners return to
To discover the dog had
Chewed up every single one of their tires
Be the dog.
Distracted a gang of robbers by humping their legs
Until the cops
Came
See the next time thieves broken they stole the dog and some more tires
Oh God I'm going to
I'm going to go with c
They actually destroy the guard dog
Stealing the tires
The thieves must have had treats there or he must have flunked guard dogs
Alright Reddit you are doing great
You got one right
Here is your last question
We like to give our dogs what they need
Which of these was created
Just for dogs
A a new dating website called fetch me
Helps your pup find true love by
Displaying photos and bark
Parts of the dogs Reddit
Mister with it
B
Spotify launched
Adopt
Defy a music service that helps you
You find a dog that shares your taste in music
Orsi Petco created a new line of dog beds that you
You can custom order
Smell like your dogs
Favorite butt
I'm going to go with B
Spotify yes that is correct
Find a dog that loves
Kind
Weird Emo music that you're into
And I say no matter how
Cute the dog is it
If that dog isn't
2 Red Hot Chili Peppers
Even moving. Bill how did Reddit do is a winner of our book
Beretta stars in the series
Good girls which was just renewed for a second season on end
NBC. Thank you so much for joining us on wait wait don't tell me
Is it was an audience to whom I didn't need to explain
What Doctor Who is I am looking at it
Actors who played Doctor Who is Matt
Smith who also plays the Young
Prince Philip in the hit TV show
The crown
Peter began our interview
Earlier this year by asking him which
Show
Had the most obsessive
Fans
Does Ian leave
You were the youngest person to
To take over the role of
The doctor is that
App for people who don't know the doctor has been played over the car
Corset 50 years
Buy a bunch of different
Her new book
Fun
Thank you very much yeah well you know she is here
That's what's so great about that
Be there in 10
Like parent
For example
To get from a to zed
Dakota kccd
That
We lost a lot of those letters
During the government shutdown
Shut down I mean
Lanikai
Look before you get all high-and-mighty your country's about
The fall off the edge of the Earth
You know what's funny of course man if Doctor Who were real
None of this ever would have happened
So you go from Doctor Who
What is incredibly popular
Two-player
Prince Philip
Who is a very real person
Did you guys working in the show ever get anything back
From the actual royal family
About how they felt about how you were
I think the fit it was off
If he works there and he just turned around and said
So sadly you've been phased out of the crown because
Is that their aging you out
You got to be replaced by an older actor
Tobias Menzies
Did you argue with him and say I can be old and
Decrepit
It'll be wonderful looking forward to the first season of The Next Step
Episode 1 of course
Prince Philip
Dies and regenerates
Has Tobias Menzies
And then I just want to talk to you about your latest
Film witches mapplethorpe
It's out now in which
You play Robert mapplethorpe again a very real person
He was
An infamous
Best photographer
Did you decide like okay I'm going to play this
Is gay promiscuous guy who did hard
Record
Sort of Photography as art
Did you say like I will show all the people who love me
Prince Philip and doctor
The distinctively
Trying to do something
No it wasn't that much of a considered Choice Realty
Descriptions around 9 I found him very
Sing I Love New York in the 7th season
Difficult and I was interested in.
Until after playing a very
Difficult synonym
Complicated figure like Robert mapplethorpe
We decided to do something light and
Play Charlie Mann
Mancini someone I got 29 ways
Is truth lies and the wall
Thing I took away from them was I just went
Really annoying
We have a game to play
But there is a question
And we ask this I don't know if you know
We ask this of all our gas
Tradition
Have you ever been stung in the test
Testicles by a wasp
Yes
Finally we got one
About it
I mean
Yes I know
Outdoor arenas
Insect bite
The passion
Text to say Enjoy.
Stop
Woodstock on the products
Yeah
Uncomfortable when we find side
Matt Smith
We are all delighted to talk to you and could all day but it is time to play a game as
Wonderful
And this time we're calling the game
You don't have to be beautiful to
To turn me on
So you play Prince
Prince Philip in the
The crown but what do you know about the true Prince
Prince
We're going to ask you three questions about the purple one
Blessed Be he
Get to write under $1 prize one of our listeners bill whoismatt
Smith playing for
Cody Benjamin of Atlanta Georgia
Now Prince was Prince's real name
Is born Prince Rogers Nelson
But when he was very young
He preferred to be
Called by a nickname what was it
Hey
Sex monster
Be better
Orsi
Skipper
Better
I'm going to go to bed
We should have anticipated you being
Not knowing about
The answer was
Skipper
Prince guitar
Was a child yet like
Call me skipper
Prince got an early break
When he was hired to open
For the rolling
Stonebridge
Dan lan
91 but it didn't go well
What happened
A
Mick Jagger looked at him
Kevin said nobody goes on stage
Who's skinnier than I am
Beef and chased him off stage by throwing garbage at him
Percy Prince
Announce his set by saying sorry but it all goes downhill after I'm finished
They chased him off
The stage with Garba
And he was very upset
But it was too nice and they said don't worry about it
Those crazy we're so sorry go on
The second night
I'll be fine anyone on this
Second night
And they chased him up
But why
By becoming
Amazing Music popular
Last question if you get it right
You win
Prince
Once later in his life
Gave NBA
Star
Carlos Boozer a check
Half a million dollars
Just to apologize for so
What had
Prince
Done a
He wants criticized Boozer
There's playing style on the basketball court
By saying more like Carlos
Snoozer
Am I right
Be when Prince rented boozers home he turned boozers bedroom into a hair salon without asking
Or Seattle
2007 NBA All-Star Weekend Prince hooked up
With Boosie's girlfriend
Boozer's ex-girlfriend
And then
Hoosiers mom
Hahaha
God I wish I wish
It would say but it's happened
Hoosier Renegade
Princess
Is LA manche
Prince totally redecorated made the bedroom
Hoosiers like what you do principal here here's a half a million dollars
I'm sorry but then Prince
Totally redid the house back to the way it was
Who's the gay Batman
Bill how did Matt Smith
He would make Prince Philip proud he got
A2 Auto
Three so you are winner
Special training all the fun in the limited time left Edition
Wait wait don't tell me the production of NPR WBEZ Chicago in association with urgent haircut Productions at Doug
Berman benevolent overlord
Philip go to get right the Olympics are public address announcer is Paul Friedman
Our insurance company naviti and Lila Francis rweb Guru
Is Beth Novey BJ leiderman composed RCU
A broken is produced by Jennifer Mills miles during Boston Lily and King technical directions morning wider business an ops manager
Is Colin Miller a production manager is Robert Newhouse or senior producers and chill out
An executive producers wait wait don't tell me is Michael Danforth
Curtis all of our panelists all of our special guest
And of course thanks to all of you for listening I am Peter Sagal
I will see you
Next
WIC
This
Is NPR