Support
PRN the following message
Come from Subaru
Featuring the all-new
3 row ascent
With seating for up to eight and a choice of 2nd row captains
Love is now.
Bigger than ever
Learn more
At Subaru.
Bill Kurtis here
On the wait wait podcast you are about to listen
You'll be able to hear Peter
Emily
But
We can't hear you
But it doesn't have to be that way
With the new wait wait
Quiz for your smart
Askew
Be able to hear you
Imagine that
A little back and forth between the three of us
So what
Gloria's age we're living
Just ask
Alexa or Google home
To open the weight
Weight quiz
To try it out
If you do well enough
Who could win my voice on your voice
That's right
Get these pipes
Without
A plumber
Give it a try
From NPR and WBEZ Chicago
This is wait wait don't tell me the NPR news quiz
Remember the
I'm Bill Kurtis
And Hitler's your hose from Trinity University
San Antonio
Peter Sagan thank you so much
We are so happy to finally be able to do our show here in San Antonio
And we made it just in time right before the federal government
Forces
The city to change its
And Anthony patch
Senator Cruz will be allowed to keep his name but he has to
Spelling it like
Tom does
Later on we're going to be talking to a Texan who reported on just about every major
Story of the post-war era Mr Dan Rather himself video
Do you want to hear a live report
From your house give us a call the number is 1
AAA wait wait
That's one eight eight eight
Two for now let's welcome our first lesson
Contested how you're on wait wait don't tell me
Hi Peter this is Megan Doherty from Oberlin Ohio
Oberlin Ohio Megan's home of course of Oberlin University
Do I have any affiliation
ICampus rabbi
So you work at the Hillel
Yeah yeah and how are you in and how do you find that work
It's really fun
The characters on Lena Dunham Showgirls roll Oberlin graduate
Is that true to life in terms of weather
I have never seen girls
Giving your job I wouldn't recommend
Let me introduce you to our panel this week
First the comedian and host of the podcast
Fake the nation it's just been nominated
Weather
News in politics
Itsnickbean farsa
Make the comedian you can see in Philadelphia at
Helium Comedy
Key Club on April 8th
Alonzo bodden
Hello finally a comedian whose new book May Venom
America is out now it's made Higgins
Play who is Bill this time Bill Kurtis a good review three quotations
Snooze
If you can correctly identify Iris
Two of them you're winner
Surprise any voice
Marsho you might choose in your voice
Ready to play
Here we go here's the first quote
For what
We need wall that was a quote
From a woman
Who got fired last weekend despite doing her best
To get wall
For the president
Who is it
Kirsten
Unpronounceable last name Pearson unpronounceable last name Nielsen
Spell it
Former Secretary of Homeland
Security is the latest victim
All the presidents
Cabinet
Separation
In policy
Everyone must go sale the White House
The President also got rid of the guy who was supposed to head up ice the actor
Indirect or he's out he wanted someone who is quote tougher
And he fired the head of
The Secret Service
Right while the guy was diving in front of him yelling
Acting secretary
What's an acting homeless
Reenacting
Is that in an acting head of the Secret Service
There are more actors in the president
Cabinet
Then there are in the wait staff
Los Angeles restaurant
Nobody even better though and over
Acting Secretary of Defense
My favorite thing
About yours
Nielsen being the
Homeland Security director
Anti-immigrant and everything else is
She spells Kirsten with a
JS middle
Like that's not American
No not at all where you get that Jay from what
Talk because
You know
You leave the Tropicana
If you get fired
It's terribly reputation
Is ruin people yell at you wherever you go
And you know what the
The Trump administration's IDF
Cobra benefits
To tie you into a sack
With a cold
Put the demon having all these acts
Sing secretary said they're basically like
Cancel accept
Teacher
Which means that our
Pictures of bunch of people.
Doing whip equal
Pushing jokes and throwing
Spit wads at acting cabinet members
It's chaos
That's true today at the Pentagon they're just showing a movie
Alright Megan your next quote is
Someone who is known
Attacking
Millionaire
And billionaire
I wrote a best-selling book
If you write a best-selling book you can be a millionaire
That is the new Democratic polls who is it
That was Bernie Sanders Bernie Sanders
Pic of the guy who for years has
I've been saying we've had enough of our country being run by millions
Revealed that he is in fact a millionaire
Surprising
Because most millionaires
Afford haircut
We should have known things were changing for him economically
When his
Stump speech
Change to we've had enough of our country being run by billionaires
Billionaire
But Bernie has promised
Not to enjoy the money because in his entire life he has never enjoyed anything
I just can't believe he got rich
Writing a book
Because everybody I know who's written
Is so broke its true
But also like what can
Can you buy in Vermont
And are a million dollars in Vermont
You can buy like half of Vermont
Stroke
By the way this is all
In preparation for Bernie releasing his
Did you know that Bernie has not
Not released
Didn't do it in
He says he's going to do it now
Next week
He's the perfect candidate for
People who both hate President Trump
Jealous of Republican
Why can't liberals have an angry old man with
With terrible hair who won't
The tax return
I'm sitting here Peter trying to think about it joke
It shows I care about rich white men but I got nothing
Just one more time white people complaining about
And I done made a million dollars
I don't know how to help you on that one good luck with that Megan here is your last
Einstein must be
That was a very happy astronomer quoted in the New York Times
Talking about
The first ever photograph
Ever made
Of a what
A black hole a black hole yes
Of an actual massive
Interstellar black hole in a gallon
Auntie known as
Has Messi
I-55
Million light-years away
It looks like a welt
A black hole
Surrounded by a ring of arms light like
The eye of Sauron
Really evil bagel
I thought it was a scientific
Triumph it was unlike anything
4 photos
Of their colonoscopy
Interesting life
Waited all I can tell you
How many people colonoscopy photos you look at
Interesting man this is
Pretty cool because of
Time it takes the light
To get here 55 million years
The photo
Is the black
A hole when it was much younger than it is now
So what do you know
The black hole is
Just like everyone
My first thought when I saw that photo is like
They're really great
Yeah that's who I really I really feel happy
Before those
Astrophysicist
The other side
The geniuses
Says who
Spend your whole life
Studying and working in and they can finally say
That's what I do
This is what I do. What do you do at work
This is what I do and this is really cool
This picture of this
Extraordinarily Disston
There's no single telescope
That's strong enough to do it
So they had to get data
Different telescopes
All around the world
And combine them in an incredibly complicated way
Figured out by 8
29 year old
And they say that's at the Precision of this
Virtual instrument they created
Was so precise
They could see
Orange
On the moon
Which makes you say why are they going on about a black hole there are oranges on the moon
Everything about this
Read like if you were
Deer tracks
Explain what happens if
You go into
To the black hole
Park City events
Horizon
Unscathed
And then you get to this point
Where the black hole
Stretches
Do you like a
Noodle
Which for a minute I was like
I'm okay with that ass so what the f*** he was like
Like you kind of
Microsecond you finally be a size one yeah I know
Integrace worth it
Thank you
Pantelis now some questions about the rest of the week
Are you Alonzo a Taurus getting a ride in a fighter jet
When France got the
Full experience when the pilot accidentally did
Ejected yes that's what happened
You know the whole thing with a canopy blowing off in
Tennessee rocketing into the air
Don't worry he parachuted safely to the runway below French authorities say he's fine
Or wait French authorities actually said quote
His health is not a cause for
Weirdly that's exactly with the same guy who
Rented the island had
How to say
The 64 year old man was riding along
A French Air Force fighter jet
Which isn't supposed to
To eject past
Messengers just because it feels like it
It's not a nightclub it's a fighter jet
Most likely nobody knows exactly what happened
The most likely the passenger
Close to
Fulfill his lifelong dream but
His Last Words Be
What does this button do
Peter is someone who used to work on on fighter planes
I think that's
Exactly what happened I think
He saw that red lever and said I wonder what this does and then he found out maybe this fire
But that is the ultimate I mean
You know it's great to get a ride in a fighter jet but it has to kind of
Be cooler
Stephen ba
Ejected from a fighter jet
Imagine being
At a party
And some guys bragging that yeah man I was riding in a fighter jet
Oh you were only riding in one
Coming up wrench that talks at me prommy Bluff The Listener game Co 10008 way to play will be back in a minute
More quickly.
From NPR
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Park Inn
The newest Resort in the center of the Las Vegas
It's weird Lady Gaga
Bruno Mars and Aerosmith
Bring down the house
What's in the intimacy of the
The Park theater
It's where l a chef
Roy Choi
Mashes up
Korean flavor
Where is Eddie's new restaurant
Best friend
Be inspired
At Eataly Market
Enjoy your spin on fine dining
And no matter
And let it all go
At on the record
Biggest his first speakeasy
Park MGM
Intimate moments
Big experience
Hazel ophira eisenberg host of NPR's ask
Me another and I'm here to let you know that every
Free Friday in April we're bringing you an epic
Episode that spotlights
Women in comedy
You'll hear from redis
The star of NBC's parks
Recreation
And I'll talk to you Russian doll actor Greta Lee and co-creator leslye headland
And many more
Listen now
NPR
And WBEZ Chicago this is
Wait wait don't tell me
Play NPR news
I'm Bill Curtis Ware playing this week with nageem farsad Alonzo bodden
And Maeve Higgins
Here again is you're a host at Trinity University Laurie Auditorium
Antonio
Peter Schrager everybody take it out right now it's time for the wait wait
Show me Bluff The Listener game 41888 Waco player game in the air how you were on wait wait don't tell me
Hi this is Devon O'Donnell from Salt Lake City Utah
Who plays what do you do there
So I work in a warehouse during the day
Go to cosmetology school at night and I also work at the drag performer
What can I ask what you're even number question
What is your drag name
It's Gemini
Gemini okay sounds exotic
And
So when your in cosmetology school year
You're going to be at
Hair stylist
Yeah absolutely her makeup that's fabulous well as a drag queen you will absolutely be ready to
When you think about it
You want your silence to be a drag queen
Better how to do makeup than someone who beat their face weekly
That's true
Kevin it's nice to have you with Azure two-player game and what you must ride to tell truth from fiction what is the
Chick-fil-A
Will you go to prom with me it's prom season
And that means two things one photos your children will regret forever
Into new
Prom
Ren
Are pandas going to tell you about what's new at prom this year pick someone is telling the truth you win a prize
What's the weight waiver of your choice on your
Ready to play
Absolutely alright
Let's hear first then from nageem farsad
The 1990s hip-hop
Chris
Cross made an unlikely
Sunset Boise Idaho Center
Centennial High School
You might remember them from that one hit
Jump jump the daddy Mac will make you
Do Jump Jump Kriss Kross will make you jump jump the daddy Mac will make you jump
Johnson sure it was a
Huge hit with NPR audiences
You may also remember the
Curious fact that they wore their pants backwards
The kids at Centennial High could not get enough
Kris Kross and started dressing back
On campus
Weather a few awkward address
Set the boys urinal
School administrator
The whole thing is a passing
Throwback bad
But the trend
Continue to grow in
The senior class decided to
The theme of prom backwards so they renamed it more
Which is proper back work for those of you who lack backwards speaking facility
Not only did this
Students decide to dress backwards
Long dress
And flowing forward on girls and corsages
Depend on boys back
But they made everything backwards
Morphe night
It started with the after party wear
Just got exceedingly drunk and made mistakes they would sue
Tune regret for the rest of their lives
As a dancer
Through the night they turn their moonwalk
Forward and there
Flossing upward their twerking had more chest and less booty and their Gangnam style look like a horse
Was riding them
The backwards from where everything is backwards including the progression of events in Boise
Next promposal will
Is your problem really chaperones when The Chaperone
Is Charlie Sheen
You might have to figure that out
Especially is the trend of celebrity prom chaperones
The spreading
And also because
Machine is looking
For work
TMZ reporter Salena Jones says
It started at Calabasas
Aces High School
Southern California
The Calabasas
This is well known as the home of the car dash
Sheen family
One parent called in
Favor from a friend Chris
Is Jenna and the next thing you know Khloe Kardashian
Xi'an is at the prom
Checking kids for alcohol
Not to be outdone
ICM
I'm super Asian
E&R Getty
Has a friend whose daughter is at Beverly Hills High School of the Arts
So now they're probably monitored by
Idris Elba
Interesting League that maybe more mom Volunteers in action
Fast and even faster on
Snapchat
La kids
Bragging got Nashville kids jealous so their parents got into the ACT
And now country
Three stars Carrie Underwood and Reba McEntire
Will be at the Nashville High School
Senior prom makeup
I'm sure the kids don't do anything that they'll have to later right
Country songs about
Not to be outdone New York
Started rumors of
Jay-Z at a Brooklyn Heights
But these were unfounded
It's a Brooklyn Tech will have to settle for Chris Rock
All of this led to the nightmares
Scenario parts
True
Charlie Sheen
Through his lawyers
Asked if
Chaperoning the LA Performing Arts High School prom
Would count as part of his
Community service
TMZ is waiting for the judges
Celebrity chaperones is the new trend your last story of what's new
Under the Sea comes from
This year's big
Prom friend is inspired by attack
Sing fail
Teams across the country text their dates
To check what kind of
Of course size they want
Only to find that their phones autocorrected the word corsage
2 crossbow
Seems like a rose by any other name is pastry
Cheddar's scratch
Kitchen at Dallas Bakery is now selling the crosstown corsage
After the cricket autocorrect
Mistake blew up on Samsung
Instead of wearing delicate carnations infragilis
Youngsters are getting their prom dates corsages made from actual croissants
It's a lovely way
How to make a memory on the Green
Restain that will last forever
Siri this is just the first in a long line of carbohydrate
From why is there so many French words
During this is the first in the long line
Carbohydrate accessories
From Bagel buttonholes cupcake cufflinks and of course
A Converse
Sticky bun
It's all part of a lovely trend of having some fun and providing gluten intolerant
People with yet another activities
They can't participate in all right
Which of these is the real prom theme or trend
This year wasn't from the gihon the backwards
Prom
More pain with everything have
Backwards
From Alonzo celebrity chaperones a famous person standing there at the door for you
Or from Maeve Higgins
Kids wearing croissants
Instead of corsages
Because of an auto
Correct
Failure
Which of these is the real story of a promise
Well I think I'm going to go with the corsage
Prasad
We spoke to someone playing a role
They would be asking a prom dates what kind of corsage they wanted
Autocorrect on iPhone
I'm from Cheddars scratch
Which kitchen which is making croissant corsages for the
This year's
Prom goers congratulations that when you got it right
You're the one for me
Voice of your choice on your voicemail
Thank you so much for playing with us
Thank you thank you.
And now the game where people live a rich full life
And yet somehow end up
With us
If all the major events
Of the late 20th century at a single thing in common it might be best they were reported on
By Dan Rather
He was at Dealey Plaza when Kennedy was shot he reported from Vietnam he challenged Nixon on Watergate
He covered the Cold War and was there to cover it
He is a proud Texas native and still a resident we are honored to have him with us Dan Rather welcome to wait wait don't tell me
So
Don't have a home here in Texas you grew up
Your text I was born in Wharton Texas I grew up in Houston and
I'm not just from Texas
I am up
Newark
You started and it turns out that many reporters I know including Bill started the
This what you were a local guy you
I want what you were doing minor league baseball games at one point
I did I once have always been used
Good news for once
How to supplement my income
Tickets lower level Chino
Broadcast News and pay all that
So I did I did play-by-play as a way of supplement my income I did play by play football and baseball basket
Ball
Track fracas rediff
Difficult to do play-by-play.
How would you do that well he's running it seems to be running more
Call Hughes boxing or he has this shot put in his hand and
He takes 5 Steps and Heathrow
Do you think there's one moment that which you sort of got your start that started your
The career that we ball
I've been watching Lotus menu
Well I do that there was a great hurricane
In 19
61 hurricane
Carla
Which was it that Donna nothing
I'm still the largest
In terms of sheer size
Hurricane on record in the Gulf
Oh and I had just started and television had made my move from
Radio India
Your television
We're still new to
And we
Wound up in the right place
Wait time on Galvez
Kitchen island
The hurricane came in
And that was picked up by other stations nobody else was there
Broadcast
So if I had to point the one moment
It's sort of quote
Made my career
That was prop
Yeah it's funny cuz Bill got his sword
Start over the great tattoo
A tornado in
Kansas tornado
Maybe these
Maybe these weather events are being caused by ambitious young reporter
You were known for many things but certainly for being
Fearless not know of not only the places you went like War zones but also the way you treat
The people in power there was a famous incident
Where you got up and you ask
The President Nixon
Questionable
During Watergate
He didn't like it
And I believe you said are you running for something
And you're famous
Response was
No service
President
Are you
You of course took over as the anchor of the CBS Evening News taking the Baton from Walter Cronkite another Legend
Took it from Edward R Murrow so
You're part of that line one of the things that people
Noticing as you as you settled into that role was you were looking for your
Your sign off
Cuz famously of course Cronkite would end his broadcast with ATS
The way it is
And what was your thinking
I needed something different you needed
Suggested to me that you need to sign up
Following a legend like that is not easy
I did write my first suggestion was maybe I can say well
That's some of the way it is
That's the way it might be.
What is rape
My father
I like father's favorite word
Discourage
For a lot of reasons
Soap
I thought well maybe we could just pause and say yeah
What's the CBS Evening News Dan Rather reporting
Courage
The more I thought about it the more I got elected
Nostalgic ring for me
I will say that the executives in the company
We're horrified
Short lasted about a week
Interviews that waitress pretty much you either stop using this
Sign off or we stop using you
Wow so it was easy
I just decided not to have one
Just went with the playing my best shot didn't work
We can talk to you about your career all night but out of all the people you've interviewed and you interviewed
Just about every you know major historical
Go player in last 50 years was there a particular favor
Somebody who
He was glad to talk
Well I'm glad you put the breakfast
Places I've been
Lucky and might have a blessed I could give you the names
Maybe seven people
But if I had to pick one
It would be I was just signed my first major
Assignment for CBS News
What's the cover dr. Martens
The king and what was
First in the emerging civil rights
Stubborn donkey King
Covering donkey King
Change me as a professional
And it changed me as a person
And for that reason I would see if I had to
Typical novel
Give him Doctor Martin
Peking and covering in Bay today
Rauscher
I imagine that
NBA so you have a chance
Whomever do you ever like
Miss it
Give it like if I was there I would have the quest
Like every second
I can imagine
Well Dan Rather it is an absolute honor to talk to you but
Today we have in fact asked you here to play a game
We're calling
This game is tougher than the height of an armadillo
As I'm sure you know you are famous
Nice for what people call rather isms
Folksy sayings with colorful metaphors and colorful wisdom you've used so many of them over your career
We want to
See if you can pick the one you actually came up with
From some fake ones that we made up
Contribute to you
If you can do that two times out of three you'll win a prize for one of our specimens
Bill who is Dan Rather playing for
Tori hinderstein of Washington DC
Here's your first rather than this was when you were covering the 2000 election
Did you say
This race is tight like a too-small bathing suit and
2 long ride home from the beach
Be Papa where your good suit cuz we got ourselves a tie
Or see this race is tighter than aunt
Tilly after 1/3 Moscow mule
Daiquiri
I've always wondered
Did you just make those up off the top of your head did you like them have them ready to go
In the beginning they came from
Working in the oil field
This is way men talk about you have got to be kidding me
You can only say it
It's hot as hell so many
Hotter than a Laredo parking lot
All right we have two more
You did well with that one this is now we're moving through time to the election of 2004 that was George W bush re-elected
John Kerry
During that evenings coverage on CBS did you say a
John Kerry's wife might on Heinz but this is one night he won't catch up
Be we used to say if a frog had side
Pockets he'd carry a handgun
Or see it all comes down to 208
I o which stands for oh hi it's over
Definitely be I think you're doing really well
Here's your here's your last question this is a great metaphor you use while commenting
In the 2016 election was it a
This race is a Backcountry Tilt-A-Whirl it could go either way
Be like the talking horse
Said to the hopping Bowl I can't believe what I'm seeing
Or see if Clinton wins Florida this race will go faster than a Hamilton ticket at face value
I don't recall seeing any of them
Do you know which one you wish you had
I guess that would be
Bubba like the talking horse head to the hopping bullet is a good one but the one that we were told you said
If Clinton wins Florida this race will go faster than a Hamilton ticket at face value which I thought was great cuz you're updating your pills
References
How did your old friend and do it anyway two out of three is a big win for
Dan Rather
Is a legend of Broadcast News and the creator of news and guts
Media the new season of the big interview with Dan Rather start
16th at
At 8 p.m. on
Dan Rather
Thank you
Sunset Plaza
Google News
It just a minute we finally settle that whole cat versus dog debating our listener Limerick challenge call 1-aaa quick way to
Jonas in the air
From NPR
Support for NPR in the following message come from feather
On average
Rich people moved 12 times
Before buying a
So why are you still buying furniture
Every time you move
Feather is a Furniture subscription
That gives you flexibility
Over your furniture and your spouse
Get access to over a hundred and fifty pieces of front
And the option to change it
As your life
Subscribe now
Decide later
Visit live feather.
To start experiencing the benefits
Furniture flexibility
Feather
Furniture
That changes with
Gyros
Your host of the
TED Radio Hour
In our latest episode
We're exploring what it takes
Create social change
And the many ways to
We as
Individuals
Might be able to make it
Prince in the world
Find it
Next TED Radio Hour
From NPR
From NPR WBEZ
Chicago this is
Wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news
I'm Bill Kurtis were playing this week with Maeve Higgins
Alonzo bodden the game Pharcyde
You were gathered shallows
From Trinity University Laurie Auditorium in San Antonio
Peter Sagal in just a minute
Times of Texas are upon you in our listener Limerick challenge if you like a play
Give us a call at 1 AAA wait wait
That's one 880-892-4892
Before right now panel
Time for a game
That we call
The 20/20 dump
With millions of Americans
In signing up each day to run
Enter president as a Democrat news about all the candidates is coming in hard and fast we're going to ask you
You about some of the rapid fire stick
Question right you going to
True or false
Ready to go made true or false at a campaign event
Is an Iowa Beto O'Rourke
Ask for his autograph while in the bath
I would say that
True actually know it was false what happened was better
What started talking to the stranger in the
Who then ask him
Hey are you here.
Is he better or work
I was imagining that he kind of like off you don't seem to very over
Men are likely gets off on countertops
Size imagine him out of your rhino kind of stretching
Your cross to offer
I'm sorry excuse me
Your rhino is the new way it's for now
Is that what they call him and I are
Honestly I've never used
Nadine true or false
South Bend mayor
Pete buttigieg and his Husband chasten
We're immortalized in a butter sculpture
Feels true or false it was a diorama made of marshmallow peeps
Alonzo true or false
Former Virginia governor Terry McAuliffe who's considering a run
Tweeted out a picture of himself as a crab
Standing on the head of an alligator representing Donald
Oh absolutely
Absolutely true we have no idea what it means but that's what he did
The game true or false
Candidate Andrew Yang made empowering
Firefighters part of his official
Platform
A true no false you made empowering a mixed martial arts fighter is part of his
Official platform
Of course as for the Republican candidate
In 20/20 Alonzo true or false
On a visit to George Washington residence Mount Vernon
President Trump said I'm here to honor the legacy of President Vernon
Imma go with you on that one also
It's false what he really said was quote if Washington was smart
He would have put his name on
You got to put your name on stuff or no one remembers you
Declared while we were playing the game
Right now panels more questions for you from the week's new
Maeve a woman in Taiwan suffering from what she thought was an eye infection learned of this week it was actually what
Oh shoot
She had been working at does anybody know this made a lot of news
Bumblebee
Yeah I had get bees living in her
Otherwise a lot of Buzz around this year was
Didn't the bees were feeding on her tears
Noble skip the gross parts
Which means we will never speak of this again
She was gardening and she started having some eye pain
Will happen
When your eye has bees in them
George the doctor and she got her first clue that there might be something
Nothing seriously wrong
When he approached her wearing a head
Tutto white suit and holding one of those smokers
Piece of toast with butter
Smallwood
I didn't know
Apparently they they're small enough to fit in there and you couldn't see him one more thing to worry about
IPhone in Europe
Coming up with lightning fill in the blank was first is the game where you have to listen for the ride if you like
Play on air quality of a message
1 Triple 8 wait wait
That's 180 date 92489
Berkeley contact us
Qunar website
Let's wait wait
. NPR
. org
You can there find out about attending our weekly live shows back up
The Chase Bank audit
Chicago upcoming shows
St Louis on May 9th
July 18th
The Blossom Music Center
In Ohio
And if you want to experience this
The thrill of our show without the hassle of listening
Check out for your smart speaker
Just say open the weight weigh quiz and Bill and I will be there to ask you
Fill in the blank question
You can even win the voice of your choice on your voicemail
Taiyuan wait wait don't tell me
TJ calling from Waterbury Vermont Waterbury
Is a great place what do you do there
Groom ski trails for Sugarbush
You're so you ask a guy that's cool
Snowboarder but yeah we're up there every night just
Laying down corduroy pants
That's really cool you sound like a snowboarder I'm just going to go then
I just want to ask
If you live in Vermont
If you had $1000000
What would you do with it up there
Oh man I probably
Bye
Now that's not to say all right why wouldn't you just get one really big one
TJ welcome to the show Bill Curtis related limericks with the last word or phrase missing
Inform each
You can fill in that last word or phrase correctly into the limericks
To be a winner you ready to play
Yeah alright
Here's your first look
My pet is a bit of a brat
I'm the servant in the his
Habitat
Those who own a sweet dog
All live high on the hog
I feel lousy
Cuz I
Peppa
Chat
Yes
Dog owners are happier than cat owners it turns out it's been proven
With the new survey showing how dog owners self-identify as very happy where is
Cat owners identify as a again
The survey found dog owners are happier than those with
The survey also found and
This is
True
Fat people with
Cats are less
Happy
Then people who have no pets
At all now that doesn't necessarily mean
The cats make you unhappy and majors
Speed the cat owners are miserable losers for entirely different reasons
Can I just say hashtag not all cats
Because
What's a really great cat that was based
Physically like a dog and now I have a dog and there were like this I can't even tell them apart
Top Cat people always say that
Yeah they know my cat is different no it's not
Here is your next
Limerick
For podcast
We've got
And idea
Gay Swedish boys
Sleep Venice
Now I have no send Mom will help
You stay calm
Are podcast
Reed's name
News from
I feel very good do you need a new sleep aid
Vanguard show no longer doing it for you
Ikea is launching a podcast made
How to help people go to sleep
What is 4
In which two Swedish men
Read the names
Products
From the Ikea catalog
Which is a great idea it's much better than their original idea of reading from The Illustrated assembly manual
Cuz like I don't know a man with a hammer is sad and
On the corner of his table hurt site
The podcast is advertised as a great way to help people fall asleep and if you listen to a clip
You can hear what
Bjorksnas
Chest of 5 drawers
Queen quilt cover set
Swedish people
Reading at Ikea catalog is truly the definition
Of white noise
If this isn't enough for you you can turn into Ikea's next podcast
Some guy rods
How the hell do you build this
Alright TJ here is your last limerick
What airplanes the sound
Candy Crush
When vacuum sucks
Water is
Is Russia
Since
Just got to be scared to use bathroom
Midair
We have soften
Flushing right working to improve airplay
Plane travel but not by making sure your plane does
In Crash now
They're trying to make sure that
Toilet isn't
Too loud
People have been complaining for years about the
The deafening Roar
The airplane
Toilet flush
It terrifies children
And mask the other bathroom
I do want to do
Apparently designing a quieter mechanism that can
Ocean at high altitude
The challenge that Engineers have found a way to cut the noise of
The Flash bison
16 decimal
Fingers in ears
Stop razor elbows
Unfortunately they haven't found a way to reduce the
The sound
The guy in the seat next
Steve who can't hear himself farting cuz his head
Bill how did TJ do in AR quiz
Thanks so much for playing
Support brain
PRN the following message
Should come from fat
On average people move
12 *
Before buying
So why are you still buying
Furniture every time you move
Feather is a Furniture subscription
That gives you flexibility
Over your furniture and your space
Get access to over a hundred and fifty pieces of fur
And the option to change it as your life change
Subscribe now
Decidedly
Visit live feather.
Time to start experiencing the benefits
Furniture flexible
Feather furniture
That changes with you
Now on to our final game lightning fill in the blank Easy by players in that 60s
Answer as many phones
Is he or she can
Each correct answer
Now with two points bill can you give us a score
All
Three of our panelist
R-type
What oh my God
Okay I'm just going to randomly pick May to go first met fill-in-the-blank on Thursday the EU offered
To delay blank until October 31st
Craigslist
This week lawmakers in New Zealand overwhelmingly approved a ban on
Blank
White guys
No
Assault weapons on Monday Virginia Beach
Texas Tech to win the men's
The blank title
High School
The best award
If only
NCAA basketball
This week a high school baseball game was canceled after a group of people attempt
Did the dry the field by blank
To dry the field
By going out there
No
By dumping 25 gallons of gasoline on it and lighting it on fire
How many Connecticut on Monday the White House reversed an obama-era decision to allow baseball players from
Blank to play in the US without.
Cuba yes
Police in Oregon were surprised when a 911 call reporting a robbery in progress turned out to be blank
It was a bear
No it wasn't a bear it was a Roomba trapped in the bathroom
The homeowner heard strange noises from bathroom and called the police who arrived in the scene with guns drawn
Abus lock the door and was surprised to find a Roomba inside even more surprised when it said
Can't you knock
The woman apologized to the police are wasting their time
Any burglar under her bed breathe
Decipher
Jumped out the window
She beat her old records
She got to write
4 more points
And in her disc
Style
Delete all right
Alright Alonzo Europe next fill in the blank
On Monday a federal judge block the White House's policy forcing a blank
To stay in Mexico
Asylum-seekers on Thursday WikiLeaks founder blank was arrest
Did in London
Julian Assange
Does phone behind
Was arrested when he black
Went together
No he drove up in the stolen Jeep and ask
The cops for help
Finding his phone wouldn't that be went
How to get it I don't know but what do you think
On Thursday the CDC warned that a new drug-resistant blank is a
Global health
A new drug
Virus know it's a fungus this week a grand jury indicted former Stormy Daniels attorney Blanco
36 Federal
Against Michael avenatti
The owner of a bed and breakfast in the u.s. Canadian border called the smugglers in was arrested
Biddeford Blankets
Smuggling of course
Canadian police arrested the owner of the
Smuggler's Inn
Organizing illegal entry into Canada for 7 people
In our faces 21 criminal charges which could come with a half
The other says he's gay
Going to stay calm and really hope
Police don't find out about his other business
The every cake contains a nail file to help you break out of prison Bakery
Hahaha
Bill how did Alonzo do in Ark
Well he raced to the lead with five right 10 more points total of 13
Negeen need to win
She needs
6 to win and a very
This for the game on Tuesday
Steve mnuchin said the IRS would not meet
The house panels deadline
Fine for releasing Donald Trump
Spanx
Tax return
On Wednesday Bennigan's conceded defeat to Israeli Prime Minister
Benjamin Netanyahu
Declared a public health
Gio Bernard break
A blank on Monday the White House declared blanks revolutionary guard
Terrorist group
Huron police in South
Erica said that I'm missing
Poacher was likely blank
A missing
Poacher
Was likely
Oh so close I'm going to tear
Killed by an elephant then eaten by lion on Monday Texas Tech announced it would no longer considered blank
And it's admit
Ride on Thursday was a part of the blank hires thousands
Employees
Listen to recordings made by their smart
Amazon yes police in Detroit have opened an internal investigation
Navigation after an officer showed up drunk
The training session on
How do you use a breathalyzer exactly right
Do the police report the officer volunteered to role play the part of a drunk driver for a breathalyzer damage
Tration if you blow above the legal limit
That means you see the drinking of the job
Herb just really that good and I
Is currently being investigated and charges
Is being really really really dedicated to his job
I think Nikki did well enough to win did she not
She got a point
Teen Mom
It just a minute we're going to ask our panel to predict what we'll find when we zoom in on that photo of the black hole but first
Wait wait don't tell me on NPR and WBEZ Chicago in association with the Urgent haircut Productions
Doug Berman
Overboard
Public address announcers Paul Friedman
Klepper rweb Guru is Beth Novey
BJ leiderman composed by Jennifer Mills miles dornbos
Lillian King our patron saint is
Peter Gwinn
Technical directions from Lauren Widener business
Tomato juice
Call Miller
The executive producer of wait wait don't tell me is Michael Danforth
Now panel
What will scientist find when they
Zoom in
Of the black hole
Looking for Sade
Kirstjen Nielsen
Still nothing
Interjet MX
Alonzo bodden
They're going to find 1 billion twinkling urinal cake
Spell if that happens we'll ask you about
It's on wait wait don't tell me
Trinity University Laurie Auditorium
Slocum and everyone at Texas Public Radio
Thanks for listening by Peter Sagal and we will see you next week