Support for this NPR Podcast
In the following message
Did come from Better Health
Online counseling by license
Professional count
Specialized
Issues including the
Depression stress
And anxiety
Visit betterhelp.com wait to learn more
And get 10% off your first month
From NPR
WBEZ Chicago
This is wait wait don't
Tell me
The NPR news quiz
You ain't here
I'm going to slip into something more comfortable
I know Curtis and here is your
Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown Chicago
Peter Sagal
Very excited about this week she'll because later on we're going to be joined by the man
Who is genuinely too nice to be in the entertainment industry that's the actor
Henry Winkler
Dino
You know it was one of those weaks
Where was a little hard to find anything
Then go to the week's news but we are going to do our best
We are however going to have a moment of silence
Once during the show
Actually if our jokes get the usual
Lance will have a fair number of
The please don't you be silent give us a call the number is 10008 wait wait that's 18892
To 48924 left welcome my first listen to contesta
Hot you're on wait wait don't tell me
Hi Peter
Metro from Kings
Ontario Canada International, that's very exciting
Tell me how because I like to imagine that we have listeners in exotic places
Tell me how exotic
Kingston Ontario is
Well we're located on the North
Shore of Lake Ontario
2 hours
From
Ottawa
3 hours from Montreal
You would have to
Syracuse
I think
I think the only thing I can say is
So welcome to the show Teresa
Let me introduce you to our panel this week
First up at the comedian will be performing at the mcglohon theater
In Charlotte North Carolina
On September 26th
Next the comedian performing at youku
UPS in Vancouver Canada September 6th and 7th
Trivia podcast go fact yourself in the maximum fun
It's Helen Hong
The Side Splitters Comedy Club
Tampa auto
Is 15 to the 18th its Alonzo bodden
Welcome to the show chorizo you going to start us off
Who's Bill this time
Bill Curtis is going to read your three quotes
Snooze
If you can correctly identify or explain
Just two of them you'll win our prize any voice from our show you might choose
Your voice
Smelly Ready To Fly
I sure am
Your first quote is from the website
Jezebel about a protest in the fitness
They're taking their mesh panel leggings
Elsewhere
They're talking about people who are ditching SoulCycle and Equinox
Turns out the owner has
Zip ties
Whom
Oh my gosh
Who is someone who the kind of people who might go to SoulCycle in Equinox
Would not like
Your president that's the guy
I see you've heard about him there in your car and you're just in foreign land where is it
Travel
The coastal Elite
It's knew this day would come oh yes they wore their
Pink hats they tweeted out the most cutting meme
But this was the week the resistance got real and people had
The sacrifice something that mattered
Their front row bike
Get the 3 p.m.
Spin class
Hip hop Wednesday
Washington Post reported that Stephen Ross
The billionaire who owns both
SoulCycle ny
Equinox Gym chain
Throwing this big
Fundraiser for Donald Trump
His mansion in the hand
Beretta TuneIn $50,000 a person which
By coincidence
Is exactly the cost of a Year's membership at equinox
Frankly we should have known it was a right-wing organization
The full name is
Separate but equal
SoulCycle was originally Triumph of the wheel but anyway
I was just about to sign up and everything
That's true
Was so enraged
But I March
2 mi
Gym membership card
How to check what
Jimmy actually was
Turns out naughty
Fuhrer
Is very this gym chain
Especially
Knox is very
Play popular with celebrities
So many of them
It's big
With celebrities
Send SoulCycle
I'm you have to know somebody
To get into seoul
You don't just show up
Excuse me you
You pedal down
Street they actually have real bicep
Pedal away
Benefits of shake
Alright here is your next
Quotes
Sort your paper from your plaster
Maybe even try to kissing a man while you're at
That was GQ commenting on a new study that says some men are afraid
That doing what might make them look gay
Which is something you do when you're trying to do what
When your recycling exactly right We Cycling very good
The UN released an apocalyptic report about the effect
Climate change we also learn
But a lot of men don't like recycling because it
It's kind of gay
An article in the journal sex
Trolls
That's
Roles it's not about
Does croissant
You got that sometimes look like a butt
Anyway
Journal article says that many men feel that recycling or other kind of
Green activity
These is emasculating
So they won't do it
Right that's why you always see guys trying to kick aluminum cans out of the garbage can
Wither crotches
Men
Sulfur example
Because that
Okay
Askmen
We're guilty of a lot of things
But this one
You can't put on all the
I like I hang out with guys who approach
Pretty bad
I don't know any guy who
Who's like
If you save that aluminum can
You can't even hang out here
This study was in G
I would think more men would think
If you were gay for
For reading G
Acute
TVG
I like you you better off
Cycling
BBQ Pit on demand scale
I like you all right you are right
Auburn Exotic Furniture
But Teresa
Here is your last
Best quote
Can it walk my dog
That was one Californians reaction to sing Amazon's new
What
Delivering packages on the street
This very week
Yes
Robot
They're here you knew this day would come Amazon is
Is introduced its first delivery robot
The streets of Seattle and Southern California
Delivery robots
Scouts
Look like motorized
Beer coolers
6 wheel
Machine guns you don't see until
What's the weather
Read or seen signs
Fiction this isn't going to end well
Will let that you know we should do we should bring dinosaurs back and make a theme park cuz I don't work the worst that could happen
It is very reminiscent of the movie Wall-E
That's
True but that's how they get you
Yeah I can't I can't
Seattle
Live in LA
And and I think
These things
People are going to treat them like they do those
Electric bird
How can I
Destroy this
Instagram thing of here I am.
Destroying the Amazon robot
Johnny Miller
County
Oh yeah imma go steal things in Orange
Helen Not only would I not want to be a black guy
Stealing
Robots in Orange
Which county
I wouldn't want to be a black guy in jail for
Kastelan robots that's a lose-lose
To be the robot
How did Teresa do an AR quiz
The reason is very
Wells
She got all
Free write congratulations
Write up handle time for you to answer some questions about this week's news
Alonso forget about the sharks
This summer people all over the world are dealing with
What threat
Jellyfish
No not jellyfish
Not in the water
Look up
The Sun
Seagulls seagulls exactly right
For some reason
Summer for example ocean
City
In New Jersey
Had such a problem with
Seagulls attack
Pinterest on the beach
Fielder food
Did they have imported
Falcon
What's because nothing bad could ever happen by setting a worse animal
Free to control a less worse animal population
Natural predator of falcons
Panthers
Why hate
You keep going backwards but this shouldn't
Be a problem
Too long in New Jersey
Because once all the guys stop
Recycling
They'll be enough garbage for the seagulls to be well-fed
You're actually letting
Falcons runaround
Oceans
City New Jersey reporting falconers
That's a job you can have
In New Jersey
To somebody New Jersey says Alma Falconer he's not really in the mob
He's a falcon
And these guys come in the Falcons apparently they fly around and they don't so much
The taxes Eagles as they scared
The Seagal's away
But that's a problem
Because you know without
Seagull
Their natural
The French fry popular
Couldn't they just get some
Some badass
Pigeons from
New York pick up understand you got a little problem
We can take care of that
We don't want much we just want to dip a Beat
Coming up if there's a bustle in your Hedgerow and I Bluff The Listener game call 1aaa wait wait to play will be back in a minute with me
Wait wait don't tell me
Freemanpedia
Watch Me Whip
Support for wait wait don't
Tell me I'm the following message come
From SimpliSafe Home Security
SimpliSafe is it
Completely wireless
They can be self-installed
In under an hour
SimpliSafe sensors are built
Every point
Access
Dior Homme
And with their video verification
SimpliSafe can visually confirm when a break-in
Is happening
Which can help police get
On the scene
23.5
Bastard
Get free shipping on your system in the 60-day money-back guarantee
Simplisafe.com
Wait
It has already been uneventful summer
Yeah between the Twins
Please play the bass
And the president's battle over immigration
There's a lot
And when there's news you need to know about the NPR politics podcast
Is there to tell you
Not to mention
Hitting the road
So you can meet all of the toy
Olympios going to drive me
Make a booty crazy
The NPR politics
Subscribe
NPR
Mendota vez Chicago this is
Wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Kurtis
We're playing this week with Hari kondabolu
And here again is your host at the
Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown
Chicago
Peter Sagal thank you so much
But now it's time for the wait wait don't tell me
The Listener game call 1aaa wait wait 2player game in the air
How you were
Hi heater is
Jordan Rodgers from Atlanta to Jordan how are you
We are not as happy as you are but frankly I didn't
You're going to play our game and what you must try to tell truth
Food from fiction
Bill what is Jordan
Topic Hedgehog
In the news
Are pandas going to tell you three stories of hedgehogs
In the news pick the one we really saw on the news this week
You'll win our prize await waiter of your
Your choice in your voice
Are you ready to
I'm ready first let's hear from Alonzo
Boden
Imaging Providence
China
Men have begun
Sleeping hedgehogs as he
Hair pieces
Jimmy Kong the inventor the process says
Quote
For some reason we have a
Liege population
Hedgehogs
I noticed they sleep all day and women
Find Aamco
Cute and irresistible
Even petting them while they sleep
It occurred to me that it's a
Exactly how a man would want a woman
When to see him
Cute irresistible and
Occasionally pettable
Fine but how do you get the Hedgehog
Stick to your head
Well I adopted a removable
PizzaRev
They can be applied to the Hedgehog
It works
As long as you're not too loud and avoid sudden
Mentor get to near anything a hedgehog likes to
Kong does not recommend wearing a hedgehog
To your office or the electronic
Ex-factory
And of course does not advise
Is a hedgehog hairpiece
Is the dog on
But he said
Perfect for a
Quiet afternoon date
Stressing
The afternoon
Quote you don't want to be out after dark but
Because hedgehogs are not
Turtle and they tend to wake up hungry
Chinese man comes up with the idea of using hedgehogs for hair pieces
You're next. Hedgehog hullabaloo comes
Helen Hong
It's awkward to have to call the cops
When your neighbors are being too
Too loud
It's particularly awkward when you're
Calling because your neighbors are having loud
Saks
But as many neighborhoods in Germany have been finding out all summer
It's the most awkward when you're loud sex having Neighbors
Turn out to be
Hedgehog
The German version of 911 has been inundated with calls and
Disturbing night
Time noises
Which turn out to be
Freaky Shameless
Exhibitionist
Hedgehog
It's such a common occurrence that the hashtag Eagles set
Or Hedgehog sex
Has been trending on social media
Hedgehogs are capable of making a ranger
Sounds from a
Quiet snuffling
Two kissing
Snarling
Purring
Whistling
Clicking and even loud
Screaming
Which is wet sometimes gets the mistaken for a
Recited humans
According to a Veterinary experts
Hedgehogs
Snore loudly
During the hours-long mating ritual
Which is known in German as
Eagle carousel
Or Hedgehog carousel
Because Urban Hedgehog populations have been.
Declining
Animal experts advise everyone to leave them to their love make
They've also discovered that flashlight
Scare the animals and often break
Pics of the couple
But quiet observation will not
Disturb them
You perm
The Hedgehog carousels in the noise there of distracting people in Germany
Your last ride hedgehogs above-the-fold comes from Hari kondabolu
When Samuel Terry won a $100,000 college scholarship
Via writing contest in
New Zealand
His parents were both shocked and elated
Because he had never shown any interest in creative writing
Indicas
He is 10
However shortly after the winners were announced young Samuel was busted for plagiarism
What do you ward
Committee called a brilliant satire about what happened
When's winter morality is you
Usurp fire sign
Matific advancement
And The Temptations
The power
Was actually just a plot of the early 90 Sega Genesis
Video game
Sonic the Hedgehog
Copy of the video game in the accompanying manual in the family
And decided it was time to write it all down
Even more shocking the award committee Miss some very telling clue
Such as the stories mentioning of
Quote control
And quote
Player 1 and player 2
Professor Dina Johnson sawed this quote represented or need to balance the Divine spirit that controls
With the free will the each of us has as players
In The Game of Life
Samuel claims he didn't know the story had to be original and the rules of the contest
Never said
You could not plagiarize
The contest organizers admit this is true because they just assumed nobody would do that
Tell one of these story about a hedge
Jog or two in the news this week was it from Alonzo bodden hedgehogs being used as toupees
Spiderman in China
From Helen Hong
Hedgehog sex
Spartis
Keeping people up in Germany or
From
Hari kondabolu
The story of a guy who won
$100,000 scholarship just by retelling the story
Sonic the Hedgehog
I am going to go with
Both sexes
German Hedgehog
All the ways go with the sexy
German hedgehogs
What we spoke to an actual Hedgehog
To bring you the truth
Mitchell Carousel is a
Crucial components with the Hedgehog mating ritual
Urx spokesperson for the British Hedgehog preservation society and author of the book of the Hedgehog's dilemma
Talking about the meeting hedgehogs and by the way if you want to get your partner in the mood just talked about Hedgehog
Carousels
With a British accent
Congratulations Jordan you got it right you wanna cry you better 2.4
Helen and the boys like I said you won our prize the voice of anyone you may choose on your voicemail
Congratulations I hope it lived up to your expectation
It was everything and more thank you Jasmine take care
Now the game where we force people we admire to do something they may not like
It is a curse for an actor to be associated with one iconic role the people assume that's all he can do in that sadly my
Might be true for Henry Winkler
His performance is acting teacher Gene Cousineau on HBO
Show Barry is so amazing
That for the rest of his life people will be calling out when they see him
Hey it's the gene
Henry Winkler welcome back to wait wait don't tell me
Thank you thank you how are you
How are you tonight
Making a little joke because of course you played
The Fonz 40 years ago and hasn't gotten to the point
Given the passage of time that more people
Recognize you for a gene on the show Barry than for the cause
It is people yell out bearing
And people yell out the funds but I will say
I'm wearing jeans
Right now
That's true they both were the other one is named Jean the other one wears
Yes
That's where I didn't realize it
Truliant
Do your work
My everything
It is still amazing
But people still do
Refer to you as the van deventer
But I and I think that's wonderful but I don't want to talk to you about the funds this time I want to talk to you about Gene Cousineau this role you play in The Amazing
Really good TV show
She'll bury those who are not lucky enough
To see it every can you describe who Gina is
I am a teacher
Great
Yes
They can pay in cash on time
And I can teach a young man who came into my class
Who has kind of like another job
I'm only finding out about
And he is a necessity
Right and I he has become like a son
Write to me
What was amazing about the show is
Even given that outlandish
Premise that he's a
An assassin who decides who won
How to be an actor in friends an acting class
It really quite moving
Because you say
She does need a father and your character
Kind of provides.
Know that he was as big as much as he
And and then
The two men
Who run the show xiaomi
As I
I started to
To to bring Gina live
You could also have a heart
So then they combine the two
Should my body and lower down
Is more of a jerk
But you're Henry Winkler you can't play a complete
Jerk is not in you
Well you know what I I didn't know that was true but it seems to be
I got to ask you because of the so much of this is said in this acting class did you ever take an acting class and was it like this
You know what I had
Teachers in college
In graduate school and drama
That's cool I did research and I came across
Where there was a teacher here in LA
Literally
Barely made enough
To take his class
Made them by
Is art
Give me like he would paint pictures or whatever
And then sell it to his students
And I I thought
Yes this says everything I need
To know
About this teacher
Wow do you enjoy that aspect of the character being a little grasping and
Ben proulx
You know what I actually never thought of that cuz
When you
YouTube
You doing episode
You do scene by scene
And you concentrate
I'm making that scene
Perfect
And all the
You put all these details together and I watch along with everybody else
I don't see it until it's on the air
Will. I just love going to work
That's why I wonder what that
Would be like
Hahaha
It don't sound great you and I'm so proud of you won an Emmy
For the first season
Yes I did and I was amazed to discover this that was your first Emmy you had a lifetime of television and you've only one this
And I have it on my dining
Table
Really that where you put it in writing
Opposites
Front door so when the mailman delivers
Pictures of medicine from the pharmacy
Oh that old thing
And anybody else who comes in the front door I lead them
Bruzek dining room furniture
I want to ask you something
So you are in the show a few years ago we don't want
Full-time and Paula Poundstone said
That she saw you once
Austin Public just beyond the way that you do
On the same plane
And she said that she thought to herself
There's a happy little fella
So are you going to the fact that I'm sure
Ask you do you think that's an accurate description
It is I I have I live by
Words
Gratitude
Antoinette
Tenacity gets
Take me where I want to go
And gratitude doesn't allow me to be angry along
On the way
Well Henry Winkler it is always a pleasure to talk to you
We've invited you here to play a game
Did this time
We're calling
Who look at the twinkling
You winkle but what do you know about things that twinkle
Star
When I ask you three questions about Winkler's or Stars
Get to write you win our prize
For one of my listeners any voice they might like on their voicemail
Bill who is our friend Henry Winkler playing
Cindy Metcalf of Dallas Texas
Alright Henry ready to do this
We've learned some interesting things about stars
Since we started venturing in
Into space including which of these a
Stars can get bored
B
Stars
Smell like burnt
Steak
Or sea stars
They're just like us
Wow
We have to go with stars are just like us
Very normal person
Actually Stars they're just like us is a future in Us magazine
The real answer was star smell like burn
We didn't notice it was literally true until astronauts
Went out in space
Space suits
And came back and sniff their space suits
Felt weirdly hungry
Because it turns out that stars give off
The number of chemicals one of which
Smells like burnt steak
True
Wow
Subspace
Alright Lisa
Here's your next question
Women classified tens of thousands of
Stars during her decades-long career
The Harvard of
Before that she had another job what was it a
One day the head of the observatory got frustrated with the staff and said my Scottish made could do better
He hired her
She did
Be she was a theater critic who said people are boring I want to watch something else
Or see nobody knows you just showed up one day wearing
Silver suit
Open said
I can help
All right I'm going to eliminate C
Yes
I'm going to call with a
Did she said I'm a Scottish maid could do better you are right
Turns out she was one of those undiscovered Geniuses who became a brilliant math
Competition and astronomers
Discovered among other things
The Horsehead nebula
She is a hero I'll write you have one more question
And she died
90 years ago
Last question
Our sun is a star
About 30% of people staring into the sun will cause
Sneezing fit
What is the
Scientific name of this Reef
Hey
Squinty sneezing
Be solar snot
Horsey
Autosomal compelling helio-ophthalmic
Outburst
Or at
Shoe
I'm going to go with Shay
You go see autosomal compelling helio-ophthalmic
Ophthalmic Outburst or at you you're right
How did Henry Winkler do an AR quiz
Tell Henry to out of
3 right
Is a very good store that means um
Henry Winkler is nominated
For another Emmy for his role on HBO's Barry he has a children's book alien Superstar coming out this fall
Henry Winkler what a joy to talk to you thank you so much for coming back
In just a minute bill says I move it's a matrimonial listener Limerick challenge
Call 1aaa
From NPR
Support for wait wait don't tell me in the following message
It comes from rocket mortgage
It's by Quicken Loans
Imagine how it feels to have an award-winning team of mortgage
Make the home buying process
Smoother for
The history of industry-leading online lending technology
Rocket mortgage is changing the game
Visit rocket
Mortgage.com weight
Equal Housing lender
Licensed in all 50 states
NMLS consumer access.org number 3030
Rocket mortgage
Myquickenloan
Push button
Get mortgage
Hey it's Maria
Host of NPR
Latino USA
The podcast that takes you inside the Latinas
Text conversation
Each week will bring you stories that will Fascinate and offense
LotteryUSA
Listen And subscribe down
From NPR and WBEZ Chicago
The NPR news quiz
I know Curtis where you're playing this week
And Helen Hong and
That's a Chase Bank Auditorium
Chicago PD
Thank you girl take everybody
Spirit animal
The Rhinoceros
It's a listener Limerick challenge
That's 180 date 92489
Do for some more questions for you from the week
Alonzo the future we were promised me
May finally be here this week a man named Franky Zapata
Became the first person ever to cross the English Channel on what
Sly
Flying car
No not my car
Even cooler more futuristic
Jetpack
Blue crocodile bag
Technically
I appreciate your charitable
That you stand
So that's it
Look at that is close enough
Do all the way across the English
Channel Lake George Jets
And this is important cuz once brexit happened this will be the only way you can travel between France
Ants in Britain
This guy named Franky Zapata design the thing himself it looks like a big drone you know the flying things Alexa
Like a big version of that you
Stand on
Any fluid across the channel in 22 minutes
Zoo
Amazing
He had to land on a
Platform
Halfway across the
And he says that
Standing on the Platte
Forum
Flying through the air 210 miles an hour head first
Is incredibly painful
He said I tried to enjoy it and not think about
The pain
What was the
The Pain part on a Segway
No I'm not an idiot
Well Helen I have been on it that way
The phone's about to enjoy the occasional Segway ride my tell you that it's actually very tiring in your
Could you kind of bracing yourself against the motion
Multiply that
New Balance lacrosse so he says it hurt a lot
Which is kind of sad imagine
Neil Armstrong stepping out of the lunar lander and saying
One small step for man and all my
Read this is what all the
The equinox
People are going to do now
Hurry there's a new trend in bathing and it involves never ever
Doing what
Is it washing your hair
That's included
Not using soap
That's also included
Not bathing exactly right
Apparently more and more people are
Foregoing showers and soap opting instead
According to the guardian
Newspaper
To quote encourage friendly microbes to live on them
Turning your entire body into kombucha
A stinky thing very few people like that sometimes has a
Fix, on top of it
The people are saying a bit they say bathing is bad for you they say soap
Is dries out your skin that's even natural biome
That's good for you
Do you leave it on and they say
Did they stop
Smelling
After a couple of weeks
Because
Your friends can't complain about you and all your friend
Wet
Even do any little
Spot treating
Not like a little early enough there's there's one guy who's into this lifestyle his name is David Whitlock
He says he is not bathe
The for 15 years and he says
Quotes
If I get a specific part of my body dirty then I'll watch that specific
Pick-A-Part
And now you can't get the picture ID
I just found your dad if your head Daniel
Coming up it's lightning fill in the blank the first it's the game where you have to listen for the Rhine if you'd like to play on are called leave a message
1-aaa wait wait
That's one 888-924-8924 or
The contact us link on our website wait wait
That npr.org
Can find out about
Attending our weekly
Free live shows
Right here at the Chase Bank Auditorium in
Chicago upcoming shows August 2019
In 30th at Wolf Trap
Just outside
Of Washington
At September 12th at the New Jersey Performing Arts Center in
Newark
New Jersey
Before all you people with smart speakers check out the wait wait
Quiz it's a whole new quiz just for you and you might even win the voice of your choice
Free voicemail just say play the wait wait quiz
Hi you're on wait wait don't tell me
Desiree cool name where you from where you calling from
I'm calling from Blackfoot Idaho
Blackfoot whole wow Idaho I've never been to that part of Idaho is as beautiful as I have been told
Normal
Way to sell your hometown dude
Welcome to the show ban
Bill Kurtis is going to redo 3 News related limerick
Back to the last word or phrase missing
Sing for me tribute
Can fill in that last word or phrase
Correctly into the limo
Which will be when are you ready to play
Alright well
Then let's do it here is your first love
Like a Cayenne
It'll help
Wooden legs
Spell
Right
You never see dogs or cats
Flail
This appendage or limb also helps at the gym
I Prevail with mine
The new robot
Hell yeah say company in Japan
Has developed a strap-on smart tail
Designed to stabilize the elderly
By helping maintain their balance
You said you think your aunt is dangerous now wait till she becomes Doctor Octopus with
The guy didn't like his Tails movements and
Strategic wait actors
The counterbalance
False
Sleek metal design makes you look terrifying
The way this conversation would go with your loved ones Grandma we've all been talking
We all think
It's time for you to have a
What if you fail forward though
We are really cool
If that tail was on the front of you
Here's your next limerick
In the cheap airlines seat where I sat
I was straight
Maya twice
Airborne rap
When vampires
They need comforting
Pets
So
Sharing this flight
With her
The back yes a Newark bound
Spirit Airlines flight
The flight frenzy when a bat started flying around the cabin
Of course the bat wanted to go to New Jersey everyone was afraid of the bat until they realize that
Spirit that's your in-flight meal
Free emotional support dog
No it was just a bat that got on the plane
Somehow the bat got on the plane and they didn't find it I took off and I was in
The bat flying around the cabin what is lazy
A bat
Plane is basically a Segway
Before applying at home
Here is your last
Limerick
What I melter
The cow gave a shudder
My milk made hearts
Started
Weather
I tugged it
It said
And I said
Baidu
Light bulb Put a Ring
A Dairy Farmer in Singapore
Made headlines around the world for
Proposing to his girlfriend
By slipping a ring around her
Cow's udder
So should be surprised when she win
To milk it
We don't know yet if the woman said yes but we do know is technically the
The farmer is now engaged
To the cow
Put the ring on that's what happened
Which is pointless everybody knew he was already getting the milk
For free
So you have to get it
On the other
That's the girls fart
What do you think about it
I mean a ring another it sounds crazy but it's just a kind of
Bill how did been doing AR quiz
Congratulations
Support for NPR and the following message
Come from the real real
Deleting reseller of all
Authenticated luxury item
Shop luxury
Clothing accessories in
Fine Arts
An unreal price
From your favorite designer
Like Louis Vuitton
Gucci Cartier
And hundreds more
And the real real authenticate
Beach item
To ensure it's guaranteed office
Shopping store on the app
Or at the realreal.com
And receive 20% off select items
Wish promo code real
Now onto my final game lightning fill in the blank each of our players wives
60 Seconds
In which the answer as many fill-in-the-blank questions
Is he or she can
Each correct answer is not worth
Bill can you please give us
The scores all right and Alonzo each have to Helena
Well
What's Cesar Helena
All right
We flip the coin and Alonzo has decided to go first so here we go the clock
What's up when they begin your first question fill in the blank
On Wednesday President Trump was meant by protest
Stairs during his visits
To Dayton and
Blank El Paso
The Dow drops 500 points
Stop your blanket be valued at their
China beloved and The Bluest Eye Nobel Prize winner blank
This week the world's first-ever hotel for
Blanks opened in London
Dog snowhotel for houseplants
This week this week doctors in Rwanda stepped up efforts
To prevent blank
From spreading to the country
The bowl of rice on Tuesday movie Giant blanket
What's the monthly price of its upcoming video streaming service
Business right after receiving a 911 call from a hungry boy asking for pizza
Police in Florida blank
Deliver the pizza exactly
But first they went to his house and told him an important lesson about how to use 911
Authorities at the Sanford Florida Police Department
3 officer
Three officers
To the boys house where they talk to them about what
In emergency
Annies pizza no matter how delicious
This is not an emergency
Tell me what the Pizza Hut pizza
The boy said he's learned his lesson and next time he called nine-one-one he'll be sure to ask
Free breadsticks
It's as well
Total of 14
Then puts him in a very
All right make him uncomfortable
Fill in the blank
On Tuesday President Trump
Suda California over there new law requiring presidential candidates
To release their blank
Textron
That's right after tripping outside his home in Kentucky Senate Majority Leader blank
And fractured his show
Mitch McConnell escalating battle over
The disputed Kashmir region Pakistan and
Suspend all trade with black
Cindy
Right on Wednesday Puerto Rico Supreme Court ruled that the swearing-in of the territories new blank was
Additional
Responding to rumors that he had died
The president of Turkmenistan blanked
To prove that he was still alive
Shut up
Video no he did Donuts
What's in front of a giant flaming pit called the gateway to Hell
Following the shootings over the last weekend web company Cloud fire announce
Cutting ties
Controversial online message
Bordeaux Blanc
Right on Thursday President Trump said he was considering commuting the sentence
Disgraced Illinois governor blank
The blog blog
Rod Blagojevich
Purdue basketball player
And showed he was blank
Does pregnant
Cooper plays for the European league and he tried to cheat
The drug test by using his
Friends urine
I got some great news
His shooting accuracy
Is really high haha suspended
2 / 4
2 years which
It is a pretty amazing
Opportunity leave
And this is how he found out
They were going to have a baby
Congratulations your soon-to-be an unemployed dad
Bill how did Harry doing are quickly slipped into the lead they got seven ride
14 more points
16 is how many then does Helen Hong
Need to win
7 big ones
We got hella this is for the game fill in the blank
On Thursday the US
Issued a travel advisory over
Free continued pro-democracy
The protests in blank
Hong Kong right according to new report Apple has added software to the new blanket
Third party
Battery repair
IPhone
This week former Vice President Joe Biden accused blank of Fanning the
White supremacy
Trump
Wednesday 680 people were arrested
During ice raid
Is in blank
Who reportedly asking NYPD officers
To blank
Stop eating Donuts
No to help his daughter move
My markdown Monday authorities in Minnesota charge
Disgraced R&B singer blank
Two counts of solicitation
R Kelly on Wednesday paleontologist
Discovered the bones of the Giants
The blank that was a
Call the small child
Hedgehog
A woman in Florida is waiting on repairs after lightning struck near her home and blank
Lightning strike near home and
I'm headed Hedgehog exploded
The woman said she was startled awake by the loud
Sounds you never heard
Only to find that her bathroom with the disaster area
Your toilet have been shattered into a thousand
True that the lightning had struck her septic tank
Igniting the methane gas inside it
Shenzhen explosion
Listen to the pipes and into her bathroom
At least
That's what her husband said
Report nervously excusing himself in rushing out the door
Did Helen do well enough to win if you got 5 right 10 more points
Is the winner of the
Skypanel has to predict now that nobody's using SoulCycle what will be the next big exercise fat but first let me tell you
WBEZ
Chicago in association with urgent haircut Productions
Steve berman Eminem
Mxr public address announcer
Paul Freedman
Who is Beth Novey
This week we say goodbye tour in
Nina Beatty and Lila
Francis peanut
You will never
Be a professional Dart player but I know I'll sound great on your podcast Sunday
Delilia more energy than anyone should and without your listener feedback newsletter I would never know how many mistakes I make each
BJ's
Technical directions
Is an ops manager Colin Miller a production manager is Robert Newhouse
Angelica
Is Michael dead
Mount Hamel after SoulCycle what will be the next big exercise craze Hari kondabolu
Every time your local radio station has a pledge Drive
Run around the block where they at
Ask you for money
You might lose NPR
But you'll definitely
Lose some weight
Helen Hall
Counting all the Democrats running for president
Huge number
Ed Alonzo book
Simply jumping to conclusion
Well if any of that happens will
That's who I bought it on wait wait don't tell me
Little Lonzo ball to all of you for listening
This
Is NPR