Support for this podcast
Send the following message
Did come from
Struggling to find a purpose
Vacation home
VRBO does the hard work for
Matching you to the perfect place to stay
Every time
Download VRBO
Go in the App Store
Let Virgo find a home
That matches
From NPR and WBEZ Chicago
This is wait wait don't tell me
Tell me the NPR news
With the Herculean task
Filling in for Bill Carter
I'm one of the voices of
NPR's credit
GOP Inc
And here is your host at the
The Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown Chicago Peter Sagal
Thank you so much we have a great trip you today you really do
Saturday Night Live star 80 Bryant will be joining us later to play not my job
We are so excited to welcome Chucky I answered back
Back to the show Bill Kurtis
Is overseas this week
It's easy for him
He doesn't have to
The fly
He just goes to the beach
Commands the seat apart
And walks there
All you have to do to get to us as pick up your phone give us a call the number is 10008 wait wait
That's one 888-924-8924 it's time to welcome my first listener contesting
How you around wait wait don't tell me
Hi this is Madeline calling from Austin Texas
They're great
Beautiful hair
When that happens when that takes over the city do you
Do you participate or you just hide formatting
Wait till it's over
I was able to
The clasp
There was all traffic
Welcome to the show Madeline let me introduce
Guitar panel
First step is a writer for WGN man of the people had a comedian will be appearing at storytellers on a mission on March 4th
Xxx with Tom bodett the latches
Theater in Brattleboro Vermont
It's Adam Burke
Hello Mad Max at the host of fake the nation
Chilling author of how to make white people laugh you can read her column
Hemming and hawing and
The progressive magazine it's in the game facade
The host of the podcast
Obituaries and the just emmy-nominated host of innovation
Asian Nation
CBS
Well welcome to the show Madeline You're Gonna Play who's kyoki this time Giants and filling in
If a bill is going to redo three quotations from this week's
If you can correctly identify or explain just two of them you will win our prize
Any voice for Marshall you might choose
On your voicemail you ready to play
I am alright let's
Hear your prayers quote
I barely know him but just take a look
A stone-cold loser and husband
From hell that was President Trump
Talking about a man named George
George Conway
He's not just another Stone Cold loser he's also married
To whom
Kellyanne Conway George Conway husband
Senior presidential advisor kellyanne Conway
Is being sober
Viciously attacked by President Trump
You'd think he was a recently deceased beloved American war hero
Or a rerun of Saturday Night Live
George Conway
Dr. Donald Kelly and his
Defending Donald
It's this wacky sitcom
No one wanted to see
It's like a combination of The West Wing
Married with Children and To Catch a Predator
Treated like the Oscar
Transfer the husk
From Hell title
Do you need to
Holder of that title
It would be so stressful to have that couple
Like they come over dinner
It would be like this
This meal is amazing
It's going to nourish a lot
The people and then Georgia be like
This meal is narcissistic personality disorder terrible
The reason is came about
Is George Conway again the husband of the president senior advisor
Has been highly critical of
The president Twitter calling him among other things
Juvenal
Boorish unfit for office incompetent and mentally unstable
What is his wife's boss
So hard to understand
Possible is just PR
Right
You know they're all just doing this
For sure as if the beginning of his presidency
Donald Trump said to kellyanne
I need from Aulani and I not to be the most unbelievable marriage in the country what can you do
I think it probably I think it's called
I don't know
The romance
Cancel
Subtweet at the president
But I can I just say if like
Your theories at their hate
Every night yeah yeah
Yeah
Sometimes it mix it up and they talk about present
She hates
Should have chosen for their say
Safeword the phrase no collusion
That means I haven't gotten anywhere in years
Madeline here is your next quote
We apologize for
Now that was a statement from the antique
Social media company Myspace
They were sorry for the inconvenience they caused their former users
When they misplace
What
I was like everyone's music
Everything
Basically
Welcome to my space now with even more space
Remember Myspace assertive an early version of Facebook
Without
Any users or the destruction of Western democracy
Back in the day
A lot of people
Uploaded all kinds
The content to their Myspace
This page is including music and writing in photos
Gone Myspace
Says it was lost and they were trying to try
Transfer to new
Computer in a cat pulled out a plug
Or my space was just tidying up
None of your lives between 2003 and 2012
Spark Joy
That is the thing that hasn't been massive outcry about his
That's okay I don't have like
400 piece
Pictures of sublime fanart
The Cry for Help like my space is like
Does anyone still care about us
You don't got to throw ourselves into the ocean
That's all right yeah yeah
What what
Your son
I believe 2008 lost everything between 2003 and 2000
12 what is that
Like Stone Temple
Pilots what are the what are those Emo music or whatever they are doing at the time and there is
Men wearing cargo pants
Forever
Is Reams and reams of Lincoln
Theme park fan
Now you're last quote is
About a new trend in fashion it's
The quote from the New York Post
Talking about the supermodel's Bella and
Gigi Hadid
The gals know how to coordinate their out
To their new Brainiac
Why what have the Hadid sisters made in
New
Must-have fashion
Accessory
Just by being photograph
Carrying one
Very good Madeline
Only good ones only used by models to snort cocoa
New album books are instantly hot accessory cuz of the hadid's
The world's top
Supermodel
Have been spotted carrying books going so far
Coordinate them with her
Hoot
Outfit Couture outfits are one by owls
Gigi Hadid was spotted carrying kimonos book The Stranger while Bella was spotted
The Stephen King novel nothing makes you look
Look skinnier
Then posing with a 900-page copy of the stand
I love it it's a vintage accessory
It's like Instagram but just the comments
I love that we all assume that they're not judge
Just the covers
The books where the inside is
Lip gloss under cocaine
Believe that they're real
The greatest
Plastic fascia
Expect of a model which
Just totally blank of any game
Is the kind of expression people have on their reading books
Reading fat exactly now
What's a great when you're supermodel of course because
You're actually so skinny you can use yourself
What is a bookmark
Peter when you read out Moby-Dick deviated to the left or to the right
What does this is defective supermodels are now
Reading books
What is great news for NPR listeners
Because you all now have one thing in common with
Supermodels
Chucky how did Madeleine doing our quiz
Madeline duggen
Ingest pose
She got three correct
Making her a winner
Congratulations
Reddit panel it is time for you to answer
What are some questions about this
Week's news
Mo Congressman Devin Nunes
This has filed a
250 million dollar lawsuit
Against Twitter
And against one account in particular for defending him
Star supposedly coming from his what
Cow
How is a Twitter account
Congressman's Wrath
With tweets like
Devin is utterly worthless
Devon is Wei Wei
Hey
Over his head and cry and he may be
Movie
To prison
Because of this lawsuit
This account which had a couple of hundred followers
Now has more than Devin Nunes
Himself it has over 600000 followers it's a social media star
It's kind of a
Kim Kardashian
Run for Congress now
It's possible I guess
What's amazing is
Nobody knew
About these
Obscure Twitter accounts that were dragging Devin Nunes
Until he filed sitting congressman
A lawsuit
That list
All these pain
Fantastic insults
We got all of those from the lawsuit
I mean
Sho Nuff
How badly he's been teased he's like a kid is bullied in junior high school
Assertive saying yeah and then they shove me in the locker like lifting he climbs in and then they
Prospectus wasn't real cow
That's a good question did he even know
And also isn't this the literal definition of a Twitter beef
Coming up our panelist are busting brackets
I will be back in a minute with more wait wait don't tell me
From NPR
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Message come from Stanford children
One of the scariest things
Mom look
Because the next words are you sure
Billy can fly
Or Joey riding the dog
Or a crayon stuck in Valerie's nose
Hear something
You might want
With over 20
Pediatric office
Stanford pediatric
Christians are all over
The Bay Area
Not just in Palos
Find a Stanford
At Stanford children
I'm about boiling host of NPR's all songs
Considered and creator
Tiny desk
Series I have a message for unsigned musicians
All across
Enter the 2019 tiny desk contest
For a chance
The place your
Very own
Tiny desk concert
It'll change your life
So no matter what kind of
We want to hear
Find out more at npr.org
Tiny desk contest
Sunday 8
14th
Better hurry
From NPR and WBEZ Chicago
This is wait wait don't tell me
Make the NPR news
I'm one of the voices of NPR
Are credits and the voice of your NPR fantasy
GOP is filling in for Bill Curtis Ware playing this week with Mo Rocca
The game pawn shop in Edinburg
And here again is your house
At the Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown Chicago
Peter Sagal Beauty okay right now
The Listener game call 1aaa wait wait to play our game on the air
Hi you are on wait wait don't tell me
Hi this is
I'm calling from wilbraham ma
Wilbraham Massachusetts I've traveled message
To sit back and forth but I've never been to Wilbraham where is that
It's in the western part of
Temperature in Wilbraham
Right now
But I I just moved back from text
You were
How do you find the experience of
Cooper Democrat
I think people have this impression that has a lot of
Cowboys and the
The photos were created
That's great I think the only people who want us to believe the Texas
This is filled with Cowboys Ark
Welcome to the show Kristen
You are here to play our game and what you must try to tell to
Truth from fiction
Chucky what is Kristen's topic
I'm mad
March Madness
Mad it is time
For March Madness
That's when everybody pretends to
Care about college basketball
Do they can watch
TV at
But our panel is going to take about another competition
That caught our attention this month
Pick the one who's telling the truth and you'll win our prize the waiter of your choice on your voicemail
Ready to play
Yes. Let's
Hear from
Adam
It's that time of year again when the nation
Make believe
Sportsmobile
Roll up their sleeves dust off their special drafting laptops
I'm picked her fantasy football and baseball team
They'll come up with a hilarious name
Pour over stats and blogs
I know definitely calling you in the break room
To tell you all about it
Regardless of your level of Interest
But fear not
TDM fan
There now exists an even dollar version of your coworker
Chris favorite hobby
That's right
Fantasy bird watching
Finally attack
I never thinking cool
Is that where I get to see a Hypocrites mate with a phoenix
Not even remotely
The brainchild of vicarious ornithologist in the all-around uber-geek mat
Smith
Fancy bird-watching involves picking
Spa in America
Frequented by real-life bird watches
And then scoring points every time
Actual avian
Infuse yet report
Seeing a rare or common species
Turn online database
I know right
Sure you can go bungee jumping off the Golden Gate Bridge or
Flying a wingsuit through the Grand Tetons
But for sheer White Knuckle excitement
Nothing beats the adrenaline pounding thrill of scoring eight points every time some burger in the field spot the red
Red breasted nuthatch
Blue-footed booby for Hope of Hope
San Clemente loggerhead shrike
Because it's much baby and are you ready for some birdwatching
Fantasy bird watching from Adam
Broke your neck Story the game we're Gaga for
Comes from the game facade
Referees are never the belle of the ball
ESPN
Include a guy in stripes
It's blowing a whistle on the highlight
Real but rest are sick and tired of it
If they wanted to work
Incredibly hard for low pay and only get noticed when they
They screw up
They would have been a winner
A group of referees in Lacrosse
Sportsland
Keep have launched their own games where they can
Can finally shine
This is competitive refereeing we're a referees ability to judge a competition
Isn't it self judge
As a competition
Challenges include being timed on timing and
Red flag throwing
Precision
Agility skills are tested for how fast they can get out of the way of a
Play
After a questionable game-deciding call their tested on their composure while reading
Through a Twitter
Read where the entire globe
After winning the coveted golden whistle
NFL ref
Jeff triplette having watch
Touchdown
His four years did his own jail
Described as a white
A competition for referees themselves to compete
Your last
The story of the new competition comes from Morocco
Call it
March sister math
60/40
Teams of four women
Each team representing the for March
Sisters in the novel Little Women
Square Off
It's an event that combines the high-stakes
Savannah NCAA basketball with
Exploding popularity of Louie
Louisa May Alcott cosplay
Each player has a
Clear roll
The Joey
Is the team captain
She basically does everything on the court
The Meg place
For the first half then meets a guy gets married
Second-half watching with him and their children from
Beat
The game or help the other players
She just cheer
Former self the whole time no one really likes her
The wildcard
Pristina
The bath
She lied
Surrounded by her dolls
I was on a stretcher
Courtside
Offering words of comfort
The bands of a
And showing things for
For children
And then she died
Whichever team's back
Garners more sympathy invariably advance
Bracket
The March sisters of Purdue or top-seeded this year
Superior choice
Does Kristen you got from Adam Berg
Fantasy birding
In which people don't actually go outside
But just sort of
Score points
Where birds are found by other people
From nageen farsad a competition finally for referees to
Themselves
Or from Morocco March sister Madness
About which I can say no more
Wow
Adam two-story well
We spoke
To someone involved in
The real story to bring you
Tennessee bird eclipse
Amanda bahney the fantasy murder
And science writer at Gizmodo
Congratulations cousin you got it right Adam was telling the truth in his own particular way Sebring 2.4 him
Voice of anyone you might choose your voicemail thank you so much in French
And now the game where people go a long way just to come home and try and pin secretly counts II
Cancel that can go away again it's called
Not my job
Like a lot of stars
The comedy 80 Bryant got her start doing sketch comedy in Chicago at 2nd
Can City and Ajo and many other places
Then she went up to New York and Saturday Night Live
Which is been in the cast for the last seven
1 seasons and now she
Who stars in her own TV show
Shrill on Hulu it is
The pleasure to walk
Aidy Bryant Chicago
Is it true to say like a lot of very funny
People you've always
Funny you were like
The class clown
I was always
He's trying to
To be funny that we're sure that's all of that
You were you were doing comedy like as an improv
When you're gone
Yeah yeah
Teen Improv
You know you are
I asked what was
What's the name of
Your Improv
In Phoenix
Oh my
I've been in so many dumb
Improv teams I can't even
Droppin science Hunter
Family crest
Virgin daiquiri what else
I used to
Sitting with Carl and the passions sometimes I mean
I've done my time
Did you come to Chicago specifically to do
Do sketch comedy
Yeah yeah I knew about
Second City and IO and I wanted to
Yeah and you did we just kind of amazing a
Right I mean cuz a lot of people come to Chicago to try to make
It's my birthday.
Wait wait
You're actually alright I need this Kendrick
You say that
When I
Checked into my hotel
Today
You were right
Well that's nice
On the cover of Michigan Avenue
Well I always wait for men in their hotel room I think that's cool
What was it
A lot of times we hear about the
People who came out of
Chicago
Go to Saturday Night Live and what was it like
When you were just like
Working the street
Oh my God just standing in the corner of Michigan and Randolph
Somebody named Anna
So you went off to New York like a lot of Chicago comedians
Is do and you understand
Saturday Night Live cold open
What you got
Is rarer
People talk about that Saturday Night Live audition
Keep it coming with the character
Did you do that
I did yeah they told
Galaxy Note 5 minutes
The couple original
Purple empress
Can you tell us which
I did Adele and I did
Ethel Merman witch
Is very top
I said
This is Ethel Merman on the T
TV show my dog
What
Screamed in an Ethel Merman voice like my dog ate what
Was what got me this Saturday night
I love that I understand you I understand you recently got married
I did.
I hope you didn't make a mistake of marrying another
Yeah I did
Yeah how'd that work out
It's going real bad I don't know how
What's going to go on so sorry
Propose in a funny way
Kind of
In that like
He proposed in our home which I could
It's sort of sad
Private anime
How do you say
We know more like we would
People like get free
What's Tijuana
Jump back
And so I kind of came home from work
And open the door and then just like a
True bat out of hell like
From the back of our bedroom he came around like
Baby
Really yeah but it was it was
Yeah
Do you think it was a surprise and you were flustered you wouldn't say no
No I think he knew that
He had a very short
Time between me answering the door and walking you in 10 steps
Before my bra and anything would come off
And he wanted to catch me fully dressed and dignified
That's very thoughtful
The most romantic thing in the world
Well
Aidy Bryant we're delighted to have you here but we have asked
You here today to play a game
That this time
We are calling
80 Bryant
Eat the 80
Brian
You're too young to remember
But way back when we had a decade
Call the 80
And it was filled with wondrous
Amazing people
All of whom
Where named Brian
Brittany asked you three questions about 80s Bryan
Head to right you want a prize winner list
Wait can I ask
Your aunt please
On the spot
You give at least
One of the
Okay
I love that
Chucky who is Aidy Bryant playing
Dan Martin of Boston
First question
Composer and producer Brian
You know
Produced some of the biggest hits of the 1980s
Which of these was among his most
Popular works
Hey the main title theme
Name for Police Academy 8
Bribe me with a
The spoon
Be the startup sound
Before Windows 95
For the music and lyrics
For a Hoover vacuum
I mean this
Bad
Oh yes it's Terrell
See going to go for the
Hoover vacuum
I don't
That can't be right
The Cathy the cat
Guess what
Baby
All right bring out the Ethel Merman that, at all
Cheap Brian Eno
Was paid $30,000 to write the
The sound
The Windows 95
Started
Can you turn it off
Alright next question Bryan
DePalma
Director of the 1983
Scarface
Was forced by the MPAA
To make several cuts to get the
The film down from an x-ray
To get an R rating
After doing so what did he do
A a giant mound of
Cocaine
Be he put the deleted scenes back in because he figured no one would notice
Where's sihi
Who sang the vocals in a
Hoover vacuum jingle
Ime 9
I'm realizing I don't
YouTube
Okay I'm going to say
Actually be
Just put all the cutscenes back in the movie
Yasso
Failing our friends and boss
No you're not
You're not
Because you forget
His last one right
Cuz she didn't use you
That maybe Alaska
Last question to get this right you in
The last question is about Brian Johnson he was the lead
Singer Avicii
CDC what are the great bands
7-18-18
On the same day he auditioned
Beetle eats
Singer of ACD
Rihanna day and night
A few hours earlier what was he doing
He was doing AC repair
DC Comics
He was doing Dirty deeds and he was doing them dirt cheap
Or seen he was singing the vocals in a Hoover vacuum genuine
I mean
It's not see I got to be
To the Moon
Literally the day he successfully audition to be the lead singer of AC DC Brian Johnson
What do a commercial Studio
Any recorded this jingle
For Hoover vacuum
There you go
That sounds like something you would do on a Saturday Night Live
Yeah
Chucky
How did Aidy Bryant do in Ark with very funny and she got two out of three right making her a winner
It's all good
Switch on Hulu you can also see her on Saturday Night Live
Thank you so much for being with us
Chucky shows us his fancy new pants in the listener Limerick challenge
But 1-aaa wait wait to join us in the air will be back in a minute
Wait wait don't tell me
From NPR
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Sagemcom from Park Inn
The newest Resort
In the center of the Las Vegas
It's where Lady Gaga Bruno Mars and arrows
Bring down the house
In the intimacy of
The Park theater
It's where La Chef Roy Choi
Mashes up Korean flavors at his new restaurant best
Be inspired
At Eataly Market
Enjoy your spin on
Fine dining
And let it all go
At on the record
Biggest hits
First speaker
Park MGM
Intimate moments
Big Xperia
The world is
Complicated
And for many of us
History class was
Long time ago
That's where we come in
I'm run. V f
Armanti never blue
And where the host
Trulite NPR's new history
Podcast every week will they get forgotten
Stories in the moments that shaped our world
History like you've never heard
From NPR and WBEZ Chicago
This is wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news
Filling in for Bill Kurtis
I'm the man whose voice makes
The Joyce Foundation
So good
Topix
We're playing this week with Mo Rocca
Nageem farsad
God and Adam Burke
And here again is your house
At the Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown Chicago Peter Sagal
Just a minute milky will tell us where
Sup poet
For NPR comes from
Challenge if you like to play give us a call at 1 AAA wait wait
Ip188 92489
I-24 right now panel some more questions for you for the week's new
Making a new study shows
That it is exactly they
33 the
Begin doing what
At age 33 on the people tend to do this but now we know
Starts at age 33
Weird because that's also the date
Jesus year Jesus died
Coincidence
People start
Like really trying to identify their life
To the scorn of NPR listeners
Come on now
People are like a wrecked cars for 8 years
It's been great and they celebrate no
Didn't either have it or you just had your first child. This is going to start to happen to you
You very soon
Your
Pewter swells up
I get a title
I don't know
When you haven't when you have a kid
What are you
A parent right and so therefore
What do you start Maybe
To turn into
Europe
Now we know exactly what it happen
When you turn 33 or thereabouts which
Is Wyatt your 30s
3rd birthday party
You said to yourself wow by this age
My cousin was a docker
Scientist officer
This week that you're not an adult until you're Thirty
So that means
3 years
Of course
If you free sample turn into your mother right well
She turned
Into her mother
And her mother turned into her mother
So basically
Everybody ends up being
Exactly like our very first
Human ancestor
New Scientist
Is defined as the first
And primordial Africa
Never to stop doing what I was doing and said he was off
Oh my God I'm turning into my mom
33 is of course as you said the age
The Jesus was when he
He was crucified he didn't
Quite turn into his dad but he did decide to go live with
Beguine the
Presence of men
Can have a negative impact on women in the workplace
Need to tell you that
But a new study shows that women may have a lower income in their lifetime
If they spend an extended
Good. Of time
Wiz
Email
In what very specific
I Isaac actually it.
Swollen uterus and are exactly what's coming up
Yes what we mean is that women
Who had a male fraternal twin
Ie
They were they were rejected together
Tend to have lower career incomes than those
Female twins
Who had
A female
Well
This
It seems to have to do with the amount of testosterone
Family Birthing
No man will just suck the life right now
Start very early cuz you know mom's having a sonogram at
When she hears the heartbeat and all the sudden another heartbeat interrupts and says
Actually it's thumbs up
Are the amniotic
Explaining that the umbilical cord is really a way for them to get the internet in there
Mo Andrew Yang is yet another Democrat running for
The president you probably never heard of him
But he started making headlines this week when he staked his claim as the
The only Canada
Get to come out firmly
And strongly against
What
This is going to help him make the cut but he's
Is against Circle
That's right
Cutting Edge,
Healthcare is
Going to once again be a top issue in 2020
So there's one candidate out there was letting you know
That if you like your foreskin
You can keep it
Andrew Yang who is an entrepreneur and otherwise seemingly unqualified person
He came out this week and said circumcision is not in
Necessary
So what we don't yet know yet
Change policy in the budget overall we do know there are some cuts
Simply want me
No I mean
Maybe it's
Because
Maui Shore
Turmoil
I feel a little
About to say this guy is going to Wither in the face of the mohel lobby
She's considering commissioning a
Full on
Life-size holographic
They can be in two places at once
Really
Is the Hologram going to be circumcised
Coming up with Laney fill-in-the-blank but first it's the game where you have to listen for the rhyme if you like to play an air call and leave a message at 1
AAA Thwaites
That's one 888-924-8924 eclipse
The contact us link on our website
Wait wait. Npr.org day you can find out about attending our weekly live shows
Right here at the Chase Bank Auditorium in Chicago
In St Louis on May 9th
I want to try a new interactive quiz
If your smart speaker is updated every Wednesday just say
Open the wait wait
Quiz and you can win a chance to get the voice of your choice and your voice
Just shut up answers like you normally do but don't be frank
When this time
We talk
Byron wait wait don't tell me
Hello my name is Autumn O'Toole from
Huntington West Virginia in Huntington West Virginia
What are you do that
I
Person that finds kids
Oh you do
Nothing important thing to be doing
Welcome to the show Auto
Chucky I answered right here is going to read your 3 News related limericks for the last word or phrase missed
Sing for me
If you can fill in that last word or phrase correctly into Olympics will be a winner Ready To Fly
Here is your first
Tho Hotel guests
Say grody
Endnote
On hand washing
Daehwi give
Hope
We take slightly used
Bars
Remove hair
Burnished scars
And Wallah we are we
Recycling old
Hilton announced this week that their new eco-friendly business practice
Is recycling
All the partial use
Soaps from their hotel room
Ten bars of soap are made out of
These previous guest private I mean soap
And I should mention the new soap is sanitized before it's formed a new bars Unfortunately they clean it by rubbing it with another used bar
Hilton helps reduce 1 million bars
Recycle to apply October 15th which is global handwashing day
Maybe that's where we just set aside one day a year to wash her hands
Let's go back to the good old days
Sofas made out of
The guts of a whale
Here is your next
Limerick
Does space flight
Is meant to
Inspire us
One side effects
Less than desirable
Low gravity scares up
Herpes
To flare up
Cuz spaceflight will wake up
Virus yes exactly right of virus after not teleporting weird and
Surprising flare-ups of herpes in space
That's right
Space herpes
We finally understand the red spot on jupite
Apparently in this rain
Oh my God
Viruses
Resurge
Right so all of a sudden after not reporting
Outbreaks
Get a feel for Houston
They're getting calls from astronauts
Like Houston
I have a problem in
You might want to get checked out to
I hope we don't end up recycle
Their self
That's absolutely true
Where is your last
Limerick
I don't know which way high fashion lean
From my pants Lexile choose in between
Get them skinny or wide
Oh I just
Can't decide
So I'll get me some
Some lopsided
Guess jeans very good
The new hot thing in jeans asymmetry
One leg is really tight the other is loose
And flowing it's like one leg
Belongs to
Skinny hipster
The other leg belongs to Barack Obama
The perfect for anyone who's left leg has just been stung by a swarm of bees
My friend has some serious shoplifting plans
In any event designer says this is definitely an artistic choice
And not the result of
Massive man
Manufacturing error at the factory
Chucky how did Autumn doing AR quiz
She got them all right a perfect score
Congratulations autumn
July
Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Park
The newest Resort
What in the center of the Las Vegas
It's weird Lady Gaga Bruno Mars and Aerosmith
Bring down the house
In the intimacy of the Park theme
It's where La Chef Roy Choi
Mashes up Korean flavors
Mercedes new restaurant best
Be inspired
Natalie Mars
Enjoy your spinner
Jaan fine dining
And let it all go
At on the Wrecker
Biggest hits first
Speakeasy
Park MGM
Intimate moments
Big experience
Now on to our final game lightning fill in the blank each of our players with a 60 Seconds
The answer is many film
Questions
Is Hershey candies correct answer now with
Chucky can you give us
Moen Adam are tied with
F3 negeen Hast
All right
Begin urine third-place are going to be up first the clock will start when they begin your first question fill in the blank on Thursday
Jacinda ardern
The prime minister of blank announced
The band America
Semi-automatic weapon
On Tuesday President Trump announced plans to nominate a former Delta pilot
Delete the blank
Federal Aviation
Department
This week the FED that said that no blank hike
Extra plan for the remainder of 2019
Interest rate
Cascadia their new gaming
Google yas-23 policing
China have apologize for using a suspect
Blank on a wanted poster
Fingerprint
His Elementary School photo this week Robert Kraft
The owner of the blanks filed a motion
Listen to stop the release of elicit videos taken out of
Spa New England a woman shocked your friends when she sent out an invitation for her wedding despite the fact that her boy
Sing in a falsetto voice
She sent out the invitations for the wedding despite the fact that her boyfriend had not yet proposed
She took an online quiz that's
Suggested she might get married this year so she ran with it and send out wedding invites
It's very close friends and family
The bride-to-be
Two bees guest
Say they're excited for the I Do's which in this case they're short for I do not have a fan
All right
How did the game do in Ark
Nadine Got 5 right for 10 more points
She now has 12 points and the league
Alright Bergen again via flip a coin and mo is elected to come
So here we go
Fill in the blank
On Wednesday President Trump said that he's
Supported the public release of the blank
Mueller
That's on Tuesday the Wall Street Journal reported that the blank
Was telling supporters
He was planning to run into
20/20
I guess it's
Why was this week Theresa may ask
You for three months delay on blank
Bragg said
The blank Brazil
Because of her cat cries to go out and won't ever leave
The French foreign minister says
She is name
Aircat blank brexit yes indeed
Wednesday marked the start of the 2019 blank tournament
The NCAA
A bookstore in London has asked for the Public's help finding a man who left blank behind after shopping there
I'm going to
Say
No
He left a Jar full of bees
This week the London review Bookshop tweeted quote
If you are the friendly giant who is here half an hour ago and left a big jar of bees
Please come back and reclaim
Your bees employees didn't think that we will help especially considering the guy was at the
The store to return a book called
How to get rid of a jar of bees
Chucky how did Moe doing our quiz this week
6 rifle
12 more points
A total of 15 and now mode
Is in the lead
Alright here's the tough question how many then
Does Adam Burke me too
To win
60 * 7
Are we go out of this is for the game
Following attacks on President Trump lawmakers
Both parties
Praise the lake
Yamaka
Right on Wednesday Disney completed their 71 billion dollar acquisition of blank
A fox
Write this week documents show that the investigation
The former Trump lawyer blank began in 2017
Michael Cohen
Factor by Massive blanks
Spider-Man in Michigan is on the mend after accidentally blanket
Find me a jar of bees
He's on he's on the mend after accidentally shooting himself in the foot when he tried
How to kill a cockroach by throwing a gun at it
On Monday investigators said they found clear similarities between two crashes of
737 Max 8 planes made by blank
Bride for the second year in a row Finland was named the world blanket
Is country happy is Right a woman visit to her parents grave took an unexpected turn what you got there and blank
Play jumped out from behind trying to pay respect
That's what you started
It's sinking hip deep into the ground now
We know the sound terrifying but don't worry it's actually
Only so much worse
So she's laying a wreath on the tombstone
When a sinkhole opened up beneath her sucking your into
The ground
She fell forward and hit her head
Breaking a tooth
But you kept thinking and had to hold on to her parents tombstone
To keep from going all the way under
Is the New York Post reports she cried out for help
But no one in the graveyard
I could hear her
Screams
Chucky did Adam do well enough to win it sound like you did well
Adam got six right
412 more points
With a total of 15
Tying with MO
And so together
They are this week's champ
Congratulations congratulations Adam
Will ask the panel to protect after the my space data lost what will be the next social media Scandal the first
Let me tell you
Special thanks to Farmhouse Tavern
After feeding us I very much
Wait wait don't tell me the production of NPR WBEZ
Chicago dissociation urgent haircut Productions Doug Berman benevolent overlord
Limericks are public address announcer
Palfrey
Warehouse manager is Tyler Green Assisted by Simon Tran
And married
Oranges are Alex McCone in Rancho
The Clapper
Miles dornbos and Lillian King
Peter Gwinn
Is our copilot active
Pictures of Lord of white
Are business and office managers Colin Miller
Are senior producer C&C logging the executive producer of wait wait don't tell me
Is mr. Michael Danforth now panel what will be the next
Social media
Scandal Adam Burke
Will cause Instagram to turn off
Every filter on every
Picture
Generations
To stare directly into the unvarnished face of reality
The sound of their screams will be definitely
Contact Eugene farsad
Because of the malfunction
Twitter Tinder accidentally
Mix it up
Swiping right for swiping left
Leaving a bunch of people to date her actually
Good for one another
They will be revealed that
Friendster the ones
Mighty social network is a Communications tool
For Quaker gangsters
That happens after you about it on wait wait don't tell me
This