Support for this podcast
In the following message
Come from Duckhorn
Napa California
Duckhorn Vineyards has been
Crafting classic Napa Valley Wine
Ants with a sense of place
For more than 40 years
Learn more
Or at Duckhorn.com NPR
From NPR and WBEZ Chicago
This is wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
Roses are red
Pickles or Dill
My last name is Curtis
My middle name
Danger
Hi milk
Bank Auditorium in downtown Chicago
Peter Sagal
President Whitney with wonderful Sheffield today later on we're going to be talking
Tumat
Smith
He is the actor
You're famous
For playing the Doctor on Doctor Who The Cult
Favorite show of that
And Prince Philip in the other cult favor
Show the crown
So he appeals to both nerds
And super nerd
Which is basically are
Give us a call with
I thought your cell phone in the Tardis case
Or
Your princess phone
10 player games the number is 1 Triple 8 wait wait that's one 889-2489
Do for now let's welcome our first listener
Hiring wait wait don't tell me
Hi this is Sarah calling from Durham North Carolina
You know going well just Rockin and Rollin
North Carolina what do you do there
I am a
Student studying electrical and Computer Engineering and
Computer science
Oh wow
Now they they say that that's like a tough business for women because basically
It people in
Computer people there
Sexist jokes
Does that intimidate
Said that the whole broke
You know I'm learning to deal with people of all different
Ritz and
Be the best that I can
Paddle for sup
It's the host of the confessional podcast TV
ATL
Any public radio variety show Livewire which will be at the Alberta Rose Theater
In Portland on February 21st
Burbank
Hello Sarah
Max the comedian's book made in America is available wherever you find your books It's Made
Tommy T's comedy club in Pleasanton California March 15th and the
Alonzo bodden
Does that are welcome to the show of course you going to start us off
Who's Bill this time Bill Kurtis
This is going to recreate
Three quotations
Snooze your job
Explain or
If I just two of them
Do that
You win our prize
Is the voice of your choice on your voicemail
With all that said are you ready to start
Yes I am your first load here is
The president
I can't say I'm happy
I can't say I'm thrilled
That was the president talking about a deal that he really really doesn't like butt
Eddie's going to sign anyway
The deal to do what
App for a border funding to avoid a government shutdown
Behove
The art of the deal it turns out it's the kind of art that makes
You say Mikey
Tok the Democrats
Offered
This is how I
Last year
Wofford President Trump about
2 billion dollars for defense
And the president said no I want 5 billion and I'm going to shut down the government until you give it to me
So he did that
And now he's going to get about 1 points
4 billion
He negotiates like he's in a limbo contest
How low can you go
The president is going to save face
She's going to say face by
I totally came in the wall
Declaring a national emergency
If you have an emergency
Building a Big Wang cement wall
Slowest way to
Right if you need border security let's just send all those unvaccinated kids
Kids from Washington down there
Nobody will go near them
Kids all named
10 Hazel
Peter but you may have just solved that problem
Yeah I know you're just kidding but somebody's going to hear this
You notice that the
The president as
It's become clearer and clearer that he's just not going to get this wall
Has done this amazing thing
He simply started
Saying
That he did
To like you told rally he don't he said
The rally don't say
Build the wall say finish the walk
Cuz we're already building it no we're not
I think I think you're right I think what it is is
His handlers app
People around him
Just figured out this awake
Just tell him that we did build a wall
And put him back on Executive time I mean he's not going to know he
He's never going to go check or anything so you just like
Yeah yeah that wall are we finish
Is that wall yeah
Brewster president Garrison pictures of your wonderful wall and he'll say
That's great it looks amazing but why are all these Chinese
You're next quote
Was from Twitter
Baby I had to get out of New York to
I get it now
That was a man named Jake Flores commenting on what company that suddenly backed out on a plant
The move to New York
Amazon Amazon
Amazon came to New York with just a
The dream and the hundred billion dollars
Pocket
New York City a bunch of clowns get off at Port Authority every day
This is a city that will tolerate 3 billion rats and regularly sitting in pee in the subway
But Amazon hell no
So it stopped you know cuz it was going to go to New York and mama said New Yorkers got upset and
Back down
Set a tough week for Jeff Bezos but at least when it comes
The Amazon New York
Feel that something we can on
Set the deal look solid they were going to build this new headquarters in Queens but New Yorkers were upset that the mayor and the governor
Gave Amazon
Tax breaks
Helipad
And the right for Jeff Bezos to
The kidnap any Bride on
On her wedding night
The local officials in Union guys made such a fuss about it that Amazon sat5 will take her bottle girl home
Also every Alexa in New York is not responding to
To request you know like Alexa what's the weather by saying
How would I know
I'm not there what's going to be embarrassing is now that
Jeff Bezos is going to have to like
Make a late-night call to Gary Indiana
Well that's okay so you know how we have that whole dog-and-pony show if we made all the other C
Cities try out to be the new headquarters you up
Sarah here is your
Final quotes
It's a sentence of which there is
There's no escaping
No return
That was a US District Attorney talking about the conviction of what drug lord this week
El Chapo
Headed the Sinaloa cartel was convicted of all counts
How to drug smuggling
General Alchemist
He's not heading for life in prison but be he's known for his remarkable escapes
So this time
They are
The door
Checkmate
It was an amazing trial it was both a
It was about the trial and a movie about a trial
El Chapo's mistress testified against him singing
Here's how much you love him while his wife
Watch
From the courtroom
And his wife
Still stood by him
The whole time
Maven coordinated outfit
Is it true it's a tribute to the power of true love and billions of dollars in drugs
I think if your mistress
Is testifying on your behalf and your wife is
Sitting in the courtroom
You're like a runner
Can you lock me up for a while
There are those that mean they're being of the fact that he's going to jail for
There's only the rest of his life
People say will make any difference
Because his whole business
Is going to
The inherited
They say
By his
Twin Suns known as
Los chapitos
Roasted potatoes sounds silly but it's no sillier than
El Chapo
Which means
Shorty
That's most
Fear drug lord
Shorty
And that's
Silly
Cuz he's only 5 6
And it's insulting in an Acura Epic
T56 is well within the normal Ray
Love you doing height jokes
On radio
American headquarters for El Chapo Syndicate and
Google Drive business
Was
Chicago
It's absolutely true
So are you listening Amazon
Lots of experience in shipping and receiving just saying
Bill how did Sarah doing her quiz
Start with a perfect
Scores
Thank you Sarah thank you for playing Sarah
We want to remind everybody they can join us mostly
It's right here at the
Go tutorial
Downtown Chicago
Mission go to w
. org
You can finally get our website
Play wait wait. In
Weatherpanel it is time for you to answer
To some questions about this week
Snooze
Chuck-E-Cheese the place
Your children bring you to torture
Is it a bit of weirdly hot water this week
They actually had to come out and deny
Claims being made in the internet
That the pizza they serve is what
Are they had to deny claims that they're using
Pizza
That other customers
Have like thrown out basically
That sounded like
Pizza
Pizza served at
Jesus sometimes come in weird
Shapes
Like feel like half of 1 and 1/4 of another and
Quarter of another
It says clearly
What they're doing is they're taking the pizza that their prior customers don't eat and slapping it on your plate
Filling out with somebody else
And serving it to you is Snoopy
Also
It's made of
What if you go to Chucky
The cheese for the pizza don't you deserve that
Chuck-E-Cheese I put out a statement denying it right it's not true
I guess but they should have said luck people
What do you want organic artisanal
Pizza from what is
Basically a
Starter Casino for your sick
Jerome
Their mascot is a rat and your
Surprised
Pizza reviews
Yeah I was going to bring me fresh pizza
Coming up the mother-of-one Triple A quick way to play will be back in a minute with more weight weight
Don't tell me
From NPR
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Message come from Stanford children
One of the scariest things
Mom look
Because the next words are you sure
Billy can fly
Or Joey riding the dog
Or a crayon stuck in Valerie's nose
Here's something you might
Want to hear
With over 20
Pediatric office
Stanford pediatric
Christians are all over
The Bay Area
Not just in Palo Alto
Find a Stanford PDF
At stanfordchildrens.org
When Colin Kaepernick
Stop Standing for the national
Anthem at NFL games
It's parked in Nationwide debate
About patriotism and
Police brutality
Nginx through line
Weeks for three stories
The protest
That are rarely pulled
Essential to understanding the
Through line
The podcast where we go back in time
To understand the
From NPR
Then WBEZ Chicago this is wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Curtis we are playing this week with Luke
Burbank
Maeve Higgins
Alonzo bodden
Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown
Chicago PD
Right now it's time for the wait wait don't tell me Bluff The Listener game call 1aaa wait wait
Two player game on the air
Justin Strickland from the Scenic City Chattanooga Tennessee
Have you heard anything from Amazon recently
I'll come back to you they'll realize what's important
What what are you doing there in Chattanooga
Hospitality but actually I'm a local railroad historian I've written a book about the train stations in Chattanooga
Wait a minute
You
Write about
The Chattanooga Choo Choo
Hardy Boys
I moved here because of the railroad history and
Wrote the book about it and the rest is history
Meanwhile I'm never allowed to promote my book
But welcome to the show Justin it's
Nice to have you with us
You're the player game on but you must try to tell truth from fiction what is the top
Mom's they're not just the people you used to live inside of they also want to help you
But this week we heard the story of the mom and
Liv and Maddie went a little too far
Oropendola something to tell you about it
Pick the one who's telling the truth Hill Enterprise the wait waiter of your choice on your voicemail
Ready to play
Let's go for a ride. Let's hear from Luke
Burbank
A potential disaster was narrowly averted last week when two armed F-18 Hornets were scrambled
To respond to an Airborne disturbance over an elementary school
In the town of Sedro-Woolley washington
We didn't know if it was going to be Al-Qaeda or alien
Pilot John Bolden told
Skagit Valley Herald
It just look like a cluster of some kind of small Warcraft on the radar
It turned out to be something much more sinister
5 drones
Being piloted
By 5 different parents
Watching their kids play during recess
Apparently things started when Jan saperstein the mom of Brayden
A fourth grader
Heard from her son at the other kids were cheating at tetherball
Using a drone camera that her older son
Caden
Add quart bags for and then never use not even once Jen did uncover rampant
Tetherball and Hopscotch cheating
Uneven photo documented it sending the Drone pics to the school administrators
This led to a number of the accused kids
Parents buying their own drones
To gather their own evidence
The number eventually grew to five
Known in aviation circles as
And overparenting of drones
The mid-air dogfight that have started breaking out posts real danger to the students
Play was actually the noise from all those drones that proved to be the final straw
2087 year old Lloyd leyritz who lived
Near the school emerge from his house in full duck hunting camo
And started shooting at the aircraft with a shotgun
That was when the US military got involved
And that was when Mary Purcell Elementary School officially banned all drones
Now staring daggers across the parking lot during after school pick up that is still allowed
A drone dogfight as overprotective mothers and wash
Washington State tried to monitor their
Elementary School
Kids your neck story of a mom
Can't stop mumbling
Comes from Alonzo bodden
Every grandmother thinks their grandchild is perfect
But if you had the chance would you want to make sure
Before it was too late
Rodger Cato's mom Lindsey was delighted when he told her that he and
His girlfriend Wendy were engaged
But Lindsey became obsessed
With one question
And it wasn't the wedding day
What would her future grandchild look like
How about their health
Since Wendy's relatives weren't around the only solution
To get a sample of Wendy's
DNA
She thought it would be easy
But as it turned out
Future daughter-in-law
Is a bit of a germaphobe
Mom offered when do you taste
Cookie dough
I think you should get DNA from
Spoon
And Wendy whipped out her own sterilize spoon
Mom suggested to Wendy that she looks feverish and offered to take her temperature
But Wendy had her own ear thermometer
Mom tried the direct
The protesting will be fun for the family to send in their DNA
And find out that backgrounds
Wendy's response
Those companies
Is keeping cell personal info so no way
But it's blank
Lindsey Woods
Convince Wendy Wu
Spy or a mutant or worse
She had to have that
Which is why Lindsey Kato
Was arrested at 3 a.m. at the offices of a Tustin
California gynecology
In the possession of a
Stolen urine sample
As a first-time offender mosquito will most likely
We be sentenced to the minimum 6
In jail
But having finally gotten windy
To show her some family picture
She will spend the time in jail bragging to her cell mates
About her tall blonde
Future grandchildren
With a pinch
Breitling
A future Grandma tries to steal
Her future daughter-in-laws DNA
And your last story of a Grizzly mom comes from maven
Is there anything better than a mother's love
1 married and Mom certainly think so
She wants an actual lovers love for her son
The woman's name is unknown but she was spotted on tosin University campus
Desperately trying to find her son a date
The Baltimore Sun
Which is a newspaper and not her actual son
Reported this week that a woman in her fifties with approaching people and showing them photos of her baby boy all grown up and asking them to
Sedate him
Cheap
Chief Charles Herring said her reported Behavior may cause
Concern
He did not specify
To whom it would cause concern but it's widely assumed he meant her absolute version of
Avatar
University officials say that the woman is not being sauce for any criminal investigation
But they do want her to refrain from hustling her son
Photo of encompass
Even if it does have that cute puppy Instagram filter
Alright somewhere there was a story of an over interested mother
Where was it from
Luke Burbank a mother who said to drill into monitor
Your kid
Data Elementary School leading to a kind of aerial arms race above
The playground from Alonso
Future grandma
Who did everything she could including breaking and entering
Get
A genetic sample of her
Future daughter-in-law
Or
From made a woman
Stalking the campus of the university in Maryland trying to find a date
Her son which of these are the real story
Oven over mothering mother
Wow
Well we could not find the mother in question but we did speak to a reporter who
Who's covering
A woman in her fifties was going around campus with a picture on her phone of her son
And she was at
Asking people if they'd be willing to fight a state for it
That was George
So let's he's a reporter for WJZ-13 in Baltimore
Talking about the mom trying to find her son
Add a Tap House on University
I got the train and the train
It wasn't Pac-Man who's telling the truth
You have won our prize
And 2.4 made congratulations thank you for 222 thing me
And now the game where people who done an awful lot of things
Well they do something else
Matt Smith first became world famous playing the iconic British TV character
After the doctor on doctor
They got more famous by playing Prince Philip in the
TV series The
The crown
Now he's playing the role of the
The famously transgressive photographer Robert mapplethorpe
Before playing Charlie Manson
We're beginning to suspect
Please not ask
Actually any of those
People but instead some kind of act
Matt Smith welcome to wait wait don't tell me
Place to start is
Who are your more abs
Excessive fan
Santa Fe was the doctor or as Prince Philip on the crown
Well you would understand that the youngest person to take over the role of the doctor as a
And for people who don't know the doctor has been played over the course of 50
2 years by a bunch of different actor
Under the conceit
That he regenerates
And he gets
He becomes a different person
Yeah it in your ear doctors seem to be having a lot of
Fun
The great about that
Be there events
Like parent
For example
Ticket from a to zed
Dakota kccd
That
Shutdown I mean
Timer
Look before you get all high-and-mighty your country is about to fall off the edge of the Earth
You know what's funny of course man if Doctor Who were real none of this ever would have happened
Opt-in
So you go from Dr Who
Just incredibly popular
2 plane
Prince Philip who is a very real person
Did you guys working in the show ever get anything back from the actual royal family
About how they felt about who you were to pick
I think the fit it was off
If he if he works there and he just turned around and said
Joshua
Joe Sadler you've been phased out I want to get removed before she been phased out of the crown because that their aging you out
You got to be replaced by an older actor
Tobias Menzies
Did you argue with him to say I can be old and decrepit
Change it
2 years I think you'll be able to achieve it'll be wonderful looking forward to the first season of the next episode 1 of course
Prince Philip
Dies and regenerates as Tobias Menzies
And then I just want to talk to you about your latest film which is mapplethorpe
Is out now in which you play Robert mapplethorpe again a very real person
He was
An infamous
Photographer
Did you decide like okay I'm going to play this
Gay promiscuous guy who did hardcore
Photography as art
Did you say like I will show all the people who love me as Prince
Philip and doctor
Instinctively
Trying to do something different
No it wasn't.
You know the scriptures around and I found him very
Interesting I love New York in the seven
Season
What difficult when I was interested in.
Until after playing a very difficult than and then
Complicated figure like Robert mapplethorpe you decided to do something light and play Charlie Manson
Yeah
He's the one actually out of all the people that I've played the real
He's the one that guy still caught ready wikao
ScoreSense affiliate
Mancini someone I got 29 ways
Truth lies and the warm
Single axle truck away from them was I just went
He's just
Really annoying
Talk about we have a game to play but there is a question
And we ask this I don't know if you know
We ask this of all are gases
Tradition have you ever been stung in the testicles by a wasp
Yes
Finally we got one
Tell us about it
I mean
Yes I know
Briefly
Inside my passion and X
They enjoyed
Stop
Yeah
Run around
Matt Smith
We are all delighted to talk to you and could all day but it is time to play a game
As we do with that wonderful and this time we're calling the game
You don't have to be beautiful.
To turn me on
So you play Prince Philip in
The crown but what do you know about the true Prince
Prince
Where can I ask you three questions about the purple one Blessed Be he
Get to write on you want a price one of our listeners bill whoismatt
Smith playing for
Cody Benjamin of Atlanta Georgia this month's weather
And the wait wait quiz available on your smart
All right here we go
Now Prince was Prince's real name he was born Prince Rogers Nelson
But when he was very young sheep
I prefer to be called by a nickname what was it
Hey
Sex mod
B
Bethel
Orsi skipper
I'm going to go to bed with B
We should have anticipated you being British or not
Knowing about him
The answer was
Skipper
Prince gett off skipper
The child yet like
Call me skipper
He later decided
Let's be friends again
Prince got an early break as a musician
When he was hired to open for the Rolling Stones.
Concert in LA in 1981 but it didn't go well
What happened
Hyundai
Mick Jagger looked at him and said nobody goes on stage who's
Skinnier than I am
Beef and chased him off stage by throwing garbage at
Or see Prince announced his set by saying sorry that it all goes downhill after I'm
Call Taylor
They chased him off the stage
The garbage and he was very upset
But it was too nice and they said don't worry about it
Those crazy we're so sorry go on
The second night in
It will be fine anyone on the second night
And they chased him off the stage with garbage
But why he got his vengeance
Amazing popular
Last question if you get it right
You win
Prince once later in his life
Gave NBA star
Carlos
Boozer a check for
Half a million dollars
Just to apologize
For something that prints
Dundee
Wattpad
Prince done
Hey
He wants criticized boozers
Is playing style in the back
Basketball court
By saying more like Carlos
Snoozer
Am I right
Be when Prince rented boozers home
He turned boozers bedroom into a hair salon without asking
Or see if the 2007 NBA All-Star Weekend Prince hooked up
With Boosie's girlfriend
Hoosiers ex-girlfriend
And then
Buzzers mom
Hahaha
God I wish I'm with you
We say but it's what happened
Hoosier Renegade princess
Is La Mansion
Prince totally redecorated made the Benjamin Harrison
Hoosier like what you do princess I'm sorry
But then prints
Totally redid the house back to the way it was
Who's the gay bath million
Are we sure she didn't have
We have no evidence
But it's entirely possible
Bill how did Matt Smith
He would make Prince Philip proud he got two out of three so you are a winner.
Matt Smith new movie mapplethorpe is in theaters March 1st
He's also
No matter what he tells you now
What time lord Matt Smith thank you so much for joining us and wait wait don't tell me
In just a minute Bill reveals the secret to his youthful complexion in The Listener Limerick challenge go on AAA wait wait
From NPR
Support for this podcast
The following message
Message come from Stanford children
What are the scariest things
Mom look
Because the next words are you sure
Billy can fly
Or Joey riding the dog
Or a crayon stuck in Valerie's nose
Here's something you might
Want to hear
With over 20
Pediatric offices
Stanford pediatric
Christians are all over the
The Bay Area
Not just in Palo Alto
Find a Stanford.
At Stanford children
Castlemont high is
Different from a lot of other High School
This student he got shot for
I was just saying outside
Hacker bullets
One year after
The Parkland
Talk to kids who
Space gun violence
Every single day
Listen
On it's been a minute
NPR
NPR and WBEZ Chicago
The NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Kurtis were playing this week with me and Higgins Luke Burbank and Alonzo bodden
Here I got to your house that they Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown
Chicago
Thank you Bill Bill light some candles and gets
Rhythmatic
Did I listen here lyric challenge game you like to play
Give us a call at 1 at AAA wait wait
That's one 888-924-8924
All right guys some questions about the week's news
Alonzo The Wall Street Journal report
The kids today are
Fuse demystified whenever they incur
Kids are confusing mystified today by this
So so much
Just
It's something you and I are you
With the kids these days
I've had very little experience with
I don't know what it is
Oh they're confused by cash
Store owners
Report children being bewildered by
Currency
Paper and coins
It parents say that
Is there kids how to identify money
Well
It's the thing with all the old white man on it
No no not the US Senate
Google shopping being done online and more stores not even accepting cash kids
Never see eye-to-eye
What currency in fact
There's a new edition
Of Monopoly that doesn't even have
Metal debit cards
Player that's true
Again Peter at you know I hate to be the cultural one whenever I'm here
But I just don't think black kids are confused by money
Really
You know you you go to a black
Child or Latino child and say
Here's some money they're going to be like thank you then I can be like what is that
Anything you speak of oh no they blow my nose it's not going to happen
Money
Just money while goes away by
Eventually think of the tradition
That will be lost
Young kid standing in front of a wishing well
They close their eyes and make a wish and then they throw your iPhone down at
Maze
At high winds affected the Midwest this week the National Weather Service
This issue the warning
People with what
Tornado warning
No no no
They should be there saying to people you can watch this year
Fairy lights
With life you know how some people have
Pettibone
People with that people would like
Vornado with no people who have something that might care about that might get blown away
It's a little dog that's exactly right
Oh my God
Hang onto your hats ladies
Especially if you wear a shitzu as a hat
This week
Sworn that in some parts of the Midwest wind gust
Might be strong enough
Harry Wei
Smaller pets
A movie about that
Yeah you are in Kansas snow totals in Chicago
Midwest struggles with these windy conditions the east coast is enjoying an influx
A free dogs
Dog NATO
Beckley NWS
Twitter. A picture of a little dog getting blown away watch out they said
The photo was adorable and hilarious and an undoubtedly inspired pet owners
To throw caution
Into the winds
That is pet owners who would name their chihuahuas
Caution
Like
Luke a new study shows that if you want your son to behave in
School you should
Should really avoid doing what
Do I can I get a hint
Well I'm afraid to say your parents absolutely did this
Oh don't name them Luke exactly right
Pedro / 6
3000 Elementary
School kids and they found her
The correlation
Between the kids
Is and the name they
Example
Kids named Adam
We're done really well.
Where is Luke
Got in
Two more trouble don't worry though they said as long as their last name is not a city in Southern California
They'll be fine
There is one name that did worse
I don't feel bad all the way
I confess I've never met someone named murdered
Wow
That's
That explains a lot Peter did you feel mischievous
Angry with
I did not like my name at all
But I got on a
Like a baseball team where we got jackets
It's with her name stitched in them
I mean I was done growing cuz I was like 60 and that's it
Coming up it's lightning fill in the blank refers is the game where you have to listen for the rhyme
If you'd like to plan are called leaving
AAA wait wait
That's one eight eight eight 92489
Contact us link
On our website wait wait. Npr.org there you can
Can find out about attending
Our weekly live shows
Usually here at the Chase Bank Auditorium
Chicago upcoming show in San Antonio
And if you like our show but wish it was 4 minutes long and you were the only gas
Check out our interactive game on your smart
Speaker
Your Alexa or Google device
To open the wait wait
Quizzes
Be a star
All right
You are on wait wait don't tell me
Hi Peter. Rebecca from New York City
Well it's not a couple days ago in smart cuz he's 56 so can't really make up its mind
An argument what kind of archives
I'm work at a Jewish non-profit
Okay so you're
Archiving folder
Archives
Well welcome to the show Rebecca
3 News related limerick
Search for the last word or phrase missing
For me if you can
Feeling that last word or phrase correctly
Two of the limits you will be a winner
Ready to play
I guess so yeah
Limerick
Kim Kardashian's seems filled with file
Her skin is placidness
She won't
Define
When
And I is twinkle
That placidness crinkle
She's simply won't
Smile
Good for preventing wrinkles quote
Never smile
That's what she said you said how is that possible how can you go through life never
Smiling
Well Step 1
Mariah crazy
Did you see what said person did for Valentine's
Tell us about it
Apparently Kanye West
To celebrate Valentine's Day with
With his wife
Hire Kenny G
And then surrounded Kenny G in a
A room of roses
Single roses
Days Inn
Like little single vases
The whole room is just
Rose's vases and Kenny G
Playing
Whatever that instrument is can you imagine doing that for your wife
She doesn't smile
All right Rebecca here is your next limit
Since corruption is hard to prescribe
Allheart uniform
Change
Wilton tribe
Now can use police
Have Nopal
Without pocket
They can't
Tay k
Bridesmaids there's a problem apparently antenna
Police accepting bribes but several sources
The reporting that affects
They're just going to move
The pockets from police
The perfect deterrent
With no one to put their illicit wads of
Cash the problem is
Officer Smith walking back from Patrol and why you clenching that way
And they give up cash
Here is your last
Limerick
As
Snowstorms are starting to whale
In Portland
The grocery store is fail
The shelves are wiped clean of dark leafy greens
The northwest
Run out of
Hell yes indeed hell very good
Huge snowstorm hit the Pacific Northwest
Portland weather
Faced with the possibility
Of losing
Power for days if not weeks.
Manish
Should really find a way that makes the situation even more unbearable
And they went out and they bought all the kale they could
As we all know
Human beings can survive 48 hours without water
And forever
Without kale
Show me some pictures of organic
Grocery stores in Portland that have been ransacked by peep
Preparing for the storm
In all the kale and avocados
Gone
Left untouched
Bread and milk
They call him in Portland
Gluten bricks
Andis grassmilk
There's also just a
Kind of a table full of
Smallpox vaccine
A perfectly intact
Bill how did Rebecca do in Ark with Rebecca
Very well
Take your time
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Stanford Children's Health
What are the scariest things of Perinton
Mom look
Because the next words are usually
Billy can fly
Or Joey riding the dog
Or a crayon stuck in Valerie's nose
Here's something you might want to
With over 20 pediatric office
Stanford Pediatrics
Shins are all over the Bay Area
Not Justin
In Palo Alto
Find a Stanford pediatric
At stanfordchildrens.org
Support also comes from Duckhorn Vineyards Napa Calif
Founded by Dan and Margaret.
Nineteen
Duckhorn
Crafting classic wine
Signs with a sense of
Place for more than 40
With seven Estate Vineyards located throughout the novel
The winery produces vintage Merlot
Cabernet Sauvignon
Sauvignon blanc and Chardonnay
All showcasing the diversity of wine.
Learn more at Duckhorn. Com
NPR
Hey it's
Skyrise creator of how I built this
We're returning to San Francisco for this
Second how I built this Summit
Supported by America
Can express
I'll be joining there by founders
Companies like
Instagram Slack
Away Bliss JetBlue and me
Many many more
Visit Summit
Npr.org
To learn more and
Hope to see you there
Final game lightning fill in the blank each of our players will have 60 seconds which
The answer is many film
Why questions
Is he or she can
Still can you give us
Alonzo and Luke each have three
Babe has to
All right
Made your in third place you're up first the clock will start when I begin to first question fill in the blank
On Wednesday judge ruled the former Trump campaign manager blank had violated his
I want to say
Tyler Durden
I know that's right
No it was Paul manafort after being rebuked by Congressional Democrats blank apologize for her remarks
Facts about Israel
Melanoma
This week the blank rows above 22 trillion dollars
For the first time ever
The economy of the national debt after spending fifteen years on Mars NASA announcement
The blank Rover had
Finally died
The Mars rover
I kind of said it was on Mars
I know what
Yeah you know I only know the name of the road
Is that relevant here
The opportunity to lose this round
Denver offer to striking
Teachers their blank
Discounted weed
This week George Clooney and Brad Pitt signed a letter demanding Oscars
Cinematography and editing not
Be given out during
Ocean's 11
Broadcast
Police were able to arrest
Three bank robbers after blank / heard of them
Planning their heights
Their moms
No
They were overheard by the
Uber driver they had hired
To drive them to the bank
He was their getaway driver
They hired this Uber got to drop into the bank and all the way they discussed
Entry routes escape plans which of the man Carries a Gun
Naturally as soon as you drop them off the driver called
At least the men were arrested as soon as I walked into the bank to the bank and its customers but terrible news for
This is true for the other Uber they had called
As their getaway
Bill how did Maeve do in Ark with one right total of 4 Points
She sitting on four in first place
For the moment you flip a coin and Luke has elected
Nexo Luke
The blank on Tuesday the Senate her testimony that blank had made the little to no change
And its nuclear capabilities
North Korea for the third time this month
Former Trump lawyer blank the latest
Congressional testimony
Cohen Michael Cohen this week to us accused of former Air Force
Intelligence specialist
I'm spying for blank
Kelly
Announced he would run for
Send it
In blank Arizona
This week man in Indiana at the Opera
Opportunity to make some
Quick Cash when he was offered $200
To blank
Leave Indiana go to not call the police on the guy he just caught robbing his
Childish Gambino Kacey Musgraves and cardi B with a big butt
Grammy being criticized
He was caught blinking while riding in the back of a motorcycle
Sleeping know she was caught shaving her legs
The back of a moving motorcycle
Viral she was wearing just a bathing suit
Don't shaving her legs with one hand and holding what
Looks like a beer in the other
Bull riding a motorcycle
It's actually pretty impressive
Defeat not nearly as impressive
Does the drivers
Steering the bike
One handed shaving
His back with
The other
Bill how did Luke doing our quiz he got five right
10 more points
All right that was impressive so how many does Alonzo need
M62 wind
All right
On Monday a TV news cameraman with a
Attacked at a
The Trump rally
In blank El Paso
The blank administrator announced
His resignation
Rock Longview
You know I know what you're talkin
I got nothing
Better on Monday Utah's Republican legislature passed the bill
Curbing a blanket
Approved by voters in 28
Airport no Medicaid
On Tuesday a Wire Fox Terrier named
Ken won Top honors at the blank
Westminster kennel
According to a new study
Consumer beverages with artificial
Blank A Day Men
The risk of heart attack
Diet sodas
Sweetness police in Ontario
Recalled to break up a brawl after did women begin arguing over blank
Could you come up with a broader question
Something to women with
Would start arguing over I mean
That's a very specific one
Two women in Ontario Whitby Ontario Canada or Ontario California
A big fight over Bingo seat
Citadel retirement home
The fight started when the two women aged
79 and 86 both wanted the same chair for Bingo night
Neither was willing to back down and then somebody threw a punch
Entire bingo game turned into a bingo brawl
Pop ticket cost
Is known as
When one woman knocked out the other woman Steve's
Pick them up and put them back up
But we got three right 6
Total of 9 but that mean the law
Is a champion list
Amazon
New York from
Thanks once again to Farmhouse Tavern in Chicago
The carrots were
Wait wait don't tell me
Uchicago dissociation
Doug Berman
Benevolent overlord
Limericks are public
Assisted by Simon Tran and married
Alex
McCowan and Rachel
Clapper rweb Guru is Beth Novey
BJ leiderman composer theme
Produced every week by Jennifer Mills miles dornbos
And Lillian King Bill Kurtis
Displayed
By Peter Gwynne
Technical direction from Lorna Wyatt our business and office manager is calling Miller a production coordinator is Robert Newhouse
Our senior producer is Ian chilligan the executive producer of wait wait.
Michael Dan
Will Amazon get back in New York
For rejecting the Luke Burbank
If anyone from New York tries to order something via Amazon it'll just be like new phone who this
Higgins
Break the subway they're going to make the city state-of-the-art NCAA unreliable and slow and they're going to stay
Alonzo bodden
Amazon is going to buy Manhattan and give it back to the Native Americans
$24
We're going to ask you about it on wait wait don't tell me
May 2nd Alonzo bodden caseology
This is NPR