Support for this podcast
In the following message
Come from Duckhorn
Napa California
Duckhorn Vineyards has been
Crafting classic Napa Valley Wine
Ants with a sense of place
For more than 40 years
Learn more
Or at Duckhorn.com NPR
WBEZ Chicago
Wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
Derelique old Anchorman
Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown Chicago Peter
Everybody
Going to be talking to the actor rich
Egress recently nominated
For an oscar but first we are coming to you as we normally do
From Chicago
Where the weather has been
Someone
Brisk
A lot of businesses closed and certain
Wish I was canceled performances including Hamilton
That way
Here we are
Because the show must go off
We really need about 500 people to huddle around us on stage to keep
Does warm
We hope you have somebody to snuggle with but reach out a hand and give us a call
The number is 10008 wait wait that's 18889
Let's welcome our first listener contestant
Higher on wait wait don't tell me
Hi this is Clara from New Orleans Louisiana was just tell me what the weather is like their butts
Speak slowly
I'm going to say it in the southern way which
I'm just going to complain about how it's a minor inconvenience
But I have to wear a hoodie
I really went from liking you to hating you
What welcome to the show Claire
Let me introduce you to our panel this week. It's the co-host
Do the podcast
Listens to Paula Poundstone
Hello player
Writer to the New York Times and the author of amazing
In America
It's mean Higgins hello I'm finally an author in humerus
You jumped out of the Vermont ice
Straight into the Chicago freezer
It's Tom bodett
So Clare welcome to the show of course you're going to start us off with
Who is Belle Vista
Bill Kurtis is going to reach for youth
3 carefully curated quotation
Snooze your job
Explain or Identify two of the
Do that you win a prize The Voice
Have anyone you might like
On our show on your
You ready to play
That your first quote is from
NBC News and they are talking about
Helm
Of hell
Michigan
Hell
Has frozen over
Hell froze over this week
Due to what
The polar vortex
60 below
In some places here in the Midwest it is really cold here
Ask me how
How cold is it so cold Chicago mayor Rahm emanuel's remaining nine fingers
Snapped off
The career-oriented women in Chicago were freezing their eggs on the sidewalk
I know you have more there
The burn for everybody doing that you know viral throw boiling water in the air thing
In Chicago this
Truth they set the train tracks on fire
Didn't mean to it's just something we like
To do in Chicago
The Noblesville Police Department
Announce that due to the cold all crime
Quote will be
Be prohibited
Till further notice
But we finally cracked
I'm not supposed to do that will put your hands back down and get your money
You guys you guys are first just showed up today
A lovely shock for
I wasn't I wasn't really following the news for the last week which I'm just now realizing
Was maybe not a good idea
But it was until I was sitting on the airplane and the pilot over the intercom was like
Now that you're on the desk flight blah blah to Chicago I don't know why anyone would want to go there
Everyone started laughing but I was like
Now I understand
Cuz when I got out of the airport I was like oh my God slapping slapping me
But it said it was just the weather
Is a terrible idea why are we doing this
Is this a prank so but it was it wasn't it was just
It was just a flight to Chicago. Have you had your lips
Sprays to your upper
This yet
I am very disappointed
School teacher map
What is a tiny
Disappointed
I slept kind of a nothing to do with it or disappointment
All right
Here
Is your next
Quote
If you vote for in the machine reads his name back as
Hobart
Skulls
That was somebody on Twitter coming in the former CEO of what companies
Just announced
Presidential run
Starbucks white funny how to spell that's great
Former Starbucks CEO Howard Schultz appeared on every Network
Concluding NPR
To announce
Third party run for president
20/20
More people interviewed him on national TV
About running for president
Then would ever vote for him for president
But you know his pitch
Makes sense
He'll run the country the same way he ran his company
Example Hill build another White House
House directly across the
We already have
I don't think he's being real about like what's good about Starbucks
What does he could just provide public
Victorian era in America
Free Wi-Fi you could run on that alone
Wewe in Wi-Fi
Yes Howard Schultz just like Starbucks bathroom
You don't really enjoy it but sometimes
You just need them
That's about the best Logan he could possibly have because as you pointed out his chances are not
Shall we say
Venti no a living breathing human being
Who has said that they would consider voting
What is cuz I think we don't recognize him like I didn't know that he was
The Starbucks guy
You think of that mermaid on their cough
So if she was running
Dear klairs your last
Quotes about an issue summer close to home for me
I'm a broke college student
That my only source of entertainment
Is it a count me and my mother
Share that guy was commenting on a news article about what company that
Start bus
Sharing password
Netflix Netflix as I know
A chill ran through then there a new software package was debuted at the riza
Consumer Electronics Show in Vegas
And it basically rats out all the 35 year olds were still using their parents Netflix fast
Identifying all 35 year old people who watch
Come on Netflix there are so few good things in life
Why do you want to take away our
Sponging
People really need Netflix try inviting somebody over
CBS all access in
NCG Cinemas
When I log into Netflix
There's all these things, so who's watching it says Tom or Rita and my wife are the boys you know
So I guess because we all live together that's all we go right there
Jermaine luer to them but don't put them on your email play Tom resize Sabrina
Is another reason why they shouldn't do this was a lot of people the only contact they have with their parents
Is what I call a my baby 6 weeks
Because I forgot the password
What are families Netflix
How to clear doing AR quiz
She did them all right
Bye-bye
We want to remind everybody they can join his most weeks right here at the Chase Bank on
Auditorium in Chicago Illinois
For tickets and more information go to wbez.org
Look at our website
Wait wait
. NPR
. org
Light up handle it is time for you to answer some questions about the
This week's news
Valentine's Day is
Coming up in this time
We're going to have to get through it without
What
Without welding
It's can't do flowers going to flowers going to candy
Like today
Renault F1
Make it a kind of cat
Not alone message heart is
Valentine candy
Call conversation Hearts you know them is a candy that all the talking
From you rocked
To love bug
How to I bought you a gift out of gas
Oh God I have a chip in my front tooth from one of those things that I've had it for
Probably 30 years well your choice outlasted that company
Nico went out of
India Company very good and so basically they
Add people freaked out one
Woman this is
The true offered
Her car in
Exchange
First shipment of these candies come on people
You don't know the right words
To express your feelings just do what the rest of us do
Stare at your phone until they stop wondering about you and just stare at their own
But you know I thought there was something up
With those candies
Because the last
Do packets I got wear like
You are our only hope they were made by the same
But I miss
Dymista
Necco Wafers
Why do I like them
I'm here and I'm there
A lot of there's a lot
That's not perfect about Necco wafer
Since I was at another company has said we bought the contract
We're gonna start making them to update the messages
What they are
Tweet me and
Slide into my DM
Coming up iPad with Viber
First place The Listener game
Go on AAA wait wait to apply will be back in a minute with more wait wait don't tell me
This message comes
NPR sponsor
The Illinois office of Tourism
Who would like to add
Ask if you're up for amazing
From Chicago to Lincoln spray
From Shawnee National Forest
The Main Street Grill
There's a lot to see in Illinois
Some might even say
It's amazing
But we were
Because that's really up to
So visiting
Enjoy Illinois.
And see if you're up for what some p
People Michael
Amazing
Chicago
The NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Kurtis we are playing this week
Could Adam felber Tom bodett
And here again that you were hosted
The Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown Chicago
Bitters I call everybody right now
Time for the wait wait don't tell me
Bluff The Listener
A game called
AAA wait wait two-player game of the year
Hello this is Emily from Norfolk
Virginia
All 27° which is probably a lot warmer than what you guys have in Chicago
What do you do there
I work in the assisted living for those with Alzheimer's and Dementia as I carried
And I'm finishing up setting to be an assisted-living administrator
Bless your heart.
You two player game emoji
You must try to tell true
Bill what is Emily stop
You Blinded Me With Science
Aviano science fairs or Cutthroat competition
Your scientists
Vitacig whose parent
Can make the best
Science fair project for that
This week
The nation turns its eyes
To Lexington Kentucky where the
Mill Creek
Elementary schools
Annual fourth grade science fair
And that's science
Fair had a surprising winner this
Are you going to tell you it was but only one of them
Is telling
Pick that right person
And you will win our prize
The voice of anyone you might choose in your
I am ready first letter from Adam
Felder
The science fair at Mill Creek
10 year old Melissa gelineau
Hitechcreations
An automated Twitter bot
Named mean girl
Melissa gave her hideous progeny of profile picture in a flimsy biome
Turn her loose on Twitter
Mean girl programming with simple
She reply to a random person's tweet
What's 1 of 200 mean bookbag response
Just like that so offensive you suck
Or why you so triggered snowflake
Lol you are so stupid
It mean girl got a response she was programmed to reply back with another insult sometimes quoting her new enemy in adding
Not
Or or
I am so totally reporting you bye-bye
The goal was
To see if any adults online
Fall for her silly prank
I can get in a Twitter war with mean girl
As of last
About 432,000 users have done just that in fact gelineau was shocked to find that not only did the
Respond to the childish
Some of them
Virtual combat with mean girl for hours or days
One woman a lawyer for
Tulsa
Exchange mode
Apache Barb with mean girl
Not even noticing when her father started repeating her automated response
The project captivated everyone at the fair where Melissa set up a laptop to
So the kids can watch adult store in Quakertown
Cuz it mean girl in real time
For her part Melissa's less than Overjoyed about the results
Quotes I learned a lot
She said including a bunch of new words I'm probably not supposed to know
But as for her take away quotes
I used to worry about becoming a grown up she said but now I know there's really no such
Next thing
Melissa still not sure what you want to do with your talents down the road but she says
I'd like to meddle in at least one national election
Melissa is able to
Allure hundreds of thousands
Is it supposed to grownups
Angry cop
Asians about nothing
Directory of science
Versus
Comes from
Maeve Higgins
Frank Miller and 11 year old scientist in student
Tip Top price
At the Mill Creek Elementary science fair with his invent
Flavored braces for teeth
His project
Flavored braces putting that in math
Makes it sometimes painful often uncomfortable right of passage
Search more appealing for kids
His catchphrase
Nobody wants braces on teeth everybody wants
Streets on teeth
Might become Z
But he's a child remember and it work
Using all-natural Essences and oils he successfully developed the number of flavored beta braces
Including bubble gum flavor train tracks and avocado flavored retainers
Frank himself play guinea pig his own preference is a sophisticated combination
Toffee
Pizza flavors
Responding to a question about his youth the inventor had this to say
I guess I've always felt older than my age because
Is my name is Frank which is
Security not a child's name
The road
What's the top prize was not easy problems included an unfortunate early experiment
Where is top
Tasted like orange juice and his bottom
Tastes like toothpaste
Dr. Emmett Olivia local orthodontist with ambivalence
I'm happy about this latest wave of orthodontic enthusiasm but I can't help feeling this could lead to
Two more kids who don't need braces actually getting braces
Because they want the feeling of hot chocolate in their mouth all of the time
Frank's response
She's just jealous
Because she didn't think of it adults really suck
Pray for the flavor Grace's story of the nerd Champion comes
Tom bodett
10 year old Ace Davis of Lex
Washington won the fourth grade science fair with his ambitious and tree
Is Tom Brady a cheater
Has Brady heads to his
67 Super Bowl thinking he was finally in the clear on the whole deflategate controversy
He is faced with damning scientific evidence assembled by the
Intrepid Ace Davis
That he did in fact gain a distinct advantage
Spidey inflating his football during the 2014
Season
Using randomly selected study
Subjects from his immediate family
Davis had them toss footballs filled with varying degrees
The pressure to see which ones went
The farthest
Why the NFL investigators didn't think of this
Is anyone's guess
Test results prove incontrovertibly that low pressure in a football makes them
Fly further and are easier to catch
Having answered the question is Tom Brady a cheater
Ace Davis now goes on to the Kentucky
He District science fair finals while the disc
Disgraced Brady slinks off to Atlanta Georgia and no doubt
Obscurity
Alright so what are the three bright
Kids in Kentucky
Wonderforce
Fifth grade science fair with a
Was it from Adam
Melissa who created
The Mean Girl Twitter bot
From Maine
Frank who came up with the notion of flavored Grace
Or
From Tom bodett
The impish
Who set out to prove and did
The Tom Brady was a
So as much as I wish the first somewhere to expect want to see how my
How many times Donald Trump
Engage with the meantime
I do believe I saw this on my Facebook feed with the Tom Brady
Sorry
Again
Get on Facebook you know that
You're going to go to Tom's story of
Tom Brady is
Is he a cheater
To bring you the correct answer
We were able to
Speak with
The budding Ian
Tom Brady is a cheater
Know that
That was a generous
Elementary school science fair
Chase Davis
He's got a future this kid
Congratulations as is obvious you got it right Tom was telling the real story so
You want my dick in you
That means anyone you might choose
Graduation thank you
Thank you
And now the game where a lifetime of success is met with a moment to confer
Fusion it's called not my job
Richard he grabs one of those Acts
Disappeared in Everett
Game of Thrones
The Gosford Park
He's not really one of those character actors
Are you seeing that guy
Is the kind of character actor you see and say that guys
Grizzly awesome
This week he is Center Stage celebrating his Oscar nomination
Chris Rowland can you ever forgive me Richard
Grant welcome to wait wait don't tell me
Thank you very much I always I always asked actors this
But usually I have a guest
That's what the answer is in your case I do not know
Is there
Everybody say hi Richard
Very very good
What roles are most recognized for
Usually I can gas in your case I can't
So is their role is it with me when I that great cult movie you did long time ago is
The more recent stuff
6/4 into two distinct
People old enough to have seen with you.
Top movies
From 1997
It's another Great Masterpiece by swell the movie
Like what like a quintessential Richard E Grant Park
Is like somebody says
This is the perfect Parker Richard Grant because it's a
Because the person is usually on the edge of a nervous breakdown on manic
All seem either
Happily or unhappily
On the edge
I'm hidden that's the word I was looking for
We also ready
That you enjoyed
Smelling
How do you go about making purse
If you're an actress or something
Study
Well in 1969 when I was 12 years old the first American that I ever met feel better
Clap for the double p
I felt matting over there she was
False token
Gumtree storm how to french kiss
But you know that means it's
Use of the tongue
Oh yeah
Try to
I try to make coffee for her to gardenia rose petals pulled up in Sugar Bowl
Couldn't find me 40 years later I professionally made it as an adult so it's like marijuana Mandarin a signature
Notes of the original sin
You said marijuana
Yep
Have a name is it like
Making a passion by Richard e grant
What's it called
No you fool
It's cool jackets unisex you to come to the Union Jack bag inside a box and you can buy online here and in
Install the New York and in LA
Smoking weed all day
You're catching with my lovely
Perfume from Richard e grant
Call Jake
Grateful Dead
You can be the best
Sales pitches
We read that you're so interested in Scent
Obviously you are
But you like smell everything you encounter
I don't understand why everybody doesn't
Who is your best
Smelling
Swell
I don't want to offend anybody
Because everybody has their own
The sick ones
But there are some that I never want to smell again and I'm not going to tell you who they are and ask you about the
The new film which is
Is again amazed
Can you ever forgive me
You play a real person
Who really lived
When did
Some unpleasant
He was among other things a bit of a liar and a cheat
Criminal
Indeed. Did that appeal
When you got the part are you like okay that's going to be a shower
It did appeal to me because
Do you understand
The story how he falls in
His life of crime with
Please Release a pretty easy play by me
You know what you understand why people do what they do then compassion
Can flood in so you understand people in
You can feel sympathy for them
Right
The relationship between your two characters are extraordinarily sensor
The movie
And I always wonder if actors
To do this did you like
Spend time with Melissa McCarthy improvising pretending to be the people's
Get to know each other
Just going to set
And you were you were friends
On Friday
In January
A year ago Manhattan
2 hours
And we had lunch and then we saw the shooting on the Monday
And I knew within about for nanosecond
The meeting house that we were
Would probably be friends for life
Sing in a bottle so it was
It was just luck as much as I do
She did and she's having my triplets in Oregon
The game
Let's assume
That you win but even if you don't getting an Oscar nomination
Hopefully not
Gives you more options
So you been doing all kinds of different roles
All kinds of different
Is there a dream thing somebody says
Richard E grant Oscar winner
I would host your show
5 Peter
12 Richard E Grant it is a delight to talk to you but we have
Invited you here
To play a game we're calling
Richard E Grant
Meet Ulysses S Grant
Say okay. No we here in the US once a president named Ulysses S Grant
He'll probably be the star of Hip Hop musical any day now
We're going to ask you three questions about our present
Answer to correctly you want a prize
What am I listening to the voice of their choice
Voicemail
Building with Richard Grant play
Chris billig of Austin
Austin Texas
Here we go
Grant original name
At Birth was Hiram
Ulysses Grant but he eventually dropped the Hiram
Why
Hey you just like being made fun of for his initial
Hug
Be he found a Hiram was the name of his father
Favorite mule
Orsi's Hiram Grand owed a lot of money to the local
Saloon
But nobody had ever heard of Ulysses Grant
See no it was a he didn't like being called hug
Fairley Elementary School in the early 19th Cent
Vicious
Is today
One of Ulysses S Grant's lesser-known claims to
US president
Is that he had what did the first known pet fish in the white
Names you fishes s
Scranton
According to historian of hairstyles redhead the quote
Harriet
In presidential history
I've never I've never heard it described like that
Harry cabinet is a euphemism where you come from it's not
To the chief
Gucci originally title
Hail to the me
I think it has to be the Harry cabinet members
1000 mustaches every man in Grant's cabinet and the revered mustache a reception
All right last question
It is as we all know Ulysses S Grant 1st Road
The fame and National
Stature as a general in the Civil War
But that thing for him was Summit
Surprising y
Was it a he was so afraid of
Blood
He reportedly couldn't even look at a rare
Steak without
Bees High School
Voted him least likely to lead the Union Army to evict
Or see you at a terrible allergy
To heart attack
Tupac
Heart attack
Which was
The kind of
Biscuit
That one might keep it hairy cabinet yes
I think it has to be number two
They like 1834
Whatever was he graduated
Voted least likely to leave
The Union Army
Yes
If you want to go that I will respect that cuz I'm a fan
Make up your mind
Okay
Stop doing that
How many of your characters are your gloriously mistaken
The answer was of course a he was so afraid of blood apparent
Mima deal with raw steak
It does make you wonder how I guess that's why he wanted to win so bad
Be over
Fill out of Richard Grant doing Ark
We're going to give it to him because he's
Starting with one of our hometown the Stars
McCarthy
From Chicago are a winner Richards IQ
Donald Trump won
Bill is Putin
Doesn't matter
It goes as well for you
Noucome Oscar night
Has been nominated
It's so just lie for an Oscar for his performance
The can you ever
Forgive me Richie
Thank you so much
Turn heads when he walks are runway in The Listener Limerick challenge
Call 1aaa wait wait to join us on the air will be back in a minute with more wait wait don't tell me
From NPR
Support for this podcast and the following mess
Message comes from MailChimp
So you want to grow your business
Now what
MailChimp all in one marketing platform
That's what
It has all the marketing stuff you need all in one place
So you can save time and money
L powered by a marketing CRM so you can
Collect organize and understand your audience data
All to help you Market
Get smarter and grow faster
Learn more
DACA
Everyday
Underweight
To and from work
Laura Bates
It's like millions of women around the world
Suffered indignities
Big and small
It just
Made me sit down and ask myself why is this normal
What's the website called everyday sexism
And thousands of women that even some men
Started to share their stories to
Ideas around gender and
Power
TED Radio Hour
NPR
Cummins EGR WBEZ Chicago this is wait wait don't tell me
NPR news quiz
We are playing this week with Tom bodett
Maybe Higgins and Adam
Felber and here is your host
Heather Chase Bank Auditorium
Downtown
Chicago Peters
Bill is inspired by his
His favorite 30
18th century suit
Mystic
Ramey
If you like to play give us a call in one AAA wait wait
That's one 880-892-4892
For you from the rest
May this week is student France found out his parents are planning defiance
Visit
He wasn't up for all their drama
We can relate
So he did what anyone would do in a situation where we do
He's friend
Use French
Cuz that's not real
Is that a cheese or on we related
Evolve Togepi
Did he turn the plane around
In the movies
At one point
He he like
Who's the world's back on its axis
Yes
Lois Lane dies
I remember that
So something like that I don't know that you're saying
Like I said I haven't been following the news
I understand
He said it was on their plane or he said it was in the Air Force
We all know it's stressful this have your parents visit to figure out how to
Get sheets
It's off of beds
She can watch them
Explain how long you've been using your Netflix
Visit Indy
Prison life
Adam CNN business
Reports that employees across the
Country are experiencing
Extreme stress
Over what part of off
Casual Friday exactly right
Casual Friday they're stressed out by business casual
As more officers relax their dress codes
Employees don't know how to dress
When was just wear a suit and tie that's pretty obvious
When your employee handbook says use your best judgement
Or dress appropriately
Or you do you Queen
When in doubt just cover all the bases and wear a tuxedo on top and pajamas on the box
But I think
You know how that thing is like you should wear the same thing everyday likes
Eve jokes
Yeah maybe
To do that you just wear the same thing everyday
Don't worry baby
Like all the other workers
Yeah yeah like
Just like
You could wear a cop
Uniform Monday
Uniform one day
Coming up it's lightning fill in the blank but first it's the game where you have to listen
The rhyme
If you like to play on air call leave a message
1-aaa
Wait wait
That's 18892
2 4 8 9
Contact us
On a website wait wait
Npr.org
You can find out about it
Weekly live shows
Right here Chase Bank Auditorium
Chicago
And if you're tired of her
Pedal is getting questioned
Wrong
And you think you can do better
Test out your smarts anytime with our new
You smart
Speaker quiz
Just ask your Alexa or Google home to open
The wait wait quit
They open the wait wait quiz
Give yourself the sentence
Superiority
You know you
Maven win a prize
How you are wait wait don't tell me
This is Colleen from Nashville Tennessee Nashville
They are wonderful I believe shares in town tonight
Cher
That's exciting
Do you know that out of all the human beings have ever lived
She is the only one whose Acts
What do you do there in Nashville
You're a dentist
Do you work with likes
Cuz I know
Nashville is filled with aspiring
So do these guys come in and say I need a perfect smile for what am I
On the Grand Ole Opry
Music videos or whatever
Absolutely we do every we do little said that everything with teeth
Country Music Awards
That's my bike us
Welcome to the show Colleen you know what we're going to do
This point in the show Bill Kurtis is good
Going to read for you
3 News related limericks with the last word of phrase
If you can fill in that last word or phrase
Correctly to the Limit
Ready to play
Here's your first
At awards
Shows like flan
My big
My accessories
The best blank guns
Armless
It's a
Leather restraints
Let's both flashy and quaint
Like a horse
I am wearing a
That's a harness very good
Red carpets are always abuzz over who's wearing what and now it's
Who's wearing a what now
This year's hot items
The man is
Is the decorative male harness
If you like Beyonce was wearing that at the
RE Michael B Jordan
He's your fiance
Supposed to say that I got him
So you're saying that you're engaged and that holder
Restraining orders
Just a Dodge
Yeah that was a mix-up it was a restraining garment
Which was the hurricane so it was so silly what happened
For those who have not seen
Mavs
Beyonce Michael B
Jordan
The word out of the word show it sort of looks like
I'd like the straps for a backpack but they're
Isn't any backpack
Kind of like
Cloth brace
Scoliosis
At least you don't know what this looks like
Go ahead and Google mail and harness
But yeah don't do it
And don't do it at home
Yeah just don't do it the latest to wear this rock this look
Ahi
Floral Louis Vuitton harness
If you knew that it was the thing that his mom used
Do use to carry him around at the mall
You know his baby blue Jordan
Here is your neck
Limerick
How are condiments rating
With burgers or fries
It's still matched
Red pearls
In a jar like a sauce
Caviar
We're getting some real
Catch a very good
Is there someone
He thinks of ketchup is being
Ez2eat
Not gelatinous
What time zhuhai
Ketchup caviar
As it applies ketchup caviar the eggs
Rare catch
Little weird ketchup
Fill dirt
Lobular lobules yeah
It like little gel caps
Hemoglobin
Yes
Can you offer your dinner guests catch of caviar they'll know they're dying in a classy home
Or that they're about to play their tastiest game
8 ball ever
But also isn't like V
Of ketchup that nobody wants like that filmed
But you usually don't want
Very last bit of ketchup in the house
Please spell caveat
North k
That was Colleen
Here is your final limerick
This car rental gives
Svn
You feel
Having wet wipes
Close
Wedding during deal
Hams at 10
Yes
The car is really gross
At the
Driving wheel that steering wheel
Your friendly steering wheel with your own car
R4 x
Dirtier than public toilet seat
Which means it's time to remind everyone out there to always lift
When driving
People spend lots of time in their cars
Even sleeping and eating them but 32% of those surveyed admit they really clean it
Will a hundred percent of those people didn't hit that by rarely
They mean never
Every year a scientist releases
The study that points out that something that people touch all the time is really dirty in real life
How about gas pump
12000 * 2
The Germ load of a public toilet
That's why I always light a match
It's when I'm near them because I love
Bill how did
Colleen doing
Probably ingested very very well
We call it 3 at all
Congratulations, and they were hard to
Support for this podcast and the following message comes from MailChimp
So you want to grow your business
Now what
MailChimp
All-in-one marketing platform
That's what
It has all the marketing stuff you need all in one place
So you can save time and money
L powered by a marketing CRM so you
Collect organize and understand your audience
Data all to help you Market smarter
And grow fast
Learn more MailChimp
Dot-com
Support also comes from feather
Feather believe
GameStop when life change
Your furniture
I should be able to change with you
Feather is a Furniture subscription
Spell allows you to subscribe to more than a hundred and fifty pieces of quality
With options to add swap buy or return
At any time
Available in LA
Orange County
New York and San Fran
Visit leadfeather. Com
To start experiencing the benefits
Furniture
Flexibility
Feather
Furniture that changes with you
This message comes from NPR
Capital One
Is reimagining bang
By offering account
With no fees or minute
That can be open from anywhere
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Now onto my final game lightning fill in the blank
Each of our players was 60 seconds in which the answer is many fill in the blank question
Does he or she can
Each correct answer is net worth
2 Points Grille can you give us this
Adam has five
All right well we have a clear order here
Babe you're in third place for the moment
Your baby at first
Fill in the blank
On Wednesday President Trump called his intelligence
Naive
After they contradicted him on the
The dangers of
Blank
Burlington watches
According to according to the
Never here
Before I do
This week special
Counsel Robert Mueller
So that Hackers from blank
Sensitive files
Investigation
No it was Russia in
In this case
Turn everything on Wednesday Foxconn significantly
Scale back
Their plans
Tire 13,000 Factory workers
In Black
Hint
No
Airport
In Wisconsin
Hahaha
This week the United Arab Emirates
The gender equality awards were won by blank
Amon
Multiple Man multiple Awards all of the one by men following criticism
Social media giant blank shut down a particular app
The paintings
20 bucks a month
Everybody nearly Limitless access
To their data
We're looking for Facebook
According to a new report released
Thursday nearly half of all adults
What's in the US
Have some form of blank
No ha so it seems that way
Oh no I three-year-old was lost in the woods
For 2 days
His mom he survived because he was taken care of by a blank
Is that
Nobody
The answer is by a bear
Every parent sincerite open their child goes missing in the woods
Please let there be a bear nearby
The three-year-old told rescue workers
The bear hung out with him in the woods
Especially the bear
Who said this is the last time you wait until his wife gets home to eat
Eat dinner
Bill how did Maeve
Do
They've got one ride for two more points
And that's a total of 5
Which is means you're tied for first
Play with Adam
On Wednesday lawmakers had their first meeting
Reopening the government
To discuss a blank
Funding bill government budget
Security Monday the justice department under charges in
The Chinese Telecom Giant
Why why why
McConnell rails against the bill that
What would make blanket
Oh election day
After getting a tattoo that says
Seven rings in Japanese singer
Ariana Grande discovered her tattoo actual
Wechat blank
Smell my neck Japanese
BBQ
Ariana Grande
Text now it says blank
Japanese
Sushi
No it says Japanese BBQ finger heart
Abilene Colorado having trouble with his math
Homework ended up finding the answers to special
Buy blank
Find the answers
He studied
No I thought you were a father I know sometimes they do that
Choose questions by calling 911
But I'm 10 years old and I'm working my math home
Homework right now and
Can't figure out what's 71 / 3
The kids said it wasn't an emergency the operator
Police fired a nebula
What's the boy's house
In the hopes at least one of those adults still remembered
Do division
Bill how did Tom do an eclipse
It's a total of 10 puts him in the lead
Congratulations card
All right
Alright here we go atom
On Tuesday longtime Trump advisor blank plead not guilty delegate
Rodger Stone right on Wednesday the president of blank warned that a US invasion
Remove him from Power Wheel
War worse than Viet
Venezuela right this week the federal Reserve is that it
To leave blank
Interest rate right on Tuesday the Senate Judiciary Committee
William Barta
Black Attorney General Washington State
Is blank case
Continue to be
Measles
Right on Tuesday pharmaceutical executive John Kapoor became
Nodejs process
For his role in the blank
Opioid right after icy road condition
Car pile-up outside of Montreal
Canadian motorist
Stuck in an hour-long traffic.
Blank plate
Yesterday
Look at the big brain on it
I got the easy ones and the highway had to blocked off so drivers knew that be
Respect their Wild
Canadian hockey gear to go around so they
Open up
Some pads
Start to think I'm getting right there on the road
It's so sweet
Whimsical
Canadian
American Force once people realize that we're going anyway
For a while they don't laugh open up the
Simple out there
Bill
Did Adam do well enough to win
Guess who won
Well seven out of eight you were so close to perfect
14 more points you have a total of 19
Just for the record in the big game in the sky
You're the winner
It doesn't matter if we're going to ask our panelists to predict
What are we going to find that all this ice would
What is finally melt
A very special thanks once again The Farmhouse Tavern
Wait wait don't tell me
NPR WBEZ
Easy Chicago dissociation production
Doug Berman benevolent
Address announcers palfrey
Warehouse managers Tyler green
Are interns
Rachel klepper
Lizbeth no
BJ leiderman composer
Is produced by
Jennifer Mills
Miles dornbos
Emma Lillian
Peter Gwynne is arcwind Honorable Snowman
More than white
Our business and office manager
Colin Miller
An executive producer
Is Mike dead
Okay panel the Earth is now frozen solid what will we find when it all melts
Tom bodett
If I 20 some years in Alaska taught me nothing else it taught me this
Dog food
Babe Higgins
Germs and viruses
To even make the anti-vaxxers
CSUN
And Adam felber tragically the one guy who's going to vote for Howard Schultz
We're going to ask you about it
Wait don't tell me
Love you for listening
Peter Sagal
See you next
Is NPR