Support for this podcast
In the following message
Come from Duckhorn
California
Duckhorn Vin
Crafting classic
Napa Valley
Dance with the sense of
Place for more than
40 years
Learn more
Or at Duckhorn. Com
NPR
Hey it's Peter so you're listening to the show
And you're probably shouting on answers
Whispering
Public space
If you're listening to
Sly Wild
Wouldn't it be great if
Did shout out answers
Respond
Well if you have
Speaker it'll happen
Just ask
Ask your Alexa or Google
To open the wait wait
Quiz
And Bill and I will
Appear as if
If by Magic
Asking questions
For you to answer and
Bill will even
Give you your
Discord app
At the end
If you really good
When the Ulta
The voice of your choice
On your voicemail
The next best
Thing to having his come over to your house
Even better cuz
Try the weight weight quiz
G-Eazy Chicago this is wait wait don't tell me
NPR news quiz
Classy San Diego
San Diego California
Everybody we're delighted to be here in San Diego and we are lucky to be here two times over
First because of the beginning of the week the FAA decided not to ground any plane so we were able to get here and 2nd
Because then they decided to grab them after all so now we never have to leave
Believe San Diego in the first place even though he got rich and famous that would be skateboarding Legend
Tony Hawk
Turn to try your luck playing in our little Park
Give us a call the number is 18881
That's one 888-924-8924
Let's welcome our first listener contested
High urine wait wait don't tell me
Hello this is Trey
Atlanta
Hey Trey how are things in Atlanta
What you do in Atlanta
I am a y
You're a wine and
Spirits consult
Some people say is liquor good and you're like yeah
Well welcome
To the show trade let me introduce you to our panel this week first episode comedian
Who hosts
The celebrity trivia podcast
Go
Be yourself
He said carefully
On the maximum fun network is Helen Hall
What is the host of The Daily podcast
Tbtl in the public radio show Live Wire which will be at the Alberta Rose
Theater in Portland
Mark 28 Burbank
New York Times bestselling author of The Memoir you'll grow out of it in the voice of Jessie in the animated hit
Big mouth on Netflix
Hit Jessi Klein
Play who's Bill this time Bill Kurtis
Since from the week's news
If you can correctly identify
As I'm sure you'll know
You'll win
The voice of your choice
On your voicemail are you ready
To play
I am indeed
Here we go
Your first quote is from a young woman named Olivia Jade she's a student
Did the University of Southern California
And she's grateful for all the hard work it took for her to get there
School when you don't care
Anything about your learn
Turns out that Olivia is very caring
Grandparents help you get into that selected
School by doing what
Paid matches
Brides Olivia's mother Lori
Felicity Huffman and other shallow rich people who are not on TV
Where the dinosaur paying tens of thousands of dollars in Grimes to get their kids into Elite colleges
Parents who their kids we're going to need assistance getting into USC
See when the kids said Mom Dad
To us
What are the people that drive use all kinds of
Photoshopping
Santa pictures of actual student-athletes
These kids got athletic scholarships
Force Sports they did not know how to play
This is why I to freshman water polo players at Yale showed up to practice
On horses
That should be the punishment for the University
Sorry yeah
Well you're not winning at fencing this year
Perfect Chemistry
How different White
People are than a
Family
Parents went to
Hi there bribery
From there
To know how
Truly dumb they were
To me was that
The kids lunch
I really didn't
No
Their parents are doing it but then
Find that out in such a
The public
$1,000 coupon
Parents are going to jail because of how dumb you are
Just walking around
Typical college kids
Except for the fact they were feeling ever
Every class and everybody kept asking them to play lacrosse
Other than that
I have to say that as I was
A reading about
It struck me that
My parents really did not go to bat for me enough as a kid like if somebody would have come
To Walt and Susie Burbank until we can get look into Harvard
But it's going to be
$48 North Seattle Community College it is
All right tray here is your next
Quote
Destiny
And announced he would be running for president after
Who is it
That's exactly right you got
Irish Melody sounds like a Latino but looks like the teaching assistants you all had a crush on him
Freshman English finally threw his hat into the ring
That's revealing his perfect hair
From his announcement video is his hands
He just acculates like
Crazy they're all over the place
When they swear a man is President they're going to have to use a moving Bible
Sitting next to him during the announcer
And it's like she's trying to ride
Bobbing and weaving is it really that crazy
I haven't seen
Funny that said hola
The senate race
And then
Decided to run
Kind of like if you ask out
Prom queen
On a date
And you get turned down
And then
Decide to then run
For president
The prom queen
Almost
Said yeah
The prom queen only Turns You Down by
Wears his sleeves rolled up in the video
I'm not sure is that important to you
Yes
I'm when I'm with you it's hot
Senate race I mean that you seems very intelligent like Vaughn
When I saw pictures of him and his
Sleeves rolled up into
Yeah maybe literally was the last Democrat in America to say that yes he's running for
President and get none the less as soon as he did it
Everybody is all the people on cable news can talk about that or this or that
It makes sense because you really are the Democratic candidates
You smart
He's articulate thoughtful good looking
He's someone who's never been sullied by anything like
Trey your last quote is a computer scientist named Tim berners-lee he's reflecting on something he invented
30 years ago this very much
What did mr. berners-lee invented didn't quite turn out to be the bun.
Times that he hoped it would be
Internet very good and
March of 1989 we had a primitive internet use only by scientists but Timber
You look at a page of information on your computer
You click on one of the word
The interest you and it takes you to another computer
That shows you pictures of naked people
Remember life
Before the World Wide Web
Well I'm that old
Access to an Internet connect
Because I was the front desk
Person at the universe
First Tee of Washington visitor
Information center we have to compare those hooked up to the
Internet
And
Within 5 minutes of being on there I had found that they were
People making
Pictures of nature
Naked people butt out of the
Icons on the keyboard
Pictures done with like letters and symbols
Equal sign equal sign equal sign greater than
That's mine
Bill how did Trey doing our quiz he got three right he is a winner
Take me to my pet care
Right now panel it is time for you to answer some
About this week's new
Look a minor league baseball team in Florida has announced a special night
How much they will honor what near mythical figure
Is this involved is involved cryptozoology
Florida
That doesn't narrow it down at all no
The guy from Port St Lucie who tried to shoplift to Chainsaw by stuffing it down his pants
Where the guy from Volusia County in Florida who butt dialed nine-one-one while cooking meth with his mom
Florida map
Later on this
Here
Is minor league team Florida man
Is the special kind of moron committing the kind of unbelievably done crimes we depend on for our show
Florida man is the guy who Vapes out of a dead alligator or gets pulled over for drunk Drive
Having him and ask for his ID and the cop has lights
Sir Pizza
Victorian art show
So in July the Jacksonville jumbo shrimp
Baseball team
Florida man night
By breaking one law every in it
Are they giving away bobbleheads no that's just a bunch of people on meth
This is going to be the only baseball game where somebody literally steal second and then price
Ice to smoke it
That's no moon it's a game
I will be back in a minute with more wait wait don't tell me
From NPR
Support for NPR in the following message
Which comes from servicenow
In the world of work
Work better
4 people
Their cloud-based platform and solution
Is delivered digital works
Does the create great experiences
Employees
And unlock productivity for your Holt
Servicenow digitizes the work
Your people have to do so they can do the work
They want
Using technology to make people more product
Active and engaged
More at servicenow
We all have it on low
And sometimes
That's self
Can get us a
What did he say
I don't know what it is supposed to be next week
We visit a city that blurs
Reality
An online
With life-or-death
We're playing this week with Jesse Klein Helen Hong and look
Is your house at the San Diego Zoo
San Diego
No it is time for the wait wait don't tell me Bluff The Listener game
Call 1aaa quick way to play a game on the air
Hi Peter this is Carrie Phillipson I'm calling from Corvallis Oregon
What are you doing
Well I'm fairly recently retired and so I could
Spend most of my time
Doing all the things you don't have time for when you work
There you go what sort of things do you spend your time doing now do you know after work
Hiking Catalina
Doing the crossword puzzle
Wow I do those things instead of working so
Welcome to the show Carrie you're going to play a game in which you must try to tell truth from fiction Bill what is
What is carries topic
What the hell is your name
We were wondering the same thing
We came across
The term unit moon in the news this
This week what does it mean well
Are panels for each going to tell you but only one of them is telling you the truth
The real definition of the Moon and you will win our prize you ready to play
First letter
From Jessi Klein
4 decade
AIDS researchers have been trying to improve upon existing methods
Hormone birth
This week a group of reproductive science
Funded by Pfizer held a press conference to announce
Citing new pill
Being released under the name universe
The scientist Harold at Eunice
The first birth control pill that can reduce your. To literally just one minute
During the press conference
A female reporter asked if the one minute
The. Fell on a specific day of the year
A spokesman responded
Well with you the moon your period does
Liquor everyday
But just for a minute
At this point another female reporter raised her hand
So
You mean we will get her. Every single day
There be no days of the year we don't have her.
That's correct
But it's only for a quick minute
In a minute
60 second
A female reporter photo
We know how long a minute is thank you
Is there any predictability with Luna Moon as to what minute of the
The day your. Might
Strike
One of the men from the all-male team of science
Step forward again
No there isn't currently any predictability
Leah can come at any time
Another female reporter pose a question
Is there any reduction
Symptoms of PMS
To the universe
No there is not the male leader of the research team
Responded
And truthfully some of the symptoms might be way worse
Your period is only a minute a day so we think it balances out
At this point there was a murmur among the female reporters in the room and the spokesman
Step forward again
Everyone here seems cranky so we're going to end the conference early he said but please remember to check out
10 lb
You're welcome
Play the new form of hormonal birth control that reduces your. To just one minute
Everyday
Your next story of a Yuna Moon
Explain come from
Burbank
By all accounts the wedding of Irene O'Brien and Mel McClain Was A Beautiful Affair
They danced they drank and they promised
To stay together forever
Starting right after
After they got back from traveling the world without each other
Han Solo honeymoon
In one of its most Valiant efforts
Today to convince us something is actually a thing
The New York Times wedding section reported this week
That the new trend of
Solo Moon
Also known as yunnan moons are a thing
Where couples take their honeymoons
Apart from each other
In the case of O'Brien and McClain they say they realize they didn't really have the same trip in mind
He wanted to get drunk in France with his buddies and watch the Northern Ireland soccer
Routine
She wanted
To not do that
So she went and visited Niagara Falls
Other couples profiled about this very real thing what you know is a real thing
Because the sociologists the New York Times got to talk about it
Is the staff sociologists for the dating app bumble
Other couples profile
Set there solo moons or uni moons
Where the result of incompatible work schedules or just a desire to have some
Space from each other
After the stress of the wedding you remember that right the wedding the thing where you said your heart had found its other half and you
Slow dance to Toni Braxton
I mean is that not apply when the Northern Ireland soccer team is playing you guys
Do you know the new trend of going on your
Your honeymoon without your new spouse
The final definition of yunnan moon comes from Helen Hall
Kpop fans worldwide
Crazy
Are uni Moon
Arising
Sold 19 million
Albums and Counting
The fresh K-pop
Face is set to embark
Worldwide
Tour this summer
Which will be
To be missed
Spectacle
Because you need more
Trulia bleating goat
That has been autotuned
Hi kpop
BTS and Girls Generation
Set a music producer
Who asked to remain anonymous
Spider-Man
Fancy hotels in
Restaurants when traveling in their hair and makeup bills are outrageous
It just needs to
Sleep in a barn and eat hay
Uni Moon's music
Videos
Beecher the goat's head
With a holographic body of a human dancer
TwinSpires
Background dancing
Hillegeist
Pics of how to take goats
Poor are still being worked out
How to say the concert
Experience may end up being
The greatest
Alright here's what
True unimin was in the news
Here's what might be true
Tom Jesse Kline you the Moon is a new birth control pills if that's such a wonderful thing for women
Reducing that. To just one minute
Everyday
From Luke Burbank the new trend of newly married couples splitting up immediately to take their honeymoon by themselves
Unimin
For from Helen Hong you the Moon
The new hit K-pop Act
That's really just an auto-tuned
Goat
Which of these is a real
Definition of what a unit Moon
I think I'm going to have to go with the loop
Story about the
Separate
Traditional
People
Exchanging vows and then immediately taking off and not seeing each other for weeks
Bring it quick answer we spoke to someone who is very well-versed
In what unit
Is a honeymoon in which
The price or did you want to go on a honeymoon by themselves
Jessica Rubino and you know what her job is
She's the lead sociologist
At bumble
You're right Luke was telling the truth that means we got the point the deal with
Daycare
And now the game where we invite people to look back on their rich full lives and ask themselves how in the world did it leave them
Tony Hawk
More or less invented the sport
Professional skateboarding he was the first person to land a 900
Which I'm told is very impressive and the first person to
Skateboard on the grounds of the White House
Well the first person to go
Get permission to do so
He was born and raised in San Diego and still lives close to the skate park where he learn to ride Tony Hawk welcome to wait wait
So
Tony you are
50 now so what is it like being a skater
In your 50s
It's it's
Tough to
Stay up on New Tricks
How to say relevant to go up and down
Downstairs Miami
Soreness but I think it's I never quit that's my only
I understand you go around and do a lot of public speaking as well
I do yeah
Yeah
Connected into that world you you start making the rounds and
I've done
Speaking gigs
Credit Union
I've been speaking against I have cereal
Internet
Security companies
Nothing against credit unions in internet security companies
I ate some of them have all my money in the other has all my passwords
What do they want to hear
From Tony Hawk
Professional skateboarding icon
Six so far beyond cool
Yeah bro it's sick aeducan magic clips
You can get away and never said that in a speech I'm just
You could
Makeup
Anything you want it
Like she know I was
The first person to do a half left Bolivian
Whatever the heck did you ever hear someone say Fandango that sort of
The code word from
Experience skateboarders
When they're making fun of
So how would that come up
You clearly know that they're not a skateboard
Oh my God that guy was lying to me
Can I ask you a quick question I was obsessed
Skateboarder as a kid in
I wanted to build a half
Half-pipe ramp
In our backyard
Which would have taken up the
The entire backyard
My dad never let
Let me do it
Do you think if he would let me build that ramp I would
I'll be sitting where you're sitting right now
Will you tell him that
I'm going to call him really quick
Do you still practice skating everyday
Almost every day we have many children so usually our birthdays are focused on them but
Yeah absolutely I thought I was getting yesterday and I'm going to
B skating
Tomorrow on my ramp and Vista
I don't know if any other father has ever had to
Deal with this problem is a problem that you are so cool
No
Really not
And even
Even your kid
Yeah it sometimes
I have to say they are Jada cuz sometimes I get opportunities
And it's not something I want to do but it's a video to movie premiere and then I feel like they'll be excited about today.
We got invited to
Incredibles premiere
I don't know I'll see what's going on that day
Is a ride I created that snail
Andolino lime
Well I don't know how long is the drive
Is it true that you were the first person to be allowed to skateboard in the winter
I wouldn't say it loud
Oh yeah what happened
Well I saw I was there
During the previous administration
They had a bunch of
Prominent or celebritytypes fathers
Coming in they were talking to a lot of different charities around DC converter is it at the White House
4 in the morning
And I brought my skateboard because every time I go somewhere without my skateboard
People ask me that
It's always going to get caught there especially with the president
And suddenly I found myself in the hallway
Unattended
I was kind of looking around I had to wear other at a couple other pro basketball players
Insane group
And I
I said hey
Take my
Turn into photo
And I skated and
It went viral
I didn't got a date kind of ignored it
Really yeah
I think they just didn't really didn't want to say that I ever had permission they didn't want to acknowledge that I did it
But I would do it again
That's on Tony Hawk we have asked you to play a game where call
Calling
Hello you
Fancy
Bird
Tony Hawk
Obviously your name but it's also a phrase that here means
Fancy bird
A Tony Hawk
Craft fancy
Tony Hawk is a fancy bird never realized
Betty Wright
We're going to ask you three questions
How about other fancy birds get to write your Wynne AR price one of her listeners the voice of anyone they might choose in their voicemail
Who is Tony Hawk playing for
Dim light show Grand Rapids Michigan
All right I'll be ready to go
The Queen of England loves her corgi dogs
But she also has a strong connection with some fancy Birds what is it
At any time
She can choose to wear a quote Living crown
Which is a crested pigeon trained to sit on her head be
Bylaw Sion
Every
Swan
In Britain
Horsey among her bodyguards the Queen's own Eagle regiment to Squad
12 trained
Wow
I'm really wanted to be safe
You wanted to be so I'm going to go with it
It sounds so great to have those funny hats
Regal decreasing
Every British monarch
Technically owns every swan
In Britain
They're all loyal property
Wow the swan
You might get hit with a very famous person
So don't do it
Sex questions
Swiftlets
Triplets are fancy cave dwelling birds in Southeast Asia
Surprise
It's primarily for their what
Hey you're the only Birds known to lay Square egg
What's good for stacking
Be there saliva is used to make
A very expensive Gourmet soup
4C swiftlet feathers are super absorbent than used
To make the first
The Swiffer mop
Bird's nest soup I've actually had a
Yes you're right it is being the rhythmic make mess with their own saliva that saliva
Is then used to make bird nest soup Asian delicacy very good
The cape
Haley is the world's largest grouts
It's a kind of ground-dwelling bird
And the Caper Kelly has been filmed doing which of these amazing
Pete's a triple Axel while skating across a frozen lake
Be eating an entire anteater learning at the name anteater eater
Dorsey
Beating BBC natural historian David Attenborough in a fight
Wow San Diego I need some help
See I really want to believe these other scenarios though
Bro was kind of asking for it is very protective of its
Territory during mating season the watch made up of them
And the Caper Khali beat the hell out of him that's really not some flat twist
Tony Hawk in San Diego
When does the minute it's a heavy metal listener Limerick Jalen call 1-aaa twait to Jonas on the air
Sprint NPR
Support for this podcast and the following message comes from ZipRecruiter
Hiring used to be hard
Jobsite stacks
Resume but today hiring Canby
You only have to go to one play
ZipRecruiter
ZipRecruiter sends your job to
Silver 100
Of the webs
Chambord
Then ZipRecruiter scams thousands of resumes
People with the right
Experience and invite them to
To apply to your job
Transfer free is ziprecruiter.com
Slash weight
We may be on the verge
Another sexual Revolution
And this one
Coin counting machines
For companionship
And sex
My main objective is to be a perfect
Pet Companion
How artificial intelligence
And robot
A changing the landscape
Love
This week
On hidden brain
The NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Curtis Ware playing this week with Luke Burbank
Jessi Klein
At the San Diego Civic Theater
Pinterest just a minute
The Sorting Hat puts bill in Raymond and Claw in our listener limerick
Make a challenge if you like to play
Give us a call at 1 +888-288-924-8924
Bring up some more questions for you from this week's news
Look there's a new app with alerts people of nearby crimes in emergencies to help them steer
Clear of the area but now that it's out the creators of the Apple discovered one floor
The crooks are using it now
The app work
Justice
Is it intended
If you're using it it says oh there's an emergency of this nature Dinda
This place
But
The problem is people didn't do what
Go to where the emergency
Have you asked called citizen alert people to bad things happening nearby instead of running away people are running to the disaster
Masters and crime scenes because it's well-known selfies in front of bus crashes
Are guaranteed to get likes on Instagram
This is like a rubber necking finger
There's an active shooter let's go you know
Yeah but honestly we would all go
Yeah
Clown car on fire 3 blocks away
This is way better than what I'm doing right now
So much sense of finding real life disasters to watch is so much better than Netflix
But it would soon become just like what we normally do for entertainment
Building collapse already seen that one twice
Forget trying to pick which disaster to run to with your significant other
You chose carjacking last week
But we never get to see gas leak
Is it a
Kinship issue if your
Your spouse or significant other
Goes in watches
The crash without you
Open concept
Open space with no walls according to the Boston Globe
Residence
Who have these homes are saying they're great but they're just missing one thing
What
Wow yes real estate agent
The homeowners are expressing regret for
Moving into open concept homes
Families opted for the layout hoping it would promote more family togetherness and I thought the problem was
Parents are complaining they're unable to watch anything on TV racier than PG the kids are in the house right spouses are
Complaining that every time to themselves
And walk across the country are trying to make a living driving for Uber
Xen open console
Stop light with the living room in the kitchen
The real problem is went with the open concept bathrooms because yeah
A lot of hotels now with life
Like the weird open concept bathroom
Don't you want to
Stay in his room
Stay in when we go to
Chicago
Shower doesn't have a
Rush Hour.
Which I guess is
A novel
Wetness everywhere
Some homeowners are you been undergoing costly renovations to add walls back in good news though there are plenty of wolves
Family statues from down
At the Walmart
That was the lowest of the low hanging
I'm glad for one week it's not going to be me
The worst joke has been made and we know what it is
How would you make a wall out of ass
Hughes Peter
Lightning fill in the blank refers is the game where you have to listen to the rhyme if you'd like to play on air call the leave a message at 18881
AAA
Two forks forklift
The contact us link on our website wait wait. Npr.org
That you can find out about
Attending our weekly live shows back at the Chase Bank Auditorium in Chicago
Upcoming show in St Louis Missouri
May 9th
Hi my name is Maggie and I'm calling
Arcata
California
Miami theater
Teacher for children and 8
You are a performance artist
Well actually be kind of show today
We teach Ensemble base
Theater so they write their own shows
Perform in them
And we had one show that was about a baby dragon
Every 50 years in the world
That's very cool
But I'm sure that's going to be on Netflix next week
Because that's how we roll
Maggie Welcome to our show Bill Kurtis going to redo 3 News related limericks with the last word or phrase missing for me
If you can fill in that last word or phrase correctly into an alarm reaction will be a winner ready to play
I am
Here is your first
Limerick
PS5
5.7
My all liquid
Heaven Sent
Except for some beer
No food will appear
I'm giving it all up
Decided
Catholic to give up say something you love me
URL
Amateur
An Ohio man is making the much more sensible choice of giving up
Everything
Beer
It's a sacrifice in the Christian tradition of asking what would Jesus do to
Stay awake
440 days Mr Hall's only caloric intake will be beer supplemented by water or is it snowing in the Brewing into
Coors Light
Here is your next limerick
Destroy
It's more like a screaming
Squeezed
Toy
That Gravely much
Give us endorphins a rush
It feels many fans with
Pure
Psychologist
Have determined that fans of
Death metal
Arnott
Savage monsters desensitized to violence
People who just happen to like songs about stabbing ones
The researchers say that the dominant emotional response
To death
Metal lyrics is joy and empowerment
Granted it may be the joy of being a cannibal but it
It's Joy
The test group
Play music by The Band
Bloodbath
They had very positive thought
It's apparently
Well the control group who replayed
The song Happy by Pharrell Williams
Murdered for 10
Crocodile
Here is your last glimmer
Beard and beanies
Eclipse
Don't complain
Inside
That photo you saw and
Take down by law
That's not you
Well look alike
Here's what happened
Photo of a hipster
Study about
How
All hipsters
Look alike
And said hey you use my photo without my permission you lame
Do you lizards
And they checking no
It is a different hip
The handlebar mustache
This study was immediately pronounce double true and is now the single Unified
Explaining the entire universe
How did Maggie do an AR quiz
3 point
She's aware
Congratulations
Bye-bye
Support for this podcast
The following
Come from Stanford
What are the scariest thing
Mom look
Because the next
Our usual
Billy can fly
Or Joey riding the dog
Or a crayon stuck in Valerie's nose
Hear something
You might want to
With over 20
Pediatric office
Stanford.
Shins are all over
For the Bay Area
Not Justin
In Palo Alto
Find a Stanford PD
At Stanford
. org
From Duckhorn
Napa California
Founded by Dan
Ann-Margret.
Nineteen
Duckhorn
Crafting classic
With a sense of place
4 more than 40
With seven Estate Vineyards located
The winery produces vintage Merlot
Cabernet Sauvignon
Sauvignon blanc and Chardonnay
All showcasing the diversity of wine
Learn more at Duckhorn. Com
/ m p
Hey it's
Gyros creator
How I built this
We're returning to
San Francisco
Second how I built this Summit
Express
I'll be joining there by founders
Companies like
Instagram Slack
JetBlue
Many more
Summit.
Npr.org
To learn more
Now it's time for a final game lightning fill in the blank each of our players will have C
60 seconds in which the answer is many fill-in-the-blank questions he or she can
Peachwik answer net worth
Can you give us the scoop
Looking Jesse each have three Helen has two
Alright Helen you're in third place or up first the clock will start from the beginning first question fill in the blank
Wednesday moments after he was convicted on federal fraud charges
Do prosecutors in New York filed fraud charges
Against former Trump campaign chairman blank
Paul manafort
President
Impeach a
This week the Senate voted to end us support for a Saudi let military campaign in blank
Syria
A man in Michigan is facing charges after attempting to free his car from the snow by blanking
Getting his
Corgi Detroit
Take it out no shooting the snow with his
Is gun on Wednesday Mass administrator Jim breidenstein said the us could return to the blank is there
Early as next year
Citing concerns about salmonella Butterball recalled 7000 lb
The blank on Thursday
Turkey
I'm going to give it to you just because your parents would be unhappy
Call nine-one-one to report a man screaming and waving his arms the middle of the street
Was told the man was just planking
In Florida
She was told the man was just celebrating the trade of Odell Beckham to the Cleveland Browns
I just got home she's driving with the kids rights but little kids out of the car in this
Lunatics
Screaming and yelling in the middle of street
Did you call 911
And listen tops
This is what the cops found this is an actual recording of
Who's the guy that the woman song
The cops
Something good happened today explained
What was going on they
They sort it all out
To come down the general manager of the Browns and get him home safely
8 more points total of 10
Puts her in the league
Laura
350 coin in Luke is elected to go nexo
Here we go Loop
Fill in the blank
On Monday President Trump proposed the 4.7 trillion dollar budget which included 8.6 billion dollars
Search for blank
The wall
New York's attorney general for records on loans granted to blank
The Trump organization
Yeah pretty much in the World Health Organization said it was aiming to Halt the blank outbreak in the Democratic Republic of Congo
In 6 months
Ebola in South Carolina
When to do a Taco Bell and blank
No he went behind the counter to make his own Mexican pizza because he's
Said the one they made for him did not have enough meat on it
Wednesday social media giant the blank suffered the most severe outage in its history
Facebook
Instagram
This week a heartwarming photo of a four-year-old sleeping with his pet went viral because his pet
Was a blank
Taco Bell Mexican pizza is beautiful picture of a boy sleeping soundly in bed with cuddling
Help with his pet
Went viral because the pet
Was a gold
The boy took his beloved goldfish out of the bowl and cuddle with a
Has he went to sleep discovered
What happened to late
So they just took a picture which is easily the world
The cutest
Crime scene photo
But anyway
How did Luke doing our quiz
Look up for a ride
Bait more boys
Total of 11
Put him in the lead with one
All right
How many van
How many men does Jesse need to win
Portage
Biotulin here we go this is for the game
Okay on Wednesday UK lawmakers rejected a move to support a second referendum on blank
Right on Tuesday the US announced it was withdrawing its entire diplomatic
Staff from
Blank
A play
What is a place it's called Venezuela this week the house voted to release blanks report to the public
Four robbers were held at gunpoint into police arrived after the attempt
Mexican
EBay gun store
According to a new study blank uses linked to a rise in mental health problems in teens
Social media Thursday Empire actor blank pleaded not guilty
The Faking It assault in Chicago
Jussie Smollett
Then blank
No
Then an eagle pick it up and dropped it in the hole
After driving his ball onto the green the golfer assumed is only going to make part before the Eagles Swift Out of the course
Picked up the ball and dropped it right into the hole
Fancy indeed
That's right golfers
He got an eagle
Did Jesse do well enough to win
Total of 11
This week
Now that they won't be able to bribe anybody anymore how will Hollywood celebrities
Their kids into college
Chicago
Berman benevolent overlord Phillips
BJ leiderman composed erythema per game is produced by Jennifer Mills miles dornbos
Lillian
Only hope
Is Peter Quinn technical direction from Florida
Turn off managers Colin Miller oppression cordarius Robert
Executive producer Michael
Danforth now panel Howell celebs get their kids at the College calendar
Cellhire my parents
Adjust open their own College
3 words
Gary Busey state
Jessi Klein
They will take 4 years to shoot and cancer children in them
Students
Jessi Klein and Luke Burbank
Everyone at KPBS San Diego
Is NPR