Support for this podcast
Send the following message come from The Economist
A Weekly Magazine
Offering insight and a pen
On International and US News
The Economist
Is offering listeners out
Free print copy
For your free print
Just text weight
From NPR and WBEZ
You should not go this is
Wait wait don't tell me
NPR news quiz
It's Always Sunny in Philadelphia
I'm Bill Kurtis
That Harry got is your host at the Met
Performing Arts in Philadelphia
Pennsylvania Peter Sagal
It is great to be back here in Philadelphia the city where American live
Liberty was born
243 years ago next week
And can I say American Liberty you look great
Have you had some work done
Little baby talking to Jennifer Winer proud Philly resident and vessel
What's the first you want to hear
Your story the number to call is one Triple Eight wait wait
That's one 888-924-8924 let's welcome our first listen to contested how you run wait wait don't tell me
Hi this is
Karen Jones
Holly from the Queen City Charlotte North Carolina
They are raining right now but me
What do you do there
I am a Music therapist earn mental health counseling grad
So you're one of the people who uses music now people
Will feel better
Yeah yeah
I think I asked you for a nation what song would make us all feel better
Hellboy
I think this land is your land
Did the Great Wall all right we'll go with that thank you
Well let me introduce you to our panel this week first episode
Contributor to CBS Sunday Morning it's faith
Salem
Karen knackstedt the host of the public
Radio show live wire as well as the daily podcast
Pvtl which will be at the thing Festival
Port Townsend Washington
On August 24th
It's Luke Burbank
Hank Aaron and the comedian you can see August 16th
Hyannis Massachusetts at the Cape Cod Melody tent
You still host of the podcast nobody listens
Paula Poundstone
It's Paula Poundstone
Welcome to the show you're going to play who's Bill this time Bill Kurtis
Of course he's going to read for you three quotations
Suites near your job identify
Correctly
Two of them do that you win our prize
Is there any boys from our show you might choose in your voicemail
Ready to play
Asurion
Alright your first quote
Comes from Democratic presidential
Hopeful
Kirsten gillibrand
Bible
You suck
That was reportedly Kirsten gillibrand
Practicing
For what big event that happened both Wednesday and Thursday evenings this week
The Democratic
Exactly right the first Democratic debates
We're held this week in Miami
There were so many candidates they had to do it in two groups over two nights
Many of the candidates do not like
That they got split up
But not Joe Biden
He's cool with segregation
What what are the crazy things with how many
People
Were there
That you did not know John Hickenlooper
This is true he does not have he was the white guy
Do does not have much name recognition despite the fact that his name is John
Hickenlooper actually stop this is true on his way into the venue by somebody asking if he had credentials and he respond
Wanted quote I'm a candidate
Which one you think about it should be the campaign slogan for like five of these guys John Delaney 20/20
China Canada
How much minutes do they estimate that each person got to talk not very many
Well if you if you were man you got to talk 2 minutes more than any other
Is that okay
The dudes are ready to interrupt
By the way
Now that you mention it is time to declare my candidacy for the president
During the Wednesday events
The NBC audio
Fails
I'm here about 30 seconds of none of them
Speaking and now the leading candidate for the Democratic nomination
Is blessed
Silence
There is a lot of
There really was that that take you by surprise I was a
It was weird because I'm from Washington State and Jay Inslee it's the governor there in his whole thing is
Is climate change
You just like the most
Snapchat threat to anything that happens on this
And yet he got like kind of No Love after
The debate but everyone broke into Applause when like
Beto O'Rourke says
Yo quiero Taco Bell
20 years but he gets no traction
Don't you think dinosaurs had
Debates like just before
Is a problem
Debates
Alright parent is dying parent are you still there
That's great
I'm glad your name is parent
Yes to why I called you Karen
Because
Paris
I never occurred to me the parent
What's your name
How did you get that name
Today
Just
What's something transposed incorrectly on the birth record
I believe I believe your name is
Heron
That's what I hear Karen not parents
Oh I thought his parents and I thought menu
You're so lucky it wasn't
Gender weight
It's just something somebody misread that birth record
And here's your next quote it's about a phenomenon happening mainly at schools around the country
We only change things
It had Robert E
That was a spokesman for the Texas school one of many schools around the country that no longer want to be named
For whom
Robert E Lee Robert E Lee exactly
Many schools around the country not just in the south
Renamed to honor the confederate general in Imagine their shock when they discovered what Confederate
Means
Somebody's close friend you know
The problem is it's really hard and expensive to change a name
You know to take down all the signs and
Pictures and
Reprint the letterhead
To say
RuPaul Regional High School
According to the Wall Street Journal many of these schools are being sneaky
It will still be called the Lee school but it's a differently
Austin Texas is Lee Elementary School is
Now named Knox
The General
Russell Lee
Photographer from there
Lee High School in Virginia is now
Lee Harvey Oswald High School
Listen this is an easy one
Bruce Lee High
I mean if I was a kid and there was like Grover Cleveland or Bruce Lee hi
I don't care what the science program is like I'm going to Bruce Lee hi that run was badass name for his goal of all time
Sara Lee cafeteria
Karen Huger last
Quote
I hate the Heat
The humidity and
That was somebody on Twitter commenting on an article in the washer
Kitchen post
Breaking the news
That it turns out what doesn't make everyone happy
Summertime Summertime yeah
Having brought down
Thank you
Very good having brought down Nixon The Washington Post
Is now determined to destroy enjoyment
This week they published inexpensive takedown of Summer
What is wrong with these people how can you hate summer season when walking outside feels like walking
Into a bowl of soup
What how did they
It wasn't just an opinion piece or wizard
Research well there was talk to a lot of people who
Who said basically we don't like summer and the reason
God
Who did they reach out to how many people I mean how sign
Scientific
What's a study
It comes up with
People don't like summer
I don't know if they're saying like
Nobody like summer overrated
Yeah
High in the summer
Daylight and when I
Get in my Old Navy
The PJs at 7 p.m.
I feel like a loser
I got say one thing
To the post railing against
Summer
There's nothing we can do about it
What we're going to get rid of Summer we're going to get rid of old cameras
If anything we're getting rid of winter or summer yeah
How did Peron do
Should I drain
Regalo congratulations very well done
Congratulations
Time for you to answer some
What about this week's news
You're not feeling when you wake up and you have no idea where you are
How you got there
Will a woman in Canada experience that in real life
When she woke up where
Wasn't she
Stuck on a plane
She woke up in an empty airplane
She fell asleep
When she woke up she was still
Strapped in her seat
Freezing cold in the pitch-dark
Entirely empty
Keep playing
Parked on some
Image of a Runway
The Croods
Everybody was gone.
Is locked
Terrifying because the woman realize you never be this comfortable
Play Never Again
Yeah it was crazy because her
Phone have a little bit of battery life so she facetimes her friend
And said I am on an airplane
Still
Somewhere and then the phone died and she couldn't charge it because the phone does not Empower doesn't work on the airplane if it's off
So she went open the door of the plane which was like fifth
50 feet off the ground and just sat there swinging her legs
Trying to do SOS with a flashlight
She found in the car
What do the Galaxy
Reporter self
A whole can of
Yeah
All the arm wrap the emergency door except she hadn't given a verbal yes
Associate
I can
Certainly imagine that happening
Sleeping waking up in the dark
On the airplane
No one there
Yeah and if I was in an airplane I had to get off
Absolutely I would like
Inflate that slides
Oh yeah
Oh that's a good point
Yeah or put this
Feedback
Lock the way
What is a compact a quarter of an inch
Coming up we take to the streets to protest our own Bluff The Listener game
AAA
From NPR
Support for this podcast and the following message comes from
MailChimp
So you want to grow your business
No one
Male chimps all-in-one marketing platform that's why
It has all the marketing stuff you need all in one place
Do you can save time and money
It's powered by a marketing CRM so you can collect
Organize and understand your audience data
All to help you Market
Smarter and grow
Faster
Learn more at mailchimp.com
Drag his
It's been around for a while
In the Kabuki tradition in
Japan Inn Minstrel show
In Vaudeville
But one TV show made it mainstream
Now
We break down drags
Current Renaissance
Check out NPR's it's been a minute
Now
NPR
And WBEZ Chicago this is
Wait wait don't tell me the
NPR news
I'm Bill Kurtis
We're playing this week with pop out
Emma Stone
Celia look
Burbank
The man
In Philadelphia Pennsylvania
Right now it's time for the wait wait don't tell me
The Listener game call when AAA wait wait to play again in the air how you were on wait wait don't tell me
Hi this is James and I'm calling from
Salem
Exceptionally well what are you doing
I have well I guess technically for jobs now
So I do Uber or Lyft
I host trivia night
And I am
Currently being employed by you
UPS someone asked you like passengers who talked to you or the passengers who don't
It depends on the passenger Act
Call James it's very nice to talk to you without having to pay for
You're going to play a game with you must try to tell truth from fiction what's the topic
Text Bill that people will still probably be
A counter-protest
Isn't just what you do when Beto O'Rourke won't stop standing in your counter
It's a way to stand up for what you believe in in the face
Of the people who opposed
This week we heard about an unusual counter-protest
Are pandas are going to tell you about it pick the real one you want our prize
The wait waiter of your choice
You ready to play
Alright let's hear first
From faith
Salek
Denmark's most motivated anti-vaxxers
Decided to March
Search through the small city of Ross
Last week
On their way to demonstrating
Copenhagen
They expected to meet some resistance
But they never
Car and Sorensen organized the March along with her
Seven-year-old unboxing
Animated Sun
Axl
A dozen other families join them waving banners and chanting my child my choice
Young axle proudly made up his own chant
No Jabs no scabs
But he stopped
Yelling when he tripped over the body
The body of a man
Covered in boils
What the medical community might call
You both
The man managed to moan get out get out while you can
Karen grabbed Axel and let her group away from the body and noticed
Quiet
Roskilde sing like a ghost town
Door shutters
The wall of a building
Spray painted in blood red letters
Play
Inside
The terrified anti-vaxxers ran out of town back the way they came to get vaccinated against the bubonic
The mayor of Raleigh
Elizabeth Nielsen triumphantly yelled cut
And the town's pro-vaccination denizens emerged to high-five the actor
Anti-vaxxers with the bubonic
Twig and scares them away your neck story of somebody who DACA protest
The right amount
Comes from
Luke Burbank
They say neo-nazis are like ants
They're weird little creatures that can really ruin a summer afternoon
Okay nobody says that I just made that up but I think it actually has some potential
Anyway
The people of ostrich
Germany know what I'm talking about why
Because last weekend they were faced with
What the problem of a bunch of neo-nazis
Descending on their small town for a Neo-Nazi
Music Festival
The town decided to fight back against the festival how by starving the neo-nazis of their primary source
The food
Beer
First the police force got permission from a local Court to seize almost all of the beer in town
Before it fell into the wrong stomach
That Dope still left 200 crates of beer for sale in the local grocery
Restore so the people of ostrich stood up
They went to that local grocery store and they literally bought up all of the beer left in the town themselves
So the Nazis couldn't get it
The ultimate location of that beer is unknown and now appears to be completely missing
When asked
The townspeople burp
And the plan worked
Attendance at the Nazi Festival was down by over 50% this year
Peter
Spoiled
When the town bought up all the beer so that they couldn't have any your last or even
Productive
Comes from paella pan
The lucky moose Food Mart in Toronto Ontario did not get lucky when they made the decision
Not to allow soy milk and not milk
To abide in the section reserved for cow produce
Milk
The local vegan Community responded with a pro nutmilk day of Rage
Store posters
Screaming don't let dairy cream nuts
Unholster your Holstein
Someone
Watching on two feet and a cow costume wearing a sign that simply says how dare you
So at first it was assumed the people who got off the old timey truck with the hay on it with fellow vegans
They set up nut milking demonstrations with people in overalls sitting on stools trying to
Squeeze liquid from almonds and soybeans in the metal buckets
Others set up an enclosure for some nuts on the ground inside it and how come on kids
As if he can clear these were not vegans
Dairy Farmers sick and tired of raising milk cows from calves only to see them put out of a job by some damn plan
Doesn't even need refrigerated
Said a man who called himself old nuts farmer McDonald's who was actually an executive with a local
Dairy co-op
Andrew ordover
Just put it on a shelf in the weird food section
One of these was a counter-protest
It was actually quite
Success
Was it from faith saylee other people in the town in europe managed to
The foil of actors
By pretending they all have the Bubonic plague and driving them out of town
Was it from Luke Burbank Highway Nazi rally in Germany was foiled in all the towns people who don't like Nazis
Bought up all the beers of the Nazis wouldn't have any
Or from Paula Poundstone how some Dairy Farmers
Turn vegan protesters methods on their head in order
To make
Acclaim
For milk which of these is the real story of a counter-protest
I'm going to go with Luke story I say
You go with Luke story about the neo-nazis who gave up because there was no beer to be had
It sounds like something crazy German people might do well
We spoke to somebody who actually covered of the actual counter-protest
Some citizens decided to buy up all the beer
Going to local supermarket and to make it as quick as a spot for sure cuz if he doesn't end Indiana
Alcohol
That was Alex out of it she's a journalist to cover the story of the beer protest
Spiegel online news in Germany your congratulations James
You got it right boot was telling the truth
Here is the point
You winner prize the voice of anyone you might like on your voicemail congratulations
Thank you so much
It's been such a pleasure to talk to you in thanks so much
Bye-bye
Another game where we ask interesting people about things they're simply not interested in its called not my job
2001 Jennifer Weidner published a novel
Called good in bed
About a Jewish journalist struggling to balance career and a personal life
In Philadelphia
Despite its science fiction like premise became a best-seller as has many of her other novels
Meaning that what she really is
Is good
At desk
Jennifer Winer welcome to wait wait don't tell me
My mom would have been a lot Kathy or probably
That I understand I understand Philadelphia
First novel in mm
2001 which was like
A mini first novel
A graphical novel called good in bed aren't you bragging a little
Everybody says that like a happy
Happiest day of
Your life is when you
Sharon Spitz
In your book
For every author
You did not call her but good in bed I have to go tell Mom
And
My mother
He been in
Probably just
When I was writing
And every time I said I'm
Yes
You shouldn't believe me
And so I got to go home and I
Simon & Schuster publishing a novel in and she
Cry and she
It's hugging and we have this
Momentum
And then she sort of draws back a little test WhatsApp
Call
What's a good
In bed and she
What
Alexa
Bad
Not that I said it's good in bed mom and she's heard
Veggetti how much research did you do
Hahaha
Identifiable.
Tales about people you knew and had
Grown up with and perhaps who had mothered you
My mom had been
Married to my
My dad
At 1
And then they got divorced
In about ten years after that happen
All the women
We were
Me and the
My siblings
Sharks bite
Patent
Coming and shows like softball and
Stereotype but you know
People
How to come out to your parents like for your mom to come out to
Weird
Well I mean
She didn't tell us
Rachel showed you exactly what happened but you know that you know this or just the first
She's going to hit us
So what happened was
What happened was my youngest brother
Joe
What home did he was laundry
And called me at work at
Philadelphia
Inquiring
There's a woman
Living in the house
Their shoes and they're not friends shoes and their
Close and it's not friend
I'm close and then he said and I was in mom's bathroom
Toenails
When I found all these love letters
Find Karen
So the first thing I do is bite your toenails
Never going to happen again
And then like I'm the reporter and also the oldest
Just now my job so I call my mother up and I said you know a
Anything new when she
She says no and I say
I wanted to give her the chance to write took to come clean
And then she says there's nothing to do and I say
Joe says there's a woman
Winning the house
And there's this
Pause and then she says that's my
Swim coach
Oh my God
I should have known that in right
You know you're 50
For and it's not an Olympic years to what the hell
I meant and then she said you know that's that's Karen and she's the aquatics director at the West
BJCC
And we're in love with
Tattoo dates and she's moved in
But you literally said we're love to buy
Recipe for Passover
And you said yourself
It's a kind of an active
I always
Had but what I discovered when I got out of
Ecology
Like to apply for
Job like
Classified ads
Novelist
And I had to go get a job then I got a
Newspaper job in
In State College
And I had
Pretension
You said if I crash
My or fiction
One of the firsts
Refinements that they gave me was I had to type
School lunch menu
45 local
Real hot dog in bun
Milk
White chocolate I mean if it's not
Hypertension out of
Real real
At your latest novel misses everything
Is about your mother
Loosely inspired
Sickly pale
Because of the time in that it
Totally not allowed
Really
Gripping and interesting
And there's a
Sex scene in early on
I know
What was what was it like to write a sex scene
Involving us horrible mother
Horrible it was fight I just had to sort
Pretend
That she was never ever
Keurig
And she would somehow be like hit on the head and forget my
My name or the very fact of my
Fashion Fair Credit
Oh yeah
And what did she have to say
Vivid
I'm going for another swim lessons right exactly
Hi Jennifer weiner we are delighted to have you here
But now it is time to play a game that we're calling
Weather
Little whiner
It is the best ever time
Got to be named winner but
To be a whiner with so many places you can leave
Complaints
We're going to ask you three questions about negative reviews we found on
TripAdvisor
In particular reviews written by frequent TripAdvisor reviewer
My own father
Matthew Siegel
Reviews left by my father Matthew 6
Get to write you Enterprise for one of our listeners my father criticizing the size of your portions
On your voicemail
Bill who is Jennifer wyner playing
Living Diego warshawsky
You are celebrating their twat
5th anniversary beer
Hey nice don't let them down here the first question what did Ma
My father Matthew Sagel say about an Italian restaurant in Salem Mass
Massachusetts a quote
I was disappointed to find the Bread Basket did not have those crunchy breadsticks
I like them
I have little patience for excuses which we got
Like very busy tonight
I didn't notice
Busy night
Discount
Orsi's quotes despite with the waiter might tell you Pizza bagels are Italian food
And they should serve them
All right I'm I'm
Okay I have to pick one
Attempt at a joke and better than one which is what I could see
Peter Sagal father
All right
Sounds like he was trying to be
Free funny
Discount
I've got a bad review
In Sarasota Florida what did my father
Say about their ambience
Hey you don't get that warm feeling that they are glad you are there it's more like
I wish all these people would go away so I can go home
B I think those Chianti bottles with candles in them are nice
And I don't know why they don't have a few
Morrissey just so you know the picture above the bar supposedly of Rome is really is Naples
They should know that
Hi I'm going to say
The mural
You like that it was actually the first one
Olive Garden
When you're here you're family
Alright here's your last
All right part of a pretty negative review of a message
Seafood rest
What did the reviewer
My father
Say to the server
Lorna you sent her a message in the review
Was it a tool or not I won't send you the bill for the
The shirt you spilled sauce on
Because I probably would have done it myself
Soon anyway
Be more. Just so you know when I asked you to write down the specials it's not because I'm annoying it's
Because I'm hard of hearing
Or see a dagger Lorna you should be working in a place
That deserve
I'm going to say he said something
You are exactly right cuz that's my kind of guy my father is
Give her two out of three and a win
Jennifer Weiner's new book is missing
Is everything you should read it especially if you are her mom
Jennifer Winer thank you so much for being here on wait wait don't tell me
In just a minute we put on another pot of coffee in it
Listen to remember challenge game called 1-aaa wait wait to be back in a minute with more wait don't tell me
Freemanpedia
Support for this podcast and the following message
It comes from The Economist
A Weekly Magazine offering insight and opinion on International and US News
As well as economics
Politics
Business
Finance science
And Technology
There's something for everyone of you
Economist like the recent article the promise and problems of cities
Where an archaeologist
Explores the enduring appeal
Urban
Life The Economist is offering listeners a free print copy
For your free print
Copy just text
Wait wait
The nine nine
There's more to watch and read these days than any one person can get
That's why we make pop culture happy hour
From NPR
Twice a week we sort through the nonsense share reactions and
And give you the lowdown
What's worth your pressure
What's a Nazi
Subscribe to NPR's pop culture happy hour
Easy Chicago
This is wait wait don't tell me
NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Kurtis
Playing this week with Paula pounds
Luke Burbank
And faith
Salix
Had he regretted Rojos at something man in Philadelphia Pennsylvania
Thank you so much that my father gives Bill Kurtis
Performance
One88 92489
Right now panel tomorrow questions
For you for the week
Paula a new start-up
In Canada
Is the first ever to provide marijuana
Specially formulated for
Toddlers
No
Well I got it I got it
Just give me one hand and I might
Well you can lead one to water and its
Definitely going to want to take a drink because it is terrible cotton
Horses for horses
Why
Why not
For the first time in history were finally going to hear the words oh my God you know be
He's so good right now
Oats
A company called Kenna horse
Is making weed products for horses
Even though there's nothing worse than like a white horse
Thanks dreads in it
It's Menor okay
The
PPL account horse
Say this is for municipal purposes but then again that's what your 22 year old cousin with
Glaucoma says
Horses everywhere hear this news and they're like great
Okay could I use this
The day you nailed my shoes on
Is it making them high
How can you tell
You show up at a kid's birthday party in the pony is talking about how weird hooves are and
Movies
Anyway I'm really excited for the Kentucky Derby to take for Days Inn
Next year
Giving horses weed
Everytime something blows their mind and they go woah they stop
That just doesn't seem right that like horses will be the last animals we want to make
I just have this image
Tending around America around just be like
You know when I was a kid my mother would say you get off your high horse
I would think to myself
What the hell is that high horse of her time
Richard Thomas
Paula will know seals could do need things like balance a ball and clap their fins with
This week we learned the scientist
Scotland have been hard at work teaching seals how to do
And this given the healthcare crisis in
Crisis at the border and the crisis in our democracy
Is a huge breakthrough
They can sing rock and roll songs I think
They can sing yeah
Very good as well
Science time will you
What person on the planet will not benefit
From this
Are the Seals
Do we know what music
Yes we do
This
No I have like
3 Zola albums
And Josh
And what are the other ones one of them is
I just don't care anymore that's one
I love that and then there's a rap one
Kendrick Lamar
What is sololearn
Twinkle Twinkle Little Star
Star Wars
Theme song
Proving seals would do literally anything for the fish including
Selling out
But it's pretty amazing
And we want to show you some
The first of course
The real thing
He's back the thrill of hearing it
For the first time you really think I needed you to remind them the theme to Star Wars
Anyway
That was the real one obviously
Here is
Zola the singing sea
That's exactly the same oh yeah
That was a seal literally millions of fish
Don't forget that
What's the only possible way that this
Experiment
Or training or whatever you want to call it
What is Project
Could have any value
If it is if they taught at the Jaws theme
You know great white was coming up near you
Wild Kratts
And then you would know you know
Let's get out of here
Another seal to be like
What was that was like a teacher for the Peanuts cartoon
Coming up with Lenny fill-in-the-blank the first is the game where you have to listen
For the rhyme if you like a plan are called to leave a message
At 1 Triple 8 wait wait that's one 889-2489
Or click the contact us link on our website
That's wait wait I didn't hear. Org
Can find out about attending our weekly live shows back up
The Chase Bank Auditorium in Chicago and her upcoming shows in Newark New Jersey on September 12th and our show July 18th at the beautiful
Blossom Music Center just outside of Cleveland located within Cuyahoga Valley
National Park
Hi you are on wait wait don't tell me
My name is Candice
I'm from Norfolk
Virginia Norfolk Virginia bucolic Northfolk I was order like Norfolk
North Pole
I want to go local
Call it Norfolk
So you're not from Norfolk originally
I know I was
Freezing Florida
Do you ever Miss Florida
Nope
Oh so you are from there
Well welcome to the show Candice Bill Curtis is going to be the last word or phrase missing for me
If you can fill in that last word or phrase correctly into the limits will be a win
Ready to play
I am ready
Here's your first
My stomach I like
Flat
So it's coffee I drink
By the vet
I recently learned
It gets
Calories burned
Making brown kind of
There you go
New research has found that drinking coffee can stimulate a substance in the body known as brown fat
The stuff left over
For the pan after you make bacon
Would rather sell the produce heat
That then burn off the other kind of fat
Did you get from eating
Bacon
So the idea is that
Coffee helps you lose
Lose weight
This cannot be
Because if it were I would have banished
Decades ago
Want to be fun of coffee becomes a new health drink
It'll be great when it replaces Gatorade in the
Team wins the big game in dumpster
Big Ern of hot coffee on the couch
Alright here is your neck slimmer
In their enclaves the real was nesara crying
We can see the young fella is
Triumph
But his costume is
Poor Eddie's got a week
Roar
So he doesn't seem much like a
Lion the lion
An employee at a zoo in Japan finally got the role of a lifetime
Zoos emergence
The same way every time your building is a
The fire drill somebody has to
The fire
Do you have to find this on the internet
It is amazing
You think they choose like a convincing lion costume
But no it's a guy
In like
You playing the smiley lying in the school play he's got the
Does mascot
Plastic smiling lion
Walking around on two legs
You know cheerfully waving at people being a lion
Everyone on Twitter applauded the employee's job playing the line except of course for the zoos real lions
Called his performance derivative
An unreal
You know who would crush at that gig
Gritty
Here is your last
How are athletes are strong
Silverfish
Like Popeye
Their strength
What the minute
A dark leafy green makes them tough
Meaning
Lean
Yes I doping entails
Yes yes very good
Performance enhancing drugs along with unflattering shorts has been a long day
Problem in
2 banned substances well German scientist
Suggesting spinach
Should be added
To the prohibited list
Presumably
Because the scientist
Sorry team
AB 7 year old
Broccoli brussel sprouts
And cooties
So it's not it's not
Spinach it's not like
Spinach is found in some other drugs actually chemicals similar to a steroid natural
We found in Spanish
And it's so effective scientist really exposed
To the chemical compound were able to
Suddenly bench press 5
Popeye was a documentary
Yeah
That's crazy
It was that seeing that I don't didn't understand what I was
The kid where Bluto makes
Bill how did Candice doing our quiz
Alright thank you so much for playing
Take care
Support for wait wait don't tell me in the following message
It comes from rocket mortgage by Quicken Loan
Imagine how it feels to have an award-winning team of mortgage experts
Make the home buying process
Smoother for you
The history of industry-leading online lending technology
Rocket mortgage is
Changing the game
Visit rocketmortgage.com weight
Equal Housing lender
Licensed in all 50
Nmlsconsumeraccess org number 33
Rocket mortgage
My Quicken Loans push button
Get mortgage
Support also comes from
How do is a management software that covers all your business needs and a One-Stop solution
Odoo apps are perfectly integrated to each other allowing you to
Fully automate your business processes
What's a boost your business check out odoo new business games
Scale-up
It's fun it's Mart
Ennodu offers it for free
Shipping included
Use promo code weight
On Odio o.com
Scallop
Now once more final game lightning fill in the blank each of our players who have 60 Seconds
In which the answer as many fill in the blank question
Kansas he or she can
Each correct answer is worth two points bill can you give us
Walnut and Faith HM2 and Luke
We have flip a coin faces elected to go first here we go
The clock will start when it begin
First question
Fill in the
On a Tuesday special counsel blank agreed to publicly testify
At the Congress
Robert Mueller yes on Monday the White House announced
The new round of sanctions
Orr
This week the house oversight committee approval
Subpoena for White House counselor blank
Flight following a decision from there
Supreme court regarding a citizen
Question Trump threat
To delay
The blank
Yes after a cashier at Hughes
Houston Subway sandwich shop
Wouldn't give to
Two robbers all the money in the register
The thieves made off with
With blank
Foot feet long sandwich no one
Stolen cookie
On Tuesday San Francisco voted to ban the sale of blank
E-cigarette following a harrowing ordeal
A British couple is free after being held hostage
Stays
Buy Game of Life
Dormice no seagulls
Have the pair of seagulls
Nest it
And the couple's roof
They became so territorial that anytime the homeowners try to leave
The birds would attack
The couple contacted local official
Wildlife laws mean the gold
Protected and unable to be moved
In addition the Lost dates
The birds have the right to rummage through the couple's fridge
You get to choose what the four of them watch on
Every night
I thought you did quite well
Pretty good V Ride
10 more points and a total of 12
Polywrap next film
This week
John Sanders the acting Commissioner of blank announced plans
To step down
Border patrol
Write this week Senator Bernie Sanders proposed
The plan to eliminate all one points
Trillion dollars of blank
Call Steph
On Thursday former Trump campaign chair blank plead not guilty
The fraud charges in New York
Manifold right this week Japan's high-speed rail system
Suffered significant delays across the country thanks
To blank
Yes a single slug
In fact on the track
A Tuesday gun lobbying group blank severed ties with their PR firm
And halted operation of their TV
A fisherman in Michigan got more than he bargained for when he caught fish
That had
Blink
A fish that had his wedding ring
It was originally a mystery why the steelhead trout had a wedding ring and hide
Pictures of the Ring belong to another
Was looking for a poetic way to celebrate his divorce
Unfortunately
Unfortunately thanks to maritime law the man who founded is now obligated
To marry
How did Paula do I think she did really well
6 ride
12 more points
14 and believe how many did Luke Burbank
Es6 the wind will
Talking about to go have been reading the news this week I was looking for
For the best veggie
Terry and cheese
In Philadelphia
And I found it it was delicious
Let me very little time before reading the news
Give me the loop this is for the game fill in the blank
Tuesday was announced that Melania Trump
Spokesperson
Stephanie Grisham
Would become the next
What
Whitehouse post
On Monday the state of Oklahoma filed suit
Johnson & Johnson
Smallpox price
This week 1/10 America
Pinterest died will end
Are the Dominican Republic a Catholic bishop in Columbia now is that there is so much evil in this town that he plans to blank
Move to Las Vegas helicopter
On Tuesday Illinois became the 11th state to legalize and sales a recreational blank cannabis
British grocery store with the expiration date of
E-40
A British supermarket
Explained
Blank banshee
She should have gone to Wawa
Weather
Did they happen to be using the ancient Roman Calendar for their expiration date
The supermarket Shopper couldn't make sense of the bizarre 5 digit expiration date on a
The store happily explained
There was simply using the Julian calendar which was developed by Julius Caesar
It hasn't been used in 5
Hundred years
No one knows why they're using that system but I'd start by asking that one guy in the stockroom wearing a toga
Bill did Luke do well enough to win
Catch Palo Palo Palo
We're going to ask us to predict who's going to throw their hat into the presidential ring now that they
All the competition
The first let me tell you
Wait wait don't tell me the NPR WBEZ Chicago in association with urgent haircut Productions Doug Berman benevolent
Mxr public address announcer
Paul Friedman
A house manager is Tyler Green Assisted by Simon Tran
Avadian Lila Francis rweb Guru is Beth Novi
BJ leiderman composer I see my program is produced by Jennifer Mills
Miles dornbos and Lillian King
Are personal gritty
Is Peter Gwen back in our business and office manager is calling Mueller a production coordinators Robert
Are senior producer
An executive producer wait wait don't tell me
Is Mike Chim Chim Cheree Danforth now panel
Who saw the competition this weekend decided what the heck
They should run for president
Luke Burbank
The only candidate that can reach that elusive
Youth vote
Two Olsen twins on each others shoulders in a trench coat
Daily
Dora the Explorer although she has to brush up on her
Paula Poundstone
The Flex Seal guy on my television
Well if any of that happens we're going to ask you about it
Right here on wait wait don't tell me
The Hilton at Penn's Landing
Buffalo Bell on the staff and crew at the Mann Center of the Performing Arts
Thanks to everyone that hyy thank all of you here
Beautiful Mann Center for the Performing Arts great thanks for listening at home
I'm Peter Sagal we will see you next
Wait
Best