Support for this podcast
Send the following message come from the account
A Weekly Magazine
Offering insight and a pen
On International and US News
The Economist
Is offering listeners out
Free prints
For your free
Just text weight
From NPR and WBEZ Chicago
Wait wait don't tell me
NPR news quiz
Ask.
For Whom the Bell Tolls
Ask for whom the bell tolls
That's a Chase Bank
Auditorium in downtown Chicago theater
Thank you girl thank everybody thank you so much
Interesting show for you this week
Later on
To Valerie
Jarrett who not only
Was a senior advisor
President Barack
Mama but is the longest
Serving
Senior advisor to the president
In US history
Street every minute
Of all eight years that brings up an interesting question what dirty
Exactly
Does she have on him
Will be sure to ask her but first we're going to ask you some question
So give us a call
The number is 10008 wait wait that's 18892
248 nights
Two for the let's welcome our first listener
Contested how you are on wait wait don't tell
I figure this is Michael Wozniak from New Britain Connecticut
Michael wazekwa New Britain I know where that is what are you doing
Financial Solutions advisor
What is a financial
Solutions
It's kind of a financial advisor
Oh okay
Cuz I like a financial solution to be like
You need more money
Welcome to the show Michael let me introduce you to our panel this week. It's the co-host of the podcast
Nobody listens
The Paula Poundstone
Adam felber
Features writer for the style section watch
Roxanne Roberts
And the writer and actor you've seen on Veep and also playing the VP Mike Pence on the
Show with Peter Krause
Hello
Who's Bill this time
Of course Bill Kurtis
This is going to recreate for you three quotations
From the week's news your job correctly identify or explain
Just two of them
Do that you win
Enterprise avoid
Your choice
Ready to do this
I am never ready
Sounds like a great
Alright your first quote is the president of the United
It's reacting to another
Countries provocation
I have a feeling
And I may be wrong
And I may be right and I'm right a lot
But it was a mistake
That was the president
Acting is the voice of reason
Really after who shot down an American drone this
Exactly around yes if you were really into that
80s Vibe of US versus Russia you were going to love this reboot of US versus Iran
You know Madonna's on tour right now they're making a new Bill and Ted movie
What's the only more 80s thing you could have right now is a businessman named Donald Trump driving something he runs right into the
The ground but you can tell you can tell the Arabians are kind of enjoyment to sell
Altitude are even selling hats and Tehran that say make death to America great again
Got to laugh because you have to laugh
Chucky ending it all
People in charge
Just didn't notice going to work out
Things have been getting
Intense as you know for a while
First the US
Withdrew from the Iran deal then around allegedly attacks on oil tankers than
Trump
Accuse Rouhani of getting a bad facelift
No way that was
Rosinski
Then this week in Rancho
As you heard instead of responding with his usual fire and fury said hey was probably a mistake
Did he suggested it was some underling that
Was I acting about mistakes
Exactly later in the day around was like no
That's a little like get out
He said she said about
Where the Drone was we said it was
National Waters they said it was over their land
AR
Proof was
A Google Maps thing with a little
Blue.
This is where the law came from
Motorcycle that looks
Just make that
Hand drawn map
That was like a missile here and then like the golf and stuff like that it was really like I don't believe
Peter Vue
Made by Google
Is it said that it was
37 hour drive
Highest winds
Shooting down drones iOS
Use Waze
Why is Trump trying to keep this war from happening
Well he probably took a look at Iran
Anti-gay
If I woman and I do and he's like what what are we doing I ran is my base
Michael
Michael your next quote is from a former adviser to Barack Obama
When are the primary wouldn't lie all puppies and rainbows
He was talking about 23 people who find each other
Who are they
The candidates for the Democratic
This week the various presidential candidates on the Democratic side
Finally started attacking each other
It was real
Mano a mano fight
Will actually because there are 23 of them was actually mano a mano a mano Y Manalo
Joe Biden
The front runner
Bragged about his ability to get along with people he disagreed with like
He said segregation
From the cell
It is unclear why he did this
It's because Democratic voters are probably
Not looking to replace Trump
With someone who gets along with racist
Better
His face is you take away
People
People are like well now I'm listening to nobody
I mean
Oh bless his heart
Everybody love
How do you say about a cousin
He's like kind of
Yeah
Change to vote
He has the ability to
Witchcraft the island make
Congress get along and be effective
Give again is a great
Strategy
Anyway we're all going to see this
Play out because the debater next week
Who's going to be two of them
Can Canada tonight
The first question for the moderator is going to be
What is your name again
They said when they do the debate
To be like
Just go down the line
Please say you're opening
And then you're closing
Dear Michael is your last quote
Spikes
Head horns
And the phone
Bone those are nicknames given to a supposed numedica
Phenomenon
A bony Spike growing in the back of many people's heads
Is entirely due to what
Looking down on your phone exactly right Michael
It turns out that looking down at our phone so much might actually be causing a bonus
Spike to be growing in the back of her head
You can feel the bone if you press down on the back of your neck
Package right underneath the Apple logo
And the serious this is happening because we're constantly looking down
Nrr head is like growing a little
Extra bone
Help
The muscle support the weight of our hanging head
-5
It's not a problem if there's a way to get around this what we can do is we can all stop staring.
Your phone we just hang our phones
On the phone with a person walking in front of her
What if we
Instead of
Look down
You know how they have those
Headsets
Yes yes
So why don't you
Maybe do one
Where the phone
Comes out in Hangzhou
In front of you
It's always like this is such a
Play the humans
Thing that
We're doing now
Don't change
The problem like what
Innovate our way out of
Nobody is alright realistically
How did Michael do
Tony said he was never ready but boy
Congratulations Michael
Right now panel time for you to answer some questions about this week's
More and more people are using sleep tracker
Wearable gadgets
If they give you data to help him
With your sleep but according to a new study
These sleep trackers
Can also cause what
Anxiety and insomnia exactly right
You say irony they say business model
The devices monitor your heart rate your restlessness
As we roll around your REM cycle and they give you a
Sleepscore basically they have
Gamified sleep
But new research shows people are so anxious about getting a good sleep
Score
You know it goes you'll get a good sleep
Score you won't get into a good sleep
Read School
Photoshop
People
Like I don't know why it is but two
Cheat their step counter that it's
Sometimes
We I learned that from you Peter like
Tracker equivalent like attaching it to a
Corpse
Does the steps of a cat
Does the sleep tracker customize Android
Tell you what
It just gives you the raw data are asked
My phone doesn't without me asking
It says you haven't been getting enough sleep
You should get more sleep your phone. There's yeah you turn your phone off
You sleep well I've got let this thing is like it tells me time for bed
And then you go to bed yeah
That's why you have school tomorrow
Why does my stepmom
Coming up our panelist at lots of excuses in a game
To play
Wait wait don't tell me
From NPR
Support for NPR in the following message comes from
ZipRecruiter
What if you had your own personal recruiter to help you find a better job
Naot ZipRecruiter technology
What you can do that
At 4 you just download the ZipRecruiter app
Let it know what kind of jobs are in
How to put your profile in front of employers
If an employer likes your profile zipper
Recruiter lets you know
So if you're interested in the job
You can apply
Download
Free ZipRecruiter job search app
Today
I'm at the power of Technology
Work for you
Alabama man tried to forget about it
Can a decades-old
Level
Lenovo
The finally after all these years
He's admitted that he participated in
But I never have been able to get
Call ER it's White Lies listening
Drive now
From NPR and WBEZ Chicago this is wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
And here is your host at the Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown
Chicago PD
Right now
AAA wait wait to play a game on the air how you are on wait wait don't tell me
Hello Peter
Hi who's this
My name is Mark Dougherty and I'm
Taunton Massachusetts
I'm actually going off to Amherst
Falter
What you going to do with that
So I'm actually going for a double major in history and Chinese language and literature
Cool that'll be useful when they finally take over
Marcus nice to have you with us
You're going to play our game and what you must try to tell truth
Fanfiction Bill what is Mark
Topic
Where's my $22,000
Bill Kurtis is upset because he got paid $22,000 a word and there's a doll we shorted him
Last week
That's not the only missing 22 Grand are panels are going to say but someone that had the unlikely
Excuse
For the $22,000 that were missing that we heard about this week
Pick the one is selling
Enterprise
The wait wait her of
Your choice
On your voicemail you ready
Play oh yeah alright first let's hear from Adam
Felber
Mr Palmer Connery was shocked when his watch repair store called to say that his beloved
$2,000 diamond-studded Rolex Yacht-Master 2
Couldn't be fixed
Because it was infected
Fake
He had it appraised only a year ago and it never left
Was disappeared and then reappeared by that same
Magician
Wait a minute
Yes please last
Sweet arrested Glasgow Scotland beloved Illusionist the amazing Ferguson
Ferguson they discovered
Had a second career selling high-end watches on the internet
It turns out that Ferguson would inspect his audience with
The security cam before the show
Selecta Patsy was a nice watch
I didn't choose his Mark to volunteer during the show
Get him on stage and make it disappear
Moments later he cut open a fresh
Watermelon with a hat
An inside
Would be
Of course it wasn't
Police say that
The internet records show that over the past five years the amazing Ferguson
Has racked up sales of more than 1.5 million dollars in stolen watches
Stupid online boutique
Called
Appropriately enough
Magic time.
When confronted by police
Ferguson's excuse was that he
He's just a bad
Magician
I never figured out how to get that
Trip to work
I get the real watch into that melon so I just
Well
I had to get rid of all those watches
A bad magician the amazing Ferguson said they had to do with $22,000 watch
Cuz he didn't know how to make it really does
Disappear
You're next
Story
Of missing money comes from Roxanne Roberts
Colin Williams
Supposed to be in Tech
Court Monday
Instead he was
Front of a Toronto
Judge
Any white couldn't pay the
20 mm
Do taxes on
His mother's estate
Before closing on his
Sleep moms
Home
Williamson
Drew the money
From the bank on
Friday and Hilda
Giant garage
Sale on the property Saturday
Because his son
Is quote abs
Test
With money
Williamson aloud
6 year old to manage
Toy cash register
Distributing Monopoly money
According to the Toronto
2 *
At some point
During the day his son
Seoul
Some puzzles
A Yahtzee game end
Old copy of
Monopoly
Replacing
The fake bills
$22,000 in
Ncash
Williamson
Chad green
The character he had
No idea what happen
And until hours later
And zero clue who bought
The game Noir how his son
Confound the real
Currency in
Replaced it
He's asking
The judge 2
Forgive the debt
Arguing that he should
Before stew
Ways to satisfy
The tax bill
The judge has given Williams
In 30 days
To recover the money
Eeyore quotes
Do not pass
Let's go do not collect the Cavs
Romani and then it went out with the game at a garage sale
Your last
Story of a surprising excuse comes from Peter Gross
Best drama crime and intrigue
Tucanos Zoological Garden
News in Abuja Nigeria
Earlier this week
Sixpoint
Million naira the equivalent of 22
$2,000 went missing
From the zoo's office
At the end of the week officials finally cleared the suspect who have been blamed for the theft
A hungry gorilla
Butter wine
When the money first disappeared a local radio station
Nation interviewed an employee from the Zeus Finance
Best apartment who claim with a straight face even though it was on radio
Gorilla has broken into the office
Just taking the money
And then eating it
If that seems
Strange and foreign to wrap your head around just
Is the international news story exchange rate
A gorilla breaking into Nigerian Zuniga
6.8 million naira
He's like a bear breaking into a waffle house and eating 20
$2,000
They came a shocking update
Run-of-the-mill human Criminal
And how would the cops
So sure they could exonerate
Suspected Simeon
Well as Abdul
Governor of the Kano state
Told reporters
The issue of the gorilla
What is junk journaling
This is because there is no gorilla in that Zoo
That's right to the Zoological Gardens doesn't even have a gorilla
Police initially considered the possibility that the cult
Could be a dick
Gorilla from a totally different
Zulu just visiting the zoo with his family but that realize that this was ridiculous in the whole gorilla eating the money store
So where do we buy skids
If you're going to say the dog at you
Your homework make sure you own a day
All right
So $22,000
One from another went missing
What was the
Excuse offer
From Adam felber was the magician who made people's watches this
Superior but never could figure out a way to give him back
Roxanne Roberts
Money used by a child
For a monopoly said who then sold the Monopoly said at a garage sale
Or from Peter Gross
A gorilla broke into the office at the zoo and ate it
At a zoo that doesn't have
A gorilla which of these is the real story of Aeneas
Excuse for losing money
That we found
Emanuelle
VW type
Between the Monopoly in the fake gorilla
Gorillaz
Alright your choice that is Peter story about the gorilla to find out
The correct answer we spoke
Put someone who
Expertise about the real
It's not that
Crazy
How to say that a girl of my
Come across
Stack of paper that I passed and eat it
Behavior and ecology at Central Washington University talking about the Puget
Steve Cash eating gorilla
Who did not exist
But now we know
Congratulations you got the right Peter was telling the truth the whole time you knew that
You win a prize you get to choose any place you might like on your voicemail Peter got the point
Regions Bank
Thank you so much
Reply thank you very much
And now the game where we like to ask
Important people about unimportant things
We all have friends
Some of us are lucky enough to have very close to
If you are like
Enough to have friends so close they become
Family
And as far as we know only one person had a friend like that
Who got elected president
And then brought her to the White House
To work as a senior advisor for all eight years of his
His term and that's
Former
Obama White House senior adviser Valerie Jarrett Valerie welcome to wait wait don't tell me
Thank you so much
I didn't know and Marvel that you were the longest
Serving presidential advisor
In history
It's not crazy
I maybe I was old enough to appreciate the fact
Best job I would ever have so why would I leave
A second before I
1159 Secret Service Drive gave me that look
But you better get out of here girl
Are you kidding here I mean did you actually stay there till the very last day of President Obama
Exaggerating I waved
Goodbye to the Obamas when they went off to the inauguration
And that's when I finally went over to The West Wing
And turned in my credentials and my
Yeah my iPhone and just as I did that I picked in the Oval Office
They had already taken out
President Obama's Furniture was on the
The Colonnade the new PS4 going up like that okay
Guess it's time to go
Wow
No no U of course met the Obamas when you were here in
Chicago were you I'm just going to say this cuz I read your book you were kind of
Big Shot
Well I met
Michelle Robinson in 1991
When I was trying to
Recruit her to come at work
With me and the mayor's office
Running her fiance didn't think it was such a great idea so Michael who is he and why
What does he have to do with it Beauty we were taken aback by then
And she said he's going to be present
Give him a second
Pramoxine like when healing usual is that bus
Having now known them
Since 1991
Every single day
Decision he made for
About his career
She was right there at the
The table as well as more indication of the partnership
Said they were forming even before they were married
They make big decisions together and so they invited me to dinner and I said oh okay
I'll go to dinner with you too
And am I glad I did that was a
Good movie
I guess he wasn't even a state senator then
You know what I thought I thought this
Smart
Dedicated
Guy he's committed to Public Service Maybe
Just maybe one day
He could be mayor of Chicago
Besides him up that way before you noticed his ears
You know what I didn't notice his ears until everybody else started make
Making fun of them I Really they just kind of went unnoticed and that's why he loves
But I did not notice the yours
You are a senior advisor and your job was essential
Play dealing with all the other levels of government the needed things
The White House
Did you call me mr. president all the time
I called him as
President whenever we were at
The man and
Who invited you
Who is Baraka took out the cocktail
Shaker
That's exactly right
Well it is a pleasure to talk to you but we have in fact invited you here
Two-player game
We're calling
BJ's
Ceviche
Your initials of course they're BJ that made us think of it
Stick speed
She's the bjr
Video jockey the people who used introduced
Music videos
On MTV back when they still showed
Music video
Answer to every question
Correctly and you Enterprise will never listen to the voice of their choice in their answering machine
Valerie Jarrett
Christopher Jones update
Madison North Carolina
Oh I before we begin when we were speaking earlier I told you that we had your
Former boss in
Current friend of Barack Obama on the show when he was a senator
And we tried asking three questions about something we didn't think
You know anything about it and he knew all about it
And you told me that he did that all the time
The scary Annoying
Yeah
Did like you know military
Prince coming to say well the new plane and he said you mean the F-35 and he'd like know more about it than anybody else
Yeah that happened a lot
In fact
He said you know I actually know something about
I just want everything
Never gave in to the urge to just slap
Julie
Noted
Here's your first Quest
Nina Blackwood one of the first
MTV
DJ said she was reluctant to move to New York
I take the job but she felt she had to y a
She just got in the great new haircut
I was tired of just
Describing it on the radio
Beat it was the only way she can meet her Idol
Billy Idol
We're seeing MTV Executives saved her life with the Heimlich maneuver and said to her now
You owe me
I have no idea but so I need a friend
I need a phone
Barbie baby age
She got a cool haircut
It wasn't Taxi
It is actually happened at Tavern in the green she was out there talking about the jobs
I started a joke
He gave her the Heimlich maneuver and said now you owe me
No
Rue
Not sure I believe it but
She said it happened
And I came from her back
Who's your next question
Comedian Russell Brand was hired as a VJ for British MP
TV in mm
He lost
The job in late 2001 ya
He came to the
Studio dresses Osama Bin Laden just
The few days after 9/11
Be he brought his drug dealer
To the set to meet
Kylie Minogue
Horsey
He brought his drug dealers eight-year-old son to the set
Baby Kylie Minogue
Pretty good chat
That is pretty ridiculous
What was the last one
Timeline Google again
You're right but as Peter said
They were all true
Not only that
He did it all on the same day
Delorenzo's drug dealers eight-year-old son to the SAT they fired him two days later
All right
Here's your last question
Eventually MTV fire WJ stop broadcasting videos and move to reality TV like
Jersey Shore
In Japan
When they broadcast that show
What did they call it
Hey the odd human
Who do not wear shirts
Be American hellhole
The series
Orsi MTV Jersey Shore the New Jersey life of macaroni
Skulls
You know the answer
Could you just Googled it is that how you know it is in fact
Is the Japanese people sometimes used
Describe
The colorfully ethnic Italia
Bill how did Valerie Jarrett do in our quit
None of that is very flattering
I'm just going to say this
It kind of bothers you that you didn't get one right is that right
Yes
If I'm
Not
Incorrect I think Valerie and I share it
The same birthday
And
The teeny bit competitive little bit a little bit
Yeah I know I don't like
We won't tell the president that you didn't do as well as he did if
No I have no one to
Valerie Jarrett book is called
Finding my voice my Journey to the West Wing and the path
Forward it's available now
Valerie Jarrett
In just a minute we look at you with puppy dog eyes and our listener Limerick challenge game call one trip
From NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor the Illinois office of Tourism who would like to ask if you're up for a man
Amazing
Chicago to Lincoln Springfield from Shawnee National Forest to Main Street Galena
There's a lot
To see in Illinois
Some might even say it
Amazing but we won't because
That's really up to you
Visit enjoy illinois.com and see if you're up for what some people
Michael amazing
Evangelicals play an important role in
Today's politics
But how and when
This group become so political
This week on through line
The history of evangelicals
In America
Through line from NPR
The podcast where we go back in time
To understand the present
Chicago
Wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news
Who's playing this week with Peter Gross
Adam felber
Roxanne Roberts
Hear again that your house.
Set the Chase Bank Auditorium
In downtown
Chicago
Bill Carruth
CU it's not
It's rhyming
In our listener Limerick challenge
I'll give you like to play give us a call at 1 AAA wait wait
That's one 888-924-8924 but right now
I'm free from the weeks
Peter an Alabama man currently one
Good for drug possession and how many more
An Alabama man
I'm currently wanted
For drug possession and other charges insist that the
Despite reports you've heard he never ever ever gave
Crystal meth
Who is what
Okay
I'm going to get five quick gas
Sun
None
Watermelon
Close
Received to Roxanne
Is this the Mets
Squirrel
Mickey Play-Doh
Mickey Park
Is actually wanted fugitive location unknown but he called The Washington Post
He called The Washington Post just to deny the accusation that he had been given
Map to his pets
Squirrel
Names
Deez Nuts
Quote
My squirrel is baby to beyond anything anyone can imagine he's right
Besides he rescued this girl as a baby
Bottle fed
Earlier this week
Authorities in Alabama rated as a
Department of drug raid
And found what they called
Seriously
Unattached
Squirrel
And said that Mr pacu had fled
Literally have been feeding the squirrel meth to make it aggressive
They put out a warrant for mr. Fox they would leave
Is the squirrel in the woods
What
Hell yes I did that and then who was it that they wanted Fugitive
Says he went to the woods
To rescue the squirrel
He says Deez Nuts responded to his voice and came scampering down
Andouille shoulder
Then
He posted a Facebook video of him and the squirrel
Showing them
In response and I need to say I have not yet
Forgot to make anything up
The Limestone County Sheriff's
Office said
That may not even be the same
Wow
Power Ranger
Squirrel
Next story
Where
Is wandering through the woods in Alabama yelling
Deez Nuts
This again
Coming up with lightning fill in the blank the first it's a game you have to listen for the ride
If you like to play an air call leave a message
Did one AAA wait wait
Before you can always click
The contact us link on our website wait wait.
Npr.org
There you can find out about attending our weekly live shows right here at the Chase Bank
Auditorium in Chicago
Are upcoming shows on the road
Thursday at the Mann Center in Philadelphia
July 8th
The blossom
Etcetera just outside
Cuyahoga Nash
National Park
Hi you're on wait wait don't tell me
This is Renee and I'm calling
From Alpine
California
It's about a half hour
East of San Diego
Beautiful
Well I'm a wildlife biologist
So I can
To wander around looking
Endangered
Creatures and sometimes I
Mark about South American
Starting big ones
Who played Crocodile
Anaconda
That's cool
Wow
Renee welcome to the show
This is going to be a few 3 News related lyrics
The last word or phrase missing for me
If you can fill in that last word or phrase correctly into the limericks
I will be a winner
Here
Your first
All pups
Looks so cute then so why
It's not just theirs
Sweet little size
It's one little look
And I'm deeply sure
They've got those
Adorable
Yeah
How you be interested in
This is a biologist in new study
Suggest
The domesticated dogs
What type of all the ability
Deserve raise
Is there eyebrows
How to make those so-called
Puppy dog eyes at their owners
Their findings were published in the journal
Who's a good sign
But like that classic
Puppy dog look
Please love me
That look
They found the dogs and gray wolves have very similar Anatomy
Special eye muscle
Pools that allow dogs
To do that eyebrows
This is why we
Like dogs
Is in fear wolves
Apart from the console
Achilles Tang
Puppy dog eyes
What's are other apps
Try to eat them
Directions
Cute things
Can't compete
Yeah
Here is your neck
Limerick
For fried food with glazing
We go nuts
The hole in the middle is a slow cooker
The Bronze Age did the sing
Of the powerful ring
We just found
The world is old
Donut
Austria
The first-ever donut
The archaeologists believe
Bronze Age
Baker
Made the quote ring-shaped lobes
Really impressive
Archaeologist
Found the whole lot
Container Mark really really really quick
How many
Years
After early man discovered the donut did they realize that also discovered
Sunday's my case
Pass me a donut
And he dropped it in the rolls on the ground
Now we have a way to go get more Donuts
We should put a card on for donuts
Alright here is your last one
Once it's born
Who will he
She or they be
Well not a doll
But you better
Maybe
They'll need someone to blame
So put us in the game
If you pass
Will damn your new
Baby
Online baby naming company future perfect
Takes the stress out of naming your child by letting you hand it over to a complete stranger
It sounds like a good idea Until you realize the company makes all of its money
Selling at
Welcome to the world
Wild
Cherry
Pepsi
$400 a company's Founders will be for 15 minutes
15 minutes
$50 also provide you with a list of 10
Potential first names
Prudential middle name
The granted it is
Is technically a tech startup
Appsodo probably just name your baby something weird with
With no vowels
This is little baby Nixon
This is ridiculous
Bill how did Renee DeWitt AR quiz
Well Rene is going to have a good time on those Wildlife Explorations cuz he got all right
Congratulations
Support for this podcast and the following message comes from
Odoo odoo is a management software that covers all your business needs
Needs in a one
Stop solution
Odoo apps are perfectly integrated to each other
Allowing you to fully automate your business processes
What's a boost your business check out odoo new business games
Scale-up
It's fun it's Mart
Ennodu offers it for free
Shipping included
Use promo code weight
An OD
Gooo. Com
Skillet
This message comes
NPR sponsor
Capital One
With the spark
Cash card from capital
You earn Unlimited
2% cash
And all of your business
Think about it
Unlimited
2% cash back
On everything you buy
And that cash back
Canada $1,000
Would you can reinvest
Back into your business
So you can
Keep growing
Imagine what unlimit
2% cash back
Could do for your bed
Mora capitalone.com
What's in your wallet
Now it's time to move on to our final game lightning
Fill in the blank
Keep our players from that 60 seconds in which to answer as many fill in the blank
Russian does he or she can teach correct answer
Now with two
Can you give us the
Add event Peter each have two rocks
Sam has three
All right
We flip the coin Peters elected go second so adamant that means you're up first look like
I will start when I begin your first crush
Can fill in the blank
On Wednesday Mexico became the first country to
Designed the USA
MCA trade deal
Is intended to replace
Blank
Write the FBI revealed this week that they were
Conducting tax
Psychology test
Following the deaths
Tonight American Taurus
In Black who Dominican Republic this week President Trump launched his re-election
Can campaign in
Blank Orlando Florida on Thursday
Latest race Republican blank announced eat once again run
Alabama Australia
Is it stealing 18 beers
Getting drunk and starting a fight
With a cow
Kangaroo
Hey
Different Apple recalled certain blanks of a risk
Fire
IPhones
Following complaints from parents
Video streaming service blank announced
Considering moving all kids videos
To separate
To write the nominees for the Espy awards were released this week in early favorites include
Simone biles Serena Williams and blank
Ruth Bader Ginsburg
You are closer you're closer than you think
What is the answer is a fifty-year-old nun
Sister Mary Jo subject
Threw out the first pitch
Which of the Chicago White Sox game and stunned the crowd
By throwing a perfect
Curveball right across the plate
Videos which went viral
So
Don't know how viral did it go are you
Better not watch that video
The video of the pitch went viral in a sobia is up from one of sports most prestigious award
It's going to be so embarrassing when she
She wins
And during her acceptance
Forgets to thank her husband
God
So how did Adam do on Earth
You got five rights
Unsteadily
The blank on Wednesday the UN found Saudi Arabia legally responsible
Go to the death of journalist blank
Jamal khashoggi communications director blank and gave limited testimony before
Okay write this week Joe Biden came under Fire for highlighting his work with no did it blanks
As an example of bipartisan civility
Horned devil
The courtroom and was declared dead
This was Mohamed Morsi
An elderly man in England who found his entire vacation and a GoPro camera was a bit too
Disappointed Mini review the
Footage and found black
Who is older than he
I thought he was that he had the camera pointed at himself the whole time in the Dominican
Republican
The shooting of baseball star blank with a case
Mistaken identity
Big Poppa
Yeah David Ortiz according to a new survey
Over 40% of blank colonies died out there
Martian
No honey bee colony was a woman who ask for a Mariah Carey themed birthday cake
Was surprised but you got blank instead
No
Instead of Mariah Carey Can't you got to Marie Curie cake
You told the color cuz she wanted a cake of her favorite pop star but they misunderstood and got her a cake of Doom to know
Nobel prize-winning chemist Marie Curie
Bill how did
Peter doing art
4 right
8 more points
Penso he's inside
Alright how many does Roxanne need to win
Alright Roxanne this is for the game fill in the blank
On Wednesday the house Judiciary Committee held a meeting to discuss the possibility of offering blanks to African Americans
Dubai slavery
Reparations for domestic abuse
Patrick Shanahan withdrew his
Press secretary black
Defend right this week Boris Johnson took the lead to replace blank is the prime minister
Brighten reversal of obama-era climate laws EPA East
Directions on the blank end
Coal industry carbon emissions
Cancel Good Omens of show that is blank
It's it's
It's
Vic they think it
Heretical and
Dan but it's not
That's true but we were looking for is there trying to demand Netflix
Alex cancel Good Omens
The show that is not
On Netflix
According to a new study more pregnant women in the US are using blank
Are using
Alcohol marijuana Taco Bell announced they would not be adding the popular me
Meat substitute blank
The Impossible Burger
Speed internet across Kentucky
Has been delayed because of blank
Is this the one where the
Squirrels ate through all the
Going to blow the charge of the project 110 million.
Kentucky state government
High-speed internet lines
That was supposed to be up and running in April
Have been delayed thanks to rabbits squirrels
One squirrel
In particular
Did Roxanne do well enough to win
Well she needed
Sex
We're going to ask our panel
To predict what will be the
Surprise at the Democratic debates
Tweak
Thanks once again to stock and Ledger here in Chicago for free
Wait wait don't tell me
Is the production of NPR and WBEZ
Chicagoland Association
Doug Berman benevolent
Public address announcers Paul
Sweet-bitter house manager
Tyler Green Assisted by Simon
BJ leiderman composer Theme by Jennifer Mills miles dornbos and Lillian
Are Wheel of Fortune before and after is Peter Gwinnett
Technical directions to Lord of white hair business and off managers Colin Miller
Producers in Chile
An executive producer waitwaitdonttellme is Michael.
Surprise
At the Democratic
Debate Peter Gross
Everything will be going along very swimmingly until the moderator will be interrupted about an hour and a half in by Peter Cycles phone
Time to end
Roxanne rapper
The mepps squirrel run on stage
Is Joe Biden of low energy
Adam Silver
What's prize candidates
From Alabama
Is NPR