Support for this podcast
In the following message
Come from Duckhorn
California
Duckhorn Vin
Crafting classic
Napa Valley
Dance with the sense of
Place for more than
40 years
Learn more
Or at Duckhorn. Com
NPR
Summit Dr NW
Uchicago
Wait wait don't tell me
Play NPR news
Georgia style take a bite of your
Peach
Such a pleasure
Can you making your debut
It's Savannah course
He famous for among other things
I being the setting of the book
Until midnight
In the Garden of Good and Evil
Now this
What is a Corsa Pub
Public radio crowd
What is youngest we want
It's going to be more like 9 p.m.
In the Garden of Good and Evil
The first
This last week
Former
Georgia gubernatorial candidates
The Abrams
Delivered
The Democratic
And it seems it didn't go away
And I'm saying this because apparently the only talk shows
She could get put on after it
What's this one
Play not my job but first
It's your turn
To call and play our game
The number is 1 AAA
Wait wait that's 18889
48924 let's welcome
Our first list
Hi you are on wait wait don't tell me
What are you doing
Understand
I also play competitive women's kickball
Of course you did
Everybody in Austin is obligated by city ordinance
Well welcome to the show Heather
Let me introduce you
First step of the writer and performer
Put you last
Saw as mic
Pants on the president show
Peter Drucker
Hi how are you
Next to feature writer for the style section of
It's Roxanne Roberts
Hello hello
They finally responded
CBS Sunday Morning
And hosted the new podcast
Obituaries available
Wherever you get your podcasts
Play Louisville
Going to read your three quotation
From the week
You know that's your job correctly identify or explain
Two of them do that
Choose
From Marshall
Ready to play
I'm ready
Alright your first quote
We all heard
Tuesday night
Ted legislation
Nazi war and investigations
That was just one of the versus dropped by Master MC Donnell
Trump
During what
Speech
It seems crazy
All
In the delay and in the end
It was so boring
Disappointing to see
That you have
Expected Adam Levine.
To come out in the middle
This speech
Did make history somebody analyzed
And found all the words that had
Never before been
Sunset in the state
Changing address at all
This is real
Bloodthirst
Chilling
Fentanyl
Heartache
Freeloading
The dipstick
Venomous
And kissing
Where you said all those things
The President Trump still hasn't said Tiffany though I don't know
She was there she was there
She was there
Behind
Neither one of them
Glokknine
Which I think is
Vitriol there were
For example many of the Democrats
Warwick
And all of the Republican
Did wear different color
Blood Ties
That's Limited
It was amazing
I was wondering lately why is he making
Rhymes
Dr. Seuss
Lake Elementary School
I bet
Advisors
Explain
Alright your next quote
From a woman named
Silhouettes
Saint Twitter
When we said more black
We should have been more specific
All right
Scandal that was apparently end the career of every politician
What state
Virginia
Happening in Virginia
The female members of Congress are not the only group of Democrats that dress alike
Governor Ralph Northam he was elected
Over a guy who is running on a
Really racist platform but it turns out
Before you vote
You got to check under the hood
Somebody found
Photograph
Medical
And it's a picture of a guy in
Blackface
Next to a guy in a
And the governor immediately apologize even though he said
That he did not
Remember which one was him
Blackface
Is there a Jeff Foxworthy joke or it's like
I found this astounding
First of all
I was shocked
Medical schools have yearbooks
Done the Press
Best conferences
Play hard to get
Shoe polish coffee
Your skin
Wasn't me
In those
Photos
I was wrong but he says
Put shoe polish on my face
Michael Jackson
And somebody says can you feel me
And he says I would but my wife just told me it's not the right moment
Wow
Florida must be sighing relief
The Democratic
In the middle
And then we're not done
Does I edited
So seriously at this point Virginia is changing its name
East West Virginia
Headed your last quote is from a critique of a new play that
The author hopes to debut in New York City
It was long-winded in Meandering
Thankfully none of it was rap
So that was the New Yorker talking about
The play that was written
Just because the play's author hate
What
So much
Hamilton very good
You may have thought it was actually illegal to dislike Hamilton
You're not right you should be
Schmale Reed really hates the musical
Because he says that by making Hamilton himself a cool
Hip Hop
It covers up Hamilton's realized
The slave owner and generally bad.
Ishmael Reed wrote a play called The Haunting of lin-manuel Miranda
In which
The author of Hamilton played by an actor
You know that's the most beloved musical the modern time
He's visited by ghosts of people from history telling him how wrong he is
That's the plan and of course we guess
He'd be both people visited by a ghost of lin-manuel future who says don't worry about all this I am so rich
Is it be
They did a reading with the New Yorker 10 that they're hoping for back
Display
Kids Maria Von Trapp ism
Please get down from there Fiddler
How did Heather do an AR quiz
Comfortable shoes a great sport that at all those answers were right
You're a winner
Right now panel is time for you to answer
About this week's news
Peter Delta Airlines is the most recent airline Under Fire for its
Inappropriate actions
This week they're fighting a social media backlash after they passed out nap
Cocktail
Did encourage the passengers
To do what
I wear blackface
No
That I was like right down your
Yes phone number for who you have a crush on the plane
Yahari do you notice
The promotional cocktail napkin set
Quotes write down your number cuz you're in a
Airplane full of Interest
Can people in Hay
You never know
Who's the serial killer
What do you say if you want to pick up somebody you noticed on a
Plane
The drool from your mouth while you were
You were sleeping coffee life
When you walk out of
The bathroom you
There's not to go in there playing that the whole thing was creepy
It got weird when the flight attendants open up the bathroom and asked if anyone wanted
Suspend the Flight of the fantasy
Coming off our panelist are looking for clues in an Unsolved Mysteries left a listener game
From NPR
Support for this
NPR
And the following message come from better
Betterhelp offer
Licensed professional counselor
Who specialize in
An issue such as
Depression stress anxiety and
Connect with your professional
Counselor in a safe and private online
Have your can be
Get help
At your own time and your own
Schedule C
Secure video or phones
Plus chat and
Send text with your therapist
Visit betterhelp.
Slash weight
Learn more
Get 10% off your
First month
I feel pretty when do we feel pretty why do we
And who gets to decide
What pretty is
Will answer our listeners Quest
It's All About Beauty this
On the coast
Fish podcast
From NPR and WBEZ Chicago
The NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Kurtis
We are playing this week with Roxanne Roberts mobile rocket
Peter Gross
Is there a host at the Johnny Mercer theater
Georgia
Peter Sagan
I'm assuming you're all excited because it is time
For the wait wait don't tell me if you can call one Triple Eight
Wait
Play AR games in the air
Jonesboro Arkansas
Now where is that exactly
That is it
I am in outside sales and I am
Can you make a living as a competitive BBQ
Cricket player game in which humans try to tell truth from fiction
What is Chris's top
And then
The case weather
Cold
There are certain Mysteries that may never be solved
Who killed Jimmy Hoffa
Where's the Malaysian Airline
Why could no one in Virginia think of any other Halloween costume
R panel to tell you about the current unsolved mystery somewhere in the world picked one is telling the truth
You win the leader of you
Your choice on your voicemail you ready to play
Rocco
It wasn't long after
Teresa DeRosa of Sydney
Australia
Reported her pet missing
Reddit caller was found outside the nearby Chun-Li daycare center
Do you know it was like family she said about her
3 year old
Pet dingo
Then just a week later
Danny Hartman
Bingo
Went missing
The end of it
Its tail was found inside the daycare center
Astro statue
Another missing
Something go the next day
Sidney Police Inspector
Bill Keef
Can be the Press conf
What everyone already suspected
A baby
Which baby from the daycare center was fearless and hungry enough to overtake and consume at least 3:35 lb
22 babies were called in for questioning
Had to have the contents of their diapers examined
Pain 18 month old
Libre soy delicada
Not surprisingly her mother Olive vehemently deny surcharge
Lily may have a healthy appetite
And abnormally large incisors
Can you do that while I was nursing her I ate a diet rich and Jackal me
The investigation continue
Bingo
Or so say some people in Australia, your next story of someone looking for
4 Clues
Geneva
Switzerland has an alphabet
Problem
Specifically
Scrabble problem
About 3 months ago
Game lovers in the
Swiss City found the letter n
Missing from new game box
Khalsa manufacturer Mattel confirmed
But the games have been delivered
Stores in Taft
If someone in town was buying the game
Removing all the
The tiles of one letter
Resealing the Box in shrink wrap
And returning it to the
Store shelves report to BBC
Over the next few weeks
Customers reported the same problem but with different letters
D in December
J last month
And just this week two boxes had the f
Wyomissing
No security cameras have images of the
The culprit
But the mystery has
Activated game players all over Europe
Speculation ranges from a disgruntled
Delivery Man
Or an evil
Crossword puzzle fanatic
To Mattel itself as an Insidious way to boost sales
A spokesman for
Scrabble said to the BBC
Quote
This is an unacceptable breach of fair play and we will
To the letter of the law
Somebody's stealing random letters
Scrabble set
In Switzerland
Your last day of a mystery yet
Ubisoft
Canadian
Police are looking
Her mistress
Ontario Canada might sound like a strange setting for a
Taylor International
Mystery
Lakewood stolen prop
Pretty fast cars
Sex
But that's exactly what happened
This week
In the city of
Mississauga
Ontario
Police pulled over a speeding vehicle
They discovered that the vanity lights
On that beat
Stolen from another
Car and place
On that car
The sergeant Kerry Schmidt
Karaoke
Please post
The plates along with the following message
On Twitter
Is yours
Looking for the rightful owner of mist
Yoursexy license
They were unlawfully attack
To a Maserati driven by a
17 year old driver
150 km an hour
Just for the record that's about 90 miles an hour in about thirty years
Too early for a midlife crisis
Play didn't belong to the teenager when they pulled over and asked him
Are you mister sexy
Seungri replied please Mister sexy
David
Recorded incident of
Someone going on Twitter during work hours
Posting that they were looking for mister
You're sexy and not getting fired
The first vanity license plate imbroglio to rock our neighbors 2
To the north in January Manitoba
Play reading
ASI
Mila tour
Assimilate will revoke
You concerned it was an insult
Indigenous people
The owner of
Toddler explain it was actually a reference to a famous saying by the
The board
An alien species
Star Trek which allowed on
Ontario Police
How to safely scratch
Mr. Toler
Potential Miss
You're sexy
All right
There's somebody out there
And they're going to get them
But they don't know what is yet
Is it from Morocco
A baby
Will be eating dingoes
In Australia
From Roxanne Roberts
The mystery Vandal who's removing random letters in Scrabble sets in
Computer Gross
For the mister sexy
Of Ontario Canada which of these
The real
History
I'm going to go I'm going to go with Peter
Do you know what Peter Gross the story
Well we couldn't find this person who's missing but we
Could bring you
One of the people
Looking for
That was Sergeant Kerry Smith of the Ontario Provincial Police talking about the search for Mr sex
Mr. sexy if you're listening
Meanwhile congratulations Chris you got it right here with the first telling the truth
Everybody.
Sexy wherever he is also happy
He's actually
Thank you
And now the game when we asked really important people to waste their time on unimportant
What are the most popular Democratic candidates of the 2018 election cycle with Stacey Abrams
Georgia
Tri-Rail
Against Georgia Secretary of State
State
Who oversees elections it's a little bit like playing a baseball game against the umpires
Lost the race for governor but that has not kept her off the national stage
Most recently giving the Democratic response to the State of the Union Address and now she's here
We should start by saying you've been you presumably been listening for what stage do you have a response to
The first anniversary
I do but it requires
The teleprompter of fake
Non-green
Sunscreen and a union hall
The State of the Union response
You must know that that is a cursed
Draw
Yes
So I don't have a job right now
Nn
How did you say to you how did you plan that you would not end up on that list
I drink a lot of water early
I used a
Local
But very moisturizing what's
And I pray really hard
Call to respond
Did you
Think it all about what you anticipated prison
Trump might say so you could respond to
I would put it this way
I have
Hurt him
Yes
I assumed it would be some combination of
Demagoguery
Self aggrandizement
2 lines about
Something nice
Nice but he would three lines later overrule
Did you know that it would rhyme
That I missed and you know I feel sorry for whoever thought that with the right way
Way2go
State of the Union response is where you going to do it and what the background is people to try various things
You went for it was a union hall you say
And in behind you at all these
Unusual
So you were like
Looking it up
Speaking to us
And it really is blurry figures behind you and I was like oh those are the ghosts that are
They left undone
Question
Have we met
Before because
I went to Theater Camp with at least three girls named Stacey Abrams
It's entirely possible
Everybody knows you for your 2018 gubernatorial campaign here in Georgia
People may not know
His evil list
Completely different career
Reading romance novels
Can you tell us about that
So I had to turn a bad breakup
What's up
My boyfriend
He is a chemical
The wonderful person
I read his dissertation when I was in Lost
On
Microsatellite technology
And so I thought this thing he created he discovered I was like
You could have perforated increases
Chemical weapon that could be discovered by the floogals physicist
I could never happen even no imagination
I decided
It's a right to things I wrote.
Very exciting Treatise on the operational
Income tax exemption
And then I wrote
Romantic suspense novels I technically write romantic
Since I kill a lot of people and then those who survive in Fall in Love
Rules of Engagement my ex-boyfriend than the
Genesis of the story
Languages in prison for the rest of his Natural Life
Invited you here to play a game we're calling
It's a fine bromance
What do you know about bromance
You're not speak its name but instead shut it at frat parties
What are three questions about bromances get to write you when our price one of our listeners the voice of anyway
Giving response
Voicemail
Bill who is Stacey Abrams playing for
Eli Arvin of Pooler
Georgia
Which of these is a real example of a historical
Bromance
Hey Saint Augustine used to invite his bed
Best pal Olivia's to hang out
In an actual cave with him in the mountains
She called our beloved man
Cave
Be in the early 1800s
Composer Franz
Schubert
Wassup close friends with poet
Friends by shober
Did he refer to themselves
Together as
Horsey
Although it was edited out of many Bible there's one
One paragraph in the Book of Genesis about Adam and his friend Jeff
St Augustine
He did so much for the world
Do people believe the answer is B and therefore I will throw myself on their mercy and blame them if I lose again
What are the most famous bromances of course
Search between Bert and Ernie on Sesame Street
They're not gay they don't exist from the waist down
You can still make it work
Ernie for at least a decade what was it a
Said they were a hotdog and hamburger brought to life by a wizard
Be that they were intended
To be a Sly party when they were invented
Of Richard Nixon
Spiro Agnew
With secret
Sleep debt
I got dark really fast
I'm going to give you a hand
The hit is that this
Rumor with must
Prevalent in the 90
Maybe it is
You can tell because
He's not that he would never lie
Started in Paris in the 1920s
Joyce and Hemingway would often go to bars together
And they're nice
Usually ended when which of these happened
Joyce would get really drunk
Start spouting gibberish
In Hemingway would write it down eventually creating
Finnegans Wake
Be joyful get really drunk
Pick fights
And then hide behind Hemingway screening deal with it Hemingway
Deal with it
And then eventually try to pick up Joyce
Zane come on so what if you have a mustache Joyce is a woman's name
The first one I don't think anyway share
Elimination
You're right that's what it was
How did Stacey Abrams
This little contest
Chihuahua
The author of minority leader more information can be
Fair fight
Auction.com
We all get greasy fingers that are listener Limerick challenge
NPR
Score Fitness podcast
In the following math
I said come from fidelity
As a Fidelity wealth
You get a dedicated advisor
Here to help growing
Protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the in
Impact of Pacs
And make it clear recommendation
Games for your full Financial
Learn more at
Fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage service
Is LLC
Everyday
Laura Bates
Women around the world
Big and small
It just made me
It down a notch
Why is this normal
Watch the website
Thousands of women
Even some mad
Started to share
Ideas around gender and
Empower
Rmb
WBEZ Chicago
The NPR news quiz I'm Bill Kurtis
We're playing this week
And Peter Gross
Here again is your house
At the Johnny Mercer theater
Georgia
Thank you girl
Bill has an affair
Give us a call at 1 for the late wait wait
That one 888-924-8924
Right now
Panels more questions for you from the weeks
There's a new app called WeChat
You're what two people in increments
Single men
Cell phone
No
Okay let's see
Your body
Your child
Is it the people who are using if you want to rent this from you
Different number of men
I need to recharge
Your charger
No it's a car battery
It's your house
That's what it is
What about this after you dial it up you usually function and you can find
Somewhere near you a stranger
Who sings that it's totally cool to let
Stranger to them hang out in their apartment for 30 minutes
For The Travelers
It's a cost-effective and convenient way to pop a new clean home destroy their bath
Vicodin
All right
Brexit
Driverless cars already on the road
In some cities
And everything
Make everything better
A new study has issued a warning
Saying
The traffic will get much worse with automated vehicles
Because with their advanced
Artificial intelligence they will refuse to do what
Parallel park
Moana
Humans do this to we've been known to drive around block
Box for like 20 minutes
To look for a parking space
You're right I'm going to give it tomorrow so he can feel it
Pacifically what they want
You have to park
Because it can't go anywhere that you would
Automated cars can just
Just keep trying
White page
$35 for some Downtown parking lot just dropped me off I go into the little house for 10
You get to do what you need to do when you're making your appointment your ceiling their Vicodin whatever
Just kill more pedestrians and then you mean
You going to eat
It's a game where you have to listen for the Run
If you like to play on air call leave a message in one AAA wait wait
You can click the contact us link on our website wait wait. Npr.org
Where you can find out about attending our weekly live shows back at the Chase Bank Auditorium in Chicago
If you want to play along right now just ask your Alexa or Google home to
Open the week weight quiz
And you can play our new interactive game on your smart speaker
Play it again and again to prove to your friends and family
How smart you are
And you might even win
High you are
Hey this is Danielle from Atlanta Georgia
It just great I don't know the answer this is there a rivalry between Atlanta and Savannah
The two largest cities of
Everything else in between is Alabama
3 News related to the last word or phrase missing for
You can fill in that last word or phrase correctly and just
When you're ready to play
Yeah alright let's
Do it for the pride of Georgia
Here's your first limo
Patrick's Day
Butter crack
Just
Tip the bag to your lip
And Wallah
It's a one-handed
That's right very good this is the problem
The needed to be solved your face for deep into a bag of Cheetos
Can you get a text
Can you try to reply the next thing you know your thousand-dollar smartphone is so greasy
It gets actor
Well good news a snack company in Japan has created a product
Cold one hand
The chips
Instead of grabbing a handful of chips with your fingers
With one hand
You just tip a cup
Filled with hundreds of chips
Can you try
Drink them down
Best way to make sure you end up with neither any grease spots or
Human dignity
It's called a Pringles can
Tomorrow
I can float gently into your mouth
Presumably large enough so you're not just
Eating dust
A bag of soda
The chips with soda
I was about to say that's disgusting but you know that's going to be on sale next week
Here is your neck
Limerick
With each little step
I will feel that I win
When I lose
My Footwear will show when the
Calories go
I am tracking my way
With my
Google you are cold is it on a new pair of smart
Shoes
It will tell you if you need to lose weight taking the place of the technology we've all been using
Dumb
Smart
Bisect each other
Here is
Your final
They'll give you some Wonder care
But with
You soon Terrace under there
My hard-working breathe
Need frequency
Really
It is time to replace all my
Yeah apparently this came as a shock to me
Keeping your underwear around of one day at Naturally biodegrades is not
Sanitary idea I thought it was
We should be throwing them out every 6 months
Right when you started getting to know each other
This advice by the way
Is from Good Housekeeping
Pocket of big brief
Or as big reflex to be called extra large briefs
Greed should only
View
Entirely
From the
If you got hit by a bus
Play You'll Never Walk again
Bill how did Danielle do
Play
Support for this podcast
And the following math
Message come from fidelity
As a Fidelity wealth
You get a dedicated advisor
There to help grow and Brew
Protect your well
Find ways to
To minimize the
Impact impact
And make it clear recommendation
Pins for your full Financial
Learn more at
Fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage service
Is LLC
Hey it's
Gyros creator
How I built this in
We're returning to
San Francisco
Second how I built
The Summit
Supported by
Express
He join there by founders
Companies like Instagram
Slack
Bliss JetBlue
Many many more
Visit Summit
Npr.org
Morass
To see you there
This message
It comes from NPR spot
Capital One
Is reimagining Bank
By offering account
With no fees or minimum
That can be open from anywhere
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Now watch my final game lightning fill in the blank each of our players who have 60 seconds to answer fill-in-the-blank questions
Sushi Cat
2 points
All our panelists
Hive
All right
Well I'm just going to arbitrarily choose who goes
Peter Europe
On Wednesday the house intelligence committee announced
Plan to investigate whether blank has any leverage over president
Any foreign
I said they're looking to rush you but they also set other phone
I said that Isis is likely to regain territory
Following Trump's decision to withdraw troops
From Black
Siri
This week's New Mexico through most of her State's national guard troops from the Black
Southern border on Wednesday the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau
To roll back obama-era restrictions on
The blanket
Payday loan
Florida
What cars in the parking lot said he was only doing it because he blank
Because
He hated cars
Because he was really angry that he could not remember where he had Park
This week it was revealed that some apps for the blank maybe recording users
Screens without their knowledge
But this week it was confirmed that the blanks would go on without a hose
Write hoping to do with Martin manage the gray squirrel population
In the UK a business in London is blinking
They are
No they are serving customers
Gray squirrel lasagna
Gray squirrel considered an invasive species
The restaurant in London called native
Great squirrel lasagna
Where is it more commonly no no thanks I'll just have linguine
Ready lasagna
On Tuesday President Trump announce
He would hold a second
Consignment with blank in Vietnam
In late February
Kim Jong-un
Right on Thursday the German government announced plans to the Limit
The data-gathering abilities of social media sites blank
Facebook
This week in humanitarian
Convoy bound
Blanquil
Blocked by the country's military
Venezuela on Thursday
Cortez on Bill details of the so-called blank
Green New Deal
Spotify Spotify
With just 16 points scored Sunday's game between the Patriots and Rams
For the lowest scoring blank and history
Super Bowl Valentine's Day
Announce the new special offering
Free
On February 14th
Create free
No they will be offering
One free cookie
4 single
That's sad Valentine's Day Without a significant other
Get a free cookie
A cookie a shame for any single person who's looking to lessen the sting of Valentine's Day with
Something sweet
Even better news
Couples who can get
2 free cookies by splitting up and going to two different eye colors
Exactly how did Roxanne do
Well the game continues she got six right 12
Like
So how many then
Well leaking Tire
Winit at 7
On Monday Federal prosecutors in New York
Set subpoenas
To President Trump's plan
Pulling apart
Subpoenas
Precedence
The Inaugural Committee to keep troops in Iraq
Activity in blank
Monitoring
Integrity
Nancy Pelosi said that she would back any deal on blank that bipartisan negotiators
Might reach
Security the CEO of Amazon Jeff Bezos
Am I the publisher of blank and attempted to Blackmail
Why are we Whispering because audio is a
An intimate medium discovered
Can we call warning
Was put out for black
Power Wheels Barbie
Wednesday
Did the spiciest year
No
Cryptocurrency investors in Canada are unable to withdraw 140 million dollars
Of investment because the investment companies president blank
Because the investment companies
Is that he lost that he misplaced
That he died before he told anyone his password
It's always even sadder when you can't send the family flowers because all your money is tied up in Bitcoin
Did somebody didn't take the time to write down their password on a sticky note like a normal person and put it on the monitor
Expected the demand funeral will be attended by several thousand people
All of whom will consult his grieving mother
And ask her what her maiden name is
Did Mama do well enough to win
So this year's Super Bowl halftime show
Well they seem to be a disappointment so
We're going to ask her panelist in just a minute
Predict what will be
Next year
Super Bowl
Aptoide
Show
NPR and WBEZ
Chicago
Urgent haircut Productions
Overlord
And Rachel klepper rweb Google is Beth Novey
BJ leiderman
Identify money is Peter Quinn
Robert Newhouse
Wait wait
Tell me
Is Mike Danforth now pain
Super Bowl halftime show
Broadway is Patti LuPone
I guess she's great and I'd love to hear her yell at 80000 drunk
In football fans to put away their cell phone
In an effort to boost rating the halftime show will be the Barenaked Ladies
Forgot the band actual Barenaked Ladies
Gwen Stacy Abrams does a response to the first half
Happens will ask you about it
Conway
Savannah
Is NPR