Support for this podcast
In the following message
Come from Duckhorn
Napa California
Duckhorn Vineyards has been
Crafting classic Napa Valley Wine
Ants with a sense of place
For more than 40 years
Learn more
Or at Duckhorn. Com
NPR
Hey it's Peter so you're listening to the show
Oh and you're
Probably shouting on answers
Whispering
Public space
If you're listening to
Did the show on the sly while
Go on a date
Wouldn't it be great if
Did shout out answers
Respond
Well if you have a smart speaker
It'll happen
Just ask your Alexa or Google home
How to open the weight weight quiz
And Bill and I will.
Appear as if
If by Magic
Asking questions for you to answer and
Bill will even give you your
Score at the end
If you really good
When the altar
The voice of your choice
On your voicemail
The next best thing to having
Please come over to your house
Even better cuz
We tend to eat a lot
Try the weight weight quiz
On your smart speaker
From NPR WBEZ
Izzy Chicago this year
Wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news
What means
What's yours
Or salad
Vinaigrette
And here is your host
Ramen downtown
Chicago
Thank you. We have a
A wonderful show for today
Because we are going to fix
Washington
By which I mean one of the greats
Comments about wash
Is that it's nothing like the West
When
We want the real washing
Have Snappy dialogue
Thesaurus
Speech is the perfect comebacks
And then
We want it to be cancer
Aaron Sorkin himself the creator of The West Wing in the social.
The Newsroom will come on to punch up
Reality itself
But first we are interested in your Snappy dialogue so give us a call
The number is 10008 wait wait
That's one 88924
8 night
Now that's welcome our first listener
Intestine how you around
Elizabeth Stephens Gloucester Massachusetts
What are you doing I actually Anthony starting a greenhouse management position
Do the specialty
Crop
I actually don't although I do really enjoy growing potatoes potatoes are a lot of fun
I thought Matt Damon do that
Well Welcome to our show Elizabeth let me introduce you to our panel first outfits co-host
Of the new podcast OnePlus One
It'll be performing her solo show approval junkie at the alliance theater in Atlanta April 4th
Faith
Sailing
Humorous presenting
Storytellers on a mission with host Jordan Carlos + Tara Clancy and Adam Burke March 30th
Appalachia's
Theater in Brattleboro Vermont
It's Tom bodett
Elizabeth
Any comedians performing in Charlotte North Carolina tonight
Theater on April 13th
Do the hosts of the podcast nobody listen
Santa Paula Poundstone
I gave it away it's Paula Poundstone
Corsicana play who's Bill this time it's how we start over
Every show Bill Curtis
Is going to be just me quotation
Snooze
Your job as you know
Correctly identify just two of them do that you Enterprise
The voice of anyone you may like from our show on
On your voicemail
Your first quote is a man talking
Two Republican allies of
Time response
Ansible for yourself
Because I did the same thing that you're doing now for 10 years
Who's the guy warning Republican members of Congress don't be like me
Well I'd probably have to go with Michael Cohen on this would have to go with Michael Cohen
Don't go too far with him he's heading
Go to jail
The
Completely discredited liar absolutely should not be
He trusted spent a whole day in Capitol Hill saying a bunch of things
We all completely believe
President Trump's former lawyer told the country about how the president was quoted a racist
A con man and the
The cheat
Which Michael Cohen just wouldn't stand for which is why he
He quit after.
10 years
Is going to jail in the first 10 years is tradition
The iron bar in
Now the Republicans just went
After him they yelled at him and called him a liar and a fraud the even and this I tell you America is
True
They held up a big
Big poster with his
Face
And the words
Liar Liar
Pants on fire
They did that
And as embarrassing as that was it was better than the earlier draft
Whoever smelt it dealt it
Also he would hold up that sign
And it said I'm rubber you're
Yeah
Crunch numbers
And there is a water bottle in front of Michael
Cohen
On-screen with is
Which with its label
Facing America
$650,000
Free advertising
Anybody's going to go out there so I'm going to buy some Dasani the favorite brand of Michael Cohen
I really like this could be monetized
There could be some labels on our body
I never even noticed a water bottle nor did I noticed
The label and
Yaki
Did look hydrate
So if I knew what water company it was I might as well gravitate
I love learning that that Trump said that the
The person with the worst judgement in the world
3 with something
Finding out
In that way what your parents
Said about you
Alright Elizabeth your next quote how happy it's the president of the United States
When we walked away
It was a very
Mr. Trump surprised Everybody by walking away in a friendly fashion
Course from a deal
With whom
I guess that would have to be Kim Jong-un the dictator of North Korea
So when the president for his second Summit
With Kim Jeong Hoon
Because he was so eager to
To claim credit for
Who knew what he would do
North Korea Mike
Get there sanctions lifted they might
Continue with a nuclear program and also be given article
Amazing thing happened the president just walked away
He walked away no deal it's amazing for a couple of reasons first because he walked instead of using a golf cart
It must have been painful with his bones
After his first meeting
With Kim and it's kind of sad
On a human level because after his
First meeting
With Kim last
Do the president said they were quote in love
True
But Kim had to know the
Trump it always does
Meet the first time
Magical
Venture Spark
Fly Yuma
Plans together
Then the next thing you know Michael Cohen is writing you a check
So you'll go away
Here Elizabeth is your last
Level artist
And guess we did a good job
That was Lady Gaga
Talking about the
As she says artist
Officially intimate Loma
But she had with Bradley Cooper
Where
It must be the Oscars
Oscar ceremony are usually forgotten as quickly as
This year's best picture will be but
People will remember forever where they were when they said oh my God their lips
Bradley Cooper and Lady Gaga did their big song
Shallow fry
From A Star is Born
Live on stage
It was so steamy everybody was wondering not so much will they won't they
But did they just
Do it live on TV
Yeah she had
A mark
From The Pianist
Strings on her face
I think that happened during the commercial
We wanted
Was for them to
Cut
Bradley
Girlfriend
Trite
Oscar's is a night of drama that's
I want to see
Screen
Do you think
Don't you think
I don't know I mean these people are
Actors
They're paid lots of money to
Pretend to feel things
That they do not
Don't people know that
I mean another news Tom Cruise has not asked
Actually killed people
Well except for those guys who tried to leave
But they knew what they signed up for
To say like if I was watch
Touching my
Wife
Read up on
On stage with Bradley Cooper
Like that
I would think
I am
So screwed
But I was amazed that
After she won her Oscar
Gear for best average
Gentle song Lady Gaga
Backstage and she
She said something to the effect of
This was for this
Boyfriend
We told her that she never ever be famous
And here we go see my music everywhere
I'm famous
And so there
And all I can think of is like what kind of relationship did she have
What kind of boyfriend is that
Hey honey do you want to order in tonight and by the way you'll never be fat
Heated fight
Like she said
You know when you pee outside the toilet
Clean it up and he said you'll never be friends
A weak moment we do those things
Lady Gaga has been famous since she's been about
Middle School boyfriend not over it for sure
Will you give me the will you give me the answer to number 20
Stupid
Bill how did Elizabeth doing our quiz
She got them all right thank you so much
Right now panel it is time for you to answer
Some questions about the
Paula this week a man in Texas
Is proposed a novel idea for
For seniors who are considering moving into a retirement home
He calculated
Save a lot of money
By doing what instead
Can I have a hint we have to ask
The Bellboy to bring up all of you
The specifically a Holiday Inn
Pizza Holiday Inn Surrey although any
Budget Motel would do Days Inn
Days numbered
Motel 6 Feet Under
End of days in
What do start
Ready set up
They got rooms I got a little dining area you know that
I got cleaning staff
Don't have to make any changes we'll just change that door hanger to
To do not disturb or recessive
Yeah the only difference between this and the nursing home is how quickly they find your body
Oh yeah that would kill
Coming up our panel is there in a pickle in her Bluff The Listener game calling AAA way to play will be back in a minute with more weight
Wait wait don't tell me
From NPR
Support for this podcast and
The following message
It's come from Stanford Children's Health
What are the scariest things
Mom look
Because the next words are usual
Billy can fly
Or Joey riding the dog
Or a crayon stuck in Valerie's nose
Here's something you might
Want to hear
With over 20 pediatric offices
Stanford pediatric
Russians are all over the
The Bay Area
Not just
Westin Palo Alto
Find a Stanford PDF
At Stanford children
Yes. Org
We often think of a lot
Is something random
Unpredictable
But what if we actually have more control than we think we do
A lot of it has to do with taking time
It's getting out of your comfort zone it's
Paying attention to things that other people don't pay attention
Ideas
Lucky
On the TED Radio Hour
NPR
WBEZ Chicago this is
Is wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
Im Bill Kurtis
We're playing this week with Paula Poundstone
Unfaithful
Chicago Pizza
Hey Google
Right now it's time for the wait wait don't tell me Bluff The Listener game call 1aaa wait wait
2-player games on
Hi you are on wait wait don't tell me
Hi my name is Amy I'm calling from Suwanee Georgia
Suwanee Georgia okay that's great and what you do there
I'm an emergency room nurse
Did you find being an ER for an ER nurse
Is helpful in mothering
Leah and the separate times
Poor children have to walk around with
Scrapes and bruises all the time
Appendicitis for 3 days before I finally sentence for the year you know
Really
Really cuz you like they're Come on Mommy have a stomach ache and you like that scene where it says that somebody impaled
Yeah absolutely you're fine you're fine
Amy welcome to the show you're going to play a game in which you must try to tell truth from fix
Bill what is Amy's topic
To the rescue problems can only be solved by a
Most problems alcohol fix
But not all
This week about a story of someone
Figuratively in a pickle
I'm getting out of it
With an actual
Pickle
IPay listening to tell you about it picked the one that's telling the truth in it when the waiter of you
Your choice on your voice
Are you ready to play
Apple like all right
First let
Hear from
Paula pounds
After years
Being the last Ryder over the
The finish line
Horse ironic
Name the last word
Alexander Graham Bell
Was on the verge of never riding left
Word again
When he stopped by to visit
Is it the horse what
Eating a pickle
Discovered that the horse had next
Scream reaction
He mounted the horse
Took him out to the track
And show them the
Last word took off like
Rocket
We've been winning ever since
Said four valves
We get on that inside rail
Squeeze the reins in my right hand
Kind of pickle in my left
Then I reach my pickle hand in front of his muzzle and it's
Equine Magic
To date no other horse has reacted
Do pickles away last word does
Undaunted
In training session
Desperate jockey
He's way better Vegetable that can sync up
His face looking for a birthstone
Speed
Eggplants tubers
Brussel sprouts
So far nothing
Some horses actually back up when they say
Jesse Cale
The secret to a horse's speed is a pickle that's
Impala your
Next bit of pickle
GoPros come from
It's a lie
Estelle Schmidt
Of hegel's dorf buxom
Always
Bird flying
Nothing
Could get her on a plane
Except her love for her great-grand
And father
Muller
When Marcel died all of hagel's door
Because for as long as anyone
Could remember
He had provided the village
Honest Deathbed
He summoned
24 year old
Michelle and ask her to fly
I took Gibraltar
Scatter his ashes
Then he bequeathed
Per his MO
According to Legend
Can this pickle marinades in a brine made with
Water
In which Jesus washed his feet
Since Marcel's death
Estelle has carried this
Pickle contest
She Strokes it by day
And returns it to its cloudy water by night
Turi brine
She knew
The only way she could fly to Gibraltar
Was if she were clutching Marcel's pic
Burlap
But passengers on the small plane rioted over its noxious smell so the Lux Air flight attendant wrenched
The green stink bomb from a stealth hands and put it in the aircraft mini fridge
Even after being reunited with a pickle upon Landing Estelle sue the airline for mental anguish
This week the European Court of
Justice hurt
The case
After witnessing a selfie
Attachment to what one just
Just called the holy Cube
The five judges ruled unanimously in her favor legally naming it and emotional
Support pickle
Estelle funneled her grateful tears in
Into the jar of juice.
Declaring I owner of this condition
With the salt of my
An emotional support
Pickle
Your last day of someone hurting for a gherkin
Comes from Tom bodett
When a purse Australia man
Went through great fall of his own manager
It's the glue is on but to a 6ft wooden bar counter Last Friday Night
He did what any of us
Baidu
He sat there
Then he posted his predicament on Reddit which has saved so many lives
So I'm kind of sitting here with a slab jar attached to my butt cheeks watching Battlestar
Galactica and waiting for the emerge
Play services
To return my call
After realizing the only chemicals xi'an capable of divorcing his
Speaks from his board were tucked away in the garage
Stupid or he couldn't fit through
He turned back to his Reddit
Feed to find 300 comments
One more useless than the next
Until one jumped out at him
OMG what a pickle
Yes Christ
Sticky but man
He read somewhere on the Google that the vinegar in pickle
Will do so I'll break down and epoxybond and he had a jar of gherkins within his reach
One episode of Battlestar Galactica later the first pickle but posted that he was free
Saturday morning the man reported feeling a little tenderness but not much pain
If anything my butt feels thoroughly exfoliator
All right
Here are your choices
Amy from Paula Poundstone
The horse that would only run faster could win race
This has been only with the incentive of a pickle
Faith of woman makes
Emotional Journey
Only with the help
Of an emotion
Support
And from Tomball that a man who had accidentally
Superglued his own butt
To a countertop
Escaping by using the miracle of
Pickle juice
Which of these is
The real story
The pickle coming to the rescue
I am going to have
Have to go with that pickle.
Alright then your choice is
Tom story about the man in Lost
Australia hoop
Glued his butt
Who is countertop
Define. The correct answer we spoke to a reporter covering the real story
Tumblr context clue himself
Any jobs around here
Naked butt
That was a reporter from the bell tower times
Is in Perth Australia talking about
Is Home Improvement project gone wrong
You were right Indiana
The true story of the heroic uses of pickle
Congratulations boyfriend
Choose telling your child
Just calm down it's nothing
Congratulations and thanks so much for play
Thank you
And now the game or an important person does something completely trivial
It's called not mine
So have you ever said to a friend you can't handle the truth
Or maybe $1000000 is in
Cool you know what's cool a billion dollars
Well if you have first of all start thinking of your own things
But secondly you were quoting Aaron Sorkin
An author
Have a Few Good Men Creator Sports night
The West Wing
The Newsroom
And now the author of
Kill a Mockingbird
On Broadway Aaron Sorkin
Welcome to wait wait don't tell
Thank you thank you
It's great to be with you you know I came in in the middle and the very first thing I heard
Was exfoliated his butt with a pickle
At my first question is I know
So many people
Who are
Especially fans of The West Wing
Roden crater
Who are so disappointed in real life
Because the people in real life
Especially in politics are nowhere
Nearly as smart
Interesting and mostly articulate as they are on your
Shows so my first question is are you just as disappointed as they are
Sure
I go a step further I mean I'd say that most
5th graders are smarter than
You did one of the things that I was amazed that given your
Your talent
Productivity
The awards you won
Is I always assumed that you grew up wanting to be a writer
Because you're sober
Frankly good at it but that's not the case
When I was in high school I thought I was going to be an actor
Cool plays in community theater and then I went to college and studied acting and it wasn't until
Play the day after I graduated from college that I
For the first time wrote for pleasure
Android dialog
And I felt a confidence that I've never felt with acting and I was a pretty cocky actor
Really
What did you write
That day
I started writing A Few Good Men
Wow yeah
At my older sister
Debbie
I had just graduated from Law School
And she went into the Navy Judge Advocate General's Corps jag corps and she
Told me a story about this trip she was about to take the Guantanamo Bay and it became the inspiration for
A Few Good Men
I moved to New York after college and I got a job
Bartending in Broadway theaters
And I wrote
A Few Good Men on cocktail napkins during the first active look house or false
I love that was a bartender in theaters if you work during the walking and you working during intermission but your
You're not doing anything during the First Act
And there was an unlimited supply of cocktail Mac
I just envisioning like this cocktail napkin and on it is
You can't handle when you turn it over the truth
So of course known for your
For your dialogue does it
Just come into your brain
You quickly write it down like you hear the back
Enforced or is it something that you actually have to
Conjure on a good day I do but I don't have many
Good day
Pacing around and trying to get into an argument with myself
And if I can get a good one going then it starts going down on paper
Make out loud
You do this
Why was doing The West Wing
A messenger came to my office
The package from the president of NBC with a headset
That you're supposed to pair to your car phone
And there was a note from the president of NBC saying I was next to you at a red light today
Please wear this anytime you're driving your car you look like a madman
Because you were just like shouting
An imaginary people in your car shouting at CJ and Bartlett and Sam everybody's
Fighting in my car
It looks like I'm being mean to somebody
Hey Aaron one of the questions on
Wait wait don't tell me was about you
You want time
There was a story
Where you were working on dialogue I guess it you
Your house
Accidentally hit your
Head on my God my nose riding
Holding a is writing an early episode of The Newsroom and I got up in the middle of the night cuz
Play I had an idea just just for a
Sort of a classic
Comic beat where Jeff Daniels was going to lunch at one of the staffers and two staffers were going to hold them back in one of these
And
I was really excited about it was going well
And I happen to be kind of acting into the mirror
And I lunch. Jeff Daniels would but there was no one there to hold me back
So I can smash right into the bathroom
Go to the emergency room and if so what did you tell them
I called that friend that you have that you can call it midnight when you broken your nose
And she came over and she took one look at me and said you would have to go to the emergency room
And I said okay but I think it's pretty good well
Aaron Sorkin it is an honor action
Play for us to talk to you but we've asked you to play a game
We're calling
Welcome
To the hot wings
You
Created The West Wing so we can ask you about hot wings
Be delicious American
Staple food stuff
Grown on the great Wing the farm
Signs of the American Midwest
Enterprise one of our listeners
The voice of anyone they might like from our show
Bill who is Aaron Sorkin playing
John Chaplet of St Petersburg Florida. All right you ready to play
Wings
Must have been the at the center of Summer
Surprising
Legal battle
Including which of these a
A Man convicted of assault with a deadly weapon was released
After judge has agreed a hot wing was not deadly
B a lot
Colorado that
Declared from henceforth chicken wings will be
Considered
Sandwiches
Orsythia lawsuit
Between two restaurants in El Paso Texas
Over who owned the Derrick
Common name
The lord of the Wings
The first to A & B are certainly the funniest but the answers got to be sick
I'm somewhat disappointed
The last one funny
The real one was be actually
Colorado there's a kind of
Cancel liquor unless they also have sandwiches
And so on
Certain bars my problem
Chicken wings are sandwiches in Colorado
Next question
Chicken wing aficionados will go to Great Lengths
Show their love
For the food as in which of these
Hey a jewelry company in Los Angeles
Self Earrings made of
Discarded chicken wing
Be a man in Tennessee created the first ever Wing Pit
Just like a ball pit
You jump in a bounce of the chicken wing
Orsi
A Virginia man use two cups of wing sauce
To go out in wink face last Halloween
Okay
I'm going to say
USIC
It was in fact a you know you should know that you're living a life course somebody would make
Jewelry out of even as I was saying it
Yes definitely somebody's making earrings out of chicken wings
Okay
I'm going to give
The third one everything I've got all right
This is sort of like
The position cone was in
What do you mean
Die has been cast
But he's going to try one more time
This is brutal
In 2014 Philadelphia
22nd annual buffalo wing
Eating contest was one
By 125 lb Molly Schuyler
Cheetah record
Chattering
363 wings
Yay for her
But the question is
How did she say
Celebrate
Irwin
The following day did
GTA
Drive to the Des Moines Blue Ribbon Bacon Festival in need 5 lb of bacon in 3 minutes
Be celebrate with a free meal at IHOP
She won by eating 59 pancakes in one sitting
Orsi
To go to Jethro's BBQ in Iowa and 8th
Sandwich with pork tenderloin chicken tenders
White cheddar sauce
Fried cheese curds Applewood smoked bacon
Add a pound of french fries in just
15 minute
Which of those did she do
I honestly have no idea how someone who only weighs
125 lb / 300
Chicken wing
You know what I'm going to say that she had to turn it back on
You're right but she also did the other two she is all three
Bill how did Aaron Sorkin doing our quiz and you can't handle the truth
Aaron Sorkin is the creator of The West Wing Sports night and The Newsroom his plate
To Kill a Mocking
Kingbird is on Broadway now
DC it if you have the Opera
Aaron Sorkin an absolute
In just a minute there always after me Lucky Charms
To join us on the air
From NPR
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Duckhorn Vineyards Napa Calif
Founded by Dan
Ann-Margret.
Duckhorn Vineyard
Yours has been crafting classic wine
Games with a sense of
Place for more than 40 years
With seven Estate Vineyards located throughout the map of
The winery produces vintage
Cabernet Sauvignon
Sauvignon blanc and Chardonnay
All showcasing the diversity of wine.
Learn more at Duckhorn. Com
NPR
In the truck. The news moves faster than ever and the NPR politics podcast
Is there to keep you informed
Every time there's a major political story we get our best
Corresponding
Kids together to sort through the noise
Did your politics podcast what you need to know
Right after it
From NPR
And WBEZ Chicago
The NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Kurtis we are playing this week with Tom bodett
Faith Sealy and Paula Poundstone and here again is your host at the
Chase Bank in downtown Chicago Peter
Thank you Bill thanks everybody Bill knows rhyme wasn't built
Open a day and I listen to a limerick a challenge game if you'd like to play give us a call at 1 AAA wait wait
That's 18892
To 48924
Rhino panel
Some more question
Things for you from the
Faith everybody worries about their food being raised humanely
Lisa one company want
Want you to know
Their chickens were given organic food
Plenty of room to
Exercise and eat
Which of the numbers given
Something like Amazon
No I'm saying
Something
For their well-being
Something that helps
Do you understand how well their
I'd like a Fitbit
Yeah
A company in China has developed the high-tech.
Gps-enabled tracking device
That can counter chicken
Steps
So you know how active it was in its lifetime before you eat it
It also lets you read the chickens resume
Do the dragon goddess MFA
Apparently a hundred thousand chickens have already been outfitted with this technology
Traxxit steps
What did he eat
More sexy and
Empowered and their own bodies
We're on social media
Oh yeah
Sing some chickens have been cheating though
They've been cutting their own heads off so they could run around and get their step there
This answers
The question why did
Chicken cross the road
Time we had movies based on Transformers and Legos and Barbies well MGM has announced their developing what toy
Into a movie
Silly Putty would be a
Silly movie
Although I'm sure it's been done
Well I'll give you a hint if they do this correctly in order to
To see the movie Life
Ashley Holt have to hold one up and
Just press a button
Oh my God
What is that called the
You know I under the snow clothes
Remember the View-Master it's
The toys like a little
Can you put in the little thing with
The pictures and you look at him
3D
The plot has yet to be revealed
Will probably still not be revealed when the movie is
Is over
But they're really
Fade away
At movie making
The script is not included the phrase today The View
Become java master
To make movies about
We're really excited for the horror film operation
How much a bunch of children do surgery to remove all of a man's bones while he's still awake
I love that game
Everybody like that game
Crunch Fitness
Store over there
Really cuz you want it
When I did find
Get it
I'm not
Koch brothers
And
You know it's not good for
Kid with any kind of anxiety
The same principle
Don't let something bad happen
Phone without the buzzer going off
All the way your mom catches
Smoking
Don't do anything
To buy for my kids alive
Games that we had when I was going up with the ones that I
I covered it anyway
And I got four
My kids what time the game perfect
Yeah which is where you
Is shapes inside a box
The kids messed it up and they
This is whenever where you're supposed
How to say dumbass
Yeah they don't do that anymore
Dumbass
And then you have to say that you're not my child that's why
I like a bad parenting board game
Call dumbass I think I would fly off the shelves
Such Great Heights
I never raised you to be like that
Get the wrong kid from the hospital
Corner of the game that's the timeout corner
Just being there for the whole game cuz you forgot about them
You can land on the teachers going to call your mother
Whatever your score is it's not enough
Coming up
It's lightning fill in the blank the first is the game where you have to listen for the rhyme if you like to play on their call and leave a message
AAA wait wait that's 18892
Or click the contact us link on our website wait wait. Npr.org
So you can find out about attending are we
Weekly live shows right here at the Chase Bank Auditorium in Chicago
You can also check out
New weight
Weight quiz
On Alexa and Google home you could even win the Ulta
Comprise
The voice of your choice on your voicemail just say
Open the wait wait
Quiz
Hi
You are on wait wait don't tell me
Hi this is Sandra Parnell from Madison Wisconsin
Chicago
I'm a sous chef
Nothing
Nnm do you work at some kind of rest
I know I actually work for the grease Bicycle Company in Waterloo Wisconsin
Really
Wait a minute
Sous chef for the bike place
Yeah we serve great healthy tasty food to all of the employees we are in public
Country
So it's great for them to not have to go look for a picture
To work out
Quite a few do actually even in this weather
No
Los Angeles welcome to the show Bill Kurtis is going to read for you 3 News related limericks
The last word of phrase missing
For me GIF you can fill in that last word or phrase correctly into
You'll be awake ready to play
Brittany
Here is
Your first
Limerick
Thumbs up
We know these
They give letters and numbers a slowly
Squeeze
The police are annoyed
Bike up
Poop tears of joy
My vanity plate has
Emojis
Queensland Australia be on the lookout for new emoji
Vanity license
Gone are the days when you only have letters and numbers
Reveal Your nurse
Naked throwing a laughing
Face heart eyes smiley face and egg play
I guess you can't afford a Hummer
I just put an eggplant
People understand
I mean I guess it's nice that people can do that
You know spice up your life
Play but it's going to make police chase
This is really confusing
Attention all units we look out for a Honda Civic plate number 5 piece thumbs up  hamburger bagel bagel
Here is
You're next
Limerick
With blue diamond
Green Clover and
Cheer
Your hangover helper is here
How are ipas post
A sweet marshmallow to roast
It's our magical Lucky Charms
Blackbeard
If you're the type of person who hears beers
Think Saturday morning
Have we have we had a product for you with an IPA made with
Pounds of Lucky Charms marshmallows
In a new recipe the craft Brewers are calling the end of our industry forever and
Magically revolting
India Pale Ale
Kind of beer
It's like a genre
I don't like
Like beer
But it seems that count chalk
Killa other Frankenberry beer
Ibotta tricks
That would be
For kids
Here is your last limerick
Not a brunch
But a home for my erato
My shoes are like food
Status Panos
This holds
Are almost
Like some golden brown toast
And the top
Is like mashed
I'm not getting it
Millennials like this
Mast on top of toast
Avocado
Apparently you can now buy avocado toast
Shoes
What they cost $140 a pair
The equivalent of two orders of avocado
They're not really avocado toast
What's their souls are brown like
Like Brad
Tennis shoes no laces
These are wonderful green
Oh no now they're brown
The shoes are going to be
Quite the head because who doesn't seafood and think feet
You know what a good food would be to make him do a
Make a new issue of footlong hot dog
Always the right size
So how did Sandra do in Ark
With a
Wow
Thank you so much
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Duckhorn Vineyards Napa Calif
Founded by Dan and Margaret duck
19/7
Duckhorn Vineyard
Yours has been crafting classic wine
Games with a sense of
Place for more than 40
With seven Estate Vineyards located throughout the novel
The winery produces vintage Merlot
Cabernet Sauvignon
Sauvignon blanc and Chardonnay
All showcasing the diversity of wine can
Learn more at Duckhorn. Com
NPR
Now that's why I finally game lightning fill in the blank each of our players will have 60 Seconds
The answer as many fillings
My questions
Is Hershey candies correct answer net worth
Spell can you give us
The scores of each have two top three Tom ye all right
We flipped a coin faces elected to go first so Faith Hill in the blank on Wednesday
The Florida bar said they were investigating a congressman
Tweet threatening black
Michael Cohen on Sunday the White House announced
Is delaying a planned increase
The blanks on
Chinese Goods
Tara flight this week the house passed a bill calling
Expanded the blanks
For gun buyers
Background check
Write this week video streaming site of Lankenau
They were disabling
The comment section on Millions
Names of videos
Write the farthest known object in outer space known as far out
Was replaced this week by an even
Further object
Known as blank
Further out
So close
Farfara
On Thursday the directory
The CDC said the center hadn't been aggressive
Think about a missing
Information about blacks
This week Robert Kraft the owner of the blank was charged
Soliciting prostitute
Yes he was
A thief in Pennsylvania trying to make a getaway was apprehended after he tried to outrun black
Police dogs
No after he tried to outrun a running club
We'll see if we just stole a laptop and cell phone run
Ran right
Passed a local lunch time running club member
Kyle Cassidy
Said they were quote really impressed by his speed
They gave Chase eventually cornering the thief long enough
For police to arrest him he did manage to break out a week later
But
Fortunately for police his
Escape Route 2
Checking right past a local javelin
Open clock
Bill how did facetune
At 6 right
Headsets 12
I call you up next fill in the blank on Tuesday the house passed
The resolution
To block President Trump
Blank
Emergency
The Attorney General of Israel announced he would indict blank
Can corruption charge
Netanyahu this week Mark Harris dropped out of the contested convention
National election in
In blank white on Monday vice president
Tencent
The new set of sank
Venezuelan
Blank material to commemorate the baseball player Manny machado's record-breaking contract
For the San Diego Padres
Imma memorabilia cup
Is selling blank
A bobblehead
No scraps of
Of the tablecloth
She signed the contract oto
Wow
Following an investigation officer in Florida has been since
Suspended after you let two suspects
Blank
After Electra
Two suspects
Getaway know after he let them make out in the back
The suspects were arrested in shoplift
Started making out immediately after being placed
Squad car
Which is actually got it
Considering they were both
Instead of stopping them and this is completely
The true the officer put on Barry White can't get enough of your love baby
And let them enjoy themselves the cop has been suspended
Because action
Clearly violate the ban on
Xen unusual punishment
How did Paula do in Ark
She got five rights 10 more point
Close
Irwin
62 wins
Here we go Tom this is for the game
Fill in the blank on Thursday the prime minister
Pakistan
10:30 would release
Is a pilot from blank
Who shot down India
On Monday a former campaign staffer for blank filed a lawsuit
Claiming that he
He kissed her without consent
Call Bate bate o no for Donald Trump home this week Britain's Labour party said it would back the new referendum en Blanc
Brexit
On Tuesday a federal judge ruled that only
Requiring men
To sign up
For the blank was on
Show the draft
Right
After spray painting
Racial slurs
The wall in Washington
Penn State a group of Vandals
Return to the Sea
Same spot in blank
Cleaned it off now they spray-painted sorry
Underneath the slurs
This week the Department of Justice said it wouldn't challenge the approval of AT&T merger with blank
Oh that was it was that Time Warner is being sued after
3 coins into a blank for good luck
2 Coins into a public toilet
Pilots for the regional Airline
Pilot for the regional Airline said they found some loose change through the
The plane's engine in Manassa passenger
News about it one of them
Flip a coin there for good luck
Their line is now suing him
$15,000
The man says just to make sure he has good luck he'll throw a horseshoe at the judge during the
The trial for write 8 more points total
11th at memes
Bizarre weather this week
They just a minute we'll ask our panelists
Predict what will be the next
Surprised at next
Ceremony
Thanks once again for Farmhouse Tavern for feeding us and
And I got to say
Wait wait don't tell me so productive NPR WBEZ
Chicago
Association of the Urgent haircut Productions doug berman
Phillip Lim
Is there public address announcer
Warehouse managers Tyler Green Assisted by Simon
Suntran
Are interns or Alex Smith Cohen and Rachel
Klepper I webguru is Beth no
BJ leiderman composer Steve our program is produced by Jennifer Mills miles dornbos and Lily
We recognized. Win as president of Venice
Does wailer
Technical wrestler tomorrow to White her business and off managers call another eye production coordinators Robert Newhouse
Easy enchilada executive producer wait wait don't tell me it's Michael
Danforth
Now panel
Enterprise at next year's off
Lady Gaga will come on stage
Squat on top of a piano and give birth to baby Gaga Cooper
Tom bodett
To the amazement and Delight of my long-suffering wife I will sit
And watch it
Paula Poundstone
It will continue to be postless
But next year the Academy Awards will also have no
Insight recipients
Amazon will deliver their Awards
Some of that happens panel will ask you about it on wait wait
Wait don't tell me
This
Is NPR