This message comes from
NPR sponsor
Fitbit with a Father's Day gift from fit
Your dad will get used.
It's about his body and how
Visit fitbit.com
Slash weight
To save up to $30
Stores with free next-day shipping
From June 2nd
The June 15
NPR WBEZ Chicago
Wait wait don't tell me the NPR news quiz
Hey everybody
Gather in front of me and prepare to salute
Because it's
The triumph
Of the bill
I'm Bill Kurtis
Then here is your host is he Chase Bank Auditorium in Chicago
Chucky
Agree on these days it seems to be superheroes
They're everywhere
The movie theaters on TV
But surprisingly rare in real life
That's because supersuit
What's are extremely restricting
Where it matters
All superhero show today although not all heroes wear capes for example
Black panther didn't
And that was because oscar-winning costume designer Ruth e Carter decided he
Shouldn't we spoke to Ms Carter rice
After he won her Oscar in February
And she was still pretty excited about it
First of all
Congratulations on the Oscar win
Have you gotten over to you still
Still sort of a buzz you walk around
Holding it all day
But you were nominated
So were you
Surprised when you finally won or you were like it
My turn
It's been 21 years since
The last night
Really
Yeah I was like man
Going to take 21
1 years each time I better grab
You're the First costume designer weave Everett
I just wanted to go over
Some basic stuff
So you're the costume designer
Do you ever do you ever have to deal with like
Factory girls like you
I guess you deal with that cuz
He goes on
Level
Sometimes
They say you know I can't wear that color
Are you now or
But because we're discovering a character we are both
Kind of contributing to the conversation
Right just say yes
So maybe your
Character has a bigger butt
To look at the fun stuff
Which is a movie like black
Comicbookmovie
Fictional
Fantastical science book
Country
You are the most qualified person
Ask about something
That I've always thought
The great problem
Is that unlike in comic books
People wearing
Superhero suits
In real life
Essentially
Look dumb
Yeah because they don't realize it's their whole process
To make a mess
You just don't go to
The store get some
Spandex
So it up
So how do you make it so like the Black Panther when he's in his
Superhero suit run
Doesn't look dumb
Yeah well we do a month
That help
What do you mean well we take
Vacuform
I'm kind of mannequin
New version of
Chadwick Bose
Real body
Forum
And we add
Clay to his muscles and
Reform
Superhero kinder
Are you telling me that that I'm telling you the secrets not all Chadwick Boseman out of there
How much Muscle Milk
You Drake you're never going to be a
All you got to have
Play muscle amazing
Superhero suit that Chadwick Boseman is wearing in the movie
Just like those padded things
Are the kids having Halloween at the muscles I like built-in
Do this at home kids
It's not exaggerated as you might fake
It's just a little you know because we don't want to you know
How to really make
Can Banks put in the other
Marshalls
Famous line in one of the early Spiderman movie
Movies where he refers to a Scotsman says a little binding
In the crotch is that true of yours
Kira Kosarin
I know this is zipporah
So you are now an oscar-winning
Costume design
Youfit of leading costumes
Designer many many
For many many years
Does that put some pressure on you
How to dress when you got
Public oh no I've always been the answer
Fashion I think that's what makes me
Kind of
That I'm not trying to
Please
Provemyself
It's not in how I look it's how I dress other people
Come on really Halloween I would expect if I
You came to my Halloween
Puget Sound
I would expect that you would walk in with like
Vcast
Yeah that's why I don't go to Halloween
Now you're done getting accolades
I feel like you don't have to like force your way to get accolades at Halloween
Can you get that you get like people cuz
Does Hollywood people of money
I want to be an amazing Halloween costume
Who is a joke
You know that I'm going to do a Halloween
Aftermath Drive design the black
But I'm here to tell you I'm not going to do it
Well Ruth Carter what a pleasure to talk to you we've invited you here to play a game we're calling
Hate Monday
You designed Black Panther
They're so we decided to ask you about
The R&B
That is
Garfield
Inexplicably beloved comic strip character
Is correctly you want a prize one of my letters
The voice of anyone they might
Bill who is Ruth Carter playing for
Brent and Angie in Indianapolis they are withers
The wait wait quiz available now and yours
Smart speaker
You ready to play music first question
Garfield was invented by his
Creator Jim Davis
It was back in 19
In 78 what inspired mosto
Today was to create the
The character a
His own cat
Beloved
Tubby tabby
Name task
Be his brother who
Lose fat lazy love lasagna and occasionally
Cleaned himself by lick
Or see a desire to create
Quote a good marketable character
One quote that would make him a lot of money
Tubby tabby
No
It was see he wanted
How to make a lot of money he needed some research and at the time
These dogs in the
But no cat
Any figured they were like
Created it
To be popular
It 2004
Garfield the Movie
Does panda
By critics of course
The Garfield Show
Voice by legendary actor
Bill Murray
Wind
Agree
To play God
Was it a
The Producers agreed
To pay him with a lifetime
Supply of Italian beef
Sandwiches from
Favorite Chicago
Being mistakenly thought that the movie
Screenwriter Joel Cohen
Was Joel Cohen
The Coen brothers
Or see he was still angry that he wasn't allowed to provide a voice
Do the Gopher
Oh I'm going to try
B
Your
Right round
He thought that he was doing a movie that was written by one of
The Coen brothers and he says he didn't realize his mistake until he was in the studio recording his lines and all of them
We're terrible
Alright last question if you get this right you win
And here we go
Not every Garfield strip has been
Embraced by his
Is fan such a
Choose which of these
Aa2007
Jodi Burns in America
Can flag while screaming death
To America
Be a 1997 stripper
How much John's girlfriend Liz Katz
What is him wearing
Her underwear
Or see a series of scripts
What's the week of Halloween 1989 written as a horror comic
Garfield faces
Is his greatest
Spherex
Substantial lonely
Verizon Wireless
See I'm going to try
You can try to be
Jon's girlfriend Liz
Wearing her underwear
Mercy the existential horror
That's what it was
If you've never seen these
He's very real,
Maxim 1989 and highly recommend you look it up
Garfield supposed to be
Funny and chubby and angry
He wakes up in and
Happy House
Where no one is left
And he spends all week
Pelican beak
Cuz he's facing his great
Loneliness
Bill how did Ruth
Chris Carter doing AR quiz
Two out of three
3 which is a win
All uphill it's like Oscar wait wait don't tell me
Nobel
Ruthie Carter won the Oscar for costume design for Black Panther
Museum exhibits
Traveling the world
Ruth e Carter
Thank you so much for joining us away with McDonald's
I should say that
Not everybody is on board with this
New golden age of superheroes
Is Paula Poundstone
Talking about a reason
Superhero
Blockbuster
I told the second Avenger
I don't remember if I saw the first
Avengers and I hated it I thought I was
Stupid
It was a lot of surprised that wasn't on the poster
Yeah
It was just dumb
It was a stupid
There's no
It's very it's very you don't blow up in fighting
Those are the technical terms
Title
It's not a reflective film
There's not no it's not it's not example of Bergman film is not a lot of
There's not a time where in the where there's just like a
Nature scene and you're watching
Sing a bird flutter
So I don't understand
How even the app
Discern go down and I have not seen the movie myself but this is
True that
In a guy to like winter good bathroom break
Avengers endgame one of them is a scene
We're Bruce Banner
AKA The Hawk
He's eating lunch
Arrow guy is going in retrieving his arrows
Stupid Arrow guy even is a
Superhero like everybody else
And I can
Do they have like what on Earth would make anybody think the
Did that was
It doesn't he ever successful does he ever like
Shooting
In the spirit of the movie
It's not real
When we get back and then you can stop a speeding wide receiver
A woman who has the power to make anything funny
That's coming up in a minute on wait wait don't tell me
From NPR
Support for NPR in the following message
Message comes from Panera Bread here with your breakfast wake up call
At Panera breakfast to go no longer means
The saddle
Try their new maple glazed bacon scrambled egg and cheese breakfast wrap
And parrot with a new Madagascar vanilla cold brew
All made 100% clean and ready to go with rapid pick-up at the push of a button
Breakfast is the most important meal of the day and that means compromising is not an option
Panera
Food as it should be
I'm Jesse thorn
Timothy Simons played Jonah Ryan
On the show known for its insults
Has anybody
Got more of them than Jonah is the cruelty register
Sardar show would be an hour and
15 minutes long cuz every scene would be like X
Excuse me you can't speak to me that way this week
Unfold
From maximumfun.org
At NPR
Forum NPR
The naughty Bez Chicago
This is wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Kurtis
Listen here is your host at the Chase Bank Auditorium in Chicago
Peter Sagal
Thank you girl f*** everybody text me your jumping on the superhero
Bandwagon but you know not all superheroes
Disappearing movies or where amazing
Costumes or
Shoot Flames from
From their eyes
That's why we like to expand the definition
The superhero to other
Really interest
Also because Chris Evans
Blocks our number
For example
Football Hall of Famer Charles
Tomen Nota
Peanut
What's called the greatest defensive back ever to play the game
But even after
You're playing into Super Bowls had a problem believing that our cheering
Krowd
Was legit
See y'all so I do a lot of radio
They have like a
So you're you work or selling the great quarterbacks
You actually went to the Superbowl with the Bears not a lot of
And say that sadly
All I can say
I got to ask cuz you know the Super Bowls has big
Event we all watch what is it like
How to be a player involved
I mean you're preparing for a football game and I understand that's a pretty hard to think
To do did all the
Distractions of Lake media week in the week leading up to that get in the
I was just pretty damn born
I wish I could show you
You say the same
Question over and over
You know how I talk about Peyton Manning
You know I thought about Peyton Manning for 5 days
Board 5
Getting ready to eat some glue
I love it
Among other extraordinary
Who played against Tom Brady and you've intercepted that I think twice in one game
Looks like a legend about greatest football
Quarterback has ever lived it yet mean
Did you guys find that like intimidating or like
Inspiring
I'm going to go out and pick that off
Imma take option number 2 imma go on
I think he is
The greatest if not the greatest
Play the game play I don't think anyone
I mean there's a second-year player that when I was damn your Beetle so
Don't think players are in
We heard that you played a game when your wife
Extremely
She might have gone into labor at any moment
Yasso
Fifth wheels 2012
My wife was pregnant I didn't interview
McLaren phone
Laurence Holmes ask me the question hey what you going to do if your wife goes into labor before the game
Blossom well I'm missing a game I'm going to go see my daughter be born
About how they're not family man
They're their there they're just athletes but I felt like I was
Call the tax because I made
The smart choice
The Family Choice
The more important choice to go be with my family and watch the 4th of my daughter
So after they literally asked
To the game
My wife now we go home
Changes and everything gets her bags
And we go straight to the hospital at like
Midnight
Can I have my daughter literally
Next day I have a daughter that night
Well that's awesome
Come On Eileen
Talk to you but we have asked you to play a game this time we're calling
Now that's what I call a notch
Offensive line
You know a lot about defense you were very good at that but what do you know about offensive line that is
Things people said or did that offended people
We're going to ask you about three offensive lines get to
2 questions right you want a price one of our listeners
Bill who is Charles Tillman playing
Diane Schultz
Austin Texas Lauren you ready to do this
Alright big also if she on the phone
Is presumably listening at home
Subaru
Charles during the early days of space flight
TV station
Kitchens with Austin often broadcast the action
Knots live and NASA was worried that
What are there astronauts in
Particular
Would swear
When the whole world was watching him
In order to prevent that NASA did
What
Hey they told him that for safety sake
He had to wear
Gag
So he wouldn't quote inhale
Space
Be through a careful psyops campaign they convinced them that the most offencive
Just where he could possibly say
Was gadzooks
Or see they hypnotize them
So he would
Um
Anytime
He wanted
To swear
Amazon
Optionc you're right that's what they did wow
They've never said
What astronaut they did it too but it is absolutely true
That astronaut
Conrad
While he was on the moon I'm going to get polymer
Weirdly hum
All the time so we have our suspicions
BBC Radio goes to Great Lengths to keep its listeners
Safe from offensive
Content
They even
Put a decade-long ban on what
Song because they thought it was offensive
Was it a Madonna's Like a Virgin
B ice
Estes cop killer
Orsi's Bobby Pickett the Monster Mash
I'm going to have to
To go with my guy
AIC
You'd think
It was the
They said this is back in the sixties the song came out they did not plan for 10 years cuz they thought it was quote
Dota 2
Morbid
It was a graveyard smash
Last question
Even professional wrestling is not immune to worrying about getting a fence
At one time the world championship wrestling organization
How to make
What sweeping change a
Each wrestler was required to say I'm just kidding
Before trash-talking their opponent
B instead of
Heels
Wrestling villain
Those were to be called
Sensible Flats
Corsi they were told to stop calling
Chairs guitars and ladders brought into
Did the ring to hit people
Foreign object
And instead call them
Objects
Basalt Co
You're all right that's what happened
Got tommen doing AR quiz
We just saw why the peanut is
Chicago
Congratulations
Give me bedtime
I'll be there
Quarterback for the Chicago Bears
Payton Man of the Year award
Which is presented by Nature
Should wide information about his charity
The Charles Tillman Cornerstone Foundation can be found online
Charles Peanut Tillman thanks
You so much for joining us and wait wait don't tell me
Aidy Bryant with the comedian improviser
Here in Chicago
That you went out to New York City auditions
Super Saturday Night Live
We became a star in that show and then she went on to be the lead in the new Hulu series
Shrill we experienced a Supernatural charm
When she joined us on the stage in March
Skip this year
And Peter asked her
When she knew
She had powers
Is it true to say like a lot of very funny
People you've always
Even funny you were like last
Amy Ike I was always
Who is trying to
Funny joke
Yeah, you like as an improv
When you're gone
Yeah yeah
Teen Improv
You know you are
I asked
What was the name of
Improv group
In Phoenix
Oh my
I've been in so many dumb
Improv teams I can't eat
Droppin science
Family crest
Best virgin daiquiri what else
Irene IU
Used to I used to
Sitting with Carl and the Passions
Sometimes I mean I've done my time
Did you come to Chicago
Specifically to
Do sketch comedy
Yeah yeah I knew about
City in Ohio and I wanted to
Yeah and you did which is kind of amazing
Right I mean cuz a lot of people coming
Chicago Detroit
My messages
You're actually alright I need this camera
How to say that
When I
My hotel room
Today
You were right
Well that's
On the cover of Michigan Avenue
Well I always wait for men in their hotel room I think that's cool in a me-too era
What was it
A lot of times we hear about the
Who came out of Chicago
And go to Saturday Night Live
When you were just like me
Mina working the
Oh my gosh you're standing in the corner of Michigan and Randolph
Somebody named Anna
So you went off to New York like a lot of
Chicago comedian
Things do and you understand
Super Saturday Night Live did Oprah
What you got
Which is rarer
People talk about this Saturday Night Live audition
The character
Did you do that
I did yeah they told us you know 5 minutes
Couple original
Couple impress
Can you tell us what
I did Adele
And I did Ethel Merman with
Which is very top
I'm not going to ask you
I said
This is Ethel Merman on the T
Show my dog
8 what and then I sort of
Screamed in an Ethel Merman voice
Like my dog ate what
Was what got me to Saturday night
I understand you recently got married
That's very
I hope you didn't make the mistake of marrying another
Yeah I did
Yeah how'd that work out
It's going real bad I don't know how it's going to go
I'm so sorry
Kind of
Have in that like
Proposed in our home which I
It's sort of sad
Private anime
How do you say
You know more likely
People like get free
Does Tijuana
Jump back
So I kind of came home from work
And open the door and then just like a
True bat out of hell like
From the back of our bedroom he came around like
Really yeah but it would
Yeah
Surprising you were flustered you wouldn't say no
No I think he knew that
He had a very short
Time between me entering the door and walking even 10 steps
Before
My bra and anything would come off
And he wanted to catch me fully dressed
Indignify
That's very thoughtful
The most romantic thing in the world
Well
Aidy Bryant we're delighted to have you here but we have asked
You here today
To play a game
That this time
We are calling
80 Bryant
Meet the 80s
Brian
You're too young to remember
But way back when we had a decade
Call the 80s
And it was filled with wondrous and amazing people
Oliver
Renamed
Brian
Brittany asked you three questions about 80s Bryan
At to write you want a prize winner list
Okay
Awake can I ask
On the spot
You give at least
One of the
Voice aloud okay alright
What's the weather
I love that
Chucky who is Aidy Bryant playing
Dan Martin of Boston
Nora
Lucifer
First question
Composer and producer Brian
You know
Produced some of the biggest hits of the 1980s
Which of these was a manga
Popular
Works
Hey the main title theme
Name for Police Academy 8
Bribe me with
The spoon
Be the startup sound for Windows 95
Or the music and lyrics
For a Hoover vacuum jingle
See
Unigo for the Hoover vacuum
My girl
That can't be right
The cat be
Baby
I had to bring out the Ethel Merman that cuz I know
Cheap Brian Eno
Was paid $30,000 to write
Baby sound
That the Windows 95
I started
When you turned it off
Alright next question
Brian De Palma
Director of the 1980s
Scarface
Was forced by the MPAA to make several cuts
The film down
X rating to get an R rating
After doing so what did he do
Hey a giant Mound
Be he put the deleted scenes back in
Because he figured no one would notice
Where see he sang the vocals in a Hoover vacuum tank
Ime 9
I'm realizing I don't like
Okay a
I'm going to say it cuz I think it's the most
Eat at a time
Actually be he just put all the cutscenes back in the movie
Last question
Did you get this right you in
The last question is about Brian Johnson he was the lead
Lead singer of ACD
DC where the great bands
Songs of the 1980s
On the same day he auditioned
To be the lead singer of ACDC
On a day in 1980
Just a few hours earlier what was he doing
Hey
He was doing AC repair at
C comics
He was doing Dirty deeds and he was doing them dirt
Cheap or see he was singing the vocals in a Hoover vacuum jingle
I mean
If it's not
See I got it
The Moon
Then yes it was in fact him
Literally the day he successfully audition to be the lead singer of AC DC Brian Johnson went to
Commercial Studio
Any record
Is this jingle
For Hoover vacuum
There you go
I know
Saturday Night Live audition
Can you delete stickers made CDC doing a vacuum.
Yeah
Chucky how did Aidy Bryant doing
Making her a winner
Switch on Hulu you can also see her on Saturday Night Live
Aidy Bryant thank you so much
Charming and funny and a politician
Who doesn't need any help
That's in a minute on wait wait don't tell me
From NPR
Support for this podcast and the following message comes from
Choiceology
Unoriginal podcast front row
Schwab
Remember that project that you were sure you would finish over the weekend but was
Still hanging over your head come Monday morning
Why does that happen so often
The latest episode of choice ology explores why it's so difficult to forecast projects
Tell the story of the most expensive structure
Everbilt
Download it
And subscribe
Schwab.com
Or wherever
You listen
Mitch McCoy
Has become a chain
But back in the day
Scott's
Support from groups
Labor union
Get down
Things I've done in my life
So you thought about it
His face
Mitch McConnell
New series from embedded
Chicago
Wait wait don't tell me the NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Kurtis and here is your host
Chase Bank Auditorium in
Chicago
Thank you Bill for this week I'm talking about superheroes
All the TV shows about superheroes the first and greatest
Was The West Wing
I mean real people do not talk and act like that right
Writer Aaron Sorkin who created The West Wing
As well as
Sports tonight
Ben the Newsroom
Not to mention a whole bunch of movies about smart people
Join us earlier this year
Unconfessed
He didn't
Start Alex wanting to be a writer
When I was in high school I thought I was going to be an actor
Cool plays in community theater and then I went to college and studied acting and it wasn't until
Really the day after I graduated from college
That I
For the first time rope for pleasure
Pembroke dialogue
And I felt a confidence that I've never felt with acting and I was a pretty cocky actor
Really
What did you write
That day
I started writing A Few Good Men
Wow yeah my older sister
Debbie
I had just graduated from Law School
And she went into the Navy Judge Advocate General's Corps Jag Corps
And she
He told me a story about this trip she was about to take the Guantanamo Bay
And if you can't be inspiration for A Few Good Men
I moved to New York after college and I got a job
Bartending in Broadway theaters
And I wrote
A Few Good Men on cocktail napkins during the first active look how's your fault
If you work during the walk-in any working during intermission but you're not doing anything during the First Act
And there was an unlimited supply of cocktail napkins
I just envisioning like this cocktail napkin and on it is
You can't handle when you turn it over
The truth
So of course no
For your for your dialogue does it just
Coming to your brain
Can you quickly write it down like you hear the back and forth
Or is it something that you actually have to
Conjure on a good day I do but I don't have many
Icon start
Pacing around and trying to get into an argument with myself
And if I can get a good one going
Then it starts going down on paper
Make out loud
Do you do this
What are the questions on
Wait wait don't tell me was about you one time
There was just
Where you were working on dialogue I guess it
To your house
And then you
Accidentally hit your
Head on my God broke my nose riding
Is writing an early episode of The Newsroom
And I got up in the middle of the night cuz I had an idea just just for a sort of a classic
Comic beat where Jeff Daniels was going to lunch at one of the staffers and two staffers were going to hold him back in one of these
I was really excited about it was going well
And I happen to be kind of acting into the mirror
And I lunch. Jeff Daniels would but there was no one there to hold me back
So I can smash right into the bathroom
Did you go to the emergency emergency room and if so what did you tell them
I called that friend that you have that you can call it midnight when you broken your nose right
And she came over and she took one look at me and said you would have to go to the emergency room
And I said okay but I think it's pretty good well
Aaron Sorkin it is an honor
Actually
For us to talk
You but we've asked you to play a game we're calling
Welcome
To the hot wings
You
Same play
Created The West Wing
Be delicious American
Staple food stuff
Grown on the great Wing the farmers of the American Midwest
The voice of anyone they might like from our show Bill who is Aaron Sorkin playing for
John chaplain of St Petersburg
Florida all right you ready to play St Petersburg here we go here we go
Wings have been the at the center
Have some surprising legal battles
Including which of these a
A Man convicted of assault with a deadly weapon was released
After judge has agreed a hot wing was not deadly
Be alot in Colorado that the
Cleared from hence
Fourth chicken wings
Be considered
Sandwiches
Or see a lawsuit
Into restaurants in El Paso Texas over who owned their common name
The Lord
Of the Wind
The first to A & B are certainly the funniest but the answers got to be sick
I'm somewhat disappointed
The last one funny
But because the real one was be actually
Colorado there's a law that certain kind of bars
Can't sell liquor unless they also have
Sandwiches
And so on
Chicken wings are sandwiches
In Colorado
Next bus
Chicken wing aficionados will go to Great Lengths
Show their love
For the food as in which of these
Hey a jewelry company in Los Angeles
Self Earrings made of discarded chicken wing bone
Be a man in Tennessee created the first ever Wing Pit
Just like a ball pit
You jump in and bouncing
The chicken wings
Orsi
A Virginia man used
2 cups of wing sauce to go out in wink face
Last Halloween
Okay
I'm going to say
USIC
It wasn't fact
Hey you know you
Of course somebody would make
Jewelry I don't care you don't even as I was saying it
Okay I'm going to give the third one everything I've got all right
What do you mean
Well that's it then you know the Giants been cashed but he's going to try one more time
This is brutal
In 2014 Philadelphia's 22nd annual buffalo wing eating contest was one
By 125 lb male
Skylar
Record shattering
Free wings
But the question is
How did she celebrate her win
The following day did she a
Drive to the Des Moines Blue Ribbon Bacon Festival in need 5 lb of bacon in 3 minutes
B
Celebrate with a free meal at IHOP with
What you want by eating 59 pancakes in one
Horsey
To go to Jethro's BBQ in Iowa and eat a sandwich
Pork tenderloin
Chicken tenders
White cheddar
Fried cheese curds Applewood smoked bacon
Add a pound of french fries in just
15 minutes
Which of those did she do
I honestly have no idea how someone who only weighs 125 lb
8 / 300
Chicken when it's pretty bizarre
You know what I mean
AAA that she ate a ton of bacon
You're right but she also did the other two
Bill how did Aaron Sorkin do an AR quiz
Aaron Sorkin is the creator of The West Wing
Sports night and The Newsroom his
Play to
Kill a Mockingbird
Is on Broadway now play
If you have the opportunity
Aaron Sorkin an absolute vacuum
Support for NPR in the following message
It comes from the NPR wine club
Discover hand-selected wines from award-winning Vineyards around the world
Learn the stories behind each one and enjoy a unique bottles inspired by your favorite NPR shows
But without having to leave the house
The clubs welcome offer includes a bottle of the delightful
All grapes
Considered Pinot Noir
If you're 21 years or older uncork the fun
Nprwineclub.org
Support also
Songs from better
Betterhelp offers license
Professional
Specialized
You such as depression stress
Anxiety and more
Connect with your professional
Counselor in a safe and private
Online
Event at your
Get help at your own time and your own
Schedule secure video or phones
Plus chat and text with your therapy
Visit betterhelp.
Slash weight
To learn more
And get 10% off
Your first month
Finally a woman who emerged from the national stage in 2018 and run for governor of Georgia
Some people say that Stacey Abrams is a superhero but it turns out she's just another nerd
Like us
We asked her about her first
Big National gig
Back in January
I want to find out about the process of giving the State of the Union response
Yes
So I don't have a job right now
Nn
How did you say to you how did you plan that you would not end up on that one
I drink a lot of water early
I used a
Logos
What's but very moisturizing lip
And I pray really hard
It's technically called a response
Did you
Think it all about what you anticipated
Trump might say so you could respond to it
I would put it this way
I have
Hurt him
Before
Send it would be some combination of
Demagoguery
Self aggrandizement
2 lines about
Something nice that he would
With three lines later overrule
Did you know that it would rhyme
That I meant and you know I feel sorry for whoever thought that with the right way
Way2go
Have we met before because
I went to theater
Camp with at least three girls named Stacey Abrams
It's entirely possible
2018 gubernatorial campaign here in Georgia
His evil is completely different career
Reading romance novels can you tell us about that
So I had to turn a bad breakup with
My boyfriend's
He is a chemical
Wonderful person we're friends
I read his dissertation when I was in law school
On
Microsatellite technology
And so I thought
You could appropriated increase
Chemical weapon that could be discovered by the floogals physicist
Imagination
So I decided
Write two things I wrote.
Very
Second Treatise on the operational dissonance of the unrelated business
Income tax exemption
Engagement which is a romantic
Suspense I kill a lot of people in the
How to survive in Fall in Love
Engagement my ex-boyfriend
Genesis of the story
Languages in prison for the rest of his Natural Life
Play a game
It's a fine bromance
So we've established if you are a successful writer of romance
What do you know about bromance
They're not speak its name but instead shuts it at frat parties
What are three questions about bromances get to write you when our price one of our listeners the voice of anyone
Giving response
Voicemail
Bill who is Stacey Abrams playing
Eli Arvin of
Pooler Georgia
Which of these is a real example of a historical
Hey Saint Augustine used to invite his best pal Olivia's to hang out in an actual cave with him in the mount
Twitchy called
Beloved man cave
Be in the early 1800s composer Franz Schubert
What's up close friends with poet
Did he refer to themselves
Together as
Horse eat all that was edited out of many Bible there's one paragraph in the Book of Genesis about Adam and his friend
St Augustine
He did so much for the world
Do people believe the answer is B and therefore I will throw myself on their mercy and blame them if I lose them
Again
What are the most famous bromances courses
Between Bert and Ernie on Sesame Street
Xian
From the waist down can still make it work
There's another rumor that Ernie for at least a decade what was it a
Said they were a hotdog and hamburger brought to life by a wizard
Be that they were intended to be a Sly party when they were invented
Of Richard Nixon and Spiro Agnew
See that was secretly dead
I got dark really fast
I'm going to give you a hand
The hit is that this rumor was must
Prevalent in the 90s
Conspiracy theory
Ernest Hemingway
Joyce started in Paris in the night
Of course
Joyce and Hemingway would often go to bars together
And their Knights usually ended when
Joyce would get really drunk start spouting gibberish
In Hemingway would write it down eventually created
Finnegans Wake
Be joyful
Pick fights
And then hide behind anyway screening
Show me where we got really drunk
And then eventually try to pick up Joyce
Then come on so what if you have a mustache
I don't think it's the first one I don't think anyway share
The last ones I think by the process
Illumination
You're right that's what it was
So
How did Stacey Abrams
Do in this little contest
Superheroes until we come back with the inevitable sequel
Avengers
Disassemble
Wait wait don't tell me so productive NPR WBEZ Chicago Association Productions
Overlord
Are public address announcer is
Paul Friedman
Arhaus managers Tyler
Our interns are Pnina Beatty and Leila Francis
What's our weather is better
BJ leiderman composer I see my program is produced by Jennifer Mills miles dorenbos
And Lillian can the robin to our Batman
Is Peter Gwyn technical directions to Mona White
I've been dozing off managers Colin Miller
Executive producer wait wait don't tell me is Michael
Big Bill Curtis a solar panel
And thanks to all
9 Peter Sagal and we will see you
Next week
This
Is NPR