From NPR and WBEZ
Chicago this is
Don't tell me the
PR news quiz
Is Pamplona
It's the running of the Bells
I'm Bill Kurtis
Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown
Chicago PD
Give a wonderful show if you today later on we're going to be talking to Tara Fletcher
24 year old
MIT grad who is now designing of The Rock
Get that will take us
Tomorrow
But first we're very proud of the eyes of the world were on Chicago.
When an
An actual
Alligator
Was found in a pond in a city park
British shows that Illinois is
Slowly becoming
The next
Florida
Now the process of fortification
Of course will not be complete
Until the drunk shirtless guy jumps into the alligator Pond and makes out
So while we are still stable enough to answer the call
Give us a call the number is 10008 wait wait that's 188-892-4890
Let's welcome our first listener contest and how you're on wait wait don't tell me
Hi Peter
A David Lewis
Just calling from
Massachusetts Arlington Mass I know it extremely well what do you do there
Well bye
AI
University
Be here in the area
And by night
Irate,
No really
I was just close what I was hoping hoping you would say by 9
I fight crime
Actually write a book called Kismet man of faith
It's about the first
Muslims
Superhero from night
How very cool and what kind of what kind of enemies does kismet
Fight fashion
Peter and the starcatcher
You two are panel first off a features writer for the style section of the washing
Austin post
Hello
Next it's a writer for divorce
HBO and co-host of the adulting a podcast from WNYC
Studios joining us again it's Jordan Carlos hello
If I know you're Canadian performing in Hyannis Massachusetts at the Cape Cod Melody tent on August
Headed Nashville Tennessee at the Tennessee Performing Arts Center
What's the temperature
Do the coils to the podcast nobody listens to Paula Poundstone cheese
Paula Poundstone
David welcome to the show you're going to play who's Bill this time
Bill Kurtis is going to refill
U3 quotation
Snooze
If you can correctly identify or explain two of them you'll win our prize any voice
Case for Marshall you might choose in your voicemail you ready to play
I am
All right
Fear first quote here's the presidents
Speaking at the White House
What's on Thursday
Today I'm here to say we're not
Backing
Doubt
He said that
As he was backing down
Undemanding a question about citizenship
On what
The 20
That's exactly right there
Chip on to the census
For about a year
But the Supreme Court said they would not allow it
Because the White House
Lied about the reasons
For the question a little
To openly
The White House really shouldn't have gone with the class
Because our girlfriend in Canada
Wants us to
Supreme Court ruling against him made from angry but he was already angry at the census
Make some answer that impossible question
How many children do you
It was amazing because the Supreme Court
Set will you can't
Can't do this
And the rest of the government even
Commerce
What's the name of the Commerce Secretary Wilbur Ross Asia known as
The Crypt Keeper
Even he was like
I'm standing there I thought wasn't
You killed
In Raiders of the Lost Ark
I know we can do it
Until probably the last week has been people trying to convince the
The president that you
You can't just ignore this
Supreme Court
He had plans though for the whole senses he wanted to redo the whole thing
Under race
The Trump census
Would have had only two options White
Loser
Can you only count your spouse if she's a 10
Well I'm sure that they probably had him take off the article and
Are you speaking about after
Americans usually refers to what
The blacks
So
He's got a backup plan is giving up the fight
Instead of the sentence he's just going to get Jeffrey Epstein to guess everyone's age
So we're going to go there and now we're going to quickly leave David
Here is your next quote
I deserve this
I deserve everything that was Megan Rapinoe she was swinging champagne from the bottle as she cell
Celebrated her team winning what
The world
Yes the Women's World Cup in soccer
In the final on Sunday it wasn't fair they were wearing their
Wooden shoes I mean really
And they came home to a ticker-tape parade in New York
Which is interesting because they don't have ticker tape anymore they use
Shredded and recycle paper that's good to know
All the time and effort you spend separating your paper recyclable
Is done so New Yorkers can throw it at people
The women were honored with an Espy award Thursday for best team and they think the US soccer Federation
For supporting them 70% of the way
Did you get the World Cup every game
I went to the
Parade
And what was great was
After
The flood passing everything dealership
About complaint
Chili went out like this is great and said it was over like well that was terrible
Well I mean in the end
It leaves a mess
Going to the White House the White House as of course became a thing
Megan Rapinoe the star of the team
Chia preemptively refused
To go to the White House
Cobra course
It doesn't matter they're not going to be invited
Iarrapino said they'd be happy to go to the House of Representatives or two
The Senate
Or basically to the
To The Waffle House basically it is more likely that the entire team
Will show up at your house
Then the White House
Alright it's a little late for the 4th of July but it's exciting for next year's BBQ
It's an innovation that will revolutionize barbecues and wiener roast all over the
We talked to men and women across the
The country who are heavy
I'm tired of dealing with
The messy
That was somebody talkin about revolutionising
What condiment can
Container
I stink
Mustard
No it's so close
The other one
Revolutionize independent bottles for years
We have wrestled with the way to get ketchup out of a bottle when
When it clearly does not want to come out
But the problem has been solved
No longer will you struggle to get your ketchup out of the bottle thanks to a newly designed
It's called the
Standard inverted pouch named after a popular kangaroo sex
Don't get distracted this is important
Basically
A bag
With a cat
On the bottom
It looks like a fat
Toothpaste
So you squeeze out the ketchup
Onto your ketchup brush
And scrub your fries at least 30 seconds per so short
Do that well is there been moving to this up for a while so toothpaste is change
Is the sort of 2
With the cap on the body
And now they're going to it for everything in fact not just catch up
Oliver foods will soon be served in bags
The new packages
Will be used for sour cream & Yogurt
And guacamole all of which will soon be
Squeeze with great force right under your
But this is kind of fun I mean a bladder of
Catch up I feel like
Can you pass the ketchup bladder
How did David do in Ark
They've got all
3 right
And good luck to Kismet
Scourge of fashion
Thank you Peter take care
Write a panel that it's time for you to answer
Answer some questions about this week's news
Roxanne it's not just factories in cows that are
You know contributing to
Greenhouse
Gas
There's a new culprit adding to CO2 emissions what is it
Systemic or a one-off
It's it's absolutely systemic and you've done it and you probably did it today and you'll probably do it again before
For you go to bed
You need a hint okay if you learned about this because your dad forwarded it from his girlfriend
You're only making things worse
Will you forward
Beforward
Email emails
Yes the answer is email apparently are helping to warm the Earth
Only if I will
Apparently if you think about it we will sit around send emails all day that's what we do for all
That's all we do I don't know how anything else gets done
And the electricity
Needed to
Send an email has
A carbon copy
Somebody has to generate electricity
Not
Cutting back on
That's a great idea
Make you not use email because as they point out everything
Has a carbon cost for example if you decide to mail a letter
That's got a carbon footprint like 10 times the size
And smoke signals are a hundred times worse than that
Just wondering
A flake
If you were raised
Eli cologne
Time ago native
If Americans if they were
Little girls who
Just wouldn't get away from the fire
Really Native American father says
The blanket that says I got to use the fire to send a smoke signal and his teenage daughter
To the her friend
Stupid dad
The fire right now
People
They probably never got off the wall
Yeah I love the fact that you've always wondered anything but
Bad cave art
Whenever we see Kmart
If you were whiskey
People
Coming up by panelist make it rain in our Bluff The Listener game call 1aaa quick way to play will be back in a minute with more
Don't tell me
From NPR
Support for this podcast and the following message comes from ZipRecruiter
Hiring used to be hard multi
Apple job site stacks of resumes but today
Hiring can be easy
And you only have to go to one place to get it done zipper
ZipRecruiter sends your job to offer 100 of the web
Leading job boards
Then ZipRecruiter scan
Thousands of resumes
Define people with the right
Experience and invite them to
Do your job
Stryper free
Ziprecruiter.com
Slash
Wait
What do all of these
Kamala Harris
Pete buttigieg
And Bernice a
They're all running for
And they all sat down with us
On the NPR
Olympia was going to drive me completely crazy
We are going out
On the trail with
As many of the Democratic presidential
Can I bring you in-depth in
Come Along by
Subscribing to
NPR politics
From NPR and WBEZ Chicago
NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Curtis Ware playing this week with Roxanne Roberts
Jordan Carlos
Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown Chicago
Peter said thank you girl right now right now
Wait wait don't tell me Bluff The Listener game call when AAA wait wait to play our game on the air
Hi you're on wait wait don't tell me
Hi this is Devon Hill in Corning New York from Corning New York
Home of Corning Glass
Yes I'm going to ask you a strange question
My father when he got out of graduate school many decades ago
Had to job offer
There's one in New Jersey what you took
And1 in Corning
Working for them
That he didn't take
Doughboys wondering
What would it have been like
To grow up in Corning New York
So it's great we're not far from the Finger Lakes we have that entire line culture here and the museum the great week
Compton Sheriff acacia
Yeah you had me going there for a while and then you made that pun
Welcome to our show Evan
You're going to play a game but you must try to tell truth from fiction
What is the topic bill
I've got a billion dollars in
Nothing to say
Spend it on
Billionaires have it hard in fact a recent new story indicated that many billionaires don't know what to do
With all of their money
This week we heard about him very very rich person coming up with a very clever way
Spend some of that money are panelist are going to tell you about it pick the one who's telling the truth
Any winner prize await waiter of your choice on your voice
Ready to play
My first letter from
Jordan Carlos
In New York City
Your friendly Neighbourhood billionaire will tell you
The struggle
Israel
They're Chic Downtown townhouses don't even come
Equip of driveways
Are we living in communist Russia
So what the master of the universe
Do when you can't park in front of your own my own
Exactly
Construction crew to build
You a big window that looks like a garage door
Make a cut in the curb so it looks like a driveway
Put up some no parking active driveway signs and bingo your own private parking space
It's called a Publix
He even hired servants to run out and warn anybody
He who dared park in front of
The completely fake driveway
West Village Davis
It should be noted belong not to the 1%
Depop
Say thanks to those enforcers many of their cars have been towed for parking in front of
Spell garage
Hey y'all
Had to pay a hundred
It's to get his car out of the tow pound after he parked and what is technically
Parking space
Mr11 complain
And the city got involved
New York Council
Speaker Corey Johnson
If it's curb cut is it illegal
Then it should be removed
Immediately
The City Rules against him the Mogul could face
A fine
Indian Mound
Have a portfolio shattering
$500
A billionaire living in Greenwich Village fake
A driveway so we can claim a piece of this
The street for his own your neck story of Richie Rich comes from Roxanne Roberts
Everyone in
Noah's Johan Lund
Doug Loves Pam
5 years
Citgo the billionaire
Hair developer
Open Door
State-of-the-art
Hamster
And uses
Does the adorable Road
Face mask
Lundberg unveiled his new pride and joy this
This month
Monster inspired
Warehouse on the
The coast of busan
The five million euros
What state is design
Underground the series
Giant pasta
Tubes modeled after the orange habitrails of his youth
That Lumber going to
This family use
But his favor
Favorite spot is the home gym and
10 meter ham
Two wheel that supplies
Half of the energy
We used in the Echo friend
Only mansion
Quote
You know how happy I am
Jews are when they run on their wheel
When I run
I am that happy
B2
A billionaire in Europe a hamster lover makes himself a Habitrail for
For humans
Your last row of a smart spender comes from polyp
Tulsa Oklahoma is now home
To the largest
Piggy bank in the world
It belongs to wealthy
Local financier Tommy Haber
The giant brass
Swine stand
1 story high
The installation
Is reflect
Did in the mirrored Laredo
Holdings Incorporated
Office building
Play became a selfie
Teemagnet went unveil
On July 4th
Already sounds
Of climbs a tall ladder
That leans against the pigs
Substantial belly
Deposit money in
SWAT
Who do those deposit
It's fat
One percenter Tommy hoeper
I've never seen anything like
Does Sheriff Austin Micah
This is the rich
Just got in town and people are literally
Throwing money at a
But there's already
$50,000
In there
Bowling balls and chicken wings in the oven
Street performers
The Clown
Only a few bucks
Sensor melted chocolate
This clown does nothing
Stupid some of them actually think my favorite is
Alright wait a minute just one more
Kevin Bacon said one
Disappointed looking visitor stepping away from the ladder
All right
Now they're so somewhere
Something interesting with
Kids money
Was it from Jordan Carlos the guy who won the townhouse in New York decides to
The fake a driveway just so we can keep the parking
Can space on the street for himself
From Roxanne Roberts a hamster living billionaire in Europe decides to build a Habitrail
For himself so we can run to the tubes
Run around on me
Wheel
Or from Paula Poundstone a billionaire who just puts an enormous piggy bank out
Front and let people give him even more money which of these is real story of creative use
Of excess
Funds
I'm going to go with
Jordan and the fake driveway
You never Jordan in the fake driveway the guy New York where we spoke to somebody who
He was intimately involved
In the real
Story
You made it look like a
The driveway but it's all an illusion
There's no actual driveway or garage
That was a 11 whose car was towed
When he parked in front of the face
Driveway
Congratulations Ebon you got it right thank you
Jordan that he's won our prize the voice of your choice on your
Voicemail congratulations well done
Thank you so much for 3
Thank you for playing bye-bye
And now the game where we invite very smart people on to play a game about dumb things
As we call it not my job
Jerry Fletcher grew up in Atlanta and wanted to be a rocket scientist most of us give that up
Once we learned it involves math
But she took to it infects you went to MIT
It and is now at 24 years old one of the lead engineer is building the rocket that hopefully will take some of us
Tamar's
He reflects you're welcome to wait wait don't tell me
Tell before we get to your current job did I get that
That right that you wanted to be a rocket scientist
From a very young age
Age of 11 I decided to be an heiress
Engineer
What inspired you to do that
So I actually had a program at my Elementary
School that introduce students to the fundamentals of aerospace engineering I know
That's ridiculous
The fourth grade I have
Wanting to be an aerospace engineer because of that
Wow Wow you went to MIT
And I thought that was pretty impressed
Nothing and we're told we are graduated with a 5.0 average
Yes it was very interesting
As far as we knew the scale goes up to 4
How did you manage that
So my parents always in
Encouragement
Research beyond what to expect
If you
So I just worked hard worked oh my God so many hours
Late late night
And I just made it happen
So even even frigid
You were you were like a nerd at MIT
Which is already nerd heaven
Keep forget balance I was still very involved in.
So many of the cultural group
Union also MIT University and also an actor
I can dance to
I tried to mix it up a little
Will you probably understood the Dynamics of the
The movement
The team like no you
You need a 25 degree angle at your knee
All of us has kids maybe droop airplanes and rocket ships I did that and maybe made paper airplane
Ranger models
But you're like you were not satisfied you wanted to make them out of like steel and make them
Apply exactly I'm one of them
For sure
Really
So you you were recruited by was a Boeing right out of readout
School rap you work for them before you can graduate
Tell us what your job is
So I'm a rocket
Structural engineer what that means is that I
Design various parts
Path of the rocket Annalise
And then I'm off
Manufacturing
Forget all of those parts
Together in
The rocket that you
Because your girl didn't make it to the curtain
Let me do that designing the rocket engines
Everybody told us that the rocket specifically that you're working on to design
Is the one that's going to go to Mars
Is that correct
To the Moon prayer that most recent charge
Hymn to the Moon
Take it like a pit stop
Before you hit Mars you go to the moon or what's going on there
Yes it will be
We creating a NASA Gateway in order to get ready for longer Mission such
Sing a habitat
Right they're going to do that first and then we'll go then we'll go on that then you're going to Mars
Personally care about Mars
I do I do I wanted to be very exciting does the point of it
Exploring the unknown
Are you guys going to go get the Rover back
Messes
You are a rocket science
That's literally
That is
The absolute cliche Forex
Extraordinarily smart
Like waiting in another phrase
It's not rocket science
So do you intimidate people when they find out what you do for a living
Well a little bit I guess by the title
But I assure them that
Many people can be
That's just not true
Very pretty to think
So and I want everybody be encouraged
Put know what your husband is an astrophysicist
That's right
Wait a minute
What's the Rockets
ACT test
Exactly it's so cringy
That seems to me
Did it might provide
Cause for tension
He tested and it blows up
What year at home going to be like
I have to be really careful at my desire
Because I know that my husband
It's a lot of pressure
It is a lot of pressure
Do you ever say them do you want more
Coffee and he says yes
Sinuca what's
2 capacity
We do have those moments when you actually like me like you do.
Nerd humor with each other
Kind of a nerd humor
24 are already designing of the rocket that's going to go to Mars which I imagine would be
The Pinnacle of other
So do you have
Goals are something you want to do before you're finished
I do I'm a course I have my pass
To explore the site of
Claimed as well do you want to design airplane
Any particular kind of airplanes
Oh I do love military aircraft that was the
Exact type of aircraft that I fell in love with
Really you were 11 year old girl and you love like fighter jets
Imagining you at the age of 11
Play playing with your friends and they're playing like with their dolls
And your jet comes in a
Pinstripe the Tea Party
Just take straight off right
Yes it has different
I just wanted to get something right
Well. Is a pleasure to talk to you and we are going to see if we can stump you because we have invited
You here to play a game we're calling
We must defeat
The month
Who stars
Shirtspace
Is your jam
But what do you know about the movie
Space Jam
Oh no
We're going to be three questions about that 1996 movie which starred Michael Jordan and Bugs Bunny
Sounds like 1 year old
That's not cool
If you get two questions right you win a prize one of our listeners Bill whose Tiara playing
Jonathan McRae of Bangor Maine ready to do this
I'm ready
Here is your first question
Space Jam with your huge success in 99
Its appeal is far-reaching
As proven by which of these
Say in an interview Neil Armstrong said
This movie is the greatest
Space thing ever done
Be there is a VHS copy of
The movie Space Jam enshrined in the North Korea International friendship Museum
You can pyongyang
4C Smuckers sold out of its Space Jam
Which was just a jar that's quote empty
He just like the vastness of space
I might need a little help here
I can sit the audience
Thinking
I know who's the movie
There's a VHS copy of that
Movie North Korea is weird
All right
Jones
Was the original creator of Looney Tunes
Bugs Bunny
He was invited to make a
Speech to the filmmakers when who were making Space Jam
What you use
What is characters
What hap
Open today
He challenged Michael Jordan to a game of one-on-one and lost 100 + 820
Be announced that Porky Pig had been
Curative is stutter and therefore would be speaking perfectly from now on
Or see he
Insulted the film with such Vigor he had to be escorted off the Warner Brothers lot
I'm going to go with
A genius
Hated the movie
Thought it disrespected his characters and made his feelings known and he had to be escorted off
Wow
LeBron James is producing a sequel
The Space Jam starring himself there's been one problem
With the production of what
Hey LeBron's co-star Kyrie Irving
Walked off the set
After refusing to believe the original Space Jam was
Not the documentary
Be the guy who voices Elmer Fudd has not forgiven LeBron for leaving Cleveland and keeps
Adding profane insults to all of his wives
Horsey other NBA stars have reportedly refused to join the cast cuz they know the movie will just be LeBron dunking on them
Let's go to see if you're right again yes
They don't want to be embarrassed until my LeBron or Bugs Bunny Bill how did
Tara Fletcher is a rocket scientist she's building the spaceship that'll get us to Mars you can find out more about her by searching for
4 rocket with the Fletchers on
Facebook
It just a minute bill says don't talk to me till I've had my PBR in The Listener Limerick challenge Co 18880
Wait to join us on the air
Will be back in a minute with more to wait wait don't tell me
Freemanpedia
Support for wait wait don't tell me and the following men
Message comes from
Rocket mortgage by Quicken Loans
Imagine how would feel
Pills to have an award-winning team of mortgage experts
Make the home button
Process smoother for you
The history of industry-leading online lending technology
Rocket mortgage is
Changing the game
Visit rocket mortgage.com
Wait
Equal Housing lender
Licensed in office
Fifty states MLS
Consumer access. Organizer
Rocket mortgage
My Quicken Loans
Push button
Get more
This is Terry Gross The Host
The fresh air
WHYY and NPR
We do long-form interview
With journalists breaking the big news stories
And with the authors filmmakers and musicians behind
The best in pop culture
So listen And subscribe
WBEZ Chicago
Don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
This what you're playing this week with George
Carlos
Roxanne Roberts
Paula Poundstone
And here again at your house to see Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown
Chicago
Peter Sagal thank you Bill
Bill pulls out his Running Iron for a chip shot in The Listener limerick
Challenge you like to play
Give us a call at 1 AAA wait wait that's why AAA
94 ate 9 to 4
All right panel some more questions for you from the week's news Roxanne according
Fast Company magazine the hottest name
Fast fashion
Isn't H&M or J.Crew these days it's what
I'm an idiot
Well
It's great if you need to pick up a Blazer and 200 roses
Mana 15 Taylor
You look for the summer had to Costco
If you need a valve beef
Chili for 399 also had to cop
The wholesalers a clothing department is booming no longer just purchased by customers
Who went overboard in the food court
Heated back up there
Stop
You don't have to buy the two rolls of toilet paper cuz when you have a hundred pairs of pants you don't need toilet paper
Pants on a roll
Most clothing chains are struggling because they're going to Amazon online shopping but Costco has seen a 9
Percent growth over the last few years in their clothing business
Maybe it's because Costco is just in-person Amazon or maybe because you
Can't find 90 cans of Vienna sausages at Nordstrom
Are there little
Sample pants
Call IHOP you been answer this question
Paula a lot of people using DNA testing service
Define long-lost relatives many of them turn out to be serial killers who knows
But who else is now using DNA to find their siblings cousins
I need a long long
In the road
I know but it isn't animal
Yes.
Very good
So stupid
Get out
Mutts
As you probably have been using DNA test for a while to check on their dogs
Greed and prove that is indeed and scientifically a very good dog
But now they're using the same technology to try to find the dogs relatives
Too many people are looking into their dogs big sad eyes and
You love to see your littermates
Wooden shoe
When the dog is really thinking
I love you
Because you are made of
Give meat
People now submitting these DNA samples and if they get a hit a match with another dog out there they are allowed to contact the other
Other dogs owners
To arrange reunions
You know what I think dogs would like better
Tinder
Pictures of butts
And all the dogs are like
They can easily swipe it or we can do that
Oh man
Jordan according to the Clay County Missouri sheriff's office this week as suspect
In Missouri hiding from police
Gave away his location when he did what
When you did
We did what
He gave away
Today
Yes he did quite loudly
We don't know who the guy was or what he was wanted for
But the man was crouched
Hiding in some undisclosed location when he crowd
Disclosed it going to Taco Bell
He's not been arrested on drug charges proving whoever smelt it dealt
400g
Is a controlled substance
Coming up it's lightning fill in the blank but first it's the game where you have to listen for the rhyme if you'd like to plan are call and leave a message
1-aaa
That's one 889-2489
Metaphorically
The contact us link on our website weight
Pri.org
There you can find out about attending our weekly live shows right here at the Chase Bank Auditorium in Chicago
Are upcoming shows August 29th and 30th
At Wolf Trap near water
September 12th in Newark
New Jersey in July 8th
Upcoming Thursday
At the Blossom Music Center just outside of Cleveland
Cuyahoga
Hi you are on wait wait don't tell me
California
Oh yeah that's in Silicon Valley I know it what do you do there
I need
Teacher and I also work
History
No wow
You work
For a murder mystery theater troupe
Yeah that's you heard that right so what exactly is that
It started pretty popular
Recently it's like you know
And we come and whenever Act
And then everyone has
Figure out
And is it always the same person or do you sometimes get to be the murderer
Well I'm dying
Tomorrow
Do you rotate the corpses well
I understand
Welcome to the show Sarah Bill Curtis is going to redo 3 News related limericks
For the last word or phrase missing from each if you can fill in that last word or phrase correctly into the limericks
Doobie when are you ready to play
I was born ready
Here is your first
Limerick wear blue ribbon
Nightstand off
Are $2 cans just
Say
Hard seltzer
Hard cider
Yes papa
Is not Brewing
Hard
Coffee
Your favorite crappy beer will soon be your favorite crappy coffee
Pabst Blue Ribbon is releasing hard coffee drinks
The captures the
Spirit of PBR
In the taste of mud
According to a press release the beverage clocks in at 5% alcohol and is made with Arabica and Robusta coffee
Coffee beans and quote
Rich creamy American milk
Unquote
To unwind by the pool with the drink of the summer until your energy come back or at least
Feel the rich creamy American milk
Welcome back
The best option for anyone looking to party
For 5 minutes barf and then stare at the ceiling all night
Alright here is your neck
Limerick
In the one place where I can get
Cool there's more germs
That are rabid dogs
Drool
The Outlook is grim
So I'd rather not
Swim
We've been warned
To stay out of the
No no
Cool
Pool yes
Who could have guessed that public pools those brothy soup in which we soak our children
Could be spreading disease
TDCJ
Which it stands for children's diarrhea cops
Says there's an increasing number of illnesses that can be traced back to a parasite that seems to be
Flourishing in public pools
Pools reflection place to relax
In the summer heat in the answer to the question
How do you get pink eye
Here is your last limerick
In Tennessee
Scientists
Turtle
Parallel world
Where in Morton
In a good upside down
Where are racing all from
We're hard at work
Building a
Yes portal
How did you get that
Scientists at Oak Ridge National Laboratory in Tennessee
You're trying to open a portal to a parallel universe
It's kind of complicated but they're blasting
Tiny subatomic particles of the surface and depending on what happens they may get a glimpse
Set of parallel universe
Which has mirror images
Of the matter in ours
Except they're all the little particles
Have a little goatee
Scientists have attempted to build a door to an alternate universe for years but I won't I've only now figured it out
It's push not pull
Are there really scientist working on that there really are real
You're doing it wrong
Find a
Portal 2
Parallel universe
It's not even science
For god sakes high-energy physics is amazingly interesting science
There is no
Parallel you
Universe
Another place
Where someone is doing this right now
So you know I have three cats and I
Schlitterbahn
Accessport times a day in the good news about what
Just learned just
That sometimes it feels so lonely
I know what I'm sippin I'll think to myself
At least you're not the only one
You just said you had three cats
13 cast
You'll have to fear
Will let you know they don't live forever
In this universe
Three straight in our universe
Congratulations
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Goldman Sachs
Four insights from leading thinkers at Goldman
In the state of markets industry
In the global economy
What's another podcast
Exchanges
At Goldman Sachs
You'll hear a range of
Disgust from the
Tech IPO landscape
The China's economic Outlook and much more
That's exchanges at
Goldman Sachs
Available
On Apple podcast
Spotify Stitcher
SoundCloud
And Google play an
Gs.com
Slash pocket
This message comes to you from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Capital One Knows life doesn't alert you about your credit
That's why they created Dino
The Capital One assist
Catches things that might look
Wrong with your credit card
Duplicate charges or potential
Sends an alert to your phone and help you fix
It's another way Capital One
Who's watching out for your money
When you're not
Capital One
What's in your wallet
To Capital One.
Pretty tails
No one's worried final game lightning fill in the blank each of our players will have 60s
The answer is many fill in the blank
Hershey candy
Correct answers net worth
2 points
Can you give us
The score we have a 3
Leeway Tile my God here we go I am going to art
Arbitrarily decide who goes first and I'm going to say it
Journey
Here we go
Tropical storm in the beginning first question phone number
On Wednesday labor secretary Alex Acosta defended his role in blanks
2008 plea deal
Right on Monday the governor of New York signed a bill allowing Congress access to blank
Texas state tax
Yes this week stocks jumped after the FED signaled a blank
Cut
Fed rate
Interest rate yai Monday a federal judge
Block the new DHS rule requiring pharmaceutical companies
Is the disclose blank during commercial
.
Though they meant to send out next season schedule the American Hockey League accidentally sent all of their app users blank
Don't want to say
No
It was a text Amanda and $6,000 from someone named
Stuart Zimmer
Volkswagen produced the final one of their icon
Blanks
Israeli ambassador to Brazil is in trouble after being caught using Photoshop
The cover of a photo of himself
Blanket
I have to use Photoshop to try to cover up a photo of himself eating a non kosher meal
He sat down to Big plate of definitely not Kosher Lobster
Will the president of Brazil when someone snapped a picture
For it was released the Ambassador apparently alter the photo by
You know scribbling lines over the lobster
Hoping people would just say oh yes blurry black lines the national food of Brazil
38 at Rafe Miller that he Photoshopped it out but that he
He's really bad at Photoshop
Better thing to do would be just you know grabadora in Photoshop in the words bacon good
Bill how did Jordan do in her quiz
Doug at 4 right
8 more points total
12 Android
In the lead
Okay Paul that will have you go next fill-in-the-blank on
On Tuesday and appeals court ruled that it is unconstitutional
President Trump to block
Critics on
Twitter flight following weeks of protest
The Hong Kong government says there proposed extradition law with blank
Is that
China
This week the house passed a bill to
To change the wording of a law that
Describes presidents as
I don't know
Ismail
Best known for his third party presidential runs in 1992 and 90
Billionaire Black
How many official Declaration of a senate run for
Arkansas
Republican Kris kobach blank
He declined to run for
No he misspelled his own first name
A Minor League All-Star Game this week
Who was the first baseball game in history to have
Balls and Strikes called by
Blank woman a robot
Call Citizens in Australia owner alert after a wild cockatoo was spotted
Blinking
I'm not sure but if you were to look in Another Universe
You should know
It was
Trying on clothes no it ripped out all the anti bird spikes so we could sit down
How to prevent birds from squatting in the employees put up spikes across the entire
But one cockatoo just wasn't having it
Shoppers caught on video tearing up the anti bird spikes
Beacon throwing them on the ground
After the flu inside the mall smashed window and flew off with a crate of Saltine
Is because Polly wants a cracker
3 right
6 more points
Total of 10 she's in second
And how many times is Roxanne need to win that I and V
Okay Roxanne this is for the game fill in the blank on Wednesday a federal court dismissed and emoluments lawsuit filed against
Right after a delay the White House says the deportation rates conducted by blank
Should we get on Sunday
I swipe this week officials in the UK
To the blank tried to seize the British royalty
Tanker in The Purge
Bright on Thursday online retail Giant
700 billion dollars to
The code
Amazon on Tuesday a judge reject
Actor Johnson & Johnson
Send request to throw it a lawsuit
Suing the company
Ready for their part
In the blank cry
Hope you're right on Sunday UNESCO at 8 buildings by famed architect
Black Twitter
Heritage list
Write an injured baby bird found in Utah by drunk guy is fine after the man blank
Call The Uber to take it to a wildlife refuge
You're right
Mammoth out tonight with his friends you found a lost baby bird was too.
Drunk driving to the Wildlife Rehabilitation Center in selfie the next best thing called an Uber
For the backseat
Send it on its way
According
It to its review the baby bird had a great ride
Even provided bottles of water and chewed up worms in regurgitated them into my mouth to Our Stars
Bill
Roxanne one didn't she
14 more points
What is total of 8
Fort Irwin
Yeah that was inevitable
We're going to ask a panelist after the US Women's Soccer Team
Get a ticker-tape parade in New York
Special place
Stock and Ledger restaurant here
Chicago
WBEZ Chicago
Limericks
Managers Tyler Green Assisted by Simon Tran
IBD
And Leila Francis
Star webguru is Beth Novi DJ
But soft what light
Light through yonder window breaks
It is the East and Peter Gwinn
Is the Sun
Technical directions Lord of white her business and ops manager
Just calling
I forgotten coordinators Robert Newhouse
Can executive producer Michael
Lynnwood
Mount panel
Who will get the next
Ticker tape
Parade
Jordan Carlos
Well it'll be that woman's
Steam again when they win
World
The next
Tape parade will be
The 10 interchange
Changeable white male Democrats
Who drop out of the
Presidential race
Because he loved one
Carlos Robertson
Cedar Creek Ohio
This is NPR