Support for this podcast
Message come from odoo
Want to boost your business
Check out a new business game
Scale-up
It's fun it's
Smart and odoo offers at
Shipping included
Use promo code NPR on
Odio o.com
Flash scale-up
Easy Chicago
The NPR news quiz
Sleep tight baby
You're about to get a doe seven
I talked to you today
Later on we're going to be talking to American soccer
Superstar Christian Lily
Who has the most caps of any player male or female veteran of five World Cups
Game-changing defense
Against the Golden Goal in the 99
Final
You have about a half an hour to Google around so you can understand what I just said
The meantime give us a call
The number is 10008 wait wait that's one 888-924-8924
Let's welcome my first listener contestant how you were on wait wait don't tell me
Hello this is Andy Johnson
Andy how are you
Fantastic I'm glad to hear it where you calling from
I'm calling from Warrenville Illinois about 30 miles Due West
Tell me what I'm missing by never venturing out of the city limits
We are the home to The Picture of Dorian Gray it was painted here
The Picture of Dorian Gray
Yeah the Albright feather Studio here in a few go to the Art Institute of Chicago
Macau
Portrait of Dorian Gray that was painted here in Warrenville Illinois
Exciting welcome to the show
A humorous and author most recently of save room for pie it's Roy blunt
Junior
Next up is the comedian producing in
And starring in the upcoming Asian American comedy film becoming Eddie details of becoming Eddie
Film.com
So he's a writer
Black Mirror HBO's divorce and host of the adulting podcast on WNYC it's Jordan
Carlos
Dissipated that's what you're going to play who's Bill this time Bill
Curtis is going to redo three quotation
Snooze
Can you can correctly identifiers
Enterprise
Turn my show you my
Nike shoes
On your voicemail ready to play
I'm ready
All right
Here is your first quote
Yes yes yes
Celebrating her 13th and final goal on Tuesday
She was a member of what team
Team USA soccer
Reigning Women's World Cup champions the US celebrated their
Return to the tournament by laying an absolute
Beat down on the Thailand
And team
Winning 13208 it would have been more but they missed the extra
The point
Now the US team
Was criticized not too much for running up the
Score but for
Celebrating a little too much
We don't know why
They're getting grief for all these celebrations we remember when the u.s. men celebrated their 13th World Cup goal 2
We just took them
8 world
That's true by the way the US women in their first game scored more goals in the u.s. men have since like
I think I know enough about soccer the Third
Martinez a lot
13 is an awful lot
There a lot of soccer games that have only
There's a lot of soccer games
Let alone
Two or three was there a goalie
Yes
Did they cut to the poor Tide players every time
Usat
Especially the Tiger
Doorkeeper as that she
She look just look sadder and sadder in
Saturn
Didn't anybody else no one else Wonder rotate in like
After the 5th going to be like
You give it a try
That in a prior match
What they call a friendly IE in didn't count for anything
They beat
The Cambodian team 11 to 0
The American people
The cambodians
Let's play the Cambodia
All right and that your next quote is from the ladies
This person to leave
The White House
I showed up everyday
But I think
I did the very best job that I could
Perrin and the
The Onyx
Somebody just giving us one more lie for luck
As the president announced
She was leaving her job who is it
Bellasera hakkasan
Sarah Huckabee Sanders be leaving the
The White House by saying I'm resigning I never said I was resigning
Leaving on good terms
She said she was humbled to work with present
Did Trump quote the only president
The United States has ever had
However you feel about her actions I should say she was really really good at doing her job
Which was basically not
Doing her
Job
She really was
I could see right through
What's what's next
What is she says she's going to go spend more time with your family of course
She said she's going to go back to Arkansas to live with your parents Mike Huckabee
And Bernice and
She barely gave press brief
What was the crazy thing her job of courses
Just to take questions
The Price is Right
Share information from the White House with the American people
Who are media Representatives
And she ended
The daily White House Press
I think she hasn't had one
In about 95
5 days
By the end of her tenure all her official statements were just
Been there
4 months I think they finally like
Went to her bedroom and lifted up the couch covers
Great thing about this present easy has such
Big heart he likes
People that nobody
That's true
Alright Andy you're last quote
Is from CNN
And it's describing one of many fun vacation snapshot
That's from this Summer's new
Hottest
Tourist destination
One photo shows a woman and a Hazmat
Unzip
To expose her
Underwear
Where is this new vacation hot
Spot
Holy mackerel I'll give you a hint this was inspired by this
The success of an ape
HBO miniseries
Turn off the kids are going to
Operators and I'm bringing people out to the site of the nuclear accident they're offering
Souvenirs Victoria
To take home
T-shirts bumper stickers
Cancer
Isn't it closed for like a
Thousand Years
Yes well it's surrounded by What's called the exclusions are they evacuating all the Resident
30 years ago
But you're there allow people to go back in for Limited.
I love that
VI peel
It is true that there's like a hundred square mile area of Ukraine that's
Surrounded by a single Velvet Rope
Hot again I like that
What is maroon
At Disney World for me
Exactly
Wait what do you get
To do when you go there.
Do you get to pet like to head
Cindy Ernst
Pretty much I mean
Like I said there's an entire city called pripyat
Was built for the workers at
Set the plan
And it was abandoned it made the Russians
The Soviets at the time told everybody they had to leave right away
So it's is weird Ghost Town work
People's possessions
You're still sitting with a left
In Wonder through there
And as you said X
Actually yes there's this
Huge area where all the people have been barred so
Wildlife
So you can
See you know as you say deer running around enjoying their fur
Freedom and that's
Third set of legs
Bill how did Andy do in AR quiz
300 graduation
We want to remind everybody they can join his most weeks right here at the Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown
Chicago Illinois
Customer information
Go to wbez.org
You can find a look at our website wait wait
Npr.org
Handle it is time
For a game
We call
The truck
Sometimes the Trump news comes out faster than your lunch after eating a medium-rare Trump steaks
We have to cover it as fast as we can we're going to ask you about the week
In Trump
Fire style Pellissippi
It's true or false get it right you got a point you ready to play
Alright here we go guys Roy true or false
The friendship
Tree planted by Donald Trump
And French president macron last year produced its first Apple
True false it died
President Trump tweeted that the Moon is part of Mars
True
I've done nothing wrong
No false
He said he was not like Richard Nixon because quote
He left
I don't lie
Secretary of State
The threat of climate change
False know it's true
Which way is a new opportunity
Portrayed
It's a good thing
Helen in a tweet Thursday Donald Trump referred to his great relationship with the
The Prince of Wales
Yes but he
You spell whales like this
Sea creature
Ship with Moby-Dick
Jordan True or False Donald Trump issued his first liking a tweet and several years
On a tweet praising Rudolph giuliani's broad shoulder
True no false Trump's first like in years was on a tweet about Rihanna's work-life balance
What
That's it for this week's Toronto
Coming up we save the world in our Bluff The Listener game call 1aaa wait wait to apply will be back in a minute with more
Wait wait don't tell me
Stream NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Fitbit Fitbit want everyone to know their body better
Even your dad who probably doesn't know how much deep sleep you get
Answer but his heart beats faster at the smell of barbecue ribs
Or that he burn 500 calories on the back nine
Get the incredible dad in your life
The gift of finally knowing
Everything
Shop now at fitbit.com weight
And save up to $30
Free next-day shipping
Due June 15th
A language was about to die
Once it gets wiped out
That's it we will have nothing
In our language to pass to our
And the people
Will trying to save it
We're still learning how to
Hurry up
What time is working against us we're like hundred years late you know
It's codes
Geolica level 5
Listen And subscribe
From NPR
WBEZ Chicago this is
Tell me the NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Kurtis
We're playing this week with
Jordan Carlos
And Roy blunt
Junior in Henrietta zoroaster
Chase Bank Auditorium
Downtown Chicago
Peter Sagan Google right now it's gone
A game called 1-aaa 28 two-player game in the air
You're on wait wait don't tell me
Hi this is fate
Beyonce song from Keene New Hampshire
Is it going to rain
I'm a student at Keene State College in Nebraska
Are you out there are you like actually on the rocks
Climbing the rock
I personally climb Outdoors on the rocks by TJ
Endorse
It's probably lose
Fewer students that way
Transporting
What Rachel
Welcome to the show
You're going to play our game but you must try to tell truth from fiction Bill what is Rachel
Topic
It's Not Easy Being Green everybody is worried about the imminent
Global Environmental catastrophe and by everyone I mean somehow not everyone
Memorize this week we heard about somebody doing their part
The help
But having it back
Fire are panelists going to tell you about it
Pick the money telling the truth in the Winner's prize
The wait waiter of your choice on your voicemail ready to play
First let's hear from
Helen Hong
We can all agree that
That certain environmental initiatives are just
The big pain in
In the butt
But some are bigger pain than others
Just ask the inmates at Northern Vermont
Correctional Facility
Who recently had to cut
Contend with the
Particular pain in the butt that is
Recycle
Toilet paper
The warden of a prison apparently got a rock
Bottom
Deal on the product
Which is made from a blend of recycled office paper
Packing material and cardboard
Some prisoners were
Used to sit through this bum deal
Discovering that wedding
Tire rolls
Abrasive
Booty white
We repeatedly
Wedded been dried
The toilet paper solidify to
The point that is
To file away prison bars
It took only
2 weeks and
Four rolls of recycled toilet paper
Sleeper for a handful of prisoners
The Shawshank their way out of
Facility
Aldi's
Escaped inmates were recalled
Add a nearby
Convenience store
Attempting to shoplift
Rolls of Charmin
A Prison Break
Inspired and abetted
Buy some recycled toilet paper
Your next-door have an environmental scrubber comes from Roy blunt
Junior
The East-West Market
In Vancouver British
Columbia
Wanted to do something about the
The proliferation of
Plastic trash
That is littering the Earth
Choking whales and even
Coursing through human intestine
However
The market didn't want to upset at Shoppers
By denying them plastic bags
So it provided bags
Emblazoned
With embarrassing
Messages
Into the weird
Adult video
The colon care Co-op
Hand Doctor toeses War
However far from being shamed by the bag
Shoppers found them cute
Headrush to collect
The whole set
You know what went wrong those messages weren't gross enough
To be sufficiently offensive to Canadians
Those bags
I should say
IHeart
See-through vomit
Oregon This Mother Nature
Or make America great again
Astora tries to discourage Bagus
Embarrassed
Slogans in the bag but people love them so much they grabbed
Extras
Your last story of good intentions
Turn
Carlos
Fresh out of Silicon Valley a new startup
Is a meteor crater
Sustainable economy out of
The clothing we see the least
I throw away the most
Using the Rideshare model
Undersheriff
Encourages consumers
Teeth are briefs
Boxers panties
And while supporting bras in the ReUse economy
For a monthly fee users can search an interactive map
4 unmentionables that
Random strangers would otherwise.
That's right your next pair of undies
May be closer than you think
Founder of Ryan says the app
Is perfect for anyone
His face is Malaysian of waking up in a stranger's bed only to wear the same DVDs
On back-to-back days
Grab a preamp are on your way to work
Keep it moving
There's been one big problem now
Under shared receive
Hundreds of complaints
And one lawsuit
From customers who
His partners are not happy to find underwear with it
Strangers name on it and their home
Said one two star review in the App Store my partner said Brad
Who the hell is
Brad I said I don't know but I like is under
One of these stories of an environmental initiative back
Backfiring is
True is it from Helen Hong
The prison tries to use
Recycled toilet paper
And ends up inspiring you
Escape
From Roy Blount Jr a store tries to
Persuade people from using plastic bags they putting
Embarrassing slogans on them and
People just want more of
Jordan Carlos
Is it that much people can reuse and share underwear leads
Difficult moments
At home
Which of these is the real story
Of a environmental initiative that did not
I'm going to
So with
II
Roy's
The story that's why
The novelty died and came back
Roy story about the reusable bags to find out the correct answer
We spoke to someone
Familiar with a true story
It's not to embarrass them
Just to remind them that they are other Alternatives rather than using a single-use plastic bag
That was David Lee when he the owner of East West Market in Vancouver
Can you print it up those embarrassing bags
Is everybody wanted more of
Congratulations Rachel you got it right here in 2.4 Roy
U1r prize the voice of your choice on your voice
Thank you so much for playing with us today
And now the game where we ask somebody who's used to doing great things to do something silly
It's called not my job
US Women's Soccer
Has been dominant internationally for decades and for more than
20 years
Christine
Lily was it
Star she played in 5 world
Cup finals
3 Olympics
She joins us now Christian Lily welcome to weight weight
Don't tell me
The credentials you you were on the US Women's
23 years starting when you were six
Steam
I know it's hard to believe
Wow so you were on the famous team that won in 99 with the Brandy chest
Final penalty kick
What do you call someone in the neck
Text in the next ride how many championships
I want one
Too woke up the ones on the first one in 91
One in the second and 99 and then I was part of
2 gold medal
Right so you
Hardware
You got some pretty lips
What you're talking about we got to ask you about the topic of the week
Which was the American map
Against Thailand
First of all that was a little unusual right
It it was I mean
DIY Iris
Effects of the Thailand team that kept playing
Do you have
You know what's on fire by I will confess
Routing of course for the Uso
But I felt a little kitty
Fear the Titanic
Giving out gold
A bunch of balloons I was in
07 in Los de Brazil for nothing in the semi-finals with
Felt like it was 10 nothing
It's hard to be on the other side of it but like I said I
Respect Island except their heads up
Take a look at it that way and maybe forget about
Squash for now
Yeah that's not going to happen
What is it like
To be
American
Playing soccer and we all know soccer is not one of
The big Sports
Here in America
Mostly Americans
Don't care about soccer
Did he didn't like the Europeans and the Brazilians of the traditional soccer powers do they get
Frustrated because
This American tour
Thrashing them
I like it very much
I was just at the opening game
France against Korea
And there was other players from around the world that played during my time
Norwegian
French player in that was talking to the Norwegian and I was like we didn't like you and she's like we didn't like you
Was pretty Mutual playing but that's what's made it competitive that so many great rivalry and now we can sit in
Talk about it and
We learn to play the game and what
Another woman's game is going into now
Do you still dislike them a little bit
Oh yes
Do you know a lot of
Norwegian
Curse words
Yeah
Hidden curse words
Spiders that is there a
Difference between
Between the men's game in the women's game
Different styles of soccer do you see different things
If you know what to look for
That's the difference I would say right now.
Men are more dramatic
Emotional
Do your kids play soccer
They do a $2 and they both play soccer
So what kind of soccer mom are you
Oh my goodness some days it's good some days is not good
Describe a bad day
So
I get to say the things
But sometimes I'm like
Oh my gosh I really want to say something right now but I
So wait a minute
You help
Coach
So that means there's a there's a coach
And this poor woman
A 23-year veteran
Of the US Women's team with two World Cup in two Olympic titles
Standing there
Giving suck
Gesture
Can curse words
An rru gentle about it I'll coach you know
It's just an idea but maybe you could try to win it game
I'm a very good assistant
And how are you with your daughter
I mean are you the idea you like
You know give give him a talking-to if they don't play to their potential or are you one of those everybody
Oh no no no
Wow
Bagley
Never ever been that ever been tempted to cut one of your daughters from the team
Not yet
Well Christian Lily it is a pleasure to talk to you today but we have invited you here
How to play a game where call
Your cup
Runneth over of course or World Cup champion but what do you know about the world's other
Cops
3 questions about many different cups
All right answer to correctly a little prize that is not a cup
For one of our listeners instead it's the voice of their toys
From our show
Still who is Kristine Lilly playing
Shane Hyman
Running scans
All right
Ready to play
All right I am Rite Aid
And here we go
I can feel you
Getting ready to
Citgo
I know I know
Who's the first Quest
We had cups of one kind of course
Thousands of years infected
Pythagoras
The ancient
Greek mathematician
Was a Pioneer in the cup
Field as well
What did
He invent
Was it a the novelty gift
Cup
Read the message world's best
Mathematician on it
Prank call
Which spilled wine all over the user when he tried to take a sip
Horsey the travel mug
And his case a couple
Designed to be latched
Did the saddle of a horse
Call me to go see
Sagres the great genius mathematician invented the prank cup
And it's really ingenious if you
If you pour in too much wine at all of a sudden drains out onto your lap
That Pythagoras
I got a spider Christina stop laughing
We all know and love Japan's famous couple Ramen you know Safari foam cup
Before in water you get ramen noodles is great
Other countries have their own version to like which of these
Is a rushes couple match
Potatoes
Be Canada's couple bacon
Corsi Sweden's capoeira
Oh man
What was the first one again
Potatoes
Don't get all Russians will see what they got
Yeah you're right
Of course
Mashed potatoes is available in chicken beef onion and Putin flavor
And I'm going to be honest it sounds
Or last question
The shootout if you win you win
All cars have cup holders now that's pay
Passe that's for
Wearing the real innovation
Drinking while driving
He is which of these
Hey the top of the line Mercedes Maybach
Which comes with sterling silver champagne flute
Be the new model Honda Odyssey Minivan
Does holders for juice boxes
Ceiling
So you can hang them above your kids like IV bags
Or see the new Ford 150 tailgate Edition pickup which is a built-in beer keg
Is wrong
Oh wow
I'm going with the minivan with the drip
Hook up the the juice box like a gerbil
I think it's more like
But I don't agree with it
You think I have the right answer but you just think it's the wrong thing to have
You said yes
Well
The truth doesn't care about you
So you going to pick it
Yes you're right
Of course
$1,000
Luxury sedan
And you better believe for that amount of money
Keep your champagne
Cold
Bill how did Kristine Lilly doing our quiz
Christy Newton
Reward cuz you one arm
Quiz
Hall of Fame soccer players
Who played in 5 World Cups
3 Olympics
New book on team-building Powerhouse
Houses on sale now
Kristine Lilly thank you
You so much for joining us thank you thank you and good luck
It just a minute bill has a new way to get you to eat your vegetables in The Listener Limerick challenge call 1-aaa
To join us on the air will be back in a minute
From NPR
Support for wait wait don't
Tell me in the following
Message comes from rocket mortgage by Quicken Loans
Imagine how would feel
Pills to have an award-winning team of mortgage experts
Make the home button
Process smoother for you
The history of industry-leading online lending technology
Rocket mortgage is
Changing the game
Visit rocketmortgage.com weight
Equal Housing lender licensed in all 50 states
MLS
Consumer access.org number 3030
Rocket mortgage
My Quicken Loans
Push button get more
I'm Gregory Warner
Unwrapped translation
We follow a rescue
Commission in real time
After Nawrocki photojournalist goes missing on
The frontlines
We don't believe it I don't believe
Lisa's family
Annie's friends
Try to say that when you said who is this
But who are you
They respond
We are the Aslam
Mcstate
From NPR's rough translation
Listen
Unsubscribe
NPR WBEZ Chicago
Wait wait don't tell me
NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Kurtis we are playing this week with Helen Hong
Jordan Carlos
Junior
Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown
Chicago
Peter Sagan
Bill gets ready to
If you like to play give us a call at 12228 wait wait
1889 to 4
Questions for you from the week's news
Jordan a new survey has found that
Compared to their own baby boomer dad's Millennial dad
Heather sorely lacking in their ability to do what
Oh
Call their dad
Fix anything exactly right
That one
A little too close to home
He was saying all right
Are you a dad or dad
Yes I have
Mini tools from Ikea
Chiefly an allen wrench
18 allen wrench
The survey found that on the
What's two-thirds of millennial dads don't even own a hammer or
Star screwdriver
Leaving them unable to repair anything including apparently their relations
Ship with her father
Lake Havasu
Screwdriver
Phillips
Yeah yeah
Do you own a hammer
My neighbor
Sarah lahti
I have a mallet
Whittier kids come to you and ask you
Yes
And what do you say
I'd say wait till you
Coming up as lightning from the blank but first it's the game where you have to listen for the rhyme
If you like to play on a or call and leave a message
1 Triple 8 wait wait
That's 180 89248
Berkeley contact us link on our website way
That npr.org
So you can find out about attending our weekly live shows right here at
Chase Bank Auditorium
In Chicago
Are upcoming shows June 27th at the Mann Center in Philadelphia
July 18th at the Blossom Music Center just outside of Cleveland and beautiful Cuyahoga
I don't forget to show off your
Your smarts with the wait wait
Quiz are smart speaker game
Just ask your Alexa or Google home to open the wait wait quiz
Doesn't feel that sense of accomplishment
You so deaf
Wait wait don't tell me
Hey this is Jonathan from Raleigh North Carolina
Alafaya
You know you did what you do there
Well I am a sports information assistant and a professional sports play-by-play announcer
Professional
Your vet your professional play-by-play announcer deep would you have
I'll do one sport all the
Why do football men's and women's basketball and baseball
Wow is there a secret to being great play-by-play purse
Being able to
And being able to arrange word
People usually don't
Talking about a picture being like a downhill Soapbox Derby race
That's a weird metaphor
He was on a roll
I like this guy
Welcome to the show Jonathan Bill Curtis
Password phrase missing
If you can fill in that last word or phrase correctly into the limits will be a winner you ready to play
I am here is your first
Although sprinkles and
Pancakes
Exhausting
It's not money but how
That their cost
Dressing
But we are not
Stressing
Will cover our salad with
Frosting
In an effort
In an effort to get kids.
To eat more
Edibles craft is rebranding
Ranch salad dressing
Best quote salad
Frosting and selling it a little frosting tube
Craft somehow didn't realize
Did the phrase salad dressing the problem was not the
Dressing
Apart
Like if they did sell Frost
Sting in Black individual tube
The eat it
Do you know Helen
They do
The whole notion
Of
Salad frosting
Re7 frosting Cummins boost
Camp
There is can
They're like letters
That's often done with little
Professionals
Know how old are you
Frosting and stick them in your mouth
Squeeze them and never leave the house again
My mother would never
Here is your neck slimmer
My laundry routine has been squash
Cousin Couture
Is now low and deep
Punished
I'll wear them for weeks
Who cares if it rains
My clothes
Are made not to be
And selling clothing
Pieces meant to be worn for weeks at a time without ever being washed
Figure tour Travelers environmentalist and that guy was a pair of sweatpants
She considers
The dressy one
Daddy has had the clothing has the special hygienic wool-blend
And it doesn't smell even after molt
Capoeira
Tell
New brand come with a
But a bottle of deodorant
Look up with the ideas that doesn't absorb
For somehow to some amazing chemical high-tech process it does not absorb your
Sweat and smell
Also it does not
It's hard to do
21st century technology
So do you smell
Want to take them off
Honey I'm taking off the pants
Happy Father's Day
All right
Here is your last limerick
Those blood splatters leave
Imdontai
Satanic goat
Just what I wanted
We are making the sale of a
Former witch
Jail
I am buying a house
That is
Two bedroom Cottage in Essex Britain can be yours for only $50,000 as long as you don't mind it's
Se former
Haunted
Which
Prison
A cheerful yellow cottage formerly called the cage was built
In 1582 and
Sunny Garden
All new appliances
Andrew enough
414 women accused of witchcraft
Cottages in great shape it hasn't been occupied
Since 2008 when the
Current owner moved out
After in this
Is true being quote physically attacked
By the quote satanic looking ghost of a goat
Wow
Worst thing I thought they'd
Just burn them at the stake
Some of them
Where they only do that
Sorry
But there is due process
Bill how did Jonathan do it perfect 3 at all good Garden Java
Congratulations well done
Support for this podcast in the following message comes from odoo odoo is a management software that covers all your
Business needs and A1
Stop solution
Odoo apps are proof
Quickly integrated to each other
Allowing you to fully automate your business processes
What's a boost your business check out odoo new business game
Famous Kayla
It's fun at smart
Ennodu offers it for free
Shipping included
Use promo code
Wait
100 D100. Com
Skillet
Support for this podcast
Open the following message come from Home Instead Senior
Gerontologist
I'm caregiver
Cricket Lakeland
Reflects on Home Instead mission
To enhance the live
Types of Aging adults
And their
You don't stop living once you hit a certain age
You can still live a rich meaningful life through your your later years and so
We are really excited to
He's celebrating art
25th and
Home instead
And to be still I working towards armor
To learn more about home instead
Gota homeinstead.com
Now onto my final game live
Fill in the blank
Each of our players will have 60 seconds in which to answer as many fill-ins
Has he or she can
Each correct answer net worth
Spell can you give us
Spirit types
Roy 3
Helen 3
Jordan has two
Okay
What are the stakes really that hot
Life or death Jordan
All right
During an interview with ABC News on Wednesday
Trump said he would
Except damaging
Information
About her new phone
Linda given to him by blank form
Right on Wednesday Republicans and Democrats
Beautiful White House
8 billion dollar arms sale
How to blank Saudi Arabia right this week in Nevada became the first state to ban testing
Potential employees for blank
Drugs marijuana close enough on Wednesday President Trump unveiled a redesign for black
Florida man busted for drug possession
Insisted that the cocaine police found
Wasn't his
Even though they found it in blank
No even worse in his nostril
Thursday all the cases filed in the relation
The blanks Water Crisis
Dropped
Plant right on Sunday blank when his 12
French Open title Rafa Nadal
Yes Rafael Nadal
Thousand dollars in repair cost for one man's MacBook and multiple trips
Did The Genius Bar
Apple employees
Discovered the blank
Didn't turn it on
I'm going to give it to you they discovered that the
The screens bright
Turn to love
Apple employees are brought in to try to
Repair the laptop
Stop broken screen from a dark
Despite everything else
Computer working fine
Replace several key components
Even provided it
Replacement laptop
A few weeks had the same problem
It wasn't until a month
Later that a technician
Discovered the lap
Stop brightness
With all the way down
The owner says he can't wait to use it for the two weeks
Until Apple stops
Supporting it and forces him to buy a new one
Bill how did Jordan do in this
Is unbelievable
Thank you
Right out of 8
The total of 16
Will flip the coin and Roy has liked
Indigo nexo Roy fill in the blank
Following emotional testimony from John Stuart the house
Judiciary Committee
The approve funds for blank
First responder
Very good this week protesters and police
Class in the streets
The blank over
Pose changed
Extradition laws
Right on Wednesday it was reported that the suspect
The shooting of Red Sox
Star blank
Was offered $8,000 in cash to do it
Who was Big Poppa
Rockport Indiana
Sworn in their newest police off
Officer whose last job was blank
No the drummer of the band five
Finger Death Punch
On Thursday the FBI said it was investigating ym several American terrorists have died while
Vacation in blank
Dominican Republic
Haiti's town and the ferryman with a big winners
The 2019
Police in England says I'll have no trouble tracking down a drug dealer who left the giant bag of cocaine in the subway
Because he also blank
He was wearing a while I was one cocaine
He was wearing
Shirt that I
Ed Koch
No
They track down the drug dealer who left
Giant bag of cocaine in the subway
Cuz he also label the bag with
The name and address
Manchester England police
Manchester police posted about the find their Facebook page saying that in addition to the cocaine in the bag also contained about 25 pill
Several White Rock
An electronic scale name and address cards
It's as if lost
Please return to your local drug dealer
10 more points
Douglas
Second
So how many Vans does hella me to win gt72 wind.
The game on Wednesday former White House communications director blanket
Need to testify before
Sean Spicer
NoHo PAC
Us defense officials say that it's likely that Iran was behind the attack
Two blanks in
In the Gulf of Oman
Oil tanker this week 10
Penn State filed a joint loss
The block the two billion dollar merger of T-Mobile and
Blank Space
Yes on Monday
Helicopter crash
The roof of a building
Living in Blythe Manhattan
Yes after being pulled over by police for driving a hundred and five miles an hour in a
70 miles per hour Zone
A teenager in Canada told officers blank
Panda poop
That's exactly right buffalo wings and had to get home to use the bathroom
For the game 7 victory over the Boston Bruins St Louis Blues won their first-ever blank
Is it hockey
Yes
I said that Ward the
That you got a feeling yes very good to lower Wildfire risk
Best utility company
PG&E announced
The plan to cut power to
40000 custom
In blank California restoration work costing over $1000000
The newly restored 19th century ship in Germany went out to
Xen black
Thank
Right
They ran into a
Cargo ship and immediately sank
Historical restoration at 7 working on making me a hundred fifty year old chips
Seaworthy since early twenties
So they were understandably thrilled when they watched
Did finally get out
Sissy
Immediately steering for a cargo ship
NSYNC
Possible that
Salvage and restoration
But all that being put on hold while they finished
Restoring this really cool
Hydrogen-filled blimp
Bill did Helen do well enough to win any
She got 7 right
She has a total of 17
Can one
This week scientists
Discovered a massive object hidden under the surface of the Moon
In just a minute we're going to ask our panelists
Predict what
Will turn out
Text this week once again to stock and Ledger here in Chicago for feeding us
Wait wait don't tell me on NPR WBEZ
Chicago in association with urgent haircut production
Doug Berman
Benevolent
Warehouse manager
Tyler green
Assisted by Simon
Ben Tran nabedian Lila
Francis rweb Guru is Beth Novey BJ leiderman
Composer
By Jennifer Mills miles dornbos and Lillian
French Embassy consult
Is Peter Quinn
Directions to Lorna Weider business and off managers Colin Miller
Senior producer and executive producer
Discover is hidden beneath
The Moon
Tylenol
32 more Democrats running
For president Jordan Carlos
A global reach
Reset button
And Roy Blount Jr
You know how when you break a mercury thermometer the load
Shiny poisonous balls come out well once upon a time I remove was Mercury
And it got set up with a Charming all those little balls so I came over to our nice
Green Planet
So that Bob is a mix
Mercury
All of you for listening I and Peter Sagal
Will see you next week
This