Support for this podcast
In the following message
Come from Duckhorn
Napa California
Duckhorn Vineyards has been
Crafting classic Napa Valley Wine
Ants with a sense of place
For more than 40 years
Learn more
Or at Duckhorn.com NPR
Hey it's Peter so you're listening to the show and you're probably shouting on answer
Whispering
If you're in a public spacer
If you're listening
Did the show on the sly while on a date
Wouldn't it be great
Could shout out answers and
Respond
Well if you have a smart speaker
It'll happen
Just ask your Alexa or Google home to open the wait wait
Quiz
Bill and I will
Appear as if by Magic
Asking questions for you to answer and Bill will even give you your score at the end
If you really good
Win the ultimate price
The voice of your choice on your voicemail
It's the next best thing to having his come over to your house
Even better cuz
Tend to eat a lot
Try the weight weight quiz
On your smart speak
From NPR and WBEZ Chicago
NPR news
Lay me down for the triple word score I'm
Bank Auditorium in downtown Chicago
Great show for you today
Especially because we're going to go to the place
Have never gone before
For you see here at wait wait we worry about a lot of things
I panelist
Accrue the quality of our jokes
And whether or not you can tell they are Jew
But
Today we discuss something we never have to think about here which is
Closing
There's so many questions
For example should we now be wearing
Pants
So today we are going to ask all are pressing questions
To an expert Ruth
Kathy Carter
The Oscar winner for her
Her costume design on the movie Black Panther
Fortunately those she will not be able to see
Either
We don't care if you bothered to put on pants first give us a call to play our game the number is 1
AAA wait wait
That's 188-892-4890
A24 let's welcome
Our first listener contestant how you're on wait wait don't tell me
Hello
Security from Tampa Bay in Tampa Bay
Awesome
Beautiful day today 72 degrees
Yeah but I'm afraid you've lost goodbye
Welcome to our show Judy let me introduce
You two are pedal this week first episode
The co-host of the podcast nobody listens
Paula Poundstone
Hey Judy Mexican Futures right here for the
The style section of the Washington
Post-its Roxanne robber
Hello finally a writer performer you've seen playing Mike Pence on the present
Show it's Peter Gross
Tragedy you're going to start us off with who's Bill this
What time Bill Kurtis
This is going to read for you
U3 quotation
As you expected
And you know that you have to
Correctly identify
Explain just two of them do that
Surprise the voice of anyone
You may choose
From Marshall
Ready to play
I'm ready
Here is your first
Well at least
There won't be hate that was David Waldman
Twitter celebrating the passage Thursday but bold resolution in Congress condemning hate
By whom
The Congress
The Congress has which half of Congress
House Representatives
Which
On Thursday all the Democrats in the house voted to condemn bigotry so hopefully you all got in you
Your bigotry before it became illegal today
The Democrats took over the House of Representatives in January and then
Reunited
Determined and
And focused
And it was amazing that lasted all of 6 weeks
Before
They reverted to their natural state of backstabbing and purity
Testing
This week's disaster all started around representative ilhan Omar who said something something
People that was anti-Semitic
She says it wasn't
And the argument got so bad even
Finally decided
To deal with it by passing a resolution
I'm condemning all kinds of hate
Including anti-Semitism racism
Islamophobia and whatever Taylor Swift was upset about in that sauce
It didn't start with
Adjust anti-semitism
People on
Weird sort of
Bizarre political thing that only Democrats could
Resolution
We don't like hate yeah we don't like hate and they all decided they could
Rihanna
Except
21 Republicans
Voted against
I know you're tired.
I don't know why they would do that
Vote Yes and everything and Mike
It's like when someone
When someone is beating themselves up you just sort of get out of the way and make sure you don't get hit by there.
I feel like I should just be like
Works
Take a the week off and you guys like
Just fight against each other for a second
Open primary
Sure sounds that there's fight among
Can you be
Critical of Israel
Without being anti-Semitic
Okay
And if it isn't anti-Semitism if you
You just hate Jared
Alright your next quote is a Washington Post comment
On a landmark
In space exploration
And it's scheduled
It's just too astronautics
Doing their work
Is it all goes according to schedule next week NASA will stage
The first all-female
What
Flight
That's been done before
4 but with never been done
4 is just women doing one
Particular activity
A spacewalk spacewalk very good it's great
All female spacewalk is baby cousin
In space no one can hear you say one
At the end of March
Christina lashes
Do a space walk
Altogether 245 miles above the Earth
Cuz that's literally how far you have to go to
Really avoid getting harassed at work
Why do women always
Go to space
In Paris
Weird is that weird like
Yeah
The announcement that space will no longer be habitable for Mike Pence
Has been met with praise and excitement all around women are excited face
Dreads are excited TMZ is already speculating about what the lady
These will be wearing
Stop that you shut up your big historic
Spacewalker
Your photograph
Smithsonian
And you realize the woman next
She was wearing the same
Everything in this is awesome
Just really make history
Crew
Managing The Space Walk
Back down
Also all women
The whole thing
Is going to be so
Constructive
Powering in
Cooperative
Houston you don't have
No problem you're perfect
Reported kind of like old timey news
Israel store styles
Eat for dinner
Moving along before
Instantly cancel
Your last quote is in response to a big article
Forbes
Kylie Jenner
Those days got to get up at 5 a.m.
To deliver the paper in the snow
Saving app
That article announcing the world that Ms Jenner is now the youngest ever won
In all of history
Billionaire youngest billionaire although
What's interesting is that Forbes referred to
Kylie Jenner
As the world's youngest
Self-made
Billionaire
Because it's true gender did it on her own without any help from anybody
Except her incredibly famous and Wealthy family who put her on reality TV at the age of
10 how old is she now she's 21
21 how old was Zuckerberg
Call
So odious I don't know who it's like I don't feel
Like I feel bad for Zuckerberg
No I mean
I don't think Kylie Jenner is
Odious
She actually started this cover
Reselling cosmetics
Starting to lip gloss
She's actually sold a lot of lip gloss
Which may or may not be important
But you know
Zuckerberg like wow do you know how much of the world I had to ruin to get my extra
But she's done a lefse harmful things
Previous billionaires have made their money by
Denuding
Forest City
Extracting oil from the Earth
Expensive all about health
From Panda tears
She's set up a charity to help under
Underprivileged women have access
List of basic makeup
Call the Kylie Jenner
Foundation Foundation
How did Judy do an AR quiz
To be her biggest
Congratulations shooting
Thank you all. Enjoy the weather
We want to remind everybody they can join us mostly
It's right here at the Chase Bank Auditorium in Chicago Illinois
Four tickets and more information go to wbez.org or you can find a look at our website wait wait
. NPR
Rhino panel it is time for you to answer some
What about this week
News
Roxanne for the first mission to Mars NASA
Looking for scientist
Engineers in Pilot but they'll also be low
For a what
The dog in space
You know
Are dogs okay
Kind of person should have
Because it's a kind of person
Should have a dog
Space knife
The first time until you let the dog out and then you're like
No not at all
The kind of person a person is good at
A chef
A
A prostitute
How can I meet again
Isn't everybody afraid months
Tri-City hydrated veal
Comedian that's a comedian
That to get old really good
Please
Adult NASA is
Considering the value of including a comedian
Professional or otherwise
On the longest in space
So if you thought you were here
Considered a voyage to Mars he might want to think again cuz it might get locked
Carrot Top
I work with many comedians
Very few of them
Have six months
The great material what do you do
You know what's funny I recently started dating again it was like
We've been here you haven't dated anybody even the front
Right over there
The bluff The Listener call 1-aaa wait wait to apply will be back in a minute with more and wait wait don't tell me
Tremendous
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Message come from Stanford children
What are the scariest things
Mom look
Because the next words are you sure
Billy can fly
Or Joey riding the dog
Or a crayon stuck in Valerie's nose
Here's something you might
Want to hear
With over 20
Pediatric office
Stanford pediatric
Christians are all over
The Bay Area
Not just in Palo Alto
Find a Stanford
At stanfordchildrens.org
It came out of the blue one night when
Sleeping
Searing pain
The jumped from one
Evans body
Another
Why is this happening why is this happening to me
Suicune invisibilia
Pricing story of how
Helping spread through
Agriculture
WBEZ Chicago this is wait wait don't tell me the NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Curtis Ware playing this week with Roxanne Roberts Peter Gross
And Adam felber
Are we going to your host at the Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown Chicago
Peter Sagal thank you girl thank you so much right now
You know what time it is it's time to the wait wait don't tell me Bluff The Listener Gameco 1-aaa wait wait two-player game on
How many are how you are on wait wait don't
Hi this is Brian from Seattle Washington to Seattle
Healthcare of
Snow today
What do we do there in Seattle
I am an Elementary music teacher
Oh my gosh
Elementary school music teachers have to listen
The worst quality of
Is it that's true being played by beginning young students
Recorders are not fun right now
Well welcome to the show Brian you're going to play a game in which you must try to tell truth
Jacksonville what is Brian's topic
Headed Peter
What is the
The topic
Life has so many great
Question
Just as we asked
If a tree falls in the forest does it make a
Sound
I told him one day I asked what
What is a tree
This week 1 of the great questions
Actually got answered
Ipana was going to tell you about it picked the one is telling the truth and it windy wait waiter of your
Your choice doing your voice
Ready to play
Yes I am alright first letter
Hear from
Adam felber
Why Do Fools Fall In Love
1956 by Frankie Lymon and the teenager
Yours and then again in 1998
In a film starring Halle Berry now has a
Scientific answer
Because love makes you stupid
A landmark study by the UCLA School of neuropathology
Least last month reveals that falling in love can lower your IQ
Spy smut
20 point
For everyone who emerges from a bad breakup asking what was I thinking
Well the scientific answer is
You weren't
Lead researcher dr. Colburn says that
Single test subjects were issued a thorough cognitive exam is a Baseline
Edwin retested over the following years
And that when subjects found themselves in a new relationship
Their intellectual abilities
Plummeted
One subject
Show me Picasso portrait initially Road quotes
The reductive
Cubist approach has a deep anxiety about the multifarious nature of a dent
2 years later that same man now in a new relationship
Quotes
She seems pretty unhappy I like her
And he misspelled pretty
Dr. Colburn who himself has gone through two divorces
New Lover showed higher levels of adrenaline and orphans and other mentally impairing hormone
They basically put the dope and dopamine he said
However it should be noted
That would ask him follow-up question 3 weeks later dr. Colburn had recently met a wonderful new woman
And he answered quotes
Do you like pancakes
I like pancakes
Call fall in love because love makes you
Stupid
You're next
Story of the cubing Aid comes from Roxanne Roberts
It was Freud who first asked
And said he had
Never been able to answer
The Great quest
Question
What does a woman want
Stanford
School Professor Kevin McManus believe he finally knows
McManus
Who's watching
Those cheesy Valentine's Day
Commercials 2 years ago and decided to find out what women
Really want
Based on
Purchasing data
Social media algorithms advertising research and voting record
Forget the flowers chocolate diamond
According to McManus
NASA's findings
Which were released Monday women want
Point three hours of
Sleep at night
Purple yoga mat
Black yoga
Yoga pants
Book clubs if you don't have to read the
The book
Pumpable kitty litter
Idris Elba
Box wine but not in public
More animal emojis
Equal pay for equal work
Sex but not when they have to get up in 5 hours
And Hedgehog
Hedgehogs why hedgehogs
McManus
Told the New York Times
He has no idea but
Hedgehogs top every
Current metric
Female happy mcmanus's best guess
I blame
Twitter
So
The question what do women want
The answer a lot of things and for some reason hedgehogs
Your last row of a question answer to comes from Peter Gross
Humanity has long grappled with the big question
What is our purpose
How many roads must a man walk down before you
You can call him a man
The biggest question of all
Which way do I place the toilet paper on the toilet paper holder
You can go with the end-of-the-world draped over the top causing the paper to Cascade over the front like a pillow a waterfall or you can
Can go with the End of the Roll Touch This
Prickly under the rule itself
You don't care which way your toilet paper emerges from its cochiti to Plica
Cocoon side you coward
We over under debate is Rage 4 years
Is led to unmendable Rifts
Text roommates in his late weight
Tamara Sparks the bloody Iberian toilet paper 1950
Which is why the people at the magazine choice
It's a sort of Australian
Consumer Reports
Decided to settle this vexing issue once and for all
This week they published an incendiary article featuring a recently
Discovered patent
From 1891 for the original toilet paper roll
It included a detailed 128 year old
Pictograph which showed
Definitive proof of proper paper plates
Over the top of the Roll
Over
After today mankind
Brother will no longer fight against brother husband and wife
Tell no longer argue over toilet paper plates instead argue about everything else
Importantly toilet paper itself can rest easy
Knowing it shall never again before stick our under the oppressive yoke of the role for which it
It sprang majestically over the top of the Roll before being deployed
Septic destiny
Somebody food
So
These are the question
One of which
Got answers
Was it from Adam Why Do Fools Fall In Love
From Roxanne
What do women want or
From Peter Gross
Did the toilet paper roll go from
Over the top
Or come from under the bottom which of these
Is the persistent question that finally got answer
What the toilet paper toilet paper
Peter story all right you have selected
Peter story of the Great
Discovery of the
The toilet
Paper roll
Orientation
Well
To bring you the correct answer we spoked
Familiar with
The patent
Clearly shows that
Toilet paper is
Coming over the rug that was governor Pony generator
Institute of History & Art talking about toilet paper
And the fact that we now know
That it comes over the
Congratulations you won
Peter got a point but more to the point you want our prize the voice of anyone you may choose
On your voicemail
Congratulations and thank you thank you
And now the game react
Somebody who is what it all to win
Think small
The Academy Awards a few weeks ago made history
Not because the ceremony
Didn't have a host
Not because it feature
Lady Gaga and Bradley
Conceiving a child on
Because For the First time ever
African American women won Oscar
Categories other than Act
I think we are delighted to be
He joined by one of them now
Academy Award winner for
Costume design in the movie
Movie Black Panther
Ruth e Carter welcome to wait lights on,
First of all
Congratulations on the Oscar win
Have you gotten over to you still sort of a buzz you walk around holding it all day I don't know
But you were nominated a bunch of
So were you
Surprised when you finally won or you were like it
My turn
It's been 21 years
The last night
Really
Yeah I was like man if this
Going to take 21 years
Time I better grab this now
You're the First costume designer we've ever
I just wanted to go over some basic
So you're the costume designer Thrift
Do you ever do you ever deal with like actor egos like
Perfect costume for
The character like I'm not going to
Don't you know
I guess you deal with that cuz he goes on a different level you know so
Sometimes day
They say you know I can't wear that color you know or
But because we're rediscovering a character we are both
Kind of contributing to the conversation
Write the application just say yes so maybe your character has a bigger butt
It's amazing to me that everything else you have to do you have to pretend to listen to actors
I'm sorry that's a hard job
College
Become helpful for dealing with
Yeah so let's get to the fun stuff
Which is a movie like black
Comicbookmovie
Fictional Fantastical scientific
Kitchen country
You are the most qualified person to
Ask about something that I've always thought
Which is that a great problem
For making comic book
Is that unlike in
Comic books
People wearing superhero suits
In real life
Essentially look dumb
Yeah because they don't realize it's their whole process to making that
You just don't go to
The store get some
Spandex in
So it up
No
So how you think about me
I grew up where we were watching like dumb superhero shows
MTV like Batman
People just look
Dumb
Yeah
So how do you make it so like
The Black Panther when he's in his suit
Superhero suit running around
Doesn't look dumb
Yeah well we do a muscle School
That help
When will we take a vacuform kind of mannequin
New version of
Chadwick Boseman
Real
Body form
And we add
The clay to his muscles and weave
Reform
A superhero kind of stuff
The physique
Are you telling me that that
The secret not all Chadwick Boseman how much Muscle Milk you drink you're never going
Maybe a superhero you got to have some
Play muscles amazing
Superhero suit that Chadwick Boseman is wearing in the movie
The kids have it Halloween at the muscles in
It's not exaggerated as
She might think it's just a little you know because we don't want to you know to really make this up
But in the other direction
More shoulders
You are going to win more than an Oscar if
Do you make us look
Famous line in one of the early Spiderman movies
Is that true if your
Eurocopter
Oh no this is zipper
So you are now an oscar-winning
Costume designer you have leading costumes
Designer mini mini film
For many many years
Does that put some pressure on you to dress when you got in public
Oh no I've always been the answer
Fashion I think that's what makes me kind of you
That I'm not trying to
Please
Prove myself to anyone it's not
It how I look it's how I dress other people come on really
When I would expect if I
If you came to my Halloween party
Huda Beauty
I would expect that you would walk in with like
Vcast
Yeah that's why I don't go to Halloween
Now you're done getting a
Play the feel like you don't have to like force your way to get accolades at Halloween parties
He wants me to do there
People of money in
I want to be an amazing Halloween costume
What time is it joke you know and I'm going to do a Halloween costume after I've designed the black
Tell you I'm not going to do it
Well Ruth Carter what a pleasure to talk to you we've invited you here to play a game we're calling
Hate Mondays
You designed Black Panther
They're so we decided to ask you about the rmb
That is
Garfield
The inexplicably Beloved comic strip character
Three questions correctly you want our prize one of my lesser is the voice of anyone they might choose in their voice
Bill who is Ruth Carter playing for
Brenton Angie in Indianapolis they are winners of the wait wait quiz available now and yours
Smart speaker
You ready to play Ruth here's your first question
Garfield was invented by his
Creator Jim Davis back in 1978 what inspired mr. Davis to
To create the bull
All the characters
His own cat
Beloved
Tubby tabby
Name Cass
Be his brother who is fat lazy love lasagna and occasionally
Cleaned himself by licking his
Or see a desire to create a quote a good marketable character unquote
That would make him a lot of money
Tubby tabby
No
See he wanted to make a lot of money
Set the time they're all the
Please dogs in the,
But no cats and
Any figured there were like fifty million cat on
I might enjoy a cat
So he created it
To be popular
And it worked
It 2004
Garfield the Movie
We came out it was panned by critics
But Garfield was voiced by legendary actor
Bill Murray wine
Bill Murray
Agree
To play Garfield
Was it a
The Producers agreed to pay him with a lifetime
Supply of Italian beef sandwiches
Favorite Chicago restaurants
Being mistakenly thought that the movie
Screenwriter Joel Cohen with an H
Was Joel
Cohen of the Coen brothers
Or see he was still angry that he wasn't allowed to provide a voice
For the Gopher
Oh I'm going to try
B
Your
Write this down
He thought that he was doing a movie that was written by one of the Coen brothers and he says he didn't realize his mistake until he was in the studio
Recording his lines and all of them were Tara
Alright last question if you get this right you win here we go
Not every Garfield
Strip has been embraced
By his fans
Does which of these
Aa2007 strip
In which OD Burns an American flag while screaming death
To America
Be a 1997 stripping with John's girlfriend Liz catches him wearing
In her underwear
Horsey a series of Scripps the week of
Halloween 1989 written as a horror comic
Image Garfield faces his greatest
Fear existential loneliness
Brother let's see I'm going to try
Bob
In which Jon's girlfriend Liz khaki pants
Wearing her underwear
The existential horror
That's what it was
If you've never seen these very
Real comics of 1989 and highly recommend you look it up cuz Garfield supposed to be
Funny and chubby and angry he wakes up and in
Empty house
Where no one is left
Eddie spends all week
Pelican beak
Because he's facing his greatest fear
Loneliness
Bill how did Ruth Carter do an AR quiz
Two out of three which is a win
Got to be better at just all uphill it's like Oscar wait wait don't tell me
Nobel
Ruthie Carter won the Oscar for costume design for black panther just this
Museum exhibits
Featuring her design
Traveling the world rotate Carter thank you so much for joining us Army
Take care
In just a minute bills got
Solicitor Limerick challenge call 1aaa twait to join us in the air
From n
PR
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Duckhorn Vineyards Napa Calif
Founded by Dan and Margaret Duckhorn
Born in 1976
Duckhorn Vineyard
This has been crafting classic wines
Ants with a sentence
Place for more than
40 years
With seven Estate Vineyards located throughout the Napa Valley
Valley the winery produces vintage Merlot
Cabernet Sauvignon
Sauvignon blanc and Chardonnay
All showcasing the diversity of wine
Learn more
Duckhorn. Com
NPR
Gyros here
And on the latest episode of How I built this
Has Squarespace founder
Anthony casalena
Came up with the idea for a better website publishing tool
In his college dorm room
And since then
Delta Dental
Company values
1.7
Million-dollar
From NPR
WBEZ Chicago this is
Wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Kurtis we are playing this week with Peter Gross
Adam felber
The Rock said Robert
Chase
Chicago Peters
You built like a
Rhymes of a lemon a lemon to a lime Bill Kurtis
Will be here to show you how to rhyme
It's a listener Limerick challenge if you like to play give us a call at 1 AAA wait wait that's 18889
To 48924
Rhino panels more questions for you for the week's news
Peter this week and NPR report focused on a new crisis for our nation
Is elderly the desire to extend their life expect
What is a long enough
What
To see that friend died
Great-grandchildren
Politico Trump's present
Not quite
According to some Rumors in the press it might be as soon as next week some people say they have to stay alive until like later in the spring
They want to live
To see the
Exactly right wow wait a second
Play Gears
The NPR story describe the 90s
3 year old man was on his deathbed any suddenly sat up
You know
What presumably was the terminal come and look to the son and said his last words quote don't believe
I'm not going to see the Mueller report am I
He'll get the bug report he wants it happened I thought we put that
This is
Houses, with seniors all over the country and some of the matter that wants to report does come out it wouldn't hurt if their grandkids call them once in awhile
The tale
In order to extend their lifespan in order to live long enough to see this news doctors are recommending that senior stop watching
Sing the news
Peter the latest dumb thing people are doing in the internet
Well they're posting videos of Happy parents doing what
Talk to their babies
Happy parrots trying to
Cats their kids up on
The most recent
Season of
Bachelor
Bear
Throwing their babies
Did someone say they're not throwing their baby
Give it back to you
They are
Throwing something that sounds like
They're probably keys at their babies at parties
Everybody put your baby
I don't know it's a baby not a cracker
We Florida Cracker
This is called cheesing
And all you have to do
To take part
Is film yourself throwing a slice of cheese
Cheese at your baby face
And post it on the internet
A slice of American cheese
Wheel of cheddar
If they affected it hit their face, clean like sticks
Exactly.
Baby usually big musically
Repeal it off their heads
Going to eat at the first choosing the first
Cheesing video went up
Just a week ago
But not before it was seen hundreds of thousands of times and
Inspired countless imitators
Play that taken down by the parents are by like
Baby and they put it up
Like a hundred thousand years later and then
DCFS took my baby and the f
The first time I've ever wanted to have another kid
Coming up it's letting me fill in the blank refers is the game where you have to listen
For the rhyme
Would you like to play on air call and leave a message
AAA wait wait
Twenty88
To 4
You can click the contact us
Lincoln our website wait wait. In PA
Care.org
So you can find out about attending our weekly live shows here at
Chicago
I'll be sure to try out her new interact
The quisby
Are smart speakers updated every Wednesday
Just say open the wait wait quiz and you'll get your
To prove how smart you are and when your chance to get the voice of your choice on your voicemail
High urine wait wait don't tell me
Hi my name is Rachel Vaughn and I live in Des Moines Iowa
How are things in Des Moines
They are cooled and
Noe yeah
Alright Ice for use your gift are you asking
Turn yourself why you live there as we do here
Kind of everyday
Yeah I know
Monopoly made herself.
Depressed
Rachel welcome to the show
News related
Tricks with the last word or phrase
If you can fill in that last word or phrase correctly into the limerick
If you will be a winner
Ready to play
I am
Where is sauce Galileo
What flavors we're eager to play on
How are combos are valid
For me
Bedford salad
Will mix any flavor with
Mayo
Yeah yeah
You may remember mayochup
The mayonnaise ketchup combination
The huge hit
What was released last
With mayo fan
Kids baking Hines
Mixing all the goose
Together please
Our prayers have been answered with mayo must
Shorthand for mail must be the reason I had a heart attack
It supposed to mayonnaise mustard hybrid just
George W bush
Years ago they're all ciracle failed
Male turd
Right
Girls making a barbecue sauce
Mayonnaise hybrid called maoq
An antacid mayonnaise hybrid called Mayo
Peanut butter and jelly that are the same element
Like
You know two step now what
50% of your time is it
Goat cheese
Selling babies with cheese already on
Exactly
Here is your next limerick
Miss miniature Trends getting worse
I can't pay
I can just
Reimburse
My minuscule bag
Is a fun fashion gag
Cuz I can't fit my
Nikes in my
Micro purses
Are the big
Small
Breakout star power
Fashion Week
Exactly what they sound like
We're so tiny can fit the palm of your hand
Show me 2 inches long and they aren't big enough
Cash or credit card
Which is fine because
$520 a pop
You won't have any money
Anyway
You got this thing like you got the models with that serve
What is stoic expression
Was face in the walking down the runway
And they're holding the handles with just
What's the tips of their fingers
Their finger diets finally paid off
According to
Influence
The only challenge is finding
Toy poodle small enough to ride in
Inside but no problem
Here is your last limit
This week science
Gave proof to My Humps
Went on cannabis
I'll eat to lunch
How to cookies
Ensuite
Add chips
And Suites
Smoking pot really gives you the
Munchies
Is it news story ever really looked at
I mean really looked at it
You'll find analyst jokes about the munchies
Supposedly the pot inducer
Dog food
But now science has
Spoken munchies
These are
Wheel
Isatori found at states where pot has become legal
Have a 5% increase
The sales of ice cream
Chips and cookies
I think the science was in when every single person I knew game 20lb
Who pays
Is for the Dominos
Yeah
Domino's
We technology
How did Rachel do an AR quiz
She is a champion
Congratulations Rachel get all three right
Support for this podcast
Send the following message
Sitcom from Duckhorn Vineyards Napa Calif
Founded by Dan and Margaret Duckhorn
Born in 1976
Duckhorn Vineyards has been
Ben crafting classic wines
With a sense of place for more than 40
With seven Estate Vineyards located throughout the Napa Valley
The winery produces vintage Merlot
Cabernet Sauvignon
Sauvignon Blanc
And Chardonnay all showcasing the diversity of wine
Learn more at Duckhorn. Com
Support also comes
News from UCLA Anderson School of Math
Who teaches the next generation of leaders their value
Sharing success
Thinking fearlessly
And driving show
Inspired by the legacy of coach John Wooden
UCLA Anderson
Success comes from knowing that you did your best to become the best that you were capable of
More information available at Anderson. UCLA.
EDU
Peyton skyrise
Creator of how I built this in
We're returning to San Francisco for this
Second how I built this Summit
Supported by American
Express
I'll be join there by founders
Companies like Instagram
Slack away
Bliss JetBlue
Many many more
Visit Summit
. npr.org
Learn more and
See you there
I want to watch final game lightning fill in the blank
Guitar players
50 seconds
Answer as many films
My questions is he or she can
Each correct answers net worth
Spell can you please give us
The scores Hedeman Roxy chapter 2 Peter has
Oh my God so good start
Alright we flipped a coin roxana's elect
Did the Gophers Roxanne fill-in-the-blank just
One week
After Summit with President Trump blank is reportedly rebuilding a long-range
Right
On Monday Mitch McConnell said
The Descent
Would pass a measure
2 block
Blank
The national merch
This week Nicolas Maduro the embattled president of blank
Detained a freelance journalist from the US
From Venezuela
On Thursday Chinese Tech Giant
The blank filed a lawsuit
Get the us over
Urbana
Huawei customers are complaining of
To discovering
That Ikea's new blank requires assembly
No chocolate Easter Bunny
Adorable don't eat the Allen wrench on Wednesday
300 Healthcare expert
Crystal the CDC
See that there guidelines on Plank
Hurt page
Chronic pain
Pain
Best known for his role in Beverly Hills now
210 actor
Philadelphia Phillies fans excited about incoming player Bryce Harper have purchased so many jerseys
The local stores have blank
Fitwell
There's nothing funny they probably ran out of merch
Merchandising they probably had
They close the doors and they probably
Threw batteries at the cusp
Trying to buy more Harper
Well they ran out of the letter r
For the Bryce Harper
Splits
Make sure if we are putting like the words Bryce Harper
Bryce Harper in the back of shirts
The merchandiser running out of ours
Is this
I'm at the stadium people be going in the hotline
Michael Jackson Beat It
Spell how did Roxanne do in Ark
6 write 12 more points
She's in the lead all right
Next up is Adam
Please atom fill in the blank
According to CNN
President Trump pressure dates
Advanced security clearance
To blank
This week former New York mayor blank said he would not run
Mikey blumberg
Book stores would be
Tesla right on Monday President Trump tweeted that he'd give Alabama quote a plus tree
Following a string of deadly blow
Tornadoes right after firing at their last
Vital field goal
The Chicago Bears
How's that this week they signed a new kicker named Chris plank
Miss
Your clothes
You know it's even better Chicago Bears his name Peter
Blewett yeah
Blank overtook Michael Jordan is the NBA's all-time top scoring
On Thursday Mark Zuckerberg outlined his plans
Let's make blank more focused
User privacy
Facebook Live this week of the a doping Scandal of the world's number one black player to be stripped of all his medals
Bowling no bridge I know I know
Is a doping Scandal so shocking it caused people around the world
How to say wait they give out medals
Four braids
Norway's most celebrated player has been stripped of all of his
Golden band for 2019
After he
He failed a mandatory drug test
The man says he plans to appeal the ban
But for now he's focusing his energy
His new job
Captain of Russia
Spell how did Adam do in Ark
The 14 you might guess is a
All right so that means that Peter needs how many
52 Tyson
Still here we go Peter this is for the game fill in the blank on Wednesday
The DNC said they would not let blank cover any of the parties primary debates Fox News right on Tuesday President Trump said he agrees with
Plans to leave a small Force
Have US troops
In blank
Afghanistan
Syria
Excited London reported
II everpurse
Secured of
Blank HIV right on Thursday former Trump lawyer blank files
Suit against the Trump organization
The legal fees
Yes
Attempted carjacking in Wisconsin was foiled when the carjacker blank
Punch the cow that was trying to carjack
No
Realize that he couldn't drive stick
This week NASA found the first evidence of a giant underground water system
Mont Blanc
Marx right on Wednesday Jeopardy goes blank revealed
Diagnosed with
Pancreatic cancer
Alex
Write this week
The security expert studying data breaches warned that one of the most common password
Is blank
1 2 3
34 no
It's j-132 k7a you for a 8
Brock's did you know that did you have that in there something you want forget like
2K 17
Ua483
And it turns out you need to include a special character so you go with a J-1
32 k784 A3!
And then just in case you forgot that you had a password hint like your mom
Maiden name
PG-13
You might be wondering why is that password so
Common
Because it's the translation of what you get when you use
Chinese language
Keyboard to type
My password
Now that's hilarious people have that
Maybe beating us in the trade Wars but at least we American
Is Nota
My password
Bill did Peter do well enough to win
We have a
Freeway
Will you say that every time
Youngest billionaire
The first
Thanks to Farmhouse Tavern for continuing to feed us
Making me
Chicago
Urgent haircut
Productions Doug Berman benevolent overlord
Philip gotika rights are limericks are public
Address announcer e palfrey
A house manager is Tyler Green Assisted by Simon Tran in Maryville
Printers are Alex McCord
Morning Rachel Clapper I web Guru is best
BJ leiderman composer see my program is produced by Jennifer Mill miles during boss
And Lillian King if you listen real close late at night
You can still hear Peter Gwen Footsteps in the Wind
Ever close
Technical directions
Robert Newhouse our senior producer is Ian God's Own mohawk
An executive producer wait wait don't tell me is Michael Danforth now panel who will be the next young billionaire Adam felber
Crystal Kardashian
Designer amniotic fluid
And becomes a billionaire she will nonetheless be described as self-made
Rihanna
Cousin
Sandra realizing people want their
Poolside offices for all those
Office supplies
Will start Rihanna's bananas Cabana
My ten-year-old son will invent
Patent the toilet paper holder for Rebellion Thunders
Who want to repeal against the tyranny of toilet paper etiquette
Do about a tear
On wait wait don't tell me
If you're listening I am Peter Sagal and we will see you next week
Miss