This message comes from NPR Spa
Energy upgrade California
Helping to inform Californians on easy ways to
To save energy
Like unplugging unused
Used devices because it all adds up
Keep it going
Ben and get the facts
Exit energy upgrade California.
But he wasn't a match
Hey Bill Curtis here
We all know how the wait wait podcast works right
You listen quietly boiled Peter and I joke around have fun and play games
But do you ever wish you could play along
Now you can just check out her new age right now.
Well now you can
Check out our new interactive game for your smart
Speaker
We asked you the question was
And we can hear your answers
Just ask your Alexa or Google home
Do open the wait wait
Quizzed
To try it out
You could win my voice on your voicemail
Maybe
Singing my fav Jam
Real love
Patience and one taught me
Pain
So a
NPR and WBEZ Chicago this is
Wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
Is it hot in here
I blame global warming
Bill Kurtis and here is your host
At the Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown Chicago
Peter Sagal
Loud a wonderful show for you
Today later on
We're going to be talking to the actor Lance
That's radecki play flute
Kenneth Daniels on The Wire
And starring in the latest
John Wick movie
But first
Some history was made this week
Weekend broadcast
The two greatest interviewers
Of the past two decades
Terry Gross
And Howard Stern
A tattoo Park
Conversation
On fresh air
And it was
So astonished
Thing to hear someone say
Synonymous with
Decline of sea
Sast with p*** and sex
Talking
Howard Stern
If you only knew a man
We don't want to know
If you made it with your co-star we just want you to play our games give us a call the number is 10008 wait wait
That's 18892
To 48924
Let's welcome our first listener contestant higher on wait wait don't tell me
Hello this is Richie Huntington from Dallas
Pennsylvania
Dallas Pennsylvania I don't know where that is
I'm sure that you enjoy playing YouTube
People is not that Dallas
Where is it
It is near
Scranton and Wilkes-Barre northeast PA
Northeast PA
And what do you do there
My family practice.
Oh that's awesome
That's good work
And how are you doing
20 years
Welcome to the show Richard it is great to have you with us let me introduce you to our panel this week
First up the co-host
Stop the podcast
Nobody listen
Santa Paula Poundstone
Mr. Adam felber
A comedian on Bieber
Performing at the
Comedy Underground
Seattle Washington
May 30
First fidget the host of the trivia podcast go fact
Yourself on the maximum
Get Helen the hall
And a humorous and author most
Italy of save room
Number for pi
Junior
Hello doctor welcome to the show
Richard Google Play who's Bill this time Bill Kurtis right now of course is
Was going to read for you
Three quotation
From the week's news your job
Of course correctly identify
Diagnose
Two out of three
Do that and you win any voice from our show
You might like
On your voicemail ready to play
I am all right
Here is your first
Quote mules camel
Bleached beeswax
Traveling circuses
Chili
Slug those are just some of the thousands of
Things
That will be much more
Expensive because of
The US
Trade War
With whom
China China
That's right the parents our president has imposed or going to be
Even camels
More expensive
Sorry kid you might only be getting a one Humper
Christmas this year
Chine On Top of the others
These new ones include technological
Components baseball cap handbags boat spicy
Even
Cereal
So sorry your Chinese Rec
Cereal is now going to
B25 purse
Percent more expensive
No more
Asbestos
Reason lead
How about those Jaguars
You stick your fingers in
You know
Can we just watch
China
Can't make sewage sludge with you
Efficiency in price
Did the Chinese
Is you know
Cereal
When we get from
Like my cornflakes is made in China
My favorite my favorite Chinese cereal is comrade
When count China
I think we didn't get our shipment of Chinese joke
Now apparently not make up our own
Joseph be so many more they be so much better and cheaper
Dr. Richard here is your next quote
It's basically like naming your child Joseph
Stalin that was someone on Twitter making fun of a hundreds of
People who have named their child
After a character in a popular TV show
Who after the last episode probably now regret that
What is the show
Game of Thrones
Yes doctor it's Game of Thrones
If you don't wash your care about Game of Thrones I'm sorry to make your life more miserable than it already is
4 years now
Fans of the show have been rooting for a certain character
Called Kelly
Who everybody thought was
Is young attractive hero wood
Repeat bad guys in
Windermere
Elizabeth
Warren herself in Dorchester
Saying her eyes to the iron throne
With a lesson
For girls everywhere
As it turned out the lesson young girls is that if you wanted to
Seed
Kill everyone
Elizabeth Warren by the way it is
Legitimately once
If you don't care
All the Game of Thrones
Frenzy of Rage
Arguing with each other over whether that was a good thing or a bad thing
But it's a real problem though for the hundreds of P
People whoever the last
Eight or nine years
Have named their baby
Daughters Khalifa
Ordinary sir Roger named after the
This character
And the kids
Is there now like seriously mama why did you need me for
Character who
Turned out to be a ruthless mask
Murderer
It did you ignore the obvious signs that this is where she was heading and all the prior seasons including the dream sequence in
I think that I pay theirs
The solution here
Spelling
Change the middle name
Before
Season 8
Khaleesi before
A bad idea to name your kid after a character
TV series
If you don't know how it's going to turn out
Imagine how other people feel who named their kids
Is after an
Becky on Full House
It is never good idea.
Alright here is your last
Quote
Bill imitating the accent we are now told is believe it or not
Considered to be one of the sexiest in America what is the accent
That is a Boston or New England Act
You're exactly right the Boston accent
It's time to park
Carnal in the Harvard Yard
We're never going to get through this and it's all right
Are you getting beaten up by a bunch of drunk
Bruins fan
And you have this funny feeling in your tummy cuz you know
Boston accent and it is a
Apparently according to a survey of
If social media users
II
Sexiest accent in the country
After the
Texas accent
This is why so many
Lonely men are ordering mail order brides
From Worcester
When they
SpaceX
Do they mean it makes
If you want to stay
In your ear
L&I
We decided
We couldn't let this go unchallenged so we decided that we needed to talk
Wheely 2 the only
Person we knew who
You could really
Let us know
How the Boston Acts
Send at least has worked out for
For him
Toure Mali Asia
Dave Carter
Hey how are you
I'm going to having a lot of fun making fun of my
Yeah we do it all the time usually we don't let you listen
The question for you Ray
Is have you in your life
But having a boss
Have you found it to be very sexy as it had that effect
The people you'd wanted to have that effect on
Fake one for you
Years
I'm losing my voice
And here we work with my brother
Cultivator
Midwestern accent
As a kind of test
REI
We have decided
We've asked you
To read
A couple of romantic lines
From movies
Start with this one
How about this the heart knows
What the heart
Once you want me to say
How about this one
Draw me like one of your French girls Jack
Yeah
Draw me like one of your French girls
My taste
Salivary
Singular
Wow
You know what the hell
You know what that was
Fifty Shades of Grey
Are you still there
Bill how did Richard doing our quiz
Richard did very very well they got them all right
Congratulations.
Coming up a bluff The Listener game with military
Sherry Precision call 1aaa wait wait to play will be back in a minute or
Of wait wait don't tell me
From NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor SimpliSafe Home Security
SimpliSafe believes fear has no place
In a place
Like home
That's why they made a completely wireless home security system
They can be selfish
Installed
In under an hour
Their sensors are built to protect every point of access to your home
Plus SimpliSafe has no long-term con
More than 3 million
People of already Protected Their home
What SimpliSafe
Get free shipping and a 60-day money-back guarantee
SimpliSafe
Dot-com
Slash weight
Itz 1960
White minister is murdered
In Selma Alabama
But no one is
Held to account
More than 50 years later we return to the place where
Call
Allah Allah
And finally solved
White Lies
NPR
New episodes drop
Tell me
The NPR news quiz
We're playing this week with Adam felber Helen Hong and Roy Blount Jr
And here we got at your house that they Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown Chicago
If you
Missed any part of this show or you want to listen again to your favorite part
It's like this part here where I'm talking about we listening to your favor
Ford parts
You just download the wait wait podcast
Last it's the show you love whenever you want to love
Right now though it's time for the wait wait don't tell me Bluff The Listener game call 1aaa tway two-player game in the air High you are on wait wait
Hello hello who's this
Ryan Braun
Charleston West Virginia
West Virginia what are you do there
I'm a lavender farmer
Does
Hard
Scrabble men who mined the lavender in West Virginia
In like baby
Living in lavender
Welcome to the show Ryan
You're going to play our game and what you must try to tell truth
From fiction what the topic bill
We are looking for a few really really good man
Our armed forces are the best in the world of course and we all wish there were you no more Wars and which they could prove it they do.
Straight there
Everyday in
Other way
Are pandas going to tell you about the new
Kind of military achievement we just found out about
Pick the one who's telling the truth and you'll win the wait wait her of your choice in your voice
But first let's hear from Roy Blount Jr
Used to be Army's fault
2 Concord Terrace
So PAC
Or to win hearts and Minds
Obama
Today everyone's fighting for a different objective
Eyeballs
Hats the US Army All American influence our platoon
There's wisecracking Ernie from Brooklyn lyrics
Gus
From Minnesota who can fix anything mechanical is Tonga
She's extreme Punk but she'll come through in a pinch
And Daisy the come-hither
Martial arts Gala
They're all over social media
And this week
As tough on the outside
Sergeant cat
But it we took a big hill
Cover of Us magazine
All American
Platoon gets on the cover of us
Your next story of military Excellence come from Helen Hong
There's a lot of reasons why
People join the Army
Patriotism
Instance or wait
College board game
But never in the
History of the Armed Forces
Anyone join
Because they heard the
Food was amazing
But
That made
Change
In stunning gourmet food news
Prestigious James
Beard award
Oscar award for food
Has been awarded to
Scott Gray
Head chef at
The army
Now mind you mr. Not a fan
Seats for the high-ranking
Shanghai Polo I know
Scott Gray is in charge
Creating Shelf
Stable MRI
Field rat
MRE which
Stands for meals
Is ready to eat
Must have a shelf life
Years
And typically comes in a plastic
Packet which includes a wet nap
Ana tiny
Roll of toilet
Historically described by service
Miss members as
Absolutely disgusting
And
Yuck and honestly I'd rather be shot than happy
E'twaun Moore
All of that changed
This past year
When Scott Gray took the ring
Even the net call
Chicken burritos
Sublime
Raise the food
The New York time
Perfectly tender
And comes
With a side of rich
Smoking moles
Switch
One must
Squeeze out of a class
Exhaust packing
The mule have caused
Such a sensation there's
Talk that
Mr. grey may be up for a
Coveted Michelin
Star
When asked about how he feels about that
Mr. grey responded
Like the tire
The army's winzar beard award
For the Excellence of his MREs
Is your last story of Fighters going far comes
From Adam
It was a clear blue day in Washington
State two years ago when a Navy pilot at any age
Angie growler
With contrails
He drew a large and startlingly accurate
Depiction of male genitalia
Forever After
To be known
The Skype
Well
Now after a two-year investigation the Navy has an
Deed look into what was at the bottom of it
The pilot was The Prodigy elad commanding officers referred to as a
Wizkid
What is Ecuador de Don by the electron
Weapons off
Ewo
In a recorded dialogue that we now know that is so historical that I must
History Bill Kurtis
Korean actor
Noticing the optimum
The ewo said bill
You should totally try to draw
Penis
Dude
That would be so
Funny
After some maneuvering ewo
Going to be a little lopsided
Moments later ecstatically
Simply
Etc one thing complete
They realize that quote
The contrails
Naked in the sky actually
Try to fly a route that scribbled over it
In vain
And now despite their Mighty achievement in aviation
The two perpetrators
Sky phallus have been
Discharged
All right here your three choices of milk
Military excellence
From Roy Blount Jr
The US All American influencer
Splatoon getting on the cover of us
Going to Helen Hall in the guy who comes up with the recipes for MREs winning or precision
Beard Awards
For his cooking
Anthem
Adam felber the impressive details
I've had the Great
Sky phallus
The 2017 was created
In the Skies over Washington
Which of these is the real story of military
I got to go with the sky penis
Alright your choice plan is Adam story to find out the correct answer we spoke to a reporter covering
The real story
Thorne 2017 two Navy aviators to a giant Sky penis
Seaside Washington State
That was
Jeff
Zillow website
I seen the report her with navy times talking about a
Of course the great Sky penis
And if people are listening with your children right now
Please address
Your complaints
Cast of the US Navy
Congratulations Ryan
You got it right
You want a point for Adam and Eve
Kratom
Round of Applause
Surprise the voice of your choice on your voicemail congratulations
Alright thank you take care
And now the game more interesting people answer questions about things that simply don't interest them
What are those popular movie franchises
Does last few years has
Has been the John Wick
Saga in which Keanu Reeves plays a sad assassin
Was forced to shoot lots of
People with Kung Fu
When he's worn out from that he stays in a mysterious hole
Tell it is greeted by the elegants
Concierge named
Sharon that's
Lance Reddick
The wire will remember the
Daniel's or maybe they'll remember
For his roles in Lost
Lance Reddick welcome to wait wait don't tell
Let's just talk about these movie
Movie so these movies
The first one came out in 2014
Kateri plays an assassin okay
But it turns out there's this
Stream Society of other assassins in Criminal
And among other things they have this hotel where they can all stay
And you are the
Concierge
Yes NM when they
Candy with a spark
What did they tell you about this hotel in this guy
I was just
I tend to play authority figures that talk a lot
Yes
You are all I have to say you have
Again being family The Wire
Pretty intimidating presence
When you want to
Do you use that in real life like when your kids are misbehaving
That never works no
The shame
Don't talk about John Wick so you play this guy I noticed in the first two movies
First of all
How come you your character always has to end up looking after John Wicks dog
That doesn't seem right to me
People ask me this
What is
Karen
Accent
I think it is
Smooth characters very scared and you don't really
Say much but you're
It's very like
Oh this
I have to ask you because
Is Keanu Reeves
Has become such an icon
Over the years
For kind of just like laconic
Silence
We all think of like sad Keanu
Is that what it's really like in the satyrs he likes like
Costly joking around
She's one of the most
I'm going to tell you that I've heard this I know people that work with him
A generous actor went Ramsey works with people
But his interaction
With almost everybody he meets all the other actor
Christmas movie
Killed
I'm wondering like I would like oh let's say the Ninja
Just hey guys
We'll work together and
And when I stab you in the I just want you to know I really was
He was very kind
He's very kind
You stickers.
The Departed movie
It's basically
He kill people but the reason he killed people
The reason to kill people in the beginning of the first movie the bad guys kill it
Puppy
Just pretty traumatic
Nobody cares about that
Puppy
Brittonfield Greyjoy who we all know is a loser shows up and kills it
So in the movie at the end of the first movie he then gets a dog
And then at the beginning of the second movie the first thing he does is it gives the dog
Talk to you
And I say no
However
So like there's this dog and the dog has live now
To the second movie now the third movie
Oh I saw John Wick
It's really great it's even better than the last one and they say is the dog okay
Yeah because it turns out that you can do a movie and watch like literally
80 people are murdered
And all people care about is the dog
The moment if it came down to you and your character and the dog people be rooting for the dog
Unfortunately
Tonight and if the dog doesn't make
Go see John Wick 3
The dog is fine
There's nothing to worry about
Lance Reddick it is a pleasure to talk to you after being a fan for so long but we have invited you here to play a game we're calling
Anything you need
As we were discussing in the John Wick filmed you play this hotel concierge
Always at
Disposal
The cast their request for a little unusual
But we wanted to ask you about the concierge's in real life who have it much harder be
Instead of Assassins
They're dealing
With Rich
Answer to interview questions about real word concierge
Concierge and the problems they solve
You win a prize one of my listeners Bill who is Lance Reddick
Playing for
Lucy bardessono Baton Rouge Louisiana
All right
The concierge at the fancy
Carlyle Hotel
In New York
Did what
Once for a guest pampered pet
Stop
A arrange for squirrels
To be released in
In front of it on a walk in Central Park
Target Field
The Thrill of the hunt
Be imported
Sod and grass onto the
The floor of the room so it can join
An outdoor
Pee without going Outdoors
Orsi ordered the dog a custom cooked
Steak from Japan
In a private jet
So it would arrive
Warm
Wow
That's a tough one
That was actually the sod and grass in the room
Dog outside
But you didn't want the dog.
Pitter-patter something
Into the concierge
Rock the lawn to the dog
Concierge at the Ritz-Carlton Cancun was able to help guests enjoy his trip to
The beat by doing which of these
Hey
Blotting out the
Sun
With a 300-foot long shade so he wouldn't get a sunburn
Becoming the waves with the Giant
Boom so we can enjoy his swim
Orsi's covering the beach
With carpet so we didn't get sand in his toes
I'm going to give you a hint this this guy apparently had something in common
Name of the dog in the prior Quest
Sensitive toes
Sometimes concierge's have to say no
As when a guest at a safari Lodge
Did Africa ask for what
A a lion to walk up to his girlfriend
With the engagement ring around his neck
Be a giraffe ride
Or see a chance to hunt the most dangerous
This game
Man
Wow
The lion is right.
The lion to walk up to the girlfriend it would be very brief engagement
Congratulations
And definitely keep very very quiet and I listen to the max challenge
From NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Custom ink
I want you to know about the belongingness
Hypothesis
It sounds made up but is absolutely real
The hold that a sense of belonging has a positive impact on your emotions and the way
You think
One thing that can improve your sense of belonging
Is matching custom gear from CustomInk
They're easy to use website provides great design resources and hundreds of products
Build belonging with your groups
Do custom gear
For full details and 10% off your next order go to customink.com
Slash weight
A lot of people are excited that I mentioned on the air yesterday that I'll be on fresh air
With Terry Gross on NPR
It happened
I finally got the interview Howard Stern
There was so much
To talk about
The two-parter
You can listen on the
Fresh air pod
This is wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Kurtis we're playing this week with Adam felber Roy blunt
Helen Hong in the ear
At the Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown
Time Chicago
Reminder
The game of Limerick
You rhyme
Or you die
Wait wait
That's one 889-2489
24 right now
Answer some more questions
From this
Aer Lingus the Irish Airline
Has offered a new perk for upscale pass
Only four times
The normal ticket price
They guarantee you is
With what
A quiet
Suitemate
No even better
Exactly right
For only four times the normal price of a ticket
Hang on Express
It's a four times the price
Do you get a seat guaranteed to get it
An aisle or window seat
Guaranteed
No one in the middle seat in and out Aer Lingus ofcourse
Is the only airline with its own definition
Urban
But they're trying
Airlines doing short hops all over Europe
So they've offered this thing
4 times the price to get in
Nobody in the middle
A little over half price
Too dumb to realize that for only twice the price of
The standard
You can buy the seat next to you
It's very kind of you
Thank you thank you very much
Adam linguists have Trace
The evolution of modern languages backed
UPS Store time
And it turns out
There's one word that hasn't changed at all
8000 years
So
If you were able to go back in time and meet somebody who spoke
The proto-indo-european language
You can happily talk to each other about what
One word
Guys named John
No
Poop no
Very very very few words have survived the Millennia without being
Change since
Some way to different language
Is this one of course
Has
But you would have to mind the big link
Locks
Lock
What
Roblox
Hazmat salmon
Is there a smoked salmon
Thousand Years you'll be one
Word
Hasnat
Look for the salmon that they locked
Rite Aid thousand years ago
Hieroglyph
Had invented
They had the bagels at that time it was before the invention
Are the wheels of the bagels world
Square
Now we know this because like I said the word is the same in all languages that have descended from this
Proto-indo-european language
Which most of our life
You just come
So if the theory about locks is right
That means that Jews
Existed back
So we can assume proto-indo-european was mostly used to complain
Who invented fire did you have to make it so hot
Coming up it's lightning fill in the blank the first is the game where you have to listen
For the ride if you like to play on air
Call the leave a message at 1 AAA wait wait
That's 18889
Berkeley contact us link on our website wait wait. Npr.org
Do you can find out about attending our weekly live shows right here at the
Bank Auditorium
Chicago
Arab coming shows June 27th at the Mann Center in Philadelphia
Very first show The Beautiful Blossom Music Center
Located within Cuyahoga National Park
In Ohio
July 18th
Wow very high you are
Who's there
Theresa Apple
Chileno Pittsfield other in Western
How far from Lennox or sometimes we do I show what do you do there
I am
In the operating room
Ok
And My Girls High School cross country
Oh good for you
Therapist
I am very exciting but the obligation to be extremely healthy and fit yourself doing all those things
Baidu
And I am
Walter is a welcome to the show Bill Kurtis is going to be
3 News related limericks for the last word or phrase missing for me
If you can fill in that last word or phrase correctly on
Who were the members will be with
Ready to play
Let's do it here is your first one
Tell my drivers not starting a riot
He keeps talking about
His new diet
But I don't want to talk
I might get out and walk
I'll pay more
If the driver stays
Yes
Uber
You know that they're now offering quiet mode with the Press of a button when you order the car
You can let your driver know you'd rather not talk
All right it's all part of Uber's lifelong mission of making their customers rides more enjoyable
And making their drivers feel more and more like ghost
Oh my God I
Cannot wait
You should know how I know that it's only available with Uber black
That's the high-end expensive limo option
And if you don't want quiet never fear if
Do you prefer customers can also select a talkative preference
But that
Do you need to do this
You don't need to do this
It's all you need to do is get into the car
And say something like
Like so have I ever told you about the miracle of dianetics
Your driver will not talk to you
Here is your neck slimmer
Something bites
Can't be scratched
Text with Muirhead shrugs
Their nest
Fred's
Snug
It made
Pterodactyl
Throw out their mattresses
Does dinosaurs may have had
Bed bugs and yes it's true that dinosaurs
Had bed bugs really surprising thing is that dinosaurs
Had been
A new study based on
15 years of research has found the bed bugs originated 100
Million
Years ago
Just after the appearance of the first-ever best Wes
This means at Millenia
Mall at Millenia before humans walk the earth there other species that never ever changed
Easter sheets
Do bed bugs probably say we used to have
Dinosaur
All right
Here is your last
Limerick
Famous Pawn
Cowboys heart
Switch for cars
Remains found
Aston Martin will build
A new car
Captured film
They're remaking the car from
You
Oggi's good James Bond
For a limited time
You can purchase any
Exact replica of James Bond Aston Martin
Car from the movie goldfish
All the cool gadgets
Fermat movie
Rotating lights
Two plates extendable battering ram
Smoke screen device
It even comes with a removable rear facing car seat
James Bond Jr
Not for this black 3.5
Spies cars amazing it
It's great
It's also not street legal
You can't have it towed to a parking lot and driving around there
And the drivers will need to spend 30 hours with a learner's permit to kill before they get their life
I can't remember when
I can remember when cocaine meant you had too much
Yeah
Everything lady from Pittsfield
Congratulations
Congratulations well done
Bye-bye
Support for this podcast
After the following
Message comes from MailChimp
So you want to grow your business
Now what
Male chimps all-in-one marketing Platte
That's what
It has all the marketing stuff you need all in one place
So you can save time and money
L powered by a marketing CRM so yuan
Collect organize and understand your audience data
All to help you Market
Getsmarter and Grove
Learn more
DACA
Support also comes from
VRBO
Finding the perfect vacation home is hard
You start off looking for a beach house big enough for sex and wind up watching videos of Surfing dogs
VRBO does the hard work
For you
Whatever your budget or what you want from the home a Yard Grill even a private pool verbose got you covered
Download the VRBO app
VRBO to discover everything from condos and cabins
The Villas
Castles
LED VRBO find a home
That matches you
Now on to our final game lightning fill in the blank each of our players we
We have 60 seconds image
The answer is many fill in the blank
Is he or she can
The correct answer is
Bill can you give us
Adam leads with four Helena has three Roy has one
Broiler in third-place Europe first the clock will start when I begin your first Quest
It's on the blank
On Wednesday the governor of blank
Sign of the nation
The most restrictive abortion ban
Alabama right on Monday attorney general Bill Barr acai
Find a prosecutor
Look into the origins of the blanket
Russian
Yeah Usher
Holiday this weekend Reuters poll
Show blank had a commanding lead over all other democratic
The candidates for
Joe Biden yes
On Tuesday the National Labor
Relations Board concluded that blank drivers work
Contractors and not
Employees
Uber ride
A British woman was diagnosed with a sleeve
Disorder this week
After she unknowingly black
While she was sleeping
Should call the doctor
No she had bought
A full size basketball court
Best known for his work in The Carol Burnett Show comedian blank passed away at the age of 85
This week kids in Ohio or excited to hear they be starting their summer vacation early after blank was found inside their school
Dynamite
No
Enrich
Uranium John's Corner Middle School outside of Cleveland will be closed for at least 3 months after
Different types of nuclear material is found in the
Most of the middle
School students are excited
Extra time off except for one kid
Who's really upset
The time snitch ruined his chances of absolutely dominating this year's science fair
Bill how did Roy do in Ark
10 more points
Is a total of 11 right now
And he is in the lead
All right
Hurry up on a Tuesday the White House denied a Judiciary Committee
Request for documents related to the
Yes on Wednesday the US pulled all non-essential
Embassy staff out of Iraq
Over fears of s
Escalating tension
Jeans with bling
This week San Francisco became the first city to
YouTube and blank
Technology
Official record
Right on Monday President Trump welcome the far-right
Prime minister of blank to the White House
Hungry yes this week Russian Bots Wiki
Accused of rigging the result of blank
The election in Florida no a children singing contest called The Voice
On Monday actress blank plead guilty to her role in the college bribery scheme
William age
Macy's
Name is
This is nice
No Felicity Huffman this week a couple proposal went viral after the woman posted a picture of him gate
Ring
Which was blank
Swallowed by a
Will know her engagement ring
Was made from human hair
Man presented the inch wide band of hair to his girlfriend this week presumably because he was
Wanted to excitedly tell his friend
She said no
Fortunately the hair was his and not that it was Prior victim
The thrilled woman posted pictures of the Ring online
Reaction of the mix but on the plus side she doesn't have to worry about losing her ring in the shower
Entrapment
Spell how did the Helen do an AR quiz
Which means she is
Tied with Roy and how many hanged how many than
Does Adam need to LEAP ahead of them and win
The Wok in the park
42 Williams
Write Adam this is for the game
Fill in the blank on Thursday President Trump unveiled a new program
Proposing a merit-based policy on blank
Immigration
After being subpoenaed to appear before the Senate intelligence
Blank Junior High Creed
Provide limited testimony
This week New York mayor blank announced his plans
Delouse the Democratic nomination
On Monday the Supreme Court rule that an antitrust lawsuit against blank could produce
Proceed Apple write a man in Florida arrested for indecent
Exposure explained to police that he was just planking
Sunning himself he was practicing basketball and being naked quote enhance is he
Set skill level not under a new measure parents and wash
Washington State can no longer claim a personal exemption to prevent their children from getting the blank facts
Middle right on Monday it was revealed the former president blank was
Recovering from a broken hip
British man
Passport two years ago was shocked this week when it received blank
Another passport
He was shocked to receive a thank you note for
The kid who has been using it as a fake ID all the
Eminem Joe hunter lost
Lost passport right before a big trip
And don't he got an emergency replacement he never knew what happened to his original
Until this week
When you got a note from a guy saying hey I just turned legal
So I don't need your passport anymore would you like it back
It's safe to say this is the best possible version of the hey I've been using your property to commit crime story
Definitely better than hey I'm all done serial killing
Do you need your head Clippers back
Will did Adam do well enough to win
Yes
Cartier
Congratulations
Smattering
NASCAR
Panelist Now That Game of Thrones is coming to an end what will HBO's
Next big hit show B
Thank you to stock and Ledger in downtown
Chicago for feeding us today
Wait wait don't tell me on WBEZ
Chicago association with urgent haircut production
Doug Berman
Overlord
Are public address announcers Paul Friedman our house manager is Tyler green
Assisted by Simon Tran and Marydel Delaware what group is Bethany
This week we are forced
It's a sad goodbye to two wonderful
Intern Alex McCullen and Rachel klepper known as the Wonder Twins but only
Incel
Because seriously you look nothing alike guys Alex
You are unstoppable when we sent you an admission
We should have asked you to get paper the holy grail and you would have found
And Rachel we can't thank you enough for creating order within our chaos and we hope
We prepared you for your next job although we have to warn you they will not be nearly as many donor
BJ leiderman composed our team our program has produced by Jennifer Mills miles dornbos and Lillian
Peter Quinn
Chattanooga directions from Lord of white hair business and off managers Colin Miller
Production coordinators Robert Newhouse
Any executive producer of wait wait don't tell me
Is Mike Danforth
Big
Show Low Junior
Another hard-hitting
Short titled
City specific
Series from David Simon
It's called
Set in Miami in the near future
When the water is up
Did everyone leave
Helen Hall
A new series entitled
White
People in old timey cost
Words with dragon
Adam felber
What's dystopia word selfish Warlords
Schemer struggle to rule the remnants of a Dying World
Yes they're launching a Nightly News show
Right here on white white.
This
Is NPR
Support frame
NPR comes from investor.gov
Presenting this mess
When it comes to invest
We all have Quest
And investor.gov
Pass answer
If you're free resource
For tools tips and information
Sing about invest
Before you invest
Investor.gov