Support for this podcast
Send the following message
Did come from
Struggling to find a purpose
Vacation home
VRBO does the hard work for
Matching you to the perfect place to stay
Every time
Download VRBO
Let Virgo find a home
That matches
From NPR
Easy Chicago
BMV R news
News quiz
Hey
Forget the Infinity Stones
Listen to my Infinity tongue
And here's your host at the Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown Chicago Peter
Psycho
Later on we'll be talking to Laird Hamilton legendary Surfer fitness model lifestyle and exercise guru
Basically his job
Is to be cooler
Then you
But trust me wanted to commemorate
The third anniversary of one of the greatest events
CNN
NPR history
On April 28th
Take your child to work day
A child reached out
An adorable little finger push the button
And took NPR off the air
During Morning Edition
And it sounded
A little bit like that
Jeffrey katzenberg will stay behind a few marks to work on
That silence lasted for 73 seconds
In the radio business call
Forever
But due to the popular response to this event NPR has created a new corporate holiday which we celebrated
This past week
Leave your damn child at home day
Anyway we really want to hear your voice
I so give us a call the number is 10008 wait wait
That's one 889-2489
24 now that's welcome our first a listener contesta
How you are on wait wait don't tell me
Hi how is it
How are you I'm good who's this
This is me
You keep from Irvington New York
Irvington New York so what are you doing
I'm a musician
Are you reeling
How do you make a living doing that cuz I know that's hard to
Well you know me
Making a living as sort of a
Kind of a big stretch
U2 r-panel first of a comedian currently on
Tour with Dana Gould and
Show with two heads
Info Dana google.com Bobcat Goldthwait
Natural host of The Daily podcast
Tbtl in the public radio variety show Livewire which will be back at the Alberta Rose Theater
In Portland on May 16th
Burbank
Who sang Miyuki music and finally a comedian
Cancion
Santa Rosa California May 18th at the Luther Burbank Center for the Arts
And in st. Paul Minnesota on June 7th at the Fitzgerald theater
You can hear her on the podcast nobody listens to Paula Poundstone
It's Paula Poundstone
Welcome to the show you know how this works you going to play who's Bill this time Bill Kurtis right here
Going to recreate for you three quotations from the
The week's news your job correctly
Identify and explain two of them do that you win our prize the voice of anyone you may like
Call Michelle
On your voicemail ready to play
Pronounce
From the president
Does the United State
Welcome to the race
Sleepy Joe
That was a present
In his own way welcoming somebody who finally announced he was running for president
Who is it
Mr. Joe Biden
Actor just flirting with a presidential run you know
Coming up behind it rubbing at shoulders
Joe Biden announced on Thursday
He is entering a race
With eight
Declared women candidates at a time when Democrats are obsessed
With the rampant sexism
In the opening line of his
Minimale was
Quote America is an idea based on the founding principle
All
Men
Are created
Equal
Panettone ways
Vice President Biden just still has the
A video
What you said you know when I was a kid we used to call these
Takis
And he presented himself
Assertive is an Everyman candidate it doesn't matter what race
Is a gender or sexuality you are
Joe Biden
Want to smell your hair
Did you see the non-endorsement that Obama release know what are you doing
It was just
Blake
I hear my good friend Joe Biden wants to
3 president
Ricky was really non-committal it was like it was
Like if your friend asks you to come over to like their candle party
Bright like you have to go but you really want to leave with him
Maximum of
Two candles
What the problem is I mean
His connection to Obama is his primary selling point he was
Of course
Obama's vice president for 8 years
And people don't like Obama
The Democratic Party
Two people might vote for him this
History people will vote for him
For the same reason you invite somebody you don't really like
To your party cuz you hoped
He'll bring his hot
Like
Mayor Pete buttigieg is a millennial
Biden cases
Cuz he is a thousand years old
If you check the age of his hair plugs
Hugs and the age of
His teeth
The average of his body part
Which is like $0.30 or something
Just so many
Piano
I'm thinking maybe
I don't know maybe the runoff
Should be like Red Rover Red Rover
Or maybe maybe something more akin to the Hunger Games
Arm numb
Alright thank you next quote
Is from game show Legend Ken Jennings
I don't feel like enough credit for making small sensible wages
Which helped the show with it
Enterprise budget
Mr. Jennings was responding to the
Historic
Winning run of James holzhauer the current champion of what game show
Jeopardy
Jeopardy everybody is calling Jay
James holzhauer a genius
He's crazy method
Go for the questions worth the most money
Brighten citic choosing your the first one that topic
Five hundred bucks
His genius strategy is basically the
The same one is Steph Curry
Do the thing that gets more points
Do you know I was on Jeopardy one
A charity
Had to give money back to Jeopardy
Away from Alien Children
Game show in Australia where
I was tanking so I just started
Slapping the other
Buzzard
Yeah I can see what I was on the camera or not and I
Hit the button
Am I the only panelist who has not been on the game show
I have sometimes
He's gotten home early and watch
Jeopardy
But then rewound it on the DVR and then re-watch.
With my wife so I seem like
Like really smart
People are criticizing this guy
Is 2 good
He's taking all the fun out of Jeopardy
He's just going to win he's showing off in the David biggest
He calculated out the right wager so that he
His total when he won
The tribute to his daughter's birth
It all of the bitter nerd
Watching him said oh great
He had sex
Wants to
Alright baby here is your last
Quote
You'd be well advised to bandage your expectation in the sand
Give it its 3 hour plus
Runtime
Your fluid
That was NPR's own Glen Weldon giving some advice
Two people going to see what big movie this
Going to see The Avengers endgame
You even got the chapter
After title right now
Remember at the end of last year's Avengers Infinity War happen
Superheroes dried up and blew away
The sequel with takes place five years later is about the survivors coping with the fact
It superhero dust
Highly allergenic
Go to this is a film that finally brings all the Beloved, Carrick
Pictures together Iron Man
Captain America
Spider-Man
The Hulk Snoopy
Garfield
The guy from the mr. Yuk stickers
In the cast of Family Circus
Double to find the little one cuz you'll see a little broken line
The ghost of Grandpa
You guys excited
ABC this
Only if it starts with Banos
Snorting the other
Doing lines of Spider-Man
All right
I will tell you this
This thing this is actually true
That there is an active movie so long as you heard some people are
Concerned about
Let me know when you can take a bath
There is an app
That you can download in you
Press the A Button
When the movie start
And it will alert
At Good Times to go to the bathroom
Now I have a new reason to hate other
People in the movie theater
Exactly
We've already been
Discouraging is
3 years
An hour encouragement
Exactly what this is
Movie theater
In the movie
You're an actor in it and then your thing comes up and it says Hey Now is it
Bill how did Miyuki do on AR quiz
Lioki
Cut his way through our questions like it
Thank you so much for playing bye bye
Right now panel time for you to answer some questions about this week's
Paula we got a bargain
Animal lovers like you
Rare Bird
The cassowary
Auctioned off
Florida seabirds
Previous owner no longer
Can care for the bird
Why
Does bird kill that that's exactly right the cassowary
Is a flightless but apparently not murder less
Bird
It was described by the Florida medical examiner and this is real as having quote no sense
Weeks ago there were no Witnesses but neighbors reported hearing
Bring the bird saying
Safe flight list again
I freaking dare you
Now you probably don't know what that's where he looks like Richard imagine assault
A smaller
Where is an ostrich
This one
Can jump
Up to seven feet in the air
It is a 4 inch long
Razor sharp Talon on
Cloth and buries its head in the sand it comes back
Holding a gun
Despite everything in the cassowary is castor oil make a great pet
For a while
Mother's Day
Is coming
Infrastructure week finally and I'd love to listen to play will be back in a minute
Woodmore what they don't tell me from NPR
Support for this podcast
And the following message come from Stanford children
What are the scariest thing
Mom look
Because the next word
Words are usually
Billy can fly
Or Joey riding the dog
Or a crayon stuck in Valerie's nose
Here's something you might want
With over 20
Pediatric office
Stanford.
Jen's are all over the bay are
Not just in Palo Alto
Find a Stanford PDF
At stanfordchildrens.org
This weekend rough translation
I found
This crazy thing
The word in French
Ghost Rider
Is
Francis version
Oh I'm a screw like one
That story this week on rough translation
Take a listen
From NPR and WBEZ Chicago this is
Wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Kurtis and we are playing this week with Luke
Burbank Paula Poundstone
Cat Goldthwait
And here is your host
City Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown
Chicago PD
Thank you girl right now it's time for the
Bluff The Listener game called 1-aaa tway two-player game in the
Hi you are on wait wait don't tell me
Hi this is
Lacey Smith from San Antonio Texas San Antonio
I heard it but it was one thing to experience
It's wonderful with lots of culture and lots
Wonderful place
Places to eat
Yeah what are you do there
I am a event planner and a stay-at-home mom I have an 11 year old and
Three-and-a-half-year-old triplets
Wow
Wow yeah
Urine event planner professionally so do people expect that your kids birthday parties are just going to be absolutely
To be fabulous
Caterers in Dallas
Some stuff like that
I sure hope not I'm the cheapest Mom there is
What is it's great to have you in this you're going to play our game and what you must try to tell truth from
Fiction
What's the topic bill
Our crumbling infrastructure to the rescue
Is it a terrible you want to jump off a bridge cuz you're depressed about our nation's infrastructure but you can't find a bridge that's
Safe enough
This week though bad infrastructure did good our parents are just about to pick the one is telling you the truth in the winter
Surprise await waiter app
Of your choice on your voice
Are you ready to play
Yes sir
My first let's hear from
Luke Burbank
McMasters Dam located on the Columbia River near Umatilla Oregon
Has certainly seen better days
A series of cracks
Can fissures that work
Years overdue for repair
Ruptured last month
Creating one long horizontal
Gash in the dam
Through which a steady wave of water has
I've been gushing day and night
In call the
Trophy by the army
Army Corps of Engineers
A disaster by local farmers
And totally Epic
Buy Surfer magazine
Recently declared the wave
The sickest
Surf spot in America
Because it turns out the gushing water forms
The perfectly tube-like barrel of water
That is becomes the destination
For serious Surfers from around the world
People like twenty-four-year-old chasen Bradford from Vallejo California
We tried to describe the wave to a can
Infused Wall Street
Journal reporter
Bra it's like
You got the best barrels ever dude
Just drop in and whoop how you smack the lip and you get
Pitted so pitted you know
The reporter did not know
But eventually got to his real question
Asking Bradford if you felt nervous surfing in front of a dam that could burst at any moment and barium under 1.3 million acre
Acre feet of water
Bradford responded by pulling up a shirt
Exposing a Hakuna Matata tattoo
It means no worries for the rest of your days
He added without irony
What time is Umatilla is enjoying me
Research and tourism actually sees that they long-term Boon to the local economy
Since once the dam does burst
The three local funeral homes
Will be doing brisk business dealing with Jason and his buddies for the foreseeable future
Surfers taking advantage of a leaking Dam on the Columbia River your next story from the bridge and tunnel crowd
Comes from
Poundstone
Paramedics in Omaha Nebraska we're rushing a man to the hospital
Fearing for his life
His heart was racing
200 beats a minute
Which could mean imminent heart attack or heart failure
Then Fortune
For him the ambulance hit a pothole
Which Jordan to page
Patient so hard
His heart Brigade
It's normal rhythm
Dr. Andrew Gold Swag
The Nebraska medicine help
The network said of the manse
Quotes
One way to treat that is with an electrical shock
Classically
See it on television the paddle
Clear and the big jolt
Turns out you can do that with a pothole
When news of this gets out Philadelphia
Historic Cabo
Cobblestone paver
Streets will be jammed
With car is filled with drivers and passengers with racing
This hard killing
Pothole
It's made frame any move towards a nymph
Infrastructure bill as an assault on Healthcare in
On the other hand it could lead
To be unloaded
Cardiology
Just secretly filling potholes in the dead of night
A pothole in Omaha save the man's life when is an ambulance hits it and it
Fixes
His heart rate
Your last story of Decay being okay
Comes from
Bobcat Goldthwait
The Tiny Town of Cresco Iowa is enduring what might be legitimately
He called politely a poop storm
Because of recent Mass
Flooding the centuries-old sewer system has been overwhelmed
And the drains are acting in reverse
Causing a Townline prep test
Homeowners
Installed into the bathrooms and discovered that they
Sinks bath
Toilets have become Bellagio like dancing Fountains of waste
A petition is already gathered 1200
Signatures almost half the population
To change the town's motto to Cresco Iowa
Even worse than before
One resident who will not be signing the petition.
Situation is a miracle quote
Like Jesus
Concept
Tank backing up
She walked in her bathroom
This week to find her
Long lost
Engagement ring at appeared right there on the floor
I can only hope it came from the sink
She said that one of these three things happen
Is it because of a failing Dam a small town of the Columbia river is now a tourist spot
Being
Overwhelmed with happy
Happy Surfers that's from Luke from Paula a pothole
Save the man's life is the ambulance hits
And fixes his heart rate
Are from Bobcat a poop storm in Iowa
Miraculously returns
A woman's
Wedding ring from the deck
Which of these are the real story
Of an infrastructure failure being a sec
Well I love
Paula and I'm going to go with her story of the
You can go tell the story of the pothole in Omaha
Ring the correct answer we spoke to a reporter who covered it
While en route to the hospital they hit a pothole and the jolt returns got patients heart rate back to normal
There you go that was Kelsey Stewart she's a reporter for the Omaha World-Herald
Congratulations Lacey you got it right
Yonder point for Paula of course
You have won our prize the voice of your choice on your voicemail
Thank you so much for playing again congratulations
Thank you so much thank you take care
And now the game where talented people are confronted with a
The challenge that requires no Talent at all
Call not my job
Laird Hamilton is the most
Famous surfer who's never won a surfing competition
And he's never won one because he's never
Entered one
Instead he spends his time doing remarkable things like setting the record
For the biggest wave
Eversor
He has a new book out called life writer
We are pleased to welcome him now we're Hamilton welcome to wait wait don't tell me
I wanted to check that too cuz if somebody wouldn't somebody said your name as I can but it turns out
You've never actually enter to surfing,
Yeah I I tripped it a couple when I was a kid when there was a t-shirt
For the prize but it soon as it
Money came into it it seemed like that changed the Dynamics and I
I opted to not participate
We understand that it's
It's not surprising you spent your life on the water cuz you were actually born in water
Using a bathysphere which was actually like almost like a hairdressers vacuum
Went over my mother's stomach and relieve the pressure on the
On the optimum
Birth in a tub but I did have a unique birthing process was it put that way
Did you think that ended up sort of steering the course of your life
Or I would like to see it didn't affect me but other people disagree
Basic question what is your job Laird Hamilton
Innovator I like Innovation and
As an athlete
Subsidize my surfing with
A lot of different things
Leonard when you serve
Like for a living
How do they know to do that I mean
Your guy with a
Beach and there's a wave
Surfeit
Somebody runs over and
Gives you a check
No you're you'd write a giant wave somebody takes a picture they put it on the cover of National Geographic and then
Can a company says you know we love to give you some money in
And then try to get on National Geographic again
Make it clear to Paul everybody else that actually happen
Bright
So what what do you think in your estimation is sort of the craziest or riskiest
Maybe the most foolish thing you've ever done
You know there's a long list we don't have enough time but
You know I've done some crazy paddles between
Highlands II paddle from Corsica to Italy one time and
And we were kind of lost at night
In the middle of the Mediterranean Inn
You know I've had some other I've been those in Russia and I fell through Glacier when I was
Helicopter snowboarding into military helicopters
You got a ride you got to ride on a Russian military
Helicopter
Yeah to a glacier in Russia
And then you went snowboarding down the glacier
Yeah but I fell in I fell through a cornice
Sudan Iowa
Biking behind
One of my partners
You don't have been in the wrong you know a couple feet over I might not
So was it hard to get the Russian military to let you do that or they were like Laird Hamilton to be loved your short
It was more like
You know money for vodka
There's a couple bullet holes in it in the bird in
Do you know now you still got it
There's a pilot
He was whining
Are you paid with vodka
The very low bar it's refreshing to hear an American that it has no problem admitting that the rush
Yeah
Falling through a glacier and you're in a big hole in the ice
Or you are somewhere between Corsica and Italy on a paddleboard or a surfboard on that particular
Standing there in a board in the middle of the ocean
It's dark you don't know where you are
Has there ever been a point where you said oh man I screwed this up now or do you just not
Ever like losing faith
Really really
Here I am again
You're somebody other people admire so much and I'm just wondering if you ever found yourself in a moment
Man I wish I'd become a CPA like Mom wanted
Snowboard glitch
But the most terrifying thing
Is
Being asleep
EPA
Why I understand that one of the things that you're doing is you have a really rigorous
I don't know
Exercise program is not
Sufficient rhytids
It's kind of a training program
You offer to people
Stands for
Exploring Performance training but it it really is a lifestyle program
It's really about recovery move and breathe
I don't know how accurate this is but somebody told me oh yes
That's the program where you have to go underwater and Lyft
Weights while holding your
Darius Darius. Part
Recovery in the nuts
You're just killing you like a normal way program might make you go to the gym and lift weights but you because you're more generous to people make some cold water
Yes actually figured
Hold Us Down and we do a lot of explosive
Jumping
It's the Hold You Down
In the bottom of the pool
Yes
How many clients have
Are you lost
None that we know of but I haven't looked in the pool today
Willard Hamilton it is a pleasure to talk to you
We've invited you here today
To play a game we're calling
Championship
Channel surf
You of course are big wave surfer but from everything you know you're probably not very good
America
His favorite kind of surfing
Channel surfing
Weird ask you three questions about terrible moments in television history if you ask
Three questions correctly it was a prize from one of our listeners
The Voice update
Your choice on their answering machine
Phil
Who is Laird Hamilton playing for
Evan Hansen
Princeton New Jersey
And they've got a big surf seen there
I'm sure he's all right here we go
First question there was once a
Failed cable channel called Genesis
Storytime didn't last very long
It was created just
For kids
What programming
Did Genesis
Storytime offer
Was it a
It re-enacted other cable TV shows like this
Sopranos in Homeland
But with puppets
And clean language
Be it was just a series of still images of pages
Some children's books
So that a parent could sit and read
TV to their kid
Or see if
Deported to teach
Kids quotes
Real life skills
Such as asking people out on dates
Cures for hangovers
You're right Laird you nailed that very weird idea
You turn it on there be a page of a kids picture book you'd read the page and after a short. Of time
Switch to the next page
Can you read that page
Didn't last long
All right
Netflix
Next question there are some shows that have come and gone
Very very quickly
As in which of these
Which of these shows
The. Only 2 days
Disappear
Fox's who's your daddy
A game show in which an adult have been given up for adoption
Guesses which of the 25 men
On the set
Is their father
Being
PBS is
Trigonometry teaching educational comedy show
Cosine fell
Or cnbc's crossover experiment Law and Order and frayser
I have to go with B again to go to the trigonometry teaching educational comedy show
Co Seinfeld
What's the deal with hypotenuse
If you guessed right you got $100,000 at which point your dad
Suddenly took an interest in you again
All right last question if you if you sit there and channel surf long enough you'll end up on the Home Shopping Channel
Yeah that can make sometimes or unexpectedly memorable
Viewing which of these actually happened on the
Home shopping
Was it at
After a host whack the blade of a samurai sword
The counter
The blade snapped and stabbed him in the chest
Be a man showed up a photo of a moth taken by the camera he was selling but then for a full minute referred to them off as a horse
Or see a woman selling jumper cables decided to show what happens when you switch the cables on the car battery
Setting the battery on fire
I'm excited I'm going to Samurai
You're right but then again all of them really happened
Home Shopping Channel
They all could have but somehow I just kind of like the
Yeah me too I have to say
Out of out of the three of them at someone that I would be most likely to do so yeah
Bill how to learn Hamilton daughter quiz
Laird Hamilton is a legend of Surfing and many
Many other things his new book
Life Rider
He's out now
Laird Hamilton thank you so much for joining us on wait wait don't tell me a pleasure to talk to you
It just a minute Bill ties the knot and brings all his baggage of The Listener Olympic Channel
Will be back in a minute
From NPR
Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Duckhorn Vineyards
Napa Calif
Founded by Dan and Margaret Duckhorn
Born in 1970
Duckhorn Vineyard
This has been cracked
Classic wines
Ants with a sentence
Place for more than
With seven Estate Vineyards located throughout the map
The winery produces vintage
Cabernet
Sauvignon blanc and Chardonnay
All showcasing the diversity of wine
Learn more
Duckhorn. Com
NPR
Hey there it's Joshua Johnson the host of 1A
Off in the news
Is full of hot takes
Snappy comebacks
Put on the Friday news Roundup we take
The time to go deep
With guess who know the big stories inside out
Catch the Friday news Roundup in the 1A podcast
On the NPR one app or wherever you go
Get your podcast
From NPR and WBEZ Chicago
Wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Curtis Ware playing this week with Paula Poundstone
Bobcat Goldthwait
Burbank in Harrogate
That's a check
Chase Bank Auditorium
Sega in just a minute bill is recalling
Your rhyming lettuce in our listener Limerick challenge if you like to play give us a call at 1 AAA wait wait
That's one 888-924-8924 right now panel
We have some more question
For you from the Wii
Bobcat in response to a recent incident lawyers in the UK
Scrambling to figure out whether or not it's illegal.
To deny someone housing
Based on their what
Smell
No
Their weight
No not their way
We are on the right track
Because in fact somebody was
Denied housing
Say it again but one more
Dirt weight
No
Invisible thing
I'm not quite I'll give you a hint it's like good may it does make sense with Libras never pay their rent on time
Cousin
That's the answer
Is it legal to deny someone housing because their afterlife
Is the question
So that was happening
It happened a woman responded to a potential roommate
And rejected her saying quote her main concern is that you
Capricorn
But so she still wanted to live with this person
Well apparently the woman with Capricorn Moon
You're a nut
Would be great if that's what discrimination was no jugglers welcome here
People who clap after planes land need not apply
That's a pretty solid one of courts are going to side with you on that one
Bobcat
Hooters has long been known for the waitresses in tight shirts and hot pants
But now looking to extend their brand they open a new chain of rest
Specifically designed for who
4 Mormons
I have no idea
Looks like it's like you know you go there and you say that's right Timmy at the sound an owl makes and nothing else
Hooters
But for
China work clean
But you can that's the point
I know I'm trying to work clean
You bring your kids
Yes you just said it was for kids
Hooters for families
It's called
Hoots
The Hooters restaurant that is usually known as a great place for very sad dad's to
Distress eat while sitting
Nearby
What is starting a new family restaurant chain called
Boots
And it done a very good job they've even remove the nipples from the 200s on the side
To take my kids
Hooters for Mother's Day
Mother's Day
Psych
I want objectify women but I don't want to go to a strip club
Cuz those are dirty
Strip club
Wave training
Pretty much
Pretty much so this is to basically get your
Your kids use
The overall Hooters environment
When they're of age
Will feel very comfortable at a full life
Cysts on breast
Ice will be shifted away from leering at that mentored
Nursing infants
In fact the menu offers three kinds of milk chocolate 2%
And prepared tape
Hillside
Coming up with lightning fill in the blank the first is the game where you have to listen for the rhyme if you like to play on air quality of a message
That's 180 date to 924-8924 or click
The contact us link on our website wait wait
Care.org
Find out if
Be live shows here at the
Chase Bank Auditorium
Chicago upcoming shows at the Mann Center in Philadelphia
June 20
In at the Blossom Music Center in Cuyahoga
The Falls Ohio
July 18
If you think our show would be better if you were the
Star check out the quiz on your smart speaker
Just say open the wait wait quiz
And Bill and I will be there to ask
Questions about this week's news in your very home
You could even win one of our voices on your voice
You're on wait wait don't tell me
Hi
I'm from New Orleans
One of my favorite places on this Earth how do you what do you do there
Curriculum for high school
Sea level rise which is an issue
I mean people down where you live in the forest
You can't really argue about
Sea level rise because
It's basically sloshing at your ankles
Yeah that's right
Thank you every time
Even the interior
Do you think there's any chance that we here in Chicago will have OSHA
Ocean front property cuz that would be
What welcome to the show sanya Bill Curtis
This is going to be a few 3 News related limericks for the last word or phrase missing
Information
Of course the last word or phrase on just two of them
Dilwyn hour
Ready to go
Yes here is
The first limerick
With my veil through the pre-check I'm heading
The best man's late flight
We are dreads
Still
Terminal 3 is the
The right place
Southwest
The theme of our
Wedding guest wedding if you've ever gotten off a flight with a dry mouth
Mouth will also happy
Independent thought gee I wish I was getting married right now
The ticket it from a couple who got married at a baggage claim in the
The Cleveland Airport
Don't laugh have you been to a bag
Paracelsus
It is the Paris
Of Ohio
The couple get married at the Southwest baggage
Clan because they met their 12 years earlier and South
I promise any day now that their bags
Will show up at Southwest donated Airline snacks for the reception
And is a treat even let the bride and groom have a full can
Can of soda
Sadly however because they checked in late they weren't able to stand
And next to each other
The collapsible screen I'm remoulding
Now the shards of my phone
I'm beholden
This phone isn't
Smart
Cuz it just breaks apart
Like a map
It just
Camp handle
Folding rolling yes
Samsung is delaying the release of its highly-anticipated Galaxy fold
The phone which
Does a foldable screen
Now it's true the screen has a tendency to break
But it only happens
If you fold it
Breaks by the way in the bad way we're trained as a working on the good way we get to smaller phones
We can share with a friend
The phone was expected to retail for $2,000 you may be thinking wait isn't that just really an expensive flip phone
No
Because flip phone
Work
They were the folks that have the
Exploding song
Just wondering like
It's the same you know engineer
What are you got I know
My bad
Folding phones that break
Here is your life
I ran from the gym for a quick
Snack I skip
Factors context
I've neglected my app
Weather
No excess Flash
Cuz it's urgent
Scope statement
Yes very good this week this week
American Society of plastic
Dick Sargent unveiled a new technique called abdominal
Etching
Where they sculpt your belly fat into a six
Finally a simple painless way to get rocks off tabs
Requires multiple follow-up visits and for the patient to wear foam dressings on their stuff
4 weeks to keep the etchings in Play Store
Play set
So you think a tight corset
Pressing into your belly fat
Weeks
Is better than going to the
Jim
You're right it really
Have you seen the photo of
What this looks like it's terrible it's not very convincing
But all the muscles are
Just
Little pack
Sefat yeah
Where to Laird finds out he
I've done that
Bill had its own you doing I quit Sonia is good
Thank you so much for playing
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Come from Duckhorn Vineyards Napa California
Founded by Dan and Margaret.
Nineteen
Duckhorn Vineyards
Crafting classic
Lions with a sense of
The place for more than 40
With seven Estate Vineyards located throughout the map of
The winery produces vintage Merlot
Cabernet Sauvignon
Sauvignon blanc and Chardonnay
All showcasing the diversity of wine.
Learn more at Duckhorn. Com
Gyros creator of how I built this
We're returning to San Francisco for this
Second how I built this
Summit
Courted by a
Chicken Express
I'll be joining there by founders
Companies like
Instagram
Slack away
Bliss JetBlue
Many many more
Visit Summit
Npr.org
Moore and
See you there Support also comes
From Ridge wallet
Looking for a Father's Day gift
The ridge
Is the wallet real
Its innovative design you
Uses premium materials like tile
Titanium and carbon fiber
It has over 30000 5 star review
The ridge wallet comes with a lifetime warranty if you
You love it and free returns
Find the perfect
At ridge.com
NPR and get 10% off
With code
NPR
Now on to our final game lightning fill in the blank each of our players will have 60s
Dancer as a mini film
Questions
Is he or she can
Describe cancer.
Can you give us
Bobcat leads the pack with three and Paula and Luke
Flip the coin and Paula has elected to go second that means Luke
URL
On Tuesday the white has told officials not
Why was the
Subpoenas from Black
I have stomach ache
On Monday Nancy Pelosi
She said there were no immediate
Start blank
Impeachment
This week Kim Jeong Hoon held his first summit
With Russian president
Bright
On Sunday the FBI arrest
Is the leader of a right-wing militia
Detained blanks
In New Mexico
Would-be
Right on Wednesday the World Health Organization
Kitchen set that kids under 2 shouldn't spend any time with blank
Anti-vaxxers
No with screens although fossil smart on Sunday on sun
The queen of blank celebrated her 93rd
England right
This week the president of Liberia decided to work from home after being informed that his office was
Black full of loose snake exactly right Luke
Snakes snakes snakes
We reported emerging from Holes in the president's office building the president announced
Gdb telecommuting
Basset Hound standard for deciding to work from home
Do snakes commented always at home cut
We'll be right over
Bill how did Luke do in Ark
12 more points total of 4
Healing Way Out
There you got all right
On Tuesday the IRS failed to hand over blank
Spectacular
African grass
Right
After the release of the Mueller report house panel issued a subpoena for former White House counsel blank
Right on again
According to a new UN report 1 million species face blank thanks
The human activity
Write this weekend movie theater in Tennessee sparked controversy
See what I remove the movie Hellboy
Marquis and replaced it with blank
Heaven girl
Pep Boys
Oh my God on Sunday was revealed that nearly 100 Runners from China and falsified their time to get in
Into the blank mirror
The bus right this week with Rite Aid and Walgreens raised
Is the minimum age to buy blank
An Airbnb listing for rental in Scotland's book a years in advance despite the fact that renters are required to blank while
Staying there
Advance
There are
Required to
Hold their breath for
No they required to work at a bookstore from 9 to 5
If your idea of the perfect vacation is working retail 8 hours a day in a room filled with cat dander check
Workout
The open book an Airbnb rental
In Scotland Foods two bedrooms bathroom and a fully operation
Bookstore you need to manage while staying there
If you're interested but can't afford the trip
The Scotland you can probably book a room at a Motel 6 next to an Amazon distribution center
Are we still working
Bookstore Dubai paying to do it
You realize
Doesn't matter
I applaud your literary
I work for NPR
Bill how did Paula doing AR quiz
Trailing
Look of course
Hi to all right and how many vented Bobcat need
Okay bobcat
This is for the game
Following the bombings on Easter weekend the defense minister of blank
Resigned on Thursday
Right on Tuesday the first criminal charge
What is were filed
Against the drug CEO for his part in the blank
Write this week reported cases of
The blank we
What's the highest rate in 25 years
Chlamydia
Needle needle Jazz I'll give it to you on Monday Herman Cain withdrew his name from
Consideration for a spot on the board of the blank
Hon no the Federal Reserve
Police in Australia say they shouldn't have any trouble identifying a thief
What a grocery bag over
Bruce had to hide his identity
And then blank
And then took it off so we can have a place to carry his Loop
It's like I need a bag all I got one right here
This week China revealed plans to build a base
Json blank
The Moon yes done Tuesday two brothers implicated
In an attack
How to be a hoax about the defamation lawsuit
Against the lawyers for blank
Very good archaeologist Rorschach this weekend
A fossilized poop
Reveal the 1500 years ago in hunter-gatherer blank
Poop
The discovery was that he ate an entire rattlesnake
Pole
Clean the fan
Researchers say they've never seen anything like that
Recent find a dig in Texas
Which contains the remains of an entire rattlesnake
Clear Fang the archaeologist
Say the fossil
Provides great insight
Commence life
Suppose is a lot of questions like how bad does your breakup have to
To be before you eat your feelings with a live rattlesnake
Batman was Laird Hamilton
Grandfather
Birthday jackass
Bill
Did Bobcat do well enough to win
12 more points
Alaska panelist to predict what will be the Jeopardy question
It finally sinks
James holzhauer
Special thanks to stock and Ledger
For satisfying Army
Wait Wait don't Tell Me NPR WBEZ Chicago
In association with urgent haircut Productions
Overlord
Address announcers palfrey
Warehouse manager
Assignment random
Ranger Alex McGowan and Rachel Club
Car web Guru is bad
BJ leiderman composer theme my program is produced by Jennifer Mills
2 Marnie sure
Are anonymous source
Who plays Peter Quinn
Technical business and ops manager is calling Miller
Operation coordinator is Robert
Ready Winter Chill Out
Is Mike
Danforth
James holzhauer
Bobcat Goldthwait
What is
The male equivalent of Hooters
Goalie lessons
What is how to tie your own shoes Alex
And Luke Burbank
Who Let The Dogs Out
Poop poop
Tell if any of that happens we'll ask you about it on wait wait don't tell
This
Is NPR