Support for this podcast
In the following message
Come from Duckhorn
Napa California
Duckhorn Vineyards has been
Crafting classic Napa Valley Wine
Ants with a sense of place
For more than 40 years
Learn more
Or at Duckhorn. Com
NPR
Hey it's Peter Sagal if you're a normal wait wait listener
You shown up the answers
License and then you get frustrated that no one knows how brilliant you are
Here's the solution the wait wait quiz available now on your smart
Just ask you
Baker to open the wait wait quiz
Finally
Your Genius
Shelby wreck
From NPR and WBEZ Chicago this is
Wait wait don't tell me
NPR news quiz
Sorry Mitch McConnell nobody
Play blocks this bill
Then here is your host at the
Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown
Chicago PD
Have a great show for you today later on we're going to be talking
The Conan O'Brien the late night host
Towering over the competition
The mid-90s
All the first something happened last week that hasn't happened
Almost five years and that is
Bill Kurtis
Mist
Usher
We don't know
Where he was
Bill where did you go and why are you back so soon
Best news feeder
That was already kicked off the back
We don't have a rose for you if something better the voice of anyone you might like on your voicemail so give us a call the number is 18881
Wait wait that's 18892
Hi
You're on wait wait don't tell me
Hi how you doing I'm doing fine who's this this is Sam from Yuma Arizona
Yuma how are things in Yuma
Welder
Not quite as cold where you guys
What are you doing you
I am a ring scheduler for the Marine Corps Air Station down here what is the
You say your job
Range scheduler we managed
The training areas that
2D Marines and other agencies use
To conduct a training for real world
Situation right and that's an important job because if you
If you mess up the schedule guys will go out and start fighting each other
Both be bad bo3 bad I'm glad you're on the job then
Welcome to our show let me introduce you to our panel this week
First up at the correspondent for CBS Sunday Morning and host
Of the brand new podcast Mo obituaries
You can find anywhere you get your podcasts
It's Mo Rocca
Hi Sam Mexican comedian and host of the trivia
Podcasts to go
Fact
Yourself and the max
It's Helen Hall finally at the comedian
We will be at the kaaboo Festival in Grand Cayman
February 16th if you have
Going to be there it's Alonzo bodden
Hello Sam
Going to be this week location from the week news your job as a
I'm sure you know
To correctly identify
There's two of them do that you will win our prize the voice of anyone you might
For your voicemail
Are you ready to play
I just ready as I'm going to be all right your first quote is from a letter
Sad by the presence
Obviously
If you would like to make your journey by flying commercial
That would certainly
Your prerogative
That was a letter from President Trump telling someone he was canceling her trip overseas sorry
Who is trip
Nancy Pelosi speaker Pelosi very good
Get any nastier in Washington
The beef between the president and the Speaker of the House went for
Emma Constitution
Confrontation
The Real Housewives
The Pennsylvania Avenue
First
Speaker Pelosi let the president know
It was a government shutdown maybe he shouldn't deliver
The State of the Union
As schedule
It was a political equivalent of
Thanks for asking me out but I'll be washing my hair
Every night until the sun
Explode
Is it a little romantic though it's like
I don't know it's a little bit like
Tracy and Hepburn
The way the two of them are going at each other
Good really have that
Charm and Charisma ability
What's the opposite of Tracy and Hepburn
Well it would be
Fun except it's real
President and the Speaker of the House have
Fat that's affecting you know what I mean it's like it's a real thing like I fly all the time and are certain TSA
Employees
Did have this kind of like
Angry old school grandmother Vibe yeah
We need to send her
To the White House
Yeah
Should be getting paid
We have to mention only cuz we thought this is going to be the craziest thing that happened this week
The dinner the President Trump
Through
For the Clemson Tigers football team you may remember this it was a year ago on Monday
I do know or as President Trump told us
Because the government shutdown
Close the White House
Hazmat he out of the goodness of his own
Heart
Decided to pay for
For dinner himself so he made this amazing
Wonderful fast
Fast food feast in the Washington Post
Careful analysis
Decided it cost him about $3,000
That's half his net worth
Peter is dead
It's probably
Disparage fast food
Because McDonald's
French fry hat
Fresh McDonald's
French fry as a rebel
But like a 4-Hour Old MacDonald
French fry
I tried to offer that once
To a foster dog
And he was like just
Take me back to the pound
The scam he just ordered it for
He got caught
You're at your neck
Quote is
From the floor of the house of Parliament
United Kingdom
Order
That was just a little of the chaos that rained in London as British politicians voted
The plan to do what
That would be
Xidan
Brexit is happening but it's not happening and it's going to happen is going to be terrible
It's incredibly complicated
Imagine it this way you have a mommy and a Daddy who love each other very much
They decide they like to live apart
And then Daddy sets himself on
Bonfire
Britain is like blowing up there.
Destroying their own economy that can't figure out how to do it they can figure out how not
How to do it there in
Crisis still hate each other
It's a disaster button the other head
It's kind of sweet that the US
And United Kingdom were going through horrible times together
We've been allies for 4
For 200 years and now we're all falling apart it's like it when women hang out alot
Motorcycles
You know it's like that so like you said Peter who would have guessed
50 United States
Did Britain would get into a
Who's worse
You know like I know you think your leaders bad oh yeah what watch out
Well we don't even want ours when we never want it all and I mean it
It is incredible
What's going on I wonder if they've talked to each other
And been like
What Trump would be like you know I'm winning they hate me more Taytay hate me tremendously it's the most hate anyone
Had in history
Can I say I actually
But now I think the Donald Trump announce
Nancy Pelosi
Are like
Willis and Cybill
Will Shepherd in Moonlighting
Let It Go Let It Go
Richard Burton and Elizabeth Taylor who's Afraid of Virginia Woolf
I'll give you maybe Boris and Natasha
All right
We got one more quote for you here it is
To tidy up
Up the entire
That's a quote from the host of a new Netflix show that is everybody
Throwing
Everything out
Who is it
Oh my gosh I know the name of that I have seen commercials for but I cannot remember that
Set the name
Last name
It's not a co-op
Last name and first name
Murray
If you buy an apartment at
Yeah Yeah Yeahs it's Blitz Marie kondo my back
The author of the book The life-changing magic of tidying up
Marie kondo if you haven't seen her
Jesus tiny
Constantly smiling Japanese woman
Who says you should get rid of any possession that doesn't
Spark
Joy
And what is that mean she's liking this feeling
What happened
When you hold
So listen puppies of America
Stan top of the game cuz one more accident we're lovingly placing you in a dumpster
Is the whole Spark
Ecosphere
Your family members
Your spouse's spouses are being dropped off at the Salvation Army
Play just like
I'm not getting the puppy field
Do you have this weird sore
Theory of emotional relationship
Possessions for example
Is it true when you decide to throw some
Nothing out because it no longer
Joy
You have to thank it
For its service
Say for example
Thank you
Dress
For making me feel pretty at the prom
Thank you for letting
Me know how fat I am
Today
I hate to say this
This why black people laugh
TV show NFL
Yeah imma throw away everything I have
Mercedes
Does not spark enjoy
If you guys need to
Stop
Bill how did Sam do in Ark
It's two out of three
Take care bye bye
Light up handle it is time for you to answer some question
What about this week's news
Helen Costco is announced that they
Sold out
Nationwide
Of their new product that was all the rage of this
Bucket of what
Pound
Well craft
Was very very jealous
A bucket of cheese
A bucket of water
Mac and cheese mac and cheese 27lb
Was macaroni and cheese in a single
Industrial size
If you like your food like your like your walls
Spackle
That's what it is I'm headed to Costco it's an $89 27 lb
Of macaroni and cheese with
The shelf life of
20 years
What but if you are the kind of person who wants this no way are you living that way
Waited so it's not
Cook mac
Kimchi that's dry
Stable macaroni
Yeah I hate
The fact that I knew that
Did you really
You got to think that the the guys who had
The fast food at the White House or like well it could have been worse
Coming up our panelist do their part for Mother Earth
The two of them were lying about it at their Bluff The Listener game call 1aaa great way to play will be back in a minute
From NPR
Support for him
NPR and the following message come from feather
Life is constantly
And now your furniture
Can change with you
Whether you're moving in
Significant other
Or heading to a new city
Feather is a flexible way
To furnish your space
When the future is still unknown
With free delivery and assembly
Within a week of order
Now available in LA
Orange County New York and San
Visit live feather.
Start experiencing the benefit
Kitsap furniture flexibility
Feather furniture that changes with
We take most
Things for granted like
Our morning coffee
But there are a lot of
People behind that cup of coffee
Danny Jacobs
Set out
Thank all of them
It doesn't just take
A village
How to make a cup of coffee
It takes the world
Ideas around
Appreciation
TED Radio Hour
NPR
WBEZ Chicago this is wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Kurtis what you're playing this week with Alonzo bodden Mo Rocca
At Helena
At the Chase Bank Auditorium in Chicago Peters
What now
Listener game call 1aaa wait wait two-player game in the air
How you are on wait wait don't tell me
Hi this is Rebecca and flying from delmara suburb outside of Albany New York
Capital region
As they say if they're what do you do there
Environmental
Conservation are things changing in New York state understand
Political transformation
Not as far as I'm aware
Tell truth from fiction
Bill what is Rebecca
Hoot don't pollute
Or I'll cut you
According to the latest data the Earth will be
Uninhabitable in about 25 years
That hasn't stopped people
I'm trying to make
Things better
This week we read about a surprising effort
Heal the planet
Pick the real one you'll win our prize away voice of your choice on your voice
Ready to play
First let's hear from Alonzo bodden
We've all heard stories
Osaka hooligans
Drinking
Fighting and rioting before the game
At the game
After the game
On our way to the game on the way home from the game the game is just a brief intermission from their riot
Well now
To prove they're not bad people just
Overly passionate
Hooligans of come together.
Clean the streets around their arenas
The day after a match and the accompanying riots
Soccer fans
Coming down
How to pick up litter beer cans
Broken bottles you name
According to Eurosport Maga
Become competitive
Arthur Simeon
A huge Barcelona and Messi
Define says
Yes sometimes we get out of
Control but if we play Saturday we're out here
Cleaning son
We weigh our recyclables in
Lincoln Paramount
The other clubs around Europe
To see who cleans up fast
I just want to know we've out clean Portugal and Ronaldo
Daniel Bryan a Watford fan
Yeah it's a giggle to get out here and
And see what we've done the day after a win
The cleanups got people who don't even know football hoping we were
Make the neighborhood nicer
Who knows maybe it'll catch on
Even in the states
We've seen how you Yanks are after a championship
I guess it doesn't even take a championship
The Raiders may not play proper football
But those fans
Proper hooligan
Football Hooligans in Europe doing their part to clean up both
Before and after their riot
Your next story of someone working to be environmentally conscious
Comes from
Helen Hong
Drug dealers
Have a lot to worry about
Getting raided by the cops
Of course
Getting murdered by ruthless drug cartel
But also climate change is real you guys
Saving the environment has become
Come such a concern for
For cocaine dealers in
Birmingham England
But they stopped
Selling the white powder in Ziploc baggies and if
Starting using reusable pods
The practice
The woke is confusing their customers
Who frankly just want to get high
I was giving a gram of cocaine in this class
Fake punt thing
And Medina said they were serving up in past
Big Ziploc bags or wraps anymore
When confused Coke fiend told Metro. UK
He said I could bring it back
If I wanted to anybody
Refill it and that it would be better for the environment
Biodegradable paper
Straws for
Snorting RC
Cocaine dealers in Great Britain getting rid of the environment by using reusable can
Banners for their coat
Your last story of a surprising attempt to make the world a better place comes
Rimowa
Maryland
The hill is
The flight attend
I thought she lives in
Cincinnati Ohio and she
It works for Sun
Country Airlines
Sun Country Airlines they serve banana
A lot
And Marilyn really hates
Touching banana peel
And so she wears
Gloves
I'm so that should have
Touch them
But Sun Country
Has a small budget
And so sometimes she's ended up having
Handle
The slimy banana peels when she gets upset these are all talk
Hazard
Banana peels everywhere
And so she
Was so frustrated she started making a Bloody Mary on the
Plain and she
Cut her hand
She was very upset about and then she
She just impulsively cut her hand
And magically
Healed wound in her hand
She was at the flight
Channel on the flight the regular flavor
Usually has a jet lag but she found that
Potassium
From
Banana peel
Built into her system if she no longer had jet lag
Discover these amazing medic
Properties of
Banana peels
Answer she sold it to Merck
And with that money she has an hour
Up the budget for sun country's gloves
Chanel flight attendant ever needs
The touch of banana peel again
Okay
I think I've grasped
These are your choices
Alonzo bodden
Soccer hooligans doing their part 2
The clean up the grounds where they have rioted or might write
From Helen Hong cocaine dealers
Great Britain
Deciding to use reusable pods instead of
Environmentally wasteful
Plastic baggies
Enfamil Rocca
A tankless oldest I'm a flight attendant
Discovers that banana peels
Can be used
For their health benefits
Thereby
Preventing them from being
Disposed is wet
Exactly
Uber
None of these are super
Compelling
I'm going to go with Alonzo
You're going to go to Lonzo and the soccer hooligan
Running around and cleaning up
The places where they arrived at the
Because that's how they are
We spoke to somebody who knew something about the real
Story
One of the uses and Batman
Retenes refill it
I'm sure you thought that was still Helen talking because of this amazingly accurate
In fact it was Helen story that was funny that was James Rodger head of Trendz Birmingham live
Talking to us about the environmentally woke
Cocaine dealers of that sound
So I'm sorry you were fooled by alonso's very very nice story but that you have earned a point
At least for him so thank you so much for playing
Okay thank you bye bye
And now the game where we ask people who've done a lot and Been Everywhere about something they avoided the whole time
It's called not my job
Back in Maine
1893 David Letterman left his job hosting late
NBC in to replace him
The network picked a completely unknown
Comedy writer who. Has never appeared on camera
Before
And now Conan O'Brien host
Conan on
PBS has the longest
Tenure of anyone in late night
He joins us now Conan O'Brien welcome to wait wait don't tell me thank you
Thank you
Heard varying version
Love your Origins
Story as a late-night host one of them being that you were
Somebody in the Simpsons writers room said Conan he's funny and Charming let's give him a show
Other versions that you audition for what's the truth
The truth is that I had it was really my association with star Night Live
I was a young writer external alive
And I was the writer that was kind of known
To sort of perform my sketches
Three other writers and I perform them
For people when I get them laughing
I think Lorne Michaels notice that I left on a live I went onto the
Simpsons
And I work there for a
About a year-and-a-half two years
When
Lorne Michaels worth
Charged with
Who's the new guy is going to replace Letterman
And
He said you know was just Geico
He's got something
And
They looked into it and it turns out I really didn't have anything
And here we are all the
Years later it must have been crazy
Because you know you weren't a stand-up you didn't
The following is
Performing you were thrown
You're going to be in National Television
ResCare you're nervous
I was diluted
There's nothing like delusion
There's nothing like
If you think you can't do something convinced yourself that you can and then it have a few drinks and go do it
I really believed I could do it and I was also terrified
The same time but I think I had a
Deep-seated belief
Did America needed to
See me on your cell phone
He's not really shared by anyone else
Mow how dare you speak to me directly
Your question has to go through Bill Curtis and then
Bill would you ask Conan
Show how it's when they get home a lot of time they came
Remember who was the guest earlier that day of
The taping
You ask him about that can you remember the gas
Song the show that night
Bill that's a really stupid question
Funny
2 most point
No
You do the show
And it becomes
You're feeling the moment when you're doing it and I like in the hole
Experience and I'm actually not even kidding about this
I think everyone's
Dropping your audience's
Familiarity
Famous toy the Etch-a-Sketch
Yes where you turn the knobs
How to create a picture you
Create something and then you just shake it and it's gone
Start again
Everyday I come in and I learn everything I can
That I need to know for that show
And I learned it to the best that I can and I can
Tell you everything about the gas tank
Play everything about the comedy
The minute it's over
I shake the edge
Sketch
And all of its gone and I go home and I don't know what we did
I've done 4000 hours
Broadcasting I'm told
9 of it quite good
Yeah
You have I want to get on to what you're doing an hour
Which is really interesting
Variety of things
Pornography
You're tall enough of course your head would never enter the frame would be good for a 9in today
I just leaned down
I couldn't have met on one occasion it was a red for the White House Correspondents Dinner
And I have my picture taken with you, which I'm grateful for and you did something
You crouched
Instantly without being asked you to sort of Crouch
So that you and I had would be in the same frame
You must have to do that.
100 times a day
Is an initiated I am
I want taller than people think I am
And whenever I go anywhere in the country or the world
All people say to me
Good God
You're so much bigger that you are on television
But I would say you need a bigger caliber
And my daughter now has said you need a
Priceline
Will Conan O'Brien we're delighted to talk to you about we have asked you to play a game we're calling
Team Coco
Meet hot cocoa
Your supporters fans are known as Team Coco
What do you know about actual cocoa
The tasty hot chocolate
I know everything
Really that's a bold statement
There's not a thing you can ask me
About hot cocoa
But I do not know well I am interested in what's going to happen now because we have in fact prepared three questions for you
About
Hot cocoa
Correct
There's a voice of their choice
On their voice
Smell are you ready to do this
I was born ready
Who is Conan O'Brien playing
Chase McGee of Raleigh North Carolina
First question you think it's just with kids drink instead of coffee but hot cocoa can change your life
As it did for whom a Bernie Madoff
Who after he was convicted and
In prison for fraud quote
Corner to the prison Market on
Swiss Miss hot chocolate
Be Jeff Bezos who's first internet business was delivering
Steaming cups of hot chocolate
Two people suffering through the Seattle winter
Orsi Eric McMillan who is a
Inspired to invent the kids
Ball pit
By looking at mini marshmallows floating
In his house
Dancers Eric McMillan
You're very
Peter
I'm going to say this one more time
It was actually a was Bernie Madoff
I'd like to Kentucky
Noah apparently you Noah born trailer is born trailer it is apparently made of made very well for himself in prison
With the Swiss Miss
Hot chocolate
Yeah
You know why I got that one wrong
In our penal reform system and I don't poop
Stop that they would let Bernie Madoff do that too in a way I'm counting that answer is
Correct
I like your company
People really really love Coco a lot so much so that one time
People were doing what
A mixing protein powder into cocoa
So it would be the only thing that ever has
Be snorting lines of cocoa powder like Coke
Or see you trying to have a transfused into their body instead of blood
Answer is
Snorting
Cocaine
Will cocoa as cocaine
Sorry I slept there
Yeah I heart
Snorting cocoa
Snorting chocolate
Chocolate who invented a little device
Should cocoa powder into
Engineer and I work with him
Have you tried the snorting coke
I guess I have it's fantastic there's an incredible High
It lasts for about 20 minutes
And then you have to cough out the marshmallows
The wonderful spirit
When you wake up you're wearing German shorts I don't know why
All right let's go so you can get this right
For True chocolate lovers there's a
The pill created by a French scientist
Which were $13 a bottle
Will do what
Hey make anything you eat
Including me
Taste like
Bee make your fart
Smell like chocolate
4C it gives you chocolate dandruff instead of dry skin you shed chocolate flake
The answer is a
Sweet like chocolate
Yes
Yes chocolate chocolate chocolate
It's B
I'm sorry
But yes
The idea is
It's a little pill
And you take it and if you take it
Your fart smell
Like chocolate
You know what I'm going to tell you something I didn't go for that because it
Scatological I don't work blue
I didn't realize this was that kind of show
But I guess it's all about Spark
With you and I hope you're proud of yourself
How did Conan O'Brien
Do
On our show the score out because he's the only guest
We've had when he says his right
Codon
Joey King
Thank you, know Brian is a
The host of So Many shows including the new podcast Conan O'Brien needs a friend you can also see him
On Conan Without Borders on Netflix
And on Conan
On TBS Conan O'Brien what a pleasure to finally have Yuan
Thank you so much
It doesn't mean that bill to get some alone time with his Doritos in The Listener Limerick challenge. 1-aaa Thwaites to join us
I'll be back in a minute with more to wait wait don't tell me from NPR
Support frame
PRN the following message
Search come from feather
Life is
Is constantly itching
And now your furniture
I can change with you
Whether you're moving in with acid
Significant other
We're heading to a new city
Feather is a
Flexible way
Pay to furnish your space
When the future is still unknown
With free delivery and assembly
Within a week up or
Now available in LA
Orange County
New York and Sanford
Visit live feather.
Start experiencing the benefit
Furniture flexible
Feather
Furniture that changes
This week on ask me another we've got TV
Baby's favorite muscle man Terry Crews
Rosa from Brooklyn nine nine
Any chance about his multiple talents and how he stays humble and Hollywood
It's dropping in your feeds Friday January 18th on NPR Tower of puzzles where games and trivia
From NPR
G-Eazy Chicago this is
Wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
We're playing this week with Helen Hong
Mo Rocca
Ed Alonzo bodden your host of The Chase
Chase Bank Auditorium in
Chicago PD
Thank you girl
Who is the leader of an organized crime ring it's our listener Limerick challenge
Do you like to play give us a call at 1 AAA wait wait that's 18892
Rhino panel some more questions for you from the week's news
MOJ new study has found that men are more attracted to women who have
Bushy what
I bet
Shoes
Yeah I guess that
Imma track
Women Within
The study asked 2000 people to rate a series of photos on their tractor
Confounded women
Thicker eyebrows scored higher than women
With dinner
Only to a point they can leave you so take of birds start nesting in them to sit around that come out
Oh my God
Frida Kahlo
Exactly so what about
Shave the mafia
Draw them back on if they've been
Doing it wrong
As you draw them on early
It's no surprise that men would find thicker eyebrows attractive how many times have we seen women have
At a party say
Hey
My eyes are down here
Nice bushes
That's what your eyebrows that are bushy that's probably what you say nice but it is
Not know I said bushes
Mo know when to give up hope this week it was announced that a made
Finally been found
For a very lonely watch
10 years
Lonely
Need help
Found
I thought you said have made
Apartments
Security right now
Had been found
Lonely leopard
No probably
I don't know maybe
Yep clip to Uniqlo
Give me a clue sitting on his wanted some of the sheriff's lilypad
A lonely
Toad
Technically a frog but I'll give it to you
What's known in scientific circles as the world's loneliest
Frog
Now you may
Be asking how do they know this frog
Is lonely
Simple
They read his journal
Romeo was the name of the endangered
Incas frog
He's been alone in captivity for the last decade will signed is it looking for
Forum 8
You thought you had it
This guy is a team of people trying to find a match and it took them
10 years
Okay they're hoping that they'll
Started
On the 1st of April
Did anyone
The Frog costume
Sure that
Right that would be
This is like a Hallmark
Coming out
Really have to be sad it's like they got together and they
Like I'm sorry you got to go
Coming up with lightning fill in the blank the first is the game where you have to listen for the rhyme if you like a plan are called and leave a message
1 Triple 8 wait wait
That's one eight eight eight 92489
Or click the contact us link on our website
It's wait wait. Npr.org
And for all of you out there
Too nervous
To call in and play I know
Where intimidate
Now you don't have to
You can play the new
;-)
Quiz available on your
Your smarts be
Just ask your Alexa or Google home to open
The weight
Weight quiz
Open the wait wait
Quiz and Bill and I will be right there inside your little device to ask you some questions
And to hear your answers is just like the radio show
Only now when you shove things at us
We will hear you
Taiyuan wait wait don't tell me
Hi there this is actual calling from
Cedar City Utah Cedar City
Are you near some of the great national parks
Leica Zion
Between Zion and Bryce
Beautiful there what are you do there
I'm actually a park ranger for the Nash
National parks
Do you know about it are you not are you not getting paid right now
Correct sorry I believe is the official
So what are you doing with your buddy doing it all your free time
This is what I would say the highlight of it so far it's alright
Curtis Scooby-Doo 3 News related limericks the last word or phrase missing for me
Can fill in that last word or phrase
Correctly into the limo
You will be a winner
Are you ready to play
I'm ready
Here is your
Limerick
Salt and vinegar
Crumbs on my lip
Make me feel an effect
In my hips
I am put in the mood
By myself
Snack food
I'm turned on
From this big bag of
Jets
Just potato chips
Are finally sexy snack food maker tyrells
Has created a fraud
Easyacc flavor
4 crisps
As I call them over there
The sensual mood setting combination
Honey Chile
Salt and crumbs
On your sweater
Food that makes you feel
More sexy while driving away anyone you might
Actually want to
Apparently honey and chili or a powerful aphrodisiac
Combo
But it's going to really suck when you accidentally get a bag of sex
Sex tips from the office Vending
Close French
Don't Mind If I Do
I never thought of honey in chili
Going together tonight
Far apart on the
Flavor scale
I guess that's why I weed honey hot chili
That she sounds like the start of a
Good stripper bit exactly
Your next limerick
With armpits I've never been in vain
But I found this great roygbiv
Stanlow
Iexplore
All the Hills
Just like unicorns
A my armpits
Look just like a
Rainbow fashion trend you didn't know about you didn't know
That you were that you could hate it it's called unicorn armpit hair
People are dying their armpit hair all the colors of the rainbow
And this time the treasure at the end of it is a funky
Are we
Society just getting
So lonely that
People are like hey I'll try this
Absolutely anything
Chilli honey chips
We're just looking for meaning wherever we can all right
Here is your last
Limerick
Grassy green liquor will seem blah
Grab a large Rock of ice
And the clean
Straw
Pacific gluten-free malt
From Peruvian vaults
We're making our whiskey
From
Bra
I know it's a tough one me you may not even know this
I'll give it to you already won it
Quinoa
Finally a beverage that combines
Hypertension of some of the drinks
Single malt whiskey
The smug satisfaction of someone who eats quinoa
The only way I could be
Where is it the whiskey were also somehow vinyl record
Derek
Bell started
Experimenting
Quinoa based whiskey a few years ago did with quotes
Flavor
Pepper seeds health benefits
Alright
No honey
You're getting it wrong I'm not a drunk I'm a health nut
Exact exact
And I hope you get back to work soon good luck to you
Bye-bye
Support for him
NPR in the following message come from feather
Life is constantly
And now your furniture
Change width
Whether you're moving in
Significant other
Or heading to a new city
Feather is a flexible way to
To furnish your space
When the future is still unknown
With free delivery and assembly
Within a week of ordering
Now available in LA
Orange County New York and Saint Francis
Visit live feather.
Start experiencing the benefit
It's a Furniture flexibility
Feather furniture that
Changes with
Gyros creator
How I built this in
We're returning to San Francisco for this
Second how I built this Summit
Supported by American
Express
I'll be join there by founders
Companies like Instagram
Whack away
Bliss JetBlue and many many more
Visit Summit
Npr.org
Learn more and
See you there Support also
Comes from betterhelp
Betterhelp offers licensed professional
Nurse who specialize in
Do you suggest depression stress anxiety and
Connect with your professional account
Popular in a safe and private
Online environment at your
Get help at your own time and your own
Schedule secure
Video or phone session
Plus chat and text
With your therapist
Visit betterhelp.com weight
To learn more
And get 10% off your first month
That was my final game lightning fill in the blank each of our players with a 60 seconds must answer as many fill in the blank
As he or she can it
Detroit dancers net worth
Dell can you give us
Moe has three and Helen and Alonzo
Each have five oh my God how does that happen
So Helen Alonzo have five
And I'm only has
Three witch
Which is a little embarrassing
I don't know that means that you are up first so here we go
The confirmation hearings for William Barr Trump's nominee for blank concluded on Wednesday
Write many men objected and threatened
The band Razor Company Gillette after the company released an ad encouraging men
To blank
Emacs skill
Sterling testimony
In the trial of El Chapo Witness
His claim to the former president of blank
100 million dollar bribe from the
Yes on Wednesday Isis
The credit for a suicide bombing at a restaurant
Blank
Like this weekend Australian politician running for Parliament announced
Does plant
The ban unsolicited political text messages using
Blank
Unsolicited political text message
Following calls for federal investigation 80
Would no longer be
Reselling users
Blank data
Oh I'm
User data
What's the
Kind
User data that was found on
Phones
Descriptions and
Part of their
Familiarity
People who often times use a in TNT
Can I conceive tomorrow at 1:18 what kind of data
They are not
Going to sell data that you would use on your phone they would not sell the
The data that information will not sell your location
Where You Are
According to new research increasing daily movement might help elderly people stay
Stave off
Blank
Odac
Dementia
Death of the Mind
Yeah man in Kentucky trying to knock over a family 10 foot tall Snowman
This car failed because the Snowman was blank
It was actually it
Real
The Snowman
Ice House no it was
A snowman built around a giant Tree Drive
The mange
Before I do most technically the giant snowman in the front yard of the left home and couldn't resist
He revved up his car
And plowed right into a 5-foot tree stop
It's unclear if the driver was injured with
The Snowman survive
At least allow me to do
True nemesis
The Sun
Bill how did Moe doing our quiz he got five right
Is 13 is now in the lead proving
There's dumb obituary today
Thank you for the product
We flip the coin Helen has
Decided to go right now so here we go Helens on the Block
On Thursday former Trump lawyer blank with you
The president paid him
How to rig polling data
Michael Jackson on Tuesday a federal judge
Blocked President Trump proposed it is
Essential questions on
The twenty20 blank reported the Pentagon would begin scrutinizing new recruits
Who have blanks
Green car right on Monday Canadian Prime Minister Justin
Accused blank of arbitrarily sentence
A Canadian citizen
Send it to death
No China this week
People warned
The Silicon Valley's housing market was getting out of hand
For the landlord reveal to get rented
The $1,500 a month
Department to blank yes according to a new study
Blank is melting 6
Times faster than it was
On Wednesday video-sharing Giants blank announced a ban on dangerous or harmful pranks
YouTube a woman in Texas was banned for life from her local Walmart
When employees call her blanket
Drinking wine out of a Pringles can
Even though you left the best to tell she was doing that while riding around the store and one of those motorized cart
#goal
She is she is living her best life we love this woman
The boys said the woman came into the Wichita Falls Walmart in the morning grab the motorized cart
It's filled a dream that none of us realized we had until now after few hours of police arrived even though
Play band the woman from the store Pringles drunk cart Walmart racing
Is now being considered the 2022 Olympics
7 right
14 more points total of 9
Team Emily
Some of the time but the 8th
To whip that is a tall order for the game fill in the blank after a year of saying there was no collusion
To the Trump campaign and Russia
Rudolph Giuliani this week said blank
There was collusion
What you said Trump he said Trump today
Lukalula
Will give it to ring a bell
Officials at the mouse from Air Force Base in Montana has warned the public that its nuclear Arsenal
Is under a constant
Back by blank
Okay let me try to mow this one out and they have
Nuclear
Webster new
Nuclear weapons are eaten by the
Nuclear weapon eating
The trick is never stopped following
Comments about victims of the Larry Nassar
Bruce Campbell the interim president of the blank
Resigned on Wednesday
Co-op Michigan State American should limit their red meat consumption
21 blank a week
127 lb tub of
One hamburger
After repeated staffs the Washington
Penn State Department of Transportation was forced to swap out
I-69 mile marker sign with a blank
70 mile
No they replacing the 69 mile-marker sign
The 68.9 mile sign
For some reason the sign for mile marker 69 on the 195 in Washington
Date has been stolen several times over the past few years
Forcing Transportation Department officials
To replace it with a sign reading
68.9 instead
When asked why they thought the 69 mile time was getting stolen so often the state official said we're not
Just people think it's nice
Did Alonzo do well enough to win
With three points
And just a minute we're going to answer a panelist now that recondo is convinced us to throw out all our stuff what will be the next big self-help
Trend
Thanks for Farmhouse Tavern for feeding us
Even if you didn't bring carrots this
Wait wait don't tell me the production of NPR WBEZ Chicago in association with Urgent Care, production
Doug berman benevolent overlord
Philip gotika rights are limericks are public address announcer
Paul freed
Warehouse managers Tyler green
This device timeout random
Our interns are Alex and Rachel Clapper iweb the room is best
BJ leiderman composer see my program is produced by Jennifer Mills
Miles dornbos and Lillian Kent
Any other use of this broadcast
Tranny pictures description
Kids workout to the game but prohibited
Without the consent
A Peter Quinn
Tactical directions I'm going to wife her master of operations
Was Colin Miller a production coordinator is Robert Newhouse
Are senior producer and executive producer of wait wait
Is Michael Banff
For now, what will be the next
Trend in self-improvement Alonzo bodden
People stop listening to Marie kondo and
Keep their stuff
Helen Hong will break into other people's home
And throw out their stuff
Cuz why I stopped at your own
And Morocco
In her news
Do Shari's Murray
A condo goes to washing
DC
By the end of
The series
No one is left
And if any of that happens bad old will ask you about it.
Morocco today
Are Peter Sagal and we'll see you next week