Support for this podcast
In the following message
Come from Duckhorn
Napa California
Duckhorn Vineyards has been
Crafting classic Napa Valley Wine
Ants with a sense of place
For more than 40 years
Learn more
Or at Duckhorn. Com
NPR
From NPR and.
Easy Chicago this is
Wait don't tell me
NPR news quiz
Build the wall
And here is your host at the Chase Bank on
Natatorium and down
Time in Chicago
We have a Wonder
Bookshelf you today
Because as a wise man once said are you ready for it
Later on we're going to be talking
To All Pro defensive back Charles
Peanut Tillman
The most feared Chicago Bears
Prince Charles
Peanut allergy
If you're ready for game day give us a call the number is one Triple Eight wait wait that's one to 88924
Great 9 to 4
Let's welcome our first listen to contested how you're on wait wait don't tell me
Hey this is Ashley something from Winston-Salem North Carolina
Pretty good today yeah well
Brag about the weather
What are you doing
I work in a brewery and I play in a couple of ants
Oh really well that sounds like a
Excuse me sir are you a
Hipster
I'm a little too old for that
What welcome to the show as let me introduce you to our panel this week
First off this syndicated advice columnist behind ask Amy and the author of
Strangers pain
You tell me things Miss Amy Dickinson
WGN man of the people who'll be appearing at
Dandy's in Milwaukee on February 2nd and Welch's bar in Fort Wayne Indiana
February 8th
Hello how are you
Walter writer at BuzzFeed news it's a Bim adewunmi
Ashley welcome to the show we are all gathered so does time to start you're going
Play who's Bill this time as I'm sure you anticipated Bill Kurtis
Was going to read for you or week
Create three quotations in the week's news your job of course
Identify or explain just two of them do that you'll win our prize
The voice of your choice
Send your voicemail are you ready to go
Yes all right
Your first quote is this
Suspiciously well-written
This is her
Prerogative
I will do it
When the shutdown
Is over that was the president of the United States getting into the
The speaker of the house is
In agreeing to postpone what
Until the shutdown is
Over
The State of the Union
After a week of back and forth
Between President Trump and Nancy
Pelosi about whether he'd be able to
To deliver the State of the Union during the shutdown
The presidents that only gave in
In a very civil
Tweet
But even spelled
The word
Prerogative
Correctly which means
One thing the president is going to be so angry when he finds out about this
At first he said he just make the speech
From someplace else
We couldn't find anywhere even that club that lets Louis CK do is that was like now
Jaguars
My favorite insult
Tweet
You sent out
Affinity Plus Easter eggs
Something like
Nancy Pelosi
Who I call Nancy
Yeah well it's like what happened and he just nasty that's his insulting nickname
We assume that the White House senior official who's in charge of insulting nicknames has been furloughed
One point
You seem like a battle of letterheads
From the desk of
Courtroom sketch from the toilet
About what fun is a sense of who speaker Pelosi is and how she'll do with them a lot of people read
Atmos Polo season
Letter
As a c
Suggestion
But Italian grandmother
Please do not
Suggest
It's like her saying oh maybe it's a good idea to change your dress
Before you go out
Which means change that or you'll be locked in your room until you're 25 I mean
Poker now
No....
Here is your next quote
I'm afraid it'll be on my gravestone
He lied for Trump
That is someone who could be right about what his gravestone will eventually say he's been all over the airwaves recently saying all
Kinds of things about his client the president
Who is it
I would say Michael Cohen
Oh no Michael Cohen no longer represents
The president Rudy Giuliani yes very good
Make a good point about Michael Cohen there could someday be a graveyard filled with headstone saying I lied for Donald Trump
Last year apparently the
The president became
Satisfied
With
How is representatives were defending him
On TV
And since he couldn't do it himself he wanted somebody just
Is aggressive he want
Was Giuliani
When he couldn't get his first choice
Rabies
Before Giuliani
Potential Epitaph for himself
You should think about what else it might be given his career I mean here lies Rudy Giuliani
He let his wife know he was divorcing her in
In a press conference
Or here lies Rudy the only man who looked better
With a comb over
Xiaomi
Shirley's dad summer just right here lies
Message
Wow he said he was on all the
Cable news
Sunday shows of the office
But that
Quote from about his
Future based on him from this very bizarre interview
With Isaac chart
Winner of the
New Yorker
Who caught him
I said just before he was going to
Shower
And maybe it was because he
He was physically naked that he became emotionally naked
And he said all these crazy things like
For example
I've been through all the tape
And the interviewer said
Tape
And then he just changed his voice
Jason said new phone who dis
The shower an audible Subway announcement
For the most of
Obvious Child
What you kind
Did you do it
The kid ghost
Did you do it and the
12 minute oil on the carpet like a shot
Here's what I look like
Soon-to-be
Most recent ex-wife
Students Nathan
Said something like
As his
The ex-wife and
The nurse
I'm really worried about him that was in their vows
All right very good eyesight your last
Quote is from a lawsuit that was
Filed quite recently in New Orleans Louisiana
Past present
Lots of faith
Enjoyment of life
Those were damages
Is that these people
Pulseira cos
To them
Because of what
Oh man
The clue is New Orleans
Langfang
Very angry about the Saints game that's right
See playoff game on Sunday the rest
Blew a call that would have helped
The New Orleans Saints to go into the Super Bowl basically
All Saints receiver was getting ready to catch a ball when a Rams
Defender appeared
And ran him over with the garbage
Truck
Is backed up did it again
And the Rapture like well who are we to say that's not allowed
Associate's fans are demanding
Variously that the NFL apologize or that it reverse the results of the game and let the Saints go to the Super Bowl
Or that they pay a massive penalties of the hurt people of New Orleans
Saints fans lawyer Rudolph Giuliani made a strong argument
Who knows if their guy would have caught it
Some people in New Orleans are extremely upset meanwhile people in La home of the Victorious Rams or saying wait a minute we have a football team
Well that's nice
Whether this is interesting
I'm sure that everybody knows this
Super Bowls next week
Going to be the New England Patriots they are in Everett
Super Bowl by law
Versus the Rams
And it just so happens
New England quarterback Tom Brady
F41
Is it
Years older
Then the Rams
Coach
Wow who's I think 32
What are my favorite things
One who
What does inconsiderate
I appreciate you
No but like my favorite thing is
Cuz I'm coming to this with almost no knowledge
But I know that everyone hate
I just want to say thank you
T4 in golf
Sing me in the loving embrace
Yeah man I don't know
Name
He's a good-looking fellow
Believe that there is a lid for every pot but I did
With Tom Brokaw
Bill how did actually do in Ark
Give it all to ask
Thank you so much thank you
Time for you course
Some questions from the week
Snooze
Been with all the economic uncertainties some people are raising
Slaughtering their own meat
We just learned that
What person
Killed a goat with his own hands before then butchering it
And serving it to his
So I am delighted
Because I have followed the
Very closely
I'm so glad
It is one month
Zuckerberg of Facebook that's correct
A goat a goat
If it's the stuff around
Found it in an interview with Rolling Stone magazine
Twitter CEO Jack Dorsey
Revealed Mark Zuckerberg
What did the space where you only ate
Would he himself killed Dorsey
She found this out
He went to Zuckerberg house
For dinner
Where he was served
Fresh goat
Zuckerberg himself had raised and then killed
With a quote
Laser gun
And a knife
So if you ever wondered what those freaky
Ashley Young Tech billionaires dufur
For fun
They murder goats with laser
It's not that
What is been killed by a laser
That dies in his last thought
Is I cannot believe this
Physical Express
That that dweeb is he is going to hurt me
The flight into
I Need a Hero
Can I find a game called one Triple Eight way to play will be back in a minute with more wait wait don't tell me
Freemanpedia
Support for this podcast
Send the following message come from Park MD
The newest Resort in the center of the Las Vegas
It's weird Lady Gaga
Bruno Mars and Aerosmith
Bring down the house
What's in the intimacy of the Park theater
It's where l a chef
Roy Choi
Mashes up Korean flavor
Where is Eddie's new restaurant best for
Be inspired
At Eataly Market
Enjoy your spin on fine dining
And no matter
And let it all go
At on the wreck
Vegas is first
Speakeasy
Park MGM
Intimate moments
Big experience
Hey Sophie reisenberg from ask me another if you're craving nerdy trivia or celebrity in
Interviews
Got you covered
Woodhouse musician Jonathan Coulton and the sherpas
Contestants in public radio
Don't miss NPR's hour of puzzles word games and trivia
WBEZ Chicago this is wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz this we are playing this week with
Out of one many
Battenberg
And Amy Dickinson
Been here at the Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown
Chicago
Peter said she'll take everybody
Right now it's time for the wait wait don't tell me Bluff The Listener game you can call 1aaa twait if you want to play
Hi you are on wait wait don't tell me
Hi Peter this is Ken Brenneman from Pasadena Maryland I don't know Pasadena
I know the other one pretty well but where is Pasadena
It's near Annapolis Maryland
I'm the radiation safety officer for a large University
Time in Baltimore
Okay so your job is to make sure the people don't get irradiated
Correct right now we make sure that they use radiation
To safely
Because of people like you that we don't really have a Spider-Man
I'm a little disappointed
Welcome to the show can you to play our game and what you have to tell truth from fiction
Till what is kanno topic
A Real American Hero
There's a Hero inside all of us
Talking about a gyro sandwich
Action heroes
Not easy to find
Which is why we were so excited when we came across the
The story of an American who actually did
An amazing
Heroic
And we are going to have our panelists tell you three stories of American Heroes
Only one of them is real
Your dad picks at realist
Ready to do it
Here we go
First let's hear from Adam Burke
The long-running
Skating spectacular Disney on Ice
Can be a logistical nightmare.
The best of time
The downright disaster seemed inevitable Journey
Special 30th anniversary
Street performance at Madison
Square Garden
Tommy quickly the show's longtime technical director
Explain
It was a special charity show
We've got 20,000 excited kids in the audio
An hour before go time we find out that are Ursula and Ariel are in the hospital
There's a big snow storm that night and would you believe it there cabs getting on a patch of ice
Bamboo
Ordinarily understudies
He will take up the slack
But it being reassigned to a special
Play design finale
You to follow directly after The Little Mermaid.
I want to just cut the ACT explains quickly
But the whole point
That number is to give the rest of the cast time to change
So we're screwed
Which is when Paolo Productions dedicated Zamboni driver
Stepped into The Fray
I guess it seemed to show thousands of times and rehearsal
Roller skating in the zoo
Even better Palace Sun an amateur hockey player
Daily offered to Dawn the iconix
Seashell bra
It wasn't the most graceful version of that number I've seen said quickly
At Arrowhead more hockey stops fist-bumps
And I
Spray than usual but the crowd loved it
They got a standing ovation
I kept that detail from the regular performers. I figured they'd been through it
Zamboni driver and his son step into Ursula and Ariel to Carol 25
Thousand kids at Disney on Ice your neck
Story
Arby's gyro
Getting his
Is Urdu comes from
Amy
This year
Special posthumous Oscar
Will be awarded to Gone With the Wind star Vivien Leigh
Hubris
Her reputation
And her pantaloon
In a smuggling operation
The course of
Film history
While shooting Gone with the Wind
React
Krispy Kreme
Concerned about the welfare of the
The monkeys that MGM was
Going to film the flying man
Be seen in the
Wizard of Oz
Which we speak
Being filmed on the lot next
Store
The animal loving actress
First turn
Costar
Clark Gable for help and Save
Getting the monkeys
But his response
It hurts so much
That they inserted
The line it's the movie
So
In a stealth operation worthy of done
Or a Jerry Lewis
The actress had several monkey
He's under her massive
Skirt and led them away
Samoset and into a waiting ice cream
MGM reshop
CNN instead of using monkeys
He's dressed as people
They used
People suspended on wires and dress
Monkey bellhop yuan
Uniforms
Terrifying
Generations
Vivian ring finally getting credit long after her death
For her heroic Rescue of monkeys under her
Your last story of someone going from Zero to Hero comes from Bim adewunmi
Estrenos10 never said it is a truth
Universally acknowledged that there is no greater pleasure than
Cracking unit
But sometimes you need something a little more exhilarating and that's when you turned
A true American Hero
Pete the groin Crush
It was recently profiled in
The Philadelphia Inquirer
Fifty-two-year-old Pete's calvo also known as
The groin guy on
PT pressure
Used to be a welder in a past life
His true Queen
The Krush Groove
It was like the missing piece of the puzzle for me he says
Wuxi Pennsylvania
Adelaide he has one job
Applying pressure to
The people's groins off the surgery
Until the bleeding stop
Which can mean he's standing there
Crushing on your groin
Turn up to 40 minutes
Pizza Delight saying and indeed Excel
A crushing your groin
By his own estimate
He's consensually crushed more than 10,000 growing
And he's so good
That he is one
Awards
I'm holding someone's growing for 20 minutes they tend to remember me and nobody else has he
Presumably with a straight face
He might sound like a man who's watch The Sopranos a bit too enthusiastic
Ugly but he's okay henchman without technique
Pete's hotdogs groin crushing down to an art
Thanksgiving three-finger method that doesn't fatigue his whole hand
Pip crushing drawings
The save lives off of surgery but he's a gentleman to
How do you tell one patient
I couldn't have been more privileged
To hold your groin
He's been doing this for 15 years and he knows
Deep in his
Got
That it's the only job for him
You'll never forget my name
Oh my face
Sadly
One of these three stories of heroism is
True was it from Adam is Zamboni driver and his son
Let's bake
Place of Ursula the sea witch in Ariel in Disney on Ice when no one else could do it
From Amy was Vivien Leigh the famous actor
Actress who we now know
Saved
The original Monkees
The Wizard of Oz by smuggling them under her voluminous skirt
Orphan Bim adewunmi the groin Crusher
Of Philadelphia
Which of these is the real story weave
I do know that
For cardiac catheterization
They do pressure the groin
So I'll go with the groin Crusher
You're going to go to the growing pressure because of your medical knowledge all right
Your choices game story of Pete the groin Crusher what we
Spoke
I'm very proud to say
City hero him
They call me the growing pressure what you up to
That was
Pete the grindcrusher of course
Ski Avila Philadelphia we found out about
Via a profile by Stephanie Farr who writes for the Philadelphia Inquirer
She tells us
That she profiled him because so many of his patients
Got in touch with her and said you should profile this guy
We love him true story
Congratulations can you got it right by picking them story been one point but more importantly you want a prize
The voice of anyone you might choose
On your voicemail congratulations
And now the game where people who proved how good they are at their chosen profession find out how well they do with something they didn't choose
It's not my job
Charles Tillman known as peanut was one of the greatest defensive backs ever to play football
He was the winner of the Walter Payton Man of the Year Award for
Is charitable and Community work off
The field
And you'll be at the Super bowl next week to help is that it
The next winter
Charles Tillman welcome to wait wait don't tell me
And I can't see y'all so I do a lot of radio
They have like a
Yeah
1 2 3
So you're a jerk or selling the great quarterback
You actually went
The Super Bowl with the Bears not a lot of pee
People can say that sadly
I got to ask cuz we know the Super Bowls has big
Event we all watch
What is it like to be a
Player involvement
I mean you're preparing for a football game and I understand that's a pretty hard thing to do. All the
Distractions of Lake media week
In the week leading up to that get in the way
Pretty damn boring
A picture
You say the same
Over and over again
You know how
Talk about
Peyton Manning
You know I thought about Peyton Manning for 5 days straight
Someone took a picture of me with my head on the table
Getting ready to eat some glue
Getting the same boring questions did you ever like get fed up and just start making stuff up like yeah I saw Peyton Manning shoot a guy once
You you make that up with the people from like
People who normally cover football European
The people from Asia and they're just there because of Super Bowl
Do I need an umbrella
Can you set can you remember really good one
So I can feel like making up a bunch
I hate to ask but what kind of sex
This lady was
I don't know what exactly I said to the lady I just met
Get out of my way I love it
Among other extraordinary cheat
You played against Tom Brady and you've intercepted that I think twice in one game
Search like a legend about greatest football
Quarterback has ever lived it yet mean
Did you guys find that like intimidating or like
Inspiring
Like I'm going to go out and
Pick that guy off
Imma take option number 2 imma go on
I think he is
This is not the greatest
Play the game play I don't think anyone
Intimidated
I mean there's a second-year player that when I was damn your beetle
So you don't think players
If he's the greatest will I want to go again
We heard that you
You play the game when your wife was a
Extremely pregnant
And she might have gone into labor at any moment
Yasso
This was 2012 my wife was pregnant
Review with Lauren phone
Lortone back to the question hey what you going to do if your wife goes into labor before the game
Laughing well I'm missing the game I'm going to go see my daughter be born
They're their there they're just athletes but I felt like I was attacked because I made
Smart choice
The Family Choice
I want to go be with my family and watched the birth of my daughter
I know women is it hard people think
You put in a baby comes out your vajayjay
The lot of complications that can go wrong
All of a sudden I'm really interested in what you told those reporters about sex
Nickname for that
After the Glitter
To the game
My wife now we go home
Changes and everything gets her bags
And we go straight to the hospital at like
Midnight
12:30
I have my daughter's little
Next day I have a daughter that night
Come On Eileen
To talk to you but we have asked you to play a game this time we're calling
Now that's what I call an offensive line
You know a lot about defense you're very good at that but what do you know about defensive lines that is
Things people said or did that offended people
I'm going to ask you about three offensive lines get two questions right you want a price one of our listeners
Bill who is Charles Tillman playing
Diane Schultz
Alright you ready to do this
Alright big also
Is presumably listening at home
Subaru
Charles during the early days of
Spaceflight
TV stations with awesome often broadcast the Ashton
Do not slide
And that's it was worried that one of their astronauts Improv
Particular
Would swear
When the whole world was watching him
In order to prevent that NASA did
What
Hey they told him that for safety sake
He had to wear a gag
So he wouldn't quote inhale
Space
Be through a careful psyops campaign they convinced them that the most offencive swear he could possibly say
Was
Gadzooks
Or see they hypnotize them
So he would
Hum
Anytime
He wanted
To swear
Amazon
I can see you're right that's what they did wow
I've never said
What astronaut they did it
2 but it is absolutely true
That astronaut
Conrad
While he was on the moon when I get polymer
Weirdly hum
All the time so we have our suspicions
Alright Charles II
BBC Radio goes to Great Lengths
To keep its listeners
Safe from a fence
Content
They even
Put a decade-long ban on what
Song because I thought it was a fence
Was it a Madonna's Like a Virgin
Bi
Estes cop killer
Orsi's Bobby Pickett the Monster Mash
I'm going to have to
To go with my
AIC
You'd think
It was the month
They said this was back in the sixties and song came out they did not play for
For 10 years do they thought it was
A quote to
Morbid
It was a graveyard smash
You can win here we go
Even professional wrestling is not immune to worrying about giving offense
At one time the world championship wrestling
How to make
What's weeping chain
Hey each wrestler was
Required to say
I'm just kidding
Before trash-talking there Epona
B instead of heels
Wrestling villains were to be
Be called sensible Flats
Corsi they were told to
Stop calling chairs guitars and ladders brought in
Into the ring to hit people
Foreign objects
Instead call them International
No objects
Bass off the audience in them laughing
The last one
You're all right that's what happened
Bill how did Charles Peanut Tillman do in our quiz
We just saw why the peanut is
Chicago
Congratulations
Bedtime
I'll be there
Chicago Bears and Carolina Panthers he's recipient of the Walter Payton Man of the Year award
Which is presented by Nationwide information about his charity
The Charles Tillman Cornerstone Foundation can be found online
Charles peanut
Tillman thank you so much for joining us and wait wait don't tell me
In just a minute curl up with a blanket I mean really curl up with it and I
Listener Limerick challenge game call 1aaa quick way to join us on the air
Will be back in a minute with more wait wait don't tell me
From NPR
Support frame
PR in the following message
Should come from fat
Weather moving to a new city or moving down the street
Feather believe
Can you stop when life change
Your furniture should be able to
To change with
Become a featherman
And get access to over a hundred fifty
Two pieces of high quality furniture
With the option to add swap
Buy or return
When life or taste
Change
See how easy it
Need to live free of the burdens
Furniture ownership
Available in LA
Orange County New York and Saint Francis
Feather
Furniture that
Changes with
Before you can start your day you like to know what's
Happening in the news
That's what up first
The Morning News podcast from
The news you need
To take on the day
Just about 10 minutes
Listen to up first
NPR one app
Wherever you get you
From NPR and WBEZ
Easy Chicago this is wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz I'm Bill Curtis Ware playing this week with Bim adewunmi
And Amy
Dickinson
And here is your host
That's a Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown
Chicago
In just a minute bills rhymin and I'm Garfunkel and I listener Lynbrook Atlas game
Give us a call at 10008 wait wait that's one-eighth 89248
Right now panels more questions for you from this
This week's news
Amy this month
Frontier became the first major airline
When to encourage passengers
To do what to their flight attendant
Tip
Amy
Frontier Airlines will not allow you to tip your flight attendant on the food and drinks that you buy in the best way to respond
Onto that offer is if I had any
Extra money to give away do you think I'd be flying Frontier Airlines
However if you're on Frontier if you're wondering
What the right amount is to get your flight attendant
A good tip
Corset 10% great tip is 20% and the best tip is don't fly Frontier Airline
Tip the guy middle
The plane starts crashing
Can your oxygen thing
How's it Goin Down ukulele
I'm tripping the pipes that exactly
Okay fine if you need us to tip the flight attendants you're not paying them
Fine the please
Don't put in a bathroom
Damn there's never been a better time to
Baby single now that we know it
Employers in China
Offering single employees
They offering them
Small children
No
You are single
You seem to be enjoying your life in your free time
It's like maternity leave but it's very very very premature
Actually not even before that
Dating is yes
Dating Lee
Indeed
Two companies in China are offering their female employees
8 days of
Dating leave
Paid vacation
To go out and date
This is only offered to women
30 or older because apparently trying to 30 is the age were being single
Considered an emergency
I've been I've been getting
The one problem is that your boss will know exactly what you were doing on your break you coming on Monday and he likes
So how did it go
Also there any don't forget to women in
Well isn't that so
I believe that's a China for reasons that are historic
Unpleasant have
A shortage of
Available women
So
I know
Coming up as Lightning fill in the blank refers to
Is the game where you have to listen
For the rhyme if you'd like to play on air call and leave a mess
Triple Eight way
That's 18889
24 Yukon
Click the contact us link on our website that's wait wait. Npr.org
There you can find out about attending our weekly live shows right here at the Chase Bank auditor
Chicago upcoming show February 7
In Savannah
Georgia and if you don't want to leave the house but still want some wait wait action
You can play our new interactive game on your spark
Just ask your Alexa or Google home
Open the way
Weight quiz and Bill and I will be there with you just the three of us
And you might even win a prize
Hi you're on wait wait don't
Hi Peter I'm Alex and I'm in Lafayette Colorado
Lafayette is
10 miles due east of Boulder
What are you doing
I work I actually work for the city of Aurora
Manage their Water Resources Division in the water
Water Resources out there in Colorado that's pretty serious stuff you have to fight people off with the weapon
All the time
Alexander welcome to the show Bill Kurtis is going to be a few 3 News related limericks
To the last word or phrase missing
From each
If you can fill in that last word or phrase correctly into the limericks will be winter you ready to play
Yes I am so excited to play
Here
Want to know our kids
Is gender
Goodonya
Try this pasta dish
Baked by Aunt Tanya
Well
What do you think
Is the cheese blue
Or pink
It's revealed by our tasty
Gender reveal parties are all the
Rage meaning they're everywhere and they make people
Very angry
Chain Italian restaurant called Villa Italian
The kitchen is offering a new way to reveal what kind of genitals your baby will have
With their patented exclusive gender reveal lasagna
If you're having a girl the
The cheese in lasagna
Cut it and expose it is
Pink
And of course if you're having a boy the lasagna is
Is full of sausage
Story
At least a couple times
One guy started a wildfire
Holy things reveal way more about the parents
Children gender reveal party
Bread in the first place
Here is your next
Limerick
Hairzoo likes its pink
To be slim
There
City problem is Grimm
There's a pool in free weights
And some Zumba
At 8
We have built them a serpentine
Yes
It is a gym
Horse snake
The Melbourne Zoo Melbourne Australia has created
Snake gym help their chubby snakes
Some way
Can you imagine
How tough it is to lie about
Your diet when you're a snake
Don't know I didn't I didn't just gobble down for mice we can
I see them 1 2 3 4
Snakes at the gym
Now you have a great reason not to go
Straight to the
Part of me that's not my hat
Brightside for snakes using a gym is that they don't have to spend a lot of money and getting
I'm getting an outfit
But now I don't need yoga pants
Just one tube sock please I'll be on my way
All right
Here is your last
Limerick
My comforter
How will I find
It's number one
That's how I write
The weather in Tibet
You're never over
Forgetting
That's it
I will marry my
Blanket blanket
Have you thought about true love was dead
In the sad cold world
A woman in England is marrying her blanket
Something that isn't
And actually alive
Other not talking about like Michael Jack
Jackson's kid
Natural blanket
I know
England
Yes
Exotic sub
Her name is
Pascal celery
And she says closed my duvet is the longest strongest most
Unreliable relation
Kinship that I've ever had
Unquote
If things go well
In about nine months to have a new set of dish towels
She no longer put the cover on it
Yeah Bill how did Alexandra doing her quiz
Congratulations you got all free congratulations
Thank you so much thank you
Support for NPR in the following message come from feather
Weather moving to a new city
Car moving down this
Feather believe
You stop when life
Your furniture
Should be able to change
Become a feather meme
And get access to over a hundred fifty
Pieces of high quality furniture
With the option to add swap buy or return
When life or taste
Change see how easy it can
To live free of the burdens of furniture owner
Available in La Orange County
New York and San Francisco
Feather
Furniture that changes with you
That was my final game lightning fill in the blank each of our players with a 60 second
Answer as many filling
Questions is he or she
Each correct answer is worth two
Edible Amy each have two and Bim has
Alright we flip the coin Amie has elected to gophers
Fill in the blank
One day after postponing his testimony before the house
Former Trump lawyer blank was subpoenaed by the Senate
Intelligence
Michael Cohen
Like this week teachers and blank ratified a deal to end their first
Strike in 30 years
That's right on Tuesday a judge ruled that the investigation into
Do a contested Congressional
Blank sheet
Continue
Noah's North Carolina
Discovery of the Stonehenge
Play structure they said dated back
Thousands of years
Inform by residents that blank
It was
Not that
Thing but it was something else
All together
I'll give it to them today the resident said no we built that in the 1990s a state of emergency
Clear near Portland this week is health workers
Scramble 2
Contain a blank outbreak
Measles right on Tuesday Mariano Rivera
Became the first
Player ever
To be unanimously voted into the
Baseball Hall of Fame after after appearing in the local news a police officer in the UK named blank be
Became a viral sensation
Viral sensation
If your name was viral Sensation that would help
But know this police officer was named Rob
Banks
How long would I have been amazing if its name was viral sensation
The officer in question became an internet sensation
Screenshot in an interview with Britain's it
Annie posted on Twitter
Despite being praised rap
Kevin quotes the world's greatest name
Super policeman
Constable rob bank
Who is actually there to talk
But very serious issue
Law enforcement budget cuts along with his fellow office
Sergeant
Jimmy lock
And Captain
Vincent vehicular manslaughter
Bill how did any doing our quiz maybe Got 5 write 10 more points
She has a total of 12 + images
Oki doki
Saying they were treated unfairly President Trump
Tweeted his support for
From blank
Covington
Catholics
School on Tuesday the Supreme Court declined
To take action on a case that would threaten the protection
700000 undocumented
Yuan to fall under the
Blank
DACA
This week to White House recognized at 1
Secret ballistic
Missile bases
North Korea
Yes a man in Vietnam start
Ring from blood poison
The doctors gave him in in feet
Fusion of blank
Radiated Mountain Dew
No 15 cans of beer
On Tuesday research has announced a new blood test that could Aid in the early detection
The blank
New Alzheimer's
It was reported on Thursday that the ft
TC was considering a record-breaking
Heineken social media site blank
Fulfilling
To protect user data
Facebook
An Iowa man who won
$1
On a Lottery scratch off ticket demanded that the state lottery office
Blank
No
He demanded that they give him one of those
Giant novelty check name is Tyler Heath and he is truly vihear
Hero in the week's news
Just how much you paid for it immediately went down the Lottery headquarters in Des Moines
He said I'm a winner I want my big check
And the Iowa State Lottery employees said
Why not
So they made a big check pay to the order of Tyler Heap one American dollar
They took a picture of him in front of the state lottery logo he's grinning
He's having the best time
He says he's excited about his big win
But he really wishes he had gone for the lump
Some instead of opting to get a penny every 400 years
Bill how did Adam doing AR quiz
He has 12
Tide with Amy
All right how many event does bamboo need
To win
5 to win
Alright here we go this is for the game
On Tuesday the
The Supreme Court ruled that the White House could enforce Trump's ban on blanks in the military
Flight on Monday St Louis
It would no longer prosecute blank possession if it
It's under a hundred grand
No no marijuana
We're getting the cocaine don't worry but not yet
This week economic growth
Blank fell to its lowest rate in almost 30 years
No China
Lessen the large number of drones clocking the airspace over
Tokyo Japanese police
Bug zapper
No other drones with big neck
Hanging from
Rogers posted a video in which blank
Speak in his defense
Nights at the gym
His own adorable dogs
What he did the mouse
Truly amazing the favorite
Androma lead the nomination
Things for the 2019 blank award
Academy Midland Texas had to call police after getting locked in the blank that close at 10 p.m.
24-hour gym
Yes indeed
Man was a paying client of the 24 Hour Fitness
Jim Center
So he was in the locker room and was very surprised when he came out and found out he had been locked inside
Because it closed
Who's at 10
That's when a 24-hour fitness center closes cuz words no longer have meeting
The man was trapped
For just under an hour but was saved after he reached another 24 Hour Fitness which thankfully close at 11 p.m. like God intended
Bill did them do well enough to win
This is unusual Ben was headed for the Super Bowl
The only
Three rights needed five
And Adam
Special thanks once again to Farmhouse Tavern
And thanks for really bringing the
Wait wait NPR WBEZ Chicago
In association with the Urgent haircut Productions. Government benevolent over
Philip gotika rights are limericks are public address
Paul Friedman assisted by Simon Tran
Are interns are Alex McCone and Rachel klepper Lizbeth no BBJ
Jennifer Mills miles dornbos and Lillian Kingwood specials
2 Peter peanut Gwen
Technical business and office manager
Colin Miller
A production coordinator
An executive producer
Is Michael Vick
Now panel what is Rudolph Giuliani
Doing next
Bim adewunmi
He's going to be the growing Crusher general of New York
Amy Dickinson
He's going to embark on his fourth
Fifth and sixth marriages
All at once
Adam Burke
It's going to be a official spokesperson of those Choose Your Own Adventure books
If you don't like the story
Change it and then change it again and then change it back
Well it really does any of that panel
Ask you about it on wait wait don't tell me
Out of one many thanks all of you for listening
I am Peter Sagan we will see you next week
This
Is NPR