Support for this NPR Podcast
In the following message
Did come from Better Health
Online counseling by license
Professional count
Specialized
Issues including the
Depression stress
And anxiety
Visit betterhelp.com wait to learn more
And get 10% off your first month
From NPR and WBEZ Chicago
Tell me the NPR news quiz
Take me to the beach
Your friends bill
And here's your host at the chase
Chase Bank Auditorium
Chicago
Peter Sagan
It is
Summer the time to reflect take a break and think about
Where we've been
How nice will it be in a few years when we get to do that all the time because every
You season will be summer
They were taking it easy and listening back to some of my favorite moments from earlier
Year there once was a time when I was merely a
Legendary
Anchorman
But I'm so much more than that
No
Listen
From NPR and WBEZ Chicago this is
Wait wait don't tell me the
NPR news quiz
Sorry image
Mitch McConnell nobody blocks this
What's Bill
Listen to my Infinity tongue
Lay me down for the triple words
Score I'm Scrabble
Is it hot in here
I blame global warming sleep tight baby
You're about to get a dose of
Conan
Georgia I'll take a bite of your juicy Peach
Lino traduction although we
Always introduce
Anyway
When we went
St Louis in May of this year
Peter got to tell the good people of that City
That they were off
The Seether
Wizard of Oz
Everybody in St Louis love the card
And there is no card no more beloved
Other than Hall of Fame
Ozzie Smith
Winner of 13 Gold Glove award the claim is
The best shortstop ever to play the game and known around these parts as The Wizard of Oz
You're simply the wizard
Go crazy Saint Louis hits Ozzie Smith
The Ozzy you came here to steal
Louis to join us from where you live now that you're
Retired which is
Right here
Turn the game back in the nineties
You never left
And this is why
I know why would I leave I always wondered about that because there's a there's a kind of cliche
In sports that
When somebody
You know
Does something amazing for
For the local team
Like they hit the homerun to win the
Illegal
They say that guy will never pay for the beer and the
This town again
So is it true that you can't pay for your own beer and
Understand again
All right
Just say you know
I'll have a beer in just
Just stand there
I bet not
Do you still follow the game sometimes I understand
Retired players at camp
Enjoy it because they enough
Yes I follow the game I go to spring training
Yep and I usually go with
What yeah
10 days in
When they start playing games
I get out of there
Do you do NE like you do any like
Construction of the shortstop's you like wall you need to do
Is Leap 30
Sideways get the ball
Jump 10 ft over the head of the guy coming in the second base and throw to first
Did they come up to you and ask questions
What kind of questions I asked you
Wescom
How do you get into the floor
You know when the one thing that I always like
Explain the people
Yolanda Sanchez
She stays in mouth
Right sell the one thing that you don't want to do
Princess Madeleine
Is be stagnating
Yeah there has to be some type of mood
It allows you to go left
After writing
And that that probably is
The one thing
When I talk to her
She guy
To have some type of
Movement
Cuz that's what allows you
That's right
Never flat
It's interesting because you mention
Virginia laws of physics
Cuz I was watching
Your highlights
That was physically
Half of what I say
Couldn't be done
I always ask
Expression of of elite athletes like you
How young were you when you knew that
You know I don't know if you ever really knowing
Exactly when that
Was a kid I used
To lay on the floor
Roll the ball up to
The ball hitting
A hand without
Without seeing
I called my eyes
Hit it and got hit in the head
Yeah well I will happen
That's part of it but I also used
We have to pay for
I used to throw the ball up on
One sided
And run around to the other side
In Hope
Yeah
The ground
And people are sitting
You're wondering now
Yeah
Did you ever get there
Did you do it
I never did I never did
But it was
Was that type of
Termination
Yeah
That made me
I'm going to say again
Why can you play it just seems
Pure Magic
Just seems like
Natural ability
That you could leap up in the air
Both feet
3 feet off the ground
Hagler first baseman
Without her
Let me say this
Pikeville
I'm standing back there and I'll listen
Bill did you just
You just talk.
It just comes out
I'm sure
Do you know so what you do is
The gift is you
You try and maintain it as long as
Shared with a
Could you possibly can and
Never taking it
Just want to say
Chicago watch
Channel 9
I was always amazing how you
Is so cool
B-47
Even right now
Now you like the coolest
Theater
Help me understand help me be a better person
How do you keep that level of cool but still compete
Aesthetic
Brian awadis
You just
Just be yourself
Do you know okay
When your mom's friends is easy
3516 myself
The 230 lb guide
We're trying to kill me with his feet
I would pee my pants that would be honest being myself
Never let them see you sweat
Well as the Smith we've invited you here to play a game that this time we're calling
Wear off
To see the wizard
When you play it is The Wizard of Oz
Just a wizard
For your magic
Local plays at shortstop so we thought we'd ask you about
The original
Wizard of Oz
The classic
Movie
Answer to level three questions correctly you win our prize one of our listeners the boys
Is there choice in their voicemail
Bill who is the great Ozzie Smith
Drew Richardson
St Louis MO
All right all right
People say they don't make them like they used to and
It's true The Wizard of Oz
That which of these
The real reason that
Set The Wizard of Oz
Was as it was made
Could not be made
Today
Hey the actor
Who played the munchkins
Volpe to frack
The regular wage
Due to an old
Pay by height
B
The Wicked Witch's broomstick
The scarecrow's outfit in all of the fake snow we're made of a
Asbestos
Or see the 1990
Before religion
Freedom Act
Which prevents witches or wiccans
From being presented in negative light
Call
Let's see
Idiocracy
What can I tell an anecdote
So I read that you know the Tin Man with all the silver
Bet that makeup
Was so toxic
That it sent the original actor
Trip to the hospital
Genesis
Girl that seen in the poppy field Arrow sleeping
Snow falls on their faces
Alright next question The Wizard of Oz has been of course
The pop culture
Your treasure sensor
Sometimes
Things from the movie pop up an unexpected
Two places at
In which of these
Hey after Margaret Thatcher died
In 2013
The song Ding Dong
The Witch Is Dead re-entered
British music charts at number two
B Popeye's restaurant once offered something called the gizzard
Of Oz
Or see Garth Brooks
2003 man behind the curtain tour in which
What you saying his entire set
In a booming voice from behind a curtain
Just like the wizard
Is they say what are you saying that you're right that's what happened
All right
Let's see if you can be as perfect in this as you were in just about everything
Thing else
There was a fair amount of acrimonious
On the set of Wizard of
Focused on
One of the performers
Who was it
Today
Scarecrow actor Ray Bolger
Who walked around the set saying actually I'm very smart
And Mansfield
B-flat Ami roskopf a Russian method actor
Who played the lead
Flying monkey and well
All decided to act like a monkey on
On the set if you know what I mean
Orsi's Terry
Who played Toto the dog
Paid more per week than most of the human actor
He work
What's total play
Read it to me
Terry the dog who played Tuttle brought down like a hundred fifty bucks a week which of the time is
The equivalent to
$2,000
Use well-paid pup
Bill was Ozzy
As perfect as he was here as he wasn't filled
Score
I've got your lifetime stats
Ozzie Smith
Try to remember the Baseball Hall of Fame Apartments Legend president of the day
Gateway PGA reach Foundation their 10th Annual Gala and golf tournament September 22nd and 21st
The greatest shortstop who ever played thank you so much for being with you
When they come back over here are panelist as you've never heard from them before because you weren't supposed to hear it
Anna Kendrick star of Pitch Perfect
Picked a peck of pickled peppers
Will be back in a minute with more wait wait don't tell me
From NPR
Support for this podcast
Send the following message comes from
MailChimp
So you want to grow your business
No one
Male chimps all-in-one Market
Platform that's why
It has all the marketing stuff you need all in one place
Do you can save time and money
It's powered by a marketing CRM so you can
Collect organize
Understand your audience
All to help you Market
Smarter and grow
Faster
Learn more at MailChimp
I'm Shanker V.
Host of NPR's hidden brain
Deeply here to tell you about our summer series
YouTube .0
Ideas and advice
About how you can respond to life
Chaos to it just checked my
Just checked my phone real quick
With wisdom
Listen to Hidden brain
Every week
From NPR and WBEZ Chicago
PR news quiz
I'm Bill Kurtis
It's in here is your host
Chicago PD
So we got something special for you right now
Now when we get together to
Do our show we always spend a little time
Before the show begins
To just chat with yawning
It's just a little time
You know warming up
Not
Ferrer
Until now
If you've ever wondered
What we talk about when we
Thank you or not list
Sing well
Listen
I don't take up too much time but she's
But Paul had an amazing story
I flew here
To Chicago
How to do a show
What to get a puppy
I flew here to get a puppy two weeks
To go. Just outside
Chicago
It was a
Call H2
Golden retriever Newfoundland
And it was at a rescue place
South Side Chicago and
But I flew in on that day where you guys had that huge
Snow storm
Answer me in the puppy we're stuck in the airport for 24 hours
It outgrew the carrier while we're there
Can you list
To start there with a puppy
It was good there was something about it like when I was back in O'Hare today
How's it going yeah
Yeah I remember
It's like you're home now
I stood in line right here
4 hours
You were talking about the fact
After you've been getting sick
Public radio people
Yeah I get I get in
NPR people
What coming to the
Michelle and their front they are nicely
Like Tom said they nice
I can always tell him because they're the ones
Two things that I might not
What's a here
And then I'm also one
I'm on comedy
Osho
The new Negroes
So the NPR crowd
Can't say
The title of that shows without
Earlier this year we learned that the Boston accent is
Considered one of the sexiest
Shenzhen well that was surprising
And somewhat unsettling
It did give us a chance
How to call up an old
Lyndon Johnson please say hello
How to remodel Yahtzee
City of Carthage
Hey how are you
I'm Blue
You talk to having a lot of fun making fun of my
We do it all the time
The question for you Ray
Is have you in your life
Does having a boss
Have you found it to be very sexy as it had that effect
And the people you'd wanted to have that effect on
Many years ago
His wives and girlfriends also with the Boston accent
No no no no. All of them
As a kind of
Test
We have decided
That we've asked you
To read a couple of romantic line
From movies
We sent those to you
How to receive text messages
Citgo butts
I'll just wait until you say back to me
In your in your most Charming sexy bought the next
Set ready
Words that start with s
How about this the heart knows
What the heart
Wants
You want me to say
I wish I knew how to quit you
I wish I knew how to
Draw me like one of your French girls Jack
Really
Draw me like one of your French
Last one last one ready
My taste
Very
Singular
Myspace
Smoldering
You know what that was
Shades of Ray
Brenna python requests
For you from the week's news
Helen
Gwyneth Paltrow is expanding her goop
Empire
She's adding a new section of a website offer
Ring products and advice
Nice to whom
Yes it is
Universal Services Empire called Group which offers all these wonderful things
For women will now miss Paltrow has launched
Gucci Mane
Featuring a men's clothing line and mail focused articles such as what to do about low T
Testosterone and
How to have difficult conversations
With Friends
Sounds like the one where you tell your friends
You're getting lifestyle advice
From Google
She gets the worst
Advice and now she
She's trying to give the worst advice
Justin Moore
That's what she's doing at some point tell women
How to put a like a thing in their vagina
We men are very nervous about what she's going to tell us today
Oh boy
You need a vacay
Does Idina Menzel
Goop
Men's Gucci men's gopher
Gross first of all girl
I didn't actually called Goodfellas
What is men's beauty products like $340 jar of
Replenishing night
Which is the same exact night cream available in the women's store but the men's version
Incomes in a beer can
What is night cream
It's it's
It's a cream that you put on your
Fascinated
Ritual in a sentence
Have one
And I said to myself
Cocoa butter where you at absolutely
Okay not a black cross guy
Didn't we warn you
This is basically get out without the murder in Michigan
Anna Kendrick first became famous as a star of the
The Twilight
It's amazing how much
She's triumphed over that early adversity
Let's get ready to join us in September of last year until this at
Her origin story goes back
Much further than that
Yeah I started in theater when I was
Well I started in local theater when I was like five or six and then I
Did the play Annie which is near the gateway drug for all girls trip to theater then
Professional
Chosen
My parents were gracious enough to drive
Take me from Maine
To New York City for these additions and
When he was 14
Are we on the Greyhound bus
And I audition
Before
The musical high society and eventually I got that
Wow wow
I'll see your parents that we've had it
There's a bus ticket call us when you're famous
Do you remember Annie when you were in Annie in in local
No I was Tessie who said
You know they're fighting and I won't get no sleep all night you always remember your first line
Are you telling me that there is somebody who is probably still in this world whose walk around knowing that Anna Kendrick audition
For their production of Annie
And you did not get cast as Annie
Yeah she's a real succubus to this day
There's relief in that because they've done a study that shows
Kids who play Annie often become procrastinators
Sit start tomorrow
You have got away with that I mentioned I wanted to check it is
You were doing you were working a lot as a
Professional actor in films you played apus
George Clooney in
The Heir Amazon
Oscar
But is it true that the thing that really sort of propelled you was the pitch
I think I should have had a really wide audience and as you say like this
Sting really took off which was
Singing with a flask
When I
You know what everybody was
Wishing for that
Film everybody kind of meat
Did the saying just so that another thing you that you could sing
And I knew how to do this
Dorky thing with this cops on cuz I
I seen the two girls doing it on a YouTube video and I taught myself how to do it
Because I have too much free time on my hands
So I said well I mean if I'm going to say anyway I can show you the thing that I
Can do and they put it in the movie and then
No became a single and they recorded it as a
The fall song and music video for it so
You know learn de stuff
Yeah yeah if you were actually at that moment
Watching YouTube videos
Looking for the next big gimmick
Oh my God that's right
Well I was looking at stomach related videos so I'm not sure how that's
Can I help
Yeah it was it was a video of a gang of stung
What were they doing
They were scurrying across the front lawn and then they thought they heard something
And they all like almost started crying
Because you know that these were vile little creatures
Each other's backs
Do they do that like arrange themselves as I Care Central Point
Did it all directions
Really have it easy but
Pitch Perfect of course if you haven't seen it what is wrong with you let him tell him it is a movie about competitive
Acapella singing
Which is a real thing
In this world
Unfortunately I think it's pretty awesome
And ended your movies cuz they're 11
Three of them have they led to
Explosion a Revival acapella
Unfortunately yes
Do you spend some time with real acapella group
I actually didn't for
I actually had done before
Poor
So I went a friend kind of
Take me to an acapella competition
And I thought it was going to be very
Dorky and
And I ended up by the end of it I was like do you think we can go backstage and meet them
Party that they were throwing at their college I'm going to try to get to know them cuz
When you see somebody do something that
It's really impressive you know it doesn't matter if it's considered
You got really into it
Sure
Made out with a knock
Acapella member
College
Best night of my life
I wonder if ever like say it I could pillow cup
Petition
If anybody ever like
Whipped out a guitar or keyboard it just ruins it
Chicken food
We we we we we wanted to do this with you just as a little sort of pulmonary for the real quiz
Which is
We were looking around it turns out that a lot of a cappella groups
Have really odd names
Just wanted to ask if you could tell the real ones
The fake ones
And it just received
How you doing this
So I'm just going to read the names you tell me if you think they're real or not
Oh I will have no idea but absolutely
Ohio University
That is very clever
No it is it's it's a big university
Sophie's voice
Not right not real no not real
One last one
Rhythm and Jews
I love that I have bad reception in Chicago represents
Lana Kendrick
It is as delightful to talk to you as always imagined it would be and we have asked you to play a game
That we're calling
Pitching
Perfect
As we have discussed you start on the Pitch Perfect movie so we thought we talked to you
About pitching perfectly
Specifically
A no-hitter
Thrown by Pittsburgh Pirate pitcher
DACA
Back in 1970
Answer questions about Dock Ellis no no
They called in the game
And you want a price one of our listeners the voice of their choice on their voicemail
Still who is Anna Kendrick playing
Shannon Durfee of Minneapolis Minnesota
Who's the first question Dock Ellis
Walked eight batters that day he hit one but he still did not get it up a hit
In a 9 Inning
Complete game
What made his
No hitters so unique
In the annals
A baseball
Was it a right-handed pitcher he threw this one was his left hand quote
Just for kicks
Because of the walks we actually lost
The game 1-0
Orsi's he was high on LSD the whole time
I mean I wish it was C but I guess I'll
Baby
Can you can you hear the shouts of all the middle-aged men listening to radio the radio right now who is showing the right answer
Can use cuz they're all saying it was
See ya this is one of the famous games.
Pitched a no-hitter
On LSD
You still have two more chances here so there's still a chance
As you can imagine pitching in the major league game while tripping on LSD has it
Challenges
Ella said that during the game he had to picture around which of these problems a believing the catcher was Richard Nixon
Be not being able to either
Feel or see either of his arms
Corsi constantly resisting the urge to take a bite of the ball with
Smelled like a hamburger
It is a yes he
He says at one point he looked in and Richard Nixon was behind the plate and even
Where is the batter was Jimi Hendrix and he was swinging and Electric
Guitar
All right now
Dock Ellis as you can imagine
Did not limit his misbehavior to that one
Game later on in his career
The game against the Cincinnati Reds he attempted to do what
A picture underhanded
B roll the ball to the plate
Orsi
Hit with a pitch
Every
Single member of the opposing team
Are right
The reasons don't rap song
Movies angry at the Cincinnati Reds
Who decided
Throw a ball hit every single member of the opposing team
He
Hit three of them and then threw two balls over the heads of the next 2 and he was then removed
From the gang of pretty interesting fellow
Let me just say that about Dock Ellis
How did Anna Kendrick do in Ark
What a winner or two out of
3 and a graduation
Drake's new movie is a simple favor it is out now Anna Kendrick thank you so much
Thank you for everything you've done bye bye
Well they come back one of the greatest players and one of the greatest coaches of all time
Play not my job one of the worst games of all time
Olympia
Support for wait wait don't tell me in the following mess
Message comes from rocket mortgage by Quicken Loan
Imagine how would feel
Pills to have an award-winning team of mortgage experts
Make the home buying process
Smoother for you
The history of industry-leading online lending technology
Rocket mortgage is
Changing the game
Visit rocket mortgage.com
Weight Equal Housing lender
Licensing office
Fifty states MLS
Consumer access. Organizer
Rocket mortgage
My Quicken Loans
Push button
Get more
US Women's Soccer Team just won his fourth world
And it has been way more successful than
Get the women say they are paid
Less than half
What the male soccer players
And now they're suing for eco
Alipay
Find out more about this on
Indicator from and
From NPR and WBEZ Chicago
This is wait wait don't tell me the NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Kurtis and here is your house
At the Chase Bank Auditorium in Chicago Peter Sagal
Thank you though everybody because we are public radio people every
Assumes were unathletic nerds and we aren't any good at sports
And they are of course
Right
We are interested in talking to people who are good at
In 2017 we ventured
Francisco
Do talk to the
The greatest wide receiver of all-time
Jerry Rice
Although he disagreed
He thought he was the greatest
Player of all time
What is it always seem self that way
What's a star athlete
Nelson nerd
Football round myself
Really I'm so uncomfortable that when you say you were a nerd what you like
When you say nerd what do you mean
Very quiet
Have very large
And really skinny
So
I would walk around with my hands
My pocket.
Time because everybody was
4 day notice
Telling me
Is it like you were embarrassed
As a kid
Because your hands
We're so large
All time Hall of Famer
You
Adidas football
Equivalent
Rudolph the Red-Nosed Reindeer
I can do that
That is amazing
Can I tell you
Delighted to have
Incredibly large hands
I got one last question
It often the wide receivers lineup
Outside
In your office right across from
The safety or cornerback
Is going to be
Trying to cover you
Is what passes
Between you two guys
Cuz you're looking at him he's looking at you
And you and he knows he's going to try to stop you and you know he's not going to
I mean like trash talk
No I just look at the D
Tobacconist
Or Jerry Rice who's invited you here to play a game we're calling
Take a picture of antenna
Time for Hannah Montana
Reformed tandems with quarterback Joe Montana so we thought we'd ask you about that other great Montana
Hannah
You looking me with a look of confusion do you know who Hannah Montana was
The name Hannah Montana
Just so you know
With a fictional car
Played by the on the Disney Channel by the very real Miley Cyrus
The TV show about a young girl who had a normal life but her other life was being pumped
What's the plot of show
So we're going to ask you three questions about that
And if you get two of them
Are your absolute confidence you're not fidgeting in your chair looking for an exit
Who is Jerry Rice playing for
Let's do it alright
When Disney was created with your back then they considered a bunch of names based on place names
Hannah Montana
Thought of the name Alexis
Texas
Why couldn't they use that one
Hey the state of Texas charges royalties for any commercial use of its name
B cast member Moises Arias had a thick
Stiliyan accent and he pronounces
Alexis Texas
Alexis Texas is the name of a well-known adult film
Yeah it was he elected
The Texas they were afraid what would happen when kid fans of the show where they Google the name Alexis
I got that one right
Hannah Montana was a big hit man for some years influenced many artists and performers such as who may
Actor Eli Roth
Will listen to her music to prepare for his role
Stone Cold
Killer in the movie Inglorious Bastards because you said
It made him feel insane
Beat performance artist Marina Abramovic
Hearing one Hannah Montana song conceived
The artist is
Present
What she sat in silence
700 hour
4C lin-manuel Miranda are three composer who says Hannah struggles
She tried to become famous inspired
The early scenes as Alexander Hamilton
Kids climb to the top
Do you know I've been
Prepare myself
For this all day
So
You guys not going
Yes it's a
Apparently listening to Hannah Montana put him in the mood to beat people to death with a bat all right
Hannah Montana has a lot of dedicated fans but some of them may surprise you like which of these a vice president Mike Pence
Who considers her music quote
Wholesome but danceable
Who has Hannah Montana's initials
How to turn on the shoulder
Orsi's artist Damien Hirst who called his installation of a decomposing beef cow the real Hannah Montana
If we can weaponize the look of incredulity the Jerry Rice
Give me the right now
So
EOC the Damien Hirst
The British conceptual artists
Digging her fans
Put a decomposing cow in a
Thing and called it the real Hannah Montana
I wouldn't put it by him but it was actually the tattoo
Store was
Super Bowl MVP Super Bowl champ Kidney Foundation to promote Kidney Health
Thank you so much for joining us
Support for this podcast is brought to you by Discover card
You check things all the time like you
Your email or social
Media but
Discover ask
What about checking something as important as your credit
12 Discover it makes
Quick and easy
With their credit
Scorecard which is free forever
Even if you're not a cut
See your FICO credit score and other important credit
Mason and once you know your score
You should check
To see if your current credit
What is the best fit
4u discover.com
/ credit
Edit scorecard
Limitations
Apply
Support also comes from tapestry collect
By Hilton
Which dares
To be original
From a converted Warehouse
It's now home to
Cotton sail hotel in Savannah
Georgia to the hidden Speakeasy beneath the gram hoe
Washington DC
Each of their hotel
Tails and braces
It's neighborhood vibe
For a truly original
Experience
When you're looking for the sentence
Approach to the local scene stay in the
Tapestry collection by Hilton Hotel
That's as unique
As You Are
Visit hilton.com
Wait wait
Now what would be great
Play r b without a great
Coach well according to at least one of them they'd still be great player
Coach Mike D'Antoni of the Houston Rockets
Jaundice
In January
This year we asked him about working with his Superstar on his
What's it like getting to watch James Harden play every night
Special
He's better than what most people think he is
News about stocks
James Harden is known for his extraordinary offensive play and also for his amazing
Beard
Have you ever had to talk to me about the beard like
Do nobody can see your uniform number
You need to
Nomos time is like you know you got to get there or you got
Part of your duties as head coach
He seemed pretty serious are you allowed to tease him about his beard
Very carefully
When did you figure out that you could be a coach in this
I'm 39 years old now retire from playing and I'm looking around and going now why
United really good teams in Europe I got lucky
You're not like anybody else is just
Speed at the right spot at the right time and
When back and started coaching the NBA
Do you have like
Psychologic
Hugo
Techniques
Can you use
That would mean that I would have
Today and the players have to be smart so we're not messenger
Tempo Style
Do players like
Playing for you because of that or is it exist
Exhausting
There's been something to happen like that and obviously I've been to different cities
I've been fired a few times so
No no
Don't like being fired then like when you get it
No they get me fired
Well that definitely is interesting because you're
Coaching
Incredibly well-paid
Credibly talented athlete
Who have been at the
The Pinnacle of their sport
For probably the entire career
Like everybody in the NBA
For the Superstar
How do you
Handle
People like that
Who are the stars of The League
Well there's a lot of groveling and begging and
Completing rice exam that you need to have to
Psychological
Ecotechne James Harden say or Chris Paul both Superstar
If you want them to do something they're not doing
Or you want them to do something better or different
How do you do that
We work together and get my experience in there and we
We're very analytic base now so a lot of it is
Data
Driven where they can
See that it makes sense
Give me an example of a time where
The problem
Is soft by data
Will you have a player that shoots primarily two-point shots and says 3-point shot sorry I'm not going
I can show him some the data that
Shooting that shot there is not his
Affectiva shooting
3 points you have to change your name
They don't know that
Points is taking about 20 second about 20 years for the NBA
Wait a minute
Touch
I Monday at 1 a.m.
NCAA men's team
Dusklight shards you probably heard of us
I didn't name the team
We have Scouts are most tonight we lost the game
This week by 49 points do you have any
Any advice for us is how to be a better
Start score more points with three points more than two points
The biggest cliche of every sports movie any of us have ever seen
It is the halftime motivation
Speak
Really
Well
Coach it is great to have you with us we've invited here today
To play our game and we call it
Mike D'Antoni
Meet Mike
Dan
Tony since your name is built out of three first names
Smut like a Transformer
Mike D'Antoni
We thought we'd ask you one question each about a mic
Add an
Panettone
You get to write
Comedian Mike
Could you Tony and Dan
Could be a Tony in Mike
You do any of those you win our prize one of our listeners the voice of their choice
From art show
Chucky who is coach Mike D'Antoni playing for
Jim Hogan of
Are you ready
First
Michael Jordan you may have heard of him he remains the world's most famous Mike
He was so famous during his heyday
That you can find
Which of these
He's a a shrine to him in the
The Palace of North Korean dictator Kim Jong ill
Be a mega church in Lebanon the believe
He was the man
Messiah
Or see the be like Mike
Could diet book which recommended you can
Consume only Gatorade and expensive cigar
I'm probably going with this run in North Korea just cuz
Dennis Rodman stop.
You're right you're exactly right
Kim Jong-un
Got his love of the great Bulls teams of yesteryear from his father Kim Jong-il so congenial
The Dictator
Had a shrine to Michael Jordan
All right makeup is
Dan one of the most famous dance in American history was vice president
Dan Quayle
He's remembered now mostly for misspelling the word potato and for not being Jack Kennedy but
He also said
Many memorable things during his time
In the public light
Including which
Which of these
Hey
Quote
I have made good judgments in the past
I have made good judgements in the future
Future
Bee quote I believe we are on an irreversible trend
Towards more freedom and democracy
But that could change
Orsi
Quote the Holocaust was an obscene. In our nation's history
Not our nation
But in World War I mean
We all lived in this Century I didn't live in the
The century history
Unquote
Do you have D all the above time
He said all of those guns
The last up is Tony
So one of the most famous Tony's of courses Tony the Tiger
Tony the Tiger the cereal spokes animal has fans around the world
Thinking a little out of hand those such as when which of these actually happened today
A group of people started raising money to save tigers
From they said being harvested to make Frost
Did flakes
Tony the Tiger went on Twitter to ask
Furries
Please stop sending him anthropomorphic erotica
Or see somebody invented a language called
Tony talk
Which is English but you
You girl I will ever ER
Samuel McBee
You're exactly right cuz
A couple years ago with tweeting inappropriate things that Tony the Tiger so he tweeted quote
I'm all for showing your stripes feathers Etc
But let's keep things great and family-friendly if you could
Cubs could be watching
Nothing but net
Might got three out of three graduation
Houston Rockets coach Mike thank you so much
Wait wait don't tell me the production of NPR and WBEZ Chicago in association with urgent haircut Productions
Warehouse manager was Tyler Green Assisted by Simon Tran
Are interns eponine obedient Lila Francis rweb crew is Beth Novi
BJ leiderman composed RCU my program is produced by Jennifer Mills miles during Boston Lillian King technical directions from Moana
I think that's an ops manager is calling another a production coordinator is Robert Newhouse
Are senior executive producer of wait wait don't tell me
Is Mike dancing
Text to Bill Kurtis all of our panelists
Oliver special thanks to you for listening I am
This
Is NPR