Support for this podcast
In the following message
Come from Duckhorn
Napa California
Duckhorn Vineyards has been
Crafting classic Napa Valley Wine
Ants with a sense of place
For more than 40 years
Learn more
Or at Duckhorn. Com
NPR
From NPR and WBEZ Chicago this is why
Wait wait don't tell me the end
NPR news quiz
I don't know if Beale Street
Could talk
But build Street can
Sunbelt Rentals
And here is your host at the Chase Bank Auditorium in Chicago
Peter Sagal
We were handling 2019 just fine.
Things day by day
We are keeping up with
With the pace of event
But it is
Time to admit
We can
We need
To take a break
Why we breathe deeply into a paper bag
Here are some of the reasons why we're already nostalgia
Magic For Less
First in interview
That will be more and more relevant
The guy who hopes to get an offer
He'll never have
Do people like us
Ever again
The mayor of South Bend Indiana
It's a Longshot candidate for president but then again
Anythink
Is possible
You would like to
27 was made
Do the youngest mayor of a city above
People in the country
Youngest mayor of course that's a record that you only stand to lose
And then somebody send me a mess
Message on Twitter saying that you can't
I keep calling yourself
Sitting on her husband
I've got you beat
Damn skepticism like you're 29 years old what the hell do you know about being a man
Or somebody would say and I got underwear older
You're known as a Southbend booster right now
What is the best city in the
What's the best city
All right
You didn't you didn't just say it's a nice city you didn't say it's a nice place
The live you didn't say you said it the best city in the country soap
Go tell me why
Jester to the people
Leadership come on
Now that is some quality pandering how old are you now
Ulterior motive
Old enough I got to think about it first I'm 36
But I'm 35 and I haven't drank it after 8
I feel like they felt a little burn right now
Greatest city in the world
Is it
I know you you were like headed for I mean you were having baby
Finance or something like that with your background did your friend say
I'm going back to South Bend
When I moved home I remember I was I was getting very soon
And I said I was moving home to South Bend
Mom and dad are great I just want to go home that's great City and I don't want to live
Is it really
If you get out of it
Right
What does that mean
Describing a lifestyle
Damn I have no what are you a smartass
Sewer systems
Censor.net
Consumers
Anywhere in the world Smart Water technology
Don't say that you mean you mean sensors
Since we have these wifi-enabled
Sense
Pictures all through the cyst
What's the name of this man
Flowroute
2Go mitigates flows going into the river
If your
Cathay pacific
Viruses that burrito night again
I got to talk to you about your ambitions
Your rising star in the Democratic party you ran
For Democratic chair earlier last
Deer
So so
What are your plans for say 2020
The world and
Strategy
Mytown2go job
I got plenty.
Things are going
Where are you at that nobody with a funny name like
Yours could ever get elected
Around here it's actually an asset
Analysis of community
You know
Wy'east European settlement
Here in South and we got one guy
Cheapest
Who's that ran for office
Vowel
In his entirety
The real
We have invited you here to play a game we're calling
Welcome to North Bend
Stranger
The biggest booster of South Bend
But what do you know about the town's arch nemesis
North Bend Washington
Listen or you'll also get to wipe the
The town of North Bend off the map
The Great War of the Benz to a close
South Bend
2015 D North Bend fire department made the news
When they didn't which of these is a attempted to rescue
Do a cat stranded in a
A tree
The cat turned out to be a rabid raccoon and 8 firefighters had to get vaccinated
Beat reporter discovered the station's beloved Dalmatian was just a white Greyhound with
The skin condition
Or see they accidentally pump
Jet fuel instead of water onto a training fire causing a gigantic Fireball
Yeah we have
An outstanding fire tree
And I can see how is she
There might be issues
Is which fluid goes in
Which pumps on the go
You're right that's what happened
You write what happened was
Is the fuel got into the line that they use for recycling water for their neck
Next training exercise and
North Bend
True claim to fame is that it was the setting for David Lynch's TV series Twin Peaks
During the filming of the original show back in the late eighties
Is 90 one of The Producers gotten excited call
Telling him what
A
The national Apple Growers Association
She was offering a
Cool million
Switch Asia
Coopers
Favorite kind of pie
Bee Jerry Falwell had announced that the title Twin Peaks
To salacious
Just for today
Orsi Soviet Premier Mikhail Gorbachev
How to know who the murderer was right away
Yeah
I want to go with
Gorbachev
Suspenseful
Is there such a thing as
Too smart
Because
You're right again that's what happened
The call
Would heard from his friend President George HW Bush
The Gorge that Mikhail Gorbachev
Solution of mystery right away it's unclear though if garbage I've got
Last question
North Bend is home to Nintendo's main factoring Distribution Center
And Nintendo
Director Shigeru Miyamoto has spent time in this town
Where people have observed him pursuing
His favorite hobby
What is it
A leaping on mushrooms hoping that one day he'll be launched into the air
Be pulling out of tape measure and measuring everything he comes across
Horsey
Finding kids playing a Nintendo DS taking it in immediately beating their high score
Tape measure
Adjust the
Do the great video game
You're right again
He's obsessed
Mister mister Miyamoto is obsessed with measuring things like
Their size in the plot of tape measure
And Metric
That's what he does for fun
Bill how did mayor Pete buttigieg Dinner Show
3 right answers I smell re-election
They're not
If the world seems like it's
Spinning inexorably into a black hole of misery that's
Because it is
We're always happy to report on
People trying to make the world just a little better
Peter I known as the people for the ethical treatment of animals having already ended all cruelty to actual animals that's done they fixed it
They're now trying to change what
Oh they're trying to
To change the way
Idioms
That involve animals are trying to change our animal metaphors that's
That's right Peter has issued vegans
Peta has issued vegan-friendly updates
Two number of animal unfriendly phrases including changing kill two birds with one stone
To feed
Two birds
With one
Scone
Leading to a protest from the people for the ethical treatment of
Let's go bring home the bacon
Bring home the bagels
That's what they want you to say
Don't do that if you're in the Midwest and you have a visitor from New York cuz they will just not shut up about how bad your bagels are
Do you have to give props to our friendship
Exchange student Brigitte in high school
Who couldn't get a grasp of all the idiom
What you say
Two birds
Dead
We have two more for PETA in case they need more like
That was the straw with the camel
Refuse to use
Cuz those ecologically responsible
There's more than one way to shampoo a cat
Shooting star
I'd rather be skins
When we come back we celebrate 20 years
Tolerated by NPR
The two of the people who tolerated us
The most robbery
Seagull Nina totenberg
It all of you whenever
Exercise we've got another
For you
That's all in a minute I'm wait wait don't tell me
From NPR
Support frame
PRN the following message
Did come from feather
On a tree
Rich people moved 12 times
Before buying a
So why are you still buying furniture
Every time you move
Feather is a Furniture subscription
That gives you flexibility
Over your furniture and your space
Get access to over a hundred and fifty pieces of fur
And the option to change it as your life change
Subscribe now
Decide light
Visit live feather.
Time to start experiencing the benefits
Furniture flexible
Feather
Furniture
That changes with you
The current 10
The United States and North Korea is really intense and it's easy to forget that the two countries have accomplished
Get it passed
On the latest episode of through line
From NPR
We look back at the origin of the strain relationship to make sense
What's happening today
Through line
The podcast where we go back in time to understand the present
From NPR and WBEZ Chicago
Wait wait don't tell me
NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Kurtis here is your host at the
Chase Bank Auditorium in
Chicago
We are out recharging our batteries
Euphemism for gray
Drinking heavily
And sending out our resumes to radio shows that talk about something else
Anything
L
For example
How about a sports show
We could do that
We both experienced
Here's our exploration of a nuke
What kind of sports
Tree with Helen Hong
Roy Blount Jr and
Luke Burbank
Hi Peter this is Amelia calling from West Chester Pennsylvania
Philadelphia's I remember
That is correct Winchester is
The best chest
What do you do there
I will
A classically trained
Switch player
And I work as a manager at a health and fitness
Of course you are because to those worlds overlap ever
Welcome to the show Amelia you going to play the game with you must try to tell truth from fix
Bill what is Amelia's topic
Duck
You're not going to believe this
Classic injuries people have all the time runner's knee
Tennis elbow panelist
Groin
This week we heard about an injury happening in a really surprising wife
Surprising made the news
YouTuber panels going to tell you about a pic someone who's telling you
The truth and you will win our prize
The wait waiter of your choice
Ready to play
I have a lot of family that's going to be listening to this so I hope I don't let them down
Just like putting the pressure
Good idea
First let's hear from Helen Hong
Call Bradford was not having a good week
Recently separated he had
Text out of the home that he had shared with his ass
Estranged wife
I'm forced to move into a bachelor Studio
Of his mom's house
The Attic
Sparsely furnished
With three items
Awesome Ikea
Afraid
Brussels
Pull out couch
A mom
Side table and a hemnes bookshelf
Mind with his mom's romance novels
An ancient collection oven cycle
Wikipedia Britannica
And to earn
One containing Grandpa Joe
Any other
Dead hamster
Skipper
In need of a quick Furniture Fix and not one to mix things up
Carl headed to of course
Ikea
But putting together a song
Send
Drawer dresser becomes quickly
Infuriating even in the best
In sheer frustration
Carl hurled one of the half
Constructed dresser drawers at the wall
The edge of a hemnes
Bookshelf which
It turns out
Had not been properly mounted with abetted leg wallet
The bookshelf Came Crashing Down
Swinging heavy encyclopedia volume
Out the Attic Window and onto the neighbor's car
Shattering the windshield
The iron-containing Grandpa Joe also flew out the window
Narrowly missing the neighbors dog and splintering into a million pieces
Pieces on The Conch
Concrete driveway
The other earn Holdings
Skipper the hamster
Starfluid Carl
Fracturing his elbow and covering him and dead hamster
Mr.
Carl's been in a cast
For two weeks
Is remorse
Princess Beats
Experience made him
And realize how much he had
Taking his wife and properly
Furnished home for granted
He's mending his relationship
Valley more appreciation
For both his marriage
Things not Ikea
Multiple
Catastrophe cast
Scared
Courtesy of Ikea
Connect story of an unlikely injury comes from Royal Blood
Volleyball is what nudist
Play
It's a big nudist thing you see a bunch of naked people and you wonder what's up
Then you say they're playing volleyball and you go all afternoon
But golf
Nudist playing golf
It don't seem nice
Now it has happened
The first
Nude
Golf day
Set a course
In Northern Australia
Organized by 69 year-old Brian to
Shoes and hat and nothing else
Put another connotation on how you're swinging
Jack Jenkins
30 golfers took part
Only one suffered an injury
Bitten by scandalized wombat
Ball in the wrong hole
I know this fellow just didn't want to use a cart so he carried his bag of clubs over his Bear show
Kind of bad
Put another connotation on how's it hanging
Shape shoulder from a nudist golf event in Australia last story of a boo-boo in the news comes from Luke
Doctors at Kindred Hospital in Brea California listed Kevin dodrill in satisfactory condition this week
With a broken leg and Radial fracture
But they say things could have been much
Worse after he raced through a 4 way stop on his bike
And collided with a UPS truck
His family says things went about as they were
Expecting
Considering he was riding a Peloton stationary bicycle heat modified to take on the street
The bike was a birthday present to Dodgeville from his wife and
And kids
And he admits having been a little confused when he first unpacked
The gift
Well I didn't realize it was
The stationary bike at first he told the brave post this
Dispatch
And since I've already thrown out the assembly directions long before trying to put it together
I just figured it was some kind of weird because I got a screaming deal on or something
Dodge will solve the problem by latching two of his daughters light up
Heely sneakers
To the underside of the back of the bike and then unsheathing the giant heavy front wheel from its frame
So we could sort of just roll on the ground
The biggest problem is those things actually come with brake
Said dodrill from his hospital bed
So I brought some barbecue tongs with me I figured I can kind of pinch the front wheel try to slow down
For what can only be described as
Is obvious reasons
The plan failed
Dodge roll dough is not ready to admit defeat
Telling his family he just needs a Saturday where he and his buddies Dale and Pat can get under the hood of that thing
I don't have it working again in no time at all right
Let's review these injuries from Helen
It was a broken clavicle I think and other injuries from a cat
Skating Ikea furniture accent
From Roy blunt
Junior the injury was a chief
Shoulder
Inevitable result of playing golf in the nude is a bunch
Australia
Or from Luke Burbank very is terrible fractures from riding a Peloton bike in
Really happy
Good gravy
Gravy Indian
Let's go with me
So your choice is
Abby Roy the story about the nude golf tournament well to bring you the correct answer
We spoke to someone
Familiar with
This kind of injury
Nude activities such as
Jerry Durant post of unique tissue injuries
That was a doctor balloon that Rodger needs a sports medicine physician in Chicago Primary Care Sports Medicine
Being very gracious as he
She spoke to us
About this nude golf injury suffered in off
Australia
Congratulations you did get it right
Roy was telling you the truth in his patented folksy way so you have earned a point for him
As well as winning our price
Congratulation
Thank you guys bye bye
Last year we at wait wait celebrate of the fact that we have been on the air
20 years
And NPR cellar
The fact that you even after all that time
We haven't
Completely destroy their reputation
The two sides
NPR
Dignified
And us
Came together when Robert Segal in in Atoka
Stage
To celebrate
It's our anniversary
And
To apologize to them for ruining the brain
Welcome back you both Dinner Show before Robert you have you retired from after a long career
How you doing I'm doing whatever I want to do
And it's a lot of fun
Well how are you spending your time
I listen to some radio I I do anniversaries
20th anniversary is 30th anniversary
Nina you're still at it and you you still enjoying yourself after this
This many years of doing your voice
That's when I got a great story
Our age
Mommy are and there been a lot of those lately
It gets a little old yeah well I do know the one thing you've been covering the Supreme Court for many years but the party scene they
There is about to get lit
I do want to ask you
So 20 years ago NPR started this show
And you guys were I don't know the backbone of NPR serious reputation what did you think of it
It was just great
I love it and I love to be invited and we have all these
Great people here
And I don't know if the listening public Knows Best
But
Everybody in NPR most especially Nina and Robert but not only them
Actually have tremendous sense of humor
A Nintendo
I know that you wish you could indulge it more on the air
So we wanted to ask you now
Go back to some stories and see if there's anything you wish you had been able to say how many people have a job
Bob to keep us from saying what we might say
That's right I was in that what happened
Hosting All Things Considered
And I somebody handed me live on the air
What I was supposed to
Play the intro to a Robert krulwich piece
And their hands had moved
On the typewriter
And so that
It was chipperish the only thing wrong with the copy
And I had not at that point then a lot of
And I looked and I said I can't read this
And pointed is the booth to play the pig
He was in the
News director or vice president for news or whatever bloody title that gave you in those days
Called me to his office
Yes
And he could
Barely
Induct my reprimand
Because he was laughing so hard
And I figure what what should I have done
And he said you could have said we're having technical difficulties
Do you have hear me
We're having
Technical difficulties that means I don't know what the freaking hell is going on
YouTube
So
Famous
At 2
Too many people butt hurts
Pacific group
And you're also
Not recognizable like you
Close our eyes
To be like all their those famous people
Right
What what is the funniest or most memorable Fannin
Encounter
You had I remember there was a. When
The typical Washington cab driver
Had a graduate degree from University somewhere any staff
And they drove around all day and they all the same
Yuan to NPR
And them
I must have had in the course of a couple of months
Three different cab driver
With him I had the following con
Ocaso
I'm Robert Siegel
Your coverage of Eritrea is not very good
Well but you know the drill
We have asked you here to play a game we're calling
Robert Siegel actual Siegel
Nina totenberg
Meet actual
Terrible puns about your names for your entire career so why not
Make a game out of this answer three questions correctly to win our prize for one of our listeners
Price on their voicemail Bill who are Nina and Robert
Playing for
Dale Nichols Westland Michigan
She seemed like a nuisance but some groups over the years have made use of them how
A fisherman in Nicaragua tied them to their boats
Like flying sled dogs
People used to stuff a dead seagull in a bottle of water and let it ferment making
Seagull wine
40 Polynesians used to train them to race with each other and they did it by making them chase a fake
Herring
Tied to a kite
Harry
Why are Asians people across the street from my elementary school
I'll go with that one
We're going for heron
Was terrible but apparently at the job
Okay here's your next question other attempts to make use of Seagulls have failed though such as which of these
British Navy
Try to teach girls to poop on submarine periscope
Blinding the crewman inside the Amazon tried to train seagulls
Deliver light packages to ships at sea
Garcia buddy movie starring a seagull and Steven Seagal stop shooting
Stevenson sexually harassed
Well
Leo horoscope
Can you show always go
Play coding a fake Periscope with food and ideas
Tracey Oldham NC once warm it
Poop about it
And that would end
The German threat
It worked with my windshield
Yeah so your last question is
You got it you win is of course now about
Tote bags
Everybody loves tote bags of course
Well people did not like a certain tote bag that was put out by a Georgia company last year why
Hey it was a
Quotes
Security tote
Made of lead with a lock on it so it weighed
43 lb
Be it was the talking tote program to say amusing things when you put stuff in it like arugula
Horsey
Thanks to an error
It praised Hitler
On the side
It's the third one is for Hitler
It is in fact the tote bag was supposed to say
My favorite color is glitter
Felton Twitter
But do do a wheelie for choice
Java cursive font
The word glitter really looks like the word Hitler
Hahaha
Twitter
Robert Siegel and Nina totenberg NPR Legends Robert is now walking in people's homes and listening to them
Amina and Robert Indiana
When we come back it's music and murder with
Sarah Brightman and John Grisham that's coming up in a minute
From wait wait don't tell me
Support for NPR comes from investor.gov
Presenting this mess
When it comes to investing
It doesn't matter whether you're a new investor or inexperienced
Whether you have a financial
Professional or manage your own it
We all have
And investor.gov
Has answer
It's your free resource
Words for tools
Tips and information
Before yuan
Investor.
Amazon
Google
Facebook
Big companies are getting
Belief
Is that a problem
Listen to Planet Money is new series on big business
Competition
Antitrust law
In America
That's on Planet Money
NPR WBEZ Chicago
What is wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Kurtis and here is your host
City Chase Bank Auditorium in
Chicago
Theaters
Hey Google thanks so much everybody
We're taking the week off from the news
Cuz you know where
Just putting our feet up and rocking back
Looking forward saying
It's not happening
But in case you don't cha
Just want to listen to us
Descending into madness
Let's listen to our enemy with Sopranos
Peter started by asking her about a remarkable
I came across that fact and I was amazed that you are the
Most popular
Soprano and
World
City say thank you very much
Yes I mean there is some other pretty good Sopranos out there
Maria Callas
Where the f*** I'm afraid anymore
Takes over she wanted to keep up with you
Should have stayed alive
So
We had a lot of fun looking at you you had an interesting start
To your singing
Career which I didn't know about
Details about it
Your first big Act
I lost my heart
Yes
Disco
This is Paula Poundstone I'm not a musical
Aficionado
Any stretch
But it's really hard
How to see how I lost my heart to
Starship
Super DuckTales
Open Door
Soprano
Phantom of the Opera
Yes
I'm kind of motif
Is it that makes any sense it makes complete sense
The Starship Trooper
The thing was I looked up
Music conductor Progressive
Kid Rock music
And I love
Listen to
Sopranos
Listen to different music
That's what happen
You became a cat
In cats
And that you came to the attention of a gentleman named Andrew Lloyd Webber
Yes who I married you did
We understand that he wrote the lead role in
Name of the Opera for
Yes she did
Mr. Lloyd Webber I guess I need to call him Lord Weber pick
He was raised
Poppy Ridge do you have to
To call him Lord Weber
Yes I do
Yes I'm here
Hahaha
About the new record
This is it your first new record in a while
Yes
What you want to know
Tell me what it's like
It's great
I came out to feed Russian
Space Program Islam.
I decided I'm not going to sound
Myself a house
Hey wait what hold on
Rewind a little bit the Russians
Space Program
Yes I was going to go to the ISS
Straighterline that Starship Trooper
They were going to send you to the international
Space Station
It was it was an inch
Singing challenge
Time
I didn't go in the end I came out
Anthem
Came up with the
Important
And it's
It's going great
I'm really happy
And I hope you all enjoy it if you
If you weren't
They didn't listen to it
I think I'm just going to say something
You are as I said
The most popular
Soprano
The world
But you don't
Act like
I mean you seem a little
Surprised that people might want to
And you're Sarah Brightman
Sarah it's not the weird thing that you
You said the weird thing that you
You said was
I came out of the Russians
Space Program
As one.
Yeah you guys you guys are done
It is a delight to talk to
You but we have asked
Rescue here
Today
How to play a game we're calling
It's not over until Gene Simmons
Liacouras created the
The lead role in Phantom of the Opera but before that
The band Kiss
Starred in their one and only
TV movie
Koldkiss
Meet Phantom of the park
We're going to ask you three questions about the second most popular TV movie of
Get to write it when I probably won't ever listen
Rebuild who is Sarah Brightman
Susan Robertson of Atlanta Georgia
All right
Remember how this works were going to ask
3 multiple choice question
Get to write you when I cry
One of our listeners
Here we go
Future first question in the movie
The members of Kiss FC
Super powers which they used
To battle an evil scientist
Add an amusement park
Will texting with robot version
Everything I just said
Drummer Peter Criss
It's really wasn't into this project
Explain it was
Because
Was it a
He thought it was beneath his
Is dignity quote
I can't see John Lennon getting beat up by
Dracula
Be he didn't like the idea of killing the robots be
Because quote they may be artificial
But their feelings
Orsi
He didn't like it
Kids fake superpower in
In the film saying quote I want to feature my realtor
Superpower
My extraordinary empathy
It is sadly wasn't
He it was a lot about John Lennon he thought that
This this
Silly comic book movie was beneath the Dignity of
Mysterious magician
Kiss
Alright chances which is great
In the first try
Of the script of the movie all guitarists Ace
Freelee said
All his lines were just annoyed
Itzhak
Why
A freely was concerned that
Speaking dialogue will act
Thing might hurt his
Be it was
Is it tribute to freely
Recently
We're see when the film's writers met with the band to get a feel for how they spoke
Freelee refused
To say anything to them but
Wow
Yes it was in fact
He pick up the script and he says how come the only thing I say in this
Movie is at
Can they said cuz that's all you ever said to us
Said the writers
Alright last question if you get this right you win
The production was
Plagued by tension
In Clash Of egos was
Is a terrible time on the
It resulted in which of the following
Happening
Drummer Peter Criss quit the film
Producers asked
Listen to change his famous cat makeup
Do dog make
In one scene
Is Ace Frehley it stormed off the set
And a half you can
I clearly see his African-American stunt double
Instead
Or see all of the
The Kiss songs
The movie actually ended up in
Performed by Aerosmith
Okay okay
In sums if you if you watch this movie and of course
You can
In some scenes Ace Frehley scenes
Performed by a black
Stunt double wearing white face
It's that good
Bill how did Sarah Brightman doing AR quiz
Is he slipped a couple right ones
Sarah brightman's new album is
Him
Sarah Brightman what a pleasure
Talk to you thank you so much
You're talking with us
Thank you take care
Support for NPR
Are comes from investor
Presenting this
When it comes to invest
It doesn't matter whether you're a new investor or an experience
Whether you have a financial
Professional or manage your own in bed
We all have
And investor.gov
Has answers
It's your free Reese
Crispr tools tips and information
Before you invest
Investor.
Gyros creator
How I built this in
We're returning to San Francisco for
Second how I built this Summit
Supported by American
Express
I'll be joining there by founders of
Companies like Instagram
Slack away
A bliss JetBlue
Many many more
Visit Summit
Npr.org
More and
See you there
Support also comes
From Fidelity in
As a Fidelity Wealth Management
You get a dedicated advice
To help grow and protect
Find ways to minimize the impact
After taxes and make
Clear recommendation
For your full fight
Learn more
Fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage services
From the most popular soprano
One of the most beloved author
John Grisham joined us last year
To talk about his latest novel
The Reckoning
Asking about his first novel A Time to Kill witch
Did not in fact
Set the world on fire
No it came out 1989 it was published by a small unknown publishing company in New York I printed 5,000
Hardback copies and we couldn't give them away about a thousand copies and couldn't give them away so
Total disaster
Really
How did you ever get the gumption to try again
Well it was a hobby it was not a job I told my wife I was going to write one more book and if the second book didn't work
Reply to flop two
I was going to forget this whole secret Hobby and just go you know sue people all the time
And so the second book
Turn out to be the firm and that changed everything
It sure did
Did you like
Sit down and think yourself okay the first one didn't do well so what do I need to do to write up up
Books that will did you actually calculate
I need to up your game on the
I had the idea
And it could be better and my wife really liked it and so I said okay
I'm going to be something a little more commercial a little more Beano popular
It wasn't naked grab for money
That's a good title
Tumi
It is how
Relax you seem I've read that you have a schedule where you start writing
A book and what is it
The middle of the summer middle August
Did you finish my Christmas and then you take the rest of the year off
That was the old schedule
The new schedule start a book every year on January 1st
And finish July 1st at the go with you on the first
And so I get myself six months and to write during the winter time when things are slow and all that
I mean I have no real job you know this is not a real job
I work 40 hours a week in like 30 years
Okay so it's not a real job
You've got great title
You say your books have good titles are there any
Titles at
Dad that you rejected that
You look back on and think I can't believe I ever considered that like what are some of the rejected title
Gone with the Wind
Kill a Mockingbird
Every you want to start a book I think okay I want a great time I want something like to Kill a Mockingbird
Are The Grapes of Wrath
Sophie from great title
And I just can't find them so sticky
Something
I read that you are really big in the Little League Baseball I understand you have
Six Little League fields on your property
Nnnnn who plays on the
We have about 400 kids every year from our neighborhood, it's just
Spartan County
And we have 35 teams and we have seven
Open Fields and we have we have tons of baseball t-ball softball
I'm the commissioner
Because I own the damn place to pay for it it's a wonderful place
Can we have kids now to play in our ballpark for a
10 straight years but when they grow up here so it's
That's awesome gif
When you have a dictator the commissioner
Place a big role in your writing
She plays a big role she has to approve each story before I start riding it
Which moments around the house when I have a brilliant idea for a novel and
She thinks it's just not going to work
I got to get about thirty seconds to pitch an idea to her for a novel
Which is really the way you should write if you can't pitch
Stop playing in 30 minutes
And convinced your listener that it's a good story you're probably in trouble
We read somewhere that one of the things that your wife did for your writing
At least early on
What's the next the sex scenes
Well she reads a lot of books in a lot of books
Have some sex I'm not sure how much that I don't read those books but
She's always said that men cannot write sex
7 years ago I wrote the sex scene
And
She read it chapter by chapter and so I gave her the chapter to read with a sex scene
And I heard her laughing upstairs
Men cannot write sex
Well John Grisham it is a pleasure
Need to talk to you we have invited
Did you hear today to play a game we're calling
The comfy
Cotton brief legal briefs
Serena
Three questions about
Underwear you win a prize one of my listeners
Bill who is author John Grisham playing
Courtney Bond St Louis Missouri
Here's the first Quest
Saint John in olden times men's underwear was
Extremely valuable
Prize by the wealthy and Powerful how do we know that
Hey King Henry II of England have a royal supplier if I mention
Beat King Tut was buried with 145 pairs in his
Tomb
Orsi Peter the Great of Russia invaded the Crimea just
To capture
Particular Taylor
Who made underwear
Wow I mean
OC
Actually it was actually be King Tut
Because you get you know if you go into the underworld you want to need support
Next question
According to a 1933 issue of the trade Journal Menswear
A man's underwear should
Be what
Hey
Quote
Should be like a Fort Knox
For the bits
Bee quote should have the grace of Apollo the romance of Byron the
Extinction of Lord of Chester
You filled in the he's coolness and comfort
Mahatma Gandhi
Foresee quotes
Should let him at know that whether he's stagger falter or fail
At least he will not wiggle
Integrate
Wow down supposed to responses
You can do whatever the hell you didn't know which one you want I want I want to see
No it was B
I'm so sorry
We have one more for you
Authority on men's fashion
Nicora surges you not
Not to wear one kind of underwear which is it
Briefs with pictures of animal faces on the front
Be tidy whities because quote they remind every woman of their dorky little brother
Or see anything that cost over 20 bucks
Because by the time anybody else sees it they've already made up their minds about you
Haha
I don't like beer say let's go
It is obvious you should not wear the underwear with a big tiger face right there in the front but GQ apparently felt a need
David let their readers now
Do not do that
All right
How
Did John Grisham do an AR quiz
The defendant has been found guilty
With one right out of
3 John
You're still a winner
Hey Courtney in St Louis I'm really sorry about this
Look I'm going to send you an autographed copy of my next book which is not
That big of a prize
But it should be
How far you win that argument I also happen to know that John grisham's new novel The Wrecker
Is fantastic is available in stores in October 23rd
Thank you
So much
That's it for a rest and Rejuvenation week will be back next week refreshed
Austin ready to go
Or not
Will be back anyway
Special thanks once again to Farmhouse Tavern for feeding us
Thanks for really break
Wait wait don't tell me the production of NPR WBEZ Chicago in association with urgent
Haircut production
Doug watch out for the combine Berman
Overlord
Limericks are public address announcers Paul Friedman
Our weather is Beth Novey
And Lillian Kingwood special things
Peter Gwen
Why are business and off managers Colin Miller
A production coordinator is Robert Newhouse our senior producer
Cilic
An executive producer of wait wait don't tell me
Is Michael Vick
Thanks to Bill Curtis and all our panelist and listen because that's what you heard this week
Edgeworth Boston
What's the weather going to take a week off we needed it
By Peter Sagal mobile see you next week
This
Is NPR