Support for NPR
In the following method
Has come from America
You want to build your business
They can help build your butt
Business with Finance
Solutions for eligible business cast
The powerful backing
American
Don't do business without it
Terms apply
Visit americanexpress.com business
From NPR
Easy Chicago don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
You don't need a
Landline
I don't care who saying here is your host at the Chase Bank
Chicago
Thank you girl thank everybody
The game later on we're going to be doing by Anthony Anderson star of the
The sitcom
Blackish
Can host of the new
Tell the truth but
First this is
Lollapalooza weekend
And here in Chicago
The music festival that happens just a few blocks
For my sitter
So the chance to have our two different demographic
Mingling on the street
They're the young people Buzz
Just with beer and
The happiness
And all the other people muttering do their parents know they're out
Dress like that
We don't care how you're dressed cuz we cannot see you give us a call the number
Is 1 AAA wait wait that's one 888-924-8924 let's welcome our first listener contested
This is Joshua from Greenville South Carolina from Greenville how are you
I'm glad to hear it what do you do there in in in South Carolina
I am on my college
Student and I am interning at
TD Bank you're interning at TD Bank do you want to be a banker
Well I made
During an English and history
You better hope you can be a banker I guess the other side
Well welcome to the show Joshua let me introduce you to our panel this week
First of a comedian performing at hyenas in Dallas August
6 to the 10th
And her Netflix special drops
August 13th is Ida
Rodriguez
Comedian
You can see it the robin theater in Lansing Michigan on August 25th hits mr. Adam
Hello I'm finally a comedian you can see August
16th and Hyannis Massachusetts
Is the Cape Cod Melody tent in here every week
Nobody listens to Paula Poundstone it
Welcome
Of course they're going to play who's Bill this time that's how we start the show bill
Curtis is going to read your sweet quotations for
Snooze
Guess what he's talking about
Who is imitating two times out of three you will win our prize
The voice of anyone you might
I choose on your voicemail
Ready to play
I am quite ready
I'm glad to hear it because here
Go easy on
Anime kids that was 7
Speaking to Kamala Harris
Jess has the democratic debate started this week
She did not
Listen to him
Who was it
That will be Uncle Joe Uncle Joe Biden
With the second round of the democratic debates
This weekend despite the efforts of many people doing a lot of work
After the first round
We weren't able to get rid of any of those people at the Wednesday to make their two Tuesday and Wednesday at the
Wednesday debate everybody went after biting
His main response was hey
But Obama like me
Come on that was years ago
It's like the old guy who won't stop talking about high school
Rite-hite I was vice quarterback of the football team
Did you guys enjoy the debates
I take it you did there either
I feel bad for
Marion
Yeah because everybody kept tweeting her like
Affirmation
I realized they were asking her if she had like
Don't feel bad for her
I was shocked
Just see you're on the
Debate stage
For the Democrats
Very impressed in the first
Debates when she said
Her first
Couple answers
Pretty good
Third answer
Will happen like that
She doesn't go for men
Rubs herself against
Old Oakhurst conventional wisdom coming out of the
Affair was that a Joe Biden who is
Leading by a lot
Long way
The Democratic polls
All he had to do was not
Screw up
And he didn't
Scraps are always doing great
Except at the very end of it
He screwed up his own website
Right he said go to Joe 30330 when he meant X
That
I mean it was such a grandfatherly thing to do
Next quote is from
Some public service that NPR did
Sending a message to
Specific group of men
This week
Children think you're really really on a
Attractive that was NPR's and Nell greenfieldboyce talking about a new study that finds men with
What facial feature
Actually scares young children
Mustaches
Oh bigger than that go for the whole face
Obir
Wait a minute you said that his resignation and sadness do you still have
Add a beard
I definitely do not know the answer is beer
A new study finds adult
Perceive people with beards at stronger and more mature
But that young children find them
Terrifying
Single mom
Stronger and more
Mature most adults
According to psychology
Well I wasn't thin survey
This is part of it they were trying to find out how kids related to people with beards or not
Not so what they did was they took some young kid
Kids and they gave them
Specially created
It's about a Mysterious Island
We're The Kids
Help
So they tended to pek
Clean-shaven men
Convolving cooperate
And bearded men
And for tasks that called for
Strength and men's
This is all ready to copy
The kids don't like
I don't know are you
Should find band terrifying
It seemed everyone should have a beard
Children
Detective
Bearden I said I don't think that they seem
Dear Joshua is your last
Best quote
I got the horses in the back
Horse tack is it at
Those are some of the lyrics
To the song that is now broken the record
Longest run ever
At the top of the Billboard charts what is that song
So it's that horrible song old
Old Town Road in the nation disagrees
The song by Lil Nas X has been number one on the billboard charts
For 17 consecutive weeks that breaks a record
At this rate it will last longer than human civilization
Lamaze execution in the charts
True by constantly turning out new versions with diff
Collaborators include
Billy Ray Cyrus and Lil Wayne
Song keep getting updates
Burnout version 13
2.8 so it doesn't work with the old version
This is so frustrating
You know who will not ever be on a remix of Old Town Road mayor Pete buttigieg
The presidential candidate
This is true he and Lil Nas X
We're supposed to do an event together
Mr Pizza
Can I do the song with you
Lil Nas X said
No
It's true. Already done to mix with v
12 year old mason Ramsey
Nashville
So we didn't want another with a yodeling
Well according to a campaign rules it would have had to do a remix with all 19
Was turned down there is in fact
The growing trend of presidential candidates collaborated with pop stars
Bernie Sanders
Didn't event
With cardi B this
She he's actually in Chiba
Been talking for awhile she has that lyric about Bloody
Issues
And you know he heard that it was like I had that to she should be my Podiatry
She did a video on it
Instagram endorsing him
It would have been one solid beep
Cuz he was like
It was interesting
Elizabeth Warren also did some
Weather
Elizabeth Warren
She also spoke about it what she said was that she's going to use her platform
Want to talk about pilot
Fixing all the things that pee
People don't want her to talk
Talk about
And she was like if I end up there y'all know who did it
Well how did Jethro doing a quiz
Joshua. Okay
3 at all is okay congratulations thank you
Pedal pedal time for you to answer
After some questions about this week
Atom if you have an Apple device you know that the automated assist
Siri wakes up
When it hears the phrase
Hey
Siri
According to a company whistleblower
Siri also wakes up
Instruct
When it hears
What
The factory complaining about that
No I'll give you a hint if you want to avoid this everybody needs to go out and get pants with button
Implies yes the sound of a zipper
Wake
What's up Siri
Wow
Camping Siri
That Siri starts listening when it hears pants unzipped
And your first thought was
So they've heard
Oh
Let me think a little more and you're like wait they've also heard oh no
Apple sends recordings made by Siri
How to contractors
Whose job it is to make sure that it's recording what it supposed to be with
And according to an anonymous whistleblower what they
Here is quote
Discussions between doctors and patients
Business
Deals
Criminal dealings
Sexual encounters and so on
Quote
And all that is bad
But what
Business
Deals
Begin
With people taking their pants off thanks for taking the meeting gentleman
What's drop trial and talk number
People are going to go home and unzip your pants
Answer the front of your phone
What's the weather right now
How many how many people
Coming up
From NPR
Support for wait wait don't tell me comes from SimpliSafe Home Security
SimpliSafe
Protects your whole home
Every window room and door
With sensors designed to blend into your home's decor
You can set up
Your SimpliSafe system yourself
Usually in under an hour
They offer video verification and around the clock
Professional monitor
With SimpliSafe there are no contracts or hidden fees
Learn more about SimpliSafe and get free shipping on your order
At simplisafe.com
Slash
Wait
A good book
Can Transform Ya
There's a pyramid of evidence now that the more fiction
That people read the more empathic
Make the baby come
Novel exercise
To enhance your empathy
This week
A hidden brain from NPR
It's the first episode
Afar summer series
YouTube .0
From NPR
And WBEZ
Chicago this is wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Kurtis William
On the stone
Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown Chicago
Wait wait don't tell me Bluff The Listener game
Call 1aaa wait wait to play a game in the air how you are on wait wait.
Uninstall tonight from Utah where in Utah
I work as an electrocardiogram take
Oh really so you're the guys who like
Finally got out people's hearts
That's the one right
Give a route for like really interesting Heartbeats
Break up the monotony
He would never
No
You're welcome
What to the show don't you were here to play the game and what you must write itself
Tooth infection
Bill what is dolphins
Topic
It's Elementary my dear
Everybody loves a mystery
Who murdered whom
What happened to the lost city of Atlantis
Why was John Delaney at the
The debate
This weekend mystery got solved our panel is going to tell you about it
Pick the one who's telling the truth and you'll win our prize a waiter of your choice on your voicemail
Are you ready to play
All right eye first mystery and it solution comes from Ida Rodriguez
The small town of
Cashmere washing
Was turned upside down by Miss
Stuart Coleman
Pasta
Is driver's life
Took off for his
First Joyride
When he didn't come home at first I didn't worry much
Because I just
Was enjoying our new
New Chevy Spark
The clear tote
Call me finally
We called the police
I didn't show up for
Pie night
At Stewart
The people of Kashmir mobilized
Define Stewart
Woods info
Putting up posters
And delivering baked goods
The word family
But it was Jeremiah
A local farmer
On his way to pick up
Supplies from a
Store in the neighboring town
Kohl's code
Who found the boy
He pulled up in
Front of a newly-installed roundabout
Highway 2
And notices
Small red Chevy
We going around and around
With an agitated young driver
Apparently Stewart had driven into
To the roundabout realized
He didn't learn about anything like that in
Driving School
And got stuck
Going round and round in it
6 hours
Mrs. call made with
So happy to have her son
She made in
An exception
And had pop tide night all over
Lost Boys soundtrack in roundabout cuz you know how to get out of it
Your neck story of a mystery
Demystified comes from
Adam Burke
We can all agree the only thing worse than a McChicken sandwich
Is McChicken sandwich at someone's already taking a bite out of
That was the situation
Placing an Indianapolis police officer who went to reheat McDonald's meal at the beginning of his shift
Only to find someone had
Pre nibbled at
I know I didn't need it to the officer who identified himself to local press as DJ
Officer DJ immediately went to the McDonald's
Quotes from Wednesday
The sandwich originated
And demanded to know which
Stop hating malefactor
Had sabotaged
Sandwich
A joint investigation was immediately launched by both the golden arches
And the boys in blue
Just in case anyone in Indianapolis was wondering why it was taking so long to find your stolen car
And or deliver your McMuffin
Eventually the perpetrator of the masticatory misdeed
Was brought to life
None other than officer DJ himself
The employee took a bite out of the sandwich upon starting his shift
Polly said
In the statement he returned nearly 7 hours later having forgotten
Instead he had previously been in the summer
The discovery has helped to clear up a number of other investigation
DJ has been working on
Including the Curious Case of who left the front door open
The Mystery of the missing TV remote
And the baffling riddle of who use up all the toilet paper
Marcus and investigation
To see what prankster took a bite out of his own sandwich only discover that it was he
Himself
Your last story of an enigma answered
When Coral Springs
Florida resident
Nina and
Fred Russo
Return home to their C
16 year old son
After dinner out on tooth
They were shocked
Define gaping hole in the front door
Chairs were flipped
Furniture was in
Disarray
The couch cushions
And hemorrhaging phone
The refrigerator door was
Supposing it
Collapsed
Shelves and empty
Sea containers
I was so angry
Nina Ricci outside
Romeo
Her son was sitting at the computer when we left
And there was
Play lasagna a 7-Layer dip and a poppy seed bun
In the refrigerator
Two and a half hours later
He was sitting there playing fortnite or whatever it is
The apartment was awarded
Containers even under the couch
However Young Romeo
Insisted
He has done nothing wrong
I had no idea what it happened
Feeling unjust
Accused
Romeo stormed out of the apartment
Slamming what was left of
Front door and saw + 11
Alligator being wrangled
Listen to a Florida Fish and Wildlife
Mission vehicles
When their neighbors saw the alligator coming out of the front door if they immediately called the news
Alligator hotline
Authorities are not sure why the mammoth's Predator broke through the russos door and ravage their apartment
But Romeo's Perrin
Surprised that their son never know.
All right choices so one of these was a real mystery that got saw
Solve this
Was it from Ida what happened to the Lost Boy in washing
Well it turns out he was
Stuck in a roundabout
After hours
From Adam Burke who took a bite out of a cop hamburger
Well it turns out of the cop himself
Or from Paula Poundstone who trash
This house
Well the teenager was there supposedly playing video games
Well it was a large alligator which of these is the real mystery and solution
We found out about this
I'm going to go with my man out of
Adam story of the cop in the mysterious biting his hand
What to bring you the real story we spoke to somebody
Wood covered it
The police department and the McDonald's
Investigated
The cause of a bitten sandwich earlier in the day that was
Who covered the hamburger mystery in Indianapolis
For USA Today congratulations
Enterprise the voice of your choice on your voice
Thank you so much for playing thank you so much
Take character. Bye-bye
And now the game where we ask somebody who was better things to do to do something worse it's called not my job
There are dimes and then there were good times and great dad with the greatest Hazard the
The sitcom.
The ones with Crazy Love
Families who argue but always end up loving each other more in the end
America's reigning sitcom dad right now
Is Anthony Anderson of the show
Blackhat she's also the host
Tell the truth on ABC
Is a veteran actor
Comedian stand-up he's everything Anthony Anderson
Welcome to wait wait don't tell me
How many things but let's just focus on blackish
Because there's a huge tradition of like
Family sitcom
God I don't know Father Knows Best
Is it like a burden to be
Right now America's favor
Grittv.
I just want to get out there where we just want to get out there and tell our story than
And have fun doing it and then
Hopefully it resonates with an audience the way that it has for the past 6 years
Nmd
Do people like assume you're wise
Could you play a TV dad
No one would ever assume that I'm why
That's more challenging and
Important thing that you do
Which is hosting a game show
With my mother has my side
What
Nobody told me this
Your mother is your
Sidekick
Yeah my mother is Mama Doris that that's my that's my real mother the woman that birthed me
It's funny how it came about I was doing
Episode of celebrity Family Feud
Sister love my brother of my aunt
That's on the show
Poems to my mother
Where would a naked magician pull a rabbit out of
And without hesitation my mother scream to the heavens
Steve Harvey give her one of those 5-minute long-burning looked like you fanfic
You shut down literally for about five minutes after the show
The Producers came over to me today at then can we talk to you about your mother
I told you she was a Livewire I do apologize
We want your mother
Be on your game show with you
To tell the truth
And I was like really
What do you think about it I said I think
It's great because it gets her off
My payroll and puts her on to yours
Tell me how this works on to tell the truth she's like sitting next to you
The voice of the people
She asked the question is
That people
Core at home
Catwoman on the show with the longest
Fingernails
With little more than 4 5 ft long
My mother asked the question
How do you ripen
I noticed a trend in her comment
Now that uses celebrities a gun to her head is like demanding a bigger trailer than yours now
Trailer wants to get paid more than I do
She has an Entourage she has her own personal wig maker oh my God
That is a man that is truly a diva
We will question
Would it go back to the magician the naked
Images
See any other answer.
Now we heard
That you are a
Pretty enthusiastic
You golfed with President Obama what was that like
That was one of the best round of golf ever played President Obama talked a lot of trash
And this is Obama a chatty golfers in one of those serious golfers you just want to hit the ball and get down there
And I'll tell you this
It took all of our money
He's he's that good of a golfer it was Chris Paul
Myself
Michael Phelps
And our President Obama
President Obama doesn't hit the ball long off
About 220-230
Straight as an arrow
Right down the middle of the Fairway
And he ended up taking money
From all three of us
You said you took all of your money
You Chris Paul and Michael Phelps
Have a lot of money
Because
We didn't know if we could have
Amongst ourselves
And on the third hole while we work and off
Obama was like so
Blackboard
And he commenced to whip
Wow what would you like to talk to you Anthony but we have invited you here and I hope you were warned about this
Two-player games at this time we're calling
You've been sent down to double-a
Your initials are AAA
Of course which made us think of double A baseball that is the minor leagues
I'm so weird asked you three
Things about Minor League
Ball
Answer to correctly
You want a prize winner list
There's the voice of anyone they might like on their answering
Bill who is Anthony Anderson playing
Eric Christensen of Anaheim California local
Already here
I'm ready
Minor league
Teams are famous for their promotion
One promotion
Fallout by the West Virginia Power
Stop
Before it could happen what was it a
Animal sacrifice
In which they were to recreate with a live goat
An ancient Pagan rich
B
Salute to indoor plumbing night
Lakewood
Close the bathrooms and ask everyone to use porta potties in
Instead
Horsey wife
Swap night with everybody at the chance to go home with
Somebody else
Wow
I worked Virginia that's definitely wife swapping
You are very
You left for the wrong stereotype it's indoor plumbing
I really appreciate it
Access to it
But the health authority shut them down
So they weren't able
Really appreciate someone else's wife cuz you've been married as long as some other people ask that
Here's your next what she's up to Jazz didn't you can still win this
Something that
Never happened before happened at an Atlantic League minor league game
Just two weeks
What was it a
A player swing his Bat so hard it came around and hit him in the head so he knocked himself out
Be a coach with a ejected from a game for arguing with a robot
Umpire
Or see a pop fly was caught and carried away by a
Siegel resulting in the first-ever bird assisted
Home run
The baseball player swinging the bat so hard that it's working right himself in head and knocked himself out
Show the audience doesn't like that
I don't know if you can hear Anthony but they're all saying it's
B
I admire you
You sir but they were right
I wasn't Factory you're just trying out this thing where a
Robot calls balls and Strikes
A coach did not like the call
Argued and was thrown out by the
Human Empire who is monitoring
All right yeah one more chance I got one right here we go Minor League games are known for their Shenanigans but one catcher tried something
The costume is
Job
What did he do a he carved
Potato to look like a baseball
And through it to track a runner while holding on to
The real ball to tag him out
B Hughes poison ivy
Need to turn the opposing picture into an actual
Belly itcher
Percy tired of squatting behind the plate he dragged a Barcalounger out there and just sat there and challenge them to make a
Remove
Oh my God
I am going to have to go with
Call the potato
Hawaii held onto the ball that's exactly right
And I just want to say she did this
It worked you got the guy out but he was immediately thrown out of The Game and his baseball career
Was over but the big potato
An amazing thing
Call Lovett
I do to Bill how did Anthony Anderson doing her hair
Anthony Anderson's denominator
Different Emmy for best actor in a comedy again for his lead role in ABC's blackish the new season
Premieres in September
Thanks for joining us on wait wait don't tell me
Turn the air will be back in a minute with more wait wait don't tell me
From NPR
This message,
NPR sponsor
KQED
Now more than ever
People of color are hung
For conversations where the violence
Isn't the only topic that's broken
Enter kqed's new podcast
Truth be told
Advise show
Made by people of color for p
That lets us laugh
Cry moan and ultimately discover truth
That lead us closer to
Feeling whole
Truth be told
Listen And subscribe
On apple pie
And kqed.org
Going on a big group
Play sounds good
Tricky when you
You get there and
Totally different
Checkout NPR life
You got on navigate
Subscribe to life
All guys
For all our episode
All-in-one
NPR WBEZ Chicago
MPR news
Quit playing this week with
On the stone
Dhampir again is your host at the Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown
Chicago
Bill remembers of Germany
Is rymar Republic
In our listener Limerick challenge
If you like to play give us a call than one Triple Eight wait wait
That's one eight eight eight
Weather panel
Smart questions
For you from
Company magazine looked into one of the persistent mysteries of office life why no matter what we
Control ourselves
White Oak
No that's not right. You're just forcing me to ask you
Is this
A problem that you have that you cannot
Control yourself in
In the presence of white shirt Whiting out everything
Is that what you do instead of pressing the home button on your phone you just wait out this
Screen if you
Can you give me a hint
Etsy
Murray's birthday was just last week so
Probably still
Bringing in their cakes or eating the bread in cake eating the free food in the office
Why is it that all of us are helpless if there's free food in the office
And if you any fees worked in an office you know that anything edible no matter how old are gross-looking will be
Devour
Yeah from week old birthday cake to that
Caribou carcass the vultures are finished
According to a psychologist in the Cleveland Clinic
The reason we just can't resist
This food is in
In part because office
Is free
Does it appeal to our innate
Desire to get a good deal
But yeah that's single Eminem has been stepped on so much as now part of the carpet
How much does a study cost
That gave us this
World Fair
Discovery cake
Fast Company magazine wondering about this question
Getting gas
That is true if you've ever worked in an office
I mean the stuff you would never eat
Even at home
You like oh my God that big
You've been out sitting out all day
And I was like oh baby
Don't usually you cut it in half
And then you did
And half
And then later
Maestro by Annie
The other half
Describe that is the theory of the
The possibly segmented.
The ideas like you can't eat a whole donut
That's terrible for you
Gain weight but if you cut the donut
Parts and
With enough time between
It doesn't count as eating
Eating a whole donut
Did Donna is Marianne Williamson
Jimmy John Sonic and the Cheesecake Factory all have Foods topping this year's list of what
Carson
Well your clothes I'm going to give it to you anyway basically medically in advisable food
I've never heard that phrase before every
Year
Well every year
Science in the public interest does this every year they announced a list of the worst
Things you can get at
A popular wrestler
Are they called the Xtreme eating Awards
The list highlights the worst things
And you can order for example including the
The Cheesecake Factory
Cinnamon roll pancakes
What did they say are
I have the
Equivalent of 2 and 1/2 days worth
Saturated fat or
Are the same and eating 11
Krispy Kreme donut
Also featured this is Jimmy John's
16in giant gargantuan
Sandwich
Chili's 5 meat Big Boss burger and Taco Bell's big ass
Meat sack
We made that last one up but if you started salivating
You did make that up
Yeah
Right you might want to trademark that now
Coming up it's lightning fill in the blank the first hits
The game where you have to listen
For the rhyme
If you like to play on air
Call the leave a message
AAA wait wait that's 180 date night
To 48924
How quickly contact us link on our website.
That's wait wait. Npr.org
You can find out about attending a weekly live shows right now
Here at the Chase Bank Auditorium in
Chicago upcoming shows August 29th
The 30th at Wolf Trap
Just outside wash
In DC and Northern
Virginia September 12th
But the New Jersey
Performing Arts Center
High urine wait wait don't tell me
Rebecca Rubin calling from New Haven
How are things in New Haven
They're good
Then what are you do there
I work at the jail
Center for emotional intelligence
But really what what do you do with the Yale Center
Intelligence
Educators who want to implement social emotional learning
Milton K12
Really okay trying to make kids more emotionally sort of
The capable
Klonopin and where
Yes
Well good for you and welcome to the show Rebecca Bill Curtis is going to redo 3 News related limericks for the last word or phrase May
If you can fill in that last word of phrase
Is correctly into the limit
When are you ready to play
Here is your
Your first love
Avocado toast
Will not control me
But demand is up
Hit
Shocks mini holy
Now tacos and ship
Resort to fode
They have to use face
Guacamole
Guacamole yeah
Avocados are getting more and more expensive and Millennials have already taken out second mortgages
Store for them as it is so
Restaurants that started making guacamole without avocado
This mock
Guac is made often with the Mexican squash
Called calabacitas
Fun to say
But just not the same
Chef say the flavors almost identical
Princess in the text
Calabacitas tend to be thinner and running
Because he hasn't looked at a bowl of guacamole and thought
You know
I wish this was
Does damper
Here's your neck slimmer
Grab your clubs
To the church we will
Strut strap
Pray for par with no FN door
But
Across the
The turn slowly
The water trapped holy
We're going to church
To play
Putt-Putt
Rochester Cathedral outside London is almost a thousand years old and it has
The distinction of being one of the holiest places in England not only is it a church
But it is now a church
Search with an indoor mini golf
Of course only opened recently and clergy around the world too quick to condemn it describing it
Act of desecration
Some religious scholars believe the course has a place in the church
For example
Jesus
It would be a great golfer he never loses his ball in a water hazard
Murphy's in a fun mood
Hawaiian hazard
Deirdre
Here
Is your last
Limerick
When I work out
Get anxious or fret
I get stains
Funky smell
Send regrets
So I wear a new fabric
That's what when I was
Magic
It smells
Really good
When I
Sweats
Yes indeed scientists have created a new fabric that turns your body
Body odor into a fraction lemony a room
Instead of smelling like an old wet you you'll smell like somebody just
Drowned in lemonade
2 weeks ago
Special cotton fibers in the clothes bind with the proteins in your sweat release
The pleasant scent so essentially the grocery you are
The better you smell
You think about this this technology could lead to total chaos suddenly tons of Bo is a
Sexy thing to list in your dating profile
I like that idea actually
Someone who's constantly a conscious of
I think you know sometimes what other people say it like for example a car air freshener
Which I'd rather be
Car with
You know vomiting dog waste
Smell of a car air freshener
So maybe
Depends what
You think is a pledge
Spell true
It really is a pleasant
Eliminate
Pleasant lemon
Smell
Chicago
Vomit dog waste
Stop playing the lullaby
I love it more flavor option
Pumpkin spice Sports
Surprise chocolate
Men's undershirts banana Center
Sweatpants
Always be the one weirdo who chooses beef
Studio yoga
Bill how did Rebecca dewinter quiz
She's emotionally perfect
3 write congratulations
Support for this podcast
And the following message
Search come from K buxbaum
In support of the David Gilkey and zabihullah tamanna Memorial
Establish
To strengthen NPR's commitment
The training and protecting Journal
Skin high-risk environment
Now I want to watch final game lightning fill in the blank each of our players will have
560sec
Utrecht cancer Network
Worth 2 points bill can you give us
Atlanta HIV
3 palahia
All right
Well polite you are in third place you're up first the clock will start in the beginning first question fill in the blank
On Wednesday Ben Carson defended President Trump
What's the tax on representative Elijah Cummings and the City of
On Tuesday to what has claimed that blank was stalling a trade deal with the us until after
The 2020 election
China
For the first time in a decade the Federal Reserve cut
Blanks
American officials
Confirm that the Sundial Qaeda leader blank
Had been
Osama bin Laden
An 84 year old woman lost for 4 days make
Canadian wilderness
Just demanded blank upon being rest
Beef yogurt
No a cold beer and a hot
Top this week
Disney World
Competitor blank announcer opening a new theme park in Orlando
Universal homeowners
In Florida declined
Press charges
Owner of a Tesla
Drove into their living room
Known owner on the Tesla parked in Islam took out a charging cord
Install the guy's power for 12 hours
How long the Tesla been sitting in his long before we finally noticed that but after calling police to make sure the car wasn't stolen
He decided to just wait for the owners to return
When they did they didn't apologize
Isolated offer to make them in dinner
To make up for the inconvenience and then went inside his house and cooked all the foo
In his presence
Bill how did politics
10 more points total of 12
Flip a coin atom is elected to go second that means that I that you're up next fill-in-the-blank on Thursday the senate pass the bipartisan
Blank deal sending it
The Trump the song
Budget on Wednesday the Trump Administration in
It would set up a system to allow America
To legally import some drugs from blank
No Canada
Reportedly launched
Two more short-range
North Korea right after he was bitten by a shark
Surfer in Florida
Immediately got out of the water and went to blank
The bathroom
The bar a new blood test for blank
Picture signs of the disease decades
For the first symptoms arise
Cancer
Timers less than a month after winning her second consecutive World Cup
Jill Ellis the coach of the US Women's blank team in
He was stepping down
Soccer
Truck driver in Colorado avoid getting a ticket for a broken tail light
By replacing it with blank
I don't know
I don't know a gatorade bottle
Red Gatorade
The officer who pulled the truck over says he was impressed with a driver's temporary fix
Would you just a red Gatorade bottle duct tape over the broken tail light basically
An electrolyte
Electrolyte
The man was let off with a warning after agreeing to replace the tail lights
Soon Wiley marketing department of Gatorade forgiven
A great idea for their new ad campaign
Gatorade drink and drive
6 more points
Second place
Need to win
5 to win only five
You can do this before the game
Fill in the blank
On Tuesday the governor of California
Signed a law mandating the presidential candidates release their blanks
Before appearing on the primary ballot
Right on Monday the departing governor of blank selected is proposed
Successor
Puerto Rico Amanda Florida arrested for driving Under the Influence told the arresting officer
Lizards that he wasn't drinking while driving he was blinking
Classic okay
No
He said he wasn't drinking while driving he was only drinking
At stop sign
Florida
On Monday blank announcer over a hundred million customers had their data breach
Facebook Capital One
On Wednesday the organizers of the MBA
50th anniversary of the blank Music Festival announced
Woodstock
Bright South Carolina Thief who stole the FedEx package off a woman's bra
Front porch was probably surprised when they opened it and found blank
That one of those weird
Fake babies
59 tarantulas on Friday
The notification that are package
Containing 9 tarantulas that arrived but we
What you got home the box was missing yet another victim
Of the porch Pirates have been stealing deliveries
Houses throughout the neighborhood
She notified police who say they're on the lookout for a suspect
Who's 5 9
The brown and desiccated and InTune
In webs
Bill
Did
Adam do well enough to win we have a tide Adam and I died
That means Paula is the winners
Bristol Harbour
I'm surprised
Broke the record with Old Town Road what will be his next big head
Texas stock and Ledger restaurant here in Chicago
Wait wait don't tell me
Is brexit of NPR WBEZ Chicago and association with urgent care cover.
Doug Berman benevolent overlord
Is Paul Friedman or house manager is Tyler Green Assisted by Simon Tran
Are interns open in Abita
And Lila Frances Howard webguru is
Beth Novi
BJ leiderman composer theme our program is produced by Jennifer Mills miles dornbos and Lillian King
This week are writing residents are Ron metellus and Kate
Text Robert
Is Michael Danforth
Big hit after Old Town Road
Adam Burke
Electric
Song from the horse that he wrote
To the Old Town Road in title
SoundCloud rapper on your back
Adam Rodriguez
I said Birkenstock Crocs
An avocado toast
So that he can reach all the other white people that he missed call about them
Will ask you about it on wait wait don't tell me
Peter Sagal and we'll see you next week
This
Is NPR