Support for this podcast
In the following math
I said come from VRBO
Struggling to find the perfect vacation
VRBO will match you to the perfect
Place to stay
Every time
From cabins to castles
They've got it all
Download VRBO
In the App Store
Let Virgo find a hoe
That matches
Hey there is Peter as you might have figured out recently when you tried to listen to our show and got somebody else's or
Tried to listen to another show and got ours
We screwed up
NPR me to change to wear web servers
That we didn't expect to have
Any affected our podcast and we
We're wrong
As far as I know this is the first mistake of any kind of NPR has ever made
Ever
About anything and it feels
O odd
The change forced a bunch of episodes into NPR Podcast feeds
Resulting in downloads you didn't ask
It also made it hard or impossible for you to find a listen to your favorite NPR Podcast
We're really sorry for this
Especially because trust me last week's wait wait was fantastic
Best ever I feel terrible
You didn't get to hear it
We fix the root cause of the problem shortly after we discovered it but it took a while for that fit
Text to make it to all the podcast app
Some pulled it has to do with the size of
Did the tubes the internet is made of
If you unsubscribe
From the show or any other NPR show please take a minute to read
Driving to work this
You are still having problem
Let's just go to npr.org
Flash help
We're taking steps to make sure nothing like this ever happen
Once again for one thing no more letting the kids
Manage the podcast servers during take your child to work day
We're done with that
What's a bad idea
Thanks for listening
And now on to our show
From NPR and WBEZ Chicago this is this wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
Hey Arthur Miller
Step into this crucible
I'm Bill Kurtis
Chicago
Peter Sagal and everybody
We have a very interesting show free today later login to Microsoft
Co-founder Steve Ballmer
He Is We believe the richest guest we've ever had butter
Of course your true wealth is measured in your friend
And it's just an he has more
As many of you know
The NPR Podcast
Speed got all
Scooter Plus
People who tried to download our show got
How I built this
Which I apologize
And the people who wanted how I built this
Got us
For which I apologize even more
So this time you can hear us
We want to hear you the number is 10008 wait wait
Vets 18889
248 9th
Let's welcome our first listen to contested this
Sweetheart you are on wait wait
Hi. This is Gabriel Galvez
Washington DC
I'm great how are you I'm fine what are you doing in Washington
Christina George Washington University but I'm also an Analytics
Center for Amtrak
What's exciting to do in the trains how the trains doing
I'm doing all right I love working Amtrak so far
It's a great job I got to get a ton of great people every single day
I do I get unlimited business travel and get a handful of personal passes but
Kind of hard to Ride Amtrak to where I'm actually from but
Where you actually from
San Diego California
Turn around and come back
Let me introduce you to our panel this week for supper writer and
Performer you can see in the
The final season
Veep
On HBO
It's Peter Gross
Hello
Hello cowgirl comedian performing June 21st of the 23rd at
Add clusterfest
Inn San Francisco Civic Center Plaza
And the Bill Graham Civic Auditorium
I'm driving for the first time
PD the eyebrows
Play who's Bill at this time
Curtis is going to read for you three
Quotations from this week's
If you can correctly identify or explain two of them you will win our prize any voice from our show you might choose on your voice
Ready to go absolutely Attorney General
William Barr
He's talking about
What's the mail
He recently got
You know the letter was a bit
Little Foot
Apparently just didn't
Appreciate the
Tone
In the letter
He got from whom
I believe that's me
Sprint
Butter that was leaked
This week it turns out to have been sent to mr. bar by this gentleman
Right after Mr bar had sent out his summary of the mullet
No I don't think our president actually writes letters
We were not doing too hot right now
After
Years of Silence
As he was viciously attacked by the president and his allies slandered and threatened to special counsel Robert Mueller had
Enough
Is Fury ignited
Heroes up cleanse
His fist
And typed a letter
Use his nuts
So Mueller sent this letter to William Barr
Criticizing the way bar
Distorted mother
Findings about Pres
Trump
The letter said bars summary did not quote
Capture the
The context nature and substance of the investigation
Bar Zen
And summarized
That letter
To the Pratt
Saying quote Robert Mueller says
Cuz I look like I've lost
There's just such an unfortunate amount of
Notkin
Exclusive stuff
Going on it just feels like
Leading up to the report I feel like
Everybody on both sides
Want like someday
Definitive answer
Closure
I want closure I want like the last scene of the movie
Page
Movie you want to see the last you know if you want to see like the last scene
Of our eternity
The Jedi will all the
He walks her dance
Or is it more like the last scene of The Godfather where everybody
No one has ever said this but I'm choosing Ewoks
More like this
Sopranos
Black and then
Decide what
That's what's happening
There's like
No definitive thing and then even mother's letters like I
Disagree with
You drew about
He should have written letters I get stoned
Download
Interesting things about this that didn't get
A lot of attention this week
Is that Mueller and bar our old Friends Bar talked about this
During his confirmation
After 30 years
Their wives
Go to Bible
Study together
Of course bars wife insist The Ten Commandments are really just
Suggestions
More of a listicle than anything else
Can you imagine how like incredibly awkward
These people's game night as they all get together
Cherry bar
And they like play Scrabble
And it's Robert Mueller
Return
Any pics
2 years
Here
Is your next quote the fact that it's
2019 and we're dealing with
This is
Ridiculous
That was a student at UCLA who recently found out that she was among the many people who might have been exposed
What disease making a comeback
Measles that's right Google measles age of course the disease that
That's so contagious
You caught it
Just because I said its name.
America had eliminated measles but then people started saying the measles vaccine was bad for you
So now there are 700 report
Cases of music
Nationwide
And people are freaking out
Parents are trying
Adonai
They are the problem though my kid doesn't have measles
He's a bodybuilder
And that's just facts
And
Front knee
Narnian face knee
Heine
So many people are responsible for the
This crisis is anti-vax
Syncrisis does the right wing nutjobs
Left-wing Nut Job
Religious nutjobs
Dairy and Nut Job
It's so great that in this divided time we live in
Allsides can get
Together to do something
Deep least
Stupid
Now the question is
Affect
Is Scientology
Yes
The question is
Assassins
Ecology Cruise
And they have been
Quarantine off an island in the Caribbean because there's a measles Outbreak on board
This is crazy cuz means old is not the worst thing that ever happened on a cruise people he'll Diesel's is an upgrade from what
You usually get on a cruise America
Gabriel you're last quote is from a
Burger King
Customer
If you don't tell anybody
They don't know
That man was talking about the
The taste of a new Whopper the bear
The first-ever Whopper that does not contain what
Eats right
Me please very good it's called The Impossible Burger it's
All vegetable Patty the tastes amazingly like beef
Burger King offer them is a limited experiment
It was so successful they're extending a nationwide
Which could mean that non-vegetarians are choosing the burger
Which is amazing
We're could just mean that anybody who goes into a Burger King is beyond caring what the
Not sleep
Terrible
Taste like beef but here's the thing
It's still really bad
It has to be in order to taste that good
It's got all kinds of fats to make it take give that juicy taste
Listen to some of the ingredients right
Soy protein concentrate
Methylcellulose
So
Leg hemoglobin
Ingredients of a typical fast-food hamburger
Head tongue
Kidney
Horse
I got two out of three
Is good enough for the congratulations
Right now it's time for you to answer some questions about
This week's news
Peter an investigation by CBS News reported this week
Did some schools are frantically using scotch
Tape roses and old gum to try and teach
Watch kids watch
Kids what it's like
Wynyard school
Schools budget cuts
Can I have a little help sometimes in a piece of tape and a Rose Levy
Weather very much
These are the methods
Used to teach something called abstinence-only sex-ed
Which is sort of like
Starvation only cooking class
So for example
A teacher will stick
A piece of tape
On a student's arm and then tell the kids
You pull it off
And then
Hand the tape to the next
At that point
Here on it
And it's like put it in your arm so it doesn't stick as well the second time right
Which is why you should never have sex
So I get the gum
The Roses the rose Works be in the summer way is what to do
Teacher says here's a beautiful rose never been touched isn't it beautiful
Any handed
First kid in the first get hold
The second kid
Could get it in the pass it around the class
Have the time heroes has been passed around with very many shall we say
Partners
It looks bedraggled and
Bloody Rose
Coming up with some landmarks in our Bluff The Listener game call 1aaa wait wait to play will be back in a minute with more
Don't tell me from NPR
Support for this podcast in
In the following message
Search come from Stanford Children's
What are the scariest things
Mom look
Because the next words are usual
Billy can fly
Or Joey riding the dog
Or a crayon stuck in Valerie's nose
Hear something
You might want to
With over 20
Pediatric offices
Stanford pediatric
Christians are all over the
The Bay Area
Not just in Palawan
Find a Stanford PDF
Stanford children
If you love this show them check out life
Tools to help you get it together
Friend who always has
Great advice
Everything from
How to invest
How to get great workout
Subscribed
Life kit all guide
To get episodes on every topic
All-in-one
Find an Apple podcast
Npr.org
Flashlight
Wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
You're playing this week with Peter Gross Roxanne Roberts
MP3
And here is your host at the Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown
Chicago
Peter Sagan Berry que Bell right now
Don't tell me
Hi
All right and what are you doing
I'm a specialist
Teacher for Middle School
Oh yeah
Challenging job do you enjoy it
I do enjoy a lot but
Challenging is definitely the way I would also describe it
So what do you do to relax after a hard day at school
I think cross stitching and bacon give you both like relaxing and rewarding Hobbies
Really
Welcome to the show Chad
You going to play a game of what you must try to tell truth from fiction
Bill was Chad's topic
Substrate
Pizza we must do everything we can to
Preserve the world landmarks
We have
Which is why for example Egyptians
Brush and floss the pyramid
It's twice a day
This week we heard though about a landmark in
Danger of Panama City
I tell you about it
The truth you want a prize to wait waiter up
Your choice in your voice
Ready to play
Yeah alright then let's hear first from
Peter Gross
Sydney Opera House is
Is a cultural landmark in
Source of national pride for Australians
But this week the staff there discovered a shocking fact Opera might
Destroying the Opera
The current production at the theaters in Newark by the
Australian composer Oliver Bailey
Outback
It's billed as Oklahoma meets Lion King set in the Australian Outback
The first that closing number is meant to duplicate the sound of
Kangaroo Stampede and it's sung by 100-member chorus of all Bass
Spark the lowest no cement
The song begins it's metaphor
Pretty
Van Exel Rondo and Crescendo kick in and it is definitely Vivace and also pretty freaking Forte
And we are all the way to presto and fortissimo thank you very much
During a performance Tuesday night
Estate forget to sync and several performers lost their balance
Toppled over adding an unintended touch
Google, D to a dramatic
Kangaroo Slaughter
At intermission Engineers examine the safe discovered cracks in the foundation
Justice soprano notes can shatter glass it turns out all that bass
Was literally shaking the foundations
Opera House officials are raising money for repairs
And Bailey is being asked to rewrite the Opera
SS destruct
110 koala Street
And the base parts will ship to the slightly higher baritone register
So high I feel like a castrati
Set renowned Italian boss OG hakamo-o prelate
Also what the heck is the show about the anyway
He sent me off when I put it Rest by an opera Outback your
Next story of a landmark
Control comes from Roxanne Roberts
You thought travel made you were bae
And sophisticated
Yeah right
Turns out most of
The Tourist
Easter Island
Maturity of your average
12 year old
The famous Inn
Mysterious
Stone statue
Directed
Between 1100
Are threatened
Because so many
People are
Towing Rules by
Climbing on top of
From the statues
Get photos of
Who sells
Giant noses
Of the sacred stone heads
These juvenile prank
Pixark impound
The natural erosion
The Fragile lucky
Canon Rock
Offered
Instagram laugh
Quotes
I'm troubled by the lack of
Genuine
People
University of
California archaeology
Joann van
Tilburg
Scientist
Mm tours
Per year
Could ruin the world heritage
Good site
Destroying both the
Can art and the local economy
Soylent
Officials are
Creating news
To the heads
So yes
Choose Your Own Adventure
No mysterious ancient
Easter Island
By picking their noses your last story of the Historic Site in danger
Computer
The great clock on Big Ben is a fixture of London
Along with Buckingham Palace
The Tower of London and fog
But a new survey says 70
Percent of Brits under 30 have no idea how to
To read the clock
Why doesn't it just tell me the time like my phone
Says 24 year old Londoner
Lindsey Davis
Those hands are confusing
Especially because
They don't have fingers
They should call them arms
And why the Roman numeral
I don't speak Roman
The change could become a
Member of Parliament
Royston brimble
Bull says the outdated
The clock
Quotes
Pure Cotswold
Which is the most
British sentence I've ever
He wants Britain to modernize
So he's proposing
Latin Deli
LED digital clock crawl be attached
The Big Ben
Right under the old
Clock
So quote
A famous Clock Tower can be enjoyed by many illiterate generation
All right
Here are the three
Landmarks of world history
That might be in danger is it from Peter Gross the Sydney Opera House
Shaken to Pieces by an operator
Inside it from Roxanne Roberts
Sterious heads of Easter Island
Being eroded biters picking their noses
Or
From Peter Gabriel
Big Ben which is in danger by the fact that nobody knows how to read it
Clock anymore
You know as someone who works
Young people and have to tell them what time it is
All day long I'm going to have to go with C to go with c
That you think they're going to put a digital readout on on Big Ben
So that kids these days
That that's your choice
Yes
You've chosen then
PT story to try to preserve this landmark
Anees driving
One of the things they like to do is
Tickle the statues
That was Dr Joanne van tilburg director
Of the Easter Island statue project talking about Tara's habit
Of picking the noses of the giant head
So are you were full by Peter giving him a wonderful day be on our show that he can go with you
His first in this game so thank you so much
Thank you take care
And now the game where accomplish people come on to try to do something
Not generally worth accomplishing it's called not my job
Legend has it
That was a young man named Bill Gates asked
Is college dorm mate
Steve Ballmer
To come help run his new company called Microsoft bomber wasn't sure he was just looking for a summer gig
Didn't want to commit
To a real job
Well 40 years or so later Mr bombers
Retired from his job is
The CEO of Microsoft
The own the LA Clippers of the NBA
Annie's created a new nonprofit called USA facts
Mr. bomber welcome to wait wait don't tell me
Is that story true that Bill Gates ask you to join him in the
This company you're like I don't know
School what does that mean that means
My parents are college and they want me to drop out of business
Skeptical but Bill was the smartest guy ever do so
That was a real positive thing
Right and so you didn't drop out of college like like Bill did he had done that you dropped out of
Stanford Business School
Exactly
My parents were very very happy about that did you ever Lord it over built
Well at least I graduated bill
You know I'm not sure that would have worked for my
In and I'm curious about this your parents you said your parents had to go to college
The first person in you
Your family to do that
So when when you said to the Mom Dad I know you supported me and I got my Harvard degree but now I'm going to drop out of Stanford Business School
And I'm going to go do this thing at the idea that everybody will have their own computer did they like say oh okay makes sense
No
I would say
You know I don't know what that the protocol is not your show but they lost their
Dad asked what software
Now this is the craziest question
What is software computer
Did you did you believe it it did you actually had bill or whatever convinced you yes this is the way of the
Future me everybody's going to have their own computer soon then we're going to provide the soft
Well you know that's the kind of what I thought and then I move up here and within a month
I taught Cheese's
Pete I dropped out of Stanford Business School to be a bookkeeper
For a tiny little company so I
Started talking to Bill about dropping back in at Stanford
Be back
And
Bill
Whenever he was trying to make the the most to bring his dad all six feet seven of them brought him to dinner
Steve
Get it
We're going to put a computer on every desk
Getting every home
And I was mesmerised and afraid of his dad
While you were I mean
There's a famous photograph
Of
The Microsoft
Staff in the early days
Bill Gates
Send
And his partner Paul Allen
I'm not sure if you're in that photo that I'm thinking of
But man did they look 13 I wasn't here when the gang M13
Migrated from Albuquerque to Seattle
They look
So nerdy
It looks like
13 people with 13 asthma inhalers Alpharetta
Was it really like that really like hanging out with guys
Pocket protectors cuz you're a pretty you're a big guy you and Ashley were you like hanging out with his guys are going what am I doing with his
Well I mean it was pretty dirty
Place
Writing software
Pretty nerdy professor
Hello by the way dude
That was not an athlete I was a team manager which subway
I understand you were at you were like a big guy you play
Team manager
I was a big guy a team manager in a math major
I can hear already in your voice your famous enthusiasm
There's a very famous video for
I must be 20 years ago
With you and your other developers conference
And you and you start showing
I'm just going to be blunt with you cuz I think you can take it
You seem insane
I mean I'm not in the business so I did I wasn't quite sure if you were in like a
Crazy person
Has taken over the stage of this Microsoft Office
It is like is that
You is that like the Steve Ballmer that
Your colleagues knew
When does bats
Side to side of a song that famous video when does that
Steve Ballmer tend to emerge
When the Clippers are down
31 McBeth the Warriors and pull the biggest comeback in NBA playoffs
Everybody knows you were an early employee of Micah
Kristoff that company did very well
Had the wherewithal to buy the Clippers is there something about your life that would surprise people
You might imagine what a life
Picture of a man like you is
Well
I think probably the most surprising the most people is
When I was a kid
And even into college
I was a very very shy person
Really I had a hard time
Speaking up in
Class
When I started my first job I'd I met a guy that day and he
He describes it this way
Hi
Wow okay and are you still like that
I got you could tell on the show
Steve Ballmer
It is an actual pleasure to speak to you thank you so much for being with us
But we have asked you here to play a game we are calling
Be on your drive
Cracked slip
Your Steve Ballmer
So yeah we're going to ask you about Lyft
Bomber why I don't know why did you buy the Clippers
Because you could
Answer two or three questions about lip balm correctly you'll win our price one of our listeners the voice of their choice in their voicemail
Bill who is Steve Ballmer playing for Healy
Pics of Seattle Washington
Who won our Alexis marks
Speaker quiz to be in your future if you have one alright Steve you ready to play
I'm ready alright
Here's your first crush
Lip balm is Poppy
Really Poppy
The which of these actually exist
Hey
Lip balm of the day Club
Would send you a new flavor of lip balm every 24 hours because they know you already lost
The last one
Bee lip balm Anonymous a 12-step program for lip balm addict
4C CarMax full body balm for people who want that feeling every way
Easy
Yes my God
I was about to eat in touch or I was going to ask you if you were
Remember but I know you couldn't tell me
Yeah some people think that the manufacturers make lip balm to be addictive
Next question while it's good for your lips
Chapstick
Has other uses
Including which of these
Hey it's the most efficient and minty way to make sure your pancakes don't stick to the pan
Be in 1988 a prisoner in North
Dakota use lip balm to help
Come slide out of his handcuffs and
Escape prison
Orsi loaded into a revolver tubes of lip balm make a non-lethal but effective ammunition for deterring attackers
North Dakota
Greasing my way out of here
The same prisoner
Who was captured but then he later in another caper
Mailed himself
Out of a prison the guy was good last question the most famous lip balm brand is
Chapstick it was invented by the same man
Who also invented what
Hey there
The first working nuclear reactor
Be the Fleet enema
Or see the powdered form of cocaine
Not now you're going to getting me tough
But it's got to be the powder form of
Pronounce it in the original peruvian-style 2
Fleet enema
Turned out to dr. Charles fleetworks both ends
So how did Steve Ballmer do an AR quiz
Steve
That's a win
The LA Clippers in the founder of usafacts.org a nonprofit offering a data-driven portrait of American government
Thank you so much for joining us.
It doesn't it bills wearing Daisy Dukes
From NPR
Support for NPR in the following message come from feather
Weather moving to a new city
Car moving down this
Feather believe
Use that one life
I guess your furniture
Should be able to
Change with you
Become a feather meme
And get access to over a hundred fifty
Pieces of high quality furniture
With the option to add swap buy or return
When life or taste
See how easy
To live free of the burdens are Furniture owner
Available in La Orange County
New York and San Francisco
Feather
Furniture that changes with you
Hey Sophie reisenberg from ask me another
If you're craving nerdy trivia or celebrity in
Use we've got you
You covered
Woodhouse musician Jonathan Coulton
Lexington public radio
Don't miss NPR's hour of puzzles word games and trivia
From NPR and WBEZ Chicago this is wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Kurtis
We are playing this week with Pete
The Opera
Peter Gross
Roxanne Roberts
And he arose
That's a Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown Chicago Peter Sagan you so much
Come on go bills Rainbow Room in our listener Limerick challenge
Game if you like to play give us a call at 1 AAA wait wait that's 180 date 92489
2/4 Rhino panels
For you for the week
Roxanne this week Colorado Senator Michael Bennet became beat
21st
First announced the Democratic candidate for
For president
Which causes a specific problem for the Democrats what is it
I'm going to
What day is it
The debates were they
Fit like
What is SpongeBob
Two debates and
Xi an
There's not enough room at the debate
It's okay that's exactly right
We've known for months that they're too many Democrats running for president but now it's a fish
Now the first Democratic debates
Cite a debate
Gator schedule for
For June with
Han Canada tonight for
For two nights
20 spots
Now there's an extra Canada
The DNC is not happy about this I don't want to be accused
Favoritism
So they've adopted a policy
Pretending
We love all our kids equally
Looks like a dining room table is only so big so they're going to have to make Pete buttigieg go eat in the garage in the car today
More like WrestleMania
I see it I want
90s
When I want him to do
Squares that
I'm so the DNC has a plan they're going to get up at the first debate and they say this
Debate is over book
So we need volunteers to take a later today for a $300 voucher and a guaranteed spot in the car
PT of forties in Norway
They say they've captured a Russian spy
Who is it
Well that's right. I thought I saw this week
Spotted this beluga whale
When they noticed it had this
Equipment harness
On it that was labeled St Petersburg
Further Evidence it was a spy came in the asset it's
Species and it said well
Beluga whale
Buy water board again man with bat not effective
So the Russians didn't even deny that said yeah we've been using whales to spy for years and also we are told your submarines don't
Taste good get on there
This news is tough to the reputation of whales
So far until now seen as innocent in the Affairs of men
Especially killer whales
Who are now going to have to explain look man it's just my species I work at the agency is in
So I have
Yes
Alright this harness I saw a picture
Of this way
It look like it was
Look like
Look like training harness
A little whale
Coming up it's lightning fill in the blank but first
It's a game where you have to listen
In for the ride
If you like to play on air
Call the leave a message at 10008 wait wait
That's one 889-2489
We can click it
The contact us link on our website wait wait on npr.org
You can find out about attending our weekly live shows here at
Chase Bank Auditorium
Chicago
Are upcoming shows June 27th at the Mann Center in Philadelphia
July 18th
But the Blossom Music
Excedrin Cuyahoga
Ohio
Also he never thought this show would be way better if you were playing first
Step back.
It's insulting to work
Get a lot of money to be here
Ask your smart speaker 2
Play the wait wait
Hi you are on wait wait don't tell me
Hi
This is Deborah Bowman from Short Hills New Jersey
I grew up very near there in fact
When I was growing up my Mall
The one where we went
Mauling
What day was the Short Hills Mall
Yes I bet it's changed a lot since
I hope so it was pretty
Is it still there tell me it's still there
So it's still there I try to avoid it at all
Bill Kurtis is going to read your 3 news in like a limerick
To the last word or phrase
If you can fill in that last word or phrase correctly into the limit
Will be a winner ready to play
Yes that would be great
Here is your first
My office
Space cannot
Bb8
It's a curbside that
Executive
Sweet
Myspace
I am marking
With three buck
Luxor parking
My desk
Is set up
Honda
That's exactly right
When I do know in San Francisco is off the charts and co-working space
Cost 1000
The month
It turns out
You can rent
Cozy little rectangle of workspace
For as little as
Was $2 an hour
As long as you're sitting there with a
Turn signal blinking on your desk
This movement of using parking spaces on the
Street as office space started in the Bay Area
It has spread as far as friend
A lot like we work but instead of having to deal with Annoying coworkers you don't know
You just keep getting dinged in the butt by a minivan
You have people over
I'm impressed you with my luxurious
It's like real estate
People bring their desk they bring power cables and hook up their land
They have meetings
You know it's like right there
No there's no car
They just put in
Meter to feet
Apparently
Mendoza there's no law that says
You can sit there
Seems like a loop
Alright here is your neck slimmer
The girl in the live report snort
Men once
Swore them for indoor
Courtsports
When legs aren't
Then you can go skimpy
Hey man
Slip ons
Is really short
Short shorts
Despite how terrible they look product
Are making shorts for men
That are very short
It's a new thing go towards the light man the buy light do they mean the light palette part of your inner thigh
Short shorts or mini skirts for men are hitting the rack
This summer they're being Tastefully styled with Blazers and ties for professionals
Repaired
For the same team for that embarrassing father look
How much do they pay
Call they cost of course hundreds and hundreds of dollars
Do you supposed to pay this
Did they say what you have to wear your shorts down to your knees
Can you buy bunch of shirts and Ernie's Mexican Sono
You got to buy him so they hardly card
Everybody can tell if you're Jewish
All right
Here is your last
Limerick for confessional ears it's a tough
Who will not run their mouth
Like a boss
Hip secret seal Harbor
Laura Barber
The pope told them both
They can't
Little tricky
Gossip yes gossip Pope Francis
Address to gathering over 200 hairdressers and beauticians
Apparently he had no poping
And to do so and he told them to avoid the quote temptation of Gossip that is easily as so
Associated with your work
Unquote
He then gave his next pronouncement asking the Sun not
To shine
Where where was Matt's apparently I think it was in the battle
That they came to see
And there was like Hey every care dressers I know your stereotype is
It's kind of cool that he would know that that's
The stereotype
Well this is the pope of the people in the Poconos
So
Where he knows what's up
Series Page 6
Bald fade
The pub at 6 and then Page Six
The big sick
Bill how did Deborah do in our quiz
She did really well
She got everyone
Congratulations
Bloomingdale's at the mall
Support frame
TRN the following message come from feather
On average
Rich people moved 12 times
Before buying a
So why are you still buying furniture
Every time you move
Feather is a Furniture subscription
That gives you flexibility
Over your furniture and your spa
Get access to over a hundred and fifty pieces of fur
And the option to change
As your life
Subscribe now
Decide later
Visit live feather.
Start experiencing the benefits
Furniture flexibility
Feather
Furniture
That changes with
Support also
Comes from the Illinois office of Tourism
Who would like to add
If you're up for amazed
From Chicago to Lincoln
From Shawnee National Forest
The Main Street Galena
There's a lot to see in
Illinois
Some might even
It's amazing
But we won't
Because that's really up to
So busy
Enjoy Illinois.
And see if you're up for what some people might call
Amazed
Payton Scott
Gyros creator
How I built this in
We're returning to
San Francisco
Second how I
The Summit
Supported by
American Express
I'll be joining there by founders
Companies like Instagram
Slack away
Bliss JetBlue
Many many more
Visit Summit
Npr.org
More and
To see you there
Now on to our final game lightning fill in the blank each of our players are there 60 seconds in which to answer as many fill in the
Does Hershey candy stripe dancer net worth
Bill can you give us the score
We have a three-way tie
Everyone has three
Paul Ryan
I am going to arbitrarily decide the
The PD are going to go
Beginning first question film
On Wednesday the White House asked
Congress for an additional 4.5 billion dollars
Ways to address issues at the blank
Opera
Nick
This week WikiLeaks founder blank with sends
250 weeks in prison
Looking for jumping bail in the UK
According to a poll
Released on Thursday blank has it
The 26-point lead in the race
The Democratic president
I'm on the memorabilia on sale for this week
Weekend's Kentucky Derby races
Is a $200 blank
Saddle
No jar of the previous Derby winning horse
What is poop
To Kill a Mockingbird in the ferryman led the nomination
For the 2019 Blanco
Tony's
A beloved parrot at a zoo in Brazil is attracting new visitors
After it was revealed he survive blank
No
Survive being caught in a shootout bitten by a snake
And kidnapped by poacher
Freddy the pirate is he the luckiest or unluckiest bird in the world he was brought
Did the zoo after getting caught in the
Shootout between his former drug-dealing owners and please
He was bitten by a giant snake
In a few days after that kidnap
Exotic animal seller
And to relax
Looking forward
Going on a wonderful cruise with a bunch
Scientology
How did people
Boynton is in the lead with seven alright
On Wednesday
The Trump Administration
Can filed a request to a federal appeals court
To strike down the
Entirety
By the Obamas
Right on Monday the White House order tougher restrictions on people seeking blank
Beezus
Asylum from consideration
For the blank
Over eight hundred thousand people were told to evacuate
The giant Cyclone headed toward blank
My house
India best known for Boyz in the Hood oscar-nominated director
Your blank passed away
This week at the age of
Yes following their NCAA win the universe
Nu men's basketball team
Decline in Abbott
The White House right a busy Street in downtown Chicago was closed off
After police spotted a suspicious object
Which turned out to be blank
It was a
Drunken Cubs fan fighting a drunk
White Sox fan
No it was that would be great
No it was a
The can of Chef Boyardee on wheels
You can't do no shirt or not to be harmless but you know the old slug
If your Chef Boyardee something Chef Boyardee
Cordoned off the street before realizing
Suspicious mechanical object with a can of pasta on wheels
A student had made for a school project
Can you sponsor the event the police released an official
Statement saying quote
SpaghettiOs
Bill how did Pete gross doing AR quiz
At 4 right
Sigmar points
Total of 11
All right now
I have children Roxanne to go last cuz I know how much you like
From behind how many does she need to win
Toilet I-5 to win
Here we go rock
This is for the game
Fill in the blank following a meeting with President Trump Democratic leaders announced
2 trillion dollar plan to
Improve blank
On Wednesday in Naruto the new emperor of blank formerly took
The throne
Write this week Venezuelan opposition leader
Juan Guerrero said he doesn't have enough
Military backing
How's the current president blank
Medora right this week the US Women's National Team
Announce their roster
The 2019
Woke up right
When vice president Pence cave
Speech in the USS Harry Truman on Tuesday sailor said they were instructed
Blaine when he arrived
Pray
No.2
Quote clap like we're at a strip club
Gentlemen welcome to the stage Mike Pence
Billion dollars in ticket sales the latest movie in the blank series Mash opening weekend records
Maine became the first state to ban food containers made of blank
Styrofoam to Domino's in Houston was cited for assault after he punched a co-worker who blank
Stole
No after he
Spoiled the end of the new Avengers movie
Father's Day the employee punched
His coworker in the chest after he revealed massive spoilers about Avengers endgame during their shift
Sally the spoilers didn't end there and this is
Is totally true the arresting officers police report
Awesome
Spoil the movie for anyone who read it
The person said to the other person
The officer has since tried to backpedal saying that he made all the spoilers up
Just like Kevin Spacey's character made up that whole story at the end of The Usual Suspects
Bill
Did Roxanne
15 wins
Rekindle their friendship
Thanks for providing the sustenance needed
To survive another day
Wait wait don't tell me on NPR WBEZ Chicago in association with Productions
Philip gotika rights are limericks are public address announcer
Paul Friedman
Warehouse managers Tyler Green Assisted by Simon Tran
Interns Rachel Clapper
But Alex McGowan rweb Guru is
Beth Novi
BJ leiderman is produced by Jennifer Mills miles dornbos and Lillian
I am possible producer is Peter Glenn
Carrier
Our business office manager is calling producers in Chile
An executive producer of wait wait don't tell me
What will their old friendship
I think I'll probably go for a stroll downtown
Chicago
Go to the bean
Look at each other's reflection
Realized
They're going to settle into the couch
Binge watch
Season 5 of The Great Bridge
British baking show
Go to Burger King for
Salty lick blood
Burgers
What can I ask you about it
This
Is NPR