From NPR and WBEZ
Chicago
Wait don't tell me
DMV
Check out these fireworks
Bill
Heimdall
Everybody this is the time of year when we celebrate Santa Claus bringing the Declaration of
Independence to the Happy children to Philadelphia
Back in the olden time
Times of the 1920s
So you're putting presents under the independent
We thought we'd share some favor
Segments from my recent shows
Sometime
Actually
Important
Appear on our show
Probably
Because it made them
Mistake of thinking we're normal
The last year Christine Lagarde
Major director of the international
Refund
Peter began with a question
Protocol
I should say
We've never spoken to the head of a
Important International
Alliance before so how how should you be addresses
Director lillegard Madonna God we don't
Do you get to sucha Colby Christina
Most most people at the Olympics
Scold me
MD
Managing director
Very nice lady in the chain
Winston-Salem
Oh that's very cool one of the
First things were kind of curious about is what you do and now we assume that you have people killed is that
Seriously
I know this
A complicated question
But none the less cuz I understand that you spend all day
Having people call you up and asking you to lend the money
What is conscious
Improved over time
At the moment
It's full of sable
But we getting on The Bachelorette
Pictures of all sorts of issues like monetary tightening a lot Financial
Horse riding
And capital flows coming out of the big Emoji market economies around the world that's all running into troubles
Have I mentioned that we are all Humanity
Is Paula Poundstone here
Do they pay interest on this loan
Which country or developing country
If you are developing country will lend you
Money at 0
Interest rates
Because committed your
Chicken feed slow and it would be totally abusive and unfair to land at
Expensive
What's the diff definition
Of lichens between
Define directions to the amount of
Dollar
Custom interior
If you are below.
$10 purpose
Then you're alone
Discover Diamond developing countries
In addition to the Aveeno the extraordinary
Important education
And various posts
We discovered that you at one point where a competitive synchronized
Swimmer
How do you feel about men in
Speedo
But I'm more interested in actually the issue of Shaving
At least a little bit of hairs on your legs
Because that is a
Actually
How high and how good you are
In the water never heard anything like this here saying
That synchronized swimmers need to have a little bit of hair on their legs that can't be completely smooth why is
Is there anyway it's because when you're thinking too much
Did you shave your legs completely
Where You Are
What you're telling me is like when you see synchronized swimming as as you once were
And is water in the pool and their legs are straight up in the air
They can only tell that their legs are straight up in the air or wherever they're supposed to be because of the sensory
Feeling from the hairs on their legs
Exactly right
I didn't play this is wonderful because I
I did not know that I would have anything I could talk to you about
Ask if your career where you a competitive synchronized swimmer did you actually go to competition
Do you use anything that you learned there and decided who to loan money to
If there's somebody who comes from a country that
Are we not going to be good for the money
Do the little hairs in your legs
Well
Christine Lagarde we are delighted
To talk to you it is
The pleasure to get to know you but we have in fact
Invited you here
Play a game
This time we are calling
Lagarde
Meet LaGuardia
Read ask you about
America's greatest mayor fiorello LaGuardia of New York City a man much better
The airport they named after
Answer questions about the Little Flower as he was known
And you will win a prize one of our listeners the voice of anyone from her show they choose
On their voicemail boo
Boo
Sorry
Bill who is Christine Lagarde playing for
Carl Hagen
Princeton New Jersey
Are you ready to play
Your first question the funeral of the Guardia was an immensely
Popular figure in his
His day he received what tribute from president
Franklin
Roosevelt said he is just 5 feet tall
But it's all Vim
Be upon meeting Winston Churchill
Roosevelt said quote in English
Orsi Roosevelt said quote the only thing we have to fear is fiorello LaGuardia
I'd say beat your right that's what I'm saying is the highest praise I don't have
Next question LaGuardia went on a camp
Pain in New York City against
Crime in Vice
He once declared that the sale and possession of
What
Would be illegal in his town was it a violin cases
B slingshot source
Artichokes
What month does bee slingshot
Ocala State
I just want you to know now you know how I felt stuck
Going to you about international trade
Artichokes
Controlling the artichoke mark
Kentucky banned their sale in till prices
What does this is exciting if you get one to get this last question correct
What a prize
Nahmir died in 90
AK-47 but his influence lives on
What other important feature of Modern Life
Has been credited
The mayor
LaGuardia was it a
10 items
Or less
Express lane in the supermarket he demanded after having to wait in line
For 20 minutes to buy a single tomato
B thong underwear
Which strippers in New York invented to get around LaGuardia zanti nudity laws
Or see the website BuzzFeed
It was named after the marriage practice of public feeding is of his dog
Buzz
See you're going to say that the website BuzzFeed
You know the crowd is morning text mean
Do you have the chance
What's to change your answer
All right
Memphis beat
What happened was I said he went on a campaign against Vice
In the city the strippers were
We were told they had to put on underwear.
Perform
But they wanted to expose
As much of themselves as possible
So they invented
Thong underwear
Wow isn't that amazing
How did the director of international monetary fund
Do an art show
Marvelous
Congratulations
3 year old winner
Managing director of the international monetary fund
Thank you so much for joining us.
Has Ben's Lagarde found out we're not like the rest
Steve NPR
You can list it all week
Steve inskeep
Never once
Hear a news story length
Helen a new study shows that
Fish
Can potentially be what
Delicious
That's good but that's not new scientific knowledge
Yes
Well some say that
Press close enough
Pessimist
What would you be
You're right I mean if you want to fish is there a fish being a pessimist is just
Realism
You're not going to work out great for you if you're available
We had a baby
Well
This is what they did
They are
They took these
And they they
Allow these fish
Tumi
Some of the females got to mate with
Did not
Then they took those pictures
And they gave them a nap
Opportunity to
Explore places
Following along so far
It turns out
The fish
That didn't get there
Preferred maid
Just born in
They're like
Things don't work out
It's not going to
Baby food item
Care
What is the truth
A journal
Did they start listening to Morrissey and things like that
It's me that was terrible
How to hook up with
The Brad Pitt of Fish seafood
Fish that got the hook up with like
Busted fish
And they were like
Exactly the experiment
This is my entire dog
Tender exist
Scream so much
It sounds sad but remember with all the
Prescription drug
Bugs that are now in
The water supply these fish are going to feel much better and have no problem
I'm getting in a wreck
When we come back
What do you do with a
The problem like
Scunthorpe and the greatest anchor ever meet
Greatest anchor ever
How many acres will never move again will be back in a minute with more and wait wait don't tell me
From NPR
Support for this podcast
In the following message
It comes from
The Economist
A weekly mag
Ring inside
Opinion on International and US News
As well as economics
Politics business
Finance
Science and Technology
There's something for everyone
The Economist
The recent article the promise and problems of cities
Where an archaeologist
Floors the enduring appeal
Urban
The Economist is offering listeners
The free print copy
For your free print
We just text
Wait wait
The nine nine
No matter what you got planned
You need a song
Summer this week on NPR
Pop culture happy hour we are rounding up
Burt's from NPR music
We will play a ton of song
Spirits and might even find you
Text favorite artists
NPR pop culture happy hour listen
Scribe now
Wait wait don't tell me the NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Kurtis
And here is your host at the Chase Bank Auditorium in Chicago
Peter Sagal
Thank you bro
We are celebrating our nation's birth
Which bill will now
Reenact
Bush George Washington it's time to push
While we wait
Poor baby America to Crown let's keep listening back
Do I favorite segment from the last year's game we played last
September
Hi this is Megan mosto Becca and I
Live in Missoula Montana I love Missoula Montana one of my favorite places
Well I work at a local TV station full-time and I work at animal wonders which is
Local
Exotic animal rescue in
Oh no wait a minute exotic animal
Not dogs and cats
We just rescued a baby
A fever last summer are you rescuing them from
World of Beer
Beaver parents
Sodus baby beaver had a severe disability and so
He gets to live the rest of his life and sit with the rest
You so funny
Truth from fiction
Bill what is Megan's topic
These scum
Thorpe
The scunthorpe problem it sounds like
Terrible Robert Ludlum novel
And it might be we haven't checked
Realtor
For something we saw it written about in the news this
Panama starting to tell you about a picture when he's telling you
The truth and you win our prize
The voice of your choice
On your voicemail are you ready to play
Absolutely
From Helen Hall
It's a struggle that many public radio fans know all too
Too well after years of listening to the
Your favorite radio personalities
They finally get tick
Steven and person and show up
Excitedly at the venue
Only two
Experience
The shock of their lives
That's what they look like
Fresh air host
Terry Gross
Porter most commonly heard
Feedback at Live Events
But you're supposed to have long flowing hair
It happens so often that NPR has given it a name
The scunthorpe problem
Named after Eliza
Scunthorpe
Contributing member of w
Burn boss
Miss scunthorpe
Score tickets
Favorite radio show
Wait wait
Don't tell me
I guess I always imagined them to be you know
Really
Distinguished-looking
Unsettling
Experience came to a head when the host of the show
Bagel with an ounce
Leaping
Feeding dismay
Miss scunthorpe repeatedly
I don't believe your hair bring out the real Peter
Unable
How to be a tease
NYX Contour
Escorted out of the show and off the
Will you confess
Canceling my membership
There's no way that imposter was Peter
Peter Sagal
Like Pierce Brosnan
GoldenEye
Gunthorp problem is people believing the public radio figures
I'm more attractive than we really are and being shocked
Find out the truth
Yorick scunthorpe
Explanation to come from Edinburgh
With so much
Intentional obscenity on the internet it seems that unintentional obscenity is also becoming a problem
Take the case of
Sports writer Natalie weiner
Who tried to log on to a website only to have the site
It security protocols
Reject her name as a
Offensive language
It's part of what web developers refer to as the scunthorpe problem
So-called
Because when certain a eyes and internet monitoring algorithms are confront
Did by name
Like that of the English industrial town scumthorpe
They often flagged as objectionable
As it
Contained within a particular four letter word
That many find defense
Quick hands
The word isn't
Thor
As researcher Michael Veal puts it somewhere
What is a common abbreviation of the name Richard
Are harmless in certain context
But in other case
His parents might not want the muse
Imma Be flagged by certain types of program
It seems apt
So many years of being played by dirty minded 11 year old boys the internet
Has turned into one
Who can't or won't distinguish whether charity buckets is a woman's name
Or just a very particular request on GoFundMe
Cooter's Luray
Teach computers when the naughty word
It's not really a naughty word
And your last description of the scunthorpe problem comes from Navy
The scunthorpe problem if you're not familiar is a term in biology for the tendency of human beings to
To react
To the discovery of a new species
Please by immediately trying to
Qechs
It gets its name
Information
56 incident when a scientist names dr. Thomas Contour
Proudly presented the discovery of the Platypus out of conference
Described
Tis the body of
Weasel the head of a duck and a
Heats of a woman
The first question
From the audience was incredible Discovery sir what side
Is do you recommend
Weeks Later doctor scunthorpe
Released his
Findings in a paper
Recalls the Platypus
Please don't eat us
He was ignoring
Sherpas population
Somerset
Scunthorpe problem
Most boring
Orange
There is something real
Call Dad
Problem
But is it
From Helen the problem of people being inevitably this
Disappointed when they find out
What their favorite Public Radio
Actually look like
From Adam Burke
The problem of people or words with names that could be dirty not being able to use computers cuz
The computers won't let them
Or
Is it from Maeve Higgins the problem with people immediately celebrating the discovery of a new species
She's by immediately trying to
Eat it
Which of these is the real
Scunthorpe
What's the problem
Well it's really funny.
Because I'm recently I looked up
A picture of what you look like
Peter and I was very shocked to find out what he looks like
Replace the word shop
Surprise
I'm pretty sure it's Adam story
Refers to a problem in computer program
Will you chosen at
Tim Storey then
Definition of the scunthorpe problem
Talk to somebody who knows all about
My last name
Weimar quicker than algorithm
That was designed to prevent
People from using
Pornographic content or something
That was definitely Winer
A staff writer at SB Nation in the victim of the real scunthorpe problem
Because she can answer her name and will computers congratulations
You were right Adam Burke was telling the truth you picked a d got the point
You would surprise any voice you like saying pretty much anything you want
Wonderful thank you you're very very well who can ask before you
Go
What did you imagine I look like a description of a
Different sounds pretty good everybody jumps on you
Bengals play
Earlier this year we went to San Antonio Texas
That's where we were lucky
The interview one of the greatest TV Anchorman ever well
The other great
TV Anchorman ever
My old friend Dan Rather join us on stage
And Peter began in the appropriate way
Comparing him to me
You started and it turns out that many reporters I know including Bill started this way you were a local guy you were
What you were doing minor league baseball games at one point
I did I did play by play
Football baseball basketball
Ball
Track practice really difficult
How to do play-by-play.
Wait a minute how would you do that he seems to be running more
Parties voting already has this shot put in his hand and
He takes 5 Steps and Heathrow
Do you think there's one moment that which you sort of got your start
Started your
The career that we've also
Watching movies many decades
Well I do that there was a great hurricane
In 19
61 hurricane
Carla
Which was it that down and I think
I'm still the largest
In terms of sheer size
Hurricane on record
And I had just started in Tel Aviv
How to make my move from
Radio windows
Television
I'm still new to
And we
Roundup in the right place
Listen to write time on Galveston Island
Hurricane came in
And that was picked up by other stations nobody else was there
Broadcasting
So if I had to point to one moment that
Made my career
That was probably
Yeah it's funny cuz Bill got his sort of
Start over the great toe
Tornado in
Kansas tornado
It trailer maybe these
Maybe these weather events are being caused by ambitious young reporter
You were known for many things but certainly for being
Fearless not in the not only the places you went like War zones but also the way you treated
Do people in power
There's a famous into
Where you got up and you ask
The President Nixon
A question of
During Watergate and he didn't like
And I believe you said are you running for something
And you're famous for
Response was
No service
President ru
A pretty good
Horse took over as the anchor of the CBS Evening News taking the Baton from Walter Cronkite another Legend 2
Ticket from Edward R Murrow so
You're part of that line one of the things that people
Noticing as you as you
You settled into that role was you were looking for your
Sign off
Cuz famously of course contract would end his broadcast with that's the way it is
And what was your thinking
I needed something
You needed something
What was suggested to me that you need to sign up
Following a legend like that is not the easiest
I did write my first suggestion was maybe I can say well
That's some of the way it is
That's the way it might be.
What is rape
I was thinking you
My father
I like father's favorite word
Discouraged
Solana beijing
I thought well maybe we could just pause and
That's the CBS Evening News Dan Rather reporting
Courage
The more I thought about it the more I got elected
Bring for me
I will say that the executives in the
Horrified
Short lasted about a week
Interviews that week was pretty much you either stop using this site
Sign off are we stop using you
Wow so it was easy
I just decided not to have one
Just went with the playing my best shot didn't work
Out of all the people you've interviewed and you interview just about every piano major historical player in Les
50 years was there
Favorite somebody who
He was glad to talk
Well I'm glad you put the preface
Sister goes last places I've been
Lucky and might have a blessed I could give you the names and maybe seven people but
If I had to pick one it would be Doctor Martin Luther King and what we
We're still in the emergency override
Stubborn donkey Caden covering.
Peking change me as a
Professional
And it changed me as a person
And for that reason I would see if I had to pick
It going I would say
Give him dr. Martin
Luther King and covering in Bay today
Rauscher
I imagine
I'm envious of you have a chance
When you're watching whomever do you ever like
Miss it
You're like if I was there I would have the question
Like every second
I can imagine
Well then rather it is an absolute honour to
To talk to you but today we have in fact asked you here to play a game
We're calling
This game is tougher than the height of an armadillo
Sun that forgot it's something as I'm sure you know you are famous for what people called rather ism
Folksy sayings
Colorful metaphors and colorful wisdom
You've used so many of them over your career
We want to see if
You can pick
The one you actually came up with
From some fake ones that we made up
In tribute to you
Did you can do that two times out of three you'll win a prize for one of our specimens
Bill who is Dan Rather playing for
Tori hinderstein of Washington DC
Here's your first rather than this was when you were covering the 2000 election
Did you say this race is
Tight like a
Too small bathing suit and
2 long ride home from the beach
B
Papa wear your good suit cuz we got ourselves
The Thai
Or see this race is tighter than aunt
Tilly after 1/3 Moscow mule
Definitely
I've always wondered
Did you just make those up off the top of your head did you like them having ready to go
In the beginning
They came from working in the oil fields
This is way men talk
You have got to be kidding me
You can only say it
It's hot as hell so many times
Hotter than a Laredo parking lot
Use colorful language
All right we have two more
You did well with that one this is now we're moving to time to the election of 2004 that way
Was George W bush real life
Scary
During that evenings coverage on CBS did you say a
John Kerry's wife might on Heinz but this is one night he won't catch up
Be we used to say if a frog had side
Pockets he'd carry a handgun
Or see it all comes down to 208
Which i o which stands for Ojai it's over
Definitely be doing really well
Here's your here's your last question this is a great metaphor you use while commenting
The 2016 election was it a
This race is a Backcountry Tilt-A-Whirl it could go either way
Be like the talking horse
Said to the hopping Bowl I can't believe what I'm seeing
Or see if Clinton wins
Florida this race will go faster than a Hamilton ticket at face value
I don't recall saying any of
Do you know which one you wish you were
I guess that would be
Bubba like the talking horse Ed to the hopping bullet is a good one but the one that we were told you said
If Clinton wins Florida this race will go faster than a Hamilton ticket at face value which I thought was great cuz you're updating your
Wild Bill how did your old friend and do it anyway two out of three is a big win for
Dan Rather
What is a legend of Broadcast News and the creator of news and guts
What's media Dan Rather
Thank you thank you Jesus
When we come back r-panel opines and Seth Meyers recliners
Is in an armchair at Carnegie Hall that's in a minute
Wait wait don't tell me
From NPR
Support for wait wait don't
Tell me in the followings
Message comes from rocket mortgage by Quicken Loans
Imagine how would feel
Deals to have an award-winning team of mortgage X
Make the home button
Process smoother for you
The history of industry-leading online lending technology
Rocket mortgage is
Changing the game
Visit rocket mortgage.com
Wait
Equal Housing lender licensed in all 50 states
MLS
Consumer access.org number 3030
Rocket mortgage
My Quicken Loans
Push button
Get more
What is video games can help you and your
Child Bond and learn important skills
NPR life kit for parenting
Getting on screen
When the big things were working on right now is a constable resiliency
And not quitting with
Something is hard sometimes you lyrics
Can lose and loose
And games are great with the
Check out
Aimores
Subscribe to life kit all guide
Oliver episode
All-in-one
From NPR
And WBEZ Chicago this is
Honda Curtis
And here is your host at the chase
Chase Bank Auditorium in Chicago
Peter Sagal thank you girl
Father Joe's on NPR they bring you the news
Supposedly
But the important stuff isn't one of our elected leaders or do
Do another real work
Ruining everything
Is done by every day
Like you and me
Here's our panel talking about the quiet Heroes
Score making this country
A living hell
Alonso
Of Homeland Security
Is looking for creative ways to
To fund the border wall
They're saying they can
Raise up
$3000000
I was just buy collect
Eating what
Water bottle
The airport you are very close
What's actually
Because it is something that people leave at TSA
Not water bottle
Something else
Snow
Something else something else has metal in their pod
People at their sing
Drug Administration will be protecting the border the same way that lousy roommate you had that is laundry
By stealing
Your quarter
Emails obtained from the Department of Homeland Security
Security outlined their plans
How to raise 3 million dollars
300000000
Incense
In funds for the border from change people leave
When they walk away from the TSA security line
All I need is Bill Gates
The fly camera
Once
You'll be able to build
The whole wall
I don't like that the money's going
Going towards the wall but I'm off
Taking all of my check
All of the time
Really
Mm I'm able to
Things on my phone
Just looking at my face
And yet I've got
Tons of metal in my pockets like
Please can I
Get into your state will you take these
What's up with the big metal stuff
It's all grimy
It's filled with germs
Take all of it
Actually that's actually plan B
Cities like New York
LA and Washington DC
You're trying out new laws that would allow ordinary citizens
I'll give you a hint
Finally you
Fulfill your childhood dream of being a meter
Trying out people giving each other tickets yes they're allowing civilians to hand out
Parking tickets
Jeff the terrible life
Idea that's where we are faced this will be known as the era of
Terrible ideas
Frustrated
The Jerk of Park
In the bike lane
You can be the jerk
Hoot owls on them
The cops
More and more cities are turning to Citizen volunteers
To report their neighbor
Behavior
You know after a couple of years of the United States
Seeming like Nazi Germany
It's a refreshing now that I have it just seemed like
East Germany
Wow
To the program's Berry in New York City where you live so watch out face
Anybody who uses a
An app to report illegally idling vehicles
Can receive
10% of any
Fine
It's a bounty system
What man has made
$9,000 so far
That's almost one month
That's true
Yeah it is time for the various kinds of parking
What else do you want to reply say this isn't funny it just gets me all fired up
I want to read
Report my neighbor's up
Stairs I live in an apartment building and their children are
Puroland
See this is why
This is why New York
The great City
Test the system New Yorkers New Yorkers already get along so well
Is fine but like the
Those guys that walk on down the
Street out in public
Flip flop shoes
Yeah
With their big man feet hanging over the edge
Fine
You going to find
The Hangover 2
Overbite
Yeah $200 a violation
Blue shirt and
Can you have man boobs
Lipstick out of the side where the arm should be
$300
Alonzo it's almost summer camp season and you'll be happy to know that there are now summer camp
Can you children as young as four
Where they will learn all about
Wow.
That that's a pretty broad statement
Can you give me a hint
Who's actually
The reason why these camp
What are popping up
It's important.
The young people from being
Seduced by socialist
Oh so that they can learn all about what
The Bible and
Conservative
That was not about religion
Specifically
The counter the social
Capital capitalism
Kids say sharing is caring but you know what
Caring is not for
Closers
If you're a kid
Doesn't understand how capitalism works
You can send them to a camp like the one run by a company
Call the business hovater in South Florida
Their kids will quote
Learn how to monetize their Hobbies
Interview local corporate executive
And shoot YouTube commercials for their perspective businesses
Unquote
You know your little camper has mastered the principles of the free market
When he says to his counselor how much do I have
To pay to go home
Sinew meaning
Saying I want to
Chemours
That's true
Other kid is like well I
Some of the kid has while I'm making
MLB $5
Control in the market
S'mores
But he's paying off the counselor to make sure that no one else is allowed to make
S'mores annie's basically understood the American system
These kids would learn how capitalism works
Works when they're rich Perrin
Pay to get them in
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
With the Capital One Savor card you can earn 4% cashback on dining and entertainment
That means 4% on checking out the new French restaurant
Or 4%
On bowling with your friend
You'll also earn 2% cash back at grocery stores
And 1%
On all other
Now when you go out
You can't in
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Terms
Apply
Support for NPR comes from Newman's Own Foundation
Working for nourish the
The common good
By donating all profits
It's from Newman's Own food products
Tax to charitable organizations
That seek to make the world
A better place
More information
Is available
Newman's Own Foundation. Org
One thing you might know about those of us who work in these satirical industrial complex is that we all
Hang out together
All the time
And we only do it in the most fancy places
Like Carnegie Hall
Last winter we allowed in audience
I'm still listening that's we chatted with our late night
College Seth Meyers
Peter may not have been to show her who he was
I understand you have a television show up sometime it's on very late at night
Did I am never awake
I have no idea what I would do if someone said okay you're going to be starring in a in a
Evening show
Four nights a week
Was that intimidating when you got that job
It was
Saturday Night Live was so intimidating when I got that job that I was
Prepared
To be intimidated again if you can do that
When when you said yourself okay we're going to have our own our own a duration of late night
You said I want to do
What
I didn't know
Really
When I first started doing the show your biggest fear was how do you fill an hour and that is not my fear
It's been replaced with bigger fears
No I was not joking we are very proud that you came out of Northwestern
College and then you were in Ohio
Chicago improv tradition
Considered improper profession
You know my parents
Did deserve some of the blame when they
When they took me to Chicago and New Hampshire with my parents also went to Northwestern and when they took me there
For my first
The week of
School they took me to Second City because it was something they had done in college
And so
Second City and so
Which was a grave mistake because that was so much more interesting than any of my freshman year class
But then I was very lucky
Theater in Chicago
It's based in Amsterdam the Netherlands and so I audition for that and moved overseas for a couple of years
Improv in Amsterdam for Dutch people
How did that go
There were nights
It was not great
I have a love affair with the Dutch so this will sound like a criticism but it's the loving one they are the
Most honest people in the world
Okay
I remember after show
A judge guy
Came over and said hey I'd like to buy you a drink and I said oh did you like the show he said no
I said why are you buying me a drink
Serious people are they hard to make laugh
Play would only laugh if it was genuinely funny and so I do
Think looking back when you
It's been two years somewhere we're polite laughter doesn't exist it makes you better come
I put you through and you never think
You were good when you were
You know I should point out that Imports 80% of our audience
Was Dutch any other 20% were Americans who were visiting aunt
Amsterdam
And of course they weren't there cuz Improv
Was legal aid help or hurt
You know people say oh my God
A stone. Ian Smith's me the best audience they are the worst. Even because they laugh at the house
That you're wearing a perfectly crafted joke and they're already laughing
How you walked on stage
You know we have a little bit of History
But
You know well recently
Michelle wolf who who was a colleague of mine she worked at are showing in after her Correspondents Dinner key
Tweeted that she bombed as badly as I did during my Correspondents Dinner
I was thrilled
To be compared to her
Sheena well first of all I thought she was pretty great she was Fearless but you were especially Fearless
This is the famous 2011
White House Correspondents Dinner to make fun of a certain person in the audience
Donald Trump
Private citizen at the time
And you you completely mock the whole idea of him him becoming president
And some people say of course that's when he said I'll show them
Wella Color Me shown
But you're like the mrs. O'Leary's cow the national concentrate
Even mrs. O'Leary's cow that night didn't walk out of there going I crushed it
Well it's such an honor to talk to you we have invited you here to play a game
We're calling
Late night
Meet date night
So
U-Hauls late night quite famously and quite successfully we're going to ask you three questions
About date nights
It's okay
Answer to 3 questions correctly and you win our prize one of our listeners Bill who is Seth Meyers playing
Rachel Berry show
New York New York all right
Dating has changed
Significantly over the centuries if
You were for example
A Welshman looking for a date in the 17th century
What could you do to ensure you might catch her eye
Hey walk loudly pastor
As passion was considered to be proportional to the volume of footsteps
B give your crush a homemade spoon
Carpet with specific symbols indicating the nature of your love
Orsi traveled as far away as you can and send a letter as level As proved by the distance that had
New travel
Fall really
Good feasible.
Options yeah
The one of these was the
17th century Welsh equivalent of swiping right
Loudly walking path
I'm going with that I must stop
Couple of Welsh people and I've always heard him coming
No I'm sorry it was the spoon
Will Harris
Spoon presumably this means I want to spoon with you
All right you still have two more chances your next question
Scientists are nerds
But they look for love to as in which of these real life cases which which of these really have
Hey
A researcher in Antarctica
Turned on Tinder
End matched
With someone in Antarctica a few miles away
Be a clinical technician
Was really impressed with the quality of a particular blood sample and looked up the patient to ask
Ask her out
Or see a medical researcher who managed to impress his crush with
Comic dioramas
Made with euthanized lab mice
I'm going to go I'm going to say
Tinder in Ann Arbor
You're right it works
Turn on Tinder
I guess the nights get long and he actually found somebody who is camping just a short while the way
They didn't meet but nothing happened this scientist said the first Antarctic Tinder hook-up
Has yet to happen
So I question if you get this one right
Celebrities have their own dating troubles I'm sure you know that
Actress Zoe Kravitz once went on a date
Which she says went pretty well he was nice they got along
But then what have
Happened was it a at the end of the day he said that was fun
But I got to confess it only came because I thought I had a date with Lenny Kravitz
Be she pulled out her phone when she got home and saw that he had life
Tweeted the whole thing
Or see the next
Day the guy called her and asked
Ask her if she wouldn't mind looking after his quote pet turtle
I'm quoting she said yes because he was a nice guy and who doesn't like turtles and it turned out to be
A 30-pound African
Tortoise names
Gary
Who stayed with her a month while this guy totally disappeared
Italy came back and said hey want to catch a movie and they went to the movie and he never mentioned
The turtle which she ended up giving
To Eternal rest
Wow
Taiwan
I wanted not to be
Only because it's such a wonderful piece of writing
I want that to be fiction and then I tip my cap to whoever came up with it
Because of that desire
I meant to say was be
But it was live
Stream
No that's not what it was but
I'm going to say that was a hint and not a
And I'll give you another chance
It would see it what
Grade 2
Seth Meyers the host of late
Night with Seth Meyers if like me you can't stay up that late it's often on the internet the next morning
Seth Meyers thank you so much for joining us on wait wait don't tell me
That's all for a Fourth of July special
WBEZ Chicago
Tyler Green Assisted by Simon Tran intern
Carlotta Francis Symphony 2bdr webcam
BJ leiderman composer I see my program is produced by Jennifer Mills miles dornbos and million cannagar motivational speaker
Is Peter Quinn reminds us
Winning
Everything
Technical directions to Laurita Winery business managers Colin Miller a production coordinator is Robert Newhouse
Heart Senior producer and executive producer waitwaitdonttellme is Michael Dead for
Text to Bill Kurtis thanks to all of our panels that you might have heard
And we will see you next week
Is NPR