Support for this podcast
In the following message
Come from Duckhorn
Napa California
Duckhorn Vineyards
Crafting classic Napa Valley Wine
Ants with a sense of place
For more than 40 years
Learn more
Or at Duckhorn. Com
NPR
NPR WBEZ Chicago
No this is
Wait wait don't tell me
NPR news quiz
Complete
Centos
Mueller reports
I'm Bill Kurtis
Chase Bank
Raiders schedule
Later on I'm going to be talking to Andrew Reynolds
All the star of girls and they
HBO in Black Monday
And of course
The original
All Star of the
The Book of Mormon on Broadway
Now if you don't know that show
It's the one so incredibly and hilariously abs
Scene
That the only part of the score we can play for you
Is this
Hello
That's it
That's all you got
If you want to hear more
Send your children out of the room and turn it on
We'll try to keep our conversation with him pg-rated also with you give us a call the number is 18881
Wait that's one 888-924-8924
My first listener contested High you are on wait wait don't tell me
Hi I'm Tony and I'm from Jacksonville Beach
Beach Florida
Florida
That's where things get
Crazy right in spring break right
Yeah I'm actually friends with a Florida man the red headed guy that
Hurricane video
Florida men
Do you like compete to try to be the like
The top the last
Florida man is that like a
Point of Pride for you all now
It's really more like
Down the street is going to bring an alligator
Well welcome to the show Tony let me introduce you to our panel this week
Prince at the comedian who be headlining at Theater 99
In Charleston South Carolina on Wednesday April 3rd is Hari kondabolu
Map to the comedian whose debut
New comedy album Babylon Ball Z is available at all streaming platforms
I'm finally a comedian performing May 3rd in Denver at the parent
Theater in Maine
Tencent
Seattle
At the Moore Theater at the co-host of nobody listens to Paula Poundstone
Paula Poundstone
Welcome to the show you're going to play who is Bill this time Bill Kurtis
This is going to read for you three quotations in the weeks is your job of course
Explain or identify just two of them
Do that
Dillwyn
Our prize The Voice
Of your choice on your voicemail are you ready to go
Here is your first
Quote
No obstruction
Exoneration
That was the president celebrating something that literally said
Quote it does not exonerate the president
What was it
Rimowa report or the bar summary their eyes
Mueller report the Mueller report was submitted to the attorney general last weekend and according to his
Is brief summary
It says the president did not do the thing he totally did
Republicans Or democrats
Devastated
But if you want to feel sorry for somebody how about Mike
Penske found out
Last weekend
He's not going to be president after all
But the people who are really
Are the hard
Court Mueller fan
And the ones who bought the Mueller time T-shirt
And the mugs in the candles
And then one sad but true case
The guy who got Robert Mueller's face
Tattooed on his arm
Is his now telling everybody is actually a Japanese symbol that means
Serenity
You don't drive me crazy
What koala
This question
It's not the motor report
Football report
It just said something I just read
The bar summary
Of A Tale of Two Cities
Hits one line
He says
Is dickon says
It was the best of times
Owenton KY
Conclusion
Is it obstruction of justice or not
He's like such a
Talking to
Crappy therapist
Obstruction of justice
You think it's a
How do you feel about
Videos
Also write the end of The Sopranos
What happened what happened
Alright Tony your next quote is from none other
Then Oprah
They're at a billion Oprah was talking about the
Advantages of working with a ubiquitous big tech companies to join Force
What is within this week
Take for a big amount
Smith what is that company
Oh God I actually have no idea
Well it happened at their big event and Cooper
Cupertino at their headquarters
The fact that their products are in a billion pockets it's kind of a
Call Bro
Alright friend of
Viewers and secondly it's not right but I just
Would love to live in a world in which Oprah came out
Unannounced her alliance with hot pocket
You gave me
The clue that it's in
You know aliens are pockets
You put hot
That's weather
No it's not Hot Pockets like I said it was a tech
Company
Is an apple a man
Big Apple event
They didn't introduce any new Apple devices kasiri
At this point what's left
The Apple IUD
No instead they said they were getting
The two new kinds of businesses first
Apple TV
They brought out a bunch of big stars like Oprah Winfrey
You tell us they would be putting out
New original program
Everybody was so excited because I thought Opera was
The new
Apple
Product
SiriusXM
If she tells you what to do Oprah what's the weather like
If you believe in yourself the Sun never stops shining on you I'm wondering if
Now that apple is hurt
Did you mention the IUD
Hahaha
If they want now I'm not I am not a biology expert
Nora sex master
Would it be accurate
To say that it was a camera on the IUD
It would see the
Sperm going
It would have to have to be like a special
Slow motion camera
Technically
We can work that in there
Yeah we want the government having that
They already do
The amounts to that it was like
Apple credit
Red card
And then Apple are
Arcades
I don't know how Apple
Go to the bank biz
The first credit card ever to have real
Really crappy battery
Did you know
Knowing Apple you're going to have to probably buy it
Special reader and then a special adapter
All right
Here is your last
Quote
Human Barbie got together
Eminem Christine's Wicked on Twitter reacting to the news that NASA had canceled
What historic first they had schedule for this week
It was supposed to be the first all-female face wash
You want to go on this show we celebrated this planned landmark
Can space exploration the first all-women spacewalk but it was
Is canceled and why
Because they didn't have enough space suits in women's size
It is true that always thinks when you find the perfect
Outfit
Keep your blood from boiling out in the vacuum of space and they don't have it in your side
The question is right that it turns out like literally they have like
Only one
Space suit
That fits
A woman so the
Second woman
Didn't go
And the question is why
Couldn't NASA
Make another one
It's a cliche to say you know they put a man on the moon if they can't do this
These are literally the people who put a man on the moon
Hanging around
Throw their stuff down when they're done from
The trip
Put the clothes away neatly and then they don't have them
Summary Marie kondo
Congratulations Auntie
Rhino panel it is time for you to answer
Some questions about this
Knicks news
Hurry the pope as we know has some unusual opinion
Pope
Well this week
We found out he really doesn't like it
When you try to kiss his what
All right I got to be careful
Would it would
Israel
Hours to kiss
The Pope's ring but this week this
Video of Pope
Francis went viral where he
Repeatedly yanked his hand away from people trying to
Kiss it was very strange there were even trying to use their tongue
The video
It's great the Polaris heinle shaking hands with
Baseline pilgrims waiting
But when they go to kisses ringing like vinyl
Takes his hand away
And it's not
Some of it all and you can see his lips moving
As he says download too slow
The funniest thing about that video
What was it was like
Amazon
People in a row
The person behind in
We saw that
Like this
Juke music
What is done instead of taking social cues from the situation
There was strategizing
Yeah you know that
Interesting
Reading about this incident
When a pope dies
Weather Leeds office
They destroy the Pope's ring
His people
Well it's be no because
Coming up it's a very frugal Bluff The Listener game call 1aaa wait wait to play will be back in a minute with more weight
Wait don't tell me
From NPR
Support for this podcast
In the following method
Message come from Stanford Children's
What are the scariest things
American Hero
Mom look
Because the next words are usual
Billy can fly
Or Joey riding the dog
Or a crayon stuck in Valerie's nose
Hear something
You might want
With over 20
Pediatric offices
Stanford pediatric
Christians are all over the
The Bay Area
Not just in Palos
Find a Stanford PDF
At Stanford children
What does what you eat
Donkey
Say about who you are
Is the memories
And the feelings of
Nostalgia
Is what connects
It's not
Chicken or beef or pork
This is gene wfm
NPR code switch
This week on the menu
Food
And family
WBEZ Chicago
Wait wait don't tell me the NPR news
Squids
I'm Bill Kurtis
We're playing this week with Brian Babylon
Hari kondabolu
And Paula Poundstone at the Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown Chicago PD
Thank you girl right now it's gone
Wait wait two-player game on the air
Hi you are on wait wait don't tell me
Hi my name
Hey baby where you calling from
I'm across the lake
Traverse City
Trevor story
Clear Louis house
Controversy ends here
Universal
It's remarkably beautiful
Do you like cherries
Well welcome
To our show Phoebe
You to play the game but you must try to tell truth from fix
Bill what is Phoebe's topic
You know what
Not cool
$5,000
There's not a lot you can do it for
Where does $5,000 buy at
Used car 1000 Footlong sandwiches from Subway or one bag of groceries from Whole Foods
But this week I read about someone doing something
Extraordinary for just
5 grand
Their panel is going to tell you about it
Pick the one is telling the truth until when are prize awake later of your choice on
Send your voicemail you ready to play
Yes I'm alright first let's hear from
Paula
Poundstone
Good knock against Tesla
Is that the only make cars for the uber-rich
Not the Uber driver
That's been absolutely true until now
Elon Musk
Has created a car that will retail brand new for $5,000
The body of the car is made of pound
Did soda cans
It is remarkably light in the advertising potential for the beverage companies may even further lower the overall cost
Of these
Vehicles
The cars have no temperature controls the seats
Do not move there are no
Computer components
There is no phone charger there is no radio or sound
Laughingly suggest
Set this Tesla should be the real Hummer
Because if the driver wants music no have to hum
He said the baby these drivers will return to the practice of
Well they drive or even the practice of thinking about driving
The car seats only one
So although it is not a family car it is a car for someone who has spent a lot of time with their family
The majority of the interior of the
The car is storage
For the large containers of
Vinegar and baking soda that power at
The company says they don't expect to sell a lot of the $5,000 cars but that's not the point the point
To shut up all the people
Complaining about how much their other cars cost
Tesla comes out with the $5,000 model powered by
Vinegar and bake
Baking soda
Your next story of a miracle being done with
Just $5,000
Comes
From Brian Babylon
Gentrification
Toucan mean Improvement to the neighborhood
Bringing money and services
Although it often forces out longtime residents
Replaces them with Public Radio Live
Epic Johnson saw it happening in his neighborhood
Bronzeville Chicago
He own his building
But had to find a way to make a living off his do Neighbors
With very little money to do
On the day after Christmas last
Jonathan
By chance please
Scratch-off Lotto
Actually won $5,000
And later that night
His son came over with
What is white girlfriend
He asked what are you and your friends like
The answer
Goat yoga
And late-night Ramen rest
He didn't know where to get a goat
Order do yoga but he knew where to find some Ramen
A quick trip to Costco
For three crates of the stuff at 6 into Union
Plus two big Soup pot
And welcome to the hottest Ramen spot
On Martin Luther King Drive
Community coin Ramen
It's been recommended by Oprah
And that brought in new part owner
Comedian and actor Hannibal Buress
And his signature cheddar fire Ramen
The $0.25 bag of Flamin Hot Cheetos crushed on a
$0.06 Ramen
And that is sold for $11 a bowl
With a BYOB policy
Dragon closing time
It's not one of Bronzeville hottest spot
The trick Johnson
Princess
It's a be patient
Eventually
They'll get drunk enough
Just show up here
$5,000 and a lot of $0.06 ramen leads to a successful
Restaurant in Chicago your last day of someone coming in under budget
It comes from Hari kondabolu
Most people go to high school
Who plays bracing themselves
See yet another product
Action of Death of a Salesman
With a pimply Willy Loman
Or a fully clothed
Diversion of hair
Or God forbid in all white raisins
In the Sun
But audience members at North Bergen High School
Surprised to see a stage version
Teen 79
And science fiction horror movie Alien
With spaceships
Space suit
1 Facehugger and a very scary full-grown Xenomorph
All done
For judge
$5,000
Or the cost
Cost of 10 laptops for pores
Originally the school had planned to do Romeo and Juliet butts
Students felt the play about
Teenagers being overly emotional and overreact
Nothing to being told no
Just didn't seem realistic
So they went with alien
The film about the
Space crew that is forced to fight
A terrifying
Sharptooth
Extraterrestrial
Was adapted for the stage and directed by English
Teacher perfecto quavo
And was designed by fellow teacher Steven defendini
Their names clearly indicate that they are both
In the witness protection program
The fact that reproduction could cost only
$5,000 is a testament to some
Ingenuity
And hard work
Especially
Given that everything was made
Recycled material
The play went viral and the response has been in
Incredible
Patton Oswalt to saw a clip
The play tweeted
This blows my high school's adaptation of pink
Flamingos out-of-the-way
The students are asked
Anxiously awaiting the review in there
School paper
Which will almost certainly say
Quote
The play was
Lip or whatever
But don't forget
They're all still no
One of these things only $5,000 was it from polyps
Brownstone a low and model of a Tesla that runs not on battery power button
Baking soda and
Vinegar
Brian Babylon I ramen restaurant open for only $5,000 because really
That's what Ramen cost
Or
From Hari kondabolu $5,000 pays for a heist
School production of a dramatic adaptation
Of the movie Alien which of these is a real story of frugality in the news
This week
Oh man I'm going to go with
Number three alien
Right during the Truth alien
Yeah apparently everybody if you can do that as well
What we spoke to somebody who is deeply involved in this remarkable
Project
Arctic Invasion alien popped out of
Small budget
That was Brian Bonacci he's the technical and lighting director for the North Bergen High School production of
Alien I've never
Been prouder
The country New Jersey then this very moment and if you haven't seen it I highly recommend finding online
Find the videos taken of this production
It's arguably better than the movie
Meanwhile
Congratulations baby you got it right
You earned a point for hiring you want to cry the voice of your choice of your voicemail very good thank you so much
All right bye-bye in centuries
And now the game where you get rewarded for doing things that one you actual rewards instead of this
Andrew Reynolds is a Broadway star most famous for creating the lead role in Book of Mormon and he's gone on to
To start in girls and
Black Monday on Showtime
It's a good thing you did because like a lot of struggling actor is he in a lot of De jobs and apparently he was
Terrible at all of them
Andrew rannells welcome to wait wait don't tell me
Thank you so much for him
Anime did you talk to old
Managers of mine did you talk to the manager at Nacho Mama's we had heard that this was in fact a Hallmark
Cover your pre-fame days
Kept like losing jobs
Is that right
Okay well it was by my choice just to be clear all right
I was very good at an interview
A very solid job interview and then I would get the job show up
Work for one day
Decide I hated it and then leave
Braylon
So can you get me an example of the kind of job you
If you did for the day then left
Well I did work at
Restaurant near Columbia University Health Nacho Mama's
And I worked there as a host for one day and then I do
Never return
This is Paula Poundstone can I ask you a question
When you applied for work at Nacho Mama's had you been there before I do
You seen it did you know what you were
In4s Paula I am sad to say I knew exactly what I was getting
I had only been
Drunk at that bar I had never thought about what it would actually be like to work for drunk
People at the bar
Did you ask any questions during your interview did you ever say like so what will I do
I
I was a temp at Ernst & Young
And they asked me all these questions about like it
Do you know how to answer phone. Like sure
And then when you're not know how to answer phones well
I think like I think they were multiple line
Call my own experience that was watching Lily Tomlin in 92508
Now you grew up
In a Omaha we were just talking about theater kids in high school so I assumed you were one
Well I yes but I went to an all-boys Catholic
School that did not have a drama program so I did
But Community Theater shows
Which means I would often be like I remember when I was like I don't know Seventeen and I did a production of a Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum
The woman I was playing opposite was like 45
I did a lot of shows like that
6 cool things work out for you
So great
Were there things that you learned
You think perhaps were specific to Catholic School
Call I would say shame and guilt
Yes
Yeah and then also like the fast
Fastest way to make your mother feel bad
When you move off to New York
To be a performer and how quickly did it take you to get actually performing
Summer Stock jobs like right after like while I was still in college and then I did some
Dinner theater in Westchester and then I did a really unfortunate Toribash okay
Call Pokemon live
Wait till you were in a life Pokemon
Otis
How dare you
I'm a trained actor can you give us a sample I've no idea what this
Can you give us like a sample of what your lines were from Pokemon the
The stage
Spectacular
No I will not
We read that you used to audition
All the time with just one song
That's correct
Decided for myself that I sounded very good singing Born to Run
Brian wow
By Bruce Springsteen so I would just
Sing that for every audition whether it was
Correct or not
Like I sang it for my audition for the Lincoln Center Revival of stop
And sing it for the Revival of Fiddler on the Roof
Do you Channel like that
Like white men
Emotional
Next song
Perform
Well lucky for me I'm an emotional white man
Yes I was lucky enough to
See you in the Book of Mormon
Fantastical
But it's very hard for me to imagine you
Singing Born to Run
Coastal can you show us
Can you sing a little Born to Run
No
Well Andrew Riddle That is an absolute pleasure to talk to you but now it is time
Play a game with you when we are calling it
The book of
Merman
Who started the Book of Mormon
But what do you know about the book of merman
Mainly
Ethel Merman
Wait a second because I'm gay
We're going to ask you three questions about Ethel Merman to get to write I thought you need to do when our prize for one of our listeners Bill who is a
Andrew rannells playing
Andrew Johnston of New York New York
All right
All right here we go
First question there a lot of stories of Ethel Merman quote
Colorful language
Once she was backstage at Gypsy of course your big signature roll
An overheard of the stage manager swearing in front of the children in the
The cast
What did she say
Was it a
Nobody corrupts those little angels but me so blue
Be nothing she just sang a Hi-C until everybody's
LED
Or see quote she said don't say in front of the kids
I'm going with c
Your
Colorful language there's a story that when a religious Hollywood actress asks you to put a dollar in a
Swear jar for saying Hell she
She said well how much do I have
To put in to make you
Alright next question Ethel Merman fourth and final marriage was the actor Ernest Borgnine
Yeah it lasted only 32 days
Wow what did she say about the marriage in her autobiography
He was at a my marriage to Borgnine was the only thing shorter than he was
Be at work he did McHale's Navy at home he was McHale's lazy
Or see nothing the chapter entitled my marriage
Ernest Borgnine
Assisted of a single
Blank page
No was not a
See it was only a blank
Page
All right yeah it was not good after that there a very stories about why their marriage broke up
One of them believe it or not is that Borgnine used to like to fart in bed and then pull up the covers giving her a so-called Dutch of
And I wish I was kidding
What was Yoda's last one right answer you win for your list
Men's merman continued performing almost up to her death in 1980
For which of these were
Was her last
Roll a
The voice of the shrieking Poltergeist and ET
Be playing a crazy person who
Who thinks he is Ethel Merman
Orsi
Grand Moff perfidia
In The Empire Strikes Back
B
You are
Right in the movie Airplane Robert Hays is coming
A war story about the old
Corporal whatever
Who went crazy and thought he was Ethel Merman and they cut to it
And it's a full moon
That was her last
Casserole
I know Bill how did Andrew rannells doing R23 that's a big win for us Andrew
Congratulations that's awesome
I think it's awesome this will be part of your volume to I hope
I hope so too
Andrew rannells new Memoir too much is not enough is out now and
Talk to you
And thank you so much for joining us
We're shrooming on Mars in our listener Limerick challenge
From NPR
Support for this podcast
Send the following message come from Stanford children
What are the scariest things a parent
Mom look
Because the next
Passwords are usually
Billy can fly
Or Joey riding the dog
Or a crayon stuck in Valerie's nose
Here's something you might want to
With over 20
Pediatric office
Stanford pediatrician
Shins are all over the Bay Area
Not Justin
In Palo Alto
Find a Stamford PD
At stanfordchildrens.org
Planet Money tip number 7
A great analogy doesn't have
Busier than a one-legged bobcat
Junkrat
Pond
Planet Money
A poetic Park
About the account
Wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
I'm Bill Kurtis this week
Playing with Paula Poundstone the Hari kondabolu
Brian Babylon
And here again is your host
The Chase Bank Auditorium in downtown
Chicago
Thank you so much. Thank you so much in just a minute
Rime is over Bill begin fasting for Ramadan in our listener Limerick challenge
If you like to play give us a call at 1 AAA wait wait that's one 888-924-8924 right now panel
Summer Quest
For you from the week's news
Hurry it is
Is true that Americans are at each other's
Throat cut this week
Came together as one
To condemn a guy
For doing what
Wrong
Oh
Is tying their shoelaces
No
Yeah
Yeah it's like this is ridiculous where do you put the Shamir
Oh you know now you remember
Cutting
Bagels weird exactly
It was on holy Dino I thought criminal named Alex
Men posted a picture of what he said
Was St Louis
Secret namely
Laying a bagel down on the table and cutting it into little slices like a loaf
I'm sorry are there people who do that here
Shut up
What a cantaloupe
Like a cantaloupe
That's what I need to do a bagel you don't do that to a bagel
Finger food yeah you slice of bagels sideways through the middle so you
About 1/2 in your ring finger
I'm engaged and it's going to be a Jewish
So the internet responded to this with its normal restraint
And by the time
It was over Bob Mueller had his neck
Crime to investigate
People from St Louis God bless them tried to defend this track
Convenient little slices to use
Dipping in the traditional Bagel topping in St Louis
Creamed ham
I think that it's okay however anybody want
To cut their bagel
It's okay now Paula I know why you say that
And I think it speaks well of you that
You feel that way
However
You're wrong
Paula most New Yorkers have had experience
Places with rats or roaches
Are pigeons before the last two weeks
New York City has been dealing with a
Bizarre infestation of wasps
Squirrels
No they've got that
Unusual
Sorry I'm fat
Station
Give me a give me a McDonald's
Been called into hell
Actually pictures of the only kind that I haven't seen yet
There's been a
Work work here in a quack quack now I'll give it to you though it's basically
Farm animal
Farm animals in New York City
Oh that's what happened
Alright a couple of weeks ago Alam was spotted in Brooklyn on the Gowanus
Expressway
A few days ago of a cow is found in the major Deegan Expressway
If you're wondering why this is happening these animals have places
Has to go in the subway is totally unreliable
You know I would not come out what was the first one was it
Lamb there was a
Goat in the Bronx
An infestation
What was the lamb a cow a goat and another
How's that
I think what's happening
People have any
Farm Fresh
Animals like Elvis
Is this milk
It's right outside
And then you got sloppy
Skate
What happens
When you have
Yes
Instead of Farm to Plate it's backyard to play
Yeah maybe it was because all these annoying Brooklyn hipsters are moving to Farms Upstate and the farm animals
We gotta get out of here
Bone museum of Queensland Australia is having a great year in terms of Atlanta
Trippy they receive for major donation
10 from one family
The Robinson family has given them
What
The pinky ring
No
I'm going to need a
The unlike Taxidermy they can write about their taxes
Does have that
The fat dog
Yes dear
They donated all of their pets
What happened first the Robinsons 9 year old guinea pig died
The family thought it would come for the boy to nowicki
Is it caramel again
At the Museum
Flesh-eating beetles
Overdone chewing off its
Skin
In a development we're deliberately choosing not to investigate further the Robinsons
Cow dog another dog
Died in quick succession
How much donated
Into the museum
Who said it was happy to be able to help the family in their difficult time
The funny way to comfort someone I'm so sorry about your grandma can I have her bones
What is this music
Damn is it
Jeff bones bone museum
I need you
We got this different bones
Stop
Okay
Yeah
Blank refers it's a game where you have to listen for the rhyme if you'd like to play on air call and leave a message
1 Triple 8 wait wait
It's 188-892-4890
Forklift
Contact us link on our website wait wait NPR. Org
There you can find out about attending our weekly live shows here at the Chase Bank Auditorium in
Chicago
Upcoming show in St Louis Missouri
Oh really you're going there
39th and don't bring me none of yours
Silly Bagels
Speaker quiz just ask your smart speaker to play the wait wait quiz and you
You can win one of our voices on your voicemail
Hot you're on wait wait don't tell me
Hi everybody this
This is Jenna from Waltham
How are you
I just broke my leg and had surgery so on the table
I have the audacity to go walking
Oh no
That's why you should never do that
He was walking along and I just went
Yeah little bit of snow
Cuz that's the problem
They're from Australia they don't have
I'm I hope you're feeling up and welcome to the show Jenna
Bill Kurtis is going to redo 3 News related limericks
To the last word or phrase missing for
Can fill in that last word or phrase correctly
EBay big boy
When are you ready to play
Here is your first
I will bring a new life
To this earth
Toy look like the millions I'm worth
I'm like
Meghan Markle
With lip gloss Ed
Sparkle
I look really glam
Giving
Yes
Childbirth
Isn't just beautiful it's now fabulous more and more women are getting
Stylist to come in and get them gussied up for post
Parham Glamour Shots
1 New York
Spa Wilson
The Stylist to do your makeup
In your hair in the delivery room
It's part of the part of a special Beauty package called
Did you get in here
Now this.
Does ObamaCare cover
Here's your neck slimmer
On Mars
There's no plans
For the brush
But no life
Hear a big fingered hush Loom
The roofer has found roundish
Bumps on the ground
And some say
Those are picture
Pictures of
Mushroom
Prism Martian risotto as mushrooms might be growing on Mars
A recent study Envy
Journal of astrobiology and space science
Church photos that they say could be mushrooms growing on Mars
Although
Many skeptical internet commenters said quote the journal and article are both
Garbage
Unquote
Or so says what is I'm sure a real scientist
Just called himself
Ziba LaCroix
The photos show several clusters of the funky taken shortly after
The Curiosity left the Utopia Basin and moved into what NASA is calling the Trader Joe's Flats
Mushrooms
Alleged mushrooms were located next to an outcrop
Fingerling potatoes in a free sample of lemonade
The rubber couldn't stay in Trader Joe's flat so because there was no place
Park
Alright here's your last limerick
With robots
These guys
What they wish
Buzz buzz sting
Now becomes
Glug glug
It's just
The beginning
Perhaps they'll learn
Swimming
Four B's
Shut down speaker
With something
No
Yes yes
Science
Bees are not talking to fish
Scientists have devised the way
I'm not getting
To use robots
To translate baby language to fish
Advice
Mercer
Southern in the experiment the bees and the
The fish start behaving the same way
The result is Twitter's worth
Unlikely animal friendships video
Bees and fish have a lot in common
Hey you guys like moving in a group
Then suddenly changing direction
How do you
Can birds feel
About this
The birds and the bees conversation
Tell how did Jenna Dewan AR quiz
She got them all right she's a winner and quit congratulations
Bye-bye
Support for this podcast and
The following message
It's come from Stanford Children's
What are the scariest things
Mom look
Because the next words are usual
Billy can fly
Or Joey riding the dog
Or a crayon stuck in Valerie's nose
Here's something you might
Want to hear
With over 20 pediatric offices
Stanford pediatric
Russians are all over the
The Bay Area
Not just
Westin Palo Alto
Find a Stanford PDF
Stanford children
Yes. Org
Now onto my final game lightning fill in the blank each of our players will have 60 seconds in which the answer is many fill in the blank question
You can
Hitchcock dancer net worth
Spell can you give us
Scores
Paula and Brian
Each have two alright we flip the coin and Paul has elected to go seconds or Brian you're at first
The clock will start when I begin
Question fill in the blank
On Wednesday a federal judge blocked
Work requirement
People en Blanc
Kentucky anarchist
Medicaid yeah
On Tuesday the White House's ban on blanks
We're semi-automatic weapons went into effect
Bump stock has baseball season open this week the Texas Rangers Elvis Andrus used his new walk up music Black
Macarena
Baby shark
On Sunday Patriots tight end
Blanket
He was retiring
From the NFL
Gronk
Yes Rob Gronkowski after he was pulled over on
Suspicion of drunk driving
I made it South Carolina tried to hide the smell of alcohol by blanking
Drinking gas
By spraying axe
Somebody sprayed directly into his mouth
Police pulled a man over on Interstate 85 in before the office
How's your made it to his window the man quickly switched
Some Axe body
Spray to cover up the smell of alcohol
Ended up feeling a road sobriety test which in this case was just the officer asked
Did you just read
What's the max body spray in your mouth
Bill has Brian doing a quiz rewrite
6 more points for a total of 8
And that puts him in the lead
Alright congratulations flyer
Blank after the house failed to override his veto President Trump
Blank was upheld on
Emergency
Blanks
Control of the golang
Heights
Syria know I guess I'll give it to you this week
A border official said the influx of blanks at the US Mexico
Border
Had reached a Breaking Point
This week Greg nidal became the first person in March Madness history
Kappa perfect
Bracket going into this
60 and when asked about it he said blank
I have no idea
It said you're right that's what he said
Irma reach the 270 million dollar settlement
For his part in the blank
Crisis
In a fill-in the blank with the worst possible answer I company in China
Cow prod
Snow
That would be good in this case the answer is toilet seat
Finally a toilet
That puts the dye in diarrhea
These expensive toilet seat feature water sprayers hot air drying a built-in warmers but they don't
Is a grounding wire to prevent Electra
Shock
40% of the seats are faulty but don't worry they've already been pulled from the market and repackaged
A cheap at home electric shock
Therapy for your butt
Wow
No bill how did Paula doing our quiz but she did good
Total of 12
Takes over the legal right how many you need to win
52 right here we go on Tuesday
The Senate voted against advancing the Democrat so-called
Blank
Bill
New green deal
Green New Deal
This week President Trump calls for Russia to withdraw its military
Support for president
Maduro in blank
Venezuela on Tuesday officials in Rockland County New York
Ban unvaccinated children from public space
To contain a blank out
Measles right after colonist Denise McAllister tweeted that The View
Was it Roundtable of delusional mental midgets ricocheting ignorance with the picture
Your host Meghan McCain
McCain responded by tweeting
What is the middle
No she tweeted you were at my wedding
Following two crashes blankenfeld a software fix
737 Max
On Tuesday prosecutors in Illinois dropped all charges
Guest actor blank
Jussie Smollett
Thousands of passengers
Connecting flights were left stranded during their layovers this week
When are Airline blank
Wow Airlines
Went bankrupt and cancel
Yes they went completely out of business operations instantly
My flight was cancelled is so 2018
Savvy Travelers today call and say sorry honey my Airline
Was canceled
Wow Airlines a budget carrier flying between Europe and North America apparently
Shut down on Thursday
Straining some passengers were waiting to board their next flight
The airline has
Sims partner with other carriers to arrange rescue flights and those he booked on United
Come back safely
Well those who were rebooked on Spirit Airlines decide to just walk back
New York haha
Building how are you well enough to win
How does it feel
There is
Wait wait don't tell me
NPR WBEZ Chicago
Assisted by Simon Tran in Murrieta or interns or Alex
And Rachel Clapper rweb the room is Beth Novey
BJ leiderman composer Theodore Perkins produced by Jennifer Mills
Are imagineers
Gwen technical directions and Lorna White
Special things this week
Our business and office manager is calling Miller a production coordinator is Robert Newhouse our senior producer
Sherlock in the executive producer
Is Michael Danforth
Why will NASA
Cancel the space walking next time because the space shuttle was designed by Boeing
Brian Babylon Pokemon
Infestation
Are Paula Poundstone
Weather
Hahaha
Will ask you about it on wait wait don't tell me
SpongeBob
This