[Music]
stealth technology the internet GPS in
the palm of your hand autonomous
operation technology is a driver of our
times since its founding in 1958 in the
midst of the Cold War DARPA the Defense
Advanced Research Projects Agency has
been a driver of technology
welcome to voices from DARPA a window
onto DARPA score of program managers
their job to redefine what is possible
my name is Ivan Amato and I'm your DARPA
host and today I'm pleased to have with
me in the studio US Army Colonel Matt
Hepburn an active duty Army physician
and since 2013 a program manager in
DARPA biological technologies office
Colonel Hepburn holds a Bachelor of Science degree in biomedical engineering
and a Doctor of Medicine degree both
from Duke University following all of
that education he completed an internal
medicine residency and an infectious
disease fellowship at Brooke Army Medical Center at Fort Sam Houston in Texas
prior to joining DARPA Matt served as
the director of medical preparedness on
the White House national security staff
an additional previous assignments
included the chief medical officer at a
level 2 medical facility in Iraq a
clinical research director at the US
Army Medical Research Institute for
infectious diseases and an exchange
officer to the United Kingdom among
other positions matt is one of DARPA
program managers who comes to work in
his military attire in his case either
his army fatigues or a dress uniform
either way he always wears the smile of
someone who finds himself in a place
where he just might be able to realize a
dream and he has said publicly that he
wants to stop all infectious diseases
from killing people may it be so
Colonel Matt Hepburn though I will call you Matt from now on it is my pleasure
to have you in the studio today it's
fantastic to be here and and thank you
Ivan for inviting me to be on the
podcast and to tell my story and tell
you what I care so deeply about yes so
I've been greatly looking forward to
discussion so why don't we get right
into it and so you're a medical
professional who embraces clinical and
field practice as well as leading-edge
research what are the origins of those
interests for you it started pretty
young I have this childhood memory of
being asked at my school a Catholic
school and that was meeting with one of
the priests and they said well what do
you really want to do and I said I
wanted to be a pediatrician(小儿科医师) and they
said why and and and I said well because
I just want to take care of people and I
want to take care of children and I do
think it stems from my mom was a nurse
and so I think less so from the
influence of being around someone in the
medical profession but more so just
being around someone that cares very
deeply about other people
again very early on and it but it's been
it's been sort of a consistent part of
my life yeah this was in fourth grade
this whole like you know I wanted to be
a pediatrician(小儿科医师) and so as I was on this
trajectory and I didn't know of course
what I was talking about you know I mean
even you make these decisions early in
your life but my parents and my family
always had this incredibly strong ethic
of service and very deeply and
fundamentally because I reflect on this
often actually it's like Who am I and
what am I supposed to be and I think
what I do is I serve others and that's
that's how I define myself maybe one of
the greatest gifts from my parents was
that my dad was active duty Navy officer
did ROTC and served as a nuclear
engineer on a Surface Warfare ship it
was active duty for five or six years
stayed in the Navy for another 20 plus
retired as a Navy captain in the
reserves you couple my mom's passion for
helping other people in the medical
field with my dad's passion of serving
our country this was almost like all I
knew and so that trajectory has sort of
guided me through all of my decisions in
my okay well let's actually talk a
little bit about that before you came to
DARPA you spent almost 15 years in a
variety of segments that took you to for
example for - deitrick the military's
premiere facility for infectious disease
research it took you to Korea to UK the
Republic of Georgia Azerbaijan Iraq
Thailand other places I'm sure what did
you learn from all of that global experience
I would start by saying what a privilege
what a privilege to have those types of
life experiences all in the context of
again feeling that I'm serving my
country and making a difference some of
the work that I'm most proud of frankly
is work I did in the caucuses with
Georgia and Azerbaijan and the program
was under the auspices(赞助) was called the
Cooperative Threat Reduction program but
really my role there was to engage their
public health communities and their
medical research communities to
establish that capability of finding
infectious diseases diagnosing them and
ultimately treating them and it was a
capability that was those public health
systems were all part of the Soviet
Union but when the Soviet Union fell
these countries were kind of left to
their own to recreate a public health
infrastructure and so the privilege was
to work with those experts in the host
country to say how do we build that back
up again so that you can tell us that
there's an outbreak going on and then we
can collectively work together to
respond to that outbreak right so did
you bring in models like the the Centers
of Disease Control here we did yes we
did we work closely with the embassies
we work closely with the State
Department we work closely with the CDC
at the end of the day it was myself and
some of my DoD colleagues on the ground
you know rolling our sleeves up helping
these countries develop those systems
developing laboratory capabilities
developing the ability to do clinical
research to ethical standards that would
be accepted all over the world and to
figure out how to do this you know again
I look back what a privilege to be on
the ground and at this point fairly
junior in my career and to help an
entire nation improve their public
health sound like a great privilege what
is the sequence of events Matt that
resulted in your current position here
at DARPA as a program manager throughout
my medical career I had heard about
DARPA and I had seen amazing technology
that had come from DARPA that were aimed
at addressing infectious diseases
threats so I had always admired from afar
before I joined DARPA I was over
at the White House National Security
Council staff and in that role my job
was to identify what capabilities we do
have to respond to pandemics and then
how we can organize ourselves as a
government not just DoD but as an entire
government towards addressing those gaps
so we're ready for the next one and
while I was there I got tapped on the
shoulder and the concise phrase was
you're doing all of this policy what we
should do as a government how would you
then like to implement and actually make
investments that are going to address
those gaps so method where you literally
tapped on the shoulder and so who was it
that proposed this to you
it was dr. Jeff Ling who was the deputy
director of DSO at the time and he we
met him for coffee one morning and he
didn't literally actually put his hand
on my shoulder but figuratively imagine
a hand on my shoulder saying Matt how
would you like to try at DARPA to
actually invest to make a difference for
all those things that you've been
talking about in terms of big policy
words for the last few years
well and of course he provided a model of audacity
because he really took on from madison
prosthetics(修复学) and other other programs to
really help the warfighter why don't we
segue(继续) then into your life as a program
manager here in this tremendous
portfolio that you've developed which is
I think a portfolio that also reflects
some kind of audacious point of view as
is of course reflected by that statement
earlier that you want to take the lethal
power out of infectious disease so the
names are fantastic some of them like
Prometheus and Thor dialysis like
therapeutics in vivo nano platforms and
we'll probably talk more about one of
them in particular the pandemic
prevention platform what I'm hoping to
do now is is if you could briefly take
us for a tour of your programs we can't
go in-depth about any of them at this
point but take me a little bit of a tour
on what's what you're hoping to achieve
with some of these programs and then
we'll focus in a little bit more on the
pandemic prevention platform
yeah so the tour starts by saying what problems are
we trying to solve and again at the
White House National Security Council
staff I got a chance to say look for
these major outbreaks pandemics or near
pandemics how have we done as a
government think about the 2009 h1n1
pandemic think about the West Africa
Ebola crisis h1n1 that is h1n1 influenza
yeah
influenza think about the West Africa
Ebola crisis think about how we've
recently responded to Zika there are
common themes throughout and some of
those common themes are we need to be
much better at diagnosing if someone has
an infection and we need to go a step
beyond that and imagine a world that if
we could figure out if someone is going
to be sick or is going to be contagious
we can intervene and stop the outbreak
right in its tracks and that's
Prometheus and that's the Prometheus
program but we also need to make
vaccines and treatments much faster than
we currently can and that's one of the
examples as the pandemic prevention
platform we need to alternate ways of
how we treat infections and using
portable dialysis(透析) to filter the blood
and remove any type of pathogen(病原体) is a
good example but that's just in that
case is does that mean I might I might
have been exposed to some kind of
pathogenic(致病) agent(药剂) it's in my blood and
certain levels so with this kind of
technology remove that before it could
take hold and actually get me sick was
that is that the idea of that yes and
the idea would be again especially for
pathogens where we don't have a vaccine
where we don't have a treatment
especially think about now with what
we're seeing so much antimicrobial(抗菌剂) resistant bacteria
imagine if we're we
can't use antibiotics(抗生素) so if we can
filter your blood and remove that
pathogen what if it does is ultimately
gives a leg up for your own immune
response to ultimately make you well again
we like that technology especially or in
those first days when we need to buy
some time to develop a vaccine and we
need to develop new treatments and so my
point across the portfolio is that we
have lots of investments in medical
diagnostics we're investing in modeling
to forecast where infectious diseases
are going to go we have investments in
accelerating new treatments but they're
all connected together they are all
linked and let me give you an example
with our Prometheus program predicting
if someone is going to become contagious
well awesome right if we can do that but
once we predict and identify that person
we still have to treat them and so we're
going to need treatments as fast as
possible with our pandemic prevention
platform and the beauty is is that those
treatments are probably going to be most
effective when they're given as early as
possible so I think of our whole
portfolio as interconnected that we
develop a lot of different specific
projects to get capabilities but that
they're ultimately going to intertwine(纠缠在一起)
so that we stop the outbreak in its tracks
well when I think of programs
here at DARPA they all have a kind of
lifecycle to them right I mean they they
sort of start as a glimmer in the eye of
someone like you Matt a program manager
there's a period of vetting and working
with others here to really articulate
and formulate the program as best it can
be so that it can be most effective and
then kind of smoke signals go out to the
world and seeking people who maybe think
that they can pull off some of these
audacious tasks that we've put out of
course then the research is done and
hopefully in the end you succeed or if
not fully succeed you learn from all the
research that that's going on
so what is the status in that lifecycle
of the pandemic
prevention platform the payment Demick
prevention platform just launched and so
and by launch those who might not know
what that means in the DARPA context
said that that means that completing the
contracting process so that our
performers that were selected in a very
rigorous(严密的) process can now accomplish the
goals of the program so they're just
starting in there for six months as part
of the lifecycle these are early days
early days because the ultimate goal of
that program is so difficult we have a
lot you know in some ways I feel like
while we have we have a long way to go
one of the the key points though of the
pandemic prevention platform is that the
goal is incredibly ambitious but there
is foundational scientific evidence that
this can be done and that foundational
scientific evidence is derived from a
previous DARPA program and that previous
Starkel in other words prove the
concepts ADEPT that's the ADEPT program
because when I looked over the program
it's fascinating to me because it
it looks like we're trying to rev up the
whole brilliant molecular world of
antibodies and so I want you to sort of
go through this the sequence events
beginning with this earlier program at depth
[GUEST] yeah
but walk us through some of
the steps because when I look antibodies
to wear among my favorite proteins when
I look at their just brilliant things
they just so selective and they find the
thing that we don't want our bodies like
glom any way you tell us the pieces of
the program
you you know Ivan I couldn't
agree more I think all of us that are
fascinated by new yeah yeah DARPA right
that's probably a common theme is we are
just amazed by the natural world and
what the natural world has developed
antibodies are a great example I mean
there are millions and millions of these
different versions of antibodies
circulating through your body at all
times and the mechanisms are so refined
and intricate(错综复杂的) to select ok which are the
antibodies that are most protective when
you're exposed to an infection and your
body goes through the process of them
making a lot of those in a short period
of time
I think it's mind-boggling(令人惊异) how advanced
that system is we've learned so much
about antibodies in the last 50 years
you're absolutely right we want to
leverage all of that information that we
know how they work now and we know how
they know about their structure we know
how to make them in big vats(多样性) and why
can't we use that and you're seeing
incredible progress in medicine where we
are using that where you're seeing
antibodies approved as products now for
cancer treatment for treating autoimmune(自体免疫)
disease or the category biologicals in
the in the category of biologicals a
massive explosion in that space and we
want to use all of that knowledge and
that technology to solve infectious
diseases problems what we do at DARPA
though is the fun part is we couple
different fields together and so as you
have correctly pointed out this
extraordinarily powerful tool of
antibody engineering but can we couple
that with the the revolution that we've
seen in in genetics and that's that's
DARPA right it's taking two different
areas seeing if we can mix them together
again
an antibody specialist might not think
about the opportunities with genetics
the genetic specialist might not think
well
wonder if I couldn't use my use genetic
engineering to make an antibody you
bring the two fields together in a mold(模具)
you know by our our magic of bringing
them the disciplines(学科) together we achieve
that effect and so the proof of concept
which I find exhilarating(令人振奋的) it's and
chills up and down my spine is that we
can give you a piece of DNA or a piece
of RNA and we can put that into your
muscle cells and that your muscle cells
say okay got it
I am going to make this antibody that is
so protective that someone's not going
to get that's encoded by these nucleic acids (核酸)
the RNA tells that muscle
cell so the muscles I was doing what a
muscle cell does but once that RNA gets
inside that muscle cell the muscle cell
says right I'm gonna make a protective
antibody that's gonna protect you from
Ebola and to do that in a fairly short
period of time and that idea would sound
crazy ten years ago too many obstacles
can't be done the foundational
investment from DARPA proved that
concept in many different animal models
for many different infections but
because we're DARPA we said well great
we prove the concept that wasn't good
enough it wasn't good enough for me and
it wasn't good enough for the DARPA
leadership DARPA leadership said okay
that's great but we need to birth the
baby if we're going to take pandemics
off the table and that's that's why I'm
here we need to be able to put this
together as a platform that can go start
to finish from once a pathogen is
identified to making thousands of doses
of this miraculous(不可思议的) antibody based
antibody based treatment in an
incredibly short period of time right
and let's let's talk about the timescale
for a minute because that's part of the
big deal here right what I've seen is
within 60 days of identifying the the
pathogenic agent to actually have these
doses right in hand and in a
distributable form is that correct
that's correct right that compares to
what - what's the state of the art today
the state of the art today depends on
infections but let's use some some
recent examples we currently have some
Zeke(寨卡)
vaccines in clinical trials but we've
been working now for a few years and we
don't have a license to use Zeke vaccine
you think about our [..] when we talk
about gaps you think about all of these
recent outbreaks and one of the
fundamental lessons is that we haven't
had vaccines and treatments that are
ready in time and we came up the the 60
day goal has been controversial when we
talk about audacity you know I have
professional colleagues who laugh at me
I've been on I've been on panels(圆桌论坛) where
where I you know discuss the program and
the other panelists joined with the
audience at laughing at me so I knew we
were in the right space the
counter-argument that I continually make
to the critics(批评家) is 60 days is dictated(提出) by
what we need to respond to pandemics so
if you don't agree that our approach is
the right way then come up with an
alternative because we can't negotiate
with Mother Nature and say well we'd
like another six months if you don't
mind especially when you think about the
catastrophic consequences accordingly so
you know we have to be we have to do
this within 60 days and I think again
I'm profoundly excited because I think
we found a way to do it so I want to try
to make this concrete for our listeners
which you've actually done fairly well
just now what I thought of another way
we might do this and that's by combining
you know kind of almost the the gaming
out to the future where let's say you
are successful and may you be successful
with this p3 program the the pen jet
pandemic prevention platform program
let's say that you had that p3 ability
back in the 1918 Spanish flu which I've
seen different numbers I've heard 50
million people people died during that
pandemic if this technology existed back
in the early part of the last century
how would that have unfolded do you
think well my hope is that 50 million
people don't die that we and again part
of this is you detect that we have a new virus
or a new version of influenza and we
detect very early on in the process when
it's first starting out in a given
country that it's that that it's
happening we flip the switch and we say
for that new virus we need $20,000 that
have to be ready within 60 days and then
we go to win that outbreak is first
starting we identify who's sick we treat
those people that are most likely to be
contagious and we stop the outbreak in
its tracks if we add it we could have
stopped the Spanish flu I think even
more importantly right now today you and
I both know people who are getting very
sick with influenza we're seeing a
severe season and we're seeing
unfortunately children die we're seeing
unfortunately otherwise completely
healthy people having you know being
hospitalized and influenza does that to
us every year we imagine a world where
this platform could be used to take
seasonal influenza off the table as well
an amazing thought because I mean this
gets back to you to them several times
you said what a privilege it is to do
what you're doing because if you succeed
you will know I know you won't take this
it's not pumping you up personally it's
it's more for what it's doing for you
know kind of humanity but you will know
you've had a part in potentially saving
millions of people's lives by cutting
these pandemic experiences off before
they really get going and spread so a
really quite an amazing yeah and I would
make two points the first is that DARPA
my team does not do this alone
DARPA does not do this alone we we work
incredibly closely with our colleagues
and Health and Human Services with other
experts in the Department of Defense in
the US government as well as
philanthropy(慈善事业) as well as the private
sector and as well as the global
community it's ultimately a global
teamwork that's going to take these
infectious diseases off the table but
make no mistake we can say it sounds
hard and it's ambitious and it's crazy
but I challenge you to say why not
you know why aren't we as a society
putting incredible even more effort into
taking these infectious diseases off the
table if we have the if we have the
scientific know-how to do so this is
what I think one should be focusing it's
a moonshot but why not go for a moonshot
and why not go for a moonshot for
against something that could kill
another 50 million people why not take a
moonshot against infectious diseases
like malaria and tuberculosis(肺结核) I mean
we've seen you know there's there's
effort in there there's global effort
that's absolutely tremendous but why not more
so Matt just a little while ago you
and I were kind of gushing(滔滔不绝) about the
molecular beauty in the biological
beauty of antibodies and the
specificities those have to go out and
find whatever the health threatening
agent might be and kind of and the role
that plays in our own bodies fight
against health compromising exposures so
I guess I kind of want to ask you do you
have a favorite infectious disease in
the sense that you admire what the
bacterium(细菌,单数) or what the virus does and has
learned how to do over the course of
evolution?
so I'll answer in a slightly
different way I think it's a when when
when we say we want to take infectious
diseases off the table in some ways it's
or it's ridiculous because we're always
gonna have we're always going to have
viruses and bacteria that are part of
the natural world and we and we've
always seen them as the enemy or it's
pathogens is the word that we use one of
the interesting ways to think about the
problem though is that a part of it is
that there are a pathogen but part of it
is how we respond and modulating how our
own body responds to pathogens is a
major theme of what we're trying to do
with antibodies being one of many
examples and so you know one of the
traditional attitudes of antibiotics is
you know antibiotics that have been
wonderful and certainly profoundly
impactful in terms of our society as
we've as we've come along but we've also discovered
the unintended consequences of giving a
broad-spectrum antibiotic incurring(招致) my
antimicrobial(抗菌) resistance and things like
that as well so the the world that I
imagine is that there is I guess like
you said before an appreciation of
pathogens an appreciation of viruses and
bacteria understanding what they do and
what they don't do and it's not always
wiping them out but more about rendering
them harmless or figuring out ways to
kind of coexist with them is where I
would like our thinking to go in the
21st century.
it makes a lot of sense
gonna I heard statistics about the
number of mammalian(哺乳动物的) cells in me and you
and the number of bacterial cells and
there's we're almost from just a numbers
perspective way more bacterial than we
are mammalian we are but they're most of
the time this is this is a symbiosis(共生)
this is this is a mutually beneficial
relationship and so it really we
shouldn't always think about these these
microbes(微生物) as things to consider them
enemies we shouldn't consider them that's
right that's right and the other part is
that we learn from them you know it's
it's their evolution that also kind of
inspires us and so it's a that in some
ways there are adversary but in some
ways they're sort of that you know in
the superhero novels and things like
that this idea of the the the balance
between the hero and the villain(反派) and
sort of that strange relationship that
often and develops between the two and
if you will mutual appreciation is that
I think that's awesome pathogens
so Matt
we're coming toward the end of our time
here but I'm just wondering if there is
something that didn't come up during our
discussion that you think would be of
interest to our listeners given you know
your goal here of perhaps ridding us of
some of some of the concerns we have
about the pathogens in our environment
yeah one of our mantras at DARPA is this
idea of inspiring inspiring creativity
and new solutions to problems and
oftentimes we say by sort of recruiting
in people who have not traditionally
thought about our problems to help us
with those solutions and so you know I
would love for the listeners
this podcast to be more inspired to
address the problems and Infectious
Diseases and what I mean by that is I
always say people like me have to you
know we've invested our entire careers
and our life work into this and we have
deep knowledge of the subject but I love
the thought of people that have
expertise in computer science in
mathematics in what we would say well
maybe those fields aren't necessarily
obviously related that's who I think
that's how we're gonna solve the
infectious diseases problems of the 21st
century and so when I speak on this it's
almost part it's one part recruiting and
it's especially recruiting those that
may not have all of the biases of the
traditional experts in infectious
disease to come up with a creative
solution to solve it so that makes me
think of a term that we hear a lot here
at DARPA you know the innovation
ecosystem because you just mentioned a
whole bunch of disciplines that you know
maybe on first when you first think
about infectious disease you might not
think some of those come together so it
is there something about you and being
here at DARPA that is conducive to
shaking up that innovation ecosystem in
ways that could maybe move toward the
goals that you have well DARPA enables
me to do that because again they are our
program announcements when we say okay
we set the requirements solve this
problem make us a treatment in 60 days
we know that they can't do that alone
and it takes a multidisciplinary(多学科) team so
if if you want funding from DARPA you're
gonna have to work with people you're
gonna have to recruit it we design it so
that you will have to recruit in people
that may not be the traditional subject
matter experts but furthermore every
time I get a chance to speak and to talk
about this problem like on this podcast
you know again I see it as a recruiting
as a recruiting tool to inspire those to
help us address these infectious
diseases threats well what I'm realizing
now is I do not want to prevent you for
another minute going out there and
realizing your goal of taking the
lethality(致命性) of pathogenic disease
and we are out of time also so I just want to thank you
this has been immensely fascinating for
me and I just want to thank you for
sharing the stories about your your life
as a as a medical professional and and
how you're expressing your interests and
goals here at DARPA
well thank you very much for allowing me to be a part of it
and thanks listeners for sharing this
time with us I hope you join us again
for the next Voices from DARPA for more
information about Colonel Matt Hepburn
the program's he runs and the other
breakthrough technologies DARPA is
working on visit darpa.mil and for
links that enable you to download this
podcast go to the Voices from DARPA page
on DARPA website