Support for serial comes from ATT
The number one smart home security provider
With a team of 18000 employees dedicated to safeguarding your home
With connection to First Responders
Offering Custom Design Systems including doorbells indoor and outdoor cameras and smart locks and lights
All control from the ADT app or the sound of your voice
And all back
Buy 24/7 protect
Visit att.com podcast
To learn more
Moment of adrenaline
Previously
I'm cereal
We
All felt like why are we up here
I can't do anything but just keep going going out and shaking hands and I love it
And this is the one where I said I don't want to see more this f****** Lawrence of Arabia s*** I said out loud
Let's do this
First thing that comes out of our Battalion Commander his mouth is what you couldn't shave
Manipulation game going off pussies everyone's
FBI false assumption that America doesn't leave Americans behind statement is 380 page
Pages
Give me tonight
Talk to somebody I need to report a missing person
From This American Life and WBEZ Chicago its serial one story told week by week
I'm Sarah Koenig
If I were a soldier with some pride
With principal
And I had to come up with a reason for walking off into Afghanistan
Causing a crisis on so many levels
I might engineer something like those explanation
That I was sacrificing myself for the team
Because I thought they were in danger
It's a way to save face
To say my intentions were Noble and good
Over the months of reporting the story I have wondered about this
Weather bow was really telling the truth about why he left his Platoon
Or if he was telling the version he could live with
Mark and I've also debated this
Of course
Once when we were talking Mark took the microphone and started to interview me
Well I guess I'm interested in more narrow stance do you think he's lying
I mean I'm just asking
Because you 10 still bothers me
Remember the coochie
The Taliban said they first captured by when he wandered into a coochie 10 or near coochie tent
Which wasn't part of those telling it all it made me think if Bo had walked into a coochie tent
Maybe he wasn't really headed to fob sharana to tell someone about leadership problem
Maybe you should try to run away
Looking for help
Mark and I had that conversation back in September I've since moved on from the coochie
I don't think it's verifiable or that much of a discrepancy with those version of what happened actually
Promises to say I can understand why some other people both served with when I first talked to them
Hidden Bible story
I thought maybe he concocted it in hindsight
But I put a 20
Inmates chain cross he said quote
She had some years to work on that
There's a Litany of reasons why someone could be skeptical of both explanation
First his premise that leadership was dangerously bad
For the most part the soldiers we talked to didn't agree
That was some said they actually loved some of their leaders thought they were great
And Lieutenant Colonel Clint Baker the Battalion Commander Bauer responded to so negatively
Getting overall they didn't think he was putting them in situations that were crazy risky or that they couldn't handle
Then the notion that both would have to do something so dramatic to be listened to
Also not true
Which is so
Orderly outlandish
I mean it doesn't pass
Oh man because of where they were
A couple of days prior they were on fob sharana which is
Huge
And has
All sorts of off
Any any one of them could have gone and talk to you
That's Mark McCrory
Is an open door policy that allows you to approach any officer at all with a problem doesn't have to be in your chain of command
But whether an officer would have taken both seriously I have to say is doubtful
About knew that
Big one I heard from quite a few people was it Bowie either was in cahoots with local afghans
Or even wanting to contact the Taliban
Here's Darrell Hanson John Thurman
I mean for him just to like walk out where he did like he wasn't afraid of them
He will be he had to
Had some kind of compassion for him
And didn't like us for him to walk away and I like
I know where again I have to go back to the question where are you going to go
Cuz if there's no other option you've either got our side or the Taliban side
A lot of people pointed out that Bo hung out with the Afghan police who were also stationed at The Outpost at mess
Etsy with them eat meals with them
Other people did too
It was great it was great food
But some people said boat was there more often
Seems more interested in them than other people did
Josh quarter said that bull was once late for a guard shift and had to go looking for him and found him having tea with the Afghan
Stand the table went missing Josh says he heard that to the A&P guys were also unaccounted for
Two Afghan police were missing as well
So
That seemed very logical to me that all seemed to make sense cuz
Okay well now he may have to
Guides or he has two people he
Is looking to meet up with
Maybe Bo had made a deal with these guys someone betrayed him or sold them out to the Taliban
I tried to check this Intel
I called the former Governor of Pacheco province in Afghanistan the guy who'd worked pretty closely with the leaders and Bows battalion
But he wouldn't talk to me on a cell phone
I did invite me to visit in person which is very nice but not immediately helpful
I did not say anything about the missing cops in the Wikileaks reports or in general dolls investigation
Executive officer above Battalion told me he'd heard this rumor to about some missing Afghans but he did not
Know if anything came of it
Sami Yusuf side the Afghan reporter asked around about it as well he told us there was a report of some missing Afghan
And please
It was later discredited
Market
Fiasco about it
Lenny idea was you had some A&P guys who were going to help you out or no
Local police
I was right
The guys were
I have every reason to
Who said the reason he hung out with the A&P sometimes was because that was part of the mission
Build a rapport in case they ever ended up in a firefight together
Who's trying to do coin
He says that's also why he tried to learn a little patch though
Which some soldiers also said made them suspicious
The evidence people point to most often though
To support the idea that Bo was simply deserting
React no higher purpose
Was that he had talked about doing exactly that
Taking off
Several people told General doll they'd heard both say things about walking into the mount
Pakistan are heading to India
It's a one-person something like this even before he deployed while he was still in Alaska
Christmas angles
Probably about his closest friend in the platoon
Imma make him talking about
You know the mountains and how great it look and you know imagine
Just walking out there remember all that stuff I mean I always right there when you was talking about it
Chain cross if you'd had a conversation with bow the night before he left the Opie
Was evening and the guys were sitting around in the shade of a truck.
Talking
And the topic came up
How would you fake your death
I don't know
Papa cliff
They told me that he faked his death Afghanistan war
You just disappear
I want to see your casualty
Annie sez
That is goal
That he was to fake his death
Did they even get to Pakistan
And the Indians went up with a gang over there
Austin Lanford was there too
This is the first time he'd ever talked about
The night before you left the old
An Austin remembers the conversation about the same way Shane.
Wanting to be a
Mercenary
Of sorts
And it was something along the lines of
He was going to join a group
I go up in their ranks
And then
Shobaleader and then
And then he'd be known
For being a mercenary or something like that
That's what you remember that's what the gist I got
He said no Russian
Restaurant that big influence in India with games
I mean he told me about Russian that he work is left in the game
Heading into Russian mob
Hitman
Will also ask about a weapon
He was issued a saw big heavy machine gun
Chain her to Pistol and M9
He tells me I hate
What would happen if your
Dyno near disappeared
I told Mike in trouble
We are like that's a stupid question like yeah
Of course
And then
Someone took it from you
I said I'd get in trouble
Okay
Oh didn't take a gun with him when he left
Looking back on it now. Shane says it's like if an ice cream truck drove by
And somebody said hey I think I might scream
And then the next thing you know the person is gone
You going to figure they went after the ice cream truck
For his part Austin was reluctant to tell me about the conversation
Because obviously he knows how it sounds
It's a little
Extreme
And I kind of don't want to make him seem like she was
Crazy or organelle
Not in his right mind cuz we all had
Weird thoughts while we're over there isolated from anybody
Another words
Wanderlust E comments like this
All that strange
So many people told me
Fear + stress
Boredom plus Warzone means
You say some really off-the-wall stuff
Another platoon mate Jason Frye told me he wrote letters to a friend when he was in Afghanistan and got them back years later
Read through them he thought
What was I thinking who was I
Is Mark McCurry
Things that we get away with saying to each other
Completely Ludacris
Give me an example of Fort Hood shooting was when on
While we were there and I remember that we were watching it on some grainy television in the armed forces
Dish Network in the chow hall on my buddies for sale for Migos
We have to go back out again tonight I want to make Fort Hood look like church
Dark and creepy
You know the only kind of humor we understand I mean we're wound up pretty tight yeah yeah
General dog considered all the evidence
Pointing to the idea that Bo was deserting
Permanently
He heard about the weird comments about the Intel
And he concluded Beau was telling the truth
Bose quote stated motive was well-meaning in his mind.
Ironically
The basis for his stated motive was incorrect
Mark spent about a year thinking it through
And he also ended up believing though
Philosophy
Probably just for practical reason
Princess Belle with such a careful planner
He was an outdoor kid who grown up in the mountains
The intended to just disappear permanently desert why wouldn't he bring more food
More water
Beside his computer and some other stuff home in a box
Before you left the Okie
Some people see is evidence he was leaving for good
Mark sees it as the opposite
And take it with you if you're going to India
Throw it in a backpack and a charger
You know
Eight you know he sent the form yet cuz he thought he was going Stateside cuz he thought he was going to
She was going to have an audience with the general and then they're going to throne in Leavenworth
It's probably true that he that he anticipated getting his computer back
That's why there's nothing really at the end of data points to the idea
If this was a permanent departure
Shijiazhuang
Justin pack for that
Kiddo
It's just it's that simple
But details like this
Definitely not what convinced me
He's logged something like 25 hours of taped conversations with bow
And many more hours of conversation
Not on tape
The more I learn about the and the more I learn about how his mind worked
And the more I talk to him about natural history the other subjects
And realizing that
Of course I would never walk off of Base you know and yeah most of his platoon never would so
If that makes sense it is
It is a totally
Wackadoodle
Inclusion to make
But
Good night if your Bo Bergdahl
That makes perfect sense
How does it make sense to go
When I finally sat down for an interview with General doll
He didn't just go back pre-deployment to explain what happened once he got to Afghanistan
Do it all the way back
To home
Idaho
To Childhood there
He done a lot of thinking while he was locked up in that cage with the Taliban
Guy looking at myself I looking at the situation going how did I get here
And that question is put me back into my childhood
I got here because I made a choice
But that choice was bald
I'll give you a bit of a backstory I literally grew up by myself
Homeschooling
Completely isolated
So you just screw up like f****** around in the woods in like
Stuff like that
Usually likes
The Grove on 40 acres
Down a dirt road in a valley
Outside the small town of Haley
His father worked at UPS his mother homeschooled him and his older sister
I had a hard time with the school work he couldn't read very well then
He wasn't good at his work or you wouldn't do it
And he says you get punished for that and for other things in a way that he says felt unpredictable
But says he was scared all the time getting in trouble
They didn't have the greatest relationship with a
His parents his dad is a strong personality
He's pretty cool person
What is this
It's just
Complicated
Solution with the same one teenagers have used for centuries
Get out of the house
I started working efficiently when I turned 13 cuz I was illegal ish
So I started
Are spending more time at work
Turned into my
Saving Grace basically cuz it got me out of the house for the official reason at 8:30
Maybe dinner breakfast
Back to work
When he was about 15
Both fell in with a family those pretty different from the one he grown up with
How many Metro his job convinced him to take fencing
National performing arts school in Ketchum
Next town over
Haley
Kim Harrison
She's the one from episode 5 who told the story about contacting Interpol
Kim was helping run the school
Her son also took fencing
And her daughter Kayla
Ballet
What was around all the time
He ended up becoming attached to our family
That's Kayla
A few people told me
Do you want to know about Bo talk to Kayla
She understands
He was with her it was watchful and serious
And very sweet
Like one birthday
For my birthday card
He went around our small little town
And with the card and just ask random people to sign it for me
Oh really little message yeah it was the coolest idea and and
Knowing Bo and how shy he is and how little he wants to
You'll be noticed and have strangers know who he is
Yeah that was an even bigger gesture than it seems like because
You know that's hard for him he doesn't want to do that I know he doesn't like that
Write this is like teenager about like teenager but is super quiet
He would blush very easily he's getting very mad at me for saying that he brushes really easily and so
Eva's really easy to embarrass and
And
You just he didn't he he wanted
I know
Gentlemanly is a good where he is very much a gentleman
And very very conscious about
Saying the wrong thing right of being inappropriate or anything like that
The Harrisons open up a tea place in Ketchum
Skeetown
T Bar was called Strega
Miss her food and had a little Boutique and help moving eyes or Hosta
Performances The Hangout
Kayla and her brother works there they're both homeschooled to
He do his mate help me make crepes sometime
Or
Mostly he would hide weapons everywhere in like
Sit in the corner and watch people
Helix security
Play I remember we had we just had like random weapons like hidden everywhere that give his like a
Felt like a flail like
Spikeball
Amanda chain I think was like underneath the cabinet somewhere
I would like a nice pic
Hidden exit
Him it was like how you need weapons
Available when you need them
I never had to use them
Obviously but you know
He was in charge of being
The safety guys knowing that everything's cool
He wanted to be
I'm sure you've heard my mom say this but he's the protector
I have heard her mom say this
All the friends I spoke to from that Circle say the same thing
He wanted to protect me
Kitchen was kind of far from Bo's house Sobo begin staying at the Harrisons for stretches
Strega
Especially when he was younger it was like I was studying there family
See how they operated
How they got along
They argued what action would lead to reaction
Other people wandered into Strega
Begin working there and also became part of the family
Is Chad and Nick
All these people love Bo
They talked about how unusual he is
How smart
Play full how creative
How totally annoying he could be
You might argue with you unrelentingly
Just to see how far he can push
Tape his mouth shut
She will happen
What was a teenager who never been to school
And now with the Strega crowd
He was testing out ideas
Setting up Behavior
And maybe more than most people
He worked on improving his
As if you were in training
His friend said it was sometimes a little overboard
He might punch trees or bricks
His hands
He wanted to get better at things
Reading or dancing or writing
Read stories
Mostly though he was trying to figure himself out
It really matter to him
The seeking and knowing what kind of man
He was going to be
Nicholas about 5 years older than Bo
He also worked at
Watauga
And talk for hours sometimes
Nick says it wasn't so much the bow was searching for something concrete
Profession
He was wrestling with the big existential question
I know I really think so much of it had to do with
Questions of
Virtue what was right
More than anything I think that's what he
What is really working on it
Focused on all the time with
Coming up with this
Values from cell
And he just did a lot of watching to see what everyone else did
And reflected against it
And
If you don't want it to be anyone else's
Isn't going to take anyone else's word for it
About what was right
What was moral
Who's going to forge his own code
Taylor says the one he ended up adopting from self
Restrict
Uncompromising
I've had arguments about
What's this with him about this
Many times and he gets
Really you know
Passionate about it like
You know there's a problem in the world
But what kind of human are you unless you're doing something about it
Like you're not
You're not a good person if you know that there's something wrong and you're not doing everything in your power to fix it
Really
He holds
The world and everybody in it too unrealistic
Sickly high expectations
And if you don't live by those Expectations by those morals in that honor
That he thinks you should
And he tries to live
Stella said he has no respect for you
Yanny just said
He doesn't understand
It just sounds of impossibly idealistic
Yeah point where it kind of is strangles how you move through the world or something
It's really handicapping
Can I get the handicap
He's constantly struggling
Understand how people are okay with everything you know what I mean
He doesn't have an understanding of how differently they view the world
Yeah
I think he's fully understanding
That not everybody can accept the way he thinks
But that's never going to change the way he thinks
I got it yeah like his his
He has the least flexible
System ever
During his late teens or early twenties
Would work for a while in Idaho and then take off somewhere for a job or trip then come back and go off
Again
Kim Kayla's mom
Both had a hunger and an urgency about
See the world
Can experience
You wanted Adventure
Caleb boats
Field water
Salmon fishing in
In Alaska
He went down south to work at a military training camp
A place where Special Forces
Guys are gopher
Experience a topo he'd rather be doing what they were doing
The week is up they disappear to go off in
So we left
He went to Florida to complete a charter boat
At some point he left for France
To join the French Foreign Legion
Which Kim says she knows he did arrive in France
She's just not completely sure what happened after that
I didn't really talk much about it
They probably thought he was out of his mind for going there and what and this
Here's a Killer Blonde hair this young cute kid from Idaho
Blonde hair and blue eyes I'm going to join the Foreign Legion hey sign me up
They probably thought he was
Completely
Bunkers for doing that because he was ordered that was just a really bad choice
And of course when he tells me about I think part of the reason he did it was
See my face
Like
Because he didn't tell you about it beforehand though he did and was like are you kidding me
That is the dumbest thing I've ever
You know there was a beginning of me getting incredulos at his choices that was the first
No maybe at the first
The first of many or one of many
He trained on his bike Nick Sabor a lot of spandex in those days
Recycling trip down the West Coast
Which like the Foreign Legion didn't pan out
Few days and he got hit by an RV and he was okay but his bike was ruined
Who came back to catch him and started in on the next idea
Eventually the next idea became the military surprise to his friends
Does brother-in-law was in the Navy
And both had that strong protector quality
Romantic version of it to be sure
You wanted to be invisible Kayla said
Someone who'd be unnoticed in the shadows
Looking out for the innocent
Shooting in when they needed him
And they knew who wanted to put himself in situations that would require courage and Grit
That would test his mettle so that he could come out the other side and know what kind of man he was
So they understood it which is not the same as thinking it was a good idea
Please don't do that
Who it should be noted is a pacifist to begin with and he knew how I'd react is probably predictable and I'm going to ask
Are you sure this is something you want to do I think it's a horrible horrible idea
Not just
For you know not not for everyone
You know for you for all the above reasons is romantic expectations his rigid could have
Contact his judgmentalness it up join the crowd follow orders
I said look I know if you want to do that and we not going to listen to me of course you're over 18 do whatever you want
But if you're going to look into the Coast Guard because at least then you'll be helping people you'll be like
Saving people's lives sitting vessels
Are patrolling Waters being on the ocean those are all things that you like so he must
You absolutely must
Then you know that's probably a good option
Have you thought of that already know
Sweden
He join the Coast Guard
January of 2006
To Cape May New Jersey and started Trading
Is 19
It lasted only a few weeks
He didn't want to be weak
You didn't want to
Not be able to participate in that system to achieve those goals but
His sensitivities
And
It is way of pondering and overthinking things made it
Highly difficult in that environment to survive
I never actually
And being yelled and screamed at
It didn't take him long to realize he wanted to get out of there
Basic made a mistake
And in the communications that I had from him at the time they were becoming increasingly more worrisome
I was just
In pain
For him you know I breathe
These little notes
They're only like that in the spiral notebooks you flip 3 and 1/2
The four by five for 6
With the ripped off spiral at the top and just running really small and
The riding with change to you know and I didn't as well as stress level increased
People are out there
The town was changing is my rambling as more desperate it was just rapidly
Yeah
At me now eroding
I think I wrote a couple letters back like
You know are you okay I'm getting really worried this needs to end you know what
What can I do
One day out of the blue boat shows up at Strega
The t-bar
He's back
They're all thrilled to see him
And also
Confused
What happened where are you back
He told him something about a psychtest
Which he said he pretty much fake
Kevin the others
Didn't really believe them
According to General dolls investigation
What happened is that on third week of training
He was found on the floor with blood on his hands and face
Twin series
Nosebleed
Who says now he doesn't remember how he ended up on the floor
I thought he was told later he was in a fetal position and shaking crying he was taken to the hospital
He told the intake people there he felt overwhelmed he said the next day there were a psychiatrist assess him
And according to dolls report quote observe that PFC bergdahl's mental status is significant for situation
Anxiety
Any recommended discharging him knowing he would need to receive Stress Management counseling
And have quote clearance by a psychiatrist prior to reenlistment
Tide for continued service in the Coast Guard because of a diagnosis of adjustment disorder with depression
Brother sister in law
Black sheep of the family
And I figured I could do the Army because
The Army was more
Military
Yeah
Do that too when I join the Army at
I thought I was in a much better position
Because of the way that Bo had been was called separated from the Coast Guard
There was a code in his military record indicating he'd need a waiver if he ever wanted to re-enlist
In other words the Army would have to waive its usual standards to let bow in
May 2008 when both signed up
Happened to be a good time to get a waiver
There's been a surge in Iraq
Maybe another one coming in Afghanistan
The Army was hurting for recruits
Easing up on restrictions
Is criminal record
That might have disqualified people in the past
Give me a sentence in 2001 about 4% of army recruits got waivers
By 2007 it was 20%
2008 that your bow enlisted it was about Seventeen percent
Because it's Coast Guard discharge was labeled uncharacterized
It seems pretty much although had to do to get a waiver
Was write a paragraph explaining to the Boise recruiter why he been separated from the coast
Hard time adapting to change didn't feel prepared to be on his own
Adam family
Going on Altru
The statement which was typed up by the recruiter as he was speaking with bow
Says quote I have matured and know that I am her
Prepare to go into the army
Please do not allow my past records prevent me from coming into
The army
A week later about also showed the recruiter his DOD medical history form
But apparently it didn't include any mention of
His panic attack or his hospitalization or the doctor's note saying he needed clearance by a psychiatrist prior to
Reenlistment
Baoding mention this note to the Army recruiter either
He says he didn't even know about
So evidently that note was never seen by the army
It's not clear in fact if anyone ever took notice of it
Apart from the doctor who wrote it
Spring of 2008
But was accepted into the army
This time he hadn't told anyone in advance
He
Was being very evasive and I just
Was getting really annoyed
Alright what's going on
You're lying I can tell you're lying to me you're not telling what's going on
This went on for a couple months
And then all the sudden he shows up in his urine
I launched
Literally lunch myself I'm like literally grabbed his shoulders and I shaking at all you doing
Did you sign the thing already is this just a done deal
And he's
Acting really quiet and kind of a smirk smile on his face like I knew you would react like this is why I didn't tell you
And I was just out of my mind
I just
Freaked out
And this is because again
You'd had this
Fears about his suitability before he went to the Coast Guard those fears were worn out
Yes and now he was doing it I guess
And you just knew this is not this is a really bad idea
This is just the worst idea ever
It was the army
Setting aside the question of whether it was a good idea for bow to join the Army
The Army have let bow in
Next time on serial
Ciro's produced by Julie Schneider Dana chitosan me in partnership with Mark Bowl Megan Ellison Hugo Lindgren Jessica White
Page one and Annapurna pictures
Our glasses are editorial advisor Whitney Dangerfield is our digital editor research by Kevin Garnett fact-checking by
Michelle Harris
Copy editing by anaheed Alani
Emily Condon is our line producer our music is
Compose by Nick thorburn Fritz Myers and Mark Phillips
The show is mixed by Kate bilinski
Christian Taylor's our community editor other cereal staff Southland Elise bergerson and Kimberly Henderson
Thanks this week to Joey Palacios Captain Nicole Eldridge Heather Hanson and Ben mannion
A big thank you to Jonathan menjivar and Robin Simeon are great colleagues At This American Life for helping us so much
This week and last week
Thank you guys
Our website is serial podcast. Org where this week you can find a chart about Army recruits and waivers which
Is a really good picture of the surgeons in the wars in Afghanistan and Iraq
Again that serial podcast. Org
Stay tuned for preview of our next episode
Which is actually part two of this
The first
Support for serial comes
ADT
You can use the ADT app
To monitor your cameras and video doorbell from virtually anywhere
Visit att.com podcast
To learn more about how ATT can design and install your cuss
Smart Home
Back by 24/7
Cereal is a production of This American Life and WBEZ Chicago
Coming up on the next episode of serial
I wanted to be a soldier but I wanted to be a soldier
And he's writing these things is not sending emails
In the State of Mind was obvious mean it was
Stretched
Stop Believin so special powers
Big decision that I feel like you don't want to have to be God to make that kind of that's not something you can ever come
I don't care where your head was
But you still f****** did it
I really just tell the story of Bo
Unfortunately you now