Hello serial listeners
It's Sarah Cain egg with a quick reminder
That we have
Two other podcast
There's This American Life weekly show that chooses one theme and then has a mix of weird emotional and
Investigative
And personal stories on that
Cereal started as a spinoff of This American Life
Are we developed our storytelling jobs
And also s-town
A beautiful 7-part series that explores the life of one man in Alabama
S town starts out as one thing and then becomes something
Totally
Fascinatingly differ
This American Life and s-town
Available now on podcast apps
Or At This americanlife.org and s-town podcast
Yes. Org
Year-and-a-half ago clips from this video appeared on every major news broadcast
Show the rescue of a guy named Bo Bergdahl
He was a US Soldier who was captured by the Taliban and held captive for just shy of 5 years
Taliban made the video
The first thing you see is a couple of guys in traditional Afghan clothes
I got scars on their heads or covering their faces
Enter holding machine guns
They're standing next to a silver pickup truck
Different hoodies
In the back seat of the truck the door is open
Bareheaded figure is sitting with his knees up against the seat in front of them
The camera closes in and you see this pale young man
And that's for a doll
His head is shaved
He looks sort of like a cult leader from a 70s movie
He can't keep his eyes open properly they're bothering him
He keeps blinking and rubbing them
Watershot shows that the scrubby Rocky Hills all around the truck are dotted with other guys
Taliban
Holding rifles are rocket-propelled grenades
The guys lean into a bird I was sitting there talking to him
He's looking at their faces
One guy says something in Pashto which is translated on screen as
Don't come back to Afghanistan
Clifford since is that the guy said
Do not come back to Afghanistan
You will not get out alive
Black spots appear in the Cloudy sky and you see that their planes or helicopters
One gets closer and closer
Is a Blackhawk
Then you see Bergdahl again he's out of the truck now looking up at the sky
His clothes are too big
Billowy
Then at about 6 minutes in
Right after some cows wander onto the scene the helicopter lands
Dust flies
Birdsall walks forward science by two men
While three men from the helicopter US Special Operations team dog warden
The two sides meet in the middle of the clearing shake hands
What team captains right before the starting whistle
Berdoll steps forward the Americans put their hands on him
Poem towards the Blackhawk while they're walking backwards
Didn't want to turn their backs on the Taliban just yet
Bergdahl is walking stiffly
Lumbering almost
The helicopter they pat him down one more time and then he's onboard there Up and Away
Text less than 2 minutes
And it's done
The video cuts off
From This American Life and WBEZ Chicago its serial
One story told week by week
I'm Sarah Koenig
Good evening everyone or nearly the release of American servicemen after 5 years
Vibration Joy plants Temple
Pentagon sources tell NBC that Bergdahl vanished under mysterious
Circumstances has he left his base unarmed after turning against the war start
Hero or deserter that the soldiers are engaged in political smear campaign by raising
Fallen Soldiers say their sons would be alive if Bergdahl had not gone missing from this post
In the old days deserters Rashad
Very last thing is
I'm a prisoner I want to go home
Bring me home
Please
Me home
Bowe Bergdahl was rescued on May 31st 2014
Have you followed the story in the news may be expected the usual things would follow
A big welcome home and then a story would come out
Then what happened to him how we ended up with the Taliban
And it did start out that way
President Obama announced birdsall's return in the Rose Garden of the White House
Roberto's parents Bob and Jani by his side
This morning I called Bob
And Jani Bergdahl
And told them that after nearly five years
In captivity
There's sunbow
Is coming home
Birddogs hometown of Hailey Idaho which for five years had bring Bowe home posters and yellow ribbons all over the place
They playing this big celebration for him
Then so suddenly the whole story flipped
Within days within hours of his rescue in fact
People began saying that we shouldn't be celebrating him
Because Wilbur don't deliberately walked off his post into hostile territory
That's how we got captured
Some of his former platoon mates called him a deserter
Others were saying he was a traitor even who might have collaborated with the Taliban
Some people take offense that in the Rose Garden event Bob Bergdahl who drone a long beard and his son's absence
I'd spoken some phrases in Arabic and Pashto
The celebration and Haley was canceled
Congressional leaders condemned the tray the president made to get Birdo back
The release of 5 Taliban detainees from Guantanamo Bay
Sing the trade was not only ill-conceived but illegal
The Army launched a big investigation into what exactly happened why did Bergdahl leave his post
Even now other soldiers are so enraged by what Bergdahl did
For his own protection is going to have a security detail with him when he leaves his base in San Antonio
Finally the Army charge for adult with two crimes
One of which carries the possibility of a life sentence
Through all of this on himself
Was like a ghost
A blank
We never heard from him he wasn't talking on TV he wasn't quoting a newspaper
Don't seem like that was that
His story was only going to live in that kind of antiseptic upstairs Realm
Pissed off politicians and Military experts and cable TV commentators
The last spring
I found out the bo Bergdahl had been talking to someone
Promise to hear
Even talking to a filmmaker
Remarkable
Naturally I have a very large sense of humor
That's about
Write your pretty careful with it
Exactly like I've noticed him with me like you don't you don't crack many jokes
But you can you know I mean I might not laugh but you can try
Yeah give it a try if you see an opening let's see what you got
Purple is a screen writer and producer you've probably heard of his movies The Hurt Locker
Zero Dark Thirty
Mark wanted to make a movie about Beau story
A couple of months after Bo came back to the US
Mark managed to contact him and they started talking
About everything
About the Taliban and motorcycles and existence of God and how good spicy salsa is
How memory works and what a soldier should and shouldn't be Mark recorded the calls not for broadcast or any
Which is why you sometimes hear Mark making himself a snack
Were the Sioux Chef Mark sending email
Ardagh scuffling around
It's roughly 25 hours of recording conversations a lot of it Rain G and raw
They were poor assertive unexpected Mark swears a lot he can be blunt while both a soldier comes off as a soft
After 1 his go-to expletive is good grief
These tapes are not like regular interviews because Mark isn't so much after the fact of what he
Until he wants those two
Amore's after the why of what happened
Trying to get inside bows head to understand how BOCES the world
Always never monosyllabic or recalcitrant in these conversations
He's trying hard to explain himself
You can hear the bow is thinking through something
Has so far extraordinary life basically
And what's become of that
Which is understandable considering that any one piece of the story could keep a person's mind turning
Right now Bo is waiting to see if the Army is going to drop the charges against him or take them all the way to court-martial trial
Or something in between
And then there's the stunning fact the bow was held by the Taliban for almost 5 years
Pause on that for a second
5 years
Alone
That's longer than any American has ever been held by the Taliban longer than any American has survived being held by the Taliban
You can't speak Pashto
The people handling him for the most part didn't speak English
So for five years but can really talk to anyone
And then here he is and he's calls with Mark
Annies describing things vividly
Indescribable
Square one point they told me that they kind of had you in a really dark room almost sound like a basement like
Where there is no light
There's a few rooms like that
Yeah
How do I explain to a person
Standing in an empty
Remembering
I get that feeling that word is on the tip of your tongue
And I couldn't do anything
Yeah
To the point where you just want to scream
Is the entire world out there
That you're trying to breathe
Release that you're trying to get everything is beyond that door
On the other side of the door was relief
Course
But also all the various people and systems that have kicked into action after but went missing
Both parents and his friends back in Idaho
Military Intelligence analyst
Diplomat
Secret meetings with the Taliban
The briefers at Guantanamo Bay State Department the White House
At some point after I've been reporting out all these various threads of both story
Interviewing lots of people at length about low and about what he did in the consequences of what he did
This children's book I used to read my kids popped into my head
It's called Zoom
There are no words it's just pictures
It starts with these pointy red shapes
The next page you realize those shapes are Rooster's comb
Next page zoom out you see the rooster is standing on a fence
Two little kids watching him
Next page to Matt again they're in a farmhouse
And then Zoom further you realize that all of it the rooster the kids The Farmhouse
Toys being played with by another child
And at that whole scene is actually an ad in a magazine in the magazine is in the lap of someone napping on a deck chair
And so on
Out-and-out exhumes the aperture of the thing getting wider and wider
Until the original image is so far away it's unseeable
That's what the story of Bowe Bergdahl is like
This one idiosyncratic guy
Make a radical decision at the age of 23
To walk away
Into Afghanistan
And the consequences of that decision
They spin out
Wider and wider
And it'll return your surprise
Picture changes
To get the full picture
You need to go very very small
Is one person's life
And also very very big
The war in Afghanistan
Don't even really knows who he has
And nobody knows why he did it
Who's filmmaker Mark boal and his tape that got me interested in all this
We were talking the other day on the phone
About what got him interested in BO
Heyser cycle
Mysterious
Military perspective from the people's perspective is
Unforgettable walking
Blocking off and leaving his post
It's not that simple because she
Guys that you did for a lily
That's really good reason
Psych the most important for Foundry
So how do you judge something like that how do you judge him
For this story we've teamed up with Mark and his production company page 1
They come to us saying all this reporting on the story and we also got this tape
Do you think you might want to listen
And yes we did and we are kind of Blown Away
Until we begin working with them
They share their research with us and also put us in touch with many of their sources especially soldiers
We don't have anything to do with their movie
Mark and Paige 1rr partners for season 2
You might hear Mark and me talking from time to time during the course of the season so we can compare notes
Bo Bergdahl is currently an active-duty Soldier he's got a clerical job at his base in San Antonio Texas
Were you waiting on his legal situation
Again isn't talking to the Press
But he did give us permission to use the taped phone calls with Mark
So let's start at the beginning
Why do you do it
Why believe his Platoon
That's where Mark started to
Story
Well give me give me the give me the 30 second version First
This is for Mark's first tape phone call with bow
30 second version
Now you know what this one is right
But what is
Dustwun stands for Duty status
Whereabouts unknown
Is the Army's version of Man Overboard
This one is the radio signal that put out over the radio when they
Okay
Right
Who says what he was trying to do was to cause a dust one
Which already set them apart
Because it means Bo doesn't fit into any of the AWOL or desertion scenarios were used to hearing
He wasn't cavorting
Wasn't drunk or goofing off
Drop his weapon and flee in the middle of a firefight
You didn't decide in a burst of Panic or confusion to go Walkabout
Instead
Slow simmering and methodical
Oh formulated a plan
He would create a crisis
A dust one
In order to call attention to another crisis
Bo says he had serious concerns
Concerns that began back in basic training in which persisted throughout his deployment in Afghanistan
Regarding bad leadership within his unit
Call my first unit all the way up
Understand
Basically
Next to me
Literally
Something seriously going wrong
This is a big point of conflict may be b-big point of conflict in both story
The question generally of Bose true motives for leaving his post
I specifically whether his description of what was happening around him is accurate or believable
Because of course this explanation could be a story he invent it
You could argue that he did have five years to come up with it
Or he could be expressing the genuine beliefs of a whistleblower
Or the truth could be something else entirely and I'm definitely going to get into that precisely what Beau says he was
Seen during his deployment and how he reacted to it
Throw that will make more sense once you know more about Bo himself
So for now I'm going to jump over that and just give you the Bare Bones of what Beau says
And that is
He was so alarmed by what he considered crappy and potentially dangerous leadership
3 needed to ask
He needed to let his command know at the highest level
Course
Going to take me serious
Right
Those solution is the best one
At the time that a tiny Outpost known as Opie mask
Masters in human the town right across the road from the Opie
2000 people live there
Message impact chica province in eastern Afghanistan
Right near the Pakistan border
Next to the town the soldiers set up a Sur campsite
A scrubby Rocky clearing about the size of a football field
A couple of Supply roads come together right there
One of the roads leads back to the battalion's big forward operating base at Toronto
Fob sharana
Where there's relative comfort
Beds internet Burger King basketball courts
The other Road leads to the Pakistan border
The Earth there is a spine finder
Soldiers I talked to call it moondust
The one time I saw mess
And this would have been
A couple days before
Birdo disappeared
I looked at and I got chills that wow that that place sucks
That's a guy named Ben Evans
You never even went to Okemos
The driving by it was enough to take in the bleakness
It was for truck surrounded by C wire
Crammed up in a little of runoff ditch
So gave me the willies just seeing the place
Opie mast
Probably the worst place
Humanly imaginable
That's John Thurman
Job within the same company is Bo
News Blackfoot company
Different Catan
Like other soldiers I talked to John remembered most mostly for what it lacked
Trees
Plumbing electricity water shade
But Opie mastersbilt
On the side of a hill and on top of the hill there was a cemetery
And
Instagram this place is spooky from the get-go
The quality of life was
Extremely low
Everybody pretty much got some sort of GI illness while we were out there just because we couldn't keep things clean enough we did
Didn't have the resources
But what was the
Dirty just just just dust and
Dust flies the
Flies definitely the open toilets d
Burn pit
I burnt it would be called the pit of Hell
This is Shane cross who's a friend of both at the time same Platoon
The pit of Hell was his large hole they dug and they throw the trash in there and Burnet
Call the pit of Hell because
We started it and it never went out
Banded burn continuously all through the night and days
Different from the gym to burn your
Dumb s*** for lack of a better word
Bring It On
That seems like that would be the pit of Hell more than this thick the regular garbage
We think we took that they can empty Hesco
Which high school is like a large basket you fill dirt
Eight feet tall Cafe
TNT one of those
And I made a little
Hello room
And you had to go
Bucket
There went everyone should and then
What makes out with some fuel and summer jobs dinner with stick and stir it as it burned
No registering it sometimes smell Rowdy I wouldn't be a large wooden stick I got one by one
1 enough
It would
Givenchy burns down to Insurgent closer and closer as she's driving
Who was job whatever
To do a starring like did you have to draw straws for the stirring
What you just text her privates ncos at always pick one of us in
Usually you can rely on them taking the private they don't like
Bose company Blackfoot company
Add set up the Opie in the first place
They're supposed to help the Afghans keep the insurgents in check
Because the two roads there
The US called one of the root Audi the other route Dodge
Were used as supply routes for Taliban fighters
Their weapons and IEDs improvised explosive devices
They were the big threat in Afghanistan
1st platoon leader said there was an ID hotspot about a thousand out along Route Audi
The Afghan National Police had their own little Outpost further up the hill there as well
American soldiers headstrong all this concertina wire around the place
And their job was really just to be there
In the middle of nowhere making their presence felt
Keeping a lookout for suspicious vehicles
Watching the rooftops of Mast for snipers
Some of the guys I talked to said that occasionally someone would shoot at them and they shoot back
But now them said there was much action there
They didn't discover anyone transporting weapons or bombs
Mostly it was just fruit vendors are farmers or families passing through
Splatoon would go to the Opie for three or four or five days at a stretch
Sometimes doing patrols into Mast or the other nearby town malach
Or pulling around-the-clock guard Duty
Either from the trucks
Or from the hilltop up here the cemetery
Where they dug out of small Foxhole bunker
Everlong long stretches of boring
I was wondering what the hell they were doing there
All the soldiers I talked to said they just hated being a mess
He was about 20 miles Southwest of fob sharana idea was that he'd sneak away from mast
Which power refers to as a TCP for traffic control points
And run all the way back to the fob
He says he figured he could make it to sharana and maybe 24 hours or so
You spell again
PCP on a few days later after this one is called out.
CIA is alerted
Alerted the Marines are alerted
Which means it when he reappears It'll be such a big deal I'll be such a commotion everyone will want to know why he left
Why he's back
And so he'll be able to get an audience with whomever he wants
General event
And they won't be able to ignore his complaints
Weren't you afraid they were like throw you in
Widow jail or whatever
Actually what I
And how long do you figure you'd stay in there
I figured I'd stay in there until people
Situation cleared up
Somebody actually took a look at the situation and when people started
People would understand that I was right
Danger to the company
Understanding that if somebody had done something
Nascimento in Cobourg Eisenberg Splatoon
Some gutsy move dude
It's still stupid
Well
Yeah
They're not that's not mutually exclusive
Who makes preparation
Back at the farm for a spell he goes to the shrine at post office
And send some of his things back to Idaho
Some books is new laptop
Kindle Journal
In the likely event that he gets in trouble he doesn't want his personal stuff seized by the army
Does a shop run by the locals at the fob they got the hobby shop
Esl DVDs and clothes
Who buys a local outfit
Assertive robe
Because I knew
There's a possibility of
Obviously a big white guy
Yeah
He also took out $300 from his bank account
And us and Afghani money
Just in case you need to bribe someone
The end of June 2009 Splatoon was on his very last rotation at Okemos
The company was getting ready to hand the place over to the Afghans
Which really just means they're going to take their trucks and leave
In any case this would be Bose last chance to execute his plan
And this plan is risky obviously it's difficult and it's dangerous
But technically it's not impossible to do it
Physically but was capable
Who's a good runner
He runs similar distances before plus he was used to running at high altitudes and Idaho
He did well in the heat
Money talks about it now he'll sometimes acknowledge the wrongheadedness of it
Eddie overestimated his ability
He wasn't aware of the other ways he could have registered concerns about leadership
But there was this other idea but was testing out
Yes he says he wanted to bring attention to the plight of his platoon
He also admits that his plan was part Crucible
Trying to prove to myself I was trying to prove to the world
Anybody who used to know me
Being that person
Like a super soldier even
OK Google
Right
The character of death in whatever a character
I was going to prove to the world
Yeah
What it is
Movies
They all want to be that but I wanted to prove why don't you just wait and see if
You got the opportunity to prove that like on a mission
You know cuz you haven't even been there that long
Iguana when I wait a couple months and see if you get a chance to prove yourself in a
You know
Some kind of tactical engagement
Because it was a combination of situation
Right right right
Right into it
Right
Tutoring
On the morning of June 30th 2009
Open schedule to take over guard Duty
The soldiers would keep watch from the turd of one of the mrap
Switch the big armored truck
Who is supposed to take over from Austin Lanford
Atlantic comes the end of his shift
Nobo
So we gets down from the big truck which is not technically supposed to do until he's relieved but whatever
He steps down and shakes Bose little tent which is right near the mrap
To wake him up for Duty
Inline 4 goes back up in the truck
Stilnovo
So I went back down
And then opened is 10
And he wasn't in there so I was like okay well
He probably went to the bathroom or something
Sanford House to a guy headed to the toilet says see if bergdahl's in there
Guy comes back
Nope
Ben Lanford remembers that Bo had a reputation for sometimes hanging out with the Afghan National Police guys who also had an
Outpost up on the hill so
That that was my neck
Thought was he might be up there
So I radioed up to the opiates that has Bergdahl there
They said no poor does not appear
Set an alert Shane cross since he's buddies with bow and now Shane starts looking
So I got up and I said yeah I'll get him
I looked around and
Program from a little bit inside of their trucks
A few
Sportway Canton
But I said hey words with bow
I don't know I don't know
After taking too much traffic I started to get concerned
And
That's what I
Outback I woke her PL
I told him what
But what happened
Then it was gone
Who was the piano
Lieutenant Billings
John Billings was the pl the platoon leader
He testified at a military hearing that he thought Shane and Austin and the other guys were just messing with him
He said he thought quote
They just want to see me get all spazzed out freaked out you know call her headquarters
Instead Billings realizes with horror that it's real
Freaks out and calls her headquarters
He told an army prosecutor that he felt a quote internal franticness unquote
I can't find this guy
It types out a message to his company Commander back of Toronto to the effect of
We're not up
Meaning not 100% accounted for
I have a missing Soldier
At the other end of that message
Is Captain silvino s silvino
Look again there's got to be a mistake
Billings right back
Not a mistake
Sophie knows that's the best one in motion
Justin Theroux had planned
The new start circulating at the opp obviously then back up
Five of the chain of command and then all over Afghanistan
Those fellow soldiers immediately try to piece together what it happened
Here's Austin Lanford
The guy who bow is supposed to relieve from guard Duty
I knew in my mind
That
He had nobody came in until
Cuz it ain't they would have either been seeing they would have been able to get through the concertina wire
She would have fought back
Like
I didn't imagine him being taken as an option
And he left behind all his sensitive items in a nice neat little items meaning that's Mark McCrory serial number
Gear that would be a problem
His weapon
The laser for his weapon
Optic
Is night update
Stuff like that
A big problem if it went missing you left it in a nice neat little pile with a note
Of course mixed in with the facts there's just a ton of conjecture
Princeton's there's actually no evidence but left a note and Bone self says he didn't leave one
It's not clear to me where that detail came from
Other people said but I've been acting too cozy with the Afghan National Police guys
The way that he been talking to the locals in the way that he been
You know he's been showing up late to guard shift
Because he was busy talking to the locals
Does Josh quarter
Here's Darrell Hanson
Is guesses were expensive
We're like Manatee like CIA or what I mean does he like this
Crazy like mole was the discussion yeah like what were you guys thinking
What were you thinking that I've
I mean those are the things I like
Schedule complete lunatic
Or is he like CIA
Like we're trying to like we can figure it out you know
Some of these guys they'd seen so many strange and terrible things on deployments
But this was unheard of
I talked to Josh and Ben and another bandag I'm calling Scott's not his real name and Ken and John and Jace
Jason and Mark and Zach and Austin and Shane and Daryl
They remember bow differently they remember what happened after he left
Differently
The different feelings about it
They do not speak with one voice
A to a man they said they were gobsmacked when they heard someone was missing
And now it's like
This is got to be a drill
Holy crap like this is a
Drink like a I like what
You know
What is the craziest thing I could ever happen
Because it was so ludicrous
Set the time to think about it like what do you mean cuz nobody walks off
Nobody walks off of Bob
R&R a
Not even a Bobby
A combat Outpost where you going to go
I mean it's not like you can go hide out you know what the mall or something I mean that there is nowhere but Taliban
One of those friends told me that he was always a meticulous packer
This trip from Mass to sharana was no exception
Who's got his wallet and his camera he always had his camera on him
Two small knives that clip onto his belt vs utility knife
Go to notebook
Inside a few palms and journal entries
Plus a newspaper clipping about a guy who set a record for sailing
1000 days or something but loves boats
Water heats up the bladder from his Camelback
3 liters
Forgot to pack a nuts from his trail mix and some vacuum packed chicken meat from an MRE stands for meal ready to eat
Soldiers Field ration
And he had his Compass is Afghan clothing he shoved into his pocket he figured he wouldn't eat it until the sun rose
Sometime after midnight on June 30th
Boax about halfway up the hill toward that II Lookout
X over The concertina wire in a spot where someone had thrown a plastic crate down on top of it
He skirts past the Afghan and US post on top of the hill
Knowing it's a blind spot for them
Blade for one thing so people are probably tired
And if they're looking at it all they're looking into the distance not directly below them plus the Afghans don't have night vision gear
There anyway
Once he clears. He'll he heads Northwest toward the town of Malak passes to school there
Until finally he's out in open desert
And that's when it hit some
He suddenly feels the magnitude of what he's done
Basically what I decided to do about first plane was
Go from point A to point B
However 20 minutes out
When I get back to the everything
Can I use that was going to happen what time
Yeah
Not bad but I did not really do something.
Also he's profoundly scared
He's a world away from anything he knows in a country whose culture is
Is alien to him or people want to kill him
And he's outside the wire in the dark
When I picture him standing there I imagine a free-floating astronaut
No comforting tether attaching him to the Mothership
The thought crosses Bo's mind to just go back to the Opie
But he's not at all sure he could sneak back in
After all the guys there are watching for people coming toward them
And they're Manning big machine gun
He might get shot
Instead both figures he's just got to clench his jaw and go for it
Here again he makes a decision that is not the one you expect or at least not the one I would have
Because not only does he keep going but he Alters his plan
Complicated
Makes it a little grander and more ambitious
In hopes of mitigating the momentous trouble he now realizes he's in
Go figure is I'll try to arrive back at the fob with some extra thing
I guess
In the form of valuable Intel
He knew that on the road from five strata to Okemos there sometimes IDs
It heard someplace that the guys were planting ideas we're doing it at night
So he decides he'll make like a special forces guy
And try to catch someone planting an ID you're about to plant ID
I look for flashlights bobbing up and down listen for the crackle of radios
I would have been if I had seen somebody in the Darkness
Call Lake Wylie
In the morning
You left your position but I also got this information so
What are you going to do I have this information of this person who was book
Would be like justifiable like
He left his phone
Deal with
Basically hurricane
Up until this point both has he been walking in open Terrain
Between the road and a swell of hills
His idea was to make a slight detour
To shift a bit more toward the Hills
For some houses were
Thinking he'd have a better chance they're catching someone moving around in the dark unawares
Before he knows it he's in the house
He says he got completely Tangled in there
Forgot to check his compass
For 2 hours
Which is a rookie move
And so what was meant to be a slight detour turn into a major detour
By the time in straighten himself out and gotten out of the Hills
It's lost valuable time
The next morning
Workouts
By the time the sun was up bow is an open desert
Tonneau cover
And what happened some dudes drove up and just nag you or what
Baby
White motorcycles
Was a bigger one that was
7.62 7.62 x 41
I get one of those
They were driving along the road and I have
I'm off I can't tell you how they started
I don't I don't know they just
Deviated they turn off the road
Endured meaning
Maybe they were just
Maybe they just saw somebody walking through the desert they wanted to
Open
And I'm not about that run
Yeah
7 guys with AK-47
And they just pulled up and
What they said you fought like crazy
I'm not stupid enough to try and fight off
So did they basically just tie your hands and
Tasha on the back of one of the
Bikes or something or what
Hello hello
This is Sarah
That's me calling the Taliban
Hello is American robin
Melissa Regan way too much money
World War 1
Yes yes thank you very much how are you doing
The Taliban version of capture
Next time on serial
Cereals produced by Julie Snyder Dana Chavis and me and partnership with Markel Megan Ellison Hugo Lindgren
Jessica Weisberg page 1 and Annapurna pictures are glasses our editorial advisor Whitney Dangerfield is our digital editor
Research by Kevin Garnett
Fact-checking by Michelle Harris copy editing by anaheed Alani editing help this week from Joe level, Jackie well and then
Our music is composed by Nick thorburn with additional music from Mark Phillips and Fritz Myers in the show is mixed by Kate Bush
Lynskey Kristen Taylor's our community editor other cereal staff Southland Emily Condon Elise bergersen and Kimberly Henderson
Special thanks to Steve Sigmund Chad Hunt Carl Burton Rich Oris Matt Dorfman and Sarah Barrett
Our website is serial podcast. Org where you can listen to all our episodes
Sign up for a newsletter read articles by the serial staff and check-out Maps
Videos and more
This week we could a 3D map where you can fly over Okemos and fob sharana is very cool
Again that serial podcast. Org
Support for serial comes from ADT
You can monitor your home and control your system from virtually anywhere
With the ADT Go app
Including an SOS button
Is it att.com
To learn more about how ATT can design and install your custom Smart Home
Back by 24/7
Cheerios or production of This American Life and WBEZ Chicago
Coming up
Next episode of serial
They have no hesitation
And at what time we going to do with him or we going to have Nick Callahan
To behave him I mean like literally like we were charging into these towns just running out of our truck
Okay now we're going to fly you into this Bedouin Village and you're going to check all the women's faces to make sure
That they're not hiding him in women's clothing
The team went in and looked up and saw the ceiling lined with C4 he's asking about
Kabul or asking about fleece
And we told him that's we are pleased
My name is Roberto
23 years old