Serial season 3 is presented by ZipRecruiter
The smartest way to hire
Later during a break from a minor league baseball team that needed to hire a director of fun
And learn why ZipRecruiter is rated number 1 by Employers in the US
Play some hiring sites with over 1000 reviews on trustpilot
ZipRecruiter for free
It's a recruiter.com
Cereal
Support for serial comes from Squarespace
Make your business official with Google in Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and a Business website with Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and professional tools from Google
It's the simplest way to look professional online
Visit squarespace.com Google to start your free trial
Use offer code professional for a discount on your first purchase
Google and Squarespace
Make it professional make it beautiful
Previously on serial
Glenda Jackson deterrence and how to fix communities and all that type of
Stop
I try not to
I kind of think of it that way I can't prove you guilty
They'll give you a misdemeanor you may get a big judgment
This is going to go into the stack over here and then I can pay
This American Life
Dez Chicago it's serial one Courthouse told week-by-week I'm sarcastic
After the police surprise arrested Jesse Nickerson East Cleveland Courthouse
Haldeman jail for a few days he set up a call with his lawyer
Scott Ramsey
Yeah what's up Jess
How you been man
They talked through the new misdemeanor charges Jesse picked up
And also about whether Jesse's feuding with the East Cleveland Police might lead to a lawsuit
Scott Ramsey paste around his cluttered office while Jesse fill them in
Explaining the arrest at the block party on the 4th of July
How I felt like the police harassed him unfairly
My shoulder got injured at the hospital with 5 tickets
How many showed up in court to deal with those tickets
The police arrested him again
And he says to him in a locker room with no bathroom for 2 days
What can I use the bathroom can I use the bathroom can I use the bathroom
Emmanuel and I heard Jesse I've been locked in that same room where the East Cleveland Police had put Arnold black with his 22
Billion dollar verdict
We thought there's Jesse's lawsuit right there no
How could that not be a giant settlement waiting to happen
Scott Ramsey wasn't that interested in the holding cell story didn't seem outraged by it
You got it might be hard to prove
Instead he wanted to hear more about the other thing
4th of July
From Jesse's description it did sound like maybe the police had targeted him
Maybe that could lead to civil action
Okay let me ask let me ask a couple of questions the thing on
The incident on the 4th what proof do we have that it happen
I have several videos I stole videos
And they have videos
And then you and then also you have video from people's cameras and probably
Somebody cams is that what you're talking about
Scott Ramsey tells Jesse to gather video evidence
Find witnesses
7 to 10 people would be good he says
Preferably people without criminal records
And then he'll assess the potential
Her lawsuit
But I'm past it became obvious Scott Ramsey wasn't going to file a new lawsuit
Jesse didn't produce the evidence Scott Ramsey task 4
But also Jesse as a client was proving a slippery bat
His legal troubles came to Blossom Anew every couple months
Not just any Cleveland but in other municipalities
Jesse told Emmanuel about a case he was especially worried about
And Euclid
So the cops are pulled him over for no reason he has to Manuel to come to court with him so he could see for himself with Jesse
He was up against
Manuel dead
What was Jesse to a court date and Euclid
Here's a manual
I went to Euclid I'm bday Jesse was supposed to go to trial an 8 challenges
81 traffic
It happened a few months back
Jesse's been girlfriend Ashley just giving birth to the second son in the baby was premature
Available spending a lot of time at the hospital
Potassium treatment
One day because he bought his brothers car so you could drive home and get cleaned up but you could please
Just don't worry about nothing really tinted windows
When is a misdemeanor ticket
But Jesse didn't have a seatbelt on
He was driving without a license
How to draw this, but like a policy crime scene with small amounts of weed
Scale mm to open bottles of Smirnoff Ice
V8 misdemeanor charges on a case in front of Judge Deborah lebarron
Same jobs you might remember from and expenses
Episode 3
We're going to talk more about this later on this episode
Right now
I want to tell you what happened between Jesse and Dudley Baron
Since I'm starting 25 minutes late this morning
Today was a mess from the beginning
Like for one Jesse showed up late
By the time you rush into the courtroom
He was flustered
Tesla band was mad
R&R as you're well aware this matter was set for a bench for all this morning
Attorney where you can hear it
Prefab adjust LeBaron
High rotational been gathering for moms
Getting ready missed a couple cool things
352 Jesse vote
Even dealing with the case against OU Cleveland talks to take him to the park
If you could taste I drag on
Los zapaticos Jesse initially agreed to take a plea and then I've lost I can insisted on a trial
Blazing more
My trial was supposed to happen today
And yet what was Jesse had changed his mind again
A couple days ago
The way he hired a woman named Heather McCullough and notify the nevermind
Jessie does want to take a plea
LeBaron cult does the bounds goal Jessica being laid
I've been a few times to have in McCalla
I am at the Nickerson want to plead now
Is that correct yes or no excuse
I miss you tons to Jesse
Is that correct mr. Nickerson
No ma'am
Evan surprise
Jesse doesn't want to take
Advantage of spins out of control
What do you mean no man does about incest
I'm unhappy with my representation Jessie replies
Ben Jaffe accused of having the color
I'm trying to pressure him to take a plea against his wishes
Nicola standing right next to Jesse is like
Mile-a-minute
McAllen social club and this is the first time she's hearing this
And then the color and Jesse start arguing
One person talks at a time it's your lawyers
Go ahead and Asthma complications yesterday and this morning before we came in here today he made no indication that he was
Was not comfortable taking displate
So if he wants to continue on with y'all even do so if he's unhappy with my representation I will excuse myself
Cuz I'm done
I have done all I can for Mr Dickerson and if he wants to keep going on with this and playing games I can do
Does the baron
Signs of HEPA
She provided of a just-in-case for 7 months
I have a question about whose fault this is but doesn't balance. To once again send another
Michael David Jessie
Afterwards if he told me he slip fault because he was afraid that if he took the plea
Does abound was going to thrown in jail he tells me now he's gone new plan
High School proms
I'm win at trial
About a week later
Jeffy's next court date in Euclid
I go to The Cove in Little Alley
Zila cases
I heard from Sarah about Joseph Stalin was top of the weed smokers
Cement
Three of the cases that morning involve someone who had the same misdemeanor drug charge Jesse did
Does abound with hollyn all of them
When enough sleep in a drive-through came before
Does the bound Grumble that someone should contact the State Licensing Board
She told a high school kid that she saw him again on a weed charge
He was going to throw him in Adult Jail
Adult Jail
Incomes Jessie
Looking like you just rolled out of bed
You can't stop yawning
Make it running of kangaroos teeth
Like he was trying to get rid of last night's meal
Heels are weeks of weed
I mean read
Jesse and I took a couple seats in the courtroom gallery
Whispering
I got other stuff going on.
Jesse told me his plan for today
Wikipedia guilty
That's right
I'll be pissing off does LeBaron by not showing up to court
Men agreeing to a plea
Been insisting on a trial
Been agreeing to a plea again been insisting on a trial again
Jesse's planta de whatsoever schools
One more time
Except
Capri deal
So once you all want to you what's the strategy here what are you going to say to her
Tell her the truth she asked me while driving telling the truth
Could you pass a drug test today
Why would I have to
I'm just saying this is Aniya Ryan when she asks how often you take drugs right
Hawaii
Images of people that's quite a bit
Honesty test for defense
You bought a drug test today
Are you can pause
That's the one right now
You couldn't fall
I'm sorry Speak Out
Still Jessie
It smelled like his shadow would fail a drug test
Told me no
He's going to play it straight
He thinks does a battle respect
Fast forward an hour or so
And if I drove past you today you're going to be positive right
Oh you're not when's the last time you had smoked weed
Oh you think it's clear from your system
I called pasta drug test at the event.
I need to get back on the right track
Because means
Where is Gordon Ramsay from
You told me on Friday you have him here
Yeah
He wasn't able to make it
Dublin baranoff Jesse if he has anything to say from
Jesse Popp apologizing off bleeding
Tell just about about the day with pulled over
About his son being born prematurely
How uses driving home to change his clothes
Does the baron is not moved
So you're driving home with the
Open container Smirnoff Ice in the center console
I didn't know that was there
Fruity drink I did not mean
Let me know what it is that I don't think that but I did have some
But I did not yet and this is how you're going to go see your child
Under stress
Ben doesn't balance stop poking about Jesse's
Try this life
And how many open suspensions did you have on that day
I hope you
Although people walking around with multiple drivers license suspensions
Hypnosis
Which I want to talk about for 1 picks I can have
Because it's a real trap
Tiltonsville Ohio Criminal Court
One that judges seem to hate
I'm at snags lots of people
Especially poor people who live in urban areas
Use hot wax
I grew up in Ohio
Law of Ohio but it is a terrible place to try to function without being able to drive
Perhaps in part for that very reason the State of Mind. Revoking someone's drivers license is a great wave
To get her attention for any number of things
Last Call Insurance open warrants being late on child support unexcused absences from school
Belmo from 40 different ways you can get your license suspended in Ohio
According to the BMV Ohio Bureau of Motor Vehicles 1.1 million people in Ohio
Call my license suspended last year
Appleton estate
Average bb&b Fab
People with suspension don't have one Spencer
Mabry
On average
Because people keep driving
Be hard not to and every time you're caught driving on a suspended license
You get another suspension is an escalating series of penalties mandatory BMV fees and 5
Find me a payday loan company
Trying to get out from under suspension once you been corn the Tramp
Is a taobao business
Jeffy he didn't even know how much he owed
I called around to various municipal
Added up my potential BMV call
And I'd say Jesse could I would much as $10,000
He told me he's trying from time to time the 10th of the Seas
Paid one fine here going on a payment plan.
But I'm afraid he's going to probably never be able to settle his
Valid driver's license
Okay
Tactical
Mucus
Jeffy thinking of weed
Is offering to be guilty to 2 out of 8 challenges
Does Alabama accept
Men she wanted out loud whether Jesse would be a good candidate for probation instead of a jail sentence
Conclusions of the bound comes to is no no he would not
All you're going to do is argue with a probation officer over anything that I may order in this case
Kind of like you did with the officers
When they place you under arrest
And your kind of get the jail with the Corrections Officers
My contacts at the jail River Corrections Officers Jesse off
Does a bond refreshes memory
She takes out a police report from Jessie the rapper
When I hadn't seen
Well they were transporting YouTube
The jail do you remember your lovely comments to the officers
You're racist you and your partner that's why they call you pigs f*** you n****
Suck you over and over in the car
Then at the jail you're asking the officers in front of the Corrections Officers
What do you want to see him strip
Search me you f****** f*****
Want to see my dick
It's really quite bracing to hear Midwestern white ladies I'll be Inward and more
An open call
Mike listening to your 4th grade teacher read a Quentin Tarantino script
But just let down is not shy
On Jessie from what I can tell
Is embarrassed
Looks resigned and small was just about attendances then
Hundred dollars in fines 40 hours of community service
And does nine suspensions
Congratulations just appearances
You just bought suspension number 10
In the state of Ohio
Genesis Jesse
The five days in jail
Jesse tilts his head back
House designs
Are the bailiff places in handcuffs
I need some away
I want to tell you what ended up happening with Aramis Spencer the guy with the blunt I got arrested
Sit in the hallway of his own apartment building
And put in the hospital by two police officers
Because Aramis and Jesse obviously their experiences with the police
At the hands of police
Are very different and they're very different people
But in certain ways their cases Echo each other
The aftershocks
Especially
If you remember Aramis was trying to get rid of his criminal charges
So they could file a civil lawsuit
The resisting arrest was a sticking point
He was going to plead to it
The city was going to drop it
They're at a standoff
The trial date was set
And then at video came out
The one that Aramis is lawyer called a miracle
Manna From Heaven
Only legally speaking
Of course
In every other way the video was horrible
It showed a white Euclid Police Officer
Michael amiott the same one from aramis's case
Beating the crap out of a young black guy during a traffic stop
Seemingly without provocation
The guy in the video actually videos there are several
Richard Hubbard the Third
You can see Hubbard splayed out on the asphalt
Officer amiott on top of him punching in the face with both arms
Right left
You see Harper's girlfriend on her hands and knees slapping the ground just a few feet away from them
Screaming for it to stop
Pretty soon the story was in The Washington Post
The New York Post the LA Times CNN
They did the same thing to me
I mean it seems like they're going from one to another
When Aramis watched it
He recognized with bitterness
The beating in that video
The series of moves the officers make
Officer amiott straightaway tries to kick Richard Hubbard in the crotch
Guess I don't know maybe that's a new procedure and Euclid
Maybe they beg you to tell you to the ground and need you and kick you in the face and pays you and I
Maybe I don't know maybe that's the new procedure you could I don't know
Aramis is civil attorney Paul cristallo
Figured the Hubbard video would persuade the city of Euclid to drop the resisting
Maybe drop everything
Because how are you going to put an officer on the stand who's been suspended for excessive force
Who it turned out that had to resign from his previous job at the mentor Police Department
For lying about a traffic stop
Crisp uniform
Officer amiott probably would look like a bad egg if he testified
Few weeks went by Euclid did not drop the whole thing
September 7th 2017 has had his final pre-trial date in Euclid
Is it Thursday
The trial is scheduled for Monday for days from now
Spiros gonakis Armistice criminal attorney was running around the courthouse
Haggling over the most recent plea offer
Irma's arrived with his mother
Cali
They're a little tense understandably they weren't sure what was about to happen
They've been fighting these charges for a long time 9 months
That was all very real
The prospect that if they couldn't work something out today and Aramis ended up a trial and was convicted at trial
He could get jail time
Spiros walks over
Ocean City wants to speak to Aramis and Khalid
Can I come over now
No I'm not okay
They step outside the building I can see them through the plate-glass windows
Spiros gesticulating
Amazon Kelly listening nodding
Where does circulating
Or nodding
The comeback Inn
Is the judge raining out
We all go into the courtroom
Chattanooga
The prosecutor's table with a guest prosecutor
A woman named Sara fanelli from a fancy Cleveland law firm
After the scandal with officer amiott Euclid it harder to deal with air masses case
You already know the judge
Deborah lebarron
Hey my understanding is a plea agreement has been reached is that correct that is correct or on her
And The Plea is
Renaissance Festival
At this time is my understanding was responsible if not guilty
I prayed for your guilty to a drug abuse charge
For the balances
Emergent dismissed at his
After all the struggle over these four charges
And the Civil Rights Secrets they contain
We landed here
There was a sting in a last-ditch disorderly conduct
Just the weed
So you're just messing counts b c and d the theft the resisting arrest in the criminal damaging is that correct
That is correct
Churchill Baron checks with Aramis
Is that correct
Yes your honor
Just him if he's using marijuana
She says no
But he stopped after the incident
Bowser is trying to get a job
Armistice mother Kali is moving around in her seat in the gallery
You seem like you want to say something to me do you
Adult
Just a few minutes ago out in the lobby before court started
Counting I've been talkin
She's got four grown sons
Foreclosed family
She's been right there with Aramis every step of this case
She told me
The police don't realize
One day this could happen to one of their children
Someway somehow she said
Excessive force
It has to stop
I said I could care less about anything else that's my mango
Just to stop it I mean I'm not trying to throw the old race car that's another I just wanted to be fixed because
MSN police are bad
But if the system don't fix the ones as bad then
They made the whole system is corrupt
What you want us as a society
To fix what's going on in our home but you don't want to fix what's going on in your home
Okay
Enough is enough
She talked about the beating her son took
What it was like for her to see him in a hospital bed
His face disfigured
How she felt blessed she hadn't been called to come view her son's body that day
Callie was about to address the judge for the first time
I thought
Here Comes
Even though it was a bad accident happened
I'm glad because
I've been trying to get my son off of marijuana for years
Hebron cleaner 67
I couldn't ask for
A better paint for me
Is to see my son back like he was
Send him offer
Marijuana and everything else
Surplus
But that I'm fat
And I appreciate your comments me I'm unfortunately sometimes it takes something bad to happen for something good to
You come out of it
You know what you know
Well I see mr. Spencer you afraid supporting your mother
And you're very lucky to have that
On the drug abuse charge I found you guilty
It'll be $150 and cost
Spiros it said it to
This incident he told the judge has helped Aramis
He's been clean off marijuana
Straighten out
He's just happy to put this matter behind him
The elephant in the room
Kicking
Teasing the two hospitals the broken orbital bone
All of it had suddenly shrunk
To the size of a bulge
What size bolts
Is it this whole ugly Endeavor was only about getting Aramis off of weed
Aramis near the truth of it of course
Later outside the courthouse he give me a ride smile and say I'll take what I can get
In This Moment Kelly was flooded with maternal relief
She walked over to Sara fanelli the visiting prosecutor and gave her a hug
The hug not the end of the story
More after the break
This is the road to hire
Brought to you by zip recruiter Jesse Cole is a man who is more obsessed with
Fun and I think anyone I have ever met in my life
I wear yellow tuxedo every single day I step it up when you put yourself
A few years ago Jesse bought a minor league baseball team in Savannah Georgia and name them the Savannah bananas
He thought he could make Minor League Baseball more popular than making the games this crazy circus of fun
We started thinking we could have a senior citizen dance team called the banana Nana's
I knew we gave away a porta-john at the game the other day when they're on their knees and crawling
The crowd and it's very scandalous
I'll tell you you remember it
People did remember it
And they loved it
Just two years
Bananas went from selling a single ticket for game
Selling out every single game of every single season
I think bigger Jesse decided he needed some help sustaining all this fun
ZipRecruiter for position called director of fun
Immediately start getting dozens of qualified
Recruiting one guy named Tyler
Who sent Jesse videos of himself being as fun as possible
Videos but he's just going crazy and dancing and just jumping in pool I mean wearing ridiculous
Costume
Wow
It was simple it was easy
It gives us more time
To be able to have more fun at the Ballpark
Projesi ZipRecruiter delivered qualified applicants faster than other sites
In other words
Less time reviewing resumes
And what time for dancing
ZipRecruiter for free today at ziprecruiter.com cereal
But ziprecruiter.com cereal
ZipRecruiter the smartest way to hire
Support for serial comes from Squarespace
Make your business official with Google in Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and a Business website with Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and professional tools from Google
It's the simplest way to look professional online
Visit squarespace.com Google to start your free trial
And use offer code professional for a discount on your first purchase
Google and Squarespace
Make it professional make it beautiful
Impala first taking me to meet Aramis back at the end of 26
Is there a driving home he'd impressed on me how enduring the consequences of a beating can be
Pulse talk to a lot of people who've been hurt by police officer
Officers or Corrections Officers
And he said it's not something that's over
Even when it's over
When when you are seriously injured by the police when your
Send to the hospital and isn't just
Soft tissue some b*******
It really does affect
It'll it'll
That this will mess with him
Like if you stick with the story and we follow them
You'll see
Understood the broad Strokes of what Paul was saying
But there'd be some kind of fall out over time
Psychological Fallout
I wasn't sure what that was going to look like
A few weeks after Aramis is Criminal Case ended
All told me about a confusing conversation he had with Aramis
During which air mass was repeating certain things about what happened in his hallway
Different for looping in his head
Call Callie to ask whether she noticed the same thing
Over and over and over again
Wow
As if it happened yesterday
Nru
Like how worried are you
About him very
Oh really hairy
Other mothers
It's not easy watching your child go through this and you better have nowhere
Anime
For me it's like he has trust levels
Not there no more
Any time something comes up in the news she said or maybe they're watching a movie together what used to be a joy for her
Now if something comes up related to police violence or government corruption
She's worried about air masses reaction
First thing he'll say is see I told you
Can't trust nobody
It's like
I may be angry
You get to talk and you can eat his voice gets loud yuca
Filled up
A sense of Rage
And his child now
His body language is totally different
What's your fear
For him if he's kind of
Got that rage and anger
He's got some for now he's not really afraid of the street
Aramis is hurting she said
In the shape of that hurt seems to be a need to prove to everyone around him
He's not a punk
Chicago's biggest fear now
Is it'll take that hurt and that need out into the streets
And deploy them where they don't belong
Kelly's is none of her sons have been in the streets growing up
This is new for her
For them
She never thought this kind of thing would happen to her family
But she said suddenly you are that family
What is happening to
Officer Michael amiott the cop in Hermes case
Was fired from the Euclid Police Department more use-of-force incidents and come to light
Including a Dreadful thing in the Euclid Public Library
Body cam video showed him taking a 16 year old girl wearing a backpack to the ground face-first while she was in handcuffs
Couture down with his knee
Small child is watching shrieking
Amy outstayed fired for about a year
I need appeal determination and just recently an arbitrator sided with him
Officer amiott should be back on YouTube police force any day
Paul cristallo did end up filing a lawsuit on behalf of Hermes
Against the city of Euclid police officers and are misses apartment building
Sir finale the guest prosecutor who Kelly hugged defended the city of Euclid
This past summer they settled
Neither the city nor the officers admitted liability Aramis got $50,000
Wasn't as much as Paulette hoped but you felt it was the best ever going to do
Become Rocky he picked up a few new charges
Marijuana but also domestic violence
Are all misdemeanors
Still
I don't want to make excuses for whatever Aramis might have done
And to be clear neither did Paul
But I did ask call whether he thought there was a connection between then and now
Was this what he was talking about
Back in December of twenty
16 when he told me
This will mess with him
If you stick with the story and we follow him
You'll see
Paul said
I don't know
I really don't know
In a Civil Trial
Assuming you win
The jury has to figure out damages
That's the final stage of Reckoning
Cause leaf stone effect leads to compensation
For the damaged on you
Financially physically to fairly rational calculus
How do you quantify the intangible damage a cop does
Dear sense of the world
Your sense of yourself
Money kicks your ass
And then what if it's not one cause that's led to the damage
What if there are many causes
Many effects
I tried to call and message Aramis
I got worth RuPaul
Hermiston plan on calling me back
He said he didn't have any interest in that right now
Jesse Nickerson now
Different story
Does he have a lot to say to a manual
About causes and effects
I'm going to hand you back to Emmanuel now
4 months
Jessie continue to rack up all kinds of tickets in Georgia
Including a child for menacing in East Cleveland police officer at a gas station
Life is hard about this thing honestly
My fault
The police have a hat-trick of Jessie
They're probably arresting him and he gave it back
Morphine to come alive
Yeah you can find it a call
But it was nothing really
Party time
The video what happened
It really threw me
It was not time
Video is from a body cam
Fat David Duncan in East Cleveland police officer was wearing
In it you can see that Duncan standing inside a gas station convenience store
Right by the entrance
Men's Jetty interview
The frame
Coming from the back of the shop carrying a drink
Jesse's gets everyone in line at the register
Put some money down on the counter
Anime wolf paws Duncan the wolf the door stop cussing him out
I'm sorry you got it you want I ain't did nothing to you rather
Manhattan brother
Jesse leave the store but then comes back in
He walks with Duncan and then backs up
Opening the door just to leave again and again
As Duncan tell Jesse he never did anything to him
If he's trying to start something with Dunkin dunkin's really not going for it but Jesse's relentless
You need to stop the people in cops Jesse says
You account
Nothing to you
Jeff emotions about the Parthenon
Videos shocking
Jesse so aggressive
I didn't understand it didn't understand what get before he was doing
Or in the walls you could possibly get from going out to a cult this way I'm even more trouble
Few hours off I got the video I met up with Jesse to talk about it
You're right I guess you can smoking weed in his car
In the parking lot at a train and bus station will Windermere
Right in the middle of East Cleveland
A lot of people seem to come and hang out
Jesse and I got in his car and watch the video
We got to the part where Jesse seems to be challenging Duncan to fight
What are you asking him to do that
I'm telling him I'm telling him
To address the issue I'm I'm I'm saying
I'm fed up basically
I'm fed up with you people putting your hands on me
That's why I'm saying like being mad then come on
I'm not saying
I'm going to beat your ass right now I'm saying you all saying like
Step outside
Repeat
I'm telling him to take off his s*** and what do you mean take off his ship
Take office
Take off his armor is bad
And all that
And be a man like what is that mean be a man
I'm sad cuz
Cuz obviously
Everytime later ran into me they didn't beat me up water handcuffs
I guess
It's confusing to me because I'm the one who had you said I don't want any business of these police I'm going about my business I'm not
Do anything illegal
Entrusting me
Button
It seems like
But it seems like you are. You're harassing this officer right now
Like you'll starting
If I did
Jessie reminded me that David Duncan wasn't some random East Eden police officer
Duncan was the officer who don't approve a crowd of people on the 4th of July
Let everyone else alone
Grab Jess
It was Duncan who dragged it into the car
It was Duncan on the body cam from that night
Who stood over Jessie
Insisting that Jesse and hurt himself
I did feel a bat shouting in pain
Jesse also told me he was dunking even before that
Wind office in Devils Lake off of gave Jesse's phone number to the name Dixon
1 cycle mean Jesse in the park
Getting on the police department to complain about nipples
How many did it was always a Dunkin Jesse said he spoke to Jesse said Duncan often who he wanted to complain
Saying about when Jesse told him Neville's just he said Duncan told him
The f*** out of here
I tried to talk to Duncan talked about his various interactions of Jessie of the police department refused to make him
Available Jesse told me as a rule is Never back down from a fight except if a police
Sure
Before his mouth of it then but he never full back physically
Moana park at the name Dixon July 9th when he says they threw him in the holding
Jesse felt like a bullies were bullying him and he was just
Taking it
Not have been boring in more and more
Another timer a hangout at Windermere
Jesse told me he's been having dreams about being back in the park with the name and the avocado
We live in the moment the name to challenge him to a fight
It sounded like these dreams will one pop flashback
One pot fantasy about how things might have gone differently
The situation probably would have worked out for the best or the worst
If I would have defended myself like
I try to run from the situation
Nhac me and beat me around
So I'm thinking like a like if I would have handled my Village right internet cuz I'm a man
And I and I know like that you think that if you defended yourself it would have gone better for you if I was defending myself it would have been better
Cuz I know
I know I know from me
My physical well-being like
I can I can handle him like I could have
Adopted by
The name of the six-foot-four ex Arena Football linebacker
I don't know I just feel like two against one that situation I'm not trying to like
That would not listen.
I'm not saying like I would have
Daytime say Alyssa light
I hate that I couldn't defend myself
I hate that I can defend myself
When I just ran
That means I've been their surrender to him like a dentist to read it to him
I knew Jesse felt ashamed about by nitin
Buy noise for that was because it's inherently humiliating
Be physically overpowered
What song was Jesse I realized I didn't have that quite right
Really
The thing Debbie feel the same about
Bugatti ran away
Good morning watch the video in the gas station
The mall Justice confrontation with office in Duncanville
Jesse was asking Duncan to fight him like a man now that Jesse Wilkening cup
What you going to hear a fight me like your arm
Pools open Dunkin to fight Jesse like Jesse's amantu
Any video off the wall feels like an eternity of yelling at Dunkin
Does he finally gives up
Leaves
The other people in the store stopped working
A lot of my life
One guy in the stall. Duncan up
Congratulate Duncan on keeping his cool
At one point I want to says to Duncan about Jessie
That is so sad
What is over video Jesse yelling at Dunkin
I want to get my hands on as much information about Jesse's interactions with the police as possible
The same day I went from Jesse's call to be Stephen police station to see if I could pick up some more please. I'm just
What is a rest on the 4th of July
I'm a station build a man of the vestibule window I never met before Sergeant Jeff Williams
Sutherlands is an older white guy Welbilt weather
Pulled with a salt and pepper goatee
I told him I wanted a police report he got out and pulled over to a computer and I'll 2
Jason Nickerson I said I want to see the pools for the 4th of July
Williams knotted printed off reports as he won't have a window we didn't scan the pages Los Angeles
Dorothy read what Jesse said to the offices
But then when you go up to the window
Father dies from the well.
Tips
He told me that Jesse never would have talked to him that way
I've been trying for months to get anyone from the East Cleveland Police Department
Talk to me about Jesse
Impossible
Father William didn't say much else
Promotion the oven to a doll and buzz me into the back
We went to an office
Walgreens offered me a seat of the desk
He told me he didn't want to be recorded
What he said
Let me tell you why Jessie is the way it is
Keller Williams told me you've been acquainted with Jesse's family for 20 years
The Nicholson's withhold notorious annie's Cleveland
I guess he's older brother's but constantly getting in trouble
The soccer games that Jesse was a really sweet kid
Super bright
The kind of kid you want to save from the wall around him
Tyler Williams mile 22
What about it
Mini pools
Suggestive stop peeing that bright young kid
After Ricky died
Jesse told me about Ricky
His older brother
And how Ricky was murdered
T98
When Jessie was 10 years old
Who is sitting in his living room and just do a makeshift diorama on the coffee table in front of them
Using a cigarette lighter and a bottle of vodka
Just move them around Z told the story
That one night when he been with 3 friends hanging out in the parking lot
Smoking weed laced with PCP
Been one of his friends had a psychotic episode
Shot Ricky in the head
We have the guys ran
The friend of the gun on division down
One by one
Who killed them
According to Jesse
What has happened with the police officer just one street away
I don't know. Heard the gunfire
But didn't respond until after the shooting stops
The police couldn't save one person that night Jesse said
I didn't do nothing
Sign over there in three people died
Father Williams told me that after that night
Jesse Walden the same
Even a couple of years we started getting in trouble
Jesse whole family is going to reopen
He is off it was other way instead
It would constantly be picking up one of Jesse's Ava Brothers
Small crimes
Mostly drug-related
One night
Williams responded to a disturbance
When he got back
He sold his brother was
Jesse's brother was so high and out of it
Father William decided to just take him home instead of taking to the
The station
Savage Road
This is David Hulse author Williams
Baldwin's admitted he didn't know.
The only people he never lost his grandparents
Unsalted ming tombs came home that morning
Arrived to find his own 14 year old son Kyle that died
Even having a bottle of dust off computer cleaner
I'm going into cardiac arrest
Father William said the death to his family apart
You blame themselves for not knowing how dangerous hopping laws
His daughter blame herself because she seen cows make off of a bottle of dust often hadn't said anything
Father William said she never recovered
Sergeant Williams told me he's watched it to get in trouble and to him it's always look like suffering
The only war that is ever going for his suffering is he in the sergeant Williams
Was beaten up by two cops
Sent away with a little bit of money
He said these days whenever he is just his name
He braces himself for the news that Jesse's dead
He told me if I was going to do a story about Jesse Nicholson
I should talk to Jesse more about Ricky
So I did
3 weeks later
Jesse and I met in his apartment
Jesse was not in the greatest of moods
My interview had spilled into a Thursday night
I need to hear his friends drinking outside
I pulled up salted Williams
I ran into him not too long ago
And these are some really nice things about you
I started to tell him what Sergeant Williams it said
That would have sweet bright kid Jesse walls
Tyrese mother
It wasn't like that
I know officer never did it for me
Hayes Cleveland ain't never
Gave me an extra damn apple or nothing
So that's a lie
It's a lie
I mean he didn't even say that he thought he'd really done I didn't even say that
Snow officer
That never
Never been nice to me so
No
Jesse was adamant
More adamant about ever hurting be
B-29 that's all that we need to do anything about it
This is how blind and foolish she will see
He's not speaking on me you not speaking on me
He speaking on my brother William
I'm 29
I'm 29 my brother my brother got killed 20 years ago
I wouldn't out here in the streets
He would hardly wait until he wouldn't know me like that that's a lot but you said you were like a small kid that you knew you was a
Smoking I wasn't out here that I wasn't out here in the
Six-letter weather now here
I'm trying to actually do the math like I'm mad listen
I'm not interacting with an officer, school and stuff
What is
Nancy me
Jessica Sergeant Williams must be confusing him for his brother William
Live matches
Indian Desi do look a little alike
The thing Jeffy most strongly reject
This was at Ricky's death of change vehicles of Jesse's life
Anyway song Too Many people saying
His brother got killed
I seen I seen any trouble
Listen
Okay It Ain't going to cry and all that what you see me cry
If you see me cry something
That's what I supposed to do
I went through the things I was going through when I was younger cuz I was young and dumb
I was young and dumb I seen everybody out here with all the flashy stuff and all that that I wanted on the same stuff
But you know
Carter case when I was 18
Got out when I was
Any never been back by
So
It's cool. I mean I'm I'm not angry at the officers just
How to speak facts man like
I'd life is about facts
But
They want to single out something like
Why I am a trouble
Human being live while I was trouble person
Is this
A person spectating somebody else life
I mean that's it in all he trying to do is be like listen this is why
Nickerson is
The way is what is why he didn't went through the trials and tribulations either went through
That's not the case man
That's not the case
Jesse went willingly for the next 10 minutes
About Sergeant Williams
Tooth fairy
I think his reaction was so intense because
You been through so much more in Ricky's.
Is it to Denise Bugatti Wilkos to
Went missing for over a week when Jesse was a teenager
And he was found dead in her Palm
Baba Antoine died as an infant
Is teenage nephew DeAndre died in a drive-by
Then
Now over wrongs that they believe the police have done him
I think
When does peeing so much meaning on Ricky
Ricky's death effects
Jessie
Jessie found it offensive
Generalizing
Jesse wasn't in the mood to have us off his favorite
YouTube angry
I wasn't interested in being explained
Especially
Bible people
Police officer
Like I'm very serious now like
I am not
I'm tired of being treated like a I'm trying to I'm tired of being the victim so
No more Jesse Nickerson is being a victim like I'm not letting
Words that mean like timeout
Whatever it mean like I'm not
I just want the world to know that s*** like I'm not body
Keep Benedictine light
And then my father to come up on me and put a hand on me for no reason
I'm not
Going to let it happen like I'm not just about to
I do see all these are the times I never did nothing back
I just been evicted
If not I'm not about to keep being a victim and I better
Now I have to press them to get into lay it out explicitly
But Jesse was saying that the next time the police got physical with him
His plan was to find that
Petit Morrison for everyone
Especially words
Cousin the moms off the bat
That leads in East Cleveland I paid to be driving down Jetty Street a lot
Riding Jesse ticketing off a ticket for the usual
Driving under suspension read possession
Money Stephen call
Later told me
The attitude of the folks in charge was that while opposition to go out of their way to White Jesse up
Mason quote
Handle Jesse whenever the opportunity presented itself
Eventually these given, told me
The Snowball Effect
Well you know
Take effect
Las Vegas going to tell you it's how Jesse's pile up with criminal charges in East Cleveland Show
Does it beat once audit trial but the bulk of them dragged on for months
Months and months
Until one cool day in January when is Cleveland essentially held out one hand to make a deal
Imma be all the
Ithaca swing
Pacific dropped 5 challenges
I'm guessing 4th of July arrests
I didn't have body cam video about backed up the claim but Jesse will be aggressive
Invitan Jesse pleaded to three misdemeanor charges
Including the menacing charge against off the Dunkin at the gas station
I know those charges
I said he went off to him
Alcanfor year in jail
During the sentencing the city prosecutor listed some of his old felony convictions
Cleveland
Some 22 cases in the hole
Keep a body cam video from one of Jesse's previous arrest
Wow through the phone
Jesse was mouthing off to the police officer
What you didn't know
Was that Matt same arrest with suspect
Jesse later beat that case to trial
Anyway
In a brief filed is a call the city argued that Jesse pose a danger to the police
On top of that
Will the quote extremely negatively influence in the city of East Cleveland
The judge William dolsen
Didn't say move by the city's pitch
Instead he did something I did not see coming
He pretty much ignores that the city had a point
But also the manager told everyone
The evil Jesse had a point to
The city and the police had it out for him
Fulton Fab
In not so many words
That's probably true
Obviously I wasn't there I don't know what occurred but it seems like
You prevailed there was a settlement
So obviously something happy
That could be the reason you have a problem with
The police
I cannot discount
And at the same time
That may be a reason why
They have a problem with you is like okay
We we think that he prevailed and he shouldn't Prevail so yeah everytime you know his blinkers not working
This this this is Carter as blank is possible they don't like you maybe and you may not like me
So now how do we deal with encounter
So did you end up in court at the key
Josh Wilson decided some kind of solution other than jail time was in order
He said his deputies six months of probation
Enrolled him in a program designed to teach people how to have better experiences
Is hope he later told me
That Jesse would learn how to behave better
Around police
The common self-saving interactions would be less heated
It was almost kind
It also seemed like the judge was hoping Jesse would change
Because he knew
These Cleveland Police weren't going to
Just before Jesse's 30th birthday on the phone
Jessie was full of resolve
Is wasting too much energy on the court
Is ready to do something
Meaningful
Read a book about his life
You want to ride the end of his story now he said
But it would be a good ending
If you spot Jesse into a data set no one's favorite place to hang out
Sorry Jessie
But if you consider him not as a trash talker with a rap sheet
What is a 30-year old man going about his business
Aldar the criminal justice system is pretty much done with Jesse
Because people in their thirties and older
They're not the ones committing the most and the worst
Crimes does one research paper I read gently put it
Crime tends to be a Young Person's activity
To see the people that system is really focused on
We need to just lean to the left a little bit
Look behind Jessie
Are the teenagers
What's next time on cereal
Which will be in 2 weeks
I got to go out of town
But then we'll be back with our final episodes
Cereals produced by Julie Schneider manual
Goci Bend Calhoun and meet with additional reporting by Eataly uskoski and if he Scruggs episode 4
Glass weenie Daingerfield is our digital editor research and fact-checking by Ben Phelan sound design and make spiced toenails
Listen music clearance by Anthony Roman Southland is our director of operations the serial staff includes Emily Condon
Billy Whittaker Cassie Holly Francis Swanson and Matt Tierney by Adam Dorn and how Wilner with additional
Music from Matt McKinley and West Schwartz our theme song is by Nick thorburn and remix by Adam Dorn
Special thanks to Derrick jaxn Mariah Crenshaw Nick castelli judge Michael Donnelly Judge John O'Donnell
David Eisenberg and Lindsay Bohr Greg Edwards and Marsha Fisher from the Ohio Bureau of Motor Vehicles
McNeil Amanda Bates Linda Rico and Jack Greene the art on her website was made by Martinez EB he created them
Mural for this episode and moth Studio did the animation
Please check it out on our website serial podcast. Org
That serial podcast. Org
Or you can also sign up for our email newsletter and be notified when new episodes are released
Support for serial comes from ZipRecruiter
Unlike many job sites ZipRecruiter doesn't wait for candidates to find you
ZipRecruiter finds them for you
So you get qualified candidates fast
Try it free at ziprecruiter.com cereal that ziprecruiter.com cereal
Support for serial comes from Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and Business website with Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and professional tools from Google
Use offer code professional for discount on your first purchase
Serials production of This American Life and WBEZ Chicago