Previously on serial
What did he tell you
He told me that she broke his heart extremely wrong
Granny want to treat him that way
He was like The community's Golden Child I think like the odds of you getting the Charming sociopath you're just not that lucky
You don't think that I know you at all
Only talk to you on the phone
Global Tel Link prepaid call from
An inmate at a Maryland Correctional Facility
From This American Life and WBEZ Chicago
Chicago its serial one story told me five week I'm Sarah Koenig
For two months now I've been grappling with rumors about Adnan
People telling me there's stuff you don't know about Adnan
Stuff you need to know
Understand who you're dealing with
These communications came in the form of phone calls many phone calls
Sometimes one-on-one sometimes conference calls
Also text
And nervous emails
I can't tell this one I've spoken to that one and then that one gets worried that a broken my word which I
Promise I haven't
One person two doesn't confirm the thing person one told me and I report that back to person one
Person one often tells me
Person to is lying to me
All these rumors are coming from people and non knew growing up in the mosque community
The Salvation family is to attend Islamic Society of Baltimore
Some of these people I've already talked to during my first round of reporting for the story
But then once the series started and they heard how I'd known as being portrayed a new round of phone calls began
The Rumours themselves are nothing to dastardly nobody is saying I saw him do it or I
Proof
What is directly connected to the crime
There are a great many things I don't know about a non
And some of the things I was hearing we're giving me pause
Check them out as best I could
Every single one and some of them are so small that I initially was confused by the telling
Waiting for the punchline that it already slid by
Such as
He took a piece of my clothing
Piece of designer sportswear
Over explained climbing a wall
And then apologize profusely
Hi Sarah Koenig I'm going to confess something right now
I have done exactly the same thing
More than one side wager
On the other end of the scale was a story so incriminating
Well this one is true then we're done
Our story is over
Mini alcohol
This was the biggie and I work every angle I could discuss it out
I heard it second hand
That someone said something about at 9 at a party 15 years
I spent weeks trying to learn first the name and the location of that someone
Done trying to contact at someone and then finally driving several hours to question that someone in person
I nervously knock at the door nice guy comes out WeChat
He tells me what I've spent all these weeks and hours waiting for
He says I remember at 9
Nice kid
Remember he seemed sad when his girlfriend broke up
And so I promised him
I heard this
Is that true that anything else you want to tell me
The Galaxy
That's all you had for me
Can I have a file on my desk about this rumor and I just stamped it with my big cartoon stamp
Unsubstantiated
I cross it off the list
This one more rumor I'll tell you about in a minute
But first I want to talk about why relatively few people from the musk Community are willing to talk on tape
Or on the record about a 9
What I'm talking about
Here's a lie
Not his real name and this is also not his real voice
Why the secrecy
Play it on
He probably knows something how do we know he's not involved
Talking like that you're one of them I mean your supplier you're basically saying I'm sick coming to this
Irrational
I'm under 500
Ali another is told me that their Community is judgemental
Right and wrong is drummed into early and often
Adults judge kids Behavior which then gets reflected back onto their parents
This is certainly not unique to their community and the other thing that isn't unique is how close-knit it is
Information and gossip travels swiftly and you don't want to be the one who goes against the grain
Or said something that could hurt at 9 or his parents
No one wants to end up in hot water
I live in a small town I understand that
But what I haven't totally understood I think is how scared people were arrested
I got an anonymous text recently that said
Who attends the Baltimore
My father and I are good friends and have known each other for years
Anon story has always been an urban legend to us kids growing up in the Muslim Community
Clouded in mystery and used as a cautionary Tale
Some people did speak out on tape
I mean Robbie inside Chaudhary obviously dead and there are others too
A significant fraction of people including all who are scared
Police said his parents were especially protective like a 10 on the protective scale
After done was arrested they were frantic about his safety
His own life changed because of it
Are you serious that really happened
Cuz your mailbox was like at the end of the driveway or at the end
Attached to the wall of my
Really
McDonald's
It everyone just gets quiet
A bunch of people I talked to told me they feel guilty towards Adnan
They let him down
Because they let him astray
Or didn't protect him or didn't Mentor him or didn't show up enough a trial or didn't visit him in jail
Even when you're on the fence about as innocent said
Please tell him that I love him or please tell him I'm sorry
You should tell him yourself you can write to him you know
And then sometimes comes a pause
The reason
Said he wanted me to know this
About Anan
Atlanta
The name of the kind of kid who'd stand up when your parents came into the room at least said
At parties or events he be the first one to ask
How can I help you Auntie
I need help setting up those tables uncle
This was what I like
Disguise an anonymous
How to say
Normally I probably would enforce that on their face aren't connected to the crime at hand
But in this case I decided it was worthwhile because of where these rumors
Come from
I think these rumors are coming from a feeling that a handful of people have I've heard this turnabout for people people who knew it.
Growing up
Capable of committing this crime
I think they believed they saw things in his personality that they think I am not seeing
Namely that he's duplicitous
The term psychopath
Custodian sometimes
People told me he used his charm and his smarts to deflect suspicion or weasel out of things when he got caught
Pretty much what the judge said to him at a sentencing
Which brings me to the only rumor I heard that at least partly checked out
It was this
Adnan stole money
From the mosque
Donation money
Various versions of how this happened or could have happened
But from what I can tell the basic story is people who come to pray on Fridays and it's a lot of people many hundreds
Some of them put donation boxes
And that's what it done scam
Two people told me they saw him do it
One person told me he'd seen it several times
He wouldn't go on tape
But the other guy did
Every Friday
This is a guy I can't name whose voice was also changed
The explanation above
Because he was
Look upon like The Golden Child
Android
Collecting money
Organ donation boxes available around on Friday after prayer
You know he does
And nobody questions
You know good little Muslim kids
You you saw him actually take money
Noriel absolutely song empty
This guy is estimated that Adnan had stolen many thousands of dollars over time
Tens of thousands maybe $100,000
This sounded Fantastical to me so I checked with multiple Patel
He was president of the Islamic Society of Baltimore at the time
He said he's never heard of Adnan taking donation money but that it does happen from time to time
Someone stealing or trying to
There are people who take shoes yet it
My own brand new shoes were stolen
Twice he said that happened once in New York and once in Baltimore
But if it did take money he said there's no way it was a big amount
He's an average people donated about $2,500 at Friday prayers
Thousand dollars if it was a special occasion
He said keep the electricity and heat on
If they were even $100 short on any given week that have noticed
So sure maybe 20 bucks for 40 bucks here there but not hundreds
Out of the question
Anon says it's true
He did take donation money
21st ask him about it
He was unhappy
I'd ask him so many frankly insulting things
So many nosey and inappropriate questions and he's never given me push back
But this was the last straw
What does it have to do with the case you wanted to know
He's ever claimed that he's innocent of killing her because he's a perfect or even a good person
He said so why talk about this and why the double standard
I wasn't going to everyone else's closet and pulling out skeletons that made them look fat
What do I protect other people and call him out on everything
He's endured other stuff in my reporting that he didn't think was fair to him
You go for my savior to my executioner on it you know it just
But now he was sticking up from selfie set
You seem pissed
And hurt and I understood it
I'm innocent very uncomfortable thing for me to talk about something that I did
I've never denied it I've never I don't see I don't understand I just think it's really unfair to me
If this. If you don't want to talk about this that's your prerogative like I'm not going to force you to talk about if you don't want to talk about it
And this is the only thing I don't talk about
It has nothing to do with the case
Chicken called out on my stuff
Well I mean
Zen phone calls later and he told me his stealing story
It was during the summer maybe this summer before eighth grade he said
Joy like the Friday prayers
A lot of times it'll be one adult and he would get like four or five kids together
Hey look I want you guys to go around and collect
You know money from people Horst and Erica have a different days it was different ways
Who's usually anywhere from like four to five of us we don't have little boxes or something
And people would come and able to Bonnie and
Usually like it was
It was like thousands of dollars in cash
Like one
5 * 20
$1,500 in cash
I don't really remember who I'm not saying it wasn't saying it wasn't me
Yeah I just idea came up like a man we could take like 60 or $80
Go to the movies
Go to the mall
Airplane arcade
You like eating stuff like that
Eventually but you think we're like one or two of us
Would like pocket a $20 bill and another $20
And I mean
You know I mean it is nothing but I'm proud of it
You know I'm very ashamed of it you know I don't
I don't I don't say that we were kids to try to put it in contacts
How to make an excuse
Maybe I am right but it's just you know
What made you look made you realize what made you stop and what made you realize it was wrong
I mean I wish I could say that it was like you know some feeling over there or something or feeling them wrong but it wasn't me
Anon says he was caught red-handed by shamim
His mother
She said she found some money in his pants pocket and ask him where it came from and the truth came out
He said she was horrified
It was the classic I'm not angry I'm disappointed
More disappointed than she's ever been in him
Annonces back then he didn't think he was hurting anyone
They spent so much time at the mosque
Can I shovel snow and they help set up events and clean up
I told him it was akin to taking 20 bucks from the tale of the family store at the end of the night
He said the course as an adult he knows how wrong that is
Get it
Announce telling of the stealing episode is a much more boys-will-be-boys version than what I'd heard from other people
Who told me they saw in his actions something more malignant
I talked to from the mosque Community said
This was so low
To take the hard earned cache of hard-working people
At the mosque of all places
This is a terrible thing
Other people said
Mr Patel then president of the mosque was thoroughly unruffled by the whole thing
Dunkin Donuts
3 more or less
It certainly does not a murderer make
Person does something like this it's not even necessarily a sign of bad character
Didn't see how is connected to the crime
And also some people told me they'd shoplifted before they broken the rules
So people in Glass Houses man
And in the end these guys all set with most of an Old Friends Day
He didn't have it in him to kill someone
It wasn't in his DNA
To me this question is the hard center of a nonce case
Can you tell really
Can you tell if someone has a crime like this in him
I think most of us think if we know someone well we can tell
React as detectives all the time Gathering evidence
Certain scenes we remember or the look on someone's face or that thing he said when he got mad
And then we act as a judge
Character
It's just a human thing
Of course it's slippery because it's so subjective
One person's evidence of good character is another person's evidence of questionable character
Case in point
I heard from many people that Adnan was the opposite of violent
But he was someone who would take the heat out of 10 situations
I've never even seen him in a fight
I don't even see him mad at anybody
This is Atif Iqbal from the mosque
That's his real name and his real voice
Exactly
Anybody like me
And here like somebody told me that you said something about me and some other person
Or something and I went up there to confront him and he was like I don't know what you heard I didn't say anything like that
But you haven't said something like that ball blouses you know getting all Rowdy up and he just came and kissed me on my cheek
The Dodgers play
Diffuse me like completely like
I miss that he kissed you on your cheek
Beatrice Vio veggie like it just like completely like diffuse me like I couldn't even be angry anymore
So I mean that's why I like I just couldn't even fathom the thought of him
Kelly
I mean
Joe Somebody
Like I don't even know how to
Say it's just like you don't like his personality
Separatists that kiss on the cheek is a towel
It's the real at 9
Prefer that other guy who said Adnan stolen who thinks I might be guilty of a crime is in prison for
That same piece maker quality was something he brought up to me
As evidence that Adnan was full of s***
Halo taking out the tension out of a situation
It was ice breaker
Majority
Here's the Curious Thing though
The same people who tell me they think Adnan was capable of killing hey
Stealing from the moth with a great evil or that Adnan with a pathological liar
They also tell me to a man that Adnan was a great guy
Such a good guy
This is the same Anonymous person who thought Adana taken many thousands from the donation boxes
Dog friendly info
Going Father's Day
Spheal fake to you
You think a person can start of contain both those things inside their personality
I think it's
If you Corner anybody into a corner
And I don't know
Omostoday
Hundreds of
Killers I've evaluated
I've been pretty Ordinary People
This is Charles Ewing
He's a forensic psychologist and a lawyer
He teaches at the SUNY Buffalo Law School
He told me he's evaluated several thousand criminal defendant
And testified more than 700 trials as an expert witness
Mostly lately homicides committed by people in Intimate Relationships
And homicides committed by young people
You and your listen to about half the episodes of the show
Obviously he can't weigh in on a non psychological Health I'd be ridiculous
But I want him to find out what's a valid way to try to understand what's going on when someone kill someone else
What's the range of options here
He said most of the time he's doing Insanity evaluations
Evaluations for extreme emotional disturbance
Usually in cases where there's not a question of whether the defendant did it
More question of why
And again most of people he's evaluating a pretty ordinary
Some
AR
Extraordinary
Some serial killers some
Retailers
Some really awful
Psychopathic individuals
For the most part
People kill
Not in a premeditated way
They're not evil they're not sociopathic
Psychopathic
They killed
Because
Something happens
Pushes them over the edge
In other words murder isn't usually strictly speaking planned event
A lot of people who know it
They can't get their heads around the idea that an unplanned to kill hay
I hear it all the time
Here's his old Woodlawn classmate Peter Billingsley
I still I still the whole idea premeditation just doesn't fit
Trodden
No it doesn't fit it all
But
I don't know
The first one
Coasterra some plant
Matt is but I'm sure this was not a planned murder
That's Jane Efron who taught Hannah Dunne English at Woodlawn
Her father was a cop
Icon
By that because that destroys everything
That I feel about these kids so I absolutely
I think it was
Passion overdose of emotion
Of Love jealousy
Resentment
All of those things
It sneaks in on you
Dominate your thinking and you can't get away from it
But that's
Uncomfortable thinking
Premeditated murder
Can otherwise seemingly normal kid
Up and do something like this
Play something like this
Or even do it impulsively
Is snapping a thing people say that all the time also
Snap
People
Sometimes we lose
And when they lose it
It's not always
I've seen a lot of cases in which
People have
Over
A relatively short period
Time
Nurse
Feelings of
Rejection
Or
Anger
Or hostility
And they slowly
Risen
To the point
At which individual
Decides to kill somebody
Those feelings Zimmer
For a while
And
What is a thot
Maybe I should
Children's purse
I'm not going to kill this person
I want to kill this person
What if I did
And the person thinks about it
And then maybe confronts the other
The person who
Frustration V anger
And then
The victim
Her would-be victim
Says or does something
The triggers
Provokes
The ultimate killing
Looks looks
Premeditated
I'm not sure that really is premeditated in the sense that
We normally think of it
It doesn't have to
To be like
Sudden impulse to violence
So that was news to me
But there's a sort of liminal phase
A simmering contemplation
What if I kill this person
And that can take the place of actual cognizant planning that end up in the same result
Considered in my morici moments
Is weather
But doesn't know he did it
I'm not the only person is entertain that one
Here's an honest friend Laura
I mean I remember the cops on me sometimes they have murderers
Standing with a knife in their hand next to the body saying to them that they didn't do it because you're
Brain goes into the shock
And it shuts down
That's like what maybe
That happened
Maybe it was an accident maybe you got mad
7 to get mad
Maybe
Maybe he lost it for a moment
Yeah and it was an act
Apparently this is not as outlandish as it might sound
People can go into a dissociative state
Where
They're really
Psychologically not
Where they are physical
Probably half of the people
Have evaluated who killed
Other
Human beings
Have some degree of amnesia
For what they've done
Did you say have
Half the people
And it's
It's not total Amnesia usually although I've seen some people
Whoever completes
Amnesia
For killing
But
You can be partly
I don't really recall the details I don't recall doing this
Because literally like the memory isn't in there
Brain anymore or
Or it never was in their brain or
Yeah I don't think we know the mechanism
By which
This kind of
Denial or Amnesia or combination works but
In the cases that I've been involved in where people have had some kind of
Amnesia or partial Amnesia or denial
It doesn't last forever
It's it's very difficult
To maintain that cam
Sade
What I find is it overtime people do
Recover traces
Of what happened and
They know what happened
What about 15 people who has
Genuinely snapped
And who
Committed a homicide
And then
They realize what they've done
Any immediate reaction
For most people
His
Oh my God
Look what I've done
And what am I going to do about it
I got to figure out some way to cover this up
Do you think it's
Is there another scenario where are you
It starts out as a lie as assertive cognizant lie like I didn't do this had nothing to do with this
And then over time
You truly believe that lie like you view kind of
Erase
The fact that you're lying and it just
Becomes
The truth of it for you
I think that happens I haven't seen that happen and homicide cases but I certainly seen it happened
Ordinary wife
Less often in homicides
Yeah I haven't even seen that and it's probably just because
And in most homicide cases the evidence is pretty overwhelming
That
You did it
Off the top of my head I can think of five different people in the story who other people have told me they think are either
Pathological Liars are psychopaths
Russian trust anything they say
The term psychopath gets thrown around so easily
The kind of catch-all term for cold hearted and calculating killer
If it non did this and if you did it the way Jay tells it
He is so cold hearted
Tell the cops that announces to him
Motherfukers referring to like hugs and bugs and stuff
Think of hardcore
But he just killed a person with his bare hands
Lebanon said that
Does that mean the 15 years since has been this very very long con
What is calculating enough to only pretend to be the normal sounding person he is with me on the phone
A psychopath usually means a person who has little or no conscience
Is glib
You can't empathize or relate to other people's feelings
They can read other people very well
But they don't have genuine empathy
Another
Factor to be sure
Is
This
What's
Known in the profession is superficial charm
These are people who
Come across
Very smoothly
Effectively manipulate other people
And manipulate them without them knowing it very often
Now I'm running through my head
Everything you just said
And some of it maybe another stuff
I mean
It really does seem like an on
Is is like
Really
Functioning really well
Minister
Fine in prison like he's
Season 3
Adaptable and he's always had like a
Job with responsibilities and he's not cutting into he's not been
Disciplined really ever except for having a cell phone
In like doesn't appear to have any kind of antisocial
Behaviorism
Friends he's got he's maintained his relationships outside the prison with his family and With Friends
Certain friends
I mean is that
Something to taken that I should be taking into account
I think so
Certainly
Cuts against
Theory that he's a psychopath
Arteries
Some kind of
Pathological person
But it doesn't rule it out
And the fact is most psychopaths are killers
And most Killers aren't Psychopaths
There's a there's a very limited overlap between those two spheres
Finally I asked you why should I be influenced by the fact that has so consistently maintained his innocence all these years
His experience
People who are wrongfully convicted
Always maintained their innocence
Even when it hurts them like in sentencing or parole
On the other hand he said just cuz you said you didn't do it
In four decades
Doesn't mean you didn't do it
But just aren't any rules for
Here's what I take away from this conversation with Charles Ewing
I don't think that is a psychopath
I just don't
I think he has empathy I think he has real feelings
Because I've heard and seen him demonstrate empathy and emotion
Towards me and towards other people
He is able to imagine how someone else feels
Options it's a toss-up
State of Amnesia and denial and then supplanted that with actual lying
It's possible
Could've had simmering feelings of anger and resentment that then boiled over in a not quite by accident way
Could he be truly innocent
It's possible
He said he's often asked on the stand
How do you know this person isn't lying to you
What is the answer he said is always the same
I don't know
In the course of his career he's been fooled
A handful of people who are listening to the story
One thing they think makes a non look guilty is the way he talks about our brother doesn't talk about
Other people involved in the case
Especially J
But if you were really innocent we would hear him being matter
I know we talked about this
Why doesn't he sound more mad
But there's another factor I haven't mentioned
And that is as a defense attorneys explain to me
No good can come and harm can come
Attempting to contact or influence people on the outside for connected to his case
That's kind of inmate Behavior 101
Biggest what's a Cathy changed her story
Send me remember something exculpatory for Adnan
I'm in the state found out that Adnan had been writing to Kathy
Or threatening cat
He somehow
Talking smack about a podcast
By the state to challenge the validity of Kathy's new information
Anon is a smart guy he's been an inmate for 15 years he knows the deal
He also knows there's nothing he can do to change other people's minds about him
If a person genuinely doesn't think that I feel something
Put me in prison
Then
Me saying it
It really has no validity
In my eyes anyway
You know how do you think I did it
And if you think that I did it then
You can assume cuz I'm a normal
Unexpected
The monster
And they don't find that when x 8, expect
Or they don't find that
They don't know what to say
And the reality of it is I'm just a normal person
I know but I think actually
That's that's right but I think also what
People do is they put themselves immediately in your position and think what would I do
How would I be feeling how would I be asked if someone if I thought
You know someone had done me wrong and put me here and I would be screaming to the rooftops and they're not hearing you do that
System one
I mean it is really nothing to say if someone can't imagine how I feel this. There's no need for me
I mean it is what it is
I think it's a trap
To try to convince people
A few weeks ago after these rumors started surfacing I got a letter in the mail from a non
It was 18
Typed single-spaced pages
He gave me his reluctant permission to talk about it
His religion
His case how he's managed over the past 15 years
What's a good letter
Is it good writer
But it's song from pole to pole from distrust
Gratitude
Fusion
Anon is obviously aware of this podcast that it's out in the world
Negatale that my story had messed with his equilibrium
What is convicted of murder he said the biggest shock for him was that people thought he was capable of this hideous thing that people do
As I look back now he wrote I realized there were only three things I wanted after I was convicted
To stay close to my family
Prove my innocence
I just seen as a person again not a monster
The third one he says he's mad at
Inside prison
People here know me as a stand-up guy
Guards inmates
Staff has been around for 15 years I've seen me everyday
Recognize me as someone whose word can be trusted
I guess what I'm trying to say is that I was able to find a peace of mind in prison
But I lost at my trial
And now I come along as Robbie is best
Not his
And yank the store open again
To the outside world and to all its doubts about a nun's integrity
Stirring up the most painful possible questions
About whether he's a monster
It's his nightmare basically
Accused of manipulating everyone around him
Of course I had a sense of this feeling from him now and then
Over the years that we've been talkin
But in 40 hours of taped conversations
He was weighing every word
His goal was to keep it all business
Evaluate his case based on the evidence of loan
Not on his personality
I didn't want to do anything that could even remotely seem like I was trying to befriend you or Curry favor with you
I didn't want anyone to ever be able to accuse me of trying to ingratiate myself with you or manipulate you
SoundCloud
And having to do that
I had a rough year
My stepfather died in April then my father died two months later
And I knew that
Cuz I had to stick to what I know
Can you imagine what it's like to be afraid to show compassion to someone at a fear they won't believe you
I was so ashamed of that
And this second-guessing this monitoring of everything he says to me and therefore to the outside world
About anything really but especially about his case
He writes in his letter but it's crazy making
I'm always over-thinking analyzing what I say how it sounds and the fact that people always think I'm lying
All this thinking is to protect myself from being hurt
Not from being accused of his murder
But for being accused of being manipulative or lying
And I know it's crazy I know I'm paranoid but I can never shake it
Cuz no matter what I do or how careful I am it always comes back
I guess the only thing I could ask you to do is
If none of this makes any sense to you
Just read it again
Except this time please imagine that I really am innocent
And then maybe it'll make sense to you
At this point he wrote it doesn't matter to me how your story portrays me guilty or innocent
I just want it to be over
It will be
Next time
Final episode
Cereal
Cereals produced by Julie Schneider Dana chitosan me Emily Condon is our production and operations manager are glasses hereditary
Royal advisor
I didn't help today by Joel level researching fact-checking by Michelle Harris administrative support from least bergersen
Our score is by Mark Phillips who also mixed episode
Our theme song is by Nick thorburn Who provided additional scoring special thanks
Find our website horoscopos everything and Julie Farris Marianne Hamel Thomas mauriello
Chobani LabCorp forensic Outreach Productions detective Robert Sherry Thompson
Schneider Lisa scalpone Aaron hankin Jake Halpern
Serials production of This American Life and WBEZ Chicago