Support for serial comes from ATT
The number one smart home security provider
Offering everything from video doorbells
2 indoor and outdoor cameras
2 smart locks and lights
Control from the ADT app
Or the sound of your voice
Visit att.com podcast to learn more about how ADT can custom design and install your
Smart home system
Back by 24/7 40
Before we get on with episode 2 some news
A few days ago the Army announced that it will take Bo Bergdahl charges to court-martial
The trial basically
He's charged with two crimes
Desertion and something called misbehavior before the enemy
That second one it's not used very often
They carries the possibility of a life sentence
Which doesn't seem likely that would happen
I be so extreme
What does mean both could face some amount of prison time if he's convicted
The Army's decision to go to court-martial It's not that it's so surprising I mean this is always a strong possibility
Interested for a lot of people watching those case
It's been hard to handicap
All outward signs of pointed to an army that is of two minds about how to deal with what bow did
Whether to throw the book at
Or whether to say okay yes he screwed up in a huge way
The Taliban enough is enough
On the one hand the Army level pretty severe charges against Bo
But that in a military Hearing in September
The two-star general in charge of investigating those case a man named Kenneth doll
Which of the 371 page statement from Beau who assemble the 22 person team who coordinated with twins
24 government agencies interview 56 people
He said he believed that boat told him the truth about why he did what he did
The boat was remorseful
Taobao recognizes quotes
That he was young and naive and inexperienced unquote
When asked on the stand where he thought they should go to jail
Major General doll said quote I think it would be inappropriate on quote
Likewise the officer in charge of that hearing Lieutenant Colonel mark visger
In his report on what to do about the charges
Apparently recommended a lesser proceeding called a special court-martial
More like a misdemeanor trial
He also recommended
No confinement
In response to which Senator John McCain arguably our country's most powerful former poww he was held for 5
Tigers during the Vietnam war
McCain told a Boston Globe reporter that if Beau got no punishment he told a congressional hearing to look into Bird dolls
Case
And then this week the announcement that the Army will pursue the charges in the most serious way possible
A general court-martial
It's almost as if those military officials who come into close contact with bow
Are ready to forgive him
Well the Army as an institution continues to be furious
Few months ago filmmaker Mark Ball was talking about on the phone
And they were discussing the possibility of a plea deal
The weather Bellwood taken offer
First one to three years in prison in exchange for pleading guilty
I didn't think you would
Even though the basic facts of the case aren't in dispute
Admits he walked away from his post of his own volition
I told Mark he wear that if he took some plea offer he'd never get to explain himself
And people would continue to hate him
And it's true a lot of people hate him
Without ever fully understanding his reasons for doing what he did
That was his fear
After all of this
It end up misunderstood
Exhausted as I am
Scary as it is going through all of it
I made it through last
Ears
Lose whatever it is
They keep me going
Yeah
I can respect that I mean I think that
Get that up now what I must be like
I'm almost make the whole thing playlist
Basically turn it on but really stupid
From This American Life and WBEZ Chicago its serial one story told week by week
I'm Sarah Koenig
Good evening everyone or nearly the release of American servicemen after 5 years
Sources tell NBC that Bergdahl vanished under mysterious circumstances
Hero or deserter that the soldiers are engaging in political smear campaign by raising
Soldiers save our sons would be alive if Bergdahl had not gone missing from this post in the old days
Very last thing is
Just
I'm a prisoner
I want to go home
Bring me home
Please
Me home
I was talking on the phone recently to this Taliban fighter
I'm calling him we should keep her mind not his real name
You told me
But when they got Bowe Bergdahl when they caught him the Taliban knew they had scored
Mom said quotes
A Dead Soldier is worth nothing but he was captured alive
And he was like a Golden Chicken on quote
In the weeks and years really following both capture during the Tactical push and pull between the insurgents in the u.s. force
Each side would ask itself over and over
What is bow Worth to us
What is bulworth to our enemy
How much will we get
How much will you sacrifice
Remind describe one raid by US forces not long after bow disappeared
He said something like 15 Taliban were killed
American Special Operations Commander I spoke to describe the similar raid
15 enemy killed
I asked your mom through an interpreter who is sitting next to me
Was it worth it
15 of your guys in one raid
Virgo
Audio
Thousand individuals
Saying that
And he was work maybe more than 5000 individual
Exactly how did the Taliban get bow in the first place
And what did they do with him once they realized who he was
Merkel looked into this to knows his company page 1
I got in touch with a guy named Sammy yousufzai
Sammy's Afghan he's a reporter very brave reporter he's based in Islamabad but he travels around
For his work covering the war in Afghanistan. For Newsweek and other Publications
About a year-and-a-half ago page1 hired Sammy
Interview whomever he could and report back when he found and he did he didn't record these interviews on tape but Sammy fan
Found about a half-dozen people who said that either been part of the kidnapping or had interacted with bow while he was being held
What are the first people Sammy found was this guy named halal
Law is a Taliban fighter
Part of a group that was running missions in patica Province where most Battalion was based
All told Sammy is at the Taliban and gotten word from the local people in the area that sometimes a western or was coming
Close to the Village taking photos
And also that they'd seen a soldier sitting on top of a hill near us checkpoint
So alone if you guys had come to the Village to see if it was true and if it was to work out a plan to grab him
Kidnapping foreigners journalist Aid workers missionaries
This is big business for the Taliban at the time
And still is
I interviewed Sammy about what Halal told him
According to Halal
They just got into this Village to Mastin Factory Bose unit was Manning an outpost
They're taking a rest at the Moss
At that time so don't leave somebody shouted and said there is a
55 notice
And a coochie tents
Foreigner in a coochie tent
Coochie is a word for Nomads they keep flocks of animals and live in these big tents
In summer they open up the size of the tent
Fresh air
And
He's asking about Kabul or asking about please
And the Halal said you were an expected.
I know to what is this and then
He said okay let's go and find out
So how long is guys go to this coochie 10
They dropped on their motorbikes and see this Foreigner
Sammy tells it from hello
Perspective
And we told him that's we are please I mean
American normally working with the local militia which is not necessarily to be wear uniform
Right
And you told in police and he he look at us and then he jumped
Behind our bike
So is hello saying that we said oh we're local police
Set it come with us or whatever and Bergdahl seem to believe that and think he was maybe in safe hands
Bakuchiol told him that this guy you don't understand his language versus asking about
Police in Kabul was asking for something else or something or
And that's why they came and he said he was
And now why dress and sandals and he had something in his
Pocket he said there was a pistol
Knife or something
I don't know really exactly okay
Does coochie tensing comes up in various ways
The Taliban say either but walked into a couch eaten or near a 10
The Americans got some Intel the time to the same effect
And that Nomads tipped off the Taliban
For his part Bo says he was never in a coochie time
He says he was out in the open when armed man wrote up on motorcycles and grabbed him
This is one of those discrepancies and there will be others
Where I feel like it's worth mentioning
Because if both did walk into a Gucci tennis Halala saying
Well that makes his own explanation sound less solid
Maybe he wasn't really trying to cause a dust one by running from Opie Mastiff ashiana
Maybe he was simply deserting
But I also can't tell how much weight I should really give this coochie tent story
Because
The Taliban bring up all kinds of her
Like the bow is in the village to meet up with a woman
He was looking for drugs
Rumors pretty much anyone who's ever met Beau can easily dismiss
And maybe the truth is somewhere in between
It's possible bow was near
Kuji cam
And just didn't know it
And that the Nomad saw him out in the open and alerted the Taliban
But was never the wiser
Probably we're not going to get to the bottom of it
Because we can't fact check the stories these guys told Sammy we can't be sure everything they told him is true
And the details of what happened do shift around depending on who Sammy's talking to
Which isn't unusual in any kind of reporting
What I can say is that the overall chain of events
The major plot points that the Taliban describe
Are pretty consistent person to person
And Sammy's interviews with these guys they don't seem that interested in pinning down exactly how both ended up in or near us
More what they want to talk about
Is how incredible it was that it happened at all
Doraemon and hello to everyone involved this is just
Kikuchi's
Nomad
People they consider unsophisticated and uneducated
Snag this Westerner
And not just any Westerner but an American
An enemy of the Koran of the pashtun people
And not just any American
Soldier
Reminder the whole thing the way they got him and just being up close with your adversary like that
It was one of those lifetime strange experiences
And it came to into a letter
Akai CD so easily
Time in Afghanistan
Amongst all the
Have provinces in the district
Review of blessed
We were blessed
Sammy's interviews they use his expression
They call BOA ready-made loaf
A gift from God
I felt so lucky that both came to them
Deval the desert joints in all the provinces in all of Afghanistan
He walked into their
LOL told Sammy that bow fought at first
But they subdued him
One of their bikes they took him back to the mosque
Boaz again resisting throwing punches
Or maybe his captors were beating him up
Clear
Is it doctor
Garlic butter jar was kind of resisting and start like a
Not giving up and he was a good
Punching Garcinia vs boxer kind of guy
N71 Pakistani Taliban
He came close to him and he sit down on his knees and
And suddenly you know Barbie doll kitchen with his repeater
Casa speech was open and we want to start joking with a real pain. Let's even this guy know you are
Pakistani
I'm laughing here is if I get the joke
I don't
And some of these conversations the Taliban describe Bo a strong and aggressive
Other times he's meat
Empathetic
The adjectives the apply to this method
Captive
Changing to suit the
Scene
I'll tell Sammy that for them for these coochies would maybe never been up close with a western before maybe not even with an n
Non-muslim
Exotic
Hello said he was like an animal captured by kids
His pale skin was weird
Spoke was weird
His eyes were blue which Sammy says it's somewhat suspicious in Afghanistan there's a saying that you should keep away from blue-eyed
People
Animas Colossus people had gathered to discuss what to do with them
I sent his notes from his interviews
Is one part Halal talks about how bow was sitting in a dark corner of the mosque
And another Taliban fighter said to him quote
You look like a small cat baby with shining blue eyes
I think this is something
Explaining somebody weakness
But I think
I think he said there was a he was very kind of weak
He was not like a
Big Americans
Ian Wallach
The big guy heavy Americans
They thought he was like a week Americans
Yeah I'm just looking in a note that you wrote that says Bergdahl was weak and I think brainless
Yeah yeah what does he mean by that was the stupid that's why he entertained their hands
Okay somebody coming and jumping anywhere bike
Was he scared I did he say
When he was crying sometime he was
Smiling and without what's happened to this guy but X he was fired into anybody giving water it was not.
Drinking
He said he was like a Buddha Buddha Buddha Afghanistan Bamiyan Buddha statue
So I guess at Sunoco
What's the weather's been going out on him
Are we thought he's drunk
Yeah apparently deep
I mean did you want me to watch or somewhere you know to release his
Drunk messaged Authority was John Cabot
She was not drunk
I'll also Sammy that to be fair he never actually seen a drunk person
Apparently they tend to think all westerners are drunk
Do I have to be extremely careful with my
Yeah
That's bow talking to Mark on the phone
Of course
Yes I was scared
Only rational
Be scared
When the Taliban guys explain to Sami how they kidnapped bow
It kind of wax romantic sometimes or crack jokes
There's a swashbuckling quality to Sammy's notes from his interviews
But then you remember Bo himself
Is completely at their Mercy
Terrified
For excellent reason
Is in the hands of people who conduct public executions
Mass beheadings
And often film them for propaganda
Movies you watched doesn't matter how long your Martial Art fighter whatever
You have to be realistic when your face
Shell
Yeah
They have no
Hesitation
Yeah
Kill you
Amusement of being
Ghostbuster was one guy in the Convoy who spoke a little English
And he has spoke questions
Was Bo a bit Commander with an intelligence officer
You said no
You said no I'm not
No I'm not
Did you tell did you explain to them while you were out there
Yeah
Is more suitable for the situation
And what did you say
Commando
Going through
I'm trying to get guys who barely speak English understand what I'm saying
Because they were
Disrespectful
So I came up with rude and they sing understand
Moses his memories from that time or sort of thin
In large part because he says he was blindfolded
It was focused on what was happening to him minute-to-minute
Trying to comprehend his circumstances
How you could possibly reverse them
They rode me around from a couple different places
Funny
It got me to
Small village
You pull me off this
Off the motorcycle
Stop being out on the ground then
Older guys
Came up I guess
She doesn't look like a younger brother is like younger buddy or something like that
Yeah it is cell phone on me like taking a video of me and
His body was like
Scary sitting off to sign you like you know
American
And I just shook my head
And then he's fattening
And then I said that a few times all they wanted
Again
Well after they're done then they put the blindfold back on in a throw blanket over my head
And then
Safe
I don't know where that went but then like little kids started throwing rocks at me
Send up
Kind of pretended there like Flinch from
On the Rocks hitting head which kind of loud me to shift my weight
Sounds like trying to
Get my hands from behind my back and pull them around
It so I could get them in front of me
That didn't work
So then go try to lean forward so he could use his knee to move
The cloth off of his face
I kinda got it to point where
Seems like half off my left eye
Almost
May I start a blanket on my head
Nobody was really stopping and I didn't hear any voices I just like you
This is the best day
That is probably going to get so I just
Set up
Colton
I didn't get more than maybe 20 or 30 feet before he was tackled
I want felt like the entire Village
I was day one of his captivity
Buy 2009 and Afghanistan the US forces and the Taliban have been fighting for 7 years
In all that time there's never been a situation like this
American Soldier captured
It was a new kind of crisis
Eastside also knew who they were dealing with
They could anticipate what each other's moves would be
In his first few days bus knew that whoever had but would be moving him constantly
Cuz the longer you stay in one place the more likely you are to get caught
They also knew that the Taliban goal would be to get BO2 a hideout in the tribal region of Western Pakistan
Because Pakistan is like home base
Or to put it in Tom and Jerry terms
Pakistan is a hole in the baseboard where Tom cannot go
Pakistan is a Sovereign Nation are reported Ally we are not at war with Pakistan
Pakistan we can't do much about it
In Afghanistan US forces can go anywhere they want can do almost anything they want
Pakistan is much much harder for the US military to operate
Here's the other thing that happens once bogus to Pakistan
She becomes much more valuable
Because his captors don't have to get rid of him in a hurry
They can take their sweet time
Making the deal they want to make
Of course the Taliban knew that the US knew they had for Pakistan
The Taliban did the opposite
Instead of heading straight East to the Pakistan border
The Taliban guy Sammy talk to you said
They first took Bo West
The ghazni province
When was Akira mindless
Yeah, heading meal that should move in contact with Ramon
Earlier for page one
For this interview Sammy had a car pick Ramon up and they talk to me on a burner cell phone from inside the car
Which is parked in a residential neighborhood known to be fairly safe
Yeah
The call dropped about a half-dozen times during our interview
Michigan Rahman told me by the time bird dog came to him the plan was already set
Italian Commander named Kyrie Ismael sulaimon.
Taken charge of bow
And arrange to deliver him to a group known as a haqqani network
In Pakistan
In the meantime we should give her mom's orders were to
Keep both alive and out of sight for a couple of days and nights
Until the pressure on the border East a little and they could sneak bow across
By the time Ramon took charge of the motorcycle Convoy about eight people he said
Was obvious to the Taliban that US forces for pouring into Eastern Afghanistan to search for Bo
Endocrine surgeon else who that is playing today
And that's that was a reason you know we were moving around and I would buy hours
Changing location and we were left
Even though I'm never changing
Barbie dolls dress and maybe would have even if we were changing our address
FanDuel
At one point a we came
Hey Anna close contact with American Ground Forces by 500 while bulldog
Was with us
Halal told Sammy that at one point his Convoy had come within a kilometer of fob sharana or bozone.
Italian was based
But even if bowhead wanted to scream or make a commotion he couldn't have
His hands were tied
Add a large cloth wrapped around his head
Partly to disguise them but probably just to keep the dust off his face
They all wear them against the Dust
These were probably the most stressful two days of any Mission he'd ever done
Korea smile stayed in constant contact with his guy in Pakistan from the haqqani network
Mom said they used fake names and locations of the walkie talkies to confuse the Americans
That US forces tracked him anyway
Attleboro occasions
Accu we stayed in at my location
And then there were three hours later
American forces
Team and add to that place to that house and search that has
By this time of course word has spread all over the region that a US Soldier had gone missing
The military air drop leaflets saying quote
One of our American guests is missing and give a phone number to call
Another one handed out about two weeks after bow disappeared was less gentle
It should arm Western forces kicking in a door
News report translator the text as quote if you do not free the American Soldier you will be targeted
The Army claimed the leaflets
Hunted not targeted
Which actually sounds scarier to me
They also distributed chocolate
Sami Yusuf say interviewed some of the people who lived in or near mustache run at the time and they remember the Chaka
Wrapped in shiny paper
They also remember helicopter
There's all over the place
And that the Americans were saying bergdahl's name
Or at least a word that had a bee sound in it
Volkner Mobil
Yogakaraka
The people Sammy talk to you said they'd heard the missing Soldier had been wandering around drunk when the Taliban grab them
Just as hell all hits
Suspected does a common rumor that but was drunk
Or that he's gone to a holy site or that he tried to fight off the Taliban with karate
In classified US military Communications released to the public by WikiLeaks
There's all this chatter on the ground that first week after but went missing
On July 1st 2009 the day after Bo disappears
An llvi traffic report
Lvi stands for low-level voice intercept
Technology we use to eavesdrop on any voice or data Communications
Picks up this conversation
Quote
Is that true that they captured an american guy
Yes they did
He's alive
There's no way he can go
LOL
After former soldier who regularly read such messages
What LOL means in this context
And he said the only meaning that seems plausible to him was
Laugh out loud
Then a few hours later there's this intercept
We were attacking a post
He was sitting taking expletive and had no gun with him
He was taking expletive
Is not clean his butt yet
I think he's a big shot
That's why they're looking for him on quote
Mujahid Rahman of course understood bow was a US Soldier
But he didn't know precisely what kind
He said the intensity of the surge did suggest bow with a big shot
Why would they put all that effort and money into looking for him if he wasn't important
Ramon said he'd heard foreign soldiers were sometimes trained in martial arts
At first he and his men were very careful around their prisoner
But pretty soon Ramon says his main impression of boat was that he was just really scared
Sleep
And then because
He was thinking that what type of people are
We might be
And now what are we going to do with him or we going to
Hannah Callahan
And then we'll be going to behead him
How what are we going to do with him so that was his situation he was very scared in that we
You can confuse
Ramon said he didn't feel sorry for bow
I didn't think of him as innocent
From his point of view but was like all US soldiers
He traveled Halfway Around the World voluntarily
Turn day their country and kill Muslims
Remind most of the guys Sandy interviewed they also talked about how bow is there gas
How Humane they were with him
Jarring to hear
Maintain your guest to the back of a motorcycle against his will doesn't sound like great host Behavior
Explain to me they're not being ironic
Pashtun culture a guest is always treated with generosity and respect
And so the fact that Bo was labeled a guest in the situation
Made it clear to the lower down guys
Is under Korea Smiles command that they're not allowed to kill him
Or even beat the crap out of
Which reminds that was a real concern that some Al Qaeda or Taliban fighters
Especially if they had family members killed by Americans
Might try to kill Bo
Or the kidnapping for themselves
One of the lvi messages from July 1st the day after the last trades
Unidentified male says
Cut the head off
Remind himself
I've been a prisoner of The Americans
He said he was held at Bagram for about 2 years
And he said he made sure to treat bow better than he been treated
Quote someone who's in your custody he said
You treat him nicely
Unquote
I want Point Ramon says they stop the Convoy and what he calls a wine field
Like a grape Orchard
They gone there to hide from us helicopter
And while they were there they tried to help bow out
To make him feel better
I just threw boost his morale into
A cheating man
We stopped at this time
We did this
A little
Traditional dancing
Mohican
New start eating game
Benetton is an Afghan dance where typically there's a drum and you move in a circle and unison
So apparently they did one for this frightened American soldier in a grape Orchard
Did it work did it boost his morale and get him to eat
New singer that fight a wolf
Singapore dollar
No I did not have that did not help at all
Even
And have an adverse effect on him because
He did not know
Why we were doing that
Grape Orchard
That's bow
Who says he has no memory of this event
Please never seen an Italian
Set a video of the Taliban show too much later
Kenneth wolf was command sergeant major of the five-oh-first back window disappeared battalions highest-ranked
Commissioned officer
He said it first he thought they'd find bow
And I told the colonel I said you know what
I'm going to stick around here for a few days
Because
If we find him
I want to be on there
Helicopter that picks him up
And he was like why not
They're going to whip his ass
Meaning boughs fellow soldiers
I'm going to whip his ass
What was it wrong to worry about that
If we would have found them
I think a lot of us would have shot him
That tells you nothing
That's Darrell Hanson when a bone spur
14 minutes
I truly say that with
Sincerity that
I we had that much hate toward
We
Aided
Absolutely hated him
Does Mark McCrory
A specialist in the five-oh-first
But a different company from bow
Was like well we see him he's not going to last you know
Like seriously or just kind of blustery
Like I'm really pissed
Or oil you really think like
Yeah
You do
Well
I mean I don't know what kind of light that shut does not like Jets on us but he was one of those things where
The conversation had come up
I found this shocking and disturbing
But some of these guys were saying they might have killed though if they'd found them
But now after interviewing more than a dozen soldiers
I still don't sympathize with running
Kill him
But I do understand why their anger was so extreme
I got it
The dust one search and Recovery operations lasted
Officially for 45 days
Some people can't and it went on even longer
Are the most frantic time the soldier said was those first few weeks
They told me to search for both started in the immediate vicinity of where he went missing from opms in eastern Afghanistan
Right away at 9 man foot patrol headed out from the Opie
For the boys school in Melaka
Lieutenant JP Billings bows with cheerleader
So they came across a boy who told Billings yes he had seen an American in a field that morning
And he gave a specific time 6:02 a.m.
Because of his sleeve to show is Casio watch
It's a boy saying that scene in American low crawling on the ground
Or nearly fainting from dehydration
Couple of ports noted that they were also giving out candy to the kids
In one instance the kid got some Pop-Tarts
Which is notable
An army report on beau's disappearance suggests maybe it was our initial search maybe even this first Patrol
But led t'beaux's capture
But the soldiers handing out candy and asking these questions tip the kids off
And ultimately the adults
And then the Taliban
An American was missing
And so they went out looking for him and grabbed him
Which supports what Beau says that the Taliban rode right up to him on motorbike
Who says he hadn't told anyone what he plan to do
So no one in his unit or is
Battalion has any idea why he left
How could they
Only have to go on is whatever early Intel is coming in
I remember where I heard it from but I
Remember hearing that
He was in the town asking if people
Spoke English
And then that's where he
Was now
That's Austin Lanford another of those which inmates
A bunch of people I spoke to remember a report like this coming over the transom
I think they probably got it
In the Wikileaks release from the day but went missing there's an entry saying they picked up lovi traffic indicating quote
Did an American Soldier is talking and is looking for someone who speaks English
American Soldier has camera unquote
Which country is an image of both seeking contact or maybe help
Several people who know how military Intel Works told me these llvi reports can be tricky
The quick translations of over her chatter
Nuance is lost
Mistranslations are not uncommon
So for what it's
The search for boat was enormous
By the late afternoon of June 30th 2009 and had ballooned
Weirdos out that quote all operations will cease until missing Soldier is found
All assets will be focused on the dust one situation and sustainment operations unquote
Search all of PepsiCo
Province and neighboring pitea Province to
I need to Cosmoprof
Suncoast
Thousands of square miles
Anything they needed to make it happen they got
Planes helicopters drones interpreters elite units
Special Forces
Hundreds of people stopped what they were doing
Even if your job was to look for Osama bin Laden
Now
You're going to look for the best one
There was snapping into action because of a basic ground-floor principle of the army
You do not leave anyone out there in a war zone
The military knew that the
The first 24 to 48 hours would be the most critical. If they're going to find him
Based on some fancy until they understood pretty quickly that bow him and captured
And I knew whoever had him would be on the move and therefore talking on radios our phones the whole time trying to figure out their own
30 intercept that chatter you can maybe geolocate or bow might be
Battalion Commander Quest as much signals intelligence as it can get
Intercourse needs more soldiers to check out all that Intel
Five more platoons join this
An eight more platoons the entire Brigade gets pulled in
When Commander told me was like a mini surge
LIRR operation
Beltempo went
Some sort of
Casual
Presence Patrol
Driving around handing out stuff
Cordoning IDs Tilley OD came out
This is John Thurman
He was in Blackfoot company
Bose company
Different at 10
I mean nonce
Stop it was Round the Clock
Webe
Chicken indoors 1 minute setting up a blocking position and searching every single car
An hour later
A blocking position was basically a roadblock
Official mission in Afghanistan in 2009 was counterinsurgency
Coin for short
American forces were supposed to be containing the insurgents but also training Atkins
Security Forces
There was supposed to be engaging the local
Getting their trust
Improving infrastructure
All that pretty much stopped now
Here's Mark McCrory
Sure there had been fights that have been going on but
They weren't fights that we were picking
The bad guys win
Would come to Austin
Where is this was us going out every night
Looking for a guy smashed down the door
We were just looking and looking and looking
Jon Foreman again
I mean towns
I don't even know if these towns
Scene Americans
Ever
Okay now we're going to fly you into this Bedouin Village and you're going to you're going to go check every single building a room and end
Check all the woman's face
Just to make sure
That they're not
Hiding him in women's clothes
That's been Evans a specialist from Charlie Company
He said there'd been in tell that they dress bow is a woman
Wichita imposes a did
And so we you know when into this house
And then whenever you go into a house to do a search
All the women would typically huddle into one corner together and normally we wouldn't pay them any mind
Does just leave them a B&O
But the but at that point we can had to walk over and I had to I mimic
You know removing your Veil
Remove your bail so we can
Can see this kind of stuff
Making women lift their veils are kicking in doors
Doesn't exactly endear you to local populace
But didn't have time to worry about that right now
Any little fragment of actionable intelligence
They're moving him in a white truck they're heading over to someone at this location
Didn't have the luxury to ignore any of it
You can see on paper in those Wikileaks releases all the scrambling that was going on those first few days
June 30th 2009 the table left
Update 140 tab has Intel that Taliban is planning to move the u.s. pack
Paxton's personal passenger
Theguardian
Next day July 1st update
Delaware 36 reports they have received Intel that the body of the missing US soldier is due east of their current position
July 4th update spot report missing US soldier was last seen in a village at grid location VB 611
N818
A bag was covering his head and he was wearing dark khaki apparel
And so on
Day after day
Here's Mark McCoy
Apparently at one point
These guys
Said they intercepted a phone call
Where
Is one member of the Taliban speech to another and they said hey the Americans are right out
Side
And we've got this guy with us and so it like that goes all trickles all the way up and then all the way back down everybody freeze
Oh but you got you don't stay where you are
Set out an outer cordon and search wherever everybody is
But by the time
Information and traveled all the way up
Back down it was already
Despite the massive resources at their disposal the Americans were at a certain disadvantage in that landscape
Because any movement of US forces
Giant armored trucks and helicopters whatever
Makes a lot of noise
Kicks up a lot of dust
Taliban could be more nimble
Screwing around on small roads or pass off and on motorcycles
As soon as they saw her that the enemy was coming their way like we were charging
Pounds
Running out of our trucks like he's in here we're running to this clot that's Darrell Hanson again
A clot is a kind of compound
Going in with Guns by the fact I'll never forget we ran into
And as we're running in this freaking cow has a baby like right next to me
Outcome you scared the hell out of the cow and I just had it
So yeah it was it was very intense yeah
Just you know we're always seemed like one one one day behind where is that
The Americans were certainly on the right track
The Battalion leadership met with a local Afghan leader
Reported that Bill had been turned over to the local Taliban leader
Qari Ismail
Just like a little Sammy
Pretty sure those Taliban guys would turnbow over to the haqqanis and pack
Stan
In North waziristan to be precise
It also got an Intel that Bo might be in ghazni
Just like mujahid Rahman said
In fact your mom told me that a few days after he returned from delivering go to Pakistan
He got rolled up by The Americans
Detained
Questions about Bo
Ramon said everyone's getting questioned about though people from down south in Kandahar in from out west in herat
I sure the US had in front of them the very man who had shepherded bow to the haqqanis
Is Ramon told them
I have not seen this person and I don't know who this person and I haven't heard
So that was a lie
Add apply all the time to the Americans
Pulling into towns you're unfamiliar with
Based on single Source intelligence or conflicting intelligence
Almost no time to prepare your team for what's awaiting them
It's risky
Any more typical operation you mitigate the danger maximize the chance for success
By doing everything you can in advance to do what's called shape the battlefield
He might take a few days to plan and prepare
Now commanders were lucky if they got a few hours
Sometimes they felt like they were winging it
Special Operations Commander told me his team when I'm more than 50 missions looking for Bo
How many of those were during the day rather than at night when his guys have the advantage
Quote we don't work in the day
He said
Major Mike Waltz
Was commander of a special forces company
He's in charge of 7 Green Beret and one Navy SEAL Team
He took over the command on June 30th
Same-day bow left
Well infantry soldiers were out searching cars are going house-to-house in villages
What's his teams were conducting raids
Usually at night
Targeting specific compounds or houses where they hadn't elbow either was or had been
Any shred of evidence
That burger had been there with
We thought he was there
A sighting
It wasn't really vetted
It wasn't buttressed by other types of reporting there was there was just no time to check on it we just went
And I can't emphasize
I can't overemphasize how dangerous that is
1 sisters one mission that still freaks him out
His man went to ghazni
He says most of his missions were ordered in ghazni
And it had information that a young white male surrounded by Fighters have been seen in particular compound that day
So as fast as they could they got the helicopters together they heading out there
What time is it
Substantiate anything
They arrived and walk into the compound
Define the whole thing is booby trap
The team went in and looked up and saw the ceiling lined with C4
And then there was also a car bomb
With with the trunk
Packed with explosives sitting in the middle of the compound
Now by the grace of God
They evacuated before the thing to go off and it never did but I would have easily lost 20 to 30
American Green Berets that night had that thing go off and it quickly became very apparent to us that the Taliban new
And our sources began telling us
That the Taliban and the haqqani network knew that we were pulling out all the stops
To find him
And we're feeding false information into our informant Networks
All right
You got the most advanced military in the world
All this effort all this expertise and Technology are trying to find one person
Did you pull out all the stops just to get one soldier back
That's really something
Then they can't find it
And I'd only that in some instances there being played by the enemy
Learning to trap
What is going on
I don't quite understand if he should be impressed by this operation or dismayed
Jason Dempsey to answer this question for me
At the time bow disappeared Jason was a major in the 10th Mountain division
An operations officer
He planned military operations
Battalion base in logar province
Just north of pek Tikka and bacteria
I've already Jason a couple of times now and what I've learned is that he's very smart
Mercante
Stop fidgeting
Can't sit still
Ostensibly conducting counterinsurgency
Forgot the washing dishes
Jason's got a PhD and is taught at West Point
Centaurs in both Iraq and Afghanistan
And it's not a lot about what we did and didn't accomplish and I've got us
His knots
Surprised we didn't find Bo
When I think about what was happening I just have this image of
Like this
This big
Machine
That's like moving around in this region in Afghanistan and there's just like a mouse
Running through the legs on Star Wars
Comes with his little thing and he's just like type of the legs and falls over I mean I know that's not fair but but
True it's a great analogy right you got it
This big lumbering machine moving through
So I can destroy anything face on butt
It can't get it has no idea on a granular level
What's below it
Json says what's down there on the ground or towns we don't understand
Where regular people and government officials and the Taliban are impossibly in mashed
We're civilians might hate the Taliban but they might hit the Karzai government even more
So it's not clear at all that the u.s. is the team to root for
Help
It's not as simple as these people are loyal to our side and those people are loyal to their side
It's fluid
At that time and that part of Afghanistan we just didn't understand incredibly complicated politics of these town
Yeah we we pkin Target or track
Individual network but we never really wrabel the tie-in okay Which towns and Villages and
People who know their relatives who are
Happy to give them
Safe passage or
I can walk through usually even after even after 7 years
Of War at this
When we don't know we don't we don't know the networks
Well enough
No remember
When you say 7 years of war
It means we rotated
2000 dudes through the air
Every 7 to 12
Where there is no institutional knowledge
The US military in Afghanistan
Nearly nun
We never were there long enough
Actually get engaged within the supplies unfortunately after 2010 as well
We've never had anybody
Are we engaged
At all I was asking
Jason said that's the whole thing right there
The spider web of connections we never could untangle
We come into Afghanistan in 2001 and ousted the Taliban
We did a pretty good job of that through 2003
Then afterwards
Jason said our mission languished
And the Taliban use the intervening years to refresh and regroup
To learn how we operate how we track them
And now they were pushing back into the country in a big way
And exactly this region
Betty kapadia ghost
Right where bow goes missing
That's what the soldiers of the five-oh-first were up against
They were total Outsiders looking for their guy
And knowing their chances of finding him where diminishing everyday that passed
Clint Baker commander of the 1st
Italian of the five-oh-first
Said it was as high-risk in operation as he's ever had
In part because there was no clear endpoint
Any military hearing he testified
And I mean frankly I felt a bit of a loss on you know what to do
My entire time in the Army I can't think of a time where I felt that kind of adversity
Just. And really did not
You know I wasn't able to overcome it and quote
The relentlessness was what was so crushing
Is John Thurman
Darrell Hanson
They got to the point where
Sleep I mean
Sort of became
A distant reality
Twenty-four hours a day 7 days a week nose
Sleep no nothing
Ucae just ran out of juice who all the guys are just miserable and
It's just I like how on Earth you know
Of course Afghanistan was dangerous and conditions were rough before bowl last also
But now because operation Tempo was roughly doubled or even tripled in some cases
There's just more contact with the danger
Blackfoot 3rd platoon for instance hit 3 IEDs in one day
Major silvino silvino testified that the battalions mrap
Does huge armored trucks that are built to sustain IED explosion
But about 80% of them or damaged during the search.
A half a damage was caused by iuds
Therefore mine rollers all destroyed
Those numbers are one way to quantify the danger and the damage
Crystal Reckoning of the consequences including the enormous question of whether people were wounded or died looking for bow
Become publicly much later
After Bill came home
I saw some pictures Darryl Jansen took from that time
One shows him and another guy standing next to a carcass on a spit
Is that a goat
Yes that's a ghost
What was going on in that picture
What's going on is a retired of MREs
So they buy goat off of local farmer have some meat that wasn't Vacuum Pack
Some of these units couldn't go back to their fobs for what's called refit where you clean and resupply Equipment a shower you get a hot meal
4 weeks on end 2nd platoon Splatoon
They got sent out for 19 days straight
That's outside the wire living in truck
Astana ground
For nearly three weeks
Doing non-stop missions
Another
Charlie Company listen out for 37 days straight
You got all your gear on full battle rattle that weighs between 60 and 100 pounds depending on what kind of weapon your
Carrying or whether your radio operator who has two extra batteries
Might be 90 during the day or a hundred degrees
Tonight the temperature might drop by such a 30
Peter cedeno said in a military hearing
The men would huddle together at night to keep warm
Quote it would literally I'll call it spoon on quote
JT Billings was one of the people who was out for 19 days straight
He testified that he gotten diarrhea early and quote you know I shipped my pants on quote
He did have a next
Repair ripped up the inside leg on some concertina wire
Quotes annoying that I was going out and talking to locals potentially females and whatever and villages
I couldn't necessarily have an exposed region like that on my pants on quote
Civilians were the s*** pants for 19 days
People's t-shirts got shredded their socks rotted
People got sores on their skin
They can only watch with baby wipe
Baby bottled water
Undergarments
Falling off
Oh really
Yeah close
You know like something you would you would think of
Malaysia or Burma
You know
Close just falling apart
That's Ken Wolfe
The command sergeant major
The hard part was they hadn't planned for this
No one knew how long the search
Just going to go on eventually we could we had to start figuring it out
Are we going to rotate guys back in how do we resupply
Is there every
Ariana guys are everywhere
They're spread out
Everywhere I mean it was just complete
GT Logistics nightmare
And then also it wasn't just our battalion
The other battalions within the organization or looking for him to
And so what you know
How does it make you feel
When
You walked for 15 days straight
Looking for a guy
Who walked off
And he's not even in your unit
Until you see somebody
And you're like
Hey man
F*** you
We're out here looking for this guy
Maybe you're thinking all this complaining about how hard that time was Cry Me a River
They're soldiers
It's War
And this is what they signed up for
Well it's a no
Their job was to go find and rescue one of their own
They knew that and they accepted it
Is the right thing to do to go look for him
And I genuinely wanted to find him
But they also knew
Or we're at least pretty confident
The bowhead left Mesto P voluntarily
I know they felt like they were going through hell on his behalf
And it wasn't just bozone platoon doing it but other
Other battalions
What's the people I talked to you about this time they said
The search inflicted such major damage on morale
It can be a delicate thing to maintain in The Best of Thai
At the end of July about a month in major Larry glasscock
The Battalion executive officer
Went on leave back to Fort Richardson in Alaska
Italian is based
His boss and asked him to meet with a group of soldiers family members who knew that their soldiers were out looking for Bergdahl
The families knew that we were conducting significant operations in that we were
Stepping up our kinetic activities against insurgent
How to try and find him
So they knew that the risk
Afghanistan for our Battalion had increased
And it was
It was a tough tough
Meeting
There was a lot of
Concern
There are a lot of scared wives
Why police show
They wanted answers and they wanted Comfort they wanted to know that their husbands
It's going to be okay
And you know
You know
9th Edition to make those kinds prom
Shane cross was in Splatoon
Is friendly with bow
Yeah I still
Awesome so I think I so angry about it
She was out on that 19 day stent
What's a platoon
Finally made it back to
The fob on July 20th
Repeat for only a few hours
It turned out rather than the day or two they hope for
Change shot himself in the foot with his nine millimeter pistol always in the bathroom
Got sent home
Shane said it was an accident
You said the Army agreed
The other guy saw it as a statement
How beaten down there over
I'd had enough
Commander said they could see it in their faces how emotionally busted their soldiers were
How angry
They're starting to bicker with each other
Major salvino testified that he's given them pep talks but quote I can hear well you know mumbling mumbling grumbling
Tumbling expletives blah blah blah
As the weeks went on they started to hit more and more dry holes
Did air assault and some villager Target and they find nothing
I asked him to keep morale up
Can two museums like the kind of guy who can scare the crap out of you
And also hug you
In the same encounter
Ken told me he tried whatever he could to get his soldiers through
Including asking his wife to send over Copenhagen snuff from the states
What she did
Shabbat rules and roles of it and can pass it around
I remember talking to see a group of guys and I got a we don't know if we don't know every
We don't know
And in him
You know this is our mission he's one of our guys
We got to find him
We're going to do it
That was one way the other way
Giving out cans of Copenhagen
Telling dirty jokes
Putting people in the headlock
That's how you do it just being affectionate with them basically
Yeah and saying hey what you're doing
Is good and honorable and we just got to keep
Yeah
And knowing in the back of my mind
This is f****** b*******
In what way was it b*******
Hookah hose
He's in Pakistan
It's true
But wasn't
What's the date today
July 14th
This is the first hostage video the Taliban released info
What's the name
My name is Roberto
Both spend the next year
Figuring out how to escape
Next time
One cereal
Cereal is produced by Julie Schneider Dana chitosan me in partnership with Marc Bolan Megan Ellison Hugo
Lincoln Jessica Weisberg page 1 and Annapurna pictures are glasses our editorial advisor editing help this week from Joel level in
Brian Reed Whitney Dangerfield is our digital editor research by Kevin Garnett fact-checking by Michelle Harris copy-editing Bionic
Nalani our music is composed by Nick thorburn Mark Phillips
Fritz Myers
Shows mix by Kate bilinski
Christian Taylor's our community editor production help this week from Nancy Updike and Naraku jester hirstein
Other cereals
Southland Emily Connolly's bergersen and Kimberly Henderson
Special thanks this week International mapping Thomas Barfield Dr Conrad crane Bill Marsh Leo Jung Jonathan marks
David Raphael and Mark McCreary
And special thanks to Pandora where you can now also listen to serial season 1 and 2
Our website is serialpodcast.org we can listen to all our episodes
Sign up for our newsletter read articles by the serial staff and check out Maps videos and more you can also find
Link to our Tumblr page where you can submit questions to us and we will answer them
Again that serial podcast. Org
Stay tuned for a preview of the next episode of serial
The first
Support for serial comes from ADT
You can monitor your home and control your sister
Tim from virtually anywhere
The ADT Go app
Including an SOS
Is it att.com
Learn more about how ATT can design and
Install your custom Smart Home
Backed by 24/7
Cereals are production of This American Life and WBEZ Chicago
Coming up
Next episode of serial
Literally
Picture of someone taking a bath
Right
How they treated