This is Sarah Koenig please leave a message
Dammit Sarah
Hello
Hi
It's Friday night you're in Baltimore
Friday night in Baltimore
So okay so
Bu ended the day yesterday and there is this one big question which is was the phone in Lincoln Park
And I'm one very curious to know if
You got an answer to that question
So
I don't know
You texted me
You take me at lunch time and said you had an answer for me
What I have the answer to Is the thing you're dying to know is
What does AT&T mean when it says you can't use incoming calls for
Shut up
So here's here's the answer that the state's expert said today
With that means is
It's it's referring not to cell towers
But it's referring to
The switch the Serta Grant the black the giant brain of all this
The cell towers in an area is the thing that decides
Like which Tower get switch handles with call
I believe so you probably know that better than I
Yeah
Okay
And so
He's saying
The best the best explanation he could oh by the way I forgot to tell you this
The switch that covers the dc-baltimore area or at least it the one that did in 1990
And I don't know if it's the same one but it's called the dawgbone
Which I thought was funny
Hi cuz
Because it's it covers to metropolitan areas so it's like
You know like a
A ball at what ended about the other
The dog house
Even though, at the dawgbone anyway
What do you say the best
The best explanation that this cell tower expert gave
He's like he's an FBI agent
And she is his specialty is cell tower now
What you saying is what that disclaimer mean
Is
For example
Say I live in Atlanta
That's in so that's my home switch is going to be Atlanta
Say I get on an airplane I turn my phone off I get an airplane I fly to Bali
Tomorrow
And I arrive in Baltimore
I don't turn on my phone
Like I never I don't answer right away the Baltimore cellular network
But calls are coming into my phone
While it's off
Those calls
On a call log on a record of my activity will show the Atlanta switch for those calls
When I'm actually in Baltimore but my phone doesn't know yet
That I'm involved that is actually a question that I have had
For like 2 years
I know
But this FBI expert is saying
That doesn't apply to the Lincoln Park
Because the issue with those leakin Park calls was cell towers not switches
So he's saying this the cell testimony
Travis Fine
Yeah
Well he's saying there's one call actually that he disagrees with
Anyone
Who is Scott the
Call log in front of them
It's the 514 call which is a voicemail
Alcohol
But yeah basically other than that one call he's saying
He thought that
Cell tower expert to test
Defy data nuns original trial
Did a perfectly fine job in
He agreed with that test
But
The expert esl experts who testified for an onside who testified yesterday
Disagree
Completely and he is saying
That
That original
Cell testimony from anions trial
Doesn't hold up
Because the expert back then never saw that disclaimer and that this that disclaimer
Does apply to cell tower
So that's the problem
And they're going to continue to fight about that
It's going to be this is going to be a brawl over this thing
And it's still going with they they're not done
Cross-examining him
I say and they added another day to the hearing
On Monday and I could even see it going Pat be on Monday
Translate it a lot to cover
Okay so this is not this is not settled at all this is not tied up
All right no
So what else happened today
So the rest of the day was all about The Alibi issue
And two things happened in that
What is that an onside put on an investigator
And they had hired an investigator and they basically said look
They gave Christina Gutierrez is in tire
Alibi witness list that she had disclosed to the state back in the day before the first trial
Don's Original defense attorney
His original defense attorney the one who all this is about
And she had 80 some names on this list rise like a huge long last
So Justin Browns team had said to this investigator
Alright go find as many
People as you can off this list
And find out if they spoke to
Christina Gutierrez or her office back then
And what he said is
He
Was able to get in touch with 41 people
Of those
4 people said they had spoken to Christina
And none of them was spoken to about being an alibi
Only four people
Wow
And it was one of those things were like well that doesn't
Sound good you know
It was a little
Yeah
But then the state came back and sort of showed a bunch of documents from her files all of which Wii U
You and I've seen I mean they're all stuff we have as well
And I remember these two and you know it does show that they were doing some work to
Find witnesses to find Alibi witnesses to speak to
People to subpoena
People
So it was just it was a little bit mushy like the back
Can 4th of that it was kind of felt like sort of a draw or something
I don't know it's
Like really whatever she did
Wasn't
Drake
That wasn't her defense
It's like she just didn't go that route
Possibly for you no lack of trying
But
If she didn't do nothing
So it was a little hard to sounds inconclusive
It was inconclusive who won that round.
Have to say
It was there a superstar witnessed today or something like that yes it's the most
Drama probably that happened
Was that this guy Dave Irwin
Testified for the defense
As an expert witness on criminal defense criminal defense attorney
Yeah long-time attorney you know he's been been an attorney since
The early seventies and he's
I worked as a prosecutor aide worked as an assistant AG heatworks
The justice department
Has his own private
Practice
Says litigator key you know teaches how to do criminal defense work I mean he's just
Yeah Yeahs distinguished career
And she was just so unequivocal about
How
There's no excuse you can think of for why she didn't
Investigate at the minimum investigate
And he just put it in in such
In like just no uncertain terms like he said he basically said if you have a credible Alibi witness that is
Is the best
Possible defense
Can have right
And so he's like that's what you're always looking
And he told this Parable actually about a long time ago when he was I think it was he was saying he was a prosecutor at the time and he had this
This case
And the defense put up this Alibi witness you said you know actually at the time of the
Crime
I saw the defendant
On a bus traveling to Philadelphia
Summer like that
And
And he said he's her came back at this woman and he said she was
Lovely young woman and said like how do you know you had the right day
And she goes what was my birthday
And
So at your day really stuck out to me
Yeah he said it was a totally humbling to me and he said ever since I've been looking
Looking for Asia McClain
Cuz you were saying how that case really reminded him of this one
Because it was the same kind of witness
Right like that's who you want like that's in Asia McClain like that's the caliber that she was
That was that that cases Asia
McLane yeah
And it like a Glock case
And this woman who remembers
Specifically because of
It's her birthday
Exactly
Exactly very believable
Credible very likable
And then Justin Brown
Kind of ticks
Through all the things that
The states
Had criticized about her letters and
Her memories of like
You know this the
Inconsistency is willing consistencies or it seems like she's too
Too eager to help or put it have possibly contradicted
Uno estate
That Adnan had said
To the police about where he went he was just like no
No no
No he was like everything about her letters seemed
Like assets to her
He was like first of all
She's bringing up the surveillance stuff a possible surveillance cameras
In the library
And he's like regardless of whether it exists the fact that she wants it to exist mean she's so confident and what she remembers that she
He wants it corroborated
Right so that's good
That she's just very confident in what she remembers his chain saying she's not really good friends with an honours
Floor with hay
And he's like that's perfect
Because she knows them both
But she's not going to be
Be biased
Cuz she's not good friends with either one of them yeah
He said oh the fact that she's offering up her boyfriend and her
Her boyfriend's friend
You know who all he would come back and drop it.
Phuket bakeri sounds like she's giving you two more labs
He's like she's
Perfect
And he said
In a situation like that you immediately pounced you move as fast as possible and you go in person
Talk to that one
Always
You always
Very convincing
It was so he was just so
Categorical about it was like
Kiss and then
He said
In terms of what he thought he could have done for Adnan
Case
He said he called it a game changer
He said he said it would have changed the ball games results
And that's of course that they
Write that
That anions
Side needs
The show is that it would have changed
The trial if
Justified at the time
And so his upshot was just like
So
You know his analysis was
Christina's lawyer
Fell
Below the standard required by law
He sounds like a
Very good with
He was a
He was a great witness for the defense
I mean I feel convinced
Well that divide but you know hold off because they did not cross-examine him
So the state has had not had its crack at that guy okay
And like you said before this didn't turn out
Give me the last day of the year
They're going to continue on Monday
Yeah they're going to continue on Monday
Okay but I I can't be here Monday
I can't cover it Monday no
We need you to
Get we need you to go home
I know so I have to do our other are season 2 podcast I have to make the next episode or it won't
Happen
We know we needed
I think what we'll do is I'll cover it in some way
Definitely when the judge rules probably something on our website so when you write that will definitely let people know on the E
Email it'll be on the on the website
Okay yeah yeah that's
Sounds good do we know when we don't know when the judge will rule
No I mean he'll probably take some weeks and
Do it carefully in
And come up with his real name
He seems very deliver it and very
I know he seems to be listening very very careful
Can you can you just explain what the possible outcomes are like what are the possible things that
If he could
Decide so me all of this is about
Will he
He will this judge
Decide that he thinks Adnan should get a new trial
So if he decides to that he thinks at 9 could should get a new trial based on these issues
I mean I got to think the state will appeal that
So an appeal will happen
Okay if
If if he says no I don't think a Nan should get a new trial
Then it goes back
The court of Special Ops
Peels
For them to decide what
What to do
It's probably either way the outcome will be
It's going to go back to the
But that said it's like this does not feel like some sort of like technical
Bump along the way that like they're just sort of getting through to get things on the record
You know it feels like
It's a real sort of like fight for survival in there
It feels like a mini-trial really is what's happening even though it's not a trial that is how it feels
All right I should probably hang up item to let you go by Dana
Okay by the way I quit cuz I'm going to go join the FBI cell phone investigatory division
Oh no it's not called that what's it called it's called cast cellular analysis survey team
That's what you need to join
You could be a cast member