Previously
I'm cereal
Why would you admit to doing something that drastic if you hadn't done it
The mechanics the documentation the steps they took
They look good while eating not get up there and defend yourself
You know it's your face to face
He's right there he's a person
So
You know
Believable
Global Tel Link prepaid call from
Maryland Correctional Facility
From This American Life and WBEZ Chicago its serial
One story told week by week
I'm Sarah Koenig before we get to today's episode where I'm going to let an auntie
Talk for a while
I want to run by you some new information I've learned in the past week
Three things I've learned
First
Remember Laura the former Laura Estrada Sandoval
Well then who the f*** did it in the last episode
She was friends with Stephanie and with Jane with an on
I was talking to Laura on the phone the other day and she mentioned something about Best Buy
So I asked her if I could start taping
Tell me tell me again what you just told me
There's not there's never any phones at Best Buy
There were never any phones around the Best Buy no Payphone oatmeal phone this
No
Thanks
Bones bear
The Payphone in question is important because Jay tells the detectives that are non called him on January 13th 1999
And tell Jay he killed Hae
Come and get me I'm at Best Buy
When Jake gets there he says he sees Adnan standing by the phone booth wearing red gloves
Draw the map for the cops
Showing the location of the phone booth
If you're facing the front doors of the store his drawing shows the booth on the left
Outside on the sidewalk
We did a lot of research on this
Where it was whether it was and we could not account for this phone booth
That's because it never was
She said the only conceivable place for a phone at the Best Buy it would have been inside
In the foyer part of the
Play Store
But there was no phone they are either
Laura said she knows this because she's to go to that Best Buy a lot
From the time it open through 98 in 299
With her family and without her family
Yeah I don't know if deal CDs from there all the time so it's pretty aware
Like what was around
Shoplift
CDs
So you're saying you would have noticed
Thing like that
Cuz you were kind of because you're not paying attention
You go in and let you cut her more aware of your surroundings and just walking into the store at the time
I remember looking up in the ceiling and see if there was any
Eyes in the sky
Cameras you know and you know there's a whole message
You're very aware
Of like entering and who was like
I was there at the entrance and when you're leaving
You know cuz you already hardened steel in
Man there's a phone bear
Lauren i hypothesized y If there really wasn't a phone booth
When they have noted it
Laura thought maybe it wasn't a big deal to them
It's such a small D2
It's not a small detail
6 Cal comes from is that pay phone at best
Yeah I don't know why they went check it but there's no case on there man
You sure I'm positive
Testing one
I learned it also relates to this 236
Call
I talked to a woman named summer
She went to Woodlawn she's been listening to podcast
And she emailed me because when she heard this one part she said she starts shaking her head
She said if the state is saying Haley was dead by 2:36
It's impossible
Is impossible it I mean
Like I mean it's just impossible
It is not
There's no way that
He was at Best Buy 236
Summer was friends with hey
Not close friends but they have class together and they joke around and talked
I had a boyfriend who did Sports at Woodlawn and she wanted an excuse to stay after school to so she can hang around with them
He told her there was an opening for another manager of the boys wrestling team he was already doing that
Summer Joyner
The day he disappeared the wrestling team had a match at Randallstown High School
Summer remembers talking to her after school in the gym area there
The wrestlers were Milling around summer Was preparing the equipment they had to load onto the bus
And he came in to say I'm not getting on the bus to the match
But I'll see you there
And that wasn't welcomed used to Summer
She needed her by her side at the match
Because he was more experienced at scoring
Which can be tricky in wrestling if you're new at
You know I was giving her hell because I'm telling her like
I don't know what I'm doing
You know I needed her because you know we had to take points in
Things like that and she's like no no no I just have to go and
You know pick my little cousin up
Summer says it wasn't a quick conversation either
You know we used to tease each other cuz she really was hilarious so we would tease each other and you know go back and forth and
We were at least talking for lease
10 minutes
You're sure that this is the day because it's the day she didn't show up
I am positive
Very positive
I look for her the whole time at the away game
You know I was really pissed because I thought that she you know stood me up
Rachel Summers she would make her own way to Randallstown high for the match
No one but me probably remembers this now
Inez Butler Hendrix who worked at the school
Said he had told her she was playing to catch the Randallstown bus
However Inez initially told the cops the opposite
So I trust Summers memory more and summer is clear
He told her she was going to drive herself there
Summer said this conversation about hey not getting on the bus happened after the last bell and also after the reggae
Dealer school buses had cleared the loop in front of the school
She said probably around 2:30 to 45
Summer says she has no dog in this fight
She's got no opinions on an unskilled or innocent
She just knows what she knows
All of the things that I'm you know unclear about or kind of shaky about or
I am
Clear
On that
236 would not have been possible for her to even
Have met him
Whatever because I know for a fact she was probably with me during that time
4 at the school during that time
Talk to the detectives there's no mention of her in their notes which is not the only person who said they saw her after school that day
Becky Star right after school Debbie Warren said she talked to hey to
Voice note say she saw her at approximately 3 p.m. inside the school near the gym
Which would match Summers memory
So
Laura says no phone booth at Best Buy
Summer says no way no how he was at Best Buy at 2:36
A mind that if you want withhold information from Asia McClain who says she saw Adnan around 2:30 to 45
Live at the Woodland Public Library
Can we all agree that whatever happened to hey probably didn't involve a 2:36 p.m. call from that phone booth saying come and
Get me I'm at Best Buy
I don't know about you but I'm done considering that it's true this 236 thing
If you want to speculate with me here for
4 seconds
If we suspect there wasn't a phone booth at Best Buy
That means the crime maybe didn't happen there
Jay's friend Chris said he heard the crime happened in the parking lot of the Woodlawn Public Library
But I got to say if you think the Best Buy is too public a place to commit a murder you should see the library after school
Swarming with kids
And if the she said come and get me call wasn't at 2:36
Maybe it's the next incoming call on the log
At 3:15 call
After all no one actually testifies to the 236
Six timing a trial
This comes from the prosecutor's narrative alone
The problem is
Is the 315 call that really messes with Jays testimony
About where they were and what they were doing that afternoon
Now information
It's about what happened at not her real name Kathy's apartment that evening of January 13th
Kathy remember Dan on getting a call and reacting in an agitated way
Saying things like
What am I going to do what am I going to
Say they're going to come talk to me
And what am I supposed to say
Kathy testified a trial. This call was acting panicked
I think it's possible that call Kathy overheard would not from a mystery Third Man or co-conspirator
But from wait for it
He's good friend Aisha Pittman
Interview for a sec
His brother called the cops that afternoon
Officer Scott Adcock arise from the Baltimore County PD
His initial report record the time as 5:12 p.m.
I cop calls Aisha and Adnan asking if they seen hey
Here's what's new
I got an email recently from another friend and that Woodland magnet group
Krista
Then she talked to Aisha that evening of the 13th
It was around 6 p.m. that night that I talk to Aisha and she was calling around to see if anyone had heard from her
Curb meaning hey
So I checked with Aisha and she does remember speaking to a non
Here's what she wrote To Me
I do remember speaking with an on that evening but I thought he called me
From what I recall it was a super short conversation and he was annoyed that I told the police to check in with him
I thought I spoke to him after the police called him
She said it's possible her memory of who called him could be mistaken maybe she did call
There's definitely no outgoing call to Aisha on an on cell that day
Maybe it was before he'd spoken to the
The cops not after
She can't be sure but that's what she remembers
Again you've heard this information before but I'm going to review it now
There are three calls on the call log around this time that all ping towers near Kathy's apartment
607 609 and 624
The first few calls are for a little less than a minute
The third call is the longest
4 minutes
15 seconds
That was likely officer Adcock
You should call at 6:09 says I just talked to the police
I'm not going to get in touch with you too
Aisha says Adnan was annoyed
Maybe that's what Kathy interpreted
Hispanic
I think we can all stipulate that Adnan was super stoned
He told me he had weed in the car
I was worried the cops are going to find it if they came to talk to him
Searching for a second and says something like
What am I going to do what am I going to say they're going to come talk to me
And what am I supposed to say
Obviously I can't say for sure this is what happened
But if that's strange call Kathy remember it was actually Aisha
Well then for me that rearranges all the pixels and Kathy's memory
From suspicious to inocuos
If it's true
Okay we're caught up let's go back to our regularly scheduled program
Second trial
Are you prepared to make your election
Testify if you remain silent
Remain silent
What's a non not testifying
But his attorney advised against it
Not uncommon
It's a huge risk to open your client after cross-examination and impeachment
So there he was mute
True to trials
About 5 weeks total
Which is really hard for anyone
More so sitting there for so long for so many days and weeks
You sitting there looking at me
I never sometimes where it was just going to leave what was being said
I was just literally just scribbling on a piece of paper
Acting like I was taking notes
I didn't know what else to do and it was going off so long
This is so frustrating
Cuz you want to keep interrupting to say hold him but that's not true that's not the reason why I got a phone
Make a phone call if that's not you know
Me telling my parents I'm going to
Somewhere but I'm going to the club that doesn't mean that you know
You never get a chance
You never get a chance to say anything
What is the most frustrating thing in the world
I want to let a non talk now
Not so much about what happened the day of the crime
I feel like we've been over that already
But just about what it was like to be him throughout this case
What it's like now to be locked up for so long
10th 1999
Are you sure I'd broken the terrible news
Krista about his body being found
Krista Dan call Dan on who ran over twice schs
To the very close to a non
And then Krista joint in there
Stephanie came over to
They all sat there at Alicia's kitchen table
Crying
No wait
You know did I not I'm pretty sure they didn't even imagine that you know that
Turn up
I never ever consider that
Something bad happened
Explanation
Somewhere
Father California
With her new boyfriend
Lots of people told the cops and also told me
Turn on appear to be in denial when they are first heard what happened
But he said things like it's not her
They got the wrong person all Asian women look alike
Arrested
Krista Rotana chronology of everything she remembered from the previous
6 weeks
Here's what she wrote about that night at Aisha
We went inside and Adnan was sitting at the kitchen table crying after while he said that there had to be a mistake
And then he was still alive because her name was written in ayesha's agenda book
He wanted to call the detective O'Shea but when he called the precinct he wasn't there
Alarm was upset so I took the phone and talk to the woman and explain that we just wanted to get some information and she's
He said we would have to wait and call homicide in the morning
Keanu on call detective O'Shea
The the night that
We found out that she had been murdered
That's right
Adam called the Baltimore County Police Department to talk to detective O'Shea
You tell him they miss identify this girl whoever she was
Has always stayed with me
Is that something a distraught teenager would do
Or is that something a killer would do
The next day we went to school and it was you.
And
Coming up to me
Hugging me
So much so many people are you okay
What happened
It was just too much
So many people.
Talked about an honest reaction to his death
But he was blank
Orca eating waves
Or not at all
Or that he seemed normal
We're staring at a picture of him and hand psychology class
One teacher said he was tense and unresponsive when she gave him a hug
The Tick he had became more pronounced
He was so sad he was barely functioning
The school nurse testified at Adnan first trial that she thought he faked a catatonic state
She wasn't allowed to testify in the second trial
Anything strange in his behavior
Besides they said it was a strange time for everyone
Was terrifying sad
They were all so young
How are you supposed to react
Interesting late Jim trainum the former homicide detective we hired to review the investigation
Immediately disregarded every single statement about an honest reaction
In terms of evaluating someone's guilty said
Stuff like that is worthless
He advised me to do the same just toss it all out he said
Because it's subjective it's hindsight and also people have been their memories to what they think police want to hear
Adan Health Plan a memorial for hay at school
They plant a tree for her
Still there in front of the school with a plaque
This time for Anon is a blur he says
Giant events kept coming
After the other
I didn't have time to wrestle them into comprehension
Stop
The cops came to announce house to speak to him on February 26 1999
2 days before they arrest him
I had an interview Jen RJ yet
There's reporting their files about that meeting
Which is dated September 14th
Almost 7 months after the fact
I don't know why
Detectives Ritz and mcgillivary come to announce house and ask about hey
Quote when asked if Syed had a relationship with Hae Min Lee Syed replied in a soft voice
Yes
However he didn't want his father to know
That's actually what I was worried about was upset again
What is the thing I was worried about the most
Olivia settings
I was like I'm worried about you may as well say
In the living room but there's a earthquake coming in the next
I'm worried about my father being upset
And my mother has told you I have no idea whatsoever that
Even ask women after that conversation with your dad was there
You didn't think like a
Not at all.
I actually thought that I killed her
I never not one time
Stop that they actually believe that I killed her
I think I need to go
Picture of ex boyfriend
Did you know they're going to come after you now unless they find who did it because you're the most recent ex-boyfriend
You would ask me that
No ill will towards her
Anyone
Put on
Early in the morning on February 28th after they've spoken to Jay after Jay has shown them where his car was parked of Edgewood
The detectives come into a nuns bedroom and wake him up
Time to put some clothes on
Time to go
He dresses sees his mother is watching his older brother
A little brother Yusuf is crying
To the city
Interrogation room in homicide
Describes as a little hook in the wall
Detective
You know I don't condone what you did but I have an ex-wife
You know I just went through a divorce or something I can understand how you can get mad
This by the way is what Jim trainum calls offering a theme
You give the suspect an explanation
When it minimizes the crime
As a starting point
Tequila very was being more so aggressive with
Okay
It would help out a lot of
Color switch
But he did mention that
Process your car
Images of red gloves
You looking to find those red gloves or something
Announce at the detectives left the room for a while then came back
When they came back they had to
Professional crimestopper it was a picture like a reward paper
A picture of hay
Will leave you alone with this
Looking at it
Jeremy 2culi
I know what am I going to say
This is over I'm going to leave
They both came it again
On top of the Metro
And that's why I said you know
Baltimore city in the top left-hand corner
Elasticsearch document
Statement of charges
Target wheel for me
Premeditated
Deliberately
You know and
So that's what he said you know you're being charged with Hailey's murder
At this point and not ask for a lawyer he said he was thinking of Matlock
He says the detective stop questioning him
They got ready to leave the room again
Keep in mind, 17 years old
I cannot going home
And I said to him I said hello
What's in my mind is like she got to finish this
Traffic report on
She had an annotated bibliography doing his English class
She said
Let's try to make a non situation plane to him
Not going home
And did you get it
You didn't cuz you're never going home
8 year old kids
Any situation
It's very difficult to believe in the early stages at this is actually what's happening
Away away my mind
Often when a Nan tells stories about this time
He zeros in on some small moment when someone was kind to him
Dorothy said hey babe just have faith
Communicate across is like a
That's it that's the whole story
Please mention the sky to me multiple times
Also the white lady who was driving the cruiser that took him downtown
She was polite
There's a sheriff's deputy who looks like Judd Hirsch who slipped him a candy bar
The 8th grade teacher whose name he can't remember who wrote him that nice letter
I can imagine how you'd CiCi's kindnesses
Nestle into your brain forever
Obviously I need to hold onto butt
This is
Junior prom pictures
Last spring date and I went to Chris's house
Christy was good friends with Hangin On
Just Kristin Myers back then
She dug out a trove of photos
Yearbook staff in letters
Christian wrote to each other during his first year in jail
Who is trial
She visited him frequently when he was in prison in Jessup Maryland much closer than where he is now in Cumberland
Krista is clear-eyed organized and thoughtful
His death was the defining event of her youth
Invest with her
Asda did not arrest
Conviction
She's not in the camp of 100% there's no way in the world that done did this
She's more
If you did it then I don't understand human beings
Because the guy I knew
Etcetera
So
It's just
She's a normal
Kind person
These are letters from somebody that
Militia sword
Just trying to sway you believe him it's
How many the General Lee
Am I even encouraged
Try to make the best of
The bad situation
Here's the guy she knew
June 2nd 1999
Did you get that really expensive prom dress you wanted and who'd you go with
If you don't mind me asking
:-)
Things are going with Andy
They've been having problems
He tells her stories about jail
June 8th
You should send me some pictures were allowed to get them
Some guys in here get some really dirty pictures
Do you like this I've seen more that I'd wanted to have a lot of people's wives or girlfriends the last a lifetime
I'm almost guys are really protective of their pictures someone's always pulling me aside to show me their latest
Flick
It's really kind of disgust
Has gotten letters from other kids from school Justin Asia Aaron
That's all he says about Asia by the way
He doesn't seem to attach any importance to her letters
Or note that she's a potential alibi
Because he doesn't know the state's timeline for the murder yet
With the juvenile population when he was first arrested in February
It makes you turn 18
And I moved over to be with the adults
I'd assume that would be awful in Myriad ways
Button on right sister Krista
It's weird when I first came here I didn't know what the heck was going on
Let me tell you it was pretty bad
Physically like no one was trying to beat me up
People didn't know what to think of me
I mean first of all everyone in here is black and always threatening to beat the hell out of someone else
Then you have me light-skinned and quiet
I didn't say much to anyone no one said much to me
4 months later I can be anywhere in the entire jail
Seminole call Syed
People say what's up to me ask how things are and I don't even know them
The strange thing is so many people come to me saying
If anyone bothers you let me know
But there's no one left to bother me
Some of that is due to the fact that I'm a Muslim to my personality
You know I've been blessed in that I can make friends almost anywhere I go
Now I can really say anywhere
He tells her he's gotten elected to inmate Council
You can see how it not initially thinks
This is all temporary
I'll be out by graduation Maybe by Summer
Maybe by whenever
A little more the closer he gets to trial
Crystal would testify for the state a trial
She's the one who talked about hearing him ask a for a ride that afternoon which add-on said he didn't do
But he doesn't hold it against her
He's so sweet to Christen these letters
Ask about the dental work she got done
Our little sister is doing her mother's doing with
Car got fixed
He talks about his feelings they discuss religion and God
Problems Christian parents are divorcing
Intimate friends who trust each other
The most striking letters to me we're the ones he wrote to her immediately before and after his sentencing
He didn't end up facing the death penalty by the way
The first one
He writes it while he's in What's called the bullpen waiting to be sentenced
It's going to cut out from a magazine
Photo of an Asian young woman
Smiling
What's this Crystal
That's actually not
Hey it looks like her
So
He found this in a magazine
And said that it does girl look
It's like he found this in a magazine and it looked
So much
Like hey
Yes
Weird
I was looking for this Jet Magazine
In case you didn't know it features African-American issues
:-)
Unquote
He tells Christy that had been appearing in his dreams
The dreams like this have a certain significance in Islam
But he's looking for this Jet magazine and he does a double-take because the girl looks so much like hay
OverWatch looks like Haze watch
So take a look at it and tell me what you think
I hope I'm not going crazy
I found this perplexing
He seems relaxed in a letter
This is a kid who is about to be sentenced to life in prison
He knows that's what's about to happen it's the mandatory sentence for his conviction
Conviction of course was for killing
Hey Chris is good friend
And in this pregnant life-changing moment he's writing a letter to
To Krista about whether a photo be flipping through a magazine
Looks like hay
Is it to
Nonchalant or something
Is it creepy
Not explain several things about this
First he wasn't especially nervous right then that was about to change but at that point he says he was thinking of his sentencing at
The procedure he needed to get through
So he could immediately start the appeals process
It was a step toward the thing he wanted
Second it's not like they transport you from yourself right to the courtroom door and you're just outside straightening your tie before your big
Big moment
The opposite
There's an enormous collection of utter boredom and exhaustion built in
So you do other things
Read write letters whatever you can
It would be hard to understand like you spent hours
Cigna bullpens waiting
You know so it's like
If you just said if you get up at 3 in the morning
Did you let go downstairs in like the basement of the jail he's just sitting in the bullpen
Square Room
It's like a concrete bench built into the wall that goes around
And you might sit there till like that for 4 hours and you go to the court
I used to collect another for 5 hours until you go to court and let maybe 10:11 in the morning so after like
After doing this for so long it's just like you
Just like it numbs the mind
So
I mean I know people who took a plea deal just to not have to go to court anymore
I really honestly like not even exaggerating
The third thing is that Kristen was the only person he was in regular touch with who knew hey
And Krista didn't think that inanna killed her
You know so I can talk to her about hey it's not going to be like
You know like
I mean
You know she's got to me like to talk to her about anything or writer about anything
A lot of times that's what it would be
8 Days Later post-sentencing
He writes Krista another letter
ISO change
By this time he fired Christina Gutierrez
Asia letters
Public defender he doesn't really know
To tell the court he did not kill hay and it's going to continue to fight this to the end
That's what he says in his letter to Krista
And the guy says no no no terrible idea
Don't say you're innocent it'll anger the judge
I don't argue with him and according to Adnan the lawyer says
Well you can do it if you want but you're just going to f*** yourself over
That his mother was going to speak
She's been to the trial everyday I say
Sometimes I glimpsed her in the videos
Keeping perfectly still or doubled over or holding on to someone
There's more than one bench Conference during the trial in which they talked about her mother's crying being a possible distraction to the jury
Her pain throughout must have been abject
Translator Hayes mother speak
She tells the court about her daughter
She tells the court about a Korean proverb
That says when parents die they're buried in the ground
But when a child dies you bury the child in your heart
When I die
When I die my daughter will die with me
As long as I live my daughter is buried in my heart
I don't know where to hear her voice
I don't know where to touch her hand
I would like to forgive Adnan Syed
But as of now I just don't know how to do that
And I just cannot do that right now
For many many months we tried to contact his family
To tell them we were doing the story
And it hopes they might want to talk to us about hey
In my 20-plus years of reporting I've never tried as hard to find anyone
Letters in English and in Korean
Phone calls social media Friends of Friends of Friends
Two private detectives
Korean speaking researchers people knocking on doors in three different states called
South Korea
We never heard back from them
I learned a few days ago that they know what we're doing
My best guess is they want no part of it
Which I respect
About hey I can tell you only what I've heard from non-family members
But she was cheerful and light and funny
But you love the movie Titanic
But she sometimes put nail polish on just so she could pick it off
She wasn't insecure seemingly ever
Sprite was her favorite soda
The Dallas Cowboys her favorite team not because she cared about football but because she like the colors blue and silver
That you could charm you without trying
That she was a good friend to her friend
She took in their problems and their pain and try to help them if she could
At the sentencing listening to his mother
That was the first time an understood how people on his side of the courtroom saw him
Keep never felt hated before
When is June 14th 2000 letter to Krista he writes
And I feel her pain cuz I cared about her and how sad she is
But on the other I'm thinking please believe me I didn't kill your daughter
She was sitting right next to me and it was really sad but I couldn't help thinking that my mom is going through the exact same thing she's going to
Lose her son forever
Afterwards I was thinking my God No One Believes In Me
Krista I could never explain how that felt
Attorney that addresses the court
Put your honor I would ask that this honorable court if it would consider this case more crime of passion than of intent to
To kill
Permanent letter
That's all I heard him say and I turned and just stared at him wanting to hit him with a chair or something
I mean this jerk is going to get up and give away the only thing I have my innocence
When he suddenly realizes he has no idea what to say
He had his plan but now quote on the other hand I'm thinking about what the lawyer said about the judge getting upset
On a certain I'm thinking man I should just apologize for everything even though I didn't kill hay
Stupid me I end up doing a little of each
It's true when his moment comes
He maintains his innocence he asks for the mercy of the Court
He says quote I'm just sorry for all the pain that this is caused everyone
The judge
Disagreed with a nonce attorney at sentencing
We know this because she said quote I disagree with you Council
This wasn't a crime of passion
She said you planned it
Intellect
Physical strength
Use that charismatic ability of yours that made you the president or what was it the king or the prince of your prom
And even today I think you continue to manipulate even those that love you
As you did to the victim
You manipulated her to go with you to her death
Early on I asked Adnan
If you're saying you're innocent
Why aren't you bitter and angry
Why do you sound so calm
He said a lot of things
Then and since
Because there's no one answer
Realizes how lucky he is
Compared to so many other guys inside
His family visits he calls him all the time they send him money
He's got people like Robbie inside pulling for him
I refuse to be miserable
Being religious help
What you hear all the time about people in prison but I never thought about it too much
Before I got to know at 9
We end up in prison he says he made a choice
To be a better Muslim
I can say that for nearly half his life he's live like he's supposed to
He knows it's a rationalization of a situation
But it's been the most helpful one
Finally he says he's got a clear conscience
Because you didn't kill Hae
I'm here because of my own stupid actions
I have some money man
I mean
I never should have let someone hold my car let someone hold my phone
I never should have been friends with you
I mean I don't feel myself
If you think he's lying
I mean
Damn the police
Prosecutors but
I mean
But at the end of the day I have to take some responsibility
You don't really know the things that my younger brother went to
At the end of the day if I have been
You know what I mean
You know it
I can't
I can't ever admit to this crime
After all his parents have been through the fear and the money and the anguish
How could he ever turn around and say to them
Atlantic issue with that
Two most important people in the world
I know the thing that bothers me the most is not necessarily me being in prison for this
I should be done this and I told him the reason why
We're still going to take care of them
But at least we don't have any more than somewhere
They don't necessarily worry about me being imprisoned because
I'm healthy you know whatever to come pick me up
I deserve to be here
I can't say what would truly be easier for his family
Knowing their son had murdered someone or feeling as if he's been taken from them unjustly
But it is true that is not has always been fine in
In prison
Is adoptable
People never been independent anyway
First word of his parents been awarded
State
He spent the initial part of his sentence at a prison in Jessup
About a 30-minute drive for his family
It was a loser place in where he is now at North Branch
Cumberland
A maximum-security prison more than 2 hours away from Baltimore
I didn't have been like
Shifferly like corrupt places
So they're not really strict
Senseware
You know it's like all you got to do this and this time you got to do this at that time
So maybe it actually is
In Jessup especially people got away with all kinds of craziness
That person's clothes now
Only had one infraction his entire time would you guide the DLC told me was impressive
For anyone
After I asked about his prison record and non set me a stack of copies
21 difference
Certificates and awards for completing this program or helping with that activity
In 2005 he got one called the distinguished gentleman's award
You're consistent display of character mannerism self-control and ability to manage adversity
Signed by the word
Announce what infraction was for having a cell phone when she had fur
For five years
Actually had a couple of different cell phones
I knew when you got he can figure out how to make it work
I just have not had a good job he was a clerk in the chaplain's office
Which gave him access to a computer and to a printer and copier
Being an entrepreneur and a couple of side businesses
Printing stuff and making copies for people
North Branch she's a cook
He told me the only jobs at northmantrader kitchen jobs are custodial jobs
Is that a group of friends he's close with guys who came into the system the same time he did
Have a little Breakfast Club when she's in charge of
Another guy does lunch
Membership has its privileges
Game
Looks like caramelized apples and onions
They were really good and she's on their side
Banana French toast also hot cereal with peaches and raisins for lunch cheesesteaks
The other 1504 got the normal menu boiled eggs
Bologna
Anon lives in a Cell by himself he's got TV
What is getting in fights or seeing horrible things
He's not telling me about it
All the stuff he tells me about
Is that worst PG-13
He told me I have a life
It's not the life I planned or imagined
I have a life
Despite the Nisha call
Despite the leakin park cell tower evidence despite J knowing where his car was
I confess to having Reasonable Doubt about whether Adnan killed Hae
I'm talking about the normal person kind
How do you say trial isn't built to hold the stories at 9 or anyone tells about his life
Does lawyer Christina Gutierrez had to figure out another way to encourage Reasonable Doubt
Why didn't it work
Next time
Ontario
Cereals produced by Julie Schneider
Operations manager Ira Glass is our editorial advisor editorial help this week from Nancy Updike and Joel level help on all
All things Financial from Seth Lind fact-checking by Michelle Harris
Administrative support from Elise bergersen our score is by Mark Phillips who also mix the episode Arthur theme song
By Nick thorburn who also provided additional scoring special thanks
Martha Morrison and Bob versus
Our website where you can listen to all our episodes and find photos letters and other documents from the case and sign up for a week
The emails serial podcast. Org
Serials production of This American Life and WBEZ Chicago