Serial season 3 is presented by ZipRecruiter
The smartest way to hire
Later during the break
You'll hear from co-founders dedicated to preventing workplace injuries
You learn why ZipRecruiter is rated number one by Employers in the US based on hiring sites with over 1000 reviews on trust
Tricep recruiter for free
A different router. Com serial
Support for serial comes from Squarespace
Make your business official with Google in Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and a Business website with Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and professional tools from Google
It's the simplest way to look professional online
Visit squarespace.com Google to start your free trial
Use offer code professional for a discount on your first purchase
Google and Squarespace
Make it professional make it beautiful
Previously on serial
You know it first I was like haha you know that but you don't have an audio you don't care the officer's name
Police
Break it up
I'm not going to press charges it doesn't matter
Like you'll just be seen as an irritant now in this
Well it is an obstructionist you don't want to get a record
Haitian for that
That's fine but you still have to go through this
From This American Life and WBEZ Chicago its serial
One Courthouse told week by week I'm Sarah Koenig
First thing I said to myself when I looked at the list of felony judges in Cuyahoga County was
Holy cow that's a lot of Irish names
Well truthfully that was the second thing I said
First thing I said was where all the Jews
Second thing
So many Irish
There's judge Corrigan another judge Corrigan judge Hollie Gallagher judge Shannon Gallagher judge Kelly Gallagher to Sean
Manasi Joshi and George McClellan
McCormick judge McDonald's at O'Donnell and judge Donnelly
Second to the Irish or the Italian
Namely Russo Russo Russo & Russo
Judge John J Russo judge Joseph Russo judge Michael Russo and judge Nancy Margaret Russo
At the end of the last is Judge sutula
And her cousin
Church the Tula
I'm finally Gibsonburg
I know sounds like my kind of Judge
Which is actually Italian married to Centerburg
The upshot
In a courthouse where the majority of the defendants
What is black
Out of the 34 felony judges
32r White
Two are
Early on in my reporting here I was on the 19th floor of the Justice Center
And I wandered into the courtroom of Judge Daniel Gaul just in time to hear him sentencing someone
Think was 4 years ago I was about to get
I didn't record it but I took notes
You're pathetic the judge will say you're pathetic dude
My father had a saying I shouldn't say this in court but I'm going to say it you're a b******* artist
Your criminal and a liar and have used the system all your life
Send the b******* artist says to judge golf a liar a cheater
That's not what I built my life on
Don't come in here and make these pretty speeches just call says you've got what's called a mortal character flaw
A man says
I'm not going to let you down
I left the courtroom a little wigged-out
I've never heard of Judge talk to a defendant quite like that raw and brutal and confusingly in
As if these two men were locked in a personal argument rather than a legal one the man up on the bench Titan
And small acting the enrage parents
The other chin-up but shamed trying to mollify
A judge's job here when it comes to sentencing is broadly speaking to punish the offender and protect the pub
Their sentencing guidelines of course spelled out in excruciating detail in the Ohio Revised Code
Assume the guidelines meant that sentencing with Fraley mechanical a certain kind of charge would produce a certain kind of sentence
Plus or minus a little Wiggly room in the margin to account for special circumstances or whatever else
But it's not like that
County judges in Ohio have a lot of leeway instead of saying a lot of discretion to interpret what punishment can
Consist of what danger to the public looks like
Leeway discretion
That's power by another name
Today's episode we're going to spend it all in one place in judge called courtroom
We chose Israel we is our producer manual Joe Chan died because frankly it sometimes thrilling in there
The shock Factor alone is worth the price of admission
But also because his room more than any we saw laid bare this prodigious power that judges hold
And the many ways they can wield that power
Try to get what they want
Emmanuel's going to tell part of today's episode
He actually move to Cleveland for us
Went to justice center almost everyday
He'll be reporting some of this
Serious so you'll hear from him throughout
And hang on to your hats America Emmanuel went to high school and college in Ohio
But he sounds like an Englishman
Long story
Is Emmanuel
In about five months off and on watching cases and juggles courtroom
I think we're going to let some record 6117 so I can say with confidence that this
Is a typical day
Do you have any common sense at all dude
Why didn't you just pull over
Most of what's happening in jungles courtroom in any courtroom up please in sentencing
Cause of exception
So this one's.
Sentencing for 19 year old I'm going to call Tyrell is unusual anyway
When was caught driving a stolen car
Is that the police in the chase
Cupid guilty about a month
Now he was back in front of the goal for sense
Let's back up for a second please tell me who's in the corner to the left
District Thai how are you today
Jewel's family sitting back there
Which is usually a good thing for the fences
Vincent Telegraph of the people who can keep the defendant in line
Did he or she be released
Who else is here with your mother
His sister
Okay hi how are you
Tuscl grease 12 sister
Add another sister and brother
Benson's back to Terrell
Stop the China election any woman better behave siblings
When you're not in jail do you live with those 5 people
That's too bad for them
Because you've been pretty much of a bad guy
You're too nice sisters and your nice brother they don't have these problems
But you bring grief to their dog don't you
Utomik
Physical looks at 12 PSI
Pre-sentencing investigation
Which is details about to Wells background
Is your father in the picture
IC
To Alsace
Work what what does that mean
They were divorced when you were five
Director
Does your father have a criminal record
Drill size
Not that I know of
Jesse Benton penitentiary
He's a decent guy
What you do for a living
You don't know you don't know my life has deserted you and the family
Are your brothers and sisters full brothers and sisters or step sister
Four brothers and sisters
In your parents divorced when you were five
Is that correct
If you hearing a shop notice
Audino
Racial stereotyping and jungles questions
An assumption on the part of the judge that this black family is rudderless and unstable
But all these kids must be from different possibly incarcerated fathers
Yeah
I'm guessing throughout his at 2
I'm quite sure and his attorney don't stand on his it
You standing just behind the wheel
Have a podium in middle of a courtroom
You got one hand at the back of the wells neck
Any other family on throughout hip ever he's physically trying to stay throughout through this
Piccolo
Girls mama says yes she wants him back
Bocephus
Charleston Nissan
Right that was the other day he married
Are you working
No you're not you're in the county jail
Even in the county jail how long
When I asked you if you're working you don't work in the county jail you don't support your child
And you had baby at what age
Beijing
Was that a smart move
That was awesome with that decision
Rolex datejust review
Jungle list of bad decisions fat lateral to this moment
Altogether wrong
A lot of bad decisions one play
Finally
Just cool sentences to round to 4 years of probation
Not a terrible outcome for him
Considering just gold given him almost 3 years in prison
Does gold explains the 10 to 12 Probation
Periodic drug testing get a job
Attack someone lost condition
Ketosteril
But if he has another child out of wedlock
Wacom support
You consider that a violation of his probation
Mother are you with me there
Responsibility
Is responsibility to community
I'm not down with you having kids and dumping them cradle-to-grave on the shoulders of the taxpayer
I know some people don't think that politically correct
But that's my view
That's my view and if you demonstrate your responsibility to this court I will send you to the point that you get AIDS
Job
And believe me you're going to pay child support through support
Every child doesn't say anything
Attorney John Steiner banksters goal high school is by now
No one in the room went out But what does gorgeous friend to do
Is unconstitutional
Accomplished well for having a child
Not legally but this is the sort of thing does Goldust
Have the day continues
It was the same condition on two more defendants
As far as I know just Google has never made good on this issue threats over time
I'm going to talk to cell phone we can test your hair follicles for opiates right now
It sold after
The attorneys never that
And as long as you don't piss them off
Just cool isn't an especially tough sentence.
All the punishments handed out in this day of a reasonable for this building
People people on probation he could have sent to prison
And the people he did sent to prison
He said he'd consider getting out of a lease
So
For defendants and their attorneys
The strategy in just gold courtroom is
Enjoy whatever he loves it you don't challenge him
Don't trigger him
You probably come out okay
That's what a defense attorney like don't stand it is trying to convey
Sweden to Russia oldest
Just hold on
Don't say anything
Will misfire
Can you see me one second
Back in his office judge calls got souvenirs from Ireland lot of the judges have Ireland stuff in their Chambers
He's also got one of those Potter things
Hi
Carolina golf balls
Very funny fight a slip-and-fall case
From your golf balls
At home here
Is nestled into the building along with the sons of other prominent clevelanders
But his floor are two other judges whose fathers were also County judges
Does gallstones father with a Cleveland city councilman and later County Treasurer
Just got started out as a defense in civil attorney and then ran for judge in 1992
County judges are elected in Ohio
He hasn't lost an election since
Nevin four of them
He's known around here as a TV judge
Controversially entertaining
The way he talks
He reacts instantaneously to stimuli
It's why the cleveland.com reporter sometimes Parks himself and judge calls room on a slow news day
A recent headline
Woman convicted in Murder conspiracy calls judge racist
Gets life sentence
Here's another
Judge Compares man acquitted of murder charge to Las Vegas shooter
Sentencing
Note the word
Acquitted of murder
And that one just called said that if the defendant had pulled a gun on him on Judge call quote
I would have busted a cap in you unquote
The defendant's name was DiMaggio Callahan article said he remembered this guy from a previous case because quote he's gotten
Italian first name and an Irish last name
Annie's brother
Black defendants brother and dude
You got a bit of an attitude go with your brother
Emmanuel told me that in eight months of watching his courtroom the only black person he didn't hear judge call call brother or
Dude was a manual
Use the terms like baby's mama and baby's daddy which impossible for a White Guy to do without making the whole
Ballroom cringe
Is no truck with political correctness
He's out to use the term race card if you throw it down in his courtroom he says it is not going to work I eat woman calls
Ostrich racist gets life sentence
He'll work the black lives matter movement into his colleague weeds as a pun I guess
His black lives don't matter to you did it he'll say
Has said more than once
Two black defendant regarding a black victim
Just don't know if he's blind
Knows he's skirting not to quibble that I take Crossing
Various lines
Constitutionally and socially
He says he's been called all the names
Misogynist racist
But he says that is the price he pays for trying to connect with dependents
The I have been criticized in the past or maybe using a little slang or being a little bit too casual sometimes
But I'm
Talking to
A group
People and I want to speak to them in their video
In language that they can understand not in legalese not in
But noted references injury and suggest hey dude
Get real
May I really want them to understand
Me and understand that I understand
Them
He's doing something up there he's
Is not just a functionary
Say what you will about Judge calls personal views and his manner
Temperament
And I will say many things here
But he is not cynical
Is fundamentally optimistic in a way
He can fix what's broken
Defendant by defendant
And I really think
I know these people sometimes better than they know themselves and I share this information confront them I make them think about their lives
Everyday judge Gaul is seeing all these depressing stats made manifest
It's almost always there in the psi's
He'll see that the defendants parents were drug addicts or abusive
Couldn't or didn't take care of their children may be ended up in prison themselves
I know this person a product of foster care and a Board of Education
Kids are his or her own
Comes before judge call having committed a crime
The horrible crime
It's a rotten family cycle
Angelica wants to break
He told Emmanuel that's why he's asking defendants about their children
You asked me why I ask people how many kids say
What wine goes up
Because it should be an issue of social
Concern
It's not politically correct
To ask
People how many children died
Why I don't know I think
Perhaps because some people think it dis is women
It's not about that
If I believe that most of the people are in here because of abuse or abandonment or neglect as a child and I do
But I want to see to it that there aren't kids that are just born
And left
By themselves in a band
You know some people say well you're a misogynist wait a second
I'm defending a little boys and little girls were brought into this world and raised in foster care for the rest of their life
What do you think their chance
And what percentage of the kids can be born into poverty
Before
We don't have
A middle class anymore
Or there's a permanent under
So
Siri
Meet prep
Please tell me
You don't have
This woman had pleaded guilty to theft
An incident at Macy's
Her lawyer tries to help her out
Explain she has one child and a second on the way
Enter pregnant now
Even better
Wonderful
Who's the first baby's dad
Give her a couple years probation
This is on a Monday
Over the weekend just go ahead read an article about the percentage of children born on Medicaid
After the Macy's women left the courtroom he start talking about it
Anybody see the story in the paper by the percentage of children born in this country on Medicaid
Anybody see this
I don't even want to know Mona defense attorney
New Mexico I think leaves the country 72%
He told them
And the national average is over 50%
I believe it's a process
Decatur
Whittier judge calcite this statistic From the Bench several times as the months went on
Is one of the most transparent judges in the building his world using woven into every proceeding
He like the old days better
Cleveland was better in America was better
When people were more respectful or Brazilian
What's whiny
Now we're dealing with a generation raised on ADHD medication which could who knows what to their brain chemistry
Chinese Millennials nourished on participation trophies
Anchor rode something from the rest of us
All of this
The toll building
The 13,000 felony cases moving through the criminal court each year
Boat races at a frightful shortage
A personal responsibility
Sentencing in Ohio for recent history of it is similar with evolved all over the country
Back in the mid-1990s when we were freaking out about Rising violent crime
Ohio like many states revamp its sentencing laws
It redefined certain felonies made some punishments harsher
I got rid of parole for most cases
Animated shamelessly oversimplify for a second because the reasons why Ohio's prison population climb
Are complex and super interesting by the way it did climb
Mostly because people began serving longer sentences
In 1974 Ohio prisons held 10700 people
By 2011 they held almost 51,000 people
400% increase
That's expensive
More than a billion and a quarter dollars
Expensive
So that your 2011 Ohio again like other places
Swing back the other way
I passed new legislation aimed at unpacking the prison
Which has more options for diverting low-level felons to Alternative punishments
And broaden the opportunities
For probation
That suits judge called just
Spine
He likes probation
He likes lengthy probation
I probably put more people on probation than any other judge in this Courthouse
Yeah because I can always put him in prison later
And I keep my eye out
Probation gives judge Galan going control over people's lives
It does best hope for getting them to change
And I probably have at any one time
Anywhere between
I don't know
Kayak
Couple thousand people on probation
50% of people on probation
Probation what insiders call getting paper rather than time
Is what most defendants what
But probation has its own hazard
Probation here is actually called Community Control sanction
Emphasis on the control
What is why I have heard defendants tell judges they'd rather pay a big fine or just do some jail time and get it over with
Rather than be on probation
I'm probation you're out but you're not free you are still tethered
The courthouse
And the conditions of your release can worm their way into almost every aspect of your life
They can dictate who you live with
Where you work whether you can have a beer after
Whether you can go to your uncle's funeral or your niece's wedding
It's so easy to slip up
A dirty urine test and missed meeting maybe you get indicted on a new crime
And you're back before judge Gaul
That's why he's got more cases than most judges in the building
Because of all those probation violation
We watch one violation hearing
Four women named Vivian
I know you quite well we've talked on five or six occasions
Correct a good person
So I feel like a nobody
Google doesn't know Vivian pretty well but he knows our specs
She 29 single three children
Our youngest is 3 months old
Couple of years ago in 2015 she pleaded guilty to felony drug possession
Got caught with a small amount of cocaine
Rather than convicted of the felony was called an ilc intervention in lieu of conviction
Work sort of like probation
The idea is a Vivian could do everything she supposed to her case will go away
The list of requirements is significant
Report weekly undergo drug testing complete intensive outpatient drug treatment go to AA meetings at 2
Tina sponsor get counseling get her GED
She's done everything
Except stay clean
Recent drug test Church even using
Is it a violation
R6 time before judge Gaul
And I'm telling you that you got to deal with the drug problem or you're going to lose your job and your children are going to live in
Jekyll takes time with Vivian
Reminder that another judge might have dealt with in 5 minutes tops
Chekhov spent 20 minutes talking to her that's a dog's age in this building
He's been through the usual Jazz about babies daddies and bad decisions in the welfare state
Medicaid MX
Seacoast NH
We also seem sincere about trying to help her
He bores into the detail of her schedule asked about her job
She works nights in the kitchen of a casino for $10 an hour
Bad idea he tells her that's exactly the kind of place where you going to be offered cocaine
You need to stop the second shift work
I think it's set me up for failure
Get up and get the kids off and get the kids daycare and work during the daylight hours
So that you and the children to rest at the same time
You need to get honest in your working
You're working you know
16 hours a day
Without the help of anybody
Three months ago at another violation hearing
Just call that set up and said Vivian to jail for a week
To try to scare straight
That didn't work
Today she's desperate not to get locked up
She's worried she'll lose her children
4 compartment is Deft she knows not to beg in here not to whine
She missed her weakness flags are strength
She tells him all around she's enrolled herself in an intensive outpatient drug treatment program
And IOP
I just feel like I should do better and I can do better
And if you give me an opportunity I promise you I will I know I've done wrong numerous times
But I've been selfish and I'll keep her overnight without court-ordered without anybody telling me to do what I can do on my own
Vivian's attorney today request that judge call transfer Vivian to drug court
Instead of remaining under judge call supervision should be put on a specialized docket designed specifically for people like
Like her
People who aren't violent I don't want to be criminals but who get in trouble with the law because of their addiction
Over in drug court that use a therapeutic model
The question is not how can we best punish you
It's how can we best help you get better
What are the drug court judges is Joan synenberg
Does a social work background
Actually she's the recovery Court Judge what does a docket for people struggling with both mental health and drug problems
And it is a different vibe over there
Just really fast I'm going to show you
I was with her one day when she popped into that courtroom to say hi
Hi how are you how are you
Another judge was substituting for her because she was tied up on a murder trial
The participants sat in the jury box and on the benches atmosphere was casual warm
I miss you a lot
I love you the right way
On the way out judge Centerburg ran into one of the recovery Court participants in the hallway got him Craig give her a big hug
Amazing
You have been
Operations program
Little hectic and stressful but
Amazing experiences
Is amazing
I'm so proud
You have come so far
Nice right no one gets torn down in drug court
Nonna's ask why they're pregnant
I'm not saying it's a cure-all
Ohio has been devastated by the opioid crisis
But research shows that programs like these are the best way we found to help people with drug problems
Stay out of the criminal justice
So Vivian's attorney asks for drug court
Ana probation department which is staffed with substance abuse specialist
Social workers
Well-regarded around here
They're also recommending Vivian for drug court
The judge called
Flix that idea side
As if drug court is going to do something different than what we've already
It's as if you saying I got this
I deal with addiction all day long
Vivian's just got a buckle down stay the course
She doesn't need drug court
She has me
Vivian's attorney doesn't push back much on this
Even seem to agree with judge call what difference would it make
One difference
In drug court she have one defense attorney dedicated to her case
Follow her progress and update the judge
The sky is her fifth attorney
Each time she has to appear before judge golf she's assigned someone new
First there's a public defender Linda Rico negotiated the ilc deal
Instead it's been assignment list attorneys
Is Charles Morgan than jimho slick and Aaron brockler. Presented her at 2 hearings actually
Today is Joseph O'Malley
Their goal all of them is to keep Vivian out of jail
Other than that they don't have much of a stake here
You're not thinking too hard about how she progresses with drug treatment or what would work best for her
They're getting paid a hundred bucks for this hearing
The moments over she's not their client anymore
Today judge call ends up putting Vivian on house arrest at her own suggestion
I'm sure Vivian would like this interaction with judge Gaul to be her last
The last she admits
Stream
A month from now she'll be indicted for theft
Freezing a friend's credit card
Set another hearing Jessica will tell Vivian she's out of control and he'll send her to jail
Just been 51 days there while the credit card case gets sorted out
She'll be guilty to a couple of first-degree misdemeanors
God will tell her she's weak
Indulgent
Selfish
I'll tell her to quit the tears sweetheart and he'll give her a suspended jail sentence
More home detention plus two years probation
Now instead of three aana meetings a week she must go to for a week
She'll violate again
This time she'll beg for inpatient treatment
So tell Jessica her cousin died three weeks ago from an overdose and she's afraid
I need help I need help she'll say it seven times
I need to learn to get through this sickness you call it a sickness and I call it a crime he'll say will send her to jail
Once again she will leave her three sons who by this time are 9 years old 6 years old and 9 months old with their grass
Grandmother after Vivian has spent 66 days locked up
Her ninth assign lawyer will write to judge call asking him to let her out
Scala release Vivian from jail
I'll put her on probation for another year-and-a-half
Now she must attend V A N A meetings a week
I'll try to help Vivian least I think he is
But consider a drug court
That new stuff charge would have been rolled into her existing case
It would not have affected her status in drug court at all
But she been in drug court it's unlikely she would have spent even one day in the county jail much less 127.
What you been in drug court and if she's anything like the other drug court participants almost all of whom backslide and struggle
Twitter graduated from that program in about 13 months
As it stands she's been embroiled with judge Gaul for three and a half years and counting
Perkier than 5 grams of cocaine
This is possibly the most profound and least examined question in the building
What works
Court doesn't gather statistics on sentencing and that's true for most of the country by the way
No data that says defendants and Cuyahoga County do better after 6 months of probation then after 3 years of probation
In terms of reoffending
4 years in prison yields better results than 7 years in prison
We just don't know
Which I found rather astounding when I realize no one is tracking this
The court keeps extensive data regarding efficiency
How many cases are moving through who's dockets and how quickly
Which I'm not knocking efficiency it's important
People here are generally not waiting years and years for the KC
Test results and that's good
But there's no database locally or nationally that shows what works
To each judge in the building has to muddle it out for him or herself
Judge Cassandra collier-williams put it to me this way
There's 34 judges up here and it's like 34 different cities
Of course you're just here I'm just winging it mostly they're not winning it
They're basing their decisions on the sentencing guidelines
And on their professional experience
But they're also making decisions based on their life experience
And where they come from and who they know and where they live and what they read
And what it is they hold dear
Talking to various courtrooms and you feel it right away
Mr. cook how old are you
I need you to speak up just a little bit okay
That's Judge Collier Williams on the 23rd floor
Taking a plea
Case of felonious assault with a gun
He painstakingly list for Mr cook all the rights he's giving up by not going to trial
With gentleness she makes double sure he understands what she saying
Okay so what's the total time you looking at the possibility
Understand
Okay finally she lectures him
Thank you I accept your plea of guilty to count three and find you guilty there on just kidding
No muss no fuss
We have seen her do this
You have 30 days to register to vote
Superbad to your probation officer
And now you are required to vote in elections in the reason why I do that is because people died for this right
Does Keller Williams wants felons to participate in democracy
Like everybody else
But please stop doing this
Ever since the ACLU had a little
Chat with her
Again
Unconstitutional
Judge Michael Donnelly on 19 he'll only discuss please on the record no background sets in deals
Judge Janet Burnside down on 16
But she's giving people accused of serious crimes longer and longer prison terms cuz she's so struck by the sure violence you seeing
Look for probation she swings light
She wants to get people off of Court supervision
Quickly as possible 2 years ago the probation department start using what are called evidence-based practices to determine probe
Location
Ask a bunch of questions to try to figure out a defendant's risk of recidivism and then Taylor the conditions of probation to his or her level of
Risk
A PowerPoint I saw on the method included a slide that said quote avoid threatening lecturing arguing shame
Gaming or sympathizing
But you just don't have to take the probation Department's recommendations their optional
Judge Kathleen Ann sutula backup on 23 so she uses the evidence-based thing only sometimes
Velocity is akin to judge cause she told us short probation that's throwing a person away she'll tip
Typically give five years probation super strict condition
90 AA meetings in 90 days for instance if you miss a day you have to start over
She owns her reputation as a tough judge
Wake up
Mean would be the tamest thing we heard a describer
But I got to say we didn't see that so much
She was tough but we can get the feeling her toughness with self-serving
We watch the sentencing of a young guy 19
Kid stolen a bunch of cars
Other guys were involved but they didn't get indicted
It was intense
Defendant
You live with your father
So why didn't he pay your bond
Turn 50 bucks and you could have gone home months ago
Set of sitting in jail all this time
You know we called your father he said he didn't know your address or where you stay
That surprise you
Yes ma'am
He whispers
You're standing here all alone
There's no Louis there's no Mikey and even your father doesn't want to stand here with you
Is this tell you something
Do you have any thoughts about this in your head
What are they share them with
Yeah
Big time
By the end they're talking about his future plans
She mentions College
I don't know
Can one still talking to change the trajectory of a teenager's life
Maybe
Transgender is here how do you know
How do you know if what you're doing is working
They talk about the people who come back
Vista visitor who write letters or home AC on the street who say thank you for being hard on me or thank you for giving me a check
Chance you help me
I have my kids back I'm doing well
Which must be great for a judge to hear but rigorous evidence it is in
Forget to call I wasn't exactly sure what he needed to see from a defended in order to declare success
Until we came up on the case of Rayshawn Ellis
What's after this
This is the road to hire
Bicep recruiter
Kevin Reynolds grandfather was a farmer all his life
Define
Personnel
Interactive
The grandkids in the same way because
He just isn't comfortable
Kevin sound of Lumosity
It works with companies in energy farming and Construction Industries
I figure out how their employees are moving their bodies
And to teach them to move it back their arms or legs
More safely
As Kevin says
It all comes down to efficient
Which is exactly why when it came time to hire a marketing person
ZipRecruiter
Dana was the one who manage the hiring process
Let me post a job on ZipRecruiter we actually got so many qualified candidates that we ended up hiring
People
You hired someone you didn't even know you needed
That's The Power of efficiency
Just ask Evans dad
I'm like his grandfather
Kevin Hart's dad start moving more efficiently years ago
My dad
Is
Gators old
Cowboys
Russell Wilson They Ride the tractor
All kinds of stuff
And they're expensive
What's your grandfather's going to be
But I have as my grandfather
ZipRecruiter
The fast and efficient way to prevent straining your company's muscles
ZipRecruiter for free today
At ziprecruiter.com cereal
Ziprecruiter.com
Flash serial
ZipRecruiter
The smartest way to hire
Support for serial comes from Squarespace
Make your business official with Google in Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and a Business website with Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and professional tools from Google
Is the simplest way to look professional online
Visit squarespace.com Google
To start your free trial
And use offer code professional
For a discount on your first purchase
Google and Squarespace
Make it professional make it beautiful
When judge call sentences someone
The principal thing he's looking for
Is remorse
Emmanuel and I've heard him say these two phrases dozens of times
Acceptance of responsibility demonstration of remorse
Rehabilitation
Camp begin
Until there's some acceptance of responsibility
Xiaomi
Chander with the court
Some demonstration of remorse
Acceptance of responsibility
Showing remorse
Judge Gaul did not invent these phrases they come from federal and state sentencing guidelines
And they sound bed rockish like they're probably chiseled into the courthouse while someplace
Practice their controversial
Because acceptance of responsibility or showing genuine remorse
What does that mean
What's that supposed to look like
It's subject
Some judges will say well you plead guilty so that's taking responsibility right there
That's enough for me
The girls room
Play alone definitely not enough
He needs to hear you say it
Even better he wants to feel you feeling it
If you do it's a good bet your sentence will be lighter
If you deflect responsibility
We're on the subject
The sentence could be heavier
The starkest example we saw this with the sentencing of a guy named Rayshawn Ellis
Rashawn is 31 he been a defendant in many cases ever since he was a teenager
Sumter Jazzy Beats
We are before he picked up a new case
Are caught a new case is what everyone says
If it's a virus
Anyway Rayshawn caught a new case
Serious charges felonious assault weapons violations
Is a messy incident but the just was that a guy shot a gun out the window of Rayshon car while Rayshawn was driving
A fight a broken out early on Judge call me to claim he thought Rayshawn should plead guilty
Rayshawn said he wasn't the instigator of this debacle and what's more he tried to deescalate the situation to break up the fight
Fight even scared for his own life he said Rachel and took the case to trial
Anyone mostly
Who is acquitted of the most serious charge felonious assault
But he was convicted on two weapons charges
Both of which carry the possibility of prison.
Because of the gun in the car even though it wasn't Ray Sean's gun
And he didn't fire it the jury found he was still criminally response
Immediately after the verdict
With the jury still sitting there
Surgical launch
Rashan he said you should resolve this case a long time ago
Juicer
Are going to be looking
Because I'm not going to put on a screen
A person that sew
Dysfunctional and destructive
It doesn't understand that you should resolve this
Without risking
23 years on the first count in Fountain
I want to pause on this for a second so the perversity of the moment can sink in
Just go is angry at Rishon for refusing to plead guilty
For risking huge prison time on an assault charge
For which he has just been acquitted
Not guilty
That's what's dysfunctional indestructo
Refusing to plead
And that's what makes Rayshawn deserve prison
A month later Emmanuel winter rash on sentencing
You're curious to see what he was going to get
It was a Monday morning
Resume was one of his first cases of the day
And already the goal was what
You get indicted and you don't it make your responsibility
You don't demonstrate any remorse
You know you're going to go to prison on a probation violation because I told you that
Stroger attorney
Rachel has been on probation adult
Jungle stop placing arrest after arrest
Chad off the child drop the law that ratio on faith ever since he was a juvenile
And he in racing the tonnage on his Island start with either getting the facts
Current case
Don't exasperated not pretend exasperated
You often see a Chinese performing an argument
You don't often see a real one
John is insisting that racial and try to do the right thing
I keep the people around him getting shot
It's getting hot in the judge
What is a party
This goes on and on
Which one is facing five and a half years on the probation violation
Malone never mind the new charges he's
Just been convicted of
You could add another phone a half years
So 10 years total
If it doesn't Stick it to him
This fighting is annoying
Finally
Right cervical says
So you're sentenced to
Rachel interrupts
Michonne takes out a full-page letter
I'm against reading
Jana just ghoul
One of the girls grow up
What time
I was wrong
Later
Back in his Chambers
Jungle Red Palms of the letter aloud to me
Criminal my point of view has been clouded since I was first charged at 16 years old
And I have been angry ever since
I have finally opened my eyes and saw and came to realize
I have been wrong for 15 years
It has humbled me
This experience has helped save my life
And awaken me
My self-destructive illusions
You are an outstanding judge
I'm going to remind you of what you said
Then I could be your son
And I'm not assuming that as favoritism
That, truly touched me
It made me
Look at you different
I originally perceived you
To be Prejudiced and never expected you to show me your human
Personal decent
I recognize the wisdom and help you imparted on me
That was wrong
And you have been trying to reason with me
To consider my choice
To associate with the criminal lifestyle
And it goes on and on and on
In the courtroom
Rachel meadows letter from heaven 7 minutes
Finished
Does Google stand
It's really
The criminal equivalent of the Gettysburg Address
He said he wanted to get the letter laminated
Read it from.
I found it inspiring
A visit to the courtroom such as
Myself
My considerations letter at Brigham strategic move
While also wondering if it just goes up
Play it
Adjust goal believe letter was genuine
He was moved
He said to Rachel on
It's not possible for anyone to fake what you just said
It was gratifying
Of course it was
But I think it was also maybe vindicating for
Because I'm in bed.
Alphabet in the room a few weeks earlier
When do the fender and quarter go racist
Just go new I've been squinting uncomfortably farangs in the stereotyping
Announce he was proof
Gold method what
Just go with emotional about The Optimist
You mentioned the Bible story about the good thief who was redeemed
Jokes app
So
There may be
Some Redemption
He certainly on Earth
To change his attitude
Map my email
He may amount to something email
Because of Alaska
Michelin tires on Santa Fe in half
The school was going to give him 6 and 1/2 of 7 years he said
Instead
Gave him three
And I told Rachel
Come back in six months and apply for judicial release
Tony's chocolate
When cutting someone lose he's learned his lesson
Off of the Shocker prison
The six-month Seaside
Follow motion
Maybe I'll smoke you out
Six months to the day John is an enrichment attorney did file a motion for shock release
Rashawn Amazon over there
But lack the magic of the sentencing
Instead just culture alterations criminal record all over again
So much prior involvement with the system
Cruelty to animals that jumps off the page anyone that would do that to an animal
Rashawn pushback it wasn't me I was 14 years old and someone shot a cat on my porch with a BB gun and I didn't tell
What are the aggravated robbery in 2001
Well that one I didn't do it but I was there so I got caught
And then the crime at hand
Accused Rayshawn of knowing about the gun
Does putting other people in danger
Rashawn said it wasn't like that to go side wiring minimizing
The Gettysburg Address
Wasn't echoing in anyone's ears
Just call denied Rayshawn motion for judicial release
I'm denying your motion for shock probation at this time he said because you are not accepting responsibility
And therefore you're not demonstrating any remorse
Try again in six months you told him
See if your attitude has changed
It was all over I talk to Rashaan about how this whole thing went down
He told me he still hadn't made sense of it
Just go ahead all the promised to shock him out if he did well in prison and he had done well
Six months earlier when he wrote the letter
He said it was partly sincere partly political
Annuity structured call Diego
He behaves like a king he
He wants you to do no honor him
So you can see from this picture yesterday
But at the hearing for shock release
He figured they were past the stage of flattery in theater
Who's taking a bath when judge calls started in on the details of his
Does case
Rayshawn said he kept trying to talk to
Man to man
Respect you as an individual in the position at
Vodka tonic
What you want me to tell you
Rashawn didn't feel as if judge kollra leading him down the road toward responsibility and Redemption
You felt as if dead girl simply wanted submission
Furzone sake
Rashawn surgical quotes
Struck me as nothing less
In a raging slave Mass
Such a nice way
I'm not scared of you
He wanted it this way or no way and it was just like
But it is Judge calls way or no way
That's the maddening Corkscrew operations position
Jungle shouldn't require him to grovel
Michelle's right about that
But there's nothing Rayshawn can do about it
Is Rayshawn is the one who broke the law
Everything judge calls doing
Is legal
What you're wondering
The judge call ever get in trouble for the way he runs his room
Is there a rain did well let me tell you about this one last case just quickly
Was back in 2015 so I wasn't there for it but I do have a transcript
A guy named Carlton heard with indicted for shooting
He said he didn't do it you want to go to trial
After being postponed a few times day of trial finally comes
Enchroma hurts attorney asks
For another continuance
Because he said Mr herd had just informed him
Half hour ago
But he's been covering up for the real shooter
So now they need more time to investigate
Judge Gaul does not take kindly to this motion to
Continue
He thinks his last-minute new evidence claim is bogus
He sure they're just trying to delay
He does what he does
Which is to excoriate Mr hard
For being black among other things
Your black life didn't matter to you did it and
Your child's going to grow up and I'm speculating now just like you did without a dad
Did you have a father
Knossos Carlton heard
No of course not
But then even by judge Gaul standards judge Gaul veers out of bounds
He says to Colin herd
You're either going to go to trial right now
Are you going to plead guilty
Current herd hadn't asked for a plea deal
The state had not offered
No matter
Judge call comes up with his own deal for cotton hurt
He says if you plead no contest
To the indictment right now
I'll sentence you to 14 years
Quote if you take the case to trial and are convicted
You will do multiples of 14 years
Because if you're convicted of these charges that's what you deserve
You deserve to spend what could be the rest of your life in the state penal Institution
What's it going to be
Colin herd says
I'll go to trial
His mom works out no
Carlton says to her listen to what he just said
14 years seems like forever to Carlton
Little daughter will be 18 when it
Got out
But his mom was hearing the other number
Multiples
14 if he's convicted at trial
They confer for bit off the Record
Ended girl tells them at length about another case he had in which he offered a couple of knuckleheads
Ideal they didn't take
I had the same conversation with them and having with you they said right there right in that chair
I told him I said look you can do 15 years or if you're convicted of all this other stuff
You're going to get consecutive time
They both got sentenced to 78 years
Just relax again weather Carlton wants to
To plead
I didn't do it
Colin herd
The girl says look you want to go to trial go to trial
You have a beautiful suit on you can sit there and maybe the jury will think you're a great guy and you're not guilty
What do you want to do
There's a pause
Alright let's bring the jury up
Circle says
The jury is on its way
They walk into this room I deal with you is off
I'll take it
Mountain heart
It was like an hour and everything
Ritz Carlton
I asked him why he said yes.
He told me his mother persuaded him they could fight it
But they could appeal
But they did
Cuz it was like what he was saying
We just know that's not nothing that a judge really could be saying he ain't going to be
Saying and doing none of that
The court of appeals agreed
I got the sense reading their decision that the justices restraining to contain their displeasure
Aplia supposed to be knowingly intelligently and voluntarily made
That's the standard the fact that judge Gaul participated in the play by itself that's not necessarily unconscious
Traditional
The way judge called today
Can caulking the flea on his own without even asking the prosecutor the defense attorney
When you add in the pressure that threats
The way he made it obvious he thought Carlton was guilty before even seeing a scrap of evidence
The only thing Carlton heard could have knowingly and intelligently concluded the court said
Was that he was unlikely to get either a fair trial or a fair sentence after trial
Hermitage Golf
Under those circumstances they said the plea was not voluntary
It was coerced
Unconstitutional
And then took the extraordinary step of ordering that Carlton hurts case be reassigned
To a different judge
Forcefulness of the court of appeals decision was remarkable
Then something more remarkable happen
This summer almost 3 years after being locked up
Carlton heard went to trial this time in front of Judge John Russo
He was acquitted of all charges
So
What is this mean for judge call
For the moment
Nothing
I asked her to go whether he felt he'd screwed up and crawling hurts case
An answer
No
To me he said
This isn't a case about an innocent man being railroaded by the system
It's a case that clearly demonstrates how defendant and his attorney manipulated the system of justice to their benefit and betta murder
Attempted murder
Today Carlton was acquitted I called judge Russo
He presided over the trial but he's also the administrative judge for the Cuyahoga County Court of Common Pleas
He's not just ghost boss but he is the public face of
At the court
I called him on his cell right when you got home from the trial
Is there any
Consequence
For judge Gaul because of
Desk
I mean there isn't from me
So I don't know he's a colleague
Until I die
I don't reprimand or sanction him as in any way
After the verdict when Carlton heard was acquitted
Did Rousseau had apologized to him
Said coercion has no place in the system
Etc
Teresa clearly disapproved of how judge Gaul had handled the case
But now on the phone with me he was having rather me lie about that
What seems frustrating is that there isn't some automatic now review or some automatic
Yeah something vestigation something I mean
I've seen him do this and
His courtroom to other people
And if you're just doing that
Somebody needs to be later
There's a process
Whatever that's why I said says it has
By somebody
I would argue that judge Russo is a somebody
I talked to another Cuyahoga County Judge who was outraged by this case
He's a somebody
A couple of attorneys on this case whom I also spoke to
There's somebody's
The court of appeals judges who ruled in this case one of those somebody's
If any of these somebody's is afraid of reprisal from Judge Gall they can even complain anonymously
Did the Ohio Supreme Court
There's a state board on Grievances and discipline that has the authority to investigate and sanction judges just farther Madness
There goes actually been through that process once before in 2010
I won't give you the details but suffice it to say the Supreme Court Justices were appalled by what judge call had done and said in that
And then
They gave him a fairly minor reprimand
A six-month suspended suspension of his law license
Meaning he was able to stay on the bed
As of right now I've not heard that anyone has filed a complaint with the Supreme Court against judge Gaul because of hurricane
Nothing about the case has been reported in the local newspaper or on TV
No one's picketing outside
This courtroom
So just cause not to worry
He's been on the bench for 27 plus years
I take my role as per
Protecting the peace and dignity of the state of Ohio very very seriously and I wasn't elected to be stupid
He's being lied to is not going to sit back and pretend it's not happening
I wasn't
6 * to be a dumbass
As long as the voters keep voting for him then he's going to Keep On Keepin On
He's right
Yes there's the appeals court and the discipline board
But really every 6 years it's the voters who had the final say
Voters here. Everywhere
It's understood that
What are they now
For decades facing the same Irish and Italian names on the ballot almost all Democrats
What's a Russo / a Corrigan / Gallagher
I could even keep them straight
Mostly the voters are casting their ballots
And then staying far far away from the felony Courthouse
It doesn't touch that
And they don't touch it
Until there's a Shockwave
Crime and Punishment Shockwave the Billows out across the city
The county
The country
What's next time
Ontario
Cereals produced in Calhoun and me with additional reporting by Eataly has koskey
On this episode from Ira Glass Nancy Updike and Hannah joffe-walt
In fact checking by Ben Phelan sound design and mix by Stone Nelson music clearance by Anthony Roman set
Linda director of operations
General staff includes Emily Condon Julie Whitaker Cassie Holly and Francis Swanson
Our music is by Adam Dorn and how Wilner with additional music from Matt McGinley and Fritz Myers are theme song
Song is by Nick thorburn Remix by Adam Dorn special thanks to Gypsy Escobar and measures for justice Collins
Sweeney Corey Schaeffer Zoe route and the Justice programs office at American University School of public affairs David
Brown Kelly Mitchell and Julia less kerensky at the Robina Institute of criminal law and criminal justice
Sarah Andrews and Scott Shoemaker at the Ohio criminal sentencing commission
Ryan Hoffman and the pretrial Justice Institute
The art on our website was made by Adam made
He created the mural for this episode and Moss Studio did the animation please check it out at serial podcast
Yes. Org
That serial podcast. Org
Also thanks to Studio Rodrigo who did the web designs
In particular Ben Abril Juliet Wang or levite and Cory Wong
Support for serial comes from ZipRecruiter unlike many job site ZipRecruiter doesn't wait for candidates to find you
ZipRecruiter find some for you so you get qualified candidates fast
Tried free at ziprecruiter.com cereal
Ziprecruiter.com cereal
Support for serial comes from Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and Business website with Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and professional tools
Google
Use offer code professional
For discount on your first purchase
Serials production of This American Life and WBEZ Chicago