Serial season 3 is presented by ZipRecruiter the smartest way to hire
Later during the break from the CEO of a rapidly expanding matchmaking service
And then why ZipRecruiter is rated number one by Employers in the US based on hiring sites with over 1000 reviews on trustpilot
Tricep recruiter for free
Ziprecruiter.com
Cereal
Support for serial comes from Squarespace
Make your business official with Google in Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and a Business website with Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and professional tools from Google
It's the simplest way to look professional online
Visit squarespace.com Google
To start your free trial
And use offer code professional
For a discount on your first purchase
Google and Squarespace
Make it professional make it beautiful
Previously
Fun cereal
We're trying to get rid of cases if somebody is offered a plea to a misdemeanor you take it
Wonderful
I'm not going to press charges it doesn't matter if you're fine
But I have to take you to jail because you hit a police
And yes there's lots of people on the floor and there is another woman cake
Why can't you buy Frozen
From This American Life and WBEZ Chicago it's serial one quart
How's told week by week
I'm ceracade
A while back and maybe when I went to a meeting about community policing in Cleveland
The police department had invited people to a banquet hall for a workshop
Big round tables filled the space
Representatives from the police department or sprinkled throughout
Any stable had a moderator to keep things moving
The group is supposed to answer a bunch of questions about what kinds of problems they wanted police to deal with
My table was populated with rule-followers
They dutifully work their way down the list of questions
The kids are hanging out in abandoned house in your neighborhood what should the police do about that
I guess I would hope that they would start by talking to the kids and
Reminding them that some people have to go to sleep and get up and work the next
Stay and be a little more
Cigarette
Thank God for a manual
He was sitting a few tables to the east of me and he sending me over there
Because his table
Brass tacks
Lot of young African-Americans
Music particular we are afraid of the police officer
I'm just going to be on it
I have a guy with an attorney
The civil rights cases
A police Commander sitting at the table Langley responded to him
Chris that's a broad brush
That's a broad brush you just have not afraid of me you not afraid of me
Which we just met we just may I take your hand again
Exactly you see me you see me here today in my suit
This was the struggle of the table
The citizens wanting to talk historically culturally structurally
The cops wanting to talk specifically
Personally
Procedurally
The tables moderator was stalwart
She tried her level best to keep everyone on task there was just no way
We can have meeting for Dad
Mini if you said earlier we don't do a good job of getting people to come out
Would you do that way but how else do we
Send out to get feedback how can we engage more people
In this process
I want to know
What responsibilities or what
Right Discipline Do the police get for harassing the community
But I will make sure that
City of Cleveland Police Department have been corrupt for over 70 years when will
Can you go back and tell him it's right setting over 70 years that have been corrupt
When is
That's Amore Rising that one white police in here
They need to be in here here now
You tell him I said that okay you tell him I said it
This woman saying it
Miss rice
Is Samaria rice
Her son was Tamir rice
You've probably heard his name before
He was shot and killed by Cleveland Police a few years back
When he was 12 years old
Kitten playing around with a fake gun in a city park
Someone called nine-one-one the police drove up on em
Shot him in the stomach with in a couple of seconds
Whenever you talk about police or two police in Cleveland Tamir rice is right there
Below the surface on the surface
His killing causes Civic spasm
Between police and the public but still painful and still unresolved
Santa Maria rice shows up at a meeting about the community's expectations from police
She speaks with Dreadful moral Authority
At first I didn't understand what Miss rice wanted from this meeting
She didn't seem interested in the State admission of the workshop
List of questions
For the community
Because it's going to be for the police today
The reason is aggravated because
That's what this mean it should be about you
We have an estimate no that's the main thing that's the main topic
Episodes of anything else that night
All of that falls upon the Earth
One of the two police officers at the table jumps in
He says
Which I completely get
How can you help us do that
What is a solution
She's laughing
That's what I got it
But there's something absurdly wrongheaded to her and to a lot of people in Cleveland mostly black people
With this Earnest sounding question
How can you help us do that
Tamiya Raisa saying
Why are you turning his back on me
Why is it my job to help you do your job the way you're supposed to
You're the ones with the Cruisers in the handcuffs in the tasers and the god
She saying for god sakes
Physician
Heal thyself
A persistent slogan in Cleveland even four years after his killing
Is Justice for Tamir
The case was investigated by three different agencies
City state and federal
The mayor appointed his own panel for fourth investigation
None found that the officers broke the law
Steuben County prosecutor handle the case with the delicacy of a lumberjack calling it a perfect storm of human error
Mistakes and miscommunications
Should have come as a surprise to no-one when a grand jury declined to indict
Technically you can argue
How many police officers in prosecutors do that Justice was applied in Tamir rice his case
But it doesn't feel that way
Instead it feels like an open question haunting the courthouse
If you're harmed by police
What does it take
Define Justice in court
Knife feels like justice
One way to try
Is by filing a lawsuit
Suing the police
We're going to
Euclid Ohio
A little bird on the Eastside of Cleveland
To meet with
My client
Aramis Spencer
I was going with apartment
I'm going to talk to him about what happened to him a couple weeks ago
I'm in the car with Paul cristallo
Civil rights attorney
10 days earlier he sent me a text
Those photos of a guy in a hospital bed
Is face hugely puffed up on one side
Skin so tight from swelling that you could see the hospital lights reflected in his cheek
His left eye was submerged by the distortion
The guy's mother said he'd been beaten up by two police
She found Paul's number called him up
Asking is there anything we can do
I'll talk to her talk to Hermes suicide sounded cogency
Ciara
Had no criminal record to speak of
Few misdemeanor convictions but nothing violent
Spell decided
Does a good case
And we're going for me right you actually don't have business with him today as is for me
History of crack
Thank you
You're welcome
You know a lot of people in the building
Yes
Aramis his face hasn't fully healed
When I was still blood red
He described above his eyebrow
How long have you lived here
3 years
Where do you live before
I was living on 115th
Is that in Cleveland
Euclid is safer cleaner
Commerce
Then a lot of neighborhoods in Cleveland
Especially if you're from a dangerous neighborhood
Save got a teenager trying to keep out of the street
You might send them to his Andres grandma and you could put in school there
Airbus' building is called Richmond Hills
Apartment complex built in the 1960s
I'm so tired out by now
Irma's lives on the 5th floor
He wants me through his version of what happened that day
The police have a different version which will get to later
Therapist says he come downstairs to bum a cigarette from a friend on the 4th
And a couple cops were coming down the stairwell at one end of the hallway
Anime songs
Standing there knocking at his friends door
So sorry they can do that
I was going to tell you through the window
Yeah they saw me through the window I was standing at the door knocking at the door
And they came and stopped me
Right here where we standing
So they did they talk to you from there
Yes they were basically telling me to stop
You know just stay still
And they want to ask me some questions whatever
And it was two of them like mess we how y'all standing
And
Dachshund for my ID and asked me to searching for weapons in cops around the hallways before so that was
Surprised they work security here Moonlighting technically they're off-duty but they're in uniform and they are full
Police Powers most normal by the way lots of cops do this in Cuyahoga County
And Hermes had had run-ins with the police before and mostly they gone okay
Not counting the time he says he was jaywalking in East Cleveland and a cop stopped him and he ended up getting whacked in the knee repeatedly with a billy club in a rush
President put in jail for the night
But mostly he felt like he knew how to successfully navigate these interactions
With the Euclid cops that day he figured his best strategy was to cooperate and get it over with
He wasn't doing anything wrong he didn't want to give the cops any reason to suspect otherwise
So says he showed them his ID told him he lived upstairs
He said they asked if they could search him for weapons
Which means a pat down there feeling around for a gun
An air mass allowed in he didn't have a weapon on him he wasn't worried
What you did have on him with a blood
Marijuana cigarette in the pocket of his jeans
Which the cops found and which I'll get back to you because this measly blunt will become an outside player in the story
Anyway next thing Erma's new the officers went to arrest him
The other officer on this side
Acme
Put my hands behind my back I told them what am I under arrest where I'm asking like what am I under arrest for
And you never told me what I was under arrest for
At that point Irma says he stiffened his arm
The arm that one of the officers was trying to put behind his back
Who is resisting technically
And he's also asking
Why are you arresting me what did I do
No answer
Discussion
And then
The one on your side
He was like shut the f****** and need me and my boss
And I went down
Orissa my balls immediately like this
The other officer trying to tell me on the ground
I guess as if he was going to
Don't you know the procedure how they
You know if you resist arrest
They have a right to throw you to the ground
Put your hands behind your back
But they didn't put my hands on her better have one hand behind my back
And then other one to the kicking my face while I was on the ground
The kickin' Irma says is what caused the damage to his face
Broken orbital bone
That's about around your eye
A public defender in Cleveland told me how everyone's always whining about a broken orbital bone
What an air mass is case it was bad enough that the Euclid ER folks transferred him to a bigger Hospital in Cleveland
To make sure I would be okay
Anyway Aramis is down on the ground when cop is kicking him in the face another cop is holding back his right arm
His left arm is pinned underneath them
He can't get it free
Hermes got down on the gross hallway carpet to xiaomi
I didn't need him to do that but it seems as if he wanted to replay each step
Wish I could understand
It only been 10 days since it happened
Dan got his mind around it
I'm right here
My head is right here
The blood is leaking from my face
Going down dropping
What's the weather like this
So what happened was
He pays me right here
Something like this it takes me right here
Pays me and my neck
Tase me in the back of my thigh
And taste me and my left chest right here
And then I finally I told him like
I'm going to let you put my hands behind my back
And they put my hands behind my back pick me up
Oh my God is that your blood right there
There was a smear of blood with a big drip going down the wall at exactly the height of air masses I
Which isn't very high by the way
Nervous about 5657 I'd say
X-lite
The police tase him about 7 times
Not the full deployment each time where the wires come out in everything
The Lesser taser setting where it shocks and burns
Irma said he could feel electricity shoot down his legs
There's the burn marks to from the city mean
Aaron's furniture some spots that are feet where the carpet fibers were melted and Clump together
Is Hazel rare
Oh my God
Burn through my skin just like a burn through the carpet
So
Irma said while all this was going on the police were cursing at him he was cursing back
He said I just kept asking them why why are y'all doing this
What did I do to deserve this
He says they would not answer
Aramis if he'd been scared or enraged
The word he used was uncomfortable
Is it the whole thing made him feel uncomfortable which seems like an oddly muted way to express being kicked in the head by a cop
He also said he was trying not to let what happened distract him mentally not let it take him out of his everyday life
He said he just turned 30 a few days earlier
His family his girlfriend had gathered around him to cheer him up
He tried to celebrate
I got the sense he wasn't ready to stare too hard it would happen
For now
He'd leave it at uncomfortable
There's a security camera in the hallway right near the door he was knocking on
But it was pointed straight down we saw it so it seemed quite possible that even if it were working at the time
Apparently wasn't
Mapreduce footage of the floor
As the cops walked Aramis out of the building he says they were talking s*** to him
It doesn't remember exactly what they said
One more false move
Going to make it even worse for you the next
Then they put him in an ambulance
Backup an air mass is apartment we talked about that marijuana cigarette he had in his pocket
Dermis is thinking the police had no right to arrest him in the first place
That's why he's different his arm because he says he genuinely did not understand what was going on
Because of the amount of weed that I had
It was not arrested or charged
So I can never be resisting arrest for when blind
That's not impossible
Blend on me and believe me I have situations like this before
Where officers will take the weed
Throw it in the grass
Or throw it away
Flush it down the toilet
Because there's no probable cause to arrest
Sometimes officers write you a ticket
I'm not like I still couldn't be arrested no matter
No matter how mean are you sure that's true and Euclid though maybe that's true in Cleveland
That sure is a misdemeanor offense
And it's not a rustable
Is that right so
Lawyer in the room
Explain jet lazy could that
Aramis is incorrect
And Euclid Ohio any amount of weed can be charged as an M1
First degree misdemeanor
Possibility of $1,000 fine 6 months in jail
Just over the City Line back in Cleveland Ms would be correct
One blunt probably would be at
At most
But not here in Euclid
Ohio takes home rule very
Seriously
Cuyahoga County has 59 different municipalities
Each one has its own set of ordinances
Most of them align their city codes with Ohio state law
Which treats less than 100 grams of marijuana as a minor misdemeanor
But two of them treat any amount of marijuana as an M1
Broadview Heights
Little town down South
And Euclid
Euclid made its ordinance harsher in 1998
I'm not sure why
But it's worth noting that the city's black population was growing then
Curfew decades white people have been moving out and black people have been moving in
About 60% African
Euclid city government though city council six out of nine members are white mayor is white
Police chief is White City prosecutors White City law director is White City Judges White
And it's got the harshest weed law in the county
Just saying
The best Paul can do for Hermes
It's really the only thing he can do
It's a try to make everyone involved in sending Hermes to the hospital pay
How to drive back to Cleveland Paul talks about what he would do next
He also anticipated with the city's lawyer would like
Which he can do with confidence
Because Paul used to be that lawyer
Used to work the other side of these cases
Defending the government
The cops
He works for the city of Cleveland
Then he was a partner in a law firm that contracted with insurance companies to defend against civil rights claim
I was good at his job
Any make good money
Here to BMW
Convertible and hardtop
After while he couldn't stomach it
Cuz he felt like he was working for the wrong side
And start to affect
Is health so they switched over
So frequently mentioned that he drives a Hyundai now
And then I'll say
I'm fine with that
He's not totally fine with that
Aramis is case won't be huge money
Aramis wasn't permanently injured not physically
The poor things you can at least get him something
Maybe in the tens of thousands
Is a complication they have to take care of first though before Paul can get a lawsuit going
Nothing not small matter of air masses criminal charges
The Euclid Police cited Aramis
4 crimes
Drug abuse
Resisting arrest
Theft and criminal damaging
Paul said that list
Pretty typical
So I'm hitting you with four charges
And so now let's negotiate down
So I'm going to load you up so this way I mean it over overcharges and the prosecutor little something else
A little bit more left
To still get you to plead to something
I was confused
House where Aramis and Paul
What does theft and criminal damaging or about
Until I read the police report
There's a page long narrative
Didn't the cops describe an event with roughly the same Contours as what Hermes told me
But very different detail
The officers didn't talk to me for this
Story and just to say neither of them has been disciplined for what happened that night
In the report they say that after They confiscated the marijuana
Hermes try to take it out of one office
They say Aramis was fighting with
Pushing them
But everyone was getting stung by the taser in the process
They say Hermes tried to take the taser away from them
That's the FAFSA parent
And if the tasers cartridge got pulled off
And the blast door broken off
The term has knocked one officers glasses off his face
Breaking them
They never mention kicking Aramis
They do describe kneeing him in the crotch
Anclote close-fisted strikes
To his face and head
Aramis has got to get out from under these charges
Strategically
Quietly
Right now I almost doesn't think he should have to plead any
But Paul thinks it might actually be better for the civil case if he does plead to something minor
And that's hilarious is looking at
He's like like I should walk out of this
Literally
With no
Problem with that is
Nephew just take this hard-line
Like I'm not going to plead the even up
Minor misdemeanor some one of them
Play U2
I think that's going to
Raise
The flags that that
He's up to something that that he's standing on principle he's looking to sue you for the injuries
Last thing Paul wanted the stage is for Euclid to know it is being sued
Because if they know they will dig in on the criminal charges
Tell first step
Delay
Hermes was supposed to have his initial court appearance
Today actually
Are they got it postponed a couple weeks
Ticket is FaceTime to go back to normal
I don't want him walking into court looking like he just got his ass
Why
Again because
People asking a so what happened then
If you go in front of the judge
Sure
Yeah young man what happened to you
Prosecutor might notice you could police officers who happen to be in court that day they might notice
Start asking around
Paul wants Hermes to be unremarkable
Just there to take care of these charges and go on home
No big deal
Second step
Hire a beard
Paul himself has Delilah while the criminal case moves through the Municipal Court
He will not be shepherding Hermes through
Instead he's hired at Dependable local attorney who won't raise any eyebrows and Euclid
Alt farming it out in part because his specialty is not criminal defense
The more the point is the folks in Euclid C Paul's name on the docket
The Jig Is immediately up
They will know they're facing a civil lawsuit probably a big fat civil lawsuit
Because they will have heard of Paul already
Or else they'll Google him and I'll see
Alright relocate
Also known as 137 shots case
Back in 2012 two people in a car man and woman both African-American both homeless
We're driving past the Justice Center downtown
Police said the couple's fired a gun out the window toward them
What subsequent investigation suggested the noise the officers heard might have been the car backfiring they never located a gun
Spaghetti chase them
Which isn't that strange except for the debacle that ensued
The chase wolf through residential neighborhoods then onto the highway and back off the highway
20 miles and 62 police cars later
The chase ended in East Cleveland parking lot
We're police fired a total of 137 shots in the car killing both people inside
Officer alone Sergeant Michael brelo shot at them 49 times
Scrambled onto the hood of the car to shut down at them through the windshield
At close range was indicted for voluntary manslaughter
A judge found him not guilty
There's no proof brelo had actually killed them the judge
Explain an opinion
Possible they were already dead by the time he got onto the hood
The families of the two people who were killed
Sued
Paul represented one of them
And the city of Cleveland settled for $3000000
Is Paul's biggest media case
Also his biggest payout
Lately he's been struggling a little
He's not into the hustle
Doesn't show up at Memorial Gatherings looking solemn
Doesn't slip a weeping relative his card it doesn't know website or do social media
He's white which isn't always helpful and
Possess
Aramis is case is an order of magnitude smaller than 137 shots case
Or the Tamir rice case
Don't finish out his name during a protest
Call Tommy the smaller cases
They matter
Because they ricochet
Is Russia a lot of people go through incidents like this
He says the speeding will knock around inside Aramis head
And then it will rebound off of them
Out into the city
It's me.
Do you want to talk about how
You know we need to come together as a society
And
You know
Black lives matter
All life matter
Please have a hard job and
Listen to what the
Please tell you to do and you got to obey the law don't be a criminal
I mean the realities is now you just traded somebody who I mean
He's busy this walking
Perpetuation
Don't trust the police
He now knows
Let that happen
And all he
He had on
What is a blunt
In his own apartment
Not late at night
No drugs
No alcohol no gun
No criminal activity
But the blind
And that's what happened to him
That this will mess with
Like if you stick with the store and we follow up
You'll see
I mean it'll it'll f*** with them
GS family he has friends they're all going to know what happened. Going to see the pictures
And so it becomes part of his life scrap this is this this this has become something that
You know is going to be told and retold and photos are going to be shared and Andre share
You know on and on and on and on and it just one guy in Euclid Ohio
A study published in 2016 found that
Reports of police brutality not only contribute to a quote Spirit of legal cynicism
They also cause people to not call the cops when they need them
They make entire cities less safe
The researchers looked at 911 calls before and after an Infamous case in Milwaukee
The 2004 beating of a guy named Frank Jude
They found it for a year afterwards there were twenty-two thousand fewer 9-1-1 calls in Milwaukee Residence Inn
Black neighborhoods especially or far less likely to report crime
And at the same time that people were reporting fewer crimes murders in Milwaukee Rose by 32%
The goal of Paul's lawsuit
Aside from getting Hermes some justice
Dim sum dough
Is DeForest police to account for their behavior
Answer for it
And I asked him
Setting his own livelihood aside
Is it possible that his involvement could actually be hampering progress
Seramis went to the police department in complaint
The supervisors
Or the use of force in the officer's report triggered an internal investigation
And say that process were allowed to play out without the Specter of a lawsuit
Isn't it possible that apartment would fix itself
That is no that's
I mean
I know you probably hate
People say it's a great question
I love when people say that
It is
Because
I mean you know if I could even
We brought your question a little bit
I know what you're asking is
But the way you're handling is Paula kind of how you're at your ear
Triangulating orchestrating if you well you're denying the city of Euclid
And the police department the opportunity
To do this right on their own
And you're absolutely right
You're right I am doing that but that's because
Distrust
If I were to kind of do what you're saying are we were to March down there and fill out a citizen
Complaint and talk to them about constitutional rights and excessive force
I'm leaving it up to them now
Set to kind of say well you know what yeah this was awful we better do an intro investigate
Guess we better do what's right
And
And that just hasn't been my experience
I thought just hasn't been my experience
I think when you do that
They don't own it be the lawyer up
It's never situation
We're like
Did the city of the
The police are like wow
You know we really met
Is that we need to do the right thing here
It's it's
Always
And what are you talking about
This was just
Certified
Your client is a liar
And
We got insurance
Like I just
Iodide I just had
Based on my experience
Did that would happen
This is what bothered Paul the most when he worked the defense side he said
The city's disdain for the plaintiffs
A person with following excessive force claim
Runaway Paul says everyone would attack the character of the complainer
Has publicly even among themselves privately
Lawyers adjusters insurance companies of police officers the police chief the mayor
Their attitude was
What kind of loser
What kind of scumbag
But sue the police
That's after the break
This is the road to hire
Brought to you by ZipRecruiter
Talia Goldstein is the CEO of three day rule
Personalized matchmaking service
Scour the streets of your city
Looking for just the right person for you
And then
They do the most painful part for you
First date
They take people out and see if they're a good fit for you
Asking them to tough questions so that you don't have to
Do I did a match meeting with a guy and at some point you ask what body type are you most attracted to
And the guy said to me I don't want pear shape
Like you
Rude
How to make sure that you don't have to go on a date with that guy
And instead
You'll get the sensitive Rockstar you've always wanted
Tanya needs to make sure that she is passionate tenacious matchmakers
The kinds of people will chase your potential future spouse down the street for you
The super specialized roll
Talia searches for her employees on ZipRecruiter
Are there other resources out there
Where you at
Hunza resumes that you have to sit through
I find was different Critter you end up getting
The curated list
High quality
People that's because ZipRecruiter is powerful matching technology
Actively scans thousands of resumes to identify people with the right skills education and experience for
For your job
Actively invites them to apply
Wait till ZipRecruiter is going on your bad interview
For you
Exactly
Get matched with employee of your dreams
ZipRecruiter for free
Ziprecruiter.com cereal
That's ziprecruiter.com
Flash serial
ZipRecruiter the smartest way to hire
Support for serial comes from Squarespace
Make your business official with Google in Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and a Business website with Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and professional tools from Google
It's the simplest way to look professional online
Visit squarespace.com Google to start your free trial
And use offer code professional
For a discount on your first purchase
Google and Squarespace
Make it professional make it beautiful
Right now
These past few years
Is an era of law enforcement soul-searching
Or supposed to be
All over the country police departments are meant to be considering deeply and anxiously
Whether they're using Force properly whether they are operating without bias whether they're listening to and hearing the sea
Citizen State Police
In Albuquerque in New Orleans in Portland Oregon in Ferguson Missouri in Baltimore and in Cleveland
After the hundred thirty-seven shots case when were the couple was killed by police after the chase
First the Ohio attorney general investigated
Then the feds came in
Civil rights division of the Department of Justice
Less than 2 weeks after Tamir rice was killed they issued their report
The Cleveland Police Department was engaging in a pattern or practice of using unlawful excessive force
Among many other problems
The articles about the breadth and depth of the overall find eggs
Exhausted all the usual words
Scathing
Embarrassing
Staggering jaw drop
The report was not all that different from the previous doj investigation of the Cleveland Police
A decade earlier
This time the city promise things would be different
In 2015 they entered into a consent decree with the federal government
A federal judge would oversee massive reforms in the CDP
Citizen complaints don't bring change
If internal investigations don't bring change if criminal charges against cops don't break
If Pakistan has lawsuits don't bring change
Perhaps of federally mandated consent decree
A decree
Just one click from a Fiat
Would persuade police the change is nigh
Perhaps not
Political nonsense
This is detective Steve Loomis
Until recently he was the president of the Cleveland Police patrolmen's Association the police Union here
Clevelanders have a certain political persuasion including some cops I'm sure
Just left their foreheads and groan
Please no not Steve
Because they know
Bald-headed me be fisted Steve Loomis
The guy who dress convincingly in a Santa hat at the Department's Christmas party
And as the dirty biker hillbilly dude when he worked Undercover
Will say whatever the hell he wants
Steve dettelbach kiss my ass
What's his b*******
Steve dettelbach was us attorney for the Northern District of Ohio his signature is at the bottom of the doj report
Airport which devoted several pages to the substandard way in which the Cleveland Police Department dealt with citizen
Complaints
We really don't
Care about civilian
It's not that we don't not that we don't care that we get that we don't
My laughter here is born of shock
Not Mirth
I'm not going to say I like Steve Loomis I can't get there
Some of the positions he inhabits our too awful
President Obama has blood on his hands for the police officers killed in Dallas
Racist and anti-muslim tweets by a CDP sergeant
Are the First Amendment right of every American
Etcetera
I appreciate Steve Loomis
I appreciate that he's got a sense of humor about himself
I appreciate that he appears to be a True Believer
That he is sincere when he says even the lowliest rookie patrolman does more to help this community than any other person in government
I appreciate that Steve Loomis give us six hours of his time
In one day
6 hours
Sat there in his Union office pact with Trump paraphernalia
Also one or two cartoons that I called racist
He called political
Explaining his world to us
Arguing with us congeniality
Decide to clevelanders he'll complain that the media only quote Steve
Because he's colorful and available
Jose Steve doesn't represent us
What's true no other Cleveland officers were permitted to talk to us on the record and I know from off-the-record conversations that
Not all of them think like Steve
But that aside Steve is the man whom the rank-and-file elected as their leader and spokesman he does
Or did officially represent the police
So here we are
I know where activist
Stand on the question of reform
I know where a lot of non-active
The stand on the question of police reform
But I wanted to know is reform even possible
Are the police willing
As Union President Steve Loomis set on the Cleveland Community police commission
CPC
A group mandated into existence as part of the consent decree
It supposed to make recommendations on new policies for community policing bias-free policing use-of-force
Inner participate
With a full heart
Absolute the full heart
The problem that we have on the timer
Like literally had not shown
Yeah you want to believe though
The rhetoric out there
In fact there's been a steady drip of articles in the local
Cool press about Steve spotty attendance at meetings
And the many calls for his resignation
In what article he explained that he'd appointed himself as a commissioner
Because he didn't want to subject any of his patrolman to quote that farce of a commission
Still he insisted he is not an to reform
We can always improve on what we do here
He told me and I'm happy to take that challenge on
But when I asked him about possible reforms in Cleveland
Reforms that are being discussed and implemented all over the country
Vigorously whacked each one aside
Slowing down police interactions with suspects
And hopes of avoiding the need for
Perforce
Everybody wants to talk about
The escalation it's just really sexy word for talking
You know it is good that's what guess what
That's what we've done since the beginning of time
Bias
Steve would like to see one study linking implicit bias to police actions and reactions
Racial profiling
I'm not going to sit here and say that that doesn't
Happened somewhere else
And a world I am going to sit here and say
In the city of Cleveland
There's no way that it
It's not supported in fact
Right
Are you supports policy
Is coming out
Nothing is going to be atrocious
More restrictions on how and when police can use a gun is going to endanger his officers
Cuz they'll think twice
Don't be afraid of getting in trouble for doing it wrong
And then it'll be too late
The common complaint among police
Tasering people
You know why you can't teaser juvenile
Okay
Yellow
Tamir rice nobody wants to talk about it but to be racist 5-foot 791
All right
Annie's 12 years old
Does Steve the Tamir rice case is the perfect example of how people misunderstand and willfully distort what the police
Still other fixes make no sense
To me the way Steve talked about the Tamir rice case was a perfect example of why so many people in Cleveland believe the police has
0 capacity for self-reflection
Much less self-correction
The officer who shot Tamir was new Young still on probation
I pointed out that Steve himself as an experienced officer had avoided shootings by lowering his weapon
You just giving me a couple examples
So why is he saying in the Tamir rice situation any officer would have done the same thing
You wouldn't have done
And you're telling me right now you would I absolutely would have done the same
Would not have done the same
You're telling me you wouldn't
You want to get into rice we're going to get in the train tracks
So it began
Steve reiterated as he has many times
The number one camera was a big kid
As if that made him blameworthy
A child in a man's body
Bottom line
There's no denying that
Nobody can dispute
Number to Tamir rice noodle exactly why those
Policeman
We're driving that marked police car towards him
Right
He is a product of the street
He is not a product of
Loving
Home
Hang on
I did hang on and it got worse
The salvaging of Samaria rice
But I'm not going to dignify by repeating here
Steve has said unkind things about the rice family
In the past
He also helpfully suggested they should use the money they got from a lawsuit to educate kids about the dangers of
Guns
He wasn't worried about his tone or its implications then
He's not worried now
He believes the factor with him
We disagreed about whether the police drove up to close to Tamir whether they drove up
Too fast with her Tamir pulled the gun from his waistband with of the shooting of Tamir rice was a mistake at all
Okay we can disagree till the cows come home
Poem about what should have happened or why it
And my guess is we probably would
Supported in fact
That's fine but I think we can all agree it was a
Horrible
Horrible outcome right
They want I know you have I know you have
So what I'm
Wondering is
Do you see any fixes
Is there a thing where you're like
Sure isn't change that I think could have avoided
That's that isn't only on Tamir
They haven't they haven't
It's absolutely artem
It's on any suspect get shot by the police
Actions by suspects
Cause reactions by police office
Justified react
Did police take away any lessons then from the Tamir rice case
Sure he said we always learn a lot
So what is it
I don't know
It was in fact the only time I stumped him in our 6 hours together
I asked him several times
And he could not come up with one thing that wasn't two mirrors fault
It sounds like you're saying there's nothing that needs
2 Chainz
That's what needs to change
That's not what I'm saying what I'm saying is that those changes need to be based in reality
But what should the changes be
Not La La Land
Why do we fix a tan
Focus
On
Tamir rice
That's the beer question to me
Is we want to change our entire profession
Based on
A couple different
When you're saying why are we fixating on these desk
Because people are like enough is enough is enough is enough
They're saying it's one one is two
Too many one accident like this is too many let's fix
Can you race was not an accident
Tamir rice was pulling a gun out of his waist
All right we're saying you shouldn't have died for it
He shouldn't have died
I this is what I'm saying I think this is what we're all asked
But what's frustrating is
We don't go
When somebody calls us and tells us that somebody should have rec center with a gun
That's the only way to fix it
Right
Black panther hat
I think Steve might actually believe what he's saying here
The police are never to blame for harming someone in the line of duty
If you end up dead or hurt it's always because of something you did or didn't do
It follows then that the only ones who need to reform
Are the citizens
The name of Cleveland's 1500 patrolman
Steve Loomis is folding his arms
Inside his petulance is also a threat
Not like how we do business fine
. arresting people
See how you like your sitting at
It's the same stance some police officers have taken in Chicago and Minneapolis
New York and Baltimore
Cop out
Speed limit says Cleveland's problem isn't rotten police or poorly trained police or faulty policies
Problem he says is understaffing
He's not wrong even people who can't abide Steve Loomis agree that Cleveland Police Department is overburdened and under
Plaid and poorly paid
This of course is the limit of law enforcement everywhere
Civilians
We need your tax dollars
But we don't need
Is there oversight
A Cota here
A few weeks after we spoke
Steve Loomis was replaced as Union president have been voted out of office
And I'm not saying these things are necessarily connected but
8 months later the team in charge of overseeing police reforms in Cleveland release some stats
Showing the during the first five months of 2018
Police use-of-force in Cleveland has decreased by nearly 40%
Compared to the year before
It was too soon to claim victory the report said that it was encouraging
Aramis Spencer
Okay
We are here on this
Motion to suppress
5 months after he been arrested
Aramis went to court for hearing
By now the city of Euclid knew a civil lawsuit was probably coming
Which is why after all this time before criminal charges were still hungered in his case File
It's all predicted the city was unrelenting
The prosecutor was not going to drop them
Definitely not the resisting arrest
That's the linchpin charge
The resisting
The one that could really mess up air masses civil case
Because of Aramis gets convicted of resisting that could justify the officer's use-of-force
Not necessarily the excessiveness of the beating it doesn't give him carte blanche
But it does allow the officers to do what they have to do to subdue a suspect
Tavares has to eat that resisting charge it could shrivel his civil claim
That's why the city won't budge on the resist
And wireless won't budge either
Instead today Aramis is here on a motion sensor
Suppress
He's trying to get all the charges dropped by claiming that the police had no Reasonable Suspicion to stop him in that hallway
And then after they made the faulty stop they had no probable cause to search him
What you make the actual blunt they found on him
The fruit of a poisonous tree
That's the legal metaphor
So no legal stop no legal arrest
No case
When I walk into the courtroom Mary case of the city prosecutor said to me
You do know this is just a hearing right
I do I said
Then she and the other lawyers left the room
For a while
I sat waiting in the empty jewelry box
Hermes the two cops are masses mother all set on the benches
No one said anything
I wrote in my notes
It's like a tomb in
I heard a ruckus to the wall behind me where the prosecutor's office is
People were shouting
After while the lawyers filed back into the courtroom
Looking peeved
Mary case in a couple other lawyers sat on one side
How the other Aramis and his defense attorney
The local guy Paul had enlisted
Spiros gonakis
Judge Deborah lebarron announced
And
As I advised all the parties I have syroco made from the cereal
Podcast who is asking to record these
Proceedings with casein
Thank you.
You're at this time the city would request
A continuance of this hearing
We have some concerns with respect to this
During being recorded for a public podcast
It seemed I had been the cause of the Ruckus
We have an interest in protecting the city of Euclid
Any flicker of an ocean I had that the city's intentions were forthright
Withered now
Before I figured Wilshire there triangulating
Just like Paul
It also assumed that they were at least Prosecuting Aramis in good faith
Because they believe the cops
Believe he committed these crimes
And deserve punishment
But you don't try to kick a reporter out of a public proceeding unless there's something unsavory about what's about to happen
Judge LeBaron deny the prosecutor's request
For continuance
It again
Hearing would not touch on anything that came after the search so nothing about the resisting or the beating
This was only about the validity of the stop in the search
Mary Kay Satin Spiros gonakis took both cops through it Moment by moment that's where the law tends to snap into place
An instant
First up with officer Shane Rivera
He explained that he and his partner officer Michael amiott
I've been working an off-duty detail that day at the Richmond Hills Apartment Complex
Grammys live
He said they've been working this particular detail for two years there been problems in the building
Drug trafficking break-ins
Beginner usual soup of the building starting at the 5th floor
The top floor
Working their way down
The Saltair Missy said as they came down the stairs to the 4th floor who's knocking on a door
And when he was
Knocking on the door
Call if anyone answered the door
No one answered the door
At any point did the individual take keys out open the door to the apart
Usain Aramis looked suspicious right then
Reasonably so
Why would you keep knocking on a door if no one's answering
This is what burglars do in the building
Knock and then when no one answers they kick in the door
Felt as I approached I asked him if he lived in the complex he said he did
And I asked if you knew
Who I'll look at that particular requirement
And he said he did not
And
Aramis was squirming at the defense table
Shaking his head
Stifled
He told me he was knocking at his friend's apartment door
Because you wanted a cigarette
His friend wasn't home but his friend's wife was there asleep
Emma said she eventually woke up and did open the door
He said she saw him being beat up and that the police told her to go back inside
And she did
But Hermes can't say anything about that now
She's not taking the stand
The Lord didn't want the prosecutor to get a crack at cross-examining Hermes prior to trial
So he's got to suck it up
Every defendant I spoke to while I was in Cleveland eventually asked
What do I get to say my thing
When do I get to explain to the judge what happened
The answer
Often
Is never
Very anxious and nervous and
Japanese hands in his pockets as soon as you saw it
He was advised a couple of times to take his hands out of his pockets
Did he take his hands out of his pocket
Yes but it kept putting back in and say run
Three four times
And I'm how did you react to him putting his hands back in the socket
Nervously I mean makes police officer nervous
Because typically when people keep reaching into their pockets it's a
Indicator that the Apache band or a possibly weapon on their person
Soon it was faris's
Oscar Rivera wedding Spiros gonakis I represent Hermes
I'm going to ask you a few questions on cross-examination
The right
Put my hands in my pockets while I asked questions I don't want to make you nervous
I don't have any contraband.
Heroes is a spirited attorney and energetic performer
Spiros tried to show that Hermes wasn't a menacing figure in that hallway
Is this the guy
Knocking on the door
Knocking as opposed to
He wasn't doing that
Knocking on the door
He wasn't screaming
Let me in
What are you doing
What's going on
Okay
Next up officer Michael amiott
He seemed more comfortable on the standing officer Rivera
Eden so nervous
It wasn't defensive
Propose mr. Spencer he was still at the door I walked past
And as I approached him I could smell the odor marijuana
They got stronger
Westerly coming from him
And I stop
This is key to making the Stop Kosher
The smell of raw marijuana emanating from Aramis
6%
It's what allows them to detain Aramis
The prosecutor is cemented in the record
It's in your experience as a police officer can you smell raw marijuana
In a bag inside someone
And has marijuana smell the same regardless of what
Amount
Sometimes it stronger than others
Know what I smell right now
Reasonable suspicion
The officer amiott did not smell an unlit blunt wrapped in a baggie and Aramis his jeans pocket
It's not impossible you smelled it
But the level of confidence he's exhibiting here that he can smell any amount of marijuana in a person's pocket
In the hallway of a building where I am certain marijuana is not scarce
No one in the courtroom seems to register any skepticism about that
Apart from Spiros
You guys are basically
That's unnecessary
I'll take that back
Officer amiott says after he smelled the marijuana he asked Aramis if he had any drugs on him
Saving equals hands up like this I said you have any drugs on you put his hands up like this
Okay and
What do you do if your placenta
And did you find anything
Yeah I went into his pocket on epoxy was reaching into
It was a small bag of marijuana was probably a side wasn't very big wrapping a baggie
Each efficient beat of this hearing
The cops are chipping away at Hermes his chances for success
Criminal and civil
Aramis is a scary door knocker
He smells like marijuana he seems nervous
He keeps putting his hands in his pockets
He lets me search him for drugs
Is all very neat
And all very different from what Hermes says actually happened
Then comes one more
A to Z right at the end
Mary Casey squeezes it in during her closing
The testimony wasn't he patted the outside of the pocket first
Faded pat-down
He felt a ball
Objection
Services like whoa whoa whoa a bulge
Where does Bones come from
The Bulge could suggest a weapon
Which could give officer amiott reason to go into Hermes
The pockets we can make
Research legal which can make the charges stick which could hurt the civil law
Siri says wait up
Mei himself never said anything about a bulge
Event that did not happen
He said
And there was a ball
The judge says I heard it
I wrote it down right here
Just telling you
That's in my notes
So no further argument
It was over Mary Casey looks very pleased at the end
Chatting animatedly with the other lawyers at
Her table
Chino's
Everyone in the courtroom knows
And who you going to believe contest
The judge tends to presume the cops are telling the truth
So her side virtually always wins
Spiros knows it too
Expected the police to say most of what they said today
But the Bulge thing that was a new one
Out in the hallways grosses still arguing
You can't just invent testimony
Play pattern
Did you hear anything about
Where did not say that he felt a ball
Stress is right
I have the tape
Despite what the judge thought she heard
Officer amiott did not mention a bulge
Balls or no balls
Girls tries to boost Aramis spirits
This bulge is going to be an issue
Five network will form
He just can't even if he can stop you
Marijuana
Does it mean he can go inside of your pocket
Reasonable Suspicion means he can
Keep you there and figure out what's what's going on right he can catch you down for officer safety
But that would have been had a much through conversation on direct examination as to I patted him down
Over the top I felt a ball
We thought it was a weapon
The Battle of the Bulge
Let me know about that
Just lying down
Aramis is Mom Kali the only one who laughed at my joke
Aramis himself is brimming with frustration
It's been 5 months
He's having the fight criminal charges he considers illegitimate
Because of what happened in the hallway of the building management stuck a 3-day notice on his apartment door telling him he had to move out or else
Hbase eviction
He said they told him the incident was a violation of the buildings rules
I got an extension still
He said his girlfriend was harassed
In front of the building he thinks it was the same officers who stopped her
He said she told him she stayed with Aramis upstairs
The restaurant Warren
And today he's just listen to police officers tell a version of the original incident which Bears little resemblance to his own
He said they asked him to stop from down the hall
Before they even got near him they said stop don't move
He says he never told him he didn't know whose door he was knocking on
Anyway why would he be knocking on a door of a person he doesn't know
They never ask me that question who is Dory this is the never ask me that
Dachshund they stopped me and asked me search me for weapons they never ask me anything about any drugs anything's
Weather today
That's completely false
They lied under oath
I'm sitting here watching them off
They lie
Judge LeBaron deny dermis is motion to
Suppress
Which means that resisting charge is sticking
Not good
Yeah it's always something like that the police always have
Scratch with a Prosecco
Paul cristallo hadn't gone to the suppression hearing
He was still trying to remain invisible and you could
But Spirit-filled him in and he read the judge's opinion
Which amounted to
The stop
Search all legal
Xi'an get to the balls
She wrote the based on the suspicious door-knocking in the smell of marijuana
For good
If it's not
Smelling marijuana for the smell of alcohol
It's
He made a furtive movement
With his hands
He kept moving his hands
And I wasn't sure you know that's that's
Find a baby he's got a weapon
He was acting nervous and I think in fact they even
Testified that he was acting
I mean it's just
But that's your script
Everybody says for the flu
Everybody smells
Another phrase you hear a lot in these cases
Reaching toward his waistband
That's where Guns live
Waistbands
In a written report that you could officers wrote that Aramis was quote fighting with officers and pulling both arms together toward his waist
Panaderia
And a little lower down more strikes were delivered until Spencer stop fighting and stopped reaching toward his waistband
Aramis had no weapon
I know nothing tucked in his waistband
Why then in the midst of a fight would he be reaching toward his waistband
Because waistband is a magic word
Furtive
Like odor of raw marijuana
A plant's a strong seed of reasonable suspicion
The blossoms into a tree of probable cause
Which can produce untainted fruit
Justified use of force in response to resisting illegitimate arrest
I asked Paul
Back when he was working for insurance companies defending cops
Whether he done the same thing Euclid was doing now
When they could see a civil lawsuit in the distance
Would he meet with City officials are cops about doubling down on the criminal charges
To try to stop the civil case from getting traction
City Hall
Office
Flying together
When you're trying this kind of reluctantly is this
Is this why
Violet custom button that's that's like I shouldn't be like why are you
Because
I mean
Letting you know I'm doing my job you know what I was doing and I was doing my job
Antilla
And I don't regret doing my job and you know it
I think it's part of
Letting the police
Dynamic is
How much of an airtight defense is the best offense if you
And I said hesitantly a reluctant
Only because
NIU.
But you know I mean I'm not proud of that
OIC
Yeah yeah yeah no I didn't I didn't I didn't ask it as a way to be like aren't you I didn't mean to
I was going to know you.
I always were asking practically it was like are you talking from Once
Do you know
Or you just
Like I suspect
What's going on are you like no I know this is what's going on because I
Is it isn't surprising what's with problem
Surprising is
How
It remains
It cast
Source
Of aggravation
It's still hard to watch it is only to see this happening
Courtroom people
Making payments on the stand that aren't necessarily accurate they know it
But they have it of course
It's upsetting to see if a police officer lies
What's more upsetting is when a system of laws and procedures kicks in to support and sanitize those lies
So that it looks and sounds as if Justice is happening
But even wager that the officers in the prosecutor and the judge they all swear with conscience is clear
The Aramis is hearing was fair by the book
If Aramis wants these police officers to be held accountable for beating him he's now gotten the message the criminal court is
Probably the last place you should look for help
A few months later I got a call from Paul on my cell phone
Oh my God
I know
I was driving in a car heading to the airport in South Carolina
The connection was terrible
Who's this is so cute
Literally is like
This is that Miracle because they were going to come off the resisting
A video that appeared on the internet
Oh wow
A white police officer pummeling a black guy in the street
After traffic stop
A woman watching from inside a building across the street had recorded in on her phone
Her child was next to her
You doing okay Mommy
What's the biggest doing
The officer beating the motorist
Michael amiott
The you could weed smell her
The video bounce all over the internet
Made its way into national news
What happens to a case then
When everyone's paying attention
What's next time
En Serio
Cereals produced by Julie Schneider Emmanuel Jodi Ben Calhoun and meet with additional reporting by Eataly uskoski
Editing on this episode from Ira Glass and Nancy Updike Whitney Dangerfield is our digital editor research and fact-checking by Ben Fay
Soundesign Remix by Stone Nelson music clearance by Anthony Roman Southland is our director of operations this year
Your staff includes Emily Kahn and Julie Whitaker Cassie Holly Francis Swanson and Matt Tierney are music is by Adam Dorn and how
Wilner with additional music from that McKinley and Dan rights are theme song is by Nick thorburn and remix by Adam Dorn special
Thanks to Amanda Kane subodh Chandra Lisa Miller Melissa George's Jonathan witmer Rich Kyle Swenson Matthew barge Mike 2
Tobin Steve double back David toutain Daniel Hart Captain Scott roller and Tina rotor of the Euclid Police Department and Lynn have
Hampton president of the Black Shield Cleveland African American police Union thanks also to Pandora for airing the show
The art on our website was made by Darius Stewart Cleveland artist
He created the mural for this episode and my moth Studio
They did the animation please check it out on our website serial podcast. Org that serial podcast. Org
Crossover of course on Facebook and Twitter
Support for serial comes from ZipRecruiter
Unlike many job sites ZipRecruiter doesn't wait for candidates to find you
ZipRecruiter finds them for you
To get qualified candidates fast
Try it free at ziprecruiter.com cereal that ziprecruiter.com cereal
Support for serial comes from Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and Business website with Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and professional tools from Google
Use offer code professional
Pro discount on your first purchase
Serials production of This American Life and WBEZ Chicago