Hello
Are you back in your boudoir
I am I really like it in here now
I might just stay in here is all night
Alright so today was the second day of the hearing
Yes
How to how did it go for Egypt
They really went after her you know today was mostly the states
Cross-examining her and they really
Attacked her testimony
In a bunch of ways
One of the things I brought up was this whole snow issue
Because remember when I
Talk to her on the phone that time you know when I
Was reporting the store and she called me
She said she remembered that day specifically January 13
1999 the day he goes missing the day he goes missing she remembered seeing and not in the library and she said to me be
Because of the snow remember that yeah yeah right yeah she was like I remember cuz it was this
The first snow of the year and there was all the snow
And
The state today
The prosecutor
Chi
Was like
Are you sure you have the right day because there wasn't snow that day was there like he should have reference what she had said
Said to me
And that was
That was something we had a question about 2 cuz she was very clear with you she got
Snowed in at her boyfriend's house
And then the next two days were snow days
So she's very clear that she ties his memory
I2
To the snow right
Oh yeah yeah
Shireen wondered about that
Yeah because we looked up the weather right and it hadn't snow
It hasn't snowed there was a horrible ice storm that had started
Like in the wee hours of the next morning but there wasn't snow it was it was it was terrible weather and it was like a
Big emergency in Baltimore
But it was an ice storm
And so she kind of
I mean
Cheat
She did a fairly good job with it I mean she just said like
Yeah I don't know I know it was bad weather I'm not sure if it was snow or ice or whatever I just remember it was like
Hazardous bad weather
School was canceled after after that Jews like and I remember
I was happy about it because I had used the excuse of bad weather as a reason to stay later
At my boyfriend Derek's house
And my mom bought it
And then she was like and I remember it because I stayed out later I was happy that
Dance school is can
Today's
So it sounded pretty specific
.
I don't know but I have to say she was very cool and collected about it it wasn't
She didn't seem frazzled or freaked out or she was just like I don't know about it was snow ice I don't know it was bad weather huh
Yeah she seemed totally she seemed completely confident in her memories even when I was thinking like
But even when I was thinking like
Wait a minute
What happened
Yeah well so the other the main thing
That happened that least was new to me as a theory about Asia's alibi
And that made me think like wait a minute let me rethink this and in fact I
Asked you guys to go scrambling back to the records
That we have our detectives heldens this is the stuff
Yes that you want stuff
Because the prosecutor of Inuyasha went after her
For a long time about the second
Letter
That she wrote to Adnan right after he got so wasted
So we should just take a step back and explain what these letters are they that your
Talking about so the
So Asian Road Adnan to letter she wrote in the first letter
The day after he was arrested I think March 1st 1999
And Analysis
Does handwritten note where she started saying to him
I've just been to your house I'm at your parents
And I want to tell you that
I remember talking to you that day January 13th 1999
I remember seeing you in the library
So then the next day she she writes him another letter and this one is a little bit different it's a little bit longer it's
Typed up
She seems to be writing it in
Like from one of her
Classes at school
And in that one
She started reiterate again like I remember seeing you in the library that day so let me know
If you need me to
To speak up about that
All right
So today
The 2nd letter the type one was was the issue today so the state is really pressing her over and
Over to say
Are you sure you really wrote this letter on March 2nd
Because it's dated March
And infected stated on every page letter and at the bottom of each page it says March 2nd
And she keeps saying yes
Yes I am yep
And he's pointing to things in the letter that suggests It Was Written later maybe
That suggests It Was Written later because she's got all of this
Fairly specific
Information about anons case in about the
The crime in the way the crime unfolded
And he's suggesting like
How would you have known all this stuff
What were some of the things the prosecutor was pointing to the letter as like how would you know this or that
There were several things one was she notes that hey was found in a shallow grave
Another was that
She talks about someone else referencing
Fibers from Adnan on his body
So the prosecutor is saying like it's too soon for any of those details to have been out in
Republic 2 days after Adnan has been
Arrest right that what he's going to say
That's what he's
Suggesting
In fact he's not really correct about that because then
Justin Brown Adnan defense attorney
Stood up after that and showed exhibits of Baltimore Sun stories dated
Prior to
Asia's letter
That talk about these
That have these very phrases in them
Shallow Grave
Lincoln Park that you know
So that didn't hold up very well
But
There was this one thing that's in this is the thing that I was like
And that is
He's asking her
Did Adnan ever contact
Do you from jail
And she's like no
And he says did he ever
Call you know
Did he you know send you letters she's like nope
And
She says well how do you explain
Explain if Adnan never contacted
Video
How would you explain
Notes from
From a detective interview
With a non-friend
This is a kid named Joanne Gordon
And in these notes it says
That Juwan
Told the cops
That
Adnan
Written a letter to a girl and ask her to type it up
But you got the address wrong
NM
What does that mean like what does that say what does that imply I think he was trying to imply
That
Adnan hat had contact
Packard Asia and had asked her to
Type up this letter
In this way
This March 2nd letter
But he's implying
It wasn't actually written March 2nd
And it was written
Perhaps Weeks Later
That maybe he engineered that in that may be a nun asked her to write this
Type to type up this letter
Ha
Yeah
And I was able what does that mean does that mean she doesn't remember what she thinks she remembers or does that mean she's
Lying
Or whatever and Anand idrees
Did contact her and
What does that mean you know
And so
You know it started it starts to make her
Very pure story about being
Just
Potential Alibi who wanted to step forward and do the right thing to like look like some
Something slightly different
And so that's why I
Who asked you guys to look up
Notes from that detective interview with Juwan
Okay so
So I'm looking at the detective notes
From their interview with Chauhan on April 9th and they didn't record that
Interview so I've always got to these kind of like
Cryptic
Detective notes
I'll just read those to you and this is what they say I think this is what the pro
Prosecutor is
Referencing
It says
Adnan wrote me a letter
And remember at this time and on his in jail
So not wrote me a letter he called yesterday but I wasn't home
Rodenbach
He wrote a letter to a girl to
To type up with his address on it
She got it wrong
And then there's an address
101 East Eager Street
Which is the incorrect address for central booking
And then it says Asia
What's a?
12th grade
I got one just an address
And just an adder
I was a friend of Adnan zand
But
I'm just saying like those are pretty cryptic and I can also see that
Note
As implying that
Adnan ridha letter to girl and ask her could you please
Give my friends the address
So that they can write me letters
And that's all it mean
That's true that's true I mean
Right and then she did it wrong and it's
Like I can just imagine how this could play out in a totally innocent different way from what the prosecutor seems
To be suggesting
The one that stops me is
He wrote a letter to a girl
To type up
And I don't know
It's true it's not clear
It's not clear what this totally means
But
Here's the thing
It raises it does make you pause right
And that's his entire Point that's
That's the prosecutors entire point
Is that I can throw a bunch of Suspicion on Asia story
And all of these various ways
And if I can do it here before you today in this hearing
That means
The prosecutor's baky did nuns criminal trial back in
1999-2000 could have done the same
Same thing
To the state of showing
Look maybe she's not such an ironclad Alibi after all and if she's not such an ironclad alibi
Then maybe
Christina Gutierrez did have a very good reason
For not pursuing her
It wasn't a mistake it was a strategy
That's what he's trying to show
So what did you think did you buy that
Can I buy it
I mean
I would say
I don't think he liked proved that she didn't write the letter on March 2nd or anything like that and she seems very comfort
People just saying
I don't know what you want those notes about Juwan mean
But I wrote this letter March 2nd I never heard
Like she was
She just was right
Forthright about it
Or seemed very forthright about it I should say
And
But it did
You know it did make me think like
Well
It does make you wonder what
Could have happened a trial and whether it would have been
Slam dunk for a nun
Okay so can we talk about
The main event of the day which is
The cell phone testimony which I've been waiting patiently to get to
I know I so wish you were there today I was like I was like Dana would be eating this
I was like drooling part way through a minute it's it was hard to get was that exciting
So it's really important is the thing but it's
Just
It's hard to sink your teeth into in terms of emotion you know but it's
No it was I mean yeah it was interesting so basically
Today there was not a big
Bombshell on this issue but I think they're setting the stage for 1
So which turns out that the AT&T cell tower s
Does the AT&T cell tower expert who testified at a nun's original trial in mm
It turns out that
There was this disclaimer
On those records
Anna on a fax cover sheet
For those records back in 1999
That said
You can't use incoming calls they're not reliable for location
Status incoming calls are not reliable Four Loko
Kitchen status
And
Why that's important is because the two phone calls
That place Adnan in leakin park
At the time that Jay said they were burying the body
Are incoming calls
Right
So
What happened was this fall just recently
That same cell tower expert
Wrote an affidavit saying I didn't know about that disk
Disclaimer about not using the ink
Incoming calls for low
Location
So now he's saying I'm not sure now about
My testimony
I'm not sure I could
Could say that those two
Who calls Play Store
The phone in Lincoln
So that guy did not testify today actually
But the defense team brought in this other expert
Who's who said yes you know that disclaimer was very very important
And they spent a lot of the debt the afternoon arguing that the state and the defense over
Basically the meaning of location
On those cell tower record
How to interpret the word location
I'm really jealous that you get to be there for that tomorrow
No accident because no this is actually really important at this this like cell phone disclaimer thing is is something that
Bug me for really long time
Because it's sort of like it if if that is in fact the case that
You can't use incoming calls for location data
Then that kind of means
There's a chance that that cell phone was not in Lincoln Park
When the prosecution at the original trial said it was so it's no it's a real problem for the state yeah it's a real problem
So this might really get answer tomorrow of weather
Whether that's a real thing that you can't use incoming calls
Four location
That would that would
Make me really happy
I think an answer.
Seitan man
All right
Alright so you call me tomorrow
Yes I will