Previously
Ontario
She kind of just always generally in
And we made it because
Just the constant
Beijing
Her if she was out
Take a break
It was everything where I was like texting her like going to her house knocking on the door
He was going to
Color is car was broken down
And I asked her for a ride
Global Tel Link prepaid call from
Adnan Syed
An inmate from Maryland correctional facility from This American Life
WBEZ Chicago serial one story told week by week I'm Sarah Koenig
The cops who investigated the murder of Hae Min Lee experience Baltimore City Detectives
Bill Ritz and Greg macgillivray
And how I wish right now that I could play you tape of their perspective on this case
But they didn't want to be here
Wendover it's finally turned me down after 6 weeks of back-and-forth
He said he didn't see the point
The case has been adjudicated
What good would it do
I also spoke on the phone
Sentences to me
Send it
Hammer horror hesitates remember the case right away
Beyond question he did it
How did they arrive at that level of certainty
Before his body was found this is a missing person case
She disappeared January 13th
Investigation starts out a little slowly which makes sense to me she's not a small child she's 18 she's got a car because I
Also missing
At first the police call around to her friends they text Alicia
Remember that's when he tells him he's supposed to get a ride from her but didn't
The next day that Colorado Hospital's hotels motels
They checked the area around the high school parking lot where she was last seen
You can see from the reports that they immediately hone in on the most time-worn explanation for such disappearances
The boyfriends
Current and former
The first day they called on her new guy
They checked the area around his house which is in another County Northeast of Baltimore
Over the next two weeks we keep asking more questions
They checked on The Alibi he was indeed at work at the LensCrafters store the day he went missing his manager tells
Anons track coach to check anons alibi
It's inconclusive
The coach tells him he can't be sure Adnan practice that day they don't take attendance
R6 they do that awful foreboding thing you see on TV sometimes
A team of dogs to check the wooded areas and fields around Woodlawn High School
Best curling iron for send
The February 8th report saying they're going to check his computer for AOL account
There's search stops
Spect emerges
Testing one two three testing one two three
This is tape from a police interview of the man who finds hey
He's a little hard to hear on the tape
He's soft-spoken
I'm going to call this man mr. ass
I don't want to use his full name for reasons I promise will become clear
Mr.ass works in the maintenance department at a local school
Discovered
Make it pop
I think I may have discovered a body in Lincoln Park he says
Bring it to the slightly off-kilter story about how Mr s discover this body
Just a word here about Linkin Park
It's actually spelled leakin Park leakin
Linkin Park
It's huge over a thousand acres on the western edge of Baltimore city it's got a reputation
Not for the beauty of its Woods or it's Trails Arts Nature Center
What is known for sadly is dead bodies
Mention Lincoln Park two people from Baltimore as I often did
A pretty much guaranteed to get a comment like this
Well you're digging it Linkin Park the bear your body you're going to find somebody else
The rental car in West Baltimore I was working on a story about a girl who was found in leakin park he said
My uncle was found dead in Lincoln Park
McCobb website dedicated to Baltimore murders list
68 bodies found there since 1946
Alyssa's missing at least 7 years of stats that number is probably low
A lot of law-abiding baltimoreans they don't even really know where leakin Park is
Rabia chaudry that family friend of a roofers contacted me about this case
Which is explaining it to me she said yeah and how is it supposed to get to Lincoln Park so fast
It's like an hour into the city
Linkin Park is nowhere near the school
Her brother's best friend
After a non had initially got arrested
When I was on the phone with him talking like
When he was locked up I like
Lincoln Park MI where is that do you know where it is have you ever been there
And he's like I have never been there I don't even know where it is
So I mean living around here we don't know but it's somewhere in the Inner City
Is in fact less than three miles from where you are sitting right now
Office across the street from Woodlawn High School
Set a 7-minute drive
I have no idea
We wouldn't go there we go to the harbor somewhere yeah there's no reason for us to go there
I'm explaining all this just to say that the simple fact that he was found
A lot of people that alone made it
What's a nice boy like you doing a park like this
Mister s
He also told the cops he's never been to that part of Linkin Park before he did seem to know that people go fishing back there
Here's what he told the cops
At his job he got in a work order to shave down a door
But the school didn't have the tool he needed
A plane
He had one at home though
So during his lunch hour he said he drove his truck home got the plane from his basement and before you left
Grab some sustenance out of the fridge
I'd rather be unrefrigerated
On my way back
Feather-N-Fin
Jenny
She's drinking this 22 oz Budweiser and he's heading back to work
And his route to the college is through leakin Park
He stops on franklintown Road
About three miles from work
There's a small pull off and some concrete barriers and he walks back in there quite a ways seems like for a guy who just has to pee
Later they measure
127 feet back into the woods
Legos
The next tape is a little upsetting
And I got that good way
Which were your attention
The area that you
There was something there it was open
An open area
But there was also a fallen tree
Did you go to that area for certain reason
Suspicious of Mr s who by this time as become a Cessna
The tape was made on February 18th 9 days after Mr as reported finding the body
They're going over the details carefully because there are parts of a story that are a little weird
Something about the fallen tree 127 feedback Into the Woods
It was a Fallen Tree essentially a 40-foot log lime or less parallel to the road
The other side of the name of dead run
His body was buried right behind this log on the Streamside
You're standing on the street side of the logs on the other side
It's not at all obvious that you notice her
Tell me a story about why he stopped where he stopped it doesn't quite seem right
When you're walking back
This area where you finally stop
Why did you pick that particular area
That's when I sing
You said you were going to actually go back further
In this part of the tape you get a sense of how Ritz and McGillivray operate together
Or at least what I've gathered in listening to a bunch of these interviews
Montgomery starts out on judgmental just tell me your story
Ben wittes comes in and says something like
Tell me understand here
Some harder questions
Exposing weaknesses in the narrative
Then I will come back in
He's asking direct sometimes harsh questions it seemed like they'd be good at pushing someone off balance
But this one sort out of the blue
Have you ever been inside
Batgirl's carport
To the fallen tree
Purity saying wait I thought you told me
Stopped at the log.
And now you're saying you're on your way further back
Stop Larry
Getting ready to urinate
And then that's when you walked in and discovered the hair
Now you're saying you're going to actually go back further
Before you discovered
Maybe I'm a little bit confused as you're standing on the south side of the tree in a tree in the room
Minnesota Let It Go
A bunch of things are fishy
The path he takes back into the woods it doesn't really lead to the log
What is the end up there
He didn't need to find a hidden spot to pay there are so many other choices
And if you're walking through brush and brambles when you should have naturally avoid a big login into step over
What they're trying to get at is
Did you really just stumble on this body
Were you looking for this body
Because you already knew where it was
What is a reasonable question
Because his body wasn't just hard to spot
Impossible to spot
Right where in the State's Attorney's office we just got delivered the first box of what they're saying is
Disclosable under
Whatever Public Information Act
Can I attend
I didn't understand how camouflage body was until I saw photos of the crime scene
Mr s founded
Before they remove the body
State's Attorney's Office in Baltimore
I went through the crime reporter from The Baltimore Sun name is Justin George
I've been talking to Justin about the
The story and he's interested maybe writing about it too
Open a packet of photos together
Phone number awful to see if you'd imagine
There was one where you can make out a bit of black hair and the dirt and leaves
How did he notice that I don't understand that either
I mean it's it's pretty well covered
Yeah you there's barely any
I need a showing
But are we supposed to be looking at something there
What is that
Is that her that's her that's all he saw
Yeah that's
Looks to be part of the body
Yeah I expected it
To be more visible
Justin and I were the only ones who had this reaction
The city surveyor went out to the burial site to measure the distance from the road
This is before they disinterred her
Testifying at trial
When I arrived at the site where the body was
There was a log
Wunderground approximate 40 feet long
Oki
Stuck on the log I walked along the edge of the log expecting to find a body real soon I never saw
Call one
How much time
I like taking one more step
I would have walked on the grave site where the body was
And at that point or others on the scene
Yes ma'am it was a lot of people there
Inception point to somebody point out these exact location yes ma'am detective pointed to the site
I look at the ground
And I also
It looked it wasn't rushing Disturbed
Yeah just Blended in with their natural surroundings of the ground
Who's looking for the body
Knows where it's supposed to be who can see that they're a bunch of people standing around it
And still you can't find it
Does it seem reasonable that Mr s
Apparently wasn't looking for anything except a secluded place to pee would have discovered it just like that
This business of having to pee
The spot where mr.ass stops is only a few miles from his house
Only a few more miles from its work
Kitty can't wait
Here's detective questioning mistress again
While you were at home did you have to urinate or use bathroom at all
So within 7 or 8 minutes how much is a 22 in your head
That 7/8 minute.
You had to go to the bathroom
Mr. Says he never actually does pee in the woods
So the ends of waiting till I get to work
Which okay maybe that makes sense you've had a shock
Find me walk so far in in the first place
He's just trying to have a quick pee
Why was he studying the ground
Ask him about this
You got out of your vehicle Venture back
Into the Woods
What we're after we measured it was actually 127 feet off the roadway
As you're walking along why are you looking down at the ground
Are you looking every step you take
12 in February this year we went out to Linkin Park
We wanted to know whether it was strange that you done so far back into the woods
127 feet from the road look like
Producer Dana was with me and so is Justin George Baltimore Sun
The place where Mr acid entered the woods right at the road
Just a notice to sign
What's that
Just look at it I mean
The sign says a lot
This area patrolled
Dumper's will be prosecuted
They can barely read it
Charger redesign that's covered in graffiti and pierced with seven bullet holes
In fact the cops found 20 cartridge casings and right about the spot when they collected evidence in 1999
I thought the park itself was quite lovely
Rainbows and trees
It's rocking as a stream
Is uneven Transat hilly but not flat either
Not nearly as creepy as I imagined it
I think it is a nice
At night I think a dust gets it I think it is
Very bleak
3 we walked in what we figured is about 127 ft
Just in case it out by the yard
Be right about there
We actually wander around for a while trying to find the right spot
Finally I remember that we have a hand-drawn map of the site from that survey or better Meyer testified
40 ft long
15 inch log on the ground
Once you get to the right location
It depends on all of us
127 feedback doesn't feel all that far
If you're looking for privacy
You can still see the cars on the road from where we're standing
.
If he's peeing
Yeah
At least you want to come this far
There's nothing
Yeah I mean there's something
Some Dead Leaves or whatever but yeah you can totally see the cars
So actually that doesn't seem that weird to me
Emily Mister as a story seems eminently more believable
What were the woods I feel Justin in on the evidence they collected here
Was a liquor bottle
From which they got cellular material and never tested
And a rope
That was never tested
As far as I know
Personnel
And then
Up at the road they found
A condom
And a condom wrapper back in the condom was still rolled
Click on
Used condom is Harley
And they found
A bunch of shell casing
They found bullets and shell casings
Set from two different guns
And they found
Blockbuster Video to Blockbuster Video like a cases
But by the body was the only thing they got right from the area of the body was
What's the liquor bottle in the Rope
I know it sounds like a game of Clue
If the condom part
As for the liquor bottle
Back at the taped interview with mr. s
Detectives Rich McGillivray want to find out if this guy could be the source of that liquor bottle
Do you drink anything else besides beer they ask
What
Whiskey
What kind
Windsor Canadian whiskey
What denomination
Maybe half a pint
Did you ever take
A bottle
Would you ever take that in the car
Keep you warm
Yes
No risk comes in
We collected evidence
She says cans and bottles in a crime scene
We're going to test them
Is buffing hair they never do tests
We're going to find your DNA and one of those bottles yes
Baby cereal bottle out the window when you're driving past coming home from work
If so you better tell us now
But it's important we know about it because
We're going to do is Analyze That and come back 6 months
Rehab Evans
That you were deceptive with us
That we have
DNA
Proof that you were there and then say oh I forgot
Pause icon fishnet there that weekend
And yeah you know half a point
And I threw a bottle in them
The lights to take a minute
In
Or any of the items not as fine whiskey balls beer bottle soda can
Or anything like that where you may have discarded in that general area
Because I'm not sure could have
I'm not positive
Cuz I know a lot of bottles out the window
Rich asks what bottles
Beer bottles
Whiskey Maybe
Possible he says
Welfare while he switch to Rum
What rum
Dark rum Bacardi
I can't stand it
He just starts listing different kinds of booze
Legend
A long time ago
Brandy
Cognac
Just
Just keep stuff yeah
Brandy
Brandy was the answer they were looking for the bottle they found near his body is Coronet vsq Brandy
200ml blue right past it
Consider for a moment if Mr s was just trying to relieve his bladder
Modern piece that February day minding his own business
And then he sees this terrible sad sight and does the right thing
How's the cops shows and where she's buried
Well how horrible now that they're so suspicious of them
But they're considering the maybe either he did it or he knows who did
How terrifying for mr. ass
Girl I smell like a nice quiet guys Cooperative doesn't appear to be a brandy drinker
Again I can only go by the reports and files but my guess is the reason the cops are holding onto mr. ssss
Is because
Pinterest
Has a little bit of a record which isn't necessarily a big deal
But
And here's part of story where I'm hoping you'll understand why I'm not using his name
Mr. s is a Streaker kind
Freaking kind
Indecent exposure charges defense attorney under circumstances that
Hazard does not even begin to Define
Mr. SS arrested May of 94 for running about naked in a residential neighborhood two years later merchandise
36 acres and nothing else
The officer writes
The southwestern district has received numerous calls for service in the past three years to this area for the same incident
Same description
Past 3 years
The officer chases down to stress onto I-95
Pinterest jump some chain link fences the kind with razor wire at the top
End up in the hospital
It gets worse
Or better depending on whether you enjoy police reports as much as I do
December 7th of 1998
So barely two months before Mr s finds his body
There's this
Around noon during what I have to imagine is Mister as lunch break
A lady named Margaret is driving along
Jersey report
Black male dash out in front of my car and began shaking his body and up and down motion
No clothes
His penis was exposed as he faced my vehicle shaking
And this lady Margaret
Is a police officer
In uniform
She chases him but he runs down into the Metro stop
Margaret finds his work clothes in a pile and takes them which means unless that's your ass has a second outfit stashed
Someplace he is riding back to work in the altogether
Twisted the sensitive
The same day he flashes Margaret so
December 7th 98
Mr. s files his own police
Support
Jesus
From his car
Someone's taking his cellphone his money his keys
His work clothes
Who has all of it
Officer Margaret
Streaking isn't a violent crime
Or necessarily a sexual one
And there's no evidence that he was sexually assaulted anyway
But you can imagine both sets of eyebrows Rising Unwritten Aguilera's faces when they see these reports
It's strange Behavior
Mr. s about it on tape
But I figure he knew they knew
The same day they interview Monday February 18th
I also give him a polygraph test
Which he fails
Deception indicated as a conclusion
But the tester also said Mr s seem to be nervous
Cuz apparently had an important meeting with a realtor that day his wife is expecting him to pick her up
But a week later another polygraph
This time with different questions
Princeton
Do you know that girl you found I because she was hit with a tire iron
I guess that's a thing
This time there is no deception indicated
Pinterest Fades from their View
Pictures of my own thoughts were when I learn
Mr ass
I didn't really think so maybe he did it maybe he killed her
Wonder if maybe heard something about the crime
In about where she was buried
Because it did seem a tad unbelievable to me that he spotted her the way he said he did
One Theory his step kids or a neighbor had told him about the body
It heard about it through other kids
School
Mister as just as a Good Samaritan thought
Someone needs to go find this girl and tell the cops
I just want to say he's heard about it beforehand cuz you don't want to get anyone else in trouble
Mr. s didn't want to talk to me
After I made several requests he asked if I please leave him alone
Fair enough
I tried every witch way to figure out if he knew or anyone in his family knew Adnan or Jay or any of the people
I told about the murder
And vice-versa whether any of them had ever heard of mr. ass
Condo connection
The closest I got was
Bear with me
I found out the mister as his sister-in-law was a math teacher at Woodlawn back in 1999 when all this happened
He was her student she said
An excellent student top-of-the-line
But you didn't think this your ass knew anything about the crime before you found the body
She put her husband on the phone Mistresses younger half-brother
And he said you know what's crazy I used to live next door to the kid that did it
That's back when I was 9 or 10
Is it used to throw the football around with him anyway you seem like a nice kid
Again he said that his brother stumbled on the body by axe
Menopause
Chuckled and said
I think he was running through the woods
Streaking
That's how you found it
I told him that apparently had stopped to take a pee he said
That's possible to
Mr s is telling the truth
After all why would a guy who's been in trouble repeatedly for indecent exposure
Take out a dead girl
But inevitably inviting more police contact to rain down upon him
Mr. s wasn't the detectives only lead in this case
We're also looking at the boyfriend
Exactly their suspicions about an on start to percolate
Have an educated guess
Next week on serial
Cereal is produced by Julie Snyder dated Chivas and me Emily Condon is are pretty
Dakshin an operations manager Ira glasses are editorial advisor
Getting help from Nancy Updike fact-checking by Karen for Dallas Smith
Special thanks today to Natasha lesser loot Eddie Scott Calvert and Dave Rosenthal and Andy Rosen from The Baltimore Sun
RC music is composed by Nick thorburn scoring music by Nick and by Mark Phillips who also mixer show
Our website where you can listen to all our epi
Episodes and find photos letters and other documents in the case
Serialpodcast.org
Serials production of This American Life and WBEZ Chicago