Batman call you
Woodlawn
Previously on serial
They said something like we know what you AJ did we talk today
What do you mean
Soundtrack
I don't know unless I don t j a good sum of money
Llcj helping you
Global Tel Link prepaid call from
An inmate at Maryland Correctional Facility
From This American Life and WBEZ Chicago its serial
I told week by week
The first letter I got from Adnan Syed almost exactly one year ago included a challenge
He was writing about the prosecution's timeline of the crime
About when and where Hae Min Lee was killed
State contended that hay was killed between 2:15 and 2:36 p.m.
At the Best Buy parking lot about a mile from Woodlawn High School
That's a 21-minute window and wish to commit the murder
Which may seem like a long time ago
But it is virtually impossible if you consider the following facts
Which he then listed
For example
When the final bell rings at 2:15 you can't just leave and jump in your car he wrote
Quote there are 1500 other students filling the hallways and stairwells of a 4-story building on quote
Then you have to get out of the school parking lot but the parking lot is encircled by the school bus Loop
You can't get your car out until the buses fill up and leave
Which Anon Road took about 10 to 15 minutes
A picture of it
Woodlawn High School lets out
A 215
Elaborating on his letter
Free Windows 10
There's someone like
You know what just trying to not have been committed
That happens sometimes the guards come by when you're just done mid-sentence
Anyway I can pick up from add-ons letter
Best Buy
Their major intersections along the way and that there is a ton of traffic at that time on quote
And then the murder itself how would he be able to strangle hey a tall strong athletic girl
Remove her body from the car
Turn to the trunk and place her in there in broad daylight at 2:30 in the afternoon
And then I walk into the Best Buy Lobby call Jackie and tell him to come meet me there
21 minutes
Hundred percent sure that if someone tried to do it
It would be impossible on quote
Producer Dana Chavis and I gave it a shot
We tried this drive twice we tried in fact
Because full disclosure the first time we screwed it up
The second time though we were like a machine
So here we go
Woodlawn High School Wednesday afternoon
After school announcements
Okay then last bell
More than a thousand students fill the Halls just like Adnan describes in his letter
We figured he gets in her car quickly she's in a hurry
This now 217
The bell ring at exactly 2:15
Say that fast as she could have gotten to her car
Is 2 minutes
So that's getting the state the benefit of the doubt right
She's really hustling maybe she can't get to her car and say 2 minutes remember her friend Debbie Warren
Some had told her right after school that she was in a rush to see her new boyfriend Don at the mall
Presumably the Owings Mills mall where they both were
I think this is the last bus
We do indeed have to wait for the Bus Loop to clear it takes a few minutes
Just have to sit there
What timing
We're in the back of the school
Now is to drive up around to the front of the school
Up around the circle near the gym remember that's where Inez Butler Hendrix says she sees hey
Who come to grab a snack
Once we get there we're at 11 minutes 38 seconds
I'm going to run in
Set timing
I run into the gym area where the food cart was run back out to the car
Turn on to Security Boulevard
Death row
We're trying to get the Best Buy that's still there today
In 21 minutes we're at 17 minutes right about
17 minutes were just crossing under the Beltway less than a minute later
There's the sign Best Buy
A story was that when he pulled into Best Buy
He saw at 9 at the phone booth are at the edge of the building
Wearing red gloves
9 motion for Jada follow him across the front of the building around to the other side to the farthest corner of a
Side parking lot
Where Jay saw his car parked
This particular part of the parking lot Alaska
It has significance
After adhan was arrested the detectives interviewed another friend of his
A kid named Juan
He gotten high with a non one
Ananas car
Her interview
Where was this
Why did you go to Best Buy parking
Nobody
Is Joyce
And I hate to go to space
Adnan Syed
Hey
We can spend time
What they would do there
Play Verano para la colonne noted.
In case you didn't hear that he says
I think he might have said that they had sex there before
Yeah
This happened the strip to get high at Best Buy that it happened after he went missing
Meaning
He was taking John back to the exact spot where he killed Hae
He was returning to the scene of the crime
From the sounds of it right where Jay says his car was that day
Right where Dana and I are now also part
It takes Dan and me 18 minutes
To get to the spot
That leaves three minutes for the actual horror of the thing
An argument may be
And strangulation
He's got to put her body in the trunk
Somehow without anyone seeing
Granted this part of the parking lot is pretty empty but it's still it's a parking lot in the middle of the afternoon
They're definitely cars and people near enough to make this seem like a very very risky move
Counting down the quickest possible imagining of such a thing
Manual strangulation usually takes
A few minutes
We get out of our car and walk over to where we think the Payphone was according to a sketch J made for the cops
There's no phone booth there now
I just want to pause here and talk about this phone with from it we have not been able to confirm its existence
The Best Buy employees I talked to did not remember a payphone back then we spoke to the landlord at the time at the property
Manager they had no record of a peso from 2001
Thor Payphone lots of public funds did come down between 2001
Blueprints for the store when it was built in 1995 nothing
The manager also said there is no record of a service agreement between Best Buy in any pay phone company at that store
We checked with the Maryland Public Service Commission we check with Verizon
Neither could track down records from that far back
It seems crazy to me that the cops would have either not checked to make sure it existed or failed to mention it is
Somehow it wasn't there
I never got the call record from this booth there's nothing in their files about it
A trial at nuns lawyer brings up this phone booth when she's trying to attack J's credibility
She says to the judge
Quote we believe that the physical description of the actuality of Best Buy including the location of the phone booth
Best Buy
The entrance existence or non-existence of
Security cameras Etc she goes on
I don't know
We're stumped on this one
But let's assume it did exist
That day
The prosecutor said they knew he was dead by 236
Because there's a call at 2:36 to a non cell phone with J has
Miss a that must be to call Jay told the cops about
Turn on calls his own phone and says come and get me I'm at Best Buy
You can see it on the call log it just says incoming there's no phone number attached incoming calls
This 2:36 call was 5 Seconds long
We get out of quarter we put it in
Dial a number
Stop at 22 and a half
Let's just be precise about it
20 22 22 minutes into seconds
If we just did it in 22 minutes and two seconds and that was leaving about a minute and a half
In the car
For the actual
Killing Park
Should probably be the minimum
Lot of time
In the car
I mean if it seems like yeah could be done
But it seems far-fetched
It does seem far-fetched
Because there's no room for any errors any pauses even
Buses to drive the strangulation the moving of the body that they all have to happen
Quickly as I possibly can for the 236 call to work
Possible
Or at least not impossible
Which is what I was saying in that first letter
When I told him and I more or less did it in the time allowed the 21 minutes
His overall reaction was incredulity
Seems like 5 minutes
Since you have to wait for the bus
I don't know
Conscious heart
Taken out of
I don't know I mean if you guys like you did it then you did it
I don't know I don't know what to say that
I don't know what to say I just always thought in my mind
This is what I'll say is it doesn't make me think
To me it doesn't
Prove anything
Except that it
It's possible it doesn't mean that I think you're lying or that I think
It even happened at the Best Buy I'm just saying
If you're going to debunked
The states
Timeline
Like we weren't able
Yeah we weren't able to do that
We weren't able to debunked they're trying
However
States timeline
In the detective notes
Then I found a handwritten itinerary March 18th 1999
Jay II taped interview with police
This is the route J laid out for the cops his entire driving day on January 13th
This is what we're going to try to replicate
To see if it matches the call record from that day
Because right the prosecution story of the crime was mainly pin to two things
Chase statements
And the sound records
Anon remembers that at his trial the prosecution had a big blow up chart of the call record
Enlisting 34 calls made and received an on cell phone that day
With blanks beside each call
Everytime I witness identified a, list the prosecutor would label it with a sticker
Call Jen pusateri
It was a pretty powerful thing
Because as he was testifying
Cell phone records
Okay be said what happened at this time
Besides the calls themselves they also had a list of all the cell towers that paint each time up
Particular call came in or went out
Sure the prosecutor said you might have your doubts about Jay
But the call record doesn't lie
Jake and possibly have known which Towers were getting paid when he couldn't fabricate that it would be
So the cell towers and the calls and Jay Story the way they all meshed
Prosecutors argue with irrefutable
Prosecutor Casey Murphy said to the jury in her closing statement quote
The most important thing for you to remember about Jay's testimony is that it does not stand alone it is corroborated
Chatot
The cell phone records support with those Witnesses say and the witnesses support with those cell phone records say
There's no way around it
All right ready
So I started it
It's 2:51 and we're making a right out of the Best Buy parking lot
On to Belmont Ave all right so let's see if we can recreate what Jace has happened that day
The next stop after Best Buy is the I-70 park and ride
Where Jay says they leave his car for a few hours
It's just a large commuter parking lot
Jay says he follows Adnan there Anon is driving his car Jay has an on scar
He's pretty careful to let the cops know he wasn't ever in his car never touched her or her stuff
Did you get out of the car the car and
This is from J second tape statement
Trumpkin
The backseat
This detail has always struck me by the way
Anon is going through the trunk of his car at the I-70 park and ride
His body is back there
In the trunk at this point
But anyway
Several items you picked up in
Move around stuff Academy
Came over to his card
Show me Paw Patrol Paw Patrol
And then he got in the driver's seat
And we switch places
And I got the passenger
Text Dana and me 11 minutes to get to the park and ride from Best Buy
Then we wait a couple minutes to account for a nun's movement
In case you're wondering if there were no security cameras at this park and ride back in 99 which exit.
So now it's a little after 3 p.m.
I took the cops on this ride on March 18th to Matt about the timeline
He told him that after they left the park and ride they went in search of weed
He says that's when he calls his friend Patrick
And this is where things start to get off
There is indeed a call to Patrick on the call log
But it's at 3:59 p.m.
The Runaway we've got a Time problem
Jay has sorted that out so his story better match the call log
He testified that he called Jen pusateri 1st at 3:21 to find out if Patrick was home
Jen testified that no Jay would not have called her to find out where Patrick was it's just not a thing that would have happened
Trinity case there is a call to Jen a321
Chase's when they didn't find Patrick at home they switched course and headed up to Forest Park to buy weed
Didn't I drive that same route
Are they said they buy two dimes of weed here that's a side note
Done
We are making a left
Jay also mentioned another call around this time
This call is incredibly important and I will talk more about it and another episode I swear
But for right now what you need to know is
In his second interview when the cops show him the list of calls
Jay says Adnan spoke to some girl in Silver Spring
Her name was Nisha that girl would not have been flirting with
Briefly put J on the phone with her
And the reason this is so important is for two reasons one it's the only call in this stretch of time that's to some
Anondo
Rather than a friend of Jays
And
It puts Jay and Adnan together in the middle of the afternoon when a nan says he was not with Jack he was back at
High School
In the March 18th itinerary there's a note about the Nisha call
Turn on handed the phone to Jay at the golf course
On West Forest Park Avenue
Yeah that is the first okay
If indeed this is the golf course he's saying where
Suspect hands the phone to the 10 to the witness who is Jay that was the Nisha call
And that does happen right now
So the time works for this one and not just a story
Here's the problem it doesn't match the cell tower in the car records
It's picking at our back near the Best Buy West of where we are
And that is true of all these calls from the middle of the afternoon the 321 to Jen 332 Denisha 3
848-283-5092 Patrick paying the tower near where Jay tells the cops
They were driving at afternoon not a one
A child and accounted for in Jay's testimony
Prosecutors did not point out that the cell towers didn't match
Announce defense attorney
Sort of but reading a trial transcript even if she notes the discrepancy
She doesn't nail it
So it's hard to tell what the discrepancy means
So onward we are headed to Pasco state park right now
We definitely don't have time to go to Patapsco well let's see how long
This is the next stop on the itinerary The Cliffs at Patapsco State Park which is a good 20-minute Drive
From where we are right now
I don't track practice starts at 4 p.m.
It before we were sort of clinging respectively to the great upon timeline thumb our noses
Yeah I mean this just seems absurd it's 3
Set between 3:45 and 3:50 now and their world
And if I'm on on and I need to be seen for truck I'm freaking out right now that I need to get back to track
To have an alibi
What's this like
Across the county to go to a state park to smoke a blunt like
Pull up to smoke in your car and
It just seems like there had to be other places you could have just pulled over for a quick smoke
If indeed that's what needed to happen
There's a shrimp sale at The Crab Crib
Sometimes I think Dana isn't listening to me
Anyway we had to Patapsco State Park because Jay is very clear
Take statement Number One Taste
Remember to March 18th itinerary
Now is when they go smoke a blunt at the Cliffs at Patapsco
My truck in there
Domini
Refune steps
This is beautiful
You can see the river below some train tracks
Chase memories about the spider specific
Daenerys from the handwritten notes March 18th
Chinese religious texts
That's it says Patapsco Valley State Park
1630 hour
And then the next node is Sun getting ready to hit mountaintops
1630 hour means 4:30 p.m.
Sunset that day was at 5:05 p.m. so that would make sense
And then it says I can't believe I did it I'm sad but not really
Here's what J says they talked about
And before I play this mixtape just a warning that is disturbing
Percentage overlooking a whole bunch of stuff at this Cliff you're not
He starts
Tell me about
How was when he killed her house
He said he wrapped his hand around her
Started kicking then he said he looked up to make sure nobody was
Look in the car Adam
Synonym for fingernails
Emily. She's trying to say something that she thinks that she was trying to say that she was starting but that's what she deserves
How long
Do you think you're worthless
20 minutes to happiness
Other than that conversation was there anything additional
It said to me wonders where you can put the body at
Did you make any suggestions
Not at all
Did he name any location
You didn't say you know what about here yo
He didn't name up
They have dozens locations and you gave him
Thumbs up or thumbs down
John PS
Say something to me
Defective State Park where we were a little bit up the river but I told him that
People walk up and down there
AJ says they talked about the murder at the cliffs
He said they talked about whether to dispose of the body right there and Patapsco State Park
He says they're there for 20 minutes to half an hour
Come trial when json the stand talking about where they went that day
This whole trip to Patapsco and never happens
It's just not there
Instead it happens in a nun's car when they're tooling around looking to buy weed
This is a puzzle to me it's such a vivid scene describing it's so detailed
I have to think he included it for a good reason
But it doesn't fit the timeline
Patapsco story at all
It's like trying to
I'm trying to think of an analogy
The uselessness of what we're trying to do
By recreating something that doesn't
Fit
Like trying to plot
You know the coordinates of someone's dream or something we're just like 420 that doesn't like as if we're going to be surprised every single time but it's
It's not
Probably call it a Fool's errand
A trial Jason on gets another call I just dropping an on off at school for track
Before he left the car he received a phone call or placed a phone call
It was in Arabic
I don't know who he was talking to I don't know what it entails
I believe it was his mother on quote
Adnan and his family say he doesn't speak Arabic
Or Pashto or Urdu
Accent on the other end of the call
And there is a 427 call in the log maybe that's the one
But again the cell tower pings isn't near Woodlawn High School
The earliest and I can get from The Cliffs back to Woodlawn is 4:45 p.m. and that's being generous
But even so that means if an OnStar to get changed
He is very late for 4 p.m. track now which seems like a bad strategy
Wait like that
Jay says he goes next to a friend's house
I'm going to call this friend Kathy because she didn't want to be identified
Jay says he gets there by 5:20 or 5:30
He says he smokes more weed there but it's not long before an on calls him and says I'm done with track come get me
Chickens back to Woodlawn to get an on
She tells the cops that he gets to Woodlawn at about 6 p.m.
Andre season on with a friend from track
The notes for March 18th say
Said goodbye to track buddy will
That day
DJ by the wheel and then
That is Will
Amtrak
It's hard to remember that
What a contraction
You mean I should have asked you 15 years ago
Maybe
That's hard to remember
I didn't even know that I was apart of anything until you just told me that like
No one ever contacted me about everything
Really
Yeah like
No cops ever called you and said with an eye on it
Track that day no no attorneys no attorneys ever called and said
Did you work with a non present at track practice at
I don't remember any of that
Will confirm that yes track started at 4
So you had quite a bit of time from the end of school at 2:15
Big round
No playing footsies with your little girlfriend and then go get back to go get ready for practice
Ready and on top of an excuse to be late
Because there was so much
Exactly what would happen if you were really late or you skipped or
It was already,
Actually like giving you my love
Family emergency
Okay
Their coach Michaels I told the cops that are non probably was there that day
3 things you didn't notice of a non wasn't there
But I couldn't be a hundred percent sure
The other thing will told me he saw Jay pick up and also drop off at 9 for track multiple times
Yeah that was just normal
Normal to the point where no one will pay attention to it
Right
So you can't solve this crime for us
Wish I could oh my goodness
There's another problem with the track story
Jay says he gets up not at about 6
There's an outgoing call at 5:38 p.m.
2 anons friend Krista
Someone J would not be calling
Which would suggest Adnan had his phone at 5:38 p.m.
Call Pings a tower that's out near that guy Patrick's house so does near where they end up ditching his car
Not at all close to Woodlawn High School
I could keep going here to The Bitter End Of The Night
But I'm hoping you'll take my word for it
The timeline has some problems
I'm going to try very hard not to bore you right now but I do want to talk about
Outsell records for a sec
Because I want to know whether the state use the call records accurately and fairly in a dunce trial
Do the records really corroborates a story
Seen some recent reports about how cell phone evidence isn't as reliable as it was once cracked up to be
Washington Post ran a story in June for instance with the headline
Experts say law enforcement's use of cellphone records can be inaccurate
Federal courts in Oregon and Illinois have ruled cell phone evidence inadmissible
The problems arise when you're trying to say I can prove you were at such-and-such a place at such-and-such a time because of the cell
Power that your phone paint
You can't do that with certainty because of the way cell towers get activated and how much charge were they cover
In fact these kinds of records are mostly useful as a way to say where someone wasn't rather than where he or she was
Call Pings a tower in downtown Baltimore I'm going to be pretty confident that you're not making that call from
Annapolis or DC
Or Patapsco State Park
The first I know Adam case was the first in Maryland to use cell tower technology as evidence
There's a new thing
Because I am technologically speaking a moron
I asked Dana to find out
Did the cell experts who testified at trial present the technology accurately in a way that still holds up
So Dana sent this gripping testimony to two different engineering professors
Purdue and one at Stanford University
Yes
The way the science is explained in here is right
Anyway that the stakes expert a guy named Abraham aronowitz
Custody cell site
I just going around to different spots and dialing a number and noting the tower it ping
That's legit
What is not junk science
But that's a different question from
Does the science is explaining here actually support the state's case
Did the prosecution deploy that science fair Lee
That's a more complicated question with a more complicated answer
Aronowitz the cell expert and prosecutor Casey Murphy did the sight test
Together
She took him around to various locations connected to Jay story
Explain it to me
They went to the spots that matter the most in the story of the crime
What's the place is like
Jen's house
The Best Buy
We can park where where hey was buried so like those places that are really important Kathy's Apartments
2nd stage 14 of the
That's right. The state in October they do 14 of them
Do you know how many Nevada fit trial
They asked
The cell phone expert about
Four of them
Really for us
Because the rest of the tests didn't really help their argument
Which is their prerogative their job is to put on the strongest possible case
But of the foresight test they do talk about one is a test run and what's does in a place called gilston Park which I'm not even
Can explain
It's basically irrelevant to our story
The other three places
It all happened in Jay's narrative
After 6 p.m.
After J had picked a nun up from track
Serta from 12:07 until
That window of time is where
Kind of
Jay's story doesn't line up
With the cell phone records
And the timeline he's giving is also not lining up with
The times of the cell phone
So the towers the times
And Jay's story are not matching right
Anywhere in that basic
6 hour.
This is sort of what date and I have experienced on our drive that day but it wasn't plotting out
Just a word about the cell tower testimony
It took two days
And it was sort of a mess
Announce defense attorney Christina Gutierrez
Claimed she didn't have all the cell record of attention have the cell tower maps she tries to get we're running with
Testimony thrown out
The judge nearly agrees with her
Prosecutor Kevin urick and the Basking for a mistrial which isn't granted
And this might sound like exciting courtroom fireworks but I just
I can't stress enough how tedious this must have been for the jury
And also possibly confusing
This is actually a young guy on the stand he looks
Kind of like George Stephanopoulos
Except tired and fearful
Here's one of the more lively moments of his testimony prosecutor Kevin urick talks first
Wiping your breakfast
RAM for cell phones
Functioning
Wireless camera
Overruled if you know
Depends on the quality of the phone
How might that affect you
Objection
Overalls and again
If you know
Poor performance
If how so
Objection
Disappointment
Mister on York
Unless you are prepared to last position
Seriously most of it is more boring than that
Which is why I made a Nereid at all so I didn't have to
She explained that the cell site test the prosecution did bring up a trial the ones after 6 p.m.
The first one was about a site near Kathy's apartment remember that's the call Adnan get to Kathy's
When officer Adcock called asking if he seen hey
It says that one worked
At 6:24 p.m. call in the winter
It matches the cell tower and matches the call log and it matches Jay story Adnan story and Kathy
Happy Story 2
It puts Jane and on together at a certain place at a certain time
The question is what happens after that
Chase's after the Adcock called they left Kathy's and that's when they went to Barry hay and leakin Park
Then they ditched her car out of Edmondson Avenue and then they headed back toward Westview Mall where they true evidence in
Dumpsters
And if you map the cell towers that ping between 6:24 p.m. and say 805
If you imagine each Tower lighting up
Illuminate this Trail
They support the locations in Jay's story
Confirm this with riveting testimony that sounds like this
Yes
The most incriminating stop on the route that night is of course we can park
There were two incoming calls one at 7:09 and one at 7:16
The hit a tower at the Northwest end of the park
I asked Dana since the range of that leakin Park Tower reaches Beyond just the territory of the park
Could they have been someplace else besides
Digging a grave in the actual Park
I do have been at someone's house or something
It's possible you could have been here with that like this is
Patrick's house
One of his address for Catherine since these are strips
Maybe you could have been there okay
I think they were probably in Lincoln Park
Okay
Because it's
Just
I don't think I thought the amount of Lucky would have to have to make up a story like that and then have
The cell phone records corroborate those key points
I just don't
That's possible
Isn't that sort of tantamount to say
I think they were in
The truth
I'm saying I think the cell phone was in Lincoln Park
Right
Looks pretty bad for a non
Because even though the cell towers can't say who was with the phone or who was making the call
And I'm self says he's pretty sure he was with his phone at that time after track
Getting his memory is vague. I probably would have
But he says that from what he can remember the evening
After he got the call from officer Adcock
He remembers dropping Jay off at some point
And then he said he would have gone to the mosque for prayers
What is Ramadan
He doesn't say he lent his phone out or his car to Jay or anyone else that evening
So according to Adnan he was with the phone
I'm twice that night the phone ping the tower near leakin Park
So bad for Adnan
On the other hand
Also undermined what J tells the cops about that same trip to Lincoln Park
The actor called Cathy's ends about 6:29 p.m.
But we can park calls are 40 minutes later
Put chases after the iPad call henan on left Kathy's and then they do a bunch of different things
They drive to Jay's house for shovels then to I-70 park and ride for Hays
Karsten Jacobs to McDonalds back by school to wait for Adnan says he's there waiting for about 20 minutes
Then they drive all around for a while back over to Patapsco then
Security
Before they finally get to Lincoln Park
All that what I just described
That takes an hour and 20 minutes
Twice as long in other words
Pinnacle lock accounts for
I'm not trying to be Petty Here
I don't think we should hold to some Crystal Clear timeline
How could you possibly remember each twist and turn and phone call from that day 6 weeks later
Ever
If the state is saying
Adnan Syed is guilty because we have this witness and his story is backed up by cell records
What I see is have this witness but his story has shifted rather significantly over time
And you have his call records but I don't think there is Ironclad as you're making them out to be
Because for the most part they don't exactly align with your Witnesses narrative
There are key moments when they do support his version of that night
But what about the rest of the day
Whatever is true even with the prosecutor says
Moses tablet
Whatever something I'm saying is like the Holy Grail we don't know where it is
It really exists
But that's not cool though because now what you're saying is that you can use
Shuffle records
When it benefits me
That was a 30-minute cutoff
Adhan called back
So but just finished the rent went on
All the calls
The 236 call is the most Troublesome to Anan
It's the one he probably thinks about the most
Because that's the call that starts the whole chain
He also thinks about it because he says he has an alibi for that time
The Asia letters
Where she said she saw him in the library
Here's a weird thing about the 236 call
The prosecutors are very clear at trial that this is the come and get me I'm at Best Buy call
But they're not basing it on anyone's testimony
Jennifer says the call was at that time
He says repeatedly that Adnan called him around 3:40 or 3:45
Jen also says that's about when Jay left her house that day
But there is no incoming call at or near 345 on the call log
The prosecution has to go with 236
Because it's the only one that's sort of lines jstory up with the log
Is their only choice
When you tease apart the state's case you can get tripped up on details like this
Which is maybe why prosecutor Kevin urick address this head-on in his opening statement to the jury
He told them
Look at the big picture
The main plot points in Jay story have been consistent
He tells them that consistently J quote
Has always given the same story about what the defendant did wear
Consistently he tells Jennifer a consistent story
He tells police a consistent story about the defendant
It has consistently the defendants involvement
The defendant's actions on that day
He has never wavered on that point unquote
That is a lot of consistently is
Maybe it's not great oratory
It does have the advantage of being true
Commence wild a particular shifted
The spine of his story did not
Anon told Jay was going to do it and then showed him the body they buried her in Lincoln Park
They ditched her car
Jay has been consistent on those points
Itsfunneh there's this part of the trial that keeps coming back to me
Twin Christina Gutierrez is cross-examining J
Just pointing out that he lied to detectives about various things
Including the location where he says Adnan showed him his body in the trunk of the car
What you told them
Interactive showing them that place
They're not
What's the opposite of the
Objection sustained
You told them something that is not
The truth Naruto
You back it up showing them up slang
That was not true
I told him the truth
I did not show them in a location extreme now
He says I told him the truth
I did not show them a location that was true
Is oxymoronic as that sounds I think I see what he saying
Yes I told him lies
I told the truth
Overall I told the truth
Parts of J story that make no sense
It seems like there must have been more going on than he's saying
But here's what's also the truth
You can say the same thing about Adnan Story 2
Next time
On cereal
Sears produced by Julie Schneider Danish of acid me and like
A condom is our production and operations manager our glasses are editorial advisor at fact-checking by Karen fragala Smith
By Nick thorburn scoring music by Nick and my Mark Phillips show
Special thanks to fill livas and Terrence O'Connor Dan Manning Mark Thomas like Morrison and Liz Bowie our website
You can listen to all our episodes and find photos letters and other documents from the case
And sign up for a weekly emails serial podcast. Org
Ciro's Abduction of This American Life and WBEZ Chicago