Serial season 3 is the smartest way to hire
Later during the break owner of an oil exploration company
Whose top priority is hiring people who can handle a little danger in dirt
You also learn why ZipRecruiter is rated number one by Employers in the US
Based on hiring sites with over 1000 reviews on trustpilot
Ziprecruiter for free at ziprecruiter.com cereal
Support for serial comes from Squarespace
Make your business official with Google and Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and a Business website with Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and professional tools from Google
Is the simplest way to look professional online
Visit squarespace.com Google to start your free trial
And use offer code professional for a discount on your first purchase
Google and Squarespace
Make it professional make it beautiful
Previously
Hot cereal
When you're not in jail do you live with those 5 people
That's completely false
They lied under oath
Oh my God
The testimony wasn't Patty the outside of the pocket first they didn't pat down he reached into the pocket
Tell you how we fix that we don't go give this Jesus walking perpetuation
Don't trust the police
From This American Life and WBEZ Chicago
It's serial one Courthouse told week by week on Sarah Koenig
Before we get started I want to give you a warning
I know a lot of the material in this series is hard to hear and hard to think about and this story maybe especially
In part because it involves children
Rhonda gray is a police officer in Cleveland
She started as an EMT in the 80s
Then join the police force
Chris is a patrol officer
Work your way up to Detective
Then homicide detective
She's experience is what I'm saying
She seemed a lot
In early October of 2015 she spoke to a reporter from cleveland.com
Yesterday I sat at Rainbow Babies & children's hospital with a
Mother of a five month old infant
She was too distraught for me to interview her
So instead I find myself comforting her
I am
I listen to her scream that they went through the ER
The five month old infant was in davia Wakefield
She been riding in a car with her family talked into a car seat
When someone started shooting from the street
I'll be always killed
Chatterer chest
And I watch the mother the grandmother wash blood off her as she tried to save
And I just want to
Tied to the citizens of Cleveland
To speak up it's time to speak up there are people who know what happened there are people who saw what
Are people who hurt what happened
And it's time for them to speak out
Audio shooting came at the end of a hideous month for Cleveland
Four children were shot
Not teenagers
Little little kids
Three of them died
They weren't targeted
These are mistakes
Collateral damage from Street violence
The whole city was bereft
Public officials people who deal with tragedy for a living
Unravel by what was going on
And the days after IBS death cops the mayor of the County prosecutor
Beggs public to speak up
Help us talk to us speak up speak up speak up
Implored Delta chastised
Police chief Calvin Williams was plainly aggravated
All you people who complain about violence in the police
When are you going to stop yammering and do something
Didn't say it quite like that
But almost
We need people out there in the community that are concerned
Black lives
Brown lies White Lies with purple eyes
The stop out and do something not just have chance and slogans
Demarcus
We March enough
We need people to do
Help us
Which really means
Trust us
About two months after this press conference
The city held another press conference
This time they were grateful people had spoken up
They had someone in custody
This past Friday Devon Holmes was indicted on 13 felony counts
For the
Homicide of Avio Wakefield
On young guy named Devon Holmes
He just turned 19
Indictment against him was robust
2 counts of aggravated murder plus one regular murder that was for the baby
Three more attempted murders and three more felonious assault for the other passengers in the car that day
Miraculously were unhurt
And another attempted murder and felonious assault for a bystander
Was it one big law enforcement fist were pounding on the public podium
This should not be happening in our city
And we got to do something about it
Add a Vons first court appearance the prosecutor noted that quote mr. Holmes has a history of violence as a juvenile
He asked for a million-dollar Bond
The judge said sit at 1.5 million
Couple days later another judge would raise it to two million
A year after that second press conference
Almost to the day
I happen to be at a holiday party at a restaurant downtown
Biblical defense bar was trying in
I was tagging along with an attorney I've been interviewing
He's our friend and he said hey how's it going
And the friend also a defense attorney was beaming
Is a great we just got my guy out
Oh really what's the case
A murder case
Baby
We're about taking a bath
Wait what
Typically said it's a horrible case but my guy didn't do it
They got the wrong guy
Davon Holmes have been quietly released from the Cuyahoga County Jail
The charges against him dismissed
Without prejudice
Which means the county could try to resend item in future
It for now
He was free
Fabio's death
Are unassailable innocence
It's one of the 911 operator said that day
A baby baby
Killed in her car seat
It was a kind of incident that makes a city stop arguing for a bit over what the criminal justice system is doing right and what it's doing
Wrong
So that everyone seemed to lineup
Fired up
Define justice for Avio
That's why I looked into this case
And all these awful shootings from the fall of 2015
Because I figured if any homicides were going to get the full menu of police and prosecution resources
It would be these
Everyone wants to solve the case of the five month old baby
So what happened
After all that effort wrong guy
What happened why did the police think it was Davon in the first place and what happened over the course of that
At your to make the state let him go
I heard about heard about all the tiles all the kids being killed as monitor
It was it was a big issue
It was all over the news
This is Davon Holmes did you know that there was gossip that you had done it
That's what freaking me out
I didn't never thought my name was in a situation
When I knocked on his door if he'd only been out of jail for a couple of months
He was living at home with his mother I had a speech in my head about why he should talk to me but there was no need degree
Right away is it people waiting for someone to come along and ask what the heck happened
I was not able to ask the police what the heck happened
The detectives weren't allowed to talk to me and techno Cleveland officials no police officials no one from the mayor's office
Would agree to an on-the-record interview for the series
I frankly never encountered a city government with a jaw locked up tighter than Cleveland
They wanted nothing to do with us
Which is too bad because Cleveland has some interesting Leaders with ideas and lots to say about their City
Just not to me so well I did meet the homicide detectives in charge of aavielle Wakefield case I could not
Ask them
How much did you know about Davon Holmes before you arrested him
Instead
I went to Dave on
He started at the beginning right after Thanksgiving 2015
I was at my mom house going to make me a plate from
Leftover Thanksgiving
I was making a play in my mom said
What the police doing her like that
So meet me at me I just look I ain't got nothing to be scared of I ain't you know I'm saying I did nothing wrong
So I come in and dining room my mom said come here
So I woke up there
They just
Arrest
Wake up me up
I said what am I being arrested for they don't talk to you
Wouldn't talk to me
They say what I say what am I being arrested for
He say will tell you when you get downtown
It wasn't just a couple of cops at the door
It was the US Marshal's Northern Ohio violent fugitive task force in full battle rattle
There's a warrant out for his arrest
But he didn't know that
They take him downtown to the Justice Center to an interview room
And I sent a detective
You just dissed you a baby killer you you killed the baby I know you did
Everybody saying you did it we know you did it
Me I don't know what you talkin about I wasn't there I heard about the tile done
I feel bad but I'm not the one that did it y'all got the wrong guy
Are you you baby killer
You did wrong Houston
Call me baby girl
Economy all type of baby killers in
Towers in
Just belittling me
Hologram board
It was to the point that I just can't take it no more
Cuz I was cuffed up
I know what was going on
I think they was trying to scare me to
Like
Telling myself
But I can confess
I can confess to somebody to do
People do it all the time
You know
But
I was really innocent
Sussy okay I'm ready to go home
So the lady detective said no
You going
To jail for the rest of your life
The lady detective was Rhonda Gray
Same one who listen to Avila Wakefield mother screaming down the halls of the ER
Davon understood the pressure political and personal to solve crimes like these
Over weeks then months
That's what scared him
The knowledge that he didn't kill ivy all Wakefield
And he could well be convicted for killing aavielle Wakefield
Cuz I know to 3-year thano probation
Treatment this is the rest of my life
The death penalty
Does a child we talkin
So I know what to do
Davon had been locked up before but the circumstances this time made everything more foul
The creeping mold the roaches having to wash his clothes and sheets in the sink or more often the toilet
The Relentless bologna sandwiches nothing healthy to eat from commissary no no no no
Norfolk Norfolk Norfolk do this when a thing sticks in his mind
Repeat it in batches
Cuz if he's skipping a mental Stone Princeton one of his appointed attorneys Michael Shaughnessy
Is Shaughnessy a good dude though he a really good dude here real good dude
Quebedeaux ain't here just now
Savon said she honestly believed him so he didn't commit this crime
You could do what do they say do you like what do they say the state had against you
Lodi weather
Somebody saying they save me
Running with a gun in my hand somebody saying they can't identify me
No fingerprints no guns no ballistic test
No not all his work
Souly had
China Sea in another appointed attorney the one I met at the party
Would visit Des Moines periodically tell him they were working on it you have an interest in keep your head up.
Davon said he was struggling
He was pent-up in every way a person can be
He said it was almost a relief when he got in a fight with some guy and got sent to the hole
About five months in a date was set for diwan's trial
June 27th
June 27th came and went
They said another child
For late October
Week before that trial date
It too was canceled
A month after that they Vaughn's lawyers came to see him in jail
They said
Congratulations you're going home
It been a year since he was arrested
Davon said don't play with me like that
He say you go home I say when he said today
I said call my mom and tell him to come get me
Cuz I just didn't believe them
I didn't call my mom and tell her to come get me
Dakar
Can do number cry
It was just like
All my Warriors
What's relief
But it's still hurting me cuz
I just did a year
Wasted a year of my life
But telling these people is saying
They
I did not do it
David's not mad that the cops brought him in for audio Wakefield stuff
He feels like
They had information they acted on that information
Fair enough
What came after
Post-arrest
He's mad about
I feel like they should have did a little bit more investigation
Cleveland they don't
Augusta cake
They good when they come and get somebody
Today
Dang good cops for investigation
When I asked Avon why they finally let him go
He said this
Does the family
The family said that they know I had nothing to do with it
With which family
The child family
Wait that's what your lawyers told you that the child's family said you didn't have anything to do that in the Cordon
Said they heard I had nothing to do with it
How would the family now
That's what I like
Understand by the same time I'm happy that day
Realizing that I read into it
I don't think that's what happened
My mother told me
He said that's why you're getting out
So we had court in the family came
And said you didn't have nothing to do with it
And judge
Dismiss the case right there
That's crazy
If they had court why weren't you there
That's what I understand
This story made no sense to me
But once I thought about it
It makes sense why it would make no sense
Many of the defendants I talk to in Cleveland
Especially the ones who were waiting in jail
I often knew more about what was going on with their cases and they did
Just taking a quick look at the public records
Because their contact with the outside world with the workings of the Court
Is stymied by multiple layers interference like a frustrating game of telephone
Maybe you're signed attorneys checking in briefly but that's about it
So there you are in the county jail only an elevator right away from the courtroom and Prosecutors office but all you have is a
Cloudy porthole to help you decipher what's going on upstairs
I don't know what evidence Dave us attorneys did or didn't show up I don't know what they told Davon about why he was being released
Attorneys will not talk to me for the story
I think they said no out of concern for Davon
The case of Bobby a Wakefield is still open
From the list of evidence the state handed over to the
And I can roughly piece together the swatches of information that led to demands arrest
In the days right after the shooting anonymous tips began income in certain names begin to percolate and repeat
Appears 4 days after the shooting
Crime Stoppers tip Davon Holmes another one the next day
Couple days after that TC telephone call from Anonymous mail reef tank
Take his Dave on his nickname forever
Other names were still coming into
Then on October 10th
Little more than a week after the shooting police show a photo lineup to an eyewitness
I'm going to call this eyewitness the landscaper
Because he worked at a landscaper
The landscaper was there when the shooting happened
On East 145th Street off Kinsman Road
Brighten the middle of the 4th Police District
Busiest one in the city
Possibly the entire state of Ohio
The landscaper been working at a house across the street for some months
I only know the specifics because Dave owns lawyers filed a motion to suppress the evidence the landscaper gave police
In their motion they say that at first the landscaper had told police he hadn't seen the shooter
But that a little more than a week later
He came forward to say that in fact
She had
The police show him some photo arrays
He doesn't positively identify anyone
But he says two people look sort of like the shooter
Neither of them was Davon
The defense says Damon's photo was in that initial array
State says it wasn't
Any case about 5 Weeks Later the cops show the landscaper another photo lineup
First he rules out Davon
Then changes his mind
Sense of someone else's photo looks like the shooter
Finally a week after that
So 57 days after the shooting
They show the landscaper that same photo array
And he says he's going to go with his gut and that he's 90% sure it's this guy right here
Davon Holmes
Inner suppression motion Des Moines lawyers reference studies about how memory is malleable and subject to contamination
Especially in times of high stress we missed details
They argue the Davon doesn't really match the landscapers initial description of the shooter
Devon is younger shorter significantly heavier
By showing the landscaper his photo in these lineups maybe the police were in fact creating a memory
Landscaper was recognizing Davon
Because he'd seen him before in these very photo arrays
They don't mention the studies I start looking into this the talk about how when eyewitnesses pick out someone as a purpose
Trader in a police lineup they identify innocent people more than 30% of the time
30% or the ones that say you're never supposed to show an eyewitness the same photo more than once
So yeah
Nearly two months after the fact the landscaper is suddenly 90% sure of his ID
I was aware of the landscaper statement but he was more focused on and Trouble by
Another ID witness the state had
A guy I'm going to call John
Steven said John claimed to have seen Dave on after the shooting running with a gun in his hand
John had given this evidence when he himself was locked up
And facing serious charges
Aggravated robbery felonious assault
Kidnapping
Damon thinks it's John statement that got him arrested
Paper it does look as if the case clicked into place as soon as John talked
Court records show that detectives talk to John on November 18th
And that same day they showed the landscaper another photo lineup with a Vons picture in it
9 days later is when the violent fugitive task force banks on Devon store
Interruptus Thanksgiving leftover
But the disturbing part for Davon is that he knows John
Well
And why did he idea
It was it was something to happen with my brother a long time ago
Invite you want a little tangent now
Just because when I first heard what happened
I couldn't quite believe it
John's older brother and a Vons older brother
We're best friends
One day in 2007 when David's brother was 16 John's brother was 15
They tried to rob a guy coming back from the corner store
We just bought Newport cigarettes in a bag of popcorn
Teenagers had a gun
The guy also had a gun
And he shot and killed John's brother
The fifteen-year-old
Because they were together
And we're trying to commit a crime
And this is the part that blew my mind until I looked up the definition of felony murder
But de Vaughn's brother was charged with the murder of his best friend
Even though he didn't fire the weapon
Davon 16 year old brother was bound over to the Justice Center
Meaning he was transferred from Juvenile Court
Where the maximum sentence he could get was around 5 years
And prosecuted as an adult
He was sentenced to 18 years to life
He can try for parole in March of 2025
He's unlikely to get it
In the aftermath of all this
David said his family and John's family refine
Animosity
In fact his uncle is with John's mom
I thought of John has a brother
The way John statement was worded interpretation was that John wanted to hurt Deion's family
Maybe he blamed a Vons brother for his own brother's death
And wanted Revenge
I like the pain
I want to make clear that this isn't one of those cases where the honor student gets profiled by the cops because he was wearing a hoodie and lives in Ark
Kingsman
When was treated like The Usual Suspects
Because he is the usual
Who's part of the largest most Troublesome gang in Cleveland
The heartless felons
Imagine the cops in Cleveland's fourth district were familiar with the Burley kid called tank long before I'll be awake field was killed
What is brother was locked up for his best friend's death
Davon was 10 years old
Damon told me himself was first locked up
When he was 10 years old
Strong arm robbery
Much as I am tempted to connect these two events
Davon is in
Made it I was angry about it like you I lost my big brother but
That wasn't the reason I was in the streets cuz I was in the streets when he was home
My brother used to make me go home
I get out go home
And I
Fake like a act like I was going home but I'll just go down another Street
What were you doing just being in the neighborhood
Throwing rocks at cars just being bad
And were you just skipping school all the time are you going to school fight
Beautiful teachers
Breaking a cars going to school
Anyway
Dora rocks
Just
Give me food at the cafeteria in school
Run around security chasing me
They called my mama mama chase me through the school this is the school right across the street from Dave a
Don's house it's closed now boarded up
Davon has abiding respect for his mother
She loves them she tried to guide him never gave up on him
But when he was at that age he says he listen to No One not as mother definitely not as teachers
It doesn't actually know how far he got in school maybe 7th grade maybe 9th
Devin said he loved being in the streets
Infatuated with the word he used you loved all of it
The fast money and the car is in the girls the most of the rush adrenaline running away from people
Being chased he hated school but this came easily to him he said
Is a leader among his friends and organizer
You got older be sold drugs got a gun with the money got caught for Stuff Center residential programs group
Holmes Escape
Has 14 he got seriously hurt shot in the elbow going to vicious car from it
You sent to a juvenile prison for the first time that same year
By that time Davon was already a heartless felon
A gang members prefer to call it a family
That was born about 15 years ago inside Ohio's juvenile prisons
And then spread to the world outside
Loyalty in his willingness to engage in combat
Earned him a pretty high rank in prison
He got into fights with guards
Which brought new assault charges which in turn brought more prison time
Is original six-month sentence stretch to 3 years
When he was almost 18 he came home
When he got picked up for the murder of adiel Wakefield he was just starting to Tire of the streets he said
Starting to slow down
Idle hard time comprehending devons resume
Specifically Dave on the early years
When he was a little boy
9-10 years old
Richard scare though doing it by your side understand like how a little kid can be like I know why don't I
Prison intake her money order like when she terrified
Why not
Just wasn't
Did you know it was did you feel like
It was wrong do you feel like it's wrong now
What you mean
I don't I don't I don't
I'll have
Remorseful nothing I did
Minot
Cuz I did it
Okay be sorry for someone I did
La Colonia
Only
Change from it
But I ain't going to be sorry for what I did
Oh I'll regret nothing at all
Did
Lights out
Even if I see somebody today that I harm
That is some years ago
Imma be one soon as I see him honestly would as soon as I see him imma get into I'm going to get in defense mode
Did you get it
Oh no I'm probably weird to you
He is weird to me
We talked a lot about remorse which he doesn't feel
And regret
Would you also says he doesn't feel but which I think he does
And responsibilities
Which he feels keenly
He told me he's not going to deny he did something
If he did it
He says he didn't shoot that baby
He says he doesn't know who did
But even if you did now
He wouldn't tell
We're sitting right here on this couch she said
And he sees out the window someone shoots someone else
He's either going to leave before the cops show up
Or if he does get question
He's going to help
The cops is unhelpfully as he can
I don't know what happened
I didn't see it
But what if you did see it
Island I don't know
Who did it
Did you see
Okay did you see it yeah I sent it
What happened
He got killed
How
He got shot
Who did it
I don't know
Did you see him
Yeah
What do you look like I don't know
Which way he go
He just ran
I'm helping but
I'm not going to say
He having a black coat he went down that way he got in that car I'm not doing all that
Because why that's what I'm trying to understand why not
I wasn't raised like that
I don't care if you was my worst enemy I'm not telling on you
I don't care what you did
It don't matter if you was
If you was the oldest nice as mean as lady
I am the oldest makes me not even if even if it was a lady
Because it's your principal you're just saying it's not about the consequences for me it's just a principle
That's against my religion
Number say that
That's against my religion to tell us
Cuz you're going to make me I'm not going to feel right
Imma feel less of a man
What if it was like a relative who is your
The victim of it
You don't even has your principal Bend at all with
Nature of the crime yet
No
We just going to have to handle it a different way
Meaning Street Justice
Which Davon can get behind
The Cleveland Police Justice or Justice Center Justice
No way
This is precisely what vexes police investigations in cases like ivl's
It's probably as old as crime itself
Friendly's old is organized crime
No snitching
It's not just about gangster quotes of loyalty though
Over the decades it's been helped Along by the criminal justice system itself
Especially during the War on Drugs
You could argue no snitching was a rational response to the widespread use of low-level informants
To be threatened with mandatory prison sentences if they didn't talk
Prom was his Lola bond form and sometimes didn't know that much
Some people are getting arrested based on flimsy or false information
And then of course people don't cooperate because of straight up fear
Well-supported fear
Until we watch the no snitching principle play out during trials and Cleveland
I've never fully understood How Deeply it muddies cases
We watched a capital murder case
In which Witnesses were visibly scared
Even some of the jurors were scared
And they weren't paranoid
The defendant was a heartless felon
Already one witness have been shot and killed in his driveway just before he was supposed to come to court
We watched another case in which a police informant had been murdered
We saw people squirm on the stand
Prevaricate
Probably the most torture testimony we saw it was from a man who goes by RJ
Hey banana gang
He was an important witness during the trial for the murder of one of the other children killed that follow 2015
Major Howard
It was 3 years old
It was a drive-by
When the shooting happened RJ was there on his front porch
University became a bit of a media hero because you tried to help major
Any news video he's sitting on his porch shirtless being interviewed
It looks sad and dazed
He's got staples up his arm
Holding together a wound from wrist to Elbow the result of an unrelated shooting the week before
The words never snitch are tattooed in fancy script just below his collar bones
A trial the prosecutor and a fry Leah
Made it clear to the jury that RJ had told detectives he seen the defendant
Donnell Lindsey known as now
Shooting from the window of a white car
Now today almost a year-and-a-half since he made that statement
RJ was on the stand
Saying it wasn't true
Nice and nobody showing
Okay
Didn't see the shooter didn't even see the car
Soon as he heard shots he ducked down onto his porch floor he said
To all he saw was his porch ceiling
And the little chairs he's got out there
Didn't see Donnell Lindsey at all the day major Howard was killed
Jennifer Ali-A tries to tease out of him why the discrepancy between these two statements
I will
I don't know what to do
RJ begins to spiral
It's hard to follow
Which I have to think was at least partly by Design
He says he's got all this pressure on him and no one can help them
Is Eva nassios in prison
He's serving time now in a different case
What should I do should he testify
He feels it was right to help the baby says
Best thing I ever did
A lot of people in the street or talking about him
Threatening him
Is getting in fights in prison now
Because people afraid he's a snitch
Eventually he says to Anna faraglia
I didn't see Donna Lindsay myself
I just told detectives what I'd heard from other people
Because my face is already been in the news and since I was already public
People in the neighborhood started coming to me with information
People who are scared themselves with scattered before police arrived that day
It's really passing their information to the detectives not my own information
And that was also a good deed
I could have run like other people did I could have shut my door
I knew the police were looking for me for another shooting
But I tried to help that baby
I talked to detectives
What else do you want from me
It went on like this for hours
Finally
I have heard
It's a movie move
State's exhibit 351 is an autopsy photograph
Adorable little major Howard's dead body
She has the photo to RJ
Is that what you tried to help
Is that a yes or a no
You try to help us little boy
Okay
And don't you think you owe it to him
The tallest jury who shot this little boy and not be afraid anymore sir
Front
RJ swamp
Starts to cry
Play major was shot RJ random
Took off his own shirt wrapped around him
Jumping a car and held onto major
Well they rushed to the hospital
Major was still conscious
Looking up at him
Touching his chest
Dying
4 years old
RJ was still tormented by it
Did now shoot this little boy
Two-seater shooting from a white car that night
And all I asking you
Other people saying
Can you step up
Should I'm trying to do the best way I can
Alvin Gators telling the truth
I told you my truth
Anna says to him
Let's get real
You won't deliver because you're afraid of Retribution
Tell me gay members that come in the courtroom sat in the back
Trying to get Margie's head
She said to RJ
Afraid because you broke the code
He says that ship sailed the moment I picked up that little boy
I broke the code by talking to the news reporter who approached me on the street
I broke the code by speaking to the cops
I'm breaking the code right now by sitting in this courtroom
Doesn't even really matter what words I say
Just being here is enough
Like I said I already said I broke up with her talking to you
Tomorrow
Marlene is more fun to talk to you
Carpro
I talked to a few jurors about the case afterwards
Two out of the three said they didn't believe are Json Ellen the car
But there was other evidence aside from RJ and Donna Lindsay was convicted he got 37 years
Instalife
For what it's worth his lawyers don't think he did it that's actually unusual for them
Watch the whole trial and he came away not at all convinced Donnell Lindsey was guilty I still don't know what to think
So what exactly did they have on Davon Holmes
New video
No physical evidence
No fingerprints no DNA
Logan
I found out Davon apparently had made a statement placing himself in the vicinity of the crime
Saying he been at the Family Dollar at the top of the street and it seems people running
Tumi Davon denied making any such statement
Police had gotten his cell records would show that he was indeed nearby at the time of the shooting but considering he lives only a few blocks
Max from where the shooting happened
The cell records seems underwhelming
The eyewitnesses were Paramount
At least on paper they look wobbly
It was John the guy Dave on new
. offered information from jail
Witnesses like that are inherently weak
The defense can always argue the person's lying to get a deal
I wasn't able to reach John
But I did talk to someone close to him
I believe is reliable
Who said they had talked to John about his statement
This person told me
That was John told the police
Code it's not true
This person said John had lied
To save himself to try to avoid going to prison
Didn't think John did it because of his brother's death
But yes
He does still suffer over his brother
But they didn't think that was the reason John lied about Davon
So the landscapers ID was probably the strongest thing they had
I wasn't sure what to make of his sudden Clarity 57 days post shooting
Was he somehow manipulated by the police or maybe he been scared of choosing the wrong person or the right person
Maybe he just made a mistake
I went looking for him one day at various addresses around the city
Emmanuel and I left notes and our business cards talk to mail boxes in front doors
It works
I got a call that same night from the landscaper
He did not trust me
The neighbors had seen a manual and me walking around with her hands in her pockets
We look like cops
I told him it was cold outside that's why
I asked him if we could meet so we could see if himself I was harmless
But the more I asked the more suspicious he thought I was trying to set him up to arrest him
We spoke a couple of times on the phone
He was upset his name was part of Dave on the case
He was told his name would stay out of it
He said they threatened me that if they didn't come to court they put me in jail
He thinks they dropped avons case because they didn't want to pay out the reward money
Which is $25,000
Landscaper was full of conspiratorial forever
I got the feeling he come by honestly
Sometime later a woman called me
She said she was family to the landscaper
She said you should be careful what you do
Because you can come in and ask all these questions but then you get to leave we don't we live here
Kill you
Will cops in our family I know how things happen
I told her I know she's right
I am trying to tread delicately
We talked for a long time
We're finally by the end she said she tell the landscaper to talk to me
But he never did
Fred hung up with him that last time the landscaper asked me have you talked to the baby's family
You been in contact with Charles Wakefield Abigail's father he said
You should talk to the family
That's coming up
After the break
This is the road to hire
Brought to you by ZipRecruiter Charles Becker works on an oil field in Tech
For the company PML exploration services
And it's his job to hire mud loggers
Basically is a rig is drilling for oil
It's also pumping a bunch of mud out of the ground and mud loggers
Monster Mutt
They look at it and analyzed the chemicals in rocks that are coming out of the ground
You're looking for indicators of
Where
Highest amount of oil and gas is
Call methane is in Tater of oil it smells like farts that means that there's oil
H2S
Sh2 S&S bad
Because I would have already killed
Yeah drilling rigs are not the most safest place
That's just one of the reasons why it's really hard to find people who are willing to become a bloggers
You also have to be away from home 21 days out of the month in the middle of nowhere sturdy it's hot
It was so hard to find people
Until Charles started using ZipRecruiter
He started getting tons of qualified candidate
The point where I now have a pipeline of people who are waiting an eager to jump into whenever any people just turn on the hose
That's a lot of metaphors
If you are looking for candidates with Grit
ZipRecruiter is powerful matching technology for free
At ziprecruiter.com cereal
Ziprecruiter.com serial ZipRecruiter
The smartest way to hire
Support for serial comes from Squarespace
Make your business official with Google in Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and a Business website with Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and professional tools from Google
It's the simplest way to look professional online
Visit squarespace.com Google to start your free trial
And use offer code professional for a discount on your first purchase
Google and Squarespace
Make it professional make it beautiful
I've been waiting to contact mr. Wakefield
Until
I don't know I had more information I guess
But really I was avoiding it
I figured it would be painful for him and professionally a little used to me
We know I know the whole story so
I got to say it's just the waiting game
I was being a dummy
Charles Wakefield is a lovely welcoming person who says he knows exactly what happened
First shot hit in the
Back at the front
Passenger tire
And I think the bullet wanted to the dashboard in a second but it went in the corner of the passenger window
Wish where my mom was sitting at
Then the third bullet went in the back door and through her car seat
Charles wasn't there himself
He wasn't a witness
He doesn't have any proof for his version of what happened
Song information he's gathered from other people
I'm going to be beeping at a name here
The version of the story he feels confident is true
Is it some guys were shooting dice in a building on East 145th Street off Kinsman
Sometime earlier one of them had been robbed maybe at another dice game or there's been some gambling issue Charles wasn't sure about that
That part
I later learned there had been a shooting
Anyway these guys were ready to retaliate
They're on the lookout for particular car
A car that looked a lot like Charles's car
House of the guy they were after I had a white 2000 Oldsmobile Aurora
Charlesetta White
2001 Oldsmobile Aurora
Only difference was
He has had tinted windows
And ours had a sunroof
The guys playing the dice game see an Oldsmobile coming
Charles has one of them recognized it
Somebody
That was there with them
New my car
Tomato
They said that ain't the car
But once I started firing anyway
Beyonce Ayesha was driving
His elderly mother was in the passenger seat
Behind her was aviao
I'm behind Aisha was her other daughter
Who is 8 years old
They were driving to the Save-A-Lot just a few blocks away to get ingredients for Charles's birthday cake
Is his birthday the next day
I just seen the person with that car but I don't know who he is
I actually met him up at the carwash when I first met him
You know somebody got the same type of car they and you know it just bursts a conversation and next thing I know somebody was shooting at
That same car but it was my car thinking it was
His car
I'm not sure why this hadn't occurred to me before
But it was hitting me now talking to Charles
He lives right here
The shooting happened down the street from where we're sitting
The people he thinks are involved with his daughter's death they also live
Right here
Within blocks of each other some of them
Of course he knew things
I heard things
Best Charles about Davon
Tank
When he got arrested did you think oh okay they got them
Yeah I know right away was to
I know this is where I'm going to start beeping
Because trials
Doesn't think it was
He told me a story about another person
How many names
Soon as the shots was fired my car was hit
Wanted to do is come running to me
First words, his mouth is
Said he going to holler at you
And in my head I'm thinking like why would he say
And I'm putting on highlighter
What did you take that to me as he's going to holler at you
But he's got to see how to speak to you about something
I pretty much he was either gone or I believe
They didn't think my daughter was going to die
So he was going to
You know try to patch up but but she end up dying so it
I couldn't become do it no more
And then it was
Probably few days later
United States started talking then
All fingers pointing back to
How many people talk to you about it
Well for 5 p
People that came out of their mouth
And you're pretty sure it wasn't just an echo chamber where is like they'd all her the same single rumor it was a different information
Different information
Charles knows this guy he's talking about
They weren't close friends but they definitely knew each other and had been cool with each other
He says ever since the shooting this guy acts strangely when he sees them
Twitchy
Twitchy is a useful towel in the movie version of the story
But it is not evidence
Anything really
But to Charles it feels like this guy's body language is what gives him away
And it's not even me like he he will see one of my buddies that I'm kind of close within my buddy with her this hot new
Casey minajesty and I was like
He took off like he jumped in somebody car that he wasn't even in and took off
And I'm like well he did he like I know bro
Has he finally confronted the guy himself
In the street
I broke my wife cheat
Running from me
Elite
I ain't running from you I said what why I got to stay in the middle of the street to flag you down to come back right now
Is that what happened in a car
When you stood out travel to the people across the street
I was walking back from the store
He was facing this way
When I turned the corner
He backed up in my driveway and went that way
So I'm in the middle of the street
Like this with my arms up
Boyfriend look through the rearview mirror
Finally he looks through the rearview mirror
He stops
The car
He comes back when you got somebody to car one
And the look on his face was like
I think he just wanted me to do something to him so he can
Press charges and give me like that
And I'm looking at him like
Hybrid just tell me what happened I like my daughter did I know you want to live you Thailand
Running from you every time you see me
You know what I said he
I don't know what to tell you
I was at the wrong place at the wrong time or something about the card you it was the wrong car son whatever he
You told me but I'm telling him like that ain't it
I like I told him it ain't just me that's mad at you
You got it Mason of people you kill the innocent
Baby
I can't stop people from doing what they feel
In my heart
I'm not the only person to know your face now
It's like you're telling this to me in it in a very moderate tone was at
At the tone of the conversation where you screaming in the street
Girls wasn't scared when worried about someone coming after him for telling police what he'd heard is a grieving father of a day
Dead baby daughter the rules didn't apply to him or if they didn't care he should sidestep the game
M2 and turn himself in
Calling in anonymous tips about Davon
One reason he said was because Davon changed his appearance soon after the shooting it cut his dreads
Because he cut his dreads off claiming that he had a warrant for some he did on the Westside
So it made everybody think you know he has something to do with it
So
He had a gun
But he didn't shoot
Wait so you're saying tank was there
He was there and he had a gun he just didn't you
Who was there
Have you ever spoken to him
News from the tank
Oh you did
Where'd you see him
At the store
Teavana told me he didn't know the Wakefield family
And you guys speak what do you say
You know he just say
He seemed pretty much sizing me up to see if I still think if he had something to do with it or if I'm going you know.
Do something to him or you know like that but
Hino
If I want to do something other than did it
I respect that man enough he stayed in jail for about a year for something he didn't do so
But you're saying he knows what hap
He knows but I mean he didn't do it it's a difference between knowing and doing are two different things
Why do you think it took so long
For them to let
Pink out
That was too they was trying to get him to snitch on that I was just at the dry out
Turn the volume up that's all that was
They know team didn't do that and never let him out
Charles thinks the state indicted Davon on three different kinds of murder charges and held them in a filthy jail cell for a full year
And Hope
That he turn on
Kevin told me he doesn't know
Charles feels pretty sure he does
3 clear Charles did not know who Tavon was before all this happened
But he told me several times he's got no problem with him now
Okay
So I've been talking to Dave on for 4 months by this point and he had not said any of this to me
Given categorical
He knew nothing about that shooting wasn't there didn't know any of these people
After I talk to Charles I went back to Davon ran all this by him
Are you set aside from yes recognizing Charles Wakefield on the street none of it was true
He said he'd heard all these same rumors I had
That's what they were
Rumors
Stories
Which by virtue of repetition do not become true
I don't know if they Vons telling me the truth about what he knows or doesn't know
But now that I know what I know I wouldn't be surprised if he's not I might be the oldest nicest meanest lady
But at the end of the day I'm still an outsider
Well I can understand why Charles feels that his information is solid and true
At the end of the day
It's all secondhand
You're naming to me like individual people who you think were there and would know the same story your time
And yet not one of them it seems like has
Gone to the police or talk to the police about it does that surprise you
No not really I mean like I said comes the boys down to nobody want to be labeled a snitch
And everybody to tell me
Who did it
But you know cuz I can't go to the office or welts I just told me
They have to tell the you know so
I don't notice that make you mad at all your
This is me all the way up like every time I go outside I just look at everybody different like you know
What happened
Don't say that
You know so
That's just how I look at everybody like
You know that's the same one
And then I would let you cuz you know you've been through this whole time
Charles is a big man
Big and soft around the edges
His mother told me he was always a crier
But now that your seem to leak from him unbidden
His mom told me the loss of his baby was a soft hurt
Which I took to mean still tender
I didn't know him before Abigail died
But my son's now is that he is ravaged by the loss of her
Halfway through a conversation I realized I was talking to him from the same place he sleeps
An oversized armchair and matching ottoman in the living room
At the foot of the makeshift bed with a coffee table
Covered with photographs and mementos of IDL
Charles has been a stay-at-home father
I used to work and so he took care of IBL all day
He felt very close to her
Since the shooting he's had a hard time not thinking about her and her death in the unsolved case
Every minute
It just kind of makes me want to take matters to your own hand
Is that a possibility that you would do something about it yourself
No I'm not not okay
But nobody in this in
This pain that I feel
Cuz nobody else deal with it
Just the me knowing is somebody going to be sitting
Feeling like this
Hotel versus bro man
Vista disable pay yuan
It might be I got a conscious like I can't live life
But
Play worth it
I've had the opportunity
Plenty of times I know where you at
No worries they know where you be I know everything I need
That's what hurt me
Maybe I should go get her
Imma be on the road
That's where I get my satisfaction from knowing that
His life will never be the same
But
All going right now as we speak he probably laughing it
But it is mine
It's not right
Charles feels as though he can't directly ask anyone to come forward and speak to the police
Understands snitches get killed
He wants to live in a world where snitching is unnecessary
I heard this from several people interviewed in Cleveland
If the cops just did their jobs better
Civilians wouldn't be put in an impossible position
System shouldn't send
Need
The public to do its job
That's the stamp I like they all they do is get out here
Ask somebody else to do their job like no you get out here and
Look for the person you think did it
Steady want somebody else to tell on somebody
But I mean isn't that them doing their jobs always try to get how I mean they're not magic like they weren't here the only way they could
Information is people telling them information
No they get information about getting out here in these streets in in finding information except just like I did
Right but that still would require someone to tell
I mean like if they go to
The same people who talk to you they're asking them to tell
Right but no I'm saying
That person will be telling them instead of telling me
You said I was saying like this is easy like I said the whole neighborhood and told me what happened
Exactly
Because he's not a cop
I got to say most the detectives I talked to told me that back in the day
20 years ago
Even 10 years ago
They did have better relationships with the people they police
There wasn't as much animosity toward them for one thing
They used to have a substantial community policing unit
Former Commander that told me
22 police mini stations
Staff with two officers each
Plus dare officers at schools
Officers at public pools
Police didn't materialize only in the aftermath of disaster
They were visibly around
They could develop relationship
Which in turn could lead to information
You make a quiet phone call
And people on the other end of the line with trust you
To keep their names out of it
I don't know whether these guys were waxing nostalgic
But everyone I talked to agree that it has been degrading in recent years this relationship with the public
The team in charge of police reform in Cleveland recently surveyed officers
They should report a few months ago
That included officers estimating that 60% of people they come into contact with
Want nothing to do with them
The police many stations were asked more than a decade ago
Budget cuts led to the department losing hundreds of officers
Charles said he did relay everything he'd been hearing to the cops
Specifically to detective articles
And detective Rhonda gray we're running the investigation
Joe says he was calling and calling leaving messages
I got information I got another person
He says he never got a call back
My dad just went cold
The guy Charles believe shot ivl the police are aware of him
Charles didn't tell me anything he hadn't already told police
And anyway he said detective Ackles already heard that same guys name almost as soon as Charles dead
This man himself knows the police are aware of him I met him at is I recognized in one day at the justice
Center while he was sitting on a bench waiting to make a 10 a.m. Jail visit
And I asked if I could talk to him about the Wakefield case
I gave my card
He was unequivocal no
I got nothing to say I just want to leave all that in the past
It's over
The last time Charles met with the detectives was late November of 2016
They called him and Ayesha to tell them they had important news
They all gathered in the prosecutor's office
For the detectives and prosecutors explained they be letting Davon Holmes out of jail
Charles said he told them yeah
Because tank didn't do it
They said they'd still be pursuing the case
Still looking at other suspects
Including the guy Charles Blues today
They discuss that guy
They discussed Avon
I wanted to take the told me he liked well
You know I believe they're going to be at each other and you know this and that like you don't even
Basically saying they're going to kill each other
That's what he said to you
This is Echo
Olympic
That was the day they let think about you and I will you know
How do you say don't worry about it Mr Rayfield delegate they're going to still deal with each other
Pretty after a while
They're going to close passing they going you know it's going to be between them to now
That's what it was
I pretty much shocked it
Me and the guys I'll be with haven't did nothing
No kind of proud of you like you know I'm glad you ain't did nothing yet but
Don't worry it's going to happen
You know me like
That's kind of was
I wasn't able to run this by detective Ackles
Again the Cleveland Police Department didn't want to comment on it
Prosecutor at the meeting said he didn't remember detective Echols saying that
But I can kind of imagine it
I had this meeting the Cleveland Police Department had only 12 homicide detectives murders in Cleveland reaching the
Are highest numbers in a decade
So yeah I can see a cop saying to Charles
Between us I think your best bet is to let them kill each other
Quiet bitter nod to the supremacy of Street Justice
So
What did get out of jail
Well it was detective work
But not by detectives
The next time
Ontario
Cereals produced by Julie Schneider
Emmanuel jyothi Ben Calhoun and me with additional reporting by Eataly uskoski and a fee Scruggs editing on this episode from
Hourglass Whitney Dangerfield is our digital editor research and fact-checking by Ben Phelan sound design and mix by snow
Bill Nelson additional production from Kate belinski
Music lyrics by Anthony Roman said land is our director of operations zero staff includes Emily Condon
Julie Whitaker Cassie Holly Francis Swanson and Matt Tierney
Our music is by Adam Dorn and how will their with additional music from Matt McGinley Nick thorburn Fritz Myers and West Schwartz
Our theme song is by Nick thorburn and remix by Adam Dorn special thanks to Ronnie Dunn Dan Flannery
Jeff helgeson Jeff Cardenas OB Shelton Michelle Harris Marvin cross detective Philip shutter at the
The police department judge Ronald Adrian. Cassandra Collier Williams Jetta manual Groves Gary Webb
Well and Sergeant Jennifer ciaccia at the Cleveland Police Department the art on our website was made by Jess X snow
She created the mural for this episode
And my studio did the animation please check it out on our website serial podcast. Org
That serial podcast. Org
Or you can also sign up for email newsletter and be notified when new episodes are released
We're also course on Facebook and Twitter
Support for serial comes from ZipRecruiter
Unlike many job site ZipRecruiter doesn't wait for candidates to find you
ZipRecruiter find some for you
So you get qualified candidates fast
Tried free at ziprecruiter.com cereal that ziprecruiter.com cereal
Support for serial comes from Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and Business website with Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and professional tools from Google
Use offer code professional for discount on your first purchase
Serials production of This American Life and WBEZ Chicago