I spent more than a year inside the criminal courthouse in Cleveland Ohio
I want to tell you quickly about this one case I watch
Early on
The case was set for trial
Was about to start
The judge
You telling the defendant that he might be wise to just
Skip the trial
I plead guilty
Is risking a lot of prison time
Have you thought about
The judge was listing the charges
Counting all the years that defendant might be looking at if we were found guilty by a jury
So does it make sense
Taurus
Additional
28 years
In counts 1 and 2 alone
I believe he's charged with either three or four kidnappings is that correct
The numbers kept growing
36 years
42 years
For the kidnapping charges alone
Adding to the tension
Is that the defendant had a lawyer standing next to him
But he didn't want to use them
He wanted to represent himself
The judge was telling him
Awful idea you're already screwing this up
How prideful can you be
The defendant name is Greg Rucker
Was in his early twenties
He pleaded guilty instead of going to trial
Who's going to do maybe
560 years
The judge kept Adam
Sure you don't want to change your mind we're about to choose the jurors
I thought for sure Greg Rucker would cave
It was such an onslaught
Priester there in his jail scrubs and Crocs
Quiet but firm
He knew what he was doing he wanted to trial
Besides me there was only one other person in the gallery
A friend of Greg's
At riding young guy named Drake
During a break he stepped out into the hallway I followed
Craigslist started appealing to him
I'm very concerned
For your friend
Bright
The lawyer also thought it was Madness
For Greg to go to trial
She said to drink if you have any way to talk to him
I am I tried but
Drake started talking about Greg's basketball game
How he digs in
Fights Back even when he's down
Which I could see was making the lawyer wonder whether Drake was grasping the gravity of the
Situation
That Type of Way some years it's not a game
Dino
But I mean
I hope that'll be smart about it
The lawyer said he told Greg
Look if you plead you can get out from under this case
And still be in your 20s
Set of getting out when he almost 60
It seem crazy to me
The great to get Decades of prison time
Because
His alleged crime
Was mugging three people early one Sunday morning
At gunpoint so that's bad
He wasn't holding the gun
Another guy was
Co-defendant
Didn't use the gun no one was injured
But Greg was charged with seven very serious felonies
Including three kidnapping
Probably not the kind you're thinking of
The kidnappings were for hindering people's freedom
Wild it robbed them
Drake was sure he was in a cell
He said yes Greg had committed other crimes
Before they talked about it
But this one he told drag
He wasn't there
It wasn't him
I believe for a fact you didn't do it
My thought was if Greg Rucker was risking that much prison time and if he was so sure
Where is case that he wanted to argue it alone
Without the interference of a lawyer
Either Greg Rucker was innocent
He was bonkers
Next day trial again Greg decided to let his lawyer represent him
Good idea everyone agreed the state brought out all the victims and they were Charming
A guy who only Beloved ice cream business
Married couple delivering Plain Dealer newspapers
The wife of the couple Victoria with a teacher at a Christian School
Her Labyrinth sweater and hair Arrangement reminded me of Holly Hobbie
She presented as wholesome
A kind
She called the man who stole her car
Stuck a gun in her husband's face who made her feel like either he or she or the both of them are about to die
She called them the white gentleman rights could have been it was white
And the black gentleman
Choose the perfect State's Witness
Except
She couldn't identify Greg Rucker
No I did not
Her husband also couldn't identify Greg
Another guy who been mud by this Duo have been riding his bike when they came up on him
He can pick out Greg
Can I buy a hundred percent safe for sure
No one saw Greg Rucker
Also there was no physical evidence against him
I know police body camera security footage of caught him on phone
I started to think okay what are the chances I would wander into a wrongful process
Execution right off the bat
There's no way
On the other hand after two days of trial the state's case did seem kind of weak
Maybe cracker was innocent
Who's right
Vista trial
The den
There was a third day
That morning the prosecution introduced jailhouse calls between Gray
His co-defendant
In these recordings
Great sounding
Guilty
Super guilty is how he sounded
Talking about how the cops are onto them how he might avoid being identified
On top of that the co-defendant
Adobe thick tongue fell out with a superlative widow's peak
Testified that indeed Greg had helped him commit these robberies
Greg's one Alibi with
His former girlfriend
Did him no favors
Her testimony may not much sense at all
Sono
By the end I realized
Not around 4 Prosser
Secretion
Eyewitness
Irregular process
And yet inside this regular prosecution
I seen a Litany of things that shouldn't be allowed
Was like a checklist of almost all the stuff reformers complain about
Extra charges loaded onto a case
Pressure to bleed Chevy police work a police officer possibly lying on the stand
11th Hour evidence shoehorned into a trial overworked attorneys
Dozing jurors
And finally an outsized prison sentence
But no one was stomping their feet too hard about any of that
In the Cleveland Courthouse this was a nothing case
No not really watching
Besides
Why would anyone care
Greg was guilty
Did you listen to serial before you probably know that our first
Season was about a murder case in Baltimore
Ever since that story aired people have asked me in the people I work with
What is that case tell us about the criminal justice
An answer is the case of Adnan Syed wasn't typical in any way
Defendant with no criminal record
Private defense
Attorney where is Duvall a six-week trial
The vast majority of cases don't even go to trial
I don't think we can understand how the criminal justice system works
By interrogating one extraordinary case
Ordinary case
This is her where we need
To luck
The season of Serial we do just that we take a look at the entire criminal justice system
A year inside the criminal courts in Cleveland Ohio
We chose Cleveland because they let us record everywhere
Courtroom
Back hallways judge's Chambers the prosecutor's office
Then we followed those cases outside the building into neighborhoods to people's houses and in prison
Every case we looked into there came a time when I said
Wait this can't be happening
And then it did from This American Life and WBEZ Chicago its serial
1 Courthouse
Told week by week
You'll see what we saw
From the inside Hero season 3 coming
September 20th listen And subscribe on Apple podcast Google podcast Pandora
Wherever you get your podcasts
Exclusive sponsor serial season 3
Is ZipRecruiter