Hello serial listeners
It's Sarah Cain egg with a quick reminder
That we have
Two other pods
There's This American Life weekly show that chooses one theme and then has a mix of weird emotional and
Investigative
And personal stories on that
Cereal started as a spin-off of
Where we developed our storyteller
Gun shops
SOS
Beautiful 7-part series that explores the life of one man in Alabama
As Town starts out as one thing and then become something
Totally
Fascinatingly differ
This American Life and s-town
Available now on podcast
Or At This americanlife.org and s-town podcast
If I hear someone else I don't think you did it cuz you're a nice guy is not
Previously on serial
Did anybody else use
Yeah
Hainan I remember he's talking to a girl
On the phone with her so I can read minutes
I just remember he had told my daughter he had seen
Cuz of the body of a girl in the back of such are the trunk of some vehicle
I think the guy's name was maybe Adnan
Global Tel Link prepaid call from
Maryland Correctional Facility
From This American Life and WBEZ Chicago its serial one story
I told week by week I'm Sarah Koenig
I heard about this other case of a kid named Justin wolf
Actually passing I can't remember how he heard about it. A lot of different stuff in prison
Talking about the cell records and how they were used in a non case in a non said that in this other case of just
Sell records had also been used against him
But then Justin Wilson conviction was overturned
In part because of the cell record
So I looked at this case of Justin Wolfe just to see
I have to say it's sort of uncanny how many similarities there are with add-ons case
All young people first of all
Justin Wolfe was a Suburban kid 18 football player
People thought of him as a good kid though he was selling pot and hanging around with some tougher types
Does next Hearts different obviously
He was convicted in the 2001 murder of a drug dealer who was shot nine times
Justin Wolfe was not the shooter
The shooter was a slightly older friend of wolves Barber
Who got a deal in exchange for testifying against Justin Wolfe
Owen Barber told the cops that Justin wasn't hired him to kill the drug dealer
What was sentenced to death in Virginia
Wolf trial attorney later gave up his law license after the bar had initiated disciplinary charges against him for
This is the technical term
Being a crappy lawyer
And there was a witness who was never heard from
Anyhow eventually Owen Barbara mercante
He said Justin Wolfe had nothing to do with a murder
He'd only implicated wolf to avoid a death sentence for himself
Let me talk to the lawyer who helped figure out the flaws in the state's case against Justin Wolfe
Maybe she has some tips about how we should be looking at the cell records differently in Adnan case
I looked her up her name is Deirdre Enright
And she works at the University of Virginia school of law
She runs their Innocence Project Clinic their Innocence Project
Someone's been wrongfully convicted
I called her and asked how she dealt with the cell records in the Justin Wolfe case
And she was kind of so-so on that topic
She gave me a couple of names to try
Batman on every other topic I found her so help
She started asking me about anons case and I ended up sending her a summary I'd made of the detective's report
The next time we talk I asked if she'd mind going to a studio
Hey you know I read
Your
Synopsis of your
To jump right into your case okay if I have a million questions
Very very thin
Yeah
After I started reading all this
Although what you had
I started thinking
So everybody here is in high school
Right
And why is done
Doesn't appear to be
Interest anyone
Done with his new boyfriend to the police considered his Alibi Ironclad he was working at LensCrafters all day
See this is how it is with Deirdre
A conversation with her never seems to begin exactly
It's already there ongoing her thoughts
Turning and you just kind of join in when you're ready and hope you can keep up
She's not a small talker or a beat around the bushes
You discuss whatever it is you came to discuss
Looking it squarely in the face
She has no time for bulshit
And not because she's about anything but because she actually has no time
She's one of the busiest and most curious people I've ever met
You know when you first talk to me about this case the first thing I thought is okay do we have a jailhouse informant
Do we have a person
Got way too sweet of a deal
What when I read through your police notes your summary of your police notes
I just kept going back to motive
Hunting that's a big black hole for me I still don't understand
Why
You want this girl's dad
Because she broke up with you people break up with people all the time prayer and I can't and I'm a little concerned
What about racial profiling here you know in other words
Right and people are saying you know his
Darkside
And his
You know there was some notation about he was very
Trolling
And I thought I wonder if he was really very controlling
So there's that
Then a little bit I had a
The cell phone thing for us and Justin Wolfe is
That they used to the cell phone records
Say
Cabin out the period of time
When
The shooter is driving to the place where the victim is
And shooting him and then coming back
And so they they put those up on a board in the courtroom and take a look at this he calls him right before he
Commits the murder and he calls him right after he commits the murder
You know
But
And then you get everybody's phone records write all these kids that are buying pot smoking pot selling pot
And everybody's calling each other
All the time
So
It's a venue stop and stand back and say
Also what are they trying to say that Justin wolf in these kids he's a upper-middle-class kids
Are so stupid
That they
Get in the car and call and say okay I'm on my way to murder him
Okay I just murdered him I'm coming back now I just weren't you know what I mean like
Who does that
It's so you know now all these Witnesses
Oh no we were just calling each other to buy pot
Those calls
Bitter infused with meaning by the prosecution
Siri have no meaning in space
Show me itsfunneh like you get kisses like Anna's case
I feel like
From what I can tell
You know there's nuts for gross negligence or or malfeasance or something on the part of the detectives or the
State Attorney's Office like everyone seems to be doing their job
Responsibly
Just doesn't seem like there's an obvious like
Never looked at the new boyfriend they never questioned the guy who found the button
A nun on himself is not sad
Buying anything super useful to say like
Here's why I can prove I didn't do this like he has set out front like I can't
Give you
Like some
Clenching piece of information or evidence that's going to solve this like I wish I could
Cobra Kai just don't have it like I don't know
I don't know how to
Prove this
You know that's a that's why I love hearing that
Because
Somewhere along the line I started realizing that when you have an innocent client
They are the least helpful people in the whole world
They don't know they don't
They have no idea
You like as soon as I realized I have an innocent client and that's a situation that I think like
Okay well I'll talk to you again when I solved
Because I'm not going to need you here
Cuz what's happening with unknown is where
Find something out that looks kind of bad for him
And I'll come to him with it and be like
Why it does seem like you maybe made this phone call
In the middle of the afternoon at a time when you're saying you were a track
But the phone number is to someone who only you know and Jay didn't know
And so like there's this phone call with this girl Nisha and it it's like this glaring thing to me in the middle of the phone records
I'm like that's the one that kind of looks bad for you
Explain that to me how do you explain that
And then his his answer is
Had a melee or not so satisfying where he's like I don't I can't explain it like maybe it was a butt dial and like
The machine picked up and I'm like
But she's had to find that there's no machine on it
And he's like I don't know I don't know what to tell you but like I didn't I didn't have the felt like I was a track
And I'm just like I want to be like
You should have an anime cake
What's not surprising
Not at all
So there was a case that I had the federal capital murder case right where my client Daryl rice right
Is charged with killing two women hikers in the
Shenandoah National Park in blah blah blah
They filed a motion saying
The motive in this case
It was hatred it was
He hated lesbians that's why he murdered these two women
So Daryl rice was easy for me not in the beginning because
His answers
Self-serving and help
The way you think
He's had time to think about
Why
Why doesn't have a better answer than that
And then
I started to realize
Because
He hasn't been thinking about this
Because you didn't murder anybody
And so
It's like I remember one day I had in there map
Straight to show him
Like where the crime scene was versus where the lodge was first
2 square mile marker 42 points
And so I put I put this all out on the table and get my reading glasses
And then I said so when you would Camp there can you show me where you were and then he was like
Okay well I didn't
I didn't Camp there I buy wild ride bikes
There in a horse sound like
Okay well whatever you know
It's whatever you're in the park
In relation to the crime scene
And then he
Look at me it was so simple it and but he said
I don't I don't know where the crime scene was
So can you
Show me that
And I remember thinking
Course
I'm like everybody else
I think he knows
Christine is right
How many likes do you only take on cases where it's super clear to everyone involved like on your side of the bed
Your side of the bar
That that
This person isn't innocent of wrongfully convicted
Or do you take cases where like you really don't know and you start down a road in like
Three quarter staircase it turns out he probably did it so let's not take on that one or do you are you only working with cases where you're pretty sure from the
The get-go
Because we're the people that decide whether
It's going to be it's going to go or not
Ecos every different way
Right sometimes we start down the road and
Very quickly
We talked to four Witnesses all of whom say
Nose apps
Vim
They have no reason to lie you know
We did not we quickly realized okay we're being happy
We are in the weeds
About a lot of things
For a long time until we figured it out to like today
We had team meetings for R4
Clinic KC
And those are for cases
You know two of them
Are sure already two of them were just
Trying to figure it out but you're not going to a jury
You know that's relatively unusual and I'm assuming you went to a jury because he was saying I didn't do that
Right
Enzo sometimes people say I did some of the
But I didn't do all of this
So I'm going to trial but he wasn't saying that
Yeah he's always
Right
Which
I don't know people let you know a lot of her so they're all guilty they're all.
Generally feel like especially for most of my
Career I was dealing with people and I wasn't
A directorate in Innocence Project
And I had a very clear sense of which of my clients did what
And that's because they told me it's like
So I put some stock in people saying I didn't do it and staying
With that
Yeah now
Some people would say I'm naive but I also think like
I've been doing this work for a really long time I don't think naive is a good word for me
You know what I mean I mean
I feel like I'm
Because I feel like I'm having this experience where
I'll read something or I'll do an interview and I'm like
Yeah there's no way
It just doesn't add up it doesn't add up and then I'll send in the very next day I'm like
My God
Oh my God
Look at the phone call Tanisha
Yes or like
You know this friend said that he you know behave this way during a relationship at this other girl I just talked to you last night
It was like he was really overbearing and possessive
My God maybe you didn't know
Do you have that like this is that
Still happen to you or do you just
I know I know actually teach that
I tell people all the time
You are you are juggling and everything's in the air and your Frozen
And
You have to stay there until your
Just you've eliminated
Quest
Because if you if you come down or catch one and get attached to it
You're going to make the same mistakes that law enforcement do
And I think to when you keep going like
What happens to me is that
I reach a Tipping Point
I have answered
To my satisfaction
And I have answers for everything
And
Am I answers are better
Then 1/4
Dancers
So when I read what you've given me I just think
You guys just don't have it
You just didn't
Nobody's really doing anything bad ever eaten people are trying to run down their leaves and talk to people
But they don't have enough to go forward but they do anyhow
Right
So people so you've got bad feelings and you've got Jay changing a story you know like
I look at this is this is just the case that wasn't ready to be brought
You don't have enough to put Adnan away
Not to not to me
You don't
Put him away means
Well and yeah and they would say yes and I would say no and I and the reason I say that is because I look at this and think
Law enforcement and prosecutors and defense attorneys
We all react like if a jury will convict then that's fine
And I think
Those of us who know a good case from a bad case
Should know that even if we can get a jury to convict it doesn't mean we necessarily should ask them to do that
Is the
So are you not does it not happen to any more where you're just like one day you things like
For the first
However many months
Ranking of the Air Force
Oh no it's not him
But
In order to revisit it in any kind of
Careful way you have to revisit everything
Brighten the good in the bad and whatever
And look at it with
And eyebrow up
And sometimes it's going to stay exactly the way it is and it's unsatisfying
I'm going to get through all this and just be like
Yeah an end you might and I can't pretend that that
I just thought of something that I think we should do unless you don't want to do it and you can just think about this
So just today
One of my teams and it's one of my better teams because it's a kid who
Law student who has summered at the FBI
And it's going to work for the US attorney so he doesn't have my treehugger
You know
Everyone's innocent
Instagram
But he's a really hard worker and he has a team
And we just closed their case
And he came to me tonight and said are you going to find me another good case and I said yeah let me flip through tonight and see what we got
I'm sitting here thinking
Wait
You should assign them
Oh my God
Right
That's really
YG I literally just sitting here thinking
You know it's a lot of legwork
If we had a team of five students we could get those things done
You know
With people that are being supervised
So think about that
I'm totally hooked
I did think about it
I said yes
Go ahead
My job unlike theirs is not to figure out if or how I can exonerate at 9
But sure if I wanted to take a look at the case on their own of course I welcome that
Many more sets of eyes some fresh some jaded
Could only be helpful it seemed to me
Went down to Charlottesville to see how they were getting along
Here is the sound of a law clinic getting ready to consider a new case
Got the scanner scanning it's little Skinner hard out
Man by anyone Deirdre can grab her students mostly
Couple of orchids come by the office she gets one of her daughters canning
You said the scanner smells good
And I don't have to know what laundry smells like
That's Deirdre
So now what we do usually in when we are cases
Is we collect
What Mom has with inmate has what is in the court file
What
Paper everywhere that's what we do is collect all the paper
And then do exactly what they're doing
And then
Put the team in we say take a weekend and read it all
Post-conviction work often involves going back and looking at physical evidence in a case
Some Innocence Project only work with cases that have DNA evidence for instance
Children's Group isn't one of those but still she'll definitely take it if she can get it
1 point deer Teresa print out of an email regarding evidence in anons case
So this is an email in 2008 from the Baltimore Police
Saying
That
He believes items from this case have been destroyed
But he doesn't have a document saying that that
Is true so we can't be 100% sure
And he's the evidence control unit
Person
So
Yeah that's not good
I think there's two things to think about there's a
That usually
In every state about evidence retention
And you can't destroy evidence until the case is over and done with
Doesn't mean they
Always honored
The other thing I'm thinking about is
I can tell you the number of faces where somebody says
I think it's gone
And then you go
And you be annoying
And you poke around and say
Can I come back there and look
And they say
Okay will look and then
Like
So
Not Fade Away
You see how I refused
Except
Anyting
It's true I can't think of anyone more optimistic than Deirdre
Which I don't know I would have guessed that after doing this kind of work
For decades
Annoying how rare it is to reverse a conviction you naturally settle in as a pessimist
The opposite is true that because your chances are so low
You have to look on the bright side in order to do this work at all
Otherwise you can function
Students digest this massive amount of paper
The next step is decide what they've got on their hands
First thing they do says Deirdre
It's a given on back the presumption of innocence
It's kind of profound saying when you think about it
It's supposed to happen the first time around a trial
Seems like no one in the profession really believes that it does
Because you can't help it as a juror you figure the guy sitting behind the defense table must have done something wrong
So dear just team starts with the premise
But he didn't do it
And then they see where that rotates them
If they think maybe it down really is innocent
Figure out if there's any way they can prove that in court
Definitely
Because the evidence is gone the people won't change their minds
There's no legal remedy
It's just those things are just after time those things are usually
Harder to get to
As a legal question
Deirdre says they should only have to prove
Anon isn't there guy
He's not the Killer
But as a practical matter she said their chances are much better if they can go a step further
State of the State
Not only is this not your guy
We can tell you who is your guy
The truth is when you can give the answer of who it is
It makes it a whole lot easier on everybody else
To walk away and do the things no one ever wants
To do
And usually there's some logical
Explanation right
There is a guy there is somebody who's motivated to somebody who hated hey like
Usually there's something
You don't have to but I always help people
You have to
Of course after looking everything over and her team might well decide that maybe it is guilty
In which case they would quietly pack up the files
I just keep their mouth shut
But what I'm saying is like I could happen
You could look at it and be like
To me I mean not to the world
Right I would say it
I would say.
But I wouldn't say it to
4 weeks later I check back in with your for students
Read through all the files if you guys think I'm not guilty
No I wouldn't I wouldn't have been able to find
Guilty with this
This is one of the things that was
Very hot when I first started reading this case was how precisely he was convicted under this
Material
But now
Do not see him as being guilty of this
I was just at this point knowing what I know I would say
I guess I have to put them in the person of interest category because he was an old boyfriend
Even that I would think like that but I see no evidence that he was mad mountains of Reasonable Doubt
Surprise me
At least one or two of them would end up on the fence
They all sounded so forthright
They said the things that trouble with the same things that trouble me
Shifting statements to police and how the cell tower information didn't fully match Jays narrative
But the other stuff AC is done with stuff I hadn't paid much attention to it all
The forensic report
Relative lack of forensic reports
This is Katie
Because in our files we have a lot of things evidence they collected that said off
We don't have reports for everything and we are curious about the results that we
Don't have and whether or not
Does exhaustion
That's why they're not in the files that we have
The liquor bottle for 1
That bottle of Coronet vsq Brandy that was on right near his body
It says they recovered nucleated epithelial cells from the mouth of the bottle and from the cap
But that's all it just says quote retained for future possible analysis unquote
But the future never came
They never tested those cells for DNA
Like a report on the fibers
Two fibers one reddish that was found near his head was fluorescent blue it's a little hard to tell
That was found underneath her in the soil didn't think they were tested against enough samples
They weren't test against the rope that was also found right near the body
I would think that you would
Be able to compare the fibers to the Roper compare the fibrous to whatever you can get your hands on and
And I didn't actually see that ever get tested the fibers were
Some things but nothing nothing came back of significance and then the fibers just fact of the fibers just kind of went away
As for the Rope which from a photo looks like a laundry line
It wasn't tested at all for anything
Deirdre says that kind of thing happens a lot
Investigators will say
Not relevant
It's not connected to what happened so there's no point in testing
So another case that I had
Anything that didn't match the the purpose or the suspect that they had
They just ignored it right
And they would say well that's that's outside the crime scene that's really not inside the crime scene so those beer cans over there where
Too far away we're going to call that outside the clients
And when I talk to DNA experts about that
They were saying
Yeah I mean if you swab that and you get some
Some skin cells are
Saliva
And it's just randomly get no hit on anybody will then it's
Then it's neither here nor there
But they were saying
But if you if you put it in and you get a hit on a serial killer
Sprite or one of two other people who killed Asian women within a year in Baltimore
Well now we've got
Enough to charge and convict somebody
So
What you call relevant and irrelevant you can only do once you have a test result
Finally and Katie and Mario were all confused by the swabs that were taken from his body
The medical examiner had done what's known as a perk
Cat stands for physical evidence
Recovery kit
The standard procedure in a rape case
But it's also down in some murder case
There was no evidence he was sexually assaulted
But they did the swabs just the same
The medical examiner's report says they came back quote- for spermatozoa
But that's about it
Which seems very thin to Deirdre that these swabs weren't examined for thoroughly
But they were never tested for DNA which is just weird
That's just
That seems very strange to me in a case like that seems very strange and you
You almost always submit that for DNA test
And that's what we're not seeing is a lab report that says
You know if it came back and that's the other
Loosey-goosey about whether it's
Not Jay not Adnan you know
That's strange
Right
So okay
So so
Is that something that you guys
Wood
Want to get to
Tested
Absolutely
Yes it didn't correct me if I'm wrong but this certainly seems to be
Quite a bit to get started
Do you have any
Metric of how
Hopeful
/ hopeless
This one looks
Point in terms of
Finding out something useful and usable
Mario shaking his head
That's because he's a pro-government
Right-wing Republican operative
I checked with Mario he said it was fine
You know
It's always an outside shot
Always
But there's enough here is what I guess what I'm saying is there's enough here that you
I think it's worth asking these questions
You don't even like you guys independently feel like
Know something when
Or is this just like
Well we're sort of humor and show the reporter
No I would I would I would look at this as this I would have a team on this case saying
Keep going
I say
They all seem so hopeful
So sure that with enough digging they're going to shake something loose
Skeptical
I felt like I did in that same mindset for so many months and I haven't found anything that absolutely tip the scale
Favor
Noticed
There are you sound really down on Adnan today
I don't know yeah you're sometimes I'm totally with them
And then other times I'm like
Why
I can't remember anything why does nothing
I don't know that
Of all days
You knew it was important that you got a call from a cop that day
Asking where your ex girlfriend was
Surely
You must have gone over it
Before 6 weeks
Had passed
Surely
I don't have that reacts
But I see what you
And then I just am aware of like
What if he is this amazing sociopath and not just like I'm being played
When I don't get that
Sense
Really Charming he's
Really smart
He's really
Funny
And you're like yeah
Here's where I go with that like
In my 20
How I'm sick
6 years of doing this
Frey for associate
Cuz I never get those
I get the innocent ones as I get these dumb
So me and my friend smoke crack for 3 days and we drink 5 bottles of
Whatever and then we got a plan
That's who I get all the time
So I think like
The odds of you getting the Charming sociopath you're just not that lucky
Very few times if I had a client and the ones
Really did it end
Date they have serious metal
Issues and there are not
Sociopathy there
Schizophrenia or florid psychosis because of a
Whatever
I just think
The odds of
Him being that and no one having detected any signs of it until
The Kills
His girlfriend
So he's moved on
From
Deirdre and her gang they're going to stick with stuff they can bring to a quart
Friends mostly
Another explanation is
Entirely
They did not had nothing to do with this at all
Maybe it was a serial killer
Maybe there's a clue from another Baltimore Cold Case
Explorers headed for a bold new world
Imma Stay right here at home with my little garden Spade
I keep scraping at the thing that confuses me most
Jay
Next time
Ontario
Operations manager Aira glasses are auditory
Visor
Fact-checking by Karen fragala Smith
Administrative help families bergersen RC music is composed by Nick thorburn
Scoring music by neck and my Mark Phillips who also mixer show
Our website where you can listen to all our episodes and find photos letters and other documents from the case
And sign up for a weekly emails
Serialpodcast.org
Serials production of This American Life and WBEZ Chicago