Support for serial comes from ATT
The number one smart home security provider
With a team of 18000 employees
Dedicated to safeguarding your home
With connection to First Responders
Offering Custom Design Systems including doorbells
Indoor and outdoor cameras and smart locks and lights
All control from the ADT app or the sound of your voice
And all back
Buy 24/7 protect
Visit att.com podcast
To learn more
Immediately saw that there is no way I'm getting out of that cage
Previously
I'm cereal this is a metal cage or wood cage or what
Made for what purpose
For keeping me
And I
New Wok
Into the tribal areas over the mountains
The worst place you can be taken in the Afghanistan
Exon region
Very scary how kind of bad animals andronis 24 hour light
Making buzz buzz buzz
Unforgettable impunity is jumping into my head
I'm going to take a video of you
You need to think about what you're going to say
From This American Life and WBEZ Chicago its serial one story told me
In very early July of 2009 just a few days after but went missing
A woman named Kim Harrison winter local police department in Portland Oregon
And I had to go to the microphone
Because I don't have it
A person out in front
It's pretty big Police Department I think it's part of it
Excuse me can I
Talk to somebody I need to report a missing person
Hamsa
Yeah it me at the time I know this is they're going to think I'm insane
I feel what you're saying is I'm reporting a missing person out of
Mest Afghanistan
Well I didn't really want to say that right off the bat because I knew I wouldn't get
The person missing was Bo
Of course
Person missing from a place roughly seven thousand miles away
Who is this person and I said well as sub soldier in the
Can't. He's a military personnel why would you do that full it's complicated
So complicated
Here's what happened
Kim is a close friend of bows
They're like family to each other
He's friends with her kids
Full list of Kim in Army forms as a person to notify if something happened to him
June 30th 2009 Army officials came to Kim's house to tell her he was missing
Kim is not a person to sit by
That is not her nature
That first day she thinks
How can I fix this
What can I do who can I call
And then she thinks
Interpol
The friend who happens to be high up at Interpol
The international police force
She calls him and he says maybe our pole can help
Turn on Military non-political
They have Cooperative agreements
The police and more than 180 countries including Pakistan
They've been helping investigate the Mumbai terror attack
But it happened about seven months earlier which meant they've been looking into Taliban activity in India and Pakistan
Interpol can actually move around in Pakistan in ways the US military cannot
So
Interpol
Worth a shot
To get an investigation underway for bow Interpol would need to issue something called a yellow notice
Interpol's version of a missing-person report that gets distributed to police departments all over the world
To get that going out you need to establish the situation as Official Police business
Somewhere
Anywhere apparently which is why Kim ends up at the Portland PD
She needs them.
To file a missing-person report
Interpol intern can generate the yellow notice about bow
And they do they make a report
Kim sends Interpol photographs of Bones and stuff
Is fingerprints on it
DNA samples
The best thing she had for that was a Halloween mask you warned they all went as Alice in Wonderland characters
What was the Cheshire Cat
So she sent the Cheshire Cat mask
The Interpol
Is all ready to go the last thing they need before Interpol can issue the yellow notice
Is permission
From
The Department of Defense
How to say can we do this really have to get permission because he was a military personnel
And they denied permission instantly
Kim has notes she took from that time and in them it says the dod denied the yellow notice 12 hours after it was requested
A certain Colonel calls her and tells her the dod was working in concert with the FBI and the CIA
And that Interpol involvement could complicate jeopardize And Delay the investigation in the search
And PS
It was quote in her best interest to not get involved
Point is
Who's annoying
They were just like incredulous that I was
Just causing so much problem for them
I mean that's why they saw it
I might display
Squeaking nagging
Hino not behaving female
She keeps going
Women
Later that same day but Sunday Kim calls the colonel bag
Somehow gets his home number
And he reiterates
He does not foresee the yellow notice going forward
Congressman Chico
Call the senator maybe they can pressure the military to change the decision
No dice
That was that
The question Kim is left with to this day
Is what is the dod headset to Interpol yes
Go ahead
Creative work
Possibly gotten home sooner
When I heard the story the question I was left with was
What the heck
Chili Kim huffing it to the Portland PD is not the way this is supposed to work
So how is this
Bus to work
That's a bunch of people who worked on behalf of the military to get Bo home
Some on the record someone background
And they all talked about how much of a doozy this one was
Otherwise just know handbook
You had a US prisoner of war
There's being held in the friendly nation of Pakistan
By the designated terrorist group of the haqqani
On behalf of the lawful combatants
Like the Taliban
It's not like there was a Cadre of people inside the United States government who had experience on how to untie this
Killer not nobody had done this before
How do you how do you manipulate an entire country
Together
An enlisted Soldier home
How do you do that
You don't
Of course it wasn't a military operation that finally got Bo home
It was diplomacy
We negotiated with the Taliban and traded him for five minute of gitmo
And that in itself is a fascinating story and we'll get into all that
But for this episode
I'm going to lay out the twisty-turny and often emotional pass that came before the president sign off on that trade
Because before the most powerful person in the United States to call the buzz fade
Use my hands of well-meaning people much much lower down the chain
Or not in that chain at all
Because that's where the search for Bo lived
4 years
The same day but walks away the dust one goes into effect
For about a month and a half
There's this intense no-holds-barred military and intelligence effort inside
All this equipment hundreds of people redirected to search for bow
The nerve center for all that activity was back in the States
In Tampa Florida
That's where us Central Command is headquartered
Going to centcom
Centcom has a group of people whose whole job is to find missing or captured people
Guarantee are not public relations but Personnel recovery
I talked to two people who worked in the pr office at that time
Intel analyst
And they might search for anyone who's been reported missing from a conflict Zone
Not just US military personnel and not just America
Could be a contractor someone working for an NGO
Hiker foreign Nationals
Recorders
Imagine their office as a super high-tech workspace
Like the way NASA looks in the movies
It's not that sexy
It's definitely not sexy
That's Andrea not her real name
And she'll
Also not heard
They told me the office is
Cubicles
Computers
Telephones
International did not want to talk
Specifically about Bose case
Since its ongoing in military
What they told me applies to his
And two lots of other cases they work
Also these women didn't want to use their real names
Because anything bro related is so sensitive so hot
They worried they might suffer repercussions
Personally if the public knew they tried to bring boho
Anyway their job didn't stop when the dust one was called off
They kept going
Until it was over
5 years later
Again Andrew Michelle can't talk about the poor
Particulars of bows
But they were pretty candid about what made their job especially tricky
I said there were a bunch of fact
First of all at that time Andrea and then Michelle we're kind of it for Afghanistan
In terms of personnel recovery
DOD had a good system for recovering downed pilots in Afghan
But other than that there was no solid system in place to track people who went missing
Cassandra
They should have had two people
Or more sitting there in Afghanistan
Waiting to just support
Personnel recovery events
But instead everyone in the theater where dual had it or triple how did you know they had different jobs
And so when an event occurred they'd
You know they could help but they certainly weren't
Experts
And when that differed from say operations in Iraq and relax
What was the how do you compare laxatives what was in place
In Afghanistan versus what was in place in Iraq and 4 / Saturday
Iraq had a personal recovery division setup and they had upwards of
15 people sitting in the same room with the only job full-time job of
Is my only wish that we could have had something like that and I've got a
We ask for many many times
That's Michelle
I can't even begin to
Describe the
Leading of establishing a cell like that over there that would have helped us immensely
Many more people had gone missing from Iraq than from Afghanistan
So it made sense Rock was much better equipped for these events
But still with that man is that a certain point mashona and realized
We can't do this job from Tampa
I started rotating in and out of Afghanistan usually for months at a time
So they can manage their cases from the ground
When someone goes missing
PR team turns on every intelligence asset they can those assets
People
Human Torch
Are human intelligence or sigint signals intelligence
Communication to pick up from cell phones are like
Electronic messages or geoint geospatial-intelligence
Images of a landscape
And their job ideally is to layer all this Intel
To get the clearest picture they possibly can of where the person is
And then if you can get that far
Hand that information off
To the people who can actually do something about it
Either militarily can we send in Special Forces for instance
Can we engineer an escape of some kind or drone strike to set the hostage free
Or diplomatically can we get our ambassador and whatever country to try to negotiate for a hostage
Orb
A civilian
Remember when Bill Clinton went to North Korea in 2009 got those reporters at a prison there
Bose case
All of that work all of those potential Avenues
We're stymied by the defining fact
Geographical situation
News in Pakistan
In Afghanistan
.
Which Andrea Michelle Harper
DOD owns the battlespace
Meaning they have control they have authority to direct operations and use whatever assets they need
That's why the dust one for both could be as far-reaching and aggressive as
Once you no longer own the battle
You have to start relying much more on other US government agencies that might be operating a package
Pretty much any three-letter agency that has a Personnel recovery
NGA DIA
CIA FBI NSA
It's a CIA that has Authority for us operations in package
So you really need the CIA
Now it becomes a more
We're doing a lot more ask
For help
The priorities
Are all the other things that are happening inside of that country
Less important than this thing that we need right now
Or are you jumped
Trump for instance by current event
That often have
Current events
Politics on the ground and whatever country
Get in the way of your PR mission
During Bose case
We had some very rough patches in a relationship
Pakistan
One former counterterrorism analyst told us quotes
You couldn't possibly have a busier backdrop and in Pakistan
That you're started with the Raymond Davis debacle number that one was bizarre
Davis was a CIA contractor who open fire on two guys riding a motorbike in the middle of a crowded intersection in the hor
Several people were dead by the end of it caused a huge uproar in Pakistan he was thrown in jail
Then you have the US LED NATO air strikes on the afghanistan-pakistan border that killed 28 Pakistani soldiers
Economy is based in Pakistan attacked our Embassy in Kabul and NATO headquarters 16 people
And that same here the us raid in about a bad that killed Osama Bin Laden
Yeah you really can't go to the table and start talking about
Maybe humanitarian releases
On the tail end of
You know you don't lateral operation into a Sovereign Nation
Not the best time to ask for help
Those friends and family were also agitating on their own
And it's certain points their unofficial efforts became intertwined with official search business in Curious ways
In ways that actually approach success
Camphor campylobacter
Weekend
Kim lived in Idaho when I was a teenager
He spent years hanging around with her family and they were sort of home base for Beaufort long stretches
It stay with them work at
The tea Shoppe they ran
Kim is the audit out who actually loves teenagers and she loves Bo
She understood worried about him
She do anything
For I'm just as you would for own kids
Pretty early on in the search for bochum was shut out by the military
Scheming
Calling people she studied Maps
How can I get into Afghanistan
Audriana Paxton I get my bag.
Password like I really felt like I'll go
Like I'm going to go over there and talk to you PacSun please I'm going to
Do you work with peace organizations I'm going to go over there and try and go on the television
Stupid
Naive
I don't know what I'm thinking
This point there's got to be something
How hard you get with the like I'm going to go to pek
Cancel my passport
For my own safety I'm canceling your path
It wasn't a Sinister move by the government or anything like that just
Someone concerned about her safety
Who's parents were also active
Throughout trying to figure out what they could do
They decided not to speak to me on tape for this story
And an aside here I read nothing into that decision apart from their best intentions for their own family and for others
Hostages still in caps
Maven completely gracious to me throughout this process
And I'm grateful to them for
Anniversary
Perhaps things like what I'm about to tell you about Kim or happening to both parents
I just don't know for sure
Anyway Kim says in November of 2009 she did something
Which I can't talk about
Which sort of paid off
In one way and that was a got my name and telephone number to someone very obscure in Afghanistan
And he
Turned out to be someone that worked with the Taliban
About 6 weeks later Kim is at home in Portland and her cell phone rings weird number she doesn't answer
But didn't understand
A single syllable of it
And voicemail on my iPhone
Spell he didn't leave a message
I left a message in the third call I picked up
I thought I was on my phone
Weird sir
Wrong number you know Direct Mail you know
I did pick up
M&T speaking in past due is very obscene
I was not able to understand except for he said
So
That's where I went
You know this is what is going on
And my room was Adam like this
Person you know
Making faces at him as a missing to pass my
What do I do so
I told him and I said email email you know and he's going to email email
Okay
So he hangs up
I hang up I go online I try to find ways of pronouncing
Like phonetically
Letters
Write for my email like how I say
Kim blah blah blah
Where he'll get that butt
He called back like 10 minutes later
And
I'm trying to give him my email address with an ax
He's over at like 3 or 4 times
And if it worked
I had no
Hope
Hang up
30 seconds later playing I can email
It's not a single letter of
Of
Are letter forms except for booked all
The rest is in
So she cuts and pastes the message into one of those online translator sites to decipher
And what did it say complete gibberish the translation was like horrible
Happy happy celebrate Victory now
Hello haha Bridge
Tomorrow Bergdahl
That's not what it actually said just a friend stands
Understood the gist
This guy had information about bow
And he wanted something in return
So I decide I will I cannot help you I will find someone right now I will make phone calls I will find some
Very simple English
Soon
Can calls a friend
What should I do
A friend tells her
Uni the FBI
She contacts the FBI and eventually the FBI translates the message
He was proposing a deal
And the deal was
Tube chair
When heat when he had access to where
The locations were for where by would go
And where he was at any given time yet access
So he said I can give you information we're both going to be so that you guys can go get them in exchange
And I want out of the country I want how many family and how many eighths family members
It sounds too good to be true right
But incredibly this guy checked out
Kim can't say how the guy was connected to both situation
Or what proof he provided
But apparently he checked out to the extent that the FBI began exchanging emails with
They would do threaten copy
Vaguely tell me what it meant
I had stress them copy and paste it in my email and send it from my email address I'm like my computer
And not
Different location because of their guarantee he's watching my at the end and he would know with somebody else
So you are basically
The FBI at this point is communicating with
The sky through you very clear that
I have to
Get the emails if I'm not getting emails and he's going to stop
So
Horse meat you know what lol I was willing to do whatever I'm sure I'm here on this is just
At least
He knew he was also communicating with the government
When she got that first call Bo had been a prisoner with the Taliban for about 6 months
He's going through the worst winter of his whole five years
He was the coldest
The sickest hungry
Of course Kim didn't know any of that
But she was hopeful
Maybe this could spare him
The best scenario
They'll give him location of flying and Superman up and take him home you know
And
That would be great
Announcer what happened
Kim doesn't entirely know
Because your communication with the FBI was a one-way proposition
Thermometer to her was
Need to know
For good reason
All Kim does know is that for two years running
She signed releases so that the NSA could monitor
Phone or computer TV
Good follower if they wanted or hang out in front of her house
And then after that two years was up
Nothing
So just kind of fizzled away
After a while
From my perspective
I found out what happened
The FBI cultivated this source for a while
And then passed him along to the Department of Defense
And it turned out this guy
Call Kim on her cell phone one day
Because of some secret thing she did
On her own
To get her number to the Taliban
This turned out to be one of the best leads they ever had in Bo's case
One person tasked with finding bow told me quote
I thought for sure that was the answer on quote
But they could never quite make it happen
The guy wanted to bring his relatives over
And if you bring nine people to the US under some version of Witness Protection
What government agency is going to have to take care of them
For their whole lives
And my source told me none of the agencies raise their hand
Even so Visa papers started to be drawn up just in case
And then the guy withdrew
You didn't respond when asked for details about his family member
The paperwork
Over the years when they go back to the drawing board it.
Trying to think up solutions for finding Bo
Someone would always write this guy on the list
What about him
He was willing once
You still there still active
Trying again
But no one Pursuit at
When Intel expert
If you have all the tools you need
You can find someone in less than 30 days
So you can rescue them in 30 days but you can at least find them
Abo's case. He did not have all the toys
Was never able to say with 100% certainty where Bo was
The US didn't have reliable human intelligence sources on the ground in waziristan
Connie's have that area lockdown so tightly
And you're so good at propagating misinformation
That they either couldn't get in till or couldn't trust what until they did get
How to figure out Bose exact location
Which neighborhood
Which compound
They need it for instance
Drones
And the drones have to be what's called unblinking
You can't look away
He doesn't have
Drones operating in Pakistan so you have to ask other agencies to take a look for you
Such as the CIA
And occasionally they would
They might give them a few hours here there
It wasn't nearly enough
Because unless Sabo happens to get escorted to the Train on that day at that time you're not going to see him
You need to watch and listen
Solidly for say a week
The catch was going in and out what they're saying maybe you follow one of those people
In other words of the drugs give you a much better chance of
Pinpointing his location
And with the location you can at least plan a Rescue Bots
One former DOD employee told me quote
It was literally two years
Of asking for drones and quote
CIA declined to talk to us for the story they referred us to the dod
What was going on
CIA or the NSA or other agencies
They have their own boss
Their own priorities
These parties aren't General and a cereal there specific
They're written down they must be approved by the president
For the CIA their priorities were things like
Targeting top Al-Qaeda and haqqani members
Well Hast recovery might have been on the list on their radar
It certainly wasn't at the top
Umberto's specifically wasn't on anybody's
It's understandable that the CIA can't just turn over their resources and manpower to a PR mission that isn't there
In some instances these other agencies were doing the best I could under the circumstances
This tension is shot through all of these hostage cases
Are we doing enough
The answer to that depends in part on where you're sitting
If your Andrea Michelle this is all you think about all day
Getting your hostages
What else can we do
They said they had to fight
Complacency
Malaise
Because their priority wasn't everyone's
Even if on paper it was supposed
Michelle said they'd have to get Wiley sometimes
Just to get the meeting today
Specific
General
In his exact and I've been talking back and forth
I don't know if I can get
Really good friends with she worked with
We have sorry lost out there and she needs time with his General and can make that happen
Cuz she calls me she's like I think I can get that done for you but he really likes Johnnie Walker Black Label
If you can
Maybe but not on his desk maybe throw in some beef jerky
I think we can make that happen
Things like that you're like unbelievable
Just to get in front of someone to talk about significant
Personnel recovery event
I'm sure I'm sure
They do the most basic things just to remind people that yes
There are American hostages
Is in Syria
Ernest and Pakistan
They put up posters
Make a rubber bracelet
Chris Michelle
Adrian I'd gone to a
Is Veterans Day or poww Mi a day but we
She'd made
Shirts
Or us
To this event
We're walking in and
A colonel stop doesn't
What the hell is that on your shirt
This is Bernthal and he's been missing for about that
Are you kidding education
Bulletin I can't believe that story
It's it's insane and it's
You're the one that breaks my heart is Coleman
She gave birth in captivity why are we not talking about
That's Andrea
Caitlan Coleman and her husband Joshua Boyle
Disappeared in Afghanistan in 2012
Kaitlyn was pregnant at the
You just made spit makes my heart hurt
And
You asked
The America the average American on the street who she is no no no
I just want to talk for a second
About this very human thing that overlays again not just bows case but all these hostage
Pittcon Rutherford
He's a young guy in Canadian
He was freed from the Taliban last week
After more than 5 years
You've been traveling in Afghanistan when he went missing
And the day he was released the Canadian press covered it not the details of how and why just the fact of his
Return
Any online comments immediately or things like this
Who goes on vacation to Afghanistan
Boneheads or this headline should read idiot rescued who cares about the
I'm tempted to be all sanctimonious and say that's awful how can people be so awful
Truth is I thought things like this
I mean it's great there home but you know also
Throne damn fault I admit it
And I'll wager we've all thought things
It's not unconflicted which makes us no different than a lot of the people charged with finding
Caitlan Coleman arc on Rutherford or Bowe Bergdahl
The only difference is
Those people are not supposed to think like that circumstances of capture are not supposed to come into play
Adrienne Michelle told me repeatedly they really do not care about circumstances of capture first you get the person
Max and then come consequences judgement punishment
Not the other way around
Because there isn't a hostage situation out there
It doesn't involve some aspect of wrong place wrong time
Some element of human error
The surprise of their job was
Their colleagues didn't always feel the same way
I think the biggest shock for me was
The salesmanship
I didn't realize that I was going to have to
Convince them
That supporting
My mission was something that they should do
I just I didn't think that that would be an issue
Hand wipes
When you're standing before your peers
In addressing
The meeting and 1st
And foremost you have to get over the misconceptions
Circumstances of capture
And this Rings true to a lot of
If you know you hear this
The comet
He's just a journalist you should have been there anyways why should we help them
Ro they were just hiking
Why would they be hiking there they can hike
In Colorado
Even that the kid that walked off base
Yeah I can't even begin to
Tell you the amount of times that we heard
Why should I care
For she did this or this is
Bose case of course
So why should I care attitude was
Doubled
Maybe even cubed
Are the information that he walked off on his own
For the hardship you put other soldiers through
Are the rumors of treachery
Lieutenant Colonel Jason a Marino retired
Also worked on post
You know if you ask
People about Bergdahl
If they were
Completely uninformed it was so that's the traitor
If there's someone
Informed it would be
Oh that guy yeah I heard it was a pressure
And if they're a little better informed it would be well people say this but I hear he was a traitor I mean
The refrain was was almost always that the guy is a traitor even know
Actually wasn't
Eddie Albert
The trader
So that attitude
Was everywhere up and down the chain of command
Jason said he was once in a meeting with a general and they had to cut it short
Because a general got so worked up about the fact that Bo had walked off
The general was emotional about it Jason said
It's not that people refuse to help or refuse to do their jobs
Everyone I talk to who is involved in both cases
Said so many people tried so hard on this
It's just that you start to wonder
If his attitude is lurking all the way to the
The top
Then what ideas are not getting through
What's not even getting
Opposed
Because someone Lowdown fear saying something unpopular
Several people told me that for quite a while
Bose case languished because no one working on it was influential enough to make big decisions
Who are you who are you
Well I
I am an intelligence analyst
I have been
Is it a person to call Nathan
That is not his real name
You don't want to use his real name because although he's no longer in the military you still working for the military sometimes
And what he did in Bose case
Was so out of school so not done
Are you worried about the consequences for his current job
Nathan did not work directly on Bose case not officially
He was very close to it
Watching from the sidelines
Watching all these people not be able to accomplish much of anything
4 times along the way where
Various plans
Options
Get him freed
But nobody could
Position or at least
But they could they didn't
Again we're not talking about why Nathan got so personally frustrated
But know that he did
Especially when it came to what officials were saying to both parents
Bob and Jani Bergdahl
This whole telling them every day or
I once a week or once a month
We're doing everything that we can
Right
That's not enough
You need to do more you need to be doing
What it is you can't
The only way to make that happen
Nathan's estimation with push the topic up
Higher than the captains and Majors were working on Bose case
I needed to go as high as it could go
Until it reach someone who could afford to expend political capital on Bo
Meaning ultimately the president himself had to get involved
So Nathan start thinking about
How do you catch the president's attention
He did what an Intel analyst does
He thought what assets haven't we tapped
And it came to him
The berghoff
He thought he could get both parents to push the buttons
Maybe Bo's case could get unstuck
About a year-and-a-half into the case
Nathan sent a message to the bergdahl's on Facebook
He said to them the things that nobody else seemed to want to say
Like what were the bun things you could say that
Refinish it bad
You know that
I'd listen to
It's not as
This is difficult
And here's why
Nobody wanted to they want to tiptoe around
Nathan said contacting them was the
The scariest thing he'd baby ever done
Because he wasn't a high of guy
Wasn't even his job to look for
And well it wasn't illegal he wasn't telling them anything classified
Contacting them
Was so on
Professional in the world
She comes from
It's
You don't want to get personal info
Typically with an analyst
You definitely want to keep your personal feelings out of it
You start injecting bias in there
Starts becoming a problem
In most cases
This was definitely a case though that's
You needed to be personal
You needed to
There needs to be a face on
The bird dolls where the sad
Scared Fierce determined parents of a p o w
Nathan says he made it plain to them
You have more power than you know
People will take meetings
People will return your calls
At least give you 5 minutes
Bob was no slouch he knew how to use his 5 minutes he'd studied the conundrum of his son circumstances
Begin to learn Pashto poured over Islamic law read about pashtun tradition to see if there was some loophole he
Can find some argument he can make for bows release
He understood the history and the politics of the region
And he was already knocking on doors and asking questions
Nathan tried to leverage that
Why don't you go talk to somebody to join Chiefs
And I'm in bed
Weather going to tell you no
So
He he would and he eventually
Eventually
The chairman of the Joint Chiefs is the principal military advisor to the Secretary of Defense and to the Press
President who didn't have 25 media companies writing an open letter urging action by the secretary
State that sometimes happens for foreign correspondents he didn't have Ransom insurance as employees of private companies
His parents weren't switch DC players there are people who lived in rural Idaho
Bose case wasn't going anywhere
They needed someone heavy to think Bo was were thinking about and then they needed that person to give it a push
So that was the plan
Apply pressure in Myriad ways
Make it so that people with influence just happened to start hearing about Bowe Bergdahl from various sources
Get them to perk up taking interest
And then that way inch closer and closer to the present
Nathan began talking to the bird dogs regularly
Maybe monthly maybe weekly depending on what was going on
E-Sword guiding them
You know that person or that group or that commander who says he's doing everything he can
Well
He could be doing this
And were they then going back to that commander and saying
What if what if you tried apps have you done that
Yes
There was a manipulation
Indian going on
That's what makes this bird gif
Were you telling them here's what you need to
Yeah
Your face looks worried when you
You say that responded I am quite worried
New York
It's just messy
Just message
A question might be
Is the United States could pay blood money to get the CIA contractor Raymond Davis
Out of a Pakistani jail
They maybe do something similar for Bo
Some sort of Ransom issue payment that isn't Ransom
I'm making that up but that seems like a good question right
I feel like you're kind of running this
I don't know Scrappy 2nd and secrets
Mission almost that's like a she was like the shadow of the thing that's happening at the office
Yes we're running support
Right-wing supporter totally unofficial
Totally unofficial
Nathan said
It worked
I can't be specific about how it worked
What is it work
Bob's Rolodex filled up
With people at the Pentagon and also the White House and
State Department
And Nathan believes the continued pressure created a sense of urgency about those case
And got it on the desks of the people they were aiming for
It was another part of the strategy
G2
To make noise
Sometimes public
In a way they hoped would keep those safe
When the ubl raid
Osama Bin Laden raid happy
That threw everything up
And I would
What's going to happen
Is there going to be retaliatory
It's on
Sergeant Bergdahl they going to take him out in the street
Luke Walton
You want to do that then here's this
Nobody knew what was going to happen
That's about the time that Bob put out that video
I'm father of capture
US soldier
Robert Burke
These are my thoughts
I can remain silent no longer
May of 2011
Just a few days after the bin Laden raid
Bob released a video on YouTube
Futurist Melissa Holguin and haqqani is
What is main message was straight
The Pakistani government
Address the Pakistani Armed Forces
I personally appeal
General kayani
General Pasha
Our family is counting on your professional integrity
And honor
Secure the safe return of our sun
Pasha was commander of Pakistan's intelligence service
Psoriasis
Kayani was the Pakistan Army chief of staff
We are
Fat urination
Diligently help
Our son
Be freed from his captivity
There's another striking thing about this video
And that is
Bob is asking something of Pakistan
So directly
American officials would not
Are Soldiers there
We know they know he's there
Somewhere in What's called the fata
Federally administered tribal areas
And all this time the US is setting aside billions of dollars in Aid and Military Support to Pakistan
According to a recent Congressional report between 2002 and 2014 we gave him roughly Thirty billion dollars Ulta
Big money
Get we don't seem to be able to say
Hey Pakistan
Give them back
Why is that
Well again lots of experts later
Now I see why
Diplomacy isn't a snap your fingers kind of business
It's a long game
And in the long run would like to stay on decent terms with Pakistan
For some important reasons
Pakistan have nuclear weapons which would really like them to keep a lid on it also like to keep our air and ground supply lines
Open in Pakistan
Get stuff for people in Afghanistan Pakistan Al Qaeda leaders and somehow
Continue many influential people in our government would also like our drones to keep flying and some
Killing people inside Pakistan as well and we've got long-term development goals are to
We'd like to keep helping pakistanis with education and clean water maybe because we're just nice like that but more like
Likely because we want to keep them on our side because of Pakistan goes away of say Iran becomes our enemy
Plus those nuclear weapons
That's the scenario would very much like to avoid
So when we might risk our relationship with Pakistan in order to take out Osama bin Laden
We're not going to jeopardize it not to that degree
41 US servicemen
We are not going to come out publicly and boss Pakistan around
If if we could do that
Or call their leaders a bunch of liars
Ambassador Marc Grossman who is the state Department's special representative for Afghanistan and Pakistan
Meetings with high-level Pakistani government officials
But he didn't expect them to do much
He said expectations are low
But you do it because it's right and you never know what's going to happen
And he said if you say to the bird dolls and to the public
We're doing everything we can
Then you better be doing everything you can
2012-2013
Couple of army generals decided to do something
Separately
One of the generals realized the PRT Matt centcom was willfully understaffed
Wasn't getting anywhere
You signed an elite unit to the task
A Delta Force
Big deal
Which helped
Leaving so the pr team never got the until it hoped for
And then another Jenner
Soon-to-be 4-star also got involved
General Bob Bergdahl also met with
Around January of 2013 were briefing General Campbell
On our different projects
At the end of the Brave
General Campbell
Said you know hey this is all great I want you to know that
My top priority is getting Sergeant Bergdahl home so if there's anything you guys can do to help out at appreciate
Attended the meeting
That's Jason a marine again
He recently retired from the Army after 27 years
Jason is one of the most celebrated soldiers of the Afghanistan war
He was there in 2001
Commanding a special forces team that fought alongside Hamid Karzai in southern Afghanistan
The army of a Man action figure out of them
Jason is as close as you could get to putting GI Joe on the Bergdahl case
His Stellar career nearly unraveled last year in connection with his work on hostage recovery
Which maybe you heard about
Last year he testified before Congress about among other things
The dysfunction in US hostage policy
Back in January 2013 Jason was leading a team of strategist
The Pentagon
That was supposed to find solutions to some of the Army's biggest problems
This group work for General John Campbell who was in charge of operations and plans for the Army
My producer David Chavez interview Json
General Campbell just seemed
Almost
Haunted by the fact that
That we had gotten Bergdahl home it was just the way he said it to us
That this wasn't just idle banter it was really
If there's anything you could do
You know more emotional than than a tactical sword
Yeah absolutely with General Campbell it was a heartfelt
Do you know how do we get him home
That struck me
And after the meeting
I grabbed a couple of my planners
And
Yeah I said to him
It seems like something is really f***** up here
Man. That was just the feeling that I had
Jason and his team decided to do an audit of Bose case
Who was doing what all those years why I hadn't work
What they found is that the effort seems to be moving along to track
Socom was trying to put together plans
So, Special Operations Command which runs elite units
Think Delta Force or Navy Seals
And then Jason said they could see that the state department was on it
Trying to work with Qatar
Trying to get the Taliban to the negotiating
Table
A meeting seed had with FBI and others Jason learned but wasn't the only one being held hostage by the haqqanis
There's Caitlan Coleman and Josh Boyle and their child
And there were others also nearby
Warren Weinstein was being held by Al-Qaeda he was subsequently killed in a drone strike
Knowing about all these others shook Jason pretty hard I was in uniform for 27 years
Yeah for me the notion of not leaving a soldier behind
Do you know that you internalize that
And for me it was just always
A false assumption that America doesn't leave Americans behind
I I've never been
Put in such a ridiculous position before
Wait through these Americans that nobody gives a f*** about
Nobody is doing anything to get them home
Are greater bureaucracy is treating their families
Horribly while telling the families to just shut up and wait
I mean
Tamia it was bordering on criminal how we're treating our common citizens
Jason's Mission had been to try to figure out how to get bow back
Now he added another mission
Why not try for more Hosta
So Jason's team comes up with a couple of alternative
He start shopping around one idea in particular and gets pretty far with it
But then
He can't tell who exactly is in charge of a new headset, that is soon so calm had it yet so
Dokkan that assumed the state department had it and months later
I after a lot of meeting so I finally figure out that the state department assume that the military had
Wow it was this big lupus and come to friend is so come so come to front of the state department
And the state department really just referring to DOD
But there wasn't anybody there asking the question Steven figure out that it was that big of a mass
Jason took the problem to a congressman
Which rather surprisingly led to Jason being investigated by the army
Country that was all dropped
The congressman representative Duncan Hunter
A veteran of both the Iraq and Afghanistan Wars
Proposed legislation to try to fix hostage policy
Other people have spoken to in government say Jason's assessment Leeson bows case
Wasn't quite Act
That the various agencies were more aware of each other's plans and Jason gave them credit for
But still everyone I talked to agreed with Jason that our system for dealing with us
Just wasn't great
Cooperation between agencies with Shaggy
Policies were sometimes
Inconsistent people weren't on the same page
It was especially clear after reporter James Foley was killed
Gruesomely and publicly
Syria
A couple of months after Bill came home
December of 2014 President Obama ordered a review of how the US deals with
She says
And six months later he announced an update and hostage policy
Saying that he'd met with the families
Acknowledge to them in private what I want to say publicly
But it is true that there have been times where are government regardless of Good Intentions as let them down
I promised them that we can do better
When I first started looking into this question of what did we do to get bow back frankly I didn't think it would be all that difficult
To answer
Silly me baby but still at least I thought the answer would be linear
The chain of events would reveal itself
One link leading to another attached to another
Instead I found a bunch of people whose stories were all pretty different
Baidu central theme was the same
Frustration
Why are we doing more who's blocking this effort why
They describe struggling
Against
Tangle of competing interests they couldn't control sometimes can't even see
It sounded as if there was a scandal to uncover
And maybe there was dishonesty and even malevolence in some corners
But mostly I think it's because the truth is
There's a limit
There have to be limits on how much we risk how much we give up
I got one person back
For long-time balloons
Small
But of course he wasn't worth it
He was tucked in among so many other crises
A small fire
Smoldering among all these giant fires that also need to
The time to deal with him is when he becomes something else
Something useful way to put out a bigger fire
Family was always against a rescue attempt
He said he studied the afghanistan-pakistan Border in minut detail on Google Earth for 2 weeks after bow went missing
Based on where he figured Bo was
He thought a rescue in a place like miramshah even for an elite special operations unit wouldn't be viable
Was just too dangerous
Quote we thought it unethical to risk the lives of numerous individuals
Especially when we knew back-channel communication was possible or even actually happening
We Believe glow would agree with that ethic unquote
Mark talked about not exactly this
They talked about how much should have in soccer
Device to find him
And that initial dose one.
Mo said in an Ideal World which he gets isn't the one the military lives in
But if he could have directed the initial
You would have made it voluntary
And he would have been okay with soldiers who hadn't volunteered
Because he gets that they didn't understand his true motives
Right
What's happening because from what they're looking at
But what if they had known exactly why I walked
What specifically boaz seeing
Would it make any difference
Next time
Cereals produced by Julie Schneider Dana Chivas and me in partnership with Mark Bowl Megan Ellison Hugo Lindgren Jessica Weisberg page 1
An interpretive pictures
Our glasses are editorial advisor editing help this week from Joel level Whitney Dangerfield is our digital editor
Research by Kevin Garnett fact-checking by Michelle Harris copy-editing bionike tolani
Our music is composed by Nick thorburn Fritz Myers and Mark Phillips
It was mixed by Kate belinski
Christian Taylor's our community editor other cereal staff Southland Emily Condon Elise Ferguson and Kimberly Henderson
Special things this week to Viva Hartig Ari Shapiro Theo Padnos Jessica Goldstein Jeff Eggers Caitlin Hayden and
Dan Marquis
Our website
Serialpodcast.org
This week we posted the video of Bob Bergdahl appealing to the Pakistani government
Put more stuff up there next week too so keep checking
Serialpodcast.org
Stay tuned for preview of our next episode
The first
Support for serial comes from ADT
You can monitor your home and control your system
From virtually anywhere
With the ADT Go app
Including an SOS pad
Is it att.com podcast
To learn more about how ATT
She can design and install your custom
Smart Home
Backed by 24/7
Serials production of This American Life and WBEZ Chicago
Coming up
Next episode of serial
You see guys with helmets on
Nobody has a helmet on
F****** killed
But you said
I thought that I was going to die that day
It's a war it's what we all signed up to do and they were out out there handing out
In a watercolor maps of Afghanistan wondering how is this going to work now I figure there be a little bit more shooting involved
It was a bad situation
Cuz we all had
Weird thoughts while we're over there isolated from anybody things if he starts saying about the arm
Barney
Young
Decide to come up with an extreme solution