Previously on serial
I think the odds of you getting the Charming sociopath you're just not that lucky
Buy please please James Moore so I was kind of like
Maybe the police are putting them up to this
I said
What measure volume
Newton ball
Willing to take us out and show us where the vehicles Park
Are you still willing to do that
Global Tel Link prepaid call from
An inmate from Maryland Correctional Facility
Okay
My name is Miss Stella Armstrong
Baltimore Maryland
And you were a juror
Adnan Syed case right
Yes I was
From This American Life and WBEZ Chicago its serial one story told week by week
Sarah Koenig
I wanted to know from Stella Armstrong why she voted to convict Adnan Syed
She immediately talked about J
But you believed him
Like I said it's been a while but I remember the one young man
Who was the
Supposedly his
Friends
Who had enabled him to move the body
Right hand that struck me that
Why would you admit to doing something that drastic if you hadn't done it
You know what I mean for what reason what was he going to gain from that he still had to go to jail
Oh he didn't defend didn't
He walked
And estranged
The same thing I asked anyone who's come in contact with j
What is Jay's deal
I don't mean that he pled guilty to accessory after the fact in a first-degree murder
Testified against Adnan and got no prison time as a result
I'll talk more about that in another episode
What I mean is what did you make of Jay
Which of course is code for what am I supposed to make of Jay
How to become a cross sitting up there on the witness stand
What's his demeanor on the stand
Kid did he seem like
He seemed like he was
StreetWise
I hope that's the best way to put it
He seemed like he you know got around in the neighborhood tour
He was able to take care of yourself
He remind me of
He would be that friend if you got in trouble you would call
You know what I mean
Save I was back in high school and I'll and somebody was bothering me he remind me of somebody I would call
To help me
Like if somebody was fighting me or
It was believable to you that he would be that guy for I like he would be the guy that I return to
Yeah
That was my impression
And no because we all have somebody in our life like that
You know
That you may know a cousin or
A relative
Who is something go wrong
You think you can call to help you
Just said that I just did a very quick scared of all of my
I contacted my family and I said I feel like I can't think of one of their also useless
We will say they also useless
Wearing a tie sometimes a jacket
He's handsome he's tall and thin
You can see in the video over a little each time he speaks into the microphone in front of them
Since JS credibility was the state's case
Attorney Christina Gutierrez
Try to rip it to shreds
That essentially was her defense
She uses the word truth and lie as often as possible in a cross examination
Exchanges like this one
Pictures asked him
I know your second interview on tape
That you were not telling the truth were you not
Chase's
I was not telling you everything now
What you were telling them
Were they not
Some
Is it not stink
Pictures ask Jay about Best Buy told him there were security cameras in the parking lot and at the
The entrance
Jaden kill hey why would they care whether there were cameras there she asked
Cheapest to Jay almost casually
Believe
Directions to do
With the death of Haley Wright State
Funny question
Did you kill him in one
You want Frozen
The defense attorney tried to make him
But basically she was trying to show DJ killed
I was blaming it on and on
Which disorder that's what I remember
Nothing led us to believe that
She had a
Motive
To kill misli
That really stayed with me because she was so adamant that he was a liar
Right
Did you just didn't buy that he was lying about it
I didn't bother that it was a lie I bought the fact that he was telling the truth about what happened at that moment
Different
This must have been a harrowing nerve-racking stretch in his life
The trial itself really boring
Manchester procedural stuff that's always boring
The cross-examination is boring
Even if the star Witness
When defense attorney I talked to said that boring this can be a strategy
She's a lawyer's know that people can only pay close attention for so long
45 minutes an hour
Before they start to flag
So it's not see a tricks that gets people to crack
Tedium
Which would explain so much of a Gutierrez was doing if in fact that's what she was doing
She spends a lot of time on streets for instance
The trajectories of different roads where they travel Northeast or Northwest with their names change as they cross from the city into
County
On buildings how they are situated
Is
A box
Structure
With the Best Buy
Logo of an Angel
Three more visible
Home Security Boulevard
If not
Ryodan and that's
There's a light there that if you were not on Security Boulevard
He went straight
We will go into the parking lot
Up Security Mall
Jay doesn't crack though
He's alert he is polite he stays with her
He stays with her when she's calm and soothing and boring and he stays with her when she gets a little more shouting
Yes ma'am no ma'am answers which if I had to guess is probably 75% of what Jay says in Cross
There's a part where the chair is tries to suggest that Jay was cheating on his girlfriend Stephanie with Jen pusateri
If you were stepping out on Stephanie
Funny relationship
With me
With anyone
Call Stephanie
If you or stepping out
What that term means don't you
Anyone
Henning name anywhere
That would have been passive
Stephanie would it if not
If
You were stepping out with Annie girl of any name from an
Funny location
That would have been packing
Your relationship
Stephanie wood
Fishman
Irritated is Sybil
Excuse me your honor he says when Gutierrez gets loud
Could you ask her to stop yelling in my ear please
Goodyear has died a few years after this trial so I can't ask her but I have to take nothing
Doing here as accidental
Choose a successful sought-after defense attorney choose aggressive and obviously the court room is no place for pulling punches
But you got to wonder whether moments like this hurt and Nas case rather than helped it because
It's Baltimore half the jury is black 7 out of 12 actually
She probably comes off as a nice young Man and the Sea
Sometimes unwittingly testimony is almost poetic
He says you told Jen pusateri to be honest with the detectives because quote
The lies that we were telling to try to protect each other during the truth
Anon wanted to kill her
Mysterious took it as a grain of sand instead of concrete
Image of hay in the trunk of the car stuck with him he says I've never seen anyone dead before
The first thing I thought was how fragile Stephanie was
People lie in court under oath all the time
Witnesses lie lawyers lie police lie this should come as a shocker to no one
And I'm not saying that's what happened here I'm just saying that I'm not assuming that everyone who participated in a nun's trial told the
But clearly the jury found a believable or believable enough
After 6 week trial the convicted in on in Just 2 hours
We talked to six jurors and none of them had any lingering doubts about the
The case none of them wondered if the investigation was shotty
None of them are much bothered by had J statements to police had shifted over time
To be hung up on that
I should be concerned about the inconsistencies
I'm concerned about you are
As I mentioned the detectives involved in this case didn't want to talk to me for the story
I turned to this guy
You are Jim trainum James to deal with James
And we weave
We hired you
I'd like
Me you're a real detective I'm just playing one on the radio
Homicide detective in Washington DC
A jurisdiction not too different from Baltimore
He's become something of an expert on false confessions and an advocate for better interrogation techniques
It goes around the country during presentations about it
Everything we had on this case
Niles tapes transcripts
And again I want to be clear that we paid him for his time to huge amount of material to go through
Turn on two things
First just overall
How is the investigation into Hae Min Lee's murder
Did the detectives do a good job or did they screw it up
I'm second how should I be thinking about Jay as a witness
What were the detective scene that maybe I wasn't
Yes he thought the inconsistencies were a problem to
Also said don't forget the flip side
But I'm also looking at some of the consistencies to write at some of the
He took them to where the car was
Grandpa
That's a huge thing right there
Jay had a big piece of reliable information that the cops themselves did not know
Where his car was
Story complete the circle for the cops
They were suspicious of a non from the beginning
Adnan Cell records
They get to Jen who leads them to Jay who tells them it's Adnan
Their suspicions have now been born out
Thanks to Jay truan on tones phone
Satisfying investigative Circle
A murder case
On a silver platter
Substratum
Put on who they consider to be The Logical suspect
I mean yeah
It's pretty much a dream case
Part of what training does is review investigation
This one is better than most of what he sees
The detectives in this case were cautious and methodical they weren't rushing to grab suspects or to dismiss them either
The evidence collection is well-documented
Which I didn't expect to hear that even though it's basically a one witness case the cell records mostly don't match Jay state
There's no physical evidence linking Adnan to the murder
Despite all that to an experienced detective like this looks like a pretty sound investigation
I will say this is better than average
But what I'm saying is this
The mechanics the documentation the steps of a took
And all of that
They look good
Okay
I would have probably follow the same route
However
What were unsure of
Is what happened to change a story from A to B
And we do not know
What happened in the in those three hours or whatever like that
And that will always
Result
And a question
As to what the final outcome I mean should have been
Here's what he's talking about
Both of J's tape statements there's a before
Period of time before the tape recorder is turned on
When the cops first bring Jay in on February 28th
They talked to him for about an hour before the tape one on
March 15th the second interview
Jason's is initials to an explanation of Rights form at 3:15 p.m.
Send a text Art
Today's date is the 15th of March
It's a proxy
20 minutes after 6
Good night
6:20 p.m.
So from 3:15 to
3 hours have gone by since Jay sign that form
This is what's called the pre-interview
Training says that's where the Mischief can happen
The contamination
Necessarily intentionally but it happens
The pre-interview was when the cops in the witness kind of iron out the statement so could be taped as a coherent thing and that was
Standard procedure back then
Now look a lot of jurisdictions
Baltimore homicide detectives videotape the entire interview from the moment the person steps in the interview room
On March 15th we know the cops had shown J at least some photographs from the investigation they refer to that on the tape
And races at trial that he was confronted with the cell records during that interview as well
Do you have to wonder says China
Whether he was massaging his story to fit with the cops wanted to hear
Inconsistencies in Jay statements that the cops are catching him in cops are used to that
Every confession has inconsistencies
You just need to understand why they're happening
Is he minimizing his role is he
Protecting someone
JS case yes and yes
But how do you make sense of the inconsistencies that don't seem to have a purpose
Like the one about going to the Cliffs at Patapsco State Park that afternoon
Drops out of the narrative at trial
And for my where I said I'm like yeah it doesn't work because doesn't fit your timeline and he can't get back
The track in time
If you went out and smoke
Edjoin
No you're not at all because I think that you could on one of the biggest problems
That we have with the way that we interview and interrogate
I hear
And the fact that
We have a excellent Witness
Do we got somebody who's giving us the whole case right here he's broke it wide open for us we don't want to ruin him
Insults
You know how much do you want to push how much do you want to create quote unquote bad Evan
Love like there's no such
Like I said it's called bad evidence
Right
You don't want to do something if it's going to go against
Your theory of the case
I don't get that I mean that's likely with my father used to say all facts are friendly
Action that be more true for a cop than for anyone else like
You can't
Picture you can pick and choose
I'd rather than trying to get to the truth what you're trying to do is build your
Case
And make it the strongest case
Possible
But how can it be a strong
Hayes and how can he be a great Witness
Their stuff that's
Not true or or unexplained
And
Come back is it there's always going to be things that are on
Explainable
But like I said
Also remember verification biases
Kicking in here
Where is well
I want to believe you
I am because you're my witness and I think this is what happened and all that
So the fact that you're giving me something that's inconsistent
It doesn't fit my theory of the case
What is verification bias caused you to do
Ignoring push it aside
And that's what they're doing here with these inconsistencies are kind of pushing them
I was curious to him that the cops never search J's house for instance
But they never subjected him to a polygraph
He said maybe that's because he was on their team now helping so you don't want to push too hard
He said the cops quote probably settled for what they thought was good enough to be the truth on quote
He said he did have doubts about Adnan claim of Innocence
But that he definitely thought there was something quote-unquote off about this case
But we still don't know what happened in this murder
We still don't have the true story
I don't believe James Version
I think that there is a lot more to it than that
Is the eye I feel that
Definitely minimizing
His involvement
Peter to either protect himself
Peachisoda for water water freeze
Protect himself to protect somebody else
Or because I wanted it was right there with them
Right
But I cannot prove that he's given to me without contamination
Write the real problem is is that
How do you prove it one way or the other
Right
The answer's probably live in those unrecorded pre-interview hours
A black hole of crucial information
The stuff wasn't all video to Interlink their holes were never as you're saying like we're never going to know the in
But for what things that I could know the answer
You're too if your me what's the biggest thing I need to
Figure out then
Did Jada talk
Okay
Okay so we passed the city limit
Schneider and I went to CJ
We did not warren j we were coming which is not the gentlest reporter move I know
The best chance of success if we met him face-to-face
Taking a car case for why we wanted to talk to him and he could have a better sense of what we were about
Dick move to show up at someone's door
Joe and I were nervous
I am so hyped up
Listen to the tape I wanted to get myself a Xanax
Super excited to talk to him
Like if this works and I mean
He knows he knows everything we want every question we've had
For the past
7 months
Weather like
There's a
Treasure chest
Answers
That we've been looking for this
Whole time
And he
Has it
Cheez-It
Whether or not we don't even know if he's home
We arrived
He was not home
So we came back again many hours later
Knocked
Answer the door
Tall and skinny and exhausted looking
It was Friday probably end of a long work day for him
He nevertheless invited us and asked us to sit down
We didn't record anything
20 minutes maybe
Does a tense meeting
An emotional meeting in fact
Afterwards Julie and I felt like we walked into a stranger's house lobbed a Grenade on to his living room carpet and then
Goodbye
We debriefed back in the car
Here's the first thing he said I mean you said
But there are a lot of people who say that they don't
I think I did it
Keep very forcibly settled and who did
He said he did
He was like I was there
I saw it like I know what I know
He was very forceful like I can't believe he
He won't even man up
And admit it
He just totally scoffed
Shut the idea that
Anon
Whidbey Clinic
He was very calm
Like how would you describe his demeanor
Tired
Yeah
She seemed tired
And a little and weary but not
But actually very polite and actually started very
Sweet
Tired
But he also said
I'm feeling like so much are animal rage right now even you bringing this up now
But you got a good job of
You know
I'm keeping it in cuz he didn't seem like he was about to about to hit something but in
More frustrated understandable way
Jay was understandably skeptical of us and of our motives
When we left Jay said he think about an interview and get back to us
He left a strong impression
Julie maybe even more than on me
Even just hearing him
So forcefully deny in a land so forcefully say I know he did it
You know it's your face to face
He's right there he's a person
He sang at he seems
Like he really means that
This is not pleasant for him to talk about
So you know
It sounds
Believable
Add ice totally saw the appeal of him
Other
Person in a friend and a witness
Correspondence sporadically by email in the weeks following our meeting
He said he wasn't afraid of the truth
Finally in so many words
Decline an interview
What is the deal with Jay
I talked to dozens of people mostly his friends and classmates
Woodlawn High School a range of opinions about whether he was a good guy or not a good guy
Define categorization
He was different
Can you like the Rodman of our
Like
Social world
Listen to Life
Rage Against the Machine and you know
See what dies hair different colors
Columbia to BMX belt buckle
And I had a belt buckle belt buckle
Dennis Rodman is the best way I can describe it
You know if I buy if he was at my house my mom came home and he left you be like who's that
Then why is he here
Salo
Either weirdo
I didn't know too many black guys that were into all those kisses and chicks
In the big
Like that
Kenwood Los Feliz
Black neighbor black community black predominantly black high school
You know
Fs17
Anything different from you is weird
School
He loved animals giant rat eating frog
We love the outdoors
Fishing hiking swimming
I think it was actually pretty good at lacrosse
Call Winery dude could run for days there was no training needed for that kitty could just run forever
What you think he wasn't the type to put on training in
Right because he wasn't a jock
Is more of a Stoner
They didn't seem to care whether he fit in
And you always change
Very honest
With who he was
My beautifully unconventional guy
Jaden come from the same kind of household as a lot of the other kids he hung around with
He lives with his grandparents and his mom
But his friends say it seems like he was more or less taking care of himself
Had a job
His mother depended on him
Program at Woodlawn who is Gen pop
Their term not mine like general population at a prison
He hung out with some of the magnet kids because his girlfriend Stephanie was in the program
People told me contradictory things about Jay
Woodlawn including one teacher
Unflattering things about him
Nothing terrible just that he was mean or intimidating
Some kids thought of him as quote-unquote Shady
But you wouldn't want to push him
You got the sense that if you cross jaehee come after you
But then I also her descriptions of that included the word goofy
AR stoner
Or it was just a pose
Something to put on to Cintas
He's he's Alpha
Is definitely an alpha male
This is Chris who says he was one of Jay's best friends around this time
He said in the hallway at school
He wasn't mad or anything he's just messing around
Chris remember this one story or it seemed to me all the different versions of Jay I'd heard
The Goofy and the scary were contained in it
You know we have weird argument sometimes I remember outside of one of my cousin's house has he tried to stab me
I'll because I hadn't been stabbed before so we got into a fight over a actually I gave him a knife
If I work at a knife shop
I gave him
So we're literally like fighting outside of my cousin's house and he's like
Before you need to know what it's like and unlike your own I can let you stab me
I talked to three people who said they knew Jay well or hung out with him around the time of the crime
About what happened
I want to Chris first because when J spoke to detectives that first night during his first
Jay mention Chris by name
How to ask Jay if you told anyone else about this murder and Jason he told Chris
Bristol me police never questioned him
Not that he can remember anyway and he thought you remember something like that
There no notes in their files about an interview with Chris
Kristen was true Jay did tell him about what happened
His version
The building blocks are the same but this running details are unfamiliar
Of course giant caveat it's 15 years later that I'm asking Chris
Tell me
For comparison purposes here goes
Chris has Jay told him he was at a pool hall out on Route 40 in Catonsville when he got a call from a non
Precise they were crossed
Street from each other at the time
He told you that I done came to get him when he was at
He was shooting
Yo where are you we told her where it was
Add nacho. Because I know I got to talk to you is like
Convinced him to come outside with him
And
Is car or I don't know if he's driving his car Haley's
In this version the trunk pop happens at the pool hall
Chris AJ told Adnan he wanted nothing to do with it but not enforce them
He was in it now he was an accessory
Couldn't go to the cops because of his own illegal activities
CJ Woodstock
Help bury the body
Chris figured Linkin Park with likely J's idea rather than add-ons
Present information about the crime itself doesn't quite match the states version
He said Jay told him
Confronted hey about flirting with another guy
Car salesman
And when she call the nun crazy he snapped and strangled her
Chris said he heard this happened
In the parking lot of the Woodlawn Public Library
That's the one that's right there on campus
Where Asia said she saw Adnan that day
Chris has Jay told him that Adnan threatened to kill Stephanie if Jaden keep
His mouth shut this is not the first I'd heard about something like this Jay told the cops that he worried and none would hurt Stephanie to
And you also testified at trial that have not had made it clear he could get to Stephanie anytime we wanted since they were such good friends
Stuffing herself tells the cops this is in their notes from their conversation with her
The J told her to stay away from a non
Chris has Jay told him and showed up at Jay's house with Stephanie not long after the crime
I made a gesture to indicate
I'll hurt her if you're not careful
So
Stephanie goes in your inside pack jammie steps out onto the
It all the porch with Adnan he's like
Snuggling terrorize me
Can you keep your mouth shut or something
App
If it if he had any weakness it was Stephen
David duhigg move heaven and hearth if it
Kanto
Protecting Stephanie
I talked to Laura a friend of Jays and Stephanie's and John's and Alvernon
Laura Estrada Sandoval
She was close with Stephanie
They play sports together
Her parents didn't agree with their relationship cuz he was just like
They felt like he's like he wasn't going to melt anything wasn't going to school
You know Stephanie
She's beautiful and she said she was
Start Ashley
She said she got a scholarship to college Lake
Perfect you know like she ran the fastest she's always like
In-Shape no matter what you could eat anything
It Mike
She always saw the good in people no matter what like no matter if her parents are telling her
Good influence on you
Because she looked Jay so much
For him
Douglas
She was his like good thing in life
She was like out of all the craziness like Stephanie was like his amazingness
Stephanie didn't want to talk to me
I know what I spoke to who knows her was surprised by that
Two person they said she never talked to them about what happened either
I said it was like a wall came down and they can penetrate it
Lord in their friendship
Because we really needed to talk about it
And Stephanie wouldn't or couldn't
Laura hung out with Jay all that summer before the trial and she says they just didn't discuss it
His murder was this enormous sad frightening elephant nobody wanted to go near
Jason Patrick told me he couldn't get you to talk about it either
What happened
Dodge Ram
Does Patrick by the way isn't the one I've already mentioned in an earlier episode from the call log
Different Patrick
This Patrick went to Woodlawn he was a year ahead of Jaso 2 years ahead of Adnan and Hae and Stephanie
Patrick lost touch with J when all this went down he says he tried and tried to call but you never responded
Years later maybe around 2005 Jacob back in touch one day
And then they saw each other a little party
Patrick asked him about it
Turn all of these like Renditions and versions of stories from the Sun
Having fun of me now like I can get to the truth and
End
You know
I was afraid he was going to hurt
Stephanie
And I was like
Staten Island
Can you threaten her and
He said he was afraid that he was going to hurt her that's why I guess I took it as a threat now
Everyone I pushed him
Detail at Christian for more
It wasn't
I didn't get it
Like he wasn't he wasn't going to
Go any further with it you know and there was a lot of
What does drink beer
Patrick says the Stephanie explanation sounded pretty thin to him
But you can't get anything else out of Jay and figured it wasn't his place to force it
LJ's friends I spoke to whether they thought J was telling the truth about what happened that night
I got some Curious answers
Because his friends had a reputation for lying
But not for lying about something like that
Something so big
Sort of the same way he had a reputation for being scary but not
Scary scary
The first thing that popped in my head was like jail eyes
Why does that jayla's about everything
But Kathy again that's not a real name or her real voice
She's the person who said I was acting weird at her apartment that night of the murder when they brought him over
Talking about it and saying you
Vajazzling inconsistencies at the first thing that
Cuz Jay lies Jay doesn't tell the truth
About what what kind of stuff
I think it was kind of like
But everything nothing
I can definitely remember sometimes it would be telling a story
Hey what's really know it was b*******
LOL I remember one time I'm looking at Jen and generally guys like
Here we go again you know I mean like this is a b*******
Chris and Patrick told me that Jay would tell them stories
Tall Tales almost that they figured had to be made up
Then sometimes the stories turned out to be true
And Kathy said sure Jay might lie about what he had for breakfast or even whether you went to Patapsco State Park on the afternoon
January 13th 1999
But she didn't think Jay was lying about the crime itself
Because she's convinced Adnan is guilty based on a nonce behavior that night
What he was saying when you got that phone call at your house
Teresa Terry
Of all the people about this crime
She ever thought J was lying about that night
I spoke to her briefly at her work
Shorts at a discount store
But she was totally uninterested in talking to me
Nothing to hide she said she just did not want to talk about that time in her life.
She did answer my one big question though
And her answer was yes
She believes Jay then and that hasn't changed in the intervening years
But she did lie to you somewhat back then
Remember he tells Jem that night that he doesn't know where add-on put his body but they don't know enough to go to the police
Jen told me she could understand that kind of lie
But anyone in his position forced into something he wanted no part of
Anyone might have told the same kind of lie
I didn't shake her trust in his overall story
Then she was one thing she never believed
She said she never believed the murder happened at Best Buy
Because you thought there would have been security footage
And that never came out
I told her it seems like maybe there really weren't security cameras at Best Buy Back Then
She kind of shrugged and said
Oh well I don't know
I talked to said when I heard Jay was wrapped up in a murder
It didn't surprise them
Shocking
Not so shocking
People also said they couldn't Square J feeling threatened by
But that's just being wrong to them
Does Patrick and Laura and Kathy
People who spent a lot of time with j
The were shocked by Jason Baughman
Or something like that
They said that wasn't you
Same thing almost every single one of them
Says about him
So the end up in this in-between place
Swear they can't quite wrap their minds around the story of that night
Who's Patrick again
Intelligent inquisitive sweet goofy guy
Beautifully unconventional
I think
Artemis
I know this so terrible to say I hoping someone
The source that she was
They had no choice so that
Hoosier outside of his
Control in that
Maybe he was looking out for the safety and well-being of others
He wasn't such a willing participant as she was
I hope that it wasn't
That grappling you can hear in his voice that's so common among this group of friends
People like Laura who can't imagine a non killing anyone
But also can't imagine Jay doing what he said he did
Or why he would lie about something so huge
If you're Laura and there's no scenario here you can rationalize
You're left with fog
This piece of tape I'm about to play you it's my favorite piece of tape from all my reporting so far
Because I relate to it so precisely
It could be me talking to Laura instead of the other way around
So then who's affected it like why would
State five ways it doesn't make sense why would
Why would
Hayward
I just I can't
Okay just as confused as you are
A J sentencing for his accessory after the fact conviction
He's wearing a white shirt has long arms hanging at his side
Towering over his lawyer whose teeth
She tells the judge all the stuff a defense attorney tends to cover at a sentencing
Just have upbringing that he didn't have adults helping instead of moral compass
What is hardworking and loves animals and is good with kids
He's headed to college and wants to better himself
She says she underwent quotes
Rigorous and demeaning cross-examination on the part of Christina Gutierrez
And she says he's remorseful
She says just now
He was weeping in the hallway about Haley
Prosecutor Kevin urick tells the judge he is thoroughly pleased with his participation in the case
And impress
I said very satisfactory you and I believe honestly testified
And also I would say something I
You don't usually see I think he actually showed remorse
Judges impress to
NJ does seem genuinely torn up
There anything you want to say before I impose the sentence
Justin
Whatever you do decide I'm like you know that
A real hard time even sitting here
People look at me
Ameristar food
Apartment at
The judge sentences J2 two years probation no jail time
His lawyer Mouse the words
Thank you to the judge
Courtroom with the only person who came with him that day
Stephanie
Anon didn't testify at his trial which isn't unusual
Pictures aren't supposed to take that into consideration the judge tells himself that they are not allowed to hold that against the defendant when they
Deliberating
Did it bother you guys as a jury that I done himself didn't testify didn't take the stand
Yes it did
Text Lisa Flynn one of the jurors
That was huge
We just
I think
That was huge
We all kind of like gas
It's like Blown Away by that
You know why not if you're a dependent IRS
You know why would you not get up there and defend yourself
I try to prove that
The state is wrong that you weren't there that you're not guilty
We are trying to be
The open mind it was just like
Get up there and say something no
Try to persuade even though it's not your job.
Wait us.
I don't know
All this was going down
What do I know about it
But the jury didn't
Next time
Annie's cereal
Operations manager
Eyeglasses are editorial advisor
Auburn score
Special thanks to Gina DeVito
Site where you can listen to all our episodes and find photos letters and other documents from the case and sign up for a week
Serialpodcast.org
Ciro's production of This American Life and WBEZ Chicago