Support for serial comes from ATT
The number one smart home security provider
With a team of 18000 employees
Dedicated to safeguarding your home
With connection to First Responders
Offering Custom Design Systems including doorbells
Indoor and outdoor cameras and smart locks and lights
All control from the ADT app or the sound of your voice
And all back
Buy 24/7 protect
Visit att.com podcast
To learn more
How do you how do you manipulate an entire country to get a
An enlisted Soldier home
Previously
I'm cereal how can I get into Afghanistan
How can I get to Paxton I get my bag.
Are greater bureaucracy is telling the families to just shut up and waved us the Pakistani Armed Forces
Think I can get that done for you but he really likes Johnnie Walker Black Label
Exchange
The Taliban
From This American Life and WBEZ Chicago its serial one story told week by week
I'm Sarah Koenig
May 31st 2014
Sabo gets picked up by Special Operations team in Afghanistan
He's quickly pulled onto a
Leaving the ground like that
We space suddenly all around him
After 5 years of being locked in rooms
He said it was like Crossing in Abyss
When they landed at a nearby base bow wanted to communicate with these guys who rescued him
You couldn't talk yet
He hadn't spoken sentences
Has much less had a conversation in so long
He says you can think of the words
But he couldn't make them come out of his
What I ended up doing was asking for something real and at first thing I asked him was
Intel
They got me onto the plane
On the plane with the rest of the team
Background
And that was the last I saw them
I did mention
Wanted to say thank you and the other people around at the time
We got to get you some food in you and all that you know and I didn't want to
At that moment a military transport plane was standing by a Guantanamo Bay
Waiting to take 5 Taliban guys to Qatar
5 years worth of machination
High Hopes and false starts and politicking at secret meetings
Had gone into getting bow onto that helicopter
And the five Taliban prisoners onto a C-17
Response to this trade back home in the US buried
But probably the loudest response was
Can't believe I just did that
We negotiated with terrorists
To release some terrorists
To get back a deserter
It seems people also had questions in Afghanistan
Wait what was all of this about
Did they really just give up
Five leaders of the Taliban for one American Soldier
That's Hyder Akbar
He grew up in the US
Canales in Kabul
His father was governor of kunar province
How does a friend of This American Life he's done some stories for us
Spider was in Afghanistan when the trade happen
And he remembers the talk
The disbelief
This guy was definitely not if we see a general
No. She's just a soldier
Really they're going to let go of
5 there must be something greater at play here
I was supposed to be something much greater at play here
Something as big and Grand
The plan to end the war
What happened
How did this become the solution to getting Bo home
In 2009 was captured
The war in Afghanistan was going very badly for US troops
And a struggle was going on inside the Obama Administration
About what to do about it
The idea the president settled on was fully resource counterinsurgency
Peace talks meaning talking directly to the Taliban about ending the war
That was not part of the
Not yet
Person who argued the most forcefully for that to change who said we should start talking to the Taliban now
The Diplomat name Richard Holbrooke
Holbrook had just been appointed a strap
Special representative for Afghanistan and Pakistan
Basically Secretary of State Hillary Clinton had hired him
To help in the war
Holbrook was his legendary negotiator
Huge tenacious Talent
And also a huge personality
Her Memoir about being Secretary of State Clinton tells a story about how Relentless he was
I once followed her into a ladies room in Pakistan
So you can finish making his point
Rub some people in the administration the wrong way including Obama himself
Albert didn't stop lobbying for a political solution to the war
Well Richard did not think that
There was
A military solution
The war in Afghanistan
Biscotti Martin
A journalist and writer
She's also married to Richard Holbrooke
Who died in 2010
He did not think that you could
Just muscle your way to a solution
General Petraeus
Felt that doubling down
On the Taliban was the way to go Richard would have 10 second conversations with Petraeus
And at least the gist of that was
No
This is not the time for diplomacy and he's deeply
Resented Petraeus to with his friend referring to him repeatedly as his
Richard would Grumble to me since when did the Diplomat become
The military's wingman
How do you says it wasn't a personal slight Pebblebrook even care about that
It was a principal
Keep up the military had to much sway
It was dominating political strategy in these wars
Vale Nasser also work for Holbrook and a strap off
Does a special advisor
Is a Middle East scholar
Molly Nasser says in Holbrook view the whole military forces diplomacy debate was out of whack
In other words it was General Petraeus you should be holbrook's wingman
Or
Handmaiden
Military the handmaiden to diplomacy
And that balance has been lost during the bush years
And and and that's why I think he believed that that was fundamentally wrong and would find it and we get America into
Greater trouble
Call Brooksville with that you use the military
To get the Taliban to the table
But the goal is to get them to sign a document
Agreement
Holbrook is being sidelined this whole time
People in the administration are trying to get him fired in
Hillary Clinton protected in
To make matters worse Holbrook had a crummy relationship with Hamid Karzai
Cars I thought Holbrook it undermined
And the Afghan presidential elections December of 2009
Cuz I was
Entirely wrong
Around Holbrook isn't so popular
And neither is the notion of the US sitting down with the Enemy
Taliban
But it seems the enemy was interested in talking to us
Diplomats in Germany have been meeting with a 30-something Afghan guy
It was close to miloma
The Taliban leader
His name was Taya Baga
Back in Washington they didn't say his name out loud though
These two codename
A-Rod
Holbrook was a baseball fan
Yes A-Rod was a very familiar
A meeting with A-Rod would be risky
Turn off the guys for real whether you're being played
Neither side knows
Holbrook wanted to try it
He took it to Hillary Clinton who was skeptical but gave the go-ahead
For a first face-to-face meeting between the Taliban and the United States government
Ways to be just outside Munich right after Thanksgiving
And it was to be secret
Paladin insisted it
A secret or else they walk
Pakistan didn't know the British didn't know
Do people in the US government now
Two people the Taliban new
They met in a small village in a safe house run by German intelligence
Although Thai about guy had one Western suits in his earlier meetings with the Germans
At this meeting he wore traditional Afghan clothes
White tunic
Open by reading a formal propagandistic statement he knew the Americans wouldn't like
Americans don't have a set agenda
Are mostly there to listen
Weren't talking terms the US did have some non-negotiables
We wanted the Taliban to stop fighting
Break with Al-Qaeda
And support the Afghan Constitution
Including rice in there for women and girls
That was especially important to Hillary Clinton
The big goal was to get the Taliban to start talking to the cars I govern
Daddy has the state department put it
Afghans talking to other Afghans about the future of Afghanistan
So we could get out of the room
The Taliban wanted a few things too
They wanted the US to distinguish between them and Al-Qaeda take their names off a un sanctions list
Paris
They wanted a political office outside of Pakistan they wanted it in Doha
And they wanted their prisoners
And that's where boat comes in
By that time the haqqanis have been holding him for almost a year-and-a-half
Now at this meeting his fate
Becomes tied to the fate of the peace process in Afghanistan
If us hands over some Taliban prisoners
They'll hand over the American Soldier
What would be part of water called confidence-building measures
That would pave the way for substantiv
Peace talks
The Americans weren't allowed to call it a prisoner exchange by the way
I had to call it a mutual release
Sobo is part of the discussion
That is not the point of these talks
Not the Crux of any
It's pretty clear when I've asked diplomats and State Department officials about it
Like a line item
An important line item
The line-item nonetheless
I've heard and read a number of different accounts now about what the Taliban initially asked for in exchange for Bo
One source told me it was always five particular guys at gitmo the Taliban wanted
Another source
Who was at the meeting
Tell me that it first it was a simpler to man
4 Taliban prisoners held at Bagram
In Afghanistan
Cuyahoga turned us down for an interview
So I haven't been able to definitively pin this down
In any case when the Munich meeting was over the Americans
A contingent from the White House
State Department
Defy home
Report back to their bosses
Thumbs up
It's on
Holbrook Dr. To the airport to meet his guy he's so eager to hear how it went
Just a couple of weeks later
Holbrook.
He was at work when his aorta ruptured is rushed to the hospital for surgery
Put on December 13th 2010
She died
Just a pause here for a minute
A bunch of people I talk to for the story we're sad about holbrook's death
Just for him
The Frack Anniston
They have this feeling that maybe if Holbrook hadn't died when he did
The talks with the Taliban could have worked out differently
That we wouldn't still be in this mess of War
Hayes Valley Nasser
Holbrook was the only I think Statesmen at that time in the United States who was willing
To take the risk of owning reconcile
That's that wasn't afraid of it wasn't afraid of it
He advocated what was a very very unpopular and and risky
At position
I don't think anybody else was willing to do it after
Nobody stood up and said
I'm not mister reconciliation I'm now the champion
And the irony of it was that
You know he was being
So much effort was being put on marginalized
A dad that that that you know when you actually died
We realized
You know how much was he actually caring
And how important
Right after Holbrook dies
That's when political reconciliation with the Taliban officially becomes us strategy
In February of 2011
Hillary Clinton gives a speech in honor of Holbrook
Actually
Which for the first time an American official speaks out loud in public about talking peace with
The Taliban
Still many people in the government aren't happy about it
Adversary that can be as brutal as the Taliban
Sounds
Distasteful
Even
Animash
And diplomacy would be
A lot easier
If we only had to talk to our friends
But that is not how one makes
Peace
Where was the original Vision after Munich
Over the next 6 months
Everyone would agree to terms on the confidence-building measures
The office would happen trade including Bo what happened and then the goal was by December
7-Eleven at an International Conference plan in Bonn Germany cars I would be there and the talks Afghan to f
Afghan would be underway
Such an orderly vision
Instead what happens is
Football
Years of fits and starts
4 people in the diplomacy business the ping pong and trajectory of these taxes probably familiar
But to me as I was trying to figure out what happened with bow and his connection to these meetings with the Taliban
I just had no idea it would look like this
And I'm not going to take you through every step because we'd be here all week
But I just want to point out some of the moments of like only because they really bring home
How fraught and fragile diplomacy can be
So after Munich there's this brief moment of
Hopefulness
How many cars I had created a high peace Council
In anticipation of impending peace
The US had a couple more meetings with Ty abaga
And then
Stagnation
Nothing is fine
Nothing is moving
Washington is wearing
Dithering
Michael Steiner was the S trap
Germany at the time
Heat help set up the US Taliban talks in the
He says after Munich it was like the motor of the whole process
Sputtered
Time
Enormous
Precious time after 1
With every last month
Ade prospectus to get
The situation here
Becomes more difficult
No
It took so damn long
I needed to show progress to his bosses
The Taliban are getting antsy
In addition for tabaga it's no easy thing for him to get to these meetings
In secret
He worried understandably that his life might be in danger
Became public you was talkin to the US
Factions inside the Taliban didn't want peace
And no one had consulted Pakistan about any of this
Pakistan had long wanted to be a player and NEP
Karzai was perpetually worried that the US and Pakistan were up to something behind his back
It all had to stay quiet
2011 Ambassador Mark Grossman replaced Holbrook is Ezra
What was supposed to be secret it would have been better if it is
Been quiet
That as I as I know you know from doing your research
People just talk and talk and talk
They did
We suffered a lot of leaks from
Washington and also
And also from Cabo
And why well because you know it wasn't the most popular thing in the world to be doing
Result in May of 2011 The Washington Post and Der Spiegel in German
Post reported that the talks were happening and for the first time they named Cuyahoga the Taliban
Man walked away from the talks
Clinton rushed to Islamabad to smooth things over with Pakistan
Another state department official pleaded Doha to ask the Cuttery is to please please ask the Taliban to come back
Which a few months later they did
According to Michael Steiner the leaks meant the Taliban now had to Dig Inn on their demands
To reassure their own people they weren't selling out to the America
Price for the continuation
Of the process
Fire
Because the demand beckemeyer
Aunt
If you would have acted earlier
Could have been
To be paid
Steiner didn't specify but I believe he's talking about the gitmo detainees
The Taliban now fixed on that demand
That made things harder
Because getting prisoners out of gitmo
NE prison
Just ask President Obama
That's not easy
Are laws about it
You have to tell Congress you have to get the Secretary of Defense to sign off on it
Someone in the office at the time told me when they discuss it at meetings the defense department just
Really really really
Opposed transferring anybody out of Guantanamo
Big picture Mark Grossman schools were the same as Holbrook
To create a stable Afghanistan inside a stable region
I need a plan
Series of international conferences and meetings
To get other countries to commit money and support
To help not only end the war in Afghanistan but sustained a piece
Explain all of this
The tie bar go when they finally met
In what were
What did he want
Like what what became clear to you was like
Why he was there
They wanted their prisoners out of Guantanamo
Grossman's at one point they did try to offer Ty about got prisoners from Bagram
But that was a no-go
The reporter David road that they tried to offer up for different Taliban guys from gitmo lesser figure tutorial
I've been cleared for transfer but that was also rejected
Calvin wanted these Five Guys
This point in the middle of 2011 there were 17 Afghans in Guantanamo
All of them accused of being tied to the Taliban or two terrorist groups
So why was Tyga asking for these 5 back
Can exchange for battle
You look especially two of the big he's on the list
Does a mullah Fazal an oriole and Nori
What happened with them is actually a really interesting window into what was going on with the war right in the beginning
Because this is a surprise to me
About time late 2001 some Taliban commanders surrender
So there's this opportunity
People argue that we blew it it was a big missed opportunity
To get the Taliban to stop fighting
That we could have swooped in when they were weakest
Contain them
A piece
Another words all the things we'd still be struggling to do a decade-and-a-half later
I talked to Carlotta Gall about these guys
Fazal Inori coladas reporter for the New York Times
And she arrived in Afghanistan just a couple of weeks after the US started bombing
The Taliban regime was unraveling and in the north where Colorado was
Hundreds of Taliban and Al-Qaeda Fighters had just been trapped
In the city of condos
Jordan newspaper story about what happened next
But never got published
So much else was going on that in
In retrospect what you saw with a singular moment in the war
I talked to Carlotta over Skype
Shoes at our office in Tunis she's in North Africa
Correspondent now
The sound isn't great
But you told me the story of what she saw
She said she was up north
This big mud for it
Where General dostum also was
Dustin was his Infamous Commander
Who was fighting the Taliban
And the US was supporting him
So Dustin fair at this fort
And he he received the delegation of
Taliban
He wanted to surrender and it was amazing we will bunch of us reporters with waiting that all day and Sunday
Lisa
Lancome list of pickups
Surprise
Didn't sweep into the
Into this mod World Fort late at night in the dark and they will you know
Fotos de Raul Taliban they were in mining these big guns on the back of that pick up Sunday
Swept in new pretty scary but actually didn't come in
222 Logan to surrender to Dustin
Moana father was the leader
Soma lofaso
Anuria Lenora it was with him
And these are two of the guys that good decade later
The Taliban would ask us to release
In exchange for Bo
Carlotta says noriel anureet had a reputation as someone you could reason with
Music quieter guidance
A provincial governor
But fossil kaleido said he was one of the most feared men in the land
He was this this hideous
Operational commander who had a string of massacres to his name and people up there in the north with her
These guys
And he
You know you would be telling me we'll weeks I've been there a week or seven people are saying this is the line
Who would
Shoving fingers are people's nostrils and
To push the head back and then slit their throats he was
It was Beauty I would say he was the two things of many war crimes and
He was none too committed massacres all the lord of the northern tribes as the Taliban soldiers
Surprise
And here he is
Maleficent
Inori and others
They're surrendering
They head into this meeting with Dustin there Americans in the room to CIA probably
Colada's waiting outside midnight
I'm depressed and short grumpy looking
Dustin made him Bay City say on camera that you know the fight so
He did not shoot a text say the word surrender but he basically said we will give up on weapons on
And the fighting incredible moment to see many of us
We're up there and not much of it go to the papers that time but
It was
The only public surrender of
The Taliban forces
Promises in the days that followed
Puzzle delivered
Hundreds of his Fighters Taliban and also foreign Fighters and pakistanis
Can streaming in and handed over their weapons
Apparently the understanding was that fossils Fighters would be allowed safe passage back to where they came from
But it didn't happen instead many of them got killed at a now-infamous prison Uprising which lasted for days
Hundreds more got packed up in container trucks in asphyxiated
Whole other grizzley chain of events
As for fossil and Nori Justin kept them under house arrest for a while his own rather fancy guest house
But eventually he gave them up to the Americans
What we learned later was saying they were taken to one of the warships
In the Gulf I think
As quite a few PS4 at that time and then they later ended up in Guantanamo
They were in fact in that group of first arrivals at Guantanamo
On January 11th 2002
You seen the pictures from that day
Men on their knees
Orange jumpsuits barbed wire
As for the other guys on tabaka's list
They all seem to have been in contact with
If not cooperating with
Either the us or the Karzai government
When they were arrested and sent to Guantanamo
When was the Taliban is Deputy intelligence chief
I was at a meeting with CIA agent
That's when he was grabbed
And rolled up in a carpet right away like that in broad daylight
Another was a former Taliban interior minister
Hidden contacts
The Karzai about a job
And one was meeting an American
At the airport when he got a rash
So those are the five
Actually there was one other guy the Taliban wanted back
But he died at Guantanamo
Get a heart attack after exercising on an elliptical in early 2011
If the Taliban to get these guys out of gitmo
It would be symbolic and a bunch of ways
First off it's a hugely morale-boosting message
Their own fighters
Look at the links will go
How to get our prisoners out
More than that it's a huge Public Relations Act
The United States
The highest levels
Would be recognizing them
The Taliban
As legitimate organization
Not treating them as a ragtag band of terrorists
I'm finally to them it's a victory for their understanding of Justice in this one
Since most of these guys say they weren't exactly fighting with America
When they were captured in the first place
Mufasa himself explains this line of
Is Military Tribunal at Guantanamo
He tells the tribunal about the meeting with dostum
Reporters
Derek ammerman in journalist
Meaning dostum he says there's 25 year war between person-to-person Village by Village City by City
Province by province and tribe against tribe
If you think this is crime than every single person in Afghanistan should be in prison or bring them here
I never ever fought against the new government I never fought against America and I didn't do anything wrong against
And why am I an enemy combatant
It does seem true that fossil was a brutal fighter
Powerful commander and possibly a war criminal
But you can argue the same is true of General dostum
Dustin has also been accused of war crimes
Is now first vice president of Afghanistan
Our Ally
And one last thing on this in 2001
Hamid Karzai had come to an agreement with Taliban commanders in the south
The Taliban with hand over control of four provinces peacefully
And in return they did amnesty
But the US said no you can't do that
Wouldn't let it happen
Instead we proclaimed by a secretary of defense Donald Rumsfeld
That because the Taliban harbored Osama Bin Laden we would be treating them the same way we treated International terrorist
We do not give amnesty to terrorists
We do not negotiate with her
We hunt them down
The talks with the Taliban suffered so many setbacks over the years it's hard to even contain them all in
I had so many factors were in play in so many different countries
Some of the setbacks are pointed an intentional elytra
Some setbacks for immutable a simple case of bad timing and some setbacks were so human
Old fashioned screw-ups
Most obvious assault on the tops came in September of 2011
A guy came to the door of former Afghan president Brandon Rabbani
Rabbani was heading Afghanistan's High peace Council this guy said he had a message from the Taliban
Unglue app for Bonnie's house
Rabbani was killed as were four others from the council
Barney's assistant masoom stanekzai
Was badly injured
No one took responsibility for the attack but many people suspected Pakistan was behind it
Mark Roseman says losing the help of those guys and especially having Statics II out of commission for so many months
Was terrible
We talked about Afghans talking other Afghans about future Afghanistan they were the Afghans
Yeah
They they would have been doing this work
And whoever did this
It was a very
It was a very strategic move
Rabbani assassination happened a couple months before the big international meeting and bond set for December 2000
11 the one that a year earlier had been something of a Finish Line
Now it felt like they were back to square one
And then a year-and-a-half later
Screw up
With some very bad results
Mid-2013 have been in captivity for 4 years
By then
After various arm-twisting in Washington and in Kabul and a Doha
It looks as if they really might be able to crank up the talks again
Things have shifted
Instead of the prisoner exchange first
They're going to do an office
The Taliban wanted in office
In Doha
As a home base for political
It would show they were legitimate political actor
The office had become Issue Number 1 for the
And cars I was naturally cautious
About this
There's a new s Rap by now Ambassador James Dobbins
He's working with Karzai and Woodcutter
Who's the intermediary
Cautious is probably an understatement for cars on this day
He doesn't trust us
He doesn't trust our stated objectives in Afghanistan are for real
He's worried we're trying to cut him out of the
The talks make a side deal with
Pakistan maybe he obviously doesn't trust package
He thinks maybe this whole office deal is a Pakistani orchestrated plot
To get recognition for the Taliban
He's worried Cotter is essentially letting the Taliban set up a shadow government with this Doha office
So it's shaky to say the least
Car has cooperation here
The United States is trying to make sure everyone abides by the ground rules
Including the detail
The Taliban cannot throw around the words Islamic Emirate in connection with this office very important
They have to call it something like
The political office of the Taliban movement
Not as representation of the Islamic Emirate which was what they
Call
Their government so they shouldn't present themselves in a fact as an alternative government
Afghanistan
So everyone's agreeing to the starter ground rules the Assumption was that
In June
The office would open and we would begin discussions and the detainee exchange would be
Most likely the first order of business
Meaning the exchange for both would be the first order of business
June 18th the office open
It's his new pretty elaborate multi-story building
The wall around it
An opening ceremony back in the US the time difference
Means it's something like three or four in the morning in Washington
Jeff Eggers who's in Afghanistan and Pakistan director for the National Security Council
Has David been up all night waiting for the opening on TV
The first indication that there was a problem with the flag
The flag
Of the Islamic Emirate
They also had a sign outside the
It said Islamic Emirate
John Kerry was Secretary of State by then
Within minutes he calls the Emir of Qatar
Remember we're not communicating directly with the Taliban
The spine is all through the
Guitarist
So carry presumably impresses on the emir
It's not supposed to say Islamic Emirate
The one word you can't have on that flag
On that building
Is Emirate
We are upset
It's not what we agreed
And it's going to Karzai flip his lid
Exactly what he shared
Bernie Rubin works in the S rap off
An expert on Afghanistan and pay
And even hard by Holbrook
He was in the air when this happened flying to Doha
Dubai
So I got off the plane
And I seal my Blackberry oh my God
So I was I went directly to the
Embassy
The flag is lowered out of sight pretty fast
But the offending sign is still on the outside of the building
Is there all day
And a tomb is still up
Barney decides to go there to try to find someone to take down the sign
The embassy is short on cars
He gets a ride in some guys private
Arrived at the Taliban office building they're surrounded by armed
Qatari security
The whole thing for a while
So they can figure out who Barney is
What he wants
But he is not leaving until someone shows up
With some tools base
I usually leave till August
Already you stay there and watch them take it down
And then I took a photograph of the
Wall without the sign
And we emailed it
To the US Embassy in Kabul only showed at the prison
But by that time it was too late
Is Jeff Eggers but all it took was
You know the Optics
That one flag being thrown in there
To really derail
At that point years of effort
Dobbins and secretary Kerry fly to Doha
Find out if there's any way to salvage the situation
And to find out why it happened
Dobbins learned is that it seems to be a genuine misunderstanding
The Taliban thought it was fine for them to call themselves whatever they wanted
The Qatari said that
Discussions
Occurred in 2012 or 11
USS said we don't care what you call yourselves you just have to understand we won't call you that now I don't believe any us officials
Said that
But the guitar is believed it
And as I say I think it I think it was
Is a Taliban warrant
Trying to
Demonstrate bad faith
They genuinely believed what they were doing would be unexceptionable
And were I think
Surprised by the reaction
It all could have been avoided as what they
Simon says the arrangement had a whiff of amateurishness
It wasn't even being handled formally by the Qatari foreign minister
Davis Kind of B-Team on it
Bernie Rubin says the office agreement kept changing
To accommodate everyone's concerns
There was never a final document everyone signed off on line by line
Anyway now
The towel that have lost faith
They felt it once
They had been in effect humiliated by having to take down their flag and their sign
That I couldn't go forward
With the talks
So peace talks grind to a halt
I would stay in captivity for another year
And I like simple straightforward people do you want a deal or not
Naats sami yusuf side the afghan reporter
Sammy interviewed someone high up in the Taliban for us
We agreed not to say who it is
This guy told Sammy
After 4 years
1/2 years
Holding bow
They were getting fatigued but it was obvious I believe this was getting too much long did you hear that contain
Echo 2010 or 12 and 13 still nothing was
Cumming Kaiser result
Going to the American is just quiet slow and responding and they told him that we have to bring everything in the knowledge of proper
President Obama and his Nautica
Easy case
I understand so that's why there was like I'm in the kitchen while getting longer and longer
In 2013
The year before but was released
The Taliban have a lot going on
We would know it for a couple of years but mullah Omar the Taliban leader
Who died in Spring of 2013
Melissa Holguin who was in charge of keeping both her most of his time as a prisoner
Was killed in a drone strike
In September of 2013
Sammy says he imagines the pakistanis were also pushing the Taliban to settle this prisoner.
Because they were getting pressure from The Americans
So they're all those reason
And
Ford Thunderbird David's I would say it in Pakistani army operation
The Pakistani army was gearing up to launch attacks in waziristan
Against the Pakistani Taliban
And so people there were on notice
Including the haqqanis for holding bow
You might want to get out of there
Before you get killed
But obviously you know the agony people was told that we are going to do application
So they always be totally abandoned Forest
All kind of medicines
Objectified
King Wok on emu
Some of the motel Palestine in Dino in Afghanistan they could couldn't hide it
Cuz American has access to
Anywhere they want
Yeah
Early in 2014 the Taliban finally let the Americans know
They're ready to make a deal
But not on a peace plan
Instead they tell us
If you just want to swap for your prisoner
We're ready
How is now Cut Loose from the broader talks about reconciliation
He's free-floating
And it's up to us whether to grab him
Ultimately the White House would have to make the call
Jeff Eggers was working at the White House as a special assistant to the president for national
Security affairs
Dresses
They took stock of the situation
And
At around the same time there was
You have some sense that
We were
We were only going to lose opportunities to recover Bergdahl the the more the resources
The Western Coalition resources in Afghanistan decline
We're about to start withdrawing our troops transitioning out of there
This isn't going to get any easier to get him back
The United States and ask for proof of Life video of bow and in January it arrived
I haven't seen it but I've talked to a few people who have
And they said don't look to be in bad shape
Is movements for strange
The speech was incoherent
People told me it was alarming
Edgar says the White House wasn't wearing any other options
Forbetterforworse
And they worried but wasn't going to last in captivity
And the US was getting out of Afghanistan
It was that it was a combination of those factors that gave rise to the idea that
You could
Salvage
Those two line items
The two line items being
We got go back
Big at the 5 Guantanamo prisoners back
Those two line items
In the original
Confidence-building
Camphor for catalyzing
The political process
As a standalone pair
And
But at what once you had 2014
There is no water
Agreement
It's just
It's just the trade
Right well I wouldn't put it that way I would say that the broader agreement was
Sitting up on a Shelf
Gathering dust
Something was better than nothing
Maybe maybe one day someone would take down the rest of the big beautiful agreement to make p
And dusted off
And there be two fewer line items to argue about
Turn off last month before but was released
Has the Taliban started to treat him better
They fed him better more regularly
I got this little treadmill
Gain some strength
He'd already gotten a toothbrush
He said he'd ask for during a video taping
Banana gave him some science book
She also asked for
He said they gave him college-level physics and chemistry books
Us officials including Secretary of Defense Chuck Hagel start making trips back and forth to Qatar
We're not negotiating with Ty about anymore
Or anyone else from the Taliban about it directly
These aren't talks
The transaction
And the qataris are the brokers
We Droppin agreement with the
Guitar is about how they'd monitor the five Taliban were supposed to stay in Qatar for a year
There's this video I watched a few times on YouTube
Treme 26
Memorial Day
Chuck Hagel is visiting Arlington National Cemetery
Hi guys
Vietnam War veteran
Activists
Ipawn Mia cases
Confronts Hagel about bow we're getting out of
I need to get him home
July
He says please sir you got to bring him home
Eagle stands there patiently awkwardly in the Sun
Turn the guy out
Can't say anything except
The next day where comes back from the dod legal counsel
The guy hey go ahead travel to Qatar with
He says
We have a deal
Meaning the Taliban holding bow are good to go
Everything about this transfer was top secret
If it got out they were Ditka
Fall Apart
Somebody could get killed
On May 29th
Delegation
5 people from Qatar comes to Guantanamo to ask with the Taliban guys back to Doha
The qataris talked to each of the Taliban guys
And then
A weight
The deal was that the US wouldn't release them
Until bow was in US
But the Taliban holding bow are taking much
Longer than anybody enter
8 hours later they realize this is not
Happening
At the house the Cutterys in nearby Naval Hotel
Taliban guys they put in a kind of holding cell near the airport
This is not supposed to have
Carol Rosenberg reporter from the Miami Herald
I've been looking out for the Taliban trade
4 years
Carol's been covering Guantanamo since the day it opened
She watched three of these Taliban guys arrive there
Monday 1
Carol was down at Guantanamo at the end of May
She said she noticed these big
Planes 2 C-17
Across the water from where she was
She can just make them out
Squinting across the bay seeing you know the airframes of
C-17s on the airstrip
I'm like why doesn't it leave
Another day goes by
The plans are still sitting there
Now it's May 30th
Girls asking people to base what is going on with these plans
They're saying stuff like
C-17
Finally the morning of Saturday May 31st
The US gets word
The plane leaves for Doha
On it are the qataris
The Taliban prisoners
And US security personnel
According to a congressional investigation when they were planning to transfer
Defense Department officials said he thought the US security would be a good idea
Because they're concerned about quote one of the knucklehead
Trying something
Jim Dobbin said to me about the trade
It wasn't a disaster
And it wasn't a brilliant achievement
It was a successful and necessary operation
It wasn't going to end the war
Which of course is disappointing
And also makes the steel hard to assess
You can easily say wow the Taliban really got a lot of bang for their Buck on this
You look back at the things they wanted at that first Munich meeting in 2010
Well
They got some of their names off the UN sanctions list
Their office isn't official but there is that building in Doha
And they got their prisoners back
From get mono last
And all they gave up with bow
I got a plan to give up all along
Gatherer tired of holding
On Alitalia victory
On the other hand we had to get bow back somehow nothing else had worked and there was no way the end
United States government was going to let an American Soldier died in captivity
Another country's trade all the time
Israel say
Dolce prisoners even for the remains of one of their Soldier
And they're now five fewer prisoners at Guantanamo
President Obama would like to close Guantanamo
Carol Rosenberg what are the things she pointed out was at these 5 Taliban guys hadn't had Intel van
Value for a long time Osama Bin Laden was already dead and also as prisoners they didn't do any
The things you sometimes hear about from getting officials they weren't hunger-striking or gathering up their bodily fluids and cup
Cops and flinging it at the guards
The exception of one they didn't even challenge their detention in federal court
So many others
Detainees have
These guys didn't none of that
They sat there in communal confinement
Following the directions
Praying when there was prayer time eating when it was food time
Sitting there sort of you know when I don't want to like boot up but you know sitting there
Following the rules and not being a problem they were what they would call them here highly compliant
And to me that sounds like
That's like a p o w Wright
There their they're thinking I'm a prisoner of this war and when
Did politics change your the war ends
I'm going to get out of here
Good afternoon everybody
This morning I called Bob and Jani Bergdahl and told them that after nearly five years
In captivity
Their son Beau is coming home
The day the trade right after lunch
Obama appeared in the Rose Garden
Louis Bo's parents
He thanked the service members who recovered bow
He noted that the United States is committed to winding down this war
And closing gitmo
And he gave a shout-out to the erstwhile peace talks
Going forward
The United States will continue to support an afghan-led process of reconciliation
Which would help
Secure
A hard-earned peace
Within a sovereign
And unified Afghanistan
Bob and Jani Bergdahl had been reassured many times over the
Years by many people
Some very high up people
Military and a pentagon
Triple came home
You wouldn't face serious charges
What time with the Taliban would be punishment enough
They probably didn't need to consult a military law
The bird I'll start that day in the Rose Garden
It was over
Mission accomplished
Not quite
Next time
Ontario
Serial produced by
Julie Saturday natividad me and partnership with Mark Bowl Megan Ellison Hugo Lindgren Jessica Weisberg page one and Anna
Carpenter pictures
Our glasses are editorial adviser producing help this week from Jonathan menjivar
Whitney Dangerfield is our digital editor research by Kevin Garnett fact-checking by Michelle Harris copy-editing by Antojitos
Emily Condon is our line producer our music is composed by Nick thorburn Fritz Myers and Mark Phillips
Show is mixed by Kate bilinski
Kristen Taylor's our community editor other cereal staff Zeppelin Dallas Ferguson and Kimberly Henderson
Special thanks this week to David Holbrook and HBO Christopher Chavez Bruce Mason reporter Christina Lamb of the
Sunday Times David Rohde Ari Shapiro and Bizzy Bone
We learned about Carlotta Gall story from her book The Wrong Enemy America in Afghanistan
And the type of Chuck Hagel at Arlington comes from Patrick J Hughes
Got his website Patrick J Hughes. Org
And our website
Serialpodcast.org
Where this week we have a timeline of the Afghanistan peace process
Show me where both story fits in
That serial podcast. Org
Stay tuned for preview of our next episode
The first
Support for serial comes from ADT
You can use the ADT app to monitor your cameras
Video doorbell from virtually anywhere
Visit att.com
To learn more about how
Can design and install York
Backed by 24 cm
Cereals are production of This American Life and WBEZ Chicago
What
President Obama did was
It took a lot of
A lot of intestinal fortitude to make that decision
Coming up
Next episode of serial
I serve the United States with honor and distinction
It's in your face
And he sits on her we need to have a talk about this
I haven't seen
From you or any other journalists a real dig into how the Army came to that
Conclusion