Hello serial listeners
Hurricane Ike year
This week I'm going to do something I haven't done before
Which is duck back into Adnan Syed case for a few days
Report on a court proceeding that's happening in Baltimore
If you have no idea what I'm talking about right now
Quick
Go listen to season 1 of Serial and then come back to me in roughly
10 hours
What's happening this week is not a new trial is a hearing
It's actually a continuation of anions petition for post-conviction relief
That's something you try only after you've exhausted your regular Appeals
The last ditch effort
He first file that petition
How in 2010 I think
Long before I got interested in this case
In fact I think the very first time I talked to a nun was right when the court had ruled against him had denied this petition
But he appealed it
And that's when it started to get interesting
In Broad Strokes Adnan was arguing that his defense attorney at the time of his trial was incompetent
But she made mistakes that were so bad
But he should get some form of relief
Maybe his conviction for killing Hae Min Lee should be overturned
One of those mistakes in unclaimed
Was that his attorney never contacted a potential Alibi Witness
Asia McClain
Remember her
EBay after season 1 of Serial ended some new stuff came to light including some new evidence regarding Asia McClain
And about problems with the crucial cell tower testimony at Adnan trial
And over the past year the wheels of Justice rolled
Slowly slowly like they do
And finally this week
The Baltimore City circuit court will hear this new evidence
We're here with some new Witnesses have to
To say about what happened or didn't happen
Adnan original trial
16 years ago
Right now it's Tuesday February 2nd 2016
The night before the hearing starts
Soon as I'm done recording this I'm getting in my car and driving to Baltimore and I'm going to show up at the courthouse at 8 a.m. tomorrow like they tow
Told me to
And I'm going to watch and listen and I'm going to tell you what happened
That week by week but day by day
I'm fascinated to see who exactly will testify
What they say
How old are you to have all these people back in one courtroom
All right
Now we're going to refresh your memory about the case of Adnan Syed
And then after that it'll magically have turned into tomorrow
And you'll hear me calling my producer Dana chivis
To tell her and you about day 1 of an Ontario
This is a Global Tel Link prepaid call from
Adnan Syed
An inmate at a Maryland Correctional Facility
I definitely
I just and if someone can look at this with a all man you know he must be lying
So coincidental
What did he tell you
She told me that she broke his heart during extremely wrong
Anyone who treated that way
Why would you admit to doing something that drastic if you hadn't done it there is no way that
She was at Best Buy at 2:36
You getting the Charming sociopath you're just not that lucky
Believable
But I think I think you might be that technicality
It is what it is
Hello
Hi
Can you hear me okay
I can't hear you
Are you recording
I am recording I am also recording here in the studio New York so let's
Sound
Hi
Where are you
I'm in a hotel room
I am independent
Posit
Of the hotel room like in night
Got some pillows behind my back then
Either like I'm flanked by the
Two very racy bathrobes
And they're hanging on either side of me
But it's it's it's making a good little
Sound Studio Hair
Like The Classy podcast host you are
Everybody swellegant
So how'd it go
It was
Hi. I found it I found it fascinating I found all of it fast
Yeah like who were the who were the players in there today
Who were the first people who testified in like
Yes
So the first half of the day was
Establishing
Christina Gutierrez Adnan trial
Back in
In the original criminal trial
Had been
Declining in a bunch of ways to physically
Professionally financially
So they were like two attorneys
Who had worked with her
In the from the mid-to-late 90
And you know 99.
Who testified of like how bad it got
And it did seem like it was pretty bad from there
Like that she was
Physical pain
She was passing off
Cases to people
Cuz she was overwhelmed
In the courtroom scene
Definitely not
How she had been which is Kai
Legendary
You know sought-after
Very success
Defense attorney
And that she just was
Like her
Powers were
Definitely waiting
And sort of more to the point
Was
This question of
Why would she not have
I've called
Why would she not have looked into Asia map
Clean as a
Isabel Alibi Witness
Her clients right now
And is that
Is there any
Strategic reason why you would not
Check into
To this person
For her for her not
To call Asia map
Okay
And
And then you know the big witness of the day was
Asia McClain
Tell me about Asia like what did what did she say what was that like
It was
I have to say like it was kind of it was kind of intense in the courtroom when she was
When she was testifying
You know anyways
I don't even know totally how to type but likes
Cereal was a
Heart of her testimony so that's very strange
A little bit surreal like is this happening
Great Moments
When I the way that I first learned about the case right was just like
There's been this miscarriage of Justice like there was this
Key witness who is never heard from and she would have provided the perfect Alibi and
And she was never heard from and it's just like
You know this gross negligence
And so it all remember this like this is how we only have the whole thing was just like we just need to find this girl and find out what she
It will say
Yeah I was like she has a key to this thing over feeling like that
Yeah like this can't be that hard and then we do track her down and then it's it's not
That's simple right it's not at all. Just you
It's so much more complicated than her whatever
Just to see her so strident
In the courtroom
And she's pretty striking looking also she's too beautiful and yeah and she's kind of tall
Very high heels on
She looked
You know very put
Together in
Bright red lipstick and
And
And so it was just it was like wow
There she is
It was just like a lot of drama in the room when she was test
Testifying by the what was the thing she was saying that was
Called English drama
I think because there had been so much
Talk about
And about what she
Might have said would have said
You know parsing everything she said parsing her letters parsing her affidavit
Parsing the stuff that she said to me
And then to just hear her say these
Things that sounded
But very straight
Forward
Which were what
Which are kind of a resting like I don't know she was just saying like
Shih Tzu
She was very sure of herself
And very sure about what you remembered which is like you know this
Same thing we've been hearing right which is like I remember
Yunnan
I was in the library that was on public library after school on January 13th 1999
Starting in about
10:45 or so
I was waiting for hours for my boyfriend
Pick me up he was super late
I was super bored
As soon as school ended I remember I walked in
Send WeChat you know like this whole thing we chatted for 50
1820 minutes
Blink did it land like when she when she died
Glad she seemed very normal
You know and then she said these like very
Idealistic things that
I think that's probably also what
Met people what kind of emotional labor she said I'm trying to find it and they're just so simple the things that she said that she was
Sarah Blake
Anons attorney Justin Brown said why did you want to testify
And she just said I felt for justice to be served
We should put all the information on the
The table I just thought it was
Baidu
I was scribbling like crazy in my notebook I was like to serve the scribblings I was like just
Super focus on writing and so is everyone around it was exposed
In the room but
More I was trying to see what an honest face
Was doing could you see his face from where you're sitting in the back of his head or what
I was trying to see if he was even looking at that who is testifying and
You know I couldn't tell to me it seems a lot like you was just a
Looking down
Looking straight in front of them like at the hospital in front of him he was very very
Still
The entire
RC Willey
Yeah like barely moving like
She would shift
Occasionally but almost like he just became a stone
Deja today on the stands
Was it still was it did you find it was still is compelling what she was
Saying that simple things you had to say was that still has compelling to you now
Today
Hearing her explain her letters like things in her letters that seemed a little like what does that mean
And so she should have went through the letters
So she said
This is this is pretty detailed but there's a part of one of her letters where she says
If you need me like maybe I can help you account for some of your
Unaccounted for time
Between the hours of 2:15 and 8
APM
You know what she says I don't want to get here yet and that's also one of the things
In the original
Eviction hearing
That judge Walsh rules
Noted in his
Opinion where he's staying right just sounds like she's offering to lie
It sounds like she's already with my Saturday with a nod
This is a very big window of time so it what she saying like all the
And so
Anand attorney had her explain like what what do you what do you mean by that and she said oh well I had been to a nun's house
That day
To tell his parent to tell his family like
If you
You know what I knew
And
And they told
Me he was struggling to account
For that afternoon
Like he couldn't really remember what happened after school between school and going
The mosque at 8 around 8 so that was the. Of time so she was saying
I can account for this little slice of it
Of that.
If you need
It's just like she writes the letter in the first place
Yeah
Sprint
Christina we're not interested but it just felt like I got it okay to it all seems like very straightforward and clear
Haha she came out really well for the defense
And we have yet to see what the state's going to do to her tomorrow like that will continue
You tomorrow they started and you could see like they are going to go really hard on her eye
Oh really
Because of how they even started I mean the prosecutor is tough
He's tough
I'm not totally sure what they're what their plan is with Asia but I think
I think what they're going to try to do is
I don't either going to try
Credit her exactly but I think what they're going to say is
You think of yourself as a person with a really poor
Precise memory
But here appear some ways in which we're going to show you that your memory is
Restasis used
I think it is and so
I'm totally speculating here
But to show that if you had gotten on the stand
Back at Adnan
Trial
This testimony wouldn't have worked very well
It wouldn't have changed
Gett the trial
Because he has a permit
Here's all these ways I can
Kohl's in what
You're saying
In your test
Insurgents
Starting to poke holes
He was he wasn't starting to poke holes yet like he didn't get that far but you got late and then we stopped
But he was
Clearly trying to
He was he was sort of laying the foundation
For her
Do not remember stuff
Oh look at the questions that she's going to have to flounder a little bit and then yeah ultimately
Say something with either not satisfying or leg of Camilla X she had to say like I'm I don't remember I'm not sure
I don't remember I'm not clear I could
I could speculate if you want but I don't know I don't I'm not sure and it but and they didn't have anything
Student have they weren't directly related to
Statement it was like
Did you play sports
Yes I did I play volleyball and basketball woke did you have basketball practice that day
Think so I don't
I'm not sure I don't think so though
So you had basketball practice or you didn't know it was like that
But a lot of it all
Just like wow so you think they're doing this because
Do you think they're doing this
To say
You remember you're remembering a different day
I think it's possible that's where they're going but you think maybe that's
The direction they're going in
I think I got any Insurrection I go in if I
All right so you're going back to the courthouse tomorrow it's starting again 9:30 tomorrow morning
All right
So you will check
Back in with me yeah I'll call you tomorrow
All right
Bye