Support for serial comes from ATT
The number one smart home security provider
With a team of 18000 employees dedicated to safeguarding your home
With connection to First Responders
Offering Custom Design Systems including doorbells indoor and outdoor cameras and smart locks and lights
All control from the ADT app or the sound of your voice
And all back
Buy 24/7 protect
Visit att.com podcast
To learn more
One of those lawyers sent a letter to Donald Trump about a week and a half ago
Regarding a possible deposition of trump
We're possible appearance as a witness during Bose court-martial
Dear mr. Trump
A request to interview you as soon as possible
Trump's been doing this bit about Bo On The Campaign Trail I watch video of it
About how crappy the trade was how was a traitor
Are these Taliban terrorists or back in the fight
But how in the old days
We shot people like Bo on the battlefield
How many times has this stupid Ratatat thing with it
What Trump says about Bo is true not in the way Trump
But the audience always give the big meaty Roar when he does it
In the old days deserters Rashad
Ever since I've been reporting this story when I've asked people people on all sides of this thing
What bothers them the most about those case
Gosei
I wish it hadn't gotten so political
Sucks that I got so political
Usually I just know I'd like in politics
Strafer bows just one more thing for Democrats and Republicans to yell at each other about
Then when I really looked at it
I like wait a minute
Was it inevitable
I got this combative
Because
Maybe it could have gone another way
From This American Life and WBEZ Chicago its serial
One story told week by week
I'm Sarah Kane
David trade
President Obama makes this big announcement
Find my Bob and Jani Bergdahl
He hugs and kisses.
And even though the president never called bow a hero
The heft of announcing it at the White House in the Rose Garden
Pump of it has cameras
It felt like the president was communicating something heroic
Triumph
Which if you're someone who served in the military
Maybe someone who went looking for Bose
That message was bad enough
But then
Very next
Day
National Security advisor Susan Rice went on
TV
She was on one of the Sunday news shows
The host George Stephanopoulos
Ask her about though
Finally on this point I start charging for a lot of questions about how we originally was capturing whether or not he had a deserted have left
I his post is that going to be investigated and it was found that he did indeed I leave his post will he be discipline
Lindor's already paid the price
Certainly anybody who's been held
In those conditions in captivity for 5 years is paid and extraordinary price but that that is really
Not the point the point is that he's back
He's going to be safely reunited with his family he served the United States with honor and distinction
And we'll have a map
Wow
Honor and distinction
Talati military people it was like the administration had reached out of their televisions and giving them the finger
Right in our living room
And then it became this like oh he's a hero who served with honor and distinction it what what really made me angry
Facts about
Lester's Auto distinction
That I hit pretty hard
I was irate it's just like
Wait a minute
Some government officials were saying
At the circumstances
Sergeant Bergdahl capture weren't clear
And the soldiers were like
Oh the circumstances are clear he walked away
I feel so shity
We don't really know the truth
That's Mark McCrory who's in Bose battalion
It it took us
You know
Screaming into the internet to to be heard
Some of the guys from Bo's former unit got in touch with each other immediately
Someone started if he's not a hero Facebook group
People started tweeting one of them was Cody full who been in both Batoon
Actually rooms with bow back in training Alaska
He want to talk to me on the record for this story
What is Triscuit the attention of a media guy named Brad Chase and of a guy named Rick grenell a public relations strategy
Jessie's work for some big-name Republicans json Grinnell work together
And they said if you want to go on TV
Get a wider audience for what you want to say
Join me first tonight former Army specialist
Cody full and Gerald Sutton
First stop was Fox News
Cody let me start with you do you believe that Bowe Bergdahl
Deserted
Yes
I do believe he deserted without a doubt in my mind
The other guy on TV with Cody that day was Gerald Sutton
He was also in Bozeman
Is friends with bow
He told me Cody had contacted him and said we had to do something
We help me
Use before jail said he had tried to tell people would have gone down
About walked away
He wrote something on the Internet
Two others had to
He said nobody seem to pay much attention back then
And he worried the same thing would happen now
I didn't think anyone could take a seriously
I guess the reason why we had so many people behind us
Is that if one of us just came out and said it then
People just Glycol used to describe a person so maybe if
The entire platoon came out
And said they aren't that maybe it would be taken seriously for once
By 6 members of Bowe Bergdahl Splatoon guys thank you all so much for being here
2 Days Later Fox again
The timer panel of platoon mates
Soldiers made other TV appearances
CNN
ABC MSNBC
We're hearing a lot about him
From his fellow platoon members
Would you like to see a dishonorable discharge for him
Yes yes he needs to be held
100% accountable for what he did with him in Afghanistan
Is he deserted us
In the middle of Afghanistan Taliban
Among the latest they were a lot more
Like to say
Fitzgerald something again
And more precise and
They seem more entertaining to
With me I'm very Bland
Gerald didn't want to go on any more shows
Anyways limits
And he wanted to stick to the facts
No pinyin no speculation
And I don't want to
Even though it's like 30 seconds Snippets or whatever here in there like I don't want someone just to be like what the fuc
The problem was that maybe Gerald was like Bo a fact-based dude
But he was just no match for the Juggernaut that was now up and rolling
Fox News especially with all over it
In fact just before they had that panel of six guys from seconds
They dared an exclusive report breaking tonight we are learning exclusive and dramatic new details about sergeant
Including reports that he became a Muslim and declared himself a warrior for
For Islam
The story was based on frankly bulshit Intel from a discredited source
But now it was out there
Is repeated
Repeated
Next the politics of it all.
Became the story
The Obama Administration was using Bose trade
Political purposes
Note the right was using this for political
Using these former platoon mates for political
After all Ric grenell the media guy helping them he was a big Republican strategist
Again for guys like Gerald
None of that was the point
They weren't trying to attack the president
Weren't even trying to attack me
Even Cody full and often on the topic of bow
He testified at a congressional hearing
You want to make sure bow was held accountable for what he did
But even he resisted Obama bathing by Republican congressman
If you could say anything to President Obama regarding this trade what would you say
Fair enough mr. Wallace you're forewarned same question
You say that same hearing Mike Wallace also test
He told the committee he was there before them in part because of the Rose Garden
Mike's a lieutenant colonel in the Army Reserves
Former Green Beret
Cuban commander of army Special Forces
He said what I'm lots of missions looking for bow
For that he worked in the bush White House
The special advisor to Dick Cheney on South Asia and counterterrorism
What are red Mike's testimony and Cody
I like all this is because of a 5-minute ceremony in the Rose Garden
Because of how it looked
Ask Mike about that
And kind of schooled me
Are you saying like
But none of us would even be talking about this if
Basically
Do you know
The president hadn't
Done that Rose Garden thing and imma try to politicize it
I will answer I will yeah I mean I mean
It's all about the Optics
Another words or is this like what I mean are you just saying like I wouldn't even be
I wouldn't got in my legs
Feathers ruffled about this if
There had I don't think I can I don't want to speak for anyone else I don't believe that
I would have been
Asvogue
That was that was a
Justin a incredibly tone-deaf move on the part of the White House I think it shows at the it how disconnected they
They are from
Both the Pentagon and I think it is truly lacking understanding the military culture
When you have the National Security advisor
Yoanna civil-military system or them who the military has to listen to
Essentially knife handing on National Television
Sending the signal that this man was honorable
Yo I was afraid that it would all be forgotten in that this was going to be politically swept under the
Carpet
Mike and to a lot of people watching and listening to the president that
It wasn't just what he said
I'm glad those back
We're committed to ending this war
We support reconciliation
We're committed to closing gitmo
It's not just that he said all that
It's what the president didn't say
That's what was glaring
No recognition or even mention of
We understand there were some irregularities or some question about his disappearance
And I want to assure all veterans
All former pows and everyone involved with a search that we will objectively in Fairly get to the bottom of
What happened at a time
Daylight I felt that Justice
Was not going to even be a
Attempted
I've asked many people Lo these many months in other parts of government
What was the White House thank you
Why they do it
And everyone I've asked
I don't know what happened over there that day but
I'm sure they regret it now
I do regret it
Because this Rose Garden event
Picked up so much anger and resentment
Apparently it was put together kind of spur-of-the-moment
What are those things where you like I know let's have a party at the Great
Except big
That mistake
None of it
President speech
The podium the Rose Garden
None of it was the original plan for how to announce his trade
The original plan was a much quieter affair
Don't we talk to me on tape about this but off tape I talked to several people who worked in the White House at the
Time they also very similar stories about what happened that day
So this is their version
Haircuts
Rose rescue operation was touch-and-go for several days
Amber the C-17 sitting and sitting at Guantanamo
It was high wire the whole thing
It all went smoothly in the end
But leading up to it you don't know if the Special Operations guys
Are helicopters going to crash if they're going to get into a firefight
Turn off Bose going to get hurt or killed during the rescue
How to be Stone secret the whole time
The qataris have made it clear that even a word of this gets out beforehand
The deal is off
People in the White House said this might be the last real chance to get bow back
How much of the week before the trade inside the White House
What's the national security offices
They've been working around the clock
If I see the scene in the movie what is it like
Mostly I was sleeping under my desk for 4 days
Chicken curry
That's Jeff Eggers
He was a special assistant
The president for National Security affairs
He's also a retired Navy SEAL he deployed to Iraq he works in Afghanistan
Even helping coordinate those recovery with the dod and the state of
Cuz it started to gain
Momentum that week and it was your are you are you being euphemistic you're sleeping under your desk or you're actually sitting on
On your desk
No I was actually sleeping under my desk will actually is next to my desk
For 4 days
I think
That was also the week that the president made some
Significant
Announcements about trip decisions in Afghanistan that was actually a big week
It was a timing of that just coincidental
Those two really Continental
President Obama had already done a more solemn Rose Garden event that we
May 27th 2014
Announce the big drawdown of troops by the end of the year and a plan to get out of Afghanistan fully by the end of 26
Quotes
Americans have learned it is harder to end Wars than it is to begin them
And now a few days later May 31st
They just gotten word the operation to rescue bowhead work
He was alive he was safe
The National Security folks and the White House Press folks
Knew it was going to be
Lumpy
The snooze
A trading 5 Taliban
It's going to be controversial
But the circumstances of both capture we're going to be a topic
A nail
The people I talk to you in the White House weren't strangers to military culture
How many people who worked on this exchange had been in the military
Carry such as Jeff Eggers
Or had worked closely with military force in war zones
They thought it was important that the president own the decision to make this trade
That explain the policy behind it
So the original plan for how to announce it
Release a written statement from the president
The Pentagon would also release written
At the same time
Done
Well Bob and Jani Bergdahl happened to be in town
They come to DC for some meetings have been scheduled long before with the administration
No one told them this is about to take place their visit to DC was not planned to coincide with those return
Urbana Park playing with some friends little children when they got the call
And it seemed to make sense
They're in town already
Instead of just a phone call the president will see them in person
And now here's where I'd argue there was a blind spot about how all this would look
And that no one in the White House
Catch it
I've been working on this for years
First the talks with the Taliban then the operation.
Well
They met with both parents before some of them
And so what people told me is that for them it's not that they were oblivious
It's just that that day that moment they felt so
Happy
They've been on tenterhooks for days weeks even and now this horrible Saga had come to an unknown and gotten hurt
And you got both parents right there you can see their faces crying
Defecting
Meanwhile there are some very good reporters in Washington
And it Guantanamo as I mentioned
If you have them had known this was going to go down
Butthead held off
Reporting it
Turn out the White House Press people thought
Well we need to placate them
Please.
Because if we have the bergdahl's here with the president
We don't let some photographers catch that scene
Give them was called camera spray
I'm going to be pissed
Terminate let's arrange at least for that
Maybe a shot of President walking and talking with the bird dolls
Man
It was such a sunny day
Such good news for once
Why not
Do the whole thing in the Rose Garden
So in the space of a few hours
It went from a simple statement
To a Rose Garden ceremony
Nedrebo's parents talking at all from the podium
How much was Bob speaking some words in Pashto in Arabic
Does utterly impromptu
As for the Susan Rice thing
Ambassador rice politely decline to talk to me for this story
People I talked to told me
A cringed when she said it
This is talking to the Press is not her forte she got a little defensive
And this cliche tumbledown
Honor and distinction
2 Days Later rice explain herself
Thanks you just meant that volunteering to serve his country in a time of war was an honorable thing to do
By then
Honor and distinction was already caught in Amber
It was going to be any shaking it loose
You're pretty isolated when you work in The West Wing
The one person used to work there told me
You're pretty cut off from the normal workaday world
It's easy to forget how iconic it all is
Columns
Podium with presidential seal
They told me there wasn't a concerted effort to make Bowe Bergdahl into a hero
To whitewash what happened in Afghanistan
I know it looks that way but there really wasn't
Grand political calculus
They were just tired and abuzz with relief
And I thought
Everyone will feel This Joy right
I got carried away
In hindsight one former staffer told me
We should have thought about it more
But there were other audiences
What's worth watching
People who suffer
The Rose Garden put a Target on her back
And this is me talking
I think it also put a Target on Bose back
Just walk with me now
Along this path from the White House
Up the street a ways
Capitol Hill
I swear we won't stay there too long
But this is the next place where the politics of this trade Harden
An intense
Certified
I get it it's Congress
They're in a constant state of Readiness to hate anything President Obama comes up with
But this time
First off no one from the White House or DOD or the state department no one
Told Congress this trade was about to go down
So members heard about it on the news Bass
Basically like everyone else
By law the administration was supposed to notify Congress
30 days
Before any detainee was transferred out of Guantanamo
This time they didn't
And that was on purpose
The White House didn't want members to get mad
And to try to stop the deal from taking place
I hope we can get to the Press
Why did they think Congress would get mad
Well because the administration already knew that Congress. It stunk this
Back in 2012
When the trade was still linked
Peace talks
The Taliban and it really seems like it might go forward
The White House and arrange some classified briefings in
Special rooms on Capitol Hill
Stuff happens barely
And members had made themselves pretty clear at the time
The reactions to a proposed trade 5 Taliban guys
Range from skeptical
Horrified
Princeton's then Senator Saxby chambliss
Republican from Georgia and a briefing of the Senate intelligence committee on January of 2012 almost two-and-a-half
Years before it actually took place
Talking about trading the stylebender
I want to State publicly as strongly as I can
That we should not transfer these detainees from Guantanamo
Sobe ministration worried understandably
That if they brought it up again it'll get crushed
We might not be able to get bow back at all
Decision was made
Don't say anything
So by 2014 a lot of people in Congress assume the deal was dead which was a reasonable thing to think
Is that more or less what they've been told over the years
You can see in
State Department memos
In January and February of 2014 even as a ministration was working to revive the deal
Officials called around a certain offices on Capitol Hill to update certain members of Congress
About the Bergdahl situation
The calls ended with
Quote we told them we would keep them updated and continue to consult before taking any action
But they didn't consult Congress
Cuz your Converse was hearing it on the news
All of that was it was a surprise
Giselle blatant
A blatant and intentional
That's Mac Thornberry Texas Republican
The time of the trade he was a member of the House armed services committee
Notus High School
Now he's the chairman
Ask oversees the Department of Defense and has staffers in the Republican side told me that that relationship with
Tod
Has traditionally been pretty solid
Cooperative
Straightforward
Now they realized. She had been the lead on hammering out this final Bergdahl deal and had told them nothing
For instance
Three and a half months before the trade happened
The Washington Post publish the story quoting unnamed sources
Talk about the five Taliban going to Doha
Was pretty detailed
Ask stuff they said they asked the dod about it
Hey is there anything to this
And they said they were told
Nope
It's possible
Probable
Actually that the person they called wasn't lying
They weren't in the know
Meanwhile emails are singing among all these other government officials who are in the know
Quote who's leaking this very accurate info
These leaks are killing us
We need to talk about getting control back
Tony blinken at the White House sent one around about his dismay and disgust over the week since it could derail the deal quote
Simply put whoever is responsible should look him or herself in the mirror and ask
By what right did I jeopardize the life of a fellow American
Here's Thornberry again
We had specific questions you know why these press reports right
They denied
Denied it
In looking back
Now we know that in
Some instances they were too cute by half
By saying well we're not in negotiations today
When the guy was about to get on a plane and go to the Mideast to have negotiations tomorrow
What he's talking about is a congressional Hearing in late April just a month before the trade
State Department official was asked about efforts to recover bow
And he gives his kind of cryptic update
He says
Agencies across the government we're striving
In the most quote energetic and creative ways we can devise unquote
To secure Bose release
Unfortunately the Taliban broke off direct contact with us in January of 2012
We would very much like to return to direct contact with them and if we do at the top of our agenda will be Sergeant Bergdahl
It is certainly not the case as was reported that somehow
It's how that my Connie Network are seeking to release him and and that
Interagency squabbles within the United States government are
Preventing or delaying
Thank you very much
That same guy
Weather in Doha by the next day
From eating
About the Bergdahl trade
The administration wasn't exactly forthcoming with Congress
On the other hand it was an open hearing
And he's talking about a deal so fragile
He doesn't know if it's going to fall apart like the others before it
Regardless
Once Hask staffers on the Republican side went back and traced exactly what they were and weren't told
What's a investigated the whole trade
Issued a strongly-worded report about it
That report then entered the political Fray
Democrats called it an expression of shrill demagoguery
Accused the Republicans of using the tray to push their National Security agenda
Republicans accuse Democrats of exactly the same thing
I talked to some Hask staffers
Again on the Republican side about this whole thing
And they sounded to me surprisingly
Genuinely upset by what had happened to their ones collegial relationship
What's Tod
If that's going to be the relationship going forward
Then
There is nothing but can we rely upon
But they are telling us about any given issue
Like you just feel like you don't trust those guys anymore
Yes
Is this a big like I says the Big E that you've seen where you're just like I cannot believe
How this went down or is this just like oh my God there's like
This happens 3 times a year on different things
We view this is unprecedented
The staffer said
We're not just foot-stomping here that you guys didn't tell us
Actually a profound concern about
National Security risk
And the risk to
Particular our forces deployed overseas in Afghanistan
So
We're worried
She's talking about the Taliban five
They felt like the president and the dod had done an end-run around the approval process
Just forget Mo transfer
Encino
Who are these 5 Taliban guys anyway
How can we trust you that they're safe to release
But they won't rejoin the battle
Who signed off on this
This part of the fight over Bose trade
I want to talk about it for a minute because it mirrors a deeper bare-knuckled fight
Over Guantanamo
President wants to close Guantanamo
Most republicans in Congress
Even though President Bush wanted to
They've opposed the idea since Obama took office
And what are the arguments they make
Is that some of the prisoners we released from gitmo have rejoined the fight
Industrial
Most heaven
So it's a fair question right what about these five Taliban guys
Were they safe to release from Guantanamo
There's probably nobody including the military who knows the ins and outs of gitmo better than Carol Rosenberg from them
Miami Herald
I'm actually asked military people questions about Guantanamo
And they referred me
Carol Rosenberg
Explain that these five guys were what's known down there as forever prisoners
They hadn't been cleared for release
And I hadn't been and wouldn't be charged with crimes
But they also weren't going through the administration's new review
An interagency board meant to assess each detainee who is still down there
And figure out whether they could be cleared for transfer or should still be held
By all accounts this review process is a much more rigorous and we're rational look at the intelligence that has been done in the past
Again these Five Guys
Weren't on the list
Review
There's Carol
Three of these guys got there on the first day you would have thought that they'd get the first reviews
But they didn't
And I'm watching through the years why aren't they reviewing these guys why aren't these reviewing the
Disguise
When I started asking questions really early why are
Betrayed
What do you think they're trying to push them through the board to get him in position
And then they're not they're not and I'm like
I wonder if they think that they intelligent people won't clear them
Right
Got it
Right if you have it on paper
That it would look even worse for the President right
Yeah
Imagine if they been rejected for released by the board
And the USA traded them anyway
Since there wasn't a review we don't have in any public way at least
A recent intelligent assessment on these Five Guys
However I talked to someone who should know
That guy Nathan not his real name
You heard him back in episode 5
He's a guy who is close to the recovery effort for bow and it worked with both parents
Nathan is not a lefty
He's former military and he was an Intel Analyst at gitmo
The specialty was afghanistan-pakistan
He did two stints in Guantanamo for a total of 3 years
Ending in 2013
So he knew all about these Taliban guys
Is office equipment was a stone's throw from where they were being held
Nathan Radley admits that he's biased and surprised you wanted to come home and he was working for that very goal
But he was not happy about this trade
He doesn't hate it like a lot of his peers in the MLS world you just wishes it hadn't come to that
The only option left for the president was this getmoe option
It wasn't the political will to do anything else
He also thinks
These Five Guys
They're okay to release
They're being watched closely in Qatar their high-profile so they can't hide everyone knows who they are and what they look
Nathan says there's just not much they be able to pull off even if they want it
The value to the Taliban in Afghanistan he said
Is pretty much limited to a rallying cry
You know was very familiar with them and honestly
I didn't feel that it was that big of a danger to relieve so I really didn't
No not even that sort of guys
Nori and and Fazal who were the
Kind of
Biggest fish it seems like
Yeah yeah definitely
They're not going to be that they're not going to trouble trouble it's
Because
You know
We let them be trouble cuz we drop the ball on you know keep an eye on them
Do you feel like you guys had
Clear door
I know it's not your job to clear someone for release but had recommended release
Forehead seeing people released
Hoover on par with these guys
Sure sure yeah and you know we've released
But yeah I definitely would definitely release them
Not so good guys that were
Supposed to be
I'm in love with you guys
Right so it's like you didn't see the names and just like
Freak out like I
And there's only like one or two people that get mailed it would freak me out if we
That's going to be a problem going to be a problem
But it's but you're being serious like they're really only a few who
You know and
And frankly
We got it we got to do something when you get mold I'm leaving gitmo
They would have laughed anyway if you know at least we
Made use of them
Yasso
The heart reaction to this trade
Nathan says he understands it
But he also says
It's not exactly based on the fact
Leave the anger over releasing those guys comes down to a lot of the same reasons why people are
You know it's still mad at bo4 walk out the basic it's it's it's very personal thing like you don't
I think they feel very strongly about what these guys have done
And we know what kind of people they are and
You don't negotiate you don't make trades
You know so they're wrapped up in a larger moral question
Obama releases Five Guys
Congress didn't like
To be clear Congress doesn't get a vote on individual get mode transfers like this
They're just supposed to be notified
Right after the trade the White House explained that the Secretary of Defense
Had followed all the requirements
For the detainee transfers
Got the 30-day notice could have endangered bows life and that they believe the president had the Constitutional thought
Authority to make this decision
But disagreed all around Republicans and Democrats
Administration I pulled a fast one by not giving the 30 day notice
And the government accountability office which is non-partisan
Found that the dod broke the law by doing the transfer the way it did
Which that happens sometimes
President Obama's definitely not the first to claim executive power in order to make a move like this
But when a president does that rankles Congress tends to push back with whatever power it has
In this case
One way to do that get no legislation
So here's a fairly tangible effect of the trade for bow
There's this massive annual defense bill
Put together by the House and Senate armed services committee has decided for the past 5 years
Is language specifying what the Secretary of Defense has to do before he can sign off on any foreign Tran
Answers of gitmo detainees
After the trade Republicans decided to change that language to make it harder to transfer
Anyone Adam Smith Democrat from Washington State
Was one of four lawmakers trying to come to final agreement on that bill last year
I talked to him over the summer when he was still in the thick of arguing with Republicans over the harsher transfer
Smith has been a big proponent of shutting down gitmo
Can I were both on the phone when I asked him about it both of us traveling in cars actually so the tape isn't great
How much is the the Bergdahl trade for the Taliban
Does 5 Taliban guys
It is that a shadow over what you guys are doing right now and how big is shadow
It's a pretty darn big shadow
I don't think we would be having the discussion of further foreign transfer restriction
Really well
Republican Mac Thornberry
It was also one of the four lawmakers negotiating that Bill said it's true
Bergdorf thing
Corrosive
They were not going to budge on that stricter standard for letting people out of gitmo
No there's no question
I mean it was a direct result
The Bergdahl trade
And
The not telling Congress the truth
Another result less tangible Maybe
Is it outrage and suspicion over the trade
Spilled over onto Bo himself
June 11
The house armed services committee held up at hearing on the bird.
At the start of this hearing I'm pleased to welcome members of the public who have such an interest in these
Proceedings
Chairman open by saying we are not going to talk about Bergdahl personally
Let me be clear up front on the focus of today's hearing
It is not my intention
The dive into the circumstances
The parents of
Horse it came up
Testifying before the committee with defense secretary Chuck Hagel
He had to answer all the who knew what when questions that were pissing Congress off
Representative Jeff Miller Republican took a turn at the mic
Did you or did you not notify Congress within the 30-day time frame yes or no
No
Okay yes or no
Mac miller started asking questions about Bo
Stoughton American Military Hospital in Germany
And what we are doing is we are allowed
Wait a minute
Why hasn't even returned to the United States we have
Seriously wounded soldiers
Better return to the United States
Almost immediately after they are stabilized
How long did Jessica Lynch
Wait before she was returned to the United States you're trying to tell me that he's being held at Landstuhl Germany
Because of his medical condition
Cars but I hope you're not implying anything other than that
The question Mister secretary
Answer it
The implication
I think
Was it maybe something fishy was going on with bow
Something embarrassing to the Army
The baby this Bergdahl fellow
An American soldier who made just brought home at enormous cost
I walked off to join the Taliban
And now they were hiding him away in Germany
Hegel fended all of this off
This isn't just about a physical situation Congressman this guy was held for almost 5 years
And God knows what kind of conditions we do know some
Other conditions from our intelligence Community not from by-the-way Bergdahl
This is not just about Kenny get on his feet and walk and get to a plane so you're telling me she cannot be questioned because of
His condition I'm telling you is that the the medical professionals
So what was going on in Germany
An Army hospital in Landstuhl was undergoing this really pretty profound transition
The official word for it is reintegration
First imagine every single thing is weird for him
You can't talk really
He's blinking and squinting
For five years he had only a few things
A bowl
A blanket a water bottle
He says his mind adapted to the Simplicity of that
Now all the sudden they're all these people he's got to interact with them
It's all the stuff around
Furniture he's not used to
Princess one of the first things that happen
Is a bring him into this room
PenAir chairs sofa
And I tell him wherever you want to sit down is fine
Squatted down and talk down in the Indians
Until all these commanders they follow suit
Everybody was sitting down on the floor and were talking like Captain
For the senior community
That's the military
Survival evasion resistance and Escape training
This moment
Getting back
Gow who been held
That long alone
Survive
Who is huge
Hadn't happened since Vietnam
Military I've been practicing for Bose return for months
4 years real
They cleared out to entire wings of lunch till 4
And One Wing would be bo in a few CFO
Any other weighing all the Intel administrative people the Commanders
Computers
Who is interacting with just a small team
But everyone involved is so
Over-excited
All these commanders and Sykes her supposed to take over when Beau gets to San Antonio
They all showed up in Germany
Hangout
Sit around in the hospital Wing nothing to do
Apparently one psychologist from Europe arrived on his own dime
Offering his services
They said the poor guy away
One person who was on the Germany team told me that all these people
It was like they wanted to behold bow to meet him
But they wanted to touch the stone
I spoken to several people who are involved with bows reintegration and debriefing
They told me it was all planned down to the smallest detail
How to walk boat from the plane to the bus that would take him to the hospital
How to speak to him explain exactly how the day was going to go
Google, 10 there's a strategic debriefing at 1 is that okay
It's not okay we don't have to do it you want your food at 11 that's okay too
By giving me complete control over everything asking me everything even if
Are you comfortable sleeping in
Couldn't really talk yet
But you had to let them know
He was not comfortable sleeping on the bed
His body was in pain especially the spots that have been in contact
With the floor for so long
But somehow he couldn't deal with the softness of the bed either
Pause the hospital bed was out in the open
Open on all sides in a row
Somebody
Get ready to get to me
Uneasy feeling so what I had to do with that the move over by the bathroom where there was like a little hallway
First night I slept in the bathroom because there's a door
Also distance between
Room and the bathroom so I knew that there is
That allowed me to
Hear footsteps coming
You didn't end up being a model Soldier
But he been by all accounts a model p o w
And now a model returning
Cooperative
Eager to be helpful
To see her team to the until the briefers
He participated in debrief
4 weeks
His progress was being watched very very closely by lost
People
Especially at the Pentagon
Everyday all the questions
All the follow-up question
The until people were asking him
They had to clear them
All the way up to the Joint Chiefs and then all the way back down again
Team is updating all these muckety-muck
Socom centcom jpra video Everyday
And the muckety-mucks are asking
Is Bode telling the truth does he have Stockholm syndrome and he really trying to help us
All reasonable questions
Again it seemed as if the people dealing with bow in a daily way had such a different
Softer view of him than the higher-ups.
One-point Princeton
Someone gave him a compass
Illinois septic pump
Before
One person told me that when the Army Chief of Staff found out
He went quote f****** Ballista
I would you give a deserter a compass
I had to take it away
About a week and a half after Bill came to Germany
The same time that members of Congress made it clear publicly
Not hearing with Chuck Hagel
But they're also watching this process very closely
Wait a minute
Why hasn't even returned to the United States
Where comes down at launch Tool they got to speed it up
Food along to San Antonio the Army wanted him back wanted more command-and-control over there soldier
The still unknown entity who is an ocean away
Next Spartan launch Tool where like wait a second
Is a former Air Force sere psychologist who's in charge of the site team for part of bows reintegration
It really started feeling like it wasn't about the reintegration Persei anymore you know it wasn't about his overall
All well-being it was much more to start becoming really political and administrative
I just felt like wrong you know and we would have liked to have
Maybe had him stay a little bit longer but there were other competing
Pinterest
Who is there in Germany told me they start seeing these charts about bow with categories for medical side
Like an Intel colors red yellow or green green not cleared they got the picture
I had to show progress they're supposed to set specific goals for BO2 jazz is Bergdahl able to deal
Show with negative media attention
Navigate for
They need to brief the commanders to report whether they were meeting their targets every day more and more green box
Has turned up on the charts
Chris Carter bringing bo back to the modern world was letting him know
Gently and he become popular
Baldinos has been in contact with no reason
I talked about this
She didn't know that he was on TV
He didn't know that this was
That he was the subject of
National-interest he didn't know
At his parents
Had been on
Met the president
So weird to know not only like
Does the whole country know about you
But then yeah
Like it's it's not
Are there aren't having parades
Yeah I know he
It was it was really hard it was really hard because there was so much of it coming
So fast
And it was all bad
Like telling somebody that and just
So how do you prepare somebody
It's gone through something like he did and let them in and by the way let him know hey dude your home
You can relax now
As soon as you walk out that door get ready cuz there is a
There's a shitstorm
You know and it's not going away anytime soon
Back to the Congressional hearing with Chuck Hagel
One last time
Representative Jim langevin
A Democrat
Agreed that questions about Sergeant murdo's conduct should be addressed
The due process at the appropriate time
But he asked Hagel
Could you at least answer this one thing
But could you settle one
Booking report at least in terms of regarding
The number of the loss of soldiers who may have been involved in searches for
Sergeant Bergdahl
Riddle started by noting that any soldier who dies is a terrible loss to their family into their country
Mini got down to business
I knew this was coming
I personally gone back
Can ask that question inside the Pentagon
In the army
In all of our reports
I have seen no evidence
That directly links any
American combat
Death
The
Rescue or finding or shirts
I'm Sergeant Bergdahl
Hagel said it once
Right away
He said it again
. ask a question
We will ask the
I have seen no evidence
No facts presented to me
I want I asked that question
Hegel had to know that question
Was the consequential heart
Apus story
Did anyone die looking
And I have to think he also knew that his answer would not settle this
Nobody Longshot
Soldiers were talking about it
Commanders like Mike Waltrip
Testifying
The people did die looking
That's part of what was so going to them about the Rose Garden in the first place
Weren't those families being recognized by the
I asked Mike Walton
Why is the Army saying the opposite
What you're saying
Why are they saying nobody died in the search
I'm not sure who did the investigation I'm not I haven't seen
From you or any other journalist a real dig into
How the Army came to that conclusion
What did they look at
What was the basis of that statement
I don't know I can only speak to my own experience
Okay then
What's find a journalist
Kuwait
We're journalists
One of our staff Whitney Dangerfield on this question
Has there been an official investigation into whether people died looking for Bo
Is there a record of people who got injuries looking for Bo
She started with army public affairs
And they told her to ask forscom US Army Force
Command
A guy there appointed her to the investigation by Army Major General Kenneth Dahl
The general doll he didn't look into this question whether people died or got hurt in the search
That wasn't his mission
Adhering on Bose case in September Rose Attorney asked all about
I don't said he'd heard a lot of discussion about it and his own interviews and just in a press
Allegations one way or another
But he didn't pursue it
He said he was told quote
No you don't need to do that
Because Central Command is going to
Okay interesting
So Whitney went to Central Command centcom
In sent cam wrote back to her
There is no official report or investigation that we are aware of directed or conducted by us
I would direct you to the US Army for any records they may have
So Army to forscom
Which sent her back
The army
Also known as Square One
Unless we're missing something the US Military
Hasn't done an official investigation into whether any soldiers died
Because they were looking for both
Here's the other thing General doll said about this question
When he was on the stand back in September
He said quote
I had asked the appointing authority you know should I invest
To get this because really this is something that
At the end of the day
It's going to have to be answered
I mean if I was a parent I would want to know
Everybody should want to know
We really ought to close that out
Yeah
Angry
Next time
En Serio
Cereals produced by Julie Schneider Dana Chivas and me and partnership with Mark Bowl Megan
Nelson Hugo Lindgren Jessica Weisberg page 1 and Annapurna pictures
Ira Glass is our editorial advisor Whitney Dangerfield is our digital editor research by Kevin Garnett and additional research
This week by Benjamin Phelan
Fact-checking by Michelle Harris copy-editing by anaheed Alani
Emily Condon is our line producer our music is composed by Nick thorburn Fritz Myers and Mark Phillips
She was mixed by Kate Polinsky Christian Taylor's our community editor other cereal staff Southland at least Ferguson
And Kimberly Henderson special thanks this week to Carol Giacomo Jeff Melman and Rachel Hammerman our website
Serial podcast. Org where this week you can watch the Rose Garden video and you can look through some of the emails government
Officials were sending to each other in the months before Bose recovery
Again that's serialpodcast.org
Stay tuned for preview of our next
Episode the first
Support for serial comes from ADT
You can use the ADT app
To monitor your cameras
Video doorbell from virtually anywhere
Visit att.com pot
To learn more about how I can design and install your cussed
Smart Home
Back by 24/7
Serials production of This American Life and WBEZ Chicago
Coming up on the next episode of serial
It's certain there is no doubt in my mind
That you are soldiers died looking for Bowe Bergdahl
I want to let you know we're fixing to break this story people are going to get hurt people are going to get killed
And I just see the first truck
Just explode what was the mission