Serial season 3 is presented by ZipRecruiter
The smartest way to hire
Leader in the brake you hear from someone who runs a growing coffee company
ZipRecruiter is rated number one by Employers in the US
Based on hiring sites with over 1000 reviews on trustpilot
ZipRecruiter for free
A different router. Com serial
Support for serial comes from Squarespace
Make your business official with Google in Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and a Business website with Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and professional tools from Google
It's the simplest way to look professional online
Visit squarespace.com Google
To start your free trial
And use offer code professional for a discount on your first purchase
Google and Squarespace
Make it professional make it beautiful
The Justice Center in Cleveland Ohio takes up a whole city block downtown
It's a cluster of concrete towers built in the 1970
I can head here but I'm just going to say it
The buildings are hideous
Practice
Justice Center houses in one location everything at justice system needs
The city and county courts the county jail Prosecutor's offices Sheriff's Office
And headquarters for the Cleveland Police
Roughly speaking the building functions like most hierarchies
Vertically in this case from the bowels up
The main court tower is 26 stories high
To the elevator really runs the play
The persons arrested in Cleveland are coming into the Justice Center from the basement
Weary cops escort suspects from the underground parking garage
Booked
Apache floors to the jail
Once I get a court date the writing up to one of the courtroom
The lower floors are for lesser crimes less hollowed proceedings misdemeanors housing court
The higher floors starting about halfway up the building are felonies
Detectives wearing lanyards off and get off on the 9th floor for the prosecutor's office is the court stenographers
Always courteous drag their squat wheelie cases on and off the elevator
Navigate chat for a few floors with the officers from the sheriff's department in search of a coffee and a muffin
Defense attorneys are riding up and down all morning muttering to each other can you believe
Griping about Judges
Elevators are not over hearing
Elevator Mainstays of course are Crime Victims
And their families
And defendant
Their family
Sometimes
Those families are one in the same
I'm feeling optimistic
I appreciate that an elevator car and a government building is one of the few places left in our country where different kinds of people
Are forced into proximity
I like to think that we can all stand so close to one another
What are sensible heels and Timberland boots and American flag lapel pins and fake eyelashes an Axe Cologne and Orthopedic insert
Teardrop tattoos in to go coffees
And when the elevator doors open up
Spilling us out onto our floor
The fact that no one is bloody tarieven Interiors
The small pleasing reminder that we're all in this together
Other times the shoulder-to-shoulder closeness only magnifies the obvious
We're not the same
Got it all
Coming up from the lobby one morning
Young black woman is holding a little portable speaker
The white people in the elevator give each other
I don't want to reciprocate their looks
Instead I decided to my duty to break the tension by saying the lamest thing I possibly can
To be clear that wasn't my plan
Just what came naturally to me apparently
Soundtrack for the elevator
Just even bother with it this time
Now I keep my head down
The weather looks the black people are probably giving each other
This place is primarily black and white
The majority of the courthouse staff is black
Clerks are mostly black
What's their managers are white
In the sheriff's department most of the sea
Security guards are black
Most of the deputies
Are white
Most of the attorneys are white almost all the county judges are white and their bailiffs are white
Most of the defendants and Crime Victims
Are black
In the Cocoon of the elevator everyone's polite to each other
Pretends nothing is weird about this
But if the elevators were calibrated to detect a power imbalance in the load
Like a socially-conscious clothes dryer
Baby perpetually on the fritz
From This American Life and WBEZ Chicago it's cereal
Courthouse told week by week
Entertaining
If you listen to serial before you probably know that our first season was about a murder case in Baltimore
Ever since that story aired people that's me and people I work with
Question
What does this case tell us about the criminal justice system
Fair question
And to answer I usually say
Because the answer is that cases like that one there not with filling Americas
Cortland everyday
The defendant in that case
Adnan Syed
Was charged with first-degree murder
Kid never been in trouble before
His family had an expensive defense
Attorney
And rarest of all his case went to trial
It lasted 6 weeks
None of that is typical of the vast majority of cases moving through the criminal courts in this country
And even if it were I don't think we can understand how the criminal justice
System works by interrogating one
Extraordinary case
Ordinary cases
Are where we need
We need to spend at least a year
Watching ordinary criminal justice in the least exceptional most middle-of-the-road most middle of the country place we could find
Cleveland
When I first began reporting this story I called the former US attorney there for advice
Explain what I want to do
He said Cleveland's not a bad choice
And then he said
Please don't be mean to Cleveland
You can be mean to the criminal justice
System but please don't be mean
To Cleveland
I told him I didn't plan on taking cheap shots at the mistake by the lake
Because I'm a classic
Recorder
Anyway we could have gone to lots of cities and the problems would look about the same
Minneapolis or Atlanta or Pittsburgh or Sacramento
Same sorts of crime same struggle for fairness
Attempts at reform
Who scored so it's really hard to record
You might need permission from the states
Supreme Court hello Illinois
Another place is recording of any kind is Barden courtrooms
What is your
Problem Pennsylvania
Cleveland OH
They let our producer manual joji and me wander the courthouse
Unencumbered
With microphone
Extraordinary
We spent more than a year in the Justice Center
Following criminal cases of all sizes
Tiny ones reporters don't usually pause over
Like weed possession or driving under suspension
Have your cases
Assault armed robbery
The most serious crime there is
Aggravated murder
Every case Emmanuel and I followed
There came a point where we thought
No
This can't be how it works
I never liked
Oh
Oh my God
This is how it works
This is how it happened
People have been through the system work in the system maybe they know what I'm talking about
Millions more don't know
This season we're going to tell you the stories of the cases we followed
Sometimes they're going to overlap they might span two or even three episodes
You'll see what we saw
From the inside
First case we're going to talk about is small
It's a bar fight
We're starting with this one because it's a simple
It is also an example of the system work
I want to show you what that looks like in this Courthouse
Teva Baseline for what's considered functional Justice in Cuyahoga County
So
Here we go
A bar fight walks into a Justice Center
Let me show you this video I want to get your impression of it
One morning last spring Russ bensing defense attorney
Take me to little side room off the hallway on the 20th floor of the Justice Center
You want to tell me about a case he's got
I'm calling the defendant Ana
Is not her name
She's charged with assaulting a police officer which is a 4th degree felony
Russ's drafting me until one person focus group here
He wants to know whether an outsider like me will interpret the video the same way he does
I just stand in for a juror
Okay so just explain what we're looking at okay this is the surveillance tape of the bar this incident occurred in a bar
There she is right
Lower left
Corner
Yeah yeah long hair
Annie's White young looking small
She's wearing librarian glasses skinny jeans
Boots and a t-shirt that fits her just so
Even in this terribly granny video she's attractive
She's leaning on the corner of the bar
She is
And she somebody approaches
The Greer
And smack your ass
That what you just did
And I had gone out that night with her friend and some other guy to a small Corner Bar on the westside of Cleveland
When I met Anna she told me it's not the sort of place usually hangs out
It was our first time there
Just a little rougher people are there older people
Cheater girlfriend noticed these two women down the bar looking at them
I just noticed her and other girl like constantly staring at us but we still stay there for about an hour
And that's when
Did they talk to you right now no
It was why were they looking
I have no idea
I personally think it's because we were pretty
So I go and get a drink and
This guy is smack me on my rear end
And
The guy you have been talking
No just some random guy at the bar
Are you serious was a random guy
I figured you knew that guy
No I did not know him
Messages
Cuz men are dogs
They can be dogs
And I
You know at first I was like haha you know stop
And then
He kept doing it and I actually got mad and I you know I got in his face and in the surveillance video there's
A perfect view of all this
First one guy touches her butt and lets it go
But a second guy touches her but she pushes him back and playful way
Then the first guy starts in again hitting harder
Smacking her ass
3 * 4 * and it turns lips are footed M as in cut it out he stops R6
Find her a police officer walks slowly onto the screen he's not seeing any of the slapping Heat
Just come from the bathroom downstairs they've been working on the Block and come in the bar to pee meanwhile back at the counter
Smack the guy has anima 7th time and it spins around to confront the ass clapper
At that point one of the women who'd been staring at Anna from down the bar stocky blond she storms over to Anna
Gets between her and the a slapper and immediately gets into it with Anna
This is what Russ wanted me to say
Hannah was provoked
Other Woman answers
The picture frame
And they start arguing and then they go out at
It's not clear if anybody threw the first punch or what but Anika's decisively for the ladies throat
And then it's just a mess
The people around them are trying to break it up but it is not stopping she's thrashing around she could swallowed up in the crowd
Bunch of people
Knock it to the ground where this person picture
Oh my God
Well
All these boozy patrons are piling in people are grabbing and has long hair and her head is getting yanked around
Countries pull to the floor
It's awful to watch
The most disturbing woman to me is when the blonde ladies friend
Takes off her eyeglasses places next to her beer
Readies herself by sweeping back her hair and then she doesn't just kick Anna she gives her a ferocious stomp like she
Trying to kill a rat
And it gets back up or maybe she's dragged back up I can't even tell if she's fighting anyone in particular anymore
And later tells me she's got the heart of a fighter but maybe not the skills
That looks about right
Someone behind Anna's got his big arm around her neck
Can I see the cop
There's a cop right there
People are still grabbing her
Is flailing
There is where she swings
And hits
And hits the cop
Looks like she got some on the left side of his face
Then the cop who's a big dude
He's on top of her
Take her to the ground cops are
After that it's four nights in the Cleveland City Jail
$5,000 bond to get out in a fourth-degree felony charge
Assault on a peace officer
The video ends
So
You're on a jury you see that you can Victor
No I wouldn't convector
I mean I don't think I would
Just technically she connected with the cops face but to me it looked accidental
That is the answer was hoping for a solid not guilty for his client
Better yet he like a not-guilty tenants with righteous indignation which I can also provide
How does a video we just watched add up to a felony charge
A young woman tries to stop a man from hitting her ass
She's been verbally and possibly physically attacked by some puffed-up buttinsky from down the bar
End up fighting for all she's worth defending herself all 110 lb of her
Against the pack of strangers
Cop stops and she hits him from the looks of it by accident
The cop is not injured by the way and is the one who ended up scratched and bleeding
I get the bad behavior abounds in this episode and Anna's included
Felony assault
To become a spelling for this
That cannot be right
Russ thinks it's not right
You think that the system got this one wrong
Transkei should not be happening at all
He tells me today his plan is to go big
I know that they offer me a misdemeanor assault on
In this case
But he doesn't want to settle for a misdemeanor assault on this one
He's got the surveillance tape
Which way is like a closed circuit morality play
He feels like that alone ought to be strong enough evidence to force of course correction on the part of the state
To undo what's already been done
China's race
Whiteness is not really part of his calculation here but at least it doesn't work against her
After many decades in this business Russ says he's accepted to shameful truth that as a general rule and never help
Abs2b black
It never hurts to be white
So today I'm going to try to see if the Stapleton
Dismiss the charges
Okay
He's going to ask the prosecutor to drop the whole thing
This is what I've come here to see
Houses adversarial system going to turn now
How's it going to play out
Russ gathers his stuff we leave a little conference room
I follow him as he goes to look for Anna he told her to be at the courthouse this morning by 9
Siri are you doing what's your guys doing
Shannon Russell Bennett Attorney for 41 years
He's head of the Cuyahoga criminal defense Lawyers Association that's how I met him I went to a meeting of the group and Watchtower
All these people rushed him afterwards
As if you were wearing a pin that said when your case now ask me how
It's like that all the time with Ross
He walks around the Justice Center and people just come out in for advice
Ping pong in the details of their cases off of them
Attorney Krause in the hallway
So my guy was caught transporting the two kilos from Chicago to Cleveland he says
Okay but he doesn't admit to being the guy that made the secret Apartments
Yeah yeah okay Russell say rocking a little on his heels
Wearing the coins in his pants
Then Hillside the case while they need or the new ruling out of the 8th District I hadn't heard about
Russ has no personal secretary no law Clerk
Just him
You like the action here Alexa kibitzing
I need the master of doleful TGIF Courthouse red party
Die here something about Justice
And this building
I like Russ
The colleagues like him too
Not clear whether his clients like him
He can sometimes be a bit of an asshole to his clients
Actually they call him all day long
I didn't show up at the courthouse today and is confused about where he's supposed to go
Rust-Oleum
To the Justice Center
Where the court is
You've been here before
What
You don't have a warrant you don't have to get down here okay
What's the defense attorneys in this building R Us has some paid client
He also has a lot of assigned clients
People who can't afford to hire a lawyer so the court provides one
That's how they do it in Cuyahoga County
30 to 35% of indigent defendants get a public defender
The rest are assigned to private attorney
Like Ross
Russ is the difference between how he treats his paying clients and his non-paying clients
Come down to hand holding
The actual lawyer in part is the same he says
What is bedside manner change
The paying customer but he might visit them in jail just to check in make sure they're doing okay
He's not doing that with an assigned client
I'm guessing a paying client
He's not talking to them like this tell you what Mike
Okay
I've been doing this for 41 years I'm going to be willing to bet that I can do a better job of researching the law that
And you can't so let me take that weight off your shoulders
He hangs up
F****** believable
Anna is also in the same case
But so far she hasn't annoyed him is nice to her
He beats her up on the 20th floor
She's sitting in the waiting area under the TV
There's one on every floor
Set to the Food Network
Always
Anna looks small and nervous
I'm not allowed to record their meeting that would violate attorney-client confidentiality
Wrestling Turtle conference room so we can explain what's happening today
Pre-trial conference
Sounds formal but it's not
What means is that rest will track down and his prosecutor and they'll have a quick conversation about the case
And it was going to get to be there for it
She just has to sit and wait under the TV for us to report back
I don't know whether Anna knows this yet but rest for sure knows it
Prosecutors will almost always pursue a case that involves a cop
That's the way it is
Law enforcement code
The next time I see Russ he's eating a piece of carrot cake that was on offer in a judge's Chambers
He's had his pre-trial with the prosecutor on Anna's case
I made the mark
Request for dismissal
Meaning rest ask the prosecutor to drop the case
Santana
She said
That was laughable and
Power probably be marked with a felony
Probably be tried
When she wouldn't even knock it down to a misdemeanor to a misdemeanor assault
What she doesn't have the power to do anything she has to take it to her supervisor
Hoosier heart marker
Hard marker means
Yeah I just like it sounds so it's not going to
Reduce much
Russound matter-of-fact about this
I need a sort of
He's not shocked that his dismissal request was shot down
He is offended about the way it was shot down
As the day wears on and I follow rush around to his other pre-trials on other cases
The kid caught driving a stolen car a sex offender who violated a registration requirement
Guy nailed for having drugs and a scale in his car
Russ keep circling back to how the prosecutor on Anna's case
Call his requests last
It couldn't shake his irritation
Tell me about it
Tell other people waiting at the elevators about it
Irritated because he didn't make this dismissal request for Lowe's
He's been doing this a long time he's good at it
He knows how disinclined prosecutors are to drop a case
How rarely that have
You wouldn't ask for a dismissal without good reason
Protocol it laughable feels disrespected
Doesn't really know this prosecutor her name is Jennifer King
Is Hershey's a good lawyer but she's a little young
Maybe she doesn't yet understand that if you call a person's Ernest markwest laughable
Back in the professional relationship
I talked to Jennifer
Burger King
Perhaps unsurprisingly she had a different take on why they got off to a scratchy start
Jennifer's been in the prosecutor's office for 3 years in the general felony unit
She's got a huge inviting smile
She told me Russ's request for dismissal didn't sound like much of a request to her
Chillin like a stone
The defense attorney came to me at the first creature outside you're going to dismiss this
You didn't say will you dismiss as he said you were going to dismiss us I mean he was asking
Did he mean you guys are going to end up dismissing this like by the time I'm through with you you're going to wish you never like it was like
Or was he saying
Hey can you dismiss
Would you take from it
I took from it as being pretty aggressive
Hey I know you're going to dismiss this cuz
This cases
Is crap
And
You all are just charging random girls
In this fight
Jennifer felt like Ross was telling her how to do her job
You know a young female prosecutor who has never worked with an older male prosecutors probably been practicing longer than I've been
Why you no comes at me and says
You're going to dismiss this case I never told her you're going to dismiss this case
Never thought I would never say that to any prosecutor I would never I am not a confrontation
Why not
Belabor this but rust remembered yet a different interaction in which he thought Jennifer misinterpreted him
He says he tried to fix it after that first meeting told her you didn't mean any offense by anything he said but his quads
I apology didn't go over well
He knows it's hard to be a female attorney in this building especially a young one
Female attorneys get short shrift he says
There's a bias against them principally among older white men I eat a lot of the criminal bar
Jennifer told me whatever her personal feelings about a defense attorney she does not going to take them out on the defendant
That does not influence my mark
I thought maybe Jennifer would be a little sheepish about an escape
But they were Prosecuting it at all much less is a felony
The Jennifer mantis case was uncomplicated
And I was facing a felony because punching a cop is a felony
Jennifer head watch the same bar surveillance video that Ross had
And that I had
She said so yeah you can see what
But what you don't have an audio
You don't hear the officer saying
Police break it up and she still flailing
She's still kicking and she punches and officer who
Trying to keep people from being harmed
Right in the face
And I mean her arm comes around so we see
Yes there's an assault there
Did that did that punch look deliver it to you or did it look like somebody
Kind of flailing around
Try to defend
Somewhere in between I mean it ain't no it wasn't a dude stop straight punch to the face I see you kind of a thing but then again it wasn't just like her
Arm flung back and happy
Hit him in the face
Either mean she is
Aggressively
Fighting at that point and yes there's lots of people on the floor and there is another woman kicking her butt really
If she just stopped at that point nothing probably would have come of this she probably would have been charged with
With any sort of assault for the record Anna says she never heard the off
Officer say stop or Break It Up
She said she never even knew police were in the bar until someone arrested her
But that's Anna's word over cops
Jennifer will take the cops
Rust
Thinks this whole case is built on a misunderstanding
Starting from the very beginning
When a cop arrested
Did Anna
Pointed out that the cop didn't watch the surveillance video that same night
So you must have thought Anna was the troublemaker
And his police report he writes that anocote initiated the fight
Rest of the cop didn't know Anna was being harassed by some skeevy dude in a baseball cap
Didn't know the blonde lady got in Anna's face
Banana got stomped while she was on the floor
The cop had known Russ said
I don't think he would have charged
I don't think anybody
Really knew the full story of what happened
Is that true though
Police wearing body cameras that night in the bar
Listen here
This is Anna's friend Kristen who is sitting next to her in the bar
Christian talk to at least three different officers that night including Sergeant Timothy Gill
The cop who got hit in the face
And she told him all the same story
Same accurate
Story so then he wouldn't stop so she got pissed off like y'all chill the f*** out
And then
The other girl with guy in her face like
Jumped up right away
Don't talk to my friend like this and then start going at it with her
Does body camera footage is part of the evidence and Anna's case
I listen to all of it
I got to say it contains some gems for us as case
The officer did know what
And yet and it is the only one who gets in any trouble that night
Which seems extravagant Leone
Unfair
1 points are aware of the lady who got in her face
They're going to file a report saying that lady assaulted at her
That doesn't have
I never even talk to that lady
She wisely hightailed it from the bar right after Anna was
Detained
In his report Sergeant Gill will describe the other woman not as an assailant but as a quota mutual combat in
As for the a slapper he did stick around
There's this whole exchange between Kristen and Sergeant Gill where he asks her
With the guy look like he was smacking your friend
Kristen DiMera she's like I don't know and then go says
Just give me what you got
Increasing cost it up
Jesus that's him right there in the red jacket
Jacket on outside
The guys taken outside
Patted down put in the back of a cruiser
Anon
The police let him go
Why would they do that you ask
Well maybe because back inside the bar at the remaining Patron say oh guy in the red jacket
I talk to this fellow afterwards
Troy
He's nice
I felt badly about what happened to Anna
We all
As as
You know there was about four or five people that say we never seen that
Do you know
He wouldn't do something like that
You know him
No
But
He would have
Just stay like that so he wouldn't that's not how me want to do that
Troy believes this is why the a slapper was let go
Because they all voucher
Okay
So the male cop is believing
For men or six men over the women who say
He slapped her ass
Also
The cop himself Sergeant Gill the victim
She doesn't appear to care that much about being punch
Consensus from the bar patrons is of the punch was essentially an accident
I don't think anyone should get Hall Downtown including Ana
Biggest arch in gilsum sloppy pushback
You got to rest her seriously
Sergeant Gill struggles
In this tape Sergeant Gill is in the background saying
Let me make this perfectly clear nobody wants to arrest the gal
Nobody wants you arrested West 104
It's hard to hear but he says will I press charges
Do I think it's the biggest eel in the world
No I don't
He says the same thing to Anna who's outside the bar sitting in the back of a police cruiser
Half handcuff
One cup of slipped off and was dancing Every Witch Way
His tone with her is not exactly apologetic but it is conciliatory
Fieldhouse sweetheart don't worry I'm not going to press charges
I'm not going to press charges it doesn't matter if you're fine
But I have to take you to jail because you hit a policeman but it doesn't listen to me
I'm not sure why Sergeant Gill is saying he's not going to press charges
Sergeant Gill isn't the only decide on this is the first link in a chain
Here's what's going to happen
A detective will come by the bar tomorrow and look at the surveillance tape
He'll see what he needs to see
Bananas are made contact with sergeant killface
And that'll be probable cause
Felony assault Ibiza
The prosecutors will take it from there
City prosecutor Anthony County prosecutor
Sergeant Gill could stop the whole thing right now as he's talking to Anna
He could let her out of that Cruiser Center home to bed
Instead he says this
Which is the most confounding sliver of audio from the whole night
Searching girl says I know you didn't mean to punch me
I understand
Accidental
You got to go
I'm sure it was purely accidental
Maybe he's just trying to calm her down
Regardless and it is not placated
Possible nothing could have placated or just then
She told me she was a little drunk and very angry sitting in the back of the
Land Cruiser
Cop car
4 hours for no f****** reason
Bull shark
What's the new life primary
Analyst a slurry of invective
Protest
1 hour she kept it up
After how is she not scared to talk to Cops like that
She said I hate to say it, white girl
You know I'm saying
Sometimes you can get away with things and you can say things
Do understand what I'm saying
I didn't understand what you were saying
Really
And the cops on the receiving end of this
These aren't even the cops who arrested her
Never went into the bar or anyting they happen to be on duty down the block when someone deposited and in their back seat
By the time the driver to the gesture
The center and Shepherd are from the garage onto the elevator
They're arguing like family
Tired and familiar
We don't know we know just why am I here
Wendy wintersteen
I can't answer this
Define but you still have to go through this
You still have to go through this
The message to Ana from the police officers that night was we know you don't want to get on this train but too late
You're already on it
Don't worry though. For you
Eventually
Play Sergeant Gill said to the bar patrons after one of his rhetorical q and A's do I want to do it
Now I don't
He added she'll get her day in court
That's coming up
After this
This is the road to hire
Brought to you by ZipRecruiter
What is the CEO of caffe Alterra
Stuff but cost a lot less
Alter has been around since 1980
It was one of the first organic coffee companies in the United States
I mean the USDA certification for organic
Didn't even exist
When they started it was just a handshake agreement that said we didn't use pesticides we didn't use fertilizers
How old were you in 1980
I wasn't even born in 1980 I was born in 1988
They wanted to switch it up to some trendier roasts and run the business more smoothly
But that still needed to hire a director of coffee
Someone who could buy coffee beans roast them and taste them for quality control
But that person was really hard to find
Because there's not many Roasters in the country that are on our side
There's
Probably only a few thousand individuals that would have the skills and the ability to do this
It's definitely like finding a needle in a haystack
Because Dylan is smart and so very modern
He posted the job on ZipRecruiter
In just a few weeks
He found the perfect person
ZipRecruiter
Saved us time which ultimately saves US money
Which helps our customers save money on your affordable coffee
Absolutely
ZipRecruiter maze hiring as smooth as your favorite blend of coffee
Try for free at ziprecruiter.com cereal
Ziprecruiter.com cereal
ZipRecruiter the smartest way to hire
Support for serial comes from Squarespace
Make your business official with Google in Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and a Business website with Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and professional tools from Google
It's the simplest way to look professional online
Visit squarespace.com Google
To start your free trial
And use offer code professional for a discount on your first purchase
Google and Squarespace
Make it professional make it beautiful
In his heart of hearts
Rustix the real reason the prosecutor's office is pursuing this case against Anna
Is because
There was a cop involved yes
Because she's already got a record
No felonies but she's got some misdemeanors
From Florida there's a driving under suspension a DUI
And some local conviction
Including a recent one
Looks pretty bad
A case that started out as two felony theft charges but got dropped down to mr.
So it is not clean
But there a lot of clean records in the Justice
Most of the defendants
Many of the victims to have had some prior entanglement with the law
And even if it's small stuff
Marijuana possession or trespassing
You get the stink on you
Would have come to think of is this
You get a whiff of bad citizenry about you
An odor that causes the presumption of innocence to shrivel
Russ understands why I understand
Because everyone who works in this building has become accustomed to the likes of you
You are the usual
And now it feels natural that the courthouse is where you belong
Tell with the aroma of Prior misdemeanors clinging to Anna's file
The prosecutor moves from the laughable stage of negotiations
To a solid
M1 assault
First degree misdemeanor
Justice
Protected
Russ knows the whole system is primed for him to take this misdemeanor offer
Facts of the case be damned
Everyone here please
96% of convictions in this Courthouse
Confirm please
All day that's what people are doing brokering haggling Angling
Plea deal
The tenancy even among defense attorneys Russ's is to go along with the flow
We're trying to get rid of cases if somebody is offered to plead with
We don't okay that that's a win
In defense parlor
The feeling will be while she has a prior record anyway
So a plea to a misdemeanor is
No concert
I remember one judge told me
And this is
One judge told me
If Miss County innocence is a misdemeanor
What that means is if they don't have
The evidence against
Askew
Village play.
2 misdemeanor
Okay
If they can't prove you guilty
They'll give you a misdemeanor
Everyone around here prosecutors defense attorneys judges even defendants
Internalize this idea that a misdemeanor is a little consequence
Lorelei Cress sometimes has to remind himself how mangled the principle that
The prosecution can't prove its case they should drop it
Not simply shrink it until it looks harmless enough to swallow
What's more if Anna does plated this charge just to make her case go away
The judge understandably is going to treat her as if she did in fact
Assault a cop
And
She's going to give her a hard time
I'm about it
Just going to lecture her
And you know when your kind didn't do any
That that's just
I don't
But I just don't want to put her in that situation where she is belittled and accused of doing something
She didn't do
Because she didn't do it
Interjects the states offer recipes with her
Again provocation accidental hit the glaring unfairness of it all
Why should his client plea to any kind of assault
I'll take it to trial
Another decision made
Now Russ is having cold feet
Because I'm having sex
Thoughts about
You know
What about what about trying the case
Speakers for
Annie's cases no longer about what really happened in that bar
It's become a risk-benefit analysis
The surveillance video is great evidence
Rose has a slim concerned that the state might try to bring in the body cam video
Where Amazon at are
She said some ugly things in it
It's not incriminating or anything but it doesn't help her look sympathetic
And regardless of how well the child goes for Anna there's always at 5% of juries who do something weird
Like Invicta case like this
Does get convicted then there's the matter of the room
20b
Judge Maureen Clancy
Judge Clancy used to be a prosecutor just got a reputation as law enforcement friendly
Give me a test answer
Praying this judge was an unlucky draw in about 20 other rooms rest wouldn't worry about Anna getting sent to jail for this
But this room it is conceivable
Those are the risks for Anna
But then admits
There are risks for him to
In rejecting the misdemeanor assault
Risks that shouldn't matter when you're considering what's best for your client
But in reality they do
I know that when I tell the price
Shakira.
She's going to trial
And I'm relatively certain I'll get
Blowback
You know why are you taking
What's time
And not pleading this out to him this term
I wouldn't certainly get it from
From the project
Pewter it wouldn't surprise
The Drudge
I know but I will
In what form
I'll be viewed as
Somebody was complicated
Necessarily
Like you'll just be seen as an irritant now and
Well it is an obstructionist somebody who is in
Heating the disposition
Cases
I I will be
I am not going to say subject ridicule but I will be regarded as an extra
I said you know I do it
You don't want to get a
Butaton for that
Reputation is everything around here
It's a closed and somewhat circular communities as Courthouse
Everyone knows everyone
Word gets around very fast
If you're a pain in the ass
Grandstand if your boat rocker you slow dockets down
It can affect your business
Kalix Minot refer clients to you and judges might not assign you cases
About half of Russia's income is from assignments some like Anna's some appellate work
By 1 they don't pay much
Not exactly pay-by-the-hour there's a pcap
According to the court rules the most you can get paid for Anna's case is $800 whether he takes it to trial or not
The minimum he can get paid as curiously specific 250
$6
The best way to make money as an assignment attorney is a treat it like a volume business
Take lots of cases resolved them quickly but not too quickly
Patches
Judges control the assignment
Which can lead to a kind of settled self-inflicted pressure
Maybe I won't file this motion or take this case
The trial
Because that might annoy the judge
And then he might know assignment cases
Rose has a good reputation I doubt he's in real danger of reprisal
But if his Courthouse veteran is worrying about whether he'll be seen as an obstruction
A little kiss like this
Measuring a less secure attorney might do in his place
3 weeks before the trial date Raza Nanna make a last-ditch counter-offer
How about disorderly conduct
An M4
What are the smallest charges in the courthouse
Just went up from say a speeding ticket
The state rejected
Note to Jennifer this was definitely an assault
So it's either take the M1
Or try to beat the felony charge
Trial
We are here today in the cape
Hair shows up for her trial wearing a new dress you got at Marshall's
Navy blue with white piping around the collar cap sleeves
String of Pearls sparkly flats
Looks like an attorney
Which he later told me was the look she was going for
Julie the tags on the dress and hopes of returning it
Who is Shakib
Russ is there of course standing with Anna at the defense table
The prosecution's table across from them
No Jennifer
But some other guy
A young prosecutor named Jonathan
I want to know Jonathan characterizes the crime before
Disorderly conduct a misdemeanor of the fourth degree
Disorderly conduct
A misdemeanor of the fourth degree
Since Jennifer was busy on a murder trial
It's about a week ago she's handed off the case
Jonathan McDonald
Jonathan watch the bar surveillance video
And this morning before his trial began russaw Jonathan back in
Court Chambers and first thing he said to rest was
You got your disorderly conduct
Anna takes it
In the courtroom she pleads guilty
Happily
Jonathan gives a judge a quick synopsis of the case
It was a fight he says
It was chaotic
Multiple people were touching Anna
She was flailing
He closes it out with a fourth degree use of the passive voice
Sergeant Gill he tells the judge
Was struck by a blow
Diablo and I would agree with the defendant
Sergeant kill himself isn't there
You come by earlier in the day but he had to leave
Another officer was there
Does Clancy double checks with them like you're cool with this outcome
The officer mentions and already spent four days in jail
Does I mean
I would say that
Adequate
Judge Clancy find a $200 and send her on her way with the gentle
Good luck to you
Architect you
Everyone suddenly seem so chill about this felony assault on a peace officer
Just weeks earlier Jennifer had firmly rejected the M4 disorderly
What happened
What change
Obviously the prosecutor for one fresh eyes on the case
In this instance I've attached to a guy who gets along well with rust fencing
The personalities aside rest later told me it's also the timing
The eve of trial can be a magical time
Arrest on a Samuel Johnson quotation
The prospect of going to trial concentrates a man's mind wonderful
Clarity descends
Sometimes you learn things about your own case that you hadn't quite seen before
My credit sucks May
And I think that's
That's probably would have
Here
That they they just took it
I'll look at it that you know
Can you realize certain things about it
Not a tribal situation
In fact I told Jonathan
I said
You can find 12 people in your office who would convey
Would all agree that she should be convicted to this and he said touche
Did you say that after we did the deal
Did the police
This point I was sincerely confused about what to make of Anna's case
Just in a fundamental way it was this thumbs up thumbs down
Is this an example of the system
Working or not working
Oh it is it that I think
It achieved the right
Results so it's an example of
The system work
Yeah I had this gone to
Trileptal
Would be a Santa Ana
The system
Never should
To be perfectly blunt she never should
Irish twins
Setting aside the trust believes Anna didn't commit a crime
And that she just plead guilty to one
The system worked
I talked to Jennifer about this to
Xi'an Russell green
She said she was glad the case went to a prosecutor who had a good rapport with ra
That she was fine with the result
Anyway Jennifer set at the end of the day the difference between the initial offer of misdemeanor assault
And the final offer
Disorderly conduct
Really the difference between the M4 and the M1 is
So negligible but it's like
Caso4 and it worked out the justice system work
Please just point out no
An assault versus a disorderly
I'm sorry no
If it were your record or my record by Jennifer's record we were talking about
The difference is not negligible
This is what rankles me most about Anna's case
The breeziness with which everyone's looking back on it now
Clapping the dust off their hands and saying
Great that's done
Small crime smoke a small punishment all in proportion
Justice is served
But they're not saying maybe because you're not seeing it
Is the extent of Anna's punishment
Which one you take a minute
The catalog the consequences was not small
Did not fit
I'm going to do that now take you through
It said it when they say she got a fine and was sent on her way it could have been worse
You'll see why I'm arguing that it was worse
Quite a lot worse
First off and I sat in the back of a police car for at least an hour
Belligerent yes but also distraught
Then she's booked into the Cleveland City Jail
Which is
Disgusting
Agreed
I've seen parts of it
And I spent four nights there
I can say it fast four nights in jail
Or I can say it like it fell to Anna
Thursday night
Then Friday night
Saturday night
And Sunday night
Your bar fight
4 Days of Night
It was loud in there
People shouting and arguing up and down and across the cells
And I slept on a mat on the floor no blanket no sheet a pathetic little sponge on a stick
For a toothbrush
Because Aunt has white and skinny and it said people assume she was a heroin addict and gave her a hard time about that
Color clock in a junkie
Messing with each other just to pass
The time everyone's board
There's no TV
They gave you maybe like a magazine that's an interesting light
Where to eat in Cleveland by
Why do it their food cycling you're just sitting in there like
Finally Monday,
And Anna sees a judge
Who sets her bond at $5,000
That's a lot
The judge had other choices
Anna could have been let out of jail was just a promise to come back to
Court
But this was $5,000
Full payment
Which antigen have
Instead she paid a bondsman a fee of $500 to post the bond for her
Money she doesn't get back
If she hadn't been able to Muster that fee
Should have been sitting in jail for months possibly
A condition of her bond is Court supervised release
Certified pre-trial probation
Every Wednesday she's got to come back downtown
Check in
I pee in a cup for drug test
These visits are on top of the pre-trial
All told anime more than 20 trips to the Justice Center for this
She does not live close by
The judge find her $200 for the disorderly conduct plus court fees
Which she has to pay because she put guilty she was convicted
If the state had dropped the charger she going to trial in one these fees would disappear
I showed them the rest asked if he could explain the itemized list
14 different fees
Summit names that suggested deep respect for catch-all accounting
Reparations
County operations
Court special projects fund
And then call Dad fee
Russ had no idea what the stuff was
You're laughing why
Oh my
Steep is what it is
Anarosa Court a total of $784.50
On top of the 500 she paid the bondsman
Russ said there's a way you can petition the court to waive the fee Savannah can't pay
But she doesn't ask him to and he doesn't offer technically is not a lawyer anymore
List of fuse was a surprise to Anna to
Have you seen this
Before this number
Did you know about all these fees
Nope
No I mean I plan to pay it I'm just
You know
You have a job
No
Just lost my job so
Just crazy
Free I'm getting hungry Sarah
She's pregnant
She just found out
She's happy about it hoping for a girl
A month later and it was working at McDonald's
Online account with a Courtney well as turns red
Indicating that the county clerk has handed over the bill to the Attorney General's office for collection
All this
Synonym for disorderly
A felony judge I was talking to for a different story in the series
Tell me he was thinking of giving a defendant serious time
What's Sirius timeout
Explain to someone with common sense
Even one day in jail is devastating life-changing
Someone who's got no common sense
Maybe they do 3 years 5 years means nothing
They go right back out and commit more crimes
Annuity man punishment is relative what it takes to teach you a lesson depends on what you're used to
But there was a more disturbing invocation as well
When it prowls this Courthouse
Send throughout our criminal justice
That we are not like them
The ones we arrest and punish the ones with the stink
They're slightly different species
Senses dulled and toughened
I don't feel pain or sorrow or Joy or Freedom or the loss of freedom
The same way you are I would
This little case for the state of Ohio wasn't little for Anna
In our interview she couldn't bring herself to watch the bar surveillance video of that night it was too upsetting
She teared up a couple of times thinking about what a horrible year it has been
She blamed herself
She's been stupid to go to a bar like
She said the people she didn't trust
Anna doesn't have money just have a stable job
She's really young
Just 21
And I didn't feel the stress and outrage and shame of this case less than I would have
I think she felt it more
Before and his final day in court when she ended up taking a plea
Russet had only one interaction with the judge regarding Anna's case
He was coming to her Chambers by her bailiff
Who told us that judge Clancy had a question for him
Press waited around for 20 minutes
Annabelle came out and just relay the question
Curiosity the judge would like to know
Was the defendant in this case related to a County judge
Retired
Team last name
Bristol the bailiff
No
No relation
Bristol need is almost a year after it happened
What is the answer to Ben yes and it was related to the retired judge
It would have been dismissed
If they found out she was a judge's knees are related in some way
I don't think she even would have been charged
Is that how it works in Cleveland
Next time on serial
Cereals produced by Julie Snyder Emmanuel Church event Calhoun and me with additional reporting by Eataly
Laskowski
Editing on this episode from Ira Glass Brian Reed Hannah joffe-walt and Nancy Updike
Whitney Dangerfield is our digital editor research and fact-checking by Ben Phelan
Southland is our director of operations
Cheryl staff includes Emily Condon Julie Whitaker Cassie Holly and France
The Swanson
Our music is by Adam Dorn and how willner
With additional music from Matt McGinley
Our theme song is by Nick thorburn and remix by Adam Dorn
Special thanks to Dana Chivas Rich Oris Amy Callahan Lisa Noller Bennett Epstein Alex kotlowitz and Steve
Bagheera
Who spent a year in the Cook County Courthouse in Chicago
You had a great book about it called courtroom 302 that book is the inspiration for this season
We also want to thank the judges and staff at the Cuyahoga County Court of Common Pleas also everyone over the County prosecutor's office
And at the Cuyahoga County Public Defender's Office
Finally the art on our website was made by Melanie Newcomb she created a mural for this episode
Moth Studio who did the animation
Please check it out on our website serial podcast. Org
That serial podcast. Org
Support for serial comes from ZipRecruiter unlike many job sites ZipRecruiter doesn't wait for candidates to find you
ZipRecruiter finds them for you
So you get qualified candidates fast
Tried free at ziprecruiter.com cereal
Ziprecruiter.com
Cereal
Support for serial comes from Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and Business website with Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and professional tools from Google
Use offer code professional for discount on your first church
Serials production of This American Life and WBEZ Chicago