Previously
Material
While you're digging your body you're going to find somebody else
That's looking for
I walked along the edge of the log expecting to find a body real soon I never saw one
Lincoln Park MI where is that do you know where it is have you ever been there what shopping
Alex friend of mine
Normal for me to leave school to go do something and then come back
This is a Global Tel Link prepaid call from
An inmate at Maryland Correctional Facility
From This American Life and WBEZ Chicago and serial one story told
Week-by-week I'm Sarah Koenig
Remember how last time I ended by saying that the detectives had other leads in the
Does case besides mr. ask the guy who found his body
But they were also starting to look at at 9
The reason we know that is because of this memo
The memo was dated 12 February 1999
Trump detective Darryl Massey to detective Greg mcgillivary
This memo he's talking about is regarding an anonymous call
That's detective Ritz on the witness stand at trial
He's talking about how they got this Anonymous call three days after his body was found
The call came in to detective mascia Baltimore County cop
The car must have been an accident of some kind because Massey's report described him as an Asian male 18 to 21 years old
So it's unclear whether Asian in this case means East Asian like
Korean or South Asian like Pakistani
But anyway
Mystery caller says look at the ex-boyfriend
The caller for their advice with boyfriend
I'll take him to the the Beckham to Linkin Park on past occasions for sexual encounter
Project including the phone interview to call it further stated that the victim broke off the relationship with her boyfriend about a week before she
She was reported missing
The caller hangs up
Then a few minutes later the same guy calls back and says oh yeah
By the way
This time to call a remembered about a year ago the suspect informed friend of his
Francis passarelli Asian male 17
Enterprise season
If he
Ever heard his girlfriend he would drive her car into a lake
This time the color mentions a friend of an oz
Vasarely
Actually the name of this friend is Yasir Ali
The color says Yasir might know something
Hang up again the cops can't trace the call
It's out of range
Anonymous call The Detectives
Call I don't know anything quote
Wanted to get rid of the car where was he do so
Ali indicated somewhere in the woods possibly in Centennial Lake or the Inner Harbor on quote
Who has ever gotten to the bottom of who made this Anonymous call the cops in figure it out another term
He didn't figure it out figure it out 2
For a while I couldn't let it go because it seemed to me that whoever made this call he must be the key to the whole
But so far I only have gases that I can't responsibly say out loud
Today after the Pizza Hut tok on February 16th
The detectives do some paperwork that will ultimately crack the whole case open for them
They get a subpoena for a non cell phone records
The results of that sir
Subpoena include a list of all the calls dialed and received this phone on January 13th
The day he disappeared that list will become a piece of paper
All the thousands in this case
Will become their map
Snow following
I called I called like Footprints the front door
Would you look at that call log from January 13th
There are 34 calls that day
Obviously the first thing they have to do is figure out who all the phone numbers belong to
Home cell and pager numbers
Once they do they realize
Wait a minute
One person was called six times that day
Much more often than anyone else
The person is an 18 year old girl named Jennifer pusateri
Is not a friend of Adnan
She's a friend of Jay
Remember Jay had a nun's car that day
And his new cell phone
Eason Chan
Got to swear you won't tell nobody
Forgot to tell you
That's Jen talking to detectives about the night of January 13th
All right but I got to tell you I got to tell somebody I can't
Sounds like
Feels Like Home
At 9
Shohei
That's what I want to say
What do you mean okay
By what
How when
Where are you know
If you want to figure out this case with me
Now is the time to start paying close attention
Because we've arrived along with the detectives
At the heart of the FAE
This interview with Jen happens on February 27th 1999
The day before on the 26th the cops have gone to find Jen at our house
Explain to come downtown
Tok
Jen is Thoroughly we doubt she says she can't right now she's busy maybe later
Jennifer and go CJ
He's at work at a video store
She tells J
The police want to talk to me what do I do
A trial Jen says
He told me to go down there and tell them what I do tell them enough to keep me out of trouble
And tell them to go see Jay
Send them his way
Bojangles downtown to see the cops later that night
And she lies to them
So she doesn't know anything
I seen the detectives notes from that interview and they're remarkably uninteresting
By the time she left that night Jen thought it was possible she was about to get charged
A trial she said the last thing detective megillah very said to her that night was quote everyone's a suspect and no one's ass
Respect
So the next day she goes back to the detectives
This time she's got reinforcements
She's got an attorney with her plus her mom
They turn on the tape recorder
Who what where when why
That's why when you said that
Having said that
A broken heart
Did he say anything else
Emotive
Hey broken nose heart
Anime
He strangled her
Which of course they already knew
But then Jen's information gets a little muddier
Yes and where it happens
He told me
He told me is what he told me he asked asked me what we should do
He said you think we should go to the police now
And tell them right now
And I said
I don't know
I said
What was your involvement
You involved
And he said no he said show me her body
And asked me if I would help her bury his Burberry and I would help him
Carey Hart body
And
I said what did you do did you help him
Do you know where the body is
No I just
Take me to someplace in the city and I drop them off
I told you that I went down
From a different place in the city
And I don't
Number where they said they went
I said how did
Did Judas
Yeah when you don't like when was this done and over with
Yes
He strangled her
In Best Buy parking lot
I don't know how we got the Best Buy or anything like that
I saw the body in the trunk of a car
Anon asked me to help bury her but I didn't I refused
I took him some place and later picked him up someplace at some chicks house
He told her that all this went down at the Best Buy parking lot off Security Boulevard Woodlawn High
High School
Winter of 99
Almost everyday
Elementary School in the same class at Woodlawn they graduated the year before in 98
It was a freshman at UMBC University of Maryland Baltimore County
Resetting biochemistry sorority
When he disappeared gems on winter break
She's working part-time as a lifeguard
What are the jobs at F&M a discount store
Jensen on January 13th been hanging out earlier in the afternoon at her house after she got home from work
Oyster House sometime between 3:45 and 4:15
They plan to meet later that evening
But then Jenna got the message Jay was running late he wanted her to pick him up in the parking lot of Westview Mall around 8 p.m.
She goes there and she sees them together
She says J get out of a non scar non says hi to her
She says he seems to be acting normal
Jay gets in her car and that's when he tells her about the murder
After they driven a little ways Jay mentions shovels the shovels and none had used to dig in the park very hey
That they were Jays shovels
From his house
Jamison Smith at
You are an adult the shuttle
Vegetables
I don't know how many they were
But he's mentioned to me that he knew that were at my put the shuttles
Back to Westview Mall to the dumpsters back there
So the Jake and retrieve the shovels and wipe the handles clean in case of fingerprints
After that
JK back out of my car
Usually shooken up
He was like you have to take me to go see my girlfriend now
Next day Jen said she drove Jay to the F&M store the same one where he worked
So that he could throw out the clothes and boots he was wearing the previous night
He pitched into a dumpster behind the store
Tops points out
Forgot I was telling you he didn't kill anyone and didn't help dispose of a body
He sure is taking a lot of precautions
He clarifies
Jay wasn't alone when the body was buried
Jerry was a long body
The Martian
My understanding
Yeah
It wasn't until today
I was just don't think that I don't think that you would lie to me
Fishball
And like I don't know unless I want PJ a good sum of money
Llcj health
Find a cop asks
We run on and Jay best friends
More like casual acquaintances
What's the detective talk to Jen everything happens very fast
The same night the video store where you work sexual p*** video store which come trial
Attorney will stress with relish at every opportunity by the time
Turn on the tape recorder it's 1:30 in the morning on February 28th
I am willing to answer questions and do not want an attorney's this time my decision
Cheney interview room and initially he pulls a Jen he tells me nothing or less
He walked in the mall that day
Got his girlfriend a bracelet for birthday around with Jen's younger brother
Touchwood Nan sometime in the afternoon
Then after two pages of notes like that it says
All right I come clean
At least that's what I think it says the detectives handwriting is messy so maybe it says
A bright I came down
20 minutes later they start taping
Tells him a whole different story
Gwinnett more or less matches Jen's
Except for one major difference
One major piece of information about this crime that the cops are still missing
They do not know where his car is
I've been looking all over the place for it they can't find it
Now J tells them
He knows where it is
During the
Interview prior to turning the tape on
Miguel ran myself that you'd be willing to take us out and show us where the vehicles Park
Call are you still willing to do that yet
So that's huge for them
Jay will take them to the car
He does
Once they're finished at headquarters they all drive out in the middle of the night to where the car is parked
Put a grassy hill behind some row houses off Edmondson Avenue
Within a few hours they'll have a warrant for anions arrest
We know what you AJ did we talk today
What do you mean like what do you mean j a story isn't true
He says he doesn't know why either very mention J's name and connect
Action with his own arrest you just confused
You know what we talkin about
Stop playing
It's not like there was some secret feud between Jay and Adnan least not that I know of
There's no drug deal gone wrong neither had bad mouth the other Stone the others girlfriend
It sounds like they didn't even know each other very well
When I first asked him what their friendship was like what J was like as a person
I normally have to reach
He was like
It wasn't that into sports
Okay
White people music
Listen to
Heavy metal
I just you know just
Call like a huge long conversation that we ever had other than
Like a specific subject
New York
Would necessarily like
We wouldn't necessarily be kicking it per se is a non speak for
Yes we smoke weed together but we weren't close
Close with Stephanie Jay's girlfriend very close
Turn on says that's the only thing he can think of now that might have turned against him
Stephanie was smart to the top athlete at the school and she was beautiful by any standard she look like a model
She came from a family of achievers who did not approve of Jedi but had no problem with an on
Stephanie's relationship with a non affectionate they were with each other of the constant talking on the phone the prom
Prince and princess stuff
Maybe that was 9 a j
I don't know what thinking maybe Christina Saturday or someone said
Christina was a lawyer
Like you know what I was talking about clothes I was
Persephone
They were like you know
Aha moment
I'm thinking about all the things
You know that took place between us
Mad at me
Anon says exactly
Because they weren't good enough friends for betrayal
He says it was more a feeling of Injustice
Toll-by-plate
Maybe the police will put them up to this maybe somehow he got caught up
I kind of like
Don't know I don't know if there's a part of me that I don't want to make an accusation against someone else
Not being sure that could happen to me
A year after Adnan was arrested and the case came to trial
J walk up to the witness stand
There was a moment when Agnon muttered something to him he says he couldn't help himself
The judge called the attorneys after the bench
I was just informed by my Sheriff that the defendant made a comment to the witness as a witness approach the stand
Indicating that he was pathetic the judge said
Mr. Syed
But up until now he's been perfect
Don't spoil it
In the first
Turn to someone he didn't even know all that well to help him with this murder
Say why would Batman call you
Criminal element of Woodlawn he says
Is that a real or perceived perceived
Call Paula Steele body
Pictures of really know me know that I'm not like that but
Application
Because of the contact you have with
Helping him get his marijuana
He thinks that you're in that element that
Godly daddy willing to assist in
Disposing of the body
Robert Jessica
Domino's online order where
In her closing argument at trial
Prosecutor Casey Murphy pose this
Question to the jury about Jay
Think about it she said
Do you really believe that the defendant meaning Adan
Go to one of his upstanding Magnet School honor student friend or friend from the mosque to assist them with this app
Of course not
Someone who behaves a little more dangerously than those people
Can you just someone who took risks
The defendant hopes that you will look at Jay and say
I don't believe him
That is why the defendant chose J
Because if something went wrong the defendant could point the finger at J
This idea this is what J's more less trying to communicate to the cops
Ask him if you're actually not the type of guy who knows where to bury a body
Then why did you help
Why didn't you go to the police instead
He gives you his car keys
He gives you his cell phone
Called you a time that he's going to call you
50 Cent
When you do absolutely nothing
How many
Understand your train of thought of why you do absolutely nothing that one
Baton news
Things about me
Active Petco
Criminal activity
So I mean it wasn't
You're selling marijuana
So if I go to the cops
Say hey this guy's going to kill her
Jose
Donut crazy
But they're just drug dealer in
This is where you get to s***, this is how we deal with
And he's got a rap sheet this long and
Go get it at
So you've never been arrested but one time one time one time
I got my
Morning
Dog sit down
Cristiano find my own house
It's not this
I mean seriously man I've been coming home
Elena Street in the snow
Walking to my own house
These are place to do that jazz
They didn't trust any
In my mind I don't think
It never crossed my mind I could be getting shot at and I wouldn't be let's call the cops
Okay they say
So if you didn't want to go to the police yourself how about making an anonymous call then
You could have done it right after he shows you the body as you're leaving the Best Buy parking lot
You're driving off the parking lot
Why don't you stop your car and say
Call the police
Someone who just committed a murder there's a body in the trunk
Young Stan Lee
I call it is
Are you afraid of if you make Anonymous phone call you can give a description of her car
You give me the tag number
Yes
If you have any questions you can ask me on Facebook
I'm trying to understand
Why you go through all this
Adjust bike shock and then
Happy Valley
Part of it so I couldn't
J what he has over you or
Your involvement
Is beyond belief
Other than you being afraid of the police either he has paid you something or
Like I said he knows I sold drugs I mean
That was dumb
I mean
If you get me locked up for that I mean
I'm sure if I ratted him out for killing hey did he wouldn't hesitate to turn me over selling drugs
Training else that you'd like to add to this
Feel bad
Boy unique names
I feel bad
GameStop by Arrowhead
He says I just feel bad about it that's all I got to say
The cops have a struggle with j
The struggle with j
She's the biggest mystery of this whole case for me
The cops interview him at least four times that I know about
Two of those are on tape
And J also tells the story a trial not once but twice cuz the first proceeding ended in a mistrial
So at least say six
She's told what happened
And each time some details chef
Some of these discrepancies seem small to me and understandable
But summer significant and confounding
And that distance between wear a certain detail starts and where it ends up
How far it slides
Wyatt slides
I spent Untold hours trying to measure that distance
Trying to weigh it
4 Clues as to what might actually be true
This is from taped interview number one
The cops are asking about what he in a non did that morning of the 13th
Picture of where you get from that
Are we headed towards Russia Mall
Shopping together
Interview number two
March 15th
2 weeks later
And where did you go
We went to Security Square Mall
That's a different Mall Security Square Mall
Couple miles away
I put this one in the category of probably not a big deal right
Maybe Jay misspoke when he said Westview initially
They're a bunch of little things like this
For example when they're driving around that afternoon after they've ditched his car at the I-70 park and ride
For the first trial Jay says they both got high in a duns car
But the second trial he says only he smoke
Anon didn't want to
Then they're more significant changes
But still you can chop them up to Jay trying to protect his friends
Or trying to protect himself
And the first taped interview
Chase's they're grabbing some food at a restaurant when officer Adcock called and not asking if he's seen hey
The next time he tells it
He says it when that call comes that a friend's apartment
A friend whose father happens to be a homicide detective in another County
Jshealth akachi actually been to her house three different times that day but didn't want to get her in trouble
In the first tape statement Jay says he refused to help dig a grave for her
Two weeks later he says they both got the whole
But then
There are other changes
Bigger changes
Where is harder to judge why the details chef
This one for instance
In the first taped interview Jay says Adnan only told him that same day that he was going to kill her
AJ says that an ion has started talking about it beforehand
Four or five days before
I think I'm going to kill her
He said he said that a lot
Conversate with him several occasions you said that
And he says his help with the murder on the 12th
Night before he disappeared
In this version
Jay tells Jen about Advance 2
Take us back to the first version again
And then you didn't really take it seriously
There's a whole side tripping on Andreas probably take that afternoon after has been killed
Smoke some weed in Patapsco State Park
That trip disappears by trial just dropped out of the narrative
Whereabouts in between the time he drops it on back at school at midday and when he meets back up with him later that ass
Afternoon
The stories about where he is are so messy and so confusing that I can't even keep the different versions straight
But none of these discrepancies
Gives me or I think the cops
As much pause as its next one
This is the mother of what the cops called Jay's inconsistencies
It's about where it done first showed him his body in the trunk of a car
Here's from taped interview number one
Jay says Adnan called them about 3:45 p.m. saying come pick me up
I went to pick him up
Orthodontist Avenue strip and yeah
Pop the trunk opening
Edmondson Avenue off of the strip
Any cross streets on Edmondson Avenue where you go meeting I don't know my name
A strip is a small outdoor drug Market just like a block we can buy drugs
Jay tells the cops
But it takes me about 15 or 20 minutes to get to location on Edmondson
Later when the cops drive out with Jay to get his car chase chosen the spot on Edmondson Avenue
It's just a few blocks from where they ditched his car he said
Listen to what he says on March 15th
And why
In route to your house if you receive a phone call from Aetna
Yes on his cell phone which is in your possession
And
The conversation was what
That picture said
Come and get me
Best Buy
Just like John had originally told them
This is a problem for the cops
This change
Because it's not something you forget
Where you were when you saw a dead body in the trunk of a car
It's not a slip of the tongue
But it's not clear what the calculation is
Edmondson Avenue versus the Best Buy parking lot
What's the advantage of one place over the other
Why tell this lie
Maybe he's just saying it because it matches Jen Story
Or did he lie to Jen in the first place and then forget
Better friend whose work for a long time in the Baltimore judicial system
She knows a lot of cough
But you reminded me when I was telling you about this case
Cops are the most skeptical people in the world
They pretty much assume everyone is lying to them all the time
Richard macgillivray aren't newbies
Mcgillvary came from a law enforcement family his father had been catching the homicide unit in fact
And Ritz was known in the department and in the State's Attorney's office as a skilled and meticulous investigator
So they're not suckers
They're taking careful note of the changes and Jay stories
That's why they keep going back to him
Clear up the inconsistencies
In a second interview confronts J
Taking off a list of the main things he lied to them about
Enchantments to all the lies
But even so what struck me is that they don't really press him on any of it
The most forceful mcgillvary gets is in this Exchange
About the location of the trunk pop
He
Actually kill her
Add Best Buy to my house
Do you know
You weren't present for that picture
Why did you lie
About
The location
Somebody had spotted him doing what he was doing and what have you
Actually
Sister murder
Why would you lie about
Because I'm a location
But you did lie
Chasing I figured there were security cameras at Best Buy so that's why I lied
Has anyone be associated with a
What is he talking about
This is nonsensical
What he told the Edmondson Avenue version
He was already deeply associated with it
And if there were cameras at Best Buy parking lot
When that help his story
They showed his car or non walking around or putting his body in the trunk
But mcgilvery let's It Go
Lausanne to another point
Just so you know as best as we can tell from workers at the store and from the former landlord
There probably weren't security cameras in the Best Buy parking lot back in 1999
There's certainly no mention of any security footage in the police report
At the end of both of J's tape statements the detectives come out with it
Are you telling us the truth right now
On February 28th after Jay's told them off tape that he doesn't know anything about the murder
Your story has completely changed since you first came in this room
All the information that you provided during the center
Is it been a complete route
And then Jay reinforces at
All right
I believe that concludes his interview
Remember
Okay
But of course 2 weeks later big swaths of his story of changed
So I asked him again and March 15th
Detroit
Interviews if you
He's giving us right now
Is that true
To the best that I can possibly human being at this point in time member that is true
Did you
Kill
Palin
Were You There When Adnan still there
I put it to Bill Ritz when I talked to him briefly on the phone
A story kept changing catching inconsistencies and he was having to explain them and clean up a store
Dory
Ultimately
Chris said they believed a story because quote we were able to investigate and corroborate what he was saying I'm quote
So how exactly did they corroborate it
Next time on serial
Cereals produced by Julie Schneider Dana Travis and me a production and operations manager are glasses are editorial
Fact-checking by Karen fragala Smith
And by Mark Phillips who also mixed Artio special thanks to Gregory Collins Rich Orris and Lou Teddy
Our website where you can listen to all our episodes letters and other documents from the case and you can sign up for a weekly
Emails
Serialpodcast.org
Serials production of This American Life and WBEZ Chicago