Hello serial listeners
It's Sarah Cain egg with a quick reminder
That we have
Two other podcast
There's This American Life weekly show that chooses one theme and then has a mix of weird emotional and
Investigative
And personal stories on that
Cereal started as a spin-off of
Are we developed our storytelling jobs
SOS
Beautiful 7-part series that explores the life of one man in Alabama
As Town starts out as one thing and then become something
Totally
Fascinatingly differ
This American Life and s-town
Available now on podcast apps
Or At This americanlife.org and s-town podcast
Previously on serial
You left your cell phone in car with me
Call me call me
Hey now at this point
You know why he's leaving the car with you yes
And why is that
Hey
I just and it's going to look at this and stay all night. He must be lying
So coincidental
He told me to speak with Jay and I was like okay
Cuz they wanted to say hi so I said hi to Jay
And that's all I can barely recall
The uselessness of what we're trying to do by recreating something that doesn't fit
It's like trying to plot the coordinates of someone's dream or something
It is what it is. You don't have no control over
This is a Global Tel Link prepaid call from
Maryland Correctional Facility
From This American Life and WBEZ Chicago is cereal once
Story told week by week and this episode 12 is the final week
Final episode of season 1 of this podcast
It's been a year since I first contacted at 9 and I'm still talking to him regularly
I'm still asking him the basics
Still thinking I don't know that he'll remember something or maybe he'll just get so frustrated with me that he'll crack
I still want to know what you were doing that afternoon
I want to know who had your phone
I want to know what you were doing that afternoon
I don't I don't remember anything more
This is from Saturday night just this past Saturday
I mean we're down to the wire here
Oh man
We have no ending
Do I have an ending
Of course I have an ending we're going to come to an ending today
Plus a smattering of new information a review of old information cast under different light
And an ending
Even notice my thoughts about Adnan case about who is lying and why
Have not been fixed over the course of the story
Several times I have landed on a decision I've made up my mind
And stay there with relief
And then inevitably I learned something I didn't know before
And I'm up ended
Sometimes the reversal takes a few weeks
Sometimes it happens within hours
What's been astonishing to me is how the back-and-forth hasn't let up
After all of this time
Even if it is very weak and I kid you not into this very day that I'm writing this
Because I'm learning new information all the time
For instance
I talked to Don
8 months ago he told me he did not want to talk to me for the story
And then last week
He talked to me for the story
Do you want me to use tape of his voice or his last name
But he said I could use what he said
Spoiler here
Does not appear to know what happened to hey or why it happened to her or whether Adnan is guilty
It was interesting to hear what he said he remembered
About the day he disappeared
And about her and about the trial
Here's what he told me
Don said he was at his house in a town north of Baltimore City
On the night of January 12th the night before she went missing
He said she wanted to spend the whole next day with him too
She wanted to call Woodlawn High School and pretend to be some authority figure
Tell the office he couldn't be in school that day
She wanted it to be an excused absence rather than just playing hooky
But he didn't
He says he thought you should go to school
And besides he told her he had to work the next day at 9 a.m.
It was supposed to be his day off from the LensCrafters at the Owings Mills mall where they both worked
But John said he'd arranged to fill in for a friend at the store in Hunt Valley
John said he had made plans to meet up later that night of the 13th
After her work shift ended at 10 p.m.
When the cops recovered his car there was a note inside with Dawn's name on it
Hey cutie
Sorry I couldn't stay
I have to go to a wrestling match at Randallstown High
But I promise to page you as soon as I get home okay
Take care and drive safely
Always
Hey
UPS on the note he mentions a TV interview that have been taped at day
A local station it done as soon as Elite segment on her
So the note was written on the 13th the day she went missing
The snow was one of the reasons I'd initially written to Don way back when
Sorry I couldn't stay is confusing
I didn't understand what you plan to do with the note
Put it on his car maybe
But his car was so far away in Hunt Valley
But the notes dumped onto
He said he didn't know about it until I sent it to him
He didn't have a guess as to what our plan was for that afternoon
When he went missing Don was one of the first people the cops called
He said he knew immediately suspect
He said quote that was the first thought when they said she's missing
I said well okay they're going to try to blame it on me
Because she was with me last night I'm the new boyfriend
I'm obviously going to be one of the first suspect me and Anon
He said he immediately made sure he knew where he was
Have you seen this person they went missing they haven't been seen since school
You automatically retrace everything you did that day
Did I see them did I hear from them that they page me that they call me where was I at this time what was I doing at that time
Yeah
But that wasn't enough
State of reaction to getting called by the cops on the 13th
I'm tempted to make a judgment right here
But I'm going to pull a benefit of the doubt
Because Anan was 17
He was stoned
He's a different person but noted right
Also know there was one similarity and how they reacted to his disappearance
He doesn't remember calling her after the 13th
Guess who else doesn't remember try to call her after the 13th
Don
Like everyone else he said he wondered whether maybe she's going to California she told him her father live there
He says it's something he didn't think about what it happened or didn't worry
It's just I didn't know what to do
Don's Alibi was solid
His computer-generated timecard said he'd arrived at work at 9:02 a.m. on the 13th
Taking lunch from 1:10 to 1:42
Clocked out at 6 p.m.
Don's manager at the valley store with his mom
So that didn't look great
He was anxious throughout the investigation
Quote the never up until the day they arrested in
I had no idea what was going on
He said they never said okay you're cleared as a suspect
Who's left hanging and until they arrested him I had no idea
I suspected they might try to say that we were in on it together
I didn't know Jay existed until I started listening to
Podcast
According to his diary it was December 23rd
The snowy day and she'd had a minor car accident on the way into work
And she called at 9 to come help her out
They were broken up by this time it came to the rescue
In the parking lot outside LensCrafters Adnan and Don converged
Hayrides quote
Take a look at my car and told me not to drive it unanimously
Mommy is going to be so mad
But I swear it's not my fault
Don told the cops back then that he Nan Nan had a perfectly nice conversation
A trial he said an unfit some again like
Okay well I just want to make sure you are an okay guy
Done told me the same
Quotes
We sat and talked and just as everyone else described him he was very polite articulate
Just really the typical what you would expect of the ex-boyfriend meeting the new boyfriend sizing each other up
We joked we spent a good 10-15 minutes talking after we checked out the car
A trial for whatever reason this episode is firmly time-stamped as having happened in January after hey
And Don it's her dating
It's clear from the diary was December 23rd
Navigate Stones testimony at both trials he's a state's Witness
Is milk toast
He just says it was cordial
Which made me wonder why the state even called Don
But according to Don prosecutor Kevin urick might have been wondering the same thing
Don said quotes
When I testified they pulled me in a back room and let me tell you how fun that was. The prosecutor afterwards yelling at me because I did
Not make Adnan sound creepy
He said
They wanted me to make him sound creepy
So creepy that I felt intimidated which I did not
He just was very personable he was funny he was everything that I already said
He was somebody that I would have hung out with if I knew him in school
Don's memory is that you're a gelded him after both the first and second trials
Oh he was irate done said
When I say yelling he was literally yelling about it at me
I ran this by Kevin urick but he said he was not authorized to talk about the case
Don says he loves her
But he still loves her
Is that something that goes away he said
Even though they only officially dated for 13 days
He said she meant a lot to him
She was totally unshy he said
Confident
She pursued him he said for all of December whenever she saw him at work
He said she'd ask him when he was going to take her out constantly she asked him
Followed him into the lunchroom on his brake tester damn
Using someone else at the time but then that ended
And so on New Year's Eve they made their first date for the next day
He fell for a pretty quickly says
Not not like this girl
Choose aggressive intelligent
Assertive is a better word than aggressive
Genuine nice person
Anything I've heard anybody say about our sins
It's not like I want to talk bad about the dead it's just being honest it's
Hard for me to explain
You didn't like her you didn't like her because she was so likeable
But then you couldn't even be annoyed because she wasn't annoying
Thompson hay actually change them
Change the way he thought about himself
He said he'd come off a couple of bad relationships girls who cheated on them
She basically in no uncertain terms told me to knock it off he said
I have worth
I don't remember the word she used
I can't paraphrase it at this point but I am worth having self-esteem
But I should think that I am good enough
And I took it to heart
Especially after I found out that she had died
I'm sorry that it's so late in the game here
I didn't even know that this exists
Yeah that's okay that's okay
Just heard from
And speaking to him all the sudden I was hearing J's perspective
At least this guy's perspective of Jays perspective
He was scared
I mean like terrified
This guy's name is Josh yesterday not use his last name
He said he worked with Jas Southwest video cornstore Josh's 21 at the time
They were close friends he said but Josh would give Jay rides and they smoke weed together and hang out a little bit
Just said that on the night table first picked up by the cops
So late at night on February 27th and to the morning of the 28th
Jay called him at home
And ask him to come into the store cuz he didn't want to be alone there
He was that scared
He was
I mean
Frightened out of his mind and not of the police
Like they were the
The secondary fear I mean he he was afraid to go in the jail but not like
Like he was afraid
Admin I guess it's how you say his name I don't know that's it
Josh does Jay actually never told him a nun's name
But Josh is listen to the podcast so he knows the name now
The back and you didn't
He says Jay told him he was afraid that people were after him
People connected to the murderer
Across the street from the video store was
Parking lot for the Amtrak commuter train
And
Parking lot was usually empty in
In the evening
Well that particular night there was a van
In that parking lot
Which I'm
Pretty positive had nobody in it but
Jay was afraid
I mean like to the female almost in tears
You didn't
Want to go outside
It didn't even want to look out the door
Because he really thought the van that was across the street was like people waiting to get it
But the people you're talking about
Like is it only in retrospect that you're that you're thinking it's like Adnan people or did he say that to you
He said it was
Today's date
I guess at 9
Threatened
Right but you're saying you didn't know he never told you the name of the
I'm just trying to imagine is it possible that it was somebody else entirely who he was
Afraid of
I guess it could have been
But I mean
Whoever you was afraid of his obviously the person that committed the crime
Right
So I'm saying
Did you
Did he express to you at the time that this was
A person with Pakistani
Relatives or I definitely said that it was somebody to
You think I was
Middle Eastern
Josh says Jay told him it was the ex-boyfriend who killed Hae
Was Josh's impression that Jay had called the cops himself at night
Because he told Josh the cops are coming to get him
He seemed anxious that it was taking him so long to get there
Ssj was pacing checking his watch they kept asking him to look outside and see if the van was still there
I tried J testifies that the cops showed up at the video store on their own that he didn't know they were coming
It is taped interview with the police that same night February 28th
Jay doesn't mention a white van or that he's terrified of a nun's people
Just tell the cops that he talked to Adnan either yesterday or the day before
And then turn on was threatening him in a general way
Your tape from that frippery 28th interview
Detective Ritz talks first
What was the last conversation you had with
The most recent conversation you had with intent
That conversation
I'd learned that you guys were looking for me in
How did you learn that
Watch people told me I'm crazy mind told me
Calm down everything will be okay
Where did this conversation take place
I believe in front of my house and its pot
Other than you say know what f*** you do watch give me wrapped up in this
What did he say
Xiaomi
Not going to happen they don't know s***
Drinking all said during that conversation
He told me that he knew somebody I mean
Icing involving lightly whacktivity
Keep on the west side
The gist of what he told me was that you need Westside Hitman so I mean
Olin College
You let me know
Around about weighted
What if you said something for the police that
Yeah cuz I told him I mean I was like
Okay so the Westside Hitman
It's so strange I find Josh's version of J's fear
How much more believable than J's version of J's fear
Which makes me wonder if it's all just in the delivery
When she first told Josh weeks before that he knew something about the missing girl who was all over the news
I said something about you know
Like him not being really involved or whatever you know and then he's like dumb and you understand I helped
Bury the body
It seemed like he was kind of bragging in
And I mean that
Kind of the guy that Jay was
It's not that
He bragged about
Stuff that he did it
Sometimes he made up things that
And so that's kind of what I thought he was doing
Now it's like why would you say that
Did you tell
Somebody that you really don't know that well
How do I didn't believe in
If I had done it I certainly wouldn't
Me
Didn't you know maybe like my best friend
Tonight
That's somebody that you
You work with it a p*** store
The virgin of the crime that Josh has Jay eventually told them it's pretty close to the version that Jay's friend Chris told me
That Jay was out somewhere and that Adnan came to him
And show them the body and said something to the effect of you got to help me
Josh says you can't remember where Jay said he was when this happened but he is certain the words Best Buy we're never attached to the store
Josh went to that Best Buy all the time
And he says he definitely would have remembered that
He said when you heard in the podcast that Chris had mentioned the pool hall thing
That sounded right to him but he can't say for sure
Josh says he also had the impression like Chris
Trade it all gone down later in the day not mid-afternoon
Cast of the first Jason afraid the cops were going to figure out he was involved through fingerprints or DNA or something
But this time went on he seems more and more afraid of the guy who did it
That he was threatening Stephanie
It was you better keep your mouth shut or else
He says J told him the threats were getting more forceful
The Josh J was so not the type to be involved in a murder
Baby tried to act tough he said but he wasn't
He said he himself had friends who got in serious fights or who been locked up for Grand Theft Auto
But Jay was not in that category at all he said
He's a nice guy
It wasn't the type of guy that you
Did you really got the
To do something real
He wants in the Killer
And he wasn't
A song
If anything he was kind of the opposite
Like you feel like he was
In way over his head
Yeah
Remember feeling bad for him
And it was there any point made out of meat
Sound energy or something but like was there any point where you like
Go you should go tell the cops then if you know who did this
Go tell the cops
No not really
I know it's probably what I should have said but I didn't really believe him
And
Like I said
Comes to life
Reputation
I am on the street you don't want to be the guy that's like I'll go snitch
You know you don't want anybody see your week and all that stuff in the cell
I didn't ever say go to the cops
I mean that would be like
Best thing to do
Justice would never quite made sense to him when he never entirely understood
Was YJ would help Adnan bury hay
Even if I didn't call the cops but definitely wouldn't
Rio grab a shovel and help him Dig A Grave
I know that's that's what
Part about the story is you just figure like there's something that's not computing
Hear it. Definitely never sounded right which is why I never believed him
Until the cops actually picked
Josh says he only remembers seeing j one more time after that
Play DJ came by the store to pick up his check
When Josh asked him so what happened
Josh says Jay told him he couldn't talk about it
In preparation for this episode
Julian Dana the producers of the show
Went back over everything we had
All the police files the attorney files the interviews I've done sell records
They did one final sweep just to be sure weed Wade everything
Because old details can have startling new meeting
After a Year's worth of research is behind us
They came across a couple of things they wanted me to know
First and foremost
Anisha call
I'd ask them
Is there any other viable explanation for the Nisha call uninstall record
Hey Julie
We had always been under the impression that the Nisha call was a No Way Around It call looks terrible for his looks
Terrible for him it's
2 minutes and 22 seconds
Remind you the musical is the one that happens at 3:32 p.m. on January 13th
Is that girl in 9 ad been flirting with who live near Silver Spring
Keyshia Cole is the one that's always stuck out to me and I think most people who've looked at in on case closely
Because it happens on the afternoon that hate has appeared at a time when a non has said insisted even that he were
Was not with his phone
The Jay had his phone while he was in school
I told the detectives that I had called some girl in Silver Spring that afternoon
And briefly put on the phone with her
That's why the call is so important
Not only does it put together with his phone in the middle of the afternoon
It puts together with j in the middle of the afternoon
Corroborate Jay's story
I've always had some suspicions about this call because Nisha said to the cops and a trial
But there was a day when on the phone
Benicia has consistently said it happened toward the evening at the video store where they worked
Jaden have the video store job on January 13th
He started that job at the end of the month
So I never bought the idea that the 13th was the day she talked to Jay
But even so it didn't look good for an ion
Because who was calling Misha in the middle of the afternoon then
Jaden Anisha
So for me this call has remained one of the pillars of the case against Adnan
That's what Julie means when she says no way around it
But now I think that you should call might be moving from the No Way Around It this looks bad for add-on column
Into
No I'm not too sure
Announces niches number was programmed into his cell phone
So he's always said to me
Maybe the button got pushed accidentally
Like a butt dial
And then the answering machine picked up
The problem with that explanation besides how convenient it sounds
Is it there was no answering machine on that line
That's what niches has a trial
This call shows up not just on the call log but on an AT&T bill he got charged for it
So this was our Quest or really dating Julia Quest
Define out is it possible this call would have shown up in an oz Bill even if it went unanswered
This proved so elusive
First we got one answered then another and another then another
AT&T was not helping us
Finally figured out exactly what they needed to answer this question
An AT&T customer service agreement Circa 1999
They found one
In a class action lawsuit against AT&T that included as an exhibit
The very document we need it
Luckily that class action lawsuit was filed in New York so Dana was able to go down to the
The old records
Department
Supreme Court
Or something like that yeah
It look like like a Mad Hatter's
Like the archive
Are you the first humanoid
The Dana goes down there pulls the service agreement takes pictures of
The contract
Send the first picture the first picture says on the contract that says we do not bill
For unanswered calls
The Nisha call had to have been answered
If it shows up on the bill
There was fine print to the fine print
And when did a flip through the contract the last page she found
A loophole
The loophole says
AT&T won't charge for unanswered calls
Unless the call isn't terminated within a quote reasonable time
So if you call someone and it rings and rings and don't hang up within a reasonable time
AT&T will charge you for that call
Even if it's not answered
So what is a reasonable amount of time
Or rather an unreasonable amount of time
That loophole actually still exist today and the unreasonable amount of time today
Is 30 seconds or longer they'll charge
We saw one contract from 99 that specified 60 seconds or longer
So it stands to reason that 2 minutes
We're probably covered
They probably did charge
The folks at AT&T told us the only reason a contract with a very back then in 99 was if the state had passport
Make it there legislation to address it
We didn't find anything in the Maryland rules about it
So after all this work we feel pretty confident that AT&T would have charged
Furcal that rang and rang for more than 2 minutes in Maryland
In 1999
So either way it's if it's 2 minutes
2 seconds
It's probably unreasonable
It's probably time to be listening to
The phone rang I got to say without
Trying to figure this out
I know that's a long and perhaps
Way too detailed way of explaining it
All this adds up to something important
It means the Nisha call could conceivably have been a butt dial but no one answered
It means there isn't only one explanation for the Nisha call
There alternative scenarios
It could be that a non called Misha
With somebody else to call Nisha
Or maybe or someone else call Nisha by accident
A butt dial
And no one was ever the wiser
Because no one ever picked up
And if there are alternative scenarios then that means the list of things we know actually definitively know
Facts we can show about the evidence against Adnan
That list
Just got shorter
The only hard evidence in the case against Adnan
Is his cell phone record for January 13th
That's what the cops and prosecutors used to corroborate Jay statements
Julie looked at that same record all over again the call log and the cell tower map
Teased it all apart
To see if they could figure out what happened
To figure out if there was anything else I could know about what Jay and Adnan were doing that day
We talked about the call out a lot already
We already knew it didn't match Jays explanations of where they went and when
But when Julie left again she realized when she tried to assign the calls some semblance of a narrative
Her picture of the day crumbled even more
Instead of answering any of her questions the call log raise the bigger ones
Such as was everyone lying about that day
My original question going into this whole Endeavor this whole story
Was
Either json or anions lying
But what if it's not either or
What if it's both
And
The college evidence is screwy right from the beginning
Jay said that when he had an unmet up that morning when a non drove over to Jay's to give him his car they done shopping at the mall
Various things but not that they went shopping
What seems most likely according to what an Untold his
Attorney at the time
Is it an on Hangout with Jay until about
12:45 1 p.m. and then went back to
School
There's a 12:07 call and a1241 call
The first thing that our out west in Ellicott City
The next exit our back East for Baltimore City
They're pretty far apart from each other
Text Julie
Going to Ellicott City
And then going into Baltimore city where the phone is pinging off of like Edmondson Avenue area which
Actually
Assertive
Near
Drug strips
Where his car was dumped
That sort of area of Baltimore
That's not mentioned
Buy at 9
So I don't remember what we did I know we didn't go shopping
I'm not really sure
I feel
More
Concerned
And suspicious I feel suspicious
Okay have being like
Huh
Cuz I can back where I can see where the phone was moving
I know Jay story about
Security Square Mall is not true
Because of the phone if they had the phone
But I don't think it done gif
Is true either
Yeah
End end
Can I also add that at
At one point John says to the detectives that she remembers
One of those phone calls she answered and talked to J&J it said that she was downtown with an on
The prosecutor at trial said we don't really know what they were doing
But it doesn't matter
Because he was in school at that time alive
And that's true
But still the phone record tells us that there's something they're not telling us
Why
And is it related to what happened later
The next call is the incoming 236 call the supposed Best Buy call from the phone booth
That were pretty solidly convinced wasn't the come and get me call
I do have something of an update there
We've not found evidence of a phone booth outside the Best Buy on the sidewalk like Jade rosin is Matt for the cops
Anecdotal reports
That there was a payphone inside the best
We haven't been able to verify these reports but
We did get a look at the 1994 architectural plans for that Best Buy
The plants are the teeny little rectangle on the left as you walk in
Labeled
Payphone
So maybe there was one
Inside
The call log
Julie spent a long time thinking about the 321 call it opened a whole new mystery for her
Because it's confusing on about three different levels
It's an outgoing call from a non cell
To Jen's house phone
Jay and Jen both talked about some call that afternoon that comes into her landline
Someone supposedly Looking for Jay
Jen said she remembers Jake getting phone calls while he's at our house
Jay says he remembers getting phone calls
While at the house
Both of them also reference
A landline
Jay says I get a call on the landline and that's when I leave
Meaning write this incoming landline call is Adnan calling in
Looking for Jay
Why would it not be calling you on the landline the whole point of him giving you the cell phone was so that he could call you on the cell phone
It doesn't make any sense
But there is a 321
Call
Made from the cell phone
To Jen's house
Here's the second confusing thing
Jay eventually told the cops the 321 call was a call he made
Did Jen
Asking if she knew whether this guy Patrick was around
Jay was looking for weed from Patrick
Jen by the way testified this never would have happened that Jay would never call her asking about Patrick
But anyway
And here's the third thing
The confusing kicker
Both Jay and Jen also say Jay was at Jen's house
Until about 3:45 p.m. that day
That also has always confused me
AJ is still at Jen's house until 3:45
How is he calling John's house at
Why would he be calling the house that is
Sitting in
Unless Adnan has
Unless a dozen
MSU doesn't have
I'm not saying who has the phone right now
The founder
But it leads me to believe that there is a possibility that Jay doesn't have it
Phone
So what's the evidence that Jay does have the phone
Jen tells the police that she saw Jay with the phone that afternoon she's an image of the cell phone in her mind
Sitting on the coffee table at her house
At 3:21 the tower that spanked isn't the one that covers Jen's house
If she doesn't have the phone though
Then who was the phone
And more to the point if Jade doesn't have the phone
And what was going on that afternoon
Then I have no idea what was going on
There were discrepancies unresolved
All throughout the afternoon and evening right up until the end of the night when there's a big one
Beginning and he does bring it up at trial on it too long
What is odd
Jen and Jay tell different stories about where she picked him up on the night of the 13th
And about where and when they got rid of his clothes and Boots
Jen says she picked her up at Westview Mall where she saw Adnan to
That didn't happen
He says she picked him up at his house and he dumped his clothes that same night the 13th
The first time he tells that he says he threw them out in the trash at his own house
But Jen says she tossed his clothes and some dumpsters the next day
There would have been a terrible ice storm happening but maybe
Different stories
Unreconciled
And they actually assertive
Both kind of digging on it
Yeah I know it to it
And I
Somebody's wrong
Don't believe it's an oversight
But I cannot work my head around
What is the
What is the lie that is minimizing what
Right
What's the utility of which liability of which lies yeah
You can fly that same question what's the utility of which lie to this entire case
There's so much that is murky
All you can do at a certain point
Speculate
And believe me we have
Angelina I speculate about all sorts of things
Like crazy we speculate
Rest assured that in the privacy of our office
We turned over every possibility no matter how remote
99% of what we speculate I cannot report
Because
But we can't back it up speculation
But here's one I can tell you if recently discussed
We loop-de-loop all the way back to motive
I know I dismissed the mode of the state supplied way back in episode 2
But we put it back on the table just to see where it took us
Here we got
We've always said Anan was over The breakup
11 a month already
I just for argument's sake let's say he wasn't over it
Inanna hey broken up and gotten back together a few times
Break up in mid-December maybe a non-sexual change your mind again
They're still friendly several people said to me they couldn't tell or didn't even know that had another broken up
Or said and I was still referring to her as his girlfriend
Or said he told them he thought they get back together
Don said he never quite knew what the deal was between them
But judging from his diary by January her romantic feelings are completely absorbed by Don
Remember the first date is January 1st
But maybe a non didn't feel the full force
How she moved on until they got back to school after Christmas break
Richard Dana realized recently
That first week of school in 99
Anon was absent two out of four days and then Friday was a snow day
So maybe he doesn't get it that he's really lost
Until that first or second week back at
School
Christina
Maybe that's when reality sets in for him and maybe that's when
Yeah maybe that's when the
The emotion synonym
And so does kind of lose it
And so maybe he doesn't lose it
But who else does this
Hayes Ordnance friends whom I spoke to
Says they saw it like this
Set the time
I don't even speculate now that they're adults that maybe it could have been like this
So who are we to put this Theory forward
This is a very obvious problem with speculation especially of the emotional variety
You can't prove it
So you have to drop it
So where does this leave us
There's no point in trying to come up with a most likely scenario for what happened to hey
Because you could pause it a hundred scenarios
And so what
Arrest of more facts that are facts
Even the soberest most likely scenario
Holds no more water than the most hare-brained
An equation of a nonce case
All speculation is equally speculative
Most likely
How about most logical
Dana has always been very logical about a Nas case she's the mr. Spock of our staff
Herzing is
Let's say you didn't do it
But if you didn't do it
And my God that guy is ridiculously unlucky
Imma let her lay it out
Nonna's always sad
It was his idea to loan Jay the car
Because
He wanted dad to go get Stephanie
A birthday present right
So that's pretty crappy lot that you loaned this guy who ends up
Pointing finger at you for the murder that you loaned him your car
And cell phone the day that your ex girlfriend goes with
The next thing is that it seems pretty clear to me
They did not have to pay for a ride after
High School
Because
We've got
At least two of
Their friends saying they overheard him ask
Four rides okay
Did not himself tell the cop that died he asked
Center for a ride
And in his first interview with the detective
She says to them
Anon plan
Was he getting his car by telling her that
His car was broken down and asking
Perfect ride
When's the next the next piece of bad luck is the Nisha call I mean even if the Nisha call could
Potentially be a butt dial
It's still a possibility
That sucks for you that your phone butt dialed a girl that only you
No one would call
On this day that your ex-girlfriend goes missing that you happen to loan your car and your phone out to the guy who end up pointing the finger at you
That sucks
And then the last thing that I think really sucks
For him if he's innocent
Is
Jstory and the cell phone records
Matchup
From about 6 to about 8
Which is when Jay is saying that you are burying the body
And
That's the time of the day when you just have no memory
Of where you are
And you have your dad saying you were at the mosque
And maybe Bilal your your
You're useless eater
Panera test
You never testified at the trial with testifies in Grand Prairie
After Dark
At the mosque
But you would not you don't really remember where you were that evening
And that Blank Spot in your memory
That's the that's the window of time when J story actually does seem to be corroborated by the cell phone records
Seem to be corroborated yes but J statement only roughly matches the leakin park calls and 8 calls
Really roughly
The geography matches but not the timing
But I take your point
So I guess
I guess
It just it in order to make him completely innocent of this
You just have to thank God that is like you had so many terrible coincidences that day there were so many
You had such
Padlock
That day is not on
A lot of people sent this way
I've heard from people who say just so quickly
Is Tony guilty
Newsflash people lie in murder cases
On the witness stand what to do
Did we just spend a year applying excessive scrutiny to a perfectly ordinary case
Call Jim training back up he's the former homicide detective we hired to review the investigation
Unremarkable
We took a magnifying glass to any murder case would we find similar questions similar whole similar inconsistent
He said most cases sure they have some ambiguity
But overall they're fairly clear
This one is a mess
She said
The holes are bigger than they should be
Review cases lawyers
The forensic psychologist
They told us the same thing
This case is a mess
Rabbit holding in our office
Back out in the world those lawyers from the University of Virginia law school Innocence Project Clinic
I've been coming up with their own most logical explanation
But you couldn't be more different from Dana's
I haven't reported anything about it up to now but over the weekend there was a development of sorts so now I can tell you
Deirdre Enright and her students have a motion in the works
To test the DNA from anons case that wasn't tested
The swabs from his body
The material from under her fingernails the hair is found on her body
Emotion like this you have to give a viable reason to test the
The stuff you have to show how it could potentially exculpate you
And deirdre's reason is
She thinks the DNA might not some other guy
The other guy started way back when date and I went down to Charlottesville last February
Mario one of her students
Start looking online for
Possible signs of a serial killer basically
I already told him about another strangling of young woman who was also found in the Baltimore Park different Park
Thing led to another and It Came Upon yet another case
Cold Case
I stumbled Upon a
A website
That
Categorize all the unsolved murders in
In Baltimore County and she was there
I know your computer's not open now.
Anneliese
Young Circle
I believe she was also Korean
227 when she was killed strangled in her apartment
In Owings Mills
Tucson on December 13th 1999
Exactly 11 months after he disappeared
I can see why Mario was interested
So is that your get so will you look into that now
Absolutely
Slater I got a message to call Deirdre
Huge news
Deirdre Enright Sarah
Huge news in this is attorney huge not necessarily reporter huge but anyway
The news was that she spoken to someone in the Baltimore County Police Department to ask about this unsolved case of
Anneliese Lee
So I'm going to tell you quickly because I have to get on the call at 2:30 okay
But so I called Sergeant something
Sergeant something told her that they now had a suspect for this Owings Mills case from 15 years ago
They tested similar DNA and a match came back
Tube this other guy who done other crimes mostly burglaries
These at my guy was in prison a lot
And he said he had a really tiny window of being out and about and he was very active while he was out and about
And so
He said
During that time that he was out we linked him to to rape
Anna murder
Animoto
And all of them appeared to be burglary but he always have sex with people
And he said
That he got out and became active
14 months his release date is January 1
Oh my God
Right
So what's his name
He wouldn't tell me his name out loud
But I'm already accidentally referred to him as Ronald
And did he bury his victims
I didn't he was like he I think he felt like he was telling me too much already
Deirdre later learn this guy's name was Ronald Lee Moore
Ronald Morris dead now he killed himself
But it seems like he committed lots of crimes
He been in prison in Baltimore for a while on assault and burglary convictions
According to a Baltimore Sun article in 2007 he was supposed to get transferred to a different jail in Anne Arundel County
So you can be prosecuted for a different crime
But the Baltimore officials released him by accident
He was arrested about a month later in Louisiana
Burglary
I figured out who he was and that he was wanted back in Maryland
This is the guy the Baltimore County cops linked through DNA
To the death of Anneliese in Owings Mills
And this is the guy that Deirdre and her gang are naming in their motion to test the DNA from a nonce case
It's a long shot that they'll be anything testable in those samples
And it's a long shot that if there is it'll match anyone but hey
And most long shot of all that if it does match someone else
That someone else happens to be Ronald Lee Moore
As I have several times she always shoots right back
What makes more sense
That little 17 year old never been in trouble with the law Adnan kill someone
Or that Ronald more rapist and murderer who got out of prison 13 days before he disappeared
But he killed someone
Right I know I say
What about Jay
He knew where his car was
He had to be involved
How does that account for J
Big picture Sarah
Take picture
Meanwhile Adnan post-conviction petition is still alive in the Maryland Court of special Appeals
His attorney Justin Brown is working on a way to bring the issue of the Asia Alibi before the court again
I spoke to Asia recently
She told me she stand by her memories of seeing an on that January afternoon in the public library
And she stands by her affidavit
Post-conviction purposes
Asia's Alibi is still a big deal
It sure would seem to point ineffective assistance of counsel
It's funny though knowing what we now know about the state's garble timeline and that he was maybe still alive at 2:45 or 2
3 p.m.
Aces Library Alibi doesn't pack the same punch for me
As it once did
Deirdre and Justin Brown have been giving it done conflicting advice lately about how best to
Proceed
What to push for and when
But on Saturday is for the go-ahead to file the motion to test DNA
It was an emotional decision for him
Anything about my case I want to know it
I don't want anyone to be able to say what you do want to know so boom we went and found out I want to know
And I wanted you to
But I'm the one that asked for this
You guys had it sitting for 16 years
You never tested it
It's impossible
You guys never tested it
I want to see what it says
Just nothing about my case and I'm afraid of
Back to a non question
Do I have an ending
I was just thinking about everything I said I'm pretty sure she probably has people telling her like look
You know you know this
You're going to try to find out
I don't think you'll ever have 100%
Or you not inside any type of certainty about the only person in the whole world you can have that
And I mean for what it's worth whoever did it
And I will never have that I don't
Anon told me all I wanted was to take the narrative back from the prosecution just as an exercise
People could see his case without makeup on
Look at it in the eye up close
And make your own judgment
He told me
I don't think I should weigh in the middle
Just go down the middle that you know
Already but I check these things out and do things
These are the things that look bad against us
The things that you noticed a cousin really have an answer for
You can even go point-for-point
Lssu leave it up to the volume
Appreciate announce blessing to take a powder I'm not going to
Janus right to be skeptical
What are the chances one guy got so unlucky
But everything lined up against him just so
Because yes there's a police file full of information
Circumstantial information
Let's put another file next to that one side by side
In that second file let's put all the other evidence we have linking and onto the actual crime
The actual killing
What do we have
What do we know not what we think we know
What do we know
If a college does not back up Jay story
Phoenicia call is no longer set in stone
Don't think about it
All we're left with is
Jay knew where the car was
That's it
And that all by itself
This is not a story
It's a beginning but it's not a story it's not enough
To me to send anyone to prison for life nevermind a seventeen-year-old kid
Because you mean the state of Maryland
Based on the information we have before us
Don't believe any of us can say what really happened to her
As a juror I vote to acquit Adnan Syed
I have to acquit
Even if in my heart of hearts I think Adnan killed Hae
I still have to acquit
That's what the law requires of jurors
I'm not a juror
So just as a human being walking down the street next week what do I think
Do you want me to swear that Adnan Syed is innocent
I couldn't do it
I nursed out
I don't like that but I do
I mean most of the time I think he didn't do it
Four big reasons like the utter lack of evidence
But also small reasons
Things he said to me just off-the-cuff for moments when he's crying on the phone and tried to stifle it so I wouldn't hear
I just a bear fact
Why on Earth would a guilty man agree to let me do this story
Unless he was cocky to the point of delusion
I used to think that one has friends told me
I can't say for sure if he's innocent but the guy I knew there's no way he could have done this
I still think that was a cop out
Way to avoid asking yourself uncomfortable disloyal disheartening questions
But I think I'm there now too
And not for lack of asking myself those hard questions
But because as much as I want to be sure
I'm not
First told me about Adnan case
Certainty one way or the other seems so attainable
We just needed to get the right documents
Spend enough time talk to the right people find us a lullaby
And then I did find Asia and she was real and she remembered and we all thought
How hard could this possibly be
We just have to keep going
And now I'm more than a year later
I feel like shaking Everyone by the shoulders like an aggravated cop
Don't tell me it's a nice guy
Don't tell me Jay was scared
Don't tell me you might have made some 5 Second phone call
Just tell me the facts ma'am
Cuz we didn't have them 15 years ago
We still don't have them now
Materials produced by Julie Schneider Dana Chavis and me Emily Condon is our production and operation
Missions manager eyeglasses are editorial advisor
Beijing help this week from Joe level and Nancy Updike
Production help from Sean Cole
Research and fact-checking by Michelle Harris administrative support from at least bergersen
Are scores by Mark Phillips who also mix the episode our theme song is by Nick thorburn Who provided additional
Special things today to Oliver Monday David Chris Cunningham I've seen David Raphael
Spouses Ben schreier Jeff Melman and Rachel Hammerman
Thank you all
And things to WBEZ at the goalie sheikholeslami
A huge thank you to the entire staff of This American Life most especially to Southland who gave us operations of
Sports route the entire season thank you
Our website where you can listen to all our episodes and find photos letters and other documents from the case
Serialpodcast.org
If you want season 2 coming sometime in 2015 please sign up for a email newsletter
That serial podcast. Org
In the meantime we help you listen to our other show This American Life is a radio show and a podcast this American
Goodnight. Org
Serial production of This American Life and WBEZ Chicago