Hello serial listeners
It's Sarah Cain egg with a quick reminder
That we have two other podcast
There's This American Life weekly show that chooses one theme and then has a mix of weird emotional and
Investigative
And personal stories on that theme
Cereal started as a spinoff of This American Life
Are we developed our storytelling jobs
And also s-town
Beautiful 7-part series that explores the life of one man in Alabama
S town starts out as one thing and then becomes something totally
Fascinatingly different
This American Life and s-town
Available now on podcast apps
Or At This American Life. Org and stown podcast. Org
Tinseltown
Global Tel Link
Prepaid call from
Adnan Syed
Maryland Correctional Facility
It's called from This American Life and WBEZ Chicago its serial one story told week by week I'm sorry
The last year I spent everywhere
Working day trying to figure out where a highschool kid was
For an hour after school one day in 1999
Or if you want to get technical about it and apparently I do wear a high school kid was for 21 minutes after school one day
299 this search sometimes feels undignified on my part
Ask about teenagers sex lives where how often with him
I'm not a detective investigator
But yes every day this year I tried to figure out The Alibi of a 17 year old boy
Before I get into why I've been doing this I just want to point out something I never really thought about before I start working on this story
And that is really hard to account for your time and a detailed way I mean
How to get to work last Wednesday 4 instead
Drive Walker
Bike
Is it raining
Are you sure
Did you go to any stores that day
If so what did you buy
Who did you talk to
Name every person you talk to
It's hard
Now imagine you have to account for a day that happens 6 weeks back
Is that the situation in the story I'm working on
Which a bunch of teenagers had to recall a day six weeks earlier
And it was 1999 so they had to do it without the benefit of texts or Facebook or Instagram
Just for a lark I asked him teenagers to try it
Do you remember what you did on that Friday
I can't remember anything
No
I can't hear anything that fall back
Pretty I'm pretty I'm pretty sure I was in school
I think no
That's Tyler he's 18
Not clue
Albion School
Actually I can't work that day
DIY work that day and I went to school as that it
Actually on second thought
Didn't I didn't I didn't
To Sam's friend Elliott
You seem to have better recall
Actually I'm a God movie that night later
22 Jump Street
Okay
And what did you go with friends
Sam Manny
Did Shawn Carter bunch of people
Okay to Sam says he was at work
So that it wasn't that nice then
When kid did actually remember pretty well because it was the last day of State Testing at his school
Nightclub
That's the main thing I learned from this exercise which is no big shocker I guess
Is that a fun significant event happened that day
You remember that
Plus you remember the entire day much better
If nothing significant happened then the answers give very general
I most likely did this or I most likely did that
These are words I've heard a lot lately
Here's a case I've been working on
Almost 15 years ago on January 13th 1999
A girl named Hae Min Lee disappeared
She was a senior at Woodlawn High School in Baltimore County Maryland
She's Korean too smart and beautiful and cheerful and great athlete
Field hockey and Lacrosse
She was responsible
Ready for school she was supposed to pick up her little cousin from kindergarten
Drop her home
But you didn't show
That's when Halley's family knew something was up when the cousin school called
Body was found in a big Park in Baltimore
Maintenance guy who discovered her there
He noticed a bit of her black hair poking out of shallow grave
The cause of death was manual strangulation
Did it with their hands
A couple weeks after that I'm 6 weeks after she first went missing
Ex boyfriend was arrested for her murder
He's been in prison ever since
I first heard about this story more than a year ago when I got an email from a woman and Rabia choudry
Best friend
I used to be a reporter for the Baltimore Sun
And she come across some stories are written about a well-known defense attorney in Baltimore
Could been disbarred for mishandling client money
It was the same person who defended Anan
Last major trial in fat
Not just botched it actually went through the case on purpose so she could get more money for the appeal
Later she been sick
I don't get emails like this
I read a few newspaper clips about the case lookup a few trial records
The case was like a Shakespearean mashup
Young lovers from different worlds
Supporting their families
Secret assignation
Jealousy suspicion and honor besmirched
Exactly but a Muslim all the same
The Final Act of murderous Revenge
A regular old high school
Across the street from the 7-Eleven
Hi how are you I am I seeing your name correctly
Rabia
She's surrounded by paper
Files BlueStacks binders crappy looking boxes
I'll court documents in attorneys files from add-ons case
Some of the papers were warped and discolored
How do they look wet they look like wet
You have been yeah this event damage because because the boxes have been in a car on and off
For 15 years
Herself mostly does immigration stuff
At the corner of a much larger open space that I think is a Pakistani travel agency that's hard
Tell
Sing this little strip mall
Across the parking lot there's a new Pakistani restaurant and African Evangelical Church in Indian clothing shop convenience store
On the sidewalk outside I found a teeny weeny bag of marijuana
Baltimore county is like this at least on the west side
Through a lot of middle-class and working-class people go many immigrants included
To get the kids out of the badass City
Nevada city is close by
Is 40 too short and she's got a beautiful round face Rain by hijab
She's adorable looking but you definitely shouldn't mess with her
She's very smart and very tough
Crush you
Her brother's side with attributes office to the first time I went
He's 33 and mortgage broker
More laid-back and Rabia
They told me about Adnan Syed
The friend
Not just a good kid but an especially good kid
Smart
Kind goofy handsome
Arrested for murder
So many people who knew him were stunned
He was like The community's Golden Child
We'll talk more about that
He was an honor roll student
Volunteer EMT
He was like on the football team he was a
Star
Star runner on the track team
He was
Homecoming King
Healing prayers at the mosque
So he was
Yeah he everybody
New Adnan to be you know
Somebody's going to do something really big
Later fact-checked all these accolades of course
Mostly right though she sometimes gets a little loosey-goosey with the details
Anon wasn't empty but he didn't volunteer his paid for it
He was on the track team but it wasn't a star
He did play football and he did leave prayers on occasion
He wasn't homecoming King but he was Prince of his junior prom
Minnesota high school is majority black
You pick the Pakistani Muslim
To get the picture
He was incredibly likable and well-liked
White kid
This conversation with Robbie inside
This is what launch me on this year long
Obsession is maybe too strong a word what's a fascination
What does case
By the end of the shower you're going to hear different people tell different versions what happened the day Hayley was
Killed
Let's start with the most important version of the story
Told me first
And that's the one that was presented at trial
The state's case against Adnan what like this
TNA been going out since junior prom
Wasn't supposed to be dating at all was born in the US but his parents are from Pakistan
What if Muslims
No drinking smoking a girl's all that
Even though they were also
What teenagers do so long as they didn't get caught
Has relationship with a secret
The state use this against him in two ways
First
He put everything on the line
Relationships
This girl
So that when she broke up with him eight months later he was left with nothing and he was outraged
He couldn't take it
What do what a liar he is
Duplicitous
Play Sturgill Simpson at home and at the mosque but look what he was up to
Start remember the prosecutor's closing argument at trial
His family didn't know that he actually drank
He smoke
He was having sex
This was proof of bad character
Someone who could be a murderer
But that says if it not guilty of anything
Is it being a normal kid with immigrant parents
Selective prosecution
Had
Painted anion as a totally like a bipolar or like a maniacal dual personality
I mean I'm the same way I lie they could paint the same thing because I was
Was actually homecoming King which I don't know if my sister even knows
So I mean I was dating a girl that was
Why is homecoming King bad is that such a good thing
It's a damn it's a mixed-gender so so I was in the same boat
My parents
My sister didn't know about this at all I mean
It right now 10 years more than 10 years later she's fine
Hangout
Admit on one side like my family thinks I'm a virgin but on the other hand I played
But it's
Like that right there I mean it's kind of making her feel uncomfortable
Saint Raphael found the whole thing
As for physical evidence
There was none
Nothing
Apart from some fingerprints in his car which should not have been in many times
There was nothing linking him to the crime
No DNA no fibers no hair
Matching soil from the bottom of his boots
Instead with a hat on a Nan was one guy's story
I got MJ
He's the third person you need to remember in this crime story
Besides Hannah.
Was a friend of an on-site been in school together since middle school they weren't super close but no friends
Turn on smoke together
The story Jay told police had problems
Because it kept changing from telling to telling
By the time I left his office at first day I understood only one thing clearly
Understand
What is it was somebody is lying here
Give me a gun really is innocent
What did he did do it and he's got all these good people thinking he didn't
Someone is lying
And I really wanted to figure out who
In the early morning of February 28th 1999 was arrested by Baltimore City detective
He's asleep in his bed when they showed up at his house
They took him straight from his untidy bedroom
Turn interrogation room at homicide downtown
What are non didn't notice it just hours before they picked him up
The cops had interviewed his friend Jay
This is a taped interview of Jay
Black male 19 years of age
Workhouses of homicide
Specifically the Colonel's conference room
The police recorded two taped interviews with Jay and I'm going to play you the second one from a couple weeks later only because the sound quality is much better
Just a warning that the tape is a little upsetting to hear in parts
Why don't you go ahead and tell us
What you know about the death of
Pay lake
Head
Laugh out loud
What shopping
With a friend of mine
Next friend of mine hang on
We had a conversation
Going to College Station Stadium
He's going to kill that b****
The train Haley
Check in with contacts in
Standout mine
She said she didn't take it too seriously
Start again from the top
On the morning of the 13th json
Not have left school and driven to Jay's house
Graduated from school the year before and was working
But on that day
January 13th birthday of Jay's girlfriend Stephanie
And Jaden have his own card needed to go buy something for
According to go shopping at the mall
Which you do that
Place Mall
I took him to school
I dropped him off in the back of the school
You left your cell phone in car with me told me he call me
I went back to my friend Jen's house and wait from the car
Hey now at this point
You know why he's leaving the car with you yes
And why is that
Hey
And the reason you have the car
And the cell phone was why
Pick him up from
Wherever he was going to do this
And
You had talked about this
While you were shopping
BatDad
The details of
The car and all the events how they were going to
Planet
That day he told me yes she told me I'm going to leave you with my cell phone and my car I need
I need you to come get me
Yes after
After you kill Hades
Later that afternoon the Call Comes
You receive a phone call from Aetna
Yes on his cell phone
And
The conversation was what
That picture said
Come and get me I'm at
Best Buy
Directions to Best Buy
Season on in the parking lot
All my heart next to him
Cast and get out the car I get out of the car he asked me am I ready for this
And I see ready for what
And he autistic easy open the trunk and
All I can see is
Pisces lips are blue and she's like pretzel up in the back of the trunk and
The parking lot is driving his car with a body in the trunk
Jay is driving a nice car
They ditch his car at the I-70 park and ride
As if nothing happened
Buy some weed cruise around make some calls
Woodlawn High School
Why did you take him back to school you told me that I had to take him back to school because
He needed to be seen
Was he going to a certain event
Pause practice track-by-track practice
So he wanted an out
He wanted to be seen by the people
Are you guys have discussed that
He just told me that he need to be seen
Yes he told me that he needed to be seen
Itrackbites
You took it back
Are you having any conversation
With that
Defect yes don't tell anyone
He said he couldn't believe you kill somebody with their hands it all out
Motherfukers referring to like hoods and tells himself think you're hardcore but he could kill the person with his bare hands
So at this point he's
He was proud of it
Yes
After track practice Jacobsen on up again they drive around some more
His family was worried and they called the police
Who in turn called a couple of his friends including Adnan
Call comes in on his cell cops ask if he's seen her or knows where she is
Chase's after the call the drive to Jay's to get some shovels
Dollar Tree Hays Car from the park and ride
The drive around some more and finally end up at leakin Park
Red94 seeds to Barry hay
Is eating by now maybe 7 or 8 p.m.
And I
He asked me if I was going to help
He starts to shoveling dirt on top of it
Blackout really there
Free stuff
You helped him.
How long did it take you
Did they take the whole
25 minutes
Audi
Did you make the home
Maybe
Wasn't very deep at all
Equal work
I want to say that but
So those are the key points
Anon told Janet
She did it
We buried her
A story wasn't just the foundation of the state's case against Adnan
It was the state's case against Adnan
It's cold
Describing a crime of passion hair
This is something much darker
Methodically map out the death of your friend
Strangle her with her own hands so close up like that
A killer but a master liar and manipulator psychopath probably
Maximum Security Prison in Western Maryland
He calls me at my request about twice a week
Direct me from a bank of eight payphones in the Rec Hall
Pretty large room where other guys are sitting at tables with middle seats
Attached to them
Playing chess or cards using a microwave or watching TV
And get a little loud sometimes
Once I asked if all 8 phones are always occupied he said because guys have been in for a long time
How to call
21st in person I was struck by two things
He was way bigger than expected
Barrel-chested and tall
Minnesota sightseeing
30 to life in prison becoming larger and properly bearded
And the second thing what you can't miss about Adnan
Is that he has giant brown eyes like a dairy cow
That's a promise my most idiotic lines of inquiry
Could someone who looks like that really strangle his girlfriend
Idiotic
You first heard a story of the crime I didn't mean for it to happen like that
He said
It didn't happen
None of this is true
At all
He said he had nothing to do with his murder and he doesn't know who did
He was announced first serious relationship with a girl
He said he loved her in the way of high school love but then also in the way of high school got over her
So that when they broke up for good sometime before Christmas break of senior year
He says he was sad for sure but not obsessed
I just sometimes wish like they can look into my brain
I see how I really felt about it and no matter what else I'm going to say they were seen that this guy had no
I have no ill-will towards whatever the motivation is to kill someone I had absolutely
You know what I mean
Don't you ever say why
Soulmate is mad
Going to never come with any type of proof or anything
Everything
I was never mad at her that I was ever
Angry with her that I have a threatened
Yeah that's the only thing I can really hold on
He's adamant about this you can hear it right he's staunch
To go back and tell his version of what happened that day
CJ story
Everything becomes a lot in maschera
Yes he hung out with Jay on the 13th both during and after school
He doesn't remember exactly where they were
What time it was
January 14th and folded like any other day
Normal mostly uneventful day
He says there are a couple of things that do stand out though
Stephanie's birthday
Stephanie was one of a dog's best friend
And also J's girlfriend
Stephanie a birthday present
Stuffed reindeer which is given to her and second.
Miss a friend English class
It occurred to me that days at
I was going to ask your boyfriend
Did you get hurt
So sometime during the day
4 News
Hold up for a second
Stephanie of a president
Well. Stephanie was very close friend of mine
It was just
I just got to make sure that
She also got a gift from him
You know she had mentioned
She was looking forward to getting
We have to get to kiss that I gave her
So it just as I would with any friends
I just kind of
We don't want to check on that
You didn't get her a gift
Can I have free periods
Jordan schools
It was not abnormal for me to leave school to go to
And then come back
So I went to this house
What happened to
Get a present for Stephanie she said no
My car
And just come
Pick me up after track practice
So then what happened
Well then
When school is over
I would have went to the library
I know that
I use chat with other music but if I was going to check my email using the library computer
Sometimes I would go there
Because track practice didn't start until around
Maybe 3 or 3:30 ish
So I can start right after school
So they would appear to sign up almost like an hour hour and change
This hour and change after school this is the crucial window
This is the time when the state says hey was killed
School got out of 215 people remember seeing her after her last class heading to her car
Story on the cell phone records
She was dead by 2:36 p.m.
So sometime in those 21 minutes
Between 2:15 and 2:36
She strangled
Obviously the same window and non needed to account for
Dakota
My case lived and died in those 21 minutes
Well maybe the library but nobody testified at a trial
To track practice
He does remember being a track one day when it was snowing which might have been that day
The coach testified that probably was there but he can't be a hundred percent sure
As a rule he didn't take attendance
After school is when his memories become nonspecific
Usually we did this are we probably would have done that
Did come to pick up at 9 after track that pardoned on seems to more less remember
Was Ramadan so it would have been fasting all day and hungry
It probably would have been closer to time for me to break fast
He would have came to pick me up
Everybody went to go get something to eat
So sweet after I eat and then I would have had to have gone
Did home by like around 7
Or usually like the last 10 nights of Ramadan my father would spend the night at the mosque
A lot of times I would take your food
Pixel format how to take it
Evening prayer
Did you ever
Leave the campus
Before the end of track track
Did you ever
You sure
I want to say that I'm 99% sure
The reason why I can't see hundred is because
I mean I understand that it comes across as
I don't know if it does or doesn't but it seems like I remember things that are beneficial to me but things that are beneficial thing that I can't remember
It's just that I don't really know what to say that a lot of it
I do remember it
Missing pieces that comes from what other people have sex
You know that they remember write any kind of
Ananda is problematic because
If he's innocent right it's any other day of course he doesn't remember
But you can also read it as
How convenient he doesn't remember the day
Story
Because he has no story
Definitely understand it's going to look at this to say all men must be lying is so coincidental
He doesn't remember what he did
I mean I completely understand that
Can I get that
Just feel like I said
There's nothing casual I can do
You remember that day
Nothing I can do
You know to Make Me Remember transcript
Telephone records
And it is what it is you're not you not have no control over
Is a long ordeal
Cell phone expert testified for 2 days
Lifetime when you're discussing cell tower technology
Their absences and some bad weather close the courts
So six weeks before both sides rested
The jury
After just a few hours including a lunch break
They convicted in on a first-degree murder
Chaudhry was there in the courtroom when it happen
She said his mother was crying
She was crying
I hadn't slept through the whole trial so the first time she fully understood that the case came down to those 21 minutes
Was during closing arguments
When the prosecutor brought out of dummies head and strangled it in front of the jury
After the verdict Robbie went to see a nun in lockup
And so I went to go see her
I was at the first time I actually had a conversation with
I'm about
It what's going on and I was like the whole thing was turning on these 20-25 minutes like
It'll where were you at his
But you disappeared in January you know in March were asking me like where were you after school for 20 minutes on a specific date
What days are the same to me you know
He mentions that there was this one girl
An alibi girl
Block I could offer is he that I remember he's like as a girl I go to school with
Who is Asia McClain
Music right after I got arrested
She wrote me a couple of letters
And she said she was going to see my family
And she said she specifically remembers me being
At the library at the public library right after school
The Woodlawn Public Library is just across the parking lot from Woodlawn High School
Not technically part of the campus but it might as well be
He said I gave those letters to Christina Gutierrez to my attorney
He's like but you know apparently we didn't really check out so he's got to know
So they're not helpful to us
So this is the first time I heard of
The scroll
Asia McClain I had never heard of her before nobody had mentioned her before
Floor like
I wasn't Florida the time because I thought
I saw If he if this girl Road and the attorney
What criminal defense attorneys not going to check out a potential alibi
So I asked him I said you have a copy of this letter she said you have a caucus and send me a copy
A nonsense letter Sarabia and Heritage
The first letter in the first of two
Is dated March 1st 1999 that is one day after I was arrested
The top of the letter she notes
I just came from your house an hour ago
I hope I spelled it right
I'm not sure if you remember talking to me in the library on January 13th
But I remember chatting with you
She says we aren't really close friends but I want you to look into my eyes and tell me if you're innocent
If I ever find otherwise I'll hunt you down and whip your ass okay friend
My boyfriend and his best friend remember seeing you there too
That's what are number one
March 2nd another letter this one's typed
Chattier
Pieces of evidence
Students are saying
Teachers are saying
Visit to his house
I don't think I Met Your Mother I think I Met Your Dad
Does he have a big gray beard
They gave me and Justin soda and cake
There's a whole bunch of people at your house I didn't know they were
I also didn't know that most want to take their shoes off in the house
I got it and I can take mine off my everyone out cold
Why haven't you told anyone about talking to me in the library she asked
Did you think it was unimportant you didn't think that I would remember
Or did you just totally forget yourself
Remember seeing Asian Library
Then he remembers about it it's so high school
To go out with a friend Justin and Justin had confided that Asia was
A proper young lady in other words just wasn't getting any
Has Justin about teenager with her new boyfriend
Maybe the new guy was getting lucky
Rabia call Deja app
It's been a year since she wrote the letters
But she agrees to me as she told me
That day after school I went to the line Public Library
Amazon was sitting at a computer checking email or something and I sat down next to him we started chatting
And I thought was very popular boy in school is a handsome and piano
Popular with the ladies
So she was speaking to her boyfriend shows up a little bit later with a friend
And she's her boyfriend is really angry at her cuz he's like why are you talking to hit Outlets high school kids in a while you're talking to him
Family hitting on you
And she remembers specifically that that day she went home with her when she went to her boyfriend's house
With him
And they got snowed in
And I still really have late at night
And she remembered that for the following two days schools closed
Associate very specific details about
Why should remember that day
Even wrote out an affidavit on the spot
She says she in a non spoke for about 15 to 20 minutes while she was waiting for her boyfriend to give her a ride
We left around 2:40 unquote
Remember hey supposed to be dead by 2:30
The kicker
No attorney has ever contacted me about January 13th 1999 and the above information
Benefit of the doubt for a second
Maybe at 9 never actually showed the letters to Christina Gutierrez
Attorney
Sure he said he did but
Well I know
Deep inside Gutierrez notes on the case I have boxes and boxes of such stuff
There's this in her handwriting
Asia-plus boyfriend
Saw him in library 2:15 to 3
Date of July 13th more than 4 months after annan's arrest
This is written by one of the chairs as law clerks who visited in jail
Call Asia McClain saw him in the library at
Is your boyfriend saw him too
Library may have cameras
Yoy with the person never heard from a trial
Solid non crazy detail-oriented Alibi Witness
In a case that's so sorely needed Alibi Witnesses
I can't ask Christina Gutierrez cuz she died in 2004
Put that question to a few defense attorneys
Especially if it's just one person then it becomes one person's word over another
Single witness like that can backfire under cross-examination
Or they might take the focus away from the weaknesses in the states
So there are conceivable strategic reasons why Christina Gutierrez might not have wanted to put Asia McClain on the stand
What is inconceivable they all said
It's not ever contact Asia McClain
To never make the call never check it out never find out if her story helps or hurts your case
That makes no sense
Whatsoever
That is not a strategy
Is a fox
When I first heard about the letters in the word mistake
Never heard from
Such a slam dunk
Are done
Announce family hard annuity
Who filed a petition in court based on the age affidavit
His argument was an honest trial could have turned out differently if Gutierrez had checked out Asia story
Until when should get some form of what's called
Post-conviction relief
The hearing for her story by this time
He finds an address in the west coast tries calling sending messages
Nothing
Write a letter to her get it to a private investigator
Fiance come to the door opens it part way
Tell the investigator that she cannot speak to Asia
But that from what he knows about the case but not as guilty and deserve the punishment he got later the investigator
Gets a call from the fiance
We don't have to talk to you leave us alone
So I called off the search for Asia
Figuring once a witness turns on you like that it's too risky to keep pushing
And then at announce hearing on the new petition it comes out that Asia had done the very thing they dreaded
Asia had called one of the prosecutors in a nun's case
Mexican and Kevin urick
And undermined her own state
This is from a recording of the hearing
Mr. eurocast testifying on the witness
Sanlitun
A young lady named Asia called me
It was its I don't know what happened to her and why she would do
Do this again
She says it's not true that it was bullied into reading that statement 15 years ago
She can't fathom why Asia would discredit her own statement like that I don't know why they weren't the affidavit was written
Voluntarily
I'm going to turn in a license attorney I work on homeland security is like I have no reason to make
Something like this up
You know I didn't even know she existed until
On top of the convicts
So what do you think
Happened why would they have this sort of violent reaction to
Helping out an on now
I don't know
It was
Just really odd
Asian Chao app
After all they had the original letters and the affidavit that's all that should have mattered
But it didn't look good
Be natural for the judge to wonder
Why can't the defense produces Asia
Why is she making this call to a prosecutor
I mean anyone
I wondered I wondered if maybe she was pressured into writing that affidavit
She was hiding something
Like maybe she lied in those 1999 letters
Maybe she didn't really see I'm not at the library that day and I just wanted to insert herself into something exciting
She was grown up she wanted nothing to do with any of it
234 months after I first sat down with Rabia I become fixated on finding Asia
Bloodhound on this thing
Because a whole case seemed to me to be teetering on her memories of that afternoon
I have to know if I really was in the library at 2:36
TM
Because he was
Library equals innocent
It's so maddeningly simple and maybe I can crack it if I can just talk to Asia
I read her along gentle pleading letter and send it off to an address I found online
I'm calling people who know her
I think might know her
I'm checking the same Loop of Facebook MyLife LinkedIn sites over and over trawling for clues about where she might be
Kakashi might think
You're wondering why I went so nuts on this story versus some other murder case
The best I can explain is this is the one that came to me
It wasn't halfway across the world or even next door I came right to my lap and if I could
Bottom of it
Should I try
I start running down all the other information in ages 1999 letters
She mentioned they were security cameras inside the Library
I want to see the very nice manager there are Michelle hamiel
Was there a security system back in 99 that could have been checked
Set the time
Probably
Yes I'm going to say
And what system was it
I have no idea it was a old system
But you can probably video
It was video
And that was part of set up every morning you put a video tape in
Hello how are you guys recycling the videotape
Yes
Think
Ran for a week
So you had a Monday taper Tuesday for Wednesday
What's up what's up
So even if on the very day that Asia had written her first letter A Nosler had run out to find the security tape
It probably would have been non-existent by then
What about the computer using to check his email
To use a computer did people have to sign in like write their name down
They did
And what was the system that
Piece of paper and pencil
By any chance were logged
Meticulously and kept for 15 years were they
No
Hummer
We got nothing
The mystery of Ages boyfriend Derek and his friend Gerard
Winter and spring every time I went to Baltimore I went to Derek's mom's house looking for him
Vintage Rose window tinting business
And then finally
All right so you are Jerrod Johnson
You don't know how excited we are to be talkin to I've been looking for you for like 4 months
You didn't do anything but we were hoping maybe you remember this moment
On January 13th
Do you
Have any memory
By any miracle
That you went
To Woodlawn Public Library branch
Near Woodlawn High School to pick up Asia McClain
With your friend Derek
I have no idea
Aja metoyer
Is that a person or book
Jefferson
No no recollection of
Scratch girod
Derek was my last hope
Eventually I caught him at home
Considering I woke him up he was exceedingly courteous
You show me a photo of Asian him all dressed up
They dated most of senior year
What's up here
Yeah
Beautiful
That's my eyes
But there couldn't remember that day either
Shocking I know
Need to pick you up from school almost every day back then either from the library or from the front of the school
Because you spoke to a lot of her friend
AAA
It's very possible that
Could have spoken
The gentleman and her on Bad Day
But it's
Very hard to remember do you know if
15 years later
But it it's it sounds you know very
It sounds like this could have happened
I don't think he's not the type of person that would lie
I just a reminder
Person you know
To get involved
With Ally
Scioscia
It seems pretty credible
Call my cell phone from a blocked number
You guessed it
I wish I could say that my charming persuasive letter is it prompted Asia to call
But the truth is she never got my letter
I had the wrong address
But you was calling because I followed up weeks later it with a one-line email and she was responding to that
A little confused
I mean I have
I recorded our conversation on the cell which is why the sound quality is so bad sorry about that
33 year old stay-at-home mother
And she has not spent the last 15 years worrying about if he's guilty
I trust
Because I mean I was never
I was there a question now is never informed of anything pertaining to the case
I don't know why he was convicted
You just said she was spooked when the private investigator came to her house
I don't know if that's why she didn't Testify the
Securing
Why she made the call to the prosecutor but you told me that when she got the knock at the door
That was not cool
Christopher if I could do it the last thing you want is a murderer being pissed off at you knowing where you live
Potato remarkably clear memory of what happened on January 13th 1999
She had an internship at the time and so she got out of school much earlier than everyone else
Derek was supposed to come get her at the library along with the rod that they were very late
Remember seeing Adnan come in after Woodlawn let out for the day
He said the table and Frank we weren't
Really close friends or anything like that
You know
Never end
I can't remember
I think I'm going to ask her how he was doing whatever and he says Finance
Tell about it he just
I just wish the best for her attitude and
I'm not sure why ages memory of this interaction is so clear all these years later
Because she wrote it down
The time in his letters and then the affidavit
At the detail somehow stop
Do you remember what time you were talking this would have happened in the library do you remember what time that come
Conversation would have happened
I don't because
I know
School let out around 2:15.
2:30
Cuz you would said you got out of school earlier than other people so were you there were you at the library before 2:50
Teen
Oh yeah I have a few hours
Yeah I was pretty scared
And you know and he asked me what
Teenager boy
Don't even start with me
I remember that day because
That was the best
David
No
Were there snow days after that do you remember
I want to say there was because I think that was like the first snow of the year
I wouldn't have even remembered if it hadn't been for the
Snow
You know
I just remember being so pissed about being late
The First Noel
The snow is important
He disappeared on Wednesday
That night there was a huge ice storm
Which is unusual in Maryland
It ended up being a state emergency
School is closed for the rest of the week
They just started asking me questions about the case
Wasn't there DNA evidence
What exactly was James Harden the whole thing
She wasn't sure of none was guilty
She said things I've now heard from so many people since
He seems like he cared about her
He didn't seem angry or upset
There was more proof
It just you know
I didn't want to wait in here I just started something you know what I mean
Yeah
I mean
32 years old
Now and I know that
You know there's people out there
Calm demeanor you know
And I know some people who
Call Mom is known as and do something
EBay regret for the rest of your life
Yeah now it's be nice if there was some technicality something that would prove his innocence
Stephen person I've met in my life but I think I think Asia like
You might be that technicality to see what I mean like your
If you're saying
You saw him on this day at that time
That means the states
Timeline
For their this whole their whole theory of the case doesn't make any sense
Because
They're saying
He was in the car with her
At the very time that you're saying nice I'm at the library and we were talking
Do you know what I mean like that's exactly the window
Where they're saying she was
Murdered
In case you couldn't hear that it was a sigh
I completely understand that Sy
I feel a lot of the time
Because I talked to a non regularly
And he just
Doesn't seem like a murderer
Few minutes after I hung up with Asia
Adnan called
On schedule
I'm good
So I was just talking to Asia McClain
You don't sound very excited
I really don't know
This was not the reaction I expected
I felt like I just interviewed an ivory-billed woodpecker
Remembered
Instead of being excited and said it was heartbreaking
Because it's
I'm not making this up
No no I mean I I C I totally iced tea
I see what you're saying I hadn't thought about it
In that way
Because they were all correct
It was too late
The judge rules on a petition a few weeks before I spoke to Asia
The judge wrote in his opinion that Christina Gutierrez his decision not to use Asia McClain as an alibi Witness
Strategic
After all ages original letters didn't specify an exact time
Temperaturas could have reasonably concluded that Asia was offering to lie in order to help an ion
And finally he wrote his letter contradicted
Ava said she saw him at the public library
Said he was on the school campus the whole afternoon
Maybe the judge didn't understand it was on library is basically part of the campus
But anyway
Is legally worthless
Said she saw you when the state contends you're strangling
Is worthless
A few days after I spoke to Asia she wrote me an email
I've been thinking a lot about Adnan She Wrote
All this time I thought the courts prove it was Adnan that killed her
I thought he was where he deserve to be
Assure
He was our friend too and it sucks feeling like you don't know who really killed your friend
He was the sweetest person ever
If you didn't kill Hae we owe it to him to try to make that clear
We need to put this to rest
I just hope that a nun isn't some sick bastard just trying to manipulate his way out of jail
I wrote back
Believe me
Exactly the same page
Coming up this season on serial
I think that there are other people involved like maybe I think maybe he was shut up I think you would shut up somehow
Lily Patel
Something wasn't going on it wasn't good
It was just strange behavior for anybody
Basically threatened me like you know what I'm
What are you thinking right now
Literally thinking like like could have gone crazy
Cuz at 9 music
Every question we've had for the past
Yamin
Syros Greece by Julie Snyder Dana chitosan
Me and my condom is our production and operations manager Aira glasses are editorial advisor angel from Nancy Updike
Checking by Karen fragala Smith special thanks to loot Eddie Jaye Marie Seth Linda leeseberg person in the entire staff of the Sun
American life and to my in-laws Ethan Shriner and Janet Levine for putting me up in Baltimore so many times in the past year
This American Life and WBEZ Chicago