Previously on serial
There's no way that
He was at Best Buy 236
Did anybody else use the phone
Yeah
Adnan. Remember he was talking to a girl
On the phone with her so I can remix I said hello to her
FIFA 17 year old kids
No experience with the with the system nose branch negative stuff
It's very difficult to believe in the early stages of this is actually what's happening this must be just a huge mistake
Global Tel Link that a call from
Maryland Correctional Facility
From This American Life
WBEZ Chicago it's serial one story told week by week
I'm Sarah Koenig
Courtroom arguments at trial
From a jury selection
Reporter for the Baltimore Sun and I covered some trials
And if I happen to be in the courtroom for jury selection it was always such a good reminder of what living in Baltimore was like
For so many people
I'm talking about
December 8th 1999 jury selection for nuns first trial
Judge William Quarles ask the standard question of the jury pool
Have you or any close family member
Ever been the victim of a crime
Convicted of a crime
Serve time for a crime
Or have pending criminal charges
A lot of people rise from their seats and then line up to talk to the judge
I can't tell exactly what proportion of the jury pool but it looks to be at least half
Husband sign
Good morning my house was broken into and we were robbed
Security
Good morning my husband was shot
Have a brother that's wanted
P17 in May my parents and I wrecked
Cobre Miami shine
My husband
Convicted
Hana Mae Lee
And I'm by the Lipscomb it on convicted of attempted murder
And my partner is a rape victim
I was robbed of a small amount of money on the street
Next
Good morning 2:07 what did you come up to tell me
That I have
Two uncles Pool Service hours phone number
Okay
As we move from a very peaceful town in Oregon to a violent community
And just Coral says
Welcome to Baltimore
All these people impartial jurors on add-ons case
Some say yes and he sent them back to their seats
He was on the lookout for prejudice
All kinds of prejudice
Against cops
Prosecutors
Korean
And against Muslims
When I tells him he doesn't think he can be impartial because he's got a friend of the Muslim faith
And he seen him and also his son mistreat their families
Friend of mine at work
Brooklyn Fete
And I seen you mistreat expatriates wife and everything you know and I've seen this loan
Train him
And his son got up he got married he did same thing as father day so I just couldn't in it
Be honest
Okay I appreciate that out this week
This brings me to something chimene told me when I first interviewed her
Shamim Rahman and on smother
Husband Syed Rahman
They believe Adnan is innocent
There's no question about it for them
Adam's father said to me
We've had no happiness in our family since it down was arrested
It has been continuous torture
All day
I don't know what to say Billy Mays like
I mean my poor bodies like number you know I cannot think nothing to me no more
But all I know he didn't do it
What
I mean how do you guys
Makes sense of what
Happened
How do you explain
What
To yourselves I mean not to the outside
Cyworld to yourselves like how do you understand
Why we must think about that
Ebony Majestic only thing you know I still believe you don't because you are asthma
This is discrimination
And everybody feed the whole community
Because it was a Muslim
Jaundice
Taking them to other people
Espresso
You know
And do you believe she is a W-2 yet
Because it was easy to Target you know
Bottom to come in pre-K
Pick him up
We still don't know why they doing it
But again I said this termination
Because we are Muslim and we are in a minor in this country
So this Friday
I mean
You can hear me not believing her right
The notion that the cops and prosecutors in this case were driven by anti-muslim feeling
I racism anti racism alone
That I found very hard to believe but I still don't believe that by the way
I didn't want to write off what you mean was saying either
Because maybe anti-muslim this crap Dan
Contributed in some way to how the investigation and the process
Staycation operated
Advertently or inadvertently
She hadn't personally
I felt discrimination just out in the world in Baltimore
Before the trial
And she didn't feel it after not even after 9/11
What are the hearing on add-ons bail status
On March 31st 1999
She felt that
The courthouse that day was packed with people from add-ons mosque
Islamic Society Baltimore
They raised tens of thousands of dollars for his defense
The offer to put up their own houses and other properties does
Securus bail
Another attorneys during the battle phase of his case or two guys named Chris
Floor and Decor
The family would hire Christina Gutierrez soon after 4
Pretrial
Christopher remembers the busloads of people who came to a downspout proceedings
Filling the courtroom in hallways
He said he's never seen anything like it
Before or since
I remember almost
Every
Inch of the available standing space in the courthouse at the Wabash District Court with the bail
Review happened up being full up
People so a lot of beards and a lot of traditional garb
And many of the people here are people
Pool
You would almost say they're extended family they care for each other's children it's it's fashion sense
Text Doug Culver who did the talking during this hearing
Hands of the people who are here in this courtroom
Represent
Doctors and the teachers and the lawyers and accountants in the correctional officer
As well as
Three religious
Ledo's imams who are from different moths
Here in Baltimore
Community here judges here to say first of all
Bet they commit themselves
To promise to Val that they will not only supervised at 9
Should he be released should bail be set
But at the same time they will also accompany him to court as well
After he finished the prosecutor Vicki wash
Took that same crowd the people. Kolbert describes a solid respectable folk who make sure none does the right thing
Wash custom as a room full of haters
Any better
The same people who are likely to help a nun run away to Pakistan
And that's why he shouldn't get bail
The fact that the defendant has strong support from the community that is what makes him unique in this case
KitchenAid because
He has Limitless resources
He has the resources of this entire Community year
Investigation revealed that he can
Top resources from Pakistan as well
It's our position your honor that if you issue a bail
Then you are issuing him a passport under the circumstance
Just leave the country we do not want another sheinbein situation your honor
We are asking you
I told you I wasn't going to take it
That's Judge David Mitchell telling a big crowd to settle down
Sheinbein is Samuel sheinbein brutally killing another Maryland teenager in 1997
And then absconded to Israel
His wife said she talked to Mr Harry Marshall
Senior legal advisor for international affairs with a Justice
Department
Mr. Marshall had explained to her that the US had tried unsuccessfully to extradite certain criminals from Pakistan
And he cited that there is a pattern in the United States of America
We Are Young Pakistan males have been jilted have committed murder and have fled to Pakistan
And we have been unable to extradite them back
He gave me a specific instance that occurring now that spending in Chicago
Where the factual pattern is frightened least similar
Again young Pakistan Pakistan mail
Who was jilted by his girlfriend who fled the country
And they have had no success
And he indicated it would be a dim situation indeed
If the defendant would flee to Pakistan
We have information from an investigation that the defendant has an uncle in Pakistan and he has indicated that he can make
Make people disappear
That information about the badass Uncle I think I got that from
Teacher I'm not kidding
The cops talked to this teacher on March 24th
I did not know it says the teacher mr. Nicholson
But how did not as a student before
The word brooding is in there
But it says suspect
Had an uncle in Pakistan who can make people disappear on quote
Under that it says
They drain blood from cow at the mosque one day he was pumped
Nicholson ends up as an argument at Advanced bail hearing
I couldn't find any other source for it in the detectives or State's Attorney's files I looked at
Attorney made a stab at fact-checking washes information
One thing led to another and three weeks after that hearing
Miss wash writes a letter to judge Mitchell
Apologizing if she misled the court
She said she'd misconstrued information
From Mr Harry Marshal of the justice
Department
She talked to him again and he made it clear that there was not a pattern of young Pakistani men committing murder after they've been
Hilton and then running off to Pakistan
Another case you've mentioned that frightening least similar one out of Chicago
That case parallel Syed case only that it involves a Pakistani male charged with murder
Where the victim was known to the defendant washroom
Apology there's an error
Anon is not Pakistani
He's American
Pakistani heritage
Maybe this seems like I'm parsing I don't mean to
All this out because to me it shows how easy it is to stir stereotypes in with facts
All of which then gets baked
Into a story
Something like
Those Muslim men they can't control their pride their passions
They killed her Lover's Athleta concert
Sequences
Put the full support of their families and communities
That's what shocks you mean
Obviously the state never said and was careful not to
To say Adnan did this because he's a Muslim
But they did skirt this idea few times at
The trial
They wanted to show that this wasn't a normal high school Romance
But this young couple was under an unusual amount of scrutiny and pressure from their families
And because of nouns culture forbid the very thing he wanted
That's why he reacted the way he did to The Break-Up
Various Witnesses talking about what happened at the homecoming dance or how the relationship a secret
Prosecutor Casey Murphy tells the jury
The crime was not about love it was about Pride
When is opening argument
You've heard this language before in an earlier episode but it Bears repeating
Prosecutor Kevin urick talks about how Adnan reacted when he broke up with him
Became enraged
He felt betrayed that his honor has been besmirched
He became very angry
And he set out to kill Hae Min Lee
PetSmart
Syracuse by axe
Usually he replied to a 17 year old kid at Woodlawn High School
Is a word from the old country
Where honor killings come from
And this word honor
Princess when I was looking through a huge set of documents from the detective's investigation
Confidential report
In late August of 99 so six months after the rest
Consulting Group Services helps law enforcement understand other cultures
Weather report for detectives risen mcgilvery
Report on Islamic thought and culture with emphasis on package
Comparative study relevant to the upcoming trial of Adnan Syed
Airport is 8 pages long I'm going to skip to the money shot
Summary as it relates to mr. Syed
I have another man Dishonored both Adnan Syed and his belief structure
It is acceptable for a Muslim man to control the actions of a Woman by completely eliminating her
It goes on
Within this harsh culture he has not violated any code he has defended his honor
Finally
For many ethnic Pakistani incidents like this are commonplace and in Pakistan this would not have been a crime
Probably a question of Honor
I've no idea what the cops made of this report
They looked at it and thought
Deer
And stuffed it in a file never to be considered again
Or whether they thought
Interesting
But they were at the very least in regular communication with the
Consultant
Especially during the early stages of the investigation
I noticed a also gives a shout-out to Aslam
It's during the second trial
Testifying about what happened after he picked at none of it best buys their driving back to school
Jay says quote this is when we started to talk a little bit
I don't know he said to me it kind of hurt him but not really
And when someone treats him like that they deserve to die
How can you treat somebody like that that you're supposed to love
And then all-knowing is Allah
Eric asked him
Explain what he meant by that
No Chasez
It's a detail Jay mentions neither to the detectives in his tape
Nor during the first trial
So why now
Allow only knows
Reporting the story I found plenty of examples of casual prejudice against Muslims
What are the nuns teachers for example think about what he would have been taught about women and women's rights
Another teacher I talked to told me she was terrified at the time that it needs relatives were going to come after her for talking to the Dead
Detectives
She told me she assumes his parents were evil
On that website that lists all the bodies found in leakin park
The author's commentary about him in these cases
Maybe my prejudices showing through but who in their right mind lets their daughter date a man named Adnan masud Syed
The jurors we spoke to said Indians religion didn't affect their view of the case
Lisa Flynn said maybe at first it interested her but then she pretty quickly realize that more to the point
Was a teenager in America doing American Teenager things
She said once they all understood that whatever stereotypes they had went right out the window
Which is exactly what you wanted a jury
But when we press them a little more
It seems stereotypes about a nun's culture were there
Lurking in the background
I don't feel religion was why you were
American culture
What religion
I'm not sure how the culture is over there had a tree
Preacher woman
Leonard some cultures women are
Second-class citizens maybe that's
But it was I don't know
He just want to control and she wouldn't give it to him
Dr William Owens
Cristela Armstrong
They were trying to talk about in his culture and
Arabic culture
Mineral
Not women
I remember hearing that when you were deliberating one of the jurors
So
He had put his put his whole life on the line for her
You know and
She wanted to she didn't want no ball or anymore
The first thing Christina Gutierrez announced trial lawyer said in her opening statement about her client
This isn't the first trial
Was quoted masud Syed is an American citizen
He was born in this country
Like most American citizens
Jury selection
That the jurors might be prone to anti-muslim anti-foreigner sentiment
Which probably explains why she spent what seemed to me a Nutty amount of time during her opening
Talking about what an immigrant is what a mosque is what Pakistan is quote a country formed in the
Arab world in the tip of the landmass called Asia
She talks and talks about how I was raised about young Romance
The judge interrupts her four times
How much longer will you be Miss Gutierrez 5 minutes Miss Gutierrez 1 minute mask
Gutierrez
She's rushing at the end
Would you rather quickly throw suspicion on DJ and then finally on to mr. s
Earlier app
About whether she should have talked to Asia McClain or whether her style made of grated on jurors
But now I'm going to address this question head-on
Did she blow it
Christina in terms of what happened at trial
Is it she never contacted Asia McClain
He thinks it wasn't deliberate on her part he just think she made a mistake
Like a Surgeon slip of the scalpel
I personally she was nothing but compassionate towards him he said
Always asking him how he was doing
To make sure he got the skin medication he needed the glasses he needed
She was his protector
I mean I still
You just mad I just I just had like a great deal of affection for a man
Jimmy Lee have my back in the
Like she know what she was doing
Hopefully I mean
No one could explain
Standing there in that situation
Call me doctor nurse
School teacher coach in your pants
And you may have an idea of how much you know
I trusted
Ciara
Your life is really in her hands
Literally literally
I mean
No she never really mentioned what her plan would be I never really knew what it would be
Christina died in January of 2004
Play I can't ask her what her strategy was for Conjuring Reasonable Doubt
I have to go by what we seen in her notes and in the courtroom
And based on all that I can summarize her defense theory in four words
Someone else did it
Such as a or the new boyfriend or Mister as the guy who found the body
After all she argued
For sure when he died
What day
It could have been the 13th or 14th or 15th
Christina wanted to show that once the cops zeroed in on an on
Ignored other viable suspects
Putting down an alibi for a.
She dumped as much suspicion as she could on to these other players
I mentioned before that announce first trial ended in a mistrial
Here's what happened
Christina was what Chris floor described as a fighting person
Generally a good quality in an attorney
That's scratchy part of Christina though
Sometimes it could elicit a response shall we say in the courtroom
An adversarial situation both sides and announced case were suspicious that the other was playing fast and loose when they could
And it could get Presley
Prosecutor Casey Murphy during a bench conference
The first trial
Before church Coral
I'm going to attempt to defense counsel calling my co-counsel on a****** at the trial table
I did not hear
I wish I could complain to a judge every time someone called me an a******
Coral says he knows Christina to be a pitbull on the pant leg of Justice unquote but an otherwise
This person and how about everybody just behaves themselves okay
Slater Quarles loses his patience with Christina
It's over something small
Kevin urick asks if he can show exhibit 31 to the jurors
AT&T call records Herman on phone
Train calls from January 12th 13th and 14th
Christina says she hasn't seen it before
York says that's not true she has it already stipulated
Call record
She says yeah but I hadn't actually looked at it
Before I haven't physically seen this exhibit
Cross calls him up to the bench
Miss Gutierrez
You're going to stand there and lie to the jury about something that you agreed to
I'm not going to permit you to do that
Christina says judge the fact that I
That was a lie
You told a lie I'm not going to permit you to do that
That's not a lie judge I resent the implication
Christina starts getting heated now
Girl says please be quiet please be quiet
She says it's very hard to be quiet when a court has
Accusing me of lying
I don't want to overdo it here but it's possible that had this bench conference not happened
Announce whole life could have been different
That first trial according to Adnan to Kristina's colleagues to people who are watching it
Seem to be going well for Adnan Syed
It was moving fast and Jason to be more on the defensive
Then this happened
And of course jurors overheard it
Despite the White Noise they turn on during bench conferences to muffle the sound
After a break
Christina asks for a mistrial
Coral says
He's got a note from alternate number for
Infused the fact that you determine that Miss Gutierrez is a liar will she be removed
Will we start over
Call Sister Christina
Your motion for mistrial
Scranton
Julie Remy was a law clerk for
16 at this time
She said moving into trial number to Christina was confident
I mean look you know
Are the jury cold after the first incident of the state kitzies case and they're giving me indications are going to
Quit and then you turn around and tried
Different jewelry and it comes out
Completely
You know the opposite you guys pulled the jury after the mistrial
I wasn't part of it but I know the jury was polled
After the mistress
By her and I believe
Lockhart
Okay I'm not sure
But the jury was polled
And it was a fan of the state's case
The interview the duration and they gave
Every indication that they were
Heading toward acquittal
In fact it wasn't quite at the end of the state's case
AT&T expert hadn't testified about the cell tower technology
Engen hadn't taken the stand either which is significant
But it's true the jury had heard the bulk of the state's case
Used to have that information you got to feel pretty good about that you knows the defense attorney
I would expect him being at the trial tree myself that you would come
What is coursing
Keep doing the same thing get the same kind of results
True different jury but also different judge slightly different arguments
Weather for all we know winds blowing slightly more this way or that
There's so many factors
Including chance
Which no one wants to think about in a first-degree murder case
The Corrs black is part of it too
About a month later they start all over
Trial 2
Christina strategies the same
Try to show that someone else killed Hae
She did a lot of research and hopes it blinking mr. s
The crime or at least trying to link him to J
Patronize the video store where they worked
But you never succeeded
During that second trial it take some doing but she finally gets mr. s on the stand
He's so desperately didn't want to be there
The courthouse staff basically to prevent him from leaving the building
So even though he's her witness he's a hostile witness
Who's Christina trying to get him to explain how work orders at his job got filled
If you could get to the epicenter job will do it at the time we can't do it at the time we do it
Want to get you
That's my ass off
Which month is the next day
Whenever
When your work day Within
You were going to leave
I guess so
You wouldn't get well sir is that a yes or no I'm not asking so yes when your workday don't you leave
Of course mr. s was more of a side dish
Christina's main prey with j
She tells the judge
Judge am I just like to be heard it is our entire defense. To make
James the person who committed this crime
I'm with all the ways in which he acted guilty and
Describing words and thanking when she acted with consciousness of guilt by concealing
Evidence
His clothes his boots
Is powder coat
His shop was wiping shovels
To conceal evidence as he said
Wealthiness David Anton
I'm crossed to conceal evidence of his involvement
Christina cross-examined J on five different days
Choose exhaustive and exhausting
Her questions are detailed and deliberate
She questioned them and maybe it was the half speed pacing or the sing-songy aggression
It added up to something less than effective
Her punches and there were many many punches
Don't always appear to land
A masterful job of presenting the facts
Announces Christina actually he calls her Miss Gutierrez
Let me do some great things for him
True successful and barring the school nurse from testifying in a second trial for instance
I was a woman who said she thought a non was faking his reaction
Lester Hayes death
But he says he wishes some of her arguments had been clear
It was at least linear
Officials confusing things but
It wasn't like a clear outline
Like the prosecution had everything was kind of jumbled I took so long
It was just like
Right
To give you an idea
Andrea's first and second tape statements to Detectives
He tells them different stories about when Adnan first told him he was going to
Kill hay
In the first statement he says it not mentions it that same day January 13th
Weather driving Anand
School at lunch time
In the second tape statement
He says a Nan told him the night before
And also that has been talking about it for four or five days already
When you testify as a child
He goes back to the first version
That he first heard about it from a non on the 13th
So obviously Christina questions about all this
It's fertile territory for her side
Listen to how she does it
This tape goes on for awhile by the way but I want you to get the full effect
Another occasion
You told them
All the conversations I had with
For 5 days early
Jasmine
How do you make sure because now there are new
The first very first
Interest
Occur at a time
But never starts
And I'm sad agitation
Did you tell me the Crouton 13
Then your second interview after the tape recorder
Scott's room
It's at our maker level 30
Snowman
Is
15th of March
You tell me her number
I believe so
Closer to you recall the 15th of March
You told them that Adnan
Told you he was going to kill that b****
You actually told them
But you knew
A whole day ahead of time
Good Adams
This evening it spoke to me
No
Something just happened
Just admitted something or didn't admit something but I honestly can't tell if it's a point for the defense
Or for the process
Iqushion
Or if it's a draw
Stretches like this
14 dozen for cross-examination went so far into the weeds it was hard even for me reading it years later
The hack back to the main trail
A juror that Dana interviewed a guy named Sue.
Said Christina strategy was a little lost on them to
50 Frontage Rd
Everybody has been a long time ago but everybody was
Disco Converse
Startup making a point
So they were just like a lot of words
Bright
He talked and talked and didn't prove anything
I think there's a good chance though that Christina leaves these threads hanging for a reason
Was another defense attorney explain to me
During cross-examination you don't want a tie each point up in a bow in the moment
You don't want to tip your hand
Because any other side might come back with questions on redirect examination that could undo what you've just laid out
So you save all the threads
And then tie them up in a nice
Fat unassailable
Closing after all the testifying is over
Christina does revisit J's testimony at her closing
The gist of which is
The detectives arrested in on because of what Jay told them
And what was it
True
And you lied to them about many many things
It wasn't just that things didn't match up they were lies
They called them lies
Call demise
On the 15th of March on the 18th of March
On the 13th of April every single time lies
Unquote
Clearly Christina put a ton of time and effort into discrediting J
But the fact is
The jurors believed him
Didn't think you'd be sitting there talking about this if it weren't true
She was less rigorous on other ask
McKay's
The cell phone wreck
Princeton
Her main argument was at the Estates Oxford
Tested the sites
Wasn't valid
Because he used in Ericsson phone
How to make the calls
A different brand than Anon
Which turned out to be a bad debt on her part
Brand of the phone doesn't matter
But what you didn't do with the cell phone evidence
Was attack the states timeline
Call by call Tower by Tower
Or point out with Clarity that is significant swath of the day
The hours between noon and 6 p.m. on the call log
Do not match json
Testimony
30 second trial though when Christina really came to life
I just kick ass
She teased some information out of she hoped would change the course of the proceedings
Granite Woods
The state specifically the attorney who is representing Jay
When she figured this one thing out about J's lawyer she told him this is our big chance
Excited about that
Charged with a felony
Accessory after the fact of first-degree murder
Plead guilty and had an agreement with the state that if he cooperated basically showed up in court and told the truth
A sentence with reflect that
Auntie auntie got no jail time
For that he had his own lawyer
A woman named Anne Benaroya
She's representing him pro bono
She wasn't a public defender choose a private defense attorney
Christina have been complaining to the court that the prosecution hadn't been totally forthcoming about Jays plea and how it came about
Which isn't unusual in a trolley
This one
But in the middle of the second trial Jay says something
Something that Christina would later call the magic information
Happened on the stand when she's asking Jay how Benaroya came to represent him
Chess
Did anyone help provide you a lawyer
Did anyone help her body
Military prosecutor in this case provide you a law
What
Gutierrez freaks out
This is the magic information
Testifies that
April of 99
No contact with the cops or the prosecutors until September 6th
So long stretch where he doesn't know what's going on
He says he called the office of the public defender to try to see if he could get himself a lawyer
And they told him unless you've been charged we can't help you
True
So Jay says the next thing that happens is the cops come to see him on September 6th
And tell him he's about to be charged with accessory after the fact
And that he'll be able to get a lawyer
The next day September 7th
They come pick him up they booked them and they take him to the State's Attorney's office
Kevin urick prosecutor
Jay says he's never met your
Before and then he says Yorick introduces him to and Benaroya who can represent him for
For free
Talk privately for a while then they sign a plea agreement
That same day they all go across the street to the courthouse and resent the signed plea to a judge
If you were a loved one is an attorney your jaw is hanging open right now correct
Prosecutors do not find attorneys for Witnesses they are prosecuting
That is not a thing
Former prosecutor worked in the Baltimore office at that time said she's never heard of anything like that happening before
It sounded very strange to her
Gutierrez
Freak out
There is no jurisdiction in America
For the win
If you got a free lawyer thanks
To the state Christina argues that's what's called a benefit
It's worth money
And it could look like JS being paid by the state for his testimony
Tennis benefits
And therefore might lie to please them
And if it could look like that she says
The defense was entitled to know about it before the second trial or the first trial began
And here she was learning about it at this late date
That she said was a violation of the rules of discovery
She sounds
So mad
The jury is not present for this ranting by the way
But probably she was also giddy with Gaucho excitement
She told the judge this is so patently improper
Jehovah Witness who has this benefit and they feel indebted
In a way that may affect what are you trying to fight to provide a lawyer
Terminator collectible lawyer
Once you getting into this Christina did not let go
She wanted to rest from it everything she could
Maybe a mistrial maybe some other relief
They spent hours on this issue over several days of
The trial sometimes in front of the jury sometimes not
I called Benaroya about this
To find out if it was true that your exhaust her out and that the first time she met Jay was in eurex office
On the same day to sign the plea agreement
She said no it could not have happened that way absolutely not
A child out Uric doesn't dispute it
Edit J sentencing in mm
When Mr Urich first asked me first mention this case to me and asked me if I would consider speaking to
The judge Wanda heard agreed with
Christina that this Arrangement looked fishy at Bass
She was not happy about it
But she also said
The witness in question
What is Jay
She doesn't seem to be aware that it's messed up
She doesn't appear to think he's getting a benefit
Or being paid in Subway Forest
Testimony or did anything untoward went on
Testimony isn't tainted by any of this
And that's the main thing
So A for effort judge hotels
Christina
Overruled
Annette Morales
Was that
In terms of Defense Witnesses
The case Christina brought was Swift
Book about two and a half days for her to rest
Aside from the cops
A private detective and the guy who surveyed the burial site in Lincoln Park
Witnesses Christina put on the stand where mostly character Witnesses
Initial or nice things to say about Adnan
Whatever his assignment Adnan strive for excellence at all time
His teacher flea market he's a bright
Conscientious
And hard-working student or protocol stunt your studies with sobriety
But the nuns guidance counselor Betty Stuckey reading from a college recommendation she wrote for him
Which incidentally she printed out for non on January 13th
Same day he disappeared
She was the last defense Witness
Building a solar vehicle
Beijing national competition in Topeka Kansas
Flask
Rabia chaudry first told me about a Nas case
She told me she thought Christina had bungled it
On purpose even
So she can make money off the appeal
That was the only way rob you could account for screwing up the Asia thing
And she said
Chabad Christina's defense
The witnesses she brought
We're laughably week
I do not agree with Robbie's assessment of
Christina
I do not believe Christina through this case
On purpose
From reading the transcripts and watching the trial videos
You can see her scrapping on an on behalf
At every opportunity
Sometimes in long and rather beautifully
Constructed extemporaneous paragraphs
She made a thousand strategic decisions
About what
Chip for Clerk's + and Associates of five people working on the case
Like she did some sloppy rush job
I know that losing the case she was
I don't think she ever got over that case
This is Julie Remy again
Who works for
Christina at the time of announce trial
And I can tell you the physical effects
Depression that I saw firsthand
She was
I think she wanted to kind of a deep depression after that case and I don't think she ever really bounce back
And if she really
Will impacted by the loss of a case
People who works with Christina back then they all said the same thing
That she was tireless and she cared a lot about her cases including Adnan
She's always going going a hundred miles an hour
I said she's heard a fly into the office in the morning sunglasses on hair flying barking orders
She smoke and she cursed at you fiercely meant her Clerks
Chicopee a giant pain in the ass
But also she was a giant in the profession
Manchester Maryland but nationally
She did the first or at least one of the first DNA cases in Maryland
To figure out how to explain it to a jury I heard a story that she went to a grades
School and practice
Each time a kid said he or she didn't understand the science she started over
Christina Ciccone First cases in Maryland that use luminol
Attract blood spatter
But six people told me she was brilliant
Not in a hyperbolic way either
Despite her Stellar reputation though it does seem as if something not right was happening with Christina around this
Time everybody say she's the best you the best so she's
We was
Like you know you was begging her to take one
Betcha meme Jean's mother
Share husband consulted with friends and leaders the mosque about who to hire
Everyone said Christina sounded great
They felt like they were lucky to get her
What it was she asked for you know we'll just go and get it before she will lose her you don't because
Who is afraid producer we don't have no
National League
Message
Attorney
Kristina's bedside manner at least with them lacked a certain Delica
She said they were both intimidated by her
And they could never get her to talk to them about another case or what was going on
And she said she thought Christina had lost some of her magic in the courtroom by the second trial
But you seem sort of agitated
So another time she would be smoking in and out in and she was very nervous kind of person before she wasn't like that the first try
Christina initially asked for $50,000 to represent of non
That fee would more than double by the end of the second
Control
Members of the mosque and donated lots of money to help pay her
But you mean says that toward the end of the second trial Christina had begun to bully them about money
If they managed to get Christina on the phone or in a meeting
Jim said the only topic would be money
Money money
At one point she says Christina told her parents she needed them to bring her $10,000 cash.
The courthouse
Taipei forgery expert
So it was kind of strange but when I
Told my friend is so not doing what she's doing her job you know
How could you even fit $10,000
Amazing
This supposed to take the chick like you know but you said no bring you the cash already
Was that the only time that she asked for cash
Yes yes butterfish
Yes
She never hire the expert
Stream sister came another time for the end when Christina insisted in on parents owed her money and that you could take their house
House if they didn't pay up
They said they had paid her for everything
They're so scared they transfer their house into their oldest son's name
I bring all this up because my parents were not the only ones who had dealings like this with Christina
I spoke to another couple Ron and Sue Whitman
On the heels of a non-conviction in early 2000
Christina Angel pretty fast
Whitman Tire Christina to defend their 15 year old son
The worst and saddest case I've ever heard
Their son Zack was accused in ultimately
Convicted of killing their younger son Greg who is 13
It's just a terrible gruesome
Confounding case
I can't even begin to imagine but anyway they seek out Christina because she's been recommended to them
And they write about her Defense work in the paper
The first was great they said
She successfully argued a couple of important pretrial motions
Ron Whitman said she was magnificent in the courtroom
That is timing on singstar to get weird
This is around the same time she was working on a Nas case
Should be late really late
The court
The woman's case was in Pennsylvania
On the border with Maryland
The courthouse in Harrisburg
They check in 4 weeks in advance with
Christina they said
Asking how's it going when can we review
No worries
In person at Christina's office in Baltimore
Harrisburg meeting up with sewalong id38 so they could get it stamped by 4:30 p.m. at the court
Run the other way
Didn't even have time to park the car
The women's talk about many of the same things to me and told me
But they couldn't get a hold of Christina
Or saw that things were getting done but when they ask people who're
They were told don't push it
It'll be fine
Here's to women
And they would send me this is how Tina works
This is dope
Don't
Tell teen what to do
This is what she does
She's very good at it
Don't worry about it
So
Someone
That has worked with Tina for years tells you that this is just her way
Then you think that this is just your way
Has it got worse and worse
Announce trial ended in late February of 2000
By the end of that same year Christina had been hospitalized
Tanks
She diabetes
Should MS
She got very very sick
Tommy they bring files to her in the hospital
Christina would sneak cigarettes in the bathroom
Another words
She was still at it
And maybe she shouldn't have been
Robin says it should have been clear to everyone around her that Christina couldn't keep up with her cases
But no one cried uncle
Ultimately in
January of 2001 if I have my ears correct
We had a
Grief do at the Supreme Court of the United States in 10 days
And she had told us that she had
University of Baltimore law professor who is she at work with
Many times
April 4th
Doing the draft
And finally
I called him
And he said I am
Talk to Tina about your son's case for urine
Years
Christina asked them for an additional $65,000 for work she had to know full well she couldn't do
That they gave her $25,000 for an expert
The Christina never paid the guy
So he came to them for the money
They said it happened with a second expert 2 for $2,000
If she was too sick why didn't she tell them why did she leave them hanging
Kristina's career had collapsed by the spring of 2001 A year after announced trial ended
According to newspaper
Written by me
Christina got in trouble with the attorney grievance Commission of Maryland
Clients were complaining that you taken their money ahead not done the work she promised or not used it the way she said she would
The state fund that compensates people when their lawyers will choose their money
Total of $282,328
128 claims against
Christina
The largest payout was to the Whitman
So she was lying to them
Try to get as much money out of them as she could
More generous assessment would be that Christina was in denial about how sick she was
They're told me she was never much interested in the business side of things
Wasn't her forte
One former law partner of Christina's told the Whitman's that Christina had been slipping for a while
The past 5 years
This event
There's been a lot of news stories this week that it has gotten an appeal
That's not quite true
He had an initial appeal which was denied
And he had a hearing for post-conviction relief
Also denied
But he appealed to a higher Court the Maryland Court of special Appeals
Recently. Court order the states responded to one aspect of a nun's petition
By January 14th
So it is still alive
Buy thread
Announce petition is based on a claim of ineffective assistance of counsel
Meaning Christina Gutierrez screwed up
The front of the claim is about Asia McClain
But she might have provided an alibi for a. At trial if
Christina had talked
But the part of petition that the higher Court wants the state to answer is actually about a different complaint
Had to ask Christina to seek a plea deal
Twice he.
Christina never did it
Prosecutors in an ounce case said they never made an offer
Kristina also didn't sequin
Even though Adnan says he asked
Assertive
Once before his first trial and was before the second
When I first read his petition
I told him that I found it hard to believe he'd asked
Cordial
He's been so unshakable for 15 years
What is anacin
Nothing to do with his death
It also seemed to me as if he trusted back then
That the system was sort all this out
He go home
Renown told me
There were times when he was really scared
He was trying to be brave for his family
But then keep your stories or watch guys he knew get 50 year 70 year life sentence
And it would hit him
I could be in prison for the rest of my life
It is so difficult
Not ever having
Been in that situation
Like I would always think before I ever came to jail
Because they did it
You know no way would a person ever plead guilty
What you coming to like
This whole system
What time does she really learned is that
1st degree Murder cases
It's almost impossible
I can pick an all years in prison I can fly think of a handful of people
Whoever beat the first-degree murder case
Against you
Are people that like I've met
I know and I'm so jealous of them
In a good way because when we were over the jail or city jail
A lawyer's advice and looking at you taking a life
Dependable 30 years life suspended for 20 years whether you did it or not
Because the way the elements of the case are
You know
You don't have like a strong alibi
Could you have someone coming to court saying that you did it whether you did it or not
You going to go in front of a jury and tell people to panic because they have never sat in your shoes before
So it's really important that you have in a life sentence
First choice if you have in my life
Because now I still communicate with some of these guys are actually getting ready to go home
1516 years later
Annonces when he seen younger guys come in on parole violations or for whatever reason
He tells them
Take the deal
Regardless of whether you did it
Because of non has maintained his innocence
He's got no hope of getting out or very little hope
That's how the system works
I understand that now
Parole
But the chances of getting it are so slim for anyone with a life sentence for first-degree murder
But especially if you don't show remorse
Because
You know what is a psychopath right
Next time on serial
Ciro's produced by Julie Schneider Dana Chavez and me Emily Condon as ever.
Action and operations manager our glasses are editorial advisor
Research and fact-checking by Michelle Harris administrative support from Elise bergersen
Our score is by Mark Phillips you also mix the episode
Our theme song is by Nick thorburn Who provided additional scoring
Special thanks to John B minor Terry O'Connor from Purdue University
Scott Calvert Craig timberg Meredith cone Lisa Pollock Chuck Salter Blake Morrison David Cone and Natasha lesser
Our website where you can listen to all our episodes and find photos letters and other documents from the case and sign up for a week
Emails
Serialpodcast.org
Serials production of This American Life and WBEZ Chicago