Support for serial comes from ATT
The number one smart home security provider
Offering everything from video doorbells
2 indoor and outdoor cameras
2 smart locks and lights
Control from the ADT app
Or the sound of your voice
Visit att.com podcast to learn more about how ADT can custom design and install your
Smart home system
Back by 24/7 40
Previously on serial
Taking my hand out
Good grief
If anyone was standing outside
Who had shooting
We did this
A little wonder how long
Going on in Pakistan and Afghanistan
Talon bow to come home person bike
You're the officer is on your face how do they get their pasta too. I thought it was kind of like
Call that guy
From This American Life and WBEZ Chicago its serial
One story told week by week
I'm Sarah Koenig
The way Botox to Mark about his time as a prisoner
It's almost as if it's divided
Their ZR1
When he's Gathering Intel planning a escapes
Focused on getting away
And then the rest of it
And the rest of it
Four more years
What his purpose is less Sharp
Hope is blurrier
There's less action
Now he's got to endure
And that's in large part because after you're one
AfterBuzz 9 day Escape
The Taliban put him in a cage
And
There is no way I'm getting out of that cage
This is a metal cage or wood cage or what
Can iron bar cage
Made for what purpose
For keeping me
Beau says it was six parts
Four sides with the top in the bottom made of quarter inch bars
Does collapsible
When they moved into new location they rebuild the cage and whatever room they put them in
Both in padlock it together
BOCES if he stretched out his arms he could touch opposite sides of the cage with his fingers
Figured it was about 6 feet wide
Explain stuff like this
I can picture it
I can understand what he's describing
But at some point I realized
I don't actually understand what is going on
Looks like the whole thing with overlay with a scram where exactly is he who exactly is holding him
I couldn't tell what the Taliban in the colonies wanted or expected
Why is he being moved
Why is he being ignored
I didn't tell his treatment was senseless and haphazard or if it was part of a plan
Most descriptions are vivid that's not the problem
The problem is they're mainly from inside a room
Oh couldn't see what was happening outside
So I could make order of it because Bo himself couldn't make order
There's another guy who has a very good idea of bows place in haqqani World Order
His name is David Road
Davidson investigative reporter for Reuters now but back in 2008 he was on leave from the New York Times
Researching a book about Afghanistan
Arrange to interview a Taliban Commander about an hour's Drive south of Kabul
And headed over to the same people and pretty much the same place at close to the same time as bow
Once I heard David story so much of bows story clicked into place for me
ProLogistix locations
Many aspects of David's experience are really different from Bose
David the civilian first officer journalist
Two already knew a lot about Afghanistan and Pakistan
He got free after about seven months versus nearly five years
And a huge difference
David wasn't alone
He was taken with two Afghan
Asada driver anti-hero translator
So he had someone to interpret whatever he didn't understand
Also David wasn't blindfolded all the time really only when he was being moved to a different location
He wasn't chained or tied up
Inside the compound he could walk around in the courtyard
He could have conversations with his guards
And I'm not bringing all that up to suggest some sort of grim hostage contest
Only to point out that while David was imprisoned
She wasn't in the dark he wasn't in solitary confinement like Bo
So he had an awareness bow didn't have
About the system he had entered into
After they were carjacked to David and Assad anti-hair were taken around Afghanistan for a few days
And then they were told to get out of the car and start walking
Over the mountain
The next morning is clear to David where he is
For one thing the car that Picks Them Up is driving on the left hand side of the road
Like they do in package
And soon after that I saw a road sign in Urdu the national language
Pakistan and I
New weed walk
Into the tribal areas over the mountains
And I knew we were
Doomed
And that's
The worst place you can be taken in the Afghanistan
Pakistan region
David knew how utterly dangerous the tribal areas in Western Pakistan were
This place it's really just over the mountain
It's right near the border
And if you're imagining a wild
Desolate inaccessible Terrain
It's not like that
David said compare to rural Afghanistan in Fat City like miramshah
The capital of north waziristan where the haqqanis are based
The time in or near miramshah
There are more paved roads more large buildings more schools
There is
You know a market
With people selling
Goods from Pakistan proper I mean my
Kidnappers you know brought me
Bottled
Nestle water that was manufactured
From a plant in a Inn in Lahore Pakistan one of the main
Cities you know but they were able to buy it in the market
In The Travelers I bought me
Copies of
This the most well-known English language newspaper in Pakistan Dawn
Another one's called the news
And they would be 2 or 3 days old but they could buy all these things
I'm in the market
In the middle of the tribal areas
There's kids
Stairs
Farmers
You know what donkeys in there
Bring in
Their crops
The cell
There's tons of
Toyota station wagon
People driving their own also service taxes and you know became clear in those first few hours and then days and weeks that this was a
Taliban mini state that
Auction
Open legged
Hino repaired roads and ran schools and
Had some sort of basic
Form of healthcare it wasn't
Is completely backward an area as a as you know is usually described
And it's not like the Taliban are sort of skulking around dodging any Pakistani military press
David says they're fully aware of each other may be wary at times but also like waiting to each other
As I drove around the tribal areas was there a Stan North and South David said there be regular checkpoint
Solana road that would normally be mad by a Pakistani security or Army
And instead there be young Taliban fighters with kalashnikovs letting traffic through not letting traffic through
Driver of David's car had to have the right password to get by
One one time I was being driven in a car and we ran into a pack of signing Army resupply Convoy
And I thought this is this great opportunity maybe you know the Convoy will
Let us all get out of the car and we can make a run for it
And instead you know
Ark are the Taliban car just pulled over to the side of the road I remember in front of us with a car full of civilians
The civilians had to get out of the car
Hazard to put their hands up on the Pakistani army Convoy went by
In the Pakistani soldiers did seem to be really afraid
That there would be a car bomb or some sort of attack
From one of these
And I'll vehicles on the side of the road including ours
But you know they just drove by us
They never forces get out of our car
And then
The
A man driving my car he was slick the number to commander of the haqqani network is name is boughten a Connie
He explained to me that that
Tencent agreement with the Pakistani army
That the economy Vehicles just had to pull over to the side of the road that no one had to get out of the economy car
And in return the pakistanis would not inspect
The car and that if they know which one how do they know which is a haqqani car and which is it
No idea I just remember
When I watching battery and haqqani the number to come out of that kind at work
Smiling and waving
Two Pakistani soldiers as they drove by in their trucks
You know in my heart sinking
When I thought maybe they were going to rush
Oh my God so they're just it's just like
The word just like impunity is just jumping into my head like just
It's a it's a truce
So it's
You know and
Equation for x and I'll try to give you a 50 or version but
The easiest way to explain fascism
Seems like anyone I asked to explain what gives
Annie's operating so freely in Pakistan
I have to take a deep breath first
Because it is fraud it is complicated
And to do it justice it would take a long time so I'm just going to give you the basics of what I've learned
Here goes the haqqanis are a family-run operation
And they're not one thing there Islamic nationalist
There a militant group
And they have businesses
New York Times story compare them to quote The Sopranos of the Afghanistan war unquote
They've got their own alliances their own source of funds
But they're also part of the Taliban
They use the same stationary I'm not kidding about that
One expert told me their statements come out under the Seal of the Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan same as the Afghan Taliban
Counties are the most militarily effective part of the Taliban
And they're the part of the Taliban that's most under control of Pakistan
One expert told me quotes
You know they're just very very close to
The Pakistani
Sun quote
Connie family is Afghan
Are pashtun
The Roots rev Coast Prada
Cats in Afghanistan
But they're headquartered in Pakistan
Back in the 1970s they were fighting the Afghan government and then later switch to fighting the Soviets when they invaded after
Amistad
And by the way we do us like to that they were fighting the Communists from the early 80s we gave them millions of dollars to help them
I'm trained fighters in North waziristan
We helped build them up
As for Pakistan
They tolerate all this because the haqqanis are useful in them
They're useful proxies in Pakistan's decades-long effort to influence events inside Afghanistan
To keep Afghanistan a manageable neighbor
And
Stay With Me
They're useful because they help prevent Pakistan's other neighbor India
I'm establishing any serious foothold or influence in Afghanistan
Pakistan has always seen India as its biggest threat
Here's David's
Valiant 30 second explanation
The Pakistani military their goal is to
Stop India
Everywhere they can in South Asia
So the
Pakistani government
Allow the haqqanis and the Taliban to operate
Because they saw them as allies they saw
Connie's is a force that can allow Pakistan to remain
In de facto control
Of Afghanistan
And stop India from taking over f
97 and life
Three sentences
And I like your 10 what are good
And
And this is also important
Connie's help Pakistan deal with the other Taliban in their country
The Pakistani Taliban
Because the haqqanis have good relations with the Pakistani Taliban
But the Pakistani Taliban does not have good relations
The Pakistani government
So
That was the situation back in 2009 when Beau and David were held by the haqqani
In the past couple years though Pakistan strategy toward the Taliban has changed somewhat
They're bombing waziristan
Probably right now
If you've been reading the paper maybe you're caught up on all this if not I have some phone numbers for experts
David describes the haqqanis as an incredibly disciplined organized crime Network
They were super careful not to use cell phones or Communications devices that could be tracked
Jordan haqqani one of the top Commanders
What sometimes show up at a house where David was being held and he be completely alone
Because he figured the drones overhead would be looking for a commander moving around with bodyguards
David and Assad and Tasha are removed all the time
As far as David can tell the house to house system work sort of like a franchise
Each family that took them would get some share in the prisoners either some money
Or maybe they had family members who were prisoners whom they wanted released as part of a deal to exchange David
Where in houses from
Tudi
Four to five weeks at a time
And is that is there a logic to the moving that you can discern
Is it just like we will you can't you just can't stay in one place for too long cuz going to be found out or is it like I think
I think that I mean in again I have a huge Advantage because I have these two Afghans I've been kidnapped with me and their hearing all kinds of time
Relations there talking to
The boys who
Bring in bread
And so
You know I was told now and then
Families you know would get tired of holding us
Because it was very dangerous
For them
There everyone was very afraid to be a drone strike to kill me
And all their family would be killed
When they held me a densely populated neighborhoods it was cuz the nearby children they hoped
Would prevent you know the US from carrying out a drone strike to kill me because it would
Kill so many civilians at the same time
Are those like
Connie family members are they like who are those
People who are keeping you or do they just like Bustin at anyone's house and be like we're going to hang out here
Here for a while
And gear
I think they only kept us in a homes of Commanders
And family that they felt they could trust
Most
Because they were constantly
Terrified
House pies
They were rounding up
Local people and accusing them of guiding drone strikes
The young guards
Protective when we were staying in the intelligence commanders house would come
Home everyday with the cell phones and possessions of
Then they had executed that day
Cumbia guys pies and guiding
Drone strikes
And is that like did you
Know that ad
The timer is that something you understood only later
Tell me I mean
Again I was learning all this stuff through
Retire
What are the last houses David was held in Seguin
The guy who later take charge of Bose custody
They only had one conversation but David said Sunday and made an impression
He seemed more radical than my guards
He was
You know
Deeply
Incredibly so angrily anti-American
And I can check I think that there was a joke one of his men made about
Killing me here
Xiaomi my head off or something like that it was
It was much more aggressive than other
Commanders
I really
The execution videos the sickness the constant toying with you about whether they're going to let you go
Kill you
And the cultural Chasm between us and Them
David talks about all that Echoes so squarely with with BOCES
Has the my captivity went on they were more more Angry me because they weren't getting the money or prisoners are Fame they want
And they sort of became more and more disgusted with me that I was sort of
Dirty because I was a non-believer because I wasn't Muslim I was in pure and the reason I was
Having stomach problems and diarrhea was because you know I wasn't a Muslim it wasn't because of the
Conditions we were being held in
Eventually they should have
You know
Ordered me to stop washing dishes that was one of the things I did to
Filippi's them
Stay alive and then they
Stop wanting to eat
Near me
Because I was
Assertive dirty
Animal
In their minds and in one of the more amazing moments there was an older
Man
He
He came in and he started lecture the younger guards that they shouldn't
See me as dirty
Oh really
And he said
You know David is God's creation
Any took this
He said he would
Take this
Piece of ready withholding in
I could eat it
David can eat this piece of bread in and take it out of his mouth without swallowing it
And the man said he would take that piece of bread and then place it in his own mouth
Cuz that's what
The prophet talk
Then you should treat all humans
Humanely
Kind of so interesting why do you think he cared how they thought of you
Well I think that that mean this is the moment there's a civil war
Any Islamic world for the interpretation of this face and I
Saw a examples of
Islam the modern Islam I saw I practiced in in Bosnia
Pakistan and Afghanistan and Iraq
So you there was this one older man who said that to them
But he was surrounded by these young diluted
Man whose whole identity
Was you know that there was only this strict interpretation of Islam than anyone
Who didn't
Follow their interpretation of Islam deserve to die
Anyone who live they literally told me
But anyone who lived under the
Karzai government in Afghanistan or the Musharraf government in Pakistan
Where are non-believers and deserved
To die
Michaels
Those are infidels as well
Everyone's and they were worse they hated the maiamai to Afghan College more than I hated me
Because they were
They were
Munafiqeen I can't remember all these words anymore but they were traitors
Did you ever have like
Substantive conversations with
Anyone who was holding you about the first the first three days it was all about
The Warren lady magazine
Did, 911 in my book and
And I told him about the reporting it down in Bosnia exposing the
Mass executions of thousands of Muslims in
I remember after I told him about my reporting in Bosnia they said
That's good
That means you're worth more money
Oh man
Can I see the point of my story you missed it
But there was now I mean it was
You know there was no kind of rational
Conversation
Oh and David did not overlap and haqqani custody
David escaped one night along with tie hair from the compound where they were being held and they made their way over to a Pakistani
Military base about a half-mile away and they were rescued
David and Tahir got out on June 20th 2009
I was captured just ten days later
David's never met never talk to Bo
But he says he feels linked to him
In our interview he kept coming back
Guiltily tell how much better he had it then bow
Obviously he knows it's not his fault what happened to Bo
Play Feels Bad
He said as soon as he heard a US Soldier have been grabbed by the same people
He worried that he'd be treated harshly
In part because David was treated well
Which helped him get away
Sami Yusuf sari Afghan reporter told me he did hear that after David escaped
There were all kinds of rumors and accusations flying around that someone had been paid off
Infighting between economies and other Taliban without Connie's can be trusted
What news reports at the Makati suspected
Taliban guards have taken a bribe
Maybe there was a traitor among them
So yeah
It does seem they weren't planning on letting it happen
Then again maybe bows rough treatment had more to do with the fact that he had tried to escape from them right away that first week
The haqqanis are Savvy enough to know the difference
In terms of risk
In terms of danger in terms of value
Between an American journalist
An American Soldier
In the beginning
It seems that perhaps undine in the haqqanis were looking for a quick and easy deal to get rid of bow
Sami Yusuf side in an interview for us in Dubai with a high-level Taliban guy there
This guy wasn't directly involved with the negotiations for bow
But he heard about it from the people who were involved
What does Taliban told Sammy is that initially
They wanted
Ransom Maybe
Prisoners from an Afghan jail
Which is what they'd also been asking for an David Rhodes case
But then somehow the Taliban gets word from The Americans
And it's not clear how or from whom exactly
But the story is
They get word that the Americans aren't going to pay Ransom
Just True by the way
And furthermore that they're not going to free any prisoners
Because they're not too concerned with getting blowback
Tri-State can tolerate the deaths of hundreds of American soldiers in Afghanistan
One soldier in captivity isn't that big a deal for the US Army
And this message if it really came
But apparently Sunday and got upset
And his position was what and why are we wasting our time and our resources
Let's just kill him
And that's when the sky told Tammy
That someone
A well-connected person in Pakistan
Totes on game
Don't kill him
Add that said don't worry keep the guy this is a wolf DDS
Don't get upset don't lose your patience today
This is
And after. Did you okay
Economies are willing to wait
Between spell also weights
One defense official told me
If you could set aside the circumstances of both capture
Of course you can't but if you could
Both would be a huge success story for the Army
Is 23 year old kid
No training manager is not only to survive but to resist as a p o w
The most extraordinary perhaps he does it alone
And isolation
There's no one else in the recent history of the army with a story like that
Terrence Russell as principal debriefer
Testified at a military Hearing in September
Russell is an Undisputed expert on this stuff during his career he's debriefed or interviewed about a hundred and twenty-five
5 pows possibly more than anyone in the country
The hearing Russell was asked
Basically how bad did Bo have it
Russell said you'd have to go back to the Jungle camps Vietnam to begin to compare
Experience and I don't know sir that I can give you a percentage
What is experience ranks at the same Echelon of the most horrible conditions of captivity that we've seen in the last six
Steers unquote
After Bo was rescued and they took him to a hospital in Germany
Go ask them to take the clock off the wall in the room he was in time rated like that
Should have taken him years as a captive to wean yourself off of time
Even when he was locked in whatever room
There might be a light on all the time or not at all
The clock in the calendar became bendy and troublesome
Nothing you can really understand
What do you mean
You're not in tomorrow you're not in the next week you're not here next month
And the fact that there was nothing there
I mean
You can
When you were able to distract yourself
Your mind
When you don't have any of that
Yeah
Repetition
You're my you turn into a broken record
Because at some point you have only so much to think about
Right you run out of ideas yeah
Such as will I get food today
Give it to me
Why did the girl who gave it to me yesterday look annoyed why are they giving it to me is there something I can do to make them give it to me but not make it look like I'm try
Can you get it
By the way depriving someone of any discernible schedule is a time-honored method of keeping her prisoner compliant
Who said it was maddening the obsessive thoughts
Maybe you do an Abbott and Costello bit in his head or that line from the Johnny Cash song
I fell into a burning Ring of Fire he said he can't remember the rest
Or he'd look and look and look at the room around him
Not in search of something new
Just because that's all he had to look at
Are you still moving
If you're thinking maybe bone went crazy
He didn't
He says he didn't
I might have been a little easier if you had but he didn't
In fact a psychologist we talked to who was on a Seer team that plan for Bose return
He said that they assumed if you survive captivity you're more or less psychologically healthy
PTSD Maybe
I'm not crazy
Because as soon as you start to lose your mind
Your chances of surviving go down
If you spend save 5 years trying to get food trying to get water trying to escape
You need to keep your mind intact for all that
Still sanity
In both situation is psychologically exhaust
Because you're simultaneously bored
Afraid
And Hyper aware
A combination other pows
Described
Mark espo
Did you tell yourself stories
Did you try to disappear into your imagination
And surprisingly both said not really
He said he would force himself to stay in the present not succumb to what he calls his fantastic storybook tendon
And that's partly what got him in trouble in the first place
Anyway even if you'd wanted to drift off
Ebony just couldn't
I didn't have a choice about it
Pain he said
Is a great distractor
He might spend an entire day just dealing with his feet
Or the cramps from dehydration
From starvation
His body was demanding his full immediate
Attention
Dosas even when he was kind of ready to give up his body was stubborn
Nagging
Doing its own thing
Only reason why I'm still here simply because my body didn't quit
What food came he ate it
Body just
Maybe so cold
But his body would struggle to get warm
But even with that like wrapped around my shoulders
Did you ever ask for more blankets
Ended up giving me an extra blanket
I don't know I mean everybody human has some some
Did you know
Good qualities especially if somebody's
How to place a low placenta and travels in Hawaiian
I can't say for sure of course but I think it's possible the guy who gave both a blanket with a cook
Emma Brock
Sammy interviewed him for Mark's company page one who's an older guy maybe 50
Unmarried
He don't have Connie's a long time you cook for them and their people for many years
He retired and moved back to his Village from your job but he told Sammy that one day a few years ago
He got a call to come to a job
He's met my Melissa and Dean
Protection for remote farmhouse
There's no Road you have to hike way out to it
And I'm not sure but it's possible this place was somewhere in the show all Valley
Couple hours from here to Shaw
Sunken gives them an AK-47 and tell them the whole area is mined don't leave the house
If you see anyone approached shoot
Inside the house by Brock says he sees his gas
I guess he means prisoners a blue-eyed Foreigner in one small dark room and some rich Afghan guy
In another room
He said they were all stuck out there in the wild
The two prisoners 3 guards in Iraq
The guards weren't allowed walkie talkies or phones
Couple times a week someone might show up then use a code word to be let in
In Sammy's notes by Brock sounds like he was more than a little freaked out
Kisses
The only thing we could hear there was noise of drones
Dangerous animal crying dangerous animal cries at night and scary deep Darkness
Yeah
Yeah babies Montanez night time is quite scary you know it's very scary they have all kind of bad animals and draw
24-hour light
Making buzz buzz buzz and you are worried
High enough maybe there is a red or something going on
You could not leave everything like that you know because they were trusted by
The commander
Bob Rocks first menu he said was potato with gravy yogurt and naan
He said they kept one plate aside for bow since he wasn't Muslim no one else would eat off that plate
Brock said the Afghan prisoner was chatty and funny
Couldn't communicate with bow
I could see that if I wasn't doing well
Wasn't eating much
Which is an insult
By the way
Tell Sammy he wasn't sure if Beau didn't like the food or just needed a utensil
Find a spoon for him
And he said I mean every time of course he was trying to say something but you don't understand
I want English was not good
Then he said
Sometime I really wish I could understand he was trying to say something can next
Time
I brought lot of thing for him and he didn't pick up nothing kuptimi Enola
Like I brought
Pastime all I thought he may be sick or something
Understand what you're what I had in color
He says in the notes
It says
One day he was asking me something
I brought numbers of things at the NEX
Next arrival but he did not take
Either of it and was laughing
Yeah I brought himself
A tablet of painkiller
And blanket
Yeah because he was an old man you know I was trying to understand to give him something
American was
American was sitting
In the beginning of the time
Put his head on his knees and number of times
Chrome and he
Remain with his head down on his knees
Yeah that's what happened
Maybe maybe he doesn't I mean maybe was very sad depression.
He was used to coming to the door to breathe fresh air and see light
But then he gives up and stays
But then he gave up in stages place
There are lots of images out there many of them horrifying
Of cap
Usually westerners
About to be executed wearing orange jumpsuits I'll Guantanamo Bay
The symbolism
It's so clear so loud
Talk about his captivity I hadn't realized just how present Guantanamo and other US prisons
Arby's guys
It comes up all the time
Digestion displays a broad political theater
The topic is woven all through both story and in David Rhodes to
Timmy talked to another guy named Butters almond butter and his brother abdur-rahim
They've spent a few years in prison at Guantanamo
Call Sammy his brother met bow in 2010
And he went to his room
And he said I should treat him like the way I was treated by American in Ghana
Montana movie and he says the American reopen tradition was so strong
Mange
Sorry I also asking him like strange question
Like what
You know like like asking to how many dogs do you have
How many chickens do you how many eggs you are chicken
You already know
Saw nonsense questions
Translated as well but he who could speak English little bit because he learned Guantanamo
I said it's some point he had a debate with Bergdahl and told him why you are
And I understand why you can't understand in America downstairs
I'm too fly by American forces
I'm not
A decision-maker and I will reply
It's not my fault I just did what I was told
Yeah I just told him you can simply say no
Aleve or Mandarin come here
Father's alma mater happens to be a guy also talked to for a story I worked on back in 2005
He's Afghan and he and his brother
The poet and journalist
We're living in Pakistan
They pissed off some important people with their writing much of which was
Caracal
Pakistani authorities arrested them and turn them over to US forces and we sent them to Guantanamo
It wasn't much of a terrorist back then but it seems we might have turned it into one
Is reportedly working as an Isis recruiter now
David said the people holding him would tell him
We're treating you well because we're better than the American
We treat our prisoners better than Americans treat their prisoners in Guantanamo and upgrade
Bose case though
That rationale seem to work in reverse
Princeton's the guy who repeatedly tortured bow
Poses a man would come into the room
I never saw his face because either Bowl would be blindfolded or the guy's face was covered with a cloth
Cody Hancock
Sitting cross-legged on the floor
Both of the guy with painted legs down
Push me against the wall
And then cut his chest with a razor blade
Don't know don't think one or two cuts at a time
Between 60-70 cuts at a time
It hurts more
Of course if you do it slowly
I lost count how many Cuts after it reached 600
And I would he would he
What did he speak English enough to tell you why he was
Is punishing you
No it wasn't speaking English
Flalottery
What is fisa mean
Like wife
Yeah wife
Donkey
Is more like
Along the lines of Revenge Type Thing
Yeah for what
Being American
For all the things that Americans have done in their country for all the
We're done the guys in Guantanamo and diagram and all that
Stillwater boarding the dogs
Isolation Chambers
Food deprivation and sleep deprivation all those thing goes with a list of
What would you say in response
I wouldn't I wouldn't say anything usually with one-way conversations I just listened to them
He waited out
You like no otter
Would you at least say I understand I hear you and
Stuff like that
Understanding what they're saying
And that's what they wanted acknowledgement so that's what I give him
Goes in the cage against a metal cage padlock together
Is soulmate one last impotent attempt at Escape
He said he did it because he was so angry he could not stand the idea of these guys winning
Is it wasn't a second to last year
One of the guys English
Got really angry about that
After the guy left
Beau decided to risk
Lifting the particle board away from the cage
Floor she'd realize the only fly in the cage was the shotty welding down there
He thought if he could rest the welds with spit or water you can maybe get a few of the bars free and squeeze out
Because of the cold and damp the particle board how to expand it so he gets it maybe halfway up
But then he can't get it back down in place
Hide what he's trying to do so he thinks if he softens it maybe you can shave off the edges and get it to go back down
Put water on it which just makes it swell even more and that begins a fight with a particle board at last
All night
All night he's using a AAA Battery he had he popped off the top and flattened it and sharpened it against the cage
And now he's using it to try to shave down the particle board and every noise he makes he scared someone's going to hear
And come in and then who knows what the consequences would be but very bad
I can't get the board back down
Idea of losing that one chance
Exhausted
Pilfer
I don't think I ever
I'm back from it
I never stop
It's like putting water on a
Stop trying to escape
That night thing to burn something out of me
Yeah I'm back
Something inside of me that
By his last year-and-a-half
The prisoner
Moses's daily conversation had funneled down to a few words
It's a
That's fine
That's good
I say okay
Or understood
Does it
In 2011 a diplomat named Mark Grossman came in as the state Department's special representative to Afghanistan
Pakistan
At that point the US government nubo was with a Connie's in Pakistan
Griezmann said he'd often bring up with the pakistanis in those years
AA meetings with the foreign sector
Kateri the Prime Minister the president the Army chief of staff
According to Grossman the response was consistent
We're sympathetic
If we hear anything will let you know
We'll do what we can
Makes you wonder
What are we doing
To get Bo out
How hard we try
You had a bureaucracy that was broken
And a
Do you have a feeling of well he's a traitor anyway so
I bet you made that was probably the most
Truck jokes
Part of dead and I'm home was just stacking
Inclusion always a traitor
Next time on serial
Ciro's produced by Julie Schneider Dana trevisani in partnership with Marc Bolan Megan Ellison Hugo Lindgren Jessica Weisberg page 1 + anime
Turtle pictures
Our glasses are editorial advisor Whitney Dangerfield is our digital editor research by Kevin Garnett fact-checking by Michelle
Paris copyediting by anaheed Alani
Our music is composed by Nick thorburn Fritz Myers and Mark Phillips the show is mixed by Kate bilinski Christian Taylor's Arkham
Community editor
Other cereal stafseth Lind Emily Condon Elise Ferguson and Kimberly Henderson
Special thanks this week to Tamar London Glenn Palmer Barney Ruben Robert Cruz
Kevin danaher
Mark rabenhorst Alec State Dan Marquis and Jeff Mann
Our website is serial podcast. Org in this week we've got a great 3D map that flies over North and South
Waziristan
Part of the tribal areas of Pakistan where Bo was held
If you want to know more about David Rhodes kidnapping and Escape his wife wrote a book about it called a rope and a prayer
You can find a link to it on our website
Again that serial podcast
. org
Stay tuned for a preview of our next episode
The first
Support for serial comes
ADT
You can use the ADT app
To monitor your camera
Video doorbell
Virtually any
Visit att.com podcast
To learn more about how ATT can do
Design and install your cuss
Back by 24/7
Serials production of This American Life and WBEZ Chicago
Coming up
Next episode of serial
We're talking about
AAA
Recovery situation
That was so complicated
That
Nobody event
Not nobody knew how to even begin to unravel
Are Niche job is to find hostages
If you just want a few example
NGA Dia CIA FBI NSA
There had to be some political
Pressure
To make that
And that's where you come in
I want to know everything about you know
Potential terrorist Network here what are the capital networks look like where are the likely places that they would take a hot
I did pick up
M&T speaking in past it was very exhausting not
I was not able to understand except for he said.
That's when I went out