Why don't you go ahead and tell us
What you know about the death of
Pele
Previously
Interior
So you want in and out
Debbie Milligan I can say is just a normal day
Nothing abnormal.
She was concerned
Questions about an affidavit
But I think I think Asia like you might be that
Holiday
Global Tel Link
Prepaid call from
From This American Life and WBEZ Chicago
Serial one story told week by week
Hurricane Ike
Weird episode 2 you probably heard episode 1 on This American Life or through our website
Podcast. Org
If you haven't
Stop
Go back to the beginning we're telling this story in order the story of Haman Lee
An 18 year old girl who was killed in Baltimore in 1999
In the story of Adnan Syed
Her ex-boyfriend who is convicted of
Crime
Pick up where we left off
Last episode you heard how the prosecution told the story of this murder at a nun's trial
The motive the state supplied the basis for the whole thing
Was it after he broke up with a nun
She couldn't accept it
He was so wounded by her and so Furious
That he decided to kill her
Prosecutor Kevin urick told the jury in his opening statement
He became enraged
He felt betrayed that his honor has been besmirched
I became very angry
And he set out to kill Hae Min Lee
Or this is from closing quote it was humiliating what she did to him
Make no mistake about it ladies and gentlemen
This is not a crime about love
This is a crime about Pride
Is that what their relationship and breakup were really like
Was he so hurt that he decided to kill her that's what I'm trying to find out in today's episode by talking to lots of people
Close knit group known each other since elementary
High school and even though they went to a big house
High School
And their friends were come together in a magnet program of about 30 kids
High School within the school and they all took classes together and hang out together and they dated each other so we knew each other well
Any other information I have to go on our Hayes own words about their relationship because I have a copy of her diary
It was entered into evidence at trial cops prosecutors
Even at 9
What's remarkable about the diary and what makes it so helpful is that it's essentially a Chronicle of the oven on era of his life
The first entry is April 1st 1998 when they started going out
And the last entry is dated January 12th the day before she went missing
Is it not
And then another one right at the end
The first dance was junior prom
Anonymous best friend had a little competition going about who could get
Prettiest prom date that year
K2 go
After Sports practice on the little hill behind the school
He asked her to prom and she said yes
On April 27th she wrote a long entry in her diary about prom night
Her diary by the way I'm not exactly sure what I expected her diary to be like
It's such a teenage girl's diary
She jumps from her boyfriend to driver's ed
The field hockey game
She probably one minute and the next she's upset with her mother
Protecting her friend are complaining about homework
Prom night
She writes about Adnan
I swear he's the sweetest guy
Let me tell you why
She was prompt
Stephanie was prom princess
A traditionally they're supposed to dance
Together to my song
KC and JoJo All My Life
I tried to act natural and I'm jealous
10 seconds later guess who danced with me and not was
Anon
How can I not fall in love with
Of course I gave him his first
Kiss on the lips
And I totally fell in love with her
Since then I keep on falling deeper and deeper into him
The bad thing is that we have to keep things secret
Psy
But it's okay
Love conquers all
For a while I would like to know today were flaring and I will like make fun of her about it
Does Aisha Pittman
She was in the magnet program to
He was her best friend
You look show me nudes that they share it and then it just
Progressed from
From there
And but it was it was a relationship that sconce
Bentley secret because neither there
Families knew about it so that
Created much more of a lake
Her saying I'm going to be at your house but really I'm going out with him
Kind of thing
Oh she would she would tell her parents you that your play
Or others
Primarily mine
Just a lot of that sort of secrecy around
We had a lot of
I guess
A lot of real similar
Similar type of situations with our families
Since he and I both had immigrant parents they understood the expectations
And the constraints
Go to college take care of your younger brother
And Ferdinand no girls
If a female friend run his car for instance you have to make sure not to leave any longhairs behind
Where's a girl gave Adnan a ride home
You have to drop him off down the block
So his parents wouldn't see who is at the wheel
You know it was really easy
To date someone
That kind of living in the same parameters that I did with regards to you though
Speed in a vacuum
Location of me coming to her house for dinner with her family
You know she understood that
You know that
Call the house
My mother and father I would get in trouble
Vice versa
You know so we would have to come and set up our
Well Repair in your sleep
They had a whole system for this
Clear
Remember it's 1998 so not many cell phones around
Then that person would call someone 800 service
What's the weather or the time and the other one would call in so that the phone wouldn't actually rang it would come in through call waiting
And the dosing parents would never be the wiser
At the trial the state tried to paint a picture of an odd as possessive of hay
Controlling
When I spoke to his closest friends about that a couple of them did say that he over involved
Somehow
But I couldn't come up with many examples
Do people remember the time when it done showed up uninvited to a girls trip to an amusement park Aisha Pittman was one of them
She remembers nothing positive about their relationship anymore
Go by your own admission she doesn't know whether her memories are colored by what came later
I think it was probably mostly normal but things that
He kind of just always generally annoyed me because
Just
The constant
Paging
If you was out
He's like what I just wanted to know where you were in
I told you
Clear Eyes going to be
She was at my house and we were having a girl's night he
Would stop by like it would walk over and try to
Come hang out
Have some space
And it's one of those things at first it's like oh it's so cute your boyfriend is dropping by
The temp time it's like
Really
Did he ever did hey ever seen freaked out by it
No but I don't think I was ever freaked out by it in the moment
Impromptu visits I was talking about
On July 16th she writes
Carrot cake
So yeah he does not describe a nun as overbearing
Are possessive in her diary
Though she does mention a couple of moments when she's mad at
How dare you get mad at me
Replying to hang with Keisha
The time when he was nasty to her because she didn't respond to his messages
Mostly these incidents seem to be
Frittata
Attitude is not helping
Wright's engine
He hasn't called me since 12:30 this afternoon and it's definitely pushing me to the edge
I think I'm going to pick up
His friends say she had a strong personality
Strong opinions
She's no pushover
She's pissing on she let him know
But by far the majority of her diary entries are about how much she likes
And loves him
I stopped counting there was so many wonderful things
Sweetest sin best boyfriend in the world
Stuff like this from their fur
Here's Becky Klein
Back then she was Becky Walker
This is silly teenage High School relationship I remember
A lot of
Teasing and a lot of
You know
Hand holding arms around each other
I don't really remember any
Anything weirder
Anything that stands out
Around all that summer before senior year
After work and drive around
They were 17 they're in love
They were active
They have sex whenever and wherever possible
Sometimes at motels are in the car
Parker other people's houses are part
Sometimes they fight quickly makeup
A couple of times he called it off
But then would ask for a
Saturday
Remember this NF
Crimes that the state light out
Was it a non was betraying everything he held dear for this
Is it good Muslim he was not supposed to be dating
Until he was sacrificing his religion and lying to his family
All just so he could be with her
Twisted up inside
And his diary seems to be where they found some evidence for that
In fact they had a friend of his
Debbie Warren
Read excerpts from it on the witness stand
I like him know I love him
Shred-it trial
Dated May 15th
It's just all the things that stand in the middle
His religion and Muslim Customs are the main thing
It hurts me to know that I'm against his religion
He called me a double few times
I know I was only joking
Somewhat true
And then there's this which wasn't right at trial but is from July when Adnan went to an Islamic conference in Texas with
What is Dad
This is the most distressed he gets on the
When I read it I thought
Does not look so good for Adnan
I keep crying over the phone because I miss him so much
She writes
He told me that his religion means life to him
He tried to remain a faithful Muslim all his life
He fell in love with me which is a great sin
But you told me there is no way he'll ever leave me
If you can't imagine a life without me
Have to choose between me and his religion
I love him so much
And when it comes to choosing I'm going to let him go his way
I hate the fact that I'm the cause of his sin
He said that I shouldn't feel like I'm pulling him away from his religion but hello that's exactly what I'm doing
Anytime someone's writing stuff down like
CNN devil and religion means life in reference to their secret relationship
That's not good
Ask the muscle in question about it
It all sounds so much smaller
I'm going to put it as a joke
Why can't you I'm going to hell because I'm dating you were something but I never mentioned in type of way
Anon claims he just wasn't that religious
I was going to clubs and having sex with girls and smoking weed
The time he was 14 or 15
Culturally yes I'm a
But the rest he says not so much
So passages like this
He says he doesn't really recognize himself in them
I never
I never really felt as if you know
Now you know hate is tearing me away from my lips
I never
Does she kind of has
Just like the gravity
And the magnitude with which she took these things
I didn't really feel that way about these
It seems convenient
My behavior didn't change what's up
You know I just continue with the same type of behavior different people
Religious stepaside the States was guilt-ridden over line to his family. Hey
He says he wasn't all that bothered by that
He was a pretty good kid
Is doing well in school job he was volunteering at the mosque
Why should we have some fun
In the pantheon of ways a teenager could have been disrespectful or deceitful to his parents
He thought this rated pretty low
My name is shamim Rahman
And I'm the mother of Adnan Syed
When did most of his lying to his mother
She figured out something was up pretty early on
She found a nun's crown from prom in the basement where he tried
Stocks
Shamim came to the United States in 1976
Her husband is already here working as an engineer for the state of Maryland
She's from Peshawar in package
Stan were you do not date
You are either married or unmarried
How much of a middle ground
Sonance girl contact put shamim in a state of high alert
She would check the mileage on his car to see if you driven farther than he said
Eavesdrop 20
Girls on the phone
I know this makes you meme sound terrifying but she's not at all
She adores at 9
Her middle son
I'll pick up the phone or LG
You know what you say like Mom hang up the phone
You know I know you listening to me
PS I said none I'm here you said Mom stop. You know listening to us
An end
Was that conflict mean
It must have been
Set of const
Find me it was unacceptable
Solis two Advil and you know I say no you cannot do that you can.
If you like somebody you know it's alright you can get married but not without marriage you cannot
Excuse me in Italian
Anton's father was a little more loose about it
Everybody's doing it
Even my husband say you know.
Are the boys are
My children
I don't wasn't getting punished for any of the
Wasn't as if you were about to go
Kicked out of the house
He was being reminded of his responsibilities
Both at home and at his mother's request
By his youth leader at the mosque
Venting the homecoming dance
The fall of senior year
Anon and hay been together for about 7 months by then
Justanswer become a big deal a trial
Proof of just how fraught their whole relationship was
And how tormented Anon was about his double life
What happened
Anon parents got wind that very night
It had taken hey to homecoming
I know this is kind of thing happens in their Community all the time
Someone see someone else
For aunties are on the phone to the kids mother
Anyway this time Adnan parents did not wait to deal with it at home
They showed up at the dance and chastised him
Made a scene
The prosecutors argued that this scene would come to haunt him until the day he killed her
Is a prosecutor Casey Murphy told the jury about the moment when she says Adnan strangled
What is it that this defendant saw on January 13th when he looked down at Hailey
Angeles a couple things and says this
He saw his parents standing at the window of the homecoming dance
He saw his mother raised her voice
Sahalie in front of his classmates
Look what you're doing to our family
He saw the pain in his mother's face
Because she knew there were together
He saw himself in the end
Standing there with nothing to show for it but a guilty conscience
Pack of lies in which
He called himself
Compare that
With how adnan's best friend Saad remembers the homecoming debacle
11 p.m.
12:00 midnight
And he's like you're not going to believe this but he's like my mom my dad showed up and I'm like what
We're dying laughing on the phone about the xenos
This is our world
What happened at Laguna Bay showed up they made me leave
And everyone
Solid halide literally
My parents pulled me out of this relationship
Across dozens of us
Information that can either mean one thing or perhaps it's opposite depending on who's talking
Cell phone for example he bought it just two days before he disappeared
The state tried to show that that was all part of his plan that he needed the phone to carry out the murder
Pronounce says he wanted the phone so he could call girls unfettered
Is an EMT to pay for it
The job the state would argue that because he was an EMT at someone
I had the training to revive last he says he was proud of me
Score on the qualifying test if anyone in his class
Ride in the back of the ambulance with old people make sure they were okay
In the detectives notes they interview Adnan English teacher Jane Efron apparently tells them
Which is in his poetry
The words dark side
Are underlined
Saffron
Because everything in my life
I don't remember any of them having any
Upbeat to say
Shawty was just
Another one
That makes you think
But you're living on another planet
Can you look after them and they're all healthy and Hearty and playing
Cats being stupid
So you didn't stick out in
Somebody was just like all teenagers write dramatic Pro
Absolute
All this information every scrap its currency for whatever side you're on its spin
And the trouble with spin is that you can't totally disregard it because swirling around somewhere inside
Some tender love it
Is true
Innocent
Homecoming story
Is also an assassin
They didn't write about Homecoming in her diary
Tricia says it wasn't funny to her was a big deal
Are you sure members of non-parents wanting to find hey so they could talk to her
Which of course he wanted nothing to do with
So that we could leave the dance and not
Be harassed by
His parents like she walked out holding hands with my friend Sean to get away from it and she
You just felt like that
Completely
Ridiculous thing
LSU super pissed
Wanting to have
I think that for her was a I absolutely do
But this person at all because
This is what happens
On November 3rd he wrote in her diary
Who would have thought we would end like
Who would have imagined the amount of pain that comes with a broken heart
I know I'm doing the right thing
Call me selfish but this pain is way less than what it would be if we stayed together
Apparently they reunited because exactly a month later on December 3rd
She's full of love for an on-again
This feels so real
So loving and ever so amazing
I can't be any happier but yet I keep on being happier
Then just three days later there's this on December 6th
But what's the matter with me
Everytime I close my eyes I see my baby
But I keep on thinking about someone else
He's got a crush on Don
An older guy
Is 20
She works with at LensCrafters
The Owings Mills Mall
John has blue eyes and blond hair and a Camaro and she really really likes him
For the next couple of weeks she's racked with guilt and confusion over what to do
At one point she writes anions name in giant block letters made out of tiny little Adnan
And underneath that does the same thing with John in giant letters made up of tiny dots
127 *
127 Dons
Is that clear from the diary when she finally tells Adnan
It's over over
But certainly by Christmas they were split
On New Year's Day has her first official date with Don and they start going out
Hey is Head Over Heels
Are you sure remembers meeting him
On a double date
Friday's restaurant and then to see the movie Shakespeare in Love
What's the most awkward double date
Because he was older
I forget how old he was but he was significantly older than
And my boyfriend was
2 years younger
Fetishist
Horrible
With one man and one boy
Yeah
This is where the real questions begin
Important questions about Adnan
About how he responded to this break up into the fact of his new boyfriend
Because the whole premise of the state's case against Adnan
Is Eddie felt betrayed and humiliated and angry and that's why he killed her
This idea came from Jay their main Witness
It was Jane who supplied the motive to please
What did he tell you he told me that she broke his heart during extremely wrong
Granny want to treat him that way
Believe how she stays in looking face to face and told him she didn't love on me
Could be that heartless
He told me he said
Almost joking I think I'm going to kill him yeah
He didn't know how he was going
Because she approached
But nearly everyone I spoke with his friends and teachers
Announcer in Mac Francis boyfriend
But he grumbled about it in a typical guy weigh nothing strange
Everyone I talked to said some version of this
But he wasn't rage-filled or vindictive
He was just sad
It really did seem like run-of-the-mill mundane teenage
Angst
Pestana paoletti Phillips
She taught at 9 and hey AP psychology
Sentara freshman
At her job she seen a lot of high school break up
The level of frustration he must have fell
If he killed her
Doesn't register with me
I don't remember getting that vibe from
It was just
He was just another kid
Whose heart was broken
And
Goodness if I thought that the kids I teach
Today we're going to resort to
Some kind of
Horrific crime based on that kind of saying I would have stopped teaching
Because I have every other day it would be
Announce France odds that Adnan definitely wasn't mooning over hey
When they had broke up and then and had broke up
It's been like a month
Maybe more she already started dating another guy and I was like
Announce dating multiple girls I was like I can tell you some of the girls that he's dating I'd like he is not upset about him
I hate breaking up
I was like he's dating this girl honestly in Philly that he's been going to see
This girl and I know it wasn't like grapefruit but it was still proof that he wasn't obsessed with that he wasn't
I'll try to explain on 17 like he's a player
He has a lot of girls I was like he's talking about the island I am too
Miss cute and Charming
He's just a
Free
Guy
Sorry sad she's not talking about you this is Anjali the girl in Philly
And she confirmed yep couple of visits they made out nothing too serious
New Year's Eve and I'm in another girl Nisha from Silver Spring Maryland
He started calling her a lot too
Announce redneck Remember To None making out with another friend of theirs at a party that January
So yeah
The player
Describes
Breakups with us
Peach time that we broke up with each other
Relationship or take a break
It was never a thing where I was like pestering her like
Going to your house knocking on the door
We're chasing her down the Bell when I get back with you when I get back to me cuz
So
Pretty much
We we talked about things like she would tell me about
Someone is she a manager job
Chinese dog
And she was like so she really like them
And
You have 30 seconds remaining
Yeah, call me back
That's the prison phone system telling us our time is up
Happens every half hour
Surprise me every time cuz I forget where he is
But so you're you're making the breakups
Sound very
Kind of
Tom and mutual and like nobody got upset
But
I mean is that true or was there like
Crying and the usual teenage angst
15 years later I mean
She was upset I was upset you know what times I was very sad
Maybe I was trying to be like a little stubborn about it
But on the other hand
It was everything where I was like you know screaming and yelling at her why you leaving me or
So
Spell that that that that that that that was never my behavior
You know at all
It is true that no one at the time described as acting obsessed or menacing and anyway
Venetia
Never expresses any concerns about Adnan post-breakup Behavior
She writes about a time just before Christmas so after they broken up
When she gets into a little car accident
And calls up at 9 to come get her from work
Bust on her new crush and Adnan
Look at the car together and decide it's unsafe to drive so Adnan takes her home
Apparently was all very cordial
Even Don said so
You wouldn't talk to me for the story but he testified at the
Trial
At this point I'm going to say flat out that I don't buy the motive for this murder
At least I have a state explain.
I just don't see it
That one person says he was acting strangely after they broke up
By all accounts we're still friends
He was interested in other girls he was working at his job he was headed to college
About two weeks after his arrest he gets an orientation packet
University of Maryland
I don't think he was some empty shell of a kid who betrayed his family and his religion it was now left with nothing and conjured up a murderer
Age for girl who broke his heart
I simply don't buy it
And the reason I don't buy it is because no one who knew him then or now
Says that's how it was
I want to be clear though
But that doesn't mean he didn't do it
It just means that so far I think the state story about why he killed her doesn't hold up
Maybe it was more of a spur-of-the-moment thing
Maybe despite the other girls he was running after he was privately stewing about hey
After all she was apparently still flirting with them after they broke up
Stop aging him with loving messages
Spider-Man expensive jacket that Christmas
Maybe sorry start a chance with her
What their friend Debbie told me
Maybe once Don came on the scene he thought
That's a slap in the face
How dare you continue to leave me on like this
The night before he disappeared on call her from a cell phone three times
The first two calls at 11:27 p.m. and 12:01 a.m. for only 2 seconds each
The third call at 12:35 a.m.
Lasted a minute and 24 seconds
Announce that he was probably calling to give his new cell phone number he just got in the phone the day before
Kennedy in the top left corner of her diary she'd written down the number
According to Downs testimony she been at his house that night which is probably why Adnan first two calls ended so fast probably
I wasn't home yet
Her very last diary entry January 12th is brief
I love you.
I think I found my soulmate
I love you so much
I fell in love with you the moment I open my eyes
To see you in the break room for the first time
There is one detail about the missing but I need to tell you about
I detailed it doesn't look good for Adnan
And that detail has to do with whether or non tried to get in Hayes car right after school
Because that is what the state would allege
Button on fabricated a reason to get in your car that afternoon
So you could kill her
Jay had told police that was a nun's plan
Did she tell you how he's going to do it that day
No but
He tells me that
He's going to do it in her car
He said to me that
He was going to
Colors car was broken down
And I asked her for a ride
So what do we know about the end of that day
Wednesday
Generator
Shannon had a couple classes together
First. And also last. AP Psychology with Miss paoletti
That's when I usually saw hey
The end of psychology she was talking to an on
Remember seeing her on her way to her car
She told Debbie she had to get her cousin from school and then was going to see. At the mall
The very last person to see hey it's cool that day we think
Is Inez Butler Henry
Inez rental concession stand right at the gym entrance
And he would come by every day and get the same thing
Veryfine apple juice and hot fries
She drove up in front of the gym where the concession stand was
Electric car running
So she came around the circle park the car right there
Jumptown
And ran in to get something to drink
And to tell me
None of us not to leave him
The bus was for the boys wrestling team
Haywood manager and had a match later that afternoon that he was supposed to go to
And
You didn't see ref
After that
It's not anywhere near her car
No
I didn't see him there to come
Okay so no one actually testified at trial that they saw Hannah Donnelly school together
Aside from
Says they spotted a nun in her car at anytime that afternoon
Adnan has no recollection of having a stay for a ride anywhere
We talked about it many times
Here's what he said the very first time I asked him
McDonald's
The trouble for Adnan
Is it a couple of their friends say he did ask
4 ride
What are the different Crystal
If I remember correctly
I think Adnan and I worked
Class
Together
And
They pass each other in
In the hallway
And I was with him
I remember somebody saying or him things
Something about
Can you give me a ride after
After school
Different Becky told police
She heard something about a ride as well
I do remember that there was talk about it I remember I felt like
He asked her to give him a
Give him a ride somewhere
Okay
Can I just read to you what
The police notes a April 9th 99 the interview Geo
Sometime earlier that day
Apparently he asked her to take him possibly to get
Car
Before lunch
Because it was in the shop
Heard about it at lunch
I think you heard about it at lunch
Right
He said she could
There would be no problem
At end of school I saw them she said oh no I can't take you I something else
To do
She didn't say what else
Approximately 220 so that happened at approximately 2:20
He said okay I'll just ask someone else
He told her goodbye
Energy says did not see her after that
Yeah that sounds right
Kind of all comes back a little bit
Christian Becky both remembered
I'll bet he's our collection maybe Works in a nun's favor
But they turned him down for a ride he's
Cool with that
The question is still there
Was he trying to get in her car
Did she ask for a ride
Json
Evidence in support of a statement
Does even come from Crystal
Comes directly from
Because he himself told the cops the same thing that day
Who sang the state record police officer Scott Adcock to the stand
Around 6:30 p.m. after heading on missing
A Baltimore County police officer named Scott Adcock
Call Dad on cell phone
His family was worried that she hadn't turned up her cousin School
And the officer was calling around to some of her friends to see if they knew where she was
Here's Adcock testifying at trial
And he advised me that
He did see the victim in school that day
And that dumb
He was supposed to get a ride home
From the victim but he
Got detained at school when
He just got tired of waiting and left
Been a little more than two weeks after the call with officer Adcock on February 1st
But it's time to search for Jesus ramped-up
A different detective calls
Astronaut about the ride thing
Awesome did you tell officer Adcock you. Stay for a ride
According to the police report
Anan said this was incorrect
Because he drives his own car.
So
He reverses himself
Why would he do that
Why would you tell the first cop who's expecting a ride and then once it's clear Hayes missing change his story
Maybe the girls were thinking of a different day or maybe when you talk to that first guy
Maybe he did ask a for right at some point that day but he's forgotten
Or maybe he's lying I'm not a detective but I consider this a red flag
Is this a teeny tiny
The great big flapping in the breeze red flag
Next week
Cereals produced by Julie Snyder Dana Chavis and production and operations
Manager eyeglasses are editorial advisor
Thanks dilute us and Terry O'Connor zeros are production of This American Life and WB
Easy Chicago