Serial season 3 is presented by ZipRecruiter the smartest way to hire
Later during the break
The CEO of a company that's building a national team to keep little kids safe
North Illinois zip recruiter is rated number one by Employers in the US
Nissan hiring sites with over 1000 reviews on trustpilot
Ziprecruiter for free at ziprecruiter.com
Cereal
Support for serial comes from Squarespace
Make your business official with Google in Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and a Business website with Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and professional tools from Google
It's the simplest way to look professional online
Visit squarespace.com Google to start your free trial
And use offer code professional for a discount on your first purchase
Google and Squarespace
Make it professional make it beautiful
Previously on serial
Nearest versus a police officer can you smell raw marijuana
In a bag inside someone's pocket
I probably put more people on probation than any other judge in his Courthouse
Yeah because I can always put in a prison life
I don't think he had anything to do with officer
Guy currently has
How can you help us do that
From This American Life and WBEZ Chicago its serial one Courthouse
Public by week I'm Sarah Koenig
I was talking to this guy Kevin
40 years old he's been busted for giving someone out of college a marijuana cookie
It operated as a nice gesture really just pay have one
I thought the guy understood what it was ;-)
But he didn't know went wrong
Kevin ended up with a felony conviction
Another felony conviction
They sounded absurd
It been a trial over this cookie
That's funny right
I want to talk to Kevin the cookie Baker
In the hallway outside the courtroom in the Justice Center right after the verdict
Not funny
He was in what my mother would call us with it
Cracking angry jokes but also desperately upset have crying
Kevin said he been a drug dealer when he was young but he change
He was in school volunteering in a community trying to start his own business
Doing well
And now this
What Kevin called felonious childish stupidness
I got him kicked out of his college and it also triggered a probation violation on a case from a few years earlier
Kevin has been just two months shy of completing that probation
Is almost done
And now this
I'm sorry I said this is a rough day
He said it's alright it's alright
It's all right
I'm starting to get used to it actually
It started right about 16 17 in it
Kate
I Got Roots here
Just like a bad relationship I can't get out of there
So far in this series we've talked a lot about the system aspect of the justices
Other Machinery of it works
Or does it
Now for the rest of the series we want to look at the criminal justice system whole other way
We want to follow people who are like heaven
People who feel like they have roots in the system
I've been in it for years and who been shaped by its machinery
Probably nothing we've reported so far would be news to them
I know it
I know it's pretentious
To say this but I keep thinking of this Russian word
Choose two of us
It means to feel something almost sensually
To the point where you can taste
You know it in your bones
So now we're going to follow people out of the Justice Center
Out into the world into their normal lives
The guy we're going to start with
His name is Jesse Nickerson
Back in the summer of 2016 before we got to Cleveland
There been a police scandal with a satisfying twist
I'm allowed to call it that
Two officers had arrested this guy Jesse Nickerson
And instead of taking him back to the station they drove to a city park took off Jesse's handcuffed
And what are the officers got him denayne Dixon
6 foot four former linebacker in the arena football league challenge Jesse to a fight
Jesse squared off with denayne Dixon for a second but then he took off
Ran into the woods
The officers eventually found in cuff them
Jesse said they betta
The officers said he hurt himself
Story made the news
Absolutely second
Appaloosa shocks
Talking to a TV reporter
This all happened in East Cleveland East side of Cleveland East Cleveland is it
Unsmil city bordering Cleveland
17000 people in government and some Police Department
It seemed refreshingly as if those entities were taking responsibility for what happened and swiftly
Excuses police officers were fired within days
The police chief referred the case to State investigators
The County prosecutor's office criminal indictments guilty to a couple misdemeanors the other
Denayne Dixon
Plato couple felonies
We went to denayne Dixon Center
The Justice Center
He is a fog line of our criminal justice system
That's what the public see
That's the prosecutor
Ashley kilbane
Your honor
When you have
Somebody is a public official
Not only
A Lamborghini
But then tried to cover up cover it up by turning off their body
A police officer convicted for bad behavior on the job already unusual in this Courthouse
I'm here Ashley Cobain was arguing forcefully
For the harshest possible punishment
Who's pitching consecutive sentences
Minimum sentence for each crime would run back to back
The judge Nancy fuerst
Invited officer Dixon to speak
You have anything to say sir
And he did
He apologized
He said I understand I was put in a position of authority and I was entrusted with a public Trust
To make a difference
To be part of the solution and not part of the problem
And then he said
I know intention of assaulting anyone
Before
It's difficult to hear but he says it was a tactic I had seen done before
You know take a guy out of cuffs and get him to stop running his mouth or whatever
Officer Dixon's lawyer told the court that Dixon told him the same thing
Which is kind of disturbing
Other than that no one remarks on this
Kind of disturbing information
Just let it go
The judge sentenced today in Dixon to 2 years in prison
And it was over
Victim Jesse Nickerson was not in the courtroom the day of the Sun
But he's been in touch with the County Prosecutors throughout the
He told Emmanuel that it one point they given him some advice
That he found
Kind of disturbing
The prosecutor
And
Now they told me
They telling me to stay out of East Cleveland
Jesse said they told him remember the name Dixon's got friends
He said you know the name you know
You know they have you know you have people
Dallas Clayton
They like when I want to hear about you son happened to you
Daddy's Clayton
Usually these cases of police brutality the ones we hear about
The government responses
Constipated
Months sometimes years of stop-start internal investigations
Equivocating public officials officers placed on desk Duty
And then it just Peters out
In Jesse's case
There was none of that
The officers who abused him had been fired convicted and sentenced
Jessie gotten all the things there are things people say they want in cases like this
Just hit one
And yet
Jerry West
On high alert
This whole situation with the police
It was not over
Manuel he lived in Cleveland for most of the year we were reporting their
And this is one of the cases he began to look into
Manuel interviewed police and prosecutors
Any review Jesse Nickerson
And that interview
Turn into a nearly year-long Adventure is to happy a word
Misadventure I guess
A year Watching Jesse negotiate the afterwards of his case
The push and pull of one man's relationship with the police in his town
Is Emmanuel
Jesse Nickerson told me that he was so relieved the officers who taking him to the park that night
Black and white
It feels like a babe in white
He probably would have gone shop
The first time we met we went over the falls to epoxy you can walk me through what happened
Show me the spot way to hidden behind a tree
The place where you said the officers choked him
To be blacked out
They beat me right here
Looking for a reason why here
Make it to the bottom of this big hill that he says the Elvis room down when Jesse stop
How many points is something through the trees
Chapel Hill Police
Way way off in the distance
Just boarded the cop car
Black Ford Explorer
Police in block letters down the side
Jesse harbin calmly and casually residing details of his alleged assault
But now
He's uncomfortable
Got the same truck I was in at night
That's the same truck I was in when they did that to me
How do you know
They only got 1
It's been almost a year since the police took him to the park
I didn't that you just had a persistent fear of retaliation
Feels like everybody
Especially the cops
Know him is the guy who sent office at the name Dixon to prison
Why don't you receive us police truck
Levi x to me and says
I thought you was a witness in case anything happen
But then we make a way to the top of the hill and get to the truck
But I just finished eating lunch
Eaton Chipotle
Officer for the neighborhood
TV Instagram stuff
Just doesn't know this guy's real name
He does everyone calls in the new new
A few months back Nunu what's the ugliest even famous when he posted videos of himself messing around and singing
Police cruiser if he tells me
New new
Eagle right
Just relax
Justino's D's Pekin police department and they know him
Probably because he's lived there all his life
Probably because he's been arrested a lot
Let me Matt if he was 29 he spent time in prison on drug charges as well as for aggravated assault and robbery
All of that happened when Jesse was in his late teens and early twenties
He done more minor run-ins with the police in Span repossession traffic tickets
Nothing too serious
Anyway
He's not worried about nunu
Beyonce he is on the lookout for
Is a friend of the name Dixon
What's the name Wilbert Neville
He told me the story about Neville's.
Still stressing him out
Happened about six months of you
The time
The name was out in Bones
Awaiting trial for the incident with Jesse in the park
Jessie run into office and levels
On the street
I was at Chipotles on Coventry
Coventry is a big busy road
Jesse and his girlfriend we're heading back to back off to grabbing some food
East Cleveland police car rolled up
It was office in Devils
I was I was with my girlfriend Ashley
He just postcard Lightyear what's up what's up what's going on with you
Are you like holler at me like follow me
Neville's wanted Jesse to follow him down to a quiet opotamus
Presumably so they could talk in private
Jesse's no idea what this was about
His girlfriend Ashley didn't like the looks of it
Do you like
Hell no
What does he told Ashley
That's a lot of people around
So they drove down
According to a long at the End of the Street
Impact window to window
Please Rendezvous Style
Never go right to the point
Denis light said what's up you going to court on other name
Don't go to court on denayne Dixon
Human the criminal case against the name
Taking Jesse to the park
Novels with Kevin Jesse to drop the whole thing
Don't show up for court
I'll I see I'm not alright
Why would I know what to say I was scared
He asked me what's my number
He called me later on that night
When did the name Dixon on the phone
What did they say
He was saying don't go to court
Dixon
Go to court
He was saying that never go mainstream cooling PC
Amazon go to Cortana
Easy East Cleveland
What do you mean what do you mean cool NEC make sure I'm cool and easy long as I don't go to court on
Neville's interviewed by the County Post
He denied being line for that
He denied ever telling Jesse not
Did Jesse offhand about the name
Cortices number
Gabe design
And that was that
The name did call Jesse
Jesse says he kept calling
He was calling me to just check on it what's up what's up you cool everything cool how often
I mean all I got is like
Like once every two weeks to find it was telling me to get out of you telling me this
The skip out of town on you to tell me what type of stuff
Jesse felt like there was a threat behind Olivia
Schools
Sullivan unspoken or else
Gwinnett County Prosecutors found out about the goals
Bear Lake
Wait
Police officers are calling you
I'm telling you to drop this whole thing
Yeah that does not sound good
They may Define
Bad Jesse coming to the Justice Center so they can record him coolant name
Prosecutors recorded to coulson's name on vehicles the name of Jessie Nautica
Call Nicole to get out of town
You don't come and they go to the misfit
No face no case even if they don't
These goals culminated more felony charges for the name Dixon
Addition to the obvious child has to take Jesse to the park
The name pleaded guilty to obstructing justice
The names friend who Jesse says first approached him about dropping the case
Neville stayed on the falls
And so a year later
He's the focus of a lot of jet is inside about
Jesse was Shawn Neville had it out for him
I still have to walk around drive around out here
What does other officer feel like I don't owe something on him
I seen you everyday Z mug me stare at me you look at me like
He look at me
He look at me with the look
Evil like you want to kill me like
How do you say in like why do you say
I see him everyday like
Everywhere stores
Be fixing fixing on the house he ride pass
I ride up and down the street all day erryday like
Scene
Iceni
And every time I seen
He give me that look like it ain't over with
I also you Steven Police Department phone interview
Ask him if we still have the garage against death
Bubba Department refused to make nipples available
All of Me full Jesse might be the last person
I mean
The entire city of Eastvale
I'm a Cubs going to pick on the guy who go to of their own fired as a lawyer
I probably an automatic news story if anything happens to him
Why would they pick on Jessie
Then off we made our way back down to the parking lot
Another please
Black Squad
It's on towards us
Weld leyzene2 bizaardvark Mario standing
We both want
Look. Nevels
I was suddenly aware of how alone Jesse and I will
What's the middle of the afternoon and nobody was around
I was enabled in speed up
He just headed towards us
His face possibly hidden behind the clown the windshield
Makeup to us
That was made to live with circle around us
Maybe 10 miles an hour
Neville's or the Bulls lucky black guy
Turn off upstairs thermostat vacate but no like Ava
Me look straight ahead
Many drove away
Maybe it was a coincidence he showed up
Maybe not
I want Jessie shift his weight back and forth
142 B Ava
Build a fairy in his head
Listen
The officers that was right there
Then they both knew who I was
They called and told him that we was down there
Will you tell me about bad guy one of those guys up there he's like a good cop he's a good guy
You good cuz I know any but
These these officers
Good to who they work with who they know who they are here
In a field with
That's what lawyers do like
I said he was right about to come down here it came right down here
You can't write down here
All right
I'm ready to leave now cuz I'm thinking it like this
He know my car he know my car
Going to try and pull you over on the way out of here
I don't know
I don't know what you going to do
It just scared it scares me
It scares me
I see you when I get out of here
Yeah
By that point
We're both ready to get out of that
Acquired Ababa city of East Cleveland
Because everything that happened to Jesse happened in the city but doesn't function like a normal City
For example when I first started reporting about bees Cleveland Police Department I couldn't get any official information about property
Crimes violent crimes
Basic stuff
Bahamas is over
Give me the number of
A bunch of times direct call me flat out that the city simply quote
Does not compile crimes
Layoffs at disciplinary records for offices
Complaint summary report
I was initially told by City officials by the department could not supply of his records
Apparently
Asteroid
Direct violation of the city's on record retention
Optimus battering in a cool complain
City cop. Disciplinary records for just three of the 85 offices but it works in East Cleveland the last 2 years
East Cleveland can even give me records of officers who been publicly
Norfolk olbia sexually assaulted two women with a sex toy
You found in that cauldron the traffic
Is not a second income on
Completed the tax crime doctor running an illegal cigar business on the side
A note for the name Dixon
Who pleaded guilty to taking Jesse to the park
No disciplinary records what's the weather
It felt like East Cleveland has given up on basic governor
I'm not just an administrative
I got the same feeling driving around
Things are pretty bad though
One day a local took me down the street Cortez Road
We popped the fashion story apartment building
Pablo cologne
No windows
Make something outline Legend
Debris everywhere
And the guy was with told me
Watch them
Pay attention right now
Ibis point
East Weatherford Road
I'm over the Cubs
I started driving down the sidewalk
Wow
He did this to get around the potholes in the street
Thousands of
I say Paul holes but really we're talking about braces
Someone has four feet wide
Anthony Fusco schools of tire tracks
Mama drivers who done the same thing
Cuz I don't want I got to pay for this car if you get broke and driving down the street
Cleveland Golf servicepoint partly because of Decades of mismanagement and Corruption
Perusal largely because of straight-up structural racism
Is Cleveland a black City
90% black
I like many black neighborhoods in cities it's been a victim of blockbusting white flight job loss
Collapsing tax base
I'll be right here
It's 42%
Is Cleveland is the poorest city in the state of Ohio
In the park with the name Dixon challenge st205 Jessie ran
Martha. Whole thing became public
Just decided he wanted to sue the police department
Why the lawyer
Scott Ramsey
Uncle Ramsey approach the city talk about love
He was surprised to find Buddy's Cleveland was very open to him
Go to meeting with a mat
And then I apologize for what happened to Jesse
Didn't want a soft pedal that said will be offices did was wrong
The band score Ramsey says
When he in the maglev to the subject of a possible lawsuit
There was an attitude that
You can file suit if you want and you can get a judgment if you want you may get a big chest
This is going to go into the stack over here and then I can date
Being such a paucity of countless disadvantages but it doesn't have this one advantage
When a person sues you can turn your pockets inside out and show there's nothing that
You called lose what you don't have write
Scott Ramsey newest Cleveland did not have insurance and not much in assets
New reminder
You told me in a normal City could get something like a hundred to $250,000
But he didn't want Jesse to join the stack of East Cleveland's unpaid lawsuit
Gwen stock
Judgment unpaid
Out of stock in the lobby of Appeals
Cisco Prime ziemba city of East Cleveland skip the lawsuit
Instead they made a deal
City College check for Jesse
$25,000
Quote of the day
At least
Loyola school today
The cops on the other hand
Well
You'll see
More
Off the break
This is the road to hire
Brought to you by zip recruiter business school she learned about the statistic
But 95% of parents installed their kids car seat incorrectly
So she decided she wanted to build a company around that
Which would send actual experts install tune-up
Clean your kids car seat for you
I think all of my classmates thought I was
Crazy
They're writing the startup
Plans
Make the next Uber or Facebook and he's sexy Hi-Tech Concepts
Thought I was like I'm going to clean baby poop so
Everybody laughed at me and they would say oh what a cute little niche business idea
Or you're such a weirdo why are you interested in that
Her weird eladia
Was a great one
Started abandoning their impossible instruction manuals and calling her company
Pop Squad instead
Pause squat expanded from 22500 employees Nationwide last month and Jen is still in serious hiring mode
But
I'm getting kicked in the lungs by the baby right now
When I talked to her she was also 9 months pregnant
And I just hired a new operations manager through ZipRecruiter
I'm preparing for baby I just have
West time to focus on these types of things and
ZipRecruiter
Really helped me
Make the tire more quickly I didn't have to spend as much time or energy as I usually would
Because hiring people should come with a good instruction manual to
Seriously
ZipRecruiter we were able to hire somebody almost immediately
Whether you need to hire one person or an entire Squad
ZipRecruiter it makes it efficient and easy
Tricep recruiter yourself for free ziprecruiter.com cereal
Ziprecruiter.com
Cereal
ZipRecruiter the smartest way to hire
Support for serial comes from Squarespace
Make your business official with Google in Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and a Business website with Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and professional tools from Google
Is the simplest way to look professional online
Visit squarespace.com Google
To start your free trial
And use offer code professional
For a discount on your first purchase
Google and Squarespace
Make it professional make it beautiful
Before we get back to Jesse I'm going to tell you about the case of Arnold black
Because I'll help you understand some of what's going to happen to Jesse
And also because a case of Arnold black is
Crazy
I want to reach for another descriptor it starts out crazy and then it gets more crazy
First a caveat
Arnold black suit is Cleveland
I read the court transcript I interviewed his attorney
There was a trial but he's Cleveland the defendant
Did not defend itself
They did not offer evidence or Witnesses they did not cross-examine anyone
So what I'm going to tell you is one-sided
Which doesn't make it untrue
Everything I'm telling you now was testify to Underoath in the Cuyahoga County Court of Common Pleas
And again was not challenged by the city
Here's the story
This guy Arnold black East 44th
The time is driving down Euclid Avenue in the middle of East Cleveland
Nighttime
He done a landscaping job near where his mother lived
They got over to her house afterwards for dinner
Now he was heading home
He's driving his truck
A green Chevy Silverado
Equipment in the back weed wacker leaf blower lawn mower
And the cops
Poem over
One uniformed officer in a cruiser
The other officer is a detective in normal clothes
I was driving his normal car
The uniformed officer
Jonathan O'Leary
Tells Arnold to get out of the truck
Possumdown
Topsham
I take Arnold black to the rear of his truck sitting down on the bumper
The cop in street clothes detective Randy Hicks aggressively searches the truck
Ripped out the inside door panels
In court Arnold black testified to the following
He said detective Hicks
Start asking him about drugs and he's Cleveland
They told him he didn't know
Because I don't sell drugs I don't do drugs and I don't live in East Cleveland
He said he was looking for a kilo of cocaine and he said to me that I wasn't in the right truck
I don't lie detective Hicks was looking for a drug dealer and a green truck
But Arnold wasn't him
Not annoyed
He said you messed my night up
Arnold's that detective Hicks seemed off
Drunk probably
It keeps asking Arnold about drugs Arnold the saying why you keep asking me that
Then
Wham
Detective Hicks
Punches Arnold in the face
Arnold testified that he then starts to cut a slide off the bumper
Officer O'Leary props him up
Detective Hicks hits him again in the head
These are hard hits
Hard enough that three years later Arnold Blackwood need brain surgery to drain the fluid and blood from a skull
Even now he can't remember things properly his speech has slowed
Is trouble controlling his anger
His mother and fiance say his personality is changed
The officers put him in the cruiser
Take him back to the East Cleveland Police Department where the jail is
And they put him in a room that Arnold's attorney calls a storage locker East Cleveland police called it a holding cell tomato tomato
So no one can decide what this room is called but whatever it is it is not a proper jail cell
No bad no toilet no window no water
Going to bench fuel lockers the tall kind
And some cleaning supplies
Brooms mops
They lock Arnold in there
That's according to his testimony
And now the timeline of all this is a little unclear the police and County records say one thing the trial transcript says another
If we go by the Wreckers at least
This began on a Friday night
Arnold says he could hear people talking and hollering walking around he could
Cheese
I knocked on the door and was screaming like I told him I had to use the bathroom and I said anybody
Anybody
No one comes
Arnold peas in a locker
Meanwhile his girlfriend Erica is getting worried
Where is he supposed to hear from him
Just calling around to friends she called the hospital
Sunday Times
Arnold's has an officer opens a door to the room
And ask him does anyone know you're in here
Arnold says no the guy says
And points to the ceiling
There's a microphone up there he says step back they won't pick up Whispers
Send text to Zone cell phone from his back pocket Arnold gives the guard Erica's number the guard dial to phone and the
Arnold and tell them to make it quick
Arnold tells Erica the cops beat me up I'm in East Cleveland jail come get me
Colonel says a bit later that same guy comes back
Houses in one of those little milk cartons like from a school cafeteria
Erica arrives
Ask to see Arnold
Now this is according to her testimony
The cops at the reception window, look at each other for a while
Finally someone says
He's under investigation
You can't see him
She feels like something's wrong like they're lying to her
She called Arnold Family Arnold's brother he took the stand at trial to
Arnold's brother says he goes to East Cleveland and they tell him Arnold's in Cleveland jail
He drives over to Cleveland
Tell him there's no Arnold black here
And he's like I was just
They just told me to come here
Paycheck
Check again
He goes back to East Cleveland again where they again safe we don't know what to tell you
Get here
It's now Monday
Day 3 of the storage room
Arnold is in terrible pain from his head injuries he can't sleep really
Hungry
Cortana said that aside from that one little milk carton they gave him nothing to eat or drink
The p in the locker is stinking he's intensely anxious is where the cops are going to do something to Erica because he called
Feels like the room is closing in on him
Finally I got if I'm reading the records right on day 5
He's put in a van and taken to the county jail at the Justice Center
He's held there a couple days
Until Erica comes to get him paises Bond 250 bucks
But you see them walking out of the county jail she says his head is so swollen he looks like he's wearing a helmet
Take them home
Sometime later Arnold gets a letter in the mail telling him he's been indicted by a grand jury for possessing crack cocaine
I was like charged with cocaine Arnold said I never had no cocaine charge with that
In the police report officer O'Leary claims he found a baggie of crack under Arnold's tongue and also that he had a baggie of marijuana
Moana
I'll point out that the East Cleveland detective who testified about the crack before the grand jury Eric Jones was at that
That time part of a couple of East Cleveland cops who were shaking down drug dealers stealing their money and falsifying evidence
Is now in federal prison
But I digress
In any case the prosecutor could see the circumstances of Arnold arrest or shady she been told about the beating
This file was going to be trouble
They dropped the charges
Arnold hires a civil rights lawyer Bobby the cello
Jesus
Suzhou city of East Cleveland Azusa police chief Ralph
Spots
This is Officer O'Leary Jesus detective Hicks
Is asking for 35 million dollars
Bobby 2Cellos 6 a settlement from the city on behalf of Arnold black
The delegates much the same pitch Scott Ramsey got when he sought a settlement for Jessie
There's only so much we can afford
Detellos response
Very different
Has Bobby 2cello
We heard
As the chief defense
Why are you doing
We don't have anymore
Don't you see where poor don't you see we're poor poor cities
Streets aren't very good don't you see that work
In a state of
It's called Financial or physical emergency where the
State of Ohio is running our books
And has to authorize every expenditure
You can't get paid
Here's what we can do we can give you 50 Grand
Would you be happy with 50 Grand
Would that be good enough
And I would respond
Let me get this straight
You guys beat up my client put them in a in a locker storage locker made him pee
There and by the way Federal nothing to the carton of milk
4 days
And you think I'm here just for 50 Grand
Billy
I'm going to ask you to bear with me a little longer here because the story gets better
Flash worse
Are they prepare for trial tuccillo finds out there was dash cam footage of the arrest
The shows detective Hicks beating Arnold
And they also discover that that same raw video with later edited by the police
Altered
So is not
Cheshire the beating
And listen up here
At the police chief and the mayor knew about it
They discovered that the East Cleveland Police did this all the time
In fact they discover that nothing that happened to Arnold black during the time he was secretly in East Cleveland's custody was unusual
Police in East Cleveland routinely pull people over in rough them up
Badminton practice for decades
Routinely held them in jail for no reason routinely altered evidence
The police chief routinely told officers to keep quiet about abuse to avoid lawsuit
Dichello had found out about almost all this stuff from a most unlikely source
Detective Randy Hicks
The guy who beat Arnold black
Pics of walked off the job within days of Arnold arrest he said
Soon as he realized his bosses were going to blame everything on him
Event at the department for about 15 years
Head of the narcotics unit for 6
Modern commendation
He wasn't a rogue cop
He said he was doing what they'd all been taught to do in East Cleveland
We asked the city law director to respond to the story
She didn't
Neither did Officer O'Leary or detective Hicks
Then Mayor Gary Norton did respond
He's at the characterization from the Civil Trial are 1000% false
Is that all I knew about the dash cam video
Was that quote there was a gap in the tape on quote
Gap
And he said he didn't know about the holding cells / storage locker at the jail
Which is downstairs from his office
I just didn't know
I really didn't
The den police chief Ralph Spotts also called us back
He said ditto
There was no such culture of aggression within the police department he said
No pattern of altering evidence or hiding abuse
Mister spots at detective Hicks was just shifting blame for his own personal wrongdoing
The civil lawsuit drag on
Years go by
No point is East Cleveland ever hand over discovery
That one piece of paper
Nevermind the dashcam video or Personnel records or logs from the jail the cello never even gets a police report
City law director claims she doesn't know where anything is they simply have nothing to Handover
Is egregious enough this refusal to engage but the judge finally issued a ruling saying okay is Cleveland
You are now barred from introducing any evidence in trial
So we're going to have a trial but you cannot defend yourself you forfeited that right
City appeals this ruling
Once twice they get denied
In 2016 four years after Arnold's beating and arrest they finally go to trial
And the only person who shows up for the other side the only person is former East Cleveland Detective
Randy Hicks
No city law director no police chief no mayor
Just Randy hex all by himself and he admits everything
There's this extraordinary part of the trial transfer
In which two cello reads a long list of all the things officers in East Cleveland dead
And Hicks confirmed
All of it
The cello
Number for
Officer Hicks was and his fellow officers were required by Chief spots to follow a custom of using violence in the city of
East Cleveland
We had officers using force on civilians
To compel statements from them to establish control
To instill fear and submission and to show dominance during arrest in traffic stop
The judge
That true
Text yes your honor
A jury awarded Arnold black 22 million dollars in compensatory and punitive damages
22 million-dollar judgement
Victory right
Not exactly
Because got this
The morning of trial
About an hour and a half before it started the city's lawyer filed a notice of appeal with the Ohio Supreme Court
It's a notice saying hey we're planning on filing something with you guys
The city had assumed that the notice would stop the clock on the trial and retroactively it did
An appeals court later ruled that the trial should not have gone forward with that notice pending so now as I write this
In 2018 the verdict in Arnold glass case has been overturned
Now the cello is Awana peeling he's not sure if he'll prevail
He might have to retry this case
Civil lawsuits are supposed to lead to reform that's the hope the city will fix the problems that are costing it
A lot of money we talked to 11 attorneys who do civil rights cases in Cuyahoga County
What attorney said yeah bring it
I have no problem pulling the trigger against East Cleveland
The other 10 attorneys
No way they said not worth it said one
Add a business to run to another we heard there's no reward we heard
It's a b****
You heard
I turned out any case that comes from East Cleveland
And it's heartbreaking
In other words Arnold black is a cautionary Tale
What makes the cello nuts
He doesn't see it that way
Mrs. Arnold black doesn't either
The city hasn't paid Arnold like a dime but he has gotten quite a bit of money as a result of a lawsuit
Chroma funding company that loans plaintiffs Money based on likely verdict I told financial industry apparel
But more to the point dichello says there's no public record of how he's Cleveland was running as Police Department
This case this verdict was national news
Because it went to trial
I'm talking about it right now
I asked a cello can you understand though how someone like Jesse Nickerson might not want to spend six
Plus years fighting the city
Especially if they live there
Mitchell said yeah but if a client did tell him that he pushed back
With a speech that goes something like this
We are the police of the police
By constitutional mandate
Thank God
This is got to be about you understand what's happening
Do you understand what their lives are there that are at stake here
It does impact us all
You're the guy you sneaked out and you know
Got out of the way the bully for a few bucks good job
Disappointed but did your community matter to you and if it didn't get the response comes back no
It doesn't I don't do it then I'm duty-bound to listen to my client
I get that
But I understand what's going to continue and we'll have that Converse
Responsible
Like I would with my own brother or sister
Look bro I get it you don't want to be in the fight but here's what's going to happen the blade on the streets going to do this again and again and again can you live in that town
If you settle for peanuts Like Jesse did 2Cellos says
You're not going to get real change
Organic peanuts
And now you're living in your same town along with the same people you're scared of
Right
And that's
Where Jesse is
Emmanuel is going to take it from here
About three weeks off we met up in the park I wanted to check in with Jesse
See how he was doing
See if you had any more run-ins with Cleveland Police
I thought they couldn't get ahold of him
Bangkok food his girlfriend Ashley
She wants into a whole thing
Something happened between Jesse and the police on the phone
July
The police Roxanne
She said Jesse wanted to tell me about it
Get a new phone
She gave me the number
Wechat out immediately
Crazy she told me
Yes
On the 4th of July Jessie Street for a block party
Neighbors block road cones and close off the street
About 70 people came out
Pictures of all the usual
Kids playing basketball people grilling fireworks
Does he get his friends help set it up
Is potty when an old a pan into the evening
Around midnight East Cleveland police showed up
Setting off fireworks about apartment is illegal in Ohio and you called
So the police said it was time to clear out
People started heading home
Jesse says he and his friends are dragging their feet messing around of a basketball given a costume attitude when
Quite abruptly
Police officer an older guy
Yell through the crowd
You in the red shirt
Give a f*** out of UC
I look around
Jesse and some of his friends confronted by officer
Comfortable
So I ain't doing nothing wrong
The other officer was like shut the f******
I'm not sure if it's such a thing at the office it's staying out of East Cleveland
Stepping up to an East Cleveland police officer and pooping like this my Pia
Directions
Best body cam footage
Three different offices
A lot of it is blurry and dark
But I watched it over and over
According to a police football Jesse's fat on an officer
Can you conceive on the body
Instead it seems different beliefs is founded on Jessie
Does a crowd of people
But Jesse seems to be the one they want
In the body cam footage you see Jesse and some of his friends talking back to
The police officer
Death is in the Rio
I'm on point it's all tobacco way
Put your hands in the air like
Find forget this I'm out of here
I just been one of the offices watches in
Find Pappas movie of a guy standing in front of Jessie
And grab them
Navarro Instagram Jesse to
Bake Oven
Dragons rules of police car
Subleasing frente
The crowd of people on the street is screaming at me
Cozumel
Situation feels like a good boy love
How to get to the police car
It's okay I'll take you can tell exactly what time
Pepe the Frog
What is maybe Jesse slamming into the Caldwell
Baby stop screaming
My all my all
His shoulder was injured
If he's lying on the ground with his stomach
Drifting away from his hot shoulder it had only underneath the tailpipe
He's going to know Jesse
What is Jesse's name
Stop telling him to get up
Analgesic
It's not clear whether the office is saying
Uncle Jesse hunting self trying to squirm away from the cops
Now if you'll just trying to make sure that fact gets recorded on the body cams
What does a police car up from the shop Jesse in the car
Now they're trying to cover
10 minutes later
EMTs arrive
Play suggested to the hospital or he spends the night
The next morning
Jessie wake to find 5 misdemeanor tickets in the blanket of his hospital bed
Traded to the Spurs
Is only Khan.
Resisting arrest
Assault
A menacing
Uncle Jesse on the phone
I could hear how much you wanted to fight back
Total so I can see how vulnerable
I got aspect
I got a
I got to prepare myself
Every time
Is it not
You don't what do you mean
You can eat was reading it
Yeah hell yeah
What's happening
I'm not doing s*** but I'm getting I'm getting a ride
But I feel
Xiaomi
Synonym awesome
So I regret it
It feels like you
Used you don't see an end to this
You think this is going to be
This is the beginning
Jesse went to East Cleveland School House
About a week later who is arraignment on the five Dodges for 4th July
Nicole house in just one room in East Haven small City whole room is every city Department including the police depart
It's backed into a two-and-a-half story building
Cool out with Jesse before Google started
Wyatt find the courtroom
Jessie's boys got Ramsay couldn't be there that day
What he told Jesse no big deal speed not guilty don't talk too much
Nothing serious is going to happen today
Jesse Wilson good spirits
Laughing and joking
Took it in stride one of the bailiff told him for ripped jean shorts he had on
Those
We're going to go over to On the Border
I got to get some pants come in
Jessica went home to change and then came back
Michigan State's
Google started
Bajaj began to spin through the cases
Most of it was small
Traffic tickets and stuff
I have you ever had an Ohio license
Off in about 30 minutes or so
Jessica
Mount something to me
Bountiful court room
Start oven buzzing so I figured he'd left to make a call
10 minutes went by and he hadn't come back
N20
Benfatti
Cool finished
Still no Jessie
Even stranger is casein never been
I tried his phone but it went straight to voicemail
Who is girlfriend Ashley
No I'm so
The whole building
Boys bathrooms
Parking lot
Jesse was nowhere
Hawaii
Jesse Williams criminal history
That's an event not showing up
My game in a restaurant
So why would you show up
Take the time to go home and change clothes
Come back
And then leave again
Bounce around anyone I might know what was going on
Good like gold
You'd like red sneakers on
Finally a bailiff told me he seen Jesse world out of courtroom
He came out in court
In the hallway
2 hours two detectives protein
The nearest Target to me
And then after that
The Hancock MN to come downstairs
I don't know what y'all are they charging my wife
So that's a Barnett law Dino
Okay
Jessie been arrested
I need to find out why
When do the police station
Stan woman have a window with you to tell me what have been arrested for
The violation of his privacy
She said which
By the way I jacked
It's not
Marisa Tomei
Want to talk to the chief of police
Was he in
No
A little later I also different person that by the same window
A young police officer iPhone might be more helpful
Nope
He said he wasn't allowed to tell me what charges were
Even though I was a reporter
Department policy
Again
Hijacked
It's not
I don't know. This door maybe they could help
Everyone was gone for the day
Bella
Okay
Body respect
It was free in the out
Orlando pizza place
I made a bunch of cool to see all the next day
So sick of me cool thing as I was of Oz game
Did his arraignment happen already
According to the files just a did
What they like a bone set
We don't get that information out there
It should be public information right
Sir
We don't give that information out on telephone
Okay
Can I also have a glass of wine.
After while I go with a Hammonds on the phone
Bethany's Lowell director
You didn't hang up on me or ignore my arguments about things being public record
She was nice
Multiply
But I didn't want to be recorded but she did answer my question
She told me Jessie been arrested
Charged with misdemeanors for a completely different guys
Jesse the yelled at and intimidated an officer
Instead of arresting Jessie then
I believe they put a warrant out for his arrest
Also we could talk in a couple minutes
We lost if I could hold
He must have something about wedding some of the details I had a ruffle for some papers
Willis and the optavia rest just need to hit his head on the ground in the weight of a jail
They deliberately peed himself in the south
Jessie been taken to the hospital
Neuropsychological evaluation
Literally I'm just getting out
4 days went by before I heard from Jesse again as long as to ask him about your asks about what would have told me
But Jesse coming off he said he didn't have time to get into that
It's something important to tell me
No bathroom
So I'm going to go home for 2 days
Well I have to be one person
Use my
Factory wipe my ass
Like I'm stupid
I had to literally kiss
Anna Locker
You got this
I had to piss and s*** in locker room
Jesse was telling me that was believed to put them in the very same room the Arnold black been locked in 2 days
The question was
Will anyone care next time
En Serio
Cereals produced by Julissa
Schneider Emmanuel Joshi Ben Calhoun and me with additional reporting by Eataly uskoski editing on this episode
Hourglass Whitney Dangerfield is our digital editor research and fact-checking by Ben Phelan sound design in mixmeister
Joe Nelson additional protection from Kate belinski music clearance by Anthony Roman Southland is our director of
Operations aetherial staff includes Emily Condon Julie Whitaker Cassie Holly Francis Swanson and Matt Tierney
Our music is by Adam Dorn and how Wilner with additional music from Matt McGinley Fritz Myers Nick thorburn and Westshore
Our theme song is my next door brewing and remix by Adam Dorn special thanks this episode to Melissa George
Add little Eric Brewer William vodrey Nancy Jameson Molly Murphy
Chris Link at the ACLU and Colleen Cotter at Legal Aid Society of Cleveland thanks also to Pandora for airing
Bring the show
The art on our website was made by Martinez EB he created the mural for this episode and Moss Studio did the
The animation
Please check it out on our website serial podcast. Org
But serial podcast. Org
We can also sign up for our email newsletter and be notified when new episodes are released
Support for serial comes from ZipRecruiter unlike many job sites ZipRecruiter doesn't wait for candidates to find you
ZipRecruiter finds them for you so you get qualified candidates
Fast
Tried free at ziprecruiter.com cereal
Ziprecruiter.com cereal
Support for serial comes from Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and Business website with Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and professional tools from Google
Use offer code professional for discount on your first purchase