Previously on serial
It's a really tight
Free Windows time taking place right
All right ready
I started it
It's 2:51 and we're making a right out of the Best Buy parking lot
Isn't that sort of tantamount to say
I think you're telling the truth
The cell phone was in Lincoln Park
This is a Global Tel Link prepaid call from
An inmate at a Maryland Correctional Facility
From This American Life and WBEZ Chicago it's serial one story
Week-by-week I'm Sarah Koenig the most incriminating piece of fish
Physical evidence against Adnan Syed was a fingerprint
Or rather a palm print
A map
It was one of those big math books you buy at a gas station
Police found it in the backseat of his car
On the back cover with a partial print of anions left palm
One page was ripped out from the map
A trial a pointed out that it was the page that showed leakin Park
The defense argued on fingerprints
They could have been six-week-old fingerprints or six months old fingerprints there's no way to tell
Bedridden and driven his car many times all their friends said so
Show the whole lot more than just leakin park in fact it showed their whole neighborhood the school the mall
Probably 90% of where they most often drove
And that page
Didn't have enough prints on it
His palm print was only on the back cover of the book
13 other unidentified prints turned up on and in the map book
The prince weren't exactly conclusive
Over the past few weeks I've been holding up bits of evidence here and there that look bad for add-on
Today I'm just going to lay out the rest everything else that a person could reasonably add to the Adnan is guilty side of the scale
Everything that the state had that I know about before but let's just hang them all up
Side-by-side and see what they look like first off there's a question of whether Adnan asked me for a ride that day after
Score movie looking for an excuse to get in her car
So he could kill her
Officer Adcock testified that the day she disappeared Anon told him he'd asked her for a ride
Then later told he didn't ask for a ride
He can't remember much at all about the missing
I was just a normal day to him something which stands out
I wondered about that the normalness of the day
When to call from officer Adcock asking whether he's seen her
Not normal.
Something pretty unusual did happen
I do remember that phone call and I do remember being high
Because
Crazy fingers behind have the police call your phone I'll never forget that
I guess that's the only thing that seems weird to me that you wouldn't
Come into Focus for you
You got this call from the cops
You know you lit
You were high you were young you know
It's a it's a scary call together or just a jarring call to get
I mean at the time
The only thing I really associated with that call was that night
Whatever reason she didn't get no go home or she went somewhere else in no way that I associate this
Call
The beginning
I know where it is it's like
Your mother's going to be pissed
If this really was his reaction then he wasn't the only one
The seriousness of his disappearance didn't start sinking in with her friends for a while
School was canceled on January 14th and 15th because of the ice storm
And The Weeknd came then Monday was Martin Luther King Day
So the kids didn't all reconvene at school until the following Tuesday
All his friends I spoke to said they initially thought he had either run off someplace with her new boyfriend on
This is another rumor that a lot of people talked about at the time
Did she run off to California
Friend said she talked about that sometimes that her dad or maybe with her stepdad
Was in California
And she wanted to go there
I told the cops the same thing
Next the night before he disappeared and then called her house three times
Actually spoke with the third call at 12:35 a.m. that's what a non says he was probably calling to
To give his new cell phone number and she does write it in her diary
Here's something that makes me pause though
If you look at his cell records from that day forward neither Hayes home number nor her pager shows up again
Which suggests he never tried to contact her after she went missing there supposedly such good friends
His friend said she was paging her like crazy
Did you ever try to page her and just good like
You know see if you could
Find her raise her see if you could get a response from her
Well
I know that we would always
I can't remember if I just paid you're not but
We would always talk about in school I would always like get my information first-half like I used to
What usually skin contact
If I can remember she was like in contact with his family
Cypress College I would always
Christopher Orr
I mean it was like I was just sitting around like not even thinking about her
You don't not patient or whatever but I used to always get my information from them first half
It's not it's not that
I don't have a pastry or not
No just seems like
I know Krista was trying to page Rhino Aisha was trying to pager during this time to just be like where are you where are you where are you
And I was wondering if you had
We're in that group of like where are you
Ask me a question
I don't know I'm just explaining why I'm asking the I'm explaining why I'm asking
Play from the relationship you had with her
You would have been one of those people saying
Give a holler where are you okay
We're all worried about you
That mean I'm right alongside what's them though it's not like they're in a whole other everyday we're talking about it
Whatever he comes up in the conversation I'm leaving
Another side of the classroom or something like that I mean I'm just as involved as they are
DSLR mean
I don't know
Things that I don't know what they mean
In case it came up a trial
After he broke up in early November a letter
I'm really getting annoyed that the situation is going the way it is she wrote
You know people break up all the time your life is not going to end
Apparently you don't respect me enough to accept my decision and quote
Aisha Pittman read this note a trial he was her best friend
Initial letter apparently in health class
Handwritten notes to each other on the back
Asian pencil and not in pain
They were joking making fun of him making fun of themselves they'll just silliness
Event at the top of the page it says I'm going to kill
In pain
I talked about it
And I mean did you take any of that is as
Medicine or anything was it just a part of the joke
I know just seems like you guys are
Messing around on the know when I was riding with it so fruit
To see it later it was one of those things where it's like that
Weird to see that
I don't know when that would have been written or what this wasn't part of the conversation
Cuz I remember like
Show
Weather it is just
Like on it was our conversation on letterhead and then at the top of it was kind
Out of
Context
Did you or did you take it to mean anything
I mean did you take it to be meaningful I guess
I don't
No because when I'm first seeing that part of it was sitting in court
Having to read the rest of the letter
Police had found the note when they searched the nuns house
But tonight was about that one right
Seems like a detail you find in a Cheesy detective novel
The other one I'm not sure about
Is this kind of stray report in the police file
I called the cops and said
My daughter just heard something about a dead body
Tell the cops
Who's the neighbor boy who mentioned it
Names the neighbor boy but I'm just going to call him the neighbor boy
Here's Dave
I just remember he had told my daughter he had seen
Cut the body of a girl in the back of such are in the trunk of some vehicle
And
I seem to me that it was an a said it was like an oriental girl or something but that's
That's all I remember that's all I know about it
Did he tell it to you or just to your daughter my daughter didn't talk to me
They gave me his daughters number I went to see her right away
Her name is Laura
Here's what she remembered about what the neighbor boy told her that day
He was
With a friend
The friend said something like look what I have
Pop the Trunk
And
That's what he saw
Did he seem upset
You seem Disturbed
More like a
Wow I can't believe what I did
Almost like he was
Maybe getting something off his chest
Type of thing
I asked Laura
Did the neighbor boy tell you the name of this friend who showed him the body
I think the guy's name was maybe Adnan
This guy said
My friend Adnan showed me the body of a girl in the back
Car
Yes
Do you think he was telling the truth
Lord and go to Woodlawn
She didn't know at 9
Chicken on the neighbor boy since they were little they're friendly
Laura said she never spoke to police about this I never questioned her
So this sounds really really bad right
But there was another witness besides J who saw his body
Who shot at 9 with his body
That's huge
I called the neighbor boy that same night
He's now somebody else's neighbor and he's a man
He was affable and patient and he holy deny this episode
He's pretty convincing
He said the only dead body I've seen is on TV God's honest truth
Tepper my great-grandmother she died when I was like 9
Man said he wasn't friends with Adnan
He was friends with Jada they smoked weed together
I suggested
Maybe Jay told him the story and he kind of appropriated it and told it to the neighbor girl to freak her out
You said no way
I wouldn't kid around about something like that
The cops came to see him in 99 and he told them the same thing you know anything
The statement to the same effect to a private investigator who was working for the defense in an oz case
I've read it
This is what's weird
The original police report about Dave and his daughter Laura it's dated April 28th
I had already been in jail for nearly two months
I was under the impression that whatever happened to her neighborhood just happened
I told her dad right away and he called the cops right away
A guy untalented at keeping secrets
Which could play either way I guess
Nobody would tell him anything they wanted to stay quiet
I never shows up a trial he's never mentioned
Let It Go
You know what is weird
And if Laura Story is true
And there's another witness to this murder
Things about this case that kind of Bob's above the water for me
Like a disturbing buoy
Then there's Cassie
That's not a real name and we've changed your voice and I'm calling her Kathy
I mentioned her before
She saw Adnan and Jay together acting suspiciously the word cheese as Shady
At a critical time that evening of the 13th the day he disappeared
A story
He brought his apartment after he picked Adnan up from track practice
So after Haven killed but before they went to bury her body
About 6 at night
MJ and Kathy
Knowledge being together at the apartment there's no dispute about that
Kathy was a close friend of Jen's they were sorority sisters
A little bit but only for Jen
Chicken at all
Acquaintance and a stranger
Heather remembers that night pretty clearly her boyfriend Jeff was there at the apartment 2
Surprise Lake little confused because
Didn't call me last
Antlers with Jonathan
No it called
How long do you want to hang out
Nothing like that so it's a little strange that he would just pop up in the door
Cameron me like you do you want to smoke do you want to
Hang out and I remember being like why not a second
Asking Josh you know if you wanted to
Jada the door
For what
High School
So J came in and introduced his friend
Just like you know
It's a friend of mine
Kathy remembers J set over by the table on the floor on some big cushions that were there and didn't speak
And where the guy wasn't
Doing a whole lot of talking like he was just kind
Start over
Emma stole my car shows
I kind of thought it was really strange like who is a
Who is this guy
When I first heard about Kathy statement in her testimony didn't seem like a big deal to me
Does a girl who says some kid she didn't know who was high
Was acting strangely in our living room
I've been that girl for chrissakes having a deal with a stone friend-of-a-friend on the living room floor
I probably been that weird guy in the floor at least once
Listen to Kathy tell it all these years later
The way it's
Stuck with her
How she describes a whole night that's just feeling wrong
Stick with me
Happy thought J was acting out as well as super laid-back Stoner guy like Shaggy from Scooby Doo
Inconspicuously chatty
How is your day what's going on you know it's kind of like Phil
The Dominator conversation
She says why were there Jen called the apartment
Or maybe it was she who called Jen can't remember now
But she does remember talking to Jen and saying
He's here with some kid who's practically passed out on the cushions
That was curiously what's Jay doing there
Still kathy that jave been acting weird earlier in the day 2
The story he's telling is pretty close to what you told the cops during the investigation
Detective Miguel very energy Kathy in March of 99
Afternoon tea been arrested
She told him back then
Remember to nanjing only one thing to the group
How do I get rid of a high
It's really important
Do you have any idea where he was going to go who is going to be
I don't know I'm at my camera clearer but I remember him saying I have to go talk to someone actually meet someone.
I remember how to do
Incoming calls on the call log that King towers near Kathy's house
607 609 and 6:24 p.m.
That's the longest one
More than 4 minutes
We don't know for sure who they're from but officer Adcock testifies that he calls around this time and he thinks the 624
For college probably him
Young also calls are not around this time looking for a sister
I don't know who the third College from
Kathy definitely remembers Adnan getting one song called while he was at her apartment
She says they're sitting around talking one of Kathy's favorite shows is on the TV Judge Judy
The phone rings and
You had said anything the whole time he had been there
So when he answers the phone
Anything
What am I going to do what am I going to
Say they're going to come talk to me
And what am I supposed
And I remember of sounding very
Worried
It's all right you know like this was
Whatever was happening
Not good on the other line
Lamborghini
Wow you know wonder what he's
Show me driving basically
Wondering what was going on
And then I'm not too long after
He hung up the phone
Laugh
Just
Bust out the door
Left
Jay follows Adnan out
Leaves his hat and smokes behind Kathy says
Stairs and then she says they get in a car and just sit there in the car for a while
As so now they're outside in the car
Never going to the window like why they doing you know Jethro in the car that just sitting there you know what
Dallas going on you know just finding a whole situation
Super hot super strange
Jackie Chan
Don't matter what you know who cares you know
What is going on
And you never met
The other guy before it right so you didn't know what was normal behavior for him
Normal behavior for
I mean anybody I mean did I was just
Whether you know him or not
Philly Hotel
Something was going on something wasn't going on it wasn't good
Anna
Yeah
I was just drinking maybe for anybody
I think that's been
The one thing I've always remembered like
How he said how he looked when he said it
It's definitely
Panicked
He's definitely
Worried and
I can imagine if I was in the position just what I would have been saying on the phone
My best friend you know
My God what am I going to do they're going to come talk to me what am I supposed to say
You're trying to come up with some
Story quickly
Many hours later at the end of the night she came back to CAD
Without an ion
But this time John was with him
Living like so what the f***
Yeah when I remember kind of them both being like
Something you know
Smoothing it over think a little bit
And I thought it was kind of like
No big deal. You could death
A big deal and whatever
What's going on with kind of like a secret or you know because Jen and I were best friends I mean
Honey we talked about everything I mean we were
Any we don't do anything without talking about it or you know I knew what she was
Wearing in the morning anyway she was going at night you know I knew
Yoshi talk to on the phone you know it's a little strange that when I said so what happened
And I didn't get a full like
Account
Next time I talk to and I told him how Kathy still remembered all this stuff how Shady the whole scene was for her
How much water with them
First of all if someone had called him to warn him the police were about to call why would he then answer the phone when the police
What is called
Answer my phone
Turn the phone off
We're going in the scenario I'm trying to avoid the police
United mean that I wouldn't pick up the phone and engage them in a conversation
Well but there's also the other thing where you just like just act normal.
After school
You know like where you try to
Just play cool
Started visual
Right
Her story would imply a third man
A co-conspirator
Would be on the phone with
The clearly knew about the murder
Who would the third color be
Who's the third person on the phone
EBenefits
I mean it's that's a hard one it's her testimony does not look good for you you know
Because she is not really connected to Jay she's not connected to you
You know she's a little bit
More objective I would say
And she really thought you were acting
Very strangely
So it didn't it's not good for you what she has to say
I mean I listen to you but I kind of think that
This is not good for me if a person believes The Narrative of what you're saying
But if you don't believe in their civil would chase a horrible person questions
What did she say specifically that links me to Hays Market
You know she didn't say she didn't say that she saw me with any
Type of equipment or materials are charged clothes or Devils or anything like that
RTA
Well
I don't know
I feel really
All this in the car is in the context of her
Leaving okay well maybe he did this or he's charged with this and you know it now all this stuff
Make sense whatever may not have been estranged
Adam never been charged
What's this
Second thought
Had I never been charged with his murder
Maybe
Maybe not
Person who puts Jane and on together that night
Next gen
Now last episode we talked about those two incoming we can park calls on the call log at 7:09 and 7:16
She says they were burying hay
Are we think the cell phone really was in Lincoln Park
Jen has a cameo in that scene
Jen says she was one of those incoming calls
She said she call the cell phone around that time looking for Jay
Button on picked up
He didn't identify himself but she assumed it was an on
Hears from her police interview
When
I called them
I don't answer the phone
And said she would call you
You back when you're right when he's ready
Can you come and get him a few time meet him or whatever
Annum
So that's all
Very quick and very
Jen Story is true it does look an awful lot like Adnan was in Lincoln Park that night
Busy not handing the phone over to Jay
The second time Jen puts them together that night is pretty soon after that when she picks Jay up sometime after 8
So in Jesus timeline after they've already buried hey
She said she'd arranged to meet him in the parking lot of Westview Mall
She said she saw them arrive in add-ons car
And I said hi to me
Say what's up girl
And I was like Hey so
And then you left
The parking lot
Smj told me
What the exchange
Hey what's up girl how are you describe
It seems like you know
Inside that details always stuck with me to
Legend says Adnan seem so normal
She says neither his nor J's close he mustered dirty
Doesn't remember seeing Janet Westview Mall or where he dropped off Jade at night
And Jay doesn't say he met Jen at Westview either
Matter fact Chasez consistently
Turn on dropped him off at home and then Jen showed up at his house to get him
Just talked to that
Even a trial
When it contradicted Jen Story
The thing about Jen and Kathy though is that even if they don't look great for Adnan
They don't actually contradict anons on account of that evening
Which I think is why he kind of shrugs them off
Why I'm sometimes tempted to shrug them off
Because it has always admitted she was hanging out with Jay that night
So what if a couple of people saw them together
Does that prove
Now we come to the big one
The one nobody can shrug off
Just call Wilkinson a bad metaphor for a phone call but of all the calls on the log this is the one I think I've is the smoke
Pekin gun call
It's the Nisha call
Think of it as a title capitalized
The Nisha call
Between noon and 5 p.m. that there's 7 outgoing calls on the log 6 of them are two people jado's
The 7th is Tunisia
Anon story is that he and his cell phone were separated that day from lunchtime all the way until after track at around 5
5 something
Benicia call happens at 3:32 p.m.
Smack in the middle of the afternoon
The prosecution makes much of this call at closing and I can see why
NJ second tape statement granted is the one where detectives are showing him the call records
Detective mcgilvery is asking Jay about all those afternoon calls on the log between 3 and 4
Again Jace's this is when they were driving all around Forest Park and Edmondson Avenue looking for weed
Did anybody else use the phone
Yeah
Adnan I can't remember whether he received to call place to call
But I remember he was talking to a girl
Can't remember her name
On the phone with her for like 3 minutes I said hello to her
Where did she live
Silver Spring
Your caller name
No I don't
You have any idea why Adnan
We call
This individual in Silver Spring
After he hits you
No strangled his girlfriend
I don't and
I have no idea why
You call
In a conversation didn't change anything if you just done
The cops went and talked to Misha to the high school student
Yeah there was a time when I spoke to an on his cell and he put his friend Jay on the phone
Misha testified at both trials
For Smoking Gun she's very cute like a chipmunk
Good afternoon
Good afternoon to you too sir
Do you know the defendant
Yes I do
This is from trial number one
It's a little hard to recall but I remember
I'm telling you that they invited invited him over
To arm a video store. He worked at
And
He basically walked in with a cell phone and then he said
Like he told me to speak with Jay and I was like okay
Cuz they wanted to say hi so I said hi today
And that's all I can barely recall
At what time of day did that occur
I would think towards the evening but I can't be exactly sure
The prosecutor Kevin urick asked her if this call the 3:30 to call in the log
Could it be that same call Lauren on PJ on the phone
And she says
It could be but I'm not sure
Video store
He worked mostly nights there so it makes sense this call would have happened towards the evening
What doesn't make sense if Nisha saying this call happened at the video store
Is it Jaden have that job yet on January 13th
As far as I can tell from j-zone testimony and from the notes of a private investigator for the defense
Who interviewed the video store manager
Jaden start working there until the very end of January
Listen to what happens at the second trial
I don't have a tape but I have a transcript
Your gas Tanisha
Become a time when the defendant called you and put a person he identified as J on the line
Yes
Please tell the ladies and gentlemen of the jury what that call consisted of
You should start to answer
Basically
He says
No don't
Tell us the content of the call
I guess I said the prosecutor is trying to get her to not mention the video store because it contradicts their story
Ninja says okay he just asked me how I was doing the sitter and then she goes on
She doesn't mention the video start of your again
So I'm convinced this call the 3:30 to call on the 13th
That this was a call when a non put down the phone with Nisha
Still
Bernard is supposedly at school during this time and J's not talking to Nisha for 2 minutes and 22 seconds
Who the hell is calling Misha
This is what a non can't explain
I've asked him about it many times
He says niches number was entered into his phone on speed dial
You can see calls are allowed on the cell
And Fighters is the very first number he dials when the phone is activated on the 12th
What must have happened is some combination of a butt dial and an answering machine
This is from one of our very first phone calls
But if she but she says
She test
That's her phone does not have an answering machine or voicemail on it
So who is picking up that call and talkin for 2 and 1/2 minutes or whatever it was
2 minutes and 22 seconds or so
I'm sure
Call voicemail
Call Duck
Let me look let me look when I look older
I was right
Here's from the first trial
Eurocast Nisha does your home phone have an answering machine
Does your home phone have an answering machine
Not this phone number now
Past year I've swivel the Rubik's cube of this case so many different ways
I've arranged and rearranged it to come up with alternate versions of how this day might have actually gone
Certain hypothetical directions
Every time Jay says Adnan name in his story
Maybe he's really talking about someone else
Person we don't know about today's afraid of her he's trying to protect mean he's got the car j's got the phone
All these calls are to his friends
And then I remember
Tanisha call
Whole thing crumbles
No Way Around It the Nisha call is a big fat problem for a nun
His biggest fear is not being believed
When he's sure about something
He has a tendency to over explain
To inundate you with facts and information and then corroboration for the facts and information
I don't like this tendency in himself but he says he can't help it
Anyone who knows he was saying that I'll try to go over Force before my people be like alright man alright man we believe you
It rained yesterday
Because in my mind just like it just received something
Personality Quirk born of all this
I mean I really I don't like to talk about things unless I can prove
No matter how silly it is
He does it with anything
He's a cook at the prison and he said he got into a discussion with some guys recently about barbecue sauce
And I was saying if you don't have Molasses for brown sugar you can substitute pancake syrup
Breakfast
Nobody needs barbecue sauce at breakfast time at the Maximum Security Prison in Cumberland Maryland but he didn't anyway
All these things that look bad for a nun
Everything that's raised my suspicions even stupid things
I run every single one of them by him
I got this thing in my head that I'll catch him in a lie maybe just a tiny meaningless lie
And that's going to be his towel
He'll be caught
Not as smart and clever he knows that's what's going on we talk
Every time I call he's a little on guard is not sure what's coming at him
Cuz what if I ask him something he can't prove
And then I don't believe in
That notion that people out there in the world people he went to school with who knew him
Don't believe him
But they could imagine he's capable of killing hey
And I'm spent 15 years thinking about that
And then try not to think about that
What was it about me
It is what it is
What was it what was it about me
Difference between Xs
All the stuff of me like
Call me leaving with her
She said yes to going here like
MeetMe arrest
Yeah I mean that people
Not just random people clean a people who knew me that intimately do they intimately
Call Sonic daily basis
I used to really really like you know
Take me to my core
Just just like just like what is it
About me that would allow someone to even entertain the possibility that I could do this
Is that the thing
I mean when you really think about it
Pool
I don't think I ever displayed in Tennessee
He's like that like that you know
I'm actually would have assumed it was the police got the right guy they got them for the right reason
Because
You know he was ex-boyfriend
I will be doing the same thing but
But you know what I know and it's like the people who
Have told me that they think either they they should have after a long time came to the conclusion that you were guilty or the
They're kind of like I don't know maybe I've never really liked they all at some point in the conversation almost everybody
He has said well the unknown I knew didn't do it
Like the guy I knew couldn't have done it
You know what I mean
So what they're saying is maybe there was another guy in there that I just never
New
You know like everybody has
Deep dark
Not everyone has a good you do something cool and heinous like this
Uno
Galaxy paint color for June
I don't believe you're not someone who believes that like everyone put in
Anyone could kill depending on the circumstances like if they were innocent
If it's me or him
If my kids are in danger
No
Anyone
Or even majority of people
Doing something like this
What did she ever do to me that will cause me to feel so angry
But but
I thought I didn't care about this
I probably do
How could you not
How could you not care about it
What people say
I shouldn't care
I see many problems with the state's case
But then I see many problems with a non Story 2
As I start to doubt him
Then I talked to him and talk to him and talk to him and I start to doubt my doubts
I'm sucker that I don't know
That's the cycle
Once about six months after we began our phone calls and not ask me a little nervously
What's your interest in this case really
Why are you doing this
Explain all the interesting stuff I read in the people I talked to blah blah blah
But I also told him that really what hooked me most is him
Just trying to figure out who is this person
Who says he didn't kill this girl but is serving a life sentence for killing this girl
I interested it honestly has been you like you're really
Nice
I like talking to you
Give me hope so then it's kind of like this questionable what does that mean you know
Oh
You don't even really know me though
Maybe meet you know I don't
When we talk on the phone I don't understand
Weird to hear you say that because
I don't even really know you
Are you saying you don't think that I know you at all
I need for you to say that I'm a great person
I don't know
Investigating me back then
We had this conversation in July
At least 30 hours on the phone
More than I talk to a lot of people I think I know
Consider friends
I'm confused by this
This is the closest thing to hostile Adnan has ever gotten with me
The next day I came back to him about it
And so
I was a little bit like taking a bath and I still like I feel a little taken aback that like
What do you think I don't
No
About you
Myself
If I hear someone else I don't think you did it cuz you're a nice guy is not
Douglas County Schools
Cuz you wouldn't know that but I've heard people say that to me over the years
I would love someone to hear I would love you so much but I don't think that you did it because I look at the case
It looks
You're selfish
You know you're a crazy sob
And it looks
She'll like a little off
Feel like something's not right
I understand this
The nice guy doesn't count as exculpatory evidence
But if I'm going to spend a year figuring out that he's a nice guy I might as well piss off
Point taken
We need some experts on this job
Next time
I'm cereal
Ciro's produced by Julie Snyder data Travis Ami Emily Condon is Harper
Production and operations manager hourglasses are editorial advisor
Fact-checking by Karen fragala Smith AR theme music is composed by Nick thorburn scoring music by Nick and by Mark Phillips you also
Mixer show
Website where you can listen to all episodes and letters and other documents from the case and sign up for a weekly
Serialpodcast.org
Serials production of This American Life and WBEZ Chicago