Support for serial comes from ATT
The number one smart home security provider
Offering everything from video doorbells
2 indoor and outdoor cameras
2 smart locks and lights
Control from the ADT app
Or the sound of your voice
Visit att.com podcast to learn more about how ADT can custom design and install your
Smart home system
Back by 24/7 protection
Previously
Cereal
We're like man is he like CIA or what he look at us and didn't he jumped for
Behind our bike we thought he's drunk
Kill you
Amusement of being quickly became very
Apparent to us that the Taliban new f****** b*******
He's in Pakistan
From This American Life and WBEZ Chicago its serial one story told me by week
I'm Sarah Koenig
Right after Bowe Bergdahl first went missing from his Outpost in Afghanistan
Word came down that the higher-ups wanted someone from Bo's platoon second platoon Blackfoot company
Record a message to Bill that they play on local radio
They wanted it to be a voice but would recognize
So the guy Bo was friends with
Guy from Louisiana
You have a very thick Louisiana accent
So basically
Chi
She went up there and I guess he didn't like it
They came down and they got me that's Josh quarter originally from Pennsylvania
Didn't want to make a message to Bo
He says he felt a little disloyal to his platoon calling out to the guy who is causing them such turmoil
But they did the baby, come they brought me up there two officers brought me up there
And they put a piece of paper in front of me which is a script
And said read this
What was the script
I was like
It was It was kind of cheesy to it was like hey Bo this is Josh we really miss you
I know we we just
Want you to come back we hope you're safe we hope everything's going okay
You know so come back
I guess I kept thinking later on that my
Like for the entire five years movie the same thing
Going on
In Pakistan and Afghanistan
Talon bow to come home
Safe to say bone ever heard the message
Also safe to say
Was trying really hard to come home
His first year in captivity
Starts with an escape and ends with an escape
Like shity bookends to a terrible year
In between the Escape spell was learning necessary Twisted lessons of survival
How to smile when you're in agony
But if you ask for something such as water
You're likely to get less of it or less of something else such as food
If you're severely dehydrated you can't really drink your own urine because it turns into a salty Brown sludge
The filth and stink are your best weapons
More disgusting you are at the less your captors want to come hear you
Which means you can scroll things away in your bed clothes
The smaller and weaker you can make yourself the more likely the Taliban are to let you alone
And as painful as it is to be forgotten
Ultimately that's what you want
Not even an animal
Picture someone taking a bag
The closet shutting the door and just forgetting about it
Melissa Ann jeans a drone with a commander in charge of keeping go prisoner up until 2013 on Sunday was killed in a dream
Gun strike
Give me food
Other guys
Literally just
And got
Back in Afghanistan the storm of search-and-rescue operations for Bo had slowed and then doing.
They keep your eyes and ears out of course
Military have to call it
Elbow was in the worst place he could be
Anyone who's going to rescue them
Locked in a room across the border in Pakistan
It seemed like a very strong possibility that he was a Taliban sympathizer I'll put it that way and it seemed that
That she
The unrated version is like what a f****** a******
You know
That was Mark balls first casual assessment of bow we heard the early reports it would walk off
What's a lot of people's assessment
That's understandable based on the information dripping out of the time
An early propaganda video reports that boat converted to Islam
Yeah and then they remember there was nothing of him like
But there has been there have been some kind of reporting that he was riding around on a horse
I remember that too
I'm just looking at 1 from the Daily Mail
And it says
One of his captors said that he converted to his mom it was going under the name Stella and was very relaxed in her come
Anthony unquote
It has
It has also been claimed that Bergdahl was so trusted by his kidnappers but they let him sleep without restraints and go bird and rabbit hunting with
Old British rifle
Oh you know what that reminds me I heard another one that he played soccer
Information like this I learned that intelligence analysts refer to it as stray voltage
By that they mean it's almost certainly untrue
But still added up to people judging from the outside it didn't look good Mark said it made him feel like maybe Bo wasn't someone who
He should be caring about
What does the opposite feeling usually get when you hear about a p o w
Then after both came back and was in Germany recovering Mark talk to someone in the until world who knew what was going on
I actually remember somebody telling me
Oh yeah he's
He's doing
That's weird I thought he was
Call that guy
He's like he's not in this was during the jury went all the Press recording was about
You know how I like mentally damaged she was and how he was
Gradually
In a reactor that into the world and
Everyone's I cautioning like
And I don't expect him to pop up on TV anytime soon cuz he's severely
Traumatized
And then I was also hearing that like privately he was
I mean maybe all that stuff was true and I'm sure it is but
At the same time he was doing a lot of
Prefixes like wait he's
It doesn't sound like a Trader
When I finally heard Beau talk about his time with the Taliban
I thought no
He does not sound like a traitor
As brutal as both first year in captivity was
At least he had plans
His single-minded purpose
Was to get out
Asbestos Pokemon call the first Escape
You don't have the one where he ran 20 or 30 feet before I got tackled have in the first week he was in town in custody
Taliban fighters by the way have confirmed that bowed it escaped once briefly early on and then again for a longer time
Roughly a year later
That first week both as he was being held at House of some kind
His feet were tied with ropes a chain was wrapped in several loops around his wrist
He said he noticed that the previous morning a car had arrived with water and as soon as it did everyone went inside and
Another room for tea
So when the car came again with the water
Who says he saw his chance
You managed to manipulate the slack in the chain so that he could slip it over his knuckles he untied his feet
Doors of the room he was in relaxed from the outside with a thick wire to stick his hand through the crack to undo it
Sticking my hand out I mean good grief
If anyone was standing outside
Like they would have fully seen
Me fiddling with the damn liar
Basically trying to open the door
I know when does c
He runs outside turns right and then realizes he's in some kind of shallow Valley or Plateau he's 3
Houses about 200 yards off starts running is Shoeless he says there's mostly Jagged rocks underfoot but he spray
Prince's best he can at the first house he see some kids
The house
I see a woman come running out the date
She like
Seasoning does like that one footed light
Shutterstock
Staying inside
Runs back in the house
He keeps going is a group of men standing around the men also see him
Temple runs towards passes the second house comes to the third decides to climb onto the roof
And I get to the top of the roof
There's like a mud puddle there
And I'm staying low and you are basically to slide onto the roof
Happy Feet
You're covered in mud
And I like rolled a few times to try and cover myself weekly more mud
And I don't
I meant find him up there lead him back down
Is it
Interesting
I told you that's why I get to the
I guess the old lady from the house like
Old woman
Dixie House
I come out at
Commotion
Yeah I know he's like young guys are in everybody's like
Walking loudly
Yeah I'm covered in mud
This old woman comes up to me and she's like tries to like start
Like trying to wipe the mud off my face
They want young guys grabs her by that like arms
What kind of trucks are behind them
She like yells out of
Saying like leave me off
Start to finish the Escape lasted maybe 10 or 15 minutes Bo says
The aftermath was severe
They brought go back to where they've been holding him and when's evening came
Who says they beat him with a rubber hose
First it was one guy who spoke some English you twirl and twirl the hose and then whack it against both feet
Horoscopo covered his feet with his hands he wack his hands
He doesn't know exactly how long that lasted but it was a long while he says
The next morning a whole group of men came in with a guy who seem to be an elder
Nail tip turns hitting ball with the hose
Until the older man called them off
Turn
And then that evening
Those things was evening he's not sure since he was blindfolded this whole time
They moved them
A movement to a new place
Because
Pretty sure
Ser Lake out
You saw where we were or someone might have seen him
So we got to move
I'm running a new place how are you
Imprisoned or how did they continue
In the new place they
Put me on a
Afghan bed and
Change my
Feet
To the end of the bed and change my hands
Today is basically spread eagle
On the bed
That's so expensive
Basically
Majoria next 3 months
Three months but was chained spread eagle to a bed and blindfolded
It was allowed to get up twice a day to use a toilet he says that's it
In a statement bow-routt is released as part of his legal case
He said that because of the Heat and sweat his body got sore and raw where it was in contact with the bed
Is eyes burn from the pressure of the blindfold he can never wipe the salt from them
He developed open wounds on his ankles and infection which into spread to his forehead
They beat the bottoms of his feet and other parts of his body with a copper cable
Ghostbuster came a day when he tried to walk and his guards saw his legs were shaking from weakness after that they rearranged when it is
His arms
Secured it down my side instead of over his head which allowed him to at least sit up
The room had dirt walls in a dirt-floor bus as
Every three or four weeks you could shower and wash his clothes
By the time 6 months head
Had diarrhea
You would have diarrhea for roughly three and a half years
No toilet paper or regular access to water most of the time his food with scant and came unpredictably
In the broadest Strokes his captivity consisted of twins hormones
Isolation and sickness
Or as well as principal military degree for describe it there were roughly three phases to post captivity Phase 1
Torture
Phase 2 abuse phase 3
Privation
How much lighter too much Darkness
Randomness
Where is the way
Your nerves into the ground
Yeah
Eeyore
Am I going to be able to
Go to the bathroom
Without some kind of problem
The conversations between Beau and Mark started just a few months after both came back
Botox a lot about how he's numb or distant or disconnected
Which actually has the benefit of helping him talk about what happened
Still the details about the worst episodes are sometimes hard to say
And hard for Mark
To take in
As a as a story it's
It's really it's overwhelming
And I can comprehend it in little bits and pieces
Like the isolated stuff as it goes along these details that you're giving me each one of them make sense
You know
And they're kind of
Not that hard to
To imagine cuz you're good at describing it
But they when you accumulate them all together and you think about this
Stretch of time and you think about
Just day-in-and-day-out if that's going to become sort of incomprehensibly
Dark
You know
Just
And I understand why they guys this year guys in the psychologists were so
Surprised that you weren't a total vegetable you know
Cuz I think that that's our
That would have been enough
To basically put
95% of people in a
Turn them into potatoes
But was being held by the haqqanis
A group run by very powerful pashtun family allowed with the Taliban
They're based in North waziristan which is in Pakistan's tribal region bordering Afghanistan
Agreed to hold boat for the Taliban and the guy in charge of Bose physical person was Melissa MaGee
A half-dozen times over the years
In all those who is kept and maybe eight different locations different compounds different rooms
Made of mud or cement
Especially at the beginning the Taliban question him
But he said they weren't what you might normally think of as an interrogation
The questions were strange and sometimes incoherent
You're the officer is on your face how do they get their prostitutes
You know they're trying to find
Obama gay
I asked you about
How good a camera
Thankfully the guy who did speak English
And
Information
And so you never really ask me anything
That was
One time you asked me how many bombs
This hodgepodge a perfectly reasonable questions
How did the drones work
And then it kind of crazy talk
Is it true All American women are prostitutes
But they sleep with animals
It makes you wonder why they're just trying to rile though up
Or whether their understanding of our world is as paltry as our understanding of theirs
Something I learned really quickly
If you show hesitation in telling them something
I think they're onto something
But if you if they ask you a question and you just start talking to him like you're talking to a normal person
Make it extremely suspicious
Because they seemed well if he is has no problem telling me this and there's something wrong with that information
Sweeter way
They pretty much assume you're lying
Which is maybe why they didn't really pressing too hard on any of this stuff
High-ranking Taliban told us
True reporter sami yousaf zai
But ya didn't give them any useful intelligence or Corporation
Besides both said the Taliban get most of their information information they consider more trustworthy
From Afghan interpreters work with us forces
Valley wasn't Inwood Inu
It was in the sheer fact of him
A US Soldier that belong to them
Information for me wasn't like their main priority
Videos out of me
What they wanted to do
You might have seen some of these videos on the internet
Who said they made probably a dozen of them that were never released
But a small handful were
Both of the Taliban spend a lot of time making them
The morale-boosting
Plus he says the Taliban love to embarrass the United States anyway they can
But you can't make too many videos are released too many
Because every time you do you're exposing yourself
Details about the staging or someone's accent of the production values of the dacor
Might give your location away
Rosa said sometimes make a number of videos during the same shoot
Changing the backdrop for his clothes or his hair is beard
Different kind of videos have been taken at different times and different locations
Bose videos spoke English
Western educated had a slight British accent
He come into boys room always with the same irritating greeting
What's up
Freddy Fazbear
Hey what's up
I'm going to take a video of you
Think about what you're going to say
President Obama
Talk about bike
Call Carol home
How badly.
Stuff like that
Answer
Did you have to work on your answers
Talk to me
Turn the camera on
After that they wrote everything down
As my country farm and has treated their Muslim prisoners
In background
Guantanamo Bay
Abu ghraib
The other Secret
Open round the world
But I bear Witness
Discontinued
In this video bows wearing a camouflage jacket helmet
And sunglasses
He looks really weird
He said the sunglasses were so you couldn't see his eyes reading the paper and also maybe because the Taliban think sunglasses look cool
Which grade and take pictures of naked
Leather dog barking at me inviting me if I country is Don Ramon's on Prison
Nails with diamonds
Who says the bed he was chained to spread eagle
Was just off to his left
Videos of the steam a lot
How well he's being treated compared to how the u.s. trees Taliban prisoners
How are we going to do in treating you
He says how are mujahideen treating you
Better than
A regular household
America
The videos also hit other common Taliban talking points
One of which is that the US government is lying to the American public about how many American soldiers have been killed in Afghanistan
Jamaican stream Daytona 200
Escobar
Mobile
I believe the death toll of Americans in Afghanistan is higher than what the government
Loud
The world snow
The Army has moral guidelines for how a soldier is supposed to behave if he or she is captured by the enemy
Call the code of conduct
It says among other things
If I am captured I will continue to resist by all means available I will make every effort to escape
I will give no information or take part in any action which might be harmful to my comrades
And when questioned besides name rank and serial number quote
I will evade answering further questions to the utmost of my ability
I will make no oral or written statements disloyal to my country and its allies or harmful to their cause
Soldiers I talk to you from Bo's Battalion told me the fact that Bo appears in these videos at all
It is answering their questions repeating their talking points
That right there is an obvious violation of the code of conduct
They said even if someone has a gun to your head and by the way both says there were guys with guns on his video shoot
You don't participate in the enemies propaganda campaign
Well that's actually an interpretation of the code that military officials do not agree with
That is not the standard the Army is asking soldiers to live up to
You are not expected to die refusing to make a video
In the first and second Gulf War is American pows shut up and propaganda videos to
Military didn't blame them for it
I understand that as a prisoner you're going to be compelled to do things you don't want to do
And also while the US military isn't getting courage you to be in a video if you're captured
There is an upside to being filmed your government has proof you're alive
A military hearing on Bose case
Terrence Russell the guy who debriefed bow
Said Indies videos bow did what he had to do
And that is the videos go on you can see him getting better at resisting at minimizing the propaganda value
In the very first video the Taliban released in July 2009
About three weeks after bow disappeared
Who is sitting in front of a table with some green liquid in a big mug
Marcus bow what it was
Mountain Dew
I give you one of those people off in that country
It's in this video that bow explains how he was captured
Are you listening
Who captured outside of Miss Stella
What were you doing
I was
Benign
Paw Patrol
I was sneaking behind the troll
This is why they reported back in the US
Debo said he was caught while lagging behind on a patrol and again a bunch of the soldiers I talked to mention this
That when they heard it and made them mad
Is it such obvious nonsense
U.s. soldiers do not lag behind on Patrols in Afghanistan and then just disappear without anyone noticing
Katana thing
So when they heard it was in the video some of them saw it as evidence that bill was lying about what happened
But was lying
He says of course he was lying
He says he knew that Americans listening would know it was bologna
That was the point
Chinese one-way in the video
HB telling people hey
Video
Esprit rehearse
And has nothing to do with
Was it all for Hurst
Or staged
So none of it was you
You the real you
I mean would you edit
Desperately trying to figure out how to
Cooperating with them and yet cooperating him
Guys guarding Bo don't speak English which makes sense why would they
But also that same high-ranking Taliban told us they don't necessarily want someone like near anyone who speaks English
Because they might say something just inadvertently and it could help him with an escape
Even if they couldn't really talk to him though says they interacted with him they messed with them they throw things at him
AK-47 Adam just kidding
Once they tried to make him smoke a cigarette with a little firecracker in it when he handed it back healed bang and one of the guards
After that the guy gave him less food
Butler not to sleep in the daytime because it left him open to these guys they might take any opportunity
Picture of being shaved by the Taliban with a straight razor
He's handcuffed
Even then when he couldn't be more vulnerable
They have a laugh at his expense
Okay
IC
Videos to take pictures
Yourself
Yeah I'm getting worse
Basically the reality of situation
Sami Yusuf side the Afghan reporter interviewed some people who had dealings with bow while he was in captivity
Big Shot who came by and talked about his cell I got to cook for I'm a friend of one of the guards
Informal sanctions Entourage
Sammy took away from these interviews was that keeping Bergdahl was number one
Stressful
How to keep him away from everybody not truly from
Jonesy how to keep him away from Al-Qaeda Arabs in bandits in
If something happened you know
Continue our responsibility would be
You know beat anyone arrested by so that's why
These guys are watching the only US soldier who's ever been taken prisoner in this war
Other groups might want to steal him from them
Sammy said the guards had her talk that some Arabs and masks had almost made it to the house where they were holding bow
Captured and executed
Some people he thought were being paid by the US for information on bow
So even though it's a prestigious
Job is still suck
Yep
IC
Still like
Mentally lot of pressure range
I'm bored I think would happen
Boring
That's the other thing Sammy her in these interviews how tedious it was for them which is probably where the stupid and sometimes sadistic
Jokes come in
These guys are mostly young men
Are stuck inside a compound or some other prison location
Well they're Pals or maybe out and about enjoying themselves
In all
Having fun dancing Gitano something but here
And are you are bored nobody is allowed to come to visit
Because I'm just guy got in trouble
You cannot go out on we cannot go to the city we cannot make a phone call because it was not thinking
So even even even for the God you know
Do naturally happy
Write what students do what they are.
Then I'm sure
Milazzo Universe promising them a lot of thing
Lot of things
Yeah
McChicken
And you would hold more
Money
And everything
Sammy talk to a friend of one of the guards
Who told them that to amuse themselves they think up things to do to bow or how to get rid of bow
Ettalong hypothetical discussion about circumcising him
They talked about selling him
I may be calling in a funny tip the Americans that they had Osama Bin Laden so they'd be a raid they could be done with it
Another word for young guys
Shooting the shed following orders
Ghostkeepers would make him watch execution videos
Weddings are suicide bombers the very first day they got him they should have a video of mujahideen
Executing prisoners
In part because you still affected by them
Trenton details lodged in his head
In one a man is about to be beheaded and looks terrified he silent and a rooster is crowing
For both the videos are obviously disturbing on their face but they were also a Grizzly warning that this could have
Happened to him and anytime
They all had their own videos to show me
And where they showing at you like this is s*** that we've done or just stuff that other people we know are dumb
This is what other people have done
A few of them have been with his wife
My people have done
One guy who was
I would say literally
Basically out of his mind
And back to the point where the other Taliban called in Crazy Town
Tom
But where did they use for that
So they call him crazy town in
You tell me that he would kill he's killed
One time on one of those shifts
He told me to
Decapitated two guys and then a few months later it came back
He told me that he's on another
A while he was in the interim when it while you haven't seen you
I know the guys are basically their Afghans who betrayed their brothers
During all this time Bo's scheming and plotting
Gathering information that he hopes will get him out
And that he can deliver back to the US
Which by the way he does
Terrence Russell at the military hearing cookie and other debris furs
Intelligence debriefing overseer psychologist FBI agents
All found boiger to download whatever until he could
And quote remarks on the quality of information Sergeant Bergdahl with providing unquote
Also they praise His recall
Who said he was trying all the time to store in his memory mental pictures of every detail he could
For this Mission he pretty much starts from zero when he's chained down and blindfolded
When you can't see he listens
Tries to discern the daily patterns of the people who kept them
When they slept
When the AIDS how their families work who's related to whom
Didn't know if it would be useful to him or to someone else back home
In case
I think it's moved around from house to house and allowed marginally more freedom
See at the stand he sponges up new bits of information
End up staying a while at a house owned by guy who thinks was named today
By this time it was so filthy
Smelled so bad
He said the young women in little boys resented having to deal with them they might spill his food on purpose
What's a boy beat him over the head with his own chain
Asbestos pocatello's because you've been humming
Both started to suss out information
Really enthusiastic
A blue baseball cap
Oh okay
The name of the
In the corner
The name of the town
Are all in English
I also like somebody had given it to them like some like Angie or somebody
That was their school uniform
So maybe that was the name of the place he was in North waziristan
Now we just have to figure out exactly where North waziristan was
Everywhere he was held he said except for one place in the mountains
He's pretty sure he wasn't too far from what he assumed was an American base you can hear artillery he could see helicopters losing a
Altitude to land
Ignore the scream of plane engines
In fact what he was hearing was almost certainly a Pakistani bass oboe couldn't know that the best you could figure
He was still in Afghanistan very near the border
But had no special training and how to survive any of this how to deal with abuse
How to gather Intel
How to resist while making it look like you're cooperating
As an army private he had was called a level Seer training the most basic level of survival evasion
Resistance and Escape training
What it consisted of at the time of both employment according to both senior debriefer was
Here's a code of conduct on quote
She's just puzzling it out as he goes trying things and then trying them again
Days house is a sort of mud-hut attempts to dig himself out something like five times
To get rid of the dirty Blues from the wall he mix it with his own urine or feces and then smear it back on the wall
The Pebbles and rocks are harder to dispose of
Are the same house there was a dog I'm pretty aggressive dog that the little boys and men especially were scared of
Most of the women sometimes gave it leftovers so I was nicer to them
Who knew if you tried to escape he couldn't have the dog freaking out and barking so he started sneaking a bit of food out to it
When he was led to the latrine which is right near where the dog slept
And that weibo made peace with the dog eventually begin sleeping in the room where Beau was his captors that was totally weird
Incidentally someone who analyzes and telling both case tell me one of the rumors they heard along the way
With a bow had a puppy
Possibly a German Shepherd puppy
Silliness
But maybe this sometimes vicious guard dog was the so-called puppy
Over the month spell managed to gather small items
Which he turned into tools
And by the end of that first year
Taken together they become his Escape kit
He had a length of PVC tube maybe 8 inches long
He's been able to keep with him since the very first house
In one of the rooms he shoved it into the wall and peed out it so his urine wouldn't just be in the room
The people reappear later as part of a crossbar
He found a nail in a mud wall
He can make holes with it
Scrape away dirt with it
Cleaning fingernails with it
When the time came he spend weeks rubbing the head of it on a rock
Until it was just the right shape to get the old timey shackles off his rest
Is Jordan on the sole of the shoe
Probably the biggest score was a key
Feminine boy should come into his room when the boys was holding a bunch of keys on a string and dropped
When you did one of the keys got away it's all right near the mat we're both slapped
Cebu slid it underneath
Nobody seemed to notice it was missing
Wasn't the key to the padlock key needed to open
The Bose has the lost with these cheaply-made Chinese locks
Wiggling the key just so he could hit The Sweet Spot and pop them open
With that one key and using that technique it allow me to open
Padlocks that they're using the hold method
What were the years of the months
I was able to keep this key
Bowhead tried many mini Escape
He gotten as far as a courtyard up to a wall
But they were for Israeli
Is biggest best chance
Hey when he was at a remote place in the mountains
This is the farthest he ever was from a populated area
Basically Powhatan prison
Calls it the mountain Fortress
What the really it literally look like
Because
There's everything was just this really old and like it was actually
In the mountain Fortress bow is kept in a second-story room which is padlocked but there was a window
Without bars on it this place was so old and he seemed so pathetic by that point he says his guards weren't taking extra
Cautions
The key to PVC pipe plus it wouldn't stake that was in the room
Bottle of Mountain Dew hat blanket sandals
He went for it
Middle of the night
Call the night before
Putting everything together
Getting my hands tied up the water bottle that I had
The Rope was made from the two chains he's now liberated each about 6 ft long he says plus his bedding
It ended up being quite a bit longer than you need it
Drop to the ground with only about 15 feet
I didn't know that
There's a reason maybe you haven't heard other American pows Escape stories
Because there hasn't been a successful one since the Vietnam War
Again cuz you're supposed to attempt it but the Army understands especially since Vietnam
The odds are usually an overwhelmingly against you
If you're a p o w and you assess the situation and you decide
It's highly unlikely I can make it out that window without being shot
It's highly unlikely that even if I do make it out I'll be able to blend in with the local population
It is highly likely
But if the enemy finds me they will torture or kill me
So no I'm not going to try to go out that window
That is right in fine
No one will fault you for it
To me more than anything this moment in the mountain Fortress what's all the talk about Bo being a sympathizer to rest
Odoo not sympathize with the Taliban
A load the Taliban
So much so that even when he's sick
He doesn't have any food
He's already been punished for escaping the first time he knows what that's like
Instill
Goes out the window
Mixed bag out of his blanket what does water bottle in it swings it over his shoulder and starts walking
Apart from being rescued it was maybe the best moment of his five years
Yeah
It's High Desert Terrain
Cold at night hot in the day Rocky
Are bushes and trees supposed to look like Joshua trees
And something Piney not a lot of cover
But his immediate objective is not to hide though he'll have to do a lot of hiding obviously
Right now he's trying to get as far away as he can from The Fortress
He wants to spread the search party as thinly as possible
He has what he hopes is southeast
Intending to go into Pakistan
He figures he's got a better shot at encountering someone non-hostile to him in Pakistan
But the train is so difficult
He's in his shorts
Steep Maisy Mountain
Get over one there's immediately another one
And they're all about the same height so it's not like you can reach a peak and get your bearings see the twinkle of a friendly fob in the distance
He climbs and descends
Sometimes scooting on his butt
All the while he's listening for water
Three places water bottle
Images of valley
And is populated
He keeps having to fear this way or that skirt offense or house or sheepherders tent
I don't know how long I don't know how
Boat lands on a dry River bed on his left side
He said the word oof actually came out of his mouth just like in a cartoon
Loud enough so that some dog started barking their heads off
Away from where I am
I wanted to fill up my water bottle
My left hand
Your adrenaline must have just been pumping so hard this whole time
Reason why I didn't feel
End up feeling about
10 minutes later
He's done something terrible to his left leg and his left arm
And the pain of that starts to wash over him
And then just stay
It's getting later it's going to be light soon
Chabot uses the small length of bar that have been used to hold his feet together
And he uses it to Claude the Earth at the base of a tree to make a hole
It's mulchy and then just rocks underneath but it's good enough
He piles of dirt around the whole to make a berm and then sticks branches into the burn so it Blends into the landscape better
Then he gets into the hole
Imposes blanket over himself
So that was his first night of freedom
In all books has this Escape lasted about nine days
Interviews with Sammy and another media reports the Taliban admit this Escape happened though there versions vary in terms
How it happened and how long it lasted
General days
Thursday briefers settled on 8.5 days
Once morning hits bow has to stay put in the hole he can't move around in the day
And where he is it populated and it's rural so people walk everywhere their foot past criss-crossing all over the place
Over the coming week while he's hiding and holes are trenches during the day
There were so many close calls
Sheet that came close and spooked women out Gathering something-or-other From the bushes men you could tell they were
Men with guns you can hear the clock on The Middle
There was a scare with a flashlight time when he heard the familiar beeping of those Motorola type walkie talkies the Taliban use
But I'm a little girls wanted off the road and up the hill where he was hiding
Three or four
And apparently they're looking for flowers or something
Are off the road like almost directly toward me
They pass right by his feet keep going there talking to each other Emerson whatever they're doing
And then they come back down the hill a bus as they pass right by his head tiny oblivious girls
Can't walk properly because his left side is hurting so badly so he's crawling along on a combination of elbow
Or on his butt
Not going well
On top of everything he really has no idea where he's going he's completely lost
Kid learn Celestial navigation as a kid
And now he can't recall how the Big Dipper relates to the North Star
The water he's drinking is feted like I've seen too many sheep
Is eating grass
Don't make a difference
It's Isabella shrinking
Getting smaller and more helpless more primitive
Is s*** is completely green
He stuck in a hole all day
Is down to nothing no resources
Right above him
Some of the highest Tech equipment in the world for seeing and finding
Drones
American drones Guided by American eyes
They can't reach each other remembers one night being on top of the mountain
Remember
Drones
Like moving across the sky
Really
You're so close and yet
Things are so stacked against you that it's this
Time to think about what he do if a friendly Convoy Patrol came by
How did Safeway get their attention
Did you ran out them in his Afghan clothes they might think he was a suicide bomber
Fisher cat you take all his clothes off
Pics of tall skinny naked white guy coming at you
Coming to Paul's over perhaps
If anyone had, crossbow they probably have taken in the following
He's in pain on his left side
Is in gastric distress
He's starving you scared and he's lost
Did you ever think that
During the course of the Escape that maybe you made a mistake that the you know being out
That escaping was
Maybe more treacherous than just staying put
I knew it was like before I escaped I knew it was going to be more
It's going to be more immediate risk
Yeah
I get myself out the window as in basically come to terms with the fact
Very much like a suicide
Fishing you know it's like
Looking for a needle in a haystack as far as being saved
What it was like okay if I'm going to die either
Exposure out there or being shot while I escape
It's better than having my head cut off cuz I thought enough of those movies to
Are videos with honor for those two
What that would be like
Perdiendo is too debilitated to cover much ground
Is hunger pangs were gone
Please blacking out when he stood up
Getting tunnel vision
He didn't exactly stop caring about getting caught
More like he stopped having the energy to be afraid
He remembers one of the last night watching the sun go down and it's only thought
Is that it was beautiful
On the last day of bow says he had passed out on top of the mountain
How many came to he started trying to make some sort of brace out of sticks for his left knee
Your voices
Rustling bushes
I'm blowing he saw the search party coming up the mountain he was caught
Because of the drones the men wanted to get him off the mountain as quickly as I could
They took him back to the prison
One of the older guys both thinks he might have been a relative of Melissa and being attacked him
Try to rip his hair out his beard out
Rosetti mostly succeeded in doing
He was so out of it he didn't really feel it
He wasn't beaten more than that he says maybe because they knew looking at him
He might not survive a beating
Let him sleep
The next morning they cleaned him up and they took him to a meeting with Melissa and Ian
Principal message to boas
If you try to escape again will just kill you
I mean did you apologize to them
No I never apologize
Effort for trying to escape
I probably would have
Better than that escape was
The last time I saw Stars
Tonight
Horses pick me up
About 4 years inside
And while he's waiting
So many people would be trying to get Bo away from Sun game
All these huge military and diplomatic forces about to kick in
Just as the United States is realizing
We need to get out of this war
And then things get really interesting
Next time on serial
Ciro's produced by Julie Schneider Dana to visit me in partnership with Markel Megan Ellison Hugo Lindgren Jessica Weisberg page 1 +
Annapurna pictures are glasses our editorial advisor we need Dangerfield is our digital editor research by Kevin Garnett fact
Checking by Michelle Harris copy editing bionica delaunay
Our music is composed by Nick thorburn Fritz Myers and Mark Phillips
She was mixed by Kate bilinski Kristen Taylor's our community editor other cereal staff Southland Emily Condon at Leesburg
Ferguson and Kimberly Henderson special things this week and Andrew Cuomo
Our website is serial podcast. Org you can listen to all of our episodes
Sign up for our newsletter read articles by the serial staff and check out Maps videos and more
This week we posted a photograph that both has was taken right after his big Escape right after his meeting with Melissa Holguin
Again that's serialpodcast.org
Stay tuned for preview of our next episode
The first
Support for serial comes from ADT
You can use the ADT app to monitor your cameras and video doorbell from virtually anywhere
Visit att.com podcast
To learn more about how ATT can design and install York
Smart Home
Back by 24/7 Pro
Shiro's production of This American Life and WBEZ Chicago
Coming up
Next episode of serial
Was it worse than Iraq
That that deployment I mean
Yeah it was the worst year of my life it was horrible yeah
Your operations order had something to do with Bowe Bergdahl
Then people were going to give it to
The stamp of approval say go ahead and Smash Smash down some doors
Asking questions
I have some guilt like maybe there's something I could do but then what if I don't
Exactly why I've always sort of treated the way he was treated
But it's certainly plausible to me that the reason he was treated so horribly
Was because I was treated so well