Serial season 3 is the smartest way to hire
Later during the company that hired engineers
The world's first
Practical flying car
Fuel solenoid ZipRecruiter is rated number one by Employers in the US
Play some hiring sites with over 1000 reviews on trustpilot
ZipRecruiter for free at ziprecruiter.com
Cereal
Support for serial comes from Squarespace
Make your business official with Google and Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and a Business website with Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and professional tools from Google
Is the simplest way to look professional online
Visit squarespace.com Google to start your free trial
And use offer code professional for a discount on your first purchase
Google and Squarespace
Make it professional make it beautiful
Previously on serial
I don't care if you was my worst enemy I'm not telling on you
I don't care what you did
Meet people out there in the community that are concerned
Black lives with brown lies White Lies with purple eyes
The stop out and do something so I can
Tell teenagers telling the truth
I went through the things I was going through when I was younger cuz I was young and dumb
From This American Life and WBEZ Chicago
It's serial one Courthouse told week by week on Sarah Koenig
When I began this project I didn't plan on covering any juvenile case
Juvenile records are public for one thing
I figured we got plenty to look at right here in the adult system
After while juvenile cases juvenile crime became impossible to ignore the newly-elected
County prosecutor it seem to be talking about juvenile violence and every opportunity
Young people
14 to 21
A crime drivers
The data supported his alarm
More and more juveniles were being charged with the worst crime
Serious assaults robberies
Rapes homicides
All Rising for the past 5 years
Once these juvenile crimes made their way into the juvenile courts though
And once the juveniles themselves made their way into juvenile prisons
They disappear from View
Juvenile court rooms are tightly controlled
Names of juvenile defendants aren't publicized for good reason
The crimes children commit should not Forevermark them
But as a result I didn't have a picture of what Juvenile Justice look like in Cuyahoga County
I'd your mutterings at the Justice Center though
Mostly from defense attorneys grousing to each other
You're not going to believe what just happened to my juvenile quieter
Tumi
You think this place is bad
You should head over to juvenile
But I think
Why
What are you talking about
Then I met Joshua
He was 19 at the time
So not a child
He tell you he was grown
But he was still in the juvenile system
You can stay there till your 21
Keep in mind the juvenile system its mission is different from that of the adults
The point isn't to punish
Retribution
The point is to rehabilitate
In the juvenile system
That's where we're supposed to think like parents
Are the standard should be
My child
Is this what's best for my child
But this help my child
So
I'm going to tell you about Joshua
Joshua sometimes starts off a story with
Okay so boom
Boom is big in Cleveland
Shorthand for
Let me try to explain
For real
I feel like all the way like phone
All the tape I have with Joshua is from prison
So the sound is mostly at any threat of terrible
I'm sorry about that
Prison system allow me to interview Joshua and purse
But I can tell you is his longtime interlocutor I like it when Joshua says boom
Or better yet
Boom boom
Means I might start to understand something
So just how Joshua came to inhabit his current predicament
One Night in June of 2014
Joshua freshly 16i down to sleep after a night at a bar
Next thing you know
FBI agents for pulling him from his bed
They took him to an interrogation room in Cleveland Heights
They told him they had him for some robberies
Like these
Instagram Facebook
Famous 15 year olds are rarely criminal mastermind
Posing with all these other kids
The FBI agents were saying not only do we have video evidence of what you've done but thank you social media
We also know who you run with
The crimes Joshua was charged with were serious armed robberies from many months back
Gas stations in a friend held up to BP's in one day
And a third robbery of a Popeye's Joshua said he was coerced into that one by an older gang member they barely got Nemo
Money he said they left with this pathetic little plastic bucket that had small bills in it
Greenfield police reports read a hundred fifty bucks would be handed over to the boss for the restaurant had teeth
Who had to lie down on the ground with a multiple kidnapping indictment right there Joshua had jumped over the couch
Connor and pointed a gun at someone and again according to the police report said
You have 5 Seconds to open the safe or I'll shoot him
Joshua said his gun had no bullets in it that his co-defendants gun was broken the firing pin was busted
Are the customers and workers at Popeye's that Wednesday morning didn't know that
The FBI agents were telling Joshua we've got you on video so let's friends are our choices shall we
We can hand you over to the adult court system that's called a bind over
In Ohio children as young as 14 can be bound over to adult court for certain crimes
To Joshua adult Court sounded serious that was an adult system Joshua would be
Facing between 20 and 30 years in prison
Or the officer said
Another option
We can talk
If we talk
We can keep you in the juvenile
We won't find you over
Okay. When you're 21 5 years from now
With no adult felony record
My talk
Joshua was operating on a couple hours sleep
If he remembers right he was handcuffed
He said the officers weren't rude or abusive to him
This cool he said
They left him alone for a while
To think about the deal they were offering
At any point did you say to them I want to talk to a lawyer or I need to speak to my mom
Is there any
Adult or any lawyer involved in any of that
I like
Did you say can I have a lawyer
For now
No I never said that
Right
Okay
Adult store
When they said Mike was having an adult here with me what did they say
And how long do they keep you there
I was there for about like
Polite
With no adult knowing where you were
No
Really
Doesn't it sound illegal
It's not
It's allowed
My children haven't robbed any gas station so I feel the apples and oranges here
But I have to sign a permission slip for my teenager to go on a quote-unquote field trip that's a five-block walk from her school
I could check the box to allow my son's photo from summer camp to be used for promotional purposes
What year was Joshua
Followed by exhaustion and the prospect of everlasting incarceration
And no adults but a hand on his shoulder
To crouch down and whisper in his ear what I believe most of us would have whispered if we've been in that room
Ask for a lawyer
Do it now ask for
Lawyer
Joshua had
The interview would have
Should have stopped
And maybe his story would have
Should have gone another way
As it was Joshua took the deal
That fast
It was June of 2014
Two months earlier his daughter had been born
Those two months with already told me where the happiest of his life
You couldn't handle the idea of being locked up until both he and she were decades older
And also Joshua's relationship inside the gang he was in
Heartless felons
Complicated
I know it's hard to square but Joshua says he was an armed robber who wasn't into violence
Isn't the only benefit of joining the heartless felons with the protection they offered
From the heartless felons
From them
He said they extorted people into committing crimes
Especially the younger kids like him
When do serious time if they got caught
So yeah
He did stuff with them and for them
Didn't feel anything for most of them
The only one he have considered a friend you told me
You're not guy had pulled a gun on him once during an argument
So he took the deal
Juvenile life
The catch
Something called a serious youthful offender dispositional sentence
Usually people just call it an syo
It works like a suspended adult prison sentence
You young man are going to stay in the juvenile system that's
The carrot
We're hanging a ghostly adult sentence over your head that's the stick
Which we can invoke if you can't keep it together in juvenile prison
So if you want to stay in juvenile you have to behave
Joshua believed he could behave he took the deal
That same day he got arrested
Joshua says he drove around with the cops showed them places
Identify people in photographs
People associated with the heartless felons
In the coming months he'd meet with investigators a couple more times
Joshua has terrific recall for all manner of information
I'd give them dates
Addresses
X
He told them details of crimes about which they already knew and about ones they didn't
As a source
He was a champion
He really Joshua is extremely unusual
This is Lissa Rankin
She was Joshua's public defender
Choose a scientist case only after Joshua had agreed to cooperate
When I called her to ask about Joshua
It been a client for only a couple months
Earlier
Remember him immediately
She's used to clients refusing to cooperate with the police
Refusing even to tell her information that might help their defense
So for him to be
So open and volunteering information and
How this whole thing
Start is that when he had met with the office
It's worth before the arraignment
Before he was represented he had volunteered information
And he really helps them
On a number of Investigations because they didn't have starting points
This is when the heartless felons really started coming in
The play
They were freaking a lot of havoc in Cuyahoga County and I believed
The state of salar
And so the police were very desperate to get as much information as they can
And Joshua really connected a lot of.
And I think he explained it in a way
That really was almost like a tutorial
And he could tell you
Everything
You know he could explain hierarchy housings work
You know there's really no such thing as a King app
Because
There aren't people in these gangs you know studying these games that kind of studying from a sociological standpoint
I felt like Josh was probably one of the clearest historians that they've had in a long time
Really
Put himself out there and because of Josh
You know other other major crimes were solved and
You know the Hope was that
Much more dangerous individuals
Zorbing
Taking off the streets
Because of Josh
This gang is affiliated
With the heartless felons
The gang operated in the Glenville neighborhood between
Saint Clair Superior
East 105 Street area
7 months after Joshua begin cooperating
A bunch of important people in Cleveland would hold a press conference
The mayor of Cleveland police chief
People from ATF FBI County Sheriff's Office
Prosecutor
They said
Six months ago we began an investigation
Announce the 13-person indictment
All members of a heartless felons Affiliated group
Call the Cutthroats
Joshua's General neighborhood
We looked at these gang members for crimes ranging from
Voice results
Aggravated robberies kidnappings various weapons violations
They're also tied to at least one homicide that we know of right now
There were drug charges Rico charges gang charges more Gang Related rest will follow
BFDI didn't talk to me about Joshua's case or his cooperation by the way north of the Cleveland Police
Almost everyone in the Cutthroat indictment pleaded guilty
A couple of people went to trial
And again Joshua kept up his end of the deal
A year had gone by since his arrest
He thought he was all done helping
But then off they took him to the Justice Center
Or he got up in front of his dangerous Earth while friends
An out at himself as an informant
He knew that hate him for it could get killed for it if he's got the chance
We also figured
Everyone on that cuts word indictment all these cases
They were adults
They be going into adult prisons
He was staying in juvenile
He testified at the trial of one guy charged for a drive-by shooting like I was acquitted
And also in a murder trial
For that one Josh was only job was to identify the defendant
Yeah I know him
Joshua had no first-hand information about the crime
But the state put him on the stand anyway
Ask the prosecutor MOA dollar
Why put Joshua up there then
You had other people ID in your guy
Including an ATF agent
Including the defendant's own mother
Who said yeah that young man sporting the distinctively energetic ponytail in the surveillance tape
That's my son
So I put Joshua up there
You don't want to leave evidence
Not you
You know you have evidence
We're going to use it
Ensure that
Yeah something like this a homicide word person
Life is taken from him for no reason
Another person is Gravely injured
That we don't leave at the chance
You guys ever hesitate to use juveniles cuz you're just like let's try to keep them out of the stuff
Sometimes
At it again depends on the case
Your problem is a lot of our Shooters are people who are killing people are
Are Young
And other people to hang out with
The prosecutor from the other trial
The drive-by shooting told me
Of course they never want their witnesses to get hurt
He also said
In terms of Joshua after he was done testifying
I didn't really give him any thought
Lissa Rankin the public defender happened to be in the courtroom and Joshua was on the stand
He wasn't her client anymore but she recognized
And she thought
Wow they are still using him
This is still going on
You know I was very concerned for Joshua safety because we know how these
Cases go
You know any of the kid
Other defense attorneys told me they do not advise their clients to
To cooperate unless there's no other solution
Too often the benefits aren't what they're cracked up to be
Well the risks crackle on for years
I talked to another public defender in the juvenile division
Morgan Pierce
She told me she quote rarely if ever has a could cooperate with law enforcement
Unless your kid can jump out of plane she said
They're either going to go to juvenile prison and be in danger or they're going to go back to their neighborhood and be in danger
And still very much trust the system to follow through on what they say
The prosecutors are not beholden to anything
So the kids are used
Are naive
Lissa Rankin remembered how much the police officers had seemed to like Joshua when they interviewed on
I did encourage him
There's talk of him getting out of prison
Going to school
There was a lot of talk that they would check in on him and
I guess you know ideally you hope that that means
Somehow protecting him
Juvenile prisons in Ohio
Are run by the Ohio Department of Youth Services odys
And if a juvenile prison system could have a golden age
This would be it 4 Ohio
10 years ago the system was forced to remake itself
After lawsuits and a state investigation that a federal investigation
If I need a consent decree
Back in 2007 a court-ordered investigation found what sounded like child abuse
Potentially
Severely overcrowded housing units
Untrained confrontational poorly supervised sometimes even vengeful staff
Using excessive force
And quote Reckless and malicious practices
Choke holds that created extreme risks of asphyxia
Java juices tactics in strategic locations to avoid cameras
Kids were also being harmed by other kids
I need no real Avenue to complain or to get help
Sometimes they threaten suicide just to get into isolation
Then came federally-mandated and fairly massive reforms
It's hard to do away with solitary confinement as a punishment
Art staff from using Force except in extreme circumstances
And added lots of educational and therapeutic programs
Most impressively they really did redefined what juvenile prison should be for
Weather condition before
Unless your child is hurting other people using a gun committing rape setting housefires
He's probably not going to an odys closed facility
Is going to go to a smaller residential or non-residential program in his own community
I want some young hot wires and spray painters still do end up in odys prisons for the wrong reasons
Address of Alternatives in their own rural counties or around head of Judge
Generally speaking Ohio is not locking up kids like that anymore
2004 through 2000 kids in Ohio juvenile prisons
Now they're about 500
In 2015 the Department of Justice issued a report
Celebrating a turnaround that has quote resulted in what is many ways a model system
We are calling the Ohio model
Excellent progress yes
The one downside is that the kids who do get sent to odys
To borrow a phrase from Donald Rumsfeld
Are the worst of the worst
Or if Donald Rumsfeld had a compassionate social worker said she might say
The kids arriving at odys now or more traumatized and higher needs
And instead of being divided among nine institutions there now corralled into 3
The higher concentration of sometimes-violent always struggling children
Living together in a smaller space
The facility where Joshua landed in September of 2014
It's called Indian River
Not officially maximum-security but functionally it operates like Judy Mac
One big building housing at time about 140 kids
They have their own school which is across the yard
I've been inside the main building
What's clean brightly-painted
Life-size posters of basketball stars are decorating the hallway
What does 8 units roughly 20 kids doing unit
Single rooms with doors that close
Each unit has ad a room with a TV
They can play video games
Play cards of Dysart
Contraband
The kids go to school to therapy they might have jobs cleaning a cup
Cafeteria ordering maintenance
At first things went okay for Joshua to Indian River
No one knew he cooperated with law enforcement
Josh Rosen family didn't know
He saw that the heartless felons were in charge of some of the unit
Controlling the video game remote
Taxing kids for their food forcing them to clean up or to make 3-way phone calls for them
All of which Joshua had anticipated
Heartless felons were invented in Cleveland's juvenile lockup
And Joshua had been inside one of them before
When is about 13
Does the first time he saw how tightly they operated inside prison
Joshua had already passed the various tests to get absorbed into the Gang
They call it getting twisted
If you don't want to be perpetually bullied and assaulted
If you want to be able to eat
Other kids taking your food
Joshua said you try to join
And to join you have to get three bodies
Assault 3 people
Other other juveniles are staff
Strike
An Indian River Joshua with an Insider well-positioned
Nobody was asking him where you from
Always the first loaded question
She was friends with the leader of the heartless felons
The Godfather
Rgf
Vouch for him
Is good for about a year
Then he had to testify at the trial downtown
And a Slither of rumors started back at Indian River
The Joshua had told
Cuz like the beginning of 2000s
The Donald
Popped up like what are you talkin about what what specifically is happening
Working around me
Whenever I ask Joshua what it was like to testify how he felt about cooperating with the
The police
The dancers are rushed in a little mechanical
As if the subject triggers a tiny Guillotine window and is Brian to zip closed
Protecting the more fragile synapses from exposure
What account with practically digital accuracy though
Is when the trouble really really started
Indian River for about 2 years
And then he transferred
To a minimum-security juvenile prison
Call Cuyahoga Hills
Summer 2016
That's when the bare-bones rumors about Joshua started to Take On Me
Cell phone
He was like
Ambulance
Cuyahoga Hills is in a suburb right outside Cleveland
Lots of people from his neighborhood or rival neighborhoods
Coming and going
Family members visiting
Calling gossiping
And someone from the drive-by shooting case
The Joshua helped
The police with
Not one of the defendants from that case
But the victim you've been shot in the leg with an assault rifle
That victim he was also at Cuyahoga Hills
Joshua said they'd seen each other a year earlier at the Justice Center
When Joshua had to testify the trial
And now I Cuyahoga Hills that kid was telling people who Joshua was
What Joshua did
It was Open Season
Everyday
Cuyahoga Hills unlike Indian River
Is 8 units with open dorms
There's one seclusion room per unit in case
But otherwise kids are mingling all the time
Which if your target
Is tantamount to a hellscape
A quick look at the odys rundown of incidents involving Joshua
You see the rush of assaults as soon as he gets
Cuyahoga Hills
Like a blood pressure spike
July 3rd
July 7th
July 19th July 22nd
Joshua can fight
A few staff members told me he can really fight
He told me his moves got the attention of one guard who's also a gym teacher
Joshua said the guys to watch the surveillance videos
Best fights in admiration
Anyway Joshua fought back
But he said more and more people were assaulting him
First of the three people than for people than 6 people
The worst assault in terms of the physical damage done to Joshua
Was in September of 2016
It happened in the schoolhouse
Haven staying clear of school because you knew it wasn't safe there
But he said they told him he wouldn't be allowed to take his GED test
If you didn't have 90%
Attendance
Then next thing you know like I was walking through the school hall
And then
Black dolphin
I woke up in the hospital that's all I remember
Oh my god really have no memory is like
Yeah I got to start it
My head on the door
On the ground
On the doorknob when I was
Lay down and I'll just had a seizure
I was coughing up blood
Modern members
Oakland Hospital
Clothes full of blood
How long are you in the house
Hospital
I was just there for a couple of hours and I
Are they coming back in the same part of the institution with the higher higher higher ranking
I worry about wearing some back at square one
Another attack
December 30th 2016
Joshua's jumped again
This time he firmly believes a guard made that happen
You just been moved to a new unit and he started arguing with the guard on duty
Joshua said he went and took the unit phone
And the guards desk
Deploy to get some attention
He put it in his Foot Locker by his bed
When give it back
The guard had ordered pizza from the kids on the unit Joshua said when the guard came in with the pizza boxes
He told some kids
Go get the phone back from Joshua
And you can have your pizza
Knowing full well Joshua says that that would likely lead to an assault
I did
Three kids jumps Joshua
I got out of hand
Joshua said the guard then cuff them
Start to walk him out
But then a bunch more kids
Joshua thinks about five of them
They joined in
Got trash on the ground so now he's got about eight kids on them all heartless felons while he's handcuffed
Joshua said the guard didn't call a signal 88 to ask for help that's for a serious fight or riot
Is that a different guard called a signal 5
Which means other staff are more likely to mosey over to help
Rather than run
But Joshua says more guards finally did come over and one of them put his own body between Joshua and the kids
Door stopping him
If I pick you up
Sutter Clinic
Three guards were also injured
Joshua says after that they took him to operations
We sat there for another hour or two handcuffs
Then just went into seclusion cell for a while
I ran all of what Joshua told me by odys
But the department would not answer any questions about Joshua
Did you not discuss juveniles in their custody
Nor were they provide anyone for me to interview about their policies or procedures are philosophy generally
Because they said it would be in service of a story about a particular use
They did send me a general statement which will get to later
Joshua said all along he's been telling me administration at Cuyahoga Hills
I am not safe
I heard similar complaints from other kids at odys
I told them
They didn't really do anything
You see an Institutional reports and lawsuits over the years as well
Allegations that staff knew kids were in danger from other kids
I didn't do enough
Joshua said he practically begged the people in charge at Cuyahoga Hills
You got to send me back to Indian River
Snuffer's Dallas all down there
Stop
And then
Institution like they basically
I kept coming back and back for like parlay
2 months
Like I'll never stop never stop
Dancing by sending look like
And they danced they still didn't do it
Apply how to speak methadone with the
But the superintendent at the institutional Hills
He basically said like
Like it was my fault that I was getting started like
Again odys did not comment on Joshua
This case including whether he asked to be moved
But I don't know
That was bringing everything on me
Likes and like that I called the boss
People
She just told me like
You better stop or so me gorgeous what's wrong
He thinks you're a heartless felon still
Yeah that's
But nobody was saying I kept telling him I can't explain
Lights flickering off and gorgeous
Lake Emily
Like bring it back on me
Like like you just keep your mouth closed
After about six months at Cuyahoga Hills Joshua met with a couple of lawyers
Defense attorney
Who said he'd figure out if he could get Joshua early release from odys
Anna civil rights attorney mr. Paul cristallo is matter of fact
Then you might remember from aramis's case
That's how I learned about Joshua and Paul
Attorneys were shocked they said
It seemed like the heartless felons were colluding with staff
They considered asking the State Attorney General's office to launch an investigation
In the meantime
Paul had called the facility to say
I know Juvenile Justice expert but
Seems like you might want to move this kid
NPS
You might be suing you
More after the break
This is the road to hire
Brought to you by zip recruiter just Toro works as the lead recruiter for terrafugia
Latin for escape the Earth
Terrafugia is a company
That builds
Flying cars
They already have one prototype that really flies
But that's just one vehicle
They got all kinds of stuff in the works
One project will be more of an Urban Air Taxi
That will help transport
Passengers through the air invalid congested major cities
I could pick up a Supreme Being reincarnated in humanoid form on the run from authorities
But that probably would be one used because of the wrong hands yeah
Cool movies n
Yes
In order to do that they got to make a bunch of hires
In fact they've expanded from 20 people to 135
And just this past year
Embedded systems engineer
Senior controls engineer in HMI / ux engineer a manufacturing engineer
That's a lot of different kinds of Engineers
Yes
Define people qualify for some of those positions Jeff says he hires like
People who just barely missed the cut to become astronauts
Aeronautics geniuses
That's why he uses ZipRecruiter
It looks futuristic too
Aesthetically aesthetically
So it just seems to be
Very easy to Monitor and read and track all the activity
Also tracks
How many people have used the job
So it's pretty good times and metrics that way
Check to see if someone time for me
Whether you need to hire an accountant or an astronaut
ZipRecruiter is powerful matching technology will find you candidates to help your business take off
Try for free at ziprecruiter.com cereal
Ziprecruiter.com cereal
ZipRecruiter the smartest way to hire
Support for serial comes from Squarespace
Make your business official with Google in Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and a Business website with Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and professional tools from Google
It's the simplest way to look professional online
Visit squarespace.com Google to start your free trial
And use offer code professional
For a discount on your first purchase
Google and Squarespace
Make it professional make it beautiful
I have to think back now
To access a more innocent time around 18 months ago
When I was still incredulous
Give me a second
There it is
How could the government take a teenager
An unrepresented teenager
Persuade him to do the thing almost Nobody Does the thing law enforcement has been desperate for someone to step up and do
Cooperate
Get him to generously spin through his heartless felons Rolodex
Then put him on the witness stand not once but twice
Then put it back in juvenile prisons patch pretty tightly with heartless felon
Offer parting handshake and a general note to behave himself
Remember that syo hanging over your head
And I'll get that same government then sit back and watch him get jumped
Again and again and again
How do they call an ambulance
To take him to the hospital
A month later according to Joshua
Arrange transportation to a couple of neurologist
Directions to the brain bleeds he said he was diagnosed
Oh and then that other check for CAT scan
How could all that have happened
And be happening
And yet I couldn't hear anyone aside from Joshua raising an alarm
Considered
Does anyone in my position would
There's probably more to the story that I'm not seeing
I set out to fact-check Joshua
Begin with Miss Turner
Shayla Turner
Jimena literacy and Social Action Program inside Indian River and Cuyahoga Hills
Call Freedom School
It's a curriculum design by the children's defense fund
Joshua says Freedom School was by far the best thing that happened to him inside odys
I changed his whole demeanor he said
Permit enraged suspicious scholar
Young man who is beginning to recognize his feelings and manage them
Every time I got mad she asked me why
Was the first time somebody actually ever sat down and listen to me vent
I tried to coach me
Work with me
Joshua stayed in the program for two years
Longer than anyone else
When the program lost funding Miss Turner positioned herself as Joshua's mentor
Kept in touch
I asked Miss Turner about Joshua's version the pizza incident
Because I figured she knows him well she seen his worst and best behavior
I figured she'd know whether he was exaggerated
Weatherguard really have handcuff Joshua
Are there more or less allowed more kids to assault him
I'm hearing stuff like
Canal
The guard put handcuffs on them
Yes that is absolutely real in the way that I verify that is just
When asking to be able to see the footage
And their inability to do that only reason I know any of information about it is because
They called me to calm Joshua down
Are they called you yes so the facility called me with Joshua tomorrow
Kevin Thomas mentor
To calm him down and that is the most angry I've ever heard him I can hear him crying
And I couldn't even manage that myself
I told him I needed to see him I said to talk to him in person and we went to go see him
And that's when I saw the bruises
And the beating
That's was very strong
He's a fighter this is what got him into like this
This is something that
Straight comfortable answer to see him
That bad and be able to talk to him and find out what happened
It was horrible and then the guard was fired afterwards
The car wouldn't have been fired at the car when they've been in the wrong
I eventually got the Personnel records for this guard
He was fired
The later through a settlement with the Union
He was allowed to resign along with a pledge to never again working odys
The guard wasn't sanction for Joshua getting jumped
Who sanctioned because of the pizza
Did minute to taking 20 bucks from one of the kids
And using it to buy them Pizza
It's against the rules
It seems like
Every time he's telling me a story I'm just like it feels like inside of there
Certainly Cuyahoga Hills but also to return extended Indian River that it's just
Chaos
It is absolute chaos
A little chaos
And that the kids seem in charge
Or is that not true
I would absolutely agree with that
Yes and I want to resume our program was so beneficial because the children were outside with the program
If we were to have relied on just the staff I would not have failsafe
So the children
I wanted to speak to other kids who didn't odys
Juneau weather Joshua situation was real and whether it was common knowledge
It was me it was crazy I don't know
Is that
This is Malik he's 18
Music Cuyahoga Hills with Joshua
He's an adult prison now
Blake said he saw Joshua get jumped multiple times
I feel bad for me
I got Malik name from a former staff member
It suggested he might be a good person to talk to you about what life was like at Cuyahoga Hills
She giving me a couple of names of remarkably Frank former ody us kids
She didn't know Joshua and she definitely didn't know that Malik is actually Joshua's cousin
If you overlay Cleveland and odys you see a lot of coincidence
Just like this
It's a pretty small world
Malik told me Joshua had it worse than anyone he'd seen come through Cuyahoga Hills
He said he himself had been high up in the heartless felons when all this was going on
He loves his cousin
They stuck up for him
So I went in and did Shannon like
He had words with a couple of the guys he said ask them to cool it
Did you personally get any blowback of Life why are you friends
Scatter yru
Heartless felons started to turn against Malik
Sergeant steel from him he said
One night when he was sleeping someone hit a leak in the face with a combination lock
Between the eyebrows
You need stitches
I talked to another guy named Leo from Toledo
Who did at Cuyahoga Hills at the same time as Joshua
Remember the assault in the school
When Joshua woke up in the ambulance
Somebody laughing hard
Copt means hit
It was a big dog opossum
He went to sleep but he hit his face on the concrete wall
Caesar
My whole face is swollen and had went to the hospital for that
Leah said it was because where it had gone around Cuyahoga Hills the Joshua with a snitch
She was giving a prison staff information about the heartless felons
Family
Yeah
You know a lot of stuff about the time and he was just telling her a lot
He was on
Trying to get a better 10% or something
Getting a lot of people asking about his name
Okay
When you heard like all the others guys a snack or did you have any feeling about that personally one way or another
It's what he deserves
I was heavily involved in there
You were
Snitching on me
Okay
So you did you know this like this hit on him was going to happen or no
Yeah I know
Are you now okay can I ask you did you order it
I like talking to the man who ordered it
Yeah
At the time Leo said he was in charge of a section of the gang called YF
Young felons
So he called the hit on Joshua
Coincidence
He later become The Godfather
Joshua said he wasn't telling on the heartless felons at Cuyahoga Hills
But they were conflating his past cooperation
The present
Regardless
Leo said he was mostly hearing about Joshua
From the guards
Black Panther
I found out that he was on snitching
For telling you about him
In Cuyahoga Hills a kite is how you get a message to the office
Operation
And Annika superintendent
Staff was informing on Joshua Leo says to the most dangerous people in the prison
Him
Leo
And his guys
I spoke to a couple of other former and current odys units from different facilities
I also spoke to current and former guards
Not disgruntled
People who like their jobs
Also current and former odys Social Work
Mostly adults Pokemon background for fear of retaliation
What they described
Remind me of a black market
Is it the juvenile prisons have their own Subterranean economy
Sucking in both Youth and staff who trade-in favors power and also cash
Of course I know corruption exists and I know juvenile prisons in particular are prone to bullying in Tamil
But this was a system recently out from under consent decree
Metamorphosed
Ohio model
Who stated mission is not to punish but to habilitate Youth and Empower families and communities
Cuyahoga Hills has won a national award for how it treats the children in its care twice
And yet
Well I'm just going to run through some of what I learned
Take contraband
I interviewed a former guard
Edward Kennedy
Is the only guard who agreed to go on the record
Possibly because he's got nothing to lose
He lost his job already after he was charged with domestic
Silence
When we talked he was actually in prison
As a prisoner
Before that he worked the other side
Azaguard
The Cuyahoga Hills
They called him why Isis and odys
OSU special
Edward said guards bringing in contraband
Yes
Everybody knew about it
The guy worked on one of the most unruly units Edward said
When he was on duty
Everyone was curiously chill
Edward said that guard ended up getting fired
Edward said he himself didn't bring anything in like that but he said kids did ask him to
We'll keep the unit under control if you bring in a cell phone
Are some weed
A lot of feels on hand a suggestion I deal with on this phone that type of situation
That's Malik Joshua's cousin
And quite the businessman
Who's bringing stuff into the North and South buildings he said with the help of guards
Two or three at any one time he said
They go pick up stuff from his people on the outside
Bring it back into Malik
Sell it
And for the guards this wasn't just about keeping the units calm
Was about making money
Lakewood pay them
And how much were they getting
Maybe it depends
707 interior
Oh my God that's funny
Oh my God how much does a cell phone go for it
So there's that much money moving around in there
The heartless felons
They're also called the family or the fam
Which is another meaning
Forever about money
Leo the former GF told me they take it seriously
You got to move product
Malik estimated there was anywhere from 7 to $10,000 in cash circulating at Cuyahoga Hills at any one time
Muscat sending money home sometimes through visitation by the time Malik left he said he'd sent home about 2500
Dollars and had about 900 on hand
The commodity running alongside and sometimes feeding into the Contraband Market
Is violence
Three guards I talked to one current to former the guards feel hamstrung sometimes
Because some of their best tools for controlling the kids were taken away by reforms
Certain physical restraint
Seclusion
I could even put kids to bed at 7 p.m. anymore could make them keep their hands behind their back
The kids can be violent the guards are outnumbered
You can't count on Swift backup from operations
There's a fight or riot
So yeah the guards will sometimes provoke kids
Tom Thumb or insult them
So that the kid will respond in kind
And then the guard has an excuse to shut them in their rooms and not have to deal with them
I talked to a former social worker named Casey hotels
I told me she saw that kind of thing a lot
Casey worked at the Cuyahoga County Detention Center
The therapist until last summer
The Detention Center isn't technically odys
But there's a lot of cross-pollination with odys
Especially with Cuyahoga Hills
Terms of staff and kids
And gang culture
Stafford Sharon's and
Show the doorway of their room. Do something do something do something
When you come out like when they're in their transition so they're locked up in their rooms over you come out like I want to see you I see you do that
North another site happens you can lock down the whole unit and then you just sit in the Bay Area for the stripper
Watch TV
And you would see stuff like that
Yeah
Casey tell me a story about two kids who fought
And then when the loser of the fight was being a pain in this one guards ass
The guard asked the winner of the fight to go after the kid
A second time
He offered
Scott use
Extra commissary
Shoe
No
Incidents like this
Stop orchestrating youth on youth attack
Everyone I spoke to from Odyssey
It's common
Edward the former Cuyahoga Hills guard said
Yeah girl formal relationship with the highest-ranking gang member
Ross the strongest youth on the unit
And use that kid to keep the rest of the kids in line
Did you ever experience that were a guard said to you
Like can you go take care of
Sound so or called a hit on
Stephen Shore
Getting off to take care of
We're going to take care of y'all
Wait who is taking care of who
If you don't take care of whatever you need whatever you want and we going to get it
If you did what
And why were they wanting you to be honest
I mean
Disrespectful
Whatever
And what would you do
Return
Funny whatever I wanted
The final thing I'll mention
Sex
Sexual assault or attempted sexual assault
And also
Sex
Does Leo and Malik said they had sex with multiple female guards
Who are in their 20s and 30s
A Cuyahoga Hills
Before Joshua was transferred to Cuyahoga Hills back when he was
Is doing okay at Indian River he was swimming along in this corrupt Water 2
Taking advantage of it he could get anything in there he said
P*** weed lighters
Tequila
He said he never jumped anyone for money but he did operate as a middleman
Gardner Pam maybe $20 maybe 42 arranged hits on certain kids
Joshua said sometimes the hits were in retaliation for something violent a youth had done to a guard
Maybe the kids through pee on them or attacked a female
The guards aren't supposed to strike back so they use the kids are proxies
Right
Flight
I don't know man flight
Many people I spoke to about odys they didn't explanatory wall like this
Detect
You just
You have to see it you have to
I can't
Joshua's best effort I thought was when he explained it as a kind of madman's vacation
Vacation
Vacation for the youths uninor vacation for the garden
Slither going to wait for you to come in and get
Any of this I'm going to be a totally
Squeaky clean
Just do my time card and not get pulled into anything is it possible to exist like that
Or something
Yeah
Youths guards
Social workers
They all told me
Forget to quote-unquote succeed at odys
To get help stay out of trouble and get back out
You need a rare rare confluence
Havelock grit and influence
I spoke to for social workers who are two different odys facilities
Their experiences span 2012 to 2018 they all said there were plenty of people who wanted to help
The kids to advocate for them but there was no way
When former Indian River guard told me
Everything was Hush
Hush hush
The social worker said they were discouraged from Raising problems or calling out cruelties guards who added kid to sex
Defender say or look the other way when a child got jumped
The social worker said there was a strong no snitching culture
Among the staff
A couple of them told me it was made clear to them they might not be protected if they were to be assaulted on the units
One person tell me the clinical notes she was writing her kids files
Airports that had to go to the courts every 6 months
We're being edited by another staff member
Tell her boss put a stop to it
When she went to look back at a note she put in one kid's file describing a salts on him that appear to have been facilitated by staff
Her documentation was missing entirely
Several social workers told me that they started to lose their own sense of what was normal what was ethical
It felt like the kids had no protection from abuse or from coercion
I've been trying to stop it they'd help the kids navigate it
One told me there was nothing I could do
Another told me
I mean I just have to be realistic about it to pretend like they were getting rehabilitated was foolish I tell the kids all the
The time the system is not designed to help you
Georgia Cuyahoga Hills
National award winner had a mask on she said
Every story I heard about odys every allegation from Houston staff current and former
We're at it by odys again they didn't comment on anything specific but they gave us this statement
Whenever there are allegations of misconduct we swiftly investigate and take appropriate action they wrote
Dys has increased programming security and supports
Deserve the most challenging youth in the state who have lengthy criminal histories and often have gang affiliations that they bring into the
Facilities
January of 2017
Joshua went back to Indian River
This time they didn't keep him on one of the heartless felon yunnan
A alpha B Bravo an end November
Instead they put them on D Delta
Delta was the closest thing Indian River had to protective custody
Mix of kids from Columbus to Cincinnati Youngstown
A few clevelanders
When I first started talking to Joshua that's where he was
D Delta
On unit restrict
Meaning he couldn't go to the normal places in the facility
Okay the teacher comes to you
I can't go to school
All the time like now
I can't go to the school to the cafeteria
How long is that been going on that you're not leaving the unit
It's been like that
It was now mid May
5 months of unit restriction
For Joshua's own protection
He felt safe fish on his unit
He said he was cool with most everybody Indie Delta
His hopes were set on early release
And then who knows maybe a lawsuit but
Early release was the main thing he wanted
I talked to Joshua every couple of days
Sometimes everyday
Early on he started describing what sounded like
An uptick in the usual chaos
Catholic holidays
Crazy
What do you mean
Like a whole nother
He said about 15 kids from a alpha heartless felons unit
Had yanked the door open and stormed the kids on D Delta trying to conquer
Are there unit basically
Because their unit wasn't joining HF wasn't submitting to HF
Do Delta was more HB
Headbusters
Rival gang
Do Delta had kids from Columbus and Cincinnati
Kids from those places if they're in a gang they tend to BHB
That was most of the tension and then persona non Joshua was on detail tattoo
The distress dispatches kept coming
His unit had been rushed on their way to school
Doesn't the kids swarming at them from across the yard
Stop heard them back inside before anyone is hurt but it's really scary
Evan another riot
The time on a alpha
It's in stop attack of Youth in his room
There's so many people walking around here in my unit with black eyes and stuff piece
We just got two new dudes on our unit dude from Toledo they jumped him twice in one day
A dude from Cleveland
Azusa Cleveland
Sometimes in the Carl's Joshua sounding jangled
He said he couldn't take it anymore
Too much stress on me
I don't want to go to this forever
I would like
In early July Joshua's unit was put on aov protocol
Act of violence protocol
Turn up like lockdown
7 p.m. bedtime
Meanwhile he said the heartless felons were larking around
TV and video games all day
Getting to go outside
Indoor Nike shoes jogging pants
Watches
His unit Allstate issue stuff
Stuck inside watching the heartless felons the aggressors
Through the Windows
An Indian River guard I spoke to confirm
Yes they had been putting some units on aov protocol lately
But b-bravo the unit where the heartless felon leaders are
Too dangerous
Yeah this guard said
They won't even try
Who said his unit
United
They discussed it
This isn't fair we're not safe
The staff isn't protecting us
It feels like the superintendent is siding with the heartless felons
Protecting them
And we're the ones being punished
For fighting back
They all rode up grievances
Which they sent to the odys central office
Stir in three letters
Are you home are you in Spanish
Said that we don't feel safe
Nobody
Words that whose idea was to do this
This is ma
Activism
Look at that
Respectful to whom it may concern activism
WhatsApp member didn't Riverhead help Joshua with a
You should send the package
Did you go to Columbus
In care of Julie walburn
Assistant director of odys
Joshua didn't know who Julie walburn was
But the judges down in juvenile court in Cleveland.
Including Joshua's judge
Kristen Sweeney
Who's also the administrative judge for the juvenile court
Here's how she described Julie walburn to me
Stage
Drenching spring rain after
Months of drought
Julie walburn had come to work at odys that April
A month before I started talking to Joshua
And he start describing the Mayhem in Indian River
Auburn had come to a recent meeting of juvenile judges
In Cuyahoga County
And she said
We know about the violence and the world breaking we're going to fix it
Text Sweeney Todd
Finally
How long has it been that I have
Like the end
Petition is sort of not taking some of the
The violence seriously
Probably at least for 5 years
At least four or five years
That's in the post consent decree post reform era of odys
One of Jake Sweeney's colleagues judge Denise Rini
Choose Malek's judge
Give me the backstory of how the spring rain came to be
She got the case back in December
Accident Indian River
Heartless felon
Inside his case File or pictures
Heritage meaning
And I'm looking at all these photographs in their photographs of
You smoking marijuana
What weight I have
Judge Rini keeps the case folder on her desk
Remind her she explained
Power failing these use
When we let heartless felons run the facility
Instead of the adults
We look through the stack of photos together
From inside
There are definitely smoking
Diwali smoking listening to
Give me an iPod sign that
Gang signs
Why don't know from gang signs but
I assume that's what that is
So then money
Holding up
Wad of money
Where was he posting from inside
Oh really
The kid had a cell phone and an Instagram account where he was posting these photos
So just be nice all these images and December of 2016
She flipped her lid
The impunity
The message they're sending to other kids go to anyway us smoke weed make money kick it with your friends
Good rainy sits on the state judges committee for juvenile law and procedure
Can I just
Sent them to all of the members
So they started calling odys and saying this is unacceptable
In January
Officials from odys came to a judge's meeting
And they were trying to explain why this was occurring
And
I was
Visibly distraught to say the least we're done Floyd put her hand on my arm and said
Where cuz what was the explanation like how do you say it was an isolated incident I'm like he is 37
1 Pages how isolated is this we you know I'm in the facility everyday and you know this doesn't really
Only happened on my
It's on Instagram what do you mean it doesn't happen so they were basically just kind of like
Whitewashing it
My biggest issue was you are not helping our community you take these Youth and you put them in here and they come out in there
And then you know actually they've no tray there no vacation
And they have no ability to act appropriately
So what what are we doing besides housing now
Anna in a facility where we're not teaching them anything
A few months after that meeting the assistant director of odys abruptly resigned
And Julie walburn took her place
As soon as she came on board she walked through the according to her she walks are all the facilities
She met with all of the the
Heads of each facility
And she said
And we're going to take back the facilities and we are going to ensure that the Jews are not only safe because there was a lot of fighting
But the ones that are the Bad actors are going to be removed
In mid-june
Joshua told me that the superintendent of Indian River
I gather the syo
The kids who had adult time attached to their sentences
I could kick in if they didn't do well in juvenile
Odys hadn't been invoking Goose adult sentences
But now the superintendent told them
New sheriff in town
We now have a zero-tolerance policy for syo
Any infraction
Doesn't even have to be violent
We can seek a bind over
You are now on notice
Behave yourselves
Late July
Another call
Joshua told me
He just found out
Had a court date
This is tomorrow
Tomorrow
Yeah
Why would you have any court dates
Why would you have a court date coming up
Oh you're kidding
They trying to say that
Pest Control New York
Stuff like that
I told Joshua I couldn't imagine anything drastic was going to happen
How could it
The system knew his situation
The Joshua wasn't hearing that
I don't know what to do like
Hospital
Worry
Crazy
Look at 18 years life though
If Joshua got bound over
That was the adult sentence he was looking at
18 years
That was his syo
Joshua wasn't going to the court date tomorrow
But I could go
And watch the adults
Figure out where Joshua belongs
That's next time on our final episode this season
Cereal
Series produced by Julie Schneider
Emmanuel Church event Calhoun Ami with additional reporting by Eataly uskoski editing on this episode from
Updike Whitney Dangerfield is our digital editor research and fact-checking by Ben Phelan
Sound designer mix by Stone Nelson
Music clearance by Anthony Roman sethland is our director of operations
0 staff includes Emily Condon Julie Whitaker Cassie Halle Francis Swanson and Matt Tierney music is by
Adam Dorn and Hal willner with additional music from Matt McGinley and Nick thorburn are theme song is also
Mixed by Adam Doran special thanks for this episode to Alphonse gerhardstein Kimberly jumps Amma Mata head of the
Cuyahoga County Public Defender's juvenile division Abe hamaday
Gabriella Celeste Laura Austin and Brooke Burns the animation and illustration on our website was done by the
How much A Team Ed Moss Studio thanks to Dave Prosser Daniel Chester Marie Margot security scan out of it
Luke Doyle I for Ashton and Hinata Garcia
You can check out their work at our website serial podcast. Org
That serial podcast. Org
We can also sign up for our email newsletter and be notified when new episodes are released
Support for serial comes from ZipRecruiter
Unlike many jobs ZipRecruiter doesn't wait for candidates to find you
ZipRecruiter find some for you
So you get qualified candidates fast
Try it free at ziprecruiter.com cereal that ziprecruiter.com cereal
Support for serial comes from Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and Business website with Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and professional tools from Google
Use offer code professional for discount on your first purchase