Support for serial comes from ATT
The number one smart home security provider
With a team of 18000 employees dedicated to safeguarding your home
With connection to First Responders
Offering Custom Design Systems including doorbells indoor and outdoor cameras and smart locks and lights
All control from the ADT app or the sound of your voice
And all back
Buy 24/7 protect
Visit att.com podcast
To learn more
Previously
I'm cereal
Gentlemanly is a good where he is very much a gentleman
Do you think he's lying
And then all the sudden he shows up in his uniform
Where can I find WBEZ Chicago its serial one story told week by week I'm sorry.
I think the following will likely be a question I pose court-martial
Did the Army screw up
By accepting Bow by deploying him to Afghanistan
Just remind you but was separated from the Coast Guard
In 2006
After he became overwhelmed and had a breakdown during basic training
The Army in order to enlist him 2 years later
Would have to waive its usual standard
It's what you did
So the question actually is did the Army Recruiting process work like it was supposed to
Separation from the Coast Guard wasn't labeled a psych discharge on paper
But that's essentially what it was
So did the Army miss something
We talked to a retired army psychiatrist
Dr. elspeth Cameron Ritchie
Who's deployed all over to his chief of forensic psychiatry and also of inpatient Psychiatry at Walter Reed
And she was Psychiatry consultant to the Army Surgeon General
The top mental health advocacy position in the army
Dr. Ritchie's assessment of how all this went down with bow
She got the whole thing sounded pretty normal
Like standard practice
Attack of the army didn't have all the details about bows hospitalization in the Coast Guard
Not uncommon
She said getting access to more detailed medical information especially between branches of the military
Coast Guard and army was hard because the military's Network system wasn't so hot
Information sharing was incomplete
But she also didn't feel like anything we told her about those Coast Guard situation would have been disqualifying
Even if the Army had known
Had sent him for a mental health evaluation as the Coast Guard doctor recommended
Even if o had been assessed by saying Army psychiatrist dr. Ritchie said it probably would have been one session
And unless you showed obvious outward signs of psychosis or something like that
You're really depending on the potential recruit to self-report any psychological problems
So it's quite possible but would have been okayed regardless
At the end of the day doctor what she told us
The best assessment for weather someone's going to make it in the Army doesn't happen in the recruitment office anyway
What happens during the sustained high pressure test of basic training
And bow did really well in Army basic
That's one View
Now for a second opinion
Tumblr
The ball is dropped
This is dr. Michael valdovinos
He's a clinical psychologist
Is in the Air Force for about seven and a half years
Any worked in the Seer program which teaches survival evasion resistance and Escape
He knows Bo
Has led this year psych team
It helps reintegrate Bell right after his rescue
Those first few weeks when bow is at the hospital in Germany
Two things
Jalapenos has permission from bow to talk to me about their conversations
And also he was not officially Bose doctor
The job was to reintegrate them not diagnosing or anything
He never even saw both medical record back
He's not breaking any doctor patient confidentiality
All three things I guess the last being both of you knows cares about bow
Who's not just passionate on the question of what happens to him
Is that the Army recruiter should have looked harder at both situation should have asked more questions before
Signing him up
Even if the recruiter didn't have the particulars of Bose Coast Guard discharge in front of them
Or information about Bose hospitalization
He says the mere fact that Billy been separated at all from a branch of the military begged more scrutiny
Medieval bit more concerned about that
What is taking it may be a few steps further to say hey
Because what is separation like most house you just on its face
Is it for whatever reason this person couldn't hack it in basic training
Any Army recruiter's job is to send that potential recruit straight back into basic training
In both cases the same situation he washed out of two years earlier
Finally told him
At the recruiter did know about his problems in the Coast Guard
Because Beau says he told the recruiter
Who said he was afraid not to
Time since you know not a good idea to keep things from the government
No one that is
So you broke down training and
What's a hospital
As part of his application bow did a test
That he had not consulted with a behavioral health care provider in the last 7 years
General doll ask him about that
Listen to Coast Guard treatment wouldn't have triggered the idea of Consulting a psychologist
I found that to be consistent with those other paper
Since I'm his medical history form bochek yes to the question of whether he'd ever received Counseling of any type
He said he was thinking of canceling he had when he was 10 years old
General. Concluded that the Army recruiter
On paper
Did everything he was supposed
Read the codes all the regulations
Put in a footnote
Y'all seem to agree that this system isn't good enough
Situation probably should have been looked at more carefully
He wrote that when you're deciding whether to reenlist someone
Few things are more relevant than a prior separation
Seattle quotes it seems inadequate that we would rely on an interview an applicant statement
Explain the details of prior service
And not review the separation action
Where was bows head at the
This time
It's funny once you hear how both thought about the military
Why you want to join
Probably it does help explain why he decided to walk off his post
Did you did you
Think that you were going to be a career Soldier
Set my mind to get lost
World War
Yeah I wanted to be a samurai Soldier
Right
I wanted to be
I love the idea of just
Basically your hands and that's it
Bruce Lee when he was a kid
Private school
You watched his movies later read his books Asian Warriors especially Samurai he learned about the Bushido code
Which stresses honor and loyalty and self-sacrifice
Campbell's childhood bedroom his dad kept a collector set of old army manuals way up high in the bookshelf that is deadly
Love military history
Climbed up there and got the books down
He couldn't read it study the pictures
So
But I only option I had was to be
Those ideal Soldier the one from history
Fights for a cause he or she is completely personally committed to
That Soldier rallies behind military leaders
That he or she trusts
The modern Soldier turns out to have no choice about those essential aspects of combat
Instead
He's a brainless private that does whatever the government tells him to do
Come here go there go fight these people
He's just a tool
That's how Bo sauce
I knew this was going to be the case when he signed up
I sort of knew it
He thought he could handle that Gulf of meaning
And I was hoping that I had to deal with everyday
It's like an hour to play the game you have to play by the rules as they were
Being as they were busy
This is one of the things about Bo
He wants recognizes that his expectations are unrealistic
He sees things differently from other people
But at the same time he will fiercely defend his vision of how things should be
He does not let go
Especially when it comes to what he saw in Afghanistan
Do you think
What you witnessed and what you were reacting to
Was
The Army in an especially bad way
Or
Was it just the army
Meaning of self and kind of
Messed up as it you know in a kind of average weather
That make any sense
Normal
Maybe what I was looking at was
Everyday Army however
Welding leads
Regular
What I was looking at was problems when I was looking at was
SimpliSafe
Marx conclusion about Bell
After all those months
Talking to him
He's not a conscientious
But he's also not your casual deserter he throws up his hands and just says don't care about any of this out of here
Mark thinks he's the opposite of that
He's a rare person who will act
Rightly or wrongly it turns out but still he will act according to his principal
And his principles are wrapped up with the very institution that so many people now feel he betrayed
The disillusionment of somebody that really believes in the army
Be somebody that
Things that military leadership
Is a
The sacred position
He wants the Army to be better
The military is huge for him right in here and resented something
There's got to be a better word than huge but it represented something
Very powerful to him
Even before he joined
And
His sense of himself as a man
To his
Relationship to
Country to all sorts of
Big identity questions that were floating around for him
And it's still really important to him
He still kind of want his
Day of Reckoning with those values
In a way why he hasn't taken the more
Future all this which would just beat us her to stick your hands out and Save
Whatever you guys say I like
Guilty gif
Get me out of here
I think he doesn't want to cross the line
I'm saying I had no point
Which is not to say that Beau wants all this
The tension on a MAO
He wasn't speaking this big an audience
And by the way he's not asking to be some kind of like Paul Revere he just wanted he didn't
Phone never wanted
The discussion is happening now write his whole goal was to talk to
Looks like it's inter-family dispute he wanted to talk to people in the military
Yeah
There was actually reporter that was sent to
It was like embedded or something with his unit that was hanging around there and it's like he pulled the reporter aside and
Sad hey
Get loaded ass this will make a great story
You didn't do that he wanted to be heard within the military so
Obviously that didn't happen and obviously he behaved in a way which runs counter to like every single
Military precept ever known since the dawn of time which is he now you don't
You don't walk away from your from your brother so he's not a great messenger for his mess
But
I'm walking off like you did
Is it so unthinkable
Did start to see signs that Bo wasn't totally okay
At the September Hearing in Bose case
Greg Leatherman Bose weapons squad leader
Testified that at some point he noticed something was up
It started to kind of feel that he wasn't adjusting to the deployment like the rest of the guys were
Leatherman said he wasn't incredibly alarm
But he figures he got to say something to one of the higher-ups about it just in case
When did he's on a patrol somewhere southeast of Toronto
He finds himself sitting next to his first sergeant Pablo Jimenez
And so I told for sergeant that you know I thought that Sergeant Bergdahl should chat with somebody
You know whether be combat stress or a chaplain or even if it were just you know the company Commander just sit down and
Hey man how's everything going
Buzz lawyer a Slenderman how him and his responded to his seat
I'm just going to redo that part of the transcript
Answer
First sergeant said that he didn't want to he didn't want one of his guys to tell him what was wrong and his company
That was not my place to tell him if he had problems inside of his company
Question
I think when we interviewed you you had even more colorful language of what he said
Yes sir
Could you tell us that
Sure
He said f*** off
He said shut the f******
No one needs to hear what a f****** E5 has to say about a guy in my company
And I said
Rodger for sergeant
News report General Dollar includes a statement from Jimenez who says he doesn't recall this conversation with Letterman or n
Any conversation like that
Show no red flags or emotional problems as far as I could tell
Uncle
Whose friend said from his messages and letters home
I could tell he wasn't very happy with how things were going in Afghanistan
In retrospect you can sort of see his thoughts churning
Plans farming
On June 27th just three days before Bowl left mask
He wrote a letter to his parents
Venting and when she sounded pretty disgusted with how the Army was operating in Afghanistan
Give me the more loving letter to a girl he was romantically involved with
Group emails
When was titled who is John Galt
His friend Chad was on that email
I saw that was like
Hydrangea
Okay here we go
John Galt is a character from Atlas Shrugged
Very first line of the book who is John Galt
And after it's about a thousand pages
Finally learned that John Galt is this genius industrialist who said have single-handedly has shutdown the world economy
In order to fix it
He stops the machine
In the book he finally reveals himself delivering I kid you not 60 page speech laying out his
Awesome me
I rather Ayn rand's philosophy
And honestly just as an exercise you can grab almost any sentence from that John Galt
And apply it to what both ended up doing
Princeton
Call a code of values accepted by choice is a code of morality unquote
And now it just for kicks
Stirring save the Bushido code
The part that teaches that it's your duty to try to write a moral wrong
Regardless of whether you'll succeed
That's maybe a potent cocktail if your bow
Here's a text to BOS June 27th email
It is not the being of value who fails the
The system is the system that has failed the man
Her man should not stoop
To fit the system
But the system should be made and remade to fit the man who holds value as worth
I will serve no Bandon or liar
For I know John Galt and understand
This life is too short to serve those who compromise value and it's
FX
I am done compromising
His friend Nick read that email
Along with everyone else
What uses like
Or did you think like
Like
Sorting through a bimbo
Yeah this is the other kinds of things
He would say
Kim Harrison was on those emails to
And I've gotten other messages from bow and she was starting to worry
She said she could tell he was frustrated
The situation was dangerous
But he's trying to hold himself together
Here's a series writing these things is not sending email to sending all these cryptic things he's
In the State of Mind was obvious to me
What a mentally where he was at it was
Stretch
He was on that press
Gaming Warehouse
A person can make bad choices
Like really bad choices
I don't think
You know it's not suicidal or that kind of
And all it was just
He's frustrated he's on edge
And not really
Completely logical in his right mind
But is this what you
Understood at the time that you're using this in hindsight Avenue talk to him
Not really clear
Yeah
A few days later some army people show up at her door
Turbo is missing
Just a day or two after that
Boxer
Trumbo
He said it from Afghanistan
What is computer his iPod is Kindle a journal
And a copy of Atlas Shrugged
It's been pretty widely reported that a Bose military hearing
His lawyer said this carefully phrase but also somewhat vague thing regarding bows mental
Health
He said a quote neutral Army Psychiatry board has now concluded that back in June 2009
That Sergeant Bergdahl possessed a severe mental disease or defect
This past week I finally found out what he meant by
In May of last year but his defense team asked for what's called a 706 sanity
Mental health assessment
Connection with the charges against Bell
An army forensic psychiatrist a well-regarded doctor named Christopher Lang
Met with phone and give a diagnosis
Schizotypal personality disorder
Reset both would have had as of
The time of the alleged
I'm guessing this too will be part of both defense at the court-martial
Receding
Docker valdovinos this year psychologist who knows Bo
Said that when he heard this diagnosis he thought
Yeah
I think they hit the nail on the head
What's going on
Elementary his teenage years
Ilili duck tell the story of the above unfortunately
Again OGE valdovinos permission to talk about the
Describe the basic character
Diagnosed with
Black Horse Friends
Stay
Recording
External events have personal meaning to them
Peculiar ways for the century
Perceptual alterations
Assisted Living
Can I watch Bravo
Really struggled with
Those grand ideas about his future about his capabilities the Romantic Adventures he wanted to make happen
Baldinos says those all fit the profile
He said for anyone with a psychiatric illness like this
Symptoms tend to get worse when you're under stress
What are the major symptoms
Is paranoia
And the potential to misinterpret situations
Amolatina says it's not a stretch to say that's probably what happened when bow is deployed to Afghanistan
Where is actually dangerous
Obviously stressful
Who's not super tight with the guys in his unit
He starts to think his
Battalion Commander is against them
Might even send them on a suicide mission
Which is very paranoid thinking
And that all leads to a decision that isn't
Well entirely sane
I'll buy that point I think the paranoias at all
How to push him over the edge
He said I'm doing it
When you start thinking about the idea of him being Jason Bourne and
Still having pain doing Special Operations
Going to going
And then bring the hell
Not really thinking through the ramifications of walking off a bass into
Basically until the Taliban
Absolutely
Frustrated with the army
There's still something I think biologically that's going to keep us from
And I literally blocking off of
I just self-preservation at that point when taking back
You know I fell for him
Thank you likewise
Notepad
When you look at the whole total picture it starts
Alexa
Volcanoes things that would happen with bow at the Coast Guard what happened in Afghanistan
Is all the peace
The Army knows about this diagnosis
At the September hearing the Army prosecutor
Major Margaret kurz
Give a preview of the Army's thinking on the subject
One of the key points from the psychiatrist doctor Lang's report
Set in 2009 at the time of the alleged criminal misconduct the accused was able to appreciate
She ate the nature and quality and wrongfulness of his conduct unquote
Another words mental illness
Who should be held responsible for his actions
The other day I checked back in with Mark to see if the diagnosis made him think differently about anything
I guess it's it it's an interesting
Datapoint I don't know that it's the
Northstar
Of the story
Mark feels like he already knew walking off was not a rational thing to do
So putting a label on Bose way of thinking didn't really change much more
I told Mark that for me the diagnosis made me let go of any lingering doubts I had about the truthfulness of Bowser
Like all the details that didn't add up
Well yeah if you're paranoid and doing some magical thinking
Corset
It makes me believe in
He really was in his mind trying to raise an alarm
Mark already believes
So aside from a legal defense Mark wasn't sure the diagnosis made much of
Any worried in fact that once they heard the diagnosis
People
Maybe people like me
Would disregard everything but was saying about his military experience
I do think that
For you the diagnosis
It makes him more credible to you but it also
Means you take him less seriously
I think
As a as a
A kid with opinions you know
Has like an American soldier with a
Opinions
No I don't think that's correct I think that I think his Assessments in a general way
Of like the
Like I think we can all agree like the war in Afghanistan has not been a success right I guess I'm more think he was kind of right
By accident right
What is that mean right by accident
Like he sort of happens to be rich but not
He's not specifically right in the particular instances he's
That's really giving us examples of
The overall failure
But he's responding to real data points right I mean he's not thinking that stuff just from his
From his cat log cabin in Idaho
I guess but if I mean again I know we've we survived argued about on them before but I feel like
You know
His beef with Amna remember isn't like we never should have gone up there in the first place we never shut you know what I mean his beef really
At the end of the day has biggest complaint
Is this feeling of
R Commander doesn't care about our welfare
Yeah that it was to the point where he was maybe going to send us on a suicide mission to get rid of us because we
We are bad for his
Butaton
Yeah right like that's not
No I mean there's a lot of different judgments that that are stacked on top of each other and the last one is
Is is
Just deeply paranoid and
You can reject it on its face I don't think there's a
Commander of the US
Armed Forces who is
Do anything remotely like what both adjust
Okay so I just think it's just
But the other but the judgments that precede that
That
Maybe this Commander
Has other priorities in a
It besides
Purely the welfare of his soldiers I think that's clearly on the face of it true because he they did
Put American lives at risk to retrieve equipment
And that is part of the calculation of Warren you can talk to people and
Up and down the chain of command and I'll sell ya s*** like that happens all the time where you weigh
Someone's life
Against a piece of equipment
And that maybe a
An everyday calculation but that doesn't make it any less
F***** up especially if you're the kid that is
Whose life is being weighed to get the equipment back
Here's where Mark and I die virgin
He links Bose personal experience more directly to
The problems of the world than I do
He wants to be careful to separate what bows saying
From who Bo is
In a case like this though that's the rub
Moxie's.
Why I keep going back to
Tip something that somebody sent me a long time ago which is like I kind of agree with everything you said but I still want to punch him in the face
You know
It's like that line from The Big Lebowski
You're not wrong Walter
You're just an a******
I've heard something akin to that sentiment from a bunch of the soldiers who served with
It was not driving the leadership without a controller you know he's right about a lot of s***
We all are. We're all worried about it
Darrell Hanson
Does the fact of his
What he describes as his good intentions matter to you
Yes it does
I mean but it intention like that is not ever Justified today
It's something so huge and such a big decision in that caused so many consequences with it
I feel like you won't have to be God
To make that kind of decision
I want to be careful not to suggest
All the soldiers we talk to are in lockstep
Some of them even when we talked to them last summer said they'd already forgiven bow moved on
Other said they never get over it
The past week or two my producer Dan and I checked in without a half dozen soldiers
See if anything they'd heard from both so far in the podcast had made them feel differently
Some said they still thought he was lying about why you left
Other said they believe him now
What are trying to forgive what he did
But they just
Can't quite get there
Here's Ben Evans
He may have had the greatest intentions of the world but
Yeah I just don't I can't
Yeah just don't
Yeah
I talked to John Thurman for a while recently
John's mother is a therapist and like a lot of veterans he's also had counseling to help him deal with the after-effects of
Deployment
Maybe a little more
Touchy feely on the question of those Mental Health
I wanted to know if a diagnosis would help John not to say that what bow did was okay
But whether diagnosis would help John forgive bow
Personally
I got pretty pushy with John about it he was a really good sport
Yeah we all experience
The same thing
And we didn't walk off
I know I know but you're saying we all experience the same thing and we drove on
To you is you didn't experience well yes I didn't see it from his lens
You know she was she was getting
Scared by Adele you weren't
Like you're not perceiving danger in those reprimands
And he is
Yeah and I
I mean I don't think there was danger in those reprimands cuz I don't know I know that's not the poor not argue
Weather
We're not arguing whether he's correct
Yeah
I really really really
Try
To see it from
His side
Through his lens and I understand that he and I have very different brains
Perception or not
I mean I still can never
Forgiven
Mercante
And it's on Principe
He broke
That intimate Bond
That we all share with each other
That's not something you can ever come back
I don't care where your head was
Bo you still f****** dead
You walked off
And you betrayed
It's like you stop there. It stops there
And that's just that that's the infantryman and me taking over
I'm a dyed-in-the-wool civilian
From a family of civilian
My father was in the Army in World War II
But he didn't deployed overseas the only War Stories I remember him telling me we're about like
Carousing in Denver
Sorry Dad
It wasn't immediately obvious to me why some of the people both served with were not even just mad
Hurt
Deeply hurt in some case
What I understand now is that
That Bond
Brotherhood they feel
It's not just a cliche
What is a cliche but it's also profoundly true
I think about it this way
In my life who would die for me
Really
My mom maybe
Who would I die
Ikids
And so imagine you're in a platoon
You become so close
So fast
To all these guys around you
You recognize each other's cough
Are there silhouette in the dark
You would die for The Other Guys in your platoon
Even if you don't like them you do it
And they would die for you
It's not even hypothetical it happens all the time
And because of that
Personalities aside
These guys become family to one another if you walk away like Bo did
You break the promise you all have made to each other
You undermine the whole Enterprise
Your family starts to crumble
When you need it most
And that's what the soldiers say happened during the search for Bo Bo's friend Chris Engels said
It was like the soul of their platoon just dwindled people shrink into themselves
Even afterwards 2nd platoon felt like they were blamed for believing
They were sort of banished from the larger family of the
Italian
A sergeant everyone told us they just love
A guy named Larry Hein
Was moved out of the platoon
Summer Place by commander who was to put it gently
Stricter
After helping with Afghan elections in August of 2009
Between went on to a town called modicon
An embedded with Afghan Security Forces
And they did well enough there that they got commendations and a visit by General McChrystal
But still overall a lot of them just felt robbed
But their whole deployment lost it
Its meaning
When I talked to Darrell Hanson again
A couple weeks ago
He said after hearing the podcast
He softens some
I don't have as much hate as I do towards them
What up
I went shooting today
But what about the time and I think I'll let you know but
Today I pray shake his hand be like
You think about next time
For what you do think about
Think about it a little bit more you know was it worth it
Almost all the soldiers we talked to said they still thought both should go to court-martial
A mark
I'll just said it makes sense for bow to go through the military justice system
Walmart says
Do United States did put a lot of time and money and energy into getting blowback
And that's as it should be
But we did take Extraordinary Measures
Next time
Annie's cereal
Cereals produced by Julie Schneider Dana Travis and me and partnership with Mark Ball Megan
Allison Hugo Lindgren Jessica Weisberg page 1 and Annapurna pictures
Our glasses are editorial advisor Whitney Dangerfield is our digital editor research by Kevin Garnett fact-checking by Michelle
Copyediting bhayani tolani Emily Condon is our line producer our music is composed by Nick thorburn
Chris Myers and Mark Phillips the shows mix by Kate bilinski Christian Taylor's our community editor other cereal staff
Southland Elise bergersen and Kimberly Henderson special thanks this week to Jonathan menjivar and Rich Ora's
Strange bird labs
For his great work keeping our website going strong
Check it out there is lots of stuff on that website right now
The dress
Serialpodcast.org
Stay tuned for a preview of our next step
Support for serial comes from Squarespace
For free trial visit squarespace.com
When you're ready to purchase
Use the offer code cereal for special offer
Squarespace
Build it beautiful
And from MailChimp they've been with cereal since the beginning
MailChimp
Support for serial comes from ADT
You can use the ADT app to monitor your cameras and video doorbell from virtually anywhere
Is it att.com podcast
Tell me more about how ATT can design and install your
Smart Home
Back by 24/7 Pro
Serials production of This American Life and WBEZ Chicago
Coming up
Next episode of serial
I had previously
Had discussions with
Somali Warlords Haitian dictators and Afghan Insurgent leaders so
Given that range contacts I didn't find anything unusual about these without Ivana like simple straightforward.
Do you want a deal or not
He's done more serious time than anyone could possibly imagine I mean the release video and holyshit there's Bo again
The old strategy to win this with money to win this with song
Soldiers with military mites
Was doomed