Support for serial comes from ATT
The number one smart home security provider
Offering everything from video doorbells
To indoor and outdoor cameras to Smart locks and lights
Control from the ADT app
Or the sound of your voice
Visit att.com podcast to learn more about how ADT can custom design and install your
Smart home system
Back by 24/7 protection
30 second version
I know what this one is right
Previously
I'm cereal
I wanted to be a soldier but I wanted to be
And they were out out there handing out watercolor maps of Afghanistan
All felt like why are we up
This is f****** b*******
He's in Pakistan
I serve the United States with honor and distinction
That's not something you can never come back I haven't seen
From you or any other journalists a real dig into how the Army came to that conclusion
That door get ready cuz there's a
There's a shitstorm you know and it's not going away anytime soon
From This American Life and WBEZ Chicago is cereal
One story told week by week
I'm Sarah Koenig
I'm driving to go pick up
My dry cleaning
And I must things have said 7 or whatever it was and I was like
Wait a second
Doing the Coast Guard
I had a couple of conversations recently that I just want to tell you about
When was with this guy Justin
Kid email.
So I gave him a call
Boom boom boom January 2006 I like
IPods
The show
And I called my sister and I like gel you are not going to believe this
Overdose season 2 and she's like yeah
I want to be with this guy
Coast Guard boot camp
And he remembers the night Bo broke down
Remember standing outside on a freezing February night in Cape May New Jersey
Well something strange happened inside
Remember seeing blood and broken glass in the bathroom
And yellow caution tape
Justin was seventeen at the time and there's some details he couldn't recall
But he let me to another guy also from that boot camp class
John Ross
John was an older recruits 26
He remembered though do you like them
I thought he was a nice guy
One night a couple of weeks in John says there was a fire drill
They did that a lot these wee hours fire drills
I'm Commander would bang on the top of a garbage can and wake everybody up and they'd all have to rush outside and muster up
Each person had a number and they called out in order
01003 cetera
It became clear there was a number missing
Also clear
That number was Bo
John was at the edge of the group
So his commanders sends him and another guy back inside to find bow
We go running back and
The running into the head
And there he was he
Get blood even felt pretty good
We were never sure exactly how he did it
But there was
Quite a bit of blood
There was some blood on the wall
Vladimir's what are those
The sink
The countertop area
And he was bleeding from a space there was
No blood on his hands
Blake he had
Cam smashes face into the mirror
And he was
Huddled up crying
Hi yuan
Balled up
One of those moments you run into you like oh s***
What if I could I just like step into
Did you try to talk to him
I did and he was just sleeping
I was just and it was shocking
Bedtime
I like the guy so I was trying to find out what happened I remember just
Connect coaching down next to him like I do what's going on are you okay and you was sleeping like go away leave me alone
This version is more alarming than the one I'd heard previously from bow or from the Army investigation
It's why Justin emailed us in the first place
To say sure didn't look like a garden-variety panic attack to him
And it wasn't
A military psychologist I talk to you said you don't usually hospitalize someone much less eject them from the military
Based on a single panic attack
So whatever was going on with bow
Must have been more serious than that
Sobo got sent home
Dejana Justin no big surprise there
They said Coast Guard training was very demanding psychologically and it was clear bow couldn't hack it
The big surprise
Came much later
When Bill was rescued a friend of John Rolfe is called him and said
Can you believe that p o w
From bootcamp
John said it took him awhile to put it together
Techno music
Who captured by the Taliban I'm like who
Like what the hell is he doing
You are like
How do you survive five years of the Taliban you're like how that guy and lives
Exactly
Yeah
Didn't make any sense to me
That just
Blew my mind away
I guess it was a really nice guy but
If you couldn't handle
The Coast Guard
And the comfort is stressful
Make it sound like it
A cakewalk
But he should not have gone to another
French
Again in his investigation General Kenneth Dahl found the Army recruiter followed all the regulations when he signed blow up
I also wrote that he thought those regulations were inadequate in those case
His Coast Guard separation should have been looked at more carefully than it was
John spent eight years in the Coast Guard Reserves
Justin became a rescue swimmer
Like a special forces the Coast Guard
I got you drop out of helicopters into the ocean
Presumably they both know a thing or two about the military mindset
Justin had the same question as John
Why they let that guy into the army
They saw what I saw this on what happened during Coast Guard boot camp
Not at all. There's no
No reason why they should ever let him in
At all
Sometimes bouquets is summed up like this
What book did was wrong
Walking off his post was wrong
But the Army shouldn't have let him enlist in the first place
+ 5 years captivity
5 years
Scales balance
The Army messed up messed up
Let's move on
That leaves out a reckoning
And a reckoning is what the military wants understandably
Afghanistan into their families
If you don't consider the consequences of bows decision to walk off opms
Eye feels as if something important and painful has been papered over
And that doesn't feel like justice
I want an accounting
This is our last episode this season and so I want to try to answer this now
What exactly should we blame bo4
What's his fault and what is a
And the heaviest moral charge against him
The elephant in so many discussions about Bo and about the trade and about the military proceedings against him
Did any American soldiers died looking for him
Some people very high up in the military world are saying yes
People did die looking for Bowe
Michael Flynn is the highest-ranking person I've interviewed so far
He's a retired lieutenant general who is head of Dia the defense intelligence agency
Back in 2009 when both went missing Flynn was in Afghanistan
He was General Stanley McChrystal director of intelligence
What crystal in case you've forgotten was commander of us and Coalition forces for all of Afghanistan
So when just under McChrystal is a big deal
Explain to him that this was one of my outstanding questions about both story
This very thing of like will wait did people die
During this search for Bergdahl as a unit
Okay if somebody was on a mission to go
Find an American
Now there's
What did the guy did a soldier walk down a road
And in an IED blew up
And if the soldier was walking down that road in an area where
He would not have have been had it not been for the search for Bergdahl
And in fact his mission there their tactical mission was to
You know conduct a patrol
And and
Try to find intelligence or try to find
Any indications of where the soldier might be and then and in fact was blown up by that IAD or others wounded
That's a no-brainer I agree that does that.
Connect
Here's the problem now
General Flynn's no-brainer scenario I haven't found one like that
When he said those are dots he connected
He wasn't thinking of any particular cases of soldiers who died
He was there he says he knows it to be true
Durbin lots of media stories
Declarative stories citing specific cases of soldiers who died because of the search
Usually there are six names all from Bo's battalion
The first of the five-oh-first
We know for sure there was a massive search for bow
She walked off Opie Mast on June 30th 2009
For the month of July people were sent out all over praktika Province and Beyond
Doing nothing but missions to find the dust one
But brother miraculously no one died on those missions
The six names of soldiers who died
They were all on missions that happened later
7 to 10 weeks after bow disappeared
And none of those missions was a search and rescue mission
We looked into all these incidents there are four of them
Talk to soldiers who are there
And two people higher up who planned and organized them
Official information on these missions is thin
We've seen Army investigations on only two of the four cases
One of those was just a summary they were both redacted so we can't tell what the precise Mission orders and objectives were
We put in for your request with the Army long ago on all these cases but haven't gotten anything back
Again the Army itself hasn't formally investigated the question of whether people died looking for Bo
That we know of
But somehow
This idea that people died looking for Bo
To a lot of people it's not a question
It has traveled out of the realm of the murky and has solidified into concrete information
Point where a clothing company made a f*** Bergdahl T-shirt with 6 Stars underneath
To represent quote the 6 honorable soldiers from the first of the five-oh-first
That lost their lives all because of Bergdahl
Why are some people so sure about this
Where did it come from
On September 4th 2009
One of those six soldiers Darren Andrews
Was killed in Pacheco province in a village called Palau right near Okemos
Who's the second lieutenant in later
His parents
Sandra and Andy Andrews I've been told by the army that Darren was killed in an RPG attack on a mission to rest
Target Topanga
When they attack happened apparently pushed aside other men he was awarded the Silver Star posthumously
About five years later his parents were on a long drive to the hospital for Andy's cancer
When President Obama announced Bose return
Eddie says the way he remembers at the Rose Garden ceremony hadn't even finished before someone contacted them
I don't find him Saundra got a call and this gas is I want to let you know where
Fixing to break this story and tell the truth of what really happened this phone call with someone in
Aaron's unit this was the first Andy and Sandra were hearing that Darren was actually killed on a mission related to Bo
And then we were on the phone literally she was on the phone literally
From the time we left Cameron till we got to MD Anderson 3 hours later with NBC CBS
ABC and I don't everybody know
When it broke it broke hard
Started texting and sending messages on Facebook and calling and telling me
You know we're not going to stand by and let them say
He is a hero
Is your son in the other guys were a hero
And we're not going to stand for this
That same day the six names were put out there
Online
My day 3 destroy had anchored in the mainstream press
Cassandra and Andy it was such a jolt that first call
Because after 5 years they'd come to accept the original army issue version of what happened to Darren
That he been killed on a mission to rest a Taliban guy
They weren't looking for someone else to blame
They were doing okay with what they thought they knew
Uniwigs tala
Fit the story into our life
We have done
Talked about it
And now all of that
Was gone
We had a whole new story to get used to
Anna
A lot more anger
Sandra said they felt angry at Beaufort one thing
And they felt they been lied to
Are the army
I'd Aaron's Commander
Because no one had ever mentioned berdosa them before
Which goldfish eat
Like there was a cover-up
Two and a half weeks later at the andrews's went to Washington DC to testify before a congressional committee
Andy Andrews told the committee that six different soldiers who served with their son
I told him and his wife that Darren was killed while searching for Bo
Founder says at the very least
Bo was a contributing factor in his death
It may not have been directly
But indirectly
He was responsible
So this story the six names the lineup of photos in the Press
As far as I can tell it originated at the ground level from Bo's platoon mates
Documentation to back up what they were saying the defense department wasn't seconding these claims
These guys did have reasons
They were just making it up
Take Palau the tour Darren Andrews died on September 4th
I wasn't clear what exactly that mission was about
And I didn't understand what the connection to Bo was
So I asked John Thurman to explain it to me because he was on that plow mission
And I also knew John was in the camp of soldiers who thought bill was responsible for the people who died
They said we're going out for
You know up to 10 10 days
And that's
Basically all I remember
But what was your mission
But I don't actually know
That was definitely way above my paygrade we were going to be going into Palau
And we were going to be looking around and going house-to-house we had
Quite a few attachments that I'd never seen before we had a female engagement team
And we also had a combat camera team that was with us
So I don't actually know
This is an unusual actually
Trello level Soldier doesn't know the overall mission
What's communicated to Jimenez
Pac4x many days
And then before they go out each day
Every spider immediate leader
In this case Erin Andrews
We're going to go to this location or going to knock on doors or head out stuff or meet with Afghan Security Forces
Whatever
I've asked a lot of people not just John but Battalion officers people doing Intel
What was the purpose of the Palau mission
Here's what I've gathered big picture
The trip to Palau was part of a larger roughly 10-day operation
Push into the yackle district
US forces have been pretty successful in other towns but farther north
They're working up there with local leaders doing
Coin essentially making friends helping build local government and security
But not so much in my account
Which is right near Okemos
The Villages around there had quite a bit of Taliban activity they were not friendly to US forces
I said the Battalion had planned this mission to try to push back in there
That area was strategic it was between the Pakistan border and a main Highway in Afghanistan
That goes up to Kabul and then all through the country
The weight of Italian plan these larger operations
They weren't just about one objective
You try to accomplish a bunch of things at once
Get all kinds of US government agencies doing their stuff
State Department or the Department of Agriculture they might be assessing which little grapes are best to grow in whatever Valley
So you might have them along
Honest pulao Mission John remembers a female engagement team
That likely would have been headed up by a social scientist
His job is to help the US military understand Afghan culture
John doesn't remember looking for a specific high-value Taliban guy on that mission but other people I spoke to her
Who are there do remember that but they infected detain someone zip tied his hands guarded him
But then were told by higher-ups to let him go which they did
Again I haven't seen the mission order or the after-action report so I can't be sure
Adheres with John remembers
From his vantage point
In the driver's seat behind the wheel of an mrap
He remembers they had a lot of trucks that day maybe seven
Take me to court on in the village
And John in the Gunner waiting in the truck while the other guys went door-to-door about 45 minutes passed on to us
So my Gunner and I were sitting in the truck
And we just we had this Eerie feeling we were talking about
You know over some cigarettes like this
The sound is doesn't feel right it didn't give us a good vibe
And I remember a bunch of kids
Were congregating under the gigantic tree there
And then they all started to filter back into their houses
And I'm a gunner had actually been in Iraq
On the deployment prior to ours
And he said you know
I got a bad feeling we're about to go
Get f***** up
Because when the town clears out
Usually it means that the Taliban is going to stand something up there bringing the civilians back in so that they don't get hurt
I'm going to put the word out you know we're going to attack the Americans today
So we radio up
And
Everybody kind of knows what's going on
They all get ready to leave
And then someone comes out from behind a wall and shoot an RPG at one of their trucks
They shoot back
Hainan aerospace
I was Truck 3
And I just see the first truck just
Explode
Not the whole thing obviously but I see
The mine roller in the hood
Separate from the vehicle and
They rolled over pressure plate ID
And then from then on
You know it was RPG Valley so it was Small Arms fire
Recoilless rifles mortars
Everything because once they took out that first truck we were stuck
Because you're all behind that truck
Correct
Yeah that's
That's a technique that the Taliban had sort of adopted when the Soviets had invaded
Is Hino take out the first truck
Shoot up the last truck
And then everybody in The Middle's completely fuk
Darren Andrews had been in John's truck
The third track
John says Darren ran out to the first track
The one that just gotten blown up
To help the guys there
They set up what's called a casualty collection Point Littlefield trauma area
So many RPG started coming in
John says he watched Erin Andrews get killed
He watched Matt Martinez John's good friend who'd also been in his truck
That would die in a hospital in Germany a week later
John in the Gunner are inside the truck during the Ambush stuck there
Is Gunner is firing at whatever he can
And how about it like how long are you sitting there just like
Taking this attack
I think
I think the initial attack
Kick-off somewhere around 1500
And we didn't get back to mess till 0506
Oh my God you're out there all night
Yeah
Terrible
Oh man
I mean my Gunner and I just accepted it
I said am I sick and I think we're probably going to die tonight BC I think we are
So it was horrible the whole thing
People died
People were injured
Brass John again
How is any of this connected to Bo
And he said what we were always supposed to be looking
He said his platoon leader Darren Andrews
Didn't mention bow before they set off for pulao that day
But he did mention go back at 5 Sharona
A few days before they set off on the whole operation
I remember the 10 and Andrew saying you know if you hear or see
Any signs
A Bergdahl
We need to know about it
I mean and that was just the amendment to everything
They don't before any big push
And it wasn't it does also sounds like it wasn't terribly specific to any one mission
No
Got it okay now I'm beginning to understand why you could have a mission that is simultaneously not specific to birds
Doll and
Also involving Bergdahl
IC
It's hard it's hard cuz it's like an umbrella over everything you're doing exactly
It's the perfect way to describe it
So if you close the umbrella
Then
You can't make the argument it was looking for Bergdahl
Right
But if you open it you can
So it's just
Depends on who's living under the umbrella from my
From my small scope is specialist Thurmond III
I don't know
Who knows what
Above me
Right now I only know what I know
John told me it's totally possible this was a specific mission to look for bow
But that information just never filter down to him
John's Battalion Commander Lieutenant Colonel Clint Baker would probably know
I haven't been able to talk to him
But I did talk to his number two
Command sergeant major Ken Wolfe
He's out of the military now but at the time he was the highest NCO in the battalion
Who do the commanders in the privates
Cared about them
It took me quite a long time to persuade Ken to talk to
He has no love lost for bow
He thinks he's selfish plain and simple
Traitor to his unit
Finally after many emails and negotiations
Kant agreed on one condition
He wanted to be able to say this
The families who lost
Chun's
During this deployment
To let them know that
There
Their sons
Did not die
Looking
For PFC Bergdahl
Their son didn't die looking for him
Explain why
Why you're saying like why you know this to be true
Because
All you
All you got to do
Is look at a map
And look at a time frame
Okay I'm so time frame
Again the incidents that resulted in the six deaths in a battalion happened between August 18th and September
4/5 about two months after Bo left
We we we looked and we looked
And we look
And
But you can't
And this is where this is where it gets very difficult
For people to understand
Because you can never a new one in the army
Is ever going to say
We stopped looking for you
Right right
But
Here's a deal
You know it's it's been 45 + base
At this point
We know where he's at In-N-Out is in Pakistan
All right
A vanilla unit like a five-oh-first is not leaving its battle space and going into Pakistan
Define vim
By look at a map
Because if anyone is going after bow in Pakistan will be a special forces team
Not an infantry unit
Of course they were going to keep their eyes and ears open
But if your commander you're balancing no man left behind
With some very practical matters
Your Intel regarding the dust one is drying up
You're unlikely to find him in Afghanistan anyway
There's an Afghan presidential election
Prepare for
Award win
So you're not sending your guys on search missions anymore
In terms of operations they needed to get back to work
Cancers that Palau Mission had nothing to do with bow
What some of the soldiers will say is
Okay maybe not directly but it's still connected to
Because the search for bow affected everything
They talk a lot about second and third order effects
A concept that's drilled into soldiers
But everything they do has consequences
Once or twice removed
Search change the course of their deployment
Change the landscape of their overall mission in a bunch of detrimental ways
Led to people dying
I put their argument to Ken
Well sure you know the September 4th Mission wasn't expressly only to go look for birds
Doll say
But because we had been out looking for him for the past 2 months
We had been making inroads in certain places and because we had to kind of pull away from that and focus on
Looking for him and we became much more kinetic we became more aggressive we are going into places we hadn't been before
We were stretched thin
That that it gave the insurgents a foothold
In places
You know where we are kind of kept them at Bay and now those places were more dangerous like that's one of the argument still make
Minnesota fair argument
It doesn't hold water because
You you you are in a very
Bad neighborhood
Regardless
You can get killed any day
I mean
If you
You could have you could have been on it on a random patrol
In Palau on the 29th
Of
June
And hit
Shania t as well so I mean I get it
However it you know it's just purely speculation
And hypothetical
Speculation and hypothetical toucan are Far Cry from say knowledge and understanding
Ken says there were so many factors factors beyond bow these soldiers are not taking into account
70 factors they aren't aware of
I'll give you a perfect example he said
And yet you told me this whole story about Yaya cow and the surrounding villages
Different factions have been in Conflict there since the early 1970s
Playlist in the Monarch kicking around the Communist sympathizers
Well and then when the communists come in
They check the Loyalists around
Well and then
When the Taliban comes in
They took the Communists around
And then when we come in
We took the Taliban out
So now they retaliate
Well some of these folks
They went across the border into Pakistan
Because they want to get kicked around
And then when they came back
They found that their houses
We're occupied
By the people who were kicking around right
Pirate show
They're they're angry
I just come back from Pakistan and when I left her 10 years ago this was my house and now you're living in it
Well there is no
You can't go down to the county courthouse
I'm sure Anna and pull up the deed that says this house belongs to me
So what are you do
You fight over it
Chode
It doesn't it didn't matter
That PFC Bergdahl
Walked off
There was a conflict that was so much deeper
Bergdahl
NM quite frankly so much more important than Bergdahl just to solve
Dev the problem
Impact eco
That these guys
They don't understand
The guys are making these arguments and it's not because you're bad guys
It's not MacArthur ill-informed
It's because
They aren't pretty
Did the same information
That I am
And here's the deal
The story I just told you you know how long it took me to learn that
Took me 9 months
Took me 9 months rolling in there
All the time
And Hawking
The people
Before
They laid that whole story out for me
Their mission is different than mine mission
My mission was to go out there and figure out what the problem is
Why Why everytime we roll through
This one place
We got blown up
Are the soldiers who see all of this differently
Ken doesn't begrudge them their perspective
He just wishes they hadn't been so public about it
Did these young men that are that are saying these things I love every one of them and every one of those guys know
I think him
Make him get ahold of me in and I'll do anything in the world for those guys they know that
What they're doing
I just don't think that
They thought it through
And
By not thinking it through they didn't understand the ramifications
Of their verbalization
What that was going to have
On on the families
Again Ken's not being protective of Bo here
He just thinks the record. To be set straight
He doesn't want the memories of the guys who died
To be dragged into the bergdoll morass
Three Sally buy it
Are the politics of it
I think it's not fair to those men
Or their families
Are you sure something else I've heard along the way
Maybe some of these guys think they were looking for Bo
But really their commanders were only using bow as an excuse
Top cover
To get extra assets to go kick in doors and RC East
We were actually looking for him there didn't come a point where he did just become an excuse to go out
And do things but
This is a guy I'm calling Scott he arrived in Afghanistan in ghazni in mid-july
His job was classified which is why he doesn't want to use his name
All I could say was that he was attached to an elite unit he said before about left
In order for unit to leave the wire you had to have good actionable intelligence
But when when he disappeared. Does limits those thresholds for going
Hangout became much much lower so if you had
Very unreliable information about Bowe bergdahl's whereabouts
You can go anywhere
Just use him as an excuse to go wherever we wanted to go
How do you know that I mean you weren't there before
China Wok. So how do you know the threshold got lower
Because every other mission that we try to go on
That he
That didn't involve him
Was much more difficult to get out of
Get outside the wire on
So someone would say I think we need to go do ax
Forget it unless it involves
Yes
I mean I I sat through
Why briefings were
Missions were turned down
And I sat through
Live briefings were missions were accepted that probably shouldn't have been
Warfarin
So is this true
Were people just using the search as a way to get unrelated missions okayed
Or the way to scam assets
I asked and I asked and finally I found Lieutenant Colonel Paul Edgar
He was a guy in charge of managing the search for Belle he was operations officer for the Brigade
You're planning a mission for the five-oh-first and you wanted special assets
Usually aircraft or drones
You had to go through Paul
Around mid-august
I thought that there were a couple of requests from subordinate units that
That were
Taking advantage or attempting to take advantage a little bit of
Doing something else
In the name of looking for for Bowe Bergdahl
And when his team saw that they disapproved those missions
Also she didn't see rampant abuse or anything
He said it was more like a natural inclination
To try to sell your own mission spin your objectives
In a way that was going to be most persuasive to your bosses
For instance a couple of the people who helped plan missions lower down the company and Battalion level
Tell me that if you wanted extra support for operation in August or September say
You might sandwich bow in there
So the operation paperwork
Might well have included among other objectives
Language saying they were facilitating recovery of dust one or in support of dust One recovery operations
That's one meaning bow
If you had that you were more likely to get additional assets
The helicopter
On the other hand
To get approved in the first place you had to have actual Intel backing it up
Maybe it wasn't the strongest Intel but still it had to be legitimately connected to those whereabouts
And then on your mission you were actually question people about Beau
You can just invent something and get assets
Because first off that's just wrong
Resources are scarce and so you're very aware that if your getting use of an aircraft
Someone else who needs it just got denied
And second
If you try to manufacture a reason
Someone like Paul was going to catch it
A little cheating maybe little massaging
But not a scandal
But all this leads to another big question hovering over the search for Bo
By mid-july common sense told you what was probably in Pakistan
So why through August and into September are US soldiers still looking for a man Afghanistan at all
Why might an operation plan for September
Include a legitimate objective of facilitating recovery of the Dust one
When the dust one is long gone
Cross the border America Shah
Within two or three days of beau's disappearance news outlets were quoting Taliban sources saying those kidnapping was directed by
By Melissa Jean
Rose case would be referred to sirajudeen haqqani
Does guys operate in Pakistan
On July 20th right after the Taliban released the first Proof of Life video of bo ABC ran a story with the
Headline exclusive missing US soldier maybe in Pakistan
So then why were they still looking in Afghanistan 30 days later 60 days later and Beyond
Well first off Afghanistan's the only place they really can look
Since I can't go tromping into Pakistan Sovereign Nation Ally Etc
And Paul told me
Sure they sell those new stories in Pakistan and they had their own until that bow is in Pakistan
But they also had until just as persuasive that bow is in Afghanistan
Strong as a news report
Yes
Right okay
And I'm not and I'm not dissing news reports
Because sometimes sneezes
But if you see something on you know if I see something on on CNN International
And then
I go across the hallway to our Brigade intelligence cell
I ain't talked to a number of folks and
Overlay some different information
Am I suppose standing there
In front of an unknown land marker in
Pakistan
With today's newspaper or something like that
I'm going to looks very seriously and consider very seriously The credibility of
Of our information versus what what I read on CNN
Probability that Bo was in Pakistan wasn't enough
In fact Paul said his best guess was that boy was initially captured by some JV Taliban
And that rather than spiriting him across the border into Pakistan
The Taliban had sent a big cheese from Pakistan back into Afghanistan to handle the situation
DePaul wasn't at all convinced but wasn't still in Afghanistan
Army commanders are literal when they say they needed to know for a fact
That ball was in Pakistan before they would change course
General Flynn the guy who is mcchrystal's intelligence Chief at the time
Made this clear to me
If you're if you think probably a few weeks after like yeah he's probably empaques
Stan
So what do you want me to say sorry you want me to say that we're going to give up on him
No I'm not going to say that I can sit here and we will never give up
You know you don't I mean you know something American
You know I'm going to hold out hope until
Until the last possible thing that we can
Potentially doing even
And we would even pull
Intelligence threads even after
Months
I mean I'm not I'm not a satisfied person
Even if you ever talked to an intelligence officer who says they're satisfied
There's
There's something we call bulletproof intelligence and and when you get bulletproof intelligence
That's rare that is rare
And even when you think your Intel is Bulletproof
You double check
Flynn says we've consistently underestimated our enemy in these wars
I use deception a lie effectively
We never got to 100% on his location
So the search for Bowen Afghanistan was never called off
Cuz again it's an army value and American value
But you don't give up on a Conrad who's falling into enemy hands
As one battalion officer said to me
Even if they're a dick head
You will do everything you can
But
One last word on this
Zoom out one level to the US Central Command
Because it wasn't just the Army calling the shots here
Centcom ultimately control defense department Assets in Afghanistan at the time
Planes helicopters drones
Predators with and without weapons attached
About two weeks after Bo was captured so mid-july
A ground-level analysts at centcom inform the boss
We think he's in Pakistan
But this analyst
You can't write that in your assessment
Not unless you have bomb-proof evidence
Meaning to Independent corroborated sources
Which is not the normal standard for an Intel assessment
Rather that's the standard usually reserved for Recovery Mission say when you're actually sending people into Harm's Way
Not for an Intel assessment
But in this case they weren't allowed to put it in a report so they didn't
They waited another thirty
40 days or so till sometime in late August early September
Which meant the intensity of the search for bow remain high in Afghanistan for several more weeks rather than
Tapering off in mid July
My source wasn't sure why they weren't allowed to call it earlier
Maybe because this was an unprecedented situation nobody exactly knew the implications tactic
Play strategically politically
A saying a US Soldier was being held in Pakistan for the dod had no Authority
Lieutenant Colonel Mike Waltz
The Special Forces Commander
Was one of the people who went on TV very early on
And said people died looking for Bo
Men died searching for
Sergeant Bergdahl and when we believed at the time
It's the short-handed
Is stating it as a nuanced fact
But I have trouble with
It seems Reckless to throw around something like that without solid cause
If you press for the evidence
Mike and others will argue on the basis of second and third order effects
So many resources were diverted to look for bow
Depriving other units resulting in fatality
On July 4th just a few days after Bo walked
There's a big attack in an outpost in Peck Tikka called Ciroc
Which two mortar men died
Maybe it would have gone down the way it did
They had the Intel aircraft a task for
Intel aircraft
Tied up in the search for Bo
In early October another big attack on a nopi located hundreds of miles north of Pact
8 Americans were killed
It happened three months after Bo left but is also been linked to him
Plans to shut down that Opie which is considered vulnerable I've been delayed
Partly because of starch
When I interviewed Mike Waltz I pushed him on this
The causality here is tenuous
So why are people saying it
And he said look directly or indirectly killed or almost killed
Why are we parsing this
There were real consequences to what bow did why can't we talk about that
Which made me realize this is the root of what these guys are saying
What they've been saying since the day bow got traded
And that is
Don't tell me it's over his back
No harm no foul
You can spend I think the rest of Eternity parsing well it was a supply run to the base at Salerno I'm was
That indirectly yeah that was ICD-10 was that related or not
But like I mean for that period of time
That's all we were doing
And it if you were hurt
Injured I listen to it on the radio people being met of act
During ambushes
From tcp's that they had set up
Trying to find Bergdahl
My own soldiers barely escaped death from from essentially an ambush
Based on it that was set up based on information looking for Bergdahl I'm absolutely adamant my mind
That soldiers were either put In Harm's Way or were harmed looking for him
And
Thought I'd sorry I'm a I do get a bit
Not emotional but I I
Couldn't push back more forcefully
That
That his actions just had no effect
And so the notion that it didn't really affect the election there didn't really do that much
I think it's just a
It's just absolutely untrue
I think it's a stretch too far to say people were killed looking for bow or because of bow
But that's not to say there weren't major consequences
Per month or six weeks the shape and mood of the war end of the US mission in Regional command East
Changed
Resources were diverted
People stop doing some of the arguably constructive things they were doing to look for bow
And people suffered looking for Bo
They suffered psychologically and physically
A couple of cases severely
In September a Navy SEAL named Jimmy hatch went on CNN and talk to Anderson Cooper
Hatch said he was part of the team that flew to helicopters into a compound
On the night of July 9th
Qasidah immediately deal with a pre-major gunfight
And at that point what's the what's the goal
Goes to get that kid
Find GoPro.
Fast and we were close
Cuz things started right away
Hatch didn't want to talk to me but I spoke to another person who was on the mission
Do backed up hatches story
That they had information but was there
And that's why they went
It turned out but wasn't there
A lot of Taliban were killed in the fighting
Hatch was shot just above the right knee is bone was shattered
In the CNN story he talks about how he became depressed
Suicidal
One day earlier on July 8th
Sergeant First Class Mark Allen was with the National Guard team going door-to-door in a village Indila District
South of mass
There were a handful of Americans who happen to go along with a platoon of Afghan National army soldiers
Their Commander had offered them up
We spoke to the commander as well as one of the other guys on that mission
And they both said yeah it was clear
The mission was to look for bow
Which considering the date just a week out
It makes sense
They got attacked
One soldier his right hand was badly wounded
Emetic took shrapnel shot in the hip
Mark Allen was shot in the head
He survived but he's in a wheelchair
He can't walk or talk
He's got a wife and two kids
It's been awful for all of them
Obviously
So yes during the search for Bo people were very seriously injured
In ways that permanently mess with their lives mess with their families
What are the charges against Bo is that he endanger the safety of other soldiers and rawnsley cause search and Recovery
Operations
Be convicted of that
He'll be punished
Punishment is very different from blame
Flame is more delicate
It comes up almost always
In my conversations about bow with
Soldiers commanders civilians diplomats everybody really
And it can be slippery
Pecan Lodge where it shouldn't
And it can skirt where not to stay
When I was talking to Ken wolfos former command sergeant major
Going to the list of names of men from the five-oh-first who died during that deployment
Ken was explaining no BS or not to do with bow
But he stopped short when we got to the name Kurt Curtis
Cancel that one he partly blames himself
Was a firefight in a medical clinic
They're going after a Taliban guy who committed some really brutal crimes apparently
Staff sergeant Kurt Curtis was shot and killed
Curtis was supposed to work from the base in Alaska
But Ken told him our numbers are low I need you to deploy to Afghanistan
Curtis is married he been on something like for deployments already
Where the most guys
Prasad okay
I'll do it
In late August
Curtis was on the quick reaction team that was called out to the medical clinic
And a town called star hausa
Can wolves have been to that clinic many times he toured it
He said the people in the town had a lot of pride in it
So he knew the layout better than anyone
And Ken said before Curtis and the other guys went out there
They were briefed
On how the road was where the trouble spots were
I did not tell them
And this is what haunts me to this day cuz
I just didn't think about it
There's this Clinic is two parts
What's inside a wall compound like most places in that part of the world
In
So you had, like the inpatient outpatient side
And I never
Hold these guys
That it was really two different buildings
And
Today they went in with the Afghan
Police
Give me a went to the first one
No issues
And they went in a second one
End
Church rummage
Was ambushed
When he went in that building
The second building with it along with the squad
Panda
And was killed there that day
But why would it have mattered if they had known they were two buildings like why does that part on you
Their tactical plan would have changed
And maybe Kurt wouldn't have died
Is what he saying
That's why Ken's haunted by it
And John Thurman
He feels guilt about what happened in Palau
It's hard for him to talk about the guys who got killed there
One of them Matthew Martinez
Was a radiotelephone operator like John
But that day John was the driver instead
Which means you stay in the truck
Darren Andrews their platoon leader
I called Martinez out of the truck to help when the attack happened
Because Matt was RTO that day not John
And that was just by chance
Yeah and it was actually we were drawing straws and I had drawn the longest straw on that one
Are you literally Drew star-like not metaphorically like you actually Drew straws
Oh
Yeah so that's why that one's been
Pretty hard
For really long time
John is the son of Air Force veterans who grew up in Texas and Washington State
Dance Cotillion and was a competitive figure skater as a tiger
In 2007
When he was a fresh 21 years old
If something is up to no good or anything
You're selling shoes at Nordstrom
And he learned a lot about shoes
But that was not the direction he wanted his life to take
So we join the Army
I'm not even sure why I'm telling you this
Except to remind you to remind me
That these guys who deployed to war zones are so young
And then they're traumatized
All of them pretty much
It sucks
It's not John's fault that Matt Martinez died
It's not kids fault that Kurt Curtis died
In the five-oh-first
Clay Bowen and Maurice Walker
They were doing election crap on August 18th 2009 when their vehicle ran over an ID
They were both killed
They were in an armored Humvee
Not an mrap
Which writer protected them
Who's to blame for that every time Commander
Then-defense secretary Robert Gates
President Obama
You just want to blame something or somebody
I blame the Taliban
You know
Yeah
That's Risa joglar
Claiborne's mother
When I first talked to John Thurman
Last August
He blamed for the deaths in the five-oh-first
About the time we had this conversation 5 6 months later
Kid movies off of that
Not toward Clarity exactly
And I blame
I blame
I mean you can point the blame on anybody
Sometimes I
I don't know
Sorry
Sometimes I just think
Where's one of those things that
It's hard to pin down
Who's responsible
I know and I feel like that seat that sounds like a cop-out
But now it now it's not
And I've done a ton of therapy on it and I still haven't
Yeah
I meant like
75% sense of it but
I still can't get that last 25
Cuz it's you know you start playing with variables
You know what else
And that's where you can drive yourself insane
These things happen in war
It's normal
I was talking to retired lieutenant colonel Paul Edgar former brigade-level officer who managed the search for Bo
And he said something that surprised me
He said oh is also normal in war
As a society we treat bow
Yeah it's some aberration when really he's
He is
His case is simply
A very normal parts
Of War
Paul said we signed up for Afghanistan
Not every single citizen obviously but as a country reeling from the September 11th attacks
Nobody put up too much of a fuss about going after Osama bin Laden
But when we signed up we were also signing up for all the things we tend to forget but that nevertheless attend
War
Mistakes
Accidents
People dying for a voidable or even ridiculous reasons
An Army Recruiting system that lowers its standards when it needs more bodies
20-something year olds
Who quickly become disillusioned
And do something rash or Criminal
It's all
Unfortunately normal
So there's a level of responsibility here whether it's you know whether it's Bo and his particulars or the things the back
That goes along with every single one
That we signed up for society
Going to take all of that independent
Politically and otherwise
On you know this 20 year old
Is in my opinion
Very very wrong
Movie first teamed up with Mark Bowl for the story Mark had just come to the end of his own X
Extensive reporting on bow
And I wanted to know if there was anything Mark still wondered about
Any outstanding questions he had
And he said yeah he did have one
I think the biggest question I have is what the
Appropriate
Punishment for what he did
And like how do you treat
How do you treat this
This guy who after all it was
Put through the wringer by the Taliban because he was
An American Soldier
Is there some recognition that
That he was coming from a from a place which is
Basically altruistic
Maybe self-serving to but
Certainly not
You know intending to cause harm
So I don't know I guess the question about how the country ultimately views him
Is interesting to me because it it speaks to
I think our in our capacity for forgiveness in some ways and also
The other kind of
I think the ambivalence about bow
Somewhat reflects the another larger confusion about
War
The wars in Iraq and Afghanistan
Because we don't think of them like World War II the quote-unquote good War
Or like Vietnam a lot of circles a bad War
So what are these worth
Because there's just like this incredible
Like Haze over our thinking about the war on terror and because these were 16th
Biso
You know
Hard to Define
It seems like as a country we don't know what to do with this guy
A few weeks ago Zach borrow one of those between mates got in touch with us
I also interviewed Zach back in the summer
But now she wanted to say something else
He been listening to the podcast and it was bothering him
The bone might be listening to
Getting the idea that everyone was mad at him
Zach was mad at first
You said it was kinda easier to be mad
You going to any military website everyone's angry with bow
You see your friends on TV talking about all the bad stuff Bo did
Can you get it why they're mad
But after he thought it through Zack said he realized
I was not what he was mad about
I just become a kind of Repository
Maybe like we're
Holding on to all this stuff and wanting to punish this kid for stuff that
Yeah
We are all the bad situation bad stuff happens
Yes
Added to
The bad situation but I don't think maybe
As much as
People blame
Sometimes
I mean it was going to suck no matter what
I feel like he's a young guy
It was in a really stressful place
And he made a terrible mistake
And
I don't know maybe we just
For myself I guess maybe I can accept that
I can understand that
When you're young
And you're dumb obviously I didn't make that
But I can see how it happened
People
Another platoon made Austin Lanford told me he decided not to blame go anymore either
He said when he was in Afghanistan he had crazy thoughts sometimes too
He said I hated it over there
I wanted to leave extremely bad sometimes
He said that could have been me
The Army gave us some numbers
From 2001 to 2014 more than 3500 people were convicted of being a wall
980 of those
Were convicted of desertion
Most of those happened here in the US people not showing up their bases for example
But there have been cases not unlike bows
Military therapist told us about a guy who left his fob in Kandahar in 2012
Apparently trying to walk to an outpost
Rejoin his platoon
Turn the reverse of what Bo said he was planning
He was quickly picked up by asking please
Wasn't charged with anything
And in 2010 8 months after Bo disappeared
A young Soldier sneaked off fob sharana
At 3 a.m.
About 7 hours later Afghan police found him wandering around
They handed him back over to the Army
When is kid was questioned evidently he said he planned to walk to Eastern Europe
Get a sleeping bag first aid kit food and water sunscreen
An ornamental sword and ornamental battle-axe his journal and an English to Pashto translation guide
According to an army report he quote plan to make it look like you have been kidnapped on quote
Kid cut his left hand
And left a trail of blood from his bunk to the fence line of the fob then cut his way through the fence
You haven't heard of him because he didn't get kidnapped by Taliban
Because he wasn't declared us one because there was no search
You haven't heard of him because no one noticed he was even gone until the Afghan police called
You haven't heard of him because we didn't trade Five Guys out of Guantanamo Bay
To get them back
We talked to someone in this guy's command group
You told us as a group they sat down and they talked about what to do about the soldier
Which gained a lot of publicity this is very low key
Didn't make the news so there was no pressure from anybody hire
The kid wasn't charged with any crimes
The guy from the command told us
He was sent home to get the help he needed
About a year later he was medically retired from the Army
Military therapist we talked you said these soldiers who walk off
Into Afghanistan
The Army treats them as headcases
It's so dangerous you kind of have to be crazy to do it
Art suicidal
He compared them to astronauts
Taking off their helmets in space
Bose court-martial is scheduled to start in August but right now the proceedings are stayed
Because the defense in the government are fighting over this massive Trove of classified documents more than 300,000 page
Because apparently
Who knows what's in there
So it seems very unlikely to me that anything's going to start this summer
I want to recordings of Mark and there's this part where Beau explains
The most the time he was a prisoner just dealing with the day-to-day his mind felt kind of numb
But then he said there were a couple of times
Brief moments
When he got this surge
I can't breathe for a second
One of those times he said was during his first year
He was being held in a mud compound
The one where he said he made friends with
The dog and had tried to Tunnel himself out
When I managed to slip outside
Into the courtyard
And he looked up
Anything like that
Things went so far beyond me
Yeah
It is just that relief of knowing that the stupidity doesn't go any further than that
Then it's almost like you don't have to be scared
Mark still talks about occasionally not as much as he used to
Mark says there isn't much more to say until the military settles Bose case
When the Army are adversaries legally speaking
Still a soldier
As soon as he was rescued
Somewhere in a government office
Someone filled out a department of the army form for 187
Play Change post status
I'm missing captured
Present for Duty
After knocking down this huge long Serpentine geopolitical Dominos
What was assigned to an office job on his base in San Antonio
He's fighting the charges against him which means he waits a lot longer than he thought he'd have to
But
Waiting is something Bo knows how to do
Cereals produced by Julie Schneider
Saturday night trivia send me in partnership with Mark Bowl Megan Ellison Hugo Lindgren Jessica Weisberg page one and a predicate
Alright every episode for the past ten weeks I've spun through the credits pretty fast because none of you really good to him
Credits my wrong
But I do I care so much and if you listen to this whole story I'm telling you you do care
I just don't know it this reporting project was enormous but it's always me talking so what you don't know is
Entire sections of the story or doggedly and expertly reported by Dana Chavez
And then Kevin Garnett and Whitney Dangerfield they also hunted down so much information really interesting stuff
The I don't even know to look for Ira Glass sat in on endless edits no matter when they fell even if he was in
Taxi coming home after a red-eye flight he dialed in to help us I won't go on and on it's just that I've been
Been waiting all season to say how stupendously grateful I am for the Cracker Jack skill of everyone I work with that leaves
Michelle Harris our fact-checker Benjamin Phelan he did additional research for us this week I need a Lonnie that are copied
Editing Joe level help edit this week Emily Condon is our line producer our music is composed by Nick thorburn and
Fritz Myers Fritz was on call for us all season
Matt block played trumpet for a theme music on Thanksgiving weekend
Carl Burton did the artwork for each episode thanks also to Rich Urus for his work on the website and show is mixed by
I can't balinski
Kristen Taylor is our community editor other cereal staff
Southland Elise bergerson and Kimberly Henderson
Finally a special thanks this week to Mark Sparrow and Ben schreier
Our website serial podcast. Org
We will be watching those cases it moves through the court and it's possible we'll update you depending on what happens there
It's a lot of great stuff on the website right now including new stuff so please check it out
And sign up for our mailing list
Also
Do not forget to Listen to This American Life
You will be so happy did
Cereal is a production of This American Life and WBEZ Chicago
Support for serial comes from ADT
You can use the ADT app
To monitor your cameras and video doorbell from virtually anywhere
Visit att.com podcast
To learn more about how ATT can design and install your cuss
Smart Home
Back by 24/7