Serial season 3
Later during the break you'll hear from a CEO of a company that makes high-tech gadgets
Track your dog's health
Unlearn my ZipRecruiter is rated number one by Employers in the US based on hiring sites with over 1000 reviews on trustpilot
ZipRecruiter for free at ziprecruiter.com cereal
Support for serial comes from Squarespace
Make your business official with Google in Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and a Business website with Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and professional tools from Google
It's the simplest way to look professional online
Visit squarespace.com Google
To start your free trial
And use offer code professional
For a discount on your first purchase
Google and Squarespace
Make it professional make it beautiful
How can you help us do that
What is a solution
Previously on serial
That's fine but you still have to go through this
I have talked that they would check in on him and
Hope that that means
Somehow protecting him
Why would you have any court dates
Why would you have a court date coming up
From This American Life and WBEZ Chicago
It's serial one Courthouse told week by week I'm Sarah Koenig
Joshua was correct
The state was trying to invoke his syo they wanted to send them to adult prison
The morning after he called me I did inquire Dover at the Juvenile Justice Center
See what was what
So I'm actually have to
Courthouse right now
Are you at
So they're just going to set a date for
I guess hearing or the next whatever is going to happen next
But
But yeah how are you doing
I was up all night last night
I was thinking about last night
All I can muster was a solution that when I was Joshua's age
I was on irritating
Baidu
Alright try to get some sleep it's nothing's going to be better if you don't get sleep
I know you're worried I know you're worried
I know
It's not my job to comfort Joshua
Certainly not my job to tell him to go to bed
But I happen to be the one on the phone right now
Out of all the cases we watched
Joshua's got me most
I could not fathom that the state would give up on him
After all he dressed for law enforcement
I'd rather beat down teams org
A 19 year old kid
I did what I knew how to do
I reported out every beat of this sucker
Every turn
Go to Joshua almost everyday sometimes twice a day
For year-and-a-half
So that the story of Joshua would exist
Not for posterity sake
But for the sake of straight-up fairness
First thing I wanted to know
Why Joshua what was odys saying he done
I met the one with Jackson from their facilities and put them into the adult system
I got a copy of the motion to invoke Joshua's syo filed by the County prosecutor's office
Are the requests of the juvenile prison Indian River
Emotion claimed that Joshua created a substantial risk to the safety or security of the institution
But despite all the therapeutic programming Joshua completed
He consistently chooses to make criminal decisions
Then there's a list of about a dozen specific incidents just from the past 6 months assaults fights disruptive
Behaviors its own urine on a kid
It's on a remote control at a female guard
Get smashed video game console
Add later find out the incident that triggered the motion to invoke
Apparently Joshua had put out a hit on another kid
But usually means arranging for other kids to jump someone
The kid wasn't jumped but still the prosecutors considered it a serious threat
I got to say I was taken aback by the list I had that anxious jolt of hold up
Have I completely misunderstood who this person is Elizabeth bad
The summer at the end extensive
16 fights 6 menacing threats
21 disruptive behaviors
Etc but
I have another report
An internal odys report
The documents every incident involving Joshua whether as victim or aggressor
Promised all his time and odys custody
I want to cross reference request to invoke Joshua's syo with that internal odys report
I realized
These aren't isolated incidents
Many of them are connected
There's an assault
When Joshua hit a kid on February 3rd
What's missing
Is February 2nd
What you can see on that internal report
February 2nd that same kid walked up to Joshua the water fountain
And punched him in the face
There are few sequences like this
Tit for Tat sandwich only the top was included in the request to invoke his that's why I O
Yes indeed Joshua did throw pee at a kid on March 27th
3 before the same kid had assaulted Joshua
Entropy on him
Common weapon in juvenile
I'm in the list of Joshua's offenses by people who either work in odys
On behalf of kids inside odys
And I said
Sounds great but
Yeah for a kid who's been in there 3 years
Exceptional
Is cardhu known Joshua for a couple of years
She told me overall not a troublemaker
Not even on the radar in terms of major threats inside the facility
He gets mad sometimes you said
But usually for a legitimate reason
Joshua did throw a video gamer motor guard for instance
Joshua told me that's because the guard discussed his case in front of other kids
Snitches get stitches
Isn't she apologized later and they were cool after that
But there it was in their quest to invoke
Another incident on the list
Sounded as if Joshua had caused a car to get hurt during a fight
He said not accurate he was trying to defend the guard
The one time I visited Indian River
I'm at the same Garden passing she confirmed it
He was trying to protect me she said
Call Joshua honey
Again I couldn't interview anyone at odys on the record they don't participate in stories about specific youth
But in a statement they reiterated that they do investigate allegations of misconduct and take action when necessary
When I put the two reports side by side
What I saw was the Raggedy morally compromised Chronicle for the kid at War Joshua wasn't only a victim
Store with the only a perpetrator
Like a lot of kids inside odys
He was both the most powerful gang in juvenile prison was after him
Color guards couldn't be trusted everyday
He felt unsafe
So we created alliances where he could dominated where he could took advantage where you could
Sun protection where I could but didn't make his behavior right then again odys prison
Really spin on an axis of right and wrong
See previous episode
The prosecutors offer Joshua deal
He didn't fight the vine over
And transferred to adult prison
Ticket 9 years
It went forward with the hearing
Set up an argument he could end up with more than that
As many as 18 years
Josh was assigned attorney with a guy named Jim whole flick
Jim hosek hadn't done one of these syo invocations before
How many people in the county had
Joshua didn't know whether to take the deal
What's the westhouse hotel Nia
But he said he's inclined to fight it
Who's everybody
Show me
Joshua tried to Marshal support
He has some odys staff members to write letters to the court on his behalf
Cuz if you told them they were willing
Joshua's father who was in Jamaica pledge to hire Josh a private attorney just needed to arrange for payment
In the meantime Indian River declare that it wanted Joshua out now
While they waited for the final hearing on his ass yo
The superintendent claim Joshua is causing
Environment of constant response and panic
Court magistrate okay the transfer
Joshua was delivered to county jail
Adult County Jail
A couple of weeks went by and I can hear on the phone that Joshua was acclimating to the idea of an adult sentence
In adult prison
Decompress the nine years in his head
It really be 6 years
Since he'd already spent a few years in ody us
Probably less than six
It is granted judicial release
Bingham County with all these guys were getting walloped with big sentences
Joshua had a fresh perspective on the number 6
17 years
Dislike
Compare two double digits he was saying
Maybe six was a lucky break
Joshua's brought to court the morning of his hearing he still didn't know what he was going to do
He met with Jim hosek
Who laid out the probable truth
But today nine years was the best case scenario
Joshua took the deal
Dashiell proceeding is hard to stomach
Joshua stood there
Crying
A few of his umpteen yes ma'ams barely Audible
And that you have demonstrated by your conduct
That Rehabilitation during the remaining period of juvenile jurisdiction is unlikely
I want point the judge ask someone to fetch Joshua some Kleenex
No one had come to his rescue
His father hadn't hired the private lawyer he said he was going to hire
Joshua civil attorneys never did file a lawsuit on Joshua's behalf
The Indian River staff who told Joshua that stick up for him vouch for his progress
Not here
I learn they've been firmly reminded
You work for odys
While we're at it we're the FBI agents would seem to like Joshua back in 2014
When I told him to check on him
I got it
Who's all too messy
Too much
All those incidents on the list
The contacts
Tit for Tat who started what
Too messy
Told me
Sure we could have picked apart three or four of the incidents on that list
Explained
Fights on paper are more intricate than they appear
What about the 40 other items
Teetering just behind
They're going to be crushed them hoes like said
But the sheer volume of incidents
One person who had shown up
Josh was only Witness
Lashayla Turner
Joshua is Mentor from Freedom School
She said gym hopefully I could contact her yesterday
She thought she might be called upon to testify
The Turner was upset
I thought it could be spot she said
I really thought I could be fought
In his letter to invoke Joshua's syo
What do is it written that there was no more they could do to rehabilitate Joshua
After no additional interventions and treatments that can be attempted
It is unfortunate they wrote
That he threw away the opportunity he was given
Stadia that Joshua is unfixable was Turner said
That part of it is completely yes
Miss Turner isn't some wide-eyed advocate
She's worked with lots of kids in juvenile facilities
For masters in public administration with a focus on youth policy
She's from East Cleveland
To the deep and personal experience with the good and the bad of gangs
She agrees that some of the kids at Indian River aren't ready to come out yet
But they are still works in not quite enough progress
Joshua though she said he is not one of the ones she most worried about
And he's not one of the ones odys should be most worried about
She does not accept that he hasn't progressed
Because to her
Joshua at 19 such a far cry from Joshua at 16
When he was the Hot Head Eric and a****** that judge when you met at first that I met verse
There's no doubt in my mind that that's when the conversation should have been had
The conversation of should we find them out absolutely because he's becoming expensive facility and he was a child.
Could he be rehabilitated a question of the big guy had a complete question and didn't think that he could
Sister said the only fight they had in Freedom School inside the facility only one
Joshua
His first week in the program he stood up on a chair and spit on somebody like I mean just outraged
Even in conversation with him after that it was his
Arrogance to him it was this
Haughtiness
Lily doesn't exist in him
Anymore
Sota now
Serious conversation completely change
I want to get out of here I want to be a better person
I'm asking
To not be put into these situations I'm asking you put on a different unit
Saratoga this been crying out
Saying
This is what I need
I want to get out of this
And you ignore that
What most disturbs Miss Turner
It was Joshua whose ethics and behavior were being scrutinized and punished
I know no one would look at what the state had done to him
I think Joshua is the
Best case example
FYI
Is so bogus when we have these expectations for kids to speak up about what's happening in the community as a test of
And things like that and we see the ramifications
And how we don't wrap around to protect that
I think the biggest issue isn't that Joshua hasn't held up his end of the bargain
Is that the state hasn't held up theirs
Family protected him
Having protected him from the gang he inflamed
By testifying for the state
More in a minute
This is the road tired
Brought to you by zip recruiter Michelle sarzen has figured out a way
If your dog to talk to you well kind of voice
But we don't have that what our device lives due to the mobile app is like your dog to build that communication
Bu
And tell you that hey I'm not scratching I'm getting good sleep
I am happy
Marcel's the CEO of vectrex
A device that your dog wears on her collar
Can monitor how many second she spends each day
Scratching your head running and walking
Basically is a health and fitness tracker for dogs
When owners are away from the dogs at work they can check in on the app to see how their pup is doing
Marcel uses vectrax on his dog
Pepper
She's always had kind of
No ears
Smelly ears
What do they smell like
The smell is probably a lot like a ichiza starting to spoil
Which is a symptom of an ear infection
What's the sensor on her collar we know the Baseline number is for her amount of shaking that she does their head
Stanley she starts now increasing that by 25 or 50%
She's trying to tell me
I am doing a couple my ears are hurting me
Marcel you ZipRecruiter
When you started looking for a pet wearables analyst
An easily found someone who is just the right fit
The thing you like most about a search
Was at ZipRecruiter has a mobile app to
If I saw some that really excited me I could reach out to her immediately
On the go
Just like the tracks connect you to the pet you care about when you're not at home when you're not at the office ZipRecruiter connect you to the
Candidates you care about
Yeah. That's a great comparison
Cy ZipRecruiter is the fast efficient way to hire from anywhere
Dog park
Tried for free at ziprecruiter.com cereal
At ZipRecruiter. Com serial
ZipRecruiter the smartest way to hire
And you found someone who is just the right fit
He found someone who is just the right
Support for serial comes from Squarespace
Make your business official with Google in Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and a Business website with Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and professional tools from Google
It's the simplest way to look professional online
Visit squarespace.com Google to start your free trial
And use offer code professional for a discount on your first purchase
Google and Squarespace
Make it professional make it beautiful
After the hearing Joshua was taken back to the county lockup
Peter go to be shipped out to prison within a few days
That's supposed to happen once your sentence
Joshua's understanding was that early on a Tuesday or Thursday morning
They're going to drive him from County Jail to an intake prison about 40 minutes from Cleveland
Are they figure out where to put you
What's going to be your home Institution
But a couple of Tuesdays and Thursdays came and went
And Joshua sat
In limbo
He wasn't getting either of the two medications he said he's been prescribed for his brain injury
None of his personal stuff that followed him from Indian River
His papers and photographs and notebooks
And also I need to emphasize
County Jail sucks
Go Google it
Cuyahoga County Jail
To the headline
Cleveland judge
I will not send people to jail after 6
Inmate dies in 4 months
Granted that was a post Joshua headline
But it was true that as well
County is not a place you want to spend even one extra day
Insult to injury Joshua had no money on his books
He couldn't buy any edible food or an extra t-shirt or normal toothbrush or minutes on a phone account
Why were they keeping him in County
What do they want with him
Yeah I think that's pretty much what's happening
Yeah
After it sat in jail for a month of Tuesdays and Thursdays
I emailed him hopefully to ask Anton age
Can you explain why Joshua still in County
His response
Joshua Stone County
Jim hope it wasn't Joshua's lawyer anymore
He said he'd look into it
Kim discovered a communication breakdown between the juvenile court and the county sheriff's office which one's the jail
Administratively no one knew or seem to notice or care that they didn't know who had jurisdiction over Josh
Joshua
But Jim said they clear it up
Josh and I developed a new routine
He called me and asked
Any word from history
Can I say something like
So apparently now everybody knows what's up and
Lady doctors for you
Nope that was early November
Late November
2 months after you've been sentenced
Joshua was still lousy and County
I'd run out of encouraging reports from the outside
Somebody at some point has to do something that's what that's all I know
Somebody at some point we'll have to do something they cannot keep you in County Jail indefinitely
I don't know what they doing
The metaphor could not have been clumsier
The government had forgotten about Joshua
In County Jail
Joshua was bored
Sometimes it be cooked in a Cell they all would be really 24 hours straight
I noticed
The Joshua
He wasn't raging
Women getting in fights
You know you sound like you sound pretty good
Cuz it's too much Tramadol is too much
Stressful donor
Interest less stressful there
Bingham County jail with a stress reliever
Just did their jobs as far as you could tell
People are nicer to one another
More relaxed with one another more supportive he said
Who's noticing what I noticed in the shift from middle school to high school just because one person didn't like you. Didn't mean
In the whole pod was against you
It was something of a revelation to him even white people do okay in here he said
The other young man I'd spoken to Leo Malik Davon white kid named wave
We've been in both odys and then an adult jail
But all agreed
That is it was
Dangerous as it was
Still better than juvenile
Less stress
The same feeling
Less stress more relaxed
Would stretch out and hold true when Joshua arrived at adult prison
Define Alicia
11.5 weeks after he been sentenced
Place called Allen Oakwood Correctional
In Lima Ohio
Set a 3 hour drive from Cleveland
Swiss Family couldn't visit
But Joshua was just happy to be sprung from his cell
She walking back and forth just cuz I can
Because he cooperated
An adult enemies lurked in adult prison
Joshua was put in protective custody
No heartless felons on his unit
He wasn't feuding with other inmates are getting into it with CEOs
Joshua marveled
There were fewer guards yet the inmates had more freedom
Part of it was maturity he said people trying to get home to your kids
The main reason the adult system was better he said
Was because it was harsher
Haider less forgiving ship all around
If you fight or act out
Throw your in on a CSA
Severe consequences rain down
Sissy
Another one
You're saying in juvenile the worst that could happen if you shut up in your room for the day
Transferring kissing adult prison
Are you Tony Toni Tone
Guards hero put their hands on you he said
They do not play
You could lose your phone calls or visitation
You can fester in the whole 4 months
The whole especially major deterrent he said
Nodejs
The longest your health in seclusion is 4 hours
Joshua said
Juveniles take advantage of that s***
The max
If you were to propose
Juvenile Justice Reform
It would be
That they should be stricter
You
The only understands who you feel me
County Jail was better than juvenile
Adult prison was better than County Jail
Harsher punishment
Was better than let at 8
Joshua's world had rotated 180
Adult prison was going to be like he said he would have skipped juvenile
You said to those cops and prosecutors back in 2014
Just buy me over
I'll take my chances
Corporation had gotten him nothing he said no real benefit
I said what about a shorter sentence though three armed robberies in adult Court
Good morning time in the teens or twenties event
He said look at my co-defendants
Half of them already out
Yeah you run your finger down the list of the 13 people named in the cut for an indictment bunch of them got two or three years
Only if you are serving more significant sentences
11 years 13 years
Joshua B. 9
To just come straight here he said that having my ass beaten odys for 3 years
Joshua was in prison
The six years ticking
For my purposes
In terms of plot
His story had ended
But he kept calling kept calling
And I kept answering
I just took a 10-minute break in fact because you called me while I was writing these sentences
I learned day-by-day what Joshua's life was turning into
On the cusp of 20 years old
In protective custody
State police officers near me
Lawyer
Pharmacy
About 60 people who couldn't mix with the general prison population in a different building across the street
Cops
Reasons I never fully understood a lot of whites
Supremacist
Aryan Brotherhood
Just said everyone seemed to get along okay
Abtech School
I got no problem with them
Anyways are you kind of had to get along
The unit was too small for anything else
Turn off phone calls from Indian River
I often hear hollering in the background
Now from Allen Correctional I can hear the soft click of billiard balls
Are pool table in the dining room
Joshua was the youngest on the potty said that he didn't feel like the adults around and we're dangerous
An adult in charge of the prison didn't feel like Joshua was dangerous
Odys Atty Joshua as a gang member
Reset the game coordinator for the adult prison system
How to chat with them checked out his history with tattoos
Did not tag him as gang affiliated
On a scale of 1 to 5 5 being supermax material
Joshua was designated a level 2 prisoner
Sacrifice of being a prisoner in protective custody
Does the closeness of the unit and the tedium
Joshua says he couldn't take advantage of some of the programs and apprenticeships across the street
Regine Pappas house
He was feeling the time
Feeling the time
But people
Joshua's intensely social
Is a talent for Gathering people
Pulling people towards him
Including people who can help him out
Acme
I do I'm small favors
Favors the reporter shouldn't really do
Connecting him to the outside world
Mostly by three-way phone calls
My most immediate benefit to Joshua was at
I like most of the people in his life
I could afford an endless supply of Global Tel Link minutes
Alright what's the number
2 + 6
Joshua want to contact
Continual contact
Usually with family
I became the operator
The Joshua
Yellow
Your granddad's on the phone
Hello
Hey grandson
Joshua's troubles aren't news to his family obviously
Incarceration isn't news to them either
Even so it's heavy information when it comes
What's up man
I heard Mindy and Josh Mann
Break my heart
Your dad told me what happened
Joshua live with his grandfather for a year and is about 12
What you say
You say it's right
I'm good right now
Josh's relative said it was okay to use these recordings
Stanley's huge they live all over
In Cleveland of course but also in Florida California Jamaica
Skype
Funny little niece his great-grandmother his aunts and cousins parents sisters
His daughter
And every call he tells them he loves them
And they say it back
I love you
I love you too baby
When Josh was for his father was arrested by the DEA for conspiracy to distribute more than a thousand kg of marijuana and
And United States
Get along sentence in federal prison
His mother went to prison a couple years later
Once they were both locked up what happened was what you might imagine would happen to a kid longing for his absent parents
He floated from house to house
Miserable
Probably the most stable person in his life is his grandmother
She was legal guardian
He lived with her for long stretches growing up
I put you in the back to you member
Hello
By the time he was 13 Joshua began to paying at the Juvenile Court
Initially for petty stuff
Being unruly fighting at school
I got more serious
XIV was caught for strong arm robbery
And some friends mug are they new
Joshua sent to an odys residential facility
He escaped
Honda Brio with a friend
Call the sister from a gas station pay phone
She drove out to collect them
Once he was home
Heartless felons drug dealing guns
Strawberries
We held up the two BP is in the Popeyes
He was 15
50 Cent baby daughter was born
2 months later
The FBI came to get them
Hello
Hey Mami
Thank you your mommy 40 years old
Sometimes in the calls
It feels like the Master Clock of Joshua's immediate family is the criminal justice system itself
Continual pulse of court dates and visitation forms and commissary money
We come down there to drop the money off
Joshua knew I was recording these calls
Occasionally we discuss the content afterwards
Debrief
Mybatis relationship
Is open like that
Strikingly so
And you know I was rooting for him
Sometimes you call me
Just call me
I'm recording I don't know why
Fascinating to tell me
But
Yeah I got it on Friday
He was relieved
Joshua wrestled with the language arts portion of his GED twice before
Former odys guard who Joshua was a younger teenager had described him as impressionable
The kind of person who do good if he's around good
Too bad if he's around bad
Adult prison is filled by and large with adult criminals
I kept an antenna up for signs a Joshua might be listing toward Darkness
Sometimes I hear a hard blade of anger in his voice
He starts wearing more on the phone
I can really tell what that meant
Maybe was just more comfortable with me
Maybe it's just in a bad mood
On the positive side
Joshua become friends with an ex cop on the protective custody unit
A big guy who Joshua laughingly told me it was making his huge muscles even Huger
Working out all the time
Does ex-cop
Denayne Dixon
Hermes Cleveland
Jesse Nickerson case
The officer who taking Jesse to the park and pleaded guilty to a couple felonies as a result
Joshua really like the name
The new people in common
And today like Joshua
He's funny and charismatic today and told me
Feels like having a little brother around
Those interested in Janine's assessment
Once Joshua got out
Did you think Joshua could have an okay future
When that didn't include Perpetual incarceration
Right now at this point
Because why
Treason
Negativity
I hated this answer
Because Joshua was bound over he would now have an adult felony record
Joshua knew that would react the most long-term damage to his prospects once he got out
Tattoos began creeping back onto his hands and neck and face
All the places you had them removed before
I spent many phone calls looking up people on the internet for Joshua people he knew from
Cleveland County Jail
Charges he was asking
Are they going to trial
People who already been sentenced
How long they got
Which institution can give me the inmate number tell me the zip code again
Who's writing to them
Making contact
But some of the people he was having me look up their cases sounded terrible
Premeditated murder
A shot and then burned in a car
I asked him what are you doing
Looks like what you did with your pass is
That I'm not here to judge nobody
Like nobody is perfect everybody in this world made bad choices before
Sim Indiana
So might be there for a long time so you can suck you need
Good friends
Turn on lights lights
Sometimes a good friend
He was being kind
And I understood he was trying to give other people what he himself needed
Reminder that he wasn't a piece of s***
Throughs forgivable
Redeemable
He was taking a position far more Humane than the one that Criminal Justice System had taken with him
Try to think for a minute about why I was getting angry
I realized this community of inmates who was stitching together
Was worrying me
When you got out
So I think my reaction and having is like
Could you just please stay the f*** away from some criminals for a while so that
I'm not falling back into that world
And I think that's why I'm having this reaction which is it
Stairs to you
Sometimes you send me so that's why I
It is like like it's not that
Feisty
It's tempting to think that all this prison and Punishment lead somewhere
But there's a goal we can point to
People who commit crimes
Maybe if they turn their lives around a Civic reward awaits them back home
For someone like Joshua
It's hard to imagine what that reward would be
Ms Turner I told me the young men she's worked with inside the prison
Could you been able to crack open their feelings make themselves vulnerable
She's watched many of them come home
And then crumble
Because they're back and violent neighborhoods where they need armor to survive
She told me
The most successful ones I hate to say the ones that are communicating that they actually feel Joy
Are the ones who went back to the streets
Joshua new
You said it to me many times his only chance of survival was to never go back to Cleveland
If you returned home he was going to end up hurting someone
Or getting hurt
Right back at the Justice Center
The year we were in Cleveland
More than 13000 felony cases move through the Justice Center
Brutalist Tower downtown 26 stories high
Hundreds of people coming in every day
Wound up emotional
Maybe watching a little TV will help them relax
That was the idea when the court had TVs installed in the waiting areas near the courtroom
On the 15th floor an older woman's weeping
To retreat into the ladies room
I can hear howling in there
Comes back out still crying
A young man maybe it's her son is folded over head in his hands
Write about them
The Food Network
That's the courthouse soundtrack
Clean kitchen cupboards well-stocked
Administrative judge auditioned other options
The news
Took setting
History Channel and boom there's something about the Nazis in the concentration camps
Sound of Animal Planet Cartoon Network
In the end
The most reliably soothing
Food Network
It does lolyou
You forget for a moment
How much is happening all over this building
Sturdy an attorney or the mean to hire an attorney
In the space of a year all those thousands of cases begin here in the arrangement room
Crucial decisions are made in the arraignment room
The judge chooses your lawyer if you can't afford one you can't usually
Signs your case to a courtroom future Bond
Adjusted up or down if you want keeps you in jail or lets you out
Didn't really quite understand it
Dozens of people are waiting their turn with this judge available at the ready big pilot case holders
Pakistan Embassy
Asking questions slows the Rhythm
Toyota Sienna
Arraignment is the Justice Center intake valve
The Russian cases now process
They all wish upstairs into court rooms
About 2133 words
But enclosed many thousands of plea Bargains this year
Knowingly
Voluntarily
Are you doing this voluntarily
Involuntarily knowingly intelligently and voluntarily made
Floors down judge Daniel Gaul just re-elected by the way
Tell the defendant to pull up his pants
The guy's been in jail
Don't have a belt
Pull your trousers up
19th floor at Ryals just beginning jury selection
The jury pool
All white
C-41 woman is black
Jefferson it at a law firm
The defense attorney starts asking her questions
She's awesome
I think I have to go full disclosure hair
I am not emotionally
Ready to participate
In our legal system I have
So much
Personal disappointment
In
The inequities in our system
Ground floor in the hallway outside the doors to the county jail
A crowd is waiting
Fermenting Evan came to walkout
He spent 22 years in prison for murder he didn't do
People are singing Crying
Nacm
Exonerated
Radiohead
Repair
Outside on the street
Police officers from all over the county in the state
March in the annual Memorial parade
Honoring to local police officers who died during the past year in the line of duty
Separate incidents
The boat hit by cars while working on the highway
Backup on 18
Ninja Turtles courtroom sentencing
The brother of a murdered woman gives a statement
He talks quietly angrily for a few minutes
Is he glad the defendant is going to suffer every day in prison
I'm just act like you are
Seems like maybe he's winding down
And then he launches himself like a missile
At the defendant
Another sentencing for triple murder in a barbershop
The capital case
The courtrooms crammed
Relatives of the victims and of the defendant kill the gallery
The media set up in the jury box
Their cameras and microphones
Amanda and Alvin Wright comes forward
He was a victim in the case
I've been cutting someone's hair when shooting exploded the shop
These are people in New get killed
Alvin Wright had testified for the prosecution at trial
Now just before the judge issues her final decision
Whether she's going to sentence the defendant is 21
To death
Alvin Wright addresses the court
How situations f***** up
I mean
Guess what I'm dealing with though
The judge tells him to court of law
There's different words
Go ahead
I mean
The situation is messed up
List of situations
Do I agree with
Putting them down like a dog
No
Ain't nobody win
You put it down we don't get nobody back
Nothing
Just like we did we just keep losing
Dis black people. You just keep losing
You got all these white people right here
They looking at us like us like me in the zoo
This real s***
Atlanta Zoo
Nah, I'm just I'm just looking at the big picture up
Look at this
That's life
We got to do better than that
Best kept secret in the Justice Center is in the lobby it stuck between two pillars near the elevators
Looks like a wheel you might say to raffler bingo game
Three functions as a suggestion box
You can send kites for the staff
Administrative judge will get them
He's got the key
Hang around this building for your I have many suggestions just off the top of my head
Cool minimalist
Don't file charges on to a single crime when one charge will do
Don't overcharge the force that guilty plea
Don't lock anyone up unless they're demonstrable violent
Admit that police officers lie under oath
Get out of the punishment business and turned for the Urgent problem of fairness
Keep obsessive track of who exactly is being charged with what crime
Other setting shakes out and what their life looks like in 3 years or 5 years
Take me to the color of their skin and how much money they have
Don't share what you learn in a drawer and forget about it
Don't be insensibly tempted as Charles Dickens wrote
Into a loose way of letting bad things alone to take their own bad course
Cops prosecutors judges lawyers
Call out the colleagues who degrade your profession
Find attorneys in public defenders at least twice as much as you're paying them now
Judges stop choosing attorneys citizens mix up the bench stop electing judges County
Overall slowdown doubt yourself
I know how corny the sounds but
Imagine that every person in the elevator car is part of your own family
And reflect on the far-reaching paying of prosecution
Also don't take anyone's mouth shut in court that happened
And consider getting rid of the grand jury
I could cram that will to bursting
If I'm only allowed one suggestion
I say
Let's all accept that something's gone wrong
Let's make that our premise
Many times during a reporting in Cleveland when I ask about problems are reforms
Someone would throw out
Well let's remember we have the best system in the world
County prosecutor Michael O'Malley said it to me
I just think people need to realize we have the best criminal justice system in the world
The people who operate that system know about the wards and they can see we can always improve
But generally they're not chomping for an overhaul
The kind of Extreme Makeover that the data is screaming at us to undertake
We've all heard the stats
That we here in the United States
Imprison a vastly higher percentage of our population than any other country in the world
We are number one
The numbers are well-documented
Wildly out of whack
And unprecedented in our history
Also will document
Inequity
Every joint in the skeleton of our criminal justice system
Is Greece by racial discrimination
Compared to white people who committed the same crime and who have similar criminal histories
Black people and other people of color
Are rested more often they're charged more harshly given higher Bales offered where's plea deals they're handed longer prison sentences
Center probation is more often revoked
These numbers aren't floating above us in the sky they're alive all over the country
Look at studies from New York city in Alabama in Wisconsin and Iowa 6th District and Hampton Roads Virginia and Harris County Tech
Is everywhere and all are courthouses
Reporters often hear that we only report the bad stories
Exaggerated sensationalize especially when it comes to law enforcement or wonky prosecutions
But we didn't go to Cleveland and sift through hundreds of cases looking for the most egregious and justices we could find
We don't have to be ordinary ones
Told us everything we needed to know
Ciro's produced by Julie Schneider
With additional reporting by Eataly has koskey
Nancy Updike tape transcription by Robin Smith
Whitney Dangerfield is our digital editor research and fact-checking by Ben Phelan sound design a mix by Stone Nelson
Music clearance by Anthony Roman Southland is our director of operations the serial staff includes Emily Condon Julie Whitaker
Cassie Howley Francis Swanson and Matt Tierney
Our music is by Adam Dorn and Hal willner with additional music from Matt McGinley I theme song is by Nick thorburn Andrea
Next by Adam door this is our final episode this season so we have some special thank-yous Arte bloggers
Valerie Caesar Beth card nicale Rector Sarah starter and Meredith Francis thanks to the entire staff at the
Cuyahoga County Criminal Justice Center thanks to Ed ference Kevin Brickman Julian Eckert Joe Buckley rhyme a day and Cassidy
McCaffrey
At the juvenile courthouse thanks to Mary Davidson and Gregory Moore thanks also to Kimberly Henderson at least bergersen Sarah
Adams Bennett Epstein Lisa Noller Melissa George's IL gutentag Atty suker Ryan Iyengar
Call me Mohammed Christina hagner a net Navi ad results media Keisha Ladson Angela Ladson
Friedman Kevin kilbane Addison Riley Tom Shaughnessy Eric Norton when defense Danny trevathan
The Ohio highway patrol and Amy Gifford at the Stark County Clerk of Courts also a personal thanks to Jeff
Melman Venture and Arlene Richmond and huge things to Rich Oris who builds and manages are fantastic
Website The Talented team at my studio did the animation and illustration for this episode and it is great you can
Check it out on our website at serial podcast. Org that is serial podcast. Org where you can also sign up for email
Newsletter
Occasionally will take the show on the road and hold events at theaters and university is so if you're interested sign up for our newsletter and we'll send
I need the details for those and for our next season and new projects
Again you can sign up at serial podcast. Org
Support for serial comes from ZipRecruiter unlike many job sites ZipRecruiter doesn't wait for candidates to find you
ZipRecruiter finds them for you so you get qualified candidates
Fast
Try it free at ziprecruiter.com cereal
Ziprecruiter.com cereal
Support for serial comes from Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and Business website with Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and professional tools from Google
Use offer code professional for discount on your first purchase
Serials production of This American Life and WBEZ Chicago