Hello serial listeners
It's Sarah Cain egg with a quick reminder
That we have
Two other podcast
There's This American Life weekly show that chooses one theme and then has a mix of weird emotional and
Investigative
And personal stories on that
Cereal started as a spin-off of
Are we developed our storytelling jobs
And also asked
A beautiful 7-part series that explores the life of one man in Alabama
S town starts out as one thing and then becomes something
Totally
Fascinatingly differ
This American Life and s-town
Available now on podcast apps
Or At This americanlife.org and s-town podcast
First plan was
Go from point A to point B
Previously
I'm cereal
Opie master
Probably the worst place
Humanly imaginable that place sucks
He had to go
The bucket everyone should and then he was in the town asking if people spoke English
Or somebody like that
Quechee 10-second and doors one minute wrinkle has a baby this is our mission
He's one of our guys we got to find him we're going to do it if we would have found them
I think a lot of us would a shot mm yeah yeah I still
Awesome so I think I'm so angry about it
Before Mark started asking but what
Why did he walk away from his
I had already talked about it to General Kenneth Dahl
That was in charge of investigating what bow did and writing up a report for the Army
His inquiry was confined to the. That led up to Bose decision to leave
Not those time with the Taliban or anything just
White Ewok
Mark asbill about the statement he gave General doll
How long is your statement
300 pages
Shut up it's 300 pages
300 + pages
Are you f****** serious dude
Your statement is 380 pages
Why
What did you do tell him every f****** meal you had when you were deployed
That was the
He told me to tell the story
Pick me up
Our military hearing doll said he and both spoke over the course of a day and a half
Quote and frankly at the end of that I had no more questions to ask him
And he had no more story to tell me
So exhausted each other and we were done
Unquote
Statement of what happened that night
Whatever
You wanted to understand
Nobody knew who I was because I was so quiet okay stand that I thought it was just
Just about the deployment
I need to go back and explain to you where it began
From This American Life and WBEZ Chicago its serial
One story told week by week
I'm Sara Canning
And fear not I am not going to take you through every one of those 380 some pages
But in the next two episodes we are going to zoom back in so you can understand what dollar landmark and I
I came to understand about bow
Whether he told the truth about what he did
And what does truth be told
Because those are two different questions
What is the things that's interesting to me about bow
Is Eddie Brooks is cardinal rule of the military
He left his unit
Walked away from his
But at the same time he was completely devoted to being a good soldier
And up until the day he left he was a good soldier
At the military hearing his former weapons squad leader guy named Greg Leatherman
So the leadership you should do this thing sort of like fantasy football like a mock draft
If you could form a squad from anyone in the company who would you choose
And first pick you know Sergeant Bergdahl was going to be the first pick for everyone almost every time
He said he was a great Soldier
He did things like study the ranger handbook which is something we were all supposed to do but none of us actually did you look through
The way you get to know some say yeah I look at it it's Jason fry
Using Bose platoon they were friends
The ranger handbook is a pocket guide for soldiers on tactics and techniques
He come back he highlighted you look at it and study it and Leadership saw that and they were like well you know this guy's trying
He cares about his job he cares about what he's doing
And
I think that's
Pet significant as far as understanding but he isn't a person who
Carelessly does something
Back then school with special forces
He joined the army in 2008 and was assigned to the 1st Battalion the five-oh-first Infantry Regiment
Blackfoot company
As an infantry Soldier you are so far from Special Forces
You're a Workhorse
You're the guys who get sent out to guard a traffic control point in the middle of nowhere Afghanistan
Intended to be a faultless example of an infantryman
He volunteered for extra Duty
Took impeccable care of his weapon
Helping other people with their jobs when he was done with his
Show Dexter snacks in his paw
In case the other guys got hungry
He was fit
One of his former platoon mates told me he was a PT stud
PTSD often dreaded physical training soldiers have
He was with military people call squared away
Right place right time right uniform
Everybody agrees
The other thing people will say about Bobak's
Is that is not your typical grown
They can all described below
But not one of them would say they totally got him
Understood what made him tick
Chain cross was friends with Bo also there in the same Platoon
You said was an isolated from the group he just wasn't into the usual stuff
These guys play video games
Odin
They talk about sex in women
It's a I'm not into that kind of thing
He didn't want to hear live the average now
Derek Soldier lifestyle
Of drinking
All night all weekend everything
He would always listen to classical music YouTube read a lot
Would he ever joke around
David sense of humor
Humor
Joining the community of
Teasing joking around
Not the extent that mostly soldiers will
Now playing the grab a stirring stuff
He kept journals he tried to study things
Pashto for instance
In the quietness it's just how bow is he's an introvert
It was also intention
Best way to create the least amount of friction
Don't run your mouth and act like a
Don't get in people's personal space
Don't go out of your way like a know-it-all
If you're quiet if you're off to the side if you listen and if you watch
Can you view help people
And you're able to help because you're watching your seeing me when somebody needs help
Take it off
He doesn't want to annoy anyone
Or create a problem
He's thinking about the best way he can contribute to the collective how he can be most useful
You like the perfect guest
Except that this strong philosopher nerd component he has
People might find it interesting
Or irritating
Example
Pick up smoking
Sort of
A lot of private smoke cigarettes
But he smoked a pipe
The other guys were hunkered up in the windows smoking cigarettes
Bring his pipe
So you know even though I don't smoke there and you know I'm going out now
Deal with the guys because
If you look at the cigarette
Bonding
But he was participating
With an anthropological band
Probably be the first to admit that he had a bit of a 10-year for social interaction some
Not with everyone but with some
1 * Akbar I was talking about wanting to travel around Europe go to Amsterdam
For all the reasons a young man would want to go to amps
Whose contribution
He talked about Amsterdam's major exports and the financial stability of the Netherlands
Yeah cuz I got to do that weird like you would tell stories like that or talked about women and he's like
Make a factory renewed
What was a factor of endued
The problem was
He wasn't always great in the moment
At sorting out what was fact and what was it
First time in the Army started out okay
Get specific ideas about leadership
About how you practice it
And in basic training at Fort Benning Georgia both found what he was looking for
Senior drill sergeant who is everything he felt like a military leader should be
Yeah
Full size of everyone he came into contact with in the army
Nice things to say about the confidence of some of his platoon mates or
Couple of the Sergeants
As far as I was concerned not one leader especially the guys up the chain
Hold a candle to the senior drill sergeant
Like I told General.
Guardian Afghanistan
Log back in my memory
A worrisome catalog began to compile
Heifers just a comment here there
We got to his unit in Alaska where the first of the five-oh-first
Based
Someone suggested belt lock up his stuff
Because otherwise I might get Swype
Advice to a new car
The both thought
How am I supposed to go onto a Battlefield
I can't even trust these guys here
All those years later he remembered it and he told it to General Dollar
Then there was a comment by the command sergeant major
Ken Wolfe
Prior to deployment wolf did a full formal inspection of the battalion
While I was at it he explained to them what the mission would be in Afghanistan
Early sweat it wouldn't be
And basically gave
The same speech are the same spill
To all 14
Which was
Hey we're not going here to rape kill pillage
Burn
It we're doing just the opposite of that
And I said I know lots of you guys
Join the Army to do that
And everybody
In the organization
Found the humor
In that
Not Bow he did not find the humor in that
Wilfit joke that he join back in 83
The rape kill pillage and burn also
Even if he understood it was intended as a joke
He did not think it was funny
You find it distressing
He told all he was taken aback
In early 2009
Who sent an email from Alaska to his family and friends
Call my deployment dates to Afghanistan have been set to the 9th or 10th of March so the countdown has started
I'm looking forward to the next year of learning and challenges
He rode marched in a pair of new boots trying to break them in
I got a blister on his left foot that turned into a serious staph infection had to go to the
Tri-State back on what's called rear D rear detachment
But almost everyone else shipped off
Pacheco Province Eastern Afghanistan
When they land
Spring of 2009
Was a turning point for US forces there
The Taliban and other anti-government groups had pushed back into the country in a big way
There were Taliban Shadow governors in 33 as a country's 34 provinces
Casualties
Almost every measure we were losing
President Obama had ordered a review of the war when he came into office that year and by the end of March in a speech he declare
Play the situation quote increasingly perilous on quote we've been focused as a country and as a military on a
Iraq
Now he said we be turning our attention back to Afghanistan
In the next year we more than double our troop numbers there
To meet The Surge the Army was scrambling for recruits issuing waivers to people who might not have qualified a few years earlier
And units like the first of the five-oh-first bows Battalion that had just done a 15-month tour in Iraq
We're coming home absorbing new recruits and turning around and heading back into war this time to Afghanistan
The day after Obama made his increasingly perilous speech those Battalion officially began its mission in Afghanistan
And that mission was counterinsurgency
Coin pusher
General David Petraeus had embraced the doctrine
In 2006 he co-wrote a new counterinsurgency manual for the Army
Explained
Koi means you're not just going to be fighting
Soldiers and Marines are expected to be Nation Builders as well as Warriors
Study of coin in Afghanistan was to be back the enemy
And at the same time train the Afghan Security Forces to take over the fight themselves
And very important
To build support among the people for the Afghan government
Try to win them over
Shore up the economy the infrastructure
So that they'll turn away from the insurgents
Became clear hold
Build transfer
Ambitrans is Manuel there's a graphic of something that looks sort of like a double A battery
At one end are the people who are for the cause
Are the other other people who are against the cause
Everything in between was the quote uncommitted middle
Those for the people we wanted to pull over to our side
Basically the first few months all we are doing was
Making sure
Direct routes to other fobs were
Securecrt
And kind of showing
Horse I guess Orwell
Making yourself known I guess to the townspeople for the first few months
That Zack borrow
Any uncertainty in his voice about what exactly they were doing
A lot of the soldiers felt that way
I got in contact with a lot of these guys through marks company page one by the way
Super helpful
Some of the coins stuff made shenzhen
The soldiers
They might backup Afghan police and submission
Are they help rebuild a hospital
But other stuff seems fuzzier
They're doing a lot of handing out bag of salt things of ghee
Bags of rice we would hand out crayons for
For the kids
Hey
Distinctly remember the
Map puzzles of Afghanistan with watercolor paint set we handed out quite a bit of those
Does John Thurman
There was a lot of confusion
You know cuz infantryman we
A Divine definition we're not supposed to be doing humanitarian things
And we've been
We've been trained
From the get-go in basic training you know
Your mission is to close with and destroy the enemy
Anywhere
Out there hanging out
In a watercolor maps of Afghanistan wondering how is this going to work
How do we beat the Taliban this way
Is Mark Krikorian Shane cross a lot of guys were a little bit
Weirded out by
Going out and shaking hands and
You know I figured it'd be a little bit more shooting involved you want to go meet the enemy of someone take there's a bag over there you go find them and kill them
Not go give his mother-in-law sunflower
To convince her to be join your side you know
About two months after Bose platoon deployed on May 13th 2009
Finally joined up with them at fob sharana
Chain cross brought him to the barracks
But I could definitely pick up on his disappointment
He realize
What we're doing where we're living Cafe
Why
What was he disappointed about
He wanted hardships I think
I would like like Serana was to
Kakashi
Yeah we had a
Weird hardstand rooms
I want something to bambang can you put all your stuff on the top bunk
I think I will just want to have you wanted
I see what hardship you wanted more
What you been seen in the movies
I mean he
He wants he buys matching for his mattress
Danny stop on the springs
It was like a box spring was just the
Metal coils going across the
Wooden frame of the bed
Leslie on that
He was wearing a knives
She's big and not in the big Knife Guy
He slept
He hiked
Tomahawk
I slept with
When where's the tomahawk
Is challenge Jess holding it
I wanted to be a security contractor after
Special Forces
He didn't want that movie version of the military
Moment of adrenaline I wanted that moment
You know
Your contacts
I'm getting gun fights
Yeah
Less than a week after Bo arrived at his base his platoon did see action
Kona mountain plateau
And this incident and it's aftermath became the first solid building block in Buzz argument for triggering a dust one
They went on a mission to Amna
A district Center up in the mountains
I spoke to a bunch of the soldiers who were there and they all said it was the scariest thing that happened during their deployment
They've been caught up in the middle of the night to help out another Convoy that it hit an ID
That first time boy had been trying to help Afghan Security Forces up and Amna
Did recently come under Fire
But they had no idea up there and so now both Splatoon was going to recover the disabled vehicle
This was like our first
Mission like we're going somewhere we're doing something
Does Josh quarter
It was a mission that was supposed to take maybe eight hours
To get up to Amna that have to drive up to the plateau
Adjust the drive itself is heroin
The road isn't much bigger than a goat path
There's a steep drop off the side there's no room for error
And they're driving a huge trucks brand new mine-resistant trucks
Just a giant tank
Play the best description I could give but it was a really nice tank it had like leather seats and air conditioning
And since like all the
All the new stuff cuz we just literally got them
How does a dog sound like a goat path though
Well honestly a little bit better than you might expect we didn't know
Cuz we just we were brand-new to him cuz we were driving home these before that so
We're driving up this mountain and the truck right in front of me
On the last visit the second-to-last vehicle
Just explode
Austin Lanford was in the same truck as Josh
And then it just disappeared in the dust
Like I didn't see any more I was like did the truck just fall off the cliff like is it going like
We started
Trying to call
Them and be like hey are you okay are you there like where what's going on
And then like pieces of the truck fell on our truck
But they were okay
That's the beauty of these massive ungainly vehicles
The generic name is mrap
Mine-resistant ambush-protected
You can survive these IED explosion if you're inside
Now this mrap is severely damaged and axle is broken
Until they have to drag it the rest of the way up the mountain
Because you can't just ditch yet you never leave Army equipment in the battlefield if you can help it
Even if it's broken
An mrap has sophisticated systems in it you don't want the enemy to get those
Orgies the track for propaganda
Austin's driving the mrap behind the one that got blown up
They make everyone but him get out of his vehicle and it'll be ready to jump out in case your mrap goes over the cliff
Or if it disabled and rap falls back on you
Is terrified
But they managed it
If all the disabled and wrap the rest of the way up
District Center
What are the kind of Fort up on the plateau where some Afghan Security forces are stationed
They've been attacked by Taliban a couple of days earlier
Josh Gordon
This was like the first time that I saw something that I was like this place
It's f***** up
Bad
There's just
Bullet holes all through the walls there's
Kohl's from where RPGs hit
And like rockets were hitting them
Their towers were like worn down
Because they've been inspiring so many machine gun rounds that like the concrete was chipping away
And you just like oh my God this is
Serious
They came to rescue another vehicle and now they need rescuing
They spend the night in their trucks
They don't trust the Afghan Security Guys first of all
A second if a firefight starts they don't want to be trapped in a building
I want to be able to drive away
So they're nervous at first night
When they finally walk around they realize pretty quickly that the people up there done that don't want anything to do with them
Have no interest in interacting
It's tense
Pulling guard shifts in spending a ton of time crammed in their trucks
Yeah I can leave it to your imagination imagine guys with all full battle rattle on sitting in the extremely close
They're trying to sleep in contorted positions all your gear made it so you couldn't really fit in your seat if you were lucky enough to get
Odyssey
During the day they're so hot I'm bored so where they used in MRE box and caps from water bottles to play chess
Checkers undersupplied in every way it was just the most miserable place ever we
I had nothing and I I smoke so
We ran out of cigarettes we had like no chewing tobacco we had nothing they actually had to drop food and water
Water with airplanes because
They couldn't get to us
We didn't bring razors nobody had any changes of clothes
So
The first thing you said was we had no razors the last thing you would think about is like
Is that a thing it is a thing actually it's not okay
For the Army people to be growing a beard
You're aware all the time like yeah I got to shave I got to shave a goatee
Going to say like
Are they going to say I'm stupid because I didn't bring a razor or they can get pissed at us or thinking that like what's going to happen
Days are going by like nothing's happening the whole time they're trying to
Communicate with their commanders trying to figure out what they're supposed to do with these broken vehicles
Emacs in particular were valuable
Until they came along u.s. soldiers were getting killed and maimed by the hundreds because of IEDs in Iraq and Afghanistan
The arm wraps for the solution
I got you so much safer than a Humvee
By the time I got to Afghanistan
If soldiers were moving around on land they were pretty much in an mrap
But there weren't all that many of them yet
And they got blown up a lot
You could Frankenstein them back together if you had the right parts
But because they've been rushed into production by the dod and suppliers had scramble to get them to Market
Get something like four different models in circulation at any one time
All of which needed their own parts
You couldn't necessarily mix and match
So even a couple of blown-up ones on top of a plateau card value
Splatoon likely didn't know all the ins and outs of why they couldn't just
Explode the things on site and go home
All I knew was that they were waiting what seemed too preposterously long time for someone higher up to come up with a plan
Were they going to send a wrecker up there with a platoon going to have to drag these disabled monsters back down the mountain
They had a mechanic up there with them but he was stomped
I try to communicate the situation back to their Commanders
It's not going well
Sony we had the mechanic there
And they said
Send us a list of the parts
That you need to fix it
And so the mechanic gets on there and he says
Did
There's no it's not going to get fixed
The mechanics
Sergeant
Calling down the radio in town saying
The truck
Is blowing up
We can't fix it
And
And then command says why not
And in each other like what
We literally have the Jack the thing off
Try and change out a tire the mechanic sitting there
Amused look on his face
Going
You're not driving this thing off the mountain
It's been blown up
We
All felt like why are we up here
What is going on
They call the combat veterans the ones that have been there for
A lot longer in the Army we're all scratching their heads nobody understood why we were doing this
Eventually I'm about day 5
They told to head home
Another team will come and deal with the mrap
They're also instructed to take a different route back down the mountain
The pastor of Village
It's bad
Shane cross said it was military age men
No kids
I'll just stop and stare the Convoy
We passed some cattle by themselves and a burning like it was a smoldering campfire by self
I try not to sign also of welders unintended cattle unattended fire that was going
As in people booked and got out of there
I have this terrible feeling that we are about to get
Blown up or shot at Austin Lanford
Suddenly there's an IED explosion
Another truck hit and disabled
Well once again
That truck gets blown up
Right in front of me
We are like all right
Well we got to go assess the situation
So we get out an EOD guy gets out to
Explosive Ordnance disposal
Edamame
Is Josh
And so that you'll die without their sleeping with his little Minesweeper
And he comes across something
And
He picks it up
He starts pulling on it
And it's like
It's like a
A wire
I got buried wire and so you picking it up and sees it's like
String tied into the woods
And then he was going to drop it and goes oh s***
My first reaction was
That I cocked my machine gun
And I said out loud
I said let's do this
Great cliche I understand that but that was exactly what I did
That's exactly what I did I'm like
This is going down
There's not any way that we're not about to get attacked
It was so obvious
Okay let's do this
An RPG game like flying by us and
On the ground in front of us and right then like it scared the crap out of me because then
Gun started firing like
Immediately I get up and I freaking started sprinting towards the truck trying to find cover
This is what's called a complex attack they've been waiting for the Convoy to pass by this way
Now it's a mess of gunfire and explosions
Josh is a gunner so he's up in the chart of his truck
People below or calling out targets
The attack is coming from everywhere
My platoon Sergeant gets in the truck and punching me on my ass and telling me to keep firing
So
You know I went through like 400 rounds initially and I keep firing keep firing keep firing and I don't I don't let up
Who was also a gunner but he wasn't in the turd of his truck
Zac farro was up there
Immediately Zack's gun jammed so bohan's his weapon up all the saw
Zach starts firing
Another guy no hands up his saw
The third weapon works
Convoy needs to get out of this Ravine they're trapped in but now they've got this disabled truck which they need to tow out
So the platoon leader JP Billings jumps out of his truck to hook up a cable Shane was the gunner in that truck
He is he is y'all. Cover me
NEOS Adorn jumps out
It runs often
Macros are there really big heart also I can't see but here and
And here kid run off the truck behind us
Grab the cable hook to the hookah bar truck
And then rang
Climb back inside
I could see him if he would hit mud all over him
House Plaza mud from like Venom around hitting the dirt and slinging mud on to him
Oh my God
The inside he's TLC on go go for a hour drive
He yells office in Truckee says don't you ever let me do something like that again
It's our desire floor is it
And a cable snap
Intemperance calls out cover made out of vehicle again
Twice Billings goes out there
Second time to Cable holds
They move out
Air support Moves In
Incredibly no one from their unit got hurt during the firefight
One soldier who was there said that by the end he heard that up to 10 Taliban have been killed
Splatoon eventually limbs home back to the fob
The Emirates are all banged up flat tires in Vallejo
Here's my phone remembers about what happened when they pulled back into the wire after Amna
We get to the wire entrance
Commander standing there waiting for us
The grounds
Battalion Commander said something.
Did a good job out there I'm glad to see you back at congratulations anyone out there and proud of you
How are you feeling how's everything going he didn't say anything like that his concern was not anywhere close to
Hey how's the men's well-being doing how are my men were out there in a war zone
Didn't say anything like that
It's the ground in the first thing that comes out of our Battalion Commander whose mouth is what you couldn't shave
Who's usually pretty measure the way he talks to Mark in the phone calls
But whenever he talks about this incident whenever you talked at all about the Battalion Commander
Lieutenant Colonel Clint Baker
Spoken barely tapped out his anger
He goes on and on about the Shaving comment which he heard about second hand
Are you serious
We get back here and now we have to go shave
6 days movie
Because some jackass
Dave
Also but they shook it off
And then I allow guys carry to put a
I like a disposable razor and just stuck it on their kit on their chest a thing
That's like a
Nothing where I can shave anytime I need to
So is like a little
Yeah
I was noticing the same thing as the other guys were
He's getting mad at the same things they were
Other guys might b**** about something and then flush it away
These things were sticking
Attaching two other incidents he'd already lodged in his memory
Starting in Alaska
Like pieces of a puzzle only he was putting together
In the phone calls Mark comes back again and again to Amna
Trying to fit correctly into bows overall argument
When you say the problem is you're talking specifically about
Putting people at risk
Things like retrieving
Broken equipment or are you talking about
Cuz I don't know I'm not sure
Yeah
The most obvious complaint a soldier might have about Amna would be exactly what Mark is getting at
But it sounds like a wrongheaded Dangerous Mission and it's just luck that no one from his platoon. Hurt or killed
What would makes both Furious about the sauna incident
Wasn't so much the crappy communication between the mechanics of the Commanders
Or the being stranded for days
Or their unfortunate route home which clearly the enemy had had ample time to plan for
More than all that
It was a shaving thing
Yes and it was scary
When they come home the Battalion Commander doesn't acknowledge the scariness
Moreover to bow at least he seems unconcerned about the welfare of his men
That's what starts to feel scary
Maybe they're not in safe hands
An interesting Lee confusingly
But was also complaining at the time that they were playing it Tuesday
It was miserable but it was all so exciting especially for the new guys in the platoon who hadn't been in a wreck before
Something happened and they survived and bonded over it
Bodensteiner Sharon that
He hadn't fired his weapon
In an email to a friend who sent the day they got back from Mom. He wrote quote
I sat there and watched
There was nothing else I was allowed to do unquote he added but Afghanistan mountains are really beautiful
Josh Carter says he noticed something shift in bow after they got back from Moana
The tone change
I was in the truck with him a few of the missions after that
And
She was talking to one of the guys down below on the truck
And if they were to everybody's talking about the firefight and everything like that
Cuz that's like
The most significant thing that happened on deployment so of course everybody talks about it over and over again
And he
During the conversation
Said
All that stuff is just Bullshit
And like
What what's b******* about it
He's like
We should have gone out there and we should
Killed every single one of those guys
We shouldn't we should like he thought we were being cowards cuz we had no trucks and
We didn't go out there and do that and he's like well we go to these villages
And we hand out these
Blankets and all the stuff
We shouldn't be doing that we should be out there
Just killing these people who are shooting at us
Chinese people who are
Just don't care about Afghan people showing the bad guys
Then enemy he says at that point he's like
Our whole entire the whole entire Army is just
Pussies
Everyone's a pussy
Because we don't go out there and we don't
Kill the enemy
Like we're supposed to
I don't know if Josh's quotes are precisely accurate
But other guys have told me both sad versions of this sentiment
And it's true and understandable
The botox to Mark about a bunch of different feelings he had about the war
Wanting more action
But also feeling that they should be doing coin better
Should be working harder to engage with local Afghans taking every opportunity to talk to them
And he says he felt like and then a lot of guys felt like
Whatever it is we're doing over here
It's not helping regular Afghan
Everybody was saying
What we're doing here
All right
So I want to take a minute here just to stare at that notion
What is b*******
Respirometer for that is Jason Dempsey PhD he was in office
Easter at the Battalion and Brigade level
Any detours in both Iraq and Afghanistan
It was Irwin bullet missing
It was back in 2012 as a combat advisor to the Afghans
And then again in 2014 to see how that was going
So he's got a lot of perspective
I asked Jason was the mission b*******
The problem he said is that the Army said it was doing coin it planned its Mission and operations in Iraq and Afghanistan
As if it were doing coin
But it never fully committed to coin
Because we're going to work you've got to commit to a place for decades right
Probably 30-40 years
If you want to drive political change
You have to have people out there long enough to understand the politics of the place they're in
Jason said you can't rotate units in and out in 7 or 12 month increments
Unexpected
Are you really effective from
Cuz you're just figuring it out but I prefer your rocking and rolling
You're really doing great things for 6
And then you're transitioning out for those last three months
And then whether or not
The lessons momentum you learned in those six months get carried on you might as well roll a dice
Really
I don't know that cuz another unit coming in
Play Mary not share your vision even if they do share your vision they spend the first three months confused themselves
The Army didn't really train units like bows for coin in Afghanistan
Jason said they couldn't
Not the time allowed
He said he and other soldiers were basically told if you make their lives better they'll support you
Sou nicastro Afghanistan but it doesn't really understand the society there who's who
What the power dynamics are the tribes the families the alliance's the ethnic groups
The whole root system of a country that's pretty much been at War on and off for 30 years
As you pump down and try to convey your message of Goodwill on the ground
It doesn't translate very well
If you're young
American freight company Commander or platoon leader you walk into
Your typical Afghan Village Circa 2009
And an elder approaches
What's up you guys doing here
Your average young lieutenant or captain
Where to make your life better
We want to build some roads you want to connect to the central government we want
And we just want to improve your life make sure your kids go to school
Camille
That is mine is like horseshit the Stooges lion
Jewish teeth
Who the f*** comes to Afghanistan to make my life better
It's an absurd notion
In the mind of this app
That
United States of America would send people around the world just a bill
Rhodes
Look like
Today at Kansas okay that's cool thanks guys going to meet you wash the way goes back to the Village
Say you should hear it
What does marigold mean
Glad to hear
In their communion sitting there and then
The hair cuz I hate Islam
Among those two messages for average Afghan
The idea that were there cuz I hate Islam is much more rational
Write for them it's just they're more prone to believe it
When we say we're here
We re saying to them
Without young Lieutenant going to say
We want to we want to get you on our side so that we together can
Get rid of
The Taliban in foreign fighters in the arms that are coming in
Or they just saying to know we just want to give you rice and gold Road
It's in our interest for you guys to be
Supporting our mission
It's a valid point
And a lot of times that would get lost though at the
Beijing level
Loss of the platoon level because if the soldiers don't know who's supporting them who's supporting the Taliban and why
Then of course the messaging is pretty crude
Is we never really understood all these overlapping power structures and incentives and relationships that
Pre-existed us
We never one that wanted to understand what the Afghan for actually
Doing
We just want to go to walk in and say Here's a template for how you should run an army
Go for it
Getting hands dirty roses show you how we do
Great way to show you how much we do
And then if you don't end up doing that
It must not be because of Any structural issues underneath must be because you just don't care
And that's probably the most infuriating thing about all this is we have an entire generation of army folks
Marines Etc have gone through
And at the end of a deployment of
The Afghans just don't care about the
This fight as much as
Which is quite possibly the most
Preposterous thing you can say
The warning
They don't care about it
As much as we
Ground is
They're fighting their struggle
We're fighting hours
And we never bothered it's okay to these two things actually overlap
In November of 2009 then Secretary of State Hillary Clinton got a memo to the same effect
It's inside an email recently released by the state department
It's notes from a conversation and advisor clintons had
The guy named Bill Murray
He'd had a long and distinguished career at the CIA Heaven station Chief in Pakistan in the 90s
And all that apparently after starring in the movie Stripes
Anyway CIA Bill Murray said the same thing Jason is saying
There's a giant protracted misunderstanding going on
Teena Marie did not mince words
The memories almost like an urgent overseas Telegram
We are literally fighting the people
They think we are fighting Islam
The problem is not the number of troops
It's a failed mission
The Afghans believe we are there to stay
This is the thing they will never accept
They will allow armies to go through and even stay for a few years but not stay forever
I don't see how to make this work
Murray's overall advice
Bed and coin
Don't try to build the Afghan Nation or restructure society stop talking about democracy they don't care
Tell them you want to get Bin Laden and then get out
Inside the Army leadership though
Message was very different
It was we can do this
We keep trying we just need more time more money more men
Of course phone is platoon mates didn't have all this perspective
They might wonder whether what they were doing was worthwhile but mostly they were just doing their jobs doing what they were told
Knowing it was sometimes or often sucky
Right after I was sent with his platoon to mess
The little Outpost 20 miles south of Bob Serrano
Messed with deliver the rest of boast
Complaints
The messed Mission fit in exactly 2 Petraeus is coin idea
To get soldiers off the fob
Out into other more remote parts of Afghanistan
To work with and train local
Security Forces
When bo4 scotomas
In late May of 2009
There wasn't much of anything on top of the hill there
It was a cemetery and a tiny little bunker fortified with sandbag
So we're on this observation post
And they put pics of us up there the first night
Swell the first night
That Foxhole was big enough for two guys to be Undercover
So that's
Or guys
Sleeping out on a bare Hill
With a town
That is probably
Maybe 75 yards away
The bottom of this little Hill
Anybody could have
With that pillow
With an rpk
In
More than likely would have gotten
And this wasn't considered the
Security risk
This wasn't considered a safety
You know by the guys who put us up there
The sergeant that were up there made a call
Start digging a bigger hole
So that we can fortify the position
Here we are
Digging this hole in the middle of the Heat
Wave
The summer
And they called down
Staff score guidance on uniform
In other words are we allowed to take off some of our stuff
Best helmets
While we dig this hole in the punishing Heat
Members of getting a vague answer that amounted to yes
Greg weatherman who was in charge up there on the hill told doll that he did remember calling for instruction on uniform
We could see down below and they didn't have their gear on
Ask the commander when we are digging if we can take our gear off
He replied that as long as we were working on digging it should be fine I'm quote
Not all that uncommon for soldiers to do this by the way Ben the uniform rules a little
Austin Lanford wasn't messed to
He wasn't up above but he was doing similar work down below where the trucks were
Darrell Hanson was there as well
It was hot it was extremely extremely hot
And we're digging into a mountain full of rock so
You can either be in long sleeves pants and
Like the full kit
And die
Or you can drop load and
Do it how you have to do it to get it done as fast as you can because time is of the essence
And so
You decide to
Put your sleeves up
You decide to take her helmet off and maybe put a bandana on to keep your sweat out of your face
And maybe you unblock your boots
Cuz
You're hot
So here we are trying to fortify this because the first night we slept out on
Open
And so Here Comes This BC
Clint Baker
Key of the Shaving remark
Of course Baker sees them out of uniform
And you come running up that hill by himself
With Afghan governor and his Entourage
He gets up to the hill
It doesn't stop to talk to anybody doesn't stop to ask what's going on
All he does is he gets in the face
Of the sergeant there doesn't give him a chance
To explain fully what's going on nothing but aggression
And he literally went up pesto
Priceless chestplate up against the other sergeant
Like trying to get into his face
And you can see nothing but
LED turns around and throw the floor shaking
Tantrum
Configure told General doll he remember the incident and said he was quote putting on a bit of an ax to drive a point home
Unquote
Tell
That reprimand might have been the end of it
Except there was a photographer hanging around the platoon at that time
Sean Smith of the Guardian newspaper
And he published a bunch of photos online above and the others not in their proper uniform
And that sent the commanders through the roof
Call
Will you guys you guys are as bad as child
If you'd murdered
Village in Vietnam
Where is it why would you say that that's ridiculous
Because we
Yeah we we were
A little idea
When I first heard those account which again he was hearing second-hand since he wasn't in the room
I didn't quite believe it
I mean I believe they got chewed out but not to that.
I figured he was exaggerated
Carol Baker didn't respond to my request for an interview which I'm not surprised by
Until likely be involved in both court-martial
Proceeding
But I asked him about it
He was Colonel Baker's number two
It seems Kenny all the time about the photos to
Explain that yes indeed
This was a very big deal
Can you drop the guardian photographer at mess
And then kept driving further south
He was at another command center down there when someone showed him the photos
I interviewed Ken over the phone
If if we could ever find those photos
I'm pulling back up
Mishima shadam actually I just see like
Guys
Cheetah weapons at 1
Do you see by your body armor on
What does burning body armor look like except
Like if you see the video games
No I see guys
She guys with helmets on
Nobody knows a helmet on see a bunch of guys waiting to get f****** killed
That's what you see
The other thing that made Ken crazy
Was the way the weapons looked in the photos machine guns pointing up in the air not on tripods like they should be
I do look very hard at the photos even find the offending guns but Ken took it all in right away
Scarves on people's heads
And then there's Bergdahl standing off
Toot to the right and go with the pipe with a pipe
This is the one where I said
I don't want to see more this f****** Lawrence of Arabia ship
Old points out to mark that pipes actually have a longer richer place in military history than cigarettes
General Patton
Anyway to can the whole scene screams lack of discipline
Alarm Bells went off
If you guys aren't following the basic rules
How can I be trusted when a bigger problem comes along
Prior to deployment Hannah sergeants had come up with uniform rules they all agreed to enforce
And now there were saying
I know it's against the rules but
But you know what
I think
I know better
I don't care
So do whatever the f*** you
I see and that's the breakdown in discipline in fact
Is it right thing whatever the f*** you want
Write 15 people in my life go ahead
Like if you go right there
You go you go there
In your head
Now do I think these guys are ever going to let you know
15 Afghans in a room and shoot him
No not at all
But
I surely didn't want to
To let it start and then this is early in the deployment I mean this is May
Yeah right
Right
Okay we've decided
We're just going to do whatever we want
So
I'd wager bow heard what he heard
Neligh
And it was fun of you wasn't singular
That leadership genuinely consider this worthy of punishment
After the photo thing
3 people got in big trouble
Greg Leatherman was demoted
And two other sergeants were moved sideways out of the platoon
Tok Baker
I turned against them
He was going out of his way
Everything is miserable as possible in an unnecessary way
What I thought
And I saw the effect that had on the everybody
I guess you weren't the only guy that felt that way obviously
I was the one of many who thought it was a complete joke
You were just going I can't believe this is happening
I was mad about it I was
So that was the stupidest thing I've ever heard like
We're out here doing what you tell us to do like
I didn't understand
Why is Austin
Can the other guys didn't like that they never got to explain why they were out of uniform
Commanders reaction had less to do with the actual in fractions
And more to do with the fact that photographic evidence of them was on a website
Making the army look bad
I can leadership
Johansen said it felt like they were being judged unfairly
Off of
Picture
You know they had no idea what we're about
And higher so worried about
The way we look at our unprofessionalism
Not knowing
What the atmosphere is like what the actual Opie is like flies circularly constantly a hundred
10 degrees no hot food no hot shower
Getting shot at
Kind of
Ruined it
Ruin the feeling Daryl had that they were really good platoon
They were doing a good job
The punishments messed with morale
This is when those level of discontent boils over bodensee the commander
Actions of corrective
Is Autumn is punitive and where is
Irrational
Basically
Things are falling apart
You've been carrying around these worries for months he said
The Omni mission of course
Also talked to Mark and a doll
About a couple of incidents where he felt like privates were being ganged up on
Ncos raising them about their personal lives
Who's offended by that
But the uniform debacle and the photographs and Baker's freak out
Turbo that was the last straw
I ended up doing what I did
Because
He was out of control
I wouldn't put it past
Because the other person
IDK yet
He said his fear essentially was that Clint Baker would try to get rid of them
Maybe by sending them on a suicide mission
But they might get killed
Simply because he didn't like them
Botal General doll quote what could happen is this Battalion Commander
CS my platoon
As a stain on his reputation
Now sending us on a suicide mission wouldn't be the first in military history
Somebody doing somebody giving out an order on personal agendas or off of personal grievances
It is not going to be a first in military history
So worst case scenario what happens
Bizarre threat
And I saw that somebody needed to do something about it
Somebody had to do something that called the situation into check
Unquote
Go to sided
He was the somebody who should do something
He had to save them
On June 7th to close friend back home
Kim Harrison's daughter
Bowser in case you guys get word of anything weird about me from the Red Cross in the military
Please keep Kim calm
He wrote quote no red flags
I'm good
But plans have begun to form
No timeline yet
Tourettes back
Exactly what kind of plants are you thinking of
About three weeks later it was when he walked off the opiate messed
Hoping he says to cause a dust one
Hoping to show up back at fob sharana
Hoping to tell his fears to a general
Hoping to be listened to
Thinking what
Those are his reasons for leaving
Because he decided his Battalion Commander was an incompetent a*******
That's why he makes this nutty radical dangerous move
What am I missing
You Are Not Alone
One thing Marcus
We talked about this a bunch of times actually
The first time he
Kind of lay it out for me
I don't think I said this on the tape but I was thinking like at the f*** out of here.
Like what
Okay
There was no point in hearing that story that I thought oh great I have the answers cool
Thanks it was more my reaction was more just like you've got to be kidding me
All these years
So many people around boat ride to figure out
Is he selfish or selfless
Is even telling the truth
He was looking at the same set of circumstances as the other soldiers in his unit
Why do you react so different
Take such drastic steps
How do you make sense of this guy
Well
We have to go deeper
Dorian's destroy that he told didn't really ever change but my understanding of the person telling that story change
Next time
On cereal
Chris by Julie Schneider Dana chivis and me and partnership with Mark Bowl Megan Ellison Hugo Lindgren Jessica Weisberg page 1 and Annapurna
Pictures
Our glasses are editorial advisor editing help this week from Brian Reed Nancy Updike and Joel level Whitney Danger
Field is our digital editor research by Kevin Garnett fact-checking by Michelle Harris copy-editing Bionic iwalani
Emily Condon is our line producer our music is composed by Nick thorburn Fritz Myers and Mark Phillips
Shows mix by Kate bilinski
Kristen Taylor's our community editor other cereal staff Southland at least bergersen and Kimberly Henderson
Special thanks this week to Kristen lose and we'll Yurman our website is serial podcast. Org where this week you can
Can find a link to those Guardian photos I got both platoon in trouble and also for anyone nerding out on the military right now
Dana
We posted our own beautiful Army org chart showing how Bose regiment was structured
Next week we'll also have audio extras and more
Again that serial podcast. Org
Stay tuned for preview of our next
The first
Support for serial comes from ADT
You can monitor your home and control your system from virtually anywhere
With the ADT Go app
Including an SOS button
Is it att.com
Podcast to learn more about how ATT can design and install your custom Smart Home
Backed by 24/7
Cereals production of This American Life and WBEZ Chicago
So you just screw up like f****** around in the woods
Coming up on the next episode of serial
Here's a cute kid from Idaho
Blonde hair and blue eyes
First he's very quiet 19 year old kids
Probably do something about that
You are a lot of spandex in those days and then all the sudden he shows up in his uniform
Kind of
Wanting to serve and wanting to protect
Were you trying to pass the time or did you literally lose your mind and now you just got it back
They even when they hear the the tree story it's going to be
There were two think it's crazy
But will those people already filled with hate and filled with judgement
Will they change their mind