Serial season 3 is presented by ZipRecruiter the smartest way to hire
Later during the break you'll hear from the co-founder of an Innovative company that teaches kids to code with games
Unlearn my ZipRecruiter is rated number one by Employers in the US based on hiring sites with over 1000 reviews on trustpilot
Kaiser Burke Center for free at ziprecruiter.com
Cereal
Support for serial comes from Squarespace
Make your business official with Google in Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and a Business website with Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and professional tools from Google
It's the simplest way to look professional online
Visit squarespace.com Google to start your free trial
And use offer code professional for a discount on your first purchase
Google and Squarespace
Make it professional make it beautiful
You try to help with little boy
Okay
Previously on serial
The tallest jury shot this little boy and not be afraid anymore sir
The defense attorney came to me at the first pre-trial that you're going to dismiss this
You sir are going to be looking
This is me all the way up like every time I go outside I just look at everybody diff
But you know what happened but you won't say nothing
I don't think that's what happened
He said that's why you're getting out
From This American Life and WBEZ Chicago
Serial one Courthouse told week by week I'm Sarah Koenig this is one of those cases
That is so puzzling because so many people are so certain of
What is our who is involved and we just have no way of knowing
What it is and what it isn't in
Yeah one breakage and all that one break a change at all
This is a prosecutor named Brian Radigan
He's talking about the aavielle Wakefield case the one where the baby was shot in the car
Get another prosecutor in charge of that case they're the ones who saw 13 count indictment against Avon homes
They're the ones who argued a year later to let him go
Eddie Cibrian
But they haven't solved it like why why does it have to be this one
Why does it have to be the five
Gold
When I asked to interview someone about ivl's case
The County prosecutor's office easily could have said
This is still an open investigation we can't comment
But they did not do that
Instead they give me Bryan
And Brian told me a lot
I went to Brian chiefly to find out why the case fell apart
Did they release Davon Holmes because of Sumter
Kalaty
Or did they release him because wrong guy
First responder the reasons they thought it was Davon to begin with
Initially they had anonymous tips that it was Davon
People who said this is what I know but you didn't hear from me
Just said
Now this my information you'll never find me if you bring me in a court or if you try to put me on paper record me I'll deny that I ever
But you don't meet me in this park at
And I'll tell you
I mean really like the stuff you see in the movies
In the movies that's exciting
In real life
Not so great
Brian said he was hoping to persuade one or two of those people to become Witnesses by the time the trial rolled around
They have the jailhouse statement from that guy who I'm calling John the guy who'd known Davon since he was little brothers were friends
Brian told me more about what John said he also told me they didn't really find it credible
Since some of the other people John had mentioned in his statement didn't seem to have a connection to Davon
Are older one thing
Brian's office was also looking into the guy obvious father thought was responsible for the shooting
But they didn't have enough evidence to charge him with anything
And Avon they also had his cell phone records putting in the neighborhood at the time
His own neighborhood they also had a statement to the detective sandwich he said he'd been up the street at the Family Dollar when it has
Davon told me he'd never made
I didn't add up to much
But then they got the landscapers ID
The landscaper remember was the guy who finally chose de Vons picture out of a photo array
Third time around almost two months after the shooting
As I thought it was the landscapers ID that made the prosecutors
Feel comfortable
Like they're looking at the right person
Landscaper came off as genuine believable
Brian told me the landscaper he came to them
He showed up one day at the Justice Center
For the elevator up to the 9th floor
Tilapia the prosecutor's office
Brian gets a call at his desk
Is a guy says he wants to talk to you
So I show up to the front I say Hi how are you in on the interviews myself and he says I've got some information I want to talk to somebody about
So I call the homicide unit I didn't talk to him again
We want to be Witnesses so I call the homicide unit they come over here they pick him up
And they talked to him
And when they're talking to him
There was
There was a belief at the beginning
From
The officers handling the case that this guy knows who it is but
He's not going to pick him up
Brian says this guy it was like a lot of witnesses they deal with
Wanting to do the right thing
Afraid to do the right thing
Waffling
She came down here
A number of times and contacted the homicide unit or number of time saying
Listen I'm
I wanted to do this I wanted to come forward but I do not want to come to court
I do not want to testify
I got kids he talked to us he wanted us to move them out of
Where he was living because he was afraid of living in the neighborhood Evelyn and
But he wasn't but he still was working in that neighborhood afterwards and in those have been so he had
Kid his own concerns
But I think if
If you ask him again he would still believe that
Devon Holmes was the one
And do you think David Holmes is the one
I I think that there was
Pretty strong evidence
That we found
During the course of this and
That he was not
He's not
Now we turn to part two of our conversation
What made the case against Davon collapse
No I just want to know the amount of evidence Brian had laid out
Does not seem like it should be enough to take a person to
Trial for aggravated murder
Much less convince a jury to convict
A person of aggravated murder
But it is enough
Nothing would have been a slam dunk for the state but
Assuming a landscaper showed up to court and testify
It's not far-fetched to think Davon might have been convicted
Easily could have gone down for this murder
What about a month before the trial was supposed to
Start
They were made aware he doesn't want to say exactly how but they were made aware of a phone call
And exonerating phone call
We had some evidence of somebody else that we believe is involved in the case
On a recording that they didn't know
Was being recorded
Saying that
Devon was not there
Was it because I asked him to get a job
It was not
Again Brian didn't want to divulge too much about this recording
He thinks that if this case is ever going to be solved this call might be the key
Didn't want to say too much about it
But what surprised me was
It didn't come from the detectives
It didn't come from their side
The most I can say is
The recording came to them
Once it did they all sat down in a conference room in the prosecutor's office
Defense attorneys Brian the cops
And they listen to this
Call
It was between someone who knows and cares for Davon
And the young man I'm not going to name
In the call nobody identifies the shooter
But it was pretty clear the young man knew what had happened the day I'll be always killed
Brian says he understood right away that he had to take it serious
When you actually hear somebody say it
When they don't know that they're being recorded
And that
That changes things
They're only a few weeks from trial at this point
Now they scrambled
They needed to verify that the recording was real
But the people in the car were who they said they were
Not the call itself wasn't theater
Manufactured to Spring Davon
Once I did all that they reassess
Do we still think Davon Holmes is the guy
They weren't sure
Maybe not
They decided they couldn't proceed
Filed a motion to dismiss
The phone call ended the case against Avon
But it also gave Brian new evidence to work
The young man in the recording
He sounded involved in some way
Call the detectives he knew in the 4th District
Do you know anything about this guy
Funny thing they said is matter of fact we're looking at him for a carjacking
Also for shooting
Brian says can you hurry it up chop chop and they do
Pretty soon that got him in custody
They charging for the carjacking
And for the other shooting
Even though these wouldn't normally be cases for Bryan's unit since nobody died
Brian prosecute someone tries to get the guy to cooperate
Start squeezing it
I'll help you out on a plea if you help us on the Ave Wakefield case
12 years is better than tape
30 years right
The guy won't talk
Don't talk won't talk
Brian tried for months
Nothing
Last fall the guy pleaded guilty in those cases
Tag robbery and attempted murder and was sentenced to 17 years
Brian knows that this guy serving time for something entirely else might be the closest Belk
Creep towards Justice and ovules case
Kind of sideways Justice
Will Al Capone embrion headset which is a funny thing from to say because Brian looks a lot like a young Al Capone
It's unsatisfying I know
Crime isn't solved that's unsatisfying obviously
But also Dave onset accused for a year
That shouldn't have happened
The Justice Center about it people said yeah that's a shame at least I corrected it
No one was demanding an inquiry into what went wrong or yelling for reform no hand-wringing
Bismarck resignation
What you going to do judges say they can't control what cases are prosecutors bring to them prosecutor
You say they're relying on the detectives detective say their information is only as good as what the public cost up can they help it
People lie or withhold
I got it
When no one feels fully responsible for the outcome
When blame is spread out and diluted
A situation like avons becomes easier to shrug off
What are you going to do
Starts to feel like an answer
Rather than an urgent question
I ended up spending a bunch of Time with Brian ratigan hanging around while he did his job
Because I like them right away
And also because he is one of the most powerful people in the Justice Center
He'd never admit that
Police seized it
But it's true
Prosecutors are the most powerful people in any Courthouse
Defense attorneys will tell you they'd rather have a fair prosecutor and an unfair judge
Been a fair judge and an unfair Prosecco
Because of all the people who shape a criminal case the prosecutor has the most discretion
Especially at The crucial beginning when the thing is still germinating
The prosecutors deciding home to charge and with what crimes
Is also deciding what the plea deal is going to look like
And don't tell the judges in the building but often the prosecutor is more less deciding the sentences people get
Because of this big Power they hold
Prosecutors of late have been the focus of blame for a lot of the problems in our system
And the focus of Reform effort
And that's not undeserved
What is incomplete
Mostly prosecutors I've talked to it's not that they're gunning for cheap assembly-line Justice
Or for unprecedented discriminatory devastatingly High rates of incarceration
It's that
That's the job we've given them
I feel like I can't explain this without telling you some history of how we got here
I want to explain it
So here goes
Our worst modern era of crime in the US if you look at the FBI stats
Began in the 1960s and 70s
Most people now agree we were under policing and also under incarcerating
And we swanway way the other way
Cops made more arrest which meant more prosecutions
But the huge increase in arrests and charges did not respond to a commensurate increase in the number of prosecutors
Or the number of cops but that's another story
This one statistic really hit me
In 1974
They're around 17,000 local prosecutors dealing with around 300,000 felony process
Secretions
By 2007
The number of prosecutors had jumped to about 32000
A significant increase but they were dealing with nearly 3 million felony prosecution
A tenfold increase from 1974
The upshot
Vastly more prosecutions handled by relatively fewer prosecutors the only way for them to
Keep afloat plea bargains
As1 Cleveland judge said to me
Plea bargaining isn't part of the Criminal Justice System it is the criminal justice system
Kaiser Chiefs
Balita more convictions and to more incarceration
And we've given prosecutors many tools to negotiate these please lots of Forces help this push toward
Harsher criminal justice
Economic forces the forces of racism and discrimination
Unfortunate US Supreme Court decisions politics and more politics
For the one you don't always hear about his legislation
In the decades post 1970
Most states began revamping their sentencing guidelines and their criminal codes
A lot of crimes are being defined both more broadly and more specifically
Theft fraud burglary robbery assault sexual assault kidnapping
They're definitions expanded
Which made them harder to defend against
And They Carried more serious penalties same with laws about guns
Especially about drugs expensive criminal codes allow prosecutors to expansively charge
Because a single criminal act doesn't have to be singly charged you can pile on as many charges you want doesn't matter if
They overlap so long as each one requires you to prove something slightly different
That's how an armed robbery can end up charged S8 felonies
It sounds like Echoes bouncing around a canyon
Committed theft while having a deadly weapon
Committed theft while having a deadly weapon and either display the weapon brandished it indicated that he possessed it or used it
On top of all that you've got sentence enhancement what are known in Cleveland is Speck
You can tuck inside particular charges
Repeat offenders facts
Gang specs guns back to the most in Cuyahoga County
Usually one and three-year mandatory prison time for the use of a gun
Even though the use of a gun is baked into the definition of many charges already
The result
Is it kind of indictment shock and awe
Charging like this
What's known as stacking charges or just
Overcharging
Induces please
Of course it does
Because the prosecutor can accordion the indictment however he needs
If you play will drop everything but the felonious assault
Or you go to trial on the phone formidable indictment
And chances are if you go to trial you're going to get convicted of something
Just a visual of a long indictment is a signal to the jury
Look at this list
He must have done
Something
I want some charges probably are going to merge at sentencing
As a rule the more stuff you're convicted of
The longer your sentence is going to be
So yeah
You played
That's why the prevailing practice in most Prosecutor's offices is to charge crimes as harshly as they can
They might swell prisons and eviscerate entire neighborhoods
It is efficient
All of this brought me to Brian ratigan
I wanted to know something very basic
How does he make his decisions
How much of what Brian's doing is coming from Brian
His own sense of what's right
How much is beyond his control
The job we've given him
Yeah
Brian works in the major trial unit
Homicides mostly
In his office he's got a mini fridge and Annie - desk and window with the blinds drawn that overlooks Lake Erie
Nothing Fancy by Longshot
Case files and boxes of evidence of child around
Complaining chair
Brian looks chart though
He wears a suit everyday
He never knows when he might be pulled into a courtroom
By the way his beard stubble scrapes against his collar you understand he's enduring the costume not enjoying it
He doesn't appear to Revel in his power
He favors the aw shucks variety of dominance
From what I can tell Brian is universally respected in the Justice Center
He's forthright
His compassion you can't take a joke
38 married to little kids
Irregular amiable guy
Today's I spent with him he had 20 cases on his docket
One aggravated vehicular homicide
Rape case
When phone is assault which
You normally wouldn't. But the guy assaulted three police office
The rest
Murders are aggravated murders
Mostly drug deals gone bad
Some b******* like retaliation thing out
Yep
All day people are knocking calling texting
He's getting updates on cases
Giving updates on cases
He decided yeah
Iraq
Brian takes a call from Ray Diaz a homicide detective
He's working on a shooting case
Have an outside of nightclub on the Westside
Detective Diaz tells Brian they're about to interview a witness
Gregory call me when you're done
That this is a guy that we've been
He was with the defendant and we've been trying to get him to come in and then do an interview and every time he says he's coming in heat
Cancel Zoraida never ride or
Weed shop in his house and he's not there
So we last week I print out a subpoena for the two homicide detectives
They want serve them and so he just called and said he's going to be here today so
This is excellent timing
Brian has a pre-trial on that case this afternoon
Right now. He's about to have a meeting with two other detectives on another case
They just walked in
AR
Harada
Articles and Rhonda Gray
The same one from Dave on the case
I know
They wouldn't let me record them
They were there to talk about a case that it made the news
Wasn't kind of shooting you usually hear about in Cleveland
It started as a squabble between strangers on a city bus
Then spilled onto the sidewalk
When older man had shot and killed a younger man
Brian explain to me that this case was unusual for them because the entire episode was recorded by
Security cameras on the bus
This is one of those rare cases where you
You see the whole story
90% of our cases were not watching them
Unfold
The answer for if something is caught on
You know my camera whatever usually it's from a distance and you don't care the dialogue and you don't get to see everybody's reaction you don't
Have seven different angles are nine different angles of it
You know this is like the the outlier
Crazy I can't believe I have to watch this whole thing and see
All the decisions that were made that led to this guy dying
Is your watch
You're watching like God just didn't you want to tell him what to stay out the bus
Stop the bus
This incident happened three and a half weeks earlier
The older guy was in jail
But he hadn't been indicted yet
The meeting with detectives this morning is to figure out how they're going to handle it
What charges Brian should present to the grand jury
This is a tricky one now
Because Brian can see how the whole thing unspooled now he's not sure a crime even occurred
The stories in the newspaper had quoted police as saying that the older guy the shooter had been harassing passengers on the bus
But the bus videos for the opposite
The older guy the shooter
He was the one being provoked
It's possible this was self-defense
We got a conference room
Does big screen set up so they can watch the footage from the bus
Brian had mentioned something about 7 or 9 camera angles
I thought he was joking
He wasn't
For exactly this reason
Crime city buses in Cleveland or wired up like itinerant Bank Falls
The British were watching starts from before the beginning
When everything was calm
Okay what happened when they thank you thank you
The older guy the shooter
His name is Abdul Rahman
I gotten on the bus at Public Square
Right near the Justice Center
He's in his early 60s but he looks older
Is that a long grey beard a loose sweatshirt
A scruffy
He's not homeless but he might have been mistaken for homeless
You see mr. Rahman sitting in a window seat by the rear doors of the bus minding his own business
He's holding what looks like a folded newspaper or magazine in his hand
Any younger guy sits down next to him
They don't know each other
But evidently the younger guy starts insulting mr. rahkman
You can't make out what he saying but other passengers told the cops later that he was complaining to mr. Rahman that he smelled that
The younger guy is not the one who gets shot by the way
Mr. Rahman gets up
I still leave a seat
Younger man blocks him
Ryan's watched all this before but he can't help wishing it won't go the way it's going to go
Skechers keepsake
John Adam
Skip said there's an open spot right up there just go sit there
The younger guy is being an a******
Ginning up a confrontation
Is Brian pointed out assholery is not a criminal offense
He finally lets mr. Rock montage
Mr. Rahman stands by the bus doors
But it doesn't move to a different part of the bus
You still arguing with the younger guy
Who started get physical now
He slaps the folding Magazine from Mister Rock Montana
ASRock mybatis rather gracefully to the floor
Fix it up
You say you're going to get shot
It's not clear but you can hear mr. Rock monse
I like my freedom
I'm not going to fight with you start name-calling
B**** you b****
Younger guy says
Call me another b**** I'm the f*** you up
It's familiar this scene
A bunch of strangers getting into it on public transportation
And the whole time you're doing the bystanders trigonometry
How long till I stop
Should I say something
Where are we
Should I move seats
At this point a woman named Rachel asked the men to Canna she's sitting nearby with a few other people
Including her boyfriend Andrew Easley the man who's going to get killed in about 2 minutes
Rachel says to the guys arguing hey can't you see my niece is sitting right here
Get your ass off the bus and come down and he does this Rock Mine gets off at the next stop
Then he lingers on the sidewalk
You just want to scream walk
Walk the extra 5 blocks for god sakes but he gets back on the bus
10 seconds later the younger guy says this
It is especially hard to hear but it's important
Because it's possible this is what jacked up the situation
He says I got a CCW
CCW stands for carrying a concealed weapon
Gun license
He's implying that he's armed right now
Legally
He does not have a gun but presumably mr. Rahman doesn't know that
Then the younger guy pulls the cord to single he wants to get off at the next stop
He says to mr. Rahman
Get off the bus
Let's Take It Outside you and me
He's up in Mister rachmones face
Sex laughing at him
Mr. Rothman pulls a gun
His own gun
He's got it in his right hand
And he pointed at the younger guys head
Rachel and the other people in the bus
Start freaking out
The bus pulls up to the stop
Rachel muscles her way to where Mr Rock MineZ
The doors open
And then she kicks him Square in the butt
Straight off the bus
Onto the sidewalk
Her boyfriend Andrew Easley is right behind her now
He steps off the bus
Is tall and lanky
Dressed all in white
Long white shorts
White shirt white hat white sneakers
He strides toward Mr Rahman
Is walking backwards now
Is Rahman holds up his gun again
Waves it around a little
Andrew easily Retreats quickly back onto the bus
Were the younger guy who started all this is hovering by the open doors
Then you hear Rachel and someone else say something you especially wish they had not said
Which is
That's a water gun
Mr. Rahman is walking away now
But Andrew and the younger guy go after him again
Finally right as someone on the bus says something like
Why do you all go to beat up on this old man
Mr. Rahman shoots Andrew Easley in the Torso
He falls
Someone starts screaming
Mr. Rahman jobs away
The police have statements from some of the people inside the bus but the statements aren't as reliable as the Myriad recordings we
You just watched
The detectives can see for themselves how the thing cranked up emotionally block by block
As a bus traveled East on Superior Avenue
I miss rockman's house they found a gun it fell out onto detective Ackles his foot when he was looking through mr. Rock men's clothes
They don't have casings but they're 99% sure it's the same gun from the bus
Through question what happened here
Abdul-rahman used his own gun to shoot Andrew Easley
The question is
Was it a crime
Okay princess so really the issue is did he have a choice
Are these two guys coming after
What are the detectives nudges back says
I feel that argument won't work
I promise Rahman could have made other choices he could have gotten off the bus earlier
Brian says
When he gets off the bus the last time he's walking away
He's not re-engaging
And he's got you guys have
One of the detectives suggests Brian might change his mind when he sees this one last video
We watched it later
One more camera angle
The part that detectives wanted Brian to see
Is mr. rockmont posture
Right at the end
Nobel point is I mean he's going backwards
But he is doing that we're boxing Shuffle
It's true he's doing a boxing Shuffle
Like he's fixing a fight
I learned mr. Rahman wasn't always called mr. Rahman
Decades ago he was called Ricardo Spain
And he was a heavyweight fighter
He mostly lost his professional bouts 23 losses at a 26 ft
One of them
And Now ladies and gentlemen man your battle station with against Mike Tyson
Atlantic City
Auto believe that that's actually where inside a minute
Yes it is
38 seconds
Which is not the fastest Tyson ever knocked a guy out
Now I understand why the detective wanted to be sure Brian saw that last video
Because it does make you wonder
Was a former heavyweight
Who can still muster a boxing show
Really afraid of those two guys on the bus
After the meeting with the detectives
I'd say Brian was leaning slightly self-defense
But he's still not sure
And because he's not sure
He's going to let the grand jury make that call tomorrow
When they present the case for indictment
Technically of course the grand jury is always supposed to make that call
They're the ones who vote on whether there's probable cause to charge someone with a crime
But well for you lawyers and Legal Eagles
Ham sandwich I know
For the rest of you I will spare you the ham sandwich cliche and just
Explain
The grand jury is supposed to be a Citizens check on government power
But in practice grand juries usually vote the way prosecutors want them to vote
Probable cause is a Lolo standard you just have to show that it's logical to believe this person might have committed this
Describe
A grand jury presentation there's no judge no cross-examination no defense
In fact in Ohio according to the State Bar quote even if a prosecutor knows of information which would help show that they could
Cute person is innocent
He is not required to present it to the Grand Jury
How weird is that the cops in the prosecutor tell the grand jurors what they think happened
The prosecutor presents them with a proposed indictment
Hear all the charges We Believe fit this crime
If you guys agree
Sign right here
Brian's got to figure out
What charges is he going to ask them to vote on tomorrow
Like what will you write up in the indictment in terms of the charges to think
Murder I think is the high-end that it would be and
Below that is voluntary manslaughter and I think it goes between those two and involuntary manslaughter is basically like heater
The energy of passion or I are you being provoked it's it's it's a crime that's that's provoked but
And that's your
You're deciding on This Is Us
No I'm not the decider I am not the designer I don't decide anything except for what see what I'm going to wear today
It's
I'm sure he has to run stuff by the bosses down the hall usually saw at Wadala who supervises unit
Brother MO is also in the major trials unit
But the idea that Brian's not deciding anything
Because he could play this various ways
Find could show the jurors One camera angle
Or 7 camera angle
He could present all the statements from the people on the bus or just the ones that say mr. Rahman was the aggressor
He could put murder on the proposed indictment
And never mention the word self defense
But this one he tells me he really can see it either way
Crime or no crime
So his plan is to put the whole megillah in their laps
Let the grand jurors decide
He's going to show them all the camera footage
Read them all the witness statement
He talks at 3 with a paralegal
Nida
He's preparing the materials for the grand jury
Should we do the video before we talk about what each one says or play the movie
What do you think
I think I want to play the video first
See that he doesn't want the camera footage to be colored by the statement
So it's going to be footage first
And he decides
He is not only going to mention self-defense
He's going to explain self-defense
Tell them what the legal elements are
I might have you throw something together for me real quick on self-defense
Stuff
He goes and gets the pages
It's whatever self-defense the following elements must be shown in this is out of a hot spring court case
Slayer was not at fault in creating the situation giving rise the
Two situation
So you're had a Bonafide believe that he was imminent danger of death or great bodily harm
You didn't instigate it
You had a genuine fear that you'd be killed or badly hurt
Duty to retreat
And you tried to get away
But if you just want to add in those two things
I'm going to give it to you and then you can
Why later Brian tells me
He's thinking he's not going to put murder on there
Just the voluntary manslaughter
This is not set in stone yet but I believe it's just going to be voluntary manslaughter
I don't think there's going to be a murder charge
When did Becca decided I think that that's what it's what it's going to be
There's clearly some education here there's clearly some you know he's being prodded
All right I mean I think you can see that in the video it's
And it's
Clear from the beginning the guy the kid wanted to let him get out of the seat
I mean there's some
She didn't start this so
Nnnn it could be
I mean here and in really for my perspectives like it's not it if
It's not so much matter what I think right now it's it's kind of what
What the grand jury is going to think
I can also I'll play for them in
You have a point of view that you're going that's going to come across for sure
How you present things how you
What you stress what I mean it's probably hugely influential I don't mean it in a creepy way I just mean like
Yeah I think so but I also try to be fair to the process you know I mean I don't want
Down to just say
What do you think what do you think
You know because I know what what's the point I might as well just
If it was if I was going to do that way
Why even do the whole thing why
Wiper the video from y
Talk about what each witness in their size why talk about where they are in the bus I could just go in there and say
You know we shot them you should have shot them
Indictable murder
You know if
In a case like this I think it is so important to
Give the full picture
And
If they have the full picture
They should be able to make the decision based on that
Not not on what I say
Afterwards I went down to the first floor Atrium to get a snack
Bedroom has a little cafe and tables and chairs that you have to choose carefully because they are frequently sprinkled with bird poop
Now you know
I was chatting with the manual and then we started talking to these three defense attorneys we knew at a nearby table
I told him about the rocmon case
About how much material Brian ratigan was going to show the grand jury
Interfaces
Onelook
Furious
Another was smirking
One of them rolled his eyes at me but I might be making that up
Regardless the chest was clear
He's putting on a show for you it's never like that they said
They never have that much evidence before they go to the grand jury
People get indicted for stuff in 90 seconds
No discussion
I knew you were coming
Sucker
Are all people who know Brian rattigan
Who respect them
But such was their disbelief that actual fairness could be at work upstairs
That was kind of loud as possible
I told Brian about this conversation
A little awkwardly
Hebrews just like all you got played sister
Why
Because then I'll be busted
Ted
Jack Bob
Your secret's safe with me I did not tell
But I did want to know
What did Brian think of what the defense attorneys were saying
The prosecutors and cops are taking cases before the grand jury office seeking severe charges
Based on thin information
Before the crime has been investigated in any real way
His answer was
Yeah that does happen
Sometimes you do get cases that are solid right from the get-go
Or maybe get lucky with evidence I put this rock monkey
And again sometimes there's just not
There's just not enough there
And
Or we we think we have enough and then you learn information on later on I'm going to get remember a lot of times to your underwear
Time crunch
He's talking about speedy trial rights for defendants
Also if they don't indict within 10 days
The defendant get a preliminary hearing before a judge to determine probable cause
What's the prosecution does not want
That is a whole procedural nonsense that you do not want me to get into right now I promise
But what it all means is that they are in a hurry to get cases to the grand jury
Brian told me it's all about speed
Unfortunately
Again speed might not be a problem if you didn't have 13,000 felonies to process
But you do
So yeah it's obviously not ideal when investigations aren't fully cooked
But Brian said
Sometimes you've got a major crime in front of you
If somebody is arrested for it and
I'm going to make a determination I mean
What you going to do if you if you really think that you have the guy
That you have the right guy
Do you want them out on the street to
You know say it's murder
You want on the street to go do another one or
Just so you know I think we've got enough here
You know it sounds so
It's not perfect
And sometimes because of that he said they make mistakes
And sometimes because of that this is me talking now with cases like Dave on
But what are you going to do
More after the break
This is the road to hired
Brought to you by ZipRecruiter
Gretchen heebner is the co-founder of kodable
Take me to computer game starring little aliens exploring the galaxies
Family
The buses are fun
But secretly they're helping kids learn to code
By teaching them everything from algorithms to JavaScript
The game work so well
But it's now the center of a computer science curriculum that's in tens of thousands of elementary schools across the u.s.
Does the game became more successful
Gretchen.
Okay
We need to step up our graphics
I actually did all of our artwork up until
Three months ago are you trained artist
No
Basically I sat down and was like okay I need to learn illustrator
How are characters got their shape
Okay what's going to be the easiest thing for me to animate
Something without arms or legs
In order to find someone who could draw arms
Gretchen posted an ad for a game artist on ZipRecruiter
She really loved that she could pose deal-breaker questions but all her candidates had to respond to like
Why do you care about educational games
A lot of people
One sentence or one word answers
And the people who really stood out to me
Detriment
Rota thoughtful response
One of the first people to do that
Greg took 45 minutes actually
ZipRecruiter showed Gretchen exactly how long he worked on it
That's my Gretchen hired him
Did you got someone who's passionate about education
And
Making flapping Flamingo aliens
C4yourself
When it comes to hiring
ZipRecruiter has crack the code
Ziprecruiter.com cereal
ZipRecruiter the smartest way to hire
Support for serial comes from Squarespace
Make your business official with Google in Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and a Business website with Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and professional tools from Google
Is the simplest way to look professional online
Visit squarespace.com Google
To start your free trial
And use offer code professional
For a discount on your first purchase
Google and Squarespace
Make it professional make it beautiful
This afternoon the main thing Brian's got is a pretrial
Humble back of the hallway pretrial
Which is precisely where I'll get to see the most powerful guy in the equation
Brian
Do the very thing a half-century of legal tinkering has
Remind him to do
Negotiate a plea
The case is the one that detective Ray Diaz called about this morning
It's a nightclub shooting
The defendant name Dominique Williams
I've been at the M&M Saloon
And when the place went out for the night Williams allegedly shot and killed a guy right outside
Bunch of shots
Fairly close range
As Williams was running away an off-duty police officer working security at the club started after him
William shot at him
Didn't hit him with the cop shot back
And hit Dominique Williams in the butt
Who's arrested on the spot
I got was found under porch nearby
Detective Diaz calls again
And tells Brian about the witness he brought into interview
Witnesses a friend Williams was at the bar with
Apparently
The friend talk
Docker
So we've got he's identified
He identified Williams as a shooter then
Okay
All right well that's a pretty good statement for us then I guess huh
When you when you come up Ray can you are you going to do you think you'll be done with him out by what time is it
Should have said I want 15
Okay
Brian's pretrial in this case starts in 15 minutes
Does Carl puts Brian in a stronger position to negotiate
On the way to the elevator Brian sees his supervisor so I would Allah in the hallway
Kissimmee Swift update on this new evidence
What's good
We take the elevator up to 16
Head to the pre-trial area
Brian finds Dominique Williams Attorney Craig Weintraub
He's been assigned this case along with another attorney who didn't show up today
They sit down
Craig starts to talk about a possible plea
He doesn't know about the ID witness cops are interviewing downstairs at this very moment
We got to present an offer to you is that the deal
Well
One thing I should tell you
Diaz the Gotti
That
Williams was with
His body at the bar
That we were able to track him down he just interviewed him today
And he IDs your guy says yeah yeah
Walk outside
Walk out before your guy
And then
Wine walks out
He says that then I see you and I don't walk out
But the victim
Derek yanetta
Amigos United doesn't say a word and
Weimaraner off like five shots at
How is he Tracked Down what it what was the story
Put a subpoena out to one put it on azure
Did you go into drag him out of
Farmer's mom's house you know
Yeah okay
And so now that he's seen sunlight
Where did he go by the way why did he disappear and
What's been his story occamy hasn't stuff forward to say oh my God I witnessed a homicide
Understanding is that
He's been in contact with Diaz and stuff and just as
Start em up like five or six times to come down things to do
He doesn't want to be a rat is going to rat on your guy
Currently he has
Brian is used to Craig Weintraub probably done about 10 murder cases with him
Fun fun fact about Craig Weintraub
Who represented Ariel Castro
The guy who imprisoned three women in his house for 10 years
Aftertaste like that
Maybe you either quit the law
Or
You stick it out
Why is crack your way through the day
Whenever possible
Regardless
I know you're talking about now he was the guy
Walked in and I saw him link being led by Diaz yet
A cane and a dog
You think I couldn't see
Get it
Brian plays along
He was being mad by Diaz those are props you'll get rid of before the trial
I'm going to get them into the courtroom were going to practice how many steps straight how many steps to the right
You know guys do
We do best
They start talking numbers
Sounds like an auction
But that's how they're negotiating this plea
First figure out a prison sentence Dominique Williams can live with
Then figure out the charges will have to play to that'll add up to those numbers
I was looking at a range of like
Maybe 12 to 15
You don't get Smiles on their EC
Yeah I know you're not going to
I was going to rain to 12215 until you found this guy slithering around
Brian laughing because
Laughable
There's no way
12 to 15 is more like armed robbery time
What do you think about him at number is on this
Flat timer or
It's going to be a big number if it's not going to be a life tail and I mean that stuff
That's the issue here
I'll Translate
What time means the number is the number
20 years is 20 years
Murder charges in Ohio
Kanye West called a life Tale
Murder starts at a mandatory 15 to life
Aggravated murder starts in a mandatory 20 to life
Williams is charged with both kinds
Which come with a raft of gun specs
If you get a life Tale
Se22 life
Means you have to serve 20 years before you can apply for parole
Which you're not likely to get at least not the first time around
So 22 life could mean 20 years
Or it could mean you spend the rest of your life in prison
Dominique Williams is 27 years old
Understandably he wants flat time
For that to work they're going to need to reduce the charges to some kind of manslaughter
What do you think
Realistically
Centanni's I mean it's not twenties
That was before
The other guy said yeah he's the one that shot them and I watch them yeah it's not so it's not a good fact
I mean I really think it could be a manslaughter with
Are range of maybe
14 to 20
Potentially
But Peter is May I forgot I've got I have a police officer I got to worry about 2
So keep that in mind I mean that's you know that's
Where you're talkin if you if you want to range you're talkin
High twenties in the mid thirties probably
Or he just
Takes it on the Shenandoah murder
I got the light tail
Alright let's figure it out you
Whatever number they settle on
They're confident the judge will go for it
By the time we get back to Brian's office the detectives on the Williams case or waiting for him
To tell me more about the witness interview
Is Ray Diaz and also detective Jody Remington
Tourneau
Something
Yeah
Brian and the detectives are easy with each other
No errors are formalities
You can tell they were together a long time
Did you know
He said that he tried to eat
People been talkin but
Watching how closely Brian works with detectives all day
Give me an appreciation for why the system finds Prosecuting a
Cop so excruciating
Brian is had to do it
Just a month-and-a-half ago he prosecuted a Cleveland officer after he shot and killed the teenager 18
The broken into a store
The cop was charged with negligent homicide
A misdemeanor
Brian took it to trial
Not with relish
You're Nobody wants to do them
Let me know what if judges don't want them
Costumes on defense attorneys a lot of the police that are asking him don't want them
Because they're hard
Legally there complicated
Because cops are allowed to kill people in certain circumstances
But also for Brian they're morally complicated
Brian supports police officers
He knows how many guns are on the street
He thinks their job is harder than it's ever been
We also doesn't think that eighteen-year-old deserve to die that night
By Prosecuting the officer brydon feel like he was taking a side
He felt like he was doing his job
But at the trial
The police made it obvious they did not feel the same way
You were in that room
What was the thing that seemed the weirdest U&I
Me at the table by myself and like 40 police officers on the other side
Wasn't it I mean it it was weird
It was strange you know and then I had
One detective they came and sat with me
You know that's weird
I mean I know
I know that
But that's you see what I mean know how easy it can turn into
Us vs them
How they can
Alex
But it looks like we've turned on them
The all-around discomfort of that
The police feeling attacked
Brian feeling is a glaring at him like he's a traitor
Plus the public perception that the government suits on the 9th floor will never really give their all to Prosecuting their Pals and blue
Cuyahoga County recently changed its policy local cases of police shootings are now farmed out to
Prosecutors from another County
Incidentally the judge in that case found the officer not guilty
And the judge was endorsed for re-election by the police union soon after
Neither outcome surprise Bryan
Back to the Dominique Williams case nightclub shooting
That's what they think Williams is sentence should be
I know you guys usually don't give a s*** but
What are you guys thinking for a number for Williams
I'm always open when I come to that
Our victim did something before this to
Bring us about
He may have I think the problem that
Dominique Casas
I mean shoot some five times he's not armed
And then
He knowingly run from a police officer who's identifying himself and he has to
Audacity to turn and shoot a policeman
They're talking flat time and I I mean
I don't know
A mile baseball saying
Twenties is a no-go I mean your
And now that the one witness has identified him and said he's the shooter
So I mean
I'm not on the case so I don't know if it's my place to speak but yeah 20 seems low
That's Chris Schroeder another prosecutor
I was waiting to talk to Brian about a different murder case
Executed this guy outside and then he shot the cop as he was fully
Then shoot twice at the officer
Find to Casey's on that side but I know the policeman thought he shot nor
But even even this
We brought in today
Chat history over
In traffic
So it's it's if you want flat time it says
At least 30
Right I mean
I would
Okay
After the detective left
Brian and Chris Schroeder discussed a double homicide
Is that guy wants to plead
Chris said it'd have to be something like
40 to life
50 to life
It's going to have to be a high Highmark he said
I found these huge numbers shocking
I'm not even sure why
Obviously I know people get multi-decade sentences life sentences all the time
Maybe it was because I just been reading about Germany's sentencing practices
We're sentence for the very worst crimes
Usually last about 15 years at most
Or maybe because I've now seen and talked to people
Young young people
We were staring at the prospect of 10 years
14 years
Never desperate
And I talked about this for a while
I told him about my conversation with Charles Wakefield
Ariel's father
He wanted the person who killed aavielle to be punished
He also considered what happened to his daughter a quote-unquote accident
He knows whoever shot her didn't set out that day to murder a baby
It was a mistake
By Justice Center standards his Vengeance was very conservative
I can't remember how it came up at so she's kind of throughout the number like 10 years
And I was really surprised cuz I was like you don't person get convicted for that murder
There's no way 10 years is coming out the other end like
You know anybody who's interested in me like that that seemed
She could balance the scales in his head
With that with a ten year sentence like that seemed about right to
Do you think I'm 10 years for a little for killing
Kelly kid
I mean
I don't know what the fair is such a weird
Saying cuz I feel like I'm a person right to like me
Say it
An 18 year old or 7
18 year old
Maybe 10 years is fair Because by the time that person is
Closing in on 30 years old
Totally changed and matured and like realize like
Woohoo I'm a lot of horrible choices
I don't know that
You're going to
Have a difference between
30 and 50 or 30 and 60 or 30 and 70 in terms of a danger to the
Republic
I did that but that shouldn't be some aspect of
Of
A significant part
Report to
And I don't know that
Ten years after taking a life of somebody is a not I just don't I mean
I understand that there's going to be
There is going to be that change and hopefully there is there's that real late realization like in your late twenties or something like holyshit I
F***** up
Yeah I f***** up
But
I don't know that that's
Just because you have that realization then you should be able to get out there should be some aspect of a punishment with the Punisher
For I don't know any years and years for like
It's not just that it was a baby
Okay
It was a
Blatant disregard for everybody's safety on that street
Thank God we all sing
Make a chat okay
At this point I feel like even I need a reminder
It is not Ryan's job to sentence anyone
That's for the judge
But certainly Brian is teeing up the sentences people get
He's thinking about sentences
It was also striking to learn what Brian was not thinking about
Deterring crime
Or who exactly is getting locked up
He doesn't come to work every day thinking about criminal justice policy
That's not what's guiding him
You know
Deterrence and laws and how to fix communities and all that type of stuff like
I try not to
I kind of think of it that way I think it's just we're better off worrying about our
Are victims here
Because
When I'm
Talking to somebody that
They had their son killed or their daughter killed her mother raped and murdered
They don't care about the deterrent
They don't give a s*** about
Somebody else's kid or whatever
They care about what am I doing for them
And
That's what I that's how I try to keep it
So I try to think of what can I
The best thing I can do for these people you know sometimes it's a play sometimes going to try whatever
Hit some
I don't know that we ever if we deter people we hope we do I mean that's why
We have some of these sentences and things like that but
And we've got gun specs now for people that if you commit a crime with a gun you're going away from our prison
And we have one of your guns back some 3 year and 5 year and 8 year specs and
I think they're great but I don't know if it's a limited amount of guns that are on the streets you know I mean
But isn't the touring the night sky from picking up a gun I don't know
Brian is using all the legal and procedural tools at his disposal
All the tools we've given him
Resolve case
Mostly through please
But he doesn't know if what he's doing is making Cleveland any safer
You can't consult research that'll tell him what sentences equal what result
Or a Statewide database showing whether sentences are being applied equally without racial bias
Because and I know I mentioned this before but it Bears repeating because it is a massive black hole in our own understanding of
Marrone criminal justice system
But there is no comprehensive data on sentencing we don't keep track
What we do know is that overall more and more prosecution's longer and longer prison sentences
Well they do have some effect on crime
But not that much
It's very little bang for such a huge box
That's why Brian concentrates on the only result he can really see day today
We just want some measure of Peace descends on a crushed family
So that's what he aims for
A punishment big enough to trigger the healing power of Retribution
I mean that's the way you have to look at it he said
Because if you look at it any other way
Did lose your mind
Dominique Williams wasn't going to agree to 30 years flat time he also rejected an offer of 20
Need a life
Instead he took it to trial
He was convicted easily
He's now serving sentence
35 years to life
And the grand jury vote on the abdul-rahman case
They know build the voluntary manslaughter
They did not think he should be charged with a crime for shooting and you're easily
Seems they decided
It was self-defense
After spending about 7 weeks in jail this rahkman pleaded guilty to illegally having a gun
He was sentenced to two years probation
Brian met with Andrew Easley family to tell them about the grand jury vote
He said they were unhappy about it
But that he thought they understood it
Many months later I interviewed and release older sister Jacqueline
She did not understand it
Should watch the security tapes from the bus
She didn't understand why the prosecutors didn't charge the two people whom she thought inside of the thing
Andrew's girlfriend Rachel who kicked Mr Rahman off the bus
And the younger man who'd initially believed Mr rahkman
And she didn't understand why mr. Rahman himself wasn't charged
She didn't think he was acting in self-defense when he shot her brother
The two people that did put their hands on their shoes
So you had every reason to shoot
If it was self-defense
You know they come to Peyton you slapping you kicking you
Okay yes offense
Running touch
My brother and say one word to you
Could you understand how a grand jury could watch those same tapes and come to a
Different conclusion than you did
Nope
We didn't ask what how you know
Why but you know they really that
Give me an answer ASAP now all we do is present
And it's up to the grand jury
It's all I got
Now
I don't know I mean I know a lot
A lot about
Did you justice system politics
But now
I asked Jackie what would have been different for her family
What would have felt different
Mr. Rahman had been indicted for murder or manslaughter
She couldn't say exactly
It might have helped some she said
But it wouldn't have helped a great lot
Either way her brother would still be gone
The pain of that would still be radiating through her family
Even so she said
She wanted it
The best outcome you can hope for when a crime happens to you is that your pain is acknowledged
But the person who harmed you is punished
That you get some reparation and believe it or not. Trifecta does happen
We met someone next time
En Serio
Cereals produced by Julie Schneider
Emmanuel Joshi Ben Calhoun and me with additional reporting by Ilyas koskey editing on this episode from
Hourglass Whitney Dangerfield is our digital editor huge congratulations to her for having a baby this week
Research and fact-checking by Ben Phelan sound design a mix by Stone Nelson additional production from Caitlin's
Music clearance by Anthony Roman
Southland is our director of operations
0 staff includes Emily Condon Julie Whitaker Cassie Halle Francis Swanson and Matt Tierney
Our music is by Adam Dorn and how Wilner with additional music from Matt McGinley Nick thorburn and West Schwartz
Theme songs by Nick thorburn and remix by Adam Dorn special thanks to Lisa Weinberger Sarah and
Pictures of Scott Shoemaker at the Ohio criminal sentencing commission ramasubramanian at the Vera Institute of Justice John
OnStaff Paula Boggs muething Rachel dissell judge Pinkie car Kimberly Corral Kim Yoder David Ross
Mike Barber in Katy TX the art on our website is made by Adam maida he created the mural for this type of
And my studio did the animation please check it out on our website
Serialpodcast.org
Serial podcast. Org
We can also sign up for our email newsletter and be notified when new episodes are released
We're also of course on Facebook and Twitter
Support for serial comes from ZipRecruiter
Unlike many jobs ZipRecruiter doesn't wait for candidates to find you
ZipRecruiter find some for you
So you get qualified candidates fast
Try it free at ziprecruiter.com cereal that ziprecruiter.com cereal
Support for serial comes from Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and Business website with Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and professional tools from Google
Use offer code professional
For discount on your first purchase