Not too long ago the Public Zoo
Up in Calgary Alberta
Beast a unique Pro
They have these lovely Asian elephants
Sri Lanka
Animal display for almost 40 years
Swarna is
Kind of the odd one out she's Beyonce
And and then there's a biological pair Kamala and Ronnie the mother and daughter
Is a reporter for NPR who first told us about the
And she said the problem was one that will be familiar to anyone who has traveled
Canada
In the winter
The weather sucks
Especially if you are from Sri Lanka
Calgary's up in Alberta so it is chilly most of the year it's
Snowing it's slushy is gross outside
For years the zoo officials in Calgary
Had been making the best
Of this elephant Scituate
We've made Snowmen for them and
What do they do with the Snowman
Push it over
And then even
Colin Baird is the elephant curator
NFL Canadian I can say that it is always tough to accept
The perhaps
Not every creature should live in the true north strong and free
But calling says eventually they had to face reality
They had to find a new home
For the elephants
They needed to go somewhere where they could be outdoors all year round and have a whole herd of elephants
Around them
You know guys to play with
Now normally when you have something that you don't want anymore
You put up for sale right
He put an ad on Craigslist
Three elephants good condition
No reasonable offer refused
Check the Move Yourself
But zoo animals are different from most
Possessions because
Zoos have this fundamental Prince
You cannot
Cell
Garanimals
You can't buy animals either
It is unethical
Illegal even
To put a price tag on an elephant's head
I can say my name first and you say
Hello looking to Planet Money on Robert Smith Gabrielle I've been reporting for NPR's National.
Korean show
Why did zoos and Aquariums give up one of the most useful tools a business have
Ability to buy and sell their assets
What do you do
In a world
Where you can't use money
Support for this podcast and the following message comes from rocket mortgage by Quicken Loans
Rocket mortgage brings the mortgage process into the 21st century with this completely online process
Safely share your bank statements and pay stubs with the touch of a button
Ditch the paperwork and use her phone or tablet
To get approved for purchase or refinance with a custom mortgage solution in minutes
Check out rocket mortgage today at quickenloans.com money
Equal Housing lender
Licensed in all 50 states
Nmls consumer access. Org number 3030
There's a reason you can buy and sell most
Thanks on Earth
Because it makes everything so easy money let you know who wants what
And let you know how badly they want it
Money lets you get rid of things you don't need
And get things that you do need
And for hundreds of years zoos were like
Any other
They did buy and sell ads
Openly
Larry Brown is a historian at Boston College who studies
Supersprings on a competition to have Prestige animal
Get
The animals really going to
To draw
The publican
The crowds the crowd
And they're willing to spend big money
To get them
To understand
Why zoos eventually got out of the buying and selling business
We're too quick historic
Local stories
The first one happened about 150 years ago
Brown said back then zoos would basically go to explorers
And give them a checklist
For when the next went to Africa or Asia
We want one of those gorillas
Maybe I'm up here of those giraffes
And we are willing to pay
Zoll epitomized is a German man named Carl Hagen bag
He's a businessman who buys and sells wild animal
He really Built This Global Empire
Hagen back could get you anything you want
Polar bears
Can a pot of my wild Mongolian horses
I prided himself as being this honest
Above board business
He would price the animals based on size and bite
Vitality
Even at a money back guarantee
If your animal
Sick
Was not quite the color you wanted
He would refund the price
If the animal was slightly smaller than he promised
DD discount
But even back then you could see the problem
With putting a price on an animal's head
The way Carl Hagen that got his animals was
Pretty horrifying
He got a request in from a zoo in your author America and then go out on the expedition
And he find the family maybe an elephant family and actually
Kill the parents
And then take the Young
Bring them back to the zoos
Call Hagen back talks about this openly in
In his memoirs
He recounts bloody scenes in the jungle
And
The story
In addition to going out and collecting wild beast
He would also
Bring back human
Does he bring back
Eskimos Samoans people from Sudan and he exhibit them in Europe
He put whole family's on display with a little domestic scene
And he call it anthropology
Clearly this did not give Zeus
The best record
Any news
They slowly tried to distance themselves from poachers
And they're pretty horrible Tech
This is not an easy thing to
Because you can say you are going to buy from the back
But if there's a price any price on an animal's head
People will
Hunt those animal people will trap those animal
That's the incentive
And you don't always know what happened
Adam jungle
So getting ready completely out of the zoo business
Took a second
Disturbing event
This one more recent
Let me set the scene
The 1960s
Countries in Asia and Africa have been pushing back
Alex Ikea
The guys in pith helmet
Could just
Walton and Dragway animals
For some City Zoo
And then at the same time
The conservation movement is in full swing
Thanks Rachel Carson's the Silent Spring where everyone's beginning to reassess how humans and nature
Wild animals all in Iraq
In 1973 there was as big conf
Trying to figure out how to stop the Wild and
Animal trade
How to implement new conservation rules
And they're having trouble as these conferences do agreeing on anything
While they were in session
There is this surprise
News copper
One of the assistant Secretary of the Interior Nathaniel Reed stands up and says
Federal agents in New York
Have discovered this huge
Smuggling ring
There was a damaged crate
At JFK Airport
An Airline employee looked inside and saw something suspicious
Animal skin
A lot
Of animal skin
And he called federal agent
And it turns out they're all these
Furs and pelts in there
Thousand illegal pelt
And they're literally from all over the world
South America Eastern Asia
South Asia
And it's leopard skins Jaguars Pumas cheetahs
The officials look at this
They sit down and do the calculations and they figure
That one tenth of the world
Cheetah population
Is there
Impel
Representatives at the conference were horrified
This is what happens when you can buy and sell animals
Not long after they signed a global set of restrictions on the trade of endangered species
And US The Endangered Species Act passes
The same year
Now even though this was prompted by trade in pelts
Custom skins and Ivory
But the zoo Community this meant they had to change the way they did business
As you buy and sell endangered species
You need a permit and you have to prove
The buying and selling these animals is somehow going to benefit
Population that's out in the wild
Now that is really hard to prove
But there's a loophole
And that is that if you don't
Buy or sell them if you don't get money involved in this equation
Then you don't need a permit
This was specific
2 endangered species
Mizzou started to adopt these principles for most all of them
Aquariums to
Let's just take money out of the equation
The rule became the animals should not be commodities
Should not have a price
Should not be paid
How
Do you get animal
Fill up all of these lovely zoos and Aquarium
Well there is one way to distribute resources without money
It's what we did before we had money
The oldest trick in the book
Bartering
Gabriella and I went to an aquarium where they have
New England Aquarium is out on the waterfront
Boston and the centerpiece of the place
Is this amazing multi-storey
Yeah it's incredibly colorful it's a Caribbean coral reef and my favorite part was there.
Giant turtle Myrtle the Turtle
It's just huge and it's been there for four decades
Since the aquarium open
What are the advantages that aquariums have
Is that most of their animals that are not
So they can often go out of
Collect species
Make an occasional use money but
Aquarius try to trade and barter
For most of what you see on display
Are usually starts with something small
In the case of the New England Aquarium here in Boston
The basic unit of trade
Is the jelly
The New England Aquarium breed and barters
Hundreds of the little guy
Traders take us back to the vault
And the place looks like Jacques cousteau's living room there's tanks everywhere the sound of water pumps
Roaring
And hundreds of beautiful translucent
Jellyfish
Hanging out
Are your classic
Jelly designs a pulsating
Medusa with extremely long
Very diaphanous tentacles mouthparts that look like freely
Petticoats or
Unmentionables
Steve Bailey is a curator of fishes at the New England Aquarium
Every aquarium once a jelly
Evergreen with a lot of jellyfish
And Steve.
Which makes him I guess
The pretty rich man in the aquarium Fighter game
But it is a very inconvenient
Form of my
Here's how
Recently the curators had their eye
On this beautiful
Oh they wanted
It is known as
The look down
It's a silvery schooling fish with a very unusual physiognomy it's
Forehead is radically slow
And in their eyes are perched right at the edge of that plane and
They look like they're looking down
Grumpy dinner
If you can picture that
Now in aquarium in North Carolina
Had beef
But North Carolina wanted more than jellyfish
North Carolina
Wanted
So Boston had to go find the snipe fish
Which came to us
From Japan
That were the result of a trade for lumpfish
Boston Bruins and Grunts and in the end
We got lookdowns
Plain head files
Sombrero fish
Tarantulas look down
Samir grunts
By the time the truck rolls off the plaza there's probably been weeks and weeks if not months and months of disgust
If you wanted to see
What the world was like before money was invented
You should go to an aquarium
Bartering takes forever
But Steve says
This is what makes
It's so satisfying when you pull it off
What aquarium guys hang out at the bar at their meeting
They tell these incredible stories
Barter success
And Butterfield
We asked Steve what was his favorite trade
What was the trade he was most proud of
I would say that trading a school of mackerel for a flock of puffins
Was one of the best phrase that we
That we New England Aquarium lights LED
It managed to do
Dan do you remember how many puffins we got
Yeah it was at least a dozen
And how many Mac Williamson
When you did this trade and everyone knew
The puffin
The macro ratio
In the United States does that like set some sort of
Standard did everybody go out then and know like that is the official exchange rate from Michael puffins to the matter
No I think it's each institution could
Be considered a country in you operate with your own currency in the exchange rate is
Based on
The institution with whom you're dealing
I have to say
There is an easier way to do all this
Which is you could have just said
You know 600 macro are worth a thousand bucks
And the puffins are worth a thousand bucks and you could have just like done this through a bank
Like
Well money your
Is money worth more to us than the animal
Bet you can't go out and buy puffins
So
We could have been sitting on a pile of
$100,000
And we still would have been puffing
You said school kids do not come to an aquarium to see a big pile of money
They come to see the
The look down
The jellyfish
And that's the beauty of this system
The collection of an aquarium
Is an asset that can be traded in loan
But it's also.
It's also how they make their real money
I should say the Sue's do things a little
They're a little more strict about their Adam
Yeah so they don't like the bartering cyst
They don't want to set this precedent that a panda is worth a thousand Turtles
Or whatever
Instead The Association of zoos and Aquariums has set up something that's kind of like a private Craigslist
It's called the animal likes
And it's a place
Will you miss
What animals do you need and then you also list
Whatever animals you're trying to unload
Yeah you don't get money or even some sort of abstract credit when you give up an animal
You get basically
Good Karma
You get a good relationship with another Zoo
Who might do you a favor might give you an animal down the line
It's like one of those take a penny leave a penny bowls
But without
Speed elephant
Gabriella
Why don't you
Bring us up-to-date on what happened with those elephants
Canada Calgary decided it was time to give up their elephants and focus Alpha
Belize elephants
They needed a new home
So they call that the ACA the association of zoos and aquariums
And they drew up a list of possible zoos that might want these out
And then they took a road trip
They went and they visited all these issues they're different campuses they looked at the homes the dorms
And together the Aza and Calgary Zoo
Picked a new home
And the winner
The National Zoo
In Washington DC
They build this big new elephant complex
Wading pool
Sandbox
Their $2 donation to ship the elephants across the
The country home
Convoy
Veterinarians the works
And of course
All that money spent
The price for the elephants
What's 0
I went to visit them here in DC
See in their new home
And the elephants they look pretty good
They're comfortable and actually kind of wrestling with one another figuring out the social dynamics
And the crowds were pretty happy to
S4 Calgary
On the balance sheet they were the losers
In this deal
Play Chris got no money for the elephant
But the karma system
Did seem to work
Tell me that major respect
For putting the welfare of their elephants
For sending it to a better place
And lo and behold
Other zoos
Send Calgary extra animals that they have
Calgary got a new Indian rhino
Komodo dragon
For free of course
Still on the list
Lemurs
Calvary wants black and white lemurs
Call me if you got them
Muslim Snowman
Willie's love to hear what you think of Planet Money you can email us at Planet Money at NPR. Org or getting
InTouch on Facebook
Or Twitter
The story first ran in 2014 as reported by Gabrielle and Manuel and me and it was really pretty
Juice by Jessie J
Please rerun was produced by Elizabeth kulas
Looking for another short listen to may I suggest NPR's ask me another
Ask me another is like trivia night
But funnier
They taking a bar in Brooklyn I've been many times it is a hilarious show
And you always learn some
You can listen to play along it npr.org podcasts
Guanyin Tijuana
I'm Robert Smith
Thanks for listening