This message comes from NPR sponsors snowfall
The only data warehouse
Built for the cloud
Unlock deep Data Insights with the instantly scalable Cloud build data warehouse
Start your journey towards data-driven decision
It's snowflake. Com NPR
Since the very early days of Planet Money we have regularly gotten emails from people asking us
Please please do a show about this
The thing I had to buy that seems weirdly
Xbox
He got the textbook there
Ideal yeah let me grab it
That wasn't cheap.
Fisher
This is Kendall Raiden to go to school at American River College in Calif
What's it called with the title
Where is college physics
And how much was the text
How much it was
Salt $310
It was the most expensive book she'd ever seen
Really she thought
$310 for a book
But some online stuff
So I was actually kind of irritated
You know
So I ended up at some point though I just needed the book you know we were starting class
Homework and
What's after I just went and
But put on a credit card
Kendall is not questioning the value of an education or that in long-run should be earning more as a result of
Class
And the price that book will be a drop-in
It just seemed like a lot of money for what it was
And something truly strange has been going on in the text
There's this chart to get cited a lot maybe you've even seen
It's from a government report on text
Book prices
And shows the price of new textbooks over the past decade and is a very steep
The prices of new textbooks have been going up like crazy
Faster than clothing
Food
Cars
Even Healthcare
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm David kestenbaum and I'm Jacob Goldstein today on the
By popular demand why are textbooks so expensive
We talked to the students
And textbook authors and analysts and Publishers and
After all that we think
We found a pretty satisfying answer
Support for this podcast and the following message comes from rocket mortgage by Quicken Loan
Rocket mortgage brings home financing into the 21st century with
Was completely online process
Fast easy and convenient
Ditch the paperwork and use your phone or tablet to safely share your bank statements and pay stubs
In a few minutes get a custom mortgage Solution on your terms
Check out rocket mortgage today at quickenloans.com money
Equal Housing lender
Licensed in all 50 states
Nmls consumer access. Org number 3030
Let's start with a guy named James Cook
He taught economics at Old Dominion University for a long time
I never thought about the economics of tech
Xbox until at some point
Student started coming to him and asking
Excuse me professor
Do we really need this book you a sign for class
It's kind of expense
Cook's at death you need it
It's a good book
But this got him thinking about the odd nature of the text
One thing in particular
Which is that
He was the one who is choosing the book
He thought about it carefully the book was well-written
You know it was clear and it had
Good problems at the end of the chapters
Do you realize there was one key thing he did not know about it
I did not know how much it cost
Normally cook says
The person deciding to buy something is also the person paying
For that thing
In this case
That relationship was severed
The person choosing was not paying
Economist call this the principle agent problem
The principal is the person with the money
The agent is the guy figuring out how to spend
I call it the
Someone else's money Bravo
If someone spending someone else's
Is it really true Professor don't think about price when they're looking at textbook
I've been in higher education now for
What about for decades
And
I never have had a single textbook salesperson come into my office and talk about price
They're always talking about
G we have this new carburetor this new topics
We have this new DVD we have these
Ways that you can test students and
Give them quizzes and keep track of their progress It's always what's in the textbook package
Never about the price
God for a salesperson
Not a taco
Price
Well it's not odd when you think that they're talkin
To a person who doesn't have to pay it
That's the problem huh
This can lead to higher prices really into different ways I mean first the simple one is
Publishers just have less of an incentive to
Keep prices down to compete on price
But the second one is actually more interesting to me
This Market
Can lead to a fancier textbooks and you get otherwise a textbook
Loaded up with stuff that students might not need
Cuz remember it's the professor who's the customer
Two Publishers of go to professors and say hey
By your textbook it comes with online quizzes and slides and a workbook I remember when I was in college like at the
The back of the biology textbook they was this DVD sitting that I never once used
But I paid for it in the price of the book
Ask about this
Particular economic Tech
I happen to have
It is the best-selling economics
Textbook in America by Harvard Economist Greg
You can buy it on Amazon for $286 in
Tarasco
Does what you're saying
Mean that Greg McHugh your fellow Economist is making more money than he should
It was an awkward question but I had to ask
Cook did not went away in so we did something more aqua
We called up Greg mankiw himself
This is a Greg mankiw I'm a professor of Economics at Harvard University
Let me just start by saying thank you for agreeing to come in and be grilled about the price of your texts
It's my pleasure I think
I want to know what did the author of an economics
Think about the very Market that that
Textbook Within
The principal-agent problem is right there in his book
Sun page 406
So I ran the idea by him that professors who picked the books aren't paying attention to
He agreed this was not ideal
But he didn't see it as a big problem
I don't think it's unusual
A market is you suggest any less of other markets that are similar when you
Go get a medical operation you often rely on the advice of a doctor
You know your paint you are the insurance companies paying the price when you go get your car fixed you're lying in the
Mechanics pick out the parts
App for you and your building a new house or a new extension on your house you're relying on your contractor to
Find the right parts in
Look out for your best interest
So I think it's a lot of situations where we we rely on someone else
Help us make an informed decision is certainly the textbook Market
It is that way
I feel like the examples you chose Healthcare
Paying a contractor to work on your house going to a mechanic
Are all the things that people hate paying for for this reason I mean
People who get their homes renovated talk about what a nightmare it is and Healthcare is this famously broken Market
What is it whenever you have a principal-agent problem there is a risk of the agent
In this case is the professor doesn't
Doesn't do due diligence
Aspen do it doesn't do their job correctly and
Look out for the best
Interests of the principal in this case has this business student
The good professor what would do that
Thank you says Professor do think a lot about what's best for the students
The biggest expenditure for students
It's not expenditure money but expenditure of their time
A lot of time in a course they should fit a lot of time in the course if they're going to get a lot out of it
And I want their time
To use it productively that can be
And giving them the best book
To read
That I can
Is baseball more important than saving them a few dollars so if somebody comes in and I have a book
Definitely not as good but they say your students $33
I'm going to keep giving it they're going to spend
40 50 60 70 hours of reading spoke of the course of a semester
Am I really going to skimp on a textbook to get something at inferior I don't think so
Okay we have this theory about the someone else's money prop
I'm driving up
The cost of college
It makes sense
But it seems hard to
Right
You need some parallel universe with a
The people choosing the textbooks were paying
So you can see what difference
Fortunately for us that parallel universes exist
It's called
High School
Very nice
High School textbooks are chosen and paid
For by the local
It turns out that forces Publishers to keep the cost down
Jonathan helliwell is a financial analyst
Panmure Gordon one of the oldest brokerages in England
He says Publishers are much
Smaller profit
On high school textbooks than they do
Oncologist
School book publishers
Megabox
Talk to 10% profit margins and college textbook Publishers make 22nd like 20 25%
Profit margin
And you think one reason is that
The people picking the books aren't thinking about cost
The biggest reason is who's the customer and
And what's be
Thanks for the boiling process
Has anyone in the publishing business ever acknowledged you that they have this advantage of the professors on thinking about coffee
They they haven't argued about it when I put it to the minister that way
The someone else's money theory is power
But it leaves out this one big thing that just about everybody we talked to agreed was a major factor driving
And it's something that it does not seem like it would make prices go up
It is the used textbook
20 years ago that used book Market was local basically you'd go to your College bookstore
How to use copy
Buy it if not yours
The internet of course changed all that
Now in a student in Florida finishes her class she can sell her book on eBay to someone in Montana
Or just get a book on Amazon
Here looking at the page from mankiw textbook
New version $286 used
$227
If you don't mind one that's 2 years old
Then get the previous Edition used for
26th
This means that if your publisher or text book author
You have this really short window to make money off your book because
After the first semester
All the students who bought your book are going to turn around and sell it to the next batch
Robert Frank is an economist at Cornell has written a textbook with
Former fed chairman Ben Bernanke
Used to be
Your new addition would come out then the next year it would sell half as many copies as the first year and then half again
On the third year and now it's you sell copies
If you selling it all in the first year and it's it's done
Almost nothing the next year
Tell if your Textbook Company faced with this problem what do you do
You're selling fewer books
How are you going to cover your costs
Well you raised
And this it seems is what
Textbook companies did
But raising prices just made things worse
People came up with new ways to avoid those higher
Textbook rental
Illegal download
Substance
Skip buying books all together
Which meant the textbook companies were selling even fewer books
So they raised the price for new books again
You can see where this is going one textbook sales and I talked to call today
A spiral of
Destruction
So you have this battle
On the one hand the price of new textbooks going up and up and up
On the other hand
Student finding lots of ways around buying new full price books
Who's winning
Print out there's data on this
Comes from the National Association of college stores
Did UT student surveys asking
How much do you actually spend on
We talked to Richmond they went through the numbers
In 2007 how much did students spend
$702
2090 years later
I reported spending $667
It went down
Yes it did
$655
Down again
Went up a bit the next year then down even further
So what we seen essentially is flat to declining spending from students with the students were saying their spending
Required course material
Over the last 5-6 years
Students have basically fought the Publishers to a draw
And yet everyone seems to feel like they're
Students will have to pay $300 for new fee
Physics textbook
Professors who hearing their students complain
Textbook sales
People who once felt proud that they were helping further education
Banal embarrassed to be out selling these really
Which may be one reason why when I finally sat down with
David Levy
The president in
CEO
I'm one of the biggest textbook companies
Surround McGraw-Hill Edge
Education
He did not want to talk about text
I kept asking about books
He kept talking about educational soft
Peace out of the way out of this big spiral of Destruction and
And Rising price
Electronic
Interactive
WakeUpNow 500 Engineers building those full-time about a hundred and fifty million dollars a year
Going to product creation
Your grandfather's Textbook Company
Didn't do that
It's a past ride a business which was simple produce books and that's what it did
We are plowing shoes resources into creating a new set of instructional materials
Which help students
And help instructors and do so at a much lower price than ever been seen before
Really don't talk about books anymore
We we doing this isn't this is not is not very interesting to us
Digital textbooks are cheaper than traditional textbooks
Easy to update they don't weigh anything
But for students there is this one big drawback
You kept telling back to the bookstore or to anyone
At the end of the semester
There is no used market for digital textbook
I just got to find a way to keep students from downloading them
Car show today was produced by Phil Benton you can email
Illicit Planet Money at NPR. Org find us on Facebook and Twitter also special thanks to Eric Wile at
Student monitor for sharing your data on textbook spending and all the students to talk to me about their expensive textbook
Purchase Beverly Minton Jamie pipe Phillips Josh Raymond and Brittany boscell several be by the way at the
Look into why there seem to be this constant stream of new editions of textbooks are those really necessary you ask
What time is it in California
Copy
Do we ask this question
Robert Frank The Economist told us that for the microeconomics textbook that he right he did not see any good read
Why it needed to be updated as often as it is
He said for macroeconomics
You would want to update it because you know there are things like the financial crisis that have
I also asked David 11 the CEO of McGraw-Hill education about New Edition
Particular we were talking about calculus textbooks because you know subjective calculus doesn't really change
He told me they published one calculus book it had last been updated in 2011 five years after the previous Edition
He said they added a bunch of new problems and revived some parts of the text
But he wrote quote I can pretty much guarantee that we will never produce another print edition of this book
All right I think that's it
And I'm Jacob.
Thanks for listening