Everyone Robert Smith here last week who played an episode from a series that we made in 2012 when we created the
Perfect
Presidential candidate
He was a fake candidate but his policy ideas were great
At least according to economist
Today
You will hear us bring our candidate
The people
Previously on Planet Money
6 Economist from across the political Spectrum
Dean Baker Carteret Roberts
Sky News left of center
Tomaki but not necessarily pro-business
Thrown together with one impossible mission
The come up with an economic plan to rescue the economy
1 cat
In order to save the country
They're going to have to work together
To restructure the tax code
The the corporate income tax makes no sense whatsoever eliminate cherish deductions
Did mortgage interest deduction to preserve the environment
Tax energy use or carbon emissions by weight
Deal once and for all
With the scourge of illegal drugs make them legal
And maybe just maybe
This ragtag team can come up with a platform that every Economist would love
And every presidential candidate would hate
Except
For our fake one
God bless you and God bless the United States of America
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Caitlin Kenney
This
Is it for six months now we have been hatching this plan
Create a fake presidential candidate based on the best ideas to economics has to offer
Wheaton Planet Money episodes where we created the platform for presidential candidates
We hacked up disagreements we brought in political Consultants
Laughed at us at first but then said no no we can help you sell this plan
We have done it all and today
We take it to the
The people very carefully selected and Screen group
The people
You take this to a focus group in DC and ask would anyone vote for these crazy ideas anyway
Planet Money is supported by betterment
The largest independent Robo advisor with more than 180 thousand customers
Andover 5.5 billion dollars under management
Betterment makes it easier and less expensive to invest for your personal financial goals
With a beautiful user interface I'm smart Cutting Edge technology that are meant brings you sophisticated personalized
Financial advice
All of the lower-cost
Planet Money listeners get up to 6 months free
To learn more about betterment
Visit betterment.com Planet Money
In order to see what real people think
You have to go to a very
Take place
We're in Washington DC in this.
Generic off
Tower
Probably one of the blandest conference rooms you've ever seen and that's actually a picture because
This is where they do the focus groups
And nothing is supposed to be controversial here it's supposed to be very Bland nothing to distract real voters from the real
Pinyin
Sure information in this room
I got to say it was pretty sweet
We had to sit behind this two-way mirror looking into the conference room
And we watch
Does a LED 10 independent voters in
It was cool because we could see them we could hear everything they were saying
But they can see us
Thanks everybody for
For coming out
I will try and do something that you never get to do in real life
Listen to a bunch of people
Talking about you take a planet money talk about our kindness ideas
And they have no idea that we're listening
I feel like
I feel like I'm eavesdropping on my phone
Another thing that's weird is that
People in the folks
Describe there in the sterile room it's really bright
But we're here behind the glass
It's dimly-lit
There's some rows of seats
BA free drinks and all you can eat M&Ms
It's kind of like being in a movie
Ipsos public affairs in Washington DC kindly agreed to let us borrow their folks group
For the night Michael Gross is the moderator
And he told us what to look for he says
You're basically looking for something called
Resonance
Which is not only what people say
But what they don't say
Part of the beauty of focus groups
And having people
Be able to see them
Is you can see the small little Visual and physical
Ques like what you'll see people
You know kind of caulking the head maybe starts and start to nod a little bit like
Okay I get the concept and yes I I liked it so I should be taking notes on that ice
Just be watching for that
Yeah you should be watching for visual cues often times you'll see people you know if they're not really interested in something
Built the push back from the table
Cordell cross their arms in front of them which means they really don't care about talking about that
Kind of subject
We move our chairs up about 2 in
Glass
So we can catch every
Angela Clark and runs the political team at if so sits next to us and Michael moderator goes into the room with the focus
And he hands out our play
So everything we worked on in last six months is now a stack
Papers
And each page has
1 iD
One item of the presidential platform on it
Any purchased a focus group to start going through it
With a pen
He asked them to cross out what they don't like
And circle what they do
There was a lot
There's a lot of Crossing out
The first idea is one that are condoms from across the political Spectrum love
It's to get rid of the mortgage interest tax
If you want to home
You can write off of
A big chunk of your mortgage on your taxes
I kind of sake what this really is is a huge government subsidy for
People who happen to own rather than rent
Michael read off some of the argument
For eliminating
Mortgage interest deduction is an
Extremely regressive form of Taxation and music
Extremely perverse
That we shouldn't be helping Bill Gates or whoever
Subsidizing them to get an expensive home
Rich people get a larger subsidy which causes the price of houses to
The increase
Making homes less affordable for poor
And what they don't know is Bowser actual quotes from
Previous shows at Planet money has done it but he's just read them up
And
People when they hear this
They shake their head
Lakebay
Hate everything he sang
Unless a table is A well-dressed older woman her name is Irene
We have a briefing book that tells us about all the participants here and this tells us that she has a high school education
And although it doesn't say it we can tell
Woman owns her own home
Three-quarters of your mortgage goes to interest so if they eliminated that
On that deduction it would be like you're throwing your money out the window every month
You know if you didn't get that deduction get something for it
Once people start talking about this you can pretty much tell who owns a home and who doesn't because
The homeowners
Hate this idea for a very simple read
The amount they pay in taxes is going to go up
But that is inevitable
And then the moderator
Explain another argument about eliminating the mortgage interest tax deduction
What's this
This deduction is subsidy by the government
Actually
Makes the price of homes too high if you eliminate it
In the price of homes will actually go down
And you can see people just look
Karafun paid at this process
Yeah Maryland end we know from our book that she makes under $25,000
Xavier
She has some college at 2
Location
Fastest way to group when she speak
They really listened to
She hates it
If
Housing prices go down lower
This is going to be very dangerous especially for a
Decided it's top-heavy with baby boomers are the Raging
They were actually like economist
The came up with this I just want to let you read you a couple of comments that actually made a sour face when the moderator said the
Visceral reaction like
About they were like listen
No one's going to care that Economist design this plan
Hilo pretty Lake
Economist
Turns out
They were right
Yeah and it gets worse because it turns out it's not just the economist they hate
They hate the very language that the economist use to help sell the
Even the words are turning off the voters
It was one young woman
Eva a
And she dropped it to say that she hated one particular word that she her
Eliminate
Fake ID time you laminate something or get rid of it
It's going to backfire in a different area
There's lots of nodding now around the
Julia from episodes she leans over to us as soon as she hears that
This kind of thing from a focus group participants this is exactly what the political Pros are listening for
A picture of this
They might not want to use the word eliminate
Those words scare her and they wouldn't want to use those words in a communication because it would be off-putting perhaps to
Server has two people from her demographic
Strongly moderate taxes
Why candidate sound the way they do often times cuz their statements have been Focus Group
It does mean a modulate their own opinion so
Conley
I don't mind them up with American voters that some of probably there aren't reviews are lost I think that's almost certainly the
McKay's
You know it's the Challenger focus groups that are useful but to what extent you want to react to them and to what extent
Define the face of public opinion I mean
It's a balance for politicians to deal
Better to know now than later
Even if you're going to stick to your guns and say something I'm popular at least you know how people are going to react and that's useful to
It's not just the words that people hate that the pros are listening for
They're also listening for the way people describe things
The language that they use
Because what better way to appeal to the average voter
Then to use something that came out of their own mouth
Julia says that when you see those ads
Set featured this real person or that real person some of those people actually came into focus groups just like this
Yeah that's what we're kind of hoping for but at least when it comes to the mortgage interest tax deduction
There were no nice
We're not going to have
Okay so quick show of hands
How many of you would vote for a candidate that had this is
Part of the retina
Dollar policy
Without specifics
With no specific
Absolutely not
Okay
Nobody raised their hands
Tintoretto monel
I'm scared
Flight number one
They hate it
Yep no one supports eliminating the mortgage interest tax
Not single
And this is just the start of it
It was a long night people either hated the plans or they
They didn't understand them
Sometimes
Does the moderators going through our list of ideas
Boat after boat turns
Becomes had this idea about taxing health benefits that's rejected
Almost immediately
Another idea
Which was to move away from an income tax to more of a consumption-based tax collector
The bat they have in Europe
Baptist Mission
Weird and vague
2 actual words used by Focus
Participants
Another plank in our platform was eliminating the
Corporate income tax
The Economist argued
Attacks or something we want to encourage
Corporations making profit we want them to reinvest the money
So that they can go out and hire p
Yeah when people argue that we should have a high corporate income tax what they're really saying is
We want to soak the rich want the rich to pay their fair share
And it comes aren't you just don't do that through Corporation if you want it
Rich people then text rich people
Leave the corporations to create jobs and if they pay out of their profits
Their shareholders and dividends
Then you can talk
But this idea
It gets Steve
To lean forward he's sitting at the end of the table
College-educated
Middle-aged
Just isn't buying it
So if you don't
Text the the companies
Houston
Where are you going to get the money from
Just Like Heaven
Is so strange
Behind the glass
Because
You want to go in and argue with the guy
Because I kind of thought of this they've described where the money can come from and you can get it
In-N-Out places it's just basically Shifting the tax burden and what they would say if they more
Fair and effective and productive
It doesn't it doesn't matter because I'm not allowed to argue with the guy
And Julia for ipsos
She says this reaction happens all the time
And you got a client behind the screen
And the message testing is going badly
All that you can do to keep that client for marching out of this room into the focus group room
And explaining to
Joe from Cincinnati why his position is wrong
If you have to convince work that hard to convince someone of your point of view you've already lost the argument when it comes to
Vacations in messaging
But I've definitely been in this room before with a client who is
Has to be restrained literally from going around the around the corner to have a chat
What does that people on the phone
Are moderated 6-1
Particular idea for
And you can see why
He wanted to keep
So every Economist agreed absolutely
We should legalize marijuana
They said making it illegal to
Dry ice price
Drug dealers rich
The government gets no tax revenue for it and yet the government is on the hook
To build prisons
Put all those people who smoke pot into the prison
So they agree that this just
Economically makes no sense
But the folks at ipsos Julia and Michael
They predicted that talking about something like drugs was bound to divide any good
And you were right
People, think about this issue and
Consider both sides
They're just either immediately for it
Or against
You can really go to jail for a small amount
Weird
It's
It's not
Okay
Marijuana helps a lot of people
It can be social it can be for recreational use
And
I guess
Creative
It makes you creative in some ways if you're
Artistic
I have enough faith in my own creativity
That I don't need
To make myself fart
Official in my brain
To be creative
It in me
And I don't need a
Drug
To turn the key and I don't think anyone else does either
Unless you become dependent on it
But that's going off.
That was Mark in Maryland they are never going to
Agree on this issue at a fact that's true the entire focus group when they took the vote
The group is evenly
Split on legalizing pot
In some ways this was a tiny Victory because
Legalizing drugs did better than just about
Any other plank on our platform
But you cannot build
An entire campaign was approved by economist
On legalizing
It's just not going to
But little did they know we had our
Secret weapon we've been talking for weeks to
Political Consultants
Advertising experts to the best in the business
Are wechat listen
You know these ideas are going to be a tough sell
What do you got for us
Help us convince people
That they would vote for this candidate
Soap
We told the moderator
Bring up the ads
Okay picture guy in a casual shirt
He's talking straight to the camera
He's standing in front of some
Out-of-focus foliage
Annie's going to talk about
The Economist plan
Now our moderator just read up a copy to the focus group
We're going to do it with an act
Courage
Common sense
I know that the fix our economy we need some hard truths
Legalizing marijuana would save billions in law enforcement and prosecution
Add to the tax base
And stop making drug dealers rich
Mifold jobs plan would end the corporate income tax
So American companies can reinvest and create American jobs
It's about hard truth
It's about change
It's about time
Vis-a-vis by political consultant Joe Slade White
He's got a buffalo and he's won a ton of awards
He's been doing this
4 years
Right away
With the focus group
We can see that
Wasn't quite work
By including all the controversial parts of the plan
People just have this immediate visceral reaction
Part of the plan
They didn't like
Or maybe more than one part of the planet
The addres started that whole argument
We had about marijuana
I don't think it matters what he says
Because
The legalization of marijuana
Is one of those
Dairy
Pacific
Polarizing issues
Like abortion
Like gay marriage
And
You're for it or you're a Genet
And there's nothing to candidates going to say that's going to change your mind
Okay stay away from drugs in a political campaign
It took a long time to learn that
But we learned
But we had another ad
This one came from the strategy
Commedia
Alex tornero is there
Creative director
I need a different approach
Rather than putting in a bunch of ideas
He focused on just one
Eliminating the mortgage in
It's time for real tax reform to help the middle
Class
4 years our country is subsidized home mortgage
A deduction that benefits the wealthy and pushes up home prices
For everyone else
It's unfair
And I believe it's time we end that.
And return the savings to you by bolstering education
Improving Services for Seniors
Funding job training for
Okay I'm just going to pop in here for a quick second because
I just I should mention here that the ad guys came up
The bit about
Children
And seniors
Not yet
Okay proceed
Renting owning
Large house with small
American families deserve a fair tax plan that helps every home
I'm an actor
Giving voice to a plan designed by economist
And I approve this message
What's after the moderator weeds
Out this
Market
The end of the table leans in a little bit
Incest
Thumbs up
Seriously they like you to remember every single person voted against this when we use the economist link
Now
Even Maryland
The one who is so concerned about house prices for baby boomers
Kind of liked it
I think that
It's an effective ad
So we're feeling pretty good we're thinking
We are actually going to pull this off
The help of these experts we're going to convince people that these are ideas they would actually vote for
Things that they like
Yeah no
Yeah
It turned out
Defect with
After the focus group wrapped up if you were heading out I told Marilyn aside and said tell me more about how you really like
Like that at
And she said that although she liked the part about Fair taxes
JCP ad
Left you with a big Quest
Wait a minute
What are they eliminating
How does that help with
But in that quick moment
It feels good
And I guess this is why political advertising gets a bad rap as manipulative
But
I was thinking like
There is
A serious Point here which is if you can make someone
Feel good
About an issue
Even for a quick moment
Then maybe they can consider an idea that otherwise they would have completely
Shut out the
So
The whole thing the emotional content the kids
Seniors distressing
Fair tax
Airtech butt
In some ways
All we did
What's the open
I need or open a door that says
The mortgage interest tax deduction week in Italy
Just talked about
We can at least
Consider what the economist
Had to sack
One small problem
Economist
The folks who came up with these ideas
They hate
They spent a long time explaining the intricate logical reasoning behind their plant
Anime C 29 seconds of
Let's be honest like not the most sophisticated thinking in the world
So you like all of Luigi zingales from the University of Chicago
And
He looked at the ad he said you know
You picked
The wrong
He said that we should have pointed out
Dubai eliminating the mortgage interest tax deduction
We could lower tax rates for every
India you're pushing more
We can spend the money and a lot of other ways and location this and that which is also true but
Is not the way I was salad
Dean Baker another one of our comments
Hue Lights
The part about fairness
Ethos uses that argument himself
Cops we should have pointed out
Did the mortgage interest deduction
Doesn't save as much money as most
People think
In other words
We could have argued instead that getting rid of that deduction won't hurt
Too much
Everybody has ideas after you make your ad right
Captain Baker from Harvard she agreed with the Luigi and Dean Baker about some of those criticisms
But you came away with sort of a bigger lesson
Perhaps she said
She and the other economist
Perhaps they should stick
The classroom
Where they have ours
Hours
An hours
To explain this
From an economic perspective where we try to spend a lot of time going into the details of the pros and the cons of things
That just doesn't seem compatible with the 30 second sound byte
I'm going to let you decide what you
I got to stay there like
Did a pretty good job
Encapsulating that sort of warm fuzzy feeling you get from a political ad where you just look at the
The candidate say hey
I talked to that guy only wearing a tie
Check yourself
Npr.org
A little bit impressed with how
Politically ahead his if you can if you want TV
You wouldn't think twice you wouldn't think that's a radical Economist plan you would just think
Another another political ad
That actually is
Something a little
Revolutionary
About this whole project
And that's that
Arcade
Are fake Planet Money candidate
Is not going to get a single vote
I think we can agree with that but
Maybe the next
Can we become
A real character comes along and suggest one of these Economist approved ideas
Maybe that Kelly wants out his radical
If he or she can say
At least I'm not as crazy
At the Planet Money guy
On a website you can watch the two political ads we made for a candidate that npr.org money
Tell us what you think of the episode
Find us on Facebook or Twitter or email us
Planet Money at npr.org
Please rerun was produced by Randy Cohen
The election is almost here and the NPR politics podcast is counting down to election day with new episodes
Everyday
Now to November 9th
After November 9th
Who knows all bets are off
So you should subscribe or listen now on the NPR one app
I'm Robert Smith thanks for listening