So I admit it I am on Facebook a lot way more often than I should be it is kind of embarrassed
I feel you Alex me too
But I want to try a little experiment here
Can I have your
Password
No no way
I have a lot of Words With Friends games going
See your fears commentary
I don't want you to see what I'm doing
Okay so for the sake of the show
Habitus
What did experiments I will give you my password
Here here is my username and pass
Camera login for you
Hey
Ivan
It's exciting thrilling you are seeing the world
Through my digital eyes
Alex I'm in your account right now
Can I go to your private messages can I see who's friend requested you I see these two little buttons over here
Yeah go see that yeah
There's somebody who you have no friends in common with and I don't think that you should accept
Delete requests
Delete it
Okay
So you just locked into my account
I did with with my permission something I asked you to do
But according to a recent court decision we might have just committed a federal crime
Facebook has invested billions of dollars to make a place online
Just the way they wanted
All based on how each of us individually clicks and likes and friends and on Friends
Our Facebook account may feel like private property
We're not allowed to give away the keys it is Facebook's house
Not hours
And they say
But we just did
Is something like digital trespassing climbing onto their servers without permission
Which could land someone in jail hello and welcome
The planet money I'm Alex goldmark
When I Murphy shahani today on the show the story of why we may have just committed a crime
How Facebook protect
And what it means for the future of the internet
It's a story of a man who tried to open up the web
Who had a great idea that would have made it easier to use
Pretty much every site with a login and how he got
Frost
Support for today's episode of Planet Money and the following message come from Audible
Who has an unmatched selection of audiobooks from leading audiobook Publishers and business information providers
Including the road to ruin
The global Elite secret plan for the next financial crisis by James Rickard
Audible is offering Planet Money listeners are free 30-day trial membership and a free audiobook to get started
Go to audible.com Planet Money and start listening Anytime Anyplace
Our story starts in Silicon Valley in 2006 social networking is the hot new thing
Facebook is just two years old and it's growing fast there's also linked then there's Myspace or Friendster
But you're still a thing
And every single one of them have their own freaking username and password
This is when Steve acciani had his big idea
Steve is one of those Silicon Valley types who was really early to the internet game
He's friends with all of the people that are starting these social networks
And he comes up with what he thinks is an even bigger hot or newer idea
He thinks what if I can fit all of these Networks
Together
And make a supernet
And this is actually kind of what it hit me is that rather than create a social network
What am I creative site
That brings all your all your sites together
He was going to make one site to rule them all
He called it power Ventures
Answers homework
You put your usernames and passwords from your various social media accounts
All into his sight and from there you could do all your cat picture uploading and liking and hearting and poking from this place
It organizes the chaotic early social networking web into one place
And a lot of people liked it
He said 20 million people signed up he remembers checking on
How fast the company was growing over and over again in those early days
Remember how it felt
It's euphoric
You refresh the page
Every 10 seconds cuz it's you can't believe that you just had
Other
Thousand people just entering the last minute
It's kind of like pinching yourself to see it's real
Only Steve didn't have to pinch himself because he pretty much ended up getting punched in the face
My Facebook
People at Facebook saw that his company was growing fast and caught their attention and it worried them
Didn't like it because it steals their business
Under the terms of service yes we own our data
But Facebook puts ads next to it to make money so it's really important for them that you're sharing inside face
When you posed to be a power Ventures
Facebook loses money
It's even bigger
Then address
Kind of like an existential crisis for a site like Facebook
Because
Power Ventures makes it easy
For you to use it or just take all of your photos and your post and your messages
And move them from Facebook to somewhere else to the next hot new
Social network really easily
So in December of 2008
Just a few days before Christmas
Facebook send Steve an email
It was kind of an awkward email because
They were treating us like a user
That Facebook stencil I said that
Are violating Facebook's terms and conditions
You need to stop
Awkward because power Ventures wasn't the Facebook user they didn't sign Facebook's terms and conditions there were just how
Helping people manage their accounts
Facebook is protecting its
And it's trying whatever it can
Remember this is early days on the internet
The rules
They haven't really been written yet
Answer this fight set the groundwork
Put the paint on the field
Look for so many later case
So I spent about a month
Just talking to Facebook they would have five six layers on the phone every time
And they can't work it out
Facebook
Suicide
Charge one
Facebook says that logging into their site without their permission is hacking
Criminal act
Charge 2 for good measure
Spanish
Facebook also says that message was sent out on Facebook on behalf of Sears customer saying hey come use power Ventures
That was deceptive unwanted solicitation
Spam
If someone calls you a spammer is a connotation that you're from the underworld
It's like being an adulterer in puritan America
That's your Scarlet Letter
Yeah you're not respect you cannot be respected
Mattress not respected
It's really expensive to be a scammer
There's a fine for each message
15. Against the fine of
18 million dollars
And the first round of battle Facebook one
Steve doesn't have that kind of money
And
Because of the lawsuit
Pretty-much can't operate his
Company and so he shuts
Sit down
It gets so bad that Steve declare personal bankruptcy
But Facebook blocks it
He stays personally liable for that multi million dollar fine
He wants to appeal the case but he's pretty much broke by now when he goes to the big shot lawyer
To see if someone else will take up the appeal
They're all like no this is a case against Facebook and you got to have a lot of cash up front for us to sign on
For most people
This is where things would at
But Steve is not most
No Steve his dog and he's like one of those prisoners digging everyday with a cafeteria spoon
And he's got one last idea one last place
She thinks he might find
There's this website online called Elance where people would post they can do graphic
Designer build a website for cheap
And
Define
Amy summer
I have never practiced before I didn't do an internship in a law firm I didn't know the first thing about
Being a lawyer
She got in her law degree from night school a few years earlier
The only thing she had ever tried was mock trial
In law school
Amy was on Elance looking for quick money
Just doing business contracts or something simple
She's awesome posting
And it got curious
She had no idea that Steve wanted her to appear in front of a judge in federal court
I had to pay
Practice there
Did he reimburse you for that
No
No it did not
Facebook level lawyers usually charge around $1,000 an hour
Amy was only charging
$55
Just the right price
Steve like the price
And he liked her
I found her to be very
Humble
That is very naturally intelligent so it's Facebook for
Amy and Steve
I'm one side the best legal team money can buy
On the other side
I broke CEO who lost his company
Hellokaty Lance my to lawyer on Earth
First case
Amy remembers picking out what to wear to
The courts it was the same suit she wore for mock trial back in law school
Curly Sue
And she remembers in the courthouse
The first time she saw the Facebook lawyers looking like
Total Pros
And also very tall
And I'm a little person right and so my very first experience was
15 lb
It's like towering
Coming into the team of them
And I remember just thinking
Okay don't feel small don't feel small
And she can just tell they're not taking her seriously
Right from the first handshake with their lead lawyer
Very weak handshake
But he's shaking the you know woman's hand he felt condescending
He made this big show of being overly polite to her holding the
Store for her that little swinging gate door that separates the judge from the audience he's like not enough for you
So Amy walks in first
We walk up there and I
Think I picked the right side and I'm not sure
I had no idea where to go I was
Just like okay I'm just going to be no fake it till I make it
The court has already ruled that Steve and his company were guilty of the charges
Spamming a
Facebook lawyers winning ready to try and get the maximum penile
Divide 18 million.
Amy went to say hey
Lawyer
Facebook shouldn't get that automatic
We should get our chance to argue it out
Y'all have to go off at that point is intuition because
Experience
Don't know what I'm doing
Shouldn't be there
But actually she's low-balling hearse
She has more than
What Amy wants to go read the briefs
It struck her that the first judge didn't understand the basic facts
He didn't get his social networks work
Here with opportunity to explain it correctly
They can be professional be courteous
And it works
Judge tells her and the tall Facebook legal team
Any reside with
View Facebook doesn't automatically
The Way You Are
You get to keep arguing about it the case is still alive
The Weeknd tree guy was Furious
He stormed out of the Court not even holding the swinging door open for her
That's okay
Amy knows how to open her own door
And she's starting to feel like a real lawyer
Me up
It made me feel like
Like there's nothing I can't do
This means Amy gets her chance to try the case in a bigger
Or Auntie how to plant overturn that spam charged with
Define any basically points out
The team wasn't spamming he was just inviting users friends
To join power adventures at their
Stevenson basically what every other site does when your trying to grow
Facebook's entire company was built
Around
Users giving their password to Facebook saying go access my contacts on Yahoo and
Google
And
Go export all my contacts
And start communicating and send an invitation to all my friends and bring them into Facebook
The other charge the hacking charge
With Syria
It's because it fell under this law
The Computer Fraud and Abuse
A federal criminal law
That was about way more than what Steve had done in this one little kid
Now it was about what all of us are allowed to do on the internet
And because Amy got Steve that appeal
This case suddenly matters
A whole lot more people
The case was headed to the 9th circuit
Court's decision here would set precedent for a big chunk of the country is just one step below the Supreme Court
And it also happens to be broadcast on YouTube
My name is my name is Steven
I was at the time of a
December 2008 I was
Feisty
CEO of power Ventures
Almost exactly 7 years after that first letter
Open Facebook
Beef still trying to dig out of prison without plaster
Caterpillar Ventures
But
Things started off well one of the judges liked the idea of Steve's website and even tried to give him a compliment
Too nervous to hear the
The phrase
Were you the one who invented this mediasite power.
One of those
I was a founder
I was the founder of power.com
And that's crack
Divas fumbling for the right words he's got just a few minutes to lay out the arguments that have been on repeat his brain for the law
Several years
And then Amy gets a few minutes to make her case
Facebook layers they do their thing
Aleve
Anyway
4 months
Monday and you get an email
While she's in bed
Left out of
Covers
Probably yeah I know I definitely did a dance on the bed
Steve and Amy
The down-and-out CEO in the Newbie lawyer
They had killed it they got a win
Bigger than they ever imagined they
Kind of killed it
The judges
Throughout the spamming charge and with it the multimillion-dollar fine was gone
Amy's client Steve was off the hook
But they had really different reactions
The case
Because the hacking charge
At one stock
When Steve called out a me to talk about the ruling and it was ready to celebrate their win
But Steve was like
Whatever
And I can focus on the real issues
Wait what
We be happy about this for you know can we can we just reflect on this last
4 years
Doing the impossible
Yes he just won his big fight against Facebook and he was free of the millions of dollars in
But his case had just set back the internet
And this ruling
Was going to say
Huge legal precedent that could affect
Every person online
The judge said yeah it is a violation of Outlaws the Computer Fraud and Abuse Act
If you share your username and password like we did at the top of the show
And Facebook tells you not
The ruling caught the attention of some heavy
Orin Kerr is a law professor at George Washing
Peking university
He defends her
And he remembers when you heard the news about the
The decision comes down and I go oh wow
That
That is
Big
That's really troubling in terms of what it means
Four people using the internet has defended some of the most famous hackers in past cases
And now
He is joining Amy's legal team
Annies representing Steve pro bono
So if you thought any was making chump change
Orange doing it for even less
Free
He says that the 9th circuit ruling put way too much power in the hands of internet companies and the government
They're using a really heavy hammer
This is a
Federal Criminal Law
And they're saying
Using the account in a way Facebook doesn't like
That's not just a bad thing that's not you something Facebook disapproves up
That's a crime
I you should be able to be arrested for that and prosecuted and put in jail for a year
Or longer
By the way we check with other lawyers and they agree on that reading
Facebook didn't want to speak on tape
The story but a spokesperson did tell us
But letting anyone else login for you
Is dangerous you shouldn't do it
And if your data is safe inside Facebook but it could be at risk inside of another company
Like power venture
Spokesperson also said
Facebook gave Steve many chances to settle the case in a way that wouldn't have been paint
The thing about this case right it's like Facebook
Wants
This other startup
The back off
What can we use to get them to back off
And they cried this log
They got a huge wet out of it
And now they open up this Pandora's Box
Swear whoops
Sharing passwords could be a criminal act
And I don't get the sense in talking to Facebook and reading the briefs at Facebook
Why did you do that but they use what they had to do and this is Messi out
Amy and Steve just learned this morning
But the 9th Circuit Court it will not be here there
To the next stop
To take it to the Supreme Court
And he's already filed the paperwork so she can appear there
For the same low rate
$55 an hour
Just like we always do we have posted a link to this episode right there on Facebook itself so if you want to give us your feedback and
Talk about this episode using your own login
That's pretty good place to do it where on Twitter at Planet Money I'm at Alex goldmark
Aarti's 411
Air Show today was produced by Raina
And if you like this podcast and you want to keep it going the best way to show your support
Is to go and donate to your local public radio station
And tell them that Planet Money sent you
Find out what your station is at
Stations. NPR.
Don't forget
Planet Money sex
And there's a new app you've got to get on your smartphone if you don't already have it it's called
NPR one
You'll get fresh air eagleson bullseye
Alt Latino and all song inside analysis from code switch politics
Latino USA NPR one
You can get it npr.org
Flash podcast
Hi markisha honey
And I'm Alex goldmark thanks for the
I am changing my password back right now
Before you doubt me to do well it's the race would see if you can do it
Hold on hold on hold on
Traded his going to
Linquest
I'm like
Let me go into your photos
Did you go to Burning Man
This has to stop
Wow
Really
I did I would never
Excited dog out other devices
I'm going to hurt your own picture of your burning man. I just heard of your Burning Man picture before you lock me out