Years ago Jonathan Goldstein had managed to save up enough money to do what he's always dreamed
Buy a smoker
You wanted it to be a company that actually made something
I'm physically
Anyone of there to be some Secret in house
I was made some magic
He found something that seemed perfect
A small factory located on a grassy Hill in rural Pennsylvania
You made these
Handbells
Yep the kind you hear around the holiday season
Jonathan went to visit the factory to talk to the people there
The bells were beautiful
Musical perfection
But he says it turns out there was a handbell competitor
Just down the road
I said so tell me about this other company
I kind of looked around at each other and
Sarah said well you know
Historically we didn't get along too well
That it turns out was an understatement
The two Bell makers had basically been at War
The more Jonathan looked into it the weirder it all was
Handbells after all about playing nicely with others
Maybe you've seen a handbell choir in church around Christmas time or
Kern Schools
Maybe you played in one
Basically you've got dozens or more people trying to play a single piece of music
For not to sound like a total mess
Everyone has to ring the right Bell at precisely the right time
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm David kestenbaum today we have a special holiday show for you about the Epic decade
Is long feud between the two companies that make just about every hand bell in the world
How they eventually made peace
Support for this podcast and the following message come from rocket mortgage by Quicken Loans
Rocket mortgage brings home financing into the 21st century with a completely online process that's fast easy and convenient
Ditch the paperwork and use your phone or tablet to safely share your bank statements and pay stubs
In a few minutes get a custom mortgage Solution on your terms
Check out rocket mortgage today at quickenloans.com money
Equal Housing lender licensed in all 50 states
Nmls consumer access. Org number 3030
When you got two companies down the road from each other making the same thing
You can almost guess the history
Originally there was just one company
Something happen
Maybe someone got angry
Somebody left
They started the second visit
A competitor
In this case that someone was a man named Jake Malta
In the 1960s he worked at what was the only Bill shoppingtown
Place called Schumer
And Jake was Schumer's chief engineer
Is library was full of books on music and nothing was not red
Everything
And that you could see in his office had been read
Andre red
This is Jake's daughter Joanne Malta
Her dad she said was largely self educated
The kind of guy that when he got into something he got really into it
And he became obsessed with bells
He designed Schumer's first handbells
But then there was a change in management Jake Malta didn't get along with a new bosses
So we laugh
He could not stop thinking about Bell
If I had a way to make an even better handbell
A Love Supreme perfection
They haven't quite achieved Schumer
I got to explain a little bit about
About when you ring it it vibrates and produces this one Central note
But you also got these other notes in there
Overtones
Jake Malta wanted to try to get rid of as many overtones as he could
She wanted to make a bell with a very pure sound
That was the challenge of Holy Grail and Bell
So he set up shop in the family living room
Add folding table to Adam stretch out with all of his drafting supplies on there and then.
Piano behind them travel to Europe studied old books about the physics of bells
Did you lock the diagram
Cuz he knew that he could make it better
And
You know we still believe that he cheats at
Jake malta's new Bell have a slightly different shape
And this part is kiso remember
Can you remove the little brass knob at the top of the Bell where it attaches to the handle
Something called the Tang
The result he felt was a battle that produced an uncommonly pureclean song
Malta took his design and he started a new hand
Not far from his former employee
And he gave it a name like his own
Not Malta but mama
Tonight had to Bellco
The old
One show more
Selling Bells with
And Mama
Jake's Lobster
Telling Bells with the tank cut off
And before we get to the decades-long war
I'm just going to play you what they were fighting on
This is a Schumer
The one with it
And this is a mall Mark Bell Jake's new bell
With the tank cut off
I have driven myself crazy trying to compare these two Bells
Sometimes I hear a difference
But frankly I think it might just be that I was holding a microphone
Different spot
Can I play them again shoe Mark Bell with tang
Walmart Bella Notte
Some experts say they can tell the difference. They're divided over which one sounds better
The Bell Wars arguably began in 1976 here is one of the first shots fired in
It's an ad by Schumer
Trying to make the case that their original Bells with the Tang
We're better
Read
All Schumer Bells have a tank
This is the Rays Crown at the top of the Bay
Now that gives the total brilliance
The mall Mart
Hereafter referred to as brand m
How's the tangless Bell
Sing it is a New Concept in handbell design tuning and performance
In reality they're weakening the tonal quality
I'm doing it even more when drilling a hole for the handle place
This ad infuriated mr. note on his bed
The at Walmart
In fact the reason the text of this as still exist
It's because it was recorded in legal documents
Jake sued his former employer
Court cases are chance for both sides to have their say
And I have someone impartial way the f
So you can just move on
And in this case the two Bell makers did settle
And they came up with a solution
That seems like it would put all this behind them
Both sides agreed not to compare their bills to the other spells
Which seems like a fine idea
Unless of course you are in the sales department
It's your job after
To go out and talk up
Your bell
Kermit junkert wasn't Schaumburg sale.
He said these were kind of terrifying time
Because remember
Neither side was supposed to compare its belt
The others
Which means he couldn't say for instance
Are handle is solid vs. Hollow
The lawyers came up with a workaround
Special kind of awkward phrases the salespeople were cleared to use
Free sample our handle is not Hollow
Well by saying it's not
Something you would refer or infer that someone else's handle is Hollow
Indirectly of course I mean literally there were legal team
That would write here's what you can say oh here's what you can't say
And that was that would come about from
Whoever won the latest lawsuit
How long did that go on
Forever
They're even apparently spies
Kermit says sales people would be giving their pitch and they see someone in the audience watching them like a hawk
Scribbling down notes about
What they said
And then
A letter wood
From the other side lawyer
Here we actually have one this is from Walmart
The new bellmaker
Complaining about a Schaumburg sales pitch
It has been brought to our attention that you have been making false and disparaging statements about Mall mark handbells
Letter goes on to list those disparaging statements apparel
Hey by the show Mork salesperson
Quotes their handles break frequently
You must jump up and down on ours to break them
There's another one
There's a problem with polishing Mark Bells
You must only polish up and down
ARS can be polished in any direction
I asked Joanne Malta about this
Did they really have spies in the audience taking notes
I had no idea
I certainly let you know what the different conventions and all I would imagine
Are wraps attending
If they heard something
That was a negative about Mall Mark that it would come back and I'm sure that's happened in
Reverse 2
It's funny to think about all this fighting happening in front of the customers
Two of coursework
Musicians in church choir directors
Middle School
That's what the customers
And the sales people weren't trying to just sell single Bell
They're trying to convince an entire choir
To exclusively ringing their Bells only
Go all time
No go No Tag
In one mile marker Shamrock succeeded in selling a whole set to a big-name bell choir
They brag about
The music you're hearing right now this is the arsis handbell ensemble
All malmark Bells
Not a single Schumer
For years the Tang question hung over the battlefield
Did Jake malta's Innovation really make for a better bail
Where did the bell sound better with it
Here's another shumer CAD for my court
This one seems designed to drive Jake Moulton totally mad
Quote the Tang is the Rays Crown at the top of each
And not all handbells have it
But Schumer candles do
The Tank's weight and mass help reduce Fuller tone greater
Note those last words there
Greater amplitude
Basically louder
Here was a scientific claim that could actually be test
So now this conflict would consume management lawyers and salespeople
Spread to the engineering department
Sound Engineers that show Murray
How to try to back up this claim that the advertising the farm
Probably dreamed
And remember these are sound Engineers who got into the business because
They love music
I want to be creating the most beautiful instruments
And now they've been dragged into an ugly lawsuit
I had to build all this testing app
Including a robotic ringer that hits the bell with exactly the same Force
Gregory Schwartz was one of the engineers who worked on
Though
Even remembering the whole episode make some kind of weary
He says
The Tang did make a bell louder
But
Not much
Early looking at
Percent or two maybe something like that is a couple percent louder
Maybe
Is the average Joe going to know the difference
I
Don't think so
It wasn't like it sounded but it was just slightly louder
Right
That's basically
But that was a premise
NFL's with tangs produce more sound
Another side said bologna that's not true
How he said yes it is true
Like all wars this one consumed an enormous amount of research
In researching the story I could not keep track of all the lawsuits
We're just two men
McGregor told me about this one that is worth mentioning
It was over a patent on The Clapper machina
I think it actually hit the bell and makes it ring
The case got appealed and appealed
Until it was at the doorstep of the highest court in the land
US Supreme Court
The judges I just kind of threw the whole thing out and sitting on that we're not going to waste our time with that but
They
It went back and forth for years it was just horrendous
The US Supreme Court
They tried it
I tried it
I think normally when you read about lawsuits between companies
You think they're the result of some business calculus
Some strategic decision
And maybe that was true at the beginning
But pretty soon emotions
Once you get in a fight like this once you spend a lot of money on lawyers
It's hard to give up
The long Wars can be the hardest to end
Especially things good person
I can see being she'll meric the original hand outcome
Thinking who does Jake Malta think he is
Cutting off the
That's so silly
Is setting up his own Belk
And it's easy to imagine how maddening things must have seemed on the Walmart
Joe and Martha told me it's totally understandable her dad Jake
Would try to take the Bell fight literally to the Supreme Court
He felt really wounded in wrong
Things got ugly
You stole this from me know you stole it from me
Spencer tabaxi to think about it
Does because my dad was a very honest man absolutely but he was he was going to get a seminary
It was not the kind of person to steal anything so
Was the Han
Bell
Ringing world out there aware
Of all this
Oh yeah
This is perhaps the most amazing
Part about the story
I kind of imagined that
The bellringer
All those choir directors in teachers
Will be kind of laughing at all
Even be oblivious
But it was the opposite
Some of them got totally swept up
They took sides
Way more strongly than you might imagine
People at both mama can show Mark remember various in
Here's one story from the mall marks
Told by Tim Schubach
Who had gone to an industry meeting I had unbeknownst to me mistakenly
Set hello to Schumer customer
From our booth
The customer continue to walk by
An over-the-shoulder not even stopping to acknowledge me
Set Worsham rack ringer
And a very kind of
Condescending way in the end after many many years of the courts throwing up their hands
Monarch had a kind of victory
Jake Malta was awarded $2000000
That was a lot less after the legal fees
His daughter says he put a lot of the money into a handbell education fun
There Wars that end because one side surrenders
Another Wars where no one gives it
There isn't even a truce
Do sides just stop fight
A day passes than a year
In another year
Jake Malta the proud perfectionist engineer head of Mark
Wesley pastor
And so did the people calling the shots at Schumer
The younger Generations
Tim you just heard came to run Walmart
Am I summer he got word that someone knew had bought schommer
Someone who seems like a very odd fit
Fidel world
When I first heard I'm like what
What's going on here
What's the crazy story ever heard
Shomer Kevin bought by Jonathan Goldstein
The guy you hurt at the top
Former lawyer
Who knew nothing about him
I do less than nothing
I can't even read music
Author Jonathan is Jewish
There are a lot of handbells in synagogues
Very famously for my employees right after I bought the company
I brought one of my rabbis up here
Thinking you know maybe I've missed something
And I showed him the bells and I said how about it and he looked around the room
It is very long beard
And he said it took a minute or two and said
Nope nope never not going to happen no
Statue system
It was quite a moment
Shortly after Jonathan bought the company
He and Tim
The new heads of both companies
Found themselves at the same meeting in Cincinnati
He came up and is very Jonathan way and and was he's not bashful at all you know he's
Very gregarious and came up and I just bought Schumer
Hey what's up man how are you how are you how's it how's it going
So I said you know
Hi
Wow
My understanding is that these two companies went out of hammer and tongs for a lot of years and
I'm just not ready to do that it said it seems to me that
You know you're not my enemy and I'm not your enemy the enemy is the 300 million people out there who don't ring handbells
Let's go get those people
Getting ready
And this meeting between that had the two companies did not go unnoticed
If there were a weekly handbell Gazette
This would be front-page news
Historic peace Accord
We were observed just sort of sitting off in a corner talking
And the the whole place was a titter at the fact that we were even talking to each other it was simply not.
For like 20 years
Jonathan and Tim seem to actually like each
And in that meeting they talked about working together where they can
It was it was so welcomed it was just like
This great weight
Coming off of our
Chess
This is Kermit again who did Salesforce turmeric
As is often the case after a long War
The soldiers were eager for peace
Yeah we can about it as being the Hatfields and McCoys but
Hit it literally felt that way
You know it's like whoever had the bigger guns and take no hostages and
And just obliterate the other side Oliver handbells
Haulover handles amazing isn't it
Who is Bob
That I not live through it I would have thought of it
If you were to write a book about this
I think most people who say no that didn't happen
It did happen
And it was over
When I talked to Kermit he just got in a Christmas card from Walmart
The first he wrote to me in an email
Cool
And maybe this is occurred to you
It's occurred to me and it's occurred to Jonas
Does the world really need to handle companies
You got two businesses that basically make identical products
Maybe now that the bitterness is gone
There should be a wedding a merger
Maybe malmark and Shamrock should become
M&S belt
I'm not sure that's going to ever
Cuz having two companies
Kind of benefit everyone
People at Walmart and Schumer told me
Okay the Bell wars were bad
But I kind of like knowing they had a competitor down this
And if you're someone who Rings Bells
It is so much more fun to be able to pick size
Which bell sounds better
One with the Tang
Or the one without
This is the Sonos handbell Ensemble one of the few choirs that mixes chilmark and Mal Mark Bells
We would love to hear
Hear what you think of Today Show you can send this email Planet Money at npr.org
I'm sure today was produced by Jess Jiang thanks Jess
I did a casting down thanks for listening