Support for NPR and the following message come from w w Norton and Company
Publishers of people power and profits Progressive capitalism or an age of discontent
By Nobel prize-winning economist
Joseph E stiglitz
We pull it in McPherson Kansas late at night
It is a small town just off the highway
But it has the skyline
It looks like
Manhattan I swear
Towers
Shooting into the sky all lit up
You see the lights way before you see it and start wondering
WhatsApp
Vince Pinkston lives in McPherson and he works in those bright hour
This is an oil refinery
It's run by CHS
I mean everybody that's here they know what it is
Is it home it is a very strange home as we can see the next morning when we get it to her
Maybe you've driven past these things before but I never been inside it is amazing
Thousand
Pipes tanks
Little cat walks up on the Smoke Stacks
Noises that single flame burning from the highest stack
Yes the pilot light
This is where the Planet Money oil is going to be turned into gasoline
Evap sensor sounds crazy go back a couple of episodes we bought a hundred barrels of crude oil from a Kansas preacher
We got a pump
And tested and slurped into a pipeline and headed here
And this Refinery is where the magic is about to happen
Just so you can picture it we are wearing hard hats and blue lab coat
And we are the only humans walking around between the pipes
I have always wanted to ask this
What if by refinery
Do you really need so many pipes
I mean there are thousands and thousands and thousands of twisting and turning pipes and it seems except
3 fishing yet
All this time we've been talking about crude oil like it's one thing just this thick black liquid that
Pull out of the ground in
Can touch and smell
But a Refinery does not look at crude that
Them crude oil is a mixture of
All these different
Different kinds of molecule
These long and short hydrocarbon
Blocks all jumbled
It's like how I used to pick up my kids toys at the end of every single day and sort all the Legos in two different Bass
But basically Refinery does
It's sort like with like
Gasoline with gasoline diesel
With diesel
Sorting and separating over and
Which sounds easy until you think that all those different kinds of fuels are of course
Inside
Royal
That's why refineries
Are so cute
Extraction overacre
Miles and miles of pipes
Because at each step
Tank they get a little more usable
Fuel out of our oil and after
Gasoline
Diesel
Propane butane
The bits left goes to something called
CHS just got a new Coker
And the entire Refinery was buzzing about
Everyone says I look
This is our new Coker
Boheme online in February
Okay this thing that is tall and has also took like little balconies on it
Turn off the new thing
Yes
There is no way
To describe this we've been in this huge debate about how
Picture this
Powers and spiral
The best thing we came up with was a sort of
Post-industrial water park
And the Coker is made up of
These two enormous
Black Smoke Stack look
Thanks
Tower over everything
And where you separate all the
Different sizes of Molly
What's the like with like
Is essentially by cooking crude
In tray
In this koeckeritz like a very tall Ava
They called the column
Realize there's more heat at the bottom of the column then at the top
So how hot in the bottom and how hot is the top
And I'm excited about 840 on the bottom to call him
40 degrees Fahrenheit 60 on top
So you can cook a steak basically the bottom and the top is more like a cake temperature
Good sear on a good steak on the bottom yet
So I should cooking the crude oil be black
Car light
Gook stays at the bottom of the column the gases
Move up to the top
Are all the different kinds of petroleum products
Sort themselves out in between
Can you list off the different things that are oil will become here
Natural Gas Propane butane
Gasoline diesel
Are some of the sulfur that removed in other processes goes into fertilizer
Will get turned into butane propane
Gasoline and fertilizer so if we
Go eat a sandwich in town we could be eating our oil
Really
That's surprising
Defected a pretty good chance of that because CHS who runs this Refinery it is owned by a
Cooperative of farmers
So they are really interested in the diesel and
The fertilizer
But after they take that out I mean nothing else
He's wasted effect
The reason this Refinery is so huge
Is it they're trying to squeeze
Every last molecule of hydrocarbon out of our crude oil
Oil is in everything
It is in plastic
Of course but it is also in the toothpaste I brush my teeth with when I got up it's in the shampoo I used it's in my phone
It's my radio recorder
It's my sneakers and my shirt
It is even in the aspirin I took after drinking
A little too much at Montana Mike's
Hello and welcome to Planet Money and Stacey Vanek Smith
And I'm Robert Smith today in the show
How oil got into everything
And why we're having a pretty hard time getting the oil out
Of everything
Just Jack and Noah King have it story
After the break
We'd like to say a quick thank you and share a message from our planet money sponsor discover
You check things all the time like your email or social media
Discover ask
What about checking something as important as your credit
Well discover makes it quick and easy
With the Discover credit scorecard
Discover is the only major credit card to offer FICO credit score
To everyone for free even if you're not a customer
And once you know your FICO credit score
You should check to see if your current credit card
What is the best fit for you
Learn more at discover.com credit score card
Limitations apply
The story of how oil got into everything
Starts with one man
A chemist named Leo Baker
And as far as we can tell
He thought about chemistry
All the time
Yeah we heard this one story from someone in Leo's
Extended family like
He's very extended family
Call Kauffman is a
Great grandson-in-law or a great step grandson
I'll take it
Carl says
Leo had this unusual way of dealing with hot summer
He would simply
Walking Dead
The pool with his clothes on
Get himself nice
She soakin wet walk out cool off and
Go on about his business
Search without ever
Putting on a swimsuit or anything else is he said
Evaporation
The cooling process
Thinking like a chemist
Drinking like a camel
Exactly
The clothes that Leo wore into the pool would have been made of some natural fiber like
Because this is how things work back then
His toothbrush handle would have been made of sterling silver
And his comb was probably tortoiseshell
And I If he if he smoked his cigarette holder would have been
This world is all natural
And it was really expensive
Leo had the comb in the suit and all these things
Because he was a rich guy
Not everyone could afford these things
Susan Frankl a science writer says
It wasn't just
Expensive
Getting all her stuff from nature
What's hard
Now this is around the time that scientists are tinkering with electricity
Which of course will make life much easier
But at the moment it's presenting a huge challenge
Which has electricity starts a lot of fires
You've got plugs and sockets and wires and they need coding
Because Sparks are flying
And right now you know what they're using is coding
Something again all natural
Bucks
Bear using bugs
The wonderful and beautiful Lac Beetle that she
Black beetle
Get it not the guy last
Beatles the shellac Beetle shellac
The people weren't lifting up the skirts of millions of hugs and pulling out the lady ones
The shellac bug
Excreta kind of resin on tree branches
And people collect that resin and make that into shellac
But still it was a
It took 6 months
And 15,000 Beatles
To get a pound of this Reza
Leah was looking at tallac
And he saw a problem
Kind of shellac all these new electrical plugs in
Sockets and whatever
Just wouldn't work on such a big scale
And we know he was thinking about the shellac conundrum because Leah was one of those people who wrote down
Everything in his big lab notebooks
And I am amazed little diary
His step great-grandson Carl says he'd write down everything in those dire
What he even that day what he thought of the wine he had a dinner what time he went to bed
Who he was mad at
Sewing show came to visit me and he had a good idea but he's such a
Sabor
So he talked smack kids talk smack about people
He was very candid about it she talk smack about a lot of other chemists
And, smack talk is like
Oh so and so has a good idea but he
She's not controlling the conditions of his experiment
At the time there were lots of other camera
Looking for a solution
Some alternative
Shellac bug
And there was this one very abundant
Oil
It was mostly being used
Ways to make kerosene
For lighting
But after you made the kerosene
There was all this Gunk left over
With all these chemicals
It seems like
It should be useful somehow
But Susan Frankel says no one knew how to use it
John D Rockefeller looked out over his oil refinery one day and he saw these like
Blue flames coming off the
The top of the
Smoke stacks and it's like what's that somebody said well that's definitely answer you know we don't use it sweet
Just Burn It Off
It's like I don't want to waste anything you know find something to do with that
We don't know if that story is true
Not the way you like it
It works for us
The chemist for playing around with this oil-based
And the waste from coal
And hoping to invent a better insulator at the Lac bug
Process chemist would try different combinations of stuff
But the results were always a mess
The thing would boil over and there would be
Baby stuff splattering all over the place and you'd end up with
The spongy Mass
A useless gun
Useless gun
Uselessjunk
It would give off an odor so powerful that three weeks later you still couldn't go in the room with it will obviously
You can't use it for anything if it stinks so badly you can't live with it
You know you can kind of Imagine Leo writing in his
Is Diary like
These other chemist just don't know what they're doing
I'm going to do them one better
Let me try this
That's what he does he
He starts doing his own experiments in his personal lab
And it was dangerous at first
NFL
The reaction going on with
Is hot enough
There was a good chance that as you poured this in
The fumes of this alcohol like me
Material
Would burst into flame immediately
Hope you have a room full of propane gas and somebody throws a matching
Boom
The gas is
Explosion
There were
Yeah there were flash fire
Just put it that way and make it sound so delicate butterflies fire sounds
It was terrifying
Bill looked around his expensive laboratory and thought
No
So he said okay will do that in the garage so I can
Can afford to burn down my garage
I got kind of burnt out by Laboratory
For five years Leo tank
First videos
What's the big problem
The flash fire
He gets those under control
But the stuff is getting out of here
Experiments
Still a mess
He just keeps making goo
He realizes
He needs a special oven
That can give him first
Control of temperature and the pressure
But nothing like that exists
This might have stopped other chemist
But it doesn't stop the
Out in his garage
He bailed
His special
It's a couple of feet high and it's shaped like an egg in that was there pressure vessel
And you could control
Both the temperature and the
Pounds of pressure very precise
We have a picture of it here
And it does
Just look like a giant egg
Is made of iron
Yeah it's it's all soldered together and it's got a
Pipe running in one side
And then it's got this wheel up top that I guess you
Crank to open it
It just kind of looks
Steampunk
Musically memes his new machine after himself
Of course he calls it
The big lizer
And one day in 1907 he prepares his latest mixer for the bay kleiser
And this is for the chemistry Geeks
To take something called spino but you can get
From oil or coal tar and adds an alcohol
He uses formaldehyde
Combined sum in a test tube and put it in the bay kleiser
He sets his oven to
Exactly the right
And when the time is right he opens it up
And this time what he finds is not
Goo
He finds this hard amber colored material
And it is molded in the shape of a test
He just made plastic in a lab for the first time
And he calls it
Bakelite
I'm nursing a trend here he's not
Recreation
We haven't diary entry for this day
He didn't write Eureka in all caps on the page
But here's what he wrote
I consider this day is very successful work which has put me on the knot of
Several new and interesting products
Which may have a wide application as
Plastics
And varnish
And they complained about some chemist dinner that he's got to go to
Leoda's note start shopping around his new material
He talks to people making those newfangled electrical thing
Things and tell them
Stop messing with all those bugs
You can use this new thing I've made
From fossil
Eagle Eye
It doesn't melt
Burnt you can use it for those light bulb bases
Electrical sockets or light switches
And he talks to the Ford Company
The Model T had just come out and this was
Perfect timing
They needed something heat resist
Assistant for the guts of the car in the engine for things like spark plugs and distributor cap
Bakelite with it
And this is the moment when a boil starts
Peeping into everything we know
Because companies love this cheap new material
Soon everything we know is being made from plastic
And at the time
It was the really hot stuff
There was no other plastic
Compete with it there's nothing else
We had anything like the properties of Bakelite
That was it
So bakeland had in effect
He wasn't just part of the plastic manager he was Supply
In 1924 Leo made the cover of Time Magazine
Susan Frankel the science writer actually dug up a copy of the article
It's a breathless review of this thing made from oil
The material Bakelite
From the time that a man brushes his teeth in the morning with a Bakelite handled brush
Until the moment when he removes his last cigarette from a Bakelite holder
Extinguishes it in a baked like
Ashtray
And falls back Upon A Bakelite bed
All that he
Touches
Cease
Uses
Will be made of this material of a thousand years
Time Magazine wasn't overstating it
One-wheel figured out how to make plastic out of fossil fuel waste
He took us from a world where toothbrushes are made of sterling silver
Like how much would that cost
Two world where they're made of plastic
And you can get one for a couple bucks
This is
Huge
Everyone can get one of everything
Process
This was important to Leo
He was proud to be part of that he thought that was important he thought the
It is just to make products
The only
The crown jewels
Could afford to buy you know
Fun
But he would not have
Been interested in Bakelite on the Seesaw mass-market sport
And very widespread applications that would
In effect
We're down to the value of the middle class not just the elite
Bill Beekman Farm to company
And the company started calling Bakelite
The 4th
Kingdom
As an animal vegetable mineral and now
Bakelite
A whole new category of
Stuff
Leo had cracked this big chemical mystery using waste from fossil fuels and other chemists cop.
It's like
We had this molecule here and we get Ziploc bags we had this molecule and we get styrofoam
You had a different molecule
You get your kids Legos
And today
It's infinite
The shoes that I'm wearing have definitely got petroleum materials not just the plastic but the pigments in
In the coding this is John Warner
He's a chemist the telephone that I'm holding
Certainly have petroleum materials
I have a little plastic sticky thing on my phone
That my three-year-old daughter gave me I don't even really know what it is
Left made of petroleum
I've got a little statue of
Bach
On my desk and that's made out of
Petroleum
So what do we make
Of all of this
So basically today if you're going to have anything
It's going to be partly made of oil or fossils
That's Leo's Legacy
And Karl wishes
That Leo could be
Celebrate it
That he could be remembered like Thomas Edison like a great inventor
Any kind of frustrated he is it
But
Some of Leo's other
Extended family his great-grandkids
They have more complicated feelings about plastic
Because oil is so cheap and plentiful plastic is also cheap and plentiful and everywhere
Including the ocean and piling up in landfills we had this conversation with Leo's great-granddaughter Roberta roller
And she says
She's proud of Leo baekeland and plastic
He created
But she also tries to avoid using it
I try not to buy
Stopping plastic I don't buy my vegetables wrapped in plastic
You know things like that
No it's unavoidable sometimes
I order something from Amazon it all comes wrapped in plastic
And Leos great-grandson Hugh told us he goes around picking plastic bags up off the side of the road
People feel uneasy about pasta
What chemists are doing now is basically
Trying to undo what Leo baekeland discovered in
His lap I feel kind of a cosmic connection to Leo baekeland
The Blob Discovery was made
On my birthday
No I kind of make that connection
Killmeyer is a chemist at the University of Minnesota
And Mark has
Two big problems with the way we make plastic
He says for one thing
Plastic can hang around forever it's not biodegradable
And second
Oil is limited
But Mark story is a really good illustration of how hard it is to make
A new kind of plastic
One that is not made from oil
He's trying to make one made of bets
You bring an ear of corn to a knife fight
Yeah
Astride corn
Also coconut orange peels caraway seeds
And you know what worked
Peppermint
Menthol
We came up with them using menthol
Hot the same menthol
That's in cigarettes and candy
I think in my gum
Exactly like peppermint gum
The plastic made out of peppermint was
Durable like regular plastic
And it was biodegradable
We broke down in water
Marx thought you could probably use this to make a lot of stuff
Sneakers that hold up
Just like regular running shoes
But when you're ready to throw him out
Bury them in your backyard
Compostable sneakers and Mark
Published his research and got the word out
To the big pots
Look at what we can do
It was a beautiful success
Nobody was
It just was not
Inexpensive enough
To to make a product that would compete with a petroleum-based counterpart
You don't even get to make your peppermint and corn shoes and then have
People say I'm not going to pay $97 for those when I can get them for
You just didn't even have anyone ask
Try
That's right and I mean it's not really 97 versus 57
It kind of fits the shoes cost 57 these would cost 500
Peppermint is a lot more expensive than the oil-based ingredient
Polyethylene
Peppermint oil is 20 bucks
What's a kilogram Mark told us
Polyethylene is $2
Mark went back to the lab and tried a totally new strategy
Instead of trying to find the molecules he needed
Nature
He got a biochemist
Make them
A genetically modified
E-coli bacteria
Which I normally think of something that would make me sick
But in this case he use the coli
Turn sugar into a
Key ingredient for plastic
And he remembers a colleague bursting through his office door
Showing him this
Plastic made from a coli bacteria
I was thrilled
I was absolutely thrilled
What did it feel like
When you held at
Stretchy material that bounces back so much like a rubber band
When I had this material in my hand I do from my experience
The years working on these
Have projects that
We really had something
Mark says this plastic made from bacteria is just as
Cheap as the stuff made from oil
But it's new plastic isn't in stores yet
Cubes in a couple years you bites
Car tires or a box of Band-Aids
And you might be buying
E-coli
Still marks plastic only works
For certain things
Only about a fifth
Of the plastic
Fix Wii U
And it took him 20 years to get this far
This is hard to do without oil
So just
Marc hillmyer actually sent you some of his
Is e-coli
Has taken the mail right
He did and he also said he's sending
Two pairs of
Gloves
So I'm actually a little bit nervous.
For I don't know
Yeah
Moment of Truth year
Oh my god there are glass
Oh this is it okay put your clothes on it's in a little ziplock baggie
The little square it's like
I don't know an inch and 1/2 by 2 in
And it's
It's hard plastic action
It's like the kind of plastic
I think about
I don't know maybe Tupperware
Something like that
Except stretchable Tupperware
End
And it's clear and it's clear
See through it
It doesn't look
It doesn't look like cutting edge.
No I do really want it
I dare you to lick it
I dare you to lick the occult LaPlace
Okay we will do it
You licked it you licked it
Oh my God
We're wearing gloves can I didn't really curious
Okay let's go back
Daisy Robert you guys have the last word
It's Robert and Stacy again
Helen Kansas
Another oils been refined it has
One final leg of
Into Augusta
Yes actual people will be using our oil we hope
Vince Pinkston showed us the very noisy pipeline that takes are refined fuel from the refinery out
And where is this pipeline going
Council Bluffs
Where is that
Iowa
We're going to Iowa
Looks like we're going to Iowa
Play nobody's oil
Which is now Planet money's gasoline is headed to Iowa
Ends were going with it
It's like a graduation
It is like a graduation Let It Go with the oil but the oil is do something bigger and better
The other side and now it was graduated into a usable product
Usable product like you're in the petroleum business pickups
I am in the petroleum
And so are you
We have a few people that we would like to thank including the whole team at CHS
Especially Lonnie Jordan Jim Lavigne and Melissa
Also thank you Jim Crocker rigoberto advincula and Robert
This episode was produced by Sally Helm and Elisabeth Kubler-Ross
Where is love to hear what you think of the show email is Planet Money at npr.org we also have a lot of
Pictures from our oil trip
You can check those out on Facebook and
Twitter
And if you're looking for another podcast to listen to check out pop culture happy hour
Every week they have really interesting discussions about the latest movies and
TV shows and books
Including interviews with people like Shonda Rhimes and Trevor Noah
You can check them out on the NPR one app or npr.org
Podcast
And stay tuned for our next episode where Planet Money or oil
Play gasoline
Actually makes it into someone's gas
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith Robert Smith thanks for listening
Support for this podcast and the following message come from K buxbaum
In support of the David Gilkey and zabihullah tamanna memorial fund established
To strengthen NPR's commitment to training and protecting journalists in high risk environments