Some of us were really hoping
Let this presidential
This time we would hear a serious
Discussion
About economics
We've got two weeks ago
Before either Hillary Clinton or Donald Trump elected president
And it's
Just not
Going to happen
They are not going to talk seriously about two different visions
For the economy
I'm going to be fair to these
Two candidates
You do see this drink every president
4 years ago when President Obama was running for re-election against Mitt Romney
We decided to come up with the perfect
Planet Money Canada
Candidate
The Economist would love because
And it would talk about the economic issues
Here is that show from 4 years ago as relevant
Today as it was then
You're going to hear me
And Alex
Do they have a show we are talking about
Presidential
Economic
Platform
There's a mystery about the
To us here at Planet Money
Yeah he's with strange
We talked to Economist academics policymakers
All the time
Enter there is a lot of disagreement
Among them about what to do about the economy and vac we highlight that disagreement
Every week here on Planet Money
There is
Actually surprising amount of stuff
Bitdegree on
The wide range of Pontiac
All across the political Spectrum
They think our policy no-brainers thinks that the experts agree
Should be on
Any presidential candidates economics
What's an African we convene
A panel of economic experts from across the political Spectrum
And we ask them
What do you all agree on what should a candidate propose as part of
The economic agenda
And we come up with our own
Green plant
And we learn exactly why no actual politician who wants to get actual vote
Ever listens to the advice the experts
Support for Planet Money and the following message come from TIAA
Dedicated to helping those who teach
He'll answer
Achieve lifetime Financial well-being
Whether it's investing advice banking or retirement
TIAA helps those who do good
Do well
See how TIAA is a different kind of financial partner
And discover how they can help you with the new tiaa.org
Created to serve
Built to perform
All right if we come up with a dream presidential platform we need
Dream Team
NBA Dream Team of Economist we need a
Super fancy intro
From the center for economic and policy research in Washington DC weighing in on blogs and articles are round
Globe economist
Dean Baker
You could probably describe his left
Dissenter be fair
Spectrum from George Mason University
Russ Roberts
The grand spectrum of Economic Policy I'm a pretty hardcore free market
Die
Probably called a libertarian
Playing the center of the spectrum Catherine Baker
I'm a professor of Health economics at the Harvard School of Public Health
From across the ocean
Do the University of Chicago
Luigi zingales
What I like says I might
Pro-market but not necessarily probiz
And finally rounding out the panel from Cornell University
The Economist so nice they gave him a first name twice
Robert Frank
I'm a registered Democrat
I think of myself as a radical pragmatist
This is an incredible line of experts from the top of the field from all over the ideological spectrum and if you were
Would have come up with an idea that they all agreed on
You would think
This might be an idea you'd want to propose as a candidate
Running for office
And it's not a mythical Quest
We found six
6 major changes to our economy
Pretty much the entire panel sign off on the six plank economic platform that every single
What about panelist signed off on
That started here
With the tax code
And we're not talking about little tweaks to the tax code
A percentage point cut here in that Raider a bump there in that right
No to a person are panelist Ed
The tax code in this country makes
Fundamentally no sense and needs to be completely over her
The simplest thing
Is silver a overall reform of the tax code in the direction of eliminating
All the loopholes and differences and in particular the docs
That was Luigi zingales
And I do feel Alex
Like I do actually hear this line o simplify the tax code close loopholes eliminate waste that sort of thing for presidential
Right but you ever actually hear people say which loopholes they would like to eliminate
No they're usually not very specific
It sounds good to say I want to close a loophole
But yet remember every loophole every deduction
Has people voters I should say who benefit from it
All the deductions
As a history and Anna
Explanation
But even if I might
I think some of them are useful like the chargeable deduction excetera I think that the only defensible line
So you should not be able to deduct
Chatham
All them all the deductions gone
And you know this man that time that crazy to people that cuz it cuz I think what people think alike
Tax deductions loopholes missing some Corporation or some rich dude getting a sweet deal
But the biggest of these deductions
The biggest one
Is the one that most of us wouldn't think of a loophole at all
And so
Planet Money presidential platform
Like number one
Eliminate that.
When did you know I think just
If I say you know the common sense the way we have it is it is the mortgage interest deduction
Mortgage interest.
Mortgage interest is a QB
Extremely woodgrass informal taxation extremely perverse
I hate to hear this because like many Americans I have a mortgage
And I do write off the interest on my taxes
And Alex actually know exactly how much it saves me cuz you know I do that TurboTax thing and you can
Click and unclick
Parts of this program
And I figured out
Exactly what the mortgage interest deduction saves
$5,000
That is
Not nothing
Yeah but you know I feel
Sm1 in middle-class that this is not a bad thing and I feel like this is an encouragement for me to own a home to participate
My community in Brooklyn tonight
Polluter you know throw trash on the ground
I believe that this makes me a good resident of United
But from an economist's point of view this is $5,000 that the government is
Arbitrarily giving you and other mortgage holders over other people in society so I don't have them
But I live in my house
Community
Don't get any special
Text Ruben from the government so it does seem a little unfair
Enter conversate such as unfair it's actually
Distorting
There mountains of Papers written on all the bad things that the mortgage interest deduction does
For one thing are, said the bigger your mortgage
The bigger the tax break you got
The Richer you are the more money the government gives you back
He was a liberal and a conservative Dean Baker and Luigi zingales
It just makes no sense that
You know if we have Bill Gates or whoever some very wealthy person
We're subsidizing them to get an expensive home
So because which people receive a much larger subsidy
If the price of houses
Increase
So much that
It actually makes less affordable for the poor people so
It is really perverse form of
And by the way this is not a secret
The mortgage interest
Direction
Everyone knows about it a lot of Economist on record as saying it's a very bad idea somebody should come along
I try to get rid of header pics
I'll tell you why in fact I will show you why we're going to bring an actor
We're going to put in some Applause and some Reverb we're getting ready to try out
Presidential platform plank number one
That's why
When I'm elected
President
Of the United
I have a special plan for the middle class
All of you American
Who own your own home
I promise
How to raise your tax bill by $5,000 of dollars a year
Yeah.
Going to explain that actually makes things Fair overall it it gets rid of these distortions in the
Housing market
And we've all seen what kind of problems distortions in the housing market could cause
It'll probably actually lower housing prices for people who want to buy houses
In the future
And in fact the government will be bringing so much money that was formerly given back to you and all your
Mortgage holding brethren
That maybe could actually lower taxes on everyone a little
Explorations little hard to fit a bumper sticker but I think we go with it that's like number one
And if you like that you are going to love
Plank number to which involves another deduct
A deduction that made in b-more distorting
In the first one the mortgage interest deduction
Okay if you have a job
The pace for your health insurance
And you are benefiting from this deduction right now
And you might not even realize it
But a panel of economist
Be immediately zeroed in on this as something that is got to
Deduction for employer-provided health care
The way we handle it right now is it if you get health insurance through your job
You don't pay taxes on that benefit the way you would on your wages
And your employer doesn't pay taxes on that benefit
Okay I bought some people there this is a little confusing because to not economist
This is a very obscure point
But usually at work
Think about your salary
If someone asks you
How much do you are and you say you know whatever $50,000 a year
But
That's what your entire compensation
The company is actually giving you something else of value health insurance
Which frankly when you look at it is like giving you money
But the IRS views these two forms of compensation very differently they tax you on the dollars you get from your salary
But they don't tax you
On that other form of compensation your Healthcare benefits
And this is the key that
Text your employer either
Remember your employee does get taxed on the salary they pay you
So you may think it wisest problem
We don't have to tax everything in life and I think we can agree that
Having health insurance
Is a good thing why should we tax
Yes but have you ever heard the phrase
Too much of a good thing
Here is Catherine Baker
Panelist and Healthcare economist
Some people actually have
Too much health insurance
And that's a controversial thing to say
But if you have health insurance
That covers
Everything under the sun with no co-payments
You would be completely reasonable to say while I don't care how much
Benefit the MRI will give me if it gives me even if
Tiny little bit of health benefit I want it
So when health insurance
Completely insulate
People from facing any
Price of the care that they consume
They start to consume health care that has
Lower and lower and lower value in terms of producing health
And the question is
Should federal government
Pax
That should the tax code
Subsidizing
Extra extra extra care thus producing lower and lower and lower health benefits
When those monies could be going to alternative uses like
Education
Lenoir housing
Or welfare or National Defense
So you're the problem if employers being encouraged by the tax dude
Spend more and more money on
Cadillac Health Plan
That drives up the cost of healthcare overall
Which just makes it more expensive for everyone
Including people
Who don't have Healthcare through their jobs they are priced out of the market
So all this discussion we have about health care costs going to the roof we heard over and over again
And everyone wants to blame somebody okay blame the insurers
Play in the doctor's appointment trial lawyers
What are Converse a part of the blame
Is this ridiculous deduction which amounts to a huge subsidy
To an already bloated help
All right look good are fake presidential candidate
It's always talking about those of you
Regional Healthcare
I understand that's your problem
But I alone
Tackling a problem
Equally as
Those of you
With too much health
And so I pledge
Costlier
And more restrictive health plans
Foremost
Working American
And that's why no one Alexa
It sounds crazy to say I have the solution
Horizon Health
Care cost
Text your health insurance been
When you say it out loud
It sounds wrong
But the crazy thing about this particular provision in the tax code
Is that it
Inefficient
In driving use of healthcare that really has questionable value
And it's inequitable
I'm imagining fake voters
Streaming out of our fake Auditorium in which our fake candidate
Is toxic they don't even want to hear this
But fortunately you know
Plank 3
I think it's something that people can get around a massive
Tax cut
Okay are you ready yeah I texted that Sin City is text itself everywhere in the American economy it destroys jobs
Stop synovation I am all for it okay who gets the text but
Yahoo
What for being Blue Sky hair
I would say the corporate taxes
Totally awake
The the corporate income tax makes no sense whatsoever
You are killing the voters here so far we got raise taxes on the middle class and eliminate taxes on
Incorporation those are the two most liberal members of our panel Dean Baker and Robert Frank
And here's the reason the day and pretty much all our Palace
Hate the corporate income tax
Which by the way is
What are the highest
In the world here in the United States at 35
It doesn't make sense related tax
The corporation as such what we want to do is to
Did someone commit Ronnie
What we care about is if the corporation is reinvesting the money
What's wrong with that why do we want them
Prevent why do we want to prevent the corporation from investing the money what we might want to prevent is
You're giving the money to wealthy shareholders or than buying a second or third fourth home getting a new Mercedes every 6 months
Whatever my feet
That's where we want to have the taxes we don't want to prevent Microsoft or General Motors whoever might be
I'm investing more in improving their product line that's that's a good thing in my
So a lot of people
Meaning when they think the corporate tax they want to keep the corporate tax in place because
They want rich people to pay more taxes
And rich people owned corporations right but our panel agreed if you want to tax rich people and not all of our Palace Madrid
By the way that you should text rich people more than
Other stitches
But if you did if that's what you wanted to do just text rich people
Do that
Don't text the corporation
Okay
Like number three roll it
I say
Read my
Lips
No taxes
For Corporation
Nada
Nothing
Alex people are streaming out of the doors of our fake Auditorium they're literally turning out the lights on our candidate
What wait wait hold on
Not done
There's more
You're going to like this
Something else
I'm
Proposing
I promise
To eliminate all income
And payroll tax
Okay okay there's there's something we can sell
Yeah and it's not just pandering there is good solid economic reasoning behind plank number for getting rid of the income
Income tax and getting rid of those payroll taxes
The taxes on your
How to check data
Here is registered Democrat Robert Frank
Taxes have two effects they raise revenue that's the one we're focused on here but they also have a second effect which is
To discourage
The thing that you tagged
We tax income for the
For the first of the two effects
TurboTax because it's an easy way to raise revenue
But if you if you ask
Is income a Bad Thing should we do
Discourage income
Answer no
That's not a useful thing to do at all right and the payroll tax is another offender
How is it that creating a job
Is a harmful activity
It's not harmful it's
Absolutely beneficial
Why do we want to discourage that
When there are other things that we
Could and should tax
Even if we didn't need
So clearly there is a problem here the government gets most of its money from income tax
And although at least
What are members
Russ Robertson
Your general direction
At least he wouldn't have too much problem with shutting down most of the government
The rest of them and that they all agreed there needs to be some form of
The question is
What to pack
Not most of the panel
If you ask them they would say some form of a consumption tax now this is a tax that
Embedded in everything you buy
And I should say as an aside Dean Baker heat he was
Not in favor of Kentucky
Taxi says too hard to make it work
But everybody else was in support of it and had interesting clever ways of making it Progressive so that rich people and yeah
Owners would pay a bigger share of the tax burden and
People struggling to put food on the table with Payless
And just to get enough money to keep the government running there is another type of tax
That are cannabis love
And it fits into a theme that we've been sort of dancing around with all these other planks in our panel
Which is
If you subsidize something
You get more of it this is a basic principle of economics if you provide a deduction for somebody if you make something tax
Free people will consume more of it sometimes more than you want
And here's the flip side of his principal
If you tax something you get less of it
So, say
Let's
Use that
To make
The world a better place
Here's Luigi zingales
Things that would be useful to
Introduce at Woodway Economist call
Gucci and Taxation which is taxation of
Bad things like
Smoking is considered
Damaging to
Housing Authority of yourself and others
And so we tax it to try to
Force people to internalize
The cost of the put
NWI Savannah what are the worst
Things that the things that are causing the most
Problems in the world right now
Pretty clear
Pollution carbon which is causing global warming
You got to check that
Crazy Taxi
Gasoline rays
Pollution of all forms
Tax
Energy use or carbon emissions
In a way that reflected the cost of the environment that we all share
Let me work work causing damage and we
You know we can't seriously tonight
Now I should say are libertarian
Russ Roberts he rolled his eyes
Abyss
Ethiopia
No practical questions like how do you get the size of the tax rate
And how do you enforce it all around the world which
As we know winds blow over from China if you're going to do this you have to do this worldwide
But even with all those disclaimers
Russ Roberts set
The environment
Is one area where I
The case for governor
Is the strongest
Cathay spillover effect
Are most obvious
Alright so
Even our libertarian Russ Roberts
Sort of onboard
Hitfit presidential candidate
When I'm sworn in on day one
I have a word of advice for the American public
Make sure you have
Full tank
Gas
I promise to raise the price of gasoline by 60
$0.70 maybe more whatever it takes
Done
Frumcrazy
So crazy
It just might work and there's a point at which
Kidney defense
So many people he's either completely off the rails or
Maybe
He's telling the truth
He's saying things that may be painful right now
But provide the most good for the most
People think that the United States has to hear things that may have been special interest
But
We need to hear
Well if you like
That kind of bold Proclamation I present the final plank
Remember this is from our team of highly respected dignified economic thinkers from some of the leading academic institutions in the country
Country flight number 6
Illegal drug
Make them legal
We spend a huge amount of resources
Does putting people in jail and try to catch him and discourage him all does his make
Got some nasty gang members rich
And
We waste a lot of resources on putting them in prison which is just a luxury form of Hotel I mean it's it's a crazy
Crazy system we have right now that make
Next time we can all make sense but I think it also makes
Action.
Ashley crazy policy I mean we should be looking to to decriminalize you know drugs like marijuana or
In my view probably much less harmful than alcohol on the ideal we have people spending years in jail and we have
Illegal we we have home
Underground system of
Supplying these drugs you know crime syndicate that
What's the drug that acts like crazy
Eros reforming the whole tax system
That's going to be tough
Showplace 6 legalize marijuana
How to take the edge off
Thank you thank you thank you God bless you and God bless
United States of America
I love our fake president
But you don't
If you think about this
If you think that all economist
Sabri on like the platform
Serious for a moment
All of our kind of do actually agree about that and you'd think that at least some form of these recommendations would make it into
Canada flag
Yeah you would think that but
This very little overlap between R panel and the real presidential
It's it's like this is political
Poison like you just can't say yeah I'd be open to talking about eliminating the mortgage interest deduction
Why not let's talk about it Economist agree with
And this is
Perks that right we have the six
Plank plant
Always respect and they agree to it
And it deals with some of the biggest challenges that we face as a country in a rising healthcare costs
Competitiveness fairness climate change
And yet you can't play any of these ideas out loud
Robert Smith Here Again by the Met
Your radio in
Thousand
16 Hillary Clinton and Donald Trump have not
Yacht suggested
Did the changes that are cotton
Put together
Clinton and Trump are not going to get rid of
The corporate income tax
How to lower it
You're not going to get rid of
Payroll tax
The market interest
Action still
No one
We'll talk about that
The only part of the platform of the candidates are so close to adopting is
Some form of legalizing marijuana they both seem on board with metal
Medical Marijuana but
They're not exactly ready to have
Pot for sale
At the corner store
There is one character that has come
Pretty close
To adopting the Planet Money
Presidential
Economic life
And that is
Gary Johnson Gary Johnson
Libertarian party
He appears to support
5 out of
Proposals it's a little bit hard to tell me mortgage interest deduction
Because great job
Says he wants to do
Get rid of the entire
So I assume that means mortgage
Pinterest
The only thing he disagrees with
The Economist on
Is
Taxing carbon emission
He does not want to see tax on carbon
So what does this economic truth did Gary Johnson
I looked at the RealClearPolitics polling average currently
5.8% of Americans
So they will vote
See that's
Email us at Planet Money at NPR. Org org
WeChat on face
Twitter today's rerun was produced by Raina Cohen
Maybe you listen to every single Planet Money episode
Twice we recommend
Maybe you've done that to any
You trying to figure out which podcast to listen to before our next episode comes out
The big listen
He's ready to help
NPR news podcast
Host Lauren Ober interest
Podcast
You might never heard of
And give you the inside scoop
On shows you
You already love
Like nerd at Bullseye and
The Wunderlist
Meet you right now
When you want something new find the big listen on NPR one or wherever you find Pike
I'm Robert Smith
Thanks for listening