Sounds like 9:30 tonight at the supermarket
For the story but also honestly because I need milk
It's amazing how much milk two little kids drink
Tell me where the milk is
It's in the very back corner
The store
Milk
The funny thing
What are the most popular items and they put it as far as humanly possible from the entry
There's a kind of story about why this is
Maybe you've heard that my mom told this to me when I was a kid
You know why milk is in the back of the store she said
So you have to walk through the store to get it
Surpass all this other stuff is too gay to buy more things
I believe my mom
She's my mom
Over the years I told this story to other people
You know why milk is in the back of the store so you have to walk through the store
Only recently have I wondered
Is it actually true
Is that why milk is in the back
Can you really have a business model intentionally built around inconveniencing your customers
Has a long walk
Here it is
1 gallon whole milk
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm David kestenbaum today on the show
Turns out there are two theories big theories to answer this very little question why the milk is in the back of the store
Two theories that reflect very different worldviews
We tried to discover which is right
We'd like to say a quick thank you and share a message from our planet money sponsor betterment
Betterment has fundamentally changed the way Americans save and invest for their future
Traditional investing Solutions are expensive complicated and boring
The betterment was built from the ground up
With sophisticated cutting-edge technology
It recommends personalized investment plan
Simply put betterment makes it easier more straightforward
And less expensive
To invest
For more information and up to six months free
Visit betterment.com Planet Money
We set up today show as I kind of friendly debate between two people I'm going to call them milk
The theorist
When is Michael Pollan food writer author of The Omnivore's Dilemma and many other books about food
Most recently cooked a natural history of transformation
Michael gets his milk at a small grocery store in Berkeley California
I get a
Local milk
Call Saint Benoit
That which is not homogenized
But pastor
In his hole how far is it from the cache
40 sheet maybe 50 ft
Seattle
Yeah it's a hike
Also on the line I called the bay II milk theorist
Russ rapper
Economist at the Hoover institution and host of the EconTalk podcast
Shops at Costco
For the record
Is not a milk
I'm pretty lactose intolerance I don't drink much milk so you're disqualified from this conversation is being lactose intolerant
Walden academic I think I'm more than qualified by the fact that I don't you know much about it
First up Michael Pollan arguing for the idea that milk is in the back
The force has to walk through this door
He says stores do this kind of thing all the time
They're always trying to manipulate us into buying more
Grocery store she says think very carefully about where they put everything
What you see first when you walk in
They put items with higher profit margins at eye level
I've come to understand the landscape of a grocery stores I've been brilliantly designed
Landscape to get us to buy as much food and as much
Expensive food
So my general impression is that the milk is
Is
Is in the back
And it's
But it's not just milk is in the back but it's also usually very far from the bread
Both of them are very common items
That everybody needs
And so it makes you cover a lot of ground
If you want them Michael is there one thing that when you walk by in the store you have a hard time not buying
I buy a lot of things I didn't come there to buy and that's really typical there in one study something like only a
Third of the items bought in the store where on the grocery list or plan for
So you'll see some cool new cracker in your Biotin and you might not notice that it's $6 for a little box
Is that Michael view the first Dairy R Us has a very different View
The stories she says
Are not in the business of trying to manipulate us
They are trying to give us the best shopping experience possible
They have to
Because of this basic economic principle
Competition
Supermarket business is very competitive
Stores have to please us he says
Or we'll go to another store
Russ thinks the reason the milk is in the back
Is practical
It's easier to keep the milk cold
The delivery trucks come into the back of the store milk goes right into this refrigerated room that soften right behind the cooler
Where you grab your milk
Known as to love the milk through the store cuz I'm cooler in the front
Milk spoils very easily
I was told that for every degree of temperature rises it loses a day
Being available and being sellable
So the argument I'm making which is kind of a radical argument is that
You and I want the milk in the back even though it's a little less convenient if we're in the front be more expensive
Are not willing to
Pay that extra price
So I think they're actually doing what we want out what they were
Russ is it probably cheaper to have milk in the back
That keeps the cost down for the store
And for you the customer
Russell points out that
If hiding stuff people want in the back of your store is really a good business strategy
Why don't other stores do
Why don't bookstore
Put the best sellers in the back
They don't
Turn the front they don't make you go through the
Elizabethan poetry not that we wouldn't be better people
For it
If we had to go through that section but they tend to put it in the front
How to make it easy
Ayto Michael you think of his argument
It's there to serve the
Well I think a Russ's assuming a greater degree of rationality in the America
Summer than the designers of supermarket
They're trying to work on us
Subliminal level
Even like the music you know that the number of beats per minute or per second
In in the music played in supermarkets
Is designed to slow us down
And get us not to rush through
And enter that that
Interesting dream like state that comes over people in supermarket
They've studied our blink rate
Supermarkets in we blink last in the supermarket as we're gradually
Slowed and lulled into
State of
She maybe I should try the
Best new cereal
You think there's something in the air that there that they're blowing in Vegas drowsy or you're that worried
I have no evidence of that okay
I've got two very different world.
When rice goes to the supermarket he thinks competition is a wonderful thing
Look at how it forces the store to keep cost down
Look how well laid out the store
I'm in charge
When Michael Pollan goes through a supermarket
He's suspicious
Why are there certain brands of beers and not others
Why does the granola always seem to be so hard to find
To him the owners aren't
And they're making decisions that aren't always in his best interest
Rustan's grocery stores profit by helping customers
Michael thinks they also profit by manipulate
Michael Andros went back and forth
And then Michael Pollan said this
What you could instead of having two people you know speculating about it
And bringing their theories of the world to bear on the
Ask question that we don't
Clear we don't have a lot of empirical
Go data on
You could ask
Somebody who might actually
Do you have any
Have the answer
I could I could be a reporter it actually
Go and answer that's so tedious
So I'm just saying it's another way we could
We could go after
I decided to try to track down the answer
I got her intern here to look up the top 10 grocery chains
I called and send emails
Made more calls
I found industry Consultants who advise on store layout
And I got six people willing to talk on tape
People in a position to know the answer people who know about milk
I tried not to buy them
Just asked where is the milk in your store and why
When I was done I got Michael Pollan and Russ Roberts on the phone
I reff
Hello
I play them excerpts from each of the interview so they could react
And we could keep score
First up
BJ's Wholesale
Major competitor to Costco and Sam's Club
Over 200 stores from Maine to Florida
I talked to Rob Olson Dairy buyer
Do you go through a lot of milk is that right regular gallon milk we sell millions of gallons a year and if I walk into one of your stores
Where is the
The milk is in the dairy cooler which is located in the back of all of our clubs
Is it right that milk is one of the most popular items
At the store
Why it so why is it in the back
Traditionally I think
And this is just my own opinion
I believe
We want members or customers
To get to the back of the club and see the wide array of items that we carry
It is it gets them into the store I guess
Look at the other stuff inside out maybe I need that too
Correct
We call it building the basket
In the business
What do you guys think
I love the phrase building the basket
Like really talked to the Same by Michael talked to
Michael said he'd always hurt and this guy hurt the same thing the same guy
Second hand
Exactly
Hearsay
I was tempted to give this one to Michael the guy after all had a phrase for the idea building the basket
But it turns out he had another phrase also
The cold chain
There's another reason we put milk in the back of head
To preserve the cold chain
Daddy is at once the milk comes out of a cow gets pasteurized and putting that gallon jug
You never want to take the milk out of a refrigerated environment
You want to keep it cold every step of the way
Very very important person
It's brought into a cold room
And it kept in this cold room
It goes from the cold room
The coal truck
Wacoal Distribution Center
Factorio coal truck
To the club or store and its constant
Call Nicole Chang
After the call the pr person for BJ's assured me this was the primary reason
I don't know
I gave Rustin Michael each a
I also talked to Kroger 2400 stores in 34 states
The pr person they're also mentioned both
So again I gave Russ and Michael each point
The next answer that was not ambiguous
Kevin Lang works for Wegmans
Is a store manager in King of Prussia Pennsylvania
The reason for us
Why we have milk in the back is because that's where milk comes in so therefore
We don't have to worry about ever breaking the cold chain I think it's a consumer misconception
Diagonal
Retailers put milk in the back of the store to make you walk through the entire store it's not true
So he he really I think I got to go Point Ross
And it's a fabulous grocery store but
Fun2give Michael is due
Describe his incentive
Not to suggested it some Sinister policy to get people to buy stuff that we do I keep that in mind
Yeah nobody want none of these retards want to admit they're manipulating their consumers
Yeah I'm amazed Michael got to vote already
Yeah
It was a fair point which is why I also called him Consulting
Since to ask them what the Inside Story
Burt Flickinger has advised lots of supermarkets
He's managing director of a place called strategic Resource Group
I tell the retailers to put the milk in the
Front of the store for the convenience of the customers in the Retailer's typically ignore my advice
I am put the milk
Yeah in the back of the store where they've been putting it for 70 to 80 years
Why do they say they want to put
Back to the supermarket said they want to put it in back
Because it's
Hi it's it's easier for delivery agency of her stocking
So they say it's for convenience sake
Cheaper left labor I all of the above
They don't say it
So that people have to walk through a store and see other thing
And then they say we want
The people that walk through this stores
And bye-bye every everything we sell
Reaction
Oh that's another split boat there
Yeah probably
Point reach
I should mention that both Kroger in Wegmans in a lot of their stores do have small coolers in the front as Berg recommends so people in a hurry
We can just grab them
At this moment Michael Pollan was behind the count but he was just down by one point
And the next person with someone
She had selected
Brian wansink
Cornell professor expert in all the ways we get tricked when it comes to
But
Wangjing sided with Russ
He told me it's in the back
Just so they can keep the milk cold
Store managers he says are not playing Sigmund Freud
They're more worried about whether the cashiers are stealing from the register
When it comes to milk
It's in the back because it's just much easier to have it there
Piercings going on in Scotia
What matters most bottom-line savings
The money is in the panties to begin with
Are tickets for
Real consumers you can design your own thrift store
Eventually after the second or third iteration is in the back
If we designed them ourselves we put them in the back
All right
Michael what were you thinking having him call that guy
Report against yourself
It's taking a lot of you got to know what your Witnesses are going to be able to put them on the stand
I did my best Michael the truth
Call you put you in a very small Club Sur
Dial the truth
I think we have this idea in economics in a lot of things really that when there is a question there is an answer
But tonight there just isn't
Stores themselves may not
Even have a clear idea of why they're doing what they're doing
It's not like there's some binders every supermarkets headquarters title
Optimum milk placement in Dallas
I think the real question here unfortunately is a hypothetical
I put it to our last expert Jim Hotel
Supermarket consultant
Managing partner at a place called Willard Bishop
If it were easy to put the milk up front
Do you think stores would do it
Well there's a dairy
There's somebody who's
Running the dairy Department
Nintendo stock
And they can just put it wherever
Do you think stores would do it
No I don't
You don't think they would
I'd know I think
They like having people
Product
Probably operational
Reasons why it's there I think that the the secondary or the side benefit of having people walk through
The store
It's very comfy
Michael given that one to you all right
Fair enough I give that one to my
Alright so
I don't know guys it's like
Rails has one
Two three
Four five
And Michael has one too
Should we call this when I draw
Yeah
I'm happy I'm happy
Did you ask your
Let me let me ask the obvious question did this change either of your thinking
Well I think when I'm asked about this
In the future I will be more Folsom in my answer and make sure I
I pay at the fishing
Attention to the
To the idea of
Dakota
Russ
It reminds me of the importance of culture and history and some businesses Asians but I think
Which I think plays a role
But I do think
The competitive forces pretty powerful
I'm willing to concede that I may sometimes overestimate its power
In certain industries it doesn't work so well but I don't think it's this one
I think if someone asked you
Is the milk in the back of the store because it's easier
Or is it because it makes you walk through the store
A safe answer
It's just a yes today show is produced by Jess Jiang special thanks
You are excellent intern Jason De Leon
Email Planet Money at NPR.
I'm David kestenbaum
Thanks for listening