Where are we again
We're between Waterville and
Blue Rapids
And just to recap the folks at home
What happened previous episode of Planet Money go
Okay we purchased oil from json Brian's in cans
We bought a hundred barrels we transported it
To a pipeline the pipeline with the refinery the refinery turned it into diesel
And then it sent it across Kansas and so
What we are is in the middle of Kansas
In the middle of cornfield
Looking for a
Hi this is Stacy Bennett
And I am Robert Smith this is it this is the last
Episode
About our oils Journey which is now Planet Money
Diesel and we're going to follow it all the way
The Council Bluffs Iowa
An into somebody's actual car
But right now
We're on the side of the road
Staring at a cornfield looking for
Little tiny signs telling us where are diesel is at this moment
Okay can you read any of those I'm not going down there
Oh wait okay warning underground cable that's not it
Oil pipeline is a lot harder than it sounds because pipeline travel in a straight line and roll
Do not say we spend a lot of time driving north south
East west
Pride intersect with a pipeline looking for one thing
Can I see good eyes Robert Smith it's a we become
The only tourist in history of Kansas to go down to take a picture of
Warning petroleum pipeline
Oil derrick on it
Oh yeah but feel like a bright yellow sign and of course there's lightning in the distance
Always nice to see when you're following a pipeline but
What it means is it somewhere under our feet
At this moment
Is the Planet Money diesel fuel
Somewhere
Along with a whole bunch of other stuff
Yeah this is a question whether people have asked which is like wait what is is the point of oil just mixed in with everybody else
Elsa stuff
Any answers
Yes
And no
Pipeline
Do not just carry one kind of product is totally
Blue my mind they can send
A batch of Airline fee
For a couple of hours they're feeding nothing but Airline fuel right behind it
They can do a batch of diesel and they can put it back
A regular gas they're all sort of
Right next to each other like train car
And it all ends up at a tank farm
In Council Bluffs Iowa just be sleep whole bunch of tanks in a field
This is where the gas gets stored and delivered to customers and here we meet Larry bows he is a pumper Gauger
With CHS Inc
That is the company that refined-r oil
And what that means is it Larry gets a sheet of paper that tells him when the different
Heinz
Petroleum fuel
Arrived and he diverted to the correct tank so it says basically on the list when Planet Money
Is diesel was going to ride
About 4 in the morning we're going to get a bats change to diesel in here
And when it does
It's going to set off an alarm here
Do you have to press a button to do that I'm going to run around here and open one bound to a tank and close the other valve
No no no no no no no
Your manually going to like
Turn the wheel
How to take a lot of
But elbow grease to turn it I think you could do it
I'm serious
Apparently
Very easy to turn
And you know I doubt it used AC to stay up till 4 in the morning to get the sound of that
I know he only thinks I can
He's not sure I think we need some serious Planet Money Braun Robert only you can bring that
Getting up at 4 in the morning we both went to sleep
Try to think like where
Would the Planet Money
You will end up eventually
Probably in a tank
The next morning that came in at 4 in the morning
But we do know that these diesel tanks feed the Cenex brand gas station so
Masonic brand gas station only a few miles from where the pipeline in
We got to the Cenex station and we defended on this man Tom he's a math teacher in Council Bluff
If he was trying to fill up his car oil comes from well I guess my initial assumption to be sorry
Arabia possibly somebody you know one of those countries that produce oil ship United States so I guess you don't think about it very much
Not really I prefer to be from United States someplace but no I guess I do
Actually before you came from Kansas
Well that's great we were so excited to talk to Tom we were so excited
It's hard to explain to someone this entire project
In the two minutes that he's filling up his tank but we try
Will you bought our well I think so we wanted to like shake your hands and
You get 14.5 gallons free
A premium Kansas wheat back so we have to charge you
FedEx
The Cenex paid CHS the refiners the refiners paid the middleman the middleman
Paid us
And we paid json
Who should have just voted straight to him and try to recoup our investment
But we did not we thought it would just be delighted
With the story but there is this problem
With doing this whole oil and gas series
And that is that the end of it
Is so
Mundane
Filling up
The tank in your car
You don't even think about
It just sit there it's most boring thing
In the world and every time we tried to tell people
Look at the miracle
Really a miracle that just happened that some
Lincoln laid down their lives
Millions of years ago in chest
Weed in the ground
For Planet Money
To come along
And pull it out
Transforming in just a couple of days from this
Prehistoric stew really in Kansas
To drive a car in Iowa it is a mirror
Yes
It is a mere
All the problems that will causes and it causes some pretty big problems
It's a pretty miraculous substance
In fact trying to imagine a world without oil
Is almost impossible
Because not only is there oil in the tank of Tom's car there's also oil in the plastic in
Eschews
It's in his jacket
It's in a cell phone now that we've come to the end of our brief and very unprofitable journey through the
Oil Business we wanted to take a step back today on the show David kestenbaum and Jacob Goldstein asked
A simple and pretty profound question
What would the world be like without oil we'd like to say a quick thank you and share message
Which former Planet Money sponsor discover you check things all the time like your email or social media but discover ass
What about checking something as important as your credit score
Well discover makes it quick and easy with a Discover credit scorecard
Discover is the only major credit card to offer FICO credit scores to everyone for free even if you're not a customer
And once you know your FICO credit score
You should check to see if your current credit card is the best fit for you
Learn more at discover.com credit score card
Limitations apply
Jacob when we started doing the series on oil
There is one morning when I came into the off
I said to you
Have you ever thought how amazing it is
Did there was just a huge source of
Fuel and energy ripening
The more I thought about it the more I felt like
I don't know where we would be with
Could we have built this world that we live in today without fossa
Sophia cuz it does seem like this gif
Just from an energy
Yeah I had definitely never thought about it that way
I meant to be honest I never really thought about it at all but when you say the phrase
Fossil fuel my emotional reaction is
Negative you know I think
I think pollution I think climate change it so I don't know if I think what would the world be like if we had never had fossil fuel
I don't know maybe we'll be better off if we didn't have them you know what we are now minus the climate
When I was looking for people to help us think through this
I sorta got two categories
Have responses
One was like
No thank you I'm a serious historian I do not do speculative alternative hits
But the response was
That is a totally fascinating question
That is the correct response
Let me talk to two people in particular
I'm a David Keith, professor of
Whatever it's called it's called Applied Physics at Harvard also public policy
Here's the second person we talked to for some reason the can you introduce yourself portion of the interview was causing some
Can you introduce
To whom to everybody who's listening to Planet Money
I'm almost here I'm a professor of economics and history at Northwestern University David and Joel
Well, this question from different dress
David is a scientist kind of an energy nerd
Things about fossil fuels a lot
On the one hand I work on climate change for half my life
Simon fighting the fossil-fuel world forever
But also
I know how the energy system works
And so
I don't feel my
Fossil fuels he says they are an amazing Source event
David is a scientist
John MacArthur on the other hand
Things about the the Great
Sweep of hist
30 set the stage we said ok historian tell us what life was like
Before people really started using fossil
In like the 1700
Lancer
Not good
Terrible
Lots of hard work
Back-breaking work
Always a danger of not having enough to
At to eat
A threat of famine looming over
Once life everyday
Infant mortality that was reaching over 300 or 350 per thousand
Third of all newborns die
A third of all newborns died
In infancy or before the 8th day HD
Swangas
Darrell bock
You can look at this and say what we needed with science
But you could also see this as an energy
You want some source of energy to cook
Food or heat your house
Basically you got trees
You cut down a tree
Chop it up
Burn the wood
We were just living off the surface
David Keith the scientist he said
Trees are not that great as far as sources of energy
I don't think these are kind of spread out
You know like there's a
The tree here then you got to go
Pain feet to the next one
For another thing he says when you cut a tree down you got to wait you know a hundred years for another one to grow again
He says compare that to Cole
Coal companies
Huge
Sex scene
Were you can just dig it out by
Individual people with
Hose
Can pick it up by
Naked
Concentrated source of energy
Geographically constant
Sokol is sort of like millions of years of wood that was just stacked in the basement there
Well in fact
Sort of like billions of years of what essentially literally what it is
Jacob my favorite slang for oil
Is dinosaur juice
They may be an atom of dinosaur in oil but it's most
Ferns. There's an atom of dinosaur
I'm like 50%.
When a small engine runs really fast to waste
Fight-or-flight easy call
Given all this we ask them
Where would we be today
If there had been no fossil
Biofuels in the grass
How would history have
Basil leaf
Would we have been
We ran through some key historic Moana
SNS both of them how things might have gone in this
Parallel universe where fossil fuels did not
What are the first really big moments
4 fossil fuels
Comes in the 1800
Train
Railroad coal powered steam engine
Pulling all these people in all this stuff
Maybe you're like
Trains
Obviously I'm not like that right like trains are clearly
A huge moment like the moment when the modern world comes charging at a casino for the first time
You can travel over land faster than a horse
This is a huge
Breakthrough
Could you have railroads if you didn't have fossil fuels like what would have had
Absolutely
America only became more than half also fuel
Roughly in 19
Before that we had an enormous input of wind powered energy
If you think about that big steam engine
Moving across
Western North America
What are those are powered by wood Top by Cole
Add some of the more running off
Most of them
What was the dominant fuel
If you power the railroads off
What I should get a cut down an enormous number
We got this
We got down like 97% of the original forest in the lower 48
United States we basically got it all
So
We were going to run into some limits
No cap
That clearly sounds
Very bad butt
You don't think about the economic
In the parallel universe where there's no fossil fuel
Would would have been really precious
Really
Expensive
And so you would have lots of people getting into the woods
Growing new trees to tell the word
Any says thinking about Railroad
There were alternate
Like we could have relied more on Rivers you know maybe would have built a bunch of Canal Zone
Economist of actually studied what would have happened without railroads
It's not that bad
Getting around is a little
Pentecostal
Turns out it is more expensive but not so much more
That we would have had completely too because we would have remained some kind of medieval economy we would have been
A different economy with much more canals
Wait what would what would have powered the boats on the
Do it always with you we would have
Who it works vacuum with with horse
That's hot that's how can I how can I borrow
That sounds
It doesn't it's a little bit slower but it is
What's the value of time
For those of you who don't know
The horses when they were alongside pulling the barges.
Motorcycle
There were lots of other paths that we could have gone to
And yet I mean some of them seem a little bit
But that's just cuz we're locked into thinking about the world as it is
Okay so trains that run on wood
We got more canals
I can see that while I can see how you could
But they at least have this big thing right
Electricity what how do you do it like
You're that really feels like
The big one right like a sinner this
And it comes on just not that long after trains take off
Thomas Edison built the first
Central Electric Power
Right here in man has it's a few miles from where we are. It gives 82 people electrical
It is the beginning of electric
End-of-course Edison power plant ran on coal
How else would you have run that power play
We would have had to get to generate much more electricity from water
Would you run it off with us
Hudson River
The only way we would have had to build dams on the Hudson River to run electricity we could have generated in Waze
Did we never fear if you tried liking title Mills title Mills
What are title
Title meals are milsim actually used in
In the middle
They use the movement of
Water enhancer the tides
Enso demille's stuck in coastal Waters
It's moving One Direction When the tide is in moving the other direction with the tightest I doubt they create Tower
To take lunar power
Extension Luna power yes
Get to know if I actually believe this idea he was explaining but then you called it lunar power
Hippie I say you got
Still what are you going to do about
Yeah that's like the next big one right it's just a few decades after Edison
Henry Ford comes out
What time before going to do if there's no gasoline
Two words
Electric cars
I've got electric car
Quite advanced
Go suck a hundred miles and a charge
And was built in 1909
That's the baker elect
It's an electric car from like in early 1900
It's Jay Leno and its YouTube video driving around in this old
Car looks like I don't like
Box on wheels
Does it look like what Cinderella took
Back to the
Horseless Carriage
What's not prom
Wake electric cars were a thing back then
Then Henry Ford's wife
She
Drove an electric car she liked it better than her husband
Invention that ran off gasoline
There is a problem with electric cars even today there's a problem
They just don't go there
Even with monitor batteries
We asked Jomo care about
Battery Technology turns out to be
And difficult
Imagine imagine
A world in which we know we were not terribly rebuilding battery switch battery only
I'm about 40 miles okay well then we would have had to build a network in which every 40-mile you
Stop your car you
Loosen two screws
Take out the old battery put in it
Prestige Audi want to keep Tina tagging along
I would have been bit of a hassle but also his own houses
What about this one
Airplane
How do you do airplane
You don't
Not for a while
Again though he says not a disaster
You know you can still take a boat across the ocean
And maybe there would be blimps
We did for a while
Experiment with a
Technology that actually
It work reasonably well in the end endoso identity
Blimp
Yuan zhuo bonded for a while
You know the Empire State Building
The tower was built as a docking place
It's for blimps
Which I look like when I'm flying to JFK I'm like I got to get a card
I got an hour to get wherever I'm going to imagine like
What if my blimka just Dock at the Empire State
In many ways it's an extremely Pleasant way of traveling
Can I ask you a totally random one
Would we have gone to the Moon
I don't know I probably not
So what
Talking to Joel
I actually kind of came around a bit
Like maybe things would be fine if there has been no fun
Got lots more dams hydropower
What you're going to need for your life
And Joe said he'll because energy would be more scarce and work
Did we were just concerned
We built smaller houses
Together
Okay you want to go to Europe you just get on a boat and takes a week
You hate blind
You don't believe it I believe it
Okay that's what
Then we talked to David
Keep the physicist
And he frankly you the less optimistic
Cuz he done the math on a lot of these
Like when we asked him
If we damn all the rivers
How much electricity does a taxi
If your damn
Do you want the terror what units
Yeah yeah
You got all the rivers in the world you get a
A few terawatts
Currently Humanity uses like 16 or 18
To all the rivers in the world or only maybe a quarter
Of the total energy were using today
And David Keith racist problem that I had not even thought
What are you going to build those damned out
Concrete
Deal
Both of those things require a lot of
The energy to make
You know how we make steel
Any very very hot furnace
Heated by
Fossil fuel
And by the way thinking about trains he said sure you could run the trains on wood
But how you going to build the tracks in the train would you going to make those out
And on top of that
All these all these advances were talking about
Come from scientific knowledge
And we got that scientific knowledge in part because of fossil
Because we had all this easy energy
But let us advance to a place
Where they were people scientists and Engineers who had time to
Sit around and tinker and figure things out
Even wind power
When power does get you
Kenza Tara
You could power all of modern civilization
But the question is
Could you build modern wind turbine
Without the kind of fossil fuel economy to get you started
PetSmart winter advisory
Fantastic things
Huge steel shaft
You know almost hundred meter long blades made out of
Fiberglass beautifully shaped
What can you build something up just good enough you know what to get you the electricity you needed back in the 18 hundreds to do whatever the next
Maybe
If a attic central question
Could we have tunneled through
Turn an old biofield a civilization
To a post fossilization like we now want to get to
Without fossil
And if we could tunnel through what would be the best way it might be that a gradual development of wind power is it
Wind power you can just
Incrementally doing better
After all we've had wind machine
And wait the question we've been asking for this whole show
You know how would history have unfolded without
It boils down to something really
Are we where we are today because we're lucky
Or because we're
We asked Joel and David both where they stood
Domo care told us that
Based on his entire career
His life's work
He thinks we are where we are
Because we're
What's driving modern history is not
Fuel or fossil fuel or what
What is driving it is human ingenuity
And you would have come up with an alternative set of solutions
And it would not have been
I think noticeably worse
Then the one we ended up with
And in some ways
Better
That's my boy
David Keith our scientist
Started out sounding very
As much as I'm an energy can I sync all about Anna
The ultimate power source
Is people working cooperatively
Actor David Keith was done praising Humanity for our incredible ability to work together and be innovative
Keaton 170 that fossil fuels
Had really
Mini SED
Shirt eventually we would have gotten to a world something like the world we live in today
But it would have taken me
Things would have gone worse
How much slower
My testicles is like 10 times
Much lower
Eye Optical
Yeah
Does it talk about
Wow that's a big deal
Yeah
Now I mean it's it's
Getting access to
2 fossil fuels has such a
Sort of Taken
Hundreds more years to go
Yeah
Turn off
The truth is we do live in a world
David Keith says fossil fuels have given
In fact they brought us to a point
We now have the technology to live without fossil
There's a lot of detail questions about how you do
I know take some
You could get rid of fossil
They said the world would look basically the same
Dave and Jacob that is a lovely way to end
The oil series but there was one part of the journey
That
Stacy and I wanted
To share with you
Before this is over and it's a part that Stacy didn't talk about very much because she was somewhat in
Every single time we interviewed someone
Stacy had a very
Unusual line of questioning
Different issues Chinese guy Vince Bankston who works at the refinery
And she tried to link our oil with a certain delicious ice cream tree
Is there corn around here
Sophie Korn
Feed corn
Is in cattle feed corn is which referring to a lot of us
Crushed cacao food yes
So if we like drink a milkshake
Would that potentially vehicle that was fed with
Feed corn that was fertilized with oil
Yes drink
AR
Oil in a milkshake
Every single time.
Okay the milkshake obsession
This is from a very iconic scene in a great movie about American oil called There Will Be Blood
In the scene Daniel Day-Lewis is explaining
How he can steal his neighbors oil
We basically a giant straw
It's an amazing scene
Milkshake
Dart board
And then he beat them to death with a bowling pin I think
I tried to explain to Stacy this is a metaphor
But you were very insistent that we show up at a Dairy Queen in Council Bluffs and try and drink our own milkshake
You're making fun of you but you know that this is exactly where the world should end right
Yes
It should end
With me drinking your milkshake
Do what you did with me drinking your milkshake
3 2 1 go
Arena condos because
It's so good
This is going to take awhile so we're going to toss it back
Did David and Jacob for the end of the show let us know what you think you can send it to email we are planning
At money at NPR.
Where you can find us on Twitter or Facebook the show today was produced by Jess Jiang and Nick Fountain getting to the meat
Also this week we are doing a brief survey to learn more about you to learn more about who was listening to Planet Money
You can take it at npr.org
Flash
Planet Money survey
It would be a big favor to ask if you could do it
Captain valmir
This is it
You got to do it now
This Is the End
The end of my time
You got a job at this make
Mazel tov
I'm going to call you every 5 min
I can miss this place I'm going to miss all you guys
II
The thing is what I say is
Thank you
Have a mentor
And I never had one and now that you're leaving I realize
It was you
You taught me how to do this
Thank you
It's so nice
You know I mean when I came here I didn't know how to make pie
That's because I worked with you and now I know how to make
You know that's not true
Causal
A sequence of events tonight
1/8 million
Bella Thorne
I really like that I love working with you
I love you man
Cut that last part is too sad