Every once in awhile I
Take
Track train from New York to Washington
And the train goes through a couple cities that are doing really well they
Your fancy new buildings along with Skyline
But Amtrak also goes through bolts
In Baltimore so different
It is a city that is shrinking it's lost about 30
Percent of its population since 90
And what that means when the train goes through you see that Baltimore has all of these abandon
Buildings
So there's one block in particular that you can actually see from the train window it is the 900 block
North Bradford
And it's he's 17
Skinny two storey row houses that are all boarded up and they look basically like ruin
But every time I see them I wonder
Why doesn't Baltimore just
Tear those house
So couple of months ago I started going to Baltimore to ask about that
And I found out that there are a bunch of people including like everyone in the neighborhood
Really want this block to be tomorrow
Their leader
Is a woman named Janice
Jacob's Hudson
She has been around in this neighbor
Brotherhood forever
And talking to her you realize
She just knows everyone
Miss Savannah
Who was the older lady she would come outside
And it won't heal or apron
Woke up on a drug dealer in my neighborhood over you know yeah she did yes she did
Janice has been on a mission
Years
To get the city to tear this
Calling
Going downtown
Being a thorn in their side I was a nuisance and I know I was
I meant Janice one afternoon at the place she hangs out which is an abandoned Factory that's been turned into a commune
Unity center it's about four blocks from North Braddock
And we were sitting by the window and talking and all of a sudden
Poppin
It's really hard to hear it at first
Those gunshots
We got back from the windows
And then there were more shots
Okay
1 2 3 4
So let me make a call
While Janice was calling I looked over her shoulder at her
Her phone and she's got like
10 names in her contacts that start with
Major
Those are the names
The cops guy she knows personally
Has she called one of them
Listen I'm in the building right
Sound like gunshots coming from down there in the
900 block of Rose Street
Y'all got that okay good we're coming from a different place
But also one that has a bunch of abandoned house
Ingenesis
This is kind of her point right
You got all these empty houses
Emmys are places where drug dealers
Come and they hang out and they hide out
And then it's like 3:30 on a random Wednesday afternoon and people are shooting at each
Over the past six months I spent a lot of time on North Bradford
Like a lot of
And I think I have figured out why it is so hard to tear down not just 17 empty
Houses on a block and bolts
But why it is so hard to knock down
The millions of vacant houses in shrinking cities all across the United States
Hello and welcome to Planet Money
And I'm Jacob Goldstein Noel you have gone on a journey here a literal and metaphorical Journey
And you have brought back for us a story of 17 houses
$700,000
And an amazing piece
Of heavy
And I promise no more
We'd like to say a quick thank you and share a message from our planet money sponsor betterment
Betterment has fundamentally changed the way Americans save and invest for their future
Traditional investing Solutions are expensive
Complicated
I'm boring
But betterment was built from the ground up with sophisticated cutting-edge technology
It recommends a personalized investment plan
Simply put
Betterment makes it easier
More straightforward
And less expensive to invest
For more information and up to six months free
Visit betterment.com Planet Money
I am from a small town in Upstate New York jail
Crow hunks in trunks
Kerhonkson is one of those little towns that used to have a
Blooming summer tours
Industry
But in the 70s tourist stop coming to kerhonkson and they left behind all of these
Abandoned hotels and bungalows
And as a result I kind of love abandoned buildings
When I was a little kid
I didn't have so many friends
And I used to break into the building I would crawl in through a window and then I would
Hangout
So that
Is totally alien from my experience of being a little kid I grew up in Suburban San Diego
So basically in the 70s
When people were moving out of
Towns like Crow Hawks in New York they were moving into towns like Escondido California
Growing and building an empty field across the
Filled up with house
And economically
That's good you want people to leave places where there aren't too many jobs like
Pro hunks in trunks
Kerhonkson
I moved to places where it where there are jobs
Apps like San Diego
But there is this problem right
When all those people leave save kerhonkson or Baltimore for that matter
You want to be able to knock down the buildings they left behind
You're one of my earliest memories Jacob is one year some people
Set one of the abandoned hotels on fire I can actually remember seeing the Flames through the woods
Okay abandoned buildings
Crime
Take me back to Baltimore with last we left they were going to
Writing so Dennis and I got away from the windows and she called the police
Evan a couple minutes later
It was all over went back to normal we went back to the windows
And Janis starts telling me the story
This goes back seven or eight
Years
That is the first time Janice went to the city and said
Would you tear this block down
And she says
One of the guys from the city told her
He said James.
Discount expensive
I said I know
I know
Of course
It's the money right
Bummer in this story but
Good news
In this story is with not really the money big day with this
Random lucky break
Or somebody from the city
Went to a Blythe
The conference which
Apparently the real thing
Found out there was this pot of money that came from some
Federal Mortgage
Robo-signing
Scandal
Settlements
And Baltimore got millions of dollars
First to knock down empty houses
And they put North Bradford this one block
At the top of their
Yeah and when you visit North Bradford you can see exactly why it's my first one in March
And went down the block and it is as bad as it looks from the train okay so we have
One boarded-up house
One not boarded-up house note it is bordered there are 17 houses on the Block even
Numbers 909 02904
They're covered with this ugly blue and brown and yellow fake Stone
It looks like something
That would be covering a castle I'd like a mini golf
So I poked around a little bit
924 looks like I could just go right in
How many try to do I can't help it
I tried the door in the paint flaking off
The door was like painted shut
So I gave up
I said after the gunshot sound like
Paradise Okay so
It's been
4 years
From the time Baltimore got the demolition might need to the time you started visiting this
But when you went there a few months ago the city of Baltimore had not yet knock down a single one of these
These houses the people in the neighborhood want them knock down to see has the money
What is the prop
To find out I went to the housing authority and I met a woman named Wendy Redfern Curtis
Wendy's part of a team whose
Job it is
To get these houses down
So I thought. Next door in a convo
Hertz room and she started explaining why it takes so long
She pulled out this color coded Municipal map of the block of North Bradford
And she says you know I actually know this neighborhood really well
My grandmother owned
9 Oaks
6 MI
Live at 9
96 Montford right here
Show me on the map
Right here
That's your grandmother's house was my grandmother's house
And this is Brad
She's made a lot of time in this area
She's a block she's a block away from it
And I have a
Ethel is across the sea
UPS
Okay
Okay so this isn't this is kind of personal to business very personal
Wendy's job is erasing the neighborhood where she grew up
When she was a kid this neighborhood was full of people middle-class and working-class people
A lot of them worked for the Western Electric Company
And talking about it now makes Wendy a little sad
So my parents work for what
Western Electric
It was a factory job
They didn't go to college they went to work straight from high school
They met they are they married
And then and this is a familiar story in a lot of us industrial cities
In 1982 Western Electric closed
Plant
In
The cold of night
In like 1983 or 86
The same night I think the Colts left Baltimore
Western Electric decided that it
It was closing
Plant
In Baltimore
So that meant that my family had to move
Cuz we need it jobs
A lot of other families move to
And those houses on North Bradford and houses around them started
Empty out
Seeing her neighborhood
Empty
Is really tough on my
But she knows that Baltimore needs to be a smaller City it is a smaller City
Those houses of got to be knocked down
And she is fired up to do it
What happened before this wasn't easy
This is awesome
Knocking down houses is awesome
But she told me there are two big reasons it's really hard to do
In the first one goes back to 924 North Bradford that the house where I tried to open the door
Wendy had this slideshow of the houses
And she showed me a picture of that house
See that
No curtain
No curtains
Not bored it's not for it's not open to Casual entry
But it doesn't look like anybody's living there hasn't been condemned to the city can't just knock it down
They have to actually buy the house from the owner
Well guess what
Some of these owners have been missing
For decades
So the city has to track them down
Then they have to tell them we wanted to abolish then they have to negotiate a sale one of the houses
The owner was actually in Ethiopia
Ethiopia he was going to be back for another year yeah an infected Wendy and her colleagues three years
Words to get through this part of the process going out
Playhouse
The owner make
I can feel to buy the house
And you said it was wet like about $10,000 they went to paying for each house yeah that's fair market value
And by December of last year Baltimore owned every single house on that block
And demolition
Could finally begin
There was just one
Last
I'm the last of the Mohican
This is Vanessa West
She's the last person living on this block
She rents number 930 which is
Just four houses over from the end
And one day last March I went down there Vanessa and I sat out on her stoop
It seems like her favorite pastime is basically just yelling to people from the neighborhood from her stew
List out
Asset
A bunch of ice creams around there to know about a week ago
Stop bigger assholes
She's 37 years old
Message is very lovable person
When I first met her down on the Block I thought she must be a holdout
She wants to stay here for some reason
It turns out I was totally wrong
Vanessa wants to leave
First of all four houses in really bad shape
Unless
Spring not long before I met her there was a storm one night Vanessa was awake and she hears this big boom
House on North Bradford
I've literally falling over
I'm glad we're nobody called parked out here cuz it would have been total
You mean that the house actually fell into the street some of the stuff fell into
Chemistry summer fun on the side
This kind of games
Vanessa lives with her son and her grandkids she does not want them to get hit by a house
Vanessa really wants to move
But there's this federal law that uniform relocation assistance Act
Do they call it gyro
Vmate
And it's a lot makes it very hard for Vanessa to move in fact it's another big part of the reason it is taking
So long to knock down these
Give this one was actually passed
2 / 2
Text people like finesse
It was passed in the 70s after these big waves of Highway construction that ended up knocking down a lot of houses
Screwing over a lot of people who lived in those houses
And in a lot of ways the lot does what it's supposed to do it does protect people like Vanessa
I should get some money to help relocate
And also says if it's going to kick me out cuz her house is getting knocked out
The city must make sure Vanessa move someplace
Safe
Descent insanity
So last year Vanessa found a house that she really liked it was
Bigger it was newer
So yeah
Ready
I think it'll be a good
Bratz
Let me remove
But this house did not meet the requirements of
Yura or do you want whatever it didn't meet the requirements of this law that is supposed to
It wasn't
Safe and decent and sanitary under the
She's in a wheelchair and the house didn't have all the railings it was supposed to throw the city said no
You cannot move into that house in that
So when I started visiting North Bradford last spring
Everybody was just waiting on Vanessa and she was waiting for the landlord to get that house fixed up so
So she could move in
I called Vanessa once a week every week
And every week she said
It's about to happen
I'm about to move
God's will
God praise
I'll be gone next
Finally after a couple months of this
I basically said
I mean come on
Here's a minute of that phone call
What Miss Miss Vanessa what happens if things don't work out next week cuz I know we've been talking since April
And I know that you wanted to be
You thought you'd be out by December of last year
National
Don't don't don't
Don't forget it like that
I have faith that I'll be out of here
You don't you don't want to
You don't want to talk about
About that
Bad stuff like
Bad stuff
I called Vanessa the next week and she was still on North Bradford
And then in early June the city finally gave Vanessa the go-ahead
The house she had been waiting on with safe
Indecent
Unsanitary
And it was all hers
And in July I went to visit her there
Yeah it took
Real well but I found he made it
Keto me how you feel
I love it
Is more Romeo
Small spaces
I can get around a whole lot better here than I could
And I just send you a
Just love me when I first came in like a
And half a mile away
That very same day
Alright so I'm walking toward
North Bradford
Walking tour that wow look at this
Oh my God
One of the houses just
Came down there's a big orange excavator with a claw and it just
It just took an entire house down
That was number 924 that was the house where I tried the door
That was amazing
That was number 926 that was amazing
Number 926 I was the one where the owner had gone missing in Ethiopia
By the end of the day
All but
Two of the houses on the Block worth
When was Vanessa
This Old House number 930 where the water was
Still hooked up
And then the one next door 932 that one head as best
But those two houses
Came down two weeks
Soap all the houses are gone now and
The plan is to turn the block
In the some kind of parkour
Final accounting all of the 17 houses on that block of North Bradford
Prince Street are down
Total cost about
$700,000
Baltimore still has
7500 houses that need
To be demolished
The rest of the country there are millions more houses
That need to be known
A couple weeks ago I wrote Amtrak down to DC
And I looked for that block of North Bradford
Like I always do
But I missed it it like slid right by me
Because I was so used to looking for the houses
And the houses aren't there anymore
You can email us at Planet Money at npr.org or find us on Facebook or Twitter
Special thanks to Tanya Baker Michael Braverman Mabel old Jeff Carol and Jim rackauckas at thrive
Living community
That song you're hearing is take me back to Baltimore by Elizabeth Cotten and it's courtesy of Smithsonian folkways
You can find more information about it on our website npr.org money
Car show today was produced by Sally helm
What's up this week we're conducting a brief survey to learn more about you about people who are listening to Planet Money
A please visit npr.org
Planet Money survey completed
It would really help us out
Left up we've got a Bonus mini Planet Money episode I want to tell you about we just finished our big series on the American
Oil industry
But we have one extra story about aspirin yes aspirin
Aspirin is made from oil
Listen to NPR one app or at npr.org
Flash asp
I'm Noel King and I'm Jacob.
Thanks for listening
That's right
Ck2 want to know
All the way
That's right