Support for this NPR Podcast in the following message come from The UPS Store
Offering services from shredding to printing to mailbox
And instead of closing this Memorial Day we
May 24th and 25th
The UPS Store is doing another thing altogether
Opening
The UPS Store
Everything for small business
And of course shipping
Welcome to Planet Money I'm Stacey Vanek Smith and Robert Smith so
I don't know if you've heard but
Planet Money is a big deal
In the oil business
Last week we bought a hundred barrels of crude oil
Which works out to a little more than 4000 gallons of
Kansas wheat
Although the guy we bought it from ask for the price for Oklahoma sweet go back to episodes
If you want to hear
The most awkward negotiation in the
History of oil uar oil is stranded in a tank
In South Central Kansas
Because it rained and the people coming to pick up our oil
Could not make it on the money
But finally a shiny
Tanker truck
Holes into this muddy Road
Through a cornfield
And this guy
Scott Zimmerman
What do you do
How are you not covered in oil
You look clean the I don't see any oil on your you've been loading oil over
Well
You learn
When you first start out
When you go home you
Where moral home than U-Haul
And then over the years you learn how to stay clean
Part of it is
Rag management daubing up little bits of oil
Lot of rags
Scotch is the very first step
A long process of turning our crude oil hundred barrels of it fresh out of the ground
In the gasoline for your car
I always opened up the tank and we're going to
Open up Arlo blinds
Scott Putters around the truck
Well that what looks like a giant
Vacuum cleaner tube hooks it up to the tank
And we're going to kick our pump in an inch
Stop pulls out the oil refineries about 2 hours North
And so Scott could
Theoretically just drive
Right there and start processing Royal but
He doesn't do the
He heads in a different
Scott is driving to a play
Because the key to the oil business is to drive as little as poss
Type everything you can
It's slower
But it is much
Pipeline leaks
Sure but
Oil Trucks and rail cars getting more deadly EX
So we meet Scott at a place that isn't even on the map
Call Dasher station on the Jayhawk
And it is so real looking
Enormous gleaming White Tanks
Long shiny pipes going off in every direction
One of these pipes is going to carry our oil
Route to the CHS refinery in McPherson
The test
Scott tells us before you put Planet Money oil in the pipeline
He has to do a quality check
Because it's going to mix with all the other you know
Professional oil
Okay now we're going to get this sample right here
Skott porcelain little sample of Planet Money oil into a test tube
Any opens up this metal box attached to the side of his
And inside of it is something that looks like a rice cooker
Scott is traveling with his own Center
And then I put it in here and spend it out for 5 min
And what are you looking for
Beatrice boss
Settlement
And what is that dirt in Guk
Well
Just stepping oil layout
But it let you know whether they was good enough to buy
You got a really good VS sensor
There you go
Scott reaches in the box and flips switch
Diff oil does not pass this test then played it
Bunny is stuck in Kansas with 100 barrels of crappy crude
Hennessy what we got here
I am so nervous me too
See we're talkin about
Probably
710 tractor
So is that good or bad
Oh it is
So Caleb
Okay so he's not blown away by our oil it's not
A+ oil
But hey
It's good enough to get us in the pipeline
What's it mixes with the good stuff in Owatonna
Okay Robert
Should we say anything before the oil goes into the
Vitamin E oil
And now Stacy
We wait
It is 45 miles from here to McPherson Kansas
It's going to take
All night fart well together
The pipeline moves very slowly only about
3 miles an hour you could walk faster
Turn the oil but
Does me we have some time to kill now so
While we're waiting
Hear on the radio on the podcast
Stacy you and Alex goldmark are going to tell us a story a legend real
About
The man who changed it will business forever
You probably never heard his name
But you have definitely heard of
The thing that he accidentally invented
Fracking
As we know it today
We'd like to say a quick thank you and share a message from our planet money sponsor discover
You check things all the time like your email or social media
But discover asks what am I checking something as important as your credit score
Well discover makes it quick and easy with a Discover credit scorecard
Discover is the only major credit card to offer
FICO credit scores to everyone for free even if you're not a customer
And once you know your FICO credit score you should check to see if your current credit card is the best fit for you
Learn more at discover.com credit score card
Limitations apply
This whole process the planet money has been going through of buying or
If there's one thing we learned on this journey
It is that there are a lot of steps
And no one knows that better than the man behind the plan are senior producer Alex
Goldmark hey Alex Stacy more steps
Along the way then I can even possibly count
I wasn't worth it
What the whole process
All along the way
Has been fundamentally changed
By one man
My full name is Nicholas steinsberger
I'm 52 now so 1995 would have been 31
So the oil industry is legendary for these kind of aggressive swashbuckling Tycoon Thai
At least in the movies there's Daniel Day-Lewis From There Will Be Blood
Milkshake there's Jer Ewing from Dallas
Nick steinsberger is not
One of those people
Nick is an engineer
Quiet guy with a big smile
Turns red really easily
His car is super tight
It still has a new car smell
What Nick did that change the oil business forever
Is invented something called slick water fracking that's basically
Fracking
As we know it
And he showed me the spot where it all happened which is pretty much out in the middle of
So where we are between towns called of Justin and Ponder Texas which of the two small little towns in
And north of the Fort Worth area my think I'll ponder National Bank was robbed by Bonnie and Clyde back in the
30s I think so
And where we're sitting I guess
Where
Fracking was born so where the where the modern slickwater job was
Done success
By You By Me
Yes
Fracking is a charge
Has all of these
He's really emotional
Is there a visions of Environmental
Destruction earthquakes in Oklahoma stories of flammable tap water
And
There's this whole other side of
There's the big economic boom whole cities rising up out of the Prairie out of nowhere
Tens of thousands of high-paying jobs
An oil independent
It's for the US
All of this drama started out in the most boring possible way
Quiet engineer
Trying to save his job
I'm the least glamorous and
The oil business
It was 1995
Nick steinsberger was working for a company called Mitchell energy
He was 31 and he'd just gotten a big promotion
He was put in charge
200 oil and natural gas wells in Center
It was an area called the
The Barnett shale
Name for the shale rock where the gas and oil to paws
Were you in a suit
I think we had started to go to casual Fridays but we are still wearing
Coat and tie almost everyday
Nikwax
This big conference room with about 10 other men
And he's feeling pretty good he's the youngest guy there by a lot
But then one of the executive starts talking about the area that Nick has just been put in charge
The Barnett shale
And the executive says
We gotta get out of it
The Barnett was failing it was not an economic Venture and we probably we're not going to be doing it much longer
So a couple of months after you got promoted here they were like we think we're probably going to shut this down
Little depressed
I was thinking maybe my job isn't so Security will you thought you were going to get fired
The wells Nick was in charge of we're losing money
Getting natural gas out of the shale rock
It's way too expensive
Shell rock is basically like a dried
Sponge
He should have made out of some of the hardest rock on Earth
And all of those little pockets are filled with oil and natural gas
To get the gas Nick was drilling down a couple of miles
International Rock
And then blasting it
Part with this white
Gel consistency of a
Mike Snyder like jello I'm sorry
The gel shatters the little pockets in the spine
And let this
Tiny amount of oil and gas
Flow out
It's like
Trying to get a french fry That's Falling in between the car seats
Could get it but it's a lot of effort
Small reward
It's very colorful although I have to say If This Were Nick steinsberger scar
There would be no french fries no just the tidiest car in
Nobody wanted to put in that kind of effort on the Barnett shale
Exxon headquarters were just down the road from next well
Right on the Barnett Shale and they weren't doing anything
Think about it
Gregory Zuckerman is the author of The frackers
You could see that headquarters of Exxon the biggest all gas
Producer in this
Country is literally not figuratively literally
On top of the Barnett Shale and yet ExxonMobil was drilling anywhere but they're lit
Federal backyard they were off sure there were an Africa there an Asia and that was because conventional wisdom at
The time
Was don't waste your time
Trying to get gas
From Shell
Even in your backyard
So they knew that the shell was there
Yeah it would do the mystery that the thing was worth
Airtime
But it was worth Nick steins
He and his wife had a new baby and this is a rough time for the oil in
Layoffs were happening all over the place and Nick.
If I lose this job
I might not be able to get another
Silky weave the manager's meeting in Houston
He goes back to Fort Worth
And he decides that he is going to find a way
To save his job
Yunnan over the next
Dazor window at night and I was thinking
What can't what can I do
As an engineer thinks well you can become more efficient and cost-savings
Right where to trim
That chair
It was expensive
Made up of a ton of chemicals
Half the cost of fracking came from that Chow
The next idea
Just like a bar might start watering down the cocktails to stretch the liquor further
Nick started watering down
That job
He put in a little more water and a little less chemicals
So I'll keep on reducing the
Most amount of jail and Michael chemicals were pumping
Bye
Just making small squeaks every week or two
Ethnic added more water to the gel
He noticed something we
The wells with the water down gel
We're producing just as much Nacho
Gas as the wells with
Full strength gel
So
Pushing the envelope
Adding a little more water
A little more water
To do the actual Drilling
Nick contracts out to these big
Companies like Halliburton and Schlumberger
They're not fans of
Does watering down
Because
They sell
The gel and everytime Nick Waters it down
These companies sell
And so to make up for the money that they're losing from this water down gel
Nick says the company started charging him all kinds of new fees one Charger horsepower fee for the truck center
Equipment for putting on sights another company charge 89
Yelling face
Charging more
4 using less of their product
And then one day on one of the drill sites
These guys say now you've done it
You hit the ceiling
Too much water in
And now the gel
It's not yelling
And it got to be so I was head reduced in by so much that they were telling me that the product they were pumping down holes
Just a thick watery substance it just doesn't gel it's just
Sugar Waterfront so I didn't pump the jello I pump the non gel jello
Why did you decide to Pump It Anyway
Usher
I was mad at him
But
Yeah we're already on that we were already so close to their already
Set iso estrus pump it and see what happens basically
This was definitely kind of a Swagger E oil man
I drink your milkshake moment
Watching a real job is no joke
Drilling a well cost almost a million dollars
And nobody
Not even Nick
Thought the well would work without at least a little gel to crack the Rockabye
Here's the war
Conventional wisdom was that pumping too much water
Into the Barnett shale
Would make the clay down there
Swell up and become a big
Sliminess
Blocking all of those pockets of
Oil and gas and then nothing
Would come out at all
Anixter there
Super mad
And starting to get
He watched the drill team pump the super watered down non gel gel
And it was like the standoff
Joe Mixon guys are standing there getting ready for their big
Told You So moment
Nick is standing there
Braced for the big i-told-you-so moment
But
It never came
Even with the overwater jello
That will produce the same amount of gas
As the gel Wells
In fact
It produced a little bit more
Nick had no idea why the
But standing there
He had this yurikamome
What if we just use water
That would cut costs by a
Fifth Third we can add just a little bleach to kill the bacteria a little soap to make the water flow more easily down the pipes
And if we did that
The Barnett Shale Wells would be profitable no question and he could keep his job
He picked a well to test his theory on
So about 20 years ago today you were driving up
As we are right now to this well to see if you are idea had works
The well itself looks so underwhelming I know that it goes a couple of Miles underground but all
I can see it's just this little tangle of pipes sitting on a 20 by 10 gravel plot
Surrounded by a chain-link fence with a metal sign wire to it
The name of the sign says the s h Griffin number for you're still the Mitchell energy sign on it
That was their number for named after the family that sold
Total and it was June but kind of chilly and overcast and Nicorette Before Dawn put on jeans and
Can a hard hat and work boots
Gotham coffee
And arrived at the well
This whole area we're sitting on the three acres Ruben full of people and equipment and and sand water
Weather for
To do this job at that point you remember that day
What was it like there would have been
About 10 Frac pumps
Very big truck giant drilled thousands of feet long
Went down into sh Griffin number 4 and into the show
800000 gallons of Nick soapy water when he was calling slickwater were blasted into
And what did you see the pressure was going up and up and up and up and we're excited to the pressure valve
I was like the modern version of
Usher
I guess so
Nick is a reserved guy
But he told me
This was one of the biggest
Moments of his life
The gas started
Flow
And Flow
And flow tightly enclosed in tubes of course
Without any gel
The water had smashed the shell and created a gusher
NYX well-produced double what other way
Hydraulic fracturing
Fracking as we know it
Was in business
Right here
The world changed
I didn't know it realized the time but yes
No one could have realized
Set the time what a game
Fracking with water
Was way cheaper
It also produced
Way more natural gas
And they try the same technique on oil
Same result
20 years later the US is the largest producer of oil and natural gas
In the world
Because of rat
Nick's boss at Mitchell energy
Became a billionaire
Nick
Did not
In fact
He didn't even get a bonus seems unfair that
It's your invention
They were better businessman than Westbrook
Are the young engineer and
Had no idea about the business World about
I was in a very small a microcosm of that industry
I'm also quite as pretty quiet and
And Reserve so
You know a lot of people are
Bill industry has a lot of
Interesting characters in the end
And a lot of people are very outgoing very aggressive
In the meantime Nick was watching the world change
Because of his invention
When it started out his career in the early 90s
Everyone was talking about how the world was running out of oil
How the price was going to go up and up and up and
All of the problems that was going to cost
Nick's invention
Meant that there were enormous reserves of oil and gas
Right here beneath our feet that could be cheaply
Gregory Zuckerman the author of The frackers
Says it's almost impossible to overestimate
How much fracking
The consensus that we were running out of oil and gas this country
And we were going to be dependent
On nation that we really didn't want to depend on
For the future
And to think that it's a short number of years
We not only have this Surplus
Glut rashly
Exporting
Oil and gas from this country it's remarkable opens up all kinds of
Opportunities for us
Gregory says the whole Global power structure change
Saudi Arabia you're suddenly bringing in half as much money as you
You're Venezuela Rush up your whole economy is falling apart because oil prices are lower and the US is not
I find oil like a
Get used to
If you're in the US you got lots of jobs
Gas is cheaper and if you're an environmentalist this is really bad
Just starting with the issues of drilling in
Fracking has been linked to earthquakes in Oklahoma flammable tap water in Kentucky Nick says he's her.
All of these things people
Really hate tracking
I think
That's
Very disturbing to me I'm I am an environmentalist I'm a Boy Scout I love camping hiking I love
Living environment
And I'm not and I've been on thousands of Frank jobs
Frankie Muniz is a
Is misunderstood
No fracking with a k i
I just that bothers me because
Fracture stimulation does not have a K in that word but they put a K in it because it's
Quantified is also dirty word that way
Nick says the problems with Frac sites are overblown
And that fracking has really improved over the
But individual drill sites are not the real Environmental
Problem the real problem
Is what fracking
Has done to the price of
If you're an environmentalist
You want oil to be
To push us into alternative fuels
When gas is cheap
Will drive more people buy more SUVs there's no economic incentive
To change fracking took us from a world where we thought it was just going to be more and more expensive
To get that last little bit of oil out of the ground
But now it is opened up so many
New oil field
That the Alternatives solar and wind they just don't make as much economic sense anymore
Nix's
He doesn't look at it that way
Of all the potential issues or issues with it I think it creates so many benefits for our country both
Economically
The monitor jobs remote
Economic Revenue we've we've established here and
The security for our own country
Nick says he's proud to have invented
Is even made peace with the fact that
But he did not get rich
His invention
He's got his own consulting firm now
And a big family five kids
Nikki told me that if you could go back in time he would have been a little more aggressive
He would have quit Mitchell energy starting his own company
And grab some of the glory and money for himself
But as we were about to leave the oilfield Nick did something that
Totally surprised
He told me he really wanted to steal the sign
A metal sign
It was wired to the chain-link fence
The one that marks his first hydraulically fracked well
Sh Griffin number 4
I don't have any Flyers
Nick tells me he wants to put the sign in his living room
He tells me it's important to his soul and suddenly it's important to my
The Knick what's the time in Pennsylvania
In the end we could not get the sign off the fence
We had to leave it there
To say see the
Planet Money oil that you and Robert bought in a field and
That was not
But like every other well in this country in all the oil in America now
It was a fact
Goodbye next time
Because when fracking went big-time the amount of available oil in the US
More than double
Selling oil got a lot more competitive
And the price
That was good for us when we were buying LOL but we also have
How to sell
It'll eventually make its way to roof
Over the next couple episodes it'll get turned into Fuel and other products
But the refinery will not buy Direct
So say to you and Rob
Robert Smith called up
Else
My name is
Joshua way I'm with Ascent Midstream Partners
I'm a crude oil purchaser
So are you a middle man we always hear about the middleman my technically do
Take ownership of it but it's only for a fraction of a sec
Millisecond
Can you make a profit
Biotin oil for milliseconds
You can
Josh agreed to buy our hundred barrels of oil
And we were hoping to make a little profit off of
Or at least break even
So
We should probably talk
Price
So the price that we were looking to do for this Barrel is
$31.20 a barrel
Okay
That feels low
We paid Jason Bruns
The guy who drill their oil
We paid him $40 a barrel
Okay
We were starting to get the feeling that this was not
Going to go well
Just told us he could not give us $40 a barrel or even anything close to
And part of the problem was timing
Because in this market oil is bought and sold
Using a month
And we bought our oil it was July
29th
And we were using the price for July when we bought our oil from
But you might remember that huge storm
Blue and Kansas
And the roads got so muddy
Oil truck could not get in
We could not sell our
And by the time the roads right out
It was August
And the price for oil
With much lower
So when you were trying to sell our oil to Josh
We were looking at a much different
So I'm going to boil this down
It looks like we lost $820
It sounds like it'll
So you're telling me
Jason Bruns
Oilman and preacher Pastor on the weekends
Made out like a bandit off
I wouldn't say he made out like a bandit
He got a good deal
We also bought him lunch
Now depending on how much that lunch was he got a really good deal
A really good deal for August
Does anyway according
Josh
Are you saying if
It had not rain
And we could have gotten that oil out in July instead of August
Then
We would have made it better on this
And that's what happens a lot of times in this industry
Robert I think we've no business in the oil business is what I think we're a little bit curved
Well
Also that
So
We lost $800 on our oil deal but but
Are oil is in the system next time I'll send it money we follow our oil to the refinery and see what becomes of our hundred Barrel
He's got questions about our oil or want to tell us how we could have done a better deal negotiating for it send us an email
We are Planet Money at npr.org
Also we've been posting photos from our oil Journey you can check them out on Twitter and Facebook
The finest there
Today's episode was produced by Nick fat
Thanks Nick
And we want to thank Christian Kirk our comptroller at NPR who even knew we had a comptroller he had to deal with
All about regulatory filings incorporating Us in the state of Kansas to buy oil legally thank you
If you were looking for another podcast checkout NPR pop culture happy hour every week to talk about the latest movies
And books and TV shows never really interesting discussions with people like Trevor Noah and Shonda Rhimes you can check that out
On the NPR one app
Borat npr.org podcast
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith