I talked with a doctor in Venezuela the other day
Neurosurgeon
He's been working in the public hospitals in Caracas
For free
And recently he just
Had to quit
The conditions in the public Hospital
We're getting to Danger
I I didn't want to jeopardize anybody's life
Because of being responsive
I'm sure you've heard about the situation
In Venezuela right now
It's in the midst of this economic
Prices
Claps is probably a better word
There's almost no food on the shelves
The supermarket
Guitar riot
Inflation is estimated at 500%
And there are these rolling blackouts
Across the city
Which is a bad thing for neurosurgeon
I know colleagues who actually have ended their operation
With a flashlight that comes
In the cell phone
They've use that for
For surgery
Oh yeah 2
At at least to close a patient
It is inconceivable how they operate Hospital
In Venezuela
But they do
They just plant around the blackouts
And the water outages no water for hours at at
The time
And if you live in Caracas
And you have to go to the hospital you know
You should probably bring everything from home
There is essentially
Nothing there there no gloss
There no sutures
Patient has
To bring their own food their own gases
They have to bring their own
Food to the hospital
Absolutely
In in most of the hospitals there is not even
Food for the
Okay that yeah it is as dramatic as it sounds
Infant mortality is rising up 20% from last year
Diseases like tuberculosis
Malaria are coming
And the neurosurgeon says he would walk to the quarters the hospital
And see patients just
Lying on the floor on blankets
And I'm mattresses they brought from home
If you could even imagine
A war zone Hospital
This is even worse
Why
Because in a war you actually
Either didn't
Planet
You know it was something
That exploded
Happened was unpredictable
But this is something that could have been
Avoid
Long time ago with the rice
Political and economical
Venezuela designed their own collapse
Hello and welcome to Planet Money on Robert Smith
Venezuela used to be a relatively rich
Country it had money and prestige
And most importantly had oil
Venezuelans used to brag that they have the largest reserves of oil in the world
Today on the show we have an economic Horror Story what a country that made all the wrong decisions
Boil
It's a window into the fundamental way that money works and how when you try to control it
You can lose everything
Planet Money and the following message are made possible by Prezi business the better way to present if you're tired of selling to your car
Customers using the same old Exlines
Try Prezi business the engaging interactive presentation platform
It features built-in analytics cloud-based collaboration tools and the unique ability to adapt with the flow of Converse
Perhaps it's time to update your marketing and your professional reputation
With presentations customers will actually enjoy and remember
Schedule your free demo at prezi.com planet
A decade ago Venezuela was riding
So high it sweeter felt that he could take on United
States of America
This was Hugo Chavez
Former revolutionary but he had been elected president
Venezuela and how do you remember this in 2006 he came here to New York talk at the United Nations
President George Bush and just spoken at the UN the day before
Java stands there and he says
Baidu
The devil
This part of total street map
Baby crosses himself
He makes prayer hands
How many waves waiting says
I can still
Willie a suit for a Terraria
And everybody cracked up except
Probably George Bush
But it was kind of funny right
Back in those days Hugo Chavez made a sport of straight up
Trolling the United
Whenever you could
He would point out
How terribly the US was treating
It's poor
And how sad it
We
Venezuelan people
Loves you
We went I went to Bijou Brothers
And then he makes the people of the United States and offer
Venezuela has so much money and so much oil
We're going to give discounted heating oil to poor people in the US
The Venezuelan State owns an oil company and they prove it Citgo and they put out a bunch of ads in Boston and New York
Featuring Joe Kennedy
The United States
Look it up we are Venezuela We are the champions of the World by Joe Kennedy help is on the way heating oil
What's 40% off from our friends and Venezuela at Citgo
Mrs.
Google Java Style
Alright he uses oil money
YouTube I love
Listen to buy Power
The foundation for the collapse started as it always does
During the
Boomers
Travis wasn't big into saving any with oil money
Before
The day when it will run out
He was a socialist with a populist he wanted to spend
The money
Especially on programs for
Food subsidies
No education programs pretty much I was a time of economic Bonanza
Alejandro Velasco group in Caracas
He's a professor at NYU now
And he says all that oil money started to dominate the
Wheel was
By far the biggest X
Sport it paid most of the government's bills
And in the meantime everything else in the economy wilted
No one wanted to build a factory
No one wanted to grow food
Because the oil business was lucrative enough
Yeah when the country needed something it just bought it from
From someplace else
Why make it yourself when you can just
Buy the import with very cheap doll at Waimea Auto Parts
When you can buy auto parts
Why
Make sure milk
Anything
Anything absolutely ready made and I have to worry about having to go through all the procedures and you know
Investment domestically have to do they just
Buy from abroad
Friendship makes you huge the depending on him
City of a country that is living and breathing oilman
They would sell the oil
Which is priced in US dollars
10 converted
To be Venezuelan currency
Boulevard
And then every symptom of it is spent
The country running
Defeating clothing
And then all of a sudden
There's a problem
In 2003 the Oil Workers go on strike there is no oil there is no money
Minnesota desperately needed cash
Desperately need $2 to do everything anything that we've been talked about by imported it required right
Chavez freaks out
He has bills to pay
He's worried about his own currency
The Bolivar losing value
And so they keep the whole
Economy stable
He decides to
Fix
Exchange rate
Between the Boulevard and the dollar
Travis essentially said the value of our money is what I say
It is and if you want dollars
You have to come
To the government you have to come to me
Toomics
Financial sense it actually makes economic sense
As an emergency measure
What happened is that this measure was
Kept and maintained
Throughout even to today
And this
This was
The economic
Time bomb
Right even after the Oil Workers strike was settled
Thomas kept it so that every major transaction in the country
Still involved
The government
If you wanted dollars
You needed permission to have them
The government set the exchange rate the government could
Approve or reject
Any transaction
Here's Howe.
Alex Rosenberg was a clothing importer in Caracas
He brought in underwear
Jeans
Dress shirts
Love casual shoes
Sweaters jackets
Blazers
And with these have your name on them
I know they wouldn't
They would have a couple of brands on them
He was no Calvin Klein
None order to import clothing he needed to pay his
Suppliers in dollars
And in order to get the dollars from now to go to the government
Improve that he wanted to bring in something essential
So the government would give him
Zealous
They printed and Tire
Official Gazette
QuickBooks of
Yeah bucks code Mesa
Where you would check
Whether or not a particular material or a particular article of clothing
Had been centrally authorized
By the government
What is it alphabetical you go down you find underwear that you would you would find men's underwear made
8 out of polio
Lester cotton
Other fabric
And then
You would check in the book if the government deem this important enough
Tobias
Basically
I just believed you when you said oh there's a shipment of underwear out there no no you had to show them
Proof
That the underwear existed
Here's a picture of the underwear here's a picture of the brand here's what they're going to look like
Here's what they're made of and here's what they cost
And then you say I need
$10,000
And you say I need
X amount of
Yellow pieces of underwear a tax dollars
Totaling eczema
Exit node Noel
This is all for permission to spend his own money
Pain for the underwear
OSB Rock receives just to see if he could exchange his
Local Boulevard
$4
In this might seem insane
This might seem very insane
But as long as the price of oil with high
There weren't actually a lot of
Serious problem
The government would eventually give you
View your dollars
And your underwear came into the country and all was
Then two things happen
Number one
Hugo Chavez.
Mothers weeping children weeping adult men weeping
And the unluckiest man in the world takes his place
His name is Nicolas Maduro
He had been the foreign minister for Chavez for 8 years
And after all the drama and the excitement and the love of chavezz
Maduro was like it's it's like comparing a log of wood to the
To the circus that rolls into town
And then pour president log of wood
Gets hit with an axe
In 2014
The oil price
Oil price
Light switch be depended on
Drops like
The price drops in half
Over 6 MI
And this causes Panic within the Venezuelan government
Everything they have
Everything they do
Depends on oil money
And now they have half as much oil money
Took the new president Maduro goes to OPEC and he
KeyBank
We have to do some
We have to do something to keep oil prices up
Please help us
Countries like Norway in Saudi Arabia
Conceiving
Royal money
Nothing suelo
Not only are we not ready for this but there's nothing that we can do to stem the decline
What is the end of any kind of Boomers there's nothing that we can do now that isn't going to hurt
A tremendous amount
So what are they do
They did not
And every trap
Set by Hugo Chavez
Gets sprung at the same time
The first thing that happens is that the Venezuelan government all of a sudden has
Fewer US dollars
That spigot is turned off
So the government starts being stingy with them
There's a huge shortage of dollars
The price goes up
People were now willing to pay hundreds
The boulevard
For a single US dollar naira Black Market
Everywhere dealing in US Dollars yeah but the government insist on selling dollars
If the old rate which was around 6 Bolivars for a dollar
They don't want the price for basic things like food to go up there desperate to keep things
We know what happens when there are different prices in different markets the Venezuelan people aren't stupid they looked at this
At least I can buy a dollar for cheap from Venezuela government
And then sell it
On the black market
And make a fortune
Of course they started
And all Heather says
There was this amazing
Risperdal
Spouse
The scratch
Scratch
People would buy an airplane ticket
To New York
They would tell the government o
We really need dollars for our essential trip to New York
Put anyone travel
As you had the mystery of the airplanes that had all their seats sold but no one was riding on
But there's so much profit to be made you could just buy a plane ticket and not get on absolutely because you can make so much more
More from the black market rate of dollars
Now
Normally when this sort of thing starts
The country will eventually
Give up they will admit
Did their currency
Is screwed up
It's worthless
Are scamming them
And eventually don't let the exchange rates go back to
I'm not saying it's easy it is super painful.
To do with Venezuela
Had except
True
Exchange rate
Everything would have got more
Poor people that Chavez had cared so much about would not be able to afford milk
And Brad
The country would have to rebuild its industry
Rebuild its agriculture
10 things would have gotten better
But Venezuela decides to
To do exactly the off
Did any doubles down on its mistakes
Stephen did something which sounds so confusing they created different exchange rates for different people and different
Yeah and that it was confusing
They were more ways to scam
The government more ways to make money off these
Exchange rate
So the government thinks okay will print more money
Absolutely wrong
Inflation story
Okay so we'll stop reporting our inflation numbers or square numbers in fact
We will hide how badly the economy is doing but of course people figure it out they can see the prices for items in the store
Doors and the prices are going crazy
Okay so prices are going crazy we will mandate price control
What state you can only make
So much profit
This is even
Because businesses find that the losing money every month
Why
Keep selling products
You can't make any money
And even if you do make a little bit of money out of your business that money is increasingly worthless
Because of
The inflation
This is really bad for Venezuela
It is
Incredibly
Play bad and it becomes
Impossible to import
Anything I mean that's what happened to Ali
Clothing guy with the underwear right but his last big shipment was for something essential who's from medical supplies
We wanted to import a shipment of
Non woven fabric
Which is basically a blue fabric that's used for
Surgical
Also the stuff you see in the hospital if you wanted to bring in both of this so you can make
Yesterday
Yeah
Literally
The stuff
Did the neurosurgeon would have
Needed for search
To save people's lives
And Alex go to the government for approval
Spend dollars on it
And everyday
He waits for that approve
You go to your computer every morning once you get to the office
You open that system and you're like okay let's see if I hit the lottery today
And they've authorized my
And you're hitting refresh and just seeing like
No no no no no or no change in status
How long can you store
We're still waiting
To have those goods cleared and we still
Oh that money for suppliers
In NH
So Alex
Does
What he never wanted to do
He freezes
His business he steps
Away from her
And stop importing any
And this happens over and over and over again
With all of the things that Venezuela is important which is basically everything
Clothing and medicine and electronics and food
No one can get any dollars to bring anything into
And this is how Christ is
It's built out of
Simple
Economic growth
Without a real currency their massive
Shortages there
These dangerous Hospital
The government is cutting school days and office hours
Just to save electricity
And all of this
In a country that is still
Exporting oil it is still bringing in billions of dollars
And it is not enough to save
And no one seems to know what should happen next
This is a country in the middle of a political stalemate
Because no politician wants to do the DraStic things
Cindy would be drastic
That are going to be next
Passeri to fix
NYU Professor Alejandro says that everyone still just
Praying with the oil prices
Will go back up
More dollars we'll just
Solve everything
It's not like we don't know this story I'm in historian of Venezuela
I wrote about this
Premier Auto book about it
Right
And so
But we we
Just
Greeley cravos Good Times
And it seems like every time the bad times, we just say
Well at least sometime in the future
I have another good
Instead of fixing the problem
Which is at the whole economy is based on something volatile
And if you try to maintain control no matter what
You're going to lose it
Read the story part because we got a lot of emails about Venezuela we do
Read what you write to us so if you have a question about something in your world
Getting Top Planet Money at npr.org
In fact a couple of our Venezuelan listeners
Really helped us out with the show special thanks to Max arciniegas and Nelson Cohen
Also to Daniel lansberg Rodriguez
Our episode today was produced by Nick Fountain and Sally Helm thanks also to Alex goldmark I was
The coolest Jasmine cars wish the best of luck in her new job we miss you already Jasmine
And our intern Rainicorn
Also we're looking for the next
Planet Money intern is it you
Interns help out with every part of the show perhaps you've heard some of the voices on the podcast
For more information about how to apply go to our website npr.org
Buddy
Let's up if you're looking for another show to listen to check out fresh air
Toasted by the amazing Terry Gross
She recently interviewed the boss Bruce Springsteen
Talked about his childhood his very competitive relationship
His dad and how he formed his on-stage persona
That's the fresh air podcast find it on the NPR one app or whatever you get your podcast
Robert Smith