Support for NPR comes from investor.gov
Presenting this mess
When it comes to investing
We all have Quest
And investor.gov has answers
If you're free resource for
Tools tips and information about investing
Before you invest
Investor.gov
Scott Horsley
You are NPR's senior White House correspondent
Now that's senior but yes I spent the last eight years covering the Obama Administration and I've also been follow
Going to campaign in which Donald Trump promised to undo a great deal of what Barack Obama did over the last 8 years
He wants to roll back Obamacare he wants to build a
New wall on the US Southern border with Mexico
He wants to deport criminal immigrants
Drain the swamp of corruption in Washington
And undo what Trump calls
Stupid trade deals and that's just the first 100 days
Are you out there a lot of campaigns candidates say a lot of stuff on the campaign Trail a lot of it does get done some of it doesn't
But Turley Trump has filled out a bold agenda
He spelled it out in an address in Gettysburg right he sort of set for the plan for his first
Three or so months in office and time and as far as We Know
He sticking to that plan
That's right up there some stuff you can do in just a very first few days in office with the
The Stroke of a presidential pen
Other things he's going to need help from Congress and that could take a little bit longer
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Noel King
Today on the show
President
Trump we take a look at some of the things Donald Trump has said he wants to do in his first 100 days in office
And we ask
Kenny and will he really do them
Support for Planet Money in the following message come from wunder capital
Asking what if you could help combat global climate change and make money at the same time
Introducing wundercapital the award-winning online investment platform
It allows individuals to invest in solar energy projects across the US
Wonders online investment platform allows you to earn up to 8.5% annually
While diversifying your portfolio
Curbing pollution
And combating global climate change
And best of all wundercapital doesn't take any fees for investing your money
Create an account for free at Wonder capital.com Planet Money
Wunder capital
Do well
And do good
What is the biggest questions people have been asking about Trump's first 100 days in office
Has to do with the Affordable Care Act or Obamacare
Donald Trump talk a lot about wanting to repeal Obamacare on the campaign Trail it was one of his biggest campaign issue
We have a disaster
Cold
The big lie
Obamacare
We asked Stacey Vanek Smith to look into this to see if Trump actually can dismantle Obamacare within his first hundred
Days and if so how we go about it
Hey Stacy
Hi Scott
So for this question I called up Lynn Nichols he's a health Economist at George Mason University
And he spent most of his career researching Health Care reform and add
Educating for Universal
Bridge so he was a big supporter of the Affordable Care Act
In fact when he was watching the election results come in at home with his wife and daughter at the
Sitting around eating pizza
He said this one thought kept going through his head over and over
As the night wore on
What I saw Stacy was
Basically roughly
Play 25 years of my life
Being repudiated by half our nation
They seem to want to repeal
So I asked Randy from could undo Obamacare in his first 100
And he told me it wouldn't take anything near that long
If at all Trump would really have to do would be to drop the white houses
The peel of a lawsuit filed by House Republicans
A couple of years ago
In that lawsuit the House Republicans were saying the Obama Administration was
Spending tens of billions of dollars
Uncaused
Tatoosh Lake
Because Congress had not
Appropriated the money
That money is going to insurance
And if you took it away
Those insurance company some of them are already wary of the Obama Care Program
Mike Bolt
For good
Right and this year a Federal District Court ruled in favor of the house and the Obama Administration
Peeled
And that appeal is still in process
I mean Obamacare has been subject to multiple legal challenges over the last
6 years
And for the most part once they reach the higher courts
It has survived but that's because it had an aggressive Champion defending the program
Take away that aggressive champion and replace it with the
Donald Trump
Who's eager to see the law unraveled
Maybe very different
And when said if Trump wanted to he could simply
We dropped the white houses
Appeal of that
Jesus the case the house one in Federal District Court
And then Federal money would stop going to insurance come
So that means like he could basically shut off
Federal payments to
Insurance Company
Jessica
How soon like how soon can he do that
Long as it would take to file
A brief in court saying they were ending the appeal
Like a week or month
Certainly within a certain could be done within a week
So to be clear lens does not think that will happen
Been in fact Trump himself has said several times on the campaign Trail
But he's not just going to leave millions of Americans suddenly without health
What do you think will happen is that the Affordable Care Act
Slowly dismantled and replaced
With some of the plans Republicans have supported
Things like relaxing insurance company regulations when they're dealing across state lines
And also offering tax credits for
People for their health care
But let's be clear the Republicans have always been a lot more specific
Can talk about their plans to
Repeal Obamacare
Then about their plans to replace it with a plan of Their Own
If you take away Obamacare which
Provided insurance coverage
2 something like 20 million American
And replace it with something that offers coverage to a much smaller
You're talkin about still leaving millions of people who have coverage now
Without a yes exactly in in fact to cover all the people who would lose insurance
Under the Affordable Care Act
Would cost a lot
Of money
And Linden I think repair
Want to spend that kind of
Money after all
Expense was one of the main problems that Republican lawmakers
Have had with Obamacare
Thank you so much
Thanks guys
Okay Scott another big part of President Trump's plans for his first 100 days
I include something that he's calling the end illegal Immigration Act
End illegal Immigration Act
Yeah this was one of the greatest hits at Donald Trump rallies around the country where he talked about building that great big
Big beautiful wall on the US Southern border with Mexico and
Who's going to pay for it don't worry about it
Remember I said Mexico is paying for the wall
Mexico of course he said it is not
Paying for the wall
You know what I thought.
What's up
I thought let's
Stop arguing
Let's come together and just imagine that the money is
Because this will be a massive logistical undertaking
And I really wanted to know if that was at
Sleep posture
So I met this guy Todd sternfeld
Who thinks
This is possible
I'm the owner and CEO of Superior concrete products
Todd Mix Concrete and Todd build walls
And Todd has built walls all over the country
But he's in text
So when candidate Trump first said he wanted to build a wall
Todd sat down and he wrote Trump a letter
And I sent it to Eric Don and Ivanka all three of them
Dear mr. Trump
I have stated
Trump Hotel for the last several years while exhibiting my products and services
At the World of Concrete Show in Las Vegas
Your staff and the accommodation have always been superb
He told Trump what he could do walleyes
Trump didn't write back
Todd sent a second letter he hasn't gotten a response yet
But here's the thing Todd who knows a thing or two about concrete and walls has actually
Done some arithmetic about what it would take to wall off the US Southern border
How can I the first big hurdle would be
There are people along the border who owns some of this land
Who might not want a big wall going up on their proper
For that
Todd has a solution
Vectra eminent domain situation
Federal government
Or the state government has eminent domain over properties
Eminent domain of course means
Seizing people's land
This is not a popular option Republicans in particular are usually opposed to the idea of the government taking over
Private property for some ostensible public
What purpose
Wake me up to get around that
The next challenge a massive surveying operate
You got to know what your building on
Duchess that would take two months
But he thinks it's doable
Few months a lot of people
Once the surveying is all set now comes the building
The Conch
And this is the part that Todd loves and the part that Todd does
A thousand miles long
42 V
A foot high walls
How much concrete we talking about
* 1000
Tod calculator
5 million
Lineal feet
This part took him a couple of minutes there was lots of typing he was muttering numbers
It would be about 250 thousand truckloads of you know the concrete trucks
It would be about 200
50000 of those trucks
Just to make the product
Just to make the wall
Yeah and if you could build a wall to concrete you need to reinforce it so there's
Some steel rebar you need as well materials
The challenge here obviously is the scale of this Singh 1000 miles
When we first started talking
Todd sounded like he had it entirely under control
But the longer we kept talking
What's the longest wall you've ever built
The longest wall that I've ever built
Was about
Who am I
4 MI
But the border wall is 1000 MI
The sky understand
But you think you could do it
Yes I can do it
How much would it cost
I mean you know
If it put it this way if it's done that the amount of money that it would cost would just be astronomical
How much is astronomical Mexico pay for it
So he's having Mexico pay for it he might have Mexico build
That wouldn't help you would it
I have my business and I'm not going to
Very successful at
You bet
Scott he has other walls to build
Noel by point out is it there is already fencing or walls along more populated section
Of the u.s. Mexico border I used to live in San Diego or we had a
Pretty impressive triple fence
Between San Diego and Tijuana Mex
Chicago
In fact I remember covering up legal case of
I want the companies that help build that fence
They were being prosecuted for using illegal immigrant labor to do something
Construction Scott would Donald Trump be okay with just defense or does he want to walk
He talks about it as being a wall although at one of his advisers Newt Gingrich
Said this week that
He's going to focus a lot of time on
Securing the Border
Just what shape that takes is
Like everything subject
Negotiation
Another thing that is still to be determined and is
Probably going to be the biggest negotiation
Is a is Donald Trump's threat to pull out of NAFTA
NAFTA North American free trade agreement is a 20 + year old trade deal between the US
Mexico and
Canada
Trump says it's a terrible deal and he wants to renegotiate with Mexico and Canada to get a better one
Or else
He said he's going to pull out
So we asked Jess Jiang
Going to go on a quest this week to figure out
Can Donald Trump do that
So I started with Chris Wilson he's from the Wilson Center
And he's devoted his career.
Studying the relationship between the United States
On the surface
It's not very complicated
The NAFTA agreement and actually have it right here in front of me is about 1000 pages long
Article 2205 is the section withdrawal and it's only three lines long
So I can just read it for you a party May withdraw from this agreement 6 months after it provides written notice of withdrawal
Talk to the other parties
If a party withdraws the agreement shall remain in force for the remaining party
That's all that NAFTA itself says
1000 pages and that's it
Send us a note and you're out
Peace out
Seems easy
Happen all the time
When's the last time the US
Has done some
Nothing like this has
Is left
The last time is never
The United States has never done anything like this
Okay so maybe we've never left
The Free Trade Agreement
Before but
What about other kinds
For that question I went to Curtis Bradley
She's a professor of international law
She says
The US has left
These before
Defense treaty
But this was not without controversy
And for the president
It got kind of
The most famous one is when President Jimmy Carter withdrew the United States from a defense treaty with Taiwan
And it was highly controversial in Congress
And there was a challenge
Carter's actions
Brought by members of Congress
So members of Congress to be sued the president
They did
Members of Congress I think both in the house and the Senate
Suit Carter
And that case went all the way up to the US Supreme Court politicians were suing each other over
Who has the power to
To cancel a treaty
Is it constitutional for the president to just
Do this alone without Congress
And the question went to the Supreme Court
Baby sleep bed
This is too political no one was harmed
We won't answer.
I don't even know the Supreme Court could do that just take a pass
They were like
You don't want to get in the middle of it
It has never decided whether it's constitutional for the president to leave a treaty without Congress
And if Trump pleads NAFTA there could easily be another lawsuit
What's interesting about NASA is it pretty easy to imagine private parties
Importers for example companies
Bringing a lawsuit
Against Trump
Imagining like a car factory in the US
That buys parts from
From Mexico exactly and now they will have to pay more or their business will suffer in some other
Way there could be lawsuits Galore
Every manufacturer in the US that might have to pay a little bit more because
Cuz they can no longer get
Cheap parts
Mexico
They could sue or even a person cuz
Like me
Are you sad
So Kevin, consumer and my I don't know imported tequila cost more because
No water coming in free of terrace
I could bring a complaint
Ukiah died
Would want to ask
You how much tequila are you
Drinking
That you would actually want to see
The president by
Yes if you can prove you've been legitimately harmed
Then yes
Yes you could
And so we might finally get a definitive answer
The question of whether the president has the power to
Cancel NAFTA
All on his
Wouldn't there be a chance though that Supreme Court would just
Again steer clear this
Some say it's not up to us
Weather
The president
Congress unravels a tree
Yes they could always
Punted back
Congress and the president
To work out
And that could be interesting because there are a lot of Republican leaders in
In Congress who are much more
Supportive of free trade
President Donald Trump and
His populist
Yes but
Also with this new wave of populism
Congress can decide
We want to be against
Free trade and if Congress and the president
Gree knocked out will be
Wow
Precious
Trump has also talked about what he calls
Draining the swamp
We will drain the swamp
In Washington DC and replace it
With the new government of
By and for
The people
Hillary Scott the swamp is shorthand for this idea that
There is a
Corrupt group that
Doing favors for each other in Washington
The swamp monsters in this case
They are lobbying
On the topic of lobbyists Trump has also said he supports this
A 5-year ban
On White House and Congressional officials becoming lobbyists after they leave government service
Making a fortune
Alex goldmark has been looking into this house
Hi ya so this all seems logical enough
Like who wants
Big money
Are there friends
Whisper into the ears
Yeah it makes sense
And it's so much I said it's one of those things that
The good government reform types in washer
Are always asking for and they just never seem to go
So I can put them up
I would say we would definitely want to get government circles or reform Circle
That's what you hang out with in Washington
What are the four friends from different areas but yes
Larry Noble is general counsel of the
The campaign Legal Center
And before that the Federal
Little bit
Was
So he knows this
What did he say
Trump can put some restrictions on lobbying
Pretty easily
I'll have to do
Is make his staff sign a pledge not to laugh
For five years
And he can make it legally binding he can just back it up with an executive order
Which if you're the president
Pretty easy to do
Just write it up and sign it
Record
There is a catch
Trump is not the first person
Detritus
President Obama also signed an executive orders
That was limiting
Lobbyist in Hindi
And he put restrictions
I'm hiring lobbyists into his administration and a hookah Lobby
After they lie
Yeah I'm in a Barbra Streisand
He came into office
We talkin about broadband
Lobbyists out
And they started me leaving out exemptions
Is there pretty quickly
Exemption
To be able to get
The best people Obama wanted
War lobbyist
There weren't enough people willing to take the job once he ruled out
Okay so this is the swamp that Trump is talking
Government jobs
Pay all that much lobbying
A lot
The best people they tend to like
Paid a lot
Meanwhile the White House has
Hundreds of jobs
And thousands in The Wider
So
You kind of limit the candidate pool when you say
Okay but what about the second part could Trump really stop a congressperson from leaving government
And then just becoming a lobbyist
A year later
Another one of those sensible sounding ideas but it is even harder
To pull off Larry Noble says
Because he
I can't use the pledge
He doesn't
Congress
He got to have a lot
Which Larry Noble said does not lie
And your Congress has been historically reluctant
To limit
What its members can do when they leave office
Inshort Trump
Is going to have a heart
Stopping people from getting rich
As a matter of fact
Yesterday a document started circulating around Washington
DC
It had the names of
People who are going to be on Donald
Transition team
And it was filled
With lobbyists
Alex goldmark thank you so much
You got it Sekulow thanks.
I just say drain the swamp
Raining in lobbyist that was kind of a late addition
To the Donald Trump repertoire promises not necessarily as high a priority
As the things he was talking about throughout the camp
And one thing you talked about from the very first day when he
Glided down the escalator at Trump Tower in New York City
What's the take a
Hardline
Against people living in this country illegally
He singled out those
Food come from Mexico
You said they were rape
I'm drug dealer
He refined his plan
Ford supporting undocumented immigrants
In October
We will begin removing the more than 2 million criminal illegal immigrants from the country
These are drug dealers
Gang heads gang members
Killers
I just got the first thing is that number 2 million
Immigration experts don't actually know where Donald Trump got that number from
I talked to a handful of people they said there is an agreed-upon number
It's about 820000 undocumented immigrants with
Criminal record
But in this case let's give Trump the benefit of
If you wanted to deport 2 million
What would you do
On day one
To answer this I spoke to Ben gettis he's with the American action Forum which is a center-right policy group
And I called them because they've done a bunch of reports looking into
Exactly
Step 1 Step 2 Step 3 what would need to happen
And then how much it would cost
Invented the first Big Challenge
Actually finding peep
This is not as easy
Easy as it may sound
If you want a good illustration of that
Listen to the way
We are often currently finding a document
The vast majority of apprehensions happen
Local law enforcement
Meaning somebody gets picked up in a traffic
Yeah that's my understanding
Define people
More easily
A1 auction
Is to set up
Checkpoints in a bunch of people brought the
Stop these would be
Checkpoints where any one of us could be questioned and asked
To show identification
Trump has said he'd like to increase the number of immigration custom enforcement officials from 5000
To 15000
You need to hire an
And train those people then says it could cost anywhere from 8 billion
243 billion dollars
Which is a mess
Spread I mean to speak different
Between 8 and 43
3 billion
Euskara learned it the hard part here when we ask how much
Going to cost
We can only base our numbers on the numbers
We have now
So you know that it's a height of
Deportation
We
Center around 400 thousand
People out of
The country
Dennis doing his math based on that number
400001 year Well Trump + 2 million +
2 years
Multiply that by 5
But in between the time
You catch somebody who's leaving the country illegally and has a criminal record and the time you send them back to their home country
Do you have to detain them
How's it feel
Jade garden
Once you've apprehended the folks and you put them in a Detention Center there still some due process
To get through
But then Ben get us told us
The last step is actually sending people back to their home
That's easy right by everyone a bus ticket
I'm not that simple while about half of undocumented immigrants are from Mexico
The other half are from
All over the world
And I would require
Chartering flights
Places like that
America
Africa Asia
All over the
Ben says if you do the math on those two million flights that gets you up into the billions of
Of dollars
Which God actually brings us back to something I heard from everyone I talked to
Yes this plan is
Legal
Yes this plan is probably
Doable
It would take much more time and much more money
Then husband
This is a bold and flashy agenda that Donald Trump is laid out
He's known for bold and flashy
He projects many of them
Costly
But as you say if you
Have the wheel
You could probably do a lot of this stuff
Hey guys if you got a question on president-elect Trump's first 100 days in office
And we didn't get to it today
Send it over
Wet Planet Money at npr.org or you can find us on Facebook or Twitter
And now that the election is over maybe you're looking to fill the void left by all those daily politic
Tech podcast
How about some music
The all songs considered podcast from NPR music is
Here to help
It's filled with
Discussions about music and musical discoveries
As host Bob boilen and Robin Hilton share the best new music out
That's all songs considered every Tuesday on the NPR one app
Aurat npr.org
Slash podcast
Today's episode was produced by Sally helm
With help from Alyssa
Speculaas
Thank you ladies
Special things today to Alex Weinberg Michael dorf Gary hufbauer
Robert Lawrence
Our intern Rena Cohen
And of course NPR White House correspondent
Scott Horsley thank you Scott
Good to be with you
I'm Noel King
And it's gone
Thanks for listen
Support for this podcast
Send the following message
Which come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities to help ensure a brighter future for America
Just children more information is available at aecf. Org