Support for NPR comes from investor.gov
Presenting this mess
When it comes to investing
We all have Quest
And investor.gov has answers
If you're free resource for tools
Tips and information about investing
Before you invest
Investor.gov
Ghosting
The other day you and I went to Walmart
We got Peppers apples
Bread
I got a Halloween card
We are there cuz we're doing a story about self
We wanted to find out could we make it
Through self-checkout
One time just one time
Without getting some kind of
Error message
We were there with Howard Schneider
He lives a couple blocks away from this
Particular Walmart
And we were shopping there with him because he's kind of an expert on self checkout
It was Pucci right everything was going fine
Until we hit the red bell pepper
Maybe it's under red
You're scrolling through the pages looking for the right thing
Red peppers
D4 bell pepper
No peppers
It was not be for Bell Peppers doesn't even say what to do so then you're stuck here right now
Does even say get help or anything
And Felton would probably still be standing there trying to figure this out
But for the fact that Howard went and got a store employee who walked over and saved us by typing in the code for pepper
She just knew the number in Iran
The fact that the we have to call the attendant to process is little order
Expense is a failure really shouldn't happen and the Machine should deal with situations like that and why is self checkout a big
Guilty you
Because I invented it right one when did they
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Nick found
And I'm Jacob
Today on the show how an emergency room doctor created the first self-checkout machine in his spare time
Also
Why does self checkout still
Stop
Support for today's episode of Planet Money and the following message
Come from Audible
Who has more than 250 thousand audio programs from leading audiobook Publishers and business information providers
Including presents
Bringing your boldest self to your biggest challenge
By Amy Cuddy
Audible is offering Planet Money listeners a free 30-day trial membership
And a free audiobook
To get started
Go to audible.com Planet Money
And start listening
Anytime
Any place
Before we went shopping at Walmart with Howard Stern
We went to his office to me
He's a doctor you practice Tai Chi
And his office is in this old shopping mall on the edge of Toronto
What he was telling us how to get there he said okay my office is upstairs from The Pickle Barrel restaurant
And Brake near this room where people come to play cards
It sprinkled Hazel's Bridge
Think is that
Hello
Is that there is a computer
It says please check in here
Snow person
Flight self check in
There's the standard beige counter where the receptionist with normal
There's no reception
There's no paper
Tablet computer facing
Yes so we go up to that computer
Start popping through the check-in
Please answer questions before you see doctor
Schneider
Do you have an appointment this person yes
I have told the person.
Is a great to see you and or interact with you please wait a few seconds
Okay
And then Howard Walker
Hello hello
How are things late 50s he's got glasses curly hair
Black pants black polo
Blue Spa
And there's something about Howard we like you can tell there's
There's this gap between what's going on on the outside
And what's going on in his head
There's alot going on in
Yeah
So we started out with those those initial to cry
How did the doctor invent self-checkout innosphere time and Nick your question why does self checkout
Still suck
And now I got another
Which is
Why is the guy who invented self check
Check out this thing used in grocery stores all around the world
Was he working in a little office across from a bridge club in an old Mall in
We crowded into this room behind the empty receptionist area
And Howard told us
He said he always liked playing with computers tinkering with stuff
It was MIT studying engineering then came back to Canada for med school
He wound up working in an emergency room
Singh psychiatry
I'd see an average for boat
810 ambulances
Sometimes walk-ins in in the yard per day
You don't need start really started you start thinking I mean you know what's really what's going on in the brain
Have you seen all this psychiatry
If he starts thinking about
Cognition about what it means to think
At the same time you still interested in
Computers
Suigetsu this side project
Start
Dreaming up a computer that can think
And this isn't just some like abstract age
Actually
Lights out in like great detail his plan for how this is going to
Silicon-based circuitry
Interconnected by 5 billion vertical interconnecting wires
You say 5 billion wires
5 billion vertical wires but there's trillions of other wires
He submits this paper to this big NASA conference and his paper gets accepted he flies down to DC talk to a bunch of really smart
Scientist
But there's one problem
So is this a thing anyone could actually built
It hasn't been built yet essentially even though he's written it all down this is still some wild idea of some
Computer with
Williams of wires and you know it's just a dream
It's frustrating I mean Howard is a tinker
You know he likes
Building stuff he wants to come up with something that he can actually build in the real world
Around this time it's a ladies
ATMs are starting to be wise
And IBM in these other companies besides they're going to solve the next big problem
Grocery store checkout
At the Howard it's like this weird challenge that he
He takes kind of person
He goes and tells his wife
This is my big project
My wife says you've never even gone to the grocery refuse to go shopping your you hate you you get very upset going to shopping malls
Howard our hero is not deterred
He walks over to his neighborhood Supermarket to get some date
And I had a clipboard
I had a stopwatch mechanical want you got the mechanical stopwatch like tick tick tick tick tick
Sitting here at the supermarket
Supermarket cashier isn't just some simple robot like
Being a cashier is more complicated than it seems
Supermarkets are missing varmints you have things for the barcodes your produce you have people trying to steal things people
Give me this make change do this
And that's a huge
Leap and cognition to go from Banking Machine
Replacing the person in the supermarket
Power thought
Okay this is difficult
But it's also exciting
Here's the thing I can actually build
And it combines all the cognition stuff that I've been thinking about the hospital and all the computer stuff that
I've been working on his well
So he said to work
Takes all the money that him and his wife have saved up
About $50,000 at the time
It starts to build a prototype
And some pieces are pretty faithful
You know reading barcodes
Scanner
Taking a payment there's a machine that does that meant to do those things
A computer doesn't need to be aware
You know it just needs to do with a computer does
But there is a place where the computer
Does need to be
Doesn't
Yeah it's Steph
Right people steal is here I'm just going to walk out with half the stuff in my car
This is a very hard
Technical design problem
You know it's like if you're building this machine you got the sort of
Diles youku
Contritely
You can make it
Really easy to steal stuff and then people are just going to
Fuel stuff or you can make it really hard to steal stuff but then you're going to end up
Using lots of honest people of trying to steal stuff
Why I hate
Self checkout right
It's that live unexpected item in the bag
Area that phrases
Burned into my memory
And then
Then there's that moment right
Just shopping and there's a big lot of people behind you and you're trying to find red bell pepper on that little
But you just want to be done so you pick
Green pepper
You might save a buck
And is it stealing
I don't know
Yes yes
Feel it still
Howard Schneider is confronting all of these
Problems
She's trying to build a
And people around this time have already for
Figured out that you can put a scale in the bagging area
Try to prevent
Yeah and the reason behind that is simple right they want to make sure that people
Don't put stuff in their bags and walk away with them that they haven't scared
It's a simple idea but Howard found that it's a really hard technical problem to solve
Afrofuturism partly it's because
Stuff at the grocery store comes in this huge range of weight
Esl greeting cards
Hyundai South 40 lb of flour or potatoes
So how it has a scale
Custom built that can handle everything
But even then he has another problem
And that's that the weight of the same kind of items
Lincoln Berry
You know the loaves of bread they make at the store
A little bit bigger or heavier on some days in a little bit later on other day
Howard programs is machine to figure this out to
You actually learn as it goes along
How to machine seen the loaf of bread a few times and realizes wow bread can
Sorry on the other hand Coca-Cola they're pretty good
The Coke cans are within you know within with anagrammer to each time
It's not perfect
Obviously but it's good enough
He puts it all together
The good enough scale the scanner the monitor
And he's got his machine
He's ready for it to take over the
Howard showed us a picture of this
August 1st machine
And it's really striking it looks almost
Exactly like self-checkout machines still look today
Howard still doesn't quit his day job you still working at the ER but he does turn his self-checkout hobby into an actual come
He calls it optimal robotics very nineties any starts going around
Pictures of groceries
To get the meeting at a New England supermarket chain called
Stop & Shop
So he drives down
Give this presentation in this board room full of
And at the head of the table there's this execu
Who everybody is looking
This old guy sitting at the head of a table on you know he's his son
You know why people shop at Stop & Shop I said no he says
Because of our people
Because we're people that everybody around the table starts nodding their head and he says do you think people want to come in
And speaker machine
Do you know anything about retail you know anything and he says I don't think it's for us and everybody around the table not of the
Their head
And I drove back to Montreal with my tail between my legs and it was just
Horrible feeling thinking this is the stupidest thing I've ever done
Nobody will ever lie
Like it or ever use it
But Howard keeps
Loading his machine into the back of this rented Ryder truck
Keep throwing a supermarket trade shows
And eventually he gets a meeting with a supermarket chain called Price Chopper
Spaced in Upstate New
It needs a head person actually saw the machine
I need to know he said he looked at he says I like it
What's the weather
And I guess what after that everybody is very nice
CEO says
We're not going to buy the machines
But you can use one of our stores in Upstate New York
As a real world
And on August
V 1990
U2
Grocery store shoppers use
What maybe
Depending on your definition I mean we what we are going to call
The first
Fully automatic self check
What Howard gets to the supermarket that day
He sees that there are protests
Who's there
It's the cashiers Union
They're saying
These machines are
Taking our jobs
How to rid of this quotation from a union rep at a time
Immune rap basically said
The thing that I think about all the time
These machines are forcing customers to do more
Quote maybe if the customers come early
They can unload the truck and stock the shelves
No I mean like
There is a serious question underneath it right which is like
Are these machines taking people's jobs
But but
The answer is very anticlimactic let me tell you what happened at Price Chopper the machines went in people use them
And they didn't work
It crashed
It stopped working and then people have shopping carts half unloaded and everything
The story is full of angry shopper
And Howard
He just sitting there in the middle of all this chaos unscrewing the back of the machine
So that he can restart it
And the union they figure they've got nothing to worry about
They pack up their protest
And weave
BATA store manager his name is Rick
He's not happy
He says I don't know if these machines crash on throwing out of my store literally
I said it will work
I have no idea why this happened that shouldn't have happened
Machines are perfect
Amy
Those two statements it will work and I have no idea where this happened to sort of at odds with
Howard stays up all night
Sitting on the grocery store
Fixing the code
He says he can still remember smelling the cinnamon buns there bacon in the back of the store while he's sitting there trying to figure out
And the next day his machines didn't
But the Shoppers and the machines they still needed a lot of hair
In fact they need so much help that Howard has to invent something
Justin just the person who stands there next to the self-checkout
Helping the customers in pics
We drill some holes in the cabinet so that if you have to reset the machine because
Just took the long screwdriver in and hit the reset button so we give him a long screwdriver
And and and he was very friendly very nice with people and he would like he'd help them through the orders and they made a huge difference
It's clunky but it's working
The machines are getting better
And then Howard gets what looks like it's going to be his big
Break Kroger one of the biggest Supermarket chains in the country
To start buying his machine
Penny stocks
Dreaming of this very big
Future
We asked him back then when you imagine the grocery store of the future when you imagine the grocery store of Sade
What did it look
So in that in that grocery store of of your imagination
Are there any human being stocking the shelves
No are there any human beings
I doing check out the cashier snow
Are there any human beings working there at all
Yeah yeah
Do you have to have so much people taking care of the machines and feeling
Somebody wants to see humans with a human can
Come see them maybe one maybe one token human
More than that we don't like these word token
So here we are it's 2016
And the grocery store of the future looks
A lot like the grocery store the path
It looks basically like grocery stores looked in 1992
About 90% of
Checkout Lanes in US grocery stores are still managed by Q
What went wrong
Yeah we talked to a few people
And a lot of things that Howard was dealing with in the early 90s are still big problems today
Just last week there was a
The story about a police Crackdown in Australia
And Shoppers stealing stuff
At self-checkout
There is apparently this one store in sweded that's
Entirely autumn
But like of course yes we know Sweden
You are perfect
You've never stolen anything
Not going to happen to the rest of the
The rest of the world
There is a place where self checkout
In fact it's so good that we don't even think about it as self check
I'm on
You know every time you buy something from Amazon
You go through self
There is no cashier
Edits
Super
Easy it's also really hard to steal from him
True
I mean you could say sure sure self checkout from Amazon
You know they don't have to deal with the
They're not asking you to look up a bell pepper that
Doesn't seem to exist in their system
But that is my point it works it doesn't have all of these problems
You know when you think about grocery stores
I think there's a good chance that it will continue to suck
For as long as it feels like self-checkout for as long as it feels like
You are doing this work this thing that a person
I mean pretty clearly I think in the long run
The real solution is not a better self checkout machine
It's no checkout at all
We ran this idea by Dusty Lutz
He runs the self-checkout group at NCR
That's the corporation formerly known as National cash register
Dusty what is
Kind of a big deal in the self check
In fact he was in the room
When they came up with what is
Probably the most famous phrase in self-checkout
As I remember very clearly the day we actually came up with that because we're trying to figure out how
How do we communicate that you might be stealing something
But you might not be stealing something so how do we communicate that and there were many many things like stop thief
Remove this item
Don't steal this from us but but in the end
You're not fooling anybody
Where watch
Yes
He said there are already some stores where you can pick up a scanner when you walk in
And scan your stuff as you walked
After the store
But that he said is just a transition
Here's what the store the few
Do you walk in the store you pick up your items you walk out
No cash
That's right
You've already registered your phone with
The store so they know who you are and every time you pull something off the shelf there's some tag on the item or some camera that recognizes
Exactly what you're putting in your car
And when you walk out the door the store charges everything that's in your cart to your credit card
And you think that'll actually happen
That will happen
Yeah the questions will that happen in 2020 or that happen in 2013
So that is the past present and future
I'm selfish
There is one less
Why is the guy who invented Aldi
Howard Schneider
Still working in a little office across from a bridge club in a mall in
How old is really good at thinking about the
And he's really good at tinkering with mushy
But he's not really good with thinking about money
Howard told us back in the mid-90s
Is just as he was getting this big order from Kroger that was going to be his big break
He had this realization
I said well you know if I start buying more parts I'm bankrupt I couldn't afford anything
You know my wife's name
You spend every sense of these every since I made an emergency room I spent on that
You don't we had a one-year-old son like she
No money for milk this is me know what kind of father are you what's going on and I realize you know what have I done is I solved all these problems but I guess
Guess I didn't really do the financial Cromwell enough
We should say we asked Howard if we
We could talk with his wife
She said she didn't want to talk
Justice Howard was about to run out of money
An old friend of his depth
Basically save the company
Raise the bunch of money
Howard told us he was embarrassed
By his financial failure
He told us he felt like it wasn't really his company
Any left 1995
He sold his stake in the company
Says he got enough money to buy a nice house in a nice car in Toronto
And that was it for him in the
In 2004
The company that Howard had found
It sold for 30
Howard says he regrets leaving when
And not really because of
He really doesn't seem to
Care about the money
The reason is he thinks if he stayed
He could have built a lot more stuff
You would go to the airport and would they be all my machines you go to restaurant my machines would be everywhere
Lately Howard has been working on a New Prague
He calls it the dock
It's a chair
You sit in it and it takes your vital signs
Shenzhen to compete
He built this prototype in this like
Egg-shaped chairs white plastic on the outside
Red velvet on the inside it looks like a chair from The Jetsons
While we were visiting our decided
You look happy
We do love a good origin story here if you got one some Gadget in everyday life
If it has an interesting or surprising story behind it
Tell us about it people do show
You can email us at Planet Money at npr.org
Or you can find us on Facebook or Twitter
We're at Planet Money
And Nick Fountain and Jacobs
If you're looking for something else to listen to
Listen to The Fresh Air podcast to scrape fresh air but you can listen to it anytime you want
Recently Terry Gross interview David fahrenthold of the Washington
Post has been doing really interesting work
Looking into the Trump Foundation
Finances
You can find the fresh air podcast on the NPR one app
At npr.org podcasts or wherever you get
Take the Neil wessler and thanks
Producer Elizabeth cool-ass
And also thanks to our intern Rayna Cohen
We're actually accepting intern applications right now we're looking for one for the winter and spring semester
I once was an NPR intern
You should be one too
Find out more about it on our website
I'm the fountain and I'm Jacob Goldstein thanks for listening