And I can't use bad language on your program
Can I have the weather
Wearing a Nobel Laureate uses bad language on the show today
On the morning that the Nobel Prize
In economics was awarded this year I got up really early
I'm so excited I I
I pick up my phone
Open it check it and
The Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences
Has decided
To award the various Rick
Spark prize in economic Sciences
In memory of Alfred Nobel
Oliver Hart
Ambank Alstrom
For their contributions
To contract
Theory
And
I went back to bed
Contract theory tours they don't even sound good separately contract and you got theories like a lose-lose
Planning on skipping
No we don't have to do a show every year on the Nobel Prize
Robert you have this
Yeah
Tim Harford
Economist lives in the UK Big Planet Money All Star wrote the book undercover Economist we love him
He just happened to be in town
The same week econ Nobel was giving up and just wrote a book called
Messi
Edit
Clever ways to be
More creative it's about finding new techniques to solve
Old difficult problem
Which is what we had with the Nobel Prize
So we has Hartford
Can you be our adviser
You know we don't want you to explain the Nobel
But we want you to give us some like creative techniques we can use so we can explain the Nobel in some kind of a fun interesting
Creative way
It's difficult because this year it's really mathematical
Really inside baseball
And also
Everybody comes out with a really quick take on what these guys did
Why they won the prize
Until you feel coming late to a really difficult story that everyone's already done
Wow will you put it that way
More out than ever
So
See what my help is it because I am now a creative Guru yes
Tim Harford redo
Watch out
So they awarded them the price you want to send a Swedish accent no
Good choice
Hello
Show we use mystical magical techniques to unleash the creativity living with anusol
Slash to talk about contract theory in the econ Nobel
Which also has a little magic inside
Support for this
Broadcast in the following message come from transferwise
The cheap easy way to send money between the US and more than 50 countries
Including the UK Germany and Brazil
Transferwise you pay a small fee and get the real exchange rate
Like the one you see on Google
Join more than 1 million people using transferwise
By visiting transferwise.com
Or downloading the award-winning app
So Hartford you know this already but like
Are typical Nobel Prize show would be
Call the prizewinners call bengt holmstrom Oliver Hardy interview them do a lot of writing maybe come up with some practical applications
But we've been doing this for 8 years now and it's like it's starting to feel like a slob
And I think we liked about your book is that it
Talked about people who are stuck
In this rot
And it said
Where you can find creativity is essentially a force people to look at problems differently
Yeah if you
Set people a seemingly impossible all weird problem
Suddenly they stop saying everything fresh they like a tourist in a completely new city
At you're going to get somewhere fresh because you're starting somewhere
So Hartford
Famous huge fan of you
Of your work I'm delighted that you here but I have to say like
As much as I want to sort of shake off the I'm a little skeptical that there's just some like
You know one weird trick that's going to completely
You don't transform the show
I know you're probably right there probably isn't one weird trick but
Lots of examples of people who have found ways to be more creative to attend
Something they didn't know they had
One version of this that we really liked from the book and it was super simple it's a
If a deck of cards
With substring sentences written on them is called
Oblique strategies
And the creator of the stack of cards is none of a van
Brian Eno
And now ha Philistines
Assange who's he and the other half is super excited because Brian is a very interesting guy he's a musician
About his own right and he produces all the musicians that have been involved in some amazing albums
But what he often does in the studio
His to push his fellow musician out of that comfort zone
Thigh
Annie's cards
I need instructions on the couch
Very mysterious and Dracula almost
Water
Go outside shut the door
Or
Twist the spine
And then consulted magicians episode guide
Ordinances that mean
But he got amazing results
U2 with David Bowie
With Phil Collins
Amazing musician
Although they would always happy with what I was doing so at one point Collins for Goblin so frustrated with
And he's stupid instructions from the card he started throwing beer cans across the studio I feel that
Coming in the air tonight
Okay so Tim we wanted to try these oblique strategies with you we're going have you draw a card
And then whatever says on there we promise we are going to fall out
The instructions
Okay
The proper oblique strategies are beautiful Adecco
A crisp
White cons about the size of business cards
In a black
Leather case
But I did not bring that with me to New York
7 said I have the oblique strategies app on my phone
Just drove a car
I said it's it's just it's an app that has oblique strategies it's black and white so I'm just going to tap
Tricard
What context would look right
What county
Would look right
That's a very Planet Money question right there yeah it's a very Planet Money question so
In a way that's that's all most notably kanouff
It feels almost too easy so we're basically saying
Let's talk about the history of the prize
This price is controversial
We can talk about that that's even a book out at the moment about
How
Buy Avenue off of another wolf how
The Nobel Prize by City
Was trying to engineer political change in
Sweden
After offer
Oxford economic historian author of a new book on the history of the econ Nobel
Welcome to Planet Money
How long
Are we going to be here
Oh 45 minutes
Excellent okay
25 minutes of already know this but the Nobel Prize
Is an economics was not originally one of the Nobel prizes
Haters love to point that out all winter every year you know all of them except economics
We're first given out in 1901
And nobody even thought about Anakin prize until the 19th
It comes about because the Central Bank of Sweden was in a fight
With the parliament of Sweden
Yeah the head of the Swedish Central Bank
He wants Parliament to basically leave the bank alone
Disney Paris
And he comes up with this plan
To get what he wants
Is inspiration is why don't we create a Nobel prize in economics
Why economics
A Nobel prize in economics
Would endow
The policies
Of the Swedish Central Bank
With the authority of science
Comparable to physics comparable to Medicine
It is no longer the expression of the
Interest of Swedish business
And Swedish Finance
This is
Impartial Independence
It's like wearing a lab coat to work so that people will respect you more call you doctor
That is a slide rule
They want to create this nobility, and they have a lot of money
But you can't just go out and create a new Nobel Prize
You have to get the approval of the Nobel fan of somebody named know about so people from the central bank they go to me
With the fam
The
Senior member of the noble family is a 97 year old lady
Who is called Martha
And when they come to her she says
I will not have
A Nobel prize in economics she says no
I'm not aware that she says no but she makes a condition
And the condition is that it should not be called a Nobel Prize
So so she says you can't you do you got the Nobel Prize in physics Nobel Prize in medicine you cannot call this the
The Nobel prize in economics
Soap feel like okay we're going to call it the smelliest
Spunk prize in economic Sciences
In memory of Alfred Nobel
Not a Nobel Prize but the word Nobel he's in there somewhere
But you know it's it's unclear to me whether
This whole
Wu's it's a little bit of a ruse
Worked what do they did manage to dress up economics in that lab coat
You know there are a lot of things are we sure about economics
Where it is clearly not
Like a hard science like physics right like like public policy you know you can't
Run a bunch of randomized trial experiments will you have
Country a do one thing and then another country that is exactly like country a do a different thing and safe look I have sign
Intific proof that my policy is that you cannot do that
So Courthouse shouldn't build that minimum wage accelerator
I mean you know they got Cornell building the $12 accelerator they got Stanford building the $15 accelerator and we will
Once and for all
After offer for for his parts of what he thinks
I think that to the extent that
It's opposed
This View
That economics has some kind of special Authority
In the way that
Physics has about the physical well then it's not a good thing
Because
Economics does not have that
Authority
So so if we think of the
Econ Nobel Prize a sort of sitting over there next to the literature prize
That's
Good if we think of it as sitting there next to the physics prize
That's kind of bad that's problematic
I would say that to you
Economics tell stories about the way we live our lives
50 tells it describes imagined world it's
A kind of Science Fiction
I think we should stand it there
So Hartford
I'm conflicted about that that part of the story we just did
Like I like it I find it interesting
It's like every other episode of Planet Money
You feel me like that is just straight up Planet Money right there that's true and
You haven't actually answer the problem of this year's Bible
It's old picture frame beautiful picture frame with no picture
So we need to be vicious price
Let's keep going
Let's do another oblique stretch
Robert George Rowe
I can hit the button it says draw card
Breathe more deeply
I feel good I feel good I feel less worried
You have to bear in mind these strategies were originally designed for recording studio
So every now and then you get something that's very music
Where in a recording studio
Yeah but you don't have a guitar Jacob
Accepting your head but if I pulled out a guitar right now
Beijing sanlitun Jacob birthday
Go have some contract. Now all right going to do some
All right no more pussyfooting around with this Jacob
We're doing contract theory
Okay
Tell contract is the contract right it's an agreement between two people to company that just occurred
You use your hand and now your hand
I can I can I can wait one hand around here's one hand
Nice
So
You know when you're ready to contract right you want to think about all the potential things that can happen in the future
So you don't get screwed
Play right that's what lawyers are for what happens if your factory burned down what happens
If you don't deliver the product on time you know you can write all of these details into a contract as long as you want
Display man
So there's always going to be things you can't see coming
Right you can never put every future state of the world
Into account
So this is the problem right
Somebody's going to get screwed
You going to get a bad outcome
So Oliver Hart one of the guys who won the Nobel Prize write his key work is about this he called it incomplete
They're all these unknown unknowns what do you do about
And his big inside was this he said look sometimes
Certain conditions apply when company should just
Buy the other company outright
That way there's no risk of getting screwed over in the long-term when the unknown unknowns
I don't think we should talk about the coal mine to you
You got Coal Mine music, it's a perfect example
Princess if you have
An electric plant Burns coal needs to have a long-term contract with call right needs call don't think hey
I'm going to put my electric plant right next to the coal mine
I would travel so far sounds like a good idea sounds like a good idea but if you wrote up this big long contract
What if you need a different kind of cool what is the regulation change the Monday night
Put my pants tuck Mexico my home I can screw you
So under the circumstances
Electric company should just buy the coal mine
Just Own It own it and then you have control
Marca Oliver Hart and you know because it's
Science or sort of science or whatever he didn't write a novel about this
We should tell you where to keep paper with steam
Pressman
Enough to be a rich Finance guy
They wrote all these equations
I'm actually ask around yesterday so what is the most important equation in the paper
And did everybody agree on what the most important question number 14 cuz like this
A pill to buy is less than or greater than ASA by * as
5 killed somebody is less than or greater than
Fisa by star
Better than a laptop
Got to be true
Got to be true it's in an equation
So this inside had all these different applications in the real world
How people think about corporate mergers
Stop the government what's the should and shouldn't contract out the paper in the 90s arguing that Contracting out prison
Private company
Was a bad idea
Because there were too many
Unknown unknown
Set up the government to just run prisons themselves
In the theory equation
And like
More generally this paper change the way Economist think about
Firms with a firm is
About the way firms work with each other it was hugely influential
I know that cheating is account is creative
Who's we did the same thing
Was that oblique
Enough I mean
I have to say that I think play music actually did
Shake me out of my right it made me
Talk a little more slowly a be a little more like
Reflective
I think it's
That was
Weird
Beautiful
You know I could
I could listen to contact a with a bit of guitar
I do not work
I think this whole thing is working we want to do another one
Okay you ready
Yeah
Not building a wall
Making a brick
Say it again
Not building a wall making a brick
Very oblique
How many are allowed to go through
We just get a few
The gods of giving
Okay so here's what it means.
Like don't think of like this whole big
Sing
We have to make think of like
Very one little
Peace or just won something hiding in there
Kussmaul exactly Zoomin
I have a suggestion for you
If you want
I don't know if you know this but
Oliver Hart
Has changed his mind
Wheel of change
So you might want to look into that
Yes I'm here can you hear me
I can hear you
Who is this
Oliver
Oliver who
Oliver Hart Nobel Laureate
So we've been we've been looking at your your work we've been talking to people that chew your work
And try and understand more importantly
How we can explain it to other people
And we had one
Big question
Did you change your mind
Well could you plant Spotify why you ask that
Be happy to clarify that
Heart that big paper we just talked about that came out in the 80s
About a decade after that
These two prominent, they publish this
Really deep critique
Of that paper
Hearts work
It was pointed out
By actually by two other people who won Nobel prizes Eric maskin and
If people were
100 percent rational
They would be a way of overcoming the the contractual
Incompleteness
Eventually in their paper they say Okay heart
You were talking about these unknown unknowns in contacts
Betsy
Incomplete
You're assuming
People are perfectly rational cuz that's what Economist do when they do
But in the paper they say if people were perfectly rational they could solve the kind of problem you're talk
Talking about they could
Agree in advance that
They would bargain in certain ways when certain things came up
And you wouldn't have to have one company by the other company to solve the problem
And Hart look at this critique and he says
YouTube
The right
The original Theory does not hold up
And so to solve this problem that they pointed out to make it all make sense he realizes something
Tell me that for an old-school Economist like Oliver Hart is a huge deal
He realizes that he has to assume
Fat people entering into contracts are not
Entirely rational
He starts changing his theory of incomplete contracts to include
Psychology
Ideas about fairness
Magic
I mean sort of
Right to be stuffy hippie stuff that does not play much of a role in traditional economic
Oliver Hart changed his mind
Change my mind in the sense that I would have when I started doing this work if people that said
Are there any way you could have do it if you're going to depart from the assumption that
People are rational I would have I would probably lost I live for that copyright
Something
Why would you have laughed when people said that to initially
I would have said look
We're talking about
Maybe large companies that say
Venture capitalist
What I say you know government the society weather to privatize the prison
I would have thought those were pretty rational hard headed people
Heart says
A lot of other Economist they still think
And any says this warmer fuzzy or theory has has been kind of a tough sell
Yeah a lot of his fellow Economist have given him a really hard time about it and you think
Now that heart has won two Nobel
If he's moved on
No
Any slides you know I remember forever
Compliments I forget
No seriously like all these stories of specific people who had criticized his work
You didn't talk at Berkeley one
And it was his friend of his races have
Afula Street in Miami going to name him
But he's a good friend of mine
I like him very much but he said
He actually asked a question he said they should be how does this work
Compare
To your
Odiaone
What what did you take that medicine
It meant
And I can't use bad language on your program
How can I write so it meant you know that the old stuff was good and they say s***
That's what I took it to mean
And I didn't see it you know obviously I thought this is going to be a hard sell this stuff
When the Nobel committee gave all of her heart the prize this
They focused almost entirely on that original version of his theory the one where people are entirely rational
But he's still out there talking about this new version
He says he's got to do it
So he had a theory
Someone critical theory
Spot long and hard about he said okay I will incorporate those critiques
Into a new Theory
It sounds like science
It does except for one really important
Fact which is
For the most part nobody's really doing experiments here nobody's going out into the world to like
Actually see if it's true Seattle-Tacoma yeah there's no it's not evidence
Sprite
It's just whatever offer called that imagined world they're just imagining this world and I'm thinking really hard about it engraved
So you can just as easily say Oliver Hart
Told a wonderful story someone critiques some of his characters and plot points
And he told his story
Yeah I mean you can say it's kind of like literature that
I mean to me
Decora of the Oliver Hart story is
I think it's super admirable that a famous
Economist was courageous enough to change his mind
You don't have enough of the problem you realize
You know the
The way you thought it was going to work doesn't work then you
You have to consider alternative
So you're not building a wall you're making a brick
It's a nice way of putting it with you
Wow okay that sounds nice
XXX very much
Bye-bye
Hartford you're killing it
So good this is way better than I thought it would
The Odyssey
One more
So one more often
YouTube The Fixx
I love it
Okay
Gorecon
Destroy nothing
Destroy the most important
Where at
Please let us know what your favorite Phil Collins song is you email us at Planet Money at npr.org or fine.
Twitter
Today Show is produced by Sally Helm and special thanks again
To Tim
Harford for being
Are creative Guru his new book Messi is out of the United States now pick it up
And if you're looking for something else to listen to check out the Death Sex and Money podcast
They just recently did an extended version of a story that Noel King did here at Planet Money this summer
Are the stories about a man who was tortured by the Chicago Police Department
And who decades later got a reparations check from the city of Chicago
The show is called Death Sex and Money you can find it wherever you get your
I'm Robert Smith and I'm Jacob Goldstein
Thanks for listening
Call Me Maybe
Hold on