It's been kind of a rough year for people who believe in free trade you know people in one country should be
Be able to sell stuff to people in other countries
Without too much
Yeah there was this massive
Trade deal that the US has been negotiating with Europe and that seems to be falling apart
People in the UK voted to leave
What is the largest free-trade Block in the world that European Union in a word over the bricks
The boat and the TPP the trans-pacific partnership
Giant free trade deal that look like it was going to be
When a President Obama's biggest accomplishments
But the two people most likely to take Obama's job next year
The two candidates who agree on almost nothing
Big Rihanna
TPP the trade deal
Transpacific
A horrible deal for our country
I oppose it now
I'll oppose it after the election
And I'll oppose it as president
For decades
President after president Democrats and Republicans have all been Pro free trade
We've had one free trade deal after another
Now it's like the complete opposite
What happened
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Jacob Goldstein
Adam Robert Smith today on the show we pack
240 years of trade history
Into a mirror 22 minutes we have a Scotsman kidnapped by
Possibly apocryphal a hippie dream of world peace and revolutionaries in the street
Bye
The most important idea in a canal
I mean one of the most important ideas
Free train
Support for this NPR Podcast and the following message come from Blue Apron
Blue Apron partners with sustainable Farms fisheries and ranchers to bring you all the ingredients you need
To create incredible home cooked meals
Ingredients compared with an easy-to-follow recipe card delivered to your door weekly in a refrigerated box
ReDiscover have fun cooking can be while enjoying specialty ingredients
Exploring new flavors in cuisine
Get your first three Blue Apron meals free
Plus free shipping
By visiting blueapron.com planet
Robert
Jessica
I'm starting to show
I don't care what anybody says
Adams 50 super interesting
Keon trade and your world economic still have not talked about atoms within years and his big book
The Wealth of Nations
Came out in 1776
Perfect this is a show about America and trade
In three Acts
Sao chapter 1
Madam
I'm Adam
That's like a
Call Grandpa palindrome
True
So okay for Adam Smith we talked to an economic historian named Doug Irwin and we said all right
Let's start by telling the world how amazing Adam Smith
Adam Smith lived with his mother
There's a bachelor
He didn't go out at night
Come on you can do better than that
You of all people Duggar wedding
He was captured by gypsies
What is kidnapped
For real
Yes the Adam Smith
Liam Smith
He almost was lost Humanity
Okay that's
Possibly apocryphal that's
But but what is true is Adam Smith grew up and basically invented economics As We Know
An itchy part of that was
Thinking about trade
In this way that was
Really revolutionary and that frankly is
Still Central to the way economist
So at the time people measured the wealth of
The wealth
Of a Nation
By how much gold
The country hat
And and the pile of gold is what makes you rich it's gold
That's right who doesn't want to go up
And everything country did was to get
More gold they would explore they would go to war they would take over continents
And they would
Trade
International trade with a gold making machine
You said cloth
Orgreen to France
France Senegal
But the key to the way people thought about trade at the time was
You wanted to keep that gold in your country
And the way you do that is
You do not buy stuff from other
You want to buy less
From them
Then they buy from you you want to run a trade surplus that's how you get a big pile of gold in your country
So countries put up high tariffs
Taxes on
Quotas to discourage people
From buying stuff from other countries they basically said keep the gold here by everything in this country
Atoms with looked at these policies interested
Doesn't make sense
He said it's not how much gold you have
How higher wages are in the standard of living of people
Not what's socked away in the government coffers
The standard of living of ordinary people that's just
How much stuff can Ordinary People Buy
And those High tariffs
And quotas they made it so people could not buy as much
Stuff in Great Britain at the time
They had. Lot of restrictions on imported food
It's just harming working people by making them by high-priced food
Adam Smith says this at the time revolutionary thing it says
Get rid of those terrorists
Poodle get cheaper lots of things will get cheaper people's standard of living will
They'll be able to buy more stuff the nation will get wealth
Now there are farmers who are selling expensive food who might be temporarily hurt
But the idea Adam Smith said was that those farmers
They will change jobs they can start saying
Making clock
Which maybe I can make better and more cheaply than people in other countries and then they can trade that cloth
Batman Smith steps back and says
Free trade to Knicks
Everybody better off
And some sort of Rights
The original get rich
QuickBooks what four nations write The Wealth of Nations is the name of his book
And the book is a big hit in Britain and it makes its way to America
Wealth of Nations was brought over on ships
United States
And Jefferson Adams Hamilton they already Adam Smith
We have the Constitution 1787
First Congress meet 1789 the second bill they pass is a tariff bill
It's one of the first things they do because the government needs Revenue
They had the book
Jacob they read the book
They ignored the book
Yeah but tariffs
Starts out as a way to get Revenue
But as soon as the US has any industry to speak
Factory owner start going to Cairo
Hey we need more tariffs to protect us from foreign competition
Congress
And from that point forward in American history
There are apps in their downs but pretty much we are a protectionist country
And this political outcome it makes sense when you look at
It was really a classic thing you have this
Relatively small number of people who benefit from it
They care a lot about
You know these are people with factories
Who would have to compete against Imports so of course they're going to push for a tear
They're going to go to college
Person say
Look I'm going to go out of business all my workers are going to lose their jobs you have to protect
But then you have basically
Everybody else
Who are going to pay more for their stuff
As a result
But it's not as big of a deal because it's not like their job or their company depends on it they are going to get on a horse and ride the washing
DC
The other senators and complain that their stockings say cost $0.02
How dare you sir
Yep this is like a political truth you know when you have a concentrated benefit
Escape the fact
Up against the diffuse cost
Everybody else
The concentrated benefit usually win
Even if it's much smaller than the car
And that's really the story of chapter one
Tariffs win
Adam Smith
And
Tariffs in the US state really high
For a really long
But
That finally changes largely because
Of 1
Guy
I need to take this one
Chapter 2
A man
A plan
A free-trade hero
Cordell Hull
Not a pound
True but this was the man who Unleashed free-trade upon the entire world
Was he abducted by gypsy
Caesar the baby no
What is a hillbilly from Tennessee
Doug Erwin
Cordell Hull grew up in a log cabin
I read that went over the kid he would go on these trips where they would make a raft out of a bunch of logs
Float on the logs down the river and then sell the logs
In the software Hall was growing up and this is around
The turn of the 20th Cent
Most politicians
Were anti tariff
Not because they read their Adam Smith and thought every
Paper goods
But because the farmers miss out
Grew tobacco and cotton
Which people all over the world wanted to buy
They were
Beloved
But the US Factory owners these are mostly Northern Republicans at the time
They mostly wanted to sell stuff to customers in the US so they wanted
Protection from foreign competition they wanted Terror
Cordell Hull becomes a lawyer
Congressman from Tennessee
Entering World War 1
He has this revelation
He realizes
Terfs aren't just about
Economics
There is something much bigger it stay
And as he looked at the war he said
Your economic causes to this war
Those causes are that there was protectionist policies the lack of international free international trade
And that led to political fractions which led to war in there for my mission my life goal
Is to bring about free or trade
Because that will bring about world peace
Think of how amazing his argument was
He was saying Germany and France would not have needed to
The fight in those trenches
If they traded more stuff with each other
If there were thousands of businessmen in Paris and Berlin saying hey
Don't shoot them those are my customers
But that argument didn't really
I'm really convinced the
It wouldn't be the first thing you would say caused World War but he
Quail Hollow West onto it and pushed and pushed and pushed it
In the thirties hole becomes FDR Secretary of State
And he does have some success Congress passed this law that said the president could negotiate lower tariffs with other countries
Still truant says it holes
Obsession
Set the key to World Peace was free trade that all you need man
Is free trade
This just
Rain
False in the 1930s
People thought he was nuts
Reason why there's Nazi Germany is because they didn't trade enough because if not free trade
And even Roosevelt President Roosevelt.
Now he's a really a little bit misplaced here is you know
The world is burning up around us
Please talk about trade agreements
And people said that's just not yet he's off
Bass
And there was something else there was another reason why
People were not
Taking Cordell Hull Siri
He also spoke with a lisp bespoke like Elmer Fudd
Dean Acheson in his Memoirs he was at the State Department of time
He said
He's off enunciated words do to a speech impediment emerged as
Reciprocal trade
A program to reduce Telus
This is what about you
They are
They're behind us back
But we really haven't reached the Mulhall moment cuz he does win
Okay don't.
Royalty free
How Cordell Hull change the world
Cordell Hull's moment came
Because of World War II
The state department is not responsible for fighting a war that's
So they're spending the entire War thinking about what what comes next
And there's this moment there's just pause nobody knows which direction to go in and
Courthouse steps forward and says how about this direction
Absolutely
I'm going to play some music under the Oaks
Give me a Cordell Hull speech that is the most idealistic
The most Visionary the best possible pitch of his
For free trade after the war
I'd say this is the patch
By turning inward
United States
Bandits International responsibility
And we had world war that was a
Grievous mistake
We cannot repeat
Keep this mistake after World War II
We have to come an economic leader of political leader in the world
An essential component
To ensuring peace in the postwar period
Is having a strong economic Foundation
People are fully employed
And trading with one another
And their economically prosperous
Ellevest of stake in preserving peace
If they're unemployed
And there's economic rivalry and bitterness and resentment
About
Other countries stealing our jobs or this or that
It's going to lead to a political breakdown
And actually to another War
That's pretty good pets
Yeah and imagine hearing it as as world war was winding
You know the world was exhausted
Devastated
And Cordell Hull skip forward with this plan
This Plane had been working on for deck
And the president. President Roosevelt strongly supported all this and
That was his moment
Sequoia Hall
Is standing there
He finishes his pitch and there was dead silence
And then all the sudden the back
Dean Acheson
The man who had mocked him for speech impediment stands up
And start the slow clap
Boxers with Cordell Hull
And then everybody starts to stand up
Call Holly
1945 Cordell Hull
Win the Nobel
Peace Prize
Amazing
UPS astonishingly
Only the last sentence was through the whole thing about absent in the room
That's from the movie you just made up in your head
Black tattoos movie
Who won the Nobel Peace
In 1945 he won the Nobel Prize
Partly for his work creating the United Nations
Also for his idea that trade barriers are
And I'm quoting from the award speech ear quote
Barriers also to Lasting
A couple years after that holes
Free trade dream
Comes true
23 countries create
Wait for it
The general agreement
On tariffs
Contrave
It is
The Gap the first
Really big mechanism
For free trade between countries
Any amazing thing about this
Was it the usual people who would
Stand in the way of
Us manufacturer
Also mean looked around the world and said you know what we're the only factor is left standing
This is a chance for us to sell to the world yet so the manufacturers and for that matter of the Union's to like they were like
Yeah this will be more jobs for us let's lower tariff so we can sell more stuff to the rescue
And Jacob
Look what happened
The gap
Ground
Down trade barriers around the world
In 1945 at the end of the war
Tariffs on Imports to the US were round
30%
50 years later
By the mid 90s
Cursive font
Percent 30%
To 5%
That's that's essentially the end of a chapter 2
Cordell Hull and for that matter Adam Smith
They want
Chapter 3
The star last chapter chapter 3
Able was I ere I saw Seattle
So a free-trade one why does it seem like we're still arguing about this why are we talkin about trade
All the time
I called up Joe stiglitz
He is famously
Skeptical of or lot of
Globalization and parts of
The trades he's also famous economist won the Nobel Prize the econ prize
Back in the 90s he was an advisor to Bill Clinton and worked at the World Bank
And at the time when he got to Washington he noticed something
Sprint
One of the realizations I had
Was that the Free Trade Agreement
We're not free trade agreements they were just called three
Free Trade Agreement
Lower some tariffs but remember tears were already super low
A bigger deal according to stick
Other things
Going on
In these tray degrees
A corporation disagrees with a foreign government about a certain regulation
Yeah that trade deals have special like
Panels to settle those disagreements
The deals also had stuff about like
How long drug patent
It's for good in different countries
And it kind of started looking at all this stuff
And sing weight
There was a broad sense
Daddy should be in a trade agreement they were actually restricting trade
And it wasn't just a car
This is the sound of thousands of people chanting and protesting in the streets of Seattle
The year was 1999
And everybody was there to protest a meeting of the WTO the World Trade Organization
Robert Smith
You are a cub reporter in those
Well as we saw yesterday I mean clearly there are enough
Police officer
Here although I don't
See them now and I don't
Really know where they are
I'm sure they're ready
To shut down a protest
Did you get that
The wax cylinder and sent it to us
Baby Robert Smith at 12 years old your voice hasn't changed yet
Sore in the streets of Seattle people are protesting the WTO which
Is the modern incarnation of
Look at the thing they Cordell Hull inspired Avid change its name to
WTO World Trade
You better have been just a couple years before they happen in the mid-90s and I have this Theory
That I totally just made up that
Probably
Siri is
But that was a huge branding mistakes changing
Cuz you don't think I'm dad
The general agreement on tariffs and trade
So boring
You don't even get to the end of the acronym before you like I got to go do some
World Trade
WTO
We are going to Lourdes carrots Mr Bond and there's nothing you can do to stop us
I'm not even going to try and do that
Voice but but I would say that bundling would also be singing like
And we're going to monkey with your regulation we're going to change the Dynamics of power between corporations and government
And that was the amazing thing you saw it
In Seattle the protesters were not
Pairing signs that said oh we need higher tariffs on sneakers
Say
They were there dressed as seater
Saying oh what the WTO does
Is Rouen environmental regulations around the
This is still the trade fight we're having today
You know when you look at the TPP
Trans Pacific partnership
This deal that that issue in the presidential election
A lot of the fight over is over stuff like
Generic drugs and companies challenging governor
So is the TPP even a trade deal
Not really
Xxxx
Mostly about other things than trade
So is it possible to be
Pro free trade and anti TPO
Cities that are consistent
View
Yes and you here
You care a lot of this when Hillary Clinton and Donald Trump
Talk about that
Maybe they do talk about
A lot of this non-tariff stuff
Like drugs in rule
The kind of things you might have heard 200 years
Stuff that someone probably said to Adam Smith
Face you know hey what about the workers
The workers who compete against Imports are going to be hurt by this
Did they definitely both say that but when you get a little more and you read you know Hillary Clinton and Donald Trump on trade
There are some some pretty big difference
Right-wing Quint Clinton talks about
TPP
One of the things she says is
Us workers need more of a safe
You don't trade deals make our economy as a whole get wealthy
But some people do get her
One thing you can do is
Pick some of that extra wealth you're getting from trade and give it to the
People who get hurt
Is it like a standard
Economic idea
And whatever the rhetoric maybe now run PPP Clinton's views on trade are pretty firmly in the Cordell Hull
Call Adam Smith
Universe
Which is basically the same universe that Barack Obama lives in in
George W bush
For that Bill Clinton it's the universe where trade between countries
Is can make both countries better off
Donald Trump tok
More about trade in terms of winners and losers
China has been killing us on trade Mexico taking our job
Cordell Hull is a wimp and a loser sad!
It's as if
Donald Trump looks at the world and says hey
Everybody's laid down their tradeweb
End
Why don't we pick up this pointed stick when we pick up this 45% tariffs on imports from China
And poke them with Joe stiglitz says that is a dangerous stick
Cooperation
In what area does buildup
Cooperation now there's trade
Peace out
By the same token aggressive
Fitness in one area can lead to aggressiveness
In another part of the danger of trump
That you could
Throwing hand grenade
In
The construction of which took decades
I think of Cordell whole world live
Today and watching the presidential race he would
Say listen
May be tempting
To take a certain point of view for votes or it may be tempting to use a tariff as a
As a weapon for a short-term gain
What he would say is like
Think about what I lived
I quit alcohol
The horrors of world
A World War
Is Slappy a high tariff on another
Country is not just about
It's about something much bigger
We would love to hear what you
You think of the show you can email us Planet Money at npr.org or tweet at us where at
Planet Money we watch
Obsessive
Car show today was produced by Elizabeth
Special thanks to Mike
More former head of the WTO talk to us but didn't make it into
The show also Michael a butler
Author of Cordell Hull cautious
And also thanks to
My Homestay
My dear love kuow in Seattle and two producers Sally Helm who helped us
Another done with this
Particular episode may we recommend another NPR favorite the NPR politics podcast
Monday
This is the first presidential debate and the very next morning
Play NPR politics
He will have a podcast ready for you telling you
Natalie what happened during the debate
But what if
Me that the NPR politics podcast I can do special show after every debate
Subscriber listen on the NPR one app
I'm Robert Smith and I'm Jacob
Thanks for listening