Support for NPR and the following message come from service now making the world of work
Work better for me
They're cloud-based
Platform and solutions
Deliver digital workflow
Spell create great experiences and unlock productivity for your whole company
More at servicenow.com
Last year on Valentine's Day Fred Rocco was sitting on his couch at his house in Upstate New York
And his wife Natasha was playing the piano
3 planes
Something she made up
Sometimes I just sit there and let my fingers go and see what Tunes melodies come out
Red Lobster
I love them
Actually paying that much attention to the music he was paying attention to this new little kitten that they
They got so who is this
So she can introduce yourself with this is Yoda
Hey Kitty we say something
At some point I'm going to have to get Yoda to meow
Got to get the some of the cat radio when I want to try to meow
We'll get to that
Anyway friends playing with
The kitten and he takes little toy mouse that Yoda has a
Throws it across the room and it slides across
The floor and they have a rug that's a little bit Rumple.
And the mouse slides across the
Right into one of the little rumbles in the rug
The cat
Goes
Bananas
And she immediately attacked it just ran and started putting her paws underneath then playing with it and
Fred 70s that there was said we going to make the Ripple rug and I looked at Fred I said what you mean what's the Ripple rug
Ripple rug
The Ripple rug
The Ripple rug is a cat
It is basically the size
7 doormat
I'm here Robert in the show you
The Ripple rug this is it
This is
The rebel ride
I don't know how to describe describe it looks like someone's taking a carpet
They've cut holes into it so it looks like swiss cheese and then they have
Wadded-up
The carpet
Turn on the floor
Yeah that's essentially the revelry apparently Disneyland for
A year later Natasha and Fred are selling
$60,000
Ripple rug every month
David on Today Show
They have set up a shop
Open Amazon Marketplace
Sunprime
And the Ripple rug was one of Amazon's best-selling pet toys
Three 999
And then one day Fred gets this
Missed call from him
My brother-in-law's like hey did you see it's on eBay cuz he's always looking at stuff on eBay
And I was like what
Fred Goes immediately to his computer logs
EBay I just typed in the Ripple rug and there was already for sellers selling the Ripple rug and then every single
All day there would be five more six more
10 more
How much were they charging
They were going as high as 5999
That's
$20 more than he was selling them for on Amazon
Beastly people were scalping Ripple
Buying them on Amazon and selling them on eBay at a market
All these people who read a Natasha never met
We're getting rich off of their invention
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Stacey Vanek Smith Robert Smith
The internet was supposed to get rid
Of the middleman that's what they told us consumers were supposed to buy directly from manufacturers
No more going to people like
Travel agents having to pay fees
Internet was going to be about getting stuff from the source
For a wholesale price
It did not work out that way
Just ask the makers of
The Ripple rug
The internet has made it so that anyone can be a middleman
Or a middle person
Middle person doesn't sound as good as middle man
Today on the show a middleman or taking over the global economy
Support for this NPR Podcast and the following message come from Blue Apron
Blue Apron partners with sustainable Farms fisheries and Ranchers
To bring you all the ingredients you need
To create incredible home cooked meals
Ingredients compared with an easy-to-follow recipe card delivered to your door weekly in a refrigerated box
ReDiscover have fun cooking can be while enjoying specialty ingredients
Exploring new flavors in cuisine
Get your first
3 Blue Apron meals free
Plus free shipping
By visiting blueapron.com planet
Winford Rocco saw all of these
People selling the Ripple rug on eBay
He went a little nuts
He started spending hours everyday checking eBay and
Try to get in touch
The people who are selling his cattle
Did you ever try to contact any of the
Mittleman
I have reached out to many of them I've sent cease-and-desist orders to every single one of them
Well hello
One of them stop
Yes the letters did not work and then Fred started tracking down their phone number
And personally calling
I am Fred from snuggly cat the makers of the Ripple rug and calling you about you selling our product illegal alien
You know I'm not selling it illegally
Well I mean
BB guns for probably right there's nothing illegal about buying something and reselling it there's even a name for it would use the
Arbitrage Arbitrage memes
You buy something cheap in one place
You sell it expensive another
Yes but this is a
Twist on Arbitrage
Call drops
And it's kind of
Genius because there is
Basically no risk involved it all
These people never bought a ripple in their closet
And then sold it
They never actually
Touch the Ripple rug
They just
Wait until a customer buys
The Ripple rug from them
And then they buy it from the Amazon store
And ship it directly from Amazon
To the customer
And the customers
Have no idea where the River Run
Comes from all I know is they paid
$60 instead of $40 and the Ripple rug showed up they thought it came from
Whoever made it
Exactly and the dropshipper can just pocket the difference
Okay it is easy to resent
People who have found a way to make some
Easy money
This is good for Fred this is good for Fred and Natasha and for the Ripple rug
Because this
Fleet of middleman whoever they are there advertising
The product
And yeah they're adding money to order debated making a profit but they act
It's the sort of
We have sales people
Out there pushing Ripple rug
Getting into people's hands
Yes they don't actually do any of the work
But they're making more sales
But Fred says there are a couple of problems
The first is that he is trying to build a brand
It's not just about selling one ripplerock it's about building the snuggle
Cat brand so part of
A luxury cat toys
Price is a big part of
Branding and so he wants to control his Brandy wants to control the prices
She doesn't want people selling it for all kinds of
But the real problem was that he says he was losing money
Because what was happening
Is people were ordering this product on eBay
And the Box showing up at their doorstep was from Amazon
Two people get confused they would look up the product on Amazon and they would realize
They had paid $20 more
For the Ripple rug then they needed to pay
And so they would think I'm just going to return it to eBay and
Order from Amazon
Let's say you feel cheated you say I want to return it cuz
It's 3999
Honey you know Amazon for real
I paid 5990. They're both free shipping and free returns
I'll return this one order from there
But you're not returning the product
To the middleman
The people I mean by you're really returning the product
Back to friends
And that comes with a whole boatload of fees of
Apparently so Amazon charges fees all along the way they have a fever
For the purchase of
Before shipping if you for
For the return if
Restocking
And then when the customer reorders from Amazon
There's another
Another
Sprint has a lot of times the rugs with comeback used
So he had to
Destroy that he couldn't
Resell them
And just two months after
Fred noticed all of these
Dropshippers on eBay
He said he had over 200
Which was over 10000 losses in
Just a couple of months
You lost $10,000 in 2 months into months
Meanwhile the eBay people
All the people who are charging $60 for
This pocketing the extra $20 different
They get to keep the money
Yeah they're not paying any of the
The genius
Do you want me to go first you can go first
Okay I'm alright though hello my name is Nikki with a
Hello my name is Paris Witherspoon
Nicky and Paris are dropshippers I talk to them on Skype
And they said he never sold the Ripple rug
But they do sell tons of cat toys and household products and
Supplies and all kinds of
And what's make any of those things
They don't have possession of those things
Mark up the price
And send them on to
The customer
That is what they do
America got started in this business when they were both living in Baghdad
In Iraq they were working for private contractors
And they were spending all of their time
Buying stuff online
You know groceries and household type stuff
Furniture
We bought a car online
We bought a house online we bought a dog online
Cuba
Adam Schiff
Legend ship from Oklahoma to Iraq we sure did that wasn't
Nicky and Paris are very familiar with buying things online and they decide to give dropshipping
A try
Sign up for the company called
DS Domination PS4 Dropship
Exactly
And think it's software that helps them find these best selling products on Amazon
Copy the images from Amazon
Apple store on eBay
And figure out how much to charge for these
These products if they're dropped
They start out selling mostly.
Toys and novel
The items and almost right away Nikki says she realizes
This is going to be
Be a big
I'll never forget it it was like an Angry Birds Star Wars set that we had got and it it took off in
In less than 48 hours
I mean you just kind of sit back and you're like
I just paid
$0.30 for this item and it's sold were like 9 bucks
About 30 times today
You know
It was just an amazing feeling
Answer me this
Prophet I mean just in that one day they made you know what
60 bucks
Yeah nothing yeah
And after just a few months of this they were making enough money that they were both able to
Quit their jobs in Iraq
And move back to the US
To Houston
And now they say they make more than a million dollars a year in sales
Dave
McDonald's
Well they've expanded into a whole bunch of other thing
Wholesaling now and
Private label stuff but
Nikki told me they will never stop doing the drop ship
It's just it's just too easy
Portsmouth. Some some tools in there that kind of automate everything
Really just a matter of pressing a button and your store is kind of ran for you
So
You know that that's profit that you know if it's that easy to do why would we not keep it you know
Did you ever feel like
We're not actually doing anything we're just
Gorgeous charging to
Post-it you don't even like you're not adding anything to the product
Anything like that
Did you feel weird about that
Not not really honestly
You know when you're actually doing it it does require some work you're having to do the tracking
You know I'm a say for instance if Amazon is is out of her
A particular item
I'm get to go to an actual retail location grab that item put in the Box make sure your customer gets it you're doing all the cuss
Customer service you're making sure that that customer is happy
There's no issues with it
Control
If you're doing the whole thing
When you put it that way
They sound like a retail
They sound like a retail store that wants
Customers to return
And even though they don't make
The products are
Or even really even
Touch the products
They're the public face
Of the prompt
Yeah in a lot of ways retailers are
Just middle man
But to frighten
Natasha the cat rug makers
Guys on the internet or just scalp
They were making the product a lot more expensive
For customers
They were not adding anything to it
Jason feifer is the editor-in-chief of Entrepreneur magazine
He wrote about the Ruffles and
If there's a bad guy in this story
Really
It's us
What know it's us
Have you ever bought anything on eBay
Yes
Did you ever
Think where it came from
No seller the seller right where it came from
That mentality
Create this opportunity for
Still with our fault because
We aren't shopping around because we're not searching for the original Ripple rug at the original $40
Exactly we don't want to look around on the internet
That's so the middleman or saving us a couple
Keystrokes few seconds here and there
Yeah and we are willing to
To pay for that $5 10 dollars $20 we are paying for that
All I have to do is go
To another website
NC
The price is Jeff
And I don't
It's crazy like why am I not doing that
I mean
As long as we are all willing
To be taken advantage of by
Different Market
Two places even though we have all the information in front of us
It would literally take five seconds
And we don't do it
So if we're not going to do it
Why can't people take advantage of us
We are the problem
Just gets to something
Because although economic treat us like economically rational beings always
Hunting for the best price
The truth is
We are all deeply lazy
And
There's always someone who will help us
Be a little bit lazier
For a profit
And I guess it's always with all that little one-click shopping the internet has made us
Lazier
And it's simultaneously created all these opportunities for
For people to jump in and make things even easier but to take a little slice of the profiteering
Exactly
Keystrokes and Charters little more
Michael Munger is an economist at Duke
He has been studying the middleman for years
All you have to do is have a computer with a connection to the internet the ability to write code
And you can be a middleman it's the most competitive industry the world has ever known
Being a middleman
Being a middleman that's what people all over the world want to do
I want to write an app
That will sell and I'll make a lot of money but the app itself can't make any good or service all I can do is
Bring together
A buyer and a seller who otherwise wouldn't have met that's the essence of being a middleman
Think about it a lot of the hottest companies in the world right now are
Essentially just middlemen
Yeah and we don't even think of them as middleman right or I'm going to get an Uber
That's what I say I'm going to Uber so a car is going
Uber all over is a middleman
Between me
Add a driver they don't own any car
Cars they don't employ any drivers
They just take a slice of profit for connecting the two of us
Same with Airbnb
Kayak
EBay and Amazon
Alibaba all just
Mittleman
So
The future of the economy is really
Becoming more and more about
Middleman
Getting
People much much much more efficiently
Goods and services
You're not going far enough
It's about almost nothing else
It's more middlemen
Good
That's like asking is gravity good
You're comparing middlemont to gravity
I'm comparing the economic logic of selling reductions in transaction
Irresistible inevitable
So inevitable but even middlemen are worried
About middle
No
Nikki and Parish Witherspoon the Amazon to eBay drops
Chippers would not even give me the name of their store on
Because they were worried that someone would go to their store copy all the items they were selling
Set up their own store
And sell them for a little bit less
People that are lazy will go in instead of doing the research like we did
We'll just go and take what you having
You start selling it
They're not going to have to do the work that you did to go research the item
Dropshipping way I thought like the whole
Is that the whole thing
Absolutely it
It is absolutely it's not for you to call
Copy other people
Right right that's what I was
But their whole business is copying other people
Yes but they said that they know things they gotten
Really good at their business with yours and they don't want somebody stealing your ideas
Middle men are like gravity they're just inevitable
If there's any little bit of profit left on the table somewhere
Someone is going to grab
There is one man who has decided to fight
To fight the middleman
Fred Ruckel
Are Ripple rug maker
He was spending hours a day
Trying to shut down
Dropshippers
First thing in the morning check for arbitrageurs last thing at night check for Arbitrage you send out any cease-and-desist before or after
It was taking up enormous amount of time and it was a super stressful
A couple months ago red did something
Drastic
Keep hold the Ripple rug off of the Amazon Prime Market
No more free Prime shipping Amazon store
That is where the Arbitrage
We pulled out of the hole in Prime shipping thing in May
And at that point we were over 60000 a month in sales
And in a blink
60000 went down
$25
Oh my gosh
That's a big price you paid
I would say it was a huge price
Is it worth it
Well we had put together
Really that's all I mean that's so much money that's like
Integrity is important
Stress Factory trust so we removed all the stress
Bread and Atasha started doing all of their own ship
And they converted their garage in
A little pack
Gotten really good with those
Envelopes
And then I before I saw them they both been up in
Until midnight
A video had gone up online with a couple of
Cat celebrities minor cat celebrities named Cole and marmalade playing on a ripple rug
An orders had been pouring in
And so we spent two hours each packing last night and then this morning we spent another two hours each packing
Let's meat hours
For one person right there
Camp so this isn't make you wish slightly that you were still
Using Amazon zuoz shipping
People would be arbitraging our products
It seems like
Everybody's
Losing out of
Brenda Tasha are losing money they not selling it
Beat the dropshippers the arbitrageurs
They're not making as much money reselling these things
And their product
Which seems like a great product
Is harder to get cats everywhere are suffering because Freddy Natasha won't just suck it
Shut up and deal with the middleman
All of that is true
But there's an emotional component
And Fred and Natasha invented this
This River Rock
Lisa a lot of ownership
Foreign to them
It felt like people were coming in
And taking like a bite out of
The Sting main event
Essentially
Stealing there Prada
And for free that I just wanted
Control back they didn't want to be up at night and up in the morning trying to
Pull their products back from all these
Forces
They just wanted total control van end the loss of money they told me it was worth it today
Now for the Natasha are mostly selling Ripple rugs Direct
Website and they told me sales are starting to come back after
For the initial
Big drop off
And they were very pleased to say
In the last 4 months
They have only had
To return
Will you meow
Kitty kitty kitty
We reached out to both Amazon and eBay Amazon did not get back to us
EBay did respond saying that dropshipping
Is not against its rule
As always we like to hear what you think of the show email is Planet Money at npr.org
Or tweet
We are at Planet Money
Our episode today was produced by the great leap
Nick Fountain a huge thanks to Jason Pfeiffer you should really check out his
His article about Dropship
Entrepreneur magazine
And he also has a new podcast called
Pessimist archive
Apparently is a history of unfounded fears
Json is fearless
It's Vicky of entrepreneurs NPR is launching a new podcast new podcast about the way people
Start companies featuring one of our favorite people in NPR
Hey it's kyroz here from the Ted radio hour and I'm really excited
Tell you about another podcast I'm hosting
It's called how I built this
And it's a show about the most amazing innovators and Arch
Entrepreneurs
And the stories behind
Companies in movements
They built
You can find it at npr.org
Slash podcast
Itunes store
On the NPR one app
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith Robert Smith thanks for listening
Wynfred Russell the Ripple
Wynfred Russell the river
Wynfred Russell the guy
Wynfred Russell
Wynfred Russell Ripple
Stop
Fred
Celtics
Bad Boys
The people always shout there goes Red Rock and River Road