Spothero how can I help you
Working in a call center is a tough job
It's true
We visited one in Chicago the call center for this company called spothero
And it was basically just a bunch of people
Sitting in a row at a long table store
Anonymous Works B
And they were just taking call
Call
Phone up phone down phone up phone down
And even just hearing their side of the calls you can tell that a lot of people calling in are not happy
Let me ask you this is there some joke that goes on
Spothero is a startup
It's this online company that rents out
Can spaces and people get
Very emotional
About parking
I went yesterday CookieSwirlC
Park my car
Did you get that he dated for my appointment
All I'm asking
I just want to be fun
60 year old man is having to talk to you for now over half an hour.
I really want somebody to call me back that's what I want
I would have a nervous breakdown I would just cry all the time
Every once in awhile one of the calls is
Truly memorably terrible
There's one at spothero that people still talk about today it's like a legend
Making bubbly
Took the call it was rude I would Reserve.
Parking spot but when he got there someone else's
Making a for standard response
I am so sorry we're young company we have some glitches but
I'm here to help
That was not
Right answer
I don't know what the right answer was but it was not that the customer started
Screaming and then he called me
A word that
It's not appropriate for any
Podcast TV show
The c word
Is that why you're telling me story you still look like your hands are shaking a little bit
Megan said she kind of went into shock
She put the phone down walked out of the office and started running down the sidewalk
She ran 13 blocks to Lake
Adult verbally like
Scream at
It's a great place to scream
When Megan got back she went to talk to her man
Women named Julia Pott
They went into a little conference room
We asked
She started crying and
She said it's so much
And I knew how she felt
Call centers have really high turnover
Which makes sense
You're dealing with people who are anxious
And angry and frustrated all day everyday
You don't get paid a lot of money and it most companies you're at the bottom of the totem pole you're the person taking customer can
There's so many times and you
I just want to throw your headset off a
I just say
I'm done
And that's when I realized
I can't let my team have a
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Noel King
And I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Burnouts
It is not just a problem for call center
Hospitals
Tech companies schools
They're all struggling with burnout
You just really hard to fix
Companies try
And most of them fail
Today on the show the 26 year-old call center manager tried to beat
Burnouts
Planet Money is supported by betterment
The largest independent Robo advisor with more than 180 thousand customers and over 5.5 billion dollar
Sonder management
Betterment makes it easier and less expensive to invest for your personal financial goals
With a beautiful user interface and smart cutting-edge technology
Betterment brings you sophisticated personalized Financial advice
All of the lower-cost
Planet Money listeners get up to 6 months free
To learn more about betterment
Betterment.com Planet Money
The idea of burnout is not that all
The term wasn't even coined until the 1970s
It's by a guy named Herbert freudenberger
Psychologists in Manhattan
And he had a practice in a really ritzy area on the Opry
Practice was doing well it was thriving
Herbert wasn't satisfied
She was a very serious Driven Man
He was Holocaust Survivor
He fled Germany for the US when he was still just
His child kind of stopped at seven or eight
So you really did learn how to play cuz he had then had to grow up pretty quickly and surviving
New country
That's Herbert's daughter Lisa freudenberger Herbert died in 1999
We met with Lisa in Herbert's old office
She has her own psychology practice there now
In the states Herbert was taken in by his amp
She made him sleep in the Attic
Sitting upright in a chair
Herbert ran away and when he was a teenager he lived on the streets for a while
Gerber Grow Up to become someone who is always pushing himself to help people
And also to do more
In addition to his practice on the Upper East Side he opened up a storefront clinic on the Bowery which was New York Skid Row
Any work with drug addict
These young people were really
Struggling
Heroin
Cocaine
Acid
They were all becoming big problems back then
A lot of the kids he was working with words
Fried he would see them
Literally holding cigarettes and watch the cigarettes burn out
Herbert would work from 8 in the morning until
7 at night on the Upper East Side then you go down to the Bowery and work until 2 a.m.
With thousands of drug addicts
Filthy little free clinic
He began to get more and more fatigued
And he began to get stressed and he was
Not that Pleasant to live with what was that like was he a yeller was here
He had he didn't use his inside voice shall we say so
Tilly's kids tried to stay out of his way
His wife would say you look tired
And he'd say what do you want me to do
Abandon these people
When Lisa was about 5
Her mom finally said
Enough is enough we are taking the family on vacation
California
Plane tickets
Hotel reservations
Herbert got home
At 2 a.m. the day of the flight
And when it came time to wake up
Cape Cod
He was in bed for 3 days
He never took that vacation
And that was the moment he started to realize that something was really wrong
But he was a therapist
He thought maybe he could figure out what was going on with him
So he took a cue from Freud and he started self
Analysis
He would speak into a tape recorder for an hour or two
And then you take a little break
Kenny been analyzed
Himself as if he was
His own doctor
I don't know how to have fun
I don't know how to beat you really joyful this is Herbert freudenberger in an interview he did with the Shoah Foundation
I'm often very
Sad side
Play has not gotten me through
Something that I've avoided
I've never known how to do it
That's been hurtful
That's hurt me
Herbert realized what he was feeling
Wasn't just exhaustion
It was not exactly depression
It was something else
It has to do with how hard he was working how much he cared about his job and the fact
Didn't always feel like he was making a
Prince he was diagnosing something new
And he needed a word for
So his mind went to those drug addicts that he worked with down on the Bowery with
Their blank look
Cigarettes
Burning out
He called his illness
Burnout the same word that drug addicts use to describe themselves
See what a book about it
Burnout
High-cost
Of high achievement
And the concept
Totally took off all of these stressed out
Social workers
Doctors
Housewives of lawyers for like I have that
He felt like he was talking to them
But he was doing these radio shows around the country he was doing TV shows
Monday asked me how to wear makeup I was little worried
I like what's 14U makeup for kids
Is like well I think the Rings under my eyes a little dark I'm like so you need under eye cover
The TV
Herbert went on Oprah Phil Donahue
He met with President Jimmy Carter about burnout
He even came on NPR in 1981 are you forgetting appointments and deadlines are you increasingly irritable
Depressed fatigue
You may be suffering from burnout
NPR was going through like a psychedelic space Bernard Williams response to
The stress response to frustration it's a response to a demand that an individual my makeup on them self and turn
Pay requirements for protectionism or drive
Herbert became a burnout Guru
His book was a hit
Burnout
With officially a thing
But also not officially a thing because burnout never made it into the DSM that's the
Official listing of mental disorders from the American Psychiatric Association
In 240 years later companies are struggling with that
If I go to HR and say I'm burned out
There's no protocol
Still treated like an individual problem
Like no elsbernd. She should take a personal day
Not like there's a problem with the workplace
Insult people are left alone
I get depressed they start missing work
But while you pocket was talking to Megan bubble
About that terrible call sheet
We thought
This is a workplace problem
I'm going to fix it
Yes she did Leah is like a mix of head cheerleader and
In class
She radiates confidence she's always smiling so he's taking spin classes
And we should say Leah works
But off she will take calls on her days off
I just remember
Wedding I was at a year-and-a-half ago
Because I spent
Better
Part of the wedding in the lobby on the phone with a customer
I couldn't remember where I parked
I did my
So the first thing she did was something
Obvious
She cut down the number of calls or people were take
It was not uncommon
Seriously not uncommon
Someone doing over a hundred calls
IRS2Go
And
Let him know that if you're okay with people taking a hundred calls and feeling burned out you're going to have high attrition
Did you have to fight for that
I'm trying to imagine like
Finally the CEO said okay
You can have a few more employees
And that made a big difference to people's workloads down from 90 hundred calls a day
More like 60 call today
But burnout is about more than workload and research has proven this again and again and again
Tulia went into phase two of her beat burnout plan
Give people capes and call them Heroes
That is not
A metaphor
It's not
When we did our very first hero day we bought capes and had everyone wear capes really got into it
I know where's our case
At the call center workers at spothero are referred to as
Gyros
In addition to heroic
Appreciation day we started organizing a whole bunch of social of a
Bowling Happy Hours Pizza lunches
Talent show
Somebody the people taking customer complaint calls
Like the cool kids
They were doing all the fun stuff
They were the people having the best
We also wanted a place where people could go after a hard call
Sushi tuck this corner of the office and she
He converted it into a destress area called the shake.it.off area
After
Taylor Swift
It was stress balls
It was a corset a picture of Taylor Swift
I'm so walking over there was
But you know
A signal to everyone else
Hey I just got off of work really hard call I'm feeling
It right now
That sounds a little
Yeah I am going to jump a little cheese
The right but it worked
It's for employees like Megyn Kelly the woman who took that really terrible call
The biggest Testament do I want to be here I have not had one day where I woke up and I was like I can't go into the office today I don't want to go into
What's today like
Being able to wake up and not invite not have the Sunday scaries so we always joke about like
Because all my friends are at the office
What am I going to do if I'm at home
Styx
Edwin spothero move to new building
We got the CEO to take the
Shake It Off area
Can you tell me where are we right now
So right now we're sitting in this spot hero Zen Den
The Zen Den
Coloring books
Sand garden with little scraper
Big pouch sort of soothing colors everywhere
You got very into something called the
Buddha Board with anything with water and then it vanishes
Okay but, we were both a little bit skeptical
Why does zen room
Like why do you need this and why can't you just be like okay you're taking a hundred calls were going to have you take
Where's the fun in that
Then
Maybe they won't be burned out
How much work they have
But they'll be burnt out emotionally from
Feeling kind of like
Empty or not
Really thinking their work matters when
The birthday do is just
So
So important
The work they do is just so
So
Important
And this seems to be the final key
We Believe
Actually believe
Did the people who work in the call center are making the world
Better place
And she has somehow convinced everyone else at the company that this is the case
Executives the app developers the marketing team
Everybody it's bajirao is like
Fast with their call center
Truly we talked to one employee Margo conroe's and we tried to see if we could get her to
It's absolute reference
I mean we call them Heroes and we feel like
They are the heroes
The rest of us are trying to make a good product
And help our company grow
The customer heroes are on the front lines making those
You know those minut improvements to humanity all the time all day everyday
I mean you guys are an app that sells parking space
You're talkin about a department that
Is pretty minor in the grand scheme of your app
And
Which I see head-shaking by missing keep going and which a lot of companies take care of
With a website
Like frequently asked questions
And you're talking about Humanity that is really
Weird
I mean we think of them as another Heroes of the company
Because they're
You know
Heroes for individual
Humans are there in the world
But they just a customer complaints
Do they know
She was not going to break
Maybe she should because here's the thing
This culture that we are created at spothero
I said a pretty powerful
Result
Spothero call center has
Turn over nobody is quitting
And it's been this way for years
We haven't had
Anyone full-time leave
You know the
I actually honestly hadn't thought about it
Actual number
Was really next to zero companies are taking a similar approach
The Mayo Clinic is in a series of studies on burnout at
Problem for doctors and now male sponsors dinners were doctors
Convened
And bond and it started workplace training that helps people deal with stress
The important thing is that companies are naming it
This is burnout
That also turned out to be the key for Herbert freudenberger
Burnout Guru who was so fried he couldn't get out of bed
That and recognition and respect that he got for his work
His daughter Lisa says he's
Still worked Around the Clock
But he was able to enjoy his life
More when Lisa was about 9 he actually went on a family vacation
They went to Lake Carmel in Upstate New York
And there's her dad
Who was never not in a suit and tie
Wearing
Swimming trunks
And she realized he was like a different person
Come let me let me show you how I swim let me show you how I swim
He then got into the lake
And he proceeded to do a dead man's float
Waiting to see any flapping of the arms are flapping of the legs or
Something
State Fair
Got up with a
Biggest Granite I could see like this little boy
This inner child and I'm just
Florist in I'm so proud
Did you see me swimming on my
Chef dad
Fabolous
Fabulous
We want to hear story about how your workplace is changing
Could be a great boss like Aaliyah
Could be something else
Terrible boss
Email us at Planet Money at npr.org or find us on Twitter or Facebook
This episode was produced by Sally Helm thanks Ali
Special thanks also to dr. Richard Chaifetz and Jennifer Hudson at compsych Corporation Christina maslach at Berkeley
Weight piece and Whitney
Spothero Shawna Garrity and Josh grossberg from the Shoah Foundation
You're looking for another podcast listen to check out ask me another
Chess puzzles word games trivia
Is very fun
You can find ask me another on the NPR one app
Or go to npr.org
Also people sometimes ask us how they can support Planet Money
Actually there is something you can do
Donate to your local NPR station
Tell him sign it when he sent you
Helping them
Helps us
I'm Noel King and I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Thanks for listening
So we can put on a talent show for the call
Call center workers
And when we visited spothero everyone was talking about the song that one of the women there Laura O'Neill had
Performed
We got her to sing it
You can tell me
Never
Put you on home then I'm not
Farted
Loving you never gets old
Never get
Cuz you're up and I'ma here
The hate you give
Uniting