Record your message after the tone
Play Planet Money this is Cameron
In San Diego
I've always heard that money can't buy happy
But
Is there an income or wealth points
Where life satisfaction or depression changes
End of message
Jasmine gars
You and I are standing outside of an ATM in a bank in Midtown Manhattan
And at what are we doing
We're looking through the trash
We're digging through people's old ATM receipt
Because today on the show we are testing out an economic theory which says
My happiness
Depends not just on how much money I have
But it is also contingent on how much money other people have
So
At the moment I have about $1,500 in checking so we're here going through the trash to see how much money other people have
And how that makes us feel
I'm doing with surreptitiously because there is a security guard watching us I'm pulling up
I'm pulling out a handful of receipt Elga I think it's a piece of pork
Okay this person
This person has $250 in checking does that make you happier
No that doesn't make me happy or happy I do what we're looking for here is $0.01 in there
Count that does not make me feel happy at all
$5,000 okay
5035.
I feel like that's attainable
I don't feel like that makes me feel like
It makes me feel a little bad
It's checking
Oh
20 * 20291 and 4 cents in checking to
The exact does that make you unhappy it makes me feel like
I need to get my life in order you do need to listen to Lady
Hello and welcome to Planet Money on Noel King
And I'm Jasmine cars
Today on the show
Wait
What
And also why we asked you to send us questions about the economy that perplex and confuse
Use and frustrate you
And today on the show we will be answering some of those including the question Jasmine
Does more money make you happier and if it does
Planet Money is supported by Squarespace
Whether you own a small business or just need a professional portfolio
You should showcase your passion
Squarespace has the tools and website templates that you need to
To capture every detail of what makes your passion worth pursuing
Start your free trial
Today
Visit squarespace.com Planet Money
Set your website apart
Okay Jazz we have five questions on the show today
And the first one is
Can money buy happy
The simple answer is
Just like you and I probably don't quite agree on that
Neither do a lot of economist
But some have tried to answer it
We spoke to two of them
And we told them make your bed
The first Economist we spoke to is David blanchflower he works at Dartmouth
She studied the intersection of money and happy
So we asked in the first question
Does money buy happiness
And he said
Yes data shows it does
In fact the wealthier you get the happier you tend to be
And remember what we were doing at the top of the show how we were dipping our entire arms into ATM trash
Cancel
We were just doing that because we love sifting through garbage we were doing that because we were
Testing
David blanchflower Theory which is that our happiness
Depends not just on how much we have
But how much others
Relative things
So people get themselves a new BMW which is fine if nobody else
But if everybody else gets
The new one then people compare themselves to others
And relative happiness actually doesn't change so basically we're a bunch of haters
Please put me a pair to compare ourselves to others
Hello
But here we have an area of disagreement
Justin wolfers is an economist at the University of Michigan
And he told us he is very skeptical about the role of relativity
What really mattered
The people's well-being
With your income relative to other people I got a great proposition
You should leave New York
And go to Mexico
It was a small rural Mexican Village
Will you be easily the richest person in town
What matters is being rich really for the people that would make you and want to see happy
Do you think Jazz you'd be happier in a
Small Mexican Village
In fact
I would
I often fantasize
Moving to a small Mexican deli
But I don't think it would be about
Being richer
Then everyone
Yeah
Now here's a second big question that economist look at
Is there a point at which getting more money just doesn't make you any more happy
Which is there a limit
Here's David blanchflower again
Well it's certainly true that money can buy happiness
It's absolutely true
People with higher incomes are happier
But I actually as income Rises
What is the extra amount of happiness
35 fools
A famous quote that I've used it sucks is that supposed Arnold Schwarzenegger quote which says
My Syracuse million didn't make me as happy as my first
May 30th million didn't make me as happy as my first good quote it's a really good quote but is it true
Again Justin wolfers
Very skeptic
This is all very interesting
Asking social scientist about it
Is pointless
Social scientists don't know anything about what's going on among the ultra Ultra Ultra rich
Really why not
Well if you can get Arnold Schwarzenegger in Warren Buffett
Bill Gates to fill out survey forms for me all day tomorrow then we will have data
This like a full-on beef
It turns out not a lot of millionaires and billionaires answer a survey question
Since about money and happiness
They are too busy diving into their pools of money
Are the sinner Cameron
Something else too
Is there an amount at which
We become happy
The answer is
No we just we don't have an answer
There's not a number
Here's what we think you can take away
If you are making $50,000 a year you are probably happier than somebody making $25,000 a year
Someone making $100,000 a year
Probably happier than you
You're welcome
Jasmine thank you so much
And just this is your last show with us for a while
For a while I'm going off to report for a show called the world if so
Co-production
PRI and the BBC
Well we're going to miss you alot I'm going to miss you guys
Hi
This is Christopher test
And my question for the Planet Money
Is where did the idea that the FED should Target
2%
Inflation come from
Is there actual academic research
Suggest at 2% is better than 3% or 1%
Thanks
Okay so the question is
Where does the feds
Inflation Target of 2% come from
And Jacob Goldstein is here with an answer
Hell yes I have an answer I was very excited that we got a few questions with the light at the
Okay but before we get to the answer
Just do some fed 101
Okay it's been a long time since we didn't have to do it like every week is okay the FED is the Federal Reserve
The people who have the power to set interest rates in our country
This is a big Power
Right and it basically works like this
When the FED wants there to
To be more jobs
In America
They lower the interest
A lower interest rate makes it cheaper Forte businesses to borrow money
Right
So businesses borrow more money
They hire more people
Good
Good fireworks
This is good and this is what the FED does say
Intersection they lower the interest rate business hire more people great
But then you get to this point we're almost everybody who wants a job has a
So now people can start demanding raises right cuz everybody's got a job
And people start getting raises they have more money they're buying more stuff
Now prices start
May you have
Inflation
And now the FED gets
Worried that inflation is going to get to
Too high so
They do the opposite of what they did before
Before they lowered interest rate now they raise interest
This Rose is whole process in Two Rivers
Right in the feds job is to balance these two things
To have an economy with lots of jobs and not too much inflation so the question really is how do you put a
The number on not too much inflation I like
How do you pick an inflation Target that you're trying to hit
I called up Alan Blinder
He's an economist who is the vice chair of the Fed
Back in the back in the mid-90s
Not too much inflation question is a really hard question
He said in fact when he was at the fed the people there whose job was to decide what inflation tube
They couldn't
Some people thought we should be shooting
E-40
Some people thought we should be shooting for 2%
Some people were content with a 3% which is about where we were
But he told me that after he left the FED overtime
Over
Decades release
There was this conversion
This convergence on this
2%
Why 2%
What a splinter
That's a really good question
Because it's not so obvious that you was right
Okay it's still not happy
In fact you don't do the listeners question it's not like some precise
Academic answer where they did all kinds of experiments and whatever it's like
Poop like a pretty good number and and cures
Pictures of Reason Blinder
He said
You want inflation to be low obviously High inflation
But you really
Do not want inflation to go pillows
You do not want deflo
Right that means you have
Falling prices
And falling wages
And that is bad for people who have
That's it tends to lead to more bankruptcies it's just bad for the economy as a
So that's what the fallacy
Taking you know we don't want
And blenders
Defenders that whatever inflation rate at Targets they're not going to hit it like right exactly on the
Whatever Long Run Park
The central bank
Set
What you going to see in history if everything goes right is random fluctuations above and below is he
Economy gets buffeted by various
Higher lower
So if you're quite worried about going below zero
The deflation
That argues.
Give yourself a buffer
2 is a nice round number
It gives you a little wiggle room I like if we miss a little low we're still not going to be a thief
So to be clear blender says it took us a long time to agree on this info
And then after that they had to decide okay now we are ready to talk publicly
Tell the world
Until finally on January 25th
Mm
Ben Bernanke who was the chairman of the Fed
He had this press conference where
He dropped the bomb
The committee judges that inflation at the rate of 2
2%
Is most consistent over the longer run
Leather satchel
Mandate
Boom percent so here we are
4 years later
Last thing I'll say
It is a good thing that the FED gave himself that will
Because back beginning of 2012 when they announced
This target
Inflation was right there around 2
It fell below 2%
And to send for 4 years month after month after month
Inflation has been below 2% every month
So it's a good thing we have the buffer Jess
Jacob Goldstein thank you so much
Thanks man who's fun
Christian about Kirk and I just wanted to ask if you guys would consider doing a story on Wars that have
Started
Do the abundance or lack of access
Different commodities
Such as sulfur whale Alero
Or today now crude oil
Thank you
Taker
Hi Noel ACC
How's it going
Pretty well pretty well what do you got
So my question had to do with
Wars that
Overcome
Commodities
This
End
It is a such a
Just almost every come out as you can
Can think of has involved
Let me just give you a list
Salt sugar water
Bananas saffron bread
Gold Cobalt
Gas
Silverton tungsten
Tantalum
Wheat
Tea
Opium
Cocaine
Rice
Saltpeter what is saltpeter and how does it differ from saltpeter is like
Gunpowder base
Wars fought
Yeah you mean stuff in order to fight the wars and some people have wars over septic
Used to fight Wars
Of course
Bauxite
Plutonium
There was a Guana War there was a war fought over guano like that
Like bird droppings it was in the 1800's and it was these islands off of
Peru
Vet Hanover
All these centuries of bird droppings and they discovered that they were very helpful and growing things
And there was a war
Durbin Lumber their Budweiser for beaver pelts
I asked her looking through all this I think I've identified
What must be like the single
Deadliest
Item
In the world
And I have it for you
What
You have it you have it in person yeah yeah yeah
Dunkin Donuts
Don't be fooled this is deadly
Okay hang on
It is a cinnamon roll
You yeah you accidentally gave me your cinnamon roll and called it a deadly commodity
Is there an accident
This is
A blood-soaked
Death is like
Wrapped up in the
Super Stovall
There's the sugar
Sugar
The endless wars fought over sugar in the
Super bloody
Sleepman mm mm
The cinnamon itself the spice trade
Was just in
Violet it was mostly ruled by
By the Dutch
And there were multiple worse by 2%
Cinnamon and Nutmeg which there is a tiny bit in the cinnamon roll
There were multiple nutmeg Wars
Imagine going over nutmeg
But there were Wars over nutmeg also we
Big lot of wheat Wars right room in Egypt
French Revolution partly
Over some
Weed issues also I figure you know oil was involved
Delivery of the cinnamon roll
So there's oil wrapped up in there
This is just an incredibly deadly item I will never look at cinnamon rolls the same way again
Stacey Vanek Smith
Went down the rabbit hole re-emerged
Carrying cinnamon roll thank you so much
You're so welcome enjoy your Seminole
Alright Robert get on in here
11 question
I do it is not a subject near and dear to my heart
International postal rates
Hi my name is Jeff khaki so I live it in Seattle my sister lives in Sri Lanka
And I how could it be that I could send a letter to my sister and she Lanka
And to Vancouver Canada and which is just a few hours away
For the same rate
Is that really true that is really true let me show you something right here
This right here
Is an international Forever stamp cost a dollar fifteen
Shape of a bun and you put a letter and it will go anywhere
In the world
I know I did this a real thing and of course that's amazing because there's some places
That are much harder to get to
Where do you think the most expensive place
In terms of the cost and end
What is the most expensive place to send a letter
So I'm going to guess it's
The country with
Bad infrastructure
And maybe the US has some
Problems with it
So Sudan
Central African Republic
Yeah see where you going with that but you're thinking in the wrong
Directions
Because I talk to a postal expert
And he said listen most of the cost of delivery
Is paying salary
Paying the mailman and mail women
To deliver it at the end and so
He speculated the country
What is the most expensive descent 2 is Norway
Because the mail men and women are like paid really it's so very expensive
Countryman
And so if you send a letter to a place like China or India it is much much much cheaper because the labor cost parasoul
Soap to Interjet
Question that like why are we charged the same amount to gota
Vastly
Different countries
And really that's just for the
Use of the
These are sending a letter they don't you have to
Standing by the post office and be like well
Was it cost to get a piano stand
Norton Norway
Zimbabwe
Look at what you charge an amount that we know
Covers all the international
Dolphin
Dollar 15
Now Jessica did have a follow-up question
This is where it gets
Even more complicated is one rate
Then who pays for what like how who pays for the boat that goes across the ocean or the airplane that flies that your lawn
Ponca City to get my posted bear and vice versa
I mean if I send a letter to Sri Lanka for a buck
How much money does the US keep and how much does
Sri Lanka
So I went over this with Jim Campbell
Hefei postal consultant
And he said there's actually an organization called the
I was going to International
I think it's the universal
Postal Union
Cannot be real
It is a real thing there's a meeting right now in Istanbul and what they do there is they argue about the details of
Who pays
For what
You know what other words what serve little share of stamp Revenue goes to
Sri Lanka if Sri Lanka is doing the final delivery of the letter
So I'm imagining this like big boom and there's all these
Male ladies and mailmen
And in their in their shorts and they parked their little wheelie bags and then they kind of
Yell at each other always have $0.40 to $0.52
That was like going to the gym the postal Consulting he said
Now we wear suits
Well my question
Is about ensuring
Insurance is at the top of the Planet Money pyramid of the
Nerdy things that we care about
You know what I like
This question because we got it from more than one per
So we did a thing
It seems like
Here is Dave Allen
So I recently moved from Columbus Ohio to Alameda California
And transferred my Auto in
From Ohio to California
And I was floored when my
2011 Hyundai Elantra went from
$390 for every
2 / 900 every 6 months your insurance more than doubled
Yes yes for the exact same coverage
Exact same
Driving record
Same car
Why does his insurance.
Alright here's what I liked about Dave
He had theories
The first one
He said look
Maybe labor costs are higher in
State Farm agents get paid more like the mail carriers in Norway
I checked that is not
Second
Reasonable idea he said since he moved to California he's seen all of these really
Sick cars on the road
Tesla to keep seeing test
Maybe it's
The cars are $100,000 cars anymore insurance
Premium goes up
So I asked an actuary about that theory
Amy said
It's not about they're actually
He said that will bump up your premium but only about 5%
And Dave's
Doubles
So it's something
Stripes
Evening the actuaries name is Bob Hunter
I need to listen there's hundreds of variables that go into
Determining how much
To pay for your insurance
But
In the state of California which is where they've moved
There is a
Big one
If you look at that one of the key drivers of racing is traffic density
And California has some of the
Mustard's traffic to LA San Francisco
In the nation
Wait a minute like I know that's true there's a lot more cars on the road but I found
Lower
Of an accident you might
Think and yet
More cars on the road means
More things to hit
If you're out in the middle of nowhere a little distraction you can have a lot of Destruction still be going down the street road and
Nevada I mean in Nebraska
But if we have a little bit of distraction in Manhattan
If you got an accident
Totally make sentence cityman
Density test
Bob the actuary told me he still didn't really think they
Premium should have
CC
Treat mites and in fact
Text Dave after he heard $900
He was so taken aback
That he haggled with the agent a little bit and he got about a hundred and fifty bucks knocked off
So that actually suggest
Another. I'm going to pause it here which is now in California
People sometimes just
Charge more and hope that the
Rich people in California will pay for
So that agent was Clear Lake
Maybe he'll pay
You don't mess with a guy for
From Columbus Ohio
Exactly
We love to hear what you guys think of the show email us at
Planet Money at npr.org
Also while we're at it what's the best money story you've told a friend recently
Send it to us
We might make it into a podcast
You can find us on Facebook or Twitter at Planet Money
And also I should say to Art International
Listeners because we're not interested in the concept of international postage rates
Why don't you send us
A postcard
Send it to Robert Smith
NPR we're at 11 West 42nd Street
19 floor
New York New York 10036
They're going to come
I want a pilot postcards from all around the world
Especially from Norway
Find us the most expensive rare postal system
Also we did a show this week with NPR politics but the first presidential debate and coming
This Tuesday October 4th
Is the vice presidential
Debate
The next morning NPR politics
Podcast will have
The whole scoop on it
Play watch it
They'll tell you what happened
And what it all means
That is the NPR politics podcast
Private listen on the NPR one
Car show today was produced by Sally helm
Special thanks also to producer Nick Fountain and to Elizabeth kulas and Rena Cohen
I'm Robert Smith thanks for listening