Support for NPR and the following message come from service now making the world of work
Work better for people
Their cloud-based platform and solutions deliver digital workflows that create great experiences and
Unlock productivity for your whole company
More at servicenow.com
Long before there were light bulbs
There was fat
For thousands of years if you wanted to light up your cave your mud-hut or if you were really lucky Your Castle
You had to find some fat
Something to use for a wick
Maybe some Moss maybe a piece of fabric
Light it on fire
This was not easy
Even today
It's a hard way to get light
Yeah hi do you sell
Fat Moody fat
No
So I don't carry.
Okay thanks very much
A high
Giselle love
Fat like beef fat
Suet
Okay
Thanks very much
Yeah hi I do sell beef fat how much is that
Okay great thanks very much you're welcome by
I got to lb
A big nasty lump of fat came from around the couch kidney
I got some twine from the hardware store
And I went home to my apartment to try and make candles
A little harder to catch up then
You might think
Sticks to itself
I put the fat on the stove
It's pretty melted
Smells
Really nasty
Animals nasty
Stranded then I started dipping the Wicks into it
Dipping dipping
You have to let the fat dry when you have to dip the wick some more
Dipping
Was Eddie
I don't know 45 minutes or so of dip
Dip
I got kind of dip crazy in there
After hours of work
Not counting raising the cow or killing the cow or making the twine
I had six
Piney
Crooked
Smelly
Candles
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Jacob Goldstein and I'm David kestenbaum today on the show
Story of how we got from dim little candles made out of cow fat to as much light as we want at the flick of a switch and
I don't think I'm exaggerating here this one little story it explains why we are where we are today
People don't have to worry about starving today while we aren't all subsistence Farmers why we can't afford to have artists and massage
Therapist and plumbers and yes radio reporters doing stories about the history of life
Support for this podcast
Send the following message come from mrs. field who wants to help you delete your friends family and clients this holiday season
At mrs. Fields. Calm it's easy to send handcrafted treats to anyone anywhere choose from classic
Chocolate chip pan frosted buttercream cookies or Rich and flavorful Bundt Cakes all baked fresh and packaged
Holiday cheer to order visit mrs. Fields. Calm and use code NPR to save 20% at checkout
It also lets mrs. Fields know you appreciate npr2
Jacob you brought these scraggly little candles in the office I'm holding him up here they look
Gnarled
But definitely not straight and they're not like sleek
Now it looks like some mold has grown on a
On a string
My strength
So you brought these candles in the office here and we wanted to show them to
Expert
Sat down with this woman Jane brox
Jane read a book
Brilliant
The evolution of artificial light
So I made a few different candles
I tried
Beautiful Disaster
In the in the olden days
If a mother was trying to teach your daughter to make candles
She would not be pleased with his candle but we'll see what happens
I was afraid when we let these things that we might set off the fire alarm or
Sprinkler system in the office I mean that is how weird it is to have light from fire than
I was afraid we weren't going to be able to light him at all it's just be fat and Twine
But we pulled out a lighter
We have we have light
Should we see how long it lasts
It's not pretty but I'm very impressed
What colors would have been nice yellow flame wouldn't you say
Doodieman a candle
Jane says that the Quest for this
Something that gives you light
After the sun goes down
Go people to do all kinds of
In the United States
In the Pacific Northwest
Native Americans used
Dried
Salmon
Basically made a Salmon Canned
In the tropics people would catch fireflies and try to make
Can a firefly Lantern
And then there's this bird
Call the Petro
The storm Petrel
And then north of Scotland where they would just
At which is a very oily seabird
Which they catch and dry
And
Thread a wick down its throat and then light it and
The net was a lamp
Chiron a dead bird is that
And I would imagine they'd have a little storage area with a lot of dead
Storm Petrel
Martha we need another petrol
The petrol supply is getting low ways of making light where all
A huge house
They took a lot of work
It was not just that I didn't know what I was doing when I made those candles
Writer Harriet Beecher Stowe said
Making candles from animal fat with
7 times as bad as washing clothes
Let me think about it you got to get a cow
You got a raise the calorie going to have food to feed the cow you got to kill the cow you got to get the fat out of the couch
You got to put the fat in your Cuisinart
Which isn't going to be invented for a hundred years
From an economic perspective if you want to try to quantify how much of a pain in the butt it is to make something or at least
How hard is it to get that thing
You can ask a simple
How much does it
It cost
Bill nordhaus Anaconda Misty yellow while back got obsessed
He decided he wanted to calculate exactly how expensive light was
Thousands of year
And how that caused change
Because light you know light is this thing Society has needed and sought
Forever
It was a way to track progress
Not just in light but in all kinds of thing
Unfortunately in order to do this
He needed to know how much things cost thousands of years ago
Like an ancient Babylon
It was even true those numbers existed
But they did
I ran into a woman that yeah
And she believe it or not she is just
Unbelievable actually
She actually had wage data and price data
From
The Babylonian era
4000 years ago
Now he has these numbers but he needs to know one other thing
How much light are people getting for their money
In ancient Babylon people used lamps
4 light
So nordhaus
Decided to make
I did this in my dining room
Where else
Devised an ancient style lamp from a catalog he gets it burning
Measure how bright it is he borrows a light meter from a facility sky at Yale
Andy
Does some science
And that would just make sure it didn't write it down to just the way you see in the
In the old movies are some guy with men is lab coat running down the measurements
Jacob
I'd little note here I happen to be taking nordhaus is economics class right around this time
Which I was a was a pretty serious like no-nonsense
Class and it's so funny for me to think that the night he was going home and measuring ancient
Lamp placement is dining room with a lightning
Who does this the light meter the ancient lamp
You have to figure out a way to compare the price of light over thousands of years
So here's one measure heat
If you take a day's wait
You work all day you take all the money or
And you spend it on
How many minutes
Could you light up a small
With as much light as you get
Today's modern
Your dancer for ancient battle
Maybe 10 minutes
It was really
An entire day's wages got you the equivalent of
10 minutes of light from a kind of dim light bulb
Economist talked a lot about productivity
How much one person
And back then the answer was not much
Everything was hard
Growing food was hard
Making candles for instance took hours
Use of fat
Fat which by the way was expensive because raising animals
This was a world where when the sun went down almost everyone lived in the dark
And this might sound sort of romantic but basically it was awful
The dark was not some beautiful thing you went out and explored
It was dangerous
What's something that trapped
In Paris at one point it was actually a law that said
Every night everybody has to give their keys to a magistrate go home and lock themselves in the house
For basically 4000 years
Very little hot
With light
Are we the economy in general
Most people work all day
Naked women
The way things get better
The way an economy grows the way people get richer
Where is that
Someone
Comes up with a better way to do something
A way to take a little less work
Overtime there are small improvements in life
And in light
The Romans figure out how to make a lamp that's a little more efficient
People start use whale oil this of course is very very bad for whales but
Wheels have a lot of fat they were like these big
Swimming sources
The fuel
Still even when you get all the way to the 1700
Like still looks more like ancient Babylon than the modern world
People still travel the same way by foot by horse by sailing ship
Most people are still subsistence farmers
Usually living in some kind of Hut
Trying to grow enough food not to starve to death
Yorkshire are there are tiny games in product
Little bits of acne
But not a lot
And Light
Light still comes from finding stuff that's flying around in
Lighting it on fire
Again Economist Bill Nord
You look at the picture
Love what happened here
Its economic history in a nutshell
From Babylonian time to round 1800
They were even though that were improvements as best we can tell
They were very modest
And then around 1800 in the lighting you can see it so clearly and Lighting
Just a
Enormous change
In the pace
Of improvement
What happens in the 1800's is
A few things
We start to really actively Xperia
We try to discover
And around 1850 a guy in Canada
Comes up with something that's not just a slightly better Wick or a slightly more efficient lamp
It is this magical liquid
With the right techniques you can get it from cold
Royal
This big breakthrough
Heresy
Not cutting-edge now but back then Jane boxes
Kerosene was a huge deal
When the first kerosene lamps came out it was
As one historian said it was
Kind of oil people have dreamed about for centuries
It was brighter it was cleaner
And importantly
It was much cheaper
You work a day you got
About an hour
Whale oil
Kerosene
You get
About
5 hours
Wow so it's about
5 *
More efficient
Kerosene
Let the world and save the whales
So if kerosene was so great
Why did it take the world so long to find
Science
This idea of professional scientists this idea that there are lots of people who go to work every day at universe
Mercedes and do experiments
In the 1800 this is still a new thing
If you happen to be president of Yale University this is around the time when you're thinking you know
Maybe we should get one of those
Science
Why what why would they doing those experiments a century earlier
Well you didn't have scientists A Century earlier they would teaching Greek
General teaching logic
Now all the scientists are working on better ways to make light
And life is getting cheaper
More people are using it
No more locking yourself in and huddling in the dark all night
Around this time streetlight starpop
People start going out at night
So we have kerosene what's the next big Advance after that
Okay next big Advance after that is
The electric lamp
The big one
Well you might think so
Cheetah Jacob I thought I knew the story of the Lipo
Call Pino Thomas Edison the great inventor
Story about science and Innovation unit
Trying all these different filaments these different designs and finally getting one little glow for hours but
This Eureka lightbulb moment it is not
It's not enough to get you to the world of really cheap light
Cuz Edison needed this other thing
He needed money she needed a lot
And lots of money
Why
You can't light a light bulb without electricity
He needed to build a power plant
Right now where the location of the original Power Plant in lower Manhattan this is Paul Israel he's an
Edison scholar we met him here in New York City
We're standing in front of this
Plaque
Thomas Alva Edison in big letters
There's this picture
And the image of a show is the generator room of the power
With a bunch of guys in a really long mustaches
This is 1882
So what's of mustaches
The money part of building a power plant is so important that when they finally get this historic thing
Completed in 1882 they get the power play
My bill
And they're ready to turn it on
Edison is not here
He's a few blocks away as a big impressive stonebwoy
Where today there is another plaque
You may have heard of
JP Morgan
It reads
The capitalist capitalist
Known throughout the world of Finance
Sought out by presidents
Helped
Bankroll the industrialization
Can write that I'm too many people
JP Morgan Bank and a bunch of investors
They put up money for
The power plant
Pretty clear they built this great big expensive comp
Placated power station
First Central Power Station in the world right basically inventing
Electric light
And when they turn it on Edison is not there
Right he was
Where he needed to be with the people who had funded the whole thing right
Show 3 p.m. on September 4th Edison flipped on the switch
Here at JP Morgan's office
And what happened
It went on
Acid lights all over the disk
Bar square mile of lower Manhattan
Subway
Was lit by Electra
You think of Edison the inventor
But even more important
Is Edison the businessman
At the time buildings in lower Manhattan were running off gas light
Edison knew that was who we had to
We spent a lot of time thinking about economic
Notebooks
Constantly he's going through and comparing the cost of what he's doing to what the cost
You never think about that
Well and that's what made him such a good innovator
Right casino
You recognize that
These economic questions were just as important
In designing what he did in Labrador
When you think of economic growth how much do you think of it is coming from like
Individual like Eureka moments and inventions and stuff like that and how much is it to stuff around it
Likeability Define enticing
The economic structure
So most of it is actually the structure around
Light a square mile of lower Manhattan Edison needed the whole financial system
Do you need a patent
A way to protect his ideas so no one would steal them
Uneeda doll company
Away a bunch of different investors could come together and risk money a lot of money
To build a power plant
Play wire so you can try this crazy thing
Light Without fire
Edison comes along at a time when all this machinery
Patents corporations Banks is in place
They were consequences
Aminos first power plants burn coal
And pollution was pretty bad
Edison built a huge power plant on the east side of Manhattan and at some point the City Health Department got involved and
Is according
New York Times quote
When it was found Health Department men were trying to photograph the smokestacks Scouts were put on the company's roof ordered the feeding
King of Cole stopped whenever photographers of
The other hand you know how to City lit up with cheap electric
Trade off
Around this time everything is getting faster
Cheaper
Scientist keep making new discoveries
You get the internal combustion engine
The tractor
For the first time in human history most people don't have to work as farmers
This went on decade after decade all through the 20th century
All continents got much cheaper
Like light
And if you look at the
Really long Arc here it's
It's amazing me go all the way back to the battle on
Okay
Babylonians
You worked all day you got the equivalent of
10 minutes
10 minutes of light
4000 years later in the 19th century with kerosene lamps
Things are better
Day labor gets you five hours
And by the time nordhaus does his light study in the 1990s
If you work today
How much light do you get
Maybe 20 thousand
20000 hours
I mean you basically you you have your
You have your house lit up you have your streets lit up you have your all your
Equipment on you have your air conditioner on your all the stuff you're doing is
Are saturated with lighting the main thing is your statue look like
Economic growth isn't all good
There's pollution their environmental consequences
But fundamentally
Growth is about things getting faster
Getting cheaper
Getting more efficient
About doing the same amount of work
And being able to buy
20000 hours
Of light instead of 10 minutes
And as a result about being able to work less
What to buy other stuff that used to be just for the wealthy
We can buy books
We can take vacation
Even today there are still people who go to work everyday
Try to figure out how to make a better light bulb
This morning I went to
The ball Factory for about an hour
This is John Edmund is one of the founders of a company called
Creed they make LED light bulbs which of course are much more efficient than regular
You'll make you'll try an experiment you'll say holy crap we just got
More light out of this thing
By using
This contact material or flipping the chip over
Jacob when we talk about economic growth every year you know one
When we say the economy grew a couple percent
That happens because every day out there
Someone somewhere in some corner of the
He has figured out how to do something a little bit better
Where are a little bit fast
Our little blessings
And this process is going on year after year for hundreds of years
I want question I always have it when I think about this is like
And not just with light
But this whole story of constant
Economic growth
My question is is it going to go on forever
Or some point we going to run out of ways to make things
We might
We might double from where we are now
But we're not going to be triple and quadruple
Cuz there are physical limit
Iowa cargo many miles an hour now
It just won't it just it's not going to happen
For the light bulb at least Johnson
We may actually be near
The show originally aired in 2014
Can email us at Planet Money at npr.org you couldn't find us on Facebook or Twitter Today Show was originally produced
By Caitlin Kenney and Damiano marchetti the rerun was produced by Sally Helm if you're looking for something else to listen to
To check out radio ambulante it's in Spanish that has stories about everything from punk rock in Cuba
2 junk Bonds in Puerto Rico posted by Danielle arcone he's novelist you can find it on the NPR
At NPR. Org / podcast or wherever you get your podcast I'm Jacob Goldstein thanks for listening