A couple weeks ago we did a show about the massive banking scandal at Wells Fargo
How good employees were pushed to do some Very Bad Things
Like
Open up bank accounts
The customers Nebraska
And after the show aired we talked to ex employees who said you know what that fraud the wrong doing the stuff was going on
That's only
Because
What happened at Wells Fargo is still haunting many of us even
Years after
One of these ex-employees was
Jeremy he worked at a Wells Fargo branch in LA
Pekin 2008
He just wanted to move on with his life
I probably applied to every major Bank out there from Bank of America Washington Mutual Wachovia
It was a stressful time this is 2080
The world economy was collapsing
His wife was pregnant
And Jeremy wasn't making any progress
Until he got a lead on a banking job up in Silicon Valley
So I drove up to San Francisco I left about 3 a.m.
And made it up there in time for the interview
Forget me with this guy really nice guy
And you said listen man
You're exactly what we're looking for
You got the drive
Motivation
You know you know the industry
Let's go ahead and let's
Go through the formalities
Get y'all on the job
I've got so excited call to my wife
Looks like we're moving to San Francisco
Alright next day feels that some forms for the HR department
Check a few things
Xiaomi wait a couple of days
Wait a couple more days
Doesn't he
After about a week
Finally game
The HR lady at Collins at 8 just want to follow up
See what's going on in the process she said
I'm sorry we went with another candidate
I just sat there hung up the phone
I thought to myself
I thought I had this job what happen
Jeremy found out the answer
To this question
Just a few weeks
After another interview
A different bag
The hiring manager truck
Jeremy by the arm
And put him outside
And she says listen
I'm not really supposed to say anything because it's an HR issue but I'll tell you
I really liked you but apparently there was a blemish on your on your securities licenses that
HR says that we can't hire you
She said was on a document called a u v
This is a form in the banking in
Essentially it is a report card from all your former employers
And journey
Jamaican even know it
And yet someone had written something on there that made him on Hiram
And I said what the heck is it
Cuz I don't know I
That's all I was told by HR
But Jeremy was pretty sure he knew who wrote the comic
It was his former employer Wells Fargo
This moment right here has been playing out all across the
Country we've talked to former Wells Fargo employees
Florida New Jersey
Pennsylvania Los Angeles San Francisco
They all say the same thing
They say they pushed back again
Get the crazy sales culture at Wells Fargo
And retribution the back of Mark them with a Scarlet Letter
And that's really hurt their careers
Hello and welcome to Planet Money on Robert Smith
And I'm Chris Arnold
Prudential we continue our investigation into the third largest bank in the country into Wells Fargo
And we go deep into this mysterious document that Jeremy found out about it's called the u v
I'll tell you where it came from a Wells Fargo branded their workers with it
And how hard it's been
For people like Jeremy to fight back
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Google and Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and a beautiful Business website
Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email end
Professional tools from Google
It's the simplest way to look professional online
Visit squarespace.com Google to start your free trial
Use offer code small biz
For 10% off your first purchase
Google and Squarespace
Make it professional
Make it beautiful
Sorry Chris I'm holding in my hand
The document
That ruined Jeremy's
It's called the u v and
For something that is incredibly powerful
Can be incredibly destructive
Check out how boring
Looks pretty innocuous unless it's like something you fill out at the DMV is 24 pages of boxes and lines a little star
At the top here at that Jeremy's full name he only wants to use his first name cuz he doesn't want to
His career to be hurt even more
Before we reveal what was written on this u5 we wanted to tell you how the document how do you find was
Supposed to be
Because
Believe it or not
Bu5 had good intent
Right and Banking and investment
It's a little bit like the wild west mean someone would take your money
And you have to trust that they wouldn't run off with your life savings
And there weren't a lot of people out there enforcing the
But we found one of them
One of these early investment-banking Sheriff's
He even has the voice of Ash
My name is Tom Krebs and I'm a Securities attorney in Birmingham Alabama
Were You There When the form known as the
The u v was born
Yes
You were there
IWatch
This was in the late 1970s
Tom was working for the Alabama State
Securities Commission
Is the people responsible for keeping an eye on all the stockbrokers and investment folks in Alabama
Back in these days there was a big salad reliable bags and invest
But there were also a lot of Conures
Boiler room so you got some
Office in New Jersey with a bunch of crooks selling bogus Investments over the
Then wasn't a bad guy there were a heck of a lot of bed
There were
Boiler rooms operating
All over the country they were oil and gas salesman
Dumping
Fraction 1 divided working interest on Alabama and I don't understand what that is but it sounds bad
Who is
Fraction 1 divided working entry
Basically it was part ownership in an oil well
If people would hop these as investment opportunities over the phone
We put one salesman in jail for having sold
Entrance to a widow in Montgomery Alabama
4 of 13 and 1/2 foot well
And my guess is there wasn't much oil down 13 and a half feet
That it was nothing but still texts and
You do not mess with
Tom crabs
Alabama State
You do not but Tom fell
That when they shut down one scam
His power only went so far the people working the phones
They move to another state
You start dying again
The problem was that there was no Central Point
Where
A person could call
And determine whether or not the person on the other end of the phone from them was indeed a licensed security salesperson
So Tom and the other state investment cops developed a computerized reporting system
Central place 2
Keep track of the con man in the Dodger bankers
Are they required legitimate investment firms in bag
X22 make a note if they fired somebody if the employee was involved in
Broader
Was being investigated
That would get written down to that boring form that we were just looking at
Do you fart
What's up with the letter u
Avenue5 does you stand for something
Uniform
And was there a you one two three four
There is a u4 and I think there is a you free I'm not certain about wanting to
So this new system it was uniform standard
Tom says it's a lot of
And make sure the conman couldn't just hop from company to
The company
Bank-to-bank
And it wasn't just for investment
All bags could use this database
They could fill out a little note on a Troublesome or maybe a dishonest
Employee
Not every employee to back by the way has to have a u v but the ones that handle Investments do and there's a lot of them
And the next man could just check out the u5 before they hire someone
Read with the last bank wrote and make the decision
Essentially it set up a system whereby the banks were policing themselves
It saved us a lot of time and a lot of resources
So
This is the way it was supposed to work
A simple reporting tool for good Banks
Stop bad employees
What happens when the bank itself
Becomes the problem
Panera Bread manager
This is what we're hearing happened at Wells Fargo
Bu5 became a weapon away to threaten and punish employees
Read it if you remember our last podcast we were following this
Former Wells Fargo employment Ashley
And
If she didn't mean to sales go
Call so they call him
Solutions
Two managers would take her into a back room
Lock the door
And a teller
If you don't meet your Solutions you will be
Fired and it's going to be on your
Permanent record
I mean it was real like you were
Stuck in it was
The feeling that no other employer is going to watch you because we will
Ruined you
Ashley to know if they were exaggerating at the time but later she found out that they weren't joking around she was fired
We help your track. Are you 5 and right there on her you five
It says quote failed
To perform
Job duties
She said that makes
If it sound like she
Do I work
And she hasn't been able to get a job at a bank
Fence
She's working for 12 bucks
An hour
And you know even employees who were
Being yourself
How do you say that Wells Fargo was using the you five against them too
Jeremy the employee we heard from at the beginning of the show
Louisiana jobs
He says that his Wells Fargo Bank branch was kicking ass they were doing great
And he was being rewarded
And I can tell you one time
I got invited to go to a Lakers game
And we'll smother Branch management
The district manager
Couple of the branch manager just sat down next to me and said how are you guys getting yourselves
What is your secret
So I broke it down for
I said here's what it is there's a lot of people are rats that are doing some shady things
That is hitting your sales numbers by giving customers credit cards or checking accounts that they never asked for
In the bag that was called gaming your salesman
And everybody in the branch
You about this
But this was Jeremy's chances are what was going on with
Opera Mini
Tell the truth
I told that the other manager is
Including the district manager about
The gaming that was going on and how I didn't
I didn't approve of it I didn't like it
That was kind of a pivotal moment for me where I realized something was kind of weird going on
I spoke too much
It got back to my to my manager
Annie's like buddy
What's going on here
My Bankers don't game
You know this
Thanks. Got a cold and awkward
For Jeremy
In the office right after
His manager
One day
Pull them over
And get them on the phone with the district manager and makes him take back everything he said.
Basically told me
Lifeline
Life on
Jeremy kept complaining
Though he called the company's ethics line setup to the
Detect fraud
But nothing happened
2000's called into his manager
Jeremy said he was told basically
He could quit
Or the bank was going to open an investigation into
Weather ckp
Apple account without their
There's a good chance that that happened
He be fired
So anyway I went to lunch and came back and I said
No I'm out of here
I'm done
Jeremy walks out of bank
Totally confident that he's going to get another job but of course
He does not he's turned out time
And time and time again
That woman tells him there's a problem with your document a problem with your youth Ivan all of a sudden
The whole thing comes back
You have to call up Wells Fargo his former employer
And say hey
Send me a copy of that
I finally received the overnight mail I open it up and when I read what they wrote on there
I couldn't believe it might how is shocked they had blatantly lied on my new 5 saying that I am
Admitted to opening up fraudulent accounts I didn't open a present at the counts I was the one saying that this is
What's going on
And so
If that's what it hit me when I read this for the first time that they were retaliating against me for what I
Lighted
To be clear
We don't know if Jeremy opened accounts for customers who didn't want them
He said he didn't
The back put on music
Do 5:30 did
We don't know if the bank is retaliating against Jeremy for
Blowing whistle or if it actually had a good cause to fire him
This right here is
The point of this whole story
We don't know what really happened
Because the u v is not set up like a
The court of law
We're both sides
Tell their story and a judge decides
At the banks
Have almost all the power
They don't have to show any evidence
It's just there were
The back does have to send a copy to the
Employee
But that can be after it's all done and written and the worker doesn't have any say
Jamie says
In his case
He did not eat
Even see his u5
Is the backside of the Rock address
So how do you fight this whole thing
Jeremy look
And he was
Blown Away by how much it was going to cost
The lawyers Wanted chart Panda $20,000 retainer and there is no guarantee that anything was going to be fair
Text it was just merely to get them to say okay I'll work for you
Doesn't mean anything will be done
What you want to challenge that you 5 you are stuck in their system
With their rule
Foo Fighters run by an organization
Spinraza
AP financial industry regular
Latorre Authority
Which sounds like a government organization right but
It is not
Finra is an industry group
With Executives from Financial firms running the play
On their board we talked to a recruiter who works her bags
And we showed her Jeremy's case
And she said basically he's out of luck
If you really thought that he had a case
You should pay whatever it takes
Free lawyer because no one
We going to hire him with this Market
There may be one other way for
He's in contact with a lawyer
Please bring me a Class Act
Action lawsuit
On behalf of former Wells Fargo employees
Detroit his name is Jonathan delshad
A lot of the employees at call me
The one thing they're asking me for it looked my u5
Will you call the bank and report card
Is it possible through your lawsuit to get my u5 cleaned up
Cuz that's what I care about the most
Play some jobs in other Industries but they put they wanted to do Bank Nevada career in banking
We wanted to see what the industry had to say about all this so I called up finra
The organization
Runs that you five
System
And I was asking them look I mean we're hearing about this from all these workers who say they can't get rehired and it seems like a really big problem
Are you guys doing anything about this
And
Today they actually told me something new
They said
We are doing so
About this we started a review
Of the u5 forms that were filed by Wells Fargo
Your so they're taking another look at the
They wouldn't give you a lot of details that wouldn't say
How many workers
For how long a period of time
But they're taking another look
And this could be a big deal
We have also been calling Wells Fargo
For their side of
Dory and they provide a statement to us
It said quote
It's disturbing to hear claims of
Retaliation against
Team members
The bank says it to vet
Getting those claims in the bank also says
If assisting former employees to be rehired
When possible
And as for Jeremy the guy with the blemish on his you five
He actually found
A workaround
And what he discovered was in consumer banking where
He'd been working
They would always check it
By putting business bag
Helping out small businesses open
Right
He heard
Often they won't check the
So we reach acordes resume scored another interview
Anixter
I need a job I got the job and I was set to go and so
So far so good
He's moving up in the banking world
You making more money
Success
But Jeremy still works
There's this bad comment from Wells Fargo it's still there
Like a landmine
How does u v
And someday somebody might
I try not to think about it be honest with you
Scares the crap out of me I can everything that I've worked for these past eight years can be taken away from me because of this
This planet because of this lie because of this this one statement that Wells Fargo in
Put on there Wells Fargo has apologized for a lot of things
They have not yet talked about what happen
Open to their ex employees after they left a couple
And Jeremy and his other employees we talked to they all say the backhoe is it today
To get this career-ending stain off the Record
We're going to keep pursuing this Wells Fargo story so if you worked at the bank and there is some surprising part
Are the Scandal that we don't yet know
You should contact us
Especially
If you're one of the people
Who wrote
Out negative comments on someone else
If you fought
We would love to talk to you
You can email us at Planet Money at npr.org
Or reach us on Twitter or Facebook
Today Show is produced by the wonderful and amazing
The coolest
Special thanks to Neil Carruth or Berliner and Melanie Marshall
Love you finish play the money I know you're just sitting around going like I've possibly listen to
The very last podcast I can think of what will I listen to next
Will you were in luck
Because NPR has a new podcast called
The big listen
And the point of the show is to tell you other things you can listen to
Find the big listen
On the NPR one app or wherever you find your punch
I'm Robert Smith
And I'm Chris Arnold
Thanks for listening