Support for this in
NPR podcasts
The following message come from that UPS
Offering services from shredding
To printing to mailbox
And instead of closing this Memorial Day we
May 24th and 25th
The UPS Store
He's doing another thing
All together
Opening
The UPS Store
Everything for small business
And of course shipping
Show the horse riding a horse
This is what show I grew up watching when I was growing up in Argentina
Every afternoon after school my grandma would serve
Play tahani
Cookies and we would sit down in front of the TV set
And watch
Cold
Mighty Med
And it's obvious
From looking at this but this is a spanish-language soap opera
Telenovela they call it
Because there's a certain look
Hippy program
How would you describe
They're very over-the-top Gotti
The acting can be pretty shoddy but above all very melodramatic
Yeah every single emotion is the most extreme emotion so every time like
It goes to like here's a guy
Who is as mad as a human being
Can be angry
All of a sudden
Just breaking their just
And kisses
As romantic as you can possibly be
Yeah no one's ever like pass me the sugar
This novela is about a very poor Mexican girl growing up in a Beach town
She falls in love with a very wealthy young landowner whose impossibly handsome and
She rides horses with no shirt on with you
Just saw
And it's a whole story of how she exact
Her revenge
On his family
His family made her life
Cinderella Story it's about
Class is about dreams Rags to Riches literally she's wearing Rags here
Is everything shot at Sunset Lakes literally
That's the only time anyone have the conversation right
At
Sunset
Okay and I could go on
I can tell that you think this is super.
Listen let me tell you something about Telenovela
They're like off force of entertainment
In the US
In the last month
The top four Network
In the 18 to 49 crowd which is really big
For advertise
Does NBC
ABC
CBS
And number four on the list
Philemon
Was the fourth
Most popular Network
Not USA Network
Telemundo
They built their whole empire on Tylenol
No of course part of this
Is
The growing Hispanic
Yes it Hispanic population is growing very fast
Here's what's really up
Telemundo figured out the perfect formula
Decatur
Us Latino
They took this product that you think
Is so cheesy
And they pushed it into the modern
Hello
Welcome to Planet Money
I'm Jasmine Serena Garza Garcia
Oh that's where we're going to play it I am William Robert Anthony Smith
Today on the show
Ira Glass
But I've been keeping for 33 years Jasmine
I knew
Your mother
But our love was forbidden because I
I'm a Canadian
Papa
Okay we're going to do is straight really show we tell you a story that no does not involve evil twins
Nobody dies and comes back to life nobody's cheating on each other
But it is a dramatic story none the less because it is the story of how one net
Working fact
Telenovela
Actress
Throughout all the old Scripts
A created something new
Created something to change the landscape
Television
Mecca Spanish language television
Ulta
Support for this podcast and the following message comes from rocket mortgage by Quicken Loans
Rocket mortgage brings the mortgage process into the 21st century with this completely online process
Safely share your bank statements and pay stubs with the touch of a button
Ditch the paperwork and use her phone or tablet
To get approved for purchase or refinance with a custom mortgage solution in minutes
Check out rocket mortgage today at quickenloans.com money
Equal Housing lender licensed in all 50 states
Nmls consumer access. Org number 3030
Couple weeks ago I flew down to Miami
Me too
Head over to the Telemundo Studios
And I wanted to meet with one woman in particular her name is pride a lot fethiye
Telenovela Royals
Okay she's like
The daughter of a
Her mom is an icon
In the world of
Telenovelas
Her mom's
We are began in the 90
60s younger fans might have seen her more recently in
Torrente a whirlwind of passion
I love that the actual name a whirlwind
Apache
It's good it's a good show her father was a big-time director he directed this
Iconic telenovela 90
1980s called
Please tell what I think I could say I was born in the studio in a television Studio playground
And I did not want to be involved in 10 anyway less you know that's usually the case
When you have parents that are in Show Business
You want to be an engineer
In Paris case her dream was to be
A political scientist
More differ
Development political science
So she goes to USC studies it
Yep
The Lure of the TV Camera
Draws her back to Venezuela she's like yes
I am going to try being an actress in of course
One of her dad shows
Crystal trying to make it in the modeling
And she almost immediately realized
She had made a terrible mess
I was mine blown I was like you know because I was into the the The Hulk
Character and finding the
Seoul
And you know
At that time I would meet with actresses and and they were like oh I think you need a nose job and I was like
I'm at such a sweet warm person
Is she happy
Sparkling brown eyes and you can talk to her for hours about
Greek mythology
Politics
Feminism
She's an intellectual
And she felt like her soul was die
So she called up the head writer for the Telenovela
And ask for something that I guarantee no one ever asked for any shows
Would you kill me
You know would you mind
Killing my character off
But you literally asked
The character
Right
Okay this is what we're going to do
I'm going to send you off
To travel
And so if you change your mind you tell me and I'll bring you back in
So I was sent off to travel of course she never came back
Propeller herself didn't leave Venezuela and didn't really
Leave the TV in Des
She decided she wanted to write
The kind of telenovelas that she would want to watch
Herself something they could bring in all these different world that you knew about
Jennifer she started using soda
Subtly
Quick
The genre that we are making fun up there at the very beginning
Differences synonym
Don't often deal with the mechanic
Yeah there's a lot of
Sunset and rolling around on the beach in a swelling of romantic music
If you don't want to get pregnant just never go near
Is excellent advice
So you can imagine this
Surprised when Fela wrote a Telenovela about
A young woman who is a virgin and gets
Accidentally
Artificially
Inseminate
The it's basically takes place in her uterus the whole novela
It's called quanon
Or Jane the Virgin us version of this I have watched it is a remarkable show
Because it makes fun of the genre but it's also
Really sweet
It's genius I mean they're talking about sex
But she's a virgin and they're they're playing on all these themes of Purity and
Sexuality
But it's not too risky
Sapele got really good at doing these eyes
Twists on classic romantic
Telenovela
But then something happened that made it so she had to leave
Venezuela
It was the early 2000s and violent country
Was starting to be a pro
Different situations have happened that were
At the beach house we were some people came in an hour
I was almost kidnapped
At the third time that I got
A gun pointed at my head I said okay I think it's time to go
And sew in 2003 Butler move to Miami to be the VP of telenovela development
It's at a television network called the pneumonia
I don't know the sound glamorous you know this Tommy
Telenovelas for the US population will you really made it now
But you have to remember at the time Telemundo was a second
Rate
Network they had declared bankruptcy they've been bought by NBC
And they were just starting to make their own telenovelas build Studios but mostly
They were doing
WeChat
Novellas Buffet Dunn from South America and Mexico
Plus
There was a huge rival out there
Perhaps you've heard of it
Univision
Was
The top
Network for Spanish-speaking
They were the ones that had the very best telenovelas
They had soccer
Univision
Was always number one and they were always going to be enough
So like in telenovela lingo
Univision will be like the rich powerful uncle
The mustache and Telemundo would be like the pores
Scrappy boy who who
Big dream
UniFirst
The dreams were
We can even feed Univision we want to be as good as they are
I thought you know
This is the Golden Age of
Television Lake why are we just trying to out Univision Univision
Like what were their viewers watching when they weren't watching telenovelas
They're watching The Sopranos
They're watching The Wire
Watch Mad Men and Breaking Bad
So you have a
Renaissance of
Great TV
In the English language Market
Dad
I think our viewers are are are being exposed to
So it's hard to ignore the fact that
Hey
You know what why would
Spanish language television be
How to completely lower level
Dan English language television and we we look at ourselves and we said no
Absolutely not
I'm going to try to
Create stories and an unproduced oh stories
Add a level
That people can say listen
This is not dramatically different
Then what's in English language
So Perla is out there looking for
Different ideas
Fort Nova
Trying a lot of things some do well others bomb
But there's this one moment
It turns out to be crushed
But that was looking everywhere Friday
I've have
Next to my bed
A mountain of books
Whenever I'm in the weekends I just want to have a little more time
I
Stay in bed and I read
She picks up his book
Called La Reina Del Sur
The queen of the South
It is a novel but it's written by Spanish journalist and it is unusual taking the drug war
And she decides
Hey this could
Make a Telenovela
It starts off like the class
There's this girl
Teresa Mendoza
Poor girl in Mexico
Some drug Runner he's
The really nice guy
Do you know where this is
Almost immediately
He gets murdered like in the very
First episode the love interest is gone
It's recent she gets raped by his rival you managed to escape first of the US and then to Spain
And the rest of the story is sort of about revenge and her rise to power
Teresa
Turned out to be an excellent drug lord
Telenovela audiences had never seen anything like that at 7.
We had a
Female protagonist that was completely
Opposite
To the typical
Novella protagonist
I mean she she killed
She killed people and she was a lesbian
In the character
And that's where protagonist is huge I mean imagine coming from a
Did telenovelas her classical to learn about his could you ever imagine having that kind of a
A possibility so you know it was a big risk
Puerto Madero
They were in second place they're willing to try anything in order to beat up the capital
Univision
So the reality is is that when you are used to not winning
You take more chances
You have nothing to lose
They wanted this product to look like nothing you had ever seen before on telenovelas end of the first thing they do
Did is they spent money
On
Amazing
Mexican
Kate del Castillo
Let me just show you
Cuz
She is sensitive
This is Kate del Castillo Robert music
So she is a
She's a gorgeous
Brunette but she's like
Has this intense look
All the time but she
Looks like
She wants to kick your ass
No and she does that mean that's what she
She does me
We just totally unlike the sort of
Yu-Gi-Oh gazing up into the
Eyes of the man you normally see in a ton
A lot at all in this whole than a novella
Spanish language television
Finally had
There Tony Soprano
Kate del Castillo
Yeah okay but I got to say this was not just revolutionary for Spanish language Telugu
I mean this was like a big deal for television in general
Yes in English language TV there's the rise of the anti-hero but how many of those anti-heroes are women
What's a dude
It is mostly dudes and Kate del Castillo has
A look
They could match them all
Yeah and you know what some people weren't ready
We got to remember is in Mexico there's a drug war and The Mexican government is like do not do this
If you are glorifying the drug war
I think they push to have it banned in Venezuela it is
The first episode
A queen of the South with the highest rated Premiere in the networks
2.4
Million viewers 5 Second month of the year
It was number one in Primetime beating out
Not just Univision not that the other spanish-language rival
But English language programming to
Telemundo
Was stunned
By the way
What are the head writers Roberto
He was always the guy who started the
How do I hide a bottle of tequila in his office and every time the ratings
Would arrive he would open up the tequila bottle and go around
Let's have a little shot of tequila so yes
It was that good it was that good
Let me tell you a story
About how culturally dominant this program
Sure it was watched by Latinos all across America men loved women loved it
Internationally famous
Drug lords
We're watching this
After only one that we know
Yeah but she was the big one
Walking
Loera Guzman
El Chapo El Chapo the Most Wanted drug lord
In the world the man who knows cell can contain who digs tunnels
Out from prison under the US Mexico border
El Chapo fell in love with Kate Del Castillo's character or Kate del Castillo he probably got them
Arduino this
Because when he was captured
They
Captured his text message
They were public
And pizza things telenovelas
Armada
I will play El Chapo
ISO
Want to meet you
And get to be very good friend
You are the best thing
In this world we are going to be very
Good friend
I will take better care of
Can I take care of my own eyes
It must be too much
When you tell me that you're going to take care of me
No one has ever taken care of me
Thank you
I'm free next weekend
Okay
Folded story
At all
What happened next
Was amazing
Kate went to visit El Chapo the Most Wanted Man in Mexico
An escaped prisoner
And she met him the jungle and she brought along
Her friend
Actor Sean Penn
Who is reading an article
Rolling Stone
Yeah two of the most famous actors in the world going to the jungle and
Guess what that raises a little bit of
Suspicion so Mexican authorities
They captured El Chapo
Because of this
Yeah and when they searched his hideout
They found what you would expect
International criminal
Weapons cell phone
Hair dye
Signature mustache
And of course
Several DVDs of La Reina Del Sur
As a fan of the show and tell
I should have known
How
This was going to end
Because it doesn't end well for The Descent Mendoza in the Telenovela
In the last episode
She is
Heavily pregnant
All by herself everyone she loves
Has been killed by her
Or by someone else
And she just looks out into the Horizon and rubbing her belly
You got this feeling that
She's incredibly lonely and probably going to be in trouble
It's the least romantic Sunset ever
In a Telenovela
Right it's Dawn
.
The president of Telemundo Luis silberwasser says this
Was
The turning point this
If hou Telemundo
Went to the top
All of us
Who have something to do with Spanish language television remember La Reina Del Sur
And I think I think it did
Signal
The market in general and to Telemundo internally
The Telemundo could do something really big
And could break
Into the Spanish language and become a
A real alternative
And we did with that type of story being very real very dramatic
With a lot of action
I'm not your standard
Telenovela
That we could actually
Dino get big big nut
Telemundo had found a new formula
In fact they dropped
The name telenovela and came up with a new name for this thing
Think I'm super sweet
I prepare like it was like this aha moment
It's about the kind of character
People want
Just with the time that we're living
I think it's also a reality in the General Market
People
Doane relay
To the
Positive
Characters although what makes them human
They are billions but they're not absolutely villains
The humans
So you see the humanity
They make mistakes
All you have to do right now is look at the lineup
Telemundo they have a show called Senora Acero
Which is about a
A woman who works as a
The human Smuggler
On the US map
Border
You have an upcoming show called lasagna
It's another language
Centos a lot about violence
It's against women which is something
Honestly you don't see
In telenovelas
And they're also going to be premiering a serious called Chavez El comandante
I guess it's about
The
Biggest anti-hero of them all in Latin America
Right now
That is totally telling about that I would watch
Watch
Darling
I love you so much that I'm instituting price controls
Let us know what you thought of today's show especially
If you want to hear
More dramatic reenactment
Of El Chapo we will literally do in Tire shows
I'm the man
You can find us at Planet Money on
Facebook and Twitter or email is Planet Money at npr.org
Thank you so much
To our producer Nick fountain
El producto
And if you want to listen to another cool podcast
Which is about race and it's
Don't forget
Tune into NPR
Code switch
You can find it on iTunes or wherever you enjoy this fine podcast
I'm Robert Smith
And then Jasmine cars
Thank you for listening
Coming to Brooklyn you know that right
Awesome isn't it
He's in Brooklyn in Brooklyn
Escape the Brooklyn I am just taking the week off of work