Lots of kids dream of being Cowboys
But Sean weeks always knew he was
His mom put him on a horse before you can talk
I'm actually a 4th generation cowboy
That's my family history but he is lassoing
A stack of square hay bales
What kind of dummy ball
He's just like throw
Cinch repeat
This is not at all distracting from the interview
A rope was actually my first toy
Yeah but even for an experienced Cowboy like Sean it is harder to find work
America has fewer cattle than it has it anytime soon
Since the 1950s
And cowboy Cruz or smaller
And more specialized
Sean Weekes found himself traveling farther and farther to find
From Idaho
Nevada
The Texas there's a couple of times that I
Take a step back cuz I wouldn't have enough time with my family and
And move to town and
Drove a truck
Whole couch
And I actually spent less time with my family
And so
I just went back to the being a cowboy
And then a couple of years ago Sean got this call that he
Barely believe
A recruiter from a cattle ranch
Offered to pay him
Double
There was one catch
This Ranch would be a bit
Farther
East
The only thing I really knew about Russia's just from
What little bits of information that I
Her growing up
What Sean was ready for a change
And maybe a chance of attending relay for spam
So 3 months after that phone call
Fill the suitcase
To this one is close
And the saddle is Dad made for him
Are 44 years old
Sean Weekes
Flew to Moscow
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Gregory Warner
Damn show
Cowboy expats
Beefstick oligarchs and the Amazing Story
First Russian porterhouse steak
Support for this podcast and the following message
Come from transferwise
The cheap easy way to send money between the US
And more than 50 country
Including the UK Germany and Brazil
With transferwise you pay a small fee and get the real exchange rate
Like the one you see on Google
Join more than 1 million people using transferwise
By visiting transferwise.com
Or downloading the award-winning app
When sean gets Russia
He found himself on a ranch
In the southwest near the
Ukrainian border
It's a ranch owned by a massive Russian mean
The company is called me rhetoric
Reporter Irina zhorov at WHYY
He's been digging into this company me retarded yet they're one of the biggest Russian suppliers
A pork and chicken everything they do seems to be really huge
But in 2010 they got even bigger
They bought a bunch of land in the province of briansky
Obudu cattle ranch
And make American style Angus steak I went to the dance can I visited a couple of these ranches
And their enormous sometimes it can take hours to get from one Farm to the next one
Each one of these red
Has a hundred times more cows
In the average American read
And there are 60 of these farms and they're all owned by this one Russian
Company I've never seen anything girl this time
Havre
Its huge
Champs Auto Sales that this Ranch did feel
Weirdly familiar
But you've seen it all before you know the way this horse Act
Key points of the horse that he's riding
Sources Jack
Jackie thinks he's an old American racehorse
Which is actually very possible because all the horses on this Ranch
Are American Expo
Like Shawn
They have to import everything
Not only did me rhetoric import 500 American Quarter Horses
500 saddle
100000 American cows
The imported grass from Europe
Parasite Killers for the animals and vaccines for them
60000 units
The bull semen to artificially inseminate the cows and 10 ultrasound machines to check when they're pregnant
And then of course they recruited American Cowboy
Spiked Sean weeks
To teach the Russians how to care for the cows
How to move to
From Pastor to Pastor
My first day
Pretty stressful
Really
Is Russian students worth
Totally new
To all this
Equipment they were new to these kind of horses did never dealt
Breed of cattle
They're nervous they're they're scared there's nothing wrong with that
Hey you just got to learn how to control it
Shante is okay I'll start with the base
How to tie a lasso knot
And when to show up for work in the morning
Sun up
Especially in the summertime it gets hot
In the afternoon
Cattle and horses don't do well in the heat
But you insisted his Russian students still just didn't seem to get
The whole cowboy thing
There's a lot of things that you just
You see and you really don't even want to believe yourself
So what's your like favorite story to tell
I had a deal Last Samurai I got asked to go to a place where they were passed during a bunch of steers
Tachanka rework
600 steers that has been moved from one pasture to another
Which to him was like no big deal
Okay
What's the problem
He was thinking why can't the Russian Cowboys just do that then
So I got there and I
Me and two other guys were moving them across the pasture
Andis cattle started getting real nervous
And that's what the heck why all the sudden I hear this chi chi chi ching and I want in the world and I turn around trying to find
The sound
Here comes to guys riding over the hill behind the sun bicycles with the little
Handlebar bells on them
They thought cuz they ride around on bicycles all the time that that would be the way to do things which
Scared
They scared the cat
That that turned into a bad Fiasco
I love herding cows with a bicycle Bell
Nescac every American Cowboy on this Ranch seem to have some story like this
What's with the Russians getting creative about their cattle duties
In ways that the Americans
Couldn't even dream
So I have to see Gregory I mean I grew up in
My parents own a cattle ranch
Cowboys
It's not a job that is like any
The other job I mean on any given day you might be
Defensor pulling a thousand pound cow out of a gold
Or if you helping a cow give birth
In the middle of a blizzard at 4 in the morning
Don't we look out there and see something that needs to be done we go do it
Anomie is an incredibly hard work and you're dealing with big animals and big machinery
Dangerous
I've got a tore up body to prove it and I've broken pretty much every bone in my body
Riding on horses and dealing with cows and
You commit your mind body and soul to this
Dispatch
This romantic idea of the cowboy that a lot of Americans grow up with
This was not how many rhetoric the Russian company was approaching it
Declan Irina visited these ranches she found that they weren't even
Calling them
They called them
Operator
Every Ranch that I visited I saw these
Posters he's laminated sheets of paper with instructions on them
And it's instructions for things like
How to fix a fence
How to load
Cattle into a trailer
How to rope a steer
I think they were even illustrations
Which like
You know I used to report on ranches in the States you would never see anything like
Like that and all the sudden it seemed like
This whole Russian operation
Which member was bigger than any single Ranch in the United
Was also liking Ikea version of a cattle ranch
Shipped over
Assembled with instructions
Not everyone can I walk with Keto
It's a
Difficult
That's very similar laws here and mirror towards beef operation
From Farm to slaughterhouse
Lucy says
Annie's at the Cowboys were the biggest challenge by
Far they kept hiring Russian Cowboys and
Firing them you're right it's a it's a challenge in all the mirrors are Executives including
Larry we're trying to figure out
Why
Was it
The workout
Or was it the job skills or was it some kind of personality
Comfortability with animals
And it was all those things
But you ask Sean weeks
He said it was something Beyond.
Because being a Cowboy is more than a job
The more cattle in the more weight that I produce
The more money I make it the end of the year
But it's also a pride issue with me
I want you to look a knife cattle
You know porterhouse steak
Heading for the reason
What's the luxury product
Because you're not supposed to
Have to do much to it in the kitchen
Play all the preparation is happen
On the ranch
When Sean takes Pride that his cows are well
It's because everything that have
Slim Andres watch
In some way goes into the taste and the culture of cowboying
Has grown up around
Which is making me hungry
You brought this is some Russian beef but it is not
Islam guy
So interesting
Yeah
Because the thing is Russian so mixtape what they make
This is a Galaxy
Stuffed cabbage
I had a Russian home
I'm so this came
Oh my gosh really yes
Stacy one
Just cut in there
Do I try it yet or is some sour cream
I will always put sour cream
Flip the beef
Fit in this day
Dish
You know it's prepared in a very
Very different ways
No no it doesn't know I mean it tastes like it's
Savory and salty and and delicious but it doesn't
Taste like beat this could be I mean
Chicken
Porker
Yeah because one of these are traditional Russian food is it is
The recipe does coffee
It's boiled
Or student for a long time like these
These cabbages
I think the recipe calls for
For boiling for 2 and 1/2 hours
And the reason is is because
Russians have traditionally
Pharmd
Dairy cows
A dairy cows
Are there meat that it's not fat
Angus Cattle
They're going to tough and leave
They definitely don't fatten up in the same way and they're also a lot more docile as animals are a lot easier to
Dairy cows in these cattle
Two different monsters
Shawn says actually nothing about raising dairy cows
Which the Russians have done for centuries
Prepares you for raising
Black Angus Cattle
The dairy cattle are used to being around people all the time
These cattle are raised out in the open
And so they're borderline Wild
And so you got to learn how to handle them
And if you don't handle them right it turns out ugly
So Gregory my question is this I mean having just
Senior tuition
Cabbage
Why make American states in Russia
Why don't you stick to dairy cows
If you think about how
Cattle farming start in America
It was because we had all this land
In the American West
Russia season opportunity
They have all this cheap
People and they want to use it too
Create a beef industry that not only can export beef to
China and the Gulf State but maybe potentially create thousands of new jobs in Russia
End
The Russian company Meritor
Also has an important Ally
In this fight
A
Horse riding tiger hunting steak eating president
I think I know who you might mean
And Vladimir Putin
Very much wanted this Russian people
The Russian government
Help clear nearly 2 billion dollars
In low-interest loans
Plus a bunch of subsidies
Amir torges buying
Moreland
They're building more rat
They say their first word will top 1 billion cows by the end of the decade
When Mary took Thomas's
The beef industry will finally be profit
But they have to figure out how to solve
This Cowboy's
How do you squeeze a hundred fifty years of cowboy history
Into a decade
Well near torque says
Has found a way
To teach their Russian workers
The very spirit
Of the American West
They have imported
One more signature aspect
Of American Cowboy life
The rodeo
Okay so here we are at the Russian Rodeo it is
The 3rd annual Rodeo that me rhetoric has posted
And everything here is really similar to what you'd see it in American Rodeo but
A little Rusev I'd so
There's the same offense barrel racing roping trailer loading and the songs that the teams enter to
Are patriotic leak in the US but here there about the mightiness of Russia
Where there's another song
And about how America should give Alaska back to Russia and the chorus is something like don't be an idiot America
The radian the US didn't used to be this like big Affair you know now the rodeo championships happened in Vegas it's very
Flashy
But it started out in a very similar way Wars are better than your Cowboys my horses are better than your
Jessica way to show off
And build camaraderie
That honestly is a big help
Especially if you get some of your own agent
You're competing against them
Trying to learn the to be better
I'm about to go into battle
Let's go rope something boys
Sean is here at the rodeo he is
Coaching a team of Russia
It says that this Spirit of competition
This house turn a job
Infopass
It makes you want to master all these really tough skills
Keep working at it
Shawn how's your team doing
What's up Sean team is not doing so hot
Yeah they're doing okay
Train them up pretty good I can do better than that and they know it and I know it too
When Sean got to Russia
She was frustrated
If you wanted the Russian Cowboys to measure up
The Americans
Now he just wants them to measure up to
And self
Andrea the Russian team
When Sean's Contracting
Expires the end of this month
He can go home knowing that
He will leave something behind
Russian cowboy and culture
Maybe you can be a thing
Maybe
But they're still struggling
Either in skill or
Motivation
Gorgeous Cowboy nose
But Irina says she did me this one guy
The rodeo
The guy who she
Brisket walking by because
She assumed he was American
He was dressed like an American which is why I confuse them he had a cowboy shirt on and
Jeans and a slight camouflage vest and button-up shirt and boots and everything and he just had this like
Aura about him like he kind of stood with his
Arms on his ways than
Mike looked up in his hat would be to
Tobacco bet you know he just had like a way about him
And so when I
I heard him speaking Russian I was like oh
This Cowboy's name is Sergei Sergei Schilling
And he's bashful only approximate the American Cowboy
As if he knows he's
Counterfeit copy
He tells Arenas at on his first day on a saddle horse that was
Three and a half years
He almost fell off
Get really embarrassed
He nearly quit
Only
His wife convinced him to return to the ranch
Keep trying
And now he feels himself
Bully
A cowboy
Get some point he got offered a position as a manager and he said
No cussing
Wants to be around the animals
Everything about it has become very dear to him
Convertible
And as he's explaining this
Tips his hat
Wide Brim
Black felt
Flapper
Weather in xiamen
American Samoa
This hat
Gifted to him by an American Cowboy named David
After he lassoed his first ear and the booties wearing
They were present from another Cowboy Kurt
Pristine
This is it
Sergey's entire outfit
It was assembled
Peace pipe
Peace merit badge Style
As himself
Became something new
Yeah
And he believes in the future of the Russian cowboy
Oh for sure yeah so he has a four-month-old son
And he's already
Planning
To train them up as a cowboy to
But one thing still separate Sergei from the American Cowboys
He's never tasted a steak
In Russia a mere rhetoric porterhouse
Cost more than he makes in a day
Do you have some time soon
He'll get a chance to try one
If you enjoyed this episode we want to tell more stories like
And we need your help
I'm working on a series here looking at what happens when people take ideas or
Businesses are just themselves to a new place and try to make that work
It's going well or to go terribly awry if you heard a story like this recent Lathan
Email us at Planet Money
Npr.org
Or reach out to us on Facebook or Twitter
Thank you to Irina zhorov who brought us the story original version aired on the show called the pulse on WHYY
Why you find the link on our block NPR. Org / money for trip to Russia was made possible by the UC Berkeley
11th hour food and farming journalism
Infellowship R episode today it was produced by Jess Jiang
If you're looking for another podcast to listen to and
Speak Spanish there is a new podcast NPR called radio ambulante
The show takes a look at Latin America and us
Latino community
It brings you stories you might not otherwise hear
Punk rock in Cuba stolen books in Columbia junk Bonds in Puerto Rico
You can check out radio ambulante on the NPR one app and npr.org
Splash Park
I'm Gregory Warner
And I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Thanks for letting
My mom had racehorses
Grown up
And I one of my uncles
Who do you think the lucky Burger was that got the exercise over runaway miserable pile
Me