Wow what are you here for a really good question
Do I really need another blouse shariat is lined up here on the sidewalk in Midtown Manhattan
With about 20 other
Everybody is waiting for the Diane Von Furstenberg
Sample sale
Sample Sales are like this Fashion World
Wear fancy designer sell stuff at deep discounts in these like
Law of the jungle
Few minutes later the doors open and Sherry and everybody else rushes inside
Address
Didn't I say wasn't going to get a dress I was going to get a blouse
The dresses are $70 that's
Ridiculous it is an incredible price
Jerry's here because she loves a deal
And frankly so do I
I love you in every sense of the word
You know I definitely love a bargain
HBA retail
Russell Simmons
I love transaction
I love deals as a sport
The atomic
Unit of Economics you know this mutually agreed-upon exchange that where I think I'm getting something good and
You think you're getting something good
Do you like
A way of looking at the world
And you know they're not just about
Math and numbers
Steals her about relationships there about emotions
Heels are so serious
Respect shariat cannot simultaneously shop at the sample sale
And describe the experience
Sign off
Are you okay
I'm having trouble doing this
Can I ask you can I ask you one thing
Okay good luck
17 deals in 17 minutes
Stories about all kinds of deals from all over the world all in 17 minutes
Will some of the stories be really short
Yes
Will there be cheesy sound effects
Is this the most stories we have ever squeezed into a single episode
I think so
It is an incredible
Podcast value you will not get more stories permitted anywhere else
Planet Money is supported by betterment the largest independent Robo advisor with more than 180 thousand
Some customers and over 5.5 billion dollars under management
Betterment makes it easier and less expensive to invest for your personal financial goals
With a beautiful user interface and smart cutting-edge technology betterment brings you sophisticated personalized
Financial advice all of the lower-cost up to 6 months free to learn more about betterment
Visit betterment.com Planet Money
Okay we're doing 17 deals in 17 minutes
Start the clock now
3 2 1
Our first deal comes from Marianne McCune
She's a fantastic radio reporter
I'm back when she was in her early twenties
She went two years without paying her federal income
Then she got the letter
From the IRS saying
Back taxes and penalties and it
She called at the IRS
I don't think I knew what deal you could ask for but it was just like is there anyway that
Like a knot
Payless
So we just got another phone and she's like
247 Elizabeth
And we had a long conversation about
Italian family crest
Neighborhood is changed
You know we became friends
So you guys are saying about the old neighborhood on the phone you and the IRS lady whatever
She said all the money I owed
Getting defiled
The penalties and the interest on that
I didn't have to pay
The huge
Really
That's amazing
It just seems like so much blind luck right the same building like
I feel like you just got so lucky
I think I did get really lucky
I think it made it easy
But I also think
You can
Make a human connection with somebody and ask
4 something
And you may
Get what you ask
Nick Fountain Planet Money producer and I'm in a little Alleyway sitting on a tiny stool
Is Ho Chi Minh City Vietnam I'm eating a delicious soup that will probably cost about a dollar fifty and
I'm here is because I'm on my honeymoon with my beautiful wife and one of the reasons we chose Vietnam for a honeymoon
Because we got an amazing deal on the flights so I'm always checking these flight deal websites
One of them is called Airfarewatchdog they send an email alerts and another one is on Twitter it's called the flight deal
And what they do is they scour Airlines websites for the best deals my wife and I got
From New York to Ho Chi Minh City Vietnam and back for $400.26 per person
There may have been one too many layovers but it was well worth the trip
Just to be clear bike one too many layovers Fountain and it took him and his wife
30 hours
To get to Vietnam
I'm going to call this one to deals in one
Airfare for $400.26
Also delicious bowl of noodles for bucks
Springfest
To deal number 4
Jacob boxing how are you
Stacey Vanek Smith no time for banter we got 17 deals in 17 minutes
Any pictures of kind of a bad
It is
This happened in India a couple weeks
On the night of November 8th
If the Prime Minister got on TV and said starting at midnight
You cannot use 500 and 1000 rupee notes
Divisive
Used to go trade them in at the
A really big deal because a thousand rupee note is only worth about $15 so we're talking about most of the cash
In the country
And he did this
Is part of a
Crime-fighting measure
August criminals operating
Cash and these are some of the larger
People had to take their old Rupees to the bank with ID
Fill out a form and change their money
And there was a limit
You can only trade in 4,000 rupees per day that's about 60 bucks
And that's a
Low amount and the idea is that criminals would be stuck with these
Duffle bags full
Cash
And everybody else
Experience kind of a minor in
When this announcement happened Mohit Duval was walking home from work he teaches music in New Delhi
And we got to his house his whole family was in this deep discussion about
Mopeds cousin is getting married next month it is wedding season in India
And his family had spent months and months amassing
All of this
Cashed
Pei caterers
Yukon try everything by Shakira
Yukon
ReliOn cards
So you
Heartland cast
500 people are coming to this wedding in December
And the family for this event has saved up
Rupees
In cash
None of which they can use now
See you at 350000
Rupees
Assembled
For the wedding
That's like
87 tripsta
Yes
Got to start somewhere right so the next morning Mohit goes to the bank to
To change all of the cash account for that day
As soon as I go to the bank do they first thing I was
Watching was the
Huge queue the longest
Q I could ever imagine
How long
Let's sit 300 people in a queue
Mohit was in line for
Hours and after this heinous family realize that they needed
A plan or they were not going to get all of their cash changed out in time for
So what they decided to do was distribute this cash
Cross a whole bunch of relatives and have
Each relative convert the maximum amount of cash they could
Each day
200v have it on
829 cousins
See you at like 10 p.m.
People working together
To get this cash
So far his family has changed at about half of the cash
I do think that they will be ready
For the wedding
Hi this is Sally Helm Planet Money producer please leave message thanks
Hello this is a message for Richard calling about the silver eagle bus
That is listed in Craigslist
So you can call me back
My name is
Thank you
End of message
A couple months back I was getting a
Bunch of message
Like that's about this bus that I was allegedly
Selling
And for the record I am not selling a silver eagle bus
Which is like a giant tortoise like if I pass one on the highway I would assume
It was carrying
Like a rock band from the 1970s
So I called the sky Patrizio back
And I was like why do you want to buy this us
And he said
That he is a professional
Tango dancer
It would be the time go back
The Tango bus
To hold a portable stage
I ride with the bus
Alabama festivals somewhere wherever we go
He said that he already travels a lot for work actually he was about to go to the Mojave Desert
Doing a photoshoot
We're going to do some nude photos and others are going to be
Embarrassed
Traditional Tango clothing
Yessica plane tickets
Rental car hotel and he said he thinks it would be a better deal overall to just spend 40 or $50,000
Buy a bus
End
I wish I could sell them on
Genius that was deal number 5
When we were working on this show we asked plan of many listeners to call in with deals
Here's one of those
Iverson
Stephen Fry
Farmville Virginia
I got a rare
$400 snare drum of the yard sale for $8
And now I'm
EBay attic
Number 7 is a Vegas deal it comes from Planet Money cheap gambling correspondent Keith
Samantha Vegas with a couple buddies
And we come back one night to our
Terrible hotel room from a night of gambling and drinking and whatever
And
My buddy Jeff goes and takes a shower
Comes out of the shower completely naked
And I say to Jeff Jeff if you go down just the way you are to the casino floor and get a $1 chip
I will give you $100
Instantly he's gone door closes behind him
We got in the hallway we look for him he's gone
5 minutes
Hey babe it's Jeff
Completely out of breath
Completely naked
No $1
So
I didn't get my $100
Okay how we doing we're 8 minutes in
We've done 7 deals little behind going to try and pick it up
Deliberate we've got Jess Jiang she's a Planet Money producer she called her
Cable company earlier this year
The woman that I talked to said
We can offer you anything over the phone
But she said
Between you and me
What you should do is go into the
Because if you go into the Time Warner Cable store
Don't see that there's a chance you might quit Time Warner Cable
Maybe they'll offer you something better there
So few days later I went into the store
And I said I'm considering leaving Time Warner Cable
Can you give me a better deal to
Keep me to stay
And they said
Yes
Will give you a free Roku will give you faster
Internet
Anvil drop your bill from $60 to $45
And that's what I'm still paying
Today
A year later
I love a good vet and
Yeah I was naked so I would like your
I don't think
I just go right out the front door I'm in the hall
I'm like don't take the elevator cuz there's cameras
Golden emergency exit do like they do in the movies
Run like the AC
Floor and I'm just
Lying down emoji
The exit stairs on the stairs
Jumping from light
Florida floor and as soon as I get down to the bottom
I take a breath
I opened the door and I'm ready to do this
The alarm goes off
Kicks into
And my heart
Is just
Racing cell phone backup
The stairs best I can
Adore you guys let me in and that was it
Man with no chip
Skip intro theme going from naked Vegas
The 87 year old man who gets free beer for life
Planet Money producer Elizabeth
Deal number 9
Milton Glaser
The Famous Grouse
Among other things
Who made the I heart New York logo
About 30 years ago
This guy who's getting a little bit
Company code for
Brooklyn Brewery
Pick up the pieces
Make me the perfect
He asked if I would do the job and
He said
I don't know how much you charge
I said probably too much but I will make you a deal
How do you write that fit in your logo
And you give me beer for life
And some equity in the company
And they thought about it and said okay
How valuable has it been
Have you ever
Sat down and done the math
No but it's
Probably
Eight or nine hundred times what I would have charged
Endear loan
No
Equity
Will the beard didn't even happen cuz I don't drink enough
Beer
I drink about two beers in a year
That's crazy you wouldn't you wouldn't have any ideas you wouldn't popular everybody went to because he
Important became too much of a burden than I don't want to spend my life Distributing beer
Lisa says
He doesn't know exactly
But the company's founder recently said
It's in the Millions
Beer is wetter but equities better
NPR correspondent Quil Lawrence you got 20 seconds to give me your pickle deal on time and it go
I was living in Jerusalem as a correspondent I was living right in the marketplace and once as I was leaving for work in the morning I found out something
Very disturbing about this
Pickles and those delicious olives
Did they have on baskets in display their they're all out of pants
But then I find out something really wonderful which is that I can buy those canned off the internet
For $2 a can and the pickles are delicious
Bill number 11 back to the Planet Money listener deals line
We received a coupon in the mail from AT&T U-verse
For free movie rental
So we punched in the code in the next month I'll bill was $28 more for taxes and fees
Meanwhile back at the Diane Von Furstenberg sample
How to give me the slip
Thanks for finding me.
Minecraft 188 so the sweater dress was 42 top the boss was 40
And of course with a hundred I mean that is screaming that is a screaming good deal
40 bucks for a fancy sweater dress 40 bucks for a fancy blouse both seem like good deal
But the purse
I mean how to say I don't care how much it retails for
$100 for a bag
Just doesn't seem like that good of a deal
This one is too
Deals 12 + 30
Robert Smith
Give us steel number for
When Chelsea Arnold was first diagnosed with diabetes
She was told she had to test your blood sugar 10 times a day
So she goes to Walmart and the diabetic test strip she needs
Are $80 a box
And that's a 5-day Supply so
I would have to come up with this kind of money every 5 days and I mean
I was a poor student and
Like I I don't know what to do cuz I don't have that kind of money
And if you don't test
You can die
So she googles the words
Cheap test strips
And what comes up is this underground marketplace of inexpensive diabetic
Test strips
That we couldn't fake
Four preps stolen
The Chelsea discovers that this whole deal is because of the way health insurance
If you have coverage for diabetes you can get boxes of test strips
For cheap
We talked to a guy named Trey who
Saved if you up
At about 20 extra box
What do you put on a different kind of testing regimen
He decided to sell his strips
To someone on
Goodnight in a McDonald's parking lot
And the
I pulled up in his car was there
I came out with
The bag for the test strips and
Get his wallet for the money in
Was like
We're doing a geriatric drug deal
Geriatric drug deal
Make me feel old
It is legal to sell your diabetic test strips
As long as they don't come from Medicare Medicaid tray made about
300 box
Eventually made their way into that underground world
The Chelsea found
Middleman Internet ads bargain deals
Chelsea bought eight boxes for under a hundred bucks
It was like
You know having a life sentencing
Realizing that there's a cure
And Chelsea thinks
You know there are other diabetics out there as desperate as I am
So she buys a few extra actually started with $200
6 boxes of test strips
Seldom
Buy some more
And pretty soon Chelsea has a garage full of test strips
And that's when I
Decided the
Create Pokemon
Glucomart
Chelsea Nails between 10 and $20,000 worth of diabetic test strips a month
People can't afford the retail price
Yeah I'm looking at this tour bus you guys have online
Silver Eagle MS70
And I'd like to know a little bit more about it
Spider-Man is going on tour in a silver eagle bus in 2017
Mark my word
All right we got two minutes left and
3 deals to go
Number 15 the Planet Money t-shirt
There's still a few left
They are on sale at the NPR shop
Price $12.11
Fun fact retailers use weird price endings like $0.11 to send signals
In this case it means
It's on clearance no special discount for employees
Quantity limit
Number 16 Planet Money listener go
Hello I'm Charles from
Chicago and the most interesting deal I had was when I was driving an ice cream truck
Last summer some kid came up to me and treated me a hot dog
For an ice cream and I gladly accepted B
Because I forgot my lunch that day
Thank you
Try to get you to say your name and what you're you know I'm a retired whatever you you
Depending on me
I do I want to eat in your own words on tape
Okay my name is
Haviland Smith, retired CIA
A retired CIA office
Is bringing us a b final deal of the show
Allen Smith work during the Cold War and his job was to recruit Soviet
It's the spy for the US
It was a tough job
They were hostile they were paranoid they were very suspicious of all Americans
It was a problem
Establishing relationships with
Early in his career pedal and learned a trick
Kind of emotional deal people would make
The Soviets were the ones who named it
They have a term called bone throwing
Brushes cost
Bone throwing consisted of
When you're trying to establish a relationship with someone hostile
You you you tell him something
Revealing about yourself something
Personal
During the Vietnam war
Haviland might tell a Soviet connection about his own doubts
It's about the u.s. involvement in
How are you struggling
A lot of the time he says that could really change the dining
The guy looks at you and he says
Jesus here's another human being a he's got problems just the way I do
And
He's dealing with them
And maybe I could talk to him about some of my
Because sometimes it's Soviet acquaintances would respond bye-bye say complaining about their bosses in mosque
The kind of thing they get in trouble for
Or if they talked about it with other
So you're both vulnerable to each other
We aren't there yet but he's vulnerable
How much more objective
I thought you're emotionally vulnerable
He's vulnerable to like getting sent to the gulag
That's a good asymmetry
Sports tonight
And have you use that in your
Personal life for a non Rising buying settings
Osher
The more close you are with other people
Sommore
Self-protective you are
The less you're going to get out of a relationship
And I've always found it
The more I could knit about myself in my photos in my shortcoming
The more I became a real person to two other people so yes
I feel used
Who I am
Stop the clock
From the time we
Started the clock after the internet until now it has been
17 minutes 57 seconds
What's round down called 17 minutes
Send us the best worst most interesting deal you ever got Planet Money on NPR. Org
Twitter or Facebook
A show today was produced by Nick fountain
Special thanks to Tiffany yannetta
Elna Baker Mark schiffman and Yaniv Gilman
If you're looking for something else to listen to
And you speak or want to learn Spanish check out radio ambulante or if you prefer
Valuable
It is in Spanish
It's hosted by this
Genius polymath Danielle Argon
Dayton tons of Interest
Sing stories you can find it on the NPR one app
And that npr.org
I'm Jacob Goldstein thanks for listening
Unread message
Since yesterday at
8:02 p.m.
I am Lisa calling from Garden City Kansas most interesting daily workout with my husband bought my wedding ring at
Arby's in Conroe Texas
Fakespot
And this message
To delete this message
Message saved
Next unread message
Since yesterday at
8:17 p.m.
Is Mike from Chicago Illinois
One time I bought 5lbs
Chicken nuggets
If you get a free bottle of ketchup
I don't even like chicken