Support for NPR in the following message come from Pushkin and Des
Presenting the podcast against the rules
Michael Lewis explores the corrosion of fairness in America
And what it has done to our society mostly
Without our noticing
Listen to against the rules wherever you get your pot
Amy cop lives in Indiana and owns a white 2004 Subaru Impreza
It is not
A really nice car
It's really banged up it's almost always dirty
Even my three-year-old daughter sometimes
I prefer to pretend that
The other car is at
Herpes school at her car
What Amy really love
This car
This is the car that she drove
Through a snowstorm in Indianapolis
To bring her newborn daughter home from the house
Hospital
I just kept looking in the rearview mirror my wife was sitting back there
Baby
It was a really happy scene in the back
Seed by the
Yeah I was just full of Terror
The funny thing about this not-so-nice but beloved
Is the Amy ended up in kind of a bidding war over
About five years ago her friend Erica was selling this
Amy and her wife
I've wanted it and so did another couple
A guy in a woman
And anything said that couple was offering about $100
More
But Amy's friend
Took the hit
She sold the Subaru to Amy
She just had one requirement
You cannot peel the Human Rights Campaign sticker off of the back window
And if you don't understand exactly what I'm saying let me let Amy
She sold it to us
Because you wanted to
Go to lick another lesbian
Erica wanted for Subaru to go to another lesbian couple
Part of the reason he's laughing here is that this has become kind of a stereo
The lesbian women love
The car even has a name
Erica always call it the lesburu
This is not an exit
Subaru spent more than a decade
Carefully targeting lesbian consumers
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Noel King and I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Today on the show why Subaru started targeting a group of consumers
That just about every other company with
Was ignoring
And how that may have helped
Save the company
Planet Money is supported by betterment
The largest independent Robo advisor
It was more than 180 thousand customer
Andover 5.5 billion dollars under manager
Betterment makes it easier
Less expensive to invest for your personal financial goals
With a beautiful user interface
Smart Cutting Edge technology
Betterment brings you sophisticated personalized Financial
All of the lower-cost
Planet Money listeners get up to 6 months free
To learn more about betterment
Visit betterment.com Planet Money
In the early 90s Uber was in trouble
Fielded been slumping for about 7 years
Super was competing against Giants
Toyota and Nissan and it was loose
Tim Bennett work in sales distribution for Subaru
Back then and him the problem was pretty clear
Subaru with having an identity
These were not
Sexy cars
Boxy reliable wagons with a certain kind of fish
It's granola let's 10000 Maniacs it's
Scrunchie it's hippie
It said
Professor in a tweed jacket 10000 maniacs
They are a great Banner creepy
But but
Companies want to sell to mass markets and not just
Hippies and professor
Subaru hired a cool Ad Agency
The ones that had come up with the just
Do it slogan for Nike
But even they could not make Subarus hip
The ad campaign went nowhere
Morale at Subaru
Raises
And bonuses went out the window and Tim cecile's people started making all these really dark jokes
Books about how is C
Things got any worse
They were just going to have to start sending new Subarus directly to
To the scrap yard
If not on the winning team you're on a losing team and nobody wants to be in a loser
And if that would have felt like at this time
But the company realized one type of Subaru was actually selling pretty well
These are cars with all-wheel drive the kind of cars that are popular in places with bad weather
Super said
Alright let's start there with
The bright spot
Let's meet the people who are buying these cars
The Ransom Focus Group
And they identified four categories of
The people who are buying
The first category they called the rugged individualist basically the
Outdoorsy types
So those are the people kayakers mountain biker scares
There were technical professional
Technical professionals
Engineers
I'm educators
Teachers
Healthcare professionals
Have to get to the ER all kinds of weather.
Show me some random assortment of
Professions here
But within those
There was a Common Thread
Women
A lot of Subaru owners
In a lot of cases
They were women who identified themselves as
Head of house
Tim Mahoney was running marketing for Subaru at
The time and one day he was watching
A focus group in
San Francisco behind it
Two-way mirror
One of the guys
Who actually work for our research company who happened actually be gay
He says yeah all my friends
Turn on supers are lesbians
It was like one of those moments where everything came into Focus
Tim Mahoney realize he may have just discovered a fifth group who love Subarus
Lesbian
Subaru have to figure out too thin
Number one
Is this true or is it just anecdotal
Is actually a significant consumer group
For Subaru
Even if it was
How are they going to mark
Kathy's Kars
Super got in touch with Mariah now
So the tiny Ad Agency based in Manhattan
With specialized in marketing to Gay and Lesbian consumers
John Nash was the creative director
What was the first campaign you worked on
Waze download
Dial a match 1-800 Mattress
Names John and his business partner Ryan we're both openly gay
And they would go to these big companies and they would pitch them they would say look gay and lesbian consumers are a big
Deal they have money and we know how to talk to
Tire us
To design new ads
So with dial Mattress
Did these Billboards and beautiful
Photography of a guy like like
It was all very already a guy laying on his stomach but you can see you know he had to
Close but he had to she pulled down
Who you sleep with
Yeah here it is
Who you sleep with is your business how you sleep
Thesaurus
Dial matricide
It was a tough sell
This was the early 90s it was during the AIDS crisis
And a lot of companies would not talk directly to gay and lesbian
Consumers
Because they were afraid of alienating heterosexual
Is that John says
A lot of the companies that did
Advertise to gays and lesbians what he calls the sin Industries
It's like booze and cigarettes
And then out of the blue comes as call from Subaru
Sing hey we think lesbians might be one of our most
Markets and we need to confirm
So John and his colleagues went out to Northampton Mass
Subaru's research said
A lot of its cars were being sold
And they gathered a little group of local Subaru owners together into a room with one of those two-way mirrors
So we get up there where in the door in the observation room which always has like M&Ms and crackers is a very Danger
Nearest place to date especially if you are on
Any kind of a diet so there's
All that
Candy and then the women start coming in
But only when
Yeah that's amazing
Both groups were 100% fee
100% there were no men
John watches the women from the other side of the mirror while a researcher asks
What do you use your car for
I want to move my dog from here to here
I like throwing my stuff in the back and going camping and there's a tone and and there's a tone to how they were answer
That was different than a woman saying
I like to go to TJ Maxx and get my hair done
Wow
Okay parently
Two kinds of women in the world I know I know I know I know and John said as a human being
He hates this kind of stereotyping but as an ad guy
This is sort of what you do
You break people up into categories
You say broadly here's what they're like
And then you try to sell stuff to him
So this is exactly what he's doing he's looking at these women and he says to himself
I think they are part of a specific group
And like these are lesbians or talk
Be there lesbian
Okay not just that
These women seem to
Do love their Subaru
So John and the Ad Agency drive down to Cherry Hill New Jersey
Where Subaru is headquartered
2 pitch
The company this was not
A small
I think a lot of us forget
But the early 90s were not
Particularly
Progressive time right
This is the era of don't ask don't tell
In just a couple years Bill Clinton was going to sign the Defense of Marriage Act which would effectively say same-sex Partners cannot be
Considered spouses
And even inside Subaru being openly gay was not easy
Tim Bennett the guy who saw Subaru having an identity crisis he later worked on this campaign
Tim is gay
And he never came out at Super because
He saw what
What could happen if
There was a out
Gentleman who was gay in the Mailroom they were people in the office that didn't want him to deliver mail
To their deaths because they're afraid they're going to get a hit
So this is the environment
I know a lot of people thinking of the campaign notes
What happened
So here comes Mariah and Nash
Into this conference room with about 20 Subaru bigwigs
John and the team start a PowerPoint presentation
Here is we are
Here is what we were doing in Northampton
And then
And then it was time for the bombshell basically in and that's it I think that was like 6 or 7 panels into this PowerPoint
Thing you know you've
You click the button up Pops this thing you know the
Target consumer in Northampton is a lesbian
John is braced for resist
We have to remember his agency
He had been going to
Years with
Number statistics data sing look
Gay and lesbian consumers are very important you need to start marketing today
Look at the numbers
And companies have been looking at this and saying
You're very interesting but
No thanks
And now here he is pitching to a car
Which is like the definition of mainstream
Annie's telling him
You got to Market your car so lesbian
In the middle of the pitch John keeps sneaking these glances at the president of the company trying to figure out what he say
He just kind of dogs
Sydney Sydney crosses his arms and you know you always learn in business that when pee
People cross their arms
They're closing themselves off
Do you or something crazy like that like we at that's where you always have to be careful cocktail party.
Pressure arm
Other people around the table are also looking at the president of Subaru wondering
Do what
Going to say
But he doesn't do or say anything
He just keeps watching
Pitch so they finish the presentation and then I don't need to invent a group to speak to
It looks like you found a group of people we can already talk
He said so this looks like a good thing
He didn't forget
Not only did he not freak out
She hired
Remember this is a car company
This is what every Ad Agency
And now this tiny little ad firm has been hired to create ads for Gay and Lesbian consumers
4 super
Now of course they had to get down to designing
The actual ads
Johnson's this proved to be a little bit
Remember they were breaking new ground here and so John had to find ads
It would fit both of the image that Subaru had been cultivating for years and years
And
With this new group of consumers
Find a Target
That's right in fact John showed me the first print ad
That he did in 1995
Until what it is is there's a Subaru up at the top
Bright and there's
Two women down at the bottom and the headline is
It loves camping
Dogs and long-term commitment
Too bad
It's only a car
Good right it's good good and then down at the bottom there's a pig
Picture of two women
When the ad first went to be executives
The two women were together
The executive see this and they tell John listen listen
Separate them please put some copy in between them
Can opposite corners of
Looking at each other
Looking looking over the tech
What can I do with a text at
Each other
Miss Johnson's the kind of settled into a
Were they would use references that were obvious to Gay and Lesbian consumers
But not really to anybody yet
And at the time there was
Xena Warrior Princess
Was the show that was airing like on
The WB Network or something and the lesbians love
Lucy Lawless
And everybody loves Dean
So one of the license place is going to be Xena lover Xena lvr
One of them was ptownie
P dash townie
Provincetown another one was a camp
Out
It was so settled the message was there
But you would have to look at the license plate on the car
In the picture in the print
To get it
John was in San Francisco when the ACT
Campaign launched she was at a bus
Stop any bus pulled up to the stop with his add on it
Immediately looked everybody standing there at punch old ladies look at
The car is done to a saying
Two gay guys and believe me I knew they were gay gaydar
Finely tuned
They both look at each other and just kind of smile like they got it
Yeah they got it
In about 2 years after this campaign started
Subaru sales started growing
The niche marketing was working
From those groups that Subaru had identified the outdoorsy types of nurses and engineers
Subaru head marketing to Olive
Edit sales were going up
And then
In 2000 Subaru made a bold move aimed right at lesbian consumers
Martina
Navratilova
Subaru hired the retired tennis star who is
One of the most high-profile lesbians in the world at that
To do this
Big at camp
How do I know about the foreman I know about control
Who do I know everything
She nose everything
Pam derderian was responsible for this campaign
She runs a marketing firm called 15 minutes ink and she introduced Martina Navratilova to the people at Subaru
In the 90s
And she says
This was the moment
When Subarus Niche marketing campaign be
Became not-so-nice
She was on mainstream television commercials
Promoting the car
She was in
Print ads promoting the car
She was an outdoor
Billboard advert
Advertising promoting
The cars
She was in Maine
Stream
Advertise
Not that there wasn't some push
Super good always faced resistance from some of its
Steelers who had problems
Sprint ads
But when ads started to hit TV the campaign got a lot more
This wasn't just
Xena on a license
These were really high-profile ads
John Nash said they were angry letters
Gears of a boycott
It's anxiety-inducing only because you don't want to lose money
Your favorite client
Over something if
Completely out of
If the business marched away was going to be because someone
Wrote a letter in crayon
I'm saying you know how dare you sell cars to be
These dirty gay p
Subaru didn't March away
They kept up the camp
A year after they hired Martina Navratilova they had their best
Sales year
Eminem 2004 there was this big opportunity for
Product
Placement
There was a show on Showtime called
The L Word
And Pam derderian helped create a storyline on The L Word
Where lesbian tennis player
Got an endorsement deal with soup
Subaru
So a Subaru supposed to get her some kind of charity event to support the Arts
Public School
How hot is that
Pam derderian says
Olive
Was a really big deal
All of this was a watershed
I kept using the term nice
Marketing and she kept shutting me down and saying
Subaru went so far beyond nice mark
We're more comfortable
Who would ever think that an ABS
AC program Modern Family two weeks ago would have a 9 or 8 year old trans
Gendered character
On this is not niche
Any longer
This is just being out
And proud
And owning who you
You are and living in a diverse
Inclusive
Society
By about
Subaru had grown into a very steady
Success
It wasn't Toyota wasn't Ford
But it's numbers were going up and when the recession hits
Super Wings
The only car company in the US
Not to lose Market
But in spite of the success Subaru
Seems to kind of
Change direction
I mean if you look at their ads now there's
New Martina Navratilova know Xena
Instead most of the ads
Speech Europe heterosexual an outdoorsy couples on their way to hike
And things like that
And the moment when our societies become so much more inclusive
It's strange
Why did Subaru back off
Yeah I was really curious about this so I called Subaru and I asked a spokesman
Any City troop we don't directly Target gay and lesbian consumers anymore our ad campaigns.
These days focus on Ark
Customers Hobby
Decent interest
Lake mountain biking and kayaking
Pamper Darien has a theory about
She says since the 90s when this started
So many more people are just living out
And what was Niche is now just much more mainstream
Sony's marketing is
Kind of passe
Brightwok Niche marketing became a victim of its own success
Of course that raises the
The question
Do ad campaign
Actually
Influence the
Or do they just
Reflective culture
Yeah I kept asking myself that question and the answer is I honestly don't know
I put that question to Amy the woman from the beginning of the show who owns a Subaru and loves the Subaru
She said honestly she does not know
But then she told me this
Amy Wendt
To college in small-town
In a place that
Was not especially friends
She did not have an easy time
And then after school she moved to Washington D
And one day she's in Dupont Circle and she's
Cease this Superbad
And I remember seeing this ad on the bus stop that said
It's not a choice it's the way were born
And it made me smile
It made her smile because it was talking to her
It's not a choice
It's the way we roll
She knew exactly what that ad was saying
And not everyone would have known
Exactly what that ad was
It was an inside joke
Enemy was finally on the in
We always love to hear what you think of the show send us an email Planet Money at npr.org or find us
On Facebook
Get a lot of people to think on this one we got the idea for the story from Alex masi Alex is the editor at
Priceonomics
You are a great story about this you can find it at priceonomics. Com
Also thanks to Dave Moore Ian Mary trispot Rebecca lindland Paul poop
A special thanks to Allison Payne
Our episode today was produced by Sally helm
Sally is a former Planet Money intern and we are looking for our next
Intern
Go to npr.org
Flash money to learn more
Also Wells Fargo has been in the news a lot this week as CEO resign
Our episode last week was all about Wells Fargo
You should go check it out it's called the Wells Fargo Hustle
Let's up if you have ever found yourself wondering
Podcast should I listen to
We have got a new show for you
It's called the big listen
Is NPR's newest podcast Lauren Ober is the host she's going to introduce you to podcast you might never have heard of
So when you want to find something new find
The big listen on the NPR one app and npr.org
Flask
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith and I'm Noel King thanks for listening