Recently I was in southern Africa and
My favorite person
That I met
Was this Apple farmer but not any Apple farmer he was
The Apple farmer of Lesotho his name was blessing
My name is Blessing
His Orchard was high up on a mountain ridge in lesutu
And You Could See For Miles out of the river and the whole Capital City off in the distance
But I was here
To see his
Trees
The all the other farms nearby consisted of just three thing
Cows
Corn in this leafy green cabbage
Blessing
We to close some Golden Delicious
Fusion
Fuji Ya
Yes we do have the cleanest meat
Granny Smith. You have a ballast
Are famous
Because blessing discovered something that no one else had
In the bright sunshine and short growing season up in the mountains where he is
His apples
Ripen faster
He could Harvest them earlier than anyone else
He could sell them in neighbouring South Africa before anyone else
And so
Fable 2
Stepped into the market
Two to three weeks.
Oh so your apples come earlier
So you get an advantage
A few farmers in lesutu who exports food
People come from all over to learn apple farming
He even has some Open Fields where he would love to
To expand his Orchard
When I asked him
What's next like what are your big plans
He said this thing
That at the time did not make sense
He was going to do
What every other Farmer in the country was already doing
He was going to start to raise Ana
Inside Man trailer
Sectional so so you're going to get cows here
But you're
One of if not the best
Apple farmer
Innocent
Is that right
Instruct
On the 12th
In the country
And my son wants to grow more apples sure if you grows more apples will make more money be able to expand even more
But explain to me look there is a drought
And have to run irrigation over from
The well to The Orchards
But you don't have the money yet and if my
So the best apple farm in the country is going to do what every other farmers
Raising cattle on the side
If the drought continues
At least he'll have something
He doesn't want to take the risk
Losing ever
Hello and welcome to Planet Money on Robert Smith
And holding millions of other small business people back in
Africa around the world
Is fear
They know what they want
They know what your payoff big
But it just seems too risky
And that is
Totally understandable
But if skilled people took more risks
The world could be better off
We have more new businesses where do ideas more delicious apples and Africa how to overcome your fear
Fear of losing every
Two Economist have two different theories
And they put them to the test in the real world
Quickly getting over their head
Support for Planet Money and the following message
Come from TIAA
Dedicated to helping those who.
Keele and sir
Achieve lifetime Financial well-being
Whether it's investing
Advice banking or retirement
TIAA helps those who do good
Do well
See how TIAA is a different kind of financial partner
And discover how they can help you what the new tiaa.org
Created to serve
Built to perform
Emerging economics building
At Yale University
There is this tiny section where they talk about this
Really big idea
Which is why do poor people
Stay poor
One of the economist you think about this alot is Chris yuan
He's a tall guy with
Gray hair
He was posted randomly
Back when he was young to Donna and the Beast
Top math
But when you become an economist he kept returning to Ghana
A once you
Live in a place like that
And meats
People
People who are
At all this
Potential
And weren't able to reach it because of the economic situations they were in
It just becomes impossible to study
Impossible to decorate with anything else his entire office is filled with Canadian Arctic
Toys
Evil wears a brightly colored ghanaians shirt when he teaches
And Chris is particularly obsessed with this
One problem that he's noticed in Ghana
When he looks at how Farmers there are doing
He sees that there hasn't been a lot of progress for them over the past couple decades you look at China or India or south
South Asia there penalties advances in farming
Farmers are using new seeds and new techniques to grow more crops to Ghana
He looks around and it doesn't
Look much
Better than it did when he was back in the Peace Corps
There's still a lot of empty field
There's a lack of irrigation
And use of fertilizer remember Robert we promised you to Economist over their heads
Dean karlan Works across the hall from Chris in the economics Department
And he started a group called Innovations for poverty action
Dean travels around the world and does experiments on what kind of help for poor people works the best for poor
Penis shorter than Chrissy's ball
Pretty fast talker he's not a Peace Corps guy Dean's early economic education
What's 2 years as investment
I just learned enough to know what I didn't want it
Which is why
All right I got to get one
Former investment banker and former Peace Corps volunteer walk into a room
To talk about the causes of rural poverty
And they have this very specific question about Ghana
Here's a place where farmers
Could clearly grow more
We could invest in irrigation and in fertilizer and they could be a lot richer
So why don't they
Dean the former investment banker
Says usually when you look at it there is a simple reason why people do things
And so
They ask the farmers
What's going on here
The answer you get when you do that most often is money
Money
Poor farmers
Are poor
Like blessing Yabba Farmer they had these
He's Big Dreams
To do things
But they say they don't have the money
And there's no one willing to lend them
But Chris you dream who remember has spent his whole life working with these kind of farmers
He suspected it was something deeper
Because you notice that sometimes the same guy as the same farmers who said they didn't have money to
Spend on their field
Would go out and maybe buy a cow
Where they start a little store on the side
So they did have some money
They do not want to put all of their eggs in one basket they're going to make sure that if
Is a disaster on one field
Pick another feel
Worth 1
Growing conditions are poor for one that got another
It wasn't just money farmers were afraid of the risk
So this became the real question between the two economy
Which one which one was it which is the bigger problem
Is it that
These Farmers don't have enough money or
Is it the eggs in one basket problem
Is it fear of risk it was
Economist
Versus economist
Did you guys
Physically fight each other or was it just verbal screaming back and forth across the hall
No I don't like that
No harsh words
Name-calling
I'm so sad I can't do anything
I was hoping for at the very least like
The caddy footnote summer
Paper
But no they are
Economist this was an intellectual question to be solved in an intellectual way which is a Rand
Demise controlled experiment
So here's what they did
They focused on Northern Ghana which is very dry and very world is a lot of farmers
And if it's a handful of villages and they started trying out various solution
Once a farmer
Chosen randomly
Got what they asked for they got money
We sent them two hundred the equivalent of $250
One time one time
And did you say
You have to use this to
Putting irrigation do some of your field now there's no rules put on how they had to use it
So that was the money group
The risk group the risk group was harder
Test because
Chris had to find a way to reduce the riskiness
A farming
That we couldn't control the weather
You can control insects or
Any other unfortunate thing that might happen out there the field
But there is a time-honored way to make something less risky
You probably have it yourself to make your life less stress
Insurance
In the case of the farmer's crop insurance
This is a concept that didn't really exist in Ghana at the
The country had health insurance
They had some forms of car and home insurance
But nobody wanted to provide for mnsure
If we want to do this we wouldn't have to
Make a Christian Dean insurance
You're going to have to start your own insurance
Yeah
There's a lot of things that go into an insurance
There's a lot of paperwork the statistics and decide how much
They would pay out
And figure out when to pay out which is not an obvious thing
You don't want to pay somebody for having
Bad crops
Because then encouraged them not to
Put a lot of effort in not to get up
So they ended up facing the insurance on rainfall something that farmers can't control but is going to affect
That you can measure
If it rained too little or too much
The insurance policy would pay money to the farmers
If there was normal rainfall no payouts
Stop now. Just need Farmers to sign up for
Farmers in Ghana had never seen anything like this I've never seen rainfall
Insurance
So
The Christian Insurance Company
8 explain what
Is this
Insurance NY
Should you get it
And so if you're in Northern Ghana a couple years back say you're a farmer you getting ready to go out into the field to grab the radio
You're going to hear this
Attention-grabbing ad
If you happy and you know clap your hands if you're happy and you know it clap your hands
Any good news it is exciting interesting indeed very good news have you heard that they got agricultural Insurance Pool
Will get past come out with a new insurance policy to protect our crops animals and poultry I cannot hide my feet
I'm so happy
Did that sound happy
I think he said so legit happy
Crop insurance
And then if you were in one of the target villages
You would then get a knock
On your door
A young researcher with Dean's group Innovations for poverty action
Would smile
And would redo a script
Hello
We're working with
The ministry of food and agriculture we recognize that
You
Need help
Dealing with the unpredictability of
Rainfall
This is Lindsey Shaughnessy
A young woman by the way who's only previous sales job was working at
Clam Box
In Ipswich where she grew up
Oh my God it's in the shape of a giant like takeout
Container
Our first year I had a lot of charts I had
30 page Scripts
Facts and figures out that this was going to be more than just getting people to sign a policy
In order for insurance to work
People need to believe in it
They need to believe in it enough to risk
More money to risk their livelihood
How to invest more than fart
Here's how Lindsay did
First off she would show people the simple economic
You pay us the equivalent of a couple US dollars
And if there isn't enough rain which is measured at a rainfall state
Then we're going to make up some of your losses
Not all of them but enough to get you
So maybe a couple hundred dollars
Not a good to the farmers
Affected sounded great to the farmers
Wendy started to notice the people were talking about the insurance
Like it was gambling
Like they were gambling on next season's rainfall
When you say you give me a little money
And you might get a lot of money that
Seems like a lottery
And were they using the word for lottery
According to my translator yes
Which was a huge
Problem
The point wasn't
For Farmers to pray for a drought so they win the lottery
Lindsey need a different
Lindsay wasn't a salesperson Clam Box aside
So it took her a long time to understand the most basic
Rule of selling
Don't pitch the mind
Pitch the heart
She started to put away her charts
And she just talked to these families
You would start out by saying
Can you remember a year
Recently in the last 20 years or so that there is a giant
Flood
Or drought
And they would say yes
Of course
Let me tell you some story The Farmers would tell me stories about oh my goodness I can't believe
You know I couldn't feed my family this year no one could in the village and so we would say to them
Okay
This would have been your payout
600 TV
These 500 CDs
And they would say
That wouldn't have been
Close to enough money to cover my loss
Sheetz I think of it
Like helping
Donna has government Health in
And yet no one hopes their child gets sick
So they got to pay up
Crop insurance you would say is the same thing
Emotional Point home
Lindsey's team created a soap opera
On radio the told this heartbreaking story
Of a man a farmer
Who is trying to decide
If he was going to get caught
Play my music.
He decides not to everyone else in the field gets the insurance
And sure enough
The insurance pays off
United Jiggy alarm
You can hear them counting up the cash
Everybody in the village gets the cash
Except for our hero
And he cries for about 10 minutes
I know it seems over-the-top
But really when you think about it when you think about
What insurance does
All the shirts has that tragedy built into it like I may get in a car wreck
I may get very sick
My house might burn down
And so they were short of teaching people
Did this is the emotion behind Ensure
And
It worked
Farmers rushed
To sign up for the
In fact a lot of fun
We expected hundreds of policies being sold and we got thousands
My first reaction was Delight
This is working this is fantastic
My second reaction was
Oh
What are we going to do
If we have to pay out all this
If it did not rain
In Northern Ghana that year
They would have been on the hook
For more money than the calculated in their Grant
They would have to pay at a half a million dollars
So they had to go to the higher-ups at Yale and say
If it goes bad will you lend us the money
And you'll said yes but we are going to take it out of your future grants
With our future at you
Which was somehow dependent on rainfall in Ghana
Well yeah
Now
Who's Gap right now who's gambling
So then we get these numbers everyday
No rain
Sprinkle
The no rain
Then
Finally the clouds
Opened up not a lot
But enough to hit the rainfall tar
This was very good for the farmers
Even better for Chris and Dean Insurance Company
Didn't have to pay out any money
If you would been a real company you would have made a profit
If we been real company we go tomato profit
That should say
Like in any
Real Insurance Company
Not everyone was happy
Lindsay said after the Harvest she started to get
Calls from
Some of the farmers who didn't get a payout
And they said let me look at my crops
They're technically was enough rain I know that
But the Harvest is terrible
They told her in my opinion my Cranston do well and I really thought you'd be helping me out
And now I'm kind of in the Lurch and so
What that large was varied it might be
That they didn't have enough
Food to bring to Market it might be worse that they didn't have enough food to give their families
So wait what did you say back
This was how Insurance works
So that was always a tough conversation
At times like that the team had to keep reminding them self
All of this
All this insurance company stuff was
For a good reason
They had to act like a real insurance company in order to get the data for
Four-wheel insurance
And finally
They had
Look at it the farmers who got cash who got the $250
They did spend more on there
They cultivated more corn they had a bigger Harvest
But even more interesting was the farmers who got the insurance
Because talking to them afterwards the researchers found that once the farmers had insurance
We would find the money to
To plant more crops
They would go and borrow it from their parents or their kids
They would go in on new field with different
Amongst the people who we had given nothing
Other than a promise
Insurance Group
The Insurance Group
So they got
Literally nothing other than a piece of paper
It said that
Under certain circumstance
Money
They increase the size of their fields
I invested more
Reply more fertilizer
To its remarkable
They found The Money Pit
Combating that far
Same people that said they didn't have fun
Yeah
So to recap
Giving Farmers money Wars
It leads to more investment and that leads to more crops
But giving them Insurance works even better
And insurance is way cheaper than just handing out cash
And as much as I begged
Chris
To Lord this result
Over Dean
Say in your face red
They would not come
You're taking all the drama I know I was sucking your drama
I just wanted a little more soap opera Opera in the show
I died there is a soap opera
Are the results of a study are
Dramatic
Enough because insurance I think we think of this as is like
Boring
Financial
Tulane we don't think about it because it's everywhere in our lives
What is this really powerful tool to study shows
To motivate Behavior
I mean thousands of farmers doing things very differently
Out of the sheer promise
Of having to risk lifted off their shell
Right now it just has to work in the real world
So when the experiment was finished Chris Indian had a private insurance company take
Silver and so far it's been
Pretty slow going right it's hard to drive out all of these World farms in to sign people up and you don't have grad students
It's not catching on
Not yet but the market is out there
Remember blessings
The Fabulous Apple farmer in lesutu
I asked him about it
Do you have to have insurance here like crop insurance
No no no no
Nothing
You can't buy them with sudo because it doesn't
Exist
He said if it did exist
Are you think about buying it
And here's where you can see the behavioral power of insurance because when I asked him like what would you do
If you knew you had this
Protection against failing
And he's like oh
Well I wouldn't need
The cows
Plant this and I can grow more Apple
Here and I could put in this thing I've been wanting to do this new irrigation
How do we get to bring back and listen bohos for
Mitigation
You would drill more holes looking for more water and you could grow more trees
I can even leave the cat on the dead animals husband
And just what sticker do this
It was definitely worth
It would be nice to have a safety net in case the rains don't come
Tell us what you think of the show send us an email at
Planet Money at npr.org or find us on Facebook or
Twitter and special thanks to Jamba and the other team members of the Ghana office of Innovations for poverty action
They were really helpful and getting us out with information and the soap opera in the advertising campaign
This episode was produced by solihull
And if you're looking for another show to listen to check out NPR's ask
Me another
Trivia night
Listen to NPR. Org
Flash podcast
Or on the NPR one app
Thanks for listening