What are things that amazes me about political.
Is it on one hand the candidates are trying to talk to
All of America
How to make this really
Big
Simple
Emotional case
But then when you're watching the base they bust out all of the
I have never heard of and everybody has to look them up online
Like OMG
BPM
Patriation in offshore
The prophets and the Dragon
When have a tremendous income
And the reason I say that is not in a braggadocious way it's because
It's about time
But this country had somebody running it
That has an idea about money
Pronunciation
Braggadocious
Sam Sanders
You've been to
This man's
Rally's
Is this a term he uses a lot
This was the first time that we really heard Trump use that word
But the root of it
Bragging
Is it thing that he does a lot over the course of the campaign
Maybe these pictures the definition
Yeah you know for him his businesses are
The best
His deal making ability is the most amazing
He will make the best jobs
The best economy everything will be
Bigly
This is Sam Sanders host of the excellent amazing
NPR politics podcast
In
Host for the special post presidential debate edition of Planet Money
Do the thing you do I'm a huge fan
Hey
Is the NPR Planet Money podcast
I love it
Play initial I have in my hands
9 of the most confusing economic terms of
The first presidential debate
And I'm telling you Robert Stacy the whole planet Money Team
What's my name
It is a glossary in alphabetical order
From the rmb
Did the TPP RMB is right next to the alphabet
Let you know me we'd like to say a quick
Thank you and share a message from our planet money sponsor betterment
Betterment has fundamentally changed the way Americans save and invest for their future
Traditional investing Solutions are expensive complicated and boring
The betterment was built from the ground up
With sophisticated cutting-edge technology
It recommends a personalized investment plan
Simply put
Betterment makes it easier more straightforward and less expensive to invest
For more information and up to six months free
Visit betterment.com Planet Money
Alright alright alright we have handled
Braggadocio
That is number one and we cannot say that word enough forget about the duchess braggadocious braggadocious braggadocious
The number two in the glossary Outlet
You do it yeah number two is carried interest
This one came up at Monday's debate
An interesting Robert because it's actually one of the rare things
Hillary Clinton and Donald Trump agree on
How much they hate
This think All Care dentures
I'm getting rid of the carried-interest provision
And if you really look it's not a tax but you would not
Great thing for the wealthy it's a great thing for middle-class it's a great thing for companies to expand
I feel bad for the people who went out to get a beer can back to the TV set and you're just like what
Is he talking about
Carried interest
So I'm going to explain
Will trump and Clinton want to get rid of this loophole
What's essentially for the
And the loophole goes by the name Carrie interest
Carried interest provision
I'm going to give you a little word origin story
He's Economist at the urbanist
Carried interest comes back from the days of shipping
Where you would give
The captain of your ship
20% of the profit on selling
Right and I give the captain a really good incentive to
Get the ship
From point A to point B
And it gives them an incentive to sell the cargo at a good price when he gets
So they had an interest in the things that they carry
Carried interest
Firms which I get there
Modern day ships
The managers of private Equity firms
They take
People's money to invest
They buy companies they sell them
And then these managers
Just like the old sea captain
They get a cut
The profits they get their percentage
The carried in
And it's essentially their paycheck
How they make their living
Thought
This is the key parts
They don't pay regular income taxes
Is carried interest
They pay much lower investment rate
So both Trump and Clinton say that we should get rid of
Call this carried in
We should just tax Rich managers like everybody else
Okay number 3
Currency manipulation
Does usually combined in a sentence with another word
China you look at what China is doing to our country in terms of making our product
They're devaluing their currency and there's nobody in our government to fight them
Currency manipulation
That does not sound
I know it sounds very blue
Nefarious
Obviously though all it is is 4 years
China was
Accused of manipulating its currency that you want so that was artificially low compared to the dollar
And what that meant was the Chinese goods were cheaper when they sold
In the US and that made them very
Competitive for us
Really hard for us
Companies to compete
It was hard for them to
Have prices that would match the prices
That is
The currency manipulation that
People were talking about and we're worried about
So is it still happening now because Trump talk about it
All the time
Yeah that's
Interesting because most people don't actually think that's happening at all anymore in fact
Anything the reverse is now true
China has been trying to kind of prop up that you want and that has made Chinese Goods more
Expensive in the US than they would
Otherwise be
And has made us Goods cheaper in China than they would have
All right number for
Robert this is a word that I hear constantly on
Manufacturer
As in I want us to invest in your future
That means jobs and infrastructure in advanced Manufacturing
Well the first thing you do is don't let the jobs leave
The companies are leaving
I could name I mean there are thousands of them they're leaving and they're leaving in bigger numbers and ever
Obviously we all know what the word manufacturing means
Sit means sit
Large facility to
Mapreduce objects
Smith machine
But, this we know Emily Oster from Brown
She pointed out that the way
Both candidates
Use the word manufacturing May mislead
You would think everyone in America was in
We either work in a factory making an air conditioner or we work in a small business making draperies
Or you know our job has been as a as a car manufacturers
Bishop doctor mask
That is the only job
That people have
Intersection of the vast
Majority of us
Make anything
We don't process anything we don't run the machines to manufacture and process things
Only 9% of jobs in the US
Orion manufacturer
Most of us do
What we're doing
Right now I mean
They're they're podcasting
Keychain
Healthcare
He working retail they're doing something for somebody else
Why not more discussion of improving jobs wages better schedule
Saturating the service act
This is where most people work
Well I have a theory about that Robert yep
Politics inherently is aspiration
We talked about and I politicians talk about what we wish things were not what they really are
In so much about the days of manufacture
I seem more American and simpler
And harder you know it's
So much of the service economy we're still figuring out and it's hard to explain and it
Difference
And it doesn't feel as good as
Going to that good ol Factory job
You know we're talking about that after the debate you know as reporters like we fall into this
Is to casino work
We're fascinated with the closing of Drive-In
Diners like we always want to do the stories on
Annan Farmers work
We're so fixated on these
Disappearing parts of America
Exactly like you don't see campaign ads about the beauty and american-ness of the emerging service economy you just know
Yeah maybe they should stay in the healthcare worker out into the field of
Greiner as the Sun is setting in the could make it more romantic
Outdoor hats
Exactly right
Take us to number what number 5
NAFTA
Okay it's me
The North American Free Trade Agreement
I
I'm actually research this a lot
I hear a lot when I'm on the road
The more I hear about it
The more I am
This is true end end disc
Kids coming up during the debate and especially
Donald Trump's you have very strong feelings
NAFTA is the worst
Trade deal maybe ever signed anywhere but certainly ever signed in this country and now
Yuan to worst
Deal
Ever
Everywhere back to the ancient Greeks the ancient Romans the sink was the Trojan Horse terrible deal
Back to the Garden of Good and Evil
Eva's like y'all mathas
Write what what NASA did was eliminate these protect
Do taxes on goods from Canada and Mac
So it made those things cheaper in the US
Which made it harder for us come
Pete
Especially since labor costs are so much lower in
Still though the worst
Steel lever
Sounded
Big so I asked Michael Munger about this he's an economy
The claim that NAFTA was a bad deal is
A very
Narrow
View
Of what
Policy should do
So the thing that NAFTA mostly did was reduce the prices of products on both sides of the Border
So that was really bad for some us businesses because they
He couldn't compete with the price of goods from Mexico the textile industry took a really big head
But it was good for consumers we could get stuff at a lower price
Yeah so I talk to my colleague Danielle Court
She covers
Policy and data for India Palace
And I asked her about nap
The end she says the thing with this deal
Is that
The good of it was hard to
A lot of the things that you buy
Got cheaper because of nap
But you didn't immediately
Thai that
Trade deal
Right but the bad of
Size was very visible
You know that some factories
And some jobs
Moved out of
Compounds to other country
Freight in FX impact on jobs was not as big as what
People worried that
It would be because our trade with Canada and Mexico
Well significant is still a really small part of
The US GDP
Okay I'm going to take number 6 all by myself
I'll be very quick
It's kind of a pet peeve of mine the TPP
The trans-pacific partnership
I do know that you got to Planet Money
I've handled this one quite a bit
But I have a small bone to pick
Here's my thing with the way politicians talk about
It's always part of a larger Rift
About trade
How the USA
Preston Trail
In China this
TPP that
And they end up
Lumping TPP together with China
But here's the thing
TPP
Does not
Involve China
Is the trade deal between the US and 11 other nations
None of which is China
And the idea is that it gives those Nations and the US
The upper hand in trade
Against China
In the region
So that's it
You can hear more of Planet Money talk about this but
Alright where are we now
We are in the T
In art list
Moving alarm
Yes we are
And so let's let Hillary Clinton take the next term because she made up the
Is joke about how to characterize Donald Trump's plane was a very memorable moment in
I call it
Trumped-up
Trickle down because that's exactly what it would be
Glass cleaner
Trumped-up trickle-down
When I get a chance of trickle-down
Yeah so this is one of those moments was like such a
Queer sort of
Quote-unquote zingers
Underground in there watching it
But Michael Munger The Economist from Duke
Said this was his favorite moment in the
It's both so hokey and yet her sort of smirk as she said it
It was a kind of pride of authorship
And the audience reacted well
And it did connect to the pad the Republican Pastor the more I thought about it the more I was taken by trumped-up trickle-down
Down economics
The Republican past
The course was
Ronald Reagan
He was big champion of cutting taxes
For the wealthy
This is called a trickle down economics bike
The idea is that if you cut taxes for the wealthy
The wealthy will take that money and they will spend it in all kinds of
They will buy cars
Houses in food Sydney will hire a landscaper as an architect
Cancel that money will then trickle down throughout the whole
Economy
And Mike Munger says Trump's plan when it comes
Taxes is
Quite classic
In that way
Trump wants to cut taxes
For the wealthy and Ferb
Businesses and Hillary Clinton was very very vocal about wanting
Increase
Now this is one of those
Perennial
Debate
Between Democrats and Republicans
Weather
Trickle down economics
Supply-side as
Blue favorite color
Whether it actually works massive tax cuts have not worked
Previous
Republican
President
What is Mike Munger say about
Trump's
Trickle-down
Trumped-up
Trumpet Circle
I know I lost my own
Bet
What Michael Munger is a Libertarian so
Told me that he actually is not a big fan of either can
He said this plan that
The trickle down economics
Plan does work in certain ways
And then also doesn't work
It just depends on where the rate of Taxation is so friend since he told me that income taxes in this country and his appeal
Are so low that if they got cut it would actually not help
The overall economy
But he said the corporate taxes
In his opinion are quite
Either 35%
And if those are cut as
Trump said he
We plan to do
He thought that actually
Would help the economy
Trickle down through the rest
To the economy and help to bring companies and jobs back in
Soap for the next term Robert
You got to say
Donald Trump uses lots of different words
To speak highly of himself
It was one that I heard last night
That
You don't usually hear
I'm extremely under leveraged
You got to play it again I deliver
Extreme
Show me stupid about you did you did you change your hair and you lose weight are you under leveraged in the debt Department
I was on the under leverage cleanse diet you're looking very leverage list
If I can say that
Thank you
So we should play leverage means
Simply you of taking out a loan
Business
And people who take on too much debt are called over-leveraged
So I think in French - thinking well if over-leveraged
Is bad
Then under Leverage is good so
Essential truck is saying I own
So much
Stuff
So much stuff that I could take out
But I I choose not to
To do so
And it's funny because like
When you hear
Him say that you realize that Donald Trump spent a lot of
Time
Talking
Two other rich
Spends a lot of time in boardroom salon
Golf courses
And so a lot of The Debaters
Explained by the sort of
Medford Spa
There's one more but I think jumped out
To all of us here
You'll hear Hillary Clinton first
Donald was one of the people who rooted for the housing crisis
He said back in 2006
GI I hope it does collapse because then I can go in and
Buy some and make some money well it did collapse
People
So what is that right there that's called business
One of the things that I've noticed about Donald Trump following him over the last few months here and there is that
He fully believes
That
To get the deal you want
It's okay to say whatever you need to
And so people will critique him and say while he contradicts himself
You know he says this one day and then that the other
That's part of his plan
He relies on exaggeration and hyperbole
And going there
To get the deal that he want
And he says that that will help him be a great deal maker
But country
That's called bisque
Juno
Alright it's time for the last word in our debate
Glossary and we're going to let Donald Marron The Economist
Do the honors
We asked him
Was there any particular
Moment
Did stood out to you at
Oh
Where is card-carrying economist
When mr. Trump was accusing the FED of being political
My ear zombies
Picked up at that point
This is Janet Yellen of the Fed
The FED is doing political by keeping the interest rates at this level
This Janet Yellen or Citrus last in list yelling,
Janet
Is the chair of the Federal Reserve
The best job is
Is the set interest rates
I Supply in Marin says Trump is leveling
This incredibly serious charge at yelling
He sang
Did the FED is monkeying around with interest rates
To try to sway the election
And that's the thing the fat is not supposed to do at all
It supposed to be in depend
To do what's best for the car
Ameritas that's what Janet Yellen in the Federer actually trying to do
So I don't see any evidence that the FED is acting
Yeah I think there's
Perfectly Fair discussion to have about
Whether the FED is pursuing the right policy
But I don't think for a minute when should you got through Athletics
How to talk to a carnival
For the show I feel like
You could feel them fighting
Between the two lens
There's a political lens
What time is the economic and they were frustrated because the economic lens
Doesn't
Really make a lot of sense
What these candidates are saying
But you sound like you're an expert in the political
Lensx
But that's sweet of you is it wrong to try and like tape
Words and in defining and say what they actually mean
It up so it is fine to geek out over these words
The Archers the definitions
But you got to understand policy does not happen without politics
You know so we need both working together to get anything done
So it's perfectly fine
To stress over these words
But it's also totally fine
Distressed over the policy
6 + 2
We're taking nominations for the Planet Money dictionary if there are other
Terms you want to find the questions you want answered
Rat Planet Money or leave a comment on the Facebook page for the Tempest
Our show today was an all-hands-on-deck
Shepherd so a lot of things to do
Alex goldmark Brian Dorsett and
Great Neck Mountain
And a special thanks
To you
Sam Sanders from the NPR politics
Podcast
This is
An amazing podcast you guys are so
Fast and so on the news and there is this
Sighting
Sort of announcement you're going to make about the end of the election
Yes
A lot of big houses
Of course we're going to have special episodes for you after every debate between now and the election
On top of our regular Thursday weekly Roundup
But for the last two weeks of the election will have an episode
Every single day
This is what we've been training for in working for for the last
Year and some months of this campaign season we are going to finish so strong you guys and I want you to be there with us listen
But who's going to host the podcast after those two weeks you guys will be
The Sleep room
That's the NPR politics podcast
NPR Planet Money
And I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
And I'm saying Sanders thanks for listening
And by the way you do look under Leverage
Well thank you so much
I feel like when people say that it means that all those times I didn't say anything I was over left
No that's not it at all you ever looked over
Why you never talk about anybody else
That load