Support for NPR comes from investor.gov
Presenting this mess
When it comes to investing
We all have Quest
And investor.gov has answers
If you're free resource for tools
Tips and information about investing
Before you invest
Investor.gov
Ian purkayastha tasted his first truffle when he was 15 years old
It was out of the fancy restaurant with a friend's family
The server came over and said okay we have a
Eye specialist for tonight and it's a black for ravioli with a foie gras sauce
And
It was music to my ears
So I should explain why a fifteen-year-old boy was
This excited by black truffle ravioli
And family had moved to the country and and it started learning to
Forage for mushrooms
And for foragers truffles are almost
Mythical
They're really hard to
Find the groundhog round
They're only found in the wild
Nobody has ever figured out how to culture
And nobody has figured out how to make anything else
Taste or smell
Quite like that there's only one thing the tastes and smells
Like a truffle
And of course truffles are ridiculously
Ridiculous
Ian ordered the Truffle dish
You know it arrived it was steaming it was
It was amazing
They were shavings of truffle on the top if you cut one of the ravioli in half
They were chunks of black truffle and the ravioli
I mean if it was earthy with snotty was mysterious
Is unknown flavor that I never tasted
That was it I mean it was like
Such a revelatory experience
You know I can t remember like
You know where I parked the car yesterday but yet I remember everything about this
It was to this day the best dish I've ever had in my life
Ian became obsessed
He took all his savings and use it to buy a kilo of truffles
Italian website
But then when they arrived you realize he had bought way too much
Who took the extra tried to sell it to restaurants
In town
I showed up on the doorstep with this
Bag of Truffles and a scale I bought at Target in an invoice book from Staples and
I said hi
I'm eating I have some truffles would you be interested in buying some truffles
I don't know if it was the novelty of this
Get out back tooth 15 year old kid walking in the door
The backfill truffles
But I sold him I made a profit
And that moment is why we are standing in a walk-in refrigerator in Queens at 11 in the morning on it
Tuesday
Cracking open a shipment of white truffles
The Ean has just flown in from Italy
So how much money is in this box
I don't know $20,000
Yep
$20,000 that's about 8 lb
Truffles and he's going to sell all a pound by 5 p.m. today that's a restaurant start their dinner rush
Also
Chocolate Junkie
Hi welcome to Planet Money I'm Dan pashman
And I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Today on the show we follow Ian
Hustled his way to some of the finest kitchens in New York
Selling
We battled traffic
Parking cops Smuggler's penny-pinching chefs and the cruel mistress of time
Also we try to figure out
What it is about truffles
That makes people pay so much for them
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Salesforce
Salesforce helps marketers get smarter about their customers and plan better campaigns that blur the lines between marketing sale
Sales and service
All in the name of customer success
Salesforce Powers marketing for the world's most Innovative brands
I'm tailored emails to engaging mobile app social media and targeted ads
That's great marketing made by you with Salesforce connect to your customers in a whole new way
See a demo at salesforce.com NPR Podcast
Before and can go in southeast
He has to make sure that they look up
He cut open the box just covered with
Us custom stickers
What is this moment like for you
Ian
Pure
Anxiety
Honestly
That's because so many things can go wrong between the time the truffles come out of the ground Italy
Ian gets them in Queens
It could get
Stolen they could be
Left on an airport tarmac
The airline maybe doesn't refrigerate them proper
They could even have bugs
And the troubles have already been on this amazing Journey 2 days ago these were underground in a forest in
Tuscany
And they were found using.
Dogs that are trained to sniff them out I'm just removing all the ice packs from top of the box
Oh is that the smell smell
What do you think my God that's no it's not good
I love it or something it's like burnt to me it's like mushrooms combined with
Dirty socks in a good way what is dirty socks in a good way
Ian takes out a truffle
He holds it up to the light smells it
Sort of golden white Yukon Gold
This one is very nice
Ian looks really really
Because he's banking on these truffles for his business
Regalis Foods
White truffles are only in season for about 12
And during that time and makes most of his money for the year
Aeropostale truffles into a dented styrofoam cooler cover with packing tape
Load them in the trunk of his car and wear off
You needs to sell these $20,000 worth of truffles by 5 p.m.
Because that is when restaurants are gearing up for
Doesn't do it
He's in trouble
Because literally every second that
The passes
The truffles are losing value or mostly water and every moment that they are out
Of the ground they are losing water they're drying up
Do it's like with every red light that we had
A few pennies fall out of your pocket
Pretty much I would say I lose about
3%
A day
If we do the math
I'm probably going to lose
About $1,500
Just an evaporation loss
Just in the trunk in the trunk do you think about that when you're sitting in traffic
I mean I've learned not to
Do red lights later we arrive at Peoria in the West Village
It's noon
We backing down a one-way Street
My back down the street
You're parking like in a red zone right now
I'm in a red zone
How much money do you budget per year in parking
Probably $10
Really
You just park wherever you just got to park the truffles will not wait
They can't wait
Ian jumps out of the car grab the Styrofoam cooler balances scale on top of it and we rushed into the restaurant
How are you
Peoria is this really romantic
Aerie restaurant and the Chef Christopher cipollone meet the cynic
Ian son rapping
Tukwila right now what are you thinking at this moment Chef as he unwraps what's it what's going through your mind I'm pretty excited
Wedding rings me
Jeffree star poking through the cooler looking through the truck
These are actually
Gorgeous
We've been doing quite well with the truffles my friend
We're doing a simple
Handmade ricotta strascinati
And we
Pleasing butter and pasta water and adjust
Chiba truffle tableside
How much is the dish
Additional $85
Bastille
Damn this boom
You think about it this is like pasta and butter
Which is basically
What you feed
A child who has a stomach flu
Images of some of the cheapest food you can get anywhere and checkers is 80
$5
Price for a plate of buttered pasta
Well butter pasta with truffles on top
Yeah and other is some logic to it because the idea is you want something kind of simple
All the focus is on the
Truffles you know what you don't you don't hang the Mona Lisa on a plaid wall
Red you put on a white wall to make Spotlight on it
And pasta with butter is
The Culinary equivalent of a white wall
And how many grams of truffles doing fire
5G
Is the weight
Of a
Nickel
That is how expense
For that amount Chef Chris is paying Ian about
$25
And he's charging his diners
About $85
What is a $60 markup
That's a powerful food
Yes it is
Inch of Chris's people are
Happy to pay this
Because truffles are special
You can't get them all the time or space
Don't have them and they're just excited to have this experience
Do customers come in
Especially because they want truffles
Yes definitely every year we've people kind of love to see what we are doing the Truffle assoc are and
Preparations are doing and
Chef Chris buys just under a half pound of truffle
Which is Trust
Cute ruffle that you wanted
The size of a racquetball
Repeat over
Annabelle
That's a lot of money for truffles $967
Hilda got a couple days it's all good
Those few truffles will make about
40 plates of pasta
Profit from those plates of pasta
Will be more than two
Thousand dollars
So this whole time we were talking a chef Chris Ian
Texting
Madly odd
Is phone glancing for the door every few minutes
Tapping his toe
On the floor
He hasn't sold a pound of truffles yet
Give me the four and a half hours to go into the restaurant start
Impacts of the Truffles and we're off
Wow
And and no ticket no ticket
The next deal went down literally on a street corner
Steven Falls over
Private chef of a wealthy family
Comes out
Play Pop the Trunk
She goes through the truffles
And then a couple minutes
Another sale
How'd it go
Good
/ 4000 sold
$4,000
Yeah
Between the private chef and Peoria and his old $5,000
We still has $15,000 more to sell
So we drive to the house of a
Hedge fund billionaire
You jump out of the car
Seldom a pound of truffles
Yeah I guess you know he's going to put a
Is coffee or something you need that
Yes by now it is 130
And the dinner rush
Starts in 3 and 1/2 hours
So how are we doing so far clockwise
We're a little behind
Old timer whiskey and he is just
In the zone
I mean he's texting he
He's driving his
Making deals on the phone and in person
The guy just has so much
Focus
He's only 24 years old which I think
Cesar reminded both of us.
Total failures
Also bolts
He has been doing this a long time he came to New York when he was 8
18 years old
At the time he bought a minivan and he would load it up everyday
With truffles
And fresh
I would drive around to restaurants
And and beg chefs to come out to the van and and take a look at what was inside my van
I was working 16-hour days like hustling and you know I have so much stress I was losing hair and I had
I have this weird like acne-like flare-up and I was embarrassed to like go outside and I would
Make an entire
Dad of macaroni and cheese and basically just like watch Netflix in like
Cry myself to sleep
On weekends and it sucks
Things Are
Much better for Ian these days in fact this year he is on track to make
6 million dollars in sales
And the whole time we're driving around with him I was just so struck by the contrast between those huge dollar figure
We keep seeing hearing
And just the ragtag nature of the operation itself
Styrofoam coolers in the back of a rental car because other car broke down
Keys
24 years old
Sort of unshaven and looking somewhat sleep
Deprived
It interferes with more in common
Mid-level weed dealer
Van
A luxury food Titan
That's what he is
Vici just signed a multimillion-dollar deal with William Sonoma
To sell truffle salt
And truffle oil
Butt and told us he's never going to stop doing this
Fresh truffle
It is the centerpiece of his business
Italian makes most of his money
It's how he keeps up his relationships with the best chefs in New York relationship that he made when he started selling mushrooms out of his
Minivan
In fact when his first
Customers who
Used to buy things out of his minivan is where we are headed
That is lure fishbar and the chef is a guy named Josh capon
This is one chance at love
Chill
Bargain
So what was your strategy going in
And it's a situation like this
Maybe start a little eye
See what he says
We're double-parked
Going in fingers crossed their tickets
Restaurant pack the middle of a lunch rush so wait a little while for the chef to come out
Inception is cooler is still texting texting texting
And then finally the kitchen doors open and the chef comes out
How are you funny
My name my name is Josh capon
We are here at the legendary lure fishbar
Was my good good buddy Ian
He is actually in my phone as Ian truffle boy
Chef Josh starts inspecting the truck
Was always a pleasure to see him and
What exciting beautiful
And in this case
Gorgeous smelling
White truffles from
Demonte Tuscany Tuscany one of the truest beautiful pleasures of the World by weather on my honey
I stay in the castle it was stupendous
I'm just smelling his wife troubles I'm transported back
Could a castle with my wife where we
Drink champagne with
Fresh peaches off the trees and
Made love in the forest together
Amongst the Hogs
Is this the radio or TV
If it was for TV I think that the screen just went dark
Totally
So Chef draft picks out a few Truffles and piles the money is little kitchen
And then they both start punching numbers and their own calculators
I say we knock this number.
1200 even
REI Fortune $1,000 even
Ladies and gentlemen $14
Just came off the bill
Amazing
Chef Josh
Vice V truffles
For $1,200
Yeah and they just they Fitness two hands
Jeff just told us he plans to serve them on a lobster risotto later tonight
And on this special cheeseburger that he makes at the burger place
Across the street
It is a $68 cheeseburger
What she says has gotten
Quite
Burger
Admiral I don't really blow your mind
We rushed back to the car and still has about $12,000 worth
Truffles
To sell
And it's 2:30
Our next stop is Minetta Tavern it's a well-known pretty high-end place in the West Village
The chef is Dan Silverman
He's at all
Reserved guy
Is this has been seeing a lot of trouble of dealers around me
Are there a lot of people who sell truffle or drug
Yeah there are this time of year people just get people just wandering off the street with like
Checkered cloth bundles full of truffles
Does just like random people always every year
Probably
I like to buy from people that I know
And hit the thing there are aliens
All over New York City
You could be passing one of the street
Right now with a backpack full of 20 grand worth of truffles
People are from other companies but a lot of them are just hustlers
The walking from one restaurant to another
With a backpack full of truffles they smuggled from Europe
And you can see why they would do this
1 truffle cost
Thousand dollars
And you can fit a lot of truffles into a suit
When we get back in the car and tells us yeah there are a lot of trouble smugglers in New York right now
And they really hurt his business
They cut out the middleman they don't pay custom
And they cut His prophets in half
Incest used to make 20% profit
Now
More like temperature
Richie restaurants like the other two and three Michelin starred restaurants are the ones that love to negotiate because
Getting so many so many different ruffle people in the door trying to sell the product but they have
Choice of who they buy from
At this point
3:30 and Ian going to leave
He's got 90 minutes left to unload like
$10,000 worth of Ruffles and let's face it Stacy
We were slowing him down
So and drop this off in SoHo and at this point we are both
Starving and
We both smell like
Dirty socks
In a good way they see your word for it
The dollar exchange
And I still have never
Tried when I've no idea
Because we're consummate journalist we had to Burger & Barrel to try Chef Josh capons
$68 drop off
Is the third week that we've been getting in white truffles and an honor that
We're doing our famous white truffle Burger
I highly recommend
I
Would like to order that
Are British arrived and they are
Beautiful
The truffles are sliced thin and
Fanned out
Over the top of the burgers you can see them
5 grams
Apparently worth of truffles
Cigar bites
Okay this is it this is a big moment
Nonon I know how to describe it it's like shoes that tastes like shoes smoke cashews
I told you dirty dirty socks in a good way
Yeah see around
She's like dirty socks in a good way
The best description I'm sorry I doubted you
I'm in
She say she want to tell you
Dirty socks in a good way
Dirty socks in a good way we actually call us and food scientists figure out what the
Dirty sock thing was
What is it about this flavor
The captive these people so much
Change DNS life
And it turns out that
Truffle smell and taste comes from this molecule called androstenol
And you just found in sweat
And urine
Yep farmers will spray female pigs Lindros known to get them in the mood
Which is
Hot and you know I'm not get it I know why humans are obsessed
What truffle is because
Picanha
Smell like us
You're eating
Humanity
The thing that we most want from the finest
Fanciest restaurants in the world
Is sweat
Sex and urine
That is why we look trouble so much
You think it'd be easier to reply
OK Google
A cheaper
Totally but I just think this is also something about this high-low combination
Which way do restaurants get
The food is like what one of their finest
Most desired ingredients in there getting it in this order sketchy
Back alley kind of way
White people wandering in off the street with napkins full of truffles or
Styrofoam
Google Earth
Speaking of which we check back in with Ian to see how the rest of his day
A little bit longer because we were his good luck charm after he left us
His car got towed
With $5,000 worth of truffles in the trunk
Was that your car getting towed with $5,000 worth of cash in the
Cash that is disintegrating
It's right but This Is Where I Leave You
Calls and texting to been doing all day paid off because he'd actually been taking orders from chefs all over the country for any left
Leftover truffles he might have
So as soon as he got his car at the impound lot
He spent the FedEx office at JFK Airport
And Indians world this is a buzzard
Because we're in the parking lot
He packed up the truffles
And got them sent out just before the
The final FedEx
Deadline
Which means
If you recently ate truffles in
Chicago Ord
Relay
Cisco
It's quite possible they were packed up
In the trunk
Car
DNA so much fun reporting this story with you and you just
How much is all the time on your podcast the sporkful
Yes the sporkful to podcast about foods that are more about people one of my recent shows was all about a food called pork roll
Roll of North Taylor ham
Iconic food in New Jersey for people that have been fighting about it
450 years
Self to find out why
And if you want some light reading and actually has a book coming out it is called truffle Boy comes out in February
Pre-order it now it's all about his
Business hustling truffles all over New York
We also want to thank Helen hollyman from the website Munchies who introduces to Ian and smell scientist Avery guilty
We always love to hear what you think of the show you can send us an email Planet Money at npr.org or you find it
On Facebook or Twitter
Today's episode was produced by the wonderful Elizabeth
And as we are ramping up to this big presidential election check of the NPR politics podcast they have new episodes
Episodes coming out everyday to come look at this
Big moment for our country
You can find that on NPR one or wherever you get your podcasts
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
And I'm Dan pashman thanks for this evening