Hey guys it's Noelle here today's episode is a rerun
It was originally reported by Hannah joffe-walt back in 2004
And we have an update for you at the end
Okay here goes
Betty and George are planners
Betty especially
Years ago that he looked around and identified George Phillips
As someone she would probably marry in the future
You're the truck mechanic same background sense of humor
Somebody made a plan
And 4 years later George Phillips quite happily
Peking Betty's husband
George and Betty plan to shovel the snow on Saturday
The call Betty's brother on Tuesday after
46 Bubba
Before 8
To finish the 1000 piece puzzle on the card table immediately after Betty has finished organizing the pieces into tile
Bicolor
And Daddy has a plan
Bird f
Oh I have been answered long time ago
Maven
Fred Meyer funeral arrangements
It's all written up in some paperwork filed in her home
With duplicates at the
The papers
Called an advance directive
Spell out exactly how Betty would like to die
No machines no feeding tubes no CPR
I want you like to have happen after
But he's not sick
She just wants everyone to know what you'd like to have happen
George has one too
Oh yes
Fix one up in 2004
So very good idea where do I be kept alive just to
Be a vegetable
She feels about like I do neither one of us
Chemotherapy
If you guys have cancer why are you talking back to me
But
Like I said
Planners
Betty and George live in Lacrosse
Wisconsin the town of 50000 people on the misses
Mississippi River
Right next to Iowa and Minnesota
And there's a lot in common with other towns that size in America except for one thing
A lot of people in this town have planned for their death
They've written down instructions of what they do and don't want to have happen
At the end of their lives
This is not just planners like Betty and George not just people in their 80s
Percent of the people who died in the cross
Have planned for their death
That is an astounding number
Across the country about 30% of adults have done some sort of end of life
Planning
And even if you look at severely ill people
It's only about half
96% here
Which means you can go to any random black and his town and stand a pretty good chance of talking to someone who has considered how
Oh here she would like to die
Like just across the street from Betty's house
Alan Jean
They made plans for the end of their lives
Years ago
Next door Sandra Legrand tells me she and her husband
Made most of the medical decisions
But they've been going back and forth lately about the burial
He wanted to have his body in
Underground
And then he said well maybe I want to be
So we both were thinking of
Cremation
Inside
And then we both decided maybe we'll just be buried
In the ground
In the urn
You know after being
After they left it when they filled out the paperwork
Cassandra says Cheerilee
This kind of plans are common enough that it's when someone does not do it
That's when you notice
In the course of our conversation Sandra mentions the Eric's
Other people about mentioned the Erikson's to me too
The Erikson's has not filled out their advance.
Sandra Legrand told me
She's an animal that is
Kathryn Erickson was putting away her yoga mat when I showed up on her doorstep
She and her husband Randy were chatting with her daughter about her homework
And a
Awkwardly mentioned that they have a rap on the Block for neglecting to make end-of-life plans
They both laughed and said oh yeah. Legrand's have been nagging us about that for a while
But we're having dinner with the Legrand
Is tomorrow and maybe we
Definitely ask
Forget about it
They're sparkly eyed teenager Annie sez
It's okay we talked about all that stuff
Before I know what to do
I know for sure if my mom is ever stuck in a coma
And there's no hope for her that she supposed to pull the plug in
Tattoo
Is she right
Yes
I feel like the teenager talking to Annie and actually everyone in Lacrosse
Asking strangers questions about death makes me uncomfortable
Because I'm from the America were talking about death is like talking about sex
You don't do it
At least
Not a lot and definitely not on some random Wednesday evening with
Your parents
Annie happens to me from this one tiny pocket of America
It just does death differently
This conversation by the way in the Erikson household
It just kept going everyone in this house
Is perfectly healthy but they seem to kind of get into talking about this
Annie starts detailing her plans for her dad's
Funeral
For my dad I do have a song in mind already
Bruce Springsteen
Terry song
Why have you thought
Which one out for your dad
It's a good
It's a good funeral song
The funny thing is it's like a hidden
Amtrak
What happened you at seventeen
Your dad's
The song that you sing at your dad's funeral
Actually sure how it's
Become such a come from
How indeed did this become such a comfortable conversation in Lacrosse
Wisconsin
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm kinda joffe-walt
Ann on Today Show we are going to answer that question with the story of the one place in America
That is at ease with mortality
I'm going to talk about how being comfortable with mortality
Save a lot of money
Planet Money is supported by betterment
The largest independent Robo advisor with more than 180 thousand customers
Andover 5.5 billion dollars under management
Betterment makes it easier and less expensive to invest for your personal financial goals
With a beautiful user interface smart Cutting Edge technology betterment brings you sophisticated personalized
Financial advice
All of the lower-cost
Planet Money listeners get up to 6 months free
To learn more about betterment
Visit betterment.com Planet Money
Lacrosse Wisconsin used to be like everywhere in America awkward and fearful about death
Couples did not go back and forth about cremation versus Burial at the dinner table like
Like they were talking about which movie to see
Neighbors didn't gossip about the one family on the Block
But had not planned for its demise
The people of a cross discuss death right now
Because one guy decided the town needed to be talking about it
Because if they were not talking about it
He was the one who ended up having to do it
Have these awkward painful conversations with everyone
This guy's name is Bud Hammes he works at the local hospital as a medical ethics
Which basically means Bud was the guy who would get called when someone's dad had a
Stroke and was being kept alive on machines
Side with the down with
The family end
Try to help them figure out what to do next
Every time
The discussion was
Excruciate
Well you could see it on you know on Face the English like
Tried it mean you could just
And in the comments that they would made you know how what do you think Mom would want I don't know I got to
Did Dad ever say anything to you
Don't know what to do here and that's why I was called in to help
These families at least sort this out asbestos
Weekend
The moral
Distress that these families were suffering
Was
Palpable you could feel it in the room
End
That no matter what they decided
They would never
Have any clarity
About whether they made the right decision
The thing that was especially maddening to bite about these conversations
Was that they were entirely predictable
Most of the time the conversation would be about a patient who had been sick for years we've been coming to the hospital
Over and over again
Sometimes multiple times
I found it distressing
That
We were taking care of patients and not giving them any opportunity
To have a voice in their care
Should they become incapacitated
Take the dialysis
The center at Gundersen health
Square Bud work
What's the hospital
There are 60 people in the dialysis
Center only two of the 60 had living wills or advance directives that specify if they were
To be kept alive on machines
And for the people in the dialysis center
This was likely to be a real question
Potentially in the near future
So that's our bed started in the dialysis center
You started with the nurses
He gave them all training on how to ask every person to complete an advance directive
How to sit with patients and go through questions like
If I have a stroke do I want to go on a ventilator or not
If I can't do this or that do I want to stay on Dallas
So the nurses all got trains
And then
The months went by
Not a single nurse asked a single patient
It was just too
Scary
So
Badass one Brave nurse to be the first
To be the model for all the other nurses and show everybody this was not going to be a big deal the patient would be open to it
And watched what happened
So the nurse assigned to this responsibility
Approached
Patient
And
How the patient started to cry
And her response was
I don't think I'm ready to have this conversation
Versation
So the nurse did the right thing and said well
That's fine
If you change your mind let us know and then we can have the conversation
It didn't seem like a success at that moment
But eventually the patient did come back to the nurse and said she was ready
Other nurses started to be ready
YouTube they started asking patients
And actually the other Hospital in the cross asked Bud to come and work with the nurse
Is there
To train people how to talk about end-of-life
Care
Verona lachman a nurse in the general surgery unit at Gundersen hospital where Bud works
She told me she had to practice saying the words to herself over and over again
Before she could finally approach a real life
Patient
And then she did
In one of the surgeons came up afterwards and said
I don't want you talkin talkin about Advance care planning with my patients before they have surgery
It's like they're going to die and I don't want them thinking it was nothing like that but a lot of people struggle with that
That of course is the whole point
It's difficult to talk about
So the more you talk about it the more
Routine the question is the more comfortable it is to be asked
Macross you were asked again and again and again
You're going to have surgery and what you have done
Hysterectomy
What we have here to in who's your doctor
I'm Steven
Debbie Thurston is in her 30s
With red hair a red face red sweatshirt
She's not sick but she will be asked
If she wants to fill out an advance directive here during her pre-op
So have you ever done anything like a a living will
No I haven't
Debbie said she's not interested right now
Tomorrow if she becomes interested
So have another opportunity shall be asked again when she comes in for her surgery
CC tells me the last time she had a procedure at the hospital someone left the paperwork by her bedside
Every every time I come to the hospital life and they asked me
I just haven't done it
And what do you think when they ask you about it every time
That's a good thing I just don't
I like to think I'm young and I'm not going to need it
Even though Debbie is saying no right now
She will almost certainly fill out the paperwork before she dies
Which hopefully will be many years from now but if you think about it 96% of the people who died here have one
Imagine how many more times Debbie will be at
All that nagging eventually leads to follow through
In Lacrosse
Even if it takes you until you were actually confronting a life-ending illness
To take a look at these questions
It won't be the first time you're considering them it won't be the first time you're thinking about all the choices you have to make about the way you want
Make yourself at home
Okay
Beautiful morning isn't it
Cool out there though I bet you
Glenn muhlenkamp is a cheery 81 year old farmer sitting on his favorite recliner at home
Annies dying
Glen's prostate cancer has spread to his bones
Season hospice
A nurse from the hospital Laura Weidman is here to help him fill out
Is advance directive
Glenn's wife Jenny is
Flitting about showing Laura the nurse pictures of every one of her 27 grandkids
And Laura
The nurse masterfully guides Jenny to a chair next
The Glen to have a conversation
Jenny clearly does not want to have
You know when people have
A chronic illness
Like you have
Sometimes complication
This can occur
There could be a point where
You might not be able to
Speak for yourself
Jenny Glenn's wife is
Sitting on the edge of a chair rocking back and forth
Her head is turned sideways away from Glen and Laura her eyes are locked on a window
And Laura the nurse is mostly talking to Glenn
But it's fine designs that his wife
Is here too
It's impossible for her to cover all the scenarios under which gland may die so the more specific
She can get from Glen
Hurt his wife Jenny to hear him say
You better
So Laura the nurse start sticking through some options listed on a stack of
Shethority
Okay
If your cancer spreads and you reach a point where the treatments will extend your life by a few months
And the side effects are pretty serious
Would you want them to continue to do all of that or would you say
No
Stop
If you had a serious complication from your kin
Cancer
But you'd probably live through the complication
You would probably not walk again
Or you might not
Be able to
Talk again
What would you choose them to do
Continue to do everything they possibly can for you
Or would you say no stop
Stop
Glenn's wife Jenny's eyes are still locked on the window
She still rocking
But she has started silently
Weeping
Laura the nurse puts
A hand on Jenny's me but forges ahead
Okay Sam's in area she says
Survive
But you never know who you are
Would you want them to continue to do everything for you or would you want to
Stop stop
Cuz I've seen that for
They're just there
And that's not for you
Jenny Glenn's wife actually gets up and walks away at this
Glenn doesn't stop her and neither does the nurse Laura
Have you had enough of this conversation
I just had to get up and see what was
Danny looks around
Aimlessly surveying the house
And then she mumbles
It's a big house
Any other room the nurse and Glen finish up the plan for the rest
Glenn's life
No machines
No feeding tube
No ventilator
No CPR
Stop
Stop stop
There are few places where you find this kind of conversation happening regularly
And the conversations actually help explain this other Salient fact about lacrosse
Something I haven't mentioned yet it is a very unusual
La Crosse Wisconsin spends Less on Healthcare than any other place in the country
That comes from a group of researchers at Dartmouth College
B study the huge variation in healthcare spending
Between what Miami stands for
Grand Junction Colorado
Miami's at the top
La Crosse Wisconsin is at the very bottom of the list
Of the 306 region
Send the Dartmouth theater
Lacrosse spends Less on each person on Medicare
Than anywhere else in America
That's not only because of these conversations about death but it's a big part of why
One-quarter of healthcare spending is on the last year of life
And planning for death
Thieves money
Because most people are like Glenn when asked ahead of time about their dying days and how they want things to go down these days
Stop stop stop stop
Here's Jeff Thompson the CEO of Gundersen Health System the hospital where but hammett's were
It turns out
That if you allow page
To choose and direct their care
And that you share that information with their families
Then
Waffen
They choose
Of course
But is much less expensive
And if people just had to guess
But humans and Jeff Thompson are panic
That I am going to make it sound like this is why lacrosse has
Advance Care Program
So let me clearly say here
It is not
In fact if you're Jeff
Running a hospital
It doesn't make any sense hospitals get paid for doing things
There's a billing code for a hysterectomy
For a hip replaced
There's a billing code for asp
There's no billing code for Advance care planning
How do you
Pay for that program
Here
Well I really can't answer that because that
That is not a
A good death sign of a CEO because of course we lose money on this program
This program makes no economic sense
Anyone taking care of
Medicare patients on a fee-for-service basis
So Jeff Camp Hill for it
It does save money to do this kind of planning
But it saves
Medicare
Money it saves insurance companies money not
Jeff
One-quarter of healthcare spending is on the last year of life
That's pending that goes to hospital
Doctors
For us we spend money on a program
That ultimately will decrease our Revenue stream
It robs you of money later
Right right but but it's clearly the right thing to do
That is a lot of money though that you're leaving on the table
You're right
Jeff says they do it because it's
It's the right thing to do
And frankly he tells me
I wasn't here at Gunderson when they started doing Advanced Care planning but if I tried to take it away now he says
The community would revolt
This is just how we do things
So you can see why most Hospital CEOs may find a program that have to run for free that would almost assure
Assuredly reduce one of the hospitals
Largest revenue streams
You can see why they might find that unattractive
But still there must be someone in Washington who would try to push through an idea that is
Relatively simple to implement and proven to save money
Right
This is the thing Tom Grissom president after president has tried to
To do reduce Healthcare spending
You think they're beat someone who would want to make this happen right
Wow
There was
You may remember in 2009 the phrase
Descant
What was in the news
That year Gundersen La Crosse Hospital helped write something for the house Reform Bill that would pay people
For doing Advance care planning with Kay
And this is what happened
Bureaucrat
Rash and care if the bill goes through as Obama wants it to go through
Sarah Palin warns that the government was going to start rationing care and was going to decide
Who could get care and who could not
It was Wildfire or seniors going to be in front of the death battle
Pulling the plug on grandma or denying her care
Sarah Palin has a rock them with that one because she's dead right they are death panels
It's weird the fact that end-of-life planning could save money you think that would have popularized the approaching a country
6 of the economy is Health Care spending but in 2009 it was actually probably why it did not
Become more widespread
It was a bug
Not a feature
Health Care reform passed without the death panels
That we're not really death panels
DuckTales actually means
But the lot did include Financial rewards for hospitals and physician practices
That could figure out how to reduce spending on their own
So a lot of them are naturally turning to Lacrosse
Trying to figure out what they're doing
And they're reaching out to but him is to ask him how do we get people to plan for death
You can hardly handle the calls coming in
They told me when he first started this in the cross in the 1990s in the dialysis center
You better to take
A year maybe to get it set up and started in the region and then maybe a few more years for it.
Spread throughout the country
20 years later but is putting off retirement because he's pretty sure this is the moment
This is when it's finally going to have
It's Noel here again to big things in the story have stayed the same and one has changed
Is Hannah said about a quarter of all Medicare spending happens in the last year of a person's life that figure hasn't budged
And neither has but he is still not retired yet
Does this sub this change roll
Give me working at least for a few more years
When I'm able to make this transition from one home to another as it were
And we have in place the next group of leaders
I'll be happy
To step down
The transition he's talking about
That is the big change
The end-of-life planning program looks like it may have finally expanded Beyond lacrosse
The program is going to
Move to a National Coalition call the coalition
To transform Advanced Care
And so we think this is going to be a better home for us because it will
Really tired send to a national platform
But says he's even spreading worldwide the EU is funding a study called the action trial that'll test a version
Canada lacrosse program in six
Countries
Including Germany and the Netherlands
That's our show for today
We always love to hear what you guys think you can email us at Planet Money at npr.org or get in touch on face
Stock for Twitter
This episode was originally produced by fear been in today's episode was produced by Raina Cohen
Thanks Reyna
Also you can take Planet Money and all of your favorite NPR shows with you on your commute or while making dinner with
NPR one
It's an app for your phone kind of like the Pandora of public radio whenever you want to listen NPR one is full of
News local stories and podcasts including Planet Money
Find it on your app store NPR one
I know Elle King thanks for listening