Support for this podcast in the following message come from NCR who believes in small businesses
That's why they build NCR silver
Worthington point-of-sale NCR silver deliveries big Enterprise management tools
Built for small business owners
Visit ncr.com silver
Hey Robert here
We thought we would try something slightly different for today's show
A very good friend of Planet Money it comes Tim Harford is launching a new project
It's a sort of quest for him
And we reach them outside
In the middle of month
Activate your new podcast for the BBC World Service called 50 things that made the modern economy
Just don't understand how it will
Came together
How the world around us where you know the kind of stuff you guys are interested in
Which brings us to where you are right now where are you
Is a step back in time
I am in a
Quiet corner of London
And I'm standing next
The Temple Church
Central London
Which is who
Nearly 900 years old
Let's see if we can get into the church
So I can hear these ethereal Voice is coming from inside the temple I
Imagine this is a concert by rehearsing was a beautiful door in front of me
A wrought iron work on it
Anoka
And above me a call a man on the top of it is a statue metal statue of
2 nights
Sharing a single horse which I think represents a vow of poverty
These nights the long for medieval order that you've probably heard of
The Knights Templar
It was funny because what we know about the knights
Templar what I know but the Knights Templar is that I don't know much about the Knights Templar
Except they Bruna Dan Brown book right
Exactly right
Exactly right there's some sort of conspiracy I'm sure of it though I don't know what it is a numerous conspiracy and
Who knows maybe some of them a true but the reason I'm here is not because of any particular
Conspiracy I'm here because the church that I'm standing in front of
It's not just
A religious site is not just an architectural site
Temple Church in London first
Bank
Hello and welcome to Planet Money on Robert Smith
And I'm Tim Harford a very old church
In London England
Change the way we think about money
It's a story of bloodshed
Will domination
And accounting
Lots and lots of accounts
It's the birth of the bank coming up
Support for NPR in the following message
Compromise shares
Because the best preparation for tomorrow is building for your future today
Ishares by BlackRock
Inspired to build
Would you like to take over the rest of the show we're going to play an excerpt
Of his new podcast right now
It's the story of the Knights Templar
XI wristband
Knights Templar
Religious order with a physiologically inspired hierarchy mission statement and code of ethics
They will also heavily armed and dedicated to a holy war
How many times can rice get into the banking game
The Templars dedicated themselves to the defense of Christ
Christian pilgrims to Jerusalem
Jerusalem has been captured by the first crusade in 1099
And pilgrims began to streaming traveling thousands of miles across Europe
If you're Christian pilgrim
Have a problem
I need to somehow found monks of food and transport in a combination
But you also want to avoid carrying huge sums of cash around
Because that makes you a target for robbers
Fortunately the Templars have that covered
Pilgrim could leave his cash at Temple Church in London
Temperature in Jerusalem
Instead of carrying cash
It carry a letter of credit
The Knights Templar with a Western Union
At The Crusade
We don't actually know how the Templars made this system work and protect themselves against fraud
Was there a secret code verifying the documents in the identity of the traveler
We can only guess
That wouldn't be the only mystery 2 shroud of the Templars
An organization sufficiently steeped in Legend
The Dan Brown had a scene at The DaVinci Code
Contempo
Church
Know where the Templars the first organization in the world
To provide such a
Several centuries area
Tang Dynasty China used phaquan
Find money
Tupac documents
Allowing Merchants to deposit profits in a regional office
And we claim that
Back in the capital
But that system was operated by the government
Templars were much closer
Tattoo a private bank
Will be at the private bank owned by the Pope
Allied to Kings and princes across Europe
And run by a partnership of monks
Sworn to poverty
Knights Templar did much more than transferring money across long distances
They provided a range of recognized B Morton Financial Services
If you wanted to buy a nice island off the west coast of France
Something King Henry the 3rd of England Aid in the 1200 with the island of Alero
Northwestern Bordeaux
Well the Templars could broker the deal
King Henry the third page 200 pounds a year for five years to the temple in London
Then what his men took possession of the island the Templars made show the seller got paid
Oh when the crown jewels of England
Stool today at the Tower of London
In the 1200
The crown jewels were at the temple
It was security
On a loan
That was the Templars operating as a very high-end pawnbroker
Knights Templar were in Europe spank forever of course
Toyota lost its reason to exist after European Christians
Completely lost control of Jerusalem
In 1244
The Templars were eventually disbanded in 1312
But then who was to step into the banking vacuum
If you'd be in at the great Fair of Leon in 1555 you could have seen the answer
Leon's fair with the greatest market for internet
National trade in Old Europe
Contagion back to Roman times
Could this particular fire spread
Italian merchants
Keyboard nothing and you have nothing to sell
All he had was a desk
In an instant
Alyssa
Day of the day at the fair continue
Receiving other Merchants assignment pieces of paper
And somehow
Becoming very rich
Extraordinary
And frankly to the locals
Fairy suspects
Thought to a new international Elite of Europe's great Merchant houses
This particular Italian activities
He had a very important role
He was buying and selling debt
And in doing so he was creating enormous economic value
Here's how the system works
Dimension from Lyon who wanted to buy say
To go to this Bank
And borrow something cold a bill of Exchange
The bill of exchange was a credit note
Iru
These are you wasn't denominated in the French liberal the florentijn lyrics
Its value was Express
In the HUD Ma
Private currency
Used by this International networkers Bank
Play Selena's Merchants travel to Florence horse and his agents that
The bill of exchange from the bank of Hakeem Lyon
Will be recognized by Bankers in Florence
Who would gladly exchange it for local currency
Through this network of bankers.
Hello, Merchant could not only exchange currencies
Also exchanged his creditworthiness in Lyon
The creditworthiness in Florence
Icty nobody had ever heard of him
That's a valuable service
No wonder that the mysterious Bangkok was rich
Add every few months
Agents of his network of Bankers would meet
The great fast
Like Leon
Go to that books
Metal full credit notes against each other
Encephalo remaining debts
How Financial system today still has a lot in common with a cyst
An Australian with a credit card can walk into a supermarket in that say Leon why not
And she can walk out with groceries
The supermarket checks the French Bank
French pancakes with Australian Bank
Australian Bank approves the payment
Happy that this woman is good for the money
What is web of banking services has always had a dark side too
By turning personal obligations into internationally tradeable debts
These medieval Bankers were creating that own private money
I'm not private money with outside the control of Europe
Kings
They were rich
And Powerful
I didn't need the coins minted by the sovereign
That description brings true even today
International Banks are locked together
In a web of mutual obligations
The Define understanding or control
They can use the international reach to try to sidestep taxes and regulations
Since their debts to each other a very real kind of private money
When the banks are fragile
The entire monetary system of the world
Ulcer becomes fat
We still trying to figure out what to do with these Banks
We can't live without them it seems
And yet we not sure we want to live with them
Governments keep searching for ways to hold them in check
Sometimes the approaches be laissez-faire
Sometimes no
Fuel Regulators have been quite is autumn
King Philip
Fourth of France
Fiat money to the Templars
And they refuse to forgive his debts
In 1307
I'm assigned to what is now the temple stop on the Paris Metro
King Philip launched the raid on the Paris Temple
Temples with tortured
Enforced confess any sin the Inquisition could imagine
The order of the Templars was disbanded by the Pope
The London Temple was rented out
I'm a lost Grand Master of the Templars
Jacques de molay
Was brought to the center of Paris
Publicly burned to death
That was Tim Harford
New podcast for the BBC World Service it's called 50 things that made the modern economy
Available on the BBC website
And wherever you get your podcasts
Before we go I wanted to finish up our conversation with
Tim Harford
Still Standing on the street corner in London
Do a chimpanzee great story of the first
Bank it's obviously one of the things you'd want if you were doing a series on 50 things that made the modern economy
But I knew some everything from the list are are some of stranger things you wouldn't think about like
The Barre code
How did you decide
What made the list and what did
What's the most important thing was to get 50 interesting things 50 things with a with a few surprises is awesome
Supposed to be just
Got the 50 most important things
That I could think of
Open Temple the steam engine
He's not on the list of the computer is not on the list because they're not important
Yeah they just so well told
So I was looking for a spread of different Industries different ideas
Different parts of the world and different surprises
The Barre code
Is interesting
Not because it's a way of processing
Transactions more quickly
It's interesting because it changed the shape of global supply chain
It changed
Who was a winner and who was a loser in the retail industry
So that that's the kind of weird looking for the economic impact as well as just
I know the computer was in poor
What's your favorite story
I have to say it's whatever I've just been working on adjusting working on management consulting
Management consulting
Yeah who invented management consulting who invented management
Who made the idea of selling consulting services to managers and why did a group of academics
Stop providing management consulting services free in India
Randomized controlled trial
The barcode the shipping container the bank
It's all here
Tim Harford thank you so much
Thank you
Tim Horton's recommend to book
About the history of banking that he relied on for this episode
William gets mint Money Changes Everything
And Felix Martin's money
The unauthorized biography
We always love to hear what you think of the show you can email us
Planet Money at npr.org
And thanks today to Marnie Chesterton and to our producer Elizabeth kulas
Robert Smith
Thanks for listening