Support for this in
NPR podcasts
The following message come from that UPS
Offering services from shredding
To printing to mailbox
And instead of closing this Memorial Day we
May 24th and 25th
The UPS Store
He's doing another thing
All together
Opening
The UPS Store
Everything for small business
And of course shipping
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
And I'm Jacob Goldstein
We are working on a few shows about the election of Donald Trump
After today though we wanted to capture a little bit of what happened in the economy just in the past
24-hours it is dinner
You know it's been a crazy day right of Aries
Surprising 24-hour soap for the show today
We are bringing back the Planet Money indicator on the show it's where we take a number from the news and
Triumph Sprint unpack it a little
Today Show is 3 + 2
Caterers that is three numbers that tells part of the story of what a trump presidency will mean for the US economy
And for the world
Support for today's episode of Planet Money
And the following message
Come from Audible
Who has more than 250 thousand audio programs from leading audiobook Publishers and business information providers
Including presents
Bringing your boldest self to your biggest challenges
By Amy Cuddy
Audible is offering Planet Money listeners a free 30-day trial membership
And a free audiobook to get started
Go to audible.com Planet Money
And start listening
Anytime Anyplace
Soap Jacob our first economic indicator
5%
That is how much the S&P 500 dropped last night
When it started to look like Donald Trump had won the US
Yeah and so the S&P 500 that's the US Stock Market
Are the stock market itself is closed in the middle of the night but there's this overnight futuristic
But the bottom line is this measure the Traxxas stock market it was tanking
Michael Farr was watching this all go down from his house in
Florida use a head of investment firm Farr Miller & Washington
When it started to become clear
That we were not going to have president-elect Clinton and we were going to have president-elect
Trump the markets
Futures
I markets
Cell
NF
Midnight last night the sentiment was sell everything
You ever owned and move to Canada
There are a couple reasons this was happening
The first thing is just that the markets don't like it when something unexpected
Clinton was expected to win and a trump Victory meant all kinds of things the market hadn't really planned on
Trump had said all of these really
Stream just erratic things
During the campaign
You know that one of the debates on national TV he threatened to lock up Hillary Clinton
And of course he talked about dissolving trade deals with other countries in
Starting something like a trade war with China so it's 3 in the morning
All around the world
Kind of panic
Futures markets are way down
And then Trump comes on TV
To give his victory speech
And Michael is watching
Hillary is worse
Very long and very hard
Over a long period of time
And we owe her
A major debt of gratitude for her service
2 hour
Country I mean that very sincerely
It was
Conciliatory
It was statesmanlike
It was gracious towards secretary Clinton
It was inclusive
It was a very good moment for him where he
Actually appeared presidential
And the Futures as he was speaking
Started to rise
Now it's time
For America to bind the wounds of division
Have to get together
A Michael says producers there was one other line in Trump speech that was especially important
I want to tell
The world community
That while we will always put America's interests first
We will deal fairly
With everyone
Call people
And all other nations
Michael says that speech changed
Are the time trading started this morning the markets were up
The entire drop Adventure Race
But they're still this question hanging over every
So is the question now like
Is President Trump going to be the
The Statesman he appeared to be in the victory speech last night or the
Candidate he was that was less statesmanlike in that made the markets drop
Please
Answer that question for me and everybody else and America's will cuz we're all on the edge of our seats are we
I mean that's the question
That's what we all want to know
Will the real Donald Trump please stand up
So I think this could mean that
We may be just one erratic speech away from another huge drop
Jacob you have our next indicator
Baidu our next indicator is
As of right now it's Wednesday afternoon
It takes 20 Mexican pesos to buy 1 USD
We talked about this with Anna azuara she's an analyst at a bank in Mexico called Banco bus
And she told us a few months back people started noticing some
The peso was tracking the polls of the US election
When Donald Trump started to do well in the pool
Ben the mick
Mexican peso started to get weaker and when Hillary Clinton did better in the polls
The peso got stronger
That's because people were looking at Trump
Trade policies Blake getting rid of NAFTA the trade deal between the US and Mexico
The worst deal ever
Yashow people heard him say this and I thought so if Trump wins
This is going to be bad for Mexico
And you know the fact that the peso was falling clearly means that people believe that Trump would do what he said he was going to do
Everything he has said about the NAFTA is
It's bad for the economy
So
Yah mean
This friend money that it's going to jail
Get out of Mexico
Antoinette foreign money gets out of Mexico the peso gets weaker
Last night on a left the office went home and watched the u.s. election results roll in on her teeth
She's All That Trump was going to win
And she felt like millions of other
People in Mexico
We're watching them
He was feeling disappointed and
Worried about
The future of that's what's going to happen
What's going to happen to Mexico
Yeah
Unlike
Millions of other people in Mexico
Anna also pulled out her phone
To check the currency
And then I saw
How the Mexican peso was getting weaker on my cell phone
As I'm sitting there watching TV and checking her phone late at night in
Traders in a jar frantically selling peso
In fact the value of the peso fell by about 10% overnight
That is the biggest fall in 22 years
According to writer
Honda says it has everything he says he's going to do
Mexico may fall into a recession in the next
Robert Smith you have our final
Trump in
I will take over Jacob seat and deliver it
To you
Are Trump indicator
Number
For today
And I'm cheating a little bit here
Care because it is not
Actually number for today at the number that is weighing heavy
On the hearts and minds of investors
Today and that number comes from Allen Cole
An economist
From the tax Foundation
1.5 trillion dollars / 2
1 + 1/2
Trillion dollars over 10 years
Robert I love this number because it represents in ongoing mystery about Donald Trump's tax
Pants that nobody has been able to solve
Text Economist like Alan Cole a man
I should say who is xian the rare ability
To intimidate Donald Trump a little bit just a little bit
The story goes back to a simpler time
Donald Trump is a candidate that no one is taking very seriously
Except
The tax Foundation
They're nonpartisan group that basically runs the numbers on the candidates tax plan
I got assigned to Donald Trump
408 days ago not that he's Counting
And the time Donald Trump was promising to cut
Everyone gets it
You get a tax cut
And you get a tax cut the richest people in the country we're going to get their taxes cut by more than
Third and uncle's job was to add up how much all this tax-cutting would cost the Federal Gov
So he took
All of everyone's income in the United States
You expect over the next 10 years
Kiwi jiggered the tax rates
Data to the numbers and
Whoa
Final
Number
Look like
The biggest tax cut in history
That number was filed trillion dollars
Did you recheck your mouth
Oh yeah I looked at this up
You know I saw that number and I thought well that's
Really really big
0 somewhere
Yeah
In order to pay for a
Trillion-dollar
Tax cut
You would either have to borrow a lot of money
Increase
Is the national debt
Or
You would have to cut government
Spending something close to a quarter of the federal budget
25%
It just slashed right off the top
Alan publishes this number it is a
Huge news story
At first Trump tries to argue with it
Then he tries to ignore it
And then
After getting criticism on that
He started to
Considered new things and
Throughout
2016 there were rumors of
A
Smaller more compact tax cut
You may be
One of the few people
In the world
Who is change Donald Trump's mind until
I do think about that
I think one thing about this is that
On policy he's prep
Morflex
Possible then he gets credit for
And it's only one someone tells him something like
His businesses are bad or his buildings are bad
Then you know he will be very
Adamantly
Defending himself super upset with that yeah yeah yeah
Personal
Policy personal
And so Donald Trump came up with a new text
A plan that would also make sure
Did you had the last laugh
On Allen
Just like the first plan this new plan also cut taxes for just about every
Very large
But the rich don't get quite as big of a tax cut I mean the richest people in the US still do benefit the most
Ghost from the Trump
Oh yeah I mean the average incomes are going to do very well under the Trump tax plan but
Overall the cost of the plan is
Half of the planet initially proposed
Although we're not entirely sure because Trump made it so that Allan Cole could not add up the total cost of
The plan and publish one big number again
And he did this by starting to say two contradictory things
Yeah what do we talk to small business
Trumpet say oh I'm going to cut
The corporate tax rate
But not just for corporations
Also for small businesses like
Mom and pop places
The file very simple tax return
Is it you
You are going to get a
Big break just like the
The big Corporation
Obviously small business people were really excited about
But when asked about it later by reporters and tax analyst
Trump seems like
No we're not going to do that not at all
Why would you think that
We've been calling it Schrodinger's tax cut
It exists
But it also does not exist at the same time
If you pick one or the other it makes this huge difference
In the budget tax revenues could go up
Or go down by
That number
That we picked
At the indicator at the very beginning
1.5 trillion dollars / 2
That's a big gap
References to small business tax cuts were quietly removed from Trump's website a couple of months
The election
And reporters had a hard time getting a straight answer about whether or not you still being
We are still watching for it and if you want to watch for it to you should know that these
Small businesses affected by the cut
Are technically called
Pass-through entity
Which is weird saying I know it's about how their income gets tax pass-through entities
But you might want to hear this term now that Trump is
Is the president
Or not
No one knows
Eventually if Trump wants to change the tax code you will have to go through
To Congress and Republicans control both houses so they might be open to the bigger tax cut option
Forbade might decide to go with the smaller
Eventually someone is going to have to make a decision on Schrodinger's tax-cut they're going to have to pick one of the two options
And actually write down
Once things are written down in legislative tax
You can't have that at
Ambiguity
And that's something that they're going to have to wrestle with
And then finally
Finally
Alan can sit down
And he can do the back
Thank you Robert you're welcome
We're guessing that you might have a lot of questions right now 7th West Planet Money at NPR
. org you can also find us on Facebook and Twitter
You're looking for something to listen to that does not have to do with politics check out all songs considered
The music podcast from NPR
These are the best new and upcoming music every Tuesday on the NPR one app
Or wherever you get your podcasts
Today Show was produced by Sally home with help from Elizabeth kulas Rena Cohen and Alex goldmark
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Thanks for listening