So just I don't know if you happen to see
See this video
It is of Theresa May the prime minister of the UK
UK and she's at a European Union council meeting in Brussels
Which type are you
Oh she's all alone
So you see all these European delegates talking and hugging in the fancy conference room and Theresa May is just standing in the middle of
Everything
Totally alone
Bomber jacket
No one will talk to her
It's brexit Chima
She's getting stubs because of brexit
And it looks almost exactly like my junior high lunch room
Does awkwardness might continue
It looks like 2017
Might be the year the European Union
Starts to break up
When the UK begins this two-year process of decoupling from the Union
Is there actually using the eu's own constitutional rules
Allah called article V
It's an exit clause
It says if any country wants to leave this new Union
It can't
It was a late addition to EU laws and it was
Controversial is it a good idea to have a prenup built into the laws of your brand new Union
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Jessica and I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
The exit clause
European Union has one United States of America does not
Spanish o we consider the exit clause
After all there has been this wave of protectionism kind of sweeping the globe and soon we could all be
These lonely Teresa maze at the EU council meeting
Support for Planet Money and the following message come from betterment
A smarter way to invest your money
Betterment combine time-tested investment principles with the transparency and ease-of-use do you expect everything
Focusing on lowering fees and taxes
And here's what you might find refreshing
Betterment really cares that you reach your financial goals and that's why they keep their fees low
Planet Money listeners can get up to six months with no advisory fees
For more information visit betterment.com Planet Money
The roots of the European Union go back to the 19th
Europe has gone through two terrible world wars
And the EU was the symbol of a new era
Peace and free trade
All of these countries coming to
Chemical element with one of the architects of that
He's from Finland a longtime Member of Parliament
And the EU is like his life's work
You are founding father
Beaver County Father's Day
Felt so strongly that now we are creating United States of Europe now
Chemo spent years in small conference room
Hammering out tree
Read he's trying to make this Union
And it was incredibly hard it meant juggling the interest of dozens of countries try to overcome
Cultural differences and language barriers
Even something as simple as cracking a joke with a nightmare
It had to be filtered
Dozens of translators into more than 20 languages
If I make a joke
The first people to live out the finished delegate and estonians who understand Finnish
Let's say 15 seconds or 10 seconds later on start to BB cloth
When that man with those who are listening to English translator
Alafia
I've been gone 10 seconds more 15 seconds more often than they have been translated from
English to the national language
Chemo and the other European delegates
Went through this process for every
Every you lie every little decision
We asked him what to tell us of finish
Mika on Bitterroot this down here
And in English
If it's a joke says that while these are common with the mouse and elephant
What is common Mouse and elephant
Daniel screwdriver
Not true
That's absolutely true
Can you know if we got
I still don't get it
All the differences in language barriers, says the EU have this goal
This idea
They wanted to create a union
That looks a lot like the United States
It's flattering to think that the Europeans wanted
To be more like us
But actually
Hold your roll
It's more that the EU we're up against the same challenges that the u.s. Founding Fathers rap again
Almost like in Philadelphia Convention of course the President says his cholesterol supposed to be George Washington
Who are you who are you I was one of the members of the collection
I'm coming from small country Finland you must understand convention so we must
Be humble
At the time the US Constitution was written 13 colonies the different states were all basically operating like
Little country
Fight with each other over land New York New Hampshire
Dover Vermont
Anyone even Tech stuff coming in from other states they actually imposed
Tariffs against
And the cultures were really different
Pennsylvania was mostly Quakers Maryland was almost all Catholics
Georgia was still really wild
Even language
Accents for really strong in the different colonies in Austin people from one state
Could not understand what people from another state
We're saying
We actually got our hands on some early recordings from the US that showed
Case the different accents of deserve more than a hundred years old so the
Recording quality is real
Really bad but if you listen really carefully you can hear how strong the accents are at the First Recording is a man from Massachusetts
And it's hard to hear him but he is talking about being a soldier and getting ammunition and being out in the cold
See if you can understand recess
Norwegian region
I have no idea what you just said
And there's another recording this is a woman from Virginia and she's talking about
Donuts vs. crawlers I think
Call
Could you make crab cakes
It was also hard for people from one state to do business with
State is each state had its own
Currency
Sterling in Rhode Island
Handmade certificate
David a Stewart is the author of The Summer of
He said a lot of times you couldn't use currency from one state
In another state
If you traveled
You could stop it and then and
Offering them
Pennsylvania pound sterling in the guy says no I don't take those
Or
He might have said while I'll take him but I'll only get a 40% discount
This is what the founders were up again
When they were trying to create the United States
They did have a loose central government
But nobody took it seriously
A lot of the states wouldn't bother showing up to the meeting
And this little Union couldn't get anything done
It couldn't even manage to get a federal tax
In order to approve a tax you needed a unanimous vote
But they never got it yunnan
Because there's always somebody does
Swan taxes
No money
But I had no money they would date ask the states
To give them up
That just sort of for donations
Public radio public radio fundraising
It was it was although the entertainment wasn't as good
Maybe they should have tried giving out death
You cannot go wrong with a tote bag
David said there was so much infighting among the states that George Washington said the states world
Pulling against each other
And it would quote
Soon bring ruin to the whole
But a lot of people thought that would be okay
Remember they had just fought a war against the British
The idea of creating a strong central government was frightening
But statesmanlike Alexander Hamilton and James Madison.
The only way for the country to survive and be a real presence in the world was to unify
So they said a meeting for all the state delegates
In 1787
Write a Constitution of the United States
We now know this as the Philadelphia
And it took place in Independence Hall
Which at that time was the State House
They
The whole summer with
Basically with each other
6 days a week
They were in that room
Every kind of smells guide
No weld you touch on us
Important point
They thought it was very important that they meet in secret
No one know what they were
Arguing about
Cuz I thought it would undermine their credibility when they finally reached it
They closed the doors and keep the windows shut
Which in July in Philadelphia
Is Kylie hot
The smaller states were worried that their voices were
Booty lost in this new year
The larger states did not want to give up
CorePower Zuni and there was a compromise
That is how we ended up with the two different houses
Congress
And the Electoral College was also part of this comp
It keeps smaller States a bigger voice in
In the presidential
And 200 years later
Europe is talking about the same things when the EU was forming
Chemical human are European Founding Father debated these kinds of issues
Flying back and forth
From Finland to Brussels
Tackling issue after issue for
4 years
You should live a very very very intensive the days
Very long days
Everything was up for debate and
Everything was a battle
What should the European Anthem be what
Flag look like
Should we have an army should be
We have a central bank
What should we put on the Euro the new currency we have
That one was a huge fight
Irwin Stelzer a columnist in
Economist
Told us all about it
There is no
Any
Image on any of the paper identifiable with any country
So what did they put on there
Well you know if you have a couple of
What look like buildings you have
Couple of birds
I understand this was a huge
Huge brawl
Over each image on the euro currency
There was also a huge fight over where the parliament should be
I couldn't settle on anyone please so the EU Parliament sits for part of the year in Brussels
And part of the year in straws
Which is a city in France right on the border
Germany
And they move the entire Parliament Lock Stock & Barrel
And even after all of those debates on
On all of those issues
A lot of countries were still
And so in the last treaty that made up that use constitute
National laws
The added article
An exit
Okay so if you kind of think about the European Union as a kind of marriage of all these
Countries
Then having this excerpt causes almost like having
A prenup right there
Having divorce option
You everywhere
We are not Catholic in the way that he said you must be my new married once you up today live
We are Protestant more so if you have the D
Divorce options
Chemosis article 50 was really essential in creating this new Union
He says when delegates from other countries
Come to him worried that the EU was going to look like the US with
Really strong centralized government
Where their country would lose its identity
No no no that's that's not us this is not that us
We have an exit clause
You can leave anytime you want
You always saying that the upgrade United States of Europe
Nobody ever created
Station exit closed
You see it there's an exit clause
You see it
And Camo says there were a lot of skeptical country
The UK was a big one they never adopted the Euro never put a ring on it
Nope
It was a very different situation from what happened in this country at the Philadelphia
Our Union was created to be a different kind of you
And it's evident from the very first line in our constitution
Does US historian David Oster
Archives
Institution. Start out saying We the People
David says
We the People meant the union answered to the
The people not the states
Patrick Henry want to get close to Constitution
Actually
Is first speech started out
How dare they say we the people in the opening of The Constitution
That's an outrage
It should say we the states
The eu's Constitutional documents do not start out with weave
NCC
Here it is
His majesty the king of the belgians
The president of the Czech
Republic
Her Majesty the
Denmark
The president the Federal
Germany the president of
The federal public westonia the president of the Hellenic Republic
His majesty the king of Spain and it just goes on like that for a peach
Basically listing out all the leaders of all the countries
The existence of an exit clause comes down to
To where the final power lies
With the union or with the individual parts
Europe chose individual parts
Weetos the Union
We have no exit
And we paid a big price for that
When a group of 11 Southern States tried to secede from the Union in 1860
Abraham Lincoln said
You can't do that
President Lincoln very much had the view
What you articulated
That the
Union was indissoluble
That no state could leave the union and that no state actually did leave the union
But even those Southern States
What they do
They've been terribly mistake
So
It
Is
At some level of
Almost metaphysical
Dirty theoretical questions
70 years after the United States was founded
It fought a civil
And chemo kill human are delegate from Finland
Does the European Union
Took a lesson
Finesse
Make the union volunteer
If a country really wants to leave
It should have that right
To be honest
I never would imagine that any country of America state of Europe a unit live with you
Then the financial crisis happen
They were bank bailouts austerity measure
A Syrian refugee crisis
NAU case
This Union isn't working for us anymore
Chemo says when he heard the news about brexit
Was devastated
He didn't even believe it at first
Still he says
He does see it as Prague
Listen to war
Usually this type of
Fundamental
Brakes
Results of War
Kitchen might leave European Union without War
That's a positive
Camo says if you have to do it all over again
He would still put in article V
So you don't regret article
Something new
I don't regret
But this civilized exit might spell the end of the EU
And that's where we are now
Next year Theresa May the prime minister of the UK is expected to trigger artic
Britain and the EU will start hammering out the terms of
Irwin Stelzer The Economist
Says if this happens
The EU is going to need to make this
Hurt as a signal to other Restless countries who might
The exit
That leaving this Union is a bad idea
The EU has to try to include a punishment Factor
In the negotiation something that makes it clear to other countries
That Britain is paying through the nose
Before leaving
That's going to make litigation very very
Who needs to be like article 50 with a bullet
Well
You you have strong a words that night
Bullet is what we did here in the US and Europe leaving the union looks more like a woman standing alone in the middle
Of a crowded room while everyone talks and shakes hands and laughs in the background
We always like to hear what you think sent us an email Planet Money at M
Npr.org or Midas on Facebook or Twitter to these episode was produced by Nick. Thank you Nick
We would also like to thank Harvey Todd from the Library of Congress for those early American recording
Podcast pop culture happy hour they have a Roundup of all the best podcast from 2016 Soca
Npr.org podcast or on NPR one I'm Stacey Vanek Smith and
I'm just saying thanks for listening
18 years 18 years she got one of your kids got you for 18 years
Sorry I'm never going to get that out my head
When she leave
Going to leave with half
Okay
It's something that you need to have
Did Kanye have a prenup