Support for this in
NPR podcasts
The following message come from The UPS Store
Offering services from shredding
To printing to mailbox
And instead of closing this Memorial Day we
May 24th and 25th
The UPS Store
He's doing another thing
All together
Opening
The UPS Store
Everything for small business
And of course shipping
Hey it's Jacob Goldstein Today Show is a rerun
It was first reported by Caitlin Kenney and David kestenbaum back in 2014
Redis
When you go to website and you type in
Whatever amazon.com facebook.com Jose
Pizza.com
Did you ever wonder how we ended up with. Cam is the ending
It turned out you have to go back to the earliest days of the year
I tracked down one of the founders
Is it right you were present when the internet was created
Yeah
But
Livy try to be careful about this
This is Steve Crocker it turns out like all things internet the creation of the internet itself was a
Collaboration
Cracker was a grad student in the 1960
These and back in those days every computer
Was separate
But there was this idea
What if you could string wires between each one and work out some way for them to communicate
Then they could send stuff back in
The project that Cracker worked on was called the arpanet
They managed to hook up for computers at different universities
You're sitting at 1 and he wanted to communicate with another
It was really very barebone
You didn't type a name for that
You have to just use a number
UCLA was one
That's where I was to
UCSB Santa Barbara was three and Utah was for and I'm being absolutely literal
Does he like connect to number one connect
The number to
Exactly so
Things quickly got more complicated more and more
Computers got added
Previous attempts have been to connect two or three computers together and by those standards this was enormous
How many computers
Well it started out with four and then quickly grew to 15 and then grew to 50
It is of course a pain to have to remember those numbers so someone writes
Few lines of computer code
Announce
You don't have to remember a mighty is
Sex
You just type MIT
So even computer people
Prefer to have letters
The numbers
Yes
Computer people really are just like everybody else there people
This it turns out was only a temporary fix
The number of computers connected
Grew to the hundreds and more
Someone needed to take charge to build a new naming system to bring order to the growing cast
And its historic task
Was given to
Paul mockapetris
Who
Just got to be
You know the only reason I got the job was nobody thought it was
Important until we tell him to
HD let's get him though.
This John
Call said there was this big debate going on
Some people wanted this internet thing organized by country other people say
Come on let's be more International
Let's group things by
Until the idea of ending web addresses with
A. And then a few letters
But remember at the time the internet was much smaller
And it was just seeing if this thing for governments and University
Again Steve Crocker
He had
Don't kneel for the military portion of the US government. Gov for the civilian side
Dot edu for universities and then
For those few commercials companies that happen to be part of it a little catch all called.com
Quartz down some major property
Dot-com was born
C o m
PetSmart commercial
Companies
I asked Paul mockapetris who actually came up
You know I've had about three sets of people asked me to testify to the fact that they did it and I don't
Don't really know
Caitlin you I was expecting something to say I just wrote it down on a napkin
Yeah it's funny to me though cuz I actually never thought that it stood for anything
I've just been so used to typing.com my whole life
Actually never thought about what.com
For reason it's crazy that it is at
This little Quirk it ended up having really big consequences for the internet because think about it
Everybody wants
The good names
The.com name
Like
Imagine you have a business and it's called Jose p
Pizza
So the first person who gets on the internet gets Jose p
Pizza.com that's it they're good they have a nice
Trine website name
But then all the other Joe's pizzas out there all across the US
They have to add words and letters they have to become Big Joe's Pizza
Pizza.com
Joe's Pizza on 7th. Com Happy Joes.
Tomato Joe's Pizza. Com
You went out Joe's Pizza of the village.
Is that one's easy to remember so for the people who were not first or not
Some of them
Have had to pay big money
People who got
Simple web
Toys R Us Princeton bought toys.com for $5000000
S****** sold for 13
This is the reason you know the photo sharing websites liquor
It's actually spelled
Flickr
Because the guy who owned the domain
The flicker with the e.com
You wouldn't sell it to the people and they love to the name for their company
So their solution was
Drop the e
Sometimes you got to do that to find a little space
That hasn't been taken
There are currently over a hundred million website sanding and.
Which is one reason
Right now
As I speak
Big changes are afoot
New options for website names not only is there. Calm and. Gov
Now
Ninja
Has been added ISO. Bike. Plumbing. Cool
In all over a thousand new domains they're called
There can be at it
It's like a whole new pieces of Internet real estate of
Everyone who dreamed of getting a short easy name on the Internet
Now they can grab one
And it is very much the wild wild
Their settlers
And a new land baron
Parents with Big Dreams hoping to strike it
Hello and welcome to find a honey I'm David kestenbaum of the new internet real estate
Meet the dreamers
And skeptic
Who thinks more land
May not be better
We'd like to say a quick thank you and share a message from our planet money sponsor betterment
Betterment has fundamentally changed the way Americans save and invest for their future
Traditional investing Solutions are expensive complicated
Boring
The betterment was built from the ground up
With sophisticated cutting-edge technology
It recommends a personalized investment plan
Simply put
Betterment makes it easier
More straightforward and less expensive to invest
For more information and up to six months free
Visit betterment.com Planet Money
This world of online web addresses the rules for it are set by a
A nonprofit group
You called I can
What stands for internet Corporation
Signed name
What a boring sound is his nonprofit group it supposed to be like an impartial caretaker
And after a long many year process of discussing pros and cons and Pros in after open forum
Arms in position papers and listening to
Everything anyone has
Had to say
They decided
It was time for noon
Those last letters that you type on a web address
Dot-com that's called a top-level domain
And basically they're going to allow all kinds of new top-level
If you're I can this is a kind of hard thing to explain to the public
Their best effort is this little
Cartoon called
The dot has friends
Starting with little animated
Miley.
Is flying around it
Rocket ship
The diet is making new friends
More than 1300 of them and they're going to change the internet like never before
Madden classic internet fashion anybody wanted to get one of these new top-level domains one of the new pieces of Real Estate
They can apply
And try to develop it
YouTube I say. Menu for example
And try to sell it to restaurant
She wanted websites ending in. Menu
Think of it Joe's Pizza. Menu Kaitlyn's Cafe. Menu
Think of it as an internet Island just for restaurants and their menus
Or instead of that menu you could apply for
You know. Cat
Whatever you want
When Adrian McAdory heard about this she thought I am definitely apply
But I'm couple years ago she was working
The Pentagon
Choose a contractor doing
Nike work and I read on the internet that the internet was expanding you actually like at work at the Pentagon
Thinking about the oh yeah in the basement
Fender Bassman in the basement of his basement Pentagon in the dungeon with the where the rest of us peons work
But then she had this question
Which domain
Should I apply for
I was thinking about lifestyle let you know where do something with lifestyle and so then you know my girlfriends and I just having sex in Converse
Can I get a boba
That's it she thought weddings
. wedi
Wet people can put all their wedding pages
Adrian Martin. Wagner
John. Wed John and John. Webb
People would pay for those kinds of sites
So she applied
Sending a really long
An application there is
$185,000 fee
Choose some
Retirement money
And her dad helped out
And finally. Wed was her
The thing about owning one of these domains is that once you get it you're like the mayor
You can set the rules
And one of Adrian's rules
Is listen sweetie I know you love your spouse but you can't hold on to that wedding webpage forever
This she says will be enforced in the following way
Price to own a. Website for the first year 70 bucks
Second gear
70 box
30 year
$30,000
That is because we want you to
Move on into the sunset and live happily ever after
And let the next Mary and John have that fight
She figures if 6000 couples in Love by websites
She'll break you
Nothing about setting your own rules that's part of the appeal of these new domain
New York for instance has. NYC
So we can require that all businesses
Want to use that
Have to actually be in New York
If you buy. Kids
You can pledge to make it totally Kids Safe material
A lot of the New Deal made the targeting very
But a couple people are thinking
I mean really why restrict yourself to
You can try to become the next
The next all purpose in
Thing you can stick on the back of any business
After all, is pretty crowded
All of the good real estate has taken the only thing that's left is something with a dash in
Or maybe three dashes and a couple numbers in it
This is Daniel McGarry he's 28 years old
As far as he knows the youngest person to be granted one of the new domain
Is Mom and some fraternity Brothers at helping him out
His Contender to take on.com is
Dot X
YZ
The way I looked at it was we on the alphabet was XYZ was
Domain names
The same way
XYZ Universal yet
Abstract
And catchy
Try and forget it I dare you
XY
Ax
You're right
XYZ it's it just sticks is it it's natural that really makes sense
About QRS
Doesn't make sense to me
The only one ending to the alphabet and there should only be one ending to a domain name
Good job working at indigo
And he tells me if I want my own personal slice
David. XYZ
Still available
And if you think of it like a land rush
Daniel and Adrian with that wed they're kind of like Pioneers with
Covered wagon
Finding a little plot of land
Hoping to start a town
And convince people to move there
They're standing there saying come live here it's awesome
It'll be so easy for friends and
Customers to come and visit
Are individuals
Taking a chance
But they're up against some very big developers who are buying up huge swath
Daniel Schindler has been the internet named business for a long time and some other folks
Raise what he told me was
Significantly over 100 million dollars
To fire a whole list
The clever internet
That wine. Cool. Coffee
307 with a number of new demands we applied for
It's a lot we were the largest applicant
In the world by a factor of 3 Google was there
Second largest applicant 101
I asked him do we really need all this new real estate I mean how often do people really even type in web addresses by hand
Why do people get where they're going using a search engine or following a link on some
How do we feel type in www. Blah blah
Every minute of every day across the world
That that's why memorable names are more valuable
You know when you dry pasta a billboard or you see a van which is go to sign written no domain name on the side
Side of it
Think yourself how much easier it is to remember if it's a short meaningful specific name
Then along a convoluted Wanda by the time you gone by you can't remember
So this is the happy vision for the future of the internet
Cleaner more spacious better organize plays
And I could see it happening I could see 10 years from now looking back and saying
Remember when everything was. Com
I was so weird
Shimmer says all this new real estate he thinks it's going to be a good thing
But there are people out there who think more real estate isn't better
Remember there are a lot of people a lot of companies doing just fine with their. Com
And for them
All of this new territory can be a threat
Another thing they have to worry about
If your Toys R Us and you just spent $5000000 on toys.com
Now you look around and you see theirs
Toys. Cool toys
Kid help toys. Toys
What are you do try to buy them all
Thomas bracky saw this anxiety first and he's an intellectual property attorney who did some work with
Organization called
Lipo
The world in
Show property
Young that with a lot of lawyers for big cup
All of the folks I was there with were brand people general counsel's for brands
They actually thought it was the worst
Because I already spent
You don't deal with the dollars patrolling in policing., protecting their brand the idea that the internet was going to expand
It was an ass
They had I can Representatives come and speak
To the folks at life Ellen I thought
The symbol
Lawyer for going to throw fruit
I mean they they hated the idea
Part of the reason they got freaked out is that we had some
Experience with this
Background mm we added about a dozen new top-level domains
Including. Biz
And things did not go well
Ben Edelman is a professor at Harvard
He looked at what happened to. Biz
Its first year
He said the people who bought a website sending and up is
Didn't really do much
That is ended up being a home for speculators
People buying up property to prevent their competition from getting it
It look like
Half of the domains in diabetes that have been sold
We're actually demanded it been sold to
People who wanted to make sure no one else claims them
And then of the remaining half most of them weren't in you seen as a ratio of. Biz domains
They were actually being used
2.
Biz domains that work
Either being held
For future use or being held to prevent other people to use them
But something like 1 to 10 1 to 20
Unsavory ratio look like most of the people were buying this not because they wanted it
Because they needed to make sure that they were protect
The hope is that this time things will be
There are new Protections in place for
For trademark
Brand names
Not so it's 10 years later
Through a lot more people on
So maybe people are finally dying to bust out of
Of course it's hard to predict what's going to happen today
These new demands
It's always possible you've got a nice piece of real estate and still nobody wants to move there
When us settlers headed west
People picked out land that is still just
Tumbleweeds
Then of course there's Phoenix Arizona
Lots of people want to live there
Tom bracky the intellectual property lawyer who
By the way
Buying. Menu in a few others
Just friends
Do bigger things will change
Butt.com that weird ending dreamed up in the early days of the internet
Going to stick around
Dotcom bubble
Is it going to go away
It's it's
It's it's full it's crowded but it's also very vital
And if you don't answer
You know
The Wild West
And we hope eventually people will will build on them
It's still early days in the Wild West
Adrian McAdory says it's been a very slow start for. Wed
And she's got competition
Somebody else bought
That wedding
But Adrian says
Bring it
Other domains like. Guru that is
One of the 307 that Danielson learned
Applied for
They seem to be attracting new settlers at
When websites on. Guru became available
50000 people
That was David kestenbaum and Caitlin Kenney this is Jacob Goldstein I'm here back in the present back in 2000
And to close today show we wanted to check in with some of those domains that were just getting started back when we first reported
We reached out to Adrian McAdory
Other Woman Behind. Wed here's what she told
Well all I can say is
I am glad I didn't think
My Willy Wonka golden ticket because it certainly has not been
You know from the bottom line perspective that I haven't made
Pretty eyes
She said she hasn't given up
She still puts in a few hours a week on. Wed
But as of right now there are only about a hundred and fifty website
Registered at
We also got in touch with Daniel nogari owner of.
XYZ
That we last talked to him in 2004
6 million domains that are currently righteous
Just heard where the number for generic top-level domain
In the world
Behind Cam Newton
Work
One big moment for Daniel came last summer when alphabet the parent company of Google
Made it home page ABC. XYZ
One Last Detail after our original Planet Money episode aired couple years ago
Nigari got sued by verisign
They are the company that owns. Com
Hi this is
First thing that I'm the next.com
And apparently didn't like that
Nicaraguan that chase about verisign is a
Today Show was originally produced by Jess Jiang the rerun was produced by Elizabeth
Coolest with help from Mark
Brandl
Thanks also to Matthew zook for his help with those domain
I'm Jacob Goldstein