Hey just a warning Baker sometimes use adult language and in this podcast
Video
Recently the
3rd
Largest bank
In the country
Wells Fargo got into trouble
Furious
Trouble a federal investigation show
That Wells Fargo was secretly opening
Bank accounts
People's names without
Their permission
Checking account
Credit cards loan
Right and not just a couple
We're talkin about up to
2 million of these
This is come out now and this is blown up into
Giants
Banking scam
Maybe saw this on the news Wells Fargo payday
Huge fine fired a bunch of low-level employees
But that wasn't enough
US Senate demanded
The bank CEO John Stumpf
Appear on Capitol Hill
Senator Elizabeth Warren
Had a few thoughts
She haven't resigned
You haven't returned to single nickel if your personal earning
Instead evidently your definition of accountable
Is to push the blame to your low-level employees who don't have the money for a fancy PR firm to defend
Michelle
It's gutless leadership
Stop sat quietly through this and when it was his turn to speak essentially what he said
With luck
There was some bad apples okay
But we fired the bad apples everything's cool now
And
Upper manager
Not guilty
We never directed
Nor wanted our team member to provide products and services to customers
That they did not want
The hearing was all over the news
And in San Francisco one of those low-level employees without a PR firm
Was watching her former boss
Ashley work for Wells Fargo for 5 years
And she
Could not believe
Use me up
B*******
Like this was such a sissy
Stomach
Thing that was taught its ass it's the sales culture
So that's just
SPS
And Ashley said you know what
I'm going to show the world
How to scam work
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Robert Smith I'm Chris Arnold and Robert today we are going inside
A Wells Fargo Bank
And not just any Wells Fargo
This is the branch
On the first floor of the Wells Fargo headquarters building in San Francisco
This is a place where a bunch of stressed-out young people were pushed
And pushed
Until they get some Very Bad Things
And while all that was going on the CEO John Stumpf
Working write-ups
Support for this podcast and the following message
Search come from OnePlus
Maker of the OnePlus
A smartphone conceived and built
Tekken
Hand in hand
With users
The OnePlus 3
Pinterest Dash charge
Innovative
Technology that sets a new Benchmark in
Charging slowly
A quick 30-minute charged with
Will replenish over 60% of your OnePlus
+ 3 battery
Allowing for 7 plus hour
HD video playback
And giving you a day's power in half an hour
Check it out at 1 plus.
I went to the Wells Fargo headquarters building Robert and it's a pretty plain Stone and glass skyscraper building right now
Downtown San Francisco
Pretty unremarkable though it's surrounded by
Taller building
For Ashley though
She came with me and said she remembers everything about
She was 23 patent finish college
Call Dad personal banker
So she dressed like she thought of personal Bankers address
Stiletto heels about a
Pounded hairspray and bobby pins in my hair
I felt
Proud and
Fortunate to be able to work for such a big company and really the sky was the ceiling
This was 2007
The beginning of the financial crisis and other bags were starting to panic
But not Wells Fargo
They were still growing they were still expanding
Wells Fargo position itself as the
Foxybae
You know the everyday friendly
Their plan was to get to the crisis by adding more customers
I taking it
More money into account
I could get more
How to get more money
They needed sale
That would be Ashley's jobs
Young
Long hair sparkly eyes
It would sit in the back lobby waiting for someone to come
Customer walks in and we'd have to go through the whole notion of standing up high mr. so-and-so what can I help you with
I'm looking to open a checking account
Great
Tell me about yourself
Part of the technique was to sell the grand history of Wells Fargo unit Wells Fargo wagons coming down the street
Stagecoach B 1800
In fact there is a giant antique Stagecoach
Parked right there in the lobby
Nextdoor Ashley
So Ashley worked with a lot of other young p
People send them had suits on for the first time they were very excited to
To be there
And we talked with a bunch of them one of them was Eric
And like Ashley he only wants to
Jesus first name
What he says they would do it they would leverage this wholesome reputation
To get people to sign up for
Does he know the reputation that we know that you were going into a safe place
Right this is where I go to
Park my money right this is where I go to
You know I'm get tools and instruments that will help me in my family advance
And succeed in life
The last thing that would be in the back your mind would be there at 8
Now every Bank
Tries to upsell
You've been there right
You have a checking account to say hey why not get a credit card
What is called cross-selling in NM to some degree make sense but Eric and Ashley say Wells Fargo took it to a whole nother level
And then we're just pushing another bank account but let's say okay
You should probably have a credit card and
Multiple savings accounts
Perhaps in and if you got kids going to college baby baby checking accounts and credit cards
Yeah how about a new line of credit
And a business line of credit
While we're at it
This was a corporate priority the more customers
The more accounts
The healthier the bank
The CEO John Stumpf
He worked upstairs
American Ashley in the headquarter
Get a slogan
Which was eight
Is great
As an everybody should have
Eat Wells Fargo
Accounts checker
King Savings credit cards another prop
And Ashley was expected to open a new account 8 new product every single day so this wasn't just some aspirin
There was a goal and her managers would push her all day long
It was how are you going to meet your goal if your numbers were
Not what they were by noon how are you going to fix it
100 calls a day call call call wework
Constantly on the
Song
Dial Dial Dial
8 new accounts a day
In January the race the gold
The 20 call the jump into January
You expected to call everyone you knew
Your friends
Your family
Cuz you'd be calling them like
Crap I got to get out of here I don't want to work Saturday let me please open you an account
Actually all the bankers we talked to said that Wells Fargo would burn through a lot of young
Workers this
Never get hired
Sell Wells Fargo products to
But everybody that they knew when they could call on the phone
And then they get pushed out when they didn't have anybody else to sell to
Ashley told us a story about how deadly
Sirius the managers were about these
Quotas
One day Ashley was working a few blocks away from headquarters that What's called the Crocker
Temperature
And
A bank robber
A bank robber and police show up outside and Ashley is telling us all about this
And whatever conversations on the phone
Cops were swarming to shut everything down
No public couldn't come in do you know your employee
You know you're watching all this and the guy jump
The counter
Crazy big Fiasco
They have the guy detained he like crapped his pants
Stinky akkineni State the heart attack it was
Don't even look at it
Dial for dollars
And Ashley is sitting at her desk
And her manager
Her district manager
Says do
Not
Leave your desk keep selling
Nope
You don't think you're walking out or going home early even though we're closed for the rest of the day style $4.
Dollars
How am I supposed to be on the phone with a client hold a conversation try to sell my checking account
Breaking a million cops in our lobby being loud and noisy
I mean it's not like
And he said where you and your co-workers dislike are you
Kidding me like
The guys like crap himself I mean it was like no
On the clock
You know course they're not going to be like okay everybody like let's have a discussion about what just happened
No no it was
What is a boiler room
Dial
$4
Yeah it just never stopped
Dial $4
And he was all of this pressure being put on Ashley and Eric
It was working
The bank was
Huge financial success
In 2009 you know some banks are still struggling from the financial
That's right
Wells Fargo announced
Record earnings
These guys were selling a lot
A product and around that time a profile and Fortune magazine called Wells Fargo a rare upbeat Tale
I meant the banking
Wreckage
The bank needed new money
Going so they added more
And Ashley says there were no excuses
Not a bank robbery
Not exhaustion when Ashley
Didn't meet her number
Two managers would show up at
They said come with us
So I walked with them followed the two of them
Through the large Bobby you know passed all my colleagues would not
You know it's like being called into the principal's office
Sit down at the large
Conference table no windows in this room they shut the door lock the door
Import neon formal warning and say
Here's your formal warning you have to sign this
You don't need your Solutions you will be fired and it's going to be on your
Permanent record
I mean it was real like you worse
Stopped in it was
The feeling that no other employer is going to watch you because we will
Ruined you
They were simply saying to Ashley
Play if you don't make it here at Wells Fargo
You're not going to get another job and pay
After one of these coaching
Sessions went back to her desk
Sat down but I got sick to my stomach
And I threw up under my desk like it really made me feel
Physically sick
You know what
I heard similar stories
Four other employees the stress
Crying
Not just an Ashley
Bankruptcy that is the sales person being pushed all over the country all over downtown Tampa
And it's not like his employees were getting rich
Ashley said she made around $35,000 a year
It's striking that she and her colleagues were
Pretty young I mean he's reserved their first corporate job
When we talked to Eric he said
The Pressure lyrics
Actually it was just
Triplet II Jesse was he was everyday man
I mean if it was literally every day
And it was I
A Grindhouse
The goals just seemed impossible
The pressure was overwhelming but
There actually was a way out
Employees cheat
The cheetah
They figured out ways to make new accounts appear out of thin air
And always
Seems to happen in the Scandal and we saw this in the mortgage crisis to write
You give someone a number
You say meet it no matter what
And they start figuring out ways
To pick shortcut
Fudge that number
And at Wellsburg Woodforest this stuff you could argue was pretty minor so up customer would come in they have any best
Sega CD
Certificate of deposit it was $10,000
So the bank employee could split that up into 10 different accounts with $1,000 in each
What account becomes 10
It's like magic
And then you meet your daily goal
It was another trick there you could just slip extra accounts
Into the paperwork
Say someone want a home equity loan
You can add a personal line of credit
Into the stack of papers they were signing and just take
Got a new account
Customer never even notice
Now the problem there was that was starting to get a little more serious because you give someone a personal line of credit for $25,000
That will affect your credit
Ashley remembers one day when a man comes into the bank
Use elderly he had Cain
He's on his own
The tolerance sent him over to me the first day I met on
Because he was overdraft and he couldn't understand why he was negative and he was saying
All I want is to buy a newspaper why can't I buy my newspaper
Ashley post office account on a computer
And she notices something really strange
This man was living off of Social Security
He got around $1,100
A month
And yet
Ohia
Crude I think over
$200 in overdraft and when I looked at is a
The accounts he had six different accounts
He had no understanding of accounts he had he just said oldest nice lady
I explained to me that I needed this new account package
Like it wasn't an option for him
High salt
So terrible for this man
Actually waved all the fees that the system would let her way for this guy
But then she did something even more shoot she went into her own checking account
How to money out and put it into the old man's account
Just getting back to zero
So you could like buy is newspaper in and not get any more overtime
Ashley said she tried
To report the employee
Wood sign this man up for so many accounts
But her managers
Didn't do anything
Later she would start to call the company's ethics line
Again
And again
But nothing
And you got to ask how far up
Did this guy did the executives know what their employees were doing to me please
I mean Wells Fargo with Bragg to top investors of the CEO would say an investor calls eight is great
I mean this is being heralded from the rooftop
And remember
Ashley and Eric are working in the lobby of the corporate headquarters actually says Wells Fargo bigwigs wood
Walked by her death
She would hold the door open sometimes and guess would come through
The CEO
John stop
Oh yeah I saw his car is always parked in the alley right behind my jaw
These people are fixtures and work directly upstairs and then
There was a
Because you can't just keep giving people accounts that they don't want
Forever Without
Is starting to come back on you to send degree right so customers were noticing the extra cat
A few lawsuits were filed because all these customers working
Complaining
But for a longtime customers were told look at the simple mistake
Any accounts were closed
It seems like no one was seeing the big picture
This game started to unravel in 2013
LA Times Reporter published a story about some of the intense
Sales pressure
People like Ashley were feeling at Wells Fargo
So after that
Regulator Surgical
Consumer Financial
Protection Bureau is investigating along with the LA City attorney's office
Last month
The cfpb hit Wells Fargo with the biggest
Penalties ever issued against any financial institution in
History
It estimated that might have been more than 2 million unwanted accounts we found up 5000 Wells Fargo employees were
You're fired
This whole thing blew up giant mess Giants game
But we should say that the fines total about a hundred and eighty-five
Million-dollar pretty small in the big scheme of banking
There is still an investigation about who knew what
And when do they know it
We contacted Wells Fargo to ask about all this and we show them with Ashley and Eric and others it said
Add Wells Fargo spokesman Oscar suris
Redis repaired
Although the vast majority of our team members do the right thing everyday on behalf of our customers
These allegations and accusations are very serious
And if any of these things transpired it's distressing and it's not who Wells Fargo is
Are bored and announced last week that it will lead an internal investigation
Into retail banking sales practices
And related matters
Ashley and Eric both left Wells Fargo
Before all of this
Eric quit his job after the
The pressure just started to get
Too much RAM to deal with
He was getting stomach problem
Xyzzy set worth
Yeah it was a good just got to a point where you know
It was just like I can't I just can't handle this man
As far as Ashley
She started to refuse to meet
Her quota she was just saying like I can't ethically do this she was
Calling the Wells Fargo Ethics Line trying to explain his butt
Eventually Wells Fargo fire
Ashley tried to get another job in banking
But she found she never made it very far past the initial interview
She suspected that Wells Fargo had put some sort of black mark on her record
Somewhere
And it turns out that is
Exactly the
Wells Fargo wasn't joking around when they said they would make it
Hard for her to find working
Wells Fargo wrote her up
On what's called a u5 document it's like a report card for Banker
Basically
We tracked it down and we asked Ashley to read what it says
Failure
To perform job duties
Any Bank
But Ashley applies to
Will see this line
Failed to do job.
The form does not mention
Fado's job duties
Where the sales go
But everyone we spoke to
They were unrealistic and that are at the center
Of a series of ongoing investigation
Is it the state
And federal level
It just has failed to do job duties
It was the first time Ashley had seen it in
It's like having a black
Cloud that
Carnival looming behind you and I'm always trying to get
In front of the cloud out of the
Cloud into the sunshine but it's always
There
But at least now with the investigation maybe people can start to see through that black cloud
And see what Wells Fargo did
We always love to hear what you think of the show you should email is Planet Money at npr.org or you can
Tweetus at Planet Money episode today was produced by Elizabeth special thanks to Neil Carruth and
Alex goldmark our senior producer here Planet Money
Who's awake
Danbury this weekend
Mazel Tov Alex
And now you're finished listening to Planet Money we have a special podcast event to tell you about everyone here in the US Noah's Ark
Course II
Presidential debate is Sunday October 9th
The very next morning the NPR politics podcast will have everything you need to know
About that debate you can subscribe to listen to NPR politics
On the NPR one app
I'm Chris Arnold
I'm Robert Smith
Thanks for listening