This message comes from NPR sponsors snowfall
The only data warehouse
Built for the cloud
Unlock deep data in
Insights with the instantly scalable
Cloudbuilt data warehouse
Start your journey towards data-driven decision
It's snowflake. Com NPR
Hey it's Jacob Goldstein quick note
Today's Show originally ran in May of 2005
What are the kid
Apples
Wer
They were called red delicious
And they were red
They were not delish
They look beautiful but then you bite into it
And almost always it would be mushy and merely just
That's it was a really bad time to be an apple eater
It was also a really bad time to be an apple grower
Everybody
Really the spot little everybody was growing red delicious
This is Dennis courtier he's the owner of
Pepin Heights Orchard in Lake City Minnesota
We were probably going broke
You know we were being asked to deliver goods for below the cost of production
Of course you're trying to raise his prices some other farmer who was growing the exact same red delicious apples would say to
The buyers hate I'll sell them to you for Less
Because
Red delicious apples were this ubiquitous interchangeable thing
They were commodities
And making commodities
Whether it's
Cheap socks or metal screws or red delicious apples
Is a terrible business to be in
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Jacob bolts
I'm down Charles I cover food and farming for NPR
Today on the show how we got from melee nasty apples
The apples you actually want to eat apples that tastes delish
Yet there was a guy who discovered a delicious Miracle Apple butt
Discovering that Apple was not enough
Support for Planet Money and the following message come from Goldman Sachs
Get insights from some of the world's leading thinkers
Saint markets Industries and the global economy on the firm's podcast
Exchanges
Goldman Sachs
You hear discussions on topics with far-reaching implications
Climate change autonomous driving the future of China's economic growth
Plus much more
That's exchanges at Goldman Sachs available on iTunes Stitcher SoundCloud
Google Play
Gs.com podcast
The guy who discovered the miracle Apple that one apple is name is David
When he was growing up you loved
Fruit but he hated Apple
Cuz all we ever knew were red delicious
But then he went off to college and one day for the first time in his life
He tasted a really good
Someone brought a bushel of yellow apples down from Michigan
Can they were fresh and they weren't really they didn't have a tough naugahyde like skin
They were crisp and juicy and I was amazed
So David Bedford thinks to himself
Why not make more amazing apples why not have amazing apples in the grocery store
He becomes an apple breeder devote his professional life to creating those
Delicious app
But this is a tough
Things to devote your life to
Inventing a better Apple is really hard
For one thing
You want a new Apple
Going to take a long time
You know you find a couple of promising apples you cross breed them to collect The Offspring you get the seeds
You put them in the ground and then
You got to wait you got to wait for an apple tree to grow up out of the ground it's takes 5 years or more
Finally the tree grows up starts producing apples you pick one you taste it
And it sucks
That's actually what happened 99.99%
I went to visit David Bedford at his trial Orchard at the University of Minnesota and he walked me out to the orchard
And I see rows and rows of little apple trees
Up the hillside ZIP down the hillside
He'd like them all to be great
But he knows they won't
If you look around you here
What we see around us here is probably five to six thousand trees that's not even enough really
Wait to have one that will be a winner
You're a you're a you're a tough judge of apple tree
Well
You know we've got a lot of responsibility here we're trying to save the world from mediocre apples and we can't
Let her guard down
And there's only one way the David Bedford can tell whether a tree is
Great mediocre worth keeping
He doesn't have a chemical test
He can't
Tell just by looking at them he has to walk the rose tree by tree
Taking an apple from each one
How many apples do you bite into it a day when you're going through Alexa
An average day at the peak of the Season would probably be five to six hundred
Is sooner or later somebody has to eat
That's the ultimate determination is the mouth and the
And the tongue in the brain
And so you have to take a bite
And you have to decide
There is a trick to tasting 500.
Bedford biting the Apple
Choose for a few seconds
End
This is
The creek doesn't swell
No great effort expended he just open the mouth and
Drop it on the ground drop it on the ground yeah
I don't even
Spit it out you just kind of
Electric Fallout like a like a two-year-old who suddenly decide take I don't want to eat this thing that's in my mouth
This trick this technique this is how he found the miracle app
It was years ago back in the early 1980s
David Bedford is walking down the trees
One by one
Bite
Spit
Eddie comes to this one tree
Tree number 17
He picks an apple
He takes a bite
There was this moment of
Confusion maybe my goodness what is this this is not
Is a red delicious texture this is not even a good apple texture this is something Beyond
The two things that came to my mind number one was watermelon
The way the watermelon woken up
Break in your mouth and then did you squeeze out of it
And the other thing was Asian pears
Is that real
Christmas of an Asian pear
But I'd sorted that out enough to say I don't know what this is but it's good
You don't know me I like it it was sweet
It was Chris
Tell they called it Honeycrisp
And Honeycrisp would eventually change the Applebee's
But it took a long time for that
Because think about this moment
David Bedford have a new app
Something different maybe better than all the apples in the store
He tells Apple Growers about this new
The Apple that's so much better than the Miele red delicious and everyone's eating
He says I got it I got it try this
Honeygrow hours
They don't want they would bedford's amazing.
They don't want it because the grocery store
Becton the produce section was still pretty boring you know you went in you wanted lettuce
There's iceberg
That's it
You want tail
It's okay
You want apples
I remember a produce market or telling me when I first got into the business he says why are you
You guys trying to make more apples we don't need that
He said we have a red one
We have a yellow one and we have a green one that's all we need
This is a classic problem for an inventor you come up with something new something in
Credible
But nobody really wants it nobody even knows about
Bedford probably needed a marketing team a big advertising
Vanquish he didn't have any
Was this one guy
That guy was Dennis courtier
Torture is the Apple grower from the beginning of the show was getting killed trying to grow red delicious
Could you to come by bedford's orchard every so often they say hey
You know you have anything good
You have anything different
One-time courtier came by and Bedford took him to 31711 Bedford took him to that honey
I said here
One of these
Courtier took a bite and thought
These could be the apples I've been waiting
They were that
Damn good and that damn difference
Porter makes a big bet
I start planning a lots of Honeycrisp
You don't know if it's going to work
Doesn't know if people are going to want these apples
But if they do so you can finally start making a decent profit because instead of growing the same Apple does everybody else
He'll be the only guy growing Honeycrisp
At least for awhile
He has a head start on every other Apple
Of course this being the Apple business he's going to have to wait a long time to figure out whether his bet will pay off
Lance the trees he waits for him to grow up they get bigger
And finally by the time the trees are starting to produce apples the supermarkets are
Ready for
They have gone beyond red delicious finally there are other apples that are starting to show up on the show
And when the Honeycrisp finally get to the store
They do great
We have retailers telling us
And it is still true
Honeycrisp
Elevated apples to a different level within their grocery stores the point that Honeycrisp has in many cases the
Dollar grossing
Not just Apple
They were the
Top grossing item in the whole store
You're not every week not every store not every part of the season
But when the air is at their Peak we have retailers who sell more dollars worth of are Honeycrisp every week
Then they sell 2 liter bottles
Coca-Cola
That changes things
Grocery stores are dying to get
Courtiers
He's finally selling his apples at apra
Doing great making money
But before long he sees other people planting Honeycrisp
And he knows that pretty soon there will be tons of farmers competing against into sell honey
He'll be back in that red delicious world where you can't make a profit
Honeycrisp will just be this delicious commodity
Courtier realized
And this was really the final step in this story
That she needed to do more than find a delicious app
He needed to figure out a way to keep that delicious apple to himself and
Maybe just a few selected other farmer
I remember
Pacific discussion
And which a number of us
What if what if
If we did this what if we did that
What if when we find the next great Apple
A small group of us could control the supply of it
Make sure we grow enough
To keep the supermarket happy not too many so the price doesn't crash make sure the apples handled well so that still good
So Shoppers still want to buy it and you might be able to do this with a patent right you can patent an apple in fact
Bedford and the University of Minnesota had patented the honey
But they let anybody who wanted to plant it Farmers just had to pay a small royalty
Anyway more importantly
A patent lasts for 20 years which in a business where it takes
5 years or more just a grow a tree is not that long
By the time Honeycrisp was really taken off its patent was expiring
Dan courtier at his friends looked around and they saw something interest
Clever Australian company gone beyond patents
They had gotten a trademark
On the name
Pink lady
Further app
That's pink lady with a little TM
Betrayed
Unlike a Patent Trademark never expire
You give an apple a name
You trademark that name
And then you get to decide forever who gets to grow and who gets to sell apples
Under that name
Cartoon his friends wanted to do that
But they needed a new app
About 10 years ago they found it they found it at that same Orchard run by David Bedford at the University of Minnesota
And quarter of this time
He talked to Bedford and the university into
Trademarking that apple
They call it
Sweet Tango
Just one key
Swe
Tianjin
TM
Only 45 farmers are allowed to grow it
We have just shy of a million trees in the ground
And it's going quite well
The great Apple
Grow more and sell more of them every year
Panda
We're trying to figure out how quickly we can wrap it up
If you are an apple grower and you are not part of the sweet Tango growing club
Well go find another club there are a lot of so-called Club apples now being grown arriving in the grocery store
Each one has a name more ridiculous
Then the last
What's new with you
Envy
Cosmic crisp
Jazz
Was kanzi Lady Alice
Pacific Rose pinata Ruby Frost
Snapdragon
Exactly
Exactly and that is not even the end of the
When one little detail it's
Only the name that's trademarked so even if you're not in the club you can roll the Apple you just can't use the name
Pro tip
If you see pink lady and
Cripps pink in the same store
Just buy whichever one's cheaper
Because they're the same Apple
All these apples with their ridiculous names are
Brandt
Each apple is brand and
You could imagine a future where saying
Hey can you pick me up some apples
Sounds as ridiculous as saying
Hey can you pick me up a six-pack of cola
You don't think Cola
You say Coke
/ Pepsi
The brand is the thin
Tim Burns used to run the promotional campaign for the sweet Tango Apple
And he says apples now will be like every other item in the groceries
They will have their own Brands they will have their own marketing teams their own advertising blitzes
It is going to be a world of managed
Brands just like the soup aisle or the potato chip aisle
Or any other aisle this is what it's going to be going forward
There's something a little sad about
Even Apple
You know this
Basic
Natural thing
Are now in the world of Brands and advertising
And marketing
But all that is driving people to create and sell
Really good app
So if you really like apples
And you're willing to pay for a really great delicious new Apple you can now find
And you know what if you don't want to pay more
You can still get red delicious
Let us know what you thought of Today Show you can email us at Planet Money at npr.org or find us on Facebook or Twitter
Today Show was originally produced by Jess Jiang and Nia Wilson
The rerun today was produced by Raina Cohen
If you're looking for something else to listen to check out the NPR politics podcast
They have been cranking out shows like crazy to keep up with the presidential campaign
They will have another show out just after the final presidential debate next week
That you'll be out on Thursday October 20th
The NPR politics podcast
You can find it wherever you get your podcast on the NPR one app
I'm Jacob Goldstein thanks for listening