Hi Stacey Vanek Smith here today show is a rerun David kestenbaum reported for us back in 2004
14 it's about a country to try to make good on a whole lot of bad things that happened during the finance
Crisis
That place
Iceland
Here's the show
There's this idea that dates back at least a biblica
It is that there should be a moment when debts are
Call the Jubilee
Used to throw this money
Now you don't
Where the Bible describes at the Jubilee with a big
Is supposed to happen every 50 years or so
Apparently a trumpet
A Ram's Horn was blown
And they're Adidas release from debt
In Deuteronomy the Jubilee is described
Vesely
Every creditor that lendeth unto his neighbor shall release it
You shall not exactly does his neighbor or of his brother
Because it is called the Lord's release
Getting with that debt is something that can enslave you
And every so often.
Was best to just wipe
Did you believe not gotten a lot of traction in the modern
You may remember after the financial crisis summary
The Occupy Wall Street protesters
We're calling for a
Basically it ended
Today on the show we have a story about a country that is actually trying it
Trying a jubilee hello and welcome to planet
Money on David kestenbaum what happens when you just wipe debt clean
Money and the following message come from Goldman Sachs get insights from some of the world's leading thinkers on markets and destroy
And the global economy on the firm's podcast exchanges at Goldman Sachs you'll hear discussions on topics
The far-reaching implications like climate change autonomous driving the future of China's economic drug plus much more
That's exchanges at Goldman Sachs available on iTunes Stitcher SoundCloud on Google Play. GS
. com podcast
Got into debt the way most people
She bought something she loved
But you didn't have them
Small wooden house in Dracut
I really like the place because it had such a homey feel they mean the
Play the floors are wooden and everything is kind of like old style
The Windows 7
Describe cute somehow
You may remember that from one of our earlier Iceland shows
She's got a little boy named Oscar
When I visited a few years ago it was cold
Bundling little Oscar out so he could sleep outside
Big stroller
That's a thing people do at Iceland
Just leave your kid outside and pop into a
I meant Heather through our former intern Boulder hidden
A tall guy who were crazy sneakers
PhD in math but also did some DJing it
Like him. He also took on a bunch of debt to buy his
An apartment downtown not far from the old Harbour
I asked him to walk out on the balcony and describe the
There's a Domino's Pizza on
And there's a seven-eleven
Hirano store Volcano
But there are like two little
Like holes in between the big houses where I can see the ocean and you know if you follow
Things close you can even see a ship sailing into Reykjavik Ocean View
Two people two mortgages
Two piles of dead
In any other country they would be expected to pay that debt
There'd be no chance of a
But Iceland is this place that does everything a little
Everything is a little more intensity
Europe close to the Arctic Circle
But the island has volcanic so there's
The lava field
And economically it's also in the news
Prince When the financial crisis mess whatever you want
Going to call it happen
It happened in a big wave
3 giant Banks
How much does the entire economy with
And something particularly horrifying happened to People's mortgages
In Iceland a lot of people have these odd adjustable more
They just with info
On a tiny Island inflation can be a
So that's a video
And when the financial crisis happened there was a lot of inflation
The amount people owe on their mortgages
Through the roof
I have to pay that to look up the numbers from what happen
I haven't gone over these numbers at all because it's
With other things depressing you but not the good
Idea to waste much time always
Wallowing in it
Hey that kept getting these statement saying she owed more and more
Let me just be clear
I don't mean that she just owed more of that month
The total amount she owed
Go to the bank went up by 30%
It's like if you borrowed $100,000 for your house
All the sudden you owed $130
It's kind of like
You are
Drowning
That's
The feeling
That you are trying to keep your head above water but what's happening is that you are just
Going deeper under
After the crisis inflation went back down
City market just didn't keep growing up
Crazy Ray's
But people were stuck with much larger mortgages than they started with
It was this wound that just did not go
If people did not forget about
So in 2013
Five years after the financial crisis
When Iceland's Progressive Party found itself with very low poll numbers
It proposed
The Jubilee
No didn't call it
They call it correct
Yeah I like the correction
Corrects like there was something you know wrongly calculated and they need to correct it
That's kind of how
Putting it right they want to put things right that's how they frame it
Satan Icelandic
Lavida thinking
One more time
Lazy idiot in Korean
The Progressive Party was promising to go back and correct
Everyone's mortgages
Basically forgive the additional debt
Everyone has built up during the crisis during those two years 2008
It's a beautiful idea that you could go back
Try to undo this one very painful
Part of the financial
Make it like it never happened
I asked if there was something Icelandic
About the Sandia
I'm going back and fixing it
Something from the stories of the Viking days
The old Saga
No you usually Messiah to just dream about what's going to happen in the future
I'm sorry for all of us
No it's not usually that anything is just going to put your head down and keep going but
So something really new
Maybe for that reason
Is very an Icelandic Miss
The Jubilee Proposal with very
Oliver arneson is an author and economic thinker he was one of the people out making the case for the Jubilee
I remember one
Raleigh
This was in February something like that February March
And to get out during during the winter it's very dark here and I sent them that we had a this was in the evening in the middle of the
The week in the east
Up the country
People drove
150 MI
Come to this rally at least
Completely
Filled the auditorium
The meeting lasted till something like 11:30 and then they had
3 hours drive back
Empty show up for work the next morning
This this was very important to people and they were really really passionate about it
One obstacle to trying out of Jubilee
Forgiving debt is that there's always someone on the
There's someone who lent
But there was a plan to make even this part feel pain
The money to pay for the Jubilee
Would come from a tax on those
Read dead Icelandic bag
Thanks that many people in Iceland blame for their financial
Today most of what remains of the bank's is owned by hedge funds
Foreign investors
Saudi money coming from hedge funds
Find investors
Going to pay off the debts of ordinary people like balder and Haida
When Oliver without making a case of those political rallies
He told people this was the right thing to do
It's a recognition
It's a recognition it's a moral
Recognition
That
Things happened here
That were beyond the control
Of Norm of the
Average people
And
The government is showing
An effort
To recognize
Did you believe became the focus of the entire election
Progressive Party ran on it
And one
This is the same last name
Election results started to come in
Hotel in Reykjavik
Where supporters of gather
Green balloons everyone clapping in unison
I'm looking at this moment it seems so perfect
Iceland
Had an ideal setup to try out this very old idea but you be
You got a clearly-defined chunk of debt
The people all across the country have
Mortgages
Any of a source of what feels like free money to pay for
Does dead bat
There's a lot of math lot of details about how it would all work
But just a couple weeks ago
It was all finalized
Headout went online to see how much that she was going to have forgiven
How much she was going to get from the Jubilee
Yes okay so what we're going to do is we are going to go into the ditch
Threats of internal revenue
And find out how they are going to amend my more
More more
Mortgage
Markets
It says welcome and here is the result
So so it is
1 1/2 well
A little over one and a half million
1.5 million Icelandic
About 12000
Now thinking of Jubilee maybe you think of a party people dancing in the streets
And someone just knocked $12,000 off
Off my mortgage
I'd be really happy
They were plenty of happy people in Iceland
One person tweeted finally finally
And another everything will be corrected today
Edit vote for her pipe
She's pretty subdued
Until I actually
I don't know if I'm really skeptical or if I'm not this trusting but
If I see the money and doing form
Then I will be quite happy
Curse
But until then
This is the still just kind of
Anna and idea and idea of money that's might come in some form over some. Of time
So that's how crazy it seems that you don't actually believe it till you again
Yeah
At father
How much money are you getting
And new
Nothing
This is the other reason head I was not celebrating the
Friend father also has a mortgage
That apartment where I can kind of see the ocean from the balcony
But he bought it
Just after the cutoff
For the Jubilee
On paper at Jubilee is this nice simple
Batting practice
You can't forgive all day
So what that exactly are you going to forgive
You got a pic
And whatever you pick
They're going to be hit has involved
People who benefit from the Jubilee living next to people who get nothing
How does it feel not to be getting any money
Doesn't feel great
Not getting
Any money I mean
I had a student loan
That.
That's been talked like crazy and they're not
I don't see why it they if they fit doing this for mortgages why don't they do this
For for students student loans as well so I mean
I'm happy for him
Let's just getting it
But the little girl singing it feels very
Unfair
Did you believe that people like Baldur
And people who arguably need help the most
People didn't have enough money to buy a house
They were hurt by the financial crisis but they're not getting anything
That's the way this Jubilee work
If you didn't have a mortgage you don't get anything
The Atlantic media have run stories about some of the weird consequences of the
There's one guy who sold his house for more money than you bought it
You made money on it
But it's still going to be getting a check from the Jubilee
He says he doesn't need it
Some people have said they're going to give their money to charity
I talked to gylfi Magnus
He's an economist at the University of
He got a mortgage and five kids
But he thinks the Jubilee is a bad idea
The money for the Jubilee May feel like free money he says
But it's not
Sure it's coming from a tax the government levied on those dead.
Recess
You should think of that money just as government revenue
Money the government has from taxes
American spend on whatever it wants
Doesn't have to be a jubilee
Could spend it on education
Healthcare
Something that would help a broader number of people
Yukon to use government resources to put everybody
Barca pre-crisis
No income and wealth
You have to be much more selective on how you use government funds because you
There are many good needs good uses for government on send that you can squander them
Getting any money from the Jubilee
Yes I will
Can I ask how much
Well the household so that will beans with me and my wife will be getting a bit over 2 million Krona
$20,000
What are you going to do with the money
Well since it's actually funds that you received but it's just the reduction of of that so
Basically we don't do anything we just or less
You're not going to donate it to charity or something I'm not saying you should have just asked
No
I have five children so I have to
Be Frugal even if I am not happy with it
Is there somebody that's happy to get the money
Not really high and it's this
Come on it's a lot of money
Well yeah I guess it is and then
Maybe somebody is happy I don't know I haven't thought about it in those terms.
I really am not happy with the program itself
If you're wondering if the Jubilee might stimulate the overall economy help the Atlantic economy grow
Both guilty and Oliver the guy out making the case for the Jubilee
Said it's not much of a
People's overall mortgages are getting reduced
The total amount they always going
But when you look at the effect on monthly payments
It's not so bad
Guilty figures his monthly payments going to go down by
About 80 bucks
I think when people talk about Jubilee
Biblical idea of wiping the Slate
Imagine That All the Troubles Disappear With
But it's not a magic solution
Once you get over the thrill of the idea
You realize
Jubilee is just a government policy
Some people think it's good so
Bad
And on the tiny Island like Iceland
It's something to have a strong opinion about
And to argue about
Haida is both happy and not happy about the job
She's happy for the extra money
The single mom these days
But she's thought about this
And father thought
And they both come down on the side of thinking that the Jubilee
It's just a bad day
It's a I think it on a personal level like if you look at
Each individual case it's in many cases great that people get money but
That is I don't know it feels like
You know they're doing some justice but
If the Injustice is
Is more than that Justice had the joint the whole thing is is not
Koosh
Is there something silly about the ATM
Thinking we can go back and fix something like
I suppose this is kind of like in the old Cyrus
Where
People are going to do something right
But they ended up doing something
Kind of worse
As in people build fires that all about
Prevent
And it just kind of ends up with everybody is killing everybody one guy kills another guy
And then he gets revenge. And then they have to Revenge because
The other guy Revenge then it's just in the anthers to shoot Bloodbath
Come on nobody's dying here and there that you're getting money from it from Ed dead Bang
But they also
Okay it's nice to go back and correct things and and make everything
You know
Nice but if the government wrote world is coming in and fixing my bad mistakes I mean I bought a car
Turned out to be crap and I spent a lot of money on it then I'm not getting any of that money back I mean
What type of car again
But then I don't deserve
But to be corrected in anyway I mean
It's not the government's job to
You know come in
Correcting
The government should be building roads and creating a system where you where it's nice to live but not
And I'm not taking on
Private that we should correct the future and not the past right
An environment that's good for the future
Hey guys have a political campaign that you can run
Directing the future is of course the path that we usually
It's an easier sell
The future is Unwritten you can dream it will be whatever you want
The past is already here
Complicated
Surprisingly hard
One more thing we're going to handle the song that hit adjust
To the musician it's actually the first song She's recorded and it did really well and got played a bunch of the radio
Headed you want to sing something
Hahaha
But if you want to play like a piece of my song that would be super cool
Online what do you want me to sing the chorus
How's it going
I got your back baby
I got your back babe
I got your back I got your back
I got your back.
Open up a link to the video that goes with this song it's really quite pretty
What Iceland looks like
Do make sure you watch the very end
Car show today was produced by the abandoned thanks.
We love to hear what you think of Today Show you can send an email Planet Money at npr.org
And if you looking for other podcast NPR recommends checking out ask me another
You can find it on iTunes Stitcher or wherever you get your podcast
I'm David Captain Bob I'm about to be on Amazon
I'm here.
Thanks for listening
Thanks Maggie
Thank you