Today's Show originally aired in 2014
Puritas
If you don't pay your credit card
The first thing you might get is an email
Hate
Just a reminder
You missed your pain
If you still don't pay you'll start getting phone call
Eventually make it a letter
Your bank might pass your dead off to a collection agency
Some guy in a cubicle start calling and interrupting your dinner night after night
And then
If you still don't pay
There's one final stop for your
You might get a call from a guy like Jim
A guy who I met last week standing outside a boarded-up house in Buffalo New York
You and the rough part of the neighborhood but I want you to know you're safe
Appreciate I feel sick I feel like
You are right but this is
This is the hood man
You know I mean this this is Buffalo
Buffalo
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Jacob Goldstein
I'm joined today by special guest Jake Halpern Hey Jake hey
Jake just wrote a book called
Bad paper all about
Jimmy on this world and that's our show today
The story of this one guy who tried to make something of himself by getting into a what's really an ugly business
Also the story of this whole low-level semi-legal debt collection economy that
Sprung up in Buffalo
And even in a small way
It's the story of the last
20 or so years of global Finance
The time when the world went wild for deck
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Google and Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and a beautiful Business website with Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and professional tools from Google
It's the simplest way to look professional online
Visit squarespace.com Google to start your free trial
Use offer code small biz for 10% off your first purchase
Google and Squarespace
Make it professional
Make it beautiful
Chick you actually went to high school to meet you
Talk to me for years for this book
And you and I met up in Buffalo last weekend we went
How you doing
Jimmy the big guy he's wearing a baseball hat and a
Gray waffle shirt
And he grew up not far
Annie sez
It's a rough neighborhood
List all the hot water tank out of this house
They're still sweetness out of sugar around here if you letter
Jimmy
Peter Rothschild
I mean after high school he got
Dealing drugs he went to jail on a gun charge
And even if you're not an ex-con Buffalo's a tough place to find
But there's one local industry.
It was hiring a place where even if you had a criminal record
You could get a job
And that's the deck
Jimmy got a job at one of the big
Corporate debt collection
Hundreds of people sitting in cubicles
Calling people who haven't paid their credit card
Al pretty quickly Jimmy realized
He was really good at
I was one of the best walking in there smoking like a pound of weed and out of all those people you know I was produced
U90 called over the PA pick pain meds
But only because of the money I was making you only good as the last payment you got
So this was the Golden Age of deck
Right we remember the mortgage part of this
But people were also in debt for gym membership for book clubs or payday loans
Normally couldn't pay
You needed someone who could
Call them up
And get them to pay
And that was Jimmy
Jimmy got in trouble with the law again and got fired from that
Corporate debt collection job
He thought I don't need that
I'm going to open up my own shop
He convinced his brothers and sisters to stake him $10,000 and he rented his own off
So I actually visited his office on a few occasions and spent a lot of time there you walk up this tight little staircase
You get up to the top
And it's an old Karate Academy
Like kids used to take classes there sometime last week
Is all the way out there's there's like
Stranded equipment in like the back behind the cubicle
It looks like the whole place could have gone up yesterday and down tomorrow
In the main room is Jimmy and one other guy each have their desk
Heather kind of the corporate side and then all the workers are in back maybe half a dozen
In a cubicle
The office it's above a liquor store next to a used car lot
Across the street there's this little women's clothing
Scott is optimistic name
Sky's the limit
Jimmy took his mom to see the off
Office just after you
But for my mom
To finally
Look at something I was doing
And smile
Pointed over across the street she says baby
You see that
That's a message for God
Jimmy has his mom's blessing
Yes his karate studio / off
Has his phone setup
He needs one more thing
He needs debt
So what that actually looks like is basically just a Microsoft Excel spreadsheet that list hundreds of names of people
Who borrow money and didn't pay it back
And last week we met up with Jimmy he shows us one of these spreadsheet
He pulls out his iPhone and the screen is all cracked up
It looks like crap
Barely read on it but
I mean it's just tracked all up the screen is cracked up
The spreadsheet shows us has hundreds and hundreds of names
If this case these names are people who took out payday loans
If reach name there is this incredible amount of information
The address of the debtor
Social security number
The balance that they that they borrow
Some of them even come with an email address such as this one
That's the bank account number
You have the home phone number
Some of them have cell phone number
The majority have place of employment
Jimmy
Bought this
Spreadsheet he says he paid $18,000
And what that means is
All these people on the spreadsheet these hundreds of people
They used to owe money to a payday loan Chopper to some big debt collection firm
Now every one of those people
Deo Jimmy
Spreadsheets like this are not easy to find
Jimmy couldn't just call the bank and say hey it's Jimmy from Buffalo yeah I can you sell me some debt
Now it doesn't work like that
Jimmy said
It's the same situation he was in when he used to sell drugs
It's just like streets I mean you know you I can't walk into Mexico and go tell some some drug cartel
Listen man I'm from the hood in Buffalo man give me all the keys you got
The man is the proper chain of command
You'll come here and talk to me
You are saying can you imagine that
In other words
Jimmy needs a dealer
He needs someone who can start getting in those Microsoft Excel spread
He puts the word out and he finds a guy named Blair
Just Larry
He asked us not to use his last name
Jimmy
Such and such
Over here has an agency and he's looking for something
I called Jimmy up
And I came right to visit him
Light
Just got to
A good level understanding
Larry has a lot in common with g
They both grew up in rough neighborhoods Larry went to prison on robbery and drug charges
They got a job at a big debt collection company
And then he went out on his own
Larry's Niche was waking up people who are looking to sell that
What those were looking to buy it he's the middleman
And in the same way that a few years back
Global debt Market was booming
Larry says in Buffalo things were booming to
Why do people like Jimmy we're getting into the business
All of a sudden
There became an explosion
Substrate level
Agencies
On just about every
Block
Geyser
I'm in out of prison literally
In a couple of months
They're running a collection
They get that that they get people on the phone
Daystar down
Start collect
Larry says those street-level guys those guys like to meet we're really good
Getting people
Collection agencies
The bread-and-butter collectors that become the top
Collectors
I always the guys from this tree
Yeah when you say from the streets what do you mean
I mean like
Didn't go to college
Didn't didn't grow up in the suburbs
You know
Pretty much came up the same way I did
On on on on on food stamps and ramen noodles
What do you think it is about growing up that way that makes people good at
At the job
Hunger
Just being hungry to want something
Jimmy was hungry
At that office in the old karate studio he hired a small staff to go through the spreadsheet
Call people who owed money
When they got people on the phone then transfer the call to Jimmy
Twitter Jimmy made a profit or went bankrupt
Came down to what Jimmy said
Jimmy is about to talk to someone
Who's refused to pay collector
Again and again
People who are so unlikely to pay
The Jimmy was able to buy their debt for pennies on the dollar
$100 payday loan he might buy for a dollar
Because the odds are if you can find them at all they're probably going to hang up on
But there's that beautiful moment when Jimmy actually gets the person on the other end of the line and then everything comes down to what he says
There's an art to it
In fact they call it
The talk off
And Jimmy has a
Few different talk off depending on who's got on the phone
Like there's a nice guy talk off
The person seems willing to pay
Nine times out of ten men these people just want somebody to listen to him you know you the first person ever talk to me like I was a human
I didn't pay the bill because the last guy I had a talk with no he was a o
I didn't pay the bill because I just didn't have it at that point time
When I first visited Jimmy a few years ago I heard him do a version of the nice guy talk off and one of the things you'll notice here besides
It's the sort of gentle tone
Is all the
Formal sign language
You can hear me try to communicate that this is an official matter
He's not just some guy in an old karate studio
Calling you up about a
The last thing we want to do is get squeezed pressure you or put you in the position as to where
You making an arrangement and you're not go
To be with a G note
Hold it if we were to table this until the 1st
I wouldn't even want to keep it for the mouth that you're sure you were going to have
If we were to give you into
You have your funds available
But we don't want you to rely on someone else
You know a reference is selling us out
If you need it until the first how sure would you be that you would have those funds
Of course that's the way it goes when people are willing
When they're not
Jimmy gives a very different
The tough-guy.
You need to pay me
Before you go shopping
For you pay your rent
We pay your phone bill
Before you take care of this
If we take care of that
Give me some money
Now and the tough guy talk off Jenny would sometimes get into a legal gray area
Under federal law guy Jimmy can't straight-up lied
I can't say payoff you're going to get thrown in jail or I'm going to take away your car
But what Jimmy would do is use the same kind of
Formal official language to imply that legal action was going to happen
Use trigger words such as refusal and this is
First substantive contact
New Jersey exam
This is a refusal you don't want to pay your bill
This is going to be considered first substantive contact we're going to contact your system before this as a refuse
We gave you an opportunity to pay it
And you didn't want to take advantage so this call actually ends with Jimmy hanging up on this one
Ian says she's going to call right back
And then boom like that
The woman called back and he's right back at it
Indian she doesn't end up collecting but that was his power move
I remember these are payday loans Jimmy's trying to collect
Meaning
The people who borrow the money we're probably people who didn't have much money in the first play
People who didn't have access to better kinds of credit
What are the ugly things about this world is
This is it people like Jimmy
Who don't have much money
Can't collect from
Other people
Who don't have much
Jimmy says
She understood
I mean look at where we sitting at right now
I don't feel good I know you I know
I'm pulling people out that take
Payday loans out I see they living condition look at mines
I've been in positions I mean just recently where you going to need a couple extra dollars and it's that in the third man I feel
Horrible
Is Dallas feel like a hustler
No don't feel like you know legitimate work
Because you Coruscant people in again creating a sense of urgency for them to pay some that they don't got
Would you Otis money
And I got kids to feed
Because I bought this portfolio
I understand
Still after a few years
Jimmy shop does well enough that he's able to move to a bigger office
In a more upscale neighborhood
That's real nice off
Fake trees all that crazy stuff
How many people were working
At one time at the most had 17 people working in there
Around the same time
It's all those street-level agencies were springing up and looking for debt to buy
Business was booming for Jimmy's dealer
Larry
Yeah
I was I was doing great
I had
Two homes paid for
Who was Playboy's
We will toast those we we have more money than the drug dealers they looked up to us
If you have a spreadsheet and a good talk off
Drink
At least
That's the way it was for a while
But just like people on Wall Street started going wild with debt going to
Far
People in Buffalo started Crossing out of that gray area
And doing things that were just blatantly Italy
So the illegal version of the talk off has its own name
Jimmy calls
The Buffalo taka fire another guy call it the shake and basically it's we're coming to your house we're going to arrest you
The kids are going to Social Services
I will taking your car all lies
The most awful things you could think of to just scare people silly into pay
The guys doing that stuff the guys doing the Buffalo talk off
They are some of the people buying debt from Larry
That is supposed to come with
Paperwork
Sometimes the paperwork is virtual sometimes it's actually boxes full of paper
Prove it
The people in the spreadsheets really owe the money
The proof that there's a clear chain of ownership from the original bank or payday loan shop all the way through
Two different debt collectors
What Larry says
The street-level guys doing the shake doing the Buffalo talk off they weren't paying attention to India
My street-level guys
They don't care nothing about the pay
Bottom don't even know about it
Just get me the portfolio I got Wolves at my agency we're going to get the money all they want is that fine
This kind of disregard for the law
It's happening all the way up to the top of the Dead food chain
Apple store
Selling the same spreadsheet
The two or three different debt collector
Chris at the same time
That means if you're one of the people who owed money you might get a call from one deck
Pay off your debt to them
And then hear from another collector saying hey you all this money
And it's important understand here that this just isn't happening at the street level in Buffalo
You got guys way up
The food chain where wealthy Finance
People who are getting their hands on files they
They don't own
And her selling a bit straight of theft
Larry Wanda broken a few deals where his
Customers got some of the stolen debt
This of course got him into trouble with his customers and no thing he says is his own fault
We let greed
Step in like we we we
We stopped doing our due diligence
Because the money was right there
To be gotten
And we wanted
For Jimmy it all came to an end
Just a few months ago
Normally
When he convince someone to pay their debt
The money would appear in his bank account
Shortly after
But one day
That money didn't show up
I was looking for some money to be deposited on a Friday and it never came
And Monday it never came
There's a company that process payments for gym
And that company turns out just
Cut him off cold decided not to work with
Jimmy says that this happened to a lot of smell like
Agencies in Buffalo
He says they got cut off and then they couldn't process
Entertainment Cinema
Bust
But you know it's hard to tell what really happened maybe it was just Jimmy went to far too many times and that
Gray area
Too many people complained about the charges on the account so the process
You just said enough
In any case without that Payment Processing Company there's no way for Jimmy to get paid I mean that just pulls the plug on his operation
He can't pay his workers
Is rent Mesa what you do with your office
I didn't do anything with it I lost it
Lost
After we talked to Jimmy I put out some calls and it turns out the federal government is cracking down on somebody's payment processor
Holding them accountable
For what payday lenders
So you'll maybe Jimmy was right it's possible that he did get shut down as part of some broader Suite
Larry Jimmy's dealer he got out of the business before this cracked
He bought a little house in a working-class suburb outside of Buffalo
We actually talked in there in his garage
Get a weight bench little mini fridge
Bottled water in it
I just want to just be a regular normal guy waking up everyday listening to the birds cutting my grass
Goodman thumbs up to the neighbor that's what I do all the time
Jimmy is now trying to get into real estate
That boarded-up house where we met him
The one where the thieves stole the hot water heater
Jimmy actually bought that house for
For $2,000
He wants to fix it up and rent it out
He said he's glad to be out of
I'm tired of running
I need something a little but a lot more
A lot more solid
Like Houses
Solid solid as houses I think is the expression
Solitude is raggedy one is but you got to start somewhere
Like a lot of the world Jimmy came out of the boom and bust
The Bowery star
Without me
Just a note about today's show
In the original version we use Jimmy's last name
Upper today show we have omitted it at Jimmy's
As always
We want to know what you think of the show you can email us at Planet Money at npr.org or you can find us on Twitter or Facebook
The show was originally produced by Jess Jiang today's rerun was produced by Rihanna
Jake Halpern book has a lot more about Larry and Jimmy and this whole world
Of debt collection
The book is called Bad
Paper if you're looking for something else to listen to check out how I built this
It's a new podcast is hosted by Guy Raz of
TED Radio Hour Fame
And in each episode of the show he talks to a founder of a company
Get the story of their company
I hate talk to people from Airbnb from Clif bar from
Epic Records
The shows called how I built this you can find it on the NPR one app or wherever you get
I'm Jacob Goldstein
Thanks for listening