Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Robert Smith
Let me tell you a secret about being a reporter
If it were not for deadlines
Reporters like myself
Would work on the same story for the rest of our lives the only way we get things done around here
Where is Denmark
But it does mean that sometimes
You don't have a real ending
To the story you're telling you just have to sort of
Figure out
Some kind of way
ATN podcast
Often times I wouldn't this often times we sort of end with a kind of
Time will tell
But not today
Today on the show
Time
Has
Call we follow up on our favorite stories of the year
And we find out what happened after we turned off our recorder after the deadline
It's an annual tradition we have here Planet Money named after a certain
Catchphrase
Of the radio Legend Paul Harvey
Today
Together
You and I are going to learn
The rest of the story
The reason why this is my favorite time of year is because I get to do my Paul Harvey impression this is
The rest
Of the story
What 2016
Support
This podcast
And the following message come from atlassian
Today nearly anything
And if we can dream it
So how do you bring everyone together to realize their shared vision
Whip it last
Makers of software
Jira
Confluence
Hipchat in bitbucket give your team everything you need to organize
Discuss
WeChat
Atlassian works that help teams large and small Ascend to new heights
Create WhatsApp
Visit atlassian.,
Tema
Mm
I'll tell you this is not an easy year to recap
Because
Most of the big scary economic stories that we
We covered all year long
Still don't have endings to them
They're still teetering on the edge
United Kingdom Francis United Kingdom still has not pulled
Trigger
To leave the European Union
Puerto Rico still
Crushed under the massive debt
Venezuela still
Just a devastating tragic story
Still collapsing
I will be falling all of the stories well into 2017 and
Of course
Will be covering our brand new
New president
That's a wrap up
This year this year there are still a few podcast that we wanted to check back
First up
Wells Fargo
We did too big investigations into the bank along with NPR economics correspondent
Chris Arnold hey Chris hey Robert
So let's just quickly recap what we did in the two podcast
What did Wells Fargo do wrong
It's okay there was this big banking scandal at Wells Fargo that people have probably heard of where
Mega Million customers got credit cards in
Stuff that they didn't ask for it and that's terrible but
What we dug into and what I think is much more interesting
Is it was the employees
Themselves at this company who probably were hurt more than anyone else
And the way that happen
Is that we found
A number of folks who who resisted the sales pressure in the fraud and all the bad stuff that was going on inside the bank
Tell him even call the Ethics Line at the bank to say hey this is terrible is all this bad stuff going on around the office
And after they did that they were either pushed out or fired
And then the bank did something very
Particular to them
It put what we call The Scarlet Letter
On their permanent record
It's called the u v is
With a permanent record
Griswold
And that prevented them
From getting a job
If any other bag is so we're just basically wrecked their career
Are we specifically for the story about a young man named Jeremy
Who had this
Scarlet Letter on his u5
And essentially had to
Change the part of the banking industry he was in and he knows
This bad Mark is still on his record
I try not to think about it to be honest with you
Scares the crap out of me I can everything that I've worked for these past eight years can be taken away from me because of this
When is because of this lie because of this this one statement that Wells Fargo in
Put on there he is it for him he's basically saying like this like a landmine
That could go off at any time
And Destroy his career
Landmine planted by his former employer by Wells Fargo right exactly Ed
So this caught the attention to a lot of people we got a lot of feedback on the story
And in particular this caught the attention of Senator Elizabeth Warren
Who as you probably know is for Massachusetts
And
She's
Made a name for himself obviously by
Challenging big powerful financial institutions and try to get reforms there
She is not somebody
You want to have
A firing
Off letters to your CEO and demanding answers and as a result of our stories
That's exactly what happened
We could report
On end
You're about
Employees
He said that Wells Fargo had
Alligator
Against the music
Statements on there
U5
That we're not true
And the
That's what
God of Interest
And so we started looking at the
You fought
Statements that are
Then required
File
And didn't and finding
More and more evidence
I'm a big problem that well
Increase when when someone says she's looking into this I mean that really means she's conducting an investigation
Right she's asked for documents from finra which is
The financial industry regulatory Authority at that sounds like a government agency is actually
Self-regulatory Industry Group but she's trying to get
All kinds of document
It's from them there the bank Industry Group that puts this Mark on the youth
Right they manage this whole u v system
So she's asking questions
Of finra
She sent a letter to Wells Fargo demanding
Answers in
And and wanting more information but I also she's making this bigger
Then Wells Fargo she's asking the question okay wait
How could this happen and
The fact that this did happen does that mean that we need some kind of Reform here
To fix the system
What's the catch with
When somebody says
Problem
An employer didn't
Taccom
Well since you have taken the attitude
Is there something wrong here
The Whistleblower
Problem
We should say there has been a few other
Get to progress after we are the podcast our Wells Fargo has talked about
At least intending to rehire some of the workers that perhaps were wrongly fired
We're following that and
Finra
Has sort of at least acknowledge
Chris that
There might be a problem
With these
You fight with these reports with these black marks on people's record
We will definitely hear more about Wells Fargo in 2017 thanks Chris
Oh you're welcome
It is my pleasure to bring in Jacob gold
Dean to talk about a great podcast you did
In the fall about self
Check out machine
These are the things that
Grocery stores
Put in
To I don't know
To make my life easier if you scan your groceries yourself
And then it breaks and they call over the store employee to fix it and then you walk out
Who sings All This Time
That's the theory anyway so for this story as you may recall Nick Fountain I we went up to
Toronto
Are we talk to the inventor of the self-checkout machine
We also talked about the future of self checkout
And for that part of the show we talked to somebody named Dusty
You were to NCR that's a big
Company that's working on this.
And just see what he described first like his vision
He's like this is the store of the future
Do you need the scanner Could you actually not have
More cameras in artificial intelligence behind the cameras
Actually know that
We just saw you pick an item up from this
Part of the Shelf
And we know
That that's where
The
The baked beans are
And therefore automatically add that
To your order
That's as frictionless as you can get you walk in the store you pick up your items you walk out
No cash register a dog that's right
And you think that'll actually happen
That will happen
Yeah the questions will that happen in 2020 or that happen in 2030
And all I get is baked beans so this would solve all of my problems store that sells baked beans
With lasers
So this is Juneau the dusty let's vision
When you talk to text people they always have their like utopian vision of the few
Futurama Netflix
Never really
Come so he says all this and I'm
But
Robert Smith
Amir 48 days
Less than 2 months
After this podcast aired
Amazon
Evian amazon.com
Announced a new project
Welcome
To Amazon go use the Amazon Go app to enter Then
Put away your phone and start shopping it's really that simple to Robert Amazon
What store is like a little 7-Eleven
And it works
Just like Dusty lots of NCR told us
The store of the future would work
Once you got everything you want you can just go when you leave are just walk out technology
Adds up your virtual card and charges your Amazon account you receive it sent straight to the app and you can keep
Go it Amazon go no lines no checkout
Apparently with the store needed was not necessary technology but lots of buzzwords like
Just walk out technology
And then let's do do do-do-do-do do-do-do-do do-do-do-do
Do we know how to do it
Amazon is glad you asked
So how does it work we use computer vision deep learning algorithms
Interfusion much like you find at self-driving cars
I have no idea what the
I suspect there's a lot of workers on closed-circuit cameras just lay like
Two cans of beans
I should I should say we just put one more note of skepticism the my skepticism apparently just got approved on butt
This is an ad
The store is not open yet
But it's supposed to be open
In early 2017 a real store
In Seattle washing
Thank you Jacob Happy New Year
Our last check in
On the rest of the story is with
Stacy fan
X-Men Stacy hi Robert we did a podcast
A year ago
Now that was about ice
And more specifically was about
The economics of Isis
Yes Isis is a horse the terrorist group that is occupied territory in Syria and Iraq
And we spoke with a man who lived in an Isis controlled town
Muhammad ketterer and his hometown is deir ezzor
And he told us a little bit about the economics of living in an Isis can
Control tower
He said Isis members you
Use dollars in
A lot of money to throw around and stores in tears or sorrow
Catering to them
Selling a lot of really
Western items
Things like energy drinks and Axe Body Spray and candy bars
Twix that's kind of fancy Goods
Twix
Twix Twix bars like only
Only Isis Fighters get to eat Twix bars
This amazing things this podcast was
Muhammad story he actually been recruited
To work for ice
Yes to design a logo for their news age
This is a graphic designer
Exactly
And after that he was asked to join Isis and
E flat
And when we talked to him he was in Turkey
He since left turkey at his now in Germany with his face
Family
Although he still in touch with people indira's or his hometown and he said things there are mostly the same but they have gotten
Worst
What is the things he said was the tax-collecting has gotten more aggressive
And now Isis is demanding
Taxes in the special
Currency that it meant
Getting used to demand
A ton of taxes in either
Syrian money or in US dollars
Exactly but I started making its own coins out of gold and silver and copper
And it sells these coins to jewelry stores
And people have to go to jewelry stores and buy them
So that when Isis members show up at their house demanding money
They can pay them in the special Isis
So Isis members
Self still use dollars but everybody has to pay Isis
Indy special
So Isis
Makes money
By minting money
Visalia to the people and then under threat of death
Demands the money back from them in Texas
Yes
Evil Genius
Yeah Evil Genius
Muhammad himself is doing pretty well
He has a new baby
He's trying to learn German but he says he still misses deer Azure everyday and
He says
The second Isis leaves
He and his family will go back
Thank you Stacey
Because I have a
Surprise
Color for you on the line
Okay
Hello
Json
Yes Jason Bruns the man who are you guys
Ice bite everyone with me in 2016 Planet Money
Got into the oil bill
We got into it hard we bought
100 barrels of 00
I thought we fancy well people cocktail
At $40 a barrel
And we lost a ton of money doing
You should go back and listen if you
Not have the check
And when we last left your Json you were standing in a muddy oil field
With our money
Where are you right now
Phoenix Arizona
What are you doing in Phoenix
A vacation
We're just down here doing a lot of golfing
I love eating
I suspect that this vacation was paid for by
The Planet Money
Incompetent at buying oil
Well I don't think that quite got it it did probably help me by one of my steak dinner so I'm not going to lie
Probably didn't do much on anything else
A lot has happened in the oil world since we lost money and left a business
OPEC
The oil cartel agreed to limited production of oil which sent the price
Shooting up
About the same oil that we bought it $40 a barrel is now fetching
$6 a barrel
If we had a way to keep that oil we could have made a huge profit but of course we did
Where we at
If you to put it in bottles and sold it like a quarter to time on your show you probably done better
You're right
Json when we last left you you had
Shut down one of your wells
Because of the low oil
Yes and you did not feel great
No no
Spell I didn't but I did start it up the next month
I started up and ran it long enough to
Does may contain call
Disable to keep the lease
And you know what make it wasn't
Profitable so to save at least I broke even
You told us that you did not
Sort of get up in the morning and check the price of oil you didn't follow all the news because it was creating
Stress and Anxiety
But that was when the prices going down
When the price is going up are you more excited to
Check your phone check the news check the price every hour
So not every hour but I check it every day
It is still amazing
To be
How all these things in the world
Can affect the price of oil
In Kansas
You know I an OPEC meeting in Geneva or rumors about
Donald Trump and how he's going to
Iran more harsh
Do you like that that can determine
Whether or not
You get to
To take a nice vacation
But I guess you know you're probably use
Yeah my grandpa used
Tell me should one day
You ready to go buy a Cadillac
And ready to go out for a steak dinner and the next day you're ready to buy a pinto and go out for a bologna sandwich
You know that's that's the roller coaster ride the oil business
And you just went out for steak dinner
We just went out for a steak dinner last night that's right
We're encouraged
All right I enjoy your golf game
Jason Bruns
Be true
Winner in the Planet Money
Oil pressure
Somebody
We love to hear what you think of Planet Money so you should
Email us
Maybe your favorite story from the past year 2016
We are Planet Money at npr.org
Today's episode and effect Oliver episodes for the year were produced by Sally Helm Jess Jiang
Nick fountain
The coolest and Alex
Mark you guys are the best
Thank you if you're looking for another podcast listen to maybe you need a little break
On family time the other podcast from NPR embedded
How I built this invisibilia
Code switch
They're all great and
You can find them at npr.org podcast or on the NPR one
Robert Smith
And I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
And
We are not married if you want to know the rest of the story the rest of the story is
We're both Smith
We're not married
There's a lot of Smith's in the world to stop writing to ask
If we're married
We're not married
Well it's interest
Because my aunt
Back in Idaho
She sent me a text message because when you Google my name
The first thing that comes up is Stacey Vanek Smith
Married
Tencent
Wedding the season-ending Smith married Robert Smith
And so my aunt Googled me
And thought that I've had hat like secretly got married
Apparently this was
The talk around
The Smith family
We're not married
So do not assume
In fact we want to do a favor for Stacey Vanek Smith
No relation really do a favor for Stacy which is
Go to your Google
And I want you to search
Stacey Vanek Smith
Genius
I don't like that she said Smith awesome reporter
Stacey Vanek Smith can she fly
Good question I've never tried
Whatever you do do not Google
If we are married
Because we are not
I would love it if my aunt calls me in 20
Stacy
The whole family's talking about whether or not you can
Reply
That would be
Thanks for listening