We all have that person on face
Maybe it's a friend maybe it's a relative
Shrek I need a person
Ford's news articles that are not
Entirely
Florist I doubt she's an NPR correspondent
Velour that person is
Her aunt
My aunt is
Really into what's fake news she thinks it's real
I mean she post things like Muslim nurses refuse to wash hands before operation
Not true
More more I'm looking I'm looking here
Michelle Obama is a transvestite
That Obama is a secret Muslim who's possibly gay so he's a gay Muslim
Set fake fake info
You must have
When that's your aunt
The stuff was fake
I did and we got into a big fight over it
She essentially didn't believe me and said will you work for the mainstream media
But it definitely got me thinking
About all of this and where was it coming from and I began to go down this road to really try
Find understand this
Call phenomena of fake news
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Robert Smith
And I'm Laura Seidel today on the show
We are going to take what
Just
Fake news story
Optically odious one that implies that Hillary Clinton
Is a murderer
And we're going to follow this fake news story all the way back
Why you wrote it
Who published it
And why
Every single word
Of this article is fake
But what is real
Is that it was shared over half a million times on Facebook
And that means
Somebody
Somewhere
Who's making Fairy real money off of
We find him
We find a fake news Mogul running a fake news Empire
Until the fallacy
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Google and Squarespace
When you create a custom domain and a beautiful Business website with Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and
Professional tools from Google
It's the simplest way to look professional online
Visit squarespace.com Google to start your free trial
Use offer code small biz
10% off your first purchase
Google and Squarespace
Make it professional
Make it beautiful
Okay where are we picked
Fake news story
Give us the head
FBI agent suspected in Hillary email leaks
Found dead in apparent murder-suicide
This article
Is amazed
It has a
Complicated dark plot about how one of the FBI investigators looking for the Clinton email scandal
Dies under mysterious circumstances their names
Dates and
And locations to murder at the suicide
Facts don't matter because of course
It's all made up
It's all fake
But it looks
So
Professional
There's this
Big photo of a
Giant Fireball looks legit
And it's on a site called the Denver Guardian
Which looks real
Weather in local stories
Someone has put a lot of time in
So this is all I have to go on I have a pile of fake
Tell if there's no author there's no name on the site and I tried to find out who owns a domain name
Denverguardian.com
And I hit a wall
It was registered anonymously
But luckily I know this guy
Let's just see if we can figure this out
One second
This is John Jansen head of engineering at Master McNeil a tech company in Berkeley California
But in his spare time he's an internet
I'm
Basically responsible for reverse engineering a whole bunch of
Different websites
Something of John like an archaeologist
He's digging around in
Into the foundation
Website
I set him to work
On this FBI murder suicide article
And he starts to look through the computer code at the site
Denverguardian.com
And there it is
The first
Entry used
Set up the website
Made by someone with the handle
Let Texas
Which sounds a lot like somebody with some kind of political agenda
That was sort of the thread that started to unravel everything really
He discovers this
Full
Network
Fake news outlets
With
Real city names
Nationalreport.net United media
Publishing.com
Conservative
Frontline.
International report
Dot net
All filled with fake news
So our detective John Jansen checks the IP address
All these websites
Share the same server
So Janssen Dixon more
He finds an old email address
Cross checks
Define the name
There's an individual whose name is jestin Coler
Who appears to be behind a bunch of the stuff
Justin
Kohler
Which cannot be a real
I mean the word jest
Is in there Justin
Kohler
And yet
This guy has a LinkedIn
It says he wants old magazine subscriptions work
Is a database administrator
And a freelance writer
Ha
Writer
The next thing is that he's a
Contributing freelance writer
International yachtsman magazine
Don't blame anyone for cycling that's okay
So Hillary is being tormented by a secret cabal of international yachtsman
Or ceiling journalist
And you know it's tempting to think that there's probably some poor writer who
Couldn't tell the article about sailing
And decided to start making stuff
But then we discover
The business
Jestin Coler
Has started a company called Epic
Disinfo media
It's so obvious
I mean like calling yourself
Evil Corp
I know but even something called disinfo media
How to write down an address when the Incorporated and that really dress
Is in a suburb of Los Angeles California
Near the ocean
Where
There are yachts
This whole thing is coming together
It's a beautiful sunny afternoon in Los Angeles I grabbed the fake article
And I take my producer Luke vanderploeg and we go
We have it's listed as the office of disinfo media
There in a triple one of these typical LA strip malls
Sushi and nail spa and then we drive up to the exact address that we have
What this appears to be a normal hold a post office box
16450 of course it is if you're fake news guy you probably would fake address
I was bummed
But I did have second address and the second address was right around the corner
Minivan all right so he's got a minivan to one-story home kind of a
Bungalow home
And it's palm tree in the front lawn because hey this is Southern California
American flag
So I may be a patriot
So we're going to give it a shot now
So we get out of the car
I am a little nervous cuz it's clearly somebody's home
Hi there
Looking for Justin Koehler
When is asking something
Had a
Story that I'm wondering if you wrote
You damn right it
I'm at just so you know I'm a reporter with NPR and
We were looking online and
You're a lot of tracing discovered the disinformation media
Was the
Owner of several websites that you know such as the national report.
Butler that was totally
Oh I'm sure it was him
We actually even check the mailman happen to be going by and we said does Justin Koehler live there and he confirmed he does
So we were sure it was him
He just didn't want to talk to you
But we did leave a mark on tag
And we went back to the office
And
Maybe an hour and a half later
We got an email from Justin Cole
He said he would
My name is Justin Koehler am the owner of disinfo media Inc
You found it Laura you found a guy
I did and he was not
Quite what I was expecting here is his kind of
Average looking 40 year old guy with a wife and two kids
And a really beautiful comfortable home
You had for yachting magazine
I did write for yachting magazine
You like jazz
I don't care for Yachts no but they hired me as a travel writer in
Today was good so
That was part of his real news career the fake part didn't start until
And that's the part we really wanted to know about
Why did he write fake news
And how did he get away with it
Justin says
He was always interested
In the art
A propaganda
You know what would people believe how do you explain that
And he says he started
Disinfo media
At first just for fun
Just a test out his ideas
And you also says
He is not a conservative
If he did not do this to bring down Hillary Clinton in fact
This really surprised me
He says he's a liberal
And then he started doing this
Fake news business
Basically to provoke
The alt right
He's like a reverse troll
Can the whole idea from the start was the kind of build
Aside the good kind of infiltrate the echo chambers of the all right
Published blatantly false or fictional stories and then
I got to be able to publicly denounce those stories and end point out the fact that they were
Queer fiction
Dessert made my head hurt
@justin claimed
Did he wrote
Fake news stories about Democrat
So that conservatives would spread them around
And then look stupid when the stories were discovered is fake
I know
I know it sounds a bit odd and we checked what we could about him
Justin Koehler is his real name and he actually is a registered Democrat
And I do have to say
When he talks about the specific fake news story
He's written
You can hear the Glee he has
In basically screwing with everyone
One of my personal favorites was the story that I wrote about a pot shop marijuana shop in Colorado
Justin wrote a news story about how customers in Colorado marijuana shops for using food stamps to buy pot
And it sounds ridiculous of course
Buddy got picked up in a spread like crazy years Fox News
I can people collecting food stamps in Colorado
Add marijuana to the shopping list
Right now the answer is
Yes
I'm so that when I got a decent chuckle out of myself I thought that was a good time
He doesn't sound like a prankster I mean he clearly Delights
And getting a ride
So yeah I went and I I looked at some of his side to use when it's called National reports
And headlines are kind of more trying to be like the onion for conservatives like
Take this one
Bernie Sanders
Conter for debate
Look at his poll numbers now
And Jesse says at least in the beginning he was an equal-opportunity pranks
He tried to Peddle fake news for lefties he says
Making a vial things about
Conservatives
It just has never worked and never takes off if people will always set you know you'll get debunk like within the first two comments
And another thing is kind of Fizzles out
I'm just going to stop occasionally hear the podcast to say that Justin is an admitted liar
And despite saying you dinner for fun at some point
Fake news
Clearly became a money maker
Progestin you get people to share a fake news article you can sell all these eyeballs to advertisers
And his fake news sites
Do you have real a
Justin would not
Give us the exact amount of money he's making up a fake news
But he eventually admitted that he made in the ballpark of
10 to $30,000 and
You are making good money at it so it also gave you a lot of incentive to keep
Doing it
Regardless of
The empire
Correct
He was a fake news businessman and he figured out the best way to deliver his product
Step one
Make it look real
He bought domain names like Washington Post
Dot-com
Doc Co
And usatoday.com
Somewhere so fake that they sounded real like the Denver Garden
You know, the idea was to
Make this ice look as is legit as possible right to the homepage of course they're going to be
Local news local forecast local sports
The actual fake news stories were going to be buried off the homepage so
You know if you were reading a story and then you click to the homepage of that car this looks like
Denver guardian or
Any number of sites
Justin could actually keep up with the demand so Step 2
You've had a lot of former writers
Just like himself willing right fake news
It's probably 20 to 25 contributors
Step 3 to profiting off of
Fake news
The arrival of Donald J Trump
I mean my gosh the number of just fake
Accounts
On Facebook exploded during the Trump election
And this brings us to the article we have been tracking this whole time the one about the FBI agent
Who is killed after his alleged involvement in leaking Clinton emails
Justin did not
Doesn't know the real name of the contributor who did but he did publish it and he says he got 1.6 million views over
10 days
Another the people wanted to hear this you know so all it took was to write that story
Everything about it was fictional the town the people that sheriff the FBI got
And then you know
How does our social media guys going to go out and do a little
Dropping it throughout
Trump groups in Trump forums in
Spread like wildfire
The story was quickly debunked on sites like snopes.com and
The real paper in Denver The Denver Post
What's a lot of trump supporters
This did not matter
They don't care that it was debunked you know snopes is Run by George Soros and Israel Obama mouthpiece to them and
You know the credibility of these kind of sources I guess it's been
Just tarnish so much that
Nobody even listens anymore
In case you didn't quite get that Snopes
.com is a sort of fact-checking websites
It is not actually owned by George Soros
Will you in some ways Justin
Did prove his point
You can prank people pretty easily you can make money off of it you can degrade the truth you can make everything worthless you can do all
All of these things
The thing is
Identifying serious business because Hillary Clinton did lose the election and some people think fake news was Atkins
Forgetting Factor today
So I asked him
Do you have somebody who identifies as liberal have any regrets
To the extent to which fake news went viral during the presidential
I don't
There are
Many factors as to why Trump won
That don't involve fake
Snooze right
Enough
As much as I like Hillary she was a poor candidate
She
Brought in a lot of baggage
So I don't I don't find myself
I don't I'm not guilty of that I'm not going to
I'm not going to live with that on my conscience
So you don't feel response
I do not
Since the election there's been a lot of hand-wringing and news organizations including ours about
How to stop people like Justin
How to stop the stuff from being spread around
At least some way to label it and Target news is fake before everyone reads it before everyone believes it
But if you're just so you know I cannot
Imagine
The dad is going to work
Like there is a demand for this product
People want
Conspiracy like people want fake news
It confirms what they already believe
And we know from history what happens when you try to Outlaw product that everyone wants
Justin told me one of his sights
Nationalreport.net was actually blocked
On Facebook and it lost its ad contract
Google
But he said from his perspective that doesn't even matter
There are literally hundreds of AD Networks
Literally hundreds of them
Early last week I just my inbox was just
Filled every day with people because they knew that Facebook was her Google excuse me was cracking down
Hundreds of people wanting to work
With my sights
You know that right
It occurs to me that there has never been a better time
To be in the fake news business I mean after all this election showed
Did their hundreds of thousands of people who view these articles
And that the articles
Work
Your projections perspective there is money to be made
And yet
Justin may turn all of this down
He's been talking with his wife
And he says he is thinking about getting out of the fake news business
Now this is something I
Head enjoy doing
Butter
How that kind of joy is gone I guess
Donovan just keep getting
Deeper into distress at iron going to stay away from this sort of stuff
So he might just be telling us what we want to hear it and it maybe I'm just go about but I have a feeling
He ended up in over his head
We're always interested in dark corners of the internet that we don't know about so if you see any other wrongdoing
Out there give us an email Planet Money at npr.org
Or you can find us on Facebook or Twitter
Our episode today was produced by Elizabeth kulas special science Shawn Gurley Dan Kaminsky and rebirth
Berliner nephew finished listening to Planet Money may we suggest a brand new show being carried by NPR it's called radio
You ambulante
It's our first ever podcast in Spanish
Think engaging stories like you here here only en espanol
Check it out on the NPR one app
Aurat npr.org
Podcast
And just a special note here a lot of people right in and say how do we support for the money can we send you a check
And weirdly enough we say no no
But here
Is something you can do
You can support your local NPR station
The way to do that is to find stations. Npr.org find your local station
Mini Donuts coupons
And tell them
Planet Money set
Helping them
Elsa
I'm Robert Smith
Laura Sydell
Thanks for listening
This message comes from NPR sponsors snowflake the only data warehouse built for the cloud
Unlock deep Data Insights with the instantly scalable Cloud build data warehouse start your journey
Towards data-driven decision-making it's snowflake. Com NPR