Support for NPR and the following message come from service now making the world of work
Work better for people
Their cloud-based platform and solutions deliver digital workflow
Spell create great experiences and unlock productivity for your whole company
More at servicenow.com
In 2008 Neel Kashkari was working in the treasury
Under George W bush
And he got what was
What was kind of a promotion
But a promotion into a job.
Sounds off
It was the middle of the financial
The crisis and Kush Curry got picked
To run the government bailout of the bank
How old were you at the time
I was 35 at the time and how much money were you
In charge of
The program is maximum size with 700 billion dollars
Taupe Qashqai trending
Massive bailout of the bank
The country made it through the finance
And a few years later Congress passed a law that changed the way banks are ready
The lot is called.
Frank
Dodd-Frank does have some good points
But when you get to the big question
Is Dodd-Frank going to protect us from having to bail out the banks again
Unfortunately no
What do you think the
The backers of Dodd-Frank are
Basing their beliefs
Hope and prayer
You really
Yes
They don't want to do anyting
Fundamentally restructure the financial system
And instead they will hope and pray
The next time will be different
So last month
Kashkari came out with his own plan
A plan he says cuz more to address the
The too-big-to-fail problem
Can anything we've done
So far
And he says the initial response has been promising
I was pleased that
Bernie Sanders came out
And supported us strongly with our process
A weave in the Wall Street Journal editorial page put a very nice editorial on our plan
If we can unite Bernie Sanders in the Wall Street Journal editorial page
I think we're on intellectually Solid Ground
Hello and welcome to Planet Money
I'm Jacob Goldstein Republicans have said for years that they want to change the way Banks or
Regulated and next year they're going to get their chance to do something
So on Today Show we talked about a big idea for how to change the rules for banks
It comes from the man who ran the last big bailout
And he says his proposed rules would make another big bailout much less likely
Before he went to Washington
Neel Kashkari worked at Goldman
And his worldview at the time was what you might expect from a young Goldman
Coming into treasury I consider myself to be a free market ideologue
I believe in markets I believe that
If you take a risk you get the benefits and you bear the Conte
Defenses
I assumed it
Successful people were successful because they were you know
More clever
So when you're bailing out the banks with hundreds of billions of dollars of
Taxpayer money
Are you thinking about that all men are you sort of
Icing reviews
Not in the moment in the moment all we were thinking about was how do we prevent
The Great Depression
Yeah
So cash car is trying to prevent the Great
And he becomes the face of the bailout
Of this program called tarp
Hino represents 700 billion taxpayer dollars given to Banks
At a moment when taxpayers are losing their houses
Getting fired from their jobs
Probably the toughest moment for me was when I had to go testify in front of Congress mr. catch Gary
We told you in there
That we wanted treasure to safeguard the tarp Money
From waste and abuse my longest hearing was almost six hours
I tell you mister cash carry
40 angry members of Congress both parties
Basically yelling at me the people that don't have saving
Are bailing out the very wealthiest in this country there's something inherently
We Wrong
In this picture
I felt like
Hey wait a second I am one of the people here
That's China
Stabilize the situation in and we need your help
And so it was very tough for me in the moment
By the spring of 2009 koshkar had given out the bailout money
Keep thinking that beating from Congress
And the country was still in bad shape
But by that point we had avoided another great
Kokkari decided to leave the treasury Department
And get as far away from Washington
I just needed to detox
My three years in Washington were grueling
I just wanted to get away from it as far as possible until I basically
Moved into the woods
Just work with my hands do something real something
Physical
To remove myself from Washington as far as I could
He lived outside Lake Tahoe
Denise big beautiful mountains
Got a couple dogs
Get off the shed
And now he did have time to rehearse
One of the things
I like to do when I was in the woods was chop wood
It was a great stress reliever and so trust me when I was sitting there chopping wood I was reliving
Some of my moments taking my beatings on Capitol Hill
And so part of the time was just reflecting on
Understanding their anger
Understanding you know could I have done something different could have done something better
But at the end of the day
What I realized when you violate the core beliefs of a society
It leads to great anger in that Society
And so as a society we have a core belief that's been passed down from generation to generation
In free market
If you take a rescue get the upside
You get the downside
But we violated that fundamentally when we bailed out the banks
Customer left the woods after a battle
He went back to work in finance for a few years
Then he ran for governor of California
As Republic
I came in second
There's no prize for coming up in an election
Not long after that he got a call from the Federal Reserve Bank
A Mini Apple
The Minneapolis fed
They were looking for someone to be their new present
He got the job started at the beginning of 2000
As part of the job
He's one of the dozen or so people who decide
What interest rates are going to be for the whole country
He's also in charge of about a thousand people who work at the
And a big part of his job is
Traveling around the Upper Midwest
Talking to people listening to them
And if he's doing this
People are telling him those bank bailouts that he led
They are still a big deal today people are still very upset about the bailouts
Here we are 8 years later
And I think a lot of the
Anger in the polarization that we see in the country today
Is directly tied back to the financial crisis and the feeling that a lot of people say hey this was not fair
Cuz, looks at Dodd-Frank
The law Congress passed in 2010
To fix the finance
If this sprawling complex law has all these different
Choices there are some useful parts
The Dodd-Frank
But overall he says it is not going to solve the bailout
Dodd-Frank has a lot of moving pieces
Is that
In theory if they all moved
Like an orchestra in perfect coordination
Perhaps it'll work
Having lived in the Frontline of a crisis
That's not how it really happened
As an example cuz Curry points to this document
What's that are required under Dodd-Frank
They're called
Living will
Yadira is
The force Banks to come up with a detailed plan for how they could be broken up if they got into
The trouble they're sort of like a user's manual
For breaking up a big bang
Well these living will these guides
Are some ten thousand pages long
Remember just for one bank for One Bank
Go back to China
This this
Decisions about is this Bank going to live or die would literally happen over the course of a weekend or people get like
What is a 10000 page book going to do for you and that's
Nothing
I need a philosophy class or an illegal class
And I'm sure it's a very interesting intellectual extra
In the middle of a crisis
From what I can tell it's totally useless
SoCal car thinks that Dodd-Frank with its
10000 page users manual for breaking up Banks
He thinks that is not going to end the bailout
And he decides his first big project with the Minneapolis fed will be
To come up with a plan to solve that problem
To finally make the banks
Crash proof
Guinness team they start having all these public meetings
They bring in Ben Bernanke
Professors Wall Street types
Some of those people said break up the banks
Some said don't do anything. Frank is just fine this is the right solution
And we wanted to learn from everybody that the only people who refuse to participate
Where the big bang stem cell
We didn't let that stop you invited
We're invited them every time
Basically through back channels told us
If we participate
We're going to be acknowledging that the too-big-to-fail problem still exist
So we're not going to participate
Really
Yes
Say more about
They want to pretend that the problem has been solved
Date the big Banks
Wanted
Pretend that they paid their debt back to society that they're more regulated now
They should be left alone and there's no more rest
And that medicine
Daughtry
Part of it is true they have paid back the literal death
The are more regulated now
But they're still too big.
And one of the things that came out
There was
Not you not unanimous consensus but there was wide content
All the experts Arcana Minneapolis Ted of one of those big Banks ran into trouble today
They would still get bailed out
They are still too big to fail
Now I'm just going to leave cuz try for just like a minute here
To talk about
About what that mean
You know like
Why don't people talk about other big companies like Google or Johnson & Johnson
Beer tube
Why is this just about
Any answer in a word
You deaf
You know we think of banks as lending out money
But thanks also borrow money they borrow tons and tons of money
They borrow from Ordinary People from businesses they borrow from other Banks
And when a bank gets into financial trouble
It can't pay back all that money that is borrowed
That is a problem for everybody who loaned that money to the trouble Bank
You know those people those businesses those Banks
Don't get their money back
So they can't pay their debt
In the case of a really big bang
Distance of Lake a lake
Chain reaction that goes through the entire
Give me a simple definition of too big
A simple definition of if a bank
Deutsche bank
Pepsi it could lead to a recession
It could have spillovers on the Main Street
Not simply onto
The customers of that
Soap cuz Curry solution to the too-big-to-fail problem is
Don't let the banks use so much borrowed money
Force them to rely Less on debt
Sports Infuse more of their own money
Money they haven't borrowed
Don't have to
That way if a bank gets into Financial
Will trouble you can take the losses out of its own money
And still have enough to pay back the people it borrowed
We decide the banks need much
Tire buffer
So that if they make mistakes
They have enough buffer to absorb those losses
If you go back to before the crisis and look at all the money
Thanks we're blending out or were using to invest
97% of that money with money they had borrow
Only 3% with their own money
Only 3% with their capital
It's the way you say that in the jar
Today
Banks are using more of their own money
It's about
7 /
Of the money
Kokkari says for the biggest banks
That number should be twice as high
Out of our plan
The rough measure is 15%
Will have to come out of their own money their Capital as we call it
The rest the other 85% the bank will still be able to borrow
There are other details in Kush cosplay
Banks that are still being too big to fail with see their Capital requirements go up even more update
Afterlife and more on their own money
They're also new rules for big finance companies that are not thanks
But forcing Banks use more of their own money
Increasing Capital requirements
15%
That is the essential first
And it sounds so simple
Eating sounds kind of like
Small or trivial
Buttkicker says it would make
A huge difference
If you go back
And imagine
The banks
You know how to infect
Made all these dumb Investments
But you don't give it out all these subprime mortgages
But instead of doing it with 3% Capital done it with 15%
How would the world have been different
Even if there was a bubble and it still popped
The banks would have been able to withstand it
They would not have had these massive failures
We would not have had to go to Congress to ask for a taxpayer bailout
And as a result
The recession we had
Would have been much much Milder
We had the deepest recession since the Great Depression
We would have had a normal recession
If this planet been in place
And just that's just they could still borrow 85% of the money they're lending at that just 15% would have salt all
Yes
So that is his plan
Now there's one last
Course
Which is
Is this going to happen in the world you know we know that Donald Trump and republicans in Congress have said they want to change the row
Rules for banks
What are the chances bill without something like cash cars
I think elements of it absolutely have a good chance I'm not talk to people on both sides of the aisle senators and representatives
Who are strongly in favor of something in this direction
In particular this idea of higher Capital requirements
Pretty popular with people who tend to be into free market
Pretend to be wary of a lot of kinds of Regulation
This is for a few reasons
For one thing
People recognize that banks are not operating in the free market now you know big banks have the implicit back
Also
Capital rules are relatively simple
You know they don't realize that much on the wisdom and discretion of regulator
And that appeals to people who are skeptical of regulators
There is one group
But pretty clearly does not like
RushCard
Big Bank
For this story I reached out to the two trade groups that represent the biggest banks in the country
Neither one of them got back to me
But when cashcars plan was released
A spokeswoman for one of the group
It's called the financial services
Sephora
Put up this
For those looking to accelerate economic growth and job creation
Tripling Bank capital
Already doubled from pre Christ
Will make it much harder to meet those goals
Packers playing what would hurt economic growth
Enter shikari
More or less agree
Will safety isn't free
If we raise Capital requirements
Make the banks
Find themselves with their own money instead of borrowed money
There will be an economic cost
Specifically
His rules would make it more expensive for ordinary people in
For businesses
To borrow money
Interest rates will be higher
Economic growth he says will be a little slower
So this is exactly like the risk
Terrorism
You and I and your listeners know
We cannot eliminate all risk
Terrorism
And we know that more safety means more law enforcement officers we have to pay for that does it cost to more safety
Choices Society weedicide
How much days do we want
And what we're going to pay for that safety
The same thing is true in
The banking system and financial stability
Kokkari looks at this trade-off
Higher interest rates lower economic growth
In exchange for a much lower risk of a financial
Crisis
And he says
It's worth it
Email us at Planet Money
Npr.org find us on Facebook or Twitter or show today was produced by Sally Helm special thing
Thanks to an automata John Cochran and Mark Calabria all of them talk to me at Great length about Kappa
Metal requirements
If you're looking for something else to listen to NPR has lots and lots of other shows
There's embedded that's a podcast with all this deep reporting there's code switch podcast about race in America
Hidden brain
Psychology is science podcast
Lots of good things listen to you can find them all on the NPR one app or at npr.org
Podcast
And one last thing if you are a fan of Planet Money
The best way to support us is donate to your local NPR station
That support helps Planet Money and all of the other NPR shows to keep going go to stations.
Dr. Org that station. Npr.org
Find your local station donate whatever you want and tell him we sent you
Your Phantom Planet Money
Thank you if you're doing this already thank you if you're going to do it in
In the future stations. Npr.org
I'm Jacob Goldstein