We're going to start Today Show by telling you the story of an innocent man
Amanda Mustafa Willis
The Story begins in the summer of 2010
Stop it was 24 years old
He's a tall guy
Wears his hair in laundry
And one day he was just walking down the street Newark New Jersey
Minding his own business
Eating a baguette
All of a sudden he's a cop car
Coming the wrong way down a one-way Street
The car stops right in front of him out, cop
Yeah they ran at me like I just like they just jumped out like that
Was swarming out like they knew they were looking for and you know I still did a whole bunch of other guys they just ran and
I just stood there they Place me on the rest
The cops found a gun at the scene
And they said the gun was mustafa's
Who's taking downtown thrown in jail
Charged with unlawful possession
And this is where your constitutional protections are supposed to kick in
The gun charge is just an accusation
Mustafa hadn't been convicted of anything
This is how the system is supposed to work
Mustafa is supposed to go home to his job at
And his family
And start Gathering some evidence
Prove that the gun
It's not his
All he has to do is post bail
And he's free to go
$50,000
Set by the judge and he can
Walk out of
He doesn't even have to come up with the whole amount right all he needs is
Is 10%
Cincinnati can pay the bail bondsman his feet 5000 bucks
And then he has to find somebody to guarantee
The rest
And he's free to go
Dumb stuff I didn't have five thousand bucks for the 10% fee
And his family didn't want to be on the hook
450 thousand
So he's facing
Roodle choice
He can either
Tough it out in jail
Or
Plead guilty to a crime that he didn't come
But I told the public defender listen man I didn't do it
He said well you're probably sitting in here pending grand jury man I said well
Hey I guess I'm have to do it tonight it ain't my weapon so there is no way I'm going
To plead guilty to a crime I didn't
So he just sits in jail
Hand weights
But he was locked up
Mustafa lost his job driving a delivery truck
He missed his cousin's funeral
All because he couldn't afford to pay
Finally after a couple months
The judge lowered mustafa's bail to $30,000
And his family feel
Once he was out
Mustafa could dig up evidence to fight the gun charge
It turns out
It was somebody on the Block who shot a video that
Mustafa says
Cruz the gun wasn't
The prosecutor the got hole today
Immediately she wanted to dismiss
This is what we stopped at
I've been saying all along
The charges were
But still
She had to spend
3 months in jail
For something he didn't do
And he ends up falling this bail bondsman
3000 bucks no refund that fee I was in dead from this and I had to pay
All this money back to a bail bondsman company for something that I didn't even did
And the case was still dismissed and I still have to pay
But not for nothing
Hell is supposed to help you
Who got charged with
The crime give them away to go home until their trial
But Mustafa Bale didn't help him get out of jail
Bill is what kept Him locked up
Hello and welcome to Planet Money
And I'm Keith Romer
Bails been around for stench
It's pretty much the law of the land in every state in this
It's supposed to protect the rights of defendants like Mustafa
You haven't been convicted of anything
And at the same time Bill is supposed to give quartz an extra guarantee
The people are actually going to show up
What is bail
Is broken
Today on the show
The New Jersey bail experience
Bunch of people who normally would not agree on anything
Got together
Change the bail system
Their solution
They threw it out
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Which come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities to help ensure a brighter future for America
Is children more information is available at aecf. Org
The first thing you need to understand about
Is that it is basically a workaround
For this fundamental problem in the
In a perfect world
If somebody got accused of a crime
The trial would happen
In a perfect world
His world that's perfect but has crime in
Hear me out
You'll get a trial the same day
If you're guilty you would go out to prison
If you're innocent you would go free
But in the real world
There is a lot of time
Between that moment when somebody's arrested
And when the jury figures out what the right ver
You can't just lock up everybody in
Because
You know that annoying thing about innocent
But if you just arrest them
Buddy and then immediately let him go
There's nothing necessarily to stop that guy from running off the bridge
Bell is a sort of compromise right
Will let you go until your trial
If you give us some money
$10,000 or $100,000 whatever it is
Show up at your trial
Get your money back
Not everybody thinks this is such a
A great sister
We talk to Roseanne Scotti
She is the sort of lawyer who looks at the criminal justice
The menses
Injured
She's the state director for the drug policy Alliance
And she thinks that this whole Bale compromise we've been talking about
Is pretty obviously unfair for one big reason
Which is it not everybody has the kind of money to be able to pay their bail understand is that
You know one of the things that most people who are in jail have in common is that they're poor
And so for these individuals having $1,000 bail or $2,500 bail
It might as well have been a million.
Spell
It's a pretty serious flaw it's built right into the
Bail is way harder on poor people
Okay so that's lawyer number one
Lawyer number 2 is guy named Elie honig
He's the Assistant Attorney General in New Jersey he's in charge of criminal prosecution to the entire state
And he had a completely different
Problem of the Bells
For him the real trouble with how the bail system treated rich
The right to bail was in mashed in the New Jersey state constitution we had a constitutional provision that said
Every criminal defendant is entitled to bail.
There's some people Ellie says who just should not be allowed to post bail at all
When you're looking at the leader of a racketeering Enterprise a Mafia Family a large drug trafficking organization
You could have
Kingpin
Somebody who's dangerous somebody you charged with murders
Now those folks can come up with money
Add the notion that those people could have could buy their way out of jail
It was really problematic
There's a reason Ellie gets so worked up about
He used to be a federal process
And the FEDS
Do not have a law
Like the one in New Jersey that says everybody my
Ellie's new boss is New Jersey Governor Chris Christie he used to be a federal prosecutor he's used to the federal system
In 2012
He proposed a constitutional amendment in New Jersey
Create something called preventive detention
Basically
Giving judges the right
Hold somebody without any bail whatsoever
New Jersey
They didn't go for
His plan did not make it out of the
To Roseanne Scotti the lawyer who's trying to make the whole system more fair
Chrissy's playing just look like a classic Law & Order me
Exactly what you did
Expect from a process
Security is now a politic
We thought that preventive detention alone
Would not
In any way solve the problem will probably make things worse because you would have preventive detention as a
New tool to keep people
I'm in jail
Jail by the way is where you wait for trial or
Serve short sentences
Prison is for people who are serving law
For folks like Scotty the problem was
But there were too many
Not tfue
To try to make a case
She got her hands on the jail population
Data for the entire
In looking at the population we found that 40% of the people who were in our jails were there
Solely
Because they lack the money for often nominal amount of money bail
Literally
Thousands of people
If you haven't been convicted
Of anything
Sitting in jail waiting for their trials
Just because they were poor
And that weight was not trivial
The average length of
The time for someone who had officially been indicted but hadn't yet gone to trial
What's 314 days
That's 10 months
Well people are sitting in there in jail for months and sometimes years
You know they're losing jobs are losing family they're using losing housing
All that time in jail is obviously bad in Nevada
No one wants to just sit in jail
But on top of that
You can start the change
Actual legal outcome
Weather people end up being found guilty or innocent
Prosecutors are not
They know that people just want to go
And they know that that give them a lot of
There is a phenomenon which I think you're not supposed to talk about publicly but I will
I called the time served and what that man is you would have defendants who would be held on low money Bells
Couldn't post it and they would sit there in
Jail for
346 months
And then when they came out to make the next appearance their lawyer would say
You been in 6 months
If you take this please you walk out today
And so you got that plate was an easy way to get please
How common a practice
I'm very,
I mean I think it happened probably in every County
Across the state so first
You get punished
Then
At the end of your jail time
Time to figure out whether or not you actually
It's a crazy system
Or you can just plead guilty even if
You're not since that means you get to go home now instead of waiting however many more months it isn't
Until your trial
This was such
A terribly
Broken
Unfair
Hauling system it was such
You know just bald
Naked Injustice and angrily corruption is a corrupt system
In 2013 Roseanne's organization put out
They basically said
This is how screwed up New Jersey's bails
Now I don't want to sound cynical but
Usually a report
Is where stories like this
Well-intentioned organization puts out
Report
Joe Rose does a heart-rending NPR story
Everyone shakes their heads
And they say Dad is
Right
But nothing really
But in New Jersey
The report copy I of
The Chief Justice of the New Jersey Supreme Court
He calls everyone into his ceremonial
The judges
The public defenders
The ACLU the prosecutor in LA
Ellie's in the room
Can you tell them
Fix it
Lot of lawyers
Lottery
We got some people say you got a lot of lawyers together they can't get nothing done I think this is it
An example to the contrary we got quite a bit
All those wires came up with a
To get rid of bail altogether
After the break
What was in that plan
How do you replace a system that we've been relying on 400
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Slack
Used by companies all over the world to get everything done
Where every part of work
From documents to decisions is stored archived and searchable in seconds
Slack where work happens find out why
Is slack.com
The most obvious proud
Problem with getting rid of bail
Is figuring out a new way of deciding who gets out before their trial and who stayed locked
Ellie says the old system was bad
But
It was simple under our old system the first thing a judge would do
Jack look at the charge against the defendant look at the chart and say
Okay his money bail is X
Post-it he walks out
If not he sits in jail until trial
Judges have a problem
If you take away the bail and bail chart
What are they supposed to do I don't know maybe use actual information about the real world
Oh
You mean like data
I mean
Big
Oh Big Daddy
Don't researchers have been trying to solve this problem
4 years
Before New Jersey start messing around.
Is that a team of researchers
I'm the Laura and John Arnold Foundation
They get the data of a million and a half people
Cases from all around the country
And they run that data through a bunch of
Statistical now
And they create something called
A risk
This algorithm basically predicts
How likely somebody is to fail to show up to court
And How likely they are to commit a new
At the risk assessment
Is automatically run
And it immediately spits out a result of 126
I on two different scales one day in love six being hot it's not even that,
The algorithm just looks at me
Does the defendant have
Prior conviction for a crime of violence
Has that conviction occurred within the past X number of years
You know has the defendant had
Failure to appear or bench warrant issued in Prior case
Interesting Lee one of the factors is how old the defendant
At the time the crime was committed
If your under the age of 23 says the algorithm
You're actually more likely to commit a new crime and somebody who is older
Not everyone thought this algorithm though it was such a good idea
The reactions to
To the risk assessment tool register
And I think it's fair to say that it first
There was
Pretty broad skepticism
First reason for the skepticism
The whole thing just seemed a little like sci-fi
I think of the movie Minority Report with Tom Cruise where
You know they feed the information to these cyborgs like beings who predict
Future
The precogs and that makes people uneasy precogs to the Future and they're never wrong ever get any false positives
Someone intends to kill a boss or his wife but they never go through with it how does prepass tell the difference
And it is weird right like the algorithm
Looks at all this information about you like have you committed a crime before did you skip your
Glass Court
And it says
Okay there's a
40% chance that
You are going to commit a new crime before your trial
So you have to stay locked
Because of something you haven't done something you might do in the future
And I just feel compelled to point out here that
Precogs
They weren't always right
That was the whole point of the movie
It's the future hasn't happened yet
But okay when you compare this system to one that depended on bail and bail charts
The pool looks pretty good
Because now people are being detained
Based on real in
About the risk
To the community
About the chances if they won't show up
There is a second concern
The people have about this risk assessment
When it comes down to buy us
People complain that the old system was biased against poor people and
Color
And what's to stop a new tool that's based on Big Data from being just as biased against
The same people
I asked Roseanne Scotti.
She's the lawyer who fought her entire life to make the justice
System more just
She loves the tool
She says the algorithm was specifically designed to avoid the bias
I think the key is what it doesn't look at you know some folks were concerned that it would look at
It would be a proxy for race and things like that which it is in it does not look at your ZIP code
Where you live or your neighborhood
Scotty says the algorithm is just as good at identifying risk
For rich people as it is for pork
Black people
As it is for white
Great idea right
Just get rid of bail
Replace it with the algorithm
No brainer
Everyone is going to love
Well
Everyone except the bail-in
Partly because
It's going to destroy their business entirely because it's going to destroy their butt
They lobbied superhard
Keep these changes
From becoming law
They warned about that crazy tsunami of crime that
Wipeout
The state got rid of
The fight
Pass this law was in
Hence we were still counting votes the morning of
It was really not
Hole in the last vote quiz called that we knew we had one
Roseanne and Elli and all the other reformers
They did win though
The old system
As of January 1st of this year
There is essentially
No more cash bail
Remember Mustafa from the beginning of the show
Under the old system
She got help
3 months in jail
On $50,000
If you want Mustafa to the new algorithm this is what you get
No prior offenses as an adult
No bench warrant
On the right side of 23 years old when he was arrested
She's A1
The lowest score on the wrist
That means under the new system
Mustafa almost
Certainly gets to go home
Instead of having to spend all that time locked up
Maybe he doesn't lose his job
Maybe he gets to go to his cousin's funeral
That's the new reality in New Jersey
You look at who's in jail and there is this real ship
More and more
The people who are locked up in jail
Are the ones who have been convicted of crimes
Instead of just accused of
Roseanne Scotti the lawyer who's been working for decades
Make the criminal just
System Warfare
She says this is easily one of the biggest achievements
Of her career
When we got the first statistics in February
That show that the jail population had been reduced
I'm by almost 30%
I cried
That was
An amazing moment to know that
You know you had done something
We're so many people were now going to go home to their families or communities
And to know that you would made a difference in
So many people would not
Face of Injustice
Was very profound
More and more in New Jersey punishment
After conviction not before it
We love to hear what you think about the show you can send it to email Planet Money at npr.org we're on face
Facebook Twitter all that stuff at Planet Money
Special things today to Jocelyn Simonson Shari's fan over Dean
Anne-Marie vanostran
Also Kurt Shaw and judge Glenn Grant
Today Show is produced by Nick fountain or chief justice is Alex goldmark or bail bondsman is Bryant
If you're looking for something else to listen to check out up first
NPR's Morning News podcast
African hair reporters like me
Get up very early to bring you the
You can find it at npr.org podcast or on the NPR one app
Angel Rose
And I'm Keith frommer
Thanks for listening