They say that money makes the world go round
Let's be more specific
It is actually the US
Dollar a French wine exporter
You need to lay in Oak for your wine barrels
You paying US dollar
If your Brazilian coffee maker
You want to sell your coffee to make drinks in Turkey
You get paid in US dollar
In every other country in the world every country that is not the United States there are basically two currencies
That matter
When to use at home with their friends
The Brazilian real to French Euro
In the one they used to trade
Which is the US dollar
And this is very
Very good
For the United States
Crucial really to our place in the world
Everyone wants our money
Everyone takes our money
And it's valuable to United States in all sorts of ways
What is when us businesses want to trade abroad
In u.s. dollars guess what
We already have
US dollar
And pretty complicated reasons it basically means
And when it comes to trade
The wind is at our back
But it wasn't always like this
There was a moment
Weirdest became the way we do business
The world got together in a rare display of
Global economic planning in decided
You need to cooperate and we need one currency
2 train
But exactly which currency would be was up for
Congrats to the fight between two men
1 British
One American
The Brittany probably heard up if you only know one Economist you know this guy's name
John Maynard
Kid is brilliant utopian dream of a common currency
The world give a guy the guy who ended up
Winning
Despite almost no one knows his name
Harry Dexter White
Somehow he managed to outwit John Maynard Keynes and put the US dollar at the center of
The world
Little monkeys playing
On the show how the US dollar one the story involves a hotel in the woods in New Hampshire
Broken world
Late night dancing in life
By the way we originally recorded this show in 2014
Support for this podcast and the following message come from
Rocket mortgage by Quicken Loan
When it comes to the big decision
Choosing a mortgage lender
It's important to work with someone you can trust
Who has your best interest in mind
With rocket mortgage
You'll get a transparent online process that gives you the confidence you need to make
Form decision
Skip the bank
Skip the waiting
And go completely online at quickenloans.com
Money Equal Housing lender license
In all 50
Nmls
Consumer access. Org
The song went down in the cool mountains of New Hampshire
We have near the Canadian border there is a giant hotel its Whitewood up on a ridge looks like a bee
Cruise ship
And it is still open today
Good evening welcome to the Mount Washington hotel in Bretton Woods of course we had to go see it
I was checking in
Yes I do want to go to the reception desk right to the left
The town of Bretton Woods would become famous for what happened in this hotel
Was the end of World War II and the great economic minds of the world came together to figure out what's next
The newsreels of the time make it seem like a very sober and serious endeavor
At Bretton Woods New Hampshire delegates from 44 Allied and Associates countries arrived for the opening up the United
Monetary and financial conference
On the newsreel you can see dozens of men in their wool suit
Hats
The flooding into the ornate lobby of the Mount Washington
These meetings are designed to promote trade in the postwar world
How to create a foundation for a lasting peace
The delegates here would create these big Global organizations that exist to this day
The international monetary fund the World Bank
But the newsreels lead out the real story this hotel was
Off the beaten path
It was up in the woods and it was pretty chaotic inside
A lot of the real action
To place in the basement of the hotel
In a bar called the Moon Room
The owner of the hotel
Strolls down a lot first night so that the the moon Raymond
Just have a look around our guide is Ed Conway he's a reporter for Sky News and he's the author of the new book The Summit
Representatives of almost every
Country in the world
That before him drinking away
Enjoying themselves
And I think that was the sense that never before had this
This corner of New Hampshire
Quite such a cosmopolitan
10 crowd
And the power of Ashen face
Still needed to be taken away
Because he was so shocked that the proceedings
I mean you sure about that more back in the day people used to faint
A lot more back then
When you picture Bretton Woods
Pictures
Cigar
Whiskey
High levels of emotion
There episodes where even the canoe
The strongest men that
Burst into tears because it was entirely stressful
They were working
18 hour days
And on top of this
Drinking
Copious amounts of olive
I rarely read
Anything economics or otherwise any account
That has
So much about the amount
Booze that way
Was conceived
Achieving a short period of time and that's
That was
One of the Fizz that that that
Canes have going into this
Casey said that
Avoid alcohol poisoning was going to session before the end of it
There was a reason for so much out
Because the problem they were dealing with was huge
They were trying to put
World.
Even before the war the global economic system was broken
Countries that mostly stop trading with
First there was The Depression countries put up these
High trade barriers
To try to protect their domestic industries
And there was a bigger problem
The world had gone off
The gold standard
How did the gold standard every country's currency was backed by a
Precise amount of gold
You knew exactly what a French franc
Gore US dollar was worth
Gold me trading easy gold standard countries could print money and they did
It and the value of their currencies went badly up and down it was hard to trade when you never knew when any given day with the
Other guys currency
She was work
So this was the issue they're trying to solve at Bretton Woods
How do we stabilize the world currency
So people can start trading at
They're basically two ideas
To deal with this
Two pretty different ideas
To buried
Different men
The first guy
John
Maynard
He ride the Bretton Woods has the biggest celebrity Economist in the world
He had a long a
This kind of stuff you'd watch the world screw up the economic recovery after World War 1
Helpguide Britain
Depression
The man is
Gregarious he's brilliant
Magnetic
He's the one that's in all the photos
He's the one that talks in the newsreel
Who was the man
New Hampshire
And I doubt
Eye doctor
We are bringing in
I love that the bigger thing we are bringing
Even today when people think about Bretton Woods conference they think about John Maynard
Hurricanes when you're at the hotel everyone knows exactly what room you stayed in
We went to it room 219
Still in use
Hi
Economics reporters and this is the room that
Famous economist slept in
John Maynard Keynes
We're just wondering if we could look at it
Sorry to bother you
It's a beautiful room fireplace big bedroom looks out on the mount
I'm so waiting here this is where John Maynard
Quintas wife
The Russian ballerina
You heard aunt
In Kansas
We know
That it was
Is this room because downstairs
Weber tried reset
Secretary morgenthau was trying to sleep
His wife Eleanor and they were getting mad
Kids ball the ballet X
Exercise is over
Bretton Woods was like a summer camp
You know if
If it's summer camp determine the
Future of the economy
It's like Dirty Dancing if John Maynard Keynes were there
Nobody puts the British pound sterling
In a corner
Because Kansas walking into this
Worried about Britain
Place in the world
When he grew up in Great Britain
It was a colonial power it ran the world economy
And now the best
He could hope for
Is a new currency system that does not put the American
He wants something where everyone's included
Frankly Britain is not bossed around by the night
Kinjaz rival is America
Harry Dexter White
He was actually the man running the conference and today everyone knows the room that
Teens
Stating no one has any idea where White
Stayed and even when he was alive he was an enigmatic
We did find a little archive
Representatives of 44 Nation
Bretton Woods
Steps to prevent a repetition
The currency chaos which is usually followed in the wake of War
Harry Dexter white was the assistant Secretary of the United States Treasury he's sort of wormed his way in there while
Kings was born an aristocrat
Wait was kind of from the wrong side of
The tracks
He had these immigrant parents his dad was
Hardware Peddler
We've worked his way up from a temp in the treasury
Department
And where teens was magnetic and Charming
What is about the most unlikeable character you will ever see even
His colleague
X4
Meyerism
Disability
Never had anything nice
Say about
No one
Says anything
Nice
About him
Bent deals with the
The Council on Foreign Relations and she wrote a book about the two guys it's called The Battle of Bretton Woods
He says Harry Dexter White had been fantasizing about this conference
4 years
Before it has
Who's time wait felt that America take its
Proper place as the leader of the world
While waiting caneswear maneuvering
Power behind the scenes
The rest of the representatives from all those other countries were having a final time arguing about global economics during the day
And partying late into
Like there was this one draft
Sherman went on to become a governor
Central Bank
He made sure every evening to the
Supply
15 minute recess
At 1:30 a.m.
So they were trying on
Pretty evening
Is 1:30 a.m.
To enable and I quote to enable the members of the drafting
Including the chairman
The joint pain
Downstairs in the moon room and observe the titillating gyration
The Peruvian bombshell
Does refreshed and reinvigorated we were able to carry on with renewed vigor
For another hour
Elmo
John Maynard Keynes allowed himself a little shampoo
But he was mostly careful
Get a bad heart
His wife was with him made him go to bed early
Harry Dexter white said he never slept for more than five
Hours cuz he was
Working all the
Can you put pretty hard during the day because
You had this plan that you come up with before the conference
The even now seems amazingly audacious
To get countries to trade with each
Kane said what the world needs
Is to create a new
International currency
To replace goal
Every Nation could still use their own money
Play inside the country
When a country traded it would use this
Brand new currency
The Brits even had a contest
To name it
Anniston Star
Flooding into
The treasury you had
Suggestions like
Traudel
Unity Bank
Bit
Hound all that
Kansas
Favorites was old
I don't know why
But he really likes old
By the time you get up on the line.
A few times but then later on because I ran a note to his church recall eggs
Do you think it's any use
Detroit
Unicorn
Honorary
It is across much more picturesque and romantic and would have the advantage
Supplying a suitable Emblem three institutions notepaper
Ferno tissue should the course of evolution
Have a bring them to
When kings actually drop his plan
There was no mention of eunuch
Can you call the new currency
Bancor
It's French
Bank gold
Bancorp
And it was such a king's like idea right that
Governments could come up with something that was actually better than gold
Can I do with the same
When you trade with another country you would use
Bancorp
And they would get Central Bank of the world
Keep track of all the Bancorp
And it would make sure that no one was
Exporting too much
Importing too much
It was utopian but it was also a little selfish for cane
Because his plan was to base this
Global bank in London
And the new currency was better than gold for
The British because
Great Britain has sold most of its gold to fund the war
He was in their best interest
To create something new
So that was the Keene proposal and Harry Dexter White had a different idea
His big plan for the world also involve the kind of
Universal currency
Not the Unicorn or the
Orb
He thought it should be the US
Dollar
Harry Dexter white knows that the best way to ensure this is here at Bretton Woods if you could somehow get all of the
The new international rules
These countries were going to sign on to
To include the dollar amount than every country
Cedar wood
Dollars
Harry Dexter white drove
Teens
Nuts
White was always try to control everything
Typical American
He was trying to slip the dollar in and all these complicated ways
It Conway read us a quote from John Mayer
This is intolerable he said
We could simply better break off negotiations
Terry Dexter wait replied to Keynes we will try to better create something your highness
Can under
This is how Harry Dexter white pulled off his little
He never openly suggested that World Trade should be based on the US dollar what he did instead was here in this UFO
Feminism in to all the
Numbers needed to talk about some form of international trade
He referred
2 gold convertible
As in every country on Earth should pick their currency to some unnamed
Gold convertible car
Of course what country
We had the gold the United States the US had 80% of the gold of the world
Ben Steele told this story
One of the committee
Indian
Got fat
Ben said that it was high time that the Americans explain
What a gold convertible
Currency was
At that point the British delegate
Skins was on
Dealing with the World Bank
Dennis rabe
Bella in Twilight
He thought that they would
Discussing a minor
Accounting issue and suggested that
Sake of clarity they might simply say
White thinking very much
And said that the matter would be referred to
Technical
Harry Dexter White had
The green light.
Heathen
Looking for Heatran this technical committee
The British suggestion that someone should just write in the word dollar he took that and ran with it
The technical committee stayed up all night going through the relevant documents
That night they went through the draft IMF articles of agreement
Ultimately 96
Pages
And changed every reference
Constable convertible currency
TUS
The British author that we talked to a Conway he doesn't think it was quite this since turquoise
This much of an ass
But the result was
All the documents governing the new monetary system had the term US dollar written right
Kings didn't even know it was all happening
He was stuck in these meetings about the World Bank
Making another part of the
Under the new agreement basically every country would have to pay their currency
To the US dollar like
Make sure that roughly is certain number of frames as always can equal the dollar
And in order to meet this work every country would have to keep a lot of dollars in their vaults
Sazitza
Reserved
That way if the currency went up or down because use dollars to stabilize it
And dollars would be the new anchor for
And these new organizations they created Bretton Woods the World Bank and the IMF
They too would use dollars
In order to become a member of the organization's you'd have to pay a fee in gold or
Gold convertible currency
Dollars dollars
Enemies organizations would lend those dollars to indebted countries at
Ben Steele says if you put a plaque up at Bretton Woods
This is what it would say
This is where
The US dollar was
Crown
The Supreme unrivaled
Currency for the world
But no one other than Harry Dexter white really knew this at the
Everyone is working such a Breakneck Pace no one had time to read over the documents as they're being written
John Maynard Keynes was struggling just to keep up
His health wasn't great
It was so overwhelming that it one point as Kansas rushing up the stairs to go to a meeting
He collapses
His wife tries to hush it up but word spreads
Quickly the Peeper say he had a heart attack
German newspapers ran obituaries
Keynes reportedly was pleased by what
But it's time to comfort it stretched on
3 weeks and there was a push to finish up
Food Supplies at the hotel we're running low final dinner at Bretton Woods
All they had was chicken and green bean
Appealing John Maynard Keynes managed to
To make it
To the podium and superstar that he was give an inspiring speech to send everyone home with
A Conway reeds
The Brotherhood of Man
Will it become
More than a phrase
List of presidents
My move to accept
Big words for a man who hadn't actually seen the final
They were presented with it for signature
As they were checking
There's no record of Harry Dexter White
Speaking at the final
Even though he had orchestrated everything
The IMF
The World Bank
Both headquartered in United States and
The thing he was really after the dollar would be the way the world did this
Tell me the Kingston read the fine print until he got back to Britain
Was reportedly Furious
That's specifically about the dollar provisions
What about all the little ways that he felt Britain had been
Screwed over by the emir
Who is laid out at Bretton Woods did work for a few decades
Everyone stayed Peg to the dollar the dollar stayed pick two goals
In 1971 famously that goes away but the Dollar by that point is entrenched
It's the way that countries trade with each other
For seventy years it's been the center of the global economy
Harry Dexter white the man behind it all
He didn't fare so well against
Will tell you more about that in just a moment support for Planet Money and the following message come from Squarespace
Squarespace offers a unique domain experience that's fully transparent and simple to setup
Make your next move by visiting squarespace.com to start your free trial
And use offer code Planet Money
For 10% off your first
Squarespace
Make your next move
Make your next website
Before we finish we need to have
A little serious talk about
Harry Dexter
Our hero the guy who sealed the dollars dominance in the world
Well
It turns out that is not how he is going to be room
Because he got in a little trouble
Harry Dexter White
Dexter white it turns out was Moonlighting as a Soviet spy
Passing some information to the Soviets
This apparently was not that uncommon at the time
The Soviets were our allies and historian Ben Steele told me
The treasury Department with literally littered with
The 1946 white defended himself in front of a congressional committee
He died of a heart attack the next day
A few years later there was a dramatic moment where is Soviet double agent
Pulled some microfilm out of a Halo
Pumpkin
That's where he'd hidden some evidence that white was indeed passing information to the Soviets
Steelbrick ounces
But no one claimed that anything he did at Bretton Woods with anything but
Patriotic
Although that is what Harry Dexter white is generally remembered for
Ild
Instead of the victory
For the US dollar
We'd love to hear what you thought of the show today you can email us Planet Money NPR.
When you're done listening check out some of the other fine podcast NPR is known for
You can search NPR on iTune And subscribe to the folks at the Mount Washington
Resort at Bretton Woods for giving us a tour historian McQueeney
And if you want to know more about the conference we can recommend these two bucks
The Battle of Bretton Woods by benn steil and the summit by
Today show with Bruce by Jess Jiang and the
A Robert Smith thanks for listening