Hey it's Robert Smith here like everyone else we have been watching this growing disaster
In Puerto Rico this week
Wait after the hurricane
And we noticed a particular issue
Coming up in the news
That we have covered before here at Planet Money
Tenchu is
The jump
The Jones Act is this old shipping law that says
Only American ships
Can carry cargo
Between American ports
Without having to pay Hefty penalties
And it makes it very difficult and expensive even in the best of time
To get anything to Puerto Rico
And in the wake of This Disaster Puerto Ricans and
Many members of Congress
Wanted this law
Suspended
Just like the law was suspended for Texas
Sanford Florida after their hurricane
Puerto Rico needs
Hey they need relief
From the rest of America
And I frankly don't care at this point whether it's an American ship
Orr Ford midship bringing aid from the rest of America
But
So far as of this recording on Wednesday
The Trump Administration has not suspended the Jones Act
Puerto Rico
The Department of Homeland Security says they're looking into it
But they're not sure if it would help it
Today we are going to replay our show about the history of the Jones Act
It is a fascinating episode
Podcast originally aired back in 2014
But as you will see it is totally relevant this way
I meant this.
In Midtown Manhattan
Over on the west side
Hudson River
We don't really think of the city as a
Or any more but it is for cruise ships
I'm looking up at
Two enormous boats there is biggest apartment building
It's windy and cold in these boats are going to The Bahamas
It was busy before out here but now it's quiet everyone is on board
The ship is getting ready to
All of a sudden
This family comes
Tearing around the corner Rowley suitcases are bouncing their backpacks all their stuff they're rushing to the Bone
Employee is yelling at them come on
And
He just misses
Begin playing
Is poor mom
Her teenage son slumped down into chairs
Soaking they all sit in this
Little terminal we can see the ship
Through the window getting ready to leave
Mom gets on the phone so it Norwegian
Cruise Lines it turned out there may be a way to catch the ship
Ward hit the Bahamas
Because it stops in Orlando for like
A day and maybe the family can get on a plane to Florida and
Save the bay
We're trying to
Contact Norwegian
Sea-Doo allow us to board in Orlando
On the phone she's taking notes
The news is good
Florida weekend
However
As long as you're boarding in the United States you will have to pay up to $300 per person extra the board
Did they tell you why
It's a booking what did she say was
And she said she falls under the Jones Act
So I don't know in your research look up the Java
She's written the words
Jones Act
On her Notepad
Underlined it and put a big box
Surrounded
We here at the light of mine did not have to look it up we've actually been wanting to do a story about the Jones act for a while it is one of those really old
Old laws
Pops up in all these strange
The Jones Act was written over 90 years ago
But today it's still governs just about anything that travels by ship
Bananas hair dryers gasoline
The core of the Jones act dictates that every time you want to send something from one us
Port to another Us Port
The cargo must travel on a ship
Built
In America
Staffed by Americans
Owned by America
The cruise ship
Play call Chris
Was foreign-owned
This is a pretty unusual
If you want to send a bunch of oranges by truck from
From Florida to Baltimore
Doesn't matter who made the truck
The truck can be made in
Germany
You want to fly some
Computer chips across the country it's fine if the planes in Airbus made
But you want to send cargo by ship
Bishop
Made in America
Hello and welcome to Planet Money on David kestenbaum
Damn sure we dig into the words that the woman's scribbled on her Notepad
The Jones Act
We look at all it's strange
Consequences that play out
All these crazy ways in this country
Cruise ship passengers cattle farmers
Guy in New Jersey who really really needed some salt
Mountain
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their own website
Lights using customizable layouts
And features including e-commerce functionality
3 + mobile app
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online presence
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
The Jones act it actually popped up in my life
Recently I live in New Jersey
And a couple weeks ago in the middle of like 5 snowstorm
We found out that the state had run out of salt
It run out of rock salt to melt the snow and
Which is a really dangerous thing to run out
There was a fairly simple solution New Jersey did not salt but
The state of Maine had a Giant Mountain of
And as it turned out right in a port in Maine
There was this really big ship
That seems like it could carry all the salt to New Jersey
I mean it was just like Serendipity here's this
Ship that's big enough to take 40000 tons of salt
It's on its way to Newark anyway this is perfect
That's Jody one of the guys in charge of getting salt furniture
He had one problem though you can almost
Extreme writing it on his Notepad
And drawing a big box around it
The Joneses
That ship was not made in America not flying in America
Can flag
The captain is it turns out
Atlas Greek
Jones act says you cannot use that kind of ship to carry anything from one Us Port to another
The workaround was quite painful
The US doesn't deal that many ships anymore especially
Pair to other country
And the only Jones Act
It's compliant ship was this little barge so you really wanted to see this little barge
One morning you
Amen
I'm here I'm looking at it dude
Enzo you recorded your best
Weather reporter on the sea
I'm standing here at Birth 13 looking at this bar
It's filled with rock salt
Salt to melt the snow
They just came down here from Searsport Maine to New Jersey
We have to ask reporter Jay field in Maine to do his part at the mountain of Saw
MJ Field in
Searsport Maine
Where the rock salt
Just came from
What's funny is that
There is still a huge
Pile
Assault in front of me
The barge was not nearly big enough to carry that mountain of salt
At least not in one trip
Pet store
Okay so this is the plan they're going to drop off the rock salt here and then this barge is going to turn
Turn around and
Head back up to you
Annies
Going to pick up another fraction
Of this
Large pile and head back down to you
And it's going to drop off the rocks out here in New Jersey and
Turn around and head back to you
And pick a contact has been around for over 90 years
And at this point coming up with workarounds
Has become a sort of art form in the maritime
Hawaii is really the
New Jersey you can drive their senses
Hawaii
There is no train that goes to Hawaii
If you want to bring stuff from Hawaii back to the rest of the United States
It's probably going to have to go
Go by boat
I talk to this one cattle ranch
In Hawaii is named is Pono Von Holt
He raises cows
In Hawaii
But the market for burgers is
Across the ocean on the mainland
The Jones act says
He needs to use a Merrick
And the thing about just made in America Creed by Americans is that
They are expensive
Are expensive to manufacture an expensive
Tony told me for a while he was using foreign ships
And what you would do if you would send the cows to
Canada
And then they travel by land over the Border back to the United
States
That didn't work out
These days he's doing something that sounds crazier witches
She said some of the cows to the mainland by airplane
Deceive money
Send the cows when they're little and don't waste them
People like cows are also subject to these old laws that was the problem
I'm at the family ran into
The cruise ship
It is illegal for a foreign-owned cruise ship
To pick you up in one Us Port and drop you in another
Which is why the family had to pay a fine for getting on Orlando
The cruise ship at the end of the trip was going to drop every
Economy
Maybe yes they are not fans of
The Jones Act
When cows
Why is the sign that there's some real distortion
In the maritimes
We called up Joseph stiglitz used to chair the Council of
Economic advisers under
President Clinton
He said the council took a look at the Jones act and said
Okay look it does save some jobs in the shipping industry
But it also makes all kinds of other thing
Things cost way more than they
How much are we paying
To save those
They did the math
So we did this calculation
And ask
The question how much did
A shop cost
What was the answer
It was something like a quarter million dollars
Job
What do you make of that number
Will that it was a very inefficient way of job creation
Stupid
Is there any economic argument in favor of the Jones
Other than an argument of certain special interest now
Send out
Do you know any Economist who like the Joneses
No I don't
I've never met one
According to an official report around this time
By the United States International Trade Commission the Jones Act was costing the country over 1 billion dollars
Why does this thing
Good question
Love you answer after the break
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial and when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Why does this thing exist
The basic idea of requiring that
Cargo travel on domestic ship
It's goes back
But this current Incarnation the Jones Act
Is from 1920
World War 1 hitches
Extended during the War the government geared up to build ship after ship after ship
But then the war ended and the ships were still being built
Cheers up Maritime historian
Jeff bolster
There's this glut
Of ships I mean
It does still being turned out now in the shipyards owned by the emergency
Ashley Corporation
Okay
As a result of that
Anybody could see that
In the short run ship
The building was going to become depressed
Because the government had stepped in to build all of this tonnage to win the war
Also means that the market will be saturated with tonnage for a while
So that shipbuilding yards would simply
Not everything to do
And you know where there are a lot of shipyards
Seattle wash
Michigan State
And Washington State happen to have a very
Powerful sin
Head of the
Senator Wesley
Elgin
Senator Jones
Concerned about his hometown shipbuilding industry
Which is Congress to pass
The Merchant Marine Act of 1920
The Jones Act
And it received some news coverage at the time here's a snippet from a new story
Written by 1gj Underwood
You do it
Indirectly it affects the
Warren transportation of
Every product of American industry upon it is also dependent the industrial expansion of the
Ignition
Literally thousands of different interest will be affected by it
That ran in the Seattle Times
Home-state which over the years clearly benefited from the hard worker
In fact
The barge with the salt in New Jersey that was made in Seattle
Jones Act
The other argument for the Jones Act made at the
What time was military readiness
Basically
If we get another War
We're going to need American ships
An American to know how to say
This is the argument that the shipbuilding industry
Makes today
There are certain things in this country that are
Record to protecting the country
Shipbuilding industrial base
Just happens to be one of the
Derrell Connor is a lobbyist with the American Maritime partnership he represents us shipbuilders you a shipbuilding come
Japanese
In Wartime he says you need people who know how to make ships
Warships that were used
To fight battles
And you also need ordinary cargo ships first
Supplies
Food and medical stuff
Almost 90%
Of the Cargoes carried in the Iraq and Afghanistan Wars
Or carried on US flag ships
Are those weren't Jones accept
A lot of the seafarers
Served on those vessels
Served in the Jones act trade so the Jones Act
Play Vital role in
Ensuring we have those Seafarer
So what you saying here is okay it is true even with the Jones act we don't have enough ships
Pet Supply are true
What time
We have to use alipay
Quadriceps but the Jones act gives us some
And it gives us strength
The Economist Joseph stiglitz says
He heard those arguments when he was in the Clinton administration
No one on the Council of economic advisers found them very convincing
We are dependent on foreign countries for a lot of stuff
Well food
Steal clothes
We need use the ports of our allies in Europe
Why do we have to insist on American-made ships
America
Crew flying under Americans
I think the view the console's economic advisor
We should get rid of it
We're not
Yo where they wear a visor
So we can just say what are the economic cost
And is there a plausible argument that there are any benefits
Metro with a cost
And we could not see any
And then what happened next
But I can
Nothing
It's a political non-starter it's been that way for 90 years when US military teams up
Up with unions and shipbuilders
That is a lot of lobbying power
Put that up against tomorrow
Who missed the cruise ship a guy who needs a bunch of salt a Hawaiian cattle rancher
They don't stand a chance
Academics have a fancy term for this the Jones act has
Concentrated benefits
And a few scars
A small group of people benefit a lot
The cost gets passed
The rest of us in little
The only way the Jones Act is going to change is it the cars become more obvious and more powerful
People start yelling about getting rid of it
That could happen
Because of the way that our economy is changing
At this moment
Bus as you probably know was in the middle of an oil boom
Thanks to fracking
Do you want to send oil from Houston to Philadelphia by sea
You have to use a Jones act ship
And there are not that many of those
So the price is going up and US oil producers are starting to get really mad
What about this restriction
But for the moment
Got to play by the rules laid out in the Joneses
If you're sending something from one Us Port to another
Got to be on the ship built in America
American Crew
Buying in America
Just reminder this show was from
2014 but this debate about the Jones Act is going on
Even to this day
We would love to hear what you thought of the show you can email is Planet Money at npr.org
You can also hit us up on Facebook or Twitter
Today show with originally produced by Jess Jiang
Rerun was produced by Elizabeth kulak
And our intern Alice weld
I'm Robert Smith
Thanks for listening
I'm Scott detrow there's so much
Political news to follow these days but you don't have to
To keep up with all of it
You just have to keep up with us
On the NPR politics
But it seems NPR political reporters and editors we record two episodes a week
And sometimes more when the big news happened
Find NPR politics podcast on the NPR one app or wherever you get your pot