Text Jacob Goldstein Today Show is a rerun from mm
I recently came across this article from 1980
It's an article about this new possibly dangerous thing that is about to transform the world
And if you read the title of this episode you already know it is
Is but let me just read you a little excerpt
In the article because
Because I love
Pier
When you quote boot
The program into your personal computer
You see little more than some letters running across the top of the display screen
And some numbers running down the side
The quote cursor
A tiny block of light on the screen that acts like a kind of
Electronic pencil
Can be moved
Parentheses by touch of the computer keyboard
Do any cell in order to
To quote input
Numbers or
It's funny when we were putting this together I thought it was going to be totally obvious what that's describing but like actually if you don't know already
What the shows about it's kind of confusing like you might not guess that in fact
That article is about
The spreadsheet
The thing we think of today as Microsoft Excel
Miracle talk about how this weird thing is going to totally transform the
But it also have this warning
Quote the spreadsheet is a tool
And it is also a world
Reality by the numbers
The article spent a long time served Welling
What does it mean
When people start to think that numbers are reality
What will it do to the world
Hello and welcome to Planet Money on David kestenbaum
And you're Jacob Goldstein
Right it's 30 years after that article was written and we know the answers to those big questions
Today on the show
Reality by the number
What the spreadsheet has done
Support for this NPR Podcast and the following message come from indochino
They're making it easy to get a
Perfectly tailored suit at an incredible price
You can choose from hundreds of top quality fabrics and personalize your suit just the way you want it whether it's
For work a wedding or another special occasion
This week Planet Money listeners can get any premium indochino suit for 50% off with Risha
Just go to indochino.com and answer code Planet at checkout
There was a time when a spreadsheet was an actual sheet
11 inch by 17 inch sheet of paper
I talked to a guy named Alan Schneider he was an accountant in the seventies and he said you spreadsheets all the time
Sometimes one sheet was not enough
So we would have to take the sheets together
So did you have like a really big death
Like how do you even manage something
Yeah I mean it it it took the greater part of a of a full-sized s
What is Frenchy does it gives you
Detailed way to look at
So if you're in the chocolate business you would put into a
Spreadsheet
The cost of cocoa the cross
Sugary
Your taxes
Rent
Salaries all that stuff
Versailles
And then
You would do a whole lot of arithmetic and math and at the end of that you would have a pretty detailed picture of your business and how it was doing
If you run in the Chocolate Factory you get your accountant to do this
Are you go to a guy like Alan Schneider and say
Put together the spreadsheet
Allen and his whole team
Dates ripe
Once he built this thing it would have hundreds of different numbers run
And then
You never failed
After I only put this whole thing together the guy who ran the factory would come to Allen and say
What if I spend just a little more on coke
What will that mean for my business
That little question
It would mean a lot of work for
You take out that large eraser and start erasing each each of the excuse to take out of couch
You later then you have to re-add
And then
Cross
Add each column
And then you'd have different tax results have a different accrual result you have it
Different cash results every column had to be changed
I'm headed to take a day like a really boring
Day to run all the numbers and that was just
When the client asked for one tiny little
It's the late seventies and not far from where Allen is working
There's a guy named
Dan Brickley
Sitting in class bored out of his
He the Guy Sebastian
The future inventor of the spreadsheet is at this moment in our story sitting in class
He's at Harvard Business School
In this big lecture hall
All end up at the front of the room there's a professor
Up on the Blackboard doing some spreadsheet type math
Brooklyn has this date
I thought that you're always kind of silly that we're writing on this Blackboard what I can't have only we had a Blackboard what I could erase
Racing number and write a new number in
And everything would recalculate
This was a timely moment to have this daydream
The Apple II computer had come out it's a computer finally that you could have at home you can put on your desk
But of course at the time most people thought of it Paisley as a
Port Authority
Like a video game
Brooklyn look the Apple II and thanks you know this could be my magic black boy
He thought I could do it
Accountants we're doing on paper with their giant spread
Erasers
So he wrote a little program for the Apple 2 he needed some way right for the user
To move around the
Screen to enter in the number
Numbers and there was no mouse
But the computer had those video game control
Tell use those
The Apple II had paddles
For playing pong
Where you could turn it left and right it was a dial
And there's a button
Push to fire you know
And the point you would turn
The dial back and forth
And the cursor would move from cell to cell
And then you push the fire button and then we go up and down as you turned it so you could actually
Kind of like a real Poor Man's Mouse
I love this early version
Spreadsheet with a video game
Yes I know trickling said in addition to pong you can also a little later play Space Invaders
But the downside is that actually from moving around a spreadsheet
How does a huge pain in the ass is going with the arrow key
But anyways his program the thing you built it actually worked
You could run this thing and it would actually calculate Go Bump Bump
You put a number in
And hit return and everything would recalculate
How you could watch it you can watch the number Shane bump bump bump it may sound
I had a real prototype
I love it I love it it makes sound the audio spreadsheet
Actually that was another problem in the early Miley said that took up a crazy amount of memory to make the sound to kill the sound
That's what happens next
Nixie hooks up with his old friends this guy named Bob Frankston also compute
A guy today noted the co-creator of this
That's it right as early partner
In frankston and bricklin they start
Giving demos around town basically showing this Prototype 2 guys like Alan Schneider to accountants
With big erasers
Outsiders on early demo
Did not get it
Do you remember the first time you saw an electronic spreadsheet
Yes
But I didn't understand what was going on in the demo like
The guy's hands are like moving really fast
The keyboard the cursor just moving around in the guy says it's be really great for your checkbook
I don't get it
The time it finally made sense to him
Is Winnie actually saw it being used in the real world and he was like oh
It's a spreadsheet the giant piece of paper but it's inside the computer that this happened for him not long after that
Super confusing demo it was at a local computer shop
The owner was testing out this program for dandruff
And he was using it for the story
Put in you know the basic stuff of his own businesses
Payroll
Renton supplies his
Sales
Any show this to Allen
I needed the key thing
Is it down
I'm going to change
1 number
And suddenly boom everything recalculate automatic
Once he did that they're mean it was like an immediate reaction to me I mean I just
Rush
I was flabbergasted this is amazing
This is amazing
And it was
L&M should get his hands on one of those early tests
And then not long after that when the spreadsheet software actually hit the market and sold under the name visit health
Allen became the first registered on
Ellen Snyder
Spreadsheet user number one
For anybody working with spreadsheets manly accountants I mean
This was like a godsend I mean you wouldn't have to
Do this grocery work over and over and over again
It was a godsend but it was also a threat because the computer could do in seconds
What used to take someone
An entire day today
Tactical
Computer was better
Computer didn't make
In that magazine article from 1984 that we talked about at the top of the show
There's this amazing little anecdote about an accountant
Right after the electronic spreadsheet
What happened was
This account he got a rush job
From what it is clean
Does the kind of thing that in the old paper Universe would it take in a couple days
This guy has this new electronic spreadsheets
He plugs in the numbers does the work in just a couple hours
Then what he does
You just wait
Let something sit on his desk for liked
FedEx is it back to the car
The client was like wow you did it so fast
It's a funny story that clearly like that was not going to be a long
If it only takes a couple hours to
To do a spreadsheet
And your billing by the hour
You're going to make less money
Right you're going to need fewer workers
Given need to get rid of
And in fact if you look at the numbers
Filipino national jobs data from the government you can see this
The number of accounting clerks and bookkeepers we're the kind of people actually do a lot of this math
Those numbers have fallen
Over the past several
Why do people got replaced by software
Dan bricklin says he thought about this when he was in betting the spread
That was an issue I had to come to terms with
Technology is a double-edged sword
I produced
General-purpose tools
They can be used
For all sorts of things
Summer good
And summer bad
Some will cause people to lose their job
Sun makes new jobs
Possible
He was right
The spreadsheet both killed jobs
And it created
While the number of bookkeepers and accounting clerks spell
The electronic spreadsheet actually meant more jobs
For regular account
A few numbers
Since 1980 right around the time the electronic spreadsheet came out
I wasn't bookkeeping and accounting clerk jobs
Have gone away
But
600000 accounting jobs have been added
What happened is that accounting basically became cheap
And sometimes when something gets cheaper
People buy a lot more of that
Allen said clients bought more accounting
They called up and asked him to run more numbers
You can play the what if
Game
You know
What if I did this instead of that
If you're that person who owned the Chocolate Factory you can now call Alan Schneider and ask
All kinds of questions what if we made our
Chocolate bars a little bit smaller
Which made of
Set larger
Can we give everyone a raise this
What if we started selling a lot of chocolate bars to
To China all these questions
Normally it would have been very expensive
Brown decided to do it out of
On paper but now it was much cheaper
Some people ask a lot more
This account
Software Dan bricklin wrote
It becomes the killer app
For the Apple II
It's the $99 piece
Software
That makes people go out and buy the $2,000 computer
And this actually went Way Beyond.
Italy
Doctors
Do better calculations
It's for anesthesiology before the
They're open heart surgery
I it was
Used bikes
A company to decide where to put
Which slot machines
On the casino floor
My mother who is a principal to Middle School
She was using the spreadsheet to be able to
How to keep track of who's in what class and all
And it wasn't to a couple years later she said
Do you know that
I can do calculations
I gave you the most
My mom
All right so there's all these examples of people sort of using spreadsheets to tweak what they do
But on top of that there is one in
Brooklyn didn't meant
Which branches were just a Monumental deal where spreadsheets became the center of the world
We'll have that and more in just a minute
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Slack
Used by companies all over the world to get everything done
Where every part of work from documents to decisions is stored archived and searchable in seconds
Slack
Where work happens find out why it's slack.com
Spreadsheets transformed one industry more than any other
The industry is finance
Richard's basically gave birth to Modern wall
To this world we have today
Wall Street became obsessed with this
What if
What if we got a slightly better
What if he two companies merge
What if we structured the deal this way
Wall Street is a place where
You know you change what number you move
Pennies around in the
Spreadsheet
Change something at
Like a third decimal place
Suddenly at the bottom of the spreadsheet the last number
Like a million dollars
And so because of this the spreadsheet becomes the language of Wall Street
Today the spreadsheet is the way
People in finance talk to
It's the way they decide
Is this a billion dollar deal is this a 950 million dollar deal should we do this deal at all
Wall Street is basically a bunch of Excel spreadsheets
Flying back in
Which explains the existence
Abyss
As the sound of nerds clapping give it up for model off 2014 basically like
The World Championships of building Financial models in Excel
It's an annual contest in people actually
Flying from around the world
To see who's best
Making financial model
The big prize comes with a little acceljoe
And so it's with great pleasure
I'm going to be presenting this trophy
With this golden keyboard
And this golden keyboard
Does not have an F1
David I'll be honest with you I did not get this joke had to Google it
Here it is the F1 key
It watches The Help menu
Christie's got done
Excel humor
This year's winner
For first prize
Of the 2014 Financial modeling
World Championship
Diarmuid early
Did people make fun of you for women
Not actually as much as I expected they would
Please do the best out of it
You're the King of the Nerds
I said that as a nerd who is not the King of the Nerds to be clear
Literally on walls
At the Deutsche Bank office down by the New York Stock
I just sit in there a couple weeks
If you've ever wondered what it looks like inside a big
Fancy office tower on Wall Street
You can just picture
Row after row
Office after office
Of people staring
In this building right now
How many people do you think are using Sprite
At this exact moment
Probably thousands of people at this exact moment using spreadsheet
In this building
Hear the mouse is for the slow for the week
If you're a badass like your
You use the keyboard
I mean I probably know
Several hundred Excel keyboard shortcuts
He has his favorite is
Alt
ESV
Press alt then you press
The evening
Ask them the V
That is for paste Special Value
Got ahold
8 years
Remove duplicates
No try that's text to columns old am is remove duplicates
There's even this story and okay
It's probably in apocrypha
Sorry but still it's a story about Ben 10
Going around and cutting the mouse chords of the rookie Stacy using the mouse in Excel
That spreadsheet article from 1984 basically predicted all of this
Here is one line
Quote a virtual Cult of the spreadsheet has form
Complete with gurus
And initiates detailed lore
Arcane rituals
And an unshakable belief that the way the world Works can be embodied in
Rose
And columns
Numbers
The article where is in
What feels like this very early computer are away about that unshakable belief
Physical
People tend to forget that even the most elegantly crafted spreadsheet is House of Cards ready to collapse
Set the first erroneous assumption
Turns out that was actually a fine worried
You may remember the London whale story from
4 years ago about a Trader at
P Morgan
Who lost the bank
6 billion dollars
That was partly spreadsheet error
I talked about the London whale with Matt Levine recent
Matt used to work at Goldman Sachs
Now he writes for Bloomberg
Eva Mendes
Somebody working with the London whale
Build a spreadsheet to estimate
How risky the group
Trades work
But there was a problem
There is one cell where
He had to divide by the average of 2 numbers and he divided by the
Some of us do not
Forgot to put in the two at the
Until that showed
Half as much risk
Has actually had
Everett
This is the thing about spreadsheet
They look really good
No matter what
Someone brings a spreadsheet
MTG it looks so precise it
Numbers in
In Grafton
Pretty fonts
Feels like it's telling you exactly how the work
It feels like
Golf Course
It's just a model
Pacific Gas
Chicken a problem with spreadsheets
Because they're very easy
How to use
So
It's really easy for like a 22 year old right out of
College to use Excel
I want to build something that really looks like
Coca-Cola model
But living says you don't most people are
Smart enough to understand the difference
Between the model and reality because most of the time people get the math right so unbalanced
Frenchie's wouldn't actually a good tool that give us more information to help people make better decisions
It's a win it's a plus net plus
Spreadsheets have left us
In a different world though it's a world where we are cons
Actually asking why
And by we I mean
Not just account
People on Wall Street length
All of us
Me more than I would like
Gone Way Beyond spreadsheet
It's like what if I flew Thursday instead of Friday
What if I took
Instead of Route 280
Where's traffic
What if I stop
Exercising what if I eat more
Those last couple kinds of questions about like what am I eat differently what if I exercise more or less
You're matharu
Excel champ he can actually answer the
You because
Of course
You built this bridge
Tracking all this personal information so he
With a spreadsheet on this data everyday and now he's got all these pretty grass
His weight and is exercise
Totally normal
Totally normal right leg doesn't even seem weird anymore
The article that inspired the show
It was called a spreadsheet way of knowledge
Megan and Steven Levy
I will have a link to it on the Block
Npr.org
Email us at Planet Money at npr.org or find us on Facebook or Twitter
Today Show was originally produced by Jess Jiang
Today's version was produced by Elizabeth kulas
If you're looking for something else to listen to and you have kids and you want to listen with your kids
Pride wow in the world podcast from NPR for kids
You can find it on the NPR one app at NPR. Org / podcast
Or wherever you get your pot
I'm Jacob Goldstein
Navigate confession
Kellogg have a spreadsheet right track my electricity meter
Bathing a difference it makes if I take a shower
I'm not single cuz like ouu suspension
So cheap it's painful
Knowledge is not always good
How much is a shower
Good morning winter
Bath and the kids last night was like a bucket