Hey it's Jacob Goldstein
Just a couple quick notes before we start the show
Note number one if you are planning on making a
Charitable donation before the end of the
Please consider supporting planet
You can do that fight donating to your local member NPR station
At
Donate. Npr.org
Slash
Planet Money
We really appreciate it it means a lot
So again you can do that at donate
. npr.org
Slash Planet Money
And if you want to
Shout Your Love of
Planet Money and public radio from the social media rooftops
There is a hashtag you can use it is
Why Public Radio
No number two
Today shows a rerun it originally ran into
And there is an update
Robertson freeway
I am wearing red
A red Overcoat
A black belt address to say
What am I wearing
You are also where I can say attitude never thought I'd see me neither but we are surrounded by
1000 people
Dressed as him
I'm trying to get my belt to work you haven't felt trouble
Yes
Hamster go to hood over it
Long-sleeve some embroidering here is beautiful gold embroidery
Oh yeah
This is SantaCon New York City 2015
It's an annual tradition you just pacetti the trunk in the city
Dance a little yeah I'm not here to do that
No you're here answer for a nerdier
Economic reason
But I'm here for what I think it's actually a more exciting reason
There is a international dispute going on right now over this
Visa question
What
Is
Fantasy
What
Is
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Jacob Goldstein but I'm staying
Oh my God your face
I will never do that again and I'm Robert Smith
Today Show is about a lawsuit over a Santa
It's it's part of this whole universe of hidden fights the shape almost everything we buy
The Santas are going to the bar right here and
I'm going to go join
I'm going to go back to the office and do the story have fun man
Support for this podcast and the following message come from twit.tv
Play This Week in Tech podcast
Every week award-winning Tech expert Leo LaPorte and top Tech pundits cover the latest news
Innovations
Privacy gear plus the pitfalls and mistakes in the world.
Your first podcast of the week
Is the last word in cell
Join the Lively Roundtable discussion and subscribe to This Week in Tech podcast on your favorite podcast
Or at twit.tv
Hohhot seems a little
What do you think of this sooner good fits good look for me
I mean
Stacy Robert disappeared into SantaCon has not been
Different since you're graciously greater cause to share with me what you think
You look very sharp
Thank you
Let me tell you about the city
Okay yes tell me about the
I got it at a place called Ruby's it's a costume shop out on Monday
So you got some Santa costumes you. That's what we're going this is Mark David she runs
Ruby's
Are you got surface Star Wars
Touch me not to stop
Star Wars
I stake out these are like really spectacular Star Wars cousin like there's this
Spiegel Darth Vader suit that look like it was actually what
V Darth Vader
Right around the corner from Darth Vader
Where we stand now what are we looking
Are you looking at Santa Claus costumes
A lot of
A lot of different Daredevil qualities in price level
Despite / Santa suits
Please out on this wall right in front of us on this wall of Santa suit
It's right in front of
And it's a fight over
Most of the suits are made of
Mercy's mark
Imports them and of course
When he supports them
Just bring through customs
And depending on what he's important sometimes he has to pay a tariff
Whether he has to pay
He that tariff
And how much she has to
Hey is laid out in the
Harmonized tariff schedule
The United States
It is 99 chapters long and it was
Tens of thousands
But it doesn't list ever
There is no line item that says costumes or Santa
So there has been this long-running
Where do costumes belong
In the Tariff
Mark beige hasn't answered today
Question is
There is a section of
Section 9505 to be precise
That is perfect for centos
It's called festive articles
I printed out the page here you could just read some of the stuff in
Okay
Christmas ornaments of glass
Of wood
Nativity scenes and figures thereof
Artificial Christmas tree
It's not just Christmas stuff this section also include stuff like party favors in
Fetty and
Streamers and all this
The festive articles
Come into the country Duty
Free notepad
Mark Imports costume so of course duty free is good for you
And according to the government some Santa suit like the cheap ones in front of us in the store
There is no question they are Festival
Made out of a yellow flannel type of fabric
Sabacc close with velcro
This one is effective article
But then Mark showed me a difference
Display a nicer
What has a b c d
The pants look like
That made out of a plush material
You have a jacket witch
Has a white fur cuffs
White fur, it's got this nice lining Customs looks at this nice or Santa suit
Incest mark
This is not a festive article
You made this so nice
This is
And clothes go under a different part of the
Import this suit
Mark has to pee
32% tax
The jacket
Add a 29.2% tax
There's a pair of gloves in a white Santa gloves those committed
10%
And Mark thinks this whole thing is ridiculous
It's a Santa suit
Clearly it's a festival
This is the epitome of a
About Festival
Let me know when else
Oberlin Christmas are you going to wear this
It's nice I can put on this red bird jacket it's a little bit chilly today that's like the perfect weight
50 degree weather
Right but what is the last time you went around dresses and Santa Claus
Calling the Santa suit clothes Mark says makes it a lot more
Kim and
Yeah of course so if you were going to pay
Pay $80 for a Santa suit for instance
10 or $15 of that $80
Would be
There is a lawsuit over this
Scituate lawsuit over the question of what is
Fantasy
The person bringing the lawsuit is him it's markbass the suit
Is Ruby Acosta
Company versus the United
Basically Mark playing government come on
Santa suit is a festival
But when I ask Mark about the lawsuit
He doesn't want to get into the detail
He actually points for this guy in a suit and tie
Who's been following us around the Sun
His lawyer
Let's jump Essex
Custom special power attorney for many many years
How did we get to a world where a lawyer needs to be present to have a conversation about a saint
And I don't even
I actually called up an expert
Douglas Irwin an economic historian
And he says
The story starts
With the beginning of the US government
Actually the second piece of legislation passed by Congress in 1789
Was
Pure Flix
Second second law Congress ever pass
Ever yes
Will the Tariff
On what
Xiamen
Everything he was in his office when I
As far as I can tell over the phone
Every copy of the
Tariff code ever written kind of
At hand
He said back then back in 1789 the Tariff code was simple imagine that's cuz they just weren't
That many different things in the world to know like everything is so much
That much
Stuff
From that first
He said it's just three pages
Distilled spirits
Molasses malt
Cast iron all-weather Candor Todd
All clothing ready-made
7/2 percenter there it is
Someone says there's a simple reason that this was the second law Congress ever passed
The government needed the money
There was no income
But there were Ships. Coming into Boston to New York
Charleston and soap the government looks at those ships and that all right
You want to come here
Give us some money
That first tariff
Didn't mention Fest
Articles
There wasn't much of a fee
Best of article industry
So Douglas Irwin started going back through old tariff
Looking for when festive articles first
Eventually you got to 1920
Oh
I think festooning is best of articles
Okay here's what it says
Doll heads toy marbles toy games toy containers toy favors toy souvenirs
Garland festooning
And Christmas tree decorations
Ferrets
That's what becomes Festival
The Tariff code is getting bigger and bigger and more and more
Complex goes from that original three pages to if I've got it right I think now it's
681 page
But in all those pages there is no line for costume
Now you have these
Two categories
Is it costumes make
If they're closed then you have to pay it
If their festive articles
Notary
And as a result of this
You have this endless fight that is been going on
And who was on the other side of this fight who in the world was arguing that
Santa suit
And costumes
Foreclosed the answer is pretty pretty fun pretty delightful
Back in the 90s on the other side was
Markbass
What's Ruby's cast
He has completely switched
And you were on the other side then right absolutely
You know it's
Good to be flexible
You're going to get right it's like you didn't seem ashamed of it at all he's clearly not like a philosopher of the Tariff
Cody's not arguing over the metaphysics of Santa suits he's a businessman
I'm back in the 90s when he was on the opposite side
He was in a pretty different business at that time he was not importing costumes you were making them here in the United States
We worry domestic
100% domestic manufacturer and of course if your domestic manufacturer if you're making
Costumes
Country you want
Importers that have to pay a tariff
Mixer costumes
So that is why markbass was on the other side and government has also
Flip-flopped on this
Miss you a lot in the last few years a lot of the costumes that you
Categorized
As festive articles
The government has changed its mind
No actually those are closed
I also asked Customs about this I said you know why why are you making
Change
They didn't comment but Mark's lawyer the guy who was with us he used to work for
And he said you know
Customs
Mostly just a bunch of
People trying their best to put things into categories
Ways to follow the rules
The categories aren't all we clear the people working at Customs change and new people come in and they say you know
That's an issue that we used to color festival I think it's actually
And here is why the story is about more than
Santa suits
Santa suits are one little fight in one little corner of the Tariff code and the Tariff code is
Is Giant
These thousands of pages long.
Tons of complicated rules
And where there are complicated rules
Money at stake
There are people for hire who will help you figure out
How to play the game
It's called tariff engineer
Harris engineering yes that's a real thing though it's a huge that you are a tariff engineer
Sure absolutely
This is Michael Cohen engineer and trade lawyer
Terpening is not just suing the government arguing that something should be in one category or another
It's figuring out how companies can build things different
How they can actually tweak their products
So that they get a better deal in the Tariff
There's one really famous example where a Shoe Company Incorporated some kind of fabric into the sole of a shoe
Just move the shoe from one tariff category
There's a similar
Kind of trick with costumes and that is
You use a velcro closure instead of the zipper or button
It's less likely to
Carter's clothing more likely to be gay
Effective article duty free
In fact a festive articles have been a big deal in his world it's not just costume
I mean there been cases for years over you know if you have a
A mug or a placemat or tablecloth
And you put a jack o'lantern or Santa Claus on it does it count as a mug replacement or tablecloth or is it effective article
And there are other things that you don't
One client came to Michael Cohn and wanted to import this big industrial machine
Emcon figured out if you split up the machine in
Two separate parts base we take it apart
Live It Up
Two separate shipment
Right on two separate ships
Come pick it up at the Tariff would be a lot
Lower
There was a lot cheaper
More than paid for myself
This is totally legal and it is a totally logical response to a tariff code that has
Tens of thousands
Line items
And different tariffs for each one
Yeah but obviously it doesn't
Feel good right it's logical but if you step back
You don't look at the work
Cone is doing here it's not doing anything for economy right I mean
We want to company spending time and money figuring out what is the best machine we can buy
Or what does costume actually be better with a zipper or with belt
Pinboys justify
Figure out how to minimize your toy
Sheriff Billy doesn't make our products better
I know you don't want to ask
Would we be better off if your job went away
That the very painful answer is
For real you really think that
Sure
Most Economist agree that the benefits of tariffs and trade barriers are greatly outweighed by
The cost of them
And most tariffs have
Either going to be completely orgone way.
Back in the 1960s for example the average tariff on the stuff we imported was around 7%
Today it's one and a half for
But the Tariff code is still a big complicate
Poker rules
And the case over the Santa suit
Rubie's Costume Company versus United States
It is likely to go to trial neck
You can picture in your mind a courtroom
And there's John desik rubies
Customs lawyer
Pointing at a red plush Santa suit and
Telling the judge
Festive article
And then another lawyer a government lawyer pointing at the same suit and saying
Swearing
Close
The lawsuit is over a particular suit it's over the premier plush nine-piece sand
Which of course I tried to buy when I went out to meet Market Ruby's of course
I think this is
Say my name
62 right they didn't have the nine PC
In stock so I got this
Basically the same thing
Don't have the beard or the wig or the plush Red Sea
But you know the jacket
The Hat the pants
Come on
Okay so that is where we left it back in 2015
And now it is 2017 and earlier this year
In fact on Halloween
The judge in the case
Handed down a ruling
We will have that ruling for you
Intimate
This message comes from NPR sponsor squares
Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their own website
Using customizable layout
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online press
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Here is what the United States Court of
International Trade rule this year in Rubie's Costume Company versus
Quotes
A relatively well made
Durable dry clean only Santa Claus cast
Constitutes fancy dress
Of textile
And is therefore excluded
From classification as effective article
Translation
A fancy Santa suit
Is closed
And you have to pay tax to bring it into the
This week I called up Glenn Ripa he is one of the lawyers
Working for rubies on
And he said
They are appealing
And their core theory of the Santos
Has not
It's not something you would wear somewhere it's it's a festive article that identifies the Christmas season in
When you would not wear it any other time other than Chris
The difference between the distinction what we're really looking at in terms of this fancy dress with talking about
A well-made say gypsy costume that you know Stevie Nicks the lead singer
Caring Concepts yourself
With that
You know it's got like a style of clothes
I'm going to wear a Santa costume cuz this is so you know
Chic
Is there a 21st
Century pop icon who exemplifies the line between
Fancy dress and festive articles
We need to know
Email us
Planet Money at npr.org
Or tweet us at Planet Money
Car show today was produced by Jess Jiang
The rerun was produced by Alice Wilder
Also just hit you up for money one more time
If you want to make a donation to support Planet Money you can do that by donating to your local member station
Donate. Npr.org
Splash Planet
Special things today to Ron cerini of sorini samet
And Associates
And Agustin Santiago of the National Council
Textile organizations
They both spoke to me for the show but didn't
Make it in
Also that band that was playing at SantaCon that we heard in the background they're playing on the sidewalk today
Rate
They are the Sunny Side social
I'm Jacob Goldstein Thanks For Less