Hate just a quick note
The show originally ran in
In mm
Sam Cohen is a business
He's in a business that until recently I didn't even know existed
So recently I asked Sam if you show me how is business works
And he said sure
Where we going right now
I will go to Toys R Us
What are you hoping to find a Toys R Us
Anything we can make money off
A picture of the coins business works like
He walks in the big box
Stores like Toys R Us
You get the car
People stuff off the shelves then goes up to the cash register and pays for
Just like any other shopper
Penny Drive
Stop back to his warehouse and sells it for a profit on Amazon
And this is not just some guy clipping coupons as a hobby
Sam is a warehouse about a dozen full-time
Employees
This is a multi-million dollar business for sale
Ancelotti
This is a thing people do now
Buying stuff at stores and selling it for more online
It's called Retail Arbitrage
You can buy special software to do it there are online tutorials that
Did you how
How is this even a job
Much less an industry
I mean how is it possible that you can build a business around buying stuff off the shelves at retail stores and
Cylinder online for a little more
Actually he's selling it for a lot more
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Today on the show Sam Cohen is a middleman
And he's in the middle of War
On one side you got the giant big box chain
On the other you got Amazon and in between them
There is Sam Cohen driving around New Jersey in a beat-up
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Is reimagining banking
I offering account
With no fees or minute
Animals that can be open from anywhere
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
It seems like Sam's business
And this whole industry
Should not exist
Because there is this thing called The Law of one price
Which is the diff everything is working the way it should
The same product should have the same price everywhere
Like the Nerf football should cost
The same at Target
As it as a Toys R Us
As it does on Amazon
Because if it's cheaper in one of those places
People will figure that out and they will just go buy it where it's cheaper and in fact the law of One Price means
Sam Cohen has a hard job
Most of the stuff at Toys R Us
Does sell for about the
The same price on Amazon
But he also knows
But there's got to be something
Something right here in the
Store that he can make money
He doesn't know what it is but he knows he can find
We start walking through the aisles
Need Sam and one of Sam's employees a guy named Jay Friday
Sam tells me why one thing after another is not going to
Graco car seat is probably too big
Really big things cost alot to ship so to pay for shipping and still make a profit same would have to charge a ton
Around the corner and starts looking upwards
Something that's a staple item like Scrabble
I don't think you'll ever make money on B
Because it's a commodity item
It's too popular
Everybody sells
And all those sellers compare
Keep with each other
Keep lowering the price and lowering the price
There's no way I'm going to be able to make a profit selling
Scrapple
But on the shelf right below
Scrabble there all these
Special Scrabble Deluxe Scrabble super Scrabble Frozen Scrabble
In the Disney movie
Princess Anna and Queen Elsa right there on the box
Games like frozen Scrabble Sam says can be right in this
Spot where they're not so popular that everybody's going to sell them and there's no profit
But they're popular enough that he can be pretty confident that he'll be able to sell it
Today though
Even Frozen Scrabble stays on the Shelf
He's not going to buy it
Because this is the wrong season
Scrabble for board games and general
They're basically holiday
Right now they're not on sale here and it's April so that doesn't make sense
Finally around the corner from the board games sammc something promising so this is interesting this is a babe
Babies R Us 800
Baby wipes
The wipes are on this
Play one of those great big things right out in the middle of the aisle
They're selling for $16.99 17 bucks
I have myself I have two young daughters
I made price-conscious Chopper and I feel like I have some insight on the baby wipes
Soap I tell Sam
Baby stuff I know how much baby stuff cost
I'm not great it's not great
800 wipes it's a valuable I mean by it if you want I don't think
I think there's a lot of margin in Florida I think you're wrong
Sam and Jay take out their phones and get to work
So we scan the UPC barcode over here and right there on his phone he can see all the time for
About how the babies are us
800 wipes
Value box
Is selling on Amazon
Basically you see what category it's in you see the size
Tear that a Tim
You see the sales rank as compared to all the other items in the category
You see how many people are selling
And crucially you see the price that is
Selling for
So this box of wipes are selling for $17 here at Toys R Us
And on Amazon this is currently selling for $46
Wait a minute
People are paying what did you say for 800 baby wipes
It's a lie
Even when you add up all the Sam's Club
Shipping the wife's to Amazon's Warehouse
He's got to pay to Amazon
The list of wipes on their site
The other fees he's got to pay to Amazon to ship the wipes again out to customers
You know what all that Sam figures he can make
$14
Profit on every box
For some reason
The law of one
That wall that says
The same thing should have basically the same price everywhere
Does not seem to apply to this value box of 800 Babies R Us baby
It seems right if you actually can unload all these
Is wipes at that 40
$6 price
He'll make money
Sojay Friday grabs every box of wipes in the display
And puts them in
Before we check out Sam spots a couple others
Thanks where he thinks he can make a profit
This is called a Little Tikes
Big Tigger
Sandbox take wraps all the sand boxes and put them in the car and one last thing it's a slumber bag
Like a sleeping bag for inside the rebels with a bonus backpack
Jay puts all the sleeping bags in the
Which is now overflowing with sandboxes
Sleeping bags
Princess this is actually just a small QuikTrip
Usually they spend half a day and still up a bunch of cards
Are cashiers seems completely unfazed by this card.
Sam pays for the stuff and we take it out to the car
Few weeks later I called sandbox
To see how he did with all this
Because so far
He's bought this
But yeah
Sold it hasn't made any profit
And you know
Nobody wants to buy from him on Amazon
You can be kind of screw
But before we get to how Sam did
Let's look at the Toys R Us side of the
This equation
Because if there is all this extra money
To be made on baby wipes
Why doesn't Toys R Us just raised the price in the store
Or why doesn't it just cut out the middleman why doesn't play the rest just sell baby wipes on Amazon itself
Yeah you know I reached out
Toys R Us to ask them these very Quest
And
And I also reached out to Walmart and
Targets
Add to Kohl's in the Home Depot
And not one of them
Agreed to be interviewed for this story
But there is this one story that's been out there in the news that suggest retailers
Our kind of
Freaking out about
Businesses likes
The story involves Target and a clothing designer Lilly Pulitzer
I learned about the story from Ina Steiner
Who writes a newsletter for people who sell stuff on
Target to the deal a special deal they collaborated with a designer called Lilly Pulitzer
To come up with 250 different items that were special made
For Target
Sundresses
Flip flops
Resort Wear
Very distinctive
Does that mean palm trees I don't know what the hell
Very colorful pastels
Do people love this stuff they love Lilly Pulitzer clothes and Target sold out almost immediately
Except for a lot of people buying the stuff on the
Dresses and flip flops
We're not actually people were planning on wearing them
Almost immediately.
These products showed up online marked way up
And consumers got really really upset
Speak out cry on social media one lady said on Twitter that there is a
Special place in hell
If you bought Willie today to sell it on eBay
It's a real anger that is so anger
Those flip-flops are cute you know
People like
Target of course is on Twitter targeted people who pay attention
The stuff
And they
Responded
And it wasn't just about Lilliput
Ina Steiner
Started hearing stories and this is just in the past few weeks now
Now she started hearing stories
About resellers about people like Sam
Who went
Target filled up their cart
Took me or whatever
20 identical boxes of Lego sets or something up to the
Couch and when they get to the cash register their told
Nope sorry we are not going to sell the
20 boxes of whatever
You can't find
I reached out to
To Target and they said they had
Change their policy
You had some particular language
From Target
That you had
Posted from a statement they sent you happen to have that can you just
Repeat that
I'm hanging on
In order to ensure we have the inventory of products
To meet our guests needs
We recently established a new policy that Reserves
Target the right to prohibit purchases
Teresa sellers
So they're saying explicitly
If you want to come in and buy all our fancy new dresses so you can sell them online
We can say no
Exact
The big fear for Target here
Is that one day soon there will be no reason
At all to go to
Kohl's or Walmart
Or anywhere
Because you can just go to Amazon and buy it online
You cannot underestimate the impact
Set Amazon
Is having on retail
Amazon is
Is 800 pound gorilla that every retailer has nightmares about
Spear of Amazon explains a lot
It's a big part of the reason that Sam Collins business is whole Retail Arbitrage world
Exist
Is Toys R Us wanted to
They could cut Sam Cohen and everyone liked him out of the loop in Tyler
Toys R Us could just sell its own wipes on
But the last
Finger Toys R Us One
Is for Shoppers to think of Amazon as the place where they can buy everything
Toys R Us does Dallas White song
They just don't sell them on Amazon
And that
Create an opportunity for
We will hear how Sam did with those wipes
After the break
Support for this podcast and the following message come from discover
Get a credit score card with your FICO credit score which is used by 90% of Copland
It's available to everyone for free
Even if you're not a cuss
Learn more at discover.com
Credit score
Limitations apply
Sam
I think about you and how you doing
Awesome awesome
Okay so a couple weeks ago we went to Toys R Us we bought some
Stuff and I want to see how how you're doing
Quick refresher payment butt wipes
He bought sleeping bags
And he bought sand
We started
Of course with the white
I believe we have one or two left most of them of already full
And what did you sell them for
We saw them for $45
So I was definitely wrong about the baby wipes I want to say that
On the record
You know I made a really basic kind of rookie mistake
And thinking about the
Because you don't hear something that I know
You can almost always find a
A giant box of wine
Around 12
17 x 20 box
And that's what I always
He's bought I didn't care what kind I was just bought the
The cheap wipes
Yeah I think you shop really differently from the way that I stopped Jacob because
When I was looking through my Amazon purchases
I noticed that I hadn't actually really
Prices that much internal sump when I looked at them but I just wanted
Everything now
I bought whatever could get shipped to be the fastest
And I think a lot of people work that way especially when it comes to baby
Used because people get very emotional about baby
He's probably also dogs
I would imagine
I'm so if a product is for a baby
And it's a particular kind of wipe that the baby seems to
Like
Or respond well to you
I feel like people go out of their way to continue to buy that burn
When you need wipes
You definitely need
White
You know
You can go on Amazon use your 1-click Amazon Prime
2-day delivery
You want your Babies R Us 800 wipes
You pay your 45 bucks
And you get it
.
And it turns out plenty of people
In fact have done that
Sam was right
About the white
And he was right about the Star Wars Rebels sleeping bag suit currently those are cell
Pretty well but the last item the little digger sandbox has Little Tikes
Spectators
The Little Tikes big digger sandbox has
Those are actually becoming kind of a problem for sale
Can't wait so he bought those at Toys R Us
And he was hoping to sell them on Amazon for 75
$5
Promise after
He bought them
The price started
Default
Middleman was getting undercut by other middlemen
He was getting out Middleman
Just this morning I looked at the pricing
And as of this morning
That sandbox was selling on Amazon for $39 at 99
The exact same price
Sam it paid at Toys R Us
At least
As of this moment
For the Little Tikes
Big digger sandbox the law of One Price seems to hold true
If you got any hot Retail Arbitrage tips
Or just want to tell us what you thought of the show you can email us at Planet Money at npr.org
You can also follow us on Twitter we are at Planet Money
Special thanks to Chris Green a Retail Arbitrage expert who actually talk to me from a Walmart that he
It arrived at
Where he was doing Retail Arbitrage
Chris I'm sorry you didn't make it into the show
Today Show was produced by Nick Fountain and Nidia Wilson the rerun was produced by our internet word psychiatry
I'm Jacob.
And I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Thanks for listening