Stacy
Roberts it's launch day
Launch date for the Planet Money satellite
October 31st
Halloween today the Planet Money satellite
Pod1
Is going to space
So course the first thing we have to do
Is join the lunch crew at a restaurant for pancakes
Because
Tradition
Of course
If you have like a
Montana tonight we're doing pancakes now
Because that's bad
Part of how we get ready for lunch
If we didn't eat pancakes one time and the rocket
I didn't make it to orbit
So we don't mess around with that anymore
The pancake God are not to be trifled with
Get an omelet
Loser Rock
So that was Mike safian and Chester Gilmore from the company Planet you may remember them they helped build the Planet Money satellite
And they make sure it got here to the coast of California for the
The planet pay for the loss
They're sending up a bunch of small satellites on the same Rock
It is hours
And so they get the ceremonial place of honor
Chester you always wears a bow tie
He will be sitting in mission control as the spacecraft on Mission director
Highest authority over lunch
What's that mean you can at the last minute just say like
Proponents say no go and everything stops
He is so
Proud of this title and everyone else at the table just serve rolls their eyes
Assembly company they work for is one of those laid back
Silicon Valley firms but on lunch date there is military
Precision
Definite IR
All of the team leaders sit in a room with headsets staring at screen
Working commands in the radio
Waiting for Chester
So if things go perfectly all I'll say is go a couple times
SMD go for launch
SM Diego Forlan
There's a lot riding on that command
This is the first time planet has filled
Any Tire rocket
With just their satellite
They're taking all of the risk improving a small satellite
They can have a rocket just like the big kit
People care about the future of the space business
Are watching this lunch
And then there's us
Anti-satellite pod1
A podcast launching a satellite into space
And this is our one shot
We're not going to get a second
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Stacey Vanek Smith Robert Smith we have a checklist ready for system check
Ready rocket status
Safety team
Not sure what you do but are you ready
Chester do the honors
Let's do it
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online
I'm presence and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layouts along with features including e-commerce functionality
And mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial and when you're ready to launch use the offer
Code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
I want to rock it
You need to think
What three things continue the rocket
But you also need a vast empty space with no key
People from miles around
And
An incredible technical infrastructure of radar and Communications equipment
That is why we are launching from a military
Rebase just north of Santa Barbara California Vandenberg Air Force
Which at least on this morning
Might be the most deserted place on the California coast
I'm lunch date the military
Clears the bee
Keep boats away stop planes from flying overhead this is a completely commercial
Orbital ATK built the rocket
Planet Rent to the space on board for it's sad
Because it's on a military base there are military personnel involved in every pot
Part of the lunch and Military protocols and Military traditions
I didn't personally I just wanted to see a little satellite Pod 1 blast into space
But there are things that we had to do first
We had paperwork
And earrings
We had to run around the
First stop is a bland little office building called
J spot
Like Spock Spock
Like SPOC operations center
This are the air traffic control of space we have to check in with them
To make sure I satellite isn't being launched
Smack-dab into
Another satellite
Boom
Lieutenant Colonel Mia Walsh and Diana mckissick are already on the case
And they're probably doing a check right about now
To make sure that our rocket will make it through and nothing but clear space ahead frac
So we will track it all the way from when it launches as it goes through its different trajectories as it reaches its final orbit and then we'll monitor
Entire time
Facebook the keeper of a list that I've never heard of before
The space catalog which is exactly as amazing as it sounds
The space catalog
Is a list
Everything
Anyone has ever said
Indoor
The catalog
Self includes every single object man-made objects and Sputnik
However currently we only track
23000 objects that are currently still on Orbitz
The wage a spark traxys 23,000 objects
Is amazing
They have radar and telescopes and they actually
Watch
The object moving through the sky they can spot something the size
Bubba softball
Hurtling around the planet
And over the life of our satellite if our little pod one gets within a kilometer of anything else so
Potentially might
Crash into some
He will send us
Email we have an email system
It says watch out Planet Money
You might want to move your stuff
These emails are a free service of the US government don't say they never gave you anything
They send them to satellite owners all around the world anytime a satellite comes close to another satellite
Which is amazing
But they're trying to avoid an incident like the one that happened
In 2009
The infamous iridium Cosmo
Dead Russian satellite called
Cosmos 2251
Collided with a communication satellite iridium
And we don't know
Animated sound
We don't know what
The Collision look like
But Jace box.
On the screen
And from their point of view was frightening
Self
Are radars actually
He said
It should be one object here and one object there but now it appears to be hundreds of different objects
No
Knowing that collided it created hundreds of little bit of salad overall created to thaw
Thousand pieces of debris
I'm which we still all track
To this day
Every little bit
Yeah well I mean some of the Kaden re-entered but we stay together as a little cloud or no
They disperse
When they come close to other satellites
So we're constantly tracking these p
Pieces of debris and now they're actually causing
Close approaches with other satellites
Still
What 8 years later
This is bring up my holes
Space junk
Anxiety problem
Yes it would be terrible for pod1 to go down in infamy by smashing into the International Space Station
Always bad
But Jesus tells us that space is
Much bigger than
We can conceive
There are tens of thousands of objects up there
But there's still plenty of room
We have a clear path
Fingers crossed
Alright G-spot
Check
We have one more stop before lunch
It is a golf course owned by the military base
Really use it for that anymore
They use it for
Parties like this one
There's one of those big white wedding tents all set up there is
Taco truck
And a selfie station took a picture with a model of satellite and
Cosby dead
There's a nice
Buffet
This is where the folks from planet are Partners satellite company have come to set up shop
We had to confirm all the scheduling pieces of today with planet
Did you technically own our satellite
Should be upfront about that and they will be doing all of the maneuvering
One spot one in space nobody wants to let a podcast Sierra satellite
Not a chance
We don't even
Really know what's going to happen to
The co-founder and the CEO of the company will Marshall was there
We asked him to
Where where exactly was a rocket go
Hopefully many app
Maybe I'll be over there around the Earth
You to make it simple for the podcast
We appreciate it
Will is an old hand at this this is planet
20th launch
Live roughly 200 small satellites in orbit
So many satellites
Did they usually
Do not have a party
Do not have a buffet or selfie stick
But this was so close to their San Francisco office that they brought in everything
In about an hour will is going to give a short speech
Just like at a wedding
But unlike at a wedding hopefully
Will is going to
Warren every
The day could end in failure and disaster
Loans can get delayed
That happens quite a lot so
Bed with us if it gets the light on
Occasionally they blow up
And that's why I'm fortunate crossing over the work that we put into a satellite
You said it to the party because we have to be remember that if that happens we go
Backup
Next
Launches coming up in
Hemomancer
Fat people fat butt
Generally it's
It's okay just about having fun and watching the launch it is successful it'll be a really really fun
I have to say I've been impressed with how comfortable will
And everyone at planet is weak
Is concept
Back in the old days when NASA was the only game in town I mean obviously
Nobody wanted to take a risk
Human beings on board billion-dollar spacecraft
But the advantage of the
Small sad
Annies cheaper Rockets
Is elasticsearch
Lower
You can pick more chance
You can try new technology
You can invent things faster
If something goes wrong
Will says
You just try again
And we ask Will how we will know if
This risk if
Pod1 made it to space for Mission with six
And he gives us these magic words to listen for on Milwaukee
Normally we pop the champagne when we get confirmation that they were successfully injected into orbit
And what did he say if it's successful
Set Side light decoration
Satellite separation
Then pod1 will be
Free of the Earth
Friv the rocket
And finally out on phone
We would love to stay and hear will speech
And possibly
Check out the taco truck because
Very delicious
But we were offered a chance to get closer to the wall
Fatso
This is it
It's finally happening
A rocket is going up
In about 90 minutes
We drove to the meeting spot on the other side of the Earth
We got on this old school bus and were driven miles into the most remote part of the base 2
A little patch of dirt and scrub brush
We can't see The Rock
But they tell us it is just over there
They're just a few people here Military Officers photographers people from the rocket company orbital ATK
People like John steinmeier
Lily Pad is evacuated
For at least a couple of miles away where
Probably about as close as anyone
At the site here
You may remember John from our Ferry
First episode
He stands next to us helping us decode the launch chatter
It comes over this walkie-talkie
Nominal is this our favorite word
Everything is okay
Nominal
I think the most sort of
Call if there's a word that is calmer than nominal I've never heard it
So someone says it is non nominal
Probably off nominal
Domino's
Previous run
Centos not not nominal
It's all funny jokes until we get within a couple minutes
Then
Suddenly
Everyone gets
Really quiet
They said T-minus
I don't know why it was whisper
We're Whispering because it's very serious and tents at the launch site and we're getting all of this
Very critical information at a very low volume over like a circus 1985 walkie-talkie
Did you give us one final
They said listen do not be alarmed
When you don't
Cure
The rocket
The rocket is apparently so far away that we will see it first
And then the sound will wash over
I have this weird feeling
Like when you're in a chair and you tilt back
And you're
About to fall and you pull yourself back its fat level
Of like beer
In anticipation
And I find myself hoping that whatever happened to the space business
This moment
Never changes
Or hear anything
What was surprised
Oh my gosh
Or shoot up so fast you can barely stare at it oh my God
It's hard to look at it
Vehicle
Successful
This was a really strange moment when I was standing there holding a bottle of champagne
We just watched a rocket
Shoot into the sky it seems like everything has gone well but
Everyone is standing around walkie-talkie
Staring at the ground
Looking like
Jet Li series
Because it's not about the rocket everyone's waiting to hear about the
Satellite that's what everyone here paid for
It's the most crucial part of the mission
Everybody's waiting every piece of crowded around that walkie-talkie
Sore falling along with this trying to search a picture
What is happening right now in space
And then
That calm voice say something
Pretty tariff
Negative
That means it must contact
I think
Negative
Telemetry so we can't see the rocket anymore it's
Gone
Do the clouds in the atmosphere somewhere and
Apparently it has stopped sending data back to Mission Control it's not communicating with Mission Control anymore
It is stopped sending data back to
Need to know what's going on
For some reason I just keep looking up
To the sky like I'm going to
See something before they do
Can we have negative
It is so quiet
And you can feel the tension in the air
And then
Coin counter
Are we are we in the clear
I literally thought I was going to throw up
Well that would happen
I was already writing the end of the series in my mind and it was not a happy and
But even if we can understand
What number is the man said
It's clear that everything is
Back on track perfectly normal
The covering at the top of the rocket has opened up
And at this point we're just listening for any mention of the Planet Money
Satellite pod one
They do not call it by the name pod1
The nickname on the watch chatter is dove
And so
The greatest moment in Planet Money history
Almost
Just goes by us
It's so quick
1 + 3
That's it
All right
Other people paid the money other people did the work
The Wii
We did the reporting cheers
It must have been the good luck pancakes
Well we did it
Somewhere up
Above the Earth
Is a cube satellite with our name on it
It's a Planet Money Pod 1
And there's a wave
Form of our voices on the side
And if you could read it
In space where that would be it would say
Hello and welcome
Planet Money
The Planet Money satellite is official it is now circling me
Are producer Elizabeth kulas
Has been holding
The microphone
This whole time
Do this incredibly tense moment
Recording everything not saying a word
And now you can tell she is a little bit choked up
People I know he started crying really sorry I couldn't believe the human Ingenuity could be so
I get to stand here
All day looking at the sky
Think about what it just happened
But
This is a military base and they are already checking their watches and
Pointing to the boss and being like Planet Money
Time to go
Don't We Gather for microphones and plastic champagne glasses
Hello Kitty bags and our Newfound knowledge of space lingo
It's been a nominal day
Extremely nominal day
And we walked back to the school bus
At home
Meanwhile
300 miles above our heads
A satellite is born
And not a soul can see
90 minutes after launch
HUD-1 make
First full orbit of the Earth
It went over the North Pole
17000 miles per hour
At this point it's just a spinning box
Picture of a loaf of bread
Tumbling through the sky
But somewhere in the first few hours
Speaks for the first time
It's just a pain that says
I'm here
I'm alive
Over the next couple of weeks the computers that control pod one try to stabilize the crash
There are these little wheels that spin inside of a satellite and each time you change the spin it nudges the saddle
By mid November
Pod one is stable
And it's solar panels have unfold
It is a camera now and it is pointed down at
And just this week just in time to finish the series
We get a call from
Are satellites has taken its first
This moment
It's called First Light
Light
We are so excited
Took a while to set up a conference call
I'm now showing at Echo again okay
Is that because
Technology
You know we can
Can send a satellite to space right
Okay so Stacy Mike has sent us an email here with a batch
Photos
Up here
It's beer
This is the first thing that pod one ever saw
Oh my god there it is
Blue and white
Images
Who has collected over Northeastern Russia
Like Siberia sakhalin
So somewhere under those clouds
Yeah
Yeah and in those are just
The first
Crappy photos first Pancake
Does it does get better luck
The next image is in North Korea
Everyone's favorite
Place to
Azim around them have your satellite oh no way
North Korea
I've always wanted to see North
Create and there it is
I think that is
A Runway
NEC mountains in NC this
This road here in some buildings in a big river there are little tiny boats on the river
Where hasn't it's already see more of the world than I thought
We can see it all I feel like this is a crochet
But the earth looks really beautiful from 300 miles up
It's really extraordinary to see the world in
I've seen a lot of photos from space
But these feel personal
It's like when you're
Toddler
Draw Surfer
But I better check with Mike Mike
How do these photos compared with
The other satellites
This is pretty good
Quite pleased with Edwin performance
I feel like I knew part 1 was
What is the people that work at Planet
They said one of the things they enjoyed about this Siri
Was to see people excited about satellites again I mean to have almost 200 of them and Mike was telling me
He just
Sort of thinks of it is at
A cloud of satellites
Inata
Not alike a single miraculous thing
I think that
It's in some ways I think about it
Commercial air travel big deal
When an airplane with
Flying
And now it's kind of like a man
Got to get to New York and I think
20 minutes late
It's a sign of progress
I don't know how to feel about that I know that's progress but it's kind of stupid
Well
I know what you mean I don't even
I don't want to end this whole thing in sad way give me give me an inspirational way for us to end
You have a satellite in space there's nothing to be sad about it is zooming around taking pictures of everywhere and
Imaginable
The satellite
Satellite
Hit the satellite
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online
And presents and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layouts along with features including e-commerce functionality
And mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial and when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
I just wanted to thank all of you the listeners
For sticking with us through our space mission I sort of felt like we were doing it on behalf of all of you so please
Email tell us what you thought Planet Money at npr.org or you can find us on Twitter or Facebook
We have been getting all of your emails about a possible future mission for pod1
And we will have a follow-up episode in a few months
Where we use our satellite to hopefully change the world
For the better
Didn't say that
Today's episode was produced by the wonderful Elizabeth who produced the entire space series and made it happen
Alex goldmark azar supervising producer and brian dorsett is our editor
To Michael stonecipher out of Vandenberg
Air Force Base who kept us on time and on Mission and a special special thing
To Trevor Hammond and all the people
At Planet
Who believed in US
A satellite
One of their companies missions is
Teach people about the world to make the world a smaller better place
And they were fantastic and allowing us humans view inside the small satellite industry we would never have done
Otherwise
But thank the planet
And this whole Adventure in fact all of Planet Money would not be possible without the amazing support of NPR and the
Give me some support of the member stations and so this month if you enjoyed the series and would like to hear more
Please think about giving to your local member station visit donate. Npr.org Planet money to give
And then share why you did with the hashtag
Why Public Radio
I'm Robert and I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Thanks for listening
One last thing Stacy remember
When I mentioned the space catalog
Yes
Here it is right here
You'll notice at the top of the list
At the top of the list
That's awesome
And let me
Go to
The bottom of the list
Right here
Catalog number 40 2990
Sex the 40 mm
Thing that ever went to space
Is the Planet Money satellite
Is that us
That is
Robert Smith official
Where in the catalog
429 + 6
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
I'm Carlos Garcia
And we are here with a new show the indicator
It's 3 days a week about 5 minutes for show and it is from the people who make Planet Money mostly about work
Business and the economy
On every show we take some number in the news or term or a story and we died
Intuit to find the big idea behind it
And we really hope is it an every show but look at least almost every show will bring you a new idea
Some new lens through which to see the world indicator Planet Money