I've been working on your taxes
This weekend
Who do we miserable
We'd like to give you a little inspiration
Really introduce you to a man you should
Keep in mind
While you're juggling
Deductions
Exemptions
Wesley Snipes
I'm not guilty
You're the one who's guilty
Lawmakers the politicians
Colombian drug lord
Wesley Snipes inspiring performance from the film New Jack City
He is of course he famous actor he has been in dozens of films but we are talking on today because
He is famous for another reason
He failed to file his tax returns
4 years on 40 million dollars worth of income according to the IRS
He was convicted went to jail for two-and-a-half years
Isb 17 million dollars
In backpack
This is big business
This is the American way
Mr. Snipes
Because we're trying to scare you into paying
Your taxes
In fact, teaches the opposite less
Because as crazy as it sounds
Wesley Snipes
By not paying his taxes
Actually acting in an economically rational way
He been cheating on his taxes
4 years
And no one seemed to notice that this
Incredibly rich and famous person
Had failed to file taxes
Texas doing what basically everyone does when they fill out their taxes
They're making a mental calculation
The cost
And the benefits of lime
The benefits are clearly
Getting away with not paying taxes the cost are
Getting caught
This is James all music
Professor and chair of Economics at
Tulane University
And he's been studying tax evasion for you
He says that for people who are self-employed or
Take certain kinds of deductions
There's actually a big Financial
Incentive
Wesley Snipes
For those types of income reporting
Your chance of getting caught a really pretty low and even if you're caught the penalties that you would pay would not be able to at great and so
On those types of reporting
We should see people cheating more than they do
Wesley Snipes got caught
Newington other people the US they never get
I get away with it
Daenerys seems to be powerless to stop them
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Caitlin Kenny and I'm Robert Smith today on the show how to get people to pay their taxes
When the rational thing to do is to cheat
This isn't just a problem in the US American taxpayers are Dudley Do-Right compared with people in some
Other on the show today we're going to head to the cheating it's places on Earth to bring you Tales from some of the rough
Tuffy's Tax Collectors around tricks special tax collector mind game that they play
How to get people to do the right thing
Pay their taxes
Just so you know the show was originally recorded and recorded in 2014
Let's take a moment to thank and share a message from our sponsor betterment a smarter way
Way to invest your money betterment creates and manages a personalized portfolio for you focusing on ease-of-use
Lowering taxes
And here's what you might find refreshing
No jargon low fees and full transparency
For a limited time sign up for betterment and you may qualify for a free Canary home security system to help secure your
Four terms and conditions visit betterment.com Planet Money
The fundamental problem is this
People know that they should pay their taxes it is
The law
But it's so tempting to cheat
Text collectors can't be everywhere they can't know everything
Cash is untraceable
I want to come to the moment when you report your income when you actually sign that form
You are generally alone
No one is looking over your shoulder
No one
He's going to know
All of the tax collector tricks
We're going to talk about station or something in common
They're designed to make you think twice in that
Private moment
To make you sweat
Turn around and think
Maybe someone's watching me after all
The first stop on our tax enforcement tour
The Philip
And we picked this country because
This is one of those places where people do not pay their tax
Access where there's a high level of corrupt
And they have an interesting solution
They're in the
Their solution
Make
The tax collector
Normally the head of the internal revenue
Is this faceless bureaucrat
But not in the Philippine
She's a celebrity
My full name is Kim as Jacinto Hernandez and the commissioner of internal revenue of the Philippines
All right let me describe Kim for you because her secret weapon is her tough
Image she's got the short cropped haircut and dresses like an off-duty
T-top
And she is his expression on her face
Such as
You're lying to me
And I know it
And here's the kicker
When she's photograph
She is invariably holding a gun or actually shooting a gun and this isn't just for
Little automatic pistol
She carries around
She is shooting assault
Weapon when Filipinos think
Tax collectors
That is their image
A woman with a very large guy
Says before she took office there was a certain mentality
It's no big deal to cheat on your taxes
Because what's the worst is going to happen
For years people think that
Anyway when they get caught they can always
Talk their way out of it
Pay their way out of it
Or they can always wait for an amnesty program
So Kim decided to
Look deep into the hearts and Minds
If you look at the psyche of the Filipino
How do you make them toe the line
It's either
They realize that they will be punished if they do something wrong
Or they will be
Placing an embarrassing situation
The Philippines has almost a hundred million people and so
JJ isn't that
Kim is going to flash her gun
At every tax cheat
She has a much more targeted
She is going to go after
The big dog
The most high-profile tax evaders
Old thing that you always here in all the prison movies
On your first day in prison you're supposed to
Take down the biggest meanest guy in the yard and then
Everyone will be afraid of you
That was Kim's plan
Anna Phillips
When you ask
Who's the toughest guy around here
There's only one
Obvious answer
When I was a boy I had to fight to feed my family
Entire life iPhoto survived my only ho
Manny
Pacquiao
The legendary Filipino boxer
Be the man who famously Rose from poverty
Two become one of the richest athlete
In the world
Super famous in the Philippines even want a seat in Congress
The dude is on a postage stamp
And Kim says when she got the job she went down this list
The richest people in
Philippines
And there was Manny Pacquiao
Strangely
What you checked
She realized
She was paying less taxes
He had the year before
Even though he was clearly more famous
Successful so Kim looks into it and she finds that Pacquiao owes
50 million dollars in back taxes
And so
She
Did something that people
Tend not to do in the Philippines
She went after somebody famous
He froze his bank account
Garnish his wages
Levies property
This whole process
Did not Stacy
Pacquiao
Nahan Daniel are using Ikea said it was unfair
Shrewd on Kim's Park
Think about the best way to get famous as a tax collector is Big Lots of famous people
When the tax collectors famous
People are more likely to pay their taxes
Avalon tax records
Human after the former presidents
Kenwood after famous socialites
The more attention she got the more people were afraid of her and so basically she started to look for a Target on the side
Cited pages
Forsyth stumbled on these pictures of
Gene Eppley
A Young Rich daughter of a very successful
Instagram or Facebook
Chauffeur
In a bathtub full of
My name is
Yeah there's a Facebook
Beach butts
Things in the social media are also reported in our traditional media
Luckily all the social media has become a a guide
The to unreported income we found this
Crazy video of Gene Napoli's
21st birthday party
Add a fancy hotel in Beverly Hills
A picture
Kim and her staff at the Internal Revenue Service
Watching this video and just
Adding up all of the expense
Closest crabs video for you it starts with
He's quick images of
Logos
Liquor bottles Grey Goose Maker's Mark
And then it's
This red carpet there's a fashion show at one point I counted she were six different dresses in the course of this one
Play Party
Happy 21st birthday
Haji
Thumbs up
You look so hot
Happy birthday Jean
The bill for the party must have been huge
Especially when you consider what happened afterwards
Are tax collector Kim
Decided to go after the debutant
And her parents on tax evasion
It's not the problem to be rich and he's not the problem to flaunt it
SOS that boxes are properly paid
So if you're rich and you flaunt it
Just make sure you have been paying the right boxes
Sooner or later I will see it
If you watch Filipino TV
You would think that Kim is everywhere that she knows
Everything knows all the cheaters
But here's the secret
The number of these rich and famous
Kim's gone after
Is shockingly small
Just 230 case
And yet
It's enough to strike fear into the
The heart of even the little guy
Kim says in 2012 for office collected its largest amount in a
Single year
Almost 15% more than the year before
Taxpayers were afraid of Kim
It's the people who work for her
Tax collectors
Kim says that she's cracking down on corruption in her own Department
So far she says
Her mom tells her that it
It's working
Her mother recently told her that the cost of riding attacks official in the Philippines
Has gone up
Percent
Lefty
Tough guy approach
The tax info
What do you do if you are in a country where your tax collector does not carry a gun
What do you do when your tax collector
Sounds like
Reddit Ama
Next stop
Where the tax collector is Kiana put Solo
And her secret weapon is called
Reddit Ama
Will explain exactly how it works in just a minute
The first you have to understand how bad the tax collection problem is
This is a place where the former prime minister
Silvio Berlusconi
Is being sentenced for tax fraud
Text Rod he committed while he was running the country
While
He was running
The country
Italy part of the fashion label Dolce & Gabbana
Well
Both of them those dudes Domenico Dolce and Stefano Gabbana
Were convicted of tax evasion
Even
Giorgio Armani
Was caught.
And yeah I'm like the Philippines all these are rest of these famous people then it seemed to have helped the problem I mean
People didn't seem scared
In fact it kind of the opposite effect like oh well those guys aren't paying their taxes
Why should I pay
Which brings us a course
To the new Italian program
Reddit Ama
We have with children.
To translate it would be
Something like
Income matter or
Income is Rabat
You know it's
If you agree
It's nice to keep the Italian word
Rave theater
Perfect
Reddit Ama
There's no tough tax agents
The gun in Italy
Instead there's Kiara patola
And this program
Redito Metro
Mickey and behind-the-scenes
The Chinese government has basically declared that they're watching how Italians spend their money
Literally
Keeping list
What Italians Buy
So they can look at
Some Italian businessman
Giovanni
Looks like they can see what Giovanni declares his
And then they can check a list that they put together
Exactly what Giovanni has
In spending his money on
His purchases
The government can see if Giovanni is spending more money than he says he may
So they know what kind of house do you want
Or a car
If you buy a car
Of course you have to register the car in the in the right in the public register
Ultimo DIA
And we automatically gathered information
So if Giovanni has a Ferrari he had better be reporting enough income
To afford a Ferrari
The tax office can also make private businesses rat you out
Some stores report to the government who exactly is buying what
Not every
Iran a shopping list
Kiara
If I went to
The store
And bought gross
Is it possible that your agency
No
That I've spent x amount of
Absolutely not
A bouquet of flowers
No
A cup of espresso no
No. Don't seem really interested
Qingdao coffee
Okay what about if I went and I bought a really fancy new product
Handbag
What you know about that big expenses
My betrayal
By the revenue
Depending on their mouth
What is what is the amount
Does our expenses Yonder
3600 Euros about $5,000 us
Yeah
The tax department day of all this
About the big purchases you
He made that year but the diamond necklace or the super expensive Rolex
Your expenses
Any match that up to what
You say you earned
That year
You're declared in
When there is a big big big discrepancy between
The two
Well
You may be off
Come to the revenue just to
Explain
What is the your source of income
She makes it sound so polite
She even said they sent you an invitation letter to come down to their offices
So far they sent out
And just like in the Philippines the power of this
Is it
Everybody knows about this new program
In fact we're looking some of the news reports from Italy
And when this was announced
People
Went
Nuts are going to Ono I can't buy art down you know I spent all my money on Earth
There was one woman who was complaining that did she has
Free horses
Because I have three horses in yet
I've spent all my money on these horses so I'm not rich
I'm just a poor person with three horses
The government
The government's going to assume that I'm rich
And then there was his Art Gallery owner complaining that people would stop buying luxury
Because they would worry
That the government was going to get tipped off to them
Which you know
If true is not a good thing for a country coming out of a recession
But you know what else is not good for Country coming out of a recession
Nobody paying their tax
That's the argument the key Arabic
Aqi says
Hey if Italy
We got to try some
All right so so far we have two very different ways the tax man
Or woman gets into your head
The gun-toting sheriff
Sneaky bureaucrat
All scary in their own ways
But maybe
There's an easier way
We're going to hear about that after this quick message
Support for Planet Money and the following message come from Squarespace
Squarespace offers a unique domain experience that's fully transparent and simple to set up
Make your next move by visiting squarespace.com to start your free trial
And use offer code Planet Money for 10% off your first purchase
Squarespace
Make your next move
Make your next website
All right we taking you from the Philippines to Italy next up let's go to the UK
In the past it was it was generally thought that Pino enforcement the only thing that matters
But increasing people thinking other things Metro
Not just
Am I going to get cool but is this the right thing
To do
This is Michael Hall
And he was part of a special team of a
Economist
Policy folks
Put together by the UK government
Did you a bunch of stuff including think about ways to get more UK residents
To pay their taxes
This bunch of brainiacs who spent years studying social science and behavioral economics
It was called the behavioral insights
Italy or the Philippines
Okay we're in a minute the UK barely has
What's the problem
They are some law-abiding folks there
But still
When the principles of life is the tax man does not rest until he or she is at 100% enforcement
And that was basically what they brought to the behavioral insights
We want to make sure that everyone in the UK
100000 people
Filed a tax return but hadn't paid up
The deadbeat
Deadbeats
With an address
So they decided to conduct this
Experiment on
Is there a way to guilt
Linda Payne there taxes
Without sending a Cop 2
And in this is this is the dream of
Tax enforcement agent everywhere you can just send out
A threatening letter and someone going to send the money
And it rarely rarely work
These guys wanted to figure out
How do you send out a letter that will convince
Double get inside
Text Sheepshead that will make her
Him her feel bad it will make someone do the right thing
If you look at it
Diverse Nomex
I want to see
Important Concepts
The keeps coming up to social norms
So what influenced by what other people do in the same situation
And they started by figuring out what does
Okay we can be bureaucratic
We can be whiny or mean
Did you consider anything like more extreme like listen idiots it's your taxes you have to pay that video you don't have a choice
No not really
This is actually a serious point which is that
Timing is really important we know that
People pick up from this if if the tone is preps overly
Aggressive people may actually react against them so they will know I'm not cancer
Looking to do this
So we really wanted to come up with something which
Which
Reasonable time
For two years they try different wording in
The tax letter some simply said that most
People pay their taxes
Others talked about the good things
Set taxes pay for
Hospital
In school
And in the end the message that work the best
Is this simple phrase
Quote
You are currently in the very small minority of people who have not
Peanuts yet
I love at the very small
Minority
A people who have not paid us yet which is probably how it makes you feel right very
Small
And Electric
Fit into what we know in economics about fairness
Basically if you think that nobody else is paying their taxes you're not going to pay your tax
Either but
If you think that everyone is if you think that you're the small or
In the morning the letter D very small minority
You will tend to go along with the crowd
And this message at work
Michael says
People more than any of the others sent in the money they owed to the government
It was so successful that the UK is still using this messaging and letters being sent out to
Delinquent taxpayers
Right now
The Economist James arm that we spoke to at the beginning
The guy who said that
Text cheats rarely get caught
He says when you use
All of these kind of techniques that we
We talked about today
When you use them
You're really making people redo their economic calculation
There may only really
Be a 1%
Or 2% chance of getting audited
What's the chance of getting caught
What you doing tricks does is it makes you
Feel
Like the chance of getting caught
The chance of somebody seeing you is big
Do you have to use
Lots of different approaches lots of different tools and import because there are so many different motivations for
People
In deciding whether to
To pay their taxes
Properly
Context matters institutions matter country matters
Until you you can't simply take
A one-size-fits-all
Approach
And assume that it's always going to have the same effects at all settings
And James alms for the records
He told us he pays all of his tax
Even at time when you 150 bucks
In NCAA
He declared it
So what is it for you like what motivates you personally to do things like
Declare your NCAA pool
Which as you yourself said
Yeah they're not going to catch you on
It's not because I am afraid of getting caught that's not because
Getting the special good service from the IRS I think it's
Because I think that's the right thing to do
To the social norms are at work on you
I'm work hard to try to overcome those social norms probably saying that been successful
As always we want to know what you thought of Today Show you can eat
MLS Planet Money at npr.org us on Twitter or Facebook
Today's rebroadcast was produced by Daniela the doll
And if you're looking for something else to listen to you need to check out NPR's brand new podcast
It's called up first
The biggest stories and ideas from politics to pop culture and here's the key they give it to you in just 10 minutes
How to get published at 6 in the morning this could be a regular part of your morning just catch up on everything that's happened to us
24 hours and you're good to go
It's called up first you can find it
Fairview gear podcasts
I'm Robert Smith thanks for listening