One of our producers here at Planet Money Elizabeth
Recently moved here from Australia
And last week she got kind of
Initiation into American
She did her tax
At first she and her husband Matthew
Do you harden try to do
Do it on their own
And the Texas kind of took over their part
On our
Dining room table
We have a pile of
WW2
V 1099
Anime some other forms like a 1095-c
Elizabeth and Matthew realized they were going to need some
So they hired an account
It could easily be $500 a weekend to spend at the accountant
What did Mayweather you say to me the other day you would be happy if was less than $1,000 that she's
This is all kind of blowing there
Because there is nothing
Like this in Australia
In Australia paying taxes is really fast and easy
In fact Elizabeth the math you couldn't even tell me when Australian tax day what
So is there an equivalent of
April 5th
Teens
In Australia
Really
Know that means yeah
I don't remember being such a thing
I think it's like February or March
It's October 31st actually but in most of the rest of the world they don't know when tax day is either
All of the crazy stress around
24-hour hotlines that software the accordion folders full of receipts the lines down the street
H&R Block
That is
Pretty much just a USA thing
So we have it the worst our taxes are the
Worst
Taxes
I filing system is the worst
Flick of objectively
Yeah objectively
Joseph bankman is a professor of
Tax Lots
And he says collectively
We spend billions of dollars
And billions of hours every year filing our taxes
Not to mention the emotional
Induces it does not have to be this way
In most of the world it's not
And Joe
Use exactly how to fix this
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Stacey Vanek Smith and with me today is Alex Massey from
Priceonomics
Alex Bay Stacy Jo
The tax system that's right it's a story of this lovable professor
To believe the paint taxes does not need to be so difficult
Goes on a year-long quest to make filing taxes easier for everyone
And you might be wondering who would want to keep taxes complicated
I will tell you who
A multibillion-dollar corporation
And one of the most important
Power Brokers in Washington
We'd like to say a quick thank you and share a message from one of our sponsors
State Farm
Over the entire course of your life
Things are changing
Whether you're buying your first car
Moving out on your own getting married having your first child or seeing your children move out on their own
Through it all
You can count on your State Farm agent for a wide range of solutions expertise and support
Local agent information is it statefarm.com
State Farm
Here to help life go right
So Alex jumping bean does not look like your typical
Warrior hero what's the best way to
When Steven Spielberg inevitably directs a Blockbuster movie about taxes
Joe bankman will be played by Tom Hanks
Mind you it's a Tom Hanks who's been teaching tax lot Stanford
Also Avery dressed down Tom Hanks
Alex when we talked to Joe Banks
Been at Stanford you were marked nobody was very dressed
Joe and I are both pretty casual
I suppose Alex is being very sweet but as I look at these Sarah slack I notice
There is a stain on one of them
And
The Cuffs are frayed
I hate taxes
But you'll bankman
Love's tax
Joe loves taxes so much that he thinks about them in his spare time
In fact
He spent time when he's not in class or on campus
Helping the state of California wear contacts
If back in 2003 Joe is part of the
Little team that was working with the state that help take down taxes
We are just done a bill to penalize a form of tax shelter
And it raised a lot of money for this day
And we're all out to lunch at a mediocre restaurant in Sacramento
Yeah we are celebrating
Joey his California tax
MRP eating lunch and Talking Shop
And they told you they have the
And I did I think would save California
A bunch of money and time and help
Most people in California
I have really simple
All of their income from a regular
And taxes are already withheld
From the paychecks
So their idea was why don't we start off
Giving them a tax return
That's already filled out with the income we know they have
And then they can make Corrections
That was their idea
Basically the government would send you a tax return that was already filled out
It would include all of the income that the state knew about all this
Taxes that had already been withheld for
Paychex
And you would look it over and
Build it
Joni this was how taxes work in most countries
Towers in Europe
Parts of Asia
Scandinavia Australia
And so he thought
Why not here
The way I think of it is
Imagine if the credit card come
Acted like the IRS
Each month you get a Visa bill and be a blank piece of paper
And you'd have to write down all of your perch
She says and add it up
And if you did it wrong you face a penalty
So the IRS could
Act like Visa
And paying taxes would be like paying a credit
And we could be like Elizabeth and Matthew are first-time taxpayer
Not know when our tax day is
So now Joe and his team had decided
But they still needed to make it real bad to figure out what this form would be
BN what it would look
And so Alice we have it we have it right
Do not look like a tax form I've ever seen
Yeah you know it's it's just one page it looks pretty friendly it's not a bunch of legalese you know it says
Easy as 1 2 3
Step 1 review return step to make any changes in step 3 send it back
That's it I know there's something so friendly about it at the top of the
Filing your taxes just got easier
And then has the name that Joe and his
Team gave to this form and enter this whole project
We called it a ready writer
I like ready return it snappy
It's snap you sent it
Now Joe and his California tax team have this form
Ready to spray friendly form
Ready return is actually going to work
If taxpayers
Use it if they would like it
Submitted a pilot program in California
In the 2004 tax season isn't ready returns out to get 11,000 tax
Along with this
Little survey
So we ask people
Do you think you'd like to use this again next
And 99% of the people said yes
99% of people don't say yes to anything
90% of 20
Beijing
I talked to someone else who's involved in ready return and what he told me is
When you work in government nothing
That's reviews like that he's a
You don't get 99% satisfaction rates with the polio vaccine it's just unheard of
Probably true
And it wasn't just the survey either the things I was actually
Proudest over there
The comments
The people had written in on their survey
And he actually brought a stack of
Please print it out comments in to talk with us
What I do
Is a rifle through some of the pages
And then I asked people to tell me when to stop
Because I don't want anybody think I'm cherry-picking so tell me
Here are Alex can see me
Tell me when to stop flipping through the pages and I will tell him to stop right now
Okay cuz on a random page on some random
And the first one thank you for allowing me to participate
Second this was very easy and convenient
3rd
No problems I loved it
So I said I loved it
I loved it
Here's one that says PS is the same service available for federal tax
Returns this is all cap
Add someone used all caps positive
Yes
There was one comment that really stuck with
Finally government's doing something to make my life better
What did you think when you read that
I was really touched them and I was really moved I'm even moved as I think about it now
For someone like me that's your your dream right
You know if you think about filing taxes he
It's one of the most important interactions you've got with your government
And how does it make you feel
It makes you pissed
You can understand that you're anxious you're worried about screwing up
And
We make 160 million people go through this each year that's
That's really bad
Did you think that
If we can prove that.
Did you think it would like help improve
People's relationship with the government
Absolutely
Joe thought his little
Ready return form
Damiki big
Difference
In the country
Of course the first ready return had to pass
The California state legislature in Sacramento
But you wasn't that worried I mean everyone who tried ready return had loved
And California governor Arnold Schwarzenegger was also on board
So just started making the two hour car trip from Stanford to Sacramento every week
To talk with lettuce
Well I thought
That if I just talked
I was kind of naive I thought well I get it
That
People are conservative or a liberal but since this is a nonpartisan issue
I'll just
Talk to all of our representative
UPS in Sacramento and explain things
I'm a talker I thought I could do that
Choza Taqueria
He is a talker and he he made a list of all the legend
Slater's would be voting on ready
Return any just started calling at their offices and asking for meeting
I wasn't getting enough meetings
People would put me off or they say we'll get back to you
And even when Joe did get a meeting
$10 go so well
Well one meeting
Somebody said I've been warned about you
Yeah that was that at startup with what did they mean
They mad that the Intuit lobbyists it already been in
Intuit
Is the company that owns
TurboTax
TurboTax is of course the very popular tax preparation software it is a multi-billion Dollar business
A multibillion-dollar business that was now staring down the barrel of Jose ready return
And if you look at this from TurboTax is point of view
This is not good I mean ready which one is all about making
Taxes easier
And if your taxes are easier you're a whole lot less likely to spend a hundred bucks on tax prep
Software
So just started hearing that into it without asking around about her
His plan
Which of these little talks you know for legislators about ready return he given academic talk for students
Professors
He started noticing something odd
Whenever he gave a talk
He would always notice someone from Intuit
In the crowd
They would show up at talks I would give
How would you know that it was that
I give a lot of talk
And I'm only going to get it like 10:30 people and everybody looks like an academic but one woman comes in
I just kind of looking a little corporate
She's like dressed better than the rest
And so that's a tip off right away tax academics or not the best dressed people in the world
Intuited want to talk to us for this piece but they sent us a statement
It said that they have long advocated for tax simplification
But they're ready return quote minimizes taxpayer engagement
They think that's bad
Who discovered the into it had been very busy in Sac
Meeting with politicians giving money
Intuit gave $1000000 to a pack.
Supported one of the key politicians on the ready return issue
This kind of thing happens all the time we have a little group it is
Very invested in an issue
A lot of people
Give me the little group in this case TurboTax
Is willing to spend tons of time and tons of money making some
Happen
And the large group of people that might benefit a little bit or not willing to spend that time in May
Prince's I would love it if filing my taxes
Easier but
I haven't called my congressman I'm not really willing to spend a whole bunch of money to make that happen
Then again
I am Nacho
So that's
The point where I decided to hire my own Lobby
I've never even heard of someone hiring their own lobbyists
It was really fun I really enjoyed hiring a lot
I hired a guy named Mike Robson
Coart smart as a whip
Really likeable
Kind of looks like a more svelte
James Gandolfini
But that lobbyists
He didn't come cheap
How much did that cost
They gave me a deal because they thought it would be kind of
Fun
The work for this
Craze Professor working for you
Yeah
They're working for me and so
The normal price I think would have been $140,000 to
To get Mike services
But he gave it to me for only
Should I pay 35000
Wake of your own money
Of my own money
Liquor savings
Yeah why did you spend the money that way
I know I felt lucky again to be able to do as a great cause
And everybody I think has some causes that think they're good causes and
This was a cause that was really good and nobody else was going to do it but
Making that investment hiring Mike
It paid off
With microbes and everybody would talk
Why
Well they had relationships with him
Legislators
Kind of like that I was with Mike
Because they also kind of legitimated
They figure if you're with Mike you're probably
Sensible
You probably are going to get good information
If I have a question I can call your lobbyist if I can't get ahold of you
The meeting start to go a little better
Legislator start listening to Joe
Telling him
You got my vote
But Joe says
He noticed
It was hard to get Republicans to back ready
It wasn't just into it or campaign money
It had to do
With a pledge
And privately I should say
A lot of Republicans told me what this just sounds like a no-brainer I just can't do it
Because
Grover norquist is supposed to
Hello my name is Grover norquist
I am the President
Of Americans
For tax
Perform we fight for taxpayers to keep taxes low
Grover norquist is a famous anti-tax Crusade
He heard about ready return
And sprang into action
What is a wave
To raise taxes
A way to send people a bill for more taxes than they owe
And they're unlikely to contested people don't fight the IRS
Norquist.
Ready return is tantamount to attack
Because once the government has taxpayer
Amazon autopilot
Signing and sending
Bill start sneaking things in like the house cell phone
Company sneakers
Little charges and you look at them and sort of wonder about them but
Any and you just pay because it's easy
And norquist has this famous pledge Republicans all across the country take it
And the pledge basically says
I will not support any plan that raises
And that was a problem
What happens if people break the pledge
When somebody breaks the pledge
Their opponents in the next election 10 to remind voters
They lied their way into office
I am depressed tends to focus on it
Northwest put out the words California Republic
If you back ready return
You have broken the pledge
Joe bankman this tax law professor and his loan lobbyists are now battling not only ammo
Multibillion-dollar soccer
Also one of the biggest
Names in US policy
Joe kept telling everyone this won't raise tax
It will just make it easier to pay them
Everyone time in money
But Joe says he talked to a lot of small government
And actually
They wanted pain
Taxes to be
Their logic wise
If paying taxes it's difficult
People will hate tax
And vote against them
Joe and Mike
And they started getting ground
Little by little with Democrats and Republicans
Locking downvotes
And a couple weeks out
They needed just
One more vote
One more vote to make ready return happen in the entire State of California
And then
I found a Republican
That was
Going to support it
Joe convinced a republican legislator to back
Pledge
Ignore the campaign money
After a year of taking on corporate lobbyists political power Brokers at so many tok
Spending $35,000 a piece
His own money
This was it
Ready return
Look like it was going to happen
Just before the vote
Joe had to drive back.
Videos of the politicians who supported ready return
To keep him up
The day of the vote
Joe remembers getting a call
I could tell by the tone in his voice
What the answer
It was before I said any
He said
So and so I didn't forgot the legislators name is not with us looks like we're going to be one vote short
Vote
Short
Republican and changed his mind and Joe
Had lost
And all of the other states that I've been calling Joe asking how they could implement the plan like this
The kind of dropped away
It was it was a little bit crushing
Hot to lose like that
How much time have you invested
In a way it was a year of my life
It's a pretty big blow
SoJO
Joann back to teaching full time
But he kept pushing ready return
A version of it did survive in California
It's buried in the state's tax site but it's there
A few hundred thousand people use it every year
Curtis had a pretty interesting Legacy
Elizabeth Warren and Bernie Sanders introduced a bill that looks a lot like red
Turn last year they referenced Jose pilot program
It didn't end up happen
But Joe says we keep getting close
Eventually
He thinks it's going to happen
My fantasy
Is that
At some point it just makes so much sense will join the rest of the world
And I don't know how that's going to happen with our current political climate
Maybe some mid-level bureaucrat I'll just make the change herself
And it'll go through it'll kind of fly under the radar
That's what I think will happen sooner or
Somehow
In the meantime people like Elizabeth and Matthew or first
Time us taxpayers and all the rest of us
Are stuck spending
Hundreds of dollars end
Many many hours
Filing our tax
It is not without its ups
I never would have even said so
Accomplishment away
Yeah it's like
I think I was saying Sally like if we can do this like we can do anything
This is probably the most daunting task
It would come across
Find tax return
Sazae-san couple could walk you to put their relationship since history file
Welcome to America
One less thing we found another
Interesting moment when someone tried to make people excited about paying their taxes
They wrote a song
Right after this
Support for Planet Money and the following message come from ishares
Because the best
Preparation for tomorrow
It's building for your future today
Ishares by BlackRock inspired to build
For most of us history most people did not pay income
I've been to the forties only about 5%
American Pie
Income taxes at all
But during the forties the government needed to raise money
4 World War
So it rolled out a larger income tax about
75% of America
And this time people were pulled behind the government there was a lot of soup
Support behind wartime
And Irving Berlin was very patriotic guy and he was moved to write this song to get people behind paint
Income taxes
To support the war
Here's a song you just called I paid my income tax today
I'm squared up with of USA
Vamos in the sky Rockefeller help the building
I think I preferred Jose version
Trying to make us love taxes
I don't know this one is so catchy
I feel like if that music were playing when I filed my taxes I would feel
So much better about finally
Everything everything is nicer with a little
Play music in the background with a jingle
She looks like a game changer
We always love to hear what you think of the show you can send us an email
Planet Money at npr.org you can also find us on Twitter or Facebook I am at s Vanek Smith
And Alex
You can find me at at a mask and you can also find a print version if you want to know more about Joseph bankman
Quest
You can go to priceonomics. Com
It's a great piece go check it out
And if you're looking for another podcast listen to NPR's embedded is back was Kelly mcevers it taking an in-depth
Look at police videos
At this week's episode gets into an officer's mine you can find a new episodes on NPR one or wherever you
You get your podcast
Today Show was produced by our very own first time US taxpayer Elizabeth coolest thank you Elizabeth
Also special thanks to Larry zelenak
And Alex thank you for bringing us the story
I'm glad we could tell her about Joe Beckman
Pax era
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
And I'm out my awesome thanks for listening