Hey it's Jacob Goldstein Today Show is a rerun that originally aired in 2000
Puritas
A few years ago Justina Clayton started a hair braiding business in our home in Centerville Utah
She learned to braid hair as a girl growing up in Sierra Leone end in Utah
She found this little niche working for local families that had adopted kids from Africa
Her business letter stay home with her own kids and
And some months you made enough to pay for grocery
Put an ad on a local website
Then one day she got an email from a stranger who had seen the ad
It said
It's illegal in the state of Utah.
How to do any kind of expand
Without a cosmetology
No way
I responded I said go ahead
Airport me
But just to be on the safe side she called the state license
And she found out that she did needle
And that to get it
She have to spend more than a year in cosmetology
Tuition would cost $16,000 or more
I was really upset
I know who am I threatening here
I did a lot of
Talking to my husband
He listened he was very kind
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Jacob Goldstein
But I'm Alex blumberg and today on the program
Why it's illegal to braid hair in Utah without a license
And why that rule and others like it are a disaster for the USA
We'd like to say a quick thank you and share a message from one of our sponsors
State Farm
State Farm it's much more than just an insurance
They're also committed to making a positive impact in the communities they serve
One way is through neighborhood of
A program connecting people who want to make a difference with causes looking for local violin
Discover over 31000 social card is it listed at neighborhood of good.com
And start turning the power of caring
Into the act of doing
State Farm
Here to help life
Go right
After she got that email and found out she needed a license
Justina close down our business
She figured it just wasn't worth it
The time and money to go to
But she did get to go and make her case to the board that regulates hair braiding in Utah
Full name of that board by the way the barber cosmetology / Barber
Aesthetics electrology
A nail technology licensing
Thank you so I took to get ready for her meeting with the b c d e n t
Shelby jestina called around to different cosmetology schools in Utah she found out
Those schools taught little or nothing about the African style hair braiding that
She also learned that there's some other states where
People can do African Hair Braiding if they pass just a basic safety and hygiene test and pay registration fee
And so she took all this and put it together into a PowerPoint presentation explaining these things and then she
Went to the board meeting on
Waited outside the meeting room while the board took care of its other piss
So finally was my turn and I got in
I was super nervous
I stood up and I started talking and there was
One lady
Just kept
Bitching in ultrasound
I side with tacos
Yeah right you know just under her breath
She kept doing that and then
What was the impression you got from what she was
That
She didn't believe anything that I said
But
Chair of the meeting
She said that I would have to change
Slow because as the law is written
If you touch her for money
If you style hair for money
Then you need a cosmetology
She said there's nothing that they can do
What happened to Justina happens all the time with all different kinds of jobs all around the country
There is this
Patchwork quilt of State Licensing Laws and it covers
Hundreds of different profession
It's not just you know doctors and lawyers
Garage door repairman its interior designers
Landscapers athletic trainers masseuses and literally hundreds of other professions
I need a sensible reason for all these licensing
Is that these requirements protect the public in some way
Charles wheelan teaches public policy at Dartmouth in the University of Chicago
That may be true but for people in license Fields a licensing law conserve
An entirely different purpose altar
It's also a way to make your competition go away
And that if you are practicing a profession anything
So let's use
Manicure assistant example
And there's a lot of competition say from
Asian immigrants which is the case in Chicago
And you want to limit that competition you can go to your State Legislature
And you can say you know what it should be harder to be a manicurist you should have to pass an exam or hold a degree
Free or do assorted other things
In that case you really just built a fence around your profession
It keeps out competition lower Supply in basic economics says that means your
Can I do better you either get paid more or you'll have more work
And for the rest of us that is for those of us getting manicures this means that managers are more expensive
Maybe you've noticed that yourself I'm paying an extra dollar or two for my manicure
Maybe
It doesn't bother you that
But there is this other big problem with these license
They make it harder for people to find work
One clear example is Justina who we heard from the top
How to get work in the special nephew have to go
Schools spend a lot of money
But even if you have a license
Chances are the state license
Probably won't work
In another state
Will licensing is not particularly good for anybody who's trying to switch profession
Or trying to move to another location where the economy may be bad
So we don't in general Mobility is pretty good as a saddle for a bad economy because some places are going to be stronger than other
Father so people may be leaving Michigan when the auto economy is weak then maybe going to the Southwest
If there's a lot of growth are so part of what we like about the labor market
Is you get price signals and unemployment signals and people should go where there's demand
As soon as you introduce State Licensing
It just makes it that much harder for people to do those things
And I want to go on record as saying that I'm not
Averse to regulation in general and I'm not even averse to the idea of Licensing some profession
I just think that we've done it so horribly
And so
Scattershot terms of who gets license
And what they have to do to become licensed that it's become kind of a monster
In the monster is huge and I were talking about a a big
Swap of the labor market
Just giving comparison
Back in the 50s one-and-twenty jobs require license
Today
One in every three jobs
So we have the situation we're at least in some cases consumers and the economy are being hurt and
It seems like the only people who benefit are actually the ones in the industries that are being regulated
Which is interesting right you always hear this idea that businesses opposed to regular
Station that businesses jelly went last regulator
And as we talked about in the podcast this is one of these examples
Businesses are often
In favor of Regulation. They love it
Exactly the reason we're talking about it helps
Make them more money
Although
Just driving
That's not what they say to the legislators when they're trying to get the
Licensing requirements pass
You can't go to the government say hey pay me some money
Because that's quite transparently not the right thing to do
What they typically do is they go to the legislature
And they don't say I quite like I'm going to say it but they essentially say we're really Danger
You need to protect the public from us
When I wrote my dissertation I actually had some case studies I looked at respiratory therapist
In the case of the respiratory therapist when they went to Springfield
They actually had a videotape
Of a truck blowing up
And the reason the truck was blowing up as it was transporting oxygen in a way that was inappropriate that they said look we can blow things
Protect the public from us
Cosmetologist as far as I know they cannot blow up
Trucks
But I did call Mayra Irizarry she works for the Professional Beauty Association is a trade group
She actually listed for me all the ways
Untrained cosmetologist couldn't harm people
There could be open wounds are to be cut
Pathogens
Could be transmitted
And here we have people that are practicing this field that could
Really
You do wonderful things for your appearance in him for your face and for your skin but also could harm you
These regulations are requirement and a necessity
For Consumer safety
I don't think that there's any way to go around
Consumer safety
That when it comes to Hair Braiding Charlie Wheeling rxperts
Doesn't buy
Mayra Irizarry the argument
Dammit this is this classic situation where you have a small group of people have passed away.
EBenefits
But he was talking to you Jacob ee got at the winners singing louder than the losers cry
You know you've got the
The small group of benefit quite a bit from these
And then you got this much
Larger crew
Consumers
Target has very minor wear that maybe they don't even notice
And then you have this this third group this
People who want to work in a field but but can't
People obviously like Justina Clayton
And for them the pain of this can really be
Cute Justina
Cheat she talked to me about how she
She grew up in Sierra Leone in the middle of the Civil War and then she came
Came to America and she had these
Ideas about America and to know when she talks about
It's a very emotional thing
When I Civil War started
And
You don't for a long time just
It's just been survival
You know just
Make sure that the next day is
You know that I'm alive the next day
That my friends are
And then
You know I finally make it here
You know
Going up you just know American supposed to be
It's just you have lots of options
Your potential
From getting from
Would low and to a higher
And as
Increases when you were here
It just
Not being able to do that
I don't know
Angry patient
Hope for the best
Justina has hooked up with the legal group called The Institute for justice
This is a Libertarian group they're actually suing the state of Utah on justina's
Half and they filed a bunch of lawsuits in in states around the country challenging different license
Any of Licensing rules have been a traditional Battleground for
For Libertarians and text me to Robert Smith
The story while I go back like a libertarian
Stitch to protest by manicuring
Somebody's fingernails on the governor's mansion lawn
But there's also this big anti licensing Bushnell from the left from more liberal Economist and activists
Michelle Obama has been talking about making things
Easier for the spouses of people who work in the military that have a hard time with licensing rules when they move from State
The state
Alan Krueger
Is now the chairman of President Obama's Council of economic
Advisors at the proposal the basically said
They should get rid of their licensing rules
If they're doing more harm than good
And that's a useful way to think about it I find because you know people often think about this issue as
Should have given profession be licensed or not yes or no
And people like Charlie will and they say that's the wrong way to think about
The question is
Do the regulations the licensing rules do they actually do what they claim
Do they protect the pub
It's not sufficient
To tell me that somebody can do harm
In a profession
Anybody can do harm in a profession if you're really incompetent
The burden of proof has to be on you
To prove to me the legislature
That whatever licensure mechanism we put in place
Will actually solve this problem
Flashy Elevate quality
It shouldn't be just a foregone conclusion that if you're potentially dangerous anything we throw on the books is going to be in approved
Some State lawmakers have also started to push back
Against
Licensing requirements
In Florida there's a bill introduced to loosen requirements
For among other things dance studios
And Auctioneers
And plus you're a legislator in Utah actually introduced a bill to allow African style hair braiding without a lie
But when Justina went to testify at the hearing
She found the room packed with
Cosmetologist
Cosmetology school
Somebody told me that they are all in a cosmetologist
Apparently they give them the day off
So they can come
And
Protest
This bill
It was intense
The cosmetologist exceeded
The built it didn't become a lot and it is still illegal in Utah to braid hair for money without a light
That was how the show ended back in 2012
I'll have an update on what happened since then
After this
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Merrill Lynch
An affiliate of Bank of America
Who asked
What could your future hold
Learn how Merrill Lynch works with you to create an investing strategy built around your life and priorities
By visiting ml.com
Merrill Lynch makes available products and services offered by Merrill Lynch
Pierce Fenner & Smith Incorporated
A registered broker-dealer
Just a few months after we did this story Justina won her case in court
A judge said the cosmetology law should not apply to her business
And a few months after that the Utah Governor made it official
He signed into law a bill that makes it legal
Two braids hair in Utah without a license
Justina was able to go back to
In the years since then this issue has continued to be a thing
In fact one case went all the way to this
Supreme Court
In that case the Dental Board in North Carolina had barred
Spas in
Hair salons from doing teeth whitening
They said that could only happen at the dentist office
The Obama Administration intervened saying hair salons and spas kudu teeth whitening
And when it got to the Supreme Court
The Court ruled against the Dental Board
It is now legal for spas and hair salons in North Carolina to do.
You can email us at Planet Money I'd npr.org or find us on Facebook
Twitter
Today show with originally produced by Jess Jiang today's update was produced by Sally helm
If you're looking for something else to listen to check out 1 in
When 8 is a daily talk show from NPR hosted by Joshua Johnson
The number 1 and letter A
You can find it on the NPR one app or wherever you get your
I'm Jacob Goldstein
Thanks for listening