Hate Today Show first Grand in 2014 there's a brief update at the end of the show
If you watch a big-time college football or basketball game
You'll see money
Everyone Michigan Michigan State
Just this past Saturday to pick an example more or less at random
The University of Michigan play Michigan State
In football what is an awesome sight 70,000 fans are in the stadium
Collectively they paid millions of dollars for tickets
The game is being broadcast around the car
On ABC
Which is owned by Disney which pays hundreds of millions of dollars a year for the right to broadcast college football game
ESPN college football presented by Kay Jewelers
Don't you buy
Pacific Life
Over on one side line the Michigan State coaches pacing back and forth
Mark dantonio
It is 8th season
Coach dantonio
$2000000
According to USA Today
Which is a lot of money $2000000
Unless you're the coach on the other side
For Brady Hoke the coaches on the hot seat
And it is a very nice seat because coach Houk
University of Michigan
Made up of four million dollars
University Michigan players they are all wearing Adidas
Shoes
Not because they're so comfortable
Or so awesome but because the University of Michigan is in the middle of a multi-year deal with Adidas
Is worth a reported
80 million dollars
All these millions of dollars
From the ticket sales from the TV contracts for the coaches salaries the shoe deals
All this money changes hands and what is basically a free mod
Universities can pay coaches as much as they want or as little as they want
School can cut deals with any shoe company they want or they can decide they're not going to cut any shoe deal at all
But the people who are wearing the shoes
The athletes on the field
The ones were crashing violently into one another
Turn the looks like he's limping a little bit as he had to pack today these guys
Or not
A long time ago a bunch of colleges got together and agreed not
To pay their college
Fellowships Roque
But anything beyond that is against the rules
The NCAA
Which oversees
Everybody who watches college sports has an opinion
About this role
Opinion about
Fiero
What's morally right or what
What's best for the athletes but we're different question
Is this legal
In most Industries if a bunch of different companies got together and decided hey we're going to cap wages it would be against
What's the lot call the cartel
And the government would put a stop to
So
Is the NCAA an illegal cartel
Or is there something special about college sports that makes a difference
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm taking bolts
And I'm Robert Smith
This is not some idle question that we cooked up sitting around the office
In the past few years College athlete has started suing the NCAA
Saying we should be paid
We should get to share in the profit
Trailer show
The legal question
Should the free market come to college
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online
Presents and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layouts along with features including e-commerce functionality
And mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial and when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
The face of these lawsuits is a guy named Eric Bana
Ed O'Bannon is a former college basketball player and he got involved with this whole thing really buy a quince
A few years ago
Bannon says
Hangout app
We're playing catch
Football out in the front yard and
Uno
Last night my kid was playing video game you want to check it out you know you're on it
Your honor
As in you Ed O'Bannon are one of the characters in this basketball video game
Obama was a star forward at UCLA
In 1995 his senior year
The team won a national championship
Sports Illustrated put a shot of O'Bannon write on the cover
And that was
Pretty much Ed O'Bannon speak
As a basketball
I played two years in a row in NBA
It didn't go well
Play in Europe for a while
By the time his friend tells him he's in a video game O'Bannon is living near Las Vegas
Selling cars at a local Toyota.
Yes sir I'm going to see myself in a
Video game penis pain go inside kid blows up the game
NCAA
And O'Bannon fees
He's a video game version of his
22 year old self
The game doesn't use his name
But everything else about the video Ed O'Bannon
That was you know 680 225 lb
You know the guy was bald-headed left-handed third number 31 Jersey
And I was like you know
That is me I can't believe I'm on this video game
I was pretty fired up you know I was excited I mean
Who wouldn't be excited
To see themselves on a video game
How are you in the video game
It was the video Ed O'Bannon
As good as the real little Banner
Good question
He was that day back was better I got to be honest
And then it just kind of a joking way o'bannon's friend point something out
While he's playing
You know my friend he says
What's crazy about this is
You know we paid
I don't know how dollars or whatever for the game and you didn't see any of it
You didn't get a dime
And
You know when he said it
I felt like I've been kicked
O'Bannon knew the rules
When he went to play at UCLA
He got a scholarship
And he agreed that
No matter how much money UCLA basketball made he would not get paid
That's the way college sports of work for a long time
What time will Bannon saw himself in the video game
A lot of people were starting to question
And not just former athletes
Lawyers
They said hey
Do something older than the NCAA
He called the Sherman Antitrust Act
Passed away back in 1890
And right there
Infection what it says
A conspiracy
In Restraint of trade
Is declared to be illegal
It's antitrust law that says it would be illegal for Coke and Pepsi to get together and agree that
Play Paul cans of Coke and Pepsi will henceforth cost
$3 each
For that matter to the illegal for them to get together and say
We're tired of competing against each other to hire the best workers the best whatever
Soda in
So we're going to agree to cap wages for all soda engine
That would definitely be illegal
Now sports leagues are kind of weird animals
Almost a hundred years ago the Supreme Court said that professional baseball was exempt from federal antitrust
Gary Roberts an expert in antitrust law in Sports Indiana University
Told us
For a sports League to exist at all
The different business
This is the team
They really have to get together
They have to make agreement
All of the teams have to agree on
What teams are going to be in the league where they're going to play what times are going to play
What are we going to charge for the tickets
When we play each other
Are we going to have the game on television
You can't have the product
Unless
You have agreement
And over the years courts have explicitly recognize that these kind of agreements
Are good for
Good for fan
That's because
Fans really like sports League
They don't have anything to watch without him
Some agreements that would possibly be antitrust violations in other Industries
R Finance
So no one questioned it when the NCAA was formed to regulate college sports
Make some rules for everyone
But in the past few decades
The NCAA started changing in this basic way
Money started pouring in
One of the big reasons all that money started coming in
Is this guy
My life change
Change when I
Took a job with Nike
India
19 West 7778
Sonny Vaccaro
Remember that 80 million dollar University of Michigan shoe deal
We mentioned at the beginning of the show
The car was the first guy
To bring that kind of sponsorship deal to occur
It started back in the 70
College
And Beckham college basketball was not much of a business
Coaches even a big schools were making around $50,000 a year
Keras basically driving around in a rental car saying the coaches hate if your team wears are shoes
We'll pay you a few thousand dollars
And I went to Nike and I
Do you want to sell shoes I'll tell you
South shoes paid college coaches
Give them the shoes for nothing
People shiting their fan base will see it no buy your product and that basically
The Genesis of the whole
The whole scene
This is totally above board by the way is not violating any rules
And not surprisingly lots of coaches are happy to take money until their players to wear Nikes
By the 80s
Everybody was paying School
Reebok got into it Adidas got into a conference got into it
Michaela starts cutting million-dollar
Outfit whole University athletic department
Nike
More and more money pours into college sports
Everything's fine with this
Keep working the shoe business making these deals
But there's one thing two
Does bug
The college players not getting any of them
Finally in 2007
Sonny Vaccaro camp
Picatinny
Quit his job
He basically becomes
An activist
Start spending his time telling anyone will listen
It schools
Really should be allowed to pay off
Eventually a big-time Law Firm
Disinterest
They might be able to file a lawsuit
But they need players
Penny plant
And sunny is the guy with the Kinect
So he starts making calls
I went down my list
I said okay
List all disk
And I talked
Everybody was enthusiastic
But no one said yes
They were afraid of maybe they couldn't go back to their University maybe they'll be their names we taking down from the wall fan
They're afraid they couldn't get a job in coaching
This thing was hard
Got it dude wants to do
What Dad sue the NCAA always likes doing the church
Uterus has given calls metal band
Former UCLA basketball
Open says that's interesting but doesn't sign on
A while later though after the video game thing O'Bannon calls
And Eddie simister Carol
I just saw my face on EA Sports
The game and I was at my friend's house last night
That thing you were talking to me about this court case black pasta lawyers
Anna's God is my judge
That's how it happened
Eddie O'Bannon called me
Felt he was wrong
And wanted to talk to somebody
In 2009
The cases filed in Federal
Ed O'Bannon vs the NCAA
And the judge decide
This is not an open and shut case
It goes to trial
And as it often happens with lawsuits
This particular case was not some broad giant challenge to the whole concept of amateur sports
This case was strictly Limited
In court o'bannon's lawyer said colleges should be allowed to pay athletes
Who appear in video game
Score on TV
Other cases filed in the last year they go further
They argue that school should be allowed to straight up pay athletes
The place
Yeah and all the cases make the same
Basic
They say under antitrust law each school should be able to decide if
If it wants to pay its players or not and
Players should be able to choose
Schools that offer them
Better deals more money
More benefit
Yeah just like workers
In any other end
But
Antitrust law is not just
About work
It's also about consumers
Remember when we brought up earlier in the show
Hypothetical
Coke and Pepsi colluding to charge $3 a can
That would clearly harm consumers
And that's why it's illegal
When the NCAA went to court in your van in case they argue
This ban on paper
For college athletes
It doesn't hurt
The fan
It doesn't hurt the concealed
In fact
The NCAA said
This is
Good for
Think about this way
If you decide to go see a football game
You have a choice
You can watch an NFL game on Sunday the best
The planet
Professionals at the peak of their careers
Or you can go see college game on Saturday also fun
But they're amateurs
The kids
People who are not Pros who are not getting
The NCAA argues that it is good for consumers to have these two very different choice
These two very different products
The pros
Any amateurs
The NCAA says this hope not paying players thing
This is what fans are coming out for when they come out to watch college football
It's not a flaw in the product it is the product
Law professor gay Robert sums up the NCAA
If you force us to treat this like a labor market then you're forcing us
They have professional sports and that's
Denying the consumer the opportunity to have amateur sports
Despite multiple calls and emails the NCAA did not provide anyone to
The interview
But their argument does have some historical wait in legal search
A Supreme Court Justice
John Paul Stevens
Even made this argument back in the 80
He said yeah
Banning payments to players allows this unique thing
Amateur college sports to exist as we know it
It means more consumer choice
It's good for competition
O'Bannon and the other plaintiffs say
College sports have changed a lot since that Supreme Court Justice
Said that in like an idiot
The games become much more commercial there's so much more money involved
Advance
Just don't care that much anymore whether players get paid
What seems like a straightforward legal question
Does the ban on paying college athletes
Violate antitrust law
The one that turning on this
Squishy fuzzy issue
What do fans want
Soap Robert
You and I to understand this issue
We went out last Saturday and did a little investigative work
We snuck into a sports bar filled with die-hard University of Michigan fans drinking Coors Light
About no Coors Light
It's actually a great Michigan Beer Bell's Two Hearted Ale
Of course
Because every TV in the place is playing at Michigan Michigan State game
Get me referred to at the beginning of the show
So we watch the game along with them talk to fan
At first they seemed to validate the ncaa's legal art
The fans we talked to
Did not want college players to be just like the pros
My name is Emily I went to the University of Michigan and graduated in 2013
Would you care if the
Players on the University of Michigan team got paid to play
Yeah I would because
In my mind someone who plays football for the University of Michigan is getting a
Free diploma with the university Michigan a stamp
On it which is
Worth a lot how much
About $80,000 and
Some of us had to pay for that exact stamp
My name is Clarence. I went to the University of Michigan and I graduated in 1989
Would you care if I the way I just got last week I went up to Michigan game
I got my first tattoo
Big block at my my ankle
Mazel tov
So here's the question
Would you care if college football players got paid to play football
I don't think I should get paid now
I think they should get paid later
I think the better course of action is to set up some sort of fun afterwards
But when we have to question another way
Got another in
How would you feel if athletes got paid
But what would you do
Would you still consume the product
Would you stop coming out to watch the games at the players were getting paid
I wish I could say that I would stop
But as a Michigan Wolverine I don't think I could
Even in a way you didn't like how they just started writing checks to sign to sign kids
Would you still come out and watch the game
Absolutely because
Tumi
I can divorce the concept of the business of College athletics
I'm actually kind of entertainment value that I get out of
Do that
That is the argument against
The NCAA
These fans at least the ones we talked to said if colleges were to pay the players
They will still bite
They will still buy The Wolverine hats
And the Wolverine t-shirts
And the Wolverines
The judge's ruling in your ban in case came down this
She found in favor of O'Bannon
She said it is a violation of antitrust Law Firm
Colleges to get together and agree
Ecologist cannot pay
At least when it comes to things like video games
But before College athlete everywhere start rolling out the keg
Thanks for the victory party
The judge did have some caviar
She said called sports are indeed
Different than the pros
It is okay she said for colleges
Limit the payment
Two players
She even said a number
$5,000 a year
Just like the guy with the tat wanted
The judge said that the money could be held in trust until the players are out
Ed O'Bannon is likely to come out of this whole thing with a few thousand dollars
Mostly to pay him first time in the
But he says he's happy with the judge's decision he's glad the rules are.
The bigger question should students be allowed to get a check for playing football or basketball
That black we decided another
It was one filed earlier this
It's been three years since we did the show
After the break we will have a quick update of where things stand now
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Capital One is reimagining Bank
I offering accounts with no fees or minimums that can be opened from anywhere in 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
So okay that ruling came down in the O'Bannon case
The NCAA appealed and in 2000
15 to the 9th circuit came out with it
The appeals court
Overturned the part of the ruling that said colleges could pay student-athletes upped
The $5,000
So here we are in 2017
Student-athletes still do not get
But the appeals court did say
Schools could offer scholarships that are a little bit more jidenna
So today
Student athletes get scholarships that cover a little bit more they cover not only room and board and tuition
But also things like money to buy clothes and to travel back and forth
Between home and school
Finally this
Broader questions a big question of paying student-athletes
It is still alive legal issue
That case that we mentioned at the end of the show the case about paying athletes to play sports
That case is likely to go to trial
Is there a cartel in your life
MLS
Play Planet Money on NPR. Org or find us on Facebook or Twitter
Today Show was originally produced by Thea Benin of the rerun was produced by Alice while
If you speak Spanish or you want to learn Spanish
And you were looking for another podcast to listen to
I have great news for you
You should listen to radio ambulante
Which is a podcast
Storytelling in Spanish
Right now they're doing a series on Cuba
Volante
You can find it on the NPR one app or wherever you get your pipe
I'm Jacob Goldstein
Thanks for the