Support for this NPR Podcast in the following message come from The UPS Store
Offering services from shredding to printing to mailbox
And instead of closing this Memorial Day weekend
May 24th and 25th
The UPS Store is doing another thing altogether
Opening
The UPS Store
Everything for small business
And of course shipping
Maybe the most dramatic thing to happen in economics
In the last year
Happened in India
On November 8th
At 10 p.m.
Prime minister Narendra Modi
Got on TV
VM out of nowhere
Said
All of the money in your wallet
It is totally worthless
Starting now
Be have decided
Got the 500 rupee
Empower the rupee currency notes
Presently in use
Will no longer be
Legal tender
Prom midnight
Moonlight
500000 rupee notes
85% of the cash in India
The pie 100000 rupee notes
Hearted by Antonis Clemente
Will become
Just
Barclays
Piece of paper
Worthless pieces of paper
And imagine that
Imagine President Trump gets on TV and says all of the 10 20 50 and $100 bills in your wallet
Not worth anything anymore
Any is not like the US where most people have credit cards and debit cards
90% of business transactions in India happen in cash
And what of that cash is
Do use modi's term black
Money back money is basically any money that is outside
Tax system
It's kind of a catch-all phrase for corruption in India
Moody said you have one month
To take your cash to the bank
And exchange it for these new bills that we have just mint
And you can change out a maxim about $60 a day
Digital diesel lot of money for most Indians most Indians live on less than
$2 a day
How much money for wealthy
Indians and this limits Edmodo
Criminals and big-time tax evaders
Who did stuff with his big stacks
The cash
Country Bill Gates
Thank you very much
Thanks a lot
Bharat Mata
After Modi speech India's entire economy
Ground to a halt
People are still on your 4 days exchange old money
Millions of Indians don't have bank accounts David Bowie died of shock but others committed suicide
Million people waited for 8 hours in the blazing sun to change their money at the banks
Small businesses went bankrupt because
Nobody had any money to buy anything
Baby died because his parents didn't have cash for a taxi to the hospital
Ranjan Gupta travel to the central bank in New Delhi on his farm in Gujarat
18 hour Journey
His wife had just died and he had found three thousand rupees
About $45 worth of old bills that she had been saving in her sorry
But the 30-day period to change money without
Solange and headed to the central bank in New Delhi because he heard that they could make exception
So he came here with his money and his wife's death certificate
What do people at the bank said
Nope you're too late you missed the deadline
Your cash is worthless
He was standing on the sidewalk outside of the bank and he showed his cash to be fans the bills out
And his hands were shaking
You told me this money represents months of farm work I can't afford to lose it
Why have you done this
What was he thinking and
How did he come up with this plan
I started looking into this
And I kept seeing one
My name is Alibaba
Anil bokil
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Three on the show we need the man who pitched this idea to move
And this man this man brought one of the biggest economies in the world to its knees
1.3 billion people is not a famous academic policymaker or government minister
He didn't even study economics
What did you study in school
Any idea that study HardieBacker
Because I want life is such a bad read Institute
So wait what did you study
It turns out and you'll plan is not about economics
Or even politics
Anil bokil says he's on a spiritual Quest
To fix India's economy we'd like to say a quick thank you in
Share a message from one of our sponsors State Farm
State Farm is much more than just an insurance company they're also committed to making a positive impact in the commune
EBay surf
One way is through neighborhood of good a program connecting people who want to make a difference with causes looking
For local volunteers discover over 31,000 social causes listed at neighborhood of good.com
And start turning the power of caring into the act of doing
State Farm here to help life go right
The term for what Prime Minister Modi
Did on November 8th
Is demonetization the government D money is the Pay-Per-View
I've been spending
Its power is currency is taken away
This usually happens when a government Falls or country has terrible in
India did it once back in the 70s
But the building's monetize were bills that most Indians did
Anil was a child at
That time
At least
Thank you
Do you mind if I ask your age
My
I know close to buy this
Oh no I didn't seem like this is very good at not answering questions
Tokyo has
Presents he's tall and lean Lumina
Looks like someone turn the flashlight on inside of it
Is deep set eyes and is very playful smile
I'm in a conference room at a hotel for he said
He would give me the same presentation he given to prime minister Narendra Modi
The one that had
Rock the entire Indian economy
Emil grew up in literature in agricultural City in central India
Both of his parents were School t
Teachers and Anil wasn't shy sensitive
I made roulette then I would good social Observer
I cannot observe very keenly that kind of
High-sensitivity I have
There was a lot of poverty in literature
Why people living on less than $1 a day
Good butterbeer.
I'm uses the economic situation around him didn't make any sense there was plenty of food
Plenty of money all around
Are all these people who couldn't get at any other
It seems so unfair and so
And you studied engineering and got a job as a mechanical engineer he ran a team that designs specialty machines for
Pharmaceutical
I used to create something new
So you don't Asians wear their wedding such a kind of
But then you'll never stop thinking about poverty
Is Minecraft going back to the same questions that he's had when he was a kid
Get a group of his engineering friends started getting together to talk about social issues
Sit around and drink tea and wonder why India struggled so much economic
What is the basic cause of all this mess
Why this happening in India
That's so something is wrong with your system
We used to enjoy that
These guys were engineers
They spent all of their time making machines and systems to fix problem
So they started to thing
Society is a system of government
Something is happening in those systems that is resulting in
Poverty
So let's fix the system
What is a product
So that's why we are in for sizing on the technical correction technical solution we need to have
And you got more and more into the side
You stay up late mapping out the process that was resulting in all of this poverty
Quality
Withdraw all these diagram
Just like he did when he was designing a machine
Finally he showed his works when a condom
And The Economist was really interested he thought it was really intriguing and he got a group of his colleagues together and a Stan
Neil to present his ideas
What happened at the end of The Talk
So it was very nice it was amazing
Standing Ovation for that
Did you think like this is what I've got to do
With my life
Yellow this is my duty that Destiny has given me this Tuesday
Edward 40
Kautz
Anil quit his job and started traveling all over India
Thousands of miles
Giving his talk to
To anyone who would listen
Local government officials professors business people how many times have you given it
Like
100 *
Thousand times
I'll get more
More than a thousand
A new move to the city of Pune
He thought it would be a good base for him it's kind of an international
Some of his very passionate engineering friends even followed him there
And they founded this
Devoted to these ideas
Arthrogram
So it means the economic Revolution
Is that
And you believe in in this revolution
Yes
Archer prunty isn't very big
There were about a dozen members mostly accountants
And engineers
And they meet here at this little cafe a couple times a month
And so I joined the one more
Hello
Hello nice to meet you outside drink
Really strong tea
Oh yeah I would listen and talk economics
Exactly economics
You've been a member for how many years
I think I'm giving birth
Lanius
9 years with long time
This is the part
What is the meaning of life and what should I do
So this isn't just economics this is like
Almost a religion
At this meeting and Neil is Revere
It was actually at the
And everybody kind of talked about him and he's
Hushtone
Anil is there visionary
He's this inspired compassionate man who
Left his job
Tom devoted himself entirely to making people's lives better
Fixing India's economy
Our mama is the brother of your mother
So it's like your uncle and you call him up Guru Uncle group was meeting a couple times a month and year was traveling
All over India hacking his ID
And then in 2013 and you'll got his big break
The chance to pitch his plan to Narendra Modi
When I meant to be somebody was not private Easter
That time it was a chief minister of one province that is Gujarat
Still word on the street was that Modi was going place
In certain ways he was controversial but he was also known as a politician who made things happen
You actually have the ability to cut through India's notorious bureaucracy
And get things done
Moody was also known for thinking outside the box get a business background and he didn't do kind of typical pallet
Kitchen things
And you have the feeling that this
Might be his guy
So you started trying to get a meeting with Modi
Sophos writing emails and letters to him
Finally he got a response
Okay nobody will see you
You have 9 minutes
The pitcher plant
Social reception time for me
You can do this in 7 minutes
Annual book you flew to Gujarat with a couple members of Arthur
He fired up his projector and started the PowerPoint presentation
The kid literally given a thousand times
The four
The one he's about to show me
You just put your
Who's on silent
And just to give you an idea of how the guru Uncle rolls
He does not click is on PowerPoint
What are the arthakranti members does it for him
When he says this
Click
And here it is
The PowerPoint presentation
That rocked India
So we're looking at a it's like an apartment building with a bunch of pipes and like the height of apartment shoes
The responsibility of God
It's a cartoon drawing of a high-rise
Apartment building
Kind of a 1990s style graphic
The building has all these pipes bringing water into it
And the building represents India
And the pipes represent
Resources
Resources that the Indian government is giving to
With citizens
But the pipes in the picture are all twisted and cracked and water is spraying out into a big pool on the ground
And this is Niall
Is the prop
The gushing of resources are called
Black money
A separate oldest Farmingdale
That's a paddlin
Click
And uses these pipes should be bringing plenty of water into the building
India should have enough
Tax revenue to support its
But the system is broken
Money is getting sucked and siphoned out of it
Tax evasion and Corruption
The building does not have enough water
And Shadow economy
Has developed
Flick
In the next picture of a giant head slides and next to the apartment building
Is smiling and wearing sunglasses
And sucking water out of the pond
Black money
With a giant straw
And you see the face the size of face
It's like a huge head
Is there
That's a good option
Book smiling and wearing sunglasses
Like a boss for mafia movies
Mafia like this
This is the corruption that is keeping India so poor
Know who is Safaree
Click
A new character appears in the
Little hunched over man with
His hands cupped under a spigot at the end of the pipe
He's waiting for a drop
The Chi-Lites the last
Mad unprivileged Commonwealth
It is around 50% of our Papa
He's our poor farm
He's not getting resources from
Sister
As long as the pipes are
Leaking the government will not get the money at me
Corruption will grow
The head will get bigger
And there will not be enough
For the poor farmer
So
How do you fix
And watch the global definition of money
I don't know
What do you think medium of Exchange
Easter definition
You look upset with me
Your soul
So just got corrected
I mean
You have to get rid of the big head
But for that what we have to correct
The black money the messed up pipes
Yes that's the solution we are asking
Fart
So excited that I got a right and you'll says India needs to make the money that is flowing through its economy
Trackable
Taxable
Cash
Is not tracker
Couple is anonymous
In order to really
Fix the pipes you have to move away from cash and towards credit cards and digital payment
Those are transparent and traceable
Only then will India have enough water for the whole building
Only then will the poor farmer
If you share
And so and you'll conclude
Any needs to start getting rid of cash
Demonetization
So you so you should slide to Modi of that this is the simplest way we can explain
Did he say anything about the cartoon
Full nicely urologist understanding of what
Plus Whitening
In fact booty got so into it
It doesn't help that the meeting went from its original 9 minutes
Some kind of a country.
If I get a chance I will do it
He said that you said that
The following year Modi was elected
Did prime minister of India
In a landslide
Daniel said he started having calls and meetings with modi's advisors
And a couple of years after that
On the evening of November 8th
Anil was at his little shared office space with some other quantity members
All the sudden
Everybody's phone started
Show me the food my phone wasn't ringing
Sing did you just see Modi on TV
I think he's doing your plan
The crazy plan that a bunch of Engineers had cooked up in their off time
The planet Anil believed in so much he left
Job
His home and devoted his life to it
The planet Neil had showed a thousand times to a thousand different people
I just
Happen
The prime minister of India
Had actually done it
Is it exciting to watch it play out in real life
If you don't refrigerate
I want joy
Next fight
You call it in light
I'm in light
Your light
I was not sure how to process any of this
The animated slides the giant Mafia head
The enlightenment
So I took everything to Bhaskar chakravorti
He's originally from India and now he teaches economics at
But yesterday I think the Indian context is is
Is helpful
First on the whole spiritual aspect of Arthur crying
Bhaskar says India has a long history of Genius ideas given to People by
By God
He told me the story of srinivasa ramanujan
A young man from the south of India yet almost no formal training in math
And totally on his own
He came up with a bunch of really sophisticated theorems that have been done by some of the best mathematicians in the world
Been asked
He said that the goddess
Spoke to him
That's nice
And gave him the proof
In many ways
People in India are actually quite comfortable being a going back and forth between science and spirituality
The lines are
Sometimes quite blood
They get bored here to
We have Christian capitalist and religious organizations that work with politicians
All the time
Alan Greenspan once said the philosophy of Ian Rand provided stability to his life
And anyway says Bhaskar taking advice from an outsider
Kind of Moody Style
Booty Prides himself on Auntie Lita
Different kind of going with her
Is got
But what I really wanted to ask Bhaskar about was the economic
He's an economist
And I wanted him to look at a Neal's plan and tell me what he thought
His first impression was
This is a really smart
Really well-thought-out
But it is very much of an engineering
Approach which takes a whole bunch of different economic and social political issues and finds logical into
Connections among then and then comes up with some conclusion
That makes Economist nervous system
Because Economist rely on data
They compare one changing data set to another changing data set
It's nuanced
The real world is a messy place and
I simply putting these
The system diagrams on a page
Is not a sufficiently strong argument for
Policy
Princeton mafiosos getting money
Is not a direct result of people not paying their tax
But you are related but it's not that simple it's not water in a pipe
And just because people pay more in taxes does not mean that the mafia will get less money
Or the corruption will go
Bhaskar says society and economy
It's not a machine it's a complex living thing made up of
Complex living people
People that you really need to take into consideration when you're making policies
That's the problem
So-called educated
Train to Columbus to Houston
Make use of every statistical data
I ran all of this by Anil
And he says this is exactly why problems like poverty never get fit
Economist an endless data collect
Endless speculating about
Consequences of every possible action
Meanwhile the system create poverty
More entrenched
And nothing
I was talking I just kept thinking of suranjan Gupta
The Grieving man who found the money in his wife sorry
Annuals
Queen logical drawings
Made a mess in his life they cost him real harm
Inconvenience
There was some harm I mean some people lost their businesses there were people who died standing in line I mean it would know if you put
Used to die in a barrel
Because
You're not emotional about it
But I mean you're such a
Compassionate person I mean all of this is to help
The guy on the end but it it's striking me that people that struggle the most words like the little old man at the end of the pipe
I mean did you feel responsible for that
She's a locked new to this kind of supply
But they suffered more because of demonitization
The treatment may feel like some kind of a pence before
But
It is for the correction of Ulysses
This is what Modi like about his plan
It was a solution
Bold crazy amazing solution
Some of India's biggest most complicated diseases
Corruption and poverty
Nvidia will be totally different
Totally different
A very Grateful Dead we are looking forward
Do this to Daniel
And it will hurt
People will struggle things will be bad
And then
The country will start
To heal
Poverty will end people get their dignity back
India will be the Great
Economic Powerhouse it was always meant to be
In the next episode we have part two of the story will get how a meal book kills plan
Play doubt we go to different parts of India talk to people in different walks of life
How did modernization affect them we have a little preview after this
Support for this podcast and the following message come from The Economic Development Authority of Bexar
Fairfax County Virginia
Home to more than 350 cyber companies and 8900 technology-related firms
Details and power of ideas. Org
You gotta know
Lot of emails about the inspired us to actually go to India
Please tell us what you want to drive out of money it will make a difference at shapes the show email us Planet Money A10
Npr.org or find us on Facebook
Twitter Planet money's editor is Brian Dorsett Alex goldmark produces the show
Today's episode was produced by Sally Howe
And I have a few people I would like to thank
Nishant dahiya aparna Lori Allison Traeger
Asheville Salt Cave and Travis Scott.
Looking for another podcast to listen to check out up first it is only about 10 minutes long but they pretty much cover
For all of the news you need to know for the day in those 10 minutes
Check out up first on the NPR one app or wherever you get your podcast
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith thanks for listening
Next time on Planet Money we travel to different parts of India and look at the effect demonitization has had on
And ask them what they think of it
70 trucks
Soft tomato
Matrone
On the road
My farmers
Because of this monetization
Mobile
These kind of problems
Pittsburgh Animal Shelter