Hate Stacey Vanek Smith here
Today's episode is a rerun for support of the story back in 2015
We have a little update for you at the end
A few years ago if you lived in Charlotte North Carolina and you bought your first house
There was a store you could go to get just about everything you need
A dishwasher a nice flat screen
A refrigerator even
Appliances
You want one of those
Charlotte is known as the Queen City
And Queen City appliances was an institution
This family-owned business
Hatts17 stores
And then one day in 2012
Word got around town the Queen City
And on February 2nd a story ran in the local
Paper
After 60 years in business
The store had filed
For bankruptcy
This is something that happens every day in this country
Last year we look
Sup 34000 companies
Could not pay their bills
And went bankrupt
Bankruptcy scenes in
Give me feels like
This terrible icky thing
But some people will tell you it's one of the greatest things
About this
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm sonari glinton
Stacey Vanek Smith today on the show The Story of Queen City appliances and bankruptcy in this country
We are really good at going bankrupt and it may actually be one of our economies
Secret weapon
This message comes from NPR sponsor squares
Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their own website
Using customizable layout
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobiledit
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online price
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
That cheery voice you heard at the top of the show selling you a washing machine for Labor Day
That is ready player
CEO of Queens
I went to visit him in Charlotte
He is super friendly and charismatic
And he kept offering to warm up by coffee
He did it for you
Oh thank you
Making friends in Charlotte I really like coffee
Coratti's dad actually started
Queen City Appliance
Andrade showed me an old photo of him at an
Early trade show
Standing next to an actual celebrity
Dentist picture back in the 50s that my dad with Miss America
Stop and come out of the service you can see their two
Body actually spent a few minutes examining this picture
And she was not looking at Miss America he was looking at the old TV
Trying to figure out what model it was
He's got this encyclopedic knowledge of televisions and appliances
He has been in this business
A long time
Sweeping the floors and I was eight years old and work on a delivery trucks and I was 12 or 13 years old and then send you
Graduate high school you can get on the sales floor so that summarize on the sales floor
Roddy eventually went on to business school and when his dad died right he became the CEO of
Clean City
The family business
Was in his hands
And for a while business was great
Charlotte
Booming and riding his family did what a lot of
Business owners where do
Doing at the time
They borrowed money and expanded
Ashley Barros
A lot of
And they expanded a lot
Queen City went from 8 stores
17 stores
Venom 2009
You see where this is
The housing bubble
No new homes no one was buying
Refrigerators
Dishwashers
Used mattresses
Sales
Kept dropping
And dropping
I want to call the eternal optimist but I always felt
Just couldn't get any worse and couldn't get any worse and couldn't get any worse
And well
It did get worse
The math just didn't add up anymore
The money from sales just
Was it enough
To pay the bills
He's going to have to do the thing that had been
Deep in the back of his mind
For a while
The thing that any small business is trying to avoid especially a family business
Bankruptcy
Bankruptcy is a grueling process
There are a lot of stuff
The first thing you have to do is call a lawyer
And then you have to sign all of these papers with
Any of the other owners of the business
In this case
That was Ronnie's mother
Francis player
Who is 83 years old
The time and they went to the office together and
Filled out the paper
They filed for bankruptcy
And that moment when you file for bankruptcy
Everything Changes I hadn't actually appreciated this
But when you file for bankruptcy
Public and all the details
Cause of your failure are also
It's there in the court papers for anyone to read
How much you owe Who You Are
It's all out there for anyone to see and just minutes after riding is Mom filed the documents
The Charlotte Observer publisher
The short story online
Rodney's phone started ringing off the
His son who is away at college
Also saw the news
Any new things are difficult for us but I don't
I think
The dinosaur filing at the public Airwaves and you know he sent me a text simplenote
Uok
Rowdy was not okay
In fact even now when he talks about the bankruptcy his whole demeanor changes
He looks down he starts fiddling with things
Gets quieter
He told me that day that he filed for bankruptcy was one of the worst days of
You know your friends your neighbors is difficult
I walk around town when you got something like that hanging over your head
Ronnie's mom Frances
Had an especially hard time
She had helped start this business
60 years
Before
She still work there four days a week
In accounts
And for her bankruptcy
Was just not something
I really did struggle with it lost a lot of sleep over
Not easy to get up and go to church that Sunday morning it really wants on after it came out in the newspaper
This was a terrible moment for rowdy
And his family
In most countries
This would have been the end of the story
Are the banks and his creditors would have come in and repossess the ranges that
Reset
Everything would have shut down
And all the pieces of the business
This would have been sold often
That would have been it
But in the United States there is another path
Chapter 11
As in Chapter 11
Of the bankruptcy
And it is a wafer
Companies
They can't pay their bills to
Not die
To keep going
Any idea predates
Appliance stores buy a lot actually it goes back to the railroad
That we learned this from historian David skeel
I have been studying bankruptcy about 30 years I just fell in love
I fell in love
Have not fallen out of love ever since
In the 1800's
Railroads
We're going bankrupt all the time
In the 19th century nearly every time we had a major economic
Crisis
A large number of railroads
Would fail at one point in the late 19th century almost 20%
Of all of the railroad track in the
What the country
Had failed
I had to fall to head
And one particular railroad got into big trouble
The Wabash River
Then it ran from Buffalo New York
Out to sync
The owners had borrowed a lot of money
To lay the track
Then the economy hit
And suddenly the Wabash rail line was in
Big trouble
It couldn't pay its debt
But nobody wanted the railroads to actually go out of
If you double the money and they
Pay you back sure you could I don't know I guess go and see is a bunch of railroad track and melt it down and sell it or something
Message
Where you really wanted was to have a functioning railroad that's where the value was
Scaring people and cattle and grain
And if that happens if you get the railroad up and running again maybe you could actually get your money back
And then Yuan
Everyone
Really would be better off
Keeping the railroads open was in everyone's interest
So instead of
You know shutting down the railroad or everyone rushing in to see what p
I could get everyone got together
All the people that loan money to the railroads
The people who ran the railroads got together and worked out a deal a way to forgive some of the money the railroads own
So don't mind could stay open and they could have finished
We get more their money back
School says this was a major economic
Innovation
That was unprecedented
In well test
No other country had had a system like this that was designed that the shutdown substantial
Businesses when they failed but but the reorganized
To give them another chance
So what did
The world's think of this
New kind of bankruptcy
What I thought we were crazy as they often do
You can kind of see their point if you set up a system where when companies sort of screw up and you for
Forgive a bunch of debt
And you let them
Keep going you might end up creating this whole environment where businesses just do
Crazy risk
He things you can end up encouraging the kind of thing you really want to avoid
Turn America we came down on the side allowing bankrupt
Is 2/2 a sec
And when ready player file for bankruptcy that's what he decided he wanted
To try and
When you file for bankruptcy it's like hitting a big pause button
All the people you owe money to
For a moment
You don't have to pay
But you do have to make a list for the court
Of everyone you owe money
Everyone
Roddy's list
You showed it to me
General electric companies on here for
In a $556,000 here's a freight company AAA Cooper Road 865
$1,000 to
Okay here's a $40 customer refund
In all
Rowdy was millions of dollars in
I mean in this is
A small biz
Business that's that's a lot of washers
And dryers
Yeah and the odds for a company like Queen City appliances
Emerging from bankruptcy
CR not good
For small companies
Only about 20%
Make it out
Queen City Appliance
To stay alive Rowdy was going to happen
To convince
General Electric and whirlpool
And the banks you're a bunch of money to
That they would be better off
If they allowed him to
Keep his doors open
He's going to have to convince them
And he was going to have to convince in this is really important
Adjudge
The judge place
Huge roll in Bangkok
We tried to talk to the judge in rotties case and
She wouldn't talk to us
Common with judges
But we did find a judge who would
Bankruptcy judge in California
Her name is Deborah
Bruce Altman and she ran through the obstacles that right
She said one of the reasons it is so hard for small companies to make it out
Bankruptcy is it a lot of them go bankrupt
For really good reason
Not every business is meant to reorganize
Yeah I think about when I was a new lawyer you back in
The late 90s
The cases I was working on
Where are music stores
Like record stores
CDs that's just out of business
So it for a company like that
Your bankruptcy isn't going to help a business that just fundamentally
Can't be successful in this economy
Ronnie was going to have to put forward a specific plan and who
Would be painful
In court there would be an actual vote where all the people he owed money
With this side
Yes or no
Surety in
Queen City Appliance
Given a second chance
If they go to yes
Andrade would actually have to make it
It works meet specific learning targets
And along the way
Every little decision he was going to make
Had to be okayed by whirlpool
NGE
Everyone he owed money to
And Deborah Saltzman the judge says
A lot of CEOs just really
Can't handle this
I think
That for a CEO or someone who's used to running a corporation
He's probably had a fair amount of success given
Terranea Corporation to find yourself in financial distress is already
Pretty jarring
If you find yourself in bankruptcy court you have
Really a whole new world that you
Never been prepared for
Suddenly
Your decisions are subject to
Court oversight
Are there public
And any of your creditors can hear about what you're planning to do and object to it
So that is what Roddy was up at
After the initial filing
The Court gives you a little time to get up
Plan together business plan
And for the moment you can keep your doors
But immediately after that
Every decision Rowdy made needed Court
You have to get approval to pay his elect
Chrissy Bell
Had to get a special approve loan to do that
Even had to get approval to put gas in the delivery
So this is the weird feeling on the one hand they file for bankruptcy
On the other hand they still had hope
We could still be open for business
Bob one worked in customer relations
Answering a
Customers are actually calling us
Having heard it on the news and
They were
A bunch of concerned customers and
We just tried to assure them that
We were still here working through it
We were answering the phones in the lights were on
Bob says some customers just called
To say good luck
We're rooting for you
Thanks USA
Come on down
Combined dryer
Restart to draw up that plan to submit to court
Explain how he was going to fix the business
He hired a turnaround expert
Look through his books
And was very blunt
Mark Holden
You want to make it out of bankruptcy
Do you want to be profitable again
You're going to have to close some of your 17
I still have nightmares about that cuz we
You know I had to Lemon a lot of jobs and then you sit across the table from somebody tell him that you have to let him go
And I can really really hurt you in his car as you to be honest with you I still to this day think about those those time things
How many stores do you have now
We got four store
17 stores to four stores is a lot fewer
But it's a lot more than zero with
Would have been the alternative
Rowdy Hetzel layoffs
30 employees
But 75
Still got to stay with him
Body found his plan for how he was going to fix
All of his creditors
People he owed money to G
GE the banks
Electric Company
They all voted
And they said
Okay
Will give this a shot
Not everyone was going to get their money back
The local newspaper that he'd advertised then when things were very good got it
Tenth of what they roll
Whirlpool and GE were higher up in the pecking order
We get paid but it would take a while
Rowdy himself had put a bunch of money into the couple
And he wasn't going to
Backpack
Ronnie ran his four remaining stores as efficiently
Trying to cut costs
At every possible
Turn and also trying to sell as many stoves and
Refrigerators
Every week he had to submit a
Progress report
To the court
To show how much money was going out and how much money was going in
Queen City appliances was in bankruptcy for a year-and-a-half
But on August 27th 2013
It was over
Right.
An official document from the court
Saying is company was no longer
Bankruptcy
Actually he was waiting for it for
Take a few extra days and I thought it was but
Free checking your email like every 2 seconds
That was the highlight
Process
It is like the shortest legal document I have ever read
There's a speaker official-looking Court seal in one corner and there's just one sentence
It says
The chapter 11 case of the above named debtor
Is closed
Rottie threw a party for his staff
He showed them a documentary about Captain Ernest Shackleton and his crew
Surviving winter in the South Pole
He handed out Queen City strong bracelet
He still wears his everyday
And that was that
Queen City
What is back
Queen City appliances has been out of bankruptcy
For two years now
And brightest companies doing really well
Profits are way up
You took me to the back of one of his stores
Into the warehouse
Second show me around some of the appliances
During the bankruptcy trustee told me it was almost empty
Now they're huge boxes
So dishwashers 5 high you know laundry products are for high
Row after row of appliances that just makes you feel good
He shows me one type of new refrigerator and I start to get the feeling he's trying to sell it to me
The gala Hideaway Shelton actually breaks away
Obi-Wan right there your wandering around
Why do you say I'm going tricker
I think what you want in there too
Amana freezers
Yeah this is this again become the most popular type
Refrigerator
Looking back on this though right he doesn't exactly to see bankruptcy
She is one of America's greatest
Best inventions
He seems to see it as a
Huge pain
His mom though who at first thought bankruptcy
She was not a thing that
Good salad
Has turned around
Actually kind of a fan of
I think it's a very
Very good way for a company to continue
So you
Your mind was changed
About bankruptcy
Yes
I really want
It would have broken my heart if we close
And around town
Francis says
People were surprisingly accepting of the whole thing
They didn't see
It as a failure of them as a failure
Like that first Sunday morning after they filed
For bankruptcy
She was so nervous about
Going
Going to church all of their friends everybody was very supportive see you went to church and it was okay it was okay
Same seat
Same seat for how many years
In the US we've decided we want in a
Economy where the CEO of Ana
Appliance store
Can dream big
Expand really fast
And if it doesn't work out
River system for dealing with the mess
So the business
Can keep going and a lot of companies out there today that are healthy now have
Been through this process
A couple of companies that I cover
General Motors
Chrysler
United Airlines
Like almost every Airline
Marvel Comics the Texas Rangers ending
This is something
Embedded
NRC
Is that other countries have started looking at RB
In part because of what happened during the last four
Procession
Hundred thousands of
Bankrupt in the US
And some of them made it out
An economist say this is one reason that our economy
Bounce back
A bit faster than others
If the economy crashes
A company
As
A bad moment
It can you know eventually Shake It Off
It doesn't mean
The end
France Ireland Germany Spain Italy
They all modified their laws
Make them a little more like our chat
They decided
They like our system of sex
So by local
And save more
Acquaintance
Where you'll always find a right product
Right price
And real answers
Guarantee
CC here again we talk to Rowdy back in 2015 and we wanted to check back
With him and see how things have been going at Queen City will have an update for you right after this
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence and run your biz
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial and when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Hi Ronnie how are you Stacy
How do you say see how are you I'm good how are you it's been five years since rowdy
And his mom Francis first went through their bankruptcy
Paparazzi this week and he told me that after a few tough years things have been looking up
I finished growing dramatically in
Aren't a lot of people Wednesday
Play I can't know for sure a bunch of big box stores
Have been closing down in this area
And that has been a whole lot of new customers
Righty opened a new Queen City in June and has another store he plans to open up before the end of the year
Does this growth feel different than the gross before the financial crash
It does
It really does she know more conservative
Stolen people don't bodies at this have to work nowadays it's more more more
And we certainly are.
Car wiring conscious of the resources that will come in a different parts of the business to make sure it's going to pay off for us
This year is Queen City 65th
Anniversary congratulations guys
We always love to hear what you think of the show send us an email Planet Money at npr.org
Or find us on Facebook or Twitter
The show is produced by Francis Harlow and rerun was produced by Elisabeth Kubler-Ross
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Thanks for letting