Support for this in
NPR podcasts
The following message
Come from the UPS
Offering services from shredding
To printing to mailbox
And instead of closing this Memorial Day we
May 24th and 20
The UPS Store
He's doing another thing
All together
Opening
The UPS Store
Everything for small business
And of course shipping
Hey everybody Stacey and Cardiff here with a bonus
We're launching a new podcast here Planet Money it's
Called the indicator
Give it as a companion to Planet Money it is shorter faster user some would argue much better-looking
We can't we love our colleagues on Planet Money
They're very good looking
It's truth
So we wanted to say one of our recent episodes with you and if you like it go subscribe to it
Search for the indicator on the NPR one app or wherever you get your podcasts
Here's our latest show
I'm Stacey Vanek
I'm Carlos Garcia in this is the indicator from Planet Money
A show about work business in the account
Also a show where we are not afraid to go
Full Walden Pond
Yesterday the Federal Communications
Mission the FCC
Voted to end the policy called net
Neutrality
The turbo tie the item is adopted with editorial privileges Grant
Net neutrality is essentially a rule that internet providers have to treat all web traffic
So princess I can't decide
To block a website or to make some content
Fast
And the reason that neutrality such a controversial issue
Boils down to
Single number
And that number
As luck would have it is today's indicator
58%
58% of Americans
Abaxis
Two at most
One option for Broadband in
And card if you know some
Something about this
Oh hell yes I do
Send see what happened was it at the end of 24
Teen
I become Fed Up
With my internet and
Cable service
Okay
It just wasn't working very well
On top of that
The amount that I was paying each month had gone up
And nobody
Told me
And I called to complain innocence
See they said that they
What about it
When I started investigating what my options
Ensworth
4 cable
Internet
How it turned out that actually Time Warner really was
The only
Realized
Yeah yeah
I was pissed off and it said see what I decided what
Who is it I was to
Not just cut the cord on cable but I was just
Stop getting any
Time Warner service is no internet
Right in your apartment
Time Warner
Bus and ice
Said screw it
I'm just going to go a few months without the internet
And without cable and see how that goes and a few more months finally became
A whole year so
Zero dark
25th
4 Walden Pond
Walden Pond
Trina show we talk net neutrality and explore its
Deeply rooted connection to
Part of your cable situation also the cable situation of most of the people in this country
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org
If you live in New York and did both of us do this in the city where you know their likes
17 different Chinese restaurants in for black
Radius so how is it possible that you would have
One good option
Denver high speed
I don't know I wish there was somebody we could ask
In fact there is
I put this question to Shane Greenstein he teaches at Harvard
Oh that is it
Wonderful question okay tell me
She says the story starts back in the
There was this new thing called
Cable TV
No more rabbit ears much better
Picture but there was a problem
It cost a lot of money
Dig up the ground
And putting cable lines to every single house
Initially
When cable was first being built out at me
Was not affordable to have more than one firm because it wasn't height a cup
What city is really wanted cable to be available
The people they wanted the cable companies to invest in putting the lines in
But the cable companies at that time where small didn't have it
So they said okay
We will put in this expensive new infrastructure will take this risk and make cable available to everyone in the city
But we want something
We want you to promise US that
If we spend all this money
To put in these cable lines
We are going to be the only ones running cable to the houses in your city
They'd get a little bit of a
Monopoly like a little mini Monopoly
Uvalde overtime into that
Over the next few decades to things happen
When was
The internet and it turned out the best way to get fast internet
People's houses was
/ cable line
Any other thing that happened was that those many monopolies who owns the cable lines merged and
Merged again and became
That's so many Monopoly
This caused some problems
Shane Greenstein with a paper about one of the most
Famous exam
Samples where Comcast Cable company
Started demanding payments from Netflix
Saying hey Netflix if you want to be available to Comcast customers
Taipei
Netflix said no way
And suddenly Comcast customers who tried to watch movies on Netflix
We're just ended
World
Buffering
Worth noting Comcast is a part owner of
Flu a direct competitor tonight
Greenside said If This Were a regular competitive market
What Comcast did but not be such a big
I mean in that case of Comcast
My Netflix
I could just switch to another internet for
Right if there were competitive market with full transparency than users would punish
The providers you don't behave well
Other countries have solved this problem by breaking up the mini Monopoly
So people can choose from lots of different internet provider
In the US the most Americans do not have a choice about where they get their broadband
And so a few years back the Obama Administration
Put net neutrality in
And it said cable companies
How to treat all internet traffic
Soap for example Comcast is not allowed to favor Hulu over
It's like a bypass or something I guess it's a regulatory mechanism to try to limit the distortions of have
Limited options
That's exactly what it isn't it
It's found it on a
Pretty long history in the United States of doing this and things like railroads electricity and telephones
Yesterday the FCC voted to end net neutrality
Internet providers will not be officially obligated
Treat all website
Now Shane says things aren't likely to ratify
Will you change overnight
Lots of people are going to be challenging this in
Quartz
But still Comcast
Could potentially put Netflix into the buffering Zone once again
And if they do and Comcast is your only high-speed internet option
There will not be that much you can do about it
Except maybe get rid of
Internet altogether
Speaking of which Cardiff Garcia
Yes
You have to tell us what it was like to have no internet
I required a few adjustments
I did read more books and that was nice
On the other hand I also
Watch Netflix shows
Was on my iPhone holding it like
4in from my face
With the lights off like
A huge weird
And by the end of the year ride
Just sort of had enough
So
Shamefully I went crawling back
You got internet I got internet I got cable
Hell I even got showtimes Ronan a picture
Overcompensated for what I've been missing
The prior-year
That's how that story
I think they learned their lesson card I think I think you're at least what I learned mine
If you like this episode of the indicator please subscribe
Our listeners asked for it
And we are delivering now you're going to hear shows on everything from taxes to toll roads to mythical beasts
Just search for the indicator wherever you get your
Support for this NPR
In the following message come from Amica Insurance offering Auto home and life insurance
With personalized coverage and a reputation for exceptional service Amigo puts customers at their top right
Priority visit meet amica.com
NPR