Let's talk about cold beer in Indiana I understand that's been a big part of your life
Yeah it has been
This is Jay Ricker runs a chain of convenience stores in Indiana called Ricker's logic
And if it sounds kind of weary here there's a reason
He spent the last few months
Deep in the fine print of Indiana state law governing the sale of
Beer and wine
You can sell
Warmed
Home
Cold wine
But we can't sell
Colby
A lot of States have
Strange rules surrounding the sale of
In New York for example
You can only buy wine at these little kind of neighborhood wine stores
In New Hampshire if you can only buy liquor at
State-run stores
And in Indiana there was a rule
But you can sell cold beer in liquor stores and in restaurant
But not
Any thought well
Restaurants
Can sell cold beer
I got these little restaurants inside my stores
He dug into the fine print
And he with the help of his lawyers worked out a very precise way for his stores to sell
So you walk up to the counter and you say I'd like to get a six pack of beer
And so we cards
Let me ring you up
Then we get it out of a cooler that's behind a counter that you can't go to the can't be self serve that's a big No-No okay
Can we pull it out of there we put it in a sack
Walk around the counter we can't sit on the counter in
What you take it off the counter
Running a bar okay and then you walk
Shut the door after we handed to
It's that
Easy
Ricker's
Started selling cold beer just
A few weeks ago
And the Indiana liquor stores the other places allowed to sell cold beer
Didn't like it
They said Ricker's was quote
Thumbing their noses at the Indiana
So I went to one of those legislators should I said hey here's what we're doing
You know and we have followed the law
And
He
He admitted yes you have
But that's not the intent of the law
And we're going to change it
Just this week Indiana Senate Bill 538 passed out of committee
If it becomes a lot records will no longer be able to sell coal
This new law may also inadvertently band other places
From selling cold beer
Bowling alley
Golf Course
Which of course this is what always happens with find
Unintended consequence
And the solution to those consequences
More fine print
Printer prints hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Jacob Goldstein
Today in the show the fine print
Three stories about what happens when you actually read
There's a nice Midwestern family with a tan Minivan and a Nationwide Bank scheme
I think battle over the essence of the Snuggie
But first a fight over fine print
And printers
That just made it to the Supreme Court
We'd like to say a quick thank you and share a message from one of our sponsors State Farm State Farm as much
More than just an insurance
They're also committed to making a positive impact in the communities they serve
One way is through neighborhood of
Good a program connecting people who want to make a difference with causes looking for local volunteers
Discover over 31000 social causes listed at neighborhood of good.com and start turning the
Power of caring
Act of doing
State Farm
Here to help life
Go right
Finkelstein should we start with the property we start with the property at Jacobs
Printer cartridge
Switch this is the toner cartridge that goes inside your standard
And there is fine print
On the outside of his toner cartridge box
And what the fine print basically says it
If you open this box you are entering into
Contract
And you're giving up some of your rights
The Supreme Court is now trying to settle an argument over this
Fine print
Depending on how this case is resolved
It is not just going to affect
The price of your printer cartridge
It actually could have
Huge impact on a lot of things that we buy
Like Alexa
Tronix like cars like medicines
All because of the fine print
I'm a sprinter car
I meant can I tell you what
Please
Okay
This cartridge
Is made by a company called Lex
Accident right here on the box and lexmark's business model is
Standard printer busy
The printer itself is pretty cheap
But then when you need to buy a new ink cartridge
That is where they get you
This cartridge
Cost $130
Think yes
And people don't want to pay $130 every time they buy a car
4 Inc
Yes
So there are these smaller third-party companies that
Find and buy empty printer cartridge
Refill them with their own it I love it so much
FML sell it to you for like
Half the price
Instead of $130
Still sell you a refilled cartridge used cartridge
For $65
Fantastic right
For these small companies
Fantastic Four you and me
Fantastic Four everybody except
Lexmark company that is selling cheap printers so that they can sell
Expensive ink
That's exactly basically destroys our business
So there's this little company that's in the business of refilling toner cartridges
25 people in West
Virginia
And Lexmark is suing that
Suing them
What what is there are
The answer lies in
The fine print
On this phone
Okay picking up the boxes
It's heavy and I'm not going to open it
For reasons which out the vault in just a second
Beside of this
Toner Baca from Lexmark it says the following
Opening this package
Or using the patented cartridge inside confirms your acceptance of the following license
Okay so I'm just going to stop you there so they're saying
If you open this box
You're agreeing to this.
That's right
The patented toner cartridge is sold at a special price
Subject to a patent restriction
That it may be used
Only
Once
One time
Use it but you cannot sell it or give it to that little company
That that takes our cartridges
Isn't that is not allowed
You're making a deal when you open this box and that deal Pro
Hibbetts you from doing that
That is lexmark's argue
Now here is the other side
Juicy argument being made by the small
There is a legal term called
Patent exhaust
Yes what it means if you Jacob Goldstein go into a store and buy some
Even if it's patent
Once you have bought it
It now belongs to you
The company that holds the patent
Can't tell you what to do with it
Their rights are exhausted patent rights on the product
Exhausted one side
Yes and you can do whatever you
Okay so that's why I can
Say by a computer and then turn around and sell it to somebody else
Because once I buy it I own it
I can do what I want
Bingos but there's a legal exception to patent
Exhaustion which says
You can do what Lexmark is doing
You can say no no no
Don't refill my stuff
Don't reuse my stuff
As long as you put it on the product itself as long as you write it
In fine print on this item
You can't resell this
You can't
Resell this
And that's what this big argument is
So when you put it that way it seems like oh okay the laws in lexmark's favor
But you know the Supreme Court doesn't take that many
And so the fact that they took it tells me a
It must be more complicated than it sounds
NB
There must be some larger thing at stake
Right cuz that's what
Steaks here for a lot of companies and for a lot of Prada
And you can see that in the fact that many many many big companies like
Costco and LG Electronics
Have filed an amicus brief
On behalf of the little company in West Virginia doing the refill
Because all of those big companies
They sell you stuff
With patented Parts all the
What time
These companies want a world where they can sell you something and you're free and clear you can do what you want with
There is
One last
Twisty
Okay there's this other brief floating around
On behalf
Flexsmart
It's signed by a bunch of
Business professors economics professors Lapras
And what they say and what Lexmark says is
Lexmark actually offers
Two different versions of this toner card
This one with the fine print on it
There is also another version
That is more expensive
But you can do whatever you want no fine print
So the concern is
If Lexmark loses this
Case it will no longer be in its interest to bother making the cheaper version
And you and me and everybody else
Could end up paying
Even higher prices
Is mapreduce new
If we're buying them from lexmod
But maybe it'll get easier to get the cheap
Prefilled cartridge
But then if we're all buying cheap refilled cartridge
Just maybe they won't tell the printer
For cheap anymore in the first
So the printer
Maniscalco
Sol yourwelcome next up a road trip
What's the first can you tell me the fur
Entry of the first
Journal
Alright so we
August 9th 1998 we Departed
Central Standard Time
This is a me mileage
10000 518 on the
She's an accountant
Her husband is also on a cow
Canton Ohio it 228 and gas was $0.81 and they took their two young kids
Kids on a rope
We got the Youngstown around 6:30 the hotel Comfort Inn was no great establishment
They too early for everyone
I first bank was in Greenville Pennsylvania about 45 minutes away we found it with no trouble and the people were very efficient
We were on our way in 20 minutes
It was the second day of their big Road
And Amy and her husband Dave
I just opened
Savings account
Our next stop was in
Hollidaysburg
What a cute downtown
We headed from here to Mount Olive and other blinding rain
It was a Mad Dash from there to Milton these are all banks.
They're like reverse
Bankruptcy
Going from bank to bank to bank and putting money into each one
Opening one savings account after another
We got the mail in time but couldn't find the base
Oh yeah that way
Until it had been closed for 5 minutes we left info in the night depository we'll see what happens
A mandate for opening all these banking
Because they wanted to make money off the fine
Two years before the road trip
David started opening Accounts at little Banks all around where they live
These Banks were a particular kind of bad
Called Mutual
Mutual banks are owned by people with Accounts at the
You can think of it like a like a co-op
Back at this time
Time back in the night
A lot of these Banks were converting
From being Mutual Banks to being just like regular Bank
Banks with stock that trades on the stock market
And here's the fine print part
Under Federal regular
People who had Accounts at the Mutual Bank
Got first crack
Get the stock
In the stock almost always went up
So Dave goes around us
Town opens Aldi's
And sure enough a little while later
You got a letter from one of the back
It was converting to become a regular
If you could be first in line to buy the stuff
So I sent money in
What's a lot of money sent it in got the shares and the shares went up this is pretty cool
Yeah and I said well
There must be more mutual's in a country
I scouted around and found a company that was selling a list
And so I bought the list
We got some maps from AAA cover them with little yellow Post-it notes on all the banks are going to hit and then
Banking Road
We were always
No honest work we don't live
Here we live in the Midwest
But you felt like when you walked out with that password when you walked out with that pass book
Weed one
They drove North from Pennsylvania into New England opening bank accounts along the way
Also better vacation
They went whale watching watch
Fenway Park
24 hikes in the mountains
By the time they got home they driven more than
2000 miles
An open account
A23
3 bags
And then
The weight
The way this thing works
You don't know when or even if any particular Mutual Bank is going to convert
Going to have an IPO
Some of the banks were Amy and Dave opened accounts on that trip almost 20 years ago are still plugging away asthma
But others did have IPOs
Esl stock
Steven Amy bought shares and they almost never lost
It's rare I think I probably lost money on three out of 60 that I've done
In other words he made a profit
57 out of 6
The family went on Moore Road
Open more account
More than 300 in all
Dave and Amy didn't want to talk about exactly how much money they made
In fact they asked me not to use their last name
They said they haven't told many people about their Bank thing
They still live in the same house they've always lived
Still driving old van
But clearly this has been good
District
This way they figured out to process
Set from the fine print
It seems to be winding down
Nobody starting new Mutual Bank
There aren't that many
Still Amy and Dave's daughter Sarah
Who is now also an accountant
Told me there may still be a little action
Last December I had a little time off and I made
EuroTrip
By myself to Boston
And looped around Massachusetts Connecticut New Jersey New York there aren't many left data
Waiting to take you to do it to to open accounts
I visited some friends along the way
Sorry figure
Sarah opened 11 accounts in all
She hasn't made any money off of them yet
In a minute the story about the meaning of a snuggie
Support for Planet Money and the following message come from ishares
Because the best preparation for tomorrow
Is building for your future today
Ishares by BlackRock inspired to build
Katie Malone
Hater
I'm good
I've been in the weeds
On something that maybe
How about 3 tonight with the Snuggie
Sure how much TV
Like a blanket with holes in it
Yeah the idea idea is that a normal blanket slips off and it's very hard to stick your arms through normal blanket
The grab the remote in there for a blanket with sleeves as the solution
So here we are with a dispute about what the snug
It's
Is it apus
The blanket
Port is it like
A piece of clothing
Like a robe
Yeah and this is this is
An important distinction their millions of dollars on the line
+ 2
Get to the bottom of this I visited a lawyer named Joe sprayer again who somebody told me
Had an office
Spoonful of Snuggies
But by the time I got to his office and
The time I met him he walk me inside
The last I'm down to one
What
Breaking open
C1
Lovely
Brown snake
SoJO represents the
Company that sell Snuggie
Udall Star Market
I'm going to wear this for us the interview if that's all right with you I prefer the term use it
Rather than lyrics
Oh I see what you're doing
What is he
Okay here's what's going on
There's a fight
Over where the Snuggie Falls
It's something called the harmonized Tariff
I love to harmonize
It's like the finest
Fine print
If it's this giant book where they try and classify
Every single object that you could theoretically ever imp
There's life foxes 4.8% tariff in there
Import Ally Fox
Walking sticks
4.0 /
Pictures of the top of your head your like coffee
0% tariff I got this thing down
SoJO at a company that
Dead cells the Snuggie
They they claim that the Snuggie would fall under Section 6301 point
40.00
Blankets and traveling rugs from synthetic fiber
Tara
8.5 /
Snuggie wants it to be a blanket
And obviously you don't
Wearable
Which is why this lawyer is playing this game if he wants to say used
That's exactly right
But
And therefore it should
To fall under Section 6 114.3 0.30
Other garments
Knitted or crocheted of man-made fiber it set
So they think it's a garment it something you wear
Fall in the same category as Maybe
Graduation gown or like a Priestly cloak or whatever
And I'm going to guess what if it's a garment it's taxed at a higher rate than if it's a blank
14.9%
Okay so it's like about 15% versus
Is 8 1/2
Speed difference
So sluggish at the blanket and a half percent the government says it's kind of like a robe 15%
What is it this battle recently went before the US court of international trade
Both parties argue their sides
And US court decided
Yeah
This thing is a black
G1
Snuggie win
But the government is probably
Course somebody's always good
So this story is
Absurd
On its face
Which is kind of the essence of fine
Is there a silly details to a
But
You know we have a world where we have
Different text
Traits for every possible thing that somebody could
Import
I'm so the only thing that can happen in that world is you wind up with lawyers
In court
Arguing over whether a blanket with holes in it is actually not a blanket but a rope
I mean find Prince
Exist for a reason
Fine print exist
Because the world is in fact not as simple as we want it to be
We need fine print
Blank
Special thanks to date to Sarah and Jack
Those were the two young kids sitting in the back of the van while their parents drove around the country opening bank accounts
They grew up to be Planet Money listeners
And they told me about their
Send your story ideas to us at Planet Money at end
Npr.org or you can also find us on Facebook or Twitter
In today's episode was edited by Brian urstadt it was produced by Nick fountain with an assist from Sally helm
And if you're looking for another podcast to listen to dry Fresh Air with Terry Gross
Fresh air
The radio show accepted the podcast you can listen to it anytime you want you can find it at npr.org podcast on the in
NPR one app
Or wherever you get your podcast and thanks for sharing your your podcast recommendations this month as part of tripod
If you have any more recommendations you can still do it even though the month is probably over
Gry pod tripod
I'm Jacob Goldstein and I'm Kenny Malone thanks for listening