Support for NPR and the following message come from service now making the world of work
Work better for me
Their cloud-based platform and solutions deliver digital workflow
Spell create great experiences and unlock productivity for your whole company
More at servicenow.com
Edward
How are you
I'm good how are you
Would you mind introducing
I met her at a cash really and I'm the Planet Money intern
We were in an editorial meeting recently
And Edward just kind of
Casually mentions
When I was in high school I tried to break a Guinness World Record
That's right
Are in turn made this very serious record-breaking attempt
Winky was
15 years old
Sorry about 6 years ago in the country
Georgia that is where Edward is from
And there was this YouTube personality that Edward really love
His name is Charlie McDonnell
Has YouTube aliases Charlie is so cool like
Charlie is so cool like
Lots of things is just as regular
He talks about his life on this you
YouTube channel what's on his mind he's really into Doctor Who
Commitments I'm afraid of multitasking I'm afraid of My Little Pony
Did you seem like very put together but not
Secretary search Lee swap because you made a big deal of how he was like
Socially awkward
I like I was a pretty socially awkward
Can I hear myself so I thought you know
I don't have to be like
Cool
I can just be like Charlie
Anyway I was watching this video one of his tours of his room
You know I feel comfortable having you around so I think it's about time that I showed you around
The crib
Here you go
He said I look that's a world record certificate right there behind me did I ever tell you that I have
Is a cuz I have a Guinness World Record
I have the world record for typing the alphabet in the fastest time on an iPad
He's even cooler because I thought I had the book
That would be the Guinness book
Of World Records Edward had a copy
Any idea of being in this book
Seemed amazing to everyone online to see what Charlie is typing record
It turned out that his time was 6.31 seconds
Everything
I'm a fast typist
Just for fun he tries typing the alphabet on his own iPad
And he's really fast after practicing for an hour he's faster than Charlie he is
Beating the world record
So I was like okay I have to have to
Like I can do this
I thought you know who
Find out about it
I know it's hard hose makers like
Equals in Samsung
Sounds right doesn't call you up
I was sort of hoping yeah totally website
Print out the rules for a tie
Tempting record as his mom to film inside
On her phone
But you know sometimes you tell your parents about something
And they started me
Make a really big deal out of it and they want to lick and bite your families are filming it and all the sudden
You just
Wish you never told them at all
This happened to Edward
Like
Times a million
I don't know if I should get into the president thing but
Should I get into it though that your dad was the president of Georgia
Edwards dad was the president of joy
And like that sargis super proud of his son and he's excited about this thing that he's trying to do
But he's also the president's was thinking about National presidential
Issues
One of the things he's been doing is trying to establish Georgia as a place for technological innovation he's been making this push
And he thinks Edwards Guinness record could fit into this
The ministry of sports
In Georgia you are summons
Seventh Son wow they set up a meeting with me
And they said we want to pay for this
We're going to pay for their travel we're going to pay them to flat fee
George want to do this up right
Flat against judge have a big official ceremony with lots of press
People eat big Edwards
YouTube inspired Guinness project
A major national
New event
It sounds like a lot
Like
Government policy and
Press and
Sounds like a lot
Yes
And I think that's sort of where the
12 again
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
You were you are joining us today on this journey through the business of breaking records because
Realize at the time when you decided to break your record was the Guinness was in the middle of a major transformation
Yeah it was a make-or-break moment for Guinness and it's Mom that a lot of companies face when they're old business model
Just stopped working
And of course Edward we follow you
Do your Guinness World Record eating
Excited
I am
Support for this podcast and the following message come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to
Support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf
. org
There is a man
In Queens
Who holds the record for most Guinness Records
Broken
Ever
His name is ashrita Furman he's been breaking records for almost 40 years
And we went to meet him he was standing in his backyard of his hands on his hips looking at this big
Wall
Covered with balloon
First record with jumping jacks
And I'm
I started in 18
SC
I went to the records and did to 27000
Yeah
That was a special record that first one
So we were at a street ice house because he was about to try to break another record
What record will this be if if this works out
Am I jinxing you
No not at all
Right now I think I have a 195 official record
Princess rb190
This is a record for
Breaking the most
Balloons with chopsticks
In a minute
We have a balloon setup on a board
You know it feels like it's like a carnival or something
It does look like a carnival
The Chopsticks have these kind of sharp
Metal tip
Like like
Like darts
Buzzing with Act
There is an official Guinness judge
Laser in a clipboard and cheese
Measuring everything out with a tape measure to make sure that she didn't stand
Exactly the proper distance away from the balloons when he starts hurling chopsticks with them
And there's a team there filming the whole event for an online video
How many records have you broken here in your backyard
Actually a lot
I probably about over a hun
I don't know hundred
Yeah I mean there's a lot of stuff this is the compost pile at me
Watermelons that do record where
I have watermelons
On my stomach my friend chopped in half
With a machete actually
Is that while I'm lying in a bed of nails
No
But that's not a bit better nails were they chapters
Concrete blocks
Well am I lying in a bed of nails
Bella Nails
The sum of the better now
They don't you like several beds of nails
Oh those boys for juggling
I see this is this is not the record
We're lifting a dolly over your head
Oh my God
African playing guitar
DeSoto records
For the most weight bouncing your chin
While playing a song on
Guitar promise I'm trying to learn that
The guitar
That's the hard part yeah
What are your what are your neighbors think
Like this these people kind of know me because
I've done I've been back here for years during records and likes have a record for
Sabering champagne that is
Yeah yeah when you when you chop the top off with the saver
Oldies
How to bottle to go into that guy's yard
What the heck are you doing up there
You know it looks like it's must be kind of interesting living down there cuz what kind of Chopsticks go down at me cuz
You know I can't help it it so it's a loaf and that you were has to be cut short because
It's time for the big moment
Record number 196
Most balloons popped
With chopsticks
In one minute
Ashrita has been practicing for a month
We are we ready
I'm actually I'm nervous are you
Ashrita takes his place
The judge
Stopwatch
For the record
Go
Ashrita is so
Focus
Queen chopstick
You can hear him just ain't himself
Come on come on
Xxxii
A lot of them aren't
Bouncy Bob
People on the live video Start commenting about
Fail fail fail not looking good
The judge calls time
Wow that wasn't Betty
Who is sitting look easy
Okay guys this is the moment of truth
Okay so it's true that today you attempted
The Guinness World Record
Title for the most balloons burst
Chopsticks in one minute
And you achieved it
Total of 20
4 Bellaire
A new Guinness World Record
Titleist right before your eyes
Speaking of new record I'm so excited to tell you guys
The 2018 Edition is out now and the United
Ashrita Furman is in this book multiple times book promotion promotion
This moment is why Genesis
Is here they want to sell books
Guinness Book of World Records is one of the best
Selling books of all time
And this is amazing
Especially if you consider the Guinness started out as a
Little book that the Guinness beer company used to hand out
Pubs to settle bar fight
Is that they were the same company for decades
The beer guys and the record guy
Eventually Guinness Brewery was bought up by this big
Beverage conglomerate
And Guinness Records Was spun off
Little company was on its own and needed to fend for itself but that was fine because every year Guinness came out with a new edition
And every year that new edition was a best
Cellar
In fact a lot of the people in the Guinness book bikinis
Cultural icon
Concert pictures were known around the world
Tallest man with shortest woman the woman with the smallest waist
Peter Harper as a senior vice president
With Guinness World Records
Longest fingernails is another totally iconic record remember that photo from the old days
Guinness book in r
Great Library that's that's it. That's one of the photos the other photo is The McCrary twins
Who are the heaviest
World's fattest twins on the motorcycle I remember that picture
The band Genesis book sale started doing what everybody
Falling
I was hoping you wouldn't get to that question
I think we're certified generally following the industry Guinness needed a new way to make
But it was not obvious
How do you make money off of the amazing photo of the man with the
Fingernails
Anybody out there could you
Google it for
For free
And that is the moment the Guinness realize
That their new business model
Was literally knocking on there
Company started coming to us asking if we could fly someone out to their event companies and people will come
Coming to Guinness wanting to break a record for publicity
To draw attention to
They've got none of the fact that if they
Achieve a record title
Did they get a lot of press for it or they get a lot of shares on social media increasingly they want to make it more of a market
Any event they want to invite one of our judicators
And then the the usage of the logo
Guinness realized they could charge for
A lot
Price tag for a full-service event starts at $12,000 and goes up over half-a-million
Peter says did you
You hundreds of events like this
Every
Reebok did a multinational bendy Brook 44 records
In one day on
Four continents to launch a new shoe
Gates Foundation help set a record for drug donation to draw 10
Diseases
Gordon Ramsay broke
Official playing records of broke his new TV show
Could a bunch of records for movies and other various things honor this weekend's big Super Bowl game
Broccoli and Bishop seven bucks digital Squad set a new Guinness World Record
The largest 7-Layer dip in the world
Gorgeous
Fascinated by the
The people were
Breaking records
Pushing the limits of
What it meant
To be a human
Genesis customers now
Are the record Breakers themselves
If you pay Guinness enough money
They will help you figure out a record you
You can break
And they will help
Break it
Guinness is even sitting up places where members of the public can come in and attempt record
Personal fear
Of course
Guinness is now in the business of selling record-breaking
And they're really good at it
There is something about you I bet Stacy that you do that no one does as well
Oh so you think I have a world record of Me Maybe I think you do somewhere you should think hard about that and you know who to call if
If you come upon something
You can still break a Guinness World Record
That does not cost
You can go to the website print out the rules for breaking a record
Before the event send it in brakes
But here's the thing that the rules for breaking a record or really really complicated in particular
Can take months to get a response from Guinness
People who pay money they got a device that can help that
Jump the line response
Does it feel at all like
Part of Guinness is Mission was compromised in a way or the
It kind of Tainted the record-breaking 2 to charge will
At the time and it is a question we are mindful of because
If we
Compromise our reputation for being an authority
The business
Goes
Down the tubes
Really
Pretty quickly
Some people think
It already has
My real name is the Reverend dr. David adamowicz retired Professor with a doctor in exercise physiology paramedic pool
Professionally trained Chef ordained minister
And in my spare time
I throw knives
My friends call me throw
The Great
Throwdini
Houdini started throwing knives when he was
50 reasons
He got really good
Really fast
He started performing in this
Live knife throwing show
We promised to end each show
With an attempted
World record
And it was in that
At that time that I had
Throne
89 surround my assistant
In one minute on stage 89th around a beautiful assistant in one
13 Augustus and film he submits that film to Guinness
He's over the moon there's not a record like this in the Guinness book
Tracker Jet and Socrates thinking
I am going to have my picture
Which is amazing record in the Guinness Book of World
And a couple months later
He gets an email
They weren't interested in the knights record
They weren't interested in a record involving
Knife throwing
Knives around human talk
How did you feel when you read that email
I was crushed
Attorney says he saw that Guinness had created a knife throwing record
How to publicize event around
Is Prince William
That was about money
Get us. This new record scene
Cool they wanted to find a way to cash in on it
So they gave it to someone else
It's it's all about money
And if you don't
Get involved with the money side
Of what they're doing
Then
What you do falls to the Wayside
All this was a decade ago and even throw Genie isn't
Sure what happened
Eventually made it into
What he says
If you're not paying money I can feel really hard
And really discourage
To break a Guinness record
13 he was mad he was so mad that he
Join arrival world record company
Colts record holders Republic
It's a non-profit owned and run by record Breakers
30 says this is a crucial open database of Records but evens rodini admits record holders Republic is never
Going to be the brand
The Guinness Guinness husband
Powerful Deep Roots
In the childhood memories of people all over the world
Venus named after all is why
Edward your dad and
Georgia. Breaking a Guinness record would bring Global attention
We are watching a video of your record-breaking attempt
End
Looking very fancy
It's very fancy in this video this 15 year old you is in The Shining
Building the TV cameras everywhere I mean this is
Clearly become a major national event
Wouldn't you seeing as you walk in
A lot of
Are standing around most of them
Auburn t-shirts
With the Guinness logo
Alantez Edwards Akashiya
Fastest time
Taipei
The alphabet on a knife
White shirts
Pictures of a man
By who
The ministry of sports
How did you feel when you saw this
I was just thinking I have to get this right
If I failed
What would the media say
Is always media weather like alive Vans what are they going to do
Die grinder breaking news story like I don't actually failed
You got a record
Crybaby I can't even
Hershey's
Yeah I'm and my great grandma was there and
Oh my God
Every dude really started out in front of an old-school Guinness
Spirit write what you just wanted to break this record
For the joy of breaking the record you are trying to promote your
Personal brand make money or anything like that but then
You kind of sucked into guinnesses new business
Yeah I mean this is just going to be for me but
Sitting there looking around at these people are the shirts and all the logos it just felt like my record have been hijacked
And in very publicly
But anyway here it is the big moment you're sitting in a chair there all these people crowded around you
I was very nervous
So there you are
You
You're typing
Tasks really fast
Yes and I stopped typing you can see I raise my arm to say stop I'm done
Okay and then the adjudicator is looking at her stopwatch
Time in Chile
Walks over
Podium it's okay not the suspense is killing me I can't even
She's now going to
Muntu
A microphone to an ABS
What has happened
And what was your time
5.26
I didn't ever kiss
I work I was out of town
Thanks
I know she's calling me over to get the certificate
Oh there you are closing at the certificate
She telling me to raise it
Oh really
She's like raising over your head
The Guinness branding and polishing at work
Anyways
Did it work was this a big news event in Georgia
Totally all the news channels running as their top item that after
Afternoon everybody found out
And then four months afterwards everybody I met
Top and Teo congratulations what a great accomplishment
So I think about a month later
Attract
The website
And it said
Oh my gosh you the record for 4 weeks
How did you feel better this record have been broken after
Just 4 weeks
I don't think I really cared honestly I was a little sick of hearing about it
How to make a phone make sense because
What Katniss was really selling
Was the
Experience of breaking a record
Write it sort of a service
I mean that is with the ministry of sports
Publicity some great sound bites
They got what they wanted
Guinness
It got what it wanted
What about you Edward I mean
You started out you wanted to meet your YouTube hero engine
Try to see if you could do this cool thing
What was your takeaway after all this
Did you get what you wanted
Even if it's covered um record I still feel like
The theory of Guinness has so much
Pull that. Even it even fools me knowing that
Even if I know
That
It's not all that it seems to me it still Falls me and makes me feel good
You just means but like
You you stand out your special special
And
Support for this podcast in the following message come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org
We always love to hear what you think of the show send us an email
Planet Money at npr.org
Or find us on Facebook
Twitter
And if you set a record definitely tell us about that
Today's show was produced by Elizabeth
Planet Money supervising producer is Alex goldmark and our editor is Brian Dorsett
Special thanks to Larry Olmsted you want to learn more about Guinness check out his book is called getting into Guinness
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
And I metal recycling Philly
Thanks for listening
So Edward
Yes I have kind of a
Surprise for you
Okay
Are you ready
Okay here you go
Headlines
This is Charlie
I'm just here because
I realized I never really firmly congratulated you
On beating my world record
So
Congratulations
I'm fixing my world record like I said
My record anymore
Still mine in my heart
You are officially better than me at typing the alphabet in the fastest time on an iPad
For now
So I'm saying
Thanks love bye-bye
So
I'm feeling really weird right now like I'm feeling a little bit like Starstruck or something like physically I have this kind of
Like heart pounding in my chest
For the feeling
I mean do you have anything you'd want to say back to him
Are you just thank you
It is a certain lightness I feel lighter
I got all this
Like all this media attention and stuff at the time but I felt like it was coming from the wrong place
But now I feel like
That Charlie thing you know good job
Finally it's coming from the right place