This message comes from NPR sponsors snowfall
The only data warehouse
Built for the cloud
Unlock deep Data Insights with the instantly scalable Cloud build data warehouse
Start your journey towards data-driven decision
It's snowflake. Com NPR
Jacob as you know there is nothing
I love more than sort of just
Digging into a nerdy tax
Reform
Play Asher and the other day I found one
It perhaps is
Too complicated to nerdy in for Planet Money No Such Thing
Well here me out here this plan is a plan to reform the corporate
Taxes the tax that corporations pay their profits with me being pushed by University of California Professor Alan R
It's called
I love this
The DBC ft
TD cfp
Yes the acronym we use as a destination based cash flow tax
But we need some PR help I realized
Yeah first of all DBC ft is obviously at least two letters too long for negative Simple Rules
Three letters Max for neck
Well the cool kids
Basketball game call at the border adjust
Attacks
Little bit better and we would not
Even be talking about this plan today except
The professor got
The pr help
That he needed
Last week President Donald Trump
I don't know where
Embrace the strange complicated tax plan
Although he didn't
Use any of the initials me the sound way marker map
Well working on a tax reform bill
That will reduce our trade deficits increase America.
Sports and will generate revenue from Mexico
That will pay for the wall if we decide to go that route
It's fair to say that
The people
Freaked out at least 4000
2 minutes they work I quit what is he talking about is he really going to tax imports from Mexico
Is it going to increase the price of avocados
Is this the star
The start of the US Mexico trade war and then people realized Trump was talking about
The dbcf
Pete the Border adjustment tax this new idea for a corporate
This was Alan Arabic
Time to shine
You've been talking about the Border just a text for 15 years
And now
There was
All over the news
One small problem
Public Safety border adjustment tax doesn't
Do all of those things that Trump promised
If his objective is to punish other countries this may not be the way to do it
But if what he wants to do is
To encourage
Investment production and employment
And higher wages in the United States then I think this
I would fit the bill
This is such a strange moment in US history
That a protectionist president and a free trade economist
May have found some common ground, ground but could overhaul
The corporate tax
Hello welcome to Planet Money I'm Robert Smith and I'm Jacob Goldstein we are taking Today's Show to just
Pause you know there's
Ordinary amount of news coming out of Washington DC
We're going to pause today and just explain this one
Wonky really important economic thing the corporate income tax and how it may be about to change in a big
Today on the show a corporate tax plan so crazy
It just
Might work
Although not the way the president thinks it will
We'd like to say a quick thank you and share a message from one of our sponsors
Freshbooks
It's 2017
And the all-new freshbooks Cloud accounting software is so ridiculously easy to use over 10
Million small businesses are now using it working in this ever-expanding DIY economy
Send a branded invoice in under 30 seconds
Avoid awkward client Shots by automating your late payment reminders
Amtrak every billable moment from your phone
For your 30-day free trial go to freshbooks.com Planet Money
An inter Planet Money in the how did You Hear About Us section
Alright let's do this thing the Border adjust
Adjustment tax
Is a replacement for
The corporate
Text
The corporate tax in America is a mess
Your classic bad
Because first of all
It is an incredibly
Hi-Tech
Percent that is the tax levied on profits of corporations that is the
Highest in the developed world
Can you bury somebody the United States of America home of
, business and capitalism
And to also have the highest corporate tax rate in the developed
Yes and on top of that
There are tons of loopholes which is your classic
Bad text combination High statutory rape
Tons of loopholes and all of these loopholes means
Companies have a huge incentive
Tahiry all these lawyers to do crazy global
Tax shenanigans
Soap for instance
Quickest route back from UC Berkeley says
A global company can sell something that it states
And say well
We make a profit United States we made a profit in our subsidiary in
Ireland
And
It would be hard to track down that money
Where does a company like apple earn the money that it makes on an iPhone
Is interning in silicon valley
Does it hurt in China
Does attorney in Ireland where it has some of its intellectual property it's really hard to know
A lot of politicians people run the US government know
This is a problem
And that's why this pretty General support for lowering the corporate tax
President Barack Obama thought the corporate tax rate was too high he wanted to lower it
President Donald Trump promise of the campaign trail that he would lower the corporate tax rate
Anthropologie in the Congress there currently proposing dropping it from 35%
To 20%
But if you lower the rate
That much
Even if you get rid of a lot of those loopholes
The government is still going to wind up with less money every year
Yes one of the major sources of income for the US government so
Where do they get the money
This
This my friend
Is where the Border adjustment tax
TBC update
DBC ft
Which winner
You will have to admit is
A pretty clever solution
Republicans in Congress
This is among the tax plan that they are looking at
Right now it is sort of on their short list of things to do
Will explain the Border adjustment
Okay the way the corporate tax works now
If you are an American come
You have to pay the Us corporate tax
On your profits wherever you sell your good so if you
Make your goods here you sell them here you pay the corporate tax you make them hear you sell them in China and Europe you also pay the Us corporate
Profit is profit you got to pay a corporate tax on profits
The word respite access to companies listen
We don't care where you technically
Book your profits Apple
We don't care what you technically book your profits
What we care about is where you sell
Your products
Do you sell your product
In the United States of America
The philosophy of is the same look
We're not exactly sure what corporate residents means anymore and we're not exactly sure where profits are being earned but we're pretty sure we know
Know where consumers are
And if meth Americans are buying things regardless of where they're produced if they're purchased in the US
We want to put a tax on them in if they're not
We don't
And that's a very viable tax system
So you're making all your money in Ireland
We don't care
We just care where you're selling your stuff if you're selling stuff to Americans in America
You're going to pay the corporate
And this is not
A new crazy idea a lot of countries around the world have something that is that is sort of similar is called
Backpacks
Value added
It's okay Robert border adjustment tax let's actually worked out how this wood pellets would actually work for a bit
Okay so let's say I have a company a company that
Sell something
Jessica podcasting
Fitmix
Annoy
Okay Shuffle the marbles marbles terrible product
Don't ever do that again
That's going to get annoying so let's just have a corporation that sells
Sweet sweet music.
Toke Robertson the current
Corporate tax Universe you got your precious little music box company in Brooklyn
You pay the corporate tax
On your profits
No matter where you sell your music
Percent
If taxes on the profit
This substantially changes under the Border adjust
Smith tax under the new tax if it were to pass
The big changes come for my music box Corporation if I decide to export a product
Or importer
And Robert at you talk about your music box business with Eleanor Bach the Berkeley process and you guys started with f
Let's just say these things
Become the rage
In Mexico City and I start to
Export the master to sell Brooklyn made music boxes
In Mexico City
How is that
Well
If you sold your music box
For $500
Dollars
You're making me New York I assume they're very high-end
Assuming that you sell it for $500
The $500 would just be ignored by the IRS
We wouldn't go into your tax calculation that would that would
Be the only change but it's obviously a very big change from the previous Circle
Under this proposal into the Border adjustment if you sell your music boxes in the US
You still have to pay tax
On your profit
Tell them in Mexico or in any other country in the world
No tax on your profit
This is a huge
Incentive for me to export music boxes and fact
Huge incentive for
Ous exporters in Wichita can music boxes here
Boeing
Boeing sells one plane
For 300 million dollars
Imagine that text free
Get this is a windfall for USA
There is another half
The tax giveth and the tax
Take it away
Because let's just say I have those music boxes made
In China
They're much cheaper
Make their I can make a larger profit
But my customers are in America and this time this time I do have to pay attack
So if you
Import that music box
For $100
Because it's cheaper to make it in China pages in New York
And then you sell it for $500
The $500 would be taxable if it's sold in New York
So you be taxable on the entire thing
Canadian / you think that the decision to Outsource your production
Or maybe I'll just
Charge people more if I'm anemic
You might
If your head is really trying to do the math I'm sure most businesses in the United States will also be trying to figure this out this is
A good time to employee
A tax lawyer but I'm going to send this up
If you are an importer in the United States of America under the Border adjustment tax
You will pay a pretty hefty tax
If you are an exporter
You will not
It's a sweet deal
And you know this
Seems like it would create an incentive to
Make more things you have to export more stuff
And and a
Disincentive to import stuff
This is the part not surprisingly that President Trump is focusing on the kind of big macro implication
But it's also worth looking at just like
What does it mean to me what is it how's it going to affect
Consumers
Well
Look at all the stuff
You bought recently
Was a lot of important
The odds are a lot of wisdom
Whether it's at Walmart or Target Crate & Barrel Best Buy
That stuff is brought into the country by American corporations and if those companies are charged
More taxes because their importers
Surprised they are probably going to raise their prices
If these companies have to pay more in taxes there's a good chance
They're going to pass that on to us will have to pay more for the stuff we bought
And importers are already logging Congress
Sing
What are you doing this plan is for judgement tax
Would kill us and not just us but your constituents and I just your considered for your pores of constituents violet
Things at Walmart and Target
They're the ones who are going to
Basically take the burden of his border adjustment
We want to know what this would mean for the broader economy so we called up Megan green
She's the chief Economist at John Hancock
As importers are having to pay this tax
They're probably going to pass the price of that on to the end consumer so that means consumers are going to have to pay more
Forgets
I mean that's bad for the consumer and also means prices will rise so we'll have inflation
And in lower gross because the consumer will be facing this big tax
So we'll be paying more but the economy won't be in as good shape
And it's negative for the US
Economy
And to be clear not everybody thinks
All these things would happen
People like Fester are boxes
Supporters of the Border adjustment tax say
Yes there will be some short time of adjustment
Where prices might go up
But eventually they say things will return to normal
If you made it this far in the podcast
Thank you first of all thank you
And
You are in for a
Because we are going to talk about
One of the most
Mystical and satisfying things
In economics
We are going to talk about
Currency
Exchange
Exchange rate
Break the value of the dollar and how that is going to affect this whole thing it'll be short we'll make it easy I promise
3 steps
Okay so step
One would you abort
Step one is
Imports get
More expensive
And as a result we import less
The point
Step 2
At this point the value of the US dollar
Relative to other currencies the value of US dollar
Goes up
The dollar gets
Stronger
And step 3
The stronger dollar
Has the effect of making Imports
Cheaper
You put the tax on Imports get more expensive
Bent the value of the dollar changes
Imports get cheaper
You are basically back where you started
In theory in the textbook
In the textbook detected any economic textbook
The debate going on right
Now I'm on, the cross the country is
How long
Will it take
For the economy
To adjust
If you put in this border adjustment tax how long will it take for the economy
To return
To normal
Days months years
No one knows
I don't know about the guy who pushes idea he think it'll happen almost overnight
Meaning
Drum roll
Marbles in a jar
The Border adjustment tax
Will in theory in the end
Have very little effect
On Imports
And Expo
Sports
Come on
I know that
Blew my mind
Robert you ask the obvious question to Professor Auerbach
If you go to all this trouble
Get people together change the laws change the very nature
Of our corporate tax system
And then at the end everything
The same
White mask White
I think the Border adjustments themselves
In terms of their impact
We are not going to have much of an impact
It's really the changes incentives to companies have
How to locate production in the US
The other versus other countries
Their loss of ability for among those companies that are aggressively shifting
Their taxable profits to other countries Westwood Village to do that
I think that's where it when should focus and thinking about which companies are going to be the winners in which going to be a loser
So you don't others
Text Shenanigans you read about about companies
Booking their profits in foreign countries about holding money overseas
All the incentives for all of those Shenanigans go away
With this tax
According.
But everything else stays the same
No one is punished
Importers are fine exporters are fine
Mexico still will not be paying for the wall if it gets built
Okay I get the theory behind that I got that textbook
Part of that but
I do still wonder
Midday am I not having that way but be
What is it going to mean for our economic relationship with the rest of the world right I mean if you're saying
Hey we're going to you don't put this tax on Imports and give a sweet deal to our exports is that going to like
I don't know what is that going to
MARTA train
This
Is a crucial question
Because as hard as it is to explain the economic
When you add diplomacy on top of that it gets even more complicated
As a final voice I wanted to talk with Carolyn freund she's a
The trade expert with the Peterson Institute
She says for the Border adjustment
Text to work
It needs to be explained crashing
AECOM lead other countries
So they don't retaliate
Donald Trump needs to say
That this is
I can't with all the other countries in the world are doing with their value-added taxes and that this border
Adjustment is standard and economic theory shows it's not protection
I think it really depends on the administration's talking points
Other rhetorical discipline
At what this is it was what I was going to say is I think this is what makes people even more nervous about this Administration
Changing
Tax the tax
Code is that from what we've seen so far and it's Granite it's only a week and there's a learning curve but still from what we've seen
So far I don't expect it to happen smoothly
You know this one normal year I would say
The best tax
Has no chance
El Paso we probably wouldn't even do a podcast
Because
Think about it there was a Walmart in just about every Congressional
District
And
It's hard to explain your constituents a prices
Might go up for a while but they'll probably come down and value of the dollar chest
United States
Political non-starter but
This is not
A normal year
And weirdly the Stars seem to be aligning to
Take some sort of
Pampa Texas
Republicans want
To pass something
It looks like Lortab
Donald Trump
He wants to pass something that has the word Border in it
And as a result
Economist
May get to see what happens if you completely transformed
The corporate tax code
It's a sort of massive experiment to see if the Real World axe
The way the textbook
Cecibel
What else
Can we explain
Pelis
On Twitter or Facebook or by emailing
Planet Money at npr.org
If you're looking for another podcast to enjoy may we suggest
The latest from NPR Latino USA in the most recent episode it's about 8
Puerto Rican who is Greta
Let me see the very last days of Obama's presidency fine Latino USA on the NPR one app or wherever
Podcast
Special things today to Alan viard who we talk to Annie
Give us valuable information about this text Today Show was produced by Nick, I'm Robert Smith and I'm Jacob Goldstein thanks for this
There's no way to stop
What the podcast is this just goes after 20 minutes they were like
Put it out of the Realtors Nautilus switch
Well it'll stop when when the wind
A little latch
I know music box works
I have a music box Corporation
Weather Channel app
Cher