Hey everybody Stacey Vanek Smith here
And we plant money has a big announce
We are launching a new podcast
I'm hosting it along with Cardiff Garcia hey Carter Stacy and you just come to us from the financial times and the
FTL
That's right in our new podcast
Called the indica
This is Planet Money
Take on the news
It's going to be several times a week
About 5 minutes long and mostly about work business and the account
If you're a longtime listener you will recognize the indicator as part of the early days of Planet Money and now it has its own show
And here's a recent episode
Why your paycheck hasn't gotten any bigger
Even though the economy has been doing pretty well
Great Wave mystery
The Great Wave mystery how to listen
If you like it will help you
The job market was a bleak
Place 9 years
Rick Ellenberg saw this firsthand he has an employment office
In Asheville
Been through the tough times
When we lost a lot of manufacturing
They were probably
10 people for every job that was
This may be available at that point
Time today he says
At least one thing is
Is different now we see just the office
10 jobs for every
One applicant out
Is that right
It's it's just really really been white-hot a long time in our job market
But not everything
Things change for instance back when times were bad says Rick most jobs he had tended to pay around $9
And now
Cavity tables have turned
What are the jobs pay
Around
$9 an hour
This isn't only happening
In Asheville right
This is happening all over the
The country
Companies that hire lot more
People but for some reason
They are paying them
They aren't competing
For all those workers
So what we're seeing is it wages or only gradually
Grindingly
Grudgingly
Rising
That is very poetic Cardiff thank you
On today's indicator in economic mystery with unemployment so low why are wages growing
So slowly
Support also comes from Fidelity invest
As a Fidelity Wealth Management
You get a dedicated advisor
To help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of tax
And make clear recommendations for your full Financial pek
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
Please in Decatur
2.5
According to numbers from the federal government released this morning
Average hourly earnings for American workers Rose
2.5% over the
The past year
Once you take inflation into account
Are we just have barely risen at all
Yeah and this is a mystery not just for Rick Nashville
By the way it's
Something has been debated really heatedly
Buy Economist everywhere because there's no clear single answer
But they have dug to the data and then come up with a few possible ideas
Clear they haven't solved the mystery
Siri just yet
But they suggested a few
Possibilities
Is your explanation
Competing with each eye
With no clear winner yet
Socure are three possibilities for why wages have been rising so slowly
The workers themselves
Changed
What about the people who are looking for jobs with a different than they were five years ago or they younger or older different set of skills
What we're saying basically is that a much younger
Job the talent coming to us
American workers are getting
Baby Boomers are retiring and Millennials are now the largest group in the world
Enforce on average a 25 year old is just going to make less money than a 55
Yeah young people that get their crappy starter jobs.
Pay that much money
Older people retire from the
A higher wage jobs
And Gilberto averages therefore just held back a bit
Write this is just math
It's not really
So this could explain part of the reason why wages have been rising so slowly but even if you would just for age
We just just
Aren't moving up the way that they should be
There is something else
And that brings it to Theory number two
It brought tears by Michael Munger
The other reason is robot
The other reason is software and that's that's a hard thing to get around me robots are cool robots or something you can do
Look at software is so boring reason number two
Robots
And
Software apparently and I like robots
And also check
As we know robots have been taking jobs
The factory workers
But what manga says is now robots and software are starting to move into the white-collar territory as well
So for instance every small business around the country used to have
Ebookee
And now watch the knot that is not the case that job is gone and that person has been replaced by
Software
Quick
Read if you think about it is robots
Software
Technology and Automation in every other category than Mike mother wants it
Include as they all take over more jobs
Economy hostel
We just
The people lost their jobs have to find
New job
And some of the jobs end up taking
Just don't pay asthma
Meanwhile the people who already have jobs
I'm more nervous about asking for a raise because they worry that Valby
And by the way this weed mystery
Happening at a moment when company profits are really
Hi says this is a problem
Because one of the core arguments in favor of
Capitalism
Is there something
Apparently Fair
At the core of it
When the system is working
Everybody benefits in some way
Play the rising tide
And if that's not happening says Munger
That is a big problem
It means that you can't you can't
With a straight face make that argument about Equity it means that
There's
The benefits of
Economic performance are not equally shared
Okay so that's their number 2 robots
Robots
And a few other things
And that brings us to Theory numbers 3/4 why wages
I've been growing so slowly and Stacy I have to
Baconfest
This one's my favorite
All right what is it
There's still a lot of
People on the
The sidelines
So yes the official unemployment rate has absolutely
Plummeted in the last
Down to 4.1%
But that number also leaves out a lot of
People specifically
It leaves out one group of people who want a job
And can't get one button
This is important they also have an act
Tivoli look for one
In the last month so maybe they've been dealing with a family emergency or they've been
Taking care of your kids or maybe they just didn't see a job in the last 4 weeks if they wanted to
Yep and it also leaves out people who work part-time but would rather have
Full-time
None of these people are officially counted as unemployed just because of how the government
Categorize
Right after the financial crisis
In the recession
There were a lot of them
What is more jobs are created
Employees of hired more of them in meanwhile
The part-timers
I've been getting more
But until now
Force haven't had to offer them a lot more money
It's okay if your pet there is correct
There could be some good news on Horizon we might be at a turning point
Write we do know that this year the share of all those
People on the sidelines
Finally has fallen
To where it was
Before the financial crisis
Just when wages were Rising
Much faster
So then they are now so it makes sense that wages
Finally start
Ketchup
Assuming the jobs Market
Kitchen proving
There's absolutely no guarantee.
It's going to happen but if it does
It means that workers may start getting pay bums.
Really make a difference
This is been the indicator from Planet Money and you can subscribe or wherever
You get your podcast like it please leave a review
Support for this podcast and the following message come from freshbooks
Accounting software that gets your small business paid up to 5 days faster
For your 30-day free trial go to freshbooks.com indicator
And enter indicator in the how did You Hear About Us section