Support for this in
NPR podcasts
The following message
Come from the UPS
Offering services from shredding
To printing to mailbox
And instead of closing this Memorial Day we
May 24th and 25th
The UPS Store
He's doing another thing
All together
Opening
The UPS Store
Everything for small business
And of course shipping
Everyone just a quick note there are some bad words in this podcast
So if you're listening with kids
Before Ill Mind was Ill Mind he was Ramona bong
A kid from New Jersey who loved to play Super Nintendo
One game inverted
Call Mario Paint
And in that game
There's a feature that allows for you to compose music which is like
Insane
The game that you make cartoons with a Nintendo
And then like as a side
Feature you can create this kind of cheesy music
You can create any beat any tune
To go with the cartoon
Don't mind got obsessed with making music in this
He didn't save any of the songs
But you can find tons of Mario Paint music today on YouTube
You would grab like the mushroom
Character and that would be your bass drum
And then like the Cooper Trooper would be like your snare drum
Mario space with a piano start with a xylophone
But this
Sitting in a room alone using technology to make music
With the start of his career
Today behind almost all of the popular music you hear there is this
Hi-Tech
Economy
An ill mind is at the center
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Jacob golden
Today on the show we go into this universe of music producers buying and selling musical Snippets
Texting each other half finish beads
Angling for back-end royalties to hit songs
Even spelling the sound of a single tap of a snare drum
Recorded just
This is the world illmind
This message comes from NPR sponsors snowflake
The only data warehouse built for the cloud
Today organizations need the agility that rapid Data Insights bring to stay a step ahead of the competition
With snowflake you can instantly and infinitely scale your data warehouse with the touch of a button
Delivering deep insights at any time for all users
Start your journey
Towards data-driven decision-making
Making it snowflake.com NPR
A few years after he got obsessed with Mario Paint my twin Optical
But it didn't last
He dropped out moved into his mom
I just messed around all day with a keyboard and a cheap
This is not what his parents had in mind when they immigrated from the Philippines
Things to give him a better life
What a tense is definitely intense I mean
The first 5-6 years
What are you in your mom's basement for five or six years I was
I was yeah that's a long time long time man
And then in 2006
Illmind github
He gets a call from a guy to record live
Could found some of the music reminded posted on my
Shout to Myspace
The guy asked if you're more of Hillman's music to develop a little bit of relationship
And not long after that
He's like hey
LL Cool J wants to use when your track
Righto
So I ended up doing a record for LL Cool J called Queens
And 50 Cent was on the record
And so they paid me $6,000
To do that track
Shitload of money
I'm have never seen that much money in my life and they pay me in cash
So what you do with it I remember I took that money and I
Put a deposit on an apartment
So I finally moved out
Bang bang meme
So this was a break for Ill Mind
But it's not like he's got at me
He is at this point like
Thousands of other young produce
Managed
To get what's called a place
Somebody paid to use
Now he wants to get to the neck
He wants to be
Not just in a 1000
He wants to be a famous producer he wants to be somebody with his own son
To do this he decides he's got to stop using the sort of generic drum beats that he's been using
And come up with something nobody else has
But it's not like he can afford to let you know read a music studio and
Pay some professional drummers
Capa drum over
So he comes up with a different technique
Yeah mean it was me it was me in a closet
Yasso
Literally me in a closet
With like
Yeah you know Tam tambourines and like shakers in like couple other snare drums
Is there a closet in your apartment closet in my apartment and I was just like
Creating my own sounds
Italy right
Top manipulate those are
Increase this whole library of hundreds of sound
Uses those to make his
Two songs
Starts getting more work
Does some more stuff with him
50 Cent works on it
Tupac Remix album
Start hanging out getting to know people in the industry and people start to know Illinois
And he's fat
So one day I woke up 2011
And I said to myself well
I have a little bit of a following
Right
And I'm wondering if there's producers out there
Who won
Illmind
He thinks
Oh my drum sounds on my
Play tambourine sound
Snaps and everything else
Are just digital files on my lap
I could sell those online
I mean not not home
Snuggle Song
Just sell a folder with like a hundred different song
Sound of a snare drum being hit
Tambourine shaking one time
Other producers could by the pack
And use it to make
Their music
He thinks it could be a way for me to make a little money
Get my name out there a little more among other producers
Or
Maybe you would be selling away the one thing that made people want to use an Ill Mind beat
Instead of some other
I'm I'm afraid that
People
Might end up sounding like me
Right in that that was the whole fear
Behind
That that old school mentality of not sharing your sound as well there's only one me
If I put my sounds out then will be
Hundreds of versions of me right and you are all you got right like your whole business is that you sounds only like you and nobody else
Sounds like you and if that's gone
You got nothing
The exactly
Three ways these options
Thinks about it and decides
You know what I'm just some guy playing the tambourine in a closet in New Jersey
Why not
So
So I said you know what 20-25 bucks
Hundred 250 sounds
Zendaya in a folder
And that's why I'm going to charge so
I went to my blog site
And I put up a PayPal Now button
And
And address I didn't think anything of it I said okay O mine drum kit I named it a black
Elap
Kit black it just like a cool name right and to be clear what he puts in this folder is not beats or songs
Just individual sounds manipulated all these two
For snare drums alone there are 46 different files
Each with its own name
There's snare basic
Snare blue
Snare board
Near born again
Near Buda
Near buzzworthy
And those are just the bees
So just this folder with 113 Whittlesey
No man has no idea what's going to happen
He posted online and
I woke up the next morning
And I found that
I had like
$2,000 in my PayPal account that I didn't have the knife
Before
So I'm like holy s*** like
People want this thing
So
So I'm like wow and then like more sales are coming in
And so I literally you know I didn't have an e-commerce store
Who is PayPal so
I was literally emailing every single customer saying hey
Appreciate you buying a drunk here's the downloads
People keep buying a
And for a while he's worried that everybody's going to start sounding
But when you listen to the music people are making with his kids
I discovered that
You know a lot of these producers that are using my sounds
Don't sound like
They're taking my sounds and they're kind of putting their own unique Twisted them
You know discovering that was was a big
Revelation for me like
I can put all these sounds out and people out there won't
Necessarily you know take my spot or steal my sound
Other people figured out the same thing
Back window mine release that first black kid drum kits with his new idea something just a few people were
And a lot of people were free
Since then the ideas taken off
Now there's this whole industry
Drum kit
Sample packs
All these different kind of like Lego blocks
Blocks that producers can use to build
Princeton's there's this company called splice in New York
Bay Breeze millions of dollars in Ventura
And they want to be
Kind of like the net
They're signing up famous producers
Create sample pack
Saxon drum kit
It's just reply
And through the company you get access to this
Huge library of
You know drums and pianos and effect
Everything you can think
Soaps place is kind of
One end of the spectrum
There's also this other very high
An end of this guy there is a big-time producer named
Frank.
Frank Dux has put out this record light
And the record label releases out
Like this one
Call the lap of Lux
But the songs on this album and the other album they are not made to go on the radio or on Spotify
They're made just for other producers to sample
Chop up
And remix and put into songs that do go on the radio
And on Spotify
When that happens
Frank Dukes often ends up getting
Royalty
This means he can make
Tons of
Don't mind just got into this high-end sample busy
But he's also still releasing those basic black kid
That people can buy for 20 or 30 bucks
And use however they
Fast forward to now
Which is 6 years later
Is become this full-blown
Like
Legit business
Give me some sense
It's like what what's the revenue more or less
Order of magnitude of Revenue
Every year every year hundreds of thousands of dollars yeah
And this is people buying kids for twenty bucks
What you turn on the radio do you just like you're like oh I know where that got that
Kick Drum
All the time
All the time I put on a Spotify playlist when I got there as my snare
I like out there's my cowbell you no listen listen
I mean Bruno Mars
His new album has blackheads all over it
You know Kendrick Lamar's new album
Taylor Swift recent album
A lot of these are just like
Ice near here or snapped
But there's one that he played for me that is a little easier for an ordinary person to
It's going to get called all grunts everything
Ill Mind Zone voice tweet in all these different way
Come on play me some
Coming
Yeah
Don't mind recently heard that last sound out in the wild
Curative
Again
Yeah
You heard it on an album called Malibu
By Anderson paak right here
A little Yeah Yeah Yeahs Play It Again
I know it's hard to hit
So this is obviously subtle
I mean I could barely hear it I was sitting there next to Ill Mind and he was pointing it out
But apparently
Two music producers
It is not
Music producers listen to a song and they hear every single part in their head
The way say
Home chef
Can be eating some
Fancy complex dish
And taste every single ingredient
Music producers listen to this song
And they hear Ill Mind you
And they recognize
And a lot of the time
Do you like it
And so the black cats have become not just a source of income for
They've been sort of an ad
Other producers hear the sea
Anthony decide
Oh I want to work more with you
All songs with her
I never been this whole other part of Ill Mind career where he has made songs for people like
Drake and
Kanye and J Cole
Will have that part of his career
In a minute
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Delta
Delta flies to 300 cities around the world
Best 300 cities
It's where many people do the same things you do
That's 300 cities were people in those 300 cities think they're the only ones who know about that
One place and 300 cities where people miss someone
One and one of Delta's other 299 cities
Delta isn't flying to 300 cities merely to bring people together
But to show that we're not that far apart in the first
Delta
Keep climbing
Illmind has been a writer or producer on songs
Drake
Kanye West
Cole
And each case each song is a little
But it is never
So a bunch of us went into a studio and made a song from
It's always more spread out than that
More technologically intermediate
What are the woman's favorites is a song that
Jake hold
Called love yours
It's been streamed like
74 million times on Spotify
Thought an album that went double
Yo man told me the story of how that song
It was 2013
And a producer ill-minded meted a Beat battle years before
Email them a folder with a bunch of little piano
Happens all the time
I'm so just another day they send me this piano Loop
This is the way music get Manor
Somebody in a room somewhere comes up with some little things
And thanks
Who do I know who might be able to to use this to work with it to create something
And so I added the strings in there
Canelo drumroll I added coming up
Don't mind doing all this just sitting at a desk playing a keyboard manipulating all those sounds on his laptop
And that's basically the beat
Real simple just straightforward
Didn't want to overdo it
How long did it take you to create a by 20 minutes
So in a day of work
Create one of those after another
Yep one after the other you know some days I'll spend
8 hours and I'll create maybe 10
10 track 10 lottery ticket
Like you said why do you call me
What mean
It is there lottery tickets because every
Every Beat every piece of music that I make has potential
To get placed somewhere
So their potential to make money but I mean most of them.
Don't write most of them don't most of them sit on a hard drive write ready to ready to make money though at some point
The email is open
The phone lines are open guys
What do you think you hear here in this part of the conversation I think is a big part of the reason you'll mind has been 6
It's because he thinks of himself
Not just as a musician or Purdue
Clearly he thinks of himself as running a small business
You Know It studio is just a room in the back of his apartment
There's a stack of books in there on the windowsill
Their business
One of them is by a marketing professor at Wharton about how things go viral amazing book
This is my second time reading through it
Around being a producer who is famous among other producer
This summer he traveled to cities around the
And help these events where aspiring producers
Paid $250 each
Come sit in the studio with your mind
Play in their beef and get it
I went to the one he had any
There's about 20 people crammed into this little studio in a kind of run-down building North
The Time Square
Someone call your name out
Basically you're going to come up
And plug the aux in
So I'm assuming people have their
Computers phones
Where to plug in
Okay cool people come up one-by-one they introduce themselves
So what's your producer name I go by spice production
Spice production
I sent you a long-winded email while ago okay
You replied you know saying and that was big for me
And then spice Productions plays his music for Alma
Don't mind let's play for a minute or two
Turns it off
Everybody applauds
And then don't mind Jesus t
In terms of the mix like the bass sound a little muddy
I think you just want to
Try to balance the
Baseline
And the kick drum feedback with technical
What's up
I don't what kind of Motors you got
Yamaha's but I got the itis
Okay
I would I always say
This is kind of what I expect
But what's really surprising to me is that Ill Mind also gives a lot of basic business at
This isn't just
Polish up your beats with a beat making
This is
How to make it in the music
This horseshit that were trying to do here
Is to just like become successful right
And the only way to do that is to
Those guys out there that are mediocre that know everyone
And they're really cool
And
There's Executives that like being around them and they're getting every opportunity
But it's a dumb you know 5:10
15 years to nurture those relationship
So I think that's another misconception to get us producers is yellow like
My Beats are good enough my Beats are better than that person that person why am I not put on
What does you don't know
You didn't put five five years in
Like you know
Pulling up to the crib and watching football and get to know the person
You didn't do that
They did it
So he's getting a shot in your knee
Does that make sense
Yeah yeah
Don't mind didn't just become the producers
He spent decades
Not just making music
But also
Becoming the guy who knows a guy
Which is why back in 2013 he got a call from someone he knew Indian
It's called me and he said hey
Yoel I work with J Cole
I'm wondering if you have any tracks for him
Immediately of that track that had started with the piano Loop those producers
Emailed it off and heard back like a week later
J Cole wants to use this on his neck
Album
Ill Mind and the producer who sent him the piano Loop in the first place both got credited as producers and writers
Which means they get royalty
Here's the song it's it's a really special song so
It's called love yours here it is
Love yourz
No such thing
No sense
Love yourz
Note to self
There It Is Love yourz by J.Cole better song
20 20 minutes
In the studio just making music freely with no intention having fun
Which eventually
Got me a Grammy nomination and
Couple bucks
But the point is it wasn't just 20 minutes
In the studio
It's what he's been working on his entire adult life
Is there some other corner of the economy that you want us to explore on a future show
Email us at Planet Money at npr.org or find us on Facebook or Twitter Today Show was produced by Nick found
Our senior producer is Alex goldmark Brian Dorsett Terry secretes of record
Special take today to alcoda who runs the site the drum broker also Gray brasstracks
And Steve martocci of spa
That Mario Paint song at the beginning of the show was by Alex Britt
You looking for something else to listen to Let Me recommend fresh air
Terry Gross is perhaps the best interviewer of musicians in America she has been doing it for
Decades now
You can get her show fresh air as a podcast listen to it anytime you want
I'm Jacob Goldstein thanks for listening