Every week at Planet Money we have
Restoring meeting
We're supposed to be pitching ideas of stories that we wanted to
But a lot of the time
We just end up talking about stories that other people have done
Stories that are so brilliant and so perfect
Did we just
Throw up our hands and see
Why didn't I think of that
And then we move on
But but one day a year
We do not
Move on
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Noel King
We have an annual tradition
Started it last
Any idea is we just give a shout out to people whose work we love
Today on the show
We send out Valentine
Tries to the best of the best
We got the secret history of ranch dressing
Coolest kid in Kansas
And Young Thug
We'd like to say a quick thank you and share a message from one of our sponsors freshbooks who are on a mission and
2017 to simplify your paperwork
Freshbooks makes Cloud accounting software for self-employed professionals that's so ridiculously easy
Easy to use babe now health over 10 million small businesses save time and get paid faster
Send an invoice in under 30 seconds
Set up online payments in two clicks
And track time using their mobile app
For your 30-day free trial go to freshbooks.com Planet Money
An inter Planet Money in the how did you hear about it
Alright first step is
Jacob Goldstein Jacob
Mario time is
The story that appeared on the front page of the Wall Street Journal on
Say on October 19th
Mm
Headline
What does Nevada
35 billion dollar fund manager do all day
Nothing
You know I didn't I didn't love the
He does nothing all day
Title of the article of course it all my coworkers are telling me to get to work
That is
Steve Edmonds
He is the manager for the pension fund for Nevada state employees
And that's heavilin on the story it's a joke about this investing strategy
Call passive man
And it's sort of become
All the rage you know the traditional style of managing money
This is true
For like a mutual funds for ordinary people's retirement funds but also for big Pension funds
The traditional style is
Active
And that is basically
You pay someone who's like really smart
Studies the market to like
Pick stocks and bonds
That they think are going to do
Guide your passive management is
That is a waste of money
But those people are not worth the money you're paying them
And you're better off
Not paying them and just more less buying all of this
And all of the bond
And not trying to
And so if your job is just buy all the stocks
You don't have to spend all day BMI
I'm going to research this one.
Call the company you just buy ammo
And the genius of this
Story from the
The journal is
It captures
This whole sort of idea of passive man
In the form of this one
Person of
Steve Edmond
You've liked the embodiment of passive men
You know he manages a lot of
As of this morning 36
Point six billion in assets
36.6 and I picture like
Udo Giant
Midtown Manhattan office would like a ridiculous sense
Parkview
A little one story building in Carson City Nevada
Got a little office and I almost get a view of the mountains not quite
Looking at the office building
He drives an old car hits its a 2005 Honda Element
So there's all these delightful details about him
In the story
But there's also I think this interesting idea here which is
You know
It is it is really contrary to human nature to like look at some massive news event or whatever be like
I think that the human instinct is to
Constantly Act
So what is he doing
Well okay so yeah
Kiki doesn't do nothing
Think of you please not like Trading
But you know
He basically has to sort of just to manage the check
Book of the funds you don't like
Employees are
Contributing intuitive
Make sure their money you don't get that out into the stock market
Retirees need to get paid
Truly doing nothing
He's just not trading my
And I should say the piece in the drill it's just a really lovely little story really nicely
The reporter who wrote it was Timothy W mark
Take a piece of grass
Yeah I know I'm getting paid by the hour. All day man
CrossFit poster
So my Valentine is something that Jacob I know you love to its it goes out to the obituaries
Section of The Economist magazine
I love it
So much
Run one obituary every week at the back of the magazine sometimes someone famous
Sometimes it's someone I've never heard of
And I wanted to know who
Who writes Ozark
Obituaries so I thought it would be some like very Grim serious buttoned-up dude
And I was completely wrong because everybody likes of The Economist is that have that in your mind right
It is actually this woman named Dan Rowe and she's not buttoned-up
Just lovely I said one you I've got a code saying I'm holding it at Bay
What it might Southern sexy or it might just sound you cranky
Give me a little about her writing is something that I think is
Is true of all great writer
You read something by her and even if her name's not on it
You know it's her
To my favorite obituary from the past year that she did was of Prince
I love
Prince so I must have read about 10 Prince obit
Fairies
And here's what most of them early
Like this is this is a real one
And it starts
Prince the songwriter singer producer One Man Studio band and consummate Showman
Died on Thursday at his home Paisley Park
In Chanhassen Minnesota
He was 50 Cent
So that is a typical obituary
But and obit in The Economist starts out talking about
Freedom
I asked her to read her opening
So sexy freedom
So sexy he couldn't begin to explain it
So sexy, freedom
Free to put on mascara
Painted lips glue on long eyelashes
Tulo aflutter and seduce
Stratton Ruffles
Squeeze in black leather
Praying his naked midriff
Shake his naked ass out of yellow gems
Maybe that's it
More
It's okay
What what are
Here's what she told me she said first thing is she will get her assignment on a Thursday
And that point she only has
36 hours
To turn this thing off
Sushi gets raped
My first port-of-call is
The London Library which is just around the corner from here
Luckily
And I raced there and
I see if my subject has written
What's a biography
Do you realize that yourself
Now I try to look at myself otherwise I mean
If I don't go who knows what they might miss do you know yours you got to you got to get yourself anyways send you the right in the corner
Givenchy goes online
My Google Google Google I cannot say like Google
Strange things with the name
You know if I was Googling prints I might Google Print
Menchie's
So none of this seems
Strange or Secret
Crimson cheese
That's something
I think she told me
The secret partner
Secret Santa
She is not really interested in what other people have to
To say about her subject
Their friends their co-workers their family
She doesn't usually talk to those p
She only wants to
To hear what the person she's profiling has
To say about themselves
That's best
Rad wait a minute and then she feels like she can hear their voices in her head
So she sits at her desk and she
Choose our pain and she channels
Like she's actually writing in their voice
You trying to get the human soul I really believe in this
And therefore what I think I'm doing is
Catching Souls end
That's an almost impossible business
TBN
And I think that's the reason that she's so memorable and so extraordinary because
When she writes
She's actually becoming someone else
Genius
Damn right
All right
That mean you want me to leave now
Hey Nick fountain
Who's your Valentine
My Valentine
Goes out to a music video director
His name is Ryan Stack
And he made only one video that I've ever seen it is a music video for the atlanta-based rapper
Young Thug
I know out the reason I love this video
Because of what I do every
Right I'm a producer here at Planet Money
And what I do largely is like
Reporter wrangling and guests wrangling and
Making sure that all the right elements for podcast are in the right place
At the right time right now
And sometimes
That delicate choreography just goes all wrong
And Ryan Stack my Valentine the music video director
Took one of these disastrous production days
Just the worst I've ever heard of
And made it into something brilliant
The the first moment I realized things were
Kind of you not going according to plan and going south is probably that that first shot
The reason things were going south
Is because Young Thug the star of the video was not there
Which undermines the entire point of a music video
Right beside things
No worries
At 11 a.m.
We got time we can do
Deschutes summer
Establishing shots
And when Young Thug arrives
We can shoot him
In those places and
Edit him in
Impost
And then from there it just got worse and worse and worse
Toast
All day long
He's shooting scenes of this young thug video
Without Young Thug
And keep in mind he'd hired a huge
Screw head blocked off
The street
He's a little nervous but he's like I'm going to make this work
She keeps shooting
And then
The sun goes down
Openstack is like
I've spent $75,000 already
I just got to get one shot of Young Thug
Sing the lyrics to this song
If I can be pretty
But I'm going to make it work
And then
After 10 hours of shooting pulled up and we thought he was going to be
Coming up shortly to be part of the scene and then
Yeah awesome feeling
And then he did not come out of the car
I have nothing that they have
Absolutely
It's just a nightmare
It's absolutely a night
Stack is like
This is the worst day ever he's driving back to the hotel
Annies with somebody from his crew and
But he's just like repeating it over and over in his head
Yeah I would just like
Mention something in the she like me and it sucks when you know
Bob what happened and he be like yeah that that sucked
And I'd like to be quiet for a while and be like
Internet part 1
You know he didn't get out of the cartoon that suck
Guy was bad
And it's just like how like repeating the same the obvious stuff over and over like almost in the days
But the reason we're here today Noel
Is because stack made something anyways
It's right he made
A music video
About making a music video where the artist
Featured in the music video
Hasn't showed up for the music
I want to play it
Perfect
Here it is
So so far
Standard music video models
Cars yeah but then
There's like the subtitles like at the foreign language film
But it's just he's like
Passive-aggressive commentaries on the day so this first one is
Young Thug didn't show up in time for that shot
Holy calling about and the next one says
In fact
She never showed up for any of our shop
And then it got better he has like these little outlines of where Young Thug should be sitting in a shot
And it's the producer me who loved this
Because
You just made
This beautiful thing
Out of nothing
And that's something we all aspire to
Alright Nick sound thank you so much one more things I reached out to Young Thug people for comment
He has not gotten back
You maybe you will by sundell
Next up is a quick one from Alex
Chick-fil-A
My Planet Money Valentine goes out to someone named Ernie
Because he is a
Connoisseur of the Monday
He is an expert in
Boredom
He runs a newsletter called tedium
What he obsesses over boring things until they become
He writes these
Long post filled with details
Where he digs up old patent filing
Clippings from hundred-year-old newspapers archival audio
Just goes
So not
And I love it
So I called them up and I asked him about some of his face
I did a really great one about
Suck the issue with umbrella patent
I was titled when it rains it pours
Inventors keep coming up with new ideas for umbrellas but consumers don't ever buy them they just
I did one on the history of ranch dressing a while ago which was
Very much
I would say a personal interest in mind
It really is from a ranch and it really was called hitting the
The history of fingernail clippers and how we put their fingernails before we had fingernail clippers
So many ways one device
Was
Kind of like an apple peeler and it's
Terrifying in
And no
Ernie Smith Never claims that these posts are important
But he sees what he's doing is it kind of antidote to the firehose of tiny updates and breathlessness
Tedium
The newsletter
I want to check it out thanks Alex you got it
Alright next up is our editor Bryan tour
Hey
This is the first time you've been on air
This is the first time I've ever been on
A podcast
Awesome
Well we're happy to have you end
Who is your Valentine
So I'm going to tell you how I found out about my valentine
My first my son came home one day and he was like Dad can we get a trampoline weight how old is your son
So
It doesn't make sense because we live in a tiny little apartment and it's only like 6 foot from wall to wall
And I don't think he's ever seen a trampoline
So there's no possible way we get a trampoline and I didn't know what he was talking about and I just sort of wrote it off and I said no we can't get it
And then he came home another day and he said
Can you take me to store so we can get some
Spiking gel
Spiking for his hair to spike it up straight
Animes like 11 okay
Okay
We can do that
And then he came home a third time and we were just sort of sitting quietly and he said
Can we move to Kansas
And I said
Kansas
Why and he said cuz that's where Tanner braungardt lives
And Tanner braungardt is a YouTube Star
Since he's about 7 he's been chronicling
Kind of his whole life
On YouTube
He makes these inventive little skits and videos and
Kind of has created a whole little entertainment Empire this just him and his friends
Is 2 million fans
Mostly like my son who just loved everything he doesn't have spiky hair and want trampolines
I got AT&T team
And he has made Kansas seem like the most interesting place you could possibly live
And
I am jealous of him because I think he's a person who has
Kind of founder figured out a new art form that didn't exist
Even just a few years ago
And he's done what
A person does with art which is take the mundane and the normal and the stuff that we think is too uninteresting to be excited about
10 made into something that everyone else wants to be a part of
Am I
I'm kind of jealous of that cuz I wish I was like that too
You wish you were an artist or you wish I wish I wish I wish I had that everything but I wish I had that sense of how to
How to transform
Just regular life into special life
Very cool
Okay Bryant one last thing before you leave
We should say that we stole the conceit of this show from the place that you used to work Bloomberg business
That's right over there we called it the jealousy list
And I
In some ways I think that was
Maybe a better name
Because
These are Valentine's here but
They're also about
Jealousy and envy which is
Which is like
One of the seven sins and it's like a serious feeling and we would get it and we would want to
Beatles people and have done the things they do
Alright thanks Brian I hope your first podcast appearance was fun
I am exhausted I have to go right now
Okay one last item it comes from Planet Money producer Sally helm
Until yours has to do is straight-up jealousy
Yes
My Valentine goes out to a website that I
Called
And what is reductress
Reductress is a satirical women's mag
Magazine
It's like the onion meets Cosmo I went down to the doctors offices a few days ago and I talked to
Three ladies there they are Beth Newell
Sarah pappalardo and Nicole silverberg
Stay at the site
And
A big job is coming up with funny
Headlines
Which
Noel I think you maybe could agree we need a little help
The headline
They are not our strong suit
Why don't you come up with to get a butt
The thing is it takes us
Forever
Like way way to
Atlanta money we tend to spend like
3 hours on a Friday afternoon just trying to come up with the headline for the one episode that we have to put out that day
How many headlights do you guys come up with everyday
A varies I mean our writers pictures
Hundreds a week
So I have a question
For you we are doing a
Show that is annual tuition for us
It's our jealousy show
It specifically about professional jealousy so jealousy of other people's work
If you were to come up with a headline for that episode
What would you call it
Oh my God I'm so happy for you oh my God I'm
So happy
Yes it's the subject of all of these Valentine
A little bit
Like
I love what you do
I wish I could have been me a little bit
But I mean I mean
So
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Showtime
Billions
The hit Showtime original series starring Emmy winner
Damian Lewis
And Paul Giamatti
Returns for season 2 on Sunday February 19th at 10 9C
Download the Showtime app now
Catch up on season 1 and start your
Your free trial
What stories have you read that you think we should have done on Planet Money
You can send us an email we are Planet Money at npr.org
You got to find us on Facebook
Or Twitter at Planet Money
Are you sure today was produced by Nick Fountain and by Elizabeth cool ass thanks guys
And if you're looking for something else listen to check out the ask me another podcast
It's like
Your favorite game night or trivia night but way funnier
Are there last Valentine goes out to them
You can find ask me another on the NPR one app
Aurat npr.org
Splash podcast
I'm finally home and I'm Noel King thanks for listening
Prince died
I never thought I'd laugh
So yeah so you read take a picture it so I must have read
10 Prince
Prince died
The best of a great artist
And I love her
Prince so I must
To read about