If you happen to be in downtown Chicago
During the first week of January this year
You would have seen something incredibly strange
Hundreds of young
20 something
Dressed in new suits and stiff new shoes a lot of them running hits
Kind of amazing there sprinting down the sidewalks the city back and forth across the Chicago River
These are graduate students
In economics
Heading to their very first
Job interview
The reason the reason they're running is that the economics profession at some point decided that it was going to create
Job market
Unlike any other
Every University or company that wants to hire professional Economist has come here to Chicago for the weekend
Every employer set up in a different hotel room in hotels all across
The city
And then every graduate student who wants a job has to show up
They try to interview for as many jobs as they can over the next three days
It's like speed dating
For cannabis
And sometimes you got to run to the next interview
I think you're aware like
4 minutes late
Search for an extra 30 seconds
Mexican Taxi
I am barely keeping up with this guy
Is Julian shoe
The Hotshot
Economics grad student
From one of the best schools in the country University of Michigan
If you were in any other academic fields
You would be wined and dined by employers right now
Not running down the street
I'm at the right Hotel this is good
Joints about to happen
The first real job interview of his life
You check to make sure a suit looks
Did you know how to tie a tie
I've got no type. Clearly I don't know how to type
Your little you little on edge a little sensitive
Yeah I mean
My livelihood
Robert Smith
And I'm Adrian ma Adrian is a producer at WNYC brought this story and the reason why
Finding the perfect job we all know this waste a lot of time and a lot of money
And you hate wasting time and money
Economy
So they decided to show the rest of us how it should be done
Be creative Market
A market for themselves
Oh not just any Market
The hyper-efficient multi bitter optimize sorting
Sister
Effortly balancing the needs of management and labor tested by game theorists
Tweaked by Nobel Prize winner himself
Draya Michele
We'll see how it works out for them
Support for this podcast and the following message come from rocket mortgage
My Quicken Loans
When it comes to the big decision of choosing a mortgage lender
It's important to work with someone you can trust who has your best interest in mind
With rocket mortgage you'll get a transparent online process that gives you the confidence you need to make
Form decision
Skip the bank
Skip the waiting
And go completely online at quickenloans.com money
Equal Housing lender
License in all 50 states
Nmls consumer access. Org number 3030
Economist decided to create a job market for themselves
I thought of every
And they started with scale
The job market is planned for the exactly weekend
At the American economic Association
So they knew all the big players in economics
Would already be around
But
Doing a conference and a job market at the same time
Means that they need thousands and thousands of cheap hotel rooms
You don't think that's really cheap and has almost no tourists
Chicago
In the first week of January
I woke up my first morning in Chicago
And I heard this already
Looks like front is 3 degrees windchill
17 below zero
At O'Hare
Will have your neck
Julian shoe was already there early
First day
To find a job
Julian standout in the crowd of Economist he has a huge smiley outgoing
He makes eye contact when he talks to you
It is not a coincidence that
He was actually the only graduate students
It agreed to be followed around by us
He's confident
What
He also says he's having these anxiety dreams about the inner
Movies that are coming
In my nightmare my interviewers ask me a question and I just
Have no response
How long is the silence last
Am I Dreaming eternity
Julian does not have
An eternity to waste
He has more than 20 interviews already scheduled for the next
Read it
He's applied to universities
Private companies
Private consulting firms
Uber Amazon some big Tech names
What Ewing is really excited
Bye
The government
He loves
Big
Dataset people have a lot of numbers
So he applied to work at of course
The treasury Department
And he's not the only one there about 1,800 other grad students just like Julian going for the same job
Pretty sweet jobs at that starting salary is usually above $100,000 a year
Restart router
First stop
Embassy Suites across the river
You ain't long underwear
Are you I am
Apparently called a walk across a couple lengths traffic
Over the bridge
Everything calm
On schedule the longest track will be Embassy Suites to the
Wyndham Grand that will take 15 minutes max minimum of 13 minutes
Wait you've done this on Google Maps you can get between this place
Are you free walk I free walk today
We make it to the Embassy Suites on time but we hit something that Julien did not plan for
The lobby is mop
The bunch of other grad students all try to make their 9 a.m. slot
Elevator
We wait for the next one
Julia uses this moment to get into the zone
His first interview is with the University of Oklahoma
University of Okla
What is this this is my crib sheet for University of Oklahoma so I kind of know who they are
Jehoiakim is into metric so if he ask me question I should give a pretty metrics the answer which means math
Not the answer I hear about it says it's a small Peach defense Maltese deprogrammed invasive
I only have four
I students this year
Good luck
Thanks
Proud moments
Julian heads-up
The hotel room alone
And there he will find faculty members of the economics Department of the University of Oklahoma
We didn't tell Julian
But we met one of them last
Hi my name is Gary Hoover
I'm the charity economics department at the University of Oklahoma
Took an idea of what the interview
Will look like he shows us around his
His hotel room is a hotel suite
Actually there is a couch
So I dropped her today won't have to sit on the bed although
That does occasionally happen
He says pretty soon the room will start getting filled with coffee cups
Snack wrappers
The interview was basically don't leave the room for days
It's interview after interview after
Interview do they get to do anything else with the conference
Sleep
And no
Hooper's looking for someone like Julian
Somebody who can work with big data
But also has the
People skills to teach undergrad
Uber doesn't necessarily get
His first
Pic of John Kennedy
It's because this is a job market
As an employer he does not have all the power
Because there's a bunch of other schools were also trying to nap the best people
Speakers at the University of Oklahoma may not be the most
Prestigious economics Department Of The Nation but you know
Here at the job market
He's in the same kind of hotel room at Harvard is
An MIT in Princeton
And if I can ask an intelligent question
And
AT-AT shows you
These guys are serious Economist this serious scholar
That you might have thought well now they're in a Cow Town and
We can impress to
Uber says this is one of the best things about the econjobmarket
In the old days
The top students
Automatic
Glee went to the tops
But clearance
Chicago
Cheap and easy for everyone
Take a chance
Yeah universities can gamble on an untraditional candy
They might not have looked at
Students can check out a
Account
That they might not have considered visit
This is us into the conversation
In theory that's what's going on inside the hotel room
Everyone's trying to impress each other
And when Julian gets out of the University of Oklahoma interview
50 am
We want to ask him
How'd it go you first meet interview
But already is eyes have that sort of
Reveal
He's got a pen interview with University of Pennsylvania at the Wyndham Hotel
Battletag
30 minutes so I'm already late
Okay time for the play-by-play
Thread his way through the streets of Chicago
He's already looked at the route to a fast walk to a jog
We hit Michigan Avenue at full speed and then boom
Don't want some did not plan for the car
Turn it to make up time to jog starts to become a Sprint the dude is running full album
You got to leave me behind
I had to stop running
I had to stop running in Julian take off
It is calling him I am barely hanging on
We get to the hotel push through the revolving doors about 5 minutes late and it shoots directly into the elevator
Funny horn
Jo-Ann's gone upstairs
Catch My Breath
Got a coffee and then Robert you finally walk in
I already have a job
I do not need to run through the streets of Chicago
Half an hour later your heart rate has returned to normal
But when Julian comes back down
He seems more rattled than winning winning
When do they cut you off so like you're supposed to have a 15-minute saying ready to go
Yeah I finished overall summary
So they're like 13 minutes
The details afterwards and then I doubt we don't hear that that's like
At work by
But I have to say
The good thing about the schedule that I know
Is that there is no.
Time
To replay the Batmobile
There is always
Another interview
Factors one at 11
At the Fairmont Hotel should be an easy walk
32 Stetson
Actually I'm not sure
Give me some amazing that this is designed as a perfect job market because in the moment it seems like so
Many
Things can go wrong
In fact when we were hanging out the conference cuz
We're not going to follow Julian all day long everyone there has been through this process at some point and they all have these
Horror stories
About what can happen
Rental professor at Cornell
Is John Colley
And he told us about the time
The job market was in Philly to Philadelphia for 5 years ago got hit with
Big snow storm and people just could not get in
And so yeah there's job Kenny to just could not interview and think of it from the perspective of the poor graduate students
I mean there's been some of the six
Years preparing for this one
Weekend
And then
Anything
So we had one job candidate we interviewed
And she got laryngitis
And so she was able to get through our interview just barely be could barely understand her
Cancel a whole bunch of other interview
By the way Callie says they interviewed her over Skype later
And they gave her a job
Stop & Shop
But I'm telling you you serve
Tray of bad clams
At the econometrics reception
And all the sudden you could lose the entire next generation of economist
Yeah okay but
Join wasn't going to a lot of these
Perceptions
He says he was basically subsisting off bread
Peanut butter
Spent the whole weekend interviewing and
And I have to say like we wanted to see what
Actual interview
Look like we called a lot of people trying to get into the route
Behind the locked door to see how it actually went down but
Lisa Bonet
Stupid these are make-or-break career moments they didn't really want someone to the microphone inside
Except
University of
University Baptist so cool
If you ain't go with it
So are we
This is where the magic happens
What would you describe as is the ideal sort of place and maybe
Does Memphis V Adder or not
Setting there multiple ways to answer that question so I'll start with what do I want
Out of my PhD
For hotel room someone has been living in for 4 days
Place seems pretty professional for an interview
Joanne sitting in a chair in front of for professors who are all lined up in front of him
Couch
Labor Economist and I use a variety of different estimation
Quantitative
Techniques
I understand different sorts of aspects of
Economics Magic
You know I have to say
I was pleasantly surprised
The guy is
Smooth
He was great he did a great job you have some good questions you remember everyone's name
It was pretty flowers
Rap-up
Pleasure to meet all of you
After Julian leaves we stick around for just a few minutes and one of the professors gym in spear
He great he said Julian was great
Maybe
Even tube
There is an irony involved in a candidate doing really well in the interview
Who also has very good recommendations like Julian
And that we're also evaluating whether we can get this person
Until we have we have had some Canada to we say man they if they were really good
And Eminem or not sure we can get them now because they're really good
And I'm not going to say Julian in that category but that is that is one thing that comes with
Somebody doing a really
Great interview
Are we might end up saying well I think they're going to go to a better school then then I serve more prestigious School than us
Usually a school offer to fly three of the best candidates the interview to the campus 2
Woo them in a second round of interviews
But the schools do not want to waste those offers
On people who would never take
Take a job
It's like dating
You think about asking somebody out
Part of that mental calculation is
Is this person going to say yes
Yeah maybe you don't ask out the hottest person in the bar because you assume that they are out of your league
Baby nobody asked that person
Which is why we have so many lonely soup
It's actually a real problem that happened in the econjobmarket not too long ago
I kind of noticed that a lot of really great candidates like Julian
We're getting offers even though they Easter interview
The only thing that Economist loves more than a perfect Market
Is finding the one flaw in an otherwise perfect
Chick Market
Economist
This is the national Economist convention
The best Minds in economics were recruited
Figure out what was going wrong one of those mine
Alvin Roth
He won a Nobel Prize for his work
On Market design he developed the way organ donors are matched
Patience this guy is a legend
He says
The problem boils down to this
Fundamental economic Concepts
Decentralized markets where
You have to evaluate people in a Time
Consuming way suffer from
Congestion
The Economist job market made it so easy to apply for
Jobs that a lot of people were applying to places
They had no interest in
They would never go to
Pachulia
We told Rob that Julian applied to
Deafness
250 jobs
Okay that's a big number it's not unheard of obviously but
But lots of people apply to 100 job so it's not an extraordinary
With so many applicants
Clogging the market
How do you know which ones are ready to commit
Rough came up with an elegant
He didn't want to crack down and limit the number.
Applications
Instead he came up with a plan to add a little bit of extra information
Into the sea
The American economic Association now runs a website
To which before the interviews
AR
Formalized
Candidates can send up to 2
Signals of Entry
And like a wink
It's like a wink and you can only send two wings
And they warn you
Don't waste one of your Winks on Harvard
Everyone wants to wink at Harvard
I think of an employer that hold a special place in your heart
A place you wouldn't mind going if you don't get into Harvard
Now that sounds like a small tweet
To the system
But it made all the difference
Now schools could look through the hundreds of application
See if there was someone who
Really love
Just in case
That doesn't work out
Rock also helped develop this
Kind of safety net for applicants who don't get any job
If I the spring they're still looking for a match
Bingo online
And see who still hiring
NFL this week's the number of successful job matches went up now 97% of people who go through this
Speed dating race
Find a job by the
We should say Julian did not wink at the University of Memphis
They probably got the message
That she wasn't really into
You know he did wake up
US Census Bureau
The man loves a good dataset
It is Sunday afternoon
And Julian shoe fits
Finally.
He collapses into a chair in the lobby
22 interviews
In
Three and a half days
The last interviews with Amazon
They're hiring a ton of Economist these days
Chewing pulls up a huge bag of Amazon swaggin
Come sit on the table
He is exhausted
He's got a blister from a noose
My foot hurts
I know your radio show but
You can't see this
But
Basically I have a cut on my right eye we do not need
Need to see that
22in
22 interview Julian is gone on more interviews
In one weekend
Did I think I've gone on in my entire life
Yeah and
Chewing himself is a little different
When we first met him at the beginning of the weekend he was like
Raring to go
Confidence
And he said his strategy was basically to get as many job offers.
Now he seems
Little more philosophical
Because sometimes
It's just you figuring out that you don't want this job
Or this job doesn't want you because
You're just not a good fit
And I think managing that expectation is really in Port
After a workout
And both people get all that was great
Like that's good
You leave interview everyone goes all that was bad that's also good because you agreed that this was not
Something that you want to do
Everyone we talked to say Julia know he's going to be snatched
I honestly expected that by the time we had flown back to New York City
Julian would be calling us about his job offer
Spot
It did not go down that way
Something was about to throw the economics job market into turmoil
It was much worse than a snowstorm or tree of bad clams
Coming up after this
Support for Planet Money and the following message come from Wonder
Allowing individuals to invest in solar projects earn up to 8.5% annual
Bob the Bursa find your portfolio and combating global climate change create an account for free at 1
Under capital.com Planet Money
We kept checking in with Juliana see how is going and pretty quickly he got
Offers for second-round interview
Few places even flew him out
University of Oklahoma brought him to campus week
We can meet the faculty
Took him out to a nice Italian dinner
But then
The market dried up
15 days after we saw Julian Chicago
The new president of the United States
Donald Trump
Butterfree
On all federal hiring
And you may remember this Julian
Had been counting on working in government
Here in Chicago with the
Treasury Department Federal Trade Commission
He said his special
Secret Love wink
The Census Bureau
And they all said to him hey
We just can't hire anyone
And I thought hum
That's not well-timed
By the end of February he still didn't have a job offer
Insight as I continue waiting
Waiting waiting waiting
And the backs my meth in the back of my head I'm still
Freaking out
Julie says he mostly stayed in his house
In Ann Arbor
Reading Game of Thrones
Made it up the book
Four five
He didn't want to go to the university and have to face everyone
Around this time other people had me getting job offers
I just didn't really want to
Talk to anyone
And I think
They have a job
I don't have a job
All right
And so
Julian out of necessity had to go back
To the old fashioned
Less efficient way of getting a job
He had the network
You been talking on and off with someone from the
The College Board
That's the company that runs the S8
And the College Board wasn't in Chicago this year
But they did have an opening for an economist
And Julian work disconnection
It's letters of recommendation were sent and in March
Julian.
The phone call
He was offered a job
As an economist
In the Philadelphia office of
The college board so you missed me last night
So I was
Jumping around instead of screaming
Right it's like this
Is the psychiatrist really excited
I feel like we should have seen this coming like that this is one of those romantic comedies
Where the hero is doing all this dating online but then
Of course
At the end
Finds his soulmate
You know
Pet Supermarket
The nerdy friend
Yeah it was the nerdy friend all along it
The College Board
It's
Tempting to try and draw some lessons
Right
But Julian is an economist
He's into Big Data
And he be the first to say
His experience is just one data point he's got lots of friends and colleagues who got jobs through their three days in Chicago
For most people and work great
I feel like I should be the motto of economic
It's right for most people works great I'm hoping this whole thing
Provides a good lesson
Or maybe the last
Economics lesson
For Julian to bring it to his new
Even the most
Especially designed Market
Has
Tiny cracks it doesn't work
And you're not going to get a Nobel Prize for saying it but
Sometimes
Give me a little luck
A little nudging
Make a market work
Good luck to all the brand new economics PhD of 2017 we would love to hear from you.
About the show or equation more equation you can write a planet money at NPR.
Oig or find us on Twitter I am radio Smith and I'm at Adrian J Mom that's Adrian j a
Yma Today show with Bruce by Nick mountain or editors bradhurst. Special thanks to Nathan marwell
Bright ass with Claudia Goldin and John Siegfried
And if you're looking for somebody else to listen to may I recommend Lee pop culture happy hour have a new episode about
At what they are looking forward to and
More portly
What they're dreading from the suburbs movie season
You can find that on npr.org podcast
Score on the NPR one app
I'm Roberts.
And I'm Adrienne mom thanks for listening