Support for this in
NPR Podcast
The following message come from that UPS
Offering services from shredding
To printing to mailbox
And instead of closing this Memorial Day we
May 24th and 25th
The UPS Store
He's doing another thing
All together
Opening
The UPS Store
Everything for small business
And of course shipping
You would have a hard time finding a country that has been
Lucky
Over the last several decades
In the Middle East State of Qatar
Qatar Qatar everyone we talked to for the story
Said it was
A little bit differently
And we might
Do so throughout the episode what we know for certain
Qatar is it is a country the size of
Connecticut
It's like a little thumb shaped peninsula
Shares a border with Saudi Arabia
But 2.2 million people live there and almost 90% of them are foreign workers
Curacao oil and gas per capita is the richest country in the world
And for such a tiny place it has this
Outside status there's a big US Air Force Base there it's going to host the World Cup in a few years
By many measures Qatar is living
The dream
Or at least it was
Until last week
Last week Qatar staber Saudi Arabia
Said it was going to
Close the border
That's Cutters only
Order
They told it to Terry's you can't use our airspace you can't move ships to our territorial Waters and other Gulf Nations joined
It was a modern-day blockade
And all of a sudden
Tiny cutter which doesn't grow its own food imports everything
Car was on its own
People panic
Noor Barakat lives in Doha the capital
To the doctor there
And she says when she went to the grocery store that day it was
Bedlam
Cars were parked on the sidewalk there was a sea of people inside
It has to be hundreds
People are standing in very long lines to the point where it even if you want to
Get to an aisle you can because they're people standing there waiting in line and dial
I definitely started thinking should I be scared
Because so much of Cutters food comes from Saudi Arabia nobody was sure if there would be food tomorrow
People with really just like
Grabbing everything like even thinks the people probably wouldn't normally Buy
Electric sample there was this one lady who clearly grabbed everything on The Daily Show
Cuz she had every single type of yogurt flavored non-flavored low-fat.
Just it was crazy was like
Was that the food going to war you know
North said she had to stand in the checkout line for 2 hours
The funny thing is the time where we're supposed to
Break our fast the daily fast for the holy month of Ramadan
We were still standing in line and people just started opening food in the supermarket and just giving out food to each other
North says somebody open some dates and those around
Some yogurt
That around
Which country is
Take for granted
In this world if your money will buy everything they could possibly need
So what went so wrong in Qatar so
Quickly
How does a country
Go from being on the top of the world
Becoming a pariah
Seemingly overnight
Hello
And welcome to Planet Money I'm Kenny Malone and I'm Robert Smith for power and money
On a collision course with his neighbor
It's story of buried treasure kidnapping
And a glowing Saudi Arabian
Don't forget the falcon
The Falcons
Support for NPR comes from LinkedIn learning proud to support the launch of life
NPR's guy to help you make better life
LinkedIn learning short video tutorials cover business Tech
And creative skills employers look for at every level
All taught by experts and new courses are added every week
+ LinkedIn learning is personalized
Recommended courses based on your interest and Life kid listeners get a month of learning free
Start your free trial at LinkedIn learning.com NPR
There are two parts
To the story of the Qatar blockade
There is a spectacularly strange events of the last 3 weeks
And then there was the even stranger stuff
They came before that
We're both
But we're going to start
Back in time
In a swimming pool in the Middle East
With an American dude
Our swimming pool where I used to go swimming after work
Was
Artificially chilled
Never heard of that before
So right so this is normal in the Gulf because it's so hot
Jim Crane is at Rice University
An expert on Qatar
Back a decade ago GIF with living in the region floating in his refrigerated Waters
And everything was cool but for Jim and for Qatar and for the neighbors they were like
A family they refer to each other as brothers the brother monarchy
The oldest brother in the biggest is Saudi
Arabia Saudi set
The rules dominate everything in the region
The most oil
Most money and the younger brothers are these at Kuwait
Bahrain
The United Arab Emirates
Oman
And little
Cutter with a lake
Saudi Arabia was discovering oil 80 years ago Qatar
Was a rickety port on the Persian Gulf the economy was built
On diving for pearls
Pro Bass economy is fine but what they really wanted was oil
Lots of oil
Phantom wheel but they wanted
Saudi Arabia levels of oil
So they kept Drilling and drilling for it
In 1971 the shell come
Is drilling off the
The coast in car
In the Persian Gulf
And it starts to get signs that it is sitting on top of a
Oh yeah something big
But they drill
And they drill
No oil
Just a bunch
Of natural gas
That's a huge disappointment so you know mean gas is you know it's got too much lower energy density than oil
And you know it's hard to store it
Hell yeah it's hard to ship it out in in barrels
Or balloons
Right so you basically have to have a pipeline from the the Wellhead all the way to the burner tip
Bottom line
You can't put natural gas on a big ship
And take it to the United States or Japan
At least you couldn't Act
And so cutter with stuck going door-to-door to it
Brother stay saying hey you know
Natural gas week
Build your pipeline
And they were like fine
We will take your stupid gas
We're not going to pay you very much
4 years Carter didn't know what to do with all of
Just natural
The country was rich in something
He could barely sell
They were eventually saved by a nice beautiful
Any form of a technological breakthrough
Liquefied Natural Gas
Apparently if you build a big enough
Plant you can take all of that Natural Gas
Make it super cold
Liquify
And put it on a ship take it wherever you want
Qatar essentially built the world's largest
Air condition
Engine crane went to see
Apparently every
You it looks like the most
Complicated bewilderingly complex massive bull of chrome spaghetti
Little flares here and there
Like spaghetti flambeed
When this liquefied Natural Gas
Plant open
It is a huge
Suddenly
You can do whatever it
You think about it this way Saudi Arabia Bahrain all the other Oil States
Basically stuck
Together they were the family business of
Crude oil
Their fortunes were tied together rising and falling with OPEC in the price of crude oil
But little brother cutter
Quickly became the largest exporter of natural gas in the world
And in the last 10 years that was a
A pretty sweet place to
To be
All around the globe countries
We're converting their electrical plants
The factories from
Coal and oil
Natural Gas
Within a generation
Cutter isn't just
Rich
It is stupid
And what of course does a little brother do with his Newfound wealth
What any little brother would do
Qatar rubs it in the face
Of its older brother
Who decides it is going to
Spend its money B
Becoming
A big shot
No longer just a nubbin on the backside of Saudi Arabia know Qatar is going to
They look around at another big
Lots of international
Influence
I miss you a lot of them have big international news channel
CNN
BBC Russia has RT
Toecutter
Start their own
Al Jazeera Al Jazeera on the very first program live
In the heart of the Middle East with a brother monarchies Al Jazeera
Was almost immediately
An annoyance because suddenly
You have a neighbor
With a News Network
Snooping through your trash digging up your dirt
Reporting on your scandal
MSY probably came to a head during the
The Arab Spring
Which you may remember there were all these sort of
Grassroots
People's movements in
Tunisia and Libya
Egypt
And I'll just a really made its name
Being there on the ground with the revolutionaries
Between them in
Glorifying
And when your Saudi Arabia or another monarchy sitting and watching this
This is not good for you
You are worried
You may be next
You're here is there one of their Brethren with this news channel that's kind of egging on the revolution you know so there you know of course there were
They're pretty upset about it
Was just getting started
For so many years their foreign policy had been essentially what their other brother States
They went along with the crowd
But now they decided to
Forge
Their own way in the world
And they had this
Radical concept
For a foreign policy in the Middle East
Qatar was going to be friends
With every
Car starts trying to broker
Peace deals they're willing to talk to Israel
Anthem author
Supporting the Muslim Brotherhood and they become
I'm friendly
With Aaron
For Colored this makes total sense
The ranchers the rights to that big natural gas field they are the country right across the Persian Gulf from them
And baby shared economic interest
Saudi Arabia this is a knife
Saudi Arabia hates Iran
Feeling is mutual
There's the religious Rift but also
Saudi Arabia and Iran
Are the two big dogs in the
Barking at each other over everything
A tiger doesn't seem
Hear their every move seems to say we do not need our family any
Anymore we have money we have Prestige we have power
We have a TV network
Confrontation was coming
And everyone
And then in just the last few months
Three things happened
3 orderly Bazar things that seem to have triggered the blockade we are seeing today against
The orb
The hack
And the falcon
The orb the hackathon
Orbach and Falcons
You're back in the Falcon
Number one
We are about to play for you some
And it is going to sound like we added music
Music to this I swear this is actually the music playing during this moment
You would almost certainly seen a picture of this or moment
Our President Donald Trump
Is visiting Saudi Arabia shiny new Global Center
For combating extremist ideology
Tunog urate this new play
The president post
With the King of Saudi Arabia
The president of Egypt and
A giant glowing orb they laid their hands on
Or everybody applauded the glowing orb
And with that
The GCC dcca I was up and running
This really was a big moment
This event was all about
A giant Command Center
It looks like it
NASA
But it's about fighting terrorists
It's a sign that Saudi Arabia is taking terrorism
Seriously
It's spending big
To fight it
The orbit self
Was not signaling trouble
It was the fact that Trump with his very first overseas trip
Is President chose to visit
Saudi
I kind of
New sheriff in town move as if to say uno
Baby does old presidents didn't take sides over here
Donald Trump and standing with the Saudi
Not
Event number 2
HAC
3 days after the orb
By the way that is how we are measuring time to heal after the orb
A very strange article showed up on the website for Cutters national news
This mysterious article
Claims that the Emir of Qatar
Give a speech
Incendiary
Trump won't last
President
Israel
Great friend
Qatar
Ron
Fake
Fake news did not happen the news website had been hacked in the story with plant
Because the story spread around the region
Which brings us to event
Number three
Falcon
This is the most complicated one
Because it involves kidnapping and ransoms
Falcons
Have a good night we're going to lean heavily on the financial
Some of the most amazing
According to that reporting this story start
In December of 2000
Atari hunting
Party was in Iraq
It was about two dozen
They were
Falconers meaning they travel with Falcons they train the Falcons to take the Falcons hunting and I assume
Stand around and drink tea while the Falcons
Fly around
The party of falconers
Kidnapped
Buying Iranian backed militia
And then held for rent
And in that band
The falconers
Remembers of the
Qatari Royal
Important people so there was a big issue
Matter kabani lives in Qatar he's with the Brookings institution in
In Doha would it be like Prince William being kidnapped in England
No I don't think
Not quite that high
But anyway cuz I chose to deal with the situation you know to negotiation negotiation
A lot of countries
Canecutters position
Would say
No
You are a terrorist group there's no chance we're going to negotiate
But it was the royal family and this was cutter who has made it their business to work with all kinds of unsavory group
Did you have a lot of money there
According to the financial times Qatar paid up to 1
Billion dollars
According to Financial Times reporting some of that money may have made its way to an al-qaeda-affiliated some may have gone to it
Ronnie and security of
Do you know the Saudis in the Rockies try their best to kind of
Push The Narrative of
Customer support of terrorism and this kind of felt
The Peloton that narrative
Write and in the eyes of Saudi Arabia
It was a problem a big problem
California terrorism funding Iran a billion dollars
Qatar admitted to the financial times
Yes there was some money paid but it claimed it
Much as people thought
I'm going to support terrorist groups
It didn't matter
The blockade
Amazon on Monday Saudi Arabia and the United Arab Emirates
Order
Nationals to leave the country
Here's where we are today two weeks into it
Saudi Arabia Bahrain the United Arab Emirates
Give him all severed ties
They won't allow Qatari planes
The fly over there
Airspace they won't allow Kotori ships
2doc although some marketing
Saudi Arabia has shut down the local out
What is your office
Close the border the only land border that
Dodger hats in Saudi Arabia's asking Qatari citizens
To leave the country
What you mean people have to leave behind
Jobs
Family members
Apartments for staff
This is usually the moment when
Powerful country with
Interest in the region would try to step in
You know what country like the United States in the United States
Has military bases in both of these countries in Saudi Arabia
Anthem color
But it's been a little tricky to tell
Exactly where the US stand
What's the message has been
BestMark
Yeah the president tweeted his support at first
For the blockade
He said
Perhaps this will be the beginning of the end
To the horror of
Terrorism
But then his own Secretary of State
Goes on TV
And he's at the Block
Is bad it is hurting
People are separating families and it hurts the US Military
And just to make everything
Slightly more confusing
Just this week as we're reporting this story
United States announced
That it plans to sell 12 billion dollars worth of fighter jets
To cut
It is as if they took
The glowing orb
Shook it looked down into it and it said
Reply hazy
Try again later
It's all very confusing at the MoMA
The one thing that we can say with some sort
We talked to a lot of people on the ground
In Qatar
Sounds like the supermarket situation
Has gotten much better
Paradise found some new sources of food are now getting yogurt and milk
From Turkey
Vegetables from
Iran
From Iran
The blockade
Was partially about Qatar being close to a run
And it may have made cutter
Even closer to a run
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Slack
Used by companies all over the world to get everything done
Where every part of work
From documents to decisions is stored archived and searchable
10 seconds
Slack
Where work happens
Find out why
At slack.com
If you have a better pronunciation of Qatar we would love to hear it on you know Freakonomics actually taking
All the suggestions for us thanks to them
The other comments Planet Money at npr.org Twitter
Facebook we are on all the things today show was produced by Nick
Fountain of very special thanks dude on the seam of the Middle East Institute she talked us through so much of
And also to Erika Solomon with the financial times they were doing fascinating reporting this stuff
And now that you're finished with Planet Money Man we recommend you disappear
Do you have a new season out and in it there looking at this question how is it that two people can look at the exact
Same thing and see something
Completely
You can hear invisible yet NPR. Org
Or onion pr1 app
I'm Robert Smith and I'm Kenny Malone thank you for
Falconry is it this is a popular things of big city like everybody's got a falcon
I'm telling everybody
What it is is it it's common enough
It's sort of like you you wouldn't look twice at at you and like someone walking a puppy for example
But it is mostly for the Super Bowl
So
Say like that it's like having a puppy but like a really expensive purebred hunting puppy
Have you have you done it personally have you have you gone Falcon Hyundai might have not been a personally I've gone to the f****** soup
Put this thing over your arm and was it as fun as having a puppy
No
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with great jeans
Madewell offers premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store or go to madewell.com