This is part 3
Everspace
If you have ever wondered how you can personally send something up into space to do it
Go back a couple of episodes in ketchup
We will wait
Are we good
I think so
Here is something that surprised me about the space
Once you build a saddle
And decide what you wanted to do and see
Your Plus shopping
For rocket
To put it on
And of course
Anytime you're shopping for something expensive there's always a guy
Right there's a guy with a
Line
I'm kind of like your your best friend that's going to find you a rocket somewhere in the world that has X
Space rocket broker meeting if the satellite
The Planet Money satellite ready to go if you have a satellite
The Phil is the man who can get you a lift to space
He says it's just like buying any other big-ticket item
There's a car for for every consumer and there is a type of rocket for every type of satellite
Where you want to go
We might still at the small satellite conference
Sprint in Logan Utah
He handed us a card it said right on their space flight
Dot-com
Anything you can book rocket flights right on the web
Just like Expedia
The Rockets
You put in a bag
Your satellite is
Want to go and Phil will find you a lunch
It may take a year or so to find room for your satellite the business
Is booming these days
But there are a lot of places to lunch
New Zealand California Florida Kazakhstan japan-india
They all have Rockets ready to go
Yes
The very existence of Phil
The existence of this conversation shows you how much
The space business has changed
Decades ago satellites work massive
And they would go up on Rockets owned by space agency
It could cost a hundred million dollars
So there weren't many deal speed
Now we're in an age
Tiny satellites
It's that you can hold in the palm of your hand
Rockets can fit dozens of them
Thank you satellite could hitch a ride to space
Where is cheapest
$300,000 bill
The consummate salesman says
295000 95-99
We tell Phil about the Planet Money satellite is about the size of a loaf of bread we adopted it from the start of satellite
Planet
Who kindly let us put our name on it and still says he can totally help
Think about what you want to rock it
Say about
It's like picking out a car
So as a podcast going to space
First time maybe we want to pick out something classic something safe
Like he's just orbital ATK
I mean there on time
Are reliable
Very few mishaps Volvo
That's actually a very apt
Description of orbital ATK it's definitely like a Volvo
Phil sister is of course
SpaceX
Elon Musk
Rocket company
Takeoff
Land super cool right now obviously it is the Tesla of the space business
Or
There is this new car
A small startup called Rocket
Out of New Zealand
It's still in the testing phase
But they have a plan to eventually launch a rocket
Every single week
There's a new Honda
Really hot
So hot so hot right now
52 launch
Any year
The Price is Right
I changed the game
For sure so what kind of car would rocket lab
I don't know after that.
Top for surprisingly long time
Head of a car that was sporty and 4WD
Curves
Like a Corvette or like one of those little sporty Miatas
Sure there's some sort of
Red sports car definitely convertible
Hotness
The hotness
Okay
So what is it going to be for the Planet Money sad
Should we pick the family sedan for sale
Or the sports car
I think
We need to take
Sol test drive
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
And I'm Robert Smith today on the show
What money is in the market for brand new rock
Rocket shopping
There is a new space race going on the US versus the Soviet Union
It's dozens of tiny startup companies competing to send tiny little satellites
Indoor rabbit has become so easy to make satellite
The Planet Money satellite
Little pod one we're calling it it is ready to Launch
But the new space race has reached a bottom
There are not enough rockets for everyone to get quickly into orb
So today on the show
We show you how the rocket makers
Trying to catch up
The problem is
When you're shopping for a tube of metal that spews out Flames at 5000 degrees
The truck doesn't always go as planned
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online
Presents and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layouts along with features including e-commerce functionality
And mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
For all its hotness
A rocket is just
A fancy Taxi
Picks up a little hunk of metal
Like a planetary satellite here on Earth
And it lets it off
Finna particular place
Now that place is 300 miles above the Earth
Yes and so doesn't just
Fall right back down
The rocket has to give the satellite some momentum
17000 miles an hour worth of momentum to be exact
That keeps the satellite in orbit rotating the Earth
The Rockets take one big satellite size of a refrigerator
Others are filled with satellites
The size of Rubik's
Or combination of both
And the way it works design-wise is that most of a rocket is engine and fuel
And a very tippy-top is the payload the satellites
I want a rocket gets to space
It's the right place
The nose opens like a flower
And a little satellite Papa
In that sense all Rockets are essentially the same
The competition is to see who can do that faster cheaper and
More reliably fast shipping on time that the rocket motto that's the dream
Our first test drive
Was with New Zealand
Rocket lab
A cute little Sports
I visit them back in April their factories right next to the Auckland Airport in one of those generic-looking Office Park
Except
What are the building
Has a slick
Good night black carbon fiber rocket
Sitting right on the side
I think that's where our satellites going to go
Inside I met by the CEO of Rocket lab
Peter Beck
The first thing I want to ask is
Why exactly did I have to come
This far to see rocket
We are looking at a map of the world here
And there you are New Zealand down in the lower right-hand corner
Basically a half an inch
Neil Young exactly
Just got wild curly hair and this baby face and as he wants me to the factory he says listen
Ynot New Zealand
No spice spices is kind of you to this
Super romantic place in an elite by switch right now it is but the whole point of Rocket lab is to break down that barrier
Ultron reinforced everybody that
Yeah yes it's this farnes excitement and and it was right right wonderful but at the end of the day we're
Company
We take the Apostle and we deliver it
End
Rocket lab wants to be like UPS
Type in a New Dress 300 miles above the Earth
Which orbit you want
You know equatorial or bed maybe you want to go around the North
Will South Pole that way
Rocket lab will take your satellite there
No drama
The Salt Lake business needs a UPS right now
Last year in 2016
85 Rockets going into space
85 Rockets
In the entire world
And if every podcast wants to put up a satellite
There is not enough rocketry to get all of a sudden
The goal of Rocket lab is to build a small rocket to specifically cater to all of these new small satellites all these cubes
That's like ours
The goal is to send a rocket up every week
52 a year
Buy rocket standards it is a pretty crazy dream
In order to do it babe model displays
After one of those Nimble Silicon Valley startups
Complete with inspirational slogans on the wall
Sup by Peter himself
Bowie radar
You want to read your own slogan
Make everything you do a work of art if it looks like crap and does not work then you have nothing
If it looks fantastic and does not work at least it looks fantastic
Exactly that's the point right
That is an interesting approach
For a person making
State-of-the-art machinery
I will say the principal here is to make it work and
And I was I was hoping to get to see a live rocket launch
Before
I committed are programmed to Rocket lab
But there is a ship
Rocket lab hasn't actually sent
A rocket to space yet
Peter shows me this live video monitor that's on the wall
There's a remote cliff on the east coast of New Zealand and there
On the cement pad
Is there very first rock
Protest Rock
In fact
That's A Neck
Well at first when it's cold at the tip
You can name the second one hopefully this one will work
UCF
Third time's a charm
Pictures of that plan for to take three tries to get this right
Already says
There's been big breakthroughs in his quest
For cheap frequent space travel
Princeton
Peter says
They will be able to launch faster than anyone else
Because of that remote
New Zealand launch pad
A company in the United States could not launch
52 times a year because
There too many people
And boats and planes flying over
If we wanted to lunch once awake
I was going to pull up United Airlines every week and tell them that we going to Delight Watsonville and I
Turn the ceiling they already have a permit to Launch
Every few days
They want to hear a lot fewer flights in and out of
Yeah these customers yelling there are fewer of everything
Exception
Except sheep
Are the other Innovative thing that rocket lab is doing used to manufacture the Rockets
Lighter and cheaper than their competitors so the tube of the rocket is made out of
Carbon fiber
The Petersons
You can even lift it
With one arm I'm going to lift stage 2 of this rocket
Well that is heavier little heavier than I thought but I'm lifting it I'm doing it
Bethel Music
Do the picks up
This gorgeous curved piece of metal looks like a bell
This is part of the rocket engine
And it was made with a 3D printer
Wait how long did that take
I know I know for years I've been hearing that the future
3D printing and then
Someone shows you like a trinket or a little
Toy they took him three days to make
And you say
This
This is part of a metal rocket in
Not made of plastic
Computer says with six printers
They can make a rocket engine every 24 hours
And you can see the tiny little holes in the side there
Those old run through here as far around here and run through here and Link back out
To that section are
Totally get rocket go off the fire that comes out the bottom that's coming out of here
Wow so rocket lab has figured out the fastest
Energy Park they are planning on each rocket costing around $5000000 what yeah I know
I know that sounds expensive
The rocket business that is cheap
Now
About the reliability
That's the real question
Because the test rocket
Is still sitting there on the video screen
Peter says it could launch any day
But basically they're going to go when they're ready when the conditions are right
And so there I was a New Zealand
Rocket just sitting there on the cliff
Not launching
So I did make Peter promise you will
Actually like
Photos and record nginx
So I go home back to New York and a month later in May
We get the phone call to test rocket is
Ago
And they not only videotape that they made a whole promotional video of the Tesla
April his New Zealand cool when the rocket went off you can
See Peter back going for jumping up and down waving his hand
I was feeling pretty high
On rocket
Okay so you are team Corvette we are officially planet is officially going to take a sports car to space
Yeah it's a tight soda mist
A crucial fact
What I was watching this video
And I learned about what I was talking about the launch with Mike staff
He's the launch director at the company that's letting us adopt a satellite planet
He's our sort of co-parenting this
Mike said
Yes it was amazing for a first test
But
The rocket did not quite
Reach orbit
It made it most of the way
So they are cheap
Most of the way that doesn't sound good
So
Building a rocket is not such a
A simple thing
And
You know that's why you have a test flight program so you can kind of work out the Kinks
Before you go into full commercial operation so
If your
Satellite
Doesn't make it to orbit in this one we would probably be able to get you on another ride that would be a bit more
Reliable
Until we start again a little bit
Nervous
Nothing silly about
Losing our satellite but about deadline
How long would it
Take rocket lab to do another test
And of course
We don't have to choose
Rocket lab I mean s build a rocket broker would say
There's always another rocket
Which planet does have deals with other Rock
And during the summer
We had to sort of real serious conversation with Planet about the options
They said luck we're not sure when rocket lab will be ready
There is another company with a planned launch that we can jump on
Without a beautiful sunny California
It is orbital ATK
Orbital ATK was the Volvo
The Volvo
Ab Rocket
Yes I know it is not the sports car
They can't watch every week the Rockets are way more expensive than the New Zealand model there like 40 million dollars
Fox
They have that
Third thing I was talking about it they are reliable super reliable
When astronauts on the International Space Station are running low on food
Who sent it to him orbitalatk the Volvo sensus supplies of orbital ATK
It's okay Robert
We have a choice here there is the
Experimental hotness
A rocket lab
Very hot
3D printer rocket
Or there's the stable to
Dependable
Madewell boxy
Orbital ATK
PK rocket
So
What are we going to do
With one satellites
Two options
What do we do
Sports car of Volvo
I am a father as you know so I do actually face this question
All the time
Am I going to do
The safe
Responsible thing
The Planet Money satellite that has been entrusted
Tumi
The people little pod one of America
Or
Am I going to do
The fun
Risky life-changing
Amazing thing
I'm in a large empty field
Scrub brush everywhere
And just over the hill is
Iraq
I made the decision the Planet Money rocket
Such a beautiful spot
In the end it was an easy choice
I have deadlines to keep
Miles to go before I sleep
The Volvo
You picked the Volvo of course I picked the Volvo I want to go to space I got that.
And the communications director from orbital ATK Jennifer Bowman
She says
Hey buddy
Did the right
We're reliable
We're affordable
And
We are
Really designing new vehicles all the time too
Meet the needs of our customers okay it does have a pretty cool day
The orbital ATK
Minotaur C
The Minotaur
After we decided to go with orbital ATK
We waiting for them to tell us a date
And then
We got a call end of October Vandenberg Air Force Base
On the Pacific coast just north of Santa Barbara
The Planet Money satellite
Part 1
Got ship they're ahead of us
To be loaded up
And when we finally see
The Rock
Iraq
The Planet Money rocket
It is a beast
Holy moly
Into how tall is this thing
It is 103 ft tall
What is it like 10 stories
So our satellite is on the top of that thing 10 stories up
It is almost twice as tall as the rocket lab rocket
It's built with some components from military missiles which
Orbital ATK also build
And so
It is a more
Powerful rocket it can take much larger satellites than ours into orbit
But everyone is getting into the small saddle
An orbital has made a deal with planet or satellite partners
To take a bunch of smaller satellites as the
Primary payroll
Looking at I still I still cannot believe it
Are satellite the one we've been working on pod1
With our logo on it with a waveform
Of our voices
Extra on the side
It is on the top of
This rocket is 24 hours away
From space
Or a blaze of glory a beautiful blaze of glory
So can we watch the rocket
Well in theory you could but
It's
They're really busy right now and it's hazard
Operations and there's crowd-control and soap
No
Top of the stack
Dangerous
The rocket uses solid
Fuel which by the way I learn
Is the consistency of a pencil eraser
Probably stick your thumb into it
If you wanted to and apparently this rocket acts like a giant
Firecracker
And it burns from the inside out and Flames shoot out the bottom
And everyone says
This design means that it will almost certainly
Not
Explode
But when I asked
What can go wrong
Tomorrow during the launch
There is this long pause
And it took me a while to work it out but apparently
A previous version of this kind of rocket
Had a bit of bad luck
There was a launch where the
Fairing
Did not
Separate properly and soap
The part on Top
The goes around
Also Catalyst Payson
And they were all trapped inside a little too heavy so it couldn't because it didn't come off
So it didn't get to the proper
Orbitz
So for this type of Rocket this is the first time this is going to space
This exact Hardware
It'll be the first time it goes to space
Apparently there is no such thing as a 100% guaranteed
Rocket launch
So we could be in for a white-knuckle ride
On the Volvo
Yeah it's a little more dangerous than we thought
Tomorrow
Launch day
It's Halloween
Halloween and our entire satellite project is resting inside of an untested rocket
Call The Minotaur the Minotaur half man
Hypebeast
Half narrative stunts
To keep the drama going
And if I remember my mythology correctly
The Minotaur
Did not have a hat
Next time I plant money weed on our silly app
Costumes for Halloween it is true I expected NPR we start the countdown and we see if the plan
Planet Money satellite
Will achieve its destiny
300 miles up in the sky
17000 miles per hour around the Earth
A pekin
Podcast app
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Capital One is reimagining Bank
I offering accounts with no fees or minimums that can be opened from anywhere in 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
If you're enjoying the series give us a shout we would love to hear from you we are at Planet Money on pretty much all social media
You know the theme of this whole series
Is creating satellite that are small and Nimble and then launching them
Well
The Planet Money
Podcast esl
Has created a different kind of satellite
A brand
New podcast
It's called the indicator it's short but 5 minutes
And Nimble and it tells you something about number in the news
And Stacey you're one of the five hosts the program that is true it is planet money's quick take on the news
Check it out you can subscribe now on your favorite spot.
It's called the indicator
Drive now
Our space series producer is Elizabeth II last with help today from Sally held our senior producer is Alex goldmark and
Predator is Bryant
Special things today to catherine moreau hammond to help set up archer
Rocket lab and nickel a Nazi
Many people especially this month
Please donate your local member station we love making his podcast and they helped make it possible did it donate
. npr.org
Planet money to get
And then you can tell us you donated and why on social media with the hashtag
Why Public Radio
Robert Smith
And I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Thanks for listening
I have here Stacy it is just been delivered a box
And inside is haha haha haha
Patches
We have a shipment
A Planet Money patches
We talked about this
Squirrel
Is a picture of our satellite there is the motto per ardua Ad Astra
The stars are like
Star Sparkle
And here's the deal we have a limited number of these patches
And you can get one of them
On our website
For the space series
Npr.org NPR. Org
Space mission
Go now and avoid
Fomo foam mop
Fear of missing out on patches
Exactly
Construction website