Support for NPR and the following message come from service now making the world of work
Work better for me
Their cloud-based platform and solutions deliver digital workflow
Spell create great experiences and unlock productivity for your whole company
More at servicenow.com
Robert
I can tell today's podcast is at least in part
An effort on your behalf to
Take a lovely little mini-vacation to Northern New Hampshire and have an excuse to expense it to Planet Money and then p
PR
Not up to the beautiful White Mountains of Northern New Hampshire close to the Canadian border
Purpure reportorial reasons
It is the site of the porcupine
Freedom Fest
And the people that call themselves porcupine
Because they're cute
The cuddly
And you don't want to mess with
And at first glance the Freedom Festival looks like
The other festival there's tents
Does young people
Is line for the bathroom
But you know how if you're into art or alternative culture you go to Burning Man every year absolutely but if you love me
Music you going to Bonnaroo
Sure all the time
I've no idea
Well if you think the Federal Reserve is illegal
That we should return our money to the gold standard if you believe we should abolish the IRS
When you go to the porcupine Fest
The pork Festival
And we should say we're talkin obviously about libertarian these are like big L libertarian
We talked a lot about the libertarian philosophy here on planet
I think it's important
Different ways of being a Libertarian summer
True anarcho-capitalist thinkers
No government but most Libertarians I've talked to believe there is a role for government but a very small limited one
Largely to
Protect property rights to
Set the conditions so that citizens can make arrangements amongst themselves
You don't need to be so much regulation
And it shouldn't be so much too
Taxation
Libertarians generally think
It's not the government's business whether or not I do drugs
Who I marry
What food I eat
And we probably series before on planet
But we wondered how do you make it work in real life how do you
Buy things
In a Libertarian Society how do you eat breakfast with no government roll
It's actually more complicated than you might
Trailer show freedom
We go to a place where we do as the founding fathers intended we buy food uninspected by any government agency
Using gold and silver mined from the Earth
And we get a nine-year-old
Who sold his alcohol
Julie reported in 2011
Andwobble updated yet
Support for this podcast
And the following message come from State Farm
Who's agents know that your car and home are more than just big purchases
They're a big part of your life
You put the time into making them your own
So now it's time to protect them
With your own personal State Farm agent
Not only do they truly get
But they'll be there for you when you need them
And with over 19008
Neighborhoods across the US
There could be one just around the corner
Moritz statefarm.com
Are 1-800 State Farm
State Farm
Here to help life
Go right
So I arrived at this Festival in the middle of the night
And the next morning at 8:30
I came out to the campground
And I smelled freedom
Which actually smoke a lot like bacon
Oh yeah we're just picking this up
Are you doing today
How much bacon do you have
I purchased a hundred 50 lb of bacon and I actually weave
90 of
And by we've I mean I made a 10-piece bacon weave pieces of bacon I weave into like a little blanket
About the size of a CD case that's a George bandra
And he set up a tent right in the middle of the campground where he sells bacon weed
And bacon weave omelette
Vici
Yeah I know you have to pick this place Adam you would love it and not just for the bacon
Everyone has their little pants while they sleep
Sleeper their RVs
Butt out front most people have set up
Some sort of stand
People where they sell
They sell precious metals gold silver
Copper
This is
What they do in the forest rather than you don't just
Make s'mores around the campfire
Bay
Participate in the market
By himself
And
You can't just fire somebody that you have to sort of brag that you are doing it
Without
The government so George tells me proudly
But he has no permit for his bacon
The kids Grill have never been inspected
The key will not pay taxes
They want their cut basically
Anyone take the intake part of my profit away from me
Are the fruits of my labor in
Hey you know they don't have any business
I don't want them in my business at all so I just
I just hate you know
If somebody wants to buy my food that's between me and then and then it's none of their business what I'm doing
We don't need to regulate George because will regulate him if he poisons may I won't buy his food
And he'll be done so
Exactly
That was it, who was waiting in line for a bacon weave
And when he says he will take you out of the campground he means
He's got a gun in a holster on his belt with an XDM Springfield
I thought you told me
And you get the impression that no matter how tough
A New Hampshire food inspector is
He's not as tough as
What do you think about it is
It is really hard to get the government
Out of your breakfast or out of your life in anyway I mean
George might be in this immediate instance
Supporting permits in taxes but
You know he got eggs
Presumably the USDA is inspecting those eggs the USDA inspects
The bacon
Yeah you're just a little
Sheepish about
He says that often times he can get unregulated eggs but you know he's serving so many breakfast he had to
To buy them in a store and so the eggs of the bacon
Are actually a
Proof by the government
At some point
And you can tell that
People give him a hard time give Aldi for the Train the hard time about
Driving on the Federal Highway is or
Search for buying things in a store
And it has a little speech that he says over and over again so slow
I am not a Hermit I do not live in the forest and avoid
All forms of Commerce
He's just trying to minimize the role
The federal government
Sup French
To pay for the bacon weave omelette
George will take dollars US dollars
He prefers golden song
What are the most common is
Do they call junk silver which is pre-1964 dimes or quarters and also certain
Years of half dollars
All kinds of things like that we also take
Bullion I've already had a
Somebody painting a gram of gold
And we just
Pretty much started a tablet counted as $50 and
We just own that money for the food so they would come by with a little less we kept track of
One gram of silver 5-gram silver
10.1 grams of gold
Wow that's cool
Well it's like a strand of gold how much is this worth
What are these ten bucks
$9
I heard it all day long
How much will the silver
What's the rate on Gold Member it is 8:30 in the morning there campers lineup for breakfast they have not had their coffee yet
And people are trying to do math in their head
It's about the price of gold and silver
But
Gold and silver in the last few years has been periods of intense volatility are they like
They got their iPhones out and they're checking the gold and silver price date Moment by moment
Yes they are I asked them this and they do another phone to do an internet connections there a little boards would have posted all over the camp
What the current prices of gold
And silver
And the weird thing is is
Although they hate
To a person
The Federal Reserve and the Federal Reserve Note
Which is what they call the US dollar
They do have to keep translating gold and silver prices
In the dollars people are constantly talking about how much for this and how much for that
And they speak in dollars
I want the most government free omelette I can get sound all you have are Federal Reserve notes
At that moment unfortunately that's what I get paid in
So I have to leave the breakfast line to go get some
Silver now luckily
At this time in the morning there is a mini Bank
And he meant an actual men
Set up on a folding table
Imma run Hellwig IMDb
I don't know if you would call it inventor designer whatever of the
Shire silver model
We're sort of the Federal Reserve chairman you're the Ben Bernanke of silver here in the camp
Well without the violence
Yeah he seems like it but you know he's
He's like the mafia Don
Who can you know
Talk reasonable but you know
If you go up against them odds are you're going to get hurt
You called
A super free-market libertarian Ben Bernanke
I know but I know that's a really dumb
That is
I think I've literally was insulting thing you cannot say you could have called him Stalin or even President Obama and it wouldn't have been quite
Is offensive to him
Turns out they do not think that the Federal Reserve is a subject for joke
I screwed up
I learned that you have to avoid the whole subject of the Fed
And I don't even ask him to elaborate on the whole violence thing because I need silver
I need coffee I need to buy my breakfast
So the thing about Ronnie is that he has invented
A very neat little version
I'm silver
That I want to buy from him
And you know how everyone Mox
The people who
Say that we should use gold and silver they say or what you do
Cherry red a bunch of coins in your pocket with your pants sagging down with all that gold
Yeah
Got that little gold piece
State was
You don't like the size of a dime and that was 400
Something dollars so if we wanted like a penny or nickel what will we do with this shave off of Microsoft
Topix back I don't know how you use
Precious metals
Inundated they transact
Actually that is what Ron does
He basically shaves off small strips of metal he buys them from a jewelry supplier
And then laminate them he take the little tiny strips of metal
And he has an office laminator
Any mix something about the size of a credit card and I have one right here it is a
Little card is a shire silver
Laminated
And on the back what do you see there
Oh wow yeah there's like a little
Tiny tiny tiny metal bar very very thin
Shire silver
Defending Traditional Values
I paid a buck 94
Wow Buck 94 this all right
Actually you know this would work credits
It's almost more convenient than
Dollar bill with the first thing about it is it in Mississippi
Terry silver
In your wallet so I bought a bunch of
All right but
Let me know
I'm assuming you know about as much
About Silver's I do which means I have no idea how much this thin little bar is worth
It is I don't know
And it also is packed inside of this card which seems much heavier than the little bar silver so I can't really weigh it
To figure out how much it is so
You're just in the woods
In New Hampshire and you hand the guy a whole lot of money and he hands you a bunch of cards in
Claims that they're worth what they're worth
Yep and he said so you can go to a jeweler but once again we are
In the woods
New Hampshire
And so he says you know basically look you have to trust
Me on this
And this is weird
Sing
Stop being a
Campground
There's a tough guy
The caring guy
They don't trust the government
But they keep saying
You got to trust me we got to trust each other
In A N N I realize that
What are the services that government off
Is the luxury of not trusting one another
I mean that's why you have inspector
That's why you have police because you assumed that
Somebody got to get
Get somebody's out there
Poison your food
Or steal your stuff
But when you're the campground you kind of have to
To take people at their word so
I take my 10 grams of silver
And I head back to the almost
Coffee
And
Even there I'm trusting George is making my bacon weave omelette
Did he wash his hands somewhere
At some point
I think this is exactly the point
All those government inspectors all of the symbols of trust in our society their false there fake
That you can't trust the restaurant
And so why not
Call it what it is
Is in force yourself to only trust people who deserve your trust rather than just believing in a government
Probably let
For my case
Not thinking about it because I'm so hungry
So have a cup of coffee and a bacon weave omelette what's it going to cost in Timber five of those
30 bucks a piece
Roughly equal about diversity okay I have a 5 gram
Have a 5-gram silver card here
Died at $10
Right now
Excellent good deal thanks
I don't know if you noticed but I actually got a great
Big deal on that omelette they valued silver at a higher price than I bought it at 10 minutes later I made a profit
Blue outfits Tumblr
They can leave
Made a profit but
It seems to me that if you don't have just
Irregular currency that everyone agrees that it's
Turn off alarm
Well I mean
Kind of the point of the porcupine petrol everything's a lot of work
You know you have to like
Track down who is selling what
And you have to figure out what they're taking some of them take silver and Grant some of them out
Until people are consciously trying to
Translate doesn't hide some people take goal
Some guy sold me copper who said that
It's Next Big Thing
Yeah it's not the neck
But they're doing all of this to make
Appoint they say they want to be ready
If the Federal Reserve dollar
When
The Federal Reserve dollar goes under when it's not in paper money isn't worth anything anymore
They're going to know what the next currency
Going to be something like
Xcel silver
If I thought it's illegal to
To print your own current
Are they allowed to ask
Do that
Well
Verum any laws about this if you legal to mint coins that resemble us
But it's also illegal so I understand it to set up systems that compete
With official currency now what does that mean
You know there was one alternative currency called The Liberty Dollar
That
Some people felt was
Competitive with the dollar
Did they were using it the currency and that got a bunch of people arrest
Secret service around ready to pounce on
On your silver
Card manufacturer
You know if you press people
They will make it clear they say listen you're not
Buying stuff
You are trading something of value
Silver
Or something else of value
Bacon weave omelette
And if you have a silver coin they don't called Silver
Coin is called a silver round
Because a coin
Really going to the government
Quiet but a silver round is
Objective value that you can trade
But listen to this is this is all just semantics because
To tell you the truth
The people here are like breaking the law a lot of
BR proud
Of Smashing what they consider stupid laws so you can buy bootleg cigarettes
$4 a pack without all the
Taxes and they will proudly say I did not pay taxes on e-cigarette
Are there illegal bars without liquor licenses and they sell moonshine
Marijuana trade
Listen
When it comes to Illegal moments my favorite
Favorite
If this little hardened
I'm Dorothy and I'm 9 years old
Dorothy
She was in the family tattoo
And they just had a lesson
For kids
About economics and Market realities but you basically it was like a little camper
Libertarian
And the camp counselor was encouraging kids to sell whatever they can think of
Do the unsuspecting adults
Walking by
Answer Dorothy had a single stack of
Woven they look like little potholder she called me
Coasters
Willie walking out of bacon out of fabric
But they never seen their five in their beautiful and I
It's out I bought one
With soap
She was very
To get silver
So I would like the yellow
Coaster pot holder
Simpler and
He got his 1 gram of silver
Thank you
You're welcome thank you
Oh yeah and we have a pothole to get a free bottle beer
Free bottle of beer
You're about a bartender and a Craftsman
Pretty much
What kind of beer do you have
C4yourself
I actually don't know
You got beer from a nine year old girl was delicious
Criminal
Utica
Contributing to the corruption of a minor
Yeah that that's probably right and listen I know it looks bad he went to
A state legislator and you said
You know I'd like to legalize children selling alcohol on little stands in for their home I mean
I mean politicians would freak out it would never happen
But I got to tell you so
This transaction seemed so innocent it was like buying a cup of lemonade from 11
Dorothy wasn't sneaking any of the
And her mom was right next to her the whole time
It's fine with us and
It's if an adult comes by and wants to have the beer
That's their choice if
Apparent comes by and
Seize the beer in
They don't want to participate in that that's their choice
As well
But your standards like if a six-year-old comes and wants to beer
I would not give beers with 6 year old know I would not
See they have standards and it brings it back to the whole trust thing
Every bootleg alcohol stand that I went to
Told me that they would not serve minors
He is
It's not because the government told them
But out of respect for the
The parents they didn't want parents come to them and say why did you serve my sick
16 year old
Beer
I got to say this is an area where I
I have a lot of sympathy
We do have a lot of insane regulations
It is true there are a lot of nutty regulations and
Liquor
Beer wine
This is an area where many of our regulations are nonsense
Neither states where you can only buy
Booze from
State
Offices
Ancient be selling alcohol in the US you can
Buy wine in wine stores
Can't buy them in
Supermarket
And no company can own several wine stores at once
Which grape inefficiencies in the marketplace
I think a lot of economy
C-diff not as
Helping
Protect our young children or anything it's just
Protecting
The interest of
Large wine distributors are large spirits
That's why I'm sympathy for them
Go out to the woods
New Hampshire I just
Buy wine at the Y
Wine store in
But it does sound like you would fit in there and
This is why so many people that I talk to
Out of the can
They talked
So proudly
About breaking the law they walk me through each and every
Gory detail of how they broke the law that gave me their full names
They basically daring
Law enforcement to drag them away
An initial reason for the
Which is
They believe that if they disobey laws
Which they feel are
Stupid
They're going to be just like a guy
Mike Fisher
The Rogue
Manicure
I know this guy is he Legend
Hear Emily porcupines in New Hampshire
In 2005
Mike Fisher had heard about all the regulations it takes to become a manicurist in New Hampshire
Just to do nails
And so he took action
In the campground I met a guy named Dave Minton who's a friend of mine
And he told the story
There was a group of us and kind of essay a civil protest
Kia called the
The board of
Manicurist or whatever their governing board is
He told me he was going to perform an illegal act
Anaconda the yard in front of their building
So we're outside the headquarters of the manicurist Association
Exactly
So what he did is he
Trimmed
Another gal
It was with us now
So what do you have to fill nail clipper in a file or nah
Yeah she was sitting on the chair and then he was kneeling in front of her you don't need to
Just trimmed upper nails
And then they called in the authorities
And
They arrested
I think they actually took him away in a police car
So Mike Fisher
Play the guilty he took the case to court
He wanted to have his moment
To talk about manicurist laws and he
Did this became
A huge press story around the nation people covered
This crazy
Rogue manager
And an in the end infected in the last session of
The state legislature in New Hampshire there were number of bills introduced
Ginobili deregulate
Manicurist
But here's the list of things that they want to abolish license
Barber
Tanning facilities Landscape Architects court reporters family mediators guides athletic trainers massage therapist Peddler's
And itinerant vendor
Looks like George
There is a big literature among Economist in the US about how often Licensing Laws
Just like liquor laws don't serve the general interest they just serve
A certain group of people allowing them
How to charge much more for their services be
Limit the number of people supplying them
End up hurting the general public which is supposedly the people were supposed to
Be protected
By this
So is that their dream of one by one
Have these little Civil Disobedience moments and
And destroy the Regulatory and monetary apparatus
So the US government and eventually we'll all be
Effectively living in the woods of New Hampshire
Well I'm sure that's a dream for some of them remember something that these these little laws are silly and they want to get rid
Those people I talked to want to get rid of
Ulta
They want to get rid of the school system
They believe people should homeschool
Private school
They want to get rid of most government services
Absolutely Healthcare Social Security all these things should be gone in their point of view
I think we should not intervene in foreign Wars we should only have a small defensive
To protect our
Boogie Nights is cute to say that
Yeah the manicure laws are silly
But these people have a serious goal I don't have a serious go to
Fundamentally change the United States of America
And a
If the campground porcupine Festival is any judge
It is going to be a difficult road because
Even the simplest things there
Are not quite working the way they should.
Remember that silver I bought
To buy my bacon with extra silver and so come dinnertime I heard about this
Thai food
Restaurant like
Thai food 10th cross the camp
Other side of the campground
And I order a Thai burrito and I whip out my little silver cars the stars of a car
And the guy looks at him
I need the shakes
Syscoin guy back home oh take the silver rounds
What does old dimes the ones that you know before 1965 whatever were they when they were made of silver
And I've been standing at the guy behind me in line says
Well you know
I'll give you a dollar 10
Which of those strips of silver
But you made a dollar 90 that's all the sudden I feel like
A total
Soccer
Now I'm the one asking where's the trust guys where's the
But you learned a valuable lesson
The iron
The market always has the last word
We'll have an update on the porcupine Freedom Festival of 2017
Support for NPR and the following message come from Exxon and Mobil the exclusive fuel partners of the plenti rewards
Words program
500 points is worth at least $5 in savings
You can pick up a plenti card at an Exxon or Mobil branded station and start earning points right away
To see how things are going at pork fest
These days 2017 I called up Matt Phillips
He's the president of the free state project they run Fork Fest
When I reach them use one around the festival I can I can picture it in my mind cell service
Still not perfect
I'm down on the main
Field where I am
And a bunch of picnic tables and I'm actually just standing right near the bonfire
Message they have made some improvements importfest they now have Wi-Fi
Which they definitely didn't have when I was
That's cleared the way for this other big change
6 years ago
You would have seen a lot of people
Call Trading
Gold and silver
This year a lot of them most of them are taking
Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies
If I look this up a hill there I can
Food truck that is a little doughy
Pizza
They got really good feedback
She just had one
And right next to the menu
Have a little QR code that you can scan with your phone
And then send them Bitcoin in order to pay for your pizza
And not only are people using Bitcoin now to buy food
The food at the festival has a slightly different
There's still a bit of bacon but there's definitely
Places that are doing smoothies and
There's a vegan spot
Sounds like you're getting a little soft at Park Fest
Well
You're part of the the thing that we're doing here is having the full mini experiment
If you got a free market and
People decide what they want
You Lie by
You know decide for themselves what their what's good for them
So pleased to hear that the libertarian the pork fest are being a little
More healthy
But is there still at least my favorite pork fest food
The food that I will forever associate with freedom
The bacon weave armor
I haven't seen the dumb and who's the who was doing that
Ascena this year
But
If he comes back I'm sure he will settle the hospital
Have you been to a fabulous fun outdoor festival or
State Fair or some other Gathering that teaches a fundamental principle of economics
We would love to hear about it it's summer vacation season
Email is Planet Money at npr.org
Or you can find us on Facebook
Sportswear
And now that you're finished listening play the money I recommend NPR's new podcast called up first it is a
Daily preview of the day's news podcast is
It goes every morning Monday through Friday at 6
In the morning which means you can hit your shower and in 12 minutes
Get
Everything you need preparing for the day while you're still soaking up and rinsing
That's called up first then you can find it wherever you get your podcast thanks for listening