Support for NPR in the following message come from Pushkin Industries
Presenting the podcast against the rules
Michael Lewis explores the corrosion of fairness in America
And what it has done to our society mostly without our noticing
Listen to against the rules wherever you get your pot
Hey it's Stacey Vanek Smith
And we Planet Money got the feeling that we're going to be hearing a lot about immigration
For the next team
So we wanted to replay an episode we did a couple of years ago that answers a fundamental question
What happens to the economy when a bunch of new immigrants come into a country
At 1
Fidel Castro had a problem
It Was 1980
And the Cuban economy was in
In terrible shape
For one of the first times in the strictly controlled country there was open to send
Thousand
Cubans
We're trying to leave
If the country
Until this time
Castro had basically kept people inside Cube
But then at this moment
Overnight
He switch tactic
He went on TV and he said
You know what
The people who want to leave Cuba
Are defective
They don't have
Revolutionary blood
You said we don't want them
We don't need them
Pastor said
You want to leave Cuba
Findlay
Go to the port of Montreal near Havana
And go
On any boat you can
And Cubans did
They filled thousands of boats
Fishing boat sailboats little makeshift rafts
Unexploded 224 mi
Florida
Tens of thousands of Cubans are fleeing the repression
The US Coast Guard is asked
The Cuban Border guard to stop over loaded boats from leaving Mario Harbor
Key West Florida
Over the course of the next few months more than a hundred thousand Cuban
Stepped out of those boats
And onto US soil
Jobs
Didn't have anything with the
And the US
Now what
You may see where we're going with this
I seem very much like this
Is playing out right now in Europe
Desperate
People fleeing their home countries on both
Coming to try and make a noose
European countries on the receiving end are asking
Now what hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Jacob Goldstein
And I'm Stacey Vanek
When tens of thousands of migrants appear in a country
There are two big economic
Number one
They're never going to get jobs and they're going to cost our country a ton of money
And number two
They are going to get job
They're going to take my job
Today on the show we find out what happened when tens of thousands of migrants showed up in Miami in 1980
Looking for work
And we try to figure out what it means for Europe today
Work for this podcast in the following message come from rocket mortgage by Quicken Loans
When it comes to the big decision of choosing a mortgage lender
It's important to work with someone you can trust
Who have your best interest in mind
With rocket mortgage
You'll get a transparent online process that gives you the confidence you need to make an informed decision
Skip the bank
Skip the waiting
And go completely online at quickenloans.com money
Equal Housing lender licensed in all 50 states
Nmls consumer access. Org number 3030
Back in 1980 when Castro said get out mirta ojito was just 16 years old and living in Hawaii
I just sat down to have lunch
It was an egg sandwich
With ketchup
Which is when the police
Kings Warehouse knocks on the door and sunset
Boat waiting for you on the porch
And
And we left everything behind exactly as it was including my lunch
On the table
After Castro speech Naruto's father had been one of the first people to get in line
Intel keeping Authority
He wanted
And mirta was ready to go
Knew what you was going to grab
2 pens
Lipstick
Head handkerchief
A cheap headed to the port of Mariel with her family
Castro had arranged for public shaming of people like nurses family
We're leaving
Musical dear hecklers chanting outside
Let them go let them go
Mirta's pens work
And she and her family
Crowded onto a little tugboat
Call Dominion
They set sail for the US
Mitchell remembers falling asleep outside on the deck of the boat
With her mother
Holding her hand
I woke up in the morning the sun woke me up
And by then we could already tell that we were very near the United States because our last one that's above surround
And we talked on in Key West around
Noon
The boat docked and mirta and her family
Walk onto the
They were surrounded by thousands of other red
Myrtis parents had no formal education
They didn't see
Speak any English
We arrived with
Absolutely nothing and no way to prove who we were
And like tens of thousands of other refugees coming from Cuba at the time
You're just parents
Headed for Miami
And started to look for work
A few years after all this
An economist
Name David card
Look at this
And
Because he's in the car
He thought this is this kind of
Beautiful unintentional experiment that could help answer a really big
Question
What does a massive sudden wave of immigration due to an economy
So he crunched the numbers
He compared what happened in Miami's economy before and after the Mariel boatlift
With what happened in other US cities
It is at the same time
Did unemployment go way up
Did all the new people competing for jobs Drive wages down
The prevailing view was that we would expect
At least a short-run effect
So what did you find
Why didn't find any evidence of that
Refugees came to Miami and there was no effect on the economy
Couldn't detect
Eddie
Strong evidence of an effect one way or the other
Now there is some debate about
Some Economist argue that in the short run
Wages for low-skilled workers
Can fall when lots of low-skilled immigrants
Arrive
But on the bigger questions about immigration in the economy
Pretty much
Greek for most workers immigration is not a problem
For most workers immigrants do not drive down
They don't
Steel Arch
And the reason for this
Is that there is not
Fixed number of jobs in it
Win a bunch of new people show up
Yes they get you
But they also start buying stuff right away
Start getting haircuts and going to
Go to the grocery store
And that means there need to be more Barbers and more Grocers
That creates more jobs
Yep pretty much the second her family arrived in the US they had to start buying stuff
From the get-go you become a consumer
You need that skinny mattresses you need sheets you need
Everything
Set up Ally them in the less you bring the more you consume
No to be cleared this does not mean we can just
Look at what happened in Miami in 1980 and say okay great
We can just let in some unlimited number of people and no matter what the economy is
David card.
The Economist says there are very particular circumstances
That allow a country to
To take in a large number
People at once
The first thing is that the country needs to have
Pretty strong economy
Because in the short-term there is a cost
To accepting Emery
Healthcare shelter
Social Services
And that burden can be pretty big
Germany did this calculation and it found that one Refugee cost
About $14,000
A fragile economy could get crushed by
David cards
Second rule the second circumstance
It needs to be true is
People who come to a new country
Have to be able to get jobs
Pretty quickly
Because of course that's when they start contributing to the economy that's when they start
New jobs
In the case of what happened in Miami back in 1980
There was a huge Cuban Community already in place
It was the Cuban community that really helped out in your toes mom and dad
Your friend of a friend somebody who knew him from Q I found him a job
Driving a truck of bananas
Company called yes bananas
And my mother found work
Sodium ions in in effect
An incredible thing to me about the story at about the United States is that
We arrived Monday
My Thursday my parents were working
On the following Monday I started summer school
Weirdest parents didn't speak any English
What's a huge Cuban community
They didn't need to
My father figure out that he only needed to learn if
Few words
To understand what was going on with the truck and I wrote him out for him once I knew that myself
He put him in the pocket of his shirt and there he went
For all of the fear that there was on both sides
The Cuban refugees
Did just fine in Miami
And Miami did just fine
But the Cuban refugees
Tokay
What does this tell us about what's happening today in Europe
Because clearly all those things that mere to live through are happening right now 35 years
I'm home run Cafe
I'm 23 and I'm from Damascus Syria his brother about
They went to Turkey and they hired a Smuggler
Anytime $1,200 each
And what about four together
People the crowded onto this little
Inflatable raft and they set sail for
About an hour into their for our journey the boat began to deflate
Water started flooding in
Pitch black outside
No one could see
Omar's brother got so scared
He fainted
Screaming door even fighting some people are fighting
Toto's crazy
I have nothing to do about praying and
I just hope that we could
Survive
Homerun held onto his brother with one arm and with the other he grabbed
Plastic bottle in Sparta
Bailing water out
Eventually they made
To this tiny Greek Island
Call danira
As soon as home run caught his breath
He texted his mom
Told her that we're okay
Can I call you once I get the chance
Omarion and his brother like a lot of migrants
Began to make their way to the
Wealthier part of Europe to Western Europe
David card The Economist he says
Western Europe meets his first Criterion for being able to absorb vitamin success
Despite the economic troubles in Europe we've heard a lot about
Western Europe is still Rich enough still has a big enough robust enough economy to absorb that the migrants that are coming in
And remember David cards rule number to getting jobs quickly
This is a little different
For the Syrian
There's not a huge establish Syrian community in Western Europe the way it was
Cute established Cuban community in Florida
But the syrians have something else
Going for them
And it's people like
My name is
I know who stole fur
And I'm the CEO of ebm-papst
Not Pepsi beer Pabst the multibillion-dollar German company that makes
Industrial fan
Tiny little fans that go inside Electronics they make
Huge 6ft tall fans that cool server Farms
Facebook and Google wouldn't work without us
Banks wouldn't work without the self
You can't escape us at all if you wouldn't be there
The Rosewood
Would stop because the road would overheat
Rainer has started a program to recruit and train Syrian
He says he is desperate for workers
Engineers
Managers
People working the assembly line
And he is hoping that all the syrians coming into Germany right now
Will mean that
He can fill all of his open jobs
We intent Health course
As much as we can
Tool
Help those people but also help us
Ballena finding good qualified
People amongst us refugee
Do you have a hard time finding workers to fill your jobs
Yes
There are a lot of companies like
Ebm papst
Populations in Western Europe are aging
Workers are retiring
Unless people can come in to fill those jobs
Companies can't grow
The economy
Campground
People like Raynor companies like taps
They need
People like Imran kassar
An Omron and some of the other Syrian refugee
Have an advantage but myrtis family did not
Home run has a college degree
A degree in economics
Actually left Syria the day after he passed
A lot of his classmates left with
If they'd stayed he says they would have been drafted
The fight in Syria civil war
Obvious obvious
The next day the next
You'll find him
Cows.
Home run in his brother made it to France
That's where they are now
And they arrived at the
The exact moment when France was trying to sort of
Show the world that they were welcoming Siri
Terrorism media
Even the president of France
You met the president of France
I miss him and I. It wasn't evtol amazing
Cancel alarm
Yeah
He said the feeling
Bienvenue welcome
Omarion expects to get his working papers this week
And eventually
He wants to get his Master's in economics at the sorbonne
Support for this podcast and the following message come from
Credit Union
Simplify your Banking and reach financials in with a lion
Get competitive credit union rates paired with the product offerings of a big bang
Visit my alliance.com NPR to learn more
Alliant is federally insured by the ncua
Mirta ojito grew up and became a journalist
Eventually she went to work for the New York Times
Covered immigration
Her parents stayed in Miami
Did you ever send them your articles
You know
When my father died
My mother gave me
Inbox
A box with the article
Did you know he'd been saving them
No
He never learned English
He saved all those articles even though he couldn't read
Naruto wrote a book about her journey from Cuba to the US
It's called finding manana
There are few people that we would like to thank
The first is Eleanor Beardsley NPR
Paris correspondent he put us in touch with Oman
Casar
Also reporter Alexander
Car show today was produced by Jess Jiang you can find us on Twitter at Planet Money or at Jake Goldstein or at
S Vanek Smith
Hispanic Smith if you're looking for more to listen to try hidden brain
You can find hidden brain on the NPR one app on iTunes or wherever you get your podcast
I'm Jacob Goldstein and I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Thanks for listening
Support for this podcast in the following message come from fundrise the future of real estate investing
Access private Market real estate projects from high rises in DC to multi-family apartments in LA
Get your first three months of fees waived at fundrise.com indicator