Support for NPR and the following message come from State Farm
When it comes to home and auto insurance
They're here through the ups and downs
Go to statefarm.com
To be connect
It was one of the 19000 ages
In neighborhoods
Across the Nation
State Farm
Here to help life
Go right
Some people are just
Bourne wrestler
Amanda lindhout is like that
She's from a small city in Canada
And when she was little her favorite thing to do was sit in her bed and flip through a pile of National Geographic
Magazines
And I used to look at the pictures on those pages and and just lose myself
When she was 19 Amanda started backpacking
To the most extreme places she could find
This of course drove her mother absolutely nuts
Like it just one time Amanda went to pack
She was like you're being so reckless
You know what I had an amazing time in Pakistan and I think I
Probably
Rubbed it in a little bit when I came back from that trip like
Pakistan was the best place I ever went Mom C
In her early twenties Amanda jump
Do stuff like that she got a little freelance assignments for her local newspaper the Red Deer
The cat and she went to more and more dangerous places
Iraq Afghanistan
And then in August of 2008 Amanda got a freelancer
Assignment in Somalia
She was going to do a story from a refugee
Somalia in 08 was what policy
People call a
A failed State there was no sense
Government
Different neighborhoods were controlled by warrant
Clans
It was basically a war zone
Until the first couple days she's stuck in the area around her hotel in Mogadishu
What about 3 days in
Local guide gives you the okay
You know the roads were clear
And it was a good day to travel so she in a photographer and a translator and some local guides they all pile
Island to a big white SUV
And they head out
And for a while there's nothing
Just roads
Scrub trees dust
She still remembers the music she was listening
Like old music from my teenage years I was listening to Ace of Base and then she feels the s
SUV slow down
And she looks to the left and there's a car pulled over on the side of the road
In about a dozen men
Rush out from behind
And they ran out across the road
Pointing AK-47 that are vehicle
All of their faces were completely wrapped in checkered scarves with only their eyes showing through they pull
Call Amanda out of the SUV
They put a gun to her head
They searched the car and they tell her get back in the SUV and they drive
For I'd say about 45 minutes just
Straight through the desert
To a little maze of a village
They take her to a 10 building and they throw into a dark
And a while later
Tall skinny man walks into the room
He's wearing an orange Polo shirt
He's got Ben Franklin glasses
And he says
I'm Adam
And then he says where you from
And she says Canada
And that is when he said
Allah has put it in my heart to ask
For a ransom
What do you think
And I
Started crying
And I said to him
My family is poor
And Amanda tells him something else that she is known for a long time
My government is not going to pay for me
The government is not going to pay Ransom
Canada in the US have what's called a no concessions policy on paying rent
Especially Tutera group
We don't negotiate
The Canadian and US governments will not pay
So what Amanda says neck
It might sound like she's playing a game of chicken but she is completely serious
She says you may as well kill me now because there is going to be no money for me
And he looked at me very coldly and he said
Are you ready to die
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Noel King
And I'm sure I understand
Today on the show
Should you ever pay Ransom
In cases like this
We want two things
When someone is kidnapped
Governments and Families
Want to get them
But at the same time no one wants to pay terrorist or professional kidnappers lots of money
It just give the more resources and more reason to kidnap more people
In the future
Countries have been dealing with this problem at the
The highest levels more and more lately
The US and Canada have this no concessions policy we don't pay Ransom
Other countries do parents
So to get their citizens out
One of these approaches has to be right or at least more right than the other one
That is what Amanda and
Her family were going to find
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with
Straight jeans
How did they make them so great
Madewell starts with premium.
Then offers men's and women's styles for seriously everyone
Also you can recycle any brand of jeans in a Madewell store
And they'll give you $20 off a new pair
They work with the blue jeans go green program
Turn old jeans
Housing insulation
4 communities in De
Terms apply
Ready to find your perfect fit
Stop by a Madewell store or go to madewell.com
The men who took Amanda were a criminal gang
They weren't some big terrorist group
But they did tell her that they were soldiers in a holy war
And the question of money first came up right after she was take
She was being driven through the desert and she turned to one of the guys sitting neck
I think it was me that
Actually
Ask
Just outright is this about money
And he says
Yes yes it is
Anna first she's relieved
Which sound might sound
Strange
But it was like okay they're not
Driving us out into the desert
You don't cut our heads off
But then a second later
It sinks in
My family my mom who is working at a bakery making minimum wage and my
Father were not going to be able to come up with me know whatever this
Ransom number was going to be
The number it turned out with one point
$5000000
It was probably a number that they picked at random
But it's a number that would freak any family out most
People don't have that
And even if they did have it there is this policy
My mother was actually
I mean not threaten to but she was certainly made aware
Of the fact that
Paying Ransom in Canada is against the law
And to pay around some and even to fundraise for a ransom actually
Is against the law
And holds like a
So you know a sentence
10 years in prison for doing that
We actually spoke to Amanda's mom her name is lorenda
She's back in Canada and now she's in the middle of this
She actually got the call from Amanda's dad and she remembers that she was visiting a friend that
And I thought okay I've got to get home and I got my car
And I was
Totally lost
I've driven the
X Factor
I couldn't find my way
Kept making on turns
I believe I was in shock
You might hear a Tremor in Lorinda Stewart voice Fair
She says that Tremor has been in her voice since this
Incident happen
Is she was about to start working with the government
What the government wanted was to get Amanda home
Without giving money to Criminal
They did have a protocol in place for cases like
They set up a Command Center in the town where Amanda's dad lived
I'd had a war room with math
Simchart
Tin crafts
And when Adam and the other kidnappers would call and demand the ransom
There was a plan in place
Hostage negotiators were living with Amanda's mom around the clock
The train her to
Stay calm
Don't yell
Have an answer for every
She would say something like we can't give you money
But we can do things to improve your country
Like Bills score
Delta Hospital
Florida says the government told her we do this all the time it works and they had said they had an impact
A couple
Painting cost
Just home
I thought well
Desk that's would be a win-win
A country is poor
Good
Desperately
Use
Help but Amanda's captors didn't want a they wanted money
And this goes on for me
Remove Amanda from house to house
And things get worse
They beat her
She gets very sick
End
They rape her
She doesn't one point try to escape she slips out a window and actually makes it as far as a local Ma
But they catch her again
And all this time the kidnappers are calling Amanda's Mom they're calling larinda
Dozens of times
They're threatening her they're giving her
Terrible updates
And all of this is meant to get her mom to pay that rent
It was excruciating for
Need to have been on the outs
It was just
Beyond wet
Any parent should ever have to go
Truth
And then after a year something big
Chefs
Three people from the government call Amanda's mom into a me
They say look this isn't going how we hope we're not making progress
And we're dropping your case
I was in a bit of a panic and said like you guys
Promise me until you're dropping me lorenda says one of them tells her explicit
It is still illegal for you to pay rent
But they say
No one has ever been
Prosecute
For paying rent
The fellows who spoke
Comedian says basically told me what the low was
Then they
Told me that I had the freedom to
Go ahead
The Retton cement pay
Raise the money
And pay
So here you see the crack between the ideal version of how this policy works
And how it plays out in the real world
We actually reached out to the Canadian government to ask them about this and they told us
We don't comment on specific
Lorenzo says the agents told her call a private company that specializes
Types of negotiation
And she did
And they told her
Right away you are going to have to pay Ransom
Time to get your daughter back
But Amanda's family didn't have anything close to a million and a half dollar
So they tried to get the number lower
Meanwhile back in Somalia Amanda is overhearing these phone conversations and she can tell
It's not going well
They said to her
You think we're playing games
LCR game
These guys have been holding Amanda for a year expecting something
And they're being told no there's still no money
They were Furious
And Lorinda realized
She was going to have to get
Some money together
I mean the love of a mother right she started
Booking meetings with
High-powered business people in the sit in the City of Calgary people that she did not know
But she would talk their secretaries into you know giving her 10 minutes
And then she would go in and she a little
Binder that she had put together with my pic
Picture on the cover
That was called Amanda's Adventures
And then inside where all these
Pictures of Meowth in the world and articles I had written and the most amazing thing
People gave I mean
Like thousands of people gave to my family I mean you know
$5 or $200,000 people gave
And then
What afternoon 15 months after she been kidnapped
A man came into the room where she was being held
Any song of her chains
And you put her into a car
And there was another long drive into the desert
In total silence
The sun went down and
It was dark when we kept driving remove tar from car to car in the dark
And after hours of this
They finally stopped
And then
A Somali man came over to the side of the vehicle and tapped on the window and I rolled it down
He hands me a cell phone
Really confused but I took it and I put it to my ear and my mother was on the other end
And she said to me
Amanda you're free
She was free
I had had
So many dreams in captivity like that
That I
What I did
In that instant was like I pinched my arm
And even though I could feel it
I was sure I'd like this was a dream
Okay listening to that
It's impossible not to rejoice
With Amanda
The thing is when her family paid ransom they did exactly what governments are trying to prevent
They gave money to
Two criminals
I mean I live with that every day and that doesn't feel good
Did we ban yes contribute to that ongoing problem globally of hostage-taking by
Rewarding these guys and paying them around 7 we dip
We definitely did
Do you agree with the no Ransom policy does that seem like an effective way to handle it
I actually think it makes
Sense
I think the government position to not pay Ransom
Is
Put in place to
Protect us so that we don't
Become.
Targets of kidnappings from individuals who would look for
Target's like that
This is kind of astonishing
Amanda Godfrey because her mom went around the policy
Still says she thinks this policy keeps us a
Like most people she believes that if you don't pay for hostages there will be no market for hot
Here's the really interesting thing about the no concessions policy
It's been around forever
But there haven't been many
Detailed
Studies of whether or not it actually work
There hasn't been that much data
And then after 9/11
Because there was this big uptick in people being kidnapped by Terror groups
All of a sudden
We did have data we did have numbers
And people started to look at
One of them was Peter Bergen
Journalist and analyst
Did the new America Foundation
And people were coming to him for answers
It began
With
Some family members of people who were taken hostage in Afghanistan to Pakistan I know a fair amount about the political
Situation in those countries when they came to me for advice
Paramount is actually a bit of an understatement
Bergen spent years in Afghanistan and Pakistan history interviewed Osama bin Laden
And it is possible that he could have been kidnapped
So Peter Bergen
And his Partners at the new America Foundation to get all this data and they start to analyze it and we focused on the plumbery difficult cases
People who were taken by
Jihadist
Terrorist groups or
Other Insurgent groups
And in the end they have 1400 cases
And he looked at how government policy works out in real life
So okay there are two group
Oops there are the no concessions
The United States
Canada
UK
And then there's a second
These are countries that will make a deal
The French the Italian
Spanish
Swiss
The Germans
They don't go around advertising it but these governments pay Ransom
They deliver cash
And they Market in their budget
Has foreign aid
Tell the world has been running this kind of horrible experiment
And here's what Peter Bergin found the outcomes were Americans with twice as bad as the word for every other
Westerners and the only people who came close in times of bad outcomes where
The British
And when you say twice as bad
What do you think
Well
Double the number of Americans
Proportionality were killed
By their captors
Americans are twice as likely to be killed in capped
This could mean killing Americans in and of itself has value as propaganda value
Or it could mean that Europeans paying Ransom get
People home
Or could mean both of those thing
But either way if not everybody sticks to the same policy
It's a problem
Yeah in front individual like a mandolin out there is a
Huge reason to break these rules
The new concessions policy is meant to
To prevent kidnappings and
To help posture
But the numbers were saying it doesn't do either of those
First there's no evidence that Americans are kidnapped less often
And there is evidence to suggest that Americans
Do worse
In captivity
It's a policy that makes sense
On paper
But in the real world there's always going to be some poor mother
With a binder filled with pictures of her
Burkett
And the system breaks down
Yeah we saw the system start to break down around the summer of 2014
Isis was holding American hostages and European Hast
The Americans were not paying Ransom but some of the Europeans were
So Isis was killing the Americans and letting the Europeans who paid Ransom go
After that summer President Obama starts a review of our policy
Is it keeping people
We talked to a couple of people who worked on that policy review and they told us
Obama saw that the system could be better
Until year later in 2005
Obama comes out and he announces
A very small
But very significant tweak to the no concessions policy
He said the government is still not going to pay rent
That is just
Completely off the table
But for families who can raise money
Or even hire a private company
The government will not get in the way
And this means that money will go to Terror groups and it will go to criminals
That's what happened in Amanda's case
All that money her family raised
Disappeared into Somalia
And she thinks about this all the time
Every person who gave to that Ransom understood that it was going to go to criminals and probably not be
Put to good use
But they had determined that my life
Was
Worth it
And so I guess what I try to do with that is to live a life that
That is worth it
And she is very sincere about that
After she was released Amanda forgave her captors she really did
She thought about them for a long time and realize
They grew up in a country where there was no government they never had
Champs
Until when she got home
Amanda raised more money to send to Somalia but
This time she knew where it was going
She started a foundation
To send Somali women and girls
Disco
Support for this podcast and the following message
Did come from the this week in Google podcast
At twit.tv
Every week
Leo Laporte
Jeff Jarvis and Stacey Higginbotham
Talk Tech media and privacy
The unapologetically question
Google Amazon Twitter Facebook and other Tech Giants are on the right
Attract subscribe to this week in Google
On your favorite podcast
Or it's wet. TV / twig
We're always looking for story ideas you can send us an email to sign up money at npr.org
Today show with produced by Elizabeth kulas Nick Fountain Stanley house and was edited by Alex goldmark
Speak things to a couple people who helped us out with this episode
Joshua geltzer of Georgetown law Institute for constitutional advocacy and
Protection
And Gary Nestor who wrote the book
Stalling for time
My life as an FBI hostage negotiator
We also relied on the reporting of rukmini callimachi who's reporting on Ransom payouts
For the New York Times is unparalleled
Thank you
I'm Noel King
And I'm Bryant or staff
Thank you for listening
So Bryant while we were reporting this there was actually a big update to Amanda Steele
Something that happened
After she got
The police set up a sting operation
To catch a
Adam the guy who is always calling her mom
For ransom
Time in Somalia
They tell him that's insane why
Which is an agent wants to give him a book.
That Amanda had forgiven him which is true
And he believed them
This guy
We spent more than a year terrorizing Amanda
Got on a plane
And flu
To Ottawa and police arrested him
At the airport
And he is in jail now