Hello and welcome to planet
Alex goldmark
Supervising producer here
And for as long as I have worked
We've been getting
One request
Pretty much more than
All the others
And your emails and your tweets
Facebook messages
I really do re
There are these two words that keep coming up
The people really want
Basic
Income
The idea basic income is that the government should give citizens
A check
Every month
Just for you
Government gives
The citizens test
Not enough to make everyone rich
But enough
So that they don't
It's an idea that depending on who you talk to
Can stop poverty make the world more fair
But it could also make government smaller
And more efficient and let citizens have more freedom and dignity
Because
A basic income could replace
Welfare and food stamps or any number of other
Social programs
This is the kind of economic idea
Yeah that is drumming up
How much excitement in females
Because it has something for almost
Their supporters on the left
Right
They all want to see the
Try
But it's also one of those ideas that is just so radical that it seems like
Like I can never really
So when our friends at the show 99%
Told us
They were going to visit
A country that is testing out basic income
Right now
And they have this great story about what it takes to get basic income to catch on
WeChat
Yeah
We want to hear that story
You don't know 99% invisible
Are the straight podcast
About design
And in this episode they bring us the clever design logic
It is behind the most exciting basic income experiment in the world
Lost Roman Mars and report a problem and pick it up.
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence
And run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobiledit
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR
To save 10% off your first purchase
Have a website or domain
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
People all over the world
Flirting with an idea
Call Basic income
Basic income basic income
Chicken comments that each citizen
Receives a payment every month
I'm paid into
Basic income
Also known as universal basic income or unconditional basic income
Or Ubi
That's producer Avery problem
Very very roughly defined Universal basic income
Is this idea
That a government would
Hey
All their citizens
And everyone will get a flat sum of money every month
To cover their basic needs
Whether or not they have a job
And this money
Would be no strings attached
No conditions
And this would hopefully remove any stigma from receiving it
It's free money
Basically it's free money
The logic behind it is this
A lot of jobs don't pay enough money for people to even make rent or buy groceries
You can work full time and still be below the poverty line
It was easy to understand why people on the left would advocate for a guaranteed income
They're also a version of this concept is popular and Libertarians are
They see basic income as a way to shrink the welfare state
For example you could take away food stamps Medicare and housing subsidies and
Replace all of it with one
Flatsound
People in Tech are also interested in the concept of basic income and they feel a certain urgency about
Robots are coming for our jobs
They say and basic income is the best way for humans to maintain a decent lifestyle when our labor is increasingly
Obsolete
Our generation is going to have to deal with 10
The millions of jobs replaced by automation like self-driving cars
But we have the potential to do
So much more than that
That's Mark Zuckerberg giving a commencement speech at Harvard
And what he's getting at is in a World War
Jobs are scarce
Everyone will need
Financial cushion
And then by his logic if people don't have to worry about food and shelter
Maybe they'd feel Freer to innovate maybe they'd start a new company or go back to
School
We should explore ideas like Universal basic income to make sure that everyone has a cushion to try new ideas
Listen to that heartbreak rap that isn't even it up
Elon Musk has also advocated for Ubi and the startup incubator y-combinator will soon begin its own pilot
Experiment right here in Oakland
Want to see what happens when I give a group of people a basic income
It's actually an idea that's been around for a long time
And there are many different variations on it
But recently
There been a number of experiments with
Forms of basic income happening around the world
A non-profit is running an experiment with Ubi in Kenya
And Ontario Canada just launched
The test in three different cities
But this recent excitement
About basic income experimentation
Is largely focused
On
Finland
Experiment
With universal basic income
Financial
In the beginning of 2017 The Finnish government began an experiment with a basic income
And this news about the Finland experiment
Was really excited
Maybe we will learn what people will do if they can make money
Without work
Will they just hang out at home
What Society grind to a halt
How do people find meaning in their lives
And how will they evaluate success
And that's of course the big question it's the kind of the Acid Test of Basic
Will receiving basic income make people more or less
Whatever the activity
Whether it's just
Walking around or whether it's taking care of your neighborhood
Keep sore
Applying for work
This is Robin mocha
Founder of Des Moines housing cake we are helsinki-based in tank
And here's what I learned
Talking to ropa and other people in Finland about this experiment with basic income
To talk about basic income Finland started
For the understanding of
What the outcomes of Altamesa
Would be or the employment Market
The Finland experiment is
Not about robe
And if not to see if people will stop working when they get
Get free money
The experiment is to find out if giving people basic income
Well actually help them
Start working
In this whole experiment is especially interesting to us here at 99 pi
Not just for what Finland is testing
But how they are testing it
Finland is trying out a unique
Design-oriented way of
Thinking about government
Rather than just rolling Outlaws on a massive scale
They're trying to crap
Legislation in stages
With user feedback
Like a piece of design
Because every good design is made to fill a need or solve a problem
And this
Is the problem
I hate it
To be unemployed
Right now in 2017
The unemployment rate in Finland is at 8.8% and that's about
Double the US unemployment
And that rate is worse than smaller finished cities like your insu
Is ephelides always being a Taurus
Parts of the country
This is Donna leskinen
Resident of Yuan Su which is about an hour's drive away from the Russian border
She's 39 and she's been unemployed for a little over two years
Unemployment
Has been here bigger
That's a in southern or Western Finland
I guess we are far
From a bigger cities where are more much much much more
Job opportunity
Santa has a master's in history and she worked as a researcher until her project ran out of funding
In the US
Depending on the state
You can generally collect unemployment for about half a year
After losing a job
In Finland you can collect unemployment for about
2 years
And then there different kinds of social assistance isn't allowances you can apply for
If you still
Don't have a job
But here's the catch
If you're collecting unemployment assistance in Finland
You definitely cannot earn additional income
Or you risk losing those benefit
And then you have to reapply
Which is a massive drag
It's really really difficult situation
This actually happened with the person we hired to record sauna
We asked what is rate was
And he said he couldn't charge us
Because he's also unemployed and would lose part of his allowance if you took on money from freelance work
So he did it for free
Thanks Jana
Basically the government of Finland realized
That something had to be done about this system
That they were accidentally disincentivizing citizens from getting small jobs
Or maybe even starting businesses of Their Own
And these are citizens who want to work
Like Santa
Being unemployed
Makes me feel anyway so whatever
I don't know
Unimportant
I mean doing a job but make you feel like you're doing something for
Purpose
Is something bad being unemployed Chvrches
Hanging around and Chestnut
Being very important to anything anybody
So this welfare system clearly needs to
This could be done in a few different ways like with an earned income tax
But first they wanted to try out something simpler
And go from there
And this is where we get to design
They wanted to design and test policy in a process very similar to the way designers come up with new products
Design policy
Is that you would think about policies ask kind of design object
Design service
And that means that you could do alteration
And tests
That's roping mocha again founder of the think-tank demos Helsinki
And the prime minister's office
Turns to them
So the prime minister's office approached ask and ask them how can I be employee
Design thinking
On
A national level
Now can we do like governments level design team
Design thinking
It goes like this
First there is a challenge or problem that must be song
Then designers
Express
Cast
And cycle
Express
That means designers come up with a few ideas and prototype
Test
Try those ideas out
Maybe with a model or sample
Getfeedback understand
What actually happens what are the outcomes
And cycle
Incorporate that feedback to make changes and revise the design
Then the process begins again
And again and again
Couple years ago
This is how the Finnish prime minister decided he wanted to design legislation
So demos helped establish and experimentation unit
Which is an actual office
Best of The Finnish prime minister
At the prime minister's office is experimentation used
The first unit
Bus like
Design
Policies in the carnival
Meaning of the word
There are other governments that are interested in experimentation
But here's what makes
Finland different
They want to create prototypes
And then change and scale and update them dynamically
As a result of their experiments show what's effective
And what's not
And in order to run these experiments
Finland actually had to pass a law to ensure that they were not in violation of their constitution
Course
All the Constitutions of
Democratic countries in the world they say that you have
How to treat people equally
And by definition if you're running experiments
You're not treating people equally
Cathay the people who are part of the experiments
I'm not being treated
So they need to be a special law
That's alright that's okay how do
The experiment fit in the Constitution
That says
That people need to be treated equally
And one of the first experiments The Finnish government decided to do was with basic income
Because the welfare office
Extensive and complicated and rather than
Rejigger in one part of it and changing a bunch of stuff around and reworking their normal operations
The basic income experiment just kind of
Chugs Along on it
The program is currently overseen by Mario keturunan
Who works for government Institution
Called Kelly
That's his social insurance institution here in Finland
So I was in charge of implementing this basic income experiment or head of it
Project leader
There's not a lot of stigma about welfare and
Everyone goes to this office every now and then in life
Because there are 40 different kinds of benefits
Stockton, CA
Including students
Support paternal care maternal care pension subsidies
And of course
Unemployment
So in January of 2017 Keller pick mm unemployed fans at random from all over the country
In this experiment we have 2,000 people who are getting this a basic income 560 Euros per month
And so they have to be
Between 25 to 5
58 so they are not students or young people
And they are not those kind of people who will fill out their pension age during this experiment so this is kind of like the pro
Profile of face
Participants didn't volunteer for the experiment
Killer just told them that they would now be receiving 500
60 Euros a month
The news came in a letter
I got an
Fat fat
Mail
Andis
Said that okay you are you happy chosen to be one
It is basic income experiment and I was like out
What's that
Sauna
The unemployed researcher and Yuan SU
Hadn't really thought about basic income until she read that big fat packet that came in the mail
Which outlines the experiment for her
560 Euros a month will be a little less than sign I would get on unemployment
But you'd also be able to work and not worry about losing it
So I was happy about it because
Two years that experiments last
It's got to be that money every month
And
I don't have
Stressed out much because I am a big
Dresser person
I stress a lot
Finding a job is very important to me
So now
Unable
If I find a job in like a part-time job
I could take it
And not lose the support money that usually would
If I wasn't part of the
Basic income experiment
Some of the participants have been talking about their basic income with the Press but
China has kept it a secret
I feel embarrassed about it
Biggest it feels like I have this
Advantage
So I haven't been very
I'm excited about spreading that information and now us
Participating
Your purchase is like okay
I'm not very many people in Finland it probably hearing composite toe
I could be open to foetus
I'm sorry to put it this way
Huge in Finland sauna
Sonic doesn't know
Anyone else involved in the study
Most people in Finland own
Her friends get kind of StarStruck when she tells them
I I get people out of court with that so
The first one I've ever met
He's kind of
Funny really
When you collect unemployment in Finland have to go to these job training meetings and check-ins every couple of months
But these two thousand participants scattered around the country
Don't have to do anything at all to get this 560 Euros every month
Even though they're part of this experiment they also don't have to report how they spent it
And at the end of the experiment
Keller will look and see if this group of unemployed people who got basic income took on work
And compare it
What are control group
Which is
The rest of the unemployed people in Finland
175000 people who are in the same profile than these mm
But they are not getting this basic income so we are comparing these two groups
People
In this two years.
I see what is happening to these how are these people behaving when they get this basic income
And that how are these people behaving
And then when they compare the results
Basic income
Dust mites
Get one step closer to becoming a reality
Play with the idea that
Is basic income would actually come a universal base
Peking compared in Finland
Which is kind of like the
Idea that I don't actually believe that
He's going to happen or I think there are lots of people who
I'm not thinking this is
It's a good idea yes the person currently overseeing the experiment for basic income
Believe that won't work
I think that it would be true drama.
So we would wipe out the whole of this
Social security system that hate we have been building up for decades
And then just replace it with one
Benefits
Children and imagines that not everyone would prefer a flat income
Some people do need more than one base some
Like what if you have children or parents with special-needs you have to take care of all day
In that case
You don't have the capacity to start
Picking up Jaguar
The basic income wouldn't be enough
And of course
Who would pay for it so who would Finance it
It's really hard to say how much basic income would actually cost
The average time
Hair wear it to be inside
And we don't quite know how it would affect the economy or inflation rates
It's all dependent on a number of factors
And there's no exact math on the
If someone truly
Planes that they know how much
More XP
Basic income
Would be
I think they're lying
It's a satchel
Systemic shift.
We decide to start paying everyone a lump sum of money will change the economy in such way that the whole system change
It's like once again something bad
Experiment
Roper says yes basic income would save money by cutting back on bureaucracy
Blue probably still be expensive to fund
That's almost technical
You know it you know if you need money raised money
It's this like fatality
Do they change
By the way
Budgets are arranged
If basic income make citizens become more active and engaged
Ropa has faith that governments will find a way to pay for it
Because I'm excited and activated population is generally good for the economy
He says that's why they have to test before anything else if basic income would really increase productivity in
Improve General well-being
At this point they're testing to see
If it'd be worth more invest
I really really
Really help
This will continue as you spread out that more people are involved
This experiment has
Invigorated sauna
Even though she gets slightly less money than she would on unemployment
She's free to do whatever she wants
I am trying to find a job
I meant sending you applications and take possibly a part-time job
She feels like she's about to start a new chapter
Ready for what's next
Tranquility of mind
It brought that to me
And if it sounds funny because the amount of money is not that big
But
Give people hope I give people a chance to take a moment
Away from that stress
As a panic of do we survive
It's really important to keep in mind that son is if one participant in a very small study
And basic income may have helped her search for part time work but
When I spoke with her she had yet to actually find employment
And also you probably know that this form of basic income is not
Universal basic income
Who are Universal
It would be money for every citizen employed or not
In this particular experiment
The basic income is only for unemployed
Yeah I think what we're experimenting that would be cold partial basic income its 8 this is a very limited
Experiment I don't know how relevant it is because
A lot of groups are missing
If we want to see what people do when they don't have to work anymore
Roper says they should next
See what happens if basic income is given to people who are already employed
To see if they then quit their jobs
Critics of the experiment also argue that 2000 people is too small a sample size
To finish Economist published an op-ed in the New York time call
Why Finland basic income experiment isn't working and said it had the potential to incentivize people to accept
Low pain and low productivity jobs
It's an experiment that's far from her
But it's not supposed to be a be-all end-all
Ideally
It's a first draft
Weekend is considered Latino
Give
This amount to something else
And some people and then we'll know for sure it's going to be
Other experiments before we can find out how to
How to renew your social
Basically if this experiment is at all successful
Or even if it's not
It should lead to another experiment
And then another and then another
In Finland isn't Justice on the experiments with basic income
Dobie experiments
For what language
Esthetician schools
How to change Child Care everything
According to their website
Experimentation office is working on 26 key projects nationally
And
Slowly
Hopefully
Finland will use the design process
To figure out
If it's possible
A worthwhile
To try radically new
Ideas
Express
Test and cycle
Will we ever get a basic income experiment right here in the US
It turns out we already had one
Decades ago
Avery explains after the break
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses
Design and build their own website
Using customizable layouts
And features including e-commerce functionality
Leanne mobile app
Squarespace also offers
First built and search engine optimization
To help you develop an online presence
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
People here in the United States are talking about
Universal basic income into me just seems like
It's not on the table at all I just feel like there's something about the US
That makes it so it would never happen here the basic income is basically something
That could only be tested in Nordic
Welfare state
The crazy thing about basic income is it's actually this very American
Idea
It was
First proposed rightly
He's kind of first mention
Buy American Founding Father Thomas
We've actually been down this road before
For as a nation
Here in the United States
We did some studies
With basic income
Back in the 70s
I shall ask the change
The framework of government
Richard Nixon wanted to see if he could guarantee a family of four
$1,600 a year
Like ten thousand
Today
Let us place a floor under the income of every family with children in America
Let us provide the means by which
More
Can help themselves
I'm so yeah and then he decided to really try and do it tens of millions of dollars
We're budgeted
So that
More than 8500 Americans
Could be involved in experiment
All around the country
And they're a bunch of different ones
And they tested like
Different variations of basic
Can come in different ideas around
And so why haven't
I heard of these at all well people started analyzing the results
And so they're like
These rumors
Swirling around
Sounds that people were dropping out of the workforce and just like enjoying this basic income
And it wasn't actually a statistically significant
Contra
Kind of a Rumour which can sometimes be more
Powerful than a fact
And they're also all these reports
Increase separation and divorce rates
And that was considered really scandalous and set off a lot of opposition but then when the data was actually Anna
It wasn't as large
That many more.
Is there a few but this wasn't necessarily A Bad Thing
Exactly exactly yeah but the American public didn't have the patience for nuance and they're like this will be the end of the family
Tolerate it and it's all just because like
They started chatting about it before they had the numbers
You know it was kind disregarded before we really had a chance
This is Elizabeth Rhodes and she is a research director of a basic income study that is happening at wyaconda
Mater research
And she's helping to launch a basic income experiment here in Oakland
Capri Pilots Mall
Group B strep test some of the logistics and preparing
For a larger randomized
Control trial that we hope to Launch.
After that local time
They want to really expended
Actually look
H22 US states
Embroidery
They
I definitely learned from these early experiments
Start small
Expand slowly and to not
Promise Too Much
Because
You know they want to wait for this
Experiment to fully play out and said he's going to run unit for several years
And so I don't expect
Tootsie
Changes overnight in anyway and so I think
We really need to give it time
Sew in
Doing this research about basic income I come across
Thousand polarizing think pieces
That are either like UTIs a great idea and we should do this right now or like this is a terrible idea and we need to
Stop it
But realistically it's going to be years
Before we know what we can learn from this privatized America
Can experiment
Orc from The Finnish experiment for that
No one has solid answers yet about what basic income would mean for the national tax code or inflation or unemployment
For the economy or the robots are happiness and well-being
And
Right now all we know is that different experimenters
All around the world
I'm trying to figure out some ants
We just don't know
So what is this is going to end like all radio stories end
Time will tell only time will tell
Time will tell
Thanks Roman
Big fangs 2 Avery truffle
Yousef and the whole crew at ninety nine percent
If you are not subscribed take out your app and do it
Right now
They have beautiful stories well told about all kinds of design issues origin stories of the world around you
Every week
You can send us an email with story ideas and suggestions
I do read them
Planet Money at npr.org
We are on Facebook
Twitter
I'm Alex goldmark