This message comes from NPR sponsors snowflake
The only data warehouse built for the cloud
Unlock deep Data Insights with the instantly scalable Cloud build data warehouse
Start your journey towards data-driven decision-making
It's snowflake. Com NPR
The other day I got an invitation that I wasn't expecting
It was from Walmart
In the past Walmart hasn't been the most open
Company safe
Famously kept the card
Cluster test
But for the last year they've been working on something
Project they wanted to tell the world about
And so I flew down there
Their headquarters
In Bentonville Ark
At this is Julia at Walmart it is I get there and I'm introduced to a guy named Jack
Pastello
Konjac
Hi
Jack is in charge of Walmart
Culinary and Innovation Center
He walks me over this table
Brothers
Plate and on it is one of these
Culinary innovation
It is a bright red a pickle
It is a bright
Red decal and it's got a lot of fruit punch loaded unless you get if you pickle it with fruit punch
Walmart would like the world to know it is creating a tropical fruit punch
Petco
They call this
The traffic
Jack says it's actually inspired by similar pickles you might find in BBQ joints in Mississippi
And you like me to try it
I can probably just cut it with a spark
I'm not sure
Amir
Time consumer for this
Well this case created
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Julia DeWitt
And I'm Kenny Malone and Walmart is inventing
Food
Because
For the last decade it has been doing everything it can
To Stave off one main competitor
Amazon
These two companies are in a battle to be the place where we buy everything
And today on the show
How it may all come down
Dill pickle
A tropical
Support for this podcast and the following message come from fidelity
As a Fidelity wealth management client
You get a dedicated advisor to help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes and make clear recommendation
Thanks for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
That's the Dogs Out.
Hold on one second
This is Charles Fishman
And his dogs
Ocala
He's an author and reporter he wrote a book called The Wal-Mart effect
And he says that when Walmart first started
Food was not part of the
The first Walmart opened in 1962 in Rogers Arkansas
And the founder Sam Walton's plan was to sell all the other everyday stuff
Like toothpaste like laundry detergent
Like diapers
But
To sell those things
Cheaper than anybody else
And a sell everything cheap
The company had to
BG
Sam Walton was
Legendarily
There's a story in trousers book about one of the company offices
Peach all that money for a desk
Chair but the chairs for the gas were
Lawn chairs
That ain't another supplier had brought a sample
Laugh
So instead of buying office furniture
Sam was like head the guy left your lawn chairs let's use them
And sure it's a funny story
But
As Walmart grew and grew
It got really good at these kinds of things that at inventive ways to save money and then sell stuff
Ridiculously
At one point Walmart decided to
Only carry concentrated detergent fruit
Cut down on shipping and plastic
And of course
Cost
It also decided to make it
Proceed shorter
It seems $7000000
A year
And they were known for not paying their employees very well
You gotten better on this but it's
Definitely a part of their cost-cutting hit
For better for worse though
These Cost Cuts resulted in big savings
Customer
Savings
And by 1988 virtually every state in the country had a war
Sam understood that if he was going to grow
He was already selling as much
Toothpaste
As much deodorant as many things like
Athletic socks that people buy and then we're out and then buy again
As as you can sell and you look around it's not hard to say what aren't we selling
Well we aren't selling milk and bread and chicken breast
And if we sell those things
We we change the game for ourselves
Until Walmart decides
To take on groceries
It started opening these
Supercenters that are basically Walmart
Grocery store attached
Intern says that even though the existing grocery industry was this big
Well oiled machine
It did not matter
Because in just ten years
Walmart had devastated the
When
A Supercenter opened near you as a grocery store
You immediately lost
The equivalent of a whole day sales each week
You lost one seventh of your sales
Regional grocery chains went bankrupt
As Wal-Mart rolled out across
Really yes
And they knew what they were doing
They were the number one seller of grocery
In the United States
Charles leader told us that he actually check that number and it was even more chance it went bankrupt because of Walmart it was 27
And in essence
Walmart became a different
Company
With cross
Speakers
Selling food meant that people just needed the store in a totally different way
People go to the grocery store once a week or twice a week
And by the way
If you're in the Walmart
To do a quick grocery shop
The grocery aisles of course a butt
The rest of the store the clothing
The underwear that light bulbs
And so you may just say oh I'm here
We need light bulbs let me go grab them
With the addition of groceries Walmart started making even more money
And eventually became the biggest company in the history of
The world
The biggest by Revenue
Last year Walmart made around 480 billion
Dollars
Half a trillion dollars
In Revenue
Which is to say that
There are now half a trillion reasons
For Walmart to do everything it can
To defend its grocery Empire
Against
I don't know what to say
A company from Seattle
Who really wants to sell gross
We are getting some breaking news on Whole Food
Such a game-changer
Amazon to buy Whole Foods
This is about 6 months ago and I think part of the shock that day
Was it not very long ago at all
Amazon was this website that just sold book
And holy cow
Now they're buying grocery stores
But the reality is
This kind of world domination
It was sort of baked into the identity of the company from the begin
Back in 19 it must have been 1995
They were
Discussing what to call Amazon
This is bradstone he wrote a biography about Jeff Bezos called
The everything
And they did register URLs like book mall.com
But he very clearly chose a name that had nothing to do with books that conveyed
A principle which was like the largest in the world the Amazon the largest river in the world the largest selection in the
The ambition was great even back
Brett says they also considered the name
Relentless.com even back then
Besos
Has Walmart
Mine
He's reading and underlining the autobiography
Sam Walton
Gets copies to
Play score
Wisdom
In about ten years after starting the company
Bezos comes to the exact same realization that Sam Walton
In order to sell everything to everyone
You have to make the leap
Into selling food
They launched the service called Amazon Fresh
Excited I have my first-ever delivery
Amazon
Sign out here there is an entire YouTube category
Of people receiving difference Amazon Fresh
Is a total rabbit-hole stay away we weren't
Many people were very excited
Giant sweet potatoes
Other people
Not as excited
I think it's the last time than Amazon Prime fresh
This because this guy his entire order was basically crushed when you got
What's this box of cereal.
Damn C
Brew
Everything's like that
What Amazon learned pretty quickly is that delivering groceries is
Way more complicated
Then delivering a pair of socks
Sucks don't go bad
And so Amazon's first crack at groceries
It didn't really go that well
Certainly
We should also say that
Walmart by revenue is still way bigger than him
You can still imagine
Walmart
Is watching all of this from Arkansas
I'm still worried
Because Amazon has a ton of money
And eventually it did figure out a way to sell groceries well
Just buy
Whole Foods
Holy cow
Once Amazon bought Whole Foods
Immediately drop food prices and they drew a bunch of new customer
One survey showed about one-in-four of those new Amazon Whole Foods shoppers
Came over from wall
And so Walmart is at a place
Where needs to get to Shoppers back
One way to do that
Used to sell food
The Amazon
Can't possibly have
The kind of food
You might have to invent
In a secret Laboratory
Hidden in Bentonville Ark
Which is how I ended up going down to Walmart's headquarters
See what they're up to
And I'm imagining like this impenetrable Fortress
You know serious cigars it's
The front door
But nope
Blakeman a very enthusiastic employee of Walmart
We're at the front desk of Walmart head
Paris and she give me a pass to get through security there a couple levels of clearance
If you're just going to the vendor rooms here at that battle get you to that but you're going to pass that you'll need it the second one
Yes
Julie did they give you top clearance at Walmart I mean I don't know I don't know how high it goes but
I feel pretty good about it anyways
It's enough to get me back into the Walmart
Where there's a bunch of buildings they all look like Walmart
And eventually
We end up over at The Culinary and Innovations
Inside we walk down this
Hall where there's a bunch of identical kitchens that are meant to
Just look like you know
Average home kitchen
And this is where I meet Victorville I
Hi
Victor is one of a bunch of people who are trying to think up and invent entirely new
From Walmart
Please tell me he's in a lab coat
At now will more Silicon Valley than that something like
Patagonia
Soft shell
Do you know what that picture like a soft coat or light coat
Soft coat
I don't know anyway this is job is
To create
Brand new kind of
PS4 Walmart
What were sitting there he pulls these little plastic bags out of his pocket
Full
Effete
We got wet but you scared to see some of these seeds are for a new tomato
I was at Walmart can ship long distances
But it still tastes really good
Sommerford Brandy
Cantaloupe they named it
The sweet Spark
Which is sweet even in the winter apparently a big problem
Cantaloupe
And the rest of the seeds were a new kind
Watermelon
Is watermelon is actually yellow skin
It's striped
In the bright red inside and the flavor is
Unbelievable
He says the yellow color was actually an accident
But it does also give them a Competitive Edge
When a piece of fruit or vegetable looks odd
I didn't at first
You know it
People really have to try hard enough to get to taste it
But if we put Demos in the stores and they love it
And that becomes your best friend
Because your kid will tell you Mommy bring me the yellow watermelon that I love
Easy to recognize
This yellow watermelon is potentially exactly the kind of weapon they'll need in the food fight with Amazon
Because it will be found
Exclusively at Walmart
I keep thinking like imagine
You could only buy something
Like a baby carrot
At Walmart
But that would be a huge
If you're a parent and you have to go to Walmart
To buy baby
Carrots may as well buy your socks
Tattoo and toothpaste
And everything else you might need
Hand soap Walmart is in search
Of the next baby carrot and it started to put
Systems in place to
Testis as they invent
They have a laboratory
Call the center
I went over there after seeing Victor and
And the way the testing works
Expensive guitar
New watermelon say
Is it hundreds of employees
Come through
The sensory lab and they taste it
And then there were eight
Turn on the damn there there are a bunch of things coming through
Protest test
I've been through them it with an employee
So we're going to do that
There's a whole route
NH Booth you sit
You face the wall
And then one by one these food inventions come out from this
Slots in the
Start with beautiful water to cleanse your palate Force
What were sitting there in the booth Reggie explain to me how this is going to work
Doodle timeout
Taste it and then he'll write it on a scale from
Dislike extremely
Till like
First step out pop some Greek yogurts Reggie taste it and then
That's really good
There's a lemon poppy seed
This one I liked very much. Say
A chicken poblano burrito bowl
Some onion bread
I know you like very much
Are you generally pretty positive guy ready
Hemisphere
Cersei
But you have to be nowadays folks
Pictures of no testing
Any breakthroughs as big as say
The tropical fruit punch pickle
Can't have a tropical everyday
But there has been some pretty groundbreaking research
Birthday cake flavored oatmeal
Okay
The cotton candy grape
Would be delighted to hear that someone finally understand him and I didn't get to taste those those are not quite in
And what struck me while I was visiting the culinary and Innovation Center
Was that this grocery war between Amazon and Walmart has reached
Almost
Point
Amazon is buying actual
Stores Walmart is inventing
Grapes
And it's all part of this
Bigger battle
Tubidy a store that sells everything
To everyone
What creates a whole new problem
Because what is the difference between two stores
That both sell everything
Why do you go to one person
The other how do you even choose
Annie's company seem to understand
What this means is that they need special stuff
Anything
You can offer that the other one
Speaking of which
I'm going to go grab something
Julia is leaving the studio
I'm waiting studio for Julia
She has left
Leftist Julia
Dawn has Julia Julie's coming back
Acting studio
Okay Kenny we got all the way from Bentonville Arkansas
Tropical
After the break we bring the tropical to a food professional
Support for this podcast and the following message come from fidelity
As a Fidelity wealth management client you get a dedicated advisor to help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes and make clear recommendations
It's for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
Kenny I want people to know what
Fish tropical
Tropical
I obviously tried it I also tried it
But it tastes like a salty
Capri Sun
But we realized we have no idea what to make
Got the tropical and so we brought in
Seafood expert
My name is Dan pashman podcast
Call the sporkful
Yes I certainly have that something that we would like you to try
It is a
Recent development of Walmart
Official I can just tell you it looks
Looks like Maraschino pickles
That's what it looks like
It is called
Tropical
Here we go about her bite
It's very sweet
Could you imagine eating barbecue and and then in
Enjoying this as a side or like
I could actually
I couldn't because Dan said that the tropical reminded him of this food concept
Called the sweet
Doubt that he learned about while he was at a barbecue joint
In Centerville Tennessee
So we finished our barbecue lunch
We're having cake and pie
They left the barbecue on the table
After we're finished with dessert
My host said to me
Now it's time for
For the sweet out have one more Taste of salty BBQ
After the desert
And the barbecue was
Even better than beef
Exit tasted saltier and smoke here
After having just
The carrot cake in the chess pie
And
What what disease
Tropicals are making me crave
Is some pulled pork more weird food
And use them to talk about economic
What have you got for us
We love to hear from you
Email us
Planet Money at npr.org or find us on
Facebook
Twitter today's episode was produced by Sally Helm Alex goldmark is are supervising producer Bryant or Stat
Runs Planet Money is culinary and Innovation Center
And if you're looking for something else to listen to
I cannot recommend more highly
Hey
Show hosted by my former colleague from way back in the day when we working in Miami Joshua Johnson gets new Z it's a
Insightful it's surprising it is a really smart conversation
That you get to eavesdrop on
That one a available wherever you get your podcast
I'm Kenny Malone
And I'm Julia do it
Thanks for listening