Support for NPR and the following message come from State Farm
When it comes to home and auto insurance
They're here through the ups and downs
Go to statefarm.com
To be connect
It was one of the 19000 ages
In neighborhoods
Across the Nation
State Farm
Here to help life
Go right
Earlier this summer
Margaret this day our walked into a room full of cameras
And microphones and Report
Thank you very much
Took a sip of water
Today the commission has decided
And answer the question that some people have been asking for a long time
Is Google abusing its power over the
Google which is now technically part of a company called Alpha
That is one of the biggest corporations on the planet that controls the information that billions of people see when they
I want to know who was FDR Secretary of State
Cordell Hull
Where is the nearest gas
Apparently it's at 51st Street and 11th Ave
Or where to order a Sony digital camera
Best Buy.
The European commission spent the last
7 years looking specifically at that last kind of saw
@ed shopping
And asking
Did Google abuse
Power over the inter
Europe's answer
Yes
Today the commission has decided
To find Google
2 points
Billion euros
For breaching EU antitrust
Bruce
Best AR by the way is Europe's competition chief
And 2.4 billion euros
2.7 billion dollars at the time of the announcement
Is the biggest
Antitrust fine against a single company in the history of Europe
And as far as we can tell
In the history of the war
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Jake goldsbie
And I'm Noel King
Three on the show the case against Google
Also the case
How the cases for and against Google help us think about competition
And Market power and the biggest companies on the plane
Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with great G
How did they make them so great Madewell starts with
Premium.
Then offers men's and women's styles for seriously ever
Also you can recycle any brand of jeans in a Madewell store
And they'll give you $20 off and you pay
They work with the blue jeans go green program
How to turn old jeans into housing insulation for communities in need
Terms apply
Ready to find your perfect fit stop by a Madewell store or go to Madewell.
Here is a thing that is happening right now in the
In all these different parts
To the economy in lots of different countries a smaller number of companies
Is controlling a larger share of the
And there's nothing Economist have been talking about for a while now lately it has started to catch on with politicians
President Trump talk a little about it during the campaign
Too much concentration of power
In the hands
Absolution
Chuck Schumer the top Democrat in the Senate just last week
We're going to fight to allow regulators
Break up big companies if they're hurting
Consumers
These are easy Applause line
But figuring out how to apply them
Figuring out what the government should actually do about this is really difficult
And it's Google case is really helpful in singing about this
It's not just some abstract question. Oh how big should a company be what does it mean it's a specific story with Spurs
Specific detail
So we're going to tell that story
This giant antitrust case against Google it started with a complaint from one
Or at least one small come
My name is Jeff
I'm the CEO and
Co-founder
I found them how do you spell found them
OU infant
Pemf
Foxtrot nuts
Mother found them
Found them like found them
It was a comparison shopping
You don't really care about these
Anymore
Kind of the point of
The story but back in 2006 when Shavonne rap started found them in the UK
There were a bunch of these sites
Can UK in the US
I used one called bizrate
Back in the day there was another one called Next tag
Here is how they work
Suppose you looking for specific digital camera
And you you guys giving you say
Show me the the cheapest
Sony dx100
To be clear she just making up an example
But when Ralph launched
Right there near the top of searches like this or just for you know specific digital camera or whatever
UNC links
Two found them in
And if you clicked on
Found them
Then you would be taken to a to a page that showed you
Comprehensive
Action of that much into our offering.
Taking a camera
And also
Price history graph that tells you
How the price that camera has changed over the Lost
6 months
If you could tell if
Now is a good time to buy or not
I figured this was just the beginning for
The technology that made the site work could be applied to almost any kind of shot
You know shopping for airplane tickets
Shopping for a sandwich for lunch
And she imagined found them growing into you know what giant search engine on its own
Google itself had a comparison shopping
Insight at the time called
Frugal
Clever name but but it just wasn't good
An internal Google Document from 2006 Edge
Quotes
Froogle simply doesn't work
That quote by the way comes from the UK
The Fountains doing pretty well it's got a couple employees some Angel funding
And almost all of their traffic
Is coming from
What's going to happen
Chaffey credit
On the 26th of June
I traffic
Post office
Off a cliff
Yeah
So we instantaneously the first thing we do is look
What has happened
In Google
And what happened is it hola pages
Disappeared from the sex
Where we might be in full sun the 25th of June
By the 26th of June we were
The guy from 4 to 47
Essentially switches off
The traffic
The first she thinks maybe the problem is something they did it sound you know some change in the way their Pages were coated or something
But then she goes on these message
Boards for people working at small internet
Juicy's
Why do mother companies also fell off the same cliff on the same
And she realizes
Oh this is something
Change that Google
When you figured out what was going on how did you feel at that
I am pretty
And a coder and a techie at Flix
I don't do it
Zydu stock
Reference
Is what sign
Being a red-blooded human obviously
Has its disadvantages
Giraffe keeps a stiff upper lip
And she figures
She just some honest
You know surely will clear it up in a
But weeks became months
Became yours
And some of the details of what happened along the way are in this
Butte but a few things are
Yes actually three things are clear
What's up let's do a list
Found him and other comparison shopping sites remain low in the rankings for years
Found them eventually sort of semi shuts down
Number two
Google eventually turns its shopping results into app
So today when you see Google shopping results for save a Sony digital camera
You're not necessarily seeing links to you know the most reliable online camera stores
Or to the stores with the lowest prices
You are seeing
Paid app
And number three
More company start complaining about what Google is doing
Siobhan actually goes to work for a while as a consultant for some of these
And government officials in both the US and in Europe
Start investigating Google
The details of the laws in the investigation on each continent or different but the same general principles
You know in both places Regulators are asking this basic
Did Google violate antitrust
Here's what antitrust law
It's the law that governs
Competition
It got started a little more than a century ago when these big companies were starting to take over really big parts
To be economy like
Oil like railroads
And there's this really interesting tension line
Right in the middle of antitrust law
Yunnan
Point of advantage
Is to encourage
You know we won
Companies competing to make
Better products
To provide better service
That is good for for us for for consumers
But the Wii competition horses
If somebody comes along and is just better than
It drives them out of business
And what's up with the whole Market to itself
Like pink
For example searching
I'm old enough to remember that there were a bunch of search engines out there for years
Before Google came along
I'm not going to lie to you
The only what I remember since Yahoo
Being used with being a finger
Infoseek
No Alta Vista Ask Jeeves
Fgxi
Lycos
Wow yeah I was into it so there were all these search engines in like the mid-to-late
Hourly weather
And then Google
They weren't the first or the second or the third of the
But when Google came along they were so
Obviously
Better
I like I remember this
You try Google
It just works ice like magic how does a
Give me the thing that I want right away
A10 Google essentially put all these other search engines out of business or made them totally marginal
Call Google just work
So much better
So then the question is
Is this a violation of antitrust
I talked about exactly this with a Herbert hovenkamp
He's an antitrust expert
At the University of
If a company comes along and it's better than its rivals
And it puts them out of business
Because it's better
You're okay under both US law and EU
You're okay
You're simply
A dominant firm
I should say by the way hovenkamp consulted for Google about 15 years ago
Has not worked for them since then and just not
Speaking on their back
Okay so just having issues Market
Cher is not in and of itself a violation of antitrust
But there are people who think maybe it should be
Maybe we should worry about firms being this big and this powerful Vera people who argue that Google
And for that matter Facebook should be treated like utility
You know like say the power
Highly regulate
But for now anyways that is not how antitrust law work
For now what antitrust law is focused on is called
Consumer welfare
He's a big powerful company using its power to charge higher prices or to reduce output
In the Google cases means
Are consumers in this case Shoppers you and me
Are we meaningfully worse off
Because of what Google
Hogenkamp answer
No
He says online Shoppers today have it better than ever
This does not even involve something as simple as getting in your car and going from one shopping mall to another one
This is much easier than that
If they're not getting what they want from Google search they can get it from
Yelp or Amazon's not like there's a small group of vaginal pH
The electrical engineers or something you know about this
11 year old kids know about this
Any sense of comparison shopping sites were so useful to Consumers then consumers would find them
Just like they found
Kayak in The Wirecutter and tons of other sites that are not Google
Open campsites treatises US law
He didn't want to weigh in on the specifics
The European
But Google itself has made arguments a lot like these in Europe
Most people who shop online don't just use Google this is what the company says
They use lots of other sites
It's like Amazon
And by the way millions of different merchants
Compete to sell stuff on Amazon
Competition Google likes to say is just
A click away
The company also argues that
Consumers use Google shopping Those ads
The top search sites
Because they're convenient and useful because you click on them and they take you to the thing you want to buy
Google incidentally declined our request to do a recorded interview
But that essentially is the case
And for the case against Google
We go now to Gary reback
Whose job is
Literally making the case against Google
He's a Silicon Valley lawyer
He's done work for found them and other comparison
People can shop on other services
That's true
So
Amazon may have lower prices
But Target may have lower prices but Walmart may have lower prices
If you want to spend the time clicking around
The 12 different sites
And you know what they are
And they'll be different for Office Products
Dan for sandwiches
Then you could do that
These comparison shopping
Sites
We're intended to do a specific thing
Show you the lowest price
Available on the web
That service is gone
And as a result Rebecca argues
Consumers are
Margaret vest are in the European commission Wade these arguments
For and against Google they study the evidence
And they concluded what Google has done
Is illegal
And most importantly
It has denied European consumers
The benefits of
Surf competition
Genuine choice and innovation
Earlier this summer win when you heard the announcement when you heard what the outcome was
What did you think
We were very very place
Dispersive unwrapped
Hymotion doesn't get any of the 2.4 billion-euro fine
By the way
They just goes into the European Commission
But she does get something
Really important
The European commission's ruling says
Google has to give
Quote
Equal treatment
Two rival comparison shop
And its own service
Google has to stop Swimming Pool services including its own
To exactly the same
Standards
An algorithm
It is not clear exactly how this is going to work
Google shopping is just fundamentally different than comparison
Shopping sites
Also Google still has an opportunity to appeal this ruling
But this is the change that Ralph has been waiting
So do you think you're going to relaunch found him
Absolutely
We will be able to rebuild our company
And
Hopefully fulfilling
To be clear the ruling only applies to Europe
In the US
The Federal Trade Commission looked into similar allegations from us comparison shopping
And decided not to bring a case against Google
Yocan
Email us at Planet Money on NPR. Org or find us on Facebook or Twitter
Neither is Brian first at Planet Money senior producer is Alex goldmark
It's a new podcast from NPR Sam Sanders great show ears twice a week on Tuesdays they do deep Dives with
One person terrific interviews
And then on Fridays they wrap up the news of the week it's
Hilarious called it's been a minute with Sam Sanders and you can find it on NPR one or wherever you get your podcast
I'm Jacob Goldstein thanks for listening
Well I did not speak with Margaret vestiaire of the European commission for the Shelby just played you know that tape of her from the Fest
But I didn't need to figure out how to say her name so I asked you on Rap by the way how do you say vestibule
Is it best to best
That would be the only man in the United States
Pronounce it correctly well you know I don't know what happened if we were the only ones
Which though this is a complicated question for a radio reporter but not one that you have
Have to solve a sheep or a wolf Jacob
Comfortable business shoes