Hey it's Jacob Goldstein
Today Show is a rerun of a story I reported with David kestenbaum back in 2014
Puritas
If you'd walked up to somebody on the street a hundred years
Inesta
How's the economy doing
It would not have had any idea what you were talking
Sure people talked about how many ships came into New York Harbor or
How the wheat Harvest was that year but
This idea that we take for granted today
But there's this thing out there called the economy
That idea did not exist 100 years ago
And today not only do we talked about the economy
We talked about it with a single number so without even really thinking about what it means we can say
Last year for US economy grew by 1.9%
I was hoping for
2.5
At least
Today on the show how we started boiling down in
Entire nations
To a single number
Haven't number made people think they could control
At least you have
Support for this podcast and the following message come from ADP
Whether you're a small business on Main Street
Aura Global Enterprise
They're leading Solutions and expert guidance help you stay compliant
Reduce cost and develop HR strategies that align with your goals to help you build a better Morford
Doctorate Workforce
From hire to retire ADP had your business cover
ADP a more human resource
So Jacob we are not making this up it really does seem like V economy
At least as we know at that notion
Really was born at a particular moment in a
You can use
Google the go back hundreds of years and search through old books for the phrase the economy
If you do that what you find is
Basically nothing
Nothing 1900 nothing
And then
Two decades after 1900 people suddenly felt this really compelling need to talk about the
Economy
This giant invisible thing that was all around
It was invented because of the Great Depression
This is Zachary karabell he just wrote a book called the leading indicators and he actually does that Google trick in his book
And it was invented because that was clearly a perception that
There was something really really bad going on
But I didn't really know what I mean
It's either homeless people
Call the street you can see that were farmers
You know the Okies heading from their Dust Bowl Farms off to California by the
Tens of thousands but there was no way of really grasping at
You can imagine say FDR same to his advisors
Will it down for me how bad is it
What's the big picture
But the answer them they needed a number
The number that today we call GDP
Gross
It's not like no one had thought about this kind of thing but
Hundreds of years they would be moments when say the king of England would tell some advisor to go ride through the countryside
Figure out how much
Stuff England had a tap all the wheat and all the horses and all the swords in
Figure out basically if england had enough stuff to go invade France
But during the Great Depression the US government decides to do this in a much more serious
They're going to go Way Beyond sending out a guy in a
They're going to try to add up
Everything that gets made in the end
Tire country in a given year
All the houses that get built all the beers sold in bars every
Fedora every Studebaker every visit to the doctor
And to do this they need a numbers guy
A guy who is willing to devote his life to waiting through really boring reports and figuring out how to add up last
Lots of numbers
And they find just the right guy
His name is Simon
We called up Economist glenwild who is written about him
And yes
What was Christmas like
Extremely extremely serious
Sundry
Not surprisingly
I suppose
But but not just like Economist or serious and dry like
He was extremely extremely sober
Totally data-driven
Just
The ultimate
Careful
Sober scholar
For even less fun than your average
Adding up all this stuff is harder than it may sound
First of all
App to figure out everything that you need to count
Just trying to find what things need to be included
Is an incredibly complicated task time in the steel industry Association
Had figures on how many tons of steel were being
Agricultural Association
You have many tons of
Grainware B
But no one had made an attempt to actually put that all together into an integrated
Picture of all the economic Act
Activity that was going on
Imagine at some point they added it up and they're like oh wait we forgot ice cream parlors
Yes
Once you figured out what the count
You have to figure out how to count it
For one thing
You have to make sure you're only counting what the US is produce
So if someone buys up Hershey bar in New York City
But the cocoa to make that chocolate bar came from Brazil
You have to subtract out the cost of the Coco because it didn't come from them
The Coco is part of Brazil
The Christmas and a bunch of other numbers guys go to work
And in 1934
At the request of Congress they publish this report
Actually makes me yawn
The title
It is called
National income 1929 to 1932
And this report this report becomes
A bestseller thousands of copies of printed
And they sell out
Here's a sampling of what Americans were so eager to read
Quote
The economic changes that occurred in this country during recent years are sufficiently striking to be a parent to any Observer with
Without the assistance of
Statistical measure
There is considerable value however
In checking the unarmed observation
Given a careful student by the lights
Have a quantitative picture of
Wealth of David
You can see why this very wonky City
Which at the time was called national income
Becomes part of an overnight sensation
More than anything before its national income is an answer to this really basic question
What the hell is going on
How bad are things are they getting worse are they getting better
I presume you can't turn on the radio without
Cheering these new numbers and what they're measuring this new thing called the economy
Here's Zachary karabell
By 1937 Roosevelt starts
Talking about
The economy and he starts talking about
National income going up
National income
Had a mounted in the year nineteen
Billion dollars
You never hear Abraham Lincoln or Teddy Roosevelt or George Washington
Talking in
That's why one of the things that's remarkable to me is how quickly went from a world where none of these
Terms and none of this conversation
Part of
Our national consciousness
To a dance at the center of our naps
This number that
Kuznets is adding
Becomes part of a kind of
Intellectual Revolution
Over in England the Brits are also adding up this number
And the British economist John Maynard Keynes starts talkin about the economy is something that the government
Control
Because you can name something you can boil the economy down to a single number single member that rises or Falls
Falls every year
Starstruck rated peep
Maybe we can change it
Maybe we can control
You got a lot of people who really start believing
That there's this thing called the economy
That's a that's a mechanical system
Database laws just like physics
And that if you can get the
If you can describe the system of the variables correctly
It's very mechanistic
Input and output out and
The part of the reason for measuring is the
The belief that
All this fuzziness that had attended human has
3 round
Waves of
But you verse of growth and then collapse and money going off in money going down
That we could capture and
Control it the same way scientist
We're capturing
Controlling physical real
This new idea of this idea that Economist and the government could really cook
Troll this new thing called The Academy
What's about to be tested in a
Hugosway
In 1941 the US enters World War
And the government basically takes over the US economy to fight the
The fighting an all-out war is not just risky for soldiers
It can be nasty food shortages at
Homemade Cannon rampant inflation
Can bankrupt a country almost overnight
If you're going to
Turn all of this domestic industry into war
Car plants
The tank plants
Parts plans into gun plans
Cino clothing factories into military apparel
How much
How far can you go in the direction of
War output before you imperil domestic
Production
And how far could you go before people started freaking out and worrying
That prices would rise and goods
Fortunately the US has a secret weapon
The most boring Economist on the planet
Simon
Christmas becomes the chief Economist on the planning committee of the war production
But fer is apparently not consulted with Guzman
And in 1942
He gives his State of the Union
Beach laying out
Incredibly specific plans for what he wants to do inter
Terms of war production
He says this year we're going to make 60000 plane
And 45000 tanks and it goes on and on with specific numbers for
Ships
An anti-aircraft
Looks at those numbers he really crunches them he uses those tools that he put together to make his early version of GDP
Videos back to the Roosevelt
And he says I've got some bad news
Your big plan
It isn't going to work
Christmas looks at how much steel and aluminum and copper the US is producing he looks at how many factories there are
And he realizes US economy just is not big enough to make all the planes and tanks and everything else that Roosevelt
And if us tries to do that
It could lead to shortages it could lead to massive inflation it could wreck the US economy
It was the generals versus The Economist
And The Economist one
Betsy Roosevelt listen
There are many people who have said and I would agree with him that the invention of GDP
Was
One of the prime factors in winning the war
The ability to
With some confidence
Be able to dedicate all these resources
Is 11 reasons why America won the war wasn't because we
Fought for
Chick-fil-A better than anyone else is
Because we had such a massive industrial machine
The dwarf the capacity of anybody else
And it was because we're able to use that with confidence that we weren't going to create huge
Domestic
Destruction
The Warren
And after the GDP really Suites the world there are these new international organizations that United
Nations international monetary fund the World Bank
And the people running these new Global Group
They love GDP
First thing you do in the 1950s and 60s if your new nation is
You open a national airline
You create a national Army and you start measuring
And you start measuring GDP because if you want to go to the World Bank where you want to go to the UN and you want some sort of economic aid
The sole criteria for those is
If we give you money
You have to show that it helped your GDP
And of course once you have a single number summing up your country's economy
It's tempting to rank country
By GDP
Like it's some kind of Olympic competition
Which people do especially during the Cold War which of the Cold War as much as anything with this battle of economic system
Who's winning
Communism or capitalism
What is GDP
Politicians around the world start to focus on this thing how do we make our GDP bigger
How do we win this competition
How do we move up in the rankings
By the 19th
60 GDP of such a big deal that it gets its own back
Robert Kennedy calls out its shortcomings in 1968
Get the gross national product does not allow for the health of our children
The quality of their education
Funny jokes
It does not include the beauty of our poetry or the strength of our marriages
Kennedy was the only one complaining about how GDP was being used
Simon kuznets the super serious sober Economist who would help
Created
He eventually won the Nobel Prize in part for that
But he was not entirely happy
With how is key
Creation was being used
Again Zachary Carroll
Just like Robert Oppenheimer who helped create the nuclear bomb
Later camera coiled at the proliferation
Have nuclear weapons and strengthening defined by that
Cuz that's themselves
Sylectus the fetishization of numbers
And the use of this number as a proxy
C for everything
Is what politicians do it's what people do
I would never have recommended that I wouldn't and it's the easy way out
Avoiding hard discussion
Data can be easily abused
In just a few decades GDP went from being a useful depression-era tool to a World War 2 weapons
2 piece of Cold War propaganda to basing its own backlash in the 1960s
And of course
GDP is still with us today
Soap in the end what should we make of
What does GDP really do
It does what it says on the tin it measures the economy
We should try to make it do something it's not intent
Diane Coyle is an economist who just wrote a book called GDP a brief but affectionate history
And she says look
GDP was never intended to measure overall well-being or a nation's standard of living
Certain things that are bad actually make GDP go up
Hurricane damage that cost a lot to fix
Sometimes it's not even clear what should count
For example suppose Jacob you and I both stay home to take care of our kids
That labor by the current rules does not count as GDP
Even though it's pretty clearly work but Jacob if you come take care of my kids and I go take care of your kids and we pay each other
And it does
And then there's the black market which means everything from off-the-books babysitters to Mafia drug
In the US
The black market does not count towards GDP but in some other countries it does
Back in the 80s Italy started counting it's black
And overnight the Italian economy became bigger than the UK economy
Italian celebrate
They called it you'll Sorpasso
Nothing is really
Change
Here's Diane Coyle
We
10 things about GDP is if it's a natural object
It's like a mountain and we have methods of measuring it that are better or worse than more or less accurate
But there is a thing that be measured
Actually that's just not true with the economy
There's no
Natural entity code GDP
In the universe
In other words
Maybe the most important thing to remember about GDP is
It's not a thing
It's an idea and that idea keeps changing
Just last year the US tweet the way it calculates GDP and in an instant
The economy was 500 billion dollars
Hate this jacob back in 2017
There is one last thing about Simon kuznets
The man who invented GDP
You may be more famous today for something else invented
Call the kuznetsov
Curt
Was his explanation for income inequality
More than that in just
Support for Planet Money and the following message
Come from ishares
Because the best preparation for tomorrow
It's building for your future today
Ishares by BlackRock inspired to build
Christmas in equality and the Christmas
Simon kuznets came up with the curve in the 19th
This was a moment when
Income inequality with
Falling in the US
And in other developed
He looked at the data
Thought about the world they said okay
Are basically three phases to historical inequality
Phase one
Pre-industrial societies
There's almost no inequality
Because almost everybody is bore
Phase 2
One comes industrialization some people get really rich most a poor
Inequalities shoots up
And then phase 3
This is what was happening in the fifties people move to the cities
Education improve the middle class emerges
Inequality Falls
The story fit the date of the time it seemed so true the idea became widely accepted
People named this curve of rising and then falling it equality after presidents
Equipnet curve
But of course a few decades later in the US and in other developed countries in equality started Rising again
And the kuznets Curve
Kind of went out the way
Recently that one Economist said maybe we should think about the world in terms of quiz netsuite
Over the very long run inequality Rises
Falls
Sunrises
Then Falls and baby
What's your favorite economic
And don't say gross net
You can tell us on Facebook on Twitter you can email us at Planet Money at npr.org
Today Show was originally produced by Jess Jiang the rerun was produced by Elizabeth
If you're looking for something else to listen to try NPR Podcast embedded
The host is Kelly mcevers and right now they're looking at videos of police encounter
And the strange afterlife that they can
You can find embedded on the NPR one app or wherever you get your
Also if you love
Planet Money or embedded or any other podcast for that matter
Do us a favor
And tell people on social media
About the punch
Use a hashtag
Tripod
Try
Pod
I'm taking Fluoxetine