When Richard feiler was in grads
He had this economics professor who was also a wine color
Bobby had a firm rule that he would
Pay more than
$30
Parabola
This professor would sometimes buy bottles of wine in
And then store them for decades
At some point Taylor found out the in this collection were a few bottles
Professor bought for like ten bucks and they had aged into Beauties and $100 bottles
And in fact
There was
A wine store in town that was happy to buy his
Old weld preserve bottles
But the professor would not sell those old well-preserved hundred dollar bar
He saved them to drink himself on
Special occasion
Which sounds reasonable enough but
Given the professor's refusal to spend more than $30
On a bottle of wine
It didn't make sense to Richard sailor it seems like a violation of basic economic
If you're not willing to pay
To buy a bottle of wine then you should
Sell it rather than drinking
When he's drinking a bottle of wine that cost $100 he's effectively sing I'm not going to sell this and get $100
I'm going to drink exactly effectively paying a hundred bucks
Exact
Richard sailor became obsessed with these kinds of stores
Where people are violating the basic rules of economic
Until we started keeping a list of them
On the chalkboard in his office
The list disorder
Dumb stuff people do
Like for example when people want fewer choices rather than more
Or when they go to a movie
I know 10 minutes and that it's going to be awful
But then they sit through the whole thing just cuz they paid for the
Taylor got pretty excited about this list and he even at some point showed it to his dissertation advisor
He didn't
Much
And Andy never did
The New York Times later reported that the advisor thought sailor had wasted a promising career
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Jacob and I'm Kenny Malone today on the show how Richard sailor went be on Netflix
Help save us from ourselves and won this year's Nobel prize in economics
Like I'm nerd superhero origins
This message comes from NPR sponsor Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimums that can be open from anywhere in 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Richard thaler got his PhD from the University of
And took a job there as an assistant professor of echo
So I'm teaching there
And I'm kind of floundering a bit
I was writing papers on the economics of crime and things like
And you know I'd decide line
Nobody really took it seriously
Goodbye sideline he means
That list on the Choctaw
Richard turned into a sort of obsession
Analyzing Waze
These people behave
Irrational when he talked about this list other account
Yeah yeah yeah
We know
Lots of people are dumb
Everybody you don't need a pot and storm around
Overall on
Average they're going to be rash
And this is a core Assumption of echo
People on average behave rash
The model that Economist build the predictions they make are based largely on this
And then one day Richard sailor meets this other young actor
Psychologist
Anntaylor starts telling him about his list
You know what you should check out
This research
By these two guys I used to work with in Israel
Daniel Kahneman
And Amos tversky
Tok Taylor walks over to the
And I had to find a whole new section of the library
The psychology section
He starts pulling down these papers by continent
And I got very very
I'm like racing
Through
One paper after another
Willits is like watching
Thriller on
With a big screen
I just to remind everyone you're reading psychology papers I'm reading psychology papers and my heart is beating
It's the most excitement
I've ever felt SSI
Really is that still true is that still true now
Yeah that was like the big light bulb
Here's what that light bulb was
Kahneman and tversky we're proving that there were all of these ways where people are
Predictably consistently irrational you would take
Morales everybody in the world put them in a pot
Sturm up
And these guys were fighting people do not
Behave rationally on
They were finding that people make the same kinds of mistakes
Over and over and
It starts to Dawn on
He's been making this list of life
Random
Cute stories
People doing weed
Cure to psychologists who are doing actual science about those same kinds of things
I mean is there some sense of like I'm not alone in this
Well there was that
Although these two guys
Are over in Jerusalem
So you're still kind of alone
I'm pretty alone you know it's a long way from Rochester
But shortly after
Sailor found out the condiment and tversky were scheduled to be in California at Stanford University
For one year
And
I decided to just
That my entire life
On this
And
Flew out to stand
Spent a few days sort of
Begging anyone
To give me a
Visiting position
So that
I could be there when my heroes arrived
And meet them and talk to them and learn stuff
You get the one-year giggetts
Meet Kahneman tversky
And
Everything clay
So I was teaching them economics in
They were teaching me psychology and
You know 40 years later Danny conoman is still my best friend
This work that condom in and tversky and sailor start doing trying to understand the ways in which
People are consistently
Irrational
It comes to be known
As behavioral economics
It's economics
With
Real people
With Kahneman and tversky
Taylor is now able
To start pulling down those
Little anecdotes from his list
And test them and say okay is this just a cute little thing I noticed or
Is this one of those things that we are
Predictably irrational about
What are the famous studies they do together, and Taylor and one of the researcher do this
Is about mugs
Mugs as in
The thing you drink coffee
So they walk into class
And they just give me
The half of the students in the class
There were
44 students
So22 mugs
That special Mugsy's we're just things that Richard sailor picked up at the Student Union
And then they told the students who got them
This is yours to keep
If you want it
You can have it
But
You are also allowed to sell it to one of the other students
Who did not get them
Play basically just said like Ready set go you don't have your money you all have money
So you guys have mugs buy it or sell it do whatever you
And what they found
What's the people who did not get a mug
Tended to offer
Like two or three bucks
The people who had the mumps like are you kidding me
Drive me to dollars is I would not sell it for a penny less than 5
I remember these people are holding onto their mugs for five bucks or better
There's some random they didn't have the mugs 5 minutes ago
Didn't have any sentimental value
And yet they value their mother
Twice as highly as people who have not been given mug
I didn't have this mug and care about this mug but now that I have that I'm not doing that
The discovery
With that simply
Having a thing
Makes you overvalue that thing
I ended up calling this the endowment effect
Like that professor of sailors who wouldn't sell that hundred dollar bottle of wine
Indominus
You got World Series tickets for face value you know you could sell them to a scalper for 2,000 bucks
You go to the game anyway
Endowment
Sofia ellar and Cottman and tversky and a few other people are doing more and more of these studies
Finding more and more ways where people are predictably irrational
But it's still just a few people
You know what they're doing is still pretty fringilla still basically outside of the mainstream of
And then Richard sailor gets this odd kind of
There's a big new economics Journal starting up
Call Dad
Journal of economic perspectives
The editor calls up sailor and he says
How much were to call in for
You can write about
The things that you and others are finding
In a column called anomalies
Was when Richard thaler and behavioral economics
Blew up
Just calling what's the best thing in Journal of economic perspectives
Famous economist Tyler Cowen
And the professions
Just got addicted to this
Every issue would come out
People would be talking about Fowler
The other thing I did was it really grabbed the interest
Undergrads like myself famous economist Betsey Stevenson
Who are we meeting them
I'm thinking oh okay so I can ask these kinds of questions
What will that mean for my res
Famous economist Greg mankiw
I don't think people appreciated
At the time that this was going to open up a whole new field and it has
And also
Famous economist
Richard thaler
It's a soapbox
Not only are you up on your soapbox with people are gathering around tools
Yeah
The column helped behavioral economics become a real thing
People were excited
But a lot of Economist had a pretty reasonable criticism
A lot of these findings were coming from classroom experiment
Oncology
Like the mug
Sure
What is that really prove
Do these findings also hold up in the Rio
And there was always looking for ways to
The testes ideas in the real world
Overtime he found more and more one classic example came when he was spending a year in New York
Taking cabs around town
And started talking to the cab driver
And you weren't at the way this business works is the most drivers will rent the cab
12 hours
And then it's up to them whether they want to work the whole 12 hours or knockoff
ISO trailer is called
Start trying to figure out how do the cab driver sort of
Manage their dead how do they decide how long to work when did knock off
Very often the cab drivers have
Some number in mind
At the start of their day
They think like okay I need to make
Say $500 in my date
And then when they hit that number they stop
So aesthetic 6 hours and then they hit five hundred bucks.
If it takes all 12 hours they work 12 hours
And then they stop this means that they wind up working less working shorter hours on the busy day
And they wind up working more working longer hours on the slow days
This is not at all what you would expect
If they were going to follow basic economic Prince
If they were trying to maximize their hourly pay
You know go the full 11 1/2 hours on the day
You're raking it in
And quit early on the day where there's nothing
To be mad
And people are doing the exact
Opposite of
They're doing exactly
Sailor called this Behavior mental account
Taxi drivers
Or treating each day like it's a different account
It's a separate bucket
And it doesn't matter what happened the day before what's going to happen the day after
All that matters is the money that you're making too
And we all do this kind of mental Accounting in one way or another
You know like
The classic example
You spent all year trying to pile up a few thousand dollars couple thousand dollars in your favor
And then one day your tax refund
Like
Jeffrey money $2,000 tax refund I'm going to take a trip I'm going to buy a fancy watch
Know know that tax money is the same money it's dollars it counts the same towards everything
And yet we treated differently
That is mental
So okay fillers done the classroom work the mugs and stuff
He said he's real world studies like with
The cab drivers
Eventually
She and other people in the face
Okay
Now we know all of these ways that people sort of
Self-sabotage
Maybe we can set up the world or at least
Kind of tweak little corners of it
To help people get what they want
So one problem that sailor noticed
People don't save enough money
Which is literally news to Noah
What's Taylor and his colleagues realized
There might be some really easy things you could do to make it easier to say
So like when they started looking at this
It was typical when you started a job at a company with like a basic 401K retirement
You have to sign up
You know you had to say yeah put some of my money in the
But most people did not
Sign up so they learn his colleagues said I'd how about that
When you start a new job
You're automatically enrolled
Into the 401K
You're going to automatically start contributing it's going to come right out of her
Your paycheck
And if you don't want to contribute
That's fine
You're just going to have to fill out some paperwork
And then no country
No big deal just had a huge
What's more people started country
But this default Optimum contribution was
Very low
Companies with star people off at a very low rate
Not enough not enough
Not enough
Don't
Stop at Throop
So another one of my students Shlomo Ben Arts
CN I tried to figure out a
And we called it save mortem
It's great cuz I don't miss I don't have to save more today first of all
I'm already exactly
Save more tomorrow means that
You start out at aloha
But then when you get a raise down the road
You automatically start saving a bigger and bigger portion of your paycheck
And all these ideas about retirement
Took off
Can I say by the way
Bloomberg News just
Yesterday
Publish the story that
Said
Some 68% of large US companies now automatically enroll employees in 401k
And
Three-quarters of those employers bump up worker savings rates
Automatically every year
That's it
That's behavioral economics
Enact
These little tweaks like changing the default option to opt-in
And automatically contributing money
Taylor and one of his colleagues started calling these
Nudges
And people in power
They like these
And all of a sudden
Governments around the world were nudging there
In the UK the government created something that people started calling of the nudge unit switch
Sounds like some you know bad band out of Seattle in 1995 but
This group
Did figure out how to get more people to
The organ donors they got more people to pay their taxes on time
In the u.s. President Obama set up his own nuts unit that helps low-income students enrolling
College and help veterans get access to
Benefits and save more money for retirement
And sailor says as of today around 75 country
Have Nigeria
Working on this stuff
Trying to take the findings
From this new field of Behavioral economics
And help us
Get the things
I mean what like what do you make of your career
What do you make of sort of the field that you've helped
Whatever you were
Just
Go big
So
Economic theory can really be boiled down
Two words
People Optima
And if I die
Choose the best alternative they can afford
What is your response
Two people OptumRx
Look look at this
I'll look over here I got a month to sell you
Exactly
The idea that
People have self control problem
And
If they don't know how to save for retirement and then they know they should
Is News 2
No one
Accepted
Yes that's the world we live in
And
Once
You accept the realization that we are
Imperfect being then there are things you can do to help
After the credits pierre-richard Baylor get the phone call after win
Meaning the study drink spiked with Alfred
Yunobo
Prize in economic science
Can you set the right way to know what's the for the fullest patties to be spanked
Prize
In economic Sciences in memory of Alfred
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One Capital One is reimagining banking by offering accounts with no fees or minimums that can be open
From anywhere in 5 minutes Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Email us at Planet Money on NPR. Org you can also find us on Facebook or Twitter today's episode was produced by Nick fountain
Ryan Hurst that is our editor
Headed for nudge unit Alex Goldman
Special thanks this week to Richard Sailors former student
Heartland into failures golf buddy
Eugene Fama
If you're looking for something else to listen to check out up
First it's a podcast from the people who make Morning Edition it comes out every day you can listen to it you can find out
What's happening and it's a podcast do it whenever you want wherever you are I'm Kenny Malone and I'm Jacob Goldstein
The Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences
Decided to award
Visalia city spine
Prize in economic Sciences
In memory of Alfred Nobel
The Richard h thaler
Forest contribution
Behavioral economics
This is from Monday October 9th
It's 11:45 a.m.
Time in Stockholm
It's 4:45 a.m. in
Chicago weather
Richard Taylor now
He was at home
He gotten a heads-up that he won the prize
And the Nobel committee called him up
Again so you could talk
Tua room full of journalists
Hello.
Taylor
This is John Hanson
Then the guy who woke you up an hour ago
Good morning John
Have you had your cup of coffee and I'll
I'm awake
Pretty good
Have a question over
Bear
There's a substantial amount of money involved here in
Enterprise
I'm wondering if you're going to be super Russian about the
This money or if you will act
Humanely
Well
You know
If this is actually quite a funny question
I will say I will
Try this
Send it
Irrationally as Pop