Warning
This podcast contains profanity
Also graphic descriptions of dead animal
White Oak pastures in Bluffton Georgia
About 2500 Acres
Will Harris runs the farm which has been in his family for more than a hundred year
And Will was raised by his father and trained in school to be a modern Industrial
Cattle farm
When I got out of college
I was excited
About a new pharmaceutical product light
Hormone implants
Why
Increase production
You you are able to do
More and more cheaper and cheaper
Will take over from his father
Made a profit every year
But at some point the way you looked at the world started to chew
I wish I had a better story to tell you I wish it was the burning bush something but got a big bed one like that
It was way more gradual than that and it happened in all these different
For one thing he started to look at the soil
I noticed that
Soil
Just over that fence
Wade
Soil right here
He saw that the soil on the other side of the fence so that had just been left alone was
Teeming with life
This will right here on his farm
Was debt
She thought it was in the world and is just a fence
A wire fence
And then there was the day he was sending off about a hundred cattle onto a double decker truck to go to a feedlot thousands of miles
He realized maybe on the truck for days
The ones on the top would be going to the bathroom on the ones on the
And
Ulysses Ramos that we have had on this Farm
Nurture them to Care album
It just didn't seem right
And eventually he decided to change everything about the way he
You bringing chickens to fertilize the grass
The grass would nurture the
The cattle Shoppers at Wholefoods with line up around the block to buy his
It was also
Perfect it was such a
Beautiful vision of the enlightened 21st century American Farm
It wasn't that so perfect that a literal symbol of America showed up at his farm
The bald eagle
But the bald eagle America's bird
Was not on board with Will Harrison
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Jacob Goldstein
Put on the show The Meat you buy in Whole Foods the farmer who makes it
And a bad-tempered All-American killing machine
Farmers have been trying to put nature in a cage for thousands of
What happens when you start to let nature out of that cage
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Rocky
Rocket mortgage by Quicken Loan
When choosing a mortgage lender
Work with one that has your best interest in mind
Rocket mortgage provides a transparent online process that helps you understand your home loan
You can even adjust the rate and length of your loan in real time to make sure you get the right mortgage
Skip the bank
Skip the waiting and go completely online at quickenloans.com money
Equal Housing lender license in all 50 states nmls
Consumer access. Org
Number 3030
Will Harris is 62
Goatee shaved head white Stetson hat
He drives around all day in history
Basically running is
And a few weeks ago I tagged along with
This house was built in 1870 something by my great grandpa one day I live with my grandfather built
Open early nineteen hundreds
My day was bigger than me and meaner than me and talk more like Foghorn Leghorn than I do
Seems impossible
I mean the f*** was like nothing mean
By the way will Harris knows we are maybe making fun of his accent
And he's fine with that
In fact he's also making fun of rxn
He told me the story about when he first started selling his meat at Whole Foods
He would visit the stores to be that sustainable farmer standing at a table handing out samples of
A guy like you or lady
Won't mind take a little sapling
Which natural killer cell phone iPhone go
Honey
Mission
I'm Whole Foods and
There's this guy here and he's serving this beef end
I know we said we were going to have salmon for dinner but what do you think get beef will you think
Can you imagine what my wife would think if I called
If she was shopping to call me
We should
Mission Food
So we're driving down this this four-lane highway that runs through the middle of Will Smith
And at some point we pull off and go down this dirt road into this really green pasture
You could see there was like a forest off in the distance really beautiful and Will turns off the engine
To tell me you know how we went from being
An industrial farmer to selling you know pasture-raised organic high-end meat at home
One of the first things he did was quit using pets
But we needed that these new kinds of grass has started growing in his field and the cows would need them
We brought in sheep and goats
He also quit using chemical fertilizer
Breading chicken
Here we buy
Feed for the chickens
And
If he turns into poultry that we sell
By product to use the menudo that goes over the pastor that makes
Scrafty
Genius
The chickens are spread out all over the farm you know that wasn't here that was in there and their manure is his fertilized
And then he realizes if he's going to sell this high-end meet at a premium
Send his animals off to the industrial slaughterhouse with all the commodity cows
So he decides to build his own sweater
Which is Barry
But he's still started growing
He got his meat into a bunch of Whole Food stores and Publix this chain of grocery stores in the South also started selling is made
He was paying off that debt
And then
About a year after he brought in the chickens
The first pair of eagles show
So I was very excited about if I was great and I love natural systems and I love
Nature nopales fantastic
We'll quickly saw that
The Eagles
Loved his
Pasture-raised organic chicken
But it was okay with it
Who's just a few Eagles
He told himself
The Eagles are like Nature's version of quality
Little kill
The quickest
Healthiest
Bird you got
Trattoria people
You never get a sick bird from White Oak pastures
Everyone you get this
Your sister can say all that random
The thing will didn't realize
Is that when Eagles discover an all-you-can-eat
Chicken buffet
The word spreads fast
The first year that was at two or three the next year that was
Maybe till 12
This year maybe 30 or 40
Last year
They said it was 77
You have more this year
As more and more Eagles started showing up
More and more chicken started die
Eva long time
Her for my employees what's eating my ass up back there
Alright I need it bad
And I wanted to be all right
But at some point I had to show you know they really are
Causing economic
Place and then Eminem lose money on broiler
Would you make money on chickens if not for the Eagles
Topix
Over the past few years will says
The Eagles have killed
Hundreds of thousands of dollars worth of his
The peak season is winter
Right now
And will says the Eagles are currently killing a hundred or more of his chicken
Everyday
Thousands of chickens a month
And this is easy to see
You just drive out into one of the fields where the chickens
So what happened with Sarah I don't know couple hundred chickens here a hundred mg I don't have a son
Cost of a thousand chickens
And there's some of them
Some around in the grass some of them are kind of chilling out under this thunder tree over there
You on the shoulder the chicken house or something or eating the feed
Drinking the water
Feel like these chickens are living the dream but for one thing man
Bald eagles
They're just
Sitting there in the trees right at the edge of the field
They don't make that screeching sound like you hear in the movies they don't really make any sound at all but they do look
Big and beautiful you know they look like a postage Stamper something you'd see airbrushed on the side of the van
But right there in front of us in this chicken Paradise were standing in our chickens the Eagles have killed
So this got so this were looking at here is basically
The back half of
Chicken right there
Feet and legs
But the top half is essentially the eagle
Easiest way into the body cavity
Have you seen that
That happening with your seen thousands of time Eagles are sticking his head in that body cavity
Episode 2 of why did it legally this is pink because it gets all that blood on it
So there's that this guy with somebody basically ate right this is a
Eating up chicken
Then there's this other chicken 3 feet away it's also dead
This chicken was just just killed
Because it was fun
Nothing is happened to it
How many
Eagle Strike
Brightness
Just like a sport just like
Screw you I'm going to kill one more ticket
The rudest Beast evolved
Will Harris has completely transformed his
Farm to live in harmony with nature
And now here is nature
Sticking its head into his body cavity and eaten his financial
WhatsApp
It's kind of in space all the time
Betting legal
Mega missile juvenile bald eagle
Looks like
Full and happy
How do you feel seeing all these Eagles just coming and eating your chicken
Oh
Universal mixed bag
You know I can have it shotgun right now he's pointing at the backseat of the
Aeropostale
He shot at other predators that were attacking his livestock
But Hair Says
Hey he doesn't want to shoot bald
And be even if he did want to
Eagles have their own special law to protect them
The bald and golden eagle protection act
Which makes it a crime to quote
Pursue shoot shoot at poison wound kill
Capture trap collect molest or disturb
Eagles
Will Harris is in a bind
Westfall he did get some good news from the Federal
Keeping granted a special permit
Not to kill that Hugo
But to harassed
Basically try and make them go away
So he's trying all of these different things
One of the first things he did
You got one of those giant inflatable people like you see outside the car wash
You don't like this some kind of fan inside of Minnesota
Bend over and snap back up
He bought one of those
And put it up next to some chicken
He says it'll take about 15 minutes
To figure out there was just like one of those floppy guys
I actually saw this quickly
It was just lying on the ground the generator that powers and was out of gas
What about 15 or 20 feet away from a bunch of chickens
And yes one of the chicken
Will also put sparkly Flags out
Eagles didn't say
Seem to notice
You got this big old noise cannon with a barrel like 3 ft long you could hear it miles away
Eagles didn't seem to care
Another thing you tried
Admit
Over the top
Like a canopy over the open area where the chickens were walking around but apparently Eagles do not have to attack from the sky
We were just walk and Landon woke up under the net and get the chicken
Will is trying one other thing to make
The Eagles go away
Maybe the most badass
Of all the things he
He sent me out with this poultry manager Jeff Lackey to see you tonight
There we go there's an eagle right there a circle around to kill a chicken
Definitely I left his lunch
Oh he just moved down
We drive across this field get out my chicken house
There's a couple thousand chickens walking
And just spot San Diego
Actually looks like there's one the Pharcyde that tree there
He pulls out what looks like a little little pistol
This is
A cap gun of sorts that takes these two caps in the back
Benny opens up this yellow box and pulls out his
Ammunition
Take two
Black and goes into the gun so those look like little
Firecracker
Chris basically asking small m-80s almost
What to say
Bird banger
Warning
Danger
15 mm
Captain has two barrels people it's one Banger in each Barrel
Posi trigger
This firecracker shoots out like
25 feet and explodes in midair
Then he pulled the trigger again
And there they go
Did you see on the backside I treat are there here's one right now
Eagle flying away
We can move them with the Birdman
And then they just come back
Or the yellow go to another spot for now or we got more birds and
Just circle around the many many pastures so this is it I can eat these chicken
I think it's going to go eat some other chicken
Yeah for the next couple hours
Then they're going to eat this chicken
Configure TV chicken
Will Harris says that you know maybe he's losing fewer chickens this year cuz of the bird bangers
Really to send it
But in any case he is still losing a lot he still losing money on his chicken
There is one other way will might be able to keep his chicken business
It's a federal program that pays Farmers whose animals are killed by protected in
Boy killed by say bald eagle
How much do you think they should give you
The maximum is $125,000 per year
And I owe me that for 15 and 16
Has the government giving you any money for the eagles killing a chicken
Now one time
No one.
He's in this legal fight with a gun
This back-and-forth
What's the right way to count the loss is what can
Can a proof do you need
Are we did reach out to the government on this they said the case is under review by the local office
And they're not allowed to discuss the
Whatever happens with the governor
It's clear that the Eagles are not going away
Are there like this living
Killing
Virgin
Of a much bigger
We want a world where we can restore some kind of balance Within
But every time we try to do that we realized
How empaths
You're right here on the farm you just keep seeing this Gap
Between how the world is and how we want it to be
But will is resourceful
Yorkie keeps trying to cross that Gap
At one point is we're driving around the farm
We're next to this field with some chicken tonight
And there's a pickup truck coming the other way
Wheel stops
The Jeep to talk to the driver
Hey how yo
I feel like you would I'm glad you did
In the bed of a truck
There's a guy with a camera with this giant telephoto lens
Which is apparently pretty common
People now come to Wells Farm to see the Eagles
Get the special Eagle day a few days before I was there is even built cabins for people to rent out
Will Harris is getting into the eagle tourism
Yep
NPR
Not usual
You can email us at Planet Money at npr.org you can find us on Facebook or on
Twitter if you're looking for something else to listen to try the NPR Podcast Latino USA
They just put out the special show it's a documentary about Oscar Lopez Rivera
Keep this controversial figure
President Obama actually granted him clemency
Just a few days before he left office
The show with latino USA you can find it on the NPR one app or wherever you get your podcast
Car show today was produced by Elizabeth Gillespie editor was Brian thirsty
I'm Jacob Goldstein thanks for letting
We also have another squirrel call Fox World Envy
But you allowed just sitting up on their haunches and people who
You not from here forever cuz I saw a monkey baby
No it was a moral it was a monkey sound to you is that my voice
Wasting your head