There is this
Race
Going on right now in Washington
To DC this week it's a sort of
Sprint
And the finish line is Friday at noon
Inauguration
The desperate Runners are all the people who work for borracho
Obama all the people in his administration
And they were trying in these last days
Put in place everything they can to ensure the legacy of this president
Before the next one comes in
They tried to match up some last-minute wins
The Obama Administration is creating new national monuments in Oregon
California Utah
Alabama Bunch places speed band offshore drilling in Parts of Alaska for trying to protect funding for play
Planned Parenthood
They released a bunch of prisoners from
Guantanamo a picture of going to the rulebook for the president and trying to figure out if there's anything else they can
Possibly do with the powers of the presidency
Before Donald Trump is smart
Andeavor your building is legacy
You can see the Republican Congress already trying to remove the bricks to undo everything they can
Fast of the Obama people
And it's amazing moment to see because a lot of this drama this race
It comes down to things
We don't usually think about when we think about government
Because it's not about passing laws
Signing bills or statue
It's rules
Rules
Thousands of pages of rules
The take vague laws and make them
A reality
The political balance in Washington DC may have shifted
But the real power is in the hands of the people who write the rules
And the rules to get put in place this week
May stick around forever
Hello and welcome
Planet Money I'm Stacey Vanek Smith and Robert Smith today on the show we will take a single last minute Obama
May very well be
The very last thing that President Obama does in office
This rule goes into effect the day before Trump is not great on Thursday
And we will show you how this rule came about and how it works
It's a rule that could help clean up polluted streams and lakes and could also cost big companies a lot
Of money it's a rule that could change this country
And it all depends on whether or not Congress could dismantle it
And that
Is a question of timing
Support for Planet Money and the following message come from betterment
A smarter way to invest your money
Betterment combine time-tested investing principles with the transparency and ease-of-use you expecting great things
Nagi focusing on lowering fees and tax
And here's what you might find
Refreshing
Betterment really cares that you reach your financial goals and that's why they keep their fees
Low
Planet Money listeners can get one month management free
For more information visit betterment.com Planet Money
This last-minute rules slipped in just under the wire is not some
Final Obama screw you to Republican
In fact it has been in the works
For a long time
A very long time
Long before Obama even got his law degree
This story started
With a coal miner
Before we get started could I get you to introduce yourself with a Hello my name is
My name is
Chuck Nelson
A retired coal miner
About 30 years at working Underground
I'm a fourth-generation coal miner so
Father grandfather great grandfather we all work in the mines
Habanero
1980s check had a job loading coal onto a conveyor
He was living in Sylvester West Virginia with his wife into
And he was used to dirt and cold us
Down in the mine
But then a coal processing plant was built right near his home
We start eating a lot of cold
Hummingbird bath
I may not go to work and come home at night
Tonight will be a half inch Eco test
Everything in the house what is coldest look like
It's just black powder
Sis light on your tables on
Ford
Beyond
It would even get in the refrigerator that's for this stuff again
Chuck's kids couldn't swim in their pool because there was this thick black skin on the water all the time
Text wife started having really bad asthma problems
Complain to the coal company
End
They ignored her
And this made Chuck angry
Sauschuck started to talk to Environmental Group
The advocacy group
On his days off at the coal mine he would gather a little group of locals together get into his Mitsubishi Eclipse
And drive for 5 hours to washing
And there he would meet with anyone who would hear
He would talk about the
Pollution he was seeing in his community and health problems
People were having
He thought the coal companies were to blame
Which did not play too well with some of his fellow coal miner
They would tell him the coal industry is struggling as it is
If you go and advocate for a bunch of new regulations
We're going to lose our jobs
They threatened it
Decorating is a threat this is Douglas down in Minecraft
Killer
But check kept making car trips to Washington
2dc specifically protected trucks refrigerator and his swimming pool from coal dust
What environmental experts pointed out that there might be another way to
To help his family
It was a law already on the books called the surface mining control and Reclamation Act
Who's passed in 1977
And it basically said that mining companies should try
Try really really hard not to kill Fish and Wildlife
Okay so here is the actual language
It says that Coal Company should not cause quote material damage to the environment
To the extent that it is
Technologically and economic
Whatever that mean
Technologically economically feasible could mean anything
Marvin sister supposed to be there supposed to be really brought it's part of what helps get Congress to vote for
And after Congress vote for the lawn after they go home on
Ktuner back to the
District whatever's there doing
That is when somebody needs to write
The specific rules
What the law should look like on the ground who it applies to
Under what circumstances can look
Really different
Depending on the
Specific
Rules
So
Bureaucrats lawyer scientist expert
They sit down in room after room after room and figure out okay so
What did Congress mean when they said material damage
What did they want to happen when they said
Technological and economic
In the case of the surface mining control and Rec
Formation Act of
Chuck and other environmental Advocates felt like the rules
They said coal companies are still open
People are have
Health problems the streams are full of heavy metals
Refrigerators are still full
Full of coal dust
This law has no teeth
So they started pushing for a real check
Same 1977 Loft restrictors
Enforcement
And when Obama took office the new rule makers
She put in charge of
Mining regulations said
Okay
Let's do this
Small problem writing this rule
Come to be known as the stream protection rule
Was not going to be in
Easy thing
It would take thousands of pages of writing callus hearings
And all this time Chuck and the other activists is community woodpile to the Mitsubishi
Drive to DC and centerpiece in Capitol Hill again and again in a
Since 2006 I might have many many trips
Washington DC
Like
20 / 25
And I mean every year we used to go we would Lobby
Ariana talk
What senators
Congressman
DPI
Louis M
Ali's agency
We did that wants to every year
It's funny because I know I follow political news fairly closely what happens in washing
DCA what I think about
What really gets done there I always think about the
Congressional debates
C-SPAN
The voting passed the big signing the president does the bill in the Rose Garden
The woodchuck was going through was the real work the real power of Washington DC
The arguing over all the details
Actual writing
Rulemaking is a process is the most important source of law in America in a rulemaking is
That kind of activity that get you really into the guts and details of how public policies and programs work
Neil Kerwin is the president of American University P also wrote a book about
Which I'm sure drives his kids nuts right I wrote the Book of Rules
You got to clean up your room
He told me that are practical reasons
Why the system works
Because politicians are
Big picture
They passed laws that give general direction the gist of what the country
It would take forever to read the kind of details that
Rules provide
Rules of taking over DC for another week
And that is because
Presidents can make rules all by themselves
Well I mean the the one thing that rulemaking does it for the president has the ability to enact
Public policy without interacting with the Congress
Rules don't usually need to be approved by Congress Congress gets
The comments of the public but basically when it comes to rules what the White House says go
That's how President Obama accomplish a lot of
What he did the Republicans controlled Congress
But Obama controlled
The rules
Music Obama has kind of gone to town with the rulemaking
Over the last few months
Since June Obama issued more than 60 rule
Covering everything from
Drone certification to how Medicare covers
The school lunches
And of course the stream protection rule
Stream protection
Environmentalist had been working on it for
Tour years and years
Years
Obama loves rules
Andy sympathetic environmental cause
This is Our Moment
Until they pressed finish this rule while Obama
Was still print
Matt Watson
An ecologist the group called Appalachian voices
Made it his mission
How many hours
Would you say you've put into the stream protection rule
Wow
I guess
15 years worth of hours
Since the early days when Chuck
The coal miner
Start complaining about the coldest in his house
The stream protection rule had balloon to 1200
Pages
Obama's first term passed without finishing the rule
His second term was nearing its end and it still wasn't fitting
Nobody could tell me why it was taking so long I asked everybody this and people just get them all that is how long
Girls take their all these rules that you have to follow when you're making
Arul there Pub
Amon.
You've to meet with all the
Involved
Companies the miners used to go to
People's homes you have to take soil samples in water sample
There's just all the stuff you have to do
And then there was the whole
Political thing to like maybe Obama did not want to piss off cool States right before the election
Perhaps he just assumed that Clinton would win
She would take care of
Whatever the reason Obama's agencies work
Really fast after Trump was elected
Anton December 20th when Matt Watson was visiting his brother in Calif
Aunt for the holidays
He woke up to see an alert on his phone
Stream protection rule was being issue
It would go into effect on January 19th
Literally on the last full day of Barack Obama's
Yokai I guess the thought was oh snap I was going to be in here
As well as some relief that they actually did get it done
Siri like
Finally after all these years I mean 15 years
Hazmat was reading the alert on his phone in California feeling that sense of relief
Members of the coal industry were also getting the news
Adam Eckman was at his desk in Washington DC that morning he heard
The rule was
Finalizing
Refreshing the department of the interior's website over and over
He's a lawyer for the national mining Association which is an advocacy group that represents mine and come
And just like the environmentalist Adam had spent years of his life
Working on this route
Thousands of his own hours on the opposite side
Fighting
The stream protection rule
Although
He does not like that name
That name is something of a misnomer
It amends or modifies 475
Existing rules
Within the code of federal
So to call it a single rule is startling
I just might be able to tell Adam is a lawyer by training and he has spent all these years talking to Congress and mining companies
And people who live near mining operations
And as the days were sleeping by Adam thought he had one it was too late in Obama's presidency
The end the stream protection rule
Would not have
But then
At the eleventh hour
It came through
An atom stop this isn't right this is a rush job
You know the comment. On it
Was only 90 days
A 90 days may sound like a lot of time but when you're reviewing thousands of pages of material
It's not it's no time at all
And I thought about all of the stakeholders
They're affected by this it doesn't just affect mining it has effects on
Farmers and land users and all different kinds of people you know
And for the agency doesn't move forward with the rulemaking
You know just
Just a couple weeks
Before the end of administration
So yeah I mean obviously I was very disappointed to put it mildly
Disappointed because once a rule
John once a rule goes into effect
I'm doing it
Is also really hard
The guy who wrote the book on rules milk Irwin says it basically takes this long to eliminate a rule
As it does
To make it in the first place
How hard is it to undo a rule
Well I mean I think you the general consensus is that a president speaking to repeal a rule
We have to write a regulation
Not to alter or eliminate
So you go through the same process to repeal a rule or alter rule as you do to write one in the first place
So a lot of work
Blood work
Analytic time years worth of testimony
Scientific studies lobbying Congress
Securing
And Thomas is agenda instantly tied up for months
So rules
Their power really
Is inertia
Penn State football
Yeah except for one thing
Congress has a secret weapon in his Bat
No countries have noticed long ago that presidents were using this rulemaking power to their advantage
This month in Congress Heights
It's when the president gets more power
So back in the 1990s the Republican Speaker of the House Newt Gingrich
He was complaining about all these
Rules at president pass especially at the last minute
Gumming up the works forcing their will
And so
He pushed through a law
That a lot of people didn't think much about it at the time sort of
Neutron Timebomb
It's called the Congressional review Act
And it says that any rule passed can be traced within 60 Congressional days
If
The House and Senate agreed and the president signs off on
The rule will vanish
It was the time it doesn't matter because of
President
Write the rule in Congress tried to overturn it
President can just veto that
But this comes into effect when there is a new president when a rule is passed
In the very last days
Of the president's Administration
And the stream protection rule is a perfect
Target for the Congressional review Act
Chuck Nelson the guy who'd been working on the screen protection accidents
The 80s the coal miner
Said this was the first thing that went through his head when he watched Trump on television
Take the podium for his victory speech
Call Liz
Workwave Denver
Careers
John Nino
Outlet work for
United
Just go to bed with wife
Wiped away with a stroke of a pen
Wiped away with a stroke
Japan
And wiped away for good because
If a rule is overturned using the Congressional review Act
A similar rule canopy
Be put in place
Everett
But it's really rare of the 73,000 rules at
Have been issued since the
Congressional review Act
Past
It is only been used successfully
Once
On one rule
And we're going to tell you about it briefly because
This could be the Fate
Of the Stream
Is 1 unlucky rule was developed by OSHA
The occupational safety and health administration
And was pushed through by Bill Clinton
It was called
The Department of Labor organized
Program
Yes it's exciting it had to do with ergonomics and repetitive stress injury
It said if multiple employees
Complained about ergonomic conditions in the workplace
The employer had to make a change
So
I get
Carpal tunnel
Have a trackball mouse and
Wavy ergonomic keyboard
Would that have been covered
That would have been cover
Okay
Stephen Cochran helped write the ergonomics rule he is a systems engineer and he spent three years writing the rule touring
Workplaces were injuries or common places
ACME Packing plants and talking to workers and
David's has the final rule with everything included was 4000 pages long
It was one of the last rules passed by the Clinton Administration and when George W
Bush took office
Republican Congress
They went after the OSHA rule
And using the Congressional review Act
Within two months
Overturned it
It was very considered very effective after
I mean it occurs to me that you spent
Years
Getting this role together Gathering puppet
Support work
Companies
And all that was just sort of
Undone in
Like 60 days 90 days
Yep
Is it was
Looking personal review Act is like the Kryptonite for rule
How much work went into a rule
I can just disappear overnight
Never to return
And I know it sounds harsh and you people put their whole lives into some of these rules and they can
If you suddenly overturned by Congress
But we're talking about here is a much bigger issue
Which is this
Balance of power between the presidency
And
The Congress
And even fighting over this sort of thing
For decades Congress has a point which is
As the present is taking more and more power in writing rules to the change laws through rulemaking
Trying to take back power
And frankly when Congress does this uses the Congressional review act they do take a vote it is democratic
And they could be getting a lot more power in the pretty near few
There is a bill going through Congress right now called the midnight rule Relief act
Just beastly this bundle and Destroy idea
And what we do is allow Congress and President Trump
To take all the rules passed by the Obama Administration since June
And undo that
With one vote
Which could dramatically shift a lot of power back to work Congress because with one vote think of what they could do to the Obama
Administration taken take away
The offshore drilling rule Planned Parenthood rule the stream protection rule we've been talking about
It could all
Just finish
Euchre when the rules expert says
Even if it passes though he's he's not sure this will hold up
Once it's enacted if it's an active do you know it too could be challenged in court I mean you know one
The one thing you learn in Washington is nothing's ever over
Another rule in Washington ever
Everything comes around
If republicans in Congress Creek
New ability
To overturn
Presidential rules
Then someday it may be used against
It may be used by a democratic Congress to overturn Republican rules
Maybe even in Donald Trump's final
In the meantime David Cochran the man who wrote the OSHA rule that got over
Has a few words of advice for the screen protection advocates
They are biting their nails waiting to see
See what will become of their rule
He says there is a quote that he has taken great solace in and he reads it to himself
When he's feeling really low
Here let me see if
I can pull it up
Quotes okay
The only kinds of fights worth fighting are those you are going to lose
Because somebody has to fight them and lose and lose and lose until someday somebody
In order for somebody to win an important major fight a hundred years hence
A lot of other people have to be willing
For the sheer Joy fun and joy of it
To go right ahead and fight knowing
You're going to lose you mustn't feel like a martyr
You got to enjoy it
I am Stone
I have stone who's Eyestone what was he talking about
Or she
I don't know
I start with a famous investigative muckraking reporter during the
Sixties and seventies
Davidson always not actually lost because it's even though his rule got erased
He still gets calls all the time from employers and workplaces asking him to send
The old rules
Take a look at it
Use it as a reference
Auntie says ergonomics repetitive stress injuries
Went from being kind of a joke
To being something that employers take really serious
You going to have to roll
Even without the rule
Where is Worcestershire
What you think of the show you should write us
Booker Twitter or email us at Planet Money at npr.org
And if you are on the lookout for something fun to listen
We recommend wait wait don't tell me it is NPR news quiz show it is a lot of fun
You can find it on the NPR one app or wherever you get your
And last week's episode posted by Tom
Thanks
Today's show was produced by Nick Fountain Elizabeth kulas and Sallie house
We would also like to thank Joseph pisarcik and Peter Morgan
Thanks guys
I am Stacey Vanek Smith Robert Smith thanks for listening
Okay Robert so I have a list here of the rules that have been finalized in the last six
Congressional days the ones that could be overturned by the Congressional review
I'm going to list them all
US citizenship and immigration service
What is fee schedule
Standards for covered
Clearing agencies
Workforce Innovation and opportunity
Trinity Act
The revised critical infrastructure
Nerc reliability standards
Operation and certification of small unmanned aircraft
Best drones
Here come the Drone rules
Standards of performance for municipal Solid Waste
Got to love bath
Federal acquisition regulation
Fair pay and
4 places
At the workforce Innovation and opportunity
Can you react
Head Start performance standards
Migratory bird hunting regulations on certain federal Indian reservations and ceded lands
For the 2016-2017 season
Justice
And what
What's going on
Here's a short margin and capital requirements
Recovered swap
That's interesting
Transition assistance program for military personnel
Amendments to
To the commission's rules of
Practice
That how long
To write it sounds or general
This one is
Is long
Medicare program hospital inpatient prospective payment
Systems Sports
Acute care hospitals and long-term care hospital
Prospective payment system and policy changes and fiscal year 2017
Rates Quality Reporting requirements for specific providers graduate medical education Hospital notification procedures
Applicable to beneficiaries
Receiving observation services
Technical changes relating to cost organization
Medicare cost reports finalization of interim final rules
With comment. On LT
Tchp
PPS payments for severe wounds
Modifications of limitations on redesign by the Medicare Geographic classification review board and
Extensions of payments
Mdhs and low volume
Hospitals
That's