Support for this in
NPR Podcast
The following message come from The UPS Store
Offering services from shredding
To printing to mailbox
And instead of closing this Memorial Day we
May 24th and 25th
The UPS Store
Is doing another thing altogether
Opening
The UPS Store
Everything for small business
And of course shipping
This is the second part in our series on India's cash experiment
Last time we told you the story of the Mist
Serious man
Who came up with the idea of reducing India's dependence
Oncap
Today
We talked about how that idea played out in real life
India is so addictive
Did the cash the regular people keep
Piles of it in their house
Under the sink indoors with people don't use Banks
They don't have credit cards
Tasha's house
People save money little stacks
A paper
So imagine the chaos when India's prime minister Narendra Modi
Got on TV one night and said
Pretty much all the cash you have
Is worth
Is called demonetization
Modi said he was doing this to fight
Corruption
No around there is black money black money is money that's outside the Texas
Moody said you have 8 weeks
Round up all of your old cash
And trade it in at the bank for these new bills we
Adjustment
As you can imagine in the weeks afterwards they were
Giant lines
To the bank Spanish
But even six months later people were discovering old money in the bookshelf or something and freaking out
When I visited New Delhi you could see people lined up in front of the Central Bank
The deadline to change old money he passed
Months ago
And each person there had a story about why they had missed
The deadline
Lycra deep-cycle
Pretty pink here today on behalf of his mother she was sick during the money chaos
I need this official-looking paper from the doctor
And so what is it what is the paper say
Paper said that she was in a coma
She was in a coma so she could not change your money
14000 rupees
About $210 his mother's like saving
She hid in her house but she didn't tell anyone because
She was in a coma
According to the day off of work and came to the bank
His mother's case
But Bank official said
No dice
Too late the money is worthless
How does it feel to look at that money now
What is the blank paper
Hard money
Am I your mother
How do you feel about all this
Upset
Democratization caused all kinds of Chaos
Austin India businesses went bankrupt because nobody had cash to buy anything
People died of heart attacks in the long lines
Some people committed suicide
When they realize that they didn't have enough
Time to change out all their money
About half the country doesn't even use bank account
And the government had not prepared for the
They didn't make enough gnucash
So parts of India world without money
And the new caste printed
Didn't fit into the old ATMs
Is public policy goes this was a disaster
And I expected for deep to be really angry at the government for taking away his mother's life savings and for all the trouble this
Disguised
But he wasn't
What is a good weight
Really
Black money
That has to be replaced
But with the condition that it should not affect the common people
But it did
What you still like it
Even then
Pradeep was not an accept
Almost everyone I talk to in India told me the same thing
Yes it's been hard for me
Yes a lot of
People were harmed
But the government did the right thing
Which is striking I mean six months ago the prime minister of India basically Dropped a Bomb on the economy
Now pull show he's never been more popular
Somehow this whole thing
It was a hit
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Prime minister Narendra Modi said this economic shock therapy was necessary
It was the only way to solve the country's corruption problem and pull India's economy into the 21st century
Six months later we will give democratization a report card
Did it work
Support for this podcast and the following message come from rocket mortgage by Quicken Loans
When it comes to the big decision of choosing a mortgage lender
It's important to work with someone you can try who has your best interest in mind
With rocket mortgage you'll get a transparent online process that gives you the confidence you need to make any
Form decision
Skip the bank
Skip the waiting
And go completely online
Quickenloans.com money
Equal Housing lender
Licensed in all 50 states nmls consumer access. Org number 3030
When Prime Minister Modi decided to take away his
PLS cash
He said this will make
India better
The first reason was corruption
Is without cash it is harder to hide money from the tax
It is also harder to
To pay a bribe or run a black market
Criminals love cats
So take the cash away it makes our lives harder
The second reason was the modernization of the Indian economy
Businesses he said could be more competitive
Grow faster
If they use Banks and electronic payments instead of pay
The third reason was Emoji said regular people would be safer and better off if they were not keeping their life savings in a drawer
Did access to Modern financial help
Safeway Mochi made cash
India eliminated the large bills put limits on new-build
They basically let everyone figure out how to deal with this new
Society
So I went to India up six months after demonitization at
Happened to check in on these three goals to see how India was coming along
See how demonetization was working
My first stop
I went to talk to some farmer
Most of the population of India Farms little tiny plots of land there's a tractor that just pulled out
I drove out to ghaziabad it's a rural area outside of New Delhi and here Farmers work little half
Alright next
Tomatoes and celery and sugarcane
I found about a dozen Farmers all standing together under a giant figure
In the middle of all the field
My name is us a preemie
My age is 93
Sources he and his friends meet here every morning and every
That my friend
Should you discuss
Everything
Really
You sit here many evening
What do you talk about
About relationship
Sometimes boring.
Relationships and politics
Things are hard
The farmers don't have much land across they raise barely cover lyrics
And everything all of the business here
All done Inc
After Prime Minister Modi said a lot of that cash will be worthless in those first few weeks
Farmers had a tough decision to make I mean obviously they had to work that depend to their field
The best way to do something about their life savings
In case it was about to be rendered worthless
Virender sodhi one of the farmer
3%
He and all the pharmacy new had to leave the fields and go get in line
There was some people who suffered a lot
Gilbert cues
Since morning 6:05 till 9:10
There are people animals
So many poor people
And these are people who cannot afford to miss a day's wages
Daniel I'm totally panic
And nobody had money to buy anything
Farmers couldn't sell the crops
But small farmers also suffer
70 trucks
Soft tomato
Phone on the road
My farmers
Because of this monetization
Mobile
No buyers
And it's not like farmers can just be patient and wait it out they have to harvest the food when it's ready
And when there were no buyers they just
How to destroy their crops
During this time pharmacist sales of produce
Drop in half
I almost feel like the government wanted to
The punished people
For using cash it was such a pain
For every one of those first few weeks
It almost seems like they're trying to send a message that the Hey look
Like you would be way better off if you just use thanks
You just had a credit
But after the lions at the banks got shorter all the farmers I talk to just went back to using cash
Michael Henderson
Gross greens and onions and
Bee stings
Yeah Bangalore
08 Lance doo doo doo
You better
You look away asthma
Yes it's a little guy
And through a translator harinder told me that he is just too old to start trying to pay for things in a new way
SM Naga Naga Somalia
Go to something I understand
So I would rather deal with cash
I don't understand these other things
So I'm happy with you
Twitter said to him credit cards dangerous
Like someone could steal the number and use it
Was exactly sure how they worked and it
He wants to stick
So we're going to try and
Grade how Modi has done on his
Answer one of the reasons for demonitization was to improve
The lot of
Regular people in India to improve the lot of farmers
I'm going to call this grade and incomplete
Because it's
Seems like
Things were very bad
And then when
Back to normal mostly
People still using cash
Write nothing really changed the government has claimed that Millions
The people open bank account
In rural areas
From everything that I've seen and read
Incomplete
Okay next stop
The suburbs of New Delhi
We're actually not too far from the fields you can actually see a lot of the high-rises from the egg
And when you drive through them it's really striking
Because it's the obvious like nice kind of high-rise buildings and all vacant building
Building to see these buildings because they have become like a symbol of corruption
Man in India
One of the main reasons modk for tomatoes
Station was to fight corruption
Black money
@booty and his advisers felt like corruption was siphoning off
The economics
Success
Now there are a lot of ways to hide cash in Indy
But these apartment buildings
This is where most of the black money in India was store
Real estate courses the big gorilla
Uncle St Lucia is the author of the making
He says in fact high-rises like these are where most of the black money in India
Store
Something like 25%
Of the countries GDP
So you want to buy an apartment
And the price is $125,000
Well officially you only pay a hundred thousand
The extra 25000
You slip to the owner
In cash
He talks about it doesn't get
So is the owner you get $25,000 in untaxed money under
Table which is great
And as the buyer you count on being able to
To do that same thing when you sell your
But when Moody ruled out his demonetization plan
The whole system
Kind of shutdown
I am stuck
If you were sitting with an inventory of cash that becomes exposed
And suddenly that black money has disappeared because now you can transact at the house at the high tomorrow
You will find that the builders are willing to offer anywhere between 10 to 30 40% discount
That's a lot that's a lot
Router table
Shock for people who are hiding or putting away the black money in some of these please
I'm delicious India's hole real estate market is Frozen
No one is buying or selling anything
Which sounds really bad
I mean it is bad for the economy although from the government's but if you I can see how they might consider this a success
Eunos warning this big pool of
A black money and eventually prices will adjust and things will return
That's normal but without the hole
That is true but it is still hard to know whether the actual goal of getting rid of corruption in India has been sick
Successful
I need the government was hoping that tax evaders and criminals would be stuck with these huge
Stacks of cash
But they wouldn't have time to
To turn in
Or when they turn them in the bank would suddenly see that they had all the
Cash that they hadn't been taxed on that crime does not
He would learn the crime does not pay
But Bhaskar chakravorti and Economist at Tufts University even after all that drama almost all of
The cash in circulation in India
Still made its way back
To the banking system
Not all of that was legal cash it just happened to be the case that India has is extremely innovator
And getting around pinstripe
Innovative
Princeton's I talked to one Banker who told me that he seen a bunch of his colleagues at the bank taking huge amounts of cash from
Rich clients and
Changing it into new bills for a little
There are also stories of Rich families
Asking their maids and drivers and Cooks
To stand in line for them and change out there
So give me a grade 2 mod
Corruption goal
Needs improvement improvement is what I would say
Yeah but still specials right and that's not terrible for
Not that it is a long-term problem
Our next and final stop
Is a market
In the city of New Delhi where we will meet people who actually are making the best
Of a capitalist economy
After this
Support for Planet Money and the following message come from ishares
Because the best
Preparation for tomorrow
Is building for your future today
Ishares by BlackRock
Inspire to build
For my final stop I wanted to see how things had changed for the urban middle-class
In India remember Modi believe that getting rid of large amounts of
The cash would help India move into the 20
Businesses he said could be more competitive
And grow faster using Banks and electronic
So I went right into the heart of New Delhi to this Market
To see what people there with
Rowenta bhardwaj is 66 and he owns a pharmacy stall in the park
I'm letting my family shopping in the last 35 years
Do you have a lot of prescriptions I'm seeing all the way
Electric ceiling
This Market was in the very middle class
It wasn't nice Market but even still almost all of the businesses had only taken cash
Including or whether he was a cash man he didn't like credit cards didn't really understand how
Mobile payments were totally out of the question
But then demonetization happened and in the weeks afterwards going to ruin his customers still needed their first
Medicine and cash was no longer an option
Sober Wyndham made himself figure it out
He started taking credit cards and he even signed up for this mobile payment service called paytm where people could pay for their prescriptions
On their mobile phone
Has it been good for business to take the cards
Is it very good for business
Now it's 6 months later about half of her Windows customers
Pay with paytm or credit card
And he said that you can buy a little bit more than that
Buy credit card
By Paytm by debit card by check
When did that checks his deposits on his phone
You no longer have to walk to the bank
With cash deposit
Everyday and he loves this he's become such a convert then in fact he has stopped using cash himself
My bus now
All credit card
Oh you don't use cash no no no no no no
Most of the stores in the market now take credit cards
All the stores in the market take mobile payments from this company called paytm everywhere I went in India
Was talking about
Paytm and how big they've gotten since tamada today
So I thought I would go check out the company paytm for BTM
Monetization was like the greatest gift ever
Because when the government got rid of most of the
The cash in the country
It really offer an alternate
Medora is the CFO of
How do you say Gwen Mooney Mages announcement the company new
This was their moment
Then we should jump into action
So we have front page ads
In the next day's newspaper
Pigeon wasn't exactly a household name
It's a lot of the ads were just like hey we are here you can pay for stuff with
Other ads with these kind of DIY instructions to businesses and employers
Basically explaining as simply and clearly as possible
How to use the paytm phone app how mobile payments work
One of the eyes that you did was quite proud off
A quarter of that bed.
The merchant who literally cut the character of that ad
I just put that up
I just put in their name and their mobile number
That they put on the wall
What's their name and their mobile number was on the wall customers could use that information to pay them through the paytm app
And businesses were desperate to do this they were all signing up little roadside vegetable stands hardware stores taxis
Even temples started letting people leave offerings with
Paytm
I know India is a big
Country but
The growth rate for KTM
Was seeing
Was pretty amazing half a million people were signing up everyday
120 million Indians now use page
I believe government this is also good news
Because unlike cash
ATM transactions are trackable they are taxable
Between the credit cards and the mobile app seems like this whole unseen part of the economy
What's up me out in the light
So if you look specific
Get the part of the Indian economy that was sort of on
The Verge
Of
Move away from cash anyway if you look at them the people were talking about here
When I give the grade
Satisfied
Satisfactory for sure
And if we talk about the beginning
Moody does deserve
Some extra credit because
I got to say I've never seen a political official
Who changed the economy overnight
And
People still
Approved
People still forgave him for what he
And it wasn't just a question of forgiveness
This milk actually made Modi
More popular
His approval ratings are now at 69%
Justin credible for a politician
And almost everyone I talk to in India supported modi's demonetization plan
Even people who really suffered
Actually especially
Would really suffered.
And when I asked him why a lot of them told me that they stand in long lines all the
The time and deal with frustrating bureaucracy all the
All the sudden that they're standing in line
For a reason
Just work corruption
Spanish Taxi
All them standing in line and going through all this bureaucracy
How to patriotic Purp
You know this explains
A lot what I was listening to the last episode with
Which was about Anil bokil
The architect
He had
This strange moment with you when he was talking about demonitization
In almost
Religious
Is it exciting to watch it play out in real life
If you don't refrigerate
I want joy
In excitement
You call it enlightened
I'm in line
Your lighting
And now I kind of understand it Enlightenment means
Finding side of a greater meaning and purpose
In even the difficult things in life
And that's essentially
What Indians doing right now
Yes and I've heard this from a lot of
People including her deep-set go to the man whose mother lost her life savings
Because she went into a coma at the wrong moment
He was standing there with his mother's worthless cash and
His hand
You said he was just so fed up and so frustrated with all the corruption in his car
Finally felt like things were changing
Like booty was fixing
I asked him what he was going to do with all the old bills that had belonged
With Mom
Baby arriving today frame
1080p snow desert 500
You frame it
Maybe
But my next next generation
Oh so that your family can see what the old
Just for the sake of showing the p
Like
Here it is
Here is a token of a sacrifice we all made
For the country
Do we all made to make a stronger India
We love to hear what you think of the show you can email us play
Planet Money at npr.org
Or find us on Facebook or Twitter
Also this week marks
30 years
Send Terry Gross started the NPR program fresh air
We're celebrating by sharing our favorite interviews
And moments using the hashtag fresh air 30
You can find the fresh air archives and new episodes on NPR one
Or wherever you get
Your podcast those of us who asked questions for a living
Are still in odd Terry Gross
Today's episode was produced by Elizabeth
The coolest planet money is edited by Brian torch set and produced by Alex
I'm Robert Smith
And I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Thanks for listening