Support for this in
NPR Podcast
The following message
Come from the UPS
Offering services from shredding
To printing to mailbox
And instead of closing this Memorial Day we
May 24th and 20
The UPS Store
He's doing another thing
All together
Opening
The UPS Store
Everything for small business
And of course shipping
Google
Mantis
Shrimp two words
Mantis like
Insect shrimp like a cocktail
Shrimp
I'm going over to images
Holy moly
What are you saying oh my god when it's like the color of a rainbow is that right
Yes I don't want it looks like a
It looks like a lobster at gay pride Ma
Right
When I first thought I was like
This thing belongs
CC with SpongeBob
I would have to deal with any men off and elephant are they are the hosts of a new podcast called undiscovered it
The story behind Thanksgiving
Discoveries
Any specially wanted
Oscar Planet Money to see this
Crazy video of the Manta
Right there actually many crazy videos of the mantis shrimp
What's a good one any
I recommend shrimp versus
Is crab is always a crowd-pleaser shrimp vs. clam close follow-up I'm guessing I should put my money on the shrimp
Shrimp vs. crab
See what comes up there
Looks like it's in an aquarium
Shrimp and crab leg staring at each other
NN wow back in the sky into a corner
Oh I think
This is
Arm looking at a little Club coming out of the head of the shrimp
Smashing crab over and over again
God
This is a badass
Sea creature
It is indeed and you are not alone if you look at the view count
Over there
They can pack over 300 lb
The force in that
Smash
People keep these mantis shrimp in in reinforced aquarium cuz they can actually smashed
The glass open
But this is not just for funsies this is not why we are here at Planet Money today because of a scientist named Sheila
And she studies
These mantis shrimp for her job
And specifically this
Heart of the mantis shrimp called
Hammer part of the arm
Club that you saw
So that hammer moves at the
Acceleration of a bullet bursting out of
Accelerations this fast at this
Scale underwater human Engineers have not been
She was researching gotten money from the Department of
Defense from the National Science Foundation
And then in 2015 something happened
A US senator
Decided that she was research
Was a waste
Of taxpayer money
Which is why you brought the story
To us here at Planet Money the rest of this episode is adapted from the latest episode of your podcast undiscovered so
Juilliard
Hello and welcome to Planet Money
I'm elevator and I'm in today on the show The Story of a scientist
And her Badass rap
There is an extremely awkward science fair Star Wars puns Galore
End of the fiscal helper nation and the future of knowledge at stake
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Sheila paddocks troubles started in December of
It was my birthday weekend
She was a biologist she has a lab at Duke
And she was at the lab answering some emails before heading home for the weekend
When she gets this one
That had and they had her Good Morning America ABC News
Query
An ABC news reporter was emailing Shelia to get her reaction
How did Sheila feel about her work being put
In a waste book
Facebook or or sometimes it's called the waste report on oversight
Fortnite lots of name
It's a document that a member of Congress puts out
Basically
Big list of projects funded with Federal money
That this Congress person thinks didn't deserve that money
And according to this ABC news reporter
This is what had happened to Sheila
A US senator
Had learned about her shrimp
Decided this was a waste of federal money
I'm put it in his ways
When I read that email I have to say my
Stomach sore
Fell through the floor
Because she knew it was coming
You will not believe what your government is wasting your tax dollars
100 examples of government
Duke University got the money to actually pick shrimp against each other
$707,000 stuff you can't make it up
The study that landed Sheila in the waist
It was actually buy one of her grads do
Do mantis shrimp they have this arm that ended up a rounded hammer
And they use this to smash open snail shells this is what they eat snails
And it's Hammer that used to crack open the shells
The other thing that the shrimp do with these hammers
Is whale on each other
And so she looks grad student want to know what is going on in the strip fight
Shrimp are using those hammers to repeatedly bash each other on a super strong
Armored tail plate
The trampolines the most hits
Which raises some interesting questions like
What is this armor tale play
Made out of
How is it that its enduring so many hits without being
It's just pretty cool engineering out
The waste book
However
It's not exactly described
The study like this
This year we have a shrimp Fight Club Fight Club Duke University gets money to actually pitch
Shrimp against each other
That is Senator Jeff Flake on Fox news on the record
Jeff Flake is a Republican senator from Arizona
And he's the one who put Sheila's Research into his 2015 waste book
A list of the most wasteful uses of taxpayer money that year
And so you know Senator flake's office declined our request for an interview both with the senator and a senior staff member
Jeff Flake is a fiscal conservative
He's a crusader against Congressional earmarking which is another practice of sneaking goodies into the budget for your constituent
He is Frugal and very proud of that fact
And he loves
Puns
Which are all over the wait book
Fake Facebook
Is straight-up campy in 2015 the full title was
The waste book
The farce awakens
Okay the Star Wars reboot was just about to come out and end the whole report is Star Wars themed hair is Jeff
Flake introducing his Facebook
On the senate floor
It's my hope my only hope that
Shreveport gives Congress
Something to chew on
Chewy
Chewbacca
For a debt and deficit saddles taxpayers
And they finally Strike Back
The cover of the ways book it features a cartoon of Lake
Wielding the lightsaber with Richie is presumably ready to lay the fat from the federal budget
Flip to page 78
And you will find a full three page write-up
Oh She Glows shrimp Fight Club
Plus a price tag
707000 taxpayer dollars
So one of the things I've noticed about the waste books
If there's kind of just like there's a lot of jokes
That's Brian Burkey former Congressional staffer
The point of this kind of
It's written from the senator right though
Showing the personalities little bit
Brian Burkey did not help write Jeff Flake wastebook but he's helped write other ways
Reports for Senator Tom Coburn and James Lankford
Goshen Bryan's home state of Oklahoma
This is Brian's executive director of
Store accountability
A nonprofit that educates young people about the Nash
Points out it is not just science pending that gets criticized
Netflix the force awakens science projects are about a quarter of the
Brian said yes the government
She totally fun science
We don't come
To that from the perspective that don't understand
Yeah the importance of basic science research
Money is being spent in the wrong
A few years ago the NIH director said
Maybe we'd have an Ebola vaccine right now if it weren't for all of those
Budget cuts
So Brian says
Okay
Not enough money for Ebola
But we have money for the stuff in the waste book
And it's not
Pit one against the other necessarily but that's
Kind of congress's job right
Budgeting is our job resources are limited
20 trillion-dollar national debt
Somebody's project Heidi behind the veil
Call Santa
Science is just
You know
We just don't agree with that
And this is basically the message that Senator Jeff Flake
6abc in December 25th
When he released his
A lot of those studies are very legitimate and useful
But a good number of them to think who would the world thought up this stuff
But somebody's got to okay this who's the person that's saying okay to the stuff who's writing the check
Great question
From Greta Van Susteren she was a Fox anchor at the time
Who is writing the checks
Where does your lab
Get money
Yeah so I'll walk you through this process
She'll pay for this so-called shrimp Fight Club
With money from the National Science Foundation
It's not easy to get these grants and Sheila's filled about 90% of proposals get rejected
But she like gets a grant she gets about $900,000 to be distributed over five
Certificate
Frites
Except now she has to knock off $400,000
If roughly
$400,000 which is going to chill at University for overhead or lab building her utilities
Now she's got about $500,000 left which works out to buy by 5.
Divided by 5 years a hundred thousand dollars a year
That goes to pay a postdoc grad student pay for everybody's Conference travel summer program that brings grade school
Teachers tissues lab Fight Club
Yeah how much was that
What I can tell you it doesn't it's in the order
Only a couple thousand dollars if that much
This is one of the things that really are Chihuahua about the waste bucket made it sound like she spent hundreds of thousands of.
Dollars on just one study on this
Shrimp Fight Club when instead she spend it on multiple totally different studies on training young scientist and mentor
Preschool teachers and so sitting there at her desk
On her birthday weekend she had a choice to make
Ignore the wastebook wait for the new cycle to move on
But she didn't
She did not want to slink away
Like a mantis shrimp who just lost a fight
A barrel of mantis shrimp
She decided to fire back
At Senator flake Strike Back
Make the case for why mantis shrimp matter and then
It becomes something constructive
Not that miserable Sinking Feeling we have to hide
Feeling like
Man what is up with politics
Why am I the focus of this now
It's just so stupid at some level
But I felt like
I deserve to have it I have a chance to
Explain why what we do is important
For the broader goal of explaining why science is important
To the world
And then she got her chance
Sheila got another email
An invitation
To washing
Which Sheila come to Capitol Hill
Is that her real
Can members of Congress
Coming up
The Tempest
Weirdest science fair you've ever attended as so-called spendthrift scientists meet Congress
The Brick
Support for this NPR Podcast and the following message come from betterman
The largest independent online financial advisor for a limited time you can get up to six months manage for
Free with your first deposit
Learn more at betterment.com
Planet Money
Okay
The trip to DC
3 months after her research showed up and Senators like sway
Facebook
Sheila Patek on an invitation
His her reception
I2 science advocate
Sea grapes
Any idea what's researchers have been singled out
In these way surfboards
Go to the hill
They would set up in the Senate Office Building
And Congress people would drop by
And the scientist would explain the value of their work
If we make the case that the wastebook got them wrong
So in April 2016 Sheila's standing in this
Beautiful Marble Room
In front of a poster about man
And she surrounded by all these
So-called pilfers of the public person a few feet away there's the scientist to put monkeys in hamster balls on treadmill
Also the public health researcher who inspired this headline
That's wonder why fat girls can get
Another Sheila
You know one thing that we heard a lot was please do not get mad at the people who show up
Flake wasn't the only politician on the invite list
In the last decade waste books of taking off in DC
Is a handle a congressman
Grinnell publish their own takes on the waste report
Slightly different spins
Senator James Lankford has his
Federal fumbles
John McCain has America's most wasted
Rand paul the waste report
Steve Russell waste watch
All have been invited
All of them
You might have noticed a Republican
But that wasn't always the case
The guy who's
Footsteps always book writers follow
The Founding Father of the waste book
Who's a Democrat
Senator William proxmire from wisco
Proxmire is someone who isn't afraid to take strong stances he is an early advocate of
Finance reform
He was a very early critic of the Vietnam War
That's my story and Melinda Baldwin she's written about proxmire and early signs
He's also a diet and drugging in
Melinda says one time during this debate about whether or not the Senate
Get approved funds
New gym
Proxmire gets up and he says that's a waste of taxpayer money
None of you need a gym
You should all learn to jog and I will teach you how
Pressler actually had a book about jogging
You can do it
!
Senator proxmire exercise diet and relaxation plan
But that moment I think it was very much in in proxmire is Grand tradition because the other thing that is really famous for
Is being an aggressive critic
Of government spending
Proxmire
Hated
You wanted to root it out
Aa1975
He hits on a brilliant idea
The Golden Fleece award
The Golden Fleece Awards work
Like that every month
Proxmire will award a prize
Imagine prizoniera quotes here because if it's not a prize it's a Badge Of Dishonor
Apprised to the most egregious use of taxpayer money
Any prizes get at
The press releases
How funny
They're funny and the little mean
Genus of flakes
A stock that is classic proxmire
I'm proxmire
Goes after science Melinda says it's not that proxmire was against
Government funding of science per se
It's just that he didn't
Want to fun stuff it seemed like it would never
Payoff
And ask Melinda
We've been doing this week's report thing for
For decades
How's the argument change
We just
Dancing the same dance
I think it's kind of the same dance I think that it in a way we're all still dancing to prox Myers tune
So she looks come all the way up to DC for this
Incredibly awkward science fair
And she wants to make the case
Senator flake for why
Mantis shrimp matter
And here she has this chance to
Break out of the stands
That we bought them stuff
Affliction
She was told somebody from his office would show up
I was expecting
You know some kind of staffer
The Intern
Yeah then turn right
And so I'm sitting there talking to somebody and I look up towards the entrance and I see Senator flake who's actually
Quite a distinctive looking person Senator flake
Tall
Pan
Beaming smile
And I and I almost passed out I freak
Ouch
And I'm like
I'm trying to get myself back to the president to talking to the person who is presenting to
And I see him
Slowly weaving his way towards me
Tell ya so gradually he made his way to my station
What do you say like what happened
Well he came up and
Was very polite
And I said you know may I present to you
No work and he said
Ensure
And here's what she was told her
Shrimpy's
Fight Club mantis shrimp
Bear claw bring us when it comes to engineering
Are performing our best systems by orders of magnitude
I started by just showing him
What engineering is not doing today
Violet has been doing 4 million
Interferes
Shrimp
The wielder hammers acceleration
On par with a bullet
Coming out of a gun
Accelerations that out
Missiles and race cars
And they don't use combustion
Justice system of
Springs and latches in their arm
Assistant that they deploy
Over
Over and over without it
Breaking
And they do this in water
A tiny scale but human Engineers can't replicate
Before example mantis shrimp can open the snail shells
With such tiny hammer
Said they weigh about the mass of
Tattoo toothpick
And they can hit one of these snails that we have to use a hammer
And they can break them
And then she really sells it
She explains what this could do
For humans
She explained
Mantis shrimp
Even though they're wielding their deadly hammers at bullet like
Accelerations
Avoid this weird fluid dynamics thing called cavity
Usually when you're moving as fast
What does a mantis shrimp does underwater
You create the
Area of Low Pro
And the water literally vaporizes in that spot it forms a little bubble called the cavity
And this bubble
Implode
In a burst of light creating heat equivalent to
To the surface of the
The Sun
Habitation will wear away the steel on a boat
Color
It's the bane of Naval engineers
Mantis shrimp avoided
Until the final moment when their Hammer hits that snail shell
Michelle crack
In a burst of heat and light
How do they do it
Or take that the tail plate that these shrimp use in fights
This template is taking blows like a punching bag over and over
But I like a punching bag
Light
And that's why Engineers have been using Sheila's research
To help him develop materials to make better Sports helmets in better armor
And I have to say
I guess we all know this
That a lot of times it really helps
To have a conversation face to face
I mean I think we all know that but it's good to be reminded
Yoshi real I really felt like he was listening or else he was a good Faker but I think it was listening
Sushi Legos for it
And I said you is any of this worthwhile to you
Any pointed to the part of her poster about human applications
And he said that that seemed worthwhile to him
But here's the thing
Senator flake
He wants these human application
But if he wants this
Particular human application this bio-inspired armor
You only get that if you gamble in the first place that investigating animals as weird as the mantis shrimp
Might pay off
And the government makes these gambles all the time
The federal government spends about 34
Billion dollars a year on basic research
So it is totally fair to ask
What kind of return are we getting on that investment like
What is the number
I think it would be very dangerous for Economist to tell you that there's a number
That is Paula Stephan
Professor of Economics at Georgia
State University
Who could not give us a number
I was like look
You want to rate of return
You've got to know what the benefits are
And you also have to know what the cost
Time for something like a stock market investment that's
Too hard to figure out
But figuring that out for science
Good luck
I mean the perfect example that everyone in my field brings up
Is the atomic clock
In 1879
A guy named Lord Kelvin rights that maybe we could use Adams
Tell time
But it takes about seven decades before a physicist named Robbie
Actually figures out how to do it
And Wallah
You know most people I think who turn on their GPS device
Don't have a clue that we would not have GPS
If it weren't for the atomic clock
This becomes a problem because if we want to calculate
How much money went into the invention of GPS like a truly transformative technology do I have to go
All the way back to Lord Kelvin
And that's just the cost side of the equation write how do you calculate the benefit
Because sometimes investments in science they
Payoff
What's PayPal
Really big
Like they did with the MRI
And the laser
And oh yeah the internet
And yeah you can try to put a number on those benefits people have tried to calculate the economic value of the internet
The problem though with those studies is that they've just been selected on winners
No
And there
A number of research projects out there that don't have a
Happy Ever After ending
So to speak
But if you ask Sheila by her work is important
Doesn't talk to you about the economics
Not the kind of payoff
She talking about
The knowledge
That we generate in my lab
Is why it's important
It's that we have
Explored biology we have tested it we have we have put it to the most rigorous scientific
Analysis that we possibly can
And from that we've been able to say new things about the world
And that
Is what I think the value of what I do is
A month after their conversation
Senator Flake released another waste
It's science beans
20 questions
Government studies that will leave you scratching your head
The cover features the latest poster children of wasteful science spending
No boxing shrimp
But there's a drunk song bird and
Sexy goldfish
But inside
The Raiders do something interesting
Table list
20 questions that they hope will guide science funding
Decisions
Questions designed to get it what the value of
Science is
Will this research Advanced science in a meaningful way
Will the study enhance technology
Advanced medicine will it expand our understanding of the universe
They're good questions
They're continuing the conversation
And then
You flip the page
And you read about how one researcher spent part of a $1000000 grant
To find out where it hurts most to get stung by a bee
And another round of the dance begin
That was a Nina and Ella Fetter their podcast is undiscovered
The folks behind the radio show Science Friday check it out undiscovered podcast. Org
Or wherever you find podcasts
If there's another podcast out there you think we should adapt something that most your friends never heard of
Let us know on Facebook or Twitter we are Planet Money
Our email is Planet Money at npr.org
Thanks for listening