You know when you walk into a grocery store and you see that beautiful produce section
All those lettuces
Tangelos and stalks of celery
Those did not arrive at the
Stop & Shop
My magic they did not drop out of the sky
At some point
The farmers
Distributors and the buyers
All got together
Perhaps
Add a giant Convention Center
Where everyone is looking for the next big thing
Today
The New York produce show and conference is now open
I'm here with Nick fountain in this place is
Chest
Amazing it'll blow your mind there are mountains of
Onions in
Potatoes
IC wine IC hummus IC guacamole basically if you can grow it over to give
The California Radicchio any props if you can process
Flaxseed if you can truck it lasted into nutrients or if you can put it into some sort of container
Play crushed chili flakes you are here at the New York produce show
Anyone who's anyone in fruits or vegetables or supermarkets or distribution is here
Today hello welcome to Planet Money on Robert Smith and I'm Nick Fountain and today on the show we have gathered together to find this reporters
Turn all the land of Planet Money Team Iron Chef
In that everyone is going to get a particular assignment and they have to go find that story so we're going to start with Kenny Malone what is the
Next superfood the next kale goji berries
I have no idea
A difficult year
Elsa training every conference has a rock star that everyone wants to meet
Find the Beyonce of the prodiscover Beyonce all right
Support for this podcast in the following message come from the Annie E Casey
Sea Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org
Guacamole
Okay we have the Planet Money Team out scouring the produce show
4 stories
It will amaze
Until light
They're looking for the hot veggie the
The cool fruit
Are senior producer
He's doing an expose on food waste
Producer Sally Helm
Trying out new food technology
And then we have
The Planet Money intern
Alice Wong
As an internet we do pay you but as an intern you're always interested in free food so
Your assignment is to find all of the things that they are giving away free samples
At this Festival
And two people list
I've been training for this
My whole life
To all the reporters when off
Finish their assignments and after the show is over
They came back to me
To check in
And tell me what they found.
Elsa Chang hello looking for
The Big Kahuna The Rock
Star
Of the
Show
And give me the lay of the land like what what is that
What is CF
The produce show is Booth after
And sitting in these boots
Waiting to be noticed
Are the Growers the distributor
Where's the manufacturer
These products roaming freely and deciding which Booth to pay a visit to
Are the buyers and those are the big guys in
In the show these are the Walmart the cost
The ShopRite
And they decide ultimately
Which produce
From these boots
Are going to end up in the customer
Pants
And you can say
Bobby's buyer's right away because they're wearing shiny red ribbons on their name tags
It's a buyer and a lot of them travel
Entourage
You're surrounded by people
Hi my name is Tony Stallone
Tony Stallone like Sylvester Stallone
He keeps claiming there is so I don't know I haven't had a check that out yet
Truthfully it is a second cousin twice
Oh my God you really
Tony Salone is the produce buyer for
They do a lot of grocery delivery
Has been in the produce business for more than a hundred years
It's in my DNA
You standing next to this food displaying is gorgeous tomatoes and he's like
He's Brooklyn he tell me exactly how you have to store tomatoes
To keep them the freshest
Image of the guy who have been examining Tomatoes since he was 5 years old so when I walk down
I'll take I just get overwhelmed
What is
Tony's
Strategy what is he looking for exactly
Well Tony has a line his strategy is
What the show come to me what do you mean by that is he's letting the show show him
The hottest ladies
He has another line
People don't buy products now
I'll pay by solution Tony Stallone has a lot of life
We have a lot of
Add another line he had is millennial
That is a problem
That he needs to find a solution for
So what tone is
Looking for a fish
How to deliver
Precious
Most ready to eat
Eat produce
Two millennia
Also they can eat
It right away
And the two items he's focused on right now
Are berries
An avocado
Because Tony is convinced
State of a grocer can keep their berries and avocados beautiful and ripe
The customer is going to buy the rest of their produce
At that store
That is 100% true that is how I live my life like little guy walk into a store because I see raspberries and avocados
Gatto's out front and they look pretty
Berries in avocados
Fun watching the show and it said enjoyed watching because everybody knows him and he knows everybody
Any glass into this booth with you
Avocado guys
Westpac
They are like the Ava
Avocado
They have mastered the complicated
It's science
Getting every avocado tree
Zack rightness that eats
Customer
Are they having like this complicated science
Discussion
Annie's thinking
He wants to do a deal with
And that moment
Robert
I noticed something
Because Tony Stallone is in that booth
Other people start
Looking at this
They start checking out
Avocado
Because Tony Stallone is just standing there it's like he's annointed this booth
Which is Magic
Eventually says
Give me a call
Kind of walks up apparently he's really excited about some new Way cauliflowers Package
Complex about to get the magic
Thanks
You're welcome
Roberts I say you are looking trim and and fit
And healthier thank you which
Is natural because your assignment was to find
The new
SuperFood
Every year there's some sort of super food
Pomegranate kale the goji berry
Something that will
Reverse the ravages of
Time and
Allow you to live forever
And Ice I have found it
Headed over
No
The journey
Okay go ahead
I'll be back I got the assignment
Walk away and it Dawns on me
I don't know what a superfood is
Superfood corn is good brussel sprouts cherries I have no idea
It's not a scientific category
It is a marketing tool
How's it going
One of my first stops
Was the place that claims to have
The original
Superfruit a pom wonderful
This is a pomegranate juice that was super popular
510 years ago
So what's up to this booth
Nice a well
Why don't you interview the Press
She happens to be right here are either present if I'm wonderful everybody who's anybody
New York produce show you can just talk to them
Elizabeth Stevenson
Explains that
About 15 years ago
Pom wonderful with having trouble getting America to fall in love with a pomegranate
Community tap
Felicidades Giant
Until they decide
Let's just make it a juice
And then we can get people to try easy
But we're not going to put it with the other two
We're going to put it in the refrigerated section
With the produce
Super healthy a year-and-a-half later they say pom juice
Switch everywhere
We still defined that super premium juice category and that you find in the photo
So
At the show like who is the next
Public art to this tells me what I should be looking for in the next race super
Number one
It needs to be juicy ball so people can try it for the first time
Okay number to it helps to be kind of an unknown fruit because then it's
Feels like we're discovering some
Ancient seek
Something in the number 3
It has to be healthy
But you shouldn't make
Too many specific Health claims
Is pom wonderful
Trouble for doing that a while ago and so it's best to look for a food that you can just say
Has the antibiotics
We've got the antitoxin
Superfood super
Announcer
With a purpose
Dragon fruit that's not quite right at sea
Star fruit and starfruit
The weirdest interesting little things called the gooseberries Regional Park
And I guess it doesn't really taste like a tomato it feels like it's me and Robert I don't know if you remember this but you totally
Interrupted my Gooseberry experience
What's a gooseberry
Super name meaning of super
Tell me about
The last stop on the
I found it and I'll just
Cut the chase
I'm going to give it to you okay okay
Dodge
Coffee
Fruit juice
No
That's not a thing
Is coffee fruit
Wait what is it
Is it like
Is it high in antioxidants
What is this is it usable
Yes really
Fairies
Come
Coffee beans are
Coffee beans
Are the pit of Cheerio coffee cherry
Yes I in the outside the fleshy part people called the
Cascara fruit
And a lot of companies
Take the bean and throw away the Shaolin
The fruit
What now
There are companies that are
Keeping that in
You can try it up you can make it in
T you could
Make it into a juice will keep me awake is this a coffee substitute yeah we thought we knew what a soup
But this one has caffeine
It is a super super fruit is so awesome have you tasted it how does it taste I did taste
I mean kind of sour it's a little bit like cranberry juice a little bit like
Pom wonderful actually it's a portion of that juices coffee
Cockatrice apparently actually very bitter
So they cut it with some pineapple juice or some other juice
And that's how they make it drinkable
Pineapple juice is basic
Listen to the task was not to find a sugar-free drink
But you asked me for super
And you got it you got juice you got antioxidants
You can stay young forever
We came back to claim with the science but
There you go
Article Mark remind me of your Simon
Waste
I got super into it right away
And when you walk here at a show that's all about freshness
And ripeness and bounty
And you start asking about
Rotting
Garbage like people do not like to talk about ways
The Banana Man
He just said
First we take what I learned that like big picture
30 to 40% of the American food supply is wasted
Every year
Throw it up
Maybe that the cow's butt
Basically
Left in the ground for ghost
And the big reason that I heard for this was
Looks
People just don't like
In America to eat ugly food
I will go through a hundred bananas
To find the right one
And so we're fuzzy were superficial
And there was this
Thing that I started to hear
Yeah we say I II appeals by a peel
No in our industry
You know if you look at what's on the Shelf if it looks pretty
And it's got great color
Well it must be good
That Peak Krieger from boo 338
Robinson fresh a giant company like one of the
The top 5 produce producers in a
So wasted because people don't like ugly
Products then the answer would be
To somehow
Make things look
Prettier
On the Shelf
No it's actually the Opera
It's to make American consumers
Look into their soul and treat fruits like they would like to treat people
And value them for what's on the inside not on the outs
It didn't work so well with people how's that going to work with fruit
They're leading in heart they have made an entire line of products called
Misfits of just owning it
So like the Cucumber that has a yellow stripe on it or the grapes that are too small
They take them out and put them in a bag they put the word
Misfits on it and then they sell it at a discount
And other companies are doing something pretty similar like pairs that were too small before now they just called them kids size and
Put it in an adorable bag watch for free
Kansai pass
So I thought
Okay
The produce industry has figured out the waste problem
And then I had to
Totally
We White
Cuz I met someone from our tribe
Turn on Brad record an associate professor and the applied economics and management school at Cornell University
I love their hiding everywhere
What is an economist a food waste Atkins he's like the perfect man just walking around the produce show
It's so Brad says yeah ugly food that is a problem
But he says there's a way bigger prop
The biggest place where food is wasted is in our kitchen
And he says that's because
Who has gotten so cheap relative to everything else
That people will buy food
Just to make sure it doesn't run out without even planning to eat
We buy too much
He does he surveys
In the store where people are making the decisions to buy food and what he's found is that we approach buying food with a different logic
Define others
Unlike many other things we buy
People
In the back of their mind
Already know that they're going to waste
A lot of food they just know that some percentage of the food that they buy or some percentage of
This food that they have in their household
Will be wasted a bunch of stuff think I'm going to cook all weekend
And then we'll go out to rest
And then Your Spinach Withers up and get small and will
It's liquid
So the way he sees it is it just
Kind of rational
To waste food
Wow
Wait for the economist like
Depressing song
Welcome to Planet Money makes Alex
Oh no way
No way
Alice
Welder Arc
Our intern has
That this is all the free stuff you picked up at the shop
Believable
Your task
Was
To go get free samples it so I imagine you eating like a a few chips and a few slices of Apple
You've you've taken everything from the show I'm misunderstood my assignment
I thought it was good as many free items
They really embrace.
So
There are entire vegetable
Skier
What is that South American potato
Malanga
This is a sparkler pumpkin
Avocado a persimmon a pomegranate cherry tomatoes
Dragon fruit
The orange
That's a bag but this is a pumpkin pie making kit
I need a listing theme song
How to check in with a few reporters but you keep doing it.
Support also comes from fidelity
As a Fidelity Wealth Management
You get a dedicated advisor
To help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes
And make
Clear recommendations for your full Financial
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
Next up our Intrepid producer Nick Fountain his assignment was to find a fruit or vegetable
Having a heart
Bruised fruit or vegetable
I found a
What pairs
Is this phone on
Good how are you
My name is Bob
What's your name
Bob
That's right Robert
Twobobs
Bobcat anello and Bob Taylor Bob Square
As well known in the industry
To the bobstay represent the
Pear Growers Association
Jennifer Washington and Oregon State
Which is where most of our pairs
So the other Bob's
Are telling you
That pairs are having
A sad sad time
Absolutely
I've worked in the produce industry for more years than I care to say
And
It's a misunderstood crew
Misunderstood
Okay
Let's put Paris on
Therapy couch
What
What is the trouble
People think of
Pears as just
Misshapen
So they go to the store
And they
Grab a fresh pair and they take a bite out of it
And it's just sort of hard and
Gracci
And then they think
Did they hate
Paris forever and the next time you go to the store they just buy it out right
I think apples have it easy
Hey Joe
Apple's Dudley Avenue Z
Apples don't need an instruction
What pairs
Paris you got to wait you got to wait 7
10 days for them to be at Peak
Ripeness you need a cat
Sure
Or you have to know when
It's ready so they invented This brilliant slogan
Same check
The net meaning like what like
Picture of your thumb into that
The neck Park
Yeah press right near the stem and if it gives a little bit
It's right
They've given up on your generation is Going On to the Next Generation
Because it's so easy I mean even you go to school
And you talked a little kids
Will you tell him
When you go home tonight
You tell your parents that you know how to tell when a pear is ripe
It Is by checking the neck
So easy check the neck
I love that
When it comes
What's 2
2 fruit and vegetables
We're letting children Loop
There's a bigger lats
Robert
Did the boxers try
Teach us all
Patience is a virtue
Okay alright thank you Nick Felton
So while the rest of us were wandering around
Hasting Delicious Fruit
And vegetables
Sally Helm had a very different assignment Sally your assignment was to
To find
Gadget something
Non-edible non-food products
Hamster the food processor
So I was walking around the aisles and I got a text from my fellow producers McFadden
And he was like
Okay Sally 6:15 Booth 6:15 is your birthday
18615 hello
What wouldn't what is this so we make a 6-inch by 6-inch limited hologram
Program with specific sets of frequencies to inhibit mold and bacteria growth Plus
We can also replicate the frequency that the Earth make a food want to stay alive
I
Saw V
15 minutes
They told me all about this card and I brought it I want it so it says food freshness car in the front
It's like a little
Square gold laminated
Card looks like one of those holographic stickers you would get from a gum machine
And at least according to Reagan RJ
What it does is
You know how strawberries like go moldy really quickly. Ideas whatever
So you put
The food freshness card in your fridge
Wither strawberries or whatever
And if it's within 5 cubic
Beat that means frequencies that are coming off the card
Will inhibit the mold
Growing
Process
And I will say I have not had time to
Talk to the proper food
Scientist
Safety expert I don't know any one who knows how science works
I'm just going I'm just going with Rick and RJ here
They took me to the card
And they point out in Dulce in the corner
They're like these shapes
So it's like circles and triangles and
Q This is a crucial part of
Why did the sacred geometry go to the science behind it like metatron's cube is 1 a sacred geometry
Is in there. You know the Flower of Life
The different layers in the hologram
When you say the frequencies are embedded in the card what do you mean
Imperative we program the inside nanocrystals
Inside
Okay well again this is welcome to the future we use Tesla technology everyday
We use
We use Tesla technology every single day
Metatron's
Flower
Nowell metatron's Cube
The flower of
Life
Using Technologies in stolen from Elon Musk in a Tesla
Nanocrystals nanocrystals
Is this a cult
That's an interesting question is possible I know it's listening
I did ask these guys are you in
I'm sure you were more polite than that number
So I'm sure you must got this all the time but this sounds crazy
We get it all the time but we say stick one in your fridge and then call US
You know
I gave you the assignment can you brought me a piece of technology
Maybe from an alternate universe
To the Future
I don't know but we're going to test it out tomatoes
On its own
And one in a file cabinet drawer across the office with the food freshness card and
We'll see what happens
We'll see science versus nanocrystals who shall win
Thank you Sally
Hey do you want an entire team of nosy economics journalist asking awkward questions at your show
For your convention
Or your wedding or bar mitzvah
We are available Planet Money at NPR
. or
The person who produced
The produce show
Woodlake fountain
With an assist from
Literally everyone on the team
And today at this time of year a special appeal to you but a money list
What are the best ways to support what we do at Planet Money is to support your local public radio station
I got my started public radio station kuer in Salt Lake City
I'm sure there's one where you live so as you're thinking about your end-of-the-year donation
Make sure you include
Public Radio
You can find your local station at donate
. NPR
Dino Archie slash
I'm Robert Smith
Thanks
A beer koozie and another mouth pain
Ganja some potato chips from Idaho this looks like a flatbread item that I put in the Tupperware
Have not eaten it
Is a pineapple stress ball some batteries hand sanitizer
Pain do you have a car
I don't have a car I don't have a car title to the car charger
Nevada water bottles is lead with load with confidence
A pen that has a single pistachio