Hey it's Kenny Malone Planet Money correspondent and
I am a huge
Horror film
I'm telling you this
Because it's been fantastic that one of the biggest movies this year
Is a horror
Chris was just telling me how you felt much more comfortable with my being you
Sorry man this movie is indeed called get out
It was number one at the box office when it
That came out last month
And it's getting love from virtually every critic out there for being a smart
Social commentary on race
And also for being a kick-ass horror
Get out is already the highest grossing film ever for
For the production company that made it
Blumhouse Productions
No we first came across them in 2015
Because our pioneering a new business model for making
Films
The store you're going to hear was first reported by Stacey Vanek Smith and Steve
Steve Henn
And at the end of the show
We talked to Jason Blum the producer
About his head
There is one rule
In Hollywood
Bigger is better
And biggest
Is best
The only example of this you need
Is a little movie franchise called
The fast
And the Furious railroad crossing up there is exactly a quarter mile away from here
I'm green I'm going for you know those car chase scenes that used to have
End movies
Fast and Furious is basically
Just the car JC that's the full movie part 2
What's right they've made
Seven of these movies and altogether they learned 3.9
Billion dollars
The box office
How to say I've always been curious
What would it be like
Direct one of these
Huge big budget
Phelps
Lots of fun from the point of view of the filth
All the toys and you have
Enough time
This is Rob Cohen
He directed the very first fast and
He created the series
After directing the Fast and the Furious
Cohen was the toast of Hollywood
And everybody was so friendly and so nice and let's have lunch and read this script
Come to this party yeah but he started getting all of these offers and he got an offer
Did you even bigger budget movie
That's the way it works
This one was a film called
Dell
Its budget 135 million.
It was like the Fast and the Furious but with
Fighter jets
And drones
Instead of cars
And at one point one of the drums.
I'm self-aware
You put a squadron at risk
Damn straight
Tin Man did what you did in Rangoon
You talk me
This film was
Total
Disaster
It lost
Close to us
A hundred million dollars
Everybody was like I had leprosy and the very same people that
We're so nice we're suddenly like
Not
You died coming to a restaurant and instead of them popping up and saying come on sit down and join us
They were like
Pretending they didn't see me
And it was that extreme
Hear failure is considered a terminal disease that's communicable
For two years Rob Cohen didn't
Park
Then you got a couple jobs but nothing close to
Before I met someone
Completely unexpected
Someone
Really didn't know better
Walked into his office
An offer
This guy was a movie
And he said
I have a different way you can
Lots of money
Forget the Blockbuster mentality
Just put that
Out of your mind
Think small
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Today on the show what happens when one director leaves the world of big budget Hollywood
For something that could be even more lucrative
Low budget
Hollywood
Support for this podcast and the following message come from rocket mortgage by Quicken Loans
When it comes to the big decision of choosing a mortgage lender
It's important to work with someone you can trust
Who have your best interest in mind
With rocket mortgage
You'll get a transparent online process that gives you the confidence you need to make an informed decision
Skip the bank
Skip the waiting
And go completely online at quickenloans.com money
Equal Housing lender licensed in all 50 states
Nmls consumer access. Org number 33
The low-budget movie producer who showed up in Cohen's office
Come told me he was kind of known around town is like a renegade
Crash
But he also happened to be one of the most
Successful producers of all
Jason Blum
Don't worry if you haven't heard
Heard of him he hasn't won a lot of oscars and students don't study him in film School
When is famous in this industry for getting the most money out of the cheapest
Possible
And when you rank movies by the return-on-investment
How much money went into making a film
Compared to how much profit created
Jason mom's name is on six of the top 20 films made in the last
Blum has developed the whole philosophy
About how to make money
Any figured it out when he saw it early cut of this little film
Called paranormal
I'm at where operational babe
Sweet
Paranormal Activity is the story of a couple that is trying to record ghosts in their own home
Basically the whole thing looks like a whole movie
I just want you to know that if things get
Thanks for grass or or get worse and anyway I don't want to mess the camera stuff anymore I don't want to make you mad
One for the film and he decided to buy become a producer
Find
And he did this because it was scary but mostly because it was
Cheap Paranormal Activity Cost Less
Used Toyota Camry
It initially cost $15,000
$15,000 how do you make a movie for $15,000 no crew
So do you have one person and one person does everything Warren and in this case he had his girlfriend and his
Brandemere there were three of them
But there was that that was a whole crew there was no sound there was no makeup there was no wardrobe there's no there's no is no one but
Ford fake blood for $15,000
Where you buy fake but it's $4
Paranormal Activity was basically the
Polar opposite
Of the fast
There were no car chases and explosions no computer-generated monsters
Nothing
Paranormal Activity made 200 million dollars
It all the film history no film has ever made a bigger return on
Basketball thinking
I mean sure not every movie
Could be
Has biggest hit
Is Paranormal Activity
And you can't really make lots of movies
But what if you created a system that made
Lots
Really cheap
Movies
Meet somebody flops but who cares they're cheap
And once in awhile you get a little of that
Paranormal Magic
A certifiable hit
And when you did you would make
Fortunate
Basically looks at films the way
Adventure capitalist
Most insulting Valley looks at
Startups
He decided
I'm going to make lots and lots of little bits and then what the market
Figure out who the big
But to make this work
Mom had to fight
Every Instinct of
Every Hollywood director
He had to force them to stop spending money
Witch's heart
Because all the kinds of standard Hollywood stuff
Is just off limits
Removal of the movie but the climactic scene is a giant explosion to break down a building.
Blippi
There was no way to end your movie without seeing the big explosion of a building falling down on screen
Not for us we have to pass
Airplane crash
Again if you have to see it I can hear someone talk about an airplane crash no problem
I can see a burning when no problem I could see rip seats after the fact no problem the actual airplane going down
Not a jet a prop plane we could do
Car chase through City
We've done them but they are
Fair they do not look nothing like Fast and Furious I'll tell you that it's a very very
Turkey
Very different version of that
Mom set up a production company
Blumhouse
And they started to churn Out movie
Horror movies and thrillers
And some names you might have heard of
Insidious
Sinister
The Purge and they're also probably films you have never heard
Like stretch
Area 51
There's really almost no way for you to know they even exist because they were never advertise
They were never released
In theaters
About 40% of blum's movies go basically nowhere
Straight to video
Buried in
40%
Is a lot of movies that's like half of his movies fail
That's incredi. This formula right but half are these huge outsized
Hits at least in terms of the return
So this is the man who is totally at peace
Switch flop
Mr. Auntie big-budget Blockbuster
And he's approaching Rob Cohen
Mr Blockbuster
The director of The Fast and the Furious
Whose career was
End of on the skids
And one says to call in
Give all that up
Let's make
A cheap
Don't remember
All of a sudden they started talk to me about a thriller with Jennifer Lopez the script is called the boy next
It's you know your classic Boy Meets Girl
Girl falls in lust kind of
Boy turns out to be a homicidal maniac
I hate it when that happens
So common
But the script wasn't bad
Cohen would be given creative control
We get to work with a certifiable movies
Jennifer Lopez
JLo
But there was this one
His budget
Would be for point
2 million.
Which probably wouldn't cover my
Catering Budget on the mummy $2000000 sounds like a lot
But in Hollywood math
That is low budget
Cohen said
Yes
And he approached making the movie almost like a game
You're going to have to be clever
And that cleverness stretches you and makes you think outside the box
Because the money
Panacea
Isn't in Your Arsenal anymore
You have to fix the problems another way
And so began the re-education of a big butt
Jason blumhouse
Low budget
Movie making
He has a series
I give you the three rules of how to make a cheap movie
There is a difference
Pay scale for people who speak
In the movie
And people who don't
Extras or Union
Van extras paid
I think I paid 80 or $900 a day
And the funny thing is of an extra speaks you have to pay an additional $400
So you'll notice and not just in our movies with that played our movies too like when the waiter doesn't say anything or like this
Post office clerk doesn't say anything
There's a reason cuz as soon as they do say something you got to get my check for 500 bucks so you don't want extra
Talk is it really cost
Dementors rule number two not to many locations
The most economical
Way to shoot a movie location wisest have it take place all inside of house and you'll notice a lot of our movies in fact too but I
I would also say
That that's where you're most vulnerable
Right couch your house and you think you're protected
You know except
When there's a ghost who possessed
Does your girlfriend
Or your boyfriend
The psychopathic
Exception and there is rule number three
This is probably the most
And it's that stars directors producers
All of your
Talent
You pay them as little as it is legally possible
To pay them
When you work on one of his movies you're not really in a
Employee
More like an investor
Partner
If the movie profits
You prob
So what we do is
We have box of us bonuses
So if you're if you have made $1000000 on a movie
In the last 2 years upfront
I say to you if the movie makes x amount of money we're going to get you to your million dollars if it make it beyond that will get you
You more than a million dollars
The movie the boy next door was designed
With these three rules
In mind
There are barely any extras
There's a dance scene in the movie and you're like looking around your like other people if it's this dance where is everybody
Also guessing most of them don't speak
I don't think there's an extra in the entire movie who says
Also the movie mostly takes place in a house and a school
To place
And
Jennifer Lopez and Rod Cohen or working for the minimum legal salary
They're getting equity in the
They get an ownership
But if the movie flops they Will Arnett
It's it's definitely
I gamble because it was like
Tighten the belt for the better part of a year because the cash upfront was idiotic
What is Rob Cohen starts mapping out the budget
For this movie
Deciding where he's
Spend
Where he's going to scream
He starts to get worried
Because there is this
Key scene where the boy next door
Psycho boyfriend
What's the brake line on J Lo's family car
And her son gets in and starts
Driving down a mountain Road
This is a terrifying moment
Wright & Cohen knows exactly how he wants to film The see this guy created The Fast and Furious
Yuan traumatic music
He wants a car tires
Reaching around corners
Sweat
White Knuckles on the kids hands at the wheel
And then finally in a climactic moment the car rushing toward
But remember this is a blumhouse
And that is not the blumhouse
How sweaty that was something that in the original script was talked about as it happened off-screen
Yeah what happened what happened to your car
Oh yeah well
I don't know the brakes went out and it's alright we had something but it's it's we're fine
This won't work when you can't you can't you know the boy next door has cut their
Brake lines
So that they're going to get killed you can't do that off-screen then talk about it you have to show it
But then it was like how can you afford it I mean how can I mean you can't be afforded and then I went
Home I think I can
SoCo and call some old friends from The Fast and Furious days and they give him a discount
But on one card
Chasing you knows a guy
You know the guy even a discount car chase cost hundreds of thousands of dollars
So Cohen is burning through his budget
And when it gets to the climactic scene the scene where Jennifer Lopez.
Fighting back where she takes out Ryan Guzman.
Evil Boy Next Door
Boyfriend
At this critical moment
And Rob Cohen
Is running out of cash
He wants to burn down a
Barn
He has to skimp on the fake fire
Not that you know spoil the surprise here
In the script JLo is supposed to stab a hypodermic needle directly into Ryan Guzman
I told him he wanted to build a prosthetic head and do the scene right
But he's basically completely out of cash
And it turns out a fake head
1 fake
Head cost
Dollars
So is that a stabbing the needle into an eye
She has to kind of fake the scene
$24,000 is more than it cost to make
Paranormal a
It's more than the cost of a used cam
There is a way to give the audience the gut shot
And there's a way to make it like LMAO that's that's
That's that's not nice Wiki
But then there's a way to make people and you want people to go
Like that it's those moments you want the whole audience going nuts when they start
Edina film Cohen realizes
They are in
I'm seeing the deficiencies of the film
And I'm not kidding I'm not a guy after making this was my 34th movie I'm not into kid
Kidding myself about what's right and wrong
And I felt
That in several areas of the movie we pulled the punch
So Cohen and Jason Blum screen the film for some
Studio execs
Universe
Nfocus
The reaction comes back
And then calling Corners JC
In the theater that night and says look
I can fix that
Just give me a little bit more money
Give me one fake hair
Another take the love scene so it's sexier than lifetime television
And a little bit more cash for more fake fire in the barn and we've got it
We will have a hip
I just need
A little bit of cash
And blum's response
No way
And his was you know what we just don't have the money we spent the money
You spent it you were partner you spend every penny you had the decision on every penny and we just
Don't have anymore and I'm going to have this whole big cup
Franchises what do you mean you don't have anymore but he was adamant and that's the that's the fee
Fiendish deal
Blum actually has a fourth rule
For cheap movie making
And it's Ironclad
Never
Ever break your
Never try to spend your way
Problem
Economist actually right about
Cydaea it's called the sunk-cost
Often companies and people who have spent a lot of money
A lot of time on something
They're more likely to
Continue plowing resources
Into that project
Even when it's a complete disaster
The sunk cost fallacy
It drives
The big budget
What the blonde way says
Spend your budget
App anymore
Did the film fails
Myself
I'll be another one
Ahmed 10 movies in the pipeline for this year already
He expect
Did for them to fail
So he just thought fine the boy next door will be one of the movies that fail
Robert Cowan
Couldn't
When Bloom says no no more money
Cohen Jewish
He reversed with old Ally
He goes to the studio
Universal
Who was thinking about Distributing the
If you guys can give me
B300
Just $300,000
I can get a couple extra days
Days of shooting
And I can make
Disgrace
Remember the sunk cost fallacy
Universal buys
Takes the bait
Gibbs Cohen the money
Cohen Rashad that love scene
Made it a little racier
Added more fake fire to that moment
In the burning Barn
And
He got his
Is $24,000
Static
So you actually see
Ryan's head and the needle gomboc right into the eye and believe me
Believe me the audience reaction at that moment was unbelievable
So the audience reaction may have been over the top
But the critics reaction
Was
Pretty awful
They hated this
Actually have some of the river
Do you want to read one sure this one is from variety and it says
January releases don't get much more January
Send it
And it's kind of an inside big January's when film studios dump
All the bad
Here's one from the Washington Post
Though it Studio blumhouse Productions
Is best known for the Paranormal Activity series and other Fright Fest
The boy next door plays best
Is
Ken Chenault
Comedy
The final one from plugged in is
If only the boy would have stayed next door
Then we would have been spared this
Khaki salacious sexual violence
It's rough
So I asked Rob Cohen about the reviews and he
Basically started swearing but really
He didn't
Because in the end
This movie was another Jason Blum Finance
London have to pay
Pay for the reshoots keyspan exactly what he planned
4.2 million dollars
But this film
Gross more than 50 million dollars
At the Box off
And for Cohen
That was a
That was Redemption
Tons of people saw the movie
Tons of people bought
Tickets he was back
It also didn't hurt
But he did pretty well financially
How much money are you going to make from this phone
Probably
Between a million and a half and $2000000
And how long did it take you to shoot it
24 days
This year including the boy next door Jason Blum is on track
To get 10 films real
They will cost somewhere in the neighborhood
50 million
And right now they are on track
To earn half
A billion
He's definitely consider now a genius
That invented a new way to make a lot of movies and make a lot of money in
Hollywood in the end it's all about money and success
Awards are nice too and last year one made a phone call to whiplash
That won three Academy Awards
But when I asked about it
He's not going to start making ardy award bait
Domes
His mission
Let's make lots of little bats on lots of little movies
Embraces flops
Force Hollywood
To confront its fear
A failure
The last time we talked to Jason Blum was in two
But this year it doesn't look like he's going to have to worry too much about embracing failure
We check in with Jason Blum in just a minute
Support for Planet Money and the following message come from ishares
Because the best preparation for tomorrow
It's building for your future today
Ishares by BlackRock inspired to build
Jason Blum has produced not one but two of this year's top earning film so far there's get out the movie that everyone
Was talking about
And then there's another Thriller called split
We wanted to hear how things are going after all of
The success and so we gave Jason Blum
Planet money from the goddamn telephone
Mom says he made get out using the same formula he applies for all of the film team
We don't look for low-budget movies and then
See if we like them
We look for movies that we like and see if they can then be done on a lower budget
Anna and get out was was kind of certainly fit into that
Of course some compromises had to be made
For one they had to scale things down the original script called for a rich family in a big house but like
Rockefeller
Set the tone that down to
Say Alabama Countryside Rec
Smaller house
Smart budget
For a big party scene that you
Macy in the movie The cut down the number of background actors and you'll notice that
Not very many of them have to be
And then another tactic
Json just really good at getting Maximum Impact on screen
4 minimum investment
I don't think this is a spoiler but there's a there's a moment when I
A deer is hit by a car and I will confess I saw that and I
I thought
That seems expensive for a Jason Blum movie
Oh no
Oh no I said beer is not expensive
It's not a Dear Abby
And I can I can do it car hitting a deer at a very very low price
Give me a give me a ballpark figure for dead deer
A debt to shoot a dead car hitting a deer
10 grand 15r and no kidding
Yeah
Jason Blum is like the movie production equivalent
Of your friend who somehow manages to go to a garage sale and find the one thing that is worth a ton of
He said he wants to make
The great movies
Everyone else
Is overlooking
And that seems to be working
Quite well
Get out
Cost 4.5 million dollars to make
According to Box Office Mojo
It's already grossed nearly a hundred and fifty million.
Is there a store you've heard that you want Planet Money to take on
Email us
Planet Money at npr.org or find us on Facebook or Twitter
Or should it be with Bruce Banner intern Danielle David all the original episodes
Produce by Frances Harlow and Jess Jiang
If you're looking for something else to listen to may we recommend Fresh Air with Terry Gross
Wheel of her conversation with Hamilton Creator lin-manuel Miranda
As well as in-depth interviews about Russia President Trump's business dealings in
Segregation
Schools
Find fresh air on the NPR one app or wherever you get your pot
Also this month
We would love you to share the podcast
That you enjoy the most
Maybe it's Planet Money maybe it's not that's okay
For example I love
The West Wing weekly
But you can tell us whatever you love
With the hashtag
Tripod
Try
Pod
I'm Kenny Malone thanks for listening