Support for Planet Money and the following message come from Michigan Economic Development Corporation Cy Michigan is a tract
Top talent and pop businesses by searching Michigan pure opportunity
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
I'm hosting a new podcast from the Planet Money Team called
The indicator
And here is a recent episode we did
If you like it check out the indicator
On NPR one or wherever you get your pie
Last month I did what many millions of Americans did
I bought a plane ticket home for the holidays
Okay depart 23rd return 29th
Finalizing prices
The suspense is killing me too
To be honest buffering buffering
Buffering
So home for me is Boise Idaho it is always kind of an expensive flight because it's a small airport there are not that many flights
In and out
What this year was
Exception
Okay so
Cheapest flight home during those dates is
Street
Not to be clear this was not a last-minute ticket I was looking for these tickets in mid November
And you also have only 5 tickets left so you actually have to buy it
I need it right now
You think I don't buy them now though go up or is this they can't go higher
They went higher
I waited a few days. Why is leap and bought the tickets for
Today's Planet Money indicator
$1,277
And $0.10
That is how much I paid for a plane ticket home
Stacy as we say in the news business
You're not alone
Your story is part of this big
Interesting shift in the US Airline Indus
Because over the last five years tickets to smaller cities
Like Boise Idaho have been getting more expensive
Wild the same time tickets
Between big cities like New York in LA or
Between New York and Miami
Maven getting cheaper
It's on today's show we asked
Why is this happening
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith I'm Carter first year and this is the indicator from Planet Money
Show about work business and the economy
And show where we are not afraid to put a price on love but that's becoming
We're getting down to pennies here
Support for NPR in the following message come from servicenow
Making the world of work work better for me
Their cloud-based platform and solutions deliver digital workflow
Clothes that create great experiences for employees and unlock productivity for your whole company
Servicenow digitizes the work your people have to do so they can do the work
They want to do
Using technology
How to make people more productive and engaged
Moritz servicenow.com
Understand why I had to pay so much to go home to Boise for the holidays I called Henry Hart about he's an airline analyst
With the atmosphere research
You must love your family a great deal and I hope they appreciate you
An awful lot as well as 10 years ago there were a lot of
A big National Airlines in the U
Price competition was released
Pierce send those Airlines started buying each other
We've had a series of mergers and now we have four
Super large Airline
United States
American
Delta Southwest and United
Which collectively control more than 80% of the airline capacity
In the United States
All of that merging in the airline industry it means a lot less
Competition at the same time the airlines were swimming way down
You are flights smaller
When you have
Your flights
You're lying
NPR seats
You end up
With higher average airfares into some of these less
Competitive cities
Less competitive cities
Tok Boise
Sorry Stacy
I thank you
So I booked my flight out of Newark
And Henry told me the average price for tickets from Newark
Boise
Everything about 10% over the last five
This is typical for smaller City
But Henry said
That's for people flying from one big city to another big city it is a completely different story
Because welfares to smaller City
I've been rising fares between big cities
Have actually been falling
And it's pretty clear reason
Those new altar
Discount Airlines
Airlines like Allegiant
Frontier
Spirit
Their prices are super cheap in the pudding
How to price pressure on the old
School Airline
Not for me and all of my fellow travelers to
Less competitive cities
There is a light at the end of the tunnel the ultra discount airlines are growing really fast and flying to more and more cities
And in fact Allegiant has just started flying into
Frontier is going to start flying into Boise next year
So Henry says it is very likely that my
2018 ticket home for Christmas
Will cost way less than 1200 and $77.10
Thank you
Do you want to send us your ideas send an email to indicator at npr.org
This podcast is produced by Darius Ruffian and edited by Jacob Goldstein
I was curious if you spent just a little bit more money where you go
Citgo
Oh no I was just in case you're tempted
Honolulu
You know which I hear is
Nicer this time of year Boise
Don't get me wrong I'm sure boys easel
Lovely lovely town
If you get there for thirteen hundred bucks
And Buenos Aires where in fact
The seasons are inverted so it's actually
Summer you get there for 1400 bucks
I'm sorry if I'm making you feel badly about the founded by
I know
Thanks for listening
If you like this episode of the indicator you can check out some of our other episodes we did one about toll roads in the science
Gridlock what about how the Republican tax bill could actually end up helping Democrats
And what about why the Federal Reserve might be fundamentally wrong about the
You can search for the indicator on NPR one or wherever you get your
Support for this NPR Podcast in the following message come from slack used by companies all over the world
How to get everything done
Where every part of work
From documents to decisions is stored archived and searchable in seconds Slack
Where work happens