This message comes from NPR sponsors snowfall
The only data warehouse
Built for the cloud
Unlock deep Data Insights with the instantly scalable Cloud build data warehouse
Start your journey towards data-driven decision
It's snowflake. Com NPR
Hello Mom it's Robby how are you I'm doing good I'm actually in a radio Studio here with my
Cohoes Kenny Malone
Hi Mr Smith
Hi
I didn't know that Robert went by Robbie
This is news to me
So
Do you remember
The knife
That I gave you when I was a kid
Yes
Okay you mean the ones that you got at the State Fair
Your check for it
How to plastic handle serrated
Sure that we have it somewhere
I'm looking at my messy drawers
This is Smith Robert has been talking incessantly
It's not exactly
That's what I was telling everyone hear about the guy who sold
Me the knife how it was
Kid
State Fair and he started to demonstrate it
He did all these tricks with again all these jokes and at one point
Cuts
An aluminum can in half
And then he slices tomatoes
So thin he says
You can read a newspaper
So then he says you can make a single tomato last all summer
I remember you
You were up
Stuffed with
You stood there for an hour right now
He stood there for an hour watching somebody demonstrate a stupid Ginsu knife
Yes
Barbie Elsa
Kid fun things
And all I really wanted to do is to demonstrate a knife
At a state fair
That really was your goal
Yeah but it was the state fair there's a million other fun things to do
But there is a million of it
He looks quite
He he was
Thought you was going to call me special
Child is worried about that
Mrs. Smith
Hypethetic
If I were to go to a state
Robert
Do you have any advice for me
Well I think you have a really
Time with him
Seal of state fairs
And
And just stay close
Because he wonders
Oh boy
What is Robert Robert Robert
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Kenny Malone and I'm Robert Smith and we are at the Ohio State
And Robert has brought me here to apparently watch people sell things
Two other
It is way more than that when I was a child that salesman that knife salesman pulled off an amazing magic trick
You can miss me
A 12 year old boy that I needed something that I did not actually need
And I loved and I loved every second of it
The state ferry still display Square
Someone can just use the sound of their voice
Mesmerize a crowd
I get people to pull out their wallet and so today we embed with the
Hitman in Pitch women of the State Fair
To ask
Why in the age of Amazon and Walmart
Why do you need to go to a building at the fairgrounds to buy anything why does this even still exist
I Will Show You Kenny and we'll finally get to look behind the curtain
To see how the magic trick is done
Support for NPR in the following message come from servicenow
Making the world of work
Work better for
They're cloud-based Platt
Form and solutions deliver digital workflow
Clothes that create great experiences for employees
And unlock productivity for your whole company
Servicenow digitizes the work your people have to
So they can do the work
They want to do
Using technology
How to make people more productive and engaged
Moritz servicenow.com
The Story Goes
One day around the year 1800
This farmer in New England he starts
Trotting his prize cheap through the town square
Like you know what
Who's got better she
So we organized is a livestock
And that's the
The first
Fair
As We Know
Credit saint
The Ohio State Fair
Has been around since
Held in Columbus Ohio right down the center through the Midway
It's where all the classics
I want a donut burger but I want the burger patties to be the bun and the donut in the middle
Of course you got all of the games here as well
I don't want any of those prices though I went the basketball with the money
We are here
Basile
All the vendors
Vendor Marketplace starts here
This is amazing
So Robert and I are standing outside of a building it
Between the pig Barn in the fry Shack
And all I can say at this point it's just a set of doors
That I would normally walk straight past if I were not at the fair with Robert just opening
This place is huge
This place has not changed since I was in a very similar place if you don't state fair when I was at
It is
It's a building like a warehouse
3 acres large
It is
Rohit
After Roe
Booth after booth
Dozen
Upon dozens of vendors
Ready
Go Gadgets Triad air fan
You guys Optimus
Hose nozzle
Toys
There are hundreds of product
Maybe
Worley's wonder which I think is jewelry cleaner solar teeth t-shirts that light up with the Sun the last glue
What does that even mean
There is a
Hot tub Bender here
So good
That was three acres
Stuff we didn't see anybody using a match
Sickle knife to slice it
Yeah but I do see at the end of the row
A light it up booth
With a cutting board
And this mountain of shredded pineapple
Cucumber and zucchini
If you are thinking at home
OMG
That's a potato peeler
You're right
It's called the OMG peeler
Y'all ever heard of a spiralizer or
Veggetti veggetti
Veggetti spaghetti
It's a veggetti
But now you don't have to get that big machine out you can already be done with your stir-fry dinner right there
Shred a julienne
What's what's your name
Planet comic
Tommie Harris
Tommy's hue
6.5
Is bright red hair
Pull back in
In a ponytail
If you if you know professional wrestling
He's a dead ringer for the Undertaker
Tommy could probably bench-press the both of us
But instead he's delicately peeling the skin
Opportunity
Once you get home you get used to it you can go right-handed left-handed you can even do it underhanded like most politicians nowadays
Who taught you how to do this for years
Come a little bit Nacho
Thomas from Texas he tells us and he's always been good at talking and one day he saw Craigslist job list
Testing for a cashier
At a fair
We started out like most of the people
Working behind the scenes
Out of the spotlight
He would take the money from the customer
He was hired
To help
But the whole time he was watching the pitchman
Thinking
I can do this
Do you remember your first time
Yeah I'm still up
Yeah what was the product
That was a hose nozzle
The ultimate Hotel
What did it feel like nervous
Nervous the first time is really
Nervous
Well you know him
Still a few jokes from some of the other pitch man and he was officer to draw crowds people started
Empire
And now Tommy has become
Part of this small band of pitchman and Pitch women
Who are like
Product
Mercenary
And say your company that
Owns some Prada
Or maybe you're a distributor of some
And you want to sell it
Will you call up
One of these products
Mercenaries wherever they made
And
They fly out stay at a hotel on the edge of town
And come in and sell the hell out of your product and it can be a different product each week one one day your
Sewing a hose nozzle in Nashville
And then they send you to Memphis for the steam mop
These folks
These are who the young Robbie Smith looked up to
When I was a kid oh my God like I thought
You guys were the greatest
That's what's so funny and it looks so smooth
Does Mickey make it look easy
But not making it look too easy where they don't think they can do it at home
If I walk behind there for just a moment
Roberts walking around 2 behind the presentation booth
The world doesn't look different because you can tell people who are sort of avoiding eye contact
They avoid you because I know you're trying to sell himself
Yeah she just gave us a two second look and then looked completely away so this guy just to look of derision
A woman's skin
Milady you want to watch while you're eating
Your sandwich
Might as well
Who that looks good right
Y'all ever heard of a spiralizer or veggetti
And boom he is back into the pitch and if we're talking about interviewing
Tommie Harris is the
If you're talking to him but someone walks by and looks like they might be interested mid-sentence
He's out and he is back in
Yesterday he works on commission Tommy did not invent
Tommy doesn't own this giant stack of
He sells them for $20 and makes about 5 bucks Commission on each way
But he is paying for his own travel and his own lodging
By our calculations you need to sell
About a hundred
Peelers
To break even on this
Scramble easy
If you have kids
I could watch him all day
Nope nope we will not watch him all day long but
Tommy says
If you want to go see someone who has a little bit of a
Different style maybe a little bit more outgoing
Check out the woman who's pitching in the row over
Who also happens to be his fiance
Roshes
She's here
She's right around the corner
We hear from here
Only if she starts laughing
Really
You got a big laugh you'll see
This is Heather Keto
Nothing Heather's great at is called the hook the hook is when you
You grab someone
Attention somehow
And then you get them interested enough
To watch your
And we see this in action we are walking
Ward Heather's Boot & Shoe
Leaning over with
Huge grin
Walking eye contact
In which she had her arm like she wants to shake my
I got to come on over here y'all want to try it out makes your life a lot easier
Into my hands
What do you say Garden
It is in fact
The Tiger
The tiger jaw
They are basically
Pruning shears
A before I could set it out Heather pulls out
A branch of real piece of wood
It offers it up right in front of me to cut
Go for it
You know you want to
Great Clips
Oh oh oh
Robert
I'm in the zone I'm cutting
And then Heather's like
And then she holds up
Her right hand
That's you are missing almost all of your pinky
And your middle fingers a little shorter
What's the story
It was a car wreck she said she's grateful.
This was the extent of the injury
But she says she does use it as part of her demonstration
And what's amazing about the way Heather has hooked Robert
Into her present a
Is it she's put him in a position where in order to walk away
He has to put down the fun new toy
It's a loss like no more chopping Sticks no more
Wow factor
Innocent thing that amazon.com
Frankly cannot do for all of their selling prowess
They cannot physically put a product in my hand while I'm considering
And there's a certain type of product that is here
It's the kind of thing that
You need to see put your hands on in order to understand
Why it's valuable at all
Or Weiss different
From from any other product
The kind of looks like
And you can see this in some of the stuff that Heather has sold in the past
The LED light candles the Steam Mop I've done I've done the hose nozzle here
The ultimate Heist novel
Hanging with Heather
This guy that walks by in
Holding by her hook and spring into its branches
There's no effort at all
That's really easy
When he starts to say well you know this might be
Be good for my mom or bring my mom buying lottery tickets
Can get one of them big ones
And then he walks
And Robert Chase
I have a quick question for you I'm going to whisper it a little bit
Soda like
I'll be back later I'll have my mom check it out thing is that just you can walk away get you out of there
Really then I can send your mom back here I'm going to tell her about it but I'm not going to
She's at home
I'll tell her about tiger Joe
But you just didn't want to
I will make her mad and upset the lady you know
Yeah Heather has a name for
People they are called
Leaner
The reason hook but then turn the presentation they start leaning away
Looking for an excuse to lie
In fact we learned that there's all kinds of greatly
Lingo in the world
Of the pitch
Heather works at what we in the
Like to call
A red giant
Give me the time that the product is selling
A red dress
Sometimes you get stuck with
O'Leary
That's a product that nobody wants
Yes we asked
Nobody knows who Larry is but man he must have been
A total JC
JCL
Stanford johnny-come-lately
Sleeping around here they just say JCL
And it's a pitchman without a lot of it
Yes I'm going to ask too many questions
Who's desperate for
The approval of the
Pitching greats
Robert
Kept going around
And asking who is the best pitch man here
Yeah and people did eventually point us towards
The booth
Where they sell
The most amazing shower head you've ever
You want to look through a little picture on it
Football pictures
Where they sell a shower
It's the most amazing shower head you ever seen as pitched
Bike
DJ mix
Let me Give an example what you get
Memo longer growing up on you sometimes play with a garden hose
And you really want to shoot that kid across the street with a hose what did you do you put your thumb on the hose
That's your first restrictor valve
All we did with this was designed it with a hundred thumbs on a hundred hoses pointing down
It is a very powerful shower head
The PJs between this
Longer than anyone else we met at the fair
He sold everything to everyone looks a lot like Louis CK
The comedian who grew up in the Bronx
Huge Yankees fan
And here's why I love him he
Still record
His pictures so we can listen back and see like artichokes Landing
How's the audience react
You don't understand this difference between a professional salesman and I got to talk to you
Really
The most insulting thing we hear is when someone says you're a natural-born Salesman
What screw you
Spent a lot of time and effort
And a lot of energy to learn how to do this properly
Until we save for PJ
The hardest quest
The hardest question of pitchman face
You pooped in your crowd
But some of them are starting to look like they're leaners
How do you close
The deal
Close move
The best clothes
The best poses asking for the money
I'll ask you three questions this product better than one you have now
Usually they say yeah
Then I was asking this but defensively and always back up and put my Palms up
If you bought this today would you use it I mean not everybody needs a new shower right okay
You cannot see this
But at this point PJ McGee has stepped back from the customer
His hands
Are like
Like he's being robbed and he like as if he sang oh oh no did I
I like to keep going
And then
PJ McGee
Has you
You want to use debit credit to cash
Biggest problem with salespeople
95% of new sales people are afraid to ask for the money
Get into another business
Nobody goes to the fair to buy a shower head
But PJ McGee
Has already sold 10
Just today
They cost
Dollars I know and if I wasn't coming to the backpack
I might about to
You used to be
Irrational economic
Text reporter when we flew
To the fair I know
I know and I do have a
The theory about this
I've been thinking about it for 30 years
Am I serious that like normally
When I shop and most of the shop
It is a pretty
Cerebral
You know you going to amazon.com
I read every review
Oh it's one of the 17cm to the 1971
How does it compare with the sc3000 model get shirt
Better normal people shop
Yeah but
The fear
Short circuits that
Logical
Heart of
Because everything here is a century
Overload
Every decision made at the fair is a decision made on
Sure
Emotion
Remember when we first got here
Remember when I first got here
And you smell
Kettle corn
I'm so happy
Remember when we first walked on the Midway when we first got there and everyone shouting out all of the choices
We can make so many bad choices we could make
And then we walk past
Games to play
Basketball you know
The size of a basketball hoop and these were way too little you could not help your side
But I can't win a basketball with pictures of money on it I do not believe that you kept losing and asking me for more money
I will give you credit you did
Get the basketball in the hoop
But it was not logical for you to do so and my theory is
50s
Century
Experian
Creates an urgent need
Inuit Cretin need you want something now
And then
All these people here
They sell you the thing that
If it feels the knee
They bring you from desire to satisfaction
In under a minute
So if you can't feel the potato you probably shouldn't drive a car stay away from clip watch out for lightning outside now
Before we leave the fair we wanted to check in one last time
With Tommy Harris
The guy we met initially Hawking the OMG
What time is pinch a few times people trying to leave for the day
And it comes to me
This
Is
My Moment
I'm going to ask Tommy
I could try just once
To do my own pest
And I'm going to live my dream
A pitching
Kitchen object
At the State Fair
To be fair Robert did not exactly ask
Not exact
He went behind the booth
Talk to Tommy
Started inching
Closer and closer
Grab the OMG peeler
Wait and started
Yell at
Do you like food you eat food to prepare food
I can do food for you look at this thing
It is super hard
Appeal and talk at the same time
I love pasta more than anybody but
Casa muscle make it look like me ladies you do not want this to happen I have no hook
I have no clothes
That's why we have this wonderful spiral
Coloring
Powerline
Spiralizer
Roberts enthusiasm
Does pull people over to the booth
It was exciting it was totally exciting but
Once real customer showed up
Tommy
Smoothly
Takes a peeler out of robbers hand
And take so
Oh sorry about that
But you got the spiralizer noodles so you can forget it
Now you can go
Robert sort of slinks to the back of the booth
Watches the pitch finish
And then goes back up
How how was I was just way too much was it you were kind of like a teenager in the back with carpet
The first time just a little like
Excited
Paul Roberts totally fair
That is totally fair
Okay okay I did not make
A single cell
But I did get to feel what it is like what it is like to be
The JCL
The johnny-come-lately and now you know what it feels like
Turn a red joint
In Tulare
Not good but
It was my
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with
Straight jeans
How did they make them so great
Madewell starts with premium.
Then offers men's and women's styles for seriously everyone
Also you can recycle any brand of jeans in a Madewell store
And they'll give you $20 off a new pair
They work with the blue jeans go green program
To turn old jeans into housing insulation for communities in need
Terms apply
Ready to find your perfect fit
Stop by a Madewell store or go to madewell.com
Do you know the strange Place filled with Commerce
You would like us to visit
Another state fair
We would love to hear from you plant money at npr.org or we're on Twitter Facebook or Instagram
Today's show was produced by Nick fountain or senior producer is Alex goldmark our editor is Bryant first at
Special thanks this week to Alicia Schultz and Samantha Bartlett
Got a treat for you NPR has a new podcast with a fist from Planet Money the podcast is called
Rough translation
Rough translation is hosted by veteran International correspondent Breakwater
It's not not as a tourist with you, not as a reporter with you but as someone who is experiencing the culture
Cease time you get to see how ideas and take for granted here in the US or other countries changing you take
As they cross borders called the rough translation to really listen you can get it wherever you find a podcast
I'm Robert Smith and I'm Kenny Malone
Thanks for listening
Oh actually
One last thing
While we were at the State Fair
We were Outlook
Looking for food
And we were stopped by somebody who was like no no no you're looking for the wrong thing
The best thing at the fair
New item I have to tell you about it
And so we said
Alright you know what
Will give you 15 seconds
You can tell the world
15 seconds
On the clock
That help people to be like
Free
Ready
Hi my name is Allison Frank and Ian the intern at the Ohio pork Council
This year at the Ohio State Fair we are selling pork chop on a stick
At the Ohio pork trailer
Come visit us and be able to walk around
Bear with a pork chop on a stick and have to cut it you can just
Busy right into it like it's easy and reliable and delicious
15 seconds
Well done