Last week the biggest investment firm in the world
Laid off a bunch of it stop stop
And replace them with
Computer Pro
This is happening all over Wall Street
Firms are moving away from having
Humans decide what stocks to buy and sell
And towards
Having humans program computers
And then letting the computer decide
What to buy and sell
Computers are cheaper than humans
They are more disciplined they can think about more things at once
Like they can scan Facebook for Trent they can count the number of cars in Walmart parking lot
And then use all that
To figure out
What stock to buy and sell
And do it automatic
This is the way the world is
This is what the stock market is becoming
And I
Want
In
I want to see this world from the inside
I want to build a machine that will buy and sell stocks
For me automatically
Based on some
Cold hard data out there in the world
No Wyld
Human MO
And I want my machine
Do it
Based
On the tweets
A president
Donald J
Trump
Hello in Welsh
Welcome to Planet Money I'm Alex goldmark and I'm Jacob Goldstein today on the show Planet Money builds a robot
A bot
Trade stocks
Real money
We have no idea what will happen
Support for Planet Money in the following message
Search come from Wonder Capital Wonder capitals online investment platform allows you to invest in solar energy project
It's across the US
Burn up to 8.5% annually while diversifying your portfolio and combating global climate change
In fact investors like you financed 40 large-scale solar projects in 2016
Offsetting the CO2 emissions from 2.8 million pounds of burned coal
Create an account for free at Wonder capital.com Planet Money
So there's a thing that
Often happens when President Trump
Tweets about
Accompany
When he said something positive about a company
The stock price tends to go up at least for a little while
What is that something negative the stock price has to go down
So here's what I want
I want to build a computer program that monitors President Trump's tweets
And when he says something nice about a company
We buy that company stock and when President Trump tweet something negative about a company we will sell that company stock
But that just means that we will set ourselves up to make a profit if the stock price goes down
If you listen to Planet Money for awhile you know that we sometimes
Make investments with our own money that was NPR's money but like my money your money are personal money
We do this weekend you don't get into the world for real feel how the world
Gotta have skin in the
For this project I did some math and I figured out
Did I needed $100 from each member of Planet Money
So I went around the office
With my pet
Starting with Noel King
Terrific is a great idea
Okay so you're in Yu-Gi-Oh how much do I owe you
$100
How to rent in New York
You'll get it back and then some and then alright I'll break your kneecaps
That is roughly how it went all around the office
Jacob going to play you the tape of when I pushed
We are going to build
Stock trading bot
That will
Trade off of Donald Trump
Tweets
You know how he does these things that I have learned about economics
Suggest me the best
Okay
I responded to her
You didn't get my $100
Let me just explain myself briefly
Mike Mike basic view of the world is if there's some way to make money out there
Somebody's already doing it
Somebody's already got their trumpet I don't believe that we can build a better Trump
But we're going to try Charnel look obviously
I'm not in it for the money I'm in it for the for the
And I gladly took your skeptical 100
I got my
Thousand dollars from
My other
Skeptical colleagues
I took everybody's money
I put it in a trading account
And then I did
The one more
Very important think before we could get started
I named
Arbat
Go on
Arbat will be called
Botas
I see what you did there.
So you know how the president's Twitter handle POTUS
President of the US the official Twitter handle
Botas
Bought of the United
Okay.
Okay it's good yeah I'm kind of proud of it but now you got to like build the thing right now you got to make the machine
So I found some professional
I found a company that
Buildbox and helps other companies with their trading
Technology is called
Trade works with an
ACT scores at the end of it
Their offices in New Jersey about 90 minutes outside of New York City
Commercial strip
It's like very low
I went there to meet with Monte Maggiore their head oven
He runs
Whole team of people making all kinds of Bot
He is very secretive about what those parts do
But explain to me the essence of trading with Bots
In a few
Take a simple idea and do it three thousand times four times a year
It doesn't have to be right that it can be like just slightly right you know and end over overtime it's
It's like a casino except for the house
Yeah we only have to be right like
Fifty-one 52% of the time right we can be wrong a lot
As long as we're right a little more often than we're wrong
We'll make a lot of money you're starting to come around I like that
So
I told him my idea
To get a bot to read Trump's tweets and then by and
Sell stocks based on that
And he said first problem
And the computer read Trump's tweets
Can't figure out
Whether the president is saying something nice or saying something mean
This is this is the this is what more than positive and negative words this is a computer actually determining the
Sentiment of it
Type any sentence in and it will give you a sense of what the cinnamon is
More than you have lying around the office more less
Computers have gotten much better at doing this kind of thing over the past
Sentiment analysis
And companies use it a lot with social media to figure out how people feel about movies and new products and whatever
It's so common now that money and his team had already done a little test by the time I show
They'd run hundreds of Donald Trump's tweets through this algorithm
This computer program that use to find the scent
And then when I got there it was time for us humans to check the computer
To see how often I found the right in
Do you want to pull up bar scores
At the computer
It read this tweet
From January
Toyota motor said will build new plant in Baja Mex
Go to build Corolla cars for us
No way!
The caps
Bill plant in us or pay big border
If my gut check says that is negative
Human say negative
Computers
Okay so the algorithm got this one right
He got a lot of them right we look through the list one after another after another
Almost every time
The algorithm got it right
And it really interesting thing about Donald Trump is stows
Does algorithms work really well
Because he uses words like bad and sad and great
They always mean what he means them to mean so
From that perspective he makes it really easy for
Computers
Not subtle easy for a computer
Which means are trading Bots
Botas
Past the first
I was feeling pretty good
And so is mine
Yeah this is definitely doable
That was a few weeks ago
Describe the offices that is
When the real work started when I got down to making
POTUS
And money handed over the project to one of his programmers
A person named Camilo Jimenez
It started out fine
Emmylou did what he usually does when he's researching
Chatting is home office a little wood desk in his bedroom
Keep it simple
Just my laptop coffee Notepad
Laptop notepads of coffee
Okay sometimes right Biblia
Sometimes red.
Yeah
Sort of a parody of a coder
Except he's a physicist by training not such a classic
So okay so we already know that the bot can tell nice from me
What's like the next
The next thing yesterday
How to do is be able to tell
What company
Trump is tweeting about
That one sounds like relatively easy
Nope
Does a Honda City for human
That's a half rack
Computer
Because they
Did the text
Cooling clothes
Either the name of a person or the company or a product
I do have to link that
Two company
So is is Donald Trump is saying he ate an Apple for lunch or she talking about Apple Computers correct
That's hot.
So this is what making a body
Puzzle solving
Over and out
For something like Apple stock versus Apple the food
We'll have to do something to train our body to tell them apart
So he added what's called a context
Right
He had her but a little but read a whole bunch of financial articles about Apple the company
And learn the kinds of things kind of words and phrases and topics associated with the company
Apple Cupertino Steve Jobs
Tim Cook iPhone exactly
Aha and the things that are not associated with the company but with apple the food
Crunchy
Mushy
Delicious
Are but might accidentally short
I actually would shorten
I think that would be a great call
I still think it's over Valentine long on food
Okay powerbot
It can now tell the different one
Russ get back on task
Focus
Focus on arbat okay our body can tell the difference between apple
The fruit
Okay right it's a big three
Another a few types of companies that were especially hard to deal with
One of them's were talking about
Trump tweets about the media all the
But that's because he is
Commenting on the media he's not saying like I'm threatening to put some tax on news right that will affect the business
I don't like the story that was on the
Usually doesn't affect the stock price of a Mediacom
So Canelo decided
Media companies
Not nurturing Universe to me because
This is like the human decision made
Right
You know we we propose this thing is like what's just going to be a machine
But once you actually have to make
The machine
You have to
Tell the machine hottest
I think the machine that in this case it's not exactly thinking for itself right Camilo
Is the is a human being
And he is setting up a set of decisions based on his kamilos human judgement
Well it's it's it's a mix of his
And the computer
The machine really is making
Decisions
It is learning about Apple
It is interpreting language
It's just that
In some places
Humans have stepped in and said
Some puzzles
They would just take way too long to solve
Not worth it
For instance
I want to give you this one I love it there is this one company
That the body
Could not record
You want to guess what it was
I guess I'm very excited I have give me a clue
Is very close to Donald Trump
Physically and emotionally
Is it
Boeing
They make Air Force
No
Here is Camilla's boss
My again
Are we
In our in our production hour then we won't trade the company Tiffany's
Cuz computer can't tell when Trump is talking about his daughter and when he's talking about the actual company Tiffany Trump
Lesser-known Trump.
And Tiffany's the Jeweler which is just down the block
From Trump Tower
It will not trade Tiffin
Stats the decision in it
Which is fine
No big deal
So okay our machine are Buddhist to be it can
Tell when the president is being positive or negative say nice things were mean things
And be
It can figure out
What companies
The president is tweeting about
The last thing we have to tell it is how soon after the Tweet to buy
And how long
Do we hold it
Okay
Okay but right away what does that mean
This is not an obvious question
So money setup
Who makes a simulation
Of the stock
Mark the whole stock market
In the past few months
He adds in Trump's tweet
And then
He runs our Bots through the
So it's like going back in time
To see what I would have done
If it had existed a few months
Clear our path did not exist a few months ago
This is not trading with your money this is just
He runs it over and over again
Tweaking the variable of when to buy and when to sell
Each time he runs
At my desk
Late for dinner
And I'm worried about that
And but I remember
Sitting there and saying you know
Here are some options you know the week
But we could try we could try holding it overnight we could try holding it for a little while
You know what you're holding for
4 days what is simulation pointed to get in and get out relatively
But
Not like the exact number of minutes matter.
You know so that that made us feel good because that made us a like well
It's not going to hold this thing for 30 minutes
I'm just something magic about 30 minutes or if I hold it for 40 minutes there's something broken
It turned out that
What mattered most was
You know
Getting reasonably close to one that we happened you know in trying to get out by the end of the
So that is what
When Donald Trump tweets about a company
Botas
Will buy a stock right away not in milliseconds like some high-speed train
Pretty much
It'll take like a few seconds
And then
30 minutes after that
Will be out
The last time I talked to money
You show me the
Chart
Show me how much money we would have made if we had lunch
Right after eating
Because we did not launch them this is just
Pns simulations more like the ad
Freibott then
Okay so now I'm looking at a chart
How much money we're going to make
And what it looks like is
You flatlines
And then it shoots up really fast
Presumably I guess that's when there's a tweet and we make money
And then there's another Flatline for a while and it shoots up again
There's one that goes down others to work as a couple work goes down but
Overhaul
It looks like we are on the slow and steady path towards riches on this chart
My interpreting it right
You are interpreting it optimistic lyrics
Yes that's what I do when I'm in Bethany
I'm not a very good investor
But money said it did pass the bar for
And if it were his but
He would start trading
You know where
We feel good about the strategy
You know
And
Can you say that with a little more confidence
Your ear your chance you're saying it to me like she don't really believe
I want to overstate
I don't understand the risk
Overstate
The benefit
Of doing something
I just feel like
You know it's not
We haven't scientifically proven anyting
I like this guy
Like I respect this guy I it actually gives me more confidence
That he is
Skeptical it was like well we don't really know maybe it's
Flukey I'm that is what he saying here and like
That makes me like him more
What was really interesting about talking with him about strategy
Is it is very clearly driven by the scientific method that he wants
Pose a hypothesis
Contested
All of the data
He understands but that has a major limitations
Because if you wait around for the data to be just right you're going to miss a lot of opportunities absolutely true
You have just described my life
You know there's just a practical aspect of it which is you know like so
You know if you have this is an option you know to invest some of your money in like
Doesn't seem like a good bat
Yes
Today
At the moment we publish this podcast
We are pushing go
Anarbagh
Botas
It will start trading real money our real money so if you are listening to this podcast
It means
The machine
Is life
You can follow botas in the real world how to do it after this
Support for this podcast and the following message come from The Economic Development Authority of Fairfax
County Virginia
Home to more than 350 cyber companies and 8900 technology-related firms
Details at Power of ideas. Org
This is more than a stock trading bot it also tweets
You can follow at
Botas on Twitter at botus
And you will see
Every trade that we make
How are you doing
Few other little surprises
And what about it starts training you will also be able to follow along on our website
Npr.org
We genuinely don't know what to do
We could make money we could lose money
Trump stop tweeting about companies perhaps the least interesting option for us but if there is something interesting we will let you know about
On the website on the Twitter account
Right here on the Pike
Today Show was produced by Sally Helm and edited by Bryant
He thinks you money and Camilo and everyone at tradeworks who helps build our bot and then endure all of my questions in the week.
Interactive brokers who let us set up a very small trading account without charging us extra fees
Kevin mcpartland
And the folks at the NPR Visual and digital
If you're looking for something else to listen to try up first its Interiors newest podcast it is a daily news show
Show hosted by some of the biggest names that NPR David Greene Steve inskeep
Rachel Martin
Called up
First and you can find it at npr.org podcast on the NPR one app or wherever you get your
I'm Jacob Goldstein
What Naruto got some footnotes
Okay footnote number one
One detail of those tweets
To the computer analyzed
Figure out which were positive and which were negative
The most negative of all of the tweets scored by the computer
It was about
Saturday Night Live
Because
@nbcnews is bad but Saturday Night Live is the worst of NBC
Not funny cast is terrible
Always a complete hit job
Really bad television
Bad
Terrible really bad
Worst
Footnote number 2
Number two
On Tiffany's the company and Tiffany stock
Donald Trump's daughter
Is reportedly named after Tiffany's the company
And Trump
Bought the air rights over Tiffany's the store
Which is what enabled him to build Trump Tower as tall as it is