Support for this podcast in the following message come from NCR who believes in small businesses
That's why they build NCR silver
Worthington point-of-sale NCR silver deliveries big Enterprise management tools built for small business owners
Visit ncr.com silver
When Lisa signed up for match.com she was at this point in her dating life where
She is ready to try something new
Not online dating
Meet people online
But just
Generally she been feeling like she needed a whole new
I had to be kind of more aggressive about it I had to be more diligent
And not just
And I had beef
Lisa was 31 years old she just moved back to New York
And she's basically spent her twenties in a series of long-term relations
I kind of decided at 31 that I didn't have that luxury anymore I couldn't do that anymore until I was much more
Efficient
He said you may recognize her very own Lisa
The Chow a report of here at Planet money but this was back in 2008 long before she joined us here and none of us
Actually knew this story until just yes
And so I started going on dates
And
And it did get a little bit overwhelming and so I did
Do something
I did make
An Excel file
And I started
Just writing down their names
You have a spread
And I kind of created these different columns actually
1 2 3 4 5 6 column
Lisa needed the spreadsheet because in a year-and-a-half
Lisa Chow went on 58th
50 First Dates
22 of the 50 I want on side
The fun
It was so much fun
Really yeah I really loved every night you didn't smell so funny
I was actually really
Pleasantly surprised meaning
The guys were really great
There's some really nice guys
That is literally the first time I've ever heard that from a woman
I really like pleasantly surprised how how many
Really great geyser
I asked we said to come open today show because
Michael Ealy set
Is a secret dating
Genius
I had no idea she went on 50 First Dates and she never once felt sad
Or stress
Order more lives
She just with efficient and rational she's thoroughly enjoyed the entire experience
Here's what you did she went on 50 days and each time she went home after the date and she would record
Months
Year of time location name
And one memorable day
Okay so I have
Pothead
Touchy
Boring
This guy
Had for gym memberships
What is the one that I'd say that I love
Here for this person
You have
Bobs his head a bit too much
Socially inept to Russian
Biscuit Head
Wei West Coast but super
Cute dude
At the time Lisa it had lots of friends who are also dating online and they would all complain all the time about you
No I wrote Five Guys and only one of them wrote me back
When I was doing online dating I never wrote
People emails NEP some people might call that a cop-out but I just said I'm going to lower my Trans Am
And purely just
Wink and if they're really interested though right back
I remember actually I'd be sitting
Like watching some HBO show
Sitting back up
Quick getaway
Wink
Rake it up
Not even thinking twice about it
The date needed to happen very soon after first Contact
Suicide didn't want to build up some idea of the guy before meeting him and then have an opportunity
To be disappointed
Similarly no dates on Friday or Saturday nights
She told me
It's depressing to come home after a bad date on a weekend so she
You just never let that happen
And if Lisa went on a third date with someone she would always take them to a social Gathering
That included some casual friends of hers
That way she could observe them in a social
In other words we took something that's normally
Sirius and Squishy
Human attraction
And she
Trying to
Strip it of all of the messy emotions
I really think that's
What made her so success
She made this thing that most people find so stressful and
Tedious that
Sucks your time and self confidence and Hope
And she made that
Fun and she did it using data and statistics and
True economics reporter Lisa Chow she applied the principles of economics to her love life
And it worked
There was one github
That was like almost like 45 number 45 right
We we were kind of dating we're seeing each other about 6
And I
Just at one point just decided
Okay
This is not going to work
So I can I cut the cord
And then I and I thought like
Diamonique mistake
Like you know we did have so many
Kind of things in common
And then the next week I went on a date with Kevin and instantly I knew I didn't make a mistake
You know and I was thinking all those times that I had
If I had stayed with that guy
And I would have had that out
Opportunity
Like the Kevin
Right into it just became very it kind of
Crystallized right there like okay that's what an opportunity cost Feels Like Rain is like when you stay with that guy
Kind of feeling iffy about
And you're missing out on
You know Kevin
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm signage a few Walt Robert Smith and that was Lisa Chow
Buttabody reporter
Now married
And Kevin have a beautiful toddler named Isaac
And Lisa story reminded us of something that we
Wonder about during our
Dark dark moments of producing this show which is
How useful is economics in our everyday life
How far can you really take
Can you take it all the way
To the most emotional intimate part of our lives
Today
We're going to try
This episode was originally recorded in 2014 economic advice for the lovelorn at the end of the show will have an
Update on how our advice
Turn dad in real life
Stick around for it
Support for Planet Money and the following message come from betterment a smarter way to invest your money
Betterment combined time-tested investing principles with the transparency and ease-of-use you expect
Great technology
Focusing on lowering fees and taxes
And here's what you might find refreshing
Betterment really cares that you reach your financial goals and that's why they keep their fees low
Planet Money listeners can get one month managed free
For more information visit betterment.com Planet Money
We had an opportunity to test this the other day because one of our favorite economist
Was in New York
Promoting a new book Tim Hart
It's in Hartford is a
Great guy he used to work as an economist for Shell in the World Bank
And then she went into the sort of thing we do explanatory journalism
He wrote a book called the undercover economist
In a column in the financial times and
I imagine it's somewhat hard to come up with a topic every week in the financial times has he had this great idea this
This jokey idea
I will do
A deer economist
Advice column
Love
And sex advice
For the Heartbreak
In many ways
Love seems to be totally divorced from economics
But then you realize well
The stakes are high
This is something that matters to us
We dealing with scarcity
I miss you
Dating one person
At the very least you don't have as much time to date another person then you may well find that you can only date one person
Strange happened
When he started to do this, I need a first date with this character he was playing
Real people started writing with real problems
Kim started think you know
Economics
Economics really does have something to offer these p
It's simultaneously
Completely useless and irrelevant and somehow in some
Brilliant
Hidden genius way keeps
Producing
Insights that are not necessarily obvious from the normal way that we think
We knew Tim was coming in and we asked all of you to send us your questions
About love and sex and whatever else you wanted to ask him about
We got some of you on the phone with him so you could ask him
Directly for his economic advice
Are there are you there yeah great High
Hi
So we have Tim Harford here do you want to introduce yourself to him
Okay
My name is Arthur I live in Pittsburgh Pennsylvania I'm a senior in high school
I'm pleased to meet you off of how I want him
Pleased to meet you
What's your question for The Economist
Alright so my question is
I'm and I'm a senior in highschool and I've never
Been on a date
Should I be worried about this
Arthur can I just ask what is it about not having been on a date that makes you
Worried what makes you think you should be worried
I know it just seems the
Everyone else
Yeah I like but not everyone else to lots of people around me
It all in
You are the prom coming up and
I'm clueless about that so
Cuz it's a little bit stressful
I think you are
The victim of what behavioral Economist call
Hyperbolic discount
More simply
You taking a very short-term Prospect
So you really miss the first 10% of your
He'll possible dating experience
And let's be honest
It's not the best 10% is it
Dating when you're a teenager
It's not that great
They're all kinds of inconveniences you have your own place
What you doing
Italy case economist
Council that you shouldn't worry about some costs that you can go back in time and have a date when you're 15 anyway
So don't worry about that
I would just be inclined to crack on with things are you planning to go to college
Yeah well experience suggests is going to get a lot more exciting from then on in don't worry
Okay
Are you going to ask somebody to prom
I
Haven't really thought about that
You know I got to wish
Probably nothing
I think a lot of people have that feeling I could give you a piece of advice specifically about the prom if you're interested
So the Great
Behavioral Economist stroke psychologist Daniel, when he won the Nobel prize in economics
Even though he's not an economist that tile Goodyear
He talks about something called loss aversion
This is a a
The discovery that was one of the first discoveries made in behavioral economics
Unlost version is pretty disproportionate anxiety
About stuff that doesn't matter very much
So for instance if you lose $5
You feel really bad about the $5 you've lost your cousin yourself your
Going to it again and again
If on the other hand you find $5
You got a great fight box I need forgotten about it really quickly
Salad think about Promenade
One of the games of
Accommodate
That goes well
Versus
The losses
From
I come back but doesn't go well or you lost someone to the prom
And they say no
Well actually you are going to have a prom date anyway if you didn't ask
So the the cost of asking somebody and being refused is
Actually really
Quite small it doesn't feel good
But it's no big deal
Where are you never had that before so it goes well this could be the start of something big for you
So
Remember loss aversion when you are
Weighing up these two choices I can't tell you what to do but I can tell you you'll probably taking the downside risk to
You seriously
I'm not thinking
Enough about the potential outside
Just don't actually use the words loss of virtue
How do you feel about that advice
I feel great
That makes you feel better really good
Economics spreads happiness
Arthur thank you so much thank you very much
Write one problem solved if you're just tuning in
Dear Economist to taking advice for the lovelorn
Next up
Russellton news
Yes I can
This is Robert Smith the co-host were here with him
Anna Russell this attempt
Other time
Just introduce yourself to our Economist and tell him your question
Well you been I guess my question is kind of long my name is Russell and
I'm a polyamorous
I'm married
Girls have to close
Other loving partner should I share my life with an intern
She also has
Other partners of her own
And in fact
We live with one of her boyfriends
The concept of abundance
And love is abundance and you can share it with whomever you want
Where is monogamy
Concentrates on scarcity
So I just
Curious to hear The Economist often the idea of scarcity in abundance in love and then what economic benefits
Terrorized from society thinking abundantly About Love in This Way
The Russell
Economics is often described as the study of scarce resources so in a way you would think that I'm kind of messed with the wrong
Wrong
Person to analyze
The situation of abundance that you find yourself in onshore a lot of listening
Contemplating about abundance right now
That what I would say is
That love
May be boundless and abundant but time isn't
Time is finite
So the challenge that I'm sure you're well aware of having to manage is
Splitting your time between your multiple partners
Another reason actually an economic theory that is related to this
It was about it by Rebecca Nobel Prize winner in economics
And he
Developed an idea of
How
Many children
You might want to have
Desert Rain up here
Because each additional child that you have
Is going to divide your time
And your attention
Are you going to have to cram them into a smaller house they can have to share a room so you might have to move into suburbs somewhere
A cheaper further away from where the job is
You can't afford to spend so much time with them
I'm so in Becca's Theory there is trade-off
Between the quantity of children
And the quality of children
And I I would imagine you face the same trade-off you have to decide what we up to Optimal number of committed
You say that love is abundant
Unconditional transparent
Foxcu
Behavior is not totally consistent with us
Because you ugly have I think what three committed promise your wife has
If you committed peronnas
Why not
5 billion / 7 billion people on the planet
Yynot love all of them
What is the Russell have you have you hit your limit
Actually the answer is yes because what I discovered this was trying to be able to have a say more than three Partners was absolutely
At least for my own relationship
And I I constantly have to be able to balance my time and be able to schedule and coordinate my time with my partners
So that I can be able to have a meaningful relationship
Otherwise it just kind of degrades over time and it's not something that's worthwhile I mean
Russell this is something I love about economics so I know
Very little about polyamory
This is a fairy that Gary Becker developed
Almost half a century ago
And yet it delivers a result that you find persuasive thank you
Okay well thanks so much
Thanks Russell
Our next guest him we we we brought in in person because
She's got some things to show you I introduce yourself
My name is Andrea celenza and I'm the host of dating podcast called yoy
Hundred
Very nice to meet you so what can I do for you
How many dating apps should I be on to do
To find a match
It stopped to get very
Difficult
When you have too many to spend any amount of time on any one of these things your question
Seems to me
Implies that you will you're trying to find the perfect
Match
Because that only if you were trying to find the perfect match would you expanded have
That we don't want to happen in a second. Going to set up Anna.
But if you're just trying to convey John goodenough
You probably want to focus
But tell me what do you see in these times
I think I'm trying to optimize here is if I'm going to spend time and I'm going to set aside a Thursday we're going to come up with the
What time we're going to find a place I'm going to get on the train
I'm going to sit down for a drink and have to meet this person I want to make it
Worth my time I want to make sure that I'm
I don't want to waste a Thursday
Discuss results here is no man has cash results yesterday
What you really need to be doing
Is
Finding out a way to have a date like experience
Before you have
The date
Because the date like experience is
What you really don't need to look at a thousand guys online what you need to do is have
Almost died
To save on the actual date which is the release cats Resort
So what you need to do is you need to have some app that lets you
Say look at
Paintings in the Metropolitan Museum together and talk about them
Watch a film together online and talk about the film online
I'm actually very quickly find out
Then
Whether that's a match or not
Is there anything that can like
Simulate
A Daily Star a real conversation
Hypothetically I can ask any guy
Hey before we decide to go to the spa in Williamsburg
Thursday how about instead we
Height for 15 minutes
I think I would know what I need to know from that Skype conversation but
It's an ask that no one else is asking
For no one else
NASCAR level commitment you're kind of not allowed to ask
I I think that you should stick to this and you know why I think you should stick to this
Because my time is incredibly valuable
And I'm so busy
Yeah you know that but
Here's the thing
Because wouldn't it be interesting
Find
The guys who would actually
Exceed
Python requests
This is actually we've already discussed you know shortage of guys out that has lots and lots of guys out there
The question is trying to find the right one
And so you and your factory setting up what
A Michael Spence Nobel Prize for economics which cool to screen
Do you say what I want from you
Happy today
All I want from you
15 minutes
All the insects
Talk
Thank you so much for having me and I feel like I learned upon I'm so excited to annoy all of Brooklyn with my Skype
Request an economics making people's lives better at tell me how this guy works out
This is how we left the show in 2014
Fun Way To Think about economic
In our real life I did not think
Did anyone would take the advice seriously
But Andreas Lindsay the last voice you heard
She did take it serious
Shortly after the show aired
Andrea started
To date
Via Skype
Any neuron podcast why oh why she told the whole story of how it worked out
Let's hear little clip
Hey hi
How to do
Ideas
No it's an economist but it was my idea to take dating advice
I kind of
So that's my
I became my boyfriend
The first conversation we ever had was recorded for the show
I even put sentimental music under it
That's how you know I like them
I feel like I owe you a drink
Can I take you out in real life
Really
Sounds like kind of just like maybe Mom
Not actually
Our first real date was to a dive bar
I went home with him
And that night he asked would bother me if he kept a light on
It's about to finish this book
Remember falling asleep to the sound of a page-turning
Knowing that this was unlike anything
Indian Mike moved in together
They plan to whole life too
And then after a couple of happy years
The relationship
Ended suddenly
And interpret Tim Harford back on her show on yoy
To talk about what how
Listen to last podcast with kind of surreal
Yeah
Okay yeah
That name rings a bell
Yeah
And then
All I remember all that crazy Planet Money
Terrible terrible advice I gave her
I meant to just to listen to it all.
I feel like I have
At least indirectly broken your heart and for these I can only
Apologize
I won't spoil the whole story the podcast is
Well worth listening to
Beautiful axe
Yoybuy mechanically Network
Episode 8
How Will I Know
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Kia Niro with the launch of Kias
First ever ground-up hybrid crossover
Discover the new Kia Niro a smarter kinder
The crossover
We are always looking for stories of how economics plays a role in your life
For good or for bad
Send an email
Planet Money at npr.org or find us on Facebook or Twitter
Today's update was produced by our intern Daniela the doll
We're also looking for our next summer interns
Plan ahead
It is a great gig in turnspit story ideas album
Make the show
Plus you get paid
And you get to hang out with
Apply you can find more information at npr.org
Flash money
Also NPR has started this new campaign in which you tell a friend about a podcast you think they'll love
Bring up think about someone you care about
What podcast would they really like
Got it now
Do it and tell him that in real life or social media and if they don't know how to find a podcast show them how to do it
Tell us what you recommended with the hashtag tripod
T r y p o d
#tripod
Thanks for spreading the word
I'm Robert Smith
Thanks for listening