Quick morning there is some bad language in the show
Charlie you know that I'm from a very small town in Upstate New
Kerhonkson for Hoxie I talk about it
I've told you that Cranston
As small towns go he's not in economics
Powerhouse Consin is a little runt
The biggest private employer there is this old hotel called The Hudson Valley Resort and Spa
Is 8 stories high
What's the tallest thing for my you showed me pictures it's like the
White box
Tower rising up in the
Blue Mountain
Beautiful area of
But as for the hotel I worked there when I was a
The kid and the hotel was not in great shape
The roof leak
And so it smells moldy
And the carpet was this
Red orange like straight out of The Shining type carpet
And I just remembered always being kind of empty you no one really stayed there
But then two years ago I found out that someone bought the hotel they paid about 13 million dollars
I don't like
Why
Is it filed for bankruptcy just a couple years
Before
Who would want this place
To the other day I went
Constant
To try to find out what we
What's going on
I drove down to
The town hall
To the one guy
Who buy the rules of small town
Should know everyone and every
That is the town supervisor Carlton
I've lived here
About home my whole life
I'm 57 years old I started
School year
Did you go to rondout
Yes I did
Hey hey go ganders
Graduating
Class of 99 Jimmy V
Okay
Carl's office is very low-key it's a little brick building with a park outside
And as soon as I tell him
I have some questions about the hotel
He says I have got a story
For you
Two summers ago he says a group of guys walk into my office
They were all wearing suits and I'm sitting here with my blue jeans on
Talk about the AC hillbilly here
Up against it
The A-Team
The men introduce themselves
They are a real estate agent and engineer and art
Text and a lawyer I'd say he was probably around 6
2 years old
Very dignified
Balding
I like bald guys like myself can't you know
He had a three piece suit and at the time it was in
In the summer and the suit was
Kind of a beige color
The lawyer says he represents a company that wants to
To buy the hotel
And they want Carl's permission to build a heliport on the property
Heliport yes so helicopters can land at the hotel
Okay so crosses all right guys which company do you represent exactly
And lawyer claims
They wouldn't give me any information at all for the buyer
What's which I thought
What kind of crazy
You know who does that
How many times did you ask
I mean did you say you guys can you can you like tell me off the Record
I did it several times
But still they told me they
They were sworn
To keep them anonymous
Eventually the lawyer finally says
My client is a big multinational
But that's all he'll tell him
So mysterious
Until I went to spend the night
In the Hudson Valley Resort
Okay here we go
Going inside
There's the cafe that I used to work in oh my God
Good afternoon
Welcome to the Hudson Valley Resort and Spa I am checking in
Last name is King
ISO big multinational company right I wanted to
To find out if they had made any changes which Spruce the place up
Is the restaurant open anymore
Is the golf course still running
And then the woman at the front desk start
Shaking her head and backing away from me
So I had to my room
Elevators on the right
And at the other end of the hallway I hear someone yelling
Is everything okay
The key won't work again
I'm can I ask you a question
What do you think of the hotel
Hotels Music Row
Can you tell me why
The hotel
Probably hasn't been updated
Since the 1950
Patrick Swayze
Smartphone on that stage over
Patrick Swayze's mom performed
Penn Station
Louis st. George is a DJ and he's at the hotel working the weekend line dance
Did you know that the hotel got bought two years ago you know who bought it
Some Asian company calls dragons
If you go through the whole book
It's jacket
You said yeah who said that those are Japanese game
Hotel was not bought by Japanese
No it was not it was bought
By one of the biggest
Companies
Anywhere
It is called The Agency Group
It is
Unusual hello and welcome to planet money i'm noel king and i'm solihull
Today on the show a story about the
Big money sloshing around the world
And how it washes up in this Tiny Town
And
Who is controlling the faucet
7000 miles away
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is
Good days start with
Straight jeans
How did they make them so great Madewell starts with
Premium denim
Then offers men's and women's styles for seriously every
Also you can recycle any brand of jeans in a Madewell store
And they'll give you $20 off a new pair
They work with the blue jeans go green program
To turn old jeans
Housing insulation for communities in need
Terms apply
Ready to find your perfect fit
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
A couple weeks after those men in suits came to town
Count Carl Chipman the town supervisor
Is having his morning coffee and reading the
Any read the story about this
Company that bought the hotel
I looked it up online and I saw these people
Were involved in so many different
Things all over the world and I'm saying
Here they are in the car on
Actually I said that's a big what's going on here
Just pretty much my question to what is going on here
End
Noel
You and I
Cannot resist
So
We started looking at the HOA
A group and we googled it famous Carl
When you go to a Chinese website
It is a little hard at first to tell
What business
Theron
Experience and enjoy life we are headed to help you fulfill your dreams we are HLA
Cheap innovating and we shall love selflessly with the world hna group sharing
H&A is sharing love selflessly in
A lot of places
This is a big company
It started small it began as a tiny airline in 1990s
And Hainan province
Is China
That's like China's Hawaii beautiful island lots of Torres
And now
H&A owns
Hundreds of planes
End
Tons of other businesses
Hotels tourism companies
Logistics firms
A Chinese one of the 200 biggest companies in the world with annual revenue of over
50 billion dollars
According to Fortune Magazine
And all of this makes me even more curious
Why did such a Savvy important company
Buy up this run-down Hotel
So we called up someone who
Like us
Has developed
Kind of an obsession with a j
Serious question for you is all of this as crazy as it sounds
Yes
It's all as crazy as it sounds
Derek scissors is an expert in us China economic relations with the American Enterprise
That's a right-leaning thing
Think tank in DC
He got interested in China in the early 90s
Derek was doing his Doctorate in economics and China was restarting economic reform
Is trying to move away from communism and toward a market economy
So Derek was traveling around China on the
So they'd see the white guy
And they say what are you doing here and I said well
An economist and I'm traveling to learn about what's going on in southern China
And every single time I said that on the train I got to cry
People would start talking other people would come to the compartment or they
Pull me out of the compartment of when asked questions
God to you as an economist you were drawing a crowd you're like a rockstar
Yeah a small stadium Rockstar but
Derek becomes a China X
And he creates this thing called the China Global invest
Sprint tracker
Which
Track Chinese invest
Of 100 million dollars or more
Oh so you look at where big Chinese money is go that's right
At the time that Derek starts working on the tracker
China is encouraging Chinese businesses
To take their money
And invested overseas
Diversify
China had a policy
He called the go out policy
And the government was helping these companies
China has stayed on face
And they were getting very large and very cheap lines of credit
But still
Most investment
It's are not a hundred
Million dollars not big enough for Derek
There were very few Investments and I could remember them all there's an uptick in 2014 partly because the Chinese government eases
Is some restrictions on big Investments makes it even easier for companies to invest money overseas
One of those companies is
Which is showing up on Derek tracker
Not huge by
Is but a pretty steady state
And then
In August 2015
There's this shock
If it goes through China.
The head of the People's Bank of China
Does china's central bank
Mix in an ounce
It's about the Yuan
Chinese currency
He says
China wants the Yuan to be more
Flexible
Direct quote right Flex
Up until then China have been controlling it
It's currency pretty tightly so here's how things had
The Chinese one is packed very tightly to the US dollar so the dollar move the one just copies of dollar movement
Is that the one
The head of the People's Bank says
We don't want it to work like that in the
What is it
Well for one China has some goals for the Yuan
He wants the one to be in a tiny group of currencies that are designated as a leaked by the international monetary
Icims
It's like the dollar or the Euro or the yen
If you want is just
Copying the dollar Peg to the dollar the IMF is not going to treat it like a major currency
And there's something else going on
The economy in China is slowing down at
And unpinning from the dollar at this moment
That's going to make the Yuan
Cheaper
It'll devalue
Great for China because a cheaper Yuan means China can sell more stuff
Which will help with growth
But
If you're holding wine you're thinking
I don't like this
It's going to be worth less is going to have less buying power
Let me get out of it
I want to send my money overseas
M&g investments tracker start
CNN
A lot of activity lot of money leaving China
Well
Yes
It goes
Nuts
Chinese companies start buying up properties and Company
Is all over the world
Because they think that soon the Yuan will buy less
So they want to buy now while it's still strong
When Chinese company in particular catches Derek's eye
And that is
The hna group
H&A has something like a growth steroid
A couple weeks after the announcement hna starts out on a buying spree
Stand up spending billions of dollars in just about a year buying steak
Since I'm come
Buying other companies outright
And we're talkin about big companies
Hntb
0.5 billion dollar stake in Hilton Hotels
They buy all of the raddus
Hotels Dubai a multibillion-dollar stake in Deutsche Bank
The drops
6 billion dollars on American Tech
These are big thighs
But remember Noel
What we are here for is a mystery about
A small one
Can I tell you what else happened right after that in the summer of 2000
Is it seems like an open question lots of things app
And tell me okay
What's interesting to me is
Right after that and ask
Start with maid
H&H
Came
To Upstate New York and they spent on the order of 30
13 million dollars
For a
Decrepit Hotel
So
Does that seem too
Do you like Chinese money trying to get out of
The country into any asset is possum
Absolutely
Alright so there's our answer Derek thinks this is why AT&T bought the hotel they were
Buying everything they could
Getting money out of China
And investing some of it here in the US
What's a good
Yeah investment is invest
So we know why they bought it
The question is
Why haven't they done anything with it I was up there
And the place is still pretty run down
Still smells a little moldy
The red orange shining carpet is still there
Why haven't they put any money into the
We got some theories
After this
Support for this podcast in
The following message come from the windows weekly podcast at twit.tv
Get inside information on all things micro
With Leo Laporte Mary Jo Foley and
Paul Theroux
Learn what's happening with Windows Microsoft Office Enterprise Xbox + Hardware reviews and
Be a part of the discussion
And subscribe to Windows weekly on your favorite podcast
Aurat twit.tv / ww.w
The question is
Why buy this beat up old hotel and then not make it better
I mean H&H has billions of dollars
Okay well
Something else has been going on in
That has made it harder for H&A to spend money overseas
Send it in places like her haunts
What happened is the China realized
Just how much money was leaving the
Uh and he's not the only company that's been taking billions of dollars out of China One Chinese company bought up AMC
Beefeaters
Bought a 3.5 billion dollar steak in the movie studio that produced Godzilla and that Matt Damon movie
Great Wall another Chinese company bought the Waldorf
Astoria hearing
New York for almost
2 billion
$10
Different company paid more than a billion for
Club Med
Cars taken Cirque du Soleil
We know that the government
Because then in July of this year just a few months ago
The Communist parties
Official newspaper published
A front page APA
Very unusual
Warning about
Gray
Rhino to gray rhino
A Green Rhino is a
Problem on the horizon that you
But you don't acknowledge it until it is trapped
Abed said
China's got to watch out for gray rhinos in our economy like
Companies taking on too much debt
Making food list
And not long after that op-ed
China started to
Weasley
These companies
Here's Derek's
They didn't shout from the roof
We are imposing very strict Capital controls
This is like HMA getting a smack on the head and being told a guy
You're done that's right
And not just a Janae Lots
China has always had Capital controls and it sort of
Tightens and loosens the flow of money whenever it's having
Feelings and China does seem to be having some feeling or does this summer Chinese police detained
Did the head of the company that bought the Waldorf
Pistorius
The company that bought AMC Theaters
Had to publicly deny that their chairman was in Custer
They started selling off assets
Emphasis where you see
So
Clearly the confusion over what kind of economy China want
You companies are
Biggest capitalist success stories
The government supported them
And now it wants to rain them in
So where does all this leave hna the little airline that
It became a giant
Will a couple weeks back hna makes a weird mood
This man comes forward out of the blue
And he says
I need Chinese largest
Shareholder and I'm transferring my shares
Which is a third of this comfy
Into a charitable foundation in New York
Could you imagine Delta Airlines
Right age and they started as an airline saying
Hey we were this airline that charge people as much money as we could
But you know what we're going to do instead we're going to turn ourselves into the United
That's the equivalent to what hna said
There is no concrete explanation for what they're doing
But this move did highlight some things about hna
Including the fact that nobody really knows or understands
Who owns this company
Which ring some real alarm Bells
Some banks are refusing to lend to hna now
And look this company is
Massive
And they're investing a lot of money in the United
And no one really knows what they're up to
I mean they know what they're up to
But we try to talk to you
You guys and this week H&H seemed
Like they had agreed to an inch
But then they backed off and said maybe a statement on tape and then they backed off of that and changed it to
Suggest an email everyone is very busy
Yes we did email we emailed about capital
Controls and the odd move with
Charity
But right up at the top or making questions work
Where did you hear about kerhonkson New York and why did you buy this hotel
Hni got back to us
They did not answer any of the other questions but
They did say some things about the hotel
Hna group views the Hudson Valley Resort as a very desirable destination
For leisure travel and business
We're proud to be an employer in the kerhonkson community and grateful to operate in a local economy
Flash
Skilled hospitality
Professionals my hometown
Okay
Not bad. Very desirable destination for leisure travel them on
I mean I am not trying to knock your hometown
But can I say something here
H&A is a multibillion-dollar
Which we have to assume means they're pretty smart about travel interest
And make me some give me some good plays over the past couple of years
Some really big
Please
Yasso
Maybe they just haven't had time to focus on this one
Vacuumed it up along with all the other big stuff
And forgot about it
Preserved
Actually maybe that's what's keeping it going
Bingo and you know the night that I stayed there it eventually did get kind of packed you remember Louis from the start of the
Line dancing
Find a cussing
Just line dancing Louis
Red Knight
Who invited me down to the law
And you know we're in the middle of the mount
Tens and there is nothing to do outside
But inside the hotel
The atmosphere was so
There were these two young guys sitting at the piano playing with journey song
And it made me think about everything that this little hotel has
Use somebody gets a bad feeling in Beijing
M Hudson Valley Resort doesn't get a new car
It's at the very end of this long chain of decisions about currency
And aspirations of the Chinese government
And it seems like maybe H&H is forgotten
And in the meantime it's a lot of
I mean that night they never open the restaurant
But someone had brought in a bottle of wine and pay
Paper cups
And we're all sitting around laughing and yakiyan
And then somebody starts blasting country music on the speakers
And somebody taught me how to do a line dance
I'm not a very good life answer is what
And to be honest I could not think of a nicer place to spend the night
We have a lot of people to thank for today's episode
First to everyone in kerhonkson New York
Especially the town's biggest booster Crist
Depew
To rob schmitz NPR Shanghai correspondent and author of the book
Street of Eternal happiness
William Kirby a professor at Harvard Business School Nicholasville Rd of the Peterson Institute for international economics
Michelle Walker who coined the term gray Rhino and wrote a book about it called
The great Rhino and Andrew Collier author of Shadow Banking and the rise of capitalism in China
Thanks also to Elizabeth kulas mapreduce
Today's Show Bryant edits Planet Money and Alex
Goldmark is RC
Supervising
I'm finally home and I'm Noel King thanks for listening
Some people like to look at the world
Rose Colored Glasses
I prefer the lens of the social sciences
More than one
Almost literally
I'm shocked review.
Host of hidden brain
Each week we ask the questions
What does it mean to be human
And why do we do what we do
Listen long as we find the answer