When we decided to go see a rocket
I thought you know somehow we would get to stay and sort of close to it
You don't like on TV you see the rocket towering above you and all the
Flames and the smoke is billowing smoke everywhere
Of course the rocket people made a stand
Miles away
It makes sense they took his old converted school bus down a little dirt road
Anything let us out in the middle
Of nowhere
It's a field of scrub brush the Pacific Ocean is off in the distance
The only side of civilization is a couple of blue porta potties
Just in case
But somewhere just over the ridge is one of Humanity's greatest
Achievement
A rock
It is called the Minotaur C
It is 100
Feet tall
And it is the rocket we've been waiting to see for the last
8 months
Worth $40
Carrying a bunch of very sophisticated satellite
But everyone stands around and acts like oh this is no
One of the executives from the rocket company John steinmeier
You make it sound
Routine
It's been a long period of time where we worked with the customer denigrate
Their satellites on to our launch vehicle make sure everything's compatible and everything will work well once they're deployed
You use all these words like vehicle but that's like a rocket
If rocket is more exciting we can call them Rockets
What is the space business boring
Is good that's what they're doing
Happy
And there is no embarrassing video footage of a rocket exploding overhead
The only drama out here comes over a set of walkie talkies
That is the only way we know what's going on
Nominal is this our favorite word
Everything is okay
Nominal
I think the most sort of
Call if there's a word that is calmer than nominal I've never heard it
So someone says it is non nominal
Probably off nominal
Domino's
Previous run not nominal
We were excited we were
Taking selfies with snake in the bottle
Champagne might be nominal for everybody else
This might be the single biggest moment in Planet Money history
Because just over that Horizon
On top
Of the Minotaur C rocket
Is
The planet
Money satellite
It is a little hunk of technology that we have adopt
We have been following for month
We've even etched the waveform
Of our voices are
Voices on the side of the satellite
If this actually works
Play nobody's going to space
1 minutes 1 minute
I really don't like I'm most
Afraid
I'm most afraid that it's just going to be boring
Silently
Hello and welcome to Planet Money Robert Smith
Window podcast has gone
Before
Specs
This crazy stunt a Planet Money satellite would never
Impossible
Space was so expensive that only governments and corporations could afford to launch a saddle
But everything is changing in the space business right now
Private rocket companies are driving down the price of launches satellites have shrunk
So much
You can hold them in the palm of your hand
He's becoming so easy
Even we can do it
So over the next few episodes of Planet Money
We're going to try to make sense of this new industry by going to space ourselves
Getting a satellite took this from rural Kentucky to Silicon Valley
To New Zealand and there are so many things that can go wrong, can you really build a working satellite on the cheap
Even if you do what can a satellite do in space
And you need to come up with a mission
What is after all this work
The rocket
The rocket just
Disappeared off the radar
We have negative telemetry
That means it's lost contact with it I think
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Did you come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org
Okay we have to be honest with you
The Planet Money satellite started out as a joke around the office
About eight months ago we were brainstorming new project
You may remember that planet money already made it
T-shirt
Fold around the globe
We did a project where we drilled for oil and turned it into
Oh you know what's next
Space
Arthur Bryant had just seen something about a SpaceX
Launch on the
The little news TV that that are elevate
I will laughed and I immediately started to sketch a mission patch
You know every space mission has a
The patch forts jumpsuits
You know we could put a squirrel on it and our names of mission patch
Emeril excited talking about it but it seems
Really impossible I mean first of all we
You obviously weren't going to
It no
Even a satellite receiver
Really out of Arlo
They're only a couple thousand active satellites in orbit and they're almost exclusively owned by like
Spy agencies
Governments and multibillion-dollar
Imagine what it takes two
Build one of these sound like
I know it's before but they are huge
What kind of satellites that provide
GPS for phones or cable
No TV or predict the weather
Can be as big as a school bus
It's so complicated so expensive they can cost
Half billion dollars
But one of our producers Elizabeth coolest was really captivated by this and she decided to look in
Super
And she said
Toilet Lizbeth coming here what did they tell you
They said
It is actually the perfect time
To go to space
We are in the middle of
Satellite Revolution
The satellites are getting smaller
And cheaper and it's easy to get to
Too Faced
It's like the early days
Official computers when internet was invented
It is
Wild out
Here right now and
We can get it on
I still wasn't completely
Sure that it was
Possible but you know I thought fun
Fight will get a guide
Maybe someone who can show us
A possible way
Into this
Anyone Kentucky but one person in particular
Apparently that the Steve Jobs
What's of the satellite Revolution
Use the guy who showed the world
Anyone could go to space
He works in Kentucky his name is Bob Quick's when we first spot Professor Twigs he is surrounded by
Bike third grade
Few kids run around
It is field trip day at the Space Science Center at Morehead State University interview then
Future graduate students
Spartacus wife here and
Waves his hands around me
Excitement
Maybe for kids but he reminds me of one of those at Owl character
As an early Pioneer in satellites
He could be running a billion-dollar
But he decided to stay in Academia and instead what he does is get students
Excited about
It's kind of like jump starting a car you know I think I'm like that
The guy with the battery pack on my back and I go around to the students and I jump start
The students and once they get running
Then I can stand out on the road and they they learn more on their own than I can teach
And that is how Bob changed
The satellite industry
In the late 1990s he was teaching graduate engineering students at Stanford
Any figured they would be way more excited about designing satellites
If they actually got
To build one in
Class
Something is big
Complicated the satellite
This is a tough assignment
The bigger it is some more things that they want to put in it and they just keep
Designing old we can add this and we can add that but was working with another researcher from University of down the road Cal Poly
It was Jordy push soiree
And what if they give the students
A constraint
A tiny box
They had to fit all of the electronics in
Soda Factory
So it goes tattoo store in Mountain View California
One of the places
Like it Container Store
You know they sell all kinds of boxes you know that you're going to put the
Your favorite baseball in or your favorite basketball up and down the aisle
Saying too big too big too small too small and then you saw I saw
French boxer
The time you know there was the Beanie Baby craze
So that was the box that they put the beanie babies and you know you bought get a beanie baby and display it on the shelves or
The satellite started from a beanie baby box
Luckily Bob did not call his invention apt
Never name your technology after a
Instead he called it the cube satellite
Cubesat
And the original cubesat is inside the trophy case at Morehead State University
Bob's boss Ben malphrus
Drags us over
The city is so proud of this Dusty
The plastic Cube
And this is a great opportunity because the original model I predict one day will be in the Smithsonian
It says
Anything you want your satellite to do
Has to fit in
You can't add more parts make a satellite bigger
You students
How to think smaller
The general Aerospace industry said that's the dumbest idea we've ever seen those academic geyser
We're out of their mind because it's so small it's not useful for any
Remember the Aerospace industry was sending up satellites
Besides
Of a box and here's this researcher holding up something a little larger than a Rubik's Cube and saying
This is satellite to
It didn't make any sense
This was not an evolution to a slightly smaller product
This was a rebel
Everything about what was inside of a satellite
Add to beer
And this way to State an academic exercise for the fines to
Stanford
Except there was this other Revolution going on at the same time
This was the early 2000
And very early smartphones
We're just being invented
And all those tiny phone transmitters
And processors
Cameras
Just happened to fit into a beanie baby box
All the sudden satellites
We're so small that students could take risks they could try new things they could design a tiny satellite to take
The Arctic
Or measure magnetic
Weaves
Earthquakes
And when you take risks with a new technology that's
When business Innovation happen
The personal computer Revolution didn't start when
Computers were the size of an entire room
It started with computers were small enough
Play around
Take risks with in a garage
That's how Apple started
Plymouth Satellite
Private companies looked at this and they said
I can think of a million things to do with a
Cubesat remembers visiting a company recently in San Francisco called planet
They make satellites that
The Earth and they have almost in assembly line process now
For making cubes
It's funded
Go in there and see you
Shelf
50 satellite setting on it never thought I'd see that how long would that it taking you back in the day
Oh
My the right we were building at almost 50 years
It's pretty easy
If you like even a podcast could build their own Cube satellite they do make kits for this
I need to probably make something that you know goes beep beep beep in space for under $10,000
Beeping in space that's cool right
That's better than beeping on the go
I thought we have a satellite that
Do something cool like
Pictures of Norco
Realtor
Cargo ships
Monitor global warming
Yeah for that level of satellite we're going to have to make some difficult
We're going to need to go shopping
For our very own
Cubesat
There is apparently a Walmart
Of satellites
It is the small satellite conference
In Logan Utah
Like small satellite conference or small satellite
Conference the satellites are small
The conference
Is map
Oh my God it's a robot it's a robot
I think it's a robot
Once Upon a Time the small satellite conference
Was for a cat
Scientists were building Hardware
Data analyst
And they are still here going to want students to
But these days you can smell the money in the air
The big rocket companies are here SpaceX
Blue origin rocket lab
It'll be 20 ft you can stop by a booth of some startup satellite
Giving away a little
Light up keychain
Foam Rockets
Is Bob's tiny cubesats are everywhere
It is an industry standard now
You can get a single box it is called A1 you as in 1 Beanie Baby unit
So just as basic as the basic basically I'm holding my hand it's like a frame with some Electronics in it
Is $10,000
Of course then you have to fill up
Cubesat their boots that will sell you
Cameras radiation monitors
Mike Creech at the booth for millennium Space Systems
Chesapeake inexpensive
Do you have to have power you need some sort of computer
You need a way to navigate know where you are in the space in the sky
And those things just take time to develop every single mission is unique
In that case you might want to upgrade to a 3
You satellite
As in
3 Beanie Baby
Yeah in the booth for the company Blue Canyon
Cool shiny floor models
So I asked your head if we wanted your
Basic model
Like you're just your cheapest strip down
Box with some Electronics
What range of cost are we talking to
Equipment is
Play the highest and that you're going to find in this category
Peerless Steel
Fraction the price of a traditional space
Dorothy want to drop the sticker price on me what's going to be
A million
Under million
Mapreduce Elizabeth
Laughing out loud at that price tag
I mean compared to the half-billion-dollar community
Location satellite pizarra Barton
But we were thinking maybe more in the lake
Thousands or
Hundreds of dollars range like I was crazy
Where
Satellite
It's always on eBay
Could always play the nonprofit
But card you know the sort of charity
Impulse
So the conference about who might
Linda Sadler
You know for journalistic purposes allow us to adopt one for short mission
We called everybody who makes
Satellite saying Hey Joe mixer satellite can we
Jump on board with your satellite we bagged tea bags
We need to put our name on a saddle
Maybe do something cool with it
And what company said
Let's talk about
Why don't you drop by our office
Certain San Francisco
And we can discuss
It was in fact the company the bobbed wigs
Had mentioned that he visit in San Francisco the company with
The strangely similar name to ours
Planet
Felt like this was a good sign
It's open
Planet San Francisco office is right down the street from the headquarters of
Twitter and Uber
And they're going for the same Tech startup vibe
Although because it is space Hardware
I have to sign a promise not to steal any military Secret
Confidential information show me any technical non-tech like my Apple terms of service contract
Did not read the fine print signed it anyway
And now I can legally in
Enjoy my time
It starts at Mission Control with the launch director
Which sounds way more serious than it is
Exception is 29 years old
Pretty laid-back guy
Admission control looks like the back of a Best Buy a budget
TVs on the wall and
Hardware piled on the desks
We have satellites lying around everywhere
Four five of them in a cabinet here yes and that's just for starters so
There's another cabinet full of satellites are there
Now you're just showing off
The reason we have so many is the planets
Business model
Changing the way we
We've all seen those satellite photos on
Google Maps satellite
Beastly only get a good shot of your house
What planet thought
All these little cubesat
Why wait for one big
Satellite to tremble by
Why not launch hundreds
Small one
Delta faster launch them faster take more risks
The Cuban way
Mike shows me a TV and back with an image of the
And you can see all these little.
Bt200 up
Each one
Is a satellite
Planet has an orbit
Over Hawaii
Alaska
Over the North Pole of a big string of satellites going down over the United Kingdom looks
Play through
France Spain Hospital satellite up in space
300 miles
Anywhere around the globe
The North Pole
To the South Pole
The back to the North Pole again every 90 minutes
Pickle pictures the whole Way North
South North Pole South Pole
If you could float in space and see it
It would look like
What would appear to be like a String of Pearls
Going over roughly the North Pole from North to South
And as the String of Pearls is rotating in its orbit
The Earth is rotating underneath
And so that
That line of satellites axes a line scanner
And so they're slowly sweeping across the Earth's surface every 24 hours
And that enables us to get it
An image of every place
A picture of almost every place on Earth
Every 24 hours
The way it works is it no matter where you are in Earth around
10 in the morning just getting coffee
There is almost certainly a
Planet satellite
Whizzing by over your head and taking a picture it is
Mine
And you know what put for started to launch a satellite to
A few years ago
They would name each one and heavy
Speak ceremonies
Now they have so many
It is totally
Working
Show routine
Would a company like this even notice
If Public Radio podcast just you know
Borrowed a satellite
For a little while
Maybe we could push a couple
Tote bags
We have one
I mean
You know just to borrow it
No money Changing Hands no contract
Just a sort of
Temporary adoption
And some calls for me to Camanche
The chain and they said
How about satellite 0f 1C
I went down to the lab
To see it
Okay so welcome to the factory
We need to put on coat
But we can help you with that
If I meet someone who's recognizable from all of the space exploration movies
The guy who builds
The satellites
He's wearing a bow tie
Dental lab coat
His name is Chester Gilmore
And this is Planet Money satellite
This is your adopted spacecraft
So they tell me
I don't know what to say that means he's gorgeous
Look at shiny
Oh okay so how how do you normally describe the size of it
About the size of a loaf of bread
Or you know media a shoebox for like ballet slipper very very nice elegant and crap
Capable ballets
Just two dudes talking about ballet slippers
I'm technically this is a 3
You that's three Beanie Baby box
It is the direct descendant of Bob wigs trip to a container store
Can I pick it up
Yes
Pause to remember
Well yeah because this is actually going to go into space
So anywhere else they would probably tell you absolutely not you can never pick up
Satellite but yes you can pick up the satellite
I'll ask you to pick it up like this
I was just allowed to touch the edges and when I pick it up it is
Super deaf you don't like
Picking up a baby
Okay
And if you break it you buy it
Joking exercise kinda
These things are pretty tough
You told me the story about one time when they were launching
A rocket
With these little cubesats in it and the rocket
Blew up
It blew up after launch
And satellites just like this would rain down all over the
Let me turn them on and they all work
Chester opens up the metal casing and shows me inside as lots of
Gold Parts but basically it's a big
Camera like one of those cameras with the giant lens you see on the sidelines
Sporting events
A normal lens is the electronic
A little antenna to send the photos back to Earth
Little gizmos that allow you to
Herne the satellites
Spirit a bit
Just as you can put together the whole thing in about 4 hours
Amazing can go from assembly to testing to space in a matter of
And that's the cutest whole new space
The idea is to move fast
Innovate
Quickly satellites like
Lick iPhone
Write a release a bunch into space
And then you two months later they come up with redesigns and updates
They launched some more and then some more and it's amore
The telescope quick
And then after a few years
After a few years back
Chester says one day you'll be looking at a photo from a satellite and you'll notice that the images of the Earth are getting closer
And closer
I'm closer
So the first thing that happens is our imagery gets better
Because we're closer
If a good-news-bad-news situation
Yeah it's like
You're talking to the whole time it's going you can talk to you the whole time it's going down
And the Earth gets closer and closer the images get better and better and then
But we all make the noise quiet quiet
Raise a glass
The death of satellite is treated as a kind of Celebration because it allows planet to replace that satellite
With a better
With more features
Even if we managed to get little zero f1c
The Planet Money satellite into space
It is not going to have long till
So we have to make the most
David short beautiful life
Manchester let me in on a little secret
Making a satellite
Pretty straightforward
Figuring out how to get it into space and what to do with it once it's there
That part
It's more complicated
Next time on Planet Money
What can you do
With a brand new satellite
What are these new companies with billions of dollars worth of
Tiny spacecraft even doing in the sky above our heads
What will be the mission
40 f
1 C
This message comes from NPR sponsor game
The Bold way to steady growth
People often think of nobodies are too conservative
Too complex or only for retirees
But annuity
These can be a smart way to Head Market risk and earn guaranteed returns
Game Bridge aims to change the game
By offering simplified annuities in a Sleek digital experience that replaces fine print and phone.
With clear conditions and a direct
Loafy model
Learn more at gamebridge. Life
8 / NPR
Game Bridge
Which is not available in all states
Any thoughts on what planet money's little 0f 1C satellite should do
Gmail
Planet Money at npr.org
You can also find us on Twitter or Facebook
And I'll be posting some behind-the-scenes photos of our satellite Adventure on my Instagram
I'm at Radio Smith
Stacy I should warn our listeners
That
My original Dream
Came a reality beautiful
Lay Your Eyes On The Planet Money
Space mission
Patch oh my gosh that is a really sharp looking Patrick at the squirrel holding a little microphone and our satellite
Play there's zero f1c
Of course our logo is on there will tell you how to get one
In
A later episode
Today's episode
And this entire series was produced by a lizard
Class with an assist from Nick
Alex goldmark azar supervising producer brian dorsett and it's the show
Special things today to our friends at Auburn University jambore singer and Michael Fogel
Also thanks to Michael stonecipher mattcraft Rachel home
And pepper Hammond who help set things up
With planet
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith and Robert Smith
Thanks for letting
We have to figure out what we're going to write on side of ourselves
Oh
Okay
So we can draw something we can put the name of The Craft
Sky's the limit sky's the limit at all
I thought you were saying at the title
Not a terrible time
WeChat
Some sort of some sort of phrase insurgents firing phrase like to the Stars
Where are you at
Through difficulty to the Stars
What is this
The Latin phrase per ardua Ad Astra
Do difficulty to the start of Kansas but is also my personal model for many years
I was just come up with name
The Starship free enterprise
Good
That's a good one
Baby productivity Rising
Productivity Rising globalization and Beyond
It literally goes around the Earth every 90 minutes
And Beyond MP3
Capital flight
Oh Capital flights not bad
No such thing as a free lunch
Free lunch is not bad
Small sat Big Data
I mean small set Big Data
I like how you translated
IPM
3cpo
I will burn up
I like that
Do maybe instead of October not maybe it's money to burn
Money to burn
Nice
Okay money to burn and then I'm going to raise money to buy
So Stacy this is
What I'm afraid of witches we came up with like a bunch of good
Jokey names
What do we really want to say them for like
Four episode
Right
They can lose steam quickly
So I'm thinking we should go with something simple
A classic
Okay I want to lay this on you
Pod1
I like it
It's got a lot of potential
Epictetus Reddit
Do not