Warning
Today Show has racial slurs and sexually explicit
Midterms
Simonton grub in San Diego
He was Chinese American and some have that made it tough
It was when I was in Middle School
And I had to stay behind cuz I was cleaning up
The sports equipment
Next thing you know I was
Pushed to the ground
And they were kicking me
I'm punching me over and over again throwing sand in my face they kept yelling at me
Kept saying
Japna capsuling gook
At one point I finally just snapped and I said you know what I'm a chink
I can be going to be racist at least do it correctly
That moment
As always stuck with him
He grew up move to Oregon and he started a band
When he was trying to figure out what to name the band
Do you want to find something that sounded like a band
But it also said something about being Asian
Something that asserted his ID
So that's my friends around Portland
What's something you think
All Asians have in common
They would immediately say slanted eyes
I found fascinating because I thought well you know it's not true
So he decides
Disease that stereotype
Own it
And turn it into something completely different
He ends up naming his van
Display the band starts playing gigs around Portland
Play songs like this
They weren't just musicians who happen to be Asian they were
Super into being Asian they raise money for families in North Korea
Racism Workshop
Anime convention
Things are going great
The band started touring more
But then Simon discovered
They were other bands that were also calling themselves
Office lamps
I was in Tucson Arizona
For some fans of art bought tickets to see
I thought it was us
It was a local band also call this late
So in 2010 Simon did what artists and for that matter companies do when there is confusion over there now
He applied to register a trademark with the Federal
So that he could have some control over who could use the name
The Slants
A few months later he got a call from his lawyer
SSA Simon we got a problem with your application
Sammy. Maybe I submitted the wrong paperwork or something so no all that's fine
But he said
The Trademark Office rejected your application because it said
It's
Disparaging two persons of Asian descent
And I remember I took a moment to
Think about
The term disparaging
What does it mean what I think it means
And then I'm like
Wait a second are they single racist to Asian people
Annie sez
Yes
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I melt the chain
An object ghosting
There is a government agent
I have to make lots of decisions about
Hate speech
Racial slurs homophobic put-downs and sex
Simon Tam got into a fight
Is agency a fight about free speech
And it went all the way to the Supreme Court
Put the kids to bed
Types of horses
Cuz it's going to get a little
Draya Michele
We're talking about the US patent and trademark
A quick shout-out to one of our sponsors who brings you this message Caspar asleep brand that offers obsessively
Engineered mattress has an in-house team of Engineers develop Casper supportive memory foam
So it has just the right sink and bounce
Try Casper for a hundred nights risk-free in your own home and if you don't love it they'll pick it up and refund you
Get $50 toward any match
Purchase by visiting casper.com
Planet Money and use promo code Planet Money
Terms and conditions apply
When Simon filed a trademark
Location in 20
And it went to Alexandria Virginia
Home of the US patent
And trademark office
Land looking government building and you're in a
Small office with a window that doesn't open
Rebecca Gunn is a trademark lawyer
Current used to work in that
She didn't handle Simon's applique
But you handled the thousands
It was her job to decide whether to approve those out
You had to follow a federal law that lets the government reject
Trademarks that quote images
Barrage
There is government speech Happening Here
And I think it is
A compelling government interest
That the government is not speaking in a way
That
Makes people think the government is okay
With the content of what is being expressed
In other words when the federal government
Agrees to register at
It is putting a stamp on an a
Like almost literally you know when you see that that little capital r with a circle around it next to a product
That is the government thing
Yes we agree to register this trademark and we're using the power of federal law.
So the question Rebecca had to answer was
When does the government give its
Stamp of approval
And when was something just too offensive
And she didn't have much time to make
You're roughly given an hour
To examine a file and sometimes some files will take more
And sometimes some files will take glass
An hour that's like zero time you're talking about a government program
That has thousands of applications
Is here
And people on the outside
Are very cranky
When their applications do not get processed
As quickly as possible
I have to speak with the lawyer at the Trademark Office who made the call in Simon's case
To look at his application and said
The Slants
We're not going to give that are
Stamp of approval
But the Trademark Office declined my request for an interview
So I ask someone else to walk me through the reject
I'm Ron Coleman
I'm a lawyer
And who's your client
Can you say that one more time
Simon Tam
Of the Slants the way
The Slants
The Slants I said it and I'm very comfortable saying it
Watch me through that rejection letter from the trademark office
And he showed me the very first Authority
Cited in the region
Urban Dictionary
Scholarly resource for you
If you've never seen it it's online its what
Parents used to look up
Playing they hear their kids use
Answers Ron Coleman reading how Urban Dictionary
Define slang
A derogatory term used to refer to those of Asian descent
Urban Dictionary is an open forum
Anyone
No matter how offensive
Ting Ting Ting look at that Slim
$5 sucky sucky
Who is this by Gangsta Gangsta
When Simon Tam saw that this was the rest
From the US patent and trademark office
You can believe
It was just one of those
Really going to serial moments that
Wow
Kind of
Stuff that you could not use in a junior high
Classroom the sport an essay was now being used by the federal government to deny me rights
Sir Simon starts
Fighting with a trademark
He makes a case for how he's using Slants in a way that celebrates Asian-American identity
Include statements from leaders of Asian American organizations and news stories about the band's activism
But the trademark of his just keeps saying no just keeps
Denying his
At one point they sent him a photocopy page from a 20 year old book called forbidden American
The killer entry
Slant a derogatory nickname for any Oriental
From Bring It
They just called Asian people orientals in the Forbidden English book
Well that's a very nice point that you make
But in 1995 I think that's what we were still saying maybe we were
But he were
Alright Elsa
I want to say at this point in the show
Ridiculous
But it's not just
The whatever some random twenty-year-old book it's not just Urban Dictionary I brought in
The paper dictionary that we have in the office
It's the New Oxford American dictionary
Okay I'm going to open it to slam
Slang
Swimsuits
One of the definitions
Says
Slant
Derogatory
Contemptuous term for an East Asian or Southeast Asian
This is Judo
About a story that is saying slant is derogatory
If this is in the dictionary like
Why
Why are the lawyers at the Trademark Office citing some random old bukit sighting Urban DIC
That's the way the law works
The trademark office is supposed to reject an application
If it uses a term that is disparaging to what's called a
Stantial
Composite
Of some group of people so in this case
A substantial composite
A vision
People of Asian descent
So the trademark office lawyer
Is fighting all these different sources to
Try to show this idea that Slants
Is derogatory
Into widespread amount of people that get it out there it's out there in lots of different place yet feeling that it's derogatory
Rebecca gone the lawyer who used
To work at the trademark office
She told me about this one case
That really illustrates
The case was over
The word
Keep
He'd people the flu against Jewish people like
Exactly and it's also the name of a magazine by and for Jews
And when Rebecca was working at the trademark office
He applied for a trademark registration
I had a subscription to heat magazine right so I was not offended
Clearly because I had a subscription
Rebecca wasn't the lawyer assigned to that case but because she's Jewish one of her colleagues asked her what she thought
I am sure
That grandmothers
And
Other folks in the community
Probably did
Does it feel the heat
It's probably
Offensive because they grew up with stories of
Their grandparents
Getting beaten up
And
Having that
Insults hurled at the
So she said even though I subscribe to this magazine
I don't think we should give the name he
The federal government stamp of approval
She told her colleagues
We should deny the application and
What happened
This is
Clearly not
Science right doesn't like well let's think about it
Colleagues
And this the system can lead to
What's he like really inconsistent out
Uses in particular with trademarks that are sexually
Like for example Rebecca told me she personally rejected a trademark for the phrase meatholes
Because she thought it was too dirty
But they're all these other super explicit sexual terms that have been approved by the
I talked to Megan Carpenter
Study this and she listed off a bunch of these approved term
Dirty b****
Drunk ass b******
Edible crotchless gummy panties
Egotistical
Where some lawyer at the government has looked at an application and said okay you got it registered
Flea market hookers
Fupa pouch
Fustercluck
Mad in the USA
Okay
Make a thing a few things are going on
1 is
The process is just a pretty random process
It depends on what your lawyer at the trademark office gets assigned to your case but she's also saying
You see meaningful changes as
Societal sensibilities change
I do think we've seen an n
A growing acceptance of terms as
Language evolved
Take picture
Used to be a slur for gate
People and used to get rejected a lot by the Traymore
Ben gay people talk talk the word back you know there was like a slogan we're here we're queer
The word
Stop being defensive
And the Trademark Office started saying yes more often to trademarks that use the word
And that is what Simon Tam wants to do
The same thing that gay people do with queer he wants to take the word back
Abraham this fight over the trademark
Bombs away to do that
Eating
The federal government doesn't get to decide what
Offensive to Asian Americans
To decide for ourselves
Simon becomes upset
Start spending 30 40 hours a week on the case
Start cutting back his time on music
Just so we can work on the key
I like I have my attorney on speed dial
He was in my
Of my friends and family
5 Willis like
That's how often we were talking
Multiple emails every single day like
Hundreds of emails between us
But by the end of 2011 it's clear to Simon that he is never going to convince the
The trademark office they just keep saying no
So Simon and his lawyers
They come up with a new plan
A new strategy
And this one is is much more ambitious
It's not just about the words
They decide they're going to attack
The law is
Self
They start to argue
That rule that says the government can deny trademark registration for disparaging term
That rule itself
Is a violation of the First Amendment violates
Our right to free speech
I talked about this with Ron Coleman
Simon's lawyer
And I should just say that
Ron is Jewish and he's been called names
So I wanted to know personally how far would he go with his first amendment argument
Is there any word
You don't think should
Ever betrayed me
Where we are at the society now we're constitutional law is in the year 2017
There can be
No
Word
And no image that cannot be registered as a trademark
No word
So Kate
Kikes
That can be registered
Absolutely
What a chink
Course
Wet vac
If you could
Demonstrate that it is
Functioning as a trademark another words you have selling a product or offering a service in connection with it
If a driver
Ron and Simon take this first
An argument.
And they lose
But the appeal
And in 2015 a federal appeals court agrees with
They find that the trademark law is unconstitutional
That it does file
Andy Obama administration appealed bats
And the Supreme Court agreed to take the case
The oral argument in the case was in January
And of course Simon went to Washington DC
2 days before the plants had a little concert on the steps
The Supreme Court
And then it was the morning
Simon went into the courtroom
And her Chief Justice John Roberts
Announce
Your arguments first this morning in case 15 1293
Lee vs. Tam
Simon sitting bear wearing his lucky dinosaur song
You thinking about
All the work he's done on this case
How it had taken over his entire life
And he realizes at that moment
It's all come down to this
I was just
I guess filled with too much emotion to even like
Think clearly for that for that
For the first few moments anyway I was I did
Me for me
Thinking
Almost a decade of my life is culminating to like this 55 minute argument
Then I have a question
At one point Justice Sotomayor seems to attack Simon's First Amendment
No one stopping your client
From calling itself the slabs
No one stopping them
From advertising themselves that way
Or signing contracts that way or engaging in any activity
But just go ahead
Call yourself to slam put on T-shirts shouted from the rooftop
The trademark office
But at another Point Justice
Haggens used to come in on the other side
Even in a government program even assuming that
Pictures of point
There's a part of First Amendment law that says the government shouldn't say
Some viewpoints are okay
But others are not
It's something called Viewpoint discrimination
I'm saying here is that maybe the government might be doing this by saying
Some trademarks are good While others
Or disparaging
You see the point
The point is that I can say good things
What about something
But I can't say bad things about something
And I would have thought that was a fairly classic case of people and discrimination
It's going back and forth
You know there
Debating these
Theoretical First Amendment implications
Assignment the key moment that morning
Went back to something that was
It was really much more
It went back to the reason he decided to call his band the slam
At one point
Justice Ruth Bader Ginsburg
Speaks in the room goes silent
If it's not count at all
Everyone
Nose
History classes using this term
But
Completed
It was like at that moment I'd like
She gets it she knows what we're trying to do
And then less than an hour after the argument started
Colorful
Jesus submitted
The Supreme Court's decision in the states is expected any day
Sometime in the next
A lot of people are watching this
Really close
Including the Washington
The football team
A few years back the Trademark Office cancel the team's trademark registration for Redskins
The office said that's a disparaging term so now the teams rooting for Simon.
They even filed an amicus
That's illegal equivalent of saying we're totally
Ebro
How do you feel about being on the same side as the Washington Redskins
I don't think I'm on the same side as the
I think the
Team name is racist
I I think it's I think
That Native Americans have made it
Womanly clear how they feel
About not only that team
But all sports in general that use human beings as mascot
What is as
The point of the first amendment is to protect people who don't agree with
That's how free switch work
As a person of color
Who has experienced a lot of racial discrimination in
And the target
A lot of racial slurs second I have to register trademark before I can call you a chink
They just go ahead and do it
Races are going to be racist whether they have a registration or not
The Slants recently released the song
Called from the heart
Simon calls it an open letter to the US patent and trademark office
Here in a minute
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Capital One
Keep your credit score at peace with a credit wise app from Capital One
Get alerts each time your credit is pulled and when your TransUnion credit report changes
Plus it's free for everyone download the creditwise app today
If you want to get in touch you can email us at Planet Money at npr.org or you can find us on Facebook or Twitter
And for those of you listening in the New York area we would love to see you in person
Planet Money will be performing on stage at the
Heat Festival
It's a night of live podcast
Storytelling
June 10th in Brooklyn
Rental at tps.org
Our show today was produced by Nick Fountain the editor is Bryant urstadt and are supervising producer is Alex
I'm Jacob.
And I'm Elsa Chang
Here's the Slants
At all
No UTA change something so strange
Highway