The other day I caught this guy Steve Dion
She lives out
In Las Vegas
Three decades he worth
At a professional game
And I was trying to get him to explain a few things to me about sports
But we had to completely stop the in
Hey can you do me a favor
Could you please tell my wife
I'm not talkin
Angel cop
Ski fumble around for a second
Then put me on speakerphone
I am as as he I'm not a cop I'm a journalist with National Public Radio
I'm very complex
It wasn't just
Paranoid
That made Steve's wife think I might be
A cop
A few years back
Police were listening into a lot of Steve's phone calls
Including one in which he arranged for a guy to meet him in a parking lot of the Palms Casino in Las Vegas
With a bag
Filled with money
How much money are we talking about
It was either 150 or 200000
In cash
Ncash
She got in trouble for that one he was arrested he spent a few nights in jail
And Steve says
It was all a big misunderstanding
Make that money
Wichita a loan from a friend of his
Completely legal
People act like
This is some kind of a nefarious transaction
Because people are meeting
Stack the money in it
Parking lot
But the nature of
Professional
Gambling
In Las Vegas is
Yes put up the cash
Tibet
The Police tour
Reddit differ
They say
That bag of cash was not just your run-of-the-mill casino parking lot hand off
But evidence of an international conspiracy
Involving not only a few gamblers
One of the most respected firms on wall
Hello and welcome to Planet Money
I'm Keith Romer
Draya Michele bags
Filled with cash
A lot of bags
And a lot of cash
All of these bags
The cash that is money people want to bet on
Sports
But it is basically illegal to bet on Sports anywhere in the country outside the stadium in
Gamblers though do not always care so much about the law they just want to get their best down
Casinos in Las Vegas figure this out years ago
Couple years back
Wall Street figured it out to
And they wanted it
We got a story about Wall Street guys trying to act
Gamblers
Gamblers find act like Wall Street guys
And a cop from New York City trying to figure out
Just where all those bags of cashword
We'd like to say a quick thank you and share a message from one of our sponsor
Morgan Stanley
Who helped First Solar raise capital
How to expand and
Newmarket
Now regions from the Atacama Desert in Chile
Guru India have access
The queen
Renewable energy
First Solar is enabling a world
Powered by reliable and affordable solar electric
Global business
It's something to see
Capital
Creates light
Mu place
Morad morganstanley.com
First Solar
Morgan Stanley
Camco LLC
Member sipi
The story starts with a Wall Street guy named Ali-A Medias
Back in the 1960s
Amita's went to a Catholic High School
Brooklyn
He's just not that into
Enamored with the horse racing
Used to cut
My classes
Go to Aqueduct
Everyday I meet us did that interview with a gambling expert name David Schwartz.
Back in 2011
We left a bunch of voicemails for a meet us but he didn't call us back
I mean just got a job as a horse trainer
But eventually gave up on the ponies and went to work on Wall Street at a firm called cancer fits
Entry level as a clerk in the back office
Eventually became a broker and then a manager and then wind up a chance of child
Cheryl second highest CEO to determine
In every picture you can find Lee meet us he looks kind exactly like what you want to Wall Street
Executive to look
Spalding
Hair slicked back
You got a big smile or not really a smile
Cantor Fitzgerald has been around since the 1940s
They've always been a really big player in the bond
In about 10 years ago a media started thinking about how to take the lessons
Keep learned buying and selling bonds
And apply them to other businesses
Cancer
Has always taken a look at low Mark and high-volume businesses
Agent by technology
What are you saying there is if you're selling Bond you only going to make it
I need percentage on each sale
So the idea is to sell a lot of bonds
I mean is finally found another business that follows the same model
It kind of went back to his days of
The horse track in Brooklyn
The new business was book made
Couple quick definitions here bookmaker also known as
The Boogie that
The person who takes the people's bets on a football game or basketball game
Sportsbook that's
The place where those bets get
So in 2009 and has created a new book making company out in Las Vegas
He called it Canter game
And before too long cancer gave me was up and running an eight
Casinos around the city
They got the signs made up they got
Sweet new ads what happens when Wall Street technology hits Las Vegas
Instant sports betting throughout the game
Decanter technology
Bathing suits power walking around a pool holding tablet
Academy Sports books betters didn't have to go to the window anymore
Now they can just bet on a tablet right from their Casino account
Before cancer you could only bet before a game started
Now we be
Huge breakthrough in cancer technology
You can bet on games
As they were happy
And people in Las Vegas
Love this
Cancer had a long-term plan
That was to get a technology up and running in case
Gambling lobbyists ever convinced Congress
To legalize gambling outside of Nevada
Because right now that's the only place it's
Only in Nevada
And I setting up computer betting outside Nevada
Contra would be ready to expand to the entire country
Which is every Sports books
Dream
You want to maximize how much money is
It's flowing in you want to capture not just
The Nevada Market
But the entire
Transactional
In the United States
On Sports illegal
200 billion + hours
80 corners of the world
No sense to me
United States
The Congress never change the law
Soapcentral is still illegal to take bets
I'm outside Nevada
Can't I found a simple way to bring in more money
They let people back more
In most sports books you could only bad 5000
Under $10,000
Canterwood let you bet
50 Grand on it
Or more
Every so often the boxer Floyd Mayweather
Wood post on social media pictures of
Betting slips
North 400
Million dollar basket
All with Cam
Here is the problem with taking a million-dollar bet
If you don't find a million dollars worth of bets on the other side of the game
You the Sportsbook are essentially just
Betting against Floyd Mayweather
And you might be tempted to start looking outside Las Vegas to find somebody to take the other side of the
It turned out the solution to cancerous problems Within
New Jersey
To explain why New Jersey we brought in former NYPD detective jerrard McNally he's been retired for a couple of years
He still speaks
Perfect cop
It was
Something
Going on with an individual that was in trouble
New proper nouns here no names no place
Did individual not give away any information you might have to give
Show in 2011 McNally was busy investigating a couple of local bookie
One of our first targets
Shower
Guy out of Jersey
We had information that he was operating illegally
Sportsbook
Again reminder if
If you are not
In Nevada
Running a Sportsbook is against
Alright so McNally got a couple wiretap up
Any tell me
Actually following them around
We learn a lot about them
Rosetta learn
Their daily routines
They're actually activities what they do and stuff like that yeah sure we learned a whole live
And while they're learning about their whole life
McNally and his team start to figure out that they are onto something much bigger than they first thought
We tracked the guy from Jersey
Almeda New York
And we're when we have our guys watching this
I can't believe this guy's walking down the middle Manhattan
And he see the bag you can see the Buddy On Top of the Bay
Like his bag was so full it was overflowing with my
Does Casey's Waukee right in the middle of the Manhattan
Over the course of his investigation in
2011 and 2012
Detective McNally's team attract a lot of guys
That's what a lot of saxophone
Do this bath net worth
Someone would get paid off
And the next day someone else will get paid off
In Las Vegas or money would appear in offshore betting accounts
Curacao
Hundred thousand
Millions of dollars
McNally says the trail of dollar bills led to this boring little Office Park in New Jersey
Where a man named odoo kyrollos
Whose friends called him Spanky was running a very sophisticated wedding operation
Through group
Of employees and Associates that police started
Call the Jersey Boys
Spanky place bets worth millions of.
Not just with local bookie
But with Shady offshore bookmakers
And
Las Vegas casinos
He was a guy that got up early in the morning was always thinking about the numbers
You just did like a normal person get up that was his job
Spanky was an investor
Emathguy
But instead of trying to figure out whether Apple was going to hit it
Quarterly earnings Target
He was trying to figure out if the Chargers could win one on the road
I think he was just trying to make money for himself and
And he had a knack for the numbers and he was using it to his advantage
Spanky was always looking for more places he
You could get that
Which was hard because
The lock has the right to Legal
It was not legal for Spanky to be bedding with the offshore bookmakers and it's
Certainly was not legal for him to be placing bets
In Las Vegas from his office
New Jersey but remember Cantor gaming and how desperate they were to find people who could help balance out some of their big bets
Cantor gaming they had an individual their time who was an executive that
Was friendly with the Jersey Boys and he would let them operate within the
Casino basically Spanky had some guys on the ground in Las Vegas
Call up and have place bets
No Kenner gaming was not supposed to be taking out-of-state bets
But the Jersey Boys were one of his biggest customers
Cantor wanted to keep them happy so they wouldn't take their business to the next
Casino down the road
Stihl quick reminder it is illegal for a Nevada Sportsbook
To take bets from out
Outside the state of Nevada
And there's another little rule that
Cantor
Is breaking here
When there is a big payouts
Casino has to report it
Booty keep Spanky and the Jersey Boys happy
Canter was not filing a lot of these
Reports
Detective McNally says Cantor actually came to dip
And on the
They knew who the Jersey
Boys War because they needed their help
What they needed was for the Jersey Boys 2
To do something called
Buy-Back
Sometimes
Cancer would take too many bets on one side of a game
So they'd have
$200,000 on the Chargers winning
And not nearly as much on the Chargers lose
So they call it spanking New Jersey
Mhal would you be willing to put down 20 or 30 or 50 Grand on the other
Other side
And a lot of the time Spanky would say GIF sure
No part of this was
He wanted to keep things friendly with
Thank you that was not just doing this to be nice remember he's a math guy and so
Just really quickly this roughly is what he's
Spanky is betting
With the Vegas sports books but he's also betting with words books in the Caribbean
The Vegas sports book
They might have the Chargers winning by
Three points
Wow the Caribbean Sportsbook
They might have the Chargers winning by 7
So Spanky bats in one place for the Chargers
Win
And then the other place for the Chargers to lose
Most the time those better going to cancel
Search other out no harm no foul
But sometimes the game is going to finish with the Chargers winning by four points
Five Points
R6 points
Spanky is going to win
Both bats
The technical term for this is meddling and it's a way for Spanky to make a lot of money without really take
Peking mushrooms
Now there's a part of me that wants
To say
What is the big deal with of
I know are we supposed to be outraged
Spanky's taking advantage of a bunch of books like if you leave out the facts
There's not that much difference between what he is doing and what a stock Trader or Bond Trader
Raiders doing all day
But detective McNally's his gambling is like a Gateway crime
It leads into all of these much bigger crime
The backbone to other crimes
Now you talkin I owe you money now what you got to do now you got
Extortion now you got loans out
They may not do what they did like in the old days where people were disappearing or whatever
But it is back on of organized crime has always been gambling and always will be
It makes a lot of money
McNally brought an organizational chart with him like you know when the cop shows that got the bulletin board with all the red string connect
Different criminals
This one for the Jersey
So am I look on this list and under some of these people
Those names
It will say Gambino associate or Genovese associate
I assume those are
Crime family
Some of these banana guys are kind of a little scary look
We're not saying they're the muffs
But there's like on the fringes of them like the margins but even Spanky the math guy
Detective McNally says he started to go down this road
There was an individual that hold a large amount of money to him
Jen with the individual
It wasn't like spank you could go to the
The police for help
And on the wiretap
McNally could hear Spanky calling up a guy connected to the Mob
Spanky wanted to send in some muscle
To try to get his money
I think he was actually asking for
Permission to hire someone else to do it
But that's a heavy thing to do to someone to say I'm going to get someone to go after
So
To me at that point I knew he wasn't Mister innocent anymore
After a couple years
Wiretap in
Telling people
Detective McNally and prosecutors
We're finally ready
Cheat to move
In New York and New Jersey and California and Las Vegas Police rolled out in force
And then one day they arrested 25 people and
Do you eat a lot of sacks
Filled with money
Along with Spanky the bookmaker
From cancer the mob guys
They also arrested
Steve diano
The Gambler I talk to at the beginning of the show the guy who got the bag full of cash in the Palms parking lot
The cop said that bag full of cash that way
Was part of the Jersey Boys operation
Well they
Banging on my door
The clock in the morning
We had a
A big dog
My wife
Let me put them in the backyard
Steve got taken to jail and thrown in a Cell for a few days until he could find someone to post is
I had a friend of mine in Philadelphia
Get a cashier's check for the amount of money
And stick somebody on a plane with it
And flight out
The Vegas at night
But that was
Not a fun couple of days
I had
Set my fan
Tennessee football lineup
That's the real the real downside to being thrown in the clink is not being able to set up your fantasy football team
Kicker was on a bye that we got us
How to make
Some kind of arrest
Even worse for Steve
The police seized over $300,000
Seth his money
She insists that money was just a loan from a friend
The cops ain't none of them and it was tied up with the Jersey Boys gambling
Steve arrange the sit down to the DA Prosecuting his case to try to clear all this up
And he asked him what the Steve seemed like the central question in his
Is there any law that would
Would prohibit me
Borrowing money
Large sum of money
Depositing it into a sports betting account
And setting my
Moth office
And he said no there's nothing illegal about that
Still the DEA was not willing to back
And rather than risk going to jail for 25 years Steve eventually pleaded guilty
26 degree conspiracy
Conspiracy basically means you know a crime is going to be committed and you're in on it
6 degree conspiracy is the least serious form
What is
Exactly that crime was in this case
Little harder to pin down
I had to Alex
Cute to having
Committed
Some crime
Unspecified
Defied
During the course of their investigation
Which to my recollection
I want
Speed limit
The real punishment for Steve
He never got his $300,000
And because of that
She is no longer a professional gambler
He can't afford it
Now
Because they took my money for no reason
I'm an Uber driver
Spanky the chief Jersey Boy ended up pleading to a felony charge of
Promoting gambling
He forfeited almost $700,000
State government
For his part detective McNally is happy
Happy with how it all worked
Still he acknowledges it stamping out illegal gambling is a pretty impossible
Do we change nearby I don't know
I don't know
Money does weird things
Spanky my Colbert the bookmaker from Cancer and Leo
All the client,
So did CG technology that's the new name for Cantor gaming
Let September they settled with Federal prosecutors
They agreed to pay fines of more than 22 million dollars
They fired their Chief bookmaker and an August Leah meatus resigned is
CEO
Also they mostly don't take those giant bats anymore the ones that cut their books so out of whack
All Wall Street wanted
It was for the rest of the world to be more like Wall Street
To have sports betting work the same way that buying a bond
Money should be able to go where I can make the most profit
Whether you're betting on a treasury bond or the San Diego Chargers
CVS but much of the rest of society doesn't see it this way
And they keep writing off
What's some good news for the Wall Street dreamers
In 2015 the Nevada legislature passed a new law making it legal for gambling and vest
To set up shop in the state
If you live in New York or New Jersey or anywhere else in the United States
Now you can buy into one of these funds and let someone else Campbell on your behalf
These funds will probably not satisfy someone likes
Because investors can't
Choose what games to bet on or weather
The Chargers
Falcons
The fund manager makes all the
Which seems like it takes all the fun out of gambling
But still it is now illegal for a guy New Jersey to allow someone else to gamble for him in Las Vegas
There's only one sports book company currently taking bets from these funds
That company is CG technology
Any of you know something happening in Vegas that shouldn't stay in Vegas
And should be a Planet Money show
Hit us up at Planet Money at npr.org or find us on Facebook and Twitter
Our episode today was produced by Nick fountain
That interview would leave me this came from the UNLV gaming podcast thank you. David Schwartz who
If you're looking for something new to listen to check out 1 A1A NPR's new Daily News show inspire
By the First Amendment
Super excited for this one it is hosted by the awesome Joshua Johnson from WAMU and NPR
It's on the NPR one app or visit npr.org
Podcast
I'm Keith Romer
Did that guy just want a weekend
What seems like my mama mama but these guys are like
What did you make any assumption that people are going to hear Italian names
Like Gambino and he says these are prime fam
Is it okay I'm going to ask
You is at the mafia and then you can explain
I'm not going to make an assumption
Half Italian
Noel King full disclosure
Is a part of the mob or the fringes of them
Will you please put that in my mother
Who is never proud of me
Soulcraft