Hey it's Jacob Goldstein Today Show is a rerun it originally aired in 2015
You know your parents are you going on about
Sometime in the past they say were
Perfect
My mama was summer catch
I have decided when I was a kid that I missed out on
VI
You didn't seem like this magical time this perfect thing from you know back in the day
The guy you're going to hear about today
Hernando de Soto
The thing his parents used to talk about all the time
Was Peru
The whole country was born and proved they had to move right there was a cool they got kicked out of the country he grew up in Switzerland
But the whole time he kept hearing about
All the time in Exile
The love of my country came through my ears
Came through my parents telling me what Latin America was like
And to them it was Paradise of course they been exiled
That's the way you thought about proof
But eventually when he was 38
He decided to move back to
Back to this
Eden heat hurt so much
And I go back to Eden find out it isn't even little bit of purgatory there
Purgatory
DeSoto knew of course that Peru was a pork
But he didn't fully appreciate what that meant until he moved
Where Switzerland was this place where the
The streets were clean
Trains ran on time
And frankly almost everybody was pretty well-off
Peru was a poor country
In the streets of the capital DeSoto saw people carrying stuff to sell on their back
Pushing stuff through the streets and tiny little carts
In the streets they sell everything from food to repair parts
Two motorcycles to bicycle
They sell everything
DeSoto
Does poverty spread out all around
Many wonders
Why is Bruce so much poorer than places like Switzerland
I have no idea I mean I didn't know where poverty came from my bread Adam Smith
I'd already started delving in marks and all that
But they also had you know I can
Replies
I didn't understand why was technology being what it is
Why in the Dickens
Arduino more-developed mean
And I said there's got to be an invisible wall someplace that's fine the wall
That's what I went to look
DeSoto went to look for the invisible wall that was trapping poor people
Poland poverty
And be found
Hello and welcome to Planet Money
What Hernando de Soto found a transform Peru in four countries around the world and also how it almost
We'd like to say a quick thank you and share a message from one of our spa
Panthers State Farm State Farm is much more than just an insurance company they're also committed to making a pot
Positive impact in the communities they serve one way is through neighborhood of good a program connecting people
I want to make a difference with causes looking for local volunteers discover over 31,000 social cause
Listed at neighborhood of good.com and start turning the power of caring into the act of doing
State Farm here to help life go right the story starts right around 1980
Right around then is when Hernando de Soto move back to
De Soto is a business
He's not an academic
But he keeps chewing over this really abstract question
What is
Holding Peru back
At first
He's kind of working over this question on the weekends is actually
Walking around talking to the guy selling stuff on the street
After a while I found out that
They were in the street but they didn't like me in the street because he needs running water he doesn't have running water
He wants to be away from thieves
And he wants to have Stocks & Refrigeration which you can't have in the street
Basically what these guys wanted was to move into a market
You know one of those places with
It's some kind of roof
Cement floor
Gotz dolls on one side
People selling vegetable
Spices
No sim installed
Butchers in
Find clothes and shoes
That's what they wanted
So why weren't they there
It was an obvious answer
I always figured they didn't have
More space they didn't have refrigeration because they didn't have the money cuz they just couldn't afford to pay for
Here I am
Stall with the same question you are right
The same pressure now they don't have the money they don't have
But at the same time since I'm befriending them I'm walking them through their homes right
I'm going to see where they live and what they do
Then I look at the roof
Cuz it's Flats okay so I look on top and I see
My God you got cement back
And you've got the bricks
And you got pieces of iron
These vendors to have at least
Somebody they saved enough to build a solid house they're saving more so they can put another floor on that house
So money is
Not the thing
Keeping the vendors out of the mark
And also to see those bricks on the roof and realizes something
People and crew aren't saving the way people in welfare cont
Instead of saving money in the bank
What you're doing is you're sitting in bricks
Cement bags
B Street vendors don't have been cake
DeSoto discovers
Poor people in Peru are missing out on all kinds of basic things we take for granted
They're basically living outside the cyst
They don't have a deed
It says they own their house
They don't have a permit that says they can run their business
Set a realizes he have to do more than just
Wander around and chat with
Really understand what
The next thing he does
I think it makes him famous
She doesn't expire
He runs an actual X
He wants to see what it would take to actually live
Inside the legal system
Instead of
So we decided to set up a shirt
To get all the proper paperwork all the permits
You rent space in a warehouse he buys a few sewing machines and
Knitting machine
But he has no plan to ever make
A Single Shard
He just wants to see what it would take
So he hires a lawyer and if
Any tell them
Go out
And do everything you have
Did make us a fully legal shirt
Figure out how long it all
Here's a stopwatch go
Get on the bus
Find out what you have to do so they went out
And they did the red tape so they'd go to an officer they were told was in office that granted
The license to
To operate a machine
And they
They find it they were told no
It's not here anymore addresses change go elsewhere if you got to take another bus
So they actually took the buses
They had to get 11 different permit
Seven different
They're asked for bribes 10 times
I'd actually pay bribe
Twice
Debbie do everything in a certain order
Lots of
Incredibly
In total
You would take at least 278 days working 8 hours a day
To get the permit
To operate
To do business with
Spotify
And and what do you get for eight or nine months of work of taking bus give you Authority
You get the authority
To open your little fact
Just the cause of being able to open that and the cop can't come in and close your factory
DeSoto get
Obsessed
He had set up a little nonprofit to do the fake shirt factory thing
Now he has his team talk to people in other
Study the rules
And he figures out
Setting up a shirt factory actually one of the easier things
If you want permission for a new bus route it takes
26 months
Open a new legal Market
Kind of place all those Street vendors want to move into that takes
13 years
These numbers started to answer.
If you scrape together enough money to start a live
Little t-shirt
You got to start selling shirts right away
You can't afford to spend 9 months getting permit
So you end up doing what everybody does
You open your factory
Illegally
You don't wait
You live outside the
And if you're outside the law DeSoto realizes
It's really hard to get ahead
It's really likely that you're going to stay
If you're running your business legally if you don't have a bank account you're not going to get a loan to expand your
Business
You can't start a company
You can't breathe
Capital
And if you can't reschedule you can you also use it for the same reasons you can't raise credit
It means you can't expand or you'd also means another thing you can't own things like a brand
I can't do anything that you got I can't don't know Branson or nothing
It means
The world before the rule of law
DeSoto had found his invisible
Unfortunately
It was one of those problems that
Really hard
You talking about
Trying to fix in the
Tire dysfunctional
Trying to change laws trying to change the culture of it
Tire country
Facebook this Monumental task
DeSoto decides on the thing he knows
He's a business
So cute lunches Ann Adkins
You put up a lot of radio Jingles a lot of TV jingles
Jingles like ads like
Too hard to start a business
Yes absolutely one of them was called they was one of them is called
Jdi yo SI tuviera Capital Galleria
Title of the song
What would I do if I had tapped
The guy says I'm going to tell you the story of a country that's doing really badly
Because only a small group of people has access to
The capital
Can I give you my honest reaction when you told me that
Tell me there's no way this week
What does it change your opinion if I tell you that
Badly and capital rhyme in Spanish
Model capital
Send text message
Every one of the problems
Is something you mentioned
In the song right there are small number of people who do have access
Those people don't want
I mean you've got corrupt officials right
They all like collecting
You've also got a bunch of rich people who already have businesses their well-connected
They like the fact that it takes someone else a year to get
Because it benefits them
There's so many things set up for the system not
And on top of all this
DeSoto has one other prom
The Shining path was a terrorist movement of Peru
Ideologically a mouse movement
Maoist as in Chairman Mao
Bees are communist guerrillas
Was there waging a civil war in the
And as communist
They have a very different view from DeSoto about what is holding the country back
For The Shining path
The reason people were poor wasn't these
Obstacles to capitalism that DeSoto had this
For The Shining path the problem was capitalism itself
DeSoto receive this ideological
And when he writes a book is part of a
Is Big Marketing
Campaign
He makes the title
Attack on The Shining
He calls his book
The other path
It becomes a bestseller
In the book he describes his findings the fake shirt factory all the facts and ideas about rules and
Businesses in poor people
And he says what proof poor need is not
Now is for evolution
Simpler more rational rules to bring poor people into the sea
The mouse were not
I wake up one day and they say the clandestine newspaper The Shining path
Says that you were going to be punished
Because you brought down the recruitment
Because of the of the fuzzy ideas that your propagandizing
Whistle Jingles with a book excetera and they're going to punish you that's what I wake up one day
The attack
Came soon after
There's a park in front of our offices
And they get into a a dirt mound in front in the back of it and they start machine-gunning the place
Richard security guard and then the attackers pulled a car up in front of the building
The car that saluted was about my note
200-300
Kilos of dynamite
And they light the fuse and there's a getaway car they all get it back into the getaway car
And leave the car to explode
Three people at desoto's office
A while later The Shining path tried again they machine-gunned desoto's car but it was protected by Bulletproof
Glass and reinforce gas
Eventually the mouse loss
The leaders of The Shining path
And two sodas moment finally
He become famous Jingles on the radio the best-selling
And he was providing proof of whatever wanted suspected
For a long time
No one was playing by the rules
Because the rules were made
Rules needed me
DeSoto get the ear of Peru's president
And the president launches a campaign to simplify the rules
To make it
Easier for
Poor people to get title to their homes
Legal ownership of their bid
To accomplish this disorder need more than
Clever radio
Penny the TV show
So they want
The TV show about cutting through bureaucratic red
Starring
The president of Peru himself
On the show the president hears about the problems people are having problems
Business
Applying for
University or even
Getting a marriage license
And then the president actually does something about
Fresno State Building
This is terrible and who should know who's ahead of the office that would be ultimately responsible for this and then
My guy would tell him well it is
Office such-and-such
Okay well if he doesn't solve the next five days he's fired
And then he signs of those decree and then the guy with a nice blue shiny uniform
Takes it into his hand gets on a motorcycle the TV Camera follows in
Any delivers it to the public go find who told you that 5-day to solve it so you're basically turning this
This wonky thing you're doing into reality TV
PS that's it
Yes I never thought of it that way it was reality TV
And it worked
It works
The rules in Peru actually got simple
It got easier for a poor people to have a title to their home or not
Start business
Move into those markets World Avengers
To be clear Peru is still a poor
And there a couple critiques of
One is just that
Poverty is more complicated
Then the simple
The second critique is that
Changing the rules is great but it doesn't
Help the poor speech
People doesn't help that
The very bottom
Still go people around the world start noticing white DeSoto
After the break how did Soto's ideas spread around the world
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Slack
Used by companies all over the world to get everything done
Where every part of work from documents to decisions is stored archived and searchable in second
Slack
Where work happens find out why
It's slack.com
Wendake DeSoto gets a call from the president of
He starts hearing from other leaders in Latin America
In Tanzania
Tanzania in other countries in Africa and Asia this becomes like a big deal
And the World Bank in Washington DC also
Checking out and thought
You know maybe there is some way we can apply this stopwatch
To the whole world to every country
If they didn't do the full on fakefactory experiment
But they started sending surveys out
The people all over the world and asking
How long does it take to do these really basic
Mcallen's it take to get a permit
Start your factory how long does it take to fill out your taxes how long does it take to get the electricity
They call this thing the doing business
They do it every year now and it actually gets a lot more attention than you know you're sort of standard
Boring World Bank
And one of the reasons is that they ranked the country
I'm like best
2 worst based on
Easter babe
Enzo people pay attention
You know people love lift like
US News & World Report rank
Colleges and colleges are always trying to move up a list it is the same with this
Rita ramallo is the head of the World Bank group that puts out the rank
Once you start keeping scores people actually start getting competitive and care about
No one wants to be last that's
Probably
The power rankings lies on that no one wants to be last
No one wants to be Eritrea
Eritrea is number
189 on the list
Get your curious number one is Singapore
Us
Is number 7
Countries want to beat out their neighbors
Government start to worry that a bad showing in the rankings my
Hurt them with the voters back home
We match with the delegation in their first question was when is the report coming out how does that match with dialect
Sometimes
No not that
Some countries look at the report and decide hey we can use it to her advantage
The Republic of Georgia for example
Used to be part of the Soviet Union it made moving up in the ranking
Part of the plan to modernize its
Economy
Country shut up from deep in the list to number 15 in just a few years
They took out ads in the Wall Street Journal in The Economist
Bragging about how they moved up the list
Country start reviewing rules that have been on their books for
In Suriname for instance
Used to take a really long time to
We're kind of strange
Suriname used to be the longest because you actually had to have permission from the president to
Start a business
President personally had to approve that yes
But that has changed
Not everybody like the rain
Labor groups complained a few years back because
When the ways you could move up the rankings was by making it easier in your country to fire workers
World Bank actually changed
Rules about 5 workers
No longer going to the couch
As for DeSoto
He's off for the world
I think you're great I think it's great
He's glad it exists
If you ask him if the world is a better place because
Is the counting of the numbers
Answers you with them
We've done it in Egypt for a bakery
548 days
It takes a year to have to open a bakery in Egypt
It takes a year-and-a-half to open a baker needs
He's a numbers guy
Still out there with this
Special things today to Michael Klein one of the co-founders of the
The doing business report and Sam shukufuku
Spend a lot of time in the Republic of Georgia
Russia Today was produced by Jess Jiang and if you're looking for something else to listen to I have good news
Invisibilia is back for season 3
This isn't there they're kind of big question is this how can two people look at the exact same thing and see
Be something completely different
You can listen to invisibilia Season 3 starting on June 1st you can find it on the NPR one app or wherever you go
Thanks for listening