Hi I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
And you're about to hear a story that I reported
Was sind Union and summoned done
Who was our internet back in 2000
Stick around because we have a quick update at the end of the show but this story is about something
Very extravagant
Very expensive
And very elusive
A sundew
Hey
So we're here finally
We're here how do you feel
I feel like I'm going to drop actually okay well don't drop in the store Stacey I feel like that is bad
Tactic
Like all Epic Heroes
I have a plan
I thought I've been going over time to say I think I'm ready
What are you going to say
Okay I'm going to say
Hey give me a Birkin bags
The Birkin bag
It's a purse made by Hermes the French luxury brand
Perkins average around $60,000
You can get a starter Birkin for around ten
There are luxury goods
And then there is the Birkin
For 30 years the Birkin
Has been the
It bag for Rich and Powerful women
Elizabeth Taylor carried one
Kate Middleton Kim Kardashian has one
Victoria Beckham currently has like a hundred of
This is the bag that proves you've made it
That you are on the top
There are people with Birkin bags
And there are the rest of us
Apparently even just getting to see one is kind of a big deal they want to show them to anyone
And this is why I'm so nervous
I'm about to walk into an Hermes store
Walk up to a salesperson
And ask to see
A Birkin bag
Just like my own personal night
I find those stores
Really intimidate
Okay you got this good luck
Thanks man I'll see you soon bye
My God I feel so bad for her
14 minutes later Stacy finally emerged from the store
There she is
Hey you're back how'd it go okay
Breathe it's okay okay it's over
Yeah
So they didn't have
Surprise surprise
This is the strange thing about Birkin bag
They always seem to be mysteriously out of stock
And
This is no accident
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Stacey Vanek Smith and I
Put on the show the elaborate strategy that has kept the freaking bad beat luxury it bag for decades
You go on a quest to see one of these bags
And find yourself in a world where the normal rules of Commerce are totally upside down
Also how you get someone to pay $60,000 for something that is
Be honest
Just a purse
Support also comes from fidelity
As a Fidelity Wealth Management
You get a dedicated advisor
To help grow and protect your wealth find ways to minimize the impact
Taxes and make clear recommendations for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
Wednesday Martin Wednesday Surfer
First name can remember the exact moment she started whining
A Birkin bag
It was right after she moved to the Upper East Side
One of the wealthiest neighborhoods in New York
And she was walking down the sidewalk and she saw this very well-dressed woman walking
And we were the only people on the sidewalk
And she walks toward me
Rather than keeping to the right she was
Slowly but surely
Walking start of at me so that I had to move further and further to the right
And I was eating more and more sidewalk territory to her
Until finally I found myself
Stopping
Right up against this garbage can that she had sort of
Walked me into
Then she brushed right by me with her handbag
That
With a dominance display
And that woman used her handbag to do it
She's pretty sure it was a Birkin bag
There a very simple boxy handbag
Cut all the larger side and they had a padlock on the clasp
And when this happened Wednesday did not think
Oh my gosh women's neighborhood
Crazy I need to move
She thought
I need one of those fat
That was the moment when I realized that
Handbags are really important in New York
And if I want to play ball on the Upper East Side
I better stop walking around
With this white plastic bag with a couple of bananas in it
I better Saddle Up
Back in 1981 the CEO of Hermes was on
A plane with the French Act
Birkin
Emptying complained she needed a weekend
The Birkin bag was
Wanting to buy a Birkin bag
That's easy
Even having the money is
Really hard
Finding one to buy
That
It's Tricky
Even for professional
Michael tonello ran into this
He had a business buying and selling luxury goods
One day one of his customers came in and said
Hey can you tell me one of those Birkin bags
I started asking for Birkin bags
But they quickly told me that they didn't have them
And I couldn't figure out why was there a medicine how many Birkin bags
It was
You know a bag that are metals made and sold
Michael started talking to other people who are trying to buy Birkins and they were all being told this
Same thing
We are sold out
But we can put you on a waiting list
I'm 2 years
4 years waiting list
At one point there was saying that there was a waiting list to get on the waiting list
And it just all seem kind of crazy to
If you got it bad that people are willing to pay to
Tens of thousands of dollars for
Why won't you sell it to them
Hermes
Has an X
Explanation this is
These bags take a really long time to make
They just can't keep up with demand
First of all some of them are made out of
Very exotic leather is like crocodile and ostrich
And Birkin bags are hand-sewn
Pipe select artisans in the south of
Air masses that is why they're always sold out
I ran this by Josh weltman he's working advertising
For years he was one of the producers of the show Mad Men
4like list
These are totally handmade
It takes
12 hours to make one people have to Apprentice for years in order to
It's the level where they can make
This product
Is
Special
No
I'm sorry it's not
Josh says that every man has wanted to make more bags
They totally quid
30 years to train those who like art
Edison's
Either the reason for the extreme scarcity of the Birkin bag has nothing to do with how it's made
Spartan Market
Josh's the whole idea of a luxury good is something that not everyone has
And there are a couple of ways you can make sure but not everyone has your product
You can jack up
Price light companies do this
Watch companies luxury car companies
Course the Birkin bag
But air mass is going to step further
They don't just charge a lot for the
They make sure that not everybody
Can get one
Hermes birkin bags really hard
Why you should go through all these weird rituals to get your hands on one
But Wednesday Martin are upper east Sider was determined to join the burger
Don't you consulted an expert I conducted myself according to tribal code
And I went to a wise tribal Elder
Other
Didn't look like an elder she looked very young for her age
It was her friend's mom who owned Burger
Actually she owns several.
And her friend's mom called the seals person she knew at Hermes and quotes
Affected an introduction
She told Wednesday to send her
Her husband to the Hermes store
To introduce himself to the salesperson
Apparently Wednesday would have a better shot at a Birkin
If her husband said he wanted to buy it for her
As a gift
She had to show up in person
And I need this lovely saleswoman who said
I hope you'll understand that
We'll have to wait
Even Wednesday
From the right neighborhood with the right connections doing everything right
Even she can get a bag
And this goes beyond scarcity
Rimowa stores try to make
Welcome trend
Special
Hermes the strategy seems to be
You reject angular
Josh Waldman The Advertiser says
That is intentional
They play hard to get
That's how they seduce you
It almost sounds like they're kind of like
Humiliating
It's a hazing process
Beijing doesn't like
Create resentment
Create Bond
Once you're in that makes you feel that you're
Worthy
It gives you identity
I mean think about this
Hermes has created a $60,000
Purse
And instead of convincing you why on Earth you
Pay that crazy amount for a Birkin bag
Hermes has people
Trying to convince
Them
To let them by 1
Like please let me spend $60,000 at
Liquor store
And is Major sound like
Does insane marketing tactic
Used on insane people
Way too much money
But Josh said that you can actually find this tax
Everywhere
The basic example is nightclubs like when they have that big line out front
And Josh's Elite colleges do the same thing
The thing that they publish about Harvard and Stanford and all the ivy League's is the ratio of
How many people they
Let in compared to
The amount of people that they reject
It's not a high status
School
Unless it's
Super select
Everyone wants to be part of a club that's just out of
That's the
The soft
Part that were poking out in advertising
You know it's a little Sinister that they're like marketing right to us but it's like we're helpless
They didn't put the soft spot there
You know you're the one that has the edge
You know
But
They're just letting you scratch it right
I mean
That's a service
Wow
You're good at your job
There is of course a very obvious cost
To the strategy of turning pee
People away
Poking at that soft spot
Fermez it means that every time someone walks into a store
And ask to buy a Birkin bag and
They say no
That is a $60,000 sale they are not making
They don't get greedy
I guess that's what I'm
I'm sort of a weird thing to say about a company that's charging $70,000 for a bag and not getting greedy pays off
Josh's the reason that the Birkin has been on the top of the
Handbag food chain for 30 years
Is exactly because it's so
Hard to get it keeps people wanting more
Of course to make money
Hermes does eventually have to sell a bag
To someone
Wednesday Martin
Did actually fight
It is totally random way
Her husband was on this business trip in June
Japan and he's on her message
So you went in and asked
Do you have a Birkin bag
He said no sorry we're out
He said I need one
They said we're out
And he said
I need
And Japan is an extremely polite culture
After they told him a few times that
They couldn't do that and he insisted a few times but
In fact they could and he wanted them to
They must have just thought
This man is so rude
And this is so awkward
The best way to get him out of here might be to just let him
Buy one of these
So
They produced a bag
And remember our luxury buyer Michael tonello
He also ended up getting a Birkin
In a totally different way
He was in an Hermes store buying a bunch of scarves for
And I piled up about 10 or 15 or more scarves
And as we were walking to the
Register to pay
Just sort of nonchalantly like I mean literally was an afterthought I said to the salesperson
We don't do you happen to have
A Birkin bag
And the sales person said oh I don't know let me look in the back
What did you think
I thought
She's going to go in the back room and come out and tell me they don't have any Birkin bag
Instead she came out with a big
Orange Box
A Birkin bag
And she let him buy it
For $20,000
It's been Michael goes across town to another Hermes store and ties the same thing
It totally work
Michael had accidentally cracked the code
Buying a bunch of really expensive stuff at the Hermes store first
Then casually ask for a bag
I don't got one
I suddenly realized it was a lot like chemistry class
The order in which you put
The chemicals into the
Beaker
Are very very important
Somehow Michael had
Turned the Hermes shopping experience
Back into a normal conversation
Have a pet theory about this
I think that after he bought all those thousands of dollars worth of scarves the sales people at Hermes felt great
They felt like they owed him
And he wanted to be nice to him
Like in a normal store
And that is the moment when Michael asked for the Birkin bag
He caught them at a weak moment
DC United
We still haven't seen a broken though
So when we met Wednesday we asked
We could see her
And we have that
Major moments after the break
Support also comes from Fidelity Investments
As a Fidelity wealth
You get a dedicated advisor
To help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes
And make clear recommendations for your full Financial
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
Do you mind it can we see your
Back so I've actually never seen one
M&M shirts
This feel kind of momentous
That is the genius of Hermes
Even just seeing a Birkin bag
Just like a big deal
She's very clean lines very simple very
Very under scary plane really
It's Dairy
Plain and simple and understated mean if I just saw this on the street and I didn't know what a special bag it was
I wouldn't like look at it twice
That bag
So underwhelming
It is like a
Recessively underwhelming
It's ugly and boxy
And leather doesn't even seem that nice
But as I was looking at it
Caught myself trying to see how special it was
Kept thinking
People pay $60,000 for this bag
This is a special bag
If I can't see that
I have the problem
Can I touch it
I feel like it's almost like a religious
I feel like I don't know there really is some weird or about it
This is really embarrassing to listen to right now
Religious Relic aura
What happened to me I was reporting a story
About bags but it's hard not to get sucked in even when you know all the mechanisms behind what's going
Going on and Wednesday Martin said she knew how I felt
Did you ever feel like a little
Suckered by Hermes
Going through all this are you kidding of course only every single second that I was doing it I thought
I have
Lost it I felt ridiculous
Tell us about it all the time
And I still do
I still hope
To come out of this interview sounding like a person
With a sensor
Humor
Rather than a zombie but in a sense
I did become a zombie
Still Wednesday says
Having a Birkin bag really did help her feel more at home on the Upper East Side
She never got pushed off the sidewalk again people who didn't have berkins approached her to ask
She got in it
Could hold it
People who did have Birkins wanted to exchange Warsaw
She said the back
Copper feel like she had a
Please in this new neighbor
Person to tonight or Quest was done
Kid seen a real life Breaking Bad
Touched it
And we decided
To celebrate we would Retreat to our own world of luxury
In this part of town we can probably only afford a copied you like want to go get a coffee
It really does taste better
Story first aired in 2015 and the Birkin bag is as coveted as ever this spring
The Bergen set a record for the most expensive handbag ever sold at auction
It was a Christie's and someone paid
$379,000 for a Birkin bag of Call of Duty
Himalaya
It is a sort of silvery white bag made out of crocodile skin
Padlock is made out of white gold and there's some
Diamonds on there
It's very shiny and
Cost as much as a house
This episode was produced by Alex goldmark the rear end was produced by Kesha mihailovic
We'd also like to thank to my sword ree-ree turetsky and Dana Thomas for helping us
If you're looking for another podcast listen to check out wait wait don't tell me it is NPR news quiz show is a lot of fun
Fun very funny and irreverent and you can check it out on the NPR one app or wherever you get your podcast
Smith and I
I'm still listening