Hi I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
And I'm Cardiff Garcia are super excited to tell you about a new thing that we've been working on the indicator
Money you can find it wherever you listen to podcast wherever you listen to Planet Money proper kind of money but it is new
Beer and shorter and course card it because we are hosting it Whittier
Smarter and better even better-looking sundown
So go check it out you just called the indicator from Planet Money and you can find it wherever you get your podcast to Yours Today Show
Hello Malcolm Santa Maria make Fountain one of the
Producers here
And I'm going to let you in on a little secret
About the news
If you work for a big
And you have some bad
There are two
Perfect times to tell the world about it
Christmas Eve
And the day before Thanksgiving
If you release your bad news on one of those days
Chances are very few people will ever hear
Which is why
When on the day before Thanksgiving
We heard some news
We almost
Mystic
And we would have missed it
If it weren't
For one person
Hey there
This is
Kelly mcevers of course host of all things considered and also one of our favorite podcast
Embedded
Kelly the latest season of your show is about
Who what exactly
President
Donald Trump we did stories about the real estate that has his name on it and about the people who he throws
And today I'm sure we're going to play a part of an episode you did about Trump Soho if this
A big hotel condominium Tower in lower Manhattan
It's called Trump Soho
Trump company the Trump organization
Did not build this Tower
Actually license the Trump name to the people who did build the Tower and they managed
And then
On the day before Thanksgiving this day when news can happen in people can miss it
The Trump organization actually announced
That they were cutting their ties with Miller
So today we are not going to let them bury that news we're going to play Kelly's Terrific show about
About the developers that built Trump Soho
A lot of developers of this building and
We focused on one in particular
The company called Bay Rock
And a guy named
Felix
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online
Presents and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial and when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Alright so
Now we're going to talk about one of the developer
Soho
And to know the story about this developer you need to know the story of a guy named
Felix Sater
The two NPR reporters who did this
Are Alina cell
Hello hello hello and
Jim zarroli
Hello hello
Satyr was from the former Soviet Union came here as a child
Living in the Brighton Beach section of Brooklyn which is home to a lot of Russian immigrants Felix taters father has it
Criminal history he wants to plead guilty to extortion charges
He wants his son to do better
You wanted Felix to
BR and aboveboard businessman
That was
Felix fathers
Hope for his son
That's David Barry he's a former AP reporter and he's spent a lot of time covering organized crime he covered the mob scene
In Providence Rhode Island
He actually ended up writing a memoir with a guy named Sal Lauria
Asbury
Your friends would say
Nation Dad here that we did try to talk to Felix Sater himself
Through his lawyer he'd
So like
David Berry just said Felix Sater father wants him to be an above-board businessman
I guess we could High School Lee take some college classes
The Graduate
And then he becomes a stockbroker
With his friend
Salary
And so Felix Sater and this guy celoria grew up
To be
Lifeline brokers
Wall Street
Bagon
Suits
Have nice watches or Suave
Diapers
And
Felix Sater
Trouble with the law starts at the
Party One Night in 1991
South hedges
Pasta Brokers exams very hard to pass
You're out celebrating a nice night of celebration at a nice restaurant that's
Specialized margaritas
There's this other broker who's there at the time somehow a fight breaks out over a woman
He looks exploded and smash this heavy margarita glass you know it was a god
Not like martini glass
And he just in
Half a second or more
Cut the skies facial
And kept swearing at him after knocking them down and leaving his face all bloody
Maps
Their times reported the man suffered nerve damage and later needed 110 stitches in his face
Felix Sater ends up going to prison
And he loses his broker's license
The really big thing for him was a
Felony conviction bars you from setting foot on a brokerage
Floor many years later in 2016 Sater told a Russian news site
But this drunken brawl is he says
Makes him a criminal
And he can't even get hired as a driver app
And yet that really wasn't the end of Felix Sater is Criminal
After Felix Sater gets out of jail
The margarita glass inside
Court documents show that he and Sal Lauria
Then started what's noon
As a pump and dumps
Satyr and other people would buy up shares of stock
Through offshore accounts without telling investors about it
By buying up a lot of shares they would artificially inflate the
Price of the Securities they were selling
What's the price was in
Inflated Court
They would sell the stock
To annoy
Knowing investor
At the time the FBI said Felix Sater and saluria were part of an operation
That made 40 million dollars
And we should say here that
Seder and salary weren't operating by themselves
They had help from the Italian mafia
Again this is from the cortex
Something like that
On a large scale you need muscle
I mean you can't just get a politely ask the other Brokers not to sell the stock
Picture trying to inflate
But if you have two guys who were soldiers for the Gambino
And they show up in
The Brokerage
Broker's license
They're not listening. In at that point
Listening to
Dominic and sunny
Valeria and Felix Sater operation is discovered by a thorn
They're arrested and
Hughes
Conspiring with the mafia to launder money
Defraud invest
In 1998 Felix Sater pleads guilty to one count of racketeering is part of the
40 million dollars
Scheme
And here is where things get even more in
Instead of being sentenced
The charges against him were sealed and the case against him with basically
Frozen four years
And the reason was that
He turned State's evidence he started to become a cooperating witness for the government
And he became a really valuable witness over the next
Next 10 years or so
There was an FBI agent who testified at a sentencing hearing gears
Translator who said
You know the difference between us
Ice cracking a case of not cracking a case is very often just one good cooperating witness in
Felix Sater was that witness for us
One thing Felix Sater reportedly help the US government do
What's to try to get Stinger missiles
Shoulder-fired surface-to-air missiles have been used in Afghanistan
Off the black market
We read this and that book by David Berry and Saul Lauria
It's called the Scorpion and the Frog
In the 90s Sater reportedly travel to Russia remember he's from there
And located a dozen of these Stinger missiles on the black market
Satyr offered to buy the weapons ostensibly
To keep them away from terrorists
And in return the CIA promise to keep Cedar from going to prison
The deal
Ultimately fell through
But the contacts that are made where helpful
To the CIA and the FBI
After 9/11
We should say here that sound.
Buda the accuracy of the Scorpion and the Frog right before it came out
In an effort to stop it from being published in the early 2000s
But since then David Berry says Sal has told him the book is accurate after all
And salary is name is still on the book
And this is where we now finally returned to the story of
I'm so ho
Because what happens after this is
Felix Sater has gone through
Trenton jail and then
Turn has an informant in order to
To avoid his
For the
I'm a dumb scheme but then that second part
Becomes a secret
Like everything you just heard about Felix Sater sporty million-dollar pump and dump scheme
And his cooperation with the government
Goes into a vault
Jim said
The file is sealed by the court
4 years
And Felix Sater
Reinvent
And the next thing that he moves on to
Is
And you real estate investment company called The Bay Rock
A new real estate company called the favor
One of the Developers
Who would later go on
To build Trump Soho
And the reason we're talking about
Satyr and
Bayrock is because
There are two very important question
One of them reportedly of interest to investigators working with
Counsel Robert Mueller right now
Here's a possible
Where did Barack
Get the money
To help build
Soho
And here's the other Quest
Did Donald Trump know about Felix Sater past
Is a convicted felon
Because if you did
Well
Be a problem
But that part of the story
This message comes from NPR sponsor Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimum
I can be open from anywhere in 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
So we've heard the story of Felix Sater now we're going to hear the story of the real estate company
Bayrock
The companies founded in 2001
And in the next few years they reportedly have their first meeting with Donald
Trump
And they got an office
At Trump Tower
2 floors beneath where the Trump family conducted their own business at the Trump organization
That's Tim O'Brien he's
Bloomberg
And he's been reporting on Donald Trump for decades
So at some point
Bayrock and the other developers come to
Did Trump with this idea of building Trump Soho
And the picture is this
Let's build this
46 story condo hotel
You put your name on it
But you don't have to invest any of your money we will raise
The money
You get equity in the building
Plus you'll be facing management
It's called a licensing
Trump is in a lot of these kind of
The Years Around the
And here's why this deal Maids
Whisper Bay Rock
It's free publicity
The Trump name is known globally
For them it amounted to hitching their
Wagon
To approve in Star
Star of The Apprentice
A well-known business name
And here's why that makes sense for
Trump
Remember
By this point
Trump's businesses have been through several bankruptcy
And Trump cannot get loans from major Bank
From Trump's perspective
Anybody walked into Trump Tower and put a bag of money on his desk
To do business with them
This conclusion is based on what Tim O'Brien sources
Told him
So this licensing deal is
Clearly a win win
For Trump and
Incomes that TV announcer
Sprint located in the center of
That we do not know everything about where they Rock and the other developers of Trumps have
Who got their money
But there is one guy
Who claims he has an inch
Inside view of
He works there
Same as Jody Kriss
And one of the few reporters who is interview Jody Chris on the record
Is Tim O'Brien
Call Jody Chris grew up in Miami he was a very good student he went to Wharton he excelled in math math
Attics and finance
And he wanted to be a New York City real estate in
At one point he meets
Felix Sater Felix called him up and said you should come and join us if a rock
We've got
A lot of money we got some big developments in the pipeline
And ultimately said you'll get a chance to work with Donald Trump
So Jodi Chris goes to work at Bay Rock
In Fairly short order he starts to realize he's in the middle of what he would describe as a car crashed poorly managed
There's a lot of money flowing through it but he doesn't know where the money's coming from Jody Chris later filed a lawsuit against
Bayrock which lays out all these allegations
In the suit Jody Chris says everytime bayrock ran out of cash money with just magically show up
Sometimes from another bayrock Founders brother
Who had access to cash from a chromium refinery in Kazakhstan
And then in 2007 this investment fund from Iceland called FL group
Announces that it will invest 50 million dollars in bayrock
And Jody Kriss
Had never heard of it
He enquired of his partner's well who is the FL group
And why are we doing business with them and in fact
We have better offers
Or at least comprable offers
From other investors so why are we going with this Bank
And Chris was told he says
That we have to go with the SL group because it's closer to Putin Vladimir Putin
President of Russia
Teddy Crystal Tim O'Brien he thought it was a joke when they said Putin
But he didn't know how to make sense of it all
The Kremlin has denied any connection to the FL
Groupon
We should be clear here
Taking money from Russian people isn't crime
But what Jody Kriss alleged in this lawsuit
Except bayrock
Was basically a money-laundering up
Operation
In other words his suit says it was taking dirty money
From Kazakhstan in Iceland
And hiding it in what looked like a legitimate business they Rock
Built Trump Soho
In the lawsuit Jody Chris says there's no evidence that Donald Trump took any
Part in or knew of
They Rock
Earrings
Either way bayrock has denied
The allegation
So back to Jody Chris and this 50 million dollar investment from FL group
To be a rock
Jody Chris was frustrate
He was a partner
He wasn't getting
He went back to his partners and said
Looky you owe me more money than you paid out the FL group just put 50 million dollars
Into our company
I think
Based on that deal and others I mode
At least several million dollars
And this
Is where Jody Chris says
Things get ugly
And according to Chris they said not only
Are we not going to pay you that but if you push the matter
Physical harm will come to you here's what the lawsuit actually says
Shader made him an offer he couldn't refuse either take $500,000 keep quiet
I had to leave all the rest of his money behind or make trouble and be killed
Jody Chris would not talk to us on the record
Bayrock said it can't comment on ongoing litigation and Felix Sater his lawyer told us
Jody Chris's lawsuit is extortionate
Litigation
Either way there's one more important thing to know about Judy Chris's lawsuit against
Bierock
The legal proceedings
Start dredging up Felix
Past
Specifically the pump and dump scheme that was kept
Secret once he started cooperating with the feds
And this is something Jody Chris and his lawsuit says was a very big concern
Inside Bay Rock
He says the firm did what it could to survive
From
Investors from Securities officials
And they were worried about it all the time
Which gets us to the final quest
Did Donald Trump know about Felix Sater conviction in the pump and dump scheme and his connection with the mob
Because if he did
At the least
He did something enough
And at the most
It's possible he broke the law
Okay so first
Here's why this could be a
Problem
Companies are required to tell investors if they have someone working for them who has a relevant felony can
Terry Crews lawsuit says bayrock
Did Felix Sater
Conviction
Somewhere
You said that if Trump worked closely with principal fundraisers at bayrock who hit this
It could be considered part of a conspiracy
Other lawyer say conspiracy would be a stretch
And they say there's no evidence that Trump was a principal fundraiser for bayrock
That is what would require him to disclose that your conviction
At the very least
If Trump knew about satyrs felony conviction and didn't disclose it
Most of the Lord's we talked you said
It's unethical
And it shows the kind of person Trump is willing to deal with
The Trump organization did not comment on this
Or anything else
Cinestory
So it is possible that from the time they met up until 2007
Donald Trump did not know about Felix satyrs Financial crime
That pump
Dump scheme.
He plead guilty to
His company does background checks as best as can
Either way the whole story broke
On December 17th
The New York Times
Published an article about
And it told the story of the margarita glass
Pump and dump
The Stinger Miss
As for what happened next
A lawyer named Richard Lerner
The story from there
He's been involved in lawsuits against Bay Rock for years
And he has internal bayrock emails from that
I never filed as part of
Jody Kriss law
The New York Times articles published on December 17th 2007
2 Days Later
In the case of
Donald Trump against Tim O'Brien he was deposed
Yes you heard that right Donald Trump versus Tim O'Brien
The same Tim O'Brien from Bloomberg that you heard earlier
Like we said he has reported on Trump for years
And Trump sued him for defamation
In a deposition from that lawsuit Trump was asked whether he knew about Felix Sater conviction in the pump and dumps
Trump says nobody knew anything about him
An attorney asks have you severed your ties with the bayrock group as a result of this
Trump answers well I'm looking into it
Because I wasn't happy with the story
So I'm looking into it
That on January 21 2008
A few weeks later their internal emails
At Bay Rock
There's going to be a meeting
And Donald jr.
Ivanka
Eric
And Donald Trump senior coming
Julia Schwartz general counsel if a rock is coming say there will be there
That we don't
Know what that meeting was
But remember just five weeks earlier than New York Times have published that article.
Seder
In that email chain of January 21 2008
Leave the very final email of the day is
Quote Donald is happy with me
Felix Sater says
I'll explain when I see you
So in 2007
Donald Trump says
I'm looking into
Felix Sater writes Donald is happy with me and as recently as 2010 Felix Sater had a business car
It said senior advisor to Donald Trump the Trump organization
And in that Russian interview he gave last year later actually says
For 10 years
She reported quote
Everything to Trump
Sometimes twice a day sometimes twice a week
Sometimes twice a month
Then in 2013 Trump does this interview with the baby
PCS John Sweeney
Why didn't you go to feel excited and say
You connected with the mafia
You'll find
Well first of all we will not develop
That was a licensing deal
But your name is on that very simple licensing deal
Did Trump give me but I don't know you're telling me things that I don't even know about I mean you're telling me about Felix Sater I know who he is
I know of him and I know who he is
You stayed
In bed
And I say so
With Felix Sater
And he was
Connect
With the mafia gang John
Maybe you're sick
But when you have a signed contract
You can't in this country just break it sometimes will sign a deal
And the partner isn't as good as we'd like but that does happen
We should say contracts can be broken or renegotiate
And then from just ends the interview
And by the way John I hate to do this but I do have that big group of people waiting so I have
Abdullah
I said let me see your hands
The same year of his BBC interview in 2013
Trump is asked again about Felix Sater
In another deposition this one related to a bayrock property in Florida
Baidu
Here's a recording of some of that
I don't think he was connected to the mafia he got into a barroom fight
And Becky was supposedly very close to the government of the United States essay
Witness or something
He got into trouble cuz he got into a barroom fight
Which a lot of people do I don't cuz I don't drink
But you know again I don't know it very well but I don't think it was connected to the mafia
X 7 W Converse
Easter Seder
Over the years over the years if you could not many
If he were sitting in the room right now I really wouldn't know
What he look like
So when you say not many I mean is that
You can count that I know I wouldn't know what to say about that cuz I don't know you
He would call
I think it dealt mostly with my company not with me
This is how licensing deals work right
I just had my name on the phone
I wasn't involved
And the day today
Jody Crystal Tim O'Brien Trump was involved
Day today
But even if Donald jr. shook your hand on a deal
He might come back downstairs to renegotiate
If his father told him to
Okay so how does any of this relate to Robert Mueller and the special investigation
It's whether the Trump campaign colluded with
We know from recent reports the investigation is broadening
To include
The financial dealings of trump and his
We know the team will be looking at contacts made during the development of trump Soho
Between Trump and his associates and any Russians who could later have been trying to influence the election
We know that Felix Sater has contacts in Russia
Where is families from the US government there
Candy certified he traveled there with Donald jr. and Ivanka Trump
To try to drum up support for a Trump Hotel in Moscow
That's never happened
And now we know that Felix Sater
In 2015
Sent this email
First reported by the New York time
Did Donald Trump's lawyer
Our boy can become president of USA and we can engineer it
Kazan
I will get all of Putin's team to buy in on this
I will manage this process
The White House says that email is a non-story
Oh and as for bayrock and Trump Soho
Bayrock has basically been dormant for several years it hasn't done business in a while Jody Chris is
Entitlement
The company
After the financial crisis Trump Soho was sold in a foreclosure auction to another real estate company which now
Atmos theater
Hotel since Donald Trump became president sports teams have refused to stay there
There earlier this year the restaurant in Trump Soho closed
Business wechat
So a new one hasn't
Opened
And just last month the Trump organization in Mount
That the Trump name
Is coming off the building
Until no longer manage
By the end of the year
Thank you so much Kelly mcevers for coming in and letting us play that episode of embedded
And just want to say that pisode was reported by Alina selyukh and gems rolly
Is produced by Chris Penn drive and Tom Dreisbach we had research helping Barbara van woerkom
It was edited by Neil Carruth
And mailing a bike
And if you like what you heard today
There is a simple way to get more of it just subscribe to the embedded podcast where can we find it
You find npr.org podcast NPR one app or anywhere else read in your pocket
I'm the fountain
I'm Kelly mcevers
Thanks for listening