Hey it's Stacey Vanek Smith here today's episode originally ran in 2015
And we have an update for you at the end
A very delicious up
My dad is the kind of guy who does not buy a lot of stuff for himself
But when I was a kid there was this one indulge
You go to the supermarket and bring home a package of these particular cookie
Hydrox
Which looked
Well they looked a lot like Oreos
But my dad insisted they were
Better
These were perfect
Hydrox is the Oreo knock-off but they were not Hydrox were the original sandwich
What you know two chocolate wafers with cream in the middle
They've been around for almost a hundred
And then one day in 1999
Hydrox cookies
He's disappeared
The company stop making
Oreos it team did won the cookie War
A my dad was
But earlier this year I saw a little news story
But a man who now 16 years later
Is hard at work trying to take possession of a hydraulic name
He's trying to discover whatever the secret
Formal headbands
You trying to bring the cookie back
Welcome to Planet Money I'm David kestenbaum Robert Smith
There is a huge
Garbage dump bucket fail products out there
Cookies Luxury Cars toys Nology sneakers
Most businesses spend their lives trying to stay out of this. But there's some people who were
Wanted to get
What to look for buried treasure
Sam the show one man dig up a very old cookie
Sublime
Cookie some people say is much better than that other one
With your real
How can I go had an Oreo cookie
Oieo
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their own website
Using customizable layouts and features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online presence go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
When you're ready to launch use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Ellia kassoff
Grew up in one of those families where if a package of cookies from the supermarket somehow made it in
To the house
It was hard to think about anything else
It just sat there in your mind
We have cookies from the supermarket
In the house
You can't believe it
His mom is going to help
She literally went through the hole
Al Haram
A recipe box and
Crossed out the sugar in honey Crosstown flower butthole weed that smells like we were like the first ones to go to health
Food stops in SF
Self
It was a big thing for me to have a Hydrox in the house
Go treasure hunting thing started as sort of a lark
When Elliot got older he's working as a recruiter for tech companies he's making good money
But then he noticed that his favorite childhood candy Astro Pop
Went away everything little lollipop shaped like rocket
Sigelei called at the CEO and said
Can I buy the rights to make this thing's astropop and ZO6 sure
And so Elliot brought Astro pops back from the dead
Enneathought
You know what this is what I want to do I'm going to find all these iconic brands
And bring them back to
I'm going to build
Empire
Which is when he decided to go for a hike
The original sandwich
The cookie that at one point had been on store shelves across the
Immediately though there was this problem
The name Hydrox
Was trademarked
Originally by the company Sunshine that it made the first cookies over
100 years ago
Sunshine had been bought by the elves
Keebler
What you been gobbled up by Kellogg
So Kellogg's is huge company
Control the trademark on the knee
Ellie looked into trademark law and he learned if someone owns a trademark but isn't using it
There is a chance you can snack
We had to show proof that they weren't using it
You called Kellogg's and be like hey you guys can do anywhere hydraulics
It's it is a methodology that we have is kind of a little proprietary thing cuz if other people knew how to do it
I wasn't going to let that
So I called up a trademark expert
Mark McKenna
And ask him is this right can someone just walked in
Grab a hundred-year-old trademarks on Lyon this whole history
It seems a little weird cuz a trademark is like a kind of property
And if you think of this like LAN
Like hey I know she mowed your lawn for a while so I'm just going to take a little part of your property
Crazy right
I'm thinking about trademarks
They're a funny kind of property
Sally ideas that you know trademarks are not property in a full sense like other things
Trademark rights
Really exist for the purpose of helping
Producers signal something to Consumers that you know we are the source of this product
So treatments are different than a patent
Owning the rights to a song
A trademark is this really
Practical thing it serves these two purposes
What prevents confusion for consumers
So if you buy a Coke and you buy it says Coke on there with a little r that means registered trademark
You know that you are about to get
Pure Coke goodness from that can
Cuz Coca-Cola is the only one is allowed.
Getting a trademark as it makes it so Coca-Cola doesn't have to worry about fakes
About someone
Putting out crummy cook with the same you no label on the can
It means I can spend a lot of money on that
Appetizing and not worried that someone else is going to free ride on all that work they're doing building up
Yes I told the trademark is this relationship between a company
And its customers and so if that relationship is broken if a company stops using the trademark
There isn't really anything to protect anymore
Trademark is deemed
Abandoned
Is that the legal term abandonment like as if you left the dog by the side of the road or something
That's right it did. It's a doctrine of Abandonment so I couldn't Siri just grab up like Enron
Amateur and run will be one you want
Put on like a box of pasta
And ronzoni or something
The San Francisco treat
The energy trading tree
The bankruptcy
I think it works
The in order for Elliott to get the hydroxide Marquis had to show that
Kellogg had no plans
And
Elia was cagey about this but I pulled up the documents
Filed and one of the things you say to the wicked
Pedia entry
But also includes this letter
From Kellogg's basically he wrote to Kellogg Shanghai
I understand you're still making Hydrox cookies can you tell me if you only make them is topping crumble or whole cookies where can I find
So he's pretending to be a customer
Alex logo on the top
Thank you for contacting
We are sorry to tell you that this item did not have enough fans and was discontinued
They just said it right there they just like toss this out to a fan but of course Elia is thinking
That's it that's what I need
If I sent this into the trademark office and they had to send the documents to Kellogg's also
Kellogg's
Had to be notified so we sat had to send the paperwork to their attorneys and say you're on your on notice that
That you're not using Hydrox and you're going to lose the trademark
And I never replied
About a year later
The stuff takes time and we got an email from the US patent and trademark office saying
Okay
You can use hydraulics
Have that feeling you got that saying it's yours all my God it's
You know how I can't believe it's mine you all decided to control this cookie is that like your dad
It is a very bizarre feeling
I called Kellogg by the way
And did not hear
It's like you don't care
I think they made it
Noelia finally had the name but
Only the name just those six letters Hydrox
You can get the logo you can get the packaging
He definitely did not get a copy of the secret rest
He's going to have to figure out how to make the Cookie by himself
He's got to do a bunch
Detective work
And where are you going to get your hands on a cookie that went away in 1999
Craigslist
I went online and I found someone had a sealed Hydrox
Cookie package from 1998
And they were selling it on Craigslist in Upstate New York
I don't like well I'm going to buy that thing this research costumes $7
Few days later the package arrived in the mail a package of 50
15 year old cookie
Look fine
Didn't actually taste them
Because he was interested in what was on the package the ingredient list
Man cookies are accomplished
Here's some ingredients
Is flour wheat flour niacin reduced iron thiamine mononitrate vitamin B1 riboflavin cocoa
Also degerminated yellow
Cornflower the key ingredients were really the Coco and the vanilla
Because Hydrox everyone
It had this darker
Chocolate taste
Oreo day
A look around for a while and I found a place I can get them the original Coco
Any kind of place that it provided the vanilla for the original cookies
I was going to sell
Is it vanilla number 6 5 3 2
Yeah I mean it really is that specific yeah I mean fortunately we you know the Manila vanilla manufacturer had
You know they still had all the records of what vanilla as they used in
And for years and years and years what is the net worth of vanilla
I can't really divulge that really cuz it's
Yeah okay there in Texas that's all I can tell you
To the guy is so
Secretive especially for like sending all these secret notes to Kellogg's and such I guess he's
He's worried he's going to snatch his like hard workers
I think the whole cookie business is this way like everything's like Trade Secrets no one talks about how they make
Elias got the ingredients right he didn't eat the food scientists
The lab
To make some prototype cook
But like how do you know you got it right I mean you can recreate the logo cuz you
How did the cookie actually tastes like taste is a funny thing to try and remember
So we had to find some expert
When was Linda Miller
Grew up in South Carolina eating lots of Hydra
Hydrox meets all your needs
Comfort
Great taste
Available
Whenever you need it
It was
I mean I think that was
The best life there was
Hydrox life
Yes
And brand is a powerful thing I mean there's the cookie itself but when Linda sees the whole thing together like
The name package
All of a sudden she's thinking of her first date with her
This is one of the things they bonded.
Hydrox
And you really appreciate
This is a kid that people have such strong feelings but
Now that we bring this up I guess we were an oil family we were an oil family from way back that's just what we bought
We were hydroxide
People really pick sides or one of the other
And for Linda it's not just like she feels like Hydrox are better than Oreo
She doesn't like Oreos
She said they're gross
Once you have a hydraulic
You don't want anything else
Because it's just a fake
But they're both cookies and they're pretty similar you know Chocolate Wafers on the outside
Handsome cream in the middle
No they're not similar
They're not
They are similar
Okay well
They're the same color
You sure are a big part of it isn't just a memory
Lily Spring spa
I'm positive
Have you had a Hydrox cookie
David
Not in probably 20 years
Ellie enlisted Linda and her husband Rogers taste tester
And one day Linda says
Some prototype cookies showed up in the mail
I was very secret I was just in this plain envelope
I think what they were for cookies
Four cookies of a
Cookie recipe
We were taste-testing
And how did they taste
Well you know one was better than the other and that's all I'm going to tell you
Secret society plotting Revolution
You wish you were
When you talk to people like Linda you think maybe Hydrox actually has a chance maybe it does taste
I remember
And yet there is the fact
Did Hydrox went away
You felt
Yeah I never really know what the story was just like one day it wasn't there in the supermarket
Good anymore
So I tracked in someone who does know this
Carolyn Burns
She was head of marketing of the cookie division
When Hydrox was made at
Keebler
You know the place with the owl
Those of us that worked at Keebler for any length of time actually take great pride in being l
Carlynton hydroxide for a couple
When is the thing that Elliot kassoff worked so hard to get
The name
100 years ago when Hydrox was launched it was meant to invoke Purity law
Like water
Hydrogen dioxide
But by the 1990s she says that was not what the name made people think of
Get your sounded like a cleaning agent
You know like you cleaned out the sink where the floor
Exactly what Clorox Clorox
You know and then hydrogen
Yeah it sounded very, Kauai
Sales are dropping year after
She said they tried to save the cookie they rebranded it as droxies and they re
Reformulated it
But that didn't stop
At some point she says
It did not make sense for Hydrox to take up shelf space of the Superman
Any stores want stuff on their shelves
The people are bringing up to the cash register
And at some point sales just fell below that threshold
What do you think about the idea of bringing it back
How to stand a chance
No
Why not
Oreo dominate that market and has a lot of money investing
Bran I asked ellia kassoff
The fact that his little company was going
Up against Oreo
Going up again
Big cookie
Is it true Oreo
Is the best selling cookie
In the United States
Actually the best selling cookie in the world
In the whole world
Yeah
Can you beat Oreo
Beat
Beats
I think from a flavor perspective absolutely I mean from a Salesman
You know what I
That's
I would love to and I think we have an opportunity especially with Millennials at love original
Products and batteries are the number one cookie in the world
Hey Galaxy. I am high
The truth is Elia doesn't have to
Beat
The world has changed a lot since Hydrox
One thing
La can sell them on Amazon
So it's okay if they just have a smaller market share
Thousand people in each day
Doesn't have to justify be on the shelves of major stores
In supermarkets have changed when we were kids there was only one or two of every kind of Cook
Cookie competition was all or nothing this really like
Will orioles survive or will hydroxyl Drive
I just went to a convenience store during your studious like a tiny convenience store
Ensure just the kinds of Oreos I saw on the Shelf there is the regular Oreo
Is the Oriole golden
Oreo Double stuff
Golden double stuf Oreo
Mega stuf
Which is something bigger than double
. mint
Oreo Oreo Thins
I get it a lot of cookies
A lot of Coke
So do you have a name like Hydrox protest some recognition give you a little bit of edge
That could be worth
SLA if you could send me a cookie
And he said no
I'm going to send you a box
Do we get the box
We got the box have it down here
I've kept this close because I want to
To capture the moment
When your childhood dreams I'll come back to this
I'll come Crashing Down
For the sup
Here you go Hydrox cookie
Look at that has hydroxide
Before you eat it
Tell me what you remember taking
It was a thinking man
Now what it taste like
Not so sweet
Like a chocolate flavor was very present
Remember that feeling being more centered
They're still getting production issues out of the way
Like this is
This is what you want some milk I bought some milk
Okay yeah
Milk
This is exciting I haven't had one in
Set alarm.
I thought I remembered what they taste like
It's good
This brings back memories of me watching Saturday morning
I should grab cookies for anyone walk
Are they late right
Dress like an Oreo
You mean Oreos taste
A lot of work to put it to resurrect and cookie
It was already basically there
Hey it's easy here again.
That was in 2015 in a moment we check in with Elliot and see how Hydrox
Is doing now
Support for this podcast comes from Discover card
Who will alert you if they find your social security number on any one of thousands of risky websites alerts are free
Cardmembers just sign up online
Learn more at discover.com free alerts limitations apply
When we first ran the story a lot of you wrote into us about how excited you were for Anew Hydra
Some of you sent it
Pictures when the first orders arrived in the mail
At the time hydroxide just become available on Amazon and Elliot was hoping to get into some actual stores
So we talked to him this week and ask how's it going
He says
It's a hit it's working you can get Hydrox in about 4000 stores across the
Elliot is in fact working on his next big project not an abandoned trademark this time
He wants to buy Nestle's American candy
But it cost so much he needs investors
Noelia is using Hydraulics to help him recruit
Business partner
She even use them
To try and recruit legendary investor Warren Buffett
Here's the letter d.
Give us our casa
I can remember the days at my grandfather's grocery store when Hydrox cookies far outsold Oreos
After biting into one that you sent me
I got with the markets verdict from the earlier day
I think you have a winner
Warren Buffett
Warren Buffett loves Hydrox
He did not however love the investment opportunity he turned it down but a very nice protection
We always love to hear what you think of the show send us an email
Planet Money at npr.org
The show is produced by Jess Jiang and the rerun was produced by eduard Saakashvili
If you're looking for something else listen to check out rough translation
NPR's newest show it's an international reporting podcast with host Gregory Warner who's been a Planet Money bunch of times
Watch the show
And he takes us to a bunch of amazing places to look at conversations were having in this country
And Heather translated in other parts of the world I cannot recommend it enough you should check it out
You can find it on the NPR one app or wherever you get your pot
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Thanks for listening