Support for NPR comes from investor.gov
Presenting this mess
When it comes to investing
We all have Quest
And investor.gov has answers
If you're free resource for tools
Tips and information about investing
Before you invest investor.gov
Paint just a quick note Today Show is a rerun it originally ran in 2014
A while back I got this
Big flat screen TV
TV for my bedroom
A better date
I took it out the box
Set up over there in the corner
You want doesn't come with
It doesn't come with the
Cables you need to connect it
All your other stuff
So I go to Best Buy
Snooty Viennese like
I'm you're going to need an H
HDMI
And bad news
The 45
$45
For some wires and plastic
And I pay
I pasted because otherwise
My TV was just a big
Thousand-dollar black
Robert today you can go online and buy that exact cable that you paid whatever 45 bucks for today UK
You can buy it for
$3.61
I should have waited
No we take it for granted the things
Get cheaper that there is,
Petition
Technological items of technological advancement
How does this exactly happened how does something that used to cost $45 that I was willing to pay $45 for
How does that now cost
3 or 4.
There's this one particular company
That got famous for selling cheap
HDMI
The company is called Monoprice
When they emerged a few years ago they started out as sort of this
Cult secret among nerds who love buying cheap table
But pretty soon
What company started noticing as well
Bernard luthi used to work for one of those
And I remember I remember sitting in a room
With our CEO
And he asked us
He hurt his company Monoprice
And he said they're getting our shorts in in
Around the Cable business eating or shortening or shorts in the
Michaela business
No
Luther was so impressed by Monoprice he went to work there
He's now the president of the company
The story of the HDMI cable
Monoprice does
Over
And over again
Electric keyboards
Speakers and
Cameras electric guitars
Literally thousands of other things
And for all that gear
The basic idea is
Is the same
Pick something
Take some of that people love
Figure out how to sell it for
Lolking Planet Money I'm Robert Smith
Jacob Goldstein
Today on the show we figure out why some stuff gets cheaper
Lexi
Consumer electronics
There's no law that says they have to get cheaper
And yet
Year after year decade after decade
Today we visit a company
What people make this happen
Support for this podcast in the following message come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org
I went out to Monoprice a few weeks ago their headquarters is in this
Super generic Office Park
In the
Awesomely named Rancho Cucamonga California
At the base of the Foothills just outside of LA and they've got their office
Is there end this big Warehouse
4000 square feet in size
I feel like everybody is how many football fields something like that with you
I looked it up you could fit three football fields in the Monoprice Warehouse
At cables it turns out
Still a big deal at model
Are some cables more cable thousand foot 500000 foot cable
The tables everywhere
What's the biggest seller
/ 6 / HDMI cable HDMI cable is product number 392
And it sounds like crazy you have like a trophy on your wall that says 3992 on it everybody knows that
Number
Everyone in this building knows that the ID number
Monoprice doesn't just buy cheap stuff
From other companies
Define little things in Market
China and then sell it retail
Bead designs
The tweet that they put the Monoprice name right on
I visited this room at the company's headquarters where a lot of this
It's called the Tesla
The first thing to say about the test lab is
It is not allowed
Picture more like rec room
Somebody who is super into Electronics
One side of the room is like
Speaker lamp
This is my neck of the woods here this is this is my little audio Corner Albert Cardenas is mono prices
Speaker Guy
What is what is that on the wall
Basically it's foam
Kind of looks like a padded cell
There's speaker parts
Speaker boxes
Speaker wires
Albert starts taking apart a speaker to show me his work
And the grill remove
And you
Can you get a
Aluminum midrange
Add a 3/4 inch aluminum
Twitter the guys in this room are tinker
There's no Brand New Concept no one's coming up with inventions that no one has ever seen but
The format progress at Monoprice
Is take like a little piece of metal
And already existing speaker
Just make it a little bit fitter
So basically I redesign was called the face play
He says this made the sound
Clear gives me a little demonstration puts his hand in front of his mouth
So this would have been the before this would have been the actor
One more time this is the before
This is the actor
Another corner of the test lab belongs to a guy named
Chris Apple
There's this big fancy monitor sitting on a desk in that corner of the room
Pro tip
If you want to sound like a Savvy Tech expert
Don't call a monitor monitor
Call it a day
That's what Christmas
This is our newest 4K display
Legalizing some of the fanciest thing on the market right now
I should turn on for you
Chris and Albert's job is to be on the hunt
At all
Looking for popular stuff that they can
Figure out how to sell at a discount
The popular stuff that Monoprice doesn't sell at all
Because
They take a look at it
And it's already soaked
One really striking example of this is
Flat screen TV
If you walk into a store and buy a TV
Almost any TV
You are probably paying
About what it cost to make that TV and get it
You're probably getting a good deal when you buy a flat screen TV
So
Monoprice does not sell flat
Because there's no way they could sell them at a disc
And make a profit
So what what happens at Monoprice is essentially detector
Seeing an object
And saying
Could we make money off of that
And this can take months or even years
And as it happens the story of this fancy monitor that Chris just turned on is actually a really good example of the
What kind of detective work these guys go through
You to figure this stuff out
But screw the monitor it starts about 4 years ago
Walking through a Best Buy
He goes there sometimes to check out the competition
And also
He needed some random things that Monoprice didn't care
So I was walking by and the images of honey bees buzzing around on the screen cut my eye
Chris was way off to the side of them
He wasn't looking straight at
Maybe ten feet away
But even so he says
It blew his mind
It was better than any monitor here to Everest
I could see
The pollen on their abdomen and I could see every fluttering detail as the wings flap it was
Spectacular
And what did you think or feel when you thought
I got to have it
But unfortunately saw the price tag shortly thereafter
And their first introduction was over a thousand
The monitor was
Me by app
A cinema display
Cinema
Chris in his own words is up
PC fanboy
So what he really wants is a monitor like this when he's staring at him
But one that's cheaper and one that's made for a p
For Chris a monitor like this would be and I'm quoting him here
A white unit
It was something I dreamed it was not available on the market it was something I so wanted to give to
To my friends my customers of my customers myself
But had no way of getting it
That really was my my like mythical creature
Standing there staring at this thing in Best Buy
Crystle Stewart
Why is this
So expensive
Why does it cost a thousand
Now it could just be the Apple brand people are willing to
To pay a lot of extra money for that logo
Or could be but only apple is able to manufacture this monitor
Perhaps they were the first ones to go to some Factory in Asia and say this is exactly what we want make this thing
In other words maybe it's expensive because
There's no competition
Chris Noth
He's not going to be able to get some other Factory
Free to start making enough
It's just too time-consuming and too expensive for Monoprice tube
But Chris also knows that when a hot new Gadget comes out
There's usually some guy
With the right connections at the factory
Who can get you the the online equivalent of a back alley
My is my thought process was here there's no way
No way in hell that they help
Apple was getting these exclusively made for just them and they weren't getting out
Coming up in a minute
Chris goes in search of his unit
Support for Planet Money and the following message come from Squarespace
Squarespace offers a unique domain experience that's fully transparent and simple to set up
Make your next move
By visiting squarespace.com to start your free trial
And use offer code Planet Money for 10% off your first purchase
Squarespace
Make your next move
Make your next website
Socrates that amazing monitor at Best Buy
And then he goes straight home and starts doing some Detective
First things first
I go to eBay attention the specs for the money
Search results come up and he sees that in fact
There are few people in Korea who are selling cheaper PC versions of these monitors on eBay
They cost $700
Increase orders to
Then he waits for them to come
By ship
All the way from
I'm so $1,400 later and almost three-and-a-half months of waiting I monitors finally
We arrived one came cracked
Essentially split in half
Well one was perfectly great in working order the one that work
Was as beautiful as the monitor Chris had seen in Best Buy
So he does more digging
Call to contacts in Korea
Search is this US Customs data
The tracks every product
It comes into this country
And Chris figures out a few things
The panel for these monitors are being made at a single Factory in Korea
And what these guys are selling on eBay is
Factory reset
Pedals that work
But that have little flaws
What's the mean Apple won't sell them at retail
This means Chris and Monoprice
There's no way we're going to go out there by Factory Rejects
Rebuild a monitor to be like hey guys the new hotness is here buy it for $500
So for now Apple still gets the market for this fancy new monitor
All to itself
But about a year later Crystal during the day
Factory in Korea
Has expanded
Production of the pan
Spider-Man for the fancy Apple monitor has not kept up
This means there may be a way for Chris and a model price to make a deal to get some of those magic
Chris goes to Korea to figure out whether the rumors are true or whether somebody still trying to pass off Factory Rejects
Once we were able to verify that we didn't have a cow bar little white unicorn we showed up with a lot of cash and
Ordered as many panels as we could
About nine months later
Monoprice started selling it
First version of that fancy
We sold it for it was
Sports for 2599
425 bucks
And Annapolis motor using the same screen with how much
Doubler cost at 999
So you sold it for half the price
To be clear even though the panel
The screen is exactly the same
Make the screen of the Apple monitor
That doesn't mean the whole package is eidetic
Equal to an apple
One review of the Monoprice monitor had the headline
Poor design
Trumped by great screen low price
Spell Chris's.
The monitors they hit Monoprice sells a ton of them
It's a happy ending
But
As usually happens in the electronic business
Happy ending doesn't last for
Because Chris Appling was not the only one chasing the white unicorn model
Samsung actual product a similar monitor around the same time
And in the two years since the monitor came out
More factories are starting to make similar panels
More companies have started selling the monitors
Which of course keep getting better and keep getting cheap
How many people sell that monitor now
Samsung BenQ
Dell
Spotify FAQ
Is definitely got a lot tighter than what it was
More companies selling the monitor means more price competition
Which means he's monitors are moving from that category of something they cost too much
To the other category
Of something
The good deal
The price of the monitor
Is now pretty close
To the cost of
The monitor Chris and I are staring at in the test lab
That is already several Generations beyond that first one he saw at Best Buy
4 years ago
And justice for all
Apple bread out the new monitor
That's even better than this
Chris once again is chasing after Apple
He says we can expect the Monoprice version
Sometime next
We all
Always love to hear what you think of the show the email is Planet Money at npr.org or tweet us
We will see it at Planet Money ever you tweeted radio Smith I tweeted Jacob Goldstein
I'd like to say thanks to Jeffrey Morrison a journalist who has written about Monoprice for CNET who talk to me
The story also to the people at IHS who helped me understand some details about the Monitor and thanks to our
Producer now that you're at the end of the episode NPR recommends that you check out the TED Radio Hour
You can find it on iTunes Stitcher or your podcast distribution mechanism
I'm Robert Smith and I'm Jacob Goldstein thanks for listening