This message comes from NPR sponsors snowfall
The only data warehouse
Built for the cloud
Unlock deep Data Insights with the instantly scalable Cloud build data warehouse
Start your journey towards data-driven decision
It's snowflake. Com NPR
I recently came to visit Los Angeles and I called up my dear friends and Eglinton
Good night you are an NPR business correspondent live out here in LA
And we're waiting some food and you told me that you were going to take me to see one of your favorite
Places in LA
Yeah where you can see the most
Celebrities in
One likes play Spotify
And I was thinking this meant we're going to go to some
Cool new restaurant
Club or something like that
Nope but that is not
Where are we right now
We are in a little park that's hidden
White off of Wilshire Boulevard which is one of the busiest streets in LA
And you can see their skyscraper
Preservative hiding
What is one of my favorite places in the world
And what is it
This is Pierce brothers
Westwood Memorial
Park
It is a cemetery
Crazy Frog
Cemetery
You know how to show it
What I tell you you know what if it's always a surprise it is always a surprise no one ever is like oh you took me to a cemetery
CC this Cemetery
Is special
Yeah let's walk around
So
First stop here
When my favorite actor
Jack Lemmon why does it say Jack Lemmon in
You ain't never going out of there like you then
Moving quickly there's somebody in there but
The great writer Truman Capote
Jackie Collins
Natalie Wood but there is one celebrity that kind of outshines
Everyone
Like walking towards the mausoleum activity around it
There are always flowers there's always something
Marilyn Monroe
Now there is Raven's very simple it almost couldn't be more simple
Except for all the kiss mark
Marilyn's grave discovered in these lipstick
Kisses probably people come up and kiss her grave every day
There's also a bouquet of roses a pair of sunglasses and
A piece of lemon cake
Take that somebody left
Butzin are you did not want to linger at Merrill
You wanted to take me to see
Someone else
Yes one of my
Favorite apps
Who is buried there and
There's a little ritual that
I have to perform you have to find
Stone
Hear it so we're going to
Show some respect to my one of my favorite comedian
This man was Jewish this is a tradition Stacy where you place a stone on a Jewish person
Grave as a sign
I remember
Rodney Dangerfield
And you have to read his Tombstone why
His inscription there goes the neighborhood
Rodney Dangerfield was not kidding this is a very
Exclusive neighborhood
It's one of most expensive graveyards in the world one podcast
$100,000
And that is for a space that is 6ft by
Yeah by that measure that makes it some of the most
Expensive real estate in the world
Hello and welcome the planet money I'm centering button and I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Death
The great mystery
It connects and unites us all
It is inspired some of the greatest works of art and literature and in a lot of ways it defines and shapes Our Lives
But it is also a business
At and wait how much did you say the average funeral cost know it's over 10,000 for a traditional burial
Wow it's expensive to die
It is expensive to die
Dan the show we look at three different parts of the deaf
Business
Because it's Rodney Dangerfield would tell you
Dining fun
Anime chibi
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Sagemcom from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and community
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org
Preference story we're going to look at buying a cemetery
Carrie plot and story because you loved the Westwood Cemetery so much
I looked around and found the guy
You could sell you a space there
Hi my name is Baron shoe
With plot brokers
So you're basically
Like a real estate agents for grave plots
It's very similar
Aaron bias
Cemetery plots from
They move or change their mind about where they want to be buried
And he has in your Cemetery scenario
It's actually
2 spot it is a double plot
Right in the middle of all the celebrities
And
It cost
Get ready for it
$600,000
Oma
Spent a lot of money this guy probably have a reality show
Krista mausoleums of the
Rich and famous
I would watch that show up bear in Stanley has been in this business for more than
Because it is a very solid business
Demand is stable and there's a lot of money involved
Barons most expensive property right now is
Crypt that is going for more than a million dollars
What are the amenities that offer
Likewise
Private entrance
One of a kind
You know 18-foot ceilings
Marble
Florida
Ceiling
Family name
As big as a freeway sign Stacy
In Hollywood
Even in death
Billing
Helen Parr
Always
But this Cemetery
It's already at 95%
Tank capacity
So it's really expensive
Hard to get in
Is there a certain cities like Los Angeles and New York
Businesses like his are always blooming
Necessities are growing populations are getting bigger cemeteries are filling up
More and more people are coming to him asking for help finding space
And Cemetery real estate is different from say home real estate in one very big way
You never move
Thanks and I are welcome
So you have your cemetery plot
But
When are you going to need
That question brings us to our second story because none of us knows when we are going to
Dianthus causes all kinds of problems
Existential of course
But also practice
Princess
It's hard to know how much money you need to
To say if you don't want to scrimp and scrape your whole life only to die before you had
You also don't want to spend and spend and then live to be a hundred and twelve
These days we have things like
Like 401ks
Life insurance
What is problems
But that was not always the case
And brynhurst at editor of Planet Money you have a tail for
I have a tail and a plan
Estranged old plant
Tell us about it
Planet Money
The ten of us weed Pony up $1,000
That's why
It's enough we bury it in the park
And we wait
And after everyone but one of us has died
That
That person
Hopefully
Meet you
You haha hopefully make you sleepy or you one of us gets all of the money
Sounds like a
Messed up
Water it is
But it's actually a kind of deal that went on for
For centuries and it is called
A tontine
Constantine
It was invented by a man named Lorenzo de tonti exactly
Okay he wanted the money to go to the government
And he said
Listen Planet money investors
Don't bury the park
Give it to me
Give it to the government and we will pay you an interest
Once a year
And as investors in the tontine
Die off
The interest payments
Get bigger for the remaining
That's why you and I would get a regular paint
And even if everyone else is gone
Will you take any money
So if Jacob Goldstein mysteriously disappears
Blood say
Princeton
We would get a little extra money to get a little extra money
Was this popular were there a lot of clear all over the place
And one of them for a while was the building that housed the New York Stock
Exchange it was really I was founded around 1794
By 200 people who got together
As I let each put in $200
Will build a building will run it
And the survivors
The Survivor will on it
And when it shut down it was a big deal and it was like all the time teen is over the famous hunting is over
Who won who got the building with somebody with a very fancy old New York name
Of course
Why are some people who always win
It's okay these were apparently
Huge but I don't know what happened to them
Are there still tontines today
There were
I know there was some problems
What happened was
The insurance company's got into the business and they started offering tontines and a kind of professional way
And people joined up
And there was all this
Invested money sitting in piles
And
People didn't really do that good a job taking care of it
And it's
Tentative
And some people lived a long time and found out at the last moment
If you know what I mean
That someone had run off with all them
Oh
Stoughton teens
Became
Essentially illegal
But you're hoping to bring the back of hand
Think about it this way it's kind of a nice thing like
It's something you do with someone you trust
And you can't make an agreement that in a way is good for everyone
I think there's a kind of sweetness to it
Thank you you're welcome
Our third and final business of death story
Comes to us from overseas
Sally helm Planet Money producer hello hello
You have the story for us yes
We are going to
And has a really good place to talk about death because it is one of the fastest aging Societies in the world right now
I talked to Alicia
Cute about this
She covers Japan for MPR and she was like oh yeah
There's a lot of old
People in Japan and it's noticeable when you walk around especially rural areas
So what does that mean for the funeral
Well you would think it would be a good thing right you was upset and that would be the
Kind of intuitive
Response but what's happening is that others there's kind of
Larger Trend against
Spending as much money on funerals
And having smaller funeral
There are a couple reasons for that Trend one kind of
Sad one is that if you died older you have fewer friends around to come to your funeral
So
What's happening in Japan is that on the one hand there are more funerals
But on the other hand people are spending less
On each one
So the funeral and death is in Japan has gotten really really competitive
And there a Benny's big expose
Where death businesses
Come together to
Basically show their stuff
Show white people should choose
Them
And Elise
Went to one of those conventions
It's called index
Short for end-of-life Expo and it's a gathering of all end-of-life related
Businesses
So coffin builders
Alter makers morticians there was an entire section on pets
Turn your
Pet remains into a memory Sapphire there were a bunch of purses on display there was a swill blinged-out hers
Example why would you need
A party bus
Elise
Did not just
Go to this Expo she actually
Participated in it
There was a mortician there who wanted to show off his skills in traditional Japanese burial practices
Is and
Elise agreed to be his model
Oh my God
The big
Climax
For me at a 10 deck
Was
An opportunity to actually have an Undertaker
I pretend that I was dead and dressed me in the traditional funeral garb
And put me in a coffin
At least at the Undertaker wrapped her in a kimono left side over right side the way you would do it for the Dead
And applied makeup and
All of this was in front of a big
Audience
There's a real ritual to all of this
And so while I was pretending to
Will be dead and getting
Prepared for
My coffin
This
Undertaker was also on display right that we were on stage
And so there was somebody narrating what he was doing
Olicity Undertaker was very gentle with seem like you really knew what he was doing
When we were all finished there was a lot
You know Ford
For the ritual mortician
I have a photo at this
In front of me and
Amazing Elise has on makeup she's in this coffin that has
Cloud
On it
End
You know if that is a business
In this case police
Became the product
And she told me that the experience wasn't really
Spiritual for her if she was in touch with anything larger than herself it was
The commercial side of death
Which
Ultimately
Unites all
That is so true
The ground after the credits the show is not dead yet we have
One final thought after this
Support for this podcast and the following message come from fidelity
As a Fidelity wealth management client
You get a dedicated advisor to help grow and protect your wealth find ways to minimize the impact of tax
Axes and make clear recommendations for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
We love to hear what you think of the show and we really love to get your story ideas so send us an email Planet Money at
Npr.org or find us on Facebook or Twitter
Today's episode was produced by the
The great Nick Fountain and Sally helm
And also we have a couple people we'd like to thank Professor Jonathan Foreman at the University of Oklahoma
An Amber carvaly with undertaking La thanks guys
Also if you want to see some pictures of Elise
In her coffin those will be up on our website
Npr.org money
And there will actually be video of this whole thing or elise's Elise tries
Series on NPR
Is an awesome series definitely check that out
Planet Money senior producer is Alex goldmark the show is edited by Bryant first.
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
And I'm finally home thanks for listening
BC I have one last person that I want YouTube
Okay
He's not around hello
Hi
Hello
Hi so sorry he's not around
But I'm sorry I'm talking
Nevada a Denver
This is Sally
I hate it when that happens this is Mike McHugh
He is a
Cemetery commissioner in a small town in Mass
So he
Runza Municipal Cemetery
Keeps track of who's buried where he
Sunblock time of grieving families
So he's really dealing with a lot of different
Logistical aspects
Pics of dad really practical Parts in this small town
And he's been doing it since he was 18 years old
So I thought he would be the perfect person to ask this question that
Army has been
How to hanging over the whole show
Which is
If you're dealing with death in this
Practical way
Does that make it easier for you
To deal with your own mortality
So I asked
Do you feel like you've learned
Things about death that you didn't know
I've learned a lot of technical
Aspects of it
I didn't realize say that I casket
Colors inside of a vault when it goes in the ground I thought they just went straight into the ground
Do you think I mean like has it changed how you
I like to think about death do you think
No I'm still terrified
So I guess no matter how often you deal with death
However many of the Practical parts of death you're dealing with everyday
It's still just the Great
Existential question
Yeah
I think that never goes out