Just a quick note Today Show originally ran in 2014
You do have a little update at the end
There's nothing that comes up in the news
CEO pay
The stories often include someone complaining that
Too high
Sometimes pointing out that it would take an average worker two centuries to earn what a top
Paid CEO makes in a single
Then there's somebody on the other side defending CEO pay
And that usually about where the stories at just people arguing back and forth about numbers
Today we have an actual story about Co
A story with a beginning a middle and an end it's the story of two guys
To Outsiders who try to cut the pay of the CEO
A small pneumatic Tool company on Long Island
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Jacob Goldstein and I'm David kestenbaum this is a piece we just finished for This American Life
Where's the nearest dry cleaner near special for Planet Money
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace Squarespace allows small businesses to design and build their
Their own websites using customizable layouts and features including e-commerce functionality and mobile added
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization to help you develop an online presence go to
Squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to launch use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or Dome
It takes an unusual person to wage a war against the CEO it is
Do you have the success or just solo
And Tim Staples was definitely an outside
He lived in a small town Laporte Indiana
In a small house
We went to visit
In the dining room there's a broken Dungeons & Dragons pinball
Tim tried to fix it
Here it is now
Sad
I made a boo-boo when I
Write out the
Display the largest disaster
Upstairs there's a room filled with old and rare board games
Timmie's to buy them at auction
And resell them
My favorite was a game called war in the Pacific which apparently nobody really plays
It got 3000 pieces
50 pages of rules
Tim a little business out of
He's good at picking the right games
Buying cheap and selling them for
Eventually Tim tried his hand at the stock
He used a computer
Pick out stocks you thought were undervalued
He still has this computer today and just so you have the right image in your head
It's the kind of computer you find sitting out on the side
It's got a floppy disk drive
It's actually connected to a dot matrix printer still works
Over the years he did well in the stock
Really well
Well enough that he was never going to have to work a regular job
Sometime in the mid-nineties Tim came across this one company
He'd end up investing hundreds of thousands of dollars
It was a small company based on Long Island
Call p&f Industries
It made pneumatic tools
You can actually buy him at Home Depot
Have you ever used one of the tools
I don't believe so no
Tim just like the company's numbers
It was a small company where you could understand everything about it
Pmf seemed like a good deal
But over the years something begin to nod
The salary of the CEO
Richard Hart
Roughly 1 and 1/2 million dollars a year total compensation
That a lot
One and a half million
Is outrageous and outlandish
Timothy rabbit similar company
Some of the same industry some of the same Geographic
You can find anywhere this year with pay
Even half
Now if you just own a few shares of a company stock
Can you take the CEOs of
There isn't much you can
But if you are more
Well liked
And by the fall of 2009
Tim around 180 thousand
Cousin shares I came down 5%
5% of the whole company
5% the entire company
His stake was worth more than half-a-million dollars
And it turned out
Tim had an ally in this fight
A guy with a little more experience
Skyrim the Hedgehog
I'm Andrew Shapiro on President portfolio manager of Lawndale Capital Management
About 8%
Hinton didn't work together directly
They had buried if
Answer with a by-the-book investor
Find a
Semi obscure military lose
We deploy with what we do we deploy what I call
The Powell Doctrine
Of Investments
And I try to take on targets
Where I can mount overwhelming Force
4 years Andrew had been arguing that the CEO was grossly overpaid
Over 110 year. He says
Richard Horowitz took home 13.5 million dollars
That's more than twice with the entire company made in profits over that
Sometimes when people complain about CEO
They talk about it as if the money's coming out of the pocket
Ordinary work
That is not how timid
Every dollar the CEO gets
Is a dollar less proper
A dollar less for Tim
And Andrew
And all the other stock quote
They overpaid CEOs taking money out of the shareowners pocket
You're not in it because he wouldn't it be wouldn't it feel great of CEOs weren't
Hate so much more than everyone else
I am I am doing this to make a return on our capital
If you think CEOs are overpaid Rich guys
Your best hope maybe other rich
People like Damon Andrew with enough money to buy a bunch of stock and
Try to cut the CEO's pay in hopes of becoming even richer themselves
Weave course wanted to know what the CEO Richard Harwood
We tried to get him
I got a bunch of talks with the company
In the end it's declined to be in
But because this is a public company
There are plenty of recordings
Public companies have what are called quarterly earnings
For investors
Really anyone who wants to listen
Good day everyone think I'm holding a safe conference will begin with a presentation and then
Operator starts the car
Is the man himself
Richard Harlow
Firstly
What's the company's revenue from continuing operations what's 14164000
Listen to a lot of earnings calls like this
Usually they are incredibly.
Analyst from Big Banks asking super specific things about the company's balance sheet
Remember
PNF is a small company
And some of these calls
There are only two people funding and requests
To people who feel the CEO is grossly overpaid
Andrew enter
They that the CEO whatever they want
Here's one Exchange
Our next question is from Timothy stable if your line is open
Tim is asking about this key thing that used to determine a CEO salary
It's called a compensation
It looks at what CEOs at comprable companies
Pmf Industries has hired an external firm to do what
Kim wanted.
Still waiting on a report from that outside for a ride
I can't tell you why I don't know what the company I mean
I don't like and a Black Russian
I don't have the knowledge shampoo
Okay
You know this is a firm that's two weeks early now that there's a firm is doing an analysis right
I can't I don't know
Handsome
I can't comment any further and this is a 2
To private school
Tutu mean second
We talked about the results of cubed
Policeman
Composite numbers Factor
Well that's fine but executive salaries are relevant to the Future profitability and and whatnot
Any further questions ask you to
That would have been helpful if you would simply said we're not going to talk about executive conversation. That's what you're essentially saying
Hilton
I'm frustrated right now Richard
Okay you'll have
Thank you
Our next question is from Andrew Shapiro in your line is open
There are a lot of calls
CEO salary set by a company's Board of director
Shapiro suspected Richard Horowitz it packed aboard with his cronies
People who paid him more than you deserve
Andrew hired a private detective and did some digging himself
He discovered that in fact several board members play golf at the same country club is the CEO
The Glen Oaks Country Club of
Westbury New York
Glen Oaks Country Club of Old Westbury New York
Nothing illegal or maybe even surprising about these guys belonging to the same country
Still what would General Colin Powell
He can get them off the board
Getting someone do when a company's board turns out to be varied
Disconnect wonky little detail is not the kind of thing that fits on a protest sign
What's the thing that really matter
Board members are elected
All the shareholders
But the thing is
It's hard to get candidates on the ballot
Any shareholder can nominate
But the board decides whether that person should be listed on the ballot
It would be like if the members of Congress got to decide who got to run for Congress
There are ways around this you can try to change a company's bylaws or you can
Wait something call the proxy
But that's expensive and even more difficult
Both Tim and Andrew took that first approach
Nominate someone for the board and
Hope the board takes her suggest
Andrew in his by-the-book way offered up some names
And Tim
Tim Sycamore unconventional
Here's the letter he wrote
And filed with the SEC
We had them
Pursuant to article 3 section 12
Penis bylaws
Please be advised that at the next meeting of stockholders at which directors will be elected
I intend to nominate myself for election as a director
Tim was trying to get himself on the board
You never been on a
Bored Button
This is like a board game
There were set of rules and they allowed for the
So why not
Very truly yours
Timothy John Stables private investor
That kind of outrageous things to do
You know I was so
Incensed I figured why not why not
Why not see how they respond
Request that they put me on the board
And see how they handle it
Tim and Andrew went to the company's annual meeting on Long Island
Want to try to convince the board to put their candidates on the ballot
It was the first time Andrew Shapiro and Richard Horowitz
The CEO had met in
It actually was quite crowded every seat in the table was full and there was
The paid for advisor standing around the periphery of the table outside you know
In the room but along the wall
Where was the CEO
I'll be sitting directly across the table from
Oh
It must be awkward what's it like
I was not awkward tonight until I go into these rooms
With the distinct View
That I am an owner of this business and you members of the board of directors or my agents
And you work for me you don't work for mr. Horowitz
You don't work for management
Management works for you
The board
And the board you work for me and all of the other shareholders
The board did not seem immediately suede
And it's easy to imagine how this whole thing might feel on the other side
If you're say Richard Harwood
You got two guys who have never even worked in the tool biz
Telling you how they think the business
That your father build-up should be right
And how much you should be paid and who should be on your board
4/10 tables what had started out as a rational investment something just based on numbers
I become emotion
It becomes something hard to let go of
At some point in this whole fight
Tim's letters to the company took on a different tone
He got rid of the lawyer who'd been better
Some of the letters starts have words in all caps
Some start to feel weirdly into
What is address just to Richard
And uses phrases like I was at the end of my rope and
Goodness knows I tried a different course
And then in the summer of 2010
What's a decade
After 10 first bought stock and pmf industries
Something finally went his way
There's a change on the board
The two guys who played golf at the same country club is the CEO step down from the committee
Also one of the people Andrew had recommended for the board got put on the ballot and elected
And a year-and-a-half later we haven't noticed this is an incredibly long process
It finally happened
The thing that almost never happen
The board of pmf
Did what and ruin someone
They cut Richard Horowitz his base salary
Buy a lot
From $975,000
To
Cut of over $300,000
It actually made the news
At least a little corner of the new
An article in a publication called the institutional
An expert in that article said it was the first time he'd ever seen shareholders get aboard
To cut the pay of a sitting CEO
Tim Staples of course was it elated about
Was so fantastic
Stop green felt like
I had
Serve to affect this change
Is that I was an agent of change
Crelike
Me from LaPorte Indiana typing my angry little letters
You know
Used to be sound board games
I just got to see you a salary cut by $320,000
Yeah yeah that's how it felt
That feeling did not last
It turns out
That new contract also made it easier for Richard Horowitz to get a bigger bonus
And in 2012
Even though Horwitz is base pay it been cut he actually ended up making more money
Then he had the previous year
And then
Richard Harwood got a raise
The board boosted is base pay by $50,000
And they also raise the bonus percentage is so he'll be able to earn even more
The bonus
The company only let us talk to one person on its side
But it was someone we definitely wanted to hear from
The board member that Andrew Shapiro
I'd recommend it
Met him one afternoon at a business Club at the top of a tall building in
His name is Howard Brownstein
And he told us he thinks Richard Horowitz his pay is reasonable
Yeah are you I would say to you that based on the work that the
Comp committee did as they reported it to us and as we listen to it
That the compensation is within the realm of reasonableness for our company and how it's doing
And
The money we make for the shareholders
We have brown Stein about that compensation
Study that Tim asked about on the
The study that compares Richard Horowitz
Pay to the CEOs of other companies
And we read Brown send this letter Tim wrote asking the board to release details from the
Airport
Ask it's probably the wrong
Tim Wright
I demand
In all caps
And then at the end
Also in caps
I have waited long enough
I am done waiting
Well
You know but
Misha Staples obviously it has been able to find the caps lock key on his typewriter
Look generally in in my world when somebody demand something is because they have a legal right to it
He may say he demands it
But the fact that you guys have a right to it
So what you really is
Where were you really meant when he said I demand it is I really really want it
I got it
It's okay
You can't have it
Next
He's one of the owners of the
Sure yes but the owners of the company only have the rights that they have
The rights the law gives them
It doesn't give them more than that
Since peanut wouldn't release that study
We asked a company that analyzes CEO cup
Compensation to take a look
The company is called a cooler
They do a lot of work for a companies were trying to figure out how much to pay theirs
Here is what ekwill are found
Among roughly 200 companies of similar size
Richard Horowitz is pay rank near the very top
In the top 7%
More than twice the app
Heckler also looked at a smaller group of company
Is that like tnf
Ironwood called the industrial goods sector
There were 13 companies in that crew
The top paid CEO was Richard heart
In other words according to the study
Richard Horowitz is one of the highest paid or D highest paid
Tim Staples lost
But he don't shares and PNF for most of his adult life
When you've been in something that long
It can be hard to know when to walk away
What happens next you going to keep at this
The question him
I thought about that
Yeah yeah I want I want the company to know that I'm not going anywhere
Everything about giving up
No really
Giving up meme
I can tell you what giving up looks like
After we talked to Tim
Had a momentary cash crunch
Had to sell all his share
The company bought the
And as part of the deal
Tim promised not to buy any shares of pmf Industries for 3 years
It turns out
Really hard to cut a CEO's pay
Even if you own 5% of the company
Now he has even less power to do anything
Now
Tim Staples
It's just like everybody else
That is how the story ended when
We first reported it two years ago
We will check back in with Tim and Andrew to see what's happened since then after the break
Support for this podcast in the following message come from Capital One keep your credit score at peace with a
Credit-wise app from
Capital One
Get alerts each time your credit is pulled and when your TransUnion credit report change
Plus it's free for everyone
Download the credit wise app today
In the past week or so we called up Tim and Andrew to see what's happening
Tim reminded us that he is still banned from owning pmf shares
But that man
Expires in October
And she told us it is more likely than not that he will invest in the company again he will buy stock
Andrew for his part said
He is actually increased
His investment in the company since we did the story
He bought more stock and he told us
You think the executive pay situation has gotten better
Or at least less bad
He went from excessive and egregious compensation
Down to only excessive compensation
Also Andrews still dialed into those earning
And it is pretty much incompetence
And he responsible for the day of this year
Continue
You can email us at Planet Money at npr.org you can find us on Facebook or Twitter and if you have ever wanted
To see Planet Money in person you will have a chance
I will be at the now hear this podcast Festival in New York City from September 8th through 10th
There'll also be a bunch of other podcast doing stuff they are
You can go to now hear this fest.com
To learn more and get your tickets the first hundred people to enter the offer code money at checkout will save
$20
Special things today to the staff at this American life especially Sean Cole who produced this story Caitlin Kenney
Planet Money also helped out
Today's rerun was produced by our intern Edwards soccer field
You want to leave you with one of their little detail in Tim's de buses dining room right next to the broken Dungeons & Dragons pinball
Time machine there was a piano that did
Rest in the playoffs
And he offered us this
Buy largely forgotten composer Louis Moreau gottschalk
Confetti blasts Jeff Barnhart
I'm David and I'm Jacob Goldstein thanks for listening
Got to love that
God that is Jay