Heights Jacob Goldstein Today Show first ran in 2014
There's a brief update at the end
This is somewhere in Utah
I'm not going to say where
Outside a small town the end of a dirt road
One of those storage for sale
You know the places where people stick stuff that they don't have room for in their basement
Were they occasionally put something really value
What kind of security do you have there
I have a padlock
The door
This is Bob Peters
Bob claim to sound that thing
People have sought
Thousands of you
An investment
Guaranteed double in value
Free money
And keeps it in the storage locker
Plug in the lights
So I can see
There's the usual stuff boxes of family photos couple bikes car seats actually an old car with a flat tire
And then in the middle of all this stuff
There it is
His secret
Treasure
When I tell you what it is
It's going to seem very Orange
Marketing College accounting or science
Books by thousands of fat used
Industries
American history
Nursing
The boringness of this
That is Bob's itch
He's figured out something about the history of the Vietnam War 4th edition in mathematics with applications that apparently
No one else knows living with art the art of public speaking
Taking loan welcome to Planet Money I'm David catching there's a term in economics for this kind of thing Arbitrage
Women's free money guaranteed way to buy low and sell high are basically impossible to find
Damn show two guys think they did
Support for this podcast in the following message come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities to help ensure a brighter future for America's
Children more information is available at aecf. Org
A little while ago we did a show about college text
And afterward we got an email
From Bob's brother-in-law
Sing
Great show
But by the way there is just one other little odd corner of the textbook world you might be
And of course we were
I called up Bob and he told me he discovered this textbook Thing by accident
He's running a small business out of his house selling
T-shirts
Flip flops and stuffed animals on
On Amazon
And sometimes telling you
He picked them up at a local thrift store
I'm trying to sell them online
Quickly you learned that
Fiction books are worthless after they come out with in 6-7 months
Everybody's got a copy of it and no one wants to buy another copy of it
Text books he noticed something weird
Their prices Jump Around
A lot
The first time you noticed this was with an economics text
He put it up on Amazon offering to sell it for 15 bucks
Someone bought it
But then as he was packaging the book to ship it off he looked online again
Any found that the going price for the book had jumped up
225 bus
Wow send this book went up in value did you wonder why that was happening
No I didn't even give it much thought that I'm just wishing that I would have sold it for more money
That was an extra $10 you could have
We started tracking a few
I saw this one book go from a few dollars up to 60
The classic example of Arbitrage is that you find one thing that is selling for
Two different
Say Toyota stock
Is trading for $100 a share on the New York Stock
Play Seether on the Japanese exchange it selling for more $102
You could buy it on the first exchange sell it on the 2nd
Done couple Mouse clicks on YouTube box
Free money
Bob thought she was seeing something similar in textbook prices
Only the prices were mismatched over
Time
Given that a fury for what's going on
He guessed that the prices were going up and down
With the College calendar
When a semester ended say it's summer
That's when the books should be cheap
Students will be eager to unload their heavy book
And there be no one particularly site to buy them
No one is looking for a nice textbook in July to curl up with on the
Beach
When the next school year start in
Classes
Aaron would be like I need a book I need a book
And prices should go up
If I was right and this was really happening
Reliably
With lots of books
She could make money
Buy Low sell High
Last year he tried it out with one book and protect
Campbell's biology
Huge thousand paged
Waiting for the price to drop anybody
Eight of them
Around 8 bucks each
Any posted them on Amazon for $39.99
You waited
And he sold them all
Powershell create I'm like okay there's something here
And this is when I approached Kenny
He's my brother-in-law
Kenny Jacobson
. if I remember correctly
It was my sister
We were on the phone she's like
Bob has some idea that has to do with
Xbox and
Programming and database I don't know you want to talk to him
Thor coming down for Easter saying talk to him then
They got together at Kenny's parents
And Bob explain his secret
What he found
He said he wanted to scale it up
Kenny was a programmer
Bob figured he could write some code to watch the prices and
Analyze them
Helping figure out what books to buy
When
Kenny listen to the
During that time I was kind of obsessed with the stock market is reading all these books and I'm a programmer
Buy trade and sell
I think every programmer goes through a phase where he or she thinks they can beat the market you know because they can
Program their way through it and and I learned
My experience.
You can't be with the stock market there were too many people
Too many computer trading algorithms all looking for any little pad
That's the thing about Arbitrage
Everyone is looking for these ways to make free money
And as soon as someone finds some little mispricing
It goes away
The act of trying to get
Free money
Pushes the prices back into a line
Stock market seems unbeatable
But maybe there was a way to beat
The textbook
Now if you're looking at stocks or bonds or some
There's a ton of data
Neglected for decades
You can make any chart or graph
Protect books there was nothing like
They needed to figure it all out
Kenny Road code that will go to the Amazon website
And automatically check what price thousands of different textbook
Trucks were selling for
It did this every night
What's Campbell's biology selling for now
Then again the next
What's Italian for now
The next day
They let this run for months
Waited patient
Computer sucking up all this
And then they started to make charts
See if they could
Find that semester
Once we had a Year's worth of data
Then you should really see the the valley
And the peak
Is it a really clear pattern not everyone has a clear proud pattern but some of them are just amazing
What one looks really amazing
Well the gold standard for this
This textbook season is adult development and aging
Let me find out what was it called
You want to buy has been number 0 0 7
E85
Force Talia
We've got six of those in inventory
Oh my gosh
Okay that is a guitar
In the summer the book it's a low of $16.92
But then
Right around January 1st
It starts shooting up
And at
January 29th
It's in the $250 range
From 16x to 250
The chance to make over
$200 on a single
The pattern was there for lots of books
Arbitrage
Free money
It's as if you'd found a stock
That went up and down at very regular time
I'm so that you know exactly when you could buy it and then you would know exactly when this
And you would guaranteed make money
Yeah that's what got us excited
They decided to go all-in
My $10,000 worth
The views textbook
Which one you're buying books for eight bucks or four bucks each
It's a lot of books
You're like a hedge fund for text
That's a good way of looking at it yes
A very small light
A very small one
1 basic operating principle of hedge funds is that
If you discovered a secret way to make money
You don't email reporters about it and then explain your whole strategy
But they got a head start
A couple years data that no one else
And when they describe the day-to-day of running a textbook Arbitrage hedge fund
I feel a lot less like free money
Bob sometimes gets 40 boxes in the mail yet to open each of them put the books in the car take him to the storage locker
Posting for sale on Amazon when someone buys a book and got to go back to the storage locker get the book packaged up ship it off
As you might imagine the folks at the post office know I'm pretty well
They let him go in through the backdoor
I don't know
I don't know if we should
Say that I don't want anyone to get in trouble
It's like he's another employee there
As investment funds go
This was worked out pretty well
For every dollar we put in we get $2 back
Does that sound right Bob
Yeah yeah it's it's about right that's pretty conservative but probably after
He doubled your money in this semester
Yeah
I looked up the top performing hedge funds and their average returns are like 25%
Meaning if you invested $1 you get
A dollar 25 back
Kenny and Bob's textbook strategy
Did much better than that
They double their money in half a year
They outperformed the best hedge
NOK
They're only looking at making $10,000
And when you factor in Bob's labor all that box opening
It looks less good
But still
In a certain light
Impressive
Not everyone is impressed
In fact some people are kind of pissed off
I have learned I have to be careful when I'm talking about it cuz I was at my mechanics one time
And
We adjust
Started to make money off this and
And I was telling him a little bit about it
And there was another lady sitting in the waiting room part
And
She overheard us
And she's like she said something like a
Well that's just immoral what you're doing and I'm like
She's like I have a daughter in college right now and I can't believe that you would
And I'm like Oh my goodness
I have to be careful cuz
You know she interpreted it she wanted her daughter to be able to buy
The textbooks at the cheapest price
I suppose
And here we are buying them cheap and selling them back hire to her daughter is kind of how
She saw it
I was not right
Yeah except
Well
I've been thinking about where the money these guys are making
He's coming soon
They're a couple non Arbitrage e-waste
You could argue that Bob and Kenny are making money here
Because they're providing a service they are providing something of value
Taking a book off someone's hands when no one else wants it
Or you could argue they're making money as a reward for taking a risk
But no one else wants to
It's possible they'll get stuck with a bunch of these books
Bob said there's a copy of nursing care plan 7th edition he would love to get rid
I think the easiest explanation is just Arbitrage
They figured out some little piece of information that other people don't know
They found a fishing hole
The People Eater passed over
Just didn't know about
The thing about free money opportunities
Is that they don't laugh
This is why Arbitrage is so rare
If other people decide to get in on this textbook game imagine a giant used bookstore with
Plenty of money in storage space
If they want in
There will be a bidding war for those textbooks in the off-season
You won't be able to get them
For $4
The price Gap will close and everyone will be better off
The students selling books will get more money for them
The people buying them when classes start
Will get them a little cheaper than they do now
Everyone win
Except Kenny and Bop
They will be out of
It's possible someone is actually already discovered the same seek
Bob and Kenny Evan getting a suspicious number of order
I'm someone named
Mary Campbell
So Mary Campbell
Is our biggest
Book buyer
Yeah yeah
They know Mary Campbell is not some really voracious reader or ambitious students
Because
She buys multiple copies
Of the same textbook
Her address is a PO Box
Kentucky
Maybe this Mary Campbell has figured out a better system
A better way to make money off their books
A way to out Arbitrage the arbitrageur
Or maybe there's something even bigger goal
It possible there's no
Real person named Mary Campbell
It might just be what we don't know
Like that's what
The mystery of United
I could be Mary Campbell as a computer program
Buying and selling According to some algra
Bob and Kenny say the word in the used book Market is at Mary Campbell
Maybe amazon.com itself
Amazon has this textbook rental Pro
So maybe it's buying books for that
We sent a reporter to that post office in
Kentucky she has to mail clerk about the PO box
Number and the guy Shadow His colleague hey
Someone wants to know about Mary Campbell
I couldn't tell us much
They did say there was no person named Mary Campbell who came to get the mail
That was how I show ended back in 2014 we will have a quick update
After the break
Support also comes from Fidelity Investments as a Fidelity wealth management client
You get a dedicated advisor to help grow and protect your wealth find ways to minimize the impact of taxes
And make clear recommendations for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com wealth
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
Our show originally aired back in 2014
Are we called Bob Peterson this week to check in and ask him if he's still in the textbook Arbitrage
Yes it's still profitable
And so we continue to do it
I think that maybe a day and next three or four years that it's just not worth the effort
Brittany Moore
Any margins have come down a little bit
But
There's still money to be made
And it's still just a numbers game
Also Bob says
Mary Campbell is still a mystery
She is disappeared
So we don't see her
Hardly any more at all now I think he's probably been well over a year since he sold a book to Mary Campbell
We have not given up on the search for Mary Campbell if you know where she is
Email us at Planet Money at npr.org or tell us on Facebook or Twitter Today Show was reported by
David kestenbaum originally produced by Thea Benin was produced by Alice wild if you're looking for something
Listen to check out about our president before he was
President it's called embedded and you can find it at NPR. Org / podcast for on the NPR one app
I'm Jacob Goldstein thanks.