Interviewing a spy
Is very strange
Yes the other day coming I were talking
2 John Braddock
Deku with the CIA will not
Officially confirm or deny
What's a spy
And he was telling us this story
That involved his phone I have my phone in my hand
I check it
Are you looking for anything in particular
Yeah I check in for messages
IMessages emails are
Do it what would you like
Yeah I'm looking for
So here we are again
And by here John means
What's the point in this story
Where if you told us
To be fair those are kind of words not John Paddock
But of course there are all kinds of spy secrets that the CIA does not want showing up at Planet Money
Unfortunately
We can neither confirm
Nor deny that John Braddock went to some
Formal top secret spy school
I can't I can't talk about training we cannot confirm the foreign countries jaundice
Peeking around in rather not
We also cannot
Confirm the method by which the CIA delivered
Top secret message
Is it get faxed to you do you pick up microfilm under the bench by the 7-Eleven
Topoint
Eye cancer
Okay the best we got was at
Tiny detail that we can
Possibly maybe
Seemingly confirm about what it's like to be a spy
Does that ever involve like
Climbing a wall with a grappling hook
The grappling hook
Was that
You know there's
There's a lot of
Things you're prepared for
I'll leave it at that
What
Wait are you saying you may have been trained
On a grappling hook
Can a male training tok
Talked about this
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm finally home and I'm Kenny Malone
Phone and we're going to level with
You hear there's less than a month of Summer left
And for just one episode we wanted to take a vacation
From The Economist
And the market and the budget
And just talk about spies because who doesn't love spies but the problem is that when you asked
Buy the big question
They usually cannot answer
Sunset today
We asked
Little question
We have three tiny tips from spies
That we found useful and fun
None of them about crap
Support for this podcast
Cast in the following message come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing Solutions disa
Support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information
Is available at aecf
. org
Okay honey
First tip
How to think like a
It comes from John Braddock who you heard from earlier
And he told us a story about when he was a case officer in the CIA
He was in an undisclosed country
On an undisclosed
It was cold out
John Braddock was wearing a trench coat
It was early in the morning around 7 hour
John's on his way to meet his source
So we head to a subway stop gets onto a train
And walks to the back of the
I sit down
I don't see anything to be alarmed by I don't see anything even really to take a second look at
And that's when
Yeah I pull up my phone
Maybe John Braddock has some fancy Spy software that makes
Recordings on his cell phone at all times
But if that's true he didn't share
This is our own
So just looking down at his phone he's checking to see if his Source has left a message for him
And that's when humans let me see your phone very short very abrupt very direct
John says the words were in the local languages
Country he cannot disclose
So maybe the guy actually said or
Or anyway it was pretty clear the let me see your phone mint give me your
John looks up and there's a guy standing over him
Is closer
Shabby
Disheveled the phone back
Indusparquet
Where the guy can grab
I stand up the face and try to move past and he does he moves to block me
John notices the guy's hands are suddenly moving towards
I look down and Bam
Headbutts
John
I fall backwards
Feel sticky
Blood streaming down
My face
And he standing over me
Start laughing
Like it's crazy how kind of laugh
All right
So maybe what you just heard sounds like John Braddock getting caught off guard and then
Getting beat
But there is a tip in there
If you could look inside John's head
He is actually using a structured
System of things
John calls it the DEA DEA Loop
It's an acronym
Starts with Gathering
Data
Data feeds into analysis which feeds into a decision which feeds into an action
DEA
DEA data
Analysis
Decision
Action
That's what makes it a loop
You do it over and over
And it's based on a similar Loop
Invented by a famous military strategy
And it's it's a way to stay focused
To slow down a stressful situation
And really see what happened
So if I were being attacked on a train
I would be thinking of some big
Situation ending actions
Runaway
Throw a punch
Scream
But John
He's not thinking
So again
He's in that train car sitting down
Pulls out his phone
And here's that
Let me see your phone
What's an expat
Does he know I'm a spy
That would be the worst
Case scenario
This is an enemy spy
An assassin
So John rapidly does this Loop he goes to find the things
Vicki needs to answer
That question
Because too much data
Is a bad thing
To scan the car
And something catches his eye on the tree
There is a camera
In the roof
Of the carriage
Despise hate
Surveillance
You're going to confront another spy
KLM Steelers phone
Very unlikely
You do it well
John also notices something about the attacker himself
He's either dancing a little bit he's not
Focused
He doesn't look
Prepare for this moment
Data collected analysis
Has done this is not a spy trying to kill John and steal his phone
This is probably a Mugger on drugs
So when you realized that are you relieved
I don't
Don't think I have an emotional reaction it's not really relief as much as it is
Okay
It's a different situation very bad situation
Because John cannot afford to lose a cell phone that might have sensitive information on
Alright so data and Analysis
Action yet
And there is an obvious one
We could take
John is not a small guy he has had extensive training that may or may not have involved grappling hook anime not
She could probably handle
A drugged up mugger without too much
Trouble
But if he showed up
In surveillance camera footage
Fighting like he is James Bond
Or Jason Bourne
That is very bad
For the bigger game
We're trying to stay under cover
In a foreign car
It's an easy thing to always think
That
The guy
Across the table from you who may pull out a gun is
Is your greatest enemy because the thread is to immediate it starts to look very
Different from the movie
Because John does not knock his attacker out he doesn't pull out some crazy weapons I'm crazy Gadget
The action that his meticulous decision-making process led him to in that moment
Was this
I put my phone in my pocket and I stood up
He stood up
He was sitting
And then he was not
Does that even count
Incredibly boring action but in a very tiny way
It does change the situation then we're face to face
You standing
And their face
If you are really good at this. Loop you can see these almost imperceptible changes in a situation
So now John's immediately back up
How to start Gathering data
Observes the mug
Girls reaction
To his bold move of standing up
The mugger is unfair
Now John knows
This isn't going
And he has another decision to make
Another action to take
Again
I moved to the side
He moves to the side to block me
To the conflict
Not going to let John runaway order
The Escalade
And now John sees the muggers
Hand moving towards I look down
Laugh like a supervillain and walks away
That John did not exact
We choose to get head-butted and bleed all over his nice trench coat and
And shirt
But he did choose over and over
Not
To act or at least not to
Over
And eventually a solution did resent itself
For whatever reason the mugger walked away without
The phone
And in this case that is what winning looks like
It's not some big active
Courage it's not even blocking an incoming headbutt
It's seeing what's important
And sometimes
Losing the small game
To win the big
Soospy tip number one when something
Unexpected happened and
You feel yourself jumping to
Take a big action
Remember the loop
Do the loop data analysis
Decision action
How to win the more important
John hightailed it out of the trains
Gash on his head blood running down
His face but
Phone
Still in his
His pocket and made it to a hospital and was already too
Explain
To a doctor what happened
How to fix story all cooked up about
The head wound to the hospital
Make him report the mugging to the police
And John says he was also ready to refuse general anesthetic
You also don't want to do that in foreign country
Why is that
Well if you don't want anybody to put you on there and make you incapacitated when you hear
When you're a spy
That's bad for business
I guess that's true that we actually may have learned
I want to get the truth serum
There you go extra have to promise five
Don't go under anesthesia in a foreign car
Bonus tip for other spots
Art can you hear can you hear us I can hear you how about a little bit low
Tiny spy chip number two
Comes from art
Color this one is about how to
Spot danger like
Art color is a former officer in the cia's counter-proliferation division
Proliferation of nuclear weapons technology
Frontier track down terrorist
I was telling us about
How when you're in the field
Undercover
And you're in a foreign car
Having to ask
Act like a criminal for want of a better word
Because you're trying to do something or not
That means you got to always be aware of your surroundings
Surveillance cameras of course foreign police officers
But the
You need to look out for even more
Then police are laps
Locks
L o p
It's an acronym spies
Really love acronyms and here's what it does not say
It does not stand for laser operated projectiles does not stand for latent opioid
Food poisoning
Lots
Are far more Danger
And that was the acronym for little old people
Little
Old peep
And man are they Lethal lethal
Little old boy
Because lops
Have nothing to do
They sit around they look out their window and they look for
Suspicious activity in
In their neighborhood
There's a famous
Cautionary tale about this
And I want to say 1998
In Switzerland
Art says there was a team of alleged Israeli spies trying to break into a house
And place a bug
And some little lady
Was up at 2 a.m. and just
Tearing out their window and you know it was like
What's this group of suspicious people and they call the cops on them and you know then you get an international incident
It was nothing
International thing sewart says if you are a spy
The trick is that lot
Are not to be under a
But
You could also look at it another way
Not a spy
Looking to buy a house
Home lops make great Neighbors
The Earth has you should let him organizer neighborhood watch and
You know
They will let their fingers do the walking in and and make the report
Our last tip
Comes from Mary Louise
She's not a spy she's our colleague here
NPR but you just cover spies
Does the CIA
And she spends lots of time
Talking
Intelligence
Picking up there
Although
Sadly they get all the cool Gadget
Disappointed to know I do now
Night Stalker on
In a trench coat
Or have any disguises arf
Passports are all the fun stuff
But she does have a tip that you could jump on the job
This past weekend
We asked her to record it just pulling into the grocery store and the Kroger parking
Looking for a spot because we are out of
You disguise letting me go in front of him cuz he's
Cuz I do not pull straight it Mary Louise Kelly
Always
Beck's
Into her pocket
So that you can get out of a bad situation fast
The sad thing is I have never one
Getaway
But I wait for the moment
YouTube advice other people
I have
Tatar babysitters
How I want them to drive our kids so now
Kitchen
Back into the driveway
Eat at this time and take a nap and whatever oh and by the way just getting back in the parking spot
I have not checked on the word ghetto
So why do they think they're backing into the parking
How are you know so they won't back into a bus 1
Backing out of the driveway I have but you told the other side
So there you go
Next time you're in a Kroger's parking lot
Just make sense
If you got time back in
Are you spy probably do nothing if that information if you are on
Undercover but otherwise get in touch with your planet money at mpr.org and you can find us on Facebook or Twitter
Food was produced by the Two of Us by our supervising producer out goldmark editor is Bryant urstadt
Honestly that
Full series on how to think like a spy in his best-selling Kindle single Apple named a spy's guide to thinking
He also has a new one that just came out it's called a spy's guide to strategy
Special thanks to our internet eduard Saakashvili he played the mugger in our Recreation
Of John Braddock's mugging didn't excellent job with that maniacal laugh on a New York City subway
And if you are looking for something else listen to you should be listening to up first
It is NPR's Morning News podcast I listen to it this very morning it tells you everything you need to know about
What is happening in the world check out up first tomorrow morning on the NPR one app or wherever you listen to podcast
I'm finally home
It does not stand for
Laser operated projectiles also does not stand for latent opioid poison
Or
Lampreys of Peru
We don't have to say lamp what is a lamprey
Creature what's my name