What are the reasons why I went into
Why a lot of people going to
Reporting
Is it weird reporters
Have short
We throw ourselves into a new thing we learned all about it
We tell her audience about it
And then we just move on to the next
Interesting thing
Sore feels like being at the state
I want a donut burger but I want the burger patties to be the bun and the donut in the middle
As you may remember Planet Money was obsessed
Put the state fair for about a hot minute
Then we went down a rabbit hole on
Tax policy no-wake Puerto Rican by
And then all the sudden we dropped everything to launch rocket
It is fun but it's also exhausting
And so at the end of every year we here at Planet Money like to stop for a moment
To think about the stories that we've done over the last 12 months
Reflect
On what they meant
And figure out what happened to the people we interviewed after we turned off the microphone
And went to go watch a rocket launch
Put on welcome to Planet Money on Robert Smith today on the show our annual year-end tradition
It is a show that we named after the catch phrase of my favorite old-timey radio reporter Paul Harvey used
USA Today
Together
You and I are going to learn
The rest of the story
That's what we call this podcast the rest of the story 2017 will check in on Vladimir Putin
Least favorite person in the world will travel back to a small town in the bayous of Louisiana
And we have a funeral for an algorithmic trading bot
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their own websites
Using customizable layout
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online presence
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial and when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Let's begin with one of the more dramatic podcast
That we did in 2000
It was about a man named Bill Browder
Brother had an investment firm in Russia after
The collapse of communism
In a podcast called the story of how Browder angered Vladimir
El Prado
Kicked out of Russia
His company taken away
And how his lawyer
What detained
Tortured
And murdered by Russian authorities
Elsa Chang with my co-host on the story house of Robert
The Russian Warriors name was Sarah gay magnets
And Bill Browder has been trying to see Justice
First air date
By helping to pass a law in the U
Call the magnitsky
Basically what the actor
Is it freezes the assets
Human rights violators like the ones responsible
Staircase murder
So that's what we left
The story when we did the podcast this summer
Since then
Thunder weirder right
It has
IU medical bill Browder last
He told me he had been traveling the world
Trying to persuade different countries
Passed their own versions of the magnitsky ACT
Human rights violators everywhere
And everything
I came to a head in mid-october
When Canada
Passed its own version of the magnets
Just days after that happened router tried to board a flight from London where he lives
To New York
When he was checking in the airline
Would not issue
Him a boarding pass
He discovered
His US Visa was
Revoked at about point I I call up a friend who works in law enforcement and I say could you
Find out
If I'm on the Interpol
And sure enough
On the same day
That the magnitsky Act was passed in Canada
The Russians
Added me
To the Interpol most wanted list
For the fifth time
So what about the Russians can just
Add somebody to the
List
Apparently I'm just extremely quickly in a pool
Is this organization
That is used all around the world
Help countries
Find
Fugitives from the law
But the problem is
Not all the countries that belong to Interpol put people on the list with the most noble
Recently can get very political and there's no robust
Vetting process to figure out
Which people actually deserved
Beyond this most wanted list
What was the Russians
Justification
For even asking for
Well the past few times it is always been some form of
Tax evasion
But this time around daughter says the Russians really upped
The anti so they now accuse me of being a serial killer
A serial killer those are words that actually appear in a document somewhere here in a document from the Russian State investigative committee
80 which is their version of the FBI they're accusing me of being a serial killer
And who are the victims you have allegedly
Are there people who are involved in the criminal group that that some
Kilt Sergei magnitsky who died
On on there
That's part of their criminal group
Do they also realize that you killed Saturday
They have been wedge
But I killed star game
What is the theory
Or why and how
You killed are Damon
Magnitsky according to their justification
I killed Sergei magnitsky so then I could get a magnitsky Act passed in the United States
Discredit Russia
That's there
After official explanation
Their explanations you went to the trouble of murdering someone so you could use his name
For a piece of legislation
Against Russia
And and and by the way in and I did this apparently
I'm from my home in London
Sodus Point
The Russians have accused him of tax evasion and being a serial killer
What else
What happened
So I've been accused of Serial killing I've been accused of
Stargate magnitsky
I've been accused of being an MI5
CIA agent transit to destabilize Russia
I've been accused of stealing 4.8 billion dollars of IMF money that was destined for Russia
I got 25 years ago
Tax evasion fraud false bankruptcy
And is that those are things I've seen the documents on
So that there's literally like 250 people
Working inside law enforcement agencies of Russia
On cases against me
So
Obviously just got cleared up
Because he
He was in that state to talk to him
Yeah that's right a couple of senators intervened and brought us because it was immediately reinstated and he got taken off the Interpol
List a few days after that
So what is Bill Browder
Doing now
Router is not going to rest do you still determined to keep
Traveling the world
Persuading different countries
De Pastor own versions of the magnitsky ACT
And right now as we're recording this
He is targeting three countries
Ukraine
Gibraltar
A small country off the coast of Spain
In South Africa
And I take it that Vladimir Putin will not be pleased
This passes in
Every time and you country passes a version of the magnitsky ACT
It seems like Russia comes up with a new way to make Bill browder's life
More difficult
Thank you all so you're welcome
Earlier this year we are the podcast called Georgetown
Louisiana was actually a two part episode and it was about this
I need
Town Mary guinn Louisiana
And Noel King joints me now
Miracle in Louisiana had a sort of mist
It did the mystery was everybody in this tiny little town in the middle of nowhere in Louisiana is related or appears to
To be related
And nobody knows why
Or how they got down to Marin
And then
After using years of wandering the New York Times ran this story and it
Solve the mystery
These folks were in world Louisiana because their ancestors had been sold
By Georgetown University and the Jesuit order in Washington
They were slaves
And Georgetown and the Jesuits were in debt
And so these 272 men women and children were sold
Downs plantations in Louisiana Georgetown paid off
Dad send
All these people ended up and roll Louisiana
And this was a big
New story at the
The time
Because
Georgetown University obviously
Preeminent educational institution and
Nation's capital
All the sudden had to Grapple with their part
In slavery in selling people
And had a realize this new story that there were thousands
Of descendants
It's out there who
They essentially owed something
What the podcast did was both
Visit some of those descendants in Louisiana
And talk to Georgetown
About what they were going to
To do about it
What direction did was a lot of on
Campus stuff educational stuff
They renamed some buildings in honor of the slaves
Students old
Are they starting some educational initiatives they're building out the library
It's a lot of it was like atoning but atoning on Georgetown campus
The big concrete thing that they were going to do for the
Descendants for the people who are alive today
Was to give them preferential admissions in the application
Process so if your descendant you want to come and Georgetown
We're going to give you a little bit of a boost
And one of things I loved about your story why is he went to visit young people
Who now had this
Amazing opportunity
Vet came in a way
That no one I guess would wish
Right it's like this it's both
Sad but it's a tremendous opportunity for them and so you talked to
One young woman in particular her name was
Elizabeth Thomas Elizabeth Thomas's 23 and then wanted to go to grad
And when I talked to her she had just put in her application
And she'd written about being a descendant in her essay
In the beginning I kind of talked about you know
My connection to Georgetown
How be an amazing opportunity not only to go to a
Excellent
Top to University but
To go to the place where my ancestors helped bill
Did you like
Flip it in or where you were you applying as a defendant and you
You sort of we're like at and by the way I mean I thought it was interesting that there is no
Where on the application to put that you are a descendant that was in March
Did you talk to Elizabeth
And so the rest of the story and the rest of the story is Elizabeth got into Georgetown
I just going to go to grad school for journalism
Starts next month she's super excited she's super nervous and one of my big questions to her
This whole time has been
When you get up there are you going to tell people that you're defend
Yeah
Definitely think
That I will
Be telling
People I mean it shouldn't be a secret
However I don't think I'm going to walk around with a
Reparations t-shirt on
A lot of love I'm going to take it that far but I definitely am going to let
People now then
I'm here
Why I'm here my special
Inoculation
If you make a great journalist
Are they are they paying her money to know they are not a scholarship
Bishop for academic
It'll cover about half of her tuition which is $14,000 each
But she was like
This is not a scholarship that I got for being a defendant and
I think I should get to go to Georgetown for free because my ancestors built this
She's really disappointed
Call met people who have the sort of
Historical context
Some college
Here are you mad
Grandfather went here where this building is named
After my family
What an interesting way to relate
A place
Knowing that
This is to share going to
Owned
Your answer
How does she expect to feel when she
She's there she actually already knows how she's going to feel because she's been to
Visit the campus
Since you was telling me about this night she spent walking around
And like wow is this the brick that
Know my ancestry late is this the door is this
You know
Is this the road is
Set the path where did they live
It's
Going to be definitely
Aerie
Sad feeling
By Nature Elizabeth is very optimistic she's very likely to
Push through this she's really
Excited about going
But there's obviously some mix
Alright thank you so much more
Hi Robert
That said voice
Is alkyl marcar senior producer because he has some very serious news
About
Something that we love deeply in 2017
Are trading Bots
The botes
The bottom of the United States
Her legs are all a little Fuller for having known
Gear bonus
Who is created
Read Donald Trump's tweets
And then trade stocks
Every time he mentioned
I want to stop putting money into an investment account that we turned over to you
And the winds
Of
A computer program a bot I don't know how to describe it
The highly thought out carefully crafted algorithm
Of practice
Wall Street trading for
Professionals are what was behind our trading bot
I think I'm going to need a little bit of music
For this update
Cuz
On November 21st 2017
We pulled the plug
Turn off the switch
Stop the little circuits
Anarbagh Taurus
Kiss me
Otis was filled with heart
It live for one purpose and one purpose only and that was to trade
Put everything that had into trading also tweeting but mostly Trading
And it wasn't very good at
No no it was not
So I'm here to tell you
The final
Portfolio of bonus and how it had a lot of questions on this
I have
All two of the trades that boat is made
To trade but they're big one
So the biggest problem was that Donald Trump stop
Tweeting about company shortly after we began this
And then when he did he did it at like 4 in the
So we
Change the algorithm so that when Donald Trump tweeted
It would then trade
First thing when the market open
That gave us a little bit of action
On August 23rd
A David
Will remain
Enshrined in memory and Glory
The president tweeted
Thank you Arizona beautiful turnout a 15000 in Phoenix tonight
Full coverage
Of the rally
Find my Facebook page Facebook
Corporation
Andy
I thought that's a positive tweet when it was a positive trait that would buy stock
-8 with seltzer
Positive tweet on Facebook
I bought 5 shares
Half an hour later
It's sold 5 shares
And we lost a total of
Dollar fifty
Downtown dollars
It could have been worse
A November 3rd
Donald Trump tweeted today we are thrilled to welcome at broadcom CEO
Hock tan to the White House to Nancy is moving their headquarters
Broadcom bye-bye bye-bye bye-bye
Bought 3 shares
So half an hour later lost
Sixth Sense
I'm a Math Genius but this does not sound like we made a hefty profit
Auburn.
No we put in $1,000 as a team and we lost
A dollar in 56
Sent
And that's not even counting the fees which were waived by The Brokerage
So that means of your hundred dollars
You get $99
At 8
Yeah this is what I'm going to fess up when you are getting money from
All the members the Planet Money staff
I just
Secured did not give you
The money I overlooked that meant to do it and I never invested in the body
Which means that my hundred dollars
Freeloader which means that my hundred dollars was invested in the stock market which had about a
2% game
During this time
I'm so
I made for
Okay well I learned something
Okay and what I learned was that is really hard to maintain a algorithmic trading
Because it takes a
Super talented computer programmer
To constantly be looking at the code
Constantly updating
That was a thing that happened
But it should have traded a lot more
But
Almost every time it was supposed to trade something was wrong
And we didn't know because we didn't have somebody
Full-time
A lesson worth every set
Thanks
Thank you Robert
Stay tuned after the credits everyone a much demanded update
Commercial about protists have we found the answer to keeping fruit
Fresh Brothers
This message comes from NPR sponsor Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimums that can be opened from anywhere in 5 minutes Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Just in case we didn't do a follow up on your favorite podcast
Let us know what it was and let us know what you want to know and we will go find out the answer
We do the show every year
You can find us on Facebook
Twitter and email were Planet Money at npr.org
And if you'd like to see the rest of the story about our little satellite
Part 1
We've been posting some of the pictures
It's been taken
And you could track where it is
Right this second let me check
Oh
You can check in on pod one on our website npr.org
Space
Today Show was produced by Nick fountain
Alex goldmark is the senior producer writer stat is the editor
And if you are desperately desperately trying to get a few more donations in before the end of the
The Year may we suggest
Public Radio
I'm no tax accountant
But maybe better to do it
This year
You should go to donate. Npr.org Planet Money
And your donations will go to your local member station
With a little thank-you to Planet Money
So everybody gets
Credit donate
. npr.org
I'm Robert Smith
Thanks for listening
Hey when last
I left for vacation before his show was actually finished
But there was one more story
It was an experiment really that we wanted to check in on
You may remember when we went to
The produce show
Producer Sally Helm found a magical hologram filled with nanocrystals
What are those are
That purported to keep
Fruit from rotting
Well she's been testing out
Discard
Take it away song
Hate so I left some tomatoes and some strawberries and some file cabinet drawers in our office
One set with discard ones that without
And I just checked and the tomatoes are actually looking okay on both sides
Not not too bad
But one of the strawberries that was actually in with the card
Has grown
A bunch of mold looking sort of blue
I don't know I'm not a scientist I don't really know how to set up a controlled experiment but
That is mold
God is goddess
I know that that is mold