Support for NPR and the following message come from w w Norton and Company
Publishers of people power and profits Progressive capitalism or an age of discontent
By Nobel prize-winning economist
Joseph E stiglitz
So there was a financial
I remember this
And then we argued for a while.
What to do about it and a few years after the financial crisis
Congress passed a great big lot
Call Dodd-Frank
That was supposed to transform the way the financial system
One thing our new President Donald Trump has made clear
He does not like.
Anna. Frank is a disaster when it be doing a big number of Dodd-Frank
We have to get rid of Dodd-Frank we expect to
You got it a lot out of Dodd-Frank
We have a president
Who says he
Is going to be doing a great thing then
We are Planet Money
Patricia bath
Let's do it
So I think about that Frank is you know we talked about it like it is this one
Sing like it if the singular object
Time for that
I'm against typing
That is not
The right way to think about
The drink is actually many many different things like all these different rules about all these different parts of the financial
All kind of rolled into one
We are going to talk to a bunch of different
In all different parts of the of the financial system
The country
About these different pieces of Dodd-Frank
And we're going to ask now that the Trump Administration is here what is going to happen to these different parts
And I started
I started with Barney Frank
The former Congressman whose name is on the
Why is it that Frank instead of franked
American history
You ever think of it as Frank.
No I don't think about you
Much of the time I refer to it as a financial Reform Bill is there some parts I'm title
Of the
Law that is
Especially important to you you have a favorite
Especially if they are people who have more than one child
And I wonder whether they have a particular child that they treasure over the others
Religion nice. That's not the way we live our life really love this wall like a baby
I mean that's why are you really
Is it
And that you're conscious distortion on your part
I'm very angry suddenly sting like a bee I mean I talk to Barney Frank for a while and he helped me understand the lawn
Think about what might happen
But he did not want to play along with the whole pick one part of the law is let's go.
Fortunately I talk to a lot of other people for the show and those interviews
Went much better
Hello and welcome to play and I'm Stacey Vanek Smith today on the show
A small-town banker the long-haired regulator and Economist and activist
And the smartest finance writer Jacob note everything you need to know about. Frank in less than 30
We'd like to say a quick thank you
And share a message from one of our sponsors freshbooks it's 2017
And the all-new freshbooks Cloud accounting software it's so ridiculously easy to use over 10
A million small businesses are now using it working in this ever-expanding DIY economy
Send a branded invoice in under 30 seconds
Avoid offered client chat by automating your late payment reminders and track every billable
Vomit from your phone
For your 30-day free trial go to freshbooks.com Planet Money and interplanet Ma
Money in the how did you hear about a session
British show we really wanted to get into
The guts
Of Dodd-Frank
Tear this thing apart
So we call it some people who have a big stake
And ask them to talk to us about the part of the law that they care about the
And we started with someone who has it
Pretty obvious take
Oh by the way tell me your name what's your name
My name is Rebecca Romero Rainey
And what's your job
I'm chairman and CEO of Central Bank
Who runs a bank
Obviously she cares about Dodd-Frank
She talked to me from her office
In Taos New Mexico
I look out the window of my office I see the gorgeous Taos mountains
Excellent snow right now great time to go skiing
Sun is shining we have incredible Vistas I can see forever around here
That's a good sales
Play banker and Chamber of Commerce all the time
Rennies bank has 220 million dollars in
Which would be a lot of money to
To me say
Metrobank it is
Kraynak's
The big National Banks you know Citibank
Chase
They're like
10 times bigger than her bank or a hundred times bigger
There are thousands of times bigger than raney's
Is a lot of the Dodd-Frank rules that
Giant trillion-dollar Banks also apply to trainees
Rainy and a lot of people who run small Bank
State fit in a lot of cases
It just doesn't make any sense to use the same rules for such vastly
Different kinds of Banks and this is true for a lot of rules in Godfrey
Especially the part about mortgage lending which is like you know
Bread-and-butter Small Town Bank
It's just I have a sense just give me one example
So what we're talking about is title 14 of Dodd-Frank which is the mortgage reform and anti predatory lending a
Specifically subtitle F appraisal a
Activities
And section 1472 as it relates to appraisal Independence
Requirements
I had no idea
Enneagram
And that's just one section
1 subsection
Subtitle
Section
Your sit down
Read. Frank Jacob I bought it on the Kindle
So like I could have
Thumb through it
It's okay on appraisal right you talking about appraisal
Which is this thing you get when you're going to get a mortgage to buy a
Somebody an appraiser
How to figure out
How much that house is worth have to appraise
During the housing bubble some appraisers were pressured by Banks to
To overstate the value of house
So that the banks could make
Reasonably Dodd-Frank tried to crack down on this
Section 14 subsection 1470
There are lots of rules about appraisals in.
Including this one that says
A bank cannot always rely on the same appraiser
Have to rotate through many different
Keep them in Japan
Yeah you're in a large city you've got a
Hunnid appraisers to work with not a problem
Enroll markets
We're fortunate to have one or two in a lot of other markets
There are no local appraisers anymore
And so it just it's becoming more and more challenging to then be able to meet the requirements of the law
And so how many appraisers do you have in in
How many pages are there in
So we were Kodama with two different appraiser
And is that enough
Does it count as rotating if you have to
Well we're working through that
To hopefully ensure the
Did The Regulators interpret that to be the case cuz that's all we have to work with
And are you worried is either one of them like near retirement age
I hope not going to work forever
And so this one little rule that she's worried about
Is ghetto part of this whole stack of new rules that Rebecca Romero rain has to follow every time
She makes a mortgage
Uniworld to say
Which Bank employees can do which
Have
Rules that require new
Kind of paperwork for the bank
And you know there is a way in which more complicated rules actually favored big Banks over small bag
A big bank already has a centralized
Compliance officer
People whose whole job
It is to deal with
The complex reggae
Rainy by comparison whole bank has a total of 48 employees
Vitalik you can just
Have some giant compliance
Okay so bad is the situation
Do we have any idea
Under the Trump Administration with the Republican Congress
What is going to happen to this part of Dodd-Frank so this is one of the things I talked about with Barney Frank other people
One thing about Community Banks in particular is their politically pretty
You know a lot of Congress people have a
Community Bank in their District
It does seem like there's a pretty good chance that some of the mortgage lending rules and Dodd-Frank could be tweaked to go easier on small bag
Next step regulator
Former
Testing 1 2 3 4 testing spark Chilton
Bart Chilton
Roberto
The park Shelton the
The long-haired freak from Planet Money years ago Jacob
How is your hair
I think you know you you me a question back
In the day whatever whether or not it was a mullet
Is it a mullet
No it's not a mall
Wait but is it a mullet
Commit Sudoku
Highly regulated in the front
Flea market in the back until just a few years ago
Big-time regulatory job
He was a commissioner at a government agency called the commodity Futures Trading Commission
Which oversees Financial products
Cut the ribbon
A derivative is basically a
Bat in the case of the financial crisis they were all these bets
The people had placed on the mortgage
Marketon on how the housing
They were sued volumes of these bets were being made going back in
And the Whitworth before the crisis is it was just like
One Banker would call up another inside
Alipay you want
Distributive
Sure and they would make the deal
And that would be it and nobody would know
Who was betting on what
Totally non-transfer
Parent nobody knew it was going
Going on Regulators or anybody else
When the housing market
Everybody, looked around and said
Who is on the hook for these derivatives now
Nobody knew the answer
That we had a big boogie man
Leading up to 2008
We didn't know what
That was the problem
We had no darn clue
What the heck was going on
The part of Dodd-Frank that part Chilton feel strongly about
Tries to solve that problem
Title 7
Wall Street transparency and accountability subtitle a
Part 1
Regulatory Authority
Section 723
Clearing
Because of Dodd-Frank those derivatives easy
To be traded over
The phone by Bankers now have to be traded out in the
What are known as
Clearing House
Basically like a stock market
But for derivative
And these clearinghouses together with other new rules they do a few things
For one thing they give Regulators a picture of who is doing what they make the market more trans
It's for another at the bank or insurance company or whoever is trading can't cover their bets
The Clearing House
Itself
Is now on the hook
So now course
That clearing house has a very strong and say
To make sure that everyone can cover their back
The buck stops there
Exactly and you know that seems good
Because the Clearinghouse is on the hook
You don't have this
Credible amount of risk
Concentrated in the clearing
Salata box
Memebox
Stop at the Clearing House
So you know I asked you
Guess you never moved the rest
But have you improve the cyst
Two clearinghouses allow us to understand
What the risk is
We can disagree whether or not they are appropriate
Rules that Shore up
The Clearing Houses
And that's something that should be constantly calibrated
Much better
They want we had when they were big dark unregulated Market
Atleast we know about
It's not hitting like it was
Exactly and he says unbalanced like that alone
Makes it that much better
Say in terms of you know what's going to happen to Dodd-Frank
This part of Dodd-Frank
Clearing house rules for derivatives
Seems
Pretty Poppy
It seems like
You know the industry has gotten used to it people generally agree with Chilton that the trade-off they're worth it
Clearing House a good idea so
Clearing house rules in Dodd-Frank
Here to stay
Stacey Vanek Smith my favorite writer about finances
You still work as a corporate lawyer as an investment banker now he writes this
Column for Bloomberg view that as I am
Endlessly thing around the office
It's just like thoughtful
And funny
And not ideological and just
You know very often you get the sense that Matt Levine sees the world
In a way that nobody else
Lots of course
I asked him
Come in and
Talk to me about.
There's some part of everything but I think the volcker rule is fascinating
It eliminates things about painting in frankly about politics
The volcker rule
Here boiled down to one sentence is
Double garage
Section 619 a
1A
Lb. Frank.
Unless otherwise provided in the section A banking entity shall not engage in proprietary trading
What's proprietary
Hunter training means trading with your own money
Soting if your bank
You can't
Trade with your own man and encased trade means
That's right
The volcker rule tries to divide the world into
Stuff we want thanks
And stuff we don't want that
The stuff we do want things to do category include
Helping their customers who want to make trade
Who want to buy and sell things
Market maker
Is the technical
In the category of things we do not want things to do
Proprietary
That is when a bank
Mike makes a bet in the market
Just to make money for it
Not in service of its customer or getting a
Adjust
But distinguishing between those two things between proprietary trading witch
Which is bad and market-making which
She's good can be harder than then I would have thought
People say I'm a bank
Stacy German customer
Okay you want to sell a bond at a bonds for to buy it
So I buy from you
Because you're my customer right
And I'm a bank
Then I turn around
And I sell them on to somebody else
For more than I paid
I just made a profit
So now
Am I helping you out or am I making a risky bet trading Bonds in the market
The volcker rule has tied itself in knots trying to answer that
You brought
Pretty fast
Like crazy fast
So when it happened is like on the volcker was finalized it is 955 Pages not quite true
Voter list 72
Came with 882 heads preamble
Useful to explain
So it is emblematic write the simple idea
Hundreds of pages of explanation trying to
Clarify what it is
It's right and this is like a classic
Regulatory problem
But living said yes okay the details Get Ridiculous
But to really understandable cruel you got to get Beyond The Hunt
Pages and zoom out
Forget about the Tea
Look at the way the volcker rule has
Change the world
If you like just think about like what it forbids how you can game it and whatever
If it feels record
But if you stop a cancer to look at what's happened
Banks have gotten rid of their proprietary trading decks
Desks that business is gone
And that mindset difference
Matters like all the people having fun to make $100
Those people whatever their living on their private islands or maybe their work
Hedge funds
But whatever they're doing they are not working at banks that hold ordinary people's money for safekeeping and government in Troy
Any food banks more boring which I think was
Lakeview overriding goal
Post-2008 Financial
One last thing about the volcker rule
President Trump's treasury secretary Steven mnuchin has said he supports the volcker rule in general
But he says it should be simple
Maybe not, 200 pages
Next up we talked to John Cochran
He's an economist at the
The Hoover Institute
And he
Love's
I'm going to say something I want you to give me just
One word a couple words
Minimum wage
Counterproductive
Government regulation
How many words do I get on this way
Often well-intended adverse consequences
Gums up the works
Thanks
Huge crony capitalists nightmare
Top-ranked
In terms of
Regulation that Lanza fourth we need a big bonfire you say a big bonfire what do we need to burn
Almost of Dodd-Frank
List of the subsidiary regulations
And most of the
Regulatory system that failed
And setup.
So does that mean we need to burn like
What almost a hundred years now of sort of ideas about how we should
Regulate things
Yeah I almost done
It's so extreme
Yeah you're not not
Entirely on
Here is what's interesting to me about
Goodnight she does not think we should burn the rules in life
Oh just leave Banks alone let thanks B banks that is not where he is coming from on the
In fact you look sad on Frank and yes he sees
There are a million new rules
But they do not solve this fundamental
Too big to
Too-big-to-fail banks are still too big to fail
Adidas
This is for a pretty simple reason
Thanks for playing almost entirely
With money they have borrowed from other
And it's this borrowing that makes the banks
The old
Too much money too
Too many people
Joe Cochran looks at this world and he says you know what
Let's do something that's actually way more rat
Let's do something in fact that Banks themselves
Really do not want to do
Kisses
Let's tell Banks they cannot use so much borrowed money
Because that's the problem so let's say
Thank you cannot do that one thing
In the most extreme version of his pitch he says you know it
Let's not let Banks use
Any borrowed money at all
I mean that sounds
Fury like a reasonable idea but
So extreme
So what happens when you pitch this idsa in washing
You can understand the way
Policyworks especially big things like
Assertive say Cochran persuaded me so we're going to tear up Dodd-Frank and we're going to do this
Ideas have to have to percolate around and everyone has to sort of understanding
And they are
It sounds like the idea is just
It's going better than he makes it sound in fact
Both Republicans and Democrats are talking a lot about
Requiring Banks to you
Use more of Their Own
Requiring more
Capital One
And that is one of the things
The people say Ken actually
Help prevent
Another Financial
Yes more of their own money
Less broad money makes Bank
And in fact
Capital requirements have gone up in the post Dodd-Frank world
Under the Trump Administration now Capital requirements
Could go up even further and they are unlikely to
To go back down
So slowly but surely the world
Is moving in Cochrane
Okay yes
No it went so fast
Finally we have Sarah Ludwig
Who runs a nonprofit in New York called the new economy
And back in 2005
They created this hotline the phone number for people to call if they needed help
You know dealing with the financial
So we thought we were going to get a lot of calls
About rent-to-own stores
Or
Payday loans
Or you know people who were trying to get access to a bank account
That is not what
Pretty much from the get-go the phone rang off the hook and almost
Every single
Call we got in this is not what we were expecting
We're from people who were saying
That they had found their bank accounts Frozen
Or their wages were garnished
Lily and her colleagues looked into it and they found this whole industry they didn't
Even know
Companies that would buy up overdue debt
Medical debt credit card debt
And then file lawsuit
Suits to collect
And she says the company is filing the lawsuit
We're very aggressive
In many cases they were breaking the law in collecting this
But nobody was going out
And here
Is where Dodd-Frank
Title 10
Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection
Subtitle a Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection
Section 1011
Establishment of the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection
The Consumer Financial Protection Bureau
Cfpb
It is a government agency created by.
Everything about the cfpb is normally with regulatory
They are organized by what they regulate
SEC Reg
Stocksund
The FDIC regulate
Thanks but the sister did is is organized
Turtle by point of view write specifically
It's created around the point of view of the consumer
And you know as a result the cfpb has started enforcing laws
That were on the books for decades lost that are not part of Dodd-Frank but these laws had largely gone unused they were just kind
Sitting there
One of these lost their Olympic says he's an old law that covers what debt collectors can and cannot do
The Federal Trade Commission
Had
That was the agency that was charged with enforcing this law
It didn't really do much it brought a few actions here and there
That's the magic of the cfpb
Is that it breathes life
Into these laws
On the box for very long time in a way that
No other agency
Ludwig says she can see the difference
So how long is still open and we're getting calls about a lot of things but the number of people calling about abusive
Collection particularly about
These debt buyers that are suing people that has
Absolute
Way way way.
Ludwig obviously loves the
The cfpb
A many Republicans do not
They say that it has too much power that it has attacked the financial system and made it harder for people to borrow money
And so of course I asked everybody I talked to what is likely to happen to the cfpb in this
In this new political
To get rid of the cfpb entirely would require 60 votes in the Senate
I could you have to change the law
Republicans have 52 votes Democrats generally like the cfpb so that means
The cfpb is probably not going to go away altogether
It'll probably stay
But
President Trump will get to appoint a new head of the cfpb
Likely to be much less aggressive
And
Congress could cut way back on Sunday
Pretty agency
Which could of course make adjustments
And that's really the picture for Dodd-Frank more Jenner
The way that it is
Forced could change a lot but it probably won't go away
I'll probably still be around for us to argue about when
The next financial
Support for Planet Money and the following message come from ishares
Because the best
Preparation for tomorrow
Is building for your future today
Ishares by BlackRock
Inspire to build
Now that the story is done
I got to come up with another
There's a kind of story I really want to do and I think you and buy you and mean you just listen to a whole show on that drink thank you maybe
Able to help me
I'd love to do a story that's like a process story about how a business
It was this
Magazine story read a few years ago I loved it was
22 hours in the life of this one Manhattan Restaurant
That's hers like 800
Weights of steak frites everyday
I want that kind of story for Planet Money
You can email us at Planet Money at npr.org
I'm on Twitter at Jacob Goldstein Stacy what are u.s. Vanek Smith that's it that's me and Ed
Edited by Brian urstadt
And we want to thank Sean
Santa Fe works at Brown Brothers Harriman and he was very helpful in talking through
What is and is not likely to happen with.
And if you like pie
Planet Money we have a favor
Askew
We would like you to tell your friends about us
On Twitter on Facebook just left
People know that you like Planet Money
There's a hashtag people are using to recommend podcasts this month
Tripod
Tlry IPO
I'm Jacob and I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Thanks for listening
I never used it for almost never used your face
Dodd-Frank
Any politician who refers to himself in the third person
Looks ridiculous with one except
I'd like General Charles de Gaulle
He was able to take
A phone say the goal is with you
And not look like a twist
But any other politician who refers to himself in the third person
Look for dick
This message comes from NPR sponsor snowflake the only data warehouse built for the cloud
Unlock deep Data Insights with the instantly scalable Cloud build data warehouse start your Journey 2
Towards data-driven decision-making it's snowflake. Com NPR