Support for this in
NPR podcasts
The following message
Come from the UPS
Offering services from shredding
To printing to mailbox
And instead of closing this Memorial Day we
May 24th and 20
The UPS Store
He's doing another thing
All together
Opening
The UPS Store
Everything for small business
And of course shipping
Steve flatow is a real estate lawyer
He works on the ground floor of an anonymous office building in New Jersey he's got a big messy desk
And when he sits in his desk and looks to the left
CFCs family photos
His kids
16 grandkids
At weddings
Disney World bar mitzvahs Bat Mitzvahs
On the opposite wall there's a
Picture of his daughter Alice
She has curly brown hair and
Deep dimples like Steve
And he says when Lisa was a teenager she was very smart
And she was very generous
And she's also very stubborn
He remembers one night she got invited to a party way out on Long Island
And
It was snowing
And the prediction was it was going to get worse
So I couldn't see myself driving an hour and 45 minutes to Long Island and then turn around
And come back in a blizzard
Well
Histrionic
But missing the party I think she spoke to me for a day is fine I could use the peace and quiet
In the spring of 95 Eliza was 20 a junior in college
She was studying abroad in Israel
And one day she called her parents
She told us she was going
On vacation
Spring break basic
Steve reminded her of the Flatow Family Travel rules
Number one no hitchhiking take the bus
Number to never travel alone
And number three
Let me know where you're going to be
When I asked her where she was going she told me gusta teeth
I don't know where it was
And then I asked if you told me Gaza
The Gaza Strip and narrow Palestinian territory along the Mediterranean Coast
Not the safest place in the world but he thought like she knows what she's doing
She's been to Israel six times
She's been working hard all semester
So instead of yelling Adam told me she couldn't go until I wished her well into the koalas and 3 days when she returns
Next morning around 8 CE was running late for synagogue
He jumped into the car and was backing out into the
Street and put the radio on in the news came on a bus bombing
And Gaza
A bus bombing
And this
Insane and
Terrible thought flashed through his head
Eliza was on that bus
I just felt it in my bones
I didn't hear the explosion
I didn't hear the sound that metal make sense for from the side of a bus
I did not hear cries of pain I just know it
His wife called a few minutes later
He was right
That afternoon he food is real
Eliza was in a hospital in a coma
And he held her hand
He was thinking that if she heard his voice
She wake up
I squeezed your hand and whispered in my ear that everything will be okay quotes Daddy was here
But when I click over here and it just fell into the side of the bed
She never woke up
And later on
Steve would learn what happened from the state department and from Israeli investigators
On the morning of April 9th 1995 Elisa boarded a bus
From Ashkelon Israel headed to
Tu casa
At noon she was dozing off
About 5 minutes afternoon a suicide bomber in a van loaded with a
Explosives
Drove into the bus
The bus
Exploded Elisa jumped up like out of a bad dream
And then she sent back down in her seat
Piece of shrapnel had pierced her skull and lodged in her brain
Steve flu her body back home
Man after the funeral
He grieved
He and his wife tried a bereavement
Her parents
And we said at least it was murdered terror attack people like that they gasped
It's a lot of the time he ended up grieving alone
People don't know what to do first of all you don't know what to say
So don't be near you
Second of all the years of
Fear that I might rub off somehow
There's no third reason people just don't know how to react to the death of a child
The man who blew up elise's bus with a member of a group called Palestinian Islamic
Jihad small group
But the US state department believes this group got funding from the government of Iran
And they told Steve is my
Steve Flatow of suburban New Jersey decided
He was going to war with Iran
To get Justice for his daughter
I wanted to send a message to the Iranian that you cannot take an innocent life and not pay it back
I'm Noel King and today I'm Planet Money we have the story of Steve Flatow swore
It was a war a lot of people didn't want fought
Billions of dollars and some of the most tenuous diplomatic relationships in the world where it's steak
And it's a war whose outcome is still echoing today
Support for Planet Money and the following message come from wunder capital
Allowing individuals to invest in solar projects
Turn up the 8.5% annually while diversifying your portfolio
And combating global climate
Create an account for free at Wonder capital.com
Planet Money
Steve Flatow was not the president
He could not start an actual war with Iran
He is a lawyer
And lawyers Sue
But he couldn't Sue Iran
Because of a US law called the foreign
Sovereign immunities Act
This loss is a US citizen can't sue a country
What's been around since the 1970s but its roots go way back to the divine right of
Kings The Sovereign the
The king is always right
You can't sue him
Countries are like that
But Steve Flatow got lucky
Because another man another lawyer down in Washington DC had been looking for an opportunity
Bust a hole in the
My name is Steven Robert
Perlis
And I am a practitioner of international reparations law
Ce4less is a big player in this corner of the legal world
You know how we all have annoying workplace stories like
Somebody use my coffee mug or somebody parked in my spot
Steve Harless is workplace stories are like
One time I was in Libya and the police thought my toothbrush was a weapon and they tried
Confiscated
Biryani and Parliament called me a snake
I am not going to pay run on vacation next year
Deeper less as far as I can tell is a professional obsessive
And in the mid-90s he was obsessed with the law that says
US citizens can sue country
He was specifically obsessed with
Exceptions to the law there are a handful of them
And most of them cover commercial
To say that the French Embassy here in New York hires me to
Paint their walls
And I do it and I do a good job
And they won't pay me
Well I can turn around and Sue France
D'aprile is wanted another exception
One that would allow us victims of Terror to sue the country's response
At some point
A foreign sovereign
Conduct
These are the US national become so noxious
That that Sovereign has no expectation of immunity
These countries
I have behaved
So badly
If they don't get
To be immune
That is correct
This argument made sense to Congress
And in the mid-90s Congress added another except
It said Americans who were victims of Terror could sue country
But the exception was very vague especially on the question of money
Could American citizens
Sue countries and win money
Steve Perlis wanted it to be clear that they could
And then as he remembers it
One day
He was in the office
The phone rang
And there was a man on the other end
He said
Tumi
My name is Steve Flatow
Do you know
Who I am
And I said yes your daughter was killed and Israel they talked and Steve Pearl has realized that
In this broken hearted father he had found a
Perfect
Test case
A man who wanted to see what country and wanted to win money
For a reason
Kirstie Floyd
I saw it as a way to possibly put the Iranians out of the terrorism business
Fat
Big
Put the Iranians out of the terror business
That's not a small countries have bottom lines also
The goal was to make their lives so miserable that they would say
We're done
In the summer of 1996 the two men went to Capitol Hill
And they knocked on doors hundreds of doors of Congress
People
And here was their pitch
Let's say you let
Steve Flatow Surat
Let's say he wins
Let's say he wins a lot
Well maybe we can make it too expensive for Ron to be in the business of blowing up bus
And their pitch work
President Bill Clinton clarify the law to say
If an American could prove a country was responsible for an act of Terror
They could sue
And they could win damages
It didn't apply to all countries
He's just a handful
Ones that the US designated State sponsors of Terror
Iran was one of those
SNL Steve and his team had to
Prove that it wrong
Did this
Veteran had given money and support to the group that killed Elisa
To do this they called up an American Economist named Patrick
Clawson
Clawson has a skill that's kind of an unusual skill for an American economist
How do you say good morning in Farsi
Silver hair
He speaks and reads
Farsi fluently
He learned it when he was doing his PhD thesis in Iran's Economic Development
I said that if I'm going to be taken seriously by people who study Iran got to learn the language and so I threw my
Myself into it
And I discovered I loved it loved it so much that
At the time he was reading 5 Iranian newspapers in Farsi everyday
And in the mid-90s the Iranians
Kind of mind-blowing Lee actually publish their National budget in the newspaper
So one day I was reading a really boring
I came across this line I fell off my chair I said why don't you mean
Way down at the bottom under the budget lines for tourism and infrastructure
Was a line item for
Support
Tutera group
Including Palestinian Islamic
What idiot is going to put down in their budget as approved by the parliament
Providing financial support
44 Terrace
Baby just wrote it in there
Yats
This was the proof Steve Plato's legal team needed
They serve dinner on papers
They sent them in the mail to tayron
The papers were mailed back
The envelope
Clearly been steamed open
There was a mini freak-out at the Law Offices of Steven curless
Football squad look at the package to make sure that it wasn't
Mind with anything
It wasn't a bomb
In fact there was no response
And one Fleet / Citron went
To trial in DC
AC in 1998 it was
Play-Doh versus and empty
Teach are there on didn't show up
Plato's lawyers made their case to the judge
We want to put Iran out of the Terabithia
And we want you to award damages to help us do that
Three weeks after the trial the judge St fleta to come back to Washington for the verdict
He's back in front of the judge by 9 a.m.
He began to read his opinion
I found the Iranian government responsible for the murder of Alisa Flatow
And if we was answering a judgement
In favor of
The family
For approximately 24 million dollars
And Trinity of Damages approximate 225
225 million dollars
And the judge makes it really clear he says right there
I'm awarding you a quarter of a billion dollars
Punish Iran
To deter terrorists
I just slammed my hand on the table when I looked up at the ceiling and I said yes Eliza
I was astounded
And that we would never see that Columbia
Okay so here is the difference between Steve Flatow and his lawyer Steve Perla
Deflate a thought he'd never see a nickel
The pearlettes on the other hand he was there too
And here's what was going through his mind
Okay now I've got a hunting license how do I go get that money
How do I go get that money
Well Iran hadn't recognized the lawsuit it wasn't going to turn over a quarter of a billion dollars
Iran in the US have been in the kind of cold war for decades
We cut diplomatic ties after summer Ronnie and students seized the US Embassy in Tehran and held Americans hostage
But Steve Perlis knew there were still a roni and Assets in the US
There was the Embassy in Washington
It was a big house that have been owned by the Ambassador also in DC
Deflator when is Warriors Got permission from the courts to
To seize those proper
And they went after them
That's when all hell broke loose
All hell broke loose because
There is another very powerful interest
The White House
And the White House Came Out Swinging
Everytime Steve's legal team identified a property and tried to seize it
The White House would drag him into
Court and put a stop
Steve remembers
Facing off against sometimes a dozen lawyers
I listen to all your nonsense
Your legal gobbledygook and how your Fairy of the quote allow us to proceed it with
Upset
Dumb
Vital relations you know foreign policy and
So why would the White House
Do this
Steve had one in court
Heated personal conversations with Bill Clinton about Eliza
He knew the president sympathize
Everyone sympathize
Stuart eizenstat was Deputy Secretary of the Treasury at the time he represented the White House
And a lot of times he was the one facing off against Steve's legal
He knew all about Eliza
It was really heart-wrenching
I have particular empathy for her because she was young Brandeis University student
Which happened to me my wife friends alma mater
But Stu has spent many years in government and in diplomacy
And he argues
If Sofrito could collect
Could get Irani and property
It could be a disaster for the United States
Because Iran could retaliate
And if that dominoes fell
If you try to satisfy these individual lawsuit
How to foreign government Frozen funds
It can encourage those governments to retaliate against the United States with reciprocal Act
We have over 10 trillion dollars and US diplomatic property abroad
And if we start attaching their property for individual claims then
They can do the same
Eman actually
Pales in comparison to the
Second reason
Stuart says
Those frozen assets are leveraged
The US uses them as bargaining chip
The Americans held in Iran in 79
Big part of how we got them home
We unfroze Irani and acid
When we wanted to get pows home from Vietnam
When we wanted to know what happened the guys are gone missing in action
We used
Frozen Vietnamese assets as Leverage
The Clinton Administration was arguing
You stack up the interest
So the United
States versus the interest
The single family
There's a clear winner
But Steve Carlos the reparations lawyer wasn't going to let this go
He'd won a quarter billion dollar judgment
His client was the man who sued Iran and
It became a public fight
And paralysis
Complete strangers started trying to help them out
The more public the fight became the more people
I try to tell us about what they think are rainy and Assets in the United States that we haven't found some
California you guys don't know about
Oh yeah
Absolutely
Doesn't matter
As far as the White House is concerned diplomatic property is diplomatic proper
And then one day in the year 2000
There's a big
What are the calls at the office that we get is from
A gentleman who purports to be a retired
Military
US military military officer give you a name
No-name no-name
This guy says
The US used to sell weapons to Iran
New secret there
That stopped after the Hosta
Did Crisis but Iran had already made a down payment
And he says
There's 420 million dollars of a ranian money sitting at the Pentagon in a weapons account that
Was never used
You should go sees that
Perlis calls around with friends on Capitol Hill.
It's true there was a little bit of hide the Pu that got the
That got played
I don't know that
High tide page disappeared
Here's what happened next
Pressure from the public was Emmett
People felt bad for Steve Flatow
So the Clinton White House back down
The White House and Congress negotiated
How to create a new statute called
Victims of trafficking and violence prevention Act
F2000
They offered Steve
25 million dollars
Not a quarter billion
But a weave of other families had now also sued Aron for Acts
They were owed some of that money to
It was a compromise
Steve says
He asked is it coming from the Iranians
And they said yes
He took it
I know I was not
Truly happy
I know the federal government was actually happy
And taking that into account
The money that we accepted roughly 10% of our judgment
We going to have to do
You decided enough was enough
I decided enough was enough
Remember he didn't think he was going to get a nickel
Can use some of the money to
How to start a scholarship fund annalise's name
He got on with his life
The man who sued Iran and won
Of course there's another man who sued Iran and one
Superlux the international reparations lawyer
He's been on a tear since the mid-90s
These on the strength of the precedents set by Steve flato
Eisenfeld versus Iran to other American Kids
Another bus
More than a hundred and fifty million in Damages
Genco versus Iran
A priest tortured for 18 months
Within 300 million in Damages
Peterson vs Iran
Gates vs Syria bombed Uso versus Sudan
Beecham vs Libya
It goes on
Sleep paralysis he's won 16 billion dollars in judgements against foreign countries
About 2 million of that so far has been paid out
He has won in court three and a half billion in judgements against Iran
Denise's remember what the point of all this was
3 1/2 billion dollars has gotten
Iran's attention how do you know that
Filed a complaint
In the international court of justice against the United States
All this worked at Perlis has been doing
That's a violation of international law we want our money back when making those people mad and that deterrence
I'm not saying that they will stop killing America
But they will think
Twice every time they playing out of
Basketball
And maybe just maybe
Some kid
Is going to
Survive somewhere in the world because the Iranians have said we're going to get chased
Forever
If we
Kill us National on one of these
Cuz you'll be doing the chasing somebody else will be doing the chasing
Perlis has another big case underway
Stop loss vs Syria
Steven sotloff was an American journalist
He was beheaded by ISIS in the fall of 2014
And Congress recently voted to pave the way for another lawsuit
And it's a big one
Families of people who died in the September 11th attacks got the go-ahead to sue Saudi Arabia
A country
And not a state sponsor of Terror either
Saudi Arabia is a US Ally
With hundreds of billions of dollars in assets tied up here
And we have hundreds of billions of dollars of assets tied up in Saudi Arabia
Deflator wasn't paying a whole lot of attention to any of this
In the fifteen years since his settlement he's been focusing on
His kids the 16 grandkids
Disney World Bar Mitzvah bat mitzvah
And then in the summer of 2015 just like you and me
Steve Flatow her this
What's on the news
Today
After two years of negotiations
United States
Together we International partners
Have the chiefs something the Decades of animosity has not
A comprehensive long-term deal
With Iran
I will prevent it
From obtaining a nuclear weapon
An unprecedented deal with Iran
In spite of years of tension between the US and Iran
Diplomacy had one the day
A year ago Iran implemented the nuclear deal
And a day later
A Swiss Air Force plane takes off from the airport in Tehran carrying three Americans
If it held in Iranian prison
They were now heading home
That seemed a on a Tarmac at the airport in Tiffin
Iranian guards unload pallets and
Pallets of cash
From an airplane
It was and the US has admitted the
It was the money
400 some odd million
That had been sitting in the Iranian weapons
The same account Steve Flatow was told
His money came
And he realized something
Who's money did you get
The end of the day American taxpayer money
He thought he got interested
He thought he got in Iran's money
He had
15 years later
You wake up you see the money going back to Iran
You feel like a star you feel like a beggar that you've taken money out of the American taxes
And you want the government
Twitter on the right thing
You wanted chords
The money is there
Do you ever want to just
Scream like
I was frustrated when I learned that the money had been released
To Iran
Your citizens
Have our judgements against
Issued by United States courts
It was it was low it was it was
Always with the word despicable
Because we didn't want American taxpayer money
What did Iranian money
Okay now here is an area of disagreement
Stuart eizenstat the former deputy treasury secretary
He says
No no
Congress spelled it out back in mm
Will pay but we are not using Iranian money
We are not losing our lives
This was not done by subterfuge was done by
A congressional action
Event is is Steve Flatow misremembering is he lying
You know when you're in intense negotiations
Things can sometimes be remembered in different ways
I don't know that we'll ever get an agreement on exactly what happens there
And in the years since
Some of these claims have ended up with victims getting actual Iranian money
Just about everyone I spoke to for this story could agree on one thing
In the coming years more Americans will likely die in Terror attacks
More lawsuits will be filed
And there will be more fight
It's over who gets paid
How
And whether or not they agree with Steve
Play-Doh diplomats and lawyers will tell you this is how the world is now
In part because of what he did
And here is what Steve will tell you
His daughter Eliza wasn't supposed to be on that bus that
Date sheet missed an earlier bus
And he still sometimes talks to her about
I hear her voice in the back of my head
She said to me Daddy why did this happen to me
I wish start out the same way I tell her that
Things happen that we don't understand
He tries to make sense of it for
That's what parents do
And he tries to cheer her up that's also what parents
He says you were in a place that you loved
You were where you were meant to
And he says
He believes that
And he says openly that he is at war with Iran
Even today
He has no remorse about this
He says a bully hurt my kid and I went after the bully
That's something that parents do to
Send us your questions about this episode of Planet Money we love to know what you think of the show
You can email us Planet Money at npr.org or find us on Facebook or
Twitter today's episode was produced by Sally Helm thank you Sally
And by Nick fountain
Thanks Nick
Special thanks on this one to eight on a Russia of global Impact Services
Jim kreindler & kreindler & kreindler
Michael and cats are at Covington & Burlington and Julia Simon & Kent depinto
If you're interested in reading more about the Plato suit let me recommend a terrific book
It's called the bus on Jaffa Road by Mike Kelly
The atavist magazine also ran an in-depth piece on the suit by Mr O'Connor
It's called kitten damages
Hey do you know an Undiscovered musician who deserves a break
All right we have an idea for them
NPR music is holding a toy
Tiny desk
Contest
Defined one great unsigned musician
Play the iconic tiny desk
Concert series and
Tour the US with NPR music
Super cool
All you have to do is shoot a video of your musical act playing an original song behind a desk
And submitted by January 29th
You can learn more at npr.org
Tiny desk
Samuel King
Thanks for listening