Edward was 28 years old
He was an academic scholar he just started teaching math at MIT
And on a gray February afternoon a blue Cadillac pulled up outside
Department
Pretty blonde got out of the passenger side
Another pretty blonde got out of the driver side
Amanda
White haired
Kind of short
Elderly man in a long cashmere coat
Got out here and snuggled up between the two blondes
They knocked on the door
The man introduced the young women as his nieces
I was not even I I believe it but my wife
Angrily disagreed is it not nice
And what was this guy's name
His name was Emmanuel Kimmel
Its 1960
Kimmel tells Thor he's a wealthy businessman
And in the parking lot
New York
He does not tell Thorpe that he used to be in the illegal gambling business
In New Jersey
Camels there because Thorpe had just published a math paper claiming that he could do what nobody has ever done before
He could consistently beat the casinos in Vegas
You come up with the system for the card game black
That he said would give the player in it
It was just a theory it was just a map
But you thought you could work in the real world
Lisa Thorpe
Practice a little bit Let's test it out and then let's get on a plane to Nevada
You can use my money
Well he wanted to start with $100,000 for myself you know
Thousand dollars by the way
Is almost ten times that amount in today's dollars looks like somebody's going to some math kid and being like
Let's go to Vegas with a million dollars and play blackjack with your system
2 months later edsource was sitting at a blackjack table in Reno
With thousands of dollars in chips and a new way of thinking about
Hello and welcome to Planet Money
Anticonvulsant
Play on the show Howard Thorpe set out to be a scholar
With sideways into gambling and went on to earn hundreds of millions of dollars as an investor
Blackjack and keep things the way Wall Street thinks about making money
He was the first one
We'd like to say a quick thank you and share a message from one of our sponsors freshbooks who are on a mission
In 2017 to simplify your paperwork
Freshbooks makes loud accounting software for self-employed professionals that's so ridiculously easy to use
Babe now helped over 10 million small businesses save time and get paid faster
Send an invoice in under 30 seconds set up online payment in two clicks
And track time using their mobile app
For your 30-day free trial
Go to freshbooks.com
Planet Money
An inter Planet Money
In the how did you hear about us
Few years before that day the Cadillac pulled up outside his house at Thorpe was living in LA with his new wife
He just finished his PhD at UCLA
Enter Professor had told him about these soldiers
Switch spent their time in the army plane black
They were mathematicians
And they wind up publishing a paper
On how to play the game
Thorpe you up a little card like this little chichi
With instructions based on their cyst
Any went to Vegas
To try it out about halfway through
People were ridiculing me that I was playing slowly and the dealer was saying you know I'd
And what form do I come from
The biggest Thorpe is just one more sucker with the new way to lose
You know people have been coming up with sister
Forever but no matter what system you use
Including the army guy sister
You were still going to lose in the long run
The odds are still going to be in the houses
In blackjack it's just
You against the
You add up the value your cards
And the winner is the person who gets closer to 21
Which by the way is why Blackjack is also
If you go over 21 you lose automatic
Even if the dealer also goes over
Start out with two cards
You keep asking for more wanted
The time that you get
Three cars maybe for more than that is really pray
Tow towards plugging away at the
Table using this little strategy
Chichi to tell them how to play
Annie's getting mocked
And after
Amanda
Amazingly the card
Created an unusual situation
In this one hand Thorpe's little Chichi told him to just keep drawing and drawing
It just seemed totally ridiculous but Thorpe didn't think about it he just did what the cheat sheet said
Kept asking for more cards with 7 cards
Unheard of
And they added up to 21 on the nose
He won
They were initially ridiculing me
And thinking another fool with the system as I looked up my little card
And then when I got to 7 card 21
They seemed
Cut it off and what was going on
So I said to myself
What are these people now
You realize the expiration date
It's the people who make the rules at the casinos
Didn't really understand black
He thought if I could just improve the army guys system a little bit
I could tip the math in my favor
I could beat blackjack
So I
Set out to devise a system
To do just that beat it
The game has been around for hundreds of years people have been trying to beat it including like
Smart people write who work
You know who knew probability
That's a good point in probability self
Got started
Because
Mathematicians
We're interested
I'm trying to figure out
The odds in gambling games in a particular how to beat gambling games
And the result was you can't beat them
Meanings of big they discovered that the house always wins
Exactly right
What you don't know matter
Going up here against not just the Vegas casinos but that you don't
Hundreds of years of the history of probability Theory
You go back to UCLA
Go to the library
To take another look at that part of
Michael from the Army
I'm standing in the stacks I pulled the article down
I started start reading while I'm standing up
Staring at the article that has this inside
Blackjack is fundamentally different than other gambling game
Most of the games
Whatever happens on
One trial or one play of the game
Doesn't have any influence on what's going to happen next
So if you roll a paradise and get a 5 on one roll
It has no influence on what totals going to come up
The next role
The roulette wheel comes up red on one spin or onto spins around 3 spin the odds of whether it's going to come up red
On the NetSpend do not change
Blackjack was differ
At the time the dealer dealt from the same deck
For several hands in a row
Which meant that say if you got an ace in the first hand
You were in fact
Less likely to get an ace in the next
Other systems at the time including the army guy strategy only looked at what was happening in one hand
It's not just what's in your hand.
It's what happened in the hand before that and the one before that
As I'm
Turn down the page
I realize I'm in order to
The cars were used up during the play of the game
The odds of shift back and forth sometimes for the casino
Sometimes for me
Sorbitol estimated to stop
Just looking at the cards in his hand
And start thinking about the whole deck
Right away he thought of this math techniques you learned in grads
Called measure Theory
That could help him work out that
The idea was pretty straightforward to me
The hard part was actually
Doing all the calculating
It took more than a year to do all the cats
You got that job teaching at MIT
Keep going to the Math building in the middle of the night to work on the calculations
Started using apartments punchcard ibm
As the weeks and months went by
I finally got to the point where I could ask
The Machinist question
What would happen if I took
All four aces out of out of the deck
Sewing machine came back inside well
Hyundai sportback
Her supplier and I can calculate
From these results
How much
In other words he now knows that if he's sitting at the table playing Blackjack
I see is a bunch of pieces go by
You're out of the deck now
Is odds in the next hand are a lot
You should bet as little as possible
Because he is probably going to
Adderall the other cards
I found out that diff
If I go out of the deck
Player gets a huge Edge bigger than
Any other card
He figures out that if a lot of small cars go by
And a lot of big cards are still in the deck
The odds are in his favor he is more likely to win than to lose
Andy calculator
30 bet small when the odds are against
And big when the odds are in his favor
He will win more than he will lose
Ed Thorp
You are the first person to develop a scientific system to beat the casinos at blackjack
What are you going to do now
I said well I'm going to publish this in a scientific journal
I want to order another
But like
Why
Like why were you more interested in publishing then in making money
What I thought
Was that I was going to leave the life
Of an academic
I thought I said
Teaching in University
Will be a great life and I would just
Enjoy doing what I did
And that's pretty much all I cared about
And it does seem like a a step in that direction like
You know making you out to be sort of an interesting
Math
Researcher scholar
Well I didn't think of it that way I just thought
Here's something that's going to amaze you guys you haven't
Doing a magic trick or something right
Exactly
The proceedings of the National Academy of Science
Published
It was titled
A favorable strategy for twenty
It got picked up by newspapers all around the cut
And once again
People start making fun of
I think he's just one more crank with a C
Casino spokesman said quote
When a lamb goes to the slaughter the lamb might kill the butcher
But we always bet on the porch
Thorpe wanted to prove that his sister was
That it would really work
So that day when Manny Kimmel drove up in the blue Cadillac and offered to stake Thorpe
Thorp City
Detox Kimmel down from that original hundred-thousand-dollar off
Just seemed like too much money made
They wanted to come with $10,000
Which was still more than Thorpe got paid
And two months after that first day
Thorpe was ready to fly up to Nevada with
But before we left
Thorpe wife asked him to call everyday just to let her know how things
And I said
Help
Phone calls are pretty expensive
Why don't we
This way we can do without having to spend any money
Here's what I'll do every night tour says I'll call you
I'll ask to speak to Edward for
And I'll add a middle initial
That will be like our secret
So if my middle initial is a
That means were
Up 02 $1,000 if it's a b or up
1002 $2,000
And so on all through the alphabet
Centos wife refuses to accept a collect call
The way of sending a message for free
And when we hit our teak I think what we're up 13,000 at one point
I asked for Edward M Thorpe at night she sounded very happy
So just to be clear
You are up by more than $10,000 you had just made more than $10,000 in a few days of play
Playing Blackjack
And you didn't want to pay for the long distance
Well you know I grew up in the depression
That mentality sticks
Kimmel is backing
To keep most of the Wind
But for chair was more than $1,000 about 2 months out
Started to change the way you felt about me
For the first time we didn't have to look at him out for a little while
Haha that was a that was a pretty nice feeling
What I thought to myself was well
Las Vegas could be kind of a piggy bank for me
I need something I can just go out there and get the money
A lot of people feel that way about casinos with differences everybody else is wrong and you are left
What does go back to
Casinos Within
Does win more money
And he writes a book called beat the dealer
The best seller
Becomes like a minor celebrity
Goes on a gameshow
What Laurel Dr Edward Barber
Please stand up
Casino start filling up with
You know people who want to be like at Thor people who are trying to count cards
They start changing the rules using mordex shuffling more often to make it harder to count cards
You know he never said how to
Get rich and casinos are done
With casinos at
But he thinks himself
You know I beat the casinos
Maybe I can go bigger there is obvious much bigger Casino out there the stock
Maybe I can beat that
You tried picking stocks
So I made a few Investments
And they worked out
Terribly
Meaning when you say they were terribly
You lost some money a lot of money
Well I bought one stock at 40
What are the 20
Suddenly Thorpe is once again just one more sucker doing what everybody else is trying
In this case
Figure out which stock is going to go up
He needs to figure out how to do what he did in Black
How to zoom out
You know not just do a better job of what everybody else is doing
Look at the market in a whole new way
He starts reading about the market in stock option
In particular something called a call
Call option gives you the right to buy a particular stock
At a set price before some future date
In the late sixties when Thorpe start looking at this
Call options were seen as really risk
In those days
It turned out that
People thought of calls as lottery tickets
There's a good chance to call wind up being worthless
And some chance that you can make a ton of money on
Store for Less that the prices people paid for calls were all over the map
They didn't know how to Value them
This is like that moment in the casino where he realized that the people running things didn't really understand what was going on
Again Edwards black Jackie sort of zooms out you know things bigger uses math as a lot of calculations and
Try to find a net
I got a really need formula
That's why I like this formula it looks right to me
I'm going to try it out
The formula worked
He figured out a way he could trade both call options in the underlying stock
So that he'd be protected
If the price of a stock went
And he started making money
Consistent
2 years later by the way
A couple Economist came up with the same formula and they published it and their work went on to win the Nobel
Anyway
Start managing money for some of his friends in college
Cassandra start an investment
The first one that is really driven by math and Technology
And the firm has this incredible run
Of using quantitative techniques
Define just one Edge after another
For something like 20 years it is one of the most successful
Investment firms in the cut
Like 230 months
We had
3 downloads
All the others were up
I'm through down my thrall less than 1%
So it's like that I feel like that's not supposed to happen
Nobody nobody makes a profit every month for
Price
Is it because just smarter than everybody else
I'd hesitate to say that there are lots of smart people in this world why did you do this wildly improbable
Why could you do
Well I was lucky
And in that I came at Investments through
The blackjack tables
And the blackjack tables are an amazingly good
Training ground
Learning
How to invest
How to think about Investments
How to manage them
And the reason is that they teach you
On the one hand
Do use
Probability and statistics to evaluate things
And I'm the other they teach you discipline
When you find something you stick to it
The Firm was called Princeton Newport partners
The Newport part was for Newport Beach California
That was where Thorpe ran the firm
Strategy
The Princeton part was for the Princeton New Jersey office that was where all the trading
In the 1980s
Some of the people in the Princeton office on the East Coast
Were convicted in federal court for this
Skiing to avoid
A lot of the charges were overturned on appeal Thorpe himself was never charged
Cuz he didn't know what was going on
But that was the end of the fur
The Firm shut down
After that or pound a few more ways to beat the market
He bought a stake in an oil tanker when oil tankers were selling for
Scrap value more or less
During the.com bubble he figured out how to profit in the middle of that craziness
And all of these
Deals at all of these markets
He's thinking about things the same way he thought about
Yeah I'm looking at it in a new way
You know and I'm using new information
From the new way that I approach the game
It's the same with all these other approaches
If you if you bring in more information
What what seemed unbeatable
May become beatable
Thorp is 84 years old now he's basically out of the investing
But the investing business
Has transformed itself to become more like Ed Thorp
You know before you came along
You didn't get a math PhD or a physics PhD and go up to Wall Street that just was not a thing people did now it is a totally
Normal thing that people do
What street is now full of people trying to do what Ed Thorp do
Trying to use math and computers to find new ways
Of looking at mark
Do you have a sure-fire money-making scheme email address of Planet Money on NPR. Org
Repeat it to us Arts contest on Facebook
Comes out later this month car show today was produced by Nick found I'm checking Boston thanks for listening
Also Tom Hanks
This is Tom Hanks
You know an Undiscovered musician who deserves a break
Well we have an idea for the NPR music is holding a tiny desk contest to find one grape
Unsigned musician
The play the iconic tiny desk Concert Series in 29 states with NPR music
All you have to do is shoot a video of your musical app
Playing an original song behind a desk
And submit it
By January 29th
Learn more npr.org tiny desk contest
One last bonus back
So he came up with that formula to Value call up
Remember a couple years later some economist
Came up with the formula again
When did winning the Nobel Prize one of those Economist Myron scholes
He went on to be a key player at a hedge fund call the long-term Capital Management
Long-term Capital Management is famous today because
It blew up
And almost took down the economy
Had to be bailed out
They used Too Much borrowed money
Too much left