If you are a Highschool student and you dream of playing in Super Bowl
You go out for the high school football team
If you want to get astronaut
You go to the sign
But if you want to someday hold in economy
In the palm of your hand
If you want the power to control interest
Print money out of thin air
The Federal Reserve High School challenges for you
Hello and welcome to Planet Money on Robert Smith and I'm Jacob Goldstein today on the show
A contest made for
Planet Money
The battle of the bomb
The Thriller
Of the vanilla
The Superbowl of monetary control am referring to
High School fed challenge
And I should just jump in here to say this show is a rerun it originally ran in
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Fidelity invest
As a Fidelity wealth management client
You get a dedicated advisor to help grow and protect your wealth find ways to minimize the impact of Pacs
And make it clear recommendations for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage services
Is LLC
Hello
Clojure
Hello everyone good morning
We're in a gym that's got a wood floor there's a basketball court but we're not at a high school where on a high floor at
At the New York Federal Reserve
Big imposing Stone building a few blocks from Wall Street
Downtown
Connection of a decent basketball court up here
Hello everyone good morning
Welcome to count high school fed challenge
About 9 on a Tuesday morning and they're about a hundred kids here from schools in New York and Connecticut and new
New Jersey
A lot of blue suits a lot of red ties
These kids they will be competing today to see who can do the best impression of a central bank
We will find out today which of these teenagers
Has the chops to control the USA
Perhaps it will be a kid from the reigning championship team from Montclair New Jersey
Montclair is a Suburban town outside of New York
How to play
You might live if say
Actually worked
At the Federal Reserve in New York
If 30 kids show up at the high school
In February to take
Spot spot
There were multiple rounds
The tryouts are School
Takes a quiet Siri
And have you been practicing since February then
We do like everyday after school for at least
2 hours like 7
Montclair is the team
And they exude so much confidence that they actually refer to eachother as
President show and tell
Governor so-and-so
As if we actually worked at the
Their competitors include the team from Ridgefield Connecticut
Team also made the finals last year
And the ritual kids they made nameplates calling themselves
Governor so-and-so of the Fed
But at the last minute they decided that was a little bit too
It's clear that they are really deep into this world in fact
You're so deep
But they've actually started to Central Banking words in ordinary
Moderate
Moderate relative because you can use relative at any time
It's a relatively good answer
Well anchors that's a good one
What's the expected to is also another good measure Quizlet cisse
Something is expected
To stabilize for example and then
I think reasonable housing prices are expected
How to stabilize Swan most recent reports
It was also on the reports
6 months ago
It's really just use words that are just
Just vague enough
Just get to a point but you know yeah
All this fed lingo will come in very handy
The team that sounds most like the fat will win this
The three parts the
Each team has to diagnose the state of the economy
They will be using many charts and graphs
Each team has a what should the FED do
Should it raise interest rates
Sore keep them low
+ 3
The teams will have to answer crafty questions from actual
Economist at the Federal Reserve
Basically these kids they want to sound like this
Incoming information suggests that the economy has been expanding moderately
Most committee participants expect economic growth remain moderate overcoming quarters
And then to pick up gradually
Ben Bernanke
Chairman of
The Federal Reserve
The gold standard
No gold standard jokes at the Fed
All right
As a state goes on as the competition
Progresses each of these teams will have to go into a small conference room
And there they will face a Stern panel of judges
And one by one each member of the team
Will do their best
Ben Bernanke
Due to significant fact in the job market as well as the lack of Weights pressure
Inflation expectations ever Madewell anchor
Turn to page 9
This kind of the flags in the pce Trap
Complacent about the headline anchor levels remain soft
Your your headline prices are up 2.3%
With court one point nine percent
Note the use of well-anchored
This is
Kevin O'Rourke is a member of that Ridgefield team
And you know one of the things that's interesting is
These kids they are not just
Parroting well-anchored and all the other jargon
Robert you and I will talk to them after their presentation out in the hallway and it's clear they really have
Solid grasp of the US
Economy and what the
Bed bug
And what it means for their own lives in this
This becomes clear when they're not doing a Ben Bernanke
Right now the economy is not in a great position but everyone is you know they're holding
It is back to 2013-2014 we don't get out of college till 2016 so
We're doing okay right now
You're willing to be patient all the high school students here don't need immediate Improvement
College with a bad economy as long as we get out we have jobs
You must also be biased toward low-interest-rate since you'll be take another look
Have housing
Housing prices are really low right now
This is exactly the way the mechanics of all this are supposed to work these kids understand it
The feds
Super low income
They are supposed to encourage
People to borrow money so
If you're about to borrow tens of thousands of dollars to go to college maybe if you're thinking about buying a house after you graduate
You love blow into
But say you're
65 years old
You're about to retire and try to live off your savings
You got a bunch of money in a savings account or is bonds
If you want to be able to live off the entry
In that case
Low interest rates are not your
I love this notion that the Fed
Current policy is the one that would be picked by an eligible teenage
You know it's funny when we talked to the Richfield team
Actually
Pretty optimistic about the economy for being a young person these days
But when they try to explain it to their friends
It doesn't go so well
I'm at think if you talk to the majority of teenagers whom we know they would say all the economy is doing terribly
So I'm not sure everyone
Pills the same
So when did you have all the stats in a little book right here
Do you spend all the time playing no it's not as bad as you think
I mean you have time to argue people but if they don't have like a fundamental knowledge of the indicators it's difficult to discuss with someone
Retail sales look at the car sales figures
What can consumer sentiment
What what's
Retail sales
The kids in the competition on the other hand they have thought about the Federal Reserve a lot
And when you start thinking about the FED it starts to seem really strange
This institution that can just
Create money out of thin air
Richfield Rivals the reigning Champs from Montclair New Jersey
They got really into the
This is Amari Shabaka
Montclair one of the really interesting things that we actually
Sort of like talked about a couple of nights ago actually was the idea that during the financial crisis to
Provide liquidity in the market the FED actually just
Created the money
To buy assets
You know the money didn't come from somewhere the FED just created a trillion dollars in the put in the market
And then when it feels like it can take that Chilean dollars and make it disappear
Well he's going to have to get his head around that concept
Pretty damn quick because Montclair
They made it to the final round of the afternoon
In Ridgefield fascinated as
So the Challenger and the reigning Champion go into the finals
You thought it was crazy before it is about to get real 15 teams came in in the morning
There are five teams that have made the finals
They are
Sequestered off
In a secret room somewhere in The Fad I don't actually know where they are and the finals it definitely feel
Like a big deal that the presentations in the morning they were in this little conference room
But the finals are here in this big fancy Auditorium with a
The stage of the
The front of my car
Griffin's one team after another comes into the auditory
They walk up on the stage
Amy answer questions from the panel of Katakana
Questions like
The Federal Reserve generally Focus
Sazon corn
Instead of mainly on headliner
What are the differences
Between these measures
Witchwood
Do your preferred measure
Call me call me I know it put your hand down we are going to hear from
Are Challenger first
The Richfield team
Biggest and most obvious difference between
Core and headline inflation
Is headline include
Energy and oil prices
Which are very volatile
And
Got to seem to change a lot
Brisk
Core generally has a more
Constant trend
Because it takes out this element of volatility
And it also includes
Oh it
It sounds like someone had to whisper that word food to
But but it was pretty good and just a restated headline inflation
It's basically a measure of how much all prices are rising
Core inflation is everything
Accept prices for
Food and energy
As each of the teams made very
Clear headline is important because
If the bottom line is it's what you and I pay every month
What is the problem
It moves around in the short
We all by oil gasoline or some form of it will prices jump up boom
Headline inflation jumpsuit
Oil prices fall
Headline inflation
If the Fed tried to change its policy
Every time
This price of oil changed
Roosevelt
It would be a mess
So in the short-term the FED pays more attention to core inflation which
Tends to be much more steady
And the Montclair team they did a really good job of explaining
But when we see political instability in the Middle East headline
Because oil price
This isn't necessarily a long-term change in inflation
Is subject
How to change a governor Lane mansion
And so core inflation is definitely
More accurate tool for judging the
Long-term increases
In price
Both teams are hitting just the right note
Of authoritativeness
And being really boring
It's so cozy this this week
And we are about to find out who won but Robert first
We have to get to a special Planet Money question that we asked
Absolutely we had
Test now
We all know what they're going to say if we ask them who's your favorite Central Banker the August 8th Ben Bernanke so we wanted to know who is your
Second
Favorite
Central Bank
I opposed to Katherine gross and Allison Schoenberg from Richfield High
They took a stab at
Yellow
Beaches on by the Federal Reserve people and
Women
John she writes speeches in just in a clear logical way and it's it's
Are high school students are able to understand your education
And we really appreciate that Janet Yellen
Vice chair of the Federal Reserve
If you are listening to this
The kids love you you are huge in Ridgefield Connecticut
Now let's go to Montclair
Who's your second-favorite central Banker
Call Boca
Good one good one
Central Bank
Dragon dragons on Hans Weidman
Weidman is the head of the bundesbank
Which let me admit I had to look that up
Draghi is Mario draghi the head of the European Central Bank and Paul volcker
He was chairman of the FED before these kids were born
You know all the challenges are very good but Montclair
Montclair
They live
Monetary policy
Winner
Is Montclair High School congratulations
And they were very excited it's funny that as soon as this was announced
They look any teenager anywhere who wins the competition
And they were 17
The team from which field they got an honorable mention
And listened okay with that I mean someone said they were interested in going into economics and
And they talked about how they're actually angling for internships at the Fed
That would be the true price
The shot at becoming
The central Bankers of
Junius brown one of the students on the Ridgefield team he took away from this a concept that I have to say as a Planet Money reporter
Where is is dear to my heart
Typically the more you look at economics the more you realize there's really a lot more going on than YouTube
Expected
Have you found yourself to be more confused the more you know
Samos depends swerve like every every question you find an answer with them with every answer comes another question
Little bit beyond
For that honorable mention Richfield gets a trophy that they can bring back to their school and they said it probably will not go into the
The case with all the sports trophies they said they'll probably keep it in the economics
Where people are more likely to
Appreciate it
Hey it's Jacob again back in 2017
Coming up in a minute
Where are they now
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org
Hey it's Jacob actually have not one but two updates here for the end of the show
Update number one is about
Real fed not the pretend fed
Janet yellen's term as chair of the FED expires in February of next
And just yesterday on Thursday
President Trump
Said that he will nominate Jerome
Howell to replace
How was originally appointed to the board of the fed by President Obama
He has consistently voted along with Janet Yellen
When setting monetary policy
You seen as a very moderate middle-of-the-road choice
The head the fat
Update number
What happened to the kids from the show
They're all grown up now
Graduated
Recology Eureka
And we managed to catch up with a few of
We didn't find anybody working or interning at the FED alas that dream did not
Come true
But those we talked to did seem to be
Gainfully employed Kevin O'Rourke
From Ridgefield he was the one who predicted that
The FED would take care of the economy that
Graduate into a healthy economy
That happened that's good
He works now at pricewaterhousecoopers
And he talked this week with
Planet money's intern Alice Wilder
He told her he think back fondly on that day at the FED challenge
But you know not
That
What did you do to celebrate
After that we went back I think we had dinner
There was no like it less at pekin
Fed challenge party that happened
Yeah surprisingly not the craziest crowd
Indefinitely
What high school things should we do a story about that
Email us at Planet Money at npr.org or tell us on Facebook or Twitter
Today Show was originally reported by me and Robert Smith the rerun was produced by Kesha mihailovic
And Alice
If you're looking for something else to listen to try up
First
It's from the people who bring you Morning Edition
Comes out every morning
Edit the podcast
So you can find out what's happening in the world anytime and
Called up first and you can
Can find it wherever you get your pot
I'm Jacob Goldstein
Thanks for listen