Hey it's Robert here I'm going to read you a very
Very exciting
I never I should say that
Has gotten a lot of people excited the number is as of
PM it is
25 point
Which seems like a really boring number until you realize that it is
Just just
Just this
Close to 20000
I'm referring of course to the Dow Jones Industrial Average and it's got everyone super excited
Thousand
On Wall Street
3 top about a little over 50 points there and we're getting very close to a major Milestone 220 South
Thousand mark
Did the Dow Jones Industrial Average
Was up 91 points
At 19900
This is NP
NPR NPR does it to we get so excited by all those zeros
The Dow Jones Industrial Average
Traditional measure of the
The stock market back in mid-December starting
High people say
This is it 2016 the year
But you're ended
Get over it couldn't pull off 20,000 before the year-end but my guest
Called it back on October 5th that we would see 20,000 before the inauguration that's January 20th
Will it happen will it happen
Who cares
This is the thing about the doubt it doesn't
Matter
If you're a longtime listener to Planet Money
You know that we
Hate the Dow Jones Industrial Average
The Terrible
Economic into
And so today as part of the celebration
Freak out that is down 20000
We are replaying it classic Planet Money rant
Here's Adam Davidson
Mk20
Hey Adam
Hey Caitlin
I'm very glad to be able to do an extended version of beating up on the stupid stupid Dow
Ever since I started working here at Planet Money
Adam you've been telling me everything that is wrong with
The Dow and I promise you
Promise you man
Today
We will go through all your gripes about the Dow
One by one
But for now can you just like maybe start
The show
Play some music and welcome people
Absolutely
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Adam Davidson today on the show we rain on the
Rate and explain why lock
A very smart people not just Adam Davidson
Hit this number so very much
We'd like to say a quick thank you and share a message from one of our sponsors
Freshbooks
It's 2017
And the all-new freshbooks Cloud accounting software is so ridiculously easy to use
Over 10 million small businesses are now using it working in this ever-expanding DIY
Send a branded invoice
In under 30 seconds
Avoid awkward client chat by automating your late payment reminders
And track every billable moment from your phone
For your 30-day free trial
Yoder freshbooks.com Planet Money
And interplanet money in the how did you hear about a sec
Let's just start with a quick introduction what is this thing called the Dow Jones Industrial
Soaps this at Big complicated
Stock market thousands of America
Can companies or if you want to get really Global you know
Tens of thousands
The companies all over the world
And people want to know how did that stock market do however
Investors looking at all those thousands
Soak the approach Dow Jones
Houses they just picked
30 large American companies
They take the share price of
Each of those
Adam up
And they divided them by a number
It's kind of arbitrary number that they made up called
The Dow divisor
And that is the Dow Jones
Industrial
And which companies are in that average
That's one of the first problems people have when they talk about what's wrong with the Dow because
Choice of a company's kind of seems arbitrary like they're all big but they're not the biggest companies in America
A lot of them like General Electric and Procter & Gamble
They kind of just seem like they're on there because I've been around forever
Stodgy it's a stodgy index Italy a company's don't to change
Frequently at all
This is John Chauvin he's director of the Stanford Institute for economic policy
You might notice
Wechat
Google
What are the door company
It's not on there
They're Facebook's not on their lot of companies to get a lot of attention
It's only got 30 companies
And by and large
These are old
Companies
So I say the Dow is
Is really
Is it the worst of it.
If I want to know how the American Stock Market is doing
I use the S&P
5000 cups
Most people who
Care about the staff use they have
Surprisingly 505000 respectively
Stocks in their indexes
A lot more than just
30 arbitrarily
Chosen One
And they give you a much better sense of how the stock market overall is
Yeah it's not just the number of companies a
It's different
Between the Dow and he's other indexes also the way the Dow does its math
Is different the way they calculate
The industrial average is different than the way the other index
Kayla why are you being so polite it's not different the way the Dow does it is idiotic it is ridiculous nobody
Play nobody nobody thinks it's a good way to do it the way they have to be
Explain people how they do it and then
All right so let's just have a company
Caitlin and Kyle Collett very creative I know
I'm going to say there's a hundred shares
I'll sell them for a dollar
Okay and I'll be Adam Incorporated and Adam Incorporated
Chooses like all corporations get the juicy
Each Corporation
Sachuest how many stocks how many shares it's going to divide itself into 2
The Selden Market
So I've decided I'm only going to have
Who shares I'm going to sell them each for $50
No even though Adam and I are selling our shares for very different prices
We were roughly the same size
This is what we call market capitalization or market cap
When you multiply the number of shares a company has X
Price of those shares
So I have a hundred shares at $1 each
I have a market cap of 100
And I only have two shares but there
$50 each so I also have a market cap
Of 100
Okay so we're the same size
Now let's say both our companies go up
10%
Yeah we have a really good month
They both got 10%
Your stock since it's divided into
100 small stocks 10%
Would a dime to each of those dollar shares
But mine because I only have two shares each worth $50
A 10% increase means each of those
Are now worth 50
The $5 I've had a $5 increase
MI share price
Even though both our companies are now still worth the same they're both worth
$110
Yeah we're both the same size we both gone up by 10%
But
The Dow
What the Dow really cares about is it cares about your $5
As opposed to my
Dime your $5
Totally overpowers my die
Because the Dow focuses on the share price
In fact if you had a good day you went up 10%
And I had a bad day I went down 10%
The net result would be the same the market was neutral
But the Dow would value it as a $4.90 loss
Just because I happen to have fewer shares than you
My stock price is
Way more influence
Now Adam I know the fact that the Dow does its mass this way
It drives you nuts
And of course you are not the only one John Chauvin from Stanford field
The same way
In fact he said doing the math this way
Is such a dumb
It could actually be
Dangerous
Marissa's let's say that IBM
Did fantastic
And the other
But most acted poorly
The dower get
Confuse cuz it over weights I be having it might say the market
It's doing okay
Where in actually bostock's
Play poorly I just happens the one that they
Overweight
Is doing well
So it's just kind of
It's honestly it's kind of a
Mistake at the
Way it was calc
Do you want to ask why do they do it
Stupid way
What 1892 there were no cook
Computers
They did the simplest thing possible which is
Take the numbers and add them up
It's so this was
Very very simple thing
We could do rapidly even
Before computers
And they've never change
Siri telling me the Dow is calculated
This way simply because
Back in the day when they started
The math with lahti
I think that's
Crazy like we have they do it like they do because they've always done it that way I'll be at
We all know people like that. That's why do they do this I've always done it that way
That's how the
It makes me think the Dalles sort of like a Luddite right that you don't want to respond to
New changes the new technology we have amazing
Calculators Inc
Computer algorithms now that
Can complicate these really precise mathematical formula
We're sticking with this way
I don't disagree that you just said
I think that's right
Following the Dow
Is an activity
For Market amateur
Nobody who really is
Haymarket professional
Taipei bachata
The Dow that want to say Caitlin there's a reason why the Dow
Asos.
It's actually a simple business
The Dow Jones Industrial Average do they like the fact obviously they
The Dow is mentioned all the time they make money off the fact that they have the
Benchmark index
And they want to keep that going but the Dow Jones Industrial Average has one advantage only one over all the other one
More accurate as we've discussed it
Doesn't have a more clever algorithm
All it's got going for us
Is it really really
That we all know it
Until they never would want to change it to make it more modern because
That would destroy the one market Advantage it has
It's really
Really old
I like the Colonial Williamsburg of Wall Street
Did you say that
And the Dow is aware of the chrises
They know that people say this about them that people criticized
The way they do their math
And on their website they respond to it they've got this
5 questions about the Dow that you always wanted to ask
Number three addresses is very issue
Is a couple paragraphs long for the last two lines basically
Said all it says quote with little to gain except maybe a reduction of criticism
We have no reason to reweight the Dow to market capitalization
And there would be a lot to lose
All the history that is in pricewaiter
I love that they're basically fessing up like the only thing we gain is all you people who know we're full of it would stop saying we're full of
That's all
Why the Dow get so much attention why we're so much more Focus
It's on it then you know the S&P
500 or other indices
They say it's history
Plain and simple
Keeshond Shogun again
The only thing going for the towel is it's a hundred twenty years old has a very long history people to follow it for you
Years until there's interest
Where it is now,
Dare to wear
Wasn't I
T29 or whatever
It's been it's been here for all of our lifetime
In all of our parents lifetime
Maybe even our grandpa
Almost every other major stock index out there
Doesn't do the math
They don't focus on just the price of the stock as much as the Dow does
To try to figure out if I move in a stock price matters or not
They look at the whole size of the company of the market capitalization
The number of shares out there
* the price of those shares
So a lot of people say the one thing the Dow is really supposed to do to tell us what's going on in the stock market
It sucks is that
Chauvin says right now yeah
Things look good and things are doing pretty well in the stock market
But overall the Dow has a lot of flies it only has 30 stock
They don't represent all the major companies in America and they do their math in this crazy way
But you know who gives the doubt
Power
It is not Dow Jones you know they'd provide the index yes but the people who give this index
It's way more power than it deserves Is Us
It is the media
Why was it is not planning
You've never heard us get all excited about the Dow Jones Industrial Average
But I will take NPR and I've talked to senior leadership here and I've made my case so far I haven't once but NPR
Reports the Dow Jones industrial average every hour during trading hours
And we
Lead news with it when it breaks a record
So do the newspapers it's not just cable news freaking out about it it's
Responsible sober
Media Outlet
Play give it all of this
Coverage
This is so puzzling.
Because I don't think you can talk to
Any Market professional or any academic Economist would say yes I think the average American consume
We we should know what the Dow Jones is doing
Every hour of the day and every day
Of the work week
In fact I talked to one guy who was particularly critical
Obsessive way
How covers the media
I asked him how often
Not everyday and I'm I'm one of the people responsible
That's John Crespo
And we were surprised to find out he was such an eloquent critic
People obsessing about the Dow
Because when we first talked to him for the story he was the editor and executive director of the Dow Jones indices
It was his job to track it
But he told us then that he didn't pay attention to it every day
And he said when you look back at Charles doubt the man who founded the Dow Jones Industrial Average in
As far as he could tell
How's the Dow didn't bother to comment on it more than once a month
What happened how did
We develop this 24-hour fit
Fixation on the
Wellcraft boats
It started like virtually all economic chain
With a panic
Panic of 1907
When I talked to press both be told me that the Panic of 1907 felt an awful lot like the Panic of 2007 and 2000
Can 8 there's this sudden severe recession Banks
For collapsing
Nobody can make sense of the economy everybody is desperate for some
Handy metrics
Palace
Clearly in an insta
Are we
Worse off today are we better off are we worse off this our than we were an hour ago
So they looked around and
They found
The Dow Jones Industrial Average
Took on a life of its own
Newspapers started referring to IT service
Easy
Way of
Talking about how the overall economy is
And then it really took off during the Great
Depression because
Obviously in the Great Depression people really wanted to know is this thing going to continue forever is this thing about
The end
General statistics that kind of Statistics we use now
The unemployment rate at Central were still very immature they were not very reliable so
The media have
This handy thing the Dow
It might satisfy that same need how's this
Economy doing
The thing is
What was true in 1907
What was true in 1937
What was true 2007 and what is true today
Is not only the Dow Jones Industrial Average
A lousy way to know how to
The stock market is doing
Even the best measure
S&P 500
The Wilshire 5000 whatever the best measure of the stock market is not necessarily going to help you understand
How the overall a
Economy
Doing
Yeah I mean it doesn't tell us about you know the things we care about about GDP the growth of the overall economy about housing
About jobs
John Sandford says
The stock market
Turn always match up with what's going on in our real economy
The Dow and and
Stock market
The General
Stu
Do better the economy grow faster than the economy
I think it's
Correlated
With the economy
Far from perfect
Reasonable gauge of how corporations are doing but after all we're interested to have workers
You're doing as well
And it doesn't
Gates that
It wouldn't be my number one gauge
App for the Econo
There's been
Plenty of times where the stock market in the Dow have done very well exactly when there's massive layoffs and low
Lots of unemployment
There have been lots of times where the Dow Jones goes up and wealth increases among the people who own stocks which
Which is disproportionately the 1% or the top 10%
You know the bottom 50% of the country by income has virtually no stocks at all
And so very often when you're
Celebrating the Dow Jones going up what you're celebrating is something that
Might be problematic
Layoffs
More income inequality
It might not necessarily be that way either it's just the Dow is just such a lousy measure of everything it doesn't real
Tell you anything
About how the economy is doing for the
Wechat Planet Money we look at
A lot of indicators but how the economy is doing we look up courses
Employment rate
Look at overall G
GDP growth we look
Look at income and Welfare
Inequality
I'm pretty sure that never in a meeting or just
Stand around the hallway we
Have ever discussed the Dow
Other than to talk about
How much we
As always work eager to hear what you think about Today show I would love to see a full-throated defensive
The Dow
Or
Join us in hating on it at Planet Money at NPR. Org
And Caitlin Kenny Davidson thank you for listening