Back in the 1950s Tom Burrell was in high school and he had to take one of those aptitude test
Test to tell you what you should be when you grow up
And take the test
Any score super high in persuasiveness
And artistic ability
A teacher says
Persuasiveness artistic ability is only one profession for you
Advertise
Copperhill is not the kind of guy who shies away from things as he gets to college and he's like
Bring on the advertising world
Well a professor of his system down and tells them
You are smart you are persuasive
The problem is there are no black
People in advertising
Stilt tumbrl is not dissuaded
He sees an opening in the mail room
In the Mailroom
Wait advertising in Chicago when he applies
And the good news
He is the only app
He is a shoe-in
Well except this is 90
Tohara me was a major
Senior Management decision
The chairman the president the Executive Vice President senior vice president
They met and conferred over the issue of even hiring a
A negro
And then after they interviewed me
They met to determine whether they were going to go ahead with this
Quote revolutionary kind of move to hire a
A a negro
The boy to work
In
The Mailroom
Isabelle Rowe
In the Mailroom
That was a major executive decision that brought the chairman
All the way back from his
His home in Delray Florida is to have a meeting to decide that
And after deliberating the decision was made they let him in he got the job
And now Tom Burrell with something few people at Sea before
A black man in advertising hello and welcome to Planet Money Robert Smith
The story of Tom Burrell and how he changed the way people write ads and change the way we think about average
Advertising thinks about us
By the way this episode was originally recorded back in 2015 but we've added a bonus conversation at the
So stick around
Support for NPR comes from LinkedIn learning how to support the launch of life
NPR's guy to help you make better life decision
LinkedIn learning short video tutorials cover business Tech
And creative skills employers look for at every level
All taught by experts and new courses are added every week
+ LinkedIn learning is personalized
Recommending courses based on your interests and Life kid listeners get a month of learning free
Start your free trial at LinkedIn learning.com NPR
It is 19
Tom Burrell has started his new job in the Mailroom and he looks around at Wade advertising Chicago
And he realizes this place
Is about
As boring as you can get
It had these
Really
Safe kind of big brands
Never took any chance
Robin Hood flour
Alka-Seltzer
The Grand ole Opry
Advertising. The time was that
To sell products
It had to be
Really sort of generic nothing too spicy to offend anybody
One-size-fits-all
Target at everyone who
Who owns Nutella
With Alka-Seltzer
Relief is just a swallow
It probably goes without saying that you could watch Alka-Seltzer ads
All day long in the 1960s
And never see a non-white face
Burrell wheelie light
Happy gif
An Advertiser
People are good to him they treated him well
And then where
None of those awkward moments that you might expect
From being the only black guy in the Asia
Except for one
You know it was Progressive Party
It's always the Christmas party Robert
This is when the CFO
The company walks up to him
Says Tom
Beetle
We're happy you're here
And
We're wondering if
Next year
You would
Be willing are interested
And singing some down-home songs
So what were you thinking
I think I think I did the same thing
I think I laughed
Who's home
And he never got it
For the record you never sang at the office Christmas party
And he didn't really stay in the Mailroom
He started writing copy coming up with
Folksy language
To self flower
He even made a big pitch
For the agency
These big account
He had a veggie idea that involve the sick monkey and Alka-Seltzer it was
Was weird it was
Crazy
But it never got made
After just a few years Tom barrels ambition
Was too big
For Wade advertising he found another agency willing to let him do edger stuff
Needham Harper
And they they didn't have to fly the CEO in from Florida
Approve his hire
Tom was the first
Black
Copy supervisor we'd ever had in the agency and
He's very tall
Good-looking has a good voice and he was very gifted
Creative guy so we were we were drawn to him
Keith Reinhardt was copyrighted there in the 60s
And I'm sure
You know his work
You'll feel better
Better knowing
Anytime anywhere
I'd like a good neighbor
State farm is there and we got lots of
Letters from English teachers who
Objected to our use of
Like a good neighbor
Instead of as a good neighbor but
Stayed with us and they're still using it today
This agency would go on to be one of those big
Historic
Innovators
Advertising
It keeps right on to the Tom Burrell was one of the best copywriter
They had
And in Wynwood advertising agencies work
These two are both
Colleagues but they were also
Competitor
The two men were often pitted against each other
To see who could come up with the best eye
One incident I remember when we were both given the assignment to
Convince
People to try Continental Airlines because they had wider seats new wider seat
And we tried to crack it and Tom and his group just nailed it I think it was Tom himself
Who came up with this idea to
Reprint
The
Seat cushions
Of these new wider seats on Continental Airlines and a double
Page newspaper spread
And the headline simply invited readers to
To sit down on the newspaper spread
NC
How
How much wider it was how much more comfortable
I mean he really killed it
Remember Robert we're talking about the
In Chicago
Civil Rights Movement is going on
And in Chicago there's sort of a
Harlem Renaissance
You got Ebony magazine
Important Beauty Outlet
For African Americans definitely at the time
And their ad reps are going around saying
This is a black magazine
The ads have to have black people in them
And that woke up a lot of
People in the advertising world and the consumer Market World in Chicago
Is advertising agency said oh yeah okay
We need a black people in these
So what they would do is they would write a script
4 TV ads
Build a sad
And personally would hire white actors
Like in this ad for Crest there these two white kids brushing their teeth at a sink
I never be Greg Surplus the toothpaste test Brookside use the same two faces mine for without
Starset my side hewescraft
And had 42% fewer cavities
Celebrities with the white
And then the end of the day swap out the cute white
Kids for equally cute black
And having pretty much do the same at
I never could talk Jeff
Been in a toothpaste test we're on opposite sides
Pyside use crest
Yes I do the same to Facebook without florestan
That's what I be Jeff
Cuz my side at 21% fewer cavities with Chris
Bro says it was pretty comical how little they thought
About black
Consumers Energy
You tell me this one famous story of a State Farm ad
That they wanted to change
Ebony magazine
Now the original ad
Had a white couple laying in bed
There was a photograph
On the side
Of the bed
And this is a family photograph
And so then they did a blank version
Of that same ad
But they forgot to change the photograph
So you got this blanket
He gets his wife family
What's the forecast for white family
Beside
Add so that was one
Example
Another example is that Schaefer's
Beer
A lot of Brands like Schaefer's like to rely on the stalgia you know
Thinking about the good old days
Well reply people the good old days weren't that good especially
When
It was before the Emancipation Proclamation
And at the time
The line was
Sex
That was a
Very Good Year
4 beer
It was a very bad year for black people
And this this ad is showing up in Ebony magazine
There's something really strategically wrong with this
Talking about how good a year 1856 was
4 beer
And
It just
Screamed
Insensitivity
Screamed at
It was a
Horrible
Year
For us
Robert you can imagine
Just how weird this was
You got a black guy who's working
All white advert
Intemporel is going home
To the south side of Chicago
Which is
Erupting
In the Civil Rights Movement
And they're the slogans
Black Panthers
And there's this idea of black power
You know what she wrestles with this idea
And he decides
He's going to come up
With his own slogan
That's especially me
For the advertising world
Black people are not
Dark skin white people
You know when we talk to people about Tom Burrell
They quote this almost
Verbatim
Back to us
He said it so often
Black people
Are not dark-skinned White
People in fact
Well decide to finally
Start his own advertising
Confirm really based on this Prince
A black
Advertising agency
The understood and could sell to the black consumer
This seems immensely Avi
What are the time it felt like
You know a real slap in the face to these
Waiting to see if you worked
I had some
Reservations about 2
Some of the things he was saying
You may remember X collie
Keith Reinhard
Whether or not we
Ask occasion the creative people would be able to appeal to the black audience I felt it too
We could and that we had in some cases but it was pretty hard to argue
With time when he said
You know blacks are not white people with dark
Skin I mean we have a culture of our own and we need to express that
So Tom Burrell eventually got a partner
Mukbang
And they formed the firm
Darrell McFadden
One of the first all-black a date
In 1971 who would eventually become Burrell Communications
And the big Brands came running
Desperate
Translate Jack Daniels Ford and one of his
Big first clients was Philip Morris and the Marlboro Man
This was a big
Hauppauge
Selling the Marlboro Man
The African American
The Marlboro Man was this
Rugged cowboy
Who was always filmed on horseback
In like a Utah like landscape
Smoking cig
The longhorn
Come to Marlboro Country
Marlboro 100
I don't even know where to start I mean
First of all restarting my Longhorns you you've lost me
You lost me on Longhorns
I'm done and then when you start talking about a hundred years ago
You lost me on that too because that's the last thing I want to do
Is go back
A hundred years
Ago
With a bunch of
Rural cowboy
White guys
That doesn't sound
How to safe
Philip Morris wanted
Create a black Marlboro
And of course
Became the Tom Burrell
What did you do to make it
Make it a PO to Someone Like You
Well I took it out of the
Marlboro Country and I put it into the city
That's one thing
And the Marlboro Man became a very cool City
City dude very well very stylish well
Dressed
Cool had a bit cool Factor going
Gone with the cowboy hat the big belt buckle
The New Black Marlboro Man
Heather sweat
And he sits there and stares out not at the range
But it is Swanky Library
Urbane Urban
Is definitely
Not a Cowboys fan
We changed the line
Which is almost
Last may we change the lion from
Come to where the flavor is
And the light was simply
Where
The flavor is
So
We're basically saying that
The city
Where black people are
Is where the
The flavor is
Burrell did was take this General marketing
Had
And
He tailored it
For a black audience
But if you really did want to be finishing someone else's work
Monkey doing something bigger he had a bigger vision
To craft
Then add in a campaign
From the ground up
And he got
The chats
He got the biggest
Chance that an ad agency can Dad have you seen Mad Men you know what this means
McDonald's call
McDonald's Caldwell actually this guy
Call
Paul shrage
You're in charge of marketing at McDonald's for quite a while right
McDonald's
And the 1970s McDonald's
One goal and one goal only
Grow
Aggressively
Crowded already conquered the suburbs
He wanted to move big into the city
It what it became apparent that the black consumer
Was growing in numbers and import
End up
Celtic we need is somebody that was specialized
In that area
But I think this is one of those moments where at
The phrase call Tom Burrell
Came out of the conference
Yeah it wasn't like they were you know sheets and Chiefs a black advertising agent
Is that the time
And when Tom Burrell finally sat down with McDonald's can't explain to them
Not hey guys you need to sell the black people
That part they got
But it was the way
The African Americans interact
Whittier restaurants
Is different
The way
In the commercial that the time they would show white family
Piling into the car
The idea was that
McDonald's to this was a tree
A destination
In the black community
McDonald's
Meant something complete
McDonald's was not used as a place where the family would go
McDonald's
Was used
As a place where working people would go
And take a break
Whatever they had a chance
It was a place where children would go very often
By themselves
The average check
For a
Family going to McDonald's on these special occasions
Was larger
The frequency was less
The average check in the black community was hot
Smaller Mickey is running in and out getting french fries
It's this big realization
Which was the McDonald's
Wasn't just
A place to
McDonald's was also place to work with a major employer in the city
And so we launched a series of ads
Noting industry ads
Pelvic is about the kid named Calvin
Hey isn't that Calvin I haven't seen him for a while I want the wave hit
You got a job at 8
Hip hop beat
Will it shows a young black teenager he strolling through the
Hood
Which looks strangely like
Brooklyn set on the back lot at
Responsibility
He's working welcome to McDonalds help you
Funny now it's
Beds are a little bit
Eazy-E in straight ahead
But the thing is
They were really successful when they ran for a decade
Can you follow Calvin
As he work this way up
To becoming a manager
I'm pretty sure that in the alternative universe
Calvin is living in
The owns McDonald
Well you probably owns like a whole chain
Is somebody watched a lot of TV in the 80s
It couldn't happen to a nicer guy
By the time this ad aired
Tom Burrell
Was certifiably
Famous he was this huge name
In advertising you what happens when you're a huge payment advertising
You also get a lot of credits
And there were people at the time we said look yeah you made a 6
Excessive
But you made a success since industry by selling brands that weren't exactly
High end luxury brand
Health food
And I have that
In your early success some of the accounts to
She got were the Marlboro Man we just talked about
Jack Daniel
The obvious question would be in these are not the best thing
Forever ever in America
That's right and in this is how you're making your living
How do you feel about
Oii struggled
With that and I struggle with
Rome ended up dropping the cigarette clients pretty early on in
In his career
What's important to note is that
At the time throw realize the kind of platform that he
Had with McDonald's
He had a theory that he wanted to work on it was called
Positive Realty
Richmond
Putting regular black people in real life
Equations
On television
It it had that kind of positive effect even though
Arguably
We were selling things
To them
That as we see now we're not
Good for
Them
And
It out but there were no things
That I recall selling that I
Declined to use
And what people saw that he was successful with doing that with McDonald
A lot of the other big American blue chip brands
Running to American Airlines Toyota Procter & Gamble General Mills cereal
Any slogan that black
People aren't dark skin white people became
But not just related to African American
That the Bro principal was one size doesn't fit all
In each group needs to be
Taking into account
What Burrell did
Open the door
For the kind of
Ethnic micro-targeting that we see
Today
Robert Clara is contributing editor at Apple
And the way that he did that was by making mainstream Brands not just aware
Of the black community as a very viable community of consumers but he also firm
Furnish them
With a means to reach them that was new and effective
And then once that in and of itself became
A mainstream thing
The Natural Evolution of that Trend was then for advertisers
Just say oh well then there must be other groups that we can reach out to
And the idea of specialized advertising targeted demographic advertising
Grows out of that but you wouldn't have had that
If you didn't have the initial awareness of the broader demographic group that Pharrell helped
To create
Cumberland is basically retired now though he does some
Consulting
Turtle trying to help major brand understand how to use or not use
Use Hip Hop
After all this time
You still have to
Teach the same lesson
Since he was teaching
50 years ago
Yeah that marketing if you're not targeting
And so
This whole business about one-size-fits-all I mean to steal our kind of a
Up movement out of part of Wishful Thinking clients
To say hey
Can't we just
Talk to one group of people in so much easier
But the whole thing is it is it is that
We now have the app
The ability
To really get in and talk to people
More individual
Basin
Now marketers realised it would be ridiculous
To just try to sell
The black guy or the white
It's about selling.
Young black
Gay guy who lives in West Hollywood plays golf listen to Frank Sinatra and likes public radio
Wait wait wait wait
You play golf
Idea Robert is that more and more
Who is this ad really for
Now you're supposed to think
This ad is especially
For me
Mary Clinton ladies and gentlemen
Back in 2015
And after this break we've got a little bonus conversation updating the show
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online
I'm presence and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layouts along with features including e-commerce functionality
And mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial and when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Okay we're back before we go though we wanted to share a little conversation with you
Futanari
Recently talked
With one of our colleagues Gene Demby
He's one of the hosts of the code switch podcast
And they talked about this episode in particular
And Woodstock
One of the things I thought was really fascinating
What's this phenomenon that you decided you wanted to call
The Oprah effect
What is the Oprah effect
Well it's something that Tom Burrell said to me that we couldn't get into the podcast which is that the
Ads that he made that were
For Africa
Can Americans
Did better with the white audience
Then the General Market
Advertising
So what you're saying is that
White people
Doug
Ads meant for black people
More than they like ads
With white people meant for white people
Fiat the ads ever
Specifically aimed at African Americans did better with the white
And what that sort of shows and we can see it and affecting our lives right
And that's why I called the Oprah
You know my mom will watch Oprah assuming your mom watches Oprah
Any number of
Minority women will watch another minority woman
The Genius of Oprah is that she gets the women of color
The white one and two and then we see this all over
It's a little weird to think of
What time parole was doing when he came out these ideas
A subversive right I mean
Oh mama what you just trying to get more people into McDonald's so they buy more french fries right but
On another level
It's hard not to think of what tamburro was doing
As when he's talking about positive realism as political right he's trying to
Make space for black people
In mainstream American
Let me know
Nobody came up with these ID
In the sixties
In the 70s
He's a part of the
Cultural
Conversation
Tomberlin and Jesse Jackson
They talk
I mean Tom Burrell
Is with
A group of
Men
Mainly men
Time
Who are transforming the way African American
I seen an advertising and he's thinking politically
He's looking through you know Martin Luther King coming to Chicago and living
This is really important to him
Showing African Americans in a positive light
Hillary Clinton and Jean Denver one of the host of NPR's code switch podcast
Which can I say you should check out by Gene and the coach which team is original reporting on
Culture and everything in between you can find code switch on NPR one or where we begin podcast
Email Planet Money at npr.org today's episode was originally produced by Prince
Arlo Nick Fountain dinner update the gangster by Robert Smith thanks for listening