Support for NPR in the following message
Did come from Pushkin and dust
Resetting the podcast broken record
Rick Rubin Malcolm Gladwell and Bruce Hedley
Sit down with the musicians you love
To talk about their lives work and the music
Listen to season 2 wherever you get your podcasts
Back in the 1980s
Louis winthorpe the Third
Was a big deal in the world of futuristic
You work at a fancy Farm in Philadelphia
And this guy knew
Commodities
Pork belly I have a hunch something very exciting is going
Having the pork belly Market this morning Louis was the best
He was about to get married in the future looked bright
We are going to make a great
We're going to have a great
Life
Until his boss is Randolph and Mortimer Duke
Took all of that away from me
And so begins
The great parable
About what happens when the rich become poor
The poor become rich at a con man inherits the Earth
The movie is Trading Places
Hello and welcome to Planet Money on Robert Smith and I'm Roman Mars
Feeling good Robert Rubin Mars is the host of the podcast 99% invisible
It's about all things design and architecture
And he don't play buddy today because
Actual question for us about this movie
What I love is movie I saw it when I was way way too young I was probably 9 or 10
And I just wanted to know
Is this
The most sophisticated depiction of the inner workings of a financial Market in the history of Cinema
That is the perfect question for arthroben because we have the ability and we shall
Bringing an entire panel
Experts in the commodity Futures Trading world
The fact
Check this movie
Today
On Planet Money
What the Movie Trading Places can teach you about financial Market
And
I know this is a particular interest you Ramen
We are finally going to explain one of the great enduring Mysteries
What the hell
Actually happened
At the end of this crazy
I definitely need that one
Just a note this show originally ran back in 2013
It is as relevant today as it ever was
Also in this episode which warned you
Eddie Murphy says a bad word
Support also comes from Fidelity invest
As a Fidelity wealth
You get a dedicated advisor
Hair to help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of tax
And make clear recommendations for your full Financial pek
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
So it's been a while since you've seen trading place
Everything is going really well for Louis winthorpe until his bosses
They have an argument about nature versus nurture
And the evil Randolph Duke that's his
Maybe even slightly more evil brother Mortimer Duke
That he can take away Lewis's job
And his fiance
Home
Friends and they can turn them into a
While at the same time
The Duke Brothers
Pick a comment from the street named Billy Ray Valentine
Display by Eddie Murphy
Any given Louis's
Empire life
His job
He's home his Butler
And they try to turn him
Into a Hotshot Commodities broker
It's kind of a modern-day Twist on Prince and the Pauper
Guinea pigs they find each other
And Lewis and Billy Ray conspire to get back at
The Dukes
And they make a brilliant plan to make themselves
Really rich
And put the Duke
Brothers in The Pour House at the same time
It is a crazy complicated plan involves Futures Trading on Commodities and cornering the market
And Frozen concentrated
Orange juice
Right there that's my first question
Frozen concentrated orange juice
Central to the move and when I first thought
I totally thought that was made up as a
Justin Bieber
Funny in the real world
My thinking was
You just trade oranges
Who would spend their life
Trading little cans of Frozen concentrated Orange
I found somebody
This guy
My name is time for honest and I'm a commodity Trader
I'm just coming back from Mom
The floor of the New York Mercantile Exchange
Where I can have spent the last 4 hours
Buying and selling orange juice options
And futures
It's real
It's totally real estate doesn't all day long
Tumblr oldest you can be a first expert on all things Frozen
Healthy orange
Just a moment
We're going to use both of them to fact-check
This premise
That you had Ramen
The Trading Places
Basically could be a university-level course
In finance
The commodities
And as someone who
Explains economics
For a living I mean this is my job I take
My hat off
To the writers of this movie
Just listen to this scene
The Duke Brothers in the scene
Lead Eddie Murphy Delirious Valentine
Wood table and settlement table
It's a beautiful day
This is not
Emil.
We are here to try
Explain to you what it is we do here
We are Commodities brokers
What are commodities
Commodities are agricultural
Products
Like
Coffee
For breakfast
Sweet which is used to make bread
Pork belly
Which is used to make
Bacon
Which you might find in a bacon and lettuce and tomato sandwich
Exoduspoint Eddie Murphy
Just deadpans right into the camera I suspect it sometimes Planet Money list
Clear so far
Reviewing the movie they really really did a good job I mean someone
Inet
Knew what they were doing
This is our second expert
Bob Lassen Trello
He's a Commodities Trader in Chicago
He used to trade cattle futures
Like Roman you might find any roast beef
Cheddar and tomato sandwich
Of course if you watch that scene you might think of these guys trade-in physical things the physical things that you see on the table.
Bacon the weed
The cans of orange juice
Baton Brian says that in that words use Market that's not quite right
Yes Duffy. Store just a little can't you have to probably have large refrigerator type units for them
What do you mean probably you buy and sell the stuff you have no idea what it looks like
No and as a matter of fact if you trade agricultural Commodities most
Commodity Traders go their whole careers without ever seeing the physical product am I used
Trade pork bellies and live Hogs and
I would know a pork belly fat dropped on the table here
Yeah the recent Tom peronace wouldn't recognize the pork belly on the table
It's because people like him who do this in real life or Trading
Contract
I'm pork belly
Or technically
The future promise to deliver a certain amount of pork bellies at a certain
I'm at a certain price
But it really is a it's a wager it's a bet on whether you think something is going to go up or down in price and
Mortimer and Randolph Duke in the movie
They make money
Whether it goes up or down
That's a good part William is that
Matter whether our clients
Make money
I lose money
Duke and Duke
Commission
Well
Do you think Valentine
Sounds to me like you guys are
I told you he'd understand
I know this whole contract thing may seem theoretical
But the bats are based on an actual contract when an actual real thing
The prettiest just hold the contract for just a few minutes or a few days
Enough time to make a little money
But before the contract
Expire
Any actual good have to be delivered
That Trader needs to unload the car
Need to sell to someone who actually
Wants
Thing underneath the car
Contract to actually wants
The oranges
Who wants to bake
Wants
The lighthouse
Remember that's what Bob Last Cinderella traded in
Live cattle futures
18:1
How he just wanted to make a bet on the future prices of
But once popped
Did you ever receive an actual cow
Oh boy did I
Yeah not a cow 40 of them
And more than 40 you made a mistake yes
You made a mistake and somebody called you on the phone and just said we have
I don't hear from you wear them
Oh yeah
Are there in the pain directly off the truck and in the pain is what it is and so
When the guys in the East st. Louis Stockyards found out that a Futures Trader took delivery on
Some cattle they generally aren't super helpful about
They don't really give you a hand letting you
Song they think they kind of stick you with some extra fees and
You know babe babe
They don't like us guys they picked it in Athens
It's Times Like These Guys
Sort of meddling in their world
Now back to the Moon
Billy Ray Valentine
Who is now called William Bell
On time by the Dukes is learning this Commodities worth
Well that turns out he has some Talent
Because it's not just about knowing the facts and the figures
The contracts
Commodities
A lot of it is about knowing psychology
Tell me just quiet
Price of pork bellies
It's going down William
Christmas time
Could we please buy now Randall
If you want to lose money go ahead
What are you trying to say what him
Okay
Potbelly prices
I'm dropping all morning
Is everybody sending me off in the waveform hit rock bottom
The people on the park by the contractor going batshit
Hey
Christmas is around the corner
Kung Fu grip
Okay and my wife ain't going
My wife want to make love to
Because I got no money right
This is Nanny Pat
Screaming
I can feel it
Department
Oh my God
I wait till you get to about 60 for the night by
If it at all the second about it
Of course
Billy Ray Valentine makes them a ton of money
Table Cinderella has a small quibble with this
He says people don't really declare up
Particular price for a commodity no one ever says
It's going to 64 I don't really know exact
But people make bets on whether things just go up and down is that right two people just have hunches
Absolutely I mean what would happen
You know
Their guys would just
You'd be standing around and you'd have to start to have a feeling that the market was going to go up or down and then you would trade accordingly
It's sort of like
Your brain
Processing all this information
Ends up
Manifesting itself as
What's called the field
And then you buy resale accordingly
So far according to RX
The Movie Trading Places
Is nailing it they have Commodities thing down pat
But then it gets a little Hollywood Lewis Winthrop are down and out Rich Boy
He teams up with his former Butler
And a prostitute
With a heart of gold
We did not
Check that one you don't even need to
It's a given
Exactly
Billy Ray the con man turned trading savant
Figures out
I've been played
A joint up with Winthrop and
Hatch this plant
Make millions of dollars
Bankrupt
And it's the end of the movie where I have my biggest question
I was a kid I saw it and
I know that
Something important is happening on the trading floor at the end
The Underdogs win
I get rich
The Dukes go bankrupt
But I didn't really understand it and I when I watch it again
The funny thing is
Still don't really understand it as an adult and I don't think I would have got it
But I have now study the movie over again we talk to The Experts
And we are going to break
This thing.
Because Roman if you were paying attention
This movie has already talked
Do everything you need to know about commodities
And how to Corner the market
Now
Remember the orange
That was in the breakfast
Yes
Frozen concentrated or
Okay so in the movie The Duke Brothers
Have bribed the guy to get an advance copy of the
Neuropathy
Copy of the USDA orange crop report
Which of the totally real things cop reports come out every month to tell you how much
Commodity is out there
Now this if they know it in advance
How many oranges are out there
They will then know whether the price
It's going to go up or down
Remember understand
And the crop report
Is going to say that the supply of oranges
Is fine
Plenty of good
Cheap orange juice
Just go around at the normal day in the market
Except our heroes are going to trick
The Duke Brothers
They're going to pull the old switcheroo
So they slip the brothers
Baked crappie
A report that says
Oh my god there was this terrible Frost in Florida lots of dead oranges
Fake report would make
Any Savvy Trainor no
Price of orange juice is going to go through the
Saudi Brothers think
Supplies low
Want to go out
And they're willing to bet everything on it
They are so long
Iraq
Our Heroes Billy Ray Valentine and Louis winthorpe
Former Trader got screwed by the Duke
They know the truth
They know that the orange Supply is fine
And they know
What did the prices going to go down
Silver Spring back roj expert Tom peronace and we're going to watch this final scene together and get a play-by-play
Our Heroes with their stolen Insider information our heroes are
Driving out onto the trading floor
Of the New York Mercantile
There's my old place of employment
That's the World Trade Center
I'd office in that building right there that's that's for the exchange was
Inside you see all the traitors in there
A grievous
Gathering on this large floor staring up at
Set the clock
And it's pandemonium
Tom says this is exactly what was like before computers
Maybe not quite so many people excited about frozen orange juice but still
Does make me nostalgic for floor-based trading
Now once again Roman got to keep all these things in your head if this give except
The Duke Brothers think there's going to be a shortage of Orange
Because according to their fake crop report
Harvest will be back
The prices should go up
They tell their guy their Floor Trader
I want you to buy as much OJ as you can in the instant pot
Don't worry if the price starts going up
Play starts at $1.02 a pound
Best Buy
Play stick to go up and up their bidding up the price of orange juice
And the rest of the traitors
Start to notice
They know something I can feel it Let's Get It On
Okay I got to tell you here Roman
But the actor who says
They know something I can feel it
That is Jack Davidson
Father of Planet money's very old Adam Davis
And as I will say really is
It really is the most critical line in the entire movement delivered by his father
That's amazing
What is universally important for the plot because
Everyone starts to buy oranges the price was higher and higher at Dollar 10
A dollar $28 30
Everyone now thinks there is an orange
Shortage
The only problem
Is
We know at the audience that's based on a lot
So Billy Ray Valentine Louis winthorpe stand quietly
In The Madness of the trading floor round
They know the price is too high they know it's getting higher
And I know it's about to collapse
And so they want to do a little trick
A product called Short Selling
They want to sell orange juice while the prices
Hi
So
When the price hits 142
Dan Aykroyd looks
And he screams and I think
Is a good candidate for the second most important line of the movie with all respect to Jack Davidson
And I totally
Mystic Ivory watch that movie again and again I have no idea
What he says they're what
Dan Aykroyd says there
Do we have time explained
Sell 30 April 142
What you doing you selling 30 Futures contracts at a price of 142 per pound
And there's kind of a Feeding Frenzy driving the market higher but these guys
Have what they believe is the real information and they're selling it at rally
So selling it to the rally means you think the price is going to go down
Yes
I'm starting to get this
Billy Ray Lewis they're selling High they're selling orange juice
To everyone who thinks that is going to go even higher than that
Yeah it's a really tricky
Find point
Here but I'm just going to say this
You don't have to
Own any orange juice
In order to sell it
Because
They're selling a promise they're selling this thing I will
Promise to deliver you orange juice in April that was a part of that
And you will pay me this large amount of money
Sometime in the
Our Heroes have until then
Find some cheap orange juice
Center fielder contract
If you heard of the old saying like Buy Low and sell High
Yes that one I know
It's
Turns out though and this is the key to short side but keep the entire movie
Is you can do it
The other way
You can sell High first
And then turn around quickly and Bi-Lo make
Ton of money
Aunt our heroes are about
Get to buy extremely low because the crop report
The real crop report
Is about to come out
It's kind of crazy cuz everyone on the tree Ford to stop
And what's the TV
Ladies and gentlemen
The orange crop estimate
For the next year
And I mean this is obviously a Hollywood moment prater's don't really just stare the TV and there's not a long awkward pause while the Secretary of
Agriculture
This is dramatic tension Robert
After calculating the estimates from
Various artists producing states
We have concluded the following
The cold winter has apparently not affected the orange Harvest
That sound you hear is a bunch of people who just realize that they bet the wrong way but there's no shortage
The Dukes
And everyone who bought with them including Adams dad
Now own a lot of various
Expensive Orange
Way too expensive
Another real proper Port is out
The price is dropping its 102
96 it's plunging to
7264 everyone who bought high now wants to sell
And cut their losses
And it's driving the price down even further
Now 46
And remember our
Gyros
I knew this was going to happen
They sold a ton of orange juice at a crazy high price
And now the entire
Trading floor including the Duke Brothers
Guitar Floyd's begging
To sell them orange juice
For Crazy Cheap
If yours were a hero skip
At the kiosk
Other people have promised to buy orange juice from them
At a price as high as 142
And a minute later people are promising to sell orange juice to them
As cheap as
$0.29 a pound
Billy Ray and Lewis
Get the pocket
It is a
Epic move probably a significantly bigger one day move in the orange
Cheese market has ever had in
Entire history
A purely fictional move but you know
And enough to enable these guys to retire handsome
We had our Commodities guys watchthisfree closely
But it's hard to estimate
Just how much money Billy Ray and Louis made on the scam
We see the price of orange juice futures
But not how many contra
That's all we know at the end of the movie is that the Duke Brothers
They are Bank
Yeah they bought all of that orange juice when he was a crazy high prices they bought High
And if and when they sell it it's going to be
A terribly low prices they did the
The opposite
Of what you need to do to make money in the market
They lost nearly 400 million dollar
Bars in the way trading works
I hear is probably pocketed most
And as far as villains
The Dukes they get their comeuppance
At the end of trading
Turns out they borrowed a lot of that money they do
Just lost
Margin Call gentlemen
Can expect The Exchange accounts to be settled at the end of the day
Trading
Without
You know perfectly well we don't have 394 million dollars in cash
Put the Juke brother seats on Exchange up for sale at once seized all assets of Duke and Dubuque
Randolph and
And this
Traumatic
Crazy clearly Hollywood ending bad guys lose everything they get
Booted out of the rich
Positions in the market
This really happened sometimes according to Tom
He said people would borrow money
All
On the market move
And when I went the opposite direction
Better pay up
Most clearinghouses had people who are referred to as leg break
They weren't like a real
Mobster you know leg Breakers but the they were the ones who say alright you know the time to Pony up alright well you know we want your house
House we want your IRA
I would happen right there on the floor
That's a little over dramatized but if it happened that day or the next day and other wouldn't be much of a time lag
He said there's one more unrealistic
At least in today's world
Computer Trading
Took over the Commodities Market
That climactic scene
If they remade the movie today it would sound a lot like
Like this
Tall people staring at screens
Today you know it is kind of
Obvious trauma is gone from
It would be a very quiet
Yes climactic Kelly and brothers will be in their own private hell you know looking at a computer screen
Head buried in their hands
Tom perona says and this makes me very happy that people still bring up the movie when he says he trades an orange juice futures
And even among his fellow traitors as a sort of
Reverence
It's for the movie
The lines from the script I become part of the lingo of Commodities Trader
Definitely some of these these lines to become stock phrases like over the years especially the ocean market Upper people say like sell Mortimer sell
Amor De Verano
Duke and Duke is buying as I've heard that
20 * 2 count
Yeah. It's definitely become part of the boj lure
There wasn't much OJ Lord had scooped the first place but the
The stuff from Trading Places makes up a significant chunk of it
After the break how Trading Places made its Mark not just in Commodities lower
But in Commodities law
Support for this NPR Podcast in the following message come from the United States Postal Service
Everyday
Innovative companies are Reinventing the way business app
But none of that is possible without the right people
People who get packages to over a hundred and fifty million delivery play
Affordably and on time with the latest technology and expertise
Who can help you deliver the future of Commerce
The United States Postal Service see why they deliver more e-commerce packages to homes than anyone in the
Country at USPS.com future
You know what I always assume
Deepest hole scam with illegal
Are you hoes basically stole inside information
They stole the crop
Report
They took all this money not just from the Duke
But
From the market
Edit the end
They're sitting on a Caribbean Beach
And I thought oh
They're on the Run
From the law
But it turns out
At the time
Insider trading was not strictly illegal in the commodities
Trying to make
Sense because there's so many people involved if you are a farmer training corn
You have the ultimate inside information about corn
Everyone in the agriculture
Business as a little something that someone else doesn't
But it's the part where they steal a crop report
That seems way way over the line the actual fact
Of the suitcase which happens
In iMovie
You shouldn't steal which is illegal in every respect but the actual way in which they made money with stolen in
Information
That was legal and I learn this
Because when Congress was coming up with the banking
Warm light. Frank
In 2010
They were debating what should be in the billing
Emmett came up
Special
Provision
It seems that the chair of the
Commodities
Future trading committee
Gary Gensler
He said we need this thing
It is called
The Eddie Murphy
A rule
It will make what happened to Trading Places
And it made it in
Dodd-Frank section 7 for 6
Federal employee can't
Leaked information about the price of a commodity so that someone can make money off of it
And a person who gets that leaked information
They can't use that to make money off of the mark
For this rule went into effect
What Eddie Murphy Billy Ray Valentine and Dan Aykroyd
North Winthrop the 3rd
But they did misappropriate information and then use it
Corner the orange juice Market
Was not
Actually illegal got away with it got away with it
Oh that makes me so happy
Is there an enduring economic mystery and yes it can be from the movies that you
You want us to solve we would love to hear from you can email us at Planet Money at npr.org Eeyore find us
At Planet Money on Facebook or Twitter this rerun was produced by our intern eduard Saakashvili and I'm telling you
Right this second
You should go and subscribe to Roman Mars excellent podcast
99% invisible you like Planet Money
I love this guy thanks so much I hope you understand the movie
I do I got it I got it you guys did a good job
Got through you guys know what you're doing
Robert Smith
I'm really Mars
Thanks for listening
Support for this podcast in the following message come from fundrise the future of real estate investing
Access private Market real estate projects from high rises in DC to multi-family apartments in LA