Hey
Take a package
Adidas sneakers
Stars
Deathberries
Hey there
Used
If they're like
They're not sweating
Sweat
Staind
Okay that's probably sweat
Hello and welcome to Planet Money
I'm Kenny Malone that was my wife Hannah and those sweaty eBay sneakers that I'm wearing on my feet right now.
As I speak
They are one of the most extraordinary experiments
Basketball sneaker history
Today on the show we know that you can put a famous basketball players name on a pair of shoes and charge more money
But what happens when you put an NBA All-Stars name on a pair of shoes and charge less
Much much less but like
Okay don't wear any worse.
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Fidelity invest
As a Fidelity wealth management client
You get a dedicated advisor to help grow and protect your wealth find ways to minimize the impact of Pacs
And make it clear recommendations for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
The Man Behind the sneakers that I'm wearing
Is an NBA All-Star Game Stephon Marbury
And he grew up during the basketball sneaker Revel
You go your mom and you would you say I'm playing basketball I need
The sneakers I said I want
Important distinction here of course especially with my mother
Gwen Stefani was born in 1977 basketball shoes were essentially just a piece of sports equipment
Like knee pads for your
The most iconic brand for decades
It was a shoe called
Chuck Taylor All Star
Basic affordable Shoes Canvas rubber nothing fancy
But when Stephon with 8 years old
The sneaker game
Change
In 1985 Nike release this commercial is Michael Jordan
Soaring in slow motion through the air
Air Jordan with the first Air Jordan sneaker and it was beautiful and look like a sports car white and black leather with
Streaks of red
Stores couldn't keep these things in stock
People wearing them has shoes not just as basketball shoes
And they cost a lot
The Air Jordan 1 retail for $65
150 bucks
In today's money
And then the next year 1986 Air Jordan The Jordan 2 came out all of the Imagine
Those hot even more $100
The Jordan fours cost 210 the Jordan 5s cost
$125
Stefan was 13 years old when those Jordan 5
About his living in Coney Island Brooklyn
One of seven kids
His family didn't have a lot
And so
When Stefan asked his mom for those shoes
She was not happy
I mean my mother I asked my mother
Look for a pair of shoes at that price
The reply was
Boy those are groceries for the month
Why am I going to go spend that type of money
For a pair of shoes
And you would say what
Cuz everybody else got them
Oh yeah you're not going to be the one that's going to have a pet
But it wasn't because she didn't want to buy them if
Because she couldn't
Define says this planted a seed
He always wondered
When there be another option here
Does a famous players basketball shoe always have to be so expensive
No lot of kids my
Think this but
Stephan got to do something about it
Because
He grew up he got very good at basketball
In 1996 he was drafted into the end
With the first pick the Milwaukee Bucks
Select
Stephon Marbury the camera cuts to the whole Margaery family they are freaking out
Stephon Marbury is standing by now with brexit
Is this moment right here
That makes me love step on Mars
Because on the first question was totally just sounds like an ice breaker
She disturbed
20 login
Can talk about your family what is it been like the camera cuts that stayed and now Stefan's mother is
Dancing is just feels so good I can put a smile on my mother face
Define join the NBA
Became an NBA All-Star twice
And year after year famous player after famous player
Signed endorsement deals to sell shoes at ridiculously high
Safari doesn't remember the exact moment
But an idea started
You can think of it this way
Sneaker is made up of foam and rubber and leather
By attaching a famous basketball players name
Can you get to charge more
And kids go crazy for
Could you use an endorsement to do the
Exact opposite
Topeka same shoe of foam and rubber and leather
And attach a famous basketball players name
But charged
Less
And still have it be cool still get the kind of buzz the Air Jordan
Stephan wanted to know
Could I
Make affordable sneakers
Cool
I can see my mom
I can see my mom being able to do something for all of her kids
Suzette is that who you pick
Picture windows
Of course
In 2005 after he been in the NBA for almost a decade
The phone finally met someone who could help him make this
A guy named Howard
Schecter
He's always talked about there has to be a different way well
We were the different way
Howard work for a clothing company called Steve & Barry's founded by a pair of long Islanders named Steve
Amberry
It was a relatively unknown chain
That's sold clothes at ridiculously low
Prices and they said they were able to do this
A couple of ways
For one they cut out the middleman they manufacture Their Own Line of clothes in China
They took the smallest markup
But they could possibly
Afford
They basically had no advertising budget
And then they open stores in struggling malls where they would
Ask for
Discount
Free space
This was a business mod
But now
Steve & Barry's
Wanted to get in
To be athletic sneaker
Howard personally had a vision for cheap basketball shoes
And he wanted to have a famous basketball player
People have told him that Stephon Marbury
Happened to be a famous basketball player
Looking
To make shoes cheaper
There was just like a light bulb went off and they said you know staff
Could be the perfect
Athlete
So where gets the stuff on that Steve & Barry's would like to me
And his first thought
Who and who
I didn't know I mean I learned of them before the meeting and I was like this is
You know I got to see this for myself
Justified took this meeting
And he remember Steven berries laying out their vision for the sneaker
They're going to call at the star berry
That's been Stefan's nicknames in high school
And they had brought some prototype
Plus some clothes that would be part of the star berryline
They start showing me and you know
The stuff that we're making the quality is really good that is
I'm saying
OK Google I was like how much is all that how much
It's like $15
You're going to make all that stuff
$15
Damn
And then he
No we're going to sell all this stuff
All the stuff you see is going to be $15 or less
I said
T okay
Like I
And it was like no serious
For real
And then I was like
Do you telling me you can make all of these different things and you can sell everything under $15
Let's do this deal
Now there are two ways
To think about it.
The obvious one is it
You want to go out
And find the most famous the biggest like the best
Person and attach them to your product
At this point in his career Stephon Marbury wasn't
Really any of those the
But the other way of thinking of endorsements is it if you have the right product
In the right person
In a story is
Perfect
Then maybe you don't have to be the most famous person in the world
So yeah there's a place for the Air Jordan where you have the most
Famous basketball player matched up with the most expensive most elite
Shoe
But maybe there's also a place for the star berry
Where you have a less famous basketball player
Who has a great story about how he couldn't afford those shoes
But now
He's matched up with a v
$18
On August 17th
The shudra
The strawberry one went on sale
Exclusively
@steven Berry
Another basketball star is lending his name to a new sneakers
At a low cost is starbury one basketball shoes
$14.98 for low income families
The story was everywhere
And so is Stefan
Showing off
Strawberry one is a mostly white shoe it has dark veins of blue cutting across the upper that's the part that goes
Over the top of your foot
The sole of the shoe with New York Knicks Orange
The Team Stefan with playing
I'm
People seemed
Excited to see it
But
Over and over
Same question
One question I might ask is are you cutting Corners at the production and cuz that's a sensitive issue everybody thought
If this cost $15
It cannot possibly
Be a good bass
I'm Good Morning America Diane Sawyer was worried about the bottom of the shoe
Basketball in here Jimmy Kimmel show the picture of Stephan holding up a shoe that look like
Someone had pulled it out of
Dumpster $15
Price signaling
Problem
In the marketing and Retail World prices communicate so much information
Especially
In an aspirational market like Athletics so
When you go out and you buy a new golf club for a little bit more money you're hoping
But that is going to buy you performance like maybe your drive will be 10 yards longer
And so pricing the star berry at $14.98
Had unintentionally signal to that this sneaker
Is crap
The Fancy Shoes are ten times more money does that mean that they are 10 times better does that mean
That the star berry is
10 *
Worse
See Premier the shuo
I forgot that so before we talked I went on eBay
The price signaling problem
Dominated the starburys
And what's the phone kept saying was
If people would just try these things out they would see that these are not
10 * 1
To be shoes for 10 years old I bought these on eBay they're my size
I'ma put you through the wringer man
I'm a play
Play games on it
I might try to run a half marathon time prediction is that they're going to hold up
You going to run a half marathon
Try try having
I haven't trained for it you good
Okay
On The Go baby go for it go for it
Don't breathe well but not the problem I am the problem
6.55
Terrible idea she was hella fine
They also actually held up really well running and cutting on a basketball court
But listen these are not the exact same as $150 pair of
Many of the differences are just cosmetic
It looks very simple the laces aren't
Fancy and I suspect the leather upper is actually pleather although I've never gotten a straight answer on that
But there are things that seem more important like there's no match for breathing there's no air bubble in the
High heel
That said
It is way closer to an expensive shoe than I expect
And so when the shoe came out
The goal was
To get people to try it and have the same experience
I had stuff on went on
Interview after interview
Trying to convince people just give it a chance
My favorite way that Stephon did this
What's he tried
I tried so hard
To just get someone to take a star berry
To take an expensive shoe and to do an analysis
My chopping them both in half
If you take a $200 shoe and you take my shoe when you cut both of the shoes down
Got a motor with a chainsaw
Over and over
You took both of the shoes you took a sword
Cut both of them down the middle
And then finally someone actually took Stephan up on this
Cut it down to half and to do the same exact
Really
It was John Stossel on 20/20 actually took a pair of Jordans and a pair of starburys
Sneaker X
So he cut both shoes up
And he and others in the business
Concluded are constructed the same way your Jordans do have this thing that looks like an air vent but
It's closed
I actually talked to the guy who is in charge of Designing Air Jordans at the time a sneaker Legend
Name Dewayne Edward
Oh yeah we bought a pair just to see cuz we were curious to like how they pull this off
Andy Wayne said Yeah we actually chop the pair of them open to
It was about the bare minimum you need to build a basketball shoe he wouldn't go play in
But that said
Is it better
Then you would expect a $15 in
It was
It was obviously no actually
People cutting shoe open
Great
But Howard Shack
You're from Steven berries
It says that both he and Stefan new
There's really only one
Test adult
Can an NBA player
Where these $15 shoes
In a real
NBA game
It is very easy to rip a $50 anything
Yeah
But if an NBA player
Kenan Trust
Their bodies
Tilly's
Gotta be good enough
It's got to be good and
The shoe launched in the summer during the autopsy
People had months to speculate
About whether the shoe could hold up or not
And then on November 1st
The day arrived
The first game of the Seas
New York Knicks
Versus the Memphis
The opening tip your Stefan wearing the black version of the starberry the version he wore for away games
Howard sheckter remembers watch
Enormous Pride every time they showed up and you saw that logo
We
Chilitos little company nobody ever heard of
We we made it we got this NBA star is wearing the sneaker we thought about on
Concord the game was going great it was
The third quarter
Stefan and the Knicks were leading by nine
And then
All of a sudden
I think Steph trip
Or something
Imma
I'm thinking it better not been the shoe remember he's playing in those reduced
Price shoes
But the wind is knocked out of me like
God forbid
The shoe ripped on court
Or it didn't hold the traction any any slipped in
Tours near something
You know
It's done
Stephon goes over to the bench
The game goes on without him
And somebody rushes over to look at his foot
And everyone is like oh my god let's hope it wasn't the shoes fault
Like like like
We don't know talking about
Define was totally fine he gotten kicked in the shin or some
Came back into the game
And honestly he doesn't even remember it
You know this is Sparta basketball
When the next game came
Stefan
Weather $15 shoe again
And then the next game and the next game
Where the entire season Stephon Marbury
War 1/5
King Dollar
Sneaker
Sales of the star berry
Tok off
Steven Berry's expanded the line Beyond just the basketball sneaker
And in total over the next year-and-a-half
They sold 4 million pairs of starbury sneakers
Insta font
For his part
Sperm Durante
Million dollars in royalties off of clothes
And shoes
Duffy's Bar not Air Jordan numbers but remember they didn't have to
Because Stefan was making affordable shoes
Fat people
Wanted
And he was making money
The experiment
What's a success it had worked
Sofantex the point of this one moment in
Particular that sums the supper
It's from one of his store appearances in his ex
When is a little kid
He shopping with his mom
And he's picking out all of these clothes and then he just goes and he walks to the camera he said
I'm living in a dream
How many me
I'm in a dream
Veteran
It did not last
Forever
Because in 2008
The financial
Crisis-hit
Howard schachter
So that hit Steven berries
Retailers
That work on thin margin
Rely heavily on the credit markets
To give them a line of credit in which to go out and buy inventory
And then you saw that inventory and pay back the bank and
And keep going
But credit lines
Froze up
And Steven Berry's filed for bankruptcy
Without the store
The $15 sneaker experiment
Steven berries was the
Exclusive provider of the sneaker and they were the ones
Handling the manufacturer
Those with their connect
Those were my connection
Other things were also going badly for stuff on it
His father had died tragic
Is basketball team was struggling
And he was getting blamed
M4a Plus
He wanted Young
And so in 2009 he decided
Was time to move on
Stefan left the NBA
And you left the starbury sneaker experiment behind
But then
Stephon Marbury resurrect
Did his career
In the one place that might still give his sneaker dream
A chance
Niihau
Washu ma bully
After the break
Stephon Marbury
What I jungle what does it mean I love China
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Slack
Used by companies all over the world to get everything done
Where every part of work
From documents to decisions is stored archived and searchable
10 seconds
Slack
Where work happens
Find out why
It's slack.com
In 2010 after Stephon Marbury had left the NBA he went to play professional basketball in
In China
After a couple years he landed on the Beijing ducks
Hey beloved perennial Underdog
They had never won
So we go we went 13 games in a row
Out the gate
Stephon Marbury led the Beijing ducks to a
First championship
And then another
He has since become one of the most famous basketball players
In Chinese basketball history
It's like a whole new life baby I can't tell you no lie
It's the truth
Statues Museum
Am I mistaken there's like a musical also did a musical
Either play
The Vice news organization actually went and recorded this play
Stefan is now very well connected in China
The global capital
Of sneaker manufacturer
And of course basketball players
Are still putting a names on basketball sneakers
And charging an absurd amount
And so Stefan
Has decided it is time
To bring back the star bear
A solid
Affordable basketball shoe with his name on
Is currently a limited run of starburys available online
They're ramping up production now
And Stefan will still sell
A $15 Bass
Can you still make and sell basketball sneakers
For $15
That you could
Play basketball in
Yes you can
The fappening
It is happening
Excited I'm very excited
Cuz I want all the little kids to be happy when they playing on the court
Fresh Pig cakes
You understand that's what it's really about
This time around though
He's also going to be selling some higher-end
Although
The fun higher-end means
50 bucks
The shoes will mostly be sold online
But there is a plan to have a couple of flagship store
One in Brooklyn possibly Coney Island the neighborhood where Stephon grew up
The other one
In Stefan's new home
Beijing
You know a product with an amazing backstory
We would love to hear about it maybe run a half of a half marathon in it email us Planet Money at NPR.
At work or courses
Find us on Facebook or Twitter this episode was produced by Sally Helm with an assist from Elizabeth
Planet money's editor is Bryant thermostat or supervising producer is Alex goldmark
Special thanks this week to Edward Saakashvili our intern
And to Chuck tatelbaum who helped me make sense of hundred
The pages of bankruptcy
And if you ever wanted to see Planet Money in person get in on the action will I have great news for you
We're bringing the show to the now hear this podcast Festival this September in New York City
Will be performing live along with a bunch of other amazing shows
To learn more in to get tickets you can go to now hear this fest.com
That's now hear this Fest
Dot-com and enter offer code money at checkout to save 20 bucks
I'm Kenny Malone thanks for listening
One last thing
NPR has a new podcast called what's good
Here are the hosts
To tell you little bit more about
Yo-yo everybody Stretch Armstrong
If you love this podcast you were listening to
Check out new show what's good with stretch and bobbito
This is not your average
You shall be telling stories that you're not going to
Find an Apple podcast the NPR one app or however
Vufine
Your pocket
It's
What's good