Support for NPR and the following message come from State Farm
When it comes to home and auto insurance they're here through the ups and downs go to statefarm.com
To be connected with one of the 19000 agents in neighborhoods Across the Nation
State Farm
Here to help life
Go right
There's a hard and fast
Rule in radio
And maybe
Noticed this
The rule is
Don't use
Numbers
Don't use very many numbers because the idea is you're listening to this and actually probably
We doing something
Walking somewhere
Working out doing the dishes
It gets confusing if I say 956
6 to 1
Four five
Because
You have no idea what I
So that's the rule
Today I'm going to review.
I actually love
To hear
Numbers
On the radio
It's a sort of like
Rhythm poetry thing like I could listen to numbers and I do
4 hours
In fact sometimes in the morning I will listen to
Bloomberg Business Radio
My family nuts
But I just let the numbers washer
Let's check in and how the markets are trading the Dow
Is down by 65 points as to be lower by 0.4% the NASDAQ is Trading
Down by one tenth of 1
10% in the bond markets you're seeing somebody going on and treasuries that you'll come eat at about 3 basis points
2.72
Percent is where the yield is on the 10
And yeah afterwards I do not
Remember any of those
But you know I can
Feel
The numbers and it makes me feel like someone has measured
Something
Calculated sum
Take a note
Of a particular moment
Every number
Has a story
And so today the show we're going to break the radio rules and just take a Shir
Delight
Numbers
Three numbers
In
3 price tag
Give me the big sad
A trillion dollars
10 million dollars
And $4
+ 66
The trillion dollars represents the dream for America
10 million dollars is the price of a single punctuation mark
And $4.66
That number involves a magical fairy
If it's in the middle of the night
Robert Smith
This is fun
Let's take a moment to thank and share a message from our sponsor betterment
A smarter way to invest your money
Betterment creates and manages a personalized portfolio for you
Focusing on ease-of-use and lowering taxes
And here's what you might find refreshing
No jargon low fees and full transparency
For a limited time sign up for betterment and you may qualify for a free Canary home security system to help secure your
Terms and conditions visit betterment.com Planet Money
On the show we're going to talk about
What different things
Caught starting with
The very small and cheap
To the inconceivably expensive
So let's just start with
A handful change
This right here around a dollar in change was what I
Used to get when I was a child
For a tooth
Place underneath my pillow at night
From the tooth fairy
Now I didn't think much about how much I got just
I wanted a lot of coins
But now that I'm a father like this has
Actually been added
Discussion I had played
Into the Night
How much should a child get
For a single tooth
From
The tooth fairy
And the more you think about the more you realize this is and overlooked economic indicator so
We brought it reporter Katie Malone
The palace
One tooth
One child
How much is it worth
I have an answer
$4.66
Cathay pacific boom
66f and we know this how we know this because there is
Strikingly good data
On what people giving their kids for teeth
What's call it bigtooth
Every year for just about the last 20 years
Delta Dental Insurance company has been conducting
The Tooth Fairy poll
A nationally representative
Survey
And currently a tooth is busy
Pulling in $4.66
So $4
$0.66
On average which is then I got as a kid
Did Robert the more I looked into this the more I realized that there is something very strange going on
With the tooth fairy right now
This sounds a little silly but I can give you an example of just how serious this can get
Set a scene for you
It's your mama White House
Members of the economic
Either
In The West Wing sitting around a table
Brilliant economist
Including Betsey Stevenson
A member of the Council of economic advisers
We are sitting around the table waiting for Jack Luther
Treasury secretary to walk over and honestly can't even tell you
What the meeting was about you know what it became about don't we
She's laughing because what it became about
What's a sort of National Economic consensus on what the Tooth Fairy should pay Betsy Stevenson's daughter for
For a tooth
I'm guessing first trial
First kid first tooth
And I think she had lost it that morning
It was
Crisis
So she turns the room and she says does anyone know
What the Tooth Fairy is
Paying these days
It's in the room lights up
Even people without kids
Start jumping in with their ideas
Betsey Stevenson her approaches
What is the tooth fairy give me as a kid
50 Cent
Gem testing mid-seventies or so
50 Cent's doesn't buy what it
You still
So the question is
Can we adjust that for inflation
This is a room full of Art
Nation's top Economist say can do it
Betsy just figured it out
What is $0.50 from the 70s worth
Now an inflation-adjusted number might put you something closer to $3 a tooth
$3 a tooth that's the inflated number but she asked the other Economist what are your kids act
Truly getting and they say
Poop 5 to $20
Some kid got $20 for a tooth there's General consensus that probably the Tooth Fairy didn't have any change on that
That does happen
In all seriousness though I mean
A serious
The story can get
I'm looking at that study
Did you gave me about
The average 2
Tooth Fairy gif
End
It is going up faster than inflation faster than you might think it would end this Robert this is the
Mystery over the last 10 years
According to that.
The price of a tooth
Skyrock
Dental inflation
What's call it
Has averaged over 10%
Per year
Which
Never got anywhere
Inflation xidan insane number
And so I
I figured we needed an expert
To the bottom of this
Yep this is Alan Blinder professor of Economics at Princeton University
The Outlanders not just some Economist in the 1990s he was
Vice chair of the Federal Reserve board
As you know Robert one of the
Most important jobs
The FED is to monitor
Inflation and keep it low
Keep it low and explain to him
The teeth
Have been going up at this crazy right around 10%
Premier
Tcsa
I can't think of anything that's gone up at 10%
And 4 comparison he said actual inflation over the last decade must be right around 2%
2% so I mean I get the obvious question is
What is so special about a tooth
That makes it go up so Robin
That was a question that I had and I thought
Maybe we could find an answer
In the way we calculate
The 2% number that's inflation for
Everything everything from
Fuel two bananas to a house
That's what's up kid by they only care about a tiny little section of
That's okay
1 Siri I had was
What if we
Ask kids
What do you actually care
Care about
And maybe that stuff maybe that stuff has gotten more expensive at a really high rate
Broad Strokes
Somebody's kids around New York City
Toys Electronics
Candy Nerf gun ice cream rock and roll guitar Pokemon card Max
Alan Blinder said actually
A lot of that stuff
Has gotten cheaper over the last decade
Sherpas toys are manufactured overseas
In China
Electronics are way more powerful UK
And anything and
Stop
By economic logic
Maybe the Tooth Fairy should actually be bringing less
Pentadecagon
Yeah I think the kids are making out like Bandits here
Do you think an intervention is necessary from your
I will Connecticut government intervention
The mystery deepens like kids are getting more money for more stuff
Then
What explains that $20 bill that I took to do my final economist
Justin wolfers who's
The professor theme
If you want to divorce me, talking into this economist talk about something called the income elasticity of demand
We do want to work Sunday, Target
The income
Elasticity of demand
Gout
10%
If all of a sudden you started making
10% more
It doesn't mean that you're going to suddenly spend 10% more on
On every single part of your life
You're not going to spend 10% more necessarily on
What are the categories of things
That we might spend
More than 10%
Now that we have the money
Wofford suspect
What's the children
Are one of those things we like to splurge
Into it doesn't surprise me to hear that the Tooth Fairy is outpaced inflation because the two trees one of those Vehicles which which
We give more to a kids
One more thing about Justin wolfers
Remember at the beginning of this we talked about
White House
Tooth Fairy Summit
Betsy Stephenson
Justin wolfers is her partner
That kid who lost her tooth
That's just
Sting's daughter so together they figured it out
We're family we taking data the median seems to be a great place to be and that's exactly where
$5
Feel like my kids have never gotten five.
The rabbit that is the going rate man
I just can't do it
Does it make you a bad father
I'm sorry I can't help it I think of it as as
Pocketful of change I think it was changed to but this particular argument always ends up with being
Back in my day
WhatsApp help
Three ways to get my tooth fairy
I just feel like you can't talk about this about to sound like a super old
Alright $5 that is $5
Kenny Malone one of the correspondents for Planet Money thank you sir thank you
We think of anything we do you're welcome you're welcome
Are the huge leap from pocket change to our next number
10 million dollars that is the voice of Noel King
Who has the story of a very
Unusual court case
Yes
It is a group of dairy truck drivers up in Maine who are suing their bosses for unpaid over
These guys were working long days 12 16 hours
The bosses were only paying them for 8
Today you are with a bunch of money
So far during normal case
Yes this court case hinges on a, that isn't a statute or actually it's a comment that is not
Gina Statute in Maine state law
The 10 million dollar, Oxford, okay
Do you know what an Oxford comma
It's right yes
I'm a firm believer in the extra, if you have a list
Like you say I like
Dessert
Soup
And oranges
You put a,
After the soup in before the amp
It's that, in a list of items the last, in a list of items but
There's a fierce debate over this some people think the Oxford comma is
Totally unnecessary
Which brings us back
Viskase in me
I'm going to give you a little
Primer on what main lost
Maine law says everybody gets overtime except for certain people there are there groups that just don't get paid.
Those people include
People who work
Who handle or ship
Perishable food
Stay don't
For some reason makeover
What's the statute spells it out really clearly it says the fall
Any worker who is involved in quote
Canning
Processing preserving freezing marketing storing
Packing for shipment or distribution of
Perishable foods
And there are commas
Between all the work on that list except
Packing for shipment or distribution
So there's no Oxford, no laugh
Comma between Shipman
And Disturbed
So that
Raise the question
Does it refer to
To packing for
Shipment of distribution
Or packing for shipment
Or distribution
That was a very hard thing to say but yet
That's exactly it
And with the workers lawyer said is
Because there's no
Oxford,
It is
Packing for shipment or distribution
Meaning
Distribution at self-driving the milk to stores in
Creating it
That
Is not
An exempt
Professor
You get overtime
And so did this court case go before an 8th grade
Teacher who decided
Actually everyone kept referencing your 10th grade teachers Wichita
Case went before three different judges
Five different times and here is where it has landed
A judge in the First Circuit Court of Appeals said
Because there is no Oxford comma
The wording is too ambiguous
For him to come down on the side
Of the company
The judge is essentially saying if the state wanted to make it clear that distribution is one of the things for which you don't
Makeover time
The probably should have put an Oxford comma in that list
So for want of a, the
Court case
This was what
The court case actually has not been one just yet what the judge said is that it
Thank you.
We are now going to ratchet this up 5
Five decimal places up to a trillion dollars at The Brick support and the following
Message come from ishares because the best preparation for tomorrow is building for your future
Today ishares by BlackRock inspired to build
Our final number today
Is 1
Trillian
Dollar
I kinda wanna do a Dr Evil One million
Dollars
That laughter comes from Elsa
Check who until very recently was NPR
Senate correspondent now a new member of Planet Money welcome and one trillion dollars is
In the news right now because because President Trump has said that he wants to spend a trillion dollars
Where's to build infrastructure
All across the United States
You probably picked this number because it sounds amazing
Between dogs but we had the question
If not a lot of money when it comes to infrastructure
Seems like a lot of mud
But there's a lot of different ways to look at this
It is a lot of money if you think about what we're already spending on it for
Struxureware spending
Two and a half trillion over the knee
10 years
Switch William on top of that more is a 40% jump
Which I put up there with the sort of
Historic level
Of of spending infrastructure
Country singer
President Eisenhower
Power spent roughly that scale
Of money
We started the interstate highways
And if you wanted to
Rebuild the entire interstate highways
Today you actually take
Paw Patrol
How to transfer
Infrastructure budget
But they did not say he wanted to spend a trillion dollars
On Road
He said he wanted to
Do everything everywhere we will rebuild our road
Al Bridge
Star tunnel
Highways airports
School
Hosp
You get a sewer system
You get a highway
You know what you want new elevators in your Municipal Building you got it
Exactly
You start to think Will trump want to do everything everywhere
How far does a trillion dollars
Actually
What is an actually bio
Yuan realtor
And that's what I said to find out
Just bobbing around New York
Yeah obviously the most expensive
Absolutely
But
The money doesn't go very far
Alright I'm Ready the Second Avenue subway right now okay so this is the new subway line on the east side of Manhattan
It cost 4 and 1/2 billion dollars just add three subway stop
I just rode the subway one
Stop which means I just burned through a billion and a half dollars
It took about
73 seconds
Or go down to the newly-built
Down by the world
Kobe
Oculus
It is a gorgeous
Gorgeous
I'm standing in basically a giant
Hallway right now it's like the lobby for a train station
4 billion dollars
It is basically just the entrance to a train
Right
You look at a list of plan projects for New York
Weekly this money can
Depleted
Another 10 billion would be needed to rebuild a Port Authority Bus
Turn on another 20 billion would be needed to build a Amtrak train
Tunnel under the Hudson River
If you want more community centers you want to rebuild housing hospitals water mains and sewers
All that money quickly as up you can get it 100 billion in a blanket
And that's just one city in the entire country
Yeah the biggest city but just one city
And I should say this when Donald Trump says
One trillion dollars
You need to keep in mind to caveat
First of all were talking about a trillion dollars
10 years
So that's a hundred billion
Per year for the entire
Country
Most of his money
The ideas is going to come from
Private investor
Yeah this was the fine print on the infrastructure plan which was the government was going to offer
Tax break
Or Private Industry to build a lot of
And a concerned about that is that maybe private investors be incentivized to invest in projects that would provide
Big revenue streams
Big shiny things they can brag about or things like toll roads I can make money
Exactly instead of say
Building sewer size
Dunellen wants to a ribbon-cutting in a sewer
You're welcome
Do you have a number you wanted to explain right up at Planet Money
Add npr.org Borg
Today's episode was produced by Nick Fountain and Sally Helm and now that you're done looking for the money may we suggest
Another fine
Podcast listening
But embedded is back for a special 3
Episode
Podcast
Mini series
About police shooting
Check it out embedded
On the NPR one app
Or where we get your find podcasts
Robert Smith
And I'm out to change thanks for listening