If you think one thing
And then at some later moment youth
I think something
If another words you change your mind sure you
You become farmer
You get called mean names wishy-washy
Flip flopper
In England is apparently
You Turner and in Australia
Back flipper
On the other hand
And if you do not
People say oh I like
He sticks to his guns I know where he stands
This is messed up
This is backwards changing your mind
Is Brave
You face the world
And you're saying
I was wrong
Admitted
Changing our minds is what we're supposed
To do
Because what are we
Right all the time about everything
No no no we're not right about everything and when we realize we're wrong
We should change armor
Hello and welcome to Planet Money on
And I'm taking
Today's Show in Praise of flip-floppers and you Turner's and back flippers
Three stories once about an economist another is about the novelist and the third is about a Scottish teenager
Who built a world where literally hundreds of thousands
People help each other change them
Support also comes from Fidelity invest
As a Fidelity wealth
You get a dedicated advisor
Hair to help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of tax
And make clear recommendations for your full Financial
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
First Step Catherine Baker
To the health economist
Set Harbor and she told us about something you care about a lot and that is
Hospital Emergency
Cheap rooms are full of people who won
Do not have health insurance
N2
Do not have a medical emergency
Because
In the emergency room under federal law they have to treat
You even if you don't have insurance
They can bill you later
But they cannot send you away
You had insurance and you could afford it you go to the doctor but if you're uninsured the emergency room the only place you can afford to
This is a problem for for a few reasons
For one thing it makes emergency rooms more crowded in general
Time for another
It's really inefficient the emergency room is annex
Pensive
Bad place to get Basic Metal
Interferes with Katherine Baker thought
If you gave people health insurance
You could solve
This problem they'd be less likely to go to the emergency room when they didn't have a medical emergency
Their health would improve you would spend less money
Because
Insured people don't go to the emergency room to get their basic care
And by the way over and above the emergency room thing in that back anomic case
Just believed in
Expanding health
So I've
Always held the view that it's a public policy priority
To ensure low income people and
Make sure they have it
The food and housing
But I know those are my views as
A voter
And is a taxpayer
Haha
That doesn't
Mean that there scientific evidence to say that's what everyone should think or that's what we ought to do
A while back
Baker Ford about this thing happening
The state decided to expand
It's health insurance program
Medicaid
1000 more
But Baker says there were still way more uninsured
People then there were available spots
So Justice
Fairway
Hand out those limited spots
Del Lottery
They got a whole bunch of people to sign up on a waiting list
They drew names by chance
And the people whose names were drawn
Got a chance to get the public insurance
And the people whose names were in
Didn't
The Sims
Kind of
Holder
Cruel somehow but
You know they had to choose some way to do
This is the way that you
And crucially for Baker organs decision
Do it this way
Create a disc disorder of natural Xperia
You know you have this big pool
Some of them are randomly selected to get Medicaid
Some of them are randomly denied
Baker looked at this in real life
You followed both groups of people
And compared what happened to them
You could learn so much
That provided
A perfect opportunity to figure out exactly what Medicaid does
The in particular you could actually test
Weather people in fact
Go to the emergency room
Less after they get mad
So Baker and her colleagues went out to Oregon talk with the people who are getting insurance
The people that weren't
But you know what the official
And then
They posted their entire study plan in advance
They explain everything they were going to measure and how they were going to measure them
So that everybody knew they weren't just like waiting until the end
And cherry-picking it was
Once I did this it was
Just a matter of waiting for the results
And then
The day arrived
Thomas like a movie we joked we should get popcorn and just watched the results and where were you and
Are you with like your co-authors just what where were you in the day.
Life isn't like a movie I was sitting by myself looking at my computer
And I got the results via email
She clicked open on the email
You saw the result
People who got health insurance
Did not
Go to the emergency room
Less
In fact
They went to the emergency room
More
40% more
And people who did not get insured
Her first thought was like maybe they done the math
Made some errors
The processing it was so surprising
I had not expected
A result of nearly that mag
40% increase was really
Much higher than I had even
Imagine
The math was correct
Bottom line Baker says her study showed
Very clearly that when people get Medicaid
They get more health
Not only do they go to the emerging
They go to the regular doctor more as well
Her study found that Medicaid does not save taxpayers
For science
It seemed
Like a really interesting important find
And
Frankly not every paper elicits that reaction I think most of my papers are dull
Important end
A major scientific contribution and that's exciting
On the other hand I felt
Disappointed for the
Cause
Of expanding health insurance coverage
The thing you're discovering as a scientist is bad for the thing that you want as a city
Yes
And that's
Really
Hard as a
Person who is both of those people at the same time
I have to say
This is a thing that I love about
It is it is this whole system of thought
And action that is designed
To change people's minds
Sure you
You have some belief about the world some story that you're telling her
Yourself and that's fine
Button test
And if it doesn't hold up
You change your mind
You come up with a new story
And obviously this is an idealized version of Sia
I know it doesn't always work
That way but sometimes it does write it worked in this case
Catherine Baker changed her mom
Here is her revised story
About what happens when pee
People get Medicaid
Wearing my
Economist hat
I couldn't really be
Oh that's
Surprised which is what made me realize my
Prior view was more of a
Hope that anything else
Because one of the basic things we know from economics is that when something Cost Less
People use it more
Emergency department no exception
It used to be really expensive to go even though they couldn't turn people away
They could still issue a Big Bill at the end
And so uninsured people were reluctant to use the emergency department because they couldn't pay for it
Once people get insurance they don't have to pay any more
So they go to the emergency room more often
The other results of the study were mixed but he did show that there were several ways in which people on Medicaid
They did seem to be
They reported being in better
They were less likely to get into financial trouble
And Baker still thinks that giving Medicaid to more people is a good idea
She thinks it's worth the money
But she says that is her view as a citizen
Not as assigned
Okay so just give it to you haven't heard from you or do you know if you have a name
Memorize I have a memorize but I read them out in order
As they are
Okay
So brulee is
This is Cowper
He's 21 years old
And he's helped to come up with a set of rules
That has done something miraculous
Created a place
On the internet
Where people can calmly and rationally
Change other people's money
It's a group that Turnbull founded on Reddit called changemyview
He found it about 4 years ago it now has more than 300 thousand members
It has been the subject of multiple academic studies where people are trying to figure out
I would think like this could actually happen
And internal says the magic for this
The secret sauce is these rule
Bruce would have taken years to figure out
And he walked us through
So Brule is explain the reasoning behind your view not just what that view is
Here's a changemyview
People go there and they post something they believe
Some view that they
We put some real examples of these
The minimum wage should be abolished
Or communism isn't that bad
Or
Voldemort from Harry Potter is actually kind of crappy
That person Route 6
Paragraphs
Explaining the reasoning
Behind the Voldemort
And that the idea behind
Making people
Explain the reason behind their view is
If you want to change people's mind it's not enough to know what they able
If you have to know why they believe
Okay next
Ruby
You must personally hold the view and be open to a change in
Turnbull told us that
He wants change my view to be a destination
Hope use that they're open to change
But that there may be embarrassed or uncomfortable
Talking about in real life
Like a couple examples of use people and posted recently
One of them
If you date outside your race
You are a race
Traitor another one
Christianity Judaism and Islam are all generally
Evil the people who posted those two they both change their views
Direction rules are basically house
Keeping roof C is about formatting
Ruby no method post
Other words for through love changemyview
Do not talk about change my view on change my view
Is a whole other subgroups
He only post if you're willing to have a conversation with those reply to you and are available to start doing so within 3 hour
Hours of posting
We don't want you to just hit and run with your post
You're if you're entering a relationship
Yep
And these are committed relationships on some of these posts
People go back and forth and back and forth for like
5080 pages
Hundreds of comments
Good next
Don't give you the hostiles other users
When you started the subreddit
Did you have a lot of these kind of
Personal attacks
Yep
This rule Usher obvious
But it's paired with another rule it's a little bit more surprises
This other world says you are not allowed to reply to someone's View
Buy just confirming or validating what they already
People were just coming in and saying yeah I agree with you
No reason to change this view productive
In these two rules the
Don't Be a Jerk rule combined with
You must disagree
Rule the show just
How difficult it is what turned
Civil discourse here is on a Razor's Edge
One side
The thinking spiral off in
The fighting
And then on the other side spirals off into agreeing
Into like an echo
All right last rule we're going to talk
Award a Delta if you've acknowledged the change in your view a Delta that the Greek letter that looks like a little triangle
And is the symbol of change
And this is basically like I change my view merit badge
And so the waitresses like
Say I show up in post my
Bob Dylan is underrated
And Kenny than you show up and you you and I say underrated they gave him a damn
Nobel Prize
And it's okay fair enough maybe he was appropriately rated
You have changed my view
And now I award you a Delta
And and what is happened
On the group's introduces is Delta's have become
This status
What I find
Really into
About this is I feel like they have flipped upside down the way status Works in this
Typically
The way you get status ended
Is not actually buy a
Appealing to the other side to the people here nominally trying to convince
What you're really doing is like showing off for your
So you get status for like
For like a sick burn or a good comeback Irwin
But those are not
What kinds of things actually
Change other people's mind
Until what the Deltas have done is
Transform the way you get status
There is like a leaderboard for the people who get the most deltas
To change other people's mind so
So in this group
The way you get to be you know a big deal is by really changing other people's money
And that's it those are the 10 rules
And taken together they
You really seem to work people come in
They post their views on things
Controversial or silly or whatever
And then there is this civil conversation
On the internet
Without name calling
And sometimes people change their views
Did you feel like you come up with rules
You know for for the world not just for your subreddit
I mean yeah that's that's why when I look at these I think this is the kind of thing that people should
Should follow when they're trying to persuade other people or just in general conversation
And having rules
Some people that sounds a bit like
Authoritarian or something
But they're not
Really rules
They're kind of advice
Because this is what works and this is what doesn't work and that's kind of what we're saying
I mean they are rules but your saying there for our own good
Exactly
In a minute we'll have the third and final chapter
I think is a lot more interesting than it would sound if I describe it now
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Capital One
Keep your credit score at
Peace with a credit wise app from Capital One
Get alerts each time your credit is pulled and when your TransUnion credit report change
Plus it's free for every
Download the credit wise app today
Cory doctorow is one of these people
Has like seven different jobs or whatever he writes novels
He's one of the editors of the website boing-boing
And he is one of the biggest names in the fight over
Copyright law
Doctor who thinks that copyright law is
Is broken that the way it works and I was bad person
Society
Bad for people who do
Do creative work
But
Doctor did not always feel this way
And the Ark
How he changed his mind
Is really Illuminating and it's a useful way to
You think about
The Arc starts
With doctors
First Servpro
Professional ID
Is a science fiction
I started writing science-fiction when I was a small kid like literally when I was six and I started sending it to magazines when I was
16 and selling it when I was 17
What is first publish stories
Was called craphound
It has been an alien who loves
Yard sales
You know I was a baby writer
I'm so what I knew about copyright was what I learned from other writers
So I thought that copyright was a thing that authors got
Because they made something new
With their brains
And that they had a moral right to it
And that by holding onto that moral right they could also make sure that big rapacious companies didn't rip them
He thought copyright should probably extend forever like if you build a house
You can pass it on to your children
They can pass it on to their kids
And so on
Why should it be any different if you write a book
Doctor went off to college became a programmer
And started a company
That in some ways grew out of that view of
Copyright this was the era of Napster
You know that the program that made it super easy to download music for free on the internet
Any idea behind doctors company was
Let people download files on the internet
But put rules on Powell and and whether they could share those files
For example you're allowed to listen to this once when you download it from someone over the internet
But if you want to listen to it again
You've got to pay some money to unlock it again
To make this technically pasa
Dr. Oz company was going to use with
Call digital rights
DRM
Basically this is a way to encode these kinds of rules
Into the software
Doctors company raised 19 million dollars
He starts flying around the world to speak it,
And it was on the road to one of those
This one was in Hong Kong
That he had his conversion
He was traveling with a corporate copyright lawyer
Who was going to go to the same card
I sat down and coach
Doctor Who was on the Isle the lawyer was
Was in the middle seat
It was in the days in which
You know I books were look like toilet seats and had a battery that lasted for 30 minutes
Atlanta laptop for our younger
Yeah that's right
And so 30-45 minutes in
We have nothing to do
Airplane food and argue about copyright
Its 30000
60 / the Pacific
The copyright lawyer
Start in on.
He says
Your view about copyright is naive
Overly simplistic in fact
This whole way of thinking about creative work
Is wrong
We don't have copyright because there's some kind of
Moral right of ownership
That that people have to their creative
Because
What thing that I did doesn't even make sense
You know the way creative stuff works
Everybody is always taking stuff from everybody else
This is true you know in music
Rock and roll was basically
The blues and if x equals all the way back everybody has always.
They call brahms's First Beethoven's tenth
That's good that's a lawyer says
Look your stories are full of ideas
You borrowed from other science fiction writers
You know all the people who wrote about aliens before you do they have a moral right
Own all stories about aliens
Indoctro says something like
Maybe maybe not
So by the time we got off the plane
1215 hours later however long
The flight is from San Francisco to Hong Kong
I had serious doubts
And then one around Hong Kong for the next two days and we weren't at the conference going to the
Cuz you're all horribly jetlag to so like going to the temple Street Market at 2 in the morning to eat
You know tentacles
And shouting about copyright
My dream trip
The lawyer convinces doctor that copyright is not about some
Moral right to
Pretty it's much more practical
In fact it's spelled out
Recently in the US comes
Institution
The new transform Cory doctorow can quote it off the top of
To promote the useful Arts and Sciences Congress shall create monopolies of limited times right
Soap so not because
You got property rights and everything you make
Butter promote
The useful Arts and Sciences
In other words the point of copyright
Used to get people to make more stuff
Because it's good for society when people make stuff
When it right songs and books and make movies
More
Is better
And in the end
I realize that
Copyright
Weather was a policy
That's created
To encourage certain kinds of creativity
And that
The limits on copyright like how long it lasts or when people can use your work without your permission
Those aren't just
Off to one side of copyright there as important as the exclusive rights that the Creator gay
Conference ends
Dr. Agosto
Before long
He decides
What my company is doing
Using digital Rights Management
Putting all these copyright rules indica
Computer code
It's not doing what I thought it was doing
It's not really encouraging creative
It's not really helping little artists
It's mostly helping big cup
And I wrote a letter to the investor
And told him I was going to work there
I was quitting
He goes to work for this Foundation that pushes for Less
Strict copyright
Start arguing publicly
That the details of copyright law serve big corporations were than little artists
He says copyright protection should be shorter
Is essentially out in public arguing
The exact opposite of what he believed
This makes him a star among a lot of
Tech nerds but a lot of espousing Science Fiction world
Much less impressed
My writing teacher
Once threatened to punch me in the face and a panel about copyright years later and there's another there's another writer who
I think literally hate
Over this
And she still one of mine
It sucks to have people say
That I have done something
Thuja
Describe the children of working artists
Of their do
I think they're wrong though
One thing is striking to me about doctors
I feel like
He changed his mind
In part because
He is one of these people who has all these different jobs
Moves in all these
You know
All his friends were writers say
I feel like the story would have been really different I feel like you probably would not have
Cory doctorow is still writing he published a novel early
This year
Another project that he's working on
Trying to get companies to stop
Using digital rights
Drf
In other words
He's trying to get rid of the exact thing his old company
You never call
Right
Contact
Email us at Planet Money NPR. Org on Facebook or Twitter
Today's episode was produced by Sally Helm Bryant urstadt is our editors supervising for
Special thanks to Liz weeks who talked to us about
And if you're looking for something else listen to check out invisibilia the show about invisible forces
The shape human behavior
The last few episodes of the third season are coming out right now and in the shows they're looking at like the ideas we
We have about RC
You know is there one true version of the self
You can find invisibilia in the NPR one app or wherever you get your pie
I'm taking both today and I'm Kenny Malone thanks for listening
One less thing NPR
Has just launched a brand new podcast
Here to tell you about it is the host
Sam sander
Hey Uncle Sam Sanders here these days I feel like I can't make sense of a News until I talk it out with my friends
I made a new show where we do that every week
It's called
It's been a minute
That's my way of saying let's catch up
Find it's been a minute now
On the NPR one app or wherever to get your podcast
Thanks