The first time Bill Penningtons house in Houston flooded it was Memorial Day of 2015
28 in of rain fell
And he had no idea what the
Doing a hindsight very stupid things like putting towels of it by the front door.
Keep the water from coming in
And then I turn around and there's
Literally water bubbling up
From
The floor like in the middle of my house
Spell grabs his wife
His two kids
The two dogs
And they go to that
And stay there for 6
Hours they're watching the water
Higher and higher porches
An interesting experience you know kids have to go to the bathroom cuz when I eat food so it's like okay yeah
The second time build house flooded
It was tax day of 26
Yaboo got 16 in but this time he knew to get out of the house so he and his family went over to the neighbor
The third time built house flooded it was Hurricane Harvey
He just late last
And by now he's an ex
Yeah he hears a meteorologist say the words
Biblical
Slide
And there's no Panic
He packs up his family and heads over to his parents
The next Monday Bill puts on his work boots any Pilots his truck a mile home
He pulls into the driveway and he sees
The weirdest
Cons of watermelon
All over
The place
Watermelon
And so I'm like what
In the world who is growing watermelon
Actually it's turns out there's a small grocery store
Four blocks away from me but it's
Upstream
And it had gotten flooded and it's some pointed door had broken open and all of these watermelons
Set flow down out of the grocery store into
The street in the yard and
Bill pushes open
In his front door and looks inside
And for the third time in three years
His house has been destroyed by a flood
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm next up
So we're going to ask why does Bill Pennington keep coming back to this house
And why does the government keep
Paying him to do it
Support also comes from Fidelity Investment
As a Fidelity wealth manager
You get a dedicated advisor
Is there to help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes
And make clear recommendations for your full Financial
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
6 years ago when Bill Pennington bought his house
His mortgage lender made him by
Flood insurance that
That right there is the simple answer to why he is still here
He's in church
Bills going to get a payout
His house and his
Get insurance is a beautiful thing it protects you against
Rescue make sure
You don't lose everything
Adventures in general are not afraid of her
They will insure just about anything
Poker games Rockets body parts
They will do that as long as they can charge enough to make it worthwhile
All interest care about is at the end of the year they
Taking in more money than they pay
Bill Pennington flood insurance policy
Is not under written by a company
Is underwritten by the Federal Gov
And when you get to pay out later this year
The money is going to come from the federal government and to understand why that is all you have to do is
Standing Bill Penningtons driveway and look up and down the
Hi
Hi. How's it going how are you doing
So
Cheese
This
Is
Looks like the inside of your house is outside your house
Yep pretty much that is
I would say somewhere on 95% of my home and possessions
Out on the curb in the trash
What are we what are we looking at what do you see
What's sheetrock about the doors
And then I turn around and I look down the street and it's the same thing
Sheetrock and doors and big bags of
Toys and clothes in
Garbage
On the lawn of just about every single house on this
Almost everyone stuff is out on everyone
And this right here what you're looking at is something insurance companies
Do not like
They call it
Correlated risk or geographically correlated
And what it means is
Right at this moment
Just about everybody on bills block is going to have a massive
Flood insurance
And that is a really scary idea to insurance
What insurance companies love
Is when risk is not Coral
Write think about car insurance
Is Bill got in a car accident
His neighbors are not
Also all going to get in car
The same day
And so insurance companies can deal with that they're not afraid of risk they just don't want it all to happen at the same time
Or in the same place
So up until the 1960s most insurance companies
Warrant offering flood insurance
And then in nineteen
65 there was this
Huge storm Hurricane Betsy hit the Gulf Coast
It was a harvey style hurricane it was a
The cataclysm
Wiped out thousands of homes
And most
People did not have flood insurance
The government decided we need to do some
And they did
They created this thing that
It still exists today is called the national flood insurance
Nfip
It does a couple of thing
Try to convince people not to build in Risky areas
But if they do
It tries to encourage them to build smart to raise their houses
But as we saw in Houston
Deterrence does not always
Cities get bigger
Weather patterns change an area that wasn't high-risk
Becomes pirate
So if you're in a risky area and you get hit by a flood
The government has your back
Just as long as you've got insurance
The government will pay your claim
Okay so the government is going to act like an insurance
It collects premiums from people like Bill and other Houston nights and it tries to collect more every year that I paid
Wrightwood
Here is where the problems
Start a couple years after the nfip the federal government
It starts offering flood insurance
They realize
Not enough
People are buying
The insurance
Sony early 70s the government doubles down
It's his
Look Joe homeowner in Houston
You live in high-risk area
You have a federally backed mortgage
You have to buy footage
But this is America in America we do not like
To be told what to do
You'll be loved in America
Cheap stuff
So in the early seventies the government pushes the price of flood insurance
Way down
In an effort to get more people
Put the sign up and here's what's been happening since
People are paying those cheap
Premium
The nfip is
Is chugging along
And then
There's a bad year
A year with a lot of fun
And those premiums haven't added up
To nearly enough money to cover everyone
If this was an insurance company
They would be bankrupt
But it's not it's a government program so
The nfip goes to the treasury
And says hey
We need to borrow some money
The pay people like Bill but then we have a couple more bad years with big flood
And the nfip is borrowing more and more from the treasury
And now here we are in 2017 and the nfip owes the treasury around
30 billion dollars
And people we spoke to for the story said
The nfip is probably never going to pay that debt back
And that means
Taxpayers eventually will be on the hook for this
Yes floods are hard to ensure that is a real thing that correlated wristband
But a big problem is
The government offering those discounted rate
Yes
Discounted rates
Great for homeowners
But that kind of sucker punches another key Concept in insurance which is
Your rates
Are supposed to reflect your wrist
Yeah Bill Pennington totally get
When my son turns 18 and he's driving
I don't want to insure him
Right so he's going to be buried
We have a long long track record of 18 year old boys doing stew
Stupid stuff
Actually went to Houston looking for someone like Bill somebody whose house
Is flooded again and again
Because while we were reading about flood insurance which is what we do here
We came across this amazing status
Over the course of the flood insurance programs life
A tiny percentage of house
1%
Have you eaten up more than a
Quarter of the
Is there houses that have flooded over and over and over
Mike Mills
So while I was standing with Bill in
The shell of his house
I asked him
How much has Insurance paid you out over the last 3 years
And he took out his phone and he is a Dropbox app
So this is
Gaiam Sol
I think I still have
Yeah the 2016 flood the 20
I-15 flood all the documentation
And look over shoulder
So this is a history of
Every claim on this property address
I'm just going to I'm just going to add it up
Okay alright let's do this together here we go
This document on his phone shows that builds house has gotten flood insurance payments
From the federal government
Different time I thought he was flooded three times
She was 43 times yes
But the house also flooded into
2001 and in 1980
So we had those up on my calculator
And then we get to Bills play
This is Memorial Day 2015
Teen Tax Day 2016
So at that point swear now at 870,000
$51 and forty
This house for which you paid $525,000
Has now cost
The national flood insurance program
$51.44
$878,000
Yes and Nick here's the thing
That is
Before hurricane Harvey right
Bill has just filed another claim
He will certainly get another payout he is insured
And this time it's for newer
Better stuff
So he's insured up to $350,000
To be conservative we typed in Vegas 300000
What is that
That's 1.18 $8000000
Change
Bill's house
Will have cost
The federal government
More than
$1000000
What is he paying in preemie
He's paying
$4,800
A year
Seems like nothing
Or at least not nearly enough
Do you feel bad that you are costing a lot of money
I mean maybe
Some sort of psychopath
After something but it doesn't necessarily feel personal to me because it's
I feel like I haven't
I didn't intentionally flood my house
I didn't decide
I'm going to buy this house and I'm going to make it
Killing on flood Revenue
Saferite so
Bill is not a psychopath I mean I've considered it for a minute
No I mean your eye if we were in Bill's position
I'm pretty sure we would do the same thing right like
Think about it the government requires bills mortgage lender to require that he has flood insurance
So he can get flood insurance
Any pays premiums just like you would to a normal insurance
Company
Except
This is not a normal insurance,
What do you think you'd be paying if there was no government flood insurance
I don't think I could get insurance
Quite right I give this point I don't there's probably not an insurance company in the world that would insure my property
It's just like if I was a
A drunk driver that had gotten the
5 DUIs in
Then two and a half years that I wouldn't be able to get insurance I probably get a driver's license I would be able to drive so
Your house is the drunk driver of Holmes your house is like this 17 year old boy on a motorcycle
Who drink
Of home
Exactly
He knows this is
I was talking to Bill he offered a solution
One thing I found out while I was driving around you
Houston is that
Moose
People in that City do not have flood insurance
It's only about 15%
Voodoo
And I'm asking them
Why
Why are you not insured
And they're telling me
Because no one ever said I had to buy flood insurance
Great cuz remember the government rule says that if you're in a flood-prone area and you are federally backed mortgage
Your lender must make you buy
Flood insurance rates so I'm talking to people who are technically outside of the high-risk area
Or in the case of some older folks
In the mortgage is paid off
Nobody can tell you you have to buy flood insurance
And there's a 30
You were supposed to buy flood insurance
But you let it lapse and nobody knows
All of this all these people were kind of rolling around in the back of my mind and then
Bill said
If you're in a flood-prone area which is
It's probably anywhere along the Gulf Coast
Everyone should
Should have flooding
Weather that has come through a federal mandate
I just want to point out that you are a text
You are texting who owns guns
You are a you say you you lean libertarian
And you are saying
Everybody should have
Dubai
For insurance
Absolutely bills argument is
We make more people buy flood insurance
So weird
Running the risk around more
If I'm not in a risky area my rates are going to be super low I'm paying $10 a month for my third-story apartment
But because there are more of us paying
There's just a bigger pool is it sounds like it makes so much sense but do you know what that would be
Oh man that would be a government mandate that you have to buy insurance
And we tried that
With health insurance and we are still going through that with health insurance
So we had to call up the people who are actually ensuring
The Federal Emergency Management agency
Yes FEMA
FEMA administers the flood insurance
Program
We called up Andy Neil who's an actuary
It's like the most boring job in the world
You know imma I'm a flood fighter I'm helping to make our country safer
Andy Mineo is basically the guy ensuring
Bill doesn't always work for the government
She's been in the private sector
So we ask this question about the national flood insurance program nfip that we had been thinking about for this
Entire time
If you are
Private company would you ensure bill
Well you know it's an interesting thing so
The nfip does not get
Diseno
So
In my rate-setting process we do have
High rates for risk Europe
People model race
Straight for moderately risky
Rates for
Glow recipe
For the very riskiest of structures
For the very riskiest
Across all lines of insurance
There's a difficulty
In offering insurance
Very highest
But you got to do it
I have to do it I have to take off
Kind of dogs are question about private in
Well
Yes but he's an employee of the federal government and as an employee of the federal government he has
Ice to ensure bills house
This would all work out better
If any nail could charge bill
More for his insurance
Me am so that bills rates would actually reflect his risk
And maybe he would want to move to another neighborhood or put his house up on stilts
Yeah but Andy Neal and FEMA don't really have control over how and when and where they
Raise rate
Those decisions are made by Congress
Well
In terms of that I would like to
To say that
Congress has a very difficult
It's it's
It's a very difficult policy area
Set aside
How to
Set the space
It's hard
You tell people
You have to buy insurance and then on top of that your rates are going to be really high
And this upsets people
And upset
People upset politician
There is this other program that FEMA has where they give grants to elevate houses
Like bells or tear them down and help people move to another neighbor
But those grants are really hard to get bill has already applied and he got
You get the impression here that FEMA and
People like Andy Neill are really trying to make the situation better
In fact back in April Bill Pennington in Houston got a letter in the mail
The letter said
Bill
You are now enrolled in National
Flood insurance program
Direct
At that point they don't
Tell you anything other than that so you know you're moving to nfip direct you didn't know what nfip direct men
You know I probably wasn't a good thing but it is not a good
It means hey buddy
Your house keeps flooding
Again
And again
We're going to keep raising your rates
Until they're closer to what you should be paying
And Bill he
He just doesn't want to do this
Flood
Rebuild
Slide
Repelled watch
Chip insurance rates
Pic higher and higher
There's an obvious question here which is why doesn't bill just move to a different neighbor
I asked him and he said look I like this neighborhood the schools are great I went to the school's my dad went to be
Lee Schools
I want to stay in my neighbor
So bill is going to figure out a way to stay
He's going to take that insurance payout
Going to try to get a loan
He's going to try to put his house up on stilts
Or maybe
Peritol down and rebuild
Just a little bit higher
But he is going to make sure that
But he never floods
Those are all things that bill
Plans
To do
But they will take time
You know what he's currently doing
He's currently paying his
Way too low insurance premium
And say he doesn't get his house elevated in
Say there's another flood
The federal government
We'll have him covered
Support also comes from fidelity
As a Fidelity Wealth Management
You get a dedicated advisor
To help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact
Taxes and make clear recommendations for your full Financial
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
We always want to hear your story ideas email us where Planet Money at npr.org
We are on Twitter
Too much probably and on face
Find it at Planet
Trisha was produced by the great Sally Helm vitamin E supervising producer is Alex goldmark Brian Dorsett
Edison show
A lot of people helped us out with Today Show we want to
Especially thank
Very brilliant Carolyn Kooskia at Wharton risk management and decision processes Center
Craig Fugate who used to run FEMA Steve Ellis at taxpayers for common sense
Rob Moore the nrdc and David Conrad who consults for the association of State floodplain managers
Garland Texas thanks to Aaron Duca and Sam
And if you're looking for another show to listen to
I highly recommend
Been a minute with Sam Sanders Noel was on a few weeks back
My favorite part about the show is once a week
They asked listeners what's the best thing that happened to you this week and they play this Montage from all around the country
I cried nearly every time
You can find it at npr.org podcast or on the NPR one app
I'm the fountain and I'm Noel King
Bill Pennington is not the only person
Right there a lot of these houses that flood
Again and again
Wellington Houston the most extreme case that I heard of is this
Legendary house that is cited in a lot of articles
It's flooded 16 times
In 18 years