This message comes from NPR sponsors snowflake
The only data warehouse built for the cloud
Unlock deep Data Insights with the instantly scalable Cloud build data warehouse
Start your journey towards data-driven decision-making
It's snowflake. Com NPR
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
And I'm Jacob
Today on the show the entire federal budget
Every dollar the federal government spent last
3.9 trillion dollars
We're going to do it in just
10 minutes
We're going to divide up our 10 minutes exactly the way the government divided up its butt
So the more money a program got from the federal government
The more time it's going to get
We are going to hit every
Social
Defense
Mowing the lawn at the White House everything
There's a poem
Support for NPR comes from LinkedIn learning proud to support the launch of Life kit
NPR's guy to help you make better life decision
LinkedIn learning short video tutorials cover business Tech
And creative skills employers look for at every level
All taught by experts and new courses are added every week
+ LinkedIn learning is personalized
Recommended courses based on your interest and Life kid listeners get a month of learning free
Start your free trial at LinkedIn learning.com NPR
Okay here's how it's going to work
10 minutes on the clock
And we're going to cover the entire federal budget
Every second of that 10 minutes
Will be worth 6.4 billion dollars
So the small programs
Super Bass
Big programs nothing but time
I'm going to bring in a bunch of people from planet money to help us out
So the first piece not show today Robert Smith is going to talk about Medicare and Medicaid
They got just over a trillion dollars that is
29% of
The federal budget
So they will get 29% of our 10 minutes
Start the clock
Now
This debate
About whether the federal government should have a responsibility to pay for healthcare
Well I got news
It already.
The federal government pays for the Healthcare of 120
Million America
People over the age of 65 families with low income
People with long term disability
They're all covered
My medicare
And Medicaid
Medicaid and Medicare
Although I always mix them up
Everyone.
Item embarrassing errors when I was a new health policy reporter wear out
Mistake these in stories
Lots of people sent me angry emails
This is Sarah Kliff a writer for vox.com she co-hosts the weeds podcast
I heard a terrible way to remember it's all ages ago someone told me
You care for the old and Aid the sick
Are no Aid the poor that's what to see if it's
Lipids chemical lab
Okay I have a better one
Silver hair
Medicare
Underpaid
Medicaid
If we live long enough we all get Medicare
But even if you don't consider yourself poor you might also find yourself on
Medicaid
Actually finances a lot of long-term nursing homes days
So a lot of middle upper class Americans eventually do end up on Medicaid when they need
That kind of coverage and they're kind of whittled away their savings
And there you have it
HTC how much time do I have left
You got about a minute and a half
Men and a half
Yeah you guys this is the big this is the biggest part of the body you got some time
Okay let's go get some coffee
What's the time
We have some fun and I can explain one more thing about Medicaid
Okay so we all heard about Obamacare we've all heard about how in Congress right now the Republican
Heartland doing Obamacare
What the fight is really about
Is the future
Of the four guys were talking about the future of Medicaid
Underpaid
Underpay
You want sugar to cup
A black coffee please
What is a big waste of Barack Obama
Got people insured was to expand Medicaid
Medicaid costs are shared between the federal government and state
States run the program
Essentially said
We are going to give you more Federal money a larger share of our budget
If you discover more people
Answer this this
Part of the budget pie I'm talking my way through this. Large
So many Republicans are thinking about how do we undo Obamacare what they thought is let's put some cat
Undergrowth
Of Medicaid
And what that means insert real-world terms is it if Republican plan passes
15 million
Fewer people covered by Medicaid
So we're going to do the show again in 10 years
There might be slightly less time for government
No coffee break
Maybe time for a short
You going to drink that by the way
No
Transportation 2% of the budget
Kenny Malone
We asked former secretary Ray lahood to write a haiku
Decline so I made one for him
Using words from his old
Oh Highway crumbles
Nisar Wheels
One big pothole
It spreads
Cross
The roads
Thank you all very much thank you very much
Next up Social Security
It accounts for 24% of federal spending
Jacob take it away
Social Security is really big
Because almost everybody gets it
In particular almost every American
Over the age of 66
Including billionaires
You know if Warren Buffett wants Social Security he can get it
I called
Ted marmor to ask about this
Is an Emeritus professor at Yale expert answers
Why does Warren Buffett
Get Social Security
That's a classic dumbbell
Under couch formulation
Okay mama said billionaires getting social
Security it's not a bug
It's a feature
When Social Security was created back in the thirties some Democrats did one
Creative version of the program
Where the money just went to Port
But President Roosevelt was like no
Program like that just won't survive Politico
What we need is something that almost all working people are eligible
Andy said we should find it with a special pass
Acts that almost all working people pay
That way people will say
I paid into social
Security I deserve social
Security when I retire
And I will vote out-of-office any politician who tries to
Take it away from me
Terms
Emoji Express
What's God damn it I'm going to be
I'm going to be sure to have a program that no damn concur
Is going to mess with because people are going to feel
Entitled
But I do think it leads to a lot of confusion
You know people seem to think
Oh I contributed
Social Security they're holding onto my money in a special box
This is not how it work
My money is paying for retired people right now and I'm crossing my fingers
Bet in 30 years when I retired there will be
40 roads were paying me
Chicken
I'll bet you any money and I want you to pay me off by putting it in my grave
The probability that you
Will receive
Social Security benefits for retirement
Is so hot
That you would should be declared irrational
The bleeding song
Why am I confident
Why am I so, cuz I understand the political economy of the United States because Roosevelt was right
Truck because almost everybody pays in and gets paid out including billionaires
Merced Social Security is politically Bulletproof
Social services and education
3%
And for the segment we wanted to get someone who is currently a beneficiary of public education
AKA
Jacob's kit
The spending in this area
Comes from
State and local governments
The federal government bid
Biggest education line
I don't
Is grants for low-income College
National Defense is
15% of federal spending
Stacy
We spend one and a half billion dollars every day on.
And this is famously one of the most controversial part 2
Democrats often come in and
Cut defense spending
Republicans come in and
Raise defense spending
What's the power in spite of all of this
If you look back over the last
20 years the share of the budget devoted to defense
It's not really changed
That much
And actually
That's pretty much true for most
Of the federal budget
It stays pretty steady
And I was
Totally shocked by this so I talked to this guy Bill Valdez about it he work for the energy department for more than 20 years ago
Out of budget
And he told me his theory of what's going on here
Yeah the real thing that keeps the budget stable is that
There are all these special interest
Hundreds of lobbyists
Battling for government funds hammering out deals with different states
Indifferent politicians
Deuces the budget status quo is really this
Hard-earned equilibrium
This is a good thing ultimately it increased stability
Do we actually have lobbyists to thank for our stable budget
In many respects yeah
It's like a little shout-out to the
The lobbyist
Well I mean I feel like that's okay right don't you think maybe the budget should be their Valentine
President Trump has proposed increasing defense spending by cutting other parts
The budget
Bill says he will have to get through the lobbyists
First
Next up
Income
Security
13% of the budget
Here is Noel
Yes income security so think of this as programs for poor people
It includes a bunch of different things like
The Earned Income Tax Credit
Housing assistance unemployment foster care is a small part of it
I'm going to talk about food stamps which are officially known as
Snap for two reasons
I'm on food stamps were really big
Program usage Spike
During the recession if you look at graphs it's basically like a straight line going up
And he stayed pretty high
More than 40 million people are getting food stamps right now
And I think there's a lot of confusion over who gets them
So it's clear that up
Two out of every three people on food stamps are kids
The elderly or they are.
All of the rest
It's roughly split between people who are working but making very low wages low enough
Qualify for food stamps
And
People who are not working but should be working soon
Because snap comes with work
For the most part if you are able-bodied and you don't have a job
You get cut off from Food Stamps after a couple of months
Interest on the national debt
6% of the budget
You can look at this in two ways
Once interest rates are really low right now
I hope so the government was able to borrow money
Spending on goods and services for Americans great
But you could also say this whole chunk of the budget
Is just the
Interest on all the money we owe
And what we get in return for all this money is
Nothing
Four more seconds
Just feeling awkward
Veterans Affairs
5%
Sally Helm
They provide things like health care and disability benefits for vets
President Trump wants to boost funding for the VA but is proposing Some Cuts including one for disabled vets when they're old
Enough to get Social Security
President Eisenhower try to do something kind of like this in the 50s he was a five-star general so maybe he thought he could get away with it
But he got totally shut down by Congress
International Affairs 1%
Nick Fountain go this goes to operating US embassies and consulates throughout the world
Providing military assistance to allies
Eating developing me everything else makes up about 3% of the budget
Was bringing Justice FBI DEA prisons Homeland Security
Community and Regional development
So we made it through the whole budget
I in 10 minutes and I have to see
The thing that strikes me about the budget
Is it
Half of it more than half of it is just made up by three program
Medicare Medicaid and Social Security and then in the rest
Overwhelmingly the biggest trunk is defense
Until there is this old line that I still love which is the federal government is basically
A big insurance company backed by a large standing on
We really did Cover almost the entire budget like this is almost everything we spend money
Except it's not the whole budget
Gone
There is a part of the budget that is known as the black budget
The black budget
Yes what is the black budget
Jacob we will talk about the Bible come on
Support for Planet Money and the following message come from Squarespace
Squarespace offers a unique domain experience that's fully transparent and simple to setup
Make your next move
By visiting
Squarespace.com
Time to start your free trial
And use offer code Planet Money for 10% off your first purchase
Squarespace
Make your next move
Make your next website
Wright State
Give me the black budget
The black budget I talked to Lindsey Koshgarian who is the research director at the national priorities project and ask her
What it is
So the black budget is
Part of the federal budget
That is
Devoted to National Security it's
Top secret
IMovie says that most of what we know about the black budget
Comes from the Edward Snowden leak
In 2013
So it includes things like the CIA
Secret agent
Strong program
The national
Security Agency and a bunch of other secret agent
Type stuff so this is all
Hidden off the bike so when you took your spreadsheets and spent a week trying to do the math for the show
All this stuff you're describing is not
In those
Spreadsheets not on those pie charts
It's secret money it's secret money
So far for all of this do we know how much
How much money the government spends
But there was kind of an unofficial official number floating around of
Half a billion dollars
And then the Snowden leak came out and we learned that it were
Was a lot more than that
It's about
Billion
Oh that's profound
70 billion epithets
About 2% of the budget
But I mean
That number is from a few years ago and to be honest
We really don't know
How big the black budget
We always love to hear what you think of the show send us an email Planet Money at npr.org or find us on face
Facebook or Twitter
And we have a few people we would like to thank Stephen bisaha Edward soccer
Ashby Lee Bernard roster Tomas Maier and Dorothy Rosen
Car show today was produced by Elizabeth kulas our editors Bryant urstadt
The supervising producer of Planet Money is Alex
Looking for another podcast to listen to check out it's been a minute with Sam Sanders it's a new podcast from the co-host
The NPR politics podcast
Check it out on the NPR one app or wherever you get your podcast
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
And I'm Jacob Goldstein
Thanks for listening
Planet Money intern eduard Saakashvili go
Planet Money is looking for its next internet is paid for information go to npr.org money
Being an intern is incredible and Spotify