There was always something a little odd about Marin Quinn
Big tree Spanish moss it's a small town in Louisiana out in the country
About 1,100 people marinwood means mosquito in Cajun French to get there you Drive West
Baton Rouge across the Mississippi pass through sugarcane fields and cotton fields in their language
Everyone always seem to be related
In a way that was strange
Even for a small
When you greet someone in Maryland
Hey cuz
Hey cuz what's up cuz
Oh cuz what's up cuz
That's Deborah Tilson she grew up in Marin going
I just the thing that made the joke about everybody being cousins so funny
Was that it was actually true
But no one really knew why
It wasn't like there was a founding grandmother founding grandfather who come there first
At least not as far as they knew
It was just this
Series of coincidence
On the night I met Deborah we went to a town hall meeting in Maryland
And afterward we're standing around in the parking lot and we
Bump into this young police officer
Dipper asks him
Are you a heretic
And he said yeah
Anime start talking about people that they know when
Jennifer Nettles
Virginia James sister what's the name of
And I'm hanging out and I'm watching them
And I'm getting eaten alive by mosquitoes
And then I realize what's actually going on in this conversation between Deborah Tilson and the police officer
You didn't know that was your cousin
He didn't know I was
Can I ask you how you feel discovering that you're too newest cousin
This
That's Mandarin
That is married
A very small town that had some big mysteries about its path
Until a year ago when some of those Mysteries
Warsaw
I'm Noel King and today on Planet Money we tell the story of what happens when people in this little town in Louisiana
Figure out how they got to Louisiana
The answer put merengon and thousands of people with roots in Marin Gwen
At the center of a fight
Over had to pay a very old and very complicated death
Let's take a moment to thank and share a message from our sponsor betterment
A smarter way to invest your money
Betterment creates and manages a personalized portfolio for you
Focusing on ease-of-use and lowering taxes
And here's what you might find refreshing
No jargon low fees and full transparency
For a limited time sign up for betterment and you may qualify for a free Canary home security system to help secure your home
Four terms and conditions visit betterment.com Planet Money
The first person from Aaron gwin to learn the truth about Marilyn with Maxine
Trump choose a well-known TV personality in Louisiana
I was a reporter
And morning show host and then a Morning Show anchor
Then a field reporter from there
She lives in Baton Rouge but she grew up in Marin going in the 50s and 60
Her family owned land in town but this was the Jim Crow South
And her dad worked a lot of jobs so that he could work for himself
He was a barber he was a farmer he on the blues Club on Wheelock Lane with a big Spotlight out front so he
Find it was called Hideout nightclub
Kid where you allowed to hang out there
No
Maxine was a very curious cat
She was always pestering grown-ups with Quest
Growing up in the country parents
Don't often sit around
An answer kids questions during the culture
The culture of the country
Is go play
Her big question was
How did the family end up here in Marin
And she was curious because there were these mystery
With the family in Marin when was Catholic
And they were black
And they spoke English and this is a bayou town in Louisiana
Most of the Catholics I knew that were black French speaking
And and
You're from the body area where a lot of people speak
Sprint do you
Dislike no
Is there anybody in your town
No none of the black people speak French
And then there was the story told by older people
Often not long before they died to the next
Maxine heard it from a 90 year old cousin
The story was
They had come from up North
Cymbalta
I was thinking how did they get here
Blacks in travel during those days
It was during slavery
So what does he mean he came from you how to get here
Maxine grew up she left Marin Gwen but she still always wondered
MN once I need a little over a year ago
Maxine's driving out to Mary went to visit her mom
Your cell phone rings
I answered my cell phone
And
Someone says my name is Richard Selene
And I have some information for you
About you a family
Maxine was like okay
But then this guy says a name
Cornelius Hocker
There are five cornelius's in her family
And Hawkins was her grandmother's name
And so Maxine asks him what do you know
And he starts to explain
And as he does
I felt like my car was moving and that I had stopped
Here's the guy who is on the other end of the line
My name is Richard chillini and I'm a software and data executive in Cambridge Massachusetts
Richard is 53 he's a moderate Republican
Richard White
Yes I'm Caucasian
He's also a proud Alum of Georgetown University
The Jesuit college in Washington DC
I look Georgetown I went to Georgetown for to University degrees and I think it's fine Institution
One day in the fall of 2015 he's noodling around online and he sees a story in the student newspaper
The Hoya
Students are protesting an ugly part of Georgetown
In the early 1800s the Maryland Jesuits owned and ran towards
They also owned
Thousands of Acres
And the Jesuits owned about 300
People
Slaves
Schoolworx their Plantation
In the 1830s Georgetown expanded and got itself into debt
It old Banks about $47,000
Shochu Jesuit priests one of them the president of Georgetown struck a deal to save the college
They sold 272 men and women and children
2 Planters from Louisiana
The sale brought in $115,000
In Georgetown
We saved
So which was reading this story
Any gets curious about those people
He wonders
What happened to them after they were sold
Georgetown had already set up a working group to examine its ties
To slavery
Richard wrote to a guy on that car
The guy writes back right away and says
We looked into it
Those people got down on Louisiana and they die
They all immediately succumb to a fever and what he described as
The malodorous swamp world
Of Louisiana
I looked at that email and I thought
That's just not possible
Even the Titanic had survivors
Richard remembers hearing that story at Georgetown back when he was an undergrad in the 80s
But now he realizes
It doesn't really make sense
To write this guy back and says listen
If you don't mind
I'm going to take a look
He goes online and he finds a digital copy of the bill of sale from 1838
With their names
The youngest was William he was 6 months old
The oldest was Daniel he was 80
Robert was sickly and
Steven was lame
Betsy was married to Sam
And here's where curiosity turned into something else
Although Richard has trouble saying exactly what it was
I think it's fair to say I began with a desire to speak with the Dead
About their lives and
What became of them
And so he decided to look for them
And it's only Richard had any experience finding
People
He did what anyone would do
I Googled them
You Google
272 people who are last
C 975 years ago
Yeah no I Google them
I put in
You know Georgetown Jesuit Plantation Slaves Louisiana
And I found them
He found one
On the 1st
Hit
There were a couple paragraphs in a genealogy Journal written by a genealogist
In Washington
State
Her name was Patricia Bayonne John
Patricia was from Louisiana
And she traced her family roots
Back from Louisiana
Back to Maryland
And then back to Georgetown
And in her post was one of the names Richard had seen in the Georgetown archives
A man named Nate
So Richard gets in touch with Patricia and she helps him find another genealogy
Down in Louisiana
Richard calls her and he asked
Do you think we could find out what happened to be
She thought about it there's a long pause and she said yes
We could do that
But you said it would take a lot of time
And a lot of money
So you know it's a Boston entrepreneur I said well
How much time and how much money
And again there was a long pause and she said
You know a hundred hours at $25 an hour
I thought
Heck I could hide that on my credit card from my wife it'll take her 3 months to figure
You know where that $2,500
The genealogist gets to work
Tracing 272 family tree
And after a couple of months the name start to come until they reach from 1838
Right up until the Press
And Richard has a spreadsheet with a hundred and fifty people
Some of them dead
But some of them living
While Richard sits on the name
He feels weird
He's an outsider he doesn't know these people
He's worried if he contacts them they'll wonder why he's poking around
But he says he did get in touch with Georgetown to tell them what he found
You know I got that act very polite
You know responses thank you very much for this information
And I wrote to senior Jesuit priest
I told them
That what we had all been told wasn't true that
The Georgetown slaves could be identified and their descendants were alive today
And was everyone like oh my God Richard you did it
No
He says Georgetown really didn't seem too interested
So in the meantime
Richard wrote to a friend at the New York time
And he said hey
I've got a story for you
A year ago the times ran a story about the Georgetown sale
And from that point on people say it was kind of a
Frenzy
Maxine Crump was profiled in the story
And people from Marin Quincy Maxine Maxine from Maryland in the New York Times
And then there were phone calls and Facebook posts and local TV coverage
When Mom told me about frantically texting her two kids from inside the same house
They were upstairs she was downstairs
To tell them
The mystery of Mary Gwen and this big family had finally been solved
So now people from Aaron gwin understood where they
And for some of them there was relief in that
And there was Pride
But the answer to this mystery
Was terrible
Maxine can't stop thinking about what the journey from Maryland to Louisiana must have been like
When they're
All loaded on this boat it wasn't like
Taking a tour anything when you get a ticket you know where you going
They didn't know where they were going
And I just
Can imagine how frightened the children
Must have been
And she can't stop thinking about how we tell ourselves that slavery so far gone
Mixing to you know how many children Cornelius had
I think six
Do you know if any of them were born
In slavery
Yes
Austin was 10th at the end of slavery
And Austin was
Your great-grandfather
Yes
My grandmother's father it is not far away it is not far away
I spoke to older people in Maryland who remember picking cotton as children
For a few dollars a week
A lot of people in Maryland when are doing just fine
But there are also some very
Very poor
1 and 3 live below the poverty line
You drive around and you see lovely brick houses
And you also see really beat up shotgun
After the New York Times story ran Richard says
Georgetown suddenly became deeply interested in The Descendants
And now that working group on slavery has another task
Figure out what we should do about the
What if anything
Do we owe them
Maxine and Richard meanwhile had become friends
Emily Hayden ID
They wrote an op-ed in the Washington
Timmy said how about
How did anyone who is descended from one of the slaves gets Legacy status if they apply to Georgia
No Legacy status is not a guarantee that you get into George
It's a boot
Say your application is just as good as another student
But your parents are your family went to Georgetown
Won't you get a boost
And if your family has donated to the alumni fund every year that's a bigger booty
Georgetown's working group was deliberating on all of this
Stand in the fall of 2016 Georgetown President John digioia stood in front of a formal group of students and
Professors
Descendants
And he said
Georgetown had decided
How it would start to atone
Do you have a list
The report makes several recommendations that addresses this responsibility
To acknowledge
Our history
And to be honest
At first it kind of seemed like Georgetown was a toning
Two Georges
It was real stuff that your joy was talking about but it was stuff at Georgetown
On campus
Two buildings on campus would be renamed
One of them for Isaac Hawkins
It's one of the enslaved men
Georgetown would strengthen support of its Library
And establish a center focused on racial
Will Justice
And create a memorial
And then president Gioia said something in a way that was so low-key that when I was watching the video at first
I didn't catch it
And some people who were there that day told me
At first they didn't catch it either
Regarding opportunity and access the working group recommends quote
Descendants of those owned by the Maryland province
Receiving advantage
In the admissions Pro
Okay that there was a lot like Maxine and Richard suggestion
Descendants kitten advantage
It's a little boost when they apply
Did Ulysses you know we do that with other students so we will provide
Same
Care and respect
The Descendants
When he got done speaking president digioia took questions from the audience
And there was this
1 Berry
Telling moment
German right behind you
Please introduce yourself
May I please join you
Sure
He's an older guy
He's bald he's got glasses and a red tie
He goes up and he stands beside to Gioia
Uncrate
My name is Joe Stewart and I'm a descender
Of the 272
And
He's holding a piece of paper but he hasn't read from it
He says
We want to collaborate with Georgetown
But this working group
It didn't include any of us
I need to send it
Pandan sold to date
We have not had the privilege
A being a part of the Georgetown University
The family and working with the working group
Nobody is hurt you got to hear from us if reconciliacion is going to take place as it is
It has to
It needs to start at home and you don't start reconciling by alienate
That was last
Fall but I heard the same thing from a lot of
Descendants
They just didn't feel listened to
I met some of them still don't
Georgetown had taken a concrete step for them with this preferential admission status yes
But who all is going to benefit
I actually found a handful of descendants who are applying to George
Remember their descendants all over the country
I talked to a brother and sister from New Orleans
Who I guess
We'll probably get in
They come from a well-heeled family
Are both very good students
But the further you get from City
The deeper you get into the car
The closer you get to Marin Quinn
The harder it becomes
Define Denny
And then on my second to last day in town
I went to visit one of the older dissent
Phyllis
I pulled up to her house and she invited me and there was a teenage girl
Girl sitting in an armchair looking kind of bored
Talk about Georgetown
Sheep
Booted out of that chair and she said
I can go to that college
Lanisha Howard is Miss memes granddaughter
She's 17 she's a High School junior
She's tall and lean she's got a goofy smile and the same brown eyes you see all over Marin
She's going to school in Baton Rouge this year to get a break from small-town life
About a month ago she bumped into her favorite teacher in the hallway
Chino
Cuz I told him last year did I was from America
When he was like all married when
Mosquito town like yeah
He was like oh so you know
Georgetown
They're doing something about descendants of slaves
Sunlight
Least interesting so you
Tell me more about he was like I'm going to get the paper
So he win the class when we got the paper
He gave it to me
He read it to me and he was like you should look into this yourself
It take it to your grandma
Lanisha has always had plans that don't include Louisiana
She's just never known what to do about them
And now here's a teacher telling her about preferential admissions to Georgetown University
And ever since then she's been imagining herself on that camp
What do you picture it being like
Well I
I seen
You know
ICB
She's big and beautiful
You know
People walking around
Acting like mature people
You know
And it's quiet
The wind blowing
Is it beautiful
She's even thought about that
Coming from Aaron gwin
Fitting into Georgetown might not be that easy
I will feel
Like
The outlier on a
Reply
Grow
Like the outlier on a graph
Is that a math term
Yes it is like you have a bunch of data
And you have
All of them
The data on a Lenny's all-in-one space and then they got these feelings out
So there are outliers
You think you'd probably be a bit of an outsider
Yes ma'am
That's not an easy thing to be when you're 17 already
I know
But I mean
If I want Gradle I want to push through it
Not think about it
So ask Lanisha if I can see her report card and she said yeah
First we have homeroom literacy 3
Well that's for the juniors
Destenee
Act English is a
English is an a
This is Spanish 2
I have a
And I understand
Spell algebra 2 is Abby
Pay English trees in a
Chemistry a
Anion chemistry
No way that's a d
Chemistry zaddy Okay so
Some really good grades in there some A's
Some bees
And then he'll need
Toodie's all right so let's talk a little bit about you you're doing the face to do in the face
What's up face
The D's I
The DC says are just not her best subjects
But she says very earnestly
If she gets into Georgetown she'll just
Be better
And she'll do better
Any supplies
She might get in
But if she's like most applicants she will not
Georgetown is one of the most competitive schools in the country
And this preferential admission status
However it's going to be defined
It is not a free pass
So georgetown's offer me be useful to some descendants
Yes absolutely
But it is not useful to those people who are most likely to need help
I asked father Matthew Carnes about
He's a professor at Georgetown and he was on the working group
I told him about Lanisha and he was sympathetic
We're very aware of how vast The Divide is 1 students that have access to the kinds of
Medications that will prepare them to Camden to Georgetown a really Thrive here because
One of our priorities as we want students who can come here and thrives they can really come and do their absolute best were
And be ready to arm to be in the space
Georgetown keep saying
Let us do what we do best
Let us educate
Of course there is another thing that Georgetown could offer
Money
Some of the descendants of brought this up
Richard Sweeney has stayed very involved with the community of
Descendants
And he also talks to people at Georgetown
And he says there are people on both sides who say
This should not
Become about money
Here's what he thinks
You know when people say
It's not about the money
You know one thing for sure
It's only about
This story has only ever been
About the money
And that part is true
This started with money
$115,000
For 272 lives
And what if it ended with my
If an institution or a person
Reason a country wrote a check to somehow atone for slavery and for its Legacy
What would that cost
And who would get paid
And what everyone except
Deborah Tilson the woman who met her cousin in the parking lot in Maryland
I talked to her about this
There is a sense of pride
This is Luke
If you wronged me
I shouldn't have to come to you and ask you
You know
You call me I'm Tim's hey look you know hey I got something for you
Next week we go back to Georgetown and back to Louisiana
To talk about money
Coming up we'll have a preview of next week's episode
Supportive podcast and the
The following message come from Pitney Bowes providing technology that helps retailers turn Us online business
Today our Global e-commerce Solutions enable retailers to sell online
I'm in 220 countries and territories
Pitney Bowes the Craftsmen of Commerce to visit Pitney Bowes. Com Craftsman
We'd love to hear your thoughts about today show you can email us Planet Money
Npr.org
Or you can find us on Twitter or Facebook
Please show was produced by Sally helm
Sally thank you
Bryant or status Planet Money Alex goldmark produces a show
Couple people we want to thank
The first and best reporting on the Georgetown sale was done by Rachel swarns of the New York Times
If you want to read more about this the times continues to have excellent rolling coverage of the story
The genealogist in Louisiana who worked with Richard Selene is Judy Riffel
Thanks to Professor Adam Rothman at Georgetown University
If you're looking for something else to listen to check out up first
It's a new podcast from NPR and it's a daily new show
It's about 10 minutes long and it comes out every weekday morning so when you wake up check out up
First you can get it at npr.org podcast
On the NPR one app or wherever you get your podcast
I'm Noel King thanks for listening
Here's a preview of next week's show
This is doable
This math is doable
Doable the data is out there if the numbers are huge but they're not