The financial crisis was the biggest economic event we will see in our life
At least let's hope it is
And it's not entirely over every day we are still dealing with the aftermath of it
And there are still so many
Questions that I have about why the financial crisis happened the ways in which he responded to it with the consequences still might be
There is only one person in the world
Really who can answer this why
Hi
Is Ben Bernanke
Glad to be here
Ben Bernanke
The former chairman of the federal
When the whole economy
Was falling apart
Ben Bernanke was the man who had to steer the ship
His book the courage to act is out
Paperback this week
It's a journey through the whole financial crisis all of the major events in
Check it out it's an amazing book tour
And we brought Ben Bernanke here to ask him some of the questions that we still have about the financial
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I've Stacey Vanek Smith today on the show
Talk to Ben Bernanke we'd like to say a quick thanks
You ain't share a message from one of our sponsors State Farm
State Farm is much more than just an insurance company
They're also committed to making a positive impact in the communities they serve
One way is through neighborhood of good a program connecting people who want to make a difference with causes looking
For local volunteers discover over 31,000 social causes listed at neighborhood of good.com
It starts hurting the power of caring to the act of doing
State Farm here to help life
Go right
There's a question I have always wanted to ask Ben Bernanke
Deluxe Princeton to go to the Federal Reserve in 2002 work under then chairman Alan Greenspan and became the chairman
One of the FED himself in mm
At the height
Of the housing
Bernanke was a really well-known scholar of the Great Depression
Affect his studies informed a lot of the ways in which
What you responded to the financial
Crisis
But there's something I've always wondered
You are scholar of the Great Depression
Certainly very
In tune with the 17 like you were in the right place at the right time
Why didn't you see this coming
Well anyways to financial crisis was a standard
Financial Panic what do Financial Panic is
Is a situation where people
Lose confidence
Into the banking system or the financial system generally
Start
Pulling out their deposits in the banking system
For example
That's a traditional
Problem in link run exactly
We thought
And I say we I mean basically everybody
Thought
That
That wasn't going to happen again because
In particular
Bank deposits are insured
And so people don't have any inside up to go run pull their money out of banks when I lose coughing
What's the banks
That was wrong
Went when things got bad enough
And prices of all assets were collapsing
And
Nobody wanted to hold even very
Safe
Assets
Other than most safe
Then a tweet we had runs
And they were again
Conceptually very similar
The bank runs of the 19th century or the 1930s
But instead of it being people lining up
Take your deposit out of the bank's it was
Electronic run
So that the
The Panic phenomenon was very much part of this
And what's the panic.
Out of control then
Everybody is
Hunkering down or selling assets
As quickly as they can
And the financial system comes to the brink of
Collapsible
We did understand that
There were problems of the subprime mortgage Market no sense of things that we did not see
Was that it could turn into a broad-based
Panic rev was losing confidence in financial system and trying to pull their money out as fast as possible
We didn't see that coming
There was always this mystery around why the banks were bailed out rather than the home
Why was it the right move to bailout the banks
AR View
Was that
You know that potential system collapses the economy collapses
And we needed to stabilize the banks in order to get
The system
Natural system stable and then that would lead us to a situation we can help the economy recover
Saint that was true
At least we know once the crisis
Began once we get in to see the
Problems emerging least we had a strategy in the strategy was
Central banks
For 300 years have been the so-called lender-of-last-resort there there
Provide
Liquidity
Try to help stabilize a financial system that's what the Fed was set up for 1913 what's the stabilizers natural
We felt that
It wasn't a question of bailing them out because we cared about
Wall Street executives
And I was an academic I came from
Small town in South Carolina never worked on Wall Street
But I knew enough about economic history to know that a financial collapse is going to lead to an economic collapse and we had to do
What are we had to do
The stop that
So that was that was critical
But actually
Could work in done probably but actually the resistance to it came mostly from Congress
The origins of the Tea Party supposedly came from
Opposition not to be I had the banks but opposition to bailing out
So-called profligate
Borrowers
Yeah people who taking irresponsibly together
It was actually became popular and and Congress
Put a lot of restrictions on what the treasury could do and I know it's certainly not the case that Treasury
Ignored homeowners they tried very hard
And every time I could go
Whatever reason to the White House
Did that time President Obama say what are we doing for all Motors had to do it was just a
A tough challenge quickly again
Since Congress I put the significant limitations on how
Money could be used
How bad could it have gotten
That was something I always want
Well it's hard to know
But
Council economic advisers in the in the White House
Did an analysis of the behavior of the US economy
In the months after leaving brothers and compared it to the 1929-1932 1931
And in 2008 was worse
I said
Meaningfully worse
The Nike 29 in terms of
Declining
Employment declining
Industrial production and so on
So it's hard to know and I can say well suppose it was only a 25% chance
Another Great Depression would you have acted then
I think I think there's a case that even if you weren't certain.
If you wanted to avoid
That risk
But
To be honest with you I mean I was one of the people
When I went to Congress
In the fall 2018 said look we got to do something
Because
If we could just natural system collapses the rest of the economy is going to come down with it
I was one of the people who was
Most pessimistic about what
The effects might be on
The US economy
I was not pessimistic enough
It felt the economy collapse even more quickly than I was fearing it
And end
Their response was really dramatic
So I mean I remember when the
Dow Jones
I remember at one point the thought going through my mind like
The market connection
She go to zero
They lost 6000 points there only 6000 points left
And I I remember
Feeling like it was such a
Such a kind of dark really frightening time
Is it really sort of felt like things were
Falling apart
What was
Like
For you during that time just like
Getting up every morning and it was a very scary time
The stock market wasn't going to go to zero it didn't go to zero even in the Great Depression
That's true for a while
But the economy was was
In free-fall as I mentioned and
The who knew what the bottom was was that
But
Once we had a plan we had a general strategy my
My focus was only psychologically my focus was
What do I have to do today what what do we have to accomplish today
What are the next steps
Biblical one day at a time
Strategy if I tried looking ahead too far it was
Too much uncertainty
But you know it
Really taking it one step at a time to get us back to
More stable
Situation
Did you stick to your
Normal routine then or did you
Well there's some periods during to physically during the hives
The crisis when I would
Sleep on my sofa
My office
No there's some weekends where we were dealing with
A big firm that was
In serious trouble in
It would be conference calls all night in
Trying to figure out
And what we could do and
We only had so many hours
Deb
What did you eat
Set the time a lot of junk
Don't be so kind of thing you know but
Yeah I know I mean I remember just at that time feeling like the whole country was kind of
Looking at you
You were like the
Countries therapist for a
But there was
Also a lot of dramatic
The drama it was not entirely without purpose
Part of the psychological and you want to get people
More confident than
And they want
Believe that the FED is taking action needed to get
Connie back on track
So I can get part was important to and like the theater of it
There was some theater to it
I would said that
Central Banking monetary policy is
90% talking 2% tax
Like 90% of the job is that a lot of it is that true
A lot of it is a lot of it is a lot of it is about
Convincing people that you'll do what you say you're going to do and that you will take whatever steps are necessary to ask about what
With all the Senate
A testimony that you had to give
One of the
Lines of questioning that I remembered that stuck out of my head was from Ron Paul I pulled the clip if you don't mind we can just play it
And histories against
I mean history is on the side hard money
If you look at it
Stable prices you have to look to the only historic sound money that's lasted more than a few years
Fiat money always in
Gold is the only thing where you can stable prices
Now you're correct that there are relationships obviously between the dollar and domestic inflation
In a relationship between the money supply and domestic inflation
But those are not perfect relationship
They're not exact relationships and
Given a choice we have to look at the
Inflation rate domestic inflation rate now I understand that you would like to see a gold standard for example but
Is really something for Congress
Who sings paint
They were fairly painful
For both good and bad reasons
The bad reasons why they think there was
Some unwarranted
Antagonism in part at least some members of
Congress of
But on the other hand
It was also the case that
You know people were very concerned about what was happening what was
What was happening to the economy what was happening
What the Fed was doing and it was my job
It wasn't always most Pleasant thing in the world but baby
Important part of my job.
Explain
Two members of Congress and
Through them to the publican
Media and the
Markets
What we're doing while we're doing it and how we saw things unfolding
I testified before you the house or the Senate something like 80 times
Oh my gosh
I had to try to remain common and certainly
Part of the
Job is
The project
Make people feel more confident about what you're trying to do
So
We would
First it would always be a written test
Which was sort of layout
The main points I want
Macon so that had to be written and
Consultation with staff
Bloody Disgusting about every word that goes into those because you guys have a meeting that goes for half a day over
The word predominantly
Is that right one word
Often
Sweat
The details in terms of
Which word are using because Marcus would say okay
They said the economy is growing moderately rather than modestly that must mean x y and z
So it was important to try to get to
Wording as accurate as possible and
You know
People say that the FED speeches can be kind of
Stephen
Encounter formulaic and there's a reason for that
Yeah but this communication going on in terms of
Exactly how the
Issues are laid out in
X words for using someone
I remember at one point you
Say that you're in a meeting at the fed and you sort of offhandedly
Ask almost a rhetorical question and
I think later in the day you get like a presentation with the bibliography and everything answering your
This was before I was Jeremy this is when I was just a governor on the board
And I
There was a
Presentation by the staff
And I was used to being an academic
Before that an engine to cause trouble
And so I post a hypothetical question I didn't realize it
Did the FED staff
Actually answering the question after that I try to be much more careful in
When I post a hypothetical good training for being there
Like every single thing you say
Market moving
We're at all so it also is
Everyone is a real
Privileges
Fed chairman or on the Fit board
Is it the staff are so strong
I had what what I came there the FED in 2002 for Direct
Princeton I had about 10
Former students
On the stand really and so their lot of folks there who I knew and already gotten a bad grade
No no not those people
Is the Fed less powerful than everybody thinks
When is it
I think it is I mean
So
Monetary policy is a powerful tool
But it can only do certain things
You know for example
People are concerned in the US economy today about slow productivity growth
They're concerned that the distribution of income
The concerned about the fact that participation rates among
Prime age workers are are lower here than other country
A lot of real problems in our economy
End the Fed
With this one tool monetary policy and I really can't address those kinds of
So
For a lot of the issues that would be too although I mean well it but it would have basically Hindu
First decan
Try to keep inflation close to the fed's Target which is
They've been pretty successful in doing
What about the target inflation rate cuz I know you were trying to hit 2% and and
During your term you weren't able to hit it
That always confused me why
Why weren't you able to hit it
It seems like you had all the all the tools
The reason is that
The main way in which the Fed
Effects inflation released
What are the main ways
Is by getting the economy at the Full Employment so that the pressure on
Labor markets in the economy tends to give extra impetus to wages and prices
That's the mechanism
So the FED in order to get inflation where once it is basically had to get the economy back
To wear watch
And that that's what's happening now we seeing
The labor market
Close to full employment with starting to see some upward pressure on wages
Inflation is
Rising very slowly
Very much in a controlled way
But it is now a meal
Moving very slowly towards the
The 2% Target.
Is there anything that you kind of keep your eye on now something that you watch carefully
As an economic indicator
Directions
My predecessor Alan Greenspan who stood watch all kinds of interesting
Obscure indicators
Oh really yeah
Apparently he would look at men's underwear sales on the grounds
On the ground
People don't buy new underwear when they're feeling economically strapped
So
Things like that
Maybe true I don't I can't verify
But I'm working ventralight
I no longer have
All the
Cats after
To help me anymore so I'm
More like a civilian
Now when you pose rhetorical question it just hangs out there
When you were in maybe the toughest position during one of the toughest points in the US economy
Is there anything that you
Miss about that time
Well I am no longer the fat of course
And
I enjoyed
Many things about the fat a lot of great people
I was really interesting to have
So many smart Economist around who can help me think about
Economic issues
But I surely wouldn't want to be in that kind of situation again
Particularly
So much uncertainty in
All the political blowback and we were getting so
I'm happy to be a civilian I'm happy to be
On the outside looking in
And I wish my successors the best of luck
Ben bernanke's book the courage to act is out in paperback
This week next step Bernanke Goes to Hollywood
For real
Stick around
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Delta Airlines
Offering 100%
Free entertainment with over a thousand hours to choose from including up to 300 movies all available on the
Delta Studio
What is your favorite television show
I'm mostly a baseball fan like to watch baseball games but I was actually
Hey an extra my wife and I were extras on The Big Bang Theory
You are extras I think I've seen all the Big Bang Theory episode where
Howard finds out that he's going to be a father
Yes wait you are on that one
So they go to celebrate
Ian
The other guys
Karaoke karaoke bar right
Customers in the karaoke bar are you serious
Yeah I'm serious
And we actually interact slightly with Sheldon
Hey how you doing
Really really good time we were there in California weed really good time
You don't spending the day in Washington film
It's a good show
We always love to hear what you think of the show
Send an email Planet Money at npr.org or you can find us on Twitter or Facebook
And if you're looking for something else to listen to NPR pop culture happy hour is just put together their annual preview of Summer movie
He will tell you which films to catch the summer and which ones you can
Define pop culture happy hour on the NPR one app
Or wherever you get your podcasts
Today Show was produced by Elizabeth glass
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Thanks for listening