If you years ago Argentina was in the city
Situation that might sound a little bit
The country had just elected
Charismatic populist president who said she was going to fix
The Argentina
Her name was Cristina Kirchner
She said
Argentina isn't making fee
We need to make
And so she had this idea
She's going to bring manufacturing from Asia and Mexico
To Argentina
Indian population
Tegan must be confessed
Looking dresses
Crusher started pressuring companies to make things in Argentina
Huge taxes on things that were manufactured overseas
Axes like 30 + 40%
And for some other things including certain kinds of electronics a Kirchner went even further
Are there she said you cannot import these
At all if you want to sell them in Argentina
You have to make them
In Argentine
Hugo bonifacci nice August 1st
Sorry
Sorry for my English
Stacy
Know your English sounds great
Is not true
Hugo was a systems engineer at a Manufacturing Company in a remote part of Art
It was it was a pretty small operation about
60 employee
And then right around 2010
Give or take
The president of Argentina makes this law that says
All these things have to be made in Argentina
And suddenly Hugo's world is like
Wheatley trans
Overnight these giant shipping containers full of parts
And Machinery fall this new Manufacturing
Start showing up
Outside his office
We don't come water house
To do Astoria
So all the parts would arrive and you didn't have anywhere to put them
Yes Yes Y'all right right
Some people are in your house you have a space
So did he put
Machinery in his house he said no he was
Never actually came close he said it came
A lot of those containers full of equipment had
Cell phone
Heart smartphone
Because one of those things that Kirchner said you cannot import it all has to be made in Argentina was
Cell phones
Some companies like apple in the iPhone for example
Would not play ball meaning you just Apple doesn't sell iPhones in an iPhone in Argentina
Okay but other company said okay
We will give it a try including the company that made
Blackberries
Honestly I didn't even know BlackBerry still existed in Chicago
He's dead
People still use MySpace anymore
But this was back in 2011 and was a hot
Phone is the most
Popular phone in art
Celebrities and politicians were all carrying blackberries around
He was kind of like the It phone
Xi'an Cantina
Everybody was crazy for Blackberry
Blackberry was on
Icon
At the time of blackberries were assembled in Mexico in
I'm hungry what are the parts were made
But Argentina was a really important market for
It's a lot of phones there
Increase your cell phone ban was costing them more than a hundred million dollars a year
So Blackberry agreed to try and make phones in Argentina
Partnered up with Hugo's company
And some leave this company in this little town
Was responsible for making
All of the blackberries for all of Argent
Millions of
Production
Explode
Explorer Stacy
Amazing
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Today on the show Making Argentina great again
What happens when a country tries to undo globalization and bring in manufacturing from overseas
We follow the argentines Blackberry through an ocean of logistical hurdles
Political posturing and free market forces
Quite literally
The ends of the Earth support for Planet Money And The Following
Message come from veteran
A smarter way to invest your money
Betterment combined time-tested investing principles with the transparency and ease-of-use you expect
Great technology
Focusing on lowering fees and taxes
And here's what you might find refreshing
Betterment really cares that you reach your financial goals
And that's why they keep their fees low
Planet Money listeners can get one month manage free
For more information visit betterment.com Planet Money
The Blackbird story is really part of a much much bigger story about
President Cristina
And how she
Came into office with this plan to really control the entire Argentina con
Turn all the dials on the account
She wanted
Exports to change an Imports to change and she started making all these rules like there was one that said like okay if your company and you
Import stuff you also have to ask
Sports writers like we got to export stuff
She went up with these ridiculous things like there was actually a portion
NRG
Your personality got import Porsche
So what this guy did was like he's like well my family has a Vineyard so I guess
I'll get into the wine business and he starts shipping wine overseas just so he can import Porsche
Mitsubishi Galant
Peanuts and Subaru started exporting tons and tons of
Chicken
Future
No one Christian would tell companies you have to make stuff in Argentine
You didn't always stop there
She would sometimes get very
Specific
In case of blackberry should a very particular part of Argentina in mind
West Nickel and blackberries South America up
Operations
The law was that you had to manufacture it down to the very southern tip of Art
Tierra Del Sol
Just makes you want to set up shop there as manufacturing hub
Fire
Do you know if we go is an island in the south of Archer
It is actually wear boots
4 in
It is manufacturing hub
Is one of the most remote places on Earth and it has a really
Harsh environment
It's cloudy all the time. The wind is always ripping through
It is hard to get to
The roads are terrible there are many fights in or out
Argentines call it
The end
Of the Earth
There's some colorful language I don't use it
Fairview out if it did that that just talked about how far away
Scared of regulars from the rest of the world is really in the middle of nowhere
It would be like if Apple suddenly had to make iPhones on a little island off the
Alaska
What was Nicole says there was a logic
Wasn't an economic logic it was
Political life
That was one of the
Population basis that was really supportive of
Cristina Fernandez de Kirchner
Help her get elected in so she was
If you wanted to pay back those constituents and
Provide jobs for them and then says she is really forcing this issue
I totally went up
Setting up shop in Tierra del Fuego and working with Hugo's company
Animal Hugo has spent his entire career working in fact
Uses blackberry's operations were just
On another love
The factory said was like a work
Are there was a
Queen room with all these very sophisticated monitors that would like
Keep track of tiny part of
Dust
There was state-of-the-art Machinery there was really high security
Ben 10 all the stuff getting it all set up took
Like a year
And even once they had the factory they were missing
Another key
Sing another key element
People
They needed like 2000 worker
Come in and make all these phone
They start having to work
True people from halfway across the country
Free to come move to this town to work in the fact
Hugo says that was not easy
You know they are the weather conditions here are very very hard
Okay for the people
I know she's dead
Salary
Yo so in order to get people to come to Tierra del Fuego to fill all these jobs they had to offer
Really high salary
Very high salary yes
Three times with that job would
Pay in another part of
Not to mention really great pensions
They make all these changes they recruit all these workers and within a year Hugo says the manufacturing companies working for
Goes from 60 workers to more than 2000
And
2 years after Argentina cell phone ban
First Argentine Blackberry rolls off the line
Eagles still remembers the MoMA
Yes yes you are everybody
Walking the line CD first really everybody was crowded around to see it
Yes everybody
This was a moment of Triumph for president
She had created thousands of jobs
Good high-end manufacturer
They're creating this product that everybody loved and it's super high-tech
So the moment this comes off the line like all of the politician
Come out to see it
Singapore
Diputado Sunday
Many many politics A-OK
We want to see the Blackberry want to
Take a picture when they open at 8 on Sunday
BlackBerry
Everybody wants
You got this picture
Do you send a campaign Politico
Campaign
Including the president herself
Cristina Kirchner made a big announcement about the first Argentine BlackBerry
People with crazy
In the news clip we found for speech therapy
For 4 minutes
Just cheering
Everybody's waiting Arjun
Flags
Down and dancing
Gracias companeros
Crusher starts Deliverance really
Passion Spa
About how Argentina is going to be
A great Center for manufacturing
About bringing jobs in from overseas
And then there's this amazing MoMA
Krishna holds the record for the crowd to see
Does book do you know what this is
This is the
First Argentine BlackBerry
Made in Tierra del Fuego
Meetup
7 Cal pistol
BlackBerry
This is an incredibly
Siding mold
First Hugo and for all of his thousands of coworker
Focusrite they have
They have done this miraculous thing in Tierra del Fuego to have made this state-of-the-art
He wasn't to get a little carried away at one point
He was giving a press to her and you so proud of this phone that he told one of the reporters if you can find
Any difference
When this phone that we made in Argentina and a Blackberry made anywhere else
I will give you this phone is
I still got my boss
Say Google I see you
Luckily no one was able to find it
Blackberry Argentina was doing
Great and you know it wasn't just black
Rewrite these new rules that the president put in place
Grove okay
Kinds of manufacturing to Tierra del Fuego
Laptops flat screen TVs microwaves air conditioners
Everything you can think of was being manufactured in Tierra del Fuego
The populations growing stores are opening money is flowing in you know people are driving around in Range Rovers
And the rest of Argentina was doing pretty well too in fact the New York Times And The Guardian published editorials about
Great job Krishna was doing
When Helen called it the turnaround Tango
Terrible headlines
Spell
Every time it's got to be the tango
The point.
Jacob is it Christmas plans like
Strong-arming companies to start producing things in this remote part of Argentina
It was working
My Spidey senses
Just tingling I feel like it's not going to
Keep working
There were a couple
What problems so first of all this setting up to the long-term
And so by the time the first Blackberry rolled off
The line
The model was 2 years old
In the world of cell phones you know it's like
Totally out
And in addition to that it was
Expensive
In fact the Blackberry Argentina was twice as expensive as newer Blackberry models in the US
So now president person who set up this you know manufacturing Miracle has a new problem
She's made companies manufacture phones in Argent
But you cannot make people in Argentina buy those phones
And this created a very interesting business opportunity for some enterprising argentines
I talked to one guy who smuggled blackberries and Argentina would hide them in pairs of shoes in his suitcase or stuff them into his
Socks before he walked through large intestine
Well you know you have
Soccer socks
Baseball socks now those that are quite tight over the knee socks
Yeah so you just like kind of put them if they be like against your leg
Outlook how many can you carry in your sock
How many you think you can carry in your sock
Why I've never tried but like I don't know what
4 in each stock is that too much
You could probably do 4
Feel like you have 8 phones in your socks
I don't trust this guy one day
You saw a little business going Jacob he would buy blackberries for
For $200 a piece in the US
And you would sell them on a website in art
For $400
And that was still cheaper than the arch
BlackBerry
Was also a better phone
Cheaper and better
How many phones overall
Did you sell juice
Collie
Morning
Prophet
$10,000
You can't afford to not smuggle phone
And that surprisingly with
Enterprising argentines walking through customs with their socks with a phone
Sales of the original Argentine BlackBerry
Started to drop
Why would you get a worse phone for more money
And West Nickel but I work for Blackberry said the Tierra del Fuego manufacturing plant
Started making less
Unless I can
They just came to a point where the business case was unjustified
We just couldn't afford to do it
Less than 2 years after Cristina Kirchner hellbat first Argentine BlackBerry
Up to the cheering crowd
The last
Argentine Blackberry roll.
Hugo bonneval Cheney remembers Atwell
How did you feel when Blackberry left
Wilson OTC for us
Kamal Khan
How old am I
So it left a bad taste in your mouth
Yes yes that's why you stop automatic
Bitter
Bitter taste
Crushers government had invested 23 million dollars
In the Black Parade
Not to mention $6,000 per worker
Per month
That was all up in smoke
And Hugo watch this company go from mm workers
Down to 600
Last year he got called into the bosses office
And was told
Your job is
What's Valley exchange date
My feeling because
Call Sierra
In this company is not going to work if they say
Yeah
Betty botter
Birthday the people
Is very angry everyday
The people is very worried every day you are thinking about who will be there next
This is happening at factories all over Argent
Sales are going down people are getting laid off
And more broadly the Argentine economy is
Starting to fall
All of kirchner's economic controls
Unraveled kind of olive
It got really bad
Inflation hit 40% 40% in a year
Yeah and Prices rose for everything
Food prices more than doubled
And a lot of companies that have been strong-armed into setting up shop
In Argentina started pulling out
Them to get a sense of where the story about Argentina Falls infertile
Greater economic contacts
We talked to Eduardo Levy yet
He's an economist in Argentina
He says the biggest problem with kirchner's
With protectionism in general
Is it while the government was spending money
Energy propping up Argent
Manufacturing
Wasn't investing that money in areas
Where Argentina
Could compete
On a global scale
Movie kind of like if Mozart has been all this time and money on ice
Do Yeti says this set the whole country back
So we're losing time we're losing
Badly needed time
Sooner or later we'll need to leave the protection but by the time we do that we have lost 10 years in which we could have
We would have a chance
And you know there are sectors where Argentina is a competitive exporter where they make
Stuff the rest of the world once you know
Beef
And wine
Biofuels these are all strong industry
So
This is like problem a right they've been
Putting all their money in the wrong Indus
And then you have problem be
Now you have created all these
Is jobs
That are economically not sustainable
So put some point you know that protectionism is going to go away
And all of these people who got these new jobs are going to be
Exact
An Argentina elected a new president who ran on this platform of wanting to get rid of a lot of
Open up trade with the rest
The world
But if he
He does that
Places like Tierra del Fuego plays with the whole economy has been built around these protectionist policies
Could collapse
Hugo bonify Cheney did manage to get a new job about a month after
He was laid off
From his old one but he says he's been luckier than most
And he's really worried about a lot of his friend
In Tierra del Fuego there have been huge strikes
And some workers pensions haven't been paid
In months
Manufactured
Things stuff
Still really expensive
In Argentina
A basic car cost
$50,000
A middle-of-the-road phone cost more than $1,000
And in Argentina you still
Can I buy a knife
Support for this project
Cast of the following message come from the Acton School of Business and Austin Texas acting for pears on tree
Open doors to lead extraordinary lives and build world-changing businesses if you are ready to pursue
Do your entrepreneurial calling get started today at Acton MBA. Org
Flash NPR
What other stories do we do on Planet Money
Tell us by emailing us at Planet Money at npr.org
Or you can reach us on Facebook or Twitter
Car show today was edited by Bryan tour set and produced by Sally how Nick Fountain and our intern Daniela
And we are looking for our next in
Vitamin E and turn Daniela Vidal tell the people why they should
Reply reply because you get to work with all of these wonderful smart people
The Empire State Building
Conference room
Do it internship is paid
A few months along the great way to come hang out and figure out what week
We have a couple people we'd like to thank special thanks to Alexandra star jasmine Gars and Matthew Bannock
You looking for something else to listen to check out ask me another
It's a quiz show with puzzles and word games
Trivia
You can play along on the NPR one app at npr.org podcast or wherever you get your
I'm Jacob
And I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Thanks for listening
When Helen called it
The turnaround Tango
Cursive y
Why the beef
Call it the Malbec miracle