Wherever you go in the world the Irish
Bar the Irish Pub
Looks pretty much the same
Dark wood smoking mirrors
And of course
Lots of old guys joking around
Any Irish in you
I'm half-irish
My mother's have shoes
This is my neighborhood Irish bar in Brooklyn
Will Ferrell
It's filled with retired police officers like Jack Scott
Andy's friend Randy Mancuso
Who works in the engine room of the Staten Island Ferry
I think women look in handshake
Old is 20 guys ain't going in that joint
We don't
Brown women coming here we don't
Is this a place to pick up girls for dating no it's not
Now the mystery of barrels to me is that it works at all
It doesn't
Why very hard to be genuinely Irish they serve bud and Bud Light in
Giant styrofoam cups
And I didn't see anyone at the time
Drinking Guinness anywhere
Is Irish because it was started by an Irish
A long time ago
I was here when I cut the ribbon in 33 all right choice open the place
Not true
Heels
Everybody knows everybody
Irish bars like this one spread around the world
And they feel pretty much the same because
Irish immigrants were copying this
Hazy memory
What pubs were like back in Ireland
Cute America the simply
Put their names on the front of it made the beer cheap
And called it a day
But one Irishman had a better idea
But if you can just
Figure out what made an Irish Pub work
Part we produce it and sell it
You can put an Irish pub in a container
Stick a label on it
And ship it anywhere
Hello and welcome to Planet Money on Robert Smith
Play Michelle we're going to knock back a bunch of beer and we're going to ponder the Eternal question
Is this an awesome borrower
The story of the man who designed a thousand Irish Pub
We'd like to say a quick thank you and share a message from one of our sponsors
State Farm
State Farm is much more than just an insurance
They're also committed to making a positive impact in the communities they serve
One way is through neighborhood of good
A program connecting people who want to make a difference with causes looking for local volunteer
Discover over 31000 social causes listed at neighborhood of good.com
And start turning the power of caring
A Buick
State Farm
Here to help life
Go right
Before we meet The Mastermind of the Modern Irish Pub
We thought we should experience his work
First ham
Pub crawl
We already checked fails off the list next stop
What is the newest pubs in New York
A pub so exclusive
You have to submit to a full body scan
Close to it
This is a general boarding cost to order many passengers travel on Virgin Atlantic flight vs46
We should tell people where we are where are we
Where in
Terminal 4
JFK Airport
The most Irish place to be
I've never felt more at home
We invited along a genuine Irish person Siobhan Brett
She's also an economics reporter
Agreed to be our guide on this part of the crawl
Siobhan wants to see the tageen pub in JFK Airport because this right here
Is a little island of authenticity
Any vast
Generic waist-length I believe this is the Irish band Maroon 5
Sitting behind us
Okay music aside so I said that the place is doing something
Much more subtle and smart
Slapping white an Irish name
Cleburne airport bar
Because it don't just look Irish
Everything in its place
From Ireland
From the dusty bottles on the shelves to the massive chairs
The furniture is also heavy duty in that steps
Tell tale sign I guess
Get these chairs weigh like a thousand pounds
Tables
Jabon recently wrote an article for eater.com that Trace back all of us
Stop
Two man named Mel McNally
And his business the Irish Pub company
AB Dublin
There's pop company finds people who want to start pubs around the world
An offer to sell them a whole package of Irish Magic
From the distressed vinyl floors
The pattern ceiling
Everything they sell has a story and everything is produced
In Ireland
And I'll send it to you in a giant shipping container
That's for selling point but if you want to really nail it
Come to us and
We're going to
Give you all of the components
That will give you an accurate and exact
Representation of what an Irish Pub is authenticity in a box
And they've been enormously successful Mel McNally has helped create
Thousands of Irish Pub
All the more unique but
There are very strict rules and things
Lakes you can order a Victorian style
Wrath
Ornate stained glass
Or you can order a pub that rips off the Irish cottage style
That's a cozy place with old Nick nacks on the shelves
Makes you feel like you're relaxing in an Irish home
And not
Where you really are
Baseball tee to get a fire for boys
Next up on the pub crawl Dublin
Or Frost back to the radio Studio to call Dublin
To call
Malik McDowell
How old were you when you first went into an Irish Pub
WW2
People bring their little Irish people live in Irish Pub
Nearly Christian the movie regression to be taken to vote later anyway
Male grew up in pubs but he
Really give him a serious thought until he was an architect
After school
It was a 1970
He and his fellow orchid
Come up with an idea for a final-year project
So what they decided to do is something
Before they decide we are going to write a paper on something
We already know a ton about
Are we
The designs of Dublin Pub
As an analysis
How did you decide that
Over a few pints
We thought it'd be good crack
We thought we'd have a good time doing it
It was frowned upon initially
Why is it frowned upon to be not think of it as architecture
That was the word obviously by the tutors that this was a bit of a
Let's come together
Just have a good time
They took it really seriously they hit all the famous pubs in Dublin they brought along their sketch pads and their tape
Measures
We were meticulous we
We looked at the craftsmanship
The artwork
A stained-glass work etc
We would say what makes this poem
Different
They quickly discovered that the very best Irish pubs were obeying a set of unspoken rules
The first rule was
No matter where you are in the bar you should be able to see the alcohol you should have a view of the center
Of the bar the second rule
Is that the space
How to be divided up in a really shrewd way
Babies tiny little rooms called
Schnucks
Time give me some privacy weather
Drink Mail system
Cool things about how you divide
The space even the Long Bar would usually be broken up into segments
Separated by the screen
These screens we Golem or dividers
Hope people together in twos and fours and Eights
And they communicate and they get to meet each other while they're having more quiet intimate time
The rest of the crowd is sort of
Funneled into the center of the Irish bar Mingo and congregate
Can be noisy and have fun
Right in the center
Is is one of the focal points of a bar
First Student
You start to see that the
These things that we might not even notice in a bar or actually directing RB
Behavior
They're creating exactly social
They're determining how my night at the pub
Will be
Exactly
Obviously male in his fellow architecture students Ace their final project
But more than that Mel realize that he was now probably
The number one expert in traditional Irish Pub design
No idling already had enough
But I'm starting to think that the rest of the world did not
Somail
Began to get on some planes wherever some eager entrepreneur wanted to open a traditional Irish Pub
And show them how it's done and done
In almost any country
Try me
Kazakhstan
I'm doing one in Kazakhstan at the moment
Give me another one
Hong Kong
Hong Kong Inn menu
The Ivory Coast
Interesting enough my son
Has nearly signed a contract for one there
Melton obit if you got the spaces and the details right there was no place to awkward or too remote
Milk came up with a really clever way to make sure that no one could just replicate his designs cheaply in a factory
3 in China
He convinced Pub owners around the world in order to build a truly authentic
In order to get the Irish Magic
You had to buy everything from iron
Where to buy everything from Mel McNally
The chairs
The lights the curtain
And in the interest of full Irish employment
He highly recommends in Irish
Bartender
And a real Irishman to hell
Help install everyday
Mel says I can run you $300,000
Maybe half a million dollars for typical Irish Pub although
He does say it goes up in
The Millions
Tickly fancy run
Particularly difficult place
And he said if you really want to go see how it all comes together
He has a container of Irish stuff on its way straight from Dublin to a pub in
Connecticut
So we went there to go check it out
This'll be the last stop of the pub crawl and that is where we meet
Darren Fagan
Who works for Melmac
Now he handles all of his
Us business
Darren Smith the morning checking the shipment for life
So there is an it's a full size crate
Weight of 40 foot container
So it went from Dublin to Liverpool Liverpool to New York
Any inside is everything Darren will need to
We do
Is pop now I should say this is already working
Irish Pub
Part of the chain called Seguin metal originally designed it
20 years ago
But the owners wanted to be up to
The basic layout of the pub will remain the same
It already perfectly conforms to the male McNally rule about
Segmented spaces
Every Patron in the pub.
82 bar no matter where the person is sitting
And it's still really easy to pair off into
Smaller
Books and snug
But other than that the entire inside is going to get nude
Decorations
Furniture
And there's another male McNally real for that too
It's very haphazard he uses the word higgledy piggledy
Notice bottles
Here in like there's some weird plate up over there
And the photos are sort of
Haphazardly arranged
But you're not so there's a deliberate in it
Recommence a reflection of Irish families wear over generations and generations they all live in the same house but the true nothing away
Celebrity went to the Shelf
The thing they're going for is Irish Porter
Gun shows us
His plans
And all the stuff they're going to update and swap out
It gave me a better appreciation for what the company is trying to do
This isn't just a prefabricated Pub the
Did you put together with
Allen wrench
Live forever
People's conception of what looks authentically old-timey
It changes all the
So they are going to swap out some of the old crap
Forbes some more up-to-date old crap
Princess some of the frame magazine ads for eggs and butter they're going to replace those as with framed black
Black and white photos of
Famous Dubliners
Girl sucking swap out some of the furniture Karen says when they first designed the pub
The tables and the chairs were too tiny
Realize people are bigger and it needs more space
I'm not overdoing so American
I can say that we happy few unarmed to
In the pub is this you have to keep changing the definition of
What exact
Is genuine
It has to feel like Dublin
But now also promises to provide a unique design
Design Taylor
To a particular location to
Particular customers
The particular size of your customers butts
But ultimately the question is is all of this
Really Irish
Differences
Yes absolutely
But at the same time he also acknowledges
They're telling a story
A lot of what we did
Over the years was spinning at a light at the archway
If I said that was done because
You know Joe's open yada yada and it came from a place in mayo land
Cuz why would you not trust an Irishman
So what at the same point to come for a disco ball in and then try and spend that one because nobody believed you
So you kind of have to to retain your own credibility
Going to have to be careful with how you spend on tail
Do you think you are in a level of dress right when you open your mouth and people here acting
There's no question about it
It's a definite
The more authentic there irishness
What's the more successful they are
But the more successful they are the harder it is to
To pull off
The authentic
Because the demand for all of this stuff
The higgly-piggly jump
It's contributing to aderans houses
Is a global
Shortage
A real authentic Irish kit
It's a crisis
The island has been ransacked
Jugs and
Old butter dishes
To create atmospheres around the world in all these different Irish Pub
And we played a part of not right so I can't be overly critical Auto
But now I kind of CD sad sites what because we're looking at reproductions were having a heart of time
Finding original bric-a-brac because it's just not there anymore
And there's poke company has competition for that breaker
They're few hours companies that started up to do the same thing
A little Irish
Procure
There an old leather chair in the corner
And your business
I guess I just don't buy that all this
Deliberate Irish magical need some help filters down into the customers
Consciousness
You can do it as a little
Tribal way I thought was everyone can't go to
A pub in Dublin it's been around for
Sort the Cayman go to Farrell's in my neighborhood
But sometimes you just want to drink
In an airport
Or on A Street near the
And you want to space that makes you feel
Feel a certain way like you're drinking with friends even if
There are no friends around and have figured out a sort of
Social short
And I think the subliminal signals of
The dusting knick knacks
Any Irish cheers I think that adds to the
Wait
What about that butter dish on the wall
At tageen in Stamford
Yeah the butter dish
So
I was taking a lot of stuff
Junk Off the Wall look
This is what I pulled the butter dish off on the back it says there
Plain as Day made in
Colon
And we were standing there looking we got you
Without even missing a Beat
Darren launches into the story about how
Theoretically being Irish
Knick-knack because during World War II Irishman scattered all over Europe
1 Irishman
Steven believen in poland
Butter dish
Went home and put it on the Shelf
And that
That is what you are paying for
In an Irish pop you're paying for an awesome story
The Met
Or may not
Be completely trip
And one more thing about Barrel
Best Irish bar in Brooklyn
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Delta
Who wants to make your travel experience easy and enjoyable
With the fly Delta app you'll stay connected and informed
Download the fly Delta app from your favorite app store today
One thing I saw at Farrell's that I did not see it any mail McNally
Pub
Piles of cash All Over the Bar
Ihs.gov
Cinnamon NY
When you go outside having a cigarette do this do that
Nobody's going to touch that money
Nobody's going to touch
Cell phone
How to play Orion on in the house
That money will be there tomorrow morning
Absolutely
Yeah I probably wouldn't touch the money either
In a park full of air
Ex-cops
Tell us what you think about the show email us at Planet Money at npr.org or find us on Twitter or Facebook
Also NPR has launched a new daily podcast is called
App for
It goes into your podcast feed at 6 in the morning 6 in the morning that working all night for you
Find me the top news stories of the day telling you what you need to know
And why it matters
And the whole things about 12 minutes
You can find up first on NPR one
Forever your podcast
Today's show was produced by Elizabeth to us and you can reach Devon bread story about the Irish Pub company at
I'm LJ
And I'm Robert Smith thanks for listening