Support for NPR and the following message
Which come from WWE
Publishers of people power and profit
Progressive capitalism for an age of discontent
By Nobel prize-winning economist
Joseph E stiglitz
In the very early days
Of satellites
You pretty much knew what the mission of Any Given satellite was going to be
Spying on the enemy
And at the time the object of Interest
Was pretty singular the Soviet Union
Robert Cargill job was to study the photos that came down from those us spy satellite
Everyday she would go to a windowless government building in Washington DC
Into a dimly lit room
And you would sit down at something called a light table
With a single photograph on it
And then imagine a microscope
Righttime now peering through a microscope
I'm looking at
Garrison's that have military equipment at I'm looking at test sites in which they might be employed
A new missile technology I'm looking at ports
To see what the development of their Naval capabilities are
Lots of people would look at the same photograph
4 hours
They called it torturing
And I had to torture the pixels because
Each and every Spy photo of the Soviet Union
What's incredibly rare and valuable
In early days of satellites would take pictures on rolls
Felt this was before digital photography where you could
Dim the picture back to Earth from space
So they're actually giant rolls of film inside of the saddle
And so they had to figure out a way to get that film back to Earth
From space
And they came up with this
Brilliant solution
The program have a secret code in Corona
And the corona satellites were designed
To take pictures
And then
Poop out the canister of film from the bottom of the satellite and inject it into space
Once it reaches the atmosphere it would deploy a parachute
I kid you not now it's floating down over the Pacific Ocean
Your spy satellite photos
Are us
Air Force plane
With basically a trapeze on the end of it so think of it
Two poles in a big net
Would have to time it
So that as it floated down it flew right over top of it
Caught the parachute in its net that's caught the canister
It's it's
Inconceivable to me
There is a
Falling canister of film from space
An airplane
Catches in a net
In midair
At American ingenuity
In the decade since then
The US has
Of course launched
Thousands of better satellites
Able to beam down Millions
The photos rather than just what it could fit on a roll of film
And Robert cardillo now runs the entire agency
In charge of all that new in
The national geospatial-intelligence agency
Any last looking back at his time in that windowless building in that damn room
Because it's problem now
Is too much
So many photographs
So many pixels.
How many people
Like you like your old job how many people would you need to go through the kind of data we're getting
So we would have to hire eight million
Image Rihanna
To accommodate such
Of course they're not going to hire
Ignoring people
In fact right now the US government training computers
To do those jobs in the future
Which highlights this issue that the entire satellite business is thinking about right now
How do we handle this
Flood pictures and data coming in from space and those the world even need anymore
Maybe we should follow this before let it but he decided to go to space
It is Monday morning satellite launching
5 4 3 2 1
Robert Smith no relation over International Space Station
Telescope biggest planet money has a brand new satellite
Two of our series you want to hear hell podcast even got our hands on a spacecraft
You should go back and listen to the first
We talked about how there was a revolution right now
In the space
Satellites are getting small and cheap
Plentiful
This is a big question for everyone
What should the Planet Money satellite do
The mission to find
The mission
Support for NPR
Thomas from LinkedIn learning
Proud to support the launch of life
NPR Sky to help you make better life decision
LinkedIn learning short video
Tutorials cover business Tech and creatives
Skills employers look for at every level all taught by expert
And new courses are added every week
+ LinkedIn learning is personal
Recommended courses based on your intro
And life kit listeners get a month of learning
Free start your free trial
Add LinkedIn learning.com
NPR
We've named The Planet Money satellite
Pod1
About 12 inches long with foot
It's basically a little telescope with a camera
And when it is up
300 miles above the Earth
It will be able to do essentially what those Corona satellites
Pic pictures of whatever
Play Nobody wants to spy on
When we last left pawed while it was sitting on a workbench at the satellite company were working with planet
No relation no relation
And in this briefcase Stacy
I have a model of it
Right here
It's okay
Cute
Little party is about the size of a loaf of bread with like solar cell wing
Little little camera lens on it
That feeling
That feeling you have right now
That excitement
About sending something you have touched into orbit
It has a name
And it's the name I heard over and over again when I talked to ex
We have
Officially diagnosed
Space fee
Yuan healthy honey wine
That is the big problem
Stacy meat
Silverado pain he is publisher of satnews he's been covering this industry for a long time
Annie sez
What we have forgotten
Is that a satellite is just
It is just a simple tool
To collect
And transmit some sort of data
Lot of people get caught up in the technology
And forget that somehow that technology has to be paid
And so there has to be a business case
There has to be a client who need some data
But you know what no one wants to work in no one wants to work at a data cap
I want to work for space company
Great
Correct
It's about us right now all sorts of company
Erasing to be in the space biz
Get the tiny satellites
Into orbit
And yet they do not have a strong plan for how they're going to make money off
Like us
Yeah I know
The challenges that too many
Plans going on this too much being built this a lot of
Venture funds around bed
I've been poured into a lot of these companies and
And they going to be sad
And I'm hoping that I'm wrong of obviously in this regard bed
As there is a bubble
Do you think
I have considered
Possible that we need
Podcast and the satellite into space
That is when you know there
That has occurred to me
Fart
This existential crisis
This is Eve
Exactly what the entire industry
Is facing right now everyone's asking the same question we are which is
Did the world really need another satellite
What can we do with the satellite
It will change the world
I mean
Such a production
To get to space
We have to do something to make it
Worthwhile we have to
Sanlitun
Party off on some kind of word omission
Yashow first went to figure out what are satellite
Is able to
To take it for a test drive ascent
So I arranged a sit-down with Kathryn Scott
She runs the image analytics team at Planet
People who let us adopt other satellites
Bibelot
200 satellites just like ours
Audience
It's already taking pictures every day
I just wanted to see like
Just today
Just today what do those satellites
Today it's almost
224 terabytes a day comes down it's something on that order of magnitude
Taking a New York today
Well there about 25 magazine
So it's about yet about 800,000 images
Everyday
800000 fotos de so no one can
Can look through them is not a human being here watching the photos come down
Everything is automatic
Planet has computers that stitch together all of the photos
Does of the Earth every day
Okay so you can essentially
Do that thing you always see in spy movies you know
Pick a spot on the Earth
Zoom and enhance exactly
All that power
At
Your fingertips
Annie like I'm such an idiot
The first thing I say when I sit down at this
Incredibly massive opportunity
Is
I would love to see my apartment building in
I know everyone does at the first
Show me my home
Area 51 and then maybe if they're really creative you're like I want to see North
Austria
I nice
So where are you on the Block
I am
Okay you see that
This this little lump right there is a is a synagogue and we're right
There
On the other side diner right on that street
You can see my apartment building my kids school a few trucks
And I realize I'm using this cutting-edge technology
To basically take the world's most
Expensive selfie
I mean it
It's not why pretty much everybody does every
Everything now though
Yeah yeah and you know
How did they do not
Underestimate the value of a selfie from space
Because she says the Planet Money satellite views not
Just
Camera
The time machine right
It is a
Time machine
Because our satellite
Will be taking photos every day
At the same time
You can then go back
And see how things change and if you can go back in time and figure out a model you can actually can guess what the future is going to hold to
Princess would look at my neighborhood in capital says
Look at this construction site
U-Box from my apartment
Delaney Park Place
You can go back in time and figure out how
Quickly
The construction crews are moving
Let me see like you can see that
Those used to be buildings they are they took it out
And
You know I mean if I did some analytics you I could use this data to figure out
When they will finally
Stop
Running
All those trucks through my neighborhood everyday
It's exciting that we finally have the technology to how
How do you fight your neighborhood battle
I have many of
We should think bigger
For the Planet Money satellite
Let's make a little bigger
So Francis planet makes money by selling access to this time
The CAT scan showing
And they should have salad in bulk right for a dollar or two for $2
You can get pictures of one square kilometer
Over the course of a
NSLC
Subscriptions to this day.
Farmers agriculture companies
To the US government Robert cardillo the photo analyst
Turn director of an agency we talked to earlier
You just made a deal for the US government to pay Planet 14 million dollars
4 photos of high-priority areas
That would be North Korea
Look the real money is not in taking photos of the
It isn't analyzing the
In finding the pattern
Patterns that no one else knows about
So
We need to think like
Spies Like spies
And I found
Some
That we talked to her
They work in believe it or not an old converted Dairy Barn in Louisville Kentucky
I visited there with producer Elizabeth
Hi there
Alfanar is the chief R&D officer
Genscape
The boring way to describe what Jem skate does
Is Market
IntelliJ
But really
We have been described as the James Bond of Commodities and energy mark
Journal no less
Oh that's a pretty good pole quote that's what you want from the Wall Street Journal
So that was pretty exciting
Different planes in the financial World everyone wants an edge
A little piece of data that no one else has
Engen ski
Something that day.
According to public documents for company brings in
Around a hundred million dollars a year
Our life here
She takes us into a room that I swear it's like that
Scene from every James Bond film
Where he gets his gadgets you know the exploding watch The Deadly pain acute
Antoine Roberts
Workout some contraption
So let's see some oil Traders somewhere want to know how much gas is flowing through a pipeline
So they can make a bet on the price of
That's what holds up a box
We can eavesdrop
On Pipeline
There's a directional microphone
And then there is an omnidirectional microphone that we attach to these
You can hear the
They pumps
When their on them when they're running
Spray high pitched I need a lower voice
If the pipeline goes quiet genscape will send out an alert
With customers
Pepsiman Gadget
It's for people who trade electricity
So energy Traders want to know if
Power plants
Are running at full capacity in the middle of the night
Get ripples out one of their night
Vision camera
Thermal imaging spy camera
So cool
So they look as
Heat signatures from power plants
That's from refineries from anything
That is
Pause
And we
Use the signal to indicate whether those refineries are running or not or the power plants are running or not
That is awesome can we do something like this
IPod one
Where Sally think do you set alight so a lot of the things that she showed me you have to get close to the pipeline
The power plant
In order to get the secret info
What satellites have allowed them to monitor everything everywhere
We walk into this huge room
And there's all these different Jackson everyone is watching different
Commodities around the globe
So shut about what's over there
Oils over there
Power power electricity
Egg
Corn beans we have a soy
Being monitoring product
To the people in this room are looking at the pictures from
Planet from satellites exactly like ours
And they're turning them into information
The people pay money for
So one research we talked to is
Boeing satellite images
Oil wells being drilled
Incel
Sudan
Another one shows me the Smoke Stacks from a power plant in India
He can tell exactly like it what
Capacity is running at
And then ask your team to show me their newest secret spy trick
It's like something out of a movie
Marcus Walter and Brett sundheimer open a window on your computer
Click click click
I see something that looks like a shipping port
As seen from space
So what are we looking at here is this an actual place
Yes this is Emma port in China
Dalian
Click click resuming
And I see what looks like a bunch of
White marshmallow
Well tanks
And you can see
In this photo
How much oil is in each tank
Cry now and I want to see that
Where is it
A few more clicks
And all the sudden there are Little Numbers
Lady of Rage
The computer is taking satellite images
Look at the Shadows
On the roof
Of the tank
Oil tanks are floating so they go up and down up and down
The computer
Looks in the shadow calculate the angle of the Sun and can tell you
The height of each route and then as we go through everything up
David Lopez
Analyze we can see every tanks
So this is 17.5% full of this Bank in China that you've never seen your life
Correct
Faustina through satellite imagery
Of course
Junkie just launched the survey
A daily news feed telling customers how much oil there is
Stored
In China
And even though it's based on planet satellite photos satellite photos like the ones we will take
It is the analysis of the day
It's the way they
And use it
And marketing
That is what is making the money
And the service is going to hit
Oil companies shipping firms commodity Traders
Can use these numbers to make decisions
When the oil tanks get low in China
You can literally start to send oilfield ships
Across the Pacific
Before China even asked
It seems like a logical end to this
Is that
Someday
Anytime there is
An additional well
An additional ship and additional tank
Somewhere in the world
We're all going to know about it
That's right yeah we're all going to note about and we're probably going to know within the day
This is just one supply chain
Yeah the same for all Commodities but it's also can be the same for
How many new homes are being built
How much more traffic is are on the highways
Avocado avocado
Grown you know exactly
How hot is a microbit atomic unit of measurement
But now they have all these spy technique
See my mind
It gets me thinking about a possible
Mission
For the Planet Money satellite for
Pod1
No I love avocados
Support any avocado mission for pod1 let's do avocado
Stacey Hill New York avocado
Popeyes pricing list
Tell me you'll go by a little store and you'll be like
I got
There's an avocado for a dollar
But then you come back the next day and they're like $3
Yes yes all the time
Yeah who knows why right I would love some data that would tell me how prices are going to change in the avocado Market
Before we leave genscape
I give this
Pitch to Deirdre and her colleague josef's palinka
I have the perfect
Name for a project
The guacamole pipeline
Miniature country needs guacamole for the Super Bowl
Nobody knows
How many avocados are out there
I mean maybe somebody knows
I mean maybe everybody mad
But we don't know
So we could use her side like to make a bet on the avocados
Supply
Before the Super
It sounds insane
And you have to let the folks at genscape because
They listen to this and they treated it like it was the most normal ID in the world probably we can look at a different
Part of the visible spectrum or a different part of the
Of the light spectrum to see
Growth quality the same way they do for corn and other crops in the United States
Seattle food trucks
Avocado truck
Count trucks
Cow chips
I don't know if they store avocados in piles or put them on pallets or put them in buckets but we could count those as well yeah
You're just suggest that maybe there's some sort of
Avocado bottleneck somewhere we can monitor her like limes and tomatoes
I don't know
Really I mean
It sounds like you're choking but there is a name for this
Tracking
Complimentary
Commodity
It's actually one of the techniques that use against
You're with you something that you know maybe the Corn Chip people
Know something
That we doubt about avocado
Let me get this straight for a second we're going to use this cutting-edge technology just like intergalactic
Whatever unprecedented moment
In space technology
To Corner the guacamole
Guac finger
I am guac finger
Whatfinger want 11101
Kid is one of the missions we are looking in
What are some other options in case you know
We want to use our satellite for
It'll good
Guacamole evolves researchers who need help collecting some data for farmers
Africa
The worthy project
We're going to know more about this once
We can get the satellite into the sky
And sending back
Real pictures
When is that going to happen
That is an excellent
Question
Because as we've been chasing the mission
There is this other big problem
Did we have not yet song
Which is
How do we put
Pod1 the Planet Money satellite
Indoor
Next week
Travel the globe
Shopping for a rocket
What you say I know a guy
I'm kind of like your your best friend that's going to find you a rocket somewhere in the world that has extra space
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Cambridge
The Bold way to steady growth
People often think annuities are too conservative
Too complex or only for retirees
But annuity
These can be a smart way to hedge Market
And earn guaranteed returns
Game Bridge
Aims to change the game
By offering simplified annuity
He's in a Sleek digital experience
That replaces fine print in
Phone tag with
Clear conditions and a direct loafy model
Learn more at gamebridge. Life
5 / NPR
Gameboy
Which is not available in all states
Would you the Planet Money listener like to join the avocado cartel
Or let's be honest you're probably a better idea for what we should do with a satellite send an email Planet Money
Npr.org you can also find us on Twitter
Facebook and Instagram
Are handle is at Planet Money
Oh and I'm posting behind the scenes photos or space journey on my Instagram
@radio Smith and we have been getting some notes about the planet money mission patch that you designed Robert the one featuring
This world a little gold star for every single member of the Planet Money Team and we will tell you
In the next episode next Wednesday how to get episode was produced by Elizabeth
Sally home and Tasha mihailovic Alex goldmark is are supervising producer Brian Dorsett and it's the show special things today
Play to Chris bitty and Broadway Negros of Astro digital
And a cheap Tipper hint from mineral rocks
Are Robert Smith and I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Thanks for lunch
Can I tell you about
The shooting star guy we met
So where at
The small satellite conference
And we're asking around like what is the
The weirdest way that anyone is making money
Off of satellite
And they said oh
You got to go talk to
Josh
Rodent bomb
This company called a l
We are creating artificial shooting stars
Artificial shooting star shooting stars
Oh really
Could you could you like buy one for your girlfriend or something exactly so shooting stars are just little debris that go through the app
Write the skies plan is he's going to launch a satellite with a bunch of little fake shooting stars
So what we do is we send up a satellite to low earth orbit with
Several hundred of our shooting star particles
When a customer calls they say hey we want we want a meteor shower this night
So maybe I'm I'm I'm Tokyo and I have the Olympics in
20 20 20 20 and I want to end my Opening Ceremonies with shooting stars coming out of sky
We say okay
And when our satellite passes over we release them
They burn
Even in the
Bright bright City you will be able to look up and see the stars
So
He has not
What's the satellite or sold any of these things yet
But he said
$1000000 will buy you
I think that's a pretty great way to spend a million.
Honestly
On a meteor shower
Okay I guess he's going to be rich