Hey it's Robert Smith here
These days as a reporter
You can never be too careful
And that's why I hear Planet Money occasionally
We send messages using an encrypted messaging app called
Signal
That is bit of Technology promises that no one can ever intercept
Or we
Your text
Yesterday I got a message
On signal from a reporter friend
And the message said
The CIA has
Figured out a way
To read
These messages
Now perhaps you saw this news to
Wikileaks has released a bunch of stolen documents from the CIA
It is a list of
Did the CIA uses to spy on people
And it's not that they can't actually break the encryption on apps
Signal but they found a way around it
Which is the CIT basically figured out how to get inside your phone
And watch
What you type
Listen to what you say
Effective also apparently hacked the Samsung voice activated TV
So the CIA can listen hit
When you're talking in the room
Or yelling back
Apple TV
Now the documents don't reveal how the CIA crack
The system
How they found the secret doors
In your phone
TV
Perhaps they have young people you know in a warehouse in Langley Virginia high on Red Bull you know and all night
Or
Perhaps the CIA
Online
Because there is a booming Marketplace
4 secret backdoor
Into technology
As soon as I read these news articles I thought oh
We did a story
About just this very thing about hackers for hire
About people who
Professionally their job is the hunt for Flaws in your smartphone
And sell that knowledge to the highest bidder
The story focused on a loner
A single hacker a tall gangly guy
Would never before told his story
I don't want to be known as somebody who talks
But I'm just saying you know
You came to an ass there's a market for this stuff absolutely there is
The show originally aired in 2015
But it literally allowed me to understand
The news that is happening right now
So I will let the original host
Take it from here
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Steve Hatton
Today on the show how one man stumbled into a flaw in Apple's operating
A way to hack into the phone you might have in your hand right now
It's a story about a million dollar deal
Friendship
Betrayal
In an all-out race
HAC
The iPhone
Support for this podcast and the following message come from upwork
The largest freelancing website connecting businesses with top web and mobile developers designers
Spiders and other Freelancers ready to lend a hand
Over a million businesses are getting more done by finding hiring and paying Freelancers through up
To learn how you can get more done with Freelancers and save $100 on your first project
Go to upwork.com money
I have a special guest
Hosting the show with me today aarthi shahani arkali get NPR who covers technology
Aarthi you were the first person to tell me about
This loner who discovered this one particular
Yes
Paideia the hacker called himself
Jonathan Stewart
He has a freelance job a computer contractor
He said he's done work for Google and Microsoft
He has a family
Was in the Phoenix suburbs
I don't know what I expected when we visited him but this was not it it was big stucco houses manager
Richard Long
So this this neighborhood sort of reminds me of a Time the neighborhood and weeds you know all the houses
It's made out of ticky-tacky for golf cart with three
Tri-tip on the back
Tucker lives in Suburban Paradise
Jonathan Stewart
Met us at the edge of Islam
Tall skinny guy 30 years old
Still dresses like a skater
Misplace
Thanks
Kids with Boston Terrier named Marley
People don't you do not fight
Don't do that
Jonathan grew up as one of those computer savant
Can you how to get into
Any system
Videos
Thought of himself as one of these good guys he still does
I'd say she helps the largest companies in the world
Find bugs
Security flaws
But at night he would poke around on its own
Ignite
He worked for himself
And had a hacker name an alter ego
Johnny Mnemonic
It's from the old science fiction story about a guy with
Computer for
At first When Johnny Comes flaws in major software programs
Tell the company
Open fix
But he got
Frustrated
He said lots of times these companies ignored him
Didn't fix the problem
Or maybe just offered to make tiny token in payments
Deserve
Major
Companies
Employing the best developers in the world
And for years we got paid zilch nothing
For finding these vulnerabilities in writing exploits for them so you know what
Like
Get paid for your work
If you find a flaw in a piece of software there are a lot of other people who will
Hey for that information
Especially if no one else knows about it
In fact there's a specific term for this kind of information
It's called a zero Day Hack
0 as in it's been 0 days since the rest of the world has known
No one knows
Not even the guys who wrote the software
Johnny Mnemonic started to make extra cash
Searching for these 0 days
In his spare time
You make a few thousand dollars here or there selling this information
It's legal
Just point out software flaws and sell them
Even if Johnny never exactly knew for sure who the buyers were
Or how they were using the hacks
His million-dollar discovery of this flaw in the iPhone
Started the same way
Just like these other
Yeah I remember exactly where I was
I was actually in Redmond
Working back in those days in 2013
Johnny was in Redmond Washington and he was working for Microsoft
On a contract so by David clock in
And in the evenings he be sitting on a sofa
Pouring over source code for Apple
The stuff that powered the MacBook and the iPhone
Okay so in the green first
Register system
Precursor this means to store this structure pointer
Johnny's reading from a black screen
Just a mash of in decipherable characters letters numbers
It was indexing something
And Johnny would sit on his couch
In Redmond and just
Pour through this code
All night
It's boring work really boring work
Hunched over looking for Treasure it's crazy
And it's all about patience and persistence
And eventually Johnny finds his
Little gold coin
Tg3 underscore soft CCA star soft sequels get soft
See
Friends
Johnny Lewis
Every piece of software even Apple's latest
Fancy stuff
Is old school
Cobble together from other bits
Software
And that like the one you just read
Believe it or not
Was Infamous back in the 90s for triggering
What was called an index in
There was
A vintage 1990s watch
Sitting in the middle of Apple's brand new iPhone
I wanted to see if it was what I thought it was you know you played bugs away I play 90s hip-hop
Yeah
These operating systems are built like fortresses or jails
What Johnny had discovered was a secret door through just
One wall
It was an important wall a wall that separated the inner sanctum of Apple system
But
And this is also important
He didn't have the key to open up that
No one
And that's kind of why Johnny didn't realize he was holding onto gold
He sat there on the couch
Told a few friends about his
Discovery
I thought that maybe somewhere down the line down the road he'd sell it for a few thousand bucks
Someone who cares
Which I didn't know
Was at that moment
There are a bunch of Chinese businessmen
Who adjust offered a vast
Sum of money
To the person who could find an open that door
Now I'm about to play you a phone call that was recorded its home around this time
The boys are going to hear is a broker of sore
This is a guy who hooks up hackers
With people who want to buy their hats
This guy's name is
Hi
Crazy parties
When this ship pops off cuz it's going to pop off big
You already know
Norfolk is over here don't know I had something to do with it I'm just going to I don't know nothing
Tired heard about Johnny Secret Door
Because one of Johnny's on Friends
Sold them out
And now that I need you
He approached one of the best digital lock
Pickers on the planet
A hacker known as go hot
Who's the guy on the other end of this phone call
And even if what he's saying makes no sense
Just listen free
Excitement in his voice
Here is the plan
Take Johnny's discovery
Basically have GL hot
Make some keys that unlock that secret door
And then sell this is a package deal to the Chinese
One-time-only
The secret to taking over the eye
Listen bro it'll be cool
We'll set it up I'll shoot over to China you shoot over there
Let him meet you that dale dale f****** go ain't nothing meet go hiding hey how you doing blah blah blah blah
I recorded this call for a Chinese buyer
Eventually it leaked
Out online
And we verified who was on the
Call
The Chinese businessman one of the iPhone hack
For a very
Specific reason
You know how the iPhone makes you go get your apps from the iPhone store
Apple takes a cut of everything controls everything is Apple's money
But with this hack
That changes
The Chinese businessman get the keys to break out of Apple's jail
To jailbreak so to speak
The phone
And then they set up their own app store so that customers buy directly from them
The Chinese businessmen get the profits
Not Apple
In the Chinese businessmen were willing to pay a lot of money
Clear
300 Yuan 350000
$350,000
Is just
Geo hot
That's it
There is no discussion of giving the money to Johnny Mnemonic or is for
You guys are going to keep the prize
Themselves
How do you want the money sent directly
To you you want to send to me listen to you
Listen
We could do it like this
Because I do have the company I'm paying you as a developer
You follow me my Mercedes list 1000
It'll look good nice paper trail
So Thai and Gio hot already spending the money their minds and Johnny Mnemonic
He's back working is Corporate gig
An office room for hire
He has no idea this is going down
But remember
This is a race
And while these guys are joking around on tape
Another group of hackers
Guess to the Finish Line first
My name is David Wong I go by Planet being on the internet and a member of The Debaters
The Invaders
4 guys
Spread across three continents
Who came up with a superhero like me
The Invaders
They also heard about Johnny Mnemonic Secret Door
And they cut a deal with a different group of Chinese businessmen with their own app store
That deal was for $1000000
Is incredible life-changing amount of money
And
You know I was
Really shocked
I was
That was
Flabbergast
I know
When it comes to hacking the iPhone David Wong is a rock
To contact in China
Flew him and his entire team
All the Invaders to China
All-expenses-paid
There it was it was pretty incredible for for everyone
The million dollar Highway
Here's the weird thing about the hacker world
Well the race is on everything is
Secret and opaque no one wants
The talk too much about money or how they get what they got
Or what color they're trying to crack
And if you talk too much
You can get burned
David Wong Tesla guy Johnny new
Canoe about Johnny's Secret Door
Send it
To the evaders
Hoping that they all could work together
David
30 turned him down and then he never looked
And this is why you don't talk
Johnny's Discovery was now worth hundreds of thousands of dollars
And people were peddling it behind his back
In the end the evaders won this race
We figured out how to jailbreak the iPhone 5S
Before anyone else
They could get around Apple's walls
Even use any software or any apps they wanted
On the iPhone
I remembered it struck a deal with a Chinese
Company
Basically how that deal work
When users in China wanted to use apps that Apple doesn't
Approve of
It going download this hack
Does jailbreak
And that meant they automatically download the software for this Chinese companies apps
For a whole bunch of reasons were not going to get into cuz it's complicated
Jailbreaking phones in China is in
Credibly,
So this hack
Was incredibly valuable
App Store charge Commission on every app they sell
Millions of people were downloading this job
That's why this was a million-dollar hat
Now where did this happen again
The spread on the internet and
Twitter
And suddenly everyone knew David Wong in the Invaders were responsive
And that's when Johnny Mnemonic
Found out
And the more he read
The matter he got
It was his secret door
Cheney Witt
He recognized it
Battles fought from the 90s
It was his fine
After eye surgery
Found out the entire story from talking to
Other people
Then I put it together in like I was kind of like I felt used
Used
Johnny Played it over in his head
He knows everything about
But he didn't realize just how big and Cutthroat the market
For this hack was going
He never thought that one of his friends
Turn on
Selma
And that's
Certify felons
Trap here like
I didn't know the background of the you know a certain individuals
You know I was from a different scene I just didn't know these people like
You know you have to know
Everybody that you're working with and I just
Young
What you're saying is that you trusted the wrong car
Yeah I've basically yeah
This is the problem with quasi-legal markets
Like this one
There are no rules no Watch Dogs
No court system to protect
Your discovery
It's winner-take-all
You snooze you lose
It slowly changing though in ways you might not expect
Companies that make this
Stop the software
Companies like Google and Facebook have woken up to the fact that
This Market in flaws
Exist
They've decided since they can't kill what they can't control it
They can't stop
They're going to join it
Do companies are beginning to pay real money
Solo hackers like Johnny
That way they can get these flaws
Find these holes in seal them up
Before someone turns the key
They weren't new versions of
The software release
Millions of songs
Fix the bug
And then of course
That race
The break-in
It starts all over again
One short epilogue about that million-dollar hack the one that David Wong on his team tried to put together
Well it fell apart
After they made the deal with the Chinese the hacker world
Loaded and anger
This new Chinese app store it turns out the one made possible by the Secret Door
It was spelled with
Pirated software and computer programmers were pissed
It was a torrent it was overwhelming
It made me feel really really terrible
I don't know they were just angry and yelling I didn't want to read most of it
So David Wang and his team cancelled
Their deal
They basically tank
That Chinese app store
And Wong says
Heinous team
Never collected
This episode was originally reported a few years ago
A quick update
On what Johnny's been up to
Injustice
Let's take a moment
The bank and share a message from our sponsor Thumbtack who makes it easy to find and hire skilled Local 4
Professionals for anything on your list
Like cleaners painters
Handyman
And more
With 1100 types of prose and
All 50
Start your project today
Thumbtack.com
After the news came out this week about the cia's tools to hack iPhones
We of course
Immediately thought
I wonder if Chinese involved
So we tracked him down this week to see if you're still in the zero-day business
And if you sold any CIA
He says he's working for a Fortune 100 company now
But he still does exploit
Homicide
Andy says
Maybe they ended up with the CIA or
Accompany
Maybe a foreign government you really have no idea
Dealers he works with
Harlem
This episode was originally produced by Jess Jiang and fee of Benin today's version was produced by Elizabeth kulas
This month Empire is collaborating with a bunch of other podcast on a project
Called
Tripod
So think about a podcast you really like
Think about someone you want to share it with think about someone who should
Try
Podcast
Tripod
And then let them know on social media
Tell us what you recommended by using the hashtag tripod
Try
Pod
Thanks for spreading the work
A Robert Smith thanks for listening
Hey everybody I'm Kelly mcevers host of NPR's embedded
On March 9th
We are back
With our new episodes
That police videos
What did he do
To deserve to be killed that night and shot so many times
People see what they want to see
Almost no one
Can see those videos from a neutral perspective
I was thinking she the gun to see the gyno don't
Going to see the guy
Find embedded on the NPR one app or at npr.org