Hey everybody
Is Kenny Malone
A quick note before we start
If you're planning on making a charitable donation this December
We really would encourage you
Disappeared Planet money but the way that you can do that
Best is by donating
To your local NPR member stations
It's really easy you just go to donate. Npr.org
Planet Money
And not only does it help us out
But it supports the amazing amazing work
That the member stations
Many of us myself included
We got our start
At the station they were little incubators for a little weird planet money people
WLRN in Miami with my home for a long time
My heart is still there and now you should send your money there or whatever your local station
Go to donate. Npr.org Planet Money
Thank you
The show
After months of scrambling and writing and rewriting and
Reese scrambling
Senate House Republicans who voted to pass
The latest and Final
Version of their tax
The Yankees are 224 and the Nazar 201
The motion is adopt
President Trump sign that bill today while we are recording this
This is the largest tax overhaul
Index
And when we say large
Not just kidding that was actually Ben bernanke's 600-page macroeconomic
The GOP tax bill
Way longer than
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Kenny Malone and I'm Cardiff Garcia
Cardiff Garcia
Famous one of the
Host of our newest
Podcast the indicator for low dat money
Annies joining us to try and cram
1100 pages
Of tax bill
Into a single Planet Money episode
That's right in today on the show we answer the question
Taxpayers are asked
For example
Should I become
Kenny Malone
Incorporated
Orb LLC or MVA or DMV or whatever
Entity tax changes mean our moms will stop bothering us about buying property
And
Who is really benefiting
From the tax cuts
This message comes from NPR sponsor squares
Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their own website
Using customizable Leo
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobiledit
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online presence
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
The big
Headline-grabbing centerpiece of this new GOP tax bill
Is the cut 2
Corporate tax rate
And we're not going to talk about that
Not yet at least we sent Cardiff Garcia out to go deal with that
He's going to bring us what he found later in the
Episode
And so to kick things off
This one's a bit of a doozy
Pass-through entities
Which I know
I know it sounds more like a
Fake science name for ghosts
But they are very real
And they are very confusing
And maybe
Very lucrative
To deal with this one
We brought in
2X
My name is Lily bachelder in the
Professor at NYU School of Law
Lily is also the co-author of a reason
Paper about
The possible loopholes in his new tax bill
That paper has gone surprisingly viral
We were pretty surprised ourselves
You are now officially
Tax paper
The rare rare status we also called up Rohit
Kumar leader of PWC tax policy Services practice
About this new tax bill
For Price Waterhouse
Cooper switch
Apparently
Just goes by PWC now I assume there were some expensive branding exercise that decided that was better
Sea of accounting firms now
I suppose yes
We should also say that in a previous life Rohit was a
Policy director for Republican Mitch
McConnell and Lily also in a previous life
With the chief
Tax counsel for Democrats in the senate committee on finance
It is true we talked about Pastor in our we ready to be great
Okay
So there's basically
Two kinds of businesses there are what are called C corporation
Which are corporations we're going to talk about those later in the show they're getting attacks
But then there's another way to structure a business
A pass-through
Apostle the easiest way to think of a past due rent
Is it is a business
But where the income of the business is showing up on the owners individual income tax
So when we think of it as if your
What's called a folder
Proprietorship in your
You know just selling a little bit of crafts
That you make on Etsy
Maybe you making cell
Knitted underwear
That is totally a real thing on at
It would be pretty complicated
And probably too much work or money to set up a whole Corporation
And file a whole separate tax as a corporation
And so we have this other way to structure a business
That's as a pass-through end
Where the prophets are immediately
Taxed at to the owners
C-cell all of your pairs of underwear as you make
Whatever profits you get from them
And then you report that as your income right all of the income rolls up passes through the business to the individual
It shows up on their individual
Income tax return
Any pastors are not just
Small
Knitted underwear sellers I mean they can be
Giant International
Companies with most
Partners they can be
Real estate companies like president
Did Trump's real estate company that is made up of a bunch of pastors
And in all these cases
Is it works the same way
The prophets
Of your business
Get reported as income
Buy you the owner or owners
And you pay tax on that income
Whatever your tax bracket says you sure
Another new tax bill
Allows these owners
To not pay tax
On as much as 20%
Of that pass-through
20%
Untaxed
Money part of the rationale is that the new tax bill also has a big tax cut for that other structure
A business Corporation
And so it's only fair that
Both structures
On the other hand a lot of
People feel like this
Is just another way
To give a tax cut
To the wealthy
So if you just looked it
The pass-through businesses that exist right now
Their ownership is really concentrated among the wealthy
So there's some estimates that
Over 60% of pass-through business income is earned by the top 1% which is
A lot more than the percentage of wage income that turn by the top 1%
Now it's not like all of those people can take all of that income and simply
Not pay taxes on
There is a built-in thrush
And if you earn more money than that threshold the bill
Had some language
Is it may restrict
Your deduction you give me one sec I can grab the conference part I've got it on my desk
Great
Do you hear me
Okay I found it okay
So the deductible amount
For each qualified trade or business is the lesser of
Hey
20% of the taxpayers qualified business income with respect to the trailer business
Or
Be the greater of
50% of the W-2 wages
It's very complicated
Language
And it may limit the abuse of this pastor
But
It does benefit some kinds of businesses over others
Some professions
Won't be able to take much of a deduction
At all so for example they excluded a whole class of
Providers are businesses service providers they call them so doctors lawyers
Accountants
Unfortunately applies specifically to high earning doctors
Employers ni
But other kinds of
Businesses that own say a lot of assets
Factories Maybe
Real estate
They're going to be able to take
A better today
Over all these new rules
Make being a small business or frankly a big one
A pretty good deal
Maybe
Even a better deal
Been being irregular
Human employee says so all of us sitting here at the who are not
Pastor businesses are we just smok sitting here paying more than our fair share
To tell until we get some more clarification on what the bills doing
And this is the thing about this new tax bill
Came together so quickly and the ink is still drying on the newest version
The even the people who have been watching this thing
Like Hawks
Are not in
Hayirli sure
About every line and every word
And how it's ultimately going to be interpreted
Enforced
So yeah
There are a lot of
People myself included who are wondering
Maybe I should die
Ask my company to fire me
Then form an LLC and then
Be rehired
Not as a human
But as a company
It may be possible
I'll go that route but then the other one note of caution
I'm other than the general little Caution which is no one should be forming a pass-through entity on the basis of his interview
If the holy artificial Arrangement there's always a risk that the IRS will come back in after the fact insane
Which is the official term
Is that is that it that's funny
The IRS is of the same term I tell my dog not to eat garbage
Yeah also my daughter when she's about to jump off something she's not supposed to
There you go
What's the business tax rate their big cuts there a big deal but
Personally speaking
When I sit down in front of TurboTax or at an H&R Block
I will almost certainly not be thinking about
Business tax
I will pull out a disgusting shoebox full of receipts and
Realize
I have no idea to ducks
Directions work the same
Any answer
Is actually do for now
Because these chains
I'll kick in
Until
You're doing your 2018 taxes
Is when in fact
Deductions are changing
In a big way
I'm going to hand this one over to Elsa
All right conduct
These are the things you spend money on during the year that you can take off or
Did.
From your tax bill
You can list
All of these items which is to
Itemized
Deductions or you can just take one standard one size
It's all d.
Options you get to itemize basically reflect
Value judgments by the government meaning when a government lets you deduct certain things got of the government telling you
How you should spend
Your money
Like what charity the government wants to encourage charitable
Contributions show it
Duck that
But this Republican plan has done kind of the opposite with
Expensive homes
And
Hi tax
States
What is new Republican plan does is make
Those homes a little harder to buy
And a high-tax States a little harder to live in
The mortgage interest deduction has shrunk and the state and local tax deductions
Now have
All right how are you hear me
So I called up Howard gleckman a
The tax policy
Sea center which is not
Partisan
What does the average person do under this new regime opossum
Deductions
Cancel the important thing to know about this bill is
There's the kind of no average person
So you and I can have the same amount of income
But a very different tax
That is especially true if one of us lives in a high
Pax
States because Republicans
Adjust taking a hammer to State and local tax.
Deductions better known as
Salt
They pass the bill that cap salt deduction how many terrible puns are used to talk about deduction
There's lots of there's a lot of them you know take this with a grain of salt
We don't want to rub salt in the wound
We don't want a text. It's worth its
Quickest weight in salt okay okay okay
Because I couldn't resist either just as too much salt can destroy a good dish
There is no such a thing as too much salt in your
Deduction
Alright so one of the Republican plan deductions for property taxes and others
State and local taxes
Now cannot exceed
Tencent
Thousand dollars
Which is really not good for taxpayers who live in high-tech
And
Who lives in the high-tech date
The high-tech stagehands Ibiza Blue State
They tend to be
States with lots of Democrats
York
New Jersey California
That is why there's been such a huge political
Fight
Over-salt
No deduction for state and local taxes
Is have been around since
The beginning of the income tax
You know the original idea
Was very simple
People should not have to
To pay taxes twice on the same thing
What ended up happening is that salt made it a lot easier for states to
Raising taxes
And the biggest beneficiaries of salt
Have generally been people who live in Rich suburbs in high-tax States
So there's been this perception that the rich states are getting a break
At the expense of
Of the rest
Abba country
But Howard says that's actually not true
There is his argument that why should low-tax
State-subsidized Hi-Tech
And the reality
Centos high-tech face
Generally contribute more
To the federal government
Then get back
Federal government
Which Howard is saying is
Federal assistance benefits lower-income
People and the numbers show that lower-income people tend to live in low-tax States
High tax states
Don't rely on federal programs at
Anyway people can argue all day about whether or not downsizing salt
Is fair but there is another deduction that Economist have been really
Excited
And that is a mortgage interest
What is so irritating
About this deduction Tuacahn
This is what Economist like to call an upside down
Seduction
Are we talkin about seduction
Score for mortgage loans of a million dollars
And the in the question is do you really want to subsidize
People who were buying
Giant houses
Cost a billion dollars
How old is referring to the old rule which let homeowners deduct interest
Payments on $1000000 or less
Of Mortgage Debt
Under the new rule now
You can only deduct interest payments on seven hundred
$50,000
Or less of
The reason a lot of Economist have
Wanted to see less of this mortgage interest deduction
Is it that they say
Distorts the economy it
Sabres people with bigger more
Expensive homes
People who don't really need help
And maybe the deduction encourages excessive borrowing
What I really wanted to know is
Can I now tell my parents
Stop bugging me about buying proper
So I'm 41 years old
I still have never been a homeowner
And you know them renting my entire adult life
My parents are convinced that I am doing the dumbest thing in the world
But under this new regime can I go back to my parents and tell them I'm actually not
Being that dumb after all
Hey what am I really that dumb
So what's going to happen here is your standard deduction is
Going to go up quite a lot
Yeah under the new rules the standard deduction I can take now as an individual has
GG
$12,000
Well the mortgage interest deduction has shrunk so
How much is a question for me now is
How those two things trade-off and a figure that out
I have to calculate
Well if I were to buy a house what are the mortgage interest payment deductions that I could
Take and if I were to itemize all my teeth
Options would that
Total
Be more than the $12,000 standard deduction I could otherwise take
And it
Hideout even under the new rule
It is still a good idea for me to buy
As long as I'm not borrowing more than $750,000 which is
Definitely
Not
Company for me
Hi Mom
You're still right
After the break
Actually you know what hold on
Particracy after the break
Corporate income
Tax
3 words stay with us
This message comes from NPR sponsor squares
Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their own website
Using customizable layout
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editor
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online press
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
All right back with me again back from
Corporate tax Odyssey
Cardiff Garcia
Spell less like an odyssey than liked
Okay then hits involve going through a lot of
Line item
But it wasn't
All right
California
If this bill were a concert
Corporate tax rate
Be the headline Act
Finally arrived
This is the big one
Here's the deal
The corporate tax rate is going down
35 /
Percent to 21
2%
This is a big issue because this taxed
It's been a good source of revenue for
For the federal government
Head over 10 years the loss of the government just from this rate cut
Is estimated to be about 1.3
Australian dollar
This may seem like a massive giveaway to corporations
But it's actually something that both Democrats and Republicans have been talking about
4 years
I mean I'm a bit skeptical about the
Like want to talk somebody who likes it and crawls Smith I'm the director of economic research at the cannon center
Niskanen Center is a kind of moderate neoliberalism
Think Tank
Carl has some problems with this bill through Raleigh thinks it makes
They're basically two rationales one is that
The Us corporate tax rate right now is
Higher than most of the developed countries in the world
Base for companies
That also means that companies won't have as much incentive to hide their profits overseas
Clever accounting trick
But I think the larger deal is that
Encourages like more investment in the United
And so the corporate tax rate is lower
That makes more investment
Profitable
And that should cause more investment more jobs and higher incomes are wedges
People United States
Let's say we're going to start a corporation
Planet Money Corporation
Obviously
We get a tax cut
Once we have that tax cut
Going to have higher profits
We'd have to make some choices about how to
Spend that new money
We can invest it we can buy new equipment
Recorders computers
We could hire more reporters
Or we could
The current staff some raises
Orchid lower prices to
Well I guess blow free because we don't charge
Podcast
Let's face it Planet Money was never going to be a great Corporation
But anyways
The last option the one that you've been hearing a lot of people worried about is that we'd end up giving our shareholders some money back
Stock dividend
BuyBacks
The Carlton other advocates
To the bill they think the Investment Park
Buy new equipment
Computers for quarters
They think that that's the most
Important part of the equation
It's okay please respond by investing more
Then that will allow it
The workers of those companies to be more productive
Lat raises
Labor productivity
Which increases the
Total amount that the economy can produce in a given year
What it means is that investment equipment research and other things
That's what I make
Planet Money
Corporation more efficient
Better and better at cracking a pot
So that's the argument for cutting the corporate tax rate
Because you're comes more productive we all get richer plus the US becomes a more competitive places
You business so the Planet Money Corporation stays here and the government keep
Collecting our taxes
A lot of people are skeptical
They still worried that companies
Just choose to give the money back to their shareholders
And here's why
Companies profits of
Mostly rebounded strongly
Instafinancial price
So they're going to invest more
For hire more workers
Give raises
They already would have
Carl doesn't buy that crate
He says it's one thing a lot of big rise in profit
Is going to just a few
Few companies
The most companies really might use the money to invest
He also says that even if
The tax cut doesn't compel every company to invest more
Could still be good for the
Economy
Even if a lot of company
Do just
Give the money back to their
Usually most investors
Hit much of
The dividends or will they get from BuyBacks and they put it into buying back more stock so it stays in the sense in
This investment system
Answer to the extent that happened
The money will find its way towards some new investment to be made
Better words
A good outcome no matter what they come
All right Carlos Garcia
You're skeptical and and I'm just curious if Carl has convinced you of anything
She did convince me about this
Specific argument he's making about the
Corporate tax
That there's a good chance
That'll leave
Invest at least
Some of it
Sure okay
That's not quite the end of the story though is it
Because there's something we kind of have to acknowledge about this
Tax rate cut
Which is that
Most people are going to bed
Directly from
The company's benefit Direct
Play from it they're the ones
To get higher profit
Most people sort of left of Hope
At the company's then use the money either
Invest more and make the workers better or
Did they hire more workers
Are they real
People salary
Do we need to wait and see who benefits
From this but
As you mentioned this is a
Cost
Leave tax Cut & Sew
It seems a little bit like a arrestor again
I think some of the most powerful
Criticisms of this bill
Haven't actually been centered on the fact that it
It's going to cost the government
A lot of money
The rather than if it's going to cost the government a lot of money there might have been
Better ways to use that money
It would have benefited
Did most Americans
Another word
There's a lot of people who agree
Did the corporate tax rate at 35% with
Too high
They just think that there were other ideas it could have had bigger benefit
It's foremost in mirror
Cardiff Garcia
Thank you for going on
Attacks Odyssey Forest by Pleasure
The tax bill is 1100 page
It is long obviously we didn't have time to get to everything but
If you're interested in other parts of it let us know about it we are Planet Money at npr.org or you can fight
Find us on Facebook
Can Twitter
Today's show was produced by Sally helm
Our editors
Is Bryant urstadt or supervising producer is Alex gold
And one more quick plug
To donate to your local NPR member station
I donate. Npr.org
3 / planet
We really appreciate the support and
Not only does it help us do our work but
It supports the important local journalism that NPR station
Are doing all around the country
Let's donate. Npr.org
Planet Money
I'm Kenny Malone
Thanks for listening