Hey ml to Chang we're about to play for UA
Classic episode of Planet Money
From 2014
It's about a very guarded industry full of tradesy
But the story really started
When David kestenbaum got a little hungry at work
The other day I went down to the lobby of our building here to get a snack
And I decided on Eminem's but I could not decide
Which kind
So I bought two packs
One regular M&M's
One peanut butter-filled
And in the elevator back up to the office so you know there's like never anything to do in the elevator actually started reading the labels
On these package
And
I found something really strange
Can I have one here
A pack of regular M&M's weighs 1.69 Oz
Pack of peanut butter M&M's
Slightly less
1.63 Oz
Are the same price a dollar each
But you get slightly less of the peanut butter M&M
0.06 Oz
Is it tiny different way down at the third decimal place
Discourse drove me crazy
So I started to look into it
That was a month ago
Turns out there is a whole weird world living down there at the third decimal place
When you pull in that little thread lots of things start to unravel
Today I'm going to take you down the Eminem Rabbit Hole I promise we'll never pop piece of candy in your mouth
Think about it the same way again
Support for this podcast and the following message come from fidelity
As a Fidelity wealth management client
You get a dedicated advisor to help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes and make clear recommendation
Thanks for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
When I get back to my desk I thought you know this is the kind of thing that someone probably has a whole blog post about
And there is nothing
I tried to lookup a company's annual reports Mars is the company that makes M&M's
But there are no annual
Sports
Marcella private company owned by the Mars fan
4 Generations
And they are incredibly secretive
Like a real-life Willy Wonka
I'm sure
Did they were
Hoping
No one like you would ever come along
To notice such a small
Tiny difference
This is Joelle Glenn Brenner
She used to work for the Washington Post and short a book called
The emperor's of chocolate
Inside the secret world of Hershey and Mars
She says she's the only journalist the Mars company has ever really let in
So I asked her
Am I crazy does this tiny little weight difference mean something
Is it just an accident
She said whatever is going on
It is no accident
2 even
Have got difference I can promise you with something
That was angst-ridden for the company
They don't want
Consumers
To have a question
Like that
The Mars family basically never ever gives interview
But I put in a request
And I kept digging
Trying to find out why one pack was slightly lighter than the other
I decided to track down a competitor after all who studies Eminem's more closely than a rival company
And I found a bill Edwards
Bill used to work for one of Mars's main rival
A company called Roundtree
Roundtree developed the British candy called Smarties which
A lot like Eminem
You should appreciate that
Victory in the street is incredibly sacred
How many more secrets of a Skype
Show me places where they make nuclear weapons
Celebrity Skype food places
Bill is a chemist by train
He's been a lot of time trying to reverse-engineer competitors products
He told me that he and his colleagues once did an extensive scientific analysis of Milky Way bar
To try to figure out why they had a double layer of Chaka
Quit coding
When you're doing something like that he says
Even little things like the weight of a package can be a clue
In some Industries companies spell out stuff like that in their patent Apple
But candy companies
Don't mess with patency says
Consider for instance the KitKat
Which is old employer invent
And I mean to be making kit kat change
Sec 1934
And
There's certain things in that process
Better than Titans
Filming in public in the 1950s
Do you know how Kit Kats are made
I do not get some ideas
You do
Yeah
Can you tell me
Secret
If I knew the secret would I think that's so
So cool
Adele Roundtree company used to have a rule
Santa be at least one difficult stage in each Pro
There are about a dozen difficult
Bill had a theory about the M&M puzzle
It's possible he said
That peanut butter M&M's
Are more expensive
That's true you'd want to put less of them in the package
Is the way to keep the profit margin the same
You're not going to tell you if you're not going to do wonders for your business
If you bring out a new product
Pitch Perfect movie images
I was like if you had M&M's are out there there's a certain profit margin
You've been introduced
Peanut butter M&M's you would never want to introduce that
Where you're going to make less money on a
I like the sex
Exactly what my sister has an NBA total
She thought was going on also
It made sense because
Imagine you introduce your exciting new peanut butter-filled Eminem
And people like them so much
They stopped buying the original milk
Chocolate and
And they switch to the peanut butter
If you're making less money per pack on the peanut butter ones
Congratulations your wonderful new product
Just lost you
Of course Mars could keep the profit margin the Same by discharging a little more than a dollar for the peanut butter M&M
Instead of putting Less in the package
John gourville
Professor of marketing at Harvard says
That's a really dumb idea
And companies almost never do
Imagine
Imagine if you did this with something like yogurt
Where
You know the peach yogurt is $0.79 the blueberry yogurt is $0.89 and the strawberry yogurt is nice
99 cents
You now are getting people thinking she's how much do I like strawberry relative to pee
Each is it worth a $0.20
It's just it's it's a layer of complexity that
Manufacturers would prefer not to get into
They want to make the decision making
Companies would rather adjust the amount of stuff in each package
So they can keep everything the same price
So that when you go to buy say M&M's
You're not doing math in your head comparing prices
You just going yeah I'm Eminem and they're all a dollar which one do I want
Even though the weights
If you look closely
Are slightly different
This was a beautiful Theory it explained everything
The dollar price of a later peanut butter M&M pack
It turns out unfortunately there's a problem
In order for it to be right peanut butter M&M's have to be more expensive to make
Remember that's why you get less in a package
But Bill Edwards the chemist told me that upon reflection
He's pretty sure peanut butter is cheaper than chocolate
I did some checking at bulk suppliers
And it seems to be
So much for the economic explanation
Maybe there was a scientific one
Is it okay if I buy a lot of Eminem
I went back down to the little store in the lobby of our building
And I bought what scientists would call a statistically significant sample size
Kennedy's
Spirit entities
I took the M&M's up to Columbia University
To a guy who had a really really precise scale
Sanat Kumar he's chair of the chemical engineering
Yeah this is a tenth of a gram and this is going to vent of a milligram
A thousand times smaller than what you looking for
This is a thousand times more accurate than we need
Talk about a little bit of an Overkill
0 that
It's not have a different
What if he said
Each bag gets filled by a machine
The drops that precise number of M&M's
Beach bag
Same number in each bag
Then if the peanut butter M&M's turn out to be a little bit later
That could explain why the package came out lighter
So we started Counting
Can 1214
One bag has 27
Another had 28
728 not keeping the number constant
It's all over the map
This is truly amazing
I have no idea what they're doing
Another beautiful Theory destroyed by date
We did discover something weird though
It would turn out to be
Critical clue
Something that somehow I'd never realized when I was shutting these things in my
And it's that the peanut butter M&Ms and the regular M&M's
Are totally different species
Original milk chocolate M&Ms are these small very precise candies with very precise weights
The peanut butter M&M's by comparison or Monster
Lumpier
Larger
We measured with the fancy scale
And a larger size turns out to be key to the whole puzzle
David pieces it all together after the break
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Delta
Delta flies to 300 cities around the world
Best 300 cities
It's where many people do the same things you do
That's 300 cities were people in those 300 cities think they're the only ones who know about that
One place and 300 cities where people miss someone
One and one of Delta's other 299 cities
Delta isn't flying to 300 cities merely to bring people together but to show that we're not that far apart
Martin the first
Delta
Keep climbing
Eventually got an email back from the Mars come
Declining our interview
Requests but it did include a statement
Which I think
Explains the whole mystery
Is nothing to do with the price of peanuts compared
Hector Coco
Or the number of M&M's that get dropped in the little bags
It was a different number
Calories
The statement said that for health and nutrition reasons
All Mars products are designed to be
250 calories or less
Proportion
It's not and I did the math
And it turns out because the peanut butter-filled M&M's are so big
If you add adjust
One more of them to the little packages
It would push the calorie count over 250
This Mark seems to be saying
Is why the package
Which weighs a little bit
I ran this by Joelle Glenn Brenner who wrote the book
On Mars and Hershey
The only Outsider who been allowed in
Do you believe this
That's on right to absolutely
She says the 250-calorie thing
That's become a kind of maximum
A line that the candy companies
Don't want to cross
Unacceptable
Snack
Calorie
Sauce
Anything larger than that you're talking like hamburger territory or something that's just too big that's not a
There was one other little things that still bug me
Why were the peanut butter M&M sober
Do I'll have an answer for this
Besides she thinks has been a long-standing problem
Album from Mars
Mars as big breakthrough with that the filling for its peanut butter M&M who's actual peanut butter
Reese's Pieces she says actually contain something called pinotage
Peanut meal
Which is easier to work with
Weather coat
True peanut butter she says
Is softer lumpier
Hard to work with
I am certain
But they did
Did herbal amount of engineering research
Search to see if there was any way possible
To reduce the overall size
Of that
Peanut butter M&M
So they could avoid this dilemma
I got avoid me calling them absolutely
But
They must have hit some wall
Where it just simply wasn't possible can get them any smaller and smaller
I sent Mars a follow-up email asking
Why the peanut butter M&M's were so much larger than the regular ones
The next day I got a one-sentence answer
Call
Because of proprietary reasons
We are unable to elaborate
On the size of peanut butter
Thanks for listening today and remember we love to hear
Email us at Planet Money at npr.org or find us on Twitter or Facebook at Planet Money this show is record
Are you back in 2014 by David kestenbaum and produced by phia bennin the rerun was produced by Kasia mihailov
Special things to Jennifer Hecht Penna and Jennifer John who helped way the M&M's at Columbia
Alex goldmark is are supervising producer and Brian Dorsett headed to show and if you're looking for another
You should listen to check out the NPR politics podcast with the great team of reporters I use word on that desk and you can
Keep up with everything going on Washington and Country all in one place with the Super Start
Eternal love for the NPR politics podcast on the NPR 1A NPR. Org
The cast or wherever you find your podcast to change thanks for listening