Robert Smith there are two sides to this work which side you want to be you want to be Andrew Jackson or Nicholas Day
Gettel of course
Twitter
Okay I'll do enter jacks
When Andrew Jackson was 13 years old
He went off to fight the British in the Revolutionary War
When Nicholas Biddle was 13 years old
He transferred from the University of Pennsylvania to Princeton
Jackson was a poor kid his father was an Irish immigrant who died before Jackson was
Little lizard
Part of Philadelphia Society
515 Andrew Jackson isn't
Basically alone in the world
515 Biddle graduated the top of the class Princeton
And with the help of family connections he sells off to Europe to take the grant
Andrew Jackson killed a man in a duel
Leave the heroic battle in the war of
1012 Nicholas Biddle and it's a literary journal called pork
Foolio
Writer's pen name Oliver olds
Finally of course Andrew Jackson becomes president of the United States
And Nicholas Biddle becomes president
Of the bank
Of the United
At the peak of their careers
Biddle and Jackson get into a fight
Jackson wants
How to kill beetles
And Biddle wants to kill Jackson's president
Close walking to Planet Money
And I'm Robert Smith today on the show we are going to tell you a 200 year old story
Because
It's just a delightful Amazing Story there's a rich Banker
Is a populist president who hates the elite and there was a panic
In the streets
And this fight between Andrew Jackson and Nicholas Biddle
In a way it's still going on today
It's a fight over who gets to control money in America
We'd like to say a quick thank you and share a message from one of our sponsors freshbooks
It's 2017
And the all-new freshbooks Cloud accounting software is so ridiculously easy to use
Over 10 million small businesses are now using it working in this ever-expanding DIY economy
Send a branded invoice in under 30 seconds
Avoid awkward client Schatz by automating your late payment reminders
Amtrak every billable moment from your phone
For your 30-day free trial go to freshbooks.com Planet Money
An inter Planet Money in the how did You Hear About Us section
Right in the middle of the city of Philadelphia
And you can see it to this day
There is a building that looks like
The Parthenon
Big me to Stone
There so many
So many definitely more columns
In the 1820s this building with the center
Of the American Financial world
It was the bank
Of the United States
The bank of the United
States in the 1812
It was unlike
Anything we have in this country
In fact
It was unlike anything else we had in the country back then
There were lots of little local state
But the bank of the US was the
Only Bank in the
The top rated all over the
It was created by an act of Congress that David a monopoly to do that
The federal government kept its money there. It's banking with the bank of
But the bank of the US was a private Corporation
Invisible to its shareholders
Run for a profit
And inside
This Greek
Building
In the very back and a giant office
Was a man with his fingertips stuck together in a thousand yard stare
Bones of Alexander Hamilton
Nicholas Biddle
The president
Of the bank of the United States
In any movie of this bill would be the villain
Oh
Oh you hurt me saying that
Cordelia Francis Biddle
Nicholas Biddle
Great
Granddaughter
You're right person
Well I take it personally because I'm writing about him
It's not even personal to Biddle though like you don't I mean it's just
Structural he's like
The rich Banker
Like of course he's the villain
Of course you're absolutely right and I would have thought I would have said that
4 years ago
You're a Biddle
Cordelia's opinion about her
Whatever great great
Great-grandfather
It changed when she learned something important
About him
Nicholas Biddle was really good at his job
As you know head of the bank of the US
And that was
Really good for the US in a bunch of
The bank of United States was doing a lot of the economics
Stop that today is the job
Government
Federal Reserve
Soap for one thing
The bank of the us back then
Printed paper money
At the time official government money was just
Gold and silver
The government didn't make any paper money
And if you took a gold coin to a local bank that bank would give you
Piece of paper
What's the bank's name on it
Can I owe you a claim check
You or anyone else could
Turn that into the bank
To get your gold back
These banknotes
Became functionally money
Almost all the banks in the country
Hit the spot because the bank
The US was the only National Bank
It's banknotes worth
We're way better at you could use them anywhere in the country
And I made it much easier to do business all around the country
You could get a big town in New York City spending New Orleans
There was another thing the bank did for the country under Biddle that was really important
It cushioned economic booms and busts
Today that is what the Federal Reserve.
The job of the Central Bank
But that didn't exist
Back that it wasn't even created until the 20th century
So bill would be there you know working in
And its economy seemed a little anemic a little slow
He could make more loans you can make it easier for people to borrow money
And if the economy seemed a little overheated maybe saw bubble out there on the horizon he could make it harder
For people to borrow money
It was an incredible amount of power
And having all of this power
Put Biddle at the center of this
Small Club of elite or running
America
And he is
Great friends with
All the all the presidents
With atoms with with Madison
Then you can see even just threw his
Diary writing
He he loved being this big
He loved being a banker so much
You are the poem
Granny
There's a couple
I prefer my last letter from bearings or hope
Berrington helper bags
I prefer my last letter from bearings or hope to the finest Epistles of Plenty or Pope
Who are writers
If is Pliny
Pliny the Elder
Don't know he was not much of a poem
He was really good at banking Nicholas
Old school Beetle had found his face
Running the bank of United
He figured you do it forever
There was only one thing standing in his way
Andrew
Jack's
As far as I can tell Jackson is the only person who would become president of the United
To Kill a Man In Cold Blood
This is HW Brands historian at the University of
He said
You know Jackson was not in biddle's
Clubwear you pal around with former presidents and write poems about Bank
Using the club of people who shot at each other in duel
He told us about this time that
Jackson demanded a duel from Charles Dickinson
A man would need the bad choice
Insulting Andrew Jackson
He
Stood
Took a bullet
From Dickinson
The bullet lodged itself quite close to Jackson carpet just miss
Antarctica's Jackson with a skinny guy and he was wearing this order
Large Overcoat
And with that bullet next to his heart
Jackson level his piss
And
Shot
Charles Dickens
Mortally wounded him he died
Several hours later
Little people love
These kind of stories
About Andrew Jackson when he was the original
He could stand in the middle of Fifth Avenue shoot somebody
And not lose voters
Yunnan
De Jackson is this
Is this really very controversial figure
Maybe best-known out for the poorest equate he treated Native American
But at the time
That was not the way people saw Jack
They saw this as this man of the people
And that he was bringing the people with him into the White House I'm quite
Literally know these stories about his inauguration
Party where there's
Skills of liquor and it's
Crowded
When people are breaking Clipper like rushing the people bringing up the whiskey
Punch out at it's like knocking it over it got so out of hand had to move the whiskey punch
Out onto the front lawn just to get p
People out of the White House
Classic solution
No more booze in the house
And what did he good populist Jackson did not like
In this particular case he even hated paper money
He thought the country should just be run on gold and silver
Which was not
Like some crazy friends viewer
I mean to get your head into it think about the way a lot of people feel now about
Like all this
Sketchy
Mortgage products that Banks cooked up in the housing bubble of the 2000s
That is how a lot of people thought about paper money
And for good cause I mean thanks for the 1800
Would all the sudden
Just go out of business
And the bank. There are no use for gold the paper money would be worthless
To imagine them how Jackson felt about a bank of the United States
With special
Powers granted by the Federal Gov
It was a private bank
It had his own board of directors
And people increasingly thought
This
Sing the National Bank
Corroborated
At the behest of the government ought to be answerable to the government
But this Bank of the United States was not answerable to be
See if a President Who hates bags
Who is
Literally killed another human being
And Nicholasville decide he's going to go visit him
And it's shockingly cordial
Jackson says the Biddle here's the quote
I do not dislike your bank any more than all
Another widget not personal I just think what you do is it
Total scam that is bad for America
Evan Biddle says
Well I'm very much gratified at this
Frank
Explanation
In other words
Thanks for not shooting me let's not do this kind of meeting ever again
And then after the meeting
Little Spike telling his friend about you
He called Jackson's ideas about banking
Quote
Be honest
The erroneous Notions of one who intends well
In other words I take Jackson seriously
But not literally
But they don't know
Trouble is
The bank of the United States
It has to be
We authorized every 20
Just to stay in business
Congress has to pass a bill and the president has to sign it into law
Otherwise the bank is done
It's a Biddle comes up
With this plant he is going to go on
Defensive
Key figures people are kind of like in the Bank of the United States
Jackson's up for re-election I'm going to push this bill now get it quickly before Congress and
Put pressure on Andrew Jackson to renew my precious picture
So Biddle pull together this Army of
Supporters Inc
You know powerful politician
Well connect
Did politicians and he's like his
Stop
Player in Congress
Is the senator for Massachusetts
Daniel Webb
If you were alive in the 1820s
You would be so
Excited right now
When Daniel Webster Rose to speak
Washington stopped
Doing what it was doing
People flock to the Senate
To listen to Daniel Webster it was high drama
It was wonderful entertainment and
You could be educated in the process
What people didn't General Lee know
Was that
Daniel Webster was on a retainer
With the bank of the United
He was getting paid by the bankers
Yeah he's getting paid by Nicholas Biddle person
Too well to represent the bank
While he was a senator
For Massachusetts
Is that legal
What's that legal could you do that
It wasn't illegal
So the great order and paid shill
Daniel Webster Rises
Just to speak
He says many of you
Many few including
President do not like Banks printing all of this paper money in
I got it
You want safe and sound money
He said
Okay
If you want safe and sound money
And who doesn't
The bank of United
What states is good
Pause off the bank of the US is your friend
The bank of us is a cautious conservative Bank
It doesn't just run around printing paper money like crazy in fact it rains in all of those States
He says
And I do quote
In the absence of a bank of the United States
The State Banks become effectively The Regulators of the public currency
Their numbers their capital and the interest connected with them
Give him a power
Which nothing
Is competent
To control
In other words Webster sing if you think the bank of the United States is Shady and out of control
You should see the statement
And
Send it
Congress passes a law to give bittles Bank another 20 years of life
Beetles in Washington DC for the event
And he gets cheered inside the capital E throws a party that goes late Into the Night
And then
On July 4th
As it happens 1832 that bill lands on Jackson
Desk for him to sign into law
Jackson looks at it
That is it for a moment
And says
Oh hell no
Go to direct quote with Jackson does veto the bill
Who writes this famous
Veto message like this
Populist.
That says in park
When the laws make the rich
Witcher and the potent more powerful
The Humble members of society have a right to come
Plane of the Injustice of their
The bank of the United States will be no more
And Biddle
Actually thinks at this moment
Got him right where I walked her
He thinks this veto is going to
Off Jackson the election he called him like
Panther biting at the bars
Cajun
Pays to reprint thousands of copies of this veto message to use as like an attack ad
Auntie mescal
People love the
Papito beloved The veto message right the humble members of society
People's president overruling a corrupt Congress
The fight elite bankers and you cannot lose with that
Jackson wins re-election in a landslide
5 years later
The economy of the United States
Is completely destroyed
Yeah
About that
Literally stuff to Daniel Webster was paid to say
It all came to pass
After the bank of the United States disappeared
The government had to find a place to
To put
It's money
Jackson publicity was says okay let's send the money out all the
State bags
State Banks all over the
The State Bank start lending money like crazy printing paper money
Fueling this massive land boom that turns into a massive bubble which means more loans
More money people buy more land
Andrew Jackson's like wait wait wait this was not the plan I wanted to list
Paper money
Soap so he make this last minute
Change
It requires that some land purchases be made
Not with paper money
But with gold
Yeah but nobody has gold XL there is this
Panic it is the biggest financial crisis in US history to this
The economy crash is so hard
The government itself
Can't get its gold out of
And this isn't
Just a financial prop
This is an entire economic
Cyclops people lose their jobs there's not enough money around
In fact
Researchers have gone back and they figured out that children who were born during the panic of 1837
Grew up to be shorter
10 people who were born before
Caramel nurse
The Panic caused them to go hungry
Ask Nicholas Biddle
She had to watch
Not only this Christ
Display out around him
But here to watch his bank his organization that you built crumble
To nothing
The bank of the United States
Glorious building in Philly
Get a new name
The bank of the United States
Of
Couch
Just another state bank now
Just another State Bank
And even that goes bust in
Cordelia Biddle told me that at the end Nicholas Biddle this manhood
How the round with presidents
He just kind of disappeared from public life
It mean it really is a very sad and because
Here's this man who
Who felt that he devoted his life to his country
And he's
Send packing
It's
It's it's terrible
For the next seventy years
United States goes from panic
And even after the United States government created a true Central Bank
The Federal Reserve in the early 1900
Even then
This fight
Continuing something
I think
I think that's because of something really
Central
About money itself
Your money is
Is like this utility we all need it
We all use it
It's created by the devil
But
You need more than just
Every successful economy has private Banks
It's the market
Bitconnect savers
Borrowers
Decide who should get a loan and this gives Banks dislike spooky power over our lives
They control money
Freak. Jackson freaks out people to the Safeway
You know you see today's famous senator from
Massachusetts Elizabeth Warren
Arguing with some Bank CEO and it feels connected
Right after doing the story I don't think anymore oh this is just some like
Temporary fight that's happening because of the financial
You know I don't think there's some
Utopia are some steady state even where everybody's like oh wait the government's going to get this power over money and
And things are going to get
That power over money
And it's done we worked it out
I don't think that I think this fight over money between the government and Banks
This is our system
The bank war is never going
Evergreen history story has a small foot
We're going to do footnotes for the show support for Planet Money and the
Following message come from ishares because the best preparation for tomorrow is building for your pee
Future today ishares by BlackRock inspired to build
Email us at Planet Money at mpr.org or you can get in touch with us on Facebook or Twitter or show today was produced by
Sally Helm special thanks to Jessica Leffler and liaquat Ahmad both come talk to me for a long time about
Banking in the early part of the nineteenth
I also you should tell a friend
How about a podcast that you maybe in Planet Money maybe it's one of my favorite podcast I liked
Tutor
Whenever you like
Put on social media and use the hashtag tripod
Try
Tod
Footnotes
What does number one
It is an enduring mystery how a president like Andrew Jackson
Who created paper money
Got his face on the $20 bill
We Believe Nicholas Biddle would have been a better choice
He thought that he was
Very handsome
Do you think he was handsome
For the.
Yes
I don't even know what that means
Footnote number 2
When you're talking to historian about this show and you want to sound smart
And you well you should refer to biddle's bank at the second
Bank of the United
Cuz America tried this whole thing before with the first
I think the United States
Existed from 1791 to 1811
We would have told you that story about it
Less interest
Not necessarily
Failed to get retarded by single vote in the Senate
Footnote number 3
Our last foot
Regarding
The panic of 1837
There's a book I read a working on the show called The Mini
Panic of 1837
We put the fact that there was a lot going on we didn't talk about all that.
You don't contributing factors included changes in credit in England
One historian has argued that actually changing demand for opium in China contributed to the panic
I don't understand exactly what it has to do with
Silver from Mexico and Britain
Trade with India I don't know that's amazing
We keeping the week
But it certainly fair to say that the end of the second Bank of the US
Played an important role in the Panama
I'm Jacob
I Roberts babe thanks for listening