Support for NPR and the following message come from service now making the world of work
Work better for people
Their cloud-based platform and solutions deliver digital workflows that create great experiences and
Unlock productivity for your whole company
More at servicenow.com
For those of you out there who are collecting the Donald Trump Russia Scandal trading cards I know you are
There emerged a new name this week
To add
To the pack
Natalia
Destiny Skye
Natalia veselnitskay
Yuba City
She's a Russian
Who met with Donald Trump jr. during last year's presidential campaign
Junior wanted to get some dirt on him
But what
Did Natalia
Want out of this meeting what did Russia want out of this
Most people had never heard of her before this
But a man named Bill Browder hat
Natalia has been sort of my archenemy for the last three and a half years
Bill Browder used to be one of the biggest foreign investors in Russia
Gas and oil companies in metal companies
Because the Russian government
Kick Bill Browder out of the country
Took away his companies threatened his life
Went after his lawyer
Sue Bill Browder got
Congress to pass the law punishing the Russians involved
And this law was
What led to that Trump meeting were all talking about
This woman Natalia veselnitskaya went to Donald Trump jr.
To talk about one thing and one thing only which was the repeal
How to make niskey Act
Which is a piece of legislation which imposes Visa sanctions and asset freezes on
Russian torturers and murderers including
How does torturers murderers who murdered Sergei magnitsky who is my lawyer in Russia
Hello and welcome to Planet Money on Robert Smith
Tax fraud and murder
Form a web of events that may have led to a speaker meeting with the president's son and his closest advisers
Bill Browder went to Russia to make a forge
I'm self in a fight with Russian oligarchs over money and power
And he lost his companies but it cost him to life
Write a story explains a lot about what the Russian government what
Billy Vladimir Putin
Once from the president of the United States
And how far he'll go together
This message comes from NPR sponsor Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimum
That can be opened from anywhere in 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Bill Browder was brought up to challenge
Authority his grandfather was a labor union organizer
President of United
States on the Communist Party ticket
His Russian grandmother was threatened with deportation during the McCarthy era
Patterson Self was
Always looking for a rule to break
So I was going through my teenage rebellion back in in the 1970s
And I was trying to figure out a great way to repel from this family communist
So I grew my hair long that didn't upset my parents I followed the grateful Dad that didn't have any impact
But one day
I came up with the perfect
Rebellion I'm for my family which was to put on a suit in time become a capitalist
And there was nothing I could do to piss off my family more than that
Router got an economics degree from the University of Chicago and MBA from Stanford and by the time he graduated he had found the purse
Perfect place to
To be a cowboy cap
Places grandparents left Russia
Is 1996 after the fall of the Berlin Wall
Russia wants to ditch
Communism overnight
They have all these old
State-owned companies they want to make private
It was some complete
Wild West Gold Rush type of situation
The Russian government had basically in their own efforts to go from communism to capitalism
They basically gave all the state assets away for free
So could you walk in and buy a factory
You could do anything you walk in by an oil company you can walk in buy a Timber Mill you can walk and do anyting
This isn't rocket science you basically could buy an oil company at a 99.9% discount
The same type of oil company in the west and so
The real
Trade was
You are already going to lose all your money if they take it away from you or is Russia going to get go from Total Chaos to a little bit less
Chaos because of ghosts
Total chaos to a little less chaos
You make 10
23 times your money
That was the capitalist dream
Soap router started and invest
Add fund at fund it would eventually be the largest one in Russia with assets worth
Billions of dollars
And we found out was it just by investing in Russia
He was suddenly thrust into this whole power struggle
Because
You couldn't just
Buy stock in a company and walk away you had to go inside each business get your hands dirty
Figure out
How a Russian business work
But what I discovered was that some there was a pretty good reason for
Why these companies were so cheap because even if you want to share of the company
A share of anything because the people who control these companies the Russian oligarchs
We're basically I'm stealing money from the companies hand-over-fist
And so at as a matter of necessity
I'm I became an anti-corruption activist
I'm trying to protect my investments
And so I just like you I mean someone trying to make money off of a country going through transition
They were but that didn't that there's two ways that people were thinking about making money you could either
Own a company in in own the shares and end
Managed it honestly and have the value of the company rise
That's that was my way
Their way the oligarchs way was to own a company and just suck out all the cash into their pockets
And I worry about the value of the shares but just worried about
Their pockets
Brother had a strategy
Every time you would discover corruption at one of these companies he was investing in
Alex bozich in the Russian media and
Wild and interesting thing happen
Each time he did it
Amanda Vladimir Putin wood
Step in and make a big show of holding
High-level oligarchy
Accountable
Uptime Putin was not the all-powerful leader of Russia that we know now
He was a new president with pretty weak Authority
My poop was making a big show of fighting
Corruption that's how he was gaining popularity and he especially liked the target corruption
Among his political rivals
We had a Confluence of interests the oligarchs were stealing power from him
And they were stealing money for me
The bill Browder did not
No Vladimir
What is conflict of interest lasted for years the arrangement work
The Russian economy boom
Putin amassed an incredible amount of power
Embroider got rich
But at some point routers
Stop being useful to Putin
Winston had the power he needed he didn't need
Fresh the remaining oligarchs
A foreigner like Browder
Was just
Starting to get in the way
In November 2005 Bill Browder was at the Moscow Airport
Houston the VIP lounge of course
And then into this room stormed for heavily-armed Border guards who grabbed me
Frog March me down to the basement of the airport into the Detention Center on this is not very nice
I'm thinking waffles
What the heck
What's going on here
Heart pumping adrenaline
Flowing through my veins
What have I done am I being arrested
Where why there are they taking me why they doing this and they wouldn't tell me anything
He's locked up overnight
And then the next morning the guards reappear
And say
You've been declared a threat to National Security
You're out of here you're out of Russia we are supporting you on the next flight
They grabbed me
Woke me right up to the airplane stick me in the middle seat on the airplane flight
And that that was last time I was in Russia
I love how they stick you in the middle
Believe me I was very happy to be on that airplane we could have put me in the toilet and I would have been
I would have been happy
Bill Browder had no more allies in Russia
Any new the Clock Was tickin
He moved to London
He told all his employees to leave Russia
Quickly as possible
Insurgent quietly cell
His Investments
Anyone
Who would buy them
And it worked
He got his money out routers gamble on Russia paid off
Anybody never given a thought to Russia again
But more than a year later
He gets this panic
Call from the last employee left
In his Moscow office
I got a phone call from from my from secretary saying there's
There's 25 officers here what should I do
And I said I don't know let me call my lawyer I called up my lawyer guy American guy named Jameson
Etta James in my office is being rated what should I do when he said I don't know my officers are being rated as well they're looking for your stuff
I remember there was no money
Leptin
Office there was no real business being done
And there they were just a few.
And that's what the police walked out
Obviously this all seems really suspicious
Router wanted to figure out what they were up to so he found attacks
Named Sarah Kate Meghan
Sergei was the smartest lawyer
In Moscow
Objectively he was one of these people
I could do 10 things in the time
Others to do one
Red circles around everybody else
Is 35 years old that's incredibly
Smart
But most importantly honest and Earnest man
And
We are we hired him to help us figure out what was going on
Is there any tracks the documents
The police stole
She find something out it's kind of amazing
Why the police had these documents
These dogs Were Somehow used to transfer ownership
Of the company away from Bill Browder
Just some Russian dude
And that guy clearly had a plan
You know how in the United States someone can get a hold of your Social Security
And I apply for a tax refund in your name to the government it is a pretty
Common scam here
Well
Apparently the same thing was happening with routers
Company
Whoever took control of these documents of the company
Apply for a tax refund
From the Russian government
A massive
Tax refund
230 million dollars
What's the largest tax refund in the history of Russia
And it was approved
And paid out
The next day
With no questions asked
I'm not sure there's any government in the world
Who would give you a 230 million dollar tax refund
The next day I mean it just seems insane it
Service engine soon to attack
Lawyer like Sergei magnitsky
And he thinks you know
This has to be
A criminal plot
You have to involve
The rug police officers who took the documents
Probably includes tax officials
Sausser Caicos
To the Russian
He tells them what happened
He testified
He takes it all the way the top telling them that this
This could very well be
The largest
Text scam in Russian
History
And then we sat back
And waited for the good guys to get the bad guys
It just turned out
Heading Putin's Russia
There are no good guys
Somebody clearly wanted this story
To go away
And the easiest way to make a scandal go away
What's to make Sergei
Go away
November 24th 2008
Police officers showed up at staircase door width
An arrest warrant
His wife was in a total
State of
Panic
And he tried to calm her down he said don't worry I'll be back tomorrow
He gets thrown in prison
Pretrial detention is what they called it
But it becomes clear pretty quickly that what they really wanted
Was to blame someone
For that giant
Tax fraud
They kept telling him to confess and Sara gay being a good lawyer that he was
Documented what happened to him every single day
They put him in cells
With 14 inmates in eight beds
And left lights on 24 hours a day
I put them in cells with no heat
And no window panes in December in Moscow
Nearly froze to death
How they put them in cells with no toilet
Just a hole in the floor where the sewage with bubble
They moving from cell to cell to cell
In the middle of the night
I think they moved him 28
Different times ms358 days in detention
And all through the Sergei magnitsky is filing legal complaints about his treat
He filed
450 formal complaint
Over a year
He competed to believe that a judge somewhere
Which stop what was happening to
Trudy had this strange
Idealistic view of the law
He was like a lawyer's lawyer and he really believed
The law would ultimately overcome everything he knew there's a lot of
Human Frailty in the system in the government
In the police etcetera buddy but he also believe that ultimately the law was the law
And while all of this is going on Browder is reading each of these excruciating update
Spitzer gauge riding he's learning about sergei's awful conditions
But he's powerless to do anything
No one ever answered any of Sergei magnitsky
And eventually got sick
Critically
Instead of putting him in the emergency room
They put him into an isolation cell
They changed him to a bed
And it a tribe guards with rubber batons
Beat him
Until he died
He was 37 years old
He left a wife and two children
I was November 16th 2009
Seven and half years ago
Bill Browder found out what happened to Sergei the next day
And he was stunned
What happened how
No
Happy
And when I finally
Was able to
Calm down enough to look at the situation objectively
It was clear that I had only one choice
Which was to put aside everything else I was doing
An undervote
All of my time energy and resources to go after the people that killed him and make sure they faced Justice
Bill Browder cannot travel to
He cannot sue the people
He thinks are responsible
But since he's a finance guy router knows how to
Hit them where it hurts
In the bank account
It was already concern in the financial World about corruption in Russia and
Sergei magnitsky dramatic story becomes
This symbol
Just how bad
Things have gotten there
Router tells his story again and again and again and he said if you want to fight corruption in Russia
You want to get Justice for Sergei magnitsky
Then let's
Freeze the money
Of the people responsible it's freeze their bank account
After years of lobbying
Router gets a u.s. senator on board
They dropped a bill
What's the name of the spread
The magnitsky ACT
Up 2012
And it passes
The u.s. congress with huge bipartisanship
This act
Includes a list of Russian names of people suspected to have a role in Saturday's death
And the law bans these people from entering the US and
Freezes their assets
They're Now 44 names on the magnets
And some of them are the most
Powerful people in Russia
Either we now have the
Head of the Russian State investigative committee there FBI
Alexander bust Ricans on the list
BM deputy
Prosecutor Russia Victor green is on the list
Have a deputy
Interior minister
Alexia nietzscheans on the
Judges
And the police officers the ones who did the raid
The ones that custody of the documents
The jailers
All these people are on the list
You know who is not on the list
Vladimir
Putin but apparently he was majorly pissed off by the mere existence
Of this list because this was
This is the US the world really taking aim at members was governor
These are the people closest
Yeah an alarm even possible for them to do business in the United States do business with
US Bank switch
Pretty much means business anywhere in the world
No the Russian government says it had nothing
To do with Sergei magnitsky
That he died of natural causes and if there's anybody involved who committed fraud it's there he magnitsky and Bill Browder
So Putin retaliated
And he retaliated within days
And this is how we did it if you remember back then thousands of Americans were adopting
Russian children from orphanage
Who's big thing in the 90s
And who decides to ban
U.s. citizens from adopting Russian kids
Never mind that this move
Hurt
Children babies hurt
Family
Wanted
U.s. citizens to be out
What she wanted us
I hate this because he wanted to send a message
That the US Congress
Should I unfreeze it
His friends assets
Okay so
Now let's bring the story back to this week
Natalia veselnitskaya the Russian lawyer that Trump jr. met with
I spent the last few years trying to pressure the US to repeal the magnitsky ACT
She lobbied us officials just try to discredit Bill Browder
And that's why she wanted to meet with
Trump jr. so badly
And when they said afterwards oh
We just talked about adoption
What they're really saying is that they
Talked about the magnitsky
Russia
Wants to know
Whether Donald Trump would be willing
To negotiate to talk about this issue of Russian bank account
To talk about this issue of the magnitsky
Versus
He is not at all surprised that Sarah gay story would come up again in the news
Russia has never given up this fight
Russian officials have
Called Browder a liar and issued arrest warrants against him
They make comments that suggested life isn't danger to and and he is well aware that people
Who have fallen out of favour with
The Kremlin have wound up
Dead
I got I got to be living completely different life than the average person which is to think very carefully about
Everything I do and what risks I take by doing it
I never go to the same restaurant twice
Really
You can't go back to a favorite restaurant
Brother went to Russia
Cuz it was the wild
Because they were no rules and so it seemed like an easy place
To make a ton of money
And now
You know talking him he just
He just blames himself
Forever wanting to set foot
Russian flag
The lesson that I've learned is that
Laws matter
The rule of law matters
Integrity matters
And if you don't have that in a in a
System in a society
And pretty much everything is worthless
Something to keep in mind
The next time a Russian lawyer calls you up
For secret meeting
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Slack
Give us by companies all over the world
To get everything done
Where every part of work
From documents to decisions is stored archived and searchable in seconds
Slack
Where work happens
Find out why
At slack.com
Today Show is produced by Elisabeth Kubler-Ross and Sally Helm our editors reinartz taxonomy
How many senior producer is Alex goldmark
If you'd like to hear more about the story Bill Browder wrote a book about his experience in Russia
It's called the red notice
The true story of High Finance murder
And one man's fight for just
If you're looking for something else to listen to check out hidden brain
Robert that was so funny I didn't get it each week they try to get it why we do what we do
Why are some people really great at recognizing faces
Or why do some people lie more than others
That's hidden brain
You can find it on the NPR one app or whatever you get your
I'm Elsa Chang Robert Smith thanks for listening