At first
Charlie's friends life was like a dream for young entrepreneur
By the time he was 22 years old
The company had started in his parents basement in Brooklyn and hit the big time
He had dozens of new in
Employees company got a real office in Manhattan
Cool high-tech name bitinstant
Somebody even wrote them a jingle to use in their ads
Do you remember the bitinstant theme song
If you have course I can sing it word for word
Would you
Yeah it's
It's your money why wait
Berenson Scott lowest rate
Get Bitcoin the fastest way in is like
Optonline
The place my order quake
Are all those all those words
As you might have guessed from the lyrics bitinstant mission was
To help people buy Bitcoin
This is back in 2012
Digital currency like Bitcoin
We're just starting to get hot did you buy Bitcoin you would have to arrange with somebody somewhere
Who knew somebody who was willing to sell you some
Or you have to wire money to a big Exchange in Japan
And wonder if you actually get the Bitcoin
Bitinstant made it as easy as getting a money
You can walk into a Walmart
Or pharmacy tech Duane Reade
Give them cash and walk out with Bitcoins in your digital wallet
Theevandi Bitcoin transactions online
Charlie says there was a lot of demand
We are processing
Over $9 a day
One of the things that people like about digital currency like Bitcoin
Was it unlike Bank transfers or personal checks
Bitcoin that you buy things anonymously
Which was really attractive to a certain kind of person
Drug dealers
Also drug buyers truck buyers to
There was a website called Silk Road where people could buy and sell
Marijuana
Cocaine
Ketamine
Horse tranquilizers Hitmen one time Hitman okay one hit
All those people using Silk Road
They drove up the demand for Bitcoin
Which Charlie says
Makes sense when you think about it
It's always going to be the people that need to use something the most hurt me the first ones to use it
One of the people who needed to use Bitcoin
Was a man who went by the screen name
BTC King
Bitcoin cash
On Silk Road BTC King served as a money changer for all the drug buyers and sellers
Who wanted to trade dollars for Bitcoin
And BTC King he got Bitcoins from Charlie shrem Company
Bitinstant
It seems to me that you knew
Roughly what this guy was up to
And
And yet
We were sort of like
Let's go ahead and do that
Curious like what you're thinking was
In terms of
Back in that moment
I wasn't thinking
That was the whole point
And for a couple of years not
Thinking
Worked out just fine for Charlie
In fact it was really really profitable
Twenty-two-year-old Charlie shrem was a million
Is there a moment that you remember
When you were kind of like
Oh no I've gone way too far down this road
Yeah
Baidu
Now is the moment that replacing the handcuffs on my hands
Glow looking to Planet Money I'm Robert Smith and I'm Keith Romer
Today on the show The Story of Charlie shrem
How does Kid From Brooklyn went from living in his parents basement
Living the life of a Bitcoin millionaire
Tube
Well Federal Prison
Charlie shrem Odyssey into prison and back out again
He's a kind of parable for everything that has happened
With Bitcoin in The Last 5 Years
Charlie and Bitcoin
I've gone from being idealist
2 Outlaws 2
Trying to make it as respectable citizen
Support for this podcast
And the following message come from upwork
The largest freelancing website connecting businesses with top web and mobile developers designers writers
And other Freelancers ready to Linda
Over a million businesses are getting more done by finding hiring and paying Freelancers through up
To learn how you can get more done with Freelancers
And save $100 on your first project
Go to upwork.com money
Understand
How and why Charlie shrem ended up in handcuffs
It helps you get your head around the culture that surrounded a lot of the early enthusiasm
You know that guy in high school who
Picks up Ian Rand
For the first time
The Fountainhead and then
Cannot stop talking about this new
World and what it means man
That was the young Charlie shrem
Only instead of The Fountainhead
For Charlie it was
Bitcoin was going to be the key to unlocking the libertarian Utopia of the future
Because think about it Bitcoin is sort of the exact opposite of something like a credit card
Credit card leave the whole paper trail that can
Be tracked by Banks or the government
If they want to get up and do your business
Chinese Bitcoin takes a power back from the banks of the government and gives it to individual
At the end of a like I have a dollar bill I handed
To you
There's no one in between the transaction
There's no law that prevents me from handing you a dollar bill
Take one is the same way so that same way that I can hand you a dollar
And the room can no longer be in the room
No one can see it now
Hear it
I can send a dollar to someone in China
The same exact way
If everyone used Bitcoin
Charlie evangelized
The time government wouldn't be able to control how and where people spent their money
Big Banks wouldn't be able to get rich charging people for moving their own property
From one place to another
Charlie didn't just kind of thing
Remember he was 22 and he was one of those twenty-two-year-old who is so sure he's figured everything out
I believe that I was
Completely right about everything all the time
Including you know that it was okay for his company to help
Drug dealers buy Bitcoin
You know who didn't think it was okay for a company to do that
The federal government
Charlie was just coming back from a Bitcoin conference in Europe when he was arrested at JFK
I did a perp walk
Into waiting vans
And then
Metropolitan Correctional Center
I wouldn't wish it on my worst enemy
In the end Charlie was convicted of aiding and abetting the operation of an unlicensed money transmitted
He was sentenced
Did two years in federal prison in Pennsylvania
You got to prison
And you say goodbye to your family
Strip down naked
The guards take away your clothes they do a full body search cavity search check
Eye doctor looks you over you get you
The prison uniform
Your bunk assignment
You're on your way
Prison was hard for Charlie at
You ever have that
That feeling that you want to cry but you
You hold yourself back
And you just want to start bawling any other place to cry in the shower
How long did that feeling last
3 weeks
That sounds like a terrible few weeks
Who was
Charlie is 5 foot 4 he's not a big guy
And there is in federal prison
He's scared I mean scared of what's going to happen
One night
Early in the sentence
He's reading in the prison dorm
And one of the other inmates comes up there
In the middle of night
Semi huge guy walked up to me and thought he was going to beat me up
Because I have my light on
I said hey man you got to turn your light off
If you want to read here borrow my book light
I was like oh wow exactly like blending his book light
Because feel like that's a good outcome
Yeah he was really we ended up here
Weekly even make me Gyros like once a week he was really nice guy
Gyros like click click Heroes like Greek food
Nothing I mean like
Cooked on a radiator whatever it still
What's the time in prison
I truly didn't just get things for
Because in prison just like the outside world
You have
The pay for most
But you can't just
We change your pocket and pull out a $5 bill right in prison there is no paper money
For a while that you cigarettes but
Federal prisons outlawed cigarettes
I'm so now there's a bunch of different ways you can pay for the
The guy who fixes headphones only accepts protein bars
The guy who cut your hair
Wants
Jars of peanut butter
But I would say the overwhelming majority
How people would accept Mac
Just because everyone else would accept it
So if the guy if I only had mackerel
Big Mac album
Yes it was like they were like packets of mackerel
In soybean oil
Nicholas about a dollar fifty
These Vacuum Pack things of macaroni
We're basically occurrence
Prison and remember Charlie
Has a lot of
Fox about current problems that come up with current
How safe was a packet of mackerel in soybean oil as a currency
Someone could steal your life savings from underneath your bunk
Or the mackerel itself could go bad those packets of mackerel had a shelf life of eggs
3 years
And that happens
Not so easy to get your hands on more macro
There's a finite amount of money that people can send you from outside
And now you can spend
At the prison commissary
And even that there's a finite amount that you can actually
Spend every week
Each week one inmate was allowed to buy a maximum of 14 packets of Mac
But Charlie says at one point
The guard sees this one guy's entire supply of mackerel
Just left it out in the common area for anyone to take you know what happens when you give out free money
Inflation
Physical macro comes with all of these built-in problems
As a currency
So
Lying in his bed at night Charlie starts
What if prison mackerel could be more like 50
Inside of people trading like
I individual mackerels between each other they be able to trade
Digitize Mac
Charlie puth has
Plenty of time
The lightest car
Mary sleeps on end and do this thought
He's in prison
Nothing but time
Okay so obviously there are a lot of problems with setting up a new digital currency in prison
I mean maybe the most obvious one is
You're in prison they don't have computer
And this is where Charlie has an insight
What's important about Bitcoin
What's most revolutionary about Bitcoin
Is not
Bitcoin
Itself
It's how the Bitcoin system
Track where the money is
Yeah with Bitcoin the computers in the network keep a record of all the transactions if
People are making
The system even has its own catchy name they call it
The blockchain
A list of the latest transactions that the block
You think that block of transaction
The block
Before
Before that
But without computers Charlie has to think of a different way to
To do the macro block
Chain so thinks you know what if we just had inmates write down all the transaction
In physical notebooks
In blockchain lingo these inmates would be
Notes
I want to pay you to mackerel to give me a hair
Yep
Instead of trading the actual mackerel
We go to one of these nodes
One of these people and say hey
I have this money in my account
Can you transfer it to his account
That way no physical macro would have to change
All going to be in Tommy Knuckles notebook
I'll be back.
I made that up by the way to the best of our knowledge Charlie was not in prison with anyone named
Okay so he solved the first
Problem how do you record transact
That's done
But there's a second problem Charlie's Got saw
All the people he wants to use his macro currency with
The criminal
Every single one that
That's why they are in prison
Even
The trust is an issue
Acute issue
Naturally know the other inmates could just go to the warden
Like third-party and say hey
I'm not sure Tommy Knuckles is always writing down the right thing in his notebook with
Would you mind being in charge of the notebook maybe they don't want the warden to have all day
Or maybe they don't trust the warden to do a good job either
The question was how do you do it without a trusted third-party
How do you do it without a centralized
Authority so if you don't want the warden to be in charge
And you don't want one guy
Tommy knuckles
Being charged
What are you doing
You make it
So that no one isn't
Instead of just Tommy knuckles with his notebook
You get lots of different inmates in different parts of the
Prison all with their own notebooks writing down all the digital macro transaction
Happening in their parts
Just kills me at every every hour or so out in the yard
He's inmate note sit down with each other and copy the new transaction
Into the Roundup
Today update each other's now you have two notes
The Hobbit
Each of these guys meet with other guys
Notebook notebook
Books baguette notebooks
And all of a sudden everyone has the same record of transactions
It is a distributor
Ledger
As they like to say in the Bitcoin world
Distributed Ledger
Kelly did not
Please set up the whole digital currency in prison
Completely against prison rules
And Charlie had learned his lesson about break
He was in prison all together for a year-and-a-half
And in that time
He did try to keep up with what
What's going on in the outside world
Blockchain and Bitcoin and all the rest of it
What prison is not
A great place to
Keep track of what are the
Bitcoin kids are talking about on websites like Reddit
People with print out like the front page of
Reddit vim for send it to me
But you couldn't click on any of the links
I know that's why I was funny was so stupid
Making print out the front page of Reddit
Email it to me but I couldn't click the links
What Charlie would have learned if you'd been able to click on the
Lynx was it thinking about Bitcoin was undergoing this huge change while he was locked
It's in the focus being what Bitcoin could do to revolutionize the world
Now we will spend it look at what the
Technology underlined
The blockchain that
Distributed Ledger
Wet vac
Could do
On its own
And the people starting to get interested in blockchain and distributed Ledger stuff we're not just libertarian 22 year olds
Now you've got like the shouty financial journalist and Fortune Magazine a new report says the blockchain
I told you that underpins the digital currency Bitcoin will become Central to the Global Financial system
I buy it hook line cigarette
Giant Global Banks
They wanted a piece of the action to
Welcome
And thank you for your interest in Block that we're going to discuss this topic today with two experts from.
Okay the banks were in
And then as proof that
Radical underground ideas of Bitcoin
Had become completely mainstream
Play gentlemen
A TED Talk
The technology
Likely to have the greatest impact
On the next few decades
Has arrived
And you'll be surprised to learn
But it's the underlying technology of digital currencies like Bitcoin
It's called the blockchain
Block
Chain
So one of the reasons that everybody in the financial in
Industry is so excited about the
Block
Chain
Is
Leather distressed problem
It's essentially the macro problem all over again except
Instead of convicted
Criminals
It's unconvicted Grumman
Unconventional
Bakers
For sorry
Okay okay so
Francis there are
Two sides to every
Two Banks One Bank might think I just sold under chairs
The other one might think
Wait I thought I just bought a thousand shares
An honest mistake
That's a lot of mistakes but for whatever reason they disagree
And this is expensive to sort out
With a distributed Ledger there's a record
The both of you made together at the time in the first place
So no disagreement
Thing is
These days for a lot of transactions it's not just
2 bags
3 or 5 or 20
And every time you add an addition
No thank you add all this complexity
And all this paperwork
And lawyers and sometimes they're even faxes still in 2017
You put all of that on the distributed Ledger though
You get rid of the fax machine
You cut way down on the lawyers having to review every little
Accounting mistake
It's all automated
Efficient
It's cheap
Thanks love the idea
In July of 2016
Charlie shrem gets out of prison
Into this
New world
His girlfriend's waiting for
I came out in my
Prison clothes and I had a box
Stuff with meaning
I got rid of my prison clothes that changed in the car and
With left what is that what is that feel like to be on the outside
You ever seen a statue of Atlas with the world on his shoulders
Imagine having that in the magic being lifted Within
You feel a physical weight being lifted off
You it's like it's as if that whole year you were slumping
And all the sudden you
Stand up straight
The first thing Charlie does when it's on the outside
Is to get a cup of coffee
The second thing is to finally
Click on those links
On the Reddit page
Everything is changed
Have you ever went to prison there were no really many blockchain products
It was only Bitcoin there were a few other like
Pledging ones but it was mostly Bitcoin when I got out that year was the year of the blockchain
That's what a lot of things happen
Twenty-two-year-old Charlie
Would have
Heated the
Back then he called himself a Bitcoin maximalist
Meaning he wanted the entire Financial system to be replaced by big toe
What was the take power away from the bank
Not give them one more tool to control us
But older wiser twenty-seven-year-old Charlie
Please find
Well I'm definitely not a Bitcoin maximalist anymore
I believe that
And it's not like one chain to rule them all
Bitcoin does
Something's really amazing but there are other projects I can do something even better
Charlie's not only okay with all the changes
He's kind of excited about
He starts thinking about
What the best way is for him to get back in the game
Meid comes up with his own clever twist
On this whole
Can't Stop
He thinks what is blockchain could be used to do an end-run around the way companies go public
The way stock
Secreted in trade
Charlie create a new company
Intelisys Kappa
Intellisys is going to run an investment
It will buy up
Privately-owned companies in the US
Shares in the fund will be sold not to run
Broker on
Stock Exchange somewhere
But
Wait for it
On the blockchain
Instead of a paper stock certificate
You're going to digital one on the distributed Ledger
A creative ability
For people to
Take their own companies public
For their own assets public
And sell sell shares to those people
Anywhere in the world
I need to wear as
Bitcoin relies on the
Collective Agreement that Bitcoin is in fact
Worth something
Charlie's new project will be based on real
Physical
Tangible
Companies
Make money to do
In this case a really physical really dance
The first company sanitary way septic tank pumping
And Porta-Potty cleaning
You are selling a
A made-up currency
That's supposed to represent shares
In a business that moves
Human excrement from place
Yes might like my dad would say Do not invest in
Your dad
You know what be very smart to tell you that never to invest in something that you don't know everything about
So your dad the smart guy and that is
My guy
Charlie is not really
Counting on the Keith rumors of this world and their dads
To invest though
The funniest close to most American investors
In fact to avoid violating us
Securities Law
He's registered his new company
In the Cayman Islands
Why are why is it in the Cayman Islands
That's just what the lawyers
Decided
And that more than anything
It's how you know when a technology has really matured
Everyone starts listening to their lawyers
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Showtime
Billions
The hit Showtime original series starring Emmy winners
Damian Lewis
Paul Giamatti
Returns for season 2 on Sunday February 19th at 10 9 Centre
Download the Showtime app now
The catch up on season 1
And start your
Free trial
We are always interested
In stories about how old Technologies find a new life
You can email us Planet Money on NPR. Org or you can find us on Facebook or Twitter
Our show today was produced by Sally Helm thanks Sally our editor is Bryant urstadt
Special thanks today also to wall and broadcast that's podcast where we first heard about Charlie shrem story
Also thanks
The Charlie Cooper at R3 and Nathaniel popper of the New York Times
Daniel's book digital gold
Is a great history of the early days of big
I'm Robert Smith
And I'm Keith from
Thanks for listening
One more thing if you're looking for something else to listen to
Check out another great show for men
I'm Linda Holmes from NPR pop culture Happy Hour podcast
What has pointy ears a cape a huge ego and knees that don't bend that's right
Lego Batman
To get the skinny on his new movie and lots of other good stuff to watch and read
Find pop culture happy hour on the NPR one app
Aurat npr.org podcasts
Hey it's Keith again with one last note in an earlier version of this podcast we miss stated the crime that Charlie was convicted
It was not money laundering it wasn't that aiding and abetting the operation of an unlicensed moneytrans
Wedding business