Newsroom this is Ed hey edits Kenny Malone from NPR how's it going man
Pick any how are you guys add shop
Who is the news director at Fox 40 a television
In Sacramento
But
On this particular day
Ed was so much
Ed
Would the key to unlocking the mystery I had been desperately trying
Find us all let's start with the fact here
On June 18th 2015
You guys were in a second
Do you remember the segment at all I do not but I clicked the link at followed it and I watched
Mets
About another big stinking deal
Show an image of wonderful Lively segment with our morning anchor Mae fesai
And Yung gravy from Raley's
Joining at this morning Patty
Raley's Something Extra
In front of me
Teen Patti
The table discovered
Parts
Cat Wine
What you described it as decadent
Do you know what today is June 18th
Nationals
Lord's Day
Need I say more
Yeah so much more
National Splurge Day
This drive me insane
Because it feels like we are suddenly swimming in Bizarro holidays
Tomorrow is national puppy day is National Pancake Day
Just seems like someone is inventing holidays
The try and sell us a bunch of
And I wanted to get
To the bottom of this
So I came up with
I figured if I could unspool the events that landed one of the
Questionable holidays on
If I can follow it back to its origin
And just maybe
Understand what was
Powering
Holiday music
And this
Is why I wound up on the phone with Edge
Head shop
Trying to figure out how National Splurge Day somehow
Roundup on Fox
Sporty in sacrament
Itsfunneh
I was able to
Turtle following back track
My calendar how we found
Oh really
Yep I have done your sleuthing for you
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Kenny Malone in joining me on this Quest
Is Noel
Today we take a Journey to the Center of the
Holiday industrial complex
Search up that takes us from TV news
To the halls of Congress
Shoe storage locker
In Chicago
It's a story of power
TR
And one woman
Actually trying to make the world
A better place
Support for this podcast and the following message come from rocket mortgage by Quicken Loans
When it comes to the big decision of choosing a mortgage lender
It's important to work with someone you can trust who has your best interest in mind
With rocket mortgage you'll get a transparent online process that gives you the confidence you need
To make an informed decision
Skip the bank skip the waiting
And go completely online at quickenloans.com money
Equal Housing lender license in all 50 states nmls consumer access. Org
Number 3030
All right we are chasing
National Splurge
And I will say it was not hard to find coverage
Does holiday today happens to be known as National splurged a day when you're supposed to treat yourself
Yeah I love this one it's a New York station that did a
What would you splurge on
Segment rings
Everything in the world super models
I do want buffalo wings
Shockingly hard to
To get someone to talk to me
Show me about how
National Splurge Day
Ended up on there
The buffalo wings Channel date
Flatout declined
I got another station
He told me
No one is going to talk to you on the record
This is like real invasion
Felt like I was kicking stuff up
But then I finally found someone who would talk our guy
Head shop
Fox 40
Sacramento
I tell you I've never heard of National Splurge Day so it doesn't surprise me like that we did something about it
It has a 5 and a half hour Morning Show today
He's no shame about National Splurge Day ending up on his are
But he too was curious how it got there
So he pulls up a log that has every segment has station has ever run
He flips back
And there it is okay I'm going to click on this National Splurge Day
!
There's a record of who pitched it and it says what does it say there
This is emailed by a
PR person
Saturday June 18th is national sports day what you're probably asking what the heck is National
Splurge Day
That that is literally what I'm asking
Then yes
So it has a contact person
And her name is cat
Madre
Okay let me if you're if you're wanting to backtrack yeah yeah
And address and phone number
A fantastic
Hello hey is this cat
It is
Kat maudru is the first lead in our investigation
She's the pr person for Raley's which is a grocery store chain in California and Nevada
Cat told me yeah
High pitch
National Splurge Day to Fox 40 it was a way to get the grocery store on
But she can't remember exactly where she got it
She told me that she just Googled food holidays and there are a crazy amount of
Do you keep a running list of these holidays I do I have a folder on my computer with the the different holidays
Do you have it in front of you
Maybe
Could you open it and read me some
Love
National garlic month National meatball day even National raisin day
I will tell you right now that that is later on this month and I have a take her
And I haven't gotten around to explore going to talk to you about we wait
You already pitched National raisin Day to a media outlet and they said yes without knowing what you would do about it
Yes and I imagine we can maybe do some trail mix
We could do some baking
We can throw it in salads put it
Okay so National raisin day is not the holiday Warehouse
But it ended up being a very helpful because because after I hung up with
With cat
We started poking around
National raisin day is over a hundred years old an article from 1910
Complaining about how it was Shameless promotion by raisin growers in the Fresno Chamber of Commerce and this is the way some
Strange days are born it's exactly what you would say
Money
What's corporate interests
Was maybe a good
Good PR person
And sometimes
Even the governor
Thank you mister speaker
In fact United States Congress
Used to be a holiday
Factory all right today to talk about National Golf day
You hear these called commemorative.
At one point, he's got a little out of hand with the passing of made-up holidays
The peak came in 1985 and 86
This is during the 99th Congress
During that time
One in every
Three laws
Was a commemorative day or week
Or
That is to say
Congress passed 606
54 laws during that session
227 of those
Worst things like National air traffic
Control day
National bowling week and national birds of prey month
Legislators were spending so much time announcing crazy holidays
It finally in 95 the House of Representative said
Enough
And the pastor rule forbidding the introduction
We looked
And during the Congressional holiday Mania
There was no National Splurge
But we also learned that after the holiday Crackdown people still wanted a way to get there made up
Special days legitimised
And they found one
Drizly
Chicago
Cold
I was here to visit Holly McGuire
If there were a VIP Club for holidays
Holly
Holly is the editor-in-chief
But something called chases
Calendar of
We walk into her office and she shows me the 2017 edition of the
It's very heavy
I haven't weighed it
It's 752 Pages 752 pages of all kinds of holiday
Everything
From Easter Sunday
To talk like a pirate
You guys call yourself like the official keeper of holidays and special days little shy about
Actually doing
Seconds were in the midwest now
Spectre could be
That could be
Yes we try to be
Places like the Oxford English Dictionary of holidays
Yeah but Jesus didn't really mean to be
Become that
This book started in 1957
Back then it was a pamphlet to help
Keep track of holidays that change around from year
But eventually Chase has started allowing submissions for
Special day
As they call them
And then when Congress issued its holiday Crackdown
The world seemed to
Turn 2 Chainz
Bright and people started submitting to us to kind of fill that void
And this
Is where the search for national sports day gets in
Because
It wasn't Chase
But it isn't anymore
What
About a decade ago
The inventor apparently called chases or emailed or something
And ask to have it pulled
Holly doesn't
Know all of the details
She said she can still help
So she scoot over to her laptop she pulls up this
Which is huge
It's device basically every special day that's been and chases since 1990
85 thousands and thousands
Next each one
Is the person
Who submitted
I've organized it alphabetically and I'm in the Nationals
National soul food month
National soy Foods month then
There it is
National Splurge Day
You want to just read the text that accompanies
Today is the day to go out and do something extraordinarily indulge
Motto have
Fun okay and so there is a name attached with the creation of this this particular day
Yeah Adrian Sue Cooper Smith
Adrian Sue
National Splurge Day was not invented by a chamber of commerce
It was not passed during the Congressional holiday boom
It was invented and then rescinded
Spy woman named Adrian Sue Cooper
And we
That's a question
Coming up the last stop on our journey we meet them maker of National Splurge Day
And he's not what we expected support for this podcast in the following message come from Delta
Airline who wants to make your travel experience easy and enjoyable with the fly Delta app you'll stay
Rejected and inform download the fly Delta app from your favorite app store today
Are National Splurge Day Quest
To taking us from a TV station in Sacramento to lawmakers in Washington
DC to the holiday gatekeeper in Chicago
And now
Chicago again
Total coincidence
But yep
Loretta
Alright I'm like
A mile away excited
I'm nervous I'm on my way to me
Kind of an old downtown Adrian Sue Cooper Smith lives in an apartment building in the Rogers Park neighbor
Chicago and when I get there
Already outside waiting for me and very concerned about my lack of
No no I'm okay it rains or 60s just long brown hair that she wears
She's very proudly a Leo
She's to be a secretary and did some freelance Public Relation
Show me to take my
Do we settle in
Read some cheesecake
And she tells me the real story behind Nash
Splurge Day
It was the 1990s
It was Taxi
And she was bombed
And she thought
What is the silver lining
So you figure you're going to have your tax return back
Within two months and three days
It's okay you going to have time to think about the fact that you want to
Splurge on something
Okay God bless you
It's my cat might catch a sneeze I would say God bless you because she's a little she's a darling
Adrian decided
The two months and three days after tax
That needs to be National
So she wrote it up
Submitted it to Chase's calendar of events
The thing is
National Splurge Day
That is
Just
The beginning of it
Adrian how many holidays have you have you created
1900 that are
Legally written down
But there's more
A few blocks away to a place called Uncle Bob's Storage
Right after this 10-foot by 20-foot storage
So this is the Empire
In this Warehouse is Adrian's lifework
Hundreds and hundreds of pages of holidays or
She calls them holiday dates
She's been making these things since the 1990s
Alright let's go in shimmy into a storage locker
Box
Open it up
Let's see what we have
This is a whole list of
Love holidays
Right here
I have my glasses on so I can't sit
Okay January 2nd To The Great Escape.
Okay
January 16th
Dealing with the dentist day
February 6th
Pack pay a compliment
It's big baby that's big-time Adrian doesn't remember all of these
Cuz she only submitted
The best of her idea
Chase's in
She's had to run 20 of these
Including National Hug a GI day
International Skeptics day
And second honeymoon
There are a handful of
People like Adrian who are prolific
Holiday contributors
There's a guy who does pun holidays
There's a couple in Pennsylvania who are known for a river
Holidays
Adrienne has her own style
Pur holidays fall somewhere between
Quirky
And profound
In fact when I was visiting the Chase's calendar at
Holly lost penny day
Her favorite Adrian Hall
Lost penny day
To put aside all those pennies stashed in candy dishes coffee cans bowls and jars
Back into circulation
Celebrated Abraham Lincoln's birthday
I just think that's really Charming
It's a poetic little holiday
Yeah and very easy
For anybody to celebrate
Your serve clutching your chest as you read that I don't always do that she sounds
Because Adrian's holidays aren't in Chase's anymore about 10 years ago
She asked Holly to pull them out
Which is weird but
Adrian had seen some of her holiday show up in commercials
Sell things in
She felt like she was losing control of the
But I talked to Adrian for our
And I actually think that there's a story that helped
Explain why these holidays mean
It starts in the 70s
She was dating this guy
He was a gorgeous
British guy
He was about five years older than I was I mean he was really really I didn't accent
The coolness the
Kill that kind of thing you know
Adrian adored this guy
It was a bad relay
He drank
If you wanted him to go into alcoholics
Synonymous
Kind of did
But not really
So they eventually broke up and she found out later
For that he had died
Adrian says it was because of him in this period Of her life that she
Started to think about
Events
A completely different
AA is very similar to an event if you can make it through one day
And your event is not doing drugs or not drinking then yes sure that is an event
But that's an event about apps
It's about not doing
And there's all this pressure attached to
Will you fail will you see
Succeed
To Adrian.
Maybe it would be easier or at least make
Happier
If there was always
Another of
To celebrate
So I started thinking
What can you do
In lieu of doing something bad do something that's an event even if it's for a minute a day to get you through the
The date that pulls you away from what you're addicted by
That's kind of beautiful right yeah it is
But
Very easy very real business machine fueled by these made up holiday
PR people use them to get company's television time
Is a book made up of these itself
475 bucks
It's all true it's all true it's just that
I think the last thing
Expected
Define at the bottom of
Where do these little homemade holidays
A woman who's not making money off of them
But who cares about these more than I knew anyone
Could ever care
About a holiday
So we're back at Adrian storage locker
We're still reading through that list of her holiday dates
June 18th
National Splurge Day is this your mom is that your Mona Lisa
Dad in National Smith day National Smith day that's
To celebrate something
Completely ordinary the last name Smith
Cooper Smith or whatever
But there's other one flips the page
And there's this list of holidays
Is that just
Goes on for
Because a lot of people fast
Ready
July 2nd take a starving artist at the lunch date July 9th International Teen Idol Day July 16th Sports Club Day July 23rd ballot
The ball Day July 30th King Biscuit Day August 6th National aunt and uncle day
Howard today August 20th going going gone day August 27th Universal doorman day September 3rd
Industrial complex
Send us your ideas Planet Money NPR. Org
What kind of stuff on Twitter or Facebook
Planet Money producer is Alex goldmark at edited by Brian urstadt today's episode was produced by our intern
Turn danielewicz
This is Danielle's last week and really miss her so much
She also knows way more about weird holidays and anyone will ever know
Thank you so much and yellow
Also can you please do us a favor
NPR's working with the Knight Foundation
You better understand how listeners like you spend time with Planet Money and other podcasts
You can help us by filling out a short Anonymous survey at NPR. Podcasting survey
It's all one word
Dot-com
It only take 10 minutes and you'll do us all a ton of money a huge favor by filling it out
Is NPR. Podcasting survey all one word. Com
I'm Kenny Malone
September 24th soup du jour day October 1st God week
Get organized dammit that was misleading
But I like it
October 8th
Olay olives day
Oh really
October 15th Gap grow a beard day
See now that that had legs did that not take off okay
I didn't promote a lot of these did you miss Ann Arbor
Opportunity on grow a beard a pretty big the one problem with robe
You can't really grow a beard in a day
Will you can't really grow a beard