When they the summer
The FBI shows up
Unannounced at home in 4
Virginia it's
Barely Dawn and they don't knock the agents just pick the lock up
Front door
And they step aside while the owner is still
Here at the home
Paul manafort
Donald Trump's former campaign chairman
You know this guy
Vgod
Who stepped into the adult in the room
The guy was hired to turn around
Pain and chaos
Manafort impose discipline in the campaign
Trump on message
Any help secure the Republican nomination
Defense present their search
And
For a bit they follow the Playbook
Agents grabbing binders filled with documents
Making copies of keys
Computerphile
And understand
What they do next
You have to know something about the
Kind of busy
Manafort is in
Paul manafort is a poo
Consulting
He specializes in what they call
How things look
He's a master of
The image makeover
Guy who can reinvent apology
Talkray
Right look right
So the FBI is doing it
Typical FBI raid stuff
And then they do something that I had not heard of before
They take photographs
Awesome suits
The closet
Those suits are evidence evidence of Paul manafort's extremely expensive
Taste metaphor it doesn't just cultivate the image of politician he carefully cultivated his
Own image to we're talking
Find a tailored very subtle very good suits
Expensive lifestyle to help build a case against him special counsel Robert
Mueller will end up accusing man of secretly moving tens of millions of dollars all around the globe
In an illegal scheme that's lasted more
Benedict
Even while he was managing the campaign of Donald Trump
Hello and welcome to Planet Money
How to change and Tabor joined by to reporters to my very good friend from where I used to work WNYC in New York
And they haven't following manafort's money for
Hey I'm like a real estate and business
Today on the show
The three of us are going to tell a story about an alleged scheme to pull tens of millions of dollars out of one of the most corrupt
Places on Earth
Stash that money in a nice neighborhood in Brooklyn
We're going to take a part of money laundering scheme that spanned continents
The anatomy of a hustle and to really get it
Talk to a real life money order
Wow he's got all these documentation at this house
Color commentary
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Fidelity invest
As a Fidelity wealth management client
You get a dedicated advisor to help grow and protect your wealth find ways to minimize the impact of Pacs
And make it clear recommendations for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
Paul manafort grew up
Around campaigns and elections
His dad was actually
The mayor of New Britain Connecticut and Paul manafort jr.
Like politics more really early age and
He started working on campaigns
Back in the 1970s he worked on every Republican political campaign that matter
And then metaforte had a realization
He was getting really close
Powerful
Politicians were starting to
Really trust him
I never look at all this good will that he's building any stinking
What can I do with all of
The answer
Salad
And he does start selling it
He has all this access
He's gained through working on these Republican campaigns at a high level
Define strongman
We're talking about people like Philippine dictator Ferdinand Marcos
Angolan Guerrilla leader
Jonas savimbi
Zaire autocrat
To set the Seco
Beer for people who are accused in their own country of murder
Torture
And they signed up Paul manafort to be there in five
And one of the most important parts of his job was to make them look better in wash
Venom 2000
He gets a new play
Detachable
Budaj
Hookah
Djokovic
Victor
Yanukovych
Put now on he wants to be the next leader of you
And also he's just
Lost an election where his opponent
Seriously fell ill
Austrian doctor said today that Ukraine's presidential candidate was poisoned with dioxin this
Paul manafort
And if you're looking to make a lot of money
Really quickly
Ukraine
Could be the place for you
It's a weak state power is shared
Between corrupt
Politicians and
Competitive oligarchy
It's a place where people will look
The other way Savannah for 10 Sub Shop
MTF
And he starts supplying his touch
Viktor Yanukovych
Which so Yanukovych starts to comb his hair
Hear better
Team starts wearing makeup and Hugo Boss suits
During TV interview
And then your coverage goes on the road he comes to Washington
Remember
He's a Putin Ally
But in Washington his message is
Pro-west
There can never be too much democracy
Ozark canopy too much freedom
So on message
That is what the indictment
Manafort
That he was working to improve yanukovych's Imogen Washington
But that he
Didn't register as a foreign lobbyist which is a crime
But on top of that the indictment says
Did manafort not register
But took active
Skeptical
Feel the fact
That he was actually the lobbyists Rihanna cover
Okay so that's one of the things the feds are accusing manafort of hiding
That he was
Lobbying for a foreign
Leader butt
There's something else.
Computers are cute
Yeah they're accusing him of hiding
Money
And more money
And even more money the government says
Viktor Yanukovych
Kept paying
Paul manafort over all these years
I told the money swelled up
275 million dollars all off the books
Just piling up in accounts
Here
Put a pin
In this but there is an island in the Mediterranean
Disparity is a way of life
Cyprus known for its beautiful beaches decades-long unresolved
No conflicts
And also banking system that
Don't ask a lot of questions
Yeah the time banks in Cyprus were really popular place for Russians to
Stash their money
When Cyprus became a member of the EU opportunities Drew for invested in a country with low Taxation and then
Expanding economy the government says manafort opens up a bunch of bank account
Not under his own name but
Under the names of
Shelter
For now the money is out of
In Cypress
This is not where manafort lives he has houses in New York
Florida
Virginia
Really expensive
Food places
You'll never probably wants to spend some of his money there
Milford Kansas wire the money home without being noticed
Banksy's more than $10,000 moving into
The system
They have to report it
Thanks a lot of rules
Instafollow
But he does get them
How he gets the money and makes for very interesting reading I have the indictment right here
What are we got
Here
Payments relating to 3 Range Road
$163,000
Or look at the sun here he wires $1000000 to an antique
Run store in Virginia
He also drops a half million bucks at a clothing store in Beverly Hills
Associated Press they did the detective work I love this is it
Emporium of choice
The house of Bijan
We're ties go for $1,000
Good afternoon beijing how can I help you
Oh okay are you are you really the most expensive store in the world is that just like a nickname
No this is not a nickname
We are
You are really the most expensive store in the world
Yes we are
All right
This man is spending money
Play fast
But there is
Still a lot of money left on Cypress remember he's stashed 75
Million dollars in this very safe
Island in 2012
Something happened
In Cypress that made it a less desirable
Nice to have an overseas bank account
A financial crisis
Pretty bad one
Cypress gets a bailout
But one of the conditions of this bailout
Is a lot more screwed
Foreign bank accounts suddenly the island doesn't look like necessarily the best place
Departure money
And right around this time prosecutors say manafort starts moving his money to the US in big
Durand bigger chunks
And that brings us
Your neighborhood Andrea
Technically but close by Carroll Gardens Brooklyn
I feel like I'm in
The Sesame Street version of Brooklyn
Sunny is glistening
Stairs
You know fall is here so I see yellow leaves and walk you through a tunnel of trees
For now on Union Street it is a nice
Block there is a row of
Brownstone houses most of them
Really pretty Gardens
Out front
Plants squatting on the windowsill
321a
Getting close
3/7
Wait a minute
We assumed it
Address has been
Scraped off of sod
Straight out front
Butcher paper covering the windows renovation
I feel nervous
It's not luck
Hello
Can we take a look
He says he's not sure it's a good idea
Didn't sound like it explicit as we know though
I don't think it's a good idea
This house is no evidence
In a federal criminal case
This Brownstone
Properties that are used in these shoes games are these gleaming Towers
Would like Central Park views
Not some nondescript Brownstone in Carroll Gardens
That we had good taste
This house seems like a normal house but there is nothing normal about the way it was
Prosecutors say
This house is how manafort moved
Millions out of Cyprus
And into the you
This is how they say he did it so
First shell company that he controls in Cypress by his house for another shell company that he controls in Brooklyn for 3
$3000000
AllCast
So that's how the money
Gets
To this country
Then
Three years later manafort
Takes out a loan on this house
For $5000000
According to the indictment what is now done as he's now taking the dirty money from Yanukovych
And turned it into
Clean money from an American Bank
So if you believe the government story
That
Is money laundering
Right and remember the timing is important
Tear in February of 2016
And it's very same month
Paul manafort's seized an opportunity a workout
To work
For the Republican front-runner in the race for president
Donald J Trump
Write a memo.
And the first thing he offers the very top of this memo
To work for free
Which is so strange
But
Donald Trump loves a deal
He says yes
Remember at this point even though Trump is leading his campaign is in
Chaos
So if people know about manafort's foreign clients
In Washington
Kissing someone that people can do business with they know him so you can almost
Hear the relief
What comes on the scene chairman of the Trump campaign the head coach if you will
Palmetto Ford
Set reminder for walking back to the shelter
Ask you about Trump how you get along with him
Manafort comes in
Trump gets all the delegates he needs
What's the system better than me
16 other candidates
Dropped out
Marches to the convention
Get the nomination
Get the convention bounds
A metaphor is brought into this place
Which is why
I alone
Can fix it
So few weeks after the convention the story start surfacing about manafort
How he's
Earned millions of dollars from a leader in you
Crane and never reported
The incoming
This mysterious Ledger turns up out of nowhere in Kiev it has all these Cyrillic scribblings in it detailing
12 million dollars of payments to manafort
Simon Says
He did nothing wrong
But
The election is now getting really close so manafort doesn't want to draw negative attention
He leaves
I mean the media was covering
Chargers what you're letting with you
After the election were proven to be false
And
Treatment for
Why is being investigated
As we all know now I mean the FBI had been zeroing in on those
Foreign payments
Then special counsel Robert Mueller enters the scene
Accelerate the investigation there's that
Raid manafort's house in
Virginia in July of this year
And then in October the FED slapping Woody
12 count indictment
Really fast
Count 1 conspiracy against the United States
Count to conspiracy to launder money counts three through six
Failure to file reports of foreign bank and financial accounts
12 Cantona
Manafort faces more than 15 years in prison
Metaphor
His spokesman and his lawyer Kevin Downing they all declined an interview
Request
Manafort
Pleaded not guilty
And in a written statement is team says that manafort quote looks forward
Having the allegations tried before a judge and jury
His lawyer says
There's no crime and having a foreign Bank
I can count and his client
Didn't register the foreign lobbyist what they say is no one gets prosecuted for that
Now there is a gag order
Before the order came down there was a court appearance and Kevin Downing spoke to reporters
And the first thing out of his mouth
Had nothing to do with money laundering
But I think you also it today
The President Donald Trump was correct
There is no additives
The Mr maniford of the Trump campaign colluded
With the Russian government
It is true
This indictment focuses
All on you
Craney and money and the only mention of Russia is when the FED say manafort had an office
Is there
But
For those of us who are reading this indictment super closely
There is the name of a shell company
That manafort use
By his apartment
In Trump Tower in Amber Trump Tower number 43 G
Not too far below Donald Trump
We know from our reporting that manafort has done the same thing with the
The Trump Tower apartment that
He did with those
Soho condo and the Brooklyn
Townhouse
Namely
He buys it for all cash
He hold on to it for a while
Name and then he takes
A loan out on that that's the same pattern outlined in the indictment
That is how prosecutors describe part of manafort's alleged money launder
Should be clear
We don't know where the money came from for the Trump Tower of
A metaphor says everything is legit
What does Transit
Factions
But
He told us the same thing last winter about that Brooklyn Brownstone
And now it's in a Federal indictment
All right after the break we're going to talk to a professional money launderer about how to not get
Support for this podcast and the following message come from the windows weekly podcast
A twit.tv
Get inside information on all things Microsoft with Leo Laporte
Mary Jo Foley and Paul Theroux
Learn what's happening with Windows Microsoft Office Enterprise Xbox
Plus Hardware reviews and more
Be a part of the discussion
Subscribe to Windows weekly on your favorite podcast
Aurat twit.tv WWE
We were curious
If you look at this whole alleged moneyline
Ukraine Cyprus
Suits houses all of it
Was it even a good scheme
We wanted to review every step
And I tracked down
Kind of an
Expert
His name is Umberto Juan Aguilar
Now that you're now that you've served your time you want to tell me how much you laundered
I don't know
I could be over 200
It's a lot of money
Okay
Does it became a full-time job
Back in the 1980s in Miami
There was a lawyer who did a lot of work
People in the narcotics industry
Coke is a very lucrative business
Very loopy
So these guys had all this cash
Just lying around in store
Piling up in their toe
Found a way
Way to get the money
And then back into the
In secret for a little while
He did serve 7
Anyway we want to discuss
On the manafort indictment
Remember he's a lawyer Mastermind of his own money laundering schemes
He devoured
Yeah I want you to tell me
What were your first thoughts
As you were looking through this
Indictment
How stupid can you be
Berta says manafort
First mistake
Hit the money well
But then he makes
Quite open fight by buying things in the United States
And another mistake
When huberto was laundering money he created shell companies
Within shell companies
Shell companies
Make a money order to
He's a visit Diamond it doesn't seem like manafort did.
It is bewildering
You committed the Perfect Crime you got paid a lot of money what you didn't declare
That's your crime
No
Keep hiding it for the rest of your life and you'll be okay
You know shelterin
Do something by property in United States not under your name or on
And don't act like this is your property
Because people it's your property
One more
America says manafort just bought too much stuff
Message was too fancy
Light retention
Lose yourself but it's not stupidity it's
It's hubris
And it's like I can do anything I want more
All of the story if you're going to do something sketchy maybe just keep a low profile
Do you know of a money-laundering story that you think we should report on let us know sent us an email at Planet Money at a
Orange or find us on Facebook or Twitter
I'm at I'm at Ilya marritz and Andrea is @andrea WNY
See today show was produced by Nick Fountain thank you
Nick
Special things to former prosecutor Jamie nowaday for Patiently explaining money laundering to all of us
Money supervising producer is Alex goldmark or editor is Bryant Ark stat
And you're looking for something else to listen to check out the NPR politics podcast
It's hosted by my great colleagues got debts Roatan
This is a really fun way to keep track of all the craziness that's happening in Washington
You can find it at npr.org
Podcast
NPR one app or wherever you get your podcasts
I'm off the chain
A million merits and I'm Andrea Prince die
Thanks for listening
Do you think that's guys that we saw on their know that they're working in Paul manafort's yes
I feel like there's been a ton of media
The neighbors have been here they put
A
Pumpkin carved
Bob Mueller's face
Really
How accurate was the depiction
Really good though that's pretty dresses
Here
Like the neighbors late I mean I don't toilet paper house
More sophisticated
Artsy critique
Frontier