This message comes from NPR sponsors snowflake
The only data warehouse built for the cloud
Unlock deep Data Insights with the instantly scalable Cloud build data warehouse
Start your journey towards data-driven decision-making
It's snowflake. Com NPR
Good morning
Today Show contains profanity and offensive racial
Something strange
Has happened
To the passage
And I don't know if you've noticed this but
It just happens to me every week
Feels like Friday
And you're like
It is Tuesday after
Here's how this bizarre time-warp is affecting all of us here
At Planet Money
Now every year you may know this right at the end of the year we do a special podcast
It is a holiday tradition
I need this podcast we look back at the long year behind us
And we update all the story
We tell you what happened
The people after we turn the mic
Microphones off
We call it the rest of the story
Named after the immortal words of broadcaster
Paul Harvey
Today
Together
You and I are going to learn
The rest of the story
But things in this world are now changing so quickly
This year
This year we're going to do the show early we're doing a Year's worth of updates
Now
In July
We're doing it hello and welcome to Planet Money on Robert Smith today on the show
We will tell you about a Supreme Court case that Unleashed from cultural demons
We're going to check back in on the robot
It was supposed to make us rich by now
And a surprising new tactic in a war that we covered extensively
Eagles vs chickens
Support for Planet Money and the following message come from the business platinum card from American Express
Take your business forward
With the resources and know-how of the business Platinum Card
Backed by the service and security of American Express
The news world is
Crazy now in fact we're going to have to do the show super quick.
Is update so quickly before we have to update the update for the rest of the story
Has its own
Rest of the story
With me in studio is Elsa Chang hey Robert good to have you here altitude and amazing podcast back
Back in May
About
A rock band a rock band with
Inoffensive name
The name was
The Slap
Well offensively
OK play plans arnesia nahmir
And they were in a battle with the federal government over registering their name
As a trademark
Because
The federal government
Did not want to put that sort of official seal
Official like r with a circle on a registered trade mark seal
On a name which
They felt
Was
Disparaging to Asian
That's right
Now Simon tan the founder of the rock group he thought
That's not fair that's the violation of My First Amendment right so he took his case all the way to this
And that is where we ended the podcast but
In the last few months a lot has happened
Ketchup
So the court agreed with Simon Tam and Aslan
They said yes this is a violation of the First Amendment the US government cannot be in the business
Deciding what trademarks are disparaging
Which ones are not and banning only the ones that are disparaging
Useless t-shirts
All money goes to the map exactly
But people have been obsessed with sort of a larger question
And because of this
And that is
Have the floodgates open
Does this mean that a bunch of racially offensive
Misogynist homophobic
Hateful phrases are now going to be registered as trademarks
You're about to hear some of these words just another warning
I called them
Trademark lawyer Ed Timberlake
And he's been tracking
All the trademark applications coming through the door since the Supreme Court decision and cure some of the names people want to trademark
Gutter s****
Chink
Damn vegans
Niger
And Nicodemus
Wow wait how many niggas
Did you just
Massage therapy
Ver
At least five here and there probably more since then
We saw at least five trademark applications for n**** have been filed since the
The Supreme Court decision
Yes I a couple on the day of the
It was actually three
And I was curious you know who were these people behind these applications to register and i g g a
On the same day that the Supreme Court decision came down because whoever they were
They must be pretty determined people people who want to own the word
For commercial purposes
And of course the fear is that this would be someone who has racist intentions
Potential
So I tracked down
This one guy in Mississippi
Who was behind two of the applications
To register niggaa on the same day as the Supreme Court decision
And his name is
Curtis bordenave
Why do you want to register this word so badly
I thought that I had a duty
You know I'm saying in a responsibility to
To protect that word to secure that word
You know I'm saying in to make sure that is used in a way
That I think would not disparage
In case you're wondering Curtis is African-American and
He's now in this
Race
Against the racist because if he can trademark the word
Then he can keep other people from
Making products
Bad people
For making pie
Okay
Curtis wants to do is basically
Brand t-shirts
Words with n i g g a
Emblazoned on the front of the T-shirt will be
Themes like Unity or Brotherhood
So people will associate those good positive ideas
With the brand Niger
I mean he know he says this is a way of
Reclaiming
Which is exactly what Simon Tam said about the name of the band
Curtis was especially grateful that he pounds so quickly that he moved in right on the same day as a supreme court opinion
Because what he noticed
Was
Another guy
Wanted to register
And IGA as a trademark
Jake Curtis a really funny feeling about the whole thing of bad feeling
Was that same guy
Also wanted to register the swastika as a trademark
To criticize sitting there thinking this can't be good
One guy wants to register and IGA and the swastika
So I called him up
His name is Steve Maynard
Why swastikas
Because
The term has an incendiary meaning behind it and it's in it
Currently used as a symbol of hate
And if we can own the brand
We will be able to control
The sale of the brand in the use of the brand as well
Ocu
You're trying to basically grab the
So real actual racist and haters
Can't grab
Have the swastika as a realtor trademark
Correct
Hi-C Maynard
Is actually trying to do the exact same thing that Curtis bordenave
He is trying to do so very good people buying very bad
But there's a catch in order to register this
Rustica as a
Trademark you have
Cell
A swastika product
So Maynard has figured out a solution to this problem he is going to sell
Blanket
Kids duvet covers socks
Apparel with the
Swastika
Totally overpriced
Hi
I have reservations about this first of all duvet covers with swastika
Should not exist
In the world
But also it's just
Such a loaded
Emotional offensive
Symbol
They even if you're doing it for good even if you put it on for the even if no one buys it the very fact of its existence
Seems wrong
And you just put your finger
On a fundamental problem
Steve Maynard
Under trademark law the government will only approve
Your trademark application if
Consumers connect your trademark
With the product that you are selling
But the swastika
It's so well-known there's so much
Terrible history behind it
The Nazis
The Holocaust
There is unlikely
Anyone would connect that symbol
To some brand of
Blankets
Miracle probably never get to trademark
Swastika
But then again
Neither will anyone else
Elsa Chang thank you so much you're welcome story
Going to be honest with you all
We are Planet Money we're not supposed to be here this week doing the show
We have plenty money we're supposed to be rich
I don't know if you remember the episode we did back in
April but Planet Money
Developed
AA stock
Trading
Twitter bot
A little program that that reads Twitter and trade stocks based on tweets from the president of the United
Donald Trump
Alex goldmark lead our development team
What happened
Yes we call it botas pot of the United States being cute
The president of the United States
It watches Donald Trump's Twitter feed and if the president mentions accompanied by name
Otis will buy or sell stock of that company depending on if
The Tweet is positive
Poor negative
And Alex you pass the Hat we all put money into it so that we have $1,000 in an online stock brokerage
Account
That is all connected up to BoatUS
And it's ready to invest and make money and double and double and double again
What hap
POTUS
Has not made
It has not sold
Or bought a single share of stock
No when we develop is it seemed like such a
Great idea
Because Donald Trump
Tweeting about
These companies
Coffin
An insult or an attaboy
And
In the market would immediately move up or down and the
Hopefully we would be on on the right side of
That trade
But
I mean at least I've noticed Donald Trump is not
Tweeting about companies
He is still Tweeting about company
But he's doing it very early in the morning
And Jessica's at 5 a.m. demon
His thumbs go as the sun is rising and you know it is not going on at that time
Stock trading doctor
Stock market does not open
Until 9:30
I ran the numbers and I check
And only about 15%
The President Trump's tweets
Happened while the stock market is
Probably good for the stock market but bad for our
Trading bot
Police + fun
So
I want more
And so do all of the people following POTUS on Twitter they've been sending us
A ton of different ideas for
Changing up the
The computer code
And making trade
So I called up money Maggiore the head of Investments at
At tradeworx he is
1 people who helped us build our bot
And I went over some of the idea
Haven't you really want to do this
Well I want bonus to get a chance
Trade
That is fair I won't bow to the tray 2
But the reason we have notice and we don't have a person doing this is because
What are the advantages is that
Otis
Can be patient
Time in discipline
This whole experiment was supposed to teach us about algorithmic trading
So letting my dumb human impulsiveness get in the way just completely defeats
Literally
This part is keeping people like us
From getting emotional just want to make money
Okay but I still have two ideas for how to do it and I wanted to do it so 1
We can trade in what is called after hours
And you hear about this
All the time right there is the
U.s. stock markets are basically open from 9:30
4 but you know if there's somebody
In another place in the world they decide they really need some
Some cash in the middle of the night
There are
Places where you can trade stocks after hour
Money said letting photos trade in the after-hours Market
It could work technically like he could make the bot do that
Toyota
Because there are so few people trading after hours
That is just
Cost more to trade
And it's
It's a really risky place for a little bottle
So like on a scale of 1 to 10 how good of an idea
It's really bad
Okay this is my money so
I agree with him what else you got
My next idea was
What if
Botas
Read Donald Trump's early morning tweet
And then
Wait until the Market opens and then buys or sells
Reitman
What's not a good idea let's call it a bad idea
A bad idea but but with
Less potential to be a disaster
Because the whole logic of Buddhist was that when Trump tweet
He moves a stock price
Right away so we would buy
Right away
And then get out
30 minutes later so that we minimize our
But if we wait hours
After the tweet
Then
All kinds of other thing
Could move the stock price in between Trump's tweets
And when the stock
Open so we lose our advantage because something happened in the world to move stocks
And
Arbat didn't detect I can only to text Donald Trump
Right there could have been a big thing tonight before
That's ready
To burst
Anthropocene when the market
It is obviously a bad idea to change your
Trading strategy
In the middle of your experiment
But you know what
We should do it anyway
POTUS is going to
Starting right now
If President Trump tweets about a company
Before the Market opens
POTUS will see it
Make a decision to buy or sell the stock
And then jump into action right when the market
I don't know if we should have told all the other stock Traders are our strategy
Botas will be looking to make a deal
At 9:30 in the morning
We're suckers on this when they kill Alex
Thank you Robert if you want to follow
The trades
You can follow botis
On Twitter today
@potus
At the sotu
And stay with us because coming up after the break we have an update on the eternal struggle
Between our national bird
International delicious bird
Eagles
Versus chickens a new technology
Has shifted the balance
Mayweather
Yo-yo everybody Stretch Armstrong my name is Bob
Podcast worth listening to
Check out new show what's good with stretch and Bobby
This is not your average
We're going to be telling stories that you're not going to
Anywhere else
Find an Apple podcast
What's the NPR one app
You find your pocket
It's
What's good
Robert Smith
I'm here for the summer recipes
Jacob Goldstein of all of the many many
Many many fine stories
You called what is the most important thing you have
Hotels right now
I got an update on Eagles versus
I meant
So okay as you recall
Early this year I went down
Georgia where Annette Will Harris he's up
A farmer who raises
Utah free-range all natural
He took me out into one of his fields
And he showed me his one big problem
Bald eagles keep killing his chicken
So this got so this were looking at here is basically
The back half of
Chicken right there
Feet and legs
But the top half is essentially the eagle
Easiest way into the body cavity
Cuz you seen that
That happening with your seen thousands of time legal to sticking his head in that body cavity
Now the problem as I remember from the pie chest was
You can't kill the eagle
This is a national symbol
Any show me all these things he tried he tried Nets
Annoys Cannon's any special guns that shoot firecrackers in the air
Not at work
And that's how we ended the podcast
You would lose it to the
Pandora listeners
God love them
Felt like this was an opportunity for them to solve
So many people wrote to us and I found out road to Will
Dozens of people with all these
Suggestions you know one person was like
I was hiking in Peru and the chickens have had little red cape
Tied around their neck
And somebody else was like I work in this Botanica
Garden
And we had bagpipe music at a wedding and that made the Eagles go away
Writable array of of suggestion
Actually called up one of the people who heard the story and wanted to help
Diesel mechanic from Southern California named Brian Hall
And when he heard the story immediately thought of this
It's really astonishing thing that happened to him 20 years
He was working at a lamp
In the landfill was just infested with
Seagulls
And if you know seagulls
You don't like this is a prop
If you're working on the equipment
Landfills
Government
Covered with drop
You never seen anything s*** until you seen a single ship
Gratuitous
And and
The people at the landfill like we'll back in Georgia had tried all these different ways to try and get rid of the birds inside
Still tried those same guns that shoot fireworks
And none of it work
Until
Out of the blue somebody came to us
And when a piece of
Fishing
Warm Springs
Up in the air between the two poles
They won't be able to laugh
We what
So okay so so actually try it and I'll explain what they did they put up
220 ft poles
Right up into the sky
One on each side of the area where they were working at the land
And then they strong a single
Big piece of fishing line or monofilament line
Between the poles up 20 feet in the sky
The weirdest thing happened
Seagulls
Stop
Flying over the area where they had sprung up the line
Then
The seagull
They just stood around in a circle
Outside where Holly and the other guy
It was really weird
You know
Thousand
Eagles
Standing around the edge looking in on you and you just take
Okay where is Alfred Hitchcock
Amazing and a month later the seagulls
Left do we know why this work no it's so easy
Something something of a mystery we actually been called a few scientists
It's not clear apparently somehow the line confuses the birds like maybe they see the light.
Glinting off it but but in some way they feel like they can
Tomorrowland
In the area underneath the
Nobody really knows it just work
At least it worked in California with the seagulls
And then when Holly heard our show he thought
Well maybe it'll work in Georgia
With the Eagles
And he really really wanted to get this message till 2 will to the chicken farm
He reached out to us
He had one of his sons go online and figure out the phone number for Will's Farm be called
The farm you got voicemail White Oak pastures in Bluffton Georgia
Finally Holly Gets on the phone with somebody at the phone
Tell him about the fish
And Will Harris runs the farm sinks
What do I got to look at everything
I may as well try the fishing wire
So few days ago I called Down to Georgia
To see how it goes
Firstly we tried that we feel good about
And it appears that it's working
What is impossible
I know
Now to be clear will says he's not ready to declare victory.
Those are his words
There's a few like big cats one is
So they've strung the wire up over two of their certain groups of chickens
Illegal just went to the other chicken
On the farm
The other big thing will is worried about is
This is the low season
They're only a few Eagles
The state for the summer
The big influx comes in the winter when the eagle migration
So the real test is going to be in a few months when they got all the wires in place
When all the migratory Eagles
Okay great I will check back
With you in a few month
We never solve problems Atlanta
I am super shy
I think it's always will
In fact he asked me to give a message to 2 or listener to Brian Howe
We need to talk. Give me my undying
Gratitude
Express my gratitude please
I will do that I will be really happy to do that okay thanks a lot will keep in touch
Are you drunk Bubba
Holly hadn't heard from the guys on the farm for a while
He didn't know how grateful will was you didn't know
But the experiment so far and you ate is a success
So I told him
Oh my God
Oh how happy this makes me to
Help someone out like this this is
Great
It's beautiful story
Baked chicken
Thanks
If you'd like to hear the original shows that we talked
About today I really should the show about Simon Pam and the slanted called unspeakable trademarked
Episode 77 for the Buddhist episode is episode 763
Eagles versus chicken episode 752 and you love to hear from you are there other stories
Want to hear follow-ups on email Planet Money at npr.org on Facebook and Twitter
Is produced by our editor is Brian first and one last thing
Live on stage this September in New York City at the now hear this
Podcast best
Go to now hear this fest.com to learn more and get your tickets
Interoperate code money at checkout to save $20
Rest of the story
Summer edition so far