One of my favorite economy
Dan ariely tells the story about a locksmith
When the locksmith was new at his job when he was an apprentice
He took a really long time to open a lock
And people say I'm working away struggling
Really having a hard time and often they'd end up giving him a tip
But then when the locksmith got better it is
We got so good at his job you could open pretty much any lock in just a minute or two
Ben
His customers started complaining
They were like you want $200 for that the stuff you like 30 seconds
And you can see why right I mean we tend to think the harder someone works the more they should get
Yeah but it's also kind of ridiculous
I mean this guy was better at his job when you call a locksmith you want to get into your car or your house as fast as pause
And that was what he was doing
He was giving customers what they really want it
But they felt cheated
His bills
Suddenly felt
Unfair
A lot of companies operate under exactly this
They were warned people for how much they work
A person who stays late at the office the person
Who comes early they are more likely to get
Promotion
But maybe this is wrong
Maybe hard work is irrelevant
Maybe we should matter is what we create
Maybe company should be measuring our output
And not keeping track of our input
What would happen if you ran a company based on that idea
What was that
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Steve Hatton and I'm Stacey Vanek Smith today on the show
We find out
Rip Astoria
Patty McCord
One woman who has waged war against the idea of rewarding hard work
In the workplace
You may not know her name
But chances are pretty good she has already affected
Did your life
Just a quick note this episode originally ran in 2015 and we have a little update for you at the end of the show
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their own website
Using customizable layout
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobiledit
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online presence
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Patty McCord is kind of an accidental
Crusader
Is a kid
She moved around a lot
She grew up in West Texas
Florida than Northern California
After High School
She got a job in a lumber
Eventually she quit that job put herself through
Watch and landed at a small startup in the late 1990
Start up with sending people
DVDs through the mail
Movies television shows
Start up with Netflix
And Patty McCord helped build Netflix
From this tiny startup into what it is today
If I die
Tomorrow other than my family
This is the thing I'm most proud of in my whole life
I mean
Which is a bunch of people came
Together we made this
At Netflix
Patty was in charge
Hiring and recruiting
And the company was growing really fast
But in the beginning Patty says the company was actually just this tiny group of people in a
How did junkie office
Working from a bunch of cards
We were poor
You know I'm the early days of Netflix
We had to buy DVDs and stamps and envelopes
This was long before it became a giant multi-billion-dollar company
In the early days it almost went bankrupt
And this was a formative event
Maybe even more than the
Company successes
Because it led them to rethink
The whole idea
How a workplace should funk
This was around 2001
The tech bubble and burst
The company was limping along
Running out of money fast
And Patty who had been in charge of hiring people
Was now in charge of firing
So we laid off 1/3 of the company
The third night we were only a hundred 20 people or so but still it's one two three one two three
Patty and the company CEO Reed Hastings had to come up
They got rid of some movie room
Actually all of them
Some engineers
And you know how every company has that one guy in the corner and you're like
What exactly does he do
That guy
They fired me
And think I would have lots of people who'd been there since the beginning but
Who maybe weren't completely essential
For people to company this was awful
It was a terrible
And then
Weirdly
It was kind of
Great
They came into work and realize the company was just
Working better
John 10 QT was an engineer there at the
The experience I had was
Much greater freedom
Nobody was there
Who didn't have a job that felt critical to Our Success
Everyone who was left was
Really really good
Bill Koontz another Engineers has afterward they could just
We can get this done
With a small group
The people we have
Have no choice
So now we got double the reason
Do it so
Let's go.
Was that fun
Oh yeah
The company was still losing money
It was still going to have to raise a lot more cash or die
But the entire vibeage
The bureaucratic garbage was
Besides
Travel approval to your expense reports fewer meetings they were all doing more accomplishing more work with
Fewer people
In those days Patty McCord and Reed Hastings Netflix
CEO would carpool to work
We're in the car driving and I'm like
Why is this so fun I can't wait to get to work I don't want to go home at 9 I mean
We're working so hard what is it about this and recycle find out
Let's find out let's write it down
And at that moment Reed Hastings and Patty McCord decided they wanted to build a big
Company that would always work
One that had exceptional people a company that rewarded employees not for trying harder showing up
Copper being there from the start
Actually accomplishing great things
They decided to try and change the social contract
Around work
And bit by bit they wrote down their ID
And eventually it became this legendary slide
Actually still shown to all new employees at Metro
And it had a huge impact
A few years ago they posted it online and it went viral
Million views
And Sheryl Sandberg the CEO of Facebook called it
The most important document to come out of Silicon Valley
Suits TV were showing me these lies and if you've ever wondered what life is like in Silicon Valley or
Why this company
He's become so successful and grow so fast
Do you slide
Tell you a lot
One of the key slides
Reeds Jewelers
Hard work
Not relevant
It says quote we don't measure people by how many hours they work or how much they're in the office
In other words
We don't really
Care how hard you
How much effort
We only care about
Results
We care about your health
Not your input
Netflix
Now offers unlimited vacation
And it pays more than pretty much any other company out here
Silicon Valley
But to get a job
They're in to keep it you have to accomplish great things
So here's another slide
And this one feels a little bit harsher
It says quote
We are 18
Not a family
And we are a pro sports
Not a kid's Recreation
In other words
If they don't need you anymore or the business changes
Or things aren't working out
You will be cut
Don't expect this to be a job
App for life don't expect to stick around
Netflix live by this philosophy
Even in really good times
Like when Netflix started streaming movies and bat
Off the company started growing like
Crazy people
Love streaming movies they thought
This is so much better than ordering a movie
Through the mail
I can just
See the movie I want click on it
Watch it right away
Netflix at this point starts growing so fast it was about to break
The internet I mean really break the internet
Streaming online takes a huge amount of data and Netflix just wasn't equipped to deal with it
If suddenly the entire country decided to
To start streaming
But it looks like that was about to happen
Soon
Executives figured they had less than a year to fix this problem so they went to This brilliant team eventually
The same people who made streaming work in the first
And they said
What we got to fix this
No worries
We'll build it
You guys going Zack something we'll build it clap you know we'll build a cloud-based Computing we can do that
Actually you guys probably could
Not 9 months
But not in 9 months
That was streaming D-Day
And that's when they had to get
The standby
So they have this incredible team
But the executive decide they're going to have to hire someone else to solve this problem
They use Amazon Data Center
Netflix's Engineers were not
They're like well are we toast right at 4 and if we're going to go to somebody else to do it what happens to us
I don't know but we got to be honest
The honest truth was they were toe
There wasn't going to be a role therefore
I mean this is a team of Engineers that was so talented
Did they had basically taken Netflix to this point of explosive growth
And now the company is just going to get rid of them because there's nothing for them to do at that moment
That just seems so
Crazy
It's actually not that Chris
I mean the entire team and read the slides they knew the deal
They were at net
That's because they wanted to solve really interesting problem
When their role didn't exist anymore
They left on their own Patti actually didn't need to fire these
They went out and found new job
Before she had the chance
In a way the system works
But this is still a big shift in terms of how you think about a job
Some people came to Netflix and expected that they be able to
The state as long as they worked
And did
Good work
Patty remembers one worker who did Prada
And she was about to lose her job
Because basically it had become automated
And this worker was
So
Upset so I called her up in my
What's up with you just like I
I can't believe you treated me this way I mean after all this time I'm like
Kim in here
So she comes in she sits down I'm like
What part of this is this
She said well I'm like we've been talking about this as a strategy for years you been I've been me I said next
We talked about this and I think you could find me another place in the company like I can but
The same things going to happen to me now
I really cannot be making something up for you and she said well
And I worked really hard this really unfair
Mike
Pranks I can like
Dry your tears and hold your head up and go be from Netflix
Why you think you're the last one here
Cuz you're the best
Credibly good at what you do we still need to do it anymore
Patty have a lot of experience
It's doing that so she became what she calls the queen
Have the good goodbye
How many
How many people do you think you have fire
Oh I would really like to remove that word from Marvel
Vocabulary because for one thing I hate all of our militaristic terminology in
We don't shoot people
And we're going to have long careers you and me I mean
We're going to work at a lot of different companies and if we can start as employees
Thinking of our careers as Journeys and
Places that we go and things that we explore then we're going to not get all wigged out
When things change and it doesn't work out
What word do you like
Severed is Pleasanton fired
How many people have you moved on
I don't know Steve this makes Netflix sound like
A really hard place to work
Yeah for some people I think it is
A lot of people I talk to really like that but there's a downside
To work in a place like that
Some employees there
Talk about a culture of
I like that for everybody
But for some people it definitely is
And you know you can look at that slide hard work doesn't matter we don't track hours
Integrate
I'll just finish early and then take the rest of the day off I'm an adult
Control of my life
But another way to read that slide
Is that hard work is not necessarily enough
Working hard is no guarantee
20 Eur
And most of the employees and
Former employees at Netflix who I talk to
They work
Frazee
Heart and Angela looks also
I think I was Employee like number 32
It was hired to do marketing but ended up in the early days doing just a bit of everything
She even spent one Christmas Eve sorting DVDs
And she loved this company
She lived in
Breathed and bled nuts
She was super loyal
She worked
Until she was exhausted
Slept then got up and did it again
And again
And eventually she work so hard she got sick
She developed chronic
Back pain
That just
Kept getting
Worse
When I was initially hurt and I needed some time away I just wanted to Paddington I have to take a break didn't want me to type it
Don't be sitting all this, okay
It's all she said okay
Let me know when you're feeling better
I was at 4 weeks
And I kept checking in like I'm thinking through fire me they're going to go there and find somebody else
I just sent a note saying they still want me to breastfeed right back
Okay hope you feel better
6 weeks
10 weeks I finally went to her and I said
You maybe should formalize this maybe I need to go on short term disability or something like that because if that's what you want to do
Kiddo I don't know
Okay
And I know it immediately is just like okay the Gordie pivoted
That's a really hard story to hear I mean to be fair
Netflix was struggling
At that point
And Angela new
There was no job there
But they needed doing
She was capable
The company had to
But you know when I hear her tell that story and I hear her talking about Netflix
I can't help but be reminded of that fly
We are a team not a family
You know
For Angela working at Netflix was one of the best
Why she still loves
People who she
But the deal
At that company is just
But maybe not that differ
At least not anymore
Because Patty and the slides
The huge impact
Oliver Silicon Valley
And all over the country
People have looked at these ideas and
I have adopted
Netflix series this is a big reason for its success
The company's business has gotten bigger and bigger and bigger butt
Its Workforce is lean and
Flexible
Mean when DVDs were no longer a thing
Fine
Netflix mastered streaming
Then when Hollywood decided to raise the prices for TV shows and movies no problem Netflix started making its own
Ten Years After the layoffs the company seem Dunst
Read what's on the cover Fortune he's the best CEO of the year we are acquiring a million subscribers a month
We were
Rolling in dough
We're alike
We are
I'm amazing and you know what
So are you awake
So are we
Amazing what can we do anything we want
Everything was gold
There's no way we're going to fail
You can guess what happened next
They failed
You know some of you may remember this
Because it made customers Furious
Netflix announced it was going to split into two separate comp
One for streaming and one for DVDs
And that meant that if you wanted to get
Both you had to pay twice
Two bills instead of one
And it was a big
Pricing
Customers revolt
Yeah I actually canceled my Netflix membership
They lost something like 800 thousand customers in a month
During this. Every morning Patty would wake up open or laptop
Check the headlines
And the backlash it was right
On the front page of every
Paper
I'd read that Stephen and I go throw up
What heart
We were so
Was so
And this is one that lean efficient machine Patty helped build
This monster of a company
Reach.
And got
Her
How do you been a big supporter of splitting Netflix into and it had been a disaster
The same time Netflix was also involving
They were moving to Hollywood
Making shows like House of Cards and Orange is the New Black
And Patty had no eggs
Burien
An entertainment
No experience hiring Direct
For that kind of
Production
Her skills were no longer needed and at the end of that year
She Andre Jesus had a conversation
How do you move
She still doesn't like to talk
But she said leaving was terrible
And painful
Sad
Today she's in a good
She's in demand
Epic Consulting
She's happy
But what you talking about nuts
Looks she still uses the pronoun
Ennui
Describe her company
And no matter what those slides she helps rights
The people who built Netflix
With her
Still feel like a family
Even though really
They are 18
And Patty
Has been cut
Hey it's Stacy against soap since we ran this episode in 2015 Steve has left and
Backyard to start his own company we miss him very much
But it also means that he's got to try some of these ideas out for himself
We check in with him right after that
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online
Presents and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layouts along with features including e-commerce functionality
And mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
So this episode ended up being kind of a pivotal moment in Steve
Penn's life
Soon after he reported the show for us
He left to start his own company
Is called tiny garage lab
They make an audio app called 60db
Patty McCord she actually became one of their early investors
And one of Steve's co-founders John Chang
Cootie is the former Netflix engineer who you heard from
Very briefly in this episode
He's so bitter that he's only in the podcast
Horrible cold
My mother heard that
Can't you called me up and she was like are you dying
Steven John met through this podcast
Any talk about the Netflix culture a lot in there
So we asked them the big Netflix question
Are you a team
Or are you a family
What are family
I think
The most concrete aspect of the team versus family
Orientation at Netflix
The willingness to let someone go when it's not a great sat
John used to work at Netflix so he has a lot more experience with this
Send Steve.
And of course it's one thing to report about this type of culture but it is another thing to actually do it
We asked Steve about the first time he fired some
@tiny garage light
John listen to me like
Agonize over that particular to ceiling for months
He did not even want to use the word fired
I mean I don't think it's I don't know I'm not sure I'd describe it as fiery
That employees still Feelin It
And John Steve agree that their company culture is not like Netflix in every way
But in some big waves
It is we always love to hear what you think the show send email
Planet Money at npr.org or tweto
At Planet Money episode today it was produced by Jess Jiang Alex goldmark Frances Harlow and edited by David kestenbaum
Sally Holmes produce the rerun
Things to Patty McCord to talk to us for this update she has been working on a book
It's called powerful
Building a culture of freedom and responsibility and it comes out in January
And if you're looking for something else to listen to check out fresh are they just marked their 30th anniversary on NPR Terry Gross
Her team put together a series of interviews from their early years
Find them on the NPR one app
Or wherever you get your podcasts
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Thanks for listening