This message comes from NPR sponsors snowflake
The only data warehouse built for the cloud
Unlock deep Data Insights with the instantly scalable Cloud build data warehouse
Start your journey towards data-driven decision
It's snowflake. Com NPR
Just so you know this podcast include some foul line
And it was originally reported back in 2015
11 update at the end
Frederick Hutson had this
Entrepreneurial
Pretty much from the day he was
In high school he had a lawn mowing business where he got other kids actually mow the lawns
You did the same thing
With a car washing business
The guy was Annette
He went to the Air Force boots Las Vegas
Starting a window tinting business
And then he bought a mailing center
One of those off brand UPS kind of stores in Las Vegas
And this store
Was key to his biggest business plan yet
He was going to deliver marijuana
All over the country using UPS
And feta
What could go wrong what could go wrong
I'm at the mail center and I'm just sitting behind the counter
And then I see
It's like all glass
And then I see agent coming from both sides about 12 people
Bra size in inches
All like Rush the Dora
Like a gun drawing
So they they they put me in cuffs
And then they come in if you could have charged more
Sotto voce
Frederick got nailed for conspiracy to
Distribute marijuana
5 years
Federal Prison
Now some guys go to prison
NBA finals
Some guys go to prison and they work out a lot
Massive biceps
Remember Frederick Hudson was
The business
So he would spend all this time
In the prison Library
Writing
Business plan
So I just spent every day writing random whatever I did even if it was even
Possible feasible
I'll just write a plan for it I would write how it went to build it I would write who I want to hire I meant White Collar guy
And I would be children how to write Financial models and we would get
Paper taken together
White people like that
Rulers and draw lines make a spreadsheet for hand like physical paper spreadsheet
So it was a tedious process but I have time to do it
Entrepreneurs do right he pick a problem and figure out a solution
But as the days went on
Frederick realize the biggest problems that need solving we're actually all around
Inside this jail
Look at from a business perspective
Prison
Was actually an unexploited gold
All water Planet Money Robert Smith and I'm Steve hen
Today on the show a business man goes to prison
It decides he is going to disrupt the largest
Captive Market in the world
This message comes from NPR sponsor Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking I offering accounts with no fees or minimums that can be opened from anywhere
In 5 minutes Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
When you're doing time in a federal prison there is no
Shortage of business
Problems
Frederick Hudson saw them everywhere
Every
Day the first thing you notice in prison is there is
No competition
You want to buy soap there is only one place to get it
Prison commissary
And it is way overpriced I looked up a price list online for federal prison
A Pepsi
Can of Pepsi cost $2
And $0.60
Ofertas that's nothing
Compared to the pay phone
Gas can charge whatever they want if you want to make a call from jail there's just one phone company to deal with
Basically when I was going to county jail I was making calls
Out but it was expensive was going to point where Tanya who's my girlfriend the time she was like I can't afford every time you call me $50
So I stopped calling as much
Whatever time you called her was $50
How long were you talking right we talked I think I called you like 15 minutes
And what reason why cost for 15 minutes for $50
Very expensive
The phones are address
But the thing that really drove Frederick nuts
What's this
Photo Pro
He wanted his girlfriend to send him a photo
But inmates aren't allowed to have cell phones or internet access so for his girlfriend to actually send him her picture
She have to go and print it out at a drugstore
Put it in an envelope and mail it to the prison
And that
Didn't
One of the main things that I used to be jealous I was ovulating my bum and I will hear mail call
And
Dell called me
My name is never called
And it's just frustrating cuz I never get mad
Fertilizer on his bunk mulling over
And then it goes to the library with his blank pieces of paper and pencils
And he starts thinking about the
Photo problem like a businessman
What if there were a company that could make
This whole photo thing easier
A website or an app some technology that would allow someone to
Take a picture
Hit a button
And then poof that printed photo would automatically get sent by mail to prison
How much Shutterfly
For contacts so this whole idea basically started because
Girlfriend naked pictures
Well you can't get naked pictures in prison
But you know the more risque the bar happy you are you know yeah
Forget pot delivery
This was going to be his perfectly legal million-dollar idea
He even came up with a name for
Got a 2010 name picture
Picture
There wasn't much he could do about building picture Graham while he was still behind bars
But we got out in September of 2011
He brought all those business plans he had developed
All this paper spreadsheet
Smart blinds
And she headed out for
Okay normally if your Tech entrepreneur
You go to Silicon Valley
But Frederick
Was not
He was
The Felon out on parole
His destination
What's a halfway house
In Tampa floor
Adherent Outlet you couldn't imagine a worse place to incubate a Tek com
At this halfway house every aspect of his life with control
He didn't have the luxury of uninterrupted time
Prison Library
Get to constantly check in or check out
And it kept saying
You have to get a job
And no
Starting your own company
That doesn't count
So we started build picture Graham on the slide
Initially is playing with the hierarchy
Couple guys website
Photos
Three causes photo processing
And he said but you know we'll be such a butt call with the CEO and other people so they need to just call my first conference call
Still living in a halfway house
And how do you take how do you take a conference call in a halfway house
So they had a rule which is stupid but
Then you can have phone they didn't let you have a cell phone so I stick my phone in and
I'll be in my bunk laying to the side and on the conference call with the CEO and the sales guy
And basic
Pigeon
And in your doing this while laying on a bunk
Speaking quietly in a halfway house probably
Eight other people
And if so
How did you how did you make that pitch it actually came out because I told him I say I'm looking to send pictures they wasn't
That you know this already
What you going to do that's different
I said well we're going after Ma
And is really no service that allowed
People send photos to inmates and we can be the first
And we're going to be the best cuz we have unique way to ask
System
We have a way to Market to
And then you say why do you know this is oportun exist
What am I going to tell him
Cuz I'm worried that he's going to say no if he knows that I've been in prison
So I take the leap and I and I tell him I said well actually I know because I did four years in federal prison almost five years in federal prison
Distribution of marijuana in a pharmacist
So I'm not I don't know which way is going to go
NCO said you know what
Is most interesting that I've heard
Let's do it I'm excited about it
Forgetting a printer guy on board was just one of a bunch of problems
Frederick needed to solve
Give me to figure out how we can get out of the halfway house and
Start a business
You weren't supposed to be doing this and this problem of finding investors I mean that pitch may work for the printer guys but winter going
For people who want to give you
You money
Saying I just spent the last five years behind bars is perhaps
Not the best
Right
Topher can one advantage he had a good friend from the airport
The guy named Alphonso Brooks who lived in Tampa
Like them
And wanted to work with him
So they decided to found this business together
They start asking friends and family
For money like
Like a couple thousand dollars here a couple thousand dollars there
And then Alfonso actually hires
Frederick officially he gives Frederick a job
It just happens to be a job at this company their founding together
Picture graph
So they have a seed money
Jack just you know some of it
They have the technology the printer guys are stats
Jack
And at least
Technically he's obeying all the rules
Of the halfway
Technically yes
Check
But of course
This is really only half the battle right
He spent all this time trying to overcome the barriers
That being a convicted felon threw up in his path
But he still faces all the classic problems every other entrepreneur faces
That's right like
How do I reach my costume
How are they going to pay
The people want this
Will it work will hear the answers in just a moment
Support for Planet Money and the following message come from ishares
Because the best
Preparation for tomorrow
It's building for your future today
Ishares by BlackRock
Inspired to build
After everything Fritter custody been through it was time to Launch
The business
In 2012 they build the website
And they just need customers but finding customers is not easy because
The customers he wants
Or in prison
They have to reach prisoners
So what they come up with a pretty low-tech advertising salute
They made
A picture postcard that they mailed out to
500 inmates
A list of inmates that they found on the internet
Bi copy was pretty
We said someone wants to send you a picture gram and
To have him send it to you go to this website and that was it
Some of these postcards had a picture of a mom
Cooking dinner
Some had pictures of kids
Some pictures of attractive women
But every postcard offered one free picture sent through the mail if their loved ones
Set up an
So basically it's just junk mail
Yeah it's absolutely
Junk mail
Standard junk mail
And you got to think for a second
What we take for this junk mail
To actually be a
I mean a prisoner has to get it after we did not throw it out in the prisoner has to like
Wait in line to make a phone call
Call their loved one say hey here here's this website go to this website explain the
Whole process
And then that person the relative has to go online
Actually send a photo
Normal piece of junk mail gets a response
Like one person
That's what he said that 500 postcards you can expect maybe 5 p
Keep all to respond
But remember Frederick Hudson knew something most people don't
Inmates
Love
Male all of a sudden like to 3 days later
All these orders started coming and people start saving photos
Out of that first batch of 500 postcards
Paying customer
The response was just
Nuts
And it was the sort of Revelation 4
For Frederick because how long he been thinking about prisoners in the
Problems of being in prison any thought of this website as a service for in
But at least artists he's responsible thought
No of course like the real customers are the families
And all these responses there are mothers
And father
Brothers and sisters
And it means as much
For them to be able to send a photo
As it means for inmates
To get that
I talked with some of the relatives who used
And it's actually pretty heartbreaking
How much they value just the tiniest bit
A contact
Yvonne hydrovac
Live in st. Petersburg Florida and her son Johnny
He is doing a 15-year stretch
Four armed robbery
Now he's been shipped
Deanna
She's now in South Carolina
Yvonne you know she doesn't have much money she's never been able to
For the visit
So
One of the only ways she stays in touch
Sending pictures through the service
What does your son what does Johnny think of the photos that you send
Oh he loved them he loved them
Oh he loves them
Does he have a favorite picture
Yeah me standing at the store
Cooking
He loved to see that one
Oh I don't know I probably was
Let's make us some meatloaf collard greens and
Macaroni cheese something like that they on Sundays I cook a lot
And he always tell me on Thanksgiving I ain't there Mama but find somebody that that ain't got none need and get my plate
Say I do it
I do it every year
Frederick sent out his first postcard
In 2012
And three years later Steve
Steve you went to visit him at in Las Vegas
Alright whenever you're ready go ahead
It's a little startup space it's really not much more than like a two-story Loft and it's just
Packed with people gives a half a dozen customer service reps at any given time they work in shifts
Answering phone call
Frederick has like your startup uniform you know t-shirts Jean
And he is busy
Cell phone on his ear
Hey Daniela
Hey hey we're on our way I'm glad you text me cuz I completely forgot to bring the check so I had to go back to get the check
Ovia
Yeah we're coming yeah we'll be there in probably about 5 minutes miles getting sick now
I think you
That check it's for new office
Bigger office
They said they need it because they're not just sending pictures anymore
Frederick's companies built this giant database
All federal prisoners in the country
And they're using it to sell all sorts of services
They started a telephone service
They gives families local numbers so they don't have to pay those sky-high prison long distance
Indoor growing
Faxed
They didn't ditch that old prison name picture Graham
The company has a little bit more 2015
Pigeonly
Pigeonly mycarrier
I travel a lot so I like traveling and no matter where I go you when I was in Japan most recently
And I notice how pigeon so common that we never pay attention to him even though they're all around us all
All the time
And that's going to help you out a lot of times it says this Market that's all that's here in present but nobody
Kind of like prisoners
How do I get sconce
Or their families
Frederick has raised a lot of money
And investors love this story of this ex-con
Made good guy who went out
After going to jail
And built a business to serve people like him
You know what you think about it none of this would have been possible none of it would have happened
If you hadn't gone
The prison if you hadn't made this huge mistake
Brokenness mother's heart
So I had to ask
You think going to prison was worth it
Do you think what you did was worth it
Yoda pic
I would say
The people that I
Hurt
It wasn't
Worth it
But
What I've been able to turn it into it's definitely worth it I don't know if
I would have grown up as fast as I've grown up Armature decisive matured without experience
Without
Conditions that I lived in for
I don't know if that
Would have happened in the same speed out of my life will be on the same track it is on now had I not experienced out
But I was given opportunity I was given
An opportunity to turn something around and make an impact
And if I squander that
And you know I'm not only my let myself down my family who went through all that is like I didn't go through all that for anything
At that point so
Haven't taken through so much pain in her I have to make a successful at this point
Because service was all for nothing
Salt Lake Frederick can never forget what he did
It recently he went to rent a new apartment
Here in Las Vegas right there on the application form there was this box
Are you a convicted
She had to answer yes
Sol.
He's raised $3000000
Delta business
And the landlords
Required the Frederick Hutson
Dad
Finally
Wish it was originally recorded in 2015 it is of course
17 now I'm Robert here in the presence
And we recently checked in with Frederick Hudson about his company to see how it's going for him
He says a lot has changed
He's now raised 6 million dollars
The service is expanding to State and County Prison
Are even approved a new Social Network
Call
Prison wives
The sort of support group for women with loved ones in prison
But there been growing pains 2
Frederick City realize that some of his employees were
Mediocre
And had let them go
And then there was
The computer at
It happened in like a 24-hour. Someone created
I want to have a million fragile accounts on all service and it was basically making a hundred thousand
A phone call
Expensive definition
That was big enough of an issue
Tooker Avenue
Thankfully it did not these days Frederick says pigeonly send about 5,000 photos a day and each month
The process is about 2 million minutes
Phone calls
He says they're on track to reach a profit
Later this year
We'd love to hear what you thought of Today Show or any other you can reach us at Planet Money at npr.org
And now that you're done with me to Planet Money recommended you check out
The storycorps podcast
It features
Amazing emotional unscripted stories about real life
Highly recommended it is storycorps and you can find the podcast
Wherever you choose to get your podcast on Robert Smith
And I'm Steve had thanks for listening