By now we are all very familiar with North Korea's accelerated mistletoe
And we're pretty sure we know how they got the
Technology
How did they get the money I mean Mercury is broke right there Extinction to the teeth
How on Earth could they afford to get their hands on some of the most expensive
Coveted technology on the planet
How old are you what is your age
26 years old how would you describe yourself to someone who's never seen you
Picture of the Cure
I'm sexy and cute at the same time
This is Jesse
She is from North
And she grabbed it has been a town on the northern border on this river called the Yellow River
Dishonest time is known as
Place that is closest
To China
When we open the door and go outside
You can basically see China there
Jesse is in Seoul South Korea now
I spoke with her over Skype through my translator G Haley
Who was able to affirm that
Yes
Jesse is sexy and cute
At the same time
It's true I can attest to that
Jesse says money was always really
Tight when she was growing up
If you needed something you had to find a way to get money for
When she was 8 years old
Her family needed matches
So she and her brother went up into the mountains
Picked a bunch of wild raspberries
And sold them at the local
The toy of Marco manga
Mommy went to the market and we started selling and it sold well not because people loves wildberries but
Because there was an eight-year-old girl trying to sell all these wild berries at the
At the market
Jesse meet 45 North Korean won selling her Berry set
That is about a name
It was the first time she's ever had money of her own and she still remembers how it felt in
So you bought the matches
And then she saw these
She says her mom
Loved
Her mom is one of those people who was always doing things for other people never really did anything for herself
So Jesse took her left over money and she bought her mom
Peach
Bolt Santa Cruz
When I got that peach and I saw her
Getting the peach and eating the peach she looks really happy and it made me really happy that's when I realized
I want to make a lot of money to make her happy
Jessie started selling berries and other things at the market right now
Saving up for earnings looking for more opportunities
And then one day she had this Flash
Of brilliance
She noticed that the men in her Village Railways gather for a drink
The end of the day
And they were drinking is alcohol that they were making themselves out of the potatoes they were farming
I just thought you could get them better stuff
So she hitched a ride to a bigger city
Oliver Berryman
All of it
Ecchi bought corn alcohol
As much as she could carry
And she walked back to her Village
It was a six hour walk
Doki-Doki because I was little I couldn't
Bring back more than 5 kg of alcohol
That's about 10
Who does he walks for 6 hours with all this corn alcohol she gets to her house
She cuts it with a little water
And then she tells her grandmother to go into town and spread the word
The day were selling the good stuff
Ikuto narcotic
My alcohol is really really popular because it was very pure there was no hangover and so
And they said it was a huge difference
Jesse had more orders than she
A small business was born
Little pilot light of capitalism
Right in the heart
Locked down restrictive socialist regime in the world
Hello
And welcome to Planet Money I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
North Korea got a lot of its missile money
From us
From ideas the US has been exporting all over the world for deca
The free market
The entrepreneurial spirit
Good old-fashioned
Capitalism
North Korea's missile money
Started with people like jazz
Today on the show we go inside the hermit Kingdom
And meet North Korea's capital
And the people who trained them
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online
Presents and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layouts along with features including e-commerce functionality
And mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial and when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
There is a special name for North Korea's entrepreneurial type
Like Jessie
They're called
The dungeon
It means Lords of
3 years ago there is no way that don't you would have existed in North
It's a socialist country people are supposed to work for the good of the whole and get everything they need from the governor
The idea of Mickey
Making a profit or growing a business or even owning something
Blasphemy
The North Korean regime in fact had a special
Term for it
Honey coated poison
And we the Western General wanted North Korea to swallow the honey coated poison
Wow that is some
Siri
Nicholas eberstadt is with the American Enterprise Institute
He's been studying the North Korean
Economy since
70s
Isis the shocking thing to him is the back then
North and South Korea are in a heated economic race
Now South Korea's economy is 50 times larger than North Korea
Just to put this into perspective
The state of Wyoming
Has a bigger economy than North Korea
North Korea is the only place in
Human history
That has suffered a famine
During peacetime
With an urbanized deliberate population it's almost impossible to do but they managed somehow to do that in the 19
Nineties
That famine was known as the arduous
North Korea's economy collapsed and made from Russia dried up
Hundreds of thousands of
People starve to death
Bodies were piled up in the street
And for years the North Korean people were
On their own
So they started scraping together what they could little bits of food basic necessities
I'm coming together in Market
Like the one where Jesse sold her ass.
And these markets got bigger and bigger
And the government just
Let it happen
From the North Korean leadership standpoint it was a devil's deal that had to be struck
To prevent
Big total breakdown of the state
It's got a long way since that
And now there's a hole
Class of
Market
Tiaras and Dungy work I gave my side don't you like North Korea Miyabi's
The country's leader Kim Jong-il what occasionally Crackdown
On the don't you throw some of them in prison
Close down some markets
But when Kim Jong-il son Kim Jong-un
Give me the power
He had a very different approach
City Island
Immigrant Song
But the era struggle is over
We declare two main goals for his country
Number one to build up the weapon
At number two
To grow the economy
Growing the economy
That meant making a little more room to maneuver for this tiny glass
Don't you
The North Korean government
Has
Illicitly
Reveal
That they believe they can take a little bit more of that
Honey-coated poison
Then would have been tolerated in the past
And that's getting economic results
But North Korean entrepreneurs with a real disadvantage
Things that are just like in our blood in
Marketing two-for-one sales venture capital
These things don't really exist in North
Kim Jeong Hoon decided to help out the don't you
He started letting business experts come in from overseas
And Coach them
For the last several years I've been involved with a nonprofit called just an exchange
The trains North Koreans in entrepreneurship and economic policy
This is Andre abrahamian
He's been to North Korea dozens of times
Teaching classes on things
Marketing management
Counting trade
North Korea cool with this they'll say like
Great
Come like spread your
Capitalist ways in art like heaven
Heavens no we're not
Spreading capitalism by any means
We are just
Introducing
Management techniques
So that
They can
Develop their economy
More
Efficiently
In 2010 Andre caught in a plane in China
Headed to north
He was on a quest to train the North Korean d'anjou
Western-style business
Basically bringing honey-coated poison into North Korea with
Kim Jong On Blessing
Nothing about this was normal
Not even the play
So it's sort of like
Stepping back in time and they were running quite old Russian play
Kind of like from the 60s wear
Cute doilies on the window as if you were
Visiting
Grandmother's house rather than
An airline a little lace curtains
Yeah I like little lace curtains
As soon as the plane took off
Music started
Blasting
For the cabin these loud rousing songs about the government and its
Triumph
They were promoting a very important National technology that they had developed
And so they had a song to go along with it
And
And you know after one or two rounds it would really
Get stuck in your head
Andres plane landed just outside of Pyongyang
Van and rode into the city for the first time
The city that had been
Totally sealed off to people like him
For decades
As you approach Victory Street your start to get confronted with the monoliths of the city so there's a huge
What they call a mortality Tower
Massive kind of obelisk
When you come around the corner and your
You're confronted with those huge statues of Kennesaw and Kim Jong-il
20 meter high
Bronze
At just
Looking out over their domain
For eternity
Audrey says it's really beautiful city very August
It's a lot of parks lot of Green Space what people outside
One thing he did not see
There are no ads
You know you're not saying
Sunglasses are
Makeup bag
The only odds are for the country
It's Elfin
Their socialism in their leadership
No
Advertising
And that was just one of the obstacles Andre encounter
Trying to teach this equal groups of don't you how to grow their businesses
Another problem
There's a lot of stuff they could not
Talk about
So in one case we wanted to talk about the trade relationship between
China and North Korea but that is obviously very political
And so what I Workshop leader very cleverly did
Was he traded
Two fictional island
Big island and small island
And
Everybody in the room
Newegg
Because they knew who the small island bus and they knew the big island was
But they were able to have a really shoot fruitful
Discussion about how to manage a trade relationship
With a much larger partner
Because it was abstracted
And Reese's don't you would
Crowded to his classes
People who ran retail shop shoe factory software companies
People with startup ideas
The government even let chosen exchange take a group of entrepreneurs and brought to see how people run businesses overseas
Understood some of the dones you were so poor they brought their luggage in plastic shopping bag
They were so excited to go and so excited to see it
What do you want to see in Singapore
That's what's in a what
What are you curious about
An ATM
Never seen one
I heard about him
Show me ATM
And what happened did you did you like go to the ATM
The guy was like awesome
This is this is so cool
Can't wait for us to get these in my country
Would you like taking photos of ATM
I took photos of everything
The don't you or getting training
Port businesses were growing
The growing local businesses was not going to be enough to
To expand North Korea's economy the way Kim Jong unwine
To do that
They were going to need to bring in money from overseas
Oh hello
Ojai
Can you hear me
Yeah although your voice is a little bit
Oh sorry I will
Is that better
No it's not that
Call Tia is a Dutch business consultant
We spoke over Skype
Currently the connection was
Great
Paul Pierce Western companies up
With Asian businesses
He's been working with North Korea since the 90
He says since Kim Jong on to power a lot more international business is being done in North Korea
For example maybe your smartphone is from
Come Samsung in South Korea
Food maker
In that case it contains some software
Which was made in North Korea
Paul says you cannot find products like
Heineken beer and Philips Electronics in North Korea
Korean stores
We talked about companies they denied doing any business in North Korea
But pauses it can be hard to know what's actually
Because companies always deny doing business in North Korea
The associated with the country is really bad
PR
Butthole says the sanctions are not as tight as you think and a lot of Western company
Do you do business with
North Korea
Although some of them don't actually
No it
Your Walt Disney Company
It happened soft area
Animation
Work took place in North Korea
Is that true was lying
The lion
Apparently partially drawn by SEK Studios
Pyongyang
North Korea
So it was outsourced I think to the Philippines
But then somebody decided it was cheaper
Situated North Korea
So it was actually done in Pyongyang
Without by the way do not Shuffle this
Kim jong-un's plan was working
Local businesses were thriving foreign investment was increasing and North Korea's economy was growing
Capital City pallet construction boom ice skating rink in a floating restaurant
Pyongyang is tightly controlled by the government
It's kind of a show place for
Princeton's people with wheelchairs are not allowed in the city because the government thinks
Nevertheless party says
The changes he saw were strike
Do you see a lot of
Recent new buildings let's say 30 40 or 50 stores
Haifa skyscrapers
Much more traffic than in the past and sometimes
You even come across traffic jams
N
I see fit
North Korean
You see fat North Koreans wear in the fall
The real change says Paul is in the mentality of the North
Everybody talks too now has a startup ID
They all want to go into
There's almost no venture capital.
We had in North
But there is the startup mentality
The tech sector has grown a bit there's a domestic
Internet and even an Amazon type company called men will song where you order online anything from noodles to two
By fours and can get them delivered
Andre abrahamian the business teacher says he has seen the effects of his teachings first-hand
Most recently when he visited the cafe of one of his students
In Pyongyang
I did notice that the barista
At the coffee shop starting to give
A little freebies making me tiny decisions
On their own. Generally North Korean
Weight.
Just do not do
So I'd like to think that we
Contributed to
Slight change in mindset there did you get a little freebie
As a customer
What did you get your number
Extra shot of espresso
Jesse aren't North Korean entrepreneur, bootleggers
Also caught this entrepreneurial spirit
Her business grew and expanded and she started trading products back and forth with China
Smuggling things across the border
She would send medicinal herbs
Animal skins and pine nuts over
China across the yalu river in
These boats
And she would bring very in-demand items back
To North Korea
I'm going to
What you doing
And what we would get in return is
Sausages
And we would get
Soaps
And there's something called
Macarena
That is an artificial sweetener that North Koreans like to use in desert
This is one of Jesse's biggest seller
In fact she uses it at her home in Seoul
She ran to the kitchen to let my translator jihae try some
Taste like
Dried whipped cream
Jessie's business had gone
International
Carnival
Jingle getting the business was prospering on a whole new level
And so was North Korea's government
Kim Jong un's plan to grow the economy with work
The don't you like Jessie Ware doing better
They were making more money and paying more in taxes and bribes to the north
Korean government
It was also more money coming in from other country
Trees from overseas
Political Economist Nicholas eberstadt says all of that money
Whistling Straits
21 place
Nuclear weapons
You have to assume that the real a rapid increase in the tempo of the testing
Has something to do with getting more funds to do it
The economic Prosperity that you helped bring to North Korea
Made the nuclear program possible for
And all the subversive semen capitalism the marketing training International relationships
All of it is ultimately gone to support the military ambitions
Of Kim Jong-il
And this puts people like Paul and Andre in a really strange position when they originally started working in North Korea to try to
Help
People's Credit
Bring money into the economy
And help a population that had at one point literally been starving in the streets
But they did help North
Korea become a wealthier country
Abe Mor weaponized
Do you ever feel
In ethical conflicts
Working with North Korea
I don't have to be ashamed
To support this
Economic cooperation
Because it also helps
The individual worker
In the Garment Factory for example
You will not hear me
Torquing
Sfsf Fentanyl
The North Korea
Cortical cyst
I'm not a fan of them
If we want to see changes in North Korea
It has to be changed from the inside
Like
We have seen in China
It is only because of an upcoming middle class
The second weekend
Chase
But that upcoming middle-class is in a really
Is North Korea the state technically owns every
Don't you were always operating in a legal Gray
Everything they have could be
Be taken away at any moment
And the wealth that they accrue can make them targets
In fact that is what happened to Jesse
Her business is booming she was making more money
And people close to her started to notice
A tattoo
My uncle realized that I was doing all this
It's business and he didn't approve of it at all in
And he reported me
I felt like everything vanished and everything just evaporated in
Snap of a moment
Basically what I had was
Almost all gone
Years and years of work just
Went up in smoke
And Jesse said she was actually lucky she wasn't sent to
But it was at that moment that Jesse realize she was never going to be able to have a stable life in North
Korea is far as building her business back up she says
Her heart just wasn't in it
Her mother had died
And her mother was the whole inspiration for her going into business in the first play
Until
It felt like the sky was falling for me I had nowhere to turn to I have nobody to lean on Jessie decided to leave nor
She had relationships with border guards in China and North Korea from
Smuggler for all those years
So one night she just
Smuggled herself out
Across the yalu river on one of the same boats that should use to transport animal skins and sweetener back in
All Jessie's money everything she owned
Taken by the government
And again
The government had always owned it all anyway
Political Economist Nicholas eberstadt says
People like Jesse are the real tragedy of the current situation in North Korea
Kim Jong on got what he wanted he got the money he needed to grow the nuclear program
But it came of course at a huge price for the North Korean peace
Yes the nuclear threat yes
The missiles Radley
Vicious
Threats against
People abroad
But that's just the Janus face
Of what's happening at home
All the time to millions and millions of people who
Don't have a voice
And
I guess I find that to be the saddest part
The latest round of sanctions and political pressure
From the US
Is having a big effect on North Korea stones
Funding has dried up for entrepreneurial training everything is more expensive and harder to get
And Patia says foreign companies are pulling out of North Korea as fast as they can
But don't you have always been a country
Prediction in North
They were allowed to exist got these little freedoms
Because they helped build up North Korea's military might
But now that Kim jung-hoon has that military might
But don't you are any more fragile position
Will give you an update on Jesse right after that
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online
Presents and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layouts along with features including e-commerce functionality
And mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Jesse is now a student in Seoul South
And I asked her if she's planning on going into business for herself and she has
All of this amazing business experience that she's now in a place where entrepreneurship is actually
Celebrated
But you told me
She doesn't think she wants to go into
Buspar years in North Korea have changed what she thinks of
A success
Linda Hamilton age I realize the value of money and
I think for me
Success is the fact that I'm alive and well
I feel like I've already succeeded in South Korea
We always love to hear what you think of the show send an email Planet Money at npr.org or find us on Facebook
Twitter
Today Show was produced by the wonderful Elizabeth kulas
Anybody senior producer is Alex goldmark Brian orsat is our editor
And I have a couple people I would like to thank so kill Park and Ian mackaye with the group Liberty in North
Also we are looking for our next entry
Come help us make the show
The fun job and it's pay
Applications are due this Sunday October 15th
You can find more information on our website npr.org
Flash money
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Thanks for listening
This is Terry Gross the host of fresh air
We have long-form interviews for all your pop culture needs
Music
Tri R Springsteen interview
Television
The creators of HBO's the deuce
Books
John Lecrae talking about his years as a spy
You can find fresh air on the NPR one app
And wherever you get your podcast