Dan Deming lives on a farm in wisc
I've got a little bit of woods I got about a 4 Acre Woods apple trees there's a couple left but
They are you know they were over a hundred years old so they're starting to
Die off
His great-grandfather boarded in the early 60s from a local
Eccentric
That man's name was Walt
Mallory
And there were all these stories about how Walt
Hated spending money
She was going to get married one time
But he would sit and wail
The food to see how much it would cost to have a wife
So he would
What are the portion of food from self and then he would weigh out a portion of
Food for
To be wife
He decided at that wasn't it wasn't worth it
A true romantic huh yeah
What Mallory state of Bachelor all his life he worked hard never spent any money
And when Dan Deming family bought the place in the 60s
Came with this Legend
The legend was that
He died alone and there had to be money buried here somewhere
NCG is Dan's family tried to find it
There is actually spots in the basement here where my grandfather tried to
Bus stop the concrete to find money
Use a sledgehammer
Didn't find it
At one point
Then himself got a metal detector as a birthday present
He didn't find anything either
I mean years later dad was knocking down this hundred-year-old chicken coop
Out in the yard
And low and behold
Take apart this one wall and
I
Didn't think anything of it at turned around with my skid loader came back
And I saw a box tipped over with a bunch of
Pieces of paper on the ground
And it
The first thing I pop my head was
My grandpa wasn't it wasn't a story it was real
Lost money I found it
He starts running to the house to tell his wife
Harry the way I was running the house she said oh no he got hurt
Can it running and screaming
I don't remember what I said
What did I say Terry I don't have
Look what I found an old metal box and it was full of money
But
Lot of it was rotted and moisture eating away at it molded
And some of it was just so degraded you couldn't even tell
I mean some of us just
Like rotten paper
Sagunto
Octopus box
Moldy bills in his
He said
I want to deposit
Emma Banks
What do they give you fresh money
But we do know someone who might
So danca
They gave me a receipt
Silver box with mutilated currency amount not known it says on the receipt the game
The bank fitdance money
Back to the place
It came from
To the US Treasury
To a team of specialists
With the legal authority to say whether moldy Chicken Coop money
Lives or dies when your life savings gets
Fortune House fire or put through a shredder
There is a room full of people who may be able to help
The mutilated currency division
It is like the customer service
For the dollar bill
Today on the show we go inside the mutilated currency division inside that room where they put broken money fast
Anthony word of counterfeiters
Money lenders who swore swore
He could terrible in half and double
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Fidelity Investment
As a Fidelity wealth management client
You get a dedicated advisor to help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes and make
Clear recommendations for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
So what is the sign say here currency division
Division what's a Divan office inside the Bureau of Engraving and
That is the Bureau that prints the country's money
How did the
Big Stone building a few blocks from the Washington
Everyday the mutilated currency division yet
A hundred or more packages
Like the one with dance
Some of it is burned some
Torrance
What is waterlogged
To get more than 30 million dollars a year
The package is make their way to his big open room
Is that a thousand wooden desks
Lots of life
And sitting at this desk
Are government employees
Currency
About eight of them are going through packages of messed up money
Peace pipe
We talked to one of them
His name is cologne card
Tell me about what
What is this
Kansas actually burn
Burned in house fire
$100,000 is $100,000
Did it this is this box is just a priority mail box here is this priority mail box with the money came in
$100,000 in a priority mail box
Kolento the money also looks like it got wet
Probably when the firemen put out the
So and you have pierced
You can barely tell right it's just like black
Ashley
I just where I don't even know where I saw the hunter on this bill you can't see it at all
But they're just in the corner you can see a hundred
Back together and
A Black Talon
Brick looking at them you just have no idea we would start to workout
I'm visiting the office I was expecting some kind of
High-tech answer to this question
A polarized light microscope kind of laser
Spectrometer I get thinking spectrometer exactly
So what color cancels out to work through this this brick is
Looks like a chisel could be made in 1850
It's just like a metal
On the front with a wood handle
And he actually
Uses the handle he takes the wooden handle
And starts rolling it back and forth with his palm over the
It's actually off
Rolling in actually make the Tennessee Loose
You really made it so birds that like as you're rolling black
Ashes coming off of it like the money is a disintegrating
But it's not
Old
Like this break is loosening up in the end of
Virtual Bill Fay I coming apart
And almost all of those bills you can start to make out like a little bit on the right hand side
So he cuts off the right hand side of the bills
Any paper clips
By the way for your money to count as as good money
You need to either sending more than 50% of a bill
Or if you send in less than 50%
You need to convince the examiner that the rest of the bill was completely destroyed
Zocaloans just going to count Applebee's Friday
Doolittle paperwork and the person who sent in the bed money they will get reimbursed for the value of every bill but kehlani
So what's going on in this room is is
Amazing
It's it's actually a free service provided by the
And you can either say wow that's great thanks government
Where you could say
Wait if somebody has $100,000 in their house
And their house burns down
Like why should I as a taxpayer
Hate government workers
Soar through the money I mean
Keep your money in a bank
If you don't want it to burn down in
So we have to about this
And they told us basically look Congress asked us to start doing
It's a long time ago
They give us the money to do it every year
So we do it
And look it's a public service
You could also say the dollar
The literal dollar bill
Lindsey Pizza
Paper it's an IOU from the US
MS Office is a way of showing the world like
But the government stand behind the
We will be there when bad things happen to good bills
And by we the government means the people in this room
We go to the desk next to Cologne
Bullmastiff
This money back here it just like if I saw it
I wouldn't even know his money I would just think like it's some I'm going to have to scrape off of my shoe
That's a different case because it's wet
Fan on it so I can dried up and about the size of
I don't even know what is high tech solution for what you doing where Monday red
Over another examiner is like
Tasted up a little
Someone sent in with their money
I've been close mutilated currency in the amount of $20,000
1000 $20 bills
To the break-ins
I in in my neighborhood
I took the precaution and hit the cash in our backyard
The currency was placed in a plastic bag
I retrieved the currency a few days ago and found out they have been mutilated
Rain and flooding in our backyard
Had caused the currency to be mutilate
$20,000
And it's a mess
The Examiner going through this money is gal free
GAO April knockout
When's that get bees telling us his name the next
We just cut the corner of $20 bills
That makes me nervous.
And then he's like slowly prying apart every single bill in the sky
We have to identify each node
Because sometime
Did knows I'm Midway conquer face
So so some of them are real but they might sneak a few counter sealer
Right
But of my voice belongs to Lydia washing
She's depressed person for this off
And she said they don't talk about counterfeit currency
The review of the times that we asked about Shady circumstances stuff
Come through the office
She shut us down every time
I mean
Come on right you have you have people sending in
$100,000 in cash
In Priority Mail Boxes
Mysteriously destroyed in a fire
Obviously there is going to be some sketchy Behavior here
They wouldn't talk about it at the office
Fortunately for us
Once in a while it does
Pop out into the public record
A cool s you actually found this one case that went to court
A few years ago
United States of America
Versus phone
$800 in mutilated
Currency
The full force of the United States government is going
Court to sue
A pile of burned up
P******
Waterlogged
Because that is what prosecutors do when they want to
Feel something
Basu
The thing
In this particular case a bank in Argentina with sending millions of mutilated.
That people do use American dollars a lot
But
The examiners in this room still thought something suspicious
So they passed the case to Federal
Who agreed
They thought maybe it was money laundering
Was criminal activity till it went to court
It was $200,000 worth of bills with two pots
The same bill was sending an indifferent
Right and the government sees that 200000
Sorry random kid from third grade your scheme to double your money didn't I
The other four million dollars they're like most of that money it went back to that bank in Argentina
Cases from this office do not wind up in
Pink Floyd Vera
And a lot of them do seem just like honest
For example one of the examiner's Sharon Williams she told us about a case that she got lost
Is a man with Alzheimer's who put his life savings
Shredder $350,000
Shred
Missing pieces
A lot of pee
It's literally been put through a machine that's supposed to make it impossible to put it back together
And your job is to put it back together
Who is this
And my heart goes out for
For the people
Chin specializes in cases where she has to put torn-up money back
I love it because I like
Doing puzzles
When we meet her she's going through
Clear plastic bag of pulling up bills
She said the DC Subway
The bills going to get toned going into the ticket machines and stuff
Safeway
My hair might have to go
Michaels here
Adam Ant
Before we left we talked to Eric Walsh he's the manager he up he's worked in the office for 13 years
Give us some of the greatest
We had a farmer who
Coweta's wallet
We always encouraged mail it in its original package
He actually shipped in the cow's stomach containing the wallet so
What would happen to the cow
The cow did not make it
I thought the cows had.
We allowed animals return season of sometimes they're actually
Process through the system B
Before we get down we by which you mean
Animal poop with money in it
They do
We do return those and have them
Please wash them off before they send it to us but
Refused Return to Sender
What's the most money anybody ever sent
Attempted armored car robbery where l
They attempted to blow off the back doors of the car and
It incinerated about 2 million dollars inside
2 Millions the most with the least
Dollar
$1 in dollars
News you can use
If your money gets wet do not put it in the microwave
There's a little metallic in the strips and it will burst into flames
If I microwave my money I'll burst into flames
South
Please don't
That totally makes me want to put money in the microwave
1 lakh
Piece of advice
Please include your name and address when
No
Baby surprised how many cases we get where there is no correspondence or no nothing and
Unfortunately we can't send out a check unless
Let me know who that money
He's going to send you
Whatever $1,000 and they won't put a return address
And that was it we left not long after that
But what about
Fandemic
What about that
Box of mutilated money he pulled out of the chicken
They gave me a receipt
It said
Silver box with
Mutilated currency amount not known
It says on the receipt
Okay and then what
It was probably almost exactly a year later
I got a letter from the bank
And it went into my account
Some dollars
I thought
I was hoping it would be more I was a little disappointed
So what
You know it's always good to get money I was
It was happy but still
Back in the thirties when Walt Mallory first Berry that Ma
You could buy a house
Windance Grandparents were living in the house in the
You could buy a new car
Then told us
You actually kind of wishes
His grandparents had found
It would have been worth so much more
What you do with it what you do with the money the money I put I already owed money on the new shed I was building so it was already spent
Cool s you have one last
Amazing little anecdote about
The mutilated coin
Division which is a whole other Division and we will have that
Support for this podcast and the following message come from discover
Get a credit score card with your FICO credit score which is used by 90% of top lenders it's available to
To everyone for free even if you're not a customer
Learn more at discover.com credit scorecard limitations apply
Do the story made me want to do more on money
On the sort of sketchy side of this
So
If you are listening and you have a great money laundering story
Tell us what it is you can email us at
Planet Money at npr.org
Find us on Facebook
Thanks today go to Matthew Herrington vehicle Ricky Alvin Lyle and Sydney Rock
Our show today was produced by Nick fountain or editors Brian urstadt and the supervising producer of Planet Money is Alex
Olympia has a new podcast when I tell you about it
It's hosted by Sam Sanders who was the co-host of NPR politics podcast
He's got this new show it's cold it's been a minute
Sanders
Check it out on the NPR one app or wherever you get your
I'm Elizabeth and I'm Jacob Goldstein
Thanks for the
Okay cool as mutilated coins
Scope
You used to be able to send mutilated coins to the US
I'll give you $19.84 for a pound of meat
Metal recycling companies spent five-and-a-half
Million dollars worth
Is it between come from cuz I've been sent from the US
To China
The scrap metal and when these cars are in China
Straighten out and collect coins
Send a message
A bunch of things about this just seemed off
The case went to court prosecutor said this had been submitted from China and lot
10 years and had
Is it being manufactured by the
.
And this one is my favorite the prosecutors they looked at the number of kozilek
Exported to China
And then look at the number of mutilated coins at Come Back Inn
The u.s. Caribbean
I'm going to work it out they said eat your vehicle being sent to China as
Scrap we have to contain $900 in loose change
$900
The defense disputed these numbers the case was eventually set
Let me suspended that coin Redemption program in 2015
No word so far on weather at 7