Here's a thing you here
I don't know
Every single day
The world
Is changing faster than ever before
How about this
Boston research
I've developed a new supercomputer
They claim it can predict if a patient is about to die will be equipped with Nano articulated
This week if not Cowboys versus Aliens if humans vs. robots the world is changing.
Faster than ever taking years or even months what you see right now
Now is
And it is not only cheesy TV news
It is all so cheesy
Podcast
Here's one from 2050
When you add up all the jobs he thinks are going to be left
There will not be nearly enough to make up for the vast number of jobs that machines are going to take over
That was you take me on Planet Money
Stating the spirit of the times you know everybody says
This the world is changing faster than ever
And yet
There is one guy
Does not
Robert Gordon
Using Economist he knows an absurd amount about that
History of Technology
And last year he came out with this big
Influential book
Paul Krugman New York Times
Call Gordon's predictions about the future shocking
Ready Mix powerful case
The world is not change
Faster than ever
In fact he says
A problem isn't too much
It's too little
How long to Planet Money I'm taking cold today
If Robert Gordon is right than a lot of really smart people are wrong today on the show Robert Gordon's argument
And its implications for everything from how the next generation of Americans will live
To whether robots really will take all our jobs
Support for Planet Money and the following message come from betterment betterment aims to answer the
Question how should I manage my money
Betterment easy-to-use platform help you set goals invest your wealth and track your progress note
Hoops to jump through
Have a complex investment situation betterment license Financial experts are ready to answer your question
For a limited time to get one month manager for free
For more information visit betterment.com Planet Money betterment investing made better
When you talk about recording you
Quickly find out that he has
Stored in his brain
Every
Single technological innovation
In America
Arranged by date
There were no window screens
They were invented in the 1880s by 1929
The ratio of Motor Vehicles
The automatic washing machine had been invented by 1920 Amazon was founded in 1994
Gordon took
All of those facts
And many more
And put them all together in that book
It's called the rise and fall of American growth
It is about 700 pages long and it is actually fascinating we both read it it's a good book a good read
And we called Robert Gordon.
Alright can you hear us
Yes I can
Excellent hello
When does the story about technological
Not just for the sake of Technology but for how it really affect
He says
Okay I understand this in like the big Longview way
Do what thought
Play It's the year
And you got some person
Weaving back then
Delivery Man
What does livery police looking fruit
They even have fruit they totally have ever dated
So he's delivering apples
He's got me he's got a horse
He's lucky he's got a cart
And you don't think of his world
If he needs to cook something
Cox overfire Longway bringing the Apple
Clothes from one town to another town where do you have to go to the bathroom
Poops in a hole there's no water there's no flush
Toilets
This is his
So we have we have our delivery
He's in your head
This world is in your
Now it's time for that
Popcorn says imagine that delivery
Lays down under
Falls asleep
For hundreds of you
He wakes up
He's in the United States
The 1800
She gets up
He looks around
NEC the world that looks
Like
Not that differ
From the world he fell asleep
Yeah they're still horses
Cuz I'm cards he still walking along way cooking over a fire poop in a hole in the ground
So you know hundreds of years apart
And
Not that much has changed
Because
1800 or so
Things did not change that much from year to year or even from
Century to Century
Now thought experiment part 2
Same delivery guy
It's tired again
In 1870 takes a nap
470 years
Short by his
Wakes up in 19 for
Princess
She wakes up in a world that is
Wheatley transfer
They would
Not
Believe
That you could pick up
An instrument
And talk to somebody
A hundred or a thousand miles away
On
The telephone
They wouldn't know that too
Illuminate a room
You could turn a switch
They would
B flabbergast
To look up at the sky
And see
Objects
Flying in the sky
So which
No more pooping in holes in the ground right now there are
Flush toilets there are cars driving around everywhere our guy even has a truck after hundreds of years of a horses
Kitchen
Teaching is like a thing right now there's a
Refrigerator which is never no more
And if you go to City lookup
And they're just like these ridiculous impossibly tall bill
The person who
Went to sleep in 1870 would have been
Completely
Astonished
How to go to New York City
Ride a Subway
Come out of the subway in gaze up
Add buildings that
We're already
A 75
Or even a hundred stories tall and then
Quesadilla
Empire State Building which was built in 90
The man knows every single date for everyone
Anybody it's for a point he has a point
And the point of this whole thought
Experiment
Sleep
Waking up going to sleep waking up
What is this
For hundreds of years
Hardly any change at all
And then
You miss one lifetime
Just this one single span
Everything came
There is just as complete transformation
Extraordinary
How much
How fast at this
And most of those changes grow out of
Two key things
Number one
Electricity
And number two
The internal combustion engine
So like what today is it's a regular rolled
Dakotaz called called things like
Electricity
The internal combustion
They called them
General-purpose technology
And the basic ideas
These Technologies
That you all kinds of different things
All across the
So you see that in this in this 1870 to 1940. You see them transforming sort of
Daily life
But they are not done yet electricity and the internal combustion engine they still got more to give
Bob Gordon says in the in the next period in the middle of the 20th century
They transformed the way we work
They make work much more efficient they let workers
Is do a lot more
He said you really see this starting right around World War
The famous Willow Run plant that was built by Henry Ford
They were producing one bomber an hour
By 1944 and 45
Bomber airplane in 1 hour
They were course making a number of them
They work but coming out the end of the factory door was one bomber an hour
Extraordinary
After the war
American workers
Keep getting more and more productive
The government building
Highway that makes truck drivers more efficient but it also means lots of other kinds of Industries get more efficient cuz they can you know me
Move all their stuff around from one place
Another Gordon says around the same time
Electricity gives us another big
Breakthrough
This one's more surprising
Air condition
Air conditioning created again
Enormous
Improvement in productivity predictably for off
Office workers
I trapped inside in the summer
And do you see like when air conditioning gets too
A sector in Officer town
That workers actually do
Do more
Yes there
There are studies that
Show distinct Improvement
All across the economy year after year
Productivity
Is going up
And not just anecdotal
The government Ashley
Track productivity
Trax how much value and average worker is creating a
Hour of work
And this number productivity productivity growth
Doesn't that you know recorded much in the Press people don't talk about it much
But Economist Arabic
Seth
Because in the long run
Productivity growth is the way society as a whole gets better off
You know productivity growth is the reason that people in the 50s
These are doing so much better than their grandpa
Tractors with internal combustion engines replaced horses
Food. Moore
Builders started using electric
Power tools instead of hand tools
An ordinary people could afford bigger more comfortable houses
Seema Mehta work
More and better stuff
Productivity growth
Trucking along in the 50s and 60s
It slows down in the seventies and eighties
And then
Get another
YouTube
In the 90s
From
Computers and internet
M computers they are a new general purpose technology
She that does all kinds of different things
All these different facets
And so in the 90s
Businesses are going online.
Replacing paper with
Computers
Workers are getting much more productive even after the.com bust into the early years of the 21st Century
Productivity is growing really fast
But then
In 2004
Something goes
Productivity growth
Comes crashing
Did not play you know in the popular press as a disaster
You know it's like that moment in the movies where the
Recite one dog that just starts
Starts barking at Anna
He's trying to tell us something
What is it boy
Productivity growth
So I kind of soda
It was maybe a temporary thing and then we had the Great Recession than I expected that ass the recovery proceeded
That we would begin to get productivity of picking up again
This is Martin Bailey he was the chairman of President Clinton's Council of economic advisers
And he has been studying productivity for a long time
So that when I looked at you know 2010-11 12 13 14
1516 and it still wasn't picking up that's when I began to get really nervous
So you're nervous now if it goes through
60 that means you're nervous right now
I know it's right now yeah
In the last few years we have heard a lot about the rise of in a koala
The idea that the economic pie is not being divided
And of course that is important
But Bailey and other economist
We also need to figure out this other thing
We also need to figure out
Why is the pi barely growing at all
Why is productivity growth
They come up with a name for this
They call it the productivity paradox
And this is what the productivity paradox
We have all of this amazing technology
Robots artificial intelligence the cloud
And it should be making us more productive that's what technology does
But
When you look at the numbers for the economy of a
All that technology does not seem to be making a difference
It does not seem to be making us more productive
I do hear that and you say
There is no way that can possibly be true right it seem so impossible which is why they call it a parrot
That's the paradox
And there are few different
Part of it
Party with cardi
Maybe we are getting more
We're just not measuring
You know it's easier to measure
A productivity output per worker per hour
When people are saying making cars but today there's lots more people working in hospital
How do you measure the productivity of a Hosta
Even if you account for that Economist say it really looks like productivity is
Still growing much more slowly than at you
They say
Listen
It doesn't feel true but trust us when we do the numbers that's what we
Robert Gordon thinks he knows what's going on
And his explanation it goes back to the delivery guy who fell asleep in 1870 and woke up in 1940 and the world
I totally change
Princess
Do another thought
Compare that
The somebody who fell asleep in 1950
And woke up to
Today for the person who woke up to
What would have seen do
To the
Would be everything to do with computers
Course computers a huge deal laptops
IPhones are everywhere all the magic that comes with
But then
Gordon says think about everything else
Think about just like a normal house
Remember that person went to sleep in 1870 and woke up in 90
40 they were shocked to see houses that had
Running water and Refrigeration
The
Person going to sleep in 1950 and waking up today with only find one
Element of the kitchen which is new
And that is the microwave oven
That's a great person for 1950
Listening as today
We find her car is entirely familiar
Guitar delivery guy
Went to sleep with the truck
Wakes up with another truck
Maybe
GPS now but remember last time
That truck
Replaced his
Horse-drawn carts
Last time we went to sleep
New York City had streets full of horses
The tallest building with a church
He woke up to Subways in skyscraper
This time just the same subway system is existed in Empire State Building Rising above
Everything else
And yes he says
Shirt the new World Trade Center is a little taller than the Empire State
But it's like with the car it's just an incremental change
It's not some big revolution
More of the same rather than something new
Gordon says
The world just has not changed as much in the past
70 years as it did in the seven years before that
Those big 20th century changes driven by electricity
The internal combustion engine
Those were just
A much bigger deal than the changes
That have been driven by computers
Gordon says computers and the internet they did give us that amazing decade in the late 90s and early aughts that was when
You know most people got the internet
Google came along it was when smartphones came along
We had all that already you know 10:12
Since then criticize
Not that much has changed
But the iPhone
Yes one of the peculiar aspects of the
Last 10 years is that so much
Innovation is gone into the iPhone and all the associated app
In fact the record for productivity growth in the last 6 years
Is about as low as has been in US recorded history
Has it ever been as far as We Know
My coming at this from the outside
I really
Do find it shocking
That's because the main ways in which computers
Raise business productivity had already happened by 10 years ago
And the
Nature of the iPhone
With most of its uses
Is in
Your personal space
So sure iPhones are a huge deal in our personal lives
But they haven't really fundamentally changed the way that most of us do our work
And other Technologies
Robots
Artificial intelligence
Because they haven't changed work that much either
I play a game called find the robot
Everywhere in my life
When I travel I get on the airplane I
I go into a hotel I see human beings do the same thing that they did to 10 or 15 years ago
Ian office situations going to the doctor the dentist the veterinarian
Going into retail stores going into restaurants
I see a large part of the economy that operating in the
The same way as it did last year and the year before
Princess this isn't just his little game of spots
He says the numbers for the economy as a whole back
If in fact robots and computers were replacing humans in vast numbers
All those machines would lead to lots more out
And there would be fewer hours of human labor
So productivity would be going up
Really fast
But it's not
Productivity is barely going up
Also
If robots and computers were
Taking our jobs overnight
The number of jobs would be declining
But that's not what's happening
The economy has been adding millions of jobs for year
Year after year
I tend to look at myself as a jobs Optima
I even if I maybe
A techno pessimist
Okay so that's Robert Gordon story of the last
150 years
Also the last 10 years
Obvious questions
We'll have that in a minute
Don't touch that dial
And by dial I mean be globally connected supercomputer in your pocket
Support for Planet Money and the following message come
From iShare
Because the best preparation for tomorrow
It's building for your future today
Ishares by BlackRock
Inspire to build
Gordon thinks about the future
He thinks that the next 10 years
They're going to look a lot like the last 10 years
Sort of incremental changes things get better slowly
But no big
We weren't book came out last
Steer this part his his claims about the future
That was what I think the most people should have quarreled with
We are smart and Bailey about
Does he smoke Economist who is nervous about the Prado
Robert Gordon has been fairly consistently pessimistic
About
Productivity growth
And so far he's been proven right
Is it going to be right in the future
It doesn't look like it
Because it looks as if
That technology Willy is moving ahead
You know
We're at the end of the show here I like I'll have to say I love
Love Gordon thought experiment about the guy falling asleep
It really
I think
It really is a lovely way to think about technology
Change anything oh we're not so special right now
But when it comes to the future I mean it feels to me and to Bailey and too many of the people who I talk to
My coordinate probably is not right
Feels like things really are about to change
Denise big
I don't know I hear people talk about things being about to change in these hugely profound ways
But
That always a kind of sounds like a V
Dream to me
And then I think about Robert Gordon who is
Just like
Down there in the
Dirt with all the details and every single date
Everyday
And what he saying is
If you take the Long View
You will see that
Slow incremental change
Is normal
We had a thousand years of just
Horses and cooking
Fires
And then we have is really strange time
Past couple hundred years or so
When things change very quick
And now
Maybe we're about to the way things have always been
To another era where change is slow
Not a horse to a car
Just an iPhone
To a better iPhone
Everyone at that we talked to you about the premise of the show
What argue with us about the show
So if you want to argue with us about the show please email us Planet Money at mpr.org or you can find us
On Facebook where you love you
Car show today was produced by Nick Fountain Bryant urstadt and Alex goldmark are the two people in charge of productivity
Free games of Planet Money special thanks to Joe machir Dale Jorgenson and John furnald all of them
Talk to me at Great length about productivity and Technology
She gave up the idea for the show if you're looking for something else to listen to
And you have kids and you want to listen to something with your kids
Got you newspaper
NPR just launched a new podcast for tip it's from Gyros who is great the show
It's called wow in the world I'm very excited to see her with my own children again is called wow in the world you can find it on NPR one
Npr.org podcast or wherever you get your partner
I'm Jacob and I'm telling him thanks for listening