There is no one who is more optimistic
More Sunny than a politician who is writing a budget
And we just saw this in Donald Trump's budget this
In order to make the numbers work
Trump makes this big assumption
The economy is going to expand and grow every year
Nothing but Blue Skies
Unicorns rainbows
If there is a number that sums up this Rosy picture
Trump's budget assumes that the US economy will speed up
And grow by 3% a year over the next decade
3%
Minimum pay for this is from Fox News
At some point
Into the future
5 and above
How to respect the optimism when you put it that way I mean growing your car
3% me 3% sounds easy
If someone
Hey
2.3% no problem at 7
40%
IPhone economy besides the United States
3% growth
Is incredibly difficult
In President Obama's first budget
He promised more than 3%
Growth and year after year we never got
And you can think of it this way
To grow 3% a year for 10 years means that in a decade the US economy would be a third larger
It is now
That is a lot of growth
Currently the US economy is growing at around a real rate
2%
Donald Trump could get us to 3% growth
He would be an economic hero
Improbable
But it is not impossible
So we got to thinking here
What would it take
What would it take for Donald Trump's economic vision
To come true
Could we
Come up with a plan to get the United States to 3% growth
You know Robert it is like what that cartoon from Schoolhouse Rock used to say
Schoolhouse Rock
What's the magic number
The magic number Blind welcome to Planet Money I'm Stacey Vanek Smith Robert Smith
3%
Bro
If Donald Trump is right we are about to enter a new golden age of jobs and progress
Increase the size of the military we can cut taxes when you build a wall roads Bridges sky's the limit
3% is doable
Show we make a plan to get there
Play Problem
Donald Trump probably is not going to like
What it's going to take
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their
Your own website
Using customizable layout
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobile added
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization to help you develop an online presence
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Okay we're going to do something today that we almost never do
We're going to come up with policy and do some math
To see how it all works out
We've sharpen some pencils
Here at the Planet Money studios in New York
And we've invited an expert into our Studios
NBC
So I'm hearing a bunch of things moving around sorry about that
But you're literally rolling up your sleep
Yeah well we're doing budgeting
Mark gold mine is the policy director with the committee for a responsible federal budget
Their nonpartisan group
Deep into the weeds
How the government spends money started by Republicans
And Democrat
I never made a president's budget I have served on two commissions
Where we had to make a series of recommendations and add actually add up
When the president's budget came out Mark was really looking forward to seeing how it added up
He started looking through when he saw this number
3%
Economic growth
He's like
The president doesn't say anything about how he's going to make this happen just
Will happen
Impact Trump's budget advisor said the core of trumponomics is to
To pick a number to pick a dream
And work your way toward that
Aspirational
Economics
So Marcus group decided to do the math that the president left out he was going to figure out exactly what it would
3% growth is
Possible hit absolutely everything goes right at the same time
And that means everything going right
In terms of policy
And it means everything going right in terms of luck
Okay so let's break this
Thing.
Economic growth is measured in
Gross domestic
Product this is the sum of all the goods and services we produce every
Year in the economy
And there was plenty of time
When the GDP grew more than
Percent of year
A lot of those times have to do with
The Baby Boomers always the Baby Boomers the Baby Boomers will bring the 1960s when the first wave of baby boomers were starting to get dry
There were more people working
More workers means more stuff
And that equal to Grant County
Same thing in the 1990s the Baby Boomers were reaching their Peak earning years
Card making stuff
There was this technological boom and computers and the internet
The economy grew really fast
From now is that the Baby Boomers always the Baby Boomers retire and we've been struggling to get
Just
2%
San Marcos team came up with soda
General
3 biggest economy
We can effect
To make sure that
The first one is to find someone
Anyone really who can take the Baby Boomers place
Need to find more work
Once again more workers make more stuff
Provide more services and
Make the GDP go up
That's exactly right and so one of the tools that folks have discussed with run the economy
Is more immigration
But first get 3% growth we would basically need to double our immigrant
Over the next decade
Wake me up existing immigrant immigrants today
That are here today
Some of them have been here for as much as
What's a 80 years
Right so we need to take the last 80 years of immigration
And do it again in the next
If we roughly did that if we roughly double the amount of
Immigrants
That could get us
Theory
Something at least
Close to free
Women it sounds like you should much more growth than 3%
For that many people take that millions of people
Play what about 40 to 50 million
People
But remember
When economy
At starting with about
350 million people
And also remember we're not only having
Adult working-age working immigrants
Right immigrants would also
Two children and the elderly and people that
Eventually would become disabled or otherwise outside of the work for
So it's not like
We can pick people one by one and
Secured that every single one of them
Is it going to be
Fast contributor to the Econo
40 million immigrants
Does not sound like something that President Trump would
Support
I mean not only
Should you not build a wall at that point that you should
Actually charter buses to bring people over
What is the definition to show you how hard 3% growth is without the Baby Boomers
You need 40 million more immigrants
To make up for it
Okay so let's just assume that 40 million immigrants is politically unfair
Right now okay
There's another way so one option is to actually look to the problem
For the solution
Part of the reason that
Our economy is slowing actually the main reason
Is that we're getting older
And part of that is because we're living longer
But embedded in that is a partial solution which is that
As we're living longer we're actually healthy
There's opportunity
Press to work
On average
More years
Press to have more productive aging more flexible retirement
So otherwise keep the baby boomers around don't let them retire
I'm not saying don't let them retire
But if everybody just worked one year
More
There be a significant effect on economic
Navigate to 3%
But that would give us a decimal point or so
10 years more
Might do it
The average retirement age right now is about 60
Evan said every work to 73
That might get us
Sitting very close to that free
What should we do to keep it working longer
Without mandating they have to work
We have a lot of signals we send people to tell them to retire early
The Social Security early age of 62
The normal age is 66
Xn
Not really going to rise of life expectancy the Medicare e26
T5 you can pull out from your IRA at 59 and a half
You know we can start to
Gradually lift these ages a little bit
We can create tax breaks like a payroll tax break for folks at work
We can change a lot of the regulations and rules
Encourage employers
To keep people on
Longer
Okay so just increasing the labor force alone unless we talked about really radical
Will not get us to 3 /
I mean that's right there's there's one more option for the labor force
So
There's also
Summerville untapped population
Currently right there is there are folks that are unemployed and are pugs that are out of the labor force.
I could be entering it
But if you took the unemployment rate down to zero
Not even be close to 3
Percent growth weed all set to do is take
Every single adult
H25 255 in every single prime age adult
And force them to work
And that includes folks that are
Homies are taking care of their kids
That includes folks that are in jail that are on disability
Include some folks that legitimately could be working with the right
Mexican citizen support
So we can get to 3% growth
It basically every single
Adult
Every single working age adult
Was working
That's not a realistic view of the economy
I feel like my dad would be excited about
Everybody works no matter
Newk's Q
I feel like you're a failure sick you got to work
OK Google
First set of ideas different ways to add more work
This is the most direct way to make up for the Baby Boomers but it's also
Insanely difficult to get people to work
When they don't want to
To drive people back from retirement
I mean people have a lot of reasons to
Cannot
Making
But let's set aside the workforce idea for now because there is another set of things that Trump could do to
To boost economic growth
And I think this one would be more up his alley
The second thing that drives economic growth is what we call
Capital and it's basically means
All of the machines buildings software
All the stuff that we use
To make more stuff
Talk about
Right I mean more factories more stores every time something gets built
You get more economic growth
More government building projects
Infrastructure
Objects
Tools hammers microphone speakers
I use Excel Microsoft Excel that's one of my
Best pieces of capital in my job
We would need to basically double
Are Capital Growth projection over the next decade
And we would
Need to do significantly better about twice as well
We need to improve about twice as wild weed in the night
Summer in the 1990s we had the
Tech Revolution
Means so much new software so much new it
Fiber optic laid out in every
Street in America
SMS around in the nineties every office bought that big desktop
Computer forever
What if their workers if your white collar worker
Exactly so back in the 1990's
There was some years we were growing over 4% and we were steady growth
That was in the
Mid-height
If we were to do that again
If we were if something were invented
Every single office
Would absolutely have to buy whether it's
I don't know
Virtual reality or hologram something that just transforms
Business in a way
And in people have to pour money in Tampa
Intuit
How much would we have to do
If we were to go back to the 90s level of Capital Growth
That would get us about two and a half
Annual growth
Ridecell
In round numbers were trying to jump from 2 to 3
And that would get us halfway there
So we would need to. Com booms
Going simultaneously at the same time
Now maybe we can get that with self-driving cars or something else
But I'm not seeing where that is right now
Okay
Altitude.com booms
Concurrently to.com booms at the same time in different arenas
So we would need a golden age of
Whole new set of tools are factories are types of businesses that didn't occur
A lot of new
More likely more realistic if you would do a lot of little things that encourage businesses
So we talked to the podcast
Before about corporate tax
Reform a lower corporate tax could decision Theory get businesses
To expand
If it's done right a lot of
Those businesses that have moved
Overseas
For tax reasons they might come back
You at all those together and Mark says you could get
Some fraction of a percent of economic
Okay
So there is a final way that we could get to three
Without the new workers without the new fact
We could just all get a whole lot better at our jobs I've been saying that a lot of pictures
Productivity
Productivity people get better and better each year and they produce more and more goods and services
Each year
Then that alone will grow in economy
Amazing
Particular sense
Pronto Pizza
Check the other two
Yeah magic as in you don't have to open the borders you don't have to convince businesses to buy all this new stuff
It's a sort of
Free Solution
But also magic and that no one really knows how productivity is
We just did a whole show about this and sometimes there's a lot of new inventions or
Technologies that transform everything about the
The way we work
But recently there's actually been a productivity slump in this
Even with the iPhone in the cloud in the internet and everything like that
Productivity hasn't really grown much over the last decade and we would have to have some
Huge leap forward
Kate at 3% growth
We need to do better than we did a 19
60s in the 1960s
Which
It's hard to believe anything about
That's really when the benefits of
Electrification
Basically the entire country
The benefits of Home Appliance
Any benefits of
The National Highway
System we're all making our labor much more productive than it has ever been
And it's it's really not clear we can never repeat
Things that are so fundamental to our lives
That way we don't even think about what it would be like
So we need to find that next thing
That next productive idea that is fundamental to our lives
And I was going to change the way we do so
Wing it faster productivity
Three things we know how to do like more research and experimentation
Like better incentives
Presta
Get higher returns
But together
Productivity Revolution like in the 1960s
Way to find something we haven't even thought of
I've been reading books of Science Fiction
Lately it has occurred to me that perhaps science fiction writers
Should come up with something should come up with this sort of new idea that can
I think the Baby Boomers are still the key I think if they pull their Collective brainpower they can get us yet another economic
Just one more I believe I've one more is all we're asking
This is part of the problem
The time we have grown up in has let us to believe
High growth
Is easy that it is the status quo
We take it apart it is really been a bunch of sort of Lucky One Time brakes I mean there is not going to be another
Baby boom
And you only get one shot at certain
Desktop computer
Revolution
From here on out
It's going to be a slow grind ticket
But what if you did like a little bit of all the
What if you had a little immigration reform some better Education and Training
What about that
Yeah what about that
We're going to park to the math after the break
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Capital One
Keep your credit score at peace with a credit wise app from Capital One
Get alerts each time your credit is pulled and when your TransUnion credit report changes
Plus it's free for everyone download the creditwise app today
Mark gold wine has been doing the math for us and I asked him okay if we got a little bit of everything we talked about
About immigration reform maybe something to
To boost productivity some of those retirement changes we talked about
What do you think the American economy
Can grow out what you hope
Michael number one is let's get to the right side of
And then I go number two is
Let's try to get into our way up to
3% I think if we
If we get serious and immigration I do think two and a half percent achievable
Just because
Immigration card
It's almost cheating because immigration just brings you more
Right that's that's a lot easier than these other things
Play easier
To bring in more people than two
Encourage people
On their own volition to work longer or to work more hours
As we said at the beginning
Donald Trump probably isn't
Going to like
But you know we have set out
The big dream it's sort of like how you know John F Kennedy challenged America to put a man on the moon
Trump quote if you wanted to challenge us to
Transform
Our society
To accomplish 3%
I mean picture
Gray haired Baby Boomers still working late into their 70s right alongside
40 million new immigrants driving on New Roads over new Bridges to new factories not driving being driven
Buy autonomous vehicles
Yes giving us time to put on a Virtual Reality helmets where we could take online courses
It would allow us to be more productive at our jobs
3D printing they always throw 3D printing it always
To paraphrase a president
That got us by the way to
6% growth
Now we are going to Q Roberts really terrible John F Kennedy impression
We choose to fight
What's 3% growth
And all these new technologies
Not because they are easy
Because
Phone
And the other two
Mark gold wine the senior policy director of the committee for a responsible federal budget for coming in and doing the math
We would love to hear from you even through old Technologies like email Planet Money at npr.org or letter
Or letter Coast Guard newfangled technology like Twitter and Facebook are also welcome
By the way Robert and I are going to be performing at a live show the Saturday June 10th in Brooklyn in Brooklyn Park
Best Madden see us we would love to have you there. Org
Our show is produced by a millennial Nick Fountain good luck to you you're taking over buddy and it was edited by
Rhinostat orsino producer is Alex go park on Robert Smith and I'm Stacey Vanek Smith thanks for listening
There's another way
There is another way another one another one
My daughter was on a rant by DJ Khaled
DJ Khaled
Do anything
Brings people together
All I do is win win win no matter what
Got money on my mind I can never get enough
Everytime I walk into the building everybody's hands go up