About 10 years ago Suzana Morgan was running
Food bank in Alaska
And she really needed fresh Pro
Produce she always did
One day the phone rang it was a speak National charity called
Feeding America
Feeding America is this network of food banks all around the country
Including Suzanne
What they do is they get these
Big donations
Food and they figure out where they should go
I'm just called they said they had a big donation
It was not fresh produce
It was a truckload of 5 gallon buckets
You're kidding me you're offering me pickles
Make a person who said yeah I know I know I know but you guys have been hanging out there at the top of the list
For quite a while
This is the first thing we've had that we think will really make it all the way to Alaska
What are you doing
We strong-armed every soup kitchen we could find instead
Peking pickles to ask the people
Feeding America
Why are we getting more fresh produce
And so
Feeding America would say well we didn't offer you that truckload of oranges
Out of California because we thought they'd Transportation be too expensive and I would say
That's green there that's because Susannah had set up her own transportation
So they're feeding America had offered her fresh fruits or vegetables
She could get them truck to Alaska really cheaply
But the people at the feeding America home office didn't know that
In a lot of food banks had this problem
One food bank director in Idaho
My home state
Complained that he got a truck load
I mean come on it's Idaho of course he already had a warehouse full of potatoes
But have been donated by local
Call Farmers
This is the real consequences for Hungry people all over the
It meant that
People in Alaska we're not getting fresh produce we're not getting saved
And at the same time the food bank in Idaho had too many
Not enough other stuff
Everybody knew this was
But for a long time they just live
And then Susanna says a new CEO came into feeding America
And as usual what happens when you bring in a pair of fresh eyes they look at
Get something and say
Can't imagine how you guys are living with that system that sucks
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Jacob Goldstein
And I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Do they have a show a bunch of food bank directors
Including at least one socialist
Tried to figure out
Better way
To get food
They're bold experiment
Free market
Sort of freak
Definitely
By the way
The show originally ran back in 2015
This message comes from NPR sponsor squares
Squarespace allows small businesses to design and build their own website
Using customizable layout
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobile added
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online price
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Bold experiment having about
10 years ago
The new CEO started gathering together a group
Time from headquarters Food Bank directors from around the country including Suzana Morgan from Alaska also
From the University of Chicago
Susanna and the other food bank directors start flying to Chicago every
Sitting down in a room
And talking about their own version
Of the pickle prop
And pretty soon Susanna says
To get to the heart of it
It is a problem for someone else to make decisions for you
It is a problem with somebody else is trying to decide whether this is something you need or not when they don't know what's in your infant
At the moment
They don't know what your local donations
Suppliers they don't know what your
What donated Transportation you've arranged for or what your fundraising is at the moment
To have a central office trying to make those decisions far away from those sources
Pictures of knowledge led to all sorts of mismatches
When it comes in the room heard Susanna and her colleagues layout
The problem this way
They got very
Excited
Suzanne remembers one Economist in
Hannah Sprint
Once we were able to lay it out in those clear terms and then Candice from the University of Chicago was able to
Jose well
Sounds like an economic problem to me
Sounds like economics 101
There's the sprays in economics
The local knowledge problem
And it's why centrally planned economies don't work
No matter how smart the people in control are
Weather there in headquarters
Capital One
The castle or whatever
They just don't have the knowledge to decide whether the people you know out in Alaska should get
Pickles are orange
When I talk to
Economist who was in the room with Suzanne in the others
He told me that
Clear answer to the local knowledge problem is
A market
Place where buyers and sellers
Because the beauty of a mark
Reticular the beauty of prices
If they show you how much different people are
In this case different Food Bag
Value different things
McKenna says that room full of food bankers
Was not very excited to hear his
Pitch for the virtues of the
The free market
One of the
To Bankers a wonderful guy called John Arnold came up to me and said look
I'm sorry
I have no interest in this I listen to you but I don't think of any entry
I should mention that John Arnold passed away a couple years ago but when I ran this quote by Susanna she said yeah I could totally am a
Johnson
And anyway John was not the only food that girl who is wearing
The market
I think many of them have
The following sentence
Markets are sometimes unfair
It benefits
The powerful
It benefits the wealthy benefits
Strong
There
Focus is so much
And the others
The ones who've been left
Behind left behind by Mark
By tomorrow night market
Flea markets
And their great fear is that
Whatever we came up with would do the same
And if it did
They would prefer they also
The idea of a market just seems
Fundamentally contrary to the spirit of food activities are places that give away food
For free too hungry
And in any case it wasn't like feeding America could just sell food to the local
One problem with that is the food banks in poor areas often have the hardest time raising money from local donors
So they wouldn't have enough money
I need to buy the
So Kanis and the other economist
Ask the food
What about fake money
What is feeding America
Did its own little economy
And give out fake money to all the food banks which they could use
To buy the food
Next question they said was
Butthead
How do we make sure the neediest
Lowes Foods
Switch reset
We getting the most fake money
And sometimes late maybe that was one of the early
Breakthrough moments which was the idea that the poor can actually be wealthier than the rich
In fake money
Exactly
You can imagine
Escaping this fake money
Need to the neediest place
Isis and then letting them buy you know whatever they want out of this National feeding America
But you still have to solve all these other problems
What should prices be in this new fake love
How do you let everybody shop in a way that's fair
Tok more flights to Chicago
Forbidden City
The Economist
And finally
Kenneth and his colleagues came up with the big idea
Suzana Morgan remembers when
China said
Well
How about eBay
How would it work if we set up a system in which all of the food
In truckloads that's donated goes onto a
A technology platform
And the decision as to whether you want it for your food bank is made at the food bank
And
How much you wanted is made by how much you bid on it
And how did that play in the room
The clouds opened and the angels sang
That never happened
Okay maybe wasn't quite.
That biblical but
Literally this
This moment in which we just went
We have had a breakthrough
And then we had to spend a year 18 months after that working out the
The details
But it was details from that point
It was like setting up a whole lot
Fake money
Prices at by auction
And with that
Kiki twist
The food banks the fed the most hungry
People would get the most
Fake money
To see how the system works in real life I went out to the Community Food Bank of New Jersey
Teva shoes Warehouse out by the Newark Airport
Tristan wallet give me
Can see some raisins up here
Can salmon you got some grapefruit juice
What else do we have here we have some tomato sauce
I think money is samsara
The pancakes are interested in particular cuz I know we just bought some pancake mix
So the moment when syrup was particularly valuable
Cuz you are a guy with pancake batter but no syrup exactly
Soap at least for now that means a lot of people in New Jersey can now have syrup
With their pancakes
Full cut up here we can head back to the office
The office is a smallest room attached to the warehouse
It's weird Tristan bids annies auction
We get in there and he open the browser on disk
Computer plugs into the feeding America
System and shows me this morning's auction
Down at the bottom of the page there's a number in red
This is like Tristan's bank account
A fake money
The money by the way has this warm fuzzy sounding name
Shares
What is this a right here yeah it says available shares at the moment I have 5439
Chairs
You can kind of you shares I I view it as like Monopoly money
Everyday feeding America gives Tristan some fake
Money in his bank of
And there's a formula so that the
The food banks that feed the most people will get the most
Make money on a typical day Tristan's Food Bank
Gets a few thousand shares
You can think of it like an allowance yes and he can treat it like an allowed
If he wants to spend it everyday on something
Little he can do that
If he wants to hoard it and splurge on something
Big
I can do that too
Today people's up the action on his computer look through the stuff there
Fanta grape soda
Polly O cheese
And then something catches his eye
It's a truckload of Siri
Clicking on here I can see that there's a lot of corn flakes
There's a little bit of Frosted Flakes on here
There's some Kashi cereal about a hundred thousand bucks
He says cereal is something people always
And that he doesn't get enough up
From his local.
He can't actually see how much the other food bank
And Candice and Susanna and the others they designed the system this way so the
The people couldn't just wait until the last second and bid one more fake dollar to get what they wanted
So it's a sealed-bid auction
You put a number in and wait
And when the options done you see if you want
The system does tell Tristan that on average
Truckloads of cereal like
Is 1/2 Old
For 4004
I currently have about 5400 chair so I'm going to
Did all my Shares are going all-in
Yeah I'm going to go all in and
Is even going all-in this is
No guarantee that I'll get it
Tristan Thompson is Bid
Click submit
Now it's a waiting game
Crossing fingers and hoping for the
I asked Justin to show me some of the other stuff
Set sold at auction
And you pulled up a bunch of results on a
What's this one pickles pickles what was surprised they put in a bit of - two
2000 - 200
For stuff that's really unpopular food banks don't want to pay the truck it in
They don't want to find a place
Place to store it
So they can bid negative share
In other words they can say sure
I will take the pickles
If you will give me extra fake money
That's what happened with the pig
So they want it by saying it will take it off your hands if you pay us exactly few minutes after Tristan bid on that cereal
This morning's auction is over
I think the results should be in if we
I'm nervous are you nervous I'm a little nervous
Tristan Hicks
Refresh
So we lost it
You didn't get someone else
Oneness load with 11500
4shared the winter bit
Twice as much as
Someone in Evansville Indiana
Christopher Bank
Yes I am trying to reach John please
This is him
This is John strain
The tri-state
Food Bank proud new owner of 100000 boxes of Siri
Was there a particular reason right now that you especially wanted cereal
I just knew that we were down
Tug
Basically about to have a trailer full of cereal and it goes
It is probably will be gone
Next two weeks
John actually gets
Less fake money allowance
Everyday Ventura
But he's been saving up for a week
And he was about to run out of cereal this food that everybody really wants
At the breakfast to supper at midnight if it doesn't matter when you keep cereal you know
Heated dry YouTube milk
Ideal whatever
So whatever makes you happy
He figured it was worth it to go big
It's been more than twice the average
And get that c
Tristan in New Jersey two sides
He really needs cereal
He can save up to
His own monster bit up the next time we're cornflakes
Come up for auction
John and Justin are too new to remember much about that old system back when feeding America just
Send people stuff
But it seems like the new system is definitely in
Suzana Morgan said the auction system that they could finally get produce at the food bank and I laugh
I can has the economist
Tommy even John Arnold the Socialist from Michigan even he came
He went from being the most skeptical
To being somebody who actually thought it was worth doing
Wait what happened
I think what he realized was the use of this Market
Would give him access to a lot of really cheap food
So what other food banks were in bidding wars over serial John Arnold could swoop in and
Pick up the stuff that everybody else
Was ignoring
And he became what we call the bottom feeders
He was one of these guys and login every morning
See what was Chief catlos office
And his solution was sent you the market allows me to get a lot of pounds of food in a way that I did not get before
And when Candace says John would login and see what was cheap
He of course means
What was cheap in fake money
What are the really interesting things that has emerged from this
System is just how different prices are in this
Fake money Food Bank economy compared to the you know
Real money economy we see if the grocer
I like peanut butter is incredibly valuable in the
Food Bank economy
The last forever because
Refrigerated and it is a great source of protein
Also kids love it
A truckload of peanut butter can cost
Tens of thousands of Cher
Dairy on the other hand
Really cheap in the food bank
Lots of food banks get local donations of dairy
Captain have to move it pretty quickly cuz has you know short expiration dates
Target store cuz you have to keep it refrigerated
Soap up in Michigan Candice's
John Arnold could buy a lot of dairy
And in the end John Arnold really help the system
Take off all around the country
He was a very persuasive figure because I think a lot of the other food bank director said
If he's in I'm in
Cuz I thought he was unlikely to be a candidate to go a long way
If the Socialist is yet on the market system how bad could it
Exactly
There was one part of the new system that did not
We'll have that part of the story
In a minute
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Is reimagining Bank
I offering accounts with no fees or minimum
That can be open from anywhere in
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Na
When Candace and Susanna and the others were in that room
Creating this news
They figured food banks should be able to
Cell food to each other for fake
So that Idaho food bank with all the potatoes
Could sell them to Susana in Alaska and get fake money to buy whatever they needed in Idaho
But when they took that idea to the people at all the food banks
They found that
Even though they're okay with buying stuff for fake money
They don't really want to sell stuff to other food
John strain
Who bought the cereal for that food bank in Indy
If I'm a food bank and I have extra product I'm going to share with another food bank I don't want no exit
Germany Nordic nothing out of it
I've shared with five different
In the last
60 days I just think you should share what you got if you got
Funny so okay food bank directors are
Fundamentally generous people
That's why they're running food banks right and that is
Part of the reason this
This corner of the market in Everett
But Susan Morgan says
There is something else
Something subtler
Really another kind of a car
This is a network built on relationships
If you work at a food bank she says you need to have friends at other
You're going to rely on those people for more than just food
You're going to rely on those people for stealing their good fundraising practice
Advertising the positions that you have open
So those people are your vest
Source of of learning and contacts
Can you can use food as one of the ways you nurture those relationship
Susannah's never running the Oregon food
And she said she does occasional use
Sell food to other
But not often
She says she would much rather just
Give it away to another
Thanks to City Harvest their part of feeding America here in New York City they let me come out and watch as they bid on and why
1 a truckload of Frozen
Email us at Planet Money at npr.org work at Planet Money at Jacob Goldstein at s venix
Today Show was originally produced by Jess Jiang the rerun was produced by Kesha mihailovic and Alice while
If you're looking for something else to listen to
Try the NPR politics
It is at least twice a week sometimes
It helps you stay up-to-date on all the latest political news
You can find the NPR politics podcast on NPR one or wherever you listen
I'm Jacob Goldstein
And I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Thanks for listening