In the winter of 2010 there was a robbery
In Detroit
Robbery at a bank
Decor jewelry store
Note these thieves robbed a Radio Shack on Jefferson Avenue
Two guys Russian holding a 38
They've got plaid laundry bag
The order the workers at gunpoint into the back room
And they force them to fill up the laundry bags
With brand new smartphone
5 days later
The same guys.
Take down a T-Mobile store
On 7 Mile Road
3 months later they drive 3 and 1/2 hours to Warren Ohio to Robert RadioShack there
And then another
Jack in Highland Park and on and on but only cell phones
And this is 2010 so you got to think
The Apple 4S
Oh yeah the Galaxy 3
And remember the T-Mobile my touches
I think so but I think I can still make this
Eventually the cops get a break in the
Andy resteghini
Michael Green
30 year old
Hold down jobs at Wendy's White Castles
The ballpark
But eventually found stealing more lucre
So the cops arrest Michael Green any immediate
He flips he starts naming names of the other guys in
They all have a nickname
There's nidhi gangs
Krippy and then they're all the Tim's big Tim Middleton baby Tim walz
But the police have a real problem because all they have
Is Michael Green's confession this one guy
And for all the cops know he could be lying
But green does
Give them something else
Cell phone
Including the phone number of
Little Tim
Who's real name is Timothy
And green tell the cops
This guy Little Tim
She's one of the Rings
And that number that one cell phone number
That
Is what does
Timothy Carr
Little Tim cell phone
Give the FBI a way to know
Where he has
Been nearly every minute of every day for months and months
And that is how
A guy accused of going on a cell phone robbery spree ends up being screwed by his own self
Hello and welcome to Planet Money
I'm Elsa Chang and I'm new Elle King
Are cell phones made feel like
Private
Personal possessions to us
But they are giving away information about us all the time
With every call every text every time we email or stream the video
That phone is pinging off some cell tower
And someone company is recording
Where We Are
Does records get stored for a long time and it turns out it's pretty easy for the government to get a hold of them
Today on the show a small-time criminal case
Kicked up to the Supreme Court
And this case could decide how much privacy we can expect
For all the footprints We Leave Behind is a digital world
Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with great G
How did they make them so great Madewell start
Premium.
Then offers men's and women's styles for seriously every
Also you can recycle any brand of jeans in a Madewell
And they'll give you $20 off and you pay
They work with the blue jeans go green program
To turn old jeans
Housing insulation for communities in need
Terms apply
Ready to find your perfect fit stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
It is
Pretty easy
Wait for the police to find out where yourself
The biggest cell phone companies have cots
Contacting them
Time
Trying to get the records of people who they think committed crimes
The cops don't even need a warrant
They just need to show up in front of a judge and say
Hey we think maybe
This guy might have committed a crime which is exactly what the police did in the case
Wilton Carpet
So
Forget the lawyer and he's really lucky
He lands one of the top criminal defense lawyers in Detroit a guy named Harold girl with
Carol takes a lot of high-profile
But he also gets appointed to represent defendants who can't afford a lawyer
And that is how he ended up with
Now the case about a string of Radio Shack robberies that's kind of small potatoes for a guy like Harold girl
In 40 Years of the defense lawyer
He has represented mob bosses
And drug kingpin
And former Detroit mayors
He knows all about wires
Jailhouse informant
Undercover cops
Hannibal
What Harold wasn't expecting was the FBI coming to him and saying
Yo we have your clients
Cell phone lot
Location record
I was
Really
Overwhelmed is it is a is an appropriate word because
I dealt with it before quite frankly
And in any of my cases
MetroPCS which is Little Tim cell phone carrier hands over a hundred and twenty seven days
Of Tim cell phone data to the FBI
Nevis is 200 pages
Spreadsheets showing everywhere that little Tim cell phone has been
At the beginning and at
The end of every call for 4
Cell towers location data
Longitude and latitude
I'm not sure that I was able to make in a clearer sense of it because
There was just too much
It was it was too difficult
To find my way through it
But it was nothing for the FBI because the feds have you
Computer programs that take those
127 days of data
And turn it all into
A map
A map that shows where was
Can carpet
And when
As you can imagine it
Turns out that Radio Shack robbery on
Jefferson Avenue
Little Timmy's nearby
The T-Mobile store robbery on 7 Mile Road
Little Tim again
Right here by you got it the RadioShack haste in Warren Ohio Wilton was in the area and the Radio Shack hold up
In Highland Park
Surprise surprise
Tim Carpenter
It's not looking good for a little
Well his lawyer Harold gurewitz is trying to figure out what to do with all this cell phone data
More of little Tim's friends
R taco
And this is their story
Little Tim was one of the guys
Is in charge it was never one of the guys inside the store with
The guns
He was usually waiting outside
Cars
And later he run the bags of these stolen cell phones down with
Fence and get 10
$20,000 in exchange now
Normally Harold girl with his lawyer could cast doubt on all this
Because these guys
Have all these reasons to lie but
Tim Carpenter cell phone data backs all the stories up
Do you think this is the evidence that got
Timothy Carpenter convicted ultimately
I do the answer is yes
It it's the kind of
Evidence that
In the end it's the most
Difficult
To argue to a jury
That they shouldn't
Credit because
The records
Are what they are
And they're presented
With the blessing of an FBI agent who says I'm an expert
And this is what I think they mean
Alright so Harold loses the case and his client Little Tim get sentenced to
Teen years in prison
Sam be at 116 years because he was convicted on several counts and the sentences couldn't run can
Currently
So the time added up
And it might have ended there
But it did in fact this is where things start to look a little
Brighter
Tim Carpenter
Because this case
Isn't just about a man knocking over some Radio Shack no
This is about
Privacy
End
It's about our expect
Patience of privacy
Should our cell phones yours in mine
Be permitted to operate as little Park
Kid sized tracking device
She's on all of us
And you know who's
Really into privacy Noel
You know who's been looking for the perfect
Test case that could go all the way up to the Supreme Court
Did you guys see any guess
I am going to guess the AC
At this point
The ACLU the American civil liberties Union has been watching a bunch of cell phone location data
Cases of prosper
None of them have made it to the Supreme Court
But for whatever reason the nine justices
Does decide to hear the cell phone data
Starring the cell phone robbery
The man at the ACLU who has made cell phone privacy his life's obsession
Is a lawyer named Nate
Wessler
Nate wessler
Swoops onto the carpet
Staircase to help Harold grow without
Need is not confounded by all the data inside
This is his sweetheart this is what he does
He does he does reserve the right
Can be confused by some of little Tim's Behavior
On one day
141 calls made or received
141 calls
One day he had
That's right because I'm cute on his phone alive not you're not every day was that
That many
By any means I have no idea why he was on the phone
That much.
The point is Tim Carpenter did not do himself any favors
Despite being on
His phone so much
When you start
Putting the data together
I'm certainly a day's worth a week's worth a month's worth and its case more than 4 months worth
You easily paint a very detailed picture
If someone's comings and goings overtime
Other patterns of life
Yeah where they sleep where they go during the
The day who else they're associating with so it starts to
To really chart quite a detailed
And enrich picture of a person's life
And this is where Nate wessler the lawyer starts
Argument
He says the cops don't just have cell phone dated that ties Little Tim too
2 crimes
They also have cell phone records that involve a lot of his
His personal business
And they argue Tim's personal business
Should be protected from government intrusion the way
Your home is protected from government intrusion
Mina police thought you committed a crime and want to break into your apartment they would need a warrant to do that
Which cell phone location data they don't need a
And needs argument is
They should get a war
Warrant for that kind of
Information because it to reveal really personal intimate details about someone's life
Details that the government should not have ready access to
Should approve this point he goes digging through Tim Carpenter cell phone data
What did the feds have on him
End with an evil person
He decides to map it out
The problem is that
The Sheds wild fine with turning over the data
We're not going to make things
Easy for the Opera
When the government turned over these records
To mr. Carpenter's defense attorney is part of the pre-trial Discovery process
They just gave them a
Disturbia scan
PDF not an Excel spreadsheet
Which meant that when when we got them from the defense attorney
We had to have our team
Painstakingly enter those numbers into an Excel spreadsheet
It was a long process they were
So diligent
Anticipation
What is the wallabies poor interns
Sitting through 7000 lines of mind-numbing
Data
Did you start to put a picture together of Tim Carpenters life
Babe actually learn two things about him
The first
He probably would never guess Noel
Apparently Tim Carpenter
What is a churchgoer
I guess you missed the sermon about not stealing cell phones from Radio Shack name is that one but he apparently went to church
And they want another little
One night
Tim Carpenter slept somewhere
Other than he
Pata Tim
Tim's boots
Cell phone now we're getting into it and that is the point Nate wessler says this is
Personal
And that is why the government shouldn't have a right to get this information so easily
Timothy Carpenter's life on a day-to-day basis
Pretty boring
In the way that all of our lives
Are pretty boring on a day-to-day basis
We get up in the morning
Breakfast
We might see a friend
We go to work
Or meet up with a family member
We all have routines
The point us here
None of us in our daily lives
As boring or interesting as they might happen to be
Expect
The Bears
Little government agent sitting in our pocket
With a notepad
Writing down
A record of everywhere we've come and gone
Over the course of that day and that we
Very scary thought
MSM turf
That is in some way
What are cell phones
Have become an and have allowed
I love that smirk
Government agent was the thing that popped
Words can be scary that's what Tim Carpenters lawyers are arguing they are saying
Your cell phone can turn into a government agent almost anytime the government
A government agent who can take a time machine and travel
Cast to monitor your movements
Twenty-four hours a day
I need you to never sleeps never gets
Board never needs a lunch break
And never ever ever
Single mom
And they're saying that should
Scare the hell out of
That's the stuff of
Dystopian fiction
That's the stuff of 1984
That kind of
Pervasive all powerful government in that suit of power
It's really just what the framers of
The Constitution were concerned about
They were well familiar
With
The English king's forces
Knocking down every door in a neighborhood looking for 1/4
Particular suspect overbroad searches
And they
Created the Fourth Amendment
Specifically to restrain government investigator
The fourth amendment is the one that says you ever right against unreasonable searches and seizures
And the carpenter case is all about how you interpret the 4th amendment in the age of
Cell phones
And because the fourth amendment is such a major part of
Eva legal argument here
I called this guy
I'm a fourth amendment nerd is that what I could say I'm up for thematic scholar criminal procedure Professor I write a lot of
That's encouraged George Washington
Christian I meant we can because I wanted to talk to someone on the government side and nobody was actually in the government would talk to
About this case
So I turned orange because he filed a brief
Supporting the government
Emigrant doesn't usually side with the government but in this case he thinks all this talk about 1984 and it
Dystopian future
Is actually just people being paranoid and a little bit ridiculous
You said that argument sounds to him
Why are you not disturbed by this
Practice how could you allow it
The way torun sees it
This is the big
Picture argument against Tim Carpenter
Is it cell site location records
Basically just
Simulate
What's publicly observable in the physical world anyway
So you can see in front of your own at exactly and just like I can expect to have privacy
Ephraim feh
A neighbor who
Snoops on even more
Window
I should expect that no one can watch me when I
Walking around outside while carrying my cell phone
The fact that somebody left their house walked out into the world that
There's a certain amount of information that's not
Traditionally protected under the Fourth Amendment
And that would be it
Someone could easily watch you leave your house
And watch you go to work and it's not like there's a fourth amendment intrusion if that person were to report
Police that he saw you leave your house and go to work
Right all right so
Cell phone location is data that reveals
Nothing more than what and eyewitness
Like a Snoopy neighbor or one of the ladies from church
Christine anyway in public
That is argument number one
And there's a second argument here and it has
What to do with
Consent
With something that you and me and everybody else out there are
Huntington
Every single day
That's right
There is information that we voluntarily give up
2/3 /
Be so we can communicate with
Yeah when I write a letter and I
Putting address on the
Or I dial cell phone
I am sharing that information with a third-party with the postman or with the phone come
Because I want to be able to communicate
Soup that address that phone number that's not private anymore
And with cell phone location data
There's a similar
Your phone needs to
Ping against a cell tower in order
To work
And the argument is the phone company
Has a right to keep a record of all those pink
And do whatever it wants with those record
But if you don't want the government
Hands on your
Cell phone location records
There is an option
For you
You can just
Turn off your phone
Forever
Is that feasible
I mean
Is that how we should live to carry cell phones turned off most of the time if we wanted for
The privacy of our movement
I think it's a lot like
The physical World Imagine you decided
You didn't want
People to be watching
Out in public
What would your options be
You have pretty limited options write your option would be the not go outside
Which is a really bad option
Yeah yes
Confining yourself to your home does not sound like a very good on you
But then at the same time we don't say
Okay well since you don't want to be stuck in your head
You should be able to walk outside and be entitled to all the privacy
Yuan
You can't tell people when you're walking down the street
Don't look at me
Believe me I've wanted
But when were talking about the digital world
What county is
Walking outside
At everything about you about
All the footprints We Leave Behind when we use technology
When we use the internet
How many of those footprints
Should be private
How easy should it be for the government
Dulce
Any of those
These are questions the Supreme Court might touch upon
Admiral argument
At the end of this month and part of the reason that little Tim Carpenters case got kicked all the way up to the Supreme Court is that it's not just
What about are smart
Everything is smart these days there are smart fridges that know how much bacon we eat
They're so smart watches that collect data on how fast are hardest
And Tim Carpenters lawyer Nate wessler thought of
Another one that
Internet connected vibrators
Incredibly
That upload to a company servers information about someone's sexual activity
You know that I started my
End
I love about the law
You start with this
Tiny criminal case in Detroit
Ate a bunch of robbers
Hauling away cell phones in laundry
Taking out a bunch of
RadioShack
And it sounds like kind of a nothing
At first
But now it's gone
All the way to the
Supreme Court
And have implications
Every single one of us
Since you are a lawyer
There's a question about this has been driving me now
Since the beginning
Let's say that the Supreme Court rules in favor of Timothy Carpenter
Does he get out of jail does he then get to ditch 216 year sentence
Well
It's not
Because of another small part of
Call the good faith
Which was like this
If the police
Follow the rules
When they got evidence to convict you of a crime
And then those rules
Change after your conviction
Unfortunately for you
Your conviction still stand
So why the world has this
Fascinating conversation about the future of privacy rules
Little Tim Carpenter is
Probably stuck in prison for the rest
Support for this podcast and the following message come from fidelity
As a Fidelity wealth management client
You get a dedicated advisor to help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes and make
Clear recommendations for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
We love to hear from you what you think of the show which one is
Alberto
Send us an email
Planet Money at npr.org
Or if you can find us on Facebook or Twitter
Today's episode was produced by the great Sally Helm Ryan or status are editor Alex goldmark is are supervising
And special thanks to Paulo Matt Georgetown law and Andrew Crocker at the Electronic Frontier Foundation
Thank you guys for educating me about
The 4th amendment
And then you just holster Johnson and her lawyer Matt from it for talking to me about how cell phone location data effective hurricane
If you're looking for something else to listen to can I recommend wait wait don't tell me
Is musically show
Funny it's irreverent
Tells it like it is
Listen to wait wait don't tell me on NPR one or wherever you get your pot
I'm Noel King
And I'm Elsa Chang thanks for listening
All right soon as well
You once had a cell phone number that was
Clearly inherited from someone else
And you would get calls all the time for some woman named
Yeah I get them like
Once or twice a month and I got a little bit of someone who is Rachel and why did she leave her phone number and
Closest I got I think Rachel Olson people some money
So we got a little
Who has Tim Carpenter's phone number now
Is he the Rachel in someone else's life
His phone numbers in
Record
Darn
Bomber yeah
I guess maybe when you
Get sent to prison for armed robbery
The cell phone company
Retires your phone number
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start with
Great genes
Madewell offers premium denim styles for seriously everyone