Support for NPR and the following message come from service now making the world of work
Work better for me
They're cloud-based
Platform and solutions
Deliver digital workflow
Spell create great experiences and unlock productivity for your whole company
More at servicenow.com
Alex goldmark
I want to talk for half a second about something that President Trump said in his inaugural
One by one
The factory shutter
And left our Shores
With not even
I thought
About the millions and millions of American workers
That were left behind
He even got kind of poetic at one point talking about
Rusted out factories
Scattered like tombstones
Across the landscape
Of our nation
And he's not totally wrong
But he's also not totally right
In parts of this country yes
Factories have been closing and Jobs been moving overseas for decade
But tree doesn't just take jobs
Any Economist will tell you trade makes the country better overall
American consumers get to buy cheaper goods and American companies sell more stuff over
And there is this idea that I
If you can just take just a little bit of the money from the people who are doing better be
And you can give it to the losers the workers
Interested outfit
Factory say then it should in theory make trade help
Everyone
And this is not just an idea this is an actual federal government program for laid-off worker
Been around since 1974
And here's how it works if you can prove that you lost your job to trade policy
The government is going to help
With money with cash
But they are also going to try and help you find a job in an industry that is not dying
It is called trade adjustment assistance
And it's like you have been adjusted out of a job we're going to
Assist you
Everyone just calls it ta
I wanted to see how ta Works in real life
So I went to Erie Pennsylvania which is a city that has lost a lot of jobs to trade lot of factories closed
VTA program is run out of this little job center in what used to be a strip mall.
Job centers called careers
Wednesday I was talking to people
It was really nice A little tense
I was going to go back the next day.
To talk some more people but I got a text message saying
No no don't come
Because
Going to blow up Careerlink
They had a bomb threat
Executive director Rick Cornwell says
There were two phone calls made this morning a man threatening to open
Fire and Blood
What's up
Erie Police or the process of searching the building for any
Suspicious materials
Cornwell believes both phone calls came from the same man who they believe is a disgruntled client
People in Erie are so frustrated
That one of them at least
Threaten to blow up a job site
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Noel King
And I'm Alex
And today on the show
Why would anyone want to blow up a place trying to get people jobs in Erie Pennsylvania
We're going to go to Erie we're going to meet some people there and we're going to find out workers really forgotten
Support for Planet Money and the following message come from Batman
A smarter way to invest your money
Betterment combines time-tested investor
Principles with the transparency and ease-of-use you expect from grey technology
Focusing on lowering fees and taxes
And here's what you might find refresh
Betterment really cares that you reach your financial goals and that's why they keep their fees low
Planet Money listeners can get up to six months with no advisory
For more information visit betterment.com Planet Money
Siri is way out in Northwest
Western Pennsylvania it's a long low City that set on the edge of Lake Erie
And Alex can I tell you something about Yuri
I've only been there once lay it on me
I loved
Erie Pennsylvania okay I love it
First thing is people who are from Erie Ray.
So hard
This one night I was going back to my hotel I got in a taxi
And the taxi driver took me to the wrong Hotel because he said my hotel was a crappy hotel and he wanted me to see
Erie had nicer places to stay so he was like TripAdvisor but
With veto power
Actually I did see one guy being rude
Was being condescending to a waitress at Applebee's
But then
He went back and he apologized
So even the one rude person turned out to be a nice person
But you were there to me
The workers who have lost their jobs
And we're part of this retraining
McFarland is one of those guys
He's 6 years old but he looks about 15 years younger
Just wearing work pants and work boots and Carhartt jacket
And he had this amazing T-shirt with a
Tiger airbrushed on it and the tiger is a
Drinking from a stream
Favorite surgery
Just one of many
Mick worked at General Electric for 8 years
GE has big plant in Erie they make locomotives
Mick was a it was a crane operator
I'm in last year GE laid off
1500 people
Just to give you a sense of a scale Erie only has a hundred thousand residents
Nick was on the shop floor working and he says his bosses came down and had him something
Make of this piece of paper saying it
Where rent being laid off
What is the piece of paper say it does it just say sorry you're fired
No sorry you're unemployed
Make it been in manufacturing since he was 25
Before that he was a car
He's been watching the jobs
Even doing what I can but when he gets that piece of paper
He knows his life
And then he gets invited to the meeting
Can the other laid-off workers are told
Come on out we're going to set you down for a seminar and at seminars run by this
Tell me what's your name
Joe Miceli
Spell your last name for me
Eli
Joe is the program supervisor for workplace
Programs that is his fancy title
They're at the job center in Erie
And he works directly with a lot of pee
People who lost their job
So he knows your name
Faces
And when there's a big layoff like the one at GE
Joe he's like the first line his first move
Is to tell the workers
But there is this thing called trade adjustment
So in the case of GE they bring in hundreds of people as many as will fit into the Local Union Hall
It's a big room like a courtroom it's got a lot of folding chairs
And there's this enormous mural on the back wall it's like
100 Years of Union history
New Joe is it a large guy he's a quiet guy
And now he's got to get up in front of
500 angry worried
About to be laid off
And this whole noise fills the hole
Realm it really
Steelers division
That many people moving talking and doing everything
Thing at once
3 super careful about everything right down to what he's wearing
In this case jeans
You can't dress up too much you're not a suit
You don't come into the room
Layoff union workers
Blue collar workers of America
Wearing a suit telling them the Third
Going to lose benefits
Naoto
Time makes you look like a suit
Absolutely
You're one of the workers you're with them
He gets up on stage clears his throat to get everyone's attention
And all those 300-500 faces first look at you
The responsibility hits you
He starts by acknowledging this
Really suck
You are a victim of the global economy
But he says
Here's some good news
Kind of
He gives everyone a Blue Book
What is a copy of the trade adjustment assistance Act
And he explains
Because your job has been lost to trade
You get to take advantage of these benefit
You might not feel lucky but you're pretty lucky
Does boss has a way of describing this
And you should just hear it directly from
This is the what we call the Cadillac of all training program
This is Ruben paasche he oversees with substrate act training in Pennsylvania
He knows the benefits
Inside and out he's been
Years
Explaining them to pee
And you will tell people
If you qualify for TAA
The federal government will pay in full
For your schooling for up to
Two and a half
Trade school Community College
Wherever you want to go
As long as you are in school
Or retraining
You'll get a check in the
It's like an unemployment check but it doesn't cut off until you are retrain for a new
Do you want to retrain
On the job then the government will pay for
Do you have an apprentice
You also get some money to go looking for work
Bill pay for gas and food and lodging as long as you're on the road looking for a job
And here's a big one
If you're willing to leave Erie
If you can get a job outside
The city federal government will pay for you to move
Anywhere in the US
Keith Urban
So far during my tenure the further sleeve
Relocated some would-be Puerto Rico
They weren't they got a job as a biologist
Really yeah
Bilingual so that helped him a lot
And the company hired in Puerto Rico so we relocated his family
To Puerto Rico
These are the kinds of stories the Joe and Ruben towel at the
The meeting in the U
And when they're done and they finished their spiel
All the workers they start rushing over and they say
When do my unemployment checks start coming in
When do I have to register for school by
Andrew banjo they tell him
Come on down to the job center
That's what we will help you figure out why
What you're going to do for the
And once they're there someone like Ruben sits down with him
Pulls up a list of jobs and says
These are the ones we think are not going to go away
We have a list
The high-priority occupations that
With the case manager
The worker can review and see if the occupation that I want
I'm able to get a job after
So if I'm looking at that list and and ice
Say I want to be an x-ray technician
They're going to look in this hole yet x-ray technician is right up at the top
If I tell them I want to be
A trapeze artist
They're going to look a trapeze artist is not on there we are not going to pay for you to train
And the way we would show that just
It's just that we're not
I'm stepping over a person's dream is let's look at the labor market information in your area
And the labor market information in in your specific area
How many trapeze
Jumpers are there how many jobs are available
And because there aren't any
Let's look at something. Perhaps
May interest you a bit
You like nudgent or an x-ray technician look at look at that one
The little like being on a trapeze
Play exactly
And this all cost more money
In a regular
Program to show a company has to prove that they're laid off workers deserve
The Department of Labor it makes the company apply and prove to the government that yes
These jobs were lost because of trade
Not a recession not bad management but
Trade
And 6 in 10 companies that apply
Don't get it
But in this case GE for this Factory
They applied
Bay Path
And so making his co-workers they're going to get ta
And they are headed to retraining for one of those new jobs on
Which means
Back to school
Here's the thing about colleges and technical schools they want your records They want your transcripts
A lot of these people have been out of school for a long time
Can I have kids
Joe Miceli was telling me about this one woman she got laid off from GE she decided to take advantage of the benefits
Chico's to apply to different schools in the first thing that they want
Has her high school transcripts
Well she went to a small
Private high school
Pittsburgh
What you sense
Close down and burned down
Sexy
She's very persistent she
She gets on Facebook
And she finds a teacher
And from the teachers
She finds the director
And the director is now a 92 year old man in nursing home
And she calls him on the phone and he remembers her
Did you get a transcript
She still can't get
Trask
I went back and I checked in with Joe about her she never did find her transcripts so she picked a different training program
Okay but hopefully she is an outlier and most people our age
Yes they enroll in schools like the Erie Institute
222 technology
I took a drive down there one night to meet with McFarland
The guy with the the Great Tiger t-shirt
To the schools in another strip mall it was dark out it's raining a little bit
And when I got inside
Classic just let out and all these people flooded into the Halls
It was so weird
Because it's a
Technical School
And so I was expecting young guys and then there was you then
But most of them were grown men
And not just grown men
They were old man
So I grabbed making two of his friends would also been laid off from GE
Is there a room we can borrow for just a couple minutes
And then we will bounce out with that one
All three of these guys are retraining in HVAC heating ventilation and air conditioning
And you know HVAC is not simple
What thermodynamic
You have to understand how pressure affects temperature
You have to tell what's inside of a closed system
It's solid science
Gnomic es6
And he has not taken a science test in 40 years
So sometimes when he's in class he
He thinks about that meeting in the union hall where they explain the benefits and they tell you about the retraining
Any thinks about one of the other workers who raised his hand and then said basically what Mick had been think
I believe he said he was 63 or 63 and a half
And said that
He just wanted to get his unemployment
Not have expensive going to school or spend time in school which
Was my thoughts also
Yes 59 and I knew if it by this time when I had to start school I'd be 60
And they told us we were not allowed to do that to get the benefit
We had to come to school
So it's costing the federal government
The cost of our school
To be here
Some of us don't want it
But this program is
Specifically designed not to be true
It is designed to give them their best shot at a new and better job
But then in the classroom these guys are telling me
They are sitting next
To Austin
Everybody wanted to talk about Austin
Because Austin is not on TAA
Austin
Is going to be 20 next month
Cheers mix friend Greg
You guys have a look at the 20 year olds like out of the side of your eye and thank
Good company
Kitchen
I feel sorry for
Why because when I was 20 years old
I had a good job I could
I could sustain a house with a family
These young kids today
In Erie they don't have a chance they don't have a chance
What's the start I don't
I feel bad
But let's be real
After they all graduate unless someone in this equation is willing to leave Erie
You guys are going to be competing with Austin for jobs
An ed is 50
3 and make a 60 and Greg at 6
U2
You can tell that they have all done this math
Sears Michigan
Do you expect to get a job in HVAC
That's my goal
Because that's part of
Retraining
Is you have to have a goal
You're smiling a little bit
Like you don't really believe it though
Well
I'm going to be 61 years old
How many people are going to hire me at 61
If they want to keep collecting unemployment they need to be in class
Basketball
So they come to
They work hard and they count on those checks
But as if things weren't
Hard enough
Pennsylvania cut 500 workers from the Department that runs the TAA program
The unemployment checks
They're not going out
Four five
6 weeks later
And now the job center in Erie is swamped with people who want to know where is my money
So these guys just keep calling
Mixed friend Ed forget should be here
His phone
Whoa on January 10th
You call that number 54 time
Are you getting through
Busy signal
Utility companies calling me
Market my mortgage company I don't have money to pay my mortgage
I really don't
No I have to call him tomorrow and make arrangements
Cuz I have no money to pay it
So here's where we're at
No job
No money
No one to call about it
And no idea what you're going to be doing in 12 to 18 months
This benefit program was supposed to mitigate some of that
But it's like these guys are feeling it more than ever
Maybe you can see how someone might break down
Which
Brings us back to
Whatever happened to that bomb threat
Well they told me not to go down there so the first thing I did was to go down there
Because you're a reporter right exactly
So by the time I got there I everyone had been evacuated
Place was empty there was just a little sign on the door that said you please come back tomorrow
And that's
Basically what it feels like to go through this program
And this is the best that we can do for people who have lost their jobs to trade yes right now it's the best Federal program
One solution could be to just make ta a way bigger
To offer to way more people to make it easier for more companies to get on ta
You got a lot more money
Another idea is to just
Stop
To say
This idea doesn't work we can't take
A little bit of the money from the people who benefit from trade
Give it to the losers and have everybody better off
Yeah and this in a way is the Donald Trump
Kamp-rite he thinks trade itself is the problem
He wants to fight trade
So he's throwing up the trans-pacific trade agreement
He's rethinking master
And all of this is supposed to help people like making his friends
Of course when you talk to Economist they say hold on no it is not that simple
Most of the jobs done by people like micosay
They aren't going to Farhan
They're just
Vanishing
As factories get more automated
Or they move within the US
So for instance
GE built a brand new plant in Fort Worth Texas where there is no Union
So there's lower pay
And to Erie Pennsylvania like its workers
Is going to have to reinvent itself
With TAA or without TAA
You just can't fight the world economy
If you work at a place that is being changed because of trade or is getting ready to change because of
Say after changing
We want to hear from you we want to hear the details
Send us an email
To Planet Money at npr.org
Or find us on Facebook or on Twitter we are at Planet Money
Today Show was produced by Sally Helm with an assist from Nick Fountain thanks guys
Our editor is bryant urstadt
We have a lot of people to thank for this episode
2 Economist helped us out with interviews and research
Are Julian park at Kent State University and Cara Reynolds at American universe
Thanks also to Sarah Goulet at the Pennsylvania Department of Labor Danforth at independent pattern. Slauson
UE 506
And thanks to everyone at CareerLink in Erie
If you're looking for another podcast to try
Check out the NPR politics podcast
Hosted by a great team of NPR reporters in it
Clear smart funny coverage of what is going on in Washington they will help you make sense
All of it
Find a pet npr.org
Podcasts or wherever you get podcasts
I'm Alex goldmark
And I know Elle King
Retraining
It transforms individuals
I've seen one of the scariest guys you'd ever meet
Large
Man Lumberjack physique
Comes up to me
A year-and-a-half later
Annie's clean-cut
He's wearing his
Rob's
And I barely recognized
And that's the kind of transformative process
Best rated
Can't perform update
That guy was a GE guy
Like I was not