Hey it's Robert Smith here we wanted to replay one of our favorite episodes today because
It seems super relevant
For what's about the
As you probably know our new President Donald J Trump
Love
To talk about
The Tariff
Tariffs
Taxes on Imports
And you want to use these terrorists mainly
As a threat
To keep factories in the United
You move manufacturing to a foreign country
We will tax
The products when they come back that's a tariff
Now this idea was not invented by President Trump in fact
We have already lived
Through these kind of tariff
And we wanted to play the story of how one of the strangest tariffs of all time
Change the thing you may be inside of right now
The automobile
We do this podcast with NPR's car correspondence sonari glinton
And after supper will get update on where things stand right now
Alright Robert this is really exciting we're in Midtown Manhattan right across from Bryant Park
I don't want to try an experiment name
At the top of their head
As many mid-sized sedans as they know
Audi A7 BMW 5 Series
Ford Focus
Kia Spectra
Chevy Impala
Dodge Charger and BMW X5 BMW X3 the 4-series 435i
And Nissan Altima
Okay I got it like the answers would have run the gamut like we have foreign cars American cars lots of different cars
Exactly
But let's try something a little less easy how many pickup trucks they can name
Pickup truck pickup truck
Definitely
Well I guess it's the Ford F-150
Ford F-450 9550 whatever is going on a Ford F-150
Midnight
Ford F-150
I think I see where you're going with this which is when you talk about trucks were simply talking about American trucks the Ford F-150
Other American-made trucks
Nobody names of foreign truck
Exactly that's because
The American Truck
Jeff dominate the space I mean absolutely completely dominate the space
And there's a reason for that Robert the reason is chicken
And not just chicken
Frozen chicken parts shipped to Germany after World War II leaving will explain
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm sonari glinton and I'm Robert Smith today at the show
Chicken trucks
Trucks and chicken
And how a trade dispute can change the entire world
Sports podcast in the following message come from rocket mortgage by Quicken Loans
When she was in a mortgage lender work with one that has your best interest in mind
Rocket mortgage provides a transparent online process that helps you understand your home loan
You can even adjust the rate and length of your loan in real time to make sure you get the right mortgage solution
Skip the bank skip the waiting and go completely online at quickenloans.com money
Equal Housing lender licensed in all 50 states
Nmls
Consumer access.org number 3030
Okay we're going to lay it out for you how we Frozen
Chicken drumstick
Led directly to the awesomeness of the Ford
It goes back to after World War II at the lake
50s early 60s
European economy
He's finally getting better and everyone sort of
Helping each other in the world
This is an era of
And Americans
Are going
Absol
Oakley bonkers
For a German Empire
Unemployed slang
I'm in a rush to get in Tichigan vets first ending in V Star
Beatles were
Everywhere in the late 50s and early 60s
Xcenda
It became sort of almost at craze
That is the voice of Bob White
He's a Car guy
Car Guys work for pretty much every car company
GM
Ford Chrysler
BMW GM again
Everybody had to have
1 Beetle to Beetle said to have a beetle plus a Volkswagen bus
And it became a
I sort of a cult object
And I think everybody was worried about it
Well everybody who worked in the American Auto industry
She was worried about it
The meanwhile
Over in Germany
They're having their own sort of trade invasion
This is not cars this is as we promised
The chicken pox
Please remember up to this time
Chicken with sort of a luxury in Germany they were recovering from the war
And they had the wrong chicken manufacturers but they were really expensive
Incomes
Frozen
American
Chicken
Frozen American Chicken on the Bountiful American Farms
Shipped over to Germany and all the sudden in Berlin
You can have chicken every night for dinner they are going crazy for in fact
We looked at the stats in 1961 alone
German chicken consumption
Went up 23%
If we were going crazy in United States for the Volkswagen Beetle
The Germans were going crazy for Americans
Yeah that's the dream of free trade
They get cheap chicken
We get cheap cars
It's a bonus for every
Except
For the German
Chicken farmers
What's the German chicken Farmers look around and they're expensive chickens are losing out to these cheap American
Big do what Farmers everywhere do
They went to their government and they said protect us against
Is cheap chicken
That's flooding the market
The German government responded
And they started attacks on American chicken
Up to 50
80%
Which is huge
An American plague
Wait wait wait wait wait
What we just helped rebuild you after the war
And you want to start
A trade dispute you attacks are chicken Vine
We will find some German things
If we can talk
It's basic playground Lodge
Right
So the US plan
It's retaliation
They draft
This idea
Advocate
John krafcik is with truecar.com
So in December of 1963
Lyndon Johnson become president
Less than two weeks before
Signed into effect
This tariff
25% tariff
On
Vehicles that were deemed to be primarily commercial Goods
Caring vehicle
The Chicken Shack
Actually called it
The chicken tax
These are pickup trucks and Commercial vans
And it's not just German pickup trucks
It's all foreign trucks
If you want to make a truck
And ship it to the US
You got to pay 25%
Extra
It's called the chicken
Any change the American car industry
Overnight
The first thing that happens is it foreign trucks are all of a sudden way too expensive
To compete
In this country
Volkswagen
Had this pic
Basically it's a VW bus with a
The flatbed
And this was going to be there next big thing in America after
The Beetle and the regular size bus but once the chicken tax goes in it is 25%
More
Expensive to pulled from the market there like we can not sell this car this truck
In America
The American companies obviously happy there's less competition
It also allowed the American car companies assertive
Kick back and relax a little bit not really in a vape
Because of the chicken tax American trucks
Basically
Stayed the same of the year
They got bigger they got fancy or they certainly got more expensive
Foreign competition
Don't want to watch a new ideas in the space
Adjective
Hyundai
And have the opportunity to build
I know some
Funky
Fuel efficient truck they brought to America that would have inspired American manufactured vehicle on
Competing with Hyundai
But there was
No foreign car
It was no incentive
Once you put a tariff on something The Innovation that would have gone into the product
Goes into getting around matera
And that's what the car company started to do
Robert things got really crazy really quickly
Toyota
So we can't directly ship our trucks from Japan
I'll tell you what we'll do
We'll build them in Parts giant parts
They ship them to the US
And then slap those parts together put them on the train
And there you go
They got around the chicken
Because technically they were assembling the car even though the parts from in Japan they were assembling
In the United States
Tighten a couple of screws
Made in America
Good2Go
And US Customs look like
Yeah I know
That's not
That's not going to play
It'll sure all the foreign car manufacturers at this point just gave up trying to get around
Of course not because this is America the most important market for any kind
Of course
Subaru which is a great car maker they make SUVs
Why not make a truck
So they didn't hear you
I'm sure you remember the Subaru Brat
Subaru Brat my neighbor had one of these it was amazing from 50 feet away
It looks like a pickup
When you got up close
There were these
Flimsy plastic sheets
Just bolted into the bed of the truck
The idea was well those seats are for people there for it
Must not be
A vehicle that is designed to carry Goods I thought it was a it was a very clever solution
Because government did not think this was a clever solution then post the chicken tax and
In the brat
Went away
As time goes by in the Global Auto industry gets more interconnected and complicated
You can't parse out necessarily
Which is an American company which is a foreign company because
Say a company like Ford makes cars and trucks on five continents
And all the sudden
American companies started to encounter the same problem for companies where which American companies had to deal with the chicken
What makes a cargo van in Europe
It's called
But I didn't want that to happen
So what they did was
They took the cargo van
Put some seats where the cargo is supposed to go
Shipped it to the US and said hey that's not a cargo van that's a passenger van
The chicken tax
Doesn't apply
Is Sean McClendon from the center for Automotive Research
And when they get here to the United States still say Ohio
The rip the seats out punch out the windows and covering with metal panels and resell the vehicle is a free
And it's cheaper to do that then pay the Tariff
After they took the seats out
They sent them back to Europe
Put them in another van
And shipped back to us
Be taken out again
Over and over and over again in his vicious and virtuous cycle
All this trade
Make sound
Liking Santa Baby is insanity
But the end of the day the chicken tax
Accomplished exactly what it was
Supposed to
Accomplish which is
The dominance of the American
American trucks own the road and they have
For 50 years
Everyone agrees in American culture now
So good have had such a
So long
But even if you got rid of the chicken
It would take
Years and years and years for the rest of the world
To catch up with American
And that's the question I've been having for years
If American trucks are so good
Why is the 25% chicken tax
Dylan place
At the most recent Detroit Auto Show I got to speak to Mark Fields
The brand new CEO of Ford Motor
And right before I talk to him
It just unveiled what almost every Ford executive would call
The most important rock that come out of the tray
50 years
Awesome
Why do you still need the chicken tax
Well in terms of the
Clearly when you look where we're free Traders
Fire by Design
We have been the best selling vehicle in the US
When we want to make sure we're on a Level Playing Field and right now around the world
Not so level depending
And you think it's fine you want it you want to keep it
You need it though that's
I thought you know that it's on the books right now
And yeah we want
That's the reality that we're dealing with
Robert let me translate that for you
What are you saying is
We don't really need the chicken tax
But we are going to demand that we get rid of it
After all
EBenefits
I thought that went so well why stop at one cu
Let's go on to the next
So I talked to Sergio marchione he's the head of the FCA
Which is the owner of
Chrysler
And this is where it gets weird because
This company is
European company
An American
It's also harm by it as well
I'm the wrong guy to ask that question
Because I would not have to check
But that's just my view
What why not
I mean you're in charge of an American car company
Number
We benefit when you run a global organization the chicken Texas and Incredibly protective measure Define deal with
I think Anil perceived threat to the stability of the auto sector I don't think it does
But it exists so it's going to take a while to try and taking out taking off the table
Finally
How much of an interesting question why would you ask
All the taxes you could be at
Because it's weird
It's weird that this
Tariff
Exist
I mean
Why not compete on a completely even
Plainfield
You sound pretty good to me I like your story I didn't say anything
I'm not the guy that invented the chicken thanks
If I comply with it
Do I need to check the text answers no
Even with
CEO double
I'm not hearing this guy saying like we are going to die
As companies
Without the chip
Well of course not because they have such a
Names of the people who buy pickups
It would take forever to break that bond with the American pickups
And that's the funny thing about
Tariffs
Which is
What's the score of the place
There's no real incentive to get rid of them
Even if you do not need the tariffs anymore
They stick around
And there's a really important reason for this which is once you have a tariff
It becomes a bargaining chip
It becomes something you can use
In the next set of training
I just didn't know here it's been
2 years since we recorded
That podcast and like clockwork
Hillary Clinton just got back from the Detroit Auto Show history
Hey how's it going
Don't do it and you're still thinking about the chicken tax
It's still a thing in the oven
It is very much still a thing in the Auto industry and actually
Listening to the Kurt
Intimations of Sergio marchione the CEO of
Fiat Chrysler Group
It's interesting cuz
GM along with the other
American CEOs of
The car company
Met with President Trump about
Manufacturing in the USA
Donald Trump talks a lot
About
Tariffs and retaliatory tariffs he talks about
Perhaps renegotiating NAFTA the North American Free Trade Agreement
And
The chicken tax
Sleeve into that right
Yeah exactly because
One of the things that NAFTA dead
Was
The industry
At least our neighbors thought
This tariff is kind of crazy
One of the things that NAFTA
Should have erased if you are an apt the country
You don't have to pay the chicken
So that's why a Ford F-150
The aluminum body
Hilton Mexico
And then assembled
I finally
Here in the US
Ram
Build a lot of its trucks
In Mexico as those Chevy
In part because it's so close
To Texas which is where a lot of pickup trucks
Bought and sold
You don't interesting scenery because sometimes I think that only those of us
Planet Money
Really are obsessed with
Tiny little weird tariffs
The past
But if you renegotiate current trade deals as the president wants to do
They're all in there all of this stuff is going to start to come to light again
Lake Erie open big trade agreements
Like now that you're going to have to
Re-litigate
All of these
All these shoes again
We think about Robert I have to say I've spent
5 1/2 years
And my Chopper last five years have been the tremendous success of the Auto industry
And there's a sphere
Hey guys if you touch any of this
It may all come come
Sonari glinton thank you so much I think about
Podcast
All
Hi
Good luck
Well of course we always want to hear what you think
You can email us at
Planet Money at npr.org and we're also on Facebook Twitter and Instagram
The episode was originally produced by Francis Harlow this rerun was produced by Nick fountain
If you're looking for more politics
In your life
Get used to it
You're going to have to do it check out the NPR politics podcast and great you can find them at npr.org podcast
NPR one app I'm Robert Smith
And thanks for joining us