Support for NPR and the following message come from service now making the world of work
Work better for people
Their cloud-based platform and solutions deliver digital workflow
Spell create great experiences and unlock productivity for your whole company
More at servicenow.com
Everyone is
Stacey Vanek Smith
Today we're going to replay one of our favorite episodes about immigration and
It's from a few years ago but it feels very relevant
Today and we will have an update
I must admit
I did not fully appreciate
How
Strange
More
Complicate
Unusual and weird
A good weird
Weird I do not appreciate how
Weird our immigration policy
Take for instance this fact
We have a cap on the number of people who can get a green card from each country
It is the same number for every kind
The number does not depend on the countryside which means
If you live in a tiny country
Luxembourg
Are plenty of open spots for you but
If you live in someplace bigger like India
Mexico
Be prepared to wait
Just because your country happens to have a lot of people
If you are a lower-skilled Mexican with a high school degree
And you have no family in the United States right now so you want to come in and work
There's virtually no way for you to do so
This is Economist Alex Norris.
If you are the lower-skilled Mexican you want to wait in line for that green card takes about 230 years
So
The notion that anybody can come here
And work
Is false
Nobody can wait in line for 130 years obviously
Infected Mexico she just split in two
10 smaller country
It'll get 10 times as many slots
If you don't feel like waiting or splitting your country up
There are other routes
The United States
Better Call Saul
Like the one Anthony Court it took
When he fell in love with the United States
Or more specifically
MidFlorida
I was a barrister in the United Kingdom actually I should say England in Wales
We had a vacation home here in Florida
I say we might my wife and I and my two children
Are we came here frequently and each time we left the nice weather of Florida have a more and more depressed about having to leave
Does it get back to London and maybe all this rain and fog he hated it
Intercourse sound
Quick way to become a USC
I found this obscure program
The basically what you buy your way into the United
States
You just have to invest
Half million dollars in American Business
That is predicted to create
10 jobs
Just
Can jobs
Truthfully it looked too good to be true that it sounded to me it not time to be fanciful
So I did more research and realize that impact he was a genuine
Quarter cast out most of his savings invested in a Vermont
Ski Resort
And he got his Visa
Now he's on his way to citizen
So there are exceptions for the rich
And it's not just the rich
There's plenty of exceptions but I'd lie
Depend on what your job is
Here's Economist Giovanni Peri
There are currently maybe more than 30 different categories of temporary visas
Weeden incredible detail
Who can come in on each there is one specific for
Models I'm sorry fashion models
Fashion model cs1 specifically for fashion models
Did you come to the US on a fashion model Visa
I tried but then I failed miserably
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm David kestenbaum and I am Robert Smith
There is for the first time in a while momentum building to try to change our immigration system
So today we ask
What would be the perfect two
We could scrap the mess that we have right now
What would be best for our economy
We have three people who have thought a lot about this and we got three answers for what their dreams were
Three big ideas
I could fix the system support for Planet Money and the following message
Come from betterment a smarter way to invest your money
Betterment combine time-tested investing principles with the transparency and ease-of-use you expect
Great technology
Focusing on lowering fees and taxes
And here's what you might find refreshing
Betterment really cares that you reach your financial goals and that's why they keep their fees low
Planet Money listener can get one month manage free
The more information visit betterment.com Planet Money
Okay our first idea to reform immigration
I'm going to give you
Okay this one is
The best and the brightest
This idea comes from Dean Baker he is co-director of the center for economic
Can policy research
Identified himself as being left us
Baker's dream system would be a lot simpler than the one we laid out at the beginning of the program
You start by picking the number of people you were going to let
The total number
So say a million and a half
For 2 million a year
Show me more than we let in now
Then you just got to decide who gets the car
Baker says
Of course he would like people to be able to reunite with their families bring their relatives
But after that
He wants to give up visas preferentially to the
The people who would benefit the economy the most
Scientist
Engineers
Lawyers computer programmers
I would like to make sure that you had a lot of them going to the high-end
Just a little unfair it's basically
Saying you know
You can only come in and have a much better chance coming in if you have a graduate degree if your
Someone who
Are you bleed
Really
Need the money more
Is less chance
Well you might say that but but in terms of
You know
Certiport World Justice
Realistically we're going to let a tiny tiny number of people from the rest
The world into the United
States
So I don't have much qualms about saying okay who are those going to be
Those are going to be
Workers with high education high qualifications and then I'd like to repatriate a portion of their earnings
So that will benefit their home countries as well so if we get a doctor from India
Take 10% of their earnings when they're here for their first 10 or 15 years
Use that to train two or three more doctors in India so maybe actually ends up with better Healthcare
As a result of doctors emigrating to United States
Thai we would require that
That's you you gave me the choice to design my dream system yes I'd like to see ensure that India benefits from that's
Story as well
So you would say
The doctor you came here we're going to tax you
10% of your earnings I don't have to come if you know the reality is again the differences in wages
They're so large that if you have a doctor come to
The United States
And 10%
Are there income off the top
Is taxed away and then sent back to to India to educate more doctors
It's still end up way ahead and again you know if they're not happy about it they don't have to come here
What about Farm Workers
You know I'm less concerned about farmworkers I mean I know there's a lot of farmers who say that you know they couldn't operate their Farm
Low-cost labor and
You know I'd say that a lot of those Farms crab shouldn't be operating I'm not really troubled by the idea that farmer should have to pay
Hey the same sort of wages to attract people as retail stores or anyone else
I don't really see a problem with that I don't think we need a special underclass of people to work at real low wages in the Farms I I don't think
That makes sense
Can you say what say we put in the system
And a picture of
How's life in United States
All in with there doctors on every corner
They're dead they're everywhere
We're going to be surrounded by doctors setting up a shop and every corner undercutting each other and prices
I think we would see Laura lower-cost Healthcare and that's obviously something
I think everyone has to
Concerned about cuz
You know we know
In terms of healthcare insurance whether paying out-of-pocket and certainly is a government category government spending it
Most rapidly Rising category government spending
So they can have a very positive impact in terms of lowering healthcare costs
On the other hand a lot of the types of Labor that you know we currently get very cheap would cost more
People work
Hainan hotels
Housekeeper
Wednesday would be getting higher wages
Pizza restaurant
The people working in the kitchen
A custodian
Can Office Buildings all these people would be getting more money
Which would mean higher costs so we probably see things
Pure restaurant
You know we got a restaurant in my Costas you know
23% more for a male witch
Most of us would go out somewhat less
So what we see is that a lot of the goods that are relatively
Cheap today
Would be somewhat more expensive waresley some of the
Bartley Healthcare wood
Is a Chrysler expensive
Would cost us less
Today
ID number one
We should point out that Dean Baker is far from alone
In wanting to let in more High School
The Chicago Booth School of Business does he surveys
A panel of expert economy
List of all stripes
What are the survey questions was
Would average US citizen
Be better off
If we let more highly educated
Kid workers in Agra
A38 economist
When did not
Respond
One said he was uncertain
All the others are
Let more professional
Now we should say there is a challenge
Which is but it still depends on the government picking who gets in and who doesn't
So you say professionals but
Which profession
How do you decide what is our economy mean
Funny people lobbying fashion model the supermodels are going to want to get in
To our second economist
He has what he thinks
Is a better way
Immigration ID number 2
The highest bidder
My name is Giovanni Peri
I am professor of economics
Except universe
California
Jovani is the guy who told us about the special category for admitting
He says the best way to figure out
Who to let in
Is that you auction your visas off
To the highest bidder
Whoever employer is willing to pay more is going to
Get the permit to hire
So if we need if it turns out we do need more fashion models or more doctors
Presumably those employers would be willing to.
To pay more and they would get
Absolutely yes indeed
Real location
All of this worker is not determined by the government
Gruesome gruesome numbers that they come up
Where the body is determined by the market
You can imagine that under the system there would not be a whole lot of
People coming into work on farms or work on
Construction site
It's hard to imagine some
Tomato Farmers trying to hire that worker
Outbidding Microsoft
Visa
I'm like with Jean Baker I mean Giovanni is worried about the situation to his idea is that you have to
Categories of Visa
One for high-skilled workers that would be an option there
And one for low-skilled workers separate auction in each category would find the right
Price for their workers
I think he's another very important point.
I don't know if I want to give some numbers numbers
We say probably in high-skilled a permit for 3-year window between 5 and $10,000
And it looks skip permit which is only one here right now
Off for these temporary worker we go probably between 1 and $2,000
The math he comes up with a figure of maybe a billion dollars
The US government can make off of oxygen
A lot of money
And you know when you hear people talk about immigration
There's all this
Language around Edina moving to America to live the American dream
The Economist we talked to they did not make a huge deal about this citizenship
The auction Giovanni's talking about would be for
Temporary work visas good for a year
A few years
He says if things work out on the job
And they're still here when time is up
We should let him stay
Become citizens
We got two options so far
Allocate visas preferentially the high-skilled workers
Or two
Auction them off
Let businesses decide
Who they needed what they're willing to pay for the Visa
Or
Or you
You could go with dream proposal number 3
Robert weekly miss one
The free-for-all
This one comes from Alex Nebraska a self-described Libertarian at the
The Cato Institute
Here's his proposal
Letterman
All of them
The dream set up my drum set up would be a system whereby only criminals
Suspected terrorists
And those with serious communicable diseases like you know drug-resistant tuberculosis
Are barred from coming to the United States
To live and work
It's pretty simple
Everyone who wants to come to America
Just show up at the border
Thought-forms background check
And boom
You're in
Not as crazy
Are the United States had a system like that
From roughly 1792 about 1882
Did you catch that
He's saying that this crazy system
Open borders
That was the law of the land for almost
100 Years of American history
Damn the crazy system is the system that we have now with all these restrictions
That's crazy
It wasn't put in place because of logic or fairness
It was put in place because
Racism
In particular fear of people from China
We're coming in and providing cheap labor working the Goldrush building Railroad
And the Chinese word convenient scapegoat
They look very different from Americans at that time
So is easy to point them as being you know difference
And third of all
A severe economic
Right to be nice
After the Chinese
We start the black European in a
Change the Lost Immigrants had to
Parts of Europe
And had have family here
This dynamic
Where we exclude groups of people this
Can you over the last hundred years
That's why they end up like this
Certain groups were afraid
Other groups would come in
And take away their job
Eventually ended up with the messy system we have today
Alex's argument
Or basically opening the borders is pretty
The more people he says the better
People immigrated to the United States they tend to work really hard
They're more likely to start up businesses
Sergey Brin the co-founder of Google
He was rushing
And if you Google
Immigrant entrepreneurs you find out
The Intel co-founded by Hungarian
EBay founded
French Yahoo by the Taiwanese
Loving a post by a Greek woman
Tok more immigrants means more entrepreneurs more doctors more compete
Programmer
Teachers Ma
More radio
Alex you probably can't tell from his accent but Roberts from Canada
Welcome
Because your country is strange to me but I I'm I'm getting along well and working hard
Assimilating very well I must say I mean if we let in
All the brilliant Canadian radio reporters and there are a lot of them
They could take my job or you know I can recover
I can get a big salary cut
I know competition is good but it is stressful if I think about it first choice
Alex told us yes looking some places this competition it could depress wages
But he figures it won't actually be too bad
Because
He said a lot of what happened
When you let a bunch of people in
Is it the economy just expands to accommodate them
Spell little
Immigration is more than stealing Talent from other countries
It's about allowing people to come to a place where they can
Flourish where they can in fact do more for the world
What's a transfer of somebody
Who are the less productive in their home country
The United States
What are three to five to ten times more productive
So what increases the size of the global pie the global economic pie tremendously as well as the pie in the United States
Which makes sense to me we have electricity here we have
Function court system we have law enforcement we have financial markets so you can get your business going
Silicon Valley
When people come here he says
It benefits them
But it also helps everybody else
Alex's proposal does have this one very nice
Feature which is that yes you have to scream at criminals and terrorists at the border
But you don't have all these undocumented immigrant
The danger of them crossing the border in the middle of the night
I'm living here
In fear
You don't need so many immigration poll
All that goes away
We're at Alex's idea of open borders by are two other economist
And both of them had the same
Too many
Too many people would want to
Christine Baker
What's that funny I was at a conference remember some years back and there were few people that they weren't all Economist there but a few people
I said what would happen if we open the borders and
All of the people who were there from developing countries just laughed and they said
Why don't you do it for a few years and see
Get out the reality is obviously United States is a much wealthier country than say sub-Saharan Africa Bangla
4 - if you had open borders you just said what do you want to come here come here you know you can work just like anyone else
My guess is you would see a massive
I mean tens of Millions
The people
Find
I don't think a lot of people would really be happy with that outcome
I'm going to be very different
Country Inn and not just talking about complexion
I'm done talking about yellow sheer numbers of pi
People
Strength and infrastructure that
Strains on the natural environment
I don't think you know what country is 310-320 million people I don't think people really be that anxious to see the
The US is a country or six or seven
Hundred million people and say it
10 15 20
We kept asking Alex about this if you open the borders
How many people would come here
Alex says there are some poles
Where they asked people around the world
You want to move to the United States
There were a lot of guests
I was about five to seven hundred million
So that would
That would more than double triple the US population
That would
But you know we have to take Graham saw a grand at Big R and salt with that
Because you know it's very easy for people to say they want to move
One of the main features of modern migration around the world is that a lot of people move temporarily for a couple years
And they move back to their home
Alex figures more like
50 to 100 million
People that want to move
Can you think
You can handle that
America is comparatively underpopulated compared to a lot of other kind
I mean compared to Western European countries in East Asian countries
America has a lot of space lot of room to build
What chances do you give this passing in Congress
About 0
How do you add the type of thing that I want right now is somewhere near to zero
There you have it
Three Economist three proposals
Each one more unlikely than the
But not impossible
Support for this podcast and the following message come from concur
A service where employees get simplified expense reports and Business Leaders get full visibility into their
Company spending habits
Expense
Travel
Invoice
Learn more at
Ker.com
NPR
Hello here we are back in the present
Sims the story ran a lot has happened to Anthony Court up the Englishmen we heard from earlier in the show the guy who move
Move to the US after falling in love
Florida
Last year the developers behind JP
Pete the Vermont ski mountain he invested in or accused of fraud
The SEC complaint alleges that the executives have quote
Systematically looted more than 50 million dollars
Race from hundreds of foreign investors
In which of these situations like this have thrown the Visa program known as eb-5 into question
Last week two senators drafted legislation to end it all together
We talked to Anthony Court. He says he is still owed around $400,000 of his investment
But
He is now a citizen
We always love to hear what you think of the show at Edison email Planet Money at npr.org or find us on Facebook
Facebook and Twitter
This episode was originally produced by Jess Jiang please version was produced by Nick
You're looking for another show to listen to check out pop culture happy hour
This week they're talking about a new film Lego Batman
If I did on npr.org podcast
Or the NPR one app
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Thanks for listening