Just a quick warning
Today's show has some adult
Themes
Last week I was in central New York
In the town of Oneida
It's really beautiful up there is
Blue Mountains and rolling fields
Farm houses
Exploring this place called the mansion house
It's this massive Brick House on a hill with a blue slate roof
It was built in 1862
Back then back in the 1800
The mansion house with a communist
Hundreds of people live there together
Many of their descendants actually grew up in this
House
Kelly Noyes Rose was showing me around the base
Look at the tunnel
Still drippy where it used
We're she and all the other kids used
Play it was our
Playhouse
This house
Really
Tons and tons of kids
It was sort of free and open it was
It was our family's house right
And then I went to the library where I met Nola DeSimone
She's also a descendant of the communist
She actually still lives here
She was visiting with all noise
They're both 82
We are two days apart in age
And how are you related
We are first cousins
Back when they were growing up their parents worked for
The company
The company was Oneida Limited
The flatworm
Knives and spoons and forks
Oneida had a very big Factory up
Did you get Oneida silver when you got married
What pattern
Raining beauty that was very playing and what the little crown
And how about you did you guys use Oneida
Did we run out of town probably if you did
Their parents owned the Oneida company
Honest Kids
You guys had a very idyllic All American Life
But the Oneida
Communes that came before the company
That hoodie very colorful history
But wasn't discussed
No I don't think
But
I agree with you wholeheartedly wasn't discussed
Also
The people who had practiced that
We're gone
The practice was
Spouse swapping
Pre-loved
The Oneida kahmune had
Some sex.
The Oneida company was a place where they took all that sex stuff
And put it away
In a silverware drawer
Hello and welcome to Planet Money
And I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Today on the show The Story of Oneida
It's an iconic All-American brand and this story has got it all the charismatic founder artisanal mastery
Marketing genius and free love
I'm at a time when America's brand of go It Alone profit or bust capitalism is not work
Working for everyone it's a reminder that our country's economic history is not all Robert
Barons and Puritan people have found all kinds of ways to drive here
Let's call this one
Communal capitalist
Support for this podcast and the following message come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and community
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org
In the 1840s there is a lot happening
It's the Industrial Revolution we are mass-producing stuff
Cities
Working in factories it's also the time of the great awake
The Second Great Awakening
This is the time of religious
Zeal
People are starting to interpret
Christianity in all of these different ways
This is when the Mormons and the Adventist pop-up and the Shakers see big growth
And all over the Northeast these groups are getting together
They're leaving civilization
They're setting up in the woods and they're creating communist
They would make shoes or they
Lakewood make chair
They would do things that people did in the Middle Ages unit
They would make brooms that
Is very common
That's a doctor Tony wonderly pizan Oneida historian
And in the 1840s there are dozens of these types of communes in and around upstate
The Oneida Community started by a guy named John Humphrey Noyes
John is from a normal upper-middle-class family in Vermont
He's a handsome guy
In pictures he looks a lot like Neil Patrick Harris mph mph
And John has
Intense
Charisma
With the kind of Charisma you write home about
In fact
More than a few young ladies did write home about it
Ellen Wayland Smith is a great great great grand niece of John
And she says
Here's what one woman said about
She said when you were in a room with him the whole room lit up and he made you want to do whatever he told you to do
John belongs to a group called The
Any idea behind being a perfectionist is it
You strive to make yourself
Free of sin
And desire
Are you work on your
So they started communism Oneida
But they need to find a way to make a live
And it first through thinking maybe Orchards
But the weather Upstate is very fickle and the Orchards keep dying
MN
Someone in the Communist tips John offices
There's this guy that just joined Sewell New
A legendary
I figured much like Davy Crockett or Daniel Boone
Sewell is a wildly talented artist
He makes animal traps
And Tony says Sewell was just like
The man
He's the fastest guy who's the best rapper the best shot
Sewell
A person like Sewell is part of what's going to make Oneida so special
The way I imagined it
The other communes Upstate are getting
The anxious
People in the depression
They're getting like if the broom makers ideally I would be a roommate
Baker Noel
John Humphrey Noyes is getting CEO.
Let me think about it
Perfectionism
Literally means you think it is possible to be
Perfect here on Earth
So he's attracting
Talented
Optimus
Catholic Soul who is a really
Talented
Trap maker
He makes animal trap
By hand
And the timing is really good because right now forever is in the height of fashion
And everybody wants
Cops
Some collars made out of
Mink and ermine
And noise has these other
Talented optimistic
Can do followers who happened to be East machine
They figure out a way to mechanize production
Action of Sewells traps
And within a couple years
The Communist cranking out
200000 animal traps
These are people who
Get mass production and the roofing on the Industrial Revolution it is manufacturing but
With a religious under
John Lewis and his followers start putting their prowess to work in other areas as well they have a bunch of side Hustle
Including
Flat where they start making flatware
This group just seems to have a knack
And all the things that come into the common all of the money is shared nobody owns n
They call it Bible communist
And it's not like Marxist communism it literally just means communist
Ism
In fact
They are capitalists very successful cap
Ellen says that meshes just fine with John's perfectionist bully
He saw it
Capitalism was going to be a way of uniting
Humans into one sort of global
Market
And that this can only bring good
Infidelity bring good
By 1862 these people have enough money to build the 93,000 square foot mansion
And then 250 or so of them move in together
It's idyllic of men and women in
Winfield's
Berries in a factory making
Animal traps
And they only have to work a few hours a day because things are going so well they can
Can afford to hire
People in town
The Hangout in the Mansion library and they
They read and they put on
Please women take off their corsets
They cut their hair short and they start wearing
Pants but they are not just sharing money
That's the other unusual part of John's perfectionist
Society
They're sharing
Spouses
Which is part of their perfectionism to
Rethink ownership and selfishness
Make people unhappy
Sockshare
John is made ground rules
To keep things from getting out of control
First of all
It's not called
Free love
It's called
Complex
Marriage
You're selling
Well the rules were that all men in the community were married to all women so in other words all women and men
And were accessible to one another sexually and Siri
If a man wanted to
They called him interviews
Interviews interviews that was our youth Commision for
Epic Sax
As a reporter
Okay so here's how it works
A man would approach a woman
Not the woman he wanted to interview
You better go between
Net2 hurt hey
I want an interview
Stacy
Can you see if she'd be up for it
And then Stacy you would get
Say yes
Organelle
Did it work both ways I think it would have been unusual for a woman to proposition a man
Damn
Oh yeah
I know right
The Perfection is are also against what they call
Sticky love that is
Selfish love
The kind of love where you get
Attached to
You are never allowed to spend the night
With anyone you have had these interviews that were literally start our sessions in a room
Yeah you're not allowed to spend the night because that would
Nope nope well you know I get into your not sure if you have a way around it
But
Technically you were not you know supposed to be cohabitating with
This person you're sleeping with because that would
That was conducive to a kind of intimacy that would not work in the community
And if you fell in love with someone if you were like you know what John Miller is going to dude for me I don't want to see you
Severely chastised
Punishment took the form of mutual
Criticism
You stand up in front of a panel of people and they would just
Tell you about yourself
And the criticisms could be literally anything from you know he laughs too loud
His stories are boring
When women get criticized for being pigeon-toed
She should try to walk with her feet
He turned out
So it was our way from the sublime to the ridiculous you know
To the Patty
Search me the sounds
Terrible but apparently some members of the community really liked it that even would volunteer to go in front of these panels and have people
Honestly about their
Flaws
And for 30 years this community gets by and thrive
But then something starts
To shift
There are things going on in Oneida that are wrong
30 stories about John Humphrey Noyes sleeping with underage
It is very disturbing to people inside the Communist and word starts to get out
The same time the country is becoming more religiously cancer
The government is starting to ask a lot of questions about some of the newer religions that have cropped up
Across the country
Tony wonderly says the oneidas get wins that the government is Prosecuting Mormons out
West and they always said when the government goes after the Mormons then we got to watch our tails
They'll be after us next
In 1879 John gets a tip if the authorities are coming
And he bolts to Canada
And when he leaves there are these
Really big question
Do we stay here
Do we go somewhere else do we keep doing things the way we're doing or do we change
And so in 1880 there's a big kahmune meeting over what
200 people vote and
And they vote
To fold the Oneida
Communists are no longer going to be spouse
Swapping
But even though they're not in bed together anymore they're still in business together
And it's 8
Thriving business
And they all on it
So they form a joint stock
Oneida Company Limited
Owned by the 200 adult commune
Companies worth about 14 million dollars in
In today's dollars
And the stock is divvied up according to how long
I've been with the Communists and how much Capital they put in when they arrive
So now these people have to change their lifestyle
Some of them get married and move out in for nuclear families
Anybody now owns their own stuff and fertilize them it really freaks them out
So they went through a period of time where they would take
Careful notice of lending one another hammer
Opinion or a nail
While they are adjusting to all of this
Newest who still up in Canada dies
How old are you
And then dissention set in
And a lot of the people running the company at that
That point
Became Advocates of spiritualism
You claim that they were in contact with
With noise
And noisy and decisions
Meaning they were talking to his ghost
These old guys are running a multimillion-dollar company
And they are getting management tips from
It's a problem
And meanwhile all around them the times are changing
Again we've entered the Gilded Age
Which is a time of
Unprecedented business competition and marketing
And at this moment Oneida probably
Should have failed
Any
What if fail
Except
The John Humphrey Noyes had a son
Who is a very extraordinary person
Most of us are about as smart as we have to be
To get through life
And very occasionally we we meet someone who is
Really intelligent and when when that happens is unmistakable the
What person is bigger than life and Pierpont was that way
Pierpont noise didn't care about free love or
Perfectionism
His religion was business
He started out as a low-level flatware salesman in New York but he didn't stay there for long
The Oneida New that time to change
They were losing money
Around the year 1900
Pierpont comes home from New York backup to Oneida
And he and a bunch of
People from the younger generation
They take over the
Now Oneida is still making a bunch of different things
And Pierpont decides it
It's time to focus
Anything he wants to focus on is silver plated flat
Where he thinks it's the
At this time the US middle class
Is really growing and there all these young people who are coming in
Money and they have new homes and they need flatware
And at this time only really rich people can afford
Sterling
And everybody else uses
Steel
A new class people all want those beautiful silver Utah
Canceled but they can't really afford them
Poop your pants
Figures out a way to make utensils that look like sterling silver and even
Buick sterling silver
Acosta
Wayless
Pierpont takes regular metal flatware
And instead of dipping it in a silver bath for a second or two
He takes it and he dunks it in for
A couple seconds more
Does it really cost that much extra but when you pull it out
It looks and feels much more like the real thing
And then his idea was to
Actron these
Elaborate
Curlicue pattern
And give them insane
Flowery names like
Avalon
Fun and coronation
End
Getting back to his salesman roots
He started knocking the competition
There were these old established silverware from dominated the market
The Pierpont was like a magician
He take his spoon and the other guy spoon
You would flashes in the customer's face he would take it you take it competition I demand you say you see this
You see this is nothing but a bunch of sausage from Tool makers
Heavier triple plated in silver
But people loved it
Anybody
At the same time. Punch rippled down on a
He hired famous artists and in the days when most ads
Just Big Blocks
Text Oneida comes out with all these ads
Drink the first
Pin-up girls
It looks like they were intelligent and having fun and wanted
Nothing more than to have fun with one another and to have Oneida silver
That's like what we all want
Right we all have fun and
Use utensil
I saw a bunch of these ads by the way it's like
Some hip looking young woman out on the town and then
Right below where there's
Just like a spoon hanging out hanging out
And by the mid-twenties this upstart Oneida comp
It was doing so well but it was buying up other silverware
Yes Oneida is a runaway American capitalists
Success
But there were some things from the old communist Pierpont
Kept alive
He had a motto
Nobody rich
Nobody poor
So when it came to their workers
Oneida did things
Their way
Pierpont called it industrial social
Oneida built its worker
Town with parks
Ballfield electricity water sewage
Half the salary of the school t
Teachers there
And executive pay was kept
Very low and when the company was going through hard times Executives to pay cuts
Before the worker
Nuala DeSimone the lady who I met in the mansion house Library
She remembers that Pierpont workers the guys on the line
Loved him so much
The one year
The pool their money and they bought him a blue cat
Cadillac
Twin up in the back remember those
First once and I was a beautiful car
I mean try to imagine in 2017
The workers of a company buying
A car for the CEO
It's unthinkable
Tony wonderly the historians
Even back then
This was extraordinary
Sf giants onesie
Are you getting choked up
What
I think these folks are
Are Inspirations for it I think they
Help to remind us what we should be doing as Americans what is most American
Business and our better nature
And are American
By the end of World War II Oneida has become
A giant it isn't
Sonic American
Enter pain through the big 100 year anniversary
Clown balloons
Comedians
Steven crown
A silver
We had Tommy Dorsey
Orchestra and that was pretty special have you heard of him
But the world was changing again
And this is a very familiar story in
Oneida has to fight to compete
Cheaper Imports that are coming in
Also take a start to change
Stainless steel becomes really popular up Silver Plate starts go
Going out of fashion
And the Oneida company starts having a lot of info
Jeff noises
Is Pierpont noises grandson he works for Oneida for many years
Things really changed in the late
Sixties when the company went public when it was listed on the stock X
Because when that happened it wasn't a family
Anymore
All these Outsiders came in executive salaries Rose
The industrial socialism
Petered out
MGF noises
United name just
Wasn't what it had
Depreciated
The value of the name of the writer by putting it in Walmart and stuff my father
Really dislike Walmart
You didn't like
What the hell is that guy's name
Walton yeah well he knew Miss
Scott Walton
Yeah cuz it was obviously they wanted an item in Walmart
And your dad did
No
Because it depreciated the name
After the break
What is left of Oneida
Support for Planet Money and the following message
Which come from ishares
Because the best preparation for tomorrow
It's building for your future today
Ishares by BlackRock inspired to build
About a decade ago Oneida filed for bankruptcy
Shareholders
Including some Oneida descendants
Lost a lot of money
You can still buy Oneida Utah
Pencils it's still a branded
In the world do United company merged
With a different company to become the
The Oneida group
It's still a really popular brand in retailing
Services
Flip over a fork in a restaurant
You might see Oneida
And of course they sell it at 1
Any Oneida family still
Chicken around up there
And they're really proud of this
BC what Oneida did as an experiment in responsible
Capitalism
They made money
But they also took care of each other
End
For a while anyway
It worked
Our Ed
Editor is kind of into utopian communities right now if you have any stories about economic Utopias please
Send a message
What planet money at npr.org
If you want to learn more about Oneida I can recommend to great books
Ellen Wayland Smith
Oneida from free love Utopia to the well-fed table and Tony wonderly's Oneida Utopia which is
Can you come out this Wednesday
Today's episode was produced by Sally Helm Bryan or sat is our editor Alex goldmark produces the show
Special thanks to Paul Gebhardt Kate Wayland Smith Pat Hoffman Molly Jessop and Kevin Coffey
New podcast to listen to check out up first it is the Morning News podcast from NPR it is
Minutes long and it tells you everything you need to know to start your day
You can find it on the NPR one app or wherever you get your podcast
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith and I'm Noel King thanks for listening
But this group is not just sharing all the money
Bayer schering