Hey it's
Sally Helm here
The Republicans are about to take control in Washington
And this week we are replaying an episode about what happened when a republican Governor cut
Taxes in
The show originally ran in October of 2014 and will have an update for you at the end
For now here is Robert Smith
And Zoe
This is the story of a politician who took a chance
And is now fighting for his political
The man is Sam Brownback
He's a republican governor of Kansas
Let me start off by saying that I am bullish
On Kansas
This guy expected to be re-elected
Sam Brownback won by a landslide
4 years
And when he was elected the Senate six years before that
Awesome Lance
And 6 years before that everyone loves Sam Brownback
But things are really upside down in Kansas right now
In fact last week I was in a library
In Topeka KS
Kansas and I'm talking to this former budget director for the state of Kansas
And he says
You will not believe what is happening next
Next door
About 500 Republicans are going to endorse
The Democratic ticket for governor
In about an hour
It seems weird is that weird
Oh yeah that's really unusual for Kansas
Yeah
I go take a look and there all these white haired guys in suits
Thank you all for being here Republicans are
Former politicians guys who presumably voted for Sam Brownback they're lined up at a small pool
To endorse
Paul Davis
Who is the Democratic
We're here today point out the worsening results
Sam brownback's failed experiment on Kansas
This whole story comes down
To this big
Experiment
And economics.
Brownback
Tried something that should have landed him in the Republican Hall of Fame
If that exists
Something that I would have thought would have cemented his support
As very Republican governor in a very Republic
Sam Brownback is close to losing his bid for re-election
Because Sam Brownback cut
Taxes
Cheese today Republican Governor lives the dream
Because taxes dramatically in his state where state in transition
From a high tax state
Tupelo tax date
He promises Good Times ahead and the good times do not
And people even the Republicans get really mad
Support for this NPR Podcast and the following message come from Blue Apron
Blue Apron partners with sustainable Farms fisheries and ranchers to bring you all the ingredients you need to
To create a credible home-cooked meal
Ingredients compared with an easy-to-follow recipe card
Delivered to your door weekly in a refrigerated box
ReDiscover how fun cooking can be while enjoying specialty ingredients and exploring new flavors and cuisine
Get your first three Blue Apron meals free
What's free shipping by visiting blueapron.com
Zoe
Sogo
I went to Kansas
And I drove all over
And everyone was either talking about
The World Series
Organics
Deep economic questions
Basically about Brown Bags
The experiment
Here's how the whole thing.
Raquan Brown Bag guidance office a few years ago
He decided to do this pretty flashy
Indus fiscally conservative
Barry non-flashy
We'll have a real live experiment we're right next to some other states that haven't lowered taxes by
We'll see how it works
Republicans
Love to talk about lowering taxes
Brown Bag decided he was going to be the guy who would go
Big
The question was
What would happen if Kansas had the lowest taxes in the Midwest
His big idea was that
People and businesses would be like yes
I am going to go to
To Kansas that is where I'm going to do business now
The business is already in Kansas
They would use the money to expand
So you really get your acceleration this like shooting adrenaline Into the Heart
I'm growing the economy
I taken at tax office
A small business were most your job creation
Brownback went back and forth with the legislature
And in the end the bill that they came up with was the tax cut plan that was way bigger than what they thought
Was even possible in the
Taxes on small businesses would go to
So they stopped paying anything
And personal income taxes went down by a lot also like the highest income bracket went down by
8% about
We've the big question which is
After this big tax cut
Where is Kansas going to get all the money that it needs to
To run the state
To pay for education and Healthcare in the stuff that comes out of the state
Budget this was the Crux of the
Experiment
There is this Venus theory behind this idea and conservative circles
That tax cut is done correctly will eventually bring more money into a CD
Mysterious pushed by this one Economist that you may have heard of
He works for Ronald
Reagan talk to me dr. Laffer yes can you hear me I am enjoying the conversation with you it's very much fun
Arthur Laffer
And Brownback wanted the regen guys help
He called me
Around the time he was proposing his tax and tax changes in Kansas
And asked me to come down and spend some time with him and talk
With the legislature Arthur Laffer is famous for something and economically called the Laffer
And it is really more of
Thought experiment then like
A mathematics
Formula
And I want to spend a minute or so
Here really
Explaining it because it is actually the theoretical underpinning of what Brownback did
Which is fascinating and weird in an oven
Robert come back for second in
Let's watch
Okay so
It is really all about tax
In which tax rate brings in the most
Let's start
Play Swift
A 100% tax rate
Basically the government takes every dime
You make
You work all day long
And you get nothing the government
Takes everything out of your paycheck
Obviously no one would work
With that kill everyone who quit their job so
In this imaginary places 1% tax rate
The government would get
No rap
Nobody
Okay so the government's like we're getting $0 at 100%
What if we lowered
To 90% rate
Which is still an incredibly High rate but
Some people would go back to work to get that money
Just for that 10% of your income
It would give the rest of the 90%
To the government
So this is laffer's big inside the Laffer Curve which
The way The Story Goes
He drew on a napkin
Somewhere in
Everything is laid out of
Always on an app
This napkin showed or so he said that the government can lower taxes
And
Get more Revenue
Is because going from 100 to 90 would yields more Revenue that doesn't mean it is always
True
Government might find if they lowered the rate from say
40% to 30% did actually just get less Revenue because it wouldn't necessarily incentivize
Why so many
People to go back to work
Revenue with just drop
This is what the Brownback experiment
What happened
At lower tax rate
Specifically what happens if you lower the tax rate for small businesses
From an already low percentage in Kansas
2-0
Will Kansas
Skip more businesses suddenly will those businesses create more jobs
Will eventually there be more people working and work
People paying other kinds of taxes that weren't lowered like sales tax
In other words
On the Laffer Curve
Will the government of Kansas make
More money by cutting
That is the bet that brown bag
It's making
And that is what I asked
Laugh about
Do you say I'm going to run one of the greatest experiments on the Laffer Curve that state tax policy has ever seen
I don't know if he actually said that or not
But he sure as heck has done that
Arthur Laffer says he
He did not design the tax cut plan himself but
You did a great job
Laughter is
Certain he is for sure
The underground bags experiment Kansas will
Wellmore employment more output more production
More sales taxes because these people have
Higher incomes they moved from Missouri to Kansas
Care more jobs
Creative in Kansas they'll be more payroll taxes
Into Republicans in Kansas that sounded
Great
Les Donovan was Republican state senator at the time
I'm he remembers it
He helped push this plan through
Do cut the tax out on
Do certain types of income business income
It's an incentive for people to
Are more people
Not pay the taxes to the state of Kansas but they're going to hire people
Give them jobs and they're going to pay taxes to
That's the way they're supposed to work
This is officially known as supply-side
Economics
Although
People who are not
Favorite often called trickle down economics
Whatever the name
Kansas was all in
The law was passed
Experiment was underway
I'm going to zero is a really big change I wanted to see what it was like for these
Much vaunted small businesses
So everywhere I went in Kansas I would go into places and ask them about it
Take the sky Alex
Harp Kansas small business person of the year
He's just starting up his second business in Wichita
Restaurants
It's a it's set beef and chicken shawarmas Falafel sandwiches how much
Salads we have the Mediterranean salad fattoush salad
You know enough reserve it there's no fat and that it's healthy and discretion is delicious and inexpensive
And it's fast
Alex Harvey move to Wichita from Lebanon 14 years ago
He already runs a computer retail and service shop
A Golden Corral franchise in Missouri
And now he runs
Meddys
Isn't the first of his many plants warmest spots
You made me order all the Shawarma that were available beef chicken and falafel
Hey Jason
Where is JC
He said he didn't even know he was going to get this Big Tex
You know I honestly didn't really believe it so I called my accountant his name is David Guevara
He's an awesome guy
He said yeah you not going to have any taxes pay any taxes
You know
Next year so great
Awesome
Alex's first move with exactly what brown bag head
I dreamed that it would be
Alex
Took his tax cut money
And he invested into his business
His computer business
Ribbit
We added more iPads into a RM in 30 without money
Got a bunch of iPads
We didn't really focus on selling iPads at Ribbit Computers
So
You know
We have more iPhone
So this is the first step in the Brown Bag experiment
The reinvestment
Across town the same thing happen
Gary Mason is the CEO of this company is I Environmental
Bee clean up things like
Graffiti he says or toxic
Weast and he knew that
Tax-cut was coming and he knew what he was supposed to do with it would free up some more money to allows to go buy more quick
Which in turn if we leverage that can hire more people
So kind of snowballs on itself
Gary Mason bought
Power washer
Very powerful power washer
$80,000
Cut through concrete
It's very very high pressure
Matter fact we got contacted by
A party yesterday to go
Cut something off a bridge tomorrow
This was all working theoretically as it should
Businesses are reinvesting and with that investment they will do more business
And then also theoretically higher
Mason says he's going to hire
Theoretically that new guy could go down
To Alex's store and buy an iPad with his new fancy salary
That generates
New revenue for the state that they wouldn't have gotten otherwise
And that is what
Economic growth
Increase spending increase
Hiring
And it's not really happening
At least at the Shawarma level of the economy
Did you hire anybody
Melanie
Not really because you hide People based on that based on how much money you have based on your business it didn't really have in Media
Help on the business I didn't really notice any
More business purchasing you know around here so
Literally
Drinking anything for hire more employees
Yeah Alex is not the only one to notice that business hasn't really picked up yet in
After the tax cuts Revenue to the state budget
Starting to drop
Very dramatic
It's obvious when you think about it that if you give someone $100 tax cut
And they spend that money
The state only gets
$6 and fifty
Keen sense back
Incel
The seat budget office they knew there would be a short fault that they started wouldn't be that bad
The projected revenues would fall by 300 million dollars
In fact State revenues fell by twice that in the
First year after the tax cut the seat was bringing in six hundred million dollars less than they had before
Which is a Big Dipper
To balance the budget Kansas spent down its reserves and tax into the highway budget
The experiment was not really going
According to
Playing at least as the plant have been laid out it was not the shot of adrenaline to the Kansas
Economy that the governor have been talking about
And some people in Kansas started to really worry about the future of the Kansas budget
Especially people
Korean School
We've watched us as Educators were watching The Strain run into the wall and
We're all sitting here watching it
Lake lots of other school superintendent
Glenn suitcase decided to Make Some Cuts in his district
And there was one really obvious thing
The whole school
This one school in the Tiny Town of Marquette right in the middle of Kansas
Last February all the schools parents met in the gym and watch the
School Board
Vote on this car
There was silence
Before
The motion
No one wanted to give the motion
They knew what they needed to do
They thought about it many times
For that night
That was
The worst moment
I believe there was another long period of
Uncomfortable time when
Before the 2nd
The motion
And as that happened in the boarding
The building was
Officially closed
That night
I went out to Market
See the town without his
I'm in the middle of nowhere there's
Grain elevator
Main Street
Restaurant
A bar
The very nice
Very empty school building
If you look through the window you can still see some of the instruments the band used inside
Xylophone in the timpani or just alone in a dark room
It's little bit creepy
Driving around the town it does seem like a really
Turned out the school had only 65 kids in it
Now those kids split up at a bus stop every morning
Take some 10 to 20 miles out of town to go to school
In the Tiny Town like this
65 people leaving it everyday is a big deal
I found that out of the grocery store Steve Piper is the owner
She was cooking pulled pork on the smoker outside
That looks so good I have been around
Decimus pork ribs too early
Steve's around bald guy wearing an apron
This is the kind of guy that was supposed to benefit from the Brownback tax
But the one school in town closing
That was a way bigger deal
For a business owner you better off having those teachers and those jobs here in Marquette
That they then shoppingtown help you out that way
Versus
Having a
Neon floor tax if you're not making me money service
Taxes mean nothing if your sales are down
Texas me nothing
Do yourself a percentage of a smaller amount right
Right
If you lose someone like this
You might lose the election
This is the guy that Brownback was eating at
Tax cut small business expansion
Not small town shriveling up and dying and businesses closing up I want to sell my stores are going to be worth anything
Has anyone going to want to move to Marquette and buy a Small Town Square without a school until
This has been a problem in rural Kansas for a long time the 1 School in town closing
Marquette is surrounded by Ghost Town
Places that wash their schools and then the town went away
This school probably would have closed it some
But because of the big experiment everyone in town is pointing to Brownback
Weaning
There is a sense they can
Is actually falling behind
Economically
And the statistics so far bear this out
After the tax cut there was not
A flood of new residents and businesses into cans
Other states that border Kansas are actually growing faster
Creating more jobs
Even with their higher tax
Sam Brownback is an interesting Stitch
He did what he believed in he has not backed away from his theory
He says look we are
Poised
To grow and
We have created
55000 private-sector jobs in Kansas is getting jobs
Just
More slowly than people maybe
He thought that it would
Brownback says if he is re-elected he is going to
Stick with this plan he's going to keep cutting income taxes all the way down to
I asked Arthur Laffer the famous economist behind the experiment
What he makes of this stuff
Situation for Governor Brownback
Isn't the point of the policy to
Create more revenue and more growth
Yes but it's not in the first hour
I'm sorry it takes people a long time to adjust to a new tax code
It takes a long time and that's why I do all of my work over a decade
And look at what the results are
Over long periods of time which is what a governor should do
When he governs
So she governs a steak
And to expect that to occur in the first year is is is not
Of course new governor is elected for
For 10 years experiments in politics they have four years to work
For years and there's a verdict
Sam brownback's
Verdict has arrived
Election day is in two weeks
And right now the reason
Is 2 closed
Call
Hey it's Allie
That race was in November of 2014 and
Sam Brownback
What
He won by a really small margin he got 49
Percent of the vote and the Democrat he was running against
Got 40
Percent of the vote
But that was enough
He had four more years.
Keep going with it
I called up Sam's f
He's a reporter at kcur in Kansas City he covers politics
And educate
I asked him how things are going now
And he said not well
It's dire it's serious
People are worried
Because the seat is right now facing a billion dollar deficit
Over the next two fiscal years
And they've been searching couch cushions all over the state
Trying to find any nickels and dimes a can
To balance the state budget
There has been job growth in Kansas he said
But it's been slower than in neighboring state
And
Sam Brownback
Sam Brownback is the least
Popular governor in a mirror
Brownback gave his
State of the State
Address on January
10th and he said he is sticking with his plan to
To cut taxes
But it seems like at least
Some people in Kansas are getting a little sick
That plan
At the elections in November a lot of Brownback allies in the latest
Play Charlie lost
The legislative session began on Monday and the state legislature has already introduced a bill to end some of the brown
The governor has two more years to see if it's
The plan will work
His term ends in 2018
Do you know of some other plan that might have had an unintended consequences
Maybe something your job something that happened in your town
We want to hear about it
As always you can email us Planet Money at npr.org
Or find us on Facebook or Twitter
This show was originally produced by Thea Benin
Today's update was produced by me I'm Sally home
Thanks for listening