Quick warning there are a lot of bad words in the show some offensive language
We have been getting flooded
Baidu
Bizarro
Phone calls
There scam phone calls but that's not the weird part
The weird part
Is the day app
Pure to be coming from a phone number
It is almost exactly the same
As our phone
So say my number is
1 2 3 4
Then I'm getting a call from
6 / 6
Same area code 898 same next three numbers
7777 difference
Last for
And I think I know this is probably my Pharmacy maybe this
This is my neighbor down the
The street and so I pick up but no
It is almost always
Aruba
Well you have been selected
A week's vacation
Orlando Florida right next to Disney what is going on I talked about robot before and we wanted to know
Know how common
So we put out a call to
You Planet Money listeners
We asked hey are you getting these phone calls
Oh my God she asked
Usually comes about once a week
Probably three or four a day
Four different phone calls
And that 8 minutes fan on
Tuesday morning
We got around a thousand
Responses from everywhere from
St Louis to Southern California
Canada
And I just got one about 10 minutes before you called as a matter of fact
Hi this is Elizabeth from Resorts Bubba Bubba blah
And I picked the phone up and looked at the caller ID
And I guess I got to
Puzzled look on my face cuz my husband said who's calling
As I said apparently we are
Because the number in the redoubt 1 hour phone number
The calls are coming
From inside the house
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Kenny Malone and I'm finally home today on the show
Why are we suddenly inundated with the spam calls from our own phone number from our neighbor's phone
Phone numbers we learn how the scam works
What happens if you pick up the phone and what can be done to stop it
Support for this podcast and the following message come from fidelity
As a Fidelity wealth management client
You get a dedicated advisor to help grow and protect your wealth find ways to minimize the impact of tax
Axes and make clear recommendations for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
We have learned that this phenomenon this thing where you
You get a phone call
And it's from a number that works
Exactly what your number
This is called Neighbor
Stupid
Neighbor
Because
Number
Neighborhood
Spoofing that isn't someone making a call to
Guys has their number with
A different number
What we're going to do today
Is dig into Neighbors
Spoofing by looking at
Three main questions
Question 1
Why is this happening so much
Right now
Question 2
What happens when you decide to
Answer
One of these calls
This part is why we put a language warning at the top of
A little crazy
And question 3 is
Candy skulls
Puppy stopped okay
Question 1
Why is this such a big
Sing all of
To help us answer this we called up
Jonathan Nelson
He's with a tech company called hiya and one of the things he does is help
Block robocalls
The confusion that that a lot of folks
Have
When receiving a phone calls you you would assume that the phone number that's shown to you
Is is the exact number that actually making the call
Yeah
Yes we don't understand how that's not
The case
Johnson says
There didn't used to be a spoof
Problem
If you got call you knew who it was from
Whether the person was calling from a landline or cell phone the number you saw on your caller ID was the number they were calling
But now
You can place a call using something called
Voice over IP
IP as an Internet Protocol basically you
You can use a computer to make a call
It's over the internet but it shows up on somebody else's phone as if it is just a regular old phone
And voice over IP has made it possible to make it look like
You're calling from a different number
That is what we call call spoofing
They're totally legitimate reasons to spoof
Number so for example maybe you are Ted launcer
Service
And you have
A few phone lines but really you want
All of your outgoing calls to have the same number so you look like this
Unified compass
Great keep things simple
But of course
Scammers have discovered that they can also
That's if they spoof numbers
They can make it to the people are more likely to pick up their calls
So there was one scam for example where they would make it look like
IRS was calling you there was another one where they would make it look like you were trying
To call yourself I actually got one of those a couple weeks ago I had a missed call from myself
Why would anyone answer a call from yourself I don't think that would work very well I'm surprised they actually are stilts
Trying it and eventually
Someone
Somewhere
Hadn't
Evil spoofing Eureka moment
And they said okay
So maybe not the exact same number that
We're calling but what if we just use the same first six digits
And then randomly select 4 more digits
It will look like the neighbor is calling in February 2017 Jonathan says the started taking off
Someone had to try this
First that had to been the one scammer who had this idea and I just picture them bragging online to their
Hacker friends but hey check this out
Is amazing and then everyone started to me and so the answer to our first question
Why is this happening all of a sudden
It's because the internet makes it
Possible and actually
Easier everyday and also the scammers have discovered
That it works if they make it look like our neighbors are calling us
We're more likely
To pick up the phone
So just out of curiosity we wanted to see how easy it is to neighbor spoof
If somebody it is
Super
There are all kinds of software online
Type in the number you want to call
Type in the number you want to look like you're calling from and boom
We tried it out on Noel King
Sound like a robot
Noel
You have won a free vacation
I have not won a free vacation
I know you have won a free vacation
All right
Question number two
What exactly is happening when we
Do answer our phone
So we had an outstanding request for a collie to your planet
If you happen to get one of these neighbors spoof
Open calls
You please just go and grab a recorder
And see if you can record a call and talk to them and find out what they want where they are like whatever you can
Figure out
And it did not take long
Until our news reporter Julia DeWitt got one of these phone calls
And we have Julia in the studio with us now hello Julia
Hey guys
And we're actually just going to hand it off to Julian out to tell us about his phone call and what she figured out
Cities called came from a spoofed number it looks like my number from boss
And it started with a robot to see if you qualify
Press 2 to be taken off the list so I pressed one
Can I get connected to a human
Services how are you doing today
Hi I'm good thanks
Okay so let's just pause here first
I just started talking to this guy and I may have already made a bunch
I know this because later on I asked an expert about what was going on
What we tell consumers is at the best thing to is something to hang up on them
This is what Maxon he works the Federal Trade
He says when I picked up that call
When I press 1 for more information
I was saying to the people calling me
Human
Pick up which means
Maybe I will also
Buy things for me
That is valuable in
The people calling me may keep a list of all the suckers like me who pick up
The phone
They might even sell that list
Two other Robo caller
But of course selling my name to the rainbow colors
Is not this guy's
Man Hustle
That's great and I believe you are responding to get yourself for that production on your credit card right
Yes
And I said I'm sorry what was your name
John Torres
John
Okay Jung so I'm actually I'm
Do you mind if I record this call
Okay so yeah tell me about how I reduce my debt
Wheeler Blues using down your interest rate on your credit card there so we can help you out with your balance
Which credit card do you consider yourself that you're being a high interest rate on
I guess I hadn't really thought that much about it
Who am I getting this from
Division masks
Court services
Capital One
Teresa
Cover an American
It's okay
What's going on
Will Max in the guy at the FTC
It says first of all it's almost always illegal for a business to robocall you to
To try and see
You may have heard of the do-not-call registry the people making these calls
They don't care
The Artie breaking the law by Robo calling you
As for the end-game of these calls
Madison says sometimes these colors they are actually trying to
To tell you a real thing
Sometimes
They're trying to steal your credit
Okay where are you calling from
I'm calling you from Atlanta Georgia map
How how is that how's the weather in Atlanta
Weather in Sumter
Like you're too cool land
Early morning
Normal
Sometimes it's too cold at night August in Atlanta
And then at some point
John Torres from Atlanta to science he has had enough
Of my question
Quick wedding hair biscuits graphic
Which car do you want a lower interest rate on
I guess I mean I don't know I'm I don't I don't know which one
Which one do you have right now in your physical position
I have a MasterCard
What is expiration date on it
January 2018
Encarta
CZ
Which bank you have the card with
I guess yeah I mean I guess I just want to know a little bit more about what this is for just before I give you my credit card
And I know I'm a I
I just am not going to want to give you more information until I understand it a little bit more
Garden shovel
Lesbian card
Excuse me don't work on what
Lesbian cars
Lesbian cards
I'm sorry I'm just trying to get more more information about that I don't I don't mean to make you angry
Open and I can get you when we can get your city of Your Love
I don't know what this has to do with lesbian
Because you're lesbian so your card is also less
I don't take particular offense to that but
That's also not a credit card
I'm sorry who you said you work for cardmember services as the name of your company
I gave you everything I gave you the wrong information about
My fav artist
So he's you're not going to tell me what the actual
You lied to me about what the company man
Playing with your daddy
Has a conversation never gone this
This badly
Cut it doesn't I mean it seems like
We've lost the thread share with
Talking about inter
Best rates
And he hung up
Wow that went
A way that I say
So Julia
The question we started this section with what happens when you answer these calls
Bad things
Very bad things happen never pick up the
Coming up will these calls ever stop
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org
Horry County
Our final question here is
Will these Robo spoof neighbor scam are they ever going to end
What is being done
National level
Potentially
And this
Which is why we have looped in
Elsa Chang
Hay House here in DC
You are the heart of Regulation
Stomach does not
Okay so the Federal Communications Commission the SEC
They oversee telecommunicate
You know
Phone calls
And also you got a chance to talk to the chairman Ajit Pai about call spoofing and neighbors 2
Yeah because robocalls telemarketing calls
Spoofed calls that whole sort of Monsters Universe of unwanted
She called
This is
Is number one consumer
Action issue
German
Have you been spoofed
Oh absolutely so every now and then. Even on my work Blackberry I'll see a call that seems to be coming
Cell phone oh yeah the old seem to be coming from
Be the 202 area code
Which is here in Washington and then are prefix for these that blackberries
And I know for a fact
That's that you know it's probably not someone from the office
Sometimes I answered just for the heck of it end
Won't hold I've wanted vacation to from Marriott and I'm assuming he told you that
He's got it all under control it's going to be completely fixed in the next six weeks tell me that that's true that the calls are end
It's not so true I mean they're trying a few different things
The easiest thing that they're trying so far he
She said is there letting phone carriers block certain calls that are known to be
Spoofed calls are robo
Before the action that we took earlier this
Spring under the SEC rule carriers were obligated to patch through any calls that they got
It was Ian so
That's one of things we did was to allow them to take action against those spoofed numbers
But if you eat pie was telling me that
What they really have in mind is something far more time
Complicated but far better as a
Which is the ultimate solution I think to this problem
Switches to best find a call authentication standard basically we would be able to
Kodak unique
Signature
In every phone number that's really being used
Answer when a call is placed using that phone number the recipient of that call can have every confidence and knowing that okay this is the
The digital fingerprint for that number
I can trust that this is not a scam artist or somebody else
Who's impersonating the owner of that number
Oh how many years would it take to get
An authentication system like that in place
Yesterday. But this is exceptionally complexo what's like a time frame are we talking
A year from now a decade from you I have no idea because we can't predict exactly how the internet
Issaquah
It sounds like I am still going to be getting calls from my fake neighbors for like the next
Months years
There's no stopping for a while
Thanks Elsa
If you got a scam
Maybe it's yours maybe somebody else is
Email us Planet Money at npr.org or find us on Facebook or Twitter
We're going to investigate it
Get the bottom of it also Planet Money is hiring
So if you have some experience in journalism or in finance or if you've ever made anyone laugh when talking about economics
We want to hear from you
Go to NPR. Org / careers
Today's episode was produced by Elizabeth cool as our editor is Bryant verse that are supervising producer is
Alex Goldman
Special things this week to Kevin Ruby who helped us understand phones
And also if you are interested in this whole phone scam world
You should really go check out the podcast reply-all
They just had two amazing episodes that are about phone scams
If reply all episodes 102 and 103 long distance
Highly recommended go check it out
I'm Kenny Malone and I'm finally home thanks for listening
One last thing
Our friend Gregory Warner has just launched
A brand new podcast
Is it called rough translation
Amazing
It's available now
And here's a little taste
Gregory Warner here to tell you about NPR new international podcast called rough translation
Each week going to take you to a different country to hear a story that reflects back on something that we are talking about here in the United States
Maybe get a perspective shift
Travel with us
Rough translations on NPR one or wherever you get your