Support for NPR and the following message come from service now making the world of work
Work better for people
Their cloud-based platform and solutions deliver digital workflow
Spell create great experiences and unlock productivity for your whole company
More at servicenow.com
Gregory Warner
Stacey Vanek Smith
Fake news fake news
You hear this phrase
And it's hard to believe that it has been less than a year that we have been talking about
No matter who you are no matter what you think about them
Media
Fake news is a big problem you keep hearing this phrase
War on
And that's a scary phrase
Definitely say cic this phrase war on truth in the subway
I given junk mail I got a piece of mail right here to save our democracy we must win the war on truth
I think they probably want you to send money involves us all
It's really hard to know how to fight
At Gregory Warner yuan international correspondent friend
NPR you've been on Planet Money many times before and you brought us this incredible story
Of a war on truth
Way Beyond anything
We have seen in this
Yeah I mean this phrase Warren truth
Actually give you a little bit of deja vu
I'd heard this phrase
Yours before and
And you just the guy to call
Respond respond
Is a journalist
In Kiev Ukraine
He spent thousands of hours watching Russian TV trying to sort the real
My family members
Stay there complaining that
OU watch
Russian television all the time
They lie all the time and we have to listen all this lies about Ukraine
I first heard about response project three years ago when I was in Ukraine Frontier
One of the stories I was
Reporting was about how fake news from Russia with streaming over the border into you
Ukraine
Ida was not using the words fake
News in 2000
American
But respond
What's
He was in fact
Busy trying to figure out
How to stop fake news
I'm starting a civil war
Anchor you
Went to the front lines of this war
Figuratively and literally at for your brand new podcast rest
Translation which
You just rolled out with
With some help from Planet Money yes rough translation to do podcast
We take a conversation that we are having in this country
And we trying to see how it's playing out in some other corner of the world maybe get a
Perspective shift
In this case Ukraine is actually the place where some of Russia's fake news tactics were first
Developed tested
And rolled up
So I ask respond
Until what do you think Americans
Can learn
From
Ukraine example
What the lesson for us
Yeah.
The very first
Lesson do not ignore these problem
Because
It allowed Russian media to influence
Local people to
Hello and welcome to rough translation
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith and I'm so excited to have Gregory Warner with me and an episode of his brand new podcast rough trans
Inflation
Today on the show we bring you
The war is fake news belt
There is a real war right now in eastern Ukraine we're going to go to the actual Frontline
But first we are going to go back in time a bit to follow the people who fought to stop fake news
Splitting a country apart
It was a fight that ended up changing them
When rough translation for charts
This message comes from NPR sponsor squares
Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their own website
Using customizable layout
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobile added
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online presence
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Sunday morning outskirts of Kiev
Responding chanko pick me up to take me to his house boys face
Grand temples
Led Zeppelin the car radio
Recent train to the journalist in America in the house where he lives is not like anything I've seen in Ukraine what are the styles
These houses
The call Tia they call it North American style North American. American it's a gated community the promises
Is American style cottage living
Down to the
Traditional American BBQ area
Names of the streets they they written in English
And
Over there is a Lexington Avenue
Andeavor yard
Has a picket fence
I don't like when people build this huge fences and
Respond can look right over his fence
His neighbors and neighbors can look over their fence
Let him this type of Life represents
My hip probably my imagination about the
The way I would like the whole country leave
More transparent
More friendly
Talking to each other discussing issues discussing problems
The reason I went to Ukraine back in 2014 was because the country just had approached
Democracy Revolution
Protesters in the capitol
Yap demanded that the government take steps to join Europe and become less dependent
Russia
Russia opposed this Uprising it wanted Ukraine
Stay a little brother
It's much cheaper.
But when the protesters succeeded and the
Pro-russian president
Flat respond realize that Russia was fighting back
But in a way that took him a while to understand
Russian tanks
First descent news
Song with turn on the TV
Russian Chan
Millions of ukrainians were watching
And keep your warranty
About Neo Nazi fascists rolling Street
People
Assault on TV
The date in danger and they need to protect their families they need to protect themselves
From fascist in Kiev
But they want a fascist
Respond could look at his window and see the streets were peaceful
Barricades on the Square in Kiev
Covered with fresh flowers
But ukrainians who are not in
Got scared
So while respond would watch these stories and think
Some some b*******
In other parts of the country
Free people started standing guard
Ukrainians in Crimea
Rose up
They rejected the regular
They want to be but everybody everyone is Russia and
The Grammy Awards Russian before protesters
In Crimea
Quoted the Russian TV stories about fascist
Big Russian troops to save them
Kind of feeling that the new government in Kiev is
Hostile to Russian speakers and ethnic Russians here
Russian troops arrived
And Crimea voted to secede
Ukraine wanted to fight back in a solution that came up with was a news blockade
A complete ban on Russian news channel 5 has a game stat decision
I was in favor of
Esmarch sources of information is possible
Ukraine the band media
This is not democratic
But that was the Ukraine that the Revolution fought for Ukraine if you want to be a democracy should allow
How to have another opinion and Western diplomats agreed this is censorship
The government back down
Free speech
Democracy
And respond came up with a radical new plan
To fight back
A team of top journalist would fact-check Russian news
And broadcaster
The results
And the time
That's a really scary
To me it actually meant that I'm
Kind of putting my life on the line
This is Marco Gonzales she was tapped to host a show that would
Debunk Russian fake
It so it would be her face on the screen.
Any Kremlin agents might
Knees shaking
I need shaking for half an hour what did you tell yourself before you went on the first time
I'm doing this
Because
I think this is
What should be done
And
I
Like I'm coping with all the consequences it can bring with it
It was actually kind of the first moment
I
Really felt connection with would like my people you can say
The name of this new show
It even sounded like a
Journalist superhero
Show scope stop fake
It's a Roundup of all the false stories you might have missed that we
Welcome to stop fake
There's also an English version of the broadcast
Ballet dancer Sergei polunin is a not sending food riots in Russian
Included nasal septum
Sphincters stopped 18 woodtrace how false quotes were shared
From Outlet to outlet
Videos to show where the vial of fake blood might be hiding publish the story with this misleading headlines
I'm here many of the stories saying is poised to enact a new language law
Which will ban Russian and Russian speakers being persecuted in Ukraine only Ukrainian cafes and shops in it
Pending legislation on the Ukrainian language
To understand what was going on
On here it helps to think
Ukraine is kind of
2u grants
East and west
The East borders Russia got more Russian speakers
The West borders Europe
That's more Ukrainian speaker
And east and west different
Ethnicities there more like cultural group
But there has been friction in
The past
Responses it was easy for Russian news to insert itself into this divided they want
One part of
The country russian-speaking
To hate another bottle
The country ukrainian-speaking
Scented water to the pool shell
This was one of the stories on Russian tea
It reported that Ukrainian soldiers had
Seize the Russian speak
Toddler
Ritually stabbed him in the nail them to a plank of wood
A literal person
Evil tattoos in the mom in the closer mom will dish of it
It looked into the story
There were no other Witnesses
This crucifixion supposedly happened in front of the
Huge crowd
Stop fake also found
Extremely similar phrasing in the Facebook post of a Russian extremist
Published three days
Before the TV channel
Reported it
And a few months before that a very similar crucifixion scene playing out in a show that is very popular in Russia
Game of Thrones
That's it for this week
Doing fake news is bad for your health
Your brain
And a psychological climate of society
The first stop taking success beyond what responded even imagine
The debug stories were hit on social media and
And other news outlets picked up their stories
More than that
Stop pit crew volunteers felt like they were winning the war
The war
And then
The real working the situation in eastern Ukraine seems to be getting worse separatist malicious or rising up
And all kinds of Eastern City Line wasn't strong enough
Came under heavy attack to rejecting the government of Kiev
Declaring allegiance to Moscow
Getting help from Russia
This morning gunman in camouflage fatigues
Respondus watching his country split into
Wondering what did I miss
What more could he have done
The clue came one sleepless night after watching all this morning
Outback
One of the stories idiot
Debunked months before
It was a little story
Russian media claimed that thousands of ukrainians were fleeing over the border to Russia
This was back before the war started when
Ukraine with peaceful
Yeah so I called the federal migration service of Russia
He take the phone call. Big asked
The the person from from
Federal immigration service if it's true or not
Was it true that even though there was no war no violence in
Crane the thousands of people in the East were abandoning their homes for Refugee status in
She told me
No this is not true
We we have just
Several phone calls
Sender
Oh yeah we have nothing unusual
Thousands of ukrainians
We're not
Cleaning to Russia
Why would that right I mean
Ukraine is totally piece
Except respond did not hang up
He kept talking to this Russian official
And what she told him next he would not realize the significance of until months later
Months later when War
Had competition
And thousands of people were fleeing their home
It was
Several months later in the middle of the night when I remember that
Phone conversation Island
I went to my computer
And I
Cindy's conversation again and Bam it was
Kind of
Thunderstrike to my head
What she told him was that yes there were no refugees right now
But she told me that
We have received an order from Moscow to prepare places for refugees
So they will know refugees but they've starting preparation process for refugees
Responded that the news was not true actually
It just wasn't true yet yes sometimes they just preparing you
Four events that
Still
Not happen
This seemed like something a lot weirder
And a lot more dangerous
Before he known the fake news could Inspire fear and distrust
But now it seems
To be planting ideas in people's heads
And for her son this little moment on the phone with Russian official
It felt like he accidentally
I pulled back the curtain on the stage set
Before it was done
To know when I saw something
Russian television
I usually ask myself what might be their plan
Respond started to doubt the truth alone could win this war
Especially if today is fake news could become tomorrow's reality
When rough translation returns we're going to go east
To the place where the information War
And the real war
Meet
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editor
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to launch use the offer code NPR
To save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
When you drive out to the front lines in East
You have to leave early
How much the trip my car is the only one on the four-lane highway
Slow down just passed through each
Ukrainian Army checkpoint
If you imagine Texas which is about the same size as you
Imagine a piece of Texas pledge allegiance to Mexico and started trading in pesos
There is now a line that's
Dividing eastern Ukraine and on one side of that line are separatists
Who reject the government in Kiev
Get help from Moscow
This side of the line is controlled by Ukrainian government true
I am the 500 miles east of Kiev 500 miles from responds Picket Fences and his Lexington Ave
And I'm getting another house tour
A list of destroyed by the shelling this one from Alexander Ivanovic 864
He shows me where she'll fell on his doghouse dog died
Oh my gosh
Another hit tree we're only alive because
Straight he tells me
Alexander lives on the government side
2 miles from the front line
His sister lives in the separatists
And his father's grave is over there
The screen door open
Myrental Gregory
His wife nadezhda greatest me and my interpreter
She says nice to meet you
Aren't you afraid to come visit
I'm out here to follow up on that odd thing that respond told me
That how today's fake news
Me tell you what really happened tomorrow
It all the folks I'm eating a vehicle it feels like
Alexander the sky show me run as backyard is the most likely to have an answer
Because he is this town only newspaper seller
I met him earlier that morning in a market at the center of town
In his corrugated metal Shack filled with newspapers
It's a market where you see if locals mixing with soldiers and their green uniforms buying provisions
Army trucks are rolling by
Alexander Scott laffline all of his face including
Front of ears like sideburns
Everyone seems to know him
I'm just calling Uncle Sasha
They come here to ribbon with jokes
And to discuss the news discuss the news with people
Carne asada
Yes course
Wishing on Forgiatos nuts
Cochrane review
He says they very much want to know what's going on
How ukrainians live
That means a lot
You know we don't want to be cut off in the country
Which makes what he tells me next
So odd
He reads the news all the time but when he sees a journalist coming around
You get scared
Narcissistic
If the television crew show up that's when the shelling begin
I don't get it though what that means
The journal is coming in they start selling Li
Mass Effect 3 that's why our relationship with the Press is very
10cc
When he sees a TV crew
He says they try to leave immediately because
They start to Shell in exactly that place
Gregory
A little later different part of town
The two other guys waving me away as soon as I approached my interpreter
Let me introduce ourselves as journalist
Alex please
Don't come to the spot
I'm not I didn't do the Shelly
You can hear it I've still treating this like a joke
I just don't get
Then
A few minutes later when those guys have left I'm standing on the same street corner with my interpreter and son
Sis you know you know everybody like strong Leviticus
Every time you arrived
Massage kind of dogs
Every town on the front lines will be will be a doctor because
When journalists arrived was a boss.
When journalists arrive the war starts
I couldn't put this out of my mind
Because it means the people here believe that this war is being fought mainly so that someone else can watch it on TV
Like a reality show War but with real bullets
And Alexander is one of the unwilling extras
Alexander even told me
We already know in advance it's a show
And we don't like it
There's actually an old Russian joke
In America you do X but in Russia
Xsu example in America
You can always find a party in Russia the party fight
In America
You break the law in Russia the law breaks you there's so many versions of this joke
Actually has a name
The Russian reversal
And listening to the people in a vehicle I felt like I'd walked into the middle of that joke
I came to see how people watched the news and they're telling me no here on the frontlines the news watches you
Back in Kiev
Unresponsive patio
Is chopping wood with this little acts like Ukrainian Village Meats
Suburban
Firing up the grill first family favorite Sunday meal cheeseburger
I want to ask Christian to make sense
But I'd heard in the front lines
About this being
Some kind of reality show War
But before I can even bring it up he wants to show me something
He leads me through living room
Is this kid playing on the floor
What is a separatist TV channel
On the screen is a guy in camouflage fatigues he's one of the Ukrainian separatists smooth
Cleared Independence
Tokyo
The press conference is actually taking place on the other side of that Frontline
But respond is not
Apparently interested in what that guy say
The channels on mute
He directs my attention down to the bottom of the screen where are the microphones are made on the podium
He's counting the Russian Mike's
When you see one or two mics
This a local
TV channels
It's okay
But when you see
10 Mikes from Russian TV Naruto
It means they're going to to do something
It is a shalling
Or
Some
Kind of events that might be Danger
See other people in a few can know that because when I came
They said we don't like you journalists cuz when you journalists come
It yeah
So I think local people
They have not
Is this correlation
There's this one
Really unnerving difference between his theory and the one that I heard out the front line
Respond
The Russian might say you have to watch out for
They're there to make Ukraine look bad
But for Alexander
It's the Ukrainian Mike's aiming to make Russia look like the bad guy
Which is
Improbable but almost impossible to fact-check
In the fog of War
The perception that it is true though is almost scary
Both respond and Alexander believe
The journalist are in
Foods with their government
Fighting the information War
Alongside
The real one
And if you believe that
You can just ignore any piece of news you don't agree with
Just chalk it up to enemy strategy
Back in Kiev respond decided that the Russian media
Was the
In fact checking with not going to save you
So
Then we realized that
We need to protect
Not just
Our profession but
To protect the whole country because it was
A question of survival for food for Ukraine
Empress and the only option left
What's the one that he'd once begged the Ukrainian government not to do
Censor the Russian news
I change my mind
Dramatically
I was hundred percent sure I was damn sure that we need to cut it right away
Stoptech handle
It's Archive of Russian propaganda techniques to the Ukrainian government
Which probably used it as evidence
If we
Did it
Earlier
I think
We might
Avoid
A lot of
Deaths
Rahsaan believes this band did stop the front line from moving further west
It prevented more Ukrainian cities from falling under separatist
Control
It also opened his mind
To the power center
Watching TV one day with the three-year-old
You're the host at this Russian kid show
Praising Vladimir Putin
For protecting Ukraine
Respond sent an angry tweet and that shows pulled off the air
And then also cut where Russian talk to us soap operas
A wildlife Channel hunting and fishing show
And respond to $10
I'm not sure if
We Hunted
Percent protected right now but at least we are
Moving
In these
In the right direction to protect ourselves
Ukraine
Then took this direction
Further
Ukrainian hacker group
Types of the government published a list of every journalist to cross that front-line to interview
Do people on the other side
Thousands of journalists were on this list
Pudding
International journalist from NPR
From The New York Times
The title of this list was simply
Scoundrels
Ukrainian lawmaker called them terrorists collaborators simply because they just gone over to the separatists out of the line
Interview people
Respond did not see any problem with the list
Why not
I think what they do is is useful
Publishing
Names
Email sender
Personal information of
Reporters
It might be okay
But labeling them
Enemies
It was
It was stupid
Wasn't worse than stupid though I mean
Seems
Pretty
Intimidating
Journalist
Yes
Naming them
Traitorous
That was
Knox
Right
Sometimes it's not very easy to
To tell
Be up to be just
Straightforward enter
Nutria
Yeah
We want this country
2xist
There are costs to fighting the information War
The obvious one of these start
To adopt the tactics of your enemy
Today's comedy or critic of Ukrainian government tagged a Kremlin agent Virginia term for someone who's an
Agent without actually getting money or direction from Russia they're called an unwitting agent
Crescendo talks about a different cost
Spending so much of his time fact-checking fakes
You got no time to write stories about Ukrainian two are making
Despite their differences
The sort of story that he imagined himself writing when he first moved to that house with the picket fence
Stories that Inspire other people
This
This inspires
This is true drone journalism
How to check somebody's lies into
Keep somebody accountable I cannot tell that
I'd be happy to do it all my life
Crate
I'm afraid that Russian distance 8 +
They do their best to
To make
Us enemies forever
And
At the end of the day it will be very difficult to see.
The table and talk like
Like France
Blah blah blah
You can listen to more episodes of rough translation on iTunes NPR one or wherever you get your podcast
We got a bunch of stories by the countries were going to Brazil we're going to go to Somalia we're going to a Syrian refugees
First date
And we're also going things to use AC to India that's right we take a look at what happens when a country tries to take some
Something that has been globalized
And take it back National
All the stories you can find an NPR. Org / rough translation
This episode was edited by Marianne McCune produced by Jess Jiang and this version was produced for Planet Money
Visalia
Thank you Lucian Kim NPR's Moscow bureau chief also Ukrainian journalist Natalia Griffin react and Anton skiba
And Peter pomerantsev Joanna schustek Megan Metzger tennis to call
Thanks for the Planet Money Team for editorial guidance also do olkowski Laura starceski Michael Mahan
Charles main fact-checking for this episode by Camille Solace and mastering by Andy
Rough translation is advised by Neil Carruth Alex goldmark matil theard and Anya grundmann
Original music composed by John Ellis
I'm Gregory Warner thanks for listening