Reporter Marianne McCune
Just got back from the border of Arkansas
And Missouri
I've been there before it is
Gorgeous
Really gorgeous
Field after
Fairfield can look like they go all the way out to the end of the Earth
It's so beautiful
But you were not there
Just lights
See you were there
Because
There was
A murder
Of a cotton and soybean farmer
And this was no random murder wasn't about a drug deal gone bad wasn't a bar fight
What About Love
Was about something people care about a lot in this region
Weeds
Nasty invasive weed
One weed in particular
It is called pigweed
Robert this thing isn't ugly
Horrible weed one plant can make more than a million Seas
This thing will choke your crops it'll spread to your neighbor's field
People are in a constant battle with
They rip it out of the ground they spread with harsh pesticides
Former technically herbicide herbicides are the kind of pesticide you use to kill weeds
Endless fight
With pigweed
Led to a real world
So set the scene for
Okay it's October 27th
A 55 year old farmer named Mike Wallace
Make a phone call
Weird
Three young man his family says he doesn't even know but who works on a farm that Mike has been having a problem with
The argument is about a pesticide that Mike thinks they're spraying
And it's a pesticide that maybe killing their pigweed
But it's also killing Mike's
Crops
To Mike Wallace and the young farmer decide to meet up
They get in their trucks
Drive to a County Road between their two field
Sir neutral ground for the both of them talking nobody knows
About what and then the younger man pulled a gun and shoot
Mike Wallace in the chair
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Robert Smith
Amber dermis
Not exactly what happened we pretty much know that or
Who did it someone has already been charged
Is prime
The mystery is why
Why would pick weed and pesticide
Turn Neighbors
So completely against
I went to Arkansas to find out
Talk to a lot of the friends and family of Mike Wallace
Spend time with the neighbors and ask the same question over and over again
What is going on here
Why would a man get murdered over pesticide Duster
Money
Money is it
Just a quick note
In this podcast will be using the word pesticides a lot
Pesticides include herbicides
Twitch kill weeds
As well as insecticides
Kill box
It's the broader term
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their own website
Lights using customizable Lake
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobile added
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online presence
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
All right
I am standing on Long dirt and gravel road
Line on either side by greenfield
Trees
And farm houses in the distance it is
Flat
The sky is blue
Only few white clouds
It is the quietest
Comus place you can imagine
And this is the spot where Mike Wallace was
Killed shot and killed
To really understand how an argument about weeds and pesticides could come to this
Points
911 call from the road between two farmers fields
I started with a visit to Mike Wallace
Is family about a half hour drive away I like your Wallace Farm sign it has been sold out shapes of
What they grow
Corn cotton
Christmas
Mike's Auto Care in and they're 33 year old son Bradley are of that Hardy farmer variety
Squinting their eyes against the Sun and wind while they keep their heads up and get their fields planted on their own without my
Well it's hard that we're pushing through it
In their Big Shed every tool is in place every machine well-cared-for
They just build the shop last year
Bradley designed it so little do we know that he's going to take over it
Beautiful
We go inside to Karen's office
To talk more about how in the world this war with pigweed
Led to Mike's
Death
The office is spare and so orderly
Just a few Family Photos above her desk
Mike with his
Square jaw buzz cut
Kennebec Christopher Reeves smile
Delena Fielding
Get it and drag it out to the end I mean he was just not going to leave the pig weight in the field
Mike was not an organic farmer or anything
He also used pesticides kill pigweed like most everyone around here
And in the 90s when the first genetically modified cotton seeds came on the market he planted those two
BOCES were engineered with a genetic trait
That protected them from a very powerful pesticide called
Roundup
And this was
Huge
For the First Time The Seas allowed Farmers to
To spray Roundup all over the cotton
Without killing the cotton itself
Imagine you see some of those pigweed plants invading
You can get out there and spray Roundup all over everything and the pigweed eyes
Well the cotton remains completely healthy
It was a dream
Hi
Harrison Bradley comes in to talk and their longtime adviser and friend Dave
Pierce and Dave jumps in to try to explain how Roundup
Fits into the confounding story of Mike's
Stop Roundup made a lot of people good Farmers he would kill everything in your field
That didn't have the trade-in
To protect it
It was a once-in-a-lifetime chemistry I mean we depended on it for years and years and we depended on too much
Too much because after a decade of spraying Roundup
Pigweed did its own genetic morphine
And became as immune to Roundup as those miraculous soybeans and Cotton Were
Spray as much Roundup if you want
The penguin
Did not care
Mother Nature's pretty shower
There were other pasta
One particularly powerful one cuz I can book
Still kill pigweed easily
So the big companies that make seeds and pesticides invented
A news
One that could survive die camba
Great
Except for one big problem
It's illegal to spray dye camp on your cotton and soybean
It's an old pesticide
And all pesticides can drift but they camba is especially prone to it
Wherever it lands
It will kill everything
Everything that isn't real
The big companies were working on a new version of the spray one that didn't drift
But it hadn't been approved yet
So the resistance e came out before you could buy the pesticide to go with it
Karen says her husband saw a right away where this
Along the way might knew that
Invincible people know that this seed
Could present a problem a problem because the old Zicam but was so tempting
The old formulation is cheap to use and I thought it would take care of the weed population and
Just would go ahead and do it anyway
As soon as those Farmers got their new seeds growing
Mike saw trouble in his
He could spot a problem pretty pretty rapidly and we knew that you know something wasn't just quite right
So hang on what it look like
The plant just curls up
Curls up in the leaves pucker and when it's bad
The plant dies
So Mike did what he always done in the situation he was
Just wanted to go out and try to talk through problems and Nash I can't believe
Medicine Bradley says this time it didn't seem to work
When Mike went to tell one neighbor
Hey you sprayed me
First time exotic dad went back out and looked and
Delta Dental
Alpha you can tell by the way he's in his field or dying
Calling back
Ignited again
So Mike called The Plant Board which is like the pesticide police
And let me just say spraying these kinds of pesticides is a serious Affair you have to have a license
Arkansas universities County offices give yearly refresher courses on the steps
Keep Farmers up
The date
I went to what they must have said read the label 15 times
And the label is like seven pages of complicated instructions
The label tells you when you can spray
What types of crops at what wind speeds even what kind of nozzle to use
What are the University of Arkansas guys I talked to Tom Barber told me if
Plant board
Suspect you did not follow the rules
They will come swab the tank that holds the pesticides Bell check your nozzle
Is hard to hide a lot
Oh so there is Avenue
So there is evidence you can
You know there's wife
To figure it out
So they're like we found a camera in your
Tank
Your crops are cotton there for you used I can loan you weren't suppose
And then they say so we're taking you to jail
Well I don't know if I took him to jail actually the farmer is called to a hearing usually months later
And if they find he did indeed spray illegally he is
Find when Mike filed his complaint with
Plant board
They called in a Missouri farmer who's got Fields next to Mike's
His name is on the transcript of the hearing so I drove over to his farm
Hello
The Masters Farm is just a little bit bigger than the Wallace
These are multimillion-dollar operations
But at the same time none of these Farmers look rich to my eyes
The Masters live in an old house
With a rickety screen door
They take out huge loans to buy the season the pesticides and
Farmers margins are thin and especially these last few years with cotton and soybean prices
I'm a Long Way From Home
Some Farm hands tell me Donald Masters at lunch and to watch out for the dogs
Bites
1 suggest
Carrying a piece of plastic pipe
When the sun Douglas arrive
Hi how are you
I'm good
Is 50's big beard wild hair
I asked him about
The plan towards visit to his farm and he says yep
They did figure out that he and his family spray dye Campbell when they weren't supposed to
If you get dye, you can smell it and taste it
I do
Taste like metal
In your mouth
You never mixed it
I haven't
Anyway Douglas said the plant board investigators were too late to actually find that I can buy in their tank
But they found plenty of other oven
Yeah everybody got in trouble
And did you know that you weren't supposed to be spraying it
You on a mission of y'all don't you actually really want to understand it what I want like is taking us.
Economics
And what what
What did that make you have duck if you would a spray dye camel a
To get rid of it
To get rid of these pigweed
Read ahead
How many of them Choppers we can bring in here by the truckload by the bus
Shoppers are people with hoes in most cases immigrant laborers who manually pull out the pickle
Over a hundred and they go bid on Phil's
They bid on feels to go chop
And you'll lose money
I mean
You lose money
When they do that
At this point
Douglas's dad gets back from lunch which they called dinner
He's got white hair eyes that look like they've been peering into the Sun for 70-plus years
And when he sees me he pays no attention just climbs up into a huge Red Machine
I head over
Can I come up and have to climb up 6
Steps to reach him
What is this machine called
Watch
What were you in
Tractors
I always want to call everything attractive but I'm never sure if I'm right
He takes a quick phone call and then we talk
Acme in a buddy seat
You know it's it it look like from the plant board record I saw in Arkansas that you were
Accused of bring that, when you weren't supposed to and
Other place Vine
And why'd you do that
While doing
Go I got weed you can't kill it away
Well he could have sprayed some other pesticides but
They were three times as expensive and not the best
And he was with these by cama tolerance
Donald told me when he bought the seeds
He thought he'd be able to buy the new improved I came and within months
And that didn't happen he just figured he
She could use the old I can buy without hurting anyone
It all
I have the machine that didn't drift
And what do you say to people who say the law is the law that you got to read the label and and do it like the labels
Your uncle drive over 60 miles an hour
Starve 35 La play but I bet you do
All right I got to work
Duluth
All right
So much
The penalty for spraying illegally was not a lot more than a very expensive speeding ticket
A maximum fine of $1,000
And that made Mike Wallace and his family
As mad as anything
Back in their offices wife Karen and Dave Pierce can crunch the numbers in there
How much does a thousand dollars matter compared to the savings that people are getting by sprained I can buy
You dealing with
Multimillion-dollar operations you know I mean just the
Harborside
Alone you know that could be saving 25-30 $40,000
So $1,000 didn't really mean that much when they're saving 14 $50,000 they go down in the
Walkaway
That first year that the dykema tolerant cotton seeds were out Farmers across Arkansas Missouri and Tennessee
Found their own plant dying because their neighbors were spraying die camba
Mike Wallace did not want
Switch to the new cotton seeds himself
They were more expensive and he liked what he had
But Karen says they switched anyway
Even though they still couldn't spray that I can buy pesos
We felt like we had to protect ourselves we plan it all
That can't be cotton just to keep from having the drift on it and the damage
But the following year another genetically-modified seed came out this time of soybean seed
I could survive die camba
So now they're words I can't be tolerant cotton and soybeans on the market
But still no updated and legal version of dye canvas spray to go along
Tom Barber says his phone started ringing off
Off the hook about cupping and curling leaves
They started calling in June and we started getting pictures of da Gama symptoms on sensitive celebrities
And what kind of level damage were you seeing results of ear and we saw
Minimal
I may not do you know if you would mean like 50% of somebody's crops or something
Ride
What yeah
Mike was pissed
He'd switch to dicamba resistant cotton
But now he's soybeans for dying
There were so many complaints of damage from drift that summer of 2016 that the
The federal government stepped in to investigate
More than 100 thousand acres damage
Millions of dollars
And Mike Wallace was speaking out
He was pushing the state to raise fine
You've been talking about mounting a lawsuit
Suit against his neighbors
He was quoted in the Wall Street Journal
Makes complaints that summer had gotten another big farmer into trouble with
What the plant board
Documents show the farmer was contesting it refusing to give over his pesticide records
And carrots is the farmer called Mike
Point upset
And then one day months later for reasons Mike's family members say they cannot figure out
Mike got a phone number for a young employee of that farm
I called him
As crop year was over
Our Harvest was done he was he was moving dirt
And you know just
From hearing
What others have said you know there was a conversation between me and my husband
And Mack
Just want to talk to him about it that day a little before 5 on a
October 27th
The two men drove their cars to that quiet County Road
Between the two Farms
Got out
Started to talk
Farmers always have
And things
Got out of control
We have continuing coverage tonight after a man in Mississippi county was arrested after reportedly shoe
And killing another man Mike was unarmed
The other man was a 26 year old named Alan Curtis Jones
There was one witness Jones's cousin had come along
And according to the Sheriff's press release
Mike Wallace grabbed
Curtis Jones by the arm
Jones pull away from him
Drew his gun
And quote
Shot Wallace until the gun with
According to sheriff Dale cook the shooting happened after the two got into an argument
Preliminary information it was
About this doc hammer drill
The sheriff's press release says the cousin Presta shirt onto one of Mike's wounds and told Jones to call 911
The 911 call log says Jones told the operator that he shot Mike in the chest
After Mike had quote attack
By the time police arrived Mike was dead
There is a lot that remains a mystery
Like why did Mike call Curtis Jones and what did they say
Harvest
Is over
Over in arbyrd Missouri where Curtis Jones is from people can't believe it happened
Farmers like Donald Masters that guy I met on a big red tractor
He says he watched Jones grow up
Oh
Well I don't know the boy shot him in the guy that got shot
They said cars were just scared
I can't believe you get those
Buddy Charters had a gun
Mike Mitchell
Have you seen him since
Yeah
Curtis Jones got out on bond the same night at the shooting
I like everyone else I talked to you was still confused about how a fight over drifting pesticides could lead one
Farmer to kill another
I did go by the place Curtis Jones work
Mileage to from the master
Walked in
And there he was sitting behind the counter
I've seen lots of photos of
Hi my name is Mary and I'm looking
Curtis Jones
But when I said I was there to talk to
The Curtis Jones
Curtis Jones said
He wasn't there
Okay
Sure
We go back to Mike Wallace Farm after this short break
Support for Planet Money and the following message come from ishares
Because the best preparation for tomorrow
Is building for your future today
Ishares by BlackRock
Inspired to build
There are a lot of ways to think about why Mike Wallace died
You can certainly fault Curtis Jones at the very least for pulling a gun on an unarmed man
Some fault the state for not regulating all this more effective
Arkansas is now raising the fines for illegal spraying
A lot of people including the wallaces
Are furious at
Company that put out that camera tolerance
Seeds
Without being able to sell the new spray to go with it
That company is Monsanto
And they say
The new seed had a lot of benefits even without the right path
How to cite a spray on it
And they wanted to get into Farmers hands fast
Possible so they could work with
They also told Farmers not
To use the old I can buy
Monsanto is now
Prove to sell an updated version of Zicam at that is less likely to drift
So it's three times as expensive as the old one
And it's still restricted during growing season in Oregon
I don't blame Monsanto
I mean.
Tumi
That Tom Barber the researcher from University of Arkansas
You know that's almost blaming
A gun manufacturer for
Making the gun
You know I
You know people make decisions
One thing that people seem to agree on is that there is a hunger for
He's
Bees that farmers experienced during those magic years of Roundup Ready
When the pigweed could be conch
Barbara says people are hoping this new died, technology would be it
I wanted to believe that he was going to be as easy
As a Roundup
Which is not
But at night they wanted to believe it was going to be that easy
Barbara is pretty convinced it's never going to be that easy
Because as soon as everyone goes with this new Dai camera technology pigweed will play that trick
Mother Nature
You know we have a history
Of just
Hitting the next herbicide using it for 3 or 4 years
And then we can resist
I mean it's just makes sense if you just rely on one and one alone
You're going to develop resistant
Back at the Wallace Farm Karen and Bradley are waiting for a rain to pass so they can get
Cotton in the ground
Without mic
Karen Wallace says more than a thousand people showed up for her husband funeral at their Church
We want to tractors around the cemetery and there was probably
5220 tractors the people got there quick
He was very very good gif
Not everyone agreed with Mike Wallace
Some didn't like his
Finger pointing
But his friends and family saw him as a man who deeply believed Farmers should be in it together
But if someone needed help digging a ditch
Michael be there
Someone got
Sick during Harvest
He be out there harvesting for them
You know it'd be a perfect world we could all get along
But it's not
Enough
I just hope it to
Tumescence
Generation
Bedtime
That we can strive for that and dad that we can
Work together for the
The greater good
It all
And now you know I just helped
Is that group of young men
Can carry on this Legacy
The young man who shot Mike Wallace
Goes on trial later this year
He pleaded not guilty to First
Degree murder
Tell us what you think of the show you can email us at Planet Money at NPR.
Work for you can find us on Twitter or Facebook and we have kind of a weird favor
To ask if you are listeners
Have you ever found
Money
Cash money that the damaged in some way or maybe you've stashed some of your own money only to discover the train of mold
Insects of eating it
We want to hear about your story our email again is Planet Money at npr.org
Also if you're looking for some new stuff to listen to invisibilia
Is back
This season they're asking this
Did question
How is it that
Two people look at the exact same thing
And see something completely different
You can find it on the NPR one app or wherever you get your podcast
Today show with produced by Elizabeth kulas
Thanks to David Hundley
Robert Smith
Why are you here
I work over money guess what
I work for a show called
Planet Money
So that is absolutely why I'm here
I wasn't pretending I wasn't