Support for NPR and the following message come from service now making the world of work
Work better for people
Their cloud-based platform and solutions deliver digital workflow
Spell create great experiences and unlock productivity for your whole company
More at servicenow.com
Mr. pool can I ask you a question I've been bothering your daughter
What do you think about all this Georgetown stuff
Logo Ford
If he
Whole lot of people want to do the right thing ain't got another whole lot
They want money off the DNA
You don't want money
Why not
I got money
What about that are about no money
But not everyone agrees with Bernie old pool
His town and his family are divided
On last week's show we went to the town of maringouin Louisiana
About a year ago many residents of Marin Gwen learns that they're the descendants of 272 people
Slaves
Who were sold in 1838
Pay a debt
The debt was owed by Georgetown University
The Jesuit college in Washington DC
The Seal of the 272 slaves saved George
And when all this came out it raised a big question
What is Georgetown The Descendants
An easy answer is
The past is the past
Georgetown doesn't owe them anything
But consider this
Georgetown itself
Believes it owes a debt
Here's Georgetown President John degioia speaking last
Fault he's quoting a working group that Georgetown set up to examine its links to
Did slavery rights quote
We have also returned frequent
To the question
A reparation
While we acknowledge
That the moral debt
Of slaveholding in the sale of enslaved people
Can never be repaid
We are convinced that reparative Justice requires
A meaningful Financial committee
From the universe
Reparations
Georgetown will study the question
What do we owe
Now that's Georgetown in Washington DC
I went down there and went to talk to descendants
My very first stop was what you heard at the beginning of the show
The driveway of berneil pools little Brick House
I was surprised by how certain he was
But he doesn't want anything
Why not money is important right and your ancestors not even ancestors your
It would have been your great
Your great-grandfather
Who was enslaved
And was sold
Yeah you don't want them to pay then argued money over there and every time I spend out on Messi
I'm spinning my dead people money
I'm Noel King and today on planet
Money we're going to talk to descendants
About what they think they're old
About what they accept
I'm going to talk to people who spent their careers
Trying to figure out
Would eat meaningful Financial commitment might look like
In the face of a moral debt that
It cannot be repaid
We're going to talk about reparations
Let's take a moment to thank and share a message from her sponsor betterment
A smarter way to invest your money
Betterment creates and manages a personalized portfolio for you
Focusing on ease-of-use and lowering taxes
And here's what you might find refreshing
No jargon low fees and full transparency
For a limited time sign up for betterment and you may qualify for a free Canary home security system to help secure your home
Four terms and conditions visit betterment.com
Planet Money
My guide on American was a woman named Deborah till
LG's Mr Poole's daughter
It is a pleasure to meet you to miss Noel
I am excited we met outside her office in Baton Rouge
30 miles west America
Debra's in her mid-50s
T-shirt
She's wearing a bracelet that says
Any spunky little earrings
With skulls on them
Deborah and I had talked on the phone before I came down so I knew a couple
First
People in this little town don't all agree on what if anything Georgetown
Second they've been getting a lot of attention from Outsiders
And 3rd
Deborah is trying to have a sense of humor about all this so it's all I've known
We were a Slave
Now I got somebody telling me now I got to start using the term insulin
Well
Slave and slave didn't make the work no easy
Just like a whipping or whooping
It don't make a difference it still hurts
Okay
Difference of kind of person who likes making fun of a certain kind
Political correct
She wanted to take me to Marin Gardens monthly town hall meeting
So people would know why I was hanging around
You're a little late getting in so we stood in the back
Overalls
Emma meeting was typical
Water
Sewerage overgrown grass
The chief of police of irritated that people call him at home
Instead of calling the station when they have a problem
The mayor brings up that Maryland could really use an adult
Literacy Center
Endeavor starts typing something on her phone
And she pulls me in
And she shows it too
She Wrote
Maybe that's something that Georgetown
Count to pay for
This is a perfect illustration of how weird this whole thing is
A year ago there was no talk of Georgetown University paying for things and little maringouin Louisiana
People weren't hiring lawyers order
Discussing payment
They are now
Deborah says she doesn't want anything for herself
But she does want Georgetown to invest in Maryland
Even though she knows
There are no guarantees
All I can do is ask
And all I can do is say either yes or no
If you notice in at town hall meeting
The mayor and everybody around that Council
They all know about Georgetown didn't know about the money
The Mulino
The Town Council could easily writable a resolution or proposal
And submit it because most of those people that were sitting on their are descendants
At this point geologists have identified more than 4000 descendants
Some of them still live in manguin some have left
Many have never met
Debra told me that she has fam
Who disagree with her
They think she's letting Georgetown off the hook
So I asked her who
And she said I have a cousin out Nash
And she gave me a phone number
Hi there can you hear me
Yes we can hear you
That is Kathleen Payne will
Deborah's first cousin
She was expecting my call but
She asked me if I would talk to her mom first
Her mom grew up in Marin
So I said sure
Miss Teresa would you just say your name for me please
My name is
Teresa a
Poo
Pain
Theresa a pool pain is 84 years old
Imbiss Teresa can you tell me a little bit about
What life was like in Maryland when you were little girl
S60 $4,000 chords
Who influenced Chris Young
Get in Marin going
All I can remember is
We were
I pick cotton when I was a young girl
I cut
Sugarcane for a few dollars
Because that's all they paid us
My parents were poor
Yeah very poor
My dad
Never went to school
I asked her about Georgetown and the first she says
They don't owe me anything
Because I got out of Marin
That was not going to stay there
I don't care if the Kennedys
Wouldn't live there
But then again
She starts thinking back to those cotton
I can tell you one thing
Even now
I look at my legs
I have
Scratches
And now
Wart on my leg
I could get my daughter
Look at my legs right now
Until you
What kind of marks
I had on my leg
And I know
That was from working in the field
So careful what you look at my legs
Is that alright
Maurice's the panther
Didn't know you were doing this so you have on some
Haider pants
But
Yeah
Can you see those marks
Yassi
And then she says
Maybe they do owe me
Naomi
What they didn't pay me
And what they didn't pay my parents
Am I Daddy
Should not have had to work
Inside is he did
To send his
Children
Coco you know
And after that Theresa got tired and her daughter Kathleen got on the phone
Kathleen move back to Nashville recently to look after her mom
But before that she was a life insurance
She work for New York Life
Which
I don't know maybe that's why Kathleen is not that shy about talking about money
My mother
Pick cotton
Okay
How much is your mother
For my mother
I was saying
Give her a million dollars
$1000000
Give her a million dollar
Why a million by a million
You know it's just the easy number to deal with the million dollars by the time any type of taxes
If anything like that comes out it'll probably be 500,000 okay to be fair to Kathleen
She is pulling numbers out of thin air
It's not everyday that a strange woman calls your home asks you questions
Then demands that you do the math on what you're owed for slavery
Kathleen actually did this kind of math for a living
But it's different when you're talking about your own family
She has a daughter Anaya
Musicology
I would say
I would say for Nia
You could maybe bet on
Million-dollar
You could maybe bet on that
Where'd you get that number from y 10 or 11 million us a lot of money
I know it's it's a lot of money and you know I'm our ancestors kept Georgetown for being bankrupt
Georgetown with cease to have existed
If it weren't for those 272 people
Is it you could come to think of it as
Generational interest
Think of it that way
Generational entry
Actually people who do the math on this
See it in very similar terms
Well I was working on the story lots of people told me I needed to talk to a guy named Richard America
Richard America jr.
Richard America Jr is a retired Professor who taught economic development at Georgetown Business School
But people didn't send me his way because of George
Richard America is kind of a legend
In 1990 he edited a book called The Wealth of race
People I talked to kept citing this book
It's a collection of essays where a bunch of Economist and thinkers
Look at how to calculate the debts of slavery
For the whole country
And how to pay that national debt
The interesting thing about Richard is that unlike everyone else I spoke to
He does not get emotional talking about reparations
It's not an emotional issue for me it's a technical issue
It's about
How we manage the economy a black man in America why isn't it emotional
Can you teach an institution
What's not about that and that's one reason why the discussion has been kind of off in my opinion for the last three
50 years what do you mean
It's not
It's an accounting problem
It's a technocratic problem
It's
It's not about
Feelings
One way or the other
It's it's show me the money that's
That's all
I read Richard's book
Or at least I skimmed it
It's a very technical work
It's an economic text
It's full of charts and graphs and equations
It's about data not emotions
Richard didn't especially want to talk about the gu272
He said their descendants are a relatively small group
And this is a national issue
Affecting millions of people
This
Was part of a system
This is not some isolated incident
This is about 400 years and this is not just about slavery this is about
The gym Pro.
From the end of the Civil War up to 1965 roughly a hundred years
And the. Since that up to this moment
He's talking about a moment that includes
Wage discrimination housing discrimination vast differences in school funding
This is not 1838
This is 2017
But I was still really interested in 1838 any of those 272 people and in their descent
So I went to someone else
Did Thomas Kramer a professor in the department of public policy at the University of Connecticut
Thomas who spent some years trying
Calculate reparations for slavery
He's lived in the US for 17 years
But he's from a place that had to deal with its own great evil and paid its own reparation
Based on my German Heritage and our own experience with with reparations
I just got naturally interested in the topic
A few years after the end of World War II the German government paid around $820
In reparations to Israel
And at the time some of the fiercest opposition to those reparations
Came from inside is real
And from juice
They felt it was cheapening the memory of their of their loved ones
I saw a similar Dynamic among many of the
People in rural Louisiana who I spoke to where they said to me
You can't put a price on my ancestors life
And so I don't want anyting
He says if you are going to put a number on this stuff
You have to acknowledge that numbers are cold
They are not human they cannot replace a life
Or dignity
They don't make up for supper
So in this case he thinks of numbers not as lives
But as labor
Slavery was legal
That was stolen from
So he showed me quickly
How he do the math
And it is uncomfortable and it feels inhumane
And here is how you do it
The average age of the Georgetown slaves when they were sold in 1838 was 24
Thomas got that from the bill of sale
That means they were on average born in 1814
You assume they worked twenty-four hours a day that is the definition of enslavement you don't pick your hours according to my
My records here in 1814 the hourly
Average wage was $0.05
So he multiplies $0.05
X 24 hours a day
X 365 days a year
For that year 1814 I get $121,304.28
Biscuitville 272 people would have learned about
$120,000 that year it even paid for their
Okay
Where do we go from there
And then I
Repeat this for 18 15 18 16 18 17 18 19 and so on until
38 38 when these men women and children were sold
And each time I'm compounding
What was not paid so that's always the previous year years amount
A+ the current Year's amount and by 1838 I I'm at
Let me read this
3000923
$1,383 + 72
3923380 $3.72
That is the amount of
Labor that is the amount of money this group of 272 would have learned
Between 1814 when on average they were born and 1838 when they were so
4 million dollars
In 1838 dollars that these people weren't pay
Let's just for the years that they worked for the Maryland Jesuits and for George
And Thomas has baked in a 1.8% interest rate to reflect the rate of inflation over the country test
And then from there I'm basically just compounding it up at the same interest rate all the way to two
For this entire group of 2in
We're sitting there and Thomas is fiddling around with boxes on his Excel spreadsheet and it's an awful feeling
But we set out to find a number and he has come up with a number
89 million
$13
+ 47
Okay 99034000 $13.40
Is the amount that these 272 people
Would have earned
If they had been paid for their
Right if it was paid today
Does 99 million dollars
99 million dollars just about does that strike you as Fair
Well let's let's
Calculated to the individual descendant nondividing that amount by
3800 individuals that have so far being
Identified and I arrive at
$26,061.58
Descendants
But then he changes the interest rate just slightly to 3%
Let's see
Now I get
And
Estimated dead in 2017
That is
914051344.
Hours and 49 cents
900 did we go from
Yes wow
Winchester from 99 million to 940 million
Is all theoretical math
And you could say
And some of you will then it's wrong to do this kind of math
Be doing this kind of cold calculation on people's lives
Was what got us in trouble in the first
But Thomas has consider what these numbers mean
That's a billion dollars in today's money
Not paid to these 272 pill
A billion dollars not passed down through their families over time
A billion dollars of inheritance
It was never inherited
They couldn't go to pay for homes
Or for school fees or for doctors
If you were to take that billion and divided Among The Descendants
You be about $250,000 at
But
More descendants are being identified all the time
As a country we've been talking about reparations for slavery since the end of slavery
Carlton Waterhouse is a professor at Indiana University law school he is also a lawyer
He's working with a team of six other lawyers to represent some of the descendants of the 272
They're working pro bono
And he specializes in reparation
My work on reparations relates mostly to scholarship I wrote my dissertation about it for my PhD degree
And then I've also written a number of articles about it as well
He says his clients aren't making money a priority
They're interested in things like memorials to their ancestor
And Museum exhibits in their honor
As a legal case reparations for slavery are really hard
If you want to sue you have to have stand
You have to prove you've been harm
And the people were talking about have been dead for a very long time
Carlton told me a story about how we dealt with reparations in the past
I mean
This is going to sound a little strange but you have to have to go with
After slavery end
After slavery ended there were plenty of people alive who been enslaved
In the 1890s there was a woman in Nashville
A very determined freed slave name
Cali house
Okay so Cali house
Begins to organize for slave pension
Which is basically to provide a pension
For all the people who were enslaved
And worked
And now
You know I live in LA
People sleep
People still alive after slavery
Yeah yeah yeah this is right after slavery
Kelly hausbarn storms across the South
Visiting black churches and lodges
Drumming up support
Keep on singing national ex-slave Mutual relief Bounty and pension Association
And within a couple of years
She has hundreds of thousands of members
And Kelly has his movement had some unexpected supporters
The idea of slave pension scheme from a white legislator in Nebraska
Because the South's economy was in Ruins no one had any money
And he figured you give freed slaves pensions you help the whole southern economy
Kelly stayed in touch with her members through mail through the US Postal Service
And the way this all ended
Not
Inventions
She was arrest
For engaging in mail fraud
For suggesting that they could in anyway pot that could anyway it ever possibly
How did they get her on mail fraud
Because she sent out a basically a flyer
Two people saying come with us campaign to help you know
Get this
Slave pension fund
Here's what happened her Association charged a small dues fee to support their push for pension
The Postal Service said
Those pensions are never going to happen
And by promising people they will and collecting dues
You're defrauding
She spent a year in prison
It is as though as a country
We've always treated reparations
Like a fairy
But it dangerous
Some descendants told me
They don't even like to use the word
I had more than one conversation where someone started
But then stopped
But that doesn't mean they're not thinking about
Hi I'm Joe Stewart
I live in the Battle Cry
Creek Michigan
How old are you
I'm 74
And where are you from
I'm from maringouin Louisiana
You might remember Joe from our last episode he's the gentleman who got up and Stood Beside georgetown's president at this big
Informal meeting
And told him the descendants don't feel listened to
You got to hear from us
If reconciliation is going to take
Play says it
And it has
It needs to start
At home and you don't
Start reconciling bael
Jill has gotten idea
Did nothing to do with individual payouts
A foundation of foundation that has the potential
Just been stained for generations to come in look like
The foundation would be based on a truck
The billion dollars
Initial trust fund
What wait hold on hold on
A billion dollars
About that billion dollars
You might hear that and think as I did
What
Well Joe Stewart from Maryland Louisiana
Knows of which he speaks
For 14 years he was a trustee of the nine billion dollar Kellogg Foundation
During his tenure that Foundation doled out hundreds of millions of dollars in Grants every year
Jose met with just about every president dating back
Carter through Kellogg
He was in South Africa in the 80s
Helping to negotiate the end of Apartheid
And probably because of all that experienced many of The Descendants
Have signed on with Joe
They're pushing for that billion dollars of seed money
Enough money to sustain educational initiative
Send business initiatives for The Descendants
So where will the money come from
Joseph
At least 700 million of it
Will come from George
But
Not
Just George
Because Joe pointed out something that I think a lot of people
Keep forgetting
Those 272 people were sold to save Georgetown from dead yes
But they were owned
By the Jesuits
An order within the Catholic Church
Angela mentioned
The Catholic Church makes Georgetown look
Puny
I've been cap
All my life I think
One of the richest
Religions are institutions on the face of the Earth
Ha
You know my question is simple
Do you understand the damage that was done in 1838
When you considered
People
Chattel
And so Joe plans to negotiate
Not just with Georgetown but with the Jesuit
This isn't going to die
And go away
And I say
Georgetown
I think the Judge
And I think the Catholic Church
Understand
That this is
It's not going away
And they eventually going to have to
How to deal with it
I asked the Maryland Jesuits and they said yes
They are talking to Joe and representatives of
His group
They wouldn't say much more except that
It's early
At the end of all this I called Deborah Tilson in Louisiana back
I'd spent so much time with her
And I wanted to ask her how we gone
From a little adult Literacy Center in Marin Gwynn
To a billion-dollar ask
I wanted to know why talking about money makes her
So ambivalent
But it doesn't for others
Who live so far away
And ever said to me
I want you to think about what happened
If Georgetown
Here I am
I'm getting along
With some of the same people that own on my family and stuff
With some people that owns your face
Yeah and then now you know Georgetown
Is giving me this
Check you know cuz they want to make amends and all of that
But then
What about
The ones who
Purchase me
You know
I would be
Sitting there like saying what okay I'll let Georgetown office
Uniform it would be like without but
What about
You know they had your family
And they will beat them and doing everything
So
Now do I go over and I asked him to hey look Georgetown page
But what about you owning me
And these wouldn't be people far away in Washington DC
She says
American black people and white people live with their past everyday
They shop together they eat together to go to church together
Deborah says
It's fine not
Saying something
By not asking for something
If they can continue to live side-by-side
And it is also by not saying something
That we allow this massive debt
To keep accruing exponential
After 3 days in Marin
I'm really had trouble leaving
All I need you to do
Just get on the highway and go back East toward Baton Rouge
We're going around in a town like Marin
You can really see
How history stretches into the present
And there was a thing that I'd heard from people who study reparations for slavery
They say the hard part about all of this
Isn't that history is so far away
The hard part is that history is just so
Close
Support for this podcast and the
The following message come from Pitney Bowes providing technology that helps retailers turn Us online business
Today our Global e-commerce Solutions enable retailers to sell online
I'm in 220 countries and territories
Pitney Bowes the Craftsmen of Commerce
Visit pitney-bowes. Com Craftsman we'd love to hear your
Thoughts on today's episode email us Planet Money NPR. Org
Or you can find us on Twitter or Facebook
Today Show was produced by Alex goldmark and Sally Helm thank you guys
Bryant or editor
We should start by saying thank you to Georgetown for their help with these two episodes they did speak to us for the first episode
But weren't available to comment for the second Richard Shalini for you heard in our previous episode
Runs to Georgetown memory project that's an independent nonprofit that was created to identify descendants of the
Georgetown University 272
If you think you might be a descendant get in touch with them there at Georgetown memory project.org and ignore
Warmest thanks to all of The Descendants both in and outside of Maryland who spent time with me for these two episodes
There are too many of you to think individually but thank you thank you all
One more thing NPR is working with the Knight Foundation to better understand how listeners like you spend time with Planet Money
Podcast
You can help us out by taking a short Anonymous survey
It's an NPR. Podcasting survey that's all one word
Dot-com
It won't take more than 10 minutes and we'd really appreciate it
NPR podcasting survey.com
I'm Noel King thanks for listening
We're closing today show with the music of Robert Pete Williams
He was a blues musician born in Zachary Louisiana about an hour's drive from arreguin
He settled in Maryland in 1900
68 and the song is
Thousand miles from nowhere
Jeremiah.