It was a big week for apology
And they all happen to come from one
Person
Richard Smith
I truly and deeply
Sorry for what happened
I deeply apologize steaks were made
Which again
I deeply apologize I apologize said that that is what happened
Okay moving on Richard Smith was testifying before Congress
Because he is
Uber CEO
Equifax
Inform this last month that
Basically all of us have been
The company announced that the information for almost 150 million Americans
Has been compromised and I know you've heard this sort of thing before with other hat
But this hack
Is different
Because for starters
You did not sign up for Equus
Which is one of the three major
Basically your entire life
They have been
Slurping up and
Storing
You're most
Personal information
Which means that Equifax
And maybe now the hackers
Know my social security
And my address
And the fact that I opened the Gap credit card in the fact that I missed
The payment last month in the fact that I only paid
$300 towards my Subaru Impreza instead of the 400 that I normally pay cuz I'm sure they know everything
150 million Americans looking over our shoulders for the rest of our lives worried about someone
Filing your tax forms
My personal nightmare is somebody walking into Home Depot opening up a credit card with my name on it grabbing a giant
Orange shopping cart
Filling it with
Drills and circular saws and shop vacs and getting 10% off the whole thing by 10%
At any rate
Bad
Which was pointed out to Richard Smith
Buy a lot of our elected
Talk about ham-handed responses this is simply unacceptable
White you should be held personally accountable
Am I last 13 seconds I'm going to speak to America
I don't to save for the hundred and forty-five
Million people
File a lawsuit otherwise
They're going to keep doing you what they've been doing it forever hello and welcome to Planet Money on Robertson
And I'm Kenny Malone
And this Equifax hack
Feels like a
Dystopian
Sci-fi future Wicked
Shadow hackers roaming through our data in the central location
The we didn't even sign up for
Feels like such a modern-day problem
I get this whole mess goes back
21 mon
A moment when two brothers in Brooklyn
Decided they were going to sell our private information to the world
And we were not going to be the customers
We were going to be the product
This happened a hundred and fifty
Years ago
And people were asking themselves the same questions we are asking ourselves now
Who owns
Your information
Who has a right to see that information
And is there any limit
On what someone is allowed to dig up on you
It is quite the story
Beloved after the break
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Did you come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities to help ensure a brighter future for America's Choice
More information is available at aecf. Org
Hey Nora this is Robert
Show us the way to the secret documents
We heard that one of the very first credit
Ever
Precursor this whole Equifax thing
Was in the archives here at the New York Pub
Book Library
North Lyons health
Portable storage
Show this to the famous
Rose reading room
APA Library
And research coordinator named Rebecca
Walks in
And gently hold
This little blue booklet out
I brought a pair of gloves I didn't know if we would need them to type in the Bible
Gloves with the Gutenberg you there
The front of this book says
Retail Mercantile agency
It looks like a
A phone book
Is a list of about 4000 people who live in Brooklyn back in the day
And then neck
To eat name
An address and then some old-timey job butchers
Druggist so many groceries
And there was a sailor of some sort with his name
Alyssa name
And sure enough next to each name is a letter
A letter grade
The tells us
Just how trustworthy
Captain Colin
So we flip to the front of the book
I'll look right here so this is the key and a means
The captain pays his debts
Right away
If they're going to be there with me
He always paid in cash
Letter C with mean perhaps
She didn't always pay its debts on time
And then there's one final code and it's an ampersand or like the
And it basically means
When I get to put this person's reading this book come talk to us there's some stuff you should probably know about this person
We had some questions about how the book
Worked in real life in Brooks
Glenn back in the day
Josh Lauer
He wrote a book
My book is called credit-worthy it history of consumer surveillance and financial identity in America
I did
Explain to us the credit in the early 1800s
It was not what we think of
Today
It wasn't credit cards or auto loans because
Delete those did not occur
What credit meant was
Tab at your town
So excited Robert Smith
You are a farmer
AT&T
What crops
Apple
Sir Robert goes to the grocery store to pick up
Whatever he need
Maybe you like
Butter
Some cigars
And Robert tells the grocer
Yeah
I don't have any money the Apple crop hasn't come in yet
And so I'm going to need you to send me some credit and I as a grocer I look at Robert
And I say
Oh mr. Smith will
I know your uncle and I've known your father and
Darn it if I don't trust the Smiths more than I trust myself
And he says
Take your butter take your cigars I know you'll come back next week and you'll settle and
And that system worked
For a long time but
After the Civil War people started moving around
Adding two cities especially Brooklyn New York
Give me a little sound effects from Brooklyn
How about this
Extra extra Read All About It
Population of Brooklyn booming
This created a problem
More Strangers for showing up the grocer
Restore looking to buy things on
And the grocer needed to answer a pretty simple question
Will this person pay me back
I know nothing about
Enter
The cells
Herman and Conrad sells
And they're missing a lot of evidence that survives about them and about who they are
Super purposes of the story we can imagine them however
We like
You know handlebar mustaches blue velvet vest
Monical's maybe pocket watches
Johnson
Kane
Yes yes the the cells is where mr. peanut
Net worth
Mr peanut
The sales Brothers
Where in Brooklyn in 1860
And he start going around
Butchers in
The druggist
Taylors
And saying
We're organizing a list of all customers
NRA
So it would be great your cobbler if you would let me look at your books and find out
Who's in there
Uses credit
Is back that credit
And that way if a stranger named Robert Smith
Walks into my store
I would just pull out the cells book
Yeah look right here Robert Smith
Plumber
1102 Lafayette Avenue
Bank
Put pants on Robert Smith model vetru that's snow
No
The one thing that struck us when we looked at
It's a little pamphlet if you can almost
Feel the cells trying to be a
Triple S
As humanly possible
Give the minimum amount of information
You're not
Judging people that slander
Put down the name the job
And a simple little Ray
It was almost
As if the cells knew that if they were going to create an industry where people's information was the product
But maybe like just maybe
You should be careful with that in
We should note it says confidential
Which means
Sitting here reading these names and these ratings this is the equivalent of an 1874 Equifax hack
18 something something and leaking everybody's credit rating
The cells idea was a huge success it was
Obviously good for retailers who could
Landmark Credit and
Sell more stuff
People who wanted to buy
People like my
Doppelganger from the 1800s Bob Smith
The plumber
She could get credit
Almost anywhere because it said in a little book that he always pay
His death
And
Frankly he could probably get a discount on the things he bought because he was not a real
These credit reports were such a big success that over the next century
Thousands
A credit bureaus were established
All over the
And like any competitive market
Replace these bureaus tried to have
The best product which
In this case means that
There was Market pressure for more and more
Yeah the self Brothers just give you a letter grade but imagine some other credit age
Nancy says well you know we have a bunch of
Personal information
About Robert Smith the plumber
Don't want to buy our book instead
And so
A lot of information
Ended up
In People's Credit files marital status
Marital status
Married men married men were considered less risky
Remain upstanding and pay their debts
Do I want to know medical condition if you could know something about that
Give a broken foot and can't work that be good to know might not pay back your debts
What about vices drinking gambling philandering absolutely
Overtime credit bureaus realize that
Southeast Asia as they were just useful for lenders
Insurance companies and
Employers might also like to see them
And so they kept growing and building their Consumer Report
Consumer sort of knew that
Mission was being collect
But the full extent of this collection
Came out in 1966
Because of an almost offhand comment in Washington DC
What happened was the Congress
Does holding a totally unrelated set of
The Bureau of Labor Statistics in the US Census Bureau work
Proposing
Computerised centralized
And the representatives were losing their mind
This was Big Brother this could not stand
So they helped urine and during one of those hearing
A computer expert
Testifying
And he was like
You guys are worried about collection and centralization of data
You do know that's already happening right
With the
Credit bureaus
In Congress was like
What
Weenie
New hearings right now let's do it
It actually took two years but let's do it
And the news coverage of the time
Could have come from this week
Weekend Washington another day of hearing on the behavior of the credit bureaus
Keep records on almost everyone
Nothing
A figurehead from
One of these
Credit attorney for the Reaper
Belk credit
Retail credit
What's one of the largest
Girls at the time
I'm in this next piece of tape has no relevant but just listen to how he talks
Cit
What came out was this
Pretty
Damning
Copy of
Someone's credit report
We have a copy of this because
It was filed during the
It's for a woman named Mary Wilson
And she was having trouble finding a job
She learned
Because of what the retail Credit Company
Put in this
It says here
That Mary is quote
Dominating
Peculiar
And worst of all
Quote neurotic
Or cicada
It does not say
Who said this about her maybe it was her neighbor or some
What you work with
For sure we know it was not a doctor diagnosing her a psychotic
It was essentially a p
The 1960 senators were outraged
At the retail Credit Company
But instead of apologizing the retail credit companies lawyer dug in his heels
Say is bandied around in these hearings result was a dirty word and it is
It was a dirty word because these hearings spawn the first major piece of legislation
Do finally regulate Credit Bureau
Call The Fair Credit Reporting Act
Of 1970
That law and some of the Amendments that they
That would come later
They would effectively stop credit bureaus
From collecting hearsay and rumor
Allow consumers to see their own credit files they would
How to fix errors
And to limit some of the reasons
The people could pull
Your consumer
The credit reporting industry change pretty quick
Computers made the data could be centralized and spread more easily
Which make you didn't need small Regional bureaus in every town to collect Aspen
Industry Consolidated Consolidated Consolidated until
Eventually there were only three big credit reporting
And Josh Lauer our credit historian
Since the retail Credit Company
Took such a beating
During these hearings
And in the years to come
But it decided to change its name
2 something
More equal sound
More
Fact-based equal and Stockbridge
They change their name
To Equifax
Welcome back from the break
A new name new round of congressional hearing
New ideas on how to fix the industry C
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Which come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities to help ensure a brighter future for America
Is children more information is available at aecf. Org
To bring us up to the present we know that Equifax got hacked
And we know it was much worse
Then what we did in the library
The sells Brothers Little Blue Book
And we should say here that
We reached out to Equifax and one of the major trade associations that represents them
They both declined
To be interviewed but
We still had questions about what we are supposed
To do now can you hear us
Consumer
The lawyer at the National Consumer Law Center
We've been telling everyone
Will listen to us freeze your credit report at all three credit bureaus
Equifax Experian and Transunion those are the big three credit bureaus and
A freeze basically means
But no one is allowed to
Pull my credit
Not unless I temporarily lift the
The freeze
For them that way if somebody tries to open a gap card with my stolen
Information
Gap would go and try to check my credit
But they wouldn't be allowed because
The fries and a gap application
Now here's the catch
And it depends on where you live but
This is something that credit bureaus
Typically charge you to do
Protect your own information to have to pay to temporarily lift or
Father freeze when you do want credit card do you have to pay again
The pressure on that
They're saying that they're going to remove their fees
Which seems like the very least they could do
But she says this is the moment where everyone who has had a beef
Over the last few decades
Credit reporting industry
Is trying to
To change whatever it is they think it's wrong
And there's a lot of
What people would like to see a higher accuracy standard
For the credit bureaus did like them
Easier for people
How to change errors in their reports
And it's also a call to limit who is allowed to
Use your credit report
To judge you
Chichi says this is true especially for employers with this sense that
The credit report is some sort of proxy for how responsible someone is
I think Robert Smith think
I think if I had a bad credit score Robert wisdom
I'm just looking across the table from him
Idlewood
Just pay the bills on time
It could have been because something bad happened to Kenny
All right yeah Robert Miss payments or default because they lose their job
They get
Sick
They get divorced if you know there's a death in the family
A lot of times bad credit is a result of bad luck
This seems to be served
Dancing around the
The Quarry issue
Why not just pass a law that says they can't have my credit information unless
I say yes that would certainly give
Consumers a measure of control
Now how effective that would be
I'm not sure because in order for you to get credit you probably end up having to agree to this
You never leave
They keep pulling you back in
Where the product where the asset
In other words we are not
And have never been
The customer
Tell me the story makes me think that like
The sellers Brothers in the 18 hundreds really did
Decide the direction of
The entire industry
Because you know they could have provided
Letters of credit
Two people like
Robert Smith the plumber back in the 1800
They could have provided little laminated if you could laminate
They could have provided a little framed letter that said this person is worthy of credit and that way the customer
Would keep control of their own information
But they decided not to do it that way they decided that the money was in the business has the businesses were willing to pay
So it ever since then you and me and
Regular consumers have had no sex
So
Let's all go freeze okra
Welcome
To the Equifax automated security freeze
This automated
System will allow you to play
Permanently remove a security Freeze from your Equifax credit file
From inside Equifax there like we need you to sound like iMovie
I got the toughest voice you have cuz we got to look up in these troubling times
Let us know what you thought of the program or email addresses Planet Money at npr.org
Vitus of Twitter and Facebook.
Today's Show with Bruce by Nick fountain
Planet Money supervising producer is Alex goldmark try first at Edison show
Thanks this week to Chris hoofnagle and
And James rule who spent a lot of time explaining the Fair Credit Reporting Act to me and special thanks
To the New York public
For letting us in
How much time do we have to still yellin the great reading room
You have
Great
I'm Kenny Malone
Thanks Melissa
It is a shrine
Palace
Vatican
Sistine Chapel two books