Support for NPR comes from investor.gov
Presenting this mess
When it comes to investing
We all have Quest
And investor.gov has answers
If you're free resource for tools
Tips and information about investing
Before you invest
Investor.gov
Ron Flores
Is overseas surveillance
At the Pechanga Casino in Southern California
And if that like calls a picture to your mind what the sky looks like slick back hair suit earpiece
Ron is not that guy
He's got a long black ponytail
Jeans to work
One for him he's got a tattoo of a medicine wheel the other the other form is a tattoo of a shield
Wood eagle feather
Ron's job is to make sure that people are not ripping off his
Casino and to do that he spends a lot of his time
In the casinos Situation Room
There's monitor wall there's monitors in front of the workers
And it's really dark room
But how many screens are we talk
Anywhere between
Some people are just flipping through the screens looking for bad dude doing bad thing
Correct
We wanted to talk to Ryan about the specific
Crew of Bad Dudes
That he dealt with back in 2014
That summer he started hearing this rumor
About this crew of Russian guys
Who would roll up
Find your favorite slot machine
Play it for a few hours and then walk out with thousands of dollars
Rumor had it they never lie
One day in July
Ron gets a
It's a friend of his who also works in the casino Security in
He said
Hey bro
You got the Russian guys landed in LAX
One of them has a
Reservation at a hotel Reddit
Street from you
So it looks like they're going to be at your place pretty soon
So when you get a call like that like what is your reaction
Let's get to work
First order of business
Keep an eye out
Ron's body sense of photographs of the Russian guy so they know who they're looking for
And shirt off
Ron gets a call from one of his age
He said we got him
He's here
By the time Ron gets
Situation Room they've got four cameras watching the skies every move
And that first run says
You didn't notice anything unusual
He was wearing a jacket and he had a satchel
Fingers jeans
Typical guy
Put money in the machine press some buttons to decide how much to bet
And then press another button
Spinning reels
If the reels lineup in a winning combination
The aces or whatever the guy wins
If they line up in some random order he loses
It's not something that you should be able to be good at
But Ron is watching this guy and he's winning
Over and over and
Over
Imran starts to notice
2 weird things about how the guy is
Play
First the way he's betting
You replace small money
And then he would put in large amount of money
And then he would play Max bet
So he's like putting in like a penny a penny a penny and then all the sudden he's better than $5
Correct
And then
Then the machine would hit
Your pull the money out and then it would start
A penny a penny a penny a penny
Put in $100
Play Max
And then he would cash
As he was doing this over and over and over again and that's the that's typically not what
Patrons do
You sure he wasn't just really lucky
Positive
The second weird thing that Ron notices
The Russian guy keeps one of his hands buried in his bag
Yeah everytime he would put money in it
And he was spending
Hitting the back button and spinning the reels
His hand would be in a satchel
And then as soon as that was done in both hands
Would come out
And maybe get some more money and then
Start that process all over again
Ron is almost certain that this guy is cheating
The run is not a cop so it's not like he can go down on the casino floor and just arrest
Instead he calls up
California Department of Justice
Stephen says
Hey
I think I've got one of these Russian guys here you want to come down and pick him up
It takes three whole hours for the California doj guide to show up
The traffic but he finally get there
Just as the Russian guy is about to leave
With his thousands of dollars
Doj
Walks up behind him says amen
How you doing
Where
And the first thing is the doj reach didn't reached into his pocket because he didn't want any type of device to be wiped
Ron what were you thinking at that moment
I think
Expletive yeah
You know what we got him
Do you literally in your mind are you just saying expletive gallon exciting things have
I do
I don't I don't curse so I just say expletive yeah
But
The trouble is Ron Flores and the doj agent
Basically have no idea how the Russian guy is winning so much money
Or if he's even actually cheating
Winning money at a slot machine
And being rushed
Turned out not to be
Quite enough evidence
The charge the guy with a crime
The doj agent
Behold the guy for as long as you can
But then he has to let him go
The guy get on the next plane to Russia
Leave the country
This guy's gone
Expletive.
Hello and welcome to Planet Money time Keith Romer and I'm bouncing a slot machine is supposed to work on
Enchant luck
But the way of slot machine decides who wins and who loses is not completely random nose
Russians with their hands buried in their bags
They had figured out a way to take advantage of the difference between real honest-to-goodness luck
And what is actually happening inside those slot machine
Play on the show a crime caper
Wrapped in hardcore computer science wrapped in layers and layers of hundred dollar bills
We'd like to say a quick thank you and share a message from one of our sponsors state
State Farm is much more than just an insurance company
They're also committed to making a positive impact in the communities they serve
One way is through neighborhood of good a program connecting people who want to make a difference with causes looking for
For local volunteers discover over 31,000 social causes listed at neighborhood of good.com
And start turning the power of caring into the act of doing
State Farm
Here to help life go right Nick
First heard about this story when you sent me an article from Wired Magazine
Buy a journalist named Brendan
Straight Outta
What was so interesting about the story was not just that somebody wanted to rip off
Because
Of course somebody wanted to rip off a
What was so
Interesting
Was how
Genuinely clever these guys way of ripping off a cat
Yeah when we talked to Ron Flores he said he had never seen
Anything like it
And he has seen
A lot of cheese
In the old days
The cheats were a lot less sophisticated
What is Rush
Well it went from Fast beating stringing
Monkey paw the light one
With fast beating you just put your quarters in the slot machine really fast and the Machine kazoo
Credit for more than you put in
Stringing slightly more advanced version of the same idea
Stringing is where they would put the coin on the string and they wouldn't and they would bounce it up and down it inside the slot
You could also mess with the way the machines paid out
Monkey monkey monkey pot is his flexible rod
You got a claw on the end of it and you slide the monkey pop-up the payout
The claw lifts up a little lever that supposed to be
Keep track of how many quarters the machine is spit out
Jackpot
Slot machine designer swap out that
Physical lever for an optical
Which brings the light one light wand
Which is basically just a tiny little flashlight on a wand that they can shove up the coin shoot to trick that new up
Okay So eventually we get
To the modern era of slot
Did you get rid of all the coin slot nonsense
And you replace the inside of the machine with
A computer
Today if you crack open a sloppy
It's basically like
Taking the top off your desktop
Which introduces this new way for cheaters to cheat
Popsicle Pete
Where you at drill hole into the machine
This one is maybe apocryphal but run Flora says once you drill that hole in the machine
You take a can of freon
You turn it upside down
Shooting in the hall and basically just freeze the computers brains in
Until it starts malfunctioning
Spitting out jackpot
Soaked in his mind
Ron has
This giant catalog
How old is she
Cheat a slot machine
But all those cheats involved physically tampering with a machine song
The Russian guy who got arrested at Pechanga
He didn't do that
Civic Center Ron has a theory about what's going on
It was something to do with the way that guy's hand was always hidden in his satchel
Something to do with his phone
And he was not alone in thinking
Yeah so many casinos
Across the country have been hit
That the FBI
The FBI does not like Russia
They do not
And when they had heard that one of these Russians have been caught
The immediately put a call out to California doj and said
Hey do you mind sending us those phone so we can take a look
Richard finneran is a federal prosecutor in Missouri
He says
That Russian guy in California he was not working alone this was a
Big R
I think our list of potential Associates is probably at one point is large is about 25 or 30 ft
Now it's against the law in most
States to use an electronic device
Ways to mess with the outcome
Of a slot machine
But if finneran can't figure out how the Russians are using their phone it's not like he's going to be able to win in
Dearest Jerry these guys are winning a lot at slot machines
Also there
Touching their cell phones while they're doing right it's not
The strongest
Bittern had some guesses about what was actually going
If a slot machine
Is just a computer
Then maybe these guys were using their phones to somehow
The programs on one of those
Which would explain why the Russians are always hitting the same slot machine
What is all the same make and model of slot machine game that we're producing these results
What was that make and model
That was the Aristocrat Mark 6 machine
Finneran has an FBI agent call out the Aristocrat the company that made the Mark 6
But Aristocrat says it finneran hacking Siri
It's not possible
We learned that the software this machines was basically too old
To be hot
There's no Wifi or Bluetooth or anything like that in the Mark 6
So there isn't even a way for the Russians phone to
Communicate
Put the slot machines computer
So if no one was physically tampering with
The machine
And no one was hacking it
It was basically only one other possibility
Someone had figured out how to predict
What the machine was going to do
Before it did it
Someone had to reverse-engineer the marks
We weren't even sure if this was actually
Ausable
So we call them an expert
His name is Leo raisin
And he teaches
Computer science at Boston University
Could you reverse engineer a slot machine
Me personally no but I could
Probably tell you you know you know a guy
I know a guy no
I know many students
We're really good at it
I know many many people in the industry for a really good at it
And if you put a team together and you pay them enough money
They would certainly be able to do
Leo says to understand why the Mark 6 was
Right Ferb reverse engineering
Think about what computers are good at
Record of a computer
Is
A processor that
Takes one instruction at a time at night
Add one in
Check the value of x 270
The more of these instructions you string together
The more complicated task UK
Move the cursor over a few spaces show some cherries on the screen
Land a probe on Mars
The one that predictable outcome
For predictable sequence of instruction
We wanted to do the same thing the same way every
We wanted to do the same thing the same way every time so that when we simulate the probe landing on Mars and then we send the floor plan
To Mars It Will
Do the same
Put the computer in a slot machine has a very different job
It's supposed to be
Opposite of pro
I mean think about it if you could predict what a slot machine was going to do ahead of time
You would just
BET right before you knew it was going to go Terry Terry Terry Terry Terry
And you would win a lot of money
Write a slot machine is supposed
To be random
But Leo says that
Hat being unpredictable
Creating Randy
That is really hard drive
Computers
It goes against their nature
In fact it is impossible
Free computer to generate
True randomness
It's all in it
Instead of a computer creates
What Leo calls
Pseudo rate
And here that works
It has some starting 929
No 2461 longer than both of those numbers and had number is called
Accede
And the computer that runs the seed through a bunch of
Really complicated math problems
Until it spits out a new number
Rinse repeat
The better your pseudo random number generator is
The harder it is
Predict what number it will spit out next
The very best ones even if you took
All the computers in the world it would take
Very long time to figure out
Pattern today they take longer to crack than a few lifetimes
Billions and billions
But not all pseudo random number generator
Hazard that
If the random number generator is bad
Then it could take you 10 observations and then you figure out the entire sea
Having a good pseudo random number generator instead of a bad one
Turned out to matter for a lot more than just
Slot machines
Joe
Every time you use your credit card on the internet
It is encrypted using something called and encryption
Which is just
It's like a long string of numbers and letters and symbols
It's gibberish
Matki tells whoever is receiving them
The computer on the other end how to translate what it's
To keep that
Kia secret from the bad guys you have to make it impossible to predict
If something is impossible to predict Leo says
Nothing is random pseudo random
Pseudo-random
The point is that without really sophisticated pseudo random number generators
We will be super vulnerable to bag
Luckyleo says
Computer scientist
Figured all this out decades
People who
How are in the
Photography community
Have known about this work since the 80s and have understood how to build Unbreakable
Pseudo random number generator
Raiders
But
A scientific research takes a long time to get disseminated
I'm interaction
Sol practice
Some companies
Took a while to catch up
Some
Slot machine
After the break
We learn the Russian Secret
Turned out beating slot machines
There's an app for that
Support for Planet Money and the following message come from ishares
Because the best preparation for tomorrow
Is building for your future today
Ishares by BlackRock
Inspired to build
Remember back at the beginning of the show there was that Russian guy who got arrested
Did Ron Flores
Casino in California
And then they released him and then he got on the next plane to Russia
It turns out that the Russian guy
Was not all that important
What was important
Where his phone
The Russian guy flees the country
But his phone's get sent to an FBI lab for like the phone version of an interrogator
They were all iPhones iPhone 5S
That's Richard finneran again
The prosecutor from before who ran the investigation in
Into the slot cheating
Veteran says
When they analyzed the phone
They find all the usual iPhone
But then there is one app that they have never seen
Shepherd
It sounds like a movie villain
Severn is not in the app store by the way
And when investigators start looking and its code
Define lots of
Clues that Severn probably has something to do with
Predicting a slot machine
There were Lan files that contain references to things that were taking place on the slot machine games
So
Phrases like strong seed
R&G threads done
So what the suspects would do is they would learn a series of swiping and tapping patterns
The correspondent
To the symbols they would see on the machine
Finneran actually emailed us a copy of
Have the key
Different swipes on the iPhone screen correspond to different symbols on the slot machine
Like Morse code
Nick are you ready for quiz yes okay. And then swipe right
Diamond
I swiped left twice
Cherry Mountain Lion swipe right then swipe down
I don't know if I know any other simple hit the crystal
Each time one of these Russian guys pushes the button to spend the reels on a slot machine
He enters on his phone whatever shows up on the screen
The screen shows
Lion Crystal King Lion Crystal
He swiped in that code on his phone and then all that information gets sent to a bunch of different servers in a bunch of different country
And we traced the connections
I'm all the way from Washington State
To London
And ultimately to a server in St Peter
Russia
Saint Petersburg Florida
Finneran thinks the folks back in St Petersburg have their own copy of an aristocrat Mark 6
Open it up
Figured out what kind of pseudo random number generator it was running
And then just watched it spit out numbers
Yeah that's how you would reverse engineer a pseudo random number generator slot machine
You just watch it for awhile record the stream of numbers that produces
Until you figure out the pad or your computer figures
Yeah your computer you're not smart enough
And then
Then you make an app
Tavern
The scary name when you say that
So the app
Feed all the data from all the spin
On the American side machine
Fees that back to a server in Russia
The computer in Russia analyze that data
And it's some point it starts to be able to predict
When a slot machine is about to pay out send a signal back to the cheaters phone back in the US
Says bet now
Eventually the FBI tracks
Two of them and on their list of suspects
To casino in Illinois
They let them in play Slots just long enough to incriminate themselves
And then they pop
Please search their hotel rooms arrest two more guys
Find a whole mess of phones
Load it up with the Severn app
And almost $70,000 in
Cash
One of the men is released for lack of evidence
The other three though are charged with conspiracy and Interstate and foreign travel in
In furtherance of unlawful Act
And then ultimately they all plead guilty and were sentenced to two years of Peace in prison
Finneran thinks they send a message
As far as he knows there have not been any cases of slot cheating like this in the US
Since the arrest in 20
The last year in Singapore police arrested a check man Filipino woman and 4 Russians for using their phone
Cheat at slots
Toledo raising the computer science Professor we talked to earlier
This is not a story about people breaking the law
This is a story about how companies don't always take responsibility for the security of the Technologies
Yeah the whole hacking angle
He doesn't buy it
I would not call these machines hacked
I would call them watched
Hack suggest that somebody
Change the machine
Did something to to make its Behavior not the way it's supposed to be but it's behaving exactly
You push the button that gives you a payout
You just need to know when to push the button to get a bigger fat
The Aristocrat Mark 6 comes in all these different flavor
You got star Drifter this one called Pelican Pete and you might think that when something like this happens all the Pelicans
Skip taken off of all the
We asked Ron Flores the casino surveillance guy from the top the show
Can we still play a Mark 6 at your Casino
Maybe
If I want to play Pelican Pete can I play it at Pechanga
That is a direct question and I liked it
However
Probably not going to answer
Well played Ron Flores well played
We should say we reached out to Aristocrat the company that manufactures the mark 6A declined a recorded interview
View but noted in a statement
That
While reports of cheats are rare this issue is a challenge for all manufacturers regulators
And operator
They also noted that around the world
There are currently more than
Hundred thousand Mark 6
Still in operation
Do you know how to hack a machine that has lots of money inside
Just write to me directly or you have any other story ideas
Please send us an email Planet Money at npr.org
Or we're on all social medias I'm at Nick fountain on Twitter real Keith Romer we want to thank today Bob Moncrief
Shane lashkari and Carrie Langan at the New Jersey Division of gaming enforcement also Willie Allison Dave Ackley
And Darren home if you want to read the article that inspired our whole story checkout Brendan korner's excellent article in wired
Today Show was produced by Sally help thank you Sally on Planet Money Alex goldmark is pure randomness
And Brian urstadt is are pseudo random numbers
And if you're looking for something else listen to check out wow in the world
It's a new podcast from one of our favorite podcasters Gyros he's a prolific podcaster
Now here's one for children for kids
Check it out at npr.org podcast or on the NPR one app I'm the fountain and I'm
Keith Romer thanks for listening