It was supposed to be a simple diplomatic trip
To some of the poorest countries in
The time for Action is now
We're not waiting anymore Nikki Haley the US ambassador to the United Nations
Went to talkative camp for refugee
People who'd been displaced by the Civil War in
South Sudan
And then this happened
The crowds of protesters were so angry and so big
And they would not be talked down
Enter the Ambassador had to be evacuated
And police with tear gas
Recalled into dispersed
Here's what they're so angry
South Sudan has four million people who
Cannot return to their home
Even though the Civil War in South Sudan is basically over
The fighting subsided
Peace has not come
All you have are these
Peace talks
The Dragon
Year after year
South Sudan in the United States have a very special relationship
South Sudan is a country
In large part because of support that it got from the United
Did States
When it decided to break off from Sudan which is its neighbor to the north
South Sudanese pussy
Become a country for years
And meanwhile here in the US
Celebrities kind of glommed onto this cause
Right now we're standing here on the border of Chad and Darfur
Lot of bad things are half
Over here right now
George Clooney went to South Sudan
And did this video diary with his
His father started in South Sudan
We are there a lot of refugees
Found a village called Jacques with over thousand displaced family
South Sudan finally became a country
Street in the summer of 2011
I'm sending good luck to all the South Sudanese and American money
Since that Independence Day
The US has put 5 billion dollars just in humanitarian Aid
Development and that is one big reason that Nikki Haley was in South Sudan
She in the Trump Administration
Have threatened to cut budgets
For UNP
They say
These long drawn-out conflict like the one in South
Sudan need to be resolved more quickly
Wait there just
But there's a different way of thinking about
The conflict going on South Sudan or what it'll take to finally end it
It took me
Years of going to South Sudan myself
To even see this thing
And the reason it took me so long to understand it is because I had to kind of
Rethink
What is money
Hello and welcome to Planet Money on Gregory Warner oil change
And vigor you taking a break from your own podcast rough translation to tell us
That's right on the rough translation podcast be looking to have the things we're talking about in United States
Are being talked about somewhere else in the world
Today I have a story about
Country that is out of War but still can't find peace
And what's that all has to do with this ancient form of currency
Support for this podcast
Send the following message come from Fidelity invest
Has a Fidelity wealth management client
You get a dedicated advisor
Here to help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes
And make clear recommendation
Games for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
Before we get to the war story
What's up with love
I met this guy Gabriel get caught in South Sudan
The custom-house fell in love
Open College in Nairobi Kenya the fellow student
And when they decide to get married her father's head
No way
Not until you pay me which is a very common thing in South Sudan is
Call the bride price
It's like a dowry
I actually worked in that of South Sudan for a couple years and I was always
Very impressed
With the system did you go to a lot of weddings
But the thing about that Dowry that Gabriel has to pay is he could not pay it in
When I'm Eddie I paid I hate cows that South Sudan accent sometimes swaps
Steve's 4fc shanghai
Paid couch
Can do you mind if I ask how many calls you paid
I paid that I will start to fade 85 cows
My wife is in Decatur
Her college education
Increases
Is the price
So the base price for a dowry would be
50 and 18 cows but if the bride is educated
You got a triple that
If she lives abroad as she in Gabriel do in Kenya
Then double that again
Discount because they're actually
In love
And
Total 85 cows that was worth in
2012 at 14000
Yeah we knew
It was right for me to pay that you know
Beta fire cause
But I have to comply
Gabriel does not have any cows
Self so
He hits up his family
What's with Dad
Uncle
Third cousin finally amasses
65 cows
20 short I have about another 20 that I need to clear in future
But fortunately his father-in-law accepted an IOU for the other 20 cows
And the wedding goes for
But that death
Gabriel definitely plans
It's going to take a few years but don't cows have babies
But then
Something happens it's going to change
Only Gabriel's life actually this whole cow system
Now to the world's youngest Nation
South Sudan
NPR Gregory Warner is in the South Sudan Capital Juba
And I graduate the fighting erupted in Juba little more than a week ago what is the situation like there now
Describe
Dairy Queen
So this is when I arrived South Sudan as a reporter
December of 2013
East Africa correspondent the time
And what had happened was
The president in
In the vice
Hated each other
And this fight between these two men triggered a much bigger fight
Gregory I was reporting from South Sudan 8 years before you were there
And the same rivalry was happening then two
Each of these men has his own little army his own militia
And they divided it along as
These divisions of gone back
Decades
With the difference now that when I was there South Sudan was its own country
Has its own government
Oil wealth and this
Scramble for power got a lot more
Deadly
Malicious
Attacking civilians from other ethnic group
Not only killing men
At the format now targeting women children small baby
People are fleeing and the police there ending up
Are these camps run by the United Nation Gabriel the college student takes me into one of these
Camps we've come to talk to villagers about
The war about the attract
The thing that they seem to
Want to talk most about
Is it
Rampaging militias also
Stole their cows
Lost cast
If you are Gabriel and answer talk against one man John gatchell
Ian guy for the grandfather and
Am I allowed to ask how many cows
You got stolen
Okay or okay
ET cast
At this point
A crowd of kids his
Powerless into the shade
The tent were talking
And
John guy Jaws telling me this terrifying story
How
Government
Militia attacked his village in the middle of the night
Burning everything to the ground
John
Hideout in a swamp
Actually shooting
At the swamp
John Escape
Antifreeze on foot
80 hundred miles
Ends up at the school and camp
Sometime after he arrived
What is UN Safe Haven
He's looking out the barbed wire fence
And he sees a herd of cows going by
In one of these County record
Hizbul
A white castrated bull with a beard
I'm so sorry this is a silly question from an American but how do you know that that
That white castrated bull with the beard with your castrated bull with the beard
My American let me see Hannah
John explains actually
He put all these markings
In the horns
Bell in the beard so he sure that
Insane
What is an alibi Studio teacher now
And tomorrow
Simi wedding at the world what would it come to your mind
I think I actually I think John would have an easier time
Can I recognize
In his bowl
Then
I might remember my
My t-shirt
Mostly because South Sudanese really care about
Are caps
Children aftercare
Sing songs to their favorite Bowl
People also just
Like to talk about cats
There's no way somebody would go for 10 minutes without mentioning your call
The color of a cow
This is Michelle Lloyd
A friend of Gabriel the Coliseum
We got married
Mission says the cows are not just used for
Dowry
Actually anytime you have a big purchase so if you want to buy a
House or
If you happen to murder some
A customary Court judge
When I send you
To jail
The sentence you to prison
He will order you to pay cows
You kill somebody and customary law Cortez
YouTube you fly 5 pregnant cows if you give less than that
People not accept you have to give a pregnant cow
Do you have gas
Maybe I have one or two
Looks away and give this nervous laugh and I realized
What did I just ask
It's like asking your bank account
Cows are like your bank account
It was actually makes a lot of sense in South
Sudan because the banks themselves are
Really unreliable
Are they go bankrupt there's big problems with currency inflation and the country is extremely rural
Very volatile climate Seoul
1 month
Strout
Flooding
And there's also
The war
Fighting
Cows have the advantage
You can run with them
Safety
You can also
Drink their milk
End
If you need a bit more protein
Machine says that you don't have to
To kill the cow
Is another option
Describe your knife
And punch
Zayn
The neck of a cow
That blood is cool
People can eat it
Instead of killing the whole cow into kind of a blood
Sausage
Which if you
Do you think about cows as a pet
Bank accounts then
If I can have living off the interest of your savings
Music app without dipping into
The principal
South Sudanese
Try really hard to not have
The kill their cows
They're valued so much
The Handle With Care
And you know I would
Able to call
What day is old or young
Represents a certain value
I don't kill them you kill them
If that is an important situation
It's not very easy to kill
So if you think about John guy Giles white castrated bull with the
That not only represents all of his wealth all of his savings
Little Zoe's ability to buy big things to make large purchases
His ability to get his sons married off
And now all of that is gone
And how do you imagine your future with Outkast
Ladron. May I see you in awhile
I can imagine I will lead a terrible life
And I was out to cause is like there's no lie
If he could get his atk's back or even just some of those cows and
If you could have peace or
Protection
From cattle Raiders
The future
He could walk out of this camp tomorrow
But if he doesn't have cows
She is going to be stuck in this un camp
For who-knows-how-long
For John there's a thin line between total dependency and self-reliance
After I left
The 10 talking to John Jay Chou
Gabriel wanted to show me the rest of this camp
I remember beginning of this war when these camps were nothing they were just
An air-filled and it's tearing strips of land no sanitation no shelter
And now it's been a couple of years into the war so these
Camps have been built up by
Did you an invite charitable organization
In fact there's literally
Tractors carving streets and building corrugated tin Shack just kind of a market going on
Sugar sugar and flour
Juice
And flip flops
People tell me they wouldn't need all this charity office International Aid
If they could just get their cows
So I start the Wonder
Where are those cows
Now where did they go to
2 in in the can't be here all these room
Some say that
River North
Tested a nor'easter
Ethiopia
And sold
Slaughter
They're gone for good
But
I found
Have not left the country have moved to areas where they usually don't move to this
Is Sylvester a my name is Sylvester
He has
Seen those cows first hit
Because
Actually the cattle Raiders
Ask him to come visit us and we talked with Mary
Is dealing with a
Totally different side
Massive cow.
Suddenly
All these stolen cows instead of being spread out
In different places around the
Each with its own little
In a patch of grass
Suddenly all the cows are
Clustered together in these massive
Cowherd in the same little area which is flowing
Heads and heads of animals coming
I did not record through
Daddy what is not flowing anymore
That's that's how dramatic it is
It's electric company also how sick
A lot of cows are
Hysen whole herd that are just
Emaciated
Drooling
With something of foot and mouth.
Because they are
Living in these overcrowded condition
Yeah you find diseases
Level switch you are not prepared for
Sylvester knows where the stolen cows are but
That doesn't mean you can return them to their owners
And right now the government and rebel forces are in the middle of yet another round
The peace talks
They're going to resume
In December but these peace talks
They're not talking about
They talking about stuff like power-sharing
And what is the timeline for election
Which ethnic group work
Control which minutes
And when I was talking to people
In the UN camps
Nobody thinks that they're going to get their cows back
Through these peace talks
They say that the
Politicians that are sitting around negotiating table are the very ones
Who stole their calves
But at the same time nobody thinks that there can be any real
No peace
Without cap
You tell them
Guys what would it take for us to have the consolation
Michelle Lloyd
The guy told me a lot about cow life in
South Sudan
He talks to people about what it will take to me
People look at you
What a way to clean siding
How can I man
With our two arms without two legs
Negotiate with somebody with two legs and two arms
No
He has cause we don't have calls
He buns are hot
Is Billy Miller hot
You know he keep my parents
Hispanics are not even sleeping in the air condition place
Two people are saying
You know when you talk about consideration it doesn't make sense you know you can order
Reconciliation after a brutal War
Is one of the hardest things there is
It's a really big part of South Sudan sister you know I was there a decade ago
Covering an entirely different conflict and an entirely different
Attempt at reconciliation
But one that looks
Remarkably similar
You know in the US was involved in the UN was involved all these Western Powers were involved
I will say one other ingredient that soften involved
Successful reconciliation
Is the sacrifice
Have a cat
There's songs about this
There's a famous peace agreement in 1999 which was
Accelerated with the sacrifice of a very beautiful
Ocala until
And when I was in
The UN Camp I was asking
People hate you remember this song I wanted to hear it
For myself
And finally this one Village Chiefs that forwarding
And he said well
I got a song
And we'll play that after
Take a break
Support also comes from fidelity
As a Fidelity Wealth Management
You get a dedicated advisor
To help grow and protect your way
Find ways to minimize the impact of tax
And make
Clear recommendations
For your full Financial
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
So I've been in this um camp and I've been asking people if they knew this song song about the peace
Famous song about killing one cow to make peace
And
Village Chiefs
Any sing me this song
Add contact to undp United Nations
Listen to the song I really should wait
Let's go back to
The United Nations
United Nation taxi to a specific un worker
Please help me go back home
The cows
Dinner in the sky
And there's no cows at home
So
Cows
Monotonous song
When you come to my location
That time.
I always love to hear from you what you think of this show what stories you want us to cover
So send us an email or Planet Money at npr.org
Or you can find us on Facebook or Twitter
Play show was produced by Jess Jiang
Yes special thanks to Naomi pendell at
The London School of Economics for many conversations about the
Economy hasn't tested anthem
Economy
There I said it
Spider-Man is editor is Bryant urstadt the supervising producer is Alex goldmark
And if you're looking for something else to listen to
Can I suggest Gregory show rough translation
It is a really wonderful podcast stories from correspondents around the world that give us a new
Perspective on things that are going on
I'm here in the US
Somehow manages to make the world bigger and smaller all at once
Highly recommend
Find it at
NPR. Org / rough translation
In Gregory Warner
And I'm Noel King thanks for listening
I love you very much you are beautiful girl
What you mean would love
You talk to you
That time that