Support for Planet Money
And the following message
Did come from Michigan Economic Development Corporation
Cy Michigan is attracting top talent and top businesses by searching Michigan pure opportunity
It is possible to spend an entire day in New York
And a pretty fun day
Eating and drinking
And hanging out
Only at places that are owned or run
By President Donald
In fact just this afternoon Noelle and I decided
To give $6
Donald Trump
Android the
The carousel he runs in Central Park
Which one you want which one
Tried on some clothing from the fine fine Trump collection
Beautiful ties
You should try the red one for this more presidential and I
Browse through the men's cologne
Success cologne by Trump
You can eat at the Trump Grill get that famous taco salad
Afterwards you can go to the Trump ice cream parlor we personally decided I different kind of dessert
The Sweet Sweet Sound of
The billionaire Martini at the Trump bar
None of this
Should come as a surprise to you we all know the Donald Trump owns a lot of stuff runs a lot of stuff
Profits off of a lot of people for his business
And you can feel uneasy about this it maybe
Unethical to be a sitting president make money off tourists
But isn't
Technically
But
Up above us in Trump
Tower there is an office being rented out by the Industrial and Commercial Bank of China
Which of the bank owned by the government
Which means
The Chinese government
Is paying rent to the president of the United States
And there was a group of lawyers who
Who says that
That is not lie
In fact they are suing the president
They say he's violating something called
The emoluments clause
A couple lines written into the Constitution
Actually have a special
Competition reading voice
No title of nobility shall be granted
By the United
A no person
Holding any office
Prophet tour
Trust under them shall
Without the consent of Congress except
Any present
Emoluments
Office
Or title of any kind
Whatever
For many King Prince reforms.
Emoluments means process
You can't profit from the office of the
And the reasoning behind this is
The president makes trade policy
He decides who are allies
Who are enemies are
We don't want him influenced by other countries
So these lawyers who filed suit
They want him to divest from his businesses
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Noel King and I'm Robert Smith
We're going to talk about this lawsuit and this strange
Work
Emoluments
It goes back to something the founders were trying to determine 250 years ago
How do you keep a US president independent
And what's his relationship be to other country
It is a story that can only be told
With singing diplomats
Corrupt Roman
And a lot of lawyers weed lights
To say a quick thank you and share a message from one of our sponsors State Farm over the entire course of your life
Things are changing whether you're buying your first car moving out on your own
Getting married
Having your first child or seeing your children move out on their own
Through it all
You can count on your State Farm agent for a wide range of solutions expertise and support
Local agent information is it statefarm.com
State Farm
Here to help life go right
Everyday it feels like we are entering new territory
What President Donald Trump
But from the very beginning of the United States of America the writers of
The Constitution
We're dealing with this exact question
How do you limit the influence of foreign on our elected officials
There was this
Really important test
It was a case that came up around the time they were writing the Constitution and it involves Benjamin
Who was Trump like in summer
Big personality.
Sonoran
When he walked into a room
He was the center
Of attention everyone was talking about Benjamin
Ben Franklin
What kind of guy are you
Write a Broadway musical
Call Mom
We have no tape of Benjamin Franklin but we have the next best thing
Clapping
Weird Broadway musical from the 1960s
Call Ben Franklin in Paris
It is no Hamilton
But it does help.
And the story is its October 1776
The United States is a brand new country the 13 colonies have just declared
And Benjamin Franklin is sent by the colonists on The Voice
Across the ocean
France to essentially be our ambassador
That's a terrible trip the weather is stormy the food is awful
And then
Finally
Brooklyn smoke
Cooking smoked
Franklin learns to speak
French grammar is
Terrible she falls in love with an extension
Widow madame helvetius
Any plays up the whole Self Made American Frontiersman thing
He wears a plain brown suit
Instead of a powdered wig which is what the french your way he wears a fur cat
I made this get it wrapped
From behind of a grizzly bear
Siri
Franklin had this penthouse
Love
And the French loved him
That is Zephyr
She's one of the lawyers suing present
Before that she was a book about
Corruption and the Cubs
The book starts with Ben Franklin and this
It's probably came up when he left France 9 years later
At the time there's a custom in much of you
When an Envoy goes home you give him a price
King Louis XVI gave Franklin age
Serious
Present
It was a portrait of himself
Peking
Illinois leasing consultant portrait that you hang up over your couch
This painting is
Tiny it's 2 and 1/2 by 2 in
Look at the size of those graduation photo
Wallet-size
445 paint
You fit in the picture the king is wearing
Powdered wig she's a fat red cheeks and blue eyes
Is freely flowered collar this kind of interesting to write you know who gives you a portrait of themselves
This is a show of a kind of deeply intimate relationship over the painting isn't a big deal
It is
The setting
The portrait is
Set in a frame of two concentric rings
Of diamond
Diamonds of
The highest water
Karina this is surf
Incredibly beautiful diamonds
Silence
Ben Franklin takes the portrait and the Diamonds back home
And Jefferson
Does people start whispering about it
They're like oh did you hear he got all these dope diamond
The king of France
I think about it the United States is a
Brand new country is in debt recovering from this
Devastating War
And everyone is
Terrified
They are now at the mercy of the world superpowers
Like
France
And here is there man in Paris Walton back in with something is
Worth more than
Just about anything else in the United States
So he asked the other sound
Can I keep these diamonds
MSA
It would probably be embarrassing if we made you return them
I'm so fine you can keep
But at the time they are ready Acosta
Didn't want to make this kind of thing happen
And so they write a clause in the Constitution
Institution making it very
You cannot accept gifts from a foreign leader
You cannot accept titles of nobility
And you can't take him all year
You can't make profits off of foreign government
Without
The permission of Congress
And I will be totally honest with you
I had seen this in new stories but until today I have never said
This word out loud
Emolument
Mario
And I imagine that even back when the Constitution was
Was written like this was not
A word you would use it
You would not go into a bar in meter
Your friends f
A hard day of Amalia wing
And say
Emoluments
Guys this is a fancy Latin word
But the guys who wrote the Constitution were really into all things Latin
And there's a reason for that
You know they were writing a constant
Nutrition in looking around at other countries to use as blueprints for the kind of country that they want
Virtuous and decent
And Democratic
But this is a world of monarch
Define the Republic like the one they wanted
You had to go all the way back to ancient Rome
The founders were
Really obsessed
With the late Roman Republic
This is historian Carl Richard he wrote Greeks and Romans bearing gifts about how Rome inspired the founding father
Yeah they copied wrong
They call the Senate the Senate like Rome
Repeat the eagle is the national bird fly Chrome
When I get in fights they write snippy letters back in
Can 4th and the ultimate digs
Is to call a guy
Cesar so Hamilton is writing that Jefferson is a
Caesar in Jefferson is writing the Hamilton is a Caesar
And they all pretty much agreed on both sides that Aaron Burr was he
Our Founders knew that roam
Eventually
I fell apart
And it was vital for them that they figure out what killed the Roman
And so they were sort of doing autopsies
Nissan ancient Roman Republic
To see what is it what killed
You know this model that we're basing things on
Corruption
That's what they decide is the big threat corruption
So when they're sitting in that room writing the Constitution yes they're talking about trade they're talkin about security but
Zephyr teachout says they keep coming back to
Corruption
The notebooks from the Constitutional Convention from
James Madison you'll see the word corrupt
Or corruption written in his
Longhand script 54 time
And yet
What I remember studying American history in high
It's cool I don't remember this
Coming up an awful lot
The Monuments
No presidents and other elected officials have been so paranoid that they might
To be in violation of it
Did they do everything they can to avoid it
In fact in the handful of times it does come up it sounds ridiculous
Martin van Buren was given a shawl
Buy a foreign government
Really I said
Another horse
And
A sword
And Van Buren says I I can't accept
It's part of a it's a fundamental law of our Republic
Or if presidents are other us officials do except gif
They do what the Clause says they got to do
They asked Congress for permission
It doesn't come up very often
But when President Obama was awarded the Nobel Peace
Peace Prize which
1.4 million-dollar check
He did ask the justice department
Can I keep
And they said yes
She could because it wasn't a government that gave him the
It was private money
And then Along Comes someone who can really
Test this part of the Constitution
President Donald
His entire being is prophet
He's a living in Monument
A president who ran on his
Is global business
I built a phenomenal business with
Incredible iconic acid
What Abby really truly great real estate business
That some of his profits
Duke
From foreign government
And that is what the lawsuit alleges
That money
Violate the emoluments
But here's where the confusion stop
No one's really pushed on this
No presidents been sued under the emoluments Clause until now
On the Monday after Trump was inaugurated
He didn't office about 70 hours
A team of lawyers files a suit says
You're violating the Constitution
That team includes
Zephyr teachout the law professor we heard from before we should also say
She's a Democrat
Who is running for office as a Democrat
It includes Richard painter
Who served as Chief ethics lawyer for George W bush
And Norm Eisen
Who was Obama's
Their lawsuits has Trump is profiting in forward
Let's do them number one rent
Like the Chinese government own bank paying rent
Trump Tower
So you have a government of China in a position to make
The president of our country richer or poorer
Through those lease
Negotiation
Number to foreign heads
State and foreign diplomats are
Staying at his hotels paying for hotel
Number three
Is television show The Apprentice
It is in countries like Britain and Vietnam
Where the television is state-owned
So at least
Indirectly
Foreign governments are paying Donald
And number for the Trump organization does a lot of business over
In places like turkey and India and Indonesia
Does real estate deals require permit
And permits can be hard
To get infected a lot of these countries the permit process is not exact
Ashley transparent
And this
Literally happened just
A couple days ago
The Chinese government granted
Preliminary approval for 38 trademarks linked
Two Donald Trump's name essentially giving him the right to
To use his name on things like
Spas
Massage parlors Gulf
Clubs hotels insurance
The list goes on and on this
Is worth something
The Donald Trump
And again there is no proof that any of this
His made the president act in an unethical way
Or a corrupt way or that there was any exchange of favors between him and try
That though is not
The point
The point is the Constitution doesn't even seem to want us
Have this
Discussion because it doesn't say in the Constitution you have to get something in return for an emolument it just says.
Take a mulligan
And this is the argument that
Zephyr and the team of lawyers want to make in court in a big question is
What is President Trump have to say about all this
I emailed the White House
I didn't hear back
But right before Trump took office he held a press conference
To address someone
He stood a table he was surrounded by piles and piles of manila folder
And he said look this is
I'm turning over Trump organization to my sons
Even though
He does still own ever
Andy introduces lawyer Sheri Dillon
And she got right to it
On emoluments and info
No one would have thought
When the Constitution was written
Not paying your hotel bill
What's an emolument
She said when the founding fathers said emoluments
They were thinking about profits you make
Because you're the president
Not profits you make
Because you're a businessman selling something of value that people want
Until when someone pays a hotel bill
They're not paying President Trump who was inaugurated in January
They're paying businessman Trump who's been in business for decades
They're actually paying his
Organization
Which employs thousands of people
But even so Trump's lawyer said at the press conference
We're going to throw all you haters and Bone
President-elect Trump has decided
We are announcing today
That he is going to voluntarily donate
All Prophets
From foreign government payments
Made to his hotel
The United States Treasury
This way
It is the American people
Who will profit
And that sounds good
But there is no Clause that says all profits made during one's time in office go to the treasure
It says
No
Prophets
Any present emolument office
What's the title of any kind,
Whatever whatever
Like you just like I don't know
It sounds bad whatever whatever you come up with
Now in order for this lawsuit to
The lawyers still have to get it in
In a lawsuit like this you have to have something called Stand
Standing means
You need to prove you're being hurt by these alleged violations
Constitute
So for instance
The Marriott Corp
Mary owns many hotels
DC area and they could say hey
All the diplomats want to stay at
Fancy Pants Trump Hotel man not staying at our hotel like they're actually materially hurt
Yes
Exactly
Except
It's not Marriott hotels that has filed a lawsuit
It's a bunch of lawyers
Forester field psychic
Moral and ethical pain not just that
They say they do have standing they say they are being hard
They belong to a government watchdog
Monitor government ethics
We can't monitor the government at this point because all of our time and energy is
Is being spent
Watching the President of the United States
We can't do our job
So we're being hurt
I am not a liar but I am going to say that that sounds like a bit of a stir
I talked to some lawyers for this story who agree with you
They say yeah this is borderline
But I also talked to a law professor who's not part of the
And he says
Winning it
Forcing the president to divest
That might not be
The point here
Maybe the point is to keep the heat on the president
Ben Franklin him ascend
Play to keep everyone talking about this
Get to let him know
We're going to be watching and as far as your business deals over Caesar concerned
The founding fathers
Have got their eyes on you
We have one more part of the story after the break
Whatever happened to Ben Franklin's diamonds
Support for Planet Money and the following message come from ishares
Because the best
Preparation for tomorrow
Is building for your future today
Ishares by BlackRock
Inspired to build
Tell Robert
When I started reporting this story I kept asking people
Whatever happened to the portrait and the Diamonds that King Louis XVI gave Benjamin Franklin
Because you wanted to describe it and tell p
What this thing is like and no one seemed to know where they had gone but
I finally found them
You found them I found them at the American philosophical Society museum in Philadelphia
Do they have a little tiny room for that little tiny portrait
No it is not on display
At this point only the portrait is left
When Ben Franklin died
He will the picture and the Diamonds to his daughter Sarah
Gesture for toothache
Please don't wear them in
Start a fancy jewelry trend
And please
Don't sell them
Selena when she did
Oh she totally saw them
She started crying them off and selling them some money to take a trip to France
Got your Ben Franklin wanted that
You know at the end of the musical Ben Franklin in Paris
I don't think this music will ever be performed
Okay
Franklin give the speech
And he says I wish I wouldn't die
I wish I could go to sleep
For 200 years
And then wake up
Stand once more on Pennsylvania lamb
And breathe the free air
I know in my heart somehow it will be free I know it
I know it even know
And I wonder
I wonder how I should find them then
Those Americans to whom the name American
Will not be new
Will they love Liberty
Been giving it out right in the crib for nothing
And will they know that if you are not free
You are so lost without open
And will they
This Harvest of ideas
Be willing to strive to preserve them
As we so willingly
Strove to platinum
If you hear term in the news that you would like
Asked to explain
Especially if we can dredge up musicals of the 60s
You should email us at Planet Money at npr.org
Or find us
On Facebook
Trisha was produced by Sally Helm our editor is Brian Kerr stats
We've a couple people who really helped us out with this episode
Jay Wexler is a
Professor at Boston University School of Law
He wrote a very funny book called The Odd clauses
Understanding the Constitution
To 10 of its most
Curious provisions
Thanks also to Seth Barrett Tillman
He's a lecturer at Maynooth University Department of Law
And thanks to Josh Katz
And we spent musical Ben Franklin Paris was written by
Sinew Michaels with music by Mark
Junior and Jerry
Now that you finished listening to Planet Money may we recommend another really great NPR show embedded
Embedded is back for a special
Three episode run Kelly mcevers
Just bring you
A really dramatic story about
We shooting and the videos of the
You can find that on NPR one or wherever you get your vodka
Robert Smith
And I know Elle King thanks for listening