Imagine you are a b
A honey and every morning you wake up in the greatest place
Honor Flight
Not so high you are
You are waking up
In rural Louisiana
You got your cypress trees
You got your flowering plants and legumes you you see your
Blue Vervain you see your buckwheat Vine you see your Tallow trees
That is the voice of your boss wescard
Well technically you work for the queen bee and she works for West but the job you have is pretty Kush
You're collecting nectar making honey
West takes your honey
Selzer honey
Your bike a team
But
Infected
One night while you were sleeping you hear it a forklift coming for your high
And all of the surrounding Heights
Hand
We start picking them up and moving around and set them on new pallets and
We are then come in with the machines and stack them onto the truck and
The Journey Begins
The journey
The truck will be taking you and 15 million of your closest
Friends
On a road trip
Louisiana Texas New Mexico Arizona
And California
2000 miles in all
To the Almond fields in the Central Valley where do you will have a new job
Pollinating
The almond flour
Making
Little almond babies
What would happen
If you didn't ship bees to California
If anybody didn't ship bees then you would see a lot of empty shelves
In the grocery stores
No Blueberries no almonds no
No strawberries no squash no pumpkins no I mean the list goes on no oranges no citrus
So the missions fees are on it to prevent
A fruit and nut epochal
Correct
You are Louisiana B and you
About to save the world
Or Beat It Anyway hello and welcome to Planet Money
Stacey Vanek Smith and Robert Smith right now almost every single commercial be
In the United States of America is on the way to the Almond fields of California
The size of this Mass migration is stunning in the span of a few weeks 30 billion bezoar
Will be shipped from around the country to the Central Valley
He will pollinate enough flowers create 700 billion almonds
Today on the show we are going to follow the beekeepers who is the co-op in logistical miracle
The birds and the bees and the flowers and the trees cannot do it alone we are going to need a lot of trucks
Support for this NPR Podcast in the following message come from Blue Apron
Blue Apron partners with sustainable Farms fisheries and ranchers to bring you all the ingredients you need
To create incredible home cooked meals
Ingredients compared with an easy-to-follow recipe card delivered to your door weekly in a refrigerated box
ReDiscover how fun cooking can be while enjoying specialty ingredients that exploring new flavors in cuisine
Get your first three Blue Apron meals free
Plus free shipping by visiting blueapron.com planet
This whole bee migration was something we did not know about until we got an email from a listener buck marcussen
He told us around Valentine's Day
If you drive through Central California
The highways are filled with honey bees
Trucks full of hungry angry
Honey bees billions of them being driven from all corners of the
Converging on the almond
Which
When you
Just seems
Insane
And we nominated you Robert Smith
To go check this out put on a
Bee suit
The whole journey started at least for me and my b
In Bunkie Louisiana
If you picture Louisiana as a boot
Bunky's right at
At the ankle bone
Good thing you drive along the Bayou
Flat open land
And then all of a sudden you see what looks like
1000 silver file cabinet
Just sitting out in the field
These are the beehives
Now they told me to get to the farm right at sunset
When Sky turns.
You only want to move bees
Welbeze always
Naturally return
To The Hive after
Sundown
If you try to move them before Sunday they wouldn't go to find their hot
Yes you leave a bunch of them hear loss
With nowhere to go
The Beekeeper West card he doesn't bother to wear a bee suit most
What's the time
That almost dares
The Beast is stinky
Elbows out his feet wide apart
You can actually see a few bees crawling in his long goatee
Actually I'd rather I'm getting stuck on the beer then staying in the chin so that's why I have a beard
Step back one more cuz this one's actually hitting the back of my head
They extract honey in a shed out in the back
The bee Wranglers all live in a Double Wide Trailer by the road
Anheuser zipping by on forklift
The only bee colonies with a thick blanket of bees
Get picked for the California
They want the strongest one
So West
Prize open the top
When I want to check
So you can see
That high
Has very few bees
Well looks like there's hundreds but
100 is not very many
So what happened with hot
That's a good question
These days and the bee business it is just a fact of life
Bees are dying at a higher rate
Then they used to
So West races to hives for everyone that the ship
You can have thousands of hives
Lined up
That just are not ready to go to California that are weak or dead
Or just not surviving for
Unknown reasons
And that's happened to you
Osher
I think it's happened every beekeeper at some point or another
But this year is a good year
They have a thousand Hive just for tonight rap stacked ready to go
Baby Wranglers add some yellow bee food in the top
Sack lunch
For the 3-day trip
And then what is fully dark
The tractor
Trailer pulse
Basin 24 truck of the California
Justin the last couple of weeks
Hundreds of wetherby farms are doing this
Same thing
All around the cut
Florida
South Carolina
Oregon from the
Dakotaz
Brother glad he's in charge of this whole loading process
You said listen like this is what
Beekeepers have done forever
I mean they've been moving bees around the country for
Decades you know when the 1800 they were moving them on the back of horses
So it's it's a natural kind of migratory thing for the bees
There's nothing natural about
What's not natural about it
It's the fact that you're putting
1000 Hive onto the back of a truck
Encinitas California
But this
That they are to perform a natural function
It's just we've we've made that function more efficient
That's one way to put it
Every almonds you have ever eaten required Abby
Single bee a bee to move the pollen from the
The flower of one on the tree to the flower of a different woman
And they're not bees in California to pollinate a small
Omicron
But over the last few decades almonds have just
Taking off
Almond milk
Almond butter
Low-carb almond snack packs
England cardi B guy says
The Almond Growers
Play Store
This whole thing coming
20 years ago
They started planning
Acres and Acres
Acres of almonds
Anticipating this demand increase in demand in
Has those Acres coming to
USA age they require more beehives
More beehives in the beekeepers of California could possibly provide
What's it going to hold me that when their grandfather started the biz
Dismiss back in Massachusetts
Of course
TCAP the bees
He's close to the crops that's what you did back
The interstate highway system was built it made sense to grow bees
You know where it was warm
I never left the flowering plant
It made sense to move the whole operation to Louisiana
And then all you need it
What's a lot of trucks
So true that you can put 15 million bees on the back of a truck in about 20 minutes
It's amazing
The steeple
Huge net
Over the Heights
And you can see the Beast inside
Pushing to get out
The lucky driver who gets to babysit these bad boys all the way to fireball California
Kermit Jones
Alright and it's going to Fireball
How you got
Covetous the hardest part
Of driving bees
Is the schedule
Because
If you stop the truck during the day while it is light out
The bees will try to escape and they're Wily they cancel to get to the Nets
So you have to
To keep the truck
Moving you have to keep the high Serta vibrating
Calm down
So Kermit drives for 11 hours
You know you get started early in the morning make sure you got your fuel
And everything and then you know you drive till it coming
Calm down a little bit
What you need to go to the bathroom
Couple cups or something like that
I was going to have to ride with you
Maybe not
Tomorrow night these bees will be sleeping somewhere to truck stop in Amarillo Texas Kingman Arizona is this
Stop the next night
Been too long Hall to the California border
An orchard and Fireball
And of course there was a whole other side to the story because out in California there is a fierce competition going on to get
The best bees
I need the entire success of an almond crop can really depend on the beach
He's better Trucking from halfway across the country
Do people in the Central Valley have been for
Preparing for months
What is big
Be converted
Convention
B con 2017
Yes it's like spring break for me
Taobao baby
Albert Furby
So I flew into San Francisco a day ahead of the
If I drove over the hills to the
Central Valley
And I was told I really need to talk to the person who knows everything and everyone
The be broke
She's easy to spot because
She's the one in the field
With the pink
Bee suit
It's a pale pink so the bees do like it
Not that I'm a fashionista but I just couldn't do the wife
And so this way people know it's me
Denise Qualls runs bee pollination
Connection
She hooks up beekeepers with almond grout
She's the one making the deals for our Louisiana be
On the way
Please header pink bee suit set up so she can take cell phone calls
On a headset from inside the bee suit
And people that actually never stop calling
Panic B drivers
Stop the California
Border inspections
A desperate almond Growers
So I've gotten pictures today of flooded Orchard
I've got a forklift
Stuck this morning
And my phone's ringing again let's see who that is
Someone is calling looking for some bees
So I need to give them a call
And find out what it is I can do for them
The Almond flowers are about to bloom so this is like
Crunch time
It's funny because ask annies
Chat on the phone
She also starts to like
Pry open the different
Bee hives in front of her
Because part of her job is also checking to make sure
That the bees survived
Oh man look at that one
Pretty
Yeah we're kind of being swarmed a little bit here but that's good that means they're super
Yes and they've been here for a few days so I'm
Pleasantly surprised with the activity
Wow
He has to check these days because nothing is
Normal in beekeeping anymore there's
This is problem with the bees called colony collapse disorder
The first noticed it in 2006 and then suddenly sometimes
Overnight
Like a hive with just dye
He would empty out
The bees would be gone and no one knew why
Why was out there with Denise Shane Ross
Who is Weber helpers he slipped into the bees in it
He says
Did she think
There is no one
Caught his pet theory is that it is all of them
It's the pesticides the herbicides the radio waves
Changing agriculture loss of bee habitat and and Bee forage leading to poor nutrition the bees
Starve to death in some areas there's just nothing for them to work
It's its death by a thousand paper cuts
Because it's like a mystery
He creates a real sense of distrust from The Beekeeper
To like
Love their hives
State obviously make a living out their hives and they just drop them off in these feel
And it's constantly asking will wait a minute are they being sprayed with pesticides
Are the farmers
Taking care of the bees
Well they imagine this is stressful for the Almond Growers to write any they might be worried that there aren't going to be bees anymore or that
There aren't going to be enough peas and the price might go way up
Yeah and it has a decade ago you can rent too high for a month
For about 50 bucks
Now it cost $185 for a single hive
For the season
And I can start to add up
This truck of bees that we are following is going to a single Orchard
And the rental charges for all the bees
Comes to around $100,000
But so far at least almond Growers don't have much of a choice
But to pay the bill.
So this is this is the tree
Is an almond tree
Deserve technical name you just called almond tree
There's two varieties Heroes.
Padres
This is Kyle Robertson
He isn't almond grower in Tracy California and over the next month
These trees will be pollinated
Bybee's from Louisiana
West cards be
Right now the two kinds of Truth abuse and Padres look totally barren
But by next week this Orchard will be
Transformed with flowers
So beautiful that Kyle took his engagement photos
Here is a one picture here
Whoa
It looks like the cherry blossoms in Washington DC
Gorgeous
White petals everywhere then you'll see white petals on the ground almost looks like
Snow
Snow covered tree with little bit of snow desktop
On the ground
The flowers are small that the size of a silver dollar and their
Delicate and the bee have to carry the pollen from
The Butte to Padre and the Padre to the Butte
Deposited just perfectly
To make a single almond
Alright so series of
A series of dumb question
Dog park
Why can't you just hire people
Take a pollen from One Tree and move it to the other
You can it's just going to take you forever to do it
Why not just get a plane filled with pollen and you could just send that address the synthetics
Look at but again it's it has
Chao
To be any better than
The natural pollination with bees
Why don't you just develop a tree that doesn't
Need a bead on it
You do if there's self pollinating trees that work there's called a variety called Independence in California
That's more popular one
You don't necessarily need bees to pollinate
And the self-pollinating tree is slowly catching on
But the almonds are not exactly what buyers are
They taste different
Difference
That does not sound like a raining indoors
Different is good
I kept trying to talk to Kyle about how
Strange
This whole be shipping situation is
Like I try and all these theories out on him you know is this the end of nature or
Maybe you just reached the limit of the amount of almond trees you can possibly plant
But he says like
I am talking
Like a news reporter from New York City
I don't understand
The way nature
You think Baron Baron the while collecting a beehive off the top of a tree and knocking it down to
Dita honey
People's image of it
That's exactly how they are this symbol of
Wild uncontrolled
Humanless nature
And so that's what feels weird when you put them on a truck and drive them mm
I can understand that
Cells that way
But then he says like remember
Lee's honey bees
We're not native
North America
They were brought over
And the almond trees
In which we grow here they came from the Middle East
The kid from Spain
There is nothing
Wild or human list
About any
Park
Of the almond
Situation it is produced on a mass scale for the lowest cost possible
And it really is massive
As I drive around the Central Valley I can go dozens of miles and see nothing but almonds
Almond trees almond trees after almond trees and then I get
Hey I'm just coming into Firebox Scar the Louisiana
Puppies have arrived.
Get me directions to an orchard and says meet me at Sunset and
I might want to wear a bee suit for this one
But we're going to want to walk a little bit further back here as we get ready to pull the screens
This is the moment
They're pulling the next off of the high remember the bees have not been able to fly
For 3
When the next come down they start to
Whirl
Around the truck it is like a funnel cloud
It rises above the field to get certified larger and larger
I know you love them but it kind of feels like we're in a horror film right now
Yeah there's a lot here
That sounds terrifying Robert
It was actually little terrified even in abuse
And what they're doing is
When a bee is in a new place
I was told
They are
Circling trying to sort of memorize the new landscape the trying to figure out
Where their hive is
What the hell's going on cuz
California
Are you sure they're not like trying to figure out who did this to them and
You know I asked Wes about that they hate you I think they like it we bring him to places that
Bring all kinds of fun things you know that's what dads always say to the kids and the kids hated
But I mean
As far as the bees are concerned you know right now they're probably not liking it too much because we got another three or four days before the blooms
Starts
But once the bloom is in once the bloom is off then
Pretty much in
All-you-can-eat buffet for the next 3 or 4 weeks
The city after the bloom is over in a month
There will not be
A flower or food source to be found
In miles
That's really the other reason why you can't just keep
All of the 30 billion bees
In California you know for next year they're already here but the bees would starve
Once the Almond flowers go away
The West has to bring them back to Louisiana
But yes to do the whole process in reverse
The whole process putting the food in loading them on the truck put internet on bringing them back on the interstate 3 days
And then
They go
For the apple season in New York state blueberries in Maine
Cranberries
In Cape Cod
Join the pollination service
See the world I know it seems sweet I mean there is
A small caveat Cosby's only survive a month
So basically the hottest Louisiana
Are filled with mostly
Nuby I mean I guess
Born in California bees
Their Generations that are born on the road in the Northeast
So I understand
Why this is happening but it still seems crazy to
And you know if you push the beekeepers
Hard enough they will say
It is
A little crazy
They just like
Literally
Could not come up with a better way to do this
If you could move the trees
I'm sure they would move the trees to the bees but
The tattoo
We've always hope that someday we could just train the bees
The fly themselves to wherever they need to go
But we haven't been able to figure that out yet
That would be something
Tracy California
I think he's choking
But after seeing the kind of logistics that I saw I'm not entirely sure
Support Fitbit
Podcast and the following message come from Kia Niro with the launch of Kias
First ever ground-up hybrid crossover
Discover the new Kia Niro a smarter kind of crossover
You know I never
Got to see the
Full bloom
Full extent of all the flowers in the Central Valley and so if you happen to be driving
Screw take a picture
I would love to see it
You can email it to us Planet Money at npr.org or send it to us on Facebook or Twitter
Our episode today was produced by Elizabeth kulas
And I want to thank the entire Card family and their many companies they have Merrimack Valley Apiaries West Coast
Pollination
And if you wanted to try the honey made by the bees in this episode
The cult crystals honey
And if you are looking for something else to listen to checkout NPR's all songs considered
They slipped through the nearly 2000 albums published each week
Bring you the best of what's just been released
You can find all songs considered on the NPR one app or wherever you get your podcast
Also we are on the hunt for the next Planet Money intern
Come and work with us we would love to have you come pitch ideas and help us edit our shows and hang out
You can find all the details on our website npr.org
Money
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith thanks for listening
There is one
Last thing that I had to see
Before I left the scene I had to
To see
The actual pain
The deed
The bees Gone Wild
As I was driving
I spotted
On the side of the road
It was one
Almond it was already in bloom
I forgot it in my car
I'll look look at the picture. It right now right now look
I don't know if you can hear it but Abby is
Basically hugging
Wiggling around
And that's it
Before I wake up