A few weeks ago President Trump and republicans in Congress
Just released a plan to change
The tax code
It is now congress's top priority
They say they'll have a bill on the president's desk by Christmas
Some of the biggest changes in this plan or to the corporate
Income tax
And this is a big deal the federal government raises more than 300 billion dollars a year from the corporate income tax
That's enough to cover all the federal spending on
Education
Public housing building roads Bridges NASA funding scientific research
It's a lot of money
Also
Pretty much everyone agrees the corporate taxes outdated
Is it efficient is ridiculously complex
We talked with Leslie Robinson a professor at Dartmouth and she made this whole thing
Very clear
Even the simplest thing
About the corporate income tax
Not that simple
And what do you study
I study corporate tax
What what is corporate tax
It's a tax on corporate income
Just to be clear what is corporate income
So that's one of the reasons I said at the beginning
Udo corporate income is just corporate profits
A company's profit its income is what is subject to the
Corporate income tax
Only it were that simple
What what is the rate for the corporate income
The rate for the corporate income tax 35
Percent
Is that really what they pay
No
Oof button
Right
Leslie says the effective rate that companies actually pay is much lower their different estimates of that but it's probably a little lower
Over 20
This Gap
Between the 35% and the 20%
This is the key to the corporate income tax
Cuz you know I'm the one that you hear people say
United States has the highest corporate tax rate in the developed world
Strictly speaking this is
But at the same time the US tax code has seized
Deductions
Exemptions
Credit things that if you don't like them
Sure and what you factor those in the rate
Companies actually pay is not the highest in the developed world is sick and normal average rate
This is not a great way to run a tax
For one thing you end up with companies spending billions and billions of dollars on tax lawyers and
Counting schemes
Rather than spending that money on you know making better stuff
Also Leslie says there's this other problem
Some companies get their deductions way more than others so when the feeling really unfair
Yeah and every few years politicians
We have to fix
Let's lower the rate let's get rid of some of these loopholes
President Obama try to do it a few years ago and President Trump and republicans in Congress are trying to do it right
Billions of dollars
Thousands of billions of dollars at the bank
Artistic
Hello and welcome to Planet Money time Jacob and Robert Smith today on the show
AR
Three favorite words
Corporate corporate
Income
Corporate income tax
You took a deduction for the whole seat but you're only going to need the edge
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Fidelity Investments
As a Fidelity wealth management client
You get a dedicated advisor to help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes and make
Clear recommendations for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com wealth
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
When President Trump and the Congressional Republicans released this text
A few weeks ago
They published
A document
9 pages long
They called it a framework
Not a plan
Supreme
In which they're going to do there
We have the framework and we are going to walk
Today we're going to tell you how it all adds up and we're going to find
Surprise we are Redemption money
Let's do it
Let's start with the headline that is a thing everyone is going to be talking about which is the Republican framework
Lowers
The corporate tax
And this is the easy
This is the thing that corporations will love it's not like
They're going to
Call up the congressperson and say like wait a minute what
Why are why are you lowering my taxes I just wanted to pay more money
So the rate right now is 35 /
The greatest year in the framework on page 7
Tax structure for corporations
The framework reduces the corporate tax rate
To 20%
.
20%
Now there is
This issue right you lower the tax rate from 35 to
To 20% there is this
Obvious consequence
The government is going to collect a lot less
Tax revenue
Right
According to the committee for a responsible federal budget a non-profit
Over the next
10 years the government would collect
1.9
William fewer dollars
1.9 trillion dollars
1900 billion dollars
What else is it
It is 1.9 million million dollars
Hole in the budget
But
To be clear the rest of the framework
The rest of our show is
Feeling that hold back in right not only are they lowering the rate
They're getting rid of those production
Exemption
Or as they will probably say loopholes cuz you're getting rid of them
Todoroki
Hundreds of bees
Houston attack
Each one has some reason for being some particular compelling story
Let's just take one
What are the few that is
Actually mentioned by name
In the Republican tax
Framework it is called
Section 199 it has its own little story like all of these
This one starts in mm
Congress created section 199 of the tax code
A tax break for domestic Manufacturing
Building stuff guys with mustaches with
Forklift moving things back and 40 gold pieces of metal Cougar Mellencamp singing in the corner yet
So this becomes law in mm
And a few hours later a text learn and Ken silverberg
He gets a call from a company
That wanted to claim a deduction under section 199
They would
Bye
Crackers
Cookies candies
And arrange them
In an artistic and beautiful way
Rapping
Attractive bows for apps
Put some
Decorative items inside the basket what company made gift
The CFO
Went to a tax conference
And he heard some speaker
Talking about this
Section 199 deduction that was available for
For companies that
Did manufacturing and he says
Why can't we use
And can the corporate tax lawyer says
You can't and this is your classic
Tax break story right
Congress opens a little door in the tax code for a specific industry
When everybody calls their tax lawyer and says hey
Get me in that door
So the gift basket Company claims the deduction and eventually the government like wait wait wait
No you can't do that you were literally just putting cookies and crackers and wine into a basket and the case went up in court
Government is saying
If is not manufacturing and 10 and his colleagues are arguing yes it is
This company is making a new thing
Gift basket
They are men
It looks just like the assembly line in any fact
Sam's forklift trucks driving
Across the floor bringing stuff to the beginning of the assembly line
You have
Lines of workers sitting there putting things together and
Mini conveyor belt
So many conveyor belt
Show me conveyor belt the judge agrees with Ken and the gift basket company
They can get a manufacturer
This ruling came down in 2013
And it's part of this push that has been going on
Frankly since section 199 has been in place
We're more and more companies one
There was something called the Starbucks footnote way back there
Beginning that basically meant that Starbucks
Coffee roasting could count under Section 199a dentist
Started cleaning this for making crowns are we manufacturing a podcast
I don't know film companies can do it cuz they are producing
IMovie
They got it
So this proliferation has not escaped congress's notice
The framework the Republicans release reset
Delete it is thin on details but it does
Call out this
Section section 199 page
Clojure framework
Because of the Frameworks of
Stancil reproduction for all businesses
Bcrypt lot domestic
Production section 199 deduction
Will no longer be necessary
What's the best way to put it we're getting rid of it
It's no longer necessary
Oh yeah I'm getting rid of this section 199 deduction it will bring in an extra
60 billion dollars
For the government over the next
Okay okay so lowering the corporate tax rate what's the government in a 1.9 trillion dollar
Eliminating this one deduction brings an extra hundred and sixty billion dollars
Yeah but this is just one deduction
There are more another big one that the Republicans are proposing is going after the gigantic
Pile of money
Corporations are holding
Outside the United States
It is just
Sitting there for the taking
And Congress wants to
Drag it back
Lots of companies are holding cash outside
When you hear a lot about is Apple
Because they have more than 200
Billion dollars
Sitting outside the US
Apple of course is an American company they just built their big
Spaceship headquarters out in Cupertino
But
When Apple sells an iPhone and say
Hamburg Germany the profit does not go to Apple in California
No the money goes to
Foreign subsidiary that is owned by Apple
Some company did Apple created and controls
Outside of United State
The way that us tax system works now
Apple does not have to pay us corporate tax
On that money from the iPhone they sold in German
Until the subsidiaries sends the money back to Apple in California
So not surprisingly Apple subsidiaries
Does
Not send the money back to Cupertino California they hold onto it
So you have to pay the tax and you're after your Apple and all these other companies are doing
And his pile of money is just getting bigger
And bigger and bigger
Anno how politicians love to talk about
This pile of money I happen to think it's double that's probably five
Trillion dollars that we can bring into a country Leicester
And with a little leadership
You get it in here
Very quickly and it could be put to use on the inner cities that a lots of other things
And it would be beautiful
Be able to
Use amounts of money
Countries with zero tax
Where do I go
That is one of the things I asked Leslie Robinson that dirt
Like where is that money
What what is that money where is it
I think most of it's in New York
Waiting New York like right next door to you
So you eat an intricate you're talking about the money
Us corporations are holding abroad the money everybody like
We need to get them to bring this money back to America
You're right
It's in New York
I believe so
I don't understand like
What does that even mean
So holding cash abroad is it has a little bit of a misnomer
Yes
Apparently this is confusing
Yes yes it is so what Leslie Robinson told me is
The company only has to pay tax
Foreign subsidiary
Fins the money back to
Us head
If a foreign subsidiary wants to do so
Something else with the money including putting it in a US Bank
That's fine
The government will not tax it
From now until forever
That's where the corporate tax works now
The big question what is the Republican plan
For this big pile of money
Robert I'm going to go to page 9 of the framework
Yeah I'm going to paraphrase
A corporation that big pile of money
We are texting it
Right now whether it's in gold bars in Switzerland
Or the New York bank account
You are going to pass text
And this is
This is a lot of money
Yeah this is big
Asterisk
And by asterisk I mean
They're going to text this money but they will almost certainly texted at some special Lo
The framework it does not say
Weather radar
So I ask somebody whose job is to kind of figure these things out
His name is Michael mundaka he worked on taxes in the Obama Administration and he now works in Washington for e&y which
Pictures of giant
How much I get a text
The best guess is somewhere around 10%
So more or less
About how much money
Multiple hundred
Billions I would think
Now we're talkin money this is the money
The one other thing to remember about this money though double asterisk
If this is a one-time deal right this
Just applies to the pile of money
That exist
Right now sitting outside View
But the framework also addresses what's going to happen in the future to Foreign Press
It says in the future companies will have to pay some minimum tax on foreign profit
Fits when they're
It'll be a low rate
But no more letting them pile up for it
Okay
Try to make this clear if
Republicans passed their text
Plan if some us companies reporting all of its foreign profits in some
Offshore low-tax
Foxhaven
The US government is going to say
Pay up every year you all
Thumbtack
Exactly right okay
So let's
Take this whole framework
What's all the numbers
See how pencils out
I will do that
After the break
Support for this podcast and the following message come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf
. org
Billiards pool
The framework to The Story So Far
There's this massive cut in the corporate tax
To 20%
And
The framework doesn't
Explicitly mention a few ways
The government is going to make more money
Getting rid of section 199 Manufacturing
I'm texting that pile of money held overseas
Couple other things
But
Just like
Roughly adding the stuff up here but it seems like the government
The US government is going to lose far more money
From cutting the tax rate
It's going to make back from closing loopholes
So there is this one
Other sentence
In the frame
It's very important sentence
And it's a very Biggs
I talked about it with Michael
Oh so she hears the setting
To get inside of
In addition numerous
Other special exclusions and deductions will be repealed or restricted
Yes
We're going to do it we're going to get rid of those loopholes
That's what they're saying
Do you believe it
It's
I think why they don't list them here because I think I want to create Targets this early in the process
This is going to be
Top whenever the house
Comes out
More specifics around
Could be as soon as later this month
Then you'll see
The high gear drive to
Get
Those
Special Provisions maintained in whatever new tax system
That is like
If you're a company and you and play a Lobby
That is the moment when you want the lobbyists to
Do every phase of their so
Super Bowl
Sisters
I'd like I always lose when I go
That is like an ordinary schmuck
I need an alarm
:-(
Do you think it's a reasonable way to feel it is
Cuz you don't have someone going up there and argue
Why you're special
Yes or arguing
Like
Why nobody should be special and everybody should just pay the same
Text whatever the rate is it could be high or could be low just
Pay it right like that that's what we want
That's what we want
But is that what we're going to get
Not according to Montauk I mean he says
His best guess
Is Congress will probably cut the corporate tax rate
Maybe not all the way to 20% but probably somewhere in the low twin
Probably will get rid of section 199a
He says he will tax that money held overseas
But he says
A lot of the other
Special corporate tax rules those are probably going to
Which means bottom line
If this thing passes
The federal government
They just wind up collecting less money overall
From the corporate
You can email us at Planet Money at npr.org or find us on Twitter or face
Facebook today show is produced by Sally helmick fountain
Special things today to our current Internet Alice Wilder we are looking for our next intern it could be you
Come help us make the show its Punjab pay you money applications are due Sunday October 15th
More information is available online at npr.org money
Now that you're finished listening to Planet Money I am going to suggest
A classic
Fresh air
Terry Gross fantastic interview program
Did the classic on the radio and
So if you haven't heard in podcast form you really should
Fresh air
Npr.org podcasts or you can find it in the NPR one app
I'm Robert Smith thanks for listening