This message comes from NPR sponsor NCR running a small business is now easier with ncrc
More than a point of sale
NCR silver is simple-to-use saves you time and helps you reach your goals faster
Visit ncr.com silver
We return from vacation this week
And found that the World As We Know It
Seems like it is about to
We are not talking about nuclear war or natural disasters although there is that too
We're talkin about the economic
Abyss
Because somehow with everything happening this summer
Someone Congress
Forgot
To do the basic work
Of keeping the US economy going
For instance the fiscal year for the United States of America ends
This month
And somebody
Once again Congress has not yet written in Ubuntu
You're something else they didn't do our government
Needs to rate
The debt ceiling
Need the authority to pay the bills that it has promised to pay or
No joke
The entire world economy will suffer
Congress has procrastinated and pushed off a whole bunch of issues that are all coming up
Right now right at the same time you got
Flood insurance
Children's Healthcare the authorization of the freaking FAA the plane
Flying
September is turned into a sore
Thriller
It's like the show 24
Dept of treasury note
Budget resolution hello and welcome
Robert Smith the red numbers accounting slowly down to zero even President Donald Trump got cancer
This week brought together the leaders of Congress into the Oval Office and we have to do something and he may have made this
Situation worse today imma show we will take apart
Three of these Congressional ticking Time Bomb we will show you why eat cashews so dangerous
Why the hell Congress is taking so long
And how it just might get resolved the blue wire cut the blue wire
It's always
This message comes from NPR sponsor game Bridge
The Bold way to steady growth
People often think annuities are too conservative to complex or only for retirees but annuities can
Envious smart way to hedge Market risk and earn guaranteed returns
Cambridge aims to change the game
By offering simplified annuities in a Sleek digital experience that replaces fine print and phone tag
With clear conditions and a direct loafy model
Learn more at gamebridge. Life / NPR
Cambridge is not available in all states
Huge Congressional deadlines
Three different issues
Any amazing thing
Is these are all traps that Congress has set
For themselves
Let's start with
The Dead Sea
Because talking about the debt ceiling
Drive
Mean.
It is simultaneously both the most dangerous
Fing
The Congress mucks around
And it is
The stupidest
Here's the way I like to think of
Any picture in your mind
The most valuable thing in the world
The Hope Diamond
No that's just a million
Plutonium
I don't know how much
Sodium is worth
But I would argue that the most valuable thing in the world
Is
Faith and the trust
The people have
In the US Capitol
Fine
That's not cool
No but it is worth
Trillian
Dollars because that is what people
In this country and around the world have lent to the US government
People have bought
Twenty trillion dollars worth of government bonds
Because
It is the safest investment in the world
It's true the US government always pays its
Dexter butt
Every few years Congress
Come close to screwing this up
When its face is this
Debt ceiling
The debt ceiling
The debt ceiling was a law passed by Congress
100 years ago
And it said
Okay we should limit our debt to at the time
A few billion dollars
And if the country grew
It had to keep erasing that number every few years and put in a Higher One
Currently
At
Twenty trillion dollars we are very close days away
Hitting a ceiling
Coming up on this number
Really fast
And if the government hits that arbitrary limit it can no longer borrow anymore
All of a sudden
The government would literally not have enough money to pay for everything it has promised to pay for
It couldn't pay
The interest to those nice people who lent
Entrusted us
It might not be able to pay for government salaries
Are Social Security payments
Or pay for Medicare or Medicaid Ed Klein Bart
He's a professor at USC
Who is study the Dead
Because we are hoping that he could help us
Make sense of this whole thing
Small problem though
It is
Completely senseless it is a nonsensical concept is unnecessary for running the government
And the ultimately correct answers just to get rid of it
Congress decides what the government is going to spend
That is it
Constitution
And Congress also decide
How much tax revenue it's going to be
Bring it every year Congress spends more than it
Takes in by a lot
They know this
So logically
They have to borrow money to make up the difference
They have essentially said we need to borrow money
And yet
Congress has to schedule an extra vote
To raise the debt ceiling and borrow the money that they have already decided
To borrow many Americans
Misunderstand the debt ceiling and think that it is the driver of debt
When it's not at all it's not the driver that just the result of spending if you don't like
The US
United States having a lot of debt
Well then you should tell Congress to spend less or tax more
But the debt ceiling is is it just an artifact
Because the debt ceiling is a vote
Hosta
No matter what
This allows any party to hold the country hostage until they get something that they want
In years past it has been
Conservative Republicans specifically
Who didn't like some form of government spending and they were threatening to vote against raising the debt
And then they extract
Concessions
This year it appears
It is Democrat
Score stalling raisin
As we record this right now
Does a deal in the works
Queen President Trump
And Democrats to put off the debt ceiling for
Three more months but
All that means is that we'll be talking about economic disaster scenarios again
In December
It is I have to admit
Pretty good block because if we do not raise the debt ceiling if we default on US debt
It'll be a global night
The entire Financial system of the world
Banks
Government
Retirees in
Tutions
All have at their Foundation
This really safe investment US Treasury
And all of a sudden this is not
The world's safest investment anymore
That's cause
Panic
And here in the US
40% of government spending is borrowed
If we do not raise the debt ceiling
Lots of people who expect to get paid
One way or another
Will not get paid
I want that happens
He got a reception because all of a sudden
If I don't have money
For my salary as a at the government employee for example I can't pay my mortgage
I can't pay my grocery bills
And so
It trickles throughout the economy
All of a sudden
Income is missing
It's also stupid because it is unnecessary
Congress could just
Approve
The borrowing when it approves
Spending
But for some reason
They you have 2-year shackle themselves to this debt ceiling
Timebomb they do always
Diffuse it at the last second
But who knows two different year
Different Congress
Mr President
It is worth noting even if Congress
Texas Thrift
Brink of default and pulls back at the last moment
There's only
So many times you can do that
And keep the world
When I hear that sound like I feel
Felix wet
Pops out
On my on my forehead
Can I sweating
Okay
So Congress is sweating it out of the debt-limit thing
But it is not the only thing on their plate the second thing that they have to worry about right now right this moment fact they are behind
Time schedule on it
Is
The Federal Bar
Here's how a budget is supposed to come
Early in the year
The president presents
His own budget
His priorities
His outline
The house
And the Senate they throw it in the garbage
Or
The fourth day take it
Ending choose to ignore some of those priorities and take other than each come up with their own budget
Those are essentially
Outlines they don't have a lot of
Details it that because the details
Are figured out bicycle
Appropriations subcommittees there are 12 in the house there 12 in the Senate
And then they divvy up the money and then they're supposed to pass
12 Appropriations bills in each and then you have to think all these up and make sure been spending the same money
All of this has to get done by the end of September
The end of the fiscal
Unfortunately
It almost never comes to
Raw procrastinators here totally understand
Except every few years
The Congress is
Pushing it in pushing it the fighting over it and they
Fail to fund themselves
And you heard of this they have to shut down the Federal
It was one of the
Worst days
That I had a job
That's the department that includes everything from the US Geological Survey to
The Bureau of Indian Affairs to the Nash
And almost as soon as Sally started the job you know she got hurt
Her little ID badge and here's where the stapler is
Ground so beautiful but she also got word
Hey you know what
You're going to need to make an emergency plan for the Department of the Interior because it is looking an awful lot
Like Congress is not going to managed
The past the bills that are going to fund the government
And sure enough within 8 months of starting the job
It happened
To me it was just incredulity
I mean like is this really happening we are actually shutting down the largest
Organization on the planet
Because people cannot get their act together to provide a budget to keep
The doors open and in what
What a waste
Of resources
It's empty the normal jobs Sally's employees were being paid
Do you know
Shut down the Washington Monument before they were furloughed themselves
So they didn't like drag barricades into protected and drained
Water fountains in lock bathrooms input
National Park
Closed signs up for the
The poor lost tourists
For foreigners visiting our country
They said what what do you mean
Your government has shut down
How do you explain that to
You know it tourist from
China who's been planning this trip for 5 years
The 2013 shutdown lasted for 16 days
Is one of the longest government shutdowns and Reese
I was talking to one of our colleagues Ron elving easterly NPR's master
Of politics talk about this particular
Time Bomb issue and he said
You know
These kinds of shutdowns
Happened maybe more than you say
It is probably
The best reason not to use the
Time Bomb metaphor
Because in the end it is not really
An explosion
So much as it is
It if you could call it an erosion of the things that people
Pandora
In the last 40 years there have been
Different shut down
Because Congress could not agree on a
And many of those were just a day or two and
And shut down like shut down sound a little more
Harsh that it actually is
Because
Essential Personnel do get to keep work
We didn't send home the air traffic
Controllers we didn't bring all of our troops home from their far-flung
Missions around the world
And we didn't stop inspecting the meat you know that sort of thing now if you did all those things
If all of the federal government's funk
Literally stop
That would be
Completely different animal
If the
The biggest impact
Of government shutdowns is usually
Political you can make this very good argument that Bill Clinton
Bill Clinton got reelected in 1996
Because because there's been these two
Big
Federal shutdown
And people ended up blaming Newt Gingrich and Republicans for them
And Bill Clinton actually came out of them looking pretty good
Iran tells us that
The shutdowns do service
Every member of Congress
How to make tough body
Sometimes decisions that might look
Bad to their constituents back home
Being able to say well you know I had to make a hard vote in a hard choice because
The clock was running out the government going to shut down that's something that constituents
Might swallow a little
Senescence
It's not that the shutdown is a real
Explosive ticking time bomb
Yeah because in Hollywood the bomb is there to create suspense so that the hero can swoop in and Save
The day and innocence
That itself is his metaphor for Congress
Will just answer the question I've always had which is
I've never understood
Why you have
Big flashing
Digital numbers
On the bottom just to make it
Easier to
Diffuse for the hero
But of course like the whole Congressional process is
All about the number
It's the number
Rite Aid
Right
Well that's for the audience.
The right because you're trying to make the audience
Feal suspension
You're trying to make the audience
See consequence
Cuz if the hero doesn't do something heroic
And that's an impression
That they are trying to create in their political audience
Much of the way the makers of Thrillers are trying to get their audiences
Normal year
This could be
Brinkmanship and games and not have a severe impact
Remember this is not a normal year
Because as they are going to
The process they also have to do the first time we talked
Definitely have to do it at the same time
As of this recording it looks like the deal that's coming together is going to
Porsche budget negotiations
Down the road
Into December
And so instead of getting to deal with each of these issues individually
Congress has taken
Two time bombs
And made them one
Giant
And that's not all
There's one
More huge issue
They have to deal with
We'll talk about that after the break
Support for this podcast
And the following message come from State Farm whose agents know that your car and home are more than just big party
They're a big part of your life
You put the time into making them your own
So now it's time to protect them
With your own personal State Farm agent
Not only do they truly get
But they'll be there for you when you need them
And with over 19,000 agents in neighborhoods across the US
There could be one just around the corner
Moritz statefarm.com
Are 1-800 State Farm
State Farm
Here to help life
Go right
You know when you're watching a thriller
And sometimes one of the sidekicks get
Killed off or
Or weirdly like just disappears for no apparent reason
And no one really mentions it or makes a big deal about it
Julie DeWitt
Will you take the empty seat
It is now in the studio
Niacin
Yeah I don't know why
Julia is here to talk about the other
Huge thing
The Congress has to deal with
Is fall something you put off dealing with for a long long
Time
I'm referring to immigration or more specifically
Deferred action for childhood arrivals
So you probably
Heard about this
This week DACA was this policy
Obama administration that gave some protection to this one like really specific group of undocumented in
All these rules you had to be under 31 years old
Your parents had to have brought you to the United States
Before you were 16 years old
You also had to be like an X
Exceptional member of
Society so
Your criminal record
Squeaky clean image of been in or have a graduate
High school or college or served
In the military and Jen
Discharged
And then you had to
Apply for DACA permit
Pay lunch money
And what's amazing is even though they were all of these
Hurdles
Around 8
Hundred
Thousand
Young people applied
For this docker protection
Animal lasted 2 years you had to
Play for every two years
What you got in exchange
Four Points Raleigh
Poop Squad
Your life changed into big wave
You could stop worrying all the time because you were
We're shielded from deportation
And
You could work
Legal you had a social security number
Doing something for this group
The dreamers
People out there
DACA
It's not actually that controversial on is
What was controversial with
The way up
A biologist
Went around Congress
Schism
Weather for obvious reasons
Because as we appointed out time and time again in his podcast
Congress has
Trouble getting things
And they could not for the life of themselves solve
This particular part of the immigration problem even though they
Debated about it for over a
Decade
Because the fate of these dreamers with
Tangled Up
In a lot of the other
Fraud immigration reform issues and so everything just stayed in a big tangle of ball
And that's what Obama
Was trying to
TSO in 2012 Obama was like
Screw it might be voted out of office in a few months I'm just going to
Do that thing
And with one stroke of the president pen DACA came to be
But what is created with a stroke
Pain
Can be undone
With a stroke
I'm here today to announce
Set the program
Known as DACA
That was effectuated
Under the Obama Administration
Is being rescinded
Stephanie General Jeff sessions from this past Tuesday and in session to President Trump
We're pretty wildly about the
This whole thing because I didn't just
Withdraw the duck
Simply said you know what
We're not going to let these protections start to expire for six months so
Covers
You been putting it off
Putting it off
You have
6 months
To fix it
Dreamers are pretty haidian
On average they were
6 years old when they came to
Some of them are in
And everything is
You know sort of by definition
The people who are covered by DACA were you no pick to be sort of these
Extraordinary members the community until they have been
Extra visible
This generation
Kids themselves having grown up in the US has been
More comfortable
Being
Out is unauthorized immigrants more comfortable standing up for themselves more comfortable interacting with American institutions
Then say their parents were that is Dara Lind
She's a reporter at 4 box
And she's done a lot of really great reporting on the
Because she
Great historical
View
Of of DACA and immigration as it affects
These young people
And we put it out there
Who reason this was a problem in the first place was because
Of Congress because of a string of unintended consequences
It came from changes in Immigration policy
Congress
Tough-on-crime tough on
Grecian
So they pass this law which may
Makes it a lot harder to cross
The Mexican
Yeah you know more surveillance more officers patrolling the sort of thing was meant to reduce undocumented immigration
What are allowances
When you build a wall you don't keep people out you keep people in
Weider explains it is like
For decades
People mostly mad
Flowed back and forth
Between Mexico and United
They came for work
And then when the work was over when they had enough money they would go back to their families in Mexico
When Congress
Lockdown the Border
People still came over
What was different was that it became too dangerous to come and go and
Go back and forth
So when undocumented immigrants when men came here to work
They stayed
And
They brought their family they brought their young kids with
So what you end up having is
A population of people who are
Semi-permanently on authorized
I even if they are as they develop ties to
America and develop connections to American citizens
But
Are totally routed because they're stuck
So because of bees
You know
Probably well-meaning laws
There was this generation stuff
Estimated to be around a million
Young people at the time there
General in their twenties now these dreamers
They were stuck in this country couldn't travel back and forth across the border and
Did not have a path
To become
And even trouble
Himself has
Express sympathy
For this dreamer generation yesterday about how DACA recipients have nothing to worry about
What Trump did this past week
Was actually
Pretty sad
Toby takes this whole mess
He gets attacked the Congress start in the first place and this time
Set timer
Forest around here
A ticking time bomb.
It's going to be
A really stressful Falls
But it's also
Going to be really stressful
For all of us
Economy
Especially for the dreamers
There's a very
Narrow path
The success
Which is possible
As long as they do not cut
The red wire
I thought you said we should cut the red wire
If you are in New York City this weekend you should come on over to you now hear this podcast Festival
Dara Lind and her crew from Fox will be taking a live version of their podcast the Weeds on Sunday
We will also be there on Sunday performing feats
Of strength
And still I'm serious here we're taking that for our next podcast
Send an emails Planet Money at npr.org
Twitter Facebook
Car show today was pretty by Sally Helm or editor is Bryant or sat or supervising producer is out of school
Now you're finished listening to Planet Money may we recommend another
Find podcast from NPR it's called
Ask me another it's a show featuring puzzles word games
Trivia played in front of a live audience
It is also hilarious it is called ask me another you can find that on NPR one
Or wherever you get your podcasts
A note here in the studio left from
Kenny Malone and Kenny says
Be sure and thank
Kelsey Snell
From The Washington Post
For helping guide us through
The Weather policy
I'm Robert Smith
I'm delighted with
Thanks
It's a what I'm thinking here is
Just so we have like a final scene in the final scene leaked pictures
The sun is coming up over New York City
And the camera store
Zooms in
On Julian die
We're dressed all in black and what's their standing over
An empty cubicle and then you can see in the background of hits of Kenny Malone
And Julie you like you put a
Bouquet of flowers down on the desk
And you say
He would have liked the end of
Podcast
He would have
I think he's listening somewhere and
When we really need him
When Congress gets close to the cliff
You'll be back