Support for Planet Money
And the following message come from Michigan Economic Development Corporation
If you want to start or grow your business Michigan is the place to make it happen
Learn Why by searching Michigan pure opportunity
Hey it's Jacob Goldstein just a quick heads up
The show first ran in 2015
Cheers the show
You don't seem like a good idea
Skyrim Robert Price thought
Where do stores get their
What is it was a store
Force
Stores
A place where people who own little Bodega
Small automotive shop could come and buy the stuff they needed
Sir Robert Bryson is Dad rented a warehouse
House in this industrial parts
We went in there there were birds flying around pigeons and
It was a god-awful looking place but we cleaned it up
They decided to be allowed to shop at their store for stores
One you had to own a business
Until you had to pay a membership
How to make $25
For the right to shop which was not really done at
It open for business on July 12th 1970
And it was a
The small businesses
Didn't come
They didn't spend money
And
We are after
Relatively short time maybe a few weeks
Where
Basically going going bankrupt
How did you feel at that moment
Desperate
My wife and I were a month away from Mars
II
Child being born
I remember my mother-in-law in particular figurine
She wasn't sure that
That her daughter had married the right person
Prince had a rough
Anja
It was really bad
Not long after the store open somebody suggested
Opening up the store to people who did not own
People just want to shop for themselves
The price was afraid that it would alienate the business owners who were they
Members of this club
I figured it out
Business owners are really going for this anyway so let's
All of a sudden they were people they were shopping and there was
There was excitement in
It's felt like
Like we have been
Just giving some kind of a gift I made it was amazing my father said you know
I think you guys
Are going to end up having a pretty good business here
You may have heard of it
The warehouse door was called Price Club which
I never knew was named after
Robert price
Yeah Robert pricing is dead
And so you know they thought it was just going to be this one warehouse but they added more stores and more
A few hours later one of their employees left
Start another Warehouse Club store Costco
Benfleet gym cost
Jim sinegal but he did work at Price Club
He did leave and start Costco
Eventually Price Club and Costco merged other Warehouse Club
Basically copying Price Club popped up all over the world
And you know this thing Robert price
Stumbled into Exeter
Is paying in order to shopping a huge Warehouse did he give a huge economic Forest today
Costco alone sells more stuff every year than am
By far
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Jacob
Robert Smith
Used to be pure at a store if you wanted to make it easy for your customers
Price Club and Costco
Went in the opposite direction
They need shopping
Harder they make shopping almost unpleasant you hated and people couldn't get it up
Today on the show how Price Club and its imitators change the way we shop
And how do companies taking what price Club started
Too unbelievable
Strips
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with
Straight jeans
How did they make them so great
Madewell starts with premium.
Then offers men's and women's styles for seriously everyone
Also you can recycle any brand of jeans in a Madewell store
And they'll give you $20 off a new pair
They work with the blue jeans go green program
Have to turn old jeans into housing insulation for communities in need
Terms apply
Ready to find your perfect fit stop by a Madewell store or go to Madewell.
I'm going to deposit some
Universal laws
Selling something to another human be
Number one
If you can have a store have a convenient location
Advertisers
Tell people where it is and how they can shop there
And when they come
Welcoming into the
Store
And then
My membership expired and also I don't have my card so I need to renew it and I guess
Carter you don't have the membership anymore I don't
The founder of a price look like
What was he thinking when he set up a story
Buy original kind of
Image of my mind
Was like a speakeasy where somebody would feel G I've got this special deal
And I can come in and shop and most people can't come in and get in here like truly like
Club o I'm a member of this like insiders Club
Exactly right
Insiders club for like a hundred million people
But still for each of those hundred million people there is a dude
At the door who says show me your membership card where in
So amazing to be a member here you just sign up for membership just renew your membership I just paid $55 for the privilege
Shopping at Costco
At this point
With your in the hole
Like you've lost money I'm down
The more I spend
Just to through TV
Turn TV as one of those things that nobody actually wants that much I'm sorry Jacob I got totally distracted
Behind the curve
TV you were about to say
Tell you about the day I paid my 55 bucks now I feel like I got to spend enough money so that I save
More than 50
Which I know is irrational I know this is
The sunk cost fallacy tok
Alta 55
So yeah making you pay to shop
Is this one big thing that Costco does that's the opposite of how normal stores
But once they locked you into this system they can do all of these weird secret things
They wouldn't fly in any other store but in
Costco can get you the Bible
I need Ziploc bags
Normal store
You will look at the sign at the end of the aisle
What's a ziplock bag
There are no side
There are no signs but why wouldn't you put aside like it makes no sense
Is Robert price
I was adamant that we would not have signed telling people where things were because
That would make it likely that they would wander through all the aisles and find other things to buy
That's a little bit
Doesn't feel like you're looking out for me
No I mean I agree with you I think it was I think I know what I do use the word devious
But it was a manipulative
Because it creates this whole
Different philosophy of shopping it is not
The kind of story you just pop into and grab a Cuppa
Little Things
You go down every aisle and if you buy something
You buy a lot of it
Churches the good call I like the characters, I don't know you normally
It's probably costing me more because I just bought 13 gallons of carrot juice
Never having drink carrot juice before my I'll buy one of those
And it'll Cordia buying in bulk is always
But for Robert Price the bulk stuff fit into this broader really surprising plan
Yeah we didn't want people to come very often
Tell me more that's
Why not
Because it was better it's much better from a cost expense point of view is to have people come less often and buy more
Sitting down
In planning ways to have people not come to their store and there's like math behind the right because
Every time you go to a store
That's where he has to pay for your parking
Has to pay for the cashier to make change or two
Authorized user credit
Right if you're the store
You would rather have a customer who comes say
Once a month
Taunton spends $400
Person comes every week
And spends $100
Now weird Ziploc
In a normal store they would be like 15 kinds of bags
Sizes different brands the ones of a little zip-top on the blue thing on it
Not
We got three choices and three choices on one
Small medium large
Costco Giant Store tiny selection
Any idea is
When you have more selection
There's more labor
You going to a grocery store
And you see everything is headstack
Everything is being touched
In other words
The wave grocery store gets those 15 kinds of Ziploc bags onto the Shelf
They pay somebody to put them in one box at a time
But if you're going to Costco and you look at them
Hinckley the grocery department those products are driven by forklifts
So they're not touching individual items they're touching a pallet
It's just
Quantum difference on labor
Soap toys for the Ziplocs at Costco small medium large I went with the small
We went to check out
It was that one last thing
I went and got a couple of those pinotage weird like half
Cut out boxes they have to put your stuff in yeah I should say that I'm not a regular member of Costco and so it surprises me
Me when I go to store spend
Where was a $350
And then like yeah you have to put them in these
Genki
Little tiny falling apart
To carry them out of the sky
Yet they don't even give you a real box
And they definitely do not get
Never had bags
For two reasons one is
It cost money to have bags
And secondly
This might be a little bit of the
Four show
Idea
But if you have bags you look like a retail store
Robert Preston
Price Club and Costco never ever want to look
Leica retail
You know they want to be that that's
Speakeasy he was
Your place
Put the cement floor
Palettes. Where you go to your special club and you buy your
Bat of carrot juice
For a great
I'm sorry it just makes me laugh every time you say the words
Because it's so clearly not that Vibe it is a cold
Harsh
Viber every part of the business is busy
I would rather regular grocery store
Take care of all those details for me and I am willing to pay
A quarter
$0.30 35
And I-35 since you mean
Hundreds of dollars a year
The Costco has basically pushed
This about as far as you could push
A physical store in
But a lot of people are looking at the same
Is there a place
I can go even further
Is there a way that you
Strip away even more of the
The comfort of traditional
Of course there is
And will tell you about it
After the break
Support for this podcast in the following message come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org
Price Club and ultimately Costco became really successful because they
Strip down physical retail as far as they
A few years ago
A company launched that in way
Is taking things even
The company is called
Jet
And in a lot of ways it's like Costco
But online
I found the company fascinating because it took this
Deconstructing idea that Costco had
To remove all the artist
Of retail
I just took it to the next level
Mark Laurie who started the company he told me what that next level
They built this
The system
The tracks millions of products scattered and warehouses all over the country
And that's all the song
It's really
Basic problem in econ
Mercury says when we buy stuff online
Even if we don't know it
We are getting killed on ship
You're buying something online for $100
20 of that is just
D battery cost
To cover shipping and fulfillment
Even if you get free shipping is already embedded in
Surprise
So you telling me
I get my Amazon Prime I get free shipping if not
Stop right now
It's embedded
Embedded in the price
Lori's big idea Jets big idea is to solve that
Lori showed me on his phone
Let's buy some stuff
So I pulled up the jet
App and his a homepage let's pick a category associate
So this is
One of the most populous is the Tide Pods laundry detergent
If we just by the ton
Somebody in a warehouse has to get that tied up
The Shelf
Put together a box put it in the Box tape up the box
And then somebody from UPS or whatever has to bring that box all the way to my house
That is not efficient that is expensive
Lori says the way to solve that problem is to get us to buy
Lots of stuff
All at once
From the same way
We do that
The shipping cost per item goes Wei Wei
Subject is basically set up
To say
Oh you get that box of Tide well there's some handy wipes over here you want those
What is what that and because this is like e-commerce giant warehouses
They're like
Thousands of things
In the same warehouses with
The Tide Pods laundry detergent
And you can see there it says savings just increased on
25717 item
That means that that particular product is located
In warehouses
That give access to another 25,000 Prada
So I feel like I haven't Costco where
This is all just too much
Information about how things work in the warehouse
This doubles and triples that idea because now it's like do I really want
Your house and how I can save a couple
I'm going to give you one more
You got one more thing to worry about
You see it when you go to check out
Okay so here so so here's the tide and I wasn't able at the time
It says wave return and Save $0.24
And there's a little little button exercise
Tokyo
Bissell push that button you'll save $0.24
Additional annual
Robert jet offers free returns like a lot of side
But they tell you
Free returns are not free
The right to return this box
Tide is worth
$0.24
Give up that right and Jet will give you the money don't give you that $24
I just
Don't want to know that much about the grocery business it is not worth it
Tumi
To save 20%
I kind of love it
The kind of love it like it's
Like I feel like I'm doing work and I'm
Saving money you know it's like
Bike tire looks like
Puttering around the house
There's a logical limit to how much work a consumer can do
I don't think we've hit that limit yet
So we first ran the show back
In 2015
Last year in 2016
Jet was acquired by Walmart
4 more than 3 billion dollars
Today Show was originally produced by Francis Harlow today is Rerun was produced by our intern
Eduard Saakashvili
Let us know what you think of the show you can email us at
Planet Money I'd npr.org
Brat Twitter or face
I'm Robert Smith and I'm Jacob
Thanks for listening