Support for Planet Money
And the following message
Did come from Michigan Economic Development
Incorporation
If you want to start or grow your business
Michigan is the place
And make it happen
Learn Why by searching Michigan pure oportun
Morning neck
Morning Karen
I guess we should say that it's 6:57 in the morning.
So we're a little groggy
Why are we here
We're here because
We're at a yard sale
Sale fishing tackle
Pet thing
That is nice
We are at a yard sale
Gadsden Alabama
And we are not here
For just this one yard sale
We are here for thousands of them
We are at the
The starting point of the Worlds
Longest
Yard sale
It's been 690 miles all the way from Alabama to Michigan
Up this little Highway Highway 127 that runs mostly through small town
Editor
Had the brilliant idea
For us to drive all 690 miles of his thing in 3 days which I was not
Totally excited
I mean I'm someone who if I see a yard sale in my neighborhood
It's like one block out of the way I'm probably not going to go out of my way to stop
About it
690 mi in km
That's worth it
Yep for me
I love yards
But I always kind of feel like
I'm the sucker and ever
690 miles to learn how to be a better yard sailor
I am definitely
I have $100
In small change
In my fanny pack
And I'm ready to go
Oh let's go to the
Maps info t-shirts the world's longest yard sale
Hi there
You are who are you my name is Aberdeen
And I work for greater Gadsden area tourism here in Gadsden Alabama
And this is the map you're here in Gadsden
All 690 mi in 3 days
What do you think are the odds that we make it
Well
This is the beginning
So if you're starting here in today's Friday Yuan nevermind
Never never ever met
690 mile
We're even have three days we have two and a half days
Worried about what you just made me really worried I'm sorry it's okay
Y'all better got that
Skip some yard sale because
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I Am Karen Duffin underground it is summer it is America
And what is more American
In the world's longest
Yard sale
Alabama Georgia Tennessee Kentucky
Ohio and Michigan
Today on the show
690 miles of microeconomic
At work
We're going to learn from the most
Ruthless fire in Southeastern Alabama
And the grumpiest seller in Tennessee
There will be haggling
It will hopefully be some deals
And it will definitely
Besom
This message comes from NPR sponsors
Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses
To design and build their own website
Using customizable light
And features in
Including e-commerce functionality
3 + mobile app
Squarespace also offer
First built and search engine optimization
To help you develop an online
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
You the offer code NPR
How to save 10% off
If your first purchase of a website or domain
Stretch Armstrong
What's good we're back with a brand new season
We got Erykah Badu Lenny Kravitz black thought and more stories from a list
Subscribe now
So much traffic
8 miles an hour
Yep
You can start early but you can't start early enough
Yeah we had not
Quite factored in
The tens of thousands of other people
Who had come along to do what we have done to be on this yard sale
Right because the world's longest yard sale is an annual thing
It's been going on
The first weekend in August for the past 29 years
A guy in Tennessee started it because he wanted to get people to come to his
Small town
And it just kind of grew from there
And now
Tens of thousands of people come every year from all over the country
And that first morning
It felt like we were stuck behind all 10000 of them
This looks like a yard sale I would mess with
Hey
Baseball
Phone cases
Stuffed animal attic
Now that's Gray
While we were debating the merits of yard sale stuffed animals
We spot this one guy
His mid-thirties super tan baseball cap
He's carrying this
Huge metal sign
What is even going on here
You have a
8 foot long sinuses manitowish
Have you ever seen another
Fair enough are enough
I've got a 48-foot trailer full of old stuff like
Excuse me
This is Josh
Crumpy's from Alabama and he's at the yard sale with his wife
Marcy
And I am like a 3rd or 4th generation
Camcorder
Her mom her grandma her great grandma
Her aunt
Literally my cousin me has his appendix surgery because she was at a yard sale and she was supposed to bring him
But that is what we're dealing with
That's the class of Hoarders that we're dealing with
The total look
This isn't just an upset
Our family has a wedding venue
And we use this stuff to decorate it right these are people who have it
Turn yard sailing into a profession
These are people we can learn
So we turn to them and we say luck
We want to be great yard salers
Give us all your tip
And Marcy says
Before the yard sailing
Starts
You got to get
I always have extra set of clothes cuz you never know when it's going to rain
I told paper cuz I'm all stopped wherever I got to use the bathroom and
Fat Snax
Animal have plenty of
Change
Did we forget to bring toilet paper
All right
That is the pregame
But at a yard sale
It's the deal that
And I want to know how Marcy gets the deal
I start with soon as I walk up I just start like down and everything they have
And I start getting in their head I just start playing with your mind
Thinking you know
Did I pass my sweetheart
Whatever even get this stuff off the ground I mean
You break him down first
They may be on antidepressant by the time they leave this year but there is one exception to this
And that's if she fine
Plain white dishware
That is her weakness
In fact her family has forbidden her from
Bringing any more home because she already has
Tubs of it
Today there is one thing that Marci
Really has her eye on
In fact
She's been looking for it for a year-and-a-half
We can find an iron twin bed you're fixing to say it go.
Cuz that's what I'm looking
I want her to find that iron
Twin bed
I want to see it go down
Is it cool if we follow you just for a few miles to see how you do your thing
We start following them through mostly Suburban Alabama There's
Couple yard sales every two black rental cars
Weather
I finally they pull over a car
She's going to look at the stuff while he parked and the first thing that Marcy buys
The one thing she is not allowed to buy how much are your platters
A dollar
What you explicitly banned from bringing home white plates
Yeah I was fat
You know how people like Fitness in just a little bit
This will get me through the day
She gets her fix
And then we hit the road again I can't believe they didn't stop
I'm shocked at this point we've been following them long enough we thought we could kind of predict when they would pull over
But then they pull into this one yard sale.
Does not look promising
What's I don't see anything here but they would want
Let's go find out
What do we got here
No
I'm pretty sure it's at a twin iron bed
Is a thing
Did Marcia been looking for
4 a year
And a half
Promise a Throwdown if she found
That okay so I can't act 2 interactive so I'm just going to come
Yeah yeah
We look around
And after we had
Faked it long enough
Finally
She goes in
How much are you want for your bed
Okay
What do you want to pay
We're fixing to Bangladesh connection
Here it is
He's going in for the kill
Would you do $50
I'm back
I can do that
50 on it
North rotary what she did have a good price
When someone spare do you want to be forever back
There was a time in Marcie's life when she probably would have negotiated down to $25
And felt like a sucker if she didn't get it
Not this time
Texting you I was expecting you to be much meaner than you were
I'm going to head like a hole
I renewal process myself
So
Yeah I'm trying to be a little bit nicer
People trying to make a living
What Marcy is reminding us
Is that yard sales are not
Anonymous economic transaction
If you're bargaining online
All you want is the lowest
Price what is your bargaining face-to-face
Like Marcy on someone's front lawn
The optimal price
Isn't necessarily the Louis
It's the lowest one you can get
Well also being able to say thanks
Maybe I'll see you next year
54 hours to go and 690 MI
We still have 684 left
We got to find a way around all of this traffic I told me how you take this dirt road over here
Every horror film should we make a rule for a cell
We can take shortcuts we can even take freeways
But we have to hit yard sales in every single state okay but even so we still have so much ground
Way too much about someone by being in the car with them
Them for way too long
Like I generally try to keep my diet coke have it hidden from people
But
You know three days in the car so secret they're okay but that Cemetery thing that you do
There's a church at the end of the Seventh Day Adventist salvation not for sale
Freely given
They put that sign up just for this weekend around Georgia when I realized
I need to Google every single thing that goes through your brain
$15 generals and all I wanted to know was how many Dollar Generals are in the United States
Which stand of course meant that I had to find out how many Walmarts are in McDonald's
Every historical fact in Billy Joel
We Didn't Start the
The fire great killing me I think we made it
Domestic
Okay if I ever hear this song again I'm going to cry
What about tomorrow in the car no no
Definitely not
Day to Tennessee
2 with
500 miles left to go in
36 hours
Do we get kind of diss track
Big American flag lots of America
Oh that's some good stuff actually
Why not
We pull into the parking lot of a restaurant
Called Shoney's
In Crossville Tennessee
There's a strip of grass work
People have set up a bunch of yard sales
And right away we see this one guy
Same as Jonathan Joe
Older chain-smoking
Grumpy Cat made a few if I don't sell it to you for twenty or stand there and bug me
Yeah
Okay
Take the clock and go but
Charming in his own way
And he's selling some things that we're looking to buy an order for
Prince record
Where we left we a star
Hey do you want us to pick up anything for you along the way and Stacey Vanek Smith
Really don't know if she was
Just trolling us here but she said
Did you get me a shaming cookie jar you know the kind that yells at you and you grab a cookie and also
French rack
And here in Tennessee
Are crates of Wrecker
Dollar rate
I feel like we're not going to find that
French Creek
What is this
French
Oh my God Stacey Vanek Smith is Corey my goodness
Ridiculous that's the only $10 album
No it's at Dollar keep digging every five
Some great rack
Commodores
Spreading Pretenders
Pretenders
As long as this has
2000 MI
Then we need it
We had over the money to Jonathan the guy selling these records
All right
We run into a
Problem
Jonathan
Does not want to sell us his Pretenders album
Sorry you had to be happy with your two
Really
I feel like the sale already happened
Yeah I didn't look close enough
Johnson says listen
This Record really mean something otherwise I really like this band a whole feel of it and see them in concert best ones
I've been to in recent years I'll make a deal with this back and you can take
Any other two records here how about that
At this point we realize
Two things
We are sitting here being awful to the 68 year old
Pretenders
And we are becoming
A living example of something in behavioral economics
I guess we should tell you like why
So we cover a kendama
Do you want to come that's going on here
But there's this economic term called the endowment effect
And that
When you
Okay so I got a little too into the weeds with Jonathan here
But basically the endowment effect
Is the idea that
The mere fact of owning something makes it more valuable
Jonathan says
That totally makes sense
This happens to me all the time
Many times
If I've got it
It's not worth much to that person with the same thing if he's got it
Oh how couldn't part with it
For that
That's exactly what the endowment effect
And that
Is happening
Right now
Because look
This is not a record that I've been
For I know one song
The one side owned it for what like seconds
No way am I giving
I realize I was being
Predictably irrational
And I told Jonathan
Sorry my bad
We will take you up on that offer
So Jonathan gives us
Folk record
Cool ass Wrecker
Other one by soul singer named Jackie Wilson
This is
That say you will
Is
Killer song
I'm gay
You have to put the pretenders record in your car
Thank you
For saving me from myself
Yeah but the only one I go home with I'll be happy
And you know what Jonathan was not just trying to
Get back his Pretenders record this is a good song
I am so glad that Jonathan told us about Jack
Jackie Wilson
I feel like
This is the first
Grapevine from this trip
And after getting this awesome record
We are, but we are really
Yard sailor
But not hipster buying silly stuff yard sales we are in
Will you go around here they won't find no better deal than air but after we hit Kentucky
Welcome to Kentucky you were buying so much stuff that
It's all sort of became a blur need luggage
Luggage I got some goblets
But I loved you hated
Welcome to Ohio
120 miles and only 24 hours to go
And
I found a miniature ironing board I've been looking for that for this
Thank you
Start justifying things that I definitely do not need no I mean I'd be doing myself a favor
We bought
So much
Stuff
Day 3
Our last day
We wake up early in Ohio
Only one thing on our mind
Addison
Michigan
The end of the world
Longest yard sale so tired
We ran out of time we have made it almost State wrestling Champs 1989
But we barely had time to celebrate because when we pulled over
We realized we had a
Where in Addison we're going to take a second to pack up her stuff
Cuz next up there
West County Fitness early
It is awesome and we're just an hour from Detroit
There's so much trash in this car
Right now I'm starting to understand how the yard sale I feel like I just don't really want to look at home
Yeah
Well you bought it
Harvest Vine
You have a lot of glass what is what even is this stuff I don't even remember
Don't forget your ironing board
I always thought of myself as someone who had great spatial reasoning
Like the baseball bat alone
Even diagonal there's no way
We have a pile of stuff here that is not going to fit in our suitcases big decision time
I think
I think that I can't think about what to do with this stuff until I get food
Maybe let's get lunch
Take me to order some ice cream
We drive just passed Addison and find ourselves a lunch spot
Cog Freddy's Fries
It is
Very delicious so we also get dessert
And as we eat in our blood sugar levels start Rising we have an ID
Freddy's
Has this big outdoor seating space
A bunch of picnic table lots of people
Maybe a captive selling audio
So we go back
To be ordering window and we ask for the manager her name is Sherry Hollowell what's going on
You're busy we're reporters from New York
We just drove the entire 127 yard sale
And we got to go to the airport
And all of our stuff is not fitting
And I love it
And we have a very strange request
With your permission
We would love to just like setup right out there
Have the smallest yard sale you've ever seen
After the break clevver side goes a long way
Leaving Michigan tonight
Must sell everything
MN NPR
No price refused
We hold the world
Tiniest yard sale in the parking lot of a small-town ice cream stand
This message comes from NPR sponsor squares
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence
Sense and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable Leo
Along with
Features including e-commerce functionality
The and mobile app
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer
Code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase
Just have a website or domain
I got a large red raspberry slush
All right red raspberry slush
Back in the parking lot of Freddy's Fries where we're holding our tiny yard sale
We quickly discovered that people coming for lunch
I'm not necessarily interested in a mini ironing
All right we'll just come look after you finish your delicious-looking meal for my amazing 70s
Amber goblets yard sale
Are you sure these are some great goblets
This is not going well
Before you guys leave you want to look at our stuff especially when it comes
To your ugly cat cookie
I love this cookie jar and nobody is buying
All those guys are going around us
So just as I'm thinking
We might just have to throw everything into the dump
We meet the first two people who are willing to
Talk to it
Oh we got some yard Sailors here
I'm downsizing
Nick James and Tiffany bass are here for lunch
So
I try to Pawn off my goblet
You try to sell your bat
What about first self-defense
Which seems very brutal
Nick and Tiffany are like
We don't actually need any
Cuz we drove a lot of this ourselves the past
But also
You guys are kind of
Doing this wrong
You know you got to tell a story
In order to sell it
Adrian Marcel something
You need to have a story
In retrospect
This seems kind of obvious
But this thing that we're doing the feels normal to us because we've been to dozens of yard sales at this point
Is actually a little weird
Like people came to their small town ice cream shop for lunch
And they found two random radio reporters in the parking lot trying to sell them
A mini ironing board
The thing we were not doing
I was telling all those strangers
The biggest
We were not
Tapping into
To the thing that makes the world's longest yard sale work
Connecting 690 miles of yard sales
Turns it from that one off yard sale in your neighborhood that you
You probably won't go to
To a destination
Illegitimate thing
You might plan your family vacation
And where you might buy some
70s Amber goblets
Alright so we got some
Primo like goblets
As soon as we start connecting
Our little yard sale to the world's longest one we've been on the road for literally a thousand miles
We're going to the world's longest yard sale everything sells
Pretty quickly
Okay Vine
To be clear we were also giving the stuff away at bargain-basement prices to Buck
Tupac last like 5 bucks on the goblets to bucks on the bat
We ended up
Giving away the ironing
Keyboard all that was left
Was Stacy
No one wants that
No one
And it
So sadly would not fit into my suit
I think here's what I think
You say you're going to take it home
I don't know if it's going to make it all the way
But I can if I stop
Some clothes inside
The cookie jar I think
I can bring it home and we can give it to say to bed excited dancing in the parking lot of Freddy's Fries
That
I'm very happy about that that is a perfect ending to this yard sale
Where
That you can
If you have any awesome yard sale
Stories or any stories at all send an email Planet Money on NPR. Org social media
Facebook Instagram
Twitter app
Play money
Are supervising producer is Alex goldmark our editor Who convinced us to drive this whole thing
Is Brian Earth set
I'm Nick fountain
I'm Karen Duffin
Thanks for listening