One of the things I like best about being able to watch TV online
Is it I can pay a small fee
Skipping bombarded
I think like
Can help my son
Are you God
Mini truck.
Local car commercials
I think we can all agree there
Pretty Tarot
Yeah I think so
I mean they're they're terrible but they're so entertaining
This is Flora Lichtman
But they're not held in by the bounds of
Yeah good taste
Florida hosts the podcast every little thing
And these terrible car ads
It's something she's been looking into on behalf of a listener which is what they do at every little thing they answer questions sent
10 by listeners
And when they ask people to submit their burning
Questions
Amongst
The many things that lister's could have submitted like you know
How do magnets work
How big is the universe
One of the questions
They got was this
All right
My coworkers and I were having a conversation today about local car commercials
And we're wondering
Why are they all so
This is Jamie Cox The Listener who submitted the question
And Chee
Is right
But it's not just the car ads
It's our bad it's that they're like consistently bad in the same kinds of ways
In fact as Flora was looking into this
She noticed that there's actually kind of a pattern to the awfulness
Yes
And it seems to be
First usually a dude and dude with deals
He often calls himself
Crazy
Not a label
That's what these guys called themselves and
This dude with DLC says he's crazy
Usually then prove that by invoking some kind of
Terrible analogy
Ford told me about
Particularly bad one
I don't know
I should say I should just send you the link but
Okay here we go
Actually showing
A big hairy
Your belly and then it like
Six-pack smaller belly
Weight does he want to be
Unstuffed
Is that the goal
He likes his lot stuff
With people are cars
It's okay but preferably by the end of the day he's got the six-pack I think you're applying
More logic to it and it deserves possibly but yeah sure
Hello and welcome to Planet Money
I'm Karen Duffin
And today we go in search of
The patient zero up bad car commercial
And we ask
How did the spread
How is it
Did someone created this
Advertising model that is so bad
And then everyone else said yeah we should definitely also dude
Dancer that we turn over the show to Flora Lichtman and the podcast every little thing
And learn
There might be a method to this madness
This message comes from NPR sponsor squares
Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their own website
Using customizable layout
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online press
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Okay we promised to find someone to blame for all these terrible local car ads
Florida.
You find us someone I did
There's actually one guy you can trade
Yes there is
A locust
Classical that Steven Gilbert he wrote a book about the history of car sales
He's a historian
And a lover of Latin
Now he wasn't sewage era
But there's an actual specific person
Who created this
Forum
Are
Hysteria
The originator
The crazy used car ad
One person
These bad ads
We can blame
Enrollment
Otherwise known
As mad
I do understand that my
Steven told me you actually want to start in a time before use
Scarce
A time that might surprise you
Yes there was
Ammoman
A prelapsarian moment
Prelapsarian
Meaning the biblical time before the fall of Man
Eidetic moment
When car salesmen were actually
What car sales worldwide
I need to be in the time of BS
Before sleazeball
Car salesmen were respect
People thought they were just knowledge
They were trustworthy
This was back in the early night
When the Model T came on the market
A few years later it gets mass-produced and mass production baguettes Mass consumption because
Cars get cheap or at least
Cheap enough that
A car becomes available to the
Middle class
It's no longer luxury
By the 1920s those New Model Tees are now a used Model T
That means even cheaper cars
And that becomes a problem
For new car
They were a sufficient number of used cars
That people had to be induced
To buy new cars
It feels obvious now
But back then this was a new problem
Car Zara
Expensive enough and durable enough
Why would you pay a ton more for a new car if your old ones
Still runs
So car dealerships adapt
They start offering trade-ins buying back cars
And now they sell not just new cars but used one
Giving birth
To the used car sales
And very quickly
They leave the parking lot of
The bad reputation then a car dealers
Begins to take deep root
In the 1920s
Selling used cars Inspire some less than honorable sales tax
On the part of the used car dealers
They were from the very beginning
Considered
Sleaziest
At least honest
The bottom
I'll be automobile biz
And that's because negotiation is baked into you
Used car sales and negotiation in which the seller is at an advantage
It's something Economist call information asymmetry
One person knows more than the other which gives the person in the know in this case
Used car dealer
A huge advance
In human terms
It's a situation where you feel like you might get
There's a famous economics paper all about this Theory and used cars called the market for Less
I mean you don't know where that thing's been
It could have
Literally
Been driven off a cliff and then
Reassembled
That's Jamie Again The Listener who brought us this
Jimmy's right you have no way of knowing
The car's history or condition
But the used car salesman does
Tino's the used car seat
Dirty and otherwise
So used car dealer see the juicy Apple of information AC
Tree and take a big old bite
They become notorious for coming up at Ric
The hide the car's fault
For a while
It was even legal
Legal
To roll back
The speedometer on the odometer
Is a long as you rolled it back to zero
Other tricks included etching Treads into balding tires to make them look younger
Using sawdust or heavy oil to mask
Mechanical problems spiking gasoline with ether to boost performance
And within a few decades
We go from trustworthy new car salesman
Just like talking odometer roll
Used car salesman
Most people would probably consider this
Sleazy reputation an obstacle
A minor
But one used car dealer
Seem to find inspiration in it
Michael Jamie are listener to introduce her to this
Please inspired car dealer because
He is the man we can play
Boj
Comparable local car ads
Who was it
The originator
Of the crazy used car ad
Is Earl month
Better now
Asthmatic
Is that what you said like
God given name Madman
Note to self given name
And here's his deal
Months is a used car dealer in California in the night
He has this idea to buy cars for cheap
In the Midwest and then sell them in
And he teams up with this advertising Mogul Michael
Sure
And it is these two who developed the madman
Persona
The Madman Behind the madness
Yeah exactly
Their strategy was to take the obvious move
IP address
And do the app
On purpose
You have to distinguish itself
Hugo the office
Daisy Cusack
That's media story and Martin Castillo
Any ideas that rather than running away from the terrible used car salesman persona
Run towards
Earl attebury Berry larger-than-life personality so it sure thought
Your eccentric you'll Wild
You're a Madman
So they built an entire ad strategy around months is self-proclaimed
And craziness
Munson the attics
Higher the studio that makes Bugs Bunny to make them a logo which is basically just a picture of months drawn to look like
Napoleon
Which fits the image they're going for it always been one of the
Cliches that if you were crazy you thought you were Napoleon
Jamie
Are you buy a computer
I want you to look at
Logo
I can look on my phone
Oh wait there is
What's a drawing of months as Napoleon wearing classic Napoleon outfit
Like then
But also he's
Strangely in red PJs
Yeah I was I was thinking that that look
A little bit like a onesie
Edmonds himself the actual person not the cartoon also appears as the madman in ads
Pictures
Google it
Mad
Man
Months
I see him next to a billboard I want to give them away but misses months won't let me
She's crazy
Yeah like your name is literally Madman
But he also it's also like you can tell he's not actually
A Madman hits like what you would imagine a Madman
To be like a caricature of a Madman
Yeah it's like I kinda want to know what
He would like in real life
Well I can tell you the answer to that
Right after this
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence
And run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editor
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to launch use the offer code NPR
To save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
So mad
Didn't just invent
Bad car ads
He also patented design for an early TV and in fact
Names his daughter TV
But spelled t e
Vee
He also invents The Four Track cassette which inspires the 8-track
Admonsters inventing method
Is kind of brilliant it actually gets named after him people call it munsing
And munsing was basically
Taking a component
Trying to strip it down to its Bare Essentials to prune away what he felt were the non-essential portions of
Of the components
This is Media historian Martin Castillo
Any ideas
The cheapest version of Saint TV is the one with the fewest part
Someone switches
Start taking away party
Until we got to the point where he clipped off one wire and then if the set went dark you said well I guess we have to keep that one
He's kind of a diss inventor
And it is time he's also kind of a papaya
Like
Bob Hope makes fun of him
The three
Stooges make fun of him the money over in that manner
His used car lot becomes an attraction on Hollywood tours
The same car lot where a new genre of car advertising
Is born
I want to get a sense of who Earl months was you can sort of understand why he took the madman advertising route
But why did other car dealers follow suit
Some experts we talked to say it comes down to the most basic goal of advertising be memorable
And if he says or anything they are hard to
Forget
Any memorable sometimes turns these car dealers into local celebrities so some experts told us that the ads are
Ego thing they bring some amount of Fame
They also said it just comes down to money these kinds of ads are cheap
To make like months is stripped on TV
Stripping down a commercial to say
A stuffed belly doesn't cost that much
And more importantly
It seems to have worked
Jamie Arliss Oregon
Does it
Wolferman's it does seem to have he was reported to have sold over 70 million dollars worth of cars in
In a single year
In present-day money that's like over half a billion dollars
Oh my gosh
But yeah that's
Really impressive
Any approach
Spread for months in the 40s
The Cal Worthington in
60s heels
Two Electronics dealer crazy
Eddie in the 70
80s
And now it's kind of everywhere
Jamie our listeners actually works in marketing so I asked her
Does she think this is a good strategy I mean
He did something right
And it must be working if it's
Got on
Since the 40s
But the thing is like
I just
I don't think I would want to trust a person like that
Steven Gilbert thinks that's
Kind of the point
Here's his theory
The whole thing is to
Create
A
A circus atmosphere
An atmosphere
Excitement and atmosphere of unsureness
Atmosphere
In a way
Help balance out that information
Asymmetry
Where the dealer knows so much more than you about the
The car
Because if the dealer is a mad
Steven stereo
It helps you feel in some odd way
More comfortable like
Sure he knows more about
I'm saner than
So maybe I actually do have an advantage
Maybe they're really getting a good deal
Maybe maybe the
Who sells Midwood
Really have sold it to this price to anybody but his mother
Give me your heart you probably know it
It's not true
Maybe you need
Thank you to every little thing who staff includes Aaron Reese Flora Lichtman
Phoebe Flanigan
The key of Gibbons and Annette Heist
They also had help from Nicole Pacifica
And scoring by Tara Hirsch
To hear more of their answers to their listeners questions
Check out every little thing on Apple podcasts or wherever you listen and if you have any questions for us
Here at Planet Money
You can send them by email Planet Money at npr.org
Or find us on Facebook Twitter or Instagram we're at Planet Money
Also if you have not seen Planet money's new video series Planet Money shorts you really should check them out
They are at npr.org Planet Money shorts that's npr.org
Planet Money shorts
Our latest one is about the economics of graveyards
Nick Fountain and Alexi Horowitz Ghazi from Planet Money helped produce Today Show
Are supervising producer is Alex goldmark and Ryan or status the show I am Karen Duffin thanks for listening