Hi
This is shame
Internship Planet Money
This is going to be a bit of a weird
Episode because
Couple of days ago we got this mysterious
Email
With an audio file attached and
I think what I say
Do
Is just play this audio file for
Okay
Here you go
Check check one two came alone here
Yeah that is what it said but yeah it's not what I expected either
It is Sunday October 28th walking up to a creepy manor house
Its 10:56 at night
Weird definitely was not supposed to rain tonight
Lights on top there are weird purple Vines everywhere
Really creepy
Set
Living at this address was
Plain-spoken Professor who toxic
Exclusively in metaphors and anecdotes and could explain to us how the market for Florida avocados explain the entire global
Nephrite
Penis alley Florida avocados
Hiley Hyundai
Planet Money it's 10:58
We have no time
Sorry we're late I please step inside
Okay follow me
I'm really sorry Professor do you mind
Turn off the music just I don't know why I can't control it
Please
I need you to follow me this is a you have a portrait Ben Bernanke
Yes
His eyes are following us
Okay
7 size
Step inside
Juilliard
Just in time
Yeah here we are
I guess why don't you
Baby blocks with a theremin music and
Can you just give me your name and title
I'm not at 4
Professor II made that
Professor story up to trick you into coming here
The Florida avocado
They're terrible and explain nothing about the world economy
Actually
The caretaker of this house
And there's something you need
Andrew Ross Sorkin too-big-to-fail just blew up that show
Tim Geithner Stress Test why did why did all of these financial crisis books have to be 500 pages long
Flying off of the Shelf caretaker what's going on
Yes
This is what I needed you to see
Every night when the clock strikes 11
Crazy
Portrait of Ben Bernanke starts walking
Take me to Sonic
Listen
I would have hired some paranormal
All of this
It all seems to be related to 2008
2 to the financial crisis
I didn't know what else
So I called
Planet Money and you want us to you have until the clock strikes midnight
Florida house
Spell save you the trouble
There's no cell phone reception here all the doors are locked
The only outdoor space you can access at the cemetery with 15 foot wall
You're not allowed in the basement and
One less
Piece of advice take a look at the bookshelf
Sally there's only one book left
Crashed how a decade of financial crises changed the world the Adam tooze books thank God that didn't fly it's like 700
100 pages I mean
If you just try to pull it off the shelf secret tunnel
Do olives have to shout into every Lord space is how we show up at the room is
Caretaker until midnight
She's gone
So now we are alone
Trapped in a haunted house
Okay not great not great
But let's think this through reasonably
Split up
Without the Bernanke portrait
The two of you should split up to explore the house
Probably a good idea I'll pick secret tunnel
Do you have your iPhone to record yourself
No I turned on the voice memo recorder and then secretly planted it on that caretaker
Nothing weird about her
She totally reminded me of somebody but you still need a recorder so here take my cell phone
What's with your battery don't go until you absolutely need to let's do this
Shutting down now
Support for NPR comes from LinkedIn learning
Proud to support the launch of life
NPR Sky to help you make better life decision
LinkedIn learning short video tutorials cover business Tech and creative skills employers look for at
Every level
All talk by XP
And new courses are added every week
+ LinkedIn learning is
Personalized
Recommended courses based on your income
And wife
Kid listeners get a month of learning
Free start your free trial
At LinkedIn learning.com NPR
Test one two test one two okay
Is that 11:15 p.m.
I am in the car
Conservatory
Apparently I have 45 minutes to wander around this haunted house and I guess
Let's find out what ghost from 2008 or so
Accommodation
Are you kidding me another talkin fed portrait
This time Alan Greenspan
Accommodation can be made for a
Measured course
Poisonous
Stereo pad
This is impenetrable fed speed
I can't
Sally
Irrational exuberance is
Conceptually identical
2 and the inverse of stagnation I know you're trying to tell me something but I have no idea what you're
Fine
How's this
Go outside
Oh
Okay
I will go into the graveyard Sherman
So
Why headstones out here
Here lies wage growth
Dead since 1970s
And my husband over here
Rip
Sally Helm
That's me straight
Are you
Are you zombie
Me
Your
Dad you're like 80 years old I'm rich Sally
I'm rich salad
Dicey
You are wearing a fancy ball gown and have a diamond ring on each finger I'm the version of you that died
Biden 2008
The financial crisis
Crushed American GDP
That cost you around
$70,000 over your life
And that's just the per capita measure estimated by the San Francisco fed
The real cost
Is what happened to your mind
My mind
You
Your whole generation
Afraid to buy home
Afraid to start Building Wealth
Parents
Yeah I mean
I guess I do feel like there's a pretty good chance I'll never own a home I bought the most beautiful
By the ocean in Maine
I live there
But you don't get to
Can you please tell me about the stuff the financial collapse
Didn't ruin for me
Like
How Did I Get Married Too ever learn to play the mandolin
Who was the living at the end of Game of Thrones
Oh my God I forgot you haven't seen it yet
So
Cersei and Jon Snow
Which
Have to be authorized
Please tell me
Hello hello
Secret tunnel
Opens up to the
Kitchen
Which opens up into
The ballroom
And now the ballroom piano is playing by itself
Willow
Wait
Is it hyperinflation does hyperinflation scare me
Stagflation
Heartless of can you just like
Show yourself please it is
Very hard to talk to disembodied
Voice
You're like
Victorian Schoolboy ghost
Are used to be a school
Oh boy
Now I work from home full-time trading cryptocurrency oh my God yeah
Cryptocurrency is what scares me I'm I'm totally scared of missing out while everyone in
Cleaning apparently a child ghost
Makes money
Yeah but at the same time
What year was Super Bowl
Study know your daughter is why you were saying that we become too speculative bubble I just it's my maximum phone
Como you got me that's my fear fear of missing out
It seems
Like a very new fear I thought this house was full of 2008
You're right
The story you need to hear I call it
Machining crypto ghost is just made an old Gateway desktop computer up here
Look at me
Oh that's the code that created the first cryptocurrency
30 Bitcoin it was
Written by by shadowy figure known as
Satoshi Nakamoto
People started
Chicken
Eventually
Oh my God
Is that a
A secret message left by Satoshi Nakamoto
Kitten inside
The name of the petition
State the headline from the front page that day
Okay it says
The times
January 3rd
Chancellor on brink
A second bailout for
Suzie candy balloon
Get sure sure
It all comes back to the bottom
It is a Satoshi we're saying I'm
Creating this new currency because
Every
Sing
We trusted has failed as the
The banks the
The government
What's been haunting you and me and all of us since 2008
Little
Whisper
The boys in the bathroom
Every
Neutron
Baby shower
Pronounce
Ghost
Are you be there
In another I think about it
Satoshi Nakamoto berries an actual secret message in the code of Bitcoin that seem super unlikely right
Hate hate crypto ghost
If that story is 100% true
Can you just
Give Me A Sign
Like a sign
Surreal
True
Oh crap also it's true
Saving battery
Hello hello check check
Billiards room
Old timey gramophone playing
This is
Super weird there is also a landline phone in here and check this out when you pick it up
Like what
I didn't even dial everything it does that every time
Adam tooze
Time to
Adam tooze author of the 700-page book
Crashed how a decade of financial crises changed the world
Yes I've no idea what's going on I've gotten hundreds of course
Who is this
I'm sorry I'm in a haunted house and
It appears the only person the house will let me call is you
What's my day like 5 minutes to go before the clock strikes midnight
Mancha
Yeah right
What do you want to talk
Well
Okay this house is already shown me how I'm
Personally being haunted by 2008
But that's not the whole story I mean how is this haunting American society
What the crisis date was to really split
The American labor market into two pieces
The jobs available to Americans with High School Educational last
Massacre
The bubble in trouble
On the other hand you have the Americas
Comes back from this crisis
College grad
The Bay Area in Manhattan
I miss you in one of the Dynamics hotspots
The US economy
You put all this behind you and I won't even
The Memphis 2000
Okay
Splintering job market growing equality
Attended in American families before Saturday
By the crisis has the largest full smooth
What's the Dust Bowl
I'm sorry those people
Did they lose that fell down the well Slaughter
So
We talked about the recovery but
For a lot of people there hasn't
Really been
Adam the clock striking midnight here I have no idea what's about to happen but I've got to get
Back to the haunted study
By the way they loved your book here and open the secret tunnel
House is kind of shaking this does not seem Optima
Hello hello okay so no big deal
The house appears to be coming to life
Come to the front door I think the house is coming to life I have to tell you
I have to tell you about which side
Okay
Can talk on the show
I'm just worried
Read about what
Find another house now
Not that really
All clear
Abby
Double check
Find words
I'm watching some kind of
Flashback
When are we
House
September 6th
Volume up
Because his family is moving out
Mom
Do you think I'll be able to go to the same school
Pussy
A house with a ballroom
Thunder Conservatory
What's an adjustable rate mortgage
Pornography
Underwater
I'm down suddenly
You get the final check a b
Yes
Everything is cleared out there's nothing left behind
Alright
All right
If there was something
Next to the candlestick
How do you spell MP3 player
I'm going to explain in a second foot first
Tell you I am
We're calling it Planet Money
Episode of her MP3 player to automatically download and play
Episode
What there open Wi-Fi in here this whole time
You were my friend
Housing Maniacs that are tight at money
What are you going through
Chapter 1 in the life of
Tempting
Today on the show
Upside down world
I love that episode
Kayla to the greatest
And the financial crisis
We didn't forget I mean we had to move on as a show as a global economy
I cannot even imagine
I know I know just
Open the doors
Settle
Kenny
Get Sally I'm over here
It is pitch
Black humor in the Forbidden basement right
Our 100%
Totally in Forbidden
Planet Money Robert Smith
I thought you were supposed to be off during summer
Prestigious Fellowship
That was
The plan but I got lured into this house by a fake story about a
Cube satellite
Cartel Robert how do I get some light in here
I got your light right here I thought you were
So it's going up to report MacBook
I was told on good information
But there was this town
That was still on the gold standard and was doing Universal basic income dream come true
No here I would have been a good story
Jacobsen stuck here longer than I have
Actually learn how to make candles
Ear wax
I got your candles right here
So many candles
Well
This basement is
Literally a crappy podcasting Studio
Congratulations you're now part of the haunted houses new family
Podcast version of the existentialist nightmare
We have to be in this house forever making podcast about the financial crisis
That no one will ever live
Can I ask you guys a question
Just a caretaker remind you of anyone
So familiar I cannot put my finger on it yet totally
We couldn't place it either
Oh no
I just remembered I secretly planted my iPhone and that care different Pockets a lot of good that does Us in the basement now
Here's something that could happen
I keep my phone in one of those special cases with extra juice
Right
Arabic word for I don't know days on end
Makes sense
And if his house as open WiFi
My recording should automatically back up to the secret Planet Money
But yeah you're right we'll never got to hear it down here in the basement
Oh crap my record is about to die
I have something that I need to tell you because I have spent
These months
Hi
This is Shane
Planet Money intern again
So that is where the
File cuts off
Read server weird what is this
Sally
Phone recording
At 72 hours long
Okay they might want me to transcribe this whole thing so I'll be right back
This message comes from NPR sponsors
Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their own webs
Using customizable layout
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online presence
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
You the offer code NPR
How to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
So I quickly went through that 72 hour-long recording and
Most of it is just like
Pocket sounds and some lady humming to herself
But
There's this super weird bit at
At the very end
It seems important I don't know I'm just saying the planet money in
Turn butts
I think if I play this bit for you it might explain like
Everything
Okay
Here you go
Have you been watching any
You don't let me out TV man
Yes
While wandering around me
Listen
Everyone's in the basement
Never see me anyway do I really need to be in this caretaker disguise right now
Change back
And I've been thinking I'm
When are planets this planet money family of yours is going to be pretty big so
If you could afford to let me go
Georgia power Federal Credit Union
Your my first friend
Okay
It's
I have this whole other company right now and
And the new show called without fail that
Hosting in
Karen Duffin
Imported Garcia
Yeah we know that's a lie and Kenny and Robert and also Jacob were all in there
Sally in Chinese recording
The rescue email with these recordings and detail directions to the house
Oh crap this is a total trap
Hello
I mean hello and welcome Planet Money
I found these credits on K Mullins desk
They say
Please tell the world they should be listening to a podcast called
Twenty thousand Hertz
Made by professional sound designers
Patel's amazing stories about the most famous sounds in the world
And there's a little note here Kenny Reitz
If I ever make a weird Halloween episode of Planet Money
I would absolutely make that in collaboration with the amazing team that makes twenty thousand Hertz
Alex goldmark is Planet Money supervising producer Brian Atwood editar stories if he were here
Special thanks to Ari Berliner Neil route
Kathy home
Hannah Sampson
Seneca stag
Carlos Rafael Rivera and Spencer Gaffney
And if
Looks like there's one final note here from Kenny
Theoretically I ever needed someone to pretend to be the knowing caretaker of haunted
House or the Victorian child ghost
I would definitely use voice actor
Jan John's
That's all that's written here
If you have any thoughts about haunted houses
Hit me up
Planet Money at NPR. Org
I'm saying the Planet Money intern
Thanks for listening
I guess
Okay I don't know how to
Shutters