Support for Planet Money
And the following message
Did come from Michigan Economic Development
Incorporation Cy Michigan
It's attracting top talent and pop business
By searching Michigan pure opportunity
Hey it's Allie home here
The other day I did something we do all the
Time. When a bunny
I called up an expert to help me understand something
In this case
I called a fundraising expert Paul Edwards
Because I wanted to know
How do you ask
People for money
Have you raised
Billions of dollars in your life
Organizations
That I help
In the campaign for the engage me have indeed raised
Billions of dollars
Paul's been doing this for decades helping universities other organizations raise money
I asked him how I might get you
R2 listener to support our journalism by going to donate
Dot NPR. Org / Planet Money
You told me about this theory of fundraising that has
To do with a
Hierarchy of questions
Because you got to know what different questions do
And you got to be able to use them all
At the lower end
The questions which
We might call them closed-ended questions
Yes no
Focus the conversation
But there are questions which are
Which who where when they're little higher up on the level those look at people
Thinking about their lives maybe even feeling some feelings
And then throw the most complex
Emotional questions of all top of the hierarchy are why questions
Why do you listen to Planet Money
Think about it
And then maybe go to donate
. npr.org
Flash Planet Money
There's something happening in China right now that revolves around
One particular company
And it tells us so much about the
Current trade fight with
China we've been following this
So closely and yet
We are still
So we called of NPR's Shanghai correspondent Rob Schmitz in the middle of the night to help us figure this out
Robinson morning there
You just got in it is morning here I had to tell you about five times I tell the same thing over and over
We called Rob because of this story that starts at the G20 Summit in Buenos Aires
Argentina on December
The leaders of the largest 20 economies on the planet that group of 20
The G20
Get together
To work out different
Huge International
Trump and Chinese leader Xi Jinping are sitting across from each other
Ready to
Talk trade War
Remember all the back-and-forth tariffs on Porkins
Steel I was paying attention to the bourbon and motorcycles in China
I'm looking at all the news wires and getting reports from other NPR reporters who are there and then suddenly the meat
Meeting is over
And the first thing I see
Is
A statement from the Chinese government saying there is a truce people kiss in the streets
Have no
Nobody is kissing in the streets
I think people were
Kind of scratching their heads
That's what that was okay almost
The White House in China agreed to hold off on any new tariffs
490 days
While they try to reach
Meanwhile on the other side of the world something is happening that is putting the trade truce in danger that very day
December 1st
A woman
Is changing planes in Vancouver Canada
And she is arrested
By Canadian authorities ended
Detained
And this is
The Chief Financial Officer
Of Huawei
One of China's
Largest and most
Important comp
Huawei is an enormous company in China the largest Telecom equipment company in
The world it sells more phones
An apple
And the woman who was arrested among long show is not just a Chief Financial Officer
The company
She is the daughter of the founder this is like if Bill Gates his daughter was arrested
And Canada has arrested her on behalf
Of the United
And at first no one really seems to know why she was arrested the Canadians won't say which is
Weird they're usually so nice
I'm surprised I didn't apologize to
So what are people saying like in China what is the coverage like does this seem like a big deal like
The Chinese State media
Had a difficult
Time not seeing this as a
Politically motivated
Arrest us immediately felt like Trump doing something
China absolutely
It felt like the United States
Was taking
A very high-profile Chinese executive hostage
As part of a plan to
Put leverage on China during the trade talk
It looks to China
Like a hostage
A prisoner of the trade War
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I Am branders that I'm Sarah Gonzales
And I'm Rob Schmitz Shanghai
Correspond
And I'm Rob Schmitz what am I are you
The earlier I'll do that again and I'm Rob Schmitz Shanghai correspondent for National Public Radio
It's the story of the rise of China in their experiment with capitalism
We trace a series of events that started on one day in three cities
Renovated Beijing and Vancouver with major
Support also comes from Fidelity in
As a Fidelity Wealth Management
You get a dedicated advice
To help grow and protect
Find ways to minimize the impact
Taxes and make
Clear recommendations
For your full Financial
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
At the heart of the story is a company
Called
Chloe they make cell phone
They make routers they make equipment for cell towers
They are developing networks so good they are five g4g like what we have they went one better
But you don't really see Huawei phones in the US
Because the government doesn't want us to
To have them cell phone providers
Don't offer up Huawei phone
NS company explains so much about our current fight with China and even the story of capitalism in China and it was started by one guy
Ren zhengfei Ren zhengfei was born
In the poorest province
In China
He was born there in 1940
For just
Before communist
Took over China
He ended up going to a very good school for engineering
And then he joined Chinese Army
What stone is the people's Liberation Army on
Are the pla
So how did it go from communist Army to founding
Huawei
Is discharged and
He moves
To Shenzhen
Shenzhen at the
The time
Was
This new economic zone
That was being set up
That would operate differently
Wrestler Chyna
In that companies
You could have privatized company
Chinese companies could
Compete with each other
They weren't just Allstate
Companies in 1980
China sets aside a little chunk of
The country near Hong Kong
Draw the line around it and says
Okay
Go try capitalism
Pierre it's called Ash engine special economic zone and it is a huge part of Chinese economic history
It's one of the first turns away from communism one of those
Pivotal moments that changed the neck
Next 40 years
Duran
Is there from the beginning
Is he goes there
And he raises around 21,000 Renminbi at the time that's around $2,000
And starts
His company called Huawei and grows and grows
It's one of the companies that turns China into the second largest economy in the world
And it is a perfect symbol of everything the China wants to be high-tech innovation
Stampy Cat
It is a
Beautiful and very bizarre campus
There are different
Parts of a campus that are in different architectural styles
Example of one of the main buildings looks like the White House
What is this
A tribute to
America
I don't think it's
I think you'd have to ask when John feijoo does not talk to
To the Press but
At the time that it was built
This camp
I think that the United States
This was
Aspirational
And
At that time a lot of
Different buildings in China were made to look like
Well-known buildings
It's just feels like an awkward building to have in the middle of your campus while your daughter is under arrest
Yeah but back then you know I don't think you know when one far away is stablished
Just campus
You know the relationship between the US and China was fine which is so point that they literally have a White House in the middle of the camp
China wanted to learn from the US
That's what this experiment was all about in the US
One China to grow us was like we fought communism for years we want you to turn to capitalism
We think it'll make you turn to democracy and into an ally what's happening China is different
Where capitalism has not brought democracy
In China
Is only
Kind of our Ally and more and more our rival
And yes technically Huawei is a private company but
In China nothing is really a private company
Exactly the way it is in the United States
Huawei like most large companies in the country has to have a Chinese Communist Party Committee inside the
So numbers of US Congress
Our little worried about Huawei this massive company
Growing
It's faster than any other company
And making all of this telecommunications equipment
Why they might be under the thumb of the Communist Party
Even though they're private
2012 Commerce says no company that's employing Huawei technology should work with the US government
October
Of that year
US Congress
I issued a blistering
Bipartisan
Report
That
Accuse Huawei and its competitor in China.
Te
Of being arms of the Chinese government
They also accused them of stealing intellectual property
American companies
And they accused them
Having the
That the potential
Despite America
Kids with their equipment
Congress is worried that Huawei is a straight up
Front for the Chinese government
But if America build cell towers used
Huawei technology
The Chinese government will use them to
Spion maybe everything in amer
And that's why you don't see much
Shuffle away stuff in the United
But there is still the
Rest of the world Huawei is
Is huge in Africa Europe the Middle East
It's in
170 countries
Including Iran here is where we get back to the arrest of mom
According to us authorities
Hmong had done business with
Iran while they were under sanction
About 10 years
And based on that
This past summer the US issued a warrant for
Was not made public
But the US toll Canada
She said that
Arrest her and send her to us
So when Mom gets off of
Cathay Pacific flight 838 in Vancouver on December 1st
The Royal Canadian Mounted Police are there waiting
Looking for her in the mountains are there on behalf of United
And this is on the same day that Trump is sitting down across from Chinese president so
Trump and XI you're sitting at the
Disabled
Meanwhile
The daughter
Of the founder of the second-largest
Company in China
Is being arrested
Did Trump know
From what John Bolton told
NPR in
His exclusive interview with us
President Trump did not know
John Bolton is Trump's National Security advisor a real Hawk on China
Bolton himself said that he
He himself knew about it
But that
The president did not
The rest becomes public and the Chinese press goes while they say the United States are resorting to
Despicable hooligan
And China threatens Canada
What grave consequence
Mom is not freed immediately
And no one knows exactly what this
But everyone is pretty short
What is going to affect
The trade war is sitting in a Canadian jail and press
Computers are like
We can't let her go on bail she has all the money in the world she's just going to get on a plane and leave
They argue about this
Her defense team says
Look she's got health problems she has hypertension
She's not a Flight Risk
+ +
If she
Did Escape
Custody in Canada
And go back to China this would
This would mean that she would lose face for her
Herself
For her father for a company
And for China
And then the defense lawyer proceeded to explain the concept of
Face
To the judge and
To the court
It was
I think a lot of China Watchers
Had a collective eye roll in response to
To this because
Oftentimes
You know this type of thing
The idea that the
Chinese are so mystically different from the rest of
The world
And that's only the Chinese would understand this
Is is commonly used as a
Defense
Mumford up around 10 million Canadian dollars
To be let out on house arrest
She gets an ankle bracelet and she is now paying for her own surveillance at her fancy house in Vancouver
Canada will decide later whether or not.
Turn her over to the US
And she's put under house arrest we start to see some of those
Grave
And they're real
On December 11th China takes Michael coverage
Former Canadian Diplomat into custody
And it looks exactly like
Retaliation
Can four monks arrest
Have a good night they take another Canadian indica
Michael spafford
You going to take one
We're going to take two
That's a message that the Chinese would understand
Immediately
Because this is exactly
Play how
China's authoritarian government Opera
The United States doesn't really arrest random people or hand over prisoners when they're trying to settle trade disputes
That President Trump recently told Reuters that
He would intervene in Mom's case
If it would help trade negotiate
People
Went ballistic
Check the criminal justice system in the United States is totally
Not supposed to be a tool
Of the president
Definitely not a trade negotiating tool runs counter to
Just it is probably everything yeah
I can't
How much of this is just the inevitable clash between two giant economies and how much is this
Two people
She in the plaza
I think it's bigger than 2 personalities I think that she's even peeing
Is the
Face of a certain
Part of China that was always there
But he's just bringing it out
And this is not how China's former leaders like dumb shopping used to handle thing
You know
China for a long time operated under this Maxim
That was
Coined by former leader Deng Xiaoping and that was
Hide your strength
And baijiu
Your time
Hiding by
Which means basically
Don't let
Other countries see
How far are you
You've come
And what you're capable of doing
Because it gives too much away
And xi jinping operates by completely different Principe
He wants to show the world that China
Is
A force to be reckoned with
And that China is
Is actually a guiding
Model
Of what a country
That model is authoritarian
State-controlled capitalism
Capitalism with Santa
Restrictions on freedoms
And the problem now is that there are two enormous countries that both want to be the guiding model for what a country
Hangzhou and
To Canadian
So far
Are trapped in the middle
Support for this podcast
Send the following message
Should come from fidelity
As a Fidelity wealth
You get a dedicated advisor to help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of Pacs
And make it clear recommendation
Games for your full Financial
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage service
LLC
Got a hot tip an emergency a political standoff
Emails Planet Money NPR. Org
Today Show was produced by Darren woods and Sally helm
Special thanks to Echo Wong
Planet Money supervising producer is Alex goldmark
I'm Bryant urstadt I'm there when that is
And I am definitely Rob Schmitz
At least I think I am
Thanks for listening
I think we should just Google and make sure something else hasn't happened because literally as every time I sit down something
It it's a good bet Something's Happened in the hour that we
We've been speaking