Support for this in
NPR podcasts
The following message come from The UPS Store
Offering services from shredding
To printing to mailbox
And instead of closing this Memorial Day we
May 24th and 25th
The UPS Store
He's doing another thing
All together
Opening
The UPS Store
Everything for small business
And of course shipping
Hey everyone just a quick note this show is a rerun
It was originally reported in 2015 when California was suffering through a long
Fierce trout
At the end of the show will give you an update on where things stand now
The drought in California has made life
Inconvenient for a lot of
People there
In a lot of way
If you hear about people not being watched
The cars
In the brown lawn
People taking slightly shorter showers
Are there places where people
Hats
Where they get their water
Are actually running
Dry where you go to the faucet turn it on and nothing comes out
And that is happening in a city called Porterville California
It's about an hour south of Fresno
The used to get their water from
Wells
Outfit supplied their homes
And the wells aren't deep enough
To reach the water ending
And their taps
Actually went drive to have no water in their house
So what are they do how do they get water just to live their daily life
The city has set up these kind of temporary facilities portable showers and sinks
I went and visited one it was in the parking lot
Epic Church
And the kind of look like an airplane bathroom
They had little benches and shower heads and a curtain
And out in the
The blazing hot afternoon sun or Rose of sinx
With mirrors
A people come there in the morning and shaved
Before work
It was a really grim and while I was walking around
A car pulled up and Karen Hendrickson roll
Window down
So what were you hoping to get today water today
Pourhouse the drinking water
Is our well is dry so you come here for support on drinking water
How long ago did your well go dry it's been a year already
Wow it's been a year
The city is helping Karen out it dropped a big
Tank of water off at her house it's it's right next door house on the school stand and they fill it up
A couple times a month
So Karen can take showers but the water is not drinkable Karen can't wash her dishes
She's with it so she has to come here a few times a week
Wait to pick up
Bottled water whatever has been donated for her household
My daughter she has twins
Oh baby twins
A boy and a girl
Yeah that must be hard with no water
How often do you come here
At least one couple times a week
Maya my daughter
She comes in and I come so could we drink a lot of water
A lot
Karen asked the security guard Jimmy water today
The security guard says no we're out
I come back tomorrow
Things heartbreaking about all of this
Is that there is
Actually water
Still left
In the valley there is water literally below
Karen's home there's a giant aquifer
Entering used to tap into it with her well
But the level is getting lower and lower
And lower so she and her neighbors can't reach anymore
It's like this race
To get the water
Karen
And the people here locked out of the way
There are people still getting this water
People who are still in this
Not that far away from Karen's house
You see it
Acres and Acres of lush farmland
Corn cotton tomatoes
Pistachio trees walnuts almonds
This is where Karen's water went
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Stacey Vanek Smith Robert Smith today on the show The screwed up
Economics
Why the most lucrative thing you can do right now in California
Is to use more and more and more of the scarce resource water
Are almonds grown or pistachios
And beat out your competitors
Sweet sweet water at the bottom of the well
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Fidelity invest
As a Fidelity wealth management client
You get a dedicated advisor to help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes and make clear recommendation
Thanks for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
Marquardt Farms 3000 acres in California Central Valley
Mark is a very energetic I super organized
He likes to pay Bliss to the steering wheel of his truck is that a to-do list on your steering wheel
We're in Mark's truck and we're driving across
Costas Farm
His field stretch as far as the eye can see
Beautiful black eyed peas and corn and pistachio trees
It's incredibly Lush and green
And the reason for this is that Mark storm sits on top of that aquifer
The same aquifer that Karen's house well
Except he's better getting to the water
He is better at getting to the water
But it's getting harder and harder even for Mark the level of the aquifer has been dropping
Really fast
I'm dropping 10 feet a week
Which term meaning 10ft a week
10 Peter week in fact half of the wheels on his 3000 acres have dried up
He chose me
That sucks
Should be producing water
It's not
See if there's any water in it
This is a good sound you like
Mark fix a rock up off the ground and he throws it into the well pipe sticking out of the ground
You was right I like the sound
Water
Oh is that with their wife Gloria
That's what you water down there
But the pump that was here
Wouldn't reach that water anymore have to deepen it
Mark is deepening Wells as fast as
And he's also putting in new well
She's putting 8 at a cost of around $2000000
And the reason for this is all around us
Pistachio tree
They're little baby ones he's just planted there like up to your hip Titan diesel
Steaks
And there are bigger ones in the next field within clusters
Of pistachios almonds
These are the pistachios
There you can see it's about half developed
It's a green
These little pistachios are very
Thirsty
It takes almost a gallon of water to grow one pistachio and a gallon of water to grow an almond
Nut trees are some of the thirstiest crops around
And yet
Here we are in the middle of a drought
And Mark is planning pistachio trees as fast as he can
Why are you planting
So many new trees right now
We just think it's financially it's the right decision to make once they get up into production
How to make good money
So there are they pretty profitable pistachios
I mean what wildly
Really
Actually 10 times more profitable than most other crops
Are pistachios marketing make $10,000 an acre
The most epic raps
$1,000
The reason for this is both Supply
And demand the demand part is that people are eating more nuts
China and India are
Discovering them until there's a much bigger Market
For not spot
Supply-side is awesome
The reason why they can make so much money
Office Depot
Crops is
Cuz of the drow
The drought has made pistachios and almonds
Harder to grow
And as a result the price has naturally shot
So everyone is planting
And when you drive to California Central Valley it's striking
All of the fields are these new trees farmers are ripping out their old crops and putting in
And it becomes will probably hear the stories about hedge funds and Big Bang
Buying California farmland
Implanting almond and pistachio
Because hedge funds and banks have plenty of cash upfront to drill
These really deep well
Happy Aquaphor
Get the water first
And the path for them could be huge
It's kind of funny to imagine these Bankers looking over Maps
The California Farmland in deciding what
Crops to plant
But apparently that's what happened
I talked to a scientist at Nasa water scientist his name is James family Eddie
And he told me he's getting calls all the time from Bankers and business people
Asking him is this a good time to get into the nut growing
People ask me about it all the time and
I do feel a conflict I generally don't respond
I don't want to encourage someone to go make a short term investment that would that would use up a lot of water
That's just my own personal bias
So it is a smart short-term Investments
Of course my time there's a dwindling resource
Right if you can if you can get it to the market sure of course
And this right here is the problem in California right now
When you have a scarce resource like water
The right thing to do from a public policy perspective
Is to find ways to conserve it right to make sure there is enough water
For everyone that's the right
But the market incentive is to use as much water as possible before your neighbors
You should plant nuts
Wildmutt prices are high that's
Basic economic logic
Go go go
And this is being reinforced by the market right now
Because crops that do well in droughts
They do not bring in that
Much money and if you're running a farm and spending hundreds of thousand
Dollars to drill new wells
You are not going to make that money back
Planting drought-friendly crops
Iran the Spy Mark wipes
I mean should you be planning something like
Flaxseed or safflower here instead of
Pistachio trees
Isis
Should I be planting
I don't know I mean
We're trying to make money here
Economist have a term
For this race for scarce resource this dilemma
And you probably heard it even if you haven't taken economics classes called
The tragedy of the commons
If you have a shared resource say a meadow where your cows graze or an underground Lake
People will use as much of it as they can't they will use a public resource until it's gone
And the reason that they call this
The tragedy is not that there are any
Bad guys in the scenario is it actually everybody is acting rationally
It's just that what is good for the individual and what is good for the group are totally different
Take more qualities of statue farmer if he were to cut back his water use
He would just lose out
His neighbors would use the water hedge funds would you
He's the water they would make the $10,000 an acre and he would be stuck with a bunch of safflower that's not worth very much
Drilling deeper and his neighbor's look at that invade Realty for 2
And this race this race were talking about because
Testing in this race you got to pick up the phone and call somebody like Steve Arthur
So do you mind reading the back of your truck
That just says Arthur and Orum well drilling Fresno
We leave you at
That's amazing
That's amazing is always what I say when I don't know what to
Arthur runs one of the biggest drilling companies in the area
And he actually mostly works out of
Hebrides it from real site to drill site all day
I get 40 or 50 calls a day easy
I can't even keep track of what the office gif
All the farmers are
Completely running out of water
So how long is the wait to get a well-drilled
Realistically
At least a year
Wells around here used to be about 200
But these days Steve is drilling Wells that are as much as to
Thousand
His company has started buying equipment off of oil drilling company
He's like fracking companies in order to get deep enough to get to the water
Years ago nobody had equipment in the area to go that deep
And modern technology
Taking care of that now so
We started drilling deeper up there that's what we found aquifers nobody's ever touch
And you know how this app to go deeper and deeper you take more and more water out of an aqua
Eventually
It is going to go away
And when we talked to the water scientist we asked him
How much is left at the space and he said
Maybe
50 years 50 years worth of water in the aquifer at the outside
And when I asked him what would happen when the water ran out what that would look like
He actually reference the movie
Mad Max
Asking people driving around
The desert
Fighting each other for water
Thunderdome
Because that is one of the logical ways that
This app the water
Goes away the wells go dry and all the sudden knowing Chris pistachios anymore no one grows anything
We're talking about functionally a dust bowl happen
In the Central Valley
Another ending could be regulation
Government steps in and says hey
You have to limit your water use you can only drill this deep
But so far the state has been reluctant to do
There is one other option that one solution to
The tragedy of the commons
In fact there's an economist named Ellen arrastra we've talked about her here before I'm Planet Money she won a Nobel Prize for her
Work on the tragedy of the commons
In 2009
And her work showed that sometimes this does not end badly
And somebody doesn't end in the government coming in putting on these rules and regulations
She said that people can come together
And work out a solution for themselves they can basically
Put the interests of their group
Ahead of their immediate
Sort of
Decide not
Trace but this is not easy as you can imagine because basically you have to convince people to give up their personal short
Interest for the long-term interests of the
And this is not exactly how humans are built this is just not what we tend to do next
But
I did manage to find some peace
People who are trying it north of Marchetti's pistachio Farm in a town near sacrum
Their story
Coming up after the
Support for this podcast and the following message come from fidelity
Has a Fidelity wealth management client you get a dedicated advisor to help
Grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes and make clear recommendations
Thanks for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
Hi my name is Jorge Heartland
I'm an attorney
Lawyer
In Texas
They call us Liars
George has been working with farmers in this area
His whole career when we looked around he saw the same things happening there as what's happening down south
The community was running out of water everyone was using as much as they could as fast
And he thought to himself
This race that's happening is going to end
We should get together and try to stop it
Because sooner or later
The government
We'll come in and when our water use
We don't know when and we don't know
How much
So he got a group of farmers together about 500 of them
In Stockton California
And he said within I have a proposal
Why don't we voluntarily cut our water use
25%
And if we do that
The government has said it will not come in later and
What are water
This way
You got certainty
You know what you can do you can play in your survival
Which must have been hard for the farmers there because basically
In this community
Water
Is Muddy Water meant crops crops me money and he's basically coming in and saying to them
I want you to take a
25%
A lot of the farmers really didn't want to do that
There were a lot of folks who thought it was extortion
They didn't like it
But Indian
Half of the farmers signed up to do this and Paula does Nair was one of the
It's costly
It's not ideal for this is your livelihood
Pilot was a dairy farm in Lodi California
And she grows a lot of corn for her cows
Or her girls
As she calls them
Using 25% less water will mean pilot will have to
Buy a lot of the
Cows and that is a lot more expensive
And that means the best all is going to be able to do this year
Is breaking
But part of the deal because she's been hearing all of the
These horror stories about her neighbors getting their water cut off
Entirely as in the government coming in and saying no more water
And the farmers are stuck
The crops are halfway grown if no water to
Stilt the decision weighs on her
Is there a feeling of like we're all in this together I don't know is there that feeling at all
I think I felt that way that I want to do what I
And you want to do what your part
You want to make I hope that everyone is doing their part because it is it is
Financial burden
You can hear her anxiety in that laugh because this particular solution to the
Tragedy of the commons
Can be brutal
If it turns out that the government
Does not put any new rule
Who plays the government does not
Make you cut back on your water
Then you just giving up your profits
For nothing
But you will feel like a chump
You cut back
And perhaps
Your neighbors didn't do it the same time perhaps baked at drinking water while you alone cut back
And maybe you get to drink more water because you gave up a big portion
Of yours
George Hartman the water lawyer told me this is his biggest
What are you going to say to the folks who took the hit
And
I don't know I think the answer is you pays your money and you takes your chances that's
Really what it is
And if it turns out that you would have done better
Not being in program okay
But
Do you want to bet the farm on it
The farmer started cutting back last month and so far people seem to be sticking to it and it's gotten a lot of people asking
Could this work in other parts
California
Is this possibly a solution to the drought
I put this question to Mark Whitey the pistachio farmer with the dry Wells
I asked the farmers in his area might come together in the same way
Would something like that work here is like everybody got together and agreed to
Use
Last
You mean as far as
Don't pump as much or something like that
I just
How come
I don't know I just
A group of
Number one you could you couldn't get consensus
If you had fought only five Farmers I don't think you could get consensus
If you got 500 Farmers I know you couldn't get a consent
So I just don't think it would be effective
Google thing to try
I mean right now
You know you just
Did there is water down there
And you got Haves and Have Nots
And the haves
I don't think we'll be in a mood to share with the Have Nots
Sohi eye
This was another thing that Elinor Ostrom the Nobel Prize winner
Discovered in her work on the tragedy
The commons
For a group to solve this problem on its own
The group needs to be small
That group Upstate with the dairy farm
They were fighting over surface-water local rivers and dams it was a smaller community
The aquifer has thousands and thousands of farmers
With their well sticking down into it
Imagine trusting them all. To take an extra sip from the aquifer just a little
The night no one will notice
And the government has been making some moves to regulate the drilling and the groundwater
But those regulations won't be in place until twenty
Until then the water level in the aquifer is expected
To keep dropping
Wells will keep drying up
Marquardt
The pistachio farmer drove me to one of his Wells
It's just about to go dry
Hello this is a
Pump that has a
Put in service in 1946
It has Faithfully produced water
And it is now
Surging which means the
The equipment is lifting the water is right at
The level of where the water level is
And I expect a week from now it will not be functioning anymore until we dry
So
It's just a
Another one that has is going to go by the wayside here quickly
What is it
Feel like to see it
Doing that
I purposely don't drive by it
And when I do I look the other way
As I was driving around the farm with Mark I kept asking him over and over why he's doing what he
Why he keeps drilling deeper and deeper well
And why he keeps at the same time
Planting crops that need so much water what is the future here
And he told me there is still a lot of water left
Is Aquaphor and he thinks things will turn around he
Kept telling me
It's going to rain next
It's going to rain next year and he might very well rain next
You're not that's going to replenish
The aquifer but it could make things
Slightly better
I think in order to be a farmer anywhere at anytime
You have to have the
This optimism
Maybe things will be better next
Maybe there will be more water
Maybe there's a small chance he's right
Or maybe that's just what you tell yourself while the tragedy plays out
And now for a quick update
Beer after we reported the story California Farmers
Did catch a break they got a year of record-setting rainfall
They barely needed to tap their underground aquifers at all
This year though things have been dry again
And some of those farmers will go back to pumping
Draining that shared Lake
Groundwater
But they also know it's about to change
2 years from now a new law is set to go into effect
Orders Farmers to stop
Draining their aqua
No more digging ever deeper well
Farmers will only be allowed to pump as much water out
As rainfall quits
It does regulations work
20 years from now when you drop a stone into a well in California
It shouldn't take much longer to hit the water than it does today
As always we love to hear what you think
The program emails Planet Money on NPR. Org or you can tweet us at Planet Money
Today's episode was originally produced by Francis Harlow and Jess Jiang the rerun was produced by Alexi Horowitz Ghazi
Robert Smith
And I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Thanks for listening