This message comes from NPR sponsor NCR running a small business is now easier with ncrc
More than a point of sale
NCR silver is simple-to-use saves you time and helps you reach your goals faster
Visit ncr.com silver
Last Friday President Trump started a trade war with
Or maybe it started months ago or maybe we're not even in one yet
But regardless
He put tariffs
50 billion dollars worth of
Chinese.
Because we have to because we've been treated very unfairly
China responded by saying we're going to slap 50 billion dollars
The tariffs on you
Did President Trump gave a reason for this
He said that China steals from the US
The China
Steals our ideas
And our technology has proved
Trump mentioned this big report that was put together by the US trade representative
It's office
It came out of my
Tok here
This right here is the US trade Representatives report
You got a big binder clip and in between it is like
70 pages
Okay and it has insanely long name
Findings of the investigation into China's Acts
Policies and practices related to
To technology transfer
Intellectual property and Innovation under Section 301
Of the trade Act
If 1974 is a banger with a thing in the report that I was really interested in
Is appendix
See
Because an appendix C there's a list of all the companies that have something to say about China
Including companies that are complaining about
But if you look at it carefully what you see is that instead of individual companies
There's mostly a lot of trade organ
Oh yeah the American Foundry
Society the biotechnology Innovation organization the motor equipment and manufacturers Association and
A bunch more
So I called and I emailed just about every Trade Organization on there
And I said can you put me in touch with
One company that can occur
Spleen what it looks like
When China steals or demands it
Intellectual property or
Technology
Yeah
And he said sure just hang on I waited a couple of days
Emily mosto got back to me
Sorry but we can't find a company that's willing to talk to you
Which makes sense
Because probably a lot of these companies are doing business in China
And they have a lot to lose
But while I was combing through appendix
See I came across this
Little company that testified for the report and it actually used its name
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Noel King and I'm exhausted today on the show is China real
Stealing from the US we read this brick of a report that the president is using to justify his trade War
And buried inside we found this strange complicated and very personal story
Two men a businessman and a sign
Together they got hold of an invention that they thought might change the world
And together they hope to make a lot of money said they descended into suspicion accusations and loss
How do you feel right now about the professor
Well I mean
I don't
Hate him
I don't trust him
And eventually they ended up in the pages of the Trump administration's report
Support for this podcast in the following message come from mizzenandmain
Mizzen & Main dress shirts are made with performance Fabrics designed to look great all day
With minimal maintenance
There moisture
Wrinkle-resistant and machine wash
So they don't require ironing or dry clean
Check out their gift guide
Where the guy on your lip
Who is always on the move
Head to mizzen & Main. Com
Mizzen & Main
Look great
Longer use code NPR at checkout
How to receive $10 off your dress shirt
The tiny company in the middle of this huge trade war is called
Bonomo's
So I called them up and I got the CEO at Rogers
And I said to him you know a lot of the companies in this report didn't want to use their name
I mean it always
Keep in the back of your mind
When you
Stand up or raise your hand that
You know somebody's going to
Probably shoot at you but
In my opinion
To hide behind anonymity
Cowardly
So I went down to Virginia to meet this guy at Rodger
Ed Rogers looks so much like Mitt Romney that he was once mistaken for Mitt Romney at a Mitt Romney event
He's got kind of Romney by peers how he described himself
I mean I'm the kind of person
Who if I see you
Wall hanging
Slightly crooked I'll go
Straightened out
Would you be offended if I'm if I'm taping the story I described you as maybe a little bit Square
No I would not be offended
Describe me how are you
It is a little bit
Square
Anyway
Here is the story that Ed told the US trade representative for the report
And the story he told me it's also the subject of a criminal investigation and a couple of Lost
We read the legal documents and so here goes
It is July 2002
And in a laboratory in Blacksburg Virginia and amazing discoveries
He's made that was sorta like a Eureka moment
It was the CEO of the company that was working out of lab his boss
The owner of the company
With a scientist
Edwardsib
So it wasn't in the lab that morning but the scientist
Is his boss
Send to miss email at 10:37 a.m.
We think it's going to work this is just amazing what a beautiful idea
This beautiful idea
With the new process to make a rare sugar called
Tagatose
Tagatose is a sugar with like magical properties
It is very low calorie it tastes like actual sugar which
Is miraculous enough
But also you eat it and it stops your blood sugar from rising
Also according to a scientist that we talked to
If you eat it in large quantities
It could give you the runs
But still
Has potential
Yes it's one of the sugars found in nature and things like apples and cacao trees
But Justin very tiny amount
Do you know if you want to talk about who invented tagatose Godin
God may have invented it but scientists have been making it in labs for years
The dream
Had always been
To put tagatose
And soda
Cereal and
Candy
Imagine being able to eat
All the crap you want
And not worry about all the bad stuff that
Do you like weight gain
Diabetes
Now the reason this hasn't happened is that tagatose is really expensive to make
This new process was a way to make it on the cheap and in huge amount
I knew the technology was
Could be
Earth-shattering I mean just globally
Globally significant
Financial perspective but also globally significant from the public health first
From a financial perspective
Sugar is about 100 billion dollar-a-year Market
This company could be on the verge of making a lot of
And I was as job he was hired to Market what was being invented
In Matlab
The scientist said was working for was a guy named Percival Zhang he was also a professor at Virginia Tech
And I told me that you really admired person
Well
She's very smart
This is a bit of a language barrier
Because
He's originally from China
It says they emailed a lot seem to have a good relationship
Everything is chugging along
And then it says he notices
I started hearing some discussion of
Travel
To China and other places
Bye
Are the professor and other
Reason the company
He didn't really think very much
Suspicious at first
Because the professor is a Chinese citizen right
Only the Chinese cities
Naturalized US citizen
I think he probably still has family over there
Buddy at
Speaking engagements
Didn't seem to be anything unusual about that personal also seem to have a relationship with a lab and Chow
I started hearing about a satellite lab
That there's another lab being set up somewhere in
China by the way principles lawyer denies that there were satellite
Did you ever just pull the professor into an office and say
Hey
Pal
It's making me uncomfortable that I'm hearing about a satellite lab setup in China
Did you ever just confront him and say
What are you doing
Well not exactly like that
I wanted to be
Respectful of
The professor because
Very smart guy
He started the company
It was his company
You know what I
I didn't want to try to order him around but also
Atone stock in person
So whatever happens to the company
Also happens to
So it says he's just kind of leery
And then in December of 2015 six months after the discovery in the lab
Principal is out of the office he's travel
NSS
If you get another email from Percival that worries him
It's about their amazing breakthrough
The tag
Ed told me that in this email Percival mentions a research institute in China
It's called the Tianjin Institute of industrial biotechnology
What is the
Tianjin Institute of biotechnology the Chinese Academy of Sciences
As I understand it so is owned by the government
And the professor tells you hey we've got an opportunity
To sell our technology
To them
Yes I the number was
Between 5 and 20 million dollars
To sell 60% of the technology
And I was like
Anadel canale we got a real problem
That is a diversion Percival denies it
It said she was like I don't know anything about this institute in China why would we agree to do this
Yeah if the technology was successful
You can get it in major soda brands
It could be an candy bar
Actually try to Spoonful it was so good the runs
I was thinking like
Little packets of tagatose for your coffee
All together this seems like it could be worth a lot more than 20 million dollar
3 days after that email the company holds a board meeting
The way I remembered it
He and Percival said across from each other at a long conference
It wasn't very long meeting and it was not a very friendly meeting
And it involves some shouting
Like what are you doing here
And why is this happening
This is not appropriate
And that's what I was told that my contract would not be extended past December 5th
Edison fire
It says he tried asking Percival
What was going on in China
Was Percival taking their technology
He's there but he says he wasn't getting clear answers
No it does know that
The company is getting it
Funding from Grants to work on tagatose in these other Technologies
Some of those grants are from the National Science Foundation
So he sits down and he does something that
I don't know
He starts reading through Grant applications looking into whether there's been Grant
And I realize okay well the grant applications
Save that the company owns these Technologies
But the professor is sang the
Meet the company does not own these techno
And that is a contradiction
And if
What the professor is saying is true
Then that makes
The statements in the grand application
Untrue
Oh that is not a small deal I'm not going to say the professor's been lying
But I will say
That
There was a
Apri big contradiction
You're not supposed to contradict yourself
Anna Grant Apple
Ed Banks out an email to the National Science Foundation
Apartment apartment
So
On page 3 says
I'm not a science
However in my understanding of the grain application
Proposed telling on the man who hired him a guy he says he admired
Respected professor
So there's a
Thing I've seen in my son's school that says
Choose the
The hard right not the easy wrong
This was I wouldn't say this
Easy decision to let the NSF no
It was a decision that I felt like I had to make
Within a few weeks the National Science Foundation froze the company's grant money walletinvestor
But interestingly despite all of this
Ed and Percival
Did not immediately cut
Which seems weird because
There's a lot of mistrust
But remember each other two
They both own shares in percival's compass
And Ed has also started another come
He called bonomo's
The two men negotiate a deal
Ed give shares in his company
Percival's company
And the tagatose technology is transferred over to Ed's new
Then
About nine months later at got good news from the US patent
And trademark office
Basically saying you guys got something unique here
And it's been out talking to food and beverage companies about this stuff and some of them were showing Brilinta
And then last April one of those companies send Zed an email
Deer head
I've attached to this email a patent from China
That is pretty similar to yours
Did you have
Chance to see this pattern
?
Best regards
That's a
What
To be clear
It is a patent Apple
Application
And it's in Chinese
And so we ran it through Google Translate
But you really ran it through Google translate instead of
Getting a translator hearing
Charter Fitness
Google translate free
And up comes a name
The Tianjin Institute of industrial
Technology the Chinese Research Institute that Ed says Percival had emailed
I'm about
Now was applying for a patent
The Maytag
Yes and according to court documents that Ed has filed that application is nearly identical to
To the process that ends company-owned
The patent has for inventors listed
But two of them are anonymous
And this is what sets said on his path
He wonders
He's one of those Anonymous inventors
Percival Zhang that was the spring of 2007
A couple months later President Trump orders this investigation into China's alleged
Theft of us IP and technology and that is when Ed Rogers
Decided to stick his head up
Write to the Trump Administration and get himself involved in this big trade War
Support for NPR comes from LinkedIn learn
Proud to support the launch of life
NPR's guy to help you make better life decision
LinkedIn learning short video tutorials cover business Tech and creative skills employers look for
At every level
All talk by X
And new courses are added every week
+ LinkedIn learning is personal
Recommended courses based on your interests
And Life kid listeners get a month of learning
Free start your free trial at LinkedIn learning.com NPR
I wish I can meet Percival Zhang
But it is not an option
I can tell you what he looks like because there a pictures online
He looks so much like a scientist
That he is practically a stock photo sign
Barry is holding a beaker
Dairy is in a lab coat
Various
Accepting an award for his research
In this one picture weirdly he's wearing a pink button-down shirt and he's holding up a loaf of bread toward the camera
So I clicked on that one and it's a new story about Percival trying to turn
Plant waste
Into food
I really wish I could meet Percival but his lawyer told me that's not a notch
So I talked to the lawyer and what you're going to hear is what Percival is alleging in a counterclaim against
Instead my name is James hoppenfeld and I am an intellectual property lawyer
Can you
Tell me a little bit about your client what kind of guy is he
Yai
Professor John is
A professor
And he Specializes
In
Industrial chemistry would be one way to put it okay that was a good answer that was a very very answer but I actually Mormon
What kind of guy is
Percival is a very passionate
Person and he believes very strongly
In
What he does that is he
He
He really wants to
Create
And develop
Technical innovations that
Benefit
He's exceptionally intelligent
And like I said very passion
But also a guy who knows
His limit so
That's why he hires at to run the business end
The talk up his inventions to potential investors
And when he does that when he hires Ed
Principles lawyer says
She now has gotten himself
Stuck in one of the oldest
Rivalries in his
The scientist versus the sales
The scientist
Will Percival wanted
He wanted to focus more
Taking the technology and
Just getting it out there
And spreading it if they have the big money on the way
Awesome
But the salesman
He
Really was focusing solely on making money
The lawyer says that within a few months
Percival realized
This was just a
Unfixable dining
And on top of that he didn't think Ed was doing a particularly good job
Sun December 2015
He fired at
And the lawyer says
Ed came after him
First kind of gently
Listen first of all I think
I know a lot more about how to commercialize all of these inventions
Can you do you're an academic
I'm I'm the money guy
Why don't we form this new company
And you assign the rights
Cities Grant and all these all this stuff to me
You go do your research
I'll focus on me
But by this point James lawyer says that Percival just didn't trust Ed
He said no
Then he started to get very aggressive
And the first thing he did as he started to hinto Elison purse
I see some improprieties annies Grant Apple
Locations that you
And he started threatening
To report
Percival for
Grant fraud
To the authorities
Why did principal not just get out of bed with this man why did he not just say look we are
Done I want you out of my life
Why continue this
Obviously
Toxic relationship
Ed Rogers had implied
The Percival
That if he
Did this deal with
That he would help Percival
We are his rep
Mutation
Now you have to understand how Percival
You understand how personal was feeling at this
He's been accused of Grant fraud
He knows he's a Chinese National
Here is Ed Rogers
Who's the All-American boy who's accusing him
Of committing this route so he scared he scared that people aren't going to believe
So the lawyer says this is why Percival agreed to that deal with Ed
His back was against the wall and so
He signed over the tag
Reddit fat is a
That is a
Very
That's like
Mustache twirling
Stuff
That you've deleted
For lack of a better word because it's really accurate I don't let you know I don't want to
Exaggerated word
But in this case it's not exaggerated to say diabolical
Let me think about it
In April 2016
Ed Rogers finds himself what with what he
He thinks it's some of Percival Jong
Most valuable technology
A year before
And Rogers didn't even probably didn't even know what tagatose was
Percival John works on this technology for years and years and years and years he has a stellar
Professional reputation is everything
He's on his way to commercializing a technology
In the space of a few months
Ed Rogers has
A large chunk of his intellectual property and is completely damaged
Reputation
That's like a coup d'etat
Not to be clear we have no idea whose
No we don't
Ed Rogers says this is all nonsense
He says he didn't threaten Percival
He never offered to help clear percival's name he didn't steal percival's company
It's company sued perceval in May of 2017
Claiming among other things
Breach of
The suit essentially says principal stole the technology in the trade secrets
And took them to China
And from that point on it got very
In November of 2017 Percival was arrested and charged
With Grant fraud
He spent three months in jail he denies the charges
Anime of this year percevault
Counter Sue dead in Ed's company for breach of contract defamation
Another clue
So he will have two trials over the next time
A civil case with Ed
In a criminal case with the USA
We did get in touch with the Tianjin Institute of industrial biotechnology in China
They told us this tagatose patent application is theirs
And that they developed it independently
So this is what a trade War looks like between two guys
In Virginia but these two guys are not the reason we're maybe not
Trade war with China
No they're really not
This us trade Representatives report was about so much more
It's about accusations that China is forcing American companies that want to do business there to turn over their technology
And of course companies do want to do business
China it is a
Huge Market hundreds of millions of
Tow companies go there and they turn some stuff over
And of course I don't want to talk about the compromise
Texas State majors
And many of them probably fear retaliation from China
It's company isn't really in that
It's a small company and they're not working
But I'm lonely I think they are representative of what's going on
At the heart of this fight between Percival and Ed is a
Ton of mistress
Over what the other guy was up to
And there's also a ton of Fury
And whenever the US trade report I came away thinking
We are afraid of China
We are afraid that they are trying to surpass Us in part by stealing our stuff
President Trump seems to think a trade War may change that
But it could be a really expensive
If you are somehow involved
In a trade war or a price war or war war let us know
Set up an email Planet Money on NPR. Org love to talk to you we're also on Twitter Facebook and Instagram
Tanisha was produced by Sally Helm our editors Brian urstadt and Alex goldmark is are supervising producer
Special things in this episode to Aaron Dennis Michael Kohn Rob Lauder Mark Cohen and Rachel Stern
Also thanks to Chad Bown who hosts the show called
Also some business we are looking for a new intern I started at NPR as an intern
Sally did as well it is a blast
You'll learn a lot and you get paid if you're in school or have recently finished check out more info at npr.org
Shmoney omnic Fountain and thanks for listening