Randy Reese owns a cattle ranch in northeastern Montana
He runs it with the sunshine
Where are we
Ranch
Middle of nowhere
The Reese Ranch borders the Badlands
These big bear whitehills stick up out of
Sagebrush and dry grass
It is really remote
The only way to get to Randy's house is on this very bumpy dirt road
So when he was pretty surprised a couple years ago when you saw it to strangers
Driving down that road
To see him
Actually guy showed up with a fruit
Did a fruit basket
And what did he say
Asked if we could go out and look around for
Fossils I guess
Look around for fossils
The men told Randy they thought his Ranch might have dinosaur bones buried on it
They offered him $5,000
Look around for
Couple years
Ants
If they found something good
The reasons would get a 10% cut
The profit
Brandi said
Go for it
They set off to a far corner of the ranch and Randy didn't see much of them for a long time
But then about a year later they showed back up
His house
They found something
Teeth
And part of a tail
And they thought
It was not just any dinosaur
Came back this year and they phoned up
T-Rex
That was kinda exciting
The Reese's are understated
But there was a T-Rex in their backyard
And this is a really big
Deal from them
Randy and his wife had Reese Rex
T-shirts made up for all their grandkids
I'm ready Sunshine Reese learned all of these scientific facts
About their dinosaur
What's the most
Complete T-rex skull
Never found
They found new
Orbital
Eye socket like bones
And maybe like
Mentally said like horns
They're getting super into it
And there is a good reason for that
This T-Rex
Could mean a lot of money
For the Reese's
In the US
If you find a T-Rex
Or any fossil in your backyard
You own it
It's yours
You don't have to hand it over to the government or Museum
You can sell it to the highest bidder
As a result
There is a dinosaur Gold Rush going on
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
And I'm quatrain bully
Today in the show
What happens when you try to put a price on the bones of a humongous 66 million-year-old monster
We can actually pinpoint the exact moment when fossils went from scientific artifact
The cash crop
It was 20 years ago
And it was the biggest
Baddest dinosaur that has ever been found
It was a T-Rex
Of course
A T-Rex
Named Sue
By the way this way was originally reported in 2000
Support also comes from Fidelity invest
As a Fidelity Wealth Management
You get a dedicated advisor
Hair to help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of tax
And make clear recommendations for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
Curious how the dinosaur world
Used to work
A team of scientists would come up to a Rancher
Ask if they can look around for bones
If they found something
They come out
Excavated pickaxes
Dental tools paint brushes
It was a painstaking process
They could take a year
The bones would end up in a museum
And the Rancher make it a little credit on a plaque
It was a handshake.
No cash
That'll change because of
Pete Larson
Peated study paleontology in college
And he thought I could make a business
Out of dinosaurs
He started paying Ranchers
To dig up Bones on their land
Then he would sell what he found
And what day you was on a dig in the Badlands of South Dakota
What are the members of his team is woman named Sue Hendrickson
She went out a walk with her dog
And you keep running back to him with something in her hand
She holds out her hand with these two pieces of bone with this honeycomb pattern
And if there's more there and she said there's a lot more there and so we ran literally ran to the side about 2 miles away
And here were these
Basically pieces of bones just dripping out of the side of this cliff
What did you do
We dug it up
It was like the most wonderful
Wonderful time
Of my life digging that fossil
It was a Tyrannosaurus Rex
And not just a piece of one
Skull was there full of teeth
The whole spine entail
The huge leg bones
One of the little arms
It was the most complete T-Rex ever found
P&A mitsu
After the woman who discovered it
Sue's bones had all of these amazing details that have been preserved
Broken rib that healed
Giant holes in her lower jaw
He thinks we're from the teeth of another T-Rex
She has
Some crushed bones at the top of your skull
The left side of the lower Jaws
Pulled out of
Play stupid could have by thing actually caused her death where she had basically the left side of her face was ripped off by another team
A rough life
Pete and his team spent
3 weeks digging her out
The carries her bones back to his shop
And started
Oculus Lee cleaning and preparing them
Pete's plan
Was not to sell her
He wanted to use her to start a museum
It is little town of Hill City South Dakota
If you want to make a place where everyone could see her
We're scientists could come in
Study her whole town was in
School kids even held bake sales to raise money for this Museum
Anu spredfast
Scientist School in from all over the world to get a look at SU
Reporters came and then one day we get up
There was a knock on my door I was showering at 7:30 in the morning and getting ready to come to work and I lived in a tree
Trailer house behind the Institute
I walked out and there's 35 FBI agents and National Guard and all kinds of people here that just
Yeah just unreal situation and they were saying that we had somehow spirited this dinosaur away in The Odyssey
Search warrant to surrender
Her bones
Suicide landed in the middle of an epic
Legal battle
It was clear that she was special
And unlike the bones Peter dug up in the past
Sue might be worth a lot of money
There was a question now about who owns
Puget Sound Sue on the land of a Rancher
He paid the rent for $5,000
There was no written contract
The renter said that money was for just digging up the land
He said he owns zoo and wild is Big custody battle is being sorted out
Sue's bones were seized by the FBI
And how old is evidence
They put Sue in
In a sea Freight container basically in the Boiler Room at the School of Mines
Sue sat in the basement at the University
He would go and talk to her at night
Actually looking in the window at the container
And what would you say
I'm just babe but basically I'm going to get you the hell out of there
It's just that was sad and lock up this wonderful animal
Just wrong
The court decided in favor of the Rancher
Pete was crushed
Now the Rancher got to side with
Annie's choice
Put her up for auction
It was a sale like nobody had ever seen
Good morning ladies and gentlemen and welcome to Sotheby's
We have for auction today the fossil of a Tyrannosaurus Rex
No Natsu
To some people this was a crazy MoMA
Auctioning off a dinosaur
That was something you didn't do
No one had any idea what to do with self
Lance grandi is a paleontologist with the Chicago Field Museum
They were one of the bidders
There all kinds of people trying to get ahold of Sue
We bet against
Are there museums
Gambling casinos real estate companies in
Even in one private individual who wanted it for an ornament in his living room
70 + $500,000 + $560,000 + $700,000
Tony and dropped out after 7.2 million
The North Carolina Museum of Natural History dropped out and now they were just
Two bidders left
Chicago Field Museum
And a real estate Baron from Florida
Keep put up a 7.3 million dollar bid
We kind of with a 7.4 million dollar bid
He bumped his 27.5
Seven five
And it looks like Sue
She was headed to Florida
But the Chicago Field Museum had a professional bitter working with them
And he told them he thought the real estate Baron
Might be tapped out
He said
Make one more big
Just one more
7600000
So are we bit
7.6 million and that was the bed that took it
Was Sotheby's 10% commission added the total price tag came to
8362000 $500
Sue went to the field museum for 8.3 million dollars
She still there today and that moment
When the gavel fell
That moment changed
Paleontology
Forever
Now everyone knew that dinosaur fossils were not just scientific relics
They had a price tag
And a pretty big one
And it didn't hurt that all of this happened around the time of a particular movie you might remember
Jurassic Park
Natural History Museum
And lots of
If people wanted to buy dinosaurs
Prices were quickly
Duckbill dinosaurs
Not worth a whole lot they're kind of everywhere
Like the cows of the dinosaur world
Triceratops
Honey in the middle
A good one can set you up to a million dollars
The by far
The most profitable dinosaur
The king of the market
The Tyrannosaurus Rex
You can imagine what happens next
Thousands of fossil Hunters started crawling all over the hills
South Dakota Wyoming Montana hoping to strike it rich
It's the only part of the world were T-Rexes are found
And paleontologist
People who dedicated their entire lives to scientific
Discovery
They were not very happy about
Jack Horner is a paleontologist at the Museum of the Rockies in Bozeman Montana
And
He's partially responsible for this whole dinosaur crazy
Is the technical advisor for the Jurassic Park movie
And one of the main characters is actually based on him
You're the cute one
Sam Neill character
I'm just glad he didn't get eaten
Jack was not excited
See all of these newcomers on his turf
Because a lot of these guys aren't scientist
If no qualification
Eminem just answered an ad on Craigslist
Angie says a lot of valuable information is getting lost
When we're looking for scientific information
You're the rock around it and how the thing is laying an
Exactly where it is geologically and geographically that's all important information
But it's basically overhead for commercial collector
Jack says doing a dinosaur dig right
Requires skill
Equipment
Precision
Like right now he is trying to find
Dinosaur DNA
Just like in dress
And he says he's close
All he needs now is to find the right
Bone
Wear white gloves we
Do extractions into
12 get it to a lab
As quickly as possible
We actually built a clean lap in the back of an 18-wheeler trailer so we could actually get our laboratory to the fee
Could something like that be lost in a commercial.
Yes
It could be us
Jack says all kinds of information
Is getting lost
Because most commercial diggers
All about
Getting
Get bones get out
When do Reese's Sons CB & Shane
Take me out to see the commercial dig site
Were there T-Rex so I have never been to a fossil
I've no idea what
What's it look like
But I have to say
This one was kind of a mess
It's like a construction site
Is yeah they had a huge bulldozer a d8 or D9 out here to do all this
The diggers left the site a month ago but she Nancy B say they can show me the spot where the dinosaur
Used to be
But when we get there there's
I have a surprise waiting for us
Well that looks like they're still bones out here
Oh my God there's still a plaster left
Wow
I better not be the skull bone out of the ground they put it right into a plaster cast
The plaster cast protects it when they're moving it from the dig site
To the lab
And there is a
Used plaster cast
It is still a
Despite just sitting on some boards
In the dirt
And from the size of the plaster cast
Shane Reese
Thinks this is the skull
The Tyrannosaurus Rex
He's really upset
You should have gotten it out by now
Cuz pretty soon they're not going to be able to get it out once winter hits
This is going to be stuck here
The Canadian dollar sitting right there
The digging company wouldn't talk to us
But they did send us an email
They said yes
That is the skull
But the reason that is still there is that they're trying to be
Be careful it's at the school waste so much they have to bring in the special equipment so that they can take it out without damaging it
After that they'll spend a year or two preparing it
And then they'll sell it
After doing some research and talking to the company
The Reese's think they're T-Rex
We'll probably go for between one and $2000000
That would mean a couple hundred thousand dollars for the Reese's
You guys have a preference for where it ends up
It really does belong Museum and not
In a private collection where only one person gets
It may end up in a private collection
If they pay more I'm okay with
Right
The cool skull with all of the bones and horns
Scientist
Might never even be able to
T-Rexes might have horns and no one will know
Except a real estate billionaire who will hang Christmas ornaments on them
We asked Lance Grande about this
Paleontologist from the Chicago Field Museum
All of this information potentially getting lost
And paleontologists getting priced out of the fossil Market
Oh that's a really tough question
I mean there is a downside
Lamp says some science
Is being lost
And a lot of ranchers won't let museums or scientists dig on their land anymore
They want the money the private companies can offer
But
Myself
For me and my locality the net is positive because
They're just a lot more fossils being excavated then
Have ever been excavated in the past
Before suit
T-Rexes were being found once every 10 years or so
Sensu
T-Rexes are being found
Once every 6 months
20 times more fossils coming out of the ground
Because there is a market for
And if the fossil smart pulled out of the ground
They would most likely a road away
And this is actually kind of important because
There's actually clock that's ticking
Fossils will start to pick out of the ground
Evan there's this little window of time for someone to see it and get it out before it crumbles to dust
Phoebe and Jane Reese tell me they see fossils all over their Ranch all the time
Take me to one place where they used to campus kids
Actually adorably called Dino Hill
Is he just a big rib sticking out of a dirt Mound that they use
Used to put their sleeping bags on
When we get there the rib is gone
Scrambled
But this is something else
Oh my God right here
Oh yeah look at that
Wow
Yeah yeah
Yeah wow that's
Welcome to Reese Ranch
If you wanted
Do you wanted a souvenir you
Did you actually take one
No I didn't
Fossils
Still seem kind of sacred
I couldn't even touch it
Actually none of us
We all just stood around
Looking at it
Super excited
Find imagine this animal running around these Hills
6 million years
We're like little kids
Probably
Pig skeleton under me
But we'll probably never know
This part of the Reese Ranch isn't getting X
Excavated
It's on government land
Reese's just lease it
And different rules apply here
No for-profit
So the shoulder blade will stay in the ground
Until University or Museum comes to
Did you get up
Or it might just a road away
Actually the same fate could have happened to the Reese's
T-Rex
It was right up against their property line
Just 40 feet away from government
2 T-Rex steps exactly if a T-Rex it taken two more steps before died
The Reese's
Wouldn't have gotten a dime
And the T-Rex
Might not have been found at all
Support for NPR comes from LinkedIn learning
Proud to support the launch of life
NPR Sky to help you make better life decisions LinkedIn learning short video tutorials cover
Business Tech and creative skills employers look for at every level all taught by experts and you
Horses are added every week
+ LinkedIn learning is personally
Recommended courses based on your interests
And life kit listeners get a month of learning
Free start your free trial
At LinkedIn learning.com NPR
Pete Larson the guy who found Sue
Did eventually build his Museum in Hill City South Dakota he lost to
But he did go on to find a few other T-Rexes we've collected 10 T-Rexes now
To Stand Stephen Duffy Bucky wirex
Oo7 a lyrics how many been found in the world
So there's about fifty specimens that really qualifies something that's important
To 20% of all the T-Rexes in the world
You put your hands on
Which isn't bad
We always love to hear what you think of the show send us an email Planet Money at npr.org
Or you can tweet us
At Planet Money
Our episode today was produced by Kristen Clark and Jess Jiang
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
And I'm qua Trinh Bui
Thanks for listening