Hey just a quick note
This episode originally ran in January 2016
It's reported by David kestenbaum and Audrey Quinn
For as long as I can remember I've seen these ads
I think the first one I saw was just on a telephone
Is a piece of paper stacked up
Say something like
You can work from home and get rich
Call this number
Is I remember there was a picture of a person wearing pajamas and there was a
Decide so now all over the Internet or even videos
This is one of my favorite
There's this woman waking up in this big
Plushbeds she's covered in what looks like a bear skin rug
Harder
What is Italy
New
She sits up crabs
The cat
Expanding its belly
So
You want to work from home huh
Nobody
No schedule making money from
Does not sound right
It does sound great and also Improv
Because of course this is a scam
But it is a very effective one
It's been around for decades and it will not die
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm David kestenbaum today
On the show the anatomy of a scam
What happens when you respond to one of those work from home as we got a secret document that reveals the tricks of the trade
Talk to one of the people who would have been on the other end trying to get your money and we have recordings actual recordings of phone
Call so you can hear
Have a whole thing goes down
Support also comes from Fidelity Investment
As a Fidelity Wealth Management
You get a dedicated advisor
Is there to help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes
And make clear recommendations for your full Financial
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
Despite what those work-from-home ads suggest
They are not offering you a job they're not trying to hire you
The companies behind those that are trying to sell you stuff
So that in theory you can get rich work
Here's how it works
When you respond to One of Those ads
You give them your name and your contact info
Then you get a call from someone at a call center
Saying so
Do you want to work from home
I would have been on the phone
That would have been
The first call you would have received
This is Ryan Jensen in 2007 he just graduated
College in St George Utah
I was looking for a job
A friend of his suggested he come to work with him at this call center
Call center Industries vegan
His friend takes him to this nondescript Office Park at the edge of town
When you first walk in
There's a secretary sitting there
They just had a couch out front
Let me know the picture maybe a plan out and then they just bleed your own back into the
Call Flora there about three guys back there on the call floor they actually called it
The bullpen
Aaron sit in cubicles with headset
Ryan's call center offered all types of
Images
Most of them would help you sell stuff online you want to set up a website they can build it for you so coach you on how to run a web
Business handle all the paperwork the accounting
Ryan said the pitch was this is the Internet it's huge
You can sell to the whole world
I didn't really understand the online world too much back then
I mean I was the guy that played football and hated computers
You know back then you think
Yeah they're going to Great coaching company they're going to get a website and they're going to learn how to sell online so great
There were some red flags
Sometimes you get to the office in fine white powder on his desk
Turned out to be residue from people snorting oxy
B cotton
Ryan's job with the
Call people
It responded to one of those work
And try to convince them that he had a very special offer
Try to make the sale
We actually have recordings of these calls not in the place where Ryan works but from a different company
The tax Club
We got the recordings from the Federal Trade Commission which has been trying to shut these places down
This one set of calls to that wasn't
Hello
You Don't Know This Woman's name is bleeped out that I like to think of her as Doris
Man calling says his name is Blake Cantor
Sanford Clinic
How are you this morning
I want to know right now
Cleaning up my grandson's bedroom
Oh yeah
Never ends right
So you sick
Steven
He spoiled
Spoiled
Aren't they all most of them anyway but that's okay grandmothers are supposed to spoil their grandson
We played this calls for Ryan the guy who worked in some of the
And he walked us through the whole
The sales people he says
They're all working off of
Script
Script is a few pages long and it lays an egg
Exactly how
Make the sale he says the scripts are basically works
Start their Homeland over years past All Around Utah they laid out the most
Time-tested most
Efficient way to get someone to eventually give you their credit card number
That's what they want your credit
In an expiration date in a CCV
That's the girl that's the
That's the bell ringer
We got our hands on one of these scripts and basically breaks the wholesale down into these differ
Parts
The first part is just called the intro
The idea is to establish rapport
Ryan says everybody had their own ways
Would say for example
Does your wife know about this business
Is she going to be involved
They said yes then say okay is she available get on the phone as well now if not
Let's reschedule this
Because obviously
I'm not a very good marriage counselor
And I don't want to get you in trouble
They got a chuckle out of that line
Oh they always
Love that way
Imma call with Blake and Doris you can tell that Blake is using a screw
Because there's this one moment where she messes up
When the dorses answers comes unexpected and he kind of trips up
Have you ever set up an e-commerce business
Just before
I did years ago
Alright listen don't worry most about I mean business successful
Pay attention Blake
Real person
After this he just plows ahead
It goes on to the next part of the screw
Which is called
The blast
Script for this part says
Ask find out question
Fleek means to figure out what Doris wants to do
So we can figure out what to push on her
You don't touch the products you're going to be selling it
I haven't done anything yet
Alright my laptop doesn't seem to do what I wanted to do right right
It's it always works that way we'll listen I'm going to let you know I'm going to guide you and getting your back
End of your business shut up
So that
You can
So that you can make as much money as possible as quickly as possible
Save as much money as possible
Taxwise okay that's good
Doris doesn't have a working computer or any idea what she wants to sell
Some people sold
Weight loss shakes or herbal supplements or skin cream that kind of stuff
She has no idea but Blake moves rate on to the next part of the script
It's called the probe
The probe is this critical delicate part
Is whole pet
Blake needs to figure out
How much money should I
So we can figure out
How much you can get
Needs to probe for finance
Which seems like a hard thing to just turn a conversation to so how much money do you have
The Blake signs away in
This is just three minutes into the call
Don't you aware of this but one out of three internet businesses are sued
Every year
For one violation
Now I just want to get an idea of what type of assets you have that we will be
Texting with this Corporation are you a homeowner
Yep
Okay
Get a mortgage on the ceiling
Do you own any vehicles
Sorry about Sam
A van
Teddy is Italy store
Picture that one
Okay on that
Ryan the guy who used to work in these call centers he says this part of the script made him feel super nervous
Yeah for him this was all just very off
Remember he was 20 something years old and he thought like who am I
Ub advising
What do I know about me
I'm broke
But some of the salesman Aries has had no problem
With some guys who like could almost always close a deal
Yeah like give me 10-15 minutes to get a smoke break I'll come back and
Hammerless down so they just call after call after call just what they do for a living
Android
How they do that
What makes some good as no fear they don't they're not afraid to talk about money
Because if you're afraid to talk about money on the phone
They're going to betray you afraid to talk about money if you just act like
$2,000 this is what it is where I guess you're broke where how many credit cards do you have that if
If you just talk to them normally
They'll feel more comfortable about
Ryan says the salesman would just be walking around the office their headsets on
They put a few golf balls while they're talking on the call on this call we're listening to
Blake the salesman does
Exactly what Ryan says
The pros do
He just plays it super
Casual
And Doris goes along
She tells him all these specific Finance
Like
She tells him for that mortgage that she owes about $200,000
It's really not that I mean I know a lot of people are stupid people everyday and then I mean I know people much much worse position
You are you have savings
Oh yeah a little bit little bit
Stealing another passed away
She
Get up kids some
So I put it away
Just a ballpark if you had to say
I don't want an exact number it's none of my business and
Non surgery right around 50000
We have working capital in the checking account
Ballpark what would you say that is
Mm
You can almost hear Blake doing the Matthew
Counting up how much money he can go after
At this point blank moves on to the next part of
And the script that we have
What it says is
Find the path
Find the fear
It is adamant about this find more pain if needed
Everybody has pain it is your job to find
It's like this demented
Twist on the classic salesman
Convince the person that you have the solution to their problems
Soap Lake manufacturers
The pain for Doris
This way you don't have to deal with the IRS on your own I don't know if you've ever dealt with them but
It's like dealing with the Gestapo
Ryan like this
So fancy line that's a fancy one liner
You think if excuse is that a lot
Absolutely
Absolutely does
How many hours a week do you think you're going to invest in
5 to 8 hours a day
Really that's fantastic
Okay because
Dedicate
7 figures that is $1000000
Darcy talking about working from home like halftime and hoping she's going to make $1000000
I've been thinking about why people fall for this
And when you're someone who's never done super great financially
It can seem kind of like magic how some people just make it
And here's this guy saying I know those Secrets I can tell him to you
It can be complicated but together we can do it
And 21 minutes and 45 seconds to call
Lake goes for it
He goes in for the cell
Silicon membership consists of a one-time initial setup fee and only a small corresponding retainer fee
Everything that we've discussed here today
It's only a one-time investment
$4,785
Okay
And
$49 and ninety-five a month
Which I will wave for the first
49 what
Who is credit Blake is upfront
Now he says we are talking about you paying $4,785 upfront
+ 4995
He says you can write it off
He tries to get her to pay out of a checking account
I have everything in the system here setup it would be very helpful to me
If
Squeaking
Start the the billing process
Okay what
I just maxed it out okay what can you do
Is there anything you could do right this moment
No not right now okay
Fine I'll just save everything here
Sorry to do that to you
She apologizes
To a guy who's trying to take her money
Fat tiger
Lake makes one more at
He says
Just give me your debit card info
Cremation now you can put the money in it tomorrow
All right you'll be using your debit card was that correct
Is that a fuse for a MasterCard
Thesis
Visa
All right what are those numbers
Your fast she tells him
And here's this moment where I'm like maybe she's caught on maybe there's something deep in her gut is saying no
This is not right
I was totally rooting for her
But then this happened
I got it
Okay the number
Is
Expiration okay in the three-digit CVV number on the back
Ryan the guy who worked in the call center
Told us that if you are the sales person you get to this point
You are site
He's doing a dance in his chair right there
He got 16 digits
CCV and an expiration date
From a woman he never met
All he done with spend 35 minutes with her on the phone
And she did transfer the money into account that she promised
She paid the 4700
$85 membership
The salesman Blake he would have made 10 to 20% of that that's as much as $1,000 for one call
Ryan told he made less from the stuff that he was selling
He was right out of college easy money
What was the story that you told yourself to make
Yourself feel okay about
Trying to make living like everyone else
But like
Just reading through the
The script we have here and I don't know how this Ramirez was
It feels awfully manipulate
You know
Thousands of dollars for people who do not have it
And if you just think about it for a second the idea that they're going to be able to set up a website
And make like $100,000
Pierre excelling
Whatever it's just you
You know like did you write that way did you feel that way at the time
You know I was a little bit young a little bit naive
I mean I'd have to
Completely say I mean I wasn't completely completely oblivious to it I mean you question the times a little bit
You do feel a little
You know aggressive
Eventually that that feeling wears off
I mean it's a sale at the end of the day is what you end up thinking
Cell-to-cell is a Sal
And once you make a sale that is not the end
Because once someone has shown their willing to buy something
You can probably get them to buy more
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org
After Doris had that call with Blake from the tax Club she gets what is supposed to be her first support call to help her
Get started
It's a different salesman list
And this new salesman he pushes her further
And this gets us to some of the craftiest few lines in this whole set of calls
We have you done anything in regards to getting a loan for the business
No because I don't really want to go into more dip
When are sign is born today what I would rather she do is take the money reinvested
It's kind of like paid off with the loan just of the business would actually claim those liabilities
Should be like paying yourself back with a business loan that make sense
Do you really not borrowing anymore money
You just kind of pain what you've already invested
Is Amazon better
But it's got to be paid back to
I can't hear you what you say I said it would still have to be paid back
What's the same exact situation you're in now isn't it
Pic of the difference
What's the
You know there's this moment in there where she has correctly identify the flaw in his logic
And your like go Doris does this math mind trick
Steamroll over
Despite his horrible it's like listening to someone get beat up
She does eventually take out a loan
Which is more money they can go after
And at the end of this call he gets another 16 digits from her
They charged her $4,000
And this is not the last call endorses file
Ryan Jensen are guide for all this says that he eventually started running his own call center
Ethology was trying to run a legitimate
Best actually give people shot at setting up a website
Of the South.
But a lot of that coaching and services he was selling they were provided by
Other companies
And at some point it started becoming pretty clear that
Does products
We're Not Afraid
His customers were being passed from company to company just getting sold more and more stuff
Call with a customer in
In particular
That kind of changed things
So I saw this guy you know
45 Grand and coaching to building a website
And do do whatnot and coaching
Well
After that
He goes to the tax club and spends another
Spell $16,000
So
This guy calls us back because we were his main point of contact and he calls us back and he's like I just spent all
All this money on a business that's not bringing any income and he's crying and I mean he spent $24,000 on speaker cry
Yuan to us
You know I mean when you have somebody that's calling you back broke $24,000 later with nothing to show for it
I mean
It hit some chords
I mean it it's some chords
If you wondering how these call centers can just keep operating
It's worth pointing out that they have pretty strong political connections Ryan's call center
It was based in Utah
And a lot of these call centers are in Utah where there has not been much of cracked
The call centers there have made some pretty major campaign contributions
Two recent Attorneys General have been charged with bribery in connection with the call centers
The lawyers at the Federal Trade Commission say trying to go after this cup
Is is a bit like
Playing whack-a-mole
Once enough customers complain
That company just shuts down and opens up under a new
The tax Club the company you've been hearing from almost calls with Doris they did actually get shut down
Reprocessing deceptive sales tax
That's why we have according to the
According to Legal filings the tax Club took in over 220 million dollars from people
There's just one more phone call endorses file
And it's a wrap
It is from someone calling on her behalf
To a financing company that the tax Club headset dorsai
Cuz he's financing a Caesar
Yeah Caesar
I'm trying to get ahold of you
Yes
Forever
Okay
Forever are you at your desk
I am
Okay fine you got a few minutes
I do how can I how can I help out here
The woman says she's trying to track down a loan that door is took out for another home business program
This
Sloan
Has to be zeroed out
Okay
Oh and why is that
Well because passed away
Okay right after
Shein.com
Oh I'm sorry to hear that all right
We've had put a freeze on all of her bank accounts
Because money has been flying out of their left and right
I just sent this for your records
I'm sending an email right now she has two accounts
Hold on and get an explanation for you
No I just want to know where like $45,000 went towards Steve
Snips and coming out of her account, and it started all in August
It's going to something
Tax Club Global
Something or another
A lot of those building
Your online business is restore fun
And so why those Services help them
Either run their business or help empty the taxes
This is a woman who had dementia 75 years old and could barely turn on his computer
The man on the phone agrees to refund the money to Doris's estate
We do not know if she got
Taking back the FTC is still so they to the mast
Something like 20000 people said they've been ripped off by the tax Club
That's enough for you
Ryan Jensen the call center guy we talked to he was eventually find $400,000 by the state of Utah
So far he's paid about $5,000
Brian said he's trying to speak out about all the corruption in the Carlson
We asked him if he felt bad about his role in it
Here's what he said
I mean that's something
That hopefully I can learn from and you know
I will learn from you
Now's my chance to apologize if I did hurt anyone then I'm more than happy to try to make that right
It says if anyone thinks he's doing the wrong
Get in touch
We should say we tried to reach out to all the people you heard in those recorded phone calls
They said they couldn't for privacy reasons I would try to reach the salesman at least by the names they gave him those recordings
No one returned our calls are show today was Bruce by Jess Jiang special things goes to Jason Jones
Provided us with the call center script and Christine Durst she runs a scam spotting sites called
You can send us email we are Planet Money at npr.org sweetest at Planet Money
And I'm a frequent thanks for listening