It's the season of giving thanks
And sharing embarrassing stories with your fam
In the spirit of that
A few days ago I called up my brother Joel
Now can you explain how in the world this all happened in the
How I ended up getting arrested
Was driving
To your house
For Thanksgiving and as usual I was on time
So I was speeding
So they could be more on time
And as I was
Speeding along
I saw police lights behind me so I pulled over
Engino normally the
This is like a five-minute thing they look at my license maybe I get a warning maybe a ticket
This time will this is a very well-known
Speed trap
Yeah I got pulled over
And he
Ask me to step out of the car and then he put me in handcuffs and put me in the cop car
Really
Anthony what's happening in
I want ask
So many questions but then the cop starts to tell me that I have the right to remain silent
And so I do
And then the cop drove me
Jail
Retook my mugshot
To the right
Face the camera
And they booked
Just felt so silly
You need to get arrested for
Gettington
Yeah
I mean
Han if you also got a speeding ticket a few years
Earlier and
Forgot to pay it before leaving
Town
And then you
Speed again
Through the same small town on a holiday
But I think the thing that made me the most nervous was that you or the one I had to call
Cuz you were my one phone call
From jail
You you felt like you would let your going to be letting me down or something
Well you're quite responsible
And you have children
That I like
Quite a bit
There was a brief moment of evaluation on we decided
Can we allow a convicted
Traffic
Violator to come to our house for Thanksgiving dinner
Did you spend the night in jail I did not Leslie I build myself out a couple hours later and
My brother did save me some turkey
And of course they all thought that it was
So funny witch
Does did start out as
Just kind of a funny family story but then
It turned into something else in
Entirely because
There is something that came after the arrest
Something to introduce me to a world that I did not know exist
That would follow me
Much longer than the other
Okay
About six months later
I get a phone call from my niece
And she tells me that
She's been online and for some reason she was Googling my name
And the first thing that came up
Was my mugshot
So one of the kids
Are you the one that found my mugshot online and they
They used it as the picture that came up when I called them
That's funny
You're telling me that
If I right now Google
Karen I'm doing it because I send
Mugshots
That's not you
There's a lot of mugshots here but
Weather today
Not mine
Not so far okay well I can tell you why that is because
As I discovered
The entire business model of the website where my photo ended up mugshots.com
Is it they say look
Will take down your mugshot
If you pay us a fee
I know right
If they charged me $399
To take down my mugshot and judging by the fact that I'm already on page
It's two of this
And
I don't see it yeah it better
I felt like I had
To pay this especially because I just left like this corporate career that
Stable behind me and I was
Tried to start over in radio so I knew that editors would
Be Googling my name
Having a mugshot come up first did not seem like it was the best first impression
So I logged on
Entering my credit card number to pay this thing and I'm
Fuming and I'm thinking like
How is this legal
Denny's occurs to me I am a reporter now
I
I'm going to get to the bottom of this
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Karen Duffin
If you are one of the more than 70 million people in America have been arrested
Chances are
You have a mugshot
And thanks to the internet
That can follow you forever
Trying to stop mugshot extortion takes us to a place where the First Amendment and our right to privacy
Crash in Freely complicated way
Cuz when it comes to the Constitution
Compromise isn't easy
Today on the show I fulfill my promise to my former self
I am going to figure out
How online mugshots turned into a business
Hyatt legal and if we can stop it
This message comes from NPR sponsors
Squarespace
Squarespace allow small business
Design and build their own webs
Using customizable layout
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobile a
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online price
Go to Squarespace.
Tom NPR for
Free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR
Hard to save 10% off your first purchase at
If a website or don't
Let's start
Fairies
Why do mugshots even
Why is it
Picture of you on your worst day available
You kind of have to go back to way before the internet even is
Back before the founding of America back to our founding Grudge
Against the British because the Brits were arresting people secretly so the colonists were like that's not cool
And they started
Publishing their own list
Everest
Has like a check on power service and after we kick the Brits out
We passed laws so that
Now Americans get to know all kinds of things about what the government's doing we get access to a lot of government records
Including mugshot
And the first mug shots were physical photographs that law enforcement would
Basically just collect in a book
And for really long time you had to go to the jail fill out a form
In order to see them so it took some effort to
To see a mugshot
And then the internet
Alright so now we don't have to go to jail again
A picture now we can just find on The Intern
Exactly so
Police departments in jails they start putting a bunch of their information online
In part because there was this push to get
More information out to victims of crime
So you have more mugshots online
And then someone takes this beuno Noble Public accessing
And turns it into a
Huge
And the guy who's credited with doing that
Is an enterprising ex-con in Florida
That you're saying we have to blame Florida man as usual
And this particular Florida man is robbed Wicca
Robert served three years in prison and he was out and trying to get back on it
Enneathought
What if I applied my computer programming skills
To Florida
Very liberal public
Record access laws
Tokyo
It's downright the program that just scraped mugshots from law enforcement websites and posted them to his
Brand new website
Florida arrests
. org
Where
Kindly let visitors
Tagged mugshots you can take them like
Hottie or w
UTF
And he also kindly let people
For a small fee remove their mugshots
But that
The online mugshot industry was born
What used to require real effort
Like drive to a government office or mail in
Quest weight
Is now just an idle curious Google search away
Yeah I used to work the graveyard shift at NPR reading the news and I would come across
So many of
Things are more like articles
Of people making fun of people who are in mugshots and I remember some of these sites names
Georgia busted
Spring break mug
Gotcha mugshots
Also
A lot of newspaper
Fight like the Tampa Bay Times about 5% of their overall site traffic is
Is to their mugshot page
There's like this online
Ecosystem around
People's worst Moana
Millions of people's worst moment cuz millions of people get arrested every year
In fact if you took all the arrestees in America right now and made them into their own country it would be bigger than
And if
All the arrestees where to stay
Hold hands
They could circle the Earth
Free time
Okay I guess that you're very into spatial metaphors right now
I also know because I said near you in the office that you have been calling up a lot of people
Quip dealt with issues
Because they're mugshots
Right yeah I wanted to get a sense for what the experience is like
For other people
Because you know my arrest is now just kind of a funny family story
Which can happen when you're a middle-class white girl
But for a lot of people I talked
The thing that change their lives
As much as the arrest
If not more
With the fact that their arrest would now tag along with them on
Dates
Job interviews
Housing applications
Forever
Even though a mugshot
Is often misleading
I talked to Sarah lageson she's a sociologist from Rutgers who study says
A mugshot doesn't tell us much about the person who's arrested
It tells us a lot about
Who the police decided to arrest
A huge chunk of people who are arrested are never charged or
In California in 2011
Actually the majority of people arrest
No charge no conviction
And the chances of getting arrested are of course much higher for some
Some people you are 16% more likely to get arrested if your a Hispanic man
And 29% more likely if you're a black man
And if we
You have some trouble with the systemic and
And structure problems with who gets arrested we should also have problem taking the mugshot says there's an indicator of who
Who is dangerous
They can make it harder to get
Job because
More than 75% of employers say that they Google every
Candidate end
If they see your mugshot they can just
Eliminate you right away without even interview
And just so you know these people just aren't qualified for the job
And as the applicant there's no way for you to challenge that you don't really know what's going on people I talked to told me that these mugshots
It harder to date
Sarah also says that people will cut way back on what she calls pro-social
They might stop volunteering at schools
Because that there's a background check
Thing there and of course you're in the small community where
People talking gossip
The last thing you want is for your kids half
To deal with it and then you take the worst
Case scenario the wrongfully convicted
People like Jacques Rivera in Chicago
He served 21 years for a murder he did not commit
But he's online mugshots still LinkedIn
To this murder even said he should
It's still be in jail
You talk to the Chicago Tribune about what it meant that his mugshot was on Mugshots
Profile salon
How to charge a murder you know
And Isis
The scary
That's all it takes is one person and
To change my life forever
Just like the wrongful convictions insult
But to be clear jock could pay the extortionary fee to the website
Side right he could but that is probably not going to solve the problem because it just keeps popping up on other side
It's like after I paid mugshots.com mine popped up on another site
To pay them
For lots of people it can end up on like a dozen
Okay what
Brings us to our second question
How is this even legal
As I looked into this
I discovered that it's
Actually kind of our fault
My fault soap reporters are the biggest
Cheerleaders for access to online mugshots
Cut up a lawyer named Adam Marshall
He is a litigator for the reporters committee for the freedom of the press
And I was trying to get some government
Okay so how does Adam defend
Your mugshot DUI mugshots
Adams job is to fight for access to government.
Documents like as many as we can get soap
He is a purist on this topic
He thinks mugshot access
Should be absolute
It's hard for us to predict
Like when
That openness is going to be really important
When is it going to be
The case of mistaken identity when is it going to be
Theodore St who's beating up by the cops
Okay but there has to be some
Reasonable way to
Handle this
An atom's mind it's a hard thing to
To do because you can't say it like
We're going to cut off access to this information because people are using that information
Poorly
McCaffrey
Start saying
Oh you can only you know have
Access to government information
If you use it in a good way
That's like a really
Dangerous road I think
To go down
What's important is that we deal with
People who are trying to again
Extort
Or abused
People
I think that's what
The way the Constitution protects ideas like the freedom of
The Press is to protect some extra stuff to stuff we don't necessarily like
So it can feel scary to Copper
How to say yes yes public records
We need them
But
The internet is weaponized some of them so for those records you need a permission
We're almost there we are almost
At the end of your quest
To avenge
Your former mugshot itself
And our final question is
Is it possible to stop these sites
There are people who are trying
18 states have passed laws
Then make it illegal for a website to charge you to
Take your mugshot off of their say
The problem is those are really hard to leverage this is Sarah lageson again this sociologist from Rutgers
The last don't have a lot of teeth
There's jurisdictional confusion
If the server's in Belize
The website operators in Florida
Play where do I begin right what court do I even go to to file this
Also some of the penalties are really low
And states that have these laws most of them don't even enforce them
Which leaves it mostly to citizens
Cystocele
Leaving aside how expensive that would be
These are the last citizens who would want to engage with
I've asked people.
Sue them ever thought about taking legal action and they look at me like I'm crazy anything why would I ever go re-enter courtroom
People who sued have found their mugshots
Suddenly multiplied across the internet
So some people get created
If they try to just do what they can to move their mug shot down in the Google
Like this one guy that Sarah enter
He created all these online profiles of the
This person last name he started blogging about the TV show Arrested Development
IC
Why
You assigned yourself
You want it so that when people
Google Karen Duffin mugshot that comes over the Planet Money episode not your mugshot
That's what you said
All jokes aside Google can fix
What they have been trying
A few years ago people started saying like why doesn't Google just cut this off
In response Google made this claim that they were going to change the algorithm and that they were going to make sure that these
Mugshots weren't showing up right away I talk to Google and they told me yes they have been working on this for years now
Sarah seems to think it actually kind of back
In reality what they did was it
Taught all the website operators how to optimize
Their websites for Google search results cuz
They no longer it's going to be
Passively happening
They needed to figure out how to make sure that their website they're showing up right away so they actually can experts message response
If they got a vaccine
And now that it made them stronger
Google told me
They promised they are
We're still trying to
I'm not going to say
You're
Disappointing
Your former self
You told your former self that you were going to find Solutions
In the show have you found any actual
The solution that some people have found is
Just go back to the system that we had
Before the
Just still let people get mugshots
But just not make it automatic
Like the fat
For a long time
Federal mugshots
We're pretty easy to get
2 years ago
The court said
I think the internet's turned mugshots into something that they were never meant
So now you can only get Federal mugshots
If you do it the old-fashioned way
You have to make a request
Sherpas
Federal arrest
Tiny frog
That is
That is true so I also looked around to see
If anyone's trying to solve this at a
State or local level
And I found this guy Mitch Lucas he is the assistant sheriff in
Charleston South Carolina
And he told me that when he heard about what mugshots.com and other sites were doing
He was Furious
Call it despicable
Respect was the only
The only one I can think of
Scribe
All the people
So
Wait wait
Decided to do what we could
Make it more.
The way he made it more difficult
Call for them
Is bite turning to his it guys
And saying
Stop letting these sites automatically slurp up are mugshots
Stop the robot
The robo
Protractor
I want photo that
Refuge 11.1 it's impossible to erase what is already out there but
They can put up a gate
To getting new mugshot
And what they did is Kai
Kind of technical but
Basically they wrote software that makes it impossible for websites
Pick up their mugshots
Kinfolk gota work
It did actually
If you go to mugshots.com and you search on Charleston
Most of the entries that come up don't have pictures
So you're saying our Collective faith
Is in the hands
Of local
Yes this is a solution
But it
Would require thousands
Civ counties
I'm guessing that the odds of that are
Pretty low
So I
Did come up with one more solution that I ran by Captain with
I have a proposal
I think that everyone
In the country has to take an unflattering photograph of themselves and post it online with
With the worst thing they ever did
And then we're all leave it but it's fine
I'm sure you'll have people jumping at the chance to participate
I don't know how to figure out how to spell it
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital
Capital One
When is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimum
That can be open from anywhere
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in Uruguay
Na
Family story ideas
Want to share an unflattering photo with us
You can let us know at Planet Money at npr.org we are also a
Twitter Facebook and
Instagram were at Planet Money episode was produced by Sally Helm Big Valley
Our editors Brian Earth that are supervising producer is out cold
Special thanks to
A lot of people Utah public radio and Alvarez
Seth Rose
Daniel Tannenbaum all the people who spoke to me about
About their mugshots
Add a huge thanks to Jonathan shub who is working on a lawsuit right now about this issue in Pennsylvania
I am Karen Duffin
Thanks for listening
Would you like to describe the makeup of our family
Well we have
People sick
Children you keep killed off one of us cuz you said there were six
Oh my goodness I try that again
Now I just want to know which kid didn't survive