This message comes from NPR sponsor NCR running a small business is now easier with ncrc
More than a point of sale
NCR silver is simple-to-use saves you time and helps you reach your goals faster
Visit ncr.com silver
Hello and welcome
The planet money I'm Kenny Malone
And I'm helica xiamen
Hilke schellmann journalism professor at NYU.
We've asked you here to join us today because
I feel like it's fair to see become
Mildly obsessed
With the topic of
Today Show me some truth to that I'm a journalist
Professor I think a lot about I worry a lot about fake news
And more generally I'm really concerned about trust
On the internet came to us
NSAID
Before
There was
Before there was a possibility of like
Xvideo in
Fake audio
The world was dealing
With
A different fake problem
Yes
Fake
Online
People have been posting
Dishonest online fake reviews
For years and this is becoming such a huge problem because like
No
I go online to buy a hoverboard
And I don't know if this hoverboard has five stars
Because it is
Awesome and I'm going to cruise around town looking
Cool or
If it is five stars because someone is making up those reviews and in fact when I take it home
It's going to set my house on fire
But
Hilka
Is here with a glimmer of hope for us
Yes
And the glimmer of hope
Is coming from it
Totally unexpected place
The online bodybuilding
Community
Today on the show The Story of one weightlifter battling fake reviews on his own website
And what happens when you took on
Amazon.com
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Cambridge
The Bold way to steady growth
People often think annuities are too conservative to complex or only for retirees
What annuities can be a smart way to
To hedge Market risk
And earn guaranteed returns
Game Bridge aims to change the game
By offering simplified annuity
Please in a Sleek digital experience
That replaces fine print in
Phone tag
With clear conditions
Ana direct loafy model
Learn more at game Bridge.
5 / NPR
Game Boy
It's not available in Austin
A couple of things to know about Tommy
He lives in Reno Nevada he likes to juggle
Weird things
So just y'all be like in the grocery store and I'll have like an avocado and a onion and a bottle of water
Oh that's high stakes
Speed ripen avocado you're buying them
Yeah
The story of how Tommy started fighting fake reviews
Begin Sivan 2006
Tommy was in college
Cal Poly San Luis Obispo at the
What time is 90
It was a bit of a gym rat that is Peak he could bench-press around 200
40 lb
Monday
Tommy was hanging out with
The friend money says hey do you want the rest of this pre-workout pre-workout it's like a powdered stimulant you're supposed
To take before you
I just gives you crazy energy and you can lift more and longer and harder
You know at least those are the claim
Just to be clear this is not a steroid
In case that's what you're saying
Tommy's very against
Anyways
Tommy's friend
Is really not happy with the Stephanie purchase
ASA Tommy
I paid 60 bucks for it
And it gives me such bad stomach issues that I
It's ruining my workouts
Counter product
If you're not familiar with the supplement world it's not the most tightly regulated
And on top of that back in
In 2006
More and more folks were starting to buy
Online like
Supplements to gears my head started turning and I started looking up supplementreviews and I couldn't find anything that was
But yet I mean I was all just written by the manufacturer they could
Amazon opportunity
He could build an online review side
What bodybuilders give honest feedback about the supplements they're putting into their bodies
And so Tommy got to work he taught himself some
Computer coding and he created what he would eventually call
Supplement reviews
Dot-com
Before long Superchips
Dudes with logging on to Super
Views
And look
I know
Not all bodybuilders down this way but
As I read through these reviews
I could not
Not here though
In The Voice
Of the situation from
Just started using this product Scott Way huge
Complain
Overall rating
Yeah you know we couldn't get the real City
Situation
Feeling it is our very own Stacey Vanek Smith
As you can tell from my voice but I'm you know I'm cute
City how much can you bench press
3 to pounds
What type of bench press
JCPenney
Okay anyway
Tommy site
Became a place where bodybuilders go
Could share all kinds of supplement experiences
Including
Great successes
This literally gives me skin splitting pumps no lie I have stretch marks all over and incredible games
Overall rating 10
Maybe more importantly
The site was
Also plays for bodybuilders
Tell each other about
Problematic products
I'm sure
This will be the last day I take
Take the
I have heart palpitations
And I'm not sure if tomorrow I will wake up
Overall rating 5
I don't know I mean it tasted pretty good okay well
Not everyone thought that same pattern
This stuff give me a strong urge to
Some sort of strange circus going on in my stomach
Overall rating
There's a lot of talk of stomach issues
Yeah
Imploding
Is bloating a big problem
Yeah
Bodybuilders
We're writing reviews
Tommy got a referral fee when customers found products they like
Through his sight
It was going so well for Tommy
That he decided to just run the side full-time
Then as it grew it started climbing the ranks
Google you know ranking number one for the term supplement reviews
Yeah
Zazzle website
Became more and more prominent
Supplement companies
Became more and more
Aware
And how their products were being reviewed on it
Tommy says that the time is maybe getting like
20 views a day
Like he wasn't reading every single one of them for using a lot of them
And he started to see the so
Suspiciously positive reviews
Creepin in
This is one frogs
University proven studies
Anyone can test
The product but have proof that it works
Keith
I absolutely enjoy the taste
Especially
Grape I also really enjoyed the unflavored and the tropical Finland
Almost reads like a sales pitch
Any kind of read it and you think all right was it a wrap that wrote this or was it someone that just
Drank the Kool-Aid of the marketing campaign
I never get bloated from it
Despite it sometimes take two times as much
Is the serving during a nap
My workout
Believe the hype is a spot a truly deliver the pain with a promises
The taste of it is very good as well as mixed crop
Super Tommy these kinds of reviews were sometimes hard to deal with because
It sounded like a person from the company just come in and written this but
What if it was someone who had tried the product and really did believe the hype
And that's the problem with online reviews in a nutshell
It's almost impossible to tell from the continent alone if the reviews fake or not
But Tommy new
If a company was coming in and pretending to be a regular bodybuilder who
Happen to love their product
The entire idea of his website
Would fall apart so I would really have to do a bunch of investigative work on each one to really see where it originated in weather
Whether it was from the company or not
So Tommy goes to work
Basically the first thing I check out is the email address that they used
To register for the site
Company email address
That happens sometime
Yes
It didn't take Tommy long to realize that these companies were coming in
And basically there were just writing press releases
Fake reviews
The flooding in
And starting to overwhelm the real reviews
And I just thought it's not fair that you know people that actually leave feedback that is
Real honest are getting silence
Tommy took all this time and created the
Displays for honest
Speed bag
And that was just being
Turns into the exact opposite
Yeah
Yeah well it's might you know it was my work as my life's work and
It's painful to see somebody just disrespected like that in the name of of money
Tommy site
Pretty small site
Starting to wonder like if this is happening
To supplement reviews.com
I wonder how big of a problem this is
Another site
So you went into the belly of the Beast of online shopping
Amazon.com
And I looked at this testosterone booster that had
560 reviews
It was actually 580 River
Tommy starts to scan through a little bit
And he speaks review Spidey senses are going bonkers
And he's like okay
I'm going to inspect every single one of
It's going to be a lot of work
And imma need my special Pandora station
For this based off of a song from
I call him Deadmau5 but the other people call him Deadmau5 it's called take care of the proper paperwork is
What's the name of this song
This certainly must be in the top 10
Songs named after paperwork don't you think
Is that is pretty accurate
So Tommy is going through every single review
And essentially asking
How do I know I can trust
I've got an Excel spreadsheet open and I got
Amazon and I've got like 500 tabs open on Amazon and I'm sitting there just
Look at the next review tally updated look at the next of your tally up to
Online fake
Some of them
Or not so tricky for example
One review he noticed there was a before and after
Skinny guy after
Super ripped
Tommy does a reverse image search
And he finds the earliest example of a photo on Reddit
And I messaged that user on Reddit and I said hey did you also use this image for a review
And I said no no no
Busted a stolen before and after
Obviously
Play fake
As he investigates Tommy's also starting to notice that
Some suspicious reviewers have almost like an
An mov
But he can identify
Didn't you start naming these different types of question
Snowball reviewer
One category of the brand monogamous
These are people that only review products
From one company
Over
And over again
Sure maybe that person really likes that company or
Maybe that person works for that
Another fake reviewer profile
The one hit wonders
These are people who review
One thing
And then
Never review anything
I mean obviously there are people that just review one thing
That's
Totally up a normal thing that happens but if it happens a lot and if
Those one hit wonders are giving the product of 5 * across-the-board then
You know again maybe there's something unnatural about that like if it's testosterone booster had
A bunch of one hit wonders that were all really positive
That is pretty
But the most unnatural
Retro pattern Tommy
Was this suspicious flood of
Have positive reviews around the exact same
Yeah it was like three days of you know this super high volume where I think like
30% of the reviews were submitted
And that's fishy because it is way more reviews than any other 3-day stretch
And they're really positive
So it looks like maybe
Somebody paid for a bunch of fake reviews
Around
The way that sometimes works is that a seller might want to boost their rank
They want to sell more product and then eat my positive reviews
So their sides when they come by these fake reviews
But then those positive reviews
All posted on the same time
And so for Tommy after reading through all those reviews learning the tricks
Utrade
What percentage of those 580
You think we're tainted or bias
Probably all of them
Like nearly 100% or maybe 100%
Yeah our something is wrong with them
Xiaomi
Was on this mission
To clean up
The fake reviews on his own website
And they looked at Amazon and he finds out
Even Amazon
Ssj ganti problem
BS reviews
Not only that
If he ever wants to go on Amazon and buy something again
He's realizing he's going to have to spend hours
Going
Review by reviewed
To figure out what is even
Untrustworthy
Or I could write a computer program to do all this in
Seconds
Access these Pages automatically
Pull the data and
Give me you know
Better picture of the reviews
And I'm sitting there thinking like and if I wrote that computer program to do all this and seconds I could point it at any product
And so Tommy Noonan went back to work and in essence
He coded a version of himself
Dolphin internet review detector
They can help any of us
Pull up an item on Amazon
And cut through all the BS reviews to find
Just a good one
He started a new website that he called review meta.
And after the break
We'll go shopping
Support for this pot
And the following message
Come from State Farm
Who's agent snow
That your car and home
Are more than just big purchase
They're a big part of your life
You put the time into making them your own
So now it's time to protect them
With your own personal State Farm
Not only do they truly get you
But they'll be there for you when you need
And with over 19000 aging
Neighborhoods across the US there could be one
Just around the corner
Moritz statefarm.com
1 800 State Farm
State Farm
Here to help life
Go right
Re touka show me how review meta
Can help me get over my fake or doing
What do you need
I just went on vacation and my
Phone died four times because I do not
Ex-div iPhone cable
Got so you go to Amazon and
You put an iPhone cable
Yes sir we have
Over 20000 results for iPhone cables that's a lot
Alright so this one has 277 reviews
Four stars like that
It looks great on the surface
And then you take the URL
Copy it and then you paste it into review meta
Okay and then I hit
Bonaparte and events a report
Rite Aid sell Computing Computing bleep bloop bleep bloop
37 reviews
Big 5 hours
At any rate eventually it spits out a report and we got Tommy Noonan on the line
To walk us through a few of the things his website
Flags about these iPhone
Okay so for this product we see that
Over the course of five days
This product got
78% of 30
And on top of that
The reviews from those high-volume days
Give the product
4.9 star rating on average
These reviews of those 5 days
Pretty suspicious
Especially when you look at the reviews from those 5 days
Compared to the average reviews
The way my pasta
Tommy says the reviews for these cables raise a few other red flags
As well there was one issue
With words that were being used over and over again in the reviews
So the phrase repetition basically what we do is we we build a gigantic list
Of all of
The
Phrases that are used in the reviews that are peanut-free words or more and then we go
Algorithm is able to filter out normal phrases
For example
It was the
And this way the algorithm can look at weird phrases that
You would not expect it
For example
The court is very tough and doesn't Bend like the cords do but that's probably a good thing
That's not
That you shouldn't see that in more than one review but for here we see it in
3 reviews
End in 7 reviews someone wrote it
It's easy to get it back onto the
The core dance music
I don't know what it means seven people feel that
Well seven people also say they performed their Duty with honor Andres
Respect and there is the incorrect
Yeah so
Tommy software roundabout
Does indifferent test on iPhone cable reviews
His reports
Get out an adjusted rate
So it went from a
Four star out of five
With 177 reviews on Amazon
Any adjusted rating on review meta
Is 1.7 Stars
After 10 reviews
Which is another way of saying
Tommy side only trusted
6% of the reviews
And a trustworthy reviews say
Actually these cables are crap
Tommy says generally speak
Cables like this
Are exactly the
The kind of product
The wines of cluttered with
Anything with like low manufacturing costs
Sand High margins
I feel like what yeah yeah iPhone cables backup batteries
Screen protectors phone cases
Weight loss pills
We of course we sell to Amazon about the
And they declined it going tape but
They are familiar with Tommy's website
Ascentis
An extensive state
About it
Review meta itself admits that they do not have the Danzig City
See if you could do
Non weightlifter
Oh okay
Review meta itself admits
They do not have the data to know or even say with icon
It's whether a review is
According to what Amazon is saying it's not necessarily different from what Tommy told us about his
Totally admits that
His sight is looking for patterns of unusual
Behavior in
There's a possibility that real reviews get flagged as a
Buy Amazon
That is a problem we have hundreds of millions of reviews on am
And of that total less than 1% are in Arthur
Amazon also told us that is investing in its own system
How to catch fake reviewers
Amazon is saying there's not a problem
But we're working on it
And this makes me like
Wonder a little bit how much should I
Trust
Beeg sites like
John are actually going to go out of their way
Fix this
So it's complicated right because these e commerce sites
They make money when they sell more
Red Lake it doesn't matter if
It's a positive fake review if someone buys a product that's good for the
There might come a time
Where there's just too many fake review
Sure like there's a Tipping Point where
Enough
Trust is lost
That
We all just give up
Yeah fun internet shop
Yes I'm going to go back to friends
Tan France
People go back to her friends for recommendation
Well yeah
There is a point
Wait just one set for all of us
And we have to go back to talking to a friend's again
You have to call your mom
Shopping advice
Yes what toothpaste you should use other than one question
Today Show
Shows produced by Nick fountain or editor is Bryant urstadt or supervising producer is Alex goldmark who told me to tell
Tell you we could use reviews to win a Mike's reviews so please don't make it no real reviews
Special thanks to fix spot which is actually another similar software to review Meto which you can use
How to spot fake reviews they've been really helpful alone
And I'm helica xiamen
Thanks for listening