Support for NPR and the following message
Which come from WWE
Publishers of people power and profit
Progressive capitalism for an age of discontent
By Nobel prize-winning economist
Joseph E stiglitz
Alright Alex I have you here where are we
Block away from her office at a liquor store
Take you on a field trip because we are doing
The rest of the story summer edition
I love this is what my favorite episodes for we revisit past
Episodes and we find out what has happened since we are done we bring you updates
And I gathered because you brought me to a liquor store
They were going to revisit the episode we did on vodka yes you are correct
So remind us what was that episode about
Is there really a difference between
Cheap vodka and expensive vodka and no not really is what we came down to
Hanging you claim that when you drink Vodka cheap vodka
You get flushed cheeks butt
When you drink Vodka during that episode your cheeks did not get flesh
I will concede that is
How that episode ended
So we thought you might be making it up about this cheap vodka allergy maybe it's just in your head
But then after the episode aired we got all these emails from listeners who were like no no this happens to me too with vodka
Three-sided we're going to give you another chance to prove that the Vodka allergy is real
I am grateful that I'm getting a chance to redeem myself
Alright well listen we are serious journalists here at Planet Money so we are going to fact check your claim here
And if you're right if your cheeks to get flushed
We will correct the record
Hello there
We're here to buy some
Some cheap vodka
Alright already
Okay but I don't want you to have to drink alone so I invited someone here to drink with you
Okay I'm very intrigued
Lesbian outside looks to introduce you
Okay
How are you
Good Sam email listener
He said that he also gets these flash red cheeks from vodka
The trouble is real
You want to do is the owners
Sure
Hello and welcome to Planet Money
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm samperio be today
Show the rest of the story
You to go drink I'm going to go back to the studio I'm going to get a bunch of updates on Pixel and giving good care of pesticides
And then I'm going to come back
To you too
And I took some information for you from a doctor about your alleged allergy and then we'll see if you go
That's what you did will set the record straight
This message comes from NPR Spa
Sergey Brin
The Bold way to steady growth
People often think of annuities are too conservative
Too complex or only for retirees
What annuities can be a smart way to
Two-head Market
And earn guaranteed
Returns game Bridge aims to change the game
By offering simplified annuity
Please in a Sleek digital Xperia
That replaces fine print in
And phone tag
With clear conditions
Ana direct loafy model
Learn more at game Bridge.
5 / NPR
Game Boy
Is not available in Austin
For our first update we are going back to episode numbers
Pig weed killer
In that episode we told you about a murder that came about because of a pet
Pesticide
And we have brought Dan Charles into
To the studio today to give us the update.
Haband and you've been with us here at Planet Money this summer
But
Your day job is to be NPR's food and farming correspondence that I was absolutely fascinated
Obsessed actually with the storyline
Last year reminds listeners
If they did not hear the original episode what what have
Basically a fight broke out beat
Farmers over weeds
Epsom farmers were killing their weeds with this
Pesticide a weed killer called Dyke
Timbuk
It worked for them because they were growing these special new soybeans
That could survive. Cambage
But I can't burp that this chemical they're using it has a big problem which is it blows away
It can just evaporate after you spray it
Any kind of drifts
Across the lands
Which is why at the time we did that episode
It was actually illegal to use that camera that
That's why these farmers
We're breaking the law and I Campbell was
Damaging crops and neighbors Fields provoking
Fights
And there was a murder
And what happened with that murder case
A man named Alan Curtis Jones went on trial he claimed self
Defense about the jury
Buy it
They found him guilty of second-degree murder he was sentenced to
224 years in
And the other thing that happened was the pesticide companies said they fixed
Static ham butt so it wouldn't
So it became legal to spray last
Thousands of farmers started using Zicam
And maybe it wasn't fixed
Millions of Acres of crops were.
And it was most intense in Arkansas that's where the problem was the worst that's also where the murder happened
And there it all landed in the lap of a regulatory body called the
The Arkansas state
This is kind of like
The pesticide police in Arkansas
They have a lot of power but these are just
Regular citizen
Who have regular lives like one I met his name
Terry Fuller he runs a farm supply Paso
So are people coming to you and saying it
Got to do something
Absolutely
Farmers
Town people community people
Lined up
We had as many as 15 people at the office before 7 in the morning
On two or three different occasions
Always
All waiting to see me and never feels
Serta personally threatened it
Somewhat there's two loaded guns in my office
And I don't need to chamber a round
I feel personally threatened somewhat
And and what they decided
How to do was to actually go back to AB and basically say until you can figure out a way to pray
Prevent this damage
No farmer in Ark
Consult during the summer when the weather is hot in this
Is drift happens
No Farmers allowed to spray dicamba on their crops
Okay so no farmers are
Sprained I can buy in Arkansas
That was the
Plant
Just last week
I called Terry Fuller back
I said well is it working and he was not a happy
There's at least 5000 Acres of soybeans in Phila
Holmes County vet
Show symptomatology
Oh wow
Curled up leaves stunted growth
Was crazy this was just
Not supposed to happen this year
Not supposed to happen this year scribs Luli correct
So people break in the lobby
Apparently
It seems like those volunteer Regulators in Arkansas have not managed
The problem the company said they were going to fix it they don't seem to have
The problem
So this is going to land in front of the Environmental Protection Agency
At the federal government level to see whether they are going to let this product stay on the market
Oh okay alright we'll keep an eye on Weeds and before you leave then I want you to settle something for it
We got literally hundreds if not thousands of tweets and emails
Challenging us
It's on our use of the word pesticide in the original episode
Can you please settle this debate for us pesticides include both insecticides and herbicides
Herbicides are a form of pesticide we can use pesticide
So please no more Tweets in email
We are all correct in this
Situation
I think Stan my pleasure
We have Sally Helm in the studio
Hi Sally
So a couple of months ago
You and Kenny Malone today
A great episode about the smoot-hawley Tariff
And I'm so sorry what
Something like 90 years old now we did
I expect to have an update on
We did not
Just a reminder the smoot-hawley Tariff swear these
Protectionist
Tariffs that Economist generally agree
We're up there
We called the episode
Worst terrorist ever it's number 833
And after aired we got an email from a listener
Who we were not expecting
Down there
Great Wolf first I have to have you introduce yourself so what is your full name
My name is Austin Smoot
Waitts Lake smooth
Smoot-hawley yes
Senator Reed Smoot
Who was one of the people responsible for the Tariff Act
Is Austin's
Great great
Grandfather's brother okay so did Austin know about the skeletons in his family's closet heat did not know about
Until he was in college
Sitting in an intro economics class
During a class discussion I raise my hand
And I asked a question I
Don't even
McCall what I asked but Professor goes down
Great question
What did you say your name was
And I responded
Austin Austin smoke
Nissan Leaf pause
I need scanned over the whole classroom
And there was a big class we probably like a hundred hundred fifty kids as well as big Auditorium one
And a little grin on his face and he just says
Smooth
Trying to learn basic economic I've never heard of such a thing
He was expecting that the class was just going to erupt
Did this amazing Joker he just told
But fortunately
An intro to economics course so there was
Silence
Looking for Alexa
Yeah they did no idea
Okay so his
Professors told the nerdiest
File jokes
Is this house
He finds out yeah he goes home after the classy shirts Googling he ends up Googling for hours reading about the
Hawley tariff act
And he actually had a
Paper due soon after this for the class and he writes about the smoot-hawley Tariff Act
Turned it in early cuz he's so into it
And Donnelly. Karen as a result of this
Experience Austin Smoot
Changes his major from electrical engineering
To finance and economics wow did you switch your major to sort of
A town
Exactly I'm out I'm trying to make up for the name and save my children
Because I'm sure they're going to sit down one day and an economics class and when they call the roll
The exact same thing is going to happen that I've no doubt
That Professor from Austin's econ 101 class he actually ended up hiring Austin to work at
Economic think-tank
Often did that little while now he is an accounting analyst in Salt Lake City Utah
All right we'll see if he can clear the family name thanks Sally thanks Karen
For this next update I want you to take your mind back to episode
Cub Bitcoin losers
We told the story of this guy named
Sell hookah
Some Bitcoin back when it was cheap
Got to write down the keys so
She could not
Access is Bitcoin
And we tried to help him find it
Did not find it
Is not that he did find it
But we did get this one email after
The story ran and are
Beloved internet Aviva dekornfeld
I was reading through these emails and she flagged it for us in
And she's actually back here as a producer with us
Today in the studio glow Aviva
Hey Karen
Okay so the listener
Who emailed us her name is Marissa Mini
And when she sent this she was in the middle of this big
From New York to LA
And while she was packing up she of course
Was listening to Planet Money all right good where she heard our reporter Kenny Malone helping sell
Rummage through his attic for his loss
And hearing this episode she remembered like
I bought cryptocurrency
A few months ago
And I also
Did she do it still did she forget to write down her
Kind of the opposite
She bought the cryptocurrency
And I wrote on the speaker
Can my very very very bad hemorrhoid
It's case sensitive
And it's $20
Okay so she wrote it down
But
Reader on hand
Okay so apparently
We need to add one more piece of
Advice write it down
Legibly exactly
So one of the lessons of the Bitcoin loser
Episode was that crypto is never really lost
The consultants make this
It's claimed that if you have even part of your key then
Are these people called Bitcoin hunters and they can help you figure out your whole key and act
Chester Wallace
I'm so nervous I heard this
An email Kenny and said
Do you know anyone who
Can possibly help
Antonis like
Yeah here's this website and it leads her
This guy name
Bitcoin
Like his screen name.
Professional name Hunter
Says
Send me all of your information
You have every bit of your illegible
Kian doll
And where our Consultants right was it enough just to have like a few letters and numbers
Bitcoin Dave was able to
How to unlock mirror
Wallet
She got back over $40,000
Minus
What's 15% cut
For doing all the hard way
Loud nice work honey Malone
And Bitcoin Dave I'll have to see you going Dave
Thanks of you guys thank you
For this next one we are going to take you on an economic scavenger hunt
This comes from an episode of we did a couple of months ago where we took questions from listeners
Including this question from Alistair name Brian Knowles
Who asked us to explain this
Very obscure economic
Term witch
Giffen good
And we brought in the great Patty Hearst to help us
Explain it he is here
The great Patty Hearst thank you
You are here with us to sort of your on the other side of the country at NPR West
And you are the editor of our daily
Play podcast
Indicator
Yes giffen Goods
Just to remind everybody
Is a staple commodity
Betsy's increasing levels of demand
Even as its price Rises
Which defies like the most fundamental laws of Economics right literally was like a unicorn of economic
Alright usually after
The price of something Rises
Demond
Sleep.
Because consumers get ticked off at paying the high price and they buy cheaper alternate
Okay and your contention was that they
They used to exist but they don't anymore
Exactly there are so many alternatives
Every commodity
That we have particularly in the developed
There really aren't any giffen goods
That's my content
Okay well our listeners have
A beef with that
We asked them
Can you send us your ideas for giffen goods and we got a
A ton of answers
Some of them I think
We can fairly safe
Please say do not qualify
If I like
Cheetos
Bison tongue
People also sent in
Like smartphones and
Subway
Some of the things they sent it I think they might
Actually qualify
Why so I have
Asked you Patty
To accept the solemn responsibility of deciding
Standing in judgment
On whether or not
These are in fact
I hate to think of the idea what I mean judgmental towards our listeners but
I don't know
Alright okay alright so
We have from our listener back
Premium coffee
Premium coffee okay Cassie.
Yet the price of premium coffee goes up and therefore demand goes up so the
Took up together
Okay I can see that I make
The problem is its premium coffee
Rite Aid Sonora Staples
If it was if it was Folgers or instant I could see that but this is not even a stand there all sorts of Alternatives any
I'm sorry does not qualify
Alright hipsters if you have hate mail send it
10 directly to patio
Okay so this next one I had not heard about until gave Robitussin about
Toilet paper
He said that there was this huge
Toilet paper shortage in Taiwan in March
Because home prices were going up and
Manufacturers were sitting there with that
Toilet paper prices were going to go up so there was like this
Huge Panic buying
Toilet paper
I know about this
And indeed there was a run on toilet
My people will literally buying up
Traits of it
In the stores
Crazy
Okay but here's the thing
Yes but price did not rise
All right so that the reason the Panic was created
People are expecting the
I actually didn't say the Panic was in fear of the high prices that never materialized
Prices actually stayed the same
So you get two or three
Okay just the idea of a toilet paper shortage
This is making me feel like
Okay I have one final contender
And this came
In various forms from Lotto
Two different people
Healthcare so
People say
Fenton like Niche drugs or emergency care but the
The one that I think might
Actually work
Basic health
Okay
Remember with a giffen good with talking about a staple with a price
Rises in the demand Rises
At the same time and it's because
You're giving up alternatives to notice.
Take the cheaper option
So I guess maybe
If you think about you
Looking after your health maybe you're giving up vacation in order to make sure
You get good health care that you
You're treated well
I could see that as a possible yeah I mean I pretty I think we have to take that apart a little bit but I think that's a really interesting
Wanted to look at I would say
We have a definite contender
Oh my goodness finally we have a winner basic Healthcare Patty is going to accept that is
I'm going to let you know I'm going to look into it but I'm certainly willing to open the door to it yet thank you so much
Ducati my pleasure, thanks for having me after the break we will return to Alex and our listeners Sam who had
Faithfully been drinking vodka
Paternalism back from the liquor store hanging out in the office
And I will fact check whether or not their cheeks to get flushed
Support for this podcast
And the following message
Search come from State Farm
Who's agent snow
That your car and home
Are more than just big purchase
They're a big part of your life
You put the time into making them your own
So now it's time to protect them
With your own person
State Farm age
Not only do they truly get
But they'll be there for you when you need
And with over 19000 age
Neighborhoods across the US
There could be
Just around the corner
Moritz statefarm.com
Are 1-800 State Fair
State Farm
Here to help life
Go right
Everyone grab a mic
I have answers
I'm very excited about this
I wanted to know if a doctor could explain this alleged cheap vodka allergy so I called one up
I'm Heather Linebarger and I'm a physician and who else are you a former roommate
That's right that she explained to me that
But the liver
Prince alcohol
And it's something that's really close to formaldehyde
Wow
Which can kind of make you flush and not feel good this is like the thing that you used in science class where you would like
Pyside cats exactly
And if you don't have enough of the
This one particular enzyme that
Get rid of formaldehyde
The formaldehyde might hang out
Anybody interior
And genetically Asian
People
Tend to have less of that particular enzyme so this is sometimes called Asian
Flash
Richard got a ton of emails about
This one but since you're
White that one is probably not it
There is one theory that Heather thought might be
The reason why this is happening to you and it actually kind of validates something that
The scientist in your episode said
Which is the cheap vodka
Might not distill out all the extra byproducts of whatever it's made out of light
Potatoes or whatever
Vodka from what I understand can come from
Any kind of stuff
If you let it from Atlanta
Valkyrie
Sakana totally is
In my guess
Best would be your boss
Does having more of an allergy
To the other
Kind of broken down
Stop
The furthermore
Important question
Which is did your cheeks get flushed
Let me just take a look
Oh yeah yeah yeah there's a little flesh
You look like a like one
Someone put like one round of blush
Yeah I don't know
Evaluate like
Round blush a little blush but like no one's going to be like oh my God hold off on
I think this means we do need to correct the record
I think we can say that your alleged flash is real
Very Vindicated right now
I definitely do
Yashow Vindicated my feelings salsa that makes me feel really good
I think that wraps up the rest of the story
I love working at Planet Money
We post a link to every episode on Facebook
You can find us there and comment you can also find us on Twitter and Instagram app
Planet Money or you can email us Planet Money at npr.org
Today show with produced by Sally Helm our editors Bryant first dad
And are supervising producer is
Alex
I'm Karen Duffin thanks for listening