This is pretty clear to me this
This is planet money Kenny Malone
This one looks bad to
But I think that's a for iMac
We're looking at a big circle on a computer screen that kind of looks like a bunch of Dippin Dots
And there is a number in the middle and a different color
Yep I literally can't see anything there
Circle of Dippin Dots has a light
Gray
An inside
There is
The number 6
Burgundy red
Dippin Dots
Start
It starts all the way here
Kenny and I have known each other for almost
Was 10 years we used to work together in Miami very colorful place
And I just found out that Kenny
Cannot see
Certain
Colors
He's one of about 300 million other people on the planet who have
Some form of
Color deficient
And medical world they've been studying colorblindness for
Centuries trying to find
Some cure
It was
Successful in a male squirrel monkey but not in humans yet
Color is
Super complicated Kenny is literally missing a
Apart of his eye
That allows us
To see certain
Colors
But
Recently
Like a lot of people I've been noticing these
Videos
There videos of
People with color blindness
All of a sudden
Perceiving
Color
Little old ladies who've gone their whole lives
Sing the world in Black
And white and red
Putting on bees
Sunglass
Suddenly noticing
All
The colors
I feel like I'm in heaven
Oh my goodness down there
It must be happy
Volcano
Thank you little kids
Having their realities suddenly
Strollers
Lionsgate films gave a bunch of kids with color blindness a pair of these glasses to watch the latest
Power Rangers movie
The Cosmetics company L'Oreal marketed a new shade of red lips
Peking South
America using these glasses
Clorox Clorox event make your brights
Brighter they wanted in on this
And you might think that the medical industry spent years
Trying to solve this and finally did it on schedule
But
That is not what happened
Frontier
Because that's
Not how inventions 10 to work
The guy who gave children the gift of color
He didn't know a decrement from a trichromat this whole thing these Miracle glasses it was all a
Total
Accident
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Sarah when Silas I can't tow
Rash from Gray I'm County Malone
Train show
Accidental inventions some of the greatest discoveries in the world
Happens by accident
Penicillin x-ray images popsicles
Scientists were massaging baby rats ones that had nothing to do with human babies but it accidentally determine
And how we care for premature babies
Accidental genius is lightning in a bottle and people have been trying to capture it forever
We're going to tell the story of one accidental inventions Miracle glasses to see if
The rest of us can create the conditions for the next great accidental invention
This message comes from NPR sponsor squares
Squarespace allow small businesses to
To design and build their own website
Using customizable Lake
And features including e-commerce functionality
Leanne mobile attic
Squarespace also offers
Built and search engine optimization
To help you develop an online price
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
To get to the guy who accidentally invented the
These glasses you walk down a dark
Concrete hallway in Berkeley California
It's one of those hallways that makes you feel like you need to
To whisper and
Duck your head down even though the ceilings are
Totally normal height
This is so dungeon e
Me to the inventor
How your back
Meet
Don McPherson
Former glassblower current
Glass scientists
Full head of white hair
Texas good shirt off when you work sitting in the chair shirt
John's office.
Smells like incense
Kind of looks like an old chemistry lab
Ground glass stopper bottles
Speakers
Pipette flask
Set thermometers
All the stuff that
Goes into languages
Chemistry
As a kid
Don used to wonder why humans would
Speak to dolphins in
Human why we were in speaking to them
Endorphin
So
Would you consider yourself
A hippie
No
I think you have 50 Tendencies this is Nebraska I might
Not a Berkeley no Berkeley hippies different
Story of how Dawn stumbled into the color blindness in
Industry start in the 90
Remember
He's a glass sign
And at the time
He was trying to solve a completely different problem that was happening
In operator
Surgeons who are using a certain laser had to wear this big orange shield in front of their face
Protect their eyes
The orange tent
Didn't block the laser but it also made everything else
Really hard to see
Insurgent hated it cuz they couldn't see anything
Everything looks Orange
Okay wait hold on what do you mean they couldn't
See anything for certain well if you put an orange filter in front of your eye
Then everything looks Orange
Green looks Orange
Yellow looks orange red looks aren't so they are trying to do surgery
And they couldn't tell the difference between bones
And tendons and tissue and blood
Lisa can see it
So it made they had to sort of rely on their their deep understanding of physiology 2
The do the work that sounds
Terrifying the top dollar
Sudan experiment
With other glass colors
Any created a pair of glasses that still block the laser butt
Allowed surgeons to see what they were actually
Operating on
That was
An intentional invention
Not an accident
But these glasses
It looks kind of cool
Kind of work is sunglasses so
The surgeons and Don start wearing them Outdoors
And one day Dawn is playing ultimate Frisbee with his friend
They're in Santa Fe
Light Breeze
And the fields
AR
Just a carpet of green bright green a pair of his surgery glasses as Sun
And his buddy Mike is like
Hey
To borrow those
What's the mon
And what the hell makes like dude when do those cones get there what are you talkin about Mike
Sure enough
There were a bunch of fluorescent orange cones marking off the playing field
But Mike
Had never seen orange before
It looked Brown to him
So did Green
Until he put on these operating room glasses
Sing orange was an accidental side of
And Dawn
John was like
This is amazing
He became obsessed with
Figuring out
Houses
What is going on here what have I stumbled onto
Pete stumbled onto a problem
1 and 12 men and 1 in 200
And I'm thinking I can help
Kenny Malone and all these other people
Ensure the glasses
Accidentally helped Mike's
The orange but no one wants to just
See orange I want to taste the color rainbow Man
So Dawn goes back to
To the lab to find the right
Color mix
Don't get funding from the national in
Institute of Health
Perfect his magic
Glasses
And he goes and he finds himself a business
Andy Schneider real brainy mathematician and former
Dancer
My
Passion was actually
What they call Ariel dance which was
Flying through the air like on like ropes and cables and stuff like that
Yuan Dairyland
Yes--go the aerialist yeah
I have an image of Andy that's hard to get out of my mind
Half-dressed
Perched on a pier
In the bay
It's part of a performance
At Twilight is that all right
Yeah
You didn't think Donald partner with some regular old basic mathematician right
Andy and Don
The math guy in the glass guy
Make a computer model of a color deficient I so that they can test different Filter Company
Still like the stop sign looks Brown at a field
Now it looks red
Good
Oh but now that filter made the grass look
Tinker with a filter 1 filter
That is just been tinkered with and tinkered with to make sure that as many colors as you possibly can look like the color that they're supposed
What the luck
That's absolutely correct finding the Perfect Blend
Took years
They're partnering with universities using clean room conditions running out of government funding doing clinical studies
+ 9
Years of research later
Andy and Don
The ugliest
Pair of octagonal shape
Glass
Sunglasses
The lens is really small
We'll put them in these tiny little friends
We could see through it
It worked
Rolling your eyes they're so
Heinously unattractive
Like
What you'd wear if you just had
Cataract surgery whatever it was a product it had a name
They called it
Enchroma
Means with
Color
Andy came up with that and then he regretted it
Later he said it should have been two syllables not three
Why it's like a trending
Can Celexa Valley Facebook Google....
What are you going to do
They make a much more attractive
Iframe website
Chroma is officially on the market.
Andy our psyche
And
No one's buying
It was difficult
Absolutely
Apparently it's hard to convince people to spend money on something they can't
See liked by this it'll give you purple and
I think you're really going to want to see purple
People saying well I don't need those
Because I've lived my whole life
Without them
And
I would be honest
That is exactly how I feel about these
Glasses I cannot imagine that whatever I've been missing out on
Is worth
Dollars
And they were actually more expensive when they first
Came out
I should say that these glasses only work on people with certain kinds of color blindness
Give me you've never seen The Color Purple you don't know how much
Purple is worth
I suspected it is less than $349
People like Kenny
They are not believers
And this happens to inventors because
They invented something it's a completely new product
Yeah completely new category
And people are not necessarily going to believe
It's going to do the thing you say it
This happened with the Xerox machine all these men were like we already have typist
They're called women why would we need this machine it took
The wives of these men to be like ya know this will actually save us a bunch of time just trust us on this
It's not enough to just
Produce a miracle
Product every new product needs a big boy
Ford on that Big Break
Came in the
The Forum
A balloon
One employee adding chroma had this great idea
To put deflated balloons in each box
Of colorblind glasses
People start blowing these balloons up and filming their loved ones
Seeing color for the first time
When I saw it I was like
I had nothing to do with it
But I was just like
Oh my God that's a world-class ideas so simple
Sarah has been sending me these videos
The sheer joy of seeing people see color for the first time it really like it makes you
Give these glasses as a gift
To anyone you know who is colorblind
Blue jeans
People could now see the glasses working the social proof
Lynch's the message the videos go
Viral
And people
Start buying
Oh my God
Is this Goosebumps
From head to toe like the whole thing two
Because I had never
Thought that this was going to happen I mean it's just came out of the blue accidental invention
Found people
Panini
And so many of the things that we have in the world happened
Just like this
Totally randomly and
By accident
The Pacemakers
Smoke detectors
Potato chips
So
Of course
Companies
Poor millions of dollars into trying
Force
The next great accent
They are trying to manufacture Serendipity serendipity
A word that in itself was a bit of an accidental invention coined in the 1700
By some guy who was obsessed with this Persian fairy tale about three princes killed in the
The art of detection in a land
Called Serendip
After the break
We go
Serendip
And also I obviously got can you pair these glasses
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence
And run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobiledit
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR
To save 10% off your first purchase
Please have a website or domain
This magical moment
Serendipity that all these companies are trying to
To tap into on a schedule and on timeline
How do you do it
We took that question
The authority
On accidental
Inventors
Taken Canada
So what who am I talking to mine as a pagan
Yes
I have to ask you about your name
Name Pagan came from high school Rebellion
Yeah her principal kept mentioning God In School she
She protested
A lot
And my friend nicknamed me pagan
Pagan used to have a column in the New York Times called who made that
Book about serendipitous inventions at one point
Stevens analysis and found
The 50% of patent
In Europe
Based on accident
And there's one inventor who taught her a lot about how they
Lonnie Johnson dr. Lonnie Johnson
He actually was a NASA engineer in the 80s was working on a water-powered
Playing with all these different nozzles
And he noticed
One of those
When the water went through it
Like
Flew out in this very cartoony way and kind of
Splattered against the wall
Very
Toilet
And this is
Similar to your inventor
He fell in love
What he saw
The NASA engineer spent the next nine years demoing this at toy fairs looking for anyone who
Would see what
He sign it
A super
Stoker a high-powered
Squirt gun
The Super Soaker 50 from Laramie
Of accidental inventions story
Sure
Finding your funny nozzle is a big moment
What people do not focus on
Is the years and years
Of time
And money and obsession
It took to finally get the suit
Super Soaker in
Spigen says just look at the greatest discoveries in science we know how they came about
Giving people lots and lots of money
And just try things
For years and years and years and years without expecting
Results
But as you can imagine people aren't really comfortable with unlimited money and time waiting for me
To happen so
Sears
All this enthusiasm right now and check in at
Demian
Science
To try to make employees
More prone
Do good acts
Stuff about
Should your screen be exactly this shade of red or blue
What kind of desk
Size would make people most
What's creative
Should the death
Have three seats added or two seats
She doesn't know why but there's
Currently an obsession with
Staircases at Big universities like
Serendipity causing staircases
Very very
Fancy staircases that in themselves cost billions of dollars that are supposed to make you bump into other
Pagan wants to
Take down
The staircase
I mean you know this is just
Hype and silliness
If you decide I want Mary from
Engineering to mingle
From with Bob in chemistry
And I'm going to make
A $3000000 staircase where they can bump into each
You are actually making the surroundings
Less
Serendipity
You have decided
The way in your mind
I'd discovery
Happen
But you are wrong
Because
Accidental
Discovery is going to be something you can't imagine
It's going to be something completely unexpected and weird
And it'll likely happen in a cup
Completely unrelated
And probably because of some chance encounter
Like Don's colorblind friend
If he didn't happen to have a
Colorblind friend on that Frisbee field
She would have never noticed
The Accidental side effect of
Sturgeon glass
Megan says
If you're looking to create xidan
You need diverse
The more diverse
Kinds of pie
People you bring in
What they can observe in the world like what kind of accidents they can have and learn from is going to be really
Much more of a spectrum
Being the believer in Miracles that I am I got Kenny a pair of these
Miracle glasses and I have determined
Kenny is going to
To fall in love
With purple Gonzalez is a force of nature
And you will not stop her from putting glass
I grabbed my inflated balloons and dry candy to a place with
The whole lot of colors
A carousel there's actually one right across the street
For my building
This will be the place where
Hayneedle
Covers
Oh my seatbelt
Baidu
Everybody
I'm calling off this carousel
Are you ready
Where they go
Today Show was produced by Sally helm
Oh my God
Broadcast super green
Look at the trash cans are so pretty
That's amazing the blue that's like this is baby blue and that's like royal blue
It's so beautiful I couldn't tell the difference in the past
It's like a whole different color
Alex goldmark is our supervising producer
Her dress purple dress is purple and pink
Special things to the Tennessee Department of Treasury
Development
They're breaking these lenses up and installing them and viewfinders around the state
So that color blind people
Can experience
The Fallen
Spring colors
This is amazing I want to show you my favorite flower
Because I think
I think you're really going to like it now that you could be purple
Red balloon
Is that what people call fuchsia
What is happening editor is Bryant or sad
Pink plus purple
That was tricky
Orange smoothie
Blue trash can
Yelling colors
This is Drake
Keep up keep up
Let skinny Malone and I'm Sarah Gonzalez
Thanks for letting