Hello Planet Money listeners this is Karen Duffin and I am here to ask you a very small paper
We would love your feedback about the show Good Bad Ugly we want all of it
All you have to do is
Is go to npr.org
Splash Planet Money survey that is all one word
You give us feedback about the show we make better shows
So I kind of think everybody win
That is npr.org Planet Money survey
Thanks so much hope you enjoy the show
Just a warning this is a story about
Drugs
And there is one brief
Bleep swear word
I got so loud here Lexie and I are at an intersection in Brooklyn Myrtle and Broadway
I think this is the most interception I've ever seen we get bodegas everywhere is Rost in graffiti cars criss-crossing
Through here whatever Direction they want to go and
Like the best thing of all
This guy standing behind us wearing a New York
Yankee Pat who keeps asking if he can swear into our microphones
Hey wait we came to this intersection because about 2 years ago something
Totally bizarre happy
There is one essential key Witness
Door waiting for him to meet us
I think he's actually walking up right behind you now
Bryan Mitsubishi man
Brian Arthur is 40 years old
He works as an overnight doorman
And in July 2006
Teen he was just getting home from a shift it was about 9 in the morning
He was walking down this street
As I sat in the corner over there
App that block is what you see
Passengers
On the floor
I'm just shaking and stuff like that
Record this
Brian decides to stream what he is seeing on Facebook
Driving directions 5 gamble at Myrtle and Broadway Hill
Ryan toy video shows two maybe three guys on their feet but just like
Wobbly
Like a bowling pin that won't follow
She got slumped over the top of a
The fire hydrant and Brian swings the camera to the left and out of the guy in the middle of the
But Street
It's too crazy
Turn out 5 6 7 of the zombified people
EMTs that started dealing with people on the ground
Shaking and Brian
Cannibal
Crazy like you
What Brian was seeing was a mass overdose
More than 30 people end up in the hospital
After taking a mysterious train of what sometimes called
Synthetic marijuana
But it is totally not like marijuana
Or like any other drug before it real
Back in the days when there was dope and it was crack
Epidemic was
Similar to this but
I've lived here for 20 plus years I've never seen disciple
Jackson drug
Ring video went viral and the Brooklyn zombie outbreak
Became national news
And these bizarre outbreaks
They keep happening
The latest outbreak of synthetic pot people are sickened on Skid Row from
And dozens of hospitalizations in Mississippi and send it least 56 people to the hospital here in Illinois
Even more than 100 overdoses in 48 hours
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Kenny Malone and I'm Alexi Horowitz Ghazi
When you watch coverage of the drug epidemic in the US you will hear the word synthetic
Over and over
Synthetic opioid synthetic cathinones and synthetic cannabinoids
Most of human history
Drugs came from plants if you wanted to get people high you had to grow things
Poppies coca plants marijuana things like LSD ecstasy meth
Chemicals synthesized in the lab instead of grown in the field
But over the last two decades the illicit drug trade has undergone a new kind of Industrial Revolution
There's been an explosion in the variety of synthetic drugs
They've gotten more potent more profitable
And you can now become a drug kingpin with just
An internet connection and email address of a chemical Factory in China
Today on the show The Story of the synthetic drug Revolution
And how it may all lead back to one well-intentioned professor
In South Carolina
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off
Off your first purchase of a website or domain
Alright this is a sprawling
A story to take us to a lot of characters
Across the world so we're going to break this into
3 chapter
Chapter one
The white girl
As in
Lab coats
First if you could just introduce yourself
Yes this is Marilyn huestis
I am a professor at Thomas Jefferson University in Philadelphia
In movies about global zombie your pathogen outbreaks
There's always a moment where somebody sees the outbreak coming
Before almost anyone else
First story about the synthetic drug epidemic
One of those moments came about 10 years ago
In Germany
Add a professional confer
The conference was the International Association
A forensic tox
Psychologist
Kia
For sure
Marilyn actually used to be the president of this organization she's kind of a big deal in the world of drug abuse research
But when Maryland showed up
The conference at
She said everyone was talking about this
Your drug outbreak
In German
People been getting high and acting
Ferry Street
They stopped at a stoplight and the light will change and change and change
And they would never go and the people are honking
Silver crashes
And they would call it
Spice
You'll hear this called a few names
Synthetic marijuana synthetic
The cannabinoids
K2 in Germany though it was spice
Andrew officials managed to get their hands on some of
When they looked at the spice and appear to be just a mixture of like dried plants
So the mystery was
What the hell
Is the stuff
Are these some new kinds of plants with never-seen-before are these plants laced with some
Is there
Charming German scientist who can help us figure this out my name is Kristen Stewart
Christian is a research pharmacist
Specializes in chemical analysis
He gets a call from a German official explaining that there has been this outbreak
Male Maltipoo
Became interested in smoking
Incense mix
It was called
And that's a spice the German government sends a sample of this spice over to Christians lab in
In Frankfurt which by the way
Apparently is very strange
Yeah it's looks like a witch's house
The Christian gets to work
Try to figure out what is in this mysterious spice blend
Injected into an hplc
Dad what you know of course gives you the UV specs which goes through the
Hplc column as we all know gets you to the gcms
SO gas chromatography, Richmond
Of course so anyway here's what he eventually figure
People were not getting high from the dried play
They were getting high
Because the dried plants
We're sprayed with a
The chemical and he was even able to figure out the name of
Jwh
O-18
Yeah jwho
182 Professor Marilyn huestis is that the German conference
I'm hearing this epic Tale
The weird symptoms the mysterious plant mix
The German chemist in a witch's house
And when it's revealed that the
The chemical these plants were sprayed with
Was called jwh
Marilyn is like
Holy crap
Those are just some random letters
Those are initials
Stands for John W Huffman
Who is an excellent medicinal chemist
I knew him personally
And he was
You know how highly respected for his work
I'm back
Hey John hello
LOL
Yeah I can hear
John W Huffman is 86 years old either retired organic chemistry professor from Clemson University
City in South Carolina and yes we know that I am Professor Hoffman
Sounds like the name of a scientist
List from a stoner movie
John W Huffman is not that
Have you ever
Taken one of your compounds
No
You say that pretty emphatically
John part of this story
Starts back in the early
Let me explain how we got
End of the synthetic cannabinoid
A few years earlier scientist to discover the thing in the body
Did they called the
Cannabinoid receptor
One thing it does get you high from pot
It's the party body that
THC interact
What does receptor seem to be connected to all sorts of other things in your body as well
Your sleep
Your appetite
Pain which meant scientist might be able to discover a new medicine
But first they needed to figure out how this receptor even works
And that sounded like a
Fun puzzles
Attack
And anyway I
Did some half-baked
Computer modeling study
Hey John I don't want to cut you off but are you aware that half-baked has marijuana connotations
Are you making a pun
No okay I just wasn't sure
I wasn't aware there's a there's a movie called half
It's very funny
I'll have to look it up John shop was to synthesize brand new chemicals that might trigger this resep
And then those compounds got tested on mice and rat brain
So John start synthesizing them
And for record-keeping
P names each new compound in his research
Using
His initials and then a number
So jwho one
Kwh
O2 eventually he makes
Jwh
It's simply a
Light yellow goo
It was the 18th
Compounded resynthesized
Then that this series and
We set it off and it was
Pretty potent never thought anything of it
John and his colleagues eventually created and tested over 300 brand new comp
Jwh o-18 was literally one of hundreds
I forgot about
Until about 15 years later
What to get to eat
Polly mail was from a
Bloggers in Germany
And
He said that
Fayette discovered that one of our compounds had been found in a drug called spice
John was pretty sure he knew how his initials wound up on some drugs in some German
When John and his colleagues created those 300 some synthetic cannabinoids
They did what scientists are supposed to do
They publish their findings
They explained which of these compounds triggered the cannabinoid
Receptor what kinds of effects got triggered
And they also included directions
How to wrap a
John was almost certain that some enterprising chemist head look at his paper
Notice that jwho 18 was one of the most potent
Compound
And then
Follow the directions
How to make it again
The compounds are actually
Not difficult
We talkin like Easy Bake Oven children's toy easy to make
Yeah almost
You see that somewhere
Your initials
And that number
And like what do you think
I thought that this
Probably that was probably inevitable that somebody was going to use it to get high
Authorities think that the German version of John's compound was manufactured
Somewhere in China which makes sense
That's because
Over the last few decades
The US has outsourced
The ton of pharmaceutical Manufacturing
To China
That's how to build a
The capacity of
Chemical laboratories
To produce
Any kind of
Including
One ripped from a science teacher
What we don't know is exactly who did it
What lab it came from or precisely when it happened
But it's hard to overstate
What this man
For the Global Drug
It was one of the first signs that an industrial revolution had
Because think about how hard it used to be to get people high by messing with the cannabinoids
You needed marijuana plants needed space
Grow them sunlight to grow them
Needed people to do it
I need a Time
Hands of time
And after all of that
This giant plant would produce
A little bit of stuff
That would get you stoned
Jwh o-18 had only been tested on Mouse in
Rat brains but
It seemed to do something
People's brains
And more importantly
It was way more efficient
Produce and distribute the marijuana
German officials Outlaw jwho 18 the months after was identified
But it didn't matter
Chemist just tweet their formulas
And stayed one step ahead of the law
Which brings us to chapter 2
The legal grave
Subtitle
Better call Kurtz
At kurzman Grant law office
Your rights as a commercial for attorney Mark
Kurtzmann and this
Is attorney Mark
I
Received the call
From a client
He called me and asked me what I knew about K2
And I asked him why he was asking me about a mountain
In the Himalayas
Back in 2008 Martin know anything about spice
K2 but
He was better prepared than almost anyone
To navigate the legal grey area around
Represented the owners of so-called head shop
Places that sell bongs and rolling papers and other things that
Could be used to smoke marijuana
But back when marijuana was illegal in most States
A big part of Mark's job was to make sure his clients didn't say they were selling weed paraphernalia
You have to instruct them on how to speak with their
Customers
Because they cannot be
Offering things for use with illegal substances
So it's it's a
It's a scripting
Game
Quite frankly
Where everybody knows everybody else is talking about
In 2008
Headshots Worthy
Perfect place
To start selling spice
It's a marks client start calling him
Batman saying hey Mark
There's a new product
On the market
We can get it on the internet from China
We may or may not already be selling it
Is that alright
Marcus like let me look into this
And what he discovered was that many synthetic cannabinoids
At that point
We're not explicitly banned on a federal level
There was this one law Mark was
Primarily worried
The federal analog
Which essentially said
You can't knowingly sell something
It does the same thing
As an outlet stops
Since the Mark was pretty sure
She could get around that
So Mark calls as clients back and tells them
I think you can sell this
But
Here are some very important point
Number one
Please just be a responsible
Don't sell this to people underage
18 or if I don't know you think they're going to smoke it
And then get behind the wheel of a
Number two
You cannot Market this as a
A drug
The packages need to say not for human consumption
And your employees they need to stick to a tight skirt
Will you play the cashier for me
At at a store
So I walk should I heard about it
I'm pretty naive I'm saying
Is this the
The spice that my friends have been talking about is this is the right stuff
And you would be able to say what
I have no idea what your friends are speaking of
They told me there's this thing that's like a little bit like pot and I can
I don't like gas smoke it or snort it or something
Not to my knowledge
And if that's something that you want to get you can't buy anything here
Please leave
Okay so that would be a bad way for me to go to one of your stores that are complying if you if you wanted to
Death
W Broadway
But four more Savvy customers who didn't ask a lot of questions
They can walk into a head shop by a packet of synthetic cannabinoids and walk out the door
I just want to just head shops you may remember this weird. Of time
Where you would walk into a bodega or a gas station
And they were all of these
Bright shiny package
Labeled is like incense
What are potpourri
I personally speaking I had no idea what any other way
Sue Perkins
But what it was
Was a drug Market in
In plain sight
Notably drug enforcement officials were not aware of this
Problem many states
We're trying to ban particular strains of
Synthetic cannabinoids
As they popped up butt
Made made the problem worse
Because the chemist
Making these
We just change their recipe
One expert told us it was like a hydras
You stop one strain three or four new ones my pop up to take its place
It's not what it started as spice in Germany eventually turned into
Dozens of different products
With different strains of chemicals
Different fancy packages
Sporting
Ridiculous branding
Krypton for one
Mr. happy there was banana cream nuke
I can't tell if that sounds
Delicious and days
The exploding synthetic cannabinoid Market was
Quite profitable for marks
All of a sudden
Significance
They would buy something for
Pennies and they would sell it $2
I mean that's a thousand percent markup
The clients who previously have been making
Five six seven hundred thousand dollars yearly making
4 5 6 7
Did you ever try the product
No
Were you worried about
The
Chemical impacts of it
I don't take unknown substances into my body
I think that's incredibly risky
End
Very stupid thing to do
But you're okay with other people doing it
I'm okay with people making their own decisions
About what they do with their own bodies
So long as they are not doing it in a way
That is going to be directly harmful to other
Word got out that Mark was a guy who could help you sell this stuff
Legally he did insist that his clients got their chemicals tested
To make sure that there weren't obvious poisons or banned chemicals
He ended up with around 50
Clients from Pet Shop owners to wholesalers
Importing from China
And for a while it became his entire business
This period of time
Is one of the big reasons the synthetic drug Market got so big from the Des Moines
For a few years customers could buy legal substances
Cheap
Potent
And would not show up
On standard drug
But eventually marks part of the spies party started to wind down around
It's a little complicated but Mark lost a legal Challenge and felt like he couldn't tell his clients in good faith
But they could still sell this stuff legally
And then in 2012
President Obama signed a synthetic drug abuse prevention Act
Which explicitly band
A broadly
Absent that accept
And so
Anybody who wanted to follow the law
New
At that point
You may not like it maybe
It's unfair
Now your recourse is Go lobby
Congress because you can't
Say anymore
I can do it because I don't understand it because stats
Ben lost
So basically what you're saying is
Once the writing was on the wall like
I guess in this case
It literally wants to Federal legislation was
Was dry
You were just like
I have no more
If you want me
To help you do this I'm not going to do it
There's no tightrope to walk anymore
It is all cut and dry
And I'm gone
Yep
So it's all fixed it no more spice
No problem
Yeah sure
Okay so we had the white coats
We had to leave a gray area
And after the break
The spice world turns into a full-fledged
Black Market
Can we visit a lab of scientists
Trying to
Predict the
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimum
That can be open from anywhere
Are in 5 min
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Chapter 3
The black
You will recall the Brooklyn zombie
This is crazy like the Romulan over here just happened
Years after jwh
Hoat
Was first identified on the streets of
Which means chemist
Have been tweaking and morphing their formulas
48 years
So whatever caused this outbreak was many generations removed from what John Huffman have created in his lab
And
Many times more potent
Go tell your kids please tell your family
Okay to stay off of that man
Topman
Police knew the Brooklyn zombies had taken some form of
K2 or synthetic
Cannabinoid they're able to figure out that it was being sold under the name
AK-47 24 Karat
They had no clue what chemicals were actually in this product
So they didn't know how to tell if other people were overdosing on the same
Drug they didn't know how best to treat those people
And if I happened to catch the person putting it out on the street
You can't successfully prosecute without knowing what
Chemical is
And so authorities got a hold of some of this
AK-47
24-karat gold stuff
I also got some
Some blood and urine samples from
Taking it
And they sent all of this off to a special lab
In San Francisco
Did you ever see the Facebook live of that outbreak I did actually medicinal chemist Sam Bannister
With a drug science research group based out of a Lab at UC Santa
San Francisco
The group has kind of a long name
It's called psychoactive surveillance Consortium and Analysis Network
They call it
P scan for short
P-scan
Intentional
Like like checking people's urine
Anyway they were the group that was asked to figure out what the Brooklyn zombies
We were able to identify
That a particular compound was responsible this drug called amb-fubinaca
Identify the number of days
From disclosing a lot of related molecules Pfizer pharmaceutical
Just like jwh o18 amb fubinaca appears to be a recipe
Straight from the literature
Instead of an academic Journal this one came from patent
Over 500 strains
Five new synthetic compounds have been identified on the
Some word invented by enterprising blackmark
Chemist but
A lot of those dreams seem to still get poached
From legitimate scientific Outlet
And this Sam Bannister says is a very troubling problem
Science is built on publishing experiments in a way that can be replicated
Major trying to do legitimate Research into the possibilities or the
The dangers of synthetic cannabinoids
You run the risk of making things worse
Case in point
A synthetic drug that was found
In Europe not so long ago
I was contacted by
The head of the Finnish police because it actually intercepted
I'm at the Border level in Finland
Andre from Hong Kong
1kg of sdb oo6
1 kg
12 sdb as in Sam D Bannister
At least one compound Sam had made for legitimate purposes seem to have been poached from an academic Journal
And then manufactured is a brand new
And he was shocked because it happened super fast
That was detected approximately six months after that article went online
It's a really pretty short short turnaround for his part when Sam discovers a new compound
And he's very intentionally does not publish it right
And this lab Sam works with is taking a radical approach to the synthetic
They have this one project that is known as
The prophetic
Prophetic as in
Trying to predict the
What building
A library of the drugs that will probably emerge on the Straits
In the next few years
So you're like searching for that street drugs of the future
I think that's probably exactly it salmon or trying to invent new synthetic drugs
Before the qemists on the black market
That way when a new drug does hit the streets
At least the prophetic Library can help officials identify what people have taken and maybe treat us
Officials can also use that
Information to Outlaw new compounds as they
But Sam says
The law is not going to change
The economic
Pics of the synthetic
It is just so profitable
To make and sell these drugs
For example Sam says
Look at amb-fubinaca
The drug from the Brooklyn zombie
I am Baker Binaca could be obtained from China
At about three and a half thousand US dollars for 1 kg of material
And we know that that's sort of at least
Somewhere between
Mental calculation
Somewhere between probably 500000 and a million dices
A dose that Sam says would sell for about a dollar app
Meaning
If you can get just three and a half thousand dollars worth of this product
In the country
You could sell it
For more than 500,000
Like I think it's just
Truly ruthless profiteering I mean there is money to be made on an enormous scale and I think that's really
Obviously there's no concern for the people are actually using these drugs
Or you wouldn't find people selling
Fentanyl analogues that site potent fentanyl as in the synthetic opioid
And it's followed pretty much the same path as
Synthetic cannabinoids
Fentanyl started out as a legitimate medicine
But black market chemists figured out how to make it
Then figured out how to make
Even more potent
And now
It's killing tens of thousands
It's part of the same synthetic drug Revolution
Ushered in by JW HOA
It's now been nearly 30 years since John Hoffman created jwa
Pho 88
And he told us For Better or Worse people now associate him with synthetic cannabinoid
He's gotten a strange array of emails
Sometimes people write and ask him for advice on how to cook their own synthetic
But sometimes these emails are from parents
In Grand Prairie
They say
These drugs are causing psychosis
In my kids
Immigrant
And they blame John
You know you've ruined my life you ruined my
Kid's life etc etc that kind of thing
That's not a very fun
Email
To get
No they're not but they're not enjoyable
And I feel sorry for them
But it is my fault
John says what else was he supposed to do
Scientists publish their science
How could he have anticipated that one compound from his research
What help jump-start
The global synthetic
Drug Revolution
The drug epidemic is a story
Much larger than 1/2
85 minutes
We would love to hear your ideas about how to cover it
You can get in touch with us
Planet Money at NPR.
Today's episode was produced by Sally Helm and Nick fountain
Are supervising producer is Alex goldmark
Our stories are edited by Bryant
I'm Alexi Horowitz Ghazi and I'm Kenny Malone
Extra lesson