Kipling money we all have our pet obsession
Mine
Is cartel
I will admit it I am fascinated by
Cartel
When businesses get together and decide
Not to
Decide that they are too powerful
And two special for the law of supply and demand
Like OPEC does for oil
And what I love about cartel
Is it they are set up
Because of greed
I mean who wouldn't love to charge more for your product
But then someone always gets to go
And starts to cheat
They stab each other in the back
Amy
Those thinking about this the life and death of cartels
When I heard a story from my friend
He works with his group called Innovations for poverty action
You could call it nurse Without Borders
Nurse Without Borders it's a nonprofit that helps get Economist to help out with problems in pork
And just was telling me about this one particular cartel
The his group had encountered in Senegal
The poop cartel
Yahoo is this poop cartel that you speak
So you've seen in the Way porta potties get serviced
I'm here when your Porta-Potty is full you've probably seen the trucks that come by with a tanker truck with a big fat
Here with a big hug and it's the same thing
I like a big porta potty
And
Tickets for, you need to get it cleaned out
But it look like
These trucks were
Perhaps
Fixing their prices they look like their prices were
Permanently High
Instead of maybe competitive
Parker that you'd expect
And obviously that put it out of the reach of a lot of people who needed it
Move over OPEC
Cuz there's price-fixing in Senegalese poop
Innovation for poverty action sent a ragtag
A team of Economist to Senegal
Each with their own skills each with a single mission
Could you create
A more efficient market
By turning the poop cartel Truckers
Against each other a poop War
This
This I have to see
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I Am Adam John and I almost journalist
And I am 35
And I'm Robert Smith
And forgiving ages I am 50 years old
Old man
50 years old
Adam is going to act as our translator and guide you give us the grand tour of the outhouses
Employment of Dakar Senegal
Jokes aside definition is
A serious business here in the car if you cannot get rid of the poop and it clean efficient way
Then you are waiting in it during rainy season
Switch industry
But you can't get rid of the poop without going through this big greedy cartel today on the show Astoria
Economic Jiu-Jitsu what happens when a group of Economist try to bring back supply and demand
The number one rule of economics and apply it to number two
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobiledit
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR
To save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
No matter where you live
In the states
Whether you are old
Are young or poor Rich
One day
You don't know when
You're going to go to the bathroom
Flush the toilet
And it won't go down
In Dakar Senegal when this happens
You have a major problem
Because a large percentage of the house is here use septic
Big concrete line pits Outback
Contain all the sewage
And when your toilet starts to overflow into car
It means you're pitiful
And you need someone to remove
Months worth of crap
You need a guide
Until you have to come
Kia
Autumn apartments in the parking lot behind the Cars
National Football State
It was built for soccer fan
But instead of bunch of very dirty
Unwanted businesses
Have set up permanent shop here
Oldest face has been invaded But it belongs
Today
Is the domain of the stadium
IC
People dumping garbage there's car part looks like taxi cabs are getting fixed over here
In the moment
Horse-drawn cart
Calling metal Chuck
Went over in the corner
Daddy pig
Tanker trucks with tubes on them these
Are the
In Senegal they call them monkey dishes
Toilet suck
These trucks are the single best way to deal with sewage here in Senegal
Because they're quick they're relatively clean
And they bring sewage to a treatment plant
Standing out in front of each truck is a smiling tracker
Waiting for
Very desperate customers
To come in
Hello my name is
Chucky
Chucky owns to
Of these toilets
He's dressed in this Immaculate right
Green shirt
Maybe because of their particular business
I found practice to be very fastidious about their periods
There are a bunch of these truckers standing around the parking lot in front of their big vacchi
They mostly work for themselves and they often sit here
All day long
Without a custom
That work
So in economic terms
A large Supply
Trucks
Not that much to man
She would think o
As a customer I can walk around and negotiate the best price
But that is not how the system
Set up
They're all members of an association
And they want to collectively charge
As much money as they can
Chucky says you cannot blame them they have to drive
All over this huge City
Ndk
Big and dirty and obvious
They get stopped by the
Applejack America
We will talk about bribes they
Glass for bride
Music
We cannot escape from the
What makes
This truck is a cartel is it they've agreed to not actively compete with each other
If a customer comes in and one of these truckers gives them a price
Then the customer is not allowed to go from driver to driver
To get a lower price
Particularly
Community Management
Yahoo groups
United
Pizza it's like a Brotherhood
A truck driver
OK Google United and they agree on
Australia
Usually 42
$60 depending on the size of the pit
There's not some internet site you can check to see whether you're getting a good deal or not
Sure there are other parking lot so I just went around the city and you can spend
Half the day trudging from
One to another
But they may offer you the same high price
Truckers perspective
They may lose a bunch of customers.
They may sit idle
But as long as they keep the prices high they make more profit
This would just be up financially
Except for a lot of people in Dakar $50
Can be a month weight
They literally
Cannot pay for it
And so the cartel prices force them to turn
To another salon
It is illegal and it's terrible for the environment but it's extremely common around here
You can hire
Some poor sap
To empty your septic tank by hand
Adam and I went to search for one of these guys
We left the page street with the car and went to one of the small neighbor
There's dirt lined alleyways
It gets narrower
And narrower as you walk
Houses are mostly unfinished
Cinder blocks
We didn't know if we'd be able to find someone
Who would actually admit to being an illegal pit emptier
But I don't know I had a brilliant idea
Starts to ask groups of teenage boys
Hannah Montana
I know exactly who you're looking for any lupus over to this Courtyard
They don't miss any
The best reporters
And the best guys the best pictures
And there
Sitting in the courtyard shade is a man without shoes
Or shirt
With a shovel by aside
It's like he was waiting for us
And he's so excited
Try out his English
Did he sort of
Interviews himself
What I what's your name
My name Jeff
Is my name is Gigi
What do you live
I live in Senegal
Jimmy is the most outgoing person I met in Seneca
Maybe
The most outgoing person I've ever
He get the buckets to sit on here for something to drink
Unexplained
The his job has a very specific name
IMO bypass
IBuyPower
Bypass
What was that mean I mean what is it
Literally mean by pal
Bike helmets
The father of the Shadow because by means
Father
Pell is travel
So by pal
The father of the Shamu
You you're the father of the shovel
This is your son
Father shovel
Ball is a time-honored job inside
If he says he'll get a knock on his door often
In the middle of the night
Someone's toilet
Is overflowing there
Desperate
And he grabs his pockets
Probably the ones
We're sitting on and his shovel
And he heads out into the night
Hippie stop showing me right in his own Courtyard how he does it
Is Jacque how he sort of
Hooks around to find the corners of the concrete
What up
Demonstrates how he lowers a bucket down with a rope
Straight months with a waste out of the pit
Polka dot one bucket at a time
Where do you put the X
Super elixir
Appendages
Yeah this is the problem
Father shovel take this bucket
Build
With PCs
And urine
And God knows what else
And he takes them
Outside the house
He'll be a very big hole in the street
Essentially
And he will dump bucket
After bucket of sewage
Into that hole
In
The street
Nobody here likes
The Neighbors
The oldest house on beerus the government tries to crack down on it
Expected to be to be
Somewhat defensive
About his job but he says listen
Keno
He knows
If this can make the
People sick in the Navy
So Sofitel
Ouija
Batman group
I think you're right because it can cause some diseases in fact
Young truth and the plane on the ground sometimes they can use this song
Play with it and something like it
In which
You can cause a lot of DVDs to the children
So uneven
All Souls who are working with this
If a danger for us
But what can you do
Someone has to clean out the pit is full
A lot of his neighbors can't afford the truck the toilet truck
Could you be charges half the price
Now
There have been public service campaigns to stop further
Sanitation nonprofit to come into the country and trade
Educate whole neighborhood
Switch inspectors prowl the back alleys looking for these holes giving up tickets
But nothing seemed to work
The people I talked to in the neighborhood said
Of course we would rather use
A truck
We just needed to be a little cheaper
And frankly
Easier to get in touch
So
How do you fight
Economic Lodge
Artificially high prices
And high transaction
The Senegalese government thought
All right
We're gonna have to ask in a car
My name is Molly Lipscomb I'm an associate professor at the University of Virginia
Molly had become interested in West Africa as a p
Peace Corps ball
She specializes in environmental issues
In developing country
Theories about what
Might work
She assembled a team along with IPA Innovations for poverty action
And she translated all of this poop talk
Into economics
So there's definitely a market power issue and that this issue is compounded in terms of the f
Efficiency consequences by the externalities that yours
Sanitation issues impose on your neighborhood
Google Translate
When poop truck
Cost too much
Then crap
Flo's in the streets
1 classic way to deal with a market power imbalance is
Even the playing field
And Molly first thought
Maybe we can get neighbors to band together
Maybe she and the government could help people get a better price from the toilets
But when they showed up at the parking lots to make deals
The truckers
Truckers of course they thought hey
American Economist with a government contract
We can charge
Even
Mormon
The faces of people we're talking about when we started where in the $60 produce Legend range
Yeah so that's what we thought
So you start to think about ways in which you could get the service
Exactly
So how do you break a cartel
You could encourage other competitors to come into the market
Princess
Is a lot less powerful now that the
The US produces too much oil
What is the Carly giant toilet suckers
Are pretty expensive and it's hard to set up shop on your own
Outsiders did not want to take on this cartel
I know there's going to be more competition
Do they were going to have to get the eggs
Existing driver
To compete against each other
There was
One way
The drivers all hits cell phone
These basic old fashioned dumb phones
I could just get texts
And she starts to think what if you could somehow get around this Brotherhood problem
The cartel
And directly connect customers with individual Truckers
Via
The self
Using your cell phone
To go directly
To a driver
It sounds familiar
Do you hate it
When people call this
Uber for poop
I know I know I know you know Uber is a very well functioning market and I think they've done great things
Transportation so if this is a preferred poop that's great
Small problems using that metaphor is at the time there was no Uber in Dakar Senegal
Defect most people didn't really use their phones to shop for any kind of sir
They're going to build a whole new system for getting desperate customers in touch with poop driver
And then they're going to teach everyone how to use it
One of the members of Molly's team
Sanderling starting to go out
Please parking lot
And to meet with the drivers
Show them what it would look like
To bid for jobs
Using text message
The training was
Amazing we had I can for different Group Training
Where we invited the designated Truckers
And we walk them through how the bidding process would go what was the main question for
Why
Why make the change
Yeah because at this point like
Things are going pretty well for them they're in demand they set their own prices
I told them
Imagine all the people who are sitting at home
With their pets overflowing
These are people who are not going to come to your garages
Even though the potential client
We want to help
Get access to these clients who have never visited you
It may never visit you
If we don't help them understand
Who you are what your work is and if there's an easier way to get your service
The researchers were super transparent with the drivers
They said you may not be able to charge as much
But think of all the new business
Meanwhile another member of the
The team Josh Jorge Ben
He was helping set up a brand new call center
Downtown Dakar
There's a window on the left side
Are the single desk on the right
And there's one of our operators sitting there with a little headset plugged into a cell phone on TV the government
Circle Rodney's animated ads
The phone number
There was a sort of graphic of somebody holding their nose and then
A stick drawing of Father shovel with a big red X through it and
And for some reason a rainbow colored toilets
What's my phone
Supplements
Know somebody called in the operator would answer something that then who did he know he's going to ask you questions about your location
And your pip was up early, with everything
The operator would send out a short text message to 10 or 15 randomly select
Truckers
It would say something like medium pit
Making a good ass neighborhood and truckers had an hour to send back a text
With their best bit
Seduction lowest price twins
The trucker's could have just stuck with their cartel with the Brotherhood
They could have compared bids on their phones and all sent in a high price
But that's not what happened
CERN yearling with hanging out with the
The trucker's in the parking lot
And she could see cracks forming the cartel right before her eyes
Quit see someone
This phone would vibrate
A trucker and he would just
Kind of step to the signs a hold on you guys I got to take this
And the heat go behind a truck
And we were told that they were bidding
Sometimes
JustFab
Other truckers didn't know that you had received a bid
You say oh you know my cousin texted me or you'd say something to walk away and then respond to the bid
Back at the call center Josh deutschmann could see
A market
Being bored
There were a couple guys that figured it out right away
They figured out
Okay here's the price that I think can win in this neighborhood
Started winning a lot of jobs
And then over time you started to see these
More and more truckers that
Maybe initially they would send bids but they were totally
Outlandish they were never going to win
But then they would start seeing okay this is the price that wins in this neighborhood maybe I can undercut battle
A little bit next time
And just watching start of the
The real-time process of
Competition
Unfolding over the space of weeks and months was was really really exciting
Because remember the price is going down
And
More truckers are participating
Even turkey the truck owner I talk to about the power of the Brotherhood
And the need for high prices
He got into the auction
He bragged to me about his strategy for winning
Events near me
DaVinci me
Usually what I do is I wait until there are only 10 minutes left
10 minutes if no one
I think during the offer
Then I propose a price and then immediately I go
So that I have this
You said earlier
That
The truckers were United
Did the text messages to the auction
Make you less United because you were
Competing with each other for price
Santander
Even though we used to be United
But now it's a competition and you need to
Two Tylenol together
How to get something in your business
The Economist ran the call center as an experiment for a couple of
Tweaking the system every once in awhile
Is it better to have truckers just give their best.
Or have them give multiple bids over the hour
How many is a perfect number of truckers in an auction in their competition
You don't want so many that feels hope
You never win
Eventually Molly ran
The numbers
Did the phone auction
Make a debt
In the thing that matter
Can you make a dent in prices
The Excel Center brought down prices by about 7% versus the price that a given household would have
Paid
In the market
7% how should I feel about that seems like a small lamp
Does it
I don't know I guess I don't know
Definitely like 7% off my Plumbing Service
Remember that the 7% is average to some neighborhoods are getting you know 12 /
Percent or 11%
And that number does not include
The transaction cost
People using the phone auction we're saving 1/2 days worth of travel and negotiating in that big Stadium parking lot
Molly said the key thing is that even a small reduction in price
Can change Behavior
Remember what people that car would really prefer to use
Trucks anyway
But they can't afford it
Even to be
The father shovel I talked to
Said he would call a poop truck
For his
If you just had more money
Molly still working on the numbers but she figures it up to 20% of people
May switch
From shovel to truck
If they can wrap up this project across the city
And get prices down
Big question now
Is what's going to happen
The system
The experiment is officially over the researchers have gone home
The government of Senegal ran the call center for a while
And now they're moving it over to a private company that will
Probably figure out a way to take a little cut of the business
For themselves
But you need to take them lesson is it the poop cartel
Will never
Be the same
The experiment showed that
Cartels have
A weakness
They can be exploited
Once you see your fellow truckers stepping outside undercut you in a text message
You are more likely to undercut him next time
It is brutal
But you know the old saying
Competition topic
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online
And presents and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layouts along with features including e-commerce functionality
And mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial and when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Do you have a great story about Economist riding to the rescue drop us a line
Planet Money at NPR. Org
We post a link to every episode on Facebook by the way you can go there leave a comment on the post
Mix it up with the other Planet Money listeners
One personal notify me you'll be hearing a bit less of my voice on the 5K
Cast over the next year I'm going to be on a night badgett Fellowship to Columbia University and their business and turn
Journalism schools
You should stay in touch on Instagram and Twitter I'm at Radio Smith are shows produced by Sally Helm and Taylor Haney
Nitrostat is our editor Alex goldmark is our senior producer Robert Smith thanks for listening
Wow looking opening the Giant
You get back a little bit
Smell like human waste that smells like
Quick sharp sort of like bad milk
Call me later