Just a quick note
There is a curse word in
Today Show
One thing that I think is genuinely interested
About economic inequality is that it's kind of like a
Puzzle
Does all of these contributing fact
There's history and globalization and
Technology
Racism
Sexism all of these ones are there
But the thing that I hate about covering inequality is that it very quickly turns into a political fight
Conservatives have one solution liberals have another
Awesome groups don't even think inequality is such a bad thing
And I just want a couple months ago my mind was
Blown when I heard that there would be
These two guys
From very different ends of the political Spectrum who were working on the problem of inequality
Together
The first is brincolin
Vice president and director of the open Society project at the niskanen center
Center in Washington DC
What is anise candy
It's a libertarian-leaning think tank
I spent a lot of time covering the libertarian
And here's what they'll generally tell you
Governments to Big there too many regulations
We should let the market
Flourish on its own and that
Takes care of most problems in the world surprise me so much
The brink is working with this guy
I describe myself as
Is a liberal that is Steve Tellez he's a professor of political science at Johns Hopkins
He's also a fellow at the niskanen said
Center and by liberal he means he thinks
Government can play a role in solving problem
So we have a little.
And we have a liberal and together
You are
Liberal.
Do that together with at 3
Do it together
Together you are
Libertarian hello and welcome to Planet Money on new album
That word is not going to take off a Robert Smith
Travel show two guys from different sides of the
The political Spectrum ask
What is causing inequality
And it come up with an answer
Did strangely they both agree on
The economy is rigged
And they think they know how it's being rigged
And he's working it
Support for this podcast
Cast in the following message come from the Annie E Casey
Sea Foundation
Developing Solutions
It support strong families and community
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is
Is available at aecf
. org
They will interview these two very different
Gentleman at the same time and since this is Radio we want you to be able
How to tell them apart
Okay so Steve
Steve is the liberal
With the kind of voice that might be
Appreciated
Steve I think you sound a little bit like Tom
The 4000
I'm somebody
We really
Yes good ok good so I was dead on my head
Now
II
The libertarian
Brink you sound like an old timey newscast
4 News
You're hired
Beast you guys to Liberal Therrien Smet about a decade ago
Springfield an article for the new Republic about how liberals and Libertarians had more in common than they thought
And Steve had just moved to Washington DC and he was trying to make
Brinks still remembers the first time they
Steve
Call me up a month or two after that article came out and said hey I think I'm a liberal Therrien
I have a
Tennessee be pushy
And to call people when I read things I like them and I send them notes and say hey that's great
We should get together we get together
Alfred coffee
The immediate they started hanging out in wash
Can Emily realize that they both saw the world the same way
Stable sort of hopeful
And there was sort of skipped
Optical and they're both obsessed with these
Two big problems in the US
Economy
The first is how slowly the economic pie
Is growing slow economic
And the second is
How the pie is divided
Some people have very big slices some people have little sliver
Inequality
So bring it to Beaver looking at these two problem
And we should say that neither of them is an economist by training
Steve is a political scientist and Brink is a recovering lawyer
But they say in this case that's
Surplus
Economist are
At least somewhat hamstrung by the fan
That day
Hampton start out at least in in
Canterbury economics
With a fairly simplified model of the economy a model of perfect
Competition
And then they trying to
Explain things as deviations from that
Simplified model of perf
The competition
Perfect
Competition
Where all the firms are fighting on a Level Playing Field to get
Consumers better
Cheaper products in the most efficient way
I dream of at night
And industries are constantly innovating and workers are finding new and better jobs
Moving up the ladder
Sounds good
But is that how our economy is actually working right now
Now with perfect competition release very good company
The guy say no
Yes some people are doing really well in the
A lot of others aren't
Something is going wrong with comp
Cricket Steve they have this nerdy French
Where they talk about all of this all the time
And he started holding on something that
Liberals and Libertarians
Generally do not agree
Which is regulation
Why do we have regulation
So you have economic activity and it causes some potential harm to workers or to consumers or to the
The environment and therefore you need rules to align that Industries interests with the public
And so the purpose then of Regulation
Is to do that
Is to make sure
That the companies in that industry are following the rules in the rules are structured so that the public benefits
To help consumers
The brink and Steve say if you look around the economy there are a lot of place
This is where regulations
Are helping businesses and industries
And particular profession
Not all consumed
This is the moment
Where we address the great North Carolinian teeth whitening scandal
Up 2000
It started
With the den
Dentistry is a practice that is highly regulated in North Carolina and pretty much everywhere else
If you want to be a dentist you have to have
Schooling and Eliza
And you don't
Behind
Licensing dentist all the way these are people who work with drills
They come at your face
With the drills
So make them get lice
Yeah you want to see something
Framed on the wall before they start to
Give you drugs and take out parts of your mouth that makes sense
But the issue is what you have a corner on the
Food market
You have this desire disorder
Ctrl Alt
Related activity
So when the technology came about dentist started to offer teeth whitening
You know why not
The thing is
Teeth whitening is a fairly simple process
It doesn't require a lot of years of
School
And people in North Carolina had started opening up these little
Teeth whitening kiosk
Good malls
Salons
They charge less than a license dentist
And
Dentist didn't like that
Competition and so the
Licensing board for dentistry in North Carolina issued cease-and-desist orders to teeth whitening clinics Bellingham
Stop the unauthorized practice
Dentistry teeth whitening revolutionaries are cute
Winter practicing Dentistry
We take little plastic trays we pour some liquid in there and then
Place them against your
I mean it's more like
Give me a pedicure
For the
Eminem normal free market we can trust consumers to decide if they wanted to go to a mall to get their teeth
Where to go to the dentist office
But in this case regulators
Stepped in and they said no we are making the decision
For you
You know I picture dentist
In a castle
A big banquet table together
Oxide canisters
Fun
Tapestries of incisors on the wall
And outside you have to pee
Teeth whiteners trying to get in
But there is a moat
And the smoke is regulation
Blocking away
You need a license to come in
Brink and Steve start
To see this everywhere
In so many parts of the economy
Business and Regulation are not at odds
It's not that Regulators are just stepping into stop industry from dumping toxins into the ocean
In what cases industry actually loves regulation
Because it's figured out how to make Regulatory Agencies and the government work
For it
This is called
Regulatory
Regulatory capture is the process by which narrow industries use
Government in order to entrench themselves in
Notice that Steve said narrow industry
She's not saying all regulation is bad
But some industry regulation is
Is being manipulated
And that's hurting the economy
Those teeth whiteners had to close up shop that right there that's job loss
The dentist
To shut them down they were doing okay
Now they're doing even better
And it's a small example of how you get growing inequality
Brink and Steve decided to write a book together about all of this it's called the captured economy came out a couple months
And it's about regulatory capture
The theory of regulatory capture was developed largely by an economist named George Stigler in the early 70s
But this idea goes back along
In bring conceived book they have this
Quote that I love from Adam Smith
Now that's an Adam Smith
Play by Tom
People of the same trade seldom meet
Even for merriment and diversion
But the conversation ends in a
Conspiracy against the public
Or in some contrivance
Foods to raise price
I don't know why but that quote makes me laugh and I think maybe it's a conspiracy part but Adam Smith was not joke
Was he
You know who else wasn't joking
The teeth whitener
Years of North Carolina has conspiracy against them
And the Federal Trade Commission agree with him
They sued North Carolina Dental
It went all the way to the Supreme Court
And the outcome
Bright Smiles all around
This time The Outsiders
The teeth whiteners one
Bringing Steve this is a good example of a son rigging the economy a lid
But in other states the same fight dentist versus teeth whiteners is playing out
And it's also playing out in a lot of Industries I mean you think about it
There are taxi boards taxi regulators
Versus
Uber and Lyft
Optometry Regulators are fighting on behalf of
Optometrists against online eye exam
End hair braiders we did a whole episode about this
Hair braiders are fighting to be able to braid hair
Without State Licensing boards shutting them down
It seems like wherever there's a
Profession where someone is put time
An effort into building their business
They're also fighting to keep
Keep the doors to the
Profession
Close Dentistry doctors
Lawyers
Limit the number of entrance
Limit the amount of copper
Petition
That they're going to have which
I understand
You already have a business
You think
You're good at it
Your customers like you
I want more peep
Yeah the problem is The Regulators
The referees are not supposed to be taking
Decide
And when they do take a side sometimes it leads
Stewby's really warped outcome
Is there a Hall of Fame
Hall of Fame for regulatory capture
Right up front would be a
Talking
Statue
In the shape
Of a giant mouse
Everybody hates me
Yeah we're going to get sued for playing
We might get sued
Because of regulatory capture
So it's semi-serious
But observers joke that
Development of copyright law
The past half-century
We can be explained by making sure that Mickey Mouse never enters
Where's the public domain
I mean copyright law this is not a small thing
The Story Goes
Walt Disney created Mickey Mouse in 90
Teen 28 and under the copyright law of
But I'm here to copyright on Mickey
That was extended a little bit when copyright law changed in
In 76
So then we get to the late 1990
And just a couple years before the copyright on Mickey Mouse is about to expire
And the Disney Corporation seems to realize what is it
Steak so the open up an office in washing
The higher Ubuntu lappe
I may go to Congress
And they get copyright law change
To extend the copyright on
Not to mention Donald Duck
Pluto dog
This protected Disney's profit
But not just there to change the law
Allowed all of these other creative Industries
To keep extracting more profits off of their own copyrighted stuff
So huge
Record company movie industry
Fortunes are much larger than they would be
In a senior copyright regime they could hold on to them for a few years
And then they would have to face competition
Competition you know the thing that keeps the economy going and growing
So they're doing a direct line between
Mickey Mouse and copyright law and this problem within a koala
Everybody last couple decades
Deceased going to sue you
Person Wiki
Steven brinker eigen missing
Mickey and the dentist and lawyers the more they protect their share
The Less groceries the less Mobility
I want to learn about regulatory capture
Are you start to
See it everywhere
Wherever you see a power imbalance in society you could ask yourself
Who are the dentists
And who are the teeth white
And is there some in French power is there some regulator that is tilting the balance in favor of one
Bracket Steve talked a lot about an example
That everyone will know
And that is housing and rap
In the book they talk about the Bay Area
Sanford
1 most expensive places to live in the United
State we live in New York
And with my stories
Horrifying I'm sorry
Sorry Bae are people
But like
It's traffic
And you know the reasons that are often given
Which is a lot of new
Tech money rents are rising higher and higher landlord's
Can charge more and people don't want housing built in their backyards
Yeah it's the obvious problem is
In a competitive market for housing there's just
Not enough places to live
Casa de practica
Which is such a simple explanation there's just not enough
But look at it from a captured economy point of view
People who own houses in San Francisco
They're already inside the castle they have got it good
Until when there's a proposal to build new houses
And you see this
They go to the zoning board
They go to the regulators and they get the proposal shot down
What do I do
Those big cities that are now the powerhouses of our information
Economy of pulled up the drawbridges
By making it so expensive for people to
To buy housing there
And so is the result we're having this economic boom
That is throttled
Because ordinary people can't participate because I can't move to those Metro areas and live there
Wait some kid from Dayton can't move
22 Sanford
Francisco right now some kid from Dayton Camp moved
To New York
And that means if that kid is stuck in Dayton
Or Cleveland or that's right disclaimer time
I pulled those two cities out of thin air Dayton and Cleveland are
Fine Place
And we also do want to give San Francisco a hard time it
Has its housing issue New York has a lot of those
Same problem
What we're saying here is that in a country that is sort of built
On Mobility
Choice
We have set up rules in a lot of the economically dynamic
The keep the nice stuff for the people there
And make it harder
For people to come
So what you see this in the economy regulatory capture
What are you doing
Well the first thing they're arguing is that you just have to
Cenotes
Sit and notice when your benefit
When I was talking to bring
I said something very funny they said a lot of the people who read our book
Will be the people in interest
Mysteries for benefiting from regulatory
Do you ever go into your dentist
Brink
And kind of like look at him and think
Mac
Yeah yeah yeah
I don't want to try not to personalize things visit these RC
Systemic problems and
Dentists work hard they think they work hard and
They do what everybody else is trying to do when the economy is just ultimately
It's ultimately the duty of the governors
To make sure that the rules are in the public interest rather than in the narrow interests of the various clamoring claimants who come before
The funny thing is it Planet Money all we do is personalised
Bookman
I actually do think that it's useful to have
Some righteous
Personalized anger
One of the
Powers
That existing interest have is what political science
To call policy
The fact that
In general those practitioners
Have a positive image that people think oh dentists there good doctors
They help people write
Very powerful resource
Against people who are coming in and saying
Hey you're not acting up in the public interest you're just using this regulation
For your own benefit and unless we can actually mobilize some of that unless you can ding some of people's reputation
It's going to be hard to actually
Mobilize politically against
And really that's
Why they wrote
The book they wrote the book to make
All of us mad
To make us look around in our lives and say wait a minute that's regulatory capture their and they're
And there and knowing it's going on
Is part of the solution
Yeah it's better than looking back in 10 years and say there's another industry that captured its regulators
And now no one can get a foot massage
In fact I was reading the paper the other day that there is this
Hearing on Capitol Hill this week about banking
Thanks for trying to get out from under some of the restrictions put on them after the financial crisis and there was quite a robust debate
Over this but we noticed that the robots debate was mostly
Among the people who showed up who were mostly bankers
And in the end if we've learned anything from Steve and Brink in their book it's that the people who show up
Tend to be the people who with
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Message come from the Annie E Casey
The foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and community
To help ensure a brighter future for America's shield
More information is available at aecf. Org
Play shows produced by Sally how are senior producer is Alex goldmark or editor is Bryant or Stat
When you need engineering you call Isaac Gonzalez or no rush we are at Planet Money on all social media
Weekender Instagram PDF a wonderful picture of Robert Smith
Channeling The Godfather
I'm Robert Smith
Thanks for listening
You got all these people who can't
Go out and get jobs as teeth whitener
Because industry
Industry shut them now
No
Dum Dums
Guess you don't want to see a little
Rat with teeth