Support for NPR and the following message come from State Farm
When it comes to home and auto insurance
They're here through the ups and downs
Go to statefarm.com
To be connected with one of the 19000 ages
In neighborhoods
Across the Nation
State Farm
Here to help life
Go right
Quick morning there is some profanity in this episode
Hey it's Stacey Vanek Smith
Today Show originally aired in 2016
Dean it is about
CEO pay
Are we going to watch new really interesting information about CEO pay because of this rule put in place as part of the.
Frank Lott which is the big 2010 banking right
Regulation Lop it was
Financial crisis
Enrollment
Did this year
Some big companies
Had to report their pay ratios basically comparing how much money CEOs make
How much the median worker at
At the company make
And those numbers show
Surprise
Did CEOs get paid
Way more than other workers do
The New York Times calculated that an employee at Walmart making the company's median salary
Would have to work for more than a thousand years
To make as much money as Walmart CEO got in
So here's our episode looking at how we got here
Cheers the show
This is the other day
I was looking at this chart
I brought it into the studio
The chart is
Average pay for CEOs at Big us corporations over the past several deck
And I saw something really surprising
I'd always assumed you know that co-pay just goes up and up and up a kind of steady way year after year
But what this chart
Clearly shows is in fact there is this one moment I can put my finger on it here it's right in the mid 1990
Weird CEO Pago's
Banana
Right before then it's kind of engine along and then just
All of a sudden midnight
Straight up
But you don't when I say Goes Bananas I don't even mean that in like a value judgment kind of way I just mean
Whatever you think about CEO pay
Anybody would look at this chart
Point of this moment in history and say
What happens right here hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
An object today on the show that's her show what happened with video Pay right
Support also comes from NPR sponsor gamebridge the Bold way to steady growth
People often think annuities are too conservative to complex or only for retirees but annuities can
Can be a smart way to hedge Market risk and earn guaranteed returns
Game Bridge aims to change the game by offering simplified annuities in a Sleek digital experience that replace
Places fine print and phone tag
Nike with clear conditions and a direct low-fee model learn more at game Bridge. Lives NPR
Game Bridge is not available in all states
You got one week to fix the country's failing preschools
Go on rough translation of bold experiment by a country to transform its culture teaching
It works until the very people that most want the school to succeed
Start getting in the way
Rough translation
Wherever you get your podcasts
The story of this moment when co-pay started going up really fast
Among other things it's like a story of unintended
And it starts or at least we're going to start it a few years
Before things go bananas 1990
There was this economist named
Kevin Murphy
And he was looking at this and he wasn't so much concerned with how much CEOs
We're getting paid
As he was with
How they were getting paid
He thought a lot of CEOs were getting paid a lot of money
Basically just sit around
The biggest sole determinant of your compensation was
How big of company you were running
And it was a
Turned out to be just a lousy way to do business
If the CEO had a great year
They got paid
See you had a terrible year
Also got paid
Didn't really matter
Who is result Murphy says
There was a tendency for CEOs to just kind of be on autopilot
Go to work pay, nice big paycheck
Murphy co-wrote this really influence
Paper or he basically argued
That the way CEOs were being paid
Was wrong
CEO pay he said should be based on performance
If the company does well the CEO should get more
Company doesn't do so well
CEOs should get less
The really logical idea
And you wrote the paper at just the right time
Fruit to get a lot of attention the US was going through a recession
Not not a major recession but
Recession where
Executives for getting rich
At the same time they were laying off their employees
And of course
Is it that's a minefield
It's a Minefield if you're a CEO making millions of dollars a year
But if you are paid a young Governor running for president this is a gif
If companies want to overpay their executive they shouldn't get any special treatment from Uncle Sam
Oh I know that boy
Young Bill Clinton and listen here because this is not just
One more sort of abstract
Campaign rant about co-pay
Clint here is making an actual policy proposed
Bill Clinton spoiler alert wins the election end in 1993 decides
He's going to make good on that campaign promise and change that
Here is how the tax code works
If your company
To figure out how much income you have to
Taxes on you to take all the money you make
And then subtract Yorick
If you rent Office Space.
That you buy bunch of
Computers
You can subtract that
And all of the money you pay your
Please
Including CEO
You can subtract that too
It's an expense like anything else
And with the help of Congress Clinton made a little change to the tech
He put a limit on how much CEO pay
Companies could subtract
You limited how much they could do.
That limit
$1000000
So if you pay your CEO $1000000
You can deduct that
But if you pay them
2 million dollars were $5 or $10 you can only deduct
The first milk
It was a notch for the federal government to pay CEOs less
There was also a second nut
In this new part of the
And this one was tied to the idea that that economist
Kevin Murphy
I've been pushing
Yeah yeah that CEO should be paid for performance
That needed him to the tax code
Specifically it is in subparagraph
4C
Perhaps the most important subparagraph in history of
Taxes
Endo case
CEO pay
And that's a paragraph says this million-dollar cap
Does not
Apply to pay
It is tied
Performance
Tell tell the government here is like paste
You want to keep paying those multimillion-dollar salaries for CEOs just showing up in collecting a paycheck
Hospital
But you want to try out this new idea this pay-for-performance thing
We like that as long as the pay is clearly tied to Performance
There is no limit no matter how much you pay you can deduct it all
Bill white remembers when the tax law change the time with the CEO of a company called Bell & Howell
And served on various Boards of directors
The law that created this this rule
Was that a big deal
You know what the time it probably didn't look like it but in retrospect it was huge
Yuge
Who is huge because it changed the way that needle
Compensator top executives
Bill says
Compensation committees the part of the board that says
The pay for the
Yo looked at this new tax code and said
Okay
What style are CEOs paid a performance
The compensation committee Square aisuru
Immediately
Started thinking about
How we will change the pieces
Troy top executive truck CEO
And the obvious way to move
Wish it was to move to stock options
Because of that law
Spock
Options
Stock option gives you as the name suggests the option to buy a share of stock
Little quasi real world example Stacy what state
You get promoted to the CEO of
Planet Money worldwide owner
Oh and your boss
You're my boss
Are stock right now is trading at say $10
KS part of your pay
I'm going to give you one stock up
Just one
And this gives you the right to buy
1 share
A Planet Money stock for $10 at some point in the future
Okay
So now
Let's say you're doing your job
Great
Stock in Planet Money Enterprises goes up
It goes up from $10 this year to $15
Do I want to cash out how do I cash out
You can so what you doing
You use your option to exercise your right to
To buy a share of Planet Money stock for $10
And then you turn around and sell it for the market price sell it for $15
You get the pocket
$5
Which in Midtown Manhattan will buy me
Hakkasan
I want a raise
Okay so that is the good case scenario that's if things go well right
Can you do a terrible job
Paseo Pointe
Nothing to it but say you do
So you want to 10 part series on the
On the history of the penny
AR stock goes down
2 $8
Now that stock option at 10 it is not going to do anything for
We've effectively
Tiger pay to the performance of Planet Money Enterprises
I like this Penny ID
All right
Anyways
This paper performance idea it seems
Sensible enough
Kevin Murphy The Economist who been pushing me idea
His Hope was
Companies with pay CEOs more with option
And less
Through base pay
And after that law passed
Companies did pay more with option
But that other part
The cutting the base pay part
That's not going to happen
This is Bill White
The former CEO and board member
It's a very nice concept
But if you are Nadia if your CEO you're not going to want that to happen and if you're on the board of director
You have a good day
The last thing you're going to do is go to them and say you know it was going to take away from your base cop
That the rising payments through options this was not like this
Just happening at
One company here in another day
What's happening at Lots
And lots of
Dumbbells with a compensation consultant at the time
And before options payments to
CEO has been growing at a cup
Couple percentage
After Bill Clinton signed that tax law
Exploded
He remembers looking at this one survey in the mid-90s
We looked at the survey
And said
Oh my gosh so I got
Gone off
By 40%
And we're caught
And
Must be wrong
So you're saying you actually looked at this number you thought know this must be a
Hyperwear somebody must have made a math
Bright
Right now this is not this must be in the steak
It wasn't a mistake
Between 1992 and 1996
Average pay for CEOs at 500 of the biggest US corporations
Roughly doubled
From $4000000
28 million
This is that moment on the chart where CEO pay takes off or
When it starts today
Take off after this it just keep going up and up and up and that happens for a few reasons
The first one is
Kind of surprising a lot of companies are giving their CEOs a set number of option
As part of their pay every year
Tech company gives a CEO a hundred options as part of their pay in
Tape 1990
6 in 1997 there's a good chance that that company is going to give the CEO another hundred options as part of their
Their pay package for that
Which Bureau seems reasonable out of
But the stock market at the time was going up
Higher the market. The more of those options were were
Didn't that the value of the pay packages of a lot of CEOs was
It was essentially automatically increasing every year
But there's a second reason that CEO pay took off around
Way more interest
I learned it eventually doing the reporting for
Yes everybody you know why around this time
What company is giving out so many
And they all mentioned this thing
That really seems to come down to five
We thought they were free
We
Thought they were free
V words
This is Barbara Franklin she is served on corporate boards for decades
She went to Harvard Business School she's also a former Secretary of Commerce for the United States of America
And she told me what a lot of people
Back in the 90s almost everybody thought options were free
We thought they were free that was the bottom line did you really think they were free
Sure we did
The idea that options were free
Had nothing to do with that tax law passed under Bill Clinton
It has to do with an accounting rule that had been in place for decades
Under that accounting rule when companies issue their financial statements
They didn't have to account for stock options
The way they had to account for other kinds of
The under that accounting rule options kind of worth
You can sort of see why I like think about it like this
If your company
Can you pay someone a salary you write him a check
You are giving them
That is
Obviously not
What is stock option
I mean stock option I don't have to take any money out of the company bank account to give it to
And if you decide to use it in the Future II to buy that chair stock
I can just
Create a new stock for you
Out of thin air that also doesn't cost us anything
Of course the truth is that does cost
Stock options are not free
Someone in the pain
Specifically
Every other person who owns stock in the company
Every time a new share is created
All of the existing shares of stock
Are worth a little less
So say you have a retirement fund
Some of your retirement funds
In stock
This extra pay for the CEO these options they are coming from you
Don delves the compensation Consultants City kept trying to explain this to people at the time
First of all we built this
Shirley Lambert model of trailer to show people
Look this is what's happening
You know your
Hurting your shareholders you're hurting the value of the company
United States located
Nah
We don't need that
They're really free
The options are
He finally found one company that was willing to listen
That really wanted to understand what was going on
We took him and threw it in detail
Look this is what your stock options are
Costing you this is what they're costing or shareholder
I know you know they eat they understood at
They understood it then we even got to the end and the meeting and they said
Sidwell
Thank you
But we're still going to go hide and Grant the options
They said they had to do it
Because everybody else was doing
Once options took off like this in the 90s
The group that sets the accounting rules for us come
Looked at that old rule that made options feel free and they said oh obviously this is wrong
We're going to change the
So that companies cannot keep pretending that options are
Companies went ballistic
Here is a local news broadcast from 1990
Before becoming a protest
In San Jose
Get the marching band doesn't get your attention maybe the song
Find will
A couple of thousand Silicon Valley workers
Are fighting mad about losing their stock options because of the fasb or Faz B
Is the Financial Accounting Standards Board that group that wants to change the world
And all these people are coming out to protest
That's because stock options were not just been given out to CEOs and executives
Especially
They were being given out to lots and lots of
And in this new spot you see people marching with signs
What's the safe
Stock options equal job
You see people
Wendy's red buttons
It's in the shape of stop sign
Say stop fast
And they did stop fast
There were enough protest and a nap
Pressure The Fez be back
Options were still
Treated as free
And CEOs
Kept getting more of them
Co-pay kept going up
Yeah I asked Don Dells the compensation consultant what it was like to be doing his job
At this moment
How are you feeling at this point
Like you're in the middle of
Bright
How do you feel doing a job in the
Late 90s
That's a very good question
Jacob Plumbing
Think about that for a second
Uncomfortable
Very
Did you feel like because of the job you had you were
Contributing to this problem
Death
Absolutely
Absolutely in Italian
Crazy Crepe
Concern
Kevin Murphy The Economist would argue that CEOs should get more options
Also wasn't feeling so great
He says he felt like a doctor who recommends a glass of wine every night
And suddenly companies are giving their CEOs and their workers
A bottle of wine
And saying
Drink up it's good for you
I started being worried about
Watch watching in real-time the the largest
Transfer of wealth from shareholders to workers that we'd ever seen in Corporate America
Average pay for CEOs at Big corporations which has been at four million dollars in 1992
19 million dollars in the year 2000
Is it almost Queen toppled in less than a decade
And then
Stop going
What happened
Support for this podcast
And the following message come from the Wall Street journal's New weekend edition
Digest the past week
People places and stories in business news
And prepare for what's ahead
Join now and receive 50% off one year at wsj.com
Planet Money
Hate this guy right here host of how I built this
In our latest episode
Chip Wilson turned workout clothes
Into a fashion statement
And along the way
Build a breakout brand Lululemon
Now worth
Jillian
You can listen to how I built this on Apple podcast
Or however you get your pocket
Eventually CEO pay did start to come
And this happened for a bunch of
The.com bubble popped the whole stock market plunged
And shareholders finally started noticing
Caring about all those stock option
Companies working
Something hey
That's our money you're giving
Suddenly Boards of directors World lot more interested in what Don delves that compensation consultant had to say
He remembers this one call he got around this
Time from a board of directors
It was starting to worry about how much they've been paying their top executives
Nicki Minaj
Can you show us a little bit about everything is whining like a five-page report we gave him a hundred picture for it
And we started calling it that the holy s*** moments
They kept sucking the pages and each one of you are holy s***
Going to go
Oh holy s***
Meaning what
Meaning they didn't realize how
Obviously overpaid
The executive team
And how it is gotten out of
Control
That board Roundup cutting it
CEOs pay in
Also fast beat the accounting rules people finally had the support for what they wanted to
They changed that accounting rules so companies could no longer
Street stock options
The most surprising thing to me in this whole story
Happens now right around this time
CEO pay
Goes down
Which I never would have guessed it just goes up and up and up forever but no
When you look at
The average pay of the CEOs of the biggest US corporations
From 19 million dollars in 2000
212 million dollars in 2014
The end of all the interviews I did for the story I asked everybody the same
Question
How do you feel about how much CEOs are paid
Some said well it depends on the CEO you know these people are running
Corporations that are worth
Billions of dollars
Tell somebody you can make that company a little bit better
It's worth a lot of money
Tio today still over
And to be clear CEO pay has gone down
But not nearly as much as it went up
CEO pay today
Is still much much higher than it was
Back in the early nineties
Quit the numbers we use in the story for co-pay they are adjusted for inflation they are in mm
$14 they are based on CEOs of companies that are in the S&P 500 and they come from Kevin
The Economist we talked to in the story who is now a professor at USC
Sandals the compensation consultant in the story he is still a compensation consultant he works at a firm called
Willis Towers Watson we always love to hear what you think of the show send us an email Planet Money
Me at npr.org
Or find us on Facebook
You can give us your two cents or episode today was produced by Nick fountain
Thanks also to Brian Dunn a compensation consultant who I talked with her the story but did not make it into the show
Jacob and Stacey Vanek Smith thanks for listening