Shear engine is in it and
Is 32 years old
And he lives in rongcheng China
It is a city of around 700 thousand people on the E
And he says it is a really nice
But like any City it has its
Issues
The traffic for instance
Has always been totally cray
Would not give way to pedestrians
And sometimes when they saw people crossing then they will
Break all of a sudden and the cause a lot of accidents exactly for example the car behind what
Bump on to the car in front of
The show the fender bender we spoke with Ron Jon through our producer ecowatt
Rain chances being a pedestrian was just
Terrifying
You basically just have to hurl yourself across the street when you saw a break
In traffic
You know hope for the best
But now after the changes have happened to the cars and it will wait for you
The changes that have happy
Have to do with the implementation of a new policy in China called the social credit score
Cities like wrong turn or testing out a version of this system
And the planets it'll be in place all across the country
By the year 2020
The social credit score is similar to the credit score we happy
And the idea behind both
Best
In a big complex economy you have to do business
With strangers
And you want some way to know whether or not you can
Can trust them whether they're going to pay back a loan whether they'll be a good tenant if you rent
Apartments
Weather
The Advil they're selling you is
You know
Advil
And not Imodium
Say
It does not be super rough
China does not have a traditional credit score
And this has been causing some problems
White people not paying back loan
And not really seeing any consequences of not paying back
But just imposing a credit score system was tricky
Because here's the thing
Many Chinese citizens
Don't have
A credit history
A lot of Chinese citizens don't even have Bank
So when China set out to make their trust score they kind of leapfrogged over
Credit score and came up with something broader
More sweeping
The Chinese social credit score will measure things like whether or not you
Cologne
But it also includes Behavior
Like how you act at work or
Whether you obey traffic
Turn up giving way to people were crossing the traffic light
Your points will get deduct
Forget the noise of a fender bender
If you don't yield to pedestrians in wrong turn these days
You might not be able to take out a home loan
Get a good seat
Train
And if your social credit score is low or if you're one of the people who doesn't pay back a debt ordered by the
The court you could end up on something called a list of untrustworthy people
R The Blacklist
Right now The Blacklist is in effect Nationwide
And people on The Blacklist can't get a credit card
They can't take out a loan or open a bank account
Not to mention a whole other raft of restrictions and humiliation
For instance in some parts of China
If your on The Blacklist and someone calls your phone
They will hear this
That is a recording Bass
Cliche
Warning
This person is on
On The Blacklist
Be careful in your dealings with them and
Resorts them to pay back their debts
Hello welcome to Planet Money I'm Carlos Garcia
And I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
We are the hosts of Planet money daily podcast the indicator
And we've been doing a lot of reporting on the indicator about China's social
Credit system
The China is building a giant system to measure how trustworthy its citizens are
This system will reach into almost every part of daily life
It will determine things like who can get a loan
Give me the country
You can take an airplane
Kgf someone tracking our data and using it to make judgments about us
That's nothing new
We know that companies do it we know the government
But China social credit system will take all of that to a whole new level
It is changing how people shop how they socialize
How they behave in traffic
And even what it means to be an individual
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Should come from fidelity
Has a Fidelity Wealth Management
You get a dedicated advisor to help
Grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of Pacs
And make it clear recommendation
Thanks for your full Financial
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage services
LLC
Rachel botsman teaches trust in technology and is the author of who can you
As she was researching china's social credit system in trying to consider the broader and
Applications
Her mind kept going back to this one
Place
I don't know if you've ever
Tina episode of Black Mirror that everyone talks about couldn't nosedive which is just an amazing piece
Black Mirror on Netflix Sci-Fi show
In this episode
Call nosedive
Everyone has a smartphone with
Them all the time
And the reading everyone around them
Every interaction
People are being evaluated on how they act
I'm ignoring you
Five star steaks
Are you all the time episode every one of these interaction
Contributes to your overall
Score and people can see your score on their phones as you walk around in the world
And that score determines off
Kinds of thing
That's reserved for members around primeflight programme got to be a full point to her over to qualify
Don't come I don't want you here
I don't know what is up with you but I cannot have a two 6 at my way
I have a 260 year wedding
Wings Over
Rachel emphasizes that this is
Fiction but you says the show make some really smart point
Points about a system where people have a kind of centralized rating
Live and die by
That we are familiar with a centralized rating
Credit score
But how do you build a system like this in a country where a lot of people just don't have much of a
Credit history
Well you can find records
The people's behavior in other areas
And extrapolate trustworthiness
From that
And no Cardiff who has lots and lots
And lots of data on how people behave
Big companies
All the company companies in China the big companies are
Really
Alibaba is like China's version of
Amazon it has more than
Alien cast
Tons of data on what these
Best Buy
It Ali Baba also owns one of the largest online payment
In the country
And has its own credit scoring
Cold sesame
Credit Alibaba nose
A lot of
How people spend
And borrow
And how much money they like
We have
So do other private
And the government is partnered with some of them to share data
Dad of the number of China Watchers believe will be used to formulate
Kohl's credit score
Does Rachel says
It's unclear how much data or what data
Alibaba and other Chinese
These are sharing
With the government
Or how the data is getting
The way people escorted is not somebody with a mr. bill it could be what they buy online
It could be
Like a low-cut dress well it's not far from that I mean I think these on pools
The head of Sesame credit with example
Cheap public who gave the Press was
You know if you buy nappies you're responsible
So your school will go out but if you
Buying video games
You're lazy
ECU school will go down
Nappy
Yes
It sounds so much nicer than
Of course
Of course his data collection and the weird assumptions it companies make based on our actions
Does happen in the US and everywhere else
Rachel says it with different China is hausa
Severe and comprehensive the consequence
We reached out to
The Chinese government by the way but they did not respond
Request for comment
Social credit score will not be all about
What you buy
The government is also collecting data of its own
And that did it will Factor
People social credit
It's worse to
And we got a glimpse into how this might work because pilot cities around China have already been testing out there versions
Of the system
One of those cities is wrong.
Where are it engineer
And he says the dad about him has
All been bundled together into a single
So in a system everyone starts out with a score of
What did she want
Insolvent
So he's still got a thousand by the way you can get more than
It's true there's a whole letter grade 6
Whitesell from 962
1000 + points
Is an a
959 points is Abby 8:49 to 600 is
See and this is considered a warning letter
Blue bat
You are a dick
You're labeled an untrustworthy City
Like it's really hard
You can gain or lose points for all kinds of read
Get a DUI
That is an automatic downgrade to Abby
Get into a spat with your neighbors
-10 points
Give to charity thing meaning
What's 5.
And if you spread rumors online minus
50 point
Forget to clean up after your pet
-10 points
Keep track of all this
Neighborhoods have designated
Watchers
People who keep track of neighbors Behavior
Update people's scores all monitors that they used to have in Greece
School now they actually have
And it is real power
Because if you have a really high score you could discount and a bunch of local businesses
Your heating bill goes down
You get some cable channels
Including a soap opera Channel
Indica
Weather Channel
You also get special invitations to community event
If your score is low life gets pretty hard
No invites
No free kung fu Chan
Also you might not be able to get a promotion at work even if
You've been doing a great job
You just won't be eligible
And all this is for the mind blowing and you can kind of amusing to hear about
But there are some very real consequences to this system
One person who is experience them first-hand
Is a man named loud
He's 42
And he asked us not to use his full name because he
She could get in trouble with the government for talking to them
Loud one used to work in
In the coal industry
Few years ago the price of
The coal in China
Plummeted mycashflow
Cut off
Because the money was just gone into
Smoked loved one would buy
Tons of coal from
Coal mines and sell it to energy
Eplans it needed
But then the Chinese government change
Used its energy policy
And so the price of cold tank
Allowed one was left with Warehouse
Full of cold
He could no longer
Sell red wine about himself in terrible
Geode various creditors
One and a half million dollars
And one of them took him to court
Loud one told the judge
I just don't have this money I can't pay back these loans
But the court disagreed
And put him on China's dreaded
Blacklist
Bankruptcy does not occur
Just in China in the same way that it
It does in
Us allowed one wasn't really sure what being on The Blacklist men
He just knew that he wanted to get back on his feet and get a new business going to
To pay off those debts
Nicole business was dead
Loud wanted
Very successful
Any still had good contacts
He decided he would go to Beijing
Hit up some of those contacts
And figure out a new
So loud one went online to book
It was a high-speed train to Beijing
Put his name in
Payments
Right away this page popped up
Thank you couldn't complete the
This person
Is on the untrustworthy list from the cards
Last one was confused
Why couldn't keep up the train ticket
He started looking into
The black
The Blacklist have been rolled out
Before the full search
Credit score
But it will be part of it
It started about five years ago and it does involve cracking down on debtors
Creating consequences
For people who do not pay back
Are loans
And allowed one discovered
One of those consequences
He could not book a high-speed
Dancing that comes along with
The Blacklist are untrustworthy listings that you are
Fart
High-end
Consumption
Which means
That you can't take
Speed train
You can fly
Flying to Beijing bus one says take 90 minutes
But that's considered luxury travel so he can do that
He would end up instead taking the slow train
To Beijing which is
14 hours
And loved one was blocked from booking a lot of hotel rooms in
Because that was considered a luxury expense
Trying to start this new business
Began to feel
Impossible
The way to new business has been already blocked
I'm allowed one went to his bank
He found it all of his accounts and cards
Have been frozen
One morning
When loved one was driving through the center of town
He discovered another aspect
Being on the entrust
On what are the electronic Billboards by the side of the road
Was his face slick up on a big billboard
Electric screen
By the side of the big Plaza
There are like
Huge screens and you can really see them from afar
I saw my my pictures on that screen picture from my ID card and my ID card number
And my name
The billboard said this man is untrust
Loved one says these Billboards are all over town
But once he started to feel self-conscious
All the time
I'm really hard to go out
Ever since that I actually intentionally reduce
Eye contact with
Weather outside world
And also I try not to go
To this get-togethers With Friends
Why do you do that why do you until I am afraid that people would look at you from a in a day
Different way and I don't feel confident anymore
Bloodwine says whenever he went out
I never did see the billboard
Can we just stop and watch it
Scrolling to the untrustworthy
Waiting to see if
His face with come
The one day when he was doing that
I saw the face of someone he knew for one of them
Speed walking
The same industry as I did
No I'm there
Lisa been successful business
White Cloud wine
And now they were the same
Position he was
So he called some of them up
Started arranging dinner
Where they could all meet up
And talk
He says the other people on The Blacklist are now the only people that he can really relax or
So what I thought was actually a widespread attitude towards us is very resistant
People that was Hank why
Are you sure being happy
Why do you still have time to be happy
Why do you not go out and make money to pay back your loan
So far loud one says he has paid back about 300,000 of the 1 and 1/2 million dollars
Originally owned
So still about 1.2 million.
How long do you think it will take to pay off
The rest
Acquiesce
But even when loud one does managed to pay off his debts
Getting off The Blacklist
Could be hard
We talked to lawyers in China who deal with this by all accounts
Getting off The Blacklist
Even if you paid your debts
Well it's technically possible
But it just never seems to happen
We reached out to China Supreme Court about the
But they didn't respond to requests for
But loud one says he will keep paying off his debt he has to believe there's a way off this list
Meanwhile China is moving towards the
Full rollout of the social credit
And by 2020 the system is meant to be in place
All across
What's the country
After the break we try to understand what this all will mean for
China's economy
And Ford City
Support for this podcast
Send the following message come from Fidelity invest
As a Fidelity wealth
You get a dedicated advisor
Here to help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of tax
And make it clear recommendation
Games for your full Financial
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage service
This is LLC
Okay Stacey when we are trying to evaluate the
Is social credit
System that China is Middle
Rolling out
One thing we talked about a lot
Is it it just feels kind of creepy
Neighborhood Watchers watching
Everybody's every move
Undeniably
I mean at least you us but when we talked about this was she run John the 32 year-old it engineer and Ron Chen the pilot
What city
He told us to him the monitoring does not feel creepy
Becky says that it's made people act better like he used to be someone who
Did not stop for pedestrian
When he was driving
Not have done that
Now.run John says
He always stops
And you just feel better about it
In fact he thinks the system is a kind of step in the evolution of societies
And people living together
Where the needs of the community are put ahead of the needs of the individual
Who have become more friendly
I think in the history of human
Being developing towards
Like communities
If everybody can follow the rules
I'm sure it's
It's very good for
You know every individual living in the city
On the other hand
What are the reasons
The system gives so many people a lot of
Pause
The Chinese government will almost certainly be using it to
To try and control
Is population
Even more than it already does
The bolster it
Empower
Remember one way
To lose a lot of points in your social credit score
Is to quote
Spread rumors online
Most definitely
And you don't the whole time that we've been working on the series
I kept thinking about this one little scene from The Black
Episode and I know that it's fiction but it really stuck with
With me and I haven't been able to shake it
It's the scene where the main character is
Practicing her laugh in the bathroom mirror
She's trying really really hard to seem happy and joyful
So the people will like her and give her a high rating when they interact with her
Part of all this that I find the most troubling
Is that it makes emotions like anger or frustration or even sadness into a
Kind of suck the authenticity out of human interaction
Punishes people for
Being Human
For their own Humanity
Episode please check out our show the indicator from Planet Money posted by
It's 10 minutes or less comes out everyday and you hear stories like this one or on the psychological impact
Recessions or implied or stuff like why the price of Fritos is going up in the White House vending machine even though horn price
You're going down
Really interesting mystery to solve
Oh yeah but we we did the indicator is produced by constanza Gallardo Echo Fang and dharius Rafael
We are edited by Patty Hearst and today's Planet Money episode big shout out with produced by Sally helm
Also we actually want to emphasize Echo won't roll in this she didn't just translate for she also did
All of the original reporting about
Story Forest you really appreciate it she's an absolute
Star
Also quicknote Planet Money in the indicator are both looking for interns
Good job
Head
Shape things less you could hang out with us
What could be better than that
For more information just go to our website npr.org
Flash mob
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith time Cardiff Garcia thanks for