Jose Luis gavilondo is driving me through the desert
Chihuahua Mexico in a little Ford SUV
He's wearing a dress shirt jeans boots and a beige cowboy hat and his right hand is wrapped up in the
Just lost part of his thumb
I got the dog in the with the rope and went off they put it back together but
I wasn't able to fix the whole fingers I lost like the tip it happened during a competition
That sounds like a rodeo but it's not really a rodeo
Rodeo is the same but it's a little different you throw the rope into
Horse running in front of you try to get the to the 2x + C
Stop use running
Carros throw a lasso at the back two legs of a galloping horse and then they pull on the Rope it's
Wrapped Around the Horn of the saddle and there's so much friction from
The horse
Pulling away
That the leather starts
Smoking
Smoking is really fast and I cut my finger in into the rope and the saddle
You got there so
Okay horses are Hotel Reese's Hobby
But towels
Hauser
Business
Jose Luis V
Generation cattle rancher nginx
State of Chihuahua raises Angus steer
Beef cows
Is family is 3000 head of cattle
Thousands of acres of land they rmx
Sticking cows are born in May
To go but a lot of them have American dads
Jose Luis buys bull sperm
River Ranch in New Mexico
I like my angles to be short
And their bellies to be really close to the to the ground
And you can find that easily in Mexico
That's why I like to
To buy it over there
The qualities
Perfect Mexican beef start out in
Hipec
Little straws
Filled with
Potential
Chilled to a perfect negative 70 degrees
Every year when it's time to breed when he refers to as his momma cows
Jose Luis makes a trip to New Mex
He picks up a cooler full of sperm straws
Throws them in the back seat of his pickup truck
Takes them across the border through Mexican customs
South on Highway 45
Frost a Chihuahua Desert
3 hours with ranch
And finally inseminates about a hundred of his Mexican cows with this American sperm
And they can tell you these cow
I'm going to produce these days and days it's going to be really good for this this and that
In it and they have the best
It's just that
I forgot Perfection he pays about $30
Bra
Back 30 bucks
The first step in a complex
Kind of amazing chain of economic events that is the modern beef
Discount account today isn't just a thing that happens at a farm
Not just meat
Account today is more like an economic system of Bette and
Payoffs
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Jason beaubien Jason is with us from the global help desk
NPR cheer America buys 500 million pounds of beef from Mexico
And America sells 500 million pounds of beef back to Mexico
I first heard about this we were like why would it even be worth it to ship all this beef back and
Fourth on Hoarders Dan the show we go to the Mexican border to find out
Journey of a cow in the modern economy it's a story about mothers and fathers and those little straws
Also amazing Mexican food and it all starts
Jose Luis has cooler
Support for this podcast
Send the following message come from Fidelity invest
As a Fidelity wealth
You get a dedicated advisor
Here to help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of tax
And make clear recommendation
Games for your full Financial
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
We're driving through the open airplanes worth
Mexican cattle will be born and raised
This part of the twelve desert
Incredibly harsh everything
Rachie and seems like the irritated
Like prickly like prickly yeah here you cannot have cattle during the winter
Is really cold and has a lot of sand and most of the time you just see that Miss Keisha
Send and sent called la gobernadora
The governor
Kills everything around it
He doesn't really good smell whenever it rains for you how God was that push around is Mel's awesome but is
I think this is the only thing that I like about it
The great advance in Mexican Ranch
Should have in raising caps
That they got plenty of land
It might not be
Be the best
Pasture but ranchers let these calves
Live off the country they don't have to
To spend money to
To feed them
The cast of the first 6-8 months of their lives nursing from their moms and grazing around the governor bushes and cacti
Nibbling on wild grasses
The scrubby plants
Jose Luis doesn't keep
These cows
He sells them
Back to the United States
And
There's only one way to get there
These cows
Have to walk across the border it's a long annoying Journey for these cows
Lines
Security
Just like any international border crossing
Your basic nightmare at JFK but for cattle
Jose Luis
Round up the cattle
Complex of Stockyard
It's right up against the Border fence
What's in Santa Teresa
The Chihuahua Cattlemen's
San Jose Luis is a member
There's a big building right there and Cowboys start herding the cattle into this building
The cows walk in
Single file
USDA agents are inspector
One by one
Amato's poor unsuspecting cows walk out of that big building they called on a shoe
And land in a pool of water
It's a tick bath that does not happen at JFK
At least not yet
The cows
Scramble to get out of the water and they Shake themselves off like what
Puppies
And now they're right at the border waiting
To be traded
To the United
ABS the gate over there
Opencv peaser
Just making sure it's just cattle what is crossing the US Customs and Border Protection agent
Sitting there in his white.
Pickup truck
And he has the keys
I'll let this trade happen
He has the actual keys
To the Border open it up
Slide open like a
Huge heavy sliding door
For a little bit they're kind of in
No man's land
Then they tried writing the United States
End up in a long narrow pan that's basically a big scale it
It looks like a flatbed truck
And here is where they get sorted
And Wade
This is the Sorting shoots right here
They sort of cattle and sizes
400 pounder is 507 tenders and that's how the Mexican Cattleman is fate by the way
And by the time they go out
It's already on America's
American brokers
Cattle Baron American cows
More Cows walkthrough
This gate in the Border fence than any other gate on the border
We just got our another
Permit again for to have this
Story right here opening and closing for 10 more years
We paid off
That permit
2 days ago
What else is opening in the border France
There might not be as big a ranch
Chihuahua
Beef on both sides of the board would probably be more expensive
Cattle and beef
Currently move across North America without any
Tariffs or quotas
The same used to be true for Hogs but pigs
Things got caught up in the rain
Distance. Between
Us and Mexico over
Steel tariffs
And Mexico put at 20%.
But at least for now the cattle industry has managed
To stay out of the
Jose Luis sells each of his for about a hundred bucks
Which is interesting because anyone will tell you these cows will be worth a lot more in just a few months
The reason these cows make the journey to the United States is because of decisions made in Washington and New York
By bankers
Feeding cows
Corn and Alfalfa and
Weeds until they're ready to be slaughtered is
Expensive
Renters usually have to borrow money
To feed their cows
And
It's just cheaper to borrow money in the US
The finance in Mexico it's not as cheap
That's what it is in the US
They do lend money but it's out of very high on
So you can
Really compete with that
This is William Wallace
The 4th generation
Cattle rancher
Everyone calls him Pollito
If you had to borrow money to buy
Corned Baton Rouge right now in the US
And not in Mex
Icicle
Apple 25
Interest rate interest rate
So that's something it's it's a big difference
Big Bird
Those dramatically lower interest rates are part of why more than a million cows cross the border
EGR advantages like that get talked about all the time by economist
Comparative advantage
She's one of the first things you learn about in economics class
America could raise caps on bass chunks of land
Or
It could do other more profitable things with that land
Mexico has land
And of all the things they can choose to do with it raising calves
This is a relatively good option
That's
Comparative advantage and that's why they shut all these
Giant animals
Across-the-board
Some of the cattle coming across the Mexico are sold Direct
American Rancher
Brokers
Others go up for sale auction right next to
The Stockyards owner
Westside
309 on these men 309
In all three flags the Mexican flag American flag the New Mexico flag
On the wall and Auctioneer Jack Blandford
Find a drive up the price on a batch of house
Peter Farrelly
Small compared to the others in Blandford is joking that they're so compact
You can drive them home in the cab of your pickup truck
He starts the bidding at $2 a pound
8 inches up to $2.07
And then Blandford
Declares
They're sold 43 on 30
Another nice set
As they scramble out of the auction Hall the animals
Loaded into trucks
Is all over the
Alvaro bustillos the owner of Vaquero trading says
A lot of the couch from Mexico go to the
Panhandle Colorado California
Lot of small cattle is going right now to Oklahoma
Whenever you get a million of anything moving around
High Finance
Shows up with their Wares
And Alvaro is Wall Street agent right down here on the border
He doesn't like to call himself a cattle broker
The way he describes it
The lot more than just buy and sell cows
We facilitate the trade
Between
Mexican producer and I
And I just realized
Us buyer
Which could be any anywhere from
Cattle feeder all the way to a Rancher farmer
Even we sell like I sell cattle to
Private equity
Vons
Which
Mandi sometimes
By the cattle for their portfolios folios private equity
Basically just
Big pools of investor money
Cows aren't just
House to Wall Street there
Stable commodity something worth
Buying and selling
2 Wall Street a cow is a
A series of coffee
Send opportunity
To sell
The cost to buy it
The cost to feed it
Price it sells for
Wall Street makes all kinds of options
Contracts and Deals available to the cattle rancher
They'll buy the cattle for me the live cattle
And that they'll sell the contract
For that a specific month
Where it's going to get slaughtered okay
And then they have to pencil in the input
Up to feed that
That steer which would be the future of the Corn
That's the break even
And you can even call it a crush
Are you by the
Live cattle
Seldom
Fat future and buy the corn
A crush of course you got to love trade jargon
The crush is the way you described a 3-way bet
They take bets on the cost
Difficult Without Really dealing with a real cow
Bets on the cost
Feed the cow the cost of the
The meat and if the price of the mean ends up higher than the cost
Feed the cow
You get rich
They probably aren't
Without touching any cows
Put the to like in this Futures market right people are buying selling
Cattle that
They've never even seen yet right in
Understanding of what you do you make sure that
In that
That real cow shows up eventually right or that
That's what we do like
What we do is
We buys
Cattle from Aldi's
Producers
Put them all together
And then standardized
Risorgimento
Sizes and qualities
There's always a market for everything
Last year Alvarado helped farmers and big beef companies in New York Traders by more than a hundred and fifty thousand
Head of cattle from
Because at the end of all that wheeling-and-dealing like
A real cow actually has two
Show up at American Farms and feedlots
That cow grows in weight and value
In less than a year a 400 pound calf
1400 lb
$1,600
Worth of cow
Out of the cost of the cow and the Feed and Seed
Subtracted from the sale price
Crushed
Maybe
Then they get turned into beef
Slaughtered that's
What happens
To recap
We have eight
$30 fraud
Sperm going from the US
Down to Mexico
When the calf cross the border into the US
It sold for 8
$800
The US farmer got
1600 bucks
He sold the cow to the slaughterhouse
And then the final retail value of that box me when it leaves the slaughterhouse
It is
$100
But remember
The same amount of beef going
Interview s
Is also going
Out and this is worth
It really surprised me
A lot of that meat will go
Back the next
Again
1/3
Crossing
Therapyland a gaetano's in Oklahoma
He says
It when a cow is slaughtered
Produces hundreds of different products
Hamburger
Tongue
Filet mignon
And he looks at this like a distributor would
Someone who has to get a lot of different things
A lot of different places
And there's an opportunity to make more money off some of those be
Free products
Depending on where you sell them
There's there's no reason to assume and any country that consumer preferences are going to exactly match
The mix of products that you're going to get every time you you process one of these animals
It used to be that a butcher would get a carcass and cut the meat up right there
Now the meat is box
Status slaughterhouse
The rabbis go to
To some customers
Some important pieces cows might end up
Steakhouse in
Pants and the shank might go to Mexico City
There's a natural opportunity to add value if you can
Adjust the flows of those products him and moved
Fetal move some products
Offshore to add to an export Market fee France Prince
The cut of meat from the rump of the animal
And have one value in Mexico
Different value in the US
You take round in the US you know
The big part of the round it's very lean
It does it's not something that we would typically make steaks out of her example and it gets used in other ways
In Mexico
That that round is referred to as milanezza which is a
Specific
Dish but it's also referred to as the cut very popular so you add value when you ship that
Tongue
Liver cow bones
Bareheaded
I went down to Juarez to have lunch with Eric Adela of
The El Chaparral restaurant
She's telling me about her favorite Mexican deli
The head of a cow
You either put it to boil
And you get the cheeks
You get the eyeballs for special
Gourmet tacos
You got the brains
The brains
Tasty Erica works for the state of New Mexico is kind of trade representative
She grew up in Chihuahua she's married to a Rancher
And she appears to know everybody on both sides of the Border
She also knows where to find
Good fried tripe
She says nothing in Mexico gets wasted
You get
The
The tongue
They also a dish with the oxtail
So everything that they use
The cow is utilized 100%
The waiter just delivered in order us McDonald's
I love Dwight
It's chunks of black and cow bones and their pile up on the plate
And they're still unbelievably hot as if they
Just come out of the fire
And you
Eat the question
Cooking a bone marrow out onto a tortilla
Which of the little bit of lime salt and chopped onion
Do you like a whole bunch of lime otherwise
Weird
And I
Eat but I know the United States I can go into a grocery store and get them
But they don't say where the cows
Came from because the United States acknowledges that even cows that are born in Mexico
Our kind of
Half American
It's a product of both places like me
And this is something Jose Luiz
When we were in Chihuahua he was talking to me about constant
Okay yeah it was born in Mexico
Who builded who built most of the me
Almost 1/3 or 2/3
Oh that's here it was built in the United States we thought
We the American corn
American Falls American every
He says the US and Mexico beef Industries are so intertwined now that
It's just sort of
One Industries selling steaks and threaten us to whoever wants them
Jose Luis
Is worried however that
Something could happen to disrupt
Mexican-American beef pizzle
Trade War some new set of Paris
Spotify shutting down
The import export facility
But as long as Mexican ranchers best option is to raise calves and US Traders best
Adoption is to grow and slaughter them
The cows are
Going to keep walking through the Border
Support also comes from Fidelity invest
As a Fidelity wealth
You get a dedicated advisor
To help grow and pray
Protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of tax
And make clear recommendations
Thanks for your full Finance
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
Let us know what you thought of the show you can hit us up at Planet Money at npr.org
Laura Grasso on Twitter and Instagram at Planet Money
A big thanks to William matisa to New Mexico border Authority also to David Cooper at Progressive Cattleman magazine and Professor Dave
David Anderson at Texas A&M
Alex goldmark is there supervising producer Brian Ernst at the star editor
And this episode was produced by Darian with
He's a vegetarian sardarian I'm Sarah Gonzales
Thanks for listening
Hello thank you for choosing Wendy's would you like some bacon classic
Like what is your best burger what's your best burger
The Baconator gets old
A Baconator get sword
You're the most alright well I'll try that one