In the fall of 2010 something
Expected happy
In Blue Hill Maine
A town where unexpected things rarely happen
It is a small town about 2600 people tucked in to the Maine coast
It's a beautiful
Madia isolated places he have to kind of go out of your way to get here
This is Jim Schatz who lives in Blue Hill gym is
Friendly soft-spoken the kind of guy who would
Your dishes after a party
In fact when we met he had just helped cook a town Mother's Day
Hopefully they were had a chance to have brunch didn't did you what did you get there in time
Sadly I had just eaten anyway in 2010 when a Maine state senate seat
Came open gym decided that he was going to go
For it I thought I had a really good chance I thought I would win
Jim's opponent was a republican named Brian Langley
Brian is also very friendly
But in more of a polo shirt neatly tucked in firm handshake
Sound like kind of
I say don't be an activist
Be just active in your community that is Brian
His campaign strategy
I'll give out 5000 blueberry pie recipes at the bar Harbor
Prayed he says his pie recipe is wanting more votes than his political views
But sit on the back of a
Best campaign Flyers
And Jim on the
Brightside revved up the marketing strategy that had won him eight elections before this
Is there a slogan for gym chat
Evoke
Offer gym that's about it
Yeah it's I like it and since everyone there generally knows everyone campaigns are pretty low-key
More pie than politics
But in the fall of 2010
Out of nowhere
These ads started showing up
They hit the streets Bam Bam Bam and on television it was his bam out there
So Jim showed me a few of these ads
The first one was just like this
8 by 10 flyer it has a
American flag on it
Picture in the middle
And it says baseball apple pie Fourth of July in fireworks not this Fourth of July gym shots and had other priorities
Someone with accusing Jim of the
Canceling America
Poop that leave the fireworks
But it gets worse
The next fire he shows me is if
Picture of this
Really sad young girl maybe six years old mouth wide open screaming
And says
This child just found out Jim shots cancelled Fourth of July fireworks
I'm part of this is true blue hill had canceled its Fourth of July celebration and Jim did have a say
He's in Blue Hills Local cover
But
I did not vote to get rid of it
Jim was actually the only person who voted
Keep the faith
And so it
It's just was totally misleading
This was an election so when you see something like that you just point to the other side
In this case that would be Brian Langley the Republican with the blueberry pie
I didn't set these up I didn't I have no idea where they're coming from I was just sort of Blindsided
So she calls up a big rig in the Maine State Republican party and asked
Do you know who did this
And did you some research and come back to Brian and say
It wasn't Us in fact we don't think it was anybody in May
And Brian is
Afraid that these ads are actually going to
Hurt him because
In Blue Hill
This kind of negative campaigning
So
She turns around buys his own new set of ads just to say those negative ads
I have nothing
So now Brian's platform is basically I like the guy I'm running against
I like Jim
But
Salary for Jim it was
There is all over basically
And I are not so it was
Send
It was the first time since 1992 that are Republican won that District
When Tip O'Neill said all politics
Our local now it's not local it's coming from people who have nothing to do with the local
And in the aftermath
The town was left with a very big question
If Brian didn't do this
And the state Republican party didn't
Who inserted themselves in this
Localist
If local election
I'm fly
Brian and Jim didn't know it that fall in Maine but they had gotten wrapped up in one of the most
Brilliant political schemes of our time hello and welcome to Planet Money I Am Karen.
Noel King today on the show we meet the man who took the idea that all politics are local to the bank I'm making
A tiny investment in the smallest of places he set in motion one of the biggest political shift in Generations
One that would shape elections not just in Maine but all across the country for years to come including
The midterms this fall
Support for this podcast
In the following message come from the Annie E Casey
Sea Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is
Is available at aecf
. org
To get to the bottom of what happened in Maine in that follows 2
We have to turn the clock back into the 80s into the early 90s this is Chris Jankowski
He is a longtime Republican operative
I'm back in the 1990's he had just graduated from law school and started working in the South Carolina attorney general's office
At a really unique moment
Four state pilot
I was there as a young Assistant Attorney General during a tobacco litigation
Tobacco litigation
It was 1998 and the tobacco industry paid out and his
Store Excel
They were finally forced to act
And it wasn't the federal government who did it it wasn't Congress it was
State politicians
Uniting together
That was the first sort of collective effort of state attorney generals to make a national impact
For Chris
It changed the direction of his life and eventually it changed the direction of the entire country
Chris saw that states acting
Together can wield a ton of collective National
Which is just not how people were viewing State policy
That it really is sort of
Consider the junior varsity new job working for the insurance Lobby
And insurance is mostly regulated at the state level so Chris is learning all the wonky mechanics of State politics
And while he's toiling away at the
The state level on a
All this money being thrown
National efforts in DC
Doesn't see a lot of progress
And he starts thinking they would just give me 10% of what they were spending federally I swear
I could have an impact of this untapped potential of state power
A cruise from an epiphany into sort of a chip on Chris's shoulder
And eventually he leaves Insurance lobbying and along with a few State friendly collie
He decides to start his own group
And focus just on States
What caused the Republican state leadership committee Dr SLC
Sonata 2002 and these guys start working on individuals
State elections and
State issues
And all the while
They're looking for their tobacco moment
Something big
Did all the states
Together can get
And they've been doing this for a couple of years when
One Sunday in
2009 Chris
Open finished
Paper of course
I have to admit I read New York Times but
I did and
Reading the New York Times
Shamefully
I said while I'm I'm reading a national
Congressional story
That really is about my world
The article talked about major demographic shifts that would likely show up in the
2010 census
Reshape
The elections
Cuz mine just starts
Turning okay you might remember this from history class
Every 10 years the Constitution says we have to do a census
We have to count up all the people in the United
And then we have to divide everyone up equally ish into 435 Congressional
Every district has the same number of people and gets to elect one representative to the US House
That is equal representation
And so every ten years after the census
Statesville often have to redraw their maps to adjust for population
Yeah like a bunch of people leave Kansas they moved to Missouri the match
Right so maybe Missouri gets another congressional seat
Can'ts loses one
And both States would have to
Are there maps to account for that
Redrawing District
Reshape
Elections
Because when you draw the lines when you draw them at
Super basically choosing which voters are going to end up in a district
You draw them one way in the district will send a democratic Congress
And drawing a different way might send a Republican
And districts drawn carefully, nearly guarantee a party a win
Maybe even then
Next decade this is called gerrymandering and both parties do it every chance they
So crisp
Puts down his New York Times
Probably has it
Deep in his trash can
And thanks
Found my issue
This is a way for states to wield
Massive power
Because remember Jim and Brian who are running for state senate in Maine people like them control this Pro
Process for the most part
State legislatures draw the national Maps
The redistricting is like the secret superpower of State politics
The local controls the national
So Chris can coxis
Flip State legislatures red
And they will turn the National Mall
Long-term results
Breitbart
He calls the plan
Red Mountain what does Red Lobster
Oh this is one always dumps me
Question I've asked
It's the district Republican
It's a redistricting majority
Project
Redistricting majority project
He did get it right at
Is the register
Senate majority project
And Chris just knows that his plan will work
For it to work he needs
Money
And he knows
From
Experience that selling a state-level plan for republic
Kendama Nation
Might be tough
It feels like
You're trying to fundraise for like an off-off-broadway show and everybody else wants
Invest in Lake Hamilton
Exactly
So he makes it really
Simple he goes right to the heart of the matter
Money
He does some cost analysis
And it shows that
In many cases
A dollar goes
Much farther in terms of impacting
Congressional c-diff
You spend it on Stateline
I Only Could this plan work
It is a
Huge bargain
So Chris starts Dialing for Dollars
Sorry you're wasting a
A ton of money every year on Congressional races sometimes we win sometimes we lose
For 25 cents on the dollar I can take
25 Congressional
It's off the table for the next 10 years
And slowly if
The money starts coming
From Individual donors and then later from Corporation
Chris eventually ends up with more than 30 million dollars
I just shook my head I just
Can't believe it and 30 million dollars
That amount of money
Barely make a dent in most national elections
Chris thinks that he can win
Hundreds of State
For that much
But
There's a reason that no one had ever read mapped or blue Maps
Before
Which is
There are 7383 local
State Legislative
You got to figure out which of those seats you're going to Target and then you have to influence
Hundreds of campaigns
That turn on hyper local issues
It's like in Maine with the fire
But then Chris realizes
You know it's figuring out which seats to go after
For the most part
Actually sort of just
We use data and objective research we didn't have to actually meet the candidates
To know what we could do
This math problem has
The two part of
Part 1
Identify which states might gain or lose
The congressional seat after the next
Because of demographic
About
Those dates
If they lost or gained is
They would definitely have to
To draw a new map
So we prioritize those dates
And
We came up with rough budgets
For what it would take to take control or maintain control
So at this point they've narrowed it down to
18 /
And this leads to part 2
You calculate the cost
To turn each
State legislature red
Now that is not a simple couch
Explain it
It's pretty painful
It has to do with how many voters do you need to reach in order to flip
So Chris runs the numbers and he figures out which states to Target
And how many
And he starts spending money
On things like maybe
Give the money to the state party so they
Spend it on there though
Local races
And this is way more money than you normally see in local election
Like that race in Maine that we talked
What about Chris spent four times as much money on that race
It's in 2010 then the candidates had
2 years before
Now comes the
Really hard
How to win over to
200 elections
That turn on hyper local
That really had never been done before at that level
And that's
That takes
Do you know any really good at figuring out what the hot-button local issues were
Lincoln Kentucky they paid to are these
Secretly recorded tapes
Of a state senator calling his constituents Redmond
French with my redneck constituency got here and you know like
For Kentucky
And in Pennsylvania they insinuated that a democratic incumbent
Had spent $600 on an unpopular Viper
Do you remember the most
Kind of obscure local issue that you invested in
There is someone who sat on a Town Council
Who had voted to cancel the fireworks display
So Ohio gets $1000000 to Target
Michigan also $1000000 but to go after
20 seats
44 seats in New York
We spent about 1.4 million dollars
And the money kept
Flowing in all the way up until election day
And then all Chris could do was wait
Would his bet payoff
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Should come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solution
Strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org
Tell me about election night
We had a
A war room set up all the way
Really hate that term
So
It's election night November 2nd
And Chris and his team are sitting around the
The conference table in their offices
Laptops open
And they are tracking state election results basically by hand
Because at that point
You can't turn on CNN CNN figure out who's winning control the Iowa house
That we went we all had contacts on the ground
And we start tracking
Michigan-ohio York Texas
Maine that's Brothers everyone's a sign States
The track we had a
A spreadsheet
They huddled in that war room all night
I think around 5 a.m.
I walked across the street to my hotel
Tried to sleep for about 45 minutes shower came back
And the great thing about State Legislative races
It's like having two Christmases
Back-to-back because you have election night Pennsylvania houses Flint Michigan Healthy Ohio how Iowa houses Wisconsin
Texas houseboat
And then you have the next day cuz Alexa
Results just keep coming in for Wednesday November 3rd 2010
State capitals across the country will be more Republican
Any points is a Roaring Twenties one
I knew that Wednesday afternoon
That it was
It was historic even Beyond with red Maps goals were
And the entire country was buzzing about how the
Republican today
Taking back the house
Because of the Tea Party Revolution and backlash against Obamacare
And Chris is like
Yeah that is exciting
But what is more exciting is that the Republicans had
Also just gained nearly 700
Legislative seat
They flipped
21 State houses from
Democrat to Republican
So they ended up with majorities in both State Legislative Chambers
Which meant
That they would entirely on the redistricting process
What's the country
Chris had his eye on the lung
The 2010 election was the beginning
Not the end
It's all about what happened after
What happened was redistrict
Over the next couple of years one by one
Republican state legislatures
Did start to draw the map
So they work in their favor
They were helped by very sophisticated technology that lets you gerrymander down to the last alley way down to the last
And these new red Maps
Did their job
2012 democratic house candidates got 1.1 million more votes overall
Republicans
Dominated the house with 833
Majority
In Pennsylvania Republicans got about
Half the votes so you think they'd get about
The seats but no they got nearly three-quarters of the
And over the next
Two election Cycles
Steve's reliably swing States like Pennsylvania and Ohio and Michigan
Their Congressional
Stopped swinging
The JV team was picking the varsity
So now in many states
It's more like politicians
Pick their voters than voters pick their representative
Yeah I don't
I don't feel totally great about
Tyramine because like
It's it's brilliant
But it's not something that everybody is
Comfortable with
This kind of locks
Down
The democracy
In a way that
Doesn't
Feel like democracy
Well I don't feel bad I messed up
Quite often I do not feel bad I don't apologize
I mean there's so many variables in a given election
Troubling to me that P
Just wanted to say boom this is bad you've undermined democracy
Chris points to the 2018 midterm
He said book the Democrats have
A shot at retail
House this fall
These Maps
Really undermined democracy how could that be
He also points out anybody could have done that Democrats could have done it
I'm still not sure why they didn't
This is a mistake that the Democrats
Do not plan to repay
They now have their own big plans for 2020 not going to
Call it blue mapping but today
And look this
Is legal partisan gerrymandering is legal in every single state except two of them
Although this morning in case 1611
That could change
Maybe
The Supreme Court did pick up two cases this year about partisan Jerry
Which is an issue they have mostly avoided
They've said you know how do we even
Measure how much partes
Friendship is too much
Because you know elections are in here
Partisan
The Supreme Court is looking at this now because
Beat
Started to answer that question
They started to Gin up mathematical formulas
To measure partisan
And also because this is only likely going to get worse
Which may be why the lawyer's argument sort of sounded like a desperate
Cry for help
The only Institution
Dick and solve this problem
And the court is deciding right now actually if they will be the answer
Institution to solve it
Their opinions will be issued this month
And if the Supreme Court does step in and set a standard
It could turn the countries Maps
And
The elections website
If they don't
If you let this go if you say this is good we're not going to have a Judicial remedy for this problem
In 2020 you're going to have a festival of CopyCat gerrymandering the likes of which the
This country is never seen so in 2020
We could be looking at Varsity Jerry man
Except this time both teams are suited up
We always love to hear what you think of this show we post a link to every
Free episode on Facebook
Define despair and comment you can also find us on Twitter and Instagram at Planet Money or you can email us planet
Money at npr.org Today Show was produced by Sally Helm and Aviva dekornfeld are supervising producer is
Alex goldmark
Are status the show special thanks to Kelli Ward Michael McDonald Carol kuna home at the
Excellent book by David Daley about this topic with a link to it on our website I'm Noel King and I'm Karen Duffin
Thanks for listening