Quick note there is
A cuss word on Today Show
Hey hey what's up
Right now we're going to connect
Shortly yeah
Okay cool I'm sitting in a studio that he is connected to another Studio
K UT in Austin Texas and we're waiting on this ticket broker
To show up
And tell us the story of the 2000
15 Super Bowl
So got the tape rolling
Any second his voice should pop up
But then our producer Jess Chun burst
Back into the studio
Trying to get him on the phone he was standing out of cuties like I don't see any benefit from this
You like getting cold feet
What did he say
Just pulls out her phone's pulls up an email from the broker
I'm sitting outside the station but
I don't see any benefit that could come from this thank you for your time and energy but I have to decline for my
Leon Saturday
Decline
For my own sanity hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Kenny Malone
Noel King
And Super Bowl is this weekend it's the Eagles versus the past
The Super Bowl is
Of course a huge economy in and of itself
And nowhere is this more visible than in one
Crazy
Market
Ticket sales
Usually the Super Bowl is a bonanza for professional ticket sales
People usually
But the 2015 Super Bowl
Was very good
And this is the reason no one wants to talk about
Because in the two weeks leading up to
The game there was a
Catastrophic
Market collapse in mini
Brokers went belly up tickets vanished Into Thin Air
Companies had to Shell out millions of dollars to try and fix
The great Super Bowl ticket collapse
Today on the show we're going to try and figure out what happened and
We did find somebody willing to tell us about this
From the inside
And so we're to talk about like on air because it's like one of those things is
Do we even want to talk about
Super Bowl 49 ever again
Support for this podcast
In the following message come from the this week in Google podcast
Stat twit.tv
Every week
Leo Laporte
Jeff Jarvis and Stacey Higginbotham
Talk Tech
Media and privacy
The unapologetically question
Google Amazon Twitter Facebook and other Tech Giants are on the right track
Subscribe to this weekend
Google on your favorite
Or it's wet. TV / twig
I'm going to have you start by just saying your name it's Ray
Chateau s8000 how should we identify you devoted
Seattle Seahawks fan
That works for me
Reese Auto has been a Seahawks
Season ticket holder since 90
Teen 76 that is
The first year there was
Not in the last 15 years the Seahawks have been very good
But in the beginning they were very bad
Re-watch
And cheered
And dealt with decades
Ups and down
So it's a 2014 mm
15 C's in any shaping up to be like
Mediocre at
Six games in and the sea
Seahawks had a mideling record
Being raised a loyal fan and like many loyal fans
He just had a
Feeling that maybe the Seahawks could turn it around
And even though the Super Bowl was months away
Re-found a ticket
Who offered
Pretty straightforward.
If Ray paid like a deposit
This guy
Would go and get him a ticket
For the Super Bowl
If the Seahawks made
If they don't make it
Ray loses the deposit but
He decides it's worth the risk
Tilray put the money down couple hundred bucks
And his team turned the season around they make
The playoffs
Internet what is 14 days before the 2015 Super Bowl
The Seattle Seahawks are playing the Green Bay Packer
Ray was at this game watching
The Seahawks
And this game
It's part of the day that's known as Championship Sunday because it's the day we find out which teams
Will be in the Super
And the Seahawks
Force the Packers
Overtime
And they won this improbable game
And are now going to the Superbowl
5 in
Is really just unbelievable
And it's an extra sweet for you because you happen to know
That you were going to get to go and follow this improbable run
Absolutely
The best part of this
Dealray had made with the broke
Was not just that he was getting 2 tickets
The Super Bowl
The broker was going to sell them to him
Face value
$800 a day
Which sounds like a lot to me but it is a steel for sale
Repay the broker for two tickets
And the broker is like
Congratulations you are going
Super Bowl 4
In Glendale Arizona
We will have your tickets in hand
In person
The day before
Everybody wins
But
Here's a twist
You know the ticket broker who wouldn't talk to us in the interest of his own sanity
That guy was raised ticket broker
And wasn't a scammer
He wasn't trying to defraud right
But would he enraged didn't know yet
Was that they had just jumped into one of the most UPS
Side down bass-ackwards ticket markets in Super Bowl history
Would you say you are a leading expert
In ticket mark
Without sounding pompous yes
I think I've done a lot of work in tickets
This is Pascal
Preserve economix at the University of Victoria
And I've been studying ticket markets for the past 20 years
Super Bowl tickets
Are already a weird Market
Because if you're not an NFL player or an NFL
Spell sponsor or
A very very lucky
A season ticket holder for a Super Bowl team
You almost have no chance of getting a suit
Not directly
It's not for face value
On the primary mark
So the market is
Secondary Market the resale Mart
And Pascal says if you study that resale market like he does
Ticket prices have followed a very
Predictable pattern yes so if you look at the past
A few years that would be the general pattern for the Super Bowl definitely but also for many other sports
We call these markets perishable good and the idea is that once the event starts
The value of your ticket goes down dramatically
Pascal says that
For the Super Bowl what the pattern looks like is this
14 days before the big game the day we find out which two teams will be
Keep playing
Ticket prices start to go up
The most exuberant fans are buying tickets there
The driving the price up and then we get closer to the game
The prices start
To drop
Because it because it
Imagine you're a fan
You didn't buy your
Take it yet and Euphoria is wearing off
And you're looking at all hotels are $1,000 a night
And the flight to 1200 bucks
Anythink
I don't really need to go to the zoo
And at the same time
Ticket sellers art
Once this game start
This ticket I have
Is nothing more than a souvenir
I had better by John
And then last few days then you have a Southern drawl
What is the I feel like if we see it often there should be a name for this
Is there like a does it have a cool economics name
Do you want to name it to have any suggestions last minute deep or something like that
The last minute dip is fine with me I it also sounds like
What you bring
To a Superbowl party when someone's like oh by the way can
Can you bring something on my
No I don't have anything I guess I can bring a dip at the last minute
Just about every part of the Super Bowl ticket economy is built on this pattern holding
14 days out prices are going to go up and then there will be this last minute
All of the
Professionals in the ticket industry
Are betting on me
So why the Seahawks
Where in Seattle winning their way in
3000 miles away in New York City
Brett Goldberg
Is obsessively
Watching TV
So the second the Seahawks won
Order start
Flying in
Like crazy
What is the co CEO of a company called
Tickpick
Did you want to share your unofficial tagline or is that an off mic only
Oh that one
I was about to say when most people know what stuff all this so
What do you do
Instead of giving in the Longwood an answer
We're like step up a better
Beretta course of the whole explanation
Infer why he thinks
Side is better but
Rent is one of the
Few people we found
Who's willing to talk about 2015 from the inside
And if you're trying to figure out where Brett sits in this
Chicken ecosystem
He and his website are a middleman be
Between the fans and the ticket
Bretelles is one of the reasons the Superbowl is
Particularly
Is the 14 days before the game when that demand
Ticket starts to spike
The majority of the tickets
Are not out into the world yet
The NFL is still holding on to ticket waiting to release them two teams and
Players and
Maybe sponsors
And it takes a while for those two
To get out onto the secondary Market
So when the Championship Sunday
With the vast majority of
People are actually
Buying from Brett Goldbergs website and other websites like bread
Is the promise
I would take it
Get from a broker
There are two kinds of tick
First
They're the ones who
Know what they're doing
Sell you a ticket and they know it
Exactly where it's going to come for
They know a guy who's
Company somehow gets tickets
And there's going to be an extra one
And that's the ticket the broker is selling you
And then there is the other type
Type and sometimes you'll hear these guys called speculate
Diesel you would take care of the promise if it's
Tickets and then they go hustle they go find one for you
But when they sold it to you they didn't know exactly where it was coming from
And it may not have been cleared to you
But you haven't actually bought a realtor
Now this seems
Crazy
Like it's an invisible ticket
But it is something that happens in financial markets both cases
Are versions of with called a naked
Short sale yet when you're convinced prices will go down
You offer something for sale that you don't own yet but you
You promised that you
You will get it and you'll deliver it later
Now that was what was going on in this big secondary Market
And also on Brett's website
Were you okay with people using your website to speculate
In hindsight
Definitely not
But we have no reason to believe that
There were problems
Us someone wants
If you get it in writing
You're going to feel
You're obligated to do this
The industry the resale industry as
As a whole
Is built on trust
These are Brokers livelihood
And they're going to sell these order
And the reason this worked fine
For the Super Bowl 4 years
Is because ticket prices always took
That last
And the salt and Brokers mines were
I can sell this at $2,000
And
Couple days before this
Super Bowl I could buy it
$1,500
Maybe a thousand
This is the easiest $500 of my life
The easiest
$500
Of your
Set a countdown is it 14 days
14 days until the Super Bowl
And there is a real sense that we are truly going to see the two best teams
Prices are still going up 13 days
Until the Superbowl 3012 Tesla
Three and a half thousand
This is kind of in line with the trends
I'm tracking this like a hardcore
Everyday every hour I'm refreshing all rap
One week
Until the Super Bowl prices are still going I had never in our history
Kind of seen it push it
$4,000
5000 6060
5 days
Until the Super Bowl on StubHub they start at more than $7,000
And now it's
Clear something is going on
Ticket prices we've been reporting for the Super Bowl already at a record high today or Seahawks
Andres Auto
Is watching all of it
Remember he bought his tickets for $800 I'm thinking man I got a good deal with this option
It's true
Ray doesn't have his actual physical paper ticket
It yet but he's thinking look
I already paid for it
It must be my ticket and I was just smart enough
To lock in a really great price were you thinking like maybe I should sell this took
Across your mind but I
Pretty devoted to going this is my first Superbowl
Yeah I got to go
Brett Goldberg on the other hand.
Air ticket middle name
He's been watching these prices
Go up and
4 days
He is been
Worried and info
For me I was a little late but red flags went up like
What is going on
This is
This is really scary just to be clear I mean you're making a cut of sales
It seems like a great thing the prices are going
But you're saying there's something to be alarmed about yeah
Because of the ticket speculators
Because of the naked shorts
I was not aware how exposed we were but I was aware there was exposed
Misses when I start
Pair like
I need to be
Prepared
That some of the shorts may not get
It felt so what are you saying is
Brent knew that some of the people who
Who sold tickets early on for like two grand on his website
They did not have a clue where those tickets were going to come from
They assume just like every year that they buy them during the last minute tip
But now there was no dipping
It was just speaking
That we talk to as many people as we could
About y2000
Why ticket prices went up
Instead of down
And here's what we can piece together
Super Bowl 49
Was this
Tornado
Compounding Factor
Here's that sent prices
For starters it seems like brokers
Completely underestimated how many people wanted to go to this game
Here's why
The Patriots
Are always in the Super Bowl
And the Seahawks had just won their first ever Super Bowl the year before
So logically the Brokers are thinking that people are going to be less interested this time
And it appears
They got that very wrong
Secondly the reports from the ground are that the NFL released some of the tick
It's later
10 brokers
Expected later than usual
This made them nervous
This made them willing
To pay more for the
That were available and may have driven the price up
Further
And the final factor is that
It looks like 2008
15 with a year that so many people
People piled into the ticket speculation game
Victor bubble just
They sold
Way more tickets
Promises that make
Could possibly deliver
The market was
Built on naked short-selling
In a market like that
Is a bomb
Waiting to go off
Just days now from the biggest
How big games the fans
All to sending here on the greater Phoenix
The Super Bowl is now
3 days away
Until
Prices are through the roof
Thousands of people are starting to show up in Glendale Arizona thinking they bought
Super Bowl tickets ahead of time
+ 2500 miles away
@brett Goldberg's office in New York City
The first Domino
False yes Thursday was the
What was the first time I realized that
One of our sellers wasn't going to
A call comes in to
Tickpick office
It is a broker
Saying essentially
I give up
I know I sold someone a ticket on
Website for like 2500 bucks
But it's crazy out here
78 Grand I can't find
Anythinganywhere cheap enough to make this work
We're sucking worried we're nervous
I mean I so Thursday when that call came in
I started running the books and I said okay
Worst case
Rick Goldberg website that helps sell about 200 Super Bowl tickets
And now he starts looking at every single ticket perch
Like who sold this ticket do I know this person do I trust this person
Also that was Michael
Concern is for people who have bought tickets at $2,000
Brokers. Are in a gallon
Cricket 1800
And how the heck are these Brokers going to fill these orders
We need to fill these orders
Never memberpress himself is not a broker his job is not
To go and buy tickets and then sell the
But imagine if
You're that fat
You bought it
YouTube Red
You are going to blame Brett just as much as you're going to blame the broker
Build on your own
Sabrett is getting desk
He is sending guys to Arizona
With cash
Iwired
$50,000 in cash
To one of my guys I was going there
So that we can start start buying tickets
It's as well basically
Feeling that person's backpack in cash
Returning to dab
Broker more or less right we need a booty to buy tickets and to make matters worse
StubHub which is Brett's big competitor
Is being forced
To do the same thing
Put on a market-moving scale
StubHub spends millions of dollars making up for
Busted short sales on their website
They get enough tickets to get every single one of their customers into the Super
Brett says
For the tickets that are left
That only drive the price up more
And he simply could not afford to do
Do the same thing for
His customers
Company was too new
He did not have it
Kind of money
Bought up as many tickets
Secret Ford
He says in total about 30 orders went bust
He was able to fill about half of
And for the rest of the fans
Just going to have to reimburse them
T travel they paid for
And then give them about it
200% refund
Which is still cheaper than buying the tickets
But he had to start making
King some very difficult
Difficult phone call
I ministered this was like the
The worst day of my life
Career working ever
Like you having to call someone to tell him to not get on a plane right now
When you'd like
The reason why we created business was to send people to get tickets for events
Psoriasis
Is the exact opposite
And so we're to talk about like on air because it's like one of those things it's like
Do we even want to talk about Super Bowl XLIX ever again
Sphere
Emotions and how we get it brings up a lot like the plumber like
Cry but I could cry thinking about like what we had to do to something
Calls like this were going out
All over
2 days before the Super Bowl
Seahawks Super
Fan race Auto
How does hotel booked in Arizona
He and his wife
Packed and ready to leave the next morning
After breakfast
He opens his laptop
And there's an email
From his broke
And its subject line what
Atwells Bobby Super Bowl tickets
You see it and what are you like before you can open it what do you think
I got all know said sorry guys I don't have tickets
I don't know if I'm going to have much of a business but I will
And I'll give you your money back plus 20% and
Sorry
You didn't throw the laptop across the room or anyting
It was a
A quiet
Anger
The quiet anger yeah kind of a disappointment and anger
The broker gave right his money back plus a couple extra hundred bucks to say
I am so sorry
Rain is wife talked it over they were very bummed but they decided they were going to drive to Arizona anyway
Just be part of the festivities races the scene in Arizona
It was bizarre
They were obviously
Fans but then there were these like
Light clusters
Of miserable desperate
Almost like Panhandle
Holding up
These homemade signs
Cardboard signs people
Sitting in the middle of the crowd just watching people walk by into the pep rally
With their kids with them trying to
Stir some sympathy and it was just like willing to pay $10,000
I guess not
Good Lord
It was just insanity
Sir and his wife getting the car they leave Arizona and they drive to
California to raise parents house to watch the action
And I don't know if you remember Super Bowl 40
But the Seahawks
Had the ball
With a chance to win the game
From like a yard away from
From the endzone
For the entire country it seemed as if they were about
To win the Super
Russell Wilson
Seahawks
Chose to throw the ball
Run it
And they lost
They threw an interception after the interception in my mouth
Dropped open
In disbelief
And the next thing I turn in my wife
And go
My God
I can't imagine being at this game
Can you think of what the drive home would have been like
I mean in some ways
Maybe maybe you have these tickets short-sellers to thank for
Avoiding a lot of misery
The artist the only reason I didn't know I can laugh about it and
And you know
Just let it go it's a fact that it was such a difficult ending for the Seattle fans
Are the Super Bowl is days away and after all this you may be wondering
Could this happen again this year
We will tell you
Stick with us
Support for this podcast
In the following message come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing Solutions disa
Support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf
. org
When the 2050
Teen ticket Bubble Burst
There were a lot of pissed off
People they had paid
Hotels they
Book airline tickets some of them had already
Shown up
To Arizona
And a lot of those pissed off people
Got in touch with a man
Name of Bob Ferguson you're making me go back in time to this
Painful experience during a Seahawks jersey right now general for the
The state of Washington
He was wearing that Seahawks jersey in his office
He's a huge fan
Mm
15 Super Bowl his tickets worked out fine but
Outside of the stadium
He kept running in
The devastated fan
After devastated fan
Bob eventually went after upper
Particularly
Egregious ticket broker who wasn't even reimbursing
When their tickets.
And so because there were lawsuits and
A lot of bad press and a really expensive
Meltdown
The Super Bowl ticket Market does seem to be safer today
Companies like StubHub and tick
Texas ticket middlemen
Have cracked down on
Tickets back in
Getting that require anybody who wants to sell a Super Bowl ticket
To either have a proof of purchase
Or to be a certified trusted broker with a history of delivering on Super Bowl ticket
It promises
Bob Ferguson Attorney General for washing
Chicken says you should still be pretty careful when making a giant
Purchase like this
And if it falls through
You may have recourse
You may be able to file a lawsuit
Speaking of which before I let Bob go
I had to ask him about something
It stuck out to me
Hey I noticed in the lawsuit
The complaint
There's a little flowery language around the Seahawks quote-unquote thrilling victory over the Green Bay Packers to advance to the super
Super Bowl
Did you put that in there I just didn't spend that sounds like something I would do it yes yeah
Quick note we did reach out to the NFL for
This episode and they did not receive
Today's episode was produced by Jess Chung or supervising
Producer is Alex goldmark
Brian or status Planet Money Saturday
Thanks this week to Michael Irvin
A Patriots fan who also went up without a ticket yes just did happen to Patriots fans to
As far as we can tell it's maybe the only bad thing that's ever happened to Patriots fans
Special things this week
2 Seahawks fan Eric jacks
Two pointed us towards the story in the first
I'm Kenny Malone and I'm Noel King thanks for listening