Support for this in
NPR Podcast
The following message
Come from the
Offering services from
Threading tube
Printing to mailbox
And instead of closing
This Memorial Day we
May 24th and
The UPS Store
He's doing another thing
All together
Opening
The UPS Store
Every angle
For small business
And of course shipping
I doubt they're going to let me in but I'm going to ask
I'm driving up to a private golf course about an hour north of Manhattan and before they let you and you have to stop
Guard house
Hi how are you
Hey I'm I am a reporter with NPR and I'm doing a story about
The 13th hole on this golf course is there any chance that I can just look at that
It goes away
Ask his boss
Comes back and tells me nope I'm sorry you need an appointment okay no problem
Thank you the reason Karen was at this golf course
It was because
We heard that something
It's our had happened on that 13
It was during a charity golf tournament
Back in 2000
And while I never did get into that Golf Course
We did manage to find someone who has not only
Qingdao 13th hole she was actually there during the
Entire anthem
How many charity golf tournaments would you say you think you've been to in your life
I've probably been to ya dozens of them if not I'm hundreds
This is Patricia Hannigan
She writes about golf including
Charity events
Any other of those that you've been to ended quite like this
Absolutely not
Patricia tells me
The day of this charity golf tournament it was a kind of muggy day this is
August
And it started out like a normal charity golf tournament
The early
The crowd there was a group of hostesses there and I saw them they were a bunch of implausibly beautiful girls also
Therefore the tournament you had
The basketball players and you had
The guys food
Had a certain look
But said heads
Anuradha
She declined to describe what the hedge funds are looking
We can assume it probably meant
Rich people
And that is not uncommon for
Charity golf tournament
However if the basketball players is a little unusual
But not for this event
Because this was a fundraiser for the Alonzo Mourning
Family found
If you do not know
Who wants a warning is I'm sorry for you
She's one of the greatest basketball players of all time he play for the Miami Heat
Is a 7 time
All-Star he won a championship
Did she really stop
The event kicks off and Patricia
Heads out to the course
And decides
She's going to spend the entire day at the 13th hole
That
13th hole
Which was the whole with the waterfall and the hold it was designated for this million-dollar shootout
Dollar shoot
Now this is apparently a staple of rich people golf
Razors if you donate a little bit of extra money then there is a designated hole where
Get hole in one
You win a million bucks
The odds of an amateur golfer doing that getting a hole-in-one I am told Art
12000 to 1
But just in case it does
Happened Patricia wants to be there
So she sits down at the 13th hole and starts watching
Sweetheart first golfer of
Stay up
Tr4a
After golfer comes through terrible shot
And it does not get a hole-in-one
Patricia sits there for a very long time
I have to say it had been getting a little bit
Doll
She's seen about seven or eight groups
Scott's through when it's one guy walks up to the tee and sort of seemed a little bit more like um
Maybe a Pioneer in the field that's for that way but what does that mean a Pioneer in the field and perhaps he'd been
Doing whatever it was he was doing for 4
Quite a long time
Everything he's older
Oh boy I don't like
This is the nicest way I've ever heard
I called old
Anyway
The man's name was Martin Greenberg
And he walks
Up to the Tee Martin Greenberg
Pioneer in his field
All Odds
Martin Greenberg
Hits a hole-in-one on the million-dollar
13 tall
And all my playing
I've never witnessed a hole in one
Even been at a tournament I think we're anyone made it home
How do people celebrate on a golf course do you do people clap and scream and shout or is that not
Okay
You got the golf clap
Which is kind of a restrained
Constipated like that
But not today people were jumping
And hugging because Martin Greenberg had just one
$1000000
Orso at
I think it was oh gosh it was
Couple of weeks before I really heard that there's something had gone
A little bit
Arrive with us
Award the million-dollar
Prize
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I Am Karen Duffin and I'm Kenny Malone and
The thing that went a little awry on that Golf Course
Wound up hitting millionaires against Millionaires and turned into a national scale
Today on the show
How that Scandal takes us to a pool of money
So prone to abuse that the government gave it its
Very own
Special set-up
And also how the Fallout over that hole in one
Magistrate
All the way
To the White House
This message comes from in
NPR sponsor
The only data warehouse built for the
Today organizations need the
Rapid data
Inside Springs
To stay a step ahead of the
With snow
You can instantly and infinitely
Play scale your data warehouse with the touch of a button
Delivering deep insights at any time
For all user
Start your journey
Towards data-driven decision
Snowflake.
Flash NPR
If someone hits a hole-in-one
In a charity golf turn
There is a possibility
Mark Gilmartin
Will show up
Are you like the only person at the charity golf tournament crying while everyone else is
Celebrate
Well
I guess in theory that's why I don't attend a lot of them because I like to cry behind closed doors
Fart
Marker in the company called hole in one
International
That specializes
Hole in one
Insurance we do about 10 to 15 thousand
Tournaments a Year events a year
Really yeah
That is so many more than I thought you were going to say
Got to make a living Karen
Back in 2010 Mark gilmartin's company was hired to ensure Alonzo Mourning sculpture
So
That day
Market
There has been a hole-in-one
They need to verify the claim
And then there is
Like a hole-in-one investor
Mark get the video of the hole-in-one he gets affidavits from people
Who witnessed it
Including a cop who's
Job was to stand at the 13th hole the entire day
For a million dollars they have to have a law enforcement officer witness it which they did
Mark also send an investigator to the course to meet with the man who hit the hole in one
Martin Greenberg
They escorted him out to
The whole world made a hole-in-one
And they asked him to identify the spot where he hid it from
Martin Greenberg points to the team Ark
Where's the place you're supposed to hit the ball from
And when the investigator measures
The tee markers are 150 yards from the
And this is critic
Because the rule from the insurance company is that
If the person hits from any closer than 150
2 yards
The insurance company does not have to
It it's all over our contract
It's all over the Box we ship the signs in its on the sign itself
You know we do everything possible to try and alert
The person that setting up that hole
So Mark takes all of this evidence back to what
We like to imagine must be some like hole-in-one in the
Station lab and
He goes to the evidence and
Looking good everything is checking out
But then
He pulls up that video of the Holy
And in the Hollywood version of
This is where the
Ominous music would start
Playing and Mark would look up from that video
And say
God
The yardage that yardage was quite a bit substantially shorter than 150 yards
The video showed Martin Greenberg hitting the hole in one
From tee markers that were set at only 100
39 yards
But after the event when the investigator measures
Those same team markers
We're at 100 and
50 yard
That means
It's sometime
Between the actual hole-in-one in the hole-in-one investigation
Those tee markers were
Move
After the event
Back
I have tried so hard to figure out who set up that tea and who moved it back
Serial season 4 anybody call me
Sadly I do not know
Because Martin
And his lawyers and actually Alonzo Mourning none of them would talk to
And to be clear
We are not a legend
Did Martin Greenberg or anyone else did anything intentionally deceptive here
But here is a theory that sources have proposed
To us about how this
Might have had
A hole-in-one
Is just
So rare
Maybe whoever was in charge of setting up the tea
Tease
Was just a little too casual about
He might have delegated that to someone else
Sue delegated it to someone else
Who forgot to tell their dog to delegated
To someone else
Alright kids listen up delegate delegate clearly
To the T get set up in the wrong place
Ends and the golf staff innocently move those
T markers
Back 250 yards for the next day
Or
Maybe somebody instigates a million-dollar hole-in-one cover up
We do not know
What we do know
For sure
Is it someone owed Martin Greenberg
$1000000
And it was not
The insurance
And this case we had to deny the claim based on the artist who was that the end of it for you
And then they pick it up from there
Any attorneys get involved right then everybody start singing everybody
And sure enough
Martin Greenberg
Starts
And this
Turns into a lawsuit that got so complicated
I had to make like
Serial killer flowchart out of Post-it notes across my cubicle just to sort out how it got
This is true it looks like Karen is like about to catch the zodiac
That's nextaff
Martin Greenberg sued
The Alonzo Mourning Foundation
The event management company
The hole-in-one Insurance Company
And
The company that owns
The golf course
The Trump
National
Golf Club
The owner of which of course
Is President Donald J Trump
And when the lawsuit dust
Settled
Martin Greenberg did get paid
By the Alonzo Mourning foundation and the
Foundation
Those private Foundation
Paid into Martin Greenberg private Foundation
But here's the thing
That improbable hole-in-one
Mysterious moving tee marker the
Hole-in-one investigators
It all could have just been
Wacky rig
Person golf
Except
The actual investigators started
New York attorney general
Has just announced the lawsuit
Against
The Donald J Trump Foundation
You've also got
Referral letter sent
To the IRS and
The Federal Election Commission
What happened to break
What's the New York
Attorney general found
At the 13th hole
Support also comes
From fidelity
As a Fidelity wealth
You get a dedicated advice
To help grow and protect you
Find ways to minimize the impact
Taxes and make
Clear recommendation
For your full fight
Learn more
Fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage services
LLC
President Trump
Paid his portion of the million-dollar hole-in-one settlement from his private Foundation
The Donald J Trump Foundation
He opened this foundation in 1989 and has used it to donate money all kinds of
Things like
The United Way the
New York Police Athletic League the Metropolitan
Art
His smallest donation ever
$7
Boy Scouts of America yes that is
$7 not 7000
And one of his biggest donations
And $64,000
To something that I took Kenny to see in person
We're standing
I'm a very busy Corner in Manhattan
On the edge of Central Park
And somewhere around here is one of his biggest donations ever
Hi-5 donation
Well I see some pigeons I see some art Etsy
This China founded
This mountain is in front of the famous Plaza Hotel
And back in 1989 Donald Trump own The Plaza Hotel and this Fountain was crumbling
And technically the fountain belong
What's the city of New York
But they didn't want to
Fix it so local businesses pitched in money including a big donation from the trunk found a
And this is
Arguably how philanthropy is supposed to
We agree to give
Private foundations a tax break we agree to reduce our tax return
On the promise
That
These philanthropists will use that money to benefit Society
I'm sure this Fountain benefited Trump's hotel
But also the rest of us including apparently Kenny Kenny Malone might be taking out his
Socks and waiting into the fountain
This Fountain this donation and
All of Trumps donations they are being scrutinized
Much more heavily now that he is present
And this is how the New York
Attorney general got interested in
And how Donald Trump
Settled that
Million-dollar hole-in-one
Debacle
What we are alleging is that
This
Trump Foundation
Violated a number of laws
Of the state of New York that govern the way
Foundation a non-profit
Corporation
Is required to govern itself this is the New York attorney general Barbara Underwood on
CNN
Talking about the lawsuit against
The Trump Foundation
The money
Of that
Foundation was
Distributed for
Impermissible purpose
Personal purposes
Business purposes
Political campaign purposes rather than what happened on the 13th hole
She argues
Is one of those impermissible
Martin Greenberg
Eric the guy who got the hole in one
He sued Donald Trump's Golf Course
Which is one of Trump's businesses
But then Donald Trump
Pay the legal settlement
Farthest hole-in-one with his tax
Exempt from
Foundation
The Attorney General claims that this is a violation that is known as
Self-dealing
Which just means that you
You cannot use your pool of tax-exempt
Philanthropic money
As your own personal or business
There are several other charges as well in this way
Trump by-the-way denies wrong
He also declined to comment for our story
This lawsuit is still pending it is also been referred to the IRS and the
Federal Election Commission
So we don't know what
But
What all of this got us
Curious about
Was this
Thing called a private Foundation
How many
Are there
Do other people do questionable stuff with their private foundations like what are you even allowed to do with
So we started looking into the laws around private foundations
It got a little complicated
But then we stumbled across
The official podcast of the Internal Revenue Service
Which is amazing
The following is a fictitious discussion between coat the knowledgeable straight-talking IRS Revenue agent
From the website
In case you want to hear this entire thing
This episode is titled
The wonderful world of foundation classes
Hey coach
It's been awhile
I'm glad to be back
Can I still request about coach
Yeah what is he is he a coach and what is he a coach of his attacks coach
Is named coach what is the cheese attacks coach for nonprofit
No
Anyway
If you listen to coach
Long enough what you will learn is that
Private foundations are their very own category of nonprofit
Basically they're defined as a type of nonprofit where you have one or a few donors
Putting money into a tax exempt
Pool and
Private foundations
The government has decided
Quite a bit of
Extra babysit
Right coach
Are subject to a number of anti-abuse rules and excise tax
If it don't apply to public charities
This extra scrutiny date back
The
When Congress discovered that private foundations were abusing their tax-exempt status more than any other kinds of
Nonprofits
People were doing things like
Putting their money tax-free into their Foundation
And then lending themselves that Ma
Or maybe they would put their family on the board
And then they would have a board meeting
On the beach in the Bahamas
Congress was also worried that wealthy people were using their packs
Exempt money to gain too much power over politics
And socially
And so in 1969 the government said
Private foundations
You get more rules
Then all other nonprofit
But it is of course
One thing to say
Say that private foundations
Need more monitoring
It is another to
Actually have enough resources to
To do that monitoring
Thousand or more
Foundations and then you have another
1.5 million nonprofits all of which are filing tax returns
This is David Callahan
He runs a publication called inside fillet
And you have a small
Comparatively small staff of
IRS
Officials are supposed to keep track of all that
And so
We don't really know how many of them are fully complying with the rules
They're actually now 109
Thousand
Private Foundation
Any IRS has just
Agents
Dedicated to monitor
The number of staff
Set the IRS has for monitoring all nonprofit
It's has been try
Trending down
And so have the number of
Nevada state
Thanks for
Probably most Charities are out there doing great work my senses the Trump Foundation is an outlier
On the other hand who really knows
Because the foundations
And of America receives a little scrutiny
It's hard to think that the Trump Foundation would have ever been
Crackdown on if he hadn't run for president
Yap certainly would not have
Then there would not have been scrutiny of the Trump Foundation
So if you have a private foundation and
Who knows maybe one day you want to run
For president
You should probably make sure that your you know your house is in order
And luckily
We know
Exactly
Who can help you
Hey coach
Our time's up
If we want to know more about this topic what can we do
Publication 557 tax-exempt status for your organization has an exhausted
Some would say exhausting
Discussion of foundation classifications
A huge thanks to David fahrenthold of the Washington Post
Who's excellent reporting on the Trump Foundation informed the entire story you can follow Planet Money on Twitter
And Instagram we are at Planet Money we are also on
Facebook today's episode was produced by at least a cigar say and
Sally Helm Alex goldmark is our supervising producer Brian is our editor
Our lodestar
Special thanks to Felicia Burnett and all the people who helped me understand private foundations including
David Hammack Norman silver Paul fineberg and Stanley Katz
I am Karen Duffin I'm coming alone thanks for listening