Just a quick note Today Show is a rerun it originally aired back in 2006
Also there is a new update at the end of the show
It's a good update
Okay so
Can you read me the title of the paper
Feeling the future
Experimental evidence
For anomalous retroactive influences
On cognition and Fa
Feeling a future meaning like people can see into
Basically ESP
ESP
We're talking to Brian nosek
He's a psychologist
City University of Georgia
Missy public where
In the Journal of Personality and Social Psychology
I'd like a top turn on the
That's right
Peer-reviewed
Peer-reviewed extensively
This paper came out in two thousand eleven
Brian nosek like a lot of psycho
Just thought
What is going on
Like there's no way that
But then again
Here is this paper
Describing not just one experiment
But nine
Different XP
Rhino success some of them are really pretty convincing even today when you flip through the paper
The main site hypothesis was that participants will be able to identify the position of the hidden pictures significantly more often than
In one experiment he says people were told to stare at this
Computer screen
And are told that an image
Was going to appear on either the right side or the left side
And they were asked to guess
Which side
Like looking to the Future
Which side do you think the image is going to
And people do okay on this they do better in this study than if
They just been random chat
This paper was published by a scientist that
Cornell univ
A researcher who is really well worth
And when Brian nosek read the paper
There did not seem to be any obvious problem with
The paper is beautiful
It follows all the rules
Of what one does
Doesn't look really beautiful way
This ESP paper through the field into really a crisis
Because nothing says
They're basically two possible explanations
Either
We have to
Conclude that USPS true because there's these 9 studies that show it
Or we have to change our beliefs
About the right ways to do science
Nothing is going with option
And not just for psychology
For biology economics
32nd St Pub
The policy medical decisions
She thinks there's something wrong with the way we're do
Doing science
Today on the show
Is something rotten at the heart of science is ESP real
I hope he is miserable
I need
Magazine
Discus
Support for this podcast
In the following message
It's come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org
ESP research paper raise this very deep questions
For science
In general
If It's Paper is wrong but the researcher followed all the rules and experimental protocols
What else out there
What about all those
Thousands and thousands of other studies
You know just walk through and research
Library University
UC shelves and shelves of bound volumes of
Going back decades
Full of big important experiments like hey we cloned a sheep
All that stuff you read the newspaper
Oat bran
Reducing the risk of heart attack
ARP if you want to get somebody's attention whisper in their right ear
That probably works better than the left
How much of the stuff in those books
Is just wrong
No sex after that ESP paper comes out
No one's really sure people are saying
Oh there is a huge problem or no there's no problem at all what are you talking about
And it's all speculation
And we just don't have any data
Brian I've been thinking about this stuff for a long
ESP study came out
Everybody else in the field with suddenly thinking about
Inotia figured maybe this is my moment to do so
To get to the bottom of the
He decides to do this thing that
It's supposed to be part of the whole normal scientific
But rarely actually gets
He decides he's going to try to repeat
A bunch of
Experiments redo them original papers look at how the researchers did the experiment
And try to replicate
See if it actually holds up
Joseph Lampkin repeat A1c
Set repeating study after study after study
We're not going to put aside all of our active research in order to try to replicate a bunch of studies in r
Literally just don't have the time to do it with the resources I couldn't that just be your work
Because grad students in my lab would never get jobs
Sonos it wasn't sure who else was going to join him
I mean repeating work that is already been done
Is not how you get
Tenure
You know you putting all this work
And if you confirm the original results
Aaron's going to be like yeah we knew that
Good friend figured what the heck
To try to find enough research
Interested to do that thing to repeat a lots and lots of it
So we sent out an email to people in the field saying are you interested you want to join this effort
Oh and doesn't the people
Instantly a joint there a lot of people
All that were interested in this issue and so it was like oh wow that's can really be a project
In fact there's so much interest that no 6 decides
We're going to redo 100 experiments
Nice big round impressive number
Any decides where to take them from the top journals
Free the top psychology
And so in 2012 hundreds of researchers in Labs all over the place
Get to work
Start redoing all these experiments
Michigan State
David Johnson and his colleagues were trying to repeat this experiment that had shown
People wash their hands
They make less severe moral judge
We had to have our participants
Wash their hands and it had to be
Done in a way that didn't Dart draw tension to the fact that they were washing their hands
In Virginia researchers were testing what you can think of is
The afternoon treat
Ej masicampo at wake forest university
He did the original
Search Lee showed that
A
Sugar boost
So drinking a sugary lemonade
Mixed people
Engage more effortful decision-making
If you're tired drinking something with a bunch of sugar in it helps you think harder
Makes sense but is it true
The researchers doing the replications tried to repeat the experiment exactly
They filed the original protocols
As closely as they
If the original sugary beverage experiment gave the stew
Lemonade
When they repeated it
One by one the researchers finish their work
Work submitted the result
But Brian nosek didn't look at any of those results while the project was
So when did you first see the results
It was the
Day we hit 100 studies completed
We shut down the party
We're done
We had a hundred
Someone else have been keeping a spreadsheet
Tracking all the replica
I know sex finally looks at the spreadsheet
That he just goes down the list you know there are these are these hundred studies
And for each one he answers this basic question
Did it confirm the original
Yes or no just goes down the list yes
Yes no
And then just at get to the end and count up
39 yeses
M61 News
So you found that of these hundreds that is in most of them they did not
Confirm the original
Write Jacob this is amazing
Like you know I was a physics major I want
Went to grad school like
I spent a bunch a Time
In the research
Walking past all these bound volumes of Journal article
For sure if you would ask me back then
Like if I thought the findings in them were more likely to be true than Falls I would say yes definitely
Anytime like 60% could not be replica
Like that lemonade experiment
The hand washing
Experiment neither of those could be replicated
Yet to be honest this number this 39 yeses and 60 Windows Vista number right here is why I wanted to do
May I found it
I found it completely shocked
Nintendo
Didn't know what to make
Yeah
Well I
I don't I don't know what I thought is more of
Oh how the heck did that happen
How do bunch of scientific study
Seem to follow
All the rules of the scientific
And make it into peer review journal
How is it pause
Oh that's so many of them seem to be wrong
First thing to say this is not about
Fraud I mean sure
They're examples out there of researchers just straight-up faking their results but that's not what's going on here
She thinks what is going on here is something really
More interesting
Wednesday ideas for WhatsApp
Is that a lot of what you are seeing in the journey
Are flukes
Statistical
Here let me give you an example this is from a little experiment I did this morning
Flipping a coin
Heads
Had the gun
Tell
Blue Hats
Has again
I flipped it 10 times Jacob
9 * I got heads only one tails
If you do this to tistical analysis you do for like a drug trial or any scientist
This looks like a remarkable results
Is only like a 1% chance
That this is a fluke
So I send this off to the journalist
You could get this published when you going to call it
Heads up
Bias in American quarter dollars minted in 1977
You can imagine the world going crazy right like
Workout before the game home strategies are emerging based on your study what you do not
In reading this one article
Coin flipping
And this is Keith
Is that a bunch of other researchers
Have also been doing
Feather results
Arles
Heads
Tails
Half heads half tails there lots of experiments like this
So why don't you read about these in the journal
Because it's such a bore him finding right like
You get this finding nobody's going to publish
I'm not going to send it off I'm just going to stick my results here
In this file cabinet with all the other failed
No success there's even the name
It's called the file drawer
Turtles are much more likely
To publish a positive result in a negative result
In fact
97% of results in Psychology that are published are positive results
Positive here means hey we found something
Negative is Madden
So is there some whole Shadow universe
Negative results that nobody ever heard of
Are tons of them and everyone can tell you about the effects that they have in their Labs that are published
In this
Of course this is a disaster
You know you could imagine
Lots of people doing the equivalent of testing whether coins are more likely to come up heads or tails when you
Almost all of them find of course there is no difference
But one David kestenbaum
They're more likely to come up heads and that is the one that gets published
This file drawer effect
Is the kind of thing that can help
Yes
And also it can partially explain why there were all those nose on no 6 spreadsheet why
So many studies failed to read
But
But no 6 has the file drawer effect is not enough
It doesn't explain
All of
That many studies in people's file
No she thinks there is another big issue
And this one is a little touchy or because it points to this
Human sort of weakness
Our ability to trigger
The subconsciously kind of skew the results
Okay let's go back to the coin flipping
Let's leave it at the beginning of the experiment
Our plan is
We're going to flip the coin 10 times and see what we get
We flipped a coin 10 times and we get
Seven heads now seven heads is interest
Thing you look at that
Can you say hey
Seems like we're getting more heads than tails
But it is not enough to
So you do something that seems reasonable
You say
Let's get some more.
Let's add some more
Flip a coin I don't know
4 more
You do that you get a few more heads
And now you like hey we found some
Let Pub
Seems reasonable it is not
Reasonable
You are effectively here
Changing the rules in the middle of the game in the middle of experiment
And you know you could just keep extending the experiment until you find something that seems 6th
If you do that what happens is you
You increase the chances that you'll find something that seems really interesting but is actually just
Just random
And if you're like come on does that really happen
Yeah it really happened
Steve Lindsay is a psychology
Professor at the University of
He says he and lots of other people
Have made this kind of mistake in the back
Here's how it happens
Okay let's start now Loop
Just 20 people inside glass not quite significant but it's it's looking promising let's plus test another 12 people
And the notion was just moving towards truth you test more people you're moving towards truth
But in fact and I mean I just didn't believe
Understand this properly
If you do that you increase the likelihood that you will
Jeffy
Hope significant effect
By chance alone
There are lots of ways you can trick yourself like
Just subtle ways you change the rules in the middle of an XP
Is Brian nosek
When I do research in laboratory I have choices I make
About how to analyze the data
And about what what of the data that I get to report
And so I might be more likely to find a way of analyzing the data that looks good for me
Right it confirms my hypothesis
It provides a result that's exciting that's very publishable
I might decide that must be the right way to analyze the data
And I might do that
While thinking and trying to be genuine and accurate
But the fact that I have a conflict of interest
And that's where the results have implications for me and my career advancement
Means that I might construct stories to myself
That lead me
Finding results in reporting results of literature that just are
Exaggeration of reality that just aren't true
I am start a journal called the Journal of exaggerated reality
Overtake the journal coin flipping it's number one
But that is the fear right that there a lot of journals out there that are the journals of exaggerated
Reality yeah I mean you don't you put together the file drawer effect and this
Problem of scientist tricking them
And it goes a long way toward
Explain this a long way toward explaining
Why you no one knows this project so many of those studies failed
These are not just issues in psychology
People are suddenly now really worried about this
This kind of thing in lots of
And there's this big new push to do something
We talked to an economist who's doing something similar to what no signal
Trying to repeat a bunch of experiments
The time in economics
Yeah and they're also projects going in in
Ecology another one in in cancer biology
Just to be clear like
There are certainly
Plenty of things that science knows for sure
More like smoking causes
Climate changes
The Higgs boson I'm telling you
Exist there's lots of stuff that gets published in the journals with his just no question
Like it happened on lab bench somewhere
They can repeat it other people have repeated it is definitely true
But there is this other category of scientific research you know a single studies that have not been replicated
Rely on
Correlation
Where the file drawer effect is a problem and researchers tracking themselves
Another trying not to
Is a problem
No success there is this one thing
That would go a long way toward fixing these
The file drawer effect
Kicking themselves
This thing is pretty simple
Before you do the study you write down how you're going to do it
How you going to analyze your data and what you're going to try to learn
You write all that down and then you submit it to an online register
That makes it impossible to change the rules as you go along
And then when you finish your experiment you
Put your results in the registry to
Even if you do not find a
Those results that would normally go in the file drawer
Those get made public
So that everybody knows what
What you found
In fact happened in other fields
In in drug research a while back they made this mandatory
Huge effect
According to the analysis before the registry was created
More than half of the published studies of heart disease showed positive results
After the registry was created
Only 8% had positive
From more than 50 to 8
Did Lindsey this psychologist who talked about the problem of adding more people to an existing study
To try to get a
In effect
He's also the editor right now of a journal called
Psychological
And he says when scientists come to him now with the results hoping to get Pub
He often points them to the registry
You're quite often
Saying okay this looks promising this looks interesting I want you to run a pre-registered replication
You mean you won't publish it unless they do that right
This is a hard
Sing I mean someone who used to do research and hang out with
Feels like someone saying we don't trust you got to write down exactly what you're going to do but
Like I'm somebody told me that when we were doing physics I would like flies fine but I don't need to do
Like I know it
Yeah you can really see how this whole thing that the registry and even the replication themselves
Can be an emotional issue
We haven't mentioned this yet but Brian nosek
The guy who loves replication right who headed up that whole study to repeat all those
Experiments
One of the experiments that was being
Repeated
Was when he did
And when this other lab redid his experiment
They could not replicate his original results
And that's that's a little hard for him to deal with
So do you think you were wrong
No
No I wasn't
Replication is wrong
Well it may not be wrong entirely either
So I'm willing to grant that in fact
We gave them access to the way in which we collected the data they analyze that the same way
And the results came out differently
It's all it's this is a this is the rough right I am invested in that original result
No sex after those results came out
Nobody
Not one researcher raise their hand and said
I guess that means I would
A lot of people said no.
The problem was with the replication
And no success in some cases
The problem was with the rep
But all of them
No way
So that is where we left things back in 2016
It is now 2018
And the results of that economics replication project that we mentioned are now public
We will tell you the results of that project
In a minute
Support also comes from Fidelity Investment
As a Fidelity wealth manager
You get a dedicated advisor
There to help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes
And make clear recommendations for your full Financial
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
In that economics replication project
Researchers
Redid 18 economics
Experiment
They have been published in Top Gun
The results of the project were published themselves in the journal science
And I spoke with one of the lead authors of the project
Onyx rapper of the Stockholm School of economics
And after
Out of the 18 studies
How many successfully wrap
11 out of 80
So
I don't know how to help
What what what what do we make of that number
I mean sweet weekend if we replicate fewer papers and we should have a
Expected by
Statistical power
Yeah right
Fun. Sounds is a bit disappointed
On its face it seems like
At least this replication project had a higher
Success rate than the psychology one
But honest as that is actually not the right way to look at it because
The two different projects.
Psych replication in the econ replication
They use different criteria for picking which studies to replicate
She also made another sort of big toe
And that is
A lot of economic studies
These are not these kinds of control.
Experiments
A lot of the time Economist go and get existing data from The Real World you know from the IRS or
From a big school district or whatever and then they crunch that data and come up with a result that they publishing a paper
Anna says in the last few years
Other researchers have started reanalyzing some of those kinds of studies
Going back in re crunching the data
And they've been finding worrying signs there too
And we talked about the meaning of halt
I mean I will say look
The end of this for me as a person who
Like science believes in science
Disappointing
Like I am death
Ya no me to
But I don't think that things can improve and like this reputation movement started by Bryan 06
Fantastic
Things are things are better people are more skeptical now is hard to do besides a solid wood
Tiny sample sizes finding something
Amazing about extrasensory perception or whatever
I'm upset
That's good
For the record
A bunch of people did try to replicate that original
Extrasensory perception study that ESP study
They could not do it
Today story was produced by Jess Jiang
The rear end was produced by Sindhu niana summoned
You can email us at Planet Money at npr.org
And follow us on Twitter or Facebook or Instagram
Or all of them