1 things I love about the phrase
Trade War
Is it sounds
So dramatic
Council
Viola
But at the same time a trade wars fought using these incredibly boring weapon
Percentages and lists
Spreadsheets
I am in the Excel spreadsheet trenches absolutely
This is Chad Bown a trade Economist with a Peterson in
And like ask your Planet Money
He's been pouring over these lists
Products that
The United States in
In China
Have been slapping new tariffs on
It started with President Trump's berries
Shortlist
A new set of tariffs on Chinese steel and
Lendup hitting about 3 billion dollars worth of
Chinese exports of Steel and aluminum to the u.s. owe China came up with a list of three billion dollars worth of imports from United
Red states to retaliate over
President Trump then the next day said well we're going to hit you with 50 billion dollars worth of
Tariffs on other products
China
Responded by saying okay well here's our
50 billion dollar product
And what makes the list
And doesn't make the list is a sort of international game
As a trade Economist Chad noticed that
China's list of new tariffs
We're filled with an awful lot of agricultural products
There are a lot of food products
I need less sleep make you hungry doesn't it
It really does and this is primarily because a lot of what
America sells to China
Is food
I know so many nuts
NN fruits
And
And pork
There's really something there for everyone regardless of your culinary tastes
Is there any way that you could cook a delicious meal made up of China's retaliate
We could start off with a refreshing smoothie
A lot of fruit on the on the list things like apples and pineapples
We could add a little bit of
Ginseng and maybe some coconut
And
We can actually make it with almond milk so there's not an actual dairy products on there but we could use almond milk as sort of
The base I will note that on this list
Stirrups is
Sparkling wine so we can have a nice little cocktail hour he won't go thirsty
I'm for the main dish
You did you're probably going to build around if you're thinking about meat is is a busy Port Friday
Sure lots of Chinese tariffs on American
I either ham or
Pate maybe dice up some hazelnuts pistachios and and
Set up that way
Another weird
Just joking here there is a real
Affect all these American Products in this fantasy meal are now subject to
Tariff
Which means they are 15 to 25% more
Expensive for the Chinese consumer
Which means China will buy less
Which means we might have a surplus of these products
Here
And we might just want to get
Used to smoothies and pork pate
Planet Money I'm Robert Smith
Today on the show a very special version of Iron Chef
Technically scrap
Aluminum
Chef American scrap aluminum just got hit with a 25% Chinese tariff
Yes. Planet Money reporters open up the scrumptious list of retaliation
And find some surprising stories inside
Hope you saved room for durian ice cream
Support for NPR comes from LinkedIn learning
Proud to support the launch of life
NPR's guy to help you make better life decision
LinkedIn learning short video tutorials cover business Tech and creative skills employers look
Four at every level all taught by expert
Mu courses are added every week
+ LinkedIn learning is personal I
Recommended courses based on your intro
And Life kid listeners get a month of learning
Free start your free trial
Add LinkedIn learning.com NPR
As many of you know I am a father
And one of the rules of being a
Is if you want to punish
Your child
What you do with you find the things they love the most
My God why did you take it away from them know this is how you punish children
And mostly the iPhone
Is mostly the iPhone
But in the case of retaliatory tariff
I feel like
China took a look
The United States
Ghetto what do they love
The most
Or more accurately what do they love to
To export
The most
Until today we're going to look at this list of
128 us products
Targeted by China
The delicious
List
Did we mention at the top of the show
And we're going to pick out just a few of these products.
To talk about
After flipping through this one thing that really stands out is
The list of pork products
Fresh or cold bone Pig for legs
Hindquarters in a meter
Pressure cooker pulled pork Frozen whole head in half
Pork frozen pork liver
China has slapped
A 25% extra Terra
On this thing
Stacey Vanek Smith
Yeah since you into pork world I went full bacon
And
Who did Utah
I talked to this man named Brian Duncan he
He's a hog farmer in Illinois
It is his family business his father also raised
Is there something about Hogs that
People don't know
But you know from working with them so many
Too many years
They had opposable thumbs they run the world
They are
Martin Mystery
I thought that I knew all the things I had to work hip how did life
Fat pigs with opposable thumbs is my new nightmare scene
I know and in your nightmares let's just hope that
Set the pigs are a little nicer to us
Then we are to them or at least that we are a little bit less delicious
That would help
If you are a pork producer and you all the sudden wake up one morning and find
That
One of the main places do you export your product
2 China has slap this additional
Tax on it what do you think
Well would Brian told me was it
The second he heard all the
Did Trump talk about
Steel and aluminum Industries he was just glued to the news he was just
Waiting for the other shoe
When agriculture know we will be the first targets
Nerf Retaliator take a look
I was tryna hit
Starfruit wine and pork
And so I'd say worst fears realized
And why are they always the first because it's just
I'm thinking back on trade Wars of the past
It's something you back on trade Wars of the past has agriculture always loses out in
In a trade War easy thing for a country to
And it creates the sort of emotional victims the American Farmer now suffer
Because of this
Trade War
Yes and Brandy this point too and so did I
A couple other people I talk to
That China knew that if they hit agriculture they would be hitting Trump or his voters were
Because a lot of the places hit hardest by these tariffs are places that voted for
China knew this and Brian told me that he and all of his friends in a group
Culture
Now immediately pork prices
Drop down
And what happened
Brian said his pigs lost about
10% of their value
About a million dollars on his operator
Giving up 70000
Which that looks so that's a lot of pain
We pegues
But according to Brian that is a very small operations of a thousand pigs is
Did very very little but he really counts on China
Because
China not only buys a lot of
If we're from the US but it also buys these
Cuts of pork that us consumers don't buy their called
Variety
Ears
Tails
Close
And all those variety me
Dayton Oregon
Sano fall and things that
That we don't consume your China is a very valuable market for so I
That actually provides value
2 product that maybe was was going in the dumpster as far as American consumers were concerned
So this means that we have to actually eat more
Four legs and liver
Well there will be more around
If you want them
I need the pork industry you have to understand this is a really difficult
Moments
Because according to Brian
The whole industry was really gearing up for this big bump in fur
Free trade
You might remember the trans-pacific partnership
Trade Agreement SPSS big Trade Agreement
Between the US and a bunch of country is mostly in
In Asia
Trump ended up pulling out of the agreement but the TPP was going to potentially open up a lot more Asian market
It's the pork
In the US is one of the biggest pork producers in the world
So all these poor farmers in the US or gearing up with
Crispy pork boom and building new facilities and buying more pigs and all the stuff a new golden age of bacon
Bacon has been a lot of
Infrastructure put in
The new packing plant
Should have come online
There's been new
Hog production
Can come online we're gearing up to meet this
Yashow market and now it appears we might be
Not getting knee cap
Do pigs have knees
I'm almost sure pigs have knees
If they do by the way
Friday
Don't get all serious that's like what it what is Brian
Do next
So what he told me is that he's kind of writing this out right now I mean prices have gone down for him
But what everyone's doing now is really
Looking forward
Because
A quarter of all the pork raised in the US is
A lot of ghost
Sign up but more of it goes to Canada in May
So now
Is obviously a really big deal to poor farmers and the farmers all over the country of all kind soap
He says what everyone's talking about now is what is going to happen
With NAFTA that's what he's like
Looking at in Frankfurt Airport
Stacey Vanek Smith
Robert Smith so good to have you on the program from
Are the program the indicator if you want
Smart Pick
On economic every single day
Stacey Vanek Smith
Is your host with the most
An indicator is what
Thanks Robert my pleasure
Art back to the list
128 us products targeted by China
Is there are so
Many
Fruits more fruits that I've ever heard of
Betelnut fruit
Betel nut
Is a battle or beetle
I don't know with me in the studio is our newest
Reporter Sarah Gonzalez
And you looked into just one of these many many many many
Many many fruits
China has increased
That fruit is
Number 55 on the list
The durian fresh durian not frozen durian
So are the durian is very popular in Asia
In Southeast Asia
Particular where it grows
Add to tell me a little bit more about the dirt
So the durian is
A pretty big fruit
Size of a baby's head like a pineapple it is famous for
Smell it has a very intense
Smell
And The Taste is like
Like whipped cream and caramel with
The raw onion and diced garlic
So your task was to
Define
Us
Durian farmer
Who is going to be affected by
These new Terra
And I found Ian Crown he on the farm in Las Vegas Puerto Rico
Apparently durian can only grow in areas with really high
Humidity
And so Hawaiian Puerto Rico are the only two places as far as
Department of Agriculture can tell that grows
And Ian
Love's
Fresh Dairy
Oh my God the fresh
You know rocks my world
He's a rare fruit guy robbery actually calls himself a rare fruit nut
So was in worried when he saw that his
Beloved
Durian
Was on this list of Chinese tariffs
He does not care
Even if you wanted to send durian to China
The US doesn't allow him to
No I'm not allowed to ship durian outside of Puerto Rico
Yeah has to do with pesto
Does anyone in United States
Send durian to China so I went to the Department of Agriculture and I said
How much durian does the United
It states send to China the
Department of Agriculture
Commerce
In the Department of Commerce was like no I think the department agriculture supposed to know that and then the Department of Agriculture was like we are okay hold
Let me find out
Then eventually the Department of Agriculture told me we have sent very little dirty into China Lake
Really little legs
Pretty funny that he made his way onto the list
Yes I would say that they should also put on the list that we're not allowed to ship them any unicorns
The United States has not sent a single jury into China in the past 5 years
Or mangosteens or rabbit
And Sundays are all fruits that are on
The list which raises the obvious
Why would China
Put a special Terra
On us
Durian
If
Imports
0 USD
Facebook to a couple people to try to help me understand this clearly
China and countries in general are really good about putting tariffs on things
That one actually
Hurt them
The idea is basically that when the United States threatened
Tariffs
A country has to make
If the right back and in order to
Make that threat
Credible
Flip out of the list
So it could be that they patted the list
The other theory is that they just put every fruit and nut on their list and
Drury Inn in mangosteens happened to
Be on there they just copied and pasted it into the document it just got caught up
I do want to mention that the United States has put some things on its list of proposed tariffs
That we don't import a whole lot of from China example
On recording cassette players are know what they do if they don't record but
As you can imagine we don't import a whole lot of them
Thank you sir
Thank you Robert
At 3
Soy to the world
The latest tablets work that's out Goldberg by the way
When is topless work is it you start with the smallest
The case of durian the non-existent stuff
But you want to hold back on the really big tariffs
In case the trade War escalates
We can talk it so far about products that have already been hit
With new tariff
But the Chinese have another live
A list of American Products
They are threatening to put
A tariff on
And I'm at theoretical list
Soybean
And Alex
Give me the office the other day and he said you are not going to believe what is happening
They don't even have a new tariff on them yet
But just
Idea of a new tariff is already
Changing
Where soy flows around the world
Changing Global Market
It's already
Soy flour
We had questions so we call that Mr saw himself
The man with the tofu heart
Jim Sutter
And I am the CEO of the
The US soybean export Council
Jim says about 30% of the American soy crop goes to China
Although
You would not
Really know it
If you were in China because it get crushed
And processed into
Generic cooking oil
Doesn't the USA on the air
Or feed for livestock
If you look real closely you might be able to kind of detective
The detectives from soybean meal but that might be a bit of a stretch
To the Chinese
They Don't Really Care
If their soybeans come from
The US
Or if it comes from somewhere else I just want
Yeah because it's not like
Branded American
Cancel
Weather feeding is Alaska
And so if they can save it
Few pennies they will buy from our Arch
Soy rival
So the USA and Brazil are so like the Coke and Pepsi of the soybean world
That's a great analogy if the Coke in the Pepsi the soybean world
The US embrace
Coke and Pepsi who is cheaper who is cheaper
Eminem Alex
Something changes
The entire mark
What late last week
The Chinese government announces that they might just
Might
Put a timer
On USC
Show all of the Chinese buyers are suddenly thinking way too
A tariff would
Totally change the master
So
These buyer said wow I better not buy any us soybeans for fear this may happen
So they already
Brazil and the price of Brazilian soybeans
Champs
Everyone in China
Who's buying soybeans
They want this tariff-free Brazilian soybean want to lock it in yet and
In America
Meanwhile
They're looking around there like wait a minute
We got somebody funny
So the price of American soybean
Relative to Brazilian soybeans
So it was
You know during the US night time during the day time
China
Soybean Futures on the Chicago Market
Computer Exchange
Dropped by as much as
Fifty cents a bushel at one point
And it also doesn't mean rough numbers they went from
$10.40 a bushel to $9.90 a bushel
So
You know that's a big
Shipt
Remember Alex
Nothing has changed in the world the sheer number of soybeans in Brazil and United
Exactly
The same there isn't even a tariff yet this is just a maybe in the future we might impose a tariff
Kind of comment
From China and here's my favorite part when you told the story
The rest of the world
Like buyers in Europe they look around
Brazilian prices are going up
But they don't have a dog in the
Was terrified for them on USI so they're thinking
Look at the us or because they're on sale so you're upset stomach big perch
Pieces of us
Soybean and Anthony's like
Ships that would have been going to Brazil to pick up their soybeans are now headed
Kid to kid American Fork
And Europe
Is not the only
I noticed the Taiwan bought a cargo Japan has Bots
Soybean
Turkey Egypt
And sure enough with all the new buyers
The price of American soybeans
It comes back
Attacking a gym
He is
Certainly spooked
Buy this whole incident
Words alone
Rattle his whole industry
If
If soybean tariffs going to affect it could be
Be devastating for the America
Farmer
But the interesting about the story is
Test also created these arbitrary
Winners
And losers
You're a
Chinese manufacturer who needs soybeans you're going to be paying more for
But if you're a Brazilian farmer all the sudden you this unexpected windfall
You're not even in the trade work but you get to sell your story for more
Answer this is just a reminder that a tariff cannot be a Target
You put a tariff on one product from one country
And it could rearrange the way the entire world market Opera
Never know where the soy sauce is going to flow
Find is level
Thank you Alex
Thanks Robert
Coming up
Is one thing that China
Forgot
Terrifying
Cigarettes Viet
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layouts
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
If you have
Haven't gotten enough
China's retaliatory tariff list will be putting up links to some of the sources and stories
Behind the sweets show followers at Planet Money on Twitter and Facebook
An Instagram for that
If you want to give us a story tip or send us question we are Planet Money at NPR. Org
Today shows produced by Sally Helm and Lexie Horowitz Ghazi with help her intern Aviva dekornfeld or editors Brian
First at our senior producer is Alex goldmark
Take to get to Chad Bown or economist
And menu planner we talked with the very beginning
He has his own podcast and goes into way more detail on this kind of stuff than we have time for
It's called trade talks
Thanks for listening
Sarah I know something
Pugilist
Of things there's no peanuts in them
No peanut
This dried coconut
Is Brazilian nuts shell Brazilian nuts is cashews
Does almonds and hazelnuts there's
Walnut
Chestnuts
Macadamia nuts
Red pistachios
Green pistachio
So what happened to peanut obviously I know they're legumes like everyone alright in
If we say they're not but still like peanuts
You think
Yeah I don't know I called up a peanut farmer Tim Burch in south Georgia
And he said that
Even peanut Farmers considered
That's nuts
They basically think that
Peanuts were left off by accident and they were kind of like
Don't bring attention to this what if China puts us on the list
Because if they are we forgot to include peanuts
Say my name every kind of nut I can think of
And no
I don't know why we were left off
Okay so
What's a compact
Between you and me
Okay yeah
Didn't happen