Support for NPR and the following message come from w w Norton and Company
Publishers of people power and profits Progressive capitalism or an age of discontent
By Nobel prize-winning Economist Joseph E stiglitz
Hey it's Jacob Goldstein Today Show is a real
Alex blumberg and David kestenbaum reported it back in 2013
And we did the show back when we raised money to make a Planet Money t-shirt
We raised
Hundreds of thousands of
Amazon handled the payment handled the money
And then when we went to move the money from Amazon to our bank account at Chase it took
5 days
It took 5 days
Maybe that's not surprising I mean you see this periodically it'll take 3 to 5 days for the transaction to complete her five to seven business days
But think about that
5 days once Take 5 days what is happening after you click
Send
It's not like we're sending money from some Community Bank in the United
Do a factory
Indonesia
We were moving at between two of the largest most
Wired institutions in the world
The money that we collected
It turns out a Tango by amazon.com
Amazon of we can send you anything in a day
That Amazon the money was in an Amazon payments account and we were sending the money to a checking account at Chase Bank and Chase is one of them
Largest banks in the world
I read holy order
Diapers from Amazon
I haven't delivered to my door physical diaper the huge big box
Next day
Diapers brought to me
Sending money electronically from an internet company
What are the largest banks in the world
Goodbye
Hello and welcome to Planet Money. Alex blumberg and I'm David kestenbaum today on the show
Invisible pipes that carry money from one place to another
And why a why they are so slow
This message comes from NPR sponsor game
The Bold way to steady growth
People often think of nobodies are too conservative to complex or only for retirees but annuities can be
Be a smart way to hedge Market risk and earn guaranteed returns game Bridge aims to change the game
By offering simplified annuities in a Sleek digital experience
That replaces fine print and phone tag with clear conditions and a direct loafy model
Learn more at gamebridge. Life / NPR
Game Boy
Which is not available in all states
Dates
This question why can take so long to send money from one place to another
It's a serious question
And in this Lotus I think we'll just a friend it hurts me more than it hurts
It's you and I think part of the reason that I'm excited that I can relate
That I have been burned by the Sun
I'm not as good as you
It's a sometimes I'll
Transfer money to my account think it's their pay a bill and then it won't be there and I'll get hit with a late fee
I think that happens a lot and especially if you're paycheck-to-paycheck
You're being penalized by the slowness of the system and nothing else about
Our life online is this low
My first thought you know about why it was so
Like we were transferring a lot of money
Lottabody
Over $500,000
I was going into this little regular checking account wasn't a
So I thought
You know maybe sensibly it got a little extra scrutiny and that is why it took so long
Set a test that was the case
We tried a second transfer we tried to send just $10 the reversed
From Chase to Amazon
And this transfer
Took even longer
8 days
So we did the logical thing
We called up Chase and Amazon
Amazon
What can I do to help you today
Oh I have a question about my Amazon payments account also I am a reporter for NPR National
Public radio recording this for possible fraud
Took my question is I have I have a Amazon payments
Account that was
Associate
Can't answer questions if you
You can't you can't answer questions if it's being recorded
Is there any way to
Get permission to answer questions if they're being recorded
We also tried Chase your call may be monitored or recorded
For quality purposes
Thank you for going to my name is Lolita Baker could I get your first and last name please
Yeah my name is Alex blumberg
I have a question about my Chase account
I'm at my so I'm also a reporter for NPR in recording this call for possible broadcast
K
Four possible broadcast
Yeah I have a question about my accountant it involves Amazon payments
Add involved Enron payment to Amazon amazon.com
We were able to learn that our money got sent through something called the
ACH system
Which saint for automated
Did Clearing House
What exactly that was how it operated
Why it was so slow
It was surprisingly hard to get people to talk to us on the record about it
Chase and Amazon both the client to make anyone
Available and would only answer questions
Dover email
When I did get someone on the phone to ask about the state safe
Why are you doing this story
I can tell they're hiding something or just
Embarrassed or just
They were so used to the system it didn't seem weird
And often the answers only led to more questions for example we found someone who used to work at the Federal Reserve which
Runs part of the system that handles these electronic pek
Elizabeth McQueary
And we have what we thought was a simple question
What does the
System event look like
It's a row of machine
Big tall computers with
Information being spit out on monitors where
Those are classified
You can't tell me where they are
No
Can you can you say witch
Which state they were in
You have to realize that
That those machines those servers are moving billions of dollars every day so it
Well protected where those systems are
Can you tell us what state though
So I don't think I can
Another question I thought would be simple but
What is the deal with
Weekends
Amazon and Chase both told us that the reason it took so long to transfer money
Was that there was a weekend
This is all the time and online banking and bill payment
It'll take 3 to 5 business days
5-7 business
It's always business
If you think that why should that matter
Look at my account online on weekends
I can't even go to the bank on weekends so why does the system these each system closed down a week
It's some point ACH does cut off its operating hours
Moreless has Bankers hours and then let me know cause there is so so this is
It when you talk about the ACH you said the ACH takes banker's hours
Are we taking that people are we talking about machines
We're pretty much talking about machines
So if we're talking about machines why do they need to take Bankers hours
That's a good question
I think you have to really
You have to think of it is a system that was
Conceived and implemented in the 1970s
The 1970
40 years ago
This pizza Financial Plumbing
It is 40 years old
That's the reason so slow
Adult
The system was designed long before anything like amazon.com
How long before the internet
I was born in the days
When the way to send money
Was with a paper check
What's imagine the way people made payments
Back before anything was electron
Before the system.
Right Stuff example
An electrician
Alright say it's 1970
I want to pay my electricity bill
I get out my checkbook
I write out a check
To the power company for sake
$20.16
Put the check in the mail the post office delivers the check to the power come
But that's not the end
The power company Bank
Then makes a note in his ledgers check for 2016 received
But it still doesn't have the actual money
To get the money it needs to send that same paper check
Back
To your bank.
So your bank and say yes this is from our customer 1970 Dave kestenbaum
Yes yes $1.16 in his account
And this exchange of paper checks
Between these two bags
Had to happen with every check that was written
And it wasn't something that could happen
Through the mail
The exchange of of the paper check had to happen physically
Between between two financial institutions
Bert Harkins is Senior Vice-President with a company called Fiserv which provides technology to financial institutions
He says sending money back then
Took a lot of manual labor
The banks would physically exchange bags of checks
If they weren't banks in the same physical location if you had banks in different regions
The country
Then you literally were flying bags of checks from one of the country to the other to do that Exchange
In in major metropolitan areas there were set locations which were often just
Sort of parking lots in insecurity areas where literally
Trucks with backup to one another from each individual major financial institution
And they would pass bags of checks back in
And at the very end of this whole process day if your 1970 Bank
Takes your 1970 check
Which has gotten back
From The Electric Company
Edit mails it back to you
All of the story that little check could tell if its Voyage first and Ice Postman took me the electric company
Then I went to their Bank
And I got put in a bag then I got handed off
Parking lot to our bank
Then I got put in the mail again and now I'm home
And that is the way it works for everyone
Private individuals like you
Paying my bills
But also enormous institutions huge companies that had to pay their employees
They did it
My check
Paycheck
The Social Security Administration millions of checks
Paper checks
So that was a problem
The solution to that problem led to the
And the solution was
We're going to get rid of that really annoying thing where every bank has to find a way to meet up
With other banks in parking lots
To exchange checks
I think about it if I'm the bank of David
I have to meet up with the bank of Alex to exchange checks
Maybe I have to go meet up with another bank at another location that the
In another state
It's a lot of meetings and it just doesn't make it
So they said let's just get rid of all these random meeting
Between individual banks at different locations
Let's set up a central
Clearing House
Where all these transactions happen at 1
And help facilitate all these transactions
We're going to use this magical new technology
Computers
And banks will not be sending bags of
Checks to the screen
Said sticking to be sending
Magnetic
Computer tapes
And the tapes each bangle sending it
And on the table say
Send a hundred bucks to this guy this guy at this Bank
And the Clearing House you can think of it sort of like
Enola post office
It sits sorting all the mail
The gathers up all the transactions destined for particular Bank
I can put that on it
Pain in the back pick that up
Magnetic tapes
Kingship back and forth between banks around the country and the central clearinghouses
That
What's the upgrade
What today looks like
Fairly slow process at when it was when it sort of came online
Was a huge leap forward from what they were doing
So you can get paid without
Any paper being involved
That's crap
Well when you put it that way it seems like an exciting
The Technology's drugs prices in kept getting better over the years computers got faster
Smaller
Here's a computer ad from 1977
You're looking at a small portable computer
The IBM 5150 lb
You can plug it in anywhere
High definition of portable
But you can't plug it in
Eventually we get to the internet
And this system for moving cash
What happens to it
Nothing
Basically nothing
It doesn't use magnetic tapes today but it still acts as if it
All right so as far as we can tell
Here is what happened
2R t-shirt money
What are you trying to transfer
At 8:03 p.m. on a Thursday I clicked a button on a computer screen
Sending a request
Amazon.com
To transfer the money
To our bank account
Request
Go to Amazon
And it's it's
Because as Amazon wrote To Us in an email it arrives quote
After our last batch for Thursday processing with Transit
In the old days I got this the banks had to gather all these requests to send money
And then put them on a magnetic tape and send them out at the end of the day
So if a request comes in too late
Keep you have to wait till the next day when the next it goes
But today there is no tape right at all
Connected by wires
And yet
This is still the way it works your request comes in too late
Doesn't happen.
Next day everything is done
Batches
So I request made it to Amazon's Bank the following day
Which is Friday
From there it got sent to one of the major sorting
You can imagine those big rows of computers and a secret location that Elizabeth
McCreary describe
They're two of these clearinghouses one is run by the fed the other is run by a collection of
But now
Wet Saturday
The Weeknd
So
Nothing happens
Find a
Sunday also a weekend
Nothing happens
Monday acronym
How many arrived at Chase Bank
At 7:05 in the morning
But it didn't actually appear in our account until Tuesday
Maybe because Monday was a holiday
But Tuesday it's finally
Imagine if email work this
Play right you send an email Thursday evening
It doesn't arrive until Tuesday
Any of these big secret sorting computers that run this ACH system
It's always stuck in the past
Bert Harkins the payments consultant says that the systems that they use
Are all based on a nearly extinct programming like
Cutco
We're in Atlanta and it's hard to find
Graduate from Georgia Tech who know COBOL
Like knowing Latin
This is the system that carry the T-shirt
Based on a time when we used to exchange checks
Parking lot
And that was a programming language that no one knows
And this is one of the major ways that money get sent around the United
According to the electronic payments association called nausea
In 2012 there were
21 billion transactions
Total value 36.9 trillion dollars
And the more I learn about this
As you know
The more crazy it drove me
Because it's not like you can't upgrade the system I mean
I have proof that you can
My proof
Country of England
Kristen live
People absolutely definitely
Was very act by the fattest three dice movement that exactly the same reactions you to say
I'm sending money
Compass Bank here to that bank that they are biggest uses they have lots of water and Technology why is it taking three days
It would be faster for me to take the money out of an ATM
Wookies Ramsey of the bank
And give it to them
And that was definitely
A feeling that people who dislike just give me the money out person and blow poke down the road
It's faster
And so with a push from the British government the banks are agreed
Update
Vocalink that company that Chris works for
Runs it now it cost pennies per transaction he says
And it's fast
It takes literally seconds
15 seconds
End-to-end
So in the USA took 5 days
Send the teacher money
In the UK
You can do it inside
Is it true that there's a limit of about $150,000 per transfer
In the British system so we have to do it
As for transfers
But the
Seconds Chris says business is really like the system
And his daughter really like the system she's in college
And she sometimes runs out of cash
I actually regular gas
The central St can you send me some money and I can just hit the button
And the money will be with her and intellectually mature second and you're muttering under your breath I should have never put the system in place
What Willie it does make it very easy to go about fixing to wifey that I can possibly guess it comes from somebody else know you
Unfortunately you're on the hook 24 by 7 by 365 site
What about yourself
IND
For the sake of demonstration can you send her a few pounds now
Interested meaning of Jersey City New York
If I can get my iPhone I will
Try sekai so the moment I'm looking to my online bank account to telephone my balance
I had
Payments
Paper synovial
I just bring up a list so I'll go
I think the pantofles of people and that she is
Write about a time
Jessica so I will send her
How much does a beer cost in New York
Better than ten bucks with the Beast
How come the tip
Ascend A10 crediton
NASA space Today Show you want to pay 10 lb useful check because if I just made that I accidentally
I didn't want us to get ringing out since it's always important to hear about
Faster payments in that it goes immediately and it's irrevocable
Cuz I usually don't fight 10 lbs is okay
One moment please
Sami Gayle I have a sickness at 10th and payment center
Headbang balance will I be 10 lb sloppy high on should wonder what's an s on doing sending a 10 quid
After we hung up with Kristen we have course call this daughter
How are you
I'm good thank you how are you
Did your dad tell you he might be calling
Yeah he filled me in on Africa
Did you get the money he sent
Very convenient
Yeah I know
We ask Jessica if she was going to use it to buy a beer she said
No probably something really boring instead
Like a Subway
There are individual banks in United States that have systems like this
For example in a my bank
Chase has
Popmoney where you basically can send money instantaneously to other Chase customers
But you can't send instant money to people with account that other bag
Has been thinking about building
Something more comprehend
Like what they have in the
Kristen told us that people from the FED of come over to talk to him
And just last year the banks in the United States here
How the big vote on this
Should we move to a faster
With
I know this isn't going to be enough for you Alex
Same day service
Meaning send in the morning
It could be there by the end of the day
Is Elizabeth McQueary
Not necessarily A real-time system
Where are you could have the money instantaneously
This was sort of a
A transition to something faster
Slightly faster
Yes baby bass
But still not really fast exactly
I am the banking Community voted it down
Voted it down
But was closed but the way the ACH governance sister
Works need a super majority of Italy
75%
Yes we do not know the exact tally it's not public but we do know that more than half voted yes
But not enough to cross the 75
Elizabeth McCreary says there were concerns about fraud
And also that it would just be this major overhaul
Many of these Community Banks they actually close their processing back office at 3 p.m. in the afternoon
Even before the banks
Front lobby
Is closed
So they would have to staff
In order to be able to receive these payments
Later in the day
Alex you know I'm not as irked by the slowness
Of the system as you are I know that you're not
These reasons they make some sense
Right I mean the US has far more Banks
UK has under 200 mags the USS something like 7000
And all these different states
Each with their own computer is known people who know the ACH
System you can argue look if customers are okay with the system
And it works
10 great know we built this type in the 70s
We dealt a good pipe
It still works today
Why spend a bunch of money to replace it
What's something fancy
You could have said that any point hippie the cart and buggy works fine why do we need a car
What about the Concorde
Actually need to fly
Yeah but this isn't some booty
Product were talking about the entire world is moving
The only thing that isn't is the USB
Speed of light man
The right one thing if we have disclosed them simply because
People think it suits our needs
But you know there may be something else
More going on
There's a survey done by the consulting firm called Glenbrook
Which Elizabeth McQueary now works for
Is a survey of a bunch of people in this online payment
And they were asked
What do you think is the most important apps
Obstacle to implementing faster
Most respondents
Table is beside that
There be hassled
Systemic
But 20% of respondents
Big Ripper
Set it to differ
They thought the biggest obstacle was quote
Financial institution opposition
Due to cannibalization
Existing
In other words if we upgrade the ACH
I will compete with
Black wire tree
Are fast
And I actually can tell you exactly how it's
Because there's a last part
The story of Art
Acura transferred it to a Chase account
Had to transfer it to an NPR back
The only way to do that was using a wire cutter
The cost
$30
For sending data
OverWatch
Support for this podcast
And the following message come from State Farm whose agents know that your car and home are more than just big purchase
They're a big part of your life
You put the time into making them your own
So now it's time to protect them
With your own personal State Farm agent
Not only do they truly get
But they'll be there for you when you need them
And with over 19000 agents in neighborhoods across that us
There could be one just around the corner
Moritz statefarm.com
Are 1-800 State Farm
State Farm
Here to help life
Go right
Hey tits Jacob back here in 2018
Since we ran the show back in 2013
Of course the world has changed lots of people have started using apps like venmo beaming each other money from their phones
But
Banks are largely
Still using ACH still using that old system
Still generally take
Days to send money from One bank to another
But
That will change
We checked back in with Elizabeth McQueary to get the up
Achs giving itself a multiyear period To adapt
To the changes
And now
What we're saying is the final leg of this transition
And that is
To require
That the receiving institution makes those funds available to you as the consumer
Bye
5 p.m. so that it's truly a same-day payment to you as the receiver of the payment
In other words in just a couple of months
You will finally be able to move money from One bank to another
On the same day
Scores
The same day thing it only applies to work days not holidays
I'm actually super into payment I've been trying to figure out a
Another payment show to do
If you have story ideas for me you can email us at Planet Money at npr.org or find us on Facebook or
Twitter Today Show was originally reported by Alex blumberg and David kestenbaum the rerun was produced by cash
Mihailovich
Alex goldmark is our senior producer Brian first at a theater
One last thing
Planet money has a new
Podcast spin off it is called
The indicator it is daily it is Planet Money quick take
On a number in the news
Toasted by Stacey Vanek Smith and Carlos Garcia
Call the indicator and you can get it
On the NPR one app or wherever you get your podcast
I'm Jacob Goldstein thanks for this