Support for this in
NPR podcasts
The following message
Come from the UPS
Offering services from shredding
To printing to mailbox
And instead of closing this Memorial Day we
May 24th and 25th
The UPS Store
He's doing another thing
All together
Opening
The UPS Store
Everything for small business
And of course shipping
Last week there was some huge news in the world of professional basketball
LeBron James
Decided to leave his hometown Cleveland Cavaliers
Again
And this time we'll be joining
The Los Angeles Laker
She's just signed a deal that is worth
154 million dollars / 4
And it reminded us of an episode we did
Way back in 2013
Back then LeBron James was making 17 and 1/2 million dollars a year
But
Economist told us
LeBron might be the most underpaid athlete
On the play
Yes LeBron James almost certainly has been extremely underpaid
For his entire career
That was Victor Matheson an economist at Holy Cross University
Another Economist Kevin Greer put it more bluntly he's getting hosed
But that was 2013 now LeBron has this brand new deal he's getting a lot more money
And we wanted to know
Is he still under pay
And so today
The ammunition you need to get into the nerdiest fight at your local sports
We're going to play part of our 2013 episode explaining why Lebron used to be underpaid
And after that we will run the math again
Quick no sheer
Some of the players mentioned in this original story are retired now including Mike Miller who's awesome there's no way we're cutting
Alex blumberg & Taylor Tepper pick this up
After the break
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with
Straight jeans
How did they make them so great
Madewell starts with premium.
Then offers men's and women's styles for seriously everyone
Also you can recycle any brand of jeans in a Madewell store
And they'll give you $20 off a new pair
They work with the blue jeans go green program
App to turn old jeans into housing insulation for communities in need
Terms apply
Ready to find your perfect fit stop by a Madewell store or go to madewell.com
Okay so
Taylor bus layout
For how a multi-millionaire like LeBron James
Getting hosed
And to do that
Let's imagine
A job
Monster.com or a newspaper
Wanted
Once-in-a-generation NBA super
Skills required
Must be able to soar through the air in order to execute thunderous dunks
Check
Be a team player who works well in small groups of five
Who can facilitate performance by executing and possible seeming cross-court passes to barely open teammates
Check printing
Thrive under pressure
Preference given to
2 tall strong
Extremely agile candidate
Inability to play suffocating lockdown defense
Again Economist Victor Matheson
So by lots and lots of measures LeBron James is the best
Player in the NBA
If you keep
Playing at the pace that he has for the last 10 years and has a lengthy career that is not interrupted by injury
He may go down as the best player in the history of
All right so say you work at an imaginary human resources department LeBron James resume with
I got to figure out highlight-reel lands on your desk
And you got to figure out how much do you pay this guy
What is he worth
How do you figure that out
If only there was a way to determine just
How much value he adds
The team
This job candidate somewhere in his employment history
Switch teams
And you able to compare the economic impact of that switch
If only
The answer to the question everybody wants to know
LeBron
What's your decisions to anyone with even a passing interest in sports
You remember this
LeBron James decided to leave his old team
The Cleveland Cavaliers
And go to his new team the Miami Heat and this phone will take my talents to South Beach
And join the Miami Heat Miami Heat that was the conclusion you woke up with this
That was the conclusion I woke up with this morning
This decision was actually called the decision was broadcast
On Primetime around the world
This was huge
Sports news
For everyone the Cleveland Cavaliers they felt betrayed
Fan they're burned his jersey
LeBron James
Reviled on Sports Talk Radio 4 weeks in months
Italy whole year 2
But that's not why we're talking about this moment
We're talking about it
Because it gives us a pretty clear picture of how valuable LeBron James is
When you left the Cavaliers
The value of the team
How much it would have been worth it
The teams on her head
Tried to sell it
Exactly that value drop by about
25%
Any value the team that he went to
The Miami Heat
Went up 30%
This is all according to calculations done by Forbes
When you take all this into account how much to
Ticket sales with drop how much
TV Revenue would go up
The people who study this will tell you
LeBron James
Should be making
Around 40
Million-dollar
More than double
The current salary
And there you have it
The mathematically precise amount by which
LeBron James is getting hoes
Is getting hosed
Out of over 20 million dollars a year
If that's the case
Let's say I'm the general manager of
My beloved Brooklyn Nets
We're not that good we're stuck in the middle of the pack
I'm sorry
What's the stop me from saying we'll get to your team in a minute and stop me from saying
Hey LeBron James
I will pay you your full value I'll pay you 40 million dollars a year if you come on over and play
Was you know Alex
You're not allowed to do that.
There's a salary cap in the NBA
Is a limit on how much owners can pay their players
Yeah there's a limit on how much they can
Can pay in salaries overall and there's a limit on how much an owner
Can pay any individual
Litter is called a maximum contract and you're not
Really loud to go over that
Without incurring
Very happy find
So no matter how rich a basketball team owner is
And there are some really rich ones including the Brooklyn Nets owner
They're not really able to pay LeBron James what he's actually worth
And that's one way LeBron James is getting hose
The salary cap
But the salary cap that is just the beginning
Of the long Saga of halibut
There is another feature of the NBA's rules that is arguably even worse
LeBron James
And that is
The draft
Not for sports fans
The draft system
It's so ingrained it seems
Pretty normal but when you actually described it out loud to people as we've had to
Going to be out of this podcast
Sports and all the sudden seems really bizarre
When players want to go to the NBA
They don't do what happen
Any
Field in the world
Send their resumes are highlight reels
Do the teams they want to play for
And then if it's
Makes an offer
Negotiate over that offer and then both parties come to a final say
Where they will
They're not in the NBA
It's way
Weirder than that
Cell potential job applicants
The best young basketball players in the world
Today right right
To those applicants they put their names in this big pool
Hoosier Lottery
Literally with ping pong balls in those crazy
Plastic tubes
And the 14
Worst teams in the league
I'll have to draw a number
And whoever draws the winning number gets the right to pick first my big pool of talent
And this is the weird part whatever player that
Teen pics
He can't say no
You have no choice
And Emily that
He can't negotiate his salary
His players union
Has already negotiated an upper limit
How much rookies can get paid
And this is the way it works
Even
If you are a one
In a lifetime Talent
Like LeBron James
In the 2003 NBA Draft the Cleveland Cavaliers
LeBron James play the drafted just like soldiers are drafted during a war
In this case
Cleveland drafted LeBron James
You can go work for the Los Angeles Lakers
The New York Knicks of the Boston Celtics
No
He was going to go to Cleveland whether you liked it or not
Imagine of other fields were set up
Like what that you're the best young software engineer at MIT
Silicon Valley Inn
Getting hired
Friend insane starting salary by Google
You had to put your name into a pool with other engineers
And then the worst companies in America got to draw a random numbers and then one day you would get a letter thing I know you've been hired
To work in the IT department at Best Buy
I'll just beat amazingly frustrating
But this is basically what happened to LeBron James
And everyone knew he was going to be great even in high school
In a free market there would have been a huge bidding war for him with some of the best teams in the league trying to William
But instead
Wolfel Cleveland Cavaliers happen to win the lottery
They got to select them he had no say
And they were able to pay him far less than it was worth
Cell
That brings us to an obvious question at this point
Why is it set up this way why is there a limit on how much teams can spend why is there a draft system
And who would getting all those extra million dollars
That should be going to LeBron James
Well again here is Victor Matheson from Holy Cross
There is certainly one big winner in the salary caps
Is the owners himself
By reducing the amount that they have to pay for their labor and to provide their product
They certainly
Generate significantly higher profit
And we see sports teams in the United States be far more profitable than sports teams in Europe
Which Temple don't
Have salary
All right
So I guess you can see who I owners would want to arrange things
So that they had to pay their superstars weigh less than the market value
They want to keep
Some of that money that they otherwise pay LeBron they want to keep
That themselves
And in fact it's actually illegal under antitrust laws for owners of other businesses
Collude about salaries
The way that owners of NBA teams do
But the NBA like other sports leagues
Got it. Exempted from this
Antitrust laws
But it's not just colluding owners
Are the ones holding the
His left
Talented teammates are Jose matters money as well
Set remember this salary cap rules
Thinking about is part of
The collective bargaining agreement between the owners
And the NBA players union itself
Here is our other economy
Kevin Greer
Welder Union
Is is Union votes on contracts by majority rule
And so we would think if it's
Black majority rule that it
Would be
The guy in the middle
Who would be the crucial voter
Right if you could line if you pick
Pékin anything like salary
Open Line everybody up
Who wants it the most
Cuz he wants it the least
It would be the guy right in the middle of that day
Players the medium
The answer is
The media player the non Superstar
They don't want all the money to go to LeBron James either
For themselves
Do I think about this I think of Mike Miller
Like one of LeBron James's team
Chances are even a casual fan knows about LeBron James
Probably you've heard of LeBron Superstar teammate Dwyane Wade
The Mike Miller no one outside of a hardcore back
Mike Miller is
He's a good player he's an excellent shooter he plays pretty good defense
But in a non salary cap world
He probably wouldn't be making
Nearly six million dollars a year
What is what is making now
Can a non filler Cap World
Teams would probably want to pay LeBron James a bit more
And Mike Miller
Surpassing even bigger reason
That LeBron James teammates really like this crazy system of the salary cap in the draft
Is it expands the total number of jobs
And here might be instructed to talk about my Washington
Do we have to
Unfortunately I think we did okay I got it
Cuz it's possible that without this system in place
Almost none of the players on my team
We even have a job
Dip for the tie from jannero Pargo
And it gets no I have no room no no nothing so easy to explain we're watching
A sad highlight from a Washington Wizards game of that sort of the opposite of the LeBron James highlights
Final seconds of the game the score is tied
The Wizards player jannero Pargo
Take the shot for the wind and
Hemostat
Hairball
You did as well as
The Wizards are terrible basketball team when you can buy Wizards ticket from a scalper for a dollar maybe even less
The Wizards
Existed in the real economy the Buick Studebaker
Are the Saturday evening post
Out of business
But because the Wizards are a team in the NBA
They don't go
Because
They can always rise again
If they stay one of the worst teams in the league they are guaranteed a really high drafts
Pek
Which means they got a good shot at maybe getting the next level
A great player
Who could
Get the money again
And because of the salary cap system
You'll be able to keep that player
And keep them from getting poached by a richer team in a bigger Market
So the draft system in the salary-cap system
Keeps bad teams from going out of business
And give him a chance to become competitive
Which means are more jobs
People like
Martell Webster Martell Webster Martell Webster
Is one of the worst players on my Washington Wizards
The worst team in Basque
And players like Martell love this
System that hosts LeBron James because without it
Maybe fewer NBA teams
Which means fewer NBA players
Which would almost certainly mean there be no one around to pay 1.6 million dollars a year
Tomorrow
Okay so you got this crazy system that rewards failure in
Encourages collusion by business owners set up essentially a system of conscription
As a method of recruiting and distributing Talent
It's a system that free market economist
Like Kevin Greer the one that we talk to you at the University of Oklahoma
Seem to hate
Right this wrong
You know I think it's not a horrible
Horrible overall cyst
In terms of maximizing
The viability Revenue profitability
So Kevin Kerr may be an economist
Please also a basketball fan
A basketball fan in a very small Market
That has benefited enormously from this crazy stuff
An argument is making is that by making the economics of the NBA as anti-competitive as possible
You make the league
A competitive
So even a fan
Like heaven Greer
Who lives in a small Market town like Oklahoma City
Can root for a really great competitive team
Latinos able to draft
Great players like Kevin Durant and Russell Westbrook
And pay them far less than that actually works
And Kevin Greer is not the only one out there
They're a lot more fans now
And towns all across the country that wouldn't have competitive teams to root for
If not for this crazy system
And more fans all across the country that's good for the NBA
Again
So generally players unions have agreed to
Restrictions
In order to try to increase competitive balance in the league
Which the players believe is going to increase the overall size of the pie
So again if the average sports fan Nationwide is is kind of like me saying
We want every team to have a chance at least every once in awhile to be a contender
If you think that's the sort of thing that most Sportsman's care about then that's going to generate more revenue for the
We as a whole and so the the players want that
That pie to be as big as possible so when they get their slices
As much as they can get
And this brings us to the final answer key to our mystery
There is one group who really doesn't seem to get much out of the rain
LeBron James
And his Superstar Khali
Why don't he and Kevin Durant
And all the other superstars were getting Hoes by the system why don't they band together
And go on strike
That would be the most elite labor action in history Thunder imagine right
Do they have velvet everywhere
But the problem is they kind of benefit from this to
The league overall is bigger and more popular and generating fans and all these towns that otherwise wouldn't have fans
Then that's great for LeBron
Because most of his money
Doesn't come from his salary it comes from endorsements
And the bigger the league is
The bigger his platform is
More money he'll get
For those endorsements
Again
Thomas Victor
So the NBA is a is a relatively
Minor ich component of his overall compensation
But if you wasn't in the NBA that outside compensation wouldn't wouldn't be there
Or wouldn't be there nearly as much I mean if he was the world's if he was like that
The three-time Olympic decathlon
Or he would know in no way be making near the mountains
LeBron James getting paid his full market value but it's not like it's another option that would pay him
More than he makes out getting Hoes by the NBA
The NBA create the market
For his talents
Brighton
LeBron James is a basketball player and is only one National Basketball Association
It was around before LeBron was drafted
And we'll still be around after you retire
The only thing rarer than LeBron James is basketball Talent
Is it basketball league
It will only pay him 17.5 million dollars a year
For that time
Alright a lot has happened to LeBron James insta
Episode first ran he left Miami to go back to
The Cleveland
He has now left
Cleveland to go to Los Angeles
And he's making a ton more money now
What's 17 and 1/2 million dollar salary has jumped to roughly 36 million dollars
Is he still getting hosed
Will find out
After break
Support for this podcast in the following message come from the this week in Google podcast
Stat twit.tv every week
Leo Laporte
Jeff Jarvis and Stacey Higginbotham
Talk Tech media and privacy
They unapologetically question if Google Amazon Twitter Facebook and other Tech Giants are on the right
8-track subscribe to this weekend
Google on your favorite podcast
Or it's wet. TV / twig
Okay figure out if LeBron James is still underpaid we called up one of the economist from that original report
Victor Matheson
From Holy Cross University
He happened to be on vacation at the time in Mexico
I am in Cancun I'm sitting there
Pina colada
A pina colada by the pool under a palm
I could touch a palm tree if I set up
From my love
Well don't do that don't strain yourself
Just Lounge
And we'll ask you about LeBron James
Is LeBron James
Still under page is salaries gone way up
Probably still on the page
LeBron continues to get hoes
Even with a monster deal from the Lakers
Because being the world's greatest basketball player means being responsible for
Huge economic ripple effect
Think of ticket price
Victor
Hope example in Cleveland
Stop the game
Prices for the tickets
Way more than that
Delphine some evidence
Erytop Stars
Might be making even if the NBA Max
Salary
Still might be underpaid by 2030 50%
That means LeBron James may still be underpaid
By around 20
Million
Dollars
Thanks so much
Sure Thing by
For a second opinion on this we called up Brian wind
First from ES
PN he's kind of the LeBron James guy
I sometimes and
Guilty of making things too complex so
Please don't be afraid to say hey you're not talking
NBA Board of Governors are
Luckily Brian says
This is not complex
It's wonderful babe
And
Yes because
By 6 years ago the NBA was bringing in
About seven or eight hundred million dollars per year in television money from there
Broadcast Partners turn on ESPN
That number is now closed
2.4 billion
The TV money has tripled per year Lebron James salary is only a little over double
And of course a big reason TV money is up
Is because of LeBron James
Brian says that
If LeBron salary was not tied up in all those NBA restrict
And if teams were able to pay him whatever they wanted
Migas
Is that a team in a very large Market
Would probably offer LeBron a deal approaching a hundred million dollars
Instead LeBron will have to make do with that 36 million-dollar salary
Oh and by the way LeBron is also getting hit by moving to California
A state with the highest income tax and a much higher cost of living than Ohio
Looks like poor LeBron James just
Can I catch a break
This episode originally ran
I'm back in January of 2013 it was originally reported by Alex blumberg & Taylor Tepper
This rerun was produced by Megan Cain or supervising producer is Alex goldmark or editor is Brian Dozier stats
And LeBron James is better at basketball than Michael Jordan
I'm Kenny Malone
Thanks for listening