Not too long ago I was in Switzer
Geneva specifically
And of course while I was there I did the thing you are expected to do in Switzerland
I ordered fondue
Did the plane funding or
It is a weird meow when you think about it
Especially as a main dish
It is just melted cheese
N scale bread like that is it
Like something a divorced dad
Thought up to feed an 8 year old
Affect my weight or even came over with a spoon
So I can scrape out the bottom of the pot
The end of the phone
Is a the best part of the phone
Scrape off the cheese on the bottom
Yes because so famous in Switzerland
Since I was sadly eating alone I sat there goofing around on my phone
Like trying to answer this question
Googling history of fondue
And that's what I learned this whole fondue thing
He's Not What It Seems
The reason I was eating fondue
The reason that I even know about fondue
The reason I actually own unused fondue pot that I got as a wedding gift
All this goes back
Twin Shadow Association
Swatch Swiss
Cheese dealer
Achieve cartel the basically Ruled The Swiss economy for 80 years
Until fairly recently
Bicycle say Union
Which sounds scary until you hear the English translation
The Swiss cheese Union
The Swiss
Cheese Union
Is at the root of a fondue conspiracy
Hello and welcome to Planet Money on Robert Smith
Today on the show Swiss cheese
A story about what happens when sweet
Well-meaning folks decide the rules of Economics do not apply to them
Who screw up so badly that they have to force the world did gobs of melted fat
By the way this episode was originally reported in 2014
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online
And presents and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layouts along with features including e-commerce functionality
And mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial and when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Hey I'm Kelly mcevers host of NPR's embedded and we've got a new episode all about how Scott Pruitt ended
Running to EPA
It's a story about Peru it's life in the southern baptist
Church that he handled a major pollution case and why he sued the EPA 14 times
Search for embedded on the NPR one app or wherever you get your pack
Episode of the fondue restaurant I discovered
That there is not much on the internet
About the Swiss cheese Union
Four lines in Wikipedia
It was a group of all-powerful cheesemaker
The control prices and supply
Actually it's the kitchen of the restaurant I was at
A place that looks like it buys cheese by the ton
Can I ask to speak to one of the managers
Have you ever heard of the Swiss cheese Union
No never
No one talks about the Swiss cheese Union
I almost thought the whole thing was a hoax
Until I started to call various cheese groups
Switzerland
And the response
We sort of like when you're in Italy and you ask
People about the mafia
They said
Oh we have nothing to do
Swiss Cheese near me
Battlestations defunct
Guys are wearing at the probably really really old
We can't help you
I finally reached the guy of food historian named Dominic flammer
In Zurich
He said
No no I wasn't imagining it
No they don't want to talk to you because they are the survivors of this
Gianni Morales
And they know it has a bad reputation would I say when I say I want to talk to you about Swiss cheese
Yeah they don't talk about that
Dominic wrote this giant book on the
History of Swiss cheese
Even just a small chapter on the Swiss cheese Union got people upset
That was attacked
Buy old members of the Swiss cheese Union because I criticize them
But you know this is what did they say to you
They said I'm not patriotic enough
2 to write about swiss cheese and that I would not be allowed to
To tell a story because I would not help us with cheesemakers but in the end it's accepted today
That directs the truth and nothing but the
Here is the truth
According to Dominic
Like everything in Europe
The Story begins with World War 1
Construction death crippled economies
But the Swiss had a very different problem in the wrestler
The continent
They were neutral in the war
They survived World War One just fine
It is awesome cheese industry still intact
But the customers were gone the customers have been
We can export a lot of cheese before
But in the end of the first World War II and its pretation anymore
More elastic
Nearly till the end of the second World War
Yeah the time between the wars was
Top
Tattoos all over Europe were starting to put up trade barriers
The global economy collapse
Lower cheese stopped
In Switzerland had to suddenly get by on just selling cheese
To themselves
Swiss customer
Usually this would mean that a lot of Swiss Dairy Farmers and cheese maker
Probably go bankrupt
But Switzerland came up with a way that everyone could stay in business
A way to protect themselves
That was the Swiss cheese you
It's what's known as the cartel
An agreement among competitors
Desktop computer
Get rid of OPEC
He was like that
Richie's
Operating a cartel
Is to get everyone
You have to make sure
Everyone every cheesemaker follows the rules
Swiss cheese Union took
Charge
The union set the price for milk
I told dairyman how much milk to produce and who they could sell it to
They told the cheesemakers how much cheese to make
And then set the prices for the cheese
It's all so complicated
Is cheese business
Did they actually narrow down the number of cheeses that people could produce
Switzerland used to make over a thousand different kinds of cheeses
The chief Union
Supported
7 kinds of cheese
Big 2
27 * 4
It's the biggest one with the hose
The outlet the second one the biggest one of the oldest Spanish is to gruyere
And all this was done by the way
With the approval of the Swiss government
Leaving kicked in taxpayer dollars
They subsidize the cheese
Swiss cheese Union basically
When every little part of the industry
And no one could afford to cross the
People did
Dominic Show me the picture of a guy named
Varmint
He he was the cheese Rebel
And Dominic said you know
He only lives an hour away
You should go visit
Okay I'm going to be completely honest with you
This surprised me about Switzer
I knew
The cowbells exist
But I didn't think
They were actually attached
To the cows
These days in the days of GPS but
It is true they do wear the belt
In Switzerland
Really does look like it does on the chocolate wrapper
The Rolling Green Hills the chalets
Brown and white spotted cows he's insanely beautiful
Cows but at this moment seemed very much
In love
With the cheese wrap
These are my girls your girls
The cheese Rebel brought along his son Lucas tell Translate
I told him I was still stunned by how beautiful
This area was
This is exactly how people pictures Switzerland do not right
Yeah yeah I guess that's that
Aristocat marketing thing
Lucas's father Sapp had his run-in with the Swiss cheese Union decade
I still like to tell the story
This area of Switzerland
Was always known for its
Particular Cheese's
Is a special frying cheese
Pronounce
Autosprint
Which Lucas describes as
Little like parmesan from Italy
The cheese Rebels has no no it is better
Take me down into their cheesehaus down a spiral staircase
Into the cellar
And bear of the cheese
How do you picture swiss cheese and I know how you feel
Swiss cheese
Hard stuff
This
Is differin
They're tiny wheels of soft
Coming out of France
Daenerys deep golden brown aged Wheels
This this right here
This was the problem
Sep wasn't in the making the really big popular cheese
At the time he wanted to make Spritz
Justin Smoak
Yeah it was his favourite to be produced it forever
For the cheese Rebel
To decide
Only the Swiss cheese Union was loud
Decision about who made what
In Switzerland
A large part of the country was now producing just those
2 classic
Emmental and gruyere
Springs with a loud
WhatsApp how to apply to the Swiss cheese Union in burn for a license to make the cheese
And it took about eight years until he received
Final m
Information for them years
80s
El Felix
Application paper
8 years of applications and appeals
And the answer from the Swiss cheese Union
Was no
You cannot make Sprint
You can't sell it you can't export it
Why exactly
It's hard to know in the letter they said only quote
You do not fit into the envisaged structure
They say
You are
Toledo
I I I'm too too too small
It's worth noting that Switzerland is and what's the time a modern liberal
By this time it had open competition in baking and Hi-Tech Industries
But if you wanted to make Sprint
Then you had to apply for 8 years and you had to accept no for an answer
Power of a cartel
As for the cheese Rebel
At this point he had nothing to lose
He started to experiment
Mickey's tinysoft
Traditional cheeses
No one had seen or try for years and
It said he couldn't help the big distributors or export it
He sold them one by one
The hotels in small rest
This cheese was called stands or flat
It would later become famous
After the chief cartel was destroyed and step could export again
I'm getting ahead of the story
Because we haven't gotten
Phan tuyet
Well that part of the story
After the break
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One Capital One
Is reimagining banking I offering accounts with no fees or minimums that can be opened from anywhere in
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
I've got that
There is so much political news
Instafollow
But you don't have to keep up
With all of it you just have to keep up with us
On the NPR politics
Sex podcast
You can find us on the NPR one app or wherever you get your pot
The 1950s Switzerland started exports
And with all these subsidies and everyone making the same identical cheese
Swiss cheese Union needed to come up with something
New
Achieve cartel does not prosper
Selling little slices for ham sandwich
Square crackers
They need to find a way to get people to eat
Cheese by the bucket
Dominik flammer says they looked around
And it wasn't one dish that some small towns in the Alps
Used to eat
What you know
Melted cheese always very popular in the Alps
It was when you when you were producing on an Alpine slope cheese
And even you had to melt some to some cheese if you wanted to have something warm to eat
And in the in the 50s they found out that if they want to sell
Overproduction of Swiss cheese
They started to
Search for recipes that cute
The couch help to
To to sell morphe
I'm sure you've already guessed
A big pot of emmental perhaps and gruyere
Stale bread
Fondue with you
If we could sell it with a traditional
A story behind it
To show that cheese was a very healthy food from the Alps
They were using the images of Heidi Heidi land 2
Because this is a story everybody knew worldwide because it was translated
And they took this image of Heidi they they used it also to make publicity for a fun day but
I think the tide you ever ate founded
She ever existed
Heidi is not real
And neither is this over-the-top enthusiasm for fondue
Dominique told me that Swiss people maybe a fondue few times
Definitely in the winter or maybe at a party
Ben swiss cheese ads fondue with life of every party
Good looking
Healthy shoveling cheese in their mouths who didn't want to be Swiss
I thought we had agreed that by the 1970s we are in a period of
Peak fondue
If you grew up in the 70s
Maybe you remember
Little red fondue pot
What the color coded for
McKenna's turnout
Whole Contraption Gathering dust
Up in the shelves
This was the Glory Days for
Swiss cheese
The cartel
Had one
And I picture them all having like a Swiss
Fondue party celebrating the Vic
Swiss cheese around the world
And perhaps when they're having a party they did not notice
It's Switzerland itself
Was Che
Which one was no longer
Dairy Farmers
Raising cows
They were scientist making cancer drug
They were engineers making these
Cool tunneling machine
And the notion of the Swiss government was spending so much effort and money to help out the cheese Union
Start a bug
I guess in the sixties and seventies the cheese-making is with milk producing in Twisted Switzerland
Cost of dissuade State more than than the whole cost for the army of
There's been more on cheese than on the arm
That's what they did okay the Swiss Army is not
That big
But the point here is that agricultural subsidies were taking up a huge
Share of the budget
And then we had a
A kind of Siri
Theories of corruption
Problems within the Swiss cheese Union big surprise
People who were caught
Stealing money
Then we went to jail
By the end of the 1990s
Swiss cheese Union was gone
It was disbanded
The Swiss government continue to subsidize dairies and farmers
Cheesemakers all the sudden had to
I wasn't able to get in touch with any former officials from the Swiss cheese Union
I did find some cheese makers used to be inside the Union
Arena Peter Parker made emmental during the Glory Days
They still do make emmental
But now they only make the cheese every other day
The prices plummeted
Are the neighbors used to run cheese operations
Nonna's cheese houses
Now
House
Who makes
Ontology
To be much more
English pit mix
Peter old Pepsi founded
For 500
House
Out of business
Needless to say they do miss the subs
They missed the steady price
Now she says almost look amazement
Cheese distributors
Only by former it very low prices and if she doesn't sell to them her neighbors will
The competition
Meanwhile the cheese Rebel
Is now just another swiss cheese maker
When the cartel collapse
Sup was suddenly allowed to sell the unique cheese get been working on
He could export them
Anywhere you wanted to
I can buy a beer in Manhattan
I just yesterday I stopped into Fairway at the local supermarket
Can I talk to the cheese guy James Coogan
It's amazing
He says
There has been annexed
Explosion of new cheeses from Switzerland
We have now available to us some
Really cool stuff other than
Gruyere
Amazon
You know what your everyday absolutely important cheeses
But this stuff
Beautiful
Sexy
Delicious
That's something you going to see everywhere
He told me he'd vaguely heard of the Swiss cheese cartel
But it doesn't really come up much anymore
Before you write in
Tell me how much you love fondue I will say for the record
I finished the entire pot a fondue
But I actually pretty good if you'd like to write in about anything on Planet Money
Email us Planet Money at npr.org
You've been introduced today's episode and just Jang help out with a lot of information gathering and finding swiss cheese make
Robert Smith