Do you have economic questions rattling around in your head
Driving you nuts
Keeping you awake at night
You tried shutting me out a window
Hotel rooms
But nobody answer
Your phone doesn't know what you're talkin about
Why are rotisserie chickens so cheap
I can help you find restaurants if you turn on the
Hey Google who has the time anymore
Why are
Swiss franc
Safe
Hello I know I know you're ready to give up
But there is hope
Hello I'm lighter podcast celebrity Robert Smith
Is there a Planet Money we've come up with a miracle answer system
You simply guess your question
Play Planet Money
And our team will do the Google
The reporting for you
It's any answers directly into your earbuds
Easy peasy
And work
How many minutes of your life
Would you expect to give up for all the answers you could ever want
45 minutes
3 minutes
We are planning a special deal for a listener
We're going to do it again
British Nick fountain
23 minutes
I've been recorded this but even I'm impressed with that
Do not miss out satisfaction guaranteed
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence
And run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial and when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Hey we just wanted to let you know that invisibilia
NPR show that the invisible forces shaping our behavior is back
On March 9th for the new season
This time of taking out some the biggest cultural fights of our time Russian hacking reality TV the me-too
Name a few
You can listen And subscribe to invisibilia on the NPR one app or wherever you get your podcast
People are saying to me Robert
What lizards of Planet Money
Really
Want to know
What is the number one question you get over and over again through the years
And I'll tell you what the quest
Disinfect this time it was
Chad Rohde
And the question is
Hey you know if you ever seen a coupon in tiny print
Ulta coupon it says cash value
Cash value 1
Avocet
Who is asking
What does that mean can you actually get tired of a truckload
Of coupons together and get real money could you buy a house if you
You had
Enough coupons
I think you would probably be able to build a house out of coupons before you could actually buy one but
Everyone
I kind of I think I have an answer for you
Okay where did this come from what is the deal with it
So
To answer this question I
What's the most obvious
This place I could
Imagine the coupon Institute
You're not
Far off the association of coupon professionals which
Is real and the executive director pick up the phone right away and he said
Cash value thing
We get this like every 6 months I really should have a file on hand
Their butt
I don't at the moment but here's a phone number for someone who will
Know the answer
Hello
Jesus head
Yeses
This is Edward Quebec
The association of Nashua
Advertise
A&A
Right yeah of course the coupon cash value thing
Drive from the relationship to the old trading stamps
Oh these were I you know I am
Old enough to remember these
If you would get
A bunch of stamps when you bought a
Productivity
Grocery store regular store whatever
And you put this into a buck and collecting stamps
And if you got enough of them
You could get like a like a
Oster Crock-Pot or a blender
Key Program
Four stores
That's right so so back when these programs were popular there
With some country
There wasn't like a lot of transparency around who actually benefited
And whether consumers were sort of being scammed
And so a number of different state legislature
Pass laws it said
Did you want to do the program you need to put like some
Nominal cash value on the stamps so that like
If I don't really want to go buy a
Poster I can
Use the stamps and cash them in
For money
Makes sense but how did this get on coupons today you look but here for the
Magic of tea Celestial Seasonings $1 out it's Stacey Vanek Smith coupon
This is cash value .001 set how do I get from stamps to this thing
So
Train stamps were butts
Predecessor to
The coupon that we know now and
Because these laws are on the books it's
Easier to put that nominal cash value
Yuan the coupon then to
Search by the laws
Did Hillary tell you if anyone
Uses this fine print and give cash back to the Go I mean of course I asked him about this like
How do I turn this
Celestial Seasonings
Coupon in for its cash
Well that's another question
Procedure for that
That's Amore complex
It's just like so ludicrous that he hasn't even explored this option
But
Seems to me like
Worth exploring right
Thank you for calling Celestial Seasonings
We invite you to bring the perfect balance
To your day
Hey I got a very nice customer service rep named Grace
Yes how can I help you go through the same thing you know I've got this mint scented coupon from you guys at
Worth a fraction
Of a penny
How do I get
That money
Lake is there a way to do that I fat
Never been asked
Before
Now that have you ever seen a coupon and wondered about the cash value thing yourself
I've never looked at the cash value
Honestly
Is very small
I'm going to look at it now and see how much
So
Grace Grace probably should try to get an answer but
I got this
This recording wechat
But I've already loaded up a truck
With ten thousand of these coupons headed
Towards Celestial Seasonings headquarters Kenny I actually think this is worth playing out for any Planet Money listeners
Is it major thinking about give
Because like thinks
Think through this with us for
For just a second
Most of these coupons are worth 1/100 of a cent so
Like let's say you managed to Wrangle 10000 coupons you happen upon them laying around 10,000
The same manufacturer
You're going to package those up
How much would that even way Academy have to send them someplace and then you would get
$1
But you would be a coupon Legend
Thanks you're welcome
There's some questions that are timeless
The gaskets of over and over and over again and you start to suspect that there is no answer to this question
Is God real
That is not one of the questions Nick Fountain what is the quest
The question comes from Seth Engel of Oakland California
Why is rotisserie chicken so cheap
Seems like an unnatural bargain
What's the catch
Write this happen to me
Just this past weekend
I was shopping and I noticed
The rotisserie chicken no smell
Upgrade pal the spices on it already cooked
599 for the whole chicken
I walk around the corner to where the rock chickens are
They're more expensive
10 or 12 bucks
So why is it cheaper to have someone else do the roasting and all the work
For you
And my working here this Nick
Is
That they're using old
Using expired
Chickens
I thought that too
So I went to your local supermarket my local supermarket in Brooklyn Steve's C-Town
And I found Rudy Rivera he's the deli manager
My first big question
By the way this smells delicious
Is
You sure that when
The meat department
Seeing that some chickens are going bad you sure they're not sending some over to you guys
Oh no we would never do that that's totally different chickens
I would never do it anyway
Yunnan
I live
Around here and also
I shop here
I would never do that
I didn't quite believe him 100% but he was like
We're getting a delivery of them right now come out to the truck
Yeah
Mine
Zoo what does it say
He's pulling boxes of raw chicken off the truck
Can you bring some back to the cooler and he opens them up and shows me the
The vacuum sealed in there
Already seasoned what can I season Italian
Plain & BBQ
To do they do a rub on the outside as well
Why did they inject them
Second day in Jack
Them that's the first thing I learned that's amazing
That is some high-level
Chicken mating
Yeah it means that there's not that much labor that goes
It's right so
You think that you're getting such a deal out of these roaches
Three chickens to their like rubbing them and then they're putting them in there
And they're doing the dishes
No they're injected probably by a robot at a big Purdue Factory all Rudy have to do is show up at 6 a.m.
Put the chicken in the oven
Ant trap 3 hours later
Rudy is checking the temperature of the
It's already at 180
It's going 190
Boom
Perfect
Take this cleanup
Took the boats outboard
Already got the prices on them
We put them in the heater
Are you going to do that right now
Okay so I understand
Did Steve C-Town supermarket has a kind of assembly line thing going here they can do it for super cheap
599 still
Seems cheaper than what it would cost me to cook that chicken mites
Robert you are run you fell for the oldest trick in the supermarket play but you were just looking at the price of the whole chicken
Write the raw chicken in the rotisserie chicken
But what you didn't notice is the rotisserie chickens are really small
Little over two pounds
So rude and I we do the math it's a little bit complicated because the chickens was a little bit of weight when they're cooking but whatever
We figured out that the price for rotisserie chicken
Per pound is more expensive than the price
Huaraches
So let me let me look at your calculations here
Customers are paying at least in our supermarket in Brooklyn customers are paying $0.06 more per pound for a rotisserie
Chicken
Then the rock chick
I know it's a small number 6 sense
So it's probably worth it for the convenience to
By the
Rotisserie chicken
But still it makes economic sense if the prepared food item
Cost more
Then the Rock
Totally and
I did do a little more reporting than just going to our local supermarket I called at the USDA
They pointed me to this awesome chart the USDA National Retail report for chicken where they like
Look at every Supermarket circular that they can find an a
See what the advertised prices are
And Nationwide this difference is even more pronounced
What's the price per pound for whole bag
Fryers which is like what we would
About a buck per pound and the price for rotisserie chickens is around $2 in
$0.35
Per pound
Still worth it
Totally
It's very convenient
Thank you
Thanks
Answer some
Collateral economics questions will do that after work
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Is reimagining Bank
I offering account
With no fees or minimum
Memes that can be opened from anywhere in
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Na
Your questions here to Planet Money are not all
Just fun
Games
And roasted chicken
We have
Serious
Probably econ students who demand answers to Serious economic questions with one of those questions
Here now is
Julie Simon hey how's it going
Let's hear the question
The question is
From Spence
Henderson in Birmingham Alabama
Why are they
Swiss franc and Japanese Yen
Considered Safe Haven
During times of uncertainty
We should probably start by
Explain the term
Safe Haven
So in the case of
Japan
Drain the great financial crisis when
People are panicked about banks around the world
The value of the Japanese Yen
Went up
Money poured into Japan
And it happened again during the European financial crisis
Begotten waddup actually happened
Last
Month
With the stock market dipped around the world
The Japanese garden
What up
So Julia Y in times of crisis
Do people send their money to an island
In Asia
Right or a mountainous country in Europe like Switzerland
Will these countries have a lot going for
Japan and Switzerland they have stable economies
They have trustworthy institutions
Save a lot of money sloshing around
That's true
So I called up Jane Foley she's a foreign exchange expert at Rabobank
And I asked her why Japan and Switzerland are
So special
And she told me
That the thing about these country
Is that they have a lot of pee
People saving a lot of money
They got all the savers
Putting their money in
Thanks
An investment plan
And in Good Times
This money goes all around the world
But when times get rough
The Japanese in the Swiss
They get scared
I generally what
Savers do when this times of crisis
Something bring that money
So all that money
Comes back into
Meaning there is more demand for the Japanese Yen being the Japanese Yen value starts to go up
Yeah and people all around the world are saying hey look at the Japanese Yen why did I put my money over there
Until people all around the world
Piling on
The longtime listeners a Planet Money may remember
That when your currency is strong
It's not
Always
A good thing
For the
It is not always so great
Because think about it
All those cool Japanese comic books or a Swiss Army knife
When the price of the Yen or the Swiss franc goes up
It's more
Expensive for people around the world
To buy those exports
So the Japanese
The Swiss
Be kind of resent being the safe haven currency
I was joking around with James Foley about
Can I give you an analogy do you think that this analogy works
That it's like
Being a designated driver
Ouu
Good in some ways because you're safe but you
Can't have it
Any fun
Yes
If it is
What not. That was a load of responsibility
Angers you can't have any fun in it does limit
There
Hello.
Plate well thank you Switzerland in Japan for being there for us I'm going to transfer my money there as we speak and thanks doing
Makes Robert Glenn
O'Sullivan
I was wondering
Why do most hotels
Not have Shield
I have thought about this to you know you going to a hotel
And you turn on the light in me being a little entryway the light goes on
But the rest of the hotel room is dark and you have to wander around and
And figure out if
Light switch near the bulb
The bottom
Stumbling and tripping over things
This is a weird thing about hotel room so I talked to some architects
Lighting designers
And I have
3 amp
Answer number one
Lighting designers hate
Ceiling light
They all talk about there's this one blurring light everyone looks bad in the Euro lighting
Designer so what you want is
Bombilla
Mood
So they want all of these table lamps
Lighting and
And their first go to is to spread the lamps around the room
Which
Leave me
The answer number to why not connect all those lights with one switch
Answer number two is
Switches are
Expensive
And the more switches
You have specially these 3-way switches you need to
Control everything the more money it cost and if you do nothing for the room
I can bust your budget
I swear on switches alone
And then
There's answer
Number three
3 which I found fascinating
And she said you know if
A hotel room lights are driving you crazy
Because when you come right down to it
Lighting schemes
Are crazy they're not intuitive
I need to quit your old home for a second some lamps have switches at the top and some have
Floor switches
And some have Wall switches
But you already memorized that you don't think about it
Quick quick quick quick quick
All of a sudden your whole room is flooded with light
But the moment you walk to a hotel room or any unfamiliar place
You think you're going crazy cuz you have no idea which switch corresponds to what light you don't know how to get the light anywhere you
You wanted to be
Just making the point you know she hears he's complained all the time about lighting in the hotel room
And she said you're maybe it's just because you haven't spent enough time there
To get used to
Study figure out the system
You check out
And you moved on to the next one
Our next question is a quick one
And as nerdy
As a death in the economics world
Patty Hearst
The editor for
Decatur
Uber-nerd hello
So the question came from Bryan
Knowles
And what's the question
So the question is
What is a giffen good
Things that I've read about but I have not
Consolidated
And the reason really is for that is because
It basically a unicorn
Okay it's a concept that dreamed up by this
Victorian Chapel
Sir Robert giffen
Who claimed to have identified certain products
The people consume more of
As the price goes up
Violates the law of supply and demand
Absolutely does rising prices and Rising demand usually when prices go up demand.
Notable except
What's the distance
Okay let's just go over
The first is when the product is a luxury item like a limited editions
Score to the manufacturer wants to make the car and exclusive purchase
That signal status
So they crank up the price and maybe reduce the
Supply forcing scarcity on the market
I'm hopefully driving demands
Secular cases the more you spend on
Collectible watch
Sports car in fact
The happy you are because you can Lord it over
We are friends
Drop them out
Exactly so you see demand and price rising at
At the same time in those
Cases with this particular type of good
But those very specific could you see them all the time a giffen good
It's something very very
Beaufort you pretty much never see it
Because for a product to qualify as a giffen good
It has to be a staple
Or something of comparatively low value so not like a watch
Has to be something like
Bread flour all the time
When the price
Goes up
We consume more of
The house that work
Well it only works
If there's no substitute
So free sample Robert Griffin
Was studying poor people in Victorian times
Malaysian hundred
He came up with the example of bread
That's right he said that when the price of meat
Became too high for poor people they bought more bread
That increase in demand
Time for bread Drive the price of bread High record
Because there's no alternative to bread by
Noodles or rice and
In the in the way that we do
Do today
There was no alternative
I'm meat prices were still too high people have no choice
What to buy more bread even though the price kept Rising
And the more money the poor were paying
Breadman that there was even
Less money
For me
So they had to buy even more bread and so on and so forth
It could go on forever and Siri
These days like in the present not in fear
I can't even think of something
For which there is no
Substitute
Thinking
You Gatlin
You got something that we seen today
At least at least eight very rarely happens right that might have happened in the late 1800 today there was so many Alternatives that you can buy
Rice is very difficult to find a good example of
It's the worst
Summer search done in China
But suggested that in certain parts of that country
The price of rice and noodles went up and people still kept on buying them when meat so expensive
But for the most part
The concept
Demand for a staple product increasing at the same time as prices rising
It's pretty much a mirage
Rare bird that you know
Burgers aren't sure if it even exists or not and if anyone out there see something that qualifies as giving good they should contact us will it will
Safari app
To go look for it
And send them apprised of
Thank you Patty
Thank you
I know what you're thinking you're thinking I had a question and yet I didn't get it in in time for your annual question show
But you know what will take your questions anytime
Anywhere anyhow
Emails Planet Money at npr.org
We really do read every single email
We're also on Twitter Facebook
And my favorite instant
Tricia Spruce by Sally helm
And Nick fountain or chicken man
Casino producer of Planet Money is Alex goldmark our editor is Brian first at
And special thanks today to to am architectural friend Ron Neal
And Michelle
Also we are still looking for summer
Intern
This
Is a crepe
Ja it is paid you get to be at on our edits in our story ideas
This is a job
That you what
You're in school or have recently graduated you can find out more info
Npr.org
Money
I'm Robert Smith
Thanks for listening
There was a coupon
A coupon in a violent little thing you
Abusive
Paper that is redeemable for
Goods at a spider.
It's like Groupon
Hibbett coupon