Back in 2011 Sonja trauss
Was 29 year old living in St Louis
And she was at a kind of
Crossroad
She just failed out of a Ph.D program if you can.
Really did not want to go home to fill it up
Because I have left being Lexia guys only get a PhD and I just couldn't go home after that
You're not getting it she moved in with her dad's cousin for a few months in El Cerrito just north of Berkeley
California
Got a job teaching math
At a community college in Marin
Marin County is super
Expensive like most areas around
San Francisco Bay
So she found a place
In Oakland
And her commute was
Terrible
So she spends hours every week
On our way to work with that
Economist brain
Spinning
Calculating I made $20 an hour
But I calculated my real wage when I took into account how much it cost to get there and how much
Aurora News 12
So I put that job
And got a job in a bakery where I made 1250 an hour
I wanted to move
But I couldn't even afford to move until I was reading the paper about people who are Jews
His place because
They couldn't afford
Stay
And I was like this place
And terrible you can't afford to
Stay if you want to leave you can't afford to leave
Cuz you can't save any money because moving costs
It just felt so grim
And everybody in the Bay Area and and
Big city now knows a horror story about housing
And a lot of them are way worse
If the garage is p
Cars
Poor shelters
Some people just take it as a fact
San Francisco has
Expensive housing the same way it has fog
Just does
What Sonja trauss doesn't take
Granted not after all those years
And economics
One Night in 2014 she's walking down the street in San Francisco on her way to hear some music
China bar
And in the window of that bark she sees a sign
She seen me signs here and there in the neighborhood
It says help us stop this developer
From building a big new apart
And that's not
It makes her so
Mad
Like trigger something in Huracan brand because she's thinking that apartment building is exactly what I need it's what the whole
Sitting
Will the housing shortage
The way you fix a shortage build more housing
So simple
And at that moment
Looking at that sign
She thinks
The people who put that sign up
They probably own home
They're not struggling.
They're making things worse for the rest of us
And she cried
I was just like screw you guys like I know what you
Do you make posters you write letters
You go to hearing
Thanks
So I saw that side and I was like I'm going to make signs to you know I'm going to make a website to
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Dan Charles how to fix the housing crisis
Dark Side of those cities that seem so great
Until you actually have to live there
Rent you can afford skyrocketing home prices
All kinds of ways to make housing affordable out of those things
Don't work very well
There is a solution now
It's simple it really works only problem is just about everybody hates it
Including maybe the most powerful bunch of
People in the country do we dare speak their name
Support for this podcast
Send the following message come from Fidelity invest
As a Fidelity wealth management client
You get a dedicated advisor
Hair to help grow and protect your well
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes
And make it clear recommendation
Pins for your full Financial
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
There was something but Sonja trauss found
Really weird when she first got in
This housing fight it was how people just were not talking about the one thing she thought would do the most
Sound like
Silly but it is really really
True that
You could not
Play company
You could not come out and say
I think
We need more housing I think development might be a good thing you could not say that it was ghost
Now that's not complete
There were Builders who are saying
What you need is more Construction
Let us do it
But why should we listen to greedy developers they just want to make money
Sonia's feeling was
Okay so they're greedy
So what
Well I don't see what the point is in moralizing something like that like it doesn't seem like it helps the problem
I actually think that's why I went into economics because economics
Generally it is that one of the values that underlies it is that
Moralizing about people's behavior
Isn't super productive
Yeah there's another popular response to housing crisis
Rent control rent control
San Francisco has tried it a lot of cities try it
You just make a law that says
You can't raise the rent
Antonio says that is all well and good if you happen to be living in one of those rankings
But it's not enough
You still need to sell the shortage
Right around this time she comes across an article in the news
A quotes an economist
Enrico Moretti who as it happens lives
Right in her backyard at the University of California
Berkeley
I'm already is quoted in this article saying
People here in the Bay Area should be Marching for more housing
He identified exactly
What the problem was and he was the only way this is going to get solved
Is if citizens groups
Start
That asked for housing
It was like a call to Arms
Address just to her start that group make those posters build the movement to give capitalist
What's the chance
So she sent them an email
And I was like you wrote about us
You know you predicted that this is a thing that could happen within the needs to happen and it's happening now
What did you think
When you got this invitation from Sonja trauss
I was pleased that was organizing
Is event
And that she invited
Even though he acts
I couldn't make it
Office hour slots
Two PowerPoints
When I talked to Andre comb already on Skype he was way off in the Alps on vacation
But still thinking about those housing prices in California
Fundamentally the problem of housing cost in the Bay Area is a problem of demand and supply
It sounds so basic lots of people want to live there and not enough time to go around
And it's a self-inflicted shortage
Local governments have made it hard to build housing
Does restrictive zoning neighborhood councils get to up
Object file endless apps
Even against something like a modest little building in the most convenient of location
Deposition tube
Even
You know Toy Story that elements next
The train station
Remain fierce
Haha
And I really don't
1st and Noe Dunkin Donuts
Position
When governments create a housing shortage this way don't just make life miserable for people
It forces people into decisions that hurt the whole economy maybe nurses abandon their jobs in San Francisco the Whole Health
Meridiana Kali put a price tag on the local housing District
And it was astounding
They calculated that over the last 50 years
Three cities
San Francisco San Jose in New York
They cut their growth rates
I artificially driving up the cost
Across the entire American economy
A trillion and a half.
So the problem
Israel it's
Huge
And here's how you organize the saw
Step one former Club
Give me the name of the catchy Act
Can I call the SF Bay Area renters Federation sfr
Lovett step to invite people to party start. Getting angry together
Kind of fun
I met Laura Clark at one of those parties she was one of the first people to join up with some
Oh yeah Sonia was
She was angry first and I got the girl run around and be like yeah yeah I'm going to go do what she's doing
We're going to go yell and it'll respond
Exciting
Go get a drink and then we'll like
You know gossip local politics and
Make it into a whole event
The anger bonding was real
And it felt like it was a battle of
Generation
Renters versus owners young people demanding change
Against old people
Good dinner wildin like your neighborhood
Just fine the way it was
Derogatory name for people who don't want new stuff in their neighborhood
Nimbi NIMBY not in my backyard
Sonia and her friends
Call themselves
Yimby yes in my backyard
You're so much more friendly
Step 3 go to meetings
Sign up to talk
Hi
My name is
This was a city planning meeting in West Oakland four years ago when Tony was just getting started
She walked up to the microphone
Tank top
Colorful tights
New houses
Cars rent
Thrive
No
Rising winds
Call capitalist
Houses
She's like an exasperated math
Teacher hurt her speech was pretty much the same everywhere
Build as much as possible as
Fastest
But the people she was fighting against we're different depending on the neighborhood
In working-class play
Places like West Oakland
People were suspicious of new development
Because they worried that it would mean
Richard people
Why people would take over the neighborhood
If your voice
Landlords would take this is an upscale neighborhood now maybe I will
Evict my tenant
Building
My money so their other places.
Like wealthier parts of Berkeley in San Francisco
There it was people with multimillion-dollar homes you didn't want new development because of it noise
Construction
Bigger buildings messing up their quiet streets and beautiful views
NIMBY
It seemed like everybody had a different reason.
Tuseno
Not here
And I say it loud
Right into a microphone
Recorded for pasta
Yes there are tapes
Lordy this is like SportsCenter highlights
Local democracy in action
Tete-a-tete
The meeting in Berkeley
The 10th last night
A developer wanted to put up a big new apartment building where there used to be a drugstore
And some people didn't like it said this monstrosity will block
The great view Sonia was there with some of her yimby friends and one of the other speakers turned on them
I also want to say that this little group
People over here
Is led by a woman who supposedly from what I understand lives in Oakland
And goes around to Albany San Francisco and Berkeley
Talking about the development just because she loves it so
We don't really know where she's getting her life
Because she will tell us
Wait
You have your
This can only be a friend group
Roosevelt
Personals ads
Are you going to let me have my time and then Kristoff and after
Sonja trauss got to the microphone and few minutes later
When you shop for housing
Glenwood says
Piano first lesson
Deposit and actually you know what I want
The front
Feel like I can't do that or else you can rent
How many units are there open
That's very powerless position
Please don't push us this powerless position
Property values go up
When you don't build enough
It's that econ Branigan
She's thinking if the homeowners keep new homes off the market their own homes are worth more
You can say I'm a developer but
I think that you're here as a greeting homeowners
So she and her friends were saying bill bill bill
Private development government subsidized housing
We want it all and more and more other people were saying things that were kind of similar
The mayor of San Francisco
Thai medley
He said what's it at Target
5000 new housing units
So it really seemed like progress but
When it came to real decisions there were a lot of set
Prince a couple of years after she started her
Grip the San Francisco Board of Supervisors
Which is what they call their city council was considering a new law
It would have allowed taller buildings
Denser housing into residential
Sweat the housing areas called zoning
I'm sending Bill and Sonia was a big fan
But at Community meetings around town
It did not go over well
It was terrible every
Meeting
Everybody who spoke up
Totally against
Another meeting
Hey sup was fierce over new condo building in the heart of the mission
Now seriously
You may know the mission
The working-class Latina neighborhood gentrifying a lot of people don't like that they didn't like the new condo building either
Like Scott Weaver from the Latino cultural disc
City council
Valencia Street you can have a meal for $5,200
Person you can buy fancy
The clothes you can spend $350
Forehand
These are not the types of businesses
That belong in the Latino Cultural District
Sanya got up
She laid into the building
And when you come here to the Board of Supervisors
And say that you don't want new different people in your neighborhood
You're exactly the same as Americans all over the country that don't want immigrants
It is it is the same attitude it is exactly.
That's one supervisor who said he
Come to the meeting
Intending to vote for the building
Now he wouldn't just because he didn't want to be on the same side of the issue is Sonia
The vote was 9 to nothing to delay
Fernando Marti had been on the opposite side of Sonja trauss at a lot of these meeting
Is the co-director of the Council of community housing organizations on the group
Fighting gentrify
Application in the mission
And he has two basic disagreement
The Emmys one of them is
The emps complain a lot about neighborhood making it hard to
Building
But Fernando says that's not the main reason there's a shortage of housing he says the big problem is
It's just really really expensive to build anything in the Central District
San Francisco is so expensive
The only kind of housing that developers can figure out how to
Finance is high-end Condos for rich people
They would build
Cheaper if they could but they can't
So they just build for that top
2%
The other thing that gets on his nerves is when these
Mostly young mostly white mostly educated DMVs
Adopt a language of civil rights
When they say the way Sonja said in that meeting that
You know folks in the mission are like nativist trying to keep new people out of their neighbor
I think people who have
Seen the effects of
Redlining
Gentrify
Vacation
And eviction
They want to be able
Shape their own community and shape what
Comes in
Sonia isn't apologizing for what she said at that meeting
But she was
Listening
She changed her mind about so
It started with something that she read
Probably scanning hurt
Somebody who's associated with Mission activist
Was saying
It's not fair
That all the housing is going
The mission
And not
The Westside
And I thought
True
That isn't fair
That's a great point
She realized she'd been thinking too small
Cheap spend so much time going to where the arguments were
Four arguments over this with that building
But the arguments weren't even happening in most of the city
The quiet residential part of the city mostly on the western
There were no arguments because you couldn't even think about building an apartment building there
Because of zoning rules
She realized to make a real difference those rules had
So that's the new yimby campaign their new slogan legalized housing everywhere
Not just because it's fair
But because
It's cheaper
You can add a lot of new apartments in these residential play
Places without having to build those
Expensive high-rises made of concrete
Insteel actually solving our problem in California and probably anywhere in the US
Is only going to happen
If we
Allow
Miles and miles
Acres and Acres
Of single-family large light neighborhoods
To become places
With mixed housing
People need to be able to allow their single family homes
Turn down
And build a fourplex
Maybe even if
10 unit
Garden Apartments so the new and latest phase of this campaign to make new construction cool
She's going after the suburbs
I'm serious when I say everywhere
Not kidding
There's a town sitting right on Annex
Expensive Commuter Rail Line it will not allow some apartment buildings
Let's get built
Sanya suing them
And in the past year so they can be said even started making some political progress
Remember that proposed
Is law that was going to maybe allow denser housing Construction in parts of residential service
With the housing people call up zoning such a hostile
Perception when they introduced it in 2000
16 about a year later when they went around again
By that time Jimmy's had started organizing in some of the West Side neighborhood
And so the second round of community meeting
There were like three or five you know half a dozen
Jimmy's
People who said I think this might be a good idea
I think this could help our neighbor
And just having them there
Wheatley change the possibilities for the bill
Last year the supervisors passed it 11 to 0
When it finally passed it was the first time
Ever
In the history of
The universe
That there had been an up zoning in the westside of Saint Francis
I just a couple of months ago San Francisco elected a new mayor London breed
Should grown up in public housing in the city
And she made more housing a big part of our
Right away
In her inauguration speech
She sounded a lot like AUB
The politics of no has
Play Garth City for farts
Too long
Not on my block not in my backyard
We have made a mistake
It's in the past by not moving housing production
Fort Worth all over this
And I plan to change the politics of no to the
The politics of yes
Yes we will build more houses
That is the new mayor of San Francisco
Insomnia trial
She is running for a seat on the San Francisco Board of Supervisors
The elections in November she's got three more months to make her case
Support for this podcast and the following message come from fidelity
As a Fidelity wealth management client
You get a dedicated advisor
There to help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes
And make clear recommendations for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage services
Is LLC
We post a link to every episode of Planet Money on Facebook
If your thoughts about housing in the Indies leave a comment on the post we read every single one of them you're looking for another
Funny economics podcast there is our other podcast the indicator comes out everyday 10 minutes or less this week
Explain Adam Smith
Diamond and water Paradox you need water to live it don't need diamonds so why are diamonds more expensive
Paradox subscribe to the indicator from Planet Money wherever you get your vodka
You can also get in touch with us
Twitter or Instagram
But at Planet Money we read all the emails to Planet Money NPR. Org
Today Show was produced by Sally Hill Taylor Haney
Dorset is our editor you Alex goldmark are the senior producer that is true I'm Dan Charles
And I'm the aforementioned Alex go fly thank you for listening
Announce
Last night's meeting
My family has lived 75 years in our home
And I don't plan on leaving
Until I'm in a box busy we've lived there so what we've lost six cats
To that street
That's how crazy
Children like plants
Need lights
To thrive