Hey it's Nick.
Today I got up at 4 in the morning
Biking to work
And pulled up a livestream
Have a news conference in Sweden morning everyone and
Welcome to the Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences
Today is like the Superbowl for economist
Or more accurately
Econ Nobel.
Or even more accurately the Ellis medicine expire
PCA Columbus
About to announce
William nordhaus
We know that guy
We did a show about one of his papers back in 2014
And today he won the prize for his work on climate change
Now he shares the prize with Paul Romer
Of NYU
His work
Is about how economies grow
Or as the committee said integrating technological innovations
In the long run macroeconomics
Analysis
So today to celebrate the winners we are going to replay that episode we did with Bill nordhaus a few years
Years ago.
Long before there were light bulbs
There was fat
For thousands of years if you wanted to light up your cave your mud hut or
If you were really lucky Your Castle
You had to find some fat
Something to use for a wick
Maybe some more
Fabric
This was not easy
Even today
It's a hard way to get low
Yeah hi do you sell
Fat Moody fat
No
No I don't carry. No
Okay thanks very much
A high
Giselle love fat like beef fat
Suet
Okay
Thanks Rich
Yeah hi I do so
Beef fat
How much is that
298 a pound
Okay great thanks very much you're welcome
I got to lb
Big nasty lump of fat
Came from around the couch kidney
I got some twine from the hardware store
And I went home to my Apartments have
TriMet candle
Google harder to catch up then
You might think
Sticks to itself
I put the fat on the stove
It's pretty melted
Smells really
Nasty
Animal nasty
Stranded then I started dipping the Wicks into it
Dipping dipping
You have to let the fat dry when you have to dip the wick some more
Dipping
Was Eddie
I don't know 45 minutes or so of dipping
Dip
Deal I got kind of dip crazy in there
Deal
After hours of work
Not counting raising the cow or killing the cow or making the twine
I had fixed
Tiny
Crooked
Smelly candles
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm taking Golden State and I'm David kestenbaum today on the show
Story of how we got from dim little candles made out of cow fat to as much light as we want at the flick of a switch
And I don't think I'm exaggerating here this one little story
It explains why we are where we are today by billions of people don't have to worry about starving today while we aren't also
Assistance Farmers why we can't afford to have artist massage therapist and plumbers and yes radio reporter
Doing stories about the history of light
This message comes from NPR sponsor squares
Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their own website
Using customizable Leo
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobiledit
Squarespace also offers
Built and search engine optimization
To help you develop an online presence
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Jacob you brought these scraggly little candles in the office I'm holding him up here they look
Gnarled
They're definitely not straight and they're not like
Sleek looks like some mold has grown on
On a string
String
So you brought these candles in the office here and we wanted to show them to
An expert
We sat down with this woman Jane Brock
Jane wrote a book called brilliant the evolution of artificial light
So I made a few different candles
I tried
Beautiful Disaster
In the in the olden days
If a mother was trying to teach your daughter to make candles
She would not be pleased with these candles
But we'll see what happens
I was afraid when we let these things that we might set off
The fire alarm or the
Sprinkler system in the office I mean that is how weird it is to have light from fire
I was afraid we weren't going to be able to light him at all
It's just
Beef fat and wine
But we pulled out a lighter
We have we have lights
That should we see how long it lasts
It's not pretty but I'm very impressed
Beautiful colors we would have been nice yellow flame wouldn't you say
Duty made a candle
Jane says that the quest
For this for
Something that gives you light
After the sun goes down
Go people to do all kinds of
In the United States in the Pacific Northwest
Native Americans used dried
Salmon
Basically made a salmon candle
In the tropics people would catch fireflies and try to make
A firefly Lantern
And then there's this bird called the petrol
The storm Petrel
And then north of Scotland where they would just
At which is a very oily seabird
Which they catch and dry
And thread a wick down its throat and then light it and
And that was a lamp
Chiron a dead bird without a table
And I would imagine they'd have a little storage area with a lot of dead dogs vegetables
Martha we need another petrol
The petrol supply is getting low displays of making light where all
A huge hassle
They took a lot of work
It was not just that I didn't know what I was doing when I made those candles
The writer Harriet Beecher Stowe said
Making candles from animal fat with
7 times as bad as washing clothes I mean think about it you got to get a cow you got a raise the calorie going to have food
Feed the cow you got to kill the cow you got to get the fat out of the couch
You got to put the fat in your Cuisinart
Which isn't going to be invented for a hundred years
From an economic perspective if you want to try to quantify how much of
Pain in the butt it is to make something or at least how hard it is to get that thing
You can ask a simple question
How much does it cost
Bill nordhaus Anaconda Misty yellow while back got obsessed with a
This question he decided he wanted to calculate exactly how expensive light was
Thousands of
And how that cost change.
Because light you know light is this thing Society has needed and sought
Forever
It was a way to track progress
Not just in light but in all kinds of
Unfortunately in order to do this
He needed to know how much things cost thousands of years ago
Like an ancient babel
Was even trailers numbers exist
But they did
I ran into a woman at Yale
And she believe it or not
Huey is just
Unbelievable actually
She actually had wage data and price data
From
The Babylonian era
4000 years ago
Now he has these numbers but he needs to know one other thing
How much light are people getting for their money
In ancient Babylon people used lamp
4 light
So nordhaus
Decided to make
I did this in my dining room
Where else
Devised an ancient style lamp from catalog he gets it burning
Measure how bright it is he borrows a light meter from a facility sky at Yale
And he does some science
And that would just measure it then write it down
It's the way you see in the
In the old movies are some guy with in his lab coat running down the measurements
Jacob
I'd little note here I happen to be taking nordhaus has economics class right around this time
Which I was a was a pretty serious
Like a no-nonsense class
And it's so funny for me to think that night he was going home and measuring ancient lamp placement is dining room with a light
Who does this the light meter the ancient lamp numbers but now
You have to
Figure out a way to compare the price of light over thousands of years
So here's one measure heat
If you take
A day's wages
You work all day you take all the money or not
And you spend it online
How many minutes
Could you light up a small
With as much light as you get from
Today's Modern Life
You're the answer for ancient Babylon
Maybe 10 minutes
It was really expensive
An entire day's wages got you the equivalent of
10 minutes of light from a kind of dim light
Economist talked a lot about product is
How much one person camper
Produce with a date
And the answer was not much
Everything was hot
Growing food was hard making candles for instance took hours
Fat which by the way was expensive because raising animals
This was a world where when the sun went down almost everyone lived in the dark
And this might sound sort of romantic
But basically it was awful
The dark was not some beautiful thing you went out and
Explore it was Danger
It was something that trap
In Paris
At one point
It was actually a law that said every night everybody has to give their keys to a magistrate go home and lock themselves
For basically 4000 years
Very little
With lights over the economy in general
Most people work all day
Naked women
The way things get better
The way an economy grows the way people get richer is that
Someone comes up with a better way to do some
A way to take a little less work
Overtime there are small improvements in life and in light
The Romans figure out how to make a lamp that's a little more efficient
People start use whale oil this of course is very very bad for whales
But we don't have a lot of fat they were like these big swimming sources of fuel
Still even when you get all the way to the 1700s
Life still looks more like ancient Babylon than the modern world
People still travel the same way
My foot by horse by sailing ship
Most people are still subsistence farmer
Usually living in some kind of hot
Trying to grow enough food not to starve to death
Your career there are tiny games in Friday
Little bits of a
But
Not a lot
And Light
Light still comes from finding stuff that's lying around in
Lighting it on fire
Again Economist bill nordhaus
You look at the picture
And what happened here
Its economic history in a nutshell
From Babylonian time to round 18
They were even though there were improvements as best we can tell
They were very modest
And then around 1800 in the lighting you can see it so clearly lighting
Just a
Norms change
In the pace
Of improvement
What happens in the 1800's
Is a few things
We start to really actively
We try to discover
And around 1850 a guy in Canada
Comes up with something that's not just a slightly better Wick or a slightly more efficient lamp
It is this magical liquid
With the right techniques you can get it from coal or oil
This big breakthrough
Harrison
Not cutting-edge now but back then says kerosene was a huge deal
When the first kerosene lamps came out it was
Is one yesterday and said it was the kind of oil people that dreamed about for centuries
It was brighter
It was cleaner
And importantly it was much cheaper
You work a day you got
About an hour
Whale oil
Kerosene you get
About
5 hours
Wow so it's about
5 *
More efficient
Kerosene
Let the world and save the whales
So if kerosene was so great
Why did it take the world so long to find
Science
This idea of professional scientists this idea.
There are lots of people who go to work every day at universities and do experiments
In the 1800
This is still a new thing
If you happen to be president of Yale University this is around the time when you're thinking you know maybe we should get one of those science
Why what why would they do in those experiments
A century earlier
Well you didn't have scientists A Century earlier they would teaching Greek
General teaching logic
Now all the scientists are working on better ways to make life
And life is getting cheaper
More people are using it
No more locking yourself in and huddling in the dark all night
Around this time street lights.
People start going out at night
So we have kerosene what's the next big Advance after that okay next big Advance after that is
The electric lamp
The big one
Well you might think so a Twist will be
I'll be back after this break
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence
Prince and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobiledit
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR
To save 10% off your first purchase
Just have a website or domain
Cheetah Jacob I thought I knew the story of the light bulb you know Thomas Edison the great inventor
Story about science and Innovation you medicine
Trying all these different filaments these different designs and finally getting one little glow for hours but
This Eureka lightbulb moment
And it is not
It's not enough to get you to the world of really cheap light
Is Edison needed this other
He needed money she needed lots and lots of money
Why
You can't light a light bulb without electricity
You needed to build a power play
Right now where the location of
The original Power Plant in lower Manhattan
This is Paul Israel is an Edison
Open scholar we met him here in New York City
We're standing in front of this plaque
Thomas Alva Edison in big letters and
There's this picture
And the image of a show is the generator room of the PowerPlay
With a bunch of guys in a really long mustaches
This is 1882
So what's of mustaches event
The money part of building a power plant is so important
When they finally get this historic thing completed in 1882 they get the power plant built
And they're ready to turn it on
Edison is not here
He's a few blocks away
A big impressive Stone build
Where today there is another plaque
So that you may have heard of
JPMorgan
It reads the capitalist capitalist
Known throughout the world of Finance
Sought out by presidents
Helped bankroll the industrialization of
Of America
Can write that I'm too many people
JP Morgan Bank and a bunch of investors
They put up money for the power
Pretty clear they built this great big expensive
Complicated powerstation the first
Central Power Station in the world right basically inventing
Electric light
And when they turn it on Edison is not there
Right he was
Where he needed to be with the people who had funded
The whole thing
Right
To 3 p.m. on September 4th Edison flipped on the switch
Here at JP Morgan's office
And what happened
Acid lights all over the district
Per square mile of lower Manhattan
Some lady was lit by electricity
You think of Edison the inventor
Even more important
Is Edison the businessman
At the time buildings in lower Manhattan were running off gas light
And Edison knew that was who we had to be
We spent a lot of time thinking about economic
Constantly he's going through and comparing the cost of what he's doing to what the cost of gas system
You never think about that
Well that's what made him such a good innovator
Right cuz he he recognized
These economic questions were just as important
In designing what he did in laboratory
When you think of economic growth how much do you think of it is coming from like
Individual like Eureka moments and inventions
What's up I got and how much is it
Stuff around
Ability to finance
The economic structure
So most of it is actually the structure around
To light a square mile of lower Manhattan Edison needed the whole financial system
Hats away to protect his ideas so no one would steal them
He needed a company
Play a bunch of different investors could come together and risk money
A lot of money
To build a power plant
Play wire so you can try this crazy thing
Light Without fire
Edison comes along at a time when all this machinery
Cotton's corporations Banks is in place
They were consequences
Minos first power plants burn coal
And pollution was pretty bad
Edison built a huge power plant on the east side of Manhattan
And at some point the City Health Department got involved
Is according
New York Times quote
When it was found Health Department men were trying to photograph the smokestacks Scouts were put on the company's roof
Order the feeding of coal stopped
Whenever photographers app
My other hand you know how to City lit up with cheap electric
Trade off
Around this time
Everything is getting fat
Cheaper
Scientist keep making noodle
Discoveries you get the internal combustion engine
The tractor
For the first time in human history most people don't have to work as farmers
This went on decade after decade all through the 20th
All continents got much cheaper
Like light
And if you look at the really long Arc here it's
It's amazing
Mingle all the way back to the battle on
Okay
Babylonians
Worked all day
You got the equivalent of
10 minutes
10 minutes of light
4000 years later in the 19th century with kerosene lamps
Things are better
Does Labor get through 5 hour
And by the time nordhaus does his light study in the 1990s
If you work today
How much light do you get
Maybe 20 thousand
20000 hours
I mean you basically you you have your
You have your house lit up you have your streets lit up you have your all your
Equipment on you have your air conditioner on your all the stuff you're doing is
Your your saturated with lighting the main thing is your statue is like
Economic growth isn't all good
There's pollution their environmental consequences
But fundamentally
Growth is about things getting faster
Getting cheaper
Getting more efficient
About doing the same amount of
And being able to buy
20000 hours
Light
Instead of 10 minutes
And as a result about being able to work less
Where to buy other stuff
That used to be just for the wealthy
We can buy books
We can take vacation
Even today there are still people who go to work everyday
Try to figure out how to make a better life
This morning I went to the ball Factory
For about an hour
This is John Edmund he's one of the founders of a company called Creed they make LED light bulbs which of course are much
What's more efficient than regular Bowl
You'll make you you try an experiment you'll say holy crap we just got more light out of this thing
By using
This contact material or flipping the chip over
Jacob when we talk about economic growth every year you know
When we say the economy grew a couple percent
That happens because every day out there
Someone somewhere in some corner of
Economy has figured out how to do something a little bit better
A little bit faster
There are little Essex
And this process is going on year after year for hundreds of years
I want question I always have it when I think about this is like
And not just with light but this whole story of constant economic growth
Constant product
Activity Improvement
My question is
Is it going to go on forever
Or some point we going to run out of ways to make things better
We might
We might double from where we are now
But we're not going to be tripling quadrupling it
Cuz there are physical limit
Honeywell cargo many miles an hour now
It just won't it just it's not going to happen
For the light bulb at least johntez
You may actually be near the end
The show originally aired in 2014 you can email us at Planet Money at NPR.
You couldn't find us on Facebook with Twitter Today Show was originally produced by Caitlin Penny and Damiano marchetti
The rerun was produced by Sally Helm I'm Jacob Goldstein thanks for listening