Little round the world race
And you can see the same kind of drama
Playing out over
Two sides
In a standoff
On the brink of some kind of con
So we have few nuclear situation with North Korea
There is this on-again off-again possible trade war with China
And it might not seem like it on its face
But these global conflict follow a pattern
That we see
Everywhere
Down to the tiniest little ways in our own daily lives
Like
Two roommates who are watching the dirty dishes piled up in the sink
Waiting for the other one to give up and clean them first
These are all problems were both sides are better off
If the corporate
But no one wants me to suck her in cave first
So they don't
And they end up not cooperate
This kind of stand-up is so, it comes up so often and it is so tricky to solve
It has its own name
The prisoner's dilemma
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Alex goldmark the prisoner's dilemma is one of the most famous products
Experiments in economics
. more than ever this little thought experiment is explaining so much of our world right now that we just
Have to tell this particular story
Trailer show the story of the idealistic glorious dirt who set up the solve one of the greatest problem
Human existence it right here what he found out with it sometimes the best way to win
Crystal Lewis
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their own websites
Using customizable layouts and features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization to help you develop an online presence
Squarespace.com NPR for free trial and when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Let's meet the man who changed the way we sing
Cooperation
Bob Axelrod
Lifeline PCS
Yes I've done mediator or try to help each side understand the other
Barbies and quite sure where is obsession with cooperation came from
Maybe it was growing up during the Cold War
Or maybe it's the fact that he was the youngest in his family
I think my motivation was more from my parents who bicker a lot
And I thought that's a shame and what it comes with it
They should be able to get along better
Bob went on to become a professor at the
Versity of Michigan employee
Science and public
Policy
And now instead of worrying about his
His parents bickering
He's worrying about something
Yeah to Country bickering the United States and the Soviet Union
In the 1970s and 1980s
We were all worried about
Global thermonuclear war
And Bob is trying to figure out how to solve this
He looks around thinking
What could I a professor at a Midwestern University
Possibly do
And he
See something that in
The budding technology
Specifically
Computers that play chess
Application right now
This is
My most beloved toys from my childhood 1978 Fidelity Electronics
Challenger computer chess I love that you brought this in
It's in a whole special briefcase calculator attached to a
Mini metal chest
Board that amazing
Sorry Italy
I so he sees these computers Eastchester
Thanks
Maybe he can use computers to try and figure out the smartest strategy for
Global conflict
I was inspired by a computer chess tournaments we're obviously if you're going to write a program to play computer chess
Give me a very sophisticated you can handle any contingencies
The first step that was he needs to
Frameless
Political problems in the where computer can handle
And he chooses
That famous thought experiment
Prisoner's dilemma
Quality the name comes from the
The story about
Police arresting two people might have
Committed a crime and they
The prisoner's dilemma is so important
The story that
We are going to play this out
As if it were real life so
I just pulled my lunch
Out of the fridge
And there's a mystery
I turkey sandwiches missing
Let's Round Up The Usual Suspects to The Newsroom
Sarah
Sarah Sarah Sarah
I bet you're wondering why we brought you in here
Oh yeah that laugh that laughs tells me you know exactly
Why
We brought
You in here you a Cardiff Garcia
Took the turkey sandwich out of the fridge
Oh I'm sorry
This is light too bright
Alex is in the other studio with Cardiff
Coming in here Cardiff listen we know that Roberts lunch
Has been stolen
You don't know nothing
Here's the deal you got to make a choice
You got to decide are you going to keep your mouth shut
Where are you going to rat Sera out
Because if you write Sarah out and you let her take the Fall by yourself
Will let you go free
Here's the twist if you rat you out and you rat him out
When you're both going to get punished pretty harshly
If neither of you Rats on the other one we're still going to punch you
If neither of you talk
Both of you will get the Lesser
Just got suspended for one week
The only way you can walk free
Is by telling us Cardiff
And
Aren't you can leave now
Thank you I'm going to need a sandwich bag
Gas card
Alex
Comebackszn alright Robert
To looking at this ideally
Ideally what should Cardiff and Sara
If they trust each other they should keep their mouth shut
That would overall be the best thing for both of them
But if they don't trust each other and rubber
They are criminals
Then it might be in their individual best interest to sing like a
It's on the railroad these kinds of situations don't just get played out
Once in awhile
Giddy up its kind of conflicts happen over and over again and say you keep bringing Sarah and Kardashian and Sarah speaking nut
Just about what to do but what did Cardinals do last time
And he's thinking we'll wait what did Sarah do last time
And so on and so
And this is essentially what a trade
Is between say the US
And China
They are just picking Terrace once in setting those levels they're thinking
What did the other side do
And all the round up to
And what is that tell me about what they're going to do next
There's literally a billion options
And you know who love
Sifting through a billion options
Computers
And Bob axle
So Bob thinks there might be a best way to
Play the prisoner's dilemma of all the billions of options
And that he can find so goes to the library and looks up everyone he can find
Play written about the prisoner's dilemma
And he picked up the Fast and the brightest in the biggest brains he get in touch with
Any got their dresses
I what I did is I will to other
A faculty members who had written about the prisoners
Writing a letter like
Yeah mail
Snellville
And I said you know I'm interested in and higher what's a good way to play the game and you've written about this could you
Pick a strategy
Define it in terms of a computer program
And he had one of those computer terminals
And back in the 1970s they were usually these beige boxes
Bright green glowing cursors and he takes his letters and he somehow has to get them in
Side
The Box
The first round I did all by myself
Oh you where the nerd I was
Sorry
Basically inside
The computer he designs a virtual prison
With two
Virtual prisoner
Kept separate
Player one
Tire tube
Each prisoner is given a particular strategy one of the strategy sent in by the experts and they play hundred
Frowns
Against
Each other
With those strategies
And then
They get to new strategies
Play again
Computer course
Differences one strategy was really simple be random
Sometimes you keep your mouth
Shut and cooperate with the other prisoner
And sometimes you write amount
Heat affect another strategy
Way more complicated
It was like an early version of artificial
Intelligence
The strategy was called
Look ahead
Atom model
What the other player was doing
How often would it
Cooperate after cooperation how I feel crappy.
Affection
And then it would project into the future if my model the other person's correct what's the best I can do with that kind of
Player it was when called tranquilizer that loaded
Deponent into thinking it was very cooperative
Lights out lots of
Directions
Wauna, sent in an approach called Grim trigger
It was just a giant
Complete and total threat
If you read it against it once
It would just affect on you afterwards forever and ever meant to scare the opponent
Cooperating
And there was another super simple strategy
Tit for Tat
Just do what the other side does back to the
214 different strategies
Lined up ready for a tournament inside this
Virtual prison inside this
Old school computer
Which took a while to process back in the
So wait what did you what did you do during this
Two hours while it's turning away
Had lunch
Okay
You just said it to go on your computer and your husband you walked away
Sure
He's a pretty chill tour
So who wins
The Grim trigger the tranquilizer that super fancy artificial intelligence one you go in you look at this list
And what do you say
I see that
The simplest of all the strategies was the one that did best
Which was
Tit for Tat
Worst name
Fast results
This round anyway like any good researcher Bob
Was
Doubtful
What's the result how can a simple strategy really be
You the best so
Bob decided to do the whole tournament
And so what I did is I
Scented announcement
Several computer hobby magazine saying
Here's what the prisoners Monday is I'm going to run to
A tournament and any happiest anybody that wants consenso
Some strategy in
That's amazing
You know they could be young Bill Gates Steve Jobs they're reading this in the back of the neck
Time to think about
Play with it
He got 63 competitor
All of them going to take down simpleton
And this time it took the entire night for his computer
To have all of those prisoners plate
You go home overnight
Get up in the morning to drink coffee but this is 30 years ago
Remember printing off the result
And so it was a whole bunch of pages
And I had a tape them together
To make this one huge spreadsheet
And lo and behold it was
Pacific a strategy again
Wow that's
That is really cool
Bob's tournament was revealing something fundamental about how people can get along with
And it's all wrapped up
In simple tit-for-tat
Here's how the tit-for-tat strategy War
The strategy says that the first time you walk in you assume the best from the other prisoner
And you do not wrap them out I used to work nice I said a nice rule is one that won't be the first
And I found that the nice rules
I actually did quite well
Right to start nice
You can't be nice all the
If you're playing against the Grim trigger you have to
If the other side is taking advantage of you and you don't do anything about it
I'm just going to try again harder
Settings
Straight you have to
Demonstrate that don't have consequences for their Bad Axe if your opponent is nice you stay nice
If your opponent hits you you hit back
But you still look the other side and think
Think about how to know
What they're going to
How to send a message that cooperation is the best in the long run
And that you will play next
There's something very special about tit-for-tat special to my heart for real
It never tries to beat
It's opponent remember
It won't affect unless it
Is provoke
So that in the short-term and anyone around
The best of it can do
Is Thai
But in the long run
Even if it
Loses
Some one-on-one matchups
Buy a little bit
It ends up better off overall
You do not as well as the other player but you do boo terrific and the reason you do terrific
Is you elicit a lot of cooperation for dinner
The other player to do well is Tit for Tat
Needs to cooperate a lot
Otherwise it gets punished
I think there's something
Beautiful and poetic and hopeful
About the idea that
The strategy that does the best in the long run
Is the one that never actually tries to beat its opponent
Exactly
Bob Axelrod publishes his results
80 and he sits back and waits for peace to breakout around the world
David from the White House call
Okay
Neither dinner later
But after he runs the store
And crowns tit-for-tat the two-time champion
Bob realizes
There is a
Serious
Problem here
Tit-for-tat has a dark side in
Say two countries are negotiating something in
And
One of them says or does something that the other side
Interprets as
An insult or maybe even
A threat
Well then if both sides are doing it for
For tat
All it takes is one misunderstanding
Then this can set off a chain reaction
In the world of miscommunication if you have two sides doing
Tap
Then you can start defecting against each other and you defect all the way down to annihilation
Tell Bob
Figure this out a bit late for his tournament but he comes up with a solution
And that's two
Just a tiny little tweak
Tit for Tat
He called
Generous
This version says
Yes
Retaliate when you are provoked
But also sometimes
Turn the other cheek
That simple
So when you see two countries in a standoff over
A nuclear deal or
Trade barriers
Easy to think that the back-and-forth is a petit irrational tit-for-tat it's going to bring the whole thing Crashing Down
Look for the generous moment
We're at it doesn't earn attack back it might just be The Optimist
Strategy for cooperation
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Capital One is reimagining Bank
I offering accounts with no fees or minimums that can be opened from anywhere in 5 minutes Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Hey it's Gyros here host of how I built this and I have some very exciting news to share we are hosting our first-ever
How I built this one day Summit
Sponsored by America
Express
You have a chance to hear from
And in Iraq
It's some of the world's most inspiring entrepreneurs and
Founders
Airbnb Joe gebbia
Katrina Lake of Stitch fix
John Zimmer of Lyft and many many more
Breakout sessions
With experts and guides
And the summit will be a chance for you to meet other innovators and builders
How I built this Summit will take place
October 16th
San Francisco's yerba buena Center for the Arts
Npr.org
Summit
To find out more and get your tickets
Game Theory heads up there we know we had to leave at a bunch of little tidbits so if you want to talk about it we post a link to every episode on Facebook
Are there
We're also on Twitter and Instagram
We are at
Money
You can also email us at Planet Money at npr.org
We loved in your emails especially the ones that ask us how you can help out Planet Money
Here is how
Think of the one friend in your life who would most like listening to this podcast
And tell them about your favorite episode
That's it
Today's episode was produced by Megan Pandora deters Bryant stats
I'm Robert Smith thanks for listening
That is
Quite a dilemma
For me
It's like the voice respect
It's like a voice in those movies where you like you don't got nothing on me cover
From like the 1950s or something
So
Here we are
That is actually all we need
And it's getting disgusting