The story today
It's going to take us around the world
But it starts in New York City
About a year ago there was this conference
In a fancy room some
Diplomats
The senator from
Virginia former senator from
Alaska bunch of policy nerds
This guy comes up to the podium he's wearing a purple shirt
Distinguished guests ladies and gentlemen
Good afternoon
His name is Patrick ho
He's from Hong Kong
And he's becoming a regular fixture at these types of events
It's not quite clear what he does but he does run a think tank
Seems to have a ton of money to spend
One of his favorite subjects is China Centre under the global stage
He says it's
Crucial in this increasingly unequal world
The top 10% of earners
Fa exceedingly well
Wild opossum 10%
Have continued to
The Fall Fair that be
Ultimate
Everyone is harmed by India
Equality
Houses the rise of China
Is a force
For good the world
Globe lights
Tupac
Globalization
2.0
A reorganization of the world
Balance of power
Patrick Howe was on a mission to make it happen
Well think tank
We're dedicated
To addressing issues
Relating to the emerging
Decisions
China
Besides me a thing tag
We're also a dual tank
Which we don't only think
We do things
So
Not just a think tank
I do tank
And Patrick
Was doing a lot
What people at that event didn't know
Is that over the past few years
According to Federal authorities
Patrick Howe have been trying to make
Globalization 2.0 happen
With millions of dollars in bribes
Hello and welcome to Planet Money Ian Julia
Please sign-in in New York and I'm Rob Schmitz China correspondent for NPR in Shanghai
7 months after that speech in November 2017
FBI agents arrested patrico
Us attorney's office with charging him with multiple counts of money laundering and bribery
We're going to tell you what patrico did around the world to land himself
In prison
History open the rear window into how China work
And how it works abroad
A game of trying to gain power
Smaller countries
Today Show is it
Classic onion structure
Each time we peel away layer
We find something else
Including secret Bank transfers to world leaders
Mysterious Tycoon and the global rush to control African soil in
The structure and that first layer we find it right near us
Kira Noir
With an arrest almost no one notices
Support for NPR comes from LinkedIn learning proud to support the launch of life
NPR Sky to help you make better life decision
LinkedIn learning short video tutorials cover business Tech
And creative skills employers look for at every level
All taught by experts
And new courses are added every week
+ LinkedIn learning is personalized
Recommended courses based on your interest and Life kid listeners get a month of learning
Free start your free trial at LinkedIn learning.com NPR
Okay so if this story is an onion that first
Onion layers
Is an arrest
At JFK
On a cloudy afternoon last November
Hoe gets picked up by the FBI
They pick him up because Federal authorities
Saho wasn't just a talker
He was a major fixer
We called his lawyer he declined a comment
But according to the US attorney this fixer
Patrick ho
Was bribing foreign officials
In one transfer through New York Bank
He allegedly said
$500,000
To a guy from East Africa
Find out why we're going
Do you got that I talk to you
Journalist in Kampala
We're calling him by his middle name up Willie
We're not going to use his full name because you've done is not a safe place for Journal
What's right now
A lot of them are getting arrested lately
A police told me that recently he noticed something changing
And it has to do with the barber
Normally when he goes to the barber in Kampala
Ecc's photos on loud
You definitely find Ludacris
Will Smith
Usher American celebrities
Stylish haircuts
If they collected royalties from the barbers in Africa orgasm make a ton of
That's true
But recently a Puli
Barbers popping up around Kampala
With no Usher on the outside
No lyrics
Is a barbershop Chinese words
And the Bob has a Chinese
It makes sense a lot of Chinese people are moving to Uganda
They need haircuts
But the Chinese people in Uganda
They're building more than just Barbershop
Everything from roads to buildings to Malta hotels
That Ministry of Foreign Affairs was built by
The Chinese the president's office
Whitby built
The president's office
Oh man and they built the Ministry of Foreign Affairs
Yes it did the living Ministry of Foreign Affairs
That's like
The equivalent of the state department in
In the US
Yeah and remember Patrick ho from Hong Kong the fixer
He has a connection to the Minister of Foreign Affairs of Uganda
The criminal complaint against ho
Says that he
He said half a million dollar bribe
That minister
A guy
Sam kutesa
Whatever
Issue of corruption that comes up in the country
Sample thesis
Gonzalo Vega
This is Owen cabin gay the Ugandan journalist he's working on a story about Chinese business in Uganda
We met up in New York you just gotten back from Kampala
And he has met Sam kutesa
He's one of the
What do you call the Untouchables
I mean he's well-connected
He's a very wealthy man
He knows all the players
And he's smart
He's on the top of the food chain if I'm a city
And there's another reason he's untouchable
His in-laws with the president
Can't get fired
Ana president
He's around the country longer than I've been alive
Since 1986
His arguments
Which is valid is that
He is elected whenever he runs as president
Goats are like that is
Debatable
He's gotten rid of term limits
He controls the army
But they do have elections in Uganda
Ndk
Is where the half a million dollar bracket
When that fixer Patrick ho send emails about that half a million dollars he was sending to Uganda
He called it a donation to The re-election of the president
So Sam kutesa he takes this
Donation to his in-laws the president
He's happy the president's happy and they win an election and what do the Chinese get
In one of those
Household rights
Just give me a list of all the major projects
Text from infrastructure energy agriculture to finance and banking
And we will bring the relevant heads
To your country
Kickstart
Project this is the thing is that many of these companies bidding to get these contracts from the Ugandan
Government to build
All this infrastructure
These are Chinese companies
And guess where they're getting their money
Vidya Balan got me just going to borrow money
From the Chinese Banks to undertake
Major construction of an infrastructure project
If I'm
The Ugandan
Ministry of Roads
I will get a loan from
A Chinese bank and then use that money from a Chinese Bank
To pay a Chinese construct
Right and under the government of you guys going to go through a transparent process of calling out for beads
You used air quotes again
It's actually called the Ugandan national roads Authority but you get the
The Chinese companies
Always seem to get the
And it's not just infrastructure
Also natural resources
Because the thing about Uganda
It has oil
Daughter Thai
They've only gotten into the game relatively recently
But China needs oil
They need a lot of oil nearly 1.4 billion people
That's a legit amount of people
China wants to get in on the ground floor of uganda's oil into
Mystery just as it started
Do you want access
Titties potential energy Reese
And these resources are all over after
The country of Chad also has oil
And guess what
Federal authorities say Patrick Howe ride the president of Chad to
And this is why Patrick ho is bribing these guys
He wants things for his think
Yes
But he also wants things for China
Next we find out
Where all this money is coming from
Right it comes from a huge Chinese oil company
That appeared out of nowhere in the lab
They spent money all around the world
They're worth 40 billion dollars
They're called cefc
Atracoes Think Tank was funded by
And Workforce
Okay so we're leaving Uganda
And headed to Prague
Czech Republic
Where they sometime
Play accordion
Over one week in Autumn of 2015
List new company
CFC
Winona shopping
Out of nowhere Chinese company that nobody's ever heard of
He's a journalist and a China scholar
Vying
Company they also bought a bunch of Real Estate
Hotel and a 30
3% share of a bank
Later on they realize they forgot something
So they bought part of an airline to
It after all that the head of this Chinese company of 38 year old guy named via jamming
Dapper Young
Business Pandora
Slicked back hair
He's suddenly named as the newest advisor
To the president
Of the Czech Republic
Martin the China scholar
Hedonistic feeling a little embarrassed
Because everyone is trying to him France
He should know who this guy is
Didn't nobody
Well
The Czech president
So who is gay agenda
This Dapper dude
You jamming is the CEO of CFC
The same company that the FBI says hired the
The fixer patrico
To bribe the foreign minister of Uganda
You jamming the young insta Tycoon appeared to be behind all of this
After the break
We go to China
Define doubt
How a 30-something dude
Appeared out of nowhere
To control
Billions of dollars
And why
Support for this podcast
In the following message
It's come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org
After CFCs shopping spree in Prague
Journalist here in China begin wondering
Who are these
And who is this
Tycoon
30s
Is he a Gemini
The begin digging around
They learn from the company's website that ya used to be connected to China's military
And then when they ask the company about this
It responded by deleting that information
Website
At the time Scott cendrowski was working for fortune in Beijing
He was baffled
Company just had gotten very scan coverage
Even in the the Chinese press no one really knew anything
Scott's been two years trying to land an interview with the agent
Finally
In 2016
He became the first
And only foreign journalist interview
My impressions of him he was young
You had kind of a nervous are around him
Scott said ye was surrounded by minders
People whispering in his ear
Call them
The chairman
Who's the prettiest tilted interview you know right off the bat he asked it to be off the Record and
We're travels from Beijing to Shanghai and that's
What's the last thing you want to hear before you ask your first question so I can
Quickly it's a deal was on the record
He turns you know it's beside both ways and sets
Okay and Scott have the same questions journalist in Prague
The same ones I have about
How do you private Oil Company like cefc rise so quickly
In a country where the energy sector is
Controlled so tightly by China's government
How does a guy like yeah young man with a murky
He passed behind a company now worth more than 40
A billion dollars
Who is this guy a business genius
China's government engineered all of this
Was Scott actually asked you this
And you did not being part of it
Secret government plot
Is it basically
All the other companies in this industry are
Government companies
And we need to compete with him
So we need to look
And that made sense the sky
I mean CFC
He did look like if they don't company
Write down to uhm
You see if I actually have pictures of it
Scott searches is photo library
And
Find a photo there's a gilded
Framed portrait of ya soon as you walk into the office there's a sort of
Yeah with
Something to terrorize him shaking Henry Kissinger his hands on the wall
Photo of him
Leaning against a tree smoking a pipe
Large portrait
Miles
There was also a statue of a reclining Buddha
The frame piece of calligraphy by the Chinese leader Xi Jinping head of the Communist Party
And they're on an ornate desk
Scott see something else
A red phone
When I noticed that my
My eyes lit up
Only the most powerful men in China have red phones on there.
Top leaders
In the heads of state-owned
It's so they can call each other up
Quick without worrying about being
Bugged
The most famous red phone
Sits on the desk of present
Xi Jinping
It's behind him whenever he delivers an address to the nation
Scott asked his minders about
The phone day of course I said no no no that's
Just internal line
But
The impression is
The guest know that she also has a red phone in his office so it's impressive that he has one as well
And that leads us to Xi Jinping
A leader with big plans for China
Plans that the insta Tycoon and the jail fixer
Are putting in jeopardy
To explain these plans I bring you
A bedtime story sponsored by the Chinese government
Once Upon a Time
Sample route slip
Central Asia Europe
It was called Silk Road
People
You got to see this video it's a Kiki looking blonde guy who starts reading this very odd
Bedtime story to his daughter
Who seems
Way to win
Interested I'm watching this in this is very weird
Well they got the guy just looks away
And they got a mad frog
Show me the girl with the mask
Camels
Okay
Rub what is this
It's a propaganda video on the website of the state news Outlet the China Daily
It's official government communication mint
To reach a foreigner
Few years ago it's like the old routes
Even bigger
Belt and Road initiative and Road initiative
When he took power 5 years ago Xi Jinping wanted China
Had to play a more prominent role in
Global affairs
The belt and Road initiative was how he
Plan to do it
A global trading Network
Led by China
Its banks and Company
Way to spread Chinese investment and influence abroad
It aims to be the largest infrastructure an investment project
History
But people start paying attention when you're working on the largest global investment project in history
NAD being influenced to do it
After Chinese company won the bid to build a high-speed rail network in Hungary
Investigation into building violations
Same thing happened in Nepal
The Chinese Dam
Last year in Sri Lanka
Chinese company bought one of the country's largest ports
A 99 year lease
Started a riot
That fortune writer
Scott cendrowski
He says that in much of the developing World China state-owned Enterprises
Is there they're called SOS
We're becoming synonymous with corruption
Chinese SOS don't have the the sparkling reputation
In Africa
Wire or other parts of the world where they've done business and in fact
Save tarnished the reputation of Chinese companies that come in after them
I interviewed
Several China
All of them had come to the same conclusion about Yaya
Is mysterious company
They said
Because China's state-run companies that develop such bad reputations worldwide
China's government may have essential
Chosun CEO
A private company
Seemingly no cover
Connections
To begin taking their place
Because the Optics
Is China's government
Is behind
CFC
This might explain why Patrick ho
Who works for yay in the US
If so many presentations about China's belt and Road initiative
At that event in New York
Even then he was talking about the Belton
Ncfc with sending money to the president of Chad it wasn't just to secure a lease or build a road
It was a hell of a larger Chinese state-run company reduce a billion dollar fine
That's really weird
Normal companies don't help the competition
CFC
Seems kind of like
Trojan Horse
Air China
They make friends with these guys like the foreign minister of Uganda the president of Chad
So that the Chinese government and its companies can March in
And this is what happens when your power hits its peak
You get involved in countries across the world
Yeah you end up robbing up some less than democratic governments as we've seen in Uganda
Because it's easier to bribe them and get what you want
And the same thing happened with the British Empire the
The US in the details can get pretty ugly
And seeing how the sausage gets made
It can undermine all your globulin
This right here is a real look
Into the sauce
Robert Peck is a former New York criminal defense at
Who divides his time between the US and honk
What's striking about this cases
How complete of the picture is that supplied by these emails it's almost as if
The emails and the criminal complaint that reads like a Hollywood script it's so complete
He's read the indictment of patrico and he says
The case against him is
Is so damning
He thinks it's likely cold will have little choice but
Cooperating
With prosecutors and tell them what he knows about
About CFCs activities
And it's connections inside China's government
And about China's Global plan
So this case
And the whole
Question of
Foreign corruption by Chinese companies has huge implications
For the belt and Road initiative if it turns out
And that Chinese companies are routinely bribing
Foreign officials than that
Is a stain on me
Belt and Road initiative and it's a it's a huge embarrassment
It is already pretty embarrassing
China's government
And that may be why lately it's been pretty hard to find the insta Tycoon
Asian
He has now disappeared
He's reportedly under investigation by Chinese authorities
Nobody seems to know where he is now
State Farm is taking over the company and its
Began selling off all its proper
Ask for a fixer Patrick ho
He's in jail in New York
Robert Praxis are clues that he
Please cooperate
With Federal Prosser
Scooters
Hose agreed to a trial date in November of this year
I thinks his lawyers want to negotiate with us official
It's a terrible dilemma because if he goes to trial it's very likely he'll be convicted in face years in jail
On the other hand
If he pleads guilty and he implicates others that's going to have a Fallout
As well
It could mean the people will turn against him
They they will label him
A Trader
Put pressure on family members in Hong Kong
Who might be the targets of actions by powerful people in the mainland
Praxis given what Patrick omameh know about CEO
TFCU
Connections
The Chinese government and its role in seeing things belt and Road initiative
The safest place for him might just be his current address
A jail cell
In lower Manhattan
We love to hear your story ideas and thoughts about the show
We're at Planet Money at npr.org
You can also find us on Twitter Facebook and Instagram
Today Show is produced by Sally Helm with help from Alexi Horowitz Ghazi
Are supervising producers Alex
Goldmark rhinostat
Avatar editor thanks to Giovanni to yoongi
For the music from Uganda the song we used was koliba
And thanks to Alexandra Gillies
Sirinat Shinto Until Dark Raga
Also to Yuan Shu Nan Shan tahia ho Fung hung Andrew Chubb and Marcus
Schmidt's in Shanghai and I'm Julia Simon in New York
Thanks for listening