When a source comes to you
And says hey
Come out to New Jersey
And I will tell you
How about an international price-fixing conspiracy that is giving foreign business has a major advantage of the growing
E-commerce
You have only one choice
We think it's this building yeah it's a Friday afternoon and we're on some
Being upside Street next to a junkyard
Next toll welding facility in Rahway New
Jamie
BJ me
We can be calling our source
Jamie
Jamie smaldone
Because
His real name is Jamie smaldone and he does not mind attention at all
Jamie
Jamie spelldown is a ball of a
He's constantly moving or talking
One might imagine knocking things over
The CEO of a company that makes a mug
That is very hard to knock over
It called The Mighty mug
And Jamie demonstrates that
It works because of some complicated suction cup system and I don't know
So when you put it down and you knock into it Jimmy is smacking this mug like a toddler so you see that
It's stuck to the table
But then when you lift it
Oh my God what
Few years ago Jamie started to notice that knockoff Mighty Muggs were popping up
All over the
Okay so I have all them here
I have a bunch of them
Hey Jamie is running off every great conspiracy theorist has a moment of Revelation
And Jamie's came from a plastic mug
Specifically a red knockoff Mighty mug
That he is now returning with
So this is this is
Where did you get the smoke
So I bought that particular one on eBay
For $5.69
Free shipping from China maybe you've noticed this
As well you can go on eBay or AliExpress
You can buy a mug or a like a phone charger
It comes from all the way across the world with free shipping
And the whole thing costs
Next to nothing it is dirt cheap
And this
Does not make sense
Shirt maybe you can make the stuff
The Milling across oceans
Certainly must be
And this is what Jamie was thinking when that red knock-off mug arrived
That is office like
How did this
Sing
Get here
For $5.69
Total cost
Who returns to its shipping guy
Any ask
How much would it cost
For us just to ship this mug
Like not across the ocean
Just across the street
He told me
It's going to cost us about
6:30
Text to ship this item
Across the street
Yeah and you say what
Is a direct quote
Without that Jamie is that his business is in
Deep trouble
Because somehow
His competitors can manufacture and deliver a mug
4 Less Than Jamie pays just a ship
Jamie smaldone has been telling anyone who will listen that something is wrong with International ship
He showed up at his local post office demanding answers he
Send a 15-page letter to the White House
Send a bunch of messages to us at Planet Money
And he says
He has finally figured out what is going on
There is a secretive International Organization
The get-together
To fix the price
Global ship
And it's screwing over American small
I knew I knew
It was like
The universe opened up to me
If you go back and you look at my messages too
Like I saw how everything was going to play out
Are you aware that when you say these kinds of things
I don't know I don't want to say conspiracy 10 Hattie
Look where we are
Write like you're here
I knew that you guys would eventually be here he was right
We did show up
What if he's right about
All of it
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Nick Fountain and I'm Kenny Malone today on the show we take the red mug
And we follow it
All the way down
Will find out
Why you can order a cheap gizmo from across the world
With Dirt Cheap shipping
We're going to stay the answers the Illuminati
But we're not not saying that
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Fidelity Investments
As a Fidelity wealth management client
You get a dedicated advisor to help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes and make clear recommendations for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com wealth
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
The first rule of conspiracy theory reporting
Is do not get all your information from the guy in New Jersey yelling at the top of his
Luckily we found one of the few experts on International postal policy
A guy named Jim camp
First we should check for plosives
Would you say postal policy 10 times fast
Applejack
Postal policy
Post office Post Falls people's quality
You're pretty good
Jim Stone Consulting for big private Shipping Company
UPS DHL FedEx
And he told us
Oh yeah there is absolutely a group
Postal policy
In fact
They are powerful postal policy
Private
Universal Postal Union
How do you peel
UPS headquarters in Bern Switzerland
The universal Postal Union
Part of the United Nation
And it's made up of representatives from the Postal Services of 192
Basically the UPS of the secret
But Jim tells us not only has he managed to get access to one of these meetings
He has
Video
Or maybe we might ask you to share it if it if there's some exciting times
Yai
I can share it I don't know how exciting to do
Functions
We should warn you
If you are operating heavy equipment right now or if you're on the road
Open the window
Off to the side
Cuz
This is one of the most boring things we have ever put on
This podcast will consider proposals 15.1
7.2
1.1 vs
As well as 1.1
This was the ubu's 2016 Congress in Istanbul
It looks like a fancy ballroom with chandeliers and ornate carpeting
And then Rose and Rosie
People wearing like
Translator headset
The term Postal Service in the UPS
As you sow conspiracy Point number one
Yeah
There is a secret International postal group they're not that seek
Fear secretive International postal group
But
What exactly are they up
What are they talking
Hello
DeSoto music
We took this question to Alta Mere Linares
Who's worked at the upu for 16 years
I'm curious is this
A dream of yours to work at the upu at how did you come to this
Well if I may I find you a question
White person on probably snot
To the point of our conversation we are we are supposed to have
To talk about the youth you and that's really my professional career but
Any case I had to loan a 20-year career in the Brazilian post
Cwill secretive secretive secretive
What do upu does
Requires
A bit of explain
I mean maybe we should do this as a
More like a hypothetical
The situation so let's say you send us a pack
Where in New York City
Shipping to us from Burn
Okay
What's the specialty of burn is there any what should you send as chocolate no chocolate I would not send to you
You because it's a perishable and it's not accepting the post stream
I would send you a cell phone
Let us take a breath
And appreciate
The man-made miracle
That is international mail
Alta mercante
This hypothetical cell phone to his local Swiss
Buy Swiss postage
And it will show up on our doorstep in New York he doesn't have to think about it
He doesn't have to tell Swiss post what route to take he doesn't have to buy u.s. postage or French postage
Did your postage of any other country that are cellphone my pass through
No
And this
Is because
Cue the boring sound
On functions secretive group of boring male people have boring meetings
Any work out the rules to make international mail
Okay so now for the problematic
Are cell phone is in the hands of the Swiss
At least burn
I fly to the United States
Probably to JFK Airport during this movement there is a moment where the international items
The mix
With the domestic item
And it is at that moment the cell phone switches hands
It's from the Swiss post
To the United States Postal
And USPS will finish what's known as
The final mile
The important thing here
Is that this final mile of the journey
Is generally the most
Expensive part of the
As in
It accounts for the majority of the cost
I'm getting that cell phone
From a foreign post office to our door
Because it's pretty expensive to send someone in a truck or walking down the street to deliver
Something by half
That's the idea
Yo it's somehow it's more labor-intensive when you when it comes to delivery
Then in other parts of the
Of the process
This creates
A problem
The USPS
Got stuck
With the expensive part of delivery of our cell phone
But they did not get any of Ultimate Ears money
He paid Swiss
And when the abuse started they figured
Let's not worry about
We all know the final mile
Is super expensive
Pensive but we're all send each other mail will all take
Turns eating the cost
Of that lousy final
It'll all even out
But come on
This is like going out to eat with
With a group of friends
And saying let's just put the check
But then you have that one friend
Call of Duty
Chris Godwin
Keeps ordering expensive beers
I'm here drinking water
And this is certainly not going to split evenly anyways
Yes this problem happened with International
Some countries were getting flooded with foreign male but we're barely sending
Which meant
Their Postal Service was getting stuck doing more final miles then
For the last five decades
The GPU has been trying to
Fix this by saying
Hey
Let's start reimbursing each other for that final mile but in general they still have a gentleman's agreement where they do
Don't pay each other back the full cup
And this is really important
Because there is still country is getting screwed because they're delivering a lot of packages
And eating some of the cost
We wanted to know
Who is winning
And who is losing it
And so we asked ultimate Linares
Can we see
How much it cost to send packages around the world
And also
How much countries reimburse
Is there a place
Just to like to see what these numbers are
No this alright considered sensitive data so it's not supposed to be
Open to the public
Why not it seems like
Good information to have is a Custer
Really well it could be but I've never seen this happening I don't know for example
What Walmart would be painted their franchisees or McDonald's for
For example intercompany intercompany data
These are not corporations are like
Arms of government
I understand you'll be needing this may be a better point
The first moment we really started to feel like Jamie small town
Are New Jersey mug maker
Was not just feeding us some conspiracy Mumbo
Because
There is a secret ish postal Society
They are getting together
And they're agreeing
To give each other special below-market shipping
Which brings us
To the final part
Jamie's postal Theory of Everything
America and American small businesses are somehow getting screwed by this postal Illuminati
Ultimate was like
I just work
At the U P
It's up to the members whether or not
They want to share intimate postal details with you
You guys are American
Why don't you just ask the United States Post
We did
They will neither confirm nor deny our interview
You request so
We did what we always do at Planet Money yeah we call them,
Would you say you're the foremost postal economist
In the world
Maybe I wouldn't drag it that far but finally I would say
This is Anna Muller bovie but I think that's too difficult for you
A few years ago the United States
Postal Regulatory Commission wanted to know what we want to know
Who's winning and who's losing in the CPU system they hired Honest Company
An economics Consulting
Confirm
Do a bunch of studies
Inanna tells us
In fact for a long time
The United States with a big
Time winner in this
We were a big economy exporting lots of
But also exploding a lot of Ino
Mail
Why
Ymail what are we sending
You're sending you
Catalogs letters documents
Marketing material
Yeah I junk mail this was great for the United
We were making other countries postal people do the
Expensive part of delivering stuff
And because of you. We didn't have to pay them back for it all
Sure when someone from another country send a package to
If you ask
We had to deliver their stuff and not get fully reimbursed
But on the whole
There weren't as many packages and letters coming in
As we were sending out
And this we actually do have number
8 years ago
The US was making money off this imbalance
Teletoon
Of 275 million dollars per
But then
The e
Email Matt less need for international letters but more importantly
E-commerce meant that
American started ordering stuff direct from other
Slowly
Slowly slowly
And sister Nita Justino escalated
More and more stuff came into the United
And then
3 years ago
A big
Switch flip
The first time we were losers
We started to lose money on the mail delivery in Bala
Last year the US Postal Service lost around 80 million dollars
And it's almost certainly going to be worse this year because
We are almost certainly ordering more stuff from overseas
Butter mug maker Jamie does not care
If the USPS
Is losing money
The claim he made
In the claim honestly we were most skeptic
Glove
Is it this system is actually made it cheaper
To ship a mug into the United States
From China
Send to send a mug across the
We're in this past every person we talked
Including animals
Can I tell you the the the little story that
It kind of started this whole thing
Sure
So
There's this guy who makes mug
You know Jamie
You can't knock it over it's very high I saw the YouTube clip
She didn't however know Jamie's Holst
So we told her about how Jamie was looking
Inferno cost and how it appeared to Cost Less to ship
Amug into United States from China than it did to ship them out
Across the street that story Rings true to you
Very much
And so it is possible
That shipping something from
China
Is cheaper
Then shipping something to your Neighbor Next Door
Yeah price-wise called twice no
Meaning of course it cost
A lot of money to ship something for
From China
But because of these artificially low upu reimbursement rate
The actual price for China Post is wailer
Honesty is a chart that estimates how much
And it says
If you or I wanted to send
A 3/4 pound package
Somewhere in the US
The US Postal Service
Would charge around $4.76
For the last leg of the
Yeah the so-called final mile
However
If that same package came in from China
The USPS would only charge China Post
Dollars 39
That means the USPS charges you and me
Roughly three and a half
Times more than what they charge China Post
Yes
But you get how crazy it is
Baidu
I do it i mean this is a system which totally askew
Excuse the market market function
What do you view has created
It's almost like
Over verse trade barrier
Like why would I buy something that ships from the US
When the US Postal Service
Is essentially subsidizing shipping
From China
And this is true
For virtually every country in the world there
Is often an incentive
To buy something that
Ships
From another country instead of your own
And that
Anna says
Beans that upu has been
Quietly changing the flow
At the global economy
When you think about this system
How do you feel about
Computer in a
Economics
Point of view
It's distorting pricing
That's how I would you know put it from a purely
Theoretical
And then of course it's a human
I feel frustration that is going on
What does buy a lot of things
Online
Crappy things that we shouldn't have bought otherwise
It also means you know a lot for the environment
If we
UShip a lot of things
Bye-bye airplane or you don't even vote for
But it said just bigger than
No money
And so this brings us to the final part
Of Jamie smaldones
The price-fixing postal Illuminati are screwing over American small pill
And so
I think we can say
This is
Arguably true especially if most of your customers
Learn the United States
Jamie is shipping is mugs around the
And the USPS
Is giving a better deal to China Post
Then it is
In other words Nick I think what you're saying is
A posse of powerful postal people
Are playing with parcel prices
Proliferating pandemonium and potentially Prime profits
Former protagonist
A patriotic producer
Of portable plastic
Pouring Prada
Precisely
After the break
Mcall
Poor Jamie
And tell him he was right all along
Support for NPR comes from LinkedIn learning proud to support the launch of life
NPR's guy to help you make better life decisions
LinkedIn learning short video tutorials cover business Tech
And creative skills employers look for at every level
All taught by experts and new courses are added every week
+ LinkedIn learning is personalized
Recommended courses based on your interest and Life kid listeners get a month of learning free
Start your free trial at LinkedIn learning.com NPR
Hey Jamie yep how's it going it's Nick and Kenny hey what's up guys how are you
So we know it's been a long time since we talked
I actually thought you
You forgot about
Yeah we never stopped looking into it
I mean I guess I should say Jamie when we first met you and when you told us
This expansive Theory
Beside you sounded like a little Looney
Riot
I knew how you were going to
View the whole
I mean
I think it's fair to say Nick that like
Everything Jamie told us
Is
Like true
Checks out
That makes me feel good
Could you guys know I was harassing you
Before we met
Yeah
We're about to lose the studio it was awesome talking with you
Emailed you it's incredible story
All right man I mean like okay thank you so much okay alright guy
All right
Do you know of a conspiracy theory that is not just
The theory is true if so email has Planet Money on NPR. Org or all the social media
Are supervising producer is Alex goldmark and our editor is Brian first.
I'm the fountain and I'm Kenny Malone
Thanks for listening
And one last thing
When we were visiting Jamie and testing his mighty mug
You did mention this one thing
You saying I can't spell this
This is a challenge you have to hit it with about six or seven pounds of pressure eventually anything hit
Will dislodge
Fast forward month later to this studio which has a lot of expensive equipment in it
Kenny
Bottom buddy mug and apparently forgot to list
They don't spell
That's too hard