Everyone Robert Smith here a couple weeks ago I got an email from a listener named Mark
Hummer gang
Mark listen to this episode right here when it aired back in 2013
And you heard a reporter's makeup promise at the very end of the epi
They said that they would follow up in 5 years
And so I went down to my calendar and I set an appointment for July 1at 2018
Are we actually forgot about it
But July 1st rolls around and marks ends with an image of his Google Calendar and there's a big red circle around a note
It says
Planet Money to follow up
I'm show number 472
Wild hold you guys accountable
Everybody we keep our promises for today we bring you an update on the brilliant one page plan to fix
Global warming
This one's for you mark
I've been covering climate change on and off for about
14 years
And it's one of those stories were frankly as a journalist
You get kind of burned out because
It's essentially the same story over and over again
Scientist saying hey this is real
Could be bad
Sea level rise giant storms extinctions
Then of course you hear politicians and world leaders and yes we must do something
And then
And then not a lot happens
As a sign of how gridlock we are in this country President Obama the other week laid out his plans to try to reduce carbon emission
Sentir in the United
He's having to rely on a 43 year old law that was
Originally intended to deal with smog
It had nothing to do with carbon dioxide
Guesstimate a kind of joke about it
43 years ago Congress passed a law called
The Clean Air Act
Of $0.19
Matlock passed the Senate unanimously
Think about that
Unanimously it passed the House of Representatives
I don't know who the one guy was
I haven't looked at a
Where you can barely get that many votes to name a Post Office business
You certainly can't get that many votes for a full-on climate bill in,
Chris right now
Type of thing to me is what makes
Climate change seems so hopeless
The promise so dire and get the world is finding it so impossible to act
And I've always imagined it's because the solutions are just incredibly complicated
Inexpensive
At the standard
Short-term pain versus long-term gain dining
It turns out they're fixing climate change does not have to be either of the
There is a very simple solution
That could cost us
Almost
Nothing
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm David kestenbaum and I'm Alex blumberg today on the show
The one-page dream plan to solve global warming for free
Costa
Support also comes from Fidelity Investments
As a Fidelity wealth manager
You get a dedicated advisor
There to help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes
And make it clear recommendations for your full Financial
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
What are the guys has been dreaming about this simple way to deal with climate change
His name is Henry Jacoby he's an economist at MIT
Center for Energy and environmental policy research
And he told me really if you want to address climate change
There is just one thing you need to do
If you left the economist write the legislation it could be really simple
If you were to write it how short could it be
So if I if I were to write it
Page
What you Kobe would write on that page is
A carbon tax
Basically he says you tax the fossil fuels in proportion to the amount of carbon they released
That would make coal oil and natural gas more expensive
And then
Actually that's all you have to do
Do understand how this would work I took a drive with jacobi's colleague John Riley
Obviously gasoline is a fossil fuel so under a carbon tax it gets more expensive
And driving gets more expensive
What kind of car is this
It's an Infiniti
With my kids all gone I actually decided to do something luxury this that's good something like 27 miles per gallon on the highway
The worst thing around
But it's not a it's not a Prius we pull into a gas station
In the first year of a carbon tax
He imagines the price of gasoline would rise by about
$0.25 a gallon
Over a year he figured this would cost him an extra
$125
But then it would get more expensive
So the way most people imagine a carbon tax working is that you wrap it up over time
Tighten the screws
Gradually push the economy away from
Fossil fuels
By 2050
Riley figures the carbon tax would go from $0.25 a gallon
About a dollar
Barry Allen
Predator the math to figure out how much that would cost him driving his Infiniti extra per year
Then that would be about $500 a year I might buy more fuel efficient vehicle
And right there. If that is the carbon tax
Working at the
It is that people and businesses all over the economy they would start thinking
Making changes course correction some big some small to avoid the higher cost
Here's Henry Jacoby again
You can decide
Do you want to harass your children to turn off the lights
Do you want to buy a smaller car
Do you want to drive the bus one day a week
Do you want to insulate your attic
1000 things that people think of to lower
The cost of of this activity this cut
Got the tax on it
The tax has a has small effects around us around a million different activities and that's the advantage of it gets
Its influence almost
Everywhere
And this is why Economist generally love
A carbon tax those tiny effects
Over millions and millions of people and activities
Can have
A huge impact
When change to the tax code in the entire economy all of us living in the world
We shift our Behavior
Reduce carbon emission
So do, this is super obvious of fossil fuels
Costs associated with them that aren't reflected in their price right now so you just need to correct that price
Make it more expensive
Although that does raise an obvious question here how much
More expensive
Figure out how much more expensive we're going to Imagine John Riley life under a carbon
We're going to try to figure out how much extra everything would cost him and add it up
Do we need gasoline already
In the first year of a carbon tax he estimates gasoline would cost him a total of about
125 bucks more a year
So I'm going to keep track your genres are proxy for what life would be like under a carbon tax
We're at a hundred and twenty five bucks a year so far
And then the next thing probably is electricity
Yeah so here's my electric bill
My electric bill last month was $46.27
Generali figures that would go up but not by that much
About $60 each
All right so adding that
$185 a year so far extra that were spending
What else is there
There's heating witch in New England heating can be pretty expensive
You know I think I did some calculations
I'm near the average household in
New England would spend about $1,000 on natural gas for heating your home
The carbon tax would add
About $100 today
Write another hundred rat 285 right now
Anything else
And I kept trying to find Big Ticket items I like airplane flies he said that's probably $75 a year
$360 extra a year
It turned out one of the most carbon-intensive activities is something
I had not even thought of
It's something it's right underneath our feet
Concrete
And to get to the bottom of this one John and I call if a guy on speakerphone who works
In the concrete business
My name is David Perkins and I'm with
TXI based out of Dallas Texas
And we
Manufacture cement aggregate in concrete building materials
It's fantastic to talk to you David
Likewise
David Perkins explains that concrete is basically cement with some gravel and sand added
And the process of making cement
Produces a lot of carbon dioxide
Making 1 ton of cement he says
Makes about eight tenths of a ton of
CO2
They're two reasons for this one is that there's a lot of chemistry involve do you have to heat the ingredients up to very high temperature
That often means using fossil
Desecrated
But then there's also the the process itself
Turned out to produce carbon dioxide on its own me the chemical reactions by which the cement is formed that produces carbon
Approximately 50
2%
Of those two missions at the CO2 that is
Generated from the manufacturer of at 7
That is is directly related to what we call process
And that's that chemical step it has to
Steak place
But that's largely unavoidable
That's correct
We do the math and it looks like concrete under the first year of a carbon tax
The price of concrete would go up by
25%
You be looking at a pretty significant impact abs
This is one of those Industries where
It's hard to imagine a way to adjust
Make the thing make concrete
Without producing any carbon dioxide
And David Perkins says concrete is everywhere
One of those kind of things that
Likely standing on
Or in a building that has
Cement indoor Concrete in it
It if it's really kind of a
Have a silencer thing that you don't really realize
Can you see cement or concrete from where you are right now
As matter fact I am sitting on some
So concrete a lot of
Carbon emissions associated with it but it's actually hard to account for in my Tally here right to
John Riley
He's not going to the hardware store with a girly and buying bags of concrete
Evite
Byram concrete at all he walks on concrete he may work in the concrete building but those things are no longer in meeting
The carbon they were limited to carbon when they were created but
How do we do this
I guess that's a Mighty Ducks build a new building
It works or
You know
And carpet is more expensive that means maybe less salary for John or something or if the city needs to raise taxes
Tag cover the cost of putting in new sidewalks you know that could impact him but
John Riley doesn't actually buy in a concrete
Do you think simple for our purposes with him is our products
You can add 0
Can you add zero all right
So
Is there anything else before you go on there's one other thing I asked
If you think about the stuff that we spend money on everyday
There's one big ticket thing was left out which is
Futon
What's a big budget item
So we went to the supermarket and I tried to find things that have been shipped from
Far away
Picking up
Fruits and vegetables and looking at the label and asking
John how much more expensive they would be
Would it be a big deal
Oranges oranges come from Florida
Not a big deal
Mangoes mangoes from Peru
Again not a big deal
Kiwi where are kiwis from
Originally from New Zealand so that would be about the fire far as you can
What's the distance from New Zealand
Not a big deal
The transportation part is not a big part of the cost
We look at the transportation think that's the big deal
Transportation to help you put things on boats
It's really pretty efficient in terms of fuel use
3 buy a bunch of stuff
Got to the car and then we look through the bill
So our grocery shopping $13.12 looks like
And the total carbon tax would be
About $0.17
So the headline thing carbon tax review
Yes
If we trace it all the way through because food would cost them maybe
Fifty bucks extra a year in the first year of a car
Alright so
That's it right that everything's alright to our grand total then calculate this up for the additional cost to John Riley
Are proxy under the first year of a carbon tax
$410
Puryear that's how much
What do we think about
Well first of all for a lot of families
That could be pretty paint
It's all right if you're in the lower income bracket
You're counting every dollar you're definitely going to feel
And for some people obviously it will be way more than 410
If you have a very long commute you spend a lot of fossil fuels you have
Why you left your job
If you're a coal miner you're probably going to be hit especially hard
And remember this is also just for the first year of a carpenter
Tax rate that is the tax
Is going to go off of it every year to force people to change with
I do have to say
I thought I would be more this is basically
A dollar a day
And you may have heard that phrase in Pella. I feel like if you going to pay that for public radio it seems a bargain for saving the world
Play the beginning of the podcast we said for
Free whatever you think about it is not free
That's because we're not done yet
There is one more part to this
Which is about what you do with all that money you raised from a carpet
If the tax rates of the government collecting money everyone
$110 or whatever on average
And what you do Under the Sea
And if you would take that money you brought in
And you give it right back to the
White soda
Just to be clear collect all this money from people you divide it up by the population
And then you write everyone a check
That's that's a boy to think about
Usher
How does it help it feel like a defeat the purpose you take 410 bucks from John Reilly
And then you
Better check for 410 bucks that's on average right I mean I know it's weird
It seems like magic
But I mean imagine right in this scenario
Gas and
Heating your house all that stuff
It is still more expensive even if you get the check
Great so there's still this incentive tonight
Use fossil fuel
You can think about it from Individual people
Perspectives right if you live in a city
And you get the check you might actually making money cuz the check will be more than you're paying and carbon tax
If you live in a rural area
And you have a large carbon footprint the check isn't going to offset it all but
In either case you're still going to hate paying rent tax and you're going to try and
Change your habits
Change what you doing
Maybe people moved
They still make
The more money you save
I'll be doing something differently
That's extra money in your pocket cuz you're not paying the tax
And then you still get a check at the end of the year
Does he like me
You can't work
Well
Trust me
Should
This is actually pretty basic economic
And there's a way to take this magic trick and make it even more Magic
You give the money back in a smarter way you don't write everyone to check
You just cut their income
Right so you give the money back by
Lessening their income
They get to keep more of their salary
Exactly
In polls most Economist love the carbon tax
The same Economist tend to dislike
The income tax
That's because when you tax something
You discourage it
Income is something we probably don't want to discourage we want to encourage people to
Be able to keep more of the money that they are in the job we want to encourage businesses
To hire people and income tax discourages.
Deborah, this is a chance to reduce a bad tax the income tax and replace it with
A good tax
A tax on carbon
It's like a kind of pollution
In fact if you do this John Riley
A carbon tax
Can be nearly painless
For the economy as a whole
That's right as promised
You can fight climate change
And do it
Basically
This is almost Magic
Because
In some of the work we've done
The whole economy actually benefits by that tacswap
You raise the carbon tax at does increase your energy cost
But you actually improve economic performance by reducing the other tax
And the economy is actually better off
Can it really be true
Yes
As I called around I talked to a bunch of Economist about the
The basic idea is totally sound
And if you give the money back by
Cutting taxes
Some people were skeptical the economy would actually grow faster if you do that but
But they said you could definitely offset a lot of the
Me to be clear right certain industries
Coal mining for instance would take a hit
Some people will pay more than others under the sea
System but
When you look at the economy of the whole
It doesn't miss a step
Just keeps on growing
And of course there is one other benefit the thing we're trying to fix in the first place
Climate change we're finally addressing
And it's all because of
Carbon tax write it encourages people to conserve energy and also this is something effect that that I love about it that we haven't touched on
When you make
Carbon more expensive
Other
More environmentally friendly energy sources become less expensive by comparison to for example right now
Coal is cheaper than solar
But presumably under carbon tax eventually
Kobe more expensive
Solar energy solar becomes
The financial irrational
Choice
And that's how you end up
Switching the entire life
Andrew Jacoby told me that
If you could Implement a global carbon
Tax all over the world
He says you could limit global warming to 2 degrees by the end of the century
Instead of where we're headed now which
It could be more like 5 degree
The kind of standard line that you have in the international discussions that were trying to limit that the increase the tutor
That's something that would be
Avoid the sort of the really bad.
If you hit the five degrees we're talkin about a world that we don't really understand
It's it it is deadly serious business
If we could hold it to 2 degrees which won't be easy if we could hold it to degree
I think that
Probably would survive a lot better but five five degrees
Effects on
On ecosystems and agriculture on Selah rise
Such ass is something that
That we just barely under
So let me get this straight
Beer connoisseur saying that perhaps the biggest environmental crisis that Humanity has ever faced
One that has
What policy-makers for decades
Is utterly solvable and won't cost us
Barely a penny
Basically yes I mean are there winners and losers right
A carbon tax in the US you shift a lot of money around
Some people bother
And and if you look out really long termite
Like to the end of the century they say there is some slight drag on the USA
It's pretty small I mean instead of
Our economy being say 8.6 times larger than it is now
It would be eight points
4 * log
And you know what we're talking about here at this is just for the United States
You know one of the biggest
Challenges with implementing something like
My guess is that
You need to do a global you need to do it in all
And its carbon tax would be more costly for a
They're still constructing all their buildings and Roads
They're using much more cement and concrete
Much more energy
And this coordination problem
Is of course one of the main reasons that this simple slow
Actually so
Simple to implement
You got to commit the rest of the world's come along with
You can still argue
It is basically free for us and you have to do it why don't you just go ahead
When I was in Boston I talk to Gilbert Metcalf he
Come back from
Ascent at the treasury Department needs an economist
At Tufts
And I asked him
You know what is there a special binder in the treasury Department on the Shelf somewhere in the office that says
Secret carbon tax
And he said no you know that Congress has debated a cap-and-trade plan which
Implemented isn't that different
Carbon tax
You know it's not something it's on the table right
And I said would you think a carbon tax or something like it really has any chance
And he said eventually he thinks
Yes it does
Kind of like what Churchill said about the Americans around World War II that
The Americans will always do the right thing after
You're trying everything else first
And I kind of think that's where we are around climate
We're going to try lots of foolish and silly ideas and wasteful ideas will try to ignore the problem for a while
But at some point we're going to recognize the problems there
And to a carbon tax we can raise some Revenue
To address some other problems
I think eventually
I might come around.
I'd love to have this interview in five years and see how much closer we are or maybe we can talk about how well it's working
Vitamin E listeners tuned in July 2018 we will have a follow-up
Years time we could be walking around
Hi May I
Get room number to three
To Gilbert Metcalf
Get Back cast
Hey this is Robert Smith from Planet Money
Where where are you right now
Time in Gothenburg Sweden
Where I'm attending the world
Congress of environmental and resource economy
Nice
So
Do you know why we're calling you
Nope I'll give you a hint
It's been exactly 5 years since we talked to you last
Okay
Well here let me let me play you back from 5 years ago
I'd love to have this interview
5 years
Or maybe we can talk about
How well it's working
Vitamin E listeners tuned in July 2018
You were so optimistic
Well I continue to be optimistic Robert
We have a carbon tax in British Columbia we have a carbon tax
Sweden is $130 a ton
I'm sitting here looking at a thriving economy
That doesn't seem to be you know on its knees because of the carbon tax
But in terms of us five years was
Perhaps too optimistic
Perhaps I should have said
8 to 10 years
So we don't have a national carbon tax but here's what has changed
We now have the number of very very senior Republican
Who are saying we really need a carbon tax
So I think that that's progress
So one thing that did happen in The Last 5 Years
A carbon tax was on the ballot in Washington state is very similar
To the one-page plan that we talked about in the show
Voters in Washington State
Rejected that carbon tax and surprisingly
A number of environmentalist
Rejected
What was the issue there
So
Part of the issue is
That
Some groups wanted to use the revenue to pay for for green projects
Others wanted to give it back
Two households to a carbon dividend
And there was and there was this disagreement about what to do there
So
Professor Metcalf we're going to call you
In July of
2B 2023
5 years from now
Any prediction
Well I'm going to be a little more cautious than I was 5 years ago
I won't have it we will definitely have a carbon tax but I think
I think we're on the path
I think we're going to have one
If not within 5 years
I think
I think definitely within the decade okay a decade I'm going to put this down July 2028
Will call you back look forward to talking to you
Other promises that we
We really should follow up on
Well let us know Planet Money at npr.org we can find us on all the usual social networks
Facebook
Instagram
And Twitter
Thanks to our original host of this episode David kestenbaum and Alex blumberg and the original producer chest J
Update with Bruce by Alicia's Carson
And our senior producers out School Barker editors Brian Trista and I I am Robert Smith
Thanks for listening