Support for NPR and the following message come from State Farm
When it comes to home and auto insurance
They're here through the ups and down
Go to statefarm.com
To be connect
It was one of the 19000 ages
In neighborhoods
Across the Nation
State Farm
Here to help life
Go right
Hey it's Noel King here
You probably heard that earlier this week Amazon announced the location of its new head
Headquarters and it picked two places to pick Northern Virginia and New York City
An Amazon says each place is going to get about 25000
City jobs
No that was the end of a very long
Bidding war there were dozens of states and cities that were courting Amazon by offering them billions of dollars in tax
And some other stuff too there was this one time in Georgia
Where the mayor said okay will carve out 345 Acres
We'll make a new town and we will let Jeff Bezos be the mayor or the CEO or the king or what
Whatever he wants
We think that mayor was just joking
But a bunch of you wrote to us with the same question which was basically
Why do cities and states offer these huge tax incentives
And when they do it does it actually make sense is it in their interest
Back in 2006
16 Stacey Vanek Smith and I reported a story on why this
Kansas City is kind of a unique
It's not one city it's actually two
Any split right down the middle so that half of Kansas city is in Kansas and half of Kansas city is in Missouri
There is a road running down the middle of the sea
City that divides it
It is called
Stateline Road
We are in the car driving along
Stateline Road okay Kansas is on the left and the reason right
Phillips 66 is in
Missouri
Station in Missouri
And the Capitol Federal
Prairie Village
Is in Kansas
Yeah
Yeah people make a really big deal out of
We were hearing all the stuff about this
Huge rivalry
Between the two
States
So we pulled off of Stateline Road into a little shopping center on the
Kansas I'd
To see what
People would say about
What are people in Missouri like
You look cute
We friendly we got we are good
Be around
Wilbury
A very hard-working p
Are people from Missouri like
A little differently people from Kansas
Well
Yeah
Apparently people from Kansas are a little bit
Navi
Rochelle Graham from Kansas says
We are not snobby
What are people from Kansas like
I would say very down-to-earth
Helpful kind
Big sense of community
We heard all kinds of
People from Kansas told
Missouri relay
City Folk
Real country values
Are people from Missouri told us
Kansas
We're aloof and verb
Bad drivers
We wanted to get to the bottom of this
And then there in the parking lot we met
Quinton Donnelly
Who broke it down for us like
Kansas people are
Very short minded
Yo
The Kansas
If you saw me and Noel
One of us one of us was from Missouri what would you guess
Allstate
I say you're more
Okay Kansas
She looks like
You know she gets the party started
And I look
Like
You look like you like to read books
Call Alton
He called you a nerd
I know it's like the Raiders versus the party game
But look there rivalry between Kansas and Missouri goes beyond trash talk
While we were down there people kept telling us there is a war going on along the border between
End this war is over something very important
It's a war over job
The two states are fighting to lure companies to their state and not the one across State Line Road
And they're spending millions of dollars
This is something that's happening all over the
It's just that usually it happens over much greater distances
It's like California and New York
Competing over a tech company
Or Georgia and New Jersey battling it out over car
Kansas Missouri you can see this happening
Right up close
Because the tug-of-war is
Literally across the street
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Noel King and I'm Stacey Vanek Smith today on the show The kansas-missouri
A close-up look at what politicians like to call job creation
What looks a lot of times a little bit more like jobs
And we'll tell you the story of the fight over one company you probably know it you may have even eaten one of their quesadilla burger
This message comes from NPR sponsor squares
Squarespace allow small businesses
Design and build their own website
Using customizable layout
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobile added
Squarespace also offers
Built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online press
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Inn at the Kansas Missouri border War
Just like in any War
There are General
I am a non-commissioned officer
Grace I'm actually know it I'm actually just a soldier
Blake Shrek works for a Chamber of Commerce in Kansas
And it's his job to make sure companies come to Kansas and stay in can
Jesus really Dapper guy he's got sick white hair
He wears jeans and Blazers
Izzy's tortoiseshell glasses
And his office is in this old sprawling Victorian house
It's really lovely place
But make no mistake
This is Blake
War room
He's got all these top secret documents on his desk with
Code names for the companies that use trying to attract
Because Blake doesn't want his Rivals from
Say across the sea
Missouri to know which companies are in play
What are some of the code names
Okay hand sign
Here's the latest we've got project George
Project Scout
Project standard project view twin Kodiak Lantern LSA Sesame 2
It's just the last month
Avis fantasy that Sesame 2 is like
A fast food company like Burger King
I can't stop thinking about what Sesame one was
An oldies codenames all the secrecy Blake's job wasn't always
Yeah he's been doing this for 30 years
And he said for him the war really ramped up about 10 years ago with one company
Applebee's
At the time Applebee's have their headquarters on Blake side
Encanta
And they were doing well they were growing and they came to Blake and they said
We need a bigger building
They called him up and said look we'd like to stay in Kansas we want to build this new headquarters big fancy new place
But then there's like a shift
Skin tone
And they tell him
You know we're pretty big deal we can go where we want to
And we may you know go to Missouri I'm so what can you do for us
Blake did not want to lose Apple
They were big employer they were a big company
Point of Pride for the state of Kansas
So Applebee's suggested that Kansas give it a text
A big one
Like how about for the next
10 years we basically pay no property
Are feeling what's a little bit of the time was that that just wasn't done if you really want to be in our community you need to pay
Full about this puts Blake and Kansas in a tough position
Right even give Applebee's what it's asking for then they're going to lose a lot of property tax revenue
On the other hand
Kansas said no it would lose
Even more
The corporate taxes from a multi-billion-dollar company
Payroll taxes for hundreds of employees
And all of the property taxes from Apple
Tens of millions of dollars
We're on the line
It calls the mayor and says
We can't let this payroll I mean it was a huge deal
Leave the state but we really need to step up
So Blake ways these two kind of crummy options
Any decides
We need to give Applebee's what they want
He makes his case to the local politicians
In the end
Kansas takes his advice
It makes an offer
Applebee's
You stay we will give you more than 12 million dollars in tax breaks
And some other part
Parks we will also fix up a bunch of Roads around for your shiny new
Headquarters will be
And even then Blake wasn't sure they'd be able to keep Applebee's in Kansas
Finally the company called him
Heather on speakerphone and they said Kansas has the choice
And then we're going to like
Yeah in the background but we are very happy
But we can't just jump around doing End Zone celebration we just had to say what we're glad to have you
And it's right around this time that the
Kansas Missouri rivalry
The war for job starts to heat up
Because both States put in place incentive programs
Tueller companies in
Lisa Beasley if you create jobs here will give you a text
And if you are a company in
Missouri there is a really easy way for you to create a bunch of jobs
In Kansas and get those amazing tax rate
You just move
Right across the border move across State Line Road
You don't have to hire a single new person
Your workers just changed their commute a little bit
And now you qualify for this huge tax free
The new company crosses State Line Road the politicians could say hey we created a bunch of new jobs
Won't you say creating jobs but it's kind of like
Stealing jobs
No because if it's a new job to the state of Kansas it's a new job in the state of Kansas whether it's from Missy
Mississippi or Missouri
And because it's it's not our state
Do you're creating jobs
In the state of Kansas that were like
Stolen from across the sea
Every time that somebody comes from say Missouri to Kansas that is a new Revenue stream that we create
The payroll taxes in capital investment and all the things that go along with that
That we didn't have before it's easier to come back from outer space and table that doesn't make any sense but the reality is
It does
There are blank
In every state
This is not just Kansas
According to one study
States all over the country are spending
70 billion dollars a year
Where to create
Flash steal jobs from each other
And all the kansas-missouri Border this is heated up so much
Kind of cotton
Out of control
Yeah let's list some of the companies that are hopping back in
Okay
JPMorgan retirement moved across the border from Missouri
Kansas
Free quote a shipping company Kansas to Missouri
Lake Lofts at 1
AMC the big movie chain moved from Missouri to
Kansas another win for
Kansas North American Savings Bank
Kansas to Missouri at the Los Robles
We even found one company that moved from Missouri to Kansas
And then back
To Missouri
Is an accounting and insurance firm
Cold sea bass
Right so we went by to talk to them and we met Jeff Carlstadt
The senior managing director
We met in the conference room on the 11th floor of the building
Beautiful view
From that conference room he can see his old office
From the window well it's not actually his old office it's his
Old old office
From when they used to be in Missouri before they move to Kansas and then
Came back to
Where we were
Right
Do that Skelly sign parking garage
Like and I can see my very first window that I had from
We asked him about the movie
And he said there are a lot of factors
He did admit that tax breaks and incentives played a role
He wouldn't tell us how much misery gave the company but according to what we read in the local papers
Is about 26 million dollars and incense
That was in 2014 and cbiz now has a 15-year lease
You're always going to be looking in the evaluating what that next step is I'm
Nope or 15 years away from the end of this lease and
I want to look at inside
What's the next what's even the next move would you go over the state line again
We would evaluate whatever makes the most sense
Time for unemployed eyesight
You can say that you would never say no to anything
Never say no
It's kind of like you sending a coded message over to Blake Shrek like Kansas make me an offer
Yeah for a company this makes sense
It's the smart thing to do
But you can see where all of this ends up right
The states want to keep these companies so they're slashing tax
And they're digging themselves deeper into a hole
That tax revenue was going to pay for stuff like roads and schools and police
In fact just a couple months after Kansas spent 50 million dollars
Snatching AMC Theaters from across the street in Missouri
Kansas credit education budget by 104 million dollars
And once you Laura company over
There's no guarantee it's going to stay
We met Dave Francais a lawyer in Kansas City
Is your job to leverage Kansas Missouri against
That's part of you
And one day day was talking to a friend of his another lawyer one who happens to work for a certain company that's
Let's just say
Makes a mean quesadilla
A man I knew for a long time A friend of mine was in-house lawyer at Applebee's
And we ran into each other and he mentioned to me that
They were looking
At relocating their corporate headquarters
Applebee's
Which Kansas had fought so hard to keep
A few years before
Was thinking about
Moving
It was under new ownership the company was downsizing
And the big new office building
Was too big
Applebee's hires de France saved and Dave starts
Doing his thing
We reached out to both state
And we said we are representing Applebee's here's the number of jobs here's the
Average wages here's the
The capital investment they're planning to make
And we asked each state
You know what they would propose Warrior on the Kansas side Blake is running around trying to find Apple
Smaller building
Missouri is scrambling to get its own inside
Centos package
Both States put their best
Offer on the table
Applebee's Ways to Die
Time goes by
Andy call Dave
With their decision
He was on his way to a Boy Scout camp
Where he volunteer
I remember I was driving down
And
And always on
Hands-free
Speakerphone on my
In the car and
And I said guys I got
Five more minutes and then I'm going to be out of cell range
We're going with Missouri
Lakeside Kansas
Had lost
The last thing
I did before I went out of cell range was called the two states and said
Sorry
Kansas there they've decided they're going to move to this other location and then
Called Missouri and said hey
Congratulations they've selected Missouri is our location
Applebee's move
14 MI
From Kansas to
12 million dollars
And this was just
6 years after Blake Shrek Arkansas border Warrior
Steve Applebee's millions of dollars in tax break
To stay in Kansas
Saudi fransi the lawyer negotiated this deal he's negotiated a lot of them actually
And he may be the dealmaker but even he acknowledges
This
Is madness
When I start talking to clients that are in the area
The first thing I say to him is you know before we talk about what the incentives are I need to tell you
That what we can talk about is probably the worst public policy in the history of the world
It's
Terrible
Thought process by both states of Missouri and Kansas it is also part of how Dave makes his living so
So it's not like he tells companies don't do it
It is lawful
It is encouraged by both States
And
There is an opportunity that you as a business have to consider whether you want to do that
With these help Applebee's negotiated it's moved to Missouri in 2011
We went to see their new offices
They are right on Stateline Road like a
Few feet inside of the Missouri border
Let's just go see
Okay going in the lobby
Hi good morning how are you
It's at the Applebee's building
That's shorna Andrews she's the receptionist here
It feels so good
Quiet in here
It's very quiet
It's quiet
For a reason
We ran into Dion Crooks
In the lobby is a facilities manager at Applebee's
And one day last fall he came to work
He's actually pretty excited that day because they were having a big all staff party
For the upcoming football
We had a
Had beers
You know hotdogs
Everything setup
Then
About
An hour later
I got a email
To say that we have to do a room setup for 300 people
This was not a part of the party plan
This was an all-staff meeting
Well fast for another hour
Email
Tell a party cancel
Saudi on setup
Conference room
All the employees
Please come in we got up
Stairs walk in the door
Our CEO is he the first person we saw we want
Only thing we see her we saw every department head from every
Apartment the CEO starts talkin and Dionne can tell it
It's something big
She starts out with good news
She says
We've had a great year the company's doing well
Which makes him
Suspicious
Isis cell cars for several years
I know how it is to
When the car says we like to put people up at the top
And get them happy
Evan drop a bomb on me
And then
Came the bomb
Applebee's was moving again
And not across the border
California
And most of the people in that room would be losing their job
It was kind of a
Big sigh
The entire room
What it sound like
And then the next thing everybody's head went straight down to your phone
I'm in
I personally got up and walked out
I didn't hear the rest of the wish you were saying
Came back downstairs when's opposite I just got sat there for a while
Since that meeting which happened last year Dion says people have
I've been trickling out
The office
Has gotten quieter and
Beyonce's the last Christmas party which happened just a couple of months after
After the meeting
Was truly awful
Mattress patch
What's the Christmas before last
The soul
Define energetic
Oh man it was great
In this past Christmas it was just kind of like
This is my last Christmas party
You know
I won't be here next year
Beyonce's P understands why Applebee's made this move
It's parent company is headquartered in California so it made sense to consolidate
So after years of fighting over Applebee's
Kansas and Missouri both lost
I want to hear politicians talk about creating jobs
Sometimes those are new jobs
But a lot of times it looks like this
Yeah there's been a job created in California
But somewhere else there's a guy like Deon trying to smile through a Christmas party
So here's one tally of where things stand along the kansas-missouri
From 2010 to 2015
Two jobs
Moved from Missouri
You can look at that and say it sounds pretty good for Kansas
But you know how many jobs went the other way from Kansas to Missouri almost as many
In the end it's one of those Wars where neither side has really one
But everyone
I spent a lot of money fighting
The dueling tax breaks
Cost the government
Half a billion dollar
These numbers by the way it come from the hall Family Foundation which is a local philanthropic group and it looked at a bunch of counties right around
So maybe not surprisingly Missouri and Kansas have both been talking about a truce
Missouri wrote what amounts to a
Treaty and along the lines of Kansas
If you don't steal our jobs we won't steal your
Kansas ignored it
And then just a few weeks ago Kansas wrote its own version of a
Retreat which is slightly different from Missouri
Missouri responded saying Kansas we will not sign your treaty
You should sign ours
It is a
Truce War
This is what Kansas and Missouri are fighting over now
How to make
Alright so we did that story back in the spring of 2016 did Kansas and Missouri end up calling a truce if they'd
Did whose truth did they called
That's coming up after the break
Support for this podcast and the following message
Just come from The Economic Development Authority of Fairfax County Virginia
Located near DC
And home to 8900 technology companies
And 144000 Technology jobs
Details at Fairfax
Bucks County Eda. Org
When we left off in 2016 Kansas and Missouri were talking about a truce about a way to avoid these bidding wars
So I did a quick Google search today to find out if they struck a deal and I found the story in the Kansas Star from
Be weary of this year
Kansas the state of Kansas offered 3 million dollars in tax breaks to a company called HCA mid
Midwest Health
If that company would move
4 miles across the border into Kansas
And the company took the deal so no troops as far as we can tell
We would love to hear what you think of the show you can send us an email to Planet Money NPR. Org and we're on Facebook and Instagram
Twitter at Planet Money Today Show was originally produced by Alex goldmark and Sally Helm the reruns name is produced by
Machine McKean special think of Us episode 2 Kevin Collison Frank Morris Nancy Mays and Greg Roy our editor is
Spiders that and are supervising producer is Alex goldmark I'm Stacey Vanek Smith and I'm Noel King thanks for listening