Support for this in
NPR podcasts
The following message
Come from the UPS
Offering services from shredding
To printing to mailbox
And instead of closing this Memorial Day we
May 24th and 20
The UPS Store
He's doing another thing
All together
Opening
The UPS Store
Everything for small business
And of course shipping
Hey Scott it's Dan Charles
Hey Dan
How are you
I'm doing fine I'm in Washington DC Scott flake
Is in Sacramento California
What's the what's it like out there in Sacramento
Today just weather wise
Beautiful sunny day clear skies
And warming up
Scotts Valley forecasting business he is in
The energy
So sunlight to Hannah's mom
Take a look at this website
Here's a chart showing where California is getting its electricity right at this moment
Bichos nuclear plants
Gas burning plants hydroelectric
Dams
There's a chart with different colored lines showing Renewable Power
There's wind geothermal
There's Biomat
What's leave lines are pretty flat
Except for one song about the mall is a bright
Golden Lion
That is solar power
This is an incredible
Chart
This solar curve
You like it it's like this mountain
Suddenly appears in the middle of the day
Starting about 6 this morning when the sun came up it really started ramping up quickly
It goes from 0 to like where are we right now
Just over ten thousand megawatts
Which is almost half of all the electricity that California is using right
It's pretty incredible
And just as incredible what that sunlight is doing to be price
Of electricity right now here I can see what utilities are paying for electricity
A dozen different places across the state minute by me
Sometimes it's expensive
But there are times
Especially on weekends when people are not using much electricity
This flood of solar energy does really weird things to those prices
Often times UK
Have
Moore Supply of energy
Then demand
And so what happens is the lot of those price
Start to show up as
Negative numbers
Negative
Right so how can there be negative prices what does that mean
What would it be
People don't need that much energy
And if electricity is worth less than nothing the power company
He's other people to use the power to take it off the grid attic full of junk you'll pay somebody to
To get rid of
And there is even more solar power on the way the law in California demands
Companies are building vast
Solar arrays cover
Thousands of Acres
The California is Desert
When you first came to us with a story dad
I thought
This is really
News to me
That was in our lifetime California will have the source of energy that is
Safe
And renewable that can run everything in the state
Until
The sun goes down
Until the sun goes
And this is always been the solar energy
You build up the solar cells you run out of transmission line
And then the sunset
How to breed a Ghazt
Powered generators
Just to keep your lights on which is why the biggest question energy right now
Is a way to store all that beautiful solar energy solve this
Problem and you are well on your way to solving Global warm
And all you need is a battery
They can follow the Sun
LOL, Planet Money on Robert Charles today on the show I visit the biggest battery in the world
A technology so old it's almost forgotten
It may save the planet
But it does involve moving map
Support for NPR in the following message come from servicenow
Making the world of work work better for
They're cloud-based Platt
Form and solutions
Deliver digital workflow
That create great experiences for employees
And unlock productivity
For your whole company
Servicenow digitizes the work your people have to
So they can do the work
They want
Using technology
How to make people more productive and engaged
Moret servicenow.com
We're going to begin with some high school physics and like any good high school physics teachers we've got props
We've got metaphors
And we're going to use
Now when the Sun hits
Solar cell
It starts electrons moving in a wire
The more light
The more electrons
Look that way
The wires come together the flow of electricity becomes a mighty River
Andy Kim power
Millions of smoothie blenders in Los Angeles
Grow light
It's in Humboldt
The surveillance algorithms at Facebook in Silicon Valley
All of this power is
California treasurer
But the way the electrical grid works is you have to use the
The power as
There are very few ways to store up electricity and use it later
So how
What do you catch
We called up one of the largest electricity companies in
In California PG&E
Pacific Gas and
Arrange to talk with a Senior Vice-President there
Fang one
PR guy who accidentally got dropped off the
I'm in trouble now I'm not supposed to do these interviews without lye
Communications Department obvious place to store
When we use everyday
Are you familiar with that Lithium-ion batteries yes battery is you're probably using one of your phone right
Right now in fact in California you may have charged your phone of electricity from the Sun
In-N-Out
Storing
Solar energy
In your pocket
PG&E is thinking of the same thing right now we are in the process of purchasing
A lot of battery storage
Big ones that are the size of trailers lined up in a parking
Imagine
Elon Musk speech with a
1000 of the giant batteries
He's building Outlet
This problems too big even for Elon Musk PG&E is talking
Him and
And 5 other battery
There is a slight problem here
If you remember at the beginning we found out how much
Kassidi the sun is producing
Right now in the middle of the day in Calif
Just over 10000 megawatt
All those big batteries at
But they are all built five years from now
They'll capture maybe one purse
Percent of the amount of electricity that California will need to store.
Someone is looking for something
Better
I think we need to go back to
Be a little more daring
No more
Risk-taking says the bed with no
PR person
Okay so where can you find
More battery
Well if you can't
Build that many Big Data
Maybe you could just find Millions
The small batteries
I mean we mentioned the iPhone everyone has an iPhone with a little battery in it
A lot of people have left
DARCARS
PG&E is looking into that
The idea is
If you could encourage people to charge up their electric
Cars
When the sunshine
When they're at work maybe
Then when they put their cars in at home in the evening PG&E could draw on that stored electricity
4 price
What does 3/4
There's great potential
The very challenging
We are teachers our own habits
7 p.m.
I'm probably using the car
Probably a
Bad idea to base your entire electrical grid on people getting home from work
Trip that we are not out of options
Energy is energy
You don't have to store it in the form of
Chemicals in a
You can convert electricity into something that's literally
Pent-up physical energy
Like by teenagers right now in the last week
Maybe that would work
Imagine
Compressed air
Compressed air storage is
It's very fascinating
Basically when the sun is shining you use all that extra electricity to pump air into big
Underground Caverns like blowing up a name
Incredibly strong and mask
Balloon
I've got one right here
And then at sunset
You open the valve
At all that super compressed air comes
Was blasting
I'll get ready for this
It blows through a turbine
Spins and generate power
This is not going to work
Apparently
PG&E actually tried this out they got 50 million dollars from the government to blow air into some old gas
We were able to
Successfully
Drill
In 2012
Successfully
Pump Air
A very high pressure and
The air stayed pressurized
Underground
But we went a little bit hiccup
Right now
That is not cheap all right
Compressed air to expensive batteries
Too small
What else you got
Here's another thing that stores energy
Wheels
We don't know when you pedal really fast on a bike your momentum can carry you for blocks
You can do something similar with something called a
Flywheel a giant wheel made out of
Really heavy
Conservation of angular momentum sure you use the solar electricity to get this
Giant wheels
Maybe
Giant
Record player
Which radio Studios we happen to have fun if we get this thing moving with our finger
Becomes attorney
Faster and faster and faster super fast
Then when the Sun goes down to record player still spinning at still got momentum slowing just a bit
And then later in the evening when everybody
Turns on their TVs that giant Spinning Wheel can drive a generator
Search up very very
PG&E paid some people to build
But they were not able to deliver
They couldn't make it work
Okay so flat flywheels don't work
What economically
Technically I think they actually do ey for the last hundred years we've made a ton of progress
I'm storing massive amounts of power
You have to leave good ideas in theory but
Scale
Is so incomprehensibly
The record player
So large
How do you get the money
But here's the thing
Scotland font both of them they think there is a way to
That's when I got them talking about their dream way to store Electra
They started talking about a technology that's not some hot new invention
It's actually old
It's so old some people write it off
Relic of an earlier age but this is big
It is bold
It's hidden in the Hills robbery
And I'm sure you're going to tell us what it is Robert after the break
I'm going to visit the
The biggest battery in the world
And it's made out of water
Support also comes from Fidelity Investment
As a Fidelity wealth manager
You get a dedicated advisor
There to help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes
And make clear recommendations for your full Financial
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
The biggest battery in the world is a giant Lake
Tucked away in the Appalachian Mountains on the border between Virginia and West Virginia
Ghibli beautiful driving into this place we're driving down through this Valley a region
Green on either side blue sky above grass seed
Meadows with cows grazing on them it is just idyllic hear you listening to travels
With them
The number to insomnia podcast on iTunes
See what it was kind of
Until you get close and suddenly I see these huge electrical transmission lines
And then there's a sign Dominion Energy
A gate
A guard house
Is empty but there's a
Do not skimp on the sound effects
I can picture it
Close the door
Sleep with door open
Hi my name is Dan Charles
So when we can do is open the gate for you
Okay okay
All right
One more mile
Okay got it
Okay thank you so much
I drive over the hill and realize it's actually a damn and there is the link
It feels this whole valley
500 Acres of blue water
And this is it
Well close
There is a windowless concrete building
Right on the shore of the
I go inside meet Sean Fridley the station director we getting an elevator
We're going down down into the ground
Basically
Send it
Reynolds on one side and we got the lower reservoir on our other side
On the east side
So we will be well under water
We arrived at the Beating Heart of it
6 Motors the size of carousels lined up in a row in a cavernous Hall we're looking down on top of it
But those are
These are pumps
They're pumping water from that Lake I saw up at through tunnels in the mountains
Huge tunnels big enough to drive cars
Into a valley up above us where there's another damn
The water from this lower leg goes up up up and makes a new Lake way up there and the water has to go up 12 ft
Close to 1200 that is correct
Start thinking last night that's the height of the Empire State Building
Is it
You seem kind of nonchalant about it it's a massive project
To all that one
Stuart high high high above
Forest Lake mattress store
That's right
We went up there if it just sitting there ready for when people
Turn on the air-conditioning I need more power
At that point the open a valve and millions of tons of water will rush back down through those two
Back down to those Motors
Which become generator
Instead of pumps
They spend the other way generating electricity
Sending power
Out to the country sole
It seems awfully peaceful to have that much power tied up in
It's the mountain of power and the quiet giant is
Some of the terminology we've used every
That's real isn't it I mean
Cities worth of
Power
Just waiting here
That's correct
An hour later and we're back at that concrete building
And a call comes
At the East Coast
Needs more electricity
California jokes we need East Coast uses of Power are they need electricity to over culpa
Podcast startup office
Fire up the sun tanning beds
High frequency Trading
It's time to unleash the quiet Giant
The mountain
The power
OverWatch things as they happen and I'll try to talk loud
Explain a little bit slow meatballs
Water hits the auxiliary just came on
You can actually see the water but you can hear it you can actually feel it
The whole place is vibrating
It's an adrenaline rush being so close to so much raw Force
Scary actually starting to turn a little bit
The vertical shaft in front of me
4 feet in diameter starts to rotate
Slowly at first then faster faster
500 megawatts of electricity from this one machine are flowing through wires up and down the east
East Coast
Don't mean I'm just plugging in my phone to get a little busy Mountain Power
I've done the calculation
That late can store enough electricity to keep
Keep your iPhone running for
8 million year
I totally use that
I can do that
When all six of these generators are operating the bath County pump
Storage station is one of the
The 10 biggest
Power plants in
And it's been doing this for 30 years pumping water up the mountain releasing the power
But you know physically you got to lose some energy into
Still processing
How to get up to get down
Get down you lose about 20
Sad that's similar to what you losing those big batteries we were talking to
Bath county is the biggest plant like this in the world
But there are lots of other
Doesn't
In the US they were mainly built to store electricity from Nuclear Power Plant
The thing to clear plants they run day and night
And people thought we have all this electricity at night
Let's find a way to store it
So is this
The solution
Is this the thing we can build
Pastora Soler letra
Remember Scott Blake the guy at the beginning of the show showing me the graph of solar energy
He first learned about these big water batteries
15 years ago any work for the Sacramento municipal
What Utility District
And he was hooked
What caught my imagination was
This is a technology that could
Really
This idea of renewable energy forward
Scottsdale independent
Consultant and he is working on plans to build the first big new pumped storage plant in the United States
In 30 years
There are a couple of
Mission projects
I want to send to Southern California that uses an existing
Reservoir for water supply Down by San Diego
There's also a proposal to use an abandoned iron mine also in Southern California has two huge open-pit
It's one higher than the other
Another company wants to build one Oregon
Which sounds promising but I have to think that especially in California
Barely build a Condo building without people objecting it's this idea that you're going to
Be able to do
Feeling some
Dolly up
Gorgeous beautiful Sierra Nevada mountains
And you're not going to get a thousand VAR Mentalist chaining themselves to the gate
To stop it from happening it just it just doesn't
Feel like
You can do this
And that's all true but a couple of things first there is a huge economic incentive to make this happen
Electricity prices in California already are
Three times higher in the evening as they are at noon
Think of all the money you can make if you could store that power
Buy it at noon when it's cheap
Sell it in the evening when it's
Expensive
And the second thing is yes there are environmental objections to
Do these projects
But think of the environmental opportunity to imagine if in 20 years California could take
Exist just on solar power
Until the power alone so shut down the fossil fuel
To make that happen you may have to do things that are this big
And this ambitious
And then you told us that
They're actually trying to build one of these
News in China right now
Yeah China is building one it'll be the world's largest
Pumped storage plant
Two dams up in the mountains
Just like Bath County
When it's done that plant I visited
Will then be the second largest pump storage plant in the world
No shame in being the second
Highest mountain
Where was looking for more stories about how the world works
Ashley
Starbucks Ward am somewhere
Let us know about him email us at Planet Money at npr dot O r g
WE Post every show on Facebook and we're on Twitter and Instagram at Planet Money today's episode was produced by Nick fountain
Our editors brighter set
Are supervising producers Alex gold bar
Special thanks to Mario Fitness and David kleiner md Charles
Next time
Time travels with the
You know what's amazing to think about is we are in kind of an isolated Valley
On the Far Western Edge of Virginia right next to the West Virginia border
It's really Backcountry here and it's beautiful driving on this little Country Road overlooking back
Creek and this and Back Creek you know is is the the fuel I mean
Back Creek is leading us to an energy storage facility that they put here you know because
House of the creek in because of the valley and then this electrical storage facility it's Supply
Flying energy all the way to New York City all the way down to North Carolina and ultimately
Electrical grids are interconnected it's part of the national Energy System it's it's it's the
It is what it is it's a big piece of a network that spans the country
A little dog curious dog in the yard I mean
I'm really excited but you know it feels like I shouldn't I should be cool I should be, you know
Journalistically jaded but it's kind of an amazing thing