Hey its toll road
On Tuesday California's governor Jerry Brown signed a bill that made national
California will eliminate cash bail
No more money bail
.
California is technically the first state
To do this
But another state came pretty close
New Jersey all but eliminated cash bail more than a year ago
The California law takes effect next
And it will look a lot like the system New Jersey launched
More than 18 months ago
So today in the show
We're giving New Jersey the credit it's so rarely receive
We're going to replay an episode from
2017 about how New Jersey's bail overhaul came
And at the end I'll be back with an update
On how it's going
Alright Keith take it away
We're going to start Today Show by telling you the story of an innocent
Amanda Mustafa Willis
The Story begins in the summer of 2010
We stopped it was 24 years old
He's a tall guy
Wears his hair in laundry
One day he was just walking down the street Newark New Jersey
Minding his own business
Eating a baguette
All the sudden he's he's a cop
Coming the wrong way down a one-way Street
The car stops right in front of them out, cop
Yeah they ran at me like I just like they just jumped out like that
Was swarming out like they knew what they were looking for and you know
I still did a whole bunch of other guys they just ran and I just stood there they Place me under arrest
The cops found a gun at the scene
And they said the gun was Mustafa
Who's taking downtown thrown in jail
Charged with unlawful possession
And this is where your constitutional protections are supposed to kick in
The gun charge is just an accusation
Mustafa hadn't been convicted
Have anything
This is how the system is supposed to work
Mustafa is supposed to go home to his job in
Family
And start Gathering some evidence
Prove that the gun
It's not his
All he has to do is post bail
Annie's free to go
$50,000
Set by the judge and you can
Walk out of jail
He doesn't even have to come up with the whole amount right all he needs is
Is 10%
So that he can pay the bail bondsman his feet 5,000 bucks
And then he has to find somebody to
Guarantee the rest
And he's free to go
Dumb stuff I didn't have five thousand bucks for the 10% fee
And his family didn't want to be on the hook
450 thousand
So he's facing
Roodle choice
He can either
Tough it out in jail
Or
Plead guilty to a crime that he didn't come
But I told the public defender listen man I didn't do it
He said well you're probably sitting in here pending grand jury man I said well
Hey I guess I'm have to do it tonight it ain't my weapon so
Mustafa
There is no way I'm going
To plead guilty to a crime I didn't
So he just sits in jail
Hand weights
While he was locked up
Mustafa lost his job driving a deliver
He missed his cousin's funeral
All because he couldn't afford to pay
Finally after a couple months
The judge lowered mustafa's failed
$30,000
And his family built
Once he was out
Mustafa could dig up evidence to fight the gun charge
It turns out
It was somebody on the Block who shot a video that
Mustafa says
Cruz the gun wasn't
The prosecutor that got hold today
Immediately she wanted to dismiss
This is what we stopped at
I've been saying all along
The charges were
But still
She had to spend
3 months in jail
For something he didn't do
And he end up owing this bail bondsman
3000 bucks no refunds left
I was in debt from this and I had to pay
All this money back to a bail bondsman company for something that I didn't even did
And the case was still dismissed and I still have to pay
But not for nothing
Bell is supposed to help you
Who gets charged with a crime give them away to go home until their trial
But Mustafa Bale didn't help him get out of jail
Bill is what kept Him locked up
Hello and welcome to Planet Money
And I'm Keith Romer
Bam has been around for centuries
It's pretty much the law of the land in every state in this
It's supposed to protect the rights of defendants like Mustafa
You haven't been convicted of anything
And at the same time Bill is supposed to give quartz an extra guarantee
The people are actually going to show up
But what if bail is broken
Today on the show
The New Jersey bail experience
Bunch of people who normally would not agree on anything
Got together
Change the belt
Their solution
They threw it out
Support for this podcast
Send the following message come from Fidelity invest
As a Fidelity Wealth Management
You get a dedicated advisor
To help grow and protect your well
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes
And make it clear recommendation
Transfer your full Financial
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage services
Is LLC
The first thing you need to understand about
Is it is basically a workaround
For this fundamental problem in the
In a perfect world
If somebody got accused of a crime
The trial would happen instantly in a perfect world that come in the window
His world that's perfect but has crime in it hear me out
You'll get a trial the same day
If you're guilty you would go out to prison
If you're innocent you would go
But in the real world
There is a lot of time
Between that moment when somebody's arrested
And when the jury figures out what the right verse
You can't just lock up everybody in
Because
You know that annoying thing about innocent in
But if you just arrest somebody
Buddy and then immediately let him go
There's nothing necessarily to stop that guy from running off to Brazil
Bell is a sort of compromise
That's right will let you go until your trial
If you give us some money
$10,000 or $100,000 whatever it is
Show up at your trial
Get your money back
Not everybody thinks this is such a
A great sister
We talk to Roseanne Scotti
She is the sort of lawyer who looks at the criminal just
Menses
Injured
She's the state director for the drug policy Alliance
And she thinks it is hold bail compromise we've been talking about
Is pretty obviously unfair for one big reason
Which is it not everybody has the kind of money to be able to pay their bail understand is that you know
One of the things that
Most people who are in jail have in common is that they're poor
And so for these
Yeah individuals having $1,000 bail or $2,500 bail
It might as well have been $1000000 bail
It's a pretty serious flaw it's built right into the Legal Sea
Bail is way harder on poor people in Amazon
Okay so that's lawyer number one or number two is a guy named Ellie home
He's the Assistant Attorney General in New Jersey is in charge of criminal prosecution to the entire state
And he had a completely different
Problem of the Bells
4him the real trouble with how the bail system treated rich people
The right to bail was enmeshed in the New Jersey
State constitution we had a constitutional provision that said
Every criminal defendant is entitled to bail.
There's some people Ellie says who just should not be allowed to post bail at all
When you're looking at the leader of
A racketeering Enterprise a Mafia Family a large drug trafficking organization
You could have a
Kingpin somebody who's dangerous somebody you charged with murders
Now those folks can come up with money
Add the notion that those people could have could buy their way out of jail
Was really problematic
There's a reason Ellie gets so worked up about
He used to be a federal process
And the FEDS
Do not have Allah
Like the one in New Jersey that says Everybody Must Get
Ellie's new boss is New Jersey Governor Chris Christie he used to be a federal prosecutor he's used to the federal system
In 2012
He proposed a constitutional amendment in New Jersey
Create something called preventive detention
Basically
Giving judges the right to hold somebody without any bail what's up
New Jersey
They didn't go for
His plan did not make it out of the way
To Roseanne Scotti the lawyer who's trying to make the whole system more fair
Chrissy's playing just look like a classic Law and Order
Exactly what you did
Expect from a prosecutor who is now a politician
We thought that preventive detention alone
Would not
In any way solve the problem will probably make things worse because you would have preventive detention as a new
New tool to keep people
I'm in jail
Jail by the way is where you wait for trial or serve short sentences prison is for people who are serving longer sentence
For folks like Scotty the problem was
But there were too many people in
Not tfue
To try to make a case
She got her hands on the jail population data for the entire stay
In looking at the population we found that 40% of the people who were in hard shells were there
Solely
Because they lack the money for often nominal amount of money bail
Literally
Thousands of people
If you haven't been convicted of anything
Sitting in jail waiting for their trials
Just because they were poor
And that weight was not trivial
The average length of time for someone who had officially been indicted but hadn't yet gone to trial
What's 314 days
That's 10 months
Well people are sitting in there in jail for months and sometimes years
You know they're losing jobs are losing family there use it losing housing
All that time in jail is obviously bad
In and of itself
No one wants to just sit in jail
But on top of that
You can start the change
Actual legal outcome
Weather people end up being found
Guilty or innocent
Prosecutors are not
They know that people just want to go home
And they know that that give them a lot of
There is a phenomenon which I think you're not supposed to talk about publicly but I will
I called the time served and what that man is you would have defendants
Who would be held on low money Bells
Couldn't post it and they would sit there in
Jail for
346 months
And then when it came out to make your next appearance their lawyer would say
You been in 6 months
If you take this please you walk out today
And so you got that plate was an easy way to get please
How come in a pack
Very,
I mean I think it happened probably in every County
Across the state so first
You get punished
Then
At the end of your jail time
They figure out whether or not you actually did it
It's a crazy system
You can just plead guilty even if
You're not since that means you got to go home now instead of waiting however many more months it isn't
Tell your trial
This was
Such
A terribly broken unfair appalling system it was such
You know just bald
Naked Injustice and angrily corrupt
The corrupt system
In 2013 was an organization put out a report
They basically said
This is how screwed up New Jersey's bail system is
Now I don't want to sound cynical but
Usually a report is where stories like this
And well-intentioned organization.
Report
Joe Rose does a heart-rending NPR story
Everyone shakes their heads
And they say Dad is
Right
Can we just move on to the
But nothing really
It's nothing changed
But in New Jersey
The report copy I of
The Chief Justice of the New Jersey Supreme Court
He calls everyone into his ceremonial
The judges
The public defenders
The ACLU the prosecutor Deli
Ellie's in the room
And he tells them
Fix it
Lot of lawyers
So we got some people say you got a lot of wires together they can't get nothing done I think this is it
An example to the contrary we got quite a bit done
All those lawyers came up
To get rid of bail altogether
After the break
What was in that
How do you replace a system that we've been relying on 400
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solution
It support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information
When is available at aecf. Org
The most obvious proud
Problem with getting rid of bail
Is figuring out a new way of deciding who gets out before their trial and who stays locked
Ellie says the old system
Was bad
But
It was simple under our old system the first thing a judge would do
Check the bucket the charge against the defendant look at the chart and say
Okay his money bail is X
Post-it he walks out
If not he sits in jail until trial
Judges have a problem
If you take away the bail and bail chart
What are they supposed to do I don't know maybe use actual information about the real world
Oh
You mean like data
I mean
Big
Oh Big Daddy
Researchers have been trying to solve this problem
4 years
Before New Jersey start messing around with
Is there a team of researchers
I'm the Laura and John Arnold Foundation
They get the data of a million and a half
Cases from all around the country
Any run that data through a bunch of
Statistical now
And they create something called
A risk assessment
This algorithm basically predicts
How likely somebody is
To fail to show up to court
And How likely they are to commit a new
At the risk assessment
Is automatically run
And immediately spits out a result of 126
I on two different scales one being low sex being high
It's not even that,
The algorithm just look sitting
Does the defendant have a
Prior conviction for a crime of violence
Has that conviction occurred within the past X number of years
You know what has the defendant had
Failure to appear or bench warrant issued in Prior case
Interesting Lee one of the factors is how old the defendant
At the time the crime was committed
If your under the age of 23 says the algorithm
You're actually more likely to commit a new crime and somebody who is older
Not everyone thought this algorithm though it was such a good idea
The reactions to
2 to the risk assessment tool were interesting
And I think it's fair to say that it first
There was
Pretty Broad skepta
First reason for the skepticism
The whole thing just seemed a little like sci-fi
I think of the movie Minority Report with Tom Cruise where
You know if they feed the information to these cyborgs like beings who predict
Future and that makes
The precogs and that makes people uneasy reconstitute future and they're never wrong ever get any false positives
Someone intends to kill his boss or his wife but they never go through with it out of the precogs tell the difference
And it is weird right like the algorithm
Looks at all this information about you like have you committed a crime before did you skip your
Glass Court
And it says
Okay there's a
40% chance that
You are going to commit a new crime before your trial
So you have to stay locked
Stuff because of something you haven't done something you might do in the future
And I just feel compelled to point out here that
Precogs
They weren't always right
That was the whole point of the movie
It's the future hasn't happened yet
But okay when you compare this system to one that depended on bail and bail charts
This one looks pretty good
Because now people are being detained
Based on real information
About the risk of
The community
About the chances if they won't show up
There is a second concern
The people have about this risk assessment
When it comes down to buy us
People complain that the old system was biased
Against poor people and
What color
And what's to stop a new tool that's based on Big Data from being just as biased against
The same people
I asked Roseanne Scotti.
She's the lawyer who fought her entire life to make the justice system more just
She loves the tool she says the algorithm was specifically designed to avoid the bias
I think the key is what it doesn't look at you know some folks were concerned that it would look at
It would be a proxy for race
And things like that which it is in it does not look at your ZIP code or where you live or your neighborhood
Scotty says the algorithm is just as good at identifying risk
For rich people as it is for poor people
Black people as it is for white
Great idea right
Just get rid of bail
Replace it with the algorithm
No brainer
Everyone is going to love
Well
Everyone except
The Bayland
Partly because
It's going to destroy their business entirely because it's going to destroy their business
They lobbied superhard
Keep these changes
From becoming law
They warned about the crazy tsunami of crime
Wipeout
The state got rid of
The fight pass this law was in
Hence we were still counting votes the morning of
It was really not
Hold the last vote quiz called that we knew we had
Roseanne and Elli and all the other reformers
They did win.
The old system is gone
There is essentially
No more cash bail
Remember Mustafa from the beginning of the show
Under the old system
She got help
3 months in jail
On $50,000 bill
If you want to stop at
To the new algorithm
This is what you get
No prior offenses as an adult
No bench warrant
On the right side of 23 years old when he was arrested
She's A1
The lowest score on the wrist
That means under the new system
Usafa almost certainly gets to go home
Instead of having to spend all that time locked up
Maybe he doesn't lose his job
Maybe he gets to go to his cousin's funeral
That's the new reality in New Jersey
You look at who's in jail and there is this real ship
More and more
The people who are locked up in jail
Are the ones who have been convicted of
Crimes instead of just accused of
Roseanne Scotti the lawyer who's been working for decades
Make the criminal justice
System Warfare
She says this is easily one of the biggest achievements
Of her career
When we got the
First
Statistics
In February
That show that the jail population had been reduced
I'm by almost 30%
I cried
That was
An amazing moment to know that
You know you had done something
We're so many people were now going to go home to their families are
Communities
And to know that you had made a difference in
So many people would not
Face that Injustice
Was very profound more and more
In New Jersey
Punishment
After conviction not before it
Hey it's Joel again back here in 2018 with an update
It's been more than 18 months since New Jersey's bail overhaul 2
And basically
It's working
Almost no one gets cash bail in New Jersey
The first 12 months
Happened just
44 *
Out of 10
Thousands of cases
But not Everyone likes the new law
The bail bonds industry
They still hate
The challenge the New Jersey Law in court
But that case
It was thrown out
We've also heard concerns from activists
Search for Criminal Justice Reform
They say the risk assessment
Tool that thing that replaced money Bale May itself be biased on the basis of race
What we know for sure is that the states jail population
Is way down
Almost 25
Percent
And the sky
Hasn't fallen
Crime is going down to
WE Post every episode on Facebook
You have thoughts about the show please leave a comment on the post
Special thanks today to Jocelyn Simonson Shari's fan over Dean and Marie vanostran
Also Kirk Shaw and judge Glenn Grant
Today's episode was originally produced by Nick Fountain Aviva dekornfeld produce the rerun are cheap just
This is Alex goldmark
Are bail bondsman Brian Earth. I'm go Rose
And I'm Keith Romer thanks for listening