It has been said
On Wikipedia and in some newspapers
But you are one of the greatest fundraisers
Working today is it true
That's very kind of you to say I think there are probably people who raised many many more dollars than I do
But he has raised millions of dollars for The nuyorican Poets Cafe
Nuyorican is a term for a New Yorker of Puerto Rican heritage
It's a performance space
It's been going since the 70s
Daniel took over about eleven years ago and he is a genius at raising money for artists
It's pledge time here at NPR and so I went to him to ask him how he does it
I think what's most important is
To focus on the work that you love and conveying that work
In a way that you feel good about
So it sounds like if you have a tip for me that it might be
As long as you really believe in what you're doing asking for money is not that difficult you just
Tell the truth
I would also say don't ask for money
Instead
Instead explain what you do and why you're passionate about explain who it helps why it helps them
Why you're proud to be there
While I go off and think about why I'm proud to
To be here I am also going to slip you a website URL
Donate. Npr.org planet
That's donate. Npr.org
Splash Planet
Hey just a quick heads up today's episode is a rerun it originally aired in May 2014 and will
We'll have a short update at the end
Are you ready I'm ready operation Pantego
I'm going to pretend to tie my shoe but I'm actually going to deploy a penny on the sidewalk of New York your hand
42nd Street
David playing it cool
Italian shoe
Shiny shiny penny is now the middle the sidewalk we're going to walk away
Go hide behind the lamp post over there
We got we wanted to do an experiment
See how long it would take before someone picked
The penny
In the green shirt no
Hipster in the shoes now
Those are under 8 years old nothing we hung out or
Half an hour
Types of thousand people walk by
Pennies out
Nothing worth
Penny's seem to be invisible would you
You ever pick up a penny have you ever picked up a penny
I don't pay attention to them
I think you're a little bit in the way more than invisible
What are you rich guy just walked by money on the street
Finally
We resorted to stopping people pointing at their feet and think there is a penny on the street
Are you going
I'll pick it up
Yay
Take me to spend it on
Good question
She look at the penny
Handed it to her friend
He handed it back to us hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm David kestenbaum
And I'm Robert Smith today on the show
The penny
And the strange spot it occupies in our economy it is almost worth nothing
But not quite
Free stories today
On the way
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence and run your biz
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial and when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off
Off your first purchase of a website or domain
Let's start with a very basic
Can you still buy anything
4 penny
Jacob Goldstein and I headed out on the streets of Manhattan with a pocket full of pennies
Animation
We have to think
What's really cheap
Maybe a sheet of paper there's a copy store right across the street from our off
How much would one piece of plain white paper
We never sell a piece of paper if somebody needs a please explain why you just give it to them
Alright maybe the guy with the fruit stand on the corner
What if we wanted to buy one share
Novant City
Phone
The one phone
Okay it is tough
Define something for a pet
Honey it's tough to get anyone to think in terms of pennies
Especially in Midtown Manhattan
Not itchy
Key place
But there's one upside of being in Manhattan
That's a Thursdays little weird
Super specialized stores
Excel
Tiny
Cheap thing
A few blocks from our office in the Fashion District
There's a store that just sells but
So what is the cheapest
Button in the sky
50 Cent
No
Art small
Same block as a button store
Is trim
The carnival this is a store that sells
Tidy
Chinese sequin
It's like you might
So on a dress for Mardi Gras
We walked in and we asked Krishna Verna what is the cheapest thing we can get
Hollywood get a sequin for like a penny
Single sequin
I mean something like let's say a secret like this
Dog the bag is $5 or whatever you doing didn't know a single sequence would be like a penny
But if somebody came in with a penny and said open that up
Oh you want to do it now you just told me as a pony
Why not it's not worth my time
I mean how many people would have to come in for a penny and a penny and a penny to make my make you pay my rent
A penny is not worth her time
And I should say here it's not like she's bad dizzy
Mardi Gras already happened we were the only people in the store
Everywhere we went
Everyone talked about the hassle of this kind of friends
The button guy said
The space that a button
Takes up in store cost more than
A lady at the bead store and buy the beads for necklaces
She said the paper for the receipt that you would have to give me would cost her more than a penny
Not sure if that's actually true but
There aren't super cheap things in the world
A piece of paper with tiny plastic bead
People just didn't want to sell them to us
Like the lady at 38th Street Hardware
This right here look at those things come on what is this
Electrical nut
That's all
It's free no you can make money for free
So why not just sell it for whatever a penny two cents worth
Selling
I rather keep my customer just give it to them make them happy
The value of the good will she get
From giving away a little electrical nut
Is worth more than the few sense that you have to sell
Bottom line
No one would tell us anything for
But we came as close as you could come
I would be described as what is it 3/16 washer which is you know for people who don't know Hardware a little round thing with a woman
Washer with a hole
Would you put with a screw to help hold it in place
This is
Brothers hardware and that's Jim Bankston
One of the brothers
Holding a tiny little washer
How much does it
Who said
$0.02 for this thing
By far the cheapest thing we found in Manhattan
Do we know who makes this
Price of Chinese guy
My name
Om team
Jim
Beijing China
What is the name of your company
Nimble
Because I don't
Fasteners Company Limited
Ningbo exact Fasteners Company Limited of Ningbo China actually just outside Ningbo China
They specialize in making washers just like this one
We called them because we wanted to know
How is it possible to sell this thing for $0.02
So I'm interested
In washers because they are very inexpensive
And I miss you mean cheap cheap eye treatment
Tavares
Just think of all that has to happen
To get this washer to this hardware store in Manhattan
Yep to dig the metal out of the ground
Turn it into Steel
Yuan to wash
Packages
Get it onto a ship
Send it across the world
And then the United States
There's some guy who has to unload the washers put it on a truck get it to the store unpack it
Put it on the Shelf
What are those little bit so that I can pick it up
And buy it for two set
Who says who sings
How is all the spots
Well
The labor of course
Is cheap dimple death
The workers at exact Fasteners make about $700 a month
And of course no one has a patent on washer so you have
Lots and lots of companies competing to sell the exact same thing as cheaply as pause
In the end really
Watch was just this little
Piece of metal is a commodity
It's Priceless we just goes up and down with the price of Rost
And we left at probably the biggest reason that washers are so
Cheap
Volume
Ningbo exact Fastener Company Limited sells washers by the
And I don't mean that as a metaphor
The minimum order is one
So if that's the minimum order how many washers is it
How many washers are there in one
I asked him to do the math
Yes
If you buy a ton of washers
One penny will get you
Q7
Manufacturer transportation to America storage profit for the Importer profit for the brothers who owned the hardware store
And what you end up with
Might just
Be the smallest transaction that you can make
In New York City
1 washer
2 pennies
He did go pay Robert
I actually know someone who will take those panties off
We are going to hand over the show to Zoey Chase
She's just back from hip
And that is where I met a Penny Jones
This dude has never walk past a penny and not picked it up
In fact he takes his people money his dollar bills
Go to the bank and ask for peace
I have $50 that I don't need for anything out right now so I'm going to go in here to the PNC Bank
Ask for two boxes of pennies
Most people rate that usually change in coins for dollars
Dvorak
He does the opposite
20 years old bushy red beard
The reason Steve collects the pennies is
Not to spend them not to buy one washer at a time or sequence
He wants the pennies because of the copper inside the
You should think of Steve as a very small Speculator on the price of
Copper
We looking for is
Killer vintage of
The 2013 ones
Mostly the same
With a copper plating
And they're they're worth $0.01 exactly
That is not a good investment but any penny made before 1982
Those are the ones he wants
1982 and prior
They're 95% copper and they're worth about $0.02
Maybe a little more depending on the price of copper so
I like to pull those out and double my money very slowly
Prospecting for copper one old penny at a time there are thousands of people that are doing this
What are you doing this is
Steve Womack is what's known as a queen rule Hunter
The coin roll Hunters
Do you like to go online and show off
Well guys
I did it again
Had to go and pick up another box $25 worth of penny rolls
There are dozens
These are all pre-1982 copper pennies
Some people have these
Special machines that sort out the
Pre-1982 from the post-1982 second turn off
Funeral papa show
For some people this is almost a full-time job like I talk to this one guy he had something like
$5,000
In pennies
Cuz she was hitting Banks 15 times a week
Divas more of a small-time operator
Get this coin
He brings them home to his fiance and
This is this is kind of a thing that they do at night
Together in the living room next to each other
And go through it
Got going like I'll give her a box
And I'll take my own box
U2
You actually get lucky really quick
Almost 2/3 of the penny Steve is pulling out our from 1982 or before
Difference in sound
And these are the zinc pennies that they make now in it
Sounds completely different
It sounds like fake money
Once again
Copper
Zinc
Divas collected
$475 in old pennies he figures the copper is worth double the face value so that's
$1,000
Stacked in boxes in the back of his closet
Now there is this problem with this investment strategy
Which is right now it is illegal
To melt these pennies down
The copper in the pennies is
Duck bear
Unless
And this is what these guys are hoping for
The US government kills off the penny
This is not unreasonable
Canada got rid of its Penny and
Canada's now making money
The Collector own old pennies melt them down and add them to the Canadian treasure
Politicians and Economist have talked about doing that here because
It cost more than a penny
2 mint
A penny
It has
For some years now
So we're losing millions of dollars every year making these things
Coin roll Hunters
The dream about that day that the penny dies in the US
If you turn on the computer right now you saw that they'd abolish the penny
What would you do
I would probably go by as many boxes as I could
Afford
Deep says
He would not
Cash them in right away
Actually for him
That day the day they kill the penny
That is the day that he could collect
But
Also a sad day for
When when the pennies are abolished then that's the end of one of your hobbies right there
Cuz Hey I can only look through so many more and
It's fun to do
You would miss them
Yeah yeah I would
In the meantime thousands of P
People are out there hoarding copper pennies
This one guy out in Portland you rent out some space in an armored
Car Warehouse
So he's a regular supply of coins coming in he sorts them with industrial-sized sorting machines and
Cells off the copper ones online
That that guys hold job
That's how many
People are out there betting against the penny
Old Port penny
Abandon on the street
Orphan in that little bowl by the cash register
Stored in the back of some guy's Closet in Pittsburgh
The little penny is just a waiting
Sad sad and
Our last story that was about one place that still dreams of the penny
Play some backward people think
Pennies could change
Everything
The internet
On the internet right now
They're basically two ways people get paid for Kant
The first is ads
Put advertisements on their site
The second subscription fees you want to read New York Times article or a bunch of them $15 a month
But there was always a third possibility
A path so far not taken
The path
Of the penny
The virtual pet
What if you could as you travel around on
Passe
$0.01
For the stuff you like
You watch a cat video you read a Blog without a recipe
What if each time you did that
There is an easy way
Peter pay that person a tiny amount of my
In 1997 some programmers at digital Equipment Corporation
Actually worked on this idea
Didn't have a secret code name this project it was always called Melissa
Am i l l i
Cmet
This is Russ Jones who is part of the team
What was the smallest amount you imagine someone
Pain
We were
Design the system so that you could do transaction
It's down to a penny
Turns out it is a pain to send pennies around the internet
There are always transaction costs
Between a credit card companies and processors you could end up spending
$0.30 to send one
Penny
The militant solution was to basically wait until the end of the day of the month or whatever
Add up all the small change
People were sending
And pay it to each recipient in a lump
Excited try it out
They signed up businesses willing to sell stuff
Our spare change virtual guitar
For $0.25 you could
Play it online
The Oxford English Dictionary also participated for one
Penny Uke
A very
Detailed definition of the word basically worked
But there was this down
Kind of changed the nature of surfing the web
People are used to getting stuff for free
They did not like
Even small amounts
One of the things we found out was the people
You know people would get
As aggravated
When something went wrong
With a $0.05 purchase is when something went wrong
In the real world with a $50 purchase
That wasn't the word I meant to
Look up in the air
Yeah yeah so it's like
You know I accidentally keyed in the wrong word
And I just lost my penny
I want my money back
But it's 17 years later now
Maybe it's a better time
Internet seems to be changing people are buying stuff for small amount
English song for 99 cents
A game for two box
Hawaii not pennies
A big Venture Capital firm in Silicon Valley is into this idea
People try to make it work again oh I think it's been changed it could be it would probably the
The biggest change in society occurrence of the internet
This is Lina solsun co-founder and CEO of an online payment system called
Flattered
Like flattered but
Without the
And flutter gets around that problem that millison
I'm turning web surfing into a kind of
Unpleasant shopping
How to make paint voluntary like a tip
Basically you load up your flatter account with however much
Money you want to give away in a month
10 bucks
It's whatever
Then if you see an article or a cat video you like
You click on a little flattered but
At the end of the month everyone you flattered splits the money you set aside
Actually at the system right now can can do fractions of cents
Fractions of a penny
To make the case that a penny is worth
It's worth something if there are a lot of people
The sweetest thing
Rebecca small bleeding stool
Play too many small streams forms a large river
Athen how large that River was so far
We have not managed to to break into
And mass market yet
We're not managed to do the revolution we want yet
What's the largest
Check that you've got to anybody like other people are getting thousands of dollars a month from this
Tens of thousands
No
We will have to talk customer who makes a statement from this I think he gets like
$5,000 or something he's quite public with his number
Amalia
Penny can actually be a lot in me online work
If you try to earn money by putting ads on your website
How much do you get paid for visitor
Well if one person sees that ad
You might get one one-hundredth of one penny
So a whole Penny one cent
From a certain perspective
It is worth picking them up from the sidewalk
Coming up after the break the most recent effort to get rid of the penny
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
When is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimum
That can be open from anywhere
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Noel King here with a brief update last year Senator John McCain the late Senator John McCain introduced
Used to Bill
I actually have a copy of it right here
So this is the currency optimization Innovation and National savings Act of 2017
That name like all great Bill names makes up an acronym called the coins Act
And I'm going to read a short excerpt from it
Here we go
The Secretary of the Treasury shall cease production of any new $0.01 coins for the 10-year.
Beginning on the date of enactment of this act
New new pennies for 10 years
Then maybe in a decade if the sky has not fallen from lack of new pennies
Maybe Congress decides to extend the Hiatus and minting new pen
That was John McCain's bill
He introduced it and then
Nothing happen
New Committee hearing
No vote
Nothing
Tell as far as we can tell pennies are not going anywhere anytime
Cliche
Forged by Jacob Goldstein Zoe Chace David kestenbaum and Robert Smith
Damiano marchetti produce the original
China Kitchen in Darien was produced the rerun by Earth's that is our editor Alex goldmark is our supervising producer
We are on Facebook Twitter and Instagram at Planet Money
And one more time if you like the show if the show helps you understand the world in a new way
You can support the work we do here by chipping in at
Donate. Npr.org
Splash Planet Money
I'm Noel King
Thanks for listening