Support for NPR and the following message come from service now making the world of work
Work better for me
They're cloud-based
Platform and solutions deliver digital workflow
Spell create great experiences and unlock productivity for your whole company
More at servicenow.com
Here is kind of money we work in and open
If I turn my chair around I can see the entire team
And even if I don't turn my chair around
I can hear it
So that the marginal cost is so different
I said between
David kestenbaum and Jacob Goldstein and they are bickering
All day long it's like there a married couple who
You're not really sure if they're going to make it
No I know when I first started a Planet Money on my first day they got into a fight about
Keynesian economics
An actual fight
And I remember sitting there thinking
Number one I need to
To read up on Candida
Economics right now
And number two
I'm never going to be able to get any work done in this off
It's too loud I can't even hear my own thoughts I can just hear Jacob
Robert has some really loud
Thoughts to
It was literally that's white exist
And then there is Noel Kings laugh
Love that laugh
I know it's a pretty girl
But it is hard to get work done with all of this noise app
This is the world that most of us are working in
70% of us work in some kind of open Office setup
I will be honest right here
Sometimes
I just
Dream of having
Adore
With walls
The go all the way around
Hello and welcome
Play the money I'm Nick Townsend and I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
They on the show we meet the man who stole my door
Who gave us the
Hell
That is the open on
Oh come on it's pretty nice you have a nice office
Also we have the inside story of one of the first open offices
And all the drama that ensued
Just a heads up
What episode is a rerun it originally ran in 2016
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is
Good days start with great jeans
How did they make them so great Madewell starts with
Premium denim
Then offers men's and women's styles for seriously every
Also you can recycle any brand of jeans in a Madewell store
And they'll give you $20 off a new pair
They work with the blue jeans go green program
Turn old jeans
Is the housing insulation for communities in need
Terms apply
Ready to find your perfect fit
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
So before we get into the story of the OpenOffice
I'll introduce you to one of the people who ended up working there
His name is Paul Spencer and he works an adverb
Juvenis campaigns that are really proud of
The one I most famous for and I'm still coasting on decades later
Is for the New York Lotto
Hey you never know
That was that was
No way
Wow
You probably sold a lottery
I know
Back in 1994 Paul was just starting out in his career
He was freelancing
And he got a call from chayet day
It was like the hottest
Ad Agency in New York
Shiet was
The prestigious place you know
You were really creative
If you were there and you wanted to be able to say I was a shy
Yeah
No big deal
Yeah you know no big deal they just
Baby Energizer
Funny famous animated
Super Bowl ads
No big deal just like the most creative people you can put in a room in New York advertising at the time that was
And at the time Paul got the call
All New York was buzzing about china's new office
As The Story Goes
The CEO of Sade
Jay Shetty
Had a vision
On the ski slopes
Italia right as one does as one does
Of a totally new works
So we hired the super famous
The Builder poem
His name
Gaetano Pesce
It's outpatient battalion
From Venice
I am 76
When they work on day
Female creativity
This is the man who stole my joy
Depressed
For what turned out to be such a big moment in office history
The instructions that Josh I gave Gaetano
They were pretty vague
What did he say when he came to you without people
An office without paper
Super sounds kind of Monday
But if you think about it
This was prefer
I mean most of the things
We think of as being associated with an office
Are essentially paper management
Staplers hole punches file folders
File cabinets
Even desks
Pretty much just there to hold paper
But this was 1990
Didn't really need
People that much anymore
Are laptops
Service email
The office
It was kind of just a hold over
From a more primitive time
And you guys they were trying to reinvent off
Start anew
She was given a blank
The entire floor of a skyscraper in lower Manhattan
29000 square feet
Sophie went down to check it out
Yes I remember was in the evening
This place was wrong
Empty
With bulbs attached to the ceiling
What did you think when you thought
Because you don't need
The office
You don't
Need the author
Gaetano Pesce started sketching out designs for this new office
The likes of which the world has never seen
It looks like a giant living room
Jose open space
VT Lottery
Kona results
Sulfur
Comfortable chair
Weed coffee shop
Because I think people when they meet so they like to have a drink they like to eat
This was Radical
At the time remember it's 1994
The typical workplace was all about
Cubicles everything was uniform everything was
Efficient they were neutral colors
I got tunnel was going to build
A big living
With a copy shop
There was also a ping pong table a giant steer
Nowhere
And PS Teresa stones
The floor
Poured plastic resin
And not beige or white or
Any normal color
It was the color of a
Tangerine
With all these red yellow and
Who designs
Like arrows
Oops
And words
Chord by Gaetano himself
Who had to walk around with special spiky shoes while it was dry
The way he tells it
His inspiration was
Pretty much whatever he was thinking about that day
I remember Nocona one day
When I was doing the floor
I8
I was thinking Benny's
Hey put the arrow
On the floor
Hadley and they right
Vanish because that for
Did the election of Venice
You know East
The desks in his office
Cuz we're all on Wheels and the chairs were plastic
With coil springs
4likes
Critics
Crazy over this new off
Here's a quote from the New York Times
Men's magazine it said
The workers seem to be traveling through some new improved dimension
These young Gap guard HotShots go
Breathing by
The paste
Bestride
The circle
Gesticulating with one hand clutching
Cellular phone
In the other
Or they briefly touchdown attic
Computer console one of a cluster of free-floating Workstation
They can be wheeled around the floor
To take advantage
Of the spectacular Skyline View
Thumbs up
Really long-winded for thumbs up
So many people wanted to see the office showed they started arranging tours
This is the office that Paul Spencer walked into on his
First day
That was the guy you heard from the beginning with just taking this
Exciting new job
His dream job
And when you showed up he was almost as excited to see the office
As he was to start working
The elevator took him up
To the 38th floor
And he walked into the office
You know I just remember a lot of orange and
Taupe colors in
There was a design like
Drawings and paintings built into the
Floor
It was like there were
Kind of rubbery code over at
And it felt good I remember thinking wow this is great this is so beautiful
Carrie was at one of the most
Creative places to work in advertising and in the most creative office space he ever seen
This was not a bland cubicle Farm
This was inspiring
Power walks up the reception
They had this
Cool sister
Where you would check out a laptop and a cell phone for the day
And the laptops and cell phones were kept in these lockers
It looks pretty cool they looked like they were out of a movie
You know like a police drama where there like unlocking
Metal cages in giving you your
38 revolver whatever it was like while I'm
Going into creative battle
Pump it up with this guy he was going to partner with
Is art director named Mike
And he said hey Mike it's so nice to meet you this place is amazing
Just kind of like shrugs and rolls his eyes
And you were like
I wonder why I mean
So beautiful
Paul starts his first day at work
And a few hours later he and Mike the art director are sitting in Gaetano Pesce
Caffe batting around ideas for an ad for
Telephone company
Imposters to have this
Weird feeling
It was kind of like
Late in the day looking across the table in the
The kitchen at Mike
Oh there's a problem
This place is kind of
Scorching my brain
It's like Ike
Focus
Everything was
Too bright too loud
To open
And Paul was not the only one having a bad reaction
Into the office
Shalom Auslander was a creative director at shayetet
Sitting inside of a migraine
I guess you to climb inside a migraine headache
That's what that felt like
It wasn't just the bright colors and the plastic
For although he did say that the floor had this weird smell the game
Headaches
Shalom says the real problem was the open
Extreme open
That's right cuz once you got your laptop and your cell phone
You had no idea where to go
For me it was a very unmoored on the feeling
So you spend a lot of time I walked away
I walked a lot
Cuz I was constantly walking
Around and around
You know had to deceive John yet he is
In that room or isn't that room or detention until he just left to that room
I'm passing other people who were walking around
The other direction
And all the stuff
Personal stuffs
Set the old style of office hat
Contain
It all came spilling out in this big
Openstack
The saddest element of it is that you see somebody with a
Phone
Or human being
Internist awful plastic nurse
With a phone press to their ear and clearly something was going on are getting divorced
Somebody
Somebody was die something human was happening on the other end of that phone
And they're just walking around and then other saying is hang on
Help me find a planet
Hey Jim Hayden Hayden
And just like desperately and going into some dark corner somewhere and
Iran
Trying to have
Interaction
Which was an actual human being
Shalom says he just
Couldn't get any work
Did you like coping mechanisms
Yeah it's called my house
That would go to my house which did not have plastic floors
Or hives or not
Work trannies or whatever they called it
I would just go home and sit my ordinary kitchen table and
Have an ordinary martini and
Figure out
Commercial for whatever and
And go back the next day and act like I've been there
Paul Spencer told me he started to
Hate the open Office
And he felt really bad about
He felt like maybe
He wasn't cool enough or maybe somehow he was
Failing
It's like this whole thing was a big big
To figure out
What would happen if
Free people from cubicles from their cages
What potential can be realized when you let people run free
It turns out people realized
They just
Really wanted
Walls
Paul says he would walk into the office
Is looking for his colleagues
Any find them in the few places with doors
With walls
The conference room
Clearly there was like tribal happenings going on there where people had like
Camped out in
Like oil conference rooms that were supposed to be just
Temporary he would come in and he taking them over
They like
Cobra Corner in them
We're in here
And it was like all about kind of getting in and
Getting your corner early
You felt like you were part of somebody's
Idea of how people work
Supposed to be
But we're not really that way
The architect of this space Gaetano Pesce would drop by to
To visit his
Creation
And he told me yes
He did hear this complaint
That the OpenOffice thing was just
Not working
Looking for some people
Does that make you feel bad
New things
Bother
At the beginning
When you make something you
First of the actually is I don't like
I mean do you think the OpenOffice
Went too far
No no there is never too far
I mean what would you say to somebody who said I worked in this office and
Like it was beautiful but I couldn't get any work done
Evita understand
The possibility
The creativity
Gaetano said he's heard from a lot of people
People who love this
And also
For what it's worth
These did turn out to be some of the most creative years
Forsyth Tech
They came up with a famous
Apple think different campaign
With the Taco Bell Chihuahua yo quiero Taco Bell that one and other companies look at Cheyenne days off
Space and they said
I want
The OpenOffice seemed exciting it was cool
People could communicate and collaborate really easily
And Adam plus it was cheaper you can fit more people into a smaller space
Save on rent
Innuendo
Wish I had a OpenOffice experiment
Was short-lived
It was doing so well it got bought out by another cop
A much bigger company
That moved them out of this office and into a much more traditional
Just a few years after they moved into this crazy new open Office
They moved out
Gaetano's creation was dismantled
Architecture critics started calling it a failure
A good idea taking too far
But the office didn't die in tirely
In fact Gaetano Pesce started seeing pieces of it all over the
He's not one of the Rolling desks
In Milan
A plastic chair in Paris
A piece of a wall panel in Aspen
The elf evoxac
Loaded around the world
It really was an open Office
Shalom Auslander and Paul Spencer both eventually left
But he said everywhere they went
Is office follow.
I followed all of us
If you look at pictures of the old child day and you look at pictures
Of Google or Facebook or the NPR headquarters in DC
They look the same the OpenOffice in some form
Is everywhere
Is interstate
When I die I am going to hell and it is
They've definitely gone
Over the open space
So Nick I have been working in this office with you guys for almost 2 years
And even though I had my doubts in the beginning have to say there are some things that I really like about it
I feel like my ideas get a lot better X where we
Batting around all the time
And I feel like I laugh a lot more than I did when I was working in a room by myself think I'm actually happier
Yeah I feel like
This is the most collaborative and funny place I've ever
And I think
For all of us
There's a larger just
Human Experience
Which is that as human beings
We crave human interaction
We like to be around other humans
Yes that's true
All of those things are true
And
Sometimes I just want you guys to tell you what I had a piece of chicken
So I went to hell and hearty
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with
Straight jeans
How did they make them so great
Madewell starts with premium.
Then offers men's and women's styles for seriously everyone
Also you can recycle any brand of jeans in a Madewell store
And they'll give you $20 off a new pair
They work with the blue jeans go green program
Have to turn old jeans
Housing insulation for communities in need
Terms apply
Ready to find your perfect fit stop by a Madewell store or go to Madewell.
Alright so we've left the NPR office why have you taken me here this is the one quiet place
On the floor of our whole building it is a dead-end hallway right next to a fire exit and you always see people in this hallway
Making private call
Or I guess doing the credits
If you have any horror stories from your OpenOffice experiences please send us a
Email you can send it to Planet Money at npr.org Planet Money I'm at Nick fountain
And I'm at s Bannock Smith special thanks to Sally Helm who produced today's podcast big Sally
Sally and we would also a force like to thank our wonderful colleagues they might be loud but we love them very much we would
Change the route we could maybe just the volume
Listening
All right we have a little challenge for you dear listener
Let's see if you can deal with what we deal with everyday the banter that happened
Can you do this challenge for the next 30 seconds name all the state capitals
You can
And
Hey you don't set time to take to go to Milan
Stop the ship
As they're sticking to the bottom of the ocean with all the gold
I have a
Okay time
How many to get neck