Quick warning
This episode contains one curse word
So the other day I go to a bar O'Keefe's it's a standard Irish bar in Brooklyn with someone who I thought was a friend
Dance
And we got into an arc
Yeah that's true
I am telling you it is a real thing that happens
Just about every time
You're telling me
When you drink cheap vodka you have an allergic reaction when you drink expensive vodka are fine
I am allergic to cheap vodka that is my tank when I drink cheap vodka my my face turns red
He gets a little hard to breathe
Like just a little it's not like it's going to kill me I don't buy it
You doubted my own personal plan
About my own personal hell
No offense Alex but I am just really skeptical okay I cover food for a living and I can tell you that vodkas are
Pretty much all the same
In fact they have to be
And I don't think otherwise is falling for one of the great sales jobs in modernist
Hello welcome to Planet Money I'm Dan pashman host of the sporkful food
Broadcast and I'm Alex goldmark
Rihanna show we're going to find out
It was right
We will put fancy vodka to the
We're going to go and find out how vodka is actually made
Look at the story of the marketing genius who created the whole concept of super premium vodka we will make our own vodka
Send it to a lab see how it measures up Bunsen burners
Lab coats
Liquor scientist and
Alex's face can I get one more
Have your cheapest vodka yeah
Okay sure but you didn't like it when it's going great
Okay I'm going to bring you one more stupid
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their own website
Using customizable layouts
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobile attic
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online presence
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Here it is Alex as an authentic paper sound effect
I'm about to read a lot
Break it off
This is title 27
Section 5 .22
All the Alcohol Tobacco and Firearms
Code this is the code Alex that
Aspiring vodka magnates read to their children at bedtime
It says that vodka must be distilled
Or treated until it is
Is quote without
Distinctive character
Aroma
Taste
Or color
The Taste but has no distinctive
Taste
If you're making bourbon you're going crazy trying to create a unique flavors your product will stand out
Right you're going to Asian certain barrels for a certain amount of time or whatever smokey
APD all those things
Making vodka is very little you're allowed to do
To make it taste
Different
By law you basically have to make an industrial-grade
Pure alcohol
First like the stuff you put in edhesive Zara fragrances
Detergents
And all you do is add water
And you got Vodka
That doesn't sound right
To figure out if there's a difference between fancy
Cheap vodka
Let's just start off by finding someone to show us how vodka
Is may make sense
Someone can show us how it all works standing right in front of their vodka making
Hey how are ya
This is ronak Parikh you are the guys who run industry City distillery in Brooklyn
He takes us down a long cluttered hallway pasta
The bar and then
Unlocks
Big metal door
You're answering there still room now
There's like clear jugs all around there's this
One machine
Looks kind of like where you go to
Flip a circuit breaker to turn the power back on
Tubes coming out of it
Another one looks like an angry washing machine
I'm home
Can a cramp
Smaller than a dorm room
Yeah I mean there's like
Enough room for maybe two or three people to be working
Basically yeah which is about our team
Explain how to make vodka in a nutshell
First stop
That's very small
It's really straightforward science
You can buy in sugar
And yeast
Do you eat the sugar
Oops out alcohol
But now that alcohol is sitting in a vat
Put the sugar in it
Easton junk
You got to separate it
So you heat the mixture just to the point of the alcohol turns to steam and Rises up
You do that a few times and you end up with basically pure alcohol
And every vodka Alex no matter how cheap
Has to be distilled to that point
These machines here the main purpose of them
Is to remove flavor
Incent
And any other
Characteristic except for
Alcohol exactly
Chemical constituents about Esther's they will create flavors
But in the case of vodka they will not be related to its bra material
By definition of the queso if you ever see
Packaging of State
This vodka is made
With Northwest Pacific grains kissed by the Colorado Rapids
DePaul marketing b*******
When it comes to vodka
Your raw material can I influence Final Four
The raw material doesn't matter to the final flavor
There is no flavor
But
How you
Treat that raw material
Does effect
What's in
That's because there are three stages of
Three categories heads hearts and Tails
Heads hearts
Okay Raonic explain that when you start to heat the alcohol to distill
The first part of the steam that comes out before anything else
That part is called the hens
That part is not supposed to be for drinking
It's the stuff I can contain methanol the stuff that moonshine is our get in trouble with going blind even being fatally fatally hurt by
You don't want to drink your head you want to remove that and then the next part that's the good stuff the hearts so
List of Roanoke wants to keep
That is the vapor in the middle
And then
Okay that's the stuff that's potable but stuff that's been in our industry we known to I'll give you hangovers
In case of nasty smells maromas
It's a Run xidan if you want to make a super cheap vodka
You would probably just leave in extra tails
Because you get more vodka
Her run of the steel or whatever until Cost Less
And the best part
Because if you're a stickler for quality
They would take just
The hearts
So there is a
Yeah maybe
Seems like a good guy
But remember
He's also selling vodka for 40 bucks a bottle
So I don't think he's going to say that his the same as the $10 stuff
In the plastic bottle on the bottom shelf
Other interests
He was one of the only distillers who we called out who said sure come on down take a look around
And he says that's because it a lot of labels
They don't distill their own alcohol
They buy it in bulk
From someone else
I'm at soup so weird because it went every one of these vodkas we hear this
Fairy tale about how the
Craft Copper Still blah blah blah
But I set out to find out how bulk-buying works and it's true this is one company it's huge
Everyone in the liquor industry knows
Ultra
They said they have the largest selection of bulk alcohol in the world
They sell basically pure alcohol like
Vodka concentrates a base
Lots of companies buy it and use it to make their own vodka brands
Some of the companies take the basin
Still at further they tweak it to put their own spin on
But ultrapure told me that the more price driven companies
They just take the base
Add Water
Business
Best selling vodka
So I called him up and I said hey
Can I get some of that vodka concentrate
And they said yeah no problem samples are in the mail
While we were waiting for our samples to arrive
We went to find out how this whole
Trend of
Fancy vodka.
Started because when you go to the liquor store you see
Ketel One and Belvedere and Ciroc all these
Smoky bottles and fancy design and high prices
Clearly vodka drinkers
I think that there's a day
Difference but there is one difference
The fonts
I'm a bottle
Very different Alex and this whole idea super premium vodkas it was all invented by one guy
He is a cop
Classic
American businessman
And in almost a cliche
Good way than in bad way it's like
Came from nothing
Poor
He went to Brown but he only went to Brown for one year because he couldn't afford it
This is Matthew Lackey
I'm a drink writer and the author of you suck at drinking
So how many drinks do you have
A day on average
Well I'm trying to come back
When I was at the height of my drink writing powers
Oh gosh
5 to 8
We are such amateurs
Anyway
Sidney Frank drops out of college ends up marrying a woman from a wealthy family and her family business is
Liquor
So he kind of slides in the liquor business side
In love
Liquor necessarily just looking for Niche products
And he stumbles on this
Side bar refuses old German
Folks
Drinking Jagermeister
Which is the time this is an 80s
With selling like 500 cases
Does a year
Nothing
Nothing at all
So Sydney Frank buys the rights to import Jagermeister
That's sort of herbal taste kind of like
Black licorice cost
Which probably explains the low sales
And he buys it precisely because it isn't well-known and it doesn't do much beyond the old German man Market
For a while
But then he hears about students at Louisiana State University actually liking Jaeger my
There's an article in the local paper that says all the kids know this is what you drink
When you want to get
One of them described as liquid volume
And that was what kicked off you would like
Kollege Kidd
And with Jagermeister he essentially invents all of the garbage
We may know about liquor companies and their marketing practice
This is now he's basically invented
He sponsored party
He Butters up bar
Even set up a team of scantily clad women to give away free shots
Skip Gathering
The Yeager at
That was a Sydney Frank special right there so
The other kind of guerrilla marketing
You know he doesn't play by any of the normal rules so
Just to put a button on Alex
Case it wasn't clear
Sidney Frank took a drink popular with old German men
And turned it into the hottest drink for the party set on College camp
And if you did that
He set his sights higher
Aardvark
And at the time the fanciest vodka around
Was apps
Had a great marketing
Campaign but by today's standards
Wasn't really an expensive bottle
Vodka
And that's what Sidney Frank knows is his
Competition
But the thing he focuses on
It's not the taste of absolute
Of course it is the price
The century out of thin air cuz I want to make a vodka
So absent Church in 15 or church 30
You didn't even have a product
At this point
But he already knows he's going to charge double
In order to do that he needs a product
Screams luxury
Chevy the best everything everything that is the best comes from France
Sippy cup
France
Any looks around for the Steelers as can you make vodka
Find somebody says yes of course I can
Make vodka bars with his French vodka making it seem special
He made a big deal that it was made a French weed
All kinds of things
Designed to make Grey Goose seem different from other vodka
He would give them the bottle in the wooden box
Drawings
Poseidon nicely package
Large
Clear bottle with the frost
Glass
Can you put it up on the back bar would catch whatever light
Who's there
Hello
It's not that he didn't care about taste
At all
It's just that you didn't start there
He did
Submit it to the bti which
Is the beverage
Tasting Institute
And it was awarded the best tasting vodka in the world and whatever 90 early 90s thing
And use that in his marketing
A lot
We reached out to Grey Goose for comment on this story
And didn't get back to us in time to include
Sydney Frank's whole plan worked
Back is now the most popular liquor in America and he died a very
He sold
Grey Goose
2 Bacardi
Less than 10 years after he started it for more than two
And before you even start honest and I'm tempted to start now that I see how this whole
Story argues that that it's just marketing that all vodkas are the same that my allergy
Too cheap vodkas that I genuinely feel
Is all just in my
But I think
I scientifically as we can that's right and I got good news Alex cuz guess we're just arrived in the mail
I guess if I could concentrate that in order from ultrapure and I picked at one particular I think you can be excited about
Okay
Ultrapure sells a vodka concentrate made in France
With French wheat
4 times distilled
Sounds pretty good I didn't say sounds like
Could be the best
The best that comes from France exactly Alex that's right
Outlook ultra-pure told us they don't sell to Greg
Something similar there aren't that many vodka distilleries
In France
We're not talking about wineries
Okay
And 4 time to still sounds good to me maybe even
Premium
I would go so far as to call it
Super premium Alex another we're going to do right now we can make our own Super premium vodka
I know this looks like
I get travel shampoo bottle size bottle
I would very clear liquid in it
And the wrapping bubble wrap and tape that's what we're taking off now
The label some kind of homemade go down
Yes they look like they were printed on somebody's incheon
Yeah but not even with the like the right alignment their cut off year
We've got this very handy fancy highly scientific graduated cylinder
That Planet Money owns
Going back to our story on class action lawsuit
Here comes the part of this entire store that I have most been dreading
What
Math
Grey Goose and most vodkas are 80 proof which means 40% alcohol
These battles are not some even easy to work with number there 192 proof
So we got to bring those down
Proof by adding water
It's 192 proof so if we have to make too hard because
Not 100% anything that we heard your math major
Okay and what are you cutting it with again water
Water
Petrified water we got from the drugstore
This isn't how you make vodka
So we bottled are homemade French wheat vodka
Sterilize bottle and send it to a lab
Could you want to see what measures up
Thing is tested against
Something right Alex
Sure Naturally
So we also sent
Some Grey Goose
In an unmarked bottle
And we decided to send them some of the cheap stuff the Alex special bottom shelf
Plastic bottle
Reset the whole thing to San Diego
Go to a place called
This is a whole Lab where they test different types of alcohol which I think Alex is something you and I
Play sometime ourselves
Especially this week for this episode
After the break
The results
This message comes from NPR sponsor squares
Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their own website
Using customizable Leo
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobiledit
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online presence
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
To get our results be called up Neva Parker she's a vice president are white labs
Did I just curious do they look professional
Did we look like a good vodka start up to you when you took them out
Absolutely
That's gratifying vodka samples through what they call a comprehensive Spirits test it measured
Chemicals in the alcohol the people might be able to taste
Also test for chemicals that
Just shouldn't be
We sent them three bottles with no labels just a number
Number one was Grey Goose
Number two was our homemade French with vodka and number three was the bottom shelf plastic bottle
At neighbor said one of the vodkas
Stood out
Because I did more of this one specific compound
It's called 1-propanol
And that's not a good thing
You want less of it
Vodka
I'm typically when you taste 1-propanol bats
More of that harsher alcohol kind of grainy alcohol compound
Rights of the Vodka that has more of that stuff is not as good
According to this
So it's
Possible
And that.
So is that maybe this product was Indus
Build as many times or distilled
Have the other two would have lower level
Which of these three vodkas would you suspect
Should be the
Cheapest
Least desirable vodka
Grey Goose is number one
Homemade vodka is number 2
And the cheap stuff in a plastic bottle is number three
If I had to
Choose based on this analysis alone
I would say number one
And which would be the ultra-luxury choice
Number three
303 is the best
Vodka that money can buy at least
She said the plastic bottle of vodka seems like the best
Wow
And Grey Goose
Seems like
The cheapest
But our homemade vodka
Was pretty good
It was right up there with both of these provide
I mean look at bees they all look very similar as well
So would you say that ours is basically Grey Goose
Yes I would
So we basically McGregor's
To be clear
Neighbor said that all three of these vodka
They had less of this
Bad stuff than anyone was really going to be able to
Taste
But you did say and I like to fart
That
Trace Amounts of any compound in a vodka
Could be enough to set off an allergy
Like maybe
Making your face turn red
When you're drinking
Cheap vodka
Alex so I can
Speak that but the bottom line for me
Science shows
If you don't have an allergy
All vodkas are pretty much
And if you do there is one more time
All right I'll get you moved on to drink number to how you feeling
I actually do feel the redness coming on your tummy I don't have it
I mean look Alex
You convinced me
I think what we have learned here today is that the differences between cheap and expensive vodkas made tastable
For most people maybe not even for you
Put that you're delicate
Constitution may be sensitive to them
On the inside
Brother polite way of saying
A lot of music
But I appreciate that
And I will take it
I never did turn right that night
Couldn't say
We love to hear what you thought about this episode drop us a line Planet Money at npr.org and follow us on Facebook
Twitter and Instagram at Planet Money
Today Show was produced by Sally
Home and Sindhu
Edit Planet Money thank you to our former intern Alice Wilder who helped the bunch on this episode.
Before she went off
To a new job with a podcast
Trump Inc
Congratulation
Also thank you to our current intern
Aviva dekornfeld
If you are looking for a new podcast to try can I recommend the sporkful Dan podcast
You sure can Alex I'll accept that recommendation yeah we just didn't episode all about MSG monosodium glutamate
And we looked into the
Faulty science and yes racism
That led to so many misconceptions about MSG
Accel spark plugs available when you get Planet Money
That's the sporkful you can find it on NPR one or wherever you get your
Good podcasts
And a correction
In an earlier edition of this podcast we said that Grey Goose
What's 4 *
It is distilled only
I'm Alex goldmark
I'm Dan pashman
Thanks for listening