Hey it's Noel King here and I'm going to talk about planet money for just a really quick second there about 10 of us on
The team here
We put out about a hundred episodes every year and any even one of those episodes can take a reporter week
Or even months to finish
We do a ton of research we travel all over the world and then there's a lot of behind-the-scenes stuff like figuring
Hangout how to buy 100 barrels of crude oil or when is the best time of year to launch a satellite
And the thing I think that probably takes the most time believe it or not is fact-checking we do so much fact-checking it
Planet Money
We have the time and space to do this because we're apart of NPR because we're part of public radio
And we are really grateful for all of the
People who support NPR
Who make it possible for us to do our jobs and every year around this time of year we asked you guys to
Join this group of supporters and help keep public radio what it is
Curious and independent and factually accurate if you want to show your support for planet
I need to go to donate. Npr.org Planet Money and there you can donate to your NPR station
And you'll help Planet Money as well
That's donated npr.org Planet Money
Donate. Npr.org Planet Money
Alright today's episode first aired back in 2013
It was reported by Caitlin Kenny and Robert Smith and we will have an update some fresh information for you at
If you try to see concert in the last few months
You may have had this
Experience
Sandringham really wanted to see
Taylor Swift
In Texas where she lives
So her husband computer
Waiting for the ticket
It's the moment they went on sale
They went on sale and
He told me
Waiting at a computer
Assume that he was a boy
Find the website
Get online
But he said as soon as he clicked on it they were gone he couldn't
She couldn't do any
He tried several times
Purchase them in
Was unable
Scott on eBay
What's for a while
Trying to find the best price
The best that he can
Come up with $500 for
And what was the face value of the
The tickets how much were they originally being sold for
They were under a house
And we paid about two
Now think about this
Vanderham wanting to see Taylor Swift she loves Taylor Swift
But most of the money she spent on the concert
Was going to say
Who is not Taylor
Someone who just happened to buy the tick
Only thing I visit
Someone who was waiting on the internet
Because I knew that they were going to get
Double the price
That person waiting to
Squeeze money out of true fans
What does the name scalper the situation because Sandra
She was happy
To pay the price that was asked
I need to think about the cost be
Cuz it was so much
In fact I would probably spend that amount
It's not a little bit more again
Taylor Swift if you're listening
You price your tickets way too low
You left money on the table
And somebody else
Skipped it up scalping happens all the time in the music business
Shady guy standing on the street corner in front of the Arena
An online place like StubHub
Ticketsnow
We live in a society where everyone is obsessed with making sure the Price Is Right
Supply matches demand
Entire industry
It routinely gets it wrong LOL
Today we're going to investigate why so much fan money goes into the pockets of people who can't eat
Even play an
And we're going to talk to a man
We're somewhat of an expert about being scalped
Call me Kid Rock Bobby whatever you want
Kid Rock is Waging War
Tempescope
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Is reimagining banking
I offering account
With no fees or mini
I can be open from anywhere
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Kid Rock first got big back in the late 1990s when he was known for combining Rock
And wrap here this
Huge hit called cowboy
Outsize personality
Back in the night
These days he's got more of a country Roxane going on in back in 2013
He just released a new album
What's a little bit of that
Show Kid Rock's on tour for the album
And the scalpers wanted a piece of the action
So we have to
So I actually looked
To see if I could find
StubHub for your show
Okay 780-3730
Before 490 like when people are willing to pay that much
Approached by
Scalpers in the underground
So we can make you $100,000 cash
Just give us a few of those from
Rose forever show
Will never tell any
If you do a meet-and-greet
You can have 10 grand cash on the top of that
Cash money
Is unreported money the government
So they say 10 that's 22 me cuz I paid
50 cents on the dollar
Can I meet so I can leave, we have to get out of here with that horse crap
Kid Rock is the name for the scalpers
Wechat
He says they're making money off his back
And he's not happy with this
The thing is in some ways what he's doing
Is encouraging it
Keep raising his tickets really low
The current touring get a ticket is cheap
As $20
He says he wants to do that to all his fans can attend
But these lower ticket prices
Those bring the scalp
So I asked him
Why not raise your prices
Why not charge more for your ticket
But wouldn't you rather go to Juventus
Scalpers I mean if people are willing to pay this much
To see you
Clearly they love you that much and it's worth it to them
Even though they would that's a big act late and I really appreciate that but I don't want to break you
You by coming to see me
And ask somebody sing songs about Working Class People
For them
I thought it was important to stand
Why would I
Sing about what I preached in this day and age when you see so many people
Claim missing
This that and the other they charge a hundred $200 tickets
We got figure out who those people are
I want to make
I want to make as much money as I can but I wanted I don't need to drive around in
Turn it down Rolls Royce or Maybach
Hide from people
Because I felt like I ripped them off
Madonna
Rolling Stones
I mean come on
What do you think when you see like some of you about talk about the stones
They talk about you know that 5
$600 ticket price why if you were the greatest rock and roll bands in the world which they are
I truly love the stones 11
Why for the life of me if this may be their last tour
What they not go out
The coolest rock and roll band
Spike TV cheap tickets
The fast hey this is going to be our farewell
We appreciate it so many of you
People have supported this
4050 Holabird however many years it's been
If we're going to go out and get it
We're going to be so cool we're going to get a cheap Tech
Now that sounds
Good in theory
But if the Rolling Stones sold a bunch of
$10 tickets to the concert
You know exactly what we
The scalpers
The problem is
When you have so many Cheap Trick
When you have a fan-friendly ticket price
Sometimes it actually makes it harder for
Fans
To get those two
It's easy for somebody to buy it at that
Under undervalued price and then resell it at what the market really dictates
Jed Smith is the president of
Ticketmaster North America
And he said he sees this a lot
Artists like Bruce Springsteen
Pearl Jam Kid Rock you know that keeping it real they want a price ticket
It slows the fans go see the show
The Jared attic Master he has to remind
This may not
B
The best strategy
Because those fans standing in line or
We're trying to get on the computer to buy ticket
They're up against some very sophisticated
Heated scalp
Such as people who get up early and spend all night trying to get three or four tickets
These are scalpers who use sophisticated computer Pro
But they can scoop up as many tickets online as they can
Certainly on hot shows we see a ton of that activity
And we see even a ton of that activity you know for the best seats even on a medium
Medium demand show
Show images of how much money there is to be made
Some of these outfits are or incredibly sophisticated technologist minutes a little bit of a cat mouth
Game for us because
Empty the ability to grab tickets at
Thunder Valley
The price is it is a huge incentive
The continue to pour money into the technology to fight
The defenses that somebody like Ticketmaster might throw in their in their way
There is huge money to be made doing this
Couple years ago the feds arrest
City size in California
Their company
Wise Guys
And the whole business was to use complex computer systems to get around to get Masters limits
To try to gobble up as many tickets as I could and then resell them
And these guys
They said they made more than 25 million dollars doing
I feel like this is Battle of
The Titan so on one side we have Kid Rock
Rockstar
On the other side we have
These like scalpers
These new modern
Hacker Scout
Kid Rock he doesn't want to raise his prices
The Wiseguys of the worldis Calpers
To take all his money money money that he was earning by sweating his butt off on stage
Well there is
A slightly devious way
To get around
Is problem
You know who can get Kid Rock tickets really really cheap
And get a lot of Kid Rock tickets
Kid Rock
Back in the old days back when you know
This whole electronic ticketing things started happening and people start to trade and resell tickets
Online
Artist hat sort of a way around scalp
If they didn't want the scalpers to win then
They could be scalpers
There was an article Mossy journalism reporting couple years ago.
People are taking their own tickets and putting on step out and telling them at a higher price
So that they could get that extra money without getting the bad
I might even been guilty of that
I'm not sure because
I Didn't Do It consciously but I might have been
You know I've done might have happened I'm not for sure so I'm not going to say it didn't
And I'd be willing to bet it probably did
It was kind of thing when it first came out that's what you did
You know what I mean nobody was the wiser new just you know you Scout those tickets yourself and put that money in your pocket
People willing to pay for it it's like you're saying what's the matter
There's actually kind of a good business reason for doing this
For artists and musicians to be there on scalpers
I have to do with the complicated psychology of fans
And the way fans think about their relationships
Two musicians
Remember Sandra ham paid $250 each for her Taylor Swift tickets
She says
Taylor herself wanted to charge that much
If I saw it on her website for
See I don't think everything
I don't think I could do that
Why
IJustine
How much money is it good
Concert
I mean I know she's so popular but it's just
Taylor Swift
But you paint it so sorry
It was worth it but I think it was the
Concept that
Bias
Delta ticket
So you guys paid like $150 over the face value of the ticket
Do you feel bad for Taylor Swift but she can get that money
No
Expungement money
No it was a packed house
Sure
You know the system is
Screwed up
When 8
Taylor Swift
Fan would rather give money till you know a shady guy in the corner or someone she doesn't even know on the internet
Then give it to
Sweet lovable Taylor
Swift I mean that is the system
We have now and you can see how the artist
Would you little frustrated by this I mean
What did that guy ever do
In order to get the money
They want as much money as they pay
Yeah I mean you could see whether kind of shady dealing might be appealing but
Kid Rock says you know.
Older he got
The longer he went through his career
Alas appealing it scene
Cheetahs
He didn't want to be a jerk
He want to make sure his fans could get his tickets for
Fair price
The interesting thing is
I need the latest horror
He told me he's got all these new techniques
In the war against scalp
If a ceramic is Kid Rock when he talks about the sound a little bit like an economist he's
Really
Thinking about
The economics of tickets at one thing
Scalpers to make money
There needs to be more demand for ticket
Supply
Now if Kid Rock doesn't want to change
His prices
Give another option
He can up the supply
Do more shows
Some places where Kid Rock thinks he might sell out
That there might be more scalpers
Is adding lights
Doing eight shows in Detroit
There's twenty tzumi 20000 tickets sold
In Chicago over 20000 Indianapolis St Louis March 2nd show
In the future you know we might be blessed enough to look like hey God forbid we have to move this into a stadium
Kid Rock is flooding the market with himself
Driving down price
But of course he knows that that alone will not.
Detert the scalpers
In a huge Stadium no matter the size there are still good seats
And that
And no matter
How many shows he does
There's always going to be a shortage of those really could see
Of the seats that people really want a giant Arena it actually makes
The proportion of bad seed
The Good Seed
Even larger
Discover's know that they can take advantage of that
Kid Rock
We're going to Ticketmaster it got this second
Yes
$20 seats for the masses
It's for the fans
The crank up the prices on those first 20 rosary
Platinum pricing
Is what it's called
We took a thousand tickets
And we price those whatever that that Sculpey marketware that secondary Market
Determines it to be
You know where you literally like going on 17 what are people trying to prevent tickets and then determine the price
Not me personally but we have people to
They go and see what the markets determine your hip
People are looking for
Tickets in this guy's got them for sale for 250 we have tickets to the same spot
Okcu adjusting the price as you go through
Yeah there's no set price on the Platinum tickets it's whatever the market
Now he's still under pricing
The tickets
So the question that I had when I first heard this was
Why would a stopwatch
Buy up all those premium Platinum tickets that say like a hundred
$25
And then jacket
Price even more
Well
You got another trick for that
Paperless ticketing
When you show up to the show and you have one of these Platinum seats
You have to show drivers license
And swipe your credit card
Already can't sit down
It still seems to be a little bit of a conflict of Kid Rock talks
All about oh it's about the people in about the
Fan
And then he's got the premium
Pricing
We're by ghetto basically you're staring out into a sea of rich people in the first thousand seats
Yeah he's worried about that
And that's why he has actually won last
Tweaked with pricing system
Samosa seated beside in the house 20 bucks
Premium seats near the front more expensive
But the first
Two rows
No matter how much money you got
No matter how rich you are
You can't buy it
Those seats
Are chosen by Lottery
And they're going to go to people who paid for the chi
$20
I'm tired of seeing the old bridge guy in the front row with the hot girlfriend
Not girlfriend you know where their boobs hanging out with a beer in there to screaming the whole time and then the old rich guy stand there like he could care less
Three common themes
Kid Rock concerts
Probably most people's cops I've been a lot of artists
Yeah so it'll be nice to see
The people be able to have a real
The best shot at
I could give them a kitten Espino
The best tickets
Just so I can picture
The optimum Kid Rock Show
There are
Breezy fans and Kid Rock t-shirts in the first two rows
And then behind that
There's a thousand seats of people in tuxedos all the rich folks
NF behind them filling up the rest of the Arena
Are a bunch of people who paid
$20 for their tickets
$20
Well I don't know what to text you this part
It's still a kid rock show but yes that is a general idea
And the sweet thing about this is that
Kid Rock knows that the people about the $20 tickets
They now have more money in their pocket
NetSpend
On beer
Auntie shirt
And hot
And Kid Rock
You get to cut it at
You give people fairprice I think they'll be
Don't feel a little better about spending their money
Anime
I might drink some more beer they might buy two t-shirts in might spend as much just because they don't
Feel like someone's trying to get over on
And all the pics you liked everything is transparent out in the open
And I'm going to make money off and I'm screaming this at other artists
I'm going to make
Money
You know that means and I'm happy to discuss it with any of you at any time
Mick Jagger Kid Rock Says call him
One last thing
We wanted to see
How well Kid Rocks
Plan his work at the scalpers is going and so
What way you can check to see how concert tours going anytime online so Caitlin ticket
All right here we go out so this is for a Kid Rock show on Saturday he's playing in New Jersey with Kool & the Gang and Uncle Kracker
We will be able to see all of the individual seats and which one have been sold in
This is one of the moment of
Truth because
If Kid Rock under prices
The tickets are too cheap
In a whole place will be sold out and will be scalpers standing outside
Kid Rock
Will lose money
But
Is Kid Rock
Overpriced
Discharging too much
Then
The place is going to be half empty and if they're being very very sad show
So what are you looking at
Alright Mama Tracy regato queso
We got some
Tickets available here in the official Kid Rock Platinum seating
He looks like maybe just 5% of the seats still available in the very front
The median price seat in the middle
Okay just new man out here sold out section 303 no seats available section for A2 no seats available
Now are there very
Cheap tickets a Toyota tickets any of those left
All the way in the back yeah it looks like they're still a bunch in the very back of the venue
So from Kid Rock's perspective
Economy Lumber
He's got a place to see me rock is going to be full but if you really want with the last minute you don't have to go to scalper
You can actually go to the fridge
Injured Smith from Ticketmaster if you told me that's what he likes
You know if you under price of tickets
Too many go to quickly
A few left means
They got pretty close to the right price
After the break Taylor Swift does something that Kid Rock
Wasn't even willing to try
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence
Santa run you're busy
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial and when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR
To save 10% off
Off your first purchase of a website or domain
That episode was originally reported back in 2013
The next year Taylor Swift released an album and then she went on a world tour to
Promoted
Something like 30% of those tickets ended up on reselling websites like StubHub
Which means she priced her ticket
Sue Taylor Swift was facing exactly the same sort of problem Kid Rock
If she sold her tickets at a reasonable price
Scalpers would buy him up and then sell them at a profit
But at the same time
Not a lot of artists want to make their tea
Too expensive because fans don't like that
It's not good for the brand
Kid Rock had his strategies to solve this like raffling off front row tickets
But Taylor Swift did the thing that kid rock refused
To do she just raised her ticket prices
Some of the seats cost
Hundreds of dollars
She raised the prices so high that some of her shows didn't sell out
Which for a pop Superstar
Seems worrying
But Taylor Swift apparently thinks like an economist
Do you know selling just enough that if you see
Seats are left empty that is a sign that you're pretty close to the true market price
That's how an economist would see it
And this is the thing that more and more artists are doing their setting ticket prices closer to what they're going for on reselling website
That is according to David Marcus
IMed Executive Vice President and head of Music at Ticketmaster
He says yes
This is a thing that has changed
Since 2003
I think there's no question that
The sense that fans are exposed to these prices and these other marketplaces
And are willing to
Pay those prices
Is making artist more comfortable with charging hose price
Taylor Swift actually had a second part of her strategy and it worked like this
Before tickets went on sale she had
Add fans log onto an online portal and register with your email at
Ticketmaster then ran those email addresses through an algorithm and that algorithm made a judgment on whether it's a deer
Dear John 1998 at hotmail.com is an actual fan
Or is a scalper
You get through the algorithm
Get access to reasonably priced
So that was a plan raise prices on the general public and Target actual
And Taylor Swift plan to beat the scalpers seems to actually work
The 30% of tickets that ended up on reselling website dropped
To just 5%
TV show with reporter
By Robert Smith and Caitlin Kenney
Just Jane produce the original and Shane McKee and produce the update
We're on Twitter Facebook and Instagram at Planet Money
And once again if you want to support our podcast and all the work that we do please go to donate. Npr.org
Splash Planet Money we really appreciate it I'm Noel King thanks for listening