Hi Alex goldmark here
This is a bonus episode
Because we're celebrating a special occasion
Are other podcast the indicator from Planet Money
Turned one-year-old this month
It is daily
It's short and we're proud of it so we have picked out one of our favorite episodes
From the indicators first-year to
This one ran back in March
It is
Standardized test
Kids I know it's a very
And we thought this would be the perfect time
Explore this really interesting little economic story
About creative
Creative destruction that is the idea that the
Economy is always evolving
If there are new products
Are constantly being invented
And those inventions make the
The old products
Absolutely
And his forces usually pretty
The movie reel
The video cassette
Comes to DVD becomes
Is online streaming
Things are always getting more convenient
Faster easier
Cheaper
But there are little pocket
The economy or the laws of creative destruction RC
Suspended like little islands of old school
Places where being old and outdated
Is a competitive advantage
This is the indicator on Stacey Vanek Smith
Ankara Garcia indicator is 1994
Take yourself back Bill Clinton was President
E stamp
Cost $0.29 and
The SATs decided to allow students
Graphing calculators on standardized tests
Support also comes from the UPS Store
From printing packing and copying
To faxing mailboxing and notarizing
The UPS Store offers everything for small business and this Memorial Day weekend
May 24th and 25th when others may be closing
The UPS Store is doing another thing altogether
Opening
Because small businesses
Owners can't afford to take days off
The UPS Store
Every ink for small business and of course shipping
So card if I don't know what your living room look like when you were a kid
But if we took
A time machine back to my childhood home
The technology would seem pretty amazing right now
I had in my room of course a boombox
It was pain
It's a lot of D batteries
We had a VHS player we had a landline telephone with
Is answering machine that played
These little tapes
We had a family computer it was enormous and it was beige and it weighed like a million pounds and it was connected to
A dot matrix
I remember those days
None of that technology is around today
And the reason is not around
Creative destruction
A phrase that an economist named Joseph schumpeter came up with Mark Perry is an economist at the American Enterprise
Institute
And he says creative destruction can be this really
Difficult and destructive forces
But it's also a really
Creative destruction is just
Continue all and Powerful
Very positive force in a market economy
It just reflects the dynamism and changes in technology and I'll differ
Some types of fields and so sometimes in my
On my block I call it hurricane Joseph
Ssds gales
Creative destruction that are kind of
Disrupting markets
Hurricane Joseph
Economist never change
In Creative destruction is why none of the
The technology
From my childhood exist today
Except
Cardiff it's all coming back around
The Graphic Edge
What
I know it do I don't know do you remember I said there was big calculator there like the size of a Hershey bar yeah
Borders you are sick they were like the original iPads
But without being able to do anything
Except give you a nice cosine graph
Right they could they could do calculus in an absolutely nothing else
Screen and you could type equations
I remember mine 12
We spent a lot of time together me and my graphic
And I looked on Amazon the other
And TI is still making these calculators
And so is Cassio and
Cartas de look
Exactly the same
Really busy or not
Are they still work
Even going to believe it
I mean hopefully
It
Appears to be every bit as complicated and
Like is dense with
Tiny button
As I remember
So yes you're right you're not wrong and ends in thinking it is to look and feel
Peter Belita is
The president of Education technology at 10
We could easily add features to a calculator is like a touchscreen Wi-Fi or camera
But we don't
I mean
Are blenders that can connect to the internet matter connect to the internet
Well done
Thank you my mind is still quite analog I'm afraid
But the idea that a piece of modern technology would not connect to the Internet is almost unthinkable
And yet
That fact is what makes these calculators special in fact
If the graphing calculator
Were connected to the internet
It would be less valuable
There wouldn't even be a reason for its exist
Because it you can compromise the test security and really detract from what the calculators are designed to do
Did once represent cutting-edge
Technology
It took standardized
Cast designer
Years
Before they would allow graphing calculator
To be used on the
Their testes
Test makers worried
Data calculator
Would give students
Unfair advantage
Now it's exactly the opposite
Graphing calculators are pretty much the only technology
That standardized test makers will allow
Because I'm like smart phones or laptops
The graphing calculator is not
Connected to the internet
Yes its value lies in the fact that
Technology
And speaking of value people pay a lot for this
Anachronistic
Most graphing calculators cost
Around $100
Which is about what I paid when I got mine
The technology was really cutting edge
And now you can buy devices that will do far more for far less money
M&S Peter at TI about
It does seem like the price hasn't gone down that much it seems like the price
You know considering the technology involved Maybe
Should have gone down more buying graphing calculator with graphing calculator
Really
A solution for a classroom
Apus if you think about it high school calculus and
Physics students are a captive Market
Mark says
Hurricane Joseph
Is usually inescapable but these
Or like Island
Isolated peoples
Creative destruction
Doesn't reach
Had a really interesting
Product you just think about her or appreciate I guess for there
Ability to stay frozen in time after many many decades and over a generation of changed
It's disrupted everything else
These calculators are giant in
Bulky
And students basically are forced to buy them
For school
They also look like something
From another era
And honestly
Given the archaic technology that use their still
Pretty expensive
But Peter Belita says
A lot of people still get attached to
A lot of students he says he gets calls and letters from them
All the time
Annie's got a theory as to why
Some people
Seem to love their graphing
I think it's a tool
You know that there are that they have
Time with them by their side
When studying you know what are not always the easiest classes
You know math science
Oh you know calculus you know there those are long nights and
I require a lot of hard work
And always right by their side is 30 a graphing calculator
Houston is he sees a lot of photos of
Students who are dressing up like graphing calculators
For Halloween or you
Club
The game then
He says there's like the speed Trend in using them in promposals
At the thing
By the way the idea for this episode came from a listener Thomas Hallett thank you Thomas
And if you have a graphing calculator
Please send us a photo of it
Indicator at npr.org
That was an episode of Planet Money to other parts
Weekend
Indicator comes out every weekday it's short 10 minutes or less
It's kind of like your economics crash course before what's happening in the world right now so please go and subscribe
5 to the indicator from Planet Money wherever you get your podcasts
Or ask your smart speaker
To play the indicator podcast
Alex goldmark
And thanks for listening