Everyone I'm Robert Smith
Today Show is a classic
Classic from January 2014 hope you like it
Are you ready
I'm ready
Tell the story of your bat
To my friend Shane and I
After college we're living in
And there's just one Park
That we walk by
Every single day
And
Somehow it came up in conversation where that Park was located
And Shane said it would located on 22nd Street
And I said it was located on 20th
And at the park that we walk by every day I am
Certain
That I'm right
Shane is going to space he doesn't actually know that many facts
So I'm like
All right
And then
Then you took out of map
And I was wrong
I was certain
Complete
There is something satisfying about it
How do you say
That's a nice moment where there's something it's
Where you got two sides
That is sad here is what I believe
And here is way to test
Whois ripe
One winner
And one loser
Best case scenario a bet forces you to think
Carefully about what you believe
And what you don't
I know these famous good-natured beds
In the world of science
Revival Stephen Hawking
Bet another scientist
That
Cygnus X-1
What cygnus X-1
Something up in the
The cygnus X-1 was not
A black hole
Parking lots
It was a black guy
Richard Feynman physicist
Want to bet that no one could make a motor smaller than basically a grain of sand
Smaller than
4th of an inch
Lost
But in economics
That's something to happen
The fact if you act around people really just mentioned
One story
1 bit
There was a big one over the future of humanity
And unlike those bets in science
It was not a friendly bet at all
Hello welcome to Planet Money I'm Alex blumberg
And I'm David Katz of them today we talked with historian Paul Sabin at Yale who just wrote
A book about
The book is called the bet
And the story it tells
Explain why bats like this don't happen more often
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their
Your own website
Using customizable layout
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editor
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online presence
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
This is not a bet
From like the 1800s
It happened to Alex when you and I were in Middle School
It was a bad between
A biologist and Anaconda
The biologists name was
Paul Ehrlich
Professor at Stanford
An expert on butterflies
The book called How to know the butterflies
But then in 1968 he wrote another book
Just a few weeks to put together in this book animal snap your title
Scott the population bomb
And it got them on TV
Not just any TV show
Here's Johnny
This of course is The Tonight Show at Professor Paul Ehrlich
Seema Khan Sage is a young guy got short dark hair
He's wearing a suit that today looks
Awesomely vintage with a very very wide super ornate
And the fact that he's on The Tonight Show at all is kind of amazing because when he sits down with Johnny Carson for the interview
Berlitz message
Is a bit of a downer
3.6 billion people in the world today and reading about 70 million a year and that's too many
The very delicate life-support systems
The bite of the things that suppliers
Oliver who will ultimately with Oliver oxygen
With all of our waste disposal are now severely threatened
His basic argument was that there were too many people on on Earth and that
Was going to lead to disaster this is Paul Sabin the historian at Yale who wrote the book about the bet we're describing
Early he says was not on The Tonight Show just one
That Johnny Carson had early back on The Tonight Show again and again and again
Over 20 times
Present just love the guy
And his book called the population bomb has sold over 2 million copies
And his parents is on the show probably
Drawn more audience response and anyone else would have had on would you like
He was talking about Doom
He could also be really funny he went on tour like a rockstar giving all these
Paul Sabin dug up this speech recorded in 1970
Let me just say the quality is not very good
The first line you're going to hear is
I put a lot of thought into what date mankind started to go down
I put a lot of court
At what date
Mankind started to go down to two
Today January 3rd 8000 BC
That was the day one a few enterprising Soul living
Go to be around around quarter gave up a hunting and food Gathering existence
And began to practice agriculture
Well I think that's that is the
Signature
Style of Paul Ehrlich
Has a biting wit wild same time
Telling these
Horrible stories about what was going to happen to humanity until
Ehrlich's view of the world
July people just seem
Intuitively right
I mean you can look at a graph of the world population going up year after year
And it showed no signs of stopping
We were living on a finite planet with
With limited resources
Raonic was a biologist
He'd seen this thing happened with Anna
Animals would have
Population booms during
Pleaded the resources
Food Supplies
And the result was often a population crash
Humanzee argued were not immune to the
Human race was in real trouble
Saban says he had a lot of support
There are number of biologists
And they were
Extrapolating from their studies and his case of butterflies but also have other types of
Creatures
The idea of cycles of population
A gross and then population collapse and that would be a devastating
Extraordinary apocalyptic
Crashed unless
We took action now to try to avert that
All right that are like
He is going to be on one side of
Pig on the other side
At this point is basically
At home watching her like on TV and getting really really worked up
He's an economist
His name is Julian Simon
And Simon had also been worried about popular
But the more he studied at
The last word he got
Simon feels that the growth in population is not going to be
But we are not going to run out
Know when you get the chance to explain himself publicly
He does it in the way that an economist
Here is Simon on the TV show firing line with William F Buckley and let me just say by way of inter
Kallax
Okay here he is explaining why he thinks
We will not
But it be
Copper ore
We are royal
We tend to think of the supply is being fine. We think about running out
But we think instead about our capacities to increase that Supply
By finding substitutes
The finding better ways to get more of it or by replacing it then we begin the longer to think about the supply Loyola coppers being funny
If you don't have
Cup of a telephone line that you do have satellites
Transmit messages you as well off as though you had
I recognize that moved at William F Buckley's making
Actually explaining what the person just said
Simon here is basically saying
Ehrlich
You and your population doomsayers you don't understand how the economy works we are not like butterflies we're not like any other
Species special
I will make the special
Is this economic system setup
That will keep us from harm if we people want more copper there will be an incentive to find more copper if demand for oil
Growth price will go up
Which will create an incentive for people to find alternative fuels
But as we said he likes or likes
In fact later in that Firing Line interview
He tries for a
Is that little joke about this
A kid in class was dozing
And I woke up with a sudden start
And he said the following
He said that the Sun
Is going to burn out in 7 million years
Thank goodness
I thought you said them
I'm sorry said the sun is around 7 billion years
I said thank goodness
I thought he said 7 million
Is 10
Highlights the absurdity
About worrying about
Things
In such a very long Horizon
Buckley sound so bored and they seem like coughing in the
I know Simon never made it
These are the two sides you got taller like the Megastar population biologists
And Julian Simon
Economist at
The University of
Let me just say In fairness that both of them enjoyed making very big
Make a be pretty dramatic
Ehrlich started a movement called zero population
He got a vasectomy so he couldn't have any kids
To set an example
And to try to keep population in check he proposed taxes on
Diapers
Instead of a tax break
For people who had kids you suggested
An extra tax for people who had children
Julien Simon meanwhile enjoyed poking the population wears in the eye
A certain point he took to wearing devil horns on his head while giving talks
Two things along the lines of
We're not going to run out of energy we have the Sun for crying
That loud
And he went through a drink in a colleague's face after debate
Simon felt ignored
You never got the attention
And it seems that is why he proposed
The bet
Kevin said he will learn to detect
Proposing back when he was a kid
He wrote in his autobiography about his father who would say outrageously wrong things and this is sort of a
Authoritative fashion
He would refuse to hear any questions
And Simon got so frustrated he wrote
Quote there was really nothing I can say except
Do you want to bet
That's what he said earlier
Simon rodia an article in
The journal science
Mets announcer like Ken doll
People like him and this
Was the first time I guess they're like really
Noticed I think
And there was a furious reply and then they it's spilled over into another academic Journal where they started arguing
Each other
And
And Simon proposed an actual bets
Put your money where your mouth is
What was Tesla's idea
So on one side Paul Ehrlich
And two of his scientist colleagues
On the other side
Economist Julia
They decided to
Money on this
And here it is
Here's the bet
Here's how they decided to wager over the future of humanity
They decided to bet on
The price of five Metals copper chromium nickel tin and
Wonky but there's actually a nice logic to it because
You're the basic idea is
That these metals were essential for all kinds of stuff that we do everyday there are
Going to electronics
The car is in the building
So if Paul Ehrlich was right more people on the planet would mean
We would start running out of this stuff
In which case
The price of these things
Should go up
But if
Simon was
At the markets in human Ingenuity would sort things out
Then the prices would not go
They would say the same
Or even go
The time frame
For the bat was also kind of amazed
The bet that would not come due for a decade
The bat was over what the price of these Metals would be
10 years later
So they made the BET 1980 they wouldn't know who won
Here's how the payout would work
An easy way to imagine it is
I think that
In 1980
You take a box
Can you put $200 worth of each metal in the Box
So $200 worth of copper Chromeo Metro
Got 5 medals
The total value in the Box
Is a thousand bucks
Then you wait 10 years
1990 you open the box
And you add up how much medals are worth in
The loser has to pay the winner the difference
I think if it had been maybe they've been Planet Money they would have actually bought the metals and and held on to them and seeing what what
What would happen but in their case they
They simply went by the prices
This is a good mixed drink exactly
I like that his colleagues agree to the vet to shut Simon up for tenure
But they also thought
Of course they're going to win
Here it comes just to remind people
The 1970s there's all these things happen
That made it very easy to think that he collapses
Was coming there famines in Africa wars were breaking out as a result of conflict in the Middle East OPEC
I cut up oil to the United States
Repent huge line that gas stations stretching around the block actually remember this like the gas shortage of the 70s
Things got so bad that
The president
Richard Nixon
Decided he had to do something
Good evening
3 weeks ago
I spoke to you
About the national energy crisis Ann Arbor
To drive more slowly on the highway
Leisurely Sunday drive he said maybe
Stay home I am asking
The old gasoline filling station
Close down their pumps between 9 p.m. Saturday night
And midnight Sunday every weekend
And this is perhaps the most amazing
Jimmy looking back
Nixon ask people to cut back on an outdoor ornaments with lights
We are already planning right here
The White House
Neuchatel
Touch lighting
That we would normally have at Christmas
Literally
Killed Christmas
Craigslist
No Christmas lights on the White House lawn
And Oliver to say I remember the seventies it was very easy to get the idea that
The world was just
Careening toward cats
In fact there's a Newsweek cover story around this time
The title of which was
Running out of every day
So that was the context
That the kind of narrative in America
The best started 1980s and remember it's about the price of metals
Over a deck
Tibet
Fitbit
10 years Creep by during which the world population does continue to climb we add 800 million people to the
Men
Who won the bet
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online
Find presents and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layouts along with features including e-commerce functionality
And mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial and when you're ready to launch use the offer
Code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
So Simon decisively won the bet the prices went down by
On average around 50%
In all the metals
A cryo if you if you bundle them together
And they all go down they all went down
Fairlife
For like right yeah it was it was it was a pretty substantial loss
I'm in terms of the alphabet
What are the reasons prices drop so much
Was just what time it said
People invented subs
Set of aluminum people use plastic
Paper Packaging
And where are the query that new Wars and conflict would just
Continue to escalate making scarcity
The opposite word app
Jennifer example I wore in Zaire and then be aware there was a lot of copper
Actually ended
So there's more copper in the world
The price dropped
Economist have gone back and looked at whether Simon just got lucky in
Metal prices Google
Up and down a lot
And if you pick other 10 years
Bandera Lake
But Paul Simon Says broadly
You got to give this one to say
The catastrophe Ehrlich with predicting
Just did not happen
So far we have not been just like butterfly
We're more complicated
In the sense that what Simon represent
Was the idea that
That markets and technology and prices
Would lead to adjustment of supply and demand in in the economic system I think that's
Clearly
Victory has to go at least so far that you have to go to Simon
What is the good that came out of
Bet what what did we learn
Well I think that human societies are adaptable and at the markets are powerful forces
But we also
I'd be much more cautious about same thing we learned out of this bed
Well there's a lot of fighting there is not a lot of listening
The other problem
Here is that
A bed about metal prices is really a poor proxy for thinking about the the state of the planet
Paul Sabin says he thinks the BET actually poison the water has helped set the stage for a world where environmental debates are framed
Extreme
One side warning of certain catastrophe
Do the side saying like
Are you chicken littles be quiet everything's going to be fine
In October of 1990 Julian Simon was going through the mail it is
And he found a small envelope from California
Inside was a sheet of paper listing metal prices
And a check
Impala Relic
For $576 instead
There was no no
Doing Simon died in 19
But Paul Ehrlich is still a professor at
Is 81 years old
And we caught him up
That's how I feel today about that bets
And time
It is not softened his
We were sorry that we lost because we knew that
The deniers
The people who think that everything is going to be great
That we can grow forever and so what would make a out of it so obviously we were disappointed
Political State mistake maybe but again we did shut him up pretty much for 10 years so
It was not
Catastrophic it's become
What's technically known and scientists a pain in the ass
Did you ever talk with Simon never talk to Simon
Never met him
Never wanted to
Do you think Julian Simon was entirely wrong
I did not only entirely long colossally look wrong
You it's harder to be more wrong than to say
That the only limit to The Copper human beings can have
Eyes away to the universe or to say that you can grow anything
Had any number anybody can
Chico
You know absolutely nothing about anything important what about some of the more central idea of his
Which is just that
You know
The human beings are bright and we will add that the economy is not
Like a butterfly Poppy
You know that it doesn't crash that is things get expense
Did people find out
There's no question at all the people find Alternatives when they get if things get expensive and someone there are
Plymouth Diner patient that's what he never
That's what many economist's don't crash
Did you learn something from the vet
Yeah don't make bets we certainly made a mistake and making the bed because we lost
You could argue that the world
Needs are like
And Simon
Simon one that bad but
What he was saying to work
4 Market
To be able to sort out something like pollution or climate change
You need to relax
Saying hey
We got to do something
That's after all what a market is
A bunch of our life Saint Simons fighting about what they think the future will be
Tell us what you think about the show or if you know of another wager about economics you think we should cut
Email
Planet Money at npr.org
We can find us on Facebook and Twitter
Special thanks to Paul Sabin
Who wrote the book on list called to bat David kestenbaum and Alex blumberg made the original episode back
2014 the rerun was produced by Kasia mihailovic Alex goldmark is are supervising producer and Bryant
First Step show
If you're looking for another great podcast pry
The indicated Spider-Man his new daily take on the news
Dedicated team takes one number and breaks it down for you very quick
Sherlock
Check out the indicator on NPR one app or wherever you get your podcast on Robert Smith thanks for listening