Hi Jess Jiang here
We originally reported this show back in 2013
And now we have an update for you at the end
Everybody knows dum dum
They're Deuce lollipop
You seen him at your doctor's office or you
Bank
Sugar corn syrup little wax wrapping when two different flavors
But lots of people
Don't know where they come from
Joyce Farms the Walmart's number
We're looking at thousands of
These little rapper lollipop
Clattering out
Is Big steel pipe
@the dum dum Factory
Northwest Ohio
Jean Spangler is the former CEO of the Spangler
And he's showing us around the kitchen at The Candy Factory
It's a little bit Willy Wonka
Imagine kitchen Mead for giant
With a couple of busy little chefs running around in aprons and hairnets
Where did Metals metal detector reporting these big
Eel pots
Sticky sugar in
Corn syrup into this Kitchen Aid that is as tall as a basketball hoop
And there's what looks like Pete buckets
Just standing right next
The buckets are filled with flavors and colors
Is blueberry
Cream soda root beer watermelon
Dum Dums is the signature product of
The Spangler candy company
The factory is several football fields big
We need a whole separate building just for the ingredients
What ingredient in particular
Muse about a hundred thousand pounds of sugar a day
Where's the sugar in the Sugar Shack
The room is basically big enough for for huge tanks
Of liquid sugar Olympic-sized swimming
We have about enough
Trigger storage here
For about 4 days
So we're receiving sugar
No contest
All year long all day long 24 hours a day
Lots of places replace sugar with corn syrup
And there's corn syrup in these lollipops to
But Dean says to get the true flavor of your childhood
There is
Nothing
Delivers
Flavor
Like sugar
That's a that's a real
Could we make a dumb dumb with a pure corn sweetener
Probably
Would it make the same emotional connection with you
No definitely would
It's the sugar that.
Sugar is the the sugar as the deliverer of the flavor
The Spengler company they actually make this other iconic
To Candy something even more Nostalgia inspiring than a lollipop
Red and white
Candy canes
They used to make them here at this Factory in Ohio
About 10 years ago
They moved the red and white candy
Operation
To Mexico
It had gotten too expensive to make
I'm here the places that buy the candy canes to sell the Targets in the Walmarts of the world they don't care about the brain
They don't care where they come from they want them cheap
Candy canes are treated like
Commodity by the big box stores
Completely the red lights
And when you go to the big box retailers of the world
They leave
4 quarter percent
I can't I have a son of Cain
I mean
They're going to the lowest price
So this story so far
Factory moving its operations from
Ohio to Mexico where can I bring more cheaply
That's a typical story you might think you know the real
But Kirk faccia
The currency of the singer
He's pretty sure you don't know the way
In fact
Recently he's giving a talk at the Kiwanis Club in town
Kind of like a rotary cup
And he explained
He could expand his operation
In a huge way right here in Ohio
Not send any candy canes to my
At all
I said I just need one thing
People get excited and then
I asked him to guess what's the one thing that you need and people guess
In all kinds of things up
A lower tax rates in
How about workers comp reform and let's get rid of OSHA
And let's repeal that food safety modernization act or pass the right to work law
Or let's get some government development
This is some of the things I guess
Amongst other things
I said no it's not
Any of those
In fact it's not all of those put together
If I paid 0 taxes and got all those other things
Don't even matter
It's not as important as the one thing
That I need
And people are still guessing what it is and I said
Lettuce by sugar
On the free market
And there's the silence
Animals kind of collective
Why can't you do that
And then I say it's a story
And I'm about to tell it to you
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm so itchy
And I'm just saying yes you are here today because you are amazing producer and bf
An adventure together working on this server
Yes definitely Kirk fashion story the story of a lot of American candy
It may not be exactly the story that
Kirkwood Hotel
But it takes us from a candy company in Bryan Ohio
Out to the sugar beet fields of Baden Minnesota with stops in Washington DC
Support for this podcast and the following message come from fidelity
Has a Fidelity wealth management client you get a dedicated advisor to help
Grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes and make clear recommendations
Thanks for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
Before we Dive In
Here's the most important thing you have to know to get in
Into the story
There are two price
For sugar
The price you pay when you're in the United States
And the price you pay almost everywhere else in the world
On average
Over the last decade
The price you pay in the United States
It's about $0.15 more than you pay outside the country
15 cents more per pound of sugar
$0.15 extra per pound of sugar if you're in the business of making candy
Adds up to a lot of money
Reason
100000 lb
A day
That's $15,000 a day
That's $75,000 a week
Multiply that by 52 weeks
It's three to four million dollars
Three to four million dollars a year
That's what these guys called
The sugar path
Now
Who would do that
Who would impose
Disorderly random tax
On us candy
US Congress
The food conservation and energy Act of
Is better known as the US Farm Bill
I'm going to read this one part that this whole story is really about
Subtitle d
Sugar section 150
6 Sugar program subsection B sugar
It says that the US government will guarantee
Minimum price for sugar
That is not to drop below
22.9 cents
Per pound
End
Quote
That's
The guarantee
No matter how low the price goes in the rest
Of the world
In the United States
You will be paying
At least
.9 sense
Purple
Insomnia
These guys
We're driving into the field we're going to plant sugar beets in 2013
And the snow is only about 3 in deep
At the moment right here
Just like a Barren Wasteland
Blaine Benedict
He's a sugar beet farmer here in Stephen Minnesota
And he runs a farm with his two brothers
Farms in this part of the
Country were settled in the
1870s
And
Our family has been farming here since late 1870s
Blaine and his brothers
4th generation and it is just
Back out here
Farmland as far as
You can see it's a long way out to the horizon
The clouds are low in grave supposed to snow later this afternoon
Can you hear the birds
Even though the ground is still totally White
It's a hard conversation
Someone's 4th generation farm and say
Why do you get the special treatment
Why do you deserve
Special line written in a bell that guarantees a minimum price for your product
We go around and around on it
The answer we land on is
Because all our
Foreign competitors are getting special protection to
There's government involved
In most developed countries
At some level of
Or another with
With a price
On sugar
The US sugar guys say
Just look at Brazil
The Brazilian government
Couple billion dollars in subsidies to their sugar industry
They say the Mexican Government actually owns most of its factories that make sugar
God biggest fear is that we're all in a fair playing in a competitive
Field
You know when
If you're competing against
Other
Government policies in Ohio in
I mean that's
That's what makes us nervous is it
It's a very common
Rationalization
You know the other kids are doing it or that other guy's a bully or
Something
Daniel Sumner is Economist at UC Davis in the early 90s he worked at the USDA setting us Farm policy
He says the problem with this argument is there is already a solution to unfair trade
A solution that does not involve enshrining a price guarantee into the law
On sugar there's a very specific
Remedy here
Whip something
Cold
Countervailing Duty law
States
It works like this
If you're an industry
And you think another country is unfairly subsidizing something we buy from them
There's a solution
You complain to the World Trade Organization
The US slaps a tariff
Or a tax on that import
It's bigger than the subsidy amount
And that's the way
To even the playing
A lot of people told us there is this really big reason
That sugar has a price guarantee embedded in the law
And this reason has nothing to do with Brazil or the WTO or
Actually economic
Do I just tell that
He's the store now
Back at The Candy Factory
Kirk Bashaw says
Here's a story that will really explain the US sugar policy
You got the Ken Starr report that
Careful readers of that report will notice
That
There was somebody who
Call President Clinton while he was in the Oval Office with Monica Lewinsky
And president
Took this person's phone call
22 minutes I think it was
Monica wasn't very happy
Is that the president was taking a person's phone call
Wells part of the investigation made to corroborate her story they want to look at the White House Records
And sure enough it was one of the
That this sugar tycoons is not calling
Had called that President Clinton had that conversation
That's the definition of having too much
Political power when you can call the president of the United States
When he's in the Oval Office with his mistress
And you take his phone call
That's too much political
We look this up in the star report and apparently this called came in while Clinton was trying to end things
With Monica
But the cigar incident was yet
But back to the sugar story
The sugar Lobby
It is really powerful
Super well-organized
Each year
It gives a lot of money
Political campaigns
And it spends a lot lobbying for or against Bill
Last year the sugar industry spent almost four times what the wheat soy bean and corn industry spent
Combined
And it's been almost double what the food and beverage industry spent as a whole
A big chunk of that money goes to people like
This guy US Representative
Collin Peterson he is a Democrat from Minnesota
Until recently
He was cheer of the agriculture Committee in the house
I've been called a communist before
I'm okay with that
That's because
Collin Peterson is a big advocate of the central planning of the sugar supply in the guaranteed minimum price
We asked him if the reason he's such a champion of the sugar program is that the sugar companies like them
American Crystal
Are the biggest contributors to his campaign
If American Crystal gave me zero I would take the same position
Really any difference
Well well because this is 25% of the economy in my district
You think I'm not going to fight for this
Ghetto
I mean it has nothing to do with
How much money made
They support me because I support them
Which comes first the chicken or the egg
Back in Stephen Minnesota instantly Collin Peterson's Hometown his dad farmed
Potatoes out here in sold the land to sugar be
Beet farmer
His constituents here in Minnesota
They agree with him
Crowbar is in the middle of nowhere it's a dive in the shadow of a grain elevator
And everyone here can tell you stories about Farmers driving around and Shining trucks are made
Checks from the government
But if you press them
Bill say
Nobody out here once anything to change
I talked to Chris Lang and Judy Hanson over beer
They love the system the way it is
In fact in October during the Harvest
When sugar beet Farmers start turning sugar beets
Into sugar
There's a bad smell in the air but it's the smell of money
Shoes on kids feet smells like we're building stuff
If you eliminate the sugar program
Again Congressman Collin Peterson
What will happen is we will not grow sugar in the United States
And why is it such a bad thing
Because it's it's a
Huge economic activity in many parts of this country that
Help me create a lot of jobs
And a lot of economic activity
You know everybody wants the government
The fix
You know the crate job
Let me do these polls the government
Not doing enough
The great job
And the water area that through this recession
The old one area that's worth
That's actually been successful and is actually
Maintain that increase jobs has been agriculture
Cancel the people
The claim that they want us to
Did the government to improve
The economy
Are going after sugar and Dairy
And crop insurance and every other
Aspect of the
Of the farm sector
They're trying to screw up the one thing that's actually working
The other side of this
The candy manufacturers
They make the same argument
Justin reverse
Peterson says
Jobs might be lost
The candy guy say
Jobs that might otherwise have been
Created
Weren't
That's what's so strange about this whole thing we're not so different you and I are both these
Classic American Industries
Minnesota farming
Ohio Manufacturing
In Minnesota there's four generations of farmers Farm
But in Ohio
Those guys are 4th generation 2
The Spangler Factory has been around since 1906
Always run by A Spangler
The fifth generation of spangler's worked as an intern
In the factory this year
And both guys meet
The same argument that their Industries are a multi
Supplier the candymaker's say what about the guys who Supply the wrapping paper
Paper for the Dum Dum
The lollipop
What about the sugar beet truck driver
The Tractor Sales
What will happen to them
If farming goes overseas
Is there a way the government can come up with the most
Beer policy
To both of these quintessential American industry
Farming and manufacture
And we ask the guy who's in charge of the sugar program here in the United
States that sugar commissar
Chief Economist at the USDA itself doctor
Joe glauber how do you arbitrate with sphere
Well
Never asked her in the comments about what's fair or not I mean I ate there you know it's a highly regulated market
And you know generally I think as an economist
You know I certainly would prefer a free market
Joe glauber is the guy whose job it is to manage the sugar supply in this country in order to keep up the price of pork
He's basically saying
His job should not exist
The government's really his
Hands should be off the wheel
But in this case this is something we're Congress feels that Sugar producers should be
Protected
From the world market
Congress continues to address the question of sugar
They're competing Bells
One on the Candy Maker side a sugar of Farmville that tries to dismantle a lot of the sugar program
That's a bill that shows up pretty regularly on the hill
And it's never pass
Of course there's also a new farm bill that will just
Extend the sugar program we have now
It's expected
And if it does
It means
We will continue to get our candy canes from Mexico
No sugar from Minnesota
Support for this podcast and the following message come from twit.tv
Play This Week in Tech podcast
Every week
Award-winning Tech expert Leo LaPorte and top Tech pundits cover the latest news
Innovation
Fence privacy gear plus the pitfalls and mistakes
In the world of tech
Your first podcast of the week
Is the last word in Sac
Join the Lively Roundtable discussion and subscribe to This Week in Tech podcast on your favorite podcast
Or at twit.tv
Hey it's just back here in present day
Since we ran the show originally
That farm bill passed in 2014
It left the sugar subsidies pretty much the same
We text back in with a kindness Daniel Sumner and he said those sugar reform bills
Also went nowhere
Things have gotten a little more complicated but really nothing
Exchanged of any substance
And I credit
For that
A remarkable job done by the sugar Lobby
But with all this talk these past few weeks around protecting American industry from foreign competition
Steel and aluminum tariffs in the news
Daniel says
He's hearing a bunch of politicians who are usually harsh on trade
Changing their tune
Interestingly enough those tend to be
Politically
Anti Trump
It's always possible we can put together a coalition
Of people who are frustrated with mister
Trump
Actually change them
About sugar policy
Dino Peds
Optimistic but doesn't see change happening anytime soon
We also check back in with Spangler the candymaker's
They said they are still turning out those Dum Dum lollipops in the US and candy canes in Mexico
And that
Fifth generation family member who's an intern back in 2013
She's not working for the company right now
They have this rule family members have to work somewhere else before going full-time at Spangler
But they tell us
She may be back someday
If you want to comment on Today Show head over to our Facebook page they're we also have a brand
And new Planet Money shorts video it's a story of how that tip got into your credit card and why it took so long
And you can see Kenny Malone dressed up as a French fraudster and a couple of us dressed and sheep 60
Youth clothing
The videos are also online at npr.org Planet Money shorts
Run social media everywhere as Planet Money today's rerun was produced by Aviva dekornfeld
I'm just saying thank you for listening