Maybe like me you're scrolling through your feed last night or you were sitting around watching cable news
And you noticed this little news-item
Thank you Chuck we have breaking news in Michael avenatti is about to join me live by Michael Collins closest business partners
Is flipping against
I'm sorry one of Michael Cohen business partners
Is flipping
You have my attention
Gaffney Friedman is a Russian immigrant he's known locally at least in New York
State of the taxi King
Dean Friedman
I
Know this guy
Interview come back in 2015
The heat is intensifying on President Trump
And his personal lawyer Michael Cohen after one of your business partners evgeny Friedman
When is the taxi King cut a deal with prosecutors
Veil of saying taxi cab
I understand that because it is an amazing
Concept and the News broke last night
The Friedman the taxi King has
Reportedly agreed
Help out state
And federal prosecutors in their
It's not clear if those investigations are related to Cohen still the question looming large
Could the deal give prosecutors more leverage to get Cohen to flip on President Trump
Surprising that the taxi King finds himself in the midst of this whole drama with
President Trump and
Michael Cohen
But what you meant the taxi King
It's not that
So we're going to do today is to replay
The episode that we did in 2015
And at the end we will give you an update on what
Taxi king is up to now
If you own one of those yellow taxi cab
In New York
The most
Valuable
Thing about
Is not
Car
Itself whatever
It is this
Little metal shield Bolt
To the hood
It's about the size of your hand
And it's called
Taxi medallion
And if you want to operate a cab in New York City
You have to have one of these
Which makes them kind of these rare precious
Yeah because the city
Trolls the number they're only about 13000
Taxi medallion
In exist
And because this Rarity not too long ago
Taxi medallions for selling for 1
2.2 million dollars
Gene Friedman owns Aesop
Rising number of
And he invited us out to his
Is Garage in Queens to take a look
I live these and breathe easy
I remember when I got these how I got these
Discovered here it's 9 v62 that tells you a story
Read Ben has a lot of
Because he's got a lot of Medallia
So many medallion
You've given them all
Me just to keep him straight
You can see the names on legal documents
For all of these little holding companies
And their staff
In Finders
All over the garage
Volcano Taxi
We have VIP Taxi
The wrestler
Wrestler taxi why do I rest or taxi
Cuz used to wrestle
Kind of I actually
They did a female wrestler
Yeah every name remind him of where he was in his life when he
You bought it so
Princess Diana's son
Name the taxi Medallion after him
Dylan
And at the expanded his Fleet
He started to make a lot of money and you can actually tell that by looking at the taxi
There's your cognac your Chardonnay or Cuervo hilos it's a hotel in Saint Tropez Armenian butterscotch
My brownie
Right then we got into the Suites
Good time
Not so good
We have soccer taxi wow that's that's
That's my wife we were both
Taxi
Friedman has been
Remarkably successful
Add buying up these rare precious
Taxi medallion
He controls over a
Thousand taxi medallion
Which not too long ago altogether will worth
Over billion dollars
But the taxi business is of course
Changing a lot right
Used to have to wait for a cab in New York you have to run out and hail it was terrible at it there's a definite article
The first time I've successfully hailed a cab I felt like a real New York
But now all I do is pull out my phone and go to Uber or Lyft
And
Lo and behold some guy in a hot dishes up a couple minutes later to
Take me wherever I want
And because of that guy the value of the old fashioned taxi medallions
Is plummeting
If your jean Freeman
Owner of a thousand of them
This is a real proud
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
And I'm Robert Smith today in the show The Rise
And the fall of the taxi Medallion kit
Did you really fall
You know it's not looking good I'm going to be honest with you but
This is really the story of what happens when something you own
Is suddenly worth a lot less
This message comes from NPR sponsor Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimum
That can be open from anywhere in 5
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Slash money
Hey there I'm Joshua Johnson the host of 1A there are lots of places to debate today's issues if you don't mind
I'm getting attacked for speaking your mind or asking a simple question
The1a is differ
You'll find the 1A podcast on the NPR one app or wherever you listen to podcast
Gene Friedman never wanted to be known as
The taxi guy
He is my age is in his mid-40s
But he is trying to dress
Skipper and younger gas type
Jeans and
Purple sunglasses and he's trying to grow a stubble beard that's was girlfriends making do right now
Taxis were always his dad's thing
Until his dad got sick back
In the 90s
The horrible two pack a day smoker back then
He had a heart attack
His dad at 8
Taxi medallions in New York
York which back then was
Pretty impressive
Remember to the numbers of his
Oh yeah of course
Maybe one number 137 2 + 38/6 + 60
C7
6 kol suitcase 73-74 for p97 for P90
Those are his
Does the Family Jewels
Joseph MI
Friedman grew up in New York but was working in Russia at the time
He was a high Finance guy
And when you heard about
His dad's heart attack
He rushed back to New York
Imaginext weather
Classic
Movie like seeing you.
The father in the hospital bed
Waiting outside with taxis and thanks son
Son this could all be yours
But the thing is Friedman didn't want it to all be his
He sort of thought of taxis is this grubby business
They were dirty that was smelly
They were small
And more than that
Cabs back in those days were run like a mama
You save up money to buy a cab
Or get a small business loan and buy a
Couple or few
This was the way Friedman's dad
But the song Gene Friedman
He was a finance guy
And he thought we damn it
The middle
The Medallion
If you buy a medallion you are basically buying part
Of a monopoly
The city isn't making any more of
The medallions are like gold or real estate
And yes they're
But Friedman new bankers
He knew he could get big love
And interest only loan
What's with super low rates
And he told his father you could use this borrowed money to get more and more and more
What could go wrong
Although his dad had a pretty good idea of what cookie
Diamond where it says you're an idiot he says you don't know what you're talkin about this is not the way things are done
This is not what you want to do and yet it was exactly what
Friedman wanted to
He borrowed money
He bought medallion
And then he bought more money and he bought more medallion
Anyone the price went up use those medallions as collateral
To get even more love
And Muhammad Ali
She was basically doing what Lehman Brothers and other people on Wall Street did right before the Finish
Crash massive amounts of money to buy assets
That they believed could only go up
He was a one-man Medallion hedge fund
He could not get enough medallion
And you can just bid for them
He bragged about
Overbidding
If the last Medallion in some sort of blind auction went for like
$100,000
He go up to a hundred and ten
Yeah the guy pays 400k
He paid for it
And that is when he started naming them after
Drinking at the time or his
Favorite vacation spot aarhus
Lady friend garages for taxis gas station
Keep them fuel
Infrastructure
This is my hump
This is where
We are new calves are born
An old Cavs come to die
He shows us around his garage and inside our guys
16 meters
Pulling stickers off old taxi putting a new one
Kyle
The yellow part
Everywhere
Taxi cab
The secret Friedman says
Is to make sure that he never see The Medallion Taxi
Just sitting around in the garage
Because then it's not out on the street
Not making money
Emily Spotswood he has hey why is this year
Page 121
Go to work
Yeah he's going to go to work
So when I first heard how much people were paying for it
Dalian
More than a million dollars
I thought that this can't possibly work
How can one tax
DeKalb pulling enough money
To pay off
$1000000
It doesn't seem right it does not seem right and yet the manager the garage locksmith
Joe Cresta Novak says it is all about
Generating
Steady ink
Bereavement rent all of his calves by the day
Eeyore by the way
Themes of Drive
One guy take the day shift work
Makeshift
When driver gets out
Next one gets in
They get used to each other
Smell
They know everything
Always warm
Nicorette
The drivers pay a set amount of money
Eugene Friedman
Where do they get a grape fair to the airport or whether nobody held them down the whole ship
It does not matter how many people get into their cab because
The drivers pay the same rent every time
Depends what car you get anywhere between 100 and 100
But all day for the whole day 24 hours
Usually I first texted you I will come on between 2 and 300 today
You don't like to think of cabs as these little yellow machines that just spit out money all day long
$125 a day
$45,000 a year per cap
Like clockwork
And as long as that income coming off that cab
Is Morgan Freeman have to Fork over to pay off The Medallion loans
He's good he's making a profit
This is why finances
Because if you can get a cheap loan to buy a taxi
Dalian
As long as you're paying a low-interest-rate you will make a profit
It's like getting a cheap mortgage for an apartment building
As long as you have renters paying every month
You're good
Prima basically built a taxicab Empire
He started by Captain Chicago in Boston
Philly people started referring to him
Taxi cab
So this is clearly the right
This is the rise yes
So I imagine that mean
Means we are close
The fall
Which is of course why week
Friedman and you know we always talk about
Bubbles
Right
But when you're actually looking at it happening
It's not always the way it works
Sex with the taxi industry
It's less of a pop and more of this
Sloe crumble
The first crack
The first crack is
Uber shows up
In York City of
Friedman he tried to show that he wasn't sober
It was no big deal
You know what there's nobody that's a bigger fan of uber than I
And I will save you know if they're worth 50 billion dollars
And somebody can recognize that you know what
I know maybe
Maybe I'm worth something also
Yeah I don't think he's really that big of a
Yeah he is trying to show a sort of
Bravado in the face of adversity in effect
As I talk to him longer and longer he would just
Keep putting these little jobs at Uber
Where he be like you know Uber is just
For the 1% taxi cabs are for the people
And
You know call an Uber you don't know if it's going to show up you don't know how much they're going to charge
Because clearly
Uber bugs Hamid bugs him that their customers
Who prefer calling an Uber
Just sitting in one of his Yellow Taxi
But the real problem for freedmen with Uber is actually not
About the customers
It's about the drivers the guys who rent the taxi cabs from Friedman
That is how he makes all of his money and those guys have been going over to Uber to
Sofritas had to start lowering the fee he charges everyday to rent out his Taxi
And that means less money coming in
Even that Friedman says
Heekin
Live with that he can make a little less than the drivers he can maybe in some perfect world coexist with Uber
But the thing that might just kill him
Is the thing that helped
Build his business
The finance
The bank
The banks
It was cheap loans that freedmen took out those are coming due and suddenly the banks are getting nervous the same people who gave
A Freedman a bunch of money over the years
Are saying
Hey maybe we shouldn't give you any money
Financing
The financing is in there is because you have a bunch of Steel bankers
Right
And these are guys that are extremely good friends of mine these are the guys that have made me
Financing in Bangkok
Have made me horny
But you know what they stop financing
Liquidity
Has dried
You can understand where the banks are coming from
They were lending Friedman money based on the Rarity of the taxi medallions those precious taxi medallion
But now if you could operate something that works
Pretty much exactly like attacks
Without a medallion
The banks are figuring that these medallions
Are not worth it
Stacy as I was listening to Jeanne Freedmen's woes I just kept
Flashing back to the financial crisis
The housing bubble collapsed because he talked about the same sort of things you know it's all about the value of them
The Medallion nobody knows what the value of the medallions are
Because remember
He used to have
A billion dollars where the medallions are they sold from million each
But now nobody wants to buy nobody wants to sell the market for Medallion his shutdown and
If you could have changed hands
Have done so
For something like 800
Thousand
Dollars
Witches
Way below what Freeman paid for
And just like happened in the housing crisis the banks are starting to foreclose on the taxi medallion
Infact Citibank is in court right now
Trying to foreclose on 46 of Freeman's medallion
They have names like hypnotic taxi and bombshell Taxi
He's always got a clever name even when he's in trouble
And Friedman has responded by filing bankruptcy on
Just the legal entities that own the medallion
It's getting really messy
So perhaps with is parallel to the financial crisis
It is not surprising what Friedman did this
Spring
He basically said the taxi industry is too big to fail any publicly proposed
They perhaps
The city of New York
Should bail out
It's Yellow Cab industry
He said basically
We were promised the Monopoly we are promised regulation
In the city of New York has a protector
Did that until his suggestion was you know maybe the city could guarantee the loans
Shinichi maybe the city could help the money start flowing again
We want our franchise War
Are pop-up
Are mama
R Big Brother
The city of New York the city of New York
Interested in us
Having a vested interest in moving forward
And doing what we need to do
It's a little bit hard for taxpayers who had a hard time swallowing
Some of the support of the banking industry
Altering their crisis but supporting the taxi industry
Might be too far for some
What is unsupported it sucks but it support listening
Yorkies have a vested interest
In
Yellow Taxi Cab
You need tok
Taxi cab picking people up at the airport
Movie tourist trap
What do you mean
Do you really need taxi cabs
Uber is creeping in everywhere and in fact
There was a move in the New York City Council to try and cap the number of Uber's in New York
And it just
Fields
Calculator
Even Friedman's ex-wife
She uses Uber
Of course she
I do this because his eleven-year-old son showed up
At the very beginning of the inner ear
I don't know he's my kid because
He just came over here in a cab I think was 5 in 56
And his mother
Said you can take an Uber because I feel more comfortable and he said I'm not getting into an Uber
Because it's a family business I'm taking a Yellow Cab
So that's how I know he's my kid
Is that true
You don't take the Ubers
I don't like
Why not
Only maybe maybe to the airport Maybe
Just maybe but
Ya must be particularly hard for Freeman because
Right now
He's still making money he still making a lot of money all these cats
Are still out on the roads
It's not like they're put them away in some garage or something
Ugly 24 hours a day in New York
And he's got plenty of drivers who are still willing to
To pay him by
The day and by the week
The pleasure of driving those caps
Freedmen's real problem is that he borrowed too much money
The freedmen had been doing business like his daddy done business
He would be fine
He's got all those big loans from those big nervous Banks
And he is at their Mercy
We never listen to
You know if this all goes
South 14th
If it sort of the worst case scenario
If you have to sell his beloved medallions
Or if they get foreclosed upon and suddenly medallion
What the market
The truth is
Somebody is going to buy them
Are you going to be at
Much much lower price but
Taxi medallions will be bought they will be riveted on the some yellow car in a garage somewhere in Queens
And the medallions will be right back where they've always been
On the streets of New York
Looking for fares
Okay the show was recorded back in 2000
15 three years later now what
Taxi King been up to
What's the easy stuff first
It has been a rough
3 years
Financially free
He did not get a bailout from New York City
Citibank did foreclosed on a bunch with medallions
And
His divorce
It was finalized
Then there's the bigger
The source of Gene Friedman Fortune
His medallion
The price of the medallions has
Plummeted
You can get a New York City taxicab medallion
For under $200,000
Although I would not recommend it at this
And then there's the big stuff that came out yesterday
The tax stuff
The reason that Jim Friedman in the news right now
So here's what went down
When you get into a New York City taxicab there's a bunch of little fees that they hit you with
And you're too pretty General Q's Friedman
Of not paying a $0.50 charge
To the government
Even though it scabs
Collected it
Accused of stealing $5000000 of these little fees
And he was facing big
Prison time
We don't know
Exactly what the deal is
Between the taxi King
And prosecute
But we do know that yesterday
He pleaded guilty to lesser charges he will not see jail time
And
Many people are reporting that he has agreed to assist
State and federal prosecutors in their investigation
We texted the taxi King earlier today
But by the time we put out this episode he still had not gotten back to
Let us know what you thought of Today Show You Can Eat Ellis Planet Money at NPR.
LRG Athleta money I'm at Radio Smithville you Stacy
It wasn't our show was produced today by Nick Fountain who went with the taxi garage
And found the story with those produced by Francis Harlow and it was edited
Earthquake TM capital
Robert Smith