Hey just a heads up this episode originally aired in April 2013
10 years ago Charlie Wheeling with living entry
And his wife faced a
Classic dilemma
They're trying to figure out where to send their daughter to
And then we got wind that there was a Chicago Public School in our neighborhood
That was doing some interesting things and that seemed like it would be a great place to send our oldest daughter to school
Seems like an easy choice but
Charlie was raised out in the suburbs
The people in the suburbs of Chicago
The city's public school system
Seems like a horror
A terrible place to
Tell my mother I think the best
Metaphor I could offer is it she was stricken to the point that she kind of had to lie on a couch with a compressor head
At the prospect of her grandchildren her beloved grandchildren
Spending their formative years in a Chicago Public School
The Charlie really was teaching public policy
University of Chicago
Wish we had when we were having fights with our parents
Access to data
Minecraft
And Charlie started to tell his mother that she was falling prey
To one of the
Days of Our Time
Sherpas
Chicago Public School System might have
Lower test scores
Higher Dropout rates
Private schools are
Even schools in suburbs
But that doesn't mean
Chicago Pub
Book school system
Caught
The high dropout rate
The important
Sing
And figure out whether a school is good not good somewhere between
Is how much value is added
The kids who walk in the front door
And in Suburban areas and in public schools and some charter schools
Have motivated Highly Educated affluent parents
So those kids are going to do very well no matter what happens and in the Chicago public schools had a really tough demography
XO they walked in the front door with a lot of disadvantages
This argument Charlie was having with his mom
Is over this
Really basic question
That we all struggle with all the time whether we know it or not
That basic question
What causes what
Human brain is really
Program to answer this question const
This is
How we have survived
Do dominate this planet right
What made that noise
Bear made
What caused my hand
Fire caused my hand
We're so eager to figure out what causes
What
That we often get it wrong
Oh I wear my lucky hat to the game and my team won
So I am never
Off this
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Jacob Goldstein and I'm Robert Smith today on the show
What causes what
Or if you want me fancy about it
Correlation and coffee
This message comes from NPR
Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one Platte
Time to build an online
And run your
Create your company's website
Using customizable layout
Along with me
Features including e-commerce function
And mobiledit
And Squarespace
Shoppers built-in search engine
Optimization
Go to squarespace.com
NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to love
Use the offer
Code NPR
To save 10% off you
Your first purchase
Please have a website or domain
Our Guest today
Charlie wheeler you may know him as the author of the book called naked economics
We've talked about it
Before the show
Charlie has a new book out it's called
Naked status
O'Charley's
Choose the title naked statistics of the people wouldn't really notice
Part of fix
We did in fact I did a book signing at Hanover and I saw a woman walking out of the store with 50 Shades of Grey
And naked statistics
Tide pod okay
She may be sorely disappointed with one or the other
Soak the book sort of covers a lot of ground in
Statistics we're not going to try and cover it all today we're really going to focus on this one thing on this one question
What causes what really
This question is at the core of how everybody makes all kinds of decisions I mean if you think about it
Every decision the government makes
Every decision a parent makes with their kid
Almost any decision you can think of
Trying to
Call some out
Come
Statistics can be very helpful in trying to fit
Figure out what causes what
But as you show in the book
Statistics can also
Totally
Screw you over
Yeah we wanted to start with a specific example
In the book Charlie and a really serious issue which is
The older women especially after menopause
They have an increased risk
A certain disease
Are quartz researchers
I said they wanted to look at
The tells what happened
Well there was a huge longitudinal study
It was a study of nurses over many many years decades
It was found that women
As they approach menopause
Who were given hormone replacement therapy which is estrogen
Had lower rates of heart disease and other diseases that are prominent killers of women
Bandito
This wasn't just a random connection this wasn't boy people wearing purple shoes have less click cancer
There was at least some biological
Cooperation early set theory that would make sense which is look what happens as you age is a woman
Your estrogen levels go down
We're seeing this association between lower estrogen and bad outcomes
So then estrogen therapy if it shows that has positive effects on things like heart disease
Would appear to be
A beneficial strategy
And this was like a big serious study I mean this was done
By Harvard
People looked at it there's a large sample
Full-sized and Doctor saw this and they said well if there is a correlation between reduced
Risk of disease
Can estrogen
We're going to start
Prescribing
Estrogen
Ritemed Medical Center
To get the point where not only were doctors comfortable prescribing estrogen
Thousands and thousands of women it be kind of
Became what you did when you got older
But there was even a movement to start giving estrogen to men
Now scientists look
Bissonet sad
There may be
Correlation between taking f
Estrogen heavy reduced
Heart disease but there could be a lot of
Other
Doctors here maybe the people who are
More likely to go to the doctor and ask
For estrogen
Argent
Healthier people
Maybe there are other reasons we don't know about
Did something
Scientist do all the time and it's called a randomized trial
Explain what they did
They took another large group of women
And they randomly assign them to one of two groups
Just like your seventh grade science project the treatment group or the control group
And one group got the estrogen
The other group did not
And what they found was
Was really scary
Scary and tragic they found that the opposite
Appears to be true which is
Did the women who got estrogen therapy
In this controlled experiment actually had higher rates
Of heart attack stroke breast cancer and other things that were quite damaging
And then when they looked back at the number of women
Who has been prescribed estrogen
They assumed
That thousands of women most likely had
These events or died prematurely
Because of what had been really fundamentally a correlation
And not a causal relationship and it's actually said there was a causal relationship we went the other direction that estrogen was actually bad for the help
And this is obviously a pretty girl
Large particular
Tragic case of
Can correlation and
Mistakenly thinking that there is causation
This kind of error
It happens all the time it happens everywhere I mean when we talk about
A lot of the show
The stock market
50 Cent we talk about the stock market
Market you know that
The daily moves the stock market is up
Today or down today
Basically every news story about the stock market if it's up
They just find some correlation find some good news
Assume that that good news
Is causing it to go up
On the same day if the stock market went down they would find some other news
Assume that bad news
Causing it to go down
Yeah let me give it a thousand things are having
So
I read a story not long ago in the Wall Street Journal the admittedly was a little tongue-in-cheek but
In the run-up to the Masters it pointed out
That when Tiger Woods was winning tournaments the Dow Jones Industrial Average
Consistently did better
Well that I should be tracking his golf scores and
Watch
The Masters another tournament
It's at you know with your broker on the line
And of course that is
Clearly
Just correlation
And I feel like
When we make this jump when we want to go from finding correlation
Actually figuring out
Causes
That's when we sort of
Get to the edge of
Statistics right it seems like
Statistics is amazing at figuring out correlations and even
You don't getting rid of
Extraneous variables in whatever
As far as I can tell statistics on its own is not enough
To get us to cause a
To get the causation
Stupid people for studying this stuff ultimately need to
Come up with
Clever trick
Eternally in your book you have
A number of experiments that Reese
Done
To get to this
Question of what causes white and it wasn't love was about
Crime
And especially crime in in DC in the district
Columbia
This is cute policy question about
Cops
And crime if you just
Ian Moore
Will crime go down
And it's really hard to tease out because obviously high-crime cities
Have an incentive
To hire a lot of cops
And so the date is really messy but you describe a way in which they
Figured out
This probably figured out in the desert
Columbia
Right so
There were some very clever researchers
And I said well we need to find
An example
Where we get a lot of police
For reasons unrelated to Crime now that
We would think of the relatively rare occurrence why the world would you create a lot of police we didn't have a lot of crime
And they happened upon in this is what great researchers do
The terrorism alert
System so you get all those colors orange red whatever else they are
By law
Because Washington DC is likely to be a terrorism
Target
When the terror alert level goes to Orange
Then extra police are put on the mall and other parts of Washington to protect against Terror
Has nothing to do with Street crime or things like that
So they could then ask
Bond
Orange alert days when there extra police
On the streets for reasons unrelated
Street crime
What happens if
Does it go down
Halifax it does
It turns out that when you have the extra police there for terrorism-related reasons
They're all the streets they make the street safer and things like murder robbery assault go down
And that to my mind is a very clever way of establishing a causal relationship between at least in Washington DC
Between more police and less crime
As long as we assume that the robbers are
Hiding in the room
Because they're afraid of
Elevated
Terror
It is entirely possible that they what are they considered was
Is it possible
The Tourist
We're less likely to visit Washington or to go out and about the flexbond
Photography
And you know what they did
Paycheck
Stat hypothesis
By looking at ridership levels
On the Metro
And they actually were not diminished on Haight art
Terre de so they suggested the number of victims was largely unchanged
So you even in this very clever Universal funding this very particular time there are ways you could trip up
I mean.
Do you work Taurus
Hypothesis
Impossible
No there there
Yes it so you you know even then it's tough to establish causality but you're building a case
It's circumstantial evidence
In a courtroom where you're getting closer to the point where you can be persuaded
That yes in fact this person did that cry more
A causes b or that police reduce crime
After the break
We asked Charlie Whelan
Is it worth the money to send your kids to an Ivy League school
How you figure that out
This message comes from NPR spawn
Squarespace
Is the all-in-one Platt
Come to building online free
And run your bed
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with B
Features including e-commerce functional
And mobile
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine
Go to squarespace.com
MPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR
To save 10% off
Your first purchase
Have a website or domain
So Charlie how old your kids
They're not V
Teen 12 + 10
So pretty soon you're going to be facing
A question that a lot of pee
Face which is
Which is college
Where to send your kids to college
And when your tongue
Clever ways
Tease this out
You talking book
About
Schools like Harvard and Yale
These big-name schools
Is it worthwhile to send your
Kid that will it make their life will it
Cause great success if you sent to those schools rather
Another one is problematic issues like cops and
Right and you can imagine why this is so hard to study people are not randomly assigned
To Harvard vs
A local community college that kids who get into Harvard
Are highly Talent
Did that's why they got into Harvard so when you compare
That wages or life outcomes of people went to Harvard
Versus those who went to Webster Schools
It's that is the
The classic apples-to-oranges comparison there's really no legitimacy to
Did that comparison whatsoever
On the other hand it's a very difficult thing to study
Neither Harvard nor most families
Would agree to participate in the experiment where you at a 50% chance of being sent to Harvard to 50% chance of being sent to a commune
Any college or not being able to go to college at all
So it's hard
Tease out
The value-added at these highly selective schools
But you described in your book away that some researchers managed to actually
It's not do that at least come
Write with a very clever experiment in this was done by two researchers Stacy Dale and Alan Krueger
They found
A large group of students
Who had been accepted to a group of schools that they described as the highly selective
It's cool so it's the ivy league and a whole bunch of others you would recognize
And those same students had also been selected
I admit it
To a group of schools that were less traditionally competitive less highly selective
So they were good enough
To get into Harvard
Some of them subsequently went to the highly selective schools and some of them
Didn't
And what that sets up is a nice comparison group where everybody in the sample
Is smart enough
To get into what we described usually as the very best schools
Some went those schools
Some didn't
So we can then compare their life outcomes 10 or 15 years later
And
It turns out that there doesn't appear to be any great advantage in fact I think no statistically
Significant events at all in terms of wages
For most students going to the highly selective schools with one notable exception which is Foreman or do students
There does appear
To be in a bad mood for the vast majority of folks in the sample
There was no real huge advantage to getting into and going to one of these highly selective schools
Well
So you have three kids
You are a professor of public policy you know statistics you wrote an entire book on statistics
Are you not the dad that saying queued
You don't need to go to Yale University
Well it given that I taught at the University of Chicago right now
Teacher Dartmouth I went to Princeton I would eat it
Yeah I know I know
I think that pressure cooker
High School
I'm not going to pressure them at all I think that's the takeaway is that I do think there are a lot of benefits
In terms of network effect
And things like that
That are
Appositive
Outcome related to go into those schools
But I'm certainly not going to put pressure on them and I'm certainly not going to cling to the delusion
That the thing that's going to shape
The trajectory their lives most is whether they get in or don't get in
Because really in this goes all the way back to the way I felt about
Chicago Public Schools
It's going to be the talent that they bring to the
The front door that matters most
So what will end up happening with your kids going to Chicago Public School
How did your mother end
Well there's a nice little interlude here and that we got an objective measure
Of how they were doing in the Chicago public schools because after they've been in school
For six years so my oldest started and the Chicago public schools in kindergarten
I had a sabbatical
And we move to Hanover New Hampshire Hanover New Hampshire is a privileged little Oasis that spends and ungodly amount on its paw
Public Schools
They would qualify as very good schools by any superficial measure
So these are the Good Foot certainly in my mother's eye
This is exactly where they should have been the first place so
For one year
All three kids
In first grade 4th grade and 6th grade
Transfer to the Hanover Public School so we can now see
Whether they're illiterate
It has all kinds of other problems
And in fact they did extraordinarily well in the universe
Schools with suggested that they were getting a very fine education in the Chicago Public Schools
I ended the value-added there was excellent
Did you convince your mother about the Chicago public
What's goes
You don't want to hurt you the first one she was always a little worried about safety that was
Not really an issue either but it wasn't just about the editors
I was saying her defense that she really did come around and Ona in part because of our experience and because you know was a j
Genuine
Concerned on her part you have to grantor that
That when she realize the kids were turning out okay
She has actually shifted her opinion and she's a little more skeptical
Of people who pay extraordinary amounts or devote great effort
To try and get into
A private school when the kids
3 years old in the thinking that this is going to radically change that child's life so I do think and I'm not sure that she be eager to have
Have be sending she still didn't want my daughter going to one of the highly selective high schools in Chicago
But she did come around to some extent so I'll give her credit for that
That seems like a perfect place to wrap this up Charlie will and thank you so much for walking us through the world
That was good to be back with you thank you I should say that we have established that there is a high correlation
Between a trailer Planet Money
And professional
Exactly
And I'm glad to be a part of that
Call Colleen
I have a question about quora
Correlation and causation or do you have an idea for an episode send an email
Planet Money at npr.org we're on Facebook Twitter and Instagram also at Planet
Money Shane McKee and produce this rerun our editor is brynhurst at and are supervising producer is Alex
Goldmark