Support for this in
NPR Podcast
The following message
Come from the UPS
Offering services from shredding
To printing to mailbox
And instead of closing
This Memorial Day we
May 24th and 20
The UPS Store
He's doing another thing
All together
Opening
The UPS Store
Everything for small business
And of course shipping
The other day I have
Early morning
You and I ran downstairs to get a cup of coffee
And ran into the
So
I turned on my recorder and I kind of bombarded her with my mic
Maybe you should say
Who are you
This is Kathy I'm sorry I don't know what
Catherine rampell imma calling to The Washington Post
Specifically Katherine writes about the economy for
Washington Post
It occurred to us that
Actually
The coffee shop is
Perfect
To show this thing that in
Infuriates
All right
So you're looking at an I see what size you looking
Can I get the
16 ounce iced tea
How much
3:15
Does on the board
Taxes
Okay
Okay so maybe that sounds like somebody buying ice tea and then having
To pay tax
It only sounds normal
Because we've gotten used to
What conference is here
Is one price on the board
And then this extra hidden thing that she has to pay for it's not just taxes
Sometimes it
It's fees and service charges
That seems
Pure out of thin air
Check out and drive us all
Crazy
Booking rental cars buying
Concert tickets for Lake have you booked hotel room recently sometimes
There's an internet fee parking fee sometimes there is something called a resort fee
Even though you're staying at a place that
Is not a resort
It's by the highway
Catherine
Brought her ice tea
Into the studio to explain why these fees and service charges
We're not just annoying
They are bad for the economy
Company should be competing based on
Price and quality
And not
Obfuscation
And the fact that companies do compete on apus
Is not
Create a better economy does not create a better experience
For consumers
And can infect raise prices
Consumers that are buying
Something they don't want
It's like everyone is a used car
I have a very good friend who's a used car salesman so I don't want to denigrate that profession
So what is your one tiny tweak that would change the world
My my one tiny tweak
Is that
We should require
Moron
Including taxes fees
Particularly in common types of
Consumer purchases were pplelectric
Price
Should be
The price
That is how Catherine rampell
Would make the world better
With one simple trick
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Nick Fountain and I'm Kenny Malone and Planet Money we tackle
Boba World
Big questions but
Today on the show we look for small answers this is something we've done here
Before we caught the smartest people we know and we ask them
What TV thing would you change about the world
To make our lives better
We have a suggestion for how you can get more money from your boss how to make the most boring sport
Little less boring and
How to take down the wedding Industrial
Support for NPR comes from LinkedIn learning
Proud to support the launch of life
NPR Sky to help you make better life decision
LinkedIn learning short video tutorials cover business Tech and creative
Skills employers look for at every level
All talk by XP
And new courses are added every week
+ LinkedIn learning is
Personalized
Recommended courses based on your end
And life
Get listeners get a month of learning
Free start your free trial
At LinkedIn learning.com NPR
Okay little tweaks that can make big changes Our Lives go
First idea
Comes from a labor Economist at the University of Notre Dame
Abigail
Wozniak
So I have actually a little wind up if you are interested in the moment I wish this occurred to me was
A couple of weeks ago so I am
Naturally a football fan
Since I come from Green Bay Wisconsin
Haha and I was reading about Aaron Rodgers
Contract negotiations
Aaron Rodgers is the quarterback
For the Green Bay Packers in over the summer he was asking for more money from the back
And what caught Abby's I was this quote from Raj
Where he said something like
Sure
I'm in a multimillion-dollar salary negotiation with my bosses but
Whatever I've got an agent
He's dealing with it
I'm just going to
Keep practicing football I feel amazed
And I thought that just doesn't sound like any kind of
Job negotiation that I have ever heard anyone go through personally like a normal person
They're like
I know this is a good problem to have I know I'm getting a good job but this is the most stressful thing I've ever gone through.
And
I think so
Thing that popped into my head was
More people should have someone like
Abby was next week is
All of us
Not just famous people
Should have
Agents know she's not saying this has to be your own personal Hollywood agent
Or even an expense
Lawyer
We know about those kind
She said
Make it as a different job
It doesn't exist yet
ABC
Intermediary you pay a flat fee
And then they'll have a couple of conversation
On your behalf when you need
So imagine Abby gets a call
Hate is the University of Michigan we'd like to offer you a new job
I would say thanks
That's exciting
I'm using this new service
This
Third person is going to contact you with my questions
It is it is it weird to think about actually saying that to someone offering you a job is weird
So weird right
Abby thinks that having this intermediary
Negotiate for you
Could be a huge benefit over the course of your
First of all
It would be this person's job to study your field and to know what your worth
And this takes a little Advantage away from your employer
Secondly
She says there's research showing that if you make less at the beginning of your career
You're going to make less down the road
Enter the sooner you bring someone in to negotiate a great salary
The better that is going
Also Abby says
This intermediary could help deal with some of the things that add to the gender pay Gap
Well it's clear that two things happen when is that women don't quite ask for
The same things that men will ask for in a negotiation but there's also evidence that when women ask
It's not received the same way as when men ask
Can an intermediary
Helps to fix that a little bit
LivingSocial it just kind of jams the signal a little bit
If we're going to name this new profession dude you have an idea like what we call this
Negotiator I think is maybe better than agent in terms of just capturing more what's going on
It's good talking to ghosts
You know I could do that has a neutral party but I'm not sure these people really going to be neutral
Mediaries accurate but also kind of bland
Yeah so
Yeah like negotiators good I like negotiate
I'm not in marketing
Everyone needs a negotiator
Lyle Lovett negotiator also a 1998 movie
Starring
Samuel L Jackson
What happened
Negotiates by what are you I don't know
Kenny has left the studio we assumed to go watch
The Negotiator the 1998 movie by Samuel Jackson
I'm in the studio now is
Sarah Gonzalez hey Sarah
Your tweets
Is about the wedding Industrial
And we gave you this assignment
Because you're about to get married congratulation comes from
Damon Jones he's an economist at the University of Chicago
And Demon you're planning wedding right now right
I just recently was married in
You just oh so you're out you're in the clear I am in the clear but I do have to write thank you notes
Are you behind schedule you have up to a year
To send out thank-you notes
Yeah who makes these rules
And that the time from
From the wedding gods
I don't know that I would call them the Gods
It would be like the wedding Gremlins
Damon's tweaked has to do with the way we think about wedding
Register
I hate weddings
Everyone hates them it feels like this sideways way of asking people to
Reimburse you for like
Their dinner in their boobs
Yeah and Demon also says that you can't even ask for what you really want on a wedding registry because it's
A little tacky
There's some gifts that are not acceptable to ask
For you know can you give me season tickets to the Knicks
But for some reason plates
Enforcer acceptable
We have enough plates we have enough Forks we don't need any more of those
I feel him here on the forks and plates
Maybe that made sense when those things were handmade in Pennsylvania but like this stuff is getting cheaper
And cheaper and throwing a wedding is getting more and more
Expensive
So here is Damon
I say
Let's discard the registry
And maybe just have some Tikka
Good old-fashioned tickets for the wedding
Weights
Sell people tickets
To attend your wedding
Okay we wouldn't use the word cell
Well that might be
Not popular
Instead of a wedding registry so like don't buy me a gift
Just pay for your plate of food at the wedding
Don't buy a gift just help us to
To have the best wedding
Now you want to use the right turn gif
You may want to charge different prices
Okay so no
Different prices for different people
Okay so a flat prices
Easiest but it's not fair
Like maybe you want to cut your undergrad College cousin a break
But your investment banker friend
She's paying full price
This guy is
Hold
And calculating and I kind of like it
But
Here Maps
You have plus one
Okay this is the are the worst
Yes yes
You have a really good friend that you want to invite to your wedding but they have a new boyfriend or girlfriend
And that you don't know
And now you have to spend like
About 300 person
For their food their booze there
Chair their table their Fork
Yeah and
If you have to pay for your new girlfriend's ticket
Maybe she doesn't have to come after all and there's another big benefit
No shows
Can you believe that you're going to go through this entire process
And only to have someone maybe not show up
Okay so I understand that it's a risk
Yeah so why not share the risk
You have a deposit that's none refundable on your ticket and if you decide not to show
We understand and we also appreciate that to your deposit is going toward the food that's going to be sitting there
Cold and I need
At the wedding
Okay so Sarah you are getting married in
About a month
Are you going to take
Damon suggestion
And charge
For entry to your wedding even asking people to give me
But I am going to go on the record right now
I just say this publicly
If anyone RSVP to my wedding
And fails at the last moment like that is not cool we are not going to be okay
At least tell me
Two or three days before so I can let all the Avengers know Sarah thank you so much mazel tov
And when you're out there can you get Kenny
The Comeback Inn
After the break
A modest proposal to make baseball more in
This message comes from NPR
Sergey Brin
The Bold way to steady growth
People often think annuities are too conservative
Too complex or only for retirees
But annuities can be a smart way to
Two-head marquetry
And earn guaranteed returns
Game Bridge aims to change the game
By offering simplified annuity
Please in a Sleek digital experience
That replaces fine print in
And phone tag
With clear conditions
Ana direct loafy model
Learn more at game Bridge.
5 / NPR
Cambridge
It's not available in Austin
All right for the neck
Tweak Nic
I want to eat
Introduce you to Lieutenant
Danny Roman
Pop
Hostage negotiator for the Chicago Police Department
I'm just kidding
Just tell me the plot of The Negotiator how was it
I Saw the Light
But anyway
Our actual final two
Is about
Baseball
It is also probably or most country
Yes Major League Baseball knows that it's games are a little too long
And so they've been trying their own tweaks
To speed up the game
Little things like
Limiting the number of warmup pitches making the commercial breaks between
Queen Innings shorter
That's all fine but if they
Really wanted to Speed the game up
They would be a little more serious about listening to tweet
Proposed by this man
My name is Steven Brams I'm a professor of politics at New York University
You like baseball
I'm a fan
But not a rabid fan
Nope not one who's willing to blindly follow all the rules
Expose
No I suppose some reforms
Steve and some colleagues have proposed
What is now known as
The catch up
Yeah like guy you want ketchup or mustard on that guy that's not that kind
This is the kind where if you are losing
You would like to catch
Steve
Can you give us
The simplest explanation of the catch-up rule
In baseball at works as follows that if you're the team ahead in an inning and you're at bat
Then you get
Only two outs rather than 3 oz
In that inning
In other words when you are ahead
You get fewer chances
The score your opponent who is losing
Get more
Steve and a colleague
Tested this out
Using historic baseball
We looked at the
100000 games
We went back
Spectra 1967
50 years
And we analyzed
Each pitch
Are over a hundred thousand games and asked if the ketchup bro I've been in place
How would things have changed
As an impatient baseball fan
How much
Shorter with these games have been the average game which now last 3 hours and 5 minutes
Would be caught by 24 minutes OU cutting almost a half an hour from the game and that's one of the biggest
The game yes
And not only where the games
Shorter
They were way more competitive
Which Steve thinks would probably help baseball with its de
Declining a
So
How
Have
Fans
Reacted
Teeny tiny toys
To America's past
Well critically I would say
Let's just say there have been a lot of anger
But Steve is not here to win
A popularity
In fact
He tells us
He's also got a version of the catch up rule
4 Americas
Actual favorite sport
Football
In the NFL we would
Give the winning team only $3 rather than $4 to make a first down
Steve you were like you're blowing up every single sport
Oh yeah we have an idea for basketball that we would
Instead of giving the team ahead 24 seconds to shoot leave the money
18 seconds at the end of a game
Oh my God
You are a true iconoclast
Well
We'll see what happens
We don't want to hold you any longer thank you so much for coming in
Yeah thank you professor
And don't go to any baseball games anytime soon
You might get
Is there a tweak that you would like to see
Be in the world you can email it to us we are Planet Money at
TR.
We're also at Planet Money on the Twitter's and insta so you're so happy
Alex goldmark is are supervising producer writer set
Is our chief episode tweaker
I'm Kenny Malone and I'm McFadden thanks for listening
And we have one more extra special guest
Joining us in the studio today
You want introduce yourself
It's me
Danny Roman
Lieutenant Danny Roman from The Negotiator
In the flesh
And you apparently have a tweak for us today
Great what are you got
Never say no to a hostage
It's in the manual
Illuminate
The only option that leaves
Deschutes
Understand
It sort of makes sense I mean I don't
I don't know that technically
Click qualifies as like a
Will you kiss me
Vice no offense meant
Interview
That's really
Too bad
Is Danny Roman was just