If you have a car that you want to Rally people around
It helps to have an MS
A bad guy
You promise you will fight
Tom and Jerry
Batman the Joker
Politicians
Notice and basically every politician who's ever run for office
Pit himself against
The same
I will not back down
We're going to set up a
War room we're going to focus intensively that is outdoor and Barraco
Declaring war
On the one thing that they
George Bush
Hillary Clinton and Donald Trump
Can all agree
Let's
Cut the red
Taped to the bureaucracy
No red tape the red tape red
Tape regulations
Anime accused of all kinds of crimes
Jobs death
Savannah vacation
The demise of
Small business and this battle the promised
Defeat red tape once and for all
It was a big part of Donald Trump's kids
These ridiculous
Rules and regulations
Stop making a pause
Possible for you to come pick
So we're going to take that off
And less than 12 months after Trump
Took office
Declared Victory against
Red tape
Never-ending growth of red tape in America is come
To a sudden
Screeching and beautiful Hall
Beautifulhalo
And then he said
We are just getting
At this press conference
Trump stood in front of to mounds of papers which were surrounded by 8 literal band of red tape
He pointed at one stack of papers that's
Way taller than the other over
A tall tale
Him so this is what we have now
This stack he said it is all of America's
Current regulation 185000 page
Gauges 7.3
The other stack. Shorter maybe like
1 foot high
This is where we were in 1960
This mini stack is he said
All the regulations that existed
In 1960
Wayfair
I'm your twenties house
And then he made a promise
That when he's finished cutting regulations
We will be less than where we were in nineteen
And then with a giant pair of scissors in his hands
That is the speech we found an actual red tape being cut
To get back to that 1960 stack of paper
It would mean
Dumping
T5000 pages of rules in the recycle
Reducing the current amount of rules
I-94
Percent
Fighting regulation
Takes more than a big
Pair of scissors
I mean adding regulations can take
Months sometimes years and actually getting rid of a rule it can mean the same long and tedious process
In River
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm caring definition.
Maxwell's market today on the show
We go into the battle
How to find out has Trump at last defeated the photo that has tumbled every president
To answer that question we will take you to a vending machine on the front lines of
Environmental regulation
We will
Discover the most important number no one's ever heard of and we'll introduce you to America's most powerful
Rule taming weapon
Weapon that can only be wielded
If many stars magically align state did very recently and we behold it
Power
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Which come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solution
It support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information
Is available at aecf. Org
We called in an egg
Expert to help us understand how we got all this regulation
Quickly took an unexpectedly person
Turn Denver find yourself
In front of the fridge
Just kind of seeing what's in there
Right
Maybe last night I don't want to
Talk about it sure it happens to all of us
This is Bridget dooling she's a professor at George Washing
Hampton University
But if maybe before you open the fridge you said am I actually hungry
You know you might have realized that perhaps you were thirsty
Or maybe you're just bored
Or you know maybe something else is on your mind
There is a whole agency tasked with curbing reggae
It's called the office of information and Regulatory Affairs Roi
Bridget work there under President Bush
And Obama and under President Trump
I like to think of Ira as
The nun judgy friend
Stand in front of the fridge and
When the EPA or the
FDA the USDA
Come looking for a snack
Oh Ira is there
Simply asking
What are you doing their government what's the problem that you're trying
Do you really need to put 1154 rules on Goat Farmers is a real
Number if you're saved
The EPA and you want to make a regulation you have to justify yourself to Ira
Tell them what problem you're solving
And proved that the benefits outweigh the costs
13 stair
He wanted to rule you have to just
And if you want to remove a rule
You also have to justify that
Which is a big part of white
Regulation
Just take soda
Damn long
Wichita
Usually takes so damn long because there is a very powerful weapon
And the Congress
Can use to sidestep the long slog and just
3 2 1 cut the red tape
The regulatory weapon of which we
We speak
Congressional
Review act or the
Cra
Yeah she did a whole episode on this
CRA was created in 1996 basically
Stop lame duck presidents
I'm going on a last-minute regulations free on their way out to
It's been described as soon as Cinderella rushing home after the ball
You know these projects
It's their last chance
To get them done
We call it the midnight regulations. President Obama he issued somewhere around a hundred
And 40 midnight regulation
This way out
Which by the way to a hundred
This is where the Congressional review
The CRA
Congress undo any regulation issued in the previous
60 legislative days like that
Except
The president can just veto it
You can undo the undo if he wants to
Which is why
Why the magical power of the CRA is only really used
Once in a political Blue Moon
You got to have a party change in the White House and you've got to have a congress
That is opposed to the prior
Administration's rule in the only time that happens is
Say for instance
Will be
The 45th
And with that stars were aligning
For the Congressional review Act
To be used
Before this the CRA only been used
Once
Just once
Is 2001
To strike down of all things a new rule about organized
So if your office
The stairs suck you can blame the CRA
But because it had only ever been used one time
You know we didn't we didn't really know what to expect
As soon as Trump
Got into office
Congress took those
Big scissors and they started cutting
Down with State funding for abortion providers recording work injuries
And the resource management
Planning Rule and 11 others
By the time the regulation Carnage
Complete
Congress used the CRA
To kill 14 rules
Just a few months into his term courtesy of the CRA Trump was off to a guy
Until
May 15th
When the Clock Struck
60 legislative days
And the CRA
Turned into a pub
Soap from here on out pools would have to be killed
The hard way
Good old-fashioned months and years long
Deregulation
Trump talked a big game about this to
On the campaign Trail even promised a very specific plan for cutting red
To shrink the government in general
I will work with Congress to require that for every 1 new regulation
Two old regulations must
Be immediately Eliminator
1 in
2 out
This sounds like something you would make up on the campaign Trail just like nice-sounding Words pulled out of a hat
But it's a real policy other countries do this
The UK has a version of it Canada adopted a few years ago and just days after Trump took office
So did ameri
One of the first things that Trump did as president
What sign is name on Executive Order 137
N71
I did right there
In the federal book of rules on page 9000
Running
Two out also the money has to break even on new
And old radio
So it has to
Federal government is giving vcigo they are really doing
We set a target of adding zero new regulatory cost
Onto the America
Can economy
Today I'm proud to announce that we beat our goal
BioLife
Trump has bragged about this kind of thing a few times over
The government actually measures that they now put out a yearly report card up out there.
Congress and different people have parsed the report different ways but everyone we ask said yes
Trump is holding up his promise
At least two old rules
Are going out for every new one
Regulations by the numbers are going
It might not keep going at that same page
Trump started with the easiest thing
To deregulate
We talked with Wayne Crews he studies rules at the competitive Enterprise Institute the libertarian Think Tank
You said there are
Too many rules
The low-hanging fruit
In terms of the two for one
And if you're still recording this is fine but the low-hanging fruit is probably being
And for there to be a real regulatory streamlining that goes beyond that you're going to have to have
Congressional a
Big deer
Can takes Congress pass
Laws that sweep away dozens
Hundreds or thousands of rules
The time the real impact so far of trump and his two-for-one policy when says
Is on future regulation
Agencies
Are thinking twice before they issue new rules now
So we get
Fewer new rules
One thing he has certainly
Effectively done
Put a freeze on you
Major regulation
You just simply not seeing a lot of new heavy duty regulation
Come down the pipeline and Trump
Destruction that's quite significant
In fact Bridget dueling the former regulator that we talked to earlier she studied the pace of new regulations under Trump
And she found that in the first year and a half
At the Trump
The amount of new regulation
Is down 70%
Compared to Obama
70%
And compared to Bush he's down 60
6%
This is a big
Change Trump is
Fundamentally changing the pay
But
Bridget points out that stopping the flow of new regulations
Does not do anything to end
Do the stock
Of old ones
Tens of thousands of rules are piled up over decades
And even with a two-for-one policy taking away old regulations
That's barely making a
In every aspect of your car
It's probably somehow captured by regulation
Whether it's
The food you eat for breakfast the rules around the way work is conducted in your workplace all of that is subject to Marriott
Add federal regulations that have grown up
Overtime
So something like a two-for-one
That's her chips away at 1 or 2
Is never going to reach the level of deregulatory activity that the President says he wants to achieve
If I going back to 19
But maybe accomplishing the goal of deregulation getting the big hand
Have government out of the way
It can be done without
Actually having to repeal regulations by just looking for
Smaller waist
The kind of tweaked the road
Very deep in those stacks of pages of rules
If you can find just the right line to
To change in just the right time anyway
You can have a pretty big impact
I'm at 1 I am going to give up the chair to Jason beaubien NPR's Global help desk
Who picks up the story hey Jason
Thanks Alex
Alright I'm going to head out here and let you
To take it all right
Hey Karen hey Jason
The understand what the Trump Administration is doing here
We have to first
Step back and look at what the Obama Administration
Getting creative with regulations to push through it
Environmental agenda
And it all has to do with
The most important number no one's ever heard of
He's a professor at the University of Chicago
And that mysterious number that no one's ever heard of
Is the social cost of
Carbon
The social
Cost of carbon are the monetized damages
From the release of an additional ton of CO2
Basically
How much does 1 ton of carbon dioxide
Released into the air
Buy anything from
Cars at Power Plant
How much will that one ton of carbon dioxide cost the world
Because
Apologies for stating the obvious here but
Carbon dioxide released into the atmosphere of course
Stays up there for deca
Attaching Heat global warming
It could affect
Agricultural production in Bangladesh worker productivity in Texas or life expectancy in Egypt
CO2 emissions
Lots of impacts on Lots
Stop Obama really wanted to do something about global warming
So he tried to get Congress to
To pass laws
But Congress said no we're not into that so he turned
2 regulation
Which meant
He then have to justify that the
The benefit of reducing emissions
Be greater than the cost
To say,
To do that
You have to be able to calculate how much
Damaged
Carbon dioxide
Which brings us back
Back to the social coffee
Carbon
The dollar value
On the damage
One ton of
Michael and his colleagues job was to calculate that value
Which is very very
They were plugging numbers into economic models that would just make your heads
That looks like one of them is what is the proper assume disc
Tribution for the equilibrium climate sensitivity parameter and a house that
Nerdy definitely nerdy
But all of this is related to real world things
Like what is the impact of this pollution on people's health
Open crops
An economic productivity
If you have to project that
Around the world
Way out
Indian Michael and his colleagues made of formula
Based on a mountain of economic research
And Wallah they had their number
$42
That number is like the
Keep
In
The ability of the US government
To pursue regulations
Dad
Limit CO2 emission
And they started with the importance
Your snack
So the first rule if I remember correctly
Was not the most glamorous rule
It was an energy efficiency
Rule for finding the
The President Obama had found his
Creative way to do what he couldn't do by way of legislation
But those
To live by the sword Inc if I remember correctly they die
By the sword
Yeah
And anything one president can do with a struggling Pan the next president can undo
With a bat or big scissors
Sure enough people came in and they said about undoing a bunch of environmental rules one by one
The slow laborious way
But they also found
Creative way
The weekend almost
All climate regulation
At once
It was the Trump Administration has done
Is founded Isles
Honda has the assumptions
That would most easily
I reduce the number
Grab those two dials turn.
Cracking all the way down
And then end up with
Very low estimates of the social cost of carbon
They took the social cost of carbon that $42 per ton
And a slash
Twas the last
$1
There are
To dial
That they Crank 2
First
Rather than assume that
Us CO2 emission
Have a global impact
They decided to take an America First approach
Can only count the domestic impact
About Peluche
Second they placed a very low value on the future damage
Apps that could occur from
So now if you want to cut down on pollution
Cars
You do the analysis
On the one side there's the cost of the car,
Making a bunch of change
And under Obama you could say that that cost is
It's worth it because
There's $42 of damage for each ton of pollution
But now under Trump
The damage is just a dollar
Almost nothing
The United States government is known as
Extraordinary outlier
In its valuation of the damages of an additional ton of Steel
I'm unaware of any other
Government or researcher who has
Concluded the
$1
Is the right number
So now if you
If you want to propose making sweeping admissions changes
Best new cars
It's really hard to justify anymore
And of course
The atmosphere doesn't care what number any
Wooden plugs into a
Okay we've gone through a lot of ways that Trump is changing regulations worth the little recap
Absolutely
All right
The Trump Administration has definitely stemmed the tide of
New regulation
But getting rid of that
6 foot stack all those rules that were made in the past
That still stands tall
They're not on Pace to get to Trump School of nineteen
60 levels not even close
But they are chipping away at rules
Through the normal TDS channels and looking for other ways
Peking duck carbon number
This stuff is so complicated we only got to a small fraction
Of what we wanted to
So
Obviously
We decided that we would just
Have to cram everything that we couldn't get to
NAC
We protect you right after the credits
The world premiere of
Planet Money Original Song
Stand by for
The Ender egg
As we know it
Support also comes from fidelity
As a Fidelity wealth manager
You get a dedicated advisor
To help grow and
Protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes
And make clear recommendation
Things for your full fight
Learn more at fidelity.
Comsol
Fidelity brokerage services
LLC
Today show with Bruce by Darian Woods
Special thanks to senator Pat
Toomey's office Susan Dudley for helping us understand complicated record
Laura Jones Phil wallach's amouri and Michael J Rush
Coupon for our song
Perform for your nerdy listening pleasure by
Juice cleanse
You can hear more of their music at juice cleanse. Bandcamp.com
Dirty lyrics by Karen Lori and Shane McKeon
Will post
The song and lyrics
Our website also on our social media we are at Planet Money on Instagram Facebook Twitter
Instagram I'm Karen Duffin I'm Jason beaubien
Thanks for listen
That's cool portable clean energy rule methane and waste prevention Rule and a
Arbitration rule
Scientific transparency corporate average fuel economy bureaucratic engine
Pneumatic ride safely shave and there's no escape and out these Rags as we know of
Primitively furthering fair housing rule No More Heroes Marcus kind gets received your attic in German
Had a great favorite shape and there's no escape the