This message comes from NPR sponsors snowflake
The only data warehouse built for the cloud
Unlock deep Data Insights with the instantly scalable Cloud build data warehouse
Start your journey towards data-driven decision
It's snowflake. Com NPR
Hey before we start we wanted to ask you
A favor we want to know more about
You
Listen to Planet Money
We got a survey going now it's an NPR.
Planet Money
Survey
It's about what you like about the show
What you want
Change you'll be asked to list the names of the hosts I'm Roberts
Robert
Smith
And you can tell people you think of me
It only take about 10 minutes and I'll help us out a lot
Npr.org
Splash Planet Money survey
Just around the corner from our office is a weird New York City landmark
The national
Debt clock
And I digital numerals always changing
Is the current
National debt of the United States of America
To the dollar
It's been up for almost 30 years the location keeps changing is very skyscrapers go up
But it's always in the streets around Times Square and it is always Counting
As of today the US national debt
Is
Prepare yourself for a big number
20 trillion
Million
And change
Dollars
And the number is
Is rising
In fact the tax plan signed into law late last year
Is expected to cost
About a trillion dollars over the next decade
That's according to the nonpartisan joint committee on taxation
Other analysts put the cost at
Twice
That one always.
More deficits
What that means
We're going to need a bigger billboard
And a bigger understanding of what day it is
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I Am Robert Smith today on the show we are going back in time to tell the history of
Cat in America
There's some Alexander Hamilton of course a story about how Congress created the scariest stupidest way to
Amanda Georgette and that one time the single time our country had a resolution to pay off all the
And 16 by the way it's episode Richmond VA in 2011
I reported it with that again
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Did you come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities to help ensure a brighter future for America's Choice
More information is available at aecf. Org
First up
Really basic question
What exactly is the national
Debt
It's kind of think of it as one
Think because it's actually a bunch of promise
Millions and millions of specific promises
The government has made
Two specific people
The government spends more than it takes in
Every year
That is called
Deficit of yearly deaths
And the government borrows the difference from International financier
People who know the government inside and out
People like this purse
My name is
L c Smith
And I am
And 3/4
I have an OLCC
A friend of mine and in fact she is your daughter
Yeah but that's not important right now what she is is a creditor of the US government
Listen to what she discovered in my drawer
United
State saving bonds
$50
Why did you let the government that money
To keep safe
Yeah that's actually right you did that used your money
Dubai things like maybe
A rivet on a fighter plane or something
I don't have it
The thing that holds the plane to
Her International financiers are so
You know it's funny even at 7 years old she's somehow and I can tell it is
She somehow managed to look at this thing the savings bond
And understand what is most fundamental about government debt
It's safe it's completely safe us has never gone back on it
Promise
She could get that $50 tomorrow with interest
If I let her
It's up to understand what the debt is you got to add up all the Elsa's of the world all the
Fireman funds
Central banks with lots and lots of treasury bills or savings bonds
In their drawers and even if you don't have the bond in your drawer
Are you have effectively lent the money to the government somewhere
Maybe it's your checking account
Savings account
That guaranteed interest that you got
Probably back by treasury bonds
A government that
And we're always hearing about how
China holds over a trillion dollars of us bonds Japan
Many many governments around the world
And when you add up all those promises
Aldo's
Different people in institutions
The US government has said hey we're going to pay you back
That
Is the national debt
Today we're going to explain how we got into this mess
Where are the staircase
What happened when we tried to pay it off
Who came up with this whole
Debt ceiling idea the first place
That turned out
We've been fighting about the den
Something United States was born
Okay we're going to do some old-timey music here
Good day in February
Fare Thee Well
Okay we're back in Revolutionary War 2 pictures of you
Couldn't tell from the
Spot-on impression
This is what the first debate over the national debt
It support remember that the US debt
Wasn't something that just happen automatically
United States is very first few days made a conscious decision
To Habitat
Tissue response
Promise to pay it back
I spoke with Robert E Wright
Is a professor of political economy at Augustana College
In South Dakota
What really happened is we fought a long and bloody Revolution
Against the world's greatest superpower
And racked up
80 million dollars in debt
Doing so
Couldn't we said
Sorry folks it's a revolution
We're wiping out of the deck
We could have but thankfully we didn't
And we didn't because of a man named Alexander Hamilton
He was the Secretary of Treasury the very first one
The architect United States
Baystate fundamental choice
If we don't take responsibility for the day
All those farmers
Atlantis money and the soldiers we didn't pay in the French who went this money
The rest of the world won't trust us
They won't lend us money we won't be able to trade
Will be stop United States will be stuck living off whatever we grow here in our Farts
And back then
Grow that much we brought much of our consumables
You're the HBO series John Adams
Did a great job of depicting Hamilton's argument
The future prosperity
Destination brest chiefly in trade
Directions to lend us money
And how would you propose to establish International credit
First Atwood BC
Current national debt
The grace of the Dead
Progressive credit
Recommended
President
Adults
All the debts incurred by the individual
States
Through a National Bank
John Deere
Not if the states
Oconus money
Then the other nations will feel more included
The Hamilton
Crow that was fighting with Thomas Jefferson
Because Thomas Jefferson had a very
He felt
The debt
With extremely
Dangerous
When you hear the speech that Jefferson gave at least the
HBO series game
It's a speech I feel like with very little change could be given
States are indebted to a central Authority
Increases the power of the central government exactly
I fear a revolution would have been in vain if Virginia Farmer's to be held in Hall to a New York Stock Chopper
Who in turn doesn't talk to a London Banker
Opportunities for
Avarice
Adoption
Certainly prove irresistible
And this fight between
Northeast bankers and
The rest of the country this has been going on for
For 200
It's going on today
Now Hamilton won out initially
Play the United States
Accepted it's dead
Promise
But Professor Robert Wright says that most politicians of the time they felt much more like Jeffress
Okay fine Hamilton will pay off our old debt
Let's not make a habit out
So what the battle was really about was
How quickly to pay off the debt
Now whether to pay it off or not
And
I have to give full disclosure here I spoke with
Professor rights
And he told me that he gave his son a unique name he named his son
Alexander
Hamilton
Was
Right how come the other day he told me
Alexander Hamilton is right
Gets in his view of course Hamilton is Right forever
Wow so
For the first forty years or so of the
We lived
In Hamilton's worth
The nation headed day
Manageable
Banks and bankers in the Northeast florist we did trade with Europe and everybody trusted us
The country grew and
Pretty soon
UF that that issued by the US government
Wisin is one of the safest investments in the
This was Alexander Hamilton dream
Until
1 president dared to pay it off
Circular next chapter in The Amazing life story of the US debt January 8th 18
Can we put on character again
All the big political names in Washington DC have gathered to celebrate the President Andrew Jackson
It was the anniversary of his win at the Battle of New Orleans but
There was bigger news that night a senator stood up
He raised his glasses he said gentlemen
The national debt
Is
Paid
Hot sauce around the room
Find me the national debt was Zero
It was a big deal
Scottsdale Garden fix-up she writes about financial history any
He's the author of the book Hamilton's blessing
The extraordinary life of
In times of the national
This was another American accomplished
But the wheel actually paid off our national debt know the country never done that before
Andrew Jackson becomes president
The death had become sort of this routine thing and it actually
Follow the cycles that business textbooks tell you a government that should
Drink bad time
Hamster Wars like the War of 18
12 ordering economic slowdown the country borrowed basically borrowing against their future prosperity
And then sure enough when the hard times were over and
The economy was doing well the government would
Payback
The debt that it had borrowed
Always maintaining at least
Some level
Andrew Jackson
Did not
Like this normal
Routine
Trader jacks
Politics
Is very person
He hated not just
The federal that he hated dad
At all
That's HW brands
He's a professor at the University of Texas
Anybody biography of Andrew Jackson
Call his life and time
A toughest great story about jacks
Before he was president in the wild west of Tennessee
And he was quite the land Speculator you know he would often get paid and land and he was trading on these things
At one point he trades
Some land
For some debt passed on by somebody else
Well this debt goes bad
And Andrew Jackson's left holding the bag
You got this massive dad
Worthless paper note
And
This drove him nuts affect the guy did the deal with it went to jail
So when Jackson runs for president
He knows the enemy
Banks in the national debt
He called it the national
Curse and the voters just
Eat this up
Andrew Jackson had an actual plan to get rid of the dead but he also got
Very lucky
What he took officers around
58 million dollars of death
That the US government owed
And one way that you paid it off
There happen to be a huge real estate bubble going on
And rather than bailout the banks
It turned out that at the time that you owned a lot of land in the wilderness
They sold it at these
Slated bubble price
Which brought in
A lot of money which went
The paying off the debt
Injection was I don't give a credit ruthless on the budget and he blocked every spending Bill he could
Highway government buildings it was
Vito Vito V
After 6 years in office
He paid it all off it was all gone
But Jackson
Friendly faces technical problem that no other president has
We're faced either before or since
What do you do
When the government has more money than it needs
What do you do with the Surplus
No back then there's no income tax you couldn't just give everybody a refund there wasn't really a way to return money
And what he decide to do was to
Divided among the states according to population is the only time that's happened so Andrew Jackson gets rid of the debt
All of a sudden the countries running a surplus
And we all live economically happily-ever-after right
Not exactly
How long did the good times last at last exactly one year
Beautiful year
The State Banks apparently went a little crazy with the Surplus
They're printing massive amounts
A paper money
And that land bubble
I mean the one that helped jacks
Bounce about to get rid of the debt
The limbo went out of control
And then like all bubbles
It popped
It was a huge
Crash
And the
Beginning of the longest depression in the mirror
History lesson lasted six years before
Economy began
Grow Again
And we're not saying
Every time you pay off the debt you're instantly going to cause a massive
Depression
But there was a clear lesson here
No matter how much you hate the debt
Eliminating it does not guarantee that you're going to have
Good time
Even in the early eighteen-hundreds the economy was
Far too complex
And it turns out that having the debt come back was pretty useful for the United
There was after all a civil war to pay for and a bunch of other economic downturn
The 1900s were full of them
It look like it was no end to the amount of debt the country
Cricket Akon
But that's not the end of the story
Well that
After the break
Support also comes from Fidelity invest
As a Fidelity wealth
You get a dedicated advisor
To help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of tax
And make clear recommendations for your full Financial
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
Chapter 3
Politicians
Could not
Kill the debt
But they decided one maybe we can tame it
Is he dead in United States was not just getting bigger it was getting more
Wax
World War 1 Congress have to approve every little bit of borrowing
Susan Irving's with the government accountability office
I mean you know I want to borrow money to build
Answer pressure with gold
The Congress and they would
Literally approved
The form of the security
Purpose of the security
You know
What the duration was going to be what the interest rate was going to be
So this could take all day long you could say Bridges
Is post offices
A canal through Panama
If you look at the early Appropriations Act
They're completely Aramark
I'm looking early Appropriations act so much for suing the horses for the Department of EX
Really
Very detailed control
It is so hard to imagine just
Congress or not
Finance professional sitting there and every single thing the government wants to buy they have to decide
How much data issue what the interest rate would be will it be a five-year Bond at 3.8% or
10 year bond at 4 point
2%
So hard to imagine
Is that what actually shocking is that for over a century they were able to do that they're able to keep it together
But by World War 1 it was just
Too much stuff it was too complex
You think about
The number of decisions that go on during the war you know suddenly if they're going to have to approve every single one
You're coming you're not once a year
Not once every two years
You're coming instead of constantly oh now we need to borrow
Up to so much to build up more tank
You know you think really
At some point
Jeff sheer volume of transactions overwhelmed
And begins to drive out the ability to do so thoughtful discussions about big policy
And Congress loves do thoughtful discussions of big policy so
They delicate
They delegated authority they told the treasury Department in 1970
Very sad
After that that you know
Why don't you all figure out how much borrowing mean
And how you're going to do
But Congress doesn't just
Give the executive branch
Lots and lots of power they do not
Now so they say okay
We're going to give you this job
Of figuring out what bonds
What the ratio
What interest rate and all that stuff
We're not letting you go now
We can have a ceiling
You can only borrow up to this
Amount
An upper lip
And if you need to do more if you need to borrow more money
Come back and see us and we'll decide
Whether or not to raise
But there's something crucial to understand here
Nothing gets
Bought
By the federal government
Unless Congress says
I mean in the Constitution the power of the purse rest
With Congress
So the debt limit doesn't actually limit the spending that would be unconstitutional to limit the spending if they say
Safety check
Yeah I think it is his big game of
Mother may I
Yeah that old kids
Congress has the treasure
You Are by Pink
Treasury looks and it brings up the debt limit
And the treasury Department have to come back to Congress and say
Mother may I
Buy a tank and raise the debt limit
Encounters with boats and says
Yes you may
What's so ridiculous is
All the treasury is asking approval.
To do is
Spend the money that Congress has told them
Words
Congress
Says go spend this money and then acts all huffy
But spending the money Congress approved
So maddening
And it's something that pretty much no other country
Ghost
They don't go through this whole rigmarole
Simply approve spending and
Implication the borrowing is just
Implicitly
Approved as well
But
In part that's because there isn't the separation between the executive
Like the treasury Department and the legislative branch
The Congress
The debt-ceiling turns out to be not so much something to slow the debt
It's a sign of good old American distrust
It's a way for one branch to basically give the hard work to somebody else
I don't really care
So in a sense the debt-ceiling was acid
Congress did not have to spend all of its time worrying about
Bond issues indurations and interest rates use this new freedom to come up with
The sort of economy we see today all these efficient
Forms of issuing various lengths
The dad and using the market to determine
The interest rate that is paid on the bond
All these things
Basically make it easier for the government and cheaper for the government to get money
But the debt ceiling
Did not do its fundamental Mission it did not in any way
Pain the growth
International
Every year
More than once a year the treasury Department has come to Congress
Instead
Mother may I
Increase the debt ceiling so that I can borrow the money to buy the things you already told me to buy
And Congress would say
Yes you may
And then the debt goes up
Depression
World War
And then starting about 50 years ago
The debt explodes
Happened is another word for a psycho
The debt goes up during bad times and goes down is
Paid off during Good Times
Just Administration after Administration Democratic Republican after Democrat after Republican
The debt
Just gets bigger and bigger during good times and drink.
You would love to hear what you think
Send it to email Planet Money at NPR. Org or we're on Twitter and Facebook and Instagram usual places
If you're looking for something to listen to right now may we recommend our new show it called
The indicator from Planet Money on the news 5 days a week Today Show is about to run
Why the price of eggs and thousands of people to the streets to protest
That the indicator from Planet Money you can find it wherever you find podcast if I can find it for you about this podcast I'm rubber
Thanks for listening