Hi my name is Sarah Gonzales and I'm a reporter with NPR Planet Money
Funny podcast
Okay or public radio
You guys are really good at getting people to donate money to you have a bucket full of cash right now
What is your name for my name is Christopher Meloni AKB boykova
Yes we're going to Bronx New York
Austin Public Radio we spent a lot of time trying to make really complicated things
Easy to understand also entertaining we do a lot of research
We do a lot of editing and fact-checking
But we like to have fun
So give us your
Tips like what are the tricks are getting people to donate money to you
Broth break dancers Whitney music
Entertain them
If they walk away smiling
You know they're going to give you a tip
If not it's okay
Play some music and then
Like you're funny right like you have to be funny
Florida Lottery
Core strength is all out of hands
And then okay I'm glad that that is not part of my job
Please Deport Planet money so that I don't have to work on my core strength
By donating to your local NPR station at donate. Npr.org
Planet Money
That's donate. Npr.org
Splash Planet Money
Can you get
Hey before we get started this episode is about Amazon and we should note that Amazon is one of NPR's many financials
3 2 1
Brian see where we are right now
Where in Long Island City in Queens just got off the subway
And we're here because Amazon just announced that they are going to build a brand new headquarters quarters
Quarters because he can't have 3 headquarters fair enough
Either way this is a very big deal
Hundreds of communities across the country competed for this
Amazon's going to be bringing 25000 jobs to Queens and billions of dollars in
It's right here got it they want
But almost immediately the reaction
And here was like no
No we don't want to win we don't want this
There have been protests across the city
People saying things like Amazon is going to force all the mom and pop shops out of business
They're going to drive rents up so people will be displaced
The subway is going to get even more crowded
But the thing that really upset people is that the state and the city agreed to give Amazon
1.2 billion dollars in tax breaks over 10 years
To come here
More like 500 million in cash to help build
The new quarters
So it looks like a massive subsidy
For massive company very controversial and we even had this fight in our own office
Some of us think the potential pain is worth it for 25000
And some of us were like no no New York got a bad deal from a corporate bully
And this argument was really intense and I couldn't stop thinking about it
I think it was actually at Hardin argument about capitalism about weather what's good for business
Really is good for everyone
Which for a long time
What's on the thing we were talking about
But the fact is no one in our office actually lives in Long Island
Us we don't know if people out here or going to be
Be thrilled or horrify
I thought you and I looked at each other at this argument was close
Singer like
But we got to go out there
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm your wealth and brynhurst on the move
We're spending the show walking around a neighborhood that is at the heart of a really Fierce National debate Economist and politicians have been
Been talking about this a lot
Is business investment in the community
Worth some of the drawbacks
The tax breaks
The gentrification
The loss of a neighborhood character
Today we're going to let the people who live and work in this neighborhood do the talk
What are you doing
Hard
Anecdotal
Research
Support also comes from fidelity
As a Fidelity wealth
You get a dedicated advisor
To help grow amp
Protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of tax
And make clear recommendations
Thanks for your full fight
Learn more at
Fidelity
Tom
Fidelity brokerage services
LLC
By the way before we get started there is one swearing electrician
In this episode
Okay so we went out to Long Island City and we walked around all day starting in the more
That is the sound of Long Island City like they are just
Constantly putting up buildings out here
740 Towers in like a last 10 years and it sounds like this all the time
Utica Silvia Tower
It looks like they're going to stop at about 4 but I don't know
But that poor story
Yeah I mean it's like
It's like they put on a busy man show like rich
Richard scarry's busy City like literally those guys are moving ladder someone setting a hammer
Ace crane
It's like a child
View of what a construct
Insight would be like
For a lot of years this neighborhood was mostly industrial is a lot of factories and warehouses
17 years ago the city change the zoning laws so now you can build other stuff including these big tall
Condo Towers
We are heading down 44th drive to the East River because that's where I was on
Restart
Grabbing people in the street
1 guys getting out of a white van by a construction site he's got black bandana
Tinted glasses
His name is Jeff San Pedro
Do you live in Long Island City
I know I don't but I work here
You work here and you work in
I'm an electrician
Okay
So this seems like a good neighborhood to be an Electra
Yes it does
Start building up all over the place in Long Island City
And I like.
Have you heard about Amazon coming to Long Island City
Yes I have heard that
What do you think
I love
I really do I think it's great that Amazon's yet because it's going to bring more more jobs here
I mean 20 years ago
You don't work with self 4020 is good it was that much work now you always special
Was going to come to Long Island City to work
Right now Long Island City is a hotspot
If you look on old
These corners
Varicella crane
Praying praying pois
Everywhere
Are you worried that there could be any downside to Amazon
Gentrification
Y'all really wanna go there
I mean a lot of people are worried about
I think people are just dumb
I know they have phobias
Sub certain things
Since
Like
People scared of change
Oh yeah
They're scared of change
But you know what changes good if it puts money in your pocket why not
Your capitalist
No I mean opportunist
Okay capless I don't have enough money to be capitalist
You gotta have money to make money
How to rich person using you make a good living but you're not a rich person you don't have to call
But you don't have any of that knee-jerk like all this is busy bad for work
Do people know I have my pain so give me wrong
57 I got my pain
But up
Like I said you know what
You work hard
Everyday get up for 45
Why when we get comes I party hard so I don't hear from nobody
I'm sorry but that's the way it is
He was like a walking
Springsteen song I Know I Know upper blue collar I don't think Springsteen could have written that better
Alright let's talk about what we heard Jeff say there
He said to him
Jobs are the most important
And Amazon is bringing
25000 jobs
Now those jobs we should pay on average are expected to pay more than $150,000 a year
So
People are going to be spending money in this neighborhood getting lunch going to the grocery store go to the pharmacy
Yeah and like I said there will be other jobs to wiring buildings delivering meals
Fixing the elevator
All the things that Amazon will basically pay people who don't work at Amazon to do
I'm already calls the local multiplier
He's in a bunch of research and he's found that when a high-tech company like Amazon Comes To Town
It creates one job and five other jobs in the same city
Papa
That's over the span of 10 years
So you went ahead to talk to more
People and I kind of just rattled around the street like looking at things and I just
Love Long Island City like people actually do stuff here they build things and they repair things and it's all hidden inside these
He's like dingy looking garages
Just look in the window of this completely run down red garage door that has a
View glass paint left
Siri tell me what you see in there
Run-down garage door
Whoa whoa whoa that's like the offense
The car from an 80s movie those are all old Ferraris
Hundreds of thousands of dollars
Yep I'm not really a car guy but
Try to open the door
Hell no
These cool hands dirty businesses like the car repair shops
They will probably get replacement Amazon
They're not going to survive
Yeah that's going to be a salsa
And we were standing there in the street talking about this and this woman overheard us and she walked up to us and you basically
I grabbed the microphone I was like I have something to say about
My turns before you know it on Vernon Boulevard instead of mom and pop stores
You going to find the gap
Her name was Roberta Burger
She's a Potter she works an art studio here
She says
That's a lot of artists Studios
That were in Brooklyn that are now in Long Island City and they see it happening
To them yet again
And yeah classic artist move in
Giant corporations like a wheel of artist we want a piece of the action
Have your neighborhood
After we were talking to Roberto we got disoriented for a second
I'm trying to get my bearings here
What street is that can you read that
That is Hunter Street
Alright so so
What's going to happen if
This time 10
I need you to talk about your mouthful giving that you work on the radio please
So well you chewed we walked toward the water toward the East River where Amazon's going to be
And there's just not a lot happening up here
There's nothing happening
One guy smoking a cigarette
Couple people walking
And at this point we're just a couple steps away from the East River
There's a boat here
Like someone just pulled up their boat and left it on the war
I'm going to cross the river you can see the UN building Midtown Manhattan
We couldn't go any further without getting really wet so we turned around
Right behind this is one of the buildings that people are most worked up about and legitimately
It's a building owned by the
Board of Education
And it had originally been slated to be turned into
High-rises
Of which 1000 Apartments would be for affordable housing
But that is not happening
Amazon is taking that spay
This is not a fancy building
Like it's about six stories
Stall and it's
It's an entire block
And it's as Bland as could be and I don't think anyone ever would have talked about it if Amazon hadn't showed up
It's pale yellow
And there's
I mean there's a lot of air conditioners
Why does the Board of Ed need a loading dock
Let's go ask
Hi I'm just truck with just trying to figure out
We're doing a story about the new Amazon headquarters
Okay right now
You can't talk to no pressure
You know let's talk to the Press right now
Okay. Are you at least want to tell me what what's in that this building
This is the Board of Education open
Why do you guys have a loading dock at the Board of Education
I'm going to go away
I'm going away
I think at least half of the outrage over Amazon coming here
Is about housing
People are worried that this is going to become a neighborhood where
Only rich people can afford to live
And if they do, they're going to be living right next to America's largest
Public housing project
Let's go. Let's go find the Queensbridge houses
It was about a 10-minute walk away
It doesn't seem
Particularly close
It's not I mean that's the funny thing is people have been making a really big deal about Queensbridge
And yet
Get 6600 people live here
What kind of looking at a huge field of 6 story building
I called shut it together an odd angle surrounded by little parks
It's been here for 79 years
The median household income here is under $16,000
So there are some very poor people living here
Sweet way for the first guy we saw all right there underneath the Queensboro Bridge and we asked him what do you think
I really don't think it's a problem
You don't think it's a problem
You know they can really
We can help the community you known
What jobs and everything like that
Sylvia Browne is a nurse who grew up here everybody's afraid of change you know
Part of this reaction to Amazon people being like
I just don't want something new coming down the pike
I think so
My mother feels the same way about it she kind of has that same type of fear I don't know I don't like it and you know
Three things the way it is they not they trying to get us out of here and stuff like that you know so I don't know
Is any of the fear real or is most of the fear just like
Chainsaw
We all know that
I think it's
A real Fair
Really
That's a real Fair people are afraid that the city might tear down
The Queensboro
Housing Development
Absolutely
Why aren't you afraid of that
I am
Is it fair to me to absolutely I'm not sitting here saying all day I'm not worried but I am
But you're smiling and also saying that you think Amazon coming here is a good thing
Change is always good
Keeping a big company like Amazon cares about a place like Queensbridge
I wouldn't say
Per say they care about
Queensbridge
I just think they
Is it busy
I'm saying whoever wants
To work level needs
Jobs you go out there and get it I don't think they supposed to say what we're going to put this here cuz we care about you know
This is not a Community Development
This is exactly what everyone is fighting about
Some people want Amazon held to specific standards like
They have to hire people from this local community
They have to make investments
It's in the local community
And in fact Amazon has agreed to collaborate with New York City
To build a school down
And other people to like that is not their job which is basically my position Amazon is a business it's supposed to deliver
Packages show me movies
It's the government's job
To build schools by taxing Amazon
So we walked around Queensryche for a while talking to
People
Lacey Gibbs who's retired had some very specific advice for the people who are complaining about Anna
Get yourself together to meet the criteria to have a job at Amazon
I kind of stood up a little straighter when she was talking to me and she seemed really annoyed
Like by the negative
They take the rumor about the housing
Being sold off
You're rolling your eyes
Yeah
It's not together and if they self
The apartments
Be ready to buy it
The city is not dissolving the project
By the way that's a rumor is not a plan
And then Lacey's friend came by and she called him over I asked him to spell his name
Hollis
Jack
Json
Jr. Hollis Jackson Jr he felt he had got himself together and it hadn't worked do you know anyone here
It was a college degree who is looking for a job
Yammy Kansas community college degree in business management
He's 56 years old
And he says he's watched
Businesses especially in the past couple of years hotels
Come out to Long Island City and then just
Ignore all of these local residents who want work
First of all the offering of
The jobs
Need to come out
Oh you mean the hotels don't come out to clean fridge and I put up signs a now hiring
That hasn't happened with them
That hasn't happened I don't believe that that's going to happen with Amazon
What do they need to come to you when should you get out there
Dot-dot-dot knock on my door
I have a job for you
Of course not it doesn't work that way
But it should be one hand washes
The other I need employment
You need a customer
Hire me
But I can be a customer of
Your company
To be able to pay for that could be able to
The argument he's making is basically the tiniest possible version of an
An economy but of course Amazon doesn't need to hire Hollis they don't
Need his business either
They already have everybody else's
Okay
So what did we learn today
Well
The results of our hard anecdotal research RN
And basically
Some people are pretty and Amazon moving into the neighborhood
They talked a lot about you
He did and even the people who thought they might be negatively affected like their rent might go up Stacy
Pretty resume
Yes Potter was like, Potter is part of my job to get displaced and Sylveon Sylveon the nurse who said his
Mom is worried about the project being torn down
He said he doesn't think it's really going to happen but if it does
He will find another place to live
Yep he was pretty realistic about that we did hear a lot of realism in this neighborhood
Today which made me think
Amazon coming here
Feels like a good thing for New York or at the very least for this neighbor
Long Island City
I feel like the anxieties about capitalism as
System
We're just
Lot less acute
Here on the ground and they were in the officer that we're reading online or whatever
And we can taking out on the mat and we just talked about that for a second
Like it's pretty
A billion plus dollars for all those jobs it's just not that much over 10 years in the state is picking up a lot of it
All those multiplier jobs like that feels real
I think the city just gets way more money
But they can spend on whatever they want
And it seems like a lot of New York
Seems to agree I was looking at a poll on my phone
New Yorkers by a margin of two-to-one are happy about Amazon coming here
Hard anecdotal research confirm by quick plant that cell phone
But but we need to be fair
There is a group of people that we didn't hear from today we just didn't meet any of them
And these are the critics that the folks who are fiercely opposed to this
They exist
They've held marches and rallies
At one point it was raining and we stopped into a bar to get dry
On the TV news there was an anti Amazon
Has kind of Hazard cuz we were sitting
This bar and we were
Basically the only ones there I think there's one other couple I did not
Feel like that and we're watching on TV where people have taken over the Amazon bookstore in Manhattan
And meanwhile under the television
The bartender was just standing there going to wiping down the counter whatever just talking her ears off about how she couldn't wait for a
Amazon to get here she thinks it's going to be really good for business
All right
New York weather
But there is another reason everyone is freaking out and it doesn't have anything to do with Long Island City
Or New York
Or the quarters and it's a much
Bigger question
And that question is
Is Amazon good for America
I think we're going to have to do another show
Go visit America
Support for this podcast
In the following message come from the Annie E Casey
Sea Foundation
Developing Solutions
It support strong families and community
To help ensure a brighter future for America's chilled
More information is
Is available at aecf
. org
Amazon let us know Planet Money NPR. Org
Special things in this episode to the people at LaGuardia Community College in Long Island City
Especially professors of accounting Andrea Francis and rajendra vika thank you guys so much for your time
Thanks also to Bishop Mitchell Taylor the CEO of urban upbound
Sally home produce this episode are supervising producers Alex goldmeier
And our editor is
Brynhurst Ave
I'm Noel King thanks for listening
What's your name
Billy Bob
I meant where you from
Morocco
Have you heard Amazon is coming to Long Island City liquor store
So we can go inside of shopping stuff
No it's going to be like a big job center
Osaka work there
Give him my application Amazon