The other day I went to Madison Square Garden
Fornix
With reporter tea
Fruit there for a little research
Ice cold beer
Cold water
How much is a Bud Light
Bud Light $14
1 Bud Light
Long time listener is a planet money will know that I used to work at a stadium
All the time
People would complain about the prices
It's like 425 for Coke what is that Ramen it
And I'll be like
You don't like it
Don't buy it
But now I'm just
Amir consumer
And this sort of stuff
It kind of gets to me
Hey how are you
Could I have
Two hot dogs
Two pretzels
Two beers
A popcorn in the water
Just Bud Light
Stadiums are like airports in movie theater
Their captive Market
Once you're inside
You don't have a choice
It's basically a monopoly
The reason this works out so well for the monopolist
Is you always
Think that you can somehow avoid getting hungry
But it's a waiting game and eventually you always do
Cancel demand for hot dogs and Bud
It doesn't change all that much
And I'm not once have been pushing the limits of that forever
Oh man
That's a pretty good dog though
It's like $0.75 per bite
How to say that's a good deal but if you do the math I'm not so sure
Yeah we're not so sure any of this makes sense
What if stadiums have actually been hurting themselves what if they haven't really understood their own Market
Turn on welcome to Planet Money I'm T group and I'm bouncing and teeth we are here today
Because you told me that someone is messing with this whole captive Market thing
Atlanta Falcons
The bringing prices down
You're selling hot dogs and beer for relatively normal price
Like $2 hot dogs
$5 beer
Today imma show what happens when a major sports team turn steam economics upside down
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online press
And run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layouts
Along with
Features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase
Just have a website or domain
I talked to the girl master real quick
We get to Atlanta walk to the stadium and meet Xena smart
She's been tailgating
For 17 years
What are you cooking today
We are doing burritos and tacos and nachos think about
He'll get it for a second
For the price of
Parking some charcoal and some ice
You get to eat delicious hot food medium-rare even if you want it
Pet Supermarket prices
We obviously don't know if tailgating is
Is a direct response to the
Crazy Prices inside stadium
But sometimes
Goiter feels like it
Where in Atlanta to see how the Falcons experiment with food and beer pricing is working
Last season the Falcons dropped their price
My first question is
People to notice
We have seen it
Have you noticed that the foods cheaper
She's like oh yeah
Much cheaper
But she still isn't buying more inside
That's old-time Tailgaters you know we got to tailgate so by time we're going to game really with full
So I drink
Do you know okay this next question is more of a personal Obsession of 5
Because the food is so expensive in
Side most stadiums
I always bring my own snacks
Some stadiums allow it
But many
Including the Falcons do not
The weather's a will there's a way and are Economist brains are like
Now that food prices inside the stadium of drop
Is that will lesser
Did people used to sneak in
More food
I don't know about the food
Like
Smelled alcohol
How do people sneak alcohol into they just put a little bottle under there
Oakley
We say goodbye to Tina Joe falcon
I'm walking to the stadium or first stop
Is the front office
There we find
Rich McKay
The head of the falcon
Rich is American football
Royalty
Music ID
He was the ball boy
For the Tampa Bay Buccaneers his dad was
He grew up
Became the general manager of the Bucks
Hi Tony Dungy
He seems like a walking there is no I in team poster
He only speaks in we state
Camera we just talk
Just the radio take off your shoes if you want
Rich started off on the football side of things but eventually he moved to the business side
And he started looking at the NFL ban survey
You know it's two things that the Falcons were completely failing at
The food
In the park
Parking
There wasn't much I could do about that
In the food
Could you complain about
I don't know warmbier yes you can
That's all you do is complain you don't it's not going to happen
As a result of it the way Stadium food usually works
Is people like rich
Pretty much Outsource all of the food stuff to a huge company called the concessionaire
They don't have to worry about the food at all
But also they can't do any
Switch new the food situation was bad but didn't know how bad
Until this one day
We had a ticket guy
Came to me and he said to hey I want you to go to a meeting
Are we going to meet with the concessionaire
And we're going to talk about
The setup
4 sweet
Sweet light sky Box where the fancy beef
Concessionaires run those
But I said we can talk about
And he said that the pricing
I said okay what's the weather
Concern
Well my concern is is it and now they've got
They charge this this this in
Do you know that for the little
Stir straws
They charge
36 bucks for a box of 20
So rich and the ticket guy they grabbed a box of straws and bring them to a meeting with the concessionaire
We said yeah we get my package and
And they don't really look at it and we are they just pay us for the setup and we took a look at the straws
Aren't I mean isn't this a problem
For Rich a line has been crossed
You might say
It was the final straw
That's when we asked about the contract
That's what we asked about how these prices set
And by we this time he means
Greg B
Greg is the chief operating off
Officer the falcon
A little more reserved
Numbers guy
And also
Cheap
Like when you take his wife and kids to the game
I get a hot dog cut in half
Give each of them a half of a hot dog and buy two waters and for straws
This is too expensive you guys got to got to share your water
Craigslist of the contract brings refined storage
And according to Rich
It's not good
They
We're in charge of pricing
The concessionaire was
And they were allowed to charge quote market prices
So we should
Let me know
$6 hot dog is not a market price
I need to know
Market is Define
By similarly situated
Sports
Venues
And we were like
That's a
Terrible definition of market
You notice a good definition of though
A captive Market
A place where one seller has a monopoly
And no one cannot do
The Falcons needed was a new contract
I'm heading opening
Are designing a brand new stadium
And with it comes a new concessions Conte
So they told other big concessionaires
Come to our offices in
And they all came
With the same sort of contract that everyone use
The concessionaire right there
Huge upfront check to the stadium
And then
They both split the revenues from the
Someone came in and pitched us will write you a check today for
420 million dollars
So you can buy all the equipment that you need to buy
Will give you 60% of the gross revenue so before an expense
Kaiser pay
And you're just done
And then we worry about all the rest
The best of you could possibly get right that that be the best deal you can get and and that's very enticing just we could be done with it we don't have
Don't worry about it anymore
I used to work
At a stadium
In concessions
And this right here
With a revelation
I did not know this is how these deals were structured
But now I understand
Why prices are
You're so high right from the start
The concessionaire has dug itself a multimillion-dollar hole
So for them to get their money back
There's only you know
Two sides of the balloon left to squeeze
And it's food quality let's buy the cheapest food that we can
It was charged as much as we can
And maybe I you know a third is
Is labor
Let's have as few people as possible to make all of this happen which all of that translates into
Bad Fan Experience that's why it takes so long to get a hot dog that's why the hot dog cost so much
And that's why I might be cold that's right
Exactly right
In other words
The fan loses
Elephants keep losing well at a certain point
Sitting on my couch
Watching my new HDTV with my frozen pizza
Start looking pretty awesome can't be watching the TV and the other Stadium at the same time
So the Falcons decided to take charge of concession
Can sand get rid of the whole revenue-share thing
Instead
Taipei concessionaria management fee
Potato
Control
How many cooks there are
The quality of the food
And importantly
The prices
The team didn't want to just lower prices
They wanted to make a state
We we we call it street price
Like $2 popcorn
$3 fries $2 sodas with unlimited free refills
Who plays the people be happier
Sure but also there's some economics 101
Lower the price
Increase the quantity demanded and hopefully recoup some of the cost
We were trying to figure out
Greg was through models
Okay if we were deuce
Pricing
What demand is at going to drive
Great estimated that most people will be buying
25% more than
But because they drop prices so much
It looked like they were still going to leave money on the table
Compared to the old motto
Even though they were selling more nachos and Hanukkah
But they were really invested in this idea so they decided
Let's go ask.
The owner of the Falcons Arthur
He been on them for years about improving The Fan Experience
So they drove the blanks office
Went to a conference room
Inside around a tape
Who is shaped like a football
We were a little nervous whenever you're going to go to your boss and make a pitch that
Involves
Enough
Lost Revenue potential
Are you you're a little nervous
You walked into
Arthur's office and told them he was going to lose how much money
4 million dollars
The Blake went for it
He really wanted those Fan Experience
Yet turned out convincing their paws
The hard part
Was finding a new partner
A new concessionaire
They picked it up you them hey we've got this new model for concessions
And we're going to be reducing price
Like a lot like
50%
And
Could day and what they see themselves being a partner in that
And that was a little
That chicken
Remember
The Falcons are the client
But most of these concessionaires
I just couldn't even comprehend with the falcon
Proposing
They were messing
With one of the oldest money making relationships
In the business
The team ended up working at a deal with a concession are they new
They done the food at the Royals Stadium
And so the Falcons made in an ounce
We're bringing prices down
Do you know who doesn't like to hear hey you were trying a radical experiment that might unanchor your customers perception
How much they should be paying for your overpriced product
The billionaires who owned the rest of the NFL
The first NFL owners meeting that we went to after we announced it
There were other teams that were
Mad
I mean really upset
What are you doing to us why are you guys doing this
Yeah this is a big Revenue stream for us don't forget
And that was assuming p
People bought 25% more product
Because of cheaper price
The really
They didn't know it would happen
Nobody had really done this before
Okay enough Monday morning quarterbacking
I want to see this in action it's game time
Atlanta is playing the Tampa Bay Buccaneers
And so far it's been a rough season for the falcon
I need a win
We get inside and take a look at
But I want to be roaming The Conch
Because I want to know
Are people buying
We should say
What the Falcons are doing
Is not
2 radical 4
All the time business
Is a shifter price
To increase profit
You got your supply curve or demand curve
Invite where they meet me that is the optimal price
And our question is
National anthem sorry
How much money do
You have in your wallet
Let's see I'm taking it out here and I have
You have done not tell you what
I don't lend you twenty bucks
All right
We've got twenty bucks let's go spend it
Let's go Nick we head into the con
I got to say
It's not half time yet is it
Nope we're still got a ways to go
There's a lot of people waiting in line for super like what on the way
The thing is
More lines don't necessarily mean more profit
You drop the price and your margins at dinner
Okay
You got to hot dog to fry one park on one bottle of water into Bud Light
That's right
Yotality
$20 28 dollars
Yes
No way
That's pretty much the same thing we bought at Madison Square Garden
At half staff
All right end of the first half we got a lot more food to eat
I got a lot more money to spend after the break will come back and eat the rest
Zoe Nick
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Is reimagining Bank
I offering account
With no fees or minimum
I can be open from anywhere in
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Na
We head upstairs past this guy
Right here
Find David Collins plate full of snacks
Defense defense
All the way from New Jersey
He's a big falcon
He goes and sees them when they play in Philly
My brother's an Eagles fan they suck
I go to the games with him and I thought he played in Philly it was ridiculous I have been like almost
$40
On what
Beer
A burger
And like popcorn it was ridiculous today you have Whataburger fries and a soda baking soda the second time I actually
But food like I've never bought more than one time at a stadium
Straight
That right there is the sound
Hive Fan Experience number
Breckenridge
Project has been a wild success
For 1
People are coming in way earlier
In spending more money
Because of it
They said they're selling as much before the game even starts at the new stadium
As it get the entire game at the old
Stadium Creek and Rich. That they were going to leave
4 million dollars
But it's actually
And that's because
Remember
They thought they were going to increase sales 25% at best
Big blown past that they are selling
53% more product
Another teams have noticed
Big teams
Like the Ravens the Lions Mississippi State they are all significantly lowering their price
The Falcon say they have few regrets
Except
Maybe the free refills on
As evidence by David from Jersey
The guy who thinks the Eagles suck
How many refills did you do today
Is the second one
Nice second one the second one and there's still a lot of gameplay to go people are refilling their sodas on
Average 3.7 *
And Greg says at that rate
He be happy if they're breaking even on soda
I'm headed to the bleachers and sit next to a guy
Really responding to low beer prices
How much do PCS cost
950 song
A game
Birthday weekend happy birthday
Thank you.
Is Michelob for you
Looking out
At this huge Stadium
All I could think about was yasher good story generous donor does right by the consumer everyone's happy blah blah blah
But there is more to
Building the new stadium was really expensive
And you know what
The Falcons raise their ticket price
The Falcons don't even sell single game 2
Other than for standing room
If you want to see you have to buy season 2
It seems like the Falcons
Aren't really
Even targeting the one-off take your kids in NFL game
Sora fan anymore
Their marketing towards the people who will come back
Time After Time
What's your sit back and watch the rest of the game yeah I agree have I run to the bathroom
When did Alice Through the credit we always love to hear from you send us an email at
Planet Money at npr.org or follow us on social media at Planet Money
Are supervising editor is brighter that are supervising producer is Alex goldmark I'm Nick fountain
Country group thanks for listening
Oh my God