Today we have a story about how you can dis man
Federal agency
From the inside
Any agency in question is the one that protects
Everyday Americans
It's from big bang
Lenders financial institutions
It's called the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau
The cfpb
Cfpb agency is a sort of Rorschach test
For how you view the role of government
In your life
Democrats they love the cfpb
You screwed up the financial crisis and to them it is an independent Watchdog that works
Pick the little guy from Bank fees and
Deceptive loans
And high interest rate
For republicans
It's a little different
What's your from
This Bureau is unlike any other Federal bureaucracy
It's run by one person has no accountability to Congress
It is perhaps the most unaccountable Bureau agency there is
We want to run that place
With a good deal of humility and prunes
That is Mick Mulvaney is a former Republican congressman
South Carolina
When he was in Congress he actually sponsored a bill
To destroy the cfp
BB completely
The bill failed but the Republican dream of killing the agency live.
In fact when Donald Trump was elected president
And you got a chance to name a new director of the
Cfpb
He looked around and he picked the man
Who probably hated the agency the most
The guy we just heard from
Mick Mulvaney
Of course
Consumer group
Crazy
Freaking out and it was just so odd
That when Mulvaney everything topper
Introduced himself
Pediatricians office
Despite what you might by the way thank you for having me despite what you might read
I'm pretty sure I'm not the devil
At least of my wife and my mother don't think that I am
What happens when you put the person
Who tried to murder an agency
In charge of that agency
We have not blowing the place up we've not set the building on fire detective you ever seen the building it's not possible to set it on fire
It's a brutalist architecture building with nothing flammable in it we have changed it though
Mick Mulvaney decided if he was going to have to do it one small piece at a time
Hello and welcome to Planet Money on croissants and I'm Robert Smith today on the show we will follow one man
The cfpb and one single enforcement case brought by the agency
The case is an investigation of an online loan shark
A lender charging outrageous levels of interested people who clearly could not afford
The kind of case of cfpb was designed to go after
But then Along Came Mick Mulvaney who decided he wanted to do things a little differently
Will show you what happen
Support for this NPR Podcast in the following message come from the United States Postal Service
Everyday
Innovative companies are Reinventing the way business has
But none of that is possible without the right people
People who get packages to over a hundred and fifty million delivery play
Affordably and on time with the latest technology and expertise
Who can help you deliver the future of Commerce
The United States Postal Service
See why they deliver more e-commerce packages to home
It's been anyone in the country
USPS.com future
Let's take one investigation
Did the cfpb is
1 case against
One length
I think some question is the cfpb versus Golden Valley Lending
Ink
And this lawsuit started during the Obama Administration but it was taken over Midway
Buy Trump Sky by Nick Mulvey
Frightened rabbit if you look over here we have the website it's Golden Valley lending. Com beautiful icy mountains
I would like to borrow
And you can click up to $1,000 thousand dollars get the money you needed easy apply Noteboom
Oasis
Easy steps
Put in your name
Click a few things
Seems very straightforward
That's what Julie bone-in fat.
I was
Literally facing eviction cuz I was so behind on my rent and I had no idea where I was
Money
I was just really rough
Certified does administrative work for the city of Detroit 227
But last year was just a really rough
Year
Boyfriend broke up their car got
Stolen
Angie got behind the red
It was living alone paying right by herself as she clicked around on this Golden Valley website finally just desperate for money
The way it was presented was literally presented as like
For large payments
I love you.
She makes the pain
And she thinks
She's home free
But then the lender kept taking money out of her checking account
Sochi
Contacted Golden Valley and said what is up
This and they said oh no you agreed
Online
To make a lot more pain
Nancy was all there in the fine print
Julie said she just absolutely didn't
Realize that
A10
Get this she showed me her account on the Golden Valley website
And it says for her $900 loan
Her payments are going to be
35 bucks
4 *
In less than a year
Transcribe
Obviously I didn't really want to
Tell anybody like
What had happened because it was so embarrassing and so
Shameful that I would have fallen for some
Something like this
Finally Joy said she just didn't know what else to do so
She went to her boss at work
And at
He look at it and he was like us 100% interest
This is Criminal
Back in Washington DC
Lawyers at the cfpb we're coming to a similar
They begin a complaint
All around the nation
About Golden
An April of
They sue the company
Unfair deceptive
An abusive business
Christopher Peterson was an enforcement attorney at the cfpb you back when Obama was in office
And he seen a lot of you
Is predatory lending cases places this one stands out this
This lender
Was one of the worst of
They were making loans
With interest rates of 900
50%
To Consumers that could barely afford
To pay them back and we're struggling to make ends meet
And they were doing so in ways that were illegal and deceptive
That was going to investigate a company like this what would you like why were you first have to figure out
Who's behind the company how it how does it all work
The cfpb figured out that the call center for Golden Valley was in Overland Park
Kansas
And then we found out that one of the people Finance in the operation was a gentleman named
Richard Mosley
Who had been convicted of racketeering in another online Lending
Spreckels Crossing part of the whole investigation was
Who formerly owned
Golden Valley Lending
The companies registered in the Tiny Town of Upper Lake
California
The owners are an Indian tribe
It's called a heavy metal
Pomo of Upper Lake
Indian tribe
We put on an interview requested
The tribe and we weren't hearing back from them first or
Phone number weeks
Actually but we did have an address for Golden Valley lending it was listed in the cfp
If you lost it
635 East
Highway 20
Upper Lake Calif
We gave this address to a radio producer we know janaki meta and said
Go find it
Hey there
We heard it's north of San Francisco
North of Napa
But it's it's it's much farther than
That right
Yeah it's like two and a half hours
Northeast of San Francisco
Pretty remote surrounded by mountains and lots of trees and the road kind of Narrows when you get close to the lake
Okay so I see a little town the right here this is Upper Lake
Upper Lake is this beautiful Town very green mountainous it's
God
Little houses spread out all over looks like a soap like one of those old towns out of country western
Turn films on the post office and Salon that looks like a used to say salut
Luna
So I pulled up and
I saw these three people standing outside
John Krasinski
I'm Ray
REI
My name is hippy Joe
Of course
Yeah I had a big walrus mustache and sunglasses on sale
Can you describe where we are right now we're on Main Street at the corner
Are we have hippie Jose
Starting down there at the gas station
A doctor's office you have the fire
And I'm leaning on the horse type
You know this
It sounds like a nice place was there any sign of Golden Valley Lending
Annapolis
London Christmas
Like a lending business
I haven't heard of it
And you went to that address what what did you find
I found a
You know they're running Creek Casino I went inside walked up to
To the desk where there was this woman she appeared to be Native Americans like me don't ask her a couple of questions
She was
Immediately
Interested in kind of being interviewed but I did ask her about Golden Valley in
She did say she was part of the tribe
But she was totally unwilling to talk to me she said
Golden Valley was indeed on the premises but she couldn't really say anymore and she kept telling me to talk to Sherry Trap by who
Is there a tribal official
And then
Yeah yeah when I tried to find it myself
I
Couldn't find signs anywhere I even I went outside and I drove around the building and this can cut off
Guard the subs
Security guard came from inside the building and
Decided I don't know what you're talking about all I know is it's not here you need to leave the premises so
I deleted that point
Alright well thanks for trying janaki
Robert
I'm still not sure that we have a good
Sense
Exactly what's going on with this
Tribal lender there is some kind of operation there at that casino
Yeah and the cfpb had a
A theory about the
Renuzit online lenders sometimes
Incorporate on Indian
And then claims they're not subject to
State laws
So even if state that says you
You can't charge High interest rates
A native American-owned company can claim hate that does not
Apply to us we have Tribal sovereignty
But in the lawsuit the cfpb says
Look
Not really what we're not buying that Golden Valley
Is clearly acting
Is a national lender
Even if they have an address in a
Casino
This remote area
Upper Lake California
This was where the case stood
When Mick Mulvaney was named director
Of the cfp
The Republican who did not believe that the agency should even exist
Was now heading that eat
At one of his first Acts
Is the Senate memo
Tell the entire staff
Hey everybody we are going to do things a lot
Slower
Around here
So slow in
In fact it's some things
We're doing
We're no longer going to be doing
At all
And quietly
And mysterious
Around the same time
This Golden Valley lawsuit
Get straps
He wouldn't lawsuit that have been years in the mail
It's a company accused of fleecing
Perhaps thousands of people and all of a sudden this lawsuit is about
Yeah and at the time it seemed
A little strange cuz it didn't get a lot of
Attention but
I started to hear
From people inside
The cfpb
And they were
Puzzled because this this case seems like a slam dunk it was like why all of a sudden
Is Golden Valley being let off
Can you call people inside of government agency they're not supposed to talk so
I found the sky Christopher Peterson
He's a former lawyer at the cfpb is now law professor
I asked him
So you know what what's your take on this lawsuit getting traps
These
Federal investigations can take years
To gather all the information to
Bring people who break the law to Justice
People are devastated and angry just imagine how you would feel if years of your life
Have been dedicated to pursuing Justice
And now that's all
Thrown in the trash and you lose everything
He says if the cfpb hadoop
Pursued and won the lawsuit
That could have clawed back money to help thousands of people have allegedly been hurt
People like Julie who really wasn't happy.
Did you hear that the lawsuit had been dropped
I'm really mad like really pissed because
Actually voting for Trump
So
I feel kind of like
Stupid
It's kind of like
Betrayed
I wanted to know
Who actually
Betrayed you
Play so I started to make a few calls
And I figured well start at the top Mick Mulvaney
His price guide decline the interview
But
The Prescott told me something interesting
He said
This is not Mulvaney's doing it this decision was made by quote
Professional career
Staff
In other words
There's nothing to say
See here wasn't us
Just some lawyers
Been here long
But that just seemed a little weird to me like
It just kind of felt like
He was lying because how could that
Be true until I reached out to some
The cfpb
And if it look I mean every single career staffer in this building
Wanted to push ahead with
With this case the only possible explanation
Yes
Did Mick Mulvaney dropped
Hey Chris you reported some of this
On NPR
And then
All hell broke loose
Looks at least one Senator heard the story and decided to ask
Mulvaney on the record
Did you personally kill this case against Golden Valley Lending
It was Democratic senator
Chris Van Hollen
950%
Interest rates I mean this is higher than
Mafia loan sharks
Simple question
Were you part of the
The decision to drop
The case again
Golden
Yes sir
I'll follow up with
I think it's an outrageous
Mulvaney didn't say during his hearing why he wanted to drop the lawsuit against Golden Valley but we
Tried to get into his head
And we think it shows what he means by this Mantra that the agency should exercise more
Humility and moderation
Yep mulvania said over and over again that he thinks the cfpb hasn't
Push the envelope
That's going right up to the edge of its mandate with Congress
Being as aggressive as possible some as being too aggressive
Edwin Mulvaney was talking about his
Priorities for the sea
If you be steadwell
You don't look at the list of complaints that we get here just a small fraction of the
Complaints are about
You know payday lenders are high interest loans so maybe those should be a small part of our Enforcer
Right so that's maybe what Mulvaney is
Banking
But
Some consumer advocate
It's a
There might be something else going on to
This is clear evidence that
Mick Mulvaney is a Payday industry puppet
Carl freshers with the consumer group Allied progress
He said if you look back over the last decade
You know as a congressman he took
$62,000 + from the payday lenders
And now at the cfpb he's doing their bidding of course as much as we would like to be inside Mick Mulvaney's head
We are knots and we asked him several times for interviews he's
Said no every time
So
We don't really know the motivation
But we do know that as of today
Golden Valley is free to keep
Giving out
Money their website still up
And after many weeks of calls
We did manage
To get someone from the tribe
To speak with us
Coming up after
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Did you come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org
A couple days ago I got on the phone with
A tribal official
My name is Sherry treppa I am the chairperson of the Hemet old poem of Upper Lake tribe and
Have been the chairperson since 2008
Sure trepasses lucky you have to see Golden Valley Lending
In context
As in
Hundreds of years
She says her tribe suffered the whole history book worth of ingest
Massacre in the 1800's
Worcester land of the 1900s
The try barely
Survive
And it was only 15 years ago actually that the tribe started to pull itself back together again
We have a very very young government
The mission of our of our tribal government is to improve the lives of our peace
Troy-Bilt
But it is
So remote in Upper Lake
Make it so far away from me big papa
Population centers
It doesn't make any
But then trepasses to try for the other tribes were starting make money with his online Landing fee
And he looked into it
And what happens sometimes instead of tribal disorder
Lone its name with some other company somewhere else in the country in the tribe with
Like a tiny slice the profit
That's but they're not really the letters it's called Reggie tribe
Trevor says they decided to go
In another Direction
And it turns out according to her that they're much more real owners of this thing especially at this point now
They're putting up a lot of the money and
They're making a lot more
I'm not going to share the balance sheet of our businesses but
Budget
For the current year is
Isn't millions of dollars
And it has changed the oil change the lives
Of generations
Come
Millions of dollars
All from online
Lending
She said Somebody's paying for college scholarships eldercare cultural activities for the tribe
Which is all well and good but we did have
1 peking
Yunnan
Do you have to charge 850
80% interested I mean like like why not
Dual ending operation that is
You know where that is
That's not just so painful for
People who sell them I've talked to didn't
Understand what they were getting into
Sure
We provide a good product that is well related
But it is expensive
We do know that there is a population of the customers we serve
That don't have any intentions of paying it back
So the cost of the loan is reflective of the cost to underwrite the customer
Cost to service the customer
Cost to collect
And notably the cost of the default
It's an expensive product but it is an expensive product to deliver
The Chris I have to say
I would never take that one
I would not recommend anyone
But I am a little bit
Torn because I do know that
Tribes have very few
Ways to make money
On their tribal land
And they could do things like casinos or
Fireworks
Tax-free cigarettes
And as much
As I'm so disturbed by the online Lending
I can see if that's your only option
That you might go that way
There's a profound
Legal questions
Because all the things that you're talking about
Cigarettes a gaming operation that's all happening on
Tribal land
But here
These loans
900 percentage
Straight all the rest of it that's
Happening
Microsoft
Tribal land in the near vicinity were talking about
All acrostic
Country states where these loans are illegal
And whether or not that's okay
Had this lawsuit
Going forward that would have been decided in
In court with a judge we would have had a real ant
Answer to that question
Is that okay
But when you drop a lawsuit
Will never get the answer
Right and staffers at the bureau where they look this is one case
But
There are dozens more
Investigations cases
Regulations that are in the works at the bureau and the people been working on them are really concerned that nickel babies come in now
And they're worried is that this case the one we've been talking about
Could be a blueprint
For throwing out lots of other important stuff that they're working on
If any of her listeners out there know somebody or themselves have been involved
In Sumter Landing operation or other financial situation that just didn't seem right we want to hear from you
Give it a shout at Planet Money at npr.org or you can follow along on all of our social media
You drama on Facebook Instagram and
Are shows produced today by later Richard and Nick fountain or editor is Brian first
Text pallavi gogoi Tori Berliner for their work on this story in this podcast
I'm Robert Smith
And I'm Chris Arnold
Say thanks for the
Don't you go change
Text Alyssa