Support for this in
NPR podcasts
The following message come from that UPS
Offering services from shredding
To printing to mailbox
And instead of closing this Memorial Day we
May 24th and 25th
The UPS Store
He's doing another thing
All together
Opening
The UPS Store
Everything for small business
And of course shipping
I'm Carter Garcia
And I'm Stacey Vanek Smith and we are the host of a new podcast
Planet Money is called the
Decatur and you can think of it as Planet Money quick take on the news
OraQuick Eva cash anyways yes 68 minutes
In any case we take a number or term in the news and we tell you a story behind it or give you an inside
And today on Planet Money we are bringing you three indicators
Three numbers that tell you something about the world around first
The u.s. really sells to World II we're going to tell you how conservative tax policy ended up being
Kinda sorta would a liberal Economist have been helping for and it's causing some mixed feelings
And finally going to tell you how the craft beer blew up the Hops business the big finish.
Stick around There Will Be Blood
Like human blood human blood absolutely
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editor
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to launch use the offer code NPR
To save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Iverson Decatur
2.2 trillion dollars that's about how much stuff
Goods and services
The US sells to the rest of
The world every year
That's a lot
But it's when you dig into the details that you really start to see some fascinating patterns
Set it talk about it
I called up Charles Kenny he's a senior fellow
The center for Global development
Charles has been researching and writing about globe
While
But frankly he's also
Just a fun dude
To talk to you about
Trade
You can even kind of hear it
Newsboys how delighted he is
To discuss us
In a week sportmachines report vehicle export agricultural products
Tronicsfix what minerals
Huge range of stuff I was just saying that our exports are tremendously
Varied
To get a sense of this
Consider the top three categories
Good
So physical thing
It's not service
That we export
Noah's Ark
Refined oil products
Cars
An airplane
Put them all together and they still only add up to about 11
Percent of the value of all Goods
We export
And you don't have to search far down the list
To start finding
Surprising stuff
1.4% of what the US exports of stuff
Is blood
We turn out to be a a will be done in blood exports
Majin Buu
The absolutely human blood products
What what reason is in Europe during the Mad Cow outbreak
A few years ago people worried that we couldn't
Screen map out the blood supplies and so a lot of blood plasma
Was exported from the US to Europe
I'm an exit of continued
Another is frankly that in the United States unlike most places you can pay people
Making donations of plasma in Blood and so
There a hole in his car accident victims in the United Kingdom and France and I wouldn't be alive today if it wasn't
Us blood circulating in their veins I think it's a good news story
And all this variety the
Blood and stuff Kenny mention
That's good
Because it's healthy that the country isn't really dependent on any one thing that sells abroad
Buddy says
Our exports themselves
Are depending on
Are dependent on
If you look at the Boeing Dreamliner for example the wingtips made in Korea a lot of parts of the rest of the wing and made into
Penn landing gear is made in France some of the engines made in the United Kingdom that comes together
India Boeing factories in Seattle
And then we expect
If you didn't have Alibis in Port Bowen couldn't make
The Dreamliner couldn't expose it and that we really bad the US trade
Because if we were to make all of those parts in the US
The Dreamliner would be so expensive
That would be way harder to then exported abroad
There was one last
No Doubt
Some things we export
Never leave
The country
So huge us export cattle
About 200 billion dollars
Travel
Text people from abroad who
Kunming tourist run
Business trips
Or students coming here to go to
School
Think about it this way
For something to count as an export
Someone who is outside the US just has to buy something from a business inside the U
So take somebody in Britain they can buy their Mickey Mouse doll in the Disney Store in London
And that'll count is some of that would count as an export from the United
Statesboro they can come to Disneyland in
The Mickey Mouse dolls
Then no rain by the hotel and
Call rental and food and so on
An overlap counts of Mexico and it's a really important parts of the US economy
Coming to the US
Education
American universities in
Schools make nearly
40 billion dollars from
Foreign students
It's a big one and it's a very important one possibly because most foreign students he come to the United States Phoenix Faith pay full price
They
Help
Support the university providing more money for
And I nice a sports equipment smaller class sizes better teachers hopefully
Letter words
Even though trade is about the movement of goods and services across borders
Kids separated from the movement of people across border
For a list of all the sources we used for this part of the episode and there were a lot of them
Go to npr.org money where we posted
Our next indicator is 1.8 trillion dollars
We're going to explain what that number is
First
We have to tell you about Jared Burns
Yes we do
Because Jared Bernstein
Is a man with a dog
He's a liberal Economist who worked on President Obama's economic
And he's been arguing for years.
Did the US need more economic
Stimulus
So some combination
Lower taxes
And higher spending
To really get the economy going and in particular
Start driving up wages
For workers
Even now he still thinks the economy can use a bit more
Now in the past few months the republican-controlled Congress passed
Ascot
And also approved a big new spending bill
Both of which were signed into law by a Republican president by present
Trump and combined these will add an estimated 1.8
Australian dollars
Budget deficits in the next
That is our indicator
1.8 trillion dollars
Now these two bills were not sold
A stimulus package
They are definitely not Jared Bernstein
Liberal stimulus dream come true
But they are going to mean lower tax
Suzanne higher spending
So they are
Kind of sort of
The thing he's been arguing
Not
The basic idea behind government stimulus
Is that
City economies
Not doing as well.
Sometimes the government can help the economy get back to it
Best self
By spending more money
Or putting tax
The Ordinary People themselves
Have more money to spend
So when Jared Bernstein thinks about the
Republican tax bill and
Spending increases
She has to answer to Quest
One is the economy it
Best self right now
Into
Will the tax cut in Spanish
His work as a
When roasting started working for the Obama Administration
The answer to
Is the economy
Is best self or
Stimulus
Was pretty simple
I vividly remember us getting together in December of 2008 when the economy was
Really falling off a cliff
Is the technical term
That must have been quite a meeting
Did you guys look for
Flask or some
Yeah we needed a flask so let me just tell you that there was absolutely not the slightest Inkling
Conflict
In my or my colleague mind about the need for a deep and robust and
Quick acting
Keynesian stimulus
But today
10 years later the unemployment rate is
Slow the economy
Growing is adding jobs
Every month
And the value of stimulus then is
Much less clue
We are in the midst of a
Solid economy no question
So my
Kind of nuance what I'm bringing to the table and I guess
It's different than a lot of my brothers and sisters in this
In any economic field right now
Is that I think we can go further
Jared
Esteem stimuli
And the reason is job
Unemployment seems low but Jared thinks it can go lower and that
Would be great for
Yes things are good but they can be better
Especially for people who been left behind the only way
The least Advantage people
In this economy
Experian
Their share of of the growth
Is when we get to and stay at not just full employment
But Chalkville employment really tight labor markets and that's what I'm hoping to look for
When employers are desperate for workers
It is harder for them the employers
To discriminate
Wages go up benefits go up workers
Just have more
Power but the risk to adding too much stimulus to a good economy is real
It could cause inflation it could drive prices up
An end up hurting the very
People that it's supposed to be
Be helping
Still on question number one
Is the economy is best self right now
Short answer is no
And he thinks stimulus
A question for him is question number 2
Are the tax cuts and
Spending increases
Good
Not even good just are they better than that
The benefits of these particular stimuli
Not all physical stimulus is created equal
She does like the spending in
Those are short-term
I'm just a couple of years
He thinks they'll give the economy a nice boost
The tax cuts though are not the kind of tax
Scott's to Jared with a
Chosen
He says the largely benefit
Hit the rich side
Projections
Showing that the majority of their benefits
We'll go to the wealthiest Americans
Increase
Inequalities
But he says for the next couple of years
They still might be good for the economy
According to some research that's of high-quality and I believe it
The combination of the
The tax cuts in the spending bill
Are going to add a little bit more than half a point
2 GDP growth
This year and next year
In other words
The tax cuts combined with the spending increase
Will give the economy the booze
The Jared thing
So far so good
But your toes
There's a problem
A lot of tax cut isn't just
For the next few years
Permanent
Semi permit
And he says that is a bad idea
He thinks the government
Is going to need to raise more money
You're not less just
In case there's another recession
2 pesos
Security and Medicare
Self
How does Gerard Way all of this
Yeah the brain start the kind of breakdown you are
Sharing an economist who is admittedly conflicted about all this
I think what's happening right now in terms of fiscal stimulus
And part of that is the tax cut is a welcome
Experiment I think what
Slated to happen starting in
2019-2020 and going forward
Is
Fiscally Reckless
Indian Jared said
She worries that the cost
Long term tax
That will be larger than the benefits
Short-term stimulus
If they'd come packaged together
Jared says it overall he would vote
Against that
But it was obviously a tough call for him and in any case
This is the
Stimulus we got
Just wasn't the stimulus
Just Jared wanted
So we'll just have to see in the next couple of years
What that stimulus means
The economy
And how the tax cuts play out in the years after the
Coming up after the break
A story about the
Flower
Powers beer
Flower power
I know
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editor
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to launch use the offer code NPR
To save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Our last indicator is one
Specifically $1 per pound
That is the low price of Cascade hops
I talked about this number with Douglas McKay
He is a middleman in Hobbs
Business hikinex
The farmers who grow up
With the beer makers who
In what
What are hops
Okay
We're getting really big
Goodnight I used to get that question all the time actually
About 10 or 15 years ago before craft beer became popular I would
People ask what I do they have no clue what hops were
Today it's totally different today everybody
It's kind of like a cult
Coco Pops
Hops are the flowers of the Hop plant
They look like little cone
Enter used in making beer
The help slavery
And craft beer lovers
Love heart
If you ask them
They will tell you all about it
And as the market for craft beer exploded over the last decade
The demand for hops
Intelligent
Douglas MacKinnon has lived through the whole rise and fall of hops
He started working in the business in 99
Thanks for a really bad shape.
Farmers were struggling
It was bad thanks for calling the industry unthinkable
It looked
Pretty bleak
The industry was ruled by the big beer maker
Scores in fide
But then craft beer started taking off in the
And they started becoming a bigger force in the industry
Everything was moving so fast
It was just crazy
And craft beer uses way more hops than beers like Coors and die
About ten times more hops
Also craft beer makers
Did not just want mainstream
They wanted Farmers to start planting a special Hops and a bunch of different kinds of Pop
To give their beer distinctive
Citra Simcoe
Amarillo
Mosaic
Probably the most
Popular
Is Cascade
That's kind of
Gateway hop into Aroma House
In 2012 Douglas and his wife founded the company called 47
They are middleman they take orders from Craft Brewers with a 5000 lb of
Mosaico Amarillo
Any find a farmer who will grow it
And business
Was great
For the first couple years we never had to do
Any
They'll be kind of calls when everybody was calling us
I was just
So much
Demanded so much
Excitement and so much
Energy I guess
It's like a
Ride on a rocket ship I suppose
So prices going up as
I didn't even talk about prices
Ya prices
The price of hops
Went nuts
Douglas says
Cascade
Deep Gateway hops
Win from around
$3 a pound more than $7
What's pound on hold
Farmers could not plan too fast
Meanwhile all kinds of different people were jumping into the craft beer business
Calling up people like Douglass to get hooked up
Hops and
Brewing new beers
Farmers did what farmers do with the price
Democrat Gazette
They planted more and more
Demand Justice
Kept growing
And then just over a year ago
Something changed
We noticed that cash flow started slowing down for not paying you on time
Right
The Brewers weren't paying Douglas on time because craft beer sales were not booming like they
Initially yours
All these people were trying craft beer in
Switching over to it and growth in the industry was
Crazy but like 20% a year
Most people have tried crack
You're in the people who are going to switch over to craft. Already switched over to craft beer and people are going to stay
The big beers were sticking with the big beers
Ambrose slow down
From nearly 20% to about 5
I'm still growing
Just a lot more slowly than everybody
Prepared for
And here's the thing
Planting hops
Requires huge upfront investment
And the plants take years to mature
You can just rip hops out and plan something else when the price goes down
So even if the Craft Beer Market was leveling off this
Huge wave hops that have been planted during the boom had just started coming to Market
Suddenly there was a glut
Apopse
Douglas says the wholesale price for Cascade the Gateway hops
Went from around $8 a pound
2 as little as a dollar
Suddenly Douglas's company was millions of dollars in debt
And he and his wife realized
They were drowning on the wall and it was
It was clear this was a
Beginning
Last year Douglas and his wife filed for chapter 11
Another says
The whole industry is struggling
Not that anyone's actually talking about
It's mostly a
Guy dominated industry to maybe there's some kind of Macho thing going on there I don't know but nobody wants to
Admit that they're having trouble
Publicly
But privately
Everybody's petsall Everybody's talking
Douglas still believes in Hopsin
And crafts
He thinks everyone is just going to have to adjust
This new normal
No more crazy quotes
Just more of a slow and steady
He and his wife are adjusting their company 47hops
And he says they're on track to be out of bankruptcy in June
By the way we learned about the great hospice from a story in the financial
X by Emma goat Arizona
Those were three indicators three episodes of the podcast that's
Stacy and I hope every single day every day and it's called
Appropriately enough pee indicator
And we do a lot of you're already subscribed to
Thank you very much thank you and if you are not subscribed
Then first of all
You're hurting what is going on what you waiting for
Check this out please I would like Planet money but we're a little bit more on the news we're definitely shorter 68 minutes
And we appear every single day so you can find us at NPR one or wherever you get your pot.
The indicator is produced by Darius wrathion and edited by Patty Hirsch and Jacob Goldstein
Today's Planet Money episode was produced by Sally Helm and Cindy on assembling gun
Also we have a new series of
Videos your Planet Money
And we made with NPR's awesome video team
And the latest one just came out today
It tells you the history of the
Price tag in about
3 minutes
Need to see what some of the people on the planet Money Team look like
In costume
Trust me
It's hilarious
Take it out at NPR. Org
Ford / Planet Money shorts
Again that is
Npr.org
Forward slash
Planet Money shorts
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Aaron Carter first
Text Melissa