A few weeks ago I went looking for
4 Gold I was slipping down a mountain in the Plumas National Forest in Northern California it has been snowing
Not warning for walking through the cedar trees kind of Misty and foggy
Is the Sun hits the snow sliding around
Only a guy named Josh Reinke through the forest big tall guy with a beanie and a beard he's
Carrying this big wide pan it looks like something you might make a stir-fry in
You get down the hill my goodness I hear the creek
There's this little Island In The Stream
I'm going to like
Just hop over
We get over the rocks
Josh takes the gold pan
Scoops up somebody gravel
Put in the water and I'll have to tell you this sunlight is just following on this pan
Like it's some sort of miracle
Forgot
Golden colored things
Okay
And then I see it glittering
Some small really small pieces see that right there
Certainly a little piece of gold
Listening back I sort of sound like Gollum in Lord of the Rings
That's what Google does to you
There's three little pieces for five 6 right there
1 2 3 4 5 6
You can say it
Eureka
So I'm super excited at the specs of gold
This Trace amount
But Josh isn't impressed
At that point you know of course I would do more research
Get bigger okay
Okay come on
We sent you out west
To make us rich
And you and Josh you're throwing away or treasure
What just threw away was just a tiny bit
But if we want a mine any of that gold
We need to
To stake a claim
In this part of the process
Is amazing
To stake a claim
You literally need
Estate
I could also use
Pool
Or just a pile of rocks
But today
I'm going to use a stick
What about this one
Way too long
Take this thing putting it in
The dirt and we stick some paperwork on it
A mining claim location notice
It says Who We Are
And where we are
And the date
Okay so we're going to put it in a plastic bag
Seal it against the elements
Cool so
All we have to do is
Is put a stick in the ground fill out a form
And we're going to be millionaires right
First I have to pay
The thing is
The price I'm going to pay
It's what I paid for dinner last
15 bucks
I'm going to pay
$15 an acre
The prices like this
I just get one acre let's get 40
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Nick fountain
Assignment the proud owner of the Mining rights for 40 acres of
Triangle country
For not alot of money
Which can I say that is crazy
You did what
One day at work you're about to Pony up
Not a lot of money
And you get the mind as land for a year
And even if you find
Tons of gold
You don't have to pay the government a penny more in royalty
Getting the rights to dig up gold in the US today
Not all that different than it was during the gold rush
Neither of the price
Today on the show
How has the system stay the same for almost a hundred and fifty years
Why is the country
Giving away its goals
On public land
And copper
Can silver
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Message come from the Annie E Casey
Sea Foundation
Developing Solutions
It support strong families and community
To help ensure a brighter future for America's shield
More information is
Is available at aecf. Org
So once you got the wooden stake in the
You take a copy of your claim
You go down to the local office
Of the Bureau of Land
And you register your car
The one that handles the Plumas National Forest
The forest I went to
It's in Sacramento
Hey I'm making a mineral claim we found gold
How old are you like inside
Office I meet Gary catledge
Super friendly Jean sweatshirt
He helped me make sure I didn't claim anyone else's land
It was on a stream that flowed into it we had a bit of trouble finding my spot in the beginning
I'm looking at a map you think you're interested this piece right here
That says what does it say it says creek creek
We found my spot it was in Yuba County
Then we went online to make sure that no one else looks
We were good
Hey yeah I'm going to pay for a mining claim.
Came along way
I certainly did just like the old times
Just hike deal
If this seems like a system
That was designed by Prospectors in the mid 1800
That's cuz it kind of was
Emagine 1848
We find gold in Calif
A bunch of guys
Is Russia West looking to get rich
And they make up the sister
To make sure that no one gets killed over another person
What are these gold miners
Becomes a lawyer a senator
He goes to Washington
Once he gets there
Formalize
The system he saw it West
He writes the law
The mining Act of 80
And it's important to remember that back when the miners found gold
California
Wasn't even a US state
In the mid 1800 the US
With all about
Westward
Expansion and the government wanted to make it as easy and as cheap as possible
4 people
To go out west
Find gold
And settle down
In the slot it was part of that at
The thing is I came into a public forest and steak this claim for cheap
But it's not just amateur Prospectors that are doing it
There are billion-dollar Corporation
Also getting the same deal
It's a rip-off
The rip-off of the taxpayer
Tom Udall senator from New Mexico
Not a fan of the money Act
Of 1872
Just think about it
The public
Owns this land
This is a resource sitting on public land
Udall is part of a group of lawmakers who are working to reform this law
They want to change this old system
In the loafers
But what they're really looking to change
Is the way the federal government gets
Paid for mining that happens on federal lands
They want the mining companies to pay these things called
Royalties
Lots of companies take lots of
Valuable things out of the ground
Oil for 1 natural gas call
And when they make money off those things
Maybe some of that money back to the governor
That's what royalties
Udo says in most places in the world
Mining companies
Do payroll
But in America mining companies
Don't pay royalties to the federal government
And we don't even know how much they're taking out
In 2011 I asked the
The GAO
Numbers on how much
The taxpayers are being short changed
They couldn't say
Not only
Do the Hardrock mining companies not pay they don't disclose
And under current law they don't
Have to
We don't know how much they extract
We don't know where the minerals are sold
And we don't know
The overall value
There was one report
In 2014 a house committee
Added up what they could find from publicly traded mines
Any figured that in one year
Companies who take in at least five billion dollars
Worth of gold silver copper
All these other minerals
Ida public lands
Last year you. Sponsored a bill to reform the 8th
1872 mining law
It would increase in fees and introduce a 2 to 5% Realty
Which could raise at least $100 a year
But it hasn't gone far
We always knew I mean and I knew
The beginning when
I got into
The house and then came into the Senate
When you put in a bill
On 1872 Monument
You were going to have
Huge opposition
From the mining in
You always had that
Big block of West
Western senators
Who just said no we're not doing
And and they were really acting on behalf
Of the mining
Western Center
I feel like Tom Udall is trying not to name names
Pachulia
You know he's talking to
I think I know one of the guys he's talking
Thinking about
Harry Reid
He was the most powerful man in the Senate
Senate Majority Leader
From Nevada
He stepped down last year
I made a request to talk to read about mining
And I thought it would be formal
A lot of policy
Betalk
It was not what I was expecting
First off
He invited me to his house so we're going through the gate
Hi Tennessee Senator Harry Reid
Harry Reid lives in this gated community near Las Vegas outside there's a pond
One full of ducks flying in and out
Security detail took me to the door
Meet you thanks for having me read shows me around his house his father was a gold mine
He tells me he has a bunch of his old stuff
He pulls what looks like a headlamp off of bookshelf
Create the flame using water and carbide no aux
Oxygen useful in a mine
Are you smell outside it's garbage in there
His house is like a museum of mine
There are these photos on the wall of his hometown
It's an old mining town called Searchlight
When he was little he used to go down into the mines with his dad
What do I would say keeping company
Because he worked it was a illegal but he worked alone in the mines but nobody ever came
Or not often
I can remember
The boy in Searchlight
Deborah Lane on a couch on
I do mother would pick rocks out of his back that would have their my dad had
Silicosis from
Courts in
Peroxy working and he talked every night
I just thought all kids dad's car
He shows me this rock in a glass
Frame hang on the wall
That is a very high grade or it look like a rock
I wouldn't have noticed it anywhere else
But this one his dad gave it to
Hi and he founded it to Blossom mine
And was in town connect nuggets anywhere that's pretty much anybody with me
My father committed suicide Australian man and he gave me this
The week before he killed himself if Harry Reid's house was a mining Museum the stories in
They were not happy
Happy stories
If
I heard those stories would make me think that you wouldn't like my name you know
Well I have like mining
I wish I could give you a love story that your mind but I can't do that
My name is Harsh
And many times cruel
Add my own carbide lamp
Hold my dinner and watch them drill holes in
Rock
Do all the horribly difficult hard things you have to do
Hansel
I have warm feelings about
My memories of my
My dad
In the early 80s
Harry Reid came to washing
10 and he was from Nevada this mining state
He has this
Skip connection of Mining and
Obviously
Mining super important for Nevada
She realized if he didn't defend the mining law
It was going to change
And it was going to hurt the mining it
So we went to the mining companies
And he told them they needed to get organized
I have no presence in Washington Missouri
I met them
Reno Nevada all the
Isis
And I said you better
Search
Binghamton what's going on the Washington you're going to wind up losing everything
I told him
Going to start getting your hands
Coming to wash my meetings with some of these senators
Which Senators would you tell them meet with
All the ones
I want on my side
Every once in awhile people would look around and ask the same question were asked
Driving Stakes into something
That sounds like a way to Vanquish a vampire
This isn't the 18th
Hundreds we have
Computers
We're 50 servings
Why is this law
Still on the books we need to
Updated
Prince of royalty
And Harry Reid would be there saying you can't just tweak this thing
It would be unfair to mining cup
You Senators you don't understand mining
It has to be comprehensive reform
Comprehensive reform
Issaquah
Classic Washington
Stalling move
Time and time again
Reform would come up
And it would go nowhere
Everyone know nothing would happen the matter really I was there to do I couldn't change the law
Kasai green
I wouldn't agree
Why you smiling
And it wouldn't because you wouldn't let it well if you like them
Okay but Harry Reid
Is
John now
He's retired
So you don't want some other lawmakers there at it again
They're actually trying to push a Reform Bill through right now
Harry Reid
He knew he was going to retire someday
And this mining Lobby he helped organize
Because of it
This Reform Bill doesn't really have a chance
In the meantime the mining Law Of 1872
It's still on the
West you want mining
Because you wanted to figure out the answer
A question
Right you want to figure out
Why the mining law
Is the same as it was
Just after the Civil War
And I think you found the answer
I think it's partly because of this old narrative
When we think about the mining law who was designed for
We think of people like Harry Reid's.
Guy with his son and his
Carbide lamp
Are we think of me and Josh
In the gold pan
Steak
Imagining the wrong character
The real characters in the story today
They're big mining
Companies
Yes mining is still about being rugged entrepreneurial
You have to go out and dig
Put the money at stake
It's not about the little guys
Not anymore
After the break
We tried to get
Out of the gold
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Did you come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solution
It support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information
When is available at aecf. Org
Hello
Did you hear me
Hey Josh
Yeah this is him
A few weeks after I stake my claim I got on the phone with Josh
The guy who helped me find gold in California
And I had to admit
When we were in California you know we found the gold
I was so excited
I got Gold Fever
But I think I got a little
I mean
It doesn't really make a lot of sense you know I live in New York and
I have a job I can't I can't go
I can't go back to California and Prospect on that land
Yeah you're really trying to dump
Disclaim
Yeah I tried to get him to buy it then and there
He wasn't up for it but he said he would ask around
What I can do is talk to my partner
Maybe we can
Find someone in the group that stressed
Put up the money
To do that
I can work
Thank you so much Josh appreciate it
I want to buy a gold claim let us know Planet Money at npr.org
No low balls please
Today's episode was produced by Lena Richards and Sally helm
Our editors braggarts that and are supervising producer is Alex goldmark
Special thanks to John leshy
Luke Danielson Jim Crest
And all the other gold prospectors I talked you out west
I'm Nick Fountain xiamen thanks for listening