The other day I called up next
Hey Michael Michael works at the Mothership
A fundraiser
Airworthy Association of fundraising
Professionals there truly is an association for every
They're absolutely yes
And we were calling Michael
Because there's sort of
Existential crisis
His world right now
There's a new tax law
Ann in it
There's less of an incentive
Turn on rich people to donate to charity
And then write it off on their taxes
And told Michael's question is
Will ice not so rich people still donate
That's basically the $1000000 question
Right now
It's like we're all part of some giant economic
And Michael says we won't have the results
Until the new year
December
Is critical and the last
Suica December
Can actually get crazy
To look we're in economics show we know there's less of an incentive
Good for you to donate this
But maybe
If we ask
So
Pretty please
You can support us by going to donate the NPR. Org / Planet Money
And supporting your local NPR members
We are inches from the end of 2018 which has
Has made us all a little
Reflective
We here at Planet Money have looked into a lot of different things this year
We know that the story does not end when we turn off our microphone
Sootoday
We give you
Apologies to radio Legend Paul Harvey
The rest of the story
You know I was expecting like
Fox News and CNN and CBS to all the out here
With their like live shot and yes
Maybe we're just early maybe they don't know where he is
That is our very own Kenny Malone and Nick Fountain reporting an
Update on episode 850
T7 postal Illuminati
That was the episode where a
A listener had
Emailed us
Pharisee Theory
Which
Found out with ex
Play true
It was about a worldwide
Secretive
Postal organization the universal Postal Union or
PU
Do upu sets Mail rates all over the world and those Mail rates
Transamerica
Pretty bummed
Like it can cost more to send a package to your neighbor then for somebody in
China
To send that same package to your neighbor
There has been a
Huge update
Since we first reported this story and Nick and Kenny were on the scene as the news broke a few months ago
They went to talk to The Listener who first told us about this James
Small town
All right Nick and Kenny are going to take it
Less than a month after we publish that episode the Trump Administration announced
That they were looking into this Universal Postal Union
No we're not saying Trump listen to Planet money or not
Not saying you
Probably doesn't
What today October 17
The Trump Administration announced
We're done with the
We are planning to leave the universal postal u
So immediately we thought
The conspiracy theorist was Baker
And we found out he's attending an e-commerce Meetup in New York City right now so we rushed down here
The lower Manhattan
And we are right now waiting for Jamie smaldone
To walk out of this building
We are
A press gaggle
Up to
You guys are crazy
Today's a big day male
A momentous day in mail
A fantastic day for America
Nodejs if we're being serious here
We don't actually think of the Trump Administration listened to episode 857
Planet Money
What is more likely though is it you've been
Out there talking about how American small businesses are disadvantaged against their foreign competitors because of
Rules at the upu itself
There is a chance that you had something to do
With his decision today
How are you feeling man
I think it's incredible that
Someone can complain and get a result in this country
Majestic
Has anyone told you that you specifically had a hand in this happening
What who told you that
The president
How do you speak to the president directly but I
I've connected with people in the White House and
People in Senate and Congress end
I think
Got this was an underlying issue and really my only part was just elevating the awareness
Seems like it's
Timmy results I think
Pretty fast
Yeah so
Resolve
Like they're definitely some bad things about the universal Postal Union when it comes to like small businesses like yours but also
What kind of make
Global Mail work
Youth Administration just break Global Mail
I don't know exactly how everything is going to play out right I think that's
For the future to tell but
I think that they'll figure out a way
Continue out of the mail flow around the world I think that my
My feeling is that old
Only this one thing will get
Alright Jamie smaldone
Thanks birthday
Thanks for having me
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Karen Stephen today on the show
As we near the end of this year that
Credibly long year we look back
Support for this pod
And the following message
Just come from State Farm
Who's agent snow
That your car and home
Are more than just big purchase
They're a big part of your life
You put the time
I'm into making them your own
So now it's time to protect them
With your own person
State Farm Aid
Not only do they truly get you
But they'll be there
For you when you need
And with over 19000 age
Ginseng neighborhoods across the US
There could be
Just around the corner
Moritz statefarm.com
1 800 State Farm
State Farm
Here to help life
Go right
Hey Noel you are here to give us
An update on a story that you reported earlier this year episode number 817 we called it
The gun man okay it was a very big development in the story over the summer and then there was a very unexpected
Twist as well
So lister's might remember this episode was about a man named Cody Wilson
He was the first person to ever successfully
Make a gun
Using a 3D printer
He made a pistol
And
He took the blueprints for how to make that gun
Any put them online so that anyone in the world could access them
Fist of course made lawmakers
Very nervous because
You cannot Trace these guns which is out police officer
Consult
That's right and when lawmakers came after him in the press and said
What you're doing is dangerous
Cody's response was to tell lawmakers to go to hell like he openly mocked them in the media he said
You cannot stop me
Which I assume went over well with the government loves being told to go to hell 2015
Cody got a letter from the state
Department and it said you are in violation of the law and you need to take those blueprints offline
Sweet takes the blueprints down
But he turns around and he sues the government
He says what the government is doing is a violation of my
First Amendment so he's basically putting like a right-wing issue on the back of a
More like left-wing argue
In fact some of the top First Amendment lawyers in the country ended up represent
Okay so that
Brings us to our first update
Yes
This summer
Out of the blue the government settled with Cody Wilson and gave him permission to
Put the blueprints for the 3D printed gun back online
And then immediately a group of State Attorneys General got together
And they sued the Trump Administration
Oh wow for having allowed Cody to put the the blueprints back online
A federal judge then gets involved in says
Everyone freeze
Until
I've had a chance to look at some things and make
Point Cody takes the blueprints back offline
Andis company says
Alright fine
You're not going to let us put them online will sell them to people through the mail
And that's what they start doing
That was what was happening late this summer
And then
There was a really surprising
Twist
In Cody Wilson
Story
A 16 year old girl in Austin Texas where Cody lives
Went to a counselor
And told the counselor that she met Kodi on a pay for sex website and that the two of them had
Sex in a hotel room
And that Cody paid her for it
The police investigated
And they charge Cody with 2nd degree sexual assault
Wow yeah
And Cody left the company that he founded
So the fight
That he started he's kind of had to recuse himself
That's right
And if he's convicted Keys facing up to 20 years
And if he is convicted he's a
The Felon in which case he cannot own guns
Yeah that maybe is the final twist
Wow this is not how
I think anyone thought.
Story was going to
And now everybody was really astonished alright thanks the well by the way we did Reach Out
To Cody Wilson for comment but he did not respond
4A next update we are going to take you back to episode 845 called Redman
And in this episode we talk to a Republican strategist
Named Chris Jankowski he is
Architect of red map
Which was a republican plan to control redistricting
Monster round 2009-2010
And it allowed Republicans to gerrymander maps
Across the country
And
They hoped login a republican Advantage for at least
And it did look like it was working for years after 2010 when this
Implemented
The maps did start to favor
Republicans in a lot of different state
In fact when I started reporting on gerrymandering 2 years ago I called him a bunch of Democrats and back then in two thousand
They said what
Because of gerrymandering there is no way we can win back the house like
It's basically not even
Possible
Then
As we all saw this fall
Terms happened
The Democrats
Will win the majority
In the US House of Representatives as I was watching these results come in
I was thinking about Redman
And I was wondering
What is this mean for gerrymandering does it mean that gerrymandering does
Work
Is it not the boogeyman that we think it is
So I called back Chris Jankowski that read math guy and he told me look
These results
Let's prove what I have been trying to tell people for a long time
I've said all along
District Lines
Only so influential he said
You can't lock in partisan advantage
And it's forever
Because of how the maps are drawn
You are using
The previous 10 years really
Draw maps for the next
And
Each election cycle
The data is
Less reliable
There's population shifts
Unforeseen political issues
And when he said that I thought yeah
Population should have been forcing political issues
Does feel like we've had a few of those since 2016
And so what Chris concludes from the midterms is
That voters can overrule the match they are not all pow
But I wanted I got check so I also called Kelli Ward who is the executive director of The National
Democratic redistricting
10 committee
And she sees something very
Endorsement
As you pointed to Pennsylvania
That is a swing state
That have been gerrymandered to benefit
But after a long battle the courts recently redrew the map
Enfys less gerrymandered Maps
They got less gerrymandered results
Going into the midterms Democrats
Had only
5c
And Republicans had
But with these newly drawn Maps
The new map created A99 outcome which is rep
Representative of a
A swing state like
Pennsylvania button stays
It did not try to undo partisan gerrymandering states that remained gerrymandered States like
Ohio
And North Carolina
And Georgia and Wisconsin
Democrats want about 50
Percent of the vote in those States
But only have
You know between 25 and
30% of the seats in them
Sowell Christie's the midterm results as proof that gerrymandering is not as powerful monster as everyone says
Kelly sees the results
Approve of just
How bad it actually is
Anyway around it of course all eyes are now on 20/20
My eyes
Personally are on 2021 because
That is when they
Will be redrawn
And I asked Chris
Will will you be working on redis
Starting this next Ranger
Others
Stepped up and
And I will not be doing anything with
You sound happy about
I am very happy about that
After the break we tell you about a surprising twist in a story we've reported in
California earlier this year
And we do a lightning round
This message comes from NPR sponsor squares
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online press
Sense and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable Leo
Along with
Features including e-commerce functionality
3 + mobile app
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR
Card for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase
Chase have a website or domain
Dan you are in the DC office today we are talking on the phone Dan Charles he
Is a reporter in the DC Bureau
You reported a great story for us last summer called
Yes in my backyard or yanby
It's a movement in the San Francisco Bay Area to build more housing and
Jimmy is a play on NIMBY which is not in my backyard
Enough people who are opposed to more housing
As I understand it a few things have happened since you first reported this last summer first of all
The I guess we can call her the chief DMV of our stories Sonja trauss
She launched this whole DMV movement and when we did our episode she was running for a seat on the San Francisco board
Supervisor
And the first thing I want to know is if she want
No
She lost
Damon Thor
But there is something else
Something that was happening behind the scenes while I was reporting a tapas
And nobody even knew about
That sounds mysterious
One of the places where this housing battles been going on is the city of Lafayette east of San Francisco
There were two things first they were trying to block construction of a big apartment building on a hill overlooking town
Sonja trauss
Who's suing the city of
And the other thing was a bill that would let the commuter rail system build big apartment buildings on land that it own
Towns near Trail station
DMVs wanted this bill Lafayette was
Deposing
And I'm going to play you something
It's an audio recording of one moment at a hearing in Sacramento on this bill
Good morning Stephen Falk
I'm the Lafayette city manager representing the city of Lafayette at which is opposed to this bill
Thank you so Kate for being the representative
Of the city that is
Opposing all of this
Steve doesn't sound very like enthusiastically app
No it doesn't sound that enthusiastic because Steve fought personally really supported the bill he wants apartment
Buildings near that train station
That Renaissance you hear in his voice
Is because at that moment it was kind of a personal Crossroads for a cat sounds like he it was like a conflict between his paw
Personal beliefs and what he was required to do for him
Is job if it really was
And the first time you laid out the whole story publicly was just the other day when I met him at his home
I spoke against the bill
Because I'm a
Professional city manager and I take Direction from
City Council
But I knew after that
I couldn't do this work anymore a few months later he announced he was resigning his position as manager of
The city of Lafayette
And this is because
The city manager of the city
Fighting the DMV's was secretly a yimby himself
What kind of
His motivation was slightly
The thing that makes him want more housing near public transportation is climate change
Because if people live close to trains
Less driving
Less burning fossil fuels
Analogy I'd use this I say
The house is on fire
Andar
Children and art
Grandchildren
Are trapped in the Attic
And so what are we going to do about it
Well one thing you're going to do for
For sure is passed that law that makes
Good easier to build near the parts
It did pass by the way
And now that he's resigned you can say that out loud that he's
Pleased with that
Well thank you so much Dan
Thank you
Dancing with me here in the studio welcome
Is that how we're going to do this studio dance okay
Look I brought you in here cuz I'm about to lose my voice I've been talking
Can too much
Stand here with
What to eat
There's no whiskey in it yet
But
I brought you in here
To do a lightning rod
Because this is been quite a year
So much stuff is having so many updates
I have the paper here you found a bunch of episodes that we can update
Let's start with episode 8 6
T3 the 30
18th hole was a title
And this was your episode where you told the
The story of a celebrity golf tournament that
Kind of menorah
And it was for charity
Sponsored by the
Trump found a
It was about how money for these kinds
Charity events
Doesn't always go to
To charity
Which is exactly why the New York attorney general's office has been investigating the Trump foundation for
But they put it quotes
Persistently illegal conduct
Tumbbad yes
And just this month President Trump has
Agreed to shut down the whole Foundation
And give away the remaining money
Panda lawsuit
Okay next update its
Episode number 861
Food scare Squad
It was about the aftermath
Of last year's romaine lettuce contamination
And this year just
ForeKicks 2018 brought us another romaine lettuce
Almost exactly as it was
Describe in Arabic
Happened all over
But one thing has changed and that is that the lettuce is starting to be like
It has like a birth certificate
It says I was born in California or Arizona and so that means that if there is a
Food scare
About Arizona lettuce
10 grocery stores
Can just threw out just the Arizona lettuce
And don't have to throw
Baby steps
Okay next update
Swamp gravy
Episode 843 from May
Small town in Georgia facing hard times does The Impossible
Saves Itself by putting on a musical theater show
Sadly this town was hit pretty hard by Hurricane Michael and they had to
Cancel a few of their shows it is back on
But they're still cleaning up
Episode 860
World's longest yard sale you and Nick Drive almost 700 miles
Along the world's longest yard sale buying Trinkets and making friends along the way
But
Question hanging in the air
Lots of people fighting in about this one
Cookie jar they want to know what the cookie jar I honestly think I've never gotten more tweets on but this very issue which is that
Nick and I bought a cookie jar that looks like a cat for Stacey Vanek Smith
Everyone wanted to know if they see like
I am very sad to report that the
Cookie jar broke
Before we could give me
Metastasis
Now we're getting down is here. You back here okay we're still in the market for a cookie jar
Next up episode 877
Laws of the office
And this is how he helps a lot of people in writing in about
Erudition
Are they getting done in the sink
Remember Alice Evans professor of International Development
Suggested that we get a giant trophy
To encourage people to
To do the dishes
An hour off
And we did
Like 4 feet tall
Golden bug on top
And when all the dishes were done in the sink
The trophy which is
Appear until a lot of you asked about the
The dish trophy mostly wanted to know if it worked so that they could use it
So
Knowing that I'm biased I asked
The expert on this
Okay Devon Miller our office
I'm dying to hear what
In your professional opinion do the trophy we put in the kitchen to make people do the dishes
Work
Yes
But I think it works
Because a couple individuals were more motivated to do dishes
Because someone told me it seemed passive-aggressive
An inaccurate description
Vanilla Sky
Pinkalicious
Gotten worse
I would agree with that
I don't think it had a lasting
Should we bring it back
Totally
Okay I'm not surprised cuz he's right the dishes are not being done
Nxl 2019 trophy might come back
I hope so
One more update
More like office gossip all right
Episode is about episode 826 the Vodka proof
That one is where
We need our own homemade vodka
And then tested it against fancy vodka
How to prevent fancy. Guess I'll just marketing
Tru Sol
We forgot to use at our holiday party here at the NPR New York Bureau yes we had a cocktail competition between the
Teams at the bureau and four
Planet Money is entry
Translations
Spiral is what we called it
Nowhere near
But it's basically Jen and some of our homemade vodka
It tasted awful
It was terrible
I don't I honestly don't think
Our colleague at the indicator by my other podcast
Nail the stairs
They had
Trade stats
Spritzers
Made from 7 terrorist ingredient
And everyone was drinking and had to guess what were the 7 tariff
I didn't get
Nobody got the secret
It was honey really
We posted on Instagram all the ingredients are to you
Okay but don't make the translation
That's terrible
All right I think that brings us to not just the end of the show with the
Which means we should probably go drink some trades fat
British singer
Actually it's like a picture still in the fridge
If there is anything you want to
You're more of or less out from us in 2019 please be in touch you can email us
Dr. Org or find us on Facebook Twitter Instagram wherever we are at
Art show today was produced by Sally helmar supervising producer is you Alex goldmark
Brian Dorsett and it's the show
Special thanks to Andy Greenberg of Wired Magazine
And other lump from the South China Morning Post imallexx goldmark on behalf of everyone here
Planet Money
We want to say thank you so much for listening and we hope you have a very happy New Year