John Grant grew up in Seattle
Loved his hometown
We have
Mountains we have
Beautiful bodies
Water
Also knew the city had flaws
When I was growing up walking the streets of Seattle
It also had this enormous homeless
Population
Seattle has been struggling with housing
And this became John's key issue
He did community outreach
For the homeless he worked
For the tenants Union in 2015 John decided to take his first stab at local politics
He decided to run for City Council
So we sat down
And figure it out
How to find
You make a list of everybody you know
That could potentially
Donate the maximum amount which
Back then was $700
And
You go to that list pretty quick
It was Dawning on John that
Working with the Homeless was not
The kind of job that connected him with a lot of Rich donors
He managed to get
Mostly small donation
1015-25 $50
Small grass
Donations and John was facing the
Classic well-funded incumbent who is pulling in donations
Tech giants like Amazon Insurance in pharmaceutical companies from Real Estate Developers
In the end
John Grant managed to scrape together $75,000
His opponent
Raise 5
X out of
If we just had the resources to get our message out to more voters
It's pretty clear to me at least that we would have won that race
Yeah John did not win the race
And of course this is what happened it is one of the most depressing things about American politics
The people
John wanted to represent
They were people who didn't have money to donate
Buy business interest
They can donate all day long and
Unfortunately that is just the way the cyst
That is
Until Seattle decided
To break
The system
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Kenny Malone and today I am joined by Sarah Kliff
Most of vox's the impact podcast and herself a Seattle in Seattle
Seattle light
We are joining forces with the impact because they just launched a new season and are here to tell the story
What happens when Seattle lights
Try to solve one of the most fundamental problems in American politics
Less money you have
The less people
In the wave Seattle decided to deal with this wasn't to take big money out of politics
It was too flooded their elections with small money
Today on the show The Seattle experiment it's a story that test everything you thought you knew about the way
Way our political system
And also there will be talking dogs
Support for this podcast
In the following message come from the Annie E Casey
Sea Foundation
Developing Solutions
It support strong families and community
To help ensure a brighter future for America's shield
More information is available at aecf. Org
So of course if you are going to introduce a
Crazy new program the only way to teach people about it
Is with us
Super Ernest
Public service
The city of Seattle is giving eligible Seattle residence
$100 in democracy vouchers
They can use to
Support
Oh my God why is it always like terrible acoustic music
I don't understand why so many good bands Nirvana Pearl Jam Pearl Jam could have made a PSA
Anyway
Here is what that PSA is
In 2050
Seattle residents agreed to raise property
So that the city couldn't send money
Every single Seattle light
Half a million seattleites
Right everyone will get
For $25 vouchers that they could donate to candidates
And Seattle called these things
Democracy
So you're the man
The voucher program fellow
Yes Wayne Burnett is the executive director of the
The Seattle at
10 elections,
He was told
It is your job
To somehow make this
Democracy voucher
Your program work
I was excited on one level because it is very an Innovative program
But at the same time it was
Kind of terrifying
Because it is
Innovative program
One of the first things waynehead
To do was just like
Think through what are the goals of this program
And there were a lot
Increasing small donations
Changing who donates
Giving candidates a financial incentive to actually go out and meet voters
So when his team get
Designing
Voucher the envelopes are going to come in
And pretty quickly they realized
Even tiny decisions
Are
There's been a big
Debate here about weather
They're not that made sense
Postage paid envelope
Paid postage envelope
Seems totally trivia
But if you're trying to get more people to donate money why would you make it harder
For people to use their vouchers than its
Great
It definitely makes sense
To have returned post
The counter that is we should be encouraging
Contact
Between
Candidates
And the public
Write another one of the program's goals was to get
Candidates to act
Actually go out and talk to voters
To tell him about issues and then ask for donations
That might not happen if people can just mail their donations in
Eventually they decided okay fine better to in
Include the stamp butt
The point is Wayne and his team we're redesigning Seattle
Entire campaign Finance system
And that is not easy
Alright so this is the
This isn't that the envelope that included the voucher
When should be the final product
It's an envelope with vouchers in it in it
It says $100
Seattle voters were going to receive for blue and white
Pieces of paper
They look kind of like checks
Essentially work like
You write the name of the candidate you want to donate
And then you sign your democracy voucher over to that key
The first week of 2017 Wayne Burnett steam put these vouchers in the mail
And this was unprecedented
No one in the country had tried anything like this
Seattle with flooding it's mailboxes
With millions of dollars
Worth of fake money
They could magically turn into real money
Four candidates
Here we go
City council position 8 and we have the two candidates
And we will start off
Sabbatical
Alright the alphabetical advantage
Remember John Graham
That advocate for the homeless
Ran for the city
Council and lost
Well-funded opponent well after Seattle launched this radical funding
John Grant decided to get back in the game
This is him from
A candidate forum
I put forward a proposal requiring 25% of all new development to be affordable to working-class people
I have also put
This time around
John wasn't running against a well-funded in
You got a different kind
Thank Jah
So one of the things that I'm calling for is
Real solutions Teresa Moscato
A first-time candidate
I'm calling for us to take every parcel of developable available land and turn it into a four
Affordable housing now thing about Visionary Civic programs to empower underdogs
Sure they help out underdogs like John Grant but they also bring out brand-new underdogs
Looks like
Teresa Moscato
I'm a woman
I'm a person of color
I'm a renter I still pay student loans
I'm 37
That someone like me wasn't going to be a
Expected to sell
Finance a campaign
Really was a green light
Lego arguably the Democracy vouchers were already working
The two candidates vying for this City Council seat
Both would have had trouble raising money in the pack
But now
John Grant and Teresa Mosqueda just needed to get out there
To knock on doors
And convince voters to hand over their voucher
Do you remember the first door you knocked on and asked for the voucher who really do remember that door
John Grant says there was a newspaper reporter
Tagging along
Watching this historic moment
One of the first times anyone ever has asked for democracy
Jonathan this rapidly gentrifying neighbor
And
Sweet we knock on the door and this this guy hit a mustache I don't know why I remember that but I do
Just a gentleman with a mustache
Looks at me and I gave him my my picture about
Are housing crisis center
Eventually John turns the conversation to
The Democracy vouchers
May I ask for you know $100 in democracy vouchers
Because I looked at me and he also looked at the reporter and
Was like sure
And he gave me one hit me one $25 voucher
And
Close this door I knock
The rest of the block and that was the only voucher that I got that today
Answer the reporter was like is that it and I'm like that's it
To be fair John's luck got better over the next
Few weeks meanwhile Teresa Mosqueda is also out there knocking on doors
She remembers voters being genuinely sad
Surprised that a real candidate
Would show up in purse
It's really you on this flyer you're here at my door and I was like yeah as a migrant
Disney myself
And there's a hold on I'll be right back
Find the Democracy vouchers in a pile on their table of mail
And they come back and they
Fill it out there right at the
Edwin door-knocking went like this
The program was great
But
Has these candidates for canvassing
It started to become clear
The voucher program
Had a pretty big problem
Imagine if you will knocking on the apartment door of the
Ross in Dallas
Hi Ross analysis
Are young they're politically engaged
They are the exact
Kind of Voters that John Grant
Teresa mosquito would love
To win over
And yet
If John or Teresa had shown up to their house
And asked about
The vouchers I don't want to say
You definitely threw them away
I know I definitely remember getting it in the mail because
It said it looks yeah
It seemed a lot of Seattle lights
We're like Alice
They're getting these vouchers
Mistaking them for junk mail
And then throwing the
What candy was Seattle they were
Recycling
Remember the program has never been attempted
From lot of people the idea of cutting $100
In the mail
From their government to reform campaign Finance
Was
Too good to be true
But it wasn't just
Regular old photos getting
Frankly I thought it was news about recycling so I recycled it
That's right
Even city council candidate Teresa Moscato recycled her vouchers
And home
Later did I think to myself
I think that might be the vouchers and I went back and pulled it out
And I think here it would help
To talk about the
The design of the envelope that these
Came in eye
Have a copy in the studio with us right now it's like as long as a normal envelope little taller a little bit fatter to be on
Honest it kind of looks like a thing you get from
Publishers Clearing House there is an official
Seattle City logo appear and then also it says
Your democracy vouchers are here
We look at it with wind burn at the guy in charge of deciding the envelope the program the whole thing
It has an opening envelope
And then a circle with the number $100 in
Brett I'm going to be honest Wayne
I think I would throw this away
Will you did a lot of other people
That might be an undersea
Statement win estimates that about
75% of
Seattleites either Thruway or misplaced
Their democracy
You could have written on this
Don't throw this away
Are usually
At first I didn't know they were ski
Cancel work like one
But you could have tried something like that did anybody float that I don't think so
Just brainstorming okay
Spitballing
The trash problem was a huge prop
But it was not always fault
The way this program was written up required that these vouchers go out in January
That was 10 months
Before the actual election
But as reports started to come in that
Maybe this is a bigger problem than you thought
When is office
Okay we're going to run a campaign to remind
People there is a way to replace lost out
They printed up a bunch of posters that looks like
Somebody had lost
A dog except
Instead of a dog there was a picture of
Democracy vouchers and then a pro democracy voucher group
Also made some ads about lost voucher
That's my human she's looking for democracy vouchers
This had with also dog
Featured a talking French bulldog in a red vest
Bitstamp around explaining how to replace your lost democra
Mercy doctors
By the dog's owner digs through the couch cushions
For her loss.
But she's not going to find them because I ate them
But it's not a big deal all she has to do is called 2:06
It's so good what is up with all the dog heads in Seattle though I don't understand
It took a lot of work but
Seattle
Eventually
Dealt with the Lost voucher
The advertisements
Of course but they also gave John and Teresa away
Need to show up at people's doors
Send help them replace lost voucher
On the spot
And that man
John and Teresa were collecting serious money
Remember the first time John ran
Before democracy vouchers
He only raised about $75,000
That entire year I
I didn't have a staff
It was just me
But in 2017
John raised
$300,000
In democracy
I had a campaign manager at a field director
Field organizers and you know we knocked on $50,000 and that's a lot of one-on-one conversations
What's realtor
And John's opponent
Teresa Mesquita remember she was a first-time candidate you still paying off your student loans brand new to this stuff
And itchy also managed to raise
$300,000
Democracy voucher
So if you actually I can show you
Chart that shows
How much money came in
And she showed me the chart so I could see how little of her own money
She had to put into the campaign
It's 361.
So that is B
Because I spent $250 of my own
Text myself
I use a hundred of my democracy.
And then there was an $11 face
So that's worth 306
$51
Is what I paid and after 10 months of democracy voucher problems
And solutions
Election day finally came and
The campaigns were
Teresa Moscato
She remembers being at our watch party
Looking up at the TV
And it showed us at that night at 62% of the vote
And people were just jumping with joy screaming hugging each other
And then we had a mariachi band
It was amazing oh hell yeah
Teresa ended up beating John Grant
But honestly either of these candidates was a win for
For democracy.
Neither was an established
Politician
Neither could rely on a long list of
Rich donors
The bandar campaigns they actually knocked on Doors
And met voters
Changing who runs for office getting candidates out into
The community
These were goals of the program but arguably the most important matter
Patrick was
Did people actually use these vouchers
Were there more people donating
Two campaigns what is different
About the number of people donating in Seattle now that you guys have democracy vouchers
Well bottom line is a dramatically increase the number of campaign country contributors
Again Wayne Barnett the guy in charge
Triple we had roughly eighteen thousand people who contributed and sure that's a lot of people
But
As Sarah pointed out to Wayne
Seattle
500000 residue
So I know it is
True Wayne that increase the number of contributors
What's also true that 97% of people didn't use their democracy
Christie vouchers
You know it is if the glass half-full glass
Half-empty thing
Classic on the one hand we had more contributors than ever
On the other hand we still did not have
Participation at the levels that the framers of the program had hoped
But I am a glass-half-full
I just want to drink the empty half of
What is class though because like
Everyone got free money to give away
And basically nobody did it like
The vast majority
That makes me feel worse
Like I said we increased our number of contributors
Dramatically
To me that is
Success
I will
Readily
Admit if it is
In the third or fourth
Cycle of the program if we are not seeing
More participation
Maps
I think that might actually
Cut the other way
All that being said
When will admit there is a pretty reasonable
Critique of the pro
It is not a cheap
Program to run
If there are a lot of costs associated with
Printing mailing and processing these vouchers
Which hopefully we can reduce once we get
Electronic system in place but
I would
Tell you that it is not too cheap for
In 2017
Seattle lights
Gave candidates about $1000000 in
In democracy
The administration of the whole program
What's also about $1000000
That means half of the Democracy voucher money went to administrate
And those are taxpayer dollars that could fund other things like
Schools are roads are
Affordable housing
Oswin said they are moving to an electronic system for the next election
Stomach cut out
Printing and mailing costs
The first they have to build the electronic
Excess demand that cost
Even more money
So when admits there
Are definitely
Bleach write-offs
Yeah
But I mean I think
The question is your municipality are they willing to
To pay 2 to get more people involved in the political process
Seattle made the decision that were willing to
Pay for that
Good
I think that's every music
Right exactly
Seattle appears to have weighed the pros and cons for itself
And has decided
Democracy vouchers
Are worth it
There'll be some tweaks for the city
Is going to continue with
One final quick
Story about why Seattle might have decided this
Was a success
It is true that not as many people use the vouchers
Set the city hope
But a lot of people who did use the vouchers
There's the kind of people who don't have a lot of power in American
They were able to exercise their voice in a totally new way
There was this one woman I met in
In Seattle who really drove this point home for me
Her name is Gina Owens
And I'm
Years Young
Gina have been politically active
4 years
She worked on housing and Healthcare issues
But before 2017 Gina has never donated to a campaign
She's on disability
Takes care of her 3 grandkids
So right now my finances are under $2,000 a month
Then raising three kids know that was no way I was going to find that huh
The dollar
It would not go to a candidate
When Gina got her democracy
She took them to a candidate for us
She wanted to give them to John Grant
Actually
I kind of made a big deal out of it
She waited until the Forum was over
Locked up
To the podium where they were all sitting and
David
Two vouchers
So how did it make you feel to have the opportunity to do that for the first time
Bill Gates
Got a policy experiment you think we should know about you can hit us up at Planet Money at NPR. Org we
Are also on Twitter and Instagram at Planet Money and
If you want to hear about other wild policy experiments that other cities are using to solve big challenges
You should absolutely check out the new season of Sarah Kliff podcast
Thanks Kenny yeah my colleagues and I add boxes but the
The past year crisscrossing the country
Looking at places
Seattle South Carolina Vermont that have
Try doing something radically different
And we see what happens next
You can find the impact wherever you listen to your podcast
Star new season
Today at school Barclays are supervising producer Brian Dorsett is our editor this episode was produced by Planet Money zalek
Taxi Horowitz Ghazi and vaux's bird Pinkerton and Jillian Weinberger
We also had editing help from Amy gross.
I'm Sarah Kliff and I'm Kenny Malone
Thanks for listening
Support also comes from fidelity
As a Fidelity wealth manager
You get a dedicated advisor
To help grow amp
Protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes
And make clear recommendations
Thanks for your full fight
Learn more at fidelity.
Comsol
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
One of the interesting things about the actual design of these
Is
But there's a little bit of language that is like a subtle reminder
That actually selling these vouchers
Is a big nose
Wayne Barnett told us that
Expressly illegal
In fact that he and his team thought a lot about just how much they should remind
I think the balance we were trying to strike was between that desire to
Deter
Fraud
And also
Competing desire to have people use their vouchers without fear
Write like there's a version where you send someone this wonderful democracy voucher but it's just in giant printed like