So so you know how to milk a cow by hand
Oh yeah
Oh yeah yeah
Andy novakovic spent his Summers as a kid working on
His grandparents
Dairy farm in Wisconsin
And he's still in the dairy world he is now a dairy Economist at Cornell University
What percentage of
Economist would you say are able to milk a cow by hand
Well probably you know close to 100% or able but 99.9% wouldn't have the fog
How to get started in the pantheon of milk related economic disasters there is one that rises
This is about the rat
And Andy had a ring sights
This is one of those
Slow-moving
Trainwreck
That you can see coming from a mile away
It was 1976 Jimmy Carter was running for president
And he started floating this idea
What are the ways Carter proposed giving farmers in
Raise the price of milk by about six sense
Per gallon
It was kind of a lot of the time now it's really was on the edge of that it was a big enough number that it sounded like one of these campaign price
Promises that you really didn't expect they would actually be
Fulfill still campaign promise
That's what we call those
This was not just political panda
There is an argument that our country has to be able to produce
Its own food
Cuz if our Farmers go out of
Business and we become reliant on other countries for food
Then that is the kind of National Security risk
It's our country has a tradition of programs to help
What do you need to Vacaville
Is it is one thing to
To provide
Stability
It is another to step into the market in
In a big way at maybe the wrong time
Playing with price controls
Is playing with fire
Nevertheless
When Carter got elected
He goes all
The retail price of milk
Is going up more than $0.06 a gallon soon
It's going up because the
Ngu you hear of it and
Do you like smack your forehead oh boy
Here we go it was pretty hard to predict
That it would get as bad as it got
But every Instinct I had said that I meant so sure this is going to work out so well
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Karen Duffin and I'm Kenny Malone
Today on the show The Story of what happened when
President of the United States
Decided he was going to help America's farmers
White buying milk
Lots of milk
It is a case study in what happens when price controls
Run full-speed into the realities of the market
There will be a cave in Kansas City a van down by the river
And a touching Exchange
Between Martha Stewart
And Snoop Dogg
Where do you buy government
You don't buy it you got to be on a special mailing list
Support for this podcast
Send the following message come from the Annie E Casey
Sea Foundation
Developing Solutions
It support strong families and community
To help ensure a brighter future for America's chilled
More information is
Is available at aecf
. org
So it's 1977
Jimmy Carter has announced his plan to help
Farmers in Congress is like wait no we also love the farm
Pennsylvania pass a law saying
But they want the price of milk to go up automatically
Every six
It's one thing for politicians
How to say we want the price of milk to go up
But
The government then actually have to figure out a way to
Step into the
This market and make it happen
So it is fundamental economics
Again are dairy economist
You got two levers you can pull on you can do something to make
Demand greater
Or you going to do something to make
Supply less
Either one should get you a higher price
Lever1
Lower the supply
You could do what they do in Canada and say hate no more milk
Can only produce
So much mail
But this is America we don't do milk
Quotas
No lever1
Okay lover 2
More demand
You can try to convince the public that they want to drink more milk
Does it look delicious right glass
Easier solution Maybe
The government could
Just start buying a ton of milk themselves
Yeah this was generally the approach
That we would use to support other kinds of farm into
Is the government
Goodbye up
Play massive amounts of
Corn or wheat
And then just throw it into a silo until we needed it
For some reason
But that does not work for me
Because milk starts going bad the minute it comes out of the cow fell so mostly water so you got to haul it around
And in those like
Gas tankers
The federal government wouldn't have the foggiest idea what to do with
Tanker loads
Of milk what would the government do if you drove this into downtown Washington and said here you go
So the clever Folks at USDA said what if we went down the supply chain one step
And looked at
Dairy products
That are storable
So the basic question was
What kinds of milk products can the government buy and store
Butter was one nonfat dry milk
And
Cheese and in particular
Shutter type
Soca raise the price of milk the government basically opened up the world's largest
Cheese shop
Powder milk and barbecue
So the the way this program work
Literally
Is
The federal government
Put on a piece of paper that says
We will buy as much
Cheese butter or nonfat dry milk
As you want to sell to us
At these prices
Our operators are standing by
Let us know
The USDA figured out that if
They paid about 39 bucks
For a 40 lb block of cheese
But it would have this ripple effect
Government buys more cheese
Cheese makers buy more milk
And the resulting demand just
Pushes the price of
The government is creating a price
And in order to do this
They have to be willing to buy
Oliver
Anybody wants to sell them
At this price
And if you're a cheese Cellar and you hear this that someone's going to buy your cheese at this high price you're like
Minnesota my crappy is cheese at that price
So to prevent this the government said look
If we're going to buy your cheese
First you have to meet with Bob
Yes
I started in 1967
With us
50a and I was hired as a cheese grater
You were hired someone to show up with a metal snake
A grater
We're used to do quality checks on
This must be a common confusion in the Indus
Yeah greater yeah
Bob Asher Brock
Was one of the government's cheese grater
He spent 30 years
Testing and tasting cheese for the United States
State government yes this is a real job
It sounds amazing
Are you pretty annoying to eat cheese with like are you the most picky cheese eater
In your group of friends
I am absolutely not
I will eat any cheese
In fact if you seen my shape you would know that I eat enough
To keep the tank full
Bob's
Job was to make sure that all of the cheese met
USDA grade-a
Cheddar stand
The right moisture level the proper shade of yellowish-orange
The correct flavor
Profile so if you wanted to sell cheese to the government Bob would show up
With this life
Halo Rod called
Cheese Trier
And you inserted into the block or the barrel or whatever
Turn it and you pull out a core of cheese
The core sample of cheese
And that's what you grade and they're 17 flavor defects that could happen in cheddar cheese
If I can tell you what we had a rejected for flat bitter you Steve multi old milk
Rudy Rudy
That sounds great taste like apples
That sounds lovely you don't want that no
Comet Alex our way tank weedy onion Barney
Lipase and sulfite
And you can taste all of those things in a piece
You betcha
Bob says the number one flavor defect he had to look out for
What's acidity
It was allowed
Not too much
Penny White
The government had its plan in play
Play Spit was ready to start buying cheese
And it took
A few years
But a flood of cheese starts
So much cheese
That Bob
Starts having
To spend more and more time on the road because he has to
Go to the cheese to grate it
His colleagues are drowning in cheese
And they go to their bosses they like we need more cheese graters
Until they try to hire more
I travel 39 States and I was gone as long as 10 weeks at a time doing that so getting people to do it
Was always a challenge
The young people do they say it while I can't go out with a girl or I can't go out with a guy because I'm on the road all the time who's got time for
Dating when you're traveling around eating
Now I think she's eating is better than dating
I don't disagree with you I don't disagree with you
More graders
Grading more cheese
Is that the government then buys
But then we had that issue was storing stuff
I mean every Warehouse in Wisconsin was
All our area around to everybody hits
Even though
Beverage dist
Distributors
They had Jesus
I mean we have cheese and every Cold Storage in the United States including the caves in Kansas that were full of it
The caves
In Kansas
Yeah
The underground caves
The government of the United States of America
Had caves
Full
Of cheddar cheese
And when news gets out that the government is filling a
A cave with
Cheese
The Press goes nuts
Because this is exactly what
People think of when they think of a government program gone awry
Like this is the original bridge to nowhere
This is a cave
Full of cheese
In Kansas City
Can I had to
Of course you did
I am currently about 35 feet underground
In an old converted Limestone mine
It is the size
Of 120
Football field
Government cheese
That's pretty good
You don't do that huh
I've never thought about it this is Dan Callahan
He's been working here since the 1970s
Since the cheese Dubai
And he tells me these were never government-owned
But one day
I rented out a ton of cave space
And then cheddar cheese started to show up massive blocks of the stuff
How it after palette in fact
Do you remember the exact room it went into
Oh yeah
We walk inside massive columns
It looks like something
The Lord of the Rings dwarves bill
And it is also very cold
Good for the government cheese
Haha
17 feet 16b then says the cheese took up about
An acre
Bullock space
Suggest
Wall2wall
Florida L'Oreal
And then as you kept feeling that you just worked your way right back out
Until there's no more room for you to be in this room right
By the early 1980s the dairy Support Program
With costumes
Taxpayers around 2 billion dollars a year
The government was buying one in every four pounds of a country's cheddar cheese
They actually had to rent out space in multiple cat
At one point
The government was storing
2 lb of cheese for every
Single Americans
By this point
Jimmy Carter was out of office
And the Ronald Reagan team was stuck
Dealing with you
Cheese
And not all of it with aging well
There was an in
Credible press conference
Agriculture sector
Teri Jon block went before reporters
And held up a giant hunk of cheese
Like it was a national emergency
You see that
Steak and cheese
We've got six
A million of these
Shut the government down
What's mole
Is deteriorating
We can't find a market for
Finding a market for this
Stuff is in fact a pretty fascinating
Because it's getting rid of government surplus
Anyting
Is an economically
Tricky thing
Exactly so the thing that the government was concerned about is what's called commercial this
Again Economist andina Vacaville
And he says the government could not just release a flood of surplus cheese on
Into the market because it would
Crushed cheese producer
Jeep imagined the cheese company that's in the business selling cheese is going to say
What's the deal are you took away my customer is as you know important to me
This leaves a couple of options
You could destroy the Surplus but
That was pretty bad
Or you can try to get your Surplus Goods
Two people who were not going to buy it anyway
And that's you won't be
The flooding anyone's Market
When we have a surplus of grain or soy or even powdered
We can send that stuff overseas
As part of foreign
But she's
Just doesn't travel well
So the government gave a bunch
Schools
The army
This was not putting
Even a dent in the Surplus
So they created a brand new
Special program
To give the cheese away through Food Bank
The idea was that
If you give this food
Do people who suffer from food in
Security
Then maybe it is going to go to somebody who wasn't going to buy
So you're not hurting the market
But the problem Andy says
Was that a lot of this was not easy to give away cheese
There were 40 lb
Block that
500lb Barrel
So you can imagine you know you're not just going to roll down one of these barrels down
7th Avenue in New York City and say anybody wants
You just have a big knife help yourself
So instead the cheddar cheese was processed
That helps it keep longer
And then it was repackaged in
2 + 5 lb like
Bricks and
This is what people will remember as Government
When a government starts to give away hundreds of millions of pounds of cheese
People notice
The great cheese giveaway began today in California
San Francisco is one of three cities in which needing people lined up to get the Surplus cheese
This footage
Is amazing
Massive crowds of people being handed bricks of cheese and it's
The most government packaging you will ever see just like brown cardboard some
Black USDA stamps on it
State official estimated 300000 people
Will get a taste of today's
It is this moment
The government cheese
Truly enters the American pledge
As we unloaded the caves
Full of this stuff
Government cheese started to show up everywhere
Food banks
Schools
Military mess halls for a lot of people who grew up in
1970s
80s you cannot overstate how influential government cheese
We're ready for you
Many listeners may remember Saturday Night Live
Matt Foley has played by
Chris Farley the
World's worst motivation
I'm here to tell you that you're going to end up
Eating a steady diet of government cheese
I'm living in a van down by the river
Government cheese
Starts to show up in all kinds of
Popular culture
A short story by Junot Diaz
Clear the government cheese from the refrigerator if the girls government cheese also shows up in
Tons of song
After that government cheese steak
But maybe government cheese has most
Surreal moment
Came on a television show where Martha Stewart
Cook stuff with snow
Can you stop
Suburban girl wears a knife
That's government government cheese
Is became a symbol of a crappy government
It was processed
He's kind of like a
Rekha Velveeta but
Remember the raw ingredients
Word grade a cheddar cheese
Some of it personally certified
Eyebobs
It was 10 times better than felt I hate
Okay it's got It's okay okay
Where would I buy my truck without Velveeta but I'll tell you
The government process loaf was 10 times a hundred times better
It was some of it almost tastes like natural cheddar
I mean it was really really good product
This is why there is
Is also a community of people who are
Still obsessed with government cheese
Internet chat boards trying to find some
Incomparable restaurants claiming they have a recipe for it
At one point Donnie Wahlberg of the New Kids on the Block Set
Quote
There's nothing like
Like it the way it is
Melts
For a hamburger
There is nothing
Kids doing the dance
Is carrots doing the dance
But here is why government cheese
Has become a kind of parable of how government intervention in markets can have
Like Butterfly Effect
In 1976
Jimmy Carter got on the stage and said something
Seemingly innocuous
And then within 5 years
The government was spending
Billions of dollars
Filling caves with cheese
But they could not get rid of
Fast enough
Well I think there's
There's
2 basic lessons
Andy Nabokov
1 is
It's really hard to balance
What you want to do
Socially or politically
With what you can get away with economically
The second lesson
Is
You got to pay attention to the unintended consequences cuz they can come back and bite you and bite you hard
Even if
That bite just looks like some delicious cheese
That was the unintended consequence that was fun
But
The bike came in terms of how much it cost
For that opportunity
Very very expensive
Indeed
After the break
How the government finally got out of this mess
And why the government may be getting back into the cheesecake
Support for this podcast and the following message come from fidelity
As a Fidelity Wealth Management
You get a dedicated advisor to help grow and
Protect your way
Find ways to minimize the impact
The taxes and make
Clear recommendations for your
Full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage services
Is LLC
The government cheese caves started to empty out
The guaranteed milk price
I've been going up automatically every 6 months
Was eventually Frozen
But that does not mean the government
Add fix the problem
The thing about price controls is that once you start them they are really really hard to unwind
So we have a few of the cement Surplus and now you have the political
Problem how do we
How do we get this cat out of the
The government asked economist
Including Andy novakovic
Figure out how it
Could get out of the cheese buying busy
Without devastating
The farmers they were trying to help in the first
This is a basic supply and demand
The government was demanding an unnatural amount of milk
And so farmers worst
Supplying an unnatural amount of
One part of the solution then was to
Jet Li get that milk supply.
To persuade Farmers to produce
Plus we literally paid them money to stop producing milk
That did some good
And then on the other side the Government tried to replace some of their artificial demand
Foremilk with new
Real demand for
Like
Hey
People of America
Wouldn't you like to drink more milk
We took
A small amount of money from every Dairy Farmer
Collected on every pound of milk they sold
And we created the national Dairy
But this is what gave us you know the got milk in the milk mustache and all those
Slider biconic programs that we remember
That is right
Jimmy Carter's campaign promise to help farmers in 1976
Not only gave us government
Cheese
But also
Knock knock
With a few other programs and
And sometimes things eventually got under
And the government put the milk support program on a kind of permanent
Suspension
These days
If the government wants to help farmers
What you'll generally hear about our direct subsidies as opposed to
Buying cheese
Yes but the government has
Tended to stay away
From buying cheese as solution
That is until
Last month
The White House
Who's coming to the aid of farmers hurt by its own Hardline trade policies
The Trump Administration says today it will make an estimated 12 billion dollars
Government assistance available the Trump Administration announced
In order to help farmers being hurt by Trump's tariffs
The government may be making some food purchase
Just this week we finally learned some of the details
There is currently about 85 million dollars earmarked
Tu by dariann
And distributed to places like schools and
Nope to be fair that's probably not enough
Start filling caves again
But there is a chance
With the government
Maybe in the business
Of government cheese
Do the cheese cave please episodes produced by Alexa
Gazi Nick Fountain and Rena Cohen
Are supervising producer is Alex goldmark and our editor is Bryan tour stats
You can see pictures of the cheese cave
It's huge they're literally train tracks leading into it can fit a train car
You have to follow us on Instagram we are at Planet
You can also follow us on Twitter and Facebook
Also at Planet Money
Uncaring definition
I'm Kenny Malone
Thanks for listening
No I'm not sure if you know if you've ever seen a 500 lb steel barrel of cheese
No there is a bunk what they call a bunghole
It's only about a 3 inch diameter hole
We used to plug
True that bunghole to get our sample
Well we got some real
Crafty guys that start putting 40 lb blocks
Specialties right under the Bonneville
I mean there was all kinds of tricks that you