You know who you don't meet much anymore
Alchemy
Alchemist people who look for ways to turn random stuff into gold
Rebecca the Middle Ages you met him all the time
Closing those days Alchemist with
Searching for the Philosopher's Stone
They thought there was this sort of
Mystikal
Compound
Into valuable metals like gold
John emsley is a chemist
And science writer
Alchemist State looked everywhere for this
Philosopher's stone
And there was one material that
What's golden
And abundance
Everyone has it
Alchemists were always fascinated by the golden stream is it with the golden stream
He is talking about urine
Back in 1669 there was this one Alchemist Hennig brand
And as the
The Story Goes
He had
A plan to turn urine into gold but
She needed a lot of pee for it
Sonax
Surely he borrowed some from his neighbors
Hilton put these bowls out by 10
Yes
And then he even got the local Convent to pitch in
And one evening he bought a large volume of urine down
It did not
Turn into gold magically but it did turn into something they did not expect
The books of a ball
Wax and suddenly off Candice mysterious compound
Glows in the dark
Close in the dark
But that
Was not all
Spontaneously flammable
This is seeming a little magical he thinks so he and his friend took this
Glowing
Ball of urine
And they paraded around Europe
I mean it
Tell everyone what it was but
Created quite a stir
In part because
Though he had no clue what it actually was
I did not stop him from
Improving your sex life and things like that
Penny didn't know it at the
Time but
What he had discovered
Was father
Number 15 on the periodic table
Symbol is the letter
P phosphorus
Or phosphate and its uses
Before you can pretty much everything
Some nasty things like bombs
Apparently
It explodes when it hits the air
And the poison sure but also it's nice things to
Flame retardant food additive some Pharmaceuticals M Coca-Cola contains phosphoric acid
So there's nothing to it sometimes
Places well no phosphorus no Velveeta
More importantly no phosphorus no life nothing could live without phosphate because it is part of DNA
It's part of Who We Are
But this thing we would all die without this element
You can't make it out of anything
And there's no substitute
It's either phosphorus
Or nothing
And
Not to scare you but there is a limited Supply
And we're using a lot of it
So
Some people are a little worried
Since we have a limited amount of
We know that he would not be careful
We going to be in real trouble trouble
Put a capital T that rhymes with p and that stands for phosphorus
Robert Smith
On the show we scour the Earth for one of the building blocks of the modern world and life itself
Hospice make glow-in-the-dark but it is not easy to find it is poisonous it explode and it is mainly concentrated
Ruled by a king it is a place that almost no Outsiders have been
He will take you there to the world's biggest to mine and we find a tiny band of Dreamer
Alchemist Hennig brand
This message comes from NPR sponsor squares
Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their own website
Using customizable layout
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editor
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online press
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Define the phosphorus
You've got to follow the money
Jeremy Grantham has the money
He runs a big hedge fund
And he's known for predicting things like the dotcom bust and the tooth
Crisis
He's also known for his pessimism
His latest concern
I understand that you like to talk about
I don't I can't say I'd like to talk about phosphorus
One of a long list of other
Pessimistic topics that I seem to have
Cut myself
Involved with
Phosphate again that's the more usable form of phosphorus
Phosphate is a huge mark
About 76 billion dollars
Most of it goes into fertilizer
Which is actually a little problematic because
Farmersville just
Pile it on to their crops because they know that plants can only use
Small amount of it at a time
So most of that fertilizer
80% of it
Washes right off into rivers and
The ocean
What's the phosphorus goes to the ocean
Some like it disappears
Extremely hard to get out of seawater
Show all the sponsors going to waste
If that Jeremy worried
We're on a finite planet with
Finite Reserve
A phosphorus
Amway are mining it and running through the supply
That should make
Sahara
The back of everybody's
Nike Brussels
They're widely ranging estimates for just how close we are to the phosphorus cliff
Maybe we got 30 years
And we have three hundred years
It's hard to estimate
This is Jeremy
Weather is
42 years 62 years are 82 years doesn't really matter
We have to change our way of growing food
We've known for a while that phosphorus was limited
But the price was cheap and the problem just seem to
So distant so people are kind of like me
I'll do with that problem later
Then
Happen the financial
Crisis and along with many commodities
Phosphate prices Spike
Which because
The fertilizer made food prices Skyrim
Now everybody's talking about phosphorus
What's the developing World in 2008
And the price of phosphate Rock Spot by 800%
I would argue
But that was
A shot across the bow
That was the first warning
The planet Earth
That we are beginning to run out
And of course if
You didn't take that warning you could read the US Geological Survey paper
That came out the next year predicting Peak
Phosphorus was just
24 years away
Meaning we would hit maximum production in 2033
And after that
Good luck
The estimate was revised and the price dropped
But people were paying at
Pension now
And all eyes
We're on
Morocco
Has about 75% of the Wolves high grade
Easy together
Phosphate
And that's a pretty
Overwhelming concentration that makes
The whole of OPEC
Look like ficus
Hikers
Small fry
I just got to the controls most of our phosphate everybody wants to know what what the Moroccans are doing
And
It it turns out that they don't want to tell you a lot
This is Brandon Burrell he's a freelance journalist
And he did a story for business week
About phosphorus
Couple years ago
And everybody I talked to in the industry
Sort of feels like you know their there they're trying to use this
Secrecy to their advantage
That that way they can dictate the price
The Morocco's basically playing poker with their father
Express
And the rest of us just have to make our best bet
That's exactly right
A little geography
The phosphorus is valuable cast
A phosphorus
Is split between Morocco
And Western Sahara
Which is an area that Morocco says belongs to them
Locals
Yuan very few other countries
The fight is gone unsettled for more than 25 years
Brendan was able to sneak into the mines in Morocco and
Look around some
As soon as he landed in Western Sahara get out of the plane and immediately at the airport work sort of
Swarmed by like
Three or four security officers
Who followed him the entire time
The only thing that he could see was this this one thing
Often the disc
There is literally a conveyor belt in the middle of the desert
It looks like a mirage in the in the desert
It's just this
Strange line that you can see flashing across the rising and
A few points you come closer and you can see is it you know it looks like
You know like a
Supermarket checkout conveyor belt but it's gigantic
A conveyor belt carries phosphate from the mines in the desert
To the ocean to ships for transport
It's 61 miles long
Tennessee from space
Probably be seen from our satellite
It's amazing
Who put a link on the website
And the future of the world's food
Supply rides in part on that conveyor belt
The Americans won't say how much of
The phosphate is in the western Sahara
Conveyor belt
Purses in Morocco
What date did tell Brendan was lose money on that mine
You know we
It's only a few percent of our total production
Do you believe them
No
Pizza
Way too much security light
Military grade including checkpoints and landmines
To believe that what they're guarding isn't incredibly valuable
Whatever the price tag is
Boils down to
The king of Morocco
Controls most
Of the world's phosphate
It's kind of amazing that that
Our future food food food supply depends so much on what happens in this
One country
If only there were some other supply of phosphate
Other than
The ocean works too hard to get in
Morocco who knows what
The future there is
Some other little
Fountain of phosphor
4S
There is someone who has a solution
This
Kim Nix
From Vermont
We're all our own now little fertilizer products
Factories
Probably not going to put that on my Tinder profile anytime soon
But technically Kim is right
Invest your listeners is where we will bring you
A little drop
After the break
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One Capital One
Is reimagining banking I offering accounts with no fees or minimums that can be opened from anywhere in
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Black guy from Middle Ages
Hennig brand
The man who collected his neighbors urine boiled it up and discovered phosphorus
Weirdly he's not the last person to do that
I heard about someone who is doing this
Today in Brattleboro Vermont
Remember Kim who we just heard from you had actual like
Tanks of urine in your front yard yeah big ones
Yeah big ones for a long time
To explain how those
Pink's of urine got into her front yard we should go back to Kim's child
She has long been intrigued by Sanitation
She said she would visit her aunt in New York and when I was little and I saw those skyscrapers
The very first thing I thought about always was like how do they flush the toilet
Kim actually did her college thesis about toilets that compost waste
And in 2012 she in a man named eight Noah Hayes who made composting toilets
Founding a research institute
The rich Earth Institute
That seems like it's kind of a play on
Yeah they actually originally wanted to call it the poop stool
The koopsta 2.11
It is funny but it is not quite a
Right away he knew that the first project was going to be a urine project that we wanted to start with urine
The urine is really where it's at
That is a verb
He and several others told me
Poop is
Problem Child
The toilet
Transported
Pathogens
But you're in on the other hand you know urine is actually fairly sterile
It's when it gets combined
With poop that it becomes more dangerous
This is Rebecca writer of former board member of The Institute
Keep talking
Saying bad things about poo today I've heard a lot of people say bad things about purchasing
So it sits separate
They're better than together
It outside
Like a couple you always love but they hated being with each other
So well you're happy that they're not
And I guess that's the key part as Hennig brand stumbled on
Urine is not
Just wait
It is sort of gold because it is filled
With lots of valuable nutrients
Verses of the story is the
The phosphorus
We get phosphorus from phosphate rocks and those are external
Soil which
Plants with
Us
The phosphorus that we eat goes straight
Threw us right into our urine
And even Kim's idea is that if we can
Recycle that you're in instead of flushing it
We have
Sustainably
Fertilizer
Forever
It's an idea some bigger companies are experimenting with working directly with sewage plants in big cities like London and
Chicago
But there in Vermont
They're taking a more
Hands-On
So weak
Created the urine Brigade
And literally that was our committee
They're like six of us we sat on my back porch
Who said how are we going to get this urine from people what are we going to do
Our biggest fear was definitely that
That we would become like
Certified
Hideous laughingstock
Rebecca reuter was in the urine Brigade
Soap she offered to try to find some people with kind hearts and full bladders
And she did find them at a church and this a Community Chorus which means it's open to whoever wants to come and see
Every practice there was a break where people could announce thing
An old library fundraising in school bake
Sales
Other community events
So I practice one night
Rebecca
The notorious as usual
Waited nervously for the break
And then she stood up and she said I would like to
Ask you to think about
A new a completely new thing
And this is
Collecting your urine
End
Bringing your urine
You know in a little jar or a big jar
To Kim's house
And
We really need as much urine as possible in order to test our hypothesis
End
Nobody like jumped up and down out of their chair and raise their hands
But people came to me one-on-one afterwards
I don't want to offend anybody but
This is the most Vermont story I've ever heard in my life
There is more
The Brigade that collected their urine in recycled bottles
From the granola fat
There's really a granola
Trick if there is
And to get the word out even further the next year they
Sponsored afloat
In the annual strolling of the heifers parade
It's not even going to ask
Cows marching through town
By the end of that first summer
You're engaged a pretty good haul
We had 60 people
And 600 gallons of urine
So 600 gallons of urine that that sounds like a lot that sound successful
But to me actually
Use it straight on the field
Well I went to find out okay so the next place we're going to go now is to the farm
We have two Farms that we work with now
Can I drove to a farm just on the outskirts of town
Run by this guy
Dean Hamilton
And I guess you call me a retired Dairy Farmer
Does STIHL Farm Heroes hay tell me about the size of the hay Farm
Wild
She persists 360
Give or take a course on the farm but 12 years ago Dean sold all his cows
The sorry day that the
Milk the cows in the morning and
Austin went it wasn't just nostalgia
He lost something else that
Without the cows now in a source of
Fertilizer now all my feels can use
All the nutrients you can get right now
So Dien signed up to be there test
Westfield he gets their urine after they process it there
Is it
Orange juice
And then he loads the sanitized urine into a
Container that he
Pulls behind a tractor
Literally spreading the neighbors year in
Crosses hey you run a hay farm that is entirely fertilized by human years
Right now it is yep
Yep
What is hay grown with cow manure how does that compare to hate grown with
Human urine
You don't have to use your imagination to see the difference and see what you can see the difference clearly
Easily can double the
You know the yield in my head
You can see a color
You know
Docker green
He says there is
One problem and that is it there is not enough urine
We need to get more people using the bathroom
Yep yep simple as that I can find a home for the urine if I have a
Ambika Supply even can they work
Twitter USDA
Science Foundation bunch of others
Did you test there are more scientific
But they show pretty much the same results as Dean can see with his own eyes
So
Another with Kim is right we are pretty good little fertilizer fact
Urine is just a small fraction of how phosphorus gets wasted
Remember there's Farm runoff and Wastewater
So companies are working on how to capture that
Phosphorus
What what's the hope and dream if you get everything you want
So
Araxi wrote out a statement I think it's still in my bathroom
And I put it up on the wall and I said you know my vision is it in within my lifetime
I would like to see half
People in the world
Recycling the nutrients
From their bodies
So yes I'm a I'm a real
Dreamer end
What what are the odds that your dream comes true
What are the odds of that it really depends on us
Seriously though what what are the odds of a
Well there are estimates that
Every single one of us pees about $125 a year
Is enough to grow 325 lb of weeks
I'm going to sell my urine at the Green Market
Locally sourced right sample
Not organic
Organic
You know the scheme so crazy it just might work
Planet Money at npr.org or you can find us on Facebook
Or Twitter
Today's episode is just Chung brynhurst at is the editor and he is our senior producer
Special things today to Aaron Britton of ostara Amanda Simpson Jonathan Martin and
Four people at the international fertilizer development
Now you're finished listening to this program may we recommend
Another
Define podcast
Universal indicator from Planet Money you can find it every single day
On NPR one or wherever you get your podcasts
I'm Robert Smith
Karen Duffin
Thanks for listening