Quick note
This episode has some explicit language
When Lawrence left jiangshi province
SuperAmerica
He arrived with the usual
I think I will be calling me there now. You're going to become a millionaire
So is quite have a lot of confidence in myself
But New York put him in his place
Really fast
He fell into a miserable string of odd jobs
Jobs working illegally
First set of Window and Door Company than
Glass Factory
Nothing lasts
Sometime I even me
Didn't know why I bother coming over to
Working for those ready jobs
Those what jobs
Ice a shity job
Ocean City okay
City I know that word okay
And then one day well he was still down in the
He saw an ad in the paper
An immigration law office near Chinatown needed a Chinese
Translator
Finally a prestigious opportunity a law firm
Apply for the job
You got it
But
When he walked into this
Oppressive new law firm
He saw Jesus
Three decks
Crammed into one tiny room
That was the whole
Office
Every phone call
Cough
Everybody heard everything
And what Lawrence heard most often
We're Chinese immigrants
Coming by and ask him for help
Getting asylum in the US
Which
Don't nice Torrance
He had just recently won Asylum himself and now
He could help other Chinese people
Do the exact same
By the way we're not using his real name for reasons that will become very clear later on
And with more closely
Lawrence listened from his tiny corner of that
Tiny office
The more he started to realize that these were
Very special
Asylum cases
Yes Lord From
From the beginning like what what did you say
The office manager with talked to the client
About what kind of
Storage for makeup
What kind of fake documentation provides
Made up those doors
Where it says
The Weir he worked for
Do so much specialized in Asylum
Loft
As an asylum
Broad
And then I realized
This is Open Secret
Chinese immigrant community
Men in Chinese people making Santa Claus
What brands had stumbled into was an underground Network
Professional
Story writers
Coaches and
Scammers
Gaming the asylum
Hello and welcome to planet
Money I know the Chang and I'm Karen Duffin Asylum and become a huge business in Chinatown
And it's incredibly important work
Helping immigrants please sometimes the worst imaginable circumstance
But whenever there's a system setup
Fulfilled good intentions
There will be people who will exploit it
In Florence found himself working for those people and then
Ultimately
He found himself at the
The center of
What could be one of the biggest
Crackdowns on Asylum fraud
In Isis history
I had no idea how
Complicated this story was going to be
When I started looking into the Asylum business the half year ago
I thought this was just going to be a story about one Chinese asylee
He was facing deportation
But as I investigated her case
I quickly discovered it wasn't just her
There are 13000 more people in her situation
A group of people whose stories haven't been told yet
These are mostly Chinese immigrants
Who could also
I'll be losing their Asylum status
We have to say
This is a story that
Took us to some pretty uncomfortable places
Unchallenged
What we thought we knew
The Asylum process
Support for this podcast in the following message come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org
Alright so back in Chinatown in Manhattan
It's mm
And Lawrence is working for a lawyer named Ken trial
Greasy guy who Lawrence says Randy office in kind of an absent minded
And grew up in Oklahoma City
Where he says he never met a single Chinese
Person
He graduated from law school later than most
Wellington
His 30s
And he stumbled into Asylum work
After answering an ad in the New York Law Journal
You know I was thinking myself so I don't know what kind of lawyer I'm going to be
What
If somebody wants to hire me to be a lawyer
That's the kind of lawyer I'm going to be
By the Time Warren Smith
Can cats have more than 80% of his
Cases for Asylum cases
It's you
It is absolutely huge
Everybody I know
The Praxis immigration law that has Chinese cases
It's mostly Asylum Asylum is a form of protection that the u.s. government gives to immigrants who are trying to
Escape person
Succession in their home country
In 2016 more than 20,000 people got Asylum here
And four years Chinese immigrants have been the most
Successful at getting it
The Chinese apply the most often and they win the most often
But in Ken Giles is office they were winning
By cheating
And Lord says he was really torn about this
He knew this was against the law and that there were people out there who truly deserved Asylum
But once was also an immigrant
Sometimes I justify in this way I say okay I'm helping people
I'm helping those
Lower class
Chinese people to get their status United States
They Don't Really commit a crime they don't do what they want just
Spanish job here and walking the Chinese restaurant
So that's the way I drop
Justify
My wrongdoings
And the more he justified his wrongdoings
The deeper Warren Scott
Until eventually he landed at
One of the biggest Asylum operation
Probably the largest Law Firm
Inside of town at the moment
It was a law firm run by a woman named funling love you
And it was everything at Ken Giles office was not
It was a model of a fishing
Asylum applications were manufactured along an assembly line
Where each worker was assigned a specific task
Picture of us
Become expert
In
The area we're working on
Some people was just
Answering the phone
All dealing with client
Some of them just coaching
Some of them just writing stories station in this assembly line
Writing story
Kitty hold up all day in room designated only for story writer
Trying out
We made up a silent place
Our f
After hour
Getaway at Lawrence had the most important job
A ball because
The key to getting Asylum
Is the story
You tell the US government
It has to be a story about
Suffering
But only a certain
Kind of
The kind of suffering the government has deemed worthy of its protection
And the suffering that counts in the system
Is targeted
Persecution
Based on your race your religion political opinion
Or some particular social group
You belong to
And something like fake gang violence
That doesn't usually count
Just not targeted enough
But the story is Chinese asylees tell
They tend to check the right box
Like abortions forced by the Chinese government's Family Planning policy or
Government oppression for supporting democracy or for being
Christian and Lord found the best place to start stories like that
Was actually
Wintergreen
Say a woman really did have an abortion in China even if it was by choice
He'd spend that into a story about an abortion forced by the government
Or if a client enjoyed some real life
Tragedy
He would say that tragedy
Is why she converted
To Christianity
Little specks of Truth spun just right
And you have yourself
An asylum
Like with Johnny Lee
She was a Chinese immigrant
To have run out of ways to stay in the
Until my aunt said
Just come to Asylum
Do gangaajal Hindi
Southlake people all around me for doing it
Common people I worked with
People in my circle
From what I could tell applying for Asylum to stay in this country
It was just a normal thing to do
It seemed like everyone was doing it
Tidewater
Tellonym Condado
And that's when warrants met Johnny
It was spring of 2011
Johnny was
A model
Client she was 29 college-educated which men
You can memorize more made up facts
Also Johnny actually did get an abortion in China but willingly
And she had occasionally
Time to church
So Lawrence just took all of that
And basically just turned up the volume a bit and gave them a twist
Who's the twist that even Jenny found a bit
Much
We're going to have our interpreter
Read from the actual Asylum statement that Lawrence wrote
For her
I was stopped
Hi to Family Planning cadres
At the entrance of my apartment
I knew the consequences
So I struggled against them at all my strength
But they pulled me to a nearby Van
By force
Drove me to the fictional Johnny is forced to get an abortion
She didn't slumps into
Depression what happened to me in the hospital
Became my night
What she finds her way out of by
Becoming a devout Christian the Lord Jesus Is Our Shepherd
Who's love
Healed the wounds in my heart
Until one day
They accused us
Of Traders
Please spread the Western evil
Colt the police officers try to get her to sign a confession letter
Cheap fuses thereafter
The beat me
When they found I did not cooperate with them
I was slapped in my face several times
And kicked several times
Even sexually harassed by them
So this was Johnny's Asylum
And now she had to play the part
She's at the law office had to go to church
A lot 4 times a week
Until she got a baptism
And then Lawrence coached her for the Asylum interview
He told her
What questions to expect help us
To answer them
And next he helped her rehearsed her fake Asylum story
This incident
Gave me a big blow over and over again
I was depressed for a while
I could not perform as usual
And then I love this last line
I beseech
The US government
To let us
Stay
And not
To send us back
To the hell like
China
Elmo Spaghetti House Lockport AR
I read that story and it sounded
So
Fake like
Just called you always
Okay
Outsider
Photos of style officer
Immigration charge
By this kind of fake story every day so they don't know what
Real story stupid looking like
In other words to Lawrence
The Asylum system was so
Drenched in light
That true stories of suffering
No longer sounded worthy of asylum
The truth just wasn't dramatic enough anymore
You almost had to lie
He said
To rise above the noise
Sonny Lee was granted asylum on June 28th
On her first try
Lawrence says he wrote five to six hundred stories this way
He also mapped out which Asylum officers were more likely to accept certain kinds of Asylum stories
Say
You're meeting with officer George I want to tell him an abortion story
If you meet with Officer Sally and you want to say that you
Converted to Christianity
She's going to want to hear a few Bible stories
Was there a part of you that was kind of proud of yourself
That you were so good at this
Kind of
Because I was speaking down the system
How did it feel
I just feel like they're not doing their job
This shouldn't love me
When the game so easy
That's how Lawrence.
Gaming the asylums
System was
Sport
And maybe people like Lawrence were able to game the system so easily because they were good at it
And maybe also because the lies they told
Are ones that many Americans believe
They were lies that
Supported the perception
That the communist government in China would
Oppressed
But
4 years
He just got tired of it
He decided he just wanted to get
He wanted to get out of the
So
Started
Law School
He was determined to become a legitimate lawyer
To finally live that American Dream he came here
But then in the middle of his first semester
His cell phone ring
2 weeks before Thanksgiving
I got phone call
Is FBI agent
The FBI agent said we need to talk
After the break Lawrence gets
Thrown back in
Way Back Inn
Support for this podcast and the following message come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and community
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org
Florence to meet him at the FBI office in Manhattan
Lawrence's wife who was pregnant at
The time jogging down the neck
She waited in the cafeteria well he went upstairs
And their Lawrence was greeted by two agents
Why don't them is Asian
Is a korean-american I believe so
Another one is
Regular white people
The agents told him
We know all about the Asylum fraud and we know that you are part of it
Here's how Lawrence says it all went down
The agents told him that the FBI had been tailing him for more than a year
They whipped out photos of Lawrence
Dinner with lawyers or other interpreters who are also in the Asylum business
And they told him a big raid was coming
Something massive
Something really high-profile
And they said
Look
You can either join your colleagues in prison or you can help the FBI
So
She was born
Just inches from becoming a lawyer
His wife was pregnant
He wanted to
Stay in the US he fought
He should cooperate
But some of the people they wanted him to narc on
Weir Danger
Seabird summer connected to human Smugglers
But he says the FBI told him Halo
If you cooperate we're going to protect you
And the music
A different name different social security number
Different occupation
Lawrence also says the FBI agents told him that they would make sure he would not get charged with any felonies
That way it would be easier to still become a US citizen
But we read the cooperation agreement he eventually signed
What she shared with us
And it doesn't contain those promises in fact it tells him he was still at risk of being deported
But whatever the government promised him in exchange for cooperating
Prince also had been feeling a little guilty about what he does
So when they approached him he decided
You know what
I'm not just going to
Leave this industry
So
Lauren stop
What kind of fake documentation for why
India on everything he knew
Chinese immigrant community
And so
Lawrence became the central Witness
In what the FBI would call
Operation fiction writer
Which course means
What was your code name
Yakult talk
What t o r q u e
Torque your code name was torque
Yeah
Torque
As in the force
That turns them
Lawrence became the FBI's
Twerk he turned their entire investigation around
Lawrence gave the agency a detail
Picture of all the people involved in pumping out fraudulent Asylum
Chinatown
Flashing
He poured over photo
Identify
He turned over his huge study guide
Which plane laid out every step of
The fraud from
Story writing
Evidence fabrication
Interview coach
And then the FBI turned him into we're going to call him a special agent
They gave ancient
Twerksum spy gear
That's what I would expect
Something really sophisticated from FBI from FBI by next week
That's just like
Hearing aid
How to spell
So it looks like you were wearing a
Hearing aid
Saints looks like that
A hearing aid with a ridiculously long cable
Sneaking underneath his FBI issued shirt
Every time you ask me too well
Sure
The shirt that gave me
Oh that the shirt was really ugly
How to say
The recorder for his
Special
Hearing aid microphone
Oldest conspicuously from his back pocket
And the special spy camera that they gave him
It's actually poked out from his shirt collar
Is a liger
Button
It looks like a big button the camera
Yeah
An armed with this state-of-the-art
Spy gear
Twerk
Went back into the Asylum Mills and
Started
Steam recordings in all
And one of his very first targets
What's a personal
Ken Giles
The first Asylum lawyer he'd worked for in that tiny office
Lawrence had a special district
You didn't work very hard and I got really chapped
Peoplewhiz. What
You thought it was lazy
Yeah he was lazy Cruz why we were related
Tennille Ken Laurence offer to help him write
One last
Location
Yeah completely made up story I never talk to that guy at all I didn't even call the client
Then he walked into cans off
Turn on his camera
And recorded himself telling Ken all about how he
Fabricated
This Woman's entire Asylum stay
And we never got to see the video but Lauren says it showed 10
Raising the story that
Meetup
And in December 2012
Ken Giles got
A phone call
This is Agent
So-and-so with the FBI
We have a warrant for your arrest online
Award for my arrest
Yeah
For what
Conspiracy to commit immigration
This is Ken Giles
Again and he says
The feds got it all
I Never Told
Anybody to pretend to be anything
Never
That's a lie
That is a lie
I don't think so but
I don't know
You don't know because
Because I don't speak Chinese
Still can totally acknowledges
Is that many of the stories contained in the Asylum applications he signed
Exactly the same
Over and over again
I mean a red background material
About forced abortions in China so I know what happened
You know
And if I were to bike
Oh yeah you know I had abortion you know
Pretty cool
You know if they were like that
You know
But if they start crying
And exhibiting some sort of pain
When we're counting that
You wouldn't question it
Why would question it but
And I would tend to
Give him the benefit of the doubt
So why isn't your job to figure out if they're really telling the truth how do you do that if it's 50-50 though
You know me
And if you think what could be or couldn't be
How do you say no
Faced with a warrant for his arrest
Ken Giles
Turned himself in at 9 a.m. sharp the neck
26 people have been charged in New York what happened to make false Asylum
In total operation fiction writer
Rounded up 30 immigration lawyers
Paralegals and interpreters
In December 2012
And prosecutors credited Lawrence
With providing evidence against at least
Half of those defendants
We reached out to immigration officials to weigh in on the
But they declined to do an interview
For the story
Ken Giles pleaded guilty to conspiracy to commit immigration fraud and he got 2 years in prison
Is office manager also pleaded guilty
And funlings do you was found guilty at trial
And Lawrence at this point
People recognized him from the Chinese newspaper
They knew he was a government star Witness
Did you find him at the grocery store and on
On the street
Telling him
He was a traitor
And that deal that deal he says the government made with him you know
Protect you if you help us
He got charged with more serious crimes than even Ken Giles.
Find out if your life
How did they lie to my face how did they lie to you
I find out the truck
Friendly charger
Watch artem my boss
And then I found out I couldn't
Apply for us
Cigarettes
The judge in Lawrence's case did cut him some slack
He got just six months probation even though he faced
A maximum of 25 years
But since Lawrence had pleaded guilty to
Two felonies
It would then probably be much harder for him to become a US citizen
And the witness protection stuff
That also
Never happen
Fun Spot
How to get out of here
Get far
Far away from New York
So Lawrence did his best to disa
Sapir he got into a PhD program in Arizona and he moved there to start a new life
Started going by his Chinese name instead of his English one and the lawyers who were convicted in operation fiction
Writer they helped more than 3700 immigrants
When Asylum
And when one Republican Congressman heard about that Bob goodlatte of Virginia
He sent a letter to the justice department demanding that they reopen those Asylum cases
I figure out which of those clients lied
And should therefore lose their Asylum
And the lawyer who work most closely with goodlatte on that issue
Was a man in Tracy
Short
After Donald Trump was elected
President
Trumpet that lawyer
Casey short
Basically in charge of all the lawyers who overseed deportation
And as all of this was happening back in Washington
Steve Lawrence was in Arizona building a new life
Until one day he got a call
It was immigration officials
And they said
You're not done yet
Come back to New York
And their immigration officials let him into a room filled with a
Boxes
I said they needed him
Do identify the Asylum applications of former clients that he knew
Why
And then decide to get a ticket like
Funny kids
He says they called him again in March 2017
I miss
Two ice attorneys
They said they got 200 cases
Ice even planted decoy files in the Box
Lawrence knew exactly which stories
These were his
That's why they call me
Photocopy memory
Three months later ice was on the phone again
They say they got two thousand kisses now
Oh my God mm cases I was thin
Like a decade on that
Abyss could become slaves or us dumbest
Write Warren says at this point he was thinking
I just
Can't anymore
He started trying to avoid their phone call
And then something happened that really scary
He was sitting inside a small graduate student
When are the noise he didn't wreck
The phone call
It's from my old office phone
Snow White
Record
This is like an old
Office phone that never rings
I didn't even know that phone with walking
Lord says it was a Dusty rotary dial
Phone
He picked the phone up
Slowly
The person on the other end said he was calling from Ice
He also called Lawrence by his English name
The name he was trying to bury
Out in Arizona
Lawrence
Says
This
Felt like
A message
A power play
Ice could have called him on his
Cell phone decor
Emailed him
To him
This was the government saying
We can find you
Anywhere you are
That's really big brother
Festival 1984 the guy from Ice
So the government needed him
That's out time Iowa
So scared and I refuse I say no I couldn't help you I don't really want help you
Cuz he didn't want to spend decades on
On this because at this point
Investigation had moved into a new phase
And he knew that if he helped
It would mean destroying potentially
Thousand
Supplies
During the prosecution Lawrence says
He was comfortable helping the government go after the industry
But in this new phase the government's going after the
Science
And that just didn't sit right with
What are the two situations different to you
Those
Chinese immigrants.
Science
They even
Didn't know
They commit crimes were doing that their attorney just tell lie to them too
Do that
Well some of these clients knew very well that they were lying on their Asylum
Vacation
Yes they know. But what legal attorney promise you you will be fine
They couldn't really make right judgement
The way Lawrence tells it
The government is mixing up with his legal
With what is right
It made sense to him to go after the lawyers but
Clients were just doing what the lawyers told them to do he says
Lawrence wants no part in helping the government strip Asylum
From people who wanted years ago
Even if it means going into hiding
Forever
Do you really think that the federal government won't be able to find you now
I don't think so
But what are your plans I mean are you just going to keep running from Ice forever
What else I can do
And that is why he asked to go by Lauren
Send a story and is talking to us on Skype from an undisclosed
Location
Immigration officials wouldn't confirm for us whether they really did try to
Paul Lawrence back into all these
Client case
So
We're telling boring side of the story
Even though we know he did lie
For a living
But in this case
His story checked out
The government was undertaking a massive review of client cases from operation fiction writer
And now
Lawrence's decision to disappear
Has left it to others
To wrestle with a broken aside
Alarm system
It's a system that was created after World War
And it was based on kind of a wistful ideal
That the government will protect people with true stories
Stop suffering
But over the decades the question that's persisted is
How do we know when people are telling the truth
It's impossible to fact check every detail of the 20,000 some stories that went
Asylum every year
So this is a system that runs on hunches
The hunch of the lawyer who signed your Asylum application
Asylum officer or
Immigration judge who decides your claim is
Credible
Lawrence admits he took full advantage of this
And helps the vert the very system that gave him a chance to stay in the US
But he says
His decision to disappear now
How many people
And he's proud of
Last thing I do something great
I seem to make it much harder for eyes
Deport
Thousands of people
But you were the one who helped
A lot of people
Write false things and their Asylum application
And that's why ice is going after them now
All right now
Without my help
Two eyes
I probably will make it much harder for ice to deport them and
They may have chance
To staying in the United States
They may
But we have learned that since 2014
Thousands of Asylum claims have been thrown into doubt
US citizenship and Immigration Services told us they are reviewing the Asylum cases of more than 3,000
500 former clients of all the lawyers convicted in operation fiction writer
They told us that if they don't scrutinize these old Asylum cases
The American people
Law-abiding asylum-seekers and the rule of law
Suffer
There are also reviewing the Asylum case of every spouse and child
Those clients
Meaning these are people who just
Kind of inherited Asylum status
When their parent or
Their spouse years ago and that's how they were able to stay in the country
But they may not be able to anymore
So the total USCIS confirm to us is more than
13000 immigrants
Who are now facing possible deportation
Immigration lawyers told us that they have never seen Asylum cases
Systemically reviewed on a scale like this
Indices entire history
And one of those cases
Is Johnny
Remember her
She was the Asylum applicant who Lawrence had helped
Store we had heard earlier
In the fall of 2012
She had also help the government during operation fiction writer
And in return the government promised her they wouldn't prosecute her
And that in fact they would bring her cooperation to the attention of ice
If she wanted
But in 2016
Johnny Lee received a letter from the government that bread
Notice of intent to terminate Asylum status
Georgia.
I thought the government
Thomas me
My situation wouldn't get worse
If I help them
I helped them
Good night
Why aren't they helping me
To hold your pee
So downtown the scene cooperated with the government
And now that cooperation is being used against her
Immigration officials got a hold of every self incriminating statement that she made while helping the FBI
And now they're using precisely those statements as the evidence to deport her
And not just her but also her husband who got Asylum status through her
When we were reporting this story
We can decide who to be angry with or who you feel sorry for
I mean how do we weigh the relative wrongs in the system
And then we heard Jenny say something it just kind of summed it all up for us if she'll shoot
Yes I did trick the government but in the end
The government
Tricked me back
This story would
Not have happened without Lauren hilgers her book Patriot number one American Dreams in Chinatown
Was what first got me thinking about chinatown's Asylum Disney
And special things to David custom down for being an early listener
Enter json zubo
An asylum lawyer who answered like hundreds of my question this episode was produced by Sally Helm Alexa
Steve Horowitz Ghazi and Aviva dekornfeld
Brainerd status Planet Money Alex goldmark is the supervising producer get in touch with us on Twitter
Instagram or Facebook I'm out the check and I'm Karen Duffin thanks for listening