Hey it's Jacob Goldstein just a quick note
Today Show first aired
6 years ago after David kestenbaum and I went to China
Hey
Tiny little planet
Money that's right hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm David kestenbaum
I'm Jacob.
Today on the show The Story of a secret document
Meeting in a small village and hidden in the roof of a mud
The people who signed this document were afraid it might get them exit
Instead
It warmed up completely transforming China's economy
Support for this podcast in the following message come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities to help ensure a brighter future for America
Is children more information is available at aecf. Org
Before we get to the story of the secret document that transformed China
Let's just get a feel for where China is today
Let's start out on a train
Ladies and gentlemen this is not just any train this is part of China's new bullet train
Network the largest in the world like Safari
Contrave
Can you start to move faster actually I read up at top speed
130 km an hour
3840 / 300 km/h
Miles an hour
Makes Amtrak look primitive
Bullet train stations here there are these huge gleaming things
Pek Airport
What's really striking about this whole picture is just how far China has come in just a few deck
Happens in 1978 a year when
Most Americans have cars
Garages I was
9 years old
Sitting on the couch watching Welcome Back Kotter on tell
Betsy Muir David millions of people in China didn't even have electric
And you could argue that this transformation
This change that took China from mud Huts to bullet trains
Started in a single small village in world
The village is called zhougong and we went there
Very nice to meet you thank you for talking to us
This is yuanchao and by the way none of the people we talked to and Jog on spoke English so
We're hearing here is a Transit
Genji until he's one of the people who started China on this
Path of bullet
And one of the really fun things about reporting on China's economy
Is well so if you're in the US and you want to talk to one of the founding fathers of the US economy you want to talk to
Alexander Hamilton he's been dead for hundreds of years
But in China a lot of these key people they're still around
Engine Chow is not an economist
He's not a politician
Rent a small restaurant in jalgaon
30 years ago when all this happened
There's a farm
Engine Chow open metal gate behind the restaurant
He takes out to the field where he used to farm
Back in 1978
Everyone here worked on a collective Farm
Ricky Canton ropings in winter
I say that
Oh my God I just died and it was still basically the height of communism
And on our visit this Village we actually spent a long time
Just trying to figure out how the system worked on a communist Farm
The basic idea was that people would work together
For the common good
And in this world as tianjin Chow explains it
Nobody owns anything
Do you know me gif
I used oxygen to form but they weren't mine
They belong to the group
I couldn't belong to the group
Individual student anything
At 1 meeting with Communist Party officials
When farmer ask
What about the teeth in my head do I own those
NOAA.
Your teeth
How long do they collect
Everything in this world with centrally planned
The farmers were told what to plant by a Communist Party official from outside the Village Inn
Sometimes they were told to grow rice even if they didn't have enough water to properly grow rice
Indian Child says back in this era
Every morning a whistle would blow to Mark the start of the work day
It would have to blow it twice
The farmers would drag themselves out of their huts and go to work on the fields
At the end of the day and everyone would stop
You get points for working all day
But it didn't matter how much or how hard you work you just had to show up
Even if you had decided to go out early and pull weeds or something
It wouldn't make a difference
Everyone gets the same
So people don't want to work
And after the Harvest the government collects what everyone is grown
And give the village and allotment of food
In the case of Zell Kong
Allotment was never enough
So they were hungry all the
Their kids never had enough to eat and
Jensen Chow in the others young farmers
They had to walk to other Villages and beg for food
Xiaomi
We will follow
Who is supposed to produce
Tobacco food
Was not honored
Nintendo switch
Which house is Vera Sheen
It was hard to not come to us in the back for food
What you say
This is the way things were all over China this is basically the way the entire economy
Farmers in jalgaon
We're starving
And they needed to do something
One farmer in particular was pushing for a change
His name
Ian Hunter
We tried to onion hunting as well and we talked to him in this open garage attached to his house
There were sacks of grain piled up along the wall he smokes cigarettes the whole time
It was just really cold rainy day
And he told us that
Out of desperation
The farmers
Came up with an i
But the idea they had was so dangerous
They had to call a secret meeting to discuss
Concerts
It was about 5 in the afternoon
This was a secret meeting
Doja cat
We snuck in one by one
There were eighteen Farmers crowded into the small room
Dungeon chalice
Were there were there
Enough chairs for all of you
How could there be chairs
Some of us
Close
Sunset on the floor
What's up
Little tiny stools
We have no chairs back then
Germantown says everybody there was afraid to talk so finally he spoke
Tarzana Unified
Everyone is here and knows what
This is about
I know wanted to speak
Just woke up
What Argentina
Watch Awkward
I said we're all here
Because we have to find a way
To save ourselves
To save themselves they have an idea that is both revolutionary
And as old as dirt
Rather than Farm as a collective
Each family gets to farm
Its own plot of land
And the family grows a lot of food
That family gets to keep some of that
You own what you
But owning and communist China in 1978 that's something like
Treason
I was scared
Does the Polynesian scared you wouldn't be able to do it
And that wouldn't work
So in this little dirt floor groom by the light of a broken-down oil lamp
Farmers are talking about this idea
Stop the older farmers who remember the days before communism when they could find their own land they said
We have to try this
But a lot of the guys in the room
They were really scared
Hello
Yes we want to do it
I don't think this will work
This is like high voltage wire
Farmers have never seen electricity
They had heard about
You would die
But they decide they have to do this
The alternative is to
Shunyi beijing
I'm going hungry
They decide they need to write this down
Write down a contract
Laying out how this is going to work
Put their names on it so they're all bound to
So no one can go back on
There's only one problem
Paper just plain paper is hard to come by in jalgaon in 1978
Yen Ching tell us he's going to write on a cigarette
But it turns out this other farmer had some paper
So he runs together
And then
Yin hun Chun rice this historic thing
It's short just a few sentences long
Will tell you exactly what he wrote after the break
Support also comes from Fidelity Investment
As a Fidelity Wealth Management
You get a dedicated advisor to help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes
And make clear recommendations for your full Financial
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
Do you remember the exact words that you wrote
What's a Geechee
Enrolling myself
I remember
Can you tell it to us
Bummer
Gandalf
Chattanooga weather
We will divide up Farmland between the families
Bantam head of each Family Signs old stamps his approval
Each family will give a share of the crops and the collective at the end of the year
Who are put in prison or executed
We will not complain
And the others in a group
Well raised our children to 18 years old
There in a sentence
The first capitalists of modern China
Their livelihood is in their own hands
If it works
Don't have enough to
If they get discovered
They could be killed
But one by one
The farmers come forward to sign on to the car
They realize they need to hide this thing
And eventually
Ventana winds up sleeping it inside a piece of bamboo in the roof of his house
Engine shout remembers the first day he went out to Farm after they sign
I just felt different
Basilica
I felt
I feel comfortable you my heart
Energize
I show off my abilities
Did you work harder than before
The summertime Comedia
Of course I work hard
Will do
Because whatever I produced was mine
If you didn't work hard
Nut cookie origin
And we all secretly compete
Everyone wants you to produce more than the next person
Pat
Got people watching hot
It's amazing to think this is the same land they have the same tools it's the same farmers
But just by changing the economic rules just by saying
You get to keep some of what you grow
Everything Changes
What y'all doing
We started work before the sun came up
And we would interior Woodstock
This working all the time thing
Actually get them into trouble
Engine House of the neighbors noticed it and they started to suspect something funny was go
Why were these crazy Farmers going out to work before the whistle blew
Before Dawn
Why were they working so late
And at Harvest time there was an even bigger problem
It was impossible to hide
They had an enormous Harvest
It was more food according to gun hunt Chong
Then they had grown in the previous five years combined
It was both exciting and Turf
One day young sean gets a call from some local party officials
They some of them to their offices
When you get there he says they swear at him
And they treat him like he's on death row
They said they're going to lock him up
Fortunately for Jensen Chong at this moment in history
There is this really broad debate going on in China
They're powerful people within the party who are saying we need to try some economic experiments
In fact the regional party Chief in this area
She was one of these
Pro-reform guys and he had visited yet hun Chun and it said to him
What you're doing here it looks interesting you should keep at it
So when yin and yang get called in
He begs for permission to make one
He gets it and he calls the regional party to
The guy who been supportive
And luckily for him the official answers the phone
But the local official next again hun Chun
Grab the phone away from
Hoverboard
I could still hear what
Regional party Chief was saying
He said
Do not change anything
I approved
This experiment
Challenger blow him to continue working on the phone
So they let young chango
He goes back to the village and keeps farming and this experiment it keeps working
Eventually word what's happening in Saigon
Mix it up the chain of command through the Communist party to the very top
The Deng Xiaoping the guy basically running China
Danielle Kang is one of the pro-reform guy
At this moment he is poised to become the key reformer who creates China's modern Econo
Think nothing has been wanting to change the way farming Works in China
Any lights what's happening as y'all gone but
This is still communist China
It's just 2 years after the death of Mao
And lots of people are opposed to what's going on in jail
So then can't say anything bad about Mao or Collective farming
Things big picture idea is
Let's not worry about whether something is capitalist or communist or socialist
Let's worry about whether it works
There's this
Famous quote that's attributed to dang that they would we actually heard all the time when we are in China
It doesn't matter if a cat is white or black as long as it catches mice
It's a good cat
Things up and doesn't stand up in public and give these jogging Farmers metals
He's quieter about
He decides to have these two writers tell the story
He calls them in and says
I support this
You guys should go tell the jog story to the rest of China
And pretty soon people all over China are farming like the people in jalgaon
Farmers on what they grow
The government starts trying out other economic experiments
Factory spring up in cities along the coast
China lets foreign companies
Coca-Cola open the plants in Beijing
And China's economy grows like
And this crazy economic growth has gone on and on for more than 30 years now
Who's the farmers in jail gang sign that contract
Something like 500 million people in China have risen out of poverty
They moved from mud huts with dirt floors and oil lamps 2
Houses with electricity
They moved into a world of cities and high-rises and New Roads and bullet train
People all over China know that one sentence version of visual Kong story
If you're driving by the town on the highway this little sign by the highway exit
Is a small Museum in
Telling the story of the contract
And it is this incredible true story that marks the beginning of China's economic rise
But when you look at what has happened to Jug on since then
Things get complicated
I get especially complicated when it comes to you and hung Chong the guy who should be a hero of modern China
The guy who was the first one to speak at the meeting who
Actually wrote the contract and heated in his roof
But on our first day in town when we asked the local Communist Party officials if we could talk to Yong Jun Chong
They told us he was out of town
But we went back to jogging the next day
And we found Ian Hunter
Which is why you're hurt him in the story
We asked if he had been out of
Were you here yesterday
Bonanza
I was here yesterday
We were told you were not here yesterday
Photography
I was here yesterday
When you asked about what happened in that Hut in 1978
Everybody agrees everybody tells the same story
But when you ask about what has happened in sell guns since then
Devin Chong in the party officials they tell two very different
The official version is that everything in town is
New factories are springing up there lots of jobs
Shelgon is living happily ever after
Nanchang says he's had a different experience
He says he started a few businesses over the years but once they became profitable the government
Took them away from him
He also says those new factories springing up around town
A lot of them are just empty
Local official say none of this
Detention you here though really throughout the jog angst
Between free enterprise and State Control
That is everywhere in China
The government has let go of some parts of the economy
But it's holding on tightly toddler
That fancy bullet train Network for example its run by the government
Last year
There was a collision that killed 40 people
The head of the Railway Ministry has been arrested on corruption charge
Will post some photos from chaoyang
Online at NPR. Org / money and on Instagram at Planet Money
We're also on Twitter and Facebook you can email us at Planet Money at npr.org
I'm Jacob Goldstein and I'm thankful