Hello I am Karen Duffin and I am new here at Planet Money
Hello and welcome to Planet Money Karen Duffin he really did say that to me to everybody
Karen started with us about what 18 days ago
And we asked her to look into
Non-disclosure
Something we've been hearing a lot about NDA
And as if
To prepare myself for this I had just signed one
It was part of my NPR Employment contract
Is pretty standard stuff but
Can actually tell you the details because
It says I can't
Think I probably 5-2 I think you did
So I start digging into nda's and
Somewhere deep in this rabbit hole
I kind of figured into
Pothead territory
I started to think
Actually kind of
Crazy if you
Really think about it that
You can buy Style
You can calculate what that silence is worth and buy it
And I got it I do
I worked in Silicon Valley for a decade in
I know that companies makes
I think it makes sense that they should for the most part be allowed to say
You employee can I tell the world about it
But over the past year I watched as
Me to cross my social media feeds many breaking their Silence about harassment for the first time
I felt a little bad about this
But I was surprised
It just how many people I know
But I didn't know that about
So
As I studied nda's
Spoke with
Women who signed them women have broken them
Lawyers
My mind just kept bouncing between my Silicon Valley Days
And these me two days
I started to think weight
How did we go from there
From protecting corporate secrets
To this world in which you can buy someone Silence about something
Add you've done
Like sexual harassment or assault
How did we get to that place with nda's also what happens if you break one
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I Am Karen Duffin
And today on the show
We go in search of answers for those questions
How did this happen
What happens if you break an NDA we talked to one of the most famous NDA Breakers of all time
And we learn a few things
Maybe just maybe could help people who want out of an NDA to get out legally
Support for this podcast and the following message
Come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities to help ensure a brighter future for America
Is children more information is available at aecf. Org
To find out how we got to this place where
Nda's are being
Weaponized essentially
Plate to cover up bad back
We started with this question
Where did Indians come from to begin with
I called Elie mystal to help me answer that
He is the editor of the website above the law
And the legal editor of the
Excellent podcasts more perfect
He's also the most
Entertaining La person I know
You got to remember like why nda's exist at all
And it's not
Really so that
You can get away with sexually harassing women
Wait a minute I know it seems like
That's not really why they were invented right they were invented to protect trade secret
Ellie says they weren't really created to silence whistleblowers
Okay so then the question of how did they
Become a tool to silence whistleblowers
We took that question to the head of the national whistleblower center
Steve Kerr
He says that shift can be traced
To the rise of
Title 7
It was created to prohibit workplace discrimination
Which meant that more employees started suing their companies for workplace discrimination
It opened up employers to
Liability
So why not use an NDA
To make
That liability
Harder to prove
Employers were already using nda's
Flip the standard Joplin
Talked about earlier
Birthday thought
We're getting sued by all of these people why do we also use this
Keep people silent
About bad things
Dancing snowball
So you saw this rise of x
Greenlee abusive nda's
That not
Only
You said you can't communicate
But put specific
Requirements to help
Companies
Cover up
Misconduct
Okay so that's more people are signing these
Which leads us to our next big question
What happens if you break an NDA
Help me answer this question we are going to tell you a story
A story
Maybe you think you heard
They're afraid of yuan
That is Al Pacino and Russell Crowe from the movie
The Insider
And at that point I was like cool the movie
That's about
A heroic journalist from 60 minutes
Getting the ultimate Insider to blow the whistle
On big tobacco
But we watching it now for this story
You realize all no no no no
This is a movie about non-disclosure
Case in point
The following is all from the first half of the movie
Signed a confidentiality agreement have no intention of violating my confidentiality agreement
Confidentiality is confidentiality
Most of those were Russell Crowe playing the character Jeffrey wigand
The real life person who broke
Big mean NDA from Big tobacco
As you look back
Was it worth it
Hell yes
Wow
This is the real Jeffrey wigand
And that is a hell yes
With the huge ass
So you know
Your life will never be the same
In the late 80s early 90s Jeff was a vice president at Brown & Williamson or BMW
Which is a big Tobacco Company
This was an unexpected
The career move Jeff is a scientist who worked in healthcare for 20 years before that
He agreed to join the Tobacco Company because
They told him that they wanted his help making safer cigarette
And the pay was great
Subject takes the job and he's presented with a pretty basic employment and ta that says you know
Certain parts of his work have to be kept confidential
He's like a cool
Signed it
But within just three months
The company's lawyers sitting down and they pant MD
Talking points
That nicotine is not addictive
There is no science
It says that
Smoking
Jeff obviously
Not agree with this
What did you say to them
I'm from the Bronx
I just said
I will tell you what I said but I
I think you may figure out what I say
Essentially you said screw you
And 4 years of tussling between Jeff the scientist and the
Tobacco lawyers
And Jeff gets
No at this point Jeff
He's not thinking about breaking his NDA to become a whistle blow
His NDA was tied to
Severance package
And his health
Which was especially important
Because one of his daughters
With chronically ill
Until he's going on just
Trying to put his life back together when BMW Susan
The company had heard that it's some point Jeff at talked about his Severn
Which is
Technically a violation of his employment NDA
It was true he had done this
And just company use this relatively small technical Violator
Pressure him
Into signing a new end
NDA
On steroid
If I find a zoo
Draconian agreement
I couldn't talk about anything
Sing without first talking to them
Talk about
Which is to say
Not just keep the company Secrets but if anyone ever asks him to talk about tobacco at all he had to
Tell pnw
Who asked
What he's going to say and they can even come along with him
If they want
And this brings us to the first lesson of Jeff story
Even an NDA that seems like it is buying
Kind of innocuous Isla
Can become a web
That small violation
The first NDA
Became a tool to get Jeff to sign that NDA on steroids
And where is Calais
This happens all the
And it worked in Jeff case
He says he felt like he had no choice
Mostly because of his daughter's illness
He really needed his Healthcare
So
He signs
Then a few things started
To happen
Jeff remembers for one getting these Anonymous phone calls
Like what did they say
Tobacco alone
My children
And later Jeff would find himself
Followed and it was never proved who did this
But a bullet wound up his mailbox
The intimidation terrified Jeff but it also pissed him off
And then one day
He turned on his teeth
TV NEC 7 tobacco Executives testifying before Congress
Congressman
Cigarettes and nicotine clearly do not meet the classic definitions of the dictionary
Hard to remember now
But there was a time when people were not 100% clear about that fat
But Jeff with Crystal Clear
She's a scientist and she had been a vice president at a tobacco
He has information that would
Totally refute that lie
And he had started breaking the NDA in private
PT been Consulting with politicians
The Food Drug Administration Department
Justice
And he had not told his company about the
Dislike his Mega NDA required
Came to do
We're going public that
Is it different
Jeff knows that if he does go public his company
Will definitely know and he might lose his
Health insurance
Interceptor
You also might get sued for some ungodly amount of money
But at some point those costs were
Just not worth the price of staying silent
Not for jackets
I decided I would tell 60 Minutes everyday
And this brings us to the second lesson from Jeff's
Nda's are not just used to silence The Whistleblower
They can also be used to try and silence the whistle
Somehow Ronnie Williamson got word that Jeff was talking to
60 minutes
And they threaten to sue CVS
For what CBS was afraid could be billions
Dollars
To CBS decides to kill the story and
60 Minutes host Mike Wallace even goes on air and
Kind of apologize
We learned of a tobacco Insider who might know the whole story
But we cannot broadcast what critical information
He might be able to offer
Why
Because he had to sign a confidentiality agreement
With the tobacco company he work for
An innocent CBS was also afraid
Jeff wigand
NDA
The movie version
Of Mike Wallace explains why he was okay killing the store
Well what do you think
I'm going to resign in protest to force it on the air the answer's no I don't plan to spend the end
My days wandering in the wilderness of National Public Radio
Mike
Ouch
But here here is the final lesson from Jeff wigand story
Justice nda's contain technicalities
I can get you into trouble if you accidentally violate them bike
For example talking about your severance
They're also technicalities
That might make an NDA breakable
Legally
Jeffy giving a deposition at some point that included a lot of damning information about
The tobacco in
And the Wall Street Journal have gotten hold of this.
Position and publish part of it
This is one of the ways an NDA can be deemed unenforced
If the information is already on the public record
And with that CBS becomes a lot less scared of Jeffrey wigand Zindagi
Brown Williamson's representation
Clearly missed a what they calmly knew his language within the company
60 Minutes decides it is
Now legally okay
To run their interview with Jeff White
Delivery device for nicotine
A delivery device
But in your mouth Light It Up
And you going to get your fix
How did that feel
Stream
Huh
What do you mean
The longer might
Volume now
Describe
Jeff is credited with helping Force the tobacco industry into a multibillion-dollar settlement
Which was a game-changer
And how Americans understood the dangers of tobacco
And the fact that we live in a world where no one questions whether or not smoking is bad for you just helped make that
As part of that big settlement
Jeff's former company agreed to drop their lawsuit
I told you that
Is ultimately how Jeff got out of his non-disclosure
So he didn't really face legal consequences
What does for breaking his NDA
But we wondered
If he had an
Four other people who break their ears
What punishments can the law impose
What's on NBA breaker
Curse if you violating NDA there is a penalty it is not
Jail
Again legal expert Elie mystal
We do not throw you
And the Iron Maiden for breaching a contract
And this is because an NDA is a sibling
Until Agreements are mostly settled by paying.
Could a person that changes their mind about and then DIA
It becomes a math problem
Right
If you breach the NDA there's a penalty you decide
If you want to pay that penalty
You decided that's worth it
99% of the time
The penalty for breaking an indie 8 is not jail.
It is money
But it can quickly become about much more than money
Because
You've probably just made someone in power
Very angry
And so it is always risky to break
But
We discovered that it isn't a prison
There are these little Escape hatches
Explain a few of them
Support also comes from Fidelity Investment
As a Fidelity Wealth Management
You get a dedicated advisor
To help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes
And make clear recommendations for your full Financial
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
I asked Elie mystal
Is there a way to break an NDA
Legally
Well now we get into my hair part of the NBA conversation
Which is whether or not the NBA was enforceable
To begin with
One of the
Problems that people get into
Is that they think the sign contract is Gospel
But actually there are a lot of reasons and NBA might be unenforceable it's
Tobago or the information it covers is already in the public domain
Or maybe the other side breaks it themselves
Also nda's
Can never prohibit you from talking to law enforcement
Ever
And even if that NDA is enforceable
The damage is hanging over the NBA might not be
So for example
The Stormy Daniels non-disclosure
She was paid $130,000
Can a lawyer threaten to sue her
420 million dollars
Breaking it
But
If that ever actually went to court
She's probably not going to be up
That is under
Unconscionable on its face unconscionable
Is actually also a legal standard
You cannot have damages
They're so out of whack with what the initial contract
Was for
That those damages wood
Quotes shock the conscience
I left that we have these
Legal words that sound like a southern woman declare that is unconscionable
If the damages give you the vapors then
Those aren't necessarily going to be enforced
But so
Sure this may be
There's a hole
Slew of things that you can't find a way
But people don't necessarily know that
Right right and especially the person signing it usually doesn't know that right
So most people stay silent
Because I have to
But there are laws
They can help people void their
If the secret
That person is
Hertz other
These laws are a bit of a patchwork
A very States
In a federal ones are mostly industry-specific
Laws
For example that
Let you report bad stuff in Sanitation
Food Aviation
Dozens of other specific thing
They're usually called whistleblower laws
Sometimes public policy exceptions
And as I studied these
In the midst of this me-too moment
I started to wonder to these exceptions
Extend to victims of sexual harassment
I'm not aware of any case law that says a sexual harassment NDA is invalid because it by
Violates public policy
This is Lisa Bloom an attorney that you may have heard of because she did very briefly join Harvey Weinstein's legal team
But she has spent the bulk of her career representing sexual harassment victims against powerful men like Bill O'Reilly
Bill Cosby
I don't understand why sexual harassment doesn't live as a clear policy exception to NDA
It's probably because
Nobody has challenged it far enough to get to the Appellate level which is where legal precedent gets made
In other words
Someone has to fight it to the highest level of the Court's where rules can be made that apply to
To everyone who follow
It doesn't appear that
What happened yet
Ellie and Lisa both agree that
The reason for this is pretty simple
Kind of a bummer
But simple
I think you've partially answered your own question
They made a movie about that broke again
Like if you're if you're going to be the person to do this
This is your life
This is your whole life
Being this person
And being in real kind of legal Jeopardy
Trying to get
This standard
Changed
Both in a court of law and in the court of public opinion
That's a heavy load
Text back to any one person
It's a load that many people very understandably do not want to carry and shouldn't have to
Many victims welcome into you
Stay but then get restitution and just move on with
For those who do want whistleblower laws to cover sexual harassment nda's
Ellie says
I probably won't come through
For the courts
Like many whistleblower laws
And this is not something we say often
It may be easiest
To have the change come
Through Congress
But so far
Whistleblower protections for reporting sexual harassment
Do not seem to have been established either by case law or statute
Tori law
Far as I know right now
Whistleblowing about your company's culture of sexual harassment
It's just not in that talk
Why
Cook Congress has
Not in its wisdom
Decided to elevate
People who are
Whistleblowing about
Harassment and assault
To the level of
Of a whistleblower who is
Yo talking about financial crimes
Or environmental disaster
We might be on the cusp of that
That might be the
The legal Legacy of me to for all we know to to change how we think about
At a
Statutory
Level
And maybe it will there are a few signs that things are starting to happen
Some states
Are passing and modifying statue
It say you cannot use nda's
In sexual harassment or abuse
And tucked into the new federal tax law is the provision that disincentivizes the use of nda's in sexual
Harassment and abuse case
It says that if you decide to use an NDA
You can no longer deduct the cost of that settlement from your tax
So you know
Change can show up in unexpected places
If you have a secret that you think deserves telling please get in touch we are Planet Money
Npr.org also we have a super secret way to do that if you would like you can go to securedrop
Dot NPR. Org
Money sent you
And it's probably obvious but we are not lawyers so if you are thinking of breaking an NDA you should call a lawyer
We could not have made the show without a wonderful intern Aviva dekornfeld
She puts this story she did a bunch of great reporting on it thank you
So much everybody
Today's show was produced by Sally home with help from Nick Fountain and Alexi Horowitz Ghazi our editor is Bryan Hurst
Supervising producer is Alex goldmark
Special thanks also to Jody short Mary and brown the national whistleblower Center excellent whistleblowers
Reporting from the Wilderness of National Public Radio
Stephen enzyme Kenny Malone
Thanks for listening