There is a joke they tell in China about President Donald Trump's upset victory in 26
And we learned about it from our internet go
Guangxi is from China echo
And the joke is but a province in China where they make
Flags
So I can tell us what is what is the stroke
Yes it's a Providence called you it down and people there
Basalt the word
The first in the world to know that
Trump was going to rain
Because it got way more
Black orders from Trump campaign than from
Clinics
Oh so they were making
Flags for political rallies and they got so many more orders for Trump Flags than Hillary Flags
They knew he was going to win
Lijiang owns a flag making factory in this province
It wasn't that one of the places that was making Hillary Clinton flags and Donald
Trump Flags back in
Make political Flags makes flags for
Countries all over the world
Including the USB says he's made flags for all that
Mr.lee does Nazi
Speak English so we ask
Echo Dot
To translate for
How many flags do you make do you know
Everyday around
Hannah soland
That is so many flags
Yes
Lesions Factory is big and open and the flags are these giant spools is Big fabric rolls or just flag
I got your flag after flag
And workers cut them apart
And so the sides
It's amazing to watch.
They're super fast
Mr. Lee says he makes
A ton of little Flags those 4-inch by 6-inch Flags like the ones that people were waving earlier this week at 4th
July parade
The biggest flag is ever made was
Was for a mega skyscraper in the United Arab Emirates that was more than 160 ft
Lacrosse
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Ramcard Garcia
We are the hosts of the indicator Planet Money daily pot
And he should know it is summer it is
Hot it is
Holiday
Happy Fourth of July cartafreccia yeah and do you actually here right now
No
City of the show we bring you to summer themed episodes from our podcast
First
Flags
As it turns out they are a really fascinating indicate
They can help you predict an election and they can also tell you a lot about global
We called the barn in Iowa that has gotten caught up in a national trend
There used to be a lot of teenager
Just working in the Summers
Now
Cheerleaders are gone
Where are the team
STX
What can I have character somebody wants to do like a sequel to Fast Times at Ridgemont High
Teenage employment
Baby boomers
What
That would be a such a great movie
What happened
When does summer jobs go away
Stick around
Support also comes from Fidelity invest
As a Fidelity Wealth Management
You get a dedicated advisor
To help grow and protect your way
Find ways to minimize the impact of tax
And make clear recommendations for your full Financial
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
We caught up with Mr Lee and his car
On his way home from
Dinner. Just gone out with his wife and son
What did you have in town
France
And rice
Thanks
Chinese food is really good
So do I
See we're just Building Bridges here at the indicator
Chinese food
Literally about his flag Factory and he told us that in fact his Factory did not always make flag
Polenta are actually pretty this
Red scarves for Primary School students
The young pioneers
Beyond Pioneer like the Communist Party
And in fact Miss release Factory is called we must win
From that time
China join the World Trade
What's made it easier for
To the country to trade with the rest of the world
Mr lean his wife saw this
Is chance to grow their business
To go Global themselves
Literally like what is more Global than
Nothing is more Global than
Mr.lee started making flags for countries all around the world
We're producing lot of flak spray come from Germany France Brazil
United Kingdom India
South Africa
Mr. Lee's Factory and the inexpensive labor in his country met his business quickly became competitive on a global
He started charging about a dollar
Peru flag thinking about a dime of profit on each one
A business has been going pretty consistently
With the world and with the US
Least for now
Did the US trade war with China has not yet directly affected mr. Lian
Is business there are no flag Terrace
Yet
The President Trump's escalating trade tensions
Is with trying to do worry mister
And those tensions are especially notable to
Considering one of the orders that he is currently
We also make
Flags for Trump
420 20
Seems like
He has another campaign going on
Chinese in that ride
That's right
Do the flag say made in China on them
Yes Auto
So Cardiff as you know a lot has been made of trump make America great again hats be made in China
But the fact is even though Trump has kicked off what is shaping up to be a full-on trade war with
Chinese flag
And make America great again hat for his cat
Campaign 2000
And
If you need thousands of flags and hats and t-shirts
Span of time at a reasonable price
You go to China
Does it feel
Strange to be making flags for
For him
Is completely normal
That is great we buy stuff from America and America by is fine stuff from China for it sound like
Car is from America
What kind of car do you have
It's a BMW X5
Nice car
And the wife said that it is from Germany
But he said
No I know that is from
Branch of BMW based in America
And in fact
They do make BMWs in Spartanburg County south
South Carolina
BMW move part of its production
In the 1990s and Factory employs about 9,000 workers and they had been planning a big expansion
But
Recently they have threatened to close the plant if President Trump with the Tariff
On European cars
Which he said he just might do
I see you like the car
Where am I
Google what's the best car from Germany and they're producing from Oregon
Cause I like it
This is incredible
I just want to know that right he makes flag
The symbol of a country
Pride
Which he sends to America
Which makes the
Car
Did he drive but which was designed in Germany
And not to mention that he's also talking to us on an
IPhone 7 designed in the US
Made in China
And he's on his way back to a factory where he's busy filling an order for thousands of blue and white
Trump 2020 Flags
Supporting the campaign of a man who's been speaking out
Against businesses like his
You can imagine the situation we're in the future
President Trump is campaigning again
Incel for maybe
Other people are we looking out over sea of supporters
They'll be waving flags and wearing hats
It would just shipped in from China and which are affordable to give out on Mass
In part because of the very system
The President Trump is now condemning
And Mister Lee's flag
Might eventually end up on a US tariff
Are you worried about the trade War
For money
We are not so
Worried because
First of all we have a price advantage
Overall compatibility
Our clients are very smart they would always go to the cheapest place
If China's cheap Legos
China of America
Is there actually are a lot of American flags made in the US
But if you see them at political rallies you should know that they are the expensive
American flag
And we did some searching around we looked at wholesale price
And in some cases
American flags made in the US
Or three or four
Or five times more expensive than the flag
In China
Right and this is the thing about
Because a u.s. made American flag she's going to be way more expensive than a flag made in
In fact
You see this across the whole Tech
Textile industry there used to be a big textile industry in the US up until the 90s
But a lot of that production is moved overseas
Stasia and that has allowed the US economy to grow
How It's Made way for a
A booming Tech sector and a growing healthcare industry
But it is also left some people behind
Mist releases
Even if his us business this
Disappears entirely
He'll be fine
Most of his business is with other countries
Lots of orders lately
In particular from Israel
Pakistan Saudi Arabia
And mostly mr.lee says it would just mean that he wouldn't be making any more us
Us consumers
It would mean either
Pure Flags or more expensive flags at political rallies
Anna 4th of July
I mean you have to look at flags all the time how do you think it compares the other flags looks-wise
Replete with stars and stripes 50 stars isn't it
51 or 50
After the break we bring you our next summer in Decatur reporter Danyelle Chris Layman on a mission to find
Find out where all the teenage summer jobs have gone
Support also comes from Fidelity invest
As a Fidelity wealth
You get a dedicated advisor
To help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of tax
And make clear recommendations for your full Finance
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
Stacy
Daniel Kurtz Laban
So let me ask you a
What was your first summer
Oh that's
Babysitting
Start babysitting when I was about 10 years old
I take it very serious
I have like a whole network of people I was like a little baby sitting
Since you're a one-woman babysitter
Google after while because
I
It was like this very overachieving babysitter known for being in high demand
What are you here for
You know I thought you'd never ask my first my first real summer job with w
Tutus and all that was busing tables at a rat at a restaurant and Golf Course
It was called the barn
I was 14 The Barn is a refurbished Barn actually so is
It's not just a clever name it is in rural Iowa
But
I knew I was going to be doing a story this way
Tweet about Teen son
I'm so
How can you blast from the past I called up the barn
Cuz it's still operating today to see if I could talk to one of the teenagers working there now
And
They told me there aren't any
Really there yet
I called them
Current owner of China
Mark for all I asked him
You don't get a lot of applications from teenagers anymore
Not really
Get some butt
The girls are busy they can never work when we want them
Write like there
It isn't just less of a norm
For now for for teenagers
To work then it used
To be like back when I was a teenager you were too
I think so
Yep course is big difference between
My time in your time to
I mean like Mark Ruffalo he's great I mean
Fair enough Marquis is a little older than me but I'm just bummed me out
Like I was saying everyone works there that said
Maybe I shouldn't have been surprised because what's happening at the barn as it turns out is emblematic of a bigger ship in the labor market
There's just been the shift over the last few decades away free
From the summer job
The number of teens who go out and get summer jobs
Has plummeted in the last
On top of that
Hasn't really picked up all that much since the Great
Recession
Even though unemployment on whole is as low as it's been since 2
Let's start off with a quick
Chart on the radio
If you were to look at a chart of the
Employment rate for teenagers now this is 16 to 19 year olds
There are these regular Sharp
Spike's upper
Now that spike is July
That's the month with teen employment
Peaks every year
And last July nearly 37% of teenagers were working
That's not much at least not if you compare it
The past decade
Back in the 1980s and 1970s
There were a few Summers where that teen employment rate was near Six
80%
Scooby and even the size of those
July spikes
Has gotten
The summer employment bump has shrunk
Considerably over the last
That is a big change since Paul Harrington
Had his first
So quick question what was your first
What did you do with
Well I thought I was out of the gas station attendant
I think I was about 14 then
Today Paul is a labor economist
Drexel univ
Diversity and he is in a lot of research into youth
Absolute Market is really quite good for college grads for pretty much everyone
These are really good
Good Times
Yeah the big exception of that is
Teenagers that teens are not doing very well there is summer job outlook
Is not very good
And there are a lot of reasons
Paul Walker Smith
Through some of them
The first big reason Young Americans aren't working is
Probably the most
Important thing is
Is the change of behavior in the size and behavior of older worker population
Lots and lots of older workers now are working in
Teen labor
Americans are staying in the labor force longer and longer these
For a bunch of
Living longer up some people need more money to retire others just
Want to work longer
And given the choice between a 16 year old and a 6
A six-year-old
Pulses
Most employers will pick the ladder
When you look at the demand side of things is very clear is that Supply able to work
Chris becomes available
What is clearly
Picture of them cuz employers really see all the workers
Is having the base kind of Behavioral traits
Either they need and they think the kids you know increasing we don't have those traits
Dependability reliability self control
In fact pulses tianjin
Tend to be in the back
The job line
Right now the teen unemployment rate
12.8
That is way higher than
Climate rate
3.8
Right but it's not historically high and that's an important
This isn't all about employers not wanting to him
Employ teens it's also about
Teams not wanting
To be employed
I knew it
Was there a felony or somewhere
Just get somebody angry
So many angry bat
I want the teenagers isn't it like a p
Painfully awkward
4 time it was we feeling
But nobody
China area but Spirit of life being stressful for teenagers like many have an incentive
Not work there's a
Reason they're not working
Every summer
Higher education system now I would argue punches
High school kids for working because of the rewards in high school for College admission her and not work related there
Your community service that sort of thing and yuan with respect to X
Free activities
Short version to lot of teenagers waiting tables just is not going to look as good on a college
Application essay tutoring kids are playing three sports or
Doing summer academic programs or burning Rush
And there's sort of a broader cultural aspect
Because
Becomes less of a
Thing
For teens to work for teens even can
Sitter work
Just not the normal kind of like Mark and I were talking
Also we should do
Just add this phenomenon doesn't
Call Tina
In fact the team job market is yet another area in which life is
A little bit easier if you have
A little more money
Lower the family income less likely to get it to work
In a family income Rises you know much higher probability for the for the child to work
A lot of cats
To do with how the liver Mark at work
The waking John adults get jobs is through
Flea markets of social network
The social system
I can't believe you need
Contacts now for a summer job tell about who you know kid
You don't you got to learn that early
But
One thing I should adhere is that the cause and effect kind of go both ways
Is here because aside from what Paul was
You know rich kids might just be more likely to live in healthier economies where there are more jobs anyway
Likewise Lawrence
Some kids might live in an area with fewer
So that also
DePaul the decline and teens working is really bad news because team jobs are important and giving
Basic foundational works
It's a way you develop proficiency
How do you learn behavioral traits
One of the ways to do it is you go behave
The first time
That you're a stack for almost everybody
It's the first time you're asked to act as an adult
In adults
Weather adultery precautions
For your decision
Either positive or negative
Impulse is delaying that economy-wide millions of kids
Is going to create
Workforce wide protective
That's what you worried about
But
For people like Paul who really worried about this I'm happy to report that all is not lost
I found a teen summer worker. Of course they still exist so I called up the
Swimming pool in Buffalo Center Iowa I figured if my old workplace.
Seeds around at least one of my
Friends
Add I got to talk
Crystal shutter
She's 18 years old she just graduated from North Iowa high school gobison
And this is her second summer lifeguarding at the buffalo
It's much more fun than I
Originally anticipated
I mean I work with great people and I enjoy the kids and they're goofy comments then
All of that stuff
Yeah I mean
What do you
Is that what you like most about it is
With the kids
Yeah
Truth be told I eat
Did not like kids growing up like they just kind of scared me
Crystal was great I mean she she actually took her time out of her day of lifeguarding she was talking to me from the Buffalo Center
Cool office
And she got over her phobia of kids of course how she's lifeguarding
But you never plan on making a career of this
Of course she's headed to college
Yeah I'm going to go to Iowa State
And major in animal science
Cool are you going to be a veterinarian
I that's that's the goal
Pictures of thing working at the pool Chris is not getting experience with dogs or
Like that that actually doesn't
She is that could you work while in high school
They just have more likely to work as an adult
Getty up higher
Employment rates
As adults and kids who don't work while in high school
Second thing is is that as adults 10 years later
To make somewhere between 10 and 20% more holding other factors constant
10 kids who didn't work
So Chris's job now will make her higher earnings this a better worker down the line policy
And even at age 8
Team Krista says she can see this happening
And herself
Do you feel like this is
Good job experience or prep
The real world
Absolutely I mean
Constantly interact
Parents and kids and I think it's really help
My
People skills
Interaksi
Stacey Vanek Smith
All of those
Skills you develop babysitting they've made you the reporter that you are now
Yeah it is it is similar somehow
If you don't already subscribed
The indicator
First of all what are you waiting for we post a new episode every weekday afternoon
Sellit Garcia
Better-looking
Definitely so much better looking possibly even earlier
With more lame jokes
Jason lame I meant awesome
Awesome joke last week we went to a bar to watch the world
Stop and repeat
Economic insights that came out of it
And we also got inside of what it looks like to do a big bank stress test
All
Vibrate review
It is the indicator from planet
Funny posts
Saul episodes
On Facebook
You can find us there and if your thoughts about this episode leave a comment on the post
And you can also find us on Twitter and Instagram or emails
Planet Money NPR. Org
Indicator is produced by Doris Rafi
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
And I'm Cardiff Garcia
Thanks for the