Support for NPR and the following message
Which come from WWE
Publishers of people power and profit
Progressive capitalism for an age of discontent
By Nobel prize-winning economist
Joseph E stiglitz
Just a quick note this is our second episode in a little series on elections and how you
You can gain them
The first episode is called red map it's at
Episode number 8 4 5
You can listen in any order and here's a show
There is
A type of person who follows
State Politics the way that some people follow High School football
And Dan Smith is one of
Dan is a political science professor at the universe
Florida and in the summer of 2011
He found himself
Glued to His Radio
These hearings were going on and I remember listening on the radio
To the series of
Public hearings across the state
They were hearings about this thing that Florida had just done that was kind of crazy
And that like Florida man marries
Is Burmese python crazy
It was crazy because
Florida had just up and become
Super politically response
The hearings were about this new law that Florida has
That could change politics there in a big
Very
Transparent opening of the
In process
Assure that
Why weren't going to be drawn to Advantage the Republican or Democratic Party
Florida is technically a swing state the population is pretty much
Split between Republicans and Democrats
When Florida started electing more Republicans in the 1990
And that was because of Jerry man
Where politicians draw maps in a way that favors their own party
Both Republicans and Democrats gerrymander but
In Florida at that time it was the Republican
And in 2010 the citizens of Florida said enough already
They outlawed partisan gerrymandering
Technically this was not great news for the Republican Party
But they said you know what citizens of Florida let's do this
In fact let's go nuts
You tell us
How to draw the
The state legislators put software online where citizens
Could draw and see
Submit their own
They went on a tour of 26 cities there were town halls for citizens to share their ideas
Annie's hearings were packed there sometimes standing-room-only
People would get up and they would testify about how they thought their districts should be drawn
But I would like to see us have a district where the student voice gets her Hardee County I definitely would like to see that
They keep us with the Inland counties like to be in the same district
People show up to these here
And regular people regular citizens be submit nearly 200
Play everybody is at his big redistricting pep rally
Citizens are putting maps in
Politicians won't stop talking about how their process is
Is the most open and transparent in Florida's history
But then that
Political science Professor pedals
To His Radio
He's carrying something a little different than everyone else
And I remember hearing some people that I knew
Some of the people testifying at these hearings they're like hey I'm Average Joe from Jack
Jacksonville and dance like
This guy
Isn't
Just an ordinary citizen he's been working for Republican candidates this whole political career
How many citizens are not really talking like average
Chose
Most people were being real don't even know what district they live in
And yet some of these citizens seem to have strangely specific opinions about there.
Speaking about the importance of the I-75 Corridor and being on one side and
I using that as a
Border for this new District it would be created
South of Gainesville
Dimples out a notebook and he starts keeping track of these very knowledgeable
And after Gathering all of this
Input the Florida State Legislature releases
It's newly drawn most
Citizen Centric world greatest most non-partisan map
Andes map
Still look
Pretty gerrymander
And I'm not
Clairvoyant person
I'm just a cynic
I knew
That something was going on
What I didn't realize was the depth
Dan was about to find himself deep inside this mystery
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Karen Duffin and I'm Noelle King today on the show as true political thriller we are
We are going to follow Dan Smith on his journey to uncover a conspiracy
There will be political operative there will be late nights poring over documents and maps that are perfect
Almost too perfect
Support for NPR comes from LinkedIn learn
Proud to support the launch of life
NPR's guy to help you make better life decision
LinkedIn learning short video tutorials cover
For business tax
And creative skills employers look for at every level
All talk by X
And new courses are added every week
+ LinkedIn learning
Personalized
Recommended courses based on your interest
And life
Get listeners get a month of learning
Free start your free trial
Trial at LinkedIn learning.com NPR
Okay so this is early 2012 Florida politicians have gathered all that's
Citizen input and release new electoral Maps
Right after those new map
Maps are released for the League of Women Voters has brought a legal challenge the map of Florida 27 Congressional
The League of Women Voters of Voting Rights group they say
Republicans
What we agreed to quarts
Make them draw those Maps again but nonpartisan for reals this
Right about this time Dan who was a registered Republican and gets an email
I get contacted
By the legal team working for the League of Women Voters
The woman who emailed and asked him can you help us analyze these maps and try to figure out what happened here
Dan is a full-time Professor so he already has a day job and
And a half
But he's also estate political junkie and he has very strong feelings about gerrymandering in Florida
It just makes you mad
Maybe it's cuz
I've always been a competitive athlete and I
I know that I'm not always going to win
Want to have that chance
And I don't want the deck stacked against me
The get-go
So he takes this righteous
Wonky anger
It says yes
I will help you
On my nights and weekends and whenever I can
It was a lot of
Piecemeal work that would come get working from home working in the evenings. Hours of the night
2012 he's analyzing the maps
Any very quickly Zooms in on one specific
District district 5
And it was clear that
That District was the key to the the overall Republican gerrymandering
Hurricane in Florida
To understand why that is true and what dance
Looking for you need to understand District
On the map
District 5 looks men
Kind of looks like someone spilled milk on Florida and
Just gave it a name
The district
Strips from Jacksonville all the way down to Orlando
District 5 is kind of the embodiment of gerrymandering in America
Not all gerrymandering is
The same there's partisan gerrymandering
Andrea that's what Florida made illegal
But there's another kind of gerrymandering that
Quartz sometimes actually order
Like Florida's District 5
That District was
Conceived and gerrymandered not by politicians but by the courts
Because of the federal voting rights
Was one of the big civil rights laws
The 1960
Designed to make sure that black Americans could vote and elect representatives
What's a color the law saying basically this is America in order for black candidates to win their have to be
Enough black people in the district to Alexa
So this weirdly shaped spilled milk District 5 with deliberately created
To have enough minority voters
So that a minority candidate
Could Witten
And after the courts to district5 Battersea
Exactly what
I'm the first person in 129 years a Afro-American has been elected from Florida
This is former representative Corrine Brown celebrating her election in 1992
I come from a district of people who have not been apart of the system
Corrine Brown we have to say is now in jail on fraud charges
But the goal of District 5 it work
And many African Americans
In Florida
Rejoice
So did Republican
For a really interesting reason
Black voters in Florida tend to vote for Democrat
So packing them into District
Five men that they weren't voting in sadist
4 weirdest
Which made it easier for Republican candidates
Two windows now more white
District
They were putting African-Americans and districts that would allow
These districts to elect a minority
But as result
Democrats started losing
More seats across the state
These packs
Minority districts like District 5
Are good for
Candidates of color
Good for republicans
But overall
Not so good for Democrat
Packing districts like this
Becomes the thing it becomes a strategy for republicans
Dan knows that one of the best ways to even out the party
In balance in Florida is to unpack district5 to spread out that
When he sees the new maps release
East by the state legislature
District 5 is not on
In fact it's even more packed than both
Before
Dan suspect that this has been done deliberately
And he starts to find proof
A republican consultant kind of
Spilled the beans on what was happening behind the scenes of the whole redist
Printing process
The story that the consultant tells
Explain that weird thing with Dan did noticed while he was listening to
Mishpat
German my name is Alex Patton
This is Alex
He testified at a public hearing as you know a regular Joe citizen
But then nose
Alex is the longtime Republican operative
This consultant explains what's been going on with Alex and with some other
Republican legislators have been saying we do the maps away the citizens told us
Now then learns a small group of Republican
Consultants Drew secret maps
Then pass them off to people like Alex
Who then testified and submitted the maps like they drown themselves
They had
Actively smuggled partisanship into the final match
All in order to have you know
Citizen
Input
The dance has was for the Republicans to
Point to later to just
Justify their partisan
Be citizen plans like Alex were assigned roles
His role was to act
Confuse
Siri is talking at wannabe here
But I just don't understand the language
Remember when working in politics
Next four years
But Alex Patton script didn't just say act confused
It also contained the Republicans most important talking point
Do you want to keep District 5 pack
So here's Alex's
However I want you to pay
Retention
To protect our right
Proportional districts
And the strong gains made
Dissipation
Nothing he just said protect minority games
What is essentially code for protect areas like
And legislators specifically
Pointed to statements like Alex's to justify key
Keeping District 5
Jeb regular Florida Citizens are really concerned about the diversity in District 5 we would love to
Impact District 5 but you know
Citizens
Have spoken
Wind and seas the charade he knows exactly what to
He needs to find exact matches between Maps drawn by Republican control
Maps emitted by these so-called citizens
And the final legislative
Maps the maps that became law
This would prove that partisanship deed sneak its way into
Final map
I was basically smuggled in by these Republican play
Because so many variables go into making any given map there literally millions
Configurations
It is statistically almost impossible for two different
People to draw
Exact same
To Spill the milk exactly the
So damn nose
If you can find any
Act match between 8
Consultant planted map
And one of the legislators final match
That is no coincidence
It would mean that legislators
Basically just like
Copy pasted the Consulting
Danvers diving into the maps
And Bank
We found
A map that was submitted
Supposed to be by a citizen
That had
The same genetic makeup
August final map
It was the last map submitted just before the deadline
And the citizens District 5 map is packed exactly the same way the legislators disc
Big 5 map
Danos this can't be a coincidence
Whoever submitted this map
Has to be a partisan plant
So the lawyers that Dan had been working for
They find the name of
The guy who submitted this
Vine
And it's a guy named Alejandro Perez
Next up we have Alejandro Posada
First off I just like
Got map has his name on it
He also testified at a public meeting
But no one had ever heard of
Yeah he's not a known Republican operative in Florida so
Who is he
You are a college
This map was submitted by an FSU undergraduate
Little if any
Map making
Experience
But instead of this being
Gotcha moment like we just found the partisan who drew the maps
That undergrad Alejandro
Posadas says
Wait what are you guys talking about
I did go to a hearing
But I never submitted a map
I don't know maybe someone just
Like stole my name off the sign in sheet and see
Submitted a map in my name
So they can't prove Alejandro's map came from a consult
Until one day a lawyer working on this
Casey guy name
It's called a nap and he says
Hidan swing by I have something for
Number for tanning over
A flash drive
The shape of a silver bullet
This flash drive is full of secret map
Strong by Republican Consulting
Stan's been trying to get his hands on these
4 years
It was a court order that forced the Republicans to hand them over
But now that he does have them it's just
4 weeks before the trial is set to start
Trying to get one of these puzzles and
Do it with a
Clock ticking away
Dan and Shay
A team of graduate
But students
Start combing through this cash of C
Secretly drawn partisan maps that they
Just gotten
And a zero in on one map
But has a very interesting name
It was called
Perfect pieces
Name these
Imperfect
Next time we're totally not reading the process
Conversion for
Perfect pieces was a little too perfect
District 5 was drawn exactly the same in perfect
Pieces the party center on map
In Alejandro posadas map and in the final Legend
Just latest mat
Dan found the match
These Maps where milk was spilled in a
Exactly the same
Now they are ready for trial
First case on the docket today is the
Mapmakers behind perfect
Pieces are unmasked
During match
Republican Consultants testify that they drafts of Florida Congressional Maps they were later submitted to the ledges
Slate Run to the name Alex Posada
But the Consultants say
We don't know how Alex
What's the time in Qatar
Here's one of them Rich Heffley being questioned at the trial
Can you explain to me
That
First of all you're not my districts
Second mall I won't say what my mom taught me about assuming things but
I will tell you
The I don't know Mister Posada I didn't have anything to do with submitting Maps
I don't know how they got the Bubba
Republican Consultants say
We don't know how people got our mats
And even if we did have them off our mats weren't drawn with partisan intent
But then a piece of evidence emerges to prove intent
Where is pretty damning
We'll tell you what Dan sound coming up after the
Support for
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Cambridge
The Bold way to steady growth
People often think of nobodies are too conservative
Too complex or only for retirees
But annuity
These can be a smart way to
To Head Market risk
And earn guaranteed returns
Cambridge aims to change the game
By offering simplified annuity
Please in a Sleek digital experience
That replaces fine print in
Phone tag with clear conditions
Ana direct loafy model
Learn more at gamebridge. Life
5 / NPR
Game Boy
Is not available at Allstate
Miss this report to the lawyers that shows the match were designed to gain the Voting Rights Act
It was a really sneaky way to hide partisanship under the guise of being fair to people of color
They had
Pat Moore black voters into
District 5 then it had ever
More than was needed to elect a
Color
Enough that it would likely hit this
Pacific Legal fresh
Hitting that threshold meant the district was
Protected by the Voting Rights
So if Democrats ever wanted to unpack
District 5 it would be
Very very hard
And when the judge realizes along with everyone else what has happened
He issues a scathing ruling
He says Florida Republicans have made a mockery of the democratic process
Orders them to redraw the lines
End
Many years and lawsuits later Florida
Finally does
But the Florida legislature
Couldn't agree on the maps
So in the end
The courts true
Just in time for the 2016 election
In these new maps District 5
And the claim that unpack
Packing District 5 would hurt miner
Did not pass
In fact
When voters from District 5 were now spread out across several districts
Free of those districts elected
People of color
Once the maps are redrawn politicians actually start to have to
To fight for their seeds
And in a lot of cases their positions
Start to change
Now politicians can't just politic to their base
They have to appeal to everyone
Politicians start shifting positions on issues like the minimum wage Health Care guns
Like this one state senator
She previously had a 100% rating with
With the NRA
And after the lights GIF she starts saying things
I do not support having guns on campus I do not have any
It support having guns
Airport I don't have to having guns
In school zones I don't support
Those things
So tens of millions of dollars and four years of litigation later does it was it worth it
Yeah I mean it's it's
It's a good question I think
You know in the end
It was definitely worth it not
Because it elected Democrats
Or minorities but because these Maps were objects
Wayfair
It does open up the process
If only under threat of
Subpoena
This thing that Florida did
Outline partisan gerrymandering
The Supreme Court might do it to for the rest of the
The court just heard two cases about it and it's going to issue rulings later this month
Talk to at
Kind of people in Florida
Lawyers politicians
Consultants Democrat and Republican
And a lot of them said
Some shady partisan
And stuff did go on a
District 5
But
Remember why District 5 with created and gerrymandered
In the first place
So that people of color had a fair shot at getting elected
Gerrymandering
Fix that
And as long as race
Send political affiliation state
Tangled as they are in the sky
Country
It will be really hard to figure out how to draw the line
Soap
Rest of America
Take note
Really love to hear what you think of the show email us Planet Money at npr.org or find us on Facebook too
Twitter or Instagram where at
Planet Money Today Show was produced by Sally Helm and making 10 or supervising producer is Alex goldmark and brynhurst at and it
Special thanks to the many people who spoke with us for this story including Ellen frieden Alex
Patton Beverly Colson Neal Michael McDonald
Bono
And those who spoke with me on background or off to record you know who you are thank you
I'm Karen Duffin and I know Elle King thanks for listening
In the original version of the story we miss identified Republican consultant
Who we played testifying at trial