Hey it's Robert Smith and Nick fountain
Happy birthday America you look
Great I've been working out you do not look a day over 200 years
We're taking the day off cooking up some burgers and hotdogs but we still the show for you today
Our favorite show
Yet about hot dogs
We first ran it back in 2016
And we'll have an update event
Here it is
First pitch Robert welcome to Fenway Park
It is a beautiful freezing cold evening
In April in Boston
So the reason we're here today is not to do the Tampa Bay Rays Red Sox play by play
The which we certainly could do know we're here because our beloved producer Nick fountain
You still work here in the stadium it was one of his first
Jobs ever and what you do
What do you want
Are you showing off
Turn around I want that water
It was one of the hardest jobs because I was running up and down the stairs so hot dog sewing crackerjacks I would peanut salad
Richie benaud ball game you bought something from these guys
And Nick was saying like listen there is an entire
World going on
Underneath the bleachers but you have no idea there
This entire system whereby they figure out
Who sells what how much they're going to sell it for and how much money they are going to make
An average Night Like This
Blown welcome to Planet Money I'm Nick Fountain and I'm Robert Smith today on the show
We take you inside the secret game that is played every night
Underneath
This ballpark baseball player wait till you see the fastest hot dog vendor in the world
Rookie who wants to take his place
Support also comes from Fidelity invest
As a Fidelity wealth management client
You get a dedicated advisor
To help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of tax
And make clear recommendations for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
For hot dog
And popcorn vendors the most important moment of the night happens a few hours before
That's why you are still looking for parking
They are meeting
Deep underneath
Kettle corn
Kosher hot dog vending machines really a thing
Citic Bank in a basement parking lot
Beautiful right
This is where I used to work
Beautiful dark is death
It is filled with
Empty kegs
Can use pallets but
In the middle of the lot there's this
Stainless steel table and crowding around it there's a bunch of guys
Dressed for work
Youth sports shorts
Yellow baseball hat
We got we got shot today they say menu
What's about to happen is
Is called
The pick
It's been talking
This is where the vendors get to pick what they are going to sell tonight up in the
Stay up
They work on commission
So the more they sell the more money they make until picking the right item
Either set
So right now we've noticed we have a 57 guys working tonight so we're going to make
This list available for 57 available products
The product
Coke Cracker Jack
Peanut hot dog
The product is provided by multinational food conglomerate
Aramark
All these guys work
Prayer box
Arabic does not micromanage who sells what
The company let the vendors
Fight it out every night
Take a pic like a sports Trac like the NBA draft
All the guys have this idea in their head of what product they want to pick
They all gather around Mike while she's one of the vendors he actually runs the pic
And they're going to decide 1byone what products are going to sell
In what sex
Billy home Billy Currington Bud Light on a home
Stanley will take Bud Light on a home
Bro
Roar
Love that guy
Yes silly Lynch Ebro
Some serious Boston Irish
Avengers get to pick based on senior
The top guys who have been here the longest and what's up been there 30 years I've been there for really long get to pick
First they get to pick the best products
And it's not a coincidence
Stadium
The product I want to sell
Arsenal four-letter right
Corte De hombro
Early
Blue Moon blood loss.
Ibiz gone hey there's only so many beers slot so after they're gone
Tenders
Start thinking of
I have to start using strategy
Every night at the Ballpark
You see guys checking their weather app
They want to know what's the temperature at the start of the game what's the temperature at the end of the game what's the relative humidity
You can make
Killing selling lemonade or water are frozen lemon
But this is not
A hot night I checked my fancy weather app
Thanks Yahoo
It's 49 degrees out there by the time the pick gets to number 20
The 20th person on the list Jose McGrath
Using top spot
TV
The worst night of the year problem most likely
The worst night of the year so far
It's a Wednesday
I just don't give away like last night was cold but there was Mookie Betts bobblehead giveaway
What's the strategy tonight
Something warm
Optional RV hot dogs or you can stick pretzels
Maybe a hot chocolate
I'm going to follow Jose around tonight because he is a legend
You think I'm a legend 6 years ago when I was working there
He was so cool I didn't even get to
The talk to you
That's what tonight I am stoked
To figure out what he's going to pick and his strategy in deciding what
Jose's number
The twentieth of never
Gets to sell beer at
And yet
He consistently sells more product
Than anyone else
The parkway
Which means more Commission
What's your ranking commissioned last year before before
If I were a betting man I would bet that Jose is going to have the highest Commission
You can tell just by looking at him he's a good sales
He's got the deep and what she told us he got spending a few weeks of spring training selling items down there and we keep
Pestering him
Until we get him to admit
I consider myself
The best
Reason Jose is the best
Because he doesn't just
Guess what he's
He is meticulous about
Even has a spreadsheet at home where he analyzes
What picks work the best
Jose doesn't just look at the temperature
When you mix it
He evaluates who else is selling his prime
How many guys are selling it
Who's the possible guys are up against
Elizabeth difference of
Mike is really good meme I keep trying not to sell
With each other
Oh cuz it's competition
Jose looked at the list
Has it all in his head
It makes it
I'll take dogs
In the bleachers you just took hot dogs out of waitress
Call Matt Mobley
Donkey Kong
After Jose pics
The next year they with the cold weather play
Coco's gone
They're hoping no one brought their heavy jacket
Kateri home
I'm going to take a pizza in the bleachers
What is Robert
Just picking what they're selling
Tonight they're picking the territory
So like hot dogs at a home
Pizza in the bleachers
It's because they're sizing up their customers by how much they paid for their baseball team
When I was working there Diet Coke sold really well around home plate
Cuz you know that's where the vein people sit
Coke regular Coke sold much better in the blue
Now I know Nick that you are rooting
For your idol Jose he is the best he's that
He's the Derek Jeter Pedro Martinez Pedro Martinez of
Vendors at Fenway
But I
Have a good feeling about some of the younger
Talent tonight
While those old guys have been here forever they're getting their sweet Pixar beer at home
There are some lean and hungry
Teenager standing in the back of the garage just
Waiting for
Hi my name is Mitchell lion I'm a vendor at Fenway Park
And you have been working how long here
About two weeks
5 games
Which is a senior in high school
Call Kids R
You smile
It has the new guy he will choose almost near the end of the list
He doesn't even think about picking hot dogs or beer
You're out of his League
What's the dream like maybe people didn't show up maybe play a different is there a dream for today well
Peanuts I could probably get I've heard people getting peanuts on their first year they make very good money off of that
So if for some reason there's peanut there tonight
Have you ever thrown them before
But I can figure that one out pretty easily
There is no way he's going to get peanuts today
Add to work for three years before I could sell peanut
But you can see the pitches mph
Younger
He's the new Jose if he can just
Get a good pic
Mitch goes second-to-last
And he has
Two choices
He could sell this season's newest product
Cheetos
Popcorn
Apparently you will get heckled by the Boston fat if you run up and down the stand screaming Cheetos popcorn
Or is that the choice is
Water
In the cheeks
I'll take water out of bluetooth on
Mitch's in for a really long night
Some of my worst memories from this job we're selling cold drinks on a really cold night
It was terrible
Mitch has a plan
You basically just have to yell water you get your water here ice cold water
I'm going to give you a tip that I learned working here
It's a cold night don't say ice cold
Sure thing I can do that warm water
Do the kid learns fast
He is smart
Mitch is the underdog
Good luck with that
The pic is officially over
Everyone grabs their stuff to put in the uniform which is base
Basically this bright
Yellow t-shirt each T-shirt has a specific number on the back Jose the legend he's number one
Admits the rookie selling water hundred
They had to some kitchens to pick up their product
And we had up to the stand to watch the game
Annabelle
Next time you're at a ballgame I recommend you look away from the game
Winchester
Watch
The vendors
They are
Amazing
Every second count because every second they can save
Running up the stairs are running down the stairs are doing a quicker more efficient transaction
If another second they could use
Define another customer
To make another sale it was really hard work
The first yard work there I just switch from glasses to contacts cuz I was sweating so much
I'm still watching super efficient system here
Yeah but it wasn't always like this
When I worked here and there was a manager in the corporate office
She decided at the beginning of that what mix of products are being so
Three guys selling Coke out of right field to Cotton Candy guys in the bleachers
Top down
What are the suits know at Aramark the vendors are the ones
You can feel the temperature
Airdrop 5
Subtly read
The mood of the crowd when there's no bobblehead giveaway
Yeah by letting them run the pick by having their paychecks dependent on how much they sell
They figure out the best allocation of the product
It makes way more sense that the vendors make
Decision if they have all the information
High enough. I want to go see how our guys are doing
Okay it's been really hard
To chase down
Jose
The number one performer the self-proclaimed
Best Ben-Hur
In the ballpark Rhapsody knighted states begin boots really fast really fast but we finally set up here the bleacher so we can watch
Watch him work he scans back and forth you see somebody he put down his box and hotdogs
Wax paper
There goes the dog
Call you
That was like 3 seconds
Yeah going slow today though
Hello call Nicole
Call frigid
Spell divorce law at someone
You give me 20
He's the Master look at how quick to give the change
Looking around nope no sales he runs down
Boom boom boom boom boom cat takes a very spry man to run downstairs
If somebody grab them
Wax paper bun
There goes the dog
In his hand and he has the money in his other hand while he's making the hot dog
Hygienic
A hot dog
A lot of money
He tried his best
How about now
So nice
Amazing watch a master at work
A dog
I noticed something about Jose
As soon as he makes the sale he is scared in the crowd
Annies looking not just for other sales but for his
Competitors
You can see him run up to a mile
Spot another hot dog vendor in the aisle in immediately pivot and pick another song
You don't run to where the hot dog is
You run to where the hot dog is going to be
You are vending Guru
Let's see how my pic
Mitch the underdog the rookie
What's the heaviest weight
Alright head up the stairs
Look up
Robert is pretty exhausted right terrible
Welcome to the cheap seats
High up in the bleachers
So this is the section that Mitch has chosen
To sell his water in like this is his territory tonight
And
We're watching him down there he's got his water he just is about to make a cell looks like he went out of use how's your day
So far
You guys have a good night
Yes but looking up slowly is with the money just like
He doesn't have the technique that has water over
Yours too
1050 is going to be a change
Oh my God
Struggle with that money there
Hope you enjoy today
Okay it is a little bit of a rough night permit
I will admit
I see a lot of potential here
And
His whole life struggling with the water struggling with the change thing
Sympathy
From the crowd I saw one gentleman give him a nice
She just gave him a little tip
It's a lot of stairs up here
I will see the vendors are not
Eager
Talk about
Their tips but Clues have to be
E major Park
Yeah Summers I was working there I had no shortage of
Of cash money in my wall
There's a reason why if you notice at the park the price for water is 475
A hot dog is 5:50 until when you were there did you really like slow roll.
Yeah when I was working there I was selling
Coke and diet coke a lot it was for 25 so to give
Two-person $5 back and then I would hold up the quarters and I would say
Hey guy you want your quarters like
You want me to pass these three
Dirty metal objects down this road of people
Keep the quote
Nick there is a real economic
Lesson here
About the fundamental nature of competition
It turned out hold up we're going to interrupt the podcast we're going to sing Sweet Caroline Boston tradition
Please
What was that you were saying Robert
I would like to get to make a serious point about productivity gains and
Distributed decision-making and ruthless efficiency of process
I did notice some
If past 9 p.m.
The Red Sox are up 73 against the Rays
Play the crowd is sort of starting to go home
Most of the vendors are done for the day
Night they're down below counting their money eating leftover hot dogs and
Mitch the rookie the underdog he's nowhere to be
But you know who is still around
Jose
Jose is still hustling
In fact he is the last
Bender
In the park and because he has no competition
He has left
The bleachers
It is a sight to see he's doing his whole Loop of the stadium
First base
Home
3rd Base everyone's territory running up and down the stairs
Sing the last hot dog
The last face
It's always like this is
Is why Jose is the best he just stays out longer
He works harder than everyone else this is what I came here looking
Looking for thought it was the spreadsheet of the strategy
No it's really just hustling harder Jose is the last Bender to return from the stands
He's the last with the cash out
He's the last one hang up his number one
Yellow shirt
At any point
Today did you watch
Any of the game did you look out on the stadium or
Twice
I'll check the ending to see where I'm at how much time I have left to sell and I'll take your time as well
There was one play that something happened looked up it was
It was all done for
Weber playing tonight
Feels like today
Now I don't know if I could
You spent 3 hours in a ballpark
Huge baseball fan
Yeah my chosen today
It's the Tampa Bay Rays
That feels about right
I think he was deeply embarrassed by this but
Let nothing be embarrassed about we got his final numbers he sold 270
Hot dog 270 hot dogs that works at 2
$1,500
Worth of hotdogs
We did the math
He probably made a commission of round
200 200 $50
Maybe we're guessing here you got
$150 in tips
Bottom line somewhere in the ballpark of 400
Not bad for a cold winter
What Jose called the worst
Night of the year
Mitchell rookie water kid
Are Underdog
He left early I mean he's a high school student
Hit long train ride back
The suburbs where he lives
Parents don't like him staying out too late
But we called him up to see how his night with
Haymitch hello
Hello how's it going dude says he had a much better night
How many Waters did you end up selling
Es6 not bad for a newbie
He told us he probably made sixty bucks in commission and we're guessing here but maybe 20 or $30 in tips
Some idiot $90 for a couple hours work
That's great
But Jose made were thinking around $400
$100
No contest
On the number
But you know what Mitch did remember who the socks
Complain that night
And post it was just one other thing
Standing in the back of the stadium in
All of a sudden I look down I saw the whole stadium I saw all the players all the
Stanza
It was just
And how long does that feeling last
It lasted about
Two or three seconds and then I I got back to work
I still remember it
Nick
Who really had the better night
Jose
A lot
Coming up after the break
It's 2 years later
Whatever happened to Mitch
Support for this podcast in the following message come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities to help ensure a brighter future for America's
Children more information is available at aecf. Org
Hates Robert and Nick
Here in the year 2018 we recorded that show two years ago and we want to check back in with everyone
Jose of course he is still
Working at Fenway still quote
Selling a hot dog or two
He told us
But we are really interested in what happened to the rookie
What happened to Mitch
Are you still working at Fenway
I'm still working there
I'm off right now because I hurt my leg but how did you hurt your leg was it a hot dog in tree
Almost I was walking up the stairs and my leg cramped up and I couldn't walk for like 20 minutes
Cheeseburgers
Yeah tasty burgers
Puppy bomb
I like $9
So when we last spoke to you you are kind of like a rookie right like you're just started the job
How's it been have you been getting good products hot dogs peanuts
Beer
I've been getting a lot better products yeah I've been selling ISO peanuts a few times souvenir soda has been pretty good
End
Popcorn I haven't gotten hot dogs yet maybe next year hopefully
How's your
Peanut Farm
I've had a few people but other than that I'm not bad
It's hard
One final question
Do people ever stop you and say hey you're that guy from the podcast
Yeah people wanted one guy recognize music with you and I
What
Music you're the podcast right and I was like yeah
Mitch
Thanks so much for checking in
Yeah no problem thanks for having me as
We love to hear what you think of the show especially Boston Red Sox fan come on
Come on I want to hear from you Planet Money at npr.org
Special thanks to miss rosalee's staff who is the career counselor at my high school and helps me get the job at Fenway
Also to Jake Graham felsen
Sean Ryan and Devin Garrity
For teaching me everything I know about venting you had a real future invented how did you get into radio
The reason I have a job at NPR is cuz I had an internship at NPR and we want to know that we are so
Soliciting intern application
Right now
If you're smart if you can hustle if you're in college or if you graduate in the last year
Qunar website npr.org money
I'm Robert Smith Mountain thanks for listening
You know why we're in the park
You did show me your secret weapon
For selling drinks on a cold
Sweet Diet Coke
Sora
It's all good
Frozen
I would people respond well to that
That was pretty much booze and throwing a trash at me