Hello Dan trials
So you have a story for us
And it starts
With a guy in Georgia
His name is Artie Shaw
He worked for the Georgia Department of Agriculture for many years
Mercy love garden
He wrote a column about it called Artis Garden every once in awhile he would star in a video about Georges
The flowers
And these videos they look like they were recorded on
A cell phone standing in a city
Park parties in his brown suit
He kind of like reminds me of a guy who'd Maybe
Do your taxes
Maybe like collect the plate of money at
Even though it's a cloudy day here in Atlanta I feel like I need sunscreen Sandy mix all of these Sunny blossom
Fragrance
Divine
I have been trying like crazy to reach
Arty schronce
Your call has been forwarded to an automated voice messaging
System
Hi this is Dan Charles
From National Public Radio I'd left phone mess
I sent letters
We never heard back
Honestly considering what he went through I can kind of understand if you wouldn't want to
The journalist
He got in the middle of something way bigger than him
Here's what happened
4 years artist wants hot this
Really nice job
He answered people's questions about
Culture in Georgia he talk to Luke
Gardening group
And then six years ago he moved to a different department
He became director of George's poultry
Marketing news
I can chicken
And it's not like a newspaper about chicken it's a Roundup of what is happening in George's chicken
Economy
Copy of it here
Poultry market news
And this is not an easy read this is you need a PhD
Check the market
Is study to
Occasionally week
To firm live Supply is adequate I don't know what that means the firm and live but there is a part that kind of jumps out of
Youth in both ears
A list of chicken parts and prices
So
Line run tenders are dollars
69 Holbrook
$0.92
And these are the official chicken prices for the state of Georgia
Which is important because Georgia is a giant
In the chicken world it is so big
The University of Georgia even makes inspirational videos about it
The state of Georgia
Is the number one producer of chicken meat in the United States
And
Depending on what year you look at it if you just took the state of Georgia compared to the rest of the world we be the fifth or sixth
Largest producer of meat in the entire world
So there a lot of people
Shrouds
Heat goes from
Commenting on
Spring flowers
To being right in the middle of this huge end
Annie's publishing prices that
Could affect
Nottely Georgia but the fortunes of multibillion-dollar come
Companies like supermarket
If they use this in
Fast food joints
Walmart did
Artie's index help them to figure out what they should pay for
And then
About 2 years ago
Hardee's job
Became a nightmare
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Charles
Play on the show rtt's index goes bad some shadowy Wall Street in
Pastors become convinced that chicken companies are charging Americans too much for their chicken and they try to expose
Nrt shrontz gets stuck in the middle
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Should come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solution
Strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org
Hey I'm Kelly mcevers from embedded
Bill Spencer works at a coal mine in
Kentucky
It when I start asking about
Future without coal
You know what I'm going to say so if I'm done board
Play NPR one app for wherever you get your
That list of chicken prices at RTP
This is called the Georgia.
Dock it has been around for 40 years
To every week already has a job of calling up the
And we're talking about you.
The handful of huge company
Tyson Foods
Pilgrim's Pride
Sanderson Farms
He called him up and he says well what are you selling your chicken drumsticks for
Any compiles those numbers
He puts out the end.
No Assurance is not like
The only person in the country doing this the US Department of Agriculture publishes chicken prices some other
How to companies do it
And the prices on these indexes are usually not too far apart
Couple of years ago
Things got weird
So take a look at this graph
So this line is chicken prices
According to the USDA
And this line is the Georgia doc
Price Index
So these are artists
Okay so I see what's happening
Here I mean basically so the two lines are going along
Pretty similar for many years
And then it looks like late 2015 early twenties
15 the USDA numbers would fall off a cliff there yeah they're going down and look at all these numbers
He just likes
Stay way up there
Yeah it looks like maybe like 30 even 50% higher than the USDA.
Sing chicken
Cheap already saying
Chickens expensive of course is a big missed
This is the mystery that started this whole
Because if different
Price in
Are telling us dip
Which one is telling the truth
And why would one of them
Mby
One of the people who's looking at this graph in
Scratching his head his lense
Is 1200 miles away from RT he's way up in New Hampshire
And he is a consultant to big companies that buy a lot of
Chicken
Hundreds of Millions
Sounds of every year
Like like big
Chain breast
Len looks at this graph and he sends a note to his client
We work
Pointing that out
Georgia Doc is really
Overpriced compared to the USDA
Call City Market average.
And and did you have a
Any
Thoughts on that or no
Explanation for it what did you think was going on
Sometimes it doesn't matter
What my thoughts are looking
You just noticed that
This is not
Moving the way it used to move something has changed here
One tells his clients
Watch out
Because this
Could cost you a lot of my
Here's why
The big restaurants in end in supermarkets
They want to lock in a supply of chicken for like 5 years
But they can't lock in a specific
Price so what they do as they write a contract that lets
The price go up and down
Based on some indicator of the market
Can we say
Rather than negotiate week-to-week on what the price of chicken should be
Why don't we
Just tired of this indicator
That indicator could be Artie's index
The Georgia poultry market news
Or I could be another index
And think about what happens
When are these prices all of a sudden are way higher than everybody else is if you're paying for chicken
Based on artist prices you're suddenly paying a lot more than you have to
And who's pocketing that extra money
Well it would be the chicken producers
They benefit if chicken prices are higher
And remember Artie's index has chicken prices
Higher than all the other sodas graph line
Is going far apart
So what's going on
We wanted escardi about
Perhaps no tree is as beloved as our native flowering dogwood
We do know this
The federal government got a
A tip that there was something fishy going on with this Georgia price
So the US Department of Agriculture the USDA sent three of its people down to Georgia
To talk to Arty schronce to watch how he compiled is index
And after that visit
For some
Do USDA decides to
Stop
Posting Artie's index
On the USDA website
It was a hint
Do anyone paying really close attention that maybe this index the Georgia doc those numbers
You're off
And
You know who can smell a bad price from a thousand miles away
Wall Street
I had come across investors
They work sort of
Talking about it freely but they were talking
This is Stephanie strong
I'm a former journalist from The New York Times and I covered the food business for many years around this time
Stephanie Strom was getting
Tips about chicken
From some Wall Street
Contacts investors
There
The New York watching the markets like to do
And
They see something that they think is going to be a big
Eggslut
Of chicken
You had a huge
Oversupply of chicken
More chicken than they believed
People would eat and so they were betting that the price of chicken was going to fall
Yeah they were betting that the price of chicken was going to fall in that poultry producers are going to be losing
Right
Overvalue they thought the stock
And so
They shorted the stock
These Wall Street investors will make a ton of money if there's chicken company stocks ball
So they're just
Sitting there New York waiting for the oversupply of chickens hit the market which they think
Going to cause prices to collapse and yet
When you went to the grocery store
The price of chicken was
Either stable or even going up slightly
Which was probably driving
These guys crazy
Either this is not my world
I don't know what these guys are like you talked about in the hedge-fund guys is there a type
They tend to
B
Very confident
And very confident in their investment decisions
And when they don't go the way that they think they're going to
They work
Very hard to
Figure out why their thesis
Because there's always a thesis
The investment
Didn't go that way
And
Then
To persuade you the reporter that they were always right and that whatever these other factors are
Really don't matter
Or other people are stupid is what usually it comes down to
And I'm assuming these are mostly guys
They in this case everyone was
Yes
So do you
Very confident hedge fund
Dudes are
Trying to figure out why a prices of chicken in supermarkets are not
And they start looking really hard at how those prices are set
And they realize
A lot of them are linked
To Artis
Index
So maybe that's the answer
So they go to Stephanie Strom and they tell her about
Now she is a little weary because Wall Street is always trying to get reporters to write stuff so that Wall Street
But then Stephanie
Here's just by accident that the USDA also had some problems
Hardee's in.
I was probably having lunch with somebody about something completely unrelated all the other you know the USDA looked in
That was when I decided it was
What's the story
Because
It wasn't just a bunch of guys trying to make money off of
Betrayed
It was a government Regulators that also had that exact same question
It's about this
Pricing in the
And possibly
This index might be taking money out of the pockets of
Chicken eaters Across America renew need chicken fingers to survive
BBQ hours
Throwing Chicken on their barbecued is the most
Popular meat
That was why it was a good story
Because
If
Mrs. Smith
Is paying more for chicken
Then she really should be
Just to keep
You know the executives
The chicken come
I need that nappy right
Then that's of Interest
So she writes her story the headline is
You might be paying too much for your chicken
He gets a lot of attention
But nothing like what happens next
The chicken bombs
Memo
Gilliam MO
And we should tell you that for the story we are relying on a lot of.
Big pilot.
Memo's included and
Those documents there was a lawyer at
Private firm
Who understand from government agencies use
Open records laws
He won't tell us who he was working for it but there are clues that point toward hedge funds
So one day in November 6 in the afternoon this lawyer gets a new
Released by the Georgia Department of Agri
A memo from Artie shrunk
It wasn't a dress
To anybody
At the top it just says
Notes for meeting
We don't know if there was actually me
Can we don't have any comment from RT unfortunately
Stop flower tape
This memo is 3 pages of Artie schronces doubts about his own work
He says he was thrown into the job with no training
When he calls chicken companies and asked for their prices they're not really taking him seriously they're like and put down whatever you did last
And it seems from the member of the Arty feels personally
Play Hurt by this
But most importantly he says he does not believe what the company
These are telling him
Or Patty put it in this memo he has
Come to question the validity of some of the information provided
He does not trust his own index
You see the way the Georgia doc was set up
The companies just tell him a price
Artis not asking for invoices to actually verify that the sales
What happened at that
And up till now nobody thought that was necessary
And then already
Quiet Rd
Lover of gardens
He says
Just blow this thing up
The state of Georgia should not be putting this index together he says
Get rid of it entirely or maybe transfer to a private company let them take responsibility for it basically this schronce memo
As people started calling it
Confirmed what the hedge funds had thought was happening
That the poultry companies were making up price
Isis and manipulating the Gorge
Chicken price-fixing confirmed from the inside the big deal and within a day that memo is in
In the hands of a reporter from The Washington Post
And when the post publishes it
The stocks
Companies like
Mike Tyson Sanderson Farms
The drop immediately it by about 5% that is billions of dollars in Lost
Or profits if you're short selling
This was really the end of Artis Indo
Within a month the Georgia Depart of agriculture
Decides not to publish it anymore
Now they did try to replace it with a new price
A better one
With prices that were not just reported by poultry companies that also verified by checking in
With their customer
The people setting up this new price index
Better one arranged a conference call to introduce
Only one chicken producer
Cirkled in
But there were half a dozen people from Wall Street and they
Really piled on
My question is
I mention contract prices only
Point72 Asset Management
Earlier
How many chicken companies
My name is Noah Gillespie
New York
Noah Gillespie is actually the attorney who filed all those
Request for DACA
Give us the documents we've been relying on
The government's internal emails about
Go to Georgia. Also the Arty shrine
Launch memo
And he empties other Wall Street guys they have a lot of skeptical questions about whether the
This new price index is going to be honest
After that confer
Call a bunch of a poultry producers
Decided
They didn't even want to participate anymore
They never submitted any price
Said to this new index
It never launched
So six months after the USDA first sent people down to look at RT schronce
What is working figure out what he was doing with his poultry price
The index is gone
In the state of Georgia is out of the price index
Remember
The Headstone Guys thought that if the Georgia doc went away
Poultry prices
But they don't and that is the mystery That Remains
And are two theories that took
Wonder is
Big supermarkets had just been ignoring Artie's index
Once it got weird they were negotiating a more reasonable prices on their own
But that's what happened
Maybe nobody got hurt
But there are other people who say
Know that handful of big companies that controls the chicken business
They were fixing prices in fact they still are
A bunch of the big chicken buyers like supermarkets are suing all those big poultry
Accusing them of propping up prices in all sorts of ways not just feeding fake prices to Artesia
The boelter companies say they've done nothing of
The sort that case could take years
Letrozole for there's a bigger point
Everywhere you look in the economy
People rely on indicators like Hardee's chicken
Their list of prices people are paying for things like green
Housing
I never really thought about where those numbers come from
Sometimes those numbers are really solid like
The stock market those
Zhengzhou open
See or if you're in the beef or pork business there's actually a legal requirement that you have to report how much
But in other Industries
It's just private companies making private deals
And if you're trying to figure out what are they actually paying what is that
Thing worth
It takes some serious
Detective work
Sometimes it takes a guy
Sitting in his office in Georgia
Making calls to big companies who could
Could tell him any price they want
Arty schronce is now retired from the Georgia Department of Agriculture nobody celebrates him as a whistle
Hopefully somewhere
Is peacefully 10 Garden considered
Carolina Jessamine call SRT
We want to hear your version of this song
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solution
Strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org
What does it take to start the something from nothing and what does it take to actually build it
Gyros every week of how I built this
Speak with Founders behind some of the most inspiring companies in the world
Find it on NPR one
Or wherever you get your podcasts
WE Post every episode of Planet Money on Facebook
If you have thoughts about the show leave a comment on the post
You can also find us on Twitter and Instagram at Planet Money
Or email us Planet Money at npr.org
Today show with produced by Megan tan
Our editor is Brian Hurst at alsco Market about supervising producer
I'm finally home thanks for listening
Dammit
Why is it called the Georgia.
Well actually nobody knows I asked the Georgia Department of Agriculture this by the way
It's doc
Play Ock not documents
But doc like water or dock where your ship comes in I have no idea I asked them and they said they don't know either it's been around for so long
Nobody knows which
Huh