Venezuela used to be the richest country in Latin America
Oil money
Lots of oil money
Venezuelans like Mila remember the capital city bustling with biz
Can I go see used to be
MTD full of cars and people and
Acadias but good game
But when oil prices
Does tanks a couple years ago
Bad chaos
Venezuela ran out of money
Foot started printing more money
To pay its bills
And printing all this money made the value of the money
Plummet
Venezuela's currency is called
The boulevard
Or them
Bolivar
Okay
So everyday now you need more and more
Believer has to buy the simplest things like
Chocolate
If you want a good chocolate like a
I don't know me to keep away or something like that
You can lathe
In Minnesota
But you did a black bag of
Bills
You need
Millions of body virus
Some Economist call this the wheelbarrow problem where you literally have to haul your money around in garbage bags
Suitcases or
Wheelbarrows
Dubai the tiniest thing
The term comes from Germany
In the 1920s Germany's money was
Is losing value like
So when you go to the store with your backpack filled with money
How does the person at the
The store count all of this money
They have to know their way
Of that bills
I need to weigh the bills
Yes
The smaller bills
They're not even worth the
The paper they're printed on anymore
They lined the streets and nobody bothers to pick them up
People are shredding up money to use as
Confetti
Belts
Bracelet out of money
Leaving money baskets
If you have
12 bolivares today
It's worth
6 in a couple weeks then 3 then basically
Nothing
Think of Venezuela's money as an unwrapped chocolate by the minute it touches your hand
It's melting
Disappearing
So Venezuelans are trying to get rid of their money
Right away
Trade it in for
Anything at all
Toilet paper chicken okay I have
Sugar
To it
Holds its value better than the melting Boulevard
Stimulus as you spend your whole paycheck on sacks of sugar and those sacks of sugar are now you're saving
Account those are the things you can
Hopefully cellular
Trade later to pay your rent or a cab fare maybe you can say that
Cheer are for me or some coffee
Toilet paper.
That's unique
And then Mila gets
A call
From this young guy in Mexico City and he's like
Venezuelans don't have to invest their money in bags of sugar that's
Crazy
I'm running this whole online operation that can connect
Venezuelan
To us
Dollars
Illustrates working with him
And helping Venezuelan store their money in US dollars
Turns out to be a really dangerous thing to do
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Sarah Gonzales and I Melissa S car say
Three on the show Venezuelan government has arrested hundreds of people
For trading currency
We try to find out why we talked to some people to narrowly escaped
Mila
Mina's on the Run
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence
And run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
People trade their currency for dollars all over the world
But a lot of countries make this hard to do
So this guy in Mexico made a website to help people get around these
His name is Reuben
Do when you're pretty young right
Yeah I'm pretty young
I guess
How do you
I 13 + 27
Man calls himself a Libertarian and a
Freedom Fighter russinko face of the freedom fighter because
We think that the biggest issue is money is that
Strap
So everything we do all day is tried to free p
People's money
Ruben's website is called air TM it connects you to people anywhere in the world who are willing to trade
Feel like
If you're an American going to Europe and you need some euros
You can buy them from a guy who wants your dollars
Enderman is like
I know who would love to trade their currency for dollars
Venezuelan
Why should they be stuck with money that is melting away in their back pocket
Why should you be tied to any specific type of money if it's not working for you
3 post an ad on face
It said something really simple
Set compradores
Discombobulated
$5 with Boulevard
Ender TM
Takes
Off
Thousands of people start treating their believe it is $4
Everyday
But you can't
Pay for anything in Venezuela with
US dollars so you just
Steve in dollars
And then you swap it right back out for believe it is when you need to buy
Pretty soon Ruben had 25 employees working all over
The one with the backpack full of cash
She was the first Air Command
Employee and Ben
And at some point the Venezuelan government starts
To take notice because
They do not want Venezuelans to have easy access
$2
They don't like their people
To easily train
Their local currency for foreign currency
And that's because money is
Is really only as good as your face in it if you don't believe it has value it won't have value
All of a sudden your whole country starts dumping there where you at is $4
The boulevard
Will collapse
And you can see this happen
If you go in RTM people are trading $4 every second
And all those transactions they reveal a really important number
The exchange rate
How many bolivares
People are willing to pay
For 1
US dollar
The Venezuelan government takes this number varies
Seriously
Because it's a signal to the world
How strong or weak your economy is
Exchange it is basically
Their blood
And they don't want their butt to be diluted
Rmb worth less
The Venezuelan president Nicolas Maduro is like
Hey I determine what our blood is worth
And today he says
You just need around a hundred and seventy thousand believe it is to buy a
Single
US dollar
But the free market
Andhrafriends website says
You actually need
3 + 1/2
Million what do you want us to buy a dollar
An economist say
That's the True Value
Of the body by
Huge blow to my ego
And so
Should we allow people
Buy and sell dollars
At whatever price they like
And that the controlled price
They don't like us in the team start posting this
Real exchange rate
Twitter
And now the whole world finds out just how little the boulevard is
Really
And then
Jermaine gets a letter
I was sitting at my desk
Mexico City desk
And there's an email
Free official email with
Functional difference
Color saying
Is this is the Ministry of Finance
What you doing
We don't like it
And
You got
Stop because if not
We're going to
Put in jail from 10 to 5
15 years
And I think I jumped out of my seat
Excitement
Seaside it's a good day
I saw this
Something that was exciting
Surf new
That's what we're doing was not allowed by the government we've always known that's why we exist
His family
Less excited about the whole Venezuelan prison
My mom was
Scared my grandma was like
Stupid
For doing this
My dad was like
UK
Yuan Mexico
When was safe in Mex
Citgo
But anything
Oh no
Mila and all of my other employees
They were right there
Naked
Receive someone knocking the door
Right in that moment
And that's what I started freaking out
Rtmp
Romantic Mila stop publishing the exchange rate while
We try to figure out how to get everyone out of the
They migrated 25p
People either by planes or buy cars buses
And they
Call what
Out
To the Border
Everyone
Except
I didn't want that I told I remember I told ruin a lot of times when I don't want to
Eventually she realized
She had to
The police
We're looking for
To the police were looking for you why
They say that
The charts
Fake
Exchange rate of the dollar
The reason
Can I see a hairstyle
Because you were calculating the exchange rate
Like the real exchange rate not the
The official one that the Minnesota governor
Right yeah
That's why we're not using her last
Chicken and say goodbye to anyone villages
Had to go
With her husband and her seven-month-old son
I don't know words
That is no way
Cookies fight
Malala
TrueCar
Her husband's bike
Apartment in
All her special clothes from special moments in her life
I wanted
Covering everything
And I can't
Mila and her family arrived at their hideout
Any super cold town in the mountains
She kept thinking about her sweaters her sweaters that were hanging right there in her closet and got guy
I made it
Best Buy today
And I didn't have so
Everything you and I felt because I thought that I
Something like High
I have like
Victim sweaters in my house and now I need
Urban prep all of his employees into houses just over the Border in Columbia he doesn't want to say exact
Clearwire
Was just a quiet little place
In about 2 hours from
We met there
Promotional we had this
Alibi party
He said he had a night at party
They made a day pass for us
Super nice Alibis are basically Venezuela's national food
Also
Kind of Colombia's national food
Was it
Colombian arepa Venezuelan
Super important question
With a food in Between the Bread
Not at all
For the next couple months all of are GM's Venezuelan employees
Lived
Together in this
Safe House
And they get back to work treating dollars
Is posting prices
It was crowded and stressful but
Everyone had a bed
Amelia says
It was worth it
I always wanted to do something to
Change
The story
Love my country
And I think that this is a wet vent the better way that I can do that
Helping the people
They had their way to bring some morning to
Do their house
When I get a Rapala pressure
When President talks about Venezuela's currency problems
Cheap places the blame on groups like air TM
Criminal
Ali Ali
Paralelos
You saying they're not only criminal but perverse and illegal
Which actually makes
Sense
Economist do say that the more people have access to dollars
The more the boulevarde drops in value
And I wondered what drove in the air TM CEO thought about this
About the idea that RTM is making inflation get worse
Faster
And do you think that there's
Who treats tonight
Well we do allow people to exchange their money for dollars
Easier
And so if the government is afraid of
People getting rid of their money easier
Because that will
Make it easier for inflation to
Horizon
And to be fair it's not just Robinhood
People are trading Boulevard is $4
Street in Border towns
Anyone in the world who will trade with them
The government has arrested at least 216 people
For calculating the black market
Exchange rate and for trading money
But who is it
Accepting this money who's on the other side who wants believe it is
For this week all the BS
Sprint on black market exchange rate
Justice
What one second let me
Steve hanke professor of Applied economics at Johns Hopkins University
Pinky is the guy you call when your currency is losing
Value he's worked with a bunch of
Even if I said Venezuelan president
Seconds ago
Who wants to buy
Boy rides though
If they're not worth anything
What's in it for the people
For exchanging the currency
Why would they want
Except that
One group that loves Bolivars is that group that has access to the
Official exchange rate
These are people that are close to the the regime
They love body red
Of course the few
Special people who do have access to the really low exchange rate that my little came up with
They want what you want
Because they only need a hundred and seventy thousand two
Change for a dollar
When everyone else needs
More than three
Million
These people they're called essential follows the plugged in
People or the Bullet
And this might be one reason why the government would want to keep it
Fake
Low exchange rate because powerful people
Can make money off of it
But the government
They know things
So they've announced they're just going to
Start over
Scrap the old Willy red and print a brand new one they're calling it The Bolivar soberano
Sovereign Bolivar
The plan is to Take 5 zeros off
The bill so
Imagine you had 500000 what event is
Now you just have five
Pinky says
That will make money easy to carry around again
But
As far as value it changes absolutely nothing
It will change nothing was inflation inflation won't change
Exchange rates won't change
Hanky says Venezuela should just adopt the US
Currency completely stopped using the Boulevard and officially dollarized
Just replace the local currency to get rid of it
El Salvador uses the dollar Ecuador uses it but
My little
He does not want to
I canna plant and imperialists and the Socialist president doesn't want Venezuela
Become a colony of
Of the dollar
Minnesota
Yes
But also because
Something really important happens when a government gives up their currency
They lose their power to
Print money
When they need to pay their bills
But that could happen anyway
No matter what the government wants
If Venezuelans get enough access
To US dollars
Venezuela could
Spontaneously dollars
Conceivably could this happened in Zimbabwe in November 2008
Zimbabweans stop using the
Completely stopped they refuse to use the Zimbabwe dollar
And the economy was totally.
Spontaneously dollarize
Then
The government was
Start because no one would use their money
And so they officially dollarized
Mina and her co-workers are still helping Venezuela ends together
Their hands on dollars
Virtually
But even though she's doing this work
Mina does not want Venezuela $2 right
No you do not want that
No
Because
My kids and and my
Future Generations
Wooden dowel
No they will leave it in that we had a hour
Our currency
Mila hopes she can go back to Venezuela one day
And
The Bolivar Hermione it isn't just
A piece of paper it isn't even just
Money
It's a symbol
Your currency it's one of the things that makes you your own country
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence
And run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Did you know that planet money has another podcast the indicator this week we visit a nondescript
Office building in New Jersey to meet the people who actually collect all those terrorists we hear so much about
And if you've ever wondered how much it cost to import a moonrock
And subscribe to the indicator available wherever you get your pot
Today Show was edited by Brian earthdad and produced by
Selling home with help from Aviva dekornfeld and Taylor thingy supervising producer we post a link
Every episode on Facebook leave us a comment on the post we're also on Instagram we have pictures
Planet Money
A super extra special thanks to Daniel Landsburg Rodriguez Alejandro Velasco and John Otis for helping us under
Economy
I'm there when that is and I'm Eliza is hardly thanks for listening
There's one thing me laugh really like
Facts about Colombia
The trash
That you have to separate the trash in plastic sanding
An organic
I love it
Because even if I die I didn't have
That before
So you like recycling