Hey Stacey Vanek Smith
And today we are replaying an episode I originally reported back in
2015 about recycle
A lot has changed in the world recycling
Bend soap
Please stay tuned we will have an update for you at the end of the show
A little while back engineers at MIT
He's really small
Electronic tracking devices
Just the one inch by half an inch and very very sick
This is Carlo Rossi
Who ran the
They wanted to track something that is all around us
But that is otherwise
Pretty and visit
Crush
Yes trash garbage
They did this in Seattle and they asked residents to bring in a
Piece of trash
And people did anything
From a from an old cell phone to fluorescent lights
Two banana peels
Can you put a tracker on a banana peel
Of course people brought all kinds of stuff
Somebody came to ask me the teddy bear and you Linda in the end she told us that it was a teddy bear she's being
Having all of your life
But actually now she had to throw it away from boyfriend was telling her
Songs by association
I think you threw out the boyfriend not the teddy bear
But anyway I'm a thousand percent
Is there all this that bad
And they watched
A lot of the trash ended up getting recycled
And it may be surprisingly long trip like a
Across the country sometimes you could see an item go.....
LaPorte and then.....
Out to sea
It was amazing to see how how many times has am I see some things
I've been looking into the recycling business and it's amazing
A lot of our plastic gets shipped
To China where gets turned into
Toothbrushes and carpet and
Fleece jackets get sold back to us
And a lot of our shredded documents
Get sent to Mexico where they're turned into paper towels and
Tissue papers and toilet paper
I love that are shredded documents get turned into toilet paper so some of the stuff this MIT project tract
GATRA Psych
But other stuff
Got thrown out
Those items didn't go so far lot of them ended up with a short trip to Atlanta
What is recyclable and what is
Turns out there's an economic
Line between the two
It's like they can move around alot
One day it's profitable to recycle a bottle and the next day some global economic number changes and that
That same bottle is trash
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Being around a lot.
4 bunch of totally crazy reads
It's a really tough time to be a recycler
Support for NPR comes from LinkedIn
How to support the launch of life
NPR's guide
To help you make
Better life
LinkedIn learning
Short video tutorials
Discover Business tax
I can creativescape
Employers look for
At every level
All talk by X
And new courses are added every week
+ LinkedIn learning is personal
Recommended courses based on your interest
And wife Kate
Listeners get a month of learning
Start your free
At LinkedIn learning.com NPR
Every Thursday I do what
A lot of people probably do I haul a blue bin of my recycling out to the street
To be taken away
What's in your bin newspapers in yogurt containers in soda bottles things like that
Like New York daily news and full-fat yogurt more like Wall Street Journal ends
But no fat yoga
Service where you got to see where it actually went
I followed my yogurt container and
Wall Street Journal to see
Who picks it up where it goes and
The business behind it
It goes to another part of Brooklyn soap
A producer here you've been in and I
When to check it out
I went to go under a very shady looking Highway overpass and through this abandoned warehouse District
The cold they were walking up to a guard booth
I meant 10 security
River slowly Frozen you can see Ikea
Oh my gosh
Cranes
Bales of garbage
We're definitely here
This kind of looks like where you would dump a body
Stacy what's your plan
Man comes forward as he's tall he has red hair
Looks like he just walked out of an LL Bean catalog
His name is Tom Outerbridge
Hello
Hi are you Tom
Is this your dog
Stacy you love dogs
It's true I do I do have a soft spot
Tom has this place and it's one of many operated by a company called Sims Recycling Solutions
And every hour this one place processes
14000 lb of
Yogurt containers and pet
Pepsi cans in Wall Street Journal
And I found this weirdly exciting my garbage comes here
Termite my recycling
I'm sorry
Is it bad to call the garbage
Yeah I'm going to say well we don't call garbage because we're not really in the garbage business minutes
That people make that mistake all the time
So awkward
I know it was
Tomatillo
You can kind of tell David is sort of a quiet guy he kept turning away from my microphone
Jade Gardens recycling
Because he wanted to do something to help the environment
But he's the first person to tell me that recycling is a business that's actually a huge business
What did you say it's like hundreds of billions or something
A hundred billion dollars yeah
So you have to think about this as a business understand the problems the recycling business
It haven't right
Go to make sense for him to recycle something he has to be able to
Make a profit
If you can then that thing is recite
If you can't then it
It's trash
Trash recycling those are really economic ideas
Yammy misplace it cost alot to run
Tom shows me around he takes me to this enormous machine called The Liberator
Cuz it Liberate the various valuable pieces of recycling
Exactly
They're just conveyor belt everywhere going in every direction
Indianapolis electronic sorting machine
It's sort of like
Willy Wonka and the Chocolate Factory
Except for garbage
Not garbage recycle
All right
Just the beginning of the sorting system here
We use magnets to pull out Metal review
Ballistic separator
To separate paper and plastic bags from bottles
Tom tells me what is trash and what's recycling has been changing a lot late
You just made this one thing
Right on the border between
Trash and recyclables
It's plastic
Bags for secondary belt right in front of us full plastic bags to River of them
I know we've got like bubble wrap and a
Target bag in a Dunkin Donuts bag plastic bags can be
Valuable commodity
Tom could sell them to clients in Asia
And they would use them to make
Toothbrushes and carpet and coffee makers and things like that
But recently plastic bags have not been selling very well Tom can't get a good price for them
Plastic braces are off almost 50% about
Wow
That's a lot
Not shoot
The reason for the Stacey I would not have guessed
Anaplastic
Business it is
Primarily I would say due to the
Dropping oil prices
Oil
The oil seems like something may be totally unrelated but of course
Plastic bag
ARA petroleum
They're made from oil
So if oil gets cheap
That means it's cheap
To make fresh
Plastic
So if you're in the business of making toothbrushes
It's cheaper to buy freshly made
Advantages to buy recycled
Stuck at waste recycle plastic
Plastic bag
Yeah this is especially true for flask
Because we need a lot of processing before you can
Can use the plastic in there to be washed
X many times
And they also tend to get
Stuck in machine gears and gum up the works so
It cost a lot of money to recycle
The largest recycler in the country a company called Waste Management recently gave up on recycling plastic bags
Altogether they just couldn't make money in it
Time in Brooklyn says he is still trying to make it work
But it stopped
This is really sort of the bottom of them
The Barrel in terms of the class
6 Market
Is the value of it is relatively low which means
We can't afford to put a lot of
Time and money into trying to recycle
And so then what happens to the plastic bags if you can't sell them
Borderline
Trump says he's not having any trouble selling
Higher quality
Plastic things like detergent bottles and soda bottles
But the price for those has dropped and have to
Fight so that's the misery on the plastic side of things
There's also great unhappiness in this other part of the recycling bin
Is it that
Is actually a huge part of the market account for something like 90% of our recycled export
Paper
Time takes me to another part of the processing plant
And there are pizza boxes and office paper and cereal boxes here
This is your milk carton
Oh yeah
And milk and juice carton
Is this high quality or low quality this is actually very high quality
Surprisingly you wouldn't know necessarily but this we sell two paper mills
Where the Saudi Arabia of recovered paper
That is Bill Moore he runs a consulting firm that advises recycling companies
To understand the paper problem you need to know one key
Most of our use paper get sold to one place
One very big
China is the 800-pound gorilla when it comes to using recovered paper there
They don't have many trees softwood trees so they
All their capacity to make boxes and newspapers all
100% Recycled Fiber
In normal times this is a very happy relationship
Newspaper that you read if you're still read hardcopy newspaper witch
If you put that in your recycling bin six weeks later someone in China could read their newspaper on the same
Same fiber
The problem is that recently China has not been buying a
As much of our paper
I've been getting a lot of it
From Europe instead
And the reason is the most boring thing you can
International currency
Base of the dollar has been getting stronger the Euro has been getting
Which means us
Recycle paper is more expensive than European recycle
Paper if your China
Out there at deciding where to buy from
Tom Outerbridge in Brooklyn and told me he's been on the phone a lot lately with clients in China
Cutting all these deals
But he does not want to cut
In good days a ton of paper sells for about $150
And these days Tom says it's selling for Less
The half that like
50 or $60 for a ton
And buyers are literally nickeling and diming him on this like
Can you sell it for $0.10 Less can you sell
For $0.05
Five ten cents can make it
You're negotiating around a penny or half penny
That's really weird
To make things worse for Tom China has also recently started recycling a lot of its own trash
So bad
They don't need as much
American office paper and milk carton so much anymore
Hard time to be a recycler
David Steiner is the CEO of waste
Management
It's the largest recycling company in
I don't think crisis
Drawing of a word
To say that you're seeing a crisis
And
The recycling in
Throughout the United States
So you're seeing recycling company small recycling companies go out of business
Left and right
You really are
Recycling exports of actually started to drop a little bit
But Steiner thinks this could continue as prices drop and private companies stop being able to make money recycling
Some place like California have policy
Citic mandate
Sinuses nose cases
The extra cost
Contacts
Other places are just recycling less stuff
Lots of places have given up on plastic bag
Waste management is shutting down some of its less profitable plant
Tom Outerbridge the guy who recycles your yoga
Red containers in newspaper
Bruce says the recycling business has always had its good years and it's bad years
This just feels like a particularly bad stretch
Is profit margins are getting thinner in
Tencent
He doesn't want to send stuff to landfill
Has that ever happened before
Osher
Domino's our worst case scenario
Environmentally and also for the business
Tom does not want to give up not even on plastic bags
He's hired someone called a
Picker to stand
The plastic bag conveyor belt and Palatka
Contaminants
And bad plastic bags
So only the good ones get through
So he can sell them for a higher power
The hope is that he can use this to move the line a little bit between trash and recycle
Be so much easier if the price of oil just went off of
Don't know if that's an easier way but as you know
I have no control over our Global oil prices
Pac-12 public service announcement
Oh yes
You can't recycle bowling balls
Apparently in Brooklyn a lot of people try
I'm has to pick them out
Office
Has a whole collection of them
Support for NPR comes from LinkedIn learning
Proud to support the launch of life
NPR sky
To help you make better life
LinkedIn learning
Short video tutorials
Discover Business
Pack and creatives
Employers look for
At every level
All taught by X
Mu courses are added every week
+ LinkedIn learning is person
Recommended courses based on your interest
And wife get listeners get a month of learning
Start your
At LinkedIn learning.com NPR
Hello it is Stacy from the present day and has been changing in the world over cycle
Namely China decided it did not want to take the world's recyclable
And so
January
China implemented something called the national sword policy
Which is essentially a ban on foreign paper and plastic
This was a huge deal for the recycling industry
Biz before this
China recycled about half the world's paper
Plastic Prada
When I heard about this new policy of course I thought of Tom Outerbridge
Give me the whole business of selling paper and plastic
China
And I thought surely his world must be totally upside down
Portions of
The world upside down
First class
What time does the ban on plastic
Because not really affect
He already stopped sending faster
China a few years ago because of a different Chinese
This policy called the green fence
MP started selling to domestic buyers
Put on the paper side of things it's a bit more complicated
Because Tom was still sending paper to China
So now he's looking for alternative places to ship it
He says they've rerouted their paper to other Southeast Asian countries
Entergy MS
Byers
That comes with a cost
Paper of the negative value today
Meaning you don't get paid for it
Pay someone to take it
Tom is
Paying someone to take his pay
That is cheaper than sending it to Atlanta
What time is not worried
He says he trusts that everything will sort itself
I mean alternative the materials that were talking about haven't lost their inherent value
What you have is just a very
Abrupt
Disruption to the marketplace
And shall and kill the info
Structure can re-establish itself
Yeah have some
You know very challenging pricing
We post a link to every episode of Planet Money on Facebook and if you have thoughts on Today Show please leave a comment on the post
We are also on Instagram that's right
We are officially hip you can follow us
We are at Planet Money
Today's we rent was produced by Aviva dekornfeld the episode was originally produced by meteorite
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith thanks for listening