Last week Elsa and I found ourselves in store down in Chinatown
Oh yeah
Lowe's
Ginseng the small light brown sweater bumpy root
You can find it in pretty much any Chinatown anywhere in the
Just on this one street alone there are tons of places
Like this one
Stop doing this route
798 dollars for pounds weight look on the right here
Dollars account
Julie and I are staring at this
Locked glass
Explain different trays of ginseng
Is this 1184 pounder
Seems like a lot of money especially if you spin around and you look at the bins in the back of the store
Filled with ginseng
But that ginseng is only going for $9
Okay so this is the affordable stuff
This isn't the elf
Chang budget category
Okay
The Roots were looking at
Very similar to me
Chinese yam
Yeah they're both the same color
Beige
Don't come out of the ground
The skins on both
What kind of Nabi and bumby
But there's this huge
Price difference
Which is because of one main difference
In route
And that is that the expensive stuff the stuff that's in this locked glass case going for a thousand an ounce
That is
Wild
Wild ginseng has been used in Chinese medicine for thousands of years
It said to treat anything from fatigue
Cancer Daily just over Christmas I had this terrible cold
And my mom kept pumping
Thermos bottles of ginseng tea into me day after day
To some people like your mom ginseng is the ultimate
Killer
But specifically what people want is wild ginseng
They're willing to pay
Thousands more dollars
What difference does it make when I eat it
What's wrong
And like that route is more potent
So this label Wild
It's used to make all the difference
Juliet's the label wild suddenly assigns to the route
Oldies
Potent healing power
And it
How does a huge jump in price
Which got me wondering
Who gets to decide
What's wild and wet
Not
Because whoever gets decide that
Is essentially deciding who gets to make the most
Profits interest
And this business
Is barely regulated so it makes for some pretty interesting Dynamics in the industry
I've been looking into this for a few months and what I found was it people will lie for ginseng
People cheats for ginseng they even steal
And in one case I found one man even murdered for ginseng
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Julia DeWitt and I know if the change today on the show we travel out to the woods of Appalachia
What are some of the ginseng grows wild
And some does not
Attempts to pass one off for the other can we pull out of hiding
The chance to make big profits without a lot of rules has found a dark side to the ginseng
Will meet one man
This message comes from NPR sponsor Capital One Capital One is reimagining banking by offering account
With no fees or minimums that can be open from anywhere in 5 minutes Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
I get my car in New York and my headset the Appalachian
Ginseng is native to a few places in the world like China off of Siberia
And the Appalachian Mountains in the United States what I want to talk to
Someone about that wild American ginseng there are
A lot of people out in the mountains to gather wild thing but they're not easy to find there's almost no sign
Nine of them online they're super secretive they definitely do not want some journalists coming out and poke
Being around which
Is it and it took me weeks to find anyone that would talk to me
I finally found this one guy named Larry
Do you have that in the mountains on the border of Maryland and West Virginia and that is how you ended up in your car
Heading south in Appalachia on 68 very close to Larry's house
It is full on winter here like snow on the ground I'm following these handwritten
Directions I have on the seat beside me because my GPS won't take me to the right place otherwise
There are security cameras pointing never Direction over some potholes
Then at the end of the Scrabble Road I come to a big
10 Warehouse
I parked next to a pig
As I get up close to the door I see the sign
It feels kind of like one of those home is where the heart is sign
Except this one has a picture of two shotguns on it
And says we don't call and I
How are you doing very good
Play for all the security Larry is a super nice guy when I get to his farm he comes out in a hoodie
And he shows me into his office
Larry's office is like a jin-sang
He's Got Roots in jars
Alcohol in glass cases on little bit
Pillows
On a shelf next to
He called it his Million Dollar Man
Because it shapes
Like a man
An anatomically correct
Man you got your arms
You got your legs
You got your tallywacker
I mean he's welfare
The whole nine yards
Lyrics planes that roots that look like
Humans are especially valuable in the Asia
Roots shaped like bodies are traditionally believed to be
Good for your whole body if it's shaped like
Like your arm
Your arms
Leg
Capri lighting
Is down here and some that we
Do I have a lotta
Pictures
Think like that
All over the wall
One is at his dad needs
In a field of
Can you tell me the first time you heard
Heard the word ginseng
I'll just real I don't know where I was
Larry is been going out into the woods looking for ginseng it since he was a little
Head is an Appalachian
Grandfather did it
Dad did it
His dad taught
When I was little kid dad he'd always take us out and
Biggest ginseng
Along with my three other brothers
The how I learned how to find anything that would take us out
Okay I found one
So then we'd all scramble around trying to figure out you know getting front of window try to find it you want to mean
Ask Larry to give me a quick rundown of how ginseng
He explains it first you have to have it knife
Above ground plants
Pretty modest
Doc bao
Lehigh
Leaves on top
Then when you go to dig it up
You have to be
Very careful when you extract the root
From the dirt
He damage it
Not worth it
Yeah totally different
What were standing there in his office
Larry pulled out some route
To show me what he ultimately wants to bring home
From the woods
Your wild is going to be
Really dark
Deep ring
Unlike cultivated
Wild
Ginseng
Tulare the wild staff
Meaning
Super valuable stuff
It looks obviously different to someone with a trained eye
And he says well ginseng is disappearing in Appalachia
I used to be a whole lot more of it growing in
In the area
And now it's really hard to find wild ginseng in the woods
Anywhere
Factory farming this isn't a solution to the shortage of wild
A lot of ginseng is mass-produced in Wisconsin on big farms
But they dumped a bunch of fertilizer on it and when it comes out of the ground
It looks different to expert
Mike Larry
If you look at the texture of the route is going to be more
Potato skin
Slick
Hi texture version your wild
Gnarly type texture you see your your Ringo and it has
Totally deaf
Yeah totally different looks like a staff Elsa and I saw in China
In the bins in the back of the
The cheapest
Larry doesn't want to sell the chi
Cheap stuff so over the years
People Like Larry
Developed
A workaround
If you plant ginseng in the woods
You don't call it
What fertilizer
And if you wait 10 years or so
Then you can grow something that looks a lot
Like wild
Which Larry reminds me is important
Because
Bottom line is
When we Harvest his crops
The closer
Resembles Wild
The more money we're going to receive
In the more money we want
You're saying I'm saying
Where it causes ginseng he grows in the woods
Wild simulated
Ginseng
Which sounds like an oxymoron
Simulated then
Is that
Colinas Wild
Believe just play a game with me here first
I took a received from one of your plastic that goes up there on the hillside
And I just
I threw it over there on the other side of parking lot into the woods
What would that be
That would be
A my eyes I would say that's probably
Wild you
Okay
If I tell the soil I like scraped away hole for it through it in that hole would that be
Wild simulated ginseng
Okay then if I went back
And I put fungicides on it
What would that be
Still be called wild simulated ginseng
What were standing there I mean I'm
Still having a hard time
Visualize
Like what is wild simulated ginseng what does that mean
Larry says
He'll xiaomi
We go out to the garage where we getting
I don't really know what you call it
Super
Souped up ATV
So we're looking at this Farm it basically just look like what
It looks sort of like what's but you can tell that some of the brush
Have been cleared and there are the straight lines like raised beds of dirt tell me how much is
The band a million dollars out across there when that's mature jin-sang I'll kiss your ass
So he's got this gold mine in the ground
His problem is that it actually looks so believable as wild ginseng
That it invites
Larry tells me this one story from 5
One night he's at home
And I had
Detectors
That I knew when something was moving
I thought they were deer
So
Ignored it
You go back out the next day
Wow
There you been here
What is it what did it look like
I was just
Were they just dug up all the plants all over I mean it's just
Destruction
And the ginseng is
Larry think
The neighbors they stolen
I'll probably be back
So the next weekend
She's ready
He's at home watching
Pictures
And they go off
And like 11:30
I said okay
I think you're here
Larry goes down to his property he looks happen
Into the trees
Sure enough
There was a light icing I like it to trees
Maybe down in the back
So I backed up
Lay down in the weeds and I called the law
He meets the police up at the road and they walk back into the woods
You're down there it was pitch dark
Pasadero Dr
Soon as we got about 10 yards from you
Police on the ground and they
Hit the ground and walked up to him
Turn that one guy over
That's where you found me said
Kentucky
And you could have bought me with the dollar cuz I thought they was just local people put him in the jail is on Friday night to charge them
I got restitution
I never received a time where are they now
Drink Kentucky
And hope this day in Kentucky
Larry says it's locked for them
That he wasn't carrying
Weapon that shotgun with me
The outcome would have been different
And in fact
Larry tells me a story to everyone in the ginseng business
Nose
This guy Bobby Joe Grubbs
He keeps sneaking onto the property have his neighbor Joseph cutter
2 steel Cutters ginseng
Cuttery keeps calling the police he says the police are not responding
And then
One day
Bobby Joe goes missing
The police they go search Cutters property
And they're in a mulch pile they find the dead body of Bobby Joe Grubb
Qatar had
Shot
Bobby Joe
Over ginseng
So there's a lot of crime images
And all goes back to the fact that the business itself
Pretty unregulated
Which criticism let's call it
Wiggle room
And Larry benefits from this
Mom standing with him back in the office
He pulled a bottle of ginseng infused moonshine off the show
And hold it up for me to read the label
Harding's
Wild
Ginseng moonshine
We don't have simulated in the title
We have a lot on that so it's in it's in the
It's in the back wording
I got to redo that again put your glasses on
That's the way it's supposed to be
Sweet prince
In the fine print
Larry has a wry smile on his face
Funny says this like
He knows he's definitions are a little mushy
But she also says this is just the nature of
How's the business
He always tell people it's wild simulated now
Matt Wilde when he sells a ginseng
Sometimes he writes it in that very small Prints but she still tells them
This makes me wonder what someone with a trained eye
I would say about Larry's
So
Before I leave I asked him if I can take some with
Larry's already thought of this and he goes out to his truck
To grab some food
You just pulled out of the ground just now
Okay
And this has to make to it this is some
This is roughly 14 year old
Root in these beds
To look at this route
There's actually not a dealer in the country
The conseil
This don't look like wild ginseng
Cuz this looks
Very much like wild ginseng
Larry also give me an authentic Lee wild ginseng
Kingroot so I
Compare
And he's right they look pretty similar to me
But it take both routes with
Cuz I want to check with someone that no
Next I go to Seattle
I get back on the freeway heading east to rustbelt town in
Pennsylvania called Bethlehem so I just pulled off the freeway the company
TNA ginseng is based out of the owner's house
It's a big white house up on a hill as chickens outside
And when I park and get to the door I'm greeted by a woman named Nancy
I like my pasta
Patrick catc
Like cats
The owner of TNA ginseng is a man named song live
Very well thanks
I mean him sitting at his kitchen table he's mostly speaking Mandarin
Socassie is Airtel Translate
We're not even to like it.
Fun-Lan explains his Disney
Buy ginseng
Diggers then they cauterize it and make it into capsules
He shows me some of those
Mostly says he sells it to Chinese medicine practitioners inside the U
Salam grew up around a lot of Chinese medicine
Petitioners is dad was a doctor
She prescribed it
He's been interested in
His whole life
He spent 20 years looking at it
Buying it
You got a very keen
Take out the route that I got
So actually brought a route with me to do look at it
And just tell me what tell me what you see
World icon
Fun-Lan asks his daughter to bring over his magnifying glass
He inspects the route
Wipe sit down with some water
Could you ask him what he's looking
Looking for a city
World icon
Surprise
I said
Consider
I'm trying to determine whether this is Moses Cone things in a wild things in
Is it Woods grown or wildin
Peace Lane said he's looking at the links
Stepinac how close all the way
Cozaar
They are
Ultimately if I'm elong says he needs
City of acre
You wouldn't buy it but you can't be sure how
Then
I bring out to the other room
That Larry gave me
This is the one that is actually White
Yesterday's date
And is immediately evident that
Truly pure wild ginseng
What's this word is
It's obvious
Justin Bieber
When did Popeye
Get off of Google
So if you have things are looking like this he's willing to pay on $800 pounds
$800 a pound
I expected that from Longwood have all these questions
Where I got the
Xinjiang
From and he does he wanders like it weird
Robot
Doesn't seem to actually matter that much
What matters
Is actually just what
It looks like
The price
Really is Bass
Unjust
How
Pierce
Wait okay now I'm really confused
About what is
Wild
Zing saying it's not what it looks like how it was about
How it's grown
Yeah that's
The thing
Everyone finds it
Which is why when people sell ginseng to
To each other the conversation ends up reverting to what they can determine and that is
What it looks like
What is right in front of them
Whether the neck is long a
Spindly weather looks
A human man whether the tendrils are long and whiskey
Remember when we were in Chinatown in that thing thing store
If we didn't have someone like Fung Lum at our side
How could we have known whether we should be shelling out $1,000 an ounce or just $9
What are the rules
In a way we can't
Really no
We're showing up three thousand years late to this conversation
23000 years old
Well I went out to Appalachia
And why I thought I was going to find this
Story that can help me understand what these rules are for the ginseng business but
What ended up stumbling on with thousands of years of culture and history and beliefs about
What this route can do and why people are willing to pay it so much for it end
I don't really know if there are any like that in stone rules
Okay but after the break
NPR code switch tackles race and identity in America with Humanity
And humor
You laugh you learn
You'll get them comfortable
It's worth it
Find whole switch on the NPR one app or wherever you get your pot
We would like to hear from you got a great story idea for us let us know at Planet Money at end
Care.org or friends on Facebook or Twitter
Play show with produced by Kesha mihailovic Alex goldmark is are supervising producer and set at
The show and if you're looking for something new to listen to We have it Planet money's got it
Indicator podcast
Define indicator on NPR one app
Wherever you get your pipe
And I'm Juliet
So Elsa
Your mom pump tea with Ginseng tea every Christmas yeah this box
Was waiting for me
Undertaker
After my mom listen to me sniffle and cough all Christmas Vacation
It contains
100 bags of ginseng tea and my mom told me to keep
Drinking this all vacation
Sophie's
Are Chinese characters what does that mean
It says yes on watch Houston Chaya which literally means
Wild American ginseng tea
This is a
100 bags
50 in
It's a
Big bucks
My mom says it cost her $40 at cos
For the entire box
And it's white
Yeah so it says
How's your cold now