Support for NPR and the following message
Which come from WWE
Publishers of people power and profit
Progressive capitalism for an age of discontent
By Nobel prize-winning economist
Joseph E stiglitz
We got a brilliant
Question
A question that spawned
Entire
I asked my dad about a question and he said he couldn't answer it
So you told me to come in.
Amy a thirteen-year-old listener in Bristol England
She listens with her dad and Amy question
It's about the government
10th and
What it can
And spend
Puritas
I had this idea
. because they print money
Instead of giving it
Back to the bank
Making a
Inflation go up
They could use it just
Republic Services
And it would be much easier and it would be
It would be in general really good cuz I know there's lots of
Problems with like there's not enough
Tax to go around all the schools and hospitals
So I thought maybe this might help
Thank you for listening
Yeah
Hi
This question is
Brilliant
It has so many ways
Like the first part printing money
What is stopping the government from printing as much money as it were
Basically nothing
And then the spending Park
If the government prints money
Why do we need to take my money in taxes
Amy even calls out
Possible
Fatal flaw inflation but she's like
Are we sure that this would cause inflation the answer is
Nope
Inflation ain't what it used to be
Economist of all ages are rethinking how it works at the heart of Amy's
Question is a paradox
The government can create money
But the government also says it doesn't have enough money to pay for stuff
Does I need to make sense hello and welcome to Planet Money
The whole show is Amy's Quest
Can we buy everything we want
And if we try will we be living in a Utopia or an inflation night
Support for this
NPR
In the following message come from the United States Postal
Everyday Innovative companies are Reinventing the way business
But none of that is
Possible without the right
People people who get packages to over a hundred and fifty million delivery
Affordably and on time
With the latest technology and expertise
Who can help you
Deliver the future of Commerce
The nights
State Postal
See why they deliver more e-commerce packages to home
It's been anyone in the country
Usps.com
Okay Alex
We found the perfect
Person to answer any question she's an economist
Had a similar question about 20 years ago
And I'm thinking about it
Her name is Stephanie
Hilton
So what do you think is Amy is Amy on to something
You know young people can be so clear-minded
Yeah she said that isn't
Ratably
Sort of astute way of framing it
You know the government can fund itself
By simply issuing the money
And Amy has hit on something that is well-known to economist
But it's just the most economist
Like to say
But that's not really a very serious way of going about things
But Stephanie is
Serious she's a professor at Stony Brook University she's one of the leaders of this movement within the left wing
King of economics
Call Modern monetary Theory
Or the initials mmt
And they say the government
Could create money and spend more without necessarily raising taxes or causing runaway inflation
If you're wondering before this episode is over we will all scream the word inflation together
Wait for it
So
13 year old Amy
Her questions let us straight into this whole huge alternate theory of echo
And at just
Set the right time
M&T is having a moment right now there's a corner of The Economist internet that is like
Cespedes
There are more mmtb blogs
Today then
McDonald's franchise everywhere
And it's not just the block
Politicians have been asking
Stephanie and her colleague
The Advisory Sanders earlier this year she give a keynote in
Parliament in London
In at the House of Lords of Lords
Can't Get Enough
Most Economist use to ignore these ideas
Is French or far out and a lot of them still do
Lisa Economist food
To shrug off these ideas
Going to write about mmt
And
Regular people
More and more of them
Are becoming convert every week when Stephanie is talking to a potential new convert
She often starts
With the first
Basic part of Amy's Quest
About what is money
Can the government just
Print as much money as it wants
I don't like
Phrase printing money I'll just
Laid out there
Money because most of money out there is digital not paper here right the way we mostly handle money in our lives
Only numbers taking up and down in my day
Add most of that digital money out there in the world
Actually comes from Banks making loans
It's where the second explain this one
Different than the way a lot of textbooks talk about it here is the ID
Say Economist Stephanie Kelton
Needs $100,000
Start a pancake restaurant
The bank checks out your credit history
And they're like
They decide to give me the money
The loan office
Will
Types of numbers into his or her
Computer
And my account balance is going to increase by $100,000
That is
Bank officer isn't thinking about
Cash is not
Going down to the Vault and Counting
That's crazy what was she where did the bank get the money to make the loan
I got it from the keyboard
Who is the one followed by a number of zeros
Call it the power of the keyboard
Banks have it and Stephanie says
So does the government superpower of the keyboard This is how Stephanie tells the story of governments
When Congress spends money on aircraft carriers or whatever
They just tell the government's Bank
The Federal Reserve to go and type
Some money into the account
Of basically wipers making aircraft carrier
Just type it in
Society says the question
Can the government afford something
The answer to that question is always
Yes
So so like can we afford to build
1000 Newbridge
Yes could we fill all of the potholes in all of New York City if we wanted to
F chord
And also by a
100 new aircraft carriers for the military
You could build a border wall that Trump wants
You can afford it college for everybody
How do I make a pay for
Affordable
Sounds like a Utopia
There has to be
The Wright brothers
Okay we're going to go to the cat
Quick asterisk are
These mmtb ideas apply only to governments that control their own courage
Currency that's backed by nothing but the government's good name
It's not pegged to another currency
And it doesn't work for countries that
Borrow internet
So it applies to the US into the UK
But not say to Greece
Because they use the euro
Hora Venezuela
Because they have a bunch of debt in US
Right because then Greece and Venezuela can't use the power of the
The keyboard to pay back the debt if any into in the same way
Asterix
So from here on out let's focus
Is on the US
And the UK
13 year old Amy after oak leaves
In the UK
This all leads us to the next part of our big
Question from
The government can create money
What's the point of tok
Why does the government need to take
Take my money in taxes
Astoria on taxes that I always had in my head
It says that the government spends money because you know
That needs a paper aircraft carriers in first grade teachers part of the government's job is to balance the amount of money that it
Dispense with the amount of money that it
Takes in this the part where you here are you know about Congress fighting over the budget
Government takes in money in taxes
And if
Needs a little extra to borrow some money
And then across town the Federal Reserve a central bank
They look at the
The health of the overall economy and
Change interest rates or create
It's money maybe remove some money from circulation to keep the economy in balance
Basically the FED handles that big
Picture stop light
Fighting inflation
And meanwhile
Congress by their craft
But modern monetary Theory says it doesn't have to be this
Forget everything you know
Back when Stephanie was a young red suit
She heard about a different way of looking at them
It was being shopped around by Finance guy named Warren most
He was looking at this whole system
The federal government the central bank
It's like when you're looking at one of those opt
Optical illusion
Is it a goblet
Or is it two faces staring at each other I always see the faces
He's looking at the sea
System and it's like
Suddenly
Macy's the goblet
You look at it a little differently then
Taxes don't Finance
Spending comes first and taxes
Second
This got me so let's slow down
Here's the old lady
Taxes
Bring in the money
Then government
Spend that money
Government just spent
Power the keyboard
Then the government
Has something to tap
He's out there
Stephanie was initially not sold on wine Mozart
When she was like this sounds fishy
I'm going to
So I spent a number of months reading treasury manuals fed manuals
Tracing out all of the balance sheet entries going through the minutiae of how government
Spending and Taxation and financing actually works
I wrote it all down with all the complicating details
And I ended up reaching exactly the same conclusion that Warren had reached
When she looks at all the details she's like
Well
Actually yes
This is a valid way of looking at the world throws off the whole way she was thinking about economics
Economist talking about these ideas thereabouts
Six or seven of them eventually and they become these modern monetary Theory peep
Mmt crowd is born
These are talking about that at like The Economist bar where you guys are like drinking
Economist
Ears
Poodle
Totally
Name the cocktail after it
Probably would have called it a
Actually done
So in this mind-bending world
We still have the question why does
The government tax
At all
Stephanie says one reason
Taxes
Because
It wants to remove some of the money that it spent into the economy
So that it can guard against
Asterisk
Inflation inflation
We got there okay
This is one of the big ideas
Taxes are not for spending
Taxes are for fighting inflation
And spending
That isn't just to buy stuff
The government needs
But
Power of the keyboard
Spending from that
Can be put to use for doing all kinds of good things
Put money into the economy to give it a boost or to help get to Full Employment okay so the government is spending money
AT&T economy
Spend spend spend
And eventually you're going to need
To train somebody else
And she said you can think of taxes as a way to do that
Because I mean you got to have a way to get money out of the economy right and this is a big question that we had about him
Remind the government
That it has the power of the keyboard
Is the government going to go crazy
And then when you get like
People with wheelbarrows full of cash dumping piles of money on the counter when they want to buy a cup of coffee
I'm going to start of summer I'd like
Comment of jacks
Come up to this
And I think I could summarize them sick
Succinctly by saying
Just like
Venezuela
Bymar Germany
Zimbabwe
DeFelice
Thoughtful
Objection
Yes
No I mean to vet by country that makes hyperinflation
Serious objections those aren't
Action that someone who wants to resist
What they're hearing
And so they throw out a word
Zimbabwe
Venezuela
It's okay if you think
Hyperinflation
Is a necessary result of what I just described
State government sitting down with it
It's budget in deciding
How many dollars to write in
Into each of these lines
You could well get inflation I'm not denying
Federal government could try to spend too much into an economy
That doesn't have the room to absorb
That much new spending and you begin to get an inflation, I'm not I'm not suggesting that that can't have
But she thinks it wouldn't necessarily
And we were like
Wait but wouldn't it happen if there's just a
Ton more money pumped into an economy then
Everyone has more money so there never was going to
Spend more money and that is what drives up
Prices in causes inflation
If there's more money out there
Through the government spending
It's out there and people can do whatever they want with it
So
I'm trying to get my head around like wouldn't wouldn't that cause inflation somehow if everyone a bunch of people have more money because government is spending a bunch
Smart
Then
Won't they spend that money on stuff and come back on
Where is it we've been doing it. We just did it with a one and a half trillion dollar tax cut
We did it with the 300 billion
In additional spending we've we've done it and done it and done it where is the inflation from
I don't see it in the UK
I don't see it in Japan I don't see it in the US
True
Countries including the US have had a hard time hitting the inflation targets that they want a hit for years
I just did a whole episode on this
Two weeks ago Stephanie says we shouldn't be freaking out about inflation right now
But we do need to think about it
Here is her answer to the last part of Amy's question
Should the government create
As much money as
The catch
The catch is that all of these things are affordable in money terms
But you know I like to sometimes I'll say every economy has its own internal speed
The speed limit
She says what you need to look at is how much money an economy can absorb before inflation takes
And the speed limit has to do with what economist
Call real
Resources
Economy is not
Just money like if you want to build a hospital you can't build it out of money
You need a concrete and
Glass and linoleum
Floor and sofas
Waiting room windows IV bags
Hang on those sort of rolling coat rack things
Willow doctors and nurses of course we need them
Stephanie says those things are what create the speed
So say the factory that makes those
Doing things is running at like
Half the capacity better
Then if the government decides to place a big order for those coat rack things
Nothing really happens
They just buy them at the normal price
Put him in the hospital
Great great
What if the factory is at full
Then
The government has to say hey
Spell to our new hospital instead of to your other customers
And to get them to do it
Still have to pay
Paymore
That isn't
Prices just went
And if the government spends so much
Watch that it drives up prices all over the economy
Thatcher inflation
That's what the government to think about
Not whether they have enough
Money
But whether there are enough resources in the
Economy at 2
Soak up.
That is basically your answer
Amy
The government can create money and spend it up to that internal speed
If you start to get inflation
That's a sign you might be spending too much
Maybe you could
Raise taxes to pull some of that money back in
But if you don't see inflation
Just go for
No clearly
Not everyone's
This is Tom poly he's an economist he's done work for labor unions
And he's on the left
Of the economic
But he's been a long time.
Travel Anda
And there's also hear the reason we're only hearing from Economist on the left in this episode
Is that the colonists were researching and writing about this Theory
They mostly all tend to be on the left
What time should take a more traditional or conservative you they tend to say
You have to think about taxes as a way to finance spending
That is the responsible way to run a government
Modern monetary theory is useful because it points out some flaws in mainstream economics like he thinks that
Is too obsessed with balanced budgets
But he has some doubts about mmt
Big one is the whole taxes
The idea of using taxes to fight in
Politics doesn't work like that
Pictures of very very contested no one wants their taxes raised
It's very hard for politicians to raise taxes that very slowly
Do it
Because
Guess what they don't get reelected if they do
He says it's just not realistic
Take for the government to react fast enough
Respond to inflate
We put that to Stephanie Kelton
If your concern is that it would be difficult to fight inflation
By raising taxes that is
Obviously a legitimate concern
That it is difficult to get Congress to act quickly to do the right thing and so one of the things that mmt
Economist have advocated for very long time
Is finding away
Take the
Of Congress
Of the decision
In other words
To make it happen automatically
She says something like this kind of haven't already like when the economy is booming you don't have to spend as much on a
Employment address
People have jobs
So spending goes down automatically
She says do more of
Love that more types of taxing and spending that kick in automatically if inflation starts to take
And also she says
Is not alone in saying this
Nobody has it
And she thinks the government could spend a lot more money right now and we'd still probably be fine
Okay so we went looking for a way to explain to a 13 year old
What are the government can print money to spend on schools and hospitals and not have to raise taxes
Everytime this branch of economics
Sonic this movement
Even with a whole new way of looking
How many were
You see the faces or the goblets you can pick which one you want to see
JB say you can make this mental shift about taxes and spending
Don't think about them at the way you think about your money in your private life like do I have enough to buy this thing I want to buy
The government is not
Lots of Economist agree there by the way
Instead the modern monetary Theory folks they say
Start thinking about how taxes in
Affect the big economics
Like employment and inflation
Three days now it's the Federal Reserve jobs think about that
Kind of just because that's how we set things up
Like way back when
Government spending and
Thing is actually much more direct way to go about
If you want more employment don't fiddle with the interest rate
Hire people are buy things from businesses will hire
There are definitely questions about how this
Far from the mainstream textbook way that most Economist talk about
And if you think government sucks
You probably aren't loving the
But there's some logic to the idea that
Congress should be thinking about the big stuff
Is the economy good
Are people employed
And
That money isn't just a way to buy aircraft carriers it's way more than that
That's something the M&T folks want you to keep
Don't just think about money as a
A scarce resource something you can run out of
Think about what you want money to do
And go from there
The different starting point for asking the question
Can we have
Like Nu
Hi
Amy is that you
Yeah you ask us a question a couple weeks ago it was a really good question and we have an answer for you
I'm really excited
I'm like she's right because I didn't know that
You're going to get back. I didn't think that this was going to happen
Unfortunately you have to listen to a whole episode of Planet money together
How does that sound
That's really good
Excited
After the break
Amy from Bristol
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Message come from mizzenandmain
Mizzen & Main dress shirts are made with performance fabric
Designed to look great
All day
With minimal maintenance
There moisture
Wrinkle-resistant and machine wash
So they don't require ironing
Or dry clean
Check out their gift
Where the guy on your lip
Who is always on the move
Had to visit in Maine.
Mizzen & Main
Look great
Longer use code NPR at checkout
To receive $10
There's off your dress shirt
Amy
Yeah
What do you think
That was amazing
Luxury like China
Stop myself
In like
Screaming so so good
So what do you think what's it what's your takeaway you have this question it's a really really good
We found some stuff out
What do you think now
I think it's
Pretty good like
Listening to that it just made me
Feel like
I could be on something really good
So are you going to tell the other kids at school
What you figured out here
Jazz from jazz
Are you going to tell
I'm going to tell everyone light
I'm so happy that you made
The episode
It just started
70 questions
Like that were in the question
There is a lot we didn't get to this episode locked the car here
Go hash it out on the internet repost every episode on Twitter and Facebook we all have an Instagram for pretty pictures and probably few
Fights about Inflation Nation on her Instagram what do you expect
Today's episode was produced by Nick Fountain and Diane Woods or editor is Bryant
Thank you for supervising thanks also to Brad's along and JW Mason who were among the people who helped me
I'm finally home
Yeah I just
She just came out of school today and my dad's like oh my gosh
Planet Money
Emailed me and said that
Save you strike it for now