Support for Planet Money
And the following message
Did come from Michigan Economic Development
Incorporation Cy Michigan
It's attracting top talent and pop business
By searching Michigan pure opportunity
Everybody
Just a quick note
The show is a rerun it originally aired in 2016
Amy cop lives in Indiana and owns a white 2004 Subaru Impreza
It is not
A really nice
It's really banging.
It's almost always dirty
Even my three-year-old daughter sometimes seems to
I prefer to pretend that the other car is at her preschool are her car
But Amy really loves
This car this is the car that she drove
Through a snowstorm in Indianapolis
To bring her newborn daughter home from the house
I just kept looking in the rearview mirror my wife was sitting back there
Found with the baby
It was a really happy scene in the backseat but yeah I was just
The terror
The funny thing about this not so nice but
Beloved car is that Amy ended up kind of a bidding war over it
About five years ago her friend Erica was selling the soup
Amy and her wife
Wanted it and so did another
A guy in a woman
And anything said that couple was offering about $100 more
But Amy's friend tok
She sold the Subaru to Amy
She just had one requirement
You cannot
Pob Human Rights Campaign sticker off the back window
And if you don't understand exactly what I'm saying let me let Amy explained
She sold it to us
Go to another lesbian
Erica wanted for Subaru to go to another lesbian couple
Part of the reason he's laughing here is that this has become kind of a stereotype
Type that lesbian women love
The car even has a nickname
Erica always call it the lesburu
This is not an axe
Subaru spent more than a decade
Carefully targeting lesbian consumers
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Noel King and I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Today on the show
Why Subaru started targeting a group of
Consumers that just about every other company with
Ignoring and how that may have helped
Save the company
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Search come from State Farm
Who's agent snow
That your car and home
Are more than just be
Big purchases
They're a big part of your life
You put the time
I'm into making them your own
So now it's time to protect them
With your own person
State Farm age
Not only do they truly get
But they'll be there
You when you need them
And with over 19000 age
Neighborhoods across that
There could be
Just around the corner
Morehead State Farm.
1 800 State Farm
State Farm
Here to help life
Go right
In the early 90s Uber was in trouble
Feel they've been slumping for about 7 years
Super with competing against Giants
Play Toyota and Nissan and it was losing
Tim Bennett work in sales distribution for Subaru back then
And him the problem was pretty clear
Subaru was having an identity
These were not sexy cars
Tim says they were
Boxy reliable wagons with a certain kind of feel
It's granola let's 10000 Maniacs it's crunchy gets hippie
It said
Professor in a tweed jacket
Pokemon go does not want a 10000 maniacs
They are a great Banner creepy
But but
Companies want to sell to mass Market
And not just
Hippies and professor
Subaru hired a cool Ad Agency the ones that had come up with the just do it slogan for Nike
But even they could not make Subarus
The ad campaign went nowhere
Morale at Subaru was
Raises
And bonuses went out the window
Intensive sales people started making all these
Really dark jokes
About how is things
Got any worse they were just going to have to start sending new Subarus Direct
The scrap yard
If not on a winning team you're on a losing team
Nobody wants to be an illusion
And if I would have felt like it
But the company realize
One type of Subaru was actually selling pretty well
These are cars with all-wheel drive
The kind of cars that are popular in places with bad weather
Super said alright let's start there with the bright spot let's meet the people who are buying these cars
The Ransom focus groups
And they identified four categories of
People who are buying super
The first category they called the rugged individualist basically the outdoorsy types
So those are the people kayakers mountain biker scares
Denver technical professionals
Technical professionals
Engineers
Got
I'm educators
Teachers
Healthcare professionals
Do you have to get to the ER all kinds of weather data.
So it's a random assortment of
Professions
But within those groups
There was a Common Thread
Women
A lot of Subaru owners were women
In a lot of cases
They were women who identified themselves as
Head of house
Tim Mahoney was running marketing for Subaru at the time
And one day he was watching
A focus group
San Francisco behind a two-way mirror
One of the guys
Who
Actually work for our research company who happened actually be gay
He says yeah all my friends
Turn on supers are lesbians
And it was like one of those moments where everything came into focus and it's like a wow
Tim Mahoney realize he may have just discovered a fifth
Group who loves Subaru
Lesbian
So that's who has to figure out two things
Number one
Is this true or is
Anecdotal
Is it actually a significant consumer group for
For Subaru
And then if it was how are they going to Market
Kathy's Kars to lesbian
Super got in touch with Mariah now
The tiny Ad Agency based in Manhattan
With specialized in marketing to Gay and Lesbian consumer
John Nash was the creative director at the time
What was the first campaign you worked on
Is Dalaman
Dial a match 1 800
Mattress there on Queen
Names John and his business partner date Mariah and we're both openly gay
And they would go to these big companies and they would pitch them they would say look gay and lesbian consumers are
A big deal they have
Money and
We know how to talk to her
Hire us to
To design you ask for
So with dial Mattress
You did these Billboards and beautiful photography of a guy like like
It was all three already a guy laying on his stomach but you could see you know he had to his mother wasn't wearing any clothes but he had to she pulled
Down
Who you sleep with
Yeah here it is
Who you sleep with his your business how you sleep is ours
Dial a mattress
Beside it was a tough sell
This was the early 90s it was during the AIDS
Crisis
And a lot of companies would not talk directly to gay and lesbian
Consumers because they were afraid of alienating heterosexual cancer
Is that John says
A lot of the companies that
Did advertise to gays and lesbians what he calls the sin Industries like booze and cigarettes
And then out of the blue comes as call from soup
Saying hey we think lesbians might be one of our most
Markets and we need to confirm it
So John and his colleagues went out to Northampton Mass
Subaru's research said a lot of its cars were being sold their
And they gathered a little group of local Subaru owners together into a room with one of those two-way mirror
So we get up there where in the
There any observation room which always has like M&Ms and crackers is a very dangerous place today specially if you are on
Any kind of a diet so there's
All that candy and then the women start coming in
Yeah that's the amazing thing
Both groups were 100% fee
100% there were no men
John watches the women from the other side of the mirror while a researcher ask some
What do you use your car for
I want to move my dog from here to
I like throwing my stuff in the back and going camp
There's a tone and a
There's a tone to how they were answering
That was different than a woman saying
I like to go to TJ Maxx and get my hair done
Wow
Okay parently
Two kinds of women in the world I know I know I know I know and John said as a human being
He hates
This kind of stereotyping but this is sort of what you do you break people up
Categories
Do you say broadly here's what they're like
And then you try to sell stuff to him
So this is exactly what he's doing he's looking at these women and he says to himself
I think they are part of a specific group
And like these are lesbians are talking about be there less
Okay not just that
With these women seem to
Love their Subaru
So John in the Ad Agency drive down to
Cherry Hill New Jersey which is
Where Subaru is headquartered
To pitch the company
This was not
A small d
I think a lot of us forget this
But the early 90s were not apart
Particularly
Progressive time right
This is the era of don't ask don't tell
In just a couple years Bill Clinton was going to sign the Defense of Marriage Act which would effectively say same-sex Partners cannot
Be considered spouses
And even inside Subaru
Being openly gay was not easy
Tim Bennett the guy you saw Subaru having an identity crisis
He later worked on this campaign
Tim is gay
Any never came out at Subaru
Because he saw what
Could happen if
There was a out
Johnny was gay in the Mailroom they were people in the office it didn't want him to deliver mail
To their deaths because they're afraid they're going to get AIDS
So this is the environment
I know a lot of people thinking of the campaign notes if
That's what happened
So here comes Mariah and Nash
Into this conference room with about 20 Subaru bigwig
John and the team start
A PowerPoint presentation
Here is we are
Here is what we were doing in Northampton
And then
And then it was time for the bombshell Bass
Basically in and that's it I think that was like 6 or 7 panels into this PowerPoint thing
You know
You click the button up Pops this thing you know the
The target consumer in Northampton is a lesbian woman
John is braced
Spell resistance
We have to remember his agency
I have been going to come
4 years
Number statistics data sing
Look gay and lesbian consumers are very important you need to start marketing
Look at the numbers
And companies have been looking at this and saying
You're very interesting but
No thanks
And now here he is pitching to a car
Which is like the definition of mainstream
And he's telling them you got to Market your car still West
In the middle of the pitch John keeps
Sneaking these glances
At the president of the company
Trying to figure out what he said
He just kind of dogs
Sexy crosses his arms and you know you always learn in business that when people cross their arms
The closing
Themselves off
Tea or something crazy like that likely at that's where you always have to be careful cocktail party don't cross your arm
Other people around the table are also looking at the president of Subaru wondering
Say
But he doesn't do or say anything
Just keep watching the pitch
So they finish the presentation and then I don't need to invent a group to speak to
It looks like you found a group of people we can already talked
He said so this looks like a good
He didn't forget
Not only did he not freak out he hired them
I remember
This is a car come
This is what every Ad Agency
Wingstop
And now this tiny little ad firm has been hired to
To create ads for gay and lesbian
Consumers
4 super
Now of course they had to get down to designing the actual ads
Johnson has this proved to be a little bit true
Remember they were breaking new ground
And so John had to find ads.
It would fit the image that Subaru had been cultivating for years and years
And with this new group of consumers
Find a Target
That's right in fact John showed me the first
Print ad that he did in 1995
Until what it is is there's a
The Subaru up at the top
Bright and there's
Two women down at the bottom and the headline is
It loves camping
Dogs and long-term commitment
Too bad it's only a car
Good right it's good good and then down at the bottom there's a
Two women well when they had first went to the executives with two women
Together
The executive see this and they tell John
Listen listen separate them please put some copy in
Between them like an opposite corners of the
Looking at each other
Looking looking over the tech
What can I text a teacher
From this Johnson's the kind of settled into a
What they would use references that were obvious to Gay and Lesbian consumers
But not really to anybody else
And at the time there was
Xena Warrior Princess
Was the show that was airing like on
The WB Network or something and the lesbians
Love
Lucy Lawless
And everybody loves Ino
So one of the license place is going to be Xena lover Xena lvr
One of them was ptownie
P dash
County
For Brownstown another one was a camp out
It was so subtle
The message was there but you would have to look at the license plate on the car
In the picture in the printer
Add together
Jonathan San Francisco when the ad campaign launched she was at 8
A bus stop and a bus pulled up to the stop with his add on it
Immediately looks everybody standing there a bunch of old ladies look at the cars done to a thing
Two gay guys and believe me I knew they were gay gaydar
Finely tuned
They both look at each other and just kind of smile like they got it
Yeah they got it
In about 2 years after this campaign started
Subaru sales started growing
The niche marketing was work
Remember those group
What's the Subaru had identified the outdoorsy types of nurses and engineers
Subaru head marketing to all of them
And it's sales we're going up
And then
In 2000 Subaru made
Bold move aimed right at lesbian consumers
Martina Navratilova
Subaru hired the retired tennis
Star who is
One of the most high-profile lesbians in the world at that
To do this big Act
How do I know about the performance control
Who do I know about grip
Everything
She knows everything.
Pam derderian was responsible for this campaign
She runs a marketing firm called 15 minutes
Ink and she introduced Martina Navratilova to the people at Subaru in the 90
And she says
This was the moment when Subarus Niche marketing campaign beak
Came not-so-nice
She was on mainstream television commercials
Promoting the car
She was in
Print ads
It's promoting the cars
She was an outdoor
Billboard advertising
Promoting the cars
She was in Maine
Dream
Advertise
Not that there wasn't some pushback
Superman always faced resistance from some of its dealers who
Had problems with
Print ads
But when I started to hit TV the campaign got a lot
More attention
This wasn't just
Xena Angeles
These were really high-profile ads
John Nash said they were angry letters
Boycott is anxiety-inducing only because you don't want to lose one of your favor
Your clients
Over something that's
Completely out of you
Air control
If the business marched away was going to be because someone
Wrote a letter in crayon saying you know how dare you sell cars to these dirty gay people
Subaru didn't March
They kept up the campaign
And a year after they hired Martina Navratilova they had their best
Sales year 2
Eminem 2004 there was this big opportunity for
Product placement
There was a show on Showtime called The L Word
And Pam derderian helped create a storyline on the L word where lesbian tennis player
Got an endorsement deal with Subaru
Subaru
Yeah so ask her some kind of charity event to support the Arts
How hot is that
Pam derderian says
All of this
Was a really big deal
All of this was a watershed
I kept using the term Niche marketing
And she kept shutting me down and saying
Subaru
Went so far beyond nice
We're more comfortable
Whatever think that that an ABC program Modern Family two week
Weeks ago would have nine or eight year old transgender
Character on this is not niche
Any longer
This is just being
I'm proud and owning who you
You are and living in a diverse
Inclusive
Society
By about 2006
Subaru had grown into a very steady
Success
It wasn't Toyota wasn't Ford
But it's numbers were going up
And when the recession hit
Super Wings
The only car company in the US
Not to lose mark
But in spite of the success Subaru seems to have kind of
Change direction
I mean if you look at their ads now there's
New Martina Navratilova know Xena
Instead most of the ads feature pedrosexual an outdoorsy
Couples on their way to a hike
And things like that
And the moment when our societies because
Come so much more inclusive
It's strange
Why did Subaru back off
We have that after the break
Support for NPR
Are in the following message
Message come from servicenow
Making the world of war
Work better
They're cloud-based
4 man salute
Deliver digital workflow
Clothes that create great experiences for employees
And unlock productivity
For your whole come
Servicenow digitizes the work your people have
So they can do the
They wanted
Using technology
To make people more
Productive and engage
Moritz servicenow.
I called Subaru and I asked
The spokesman
Any City true we don't directly Target gay and lesbian consumers anymore
Are at Champions these days Folk
Focus on our customers hobbies and interest
Lake mountain biking and kayaking
Panda Darien has a theory about the
She says since the 90s when the
Started
So many more
People are just
Leaving out
And what was Miche
Is now just much more means
Stream soonish marketing is kind of passe
Brightwok Niche marketing became a victim of its own
Success and of course that raises
Is the question
Do ad campaigns actually
Influence
Or do they just reflectix
Yeah I kept asking myself that question and the answer is I honestly
Don't know
I put that question to Amy the woman from the beginning of the show who owns a Subaru and loves the Subaru
She said honestly
She does not know either
But then she told me this
Amy went to college in small-town can
In a place that was not
Especially friendly
Mitigate people
She did not have an easy
Anytime and then after school she moved to Washington DC
And one day she's in Dupont Circle and she sees
Superbad
I remember seeing this ad on the bus stop that said
It's not a choice it's a labor board
It made me smile it made her smile because it was talking to her
It's not a choice it's the way we're born
She knew exactly what that ad was
I was saying and not everyone would have known exactly what that ad was saying
It was an inside joke
Any me was finally on the inside
We always love to hear what you think of the show
Please Twitter
Haggis
Do all the things
We are on social media as planet
Get a lot of people to think on this one we got the idea for this story from Alex Massey you were to great story
About this you can find it at priceonomics. Com
Also thanks to Dave Orion Mary try Spa
Rebecca lindland Paul poop
Special thanks to Allison
You can also email us at Planet Money at npr.org
We actually do read all the emails we get and we love them
Today's episode was originally produced by Sally Helm Aviva dekornfeld to produce the rerun
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
And I know Elle King thanks for listening