Did you look up today
I'd like the thing I like the thing
The statute of limitations in Pennsylvania
Misdemeanors is
2 years
Yeah so can you tell us the story but let us not do it here
Let us do it here alone has brought us to a drug store that has a
Self checkout I used to be
A cashier at a grocery store
When I was about 16 years old you have no idea dude I look like I was 11 years old a day
I can do that I can
So one day I learned that my managers
I started to keep track of the performance of all of the cashier's how friendly you are
They were measuring our like
Items scanned per minute
They're posting those
For the other cashiers to see
I'm a little competitive
Got it that's got to get my boss numbers and then
I get this item that won't scan
Rolando never stands at the grocery store cilantro in rural Pennsylvania
Food was weirdly hard to scan the label. All torn up and crap anyway I'm trying to scan this thing and
All I can think is like oh my God my items per minute is plummeting plummeting
And then finally I just
Let it go down the register
Unscanned
And I grab the next item and the cat food away for free
Cuz we would have say I stole the cat food but to be a good employee
I was just trying to be good employee I was trying to get good numbers and I got good numbers my
Items permitted where I believe the best in the entire grocery store was out
Okay but when your boss has said
Speed things up I'm sure that they didn't mean
Break the law in the process
Yes
Yes and that
Is the point of this story
I
Maven breaking
The normal law
But I have since learned
That I was simply following a different law
Known as good heart
Lock good heart
Lockhart slaw
It essentially States
But if a company decides to measure something
The employees are going to find a way to give you good numbers
You just may not like
How they do it
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Sarah Gonzalez
Dozens of these laws or rules or principles
Goodhart's law also
The Peter Principle and Parkinson's law
Today on the show we take a look at
These laws that clean to explain just about everything that can go wrong in an office
From Bad managers
Too terrible
Procrastinate
It may change everything
About the way you were
Or it may just prove it
People spend more time reading about productivity then
Actually being productive
Support also comes from Fidelity invest
As a Fidelity wealth
You get a dedicated advisor
Hair to help grow and for
Protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of tax
And make clear recommendations
Thanks for your full Finance
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
Hi is this professor guitar
Yep speaking and
You are
Professor goodhart
Of goodhart's law
I am in
Do you proudly wear that moniker
I get mixed feelings
This is Charles goodhart
Economist
Former advisor to England
Central Bank
Professor emeritus at Linens
School of economics and about 45 years ago Charles goodhart wrote a paper about monetary policy
That included in the introduction
A faithful little line
Ignoring a good hot slow
Did any observed
Statistical regularity
Will technical apps
Once pressure is placed upon
The control pill
Okay hard to understand but
He was making a very narrow point
About how measuring one tiny slice of the economy
Seems to mess up
That slice of vehicle
Put hot slow with ex
Play
Bother
Joking
Sidecar
It was not intended at that
To be taken
Bacteria
But over time it was
People took goodhart's law out of the world of monetary policy and
Came up with new formula
End of the law for example
Once you target a measure it ceases to be a good measure
I think it's one of them
The point is really fed the simple let's say that
One of the measures
All of egg hunts
Is that the waking time
Is captured
This is a real example the British government started pressuring its hospitals to
C emergency
Patience fast
Start with in 4 hours
And sure enough
Wait times
Truck
Just not always for the right
Reasons
Hospital started
Gaming the statistics
And one of the most outrageous exam
This practice wear
Patients would be asked to wait inside an ambulance
Until the hospital
With absolutely sure
That patient could be seen within the four hour time
Then the patient
Another way of stating goodhart's law
Be careful what you measure
Because
Your employees are going to make it happen
Indeed
And they will do it by reallocating resources to achieve that
One measure
And fails
Tumi
Non talkative
Measures
Because resources will it be 9 located away free
When you first introduced goodhart's law Universe specific app
That's correct
Not exactly the same
How do you how do you feel about these broader formulation
Well I know I'm perfectly happy with the mine when I woke up this
Kids cooking
Didn't some reason
750s appointed
King that I'm probably busy
Name for Walker Hayes had a chocolate comment
Off to some
Theism
Doing more reps
Considered academic
Detailed work
For which I am listening
And so Sarah I feel like
We should introduce a
The corollary to
If you decide to name Allah
It will become a law
And you may not like what it does
To your legacy
Hello check onto Carnival in here
Walking up to the task of Sarah Gonzales
Hey okay so it's like what 9:30 in the morning
Thursday November 8th
And we're supposed to be
Working on the next segment of this episode
We're not even close to finished supposed to tell you about the so-called Parkinson's law
Which states essentially that
Work expands
To the time allotted
Silver example
Penny and I have an entire week
To finish this Parkinson's law segment
If we're being honest that should really only take like one day's work
Probably yeah
But we have a whole week
So that means we're probably going to spend time like looking for
Archival tape that work
Probably not going to use we are going to do extra interviews that if we're being honest
Not room for in this piece always do that we have a week
Into the work will expand to fill the week
But today we're going to try to use Parkinson's law
Talkative
And reporter for this segment though
She does not know it yet
Is Planet Money newest producer
Alexi Horowitz Ghazi
And we are waiting for him to
Alexi
Hey man
So let me just get into work yes
Circumference do with me
Coming coming
So
We have a
Professor
On the line right now who's an expert in Parkinson's law
Hello professor
Hi
And I told you that I was going to do the interview
We want you to dinner
What
And furthermore we want you to do the whole segment
There's one catch
The time allotted for you to finish
This work
Is one day
You have to finish this by the end of the
All right let's do it she's literally rolling up his sleeves
That's right that's good
Professor can you hear me
Great
I'm okay so maybe
Start out with
Well we are back in the studio
You had a day
Your sleeves are still rolled up actually
You interviewed the professor do you have a story
The key to my success and yes I do
All right let's do it
So the first thing she told me was that
Parkinson's law started out
As
A joke yes
So it all started
With a humorous essay published
Economist
And
The author was C
Northcote Parkinson
Was a British Naval historian
That's mangs you of the Johns Hopkins Business School
In 1955 The Economist published Parkinson's essay is a kind of
Facetious argument
And he talked about why bureaucracies
Almost always grow no matter how much work
They're really doing
Actually found some archival tape of the now-deceased professor Parkinson
Talking about the essay you actually write Hazard KY
I'm serious in
Elite nice have been sent to a humorous magazine
Instead and
I think more why is it
I sent it to the London economist
Townhouse
You found someone that is more British
Then professor Charles goodhart
This is very impressive
That actually came off a 1960 vinyl album
Called Professor C Northcote Parkinson
Explain Parkinson's law
The blurb on the cover closet quote
Delightfully unprocess Oreo
I should be Planet Money slogan I feel like that's what we're going for
Makes as a Parkinson's article was mostly about why bureaucracy
Escrow
But the thing that really stuck with people that really made it a big deal was the opening line
He summarized the law in the first sentence of his essay
It basically says what
Expands so as to fill the time available
Voice competition
Make says that even though it started as a joke by the 1960s
People were actually treating this like a real
La
Add psychologist and economist
Coming up with
Experiments in a laboratory to try and figure out if
People would expand their work
To Fit changing deadlines
It seems like they actually did
And then the other people going out and trying to find Parkinson's law in the wild
Field
Cast
Across a variety of contexts
Such as
Wood Harvesters
The only industry
School system and her colleagues have actually studied this and sure enough they found that when they gave their
Subjects longer deadlines they expanded the work
To fit those deadlines
And she says that
By now
Parkinson's law has become a storied part
Cubicle lure
It has been a men's topic
Management training how how do you fight Parkinson's law
First you could
Shorten your deadlines
Know something about that. You could offer a reward for fast
Task completion are you asking us for a reward right now
This is a hold
Like a stick-up
How much money do we have in our pocket Pockets turn them out
Wallet with all the money my wallet so I got ahold taller
Thanks good work man made it rain
This is backed up by science
May says that you know even though Parkinson's law started
As a joke
It's been documented through a lot of different studies
But more importantly she says
It just makes intuitive sense
Yeah that's the thing I think
People intuitively agree with his logic arguments
Man
Mets
I think I think we just got cut off I think that means that
Our interview expanded to the time
Weed allotted for
Cutout
Alexi you did it you finish the task at hand in one day
Instead of a week
It was exactly
As good as if we had done it in a while
Better thank you Alexi thanks Connie thank Sarah and Alexa
We are going to properly reward
You for this I'm going to go buy you a pint
Have the most English Beer Week
We can possibly find
Excitement
Cheers
Okay the next light is called the
Peter Principle this one says that in a hierarchy
Every employee tents
Rise to their level of incompetence
If you're good at your job your boss
Notice is promote
See you then
Forget that job
Can you keep getting promoted
Until you get promoted to a job that
You are not
Good act
Find out what that feels like
We asked our boss
Remember this
Annual reviews just a few weeks
Jacktv we all think Alex is really good at his job
Alex react
How do you define someone who
Had the self-awareness
To realize that they were falling victim to the Peter Pan
Yes and I found
Stephanie Brown
This story starts
Almost two years ago
I was doing a job that I love and never felt like I was
Even working I loved it so much
Stephanie was a social media specialist for a large universe
Behind the scenes job what she likes
Find good stories about people around campus
And then figure out how to
Share them on social media
Creativity
She had a lot of freedom she got to
Independently
And these were the things she was looking for
It just felt it was somewhere around
It's really comfortable
It really
But that front of a lot of strengths that I have
Phase one of the Peter Prince
She is doing great
She knows that she's good at some things
And not others
And then I was asked
Have the interested in this figure all
Great promotion totally normal this is how jobs
Now she's in charge of webcon
University
Spend a lot of time in meeting
And harbor job
To tell other people how to do
Their jobs
So this is not behind this
I'm an introvert so having to
Like stand up and a group of people
Super uncomfortable for me
From the start I had to do monthly training
Let's just hope sex before that every time and she becomes a person
Who everyone brings their problems to asking her to find us a
Number one time
Haven't smoked
Let me in the cafeteria
Something they didn't like
Put on the spot
Holding my lunch and standing there not sure what
To do how to handle it
I am terrible at this time
There are
Millions of Stephanie
Everywhere
In every
Great just because you're a good teacher doesn't mean you're going to be a good principal and just because you're a good lawyer.
Does it mean you're going to be good at bringing in new clients to the law firm this is the Peter Prince
It comes from a best-selling book back in the early 70s by a professor Lawrence
J Peter
And it was actually Sarah
Kind of a joke
Course all of our logic jokes
This one was satire add the point the doctor Peter was trying to make was
Look around
This is the explanation for why
So many people are bad at their jobs like so many mistakes
Just happened over and over again
And why so many people
Hate their job
Like Stephanie Burton
And Stephanie
Is rare in the cheat
Is self-aware enough to know it and admit it
And also to do something about it
Stephanie is fighting the Peter Principle
My stepping down from her new bigger job
Today is actually my very last
Stay in a quit
She's going to the motor
She wouldn't talk to her boss and she said
Hey I want a job like my old one the one that I love the one that I was good at
Yeah you know it I don't know that a lot of
People admit that they should be demoted
But I think
For me it makes me happier
That makes me feel like I can do a better job
And I feel smarter at what I do
Because
I know
My job so well now
Self demotion that is one way to beat the Peter Principle
Get any ideas
I think there are some important meetings you have to go to I think it's
Payroll day today alright I'm going to go find Kenny tell him to come on back in here thanks letter
We go searching for a law that
Did not
Support for this podcast and the following message come from fidelity
As a Fidelity Wealth Management
You get a dedicated advisor to help grow and protect your way
Find ways to minimize the impact
Taxes and make
Clear recommendations for your
Full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage services
LLC
All right
For this last law
We figured we need something
The did not just start out as a joke
About crappy management
Or lousy procrastination
Our final log comes from Alice
And I have a long boring title
I'm Electra at King's College London
Search
Watch dogs Wiki
Got it
What you really need to know about Alice's
She is the kind of Professor
Who when a Brand New World Bank report
Comes out
She live tweets her reactions as if she is watching game of
Throat
Vitalis told us about it
Is pretty well-documented
But as far as we know it
Doesn't have a name
But here's how Alex
Social change
Satellites when we see that others are
Another word
People want to change
They just want to see other people do it
Process of a snowboard
But the tricky thing is how do you get
Snowbowl to move in the first place
So let me give you for example
For example
This is great
Brilliant intervention in
Uganda this was an intervention by Innovations for poverty
Action
Uganda was struggling with dementia
Violent it was happening at alarming rates and people didn't seem to be reporting abuse
Something needed to change
But
For this law with no name
You shouldn't just tell people to do some
You should show them that other people are doing it
And so i p a r and a video camp
Doing
Essentially
Did the video did not tell
The gender-based violence is wrong
Old shows
People going out and being supported by that community
And what they found within 6 months
Is this led to a rapid increase in repulsing a big production in gender-based violence
There are a bunch of examples of changing social norms
For example
College vintage
Instead of putting a poster that said binge drinking is bad research has put up signs that the centrally said
Hey actual statistics show that your classmates
Don't drink as much as you
You think they drink
And
That approach seem to work
So this approach
It occurred to me
I think I have a problem
The disk could help fix
Still Alice I know that
Typically your job
Deals with
Very important
Global political high stakes
Issues
But would you mind talking to me about
The fact that no one at my office watch
Cheese dishes
Shoot
It's okay
People in our office are leaving dirty dishes
In the sink all the
And so my idea was like
What if
We work with the office manager
To put up poster
Didn't say
Hey you should
Do dishes
What If instead they said
Hey did you know everybody else does
The dishes a bunch and Alice was like no this approach only works
If you are actually
Telling
The truth so I wouldn't run a fake campaign I think that's really dangerous
Because if people realize that the office manager
Putting up fake posters then that could
Undermine Trust
In the office
So I would I wouldn't do that Kenny
Drew parallels with
So for example
Alice says that in remote parts of Zambia healthcare workers often feel like no one cares what they're doing
This curbs worker morale makes it hard for them to
Show up and
Do their best work
But
One thing that really helped
Was when supervisors started awarding a trophy
For people's work there wasn't even money attached it was just a trophy just that sense of being appreciated
People saying that you're making an effort and people rewarding
And I seen that something that we did learn from
Regards to your dishes
You're saying I should make
An amazing dishwashing
Is that what you're saying I 100
Expensive dishwasher
Yeah
This episode was produced by Alexi Horowitz Ghazi brynhurst at at
And our competent supervising producer is Alec
If you have a law that you
Know about email us we are Planet Money at NPR.
RGN special thanks to our intern Shane McKean he handled
The most important part of the cell
Episode
So I have a weird request
I'm trying to make
A trophy
With a golden bug on top
Yeah of course we ask
Shana Planet Money In
Rooms To Go
And custom-order a congratulations the kitchen is clean
Trophy all I needs to say is
The dishes are all done
Shane bought a five foot tall trophy
And then let's do an! On the end Eddie real
Bug spray paint
Did gold on the very top
And when the dishes were clean this giant trophy would show up
They weren't
The chubby disappeared
We left a recorder out
Let people figure it out
It's really here
So there's this giant ass trophy
Fork and knife taped to it so I imagine it's an award for eating of some kind
Psychological experiment is being conducted without my consent
Office problems
There's no trophy
There's a dirty spoon in the sink not mine but I will wash it
Should we get the trophy back
The dishes are all done because of because I see the trophy
I feel like
I've been tricked by a trophy
Does a trophy would make me want to do that has disappeared again
There's some dishes in the sink supervising producer Alex goldmark is doing them
This was quite unsigned
But I'm just going to say it
I think there were way fewer
Unwashed dishes
Sky thing to work anyway
If you'd like to see a picture of a giant dishwashing trophy
It is on Instagram we are at
I'm Kenny Malone
And I'm Sarah Gonzales
Thanks for listening