About a month ago there was a pretty big upset in National Palace
It is easily the most shocking result of this political season
Stunning defeat this is a seismic
Political upset and I just was apparently a thesaurus Worthy
Upset but
We're talking about the race for the Democratic nominee
Can in New York
14th congressional district
Which includes parts of
The queens and the Bronx
In this primary one of the most powerful Democrats in Congress
The guy named Joe Crowley
He lost
Service First
Time in Canada at this woman who is virtually unknown
Alexandria ocasio-cortez a 28 year old male bartender Community organizer Bernie Sanders supporter working class
New Yorker if she calls herself and Democratic Socialist
Specifically ocasio-cortez
Did a member of an organization called
The Democratic socialists of a
A few years ago basically no one had ever heard of it.
Today their membership is a
Floating new chapters are popping up across the country and
So are Democratic Socialist candidate
And so this got us wondering
Who exactly are
America's new socialist
Hello and welcome to Planet Money
I'm Danielle Curtis
And I'm Kenny Malone
Today on the show
The Democratic socialists of America
Who are they what do they want
Where they come from
And how do you take an idea that was political poison for decades and relaunch it in today's chaotic full
Oracle Arena
Spoiler alert
You do not include an arm
Looking for violent revolution if that's
What's the question
I guess it's kind of what I was
Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with great jeans
How did they make them so great Madewell starts with
Premium dinner
Then offers men's and women's styles for seriously every
Also you can recycle any brand of jeans in a Madewell store
And they'll give you $20 off and you pay
They work with the blue jeans go green program
Turn old jeans into housing insulation for communities in need
Terms apply
Ready to find your perfect fit stop by a Madewell store or go to Madewell.
Okay so let's get this out of the way
This is an episode about social
But we are not here to do an episode arguing over the merits of
If you want to pick that fight call your uncle or a political
Science student there whatever
No but we were interested in was
Just like the basics for starters
Who even are
These Democratic socialists of America
We figured
We should probably go meet some of them
Which is how I found myself at a bar in West Virginia
So it's a Saturday in early July It's Just Before Sunset and I'm at a brewery near a town
Call Reidsville
It's not super hard to find the Democratic socialists inside this
There's this guy he's wearing a t-shirt that says united we bargain divided
Baby bag is also a young woman telling the story of how she
Status
Anti anti-immigration protest
And how she got arrested
The house Susan Sarandon with her
This is a sort of socialist
Happy hour
Amita
Of the local chapter of the democratic social
America or the
PSI
The BSA is not a political party
It's a non-profit
It's got chapters all over the
And that young woman talking about getting arrested
She co-founded this chapter in West Virginia
Her name is Kelly rose she's 36 years old
Probably
I think I'm 36
Yeah I'm Thursday
Kelly is a registered independent
She would bet that she's more religious than your average
I am a Christian I might be the only one in our little chapter that
Is a person
Possibly my mother would want to be me on this but I think if anybody was ever a socialist it was Jesus
3 years ago the DSA
Head only about 6000 members
Across the country
That is fewer members
In the American Racing
That is my best sound
Just nice
Socialism is a word that comes with a lot of baggage for a lot of American
It has associations with
Cold War and communism end
Severe looking totalitarian leaders
But it has been undergoing a sort of Rehabilitation
It arguably started with Bernie Sanders
Was on stage running for
Saying that he was a social
End Alexandria Ocasio Cortez nomination
Last month
Got even more people talking about socialist
In the last 3 years membership in the Democratic socialists
America has really grown in
Shut up by more than six
600%
Which is still only around 45000
Bernie Sanders however not one of those men
He does consider himself a democratic social
Ideologically
Is not a dues-paying member of the
DSA Oregon
Ization
And that is just fine by some of the DSA member
Bernie Bernie is definitely there's some policies that I think he's been a little too soft.
A little too Democrat for me as a founding member of this chapter
The DSA Prides itself on being a big socialist
Their members who want a system that looks
More like what
Scandinavian countries have that would be
Higher taxes to fund much more comprehensive government services like
Social safety net
That
And then at the other end of the spectrum you have members who think capitalism has completely failed
I think the whole system needs to be replaced
And Djoser Nelly it's more towards data
Improve capitalism ultimately want to get rid of it
Nail down what exactly the DSA want
Because you've got all of these
Is Chapters everywhere they all have different priorities
And those chapters themselves have members with different socialist ideas
But there is a national headquarters
Of the DSA
It's 400 miles away
Virginia butt
Luckily for us
It's only 3 train stops away from our office
Maria
Great to meet you
Maria svart is the national director of the day
Dsh has been a member since
Is college in the two
Go to do like a tour of the offices
Sherbet in the nerve center of the American Socialist movement
Democratic socialists of America National office
This probably is the epicenter of socialist activity right now
But there's not really too much going on in this
Does offices
Teeny it's got this
Dingy old carpet
Is there a pamphlet stacked against the wall
Fun fact
The Democratic socialists headquarters
Right next to Wall Street
Is that a coincidence
Well you know we like to be close to have an eye on them but mostly it's cuz they're meant to
The DSA is a nonprofit organization
People pay dues they join
Local chapters because
They believe in this
Unifying ideology
When it comes right down to it
People need to be able to leave live a dignified life
I mean there are certain things that should not be left up to the mark
In other words
Socialism
Which in any form has been a tough
Cell in the United
For a long time
The DSA was founded in 19
Ronald Reagan
Was the president
Deregulating
He was turning the economy.
Towards the free market
Selling socialism at this point in the US it was an uphill battle
The organization to be honest did go through. Where we were less active the membership shrank
Elected officials
Didn't want to be associated with us
Through the 1980s and 1990s to 2000s
Socialism was a dangerous political bomb to live at one of your opponent
Throw it
And your competition would have
Chaos on their hands
We actually had at one point we tried to give a donation that it was richer
So right
Maria can't remember the exact details but
She thinks it was a state-level race in mm
And the candidate was afraid of what might happen if they took this socialist money
Their opponent might send out a mailer
To everyone in their District
But a picture of them next to authoritarian dictators
From history and say they were all socialists
And then have a picture
The candidate
But of course in the last three years that has
Totally change
And they're all of these little ways you
You can tell the TSA was not quite prepared for all of the
For example
Some of their old press releases
Does have Maria's personal contact information
I was fine when nobody was calling them a writing much about the DSA
Maria says she's
Still dealing with all of the trouble that that
Caused
Saiguette
Hundreds and hundreds and hundreds of emails a day
It literally takes time just to forward them to the rest of the stuff for the DSA is now on a lot of
People's radar
And they would like to know what exactly
Is the dsa's platform
Andrea tells us
Well we don't
Really have a platform
But a year ago the chapters did get together and they hammered out
Three big National priorities that they were all going to
Push for
Number one
Winning medicare-for-all
Number two
Supporting workers and building stronger unions and
Number three
And electing Democratic Socialist office
At all levels of government are each of these ideas really
Quickly just to get a sense of what the
DSA is thinking
First
Medicare for all
This term is getting thrown around a lot on the left
These days end
Basically the idea is to take Medicare which is taxpayer-funded insurance for seniors
And give it to everyone else too
So taxpayer-funded health insurance for everyone we don't want something that's a half-measure we want to get
Private Industry totally out of the system we just want to
Make sure everybody's in
Every gets Healthcare now this is something Bernie Sanders talked about a lot
In his presidential campaign
Answer for how much it could cost which is
A lot
Trillions and trillions of dollars
Okay the second thing the DSA is working on right now
Is electing more
Democratic Socialist
The news outlets like us
We tend to focus on the Socialist
Part of the dsa's name
What's the word Democratic it's in there too
And what this means by in large is working within the existing political system
You know democratic
But it's been 20 years since a member of the DSA with
Fennel seed
Alexandria ocasio-cortez
Because of how New York politics works
He's about as close to a shirt
Is possible
And while she is the most prominent
There's a whole slate of other DSA politicians in smaller race
A couple things you might hear
Julia Salazar
She's running for a state seat in New York
And then there's Sara innamorato in Pennsylvania
So far only 5 DSA endorsed candidates have won primaries
Five primary Victory just isn't allowed in the
In the third and final priority
For the DSA
Unions
Helping to empower work
So
What that looks like is we
Show up
On picket lines and workers are trying to form a union or negotiate a contract
Alastair
Unions are kind of sitting with their head in the sand and they're not really being effective at organizing there
Your co-worker is
Are we support members
Organizing your coworkers
So those are the three priorities at the SAS
If you look at the organization's literature you realize that
Those things are not
The goal
I think they are just incremental steps towards a much more radical
Take healthcare for example
The group is pushing medicare-for-all which is a big thing it's essentially socialized insurance
But the TSA would like to go even bigger
It would like to socialize all of metal
Like in the National Health System in England
We're being a doctor is a taxpayer-funded government job
And take the dsa's focus on strengthening unions here
Is how Maria explained
Is the bigger vision
A great analogy is
You know in a union you might negotiate that you want you know what say there's a loaf of bread you're going to keep a quarter of the bread
Union
Negotiators might go to the bargaining table for contract and say we want 50%
Of the bread
Socialist would say we wanted
We want to own the bakery and run it in our own and
I love this analogy
Is bread and not iPhones
Because it sounds like we are living in lame
Do You Hear the People Sing Kenny I do
All the time
Did you say
Is talking about a big idea
Years ago from Karl Marx the workers
Controlling the means of
Now the TSA is a non-violent organization they're not advocating overthrowing the factory or the bakery
They're just starting small by Marxist standards
East find supporting unions
And to be fair the bakery owners are probably safe for now because
There aren't really that many members of the
The DSA
45000 members would not even
Instill most football
But the TSA it knows that sometimes crazy ideas can take hold
Case in point
While we were visiting
GSA National
Law offices
Maria walked over to the Bookshelf
Put down this
Buck
6 in by 4 in around last
Actually have four copies of
Of this book it is called
The other America had it flies but it did totally changed
Magnus re-written
In the 1960s by a guy named Michael Harrington
Also co-founded the DSA
He argued that there was this invisible impoverished
Class of people that no one was paying enough attention to
The other America was a big deal and it had people talking about poverty in a new way including
President John F
The book reportedly helped Inspire Kennedy
Ready to launch an assault on poverty
That would lead to a slate of program
Including Medicare
Which launched in 90
At the time
Medicare seem to a lot of conservatives like this
Crazy extension of the government
Pure socialism
And they weren't entirely wrong
Medicare is a form of socialized insurance
And today a lot of Americans take that for granted
They just see it as another government service
And so here we have this tiny book
Written in the 90
1960s
Buy a Democratic Socialist
The help Spark
A real socialist program that 50 years later
Is really popular with a lot of them
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One Capital One
Is reimagining banking I offering account
With no fees or
Items that can be opened from anywhere in
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
I'm sure many of you have strong feelings
About this
You can send those over to Planet Money
At npr.org
Prayers for our intern who has to read all those emails
Play show was produced by Megan Cain our editor is Bryant urstadt and are supervising producer is Alex goldmark
And my editor is Arnie sizes thank you Arnie for letting me hang out with the Planet Money Team to do the story
I can tell you it is a joy spending time with Daniel Chris leben if you want to spend more time with her
You can hear her on NPR politics podcast
I'm Kenny Malone
And I Danielle Kirkland
Thanks for listening