Everybody's David we are replaying one of our favorite episodes today this story is about
I'm not going to
Larry Williams has a lot of stuff
There was a quest to find Noah's Ark
Find it where's the time he ran for US Senate in Montana didn't win but he got 44% of the vote
And then there's the one we're going to tell you today
It starts in 1986
Larry and some of his buddies are up in New Mexico is Caballo Mountain
Hanging out in the sagebrush
Camping tents
And then one night he said they're all sitting on the couch
We started talking as guys do talk about a campfire about a lot of things
And nobody really enjoys paying taxes that's not surprising
The question came up the question
Do you really have to pay your income
Larry it heard about these people who had found legal ways not to pay at all
As It Happened One of the men sitting around that campfire was a lawyer
A man named Jim Knowles
I asked the gym about
Jim cigars
Now so I'll BSS you know you got to pay your taxes
Call your lawyer look into it
The lawyer Jim wasn't respectable
Active in his community in
Church total stretch
And he says
Sure
I will look into
Larry didn't hear anything for a while
Then one day he gets this call
It's Jim the lawyer
Sing
Can I come by and talk to you
Mary says sure
Jim comes by and explains he's pretty sure he's found a hole in the tax laws
A hole so big that Larry and whoever else wanted to
Could just walk right through
When he told you that did you think
Maybe I don't have to pay income tax
Yeah of course I did I'm here as a lawyer Hastings law school lawyer
And I got a lawyer for 45 years or so
Representable guy yeah and that's how Larry Williams decided to stop paying is it
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Keith Romer and I'm David kestenbaum
Nobody likes painter income taxes
We all take as many deductions
Some of us go further you know round down maybe leave a few things out and then there are people like Larry Wood
You took this very understandable impulse to pay as little as possible
And went just as far as you
You could go
Decided he wasn't going to pay
Today on the show The Story of Larry Williams
And an answer to the question
Do you really have to pay your income tax
This message comes from NPR sponsor Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimums that can be open from anywhere in 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
When Larry Williams
Decided to stop paying it
He was working as a Commodities Trader and a
Investment advisor give
Tok
He's making a really good living
You could certainly afford
Taxes that of course pay for all kinds of things people want to have in some form
The military
Court system
Rhodes wrestler about that
Don't you like roads
He said well you could pay for roads
And the other stuff
He said we just shouldn't be spending so much money on
Larry feels like people pay way too much in tax
Sales tax
Sac City tax state
Tax property tax
And then on top of all of that
Federal income tax
When somebody comes and takes 50% of my income doesn't have the courtesy to point a gun at me to do it
It's bothersome
Some people apparently doesn't bother okay they were all over and they could b**** and moan about it but they don't do anything about it
Larry
He was going to do something about it
Not only was he not going to pay he was going to use the tax lot itself to prove that what he was doing was 104
Percent legal Larry's lawyer laid out the loophole
It went back to the
There is no mention of an income tax in the original tax
In the Sixteenth Amendment ratified in 1930
The 16th Amendment is very short
And on the surface it seems pretty clear
This is how it starts
The Congress shall have power to lay and collect taxes on incomes
From whatever Source derived
Does that seem like you have a lot of wiggle room
Larry and his lawyer we're taking a close look at that
What exactly they are
Did income mean
Like what is the legal definition
What count is
His lawyer friend Jim had gone back and pulled all these old Court
Aldi's old decisions instead
You know
There's a pretty good legal argument you can make that the federal income tax can only be applied
Federal income
Like Money Paid you by the federal government
If you have a government job or some
Call the Internal Revenue Service
So think about that for Mama internal internal door what if you have an internal investigation say at the police station it's about
About police officers is so internal would be income generated
From a federal based Revenue so if you're paid by the government that would be internal to United States
If your income has
Not from the United States government
Venice
Not taxable
His lawyer friend also questioned who was legally required to
Pay this income
Sure citizens the United States
But according to his reading of the Constitution
US citizenship was basically option
Your citizenship
Isn't quite what you and I
Normally
Think your citizenship is
Larry thought about all this
And where most people would decide
No way that's crazy I could end up in prison
Larry thought
Let's give it a try
What are some party that was like
If this is legal why isn't every single America
Well that's a question people always ask but this time you know because a lot of people don't study a lot of people are afraid of the government
Why do people just roll over they don't want to test anything
The knot on the edge of always like living on the edge life of Congress more interesting out there so
To me it was like okay this is interesting let's see where this leads
So you felt like you were testing the government
It away sure absolutely that weekend we didn't hide anything with her we are this what we're doing
We filed the papers
Here's what they do
Since by his lawyers Logic the income tax you only apply to citizens
Of the United States
Larry wrote a letter to the state of California
Declaring that he was a quote
Sovereign citizen
The state of KY
And to make it doubly clear that his personal income wasn't taxable by the federal government
Larry set up something called
Pure Trust
Andy Roddick
All of his income into that trust
Now it wasn't as personal income anymore
Now the income belong to that Trust Bank of America open up a bank account for the trust you know we got.
Attack
Identification numbers and all that stuff
To basically paid almost no income tax
Correct
So after you file that are you
Are you nervous that someone's going to come after you like how does it feel after you file
Why would I be nervous I had to buy some to to CPA
And a couple lawyers
We thought at this point we should probably check with 8/3 wire
My name is Dan Evans I'm a lawyer
Do you unlike biographical details
Dennis spent a lot of time studying this tax fraud
You got interested in it because there was this whole world of people asking these questions
Or at least there was a Tuesday
HughesNet was this popular thing back in the early days of the internet
It was basically message boards where people can post questions or discuss things they were in
And there are a couple of them on taxes
There was a miscellaneous Top Texas moderated
Which
The messages had to be approved by a moderator and that kind of kind of kept the crazies out
But miscellaneous. Taxes was wide open
And I hadn't been there very long before someone posted something very emphatic very certain
About how the income tax was unconstitutional
And he cited cases
And the Bruce Haber decision and
I read it I thought
You know
I don't remember that from Law School
Then look into a bunch of these claims
Some seemed totally ridiculous like this one that Ohio had never officially filed the paperwork to become
I'm a state
What does that has to do with anything
Well that's a good question Taff was born in
Ohio
And if Ohio was an estate and then he shouldn't have been praising the United States and he could not have ratified the 16th of May
Amendment or something
The 16th Amendment which provided for the income
Another claim is that if you write these three Latin words on your tax form nunc Pro tunc
You don't have to pay
Not true by the way
They were ones that were obviously crazy
But then they were ones that took some digging
Dance Arts writing up everything he find online in an FAQ
Frequently asked questions
Those are Made Back Then
Dances called the tax protester FAQ
So I pulled it up online
I thought I'll just print this out so we can have in the studio and the printer
Went freaking insane like I thought it was just like a couple Pages there was trying to put out 289 pages
Had actually unplug the printer
Sorry about that I guess I should have printed a warning up top like do not try to print
Can you boil all these hundreds of pages down to a sentence is there anything to any of these arguments
No
Dan says it if Larry Williams had come to him and said I'm thinking about not paying my taxes
You would have said no way
But Larry had other lawyer telling him differ
So he filed a sovereign citizenship and he formed is pure
Your trust
And he didn't pay his income tax
You know what happened
Nothing happened
Internet for how long did nothing have
Hello maybe 3-4 years
The three four years you go on paying basically no income tax
Yeah
My basically not how did that feel
Why would it feel bad
My money
Years went by and nothing
Maybe she was onto something
Maybe the IRS did not have a good answer to his legal claim
Or maybe the IRS just hadn't gotten around to dealing with it yet
This message comes from NPR sponsor Capital One Capital One is reimagining banking I offering account
With no fees or minimums that can be open from anywhere in 5 minutes Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
We reached out to the IRS they declined to comment on Larry's case but you can imagine thing from their side
Maybe the first year Larry doesn't file his taxes they don't notice
There's a lot of people filing taxes he just one return among Millions
But then he does it the next year
And the year after that
If you the IRS your like
Waze
I see what's going on here
Dear Larry William
Then the IRS starts writing letters in a course gym would write letters back to their letters
If that's not a problem and then the battle really began
The IRS started taking money out of his bank account legal arguments back in
Henceforth
His lawyer Jim sang Don't worry don't worry we got this
And then Jim died
Out of the blue
You know how people feel lost
When a friend dies
Liefeld
He also was legally lost
And I'm on my own here aren't I
Larry didn't know what to do
He wasn't a lawyer he tried keeping up with all the letters back and forth to the IRS but he really didn't know the law
At some point Larry decides to make a trip to Australia to give a series of talks about
Plane lands at 2
And he's sitting there waiting to get off
When these three guys
Get on the plane and walk down the aisle
They stopped at his seat
Are you Larry Williams
Well I got love
What is this for
Maybe they wouldn't anime said you're under arrest
Okay
NYSEG Buffalo
To this romantic for I went down in the basement of us
Airport Econo car like a holding area
And went there and they said I hear the papers in United States government
You been charged with income tax evasion
The Australian police had arrested Larry on behalf of the
They take Larry down to a jail in down
Where he meets his self
He's a guy with a scar and aside from a bullet wound
Larry tells him I'm in for tax evasion
Summit says
I'm in for robbing bank
There's like
I never met a bank robber for my life
Flight to Hawaii rob a bank
Guy says he's how I do it
The trick to robbing bank first of all you need three people
You need one guy to drive a car one guy to maintain the door control traffic coming in out and one guy me I'm the
Iranian I am Square I jump over there
The counter a grab all the money and run out
You got to do it in 2 and 1/2 minutes if you don't have it in 2 and 1/2 minutes got to leave cuz that's how the coppers response time is by
About three and a half minutes
Lie gets out on bail after
U.s. government is trying to extradite him so they can actually get him into a quart
But lies like I'm not done yet
Here's a local lawyer to help him fight extra
If your the IRS Larry is an enormous pain
Because he's that little guy
But he's costing so much money to try to bring back to the country
Still the law is the law and you can just let him get away with it
For three years Larry does get away with
He lives in Australia
Is fiance flies down
See the sights.
Kangaroos
Dive the Great Barrier Reef
But at some point
It all starts to feel
Larry says fine
I will come home
Let the courts decide
What's it like to be extradited
Not fun
Two Marshals Shackled In Me said they paraded him
Through the airport then sat next to him on the plane all the way
Something like 15 years after Larry first stopped
Paying taxes
US Government finally got him in
Front of a judge
I was charged with the income tax evasion fraud multiple bank accounts all sorts of really bad things
Unidad defraud the government but I was a really bad guy
To give you a sense of what Larry was up against from a legal perspective
We ran Larry's old arguments passed the lawyer from before Dan Evans
They're all in his 300 page essay
First we asked about the pure Trust
Larry's routing all his income
Dermatrest
I don't know where to start I mean it's
I hate to tell you this but what you are talking about is pure gibberish
It is nonsense
It is ridiculous
Well let's start by looking at subchapter J of the Internal Revenue code which refers to trust
What's dangos on for a little while.
Then we tried the one about Larry being a sovereign citizen of the State of California
It doesn't make any difference whether you're citizen of the United States if you are within the physical boundaries of the United States
You have to pay federal income tax
Even Larry had seen the writing on the wall
Before he even appeared in court he agreed to pay all the back tax
The IRS said that
The question before the judge and jury
Was whether Larry should go to jail or pay huge fine for what he had done
Here we got copies of the trance
The prosecutors go first they lay out that Larry had not been paying taxes they point out
Adding onto fancy homes they show these checks he'd received for like
$100,000 $150,000 for all invest
MIT lectures
The prosecutor tell the jury this case is about greed lies deception and fraud ladies and gentlemen
But then Larry's defense lawyer starts making his case
And this part is fast
He said
You've heard the statement ignorance of the law is no excuse
That is the general rule
You can't Bop somebody on the head or kill them and say I didn't know
But because we are dealing with a special area
Complicated
Local tax laws
In tax cases
If a defendant believes that what he's doing is not against the law
Even if his belief is crazy
I will say that again even if his belief is crazy
If you believe that in good faith
He is not guilty of
The crime of tax
I love that you can literally say I didn't know what the rules are and that can get you off our tax laws are that concert
It makes it really hard for the IRS to prosecute criminal cases of
Against tax protest
Just Like Larry
Even if the arguments are totally
Larry's attorney keeps going and remember this is his attorney talking about
He says and now I will say something that I've been saying for many months
Larry Williams
Wisecrack
Not crazy in the sense
That he was insane but crazy in the sense that he believed things that were simply wrong about the meaning of the
The code about the application of the tax laws about how words are defined and what words mean in the internal revenue
Avenue code
Which counts as a legitimate defense
Because of the statute of limitations
Larry was only on trial for three years of not paying.
Larry's lawyer went on to point out that while Larry had made a lot of money in those ears
He also lost a lot
One thing it turned out his secretary had been embezzling money from him on top of that
Larry lost over $1000000 to not one but
To investment scams
And a Ponzi scheme
My wallet I was allowed to write all those losses off
Honest taxes
His lawyer said at the end of the day he didn't actually have much income
In the end after 3 days of trial the prosecutors offered Larry a plea deal
Which Larry took
Larry agreed to plead guilty to three misdemeanors and pay a $50,000 fine
We should point out that that is just for the crime of failing to pay his taxes
For the trial started Lariat Rd
Pay the back taxes for all the years not covered by the trial
And that amounts to $600,000
Text Winnie I didn't file
Still after years of flouting the law Larry Williams left the courtroom that day
A free man
Oh my gosh she don't know how good that felt
Larry says the experience change that we thought about tax
I understand that the tax protest argument
Is wrong
Or if it's correct it isn't going to be validated any court of law so it doesn't matter to losing battle
So you got to
Buckle up to the barn
Pay your taxes
Do you feel any guilt
I don't understand the question
That that you should have been paying
I did pay I pay a lot of money in taxes
It's true he did
Eventually
The US system for collecting income tax a lot of it is based on
Well people think of the IRS watching our every move
The truth is the IRS only has the resources
Tiny tiny fraction of all the
The whole system is based on what sometimes called voluntary
Which means it is up to each person to figure out
What tax rules apply to them
And calculate how much they're supposed
One consequence of that
It's People Like Larry
Will dig through our super complicated tax code and all these old court cases
Looking for any argument that will let them legally not pay their income
Especially because of the whole thing ends up in court
You can just say
I didn't know
Eventually the IRS got so fed up with hearing all these terrible arguments
That they made a list of them and put them up on their website
When I checked this morning they were 44 of them
It's actually no illegal to use any one of these arguments in
Frivolous argue
And if you try to use one you can get fined $25,000
Frivolous by the way is an actual legal term someone explain to me that it's a judge's way of saying basically
You're drunk
Go home and sober up I'm not talking to you right now
Larry Williams is finally paying his
He is moved to the US Virgin Islands in part he says for tax reasons
You get a lot of tax break
And
Let us know what you think you can send this email Planet Money and end
Npr.org or tweet us at Planet
Our episode today was produced by Jess Jiang and Nick Fountain special thanks to Mark pitcavage JJ macnab David cage
Johnson and Isaac Martin
I'm David kestenbaum and I'm Keith Romer
Thanks for listening