Support for NPR and the following message
Did come from servicenow
Making the world of work
Work better for me
They're cloud-based
Platform and solutions
Deliver digital workflow
Spell create
Great experi
Frances and unlock productivity for your Holcomb
More at servicenow.com
The 1970s
Where this very weird moment
Find an American economic
Industries were dying
It was an oil embargo
And by the end of the decade inflation was out of control
I kind of live through it and I totally remember the price of comic books going up
Like every month
I collected them for a few years and
I was paying $0.25 at the start and like a dollar twenty-five when I just gave up
And a little inflation
Is actually good for the economy
Army to 3%
But by 1980 inflation was at thirteen percent
Was making America
Crazy like
How do you decide whether to buy a new house or make a new Factory
If you don't know how much
Dollars going to be worth
A year from now
What's really interesting about ammoman
Like that is that the inflation is caused by all these different parts of the economy
But the power to do anything about it basically rests with one Institution
Federal Reserve Bank
America Central Bank
The bank that basically set interest rates
All of the other banks in the country
In 1979
The FED got a new chairman
Six foot seven
Cigar-chomping economy
Paul volcker
Volker new
There was one Surefire way to bring down in
Raise interest
Where are you
Exercises to improve.
Conditions in the long run
Volkers exercise was Raising interest rates to
Crazy level
20% of 20%
I guess it's something like that
Operation is not much fun
But in terms of if you got something the matter you better have the operation
High interest rates would make it expensive to borrow money
Consumers wouldn't spend as much
Businesses would invest as much
The economy with
Cool down
And of course it's the same idea Works in Reverse to
The FED lowers interest rates
Borrowings easier so
People and companies will spend and invest more in
Inflation goes up
Raise interest rates inflation goes down lower interest rates
If you're a central Banker that interest
It's it's kind of all you got
At least historically like
Boker
Is a very powerful tool
Invoker
Crank up interest rates to 20%
Can you change the entire economy
By 1983 inflation was down
Want to just about 3% millions of people's lives
Change
How many jobs there were
What you got paid
What stuff cost at the store all of it
Basically
Because Volker
Decided it should
But that trillion-dollar lever that is the single tool that Central Bankers can use to completely remake the Econo
It's not working the same way it used to and people really don't know why hello
Welcome to Planet Money on Bryant and I'm Keith Romer
Today on the show
We try to get to the bottom of this mystery
What has changed is Paul volcker time
It is making me interest rate lever act so strangely
It's a super nerdy macroeconomic question
But it is also equipped
It gets to the heart
How much things cost at the grocery store
How much money you take home in your paycheck
To answer this central question we go to the Center of Central Banking
Annual meeting in
In Jackson Hole Wyoming
Where the world's most powerful lever pullers are trying to figure out
What the hell is going on
Going
To the central bank is cover
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses
Design and build their own website
Using customizable lights
And features including e-commerce functionality
3 + mobile app
Squarespace also offers
Built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online price
Go to squarespace.com NPR
For free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
We should explain
Why the central bank
His conference is in Wyoming
Back in 1982
The organizers were trying to figure out
Where to get a hold of meeting that would attract
The big name in Central Bank
Paul Walker
And the only thing that balker love more than fighting inflation
And cigars I guess was fly fish
And apparently at the end of the summer Jackson Hole
Is the place
Bass Pro fly fish
So they put the conference there
Bokeh couldn't resist
He showed up
And even though he hasn't been there for years
Everyone's still goes out to Jackson Hole
So we sit around all day obsessing over wage stagnation
In the natural rate of on
Unemployment in the money supply so the chance to go to a central
Bankers conference
Who's like nerd fantasy can't we were totally in
Ladies and gentlemen welcome to Jackson Hole local * 1159 would like to thank
Thank you for flying with us today we hope you have a pleasant experience
It was such a pleasant experience it is gorgeous there and it's about a 45-minute drive through just beautiful
Straight to the conference it's a 45-minute drive if you don't stop every two miles
What about lunch it's just a Cunningham cabin
Fancy we got their teeth
There is the Jackson Lake Lodge
Giant Mountain Lodge smack in the middle
Grand Teton National
It has 60 foot windows that look out over the mountains
It's all wood beams and paintings of bighorn sheep
That's kind of nice because the Bankers Trust placed it was hard to get to but you know if you are obsessed with monetary policy
You could just basically show up which is
What we did we were not technically invited we were
We already invited
But now is open to the public
The lobby is filled with
Hikers
Families with the
The kids
And then
There are the central Banker
I mastergeorge I'm the president and CEO of the Federal Reserve Bank of Kansas City
The Kansas City fed they host this meeting every
And she's essentially the person who decides
What the conference is going to be about each year
So she's a pretty obvious place for us to start as we're trying to figure out what's going on
With the lever but talking to a central Banker is not like talking to your uncle
If your uncle's like all the economy's going to hell like nothing happen
Central Banker says that the economy actually will go to hell
So people like Esther George
Are understandably
Very careful when they talk to journalists
Bryant
If you can translate
What we've noticed is globally
The advance
Central banks
7 pudding
A lot of accommodation
Enter their economy
And yet not seen inflation
Rise
So that's George saying we're keeping interest rates low but inflation isn't going up The Way We Were
I tried to get her to give me her actual opinion about what was causing the lever to work funny
Not too much I want to be careful that I don't
Front run the conference that I don't influence the dialogue there that's pretty much her saying she is not going to answer you
In short the person who organize the conference
She's not about to explain what's wrong with
But it wasn't like she was the only person we
I mean we were in a conference filled with people
So the conference
Is held in a room just off the lobby called
The Explorers
Tablecloths
Chandeliers we hung out outside and we just watched as the endless stream of bankers
Can you buy all these like
Regional Federal
Academic heavyweight they were Central bankers
Iceland
Israel
South Africa
I run just walking up with a little plastic covered name
I'm super close to Jerome Powell
That would have not been a good idea
John Powell he is the chairman of the Federal Reserve
And according to Brian you're not allowed to touch you
I think it's a good guideline we also met
This guy Sean Sebastian in the lobby
I just talked to his fourth year coming
A whole Bank of photographers comes in and it's like the Oscars for
Economic nerd
Like us Sean
Not invited
But John is not here.
No he's actually here to protest
He's with a group called Fed Up
Clever name
The Covenant
I thought about it a lot and I'm on the fence about how clever.
Actually it up
Cuz it has fed but then the up just
Oh are they saying
They get means like you've had enough
You get it you see I would think if they took another swing out of there would be happy
Okay but
Protesting the Federal Reserve is not really like protesting your local school
There's a lot that we're not allowed
You're not allowed to have sign
They can hand out leaflets
Make a disturbance and I don't know like yeah they'll tell us what their definition of that is
The Deshawn is referring to of these
Pretty tough-looking dudes from the Federal Reserve police which is actually a
Special police force like the Secret Service
And they have these matching tan like fishing vests on and the earpieces it was like
Imagine the Secret Service went on this like 10 day fishing trip
That's what he said
Since the protesters aren't allowed to hold signs
I swear hand out leaflets
They come up with this kind of brilliant work around
They put their message
Right on the t-shirts are all where
And this
This is what I love about this
Even the protesters
Are in deep deep nerd mode
Like the front of their shirts say things like
Wordful employment
Nah ask me about my story
But the back
Is where the magic
Okay I don't have a side in this
But I have to admire that t-shirt
Percentile graph
On the bottom and has the years from 1950 to 2020
And it shows that productivity and hourly compensation has been diverging
Remarkably since 1980
Flat wages below Target inflation Rising e p o p
Look at the data
Talk to us
And the color scheme is nice
It's just a serious serious t-shirt
That graph
It's basically about how wages really haven't
Grown the way Economist expect
And wage growth
Is one of those things we were talking about before that's been behaving so weirdly in the economy
You always want to grab drone Palace
Don't do that part of Italy
Anagrams room
What you want
To grab drone
And say look at the graph
What is happy
But before we can ask Tyrone Powell or anyone else
Anything they close the doors on the Explorer
One of the Fed
Police fishing agent best guy steps
In front in the lobby goes back
To just hikers
And Planet Money reporters
And several dozen very very well-behaved protesters
Des Tucson
At this point we've got the lay of the land
And we know how this place
The go back to the lobby
And we start grabbing economist
Bankers Adda
Quickly as we can
Before the organizers ring the cowbell
It says the next session is starting the Explorer
The highlight of the conference is not the views
Or the antlers it's
The papers
Economic
And everyone keeps telling us
Dr. John Van reenen
Because his paper
It's the one
So I track him down
And we agreed to meet up later
In front of the giant stuffed grizzly bear just outside the Explorer
I'm John Van reenen I'm
Professor in the department of Economics MIT and the Sloan School of Management
Been raining paper has some really interesting
Today's big question everyone is here to solve
Why the interest rate lever isn't worth
He started by looking at how all these giant new company
Things like apple and Facebook
Amazon have been concentrating all of this power in
But I think
What's rhe surprised me when I first started looking at this
Is that mass increase of concentration
How to build faster than bows high-tech Market
But you also see it happening in
The majority of other markets
So you look at
You've got retail
Shipping thanking Healthcare Airlines insurance
Utilities
All consolidated
Actually happening
Across the wide range of sex
Sectors of the American economy
And all of these big new companies it might be
They're what make
Cantilever racks
We see this in a Century 3 Way
The first way is
Pricing
The Amazons and Walmart's of the world
The one thing they all do really really well
Is a furlough
Which we like
But those low prices are messing with how Central Bankers should even understand what inflation means
Back in Paul volcker's day
Prices going down
Might have meant that economy was in trouble
But now it might just mean these giant companies
Are getting more and more efficient
The second wave andrean says that the giant companies are making the economy Act
Weird is through borrowing
Used to be
To become a giant company the important thing was to
Build the best factories and buy the newest machines
But these days
The way you win is a company
Is by owning the best version of what Economist call intangible cap
Things like Patton
Software think about Walmart
Increase
How much school you think
Low-tax
Exacto
But will not start
Is that it's invested huge amounts of money
In building up Vasa
Software
Because Walmart is just a company would like a
Katana trucks and Warehouse
It's a company that's used all this technology
To get somewhere
Now it understands better than any other company
How to move these trucks around the warehouse is really really efficient
What about the truck
It's about how you move
And this is how it ties back to borrow
Another way that the interest rate lever is supposed to work
Is by making it cheaper or more expensive for businesses to grow
But companies may not need as many loans to build factories and warehouses that they used to
And that means that the lever won't work on businesses
The way it used to
The third wave and weed and says big companies might be messing with the levers
Is wages
And that one
Might be on us
So you going to think about so you
Google
Google dominates search and I were to use a Google I would like to search for things
So why is it the Google so Donuts
It's been raining says it's because we as consumer
Made it so
Right when I want to looks
Something up
I'm not asking geez I'm not going to be
I'm using Google because Google works fast easy
Amazon if I need something like a new garlic press I'm not going to go look on 10th
Isport
There's this other thing that happen
We're going to Google and we're going to Amazon
To get information
Buy something
We're also giving them
All this information
About
What we want and how we
Think and that actually allows Google and Amazon to make their products even more what we
The Kranks is kind of virtuous circle this kind of chicken and egg
Where buy if you can get to be a kind of a bigger
Open your kind of platform
You could cut a window most in timeout
As consumers
We're actually being pretty well served by all these giant
At least for now
But by all of us picking Amazon to be the company
For buying
Everything
We're actually changing the job
How much workers get paid
Which brings us back to the protesters nerdy green tea
The ones with the graph that shows how wages haven't grown all that much
Since the early nine
I showed John Van reenen
Photo of Fisher
Yes
So this is a
A famous
Take the statistics graph is a famous girl from the 6
It says
Flat wages below target inflation
Rising Appalachia
Which I believe means
Employments
Population ratio
Fraction of people jobs in the population
Veteran says
The graph is basically right
Bigger and bigger share of profits has been going to all these
Shipping companies
Smaller and smaller share
Has been going to work
It's amazing you can fit this on the T-shirt
And remember
4 years
A lot of Economist. Wages would rise with inflation
That was something that they could really control and count on
This is one of my angel puzzles and
I can only assume social science
Why you seem respectful to The Baby Show
So this is something we're still trying to understand the need of my post review
Is that there's not a single explanation
The protesters Sean
His theory
Is that all of this is because of
Decline in Union
Been reading things that might
Be part of it but not all of it
Is another story which is an economist open up Smith
Monopsony is like the less famous cousin to Monopoly
Imaginext just one company natal
Nobody else
Is around with higher pay
And the company can pretty much decide how much it wants
To pay workers
They can take it or leave it
That's when I was
Even if you come and go Union
What larger firms in particular
I can do
Is that can actually drive down
Wages
Below the competitive level s
Whether it's because of unions or whether it's because
Monopsony
Either way
Workers end up with less money
And that
That matters the lever
Interest rates have been low
In unemployment
Has come way down its less than 4%
But wages
Wages of knock on a company should be
Be competing with each other to get all these new workers
Now last month we did see a pickup and wages
But in the long run nothing like what a decade would
Crazy low interest
Straits should have coffee
Prashant Sebastian and the other protesters
The solution seems
You just keep interest rates low
Run the economy hot and wages will eventually pick
Don't worry so much about inflation
A lot of these people at the fed or still shape
Bye
The trauma of the 1970s inflation when inflation was actually quite
It shapes their entire worldview exactly why we're here and here in Jackson Hole is because they
Worship
Play poker like a God and so we're here we're here in Jackson Hole because
Whatever 40 years ago he decide you want to go fly fishing
There was only so much we could
I talking to protesters and professor
We wanted to talk to somebody who would actually had to make a decision about pulling the
My name is raghuram Rajan
Raghu for short
Rajan is a professor
But he used to run India Central Bank
He and I sat on a bench under a pine tree
Looking out over the
And he told me
Sean Swayze actually made a lot of sense.
People are not satisfied with the quality of the
C1 finish up what if all those jobs are in a few phones
What restaurant have good
Still Rajan knows that Central Bankers don't have the luck
Adjust
Keying in on one element in the
I'm trying to fix that
Wages interest rates
Inflation prices
They all affect one another
Even if we're less sure
What this kind of conference
Highlights is weird
Uncertain about
What really is going on
Central Bankers have the dog with making decisions
When everything is clouded with uncertainty
And it's not an easy job
What might be hardest about the job of central Bankers isn't deciding whether or not.
Pull the interest rate lever
It's deciding what description of the economy is true
On the one hand
It could just
That this is one more case of economic trend
Taking a long time to sort themselves
All of this weirdness it could just be a blip
After a decade or two
Wage growth and inflation and everything else it might just start tracking the way it always did
If that's the explanation
It might be that the liver is work
It's just working more slowly than we want
But on the other hand
Maybe everything really has changed
A lot of economist
Think these giant companies
Have remade
The way the lever works
And our take away after spending three days with all these sent
Bankers
Place
Is that the central Bankers don't really know
And so for now
They're making these
Tiny little moves with a lever
And just
Hoping it will all
This message comes from NPR sponsors
Squarespace
Squarespace allow small business
Design and build their own webs
Using customizable layout
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobile a
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online price
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR
Hard to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
We'd like to thank Bill Medley and everyone else at the Kansas City fed for letting us crash their conference
If you have a secret meeting we should be at email us
Planet Money at npr.org or find us on Facebook and Twitter this week we're posting some photos of those Fed Up
T-shirts on her Instagram so you can try to figure them out yourself we are at Planet Money
Special thanks to our internal Isa S car say it is
Is her last day
Thank you
This episode was produced by Alexi Horowitz Ghazi with editing by Karen.
Planet Money supervising producer is Alex goldmark Brian that you are Planet money's editor and Yorkie drummer
Thanks for listening
I'm from the West I know what historic cabin look like it looks like some split logs and
Can you go inside and there's like a rusty pot and then somebody has like a Little House on the Prairie fan
Missy and you work through that and get back in your car and you're still not we were going
If I childhood