You are never supposed to do this and we would normally never do this
But we're going to start this episode by reading
Someone's Social Security
This
Is the most infamous of
Security number in the world and weirdly
The most
Popular
Social security number
Okay here we go
Our apologies in advance 2
Hilda schrader whitcher
Of Lockport
York
Is her number
Is 078
I feel terrible feel bad for Voldemort like
Out loud
If it's teenage
Your social security number is this unique part of you that you are
Supposed to guard
With your life
Because it is your life somebody can use it to help steal your identity charge a bunch of
Xboxes
Is the credit cards in your name to steal your tax refund but that is not the story of how we got Hilda Witcher
Chris number know this story as you may guess from the name Hilda
Happened a while ago
In the 19th
There was a manufacturer
Of wallets
I am so sorry to interrupt
We should probably entered
Okay
This is Carolyn Puckett longtime employee of the social
Castration and how many years did you work there
I work for social security for 37 years
Back in the 90
1930s Social Security numbers were these brand new things
People didn't
Really understand what they were
Or how you
You got one
Beer invented as part of the social
Security program
You have taxes taken out of your paycheck
And in the Social Security Administration would keep
Keep track of all that money
Using your brand new social
Security number
So 1938
A wallet manufacturer in law
Lockport New York decided to promote its product by showing how a social security card with it into the wallet
But instead of putting some random number on a piece of paper
The head of the company used
A very realistic
Can use the number of his secretary
Hilda
Trader
07 8
This wallet containing Hilda's number
Was sold at Woolworths
Thousands of people
Who bought the wallet
And then got very
A lot of people when they got that
Card they started using it as their own number
I started working under that number
Why
Well you know they didn't really understand how you got a card they didn't understand the numbering system and so
People adopted this
As their social security number
This reminds me of if it's like buying a like a picture frame from a store and just going like
Hey I like
Beautiful couple that's in the frame
Is this
On my mantle
Exactly where it's like getting a frame and being like Oh
This must be my family
I should marry
Cool it took the Social Security Administration
Decades to clean up this
Matter fact the peak year that it was used was 1943
And at that time they were 5755 people
Still using that
As their own social security number and manufacturer as late as 1977 there were still 12
People
Using that social security number
Hill Golf Course
Got a new social security number
Panda in an interview
She was quoted as saying
I can't understand
How people
Canby
So stupid
Hello and welcome to Planet Money on Robert Smith I'm Kenny Malone
And in all seriousness
Who was Morse
People who thought you got a social
Security number issued
Do you throw wallet
Woolworths
Or a nation that decided to base your entire personal financial life
On a 9 digit
Today in the show we're going to answer a question that we've had for a long time
How did this happen
How did we fix
This particular system of 9 numbers
Hard to remember
Easy to steal
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses
To design and build their own website
Using customizable layout
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
Squarespace also offer
Bridge built and search engine optimization
To help you develop an online presence
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial and when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
The social security number was invented at a single meeting
A gathering of what we have to assume
Where the greatest numerical mind
Regeneration
Never be fair we know almost nothing about the
But we did ask
Did this meeting have a name like with this like the big number confab
People fly in from around the
Probably did not fly in from around the country since they were government agencies and they tended to be headquartered
In Washington DC
True that is our friend Carolyn pocket again
Stickler for facts
When Carolyn worked at the Social Security Administration
And she wrote the story
How the social
Social security number wound up
Controlling r
Yes and of course that was never the intention when the social security number was invented
Would you like to hear a little bit about the history
I think we would
It starts with
The signing of the Social Security Act on August 14th 1935
And this social security measure
Gibbs at least some protection
230 millions of asceticism
Franklin Delano Roosevelt 1935
Any idea of Social Security was pretty
We got your back
All workers would
Would pay into the system
And then when you can no longer work
Some money comes back to you or to your family
Now all they had to do was find a way to track
Every
Single
Worker in the United
There were already some social security type systems in Europe so the first thing they did was to contact the
The experts in Europe
To see what they suggested
Am I pretty much
Suggested that it just couldn't be done
Europe was like that is at
Terrible idea
You can't track every single person every single year for the West
Of their lives
Its 1935 we don't have iPhones yet in America was like yeah
Okay you're up you know what
Hold my drink
Everybody sit down
Please sit down
We bring to order the big number confab
Of 1935
The following is a re-creation but the story is based on real ideas that were on the table
Get the character
All right everybody
Yelp says it cannot be
Be done
Let's show them how we do things in the United States
Of America
Of course everyone
What yeah okay
So how do we tell everyone apart
Super easy
Let's just use everybody's names Everybody's Got a Name
Technically
That was true
What was wrong with your name
Well as you know Robert Smith they're probably a whole lot of Robert Smith
Matter fact
Back in the 1930s there was
An association of Fred Smith in New York City because there were so many of them they were getting each
Each other's mail and they set up a little Association so they could have
Change mail and get everybody straight
Alright I'm across that
The floor
Fingerprint
And everybody's like yeah fingerprints unique everybody's got those but of course that was
Connected in everybody's mind with criminals
Right
Every American worker getting hauled into a government building for fingerprinting would look
Okay fine
Odd numbers
Numbers
Human license
Play we'll just do number
Nine of them
Dashes in there
Number Dash before numbers
Who could possibly object that they're just numbers
And of course you know that somebody in the back
Have the room at this
Stands up
A reading from The Book of Revelation
Chapter 13
Verse 18
Here is wisdom
Let him that hath understanding count
The number of
The Beast
For it is the number of a man and his number
Is 600
Threescore and six
Six six six
That was knocking
Not for the first three numbers
Social security has never and never plans to use 6 6
Six steps of the Social Security Administration didn't want to be accused of
Handing out the market
The Beast
And in fact being a sign of the end times
Alright let's wrap up
This confab we all agree not number is no mark of the beast
First three numbers will be
Geographic code
We will later stop doing but let's just do it for now
Meeting adjourned
And that is a very dramatic version of how we ended up with
A social
The next hurdle
Was handing those numbers out
Sure they had to figure out what number would go to which person and then help
People would remember what their number was
At first it was a suggestion to give everyone their number on little metal
Dog tag
Looks like they have in the military
Which would have taken a literal tons
Of metal
So they went with a little thick paper car they were going to send out the
And remember this isn't a huge deal you just needed this number to track your earnings and and that's basically it
Like any good
Numerical system you start with number 1 or in this case
At first they wanted to give this lowest number away is
Like an honor
They offered it to a guy who played a huge role in helping Social Security get setup but he's like no thank you
Some other bigwig turned it down as well
And so it landed on the pile and was
Headed out like any other old number
That 0 0 1 0 1 0 0 0 1
Went to a Grace Owens in New Hampshire
We know what her job was she needed the social
Security number for
I don't really know anything about her
Other than she got the lowest number
Sounds like the job
To Intrepid reporters
Will find it okay
We started to look into this
Who was this Grace Owen
Who got the super special really easy to remember Social Security
She died decades
To go but
Hello hi this is Vivian
We were able to track down Vivian Clark
I only knew Grace
After I married
Her nephew
In 1961
Vivian is I guess you'd call her at
Json lot of Grace Owen didn't remember much about
Grace smokes like a chimney
Vivian said there is another cousin who could no more
Hello
It is
Pamper do and I am the niece of
Grace Dorothy Owen
Pam says her aunt Grace never had kids
She worked as a secretary
Was married once got divorced remarried and became
Grace Owen muzzy
And Pam remembers that
Yuan from a young age
This lowest number was a big deal she remembers her dad telling her about it
And I also remember my dad telling me
That she went on the show I've got a
I've got a secret was this show where a panel of celebrities
Tries to
To figure out why you're sort of famous
And this is actually the only tape we could find a Grace Owen muzzy
What's your name where you from
My name is Grace muzzy
Concord New Hampshire
I'm as much as a secret with you whisper to me and will
Show TV
And that's pretty much all she said she thoroughly
Stump the panel
Oh
Take me to lowest number to complicated don't worry about it
And the number is 401
At this moment they are holding up
A giant
Copy
Of her social security number for a national television audience
Like it was no big deal
Which it wasn't yet
But if someone was watching this on live television
Is ensure they could like steel gray social security number
But probably the worst thing that they could do
Is use that
At their job and then
Their social
Security taxes would go into Grace's account
Which I guess in that case with me and the
Grace would make more money
Social Security
Thank you very much
A carton of Winston's thanks for being with you
She must have loved those when he does look very happy in the tape I will say
The answer to some trivia quiz
The woman with the lowest social security number
What I saw in the tape was
Foreshadowing of something that was about to
You don't just get a number and file it away
In some weird way you are your social
Greece was considered by the world an interesting person
Because she had an interesting
Until we know that eventually this number would take over our lives
How exactly did that happen and when
Yahoo I mean who's responsible
Will the federal government to some extent
As early as 1943 there was a
Presidential executive
Order a presidential executive order that says
Look
If you're a federal agency
And you need a new records
Stop do not invent a whole new one
Take a look
At that thing they've got going on over at Social
Security pretty sweet
Money just use that
When did the IRS start using it
For taxes 1962
Around the same year the social security number becomes the ID number
For federal employees
Medicare starts using it for enrollment in
Veterans Administration started using it in 1966
Okay how about the department of
Department of Defense started using it in 1969 as the is the military to invitation number
Food stamps 1977 Federal loans 19
N82 HUD programs
And just one after another
Driver's license
Federal workers compensation marriage license
The social security number becomes so broadly use
The by default
It becomes our national identity
At any point did the people who work for the Social Security Administration
The people who
Went to all this trouble to invent
This number for legitimate
Small Focus tree
Can we tell everyone to just knock it off like
You're going to ruin this number
Will the Social Security Administration does not have the legal authority to restrict the use of the social security number
Are they still don't
So there was no way so so so
Security codes
Stop people from using it for what they wanted to
As all these agencies in
Businesses started using the number
What was the Tipping Point where it went from
And innocuous number that really didn't mean a ton
To something that
Contained your entire identity
I suspect when ones
Credit history was tied in with the social security number
Your credit
We're just basically history of how often you have
Your bills on time whether you are a
Worthwhile risks
For someone
To extend credit or to lend you money
Decades
Credit reporting agencies have been Gathering all this information all this dirt on you
But all the sudden with a social
Security number
We could tie it all together and bringing so much more information about your life
That one mistake
Follow you
For decades
Until your social security number wasn't just tied to
Government benefits
Contributions
It was tied to
Credit cards to loans to the mistakes you
That's fine
As long as you know there isn't some
Conglomerate
With
Hundreds thousands millions of these it
Could you hack one day
Welcome
To the echo
Equifax automated security freeze
The Equifax hack we did a whole episode about the history of credit bureaus and the Equifax hacking
You didn't get a chance to hear it check it out and you will
Here just how bad
Now to be fair I have personally noticed
Over the last decade or so
But there are fewer people putting my social security number on
Random forms are on my medical insurance card
People seem to be a little bit more respectful of the
Yeah in fact States and the federal government have
Tried to scale back the use but
The damage is done
No chapter asking
If you could go back
And we designed the cyst
Is there a better way to do it
And she said
No
Know the social security number
Is design fine
For what it was supposed to
But the problem clearly was that the United States sort of needed some
Kind of national
But didn't want to do it
Not with the picture and the fingerprint and all of the things you would actually need
Correctly until we find American tradition we have fast
The Pastels the closest thing that we had
9 digits
The carry the bureaucratic dreams of an entire nation
Rather than getting upset with Associates
Carolyn almost seem
Sort of like wistful about
And we do now is you Social Security numbers to children when they're born
It actually does
Track you
From your
First day on the planet
So your death
They say that everyone dies alone and when I'm on my deathbed I don't know if my kids will be there or if my wife
Still be around
But I do feel hard knowing that I'm going to be laying there with
My old companion
Robert
With no is it is that is this your real number it is my real number
When we come back I've got a secret about you by wind
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online press
Fence and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layouts
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobiledit
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase
Just have a website or domain
Achromatic Recreation of the invention of the social security number was Loosely inspired
Play the comedian Gary gulman
A special thanks this week to Janice Brown of the
Cow Hampshire blog and
The Listener are regular for sending as an email
With the wallet story we
Our planet money at npr.org
This week's episode was manufactured by Sally Helm Lena Richards Alex goldmark and Bradford
I'm Kenny Malone I'm Robert Smith
Thanks
Intern Aviva dekornfeld
Managed to track down the incredible audio
I've got a secret I never thought I would share the voice
Have a great Monday but we did
But there were some negotiations about how much of that audio we
In fact they
Required us to license a minimum
Of one minute
What you heard in the story was
Just about
35 seconds but we had to pay for a nanny
Entire minutes so let's get our money
Two ladies and gentlemen
Come back in time with us
To the year 1950
B7 you settled down on the Chesterfield with a mug of Ovaltine and a pack of winstons
You click on the old tele
And this is a very tough when I'll tell you so I'll give you an additional clue
It's something that she has is the first-of-its-kind
And this I've got a secret panel they
Just cannot crack
Mrs. Grace
Muzzy
From Concord new
Is it in the animal is it for animals
No
Love it more more
This thing was thought up as a thought about you
Oh no we're running out of time come on Vine
No
3 seconds left
2 seconds left one second