When did you first get a weird package
About 3 years ago
This is Selena Salas
Chicago
And she can remember
Package came on a Wednesday sort of late in the afternoon
My actually I was
Working at a restaurant so I had just woke up she always
Go out from restaurant afterwards late at night so I was a little hungover
And I ain't
Just walked over to my mailbox and
There was this
Little brown package sitting in there perfectly
But she had an
Ordered it
It looked like it had shipped
From China
Because it's best she could tell
Most of the label was in Chinese
So I open the box
And
Justice watch wrapped in some plastic
But like the cheapest watch you could have match
Plastic like maybe spray painted gold or something it wasn't even working
So I need like food
Maybe my mom sent me this is a joke to like
Time to grow up get a watch
Good mom troll exactly
She checked not from her mom
But then
3 months later another package
To Selena
Apparently from China
Not something she ordered
And inside is
Like a
Braided friendship bracelet in first grade
Selena head
No explanation for this and there was nothing she could do
Was getting weird packages
And they kept
3rd package comes about 4th package
Comes about lights package
Was
One of them had a crap
Ring inside she got a headphone case but no head
There was
Silly Putty Silly Putty I completely forgot about that when did that come that came after the piggy bank
Yep the other was a piggy bank as well
All of the weird junk
Pill Dan
Comparison
To The Fuzzy keychain
I think it was trying to mock like mink but it look like raccoon and it just was it was terrible
Yes it was
Terrible I opened it in like
But it dropped to the
Lauren it was that keychain should have never seen the light of day
These ghosts packages full of
Seemingly random John
There reports of people getting these all over the country all over the world
There was a woman in London who got not one
But to fake Nike sweats
There was a couple of your Boston who got a flashlight and an outdoor TV cover and woman on Long Island
You got some compression socks and a cell phone
Why are people being haunted by ghost package
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Nick fountain
And I'm Kenny Malone today on the show
We go
Ghost
Package hunt
We learn how that crappy fuzzy
The keychain is a sign of the end times
Or at least the end of trusting five star review
It All Leads us
To one of the most elaborate internet schemes we have ever heard of
Support for this podcast in the following message come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org
This whole ghost package thing
May sound a little bit
And that's because
A version of this same phenomena
Shut up
Surprising way
On a really
High stakes
Public stage
Hello New York
This is from 2015
It's an elaborate opening bell ceremony for the New York Stock
Celebrating the Alibaba company
Which organ public about a year old
Have you been in a cave for the last four years Alibaba is a massive company
That includes a bunch of e-commerce site some of them
Are like Marketplace
But connect sellers and buyers
Alibaba wechat
Huge deal when it decided to go public because it was a huge company
How huge you may ask
Well
Here is the best part of any IPO my favorite part
Of IPOs
Prospectus Ali Baba's prospectus yet so a prospectus is when you go public you have to file this
Big
With a cc
And it says basically
All the good stuff is going on in your company and all the bats
As well you lay it all out
Yeah we come mazing juicy stuff and inside here
Here are some eye-popping number
We've got millions of sellers using our sites hundreds of millions of buyers hundreds of billions of dollars
Worth of stuff sold
Intercourse
Is good stuff
In this respect
But then there's also this one strange line
It's in the potential risk section of the document
And it says quote
Sellers May engage in
Tisha's or Phantom transactions
With themselves or collaborators
In order to artificially inflate their search results
Rankings
And you can imagine like a collective
What
Phantom transaction
Somebody needs to explain this
Hey Mark are you in the office right now
I am
Is it like 10:30 there
What is 11 p.m.
Still in the office
In Beijing
We called Mark natca
Can because he's with this company called marbridge
Consulting and
Has been watching the Ali Baba story from the beginning
And Mark says Alibaba had no choice but to bring up this Phantom package thing
When it went public
Because it could be a big problem for investors
Yeah like sure Ali Baba had
250 billion dollars worth of sales on
Sites
But some of those sales
May have been
Completely fictional transaction
How many
Nobody seemed to know
Because hidden somewhere in those transactions was a phenomenon
An internet scheme really
Known
As brush
Brushing is just
Walmart gaming assist
Like what it what game is being
Normally
I'm a customer and I
Order something in the
Vendor send it to me
Then I rate the vendor based on your quality of the product delivery time
Mark is describing here
A basic
Verified reviews
Which only allows reviews from people who actually bought a Prada
Verified reviews are obviously used
Consumers but Mark says e-commerce site also use these as a way to rank the vendors who are selling
Meaning that you later
It's somebody
Some other customer goes and searches children's toys
United company any children's toy
Retailer that got high number of
Positive reviews
Which show up higher in search ranking
How important
Is this for a vendor
Crucial
Absolutely crucial why is that
Because there's an ocean
Avengers
Each of these platforms for any given product category
So
If your company is showing up on page 20
Might as well not be showing up
Answer to make sure that they didn't get buried under the ocean
Petition some very clever
Figured out a way
The game the rankings
This is the technique
The people call brush
Engineering fake perch
In hopes of boosting your search
Do you I mean have you ever talked to any
Like people that did this any brochures
We have not
Do you think if we tried to talk to brushes they would talk to us
I'll be at your side if you have a
Fluent Chinese speaker
On the ground here
You might get them to talk to you but
Could be difficult
Hi
Hi Sandy Sandy Way
Fluent Chinese speaker
On the ground there is a colleague of ours who works out of
NPR's Beijing
We've heard
A term that used called brushing have you ever heard that
Tickets a translation
The Chinese word is
Chardon it could be translated literally as
Brushing the record
I like cleaning up the reputation
Yes
Tennis is the site she's familiar with
Airbrushing allegedly happened
Just called taobao
It's people in China selling all kinds of stuff to other
Close food
Madison
Flowers everything
You can either rent
Boyfriend
Shenzhen taobao
How do I send boyfriend flowers
And she's heard that brushing is still a thing on that
We're wondering if you could
Try to find us some people who are brushing
You said I think I can do that for you
Awesome great
Sandy went off to see if she could find some
We knew it was a long shot so in the meantime
We decided to take a look at
Into a couple of other angles
I hate Sandy but within a day
Sandy was back on the phone with us again
We apologize for sending you on a wild-goose chase but
It's okay to
Did you find any brochures
Yes no kidding
After the break a real life brusher shares her secrets
Support for this podcast in the following message come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities to help ensure a brighter future for America
Is children more information is available at aecf
. org
A couple of caveats
Before we meet
Our brochure
This scheme
Got a lot of attention
Is it came up around the Ali Baba
IPO but
We talked to a lot of people about this and the general consensus
Versions of brushing are almost certainly happening in different ways
On different e-commerce
Sites
If there's a way to game a review system you can almost guarantee that someone is trying to do
But because Alibaba is
Is often associated with this
We did reach out to them for the story
And they gave us a statement that said
Impart
They have quote
No tolerance
Thanks for brushing
And that they've made huge strides
Infighting it however
It seems that it is still happening somewhere maybe on their sides maybe not
Because our NPR calling Sandy found a brochure in less than
Hello karaoke
Yeah yes
I guess this is my Hutchins by chance
She lives near Shanghai and works in Tech but
In her free time she
Takes jobs as a brochure
When was the first time
That
You got one of these jobs
Okay
Knee
Decent
When she was in college
But she can't remember
Which year
Exactly
Chances she gets about a buck for every brush
She helps out with a ton of money but it's
What kind of more fun for her stinks of it more like a hobby
So she does 10 to 15 of these Aman
And the way that works she says is that first
She goes into this chat
How it in attack prove someone will post a day
Information of the test
We need help
Making a fake purchase
This is
Usually posted by a vendor or on behalf of
Vendor
And there will be instructions
To go and buy a specific item from a specific
What sort of items
Have you
Bought and given reviews
Beautiful
Clothing
And shoes
Clothing and shoes
This is a completely fraudulent purchase but in order for the transaction to help with ranking
It has to look like a real world transaction
E-commerce sites try to spot this kind of funny
Business
And The Crushers
Try to hide this funny
Business by making fake purchases look
As normal as humanly
And so chin and her fellow brushes
Do all of these things to make themselves look
Real
Like everyday indecisive online shop
The holy Stone
And randomly clicking to
There's a difference
Links scroll down page
Go back
And then click the right thing
O so that it looks like you're searching
For the product
Yes
Omad and that is to make it look
Like a legitimate purchase
Sometimes the process is even more complicated like
Click around a bit favorite a couple things even talk to a customer service rep and then
Buy the item
But of course
This is not going to look like a verified purchase
Unless something get mailed to somebody
So the final steps of brushing her that she actually pays for the product
To get reimbursed later
And then the seller is actually going to ship something
But not the thing that she and pretended
Dunhill watches
It wasn't me
Scarves
Socks
T-shirts
Shoes or something like that
Issues
In other words what gets shipped
Are boxes full
Of seemingly random
Stuff
Which
Brings us all the way back
To where we started
The Fluffy keychain The Fluffy keychain with after the friendship bracelet
From Chicago
Then piggy banks fifth package was Silly Putty 6 would be the ring
And unlike and you're sure you didn't sign up
For some obscure subscription box service
I don't even know what what would connection
The assortment of things is just so odd
I can't even
Thing 2
Who why who when where why
Why me
Why do things
Who are you and where is it coming
Okay so by Design
He's brushing skis are very dim
Call to track
Our best guess for what is happening to Selena
Is it her name
And her dress are being used in an international version of the brush
So I have a question about that
Did you have you ordered random stuff from China before
Yes
I used to order phone cases a lot while I was in college
This address
Okay
That's a clue always all a dollar and I thought it was the greatest deal ever like yeah I had to wait a month for that
To get here but
I have a cool phone case and then it turns out those phone cases break instead of your phone so
So I found it like it's not even worth it and
Stop buying those
You could imagine that Salinas address would be especially useful to a brush her she has
Buttstuff Direct
China before her dress
Clearly still active
She looks like a real person
Kumite make this purchase
As we looked at this whole ghost package thing
We started to wonder
Who exactly is the victim here
There are arguably victims there are
Investors who buy into a company where
It's not entirely clear how many transactions are real
And how many are
Are fake does the sellers any sites that
Actually play by the rules
And then get
Be out by the vendors who were brushing
And then there are the online Shoppers you and me
Who think verified reviews light come on at least this is something I can
Entrust
But it turns out
Not always
One person who doesn't
Exactly feel like a victim here is Selena Sala
The Phantom packages were little
Creepy at first
But now she looks forward to them
Ensure she says d
Piggy bank broke almost immediately The Watch
Never work to begin with
Park at destroyed the
The furry keychain
But there was a ring that ring
The real metal ring
I like a little silver ring
Or
It's at the CID looks over but
Right
Right I actually I'm wearing it right now actually
I've been wearing it and it has not turned my finger green yet
So
Yeah
Then a few can hear that but is there
Anything mysterious in your world that you would like us to look into please let us know we are Planet Money at NPR.
RG Today Show was produced by Alexi Horowitz Ghazi
Are supervising producer is Alex goldmark
Bryant or status
The show thanks this week to Alexandra Lee Young and a very very special thanks to Sandy Way who
Who helped us
The story
There will come remember to get me five star evaluation
I'm Kenny Malone and I'm Nick fountain
Thanks for listening