We thought that we had heard every kind of story about a dying small town trying to say
And then we went
To Colquitt Georgia
Leaving water in car
Oh it's humid I like it
Coco has a population of about 2000
It claims to be the mayhaw capital of the world
Met high is a kind of berry that people like to make jam out of
And this city feels like it pops
Straight out of a book by the children's author
Like
Colquitt
Is built around this town square it's got the County hall right there in the middle
You walk 5 minutes
And there's the Town Newspaper
Hello
Inside is the editor and publisher by himself
Finishing up that week paper
Are you how many people work here
Man one mole
Wow
Wow you don't know what a small community un
We learn and then you walk another five minutes and you're at the Town Firehouse
Cheap
Their Chief Tully at his desk by himself working on some firefighting
I mean that's what I was doing before y'all come in I'm having to a Jew
Eman you walk another 5 minutes and there's the town bed and breakfast
Where the manager is saying welcome
And also
Your room is haunted are you able to record player
Play sometime
We can do it
Go Smith Ali the record mostly nice
Has allegedly thrown silverware at
Anyway
It is in the lobby of this bed and
What's that we meet the woman we
We came to call
Joy
Brought you all goodie bag
Goodie bags choices
Joy Jinks is Colquitt biggest booster
Cancel course she has brought us local honey
And local peanuts in these
Beautiful flowers
Camellia
That's a beautiful that came out of my yard
Welcome to call Quinn
Both Noel and I thought Joey was in her purse
60s
She is in fact in her eighties
She just has this like
Vibrant
Giant smile and a head full
Of what someone describes me as
Bright red
Little Orphan Annie hair
Joy was a social worker she was born and raised and retired and Coke
Emma's place is everything to her
The way she talks about Colquitt
She says things that sounds like but are not
Quotes from like some famous Southern novel
I lived my childhood sitting in a mimosa tree reading
Sitting in a mimosa tree
Pretty curtains
But since Joy was a little girl she's watched Colquitt died the same slow death as a lot of America's rural City
Starting around World War II
Farm equipment. Better
Low-skilled farming jobs started to die
Pen manufacturer
Factories went
Overseas
Colquitt sewing play
Plant closed down
Population
Shrunk
Is that undercurrent of well are we going to
Survive you know what is
Future for this town
Yeah that must be scary feeling
Feeling like
Abdomen and death
The stores are boarded up and no no cars parked
They know people
And then Joy Jinks
Stumbled across a bizarre way
4 Colquitt Street
The town would write
Stage and star in
An original musical hello and welcome
The planet money I'm Kenny Malone the idea modern idea let's build a town
Town around me
But 25 years ago before the books in the TED Talks
It was just a crazy idea
Play on the show what happened to a
Tiny peanut farming town where things got so bad
They brought in the big city director to try and save themselves
With music
And awarding at there is
One very bad
Swear words in it
In fact
That word almost
Ended
Degrate Colquitt Georgia
Your experiment
Support for this podcast
Cast in the following message come from the Annie E Casey
Sea Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf
. org
Around 1990
Joy Jinks went to leadership
Retreat in Upstate New
Was totally unrelated to theater
But at this retreat
Was none other
Then Richard
Gear my name is Richard Owen gear and I use my middle name so you don't think you're talking to Pretty Woman actor
I mean to be fair I don't know what pretty woman actress middle name is
Yeah if it isn't Owen
Richard Owen Gere is also an actor
But he's primarily a theater director
Are people disappointed when you show up and you're not that Richard Gere thank you you just stolen my favorite line which
I'm a disappointment wherever I go and they laughed just like that
And we're off to the
Back in 1990 Richard Gere was a grad
He was getting his PhD in performance studies you know like a fancy theater degree that comes
The splash of anthropology
And that is why grads do
Was working through it
Efficient
Really
That he was dying to try out
He thought
If a group
Full of non perfect
Collected their communities
In those stories on
Onstage that this
Could be
A powerful
And especially from a part of the world that was thought to be a throwaway
That's what the rest of the country thought
And I knew if they could see something radically different
That's theater
Is Richard Gere's at this retreat in New York
He's talking about his
Is Big Ideas
Is when this woman
Here's him
Incomes up to
She said that
Her community
Was dying and
Her community wasn't able to get industry to come in and we try to get some factories in here that
Catwoman of course was Joyce
But we realize nobody was coming here
But we wanted to do something to celebrate who we are is the people left behind
Words that I spoke to her other than hello or something like that
I said
If you do a play about
Your community stories
I'd love to direct it
Now it is important to know that at this point
Joy was not thinking of this project as an economic driver
In her mind this was a celebration of the people of coffee
But you were
Sticking it out in a city that was being left behind
Sir Richard fluid to Tallahassee Florida
Enjoy pick them up at the airport and they drove to call
It literally crashed into a log truck on their way there they were okay
And the main reason for this trip was that Julie needed Richard to go before the town Arts Council to get support to do this
No Richard pitch
Siri
Was very simple
We're going to collect oral histories
We're going to Stage those as vignettes
But you know
Richard was a grad student
And
He kept talking in this
Jogging that we had no idea what it is
He's talking about you know you wake up
PhD jargon
Like a goose wi-lan you know theater of the oppressed
Too too smart
Too smart for us
And according to Joy it was during this pitch
That Richard started talking about economic
Is Joy wrong that you
Had the idea of this as an economic driver
Early on
No I probably said that
I'm no I'm I'm sure I did
It would grow the pie
Is he said
It would bring in people and
And create a bigger economic base
And you guys were thinking what
What
It's a wonder we went along with this idea but I guess we was so desperate we did
The Arts Council gave Richard the green light
And it started to raise money
Yeah they sold sausage and biscuits at farm shows
They held a bake sale in the town
Square foot most effective of all
The apply for Grants
Come on
Doesn't mean you don't know how to raise money
End it was agreed that the name for the show was going to be
Swamp
Gravy
Now look we could explain this to you
Why would we
When we have someone like
Swamp gravy three to four people can't catch a lot of fish and they have to eat something else
That again is fire chief Craig Tully and he says
People that make swamp gravy on the side of the creek when they went fishing
And just a little bit of Grease
And whatever you
Clean out the refrigerator
Taters
Okra
Korn whatever you want to put in there
Covfefe Friday move to Dripping put in there
It was good stuff
The Iliad
That's where it started to get out that the
The town was going to put on a play
Chief Tully
Was not a fan
I'm not going to say stupid
Silly silly would would be more the word and he's got like a couple of pretty good singers about them
First of all this idea you're going to make plays out of Colquitt oral history stories
I didn't understand
Why people would pay money to come see stories that they already knew
I mean if I got time to go do that I got time to go fishing that's kind of what I was looking
Speaking of
The swamp gravy
Swamp gravy
I come a beating swamp gravy and iWatch
You know when though
Listen I wasn't in the Menards
I was in the majority
Because nobody in car
Really supportive
The swamp gravy dissenters could be divided into two
There was the chief Tully camp this is
Is a dumb idea
And then there was a group with
A deeper citic
At the project got going
A team of people including Richard we're out and about town interviewing
People collecting oral histories
They were going to become the show
And it was around this idea that Joy started to hear somewhere
I remember that people
Started saying
To my friends and therefore to me
That we don't really want to do this week
Don't really need to do this
Because
If we start telling our old
Bad
Bad stuff
But you know it might stir up trouble in our community
When you live in a little town you know all the dirt that's happened for a lot of years
And you're not pray about it
What were the kinds of stories that people
We don't
We don't want that to get out
This pain
Political stories
About
Dirty crooked politics
There was stories about when this town was really like a West
Stringtown
And then this been race
Conflict in
You know we had two colored fountains in the wipe down
The colored waiting rooms in the White waiting room
And so people were afraid that something might be told that would really be detrimental to the
While we were in Colquitt Noel I stopped in
The public library
And there are oral histories written down there
Including some of the transcripts from the swamp gravy interview
This one's about making moonshine and getting ready to get up to the elderly
And it's a good illustration of this concern
If you start interviewing
People about old stories
All kinds of stuff is go
Some of it is totally Charming there are stories in there about Dad dressing up like Santa Claus
Stories about ghosts
So many jokes
And then there are
Deeply troubling stories
Including an account
From a man whose earliest memory was Whitney
The population of Colquitt is about half white
Aflac
And as much as Richard Gere wanted to
Stages show that help
The city confront
It's past
He also didn't feel like this was the right
Time to do that baton was already struggling the show with a long shot to begin with and to swamp gravy Wood Ave
Avoid call quits most difficult stories if it went well if they got a second 1/3 show maybe then swamp
Pretty good start to deal with more challenging material
The show was starting to come together the stories have been collected
It hired a playwright
Ditch those stories into a script
There was a music team they were writing original songs
Swamp gravy was going to be an hour long
It will be held at the elementary school auditorium
Anastasia would be like old timey down on the farm soap hay bales
Overalls
Anycast was all okay
SeaWorld volunteer
Cersei roll amateur
Was there anything surprising was there anyone where you were like my God she has a beautiful voice and we didn't know well
We had two African-American women
That knew more about
Comedy in
Theater
Then most people on Broadway
One of the women was a house
Keeper the other was a factory worker from the next town
Then you exactly how to pause
To do the punchline they're also kids
Kerry seems like nobody's business
There was an ambulance dispatcher with an amazing voice
She would get the big song on opening night Richard was direct
Joy was
I kind of producing I guess who's making sure that things were going smoothly in
Shooting Richard from a lot of the negative feelings
And up to this point Richard had mostly avoided
Causing those negative
One of the biggest concerns Richard had when he agreed to parachute in indirect the show
We said he'd mess up and get run out of town
Which may have sounded like some overblown Dramatics
Fear
Until
The inside
Well it was a week before we were
To open our first
Show
If we were in the schoolhouse Auditorium
And there were people on the stage
And in doing this
Show with in crunch mode it was time for rehearsal
Richard looked up
And not all of the ACT
And Richard just let it all out he went into his a professional
Theater director
Mode
The state of mine
And he kind of
Blurted out
Whatever
And what was whatever
It was bad it was it was it was a bad it was bad it was hell or damn
Whatever those ones are like the lowest
In the hierarchy of squares so it might have been that low
I think probably was
Because I mean we're not used to people
Swearing
In front of chilled
You don't do that
The South
There was some debate as to what you said
Really to just for that I don't think there's much debate about what I said but
That's fine for the record
The offending
Rephrase
Was what
I don't think it was a phrase I just said
Bach at the top of my lungs and started kicking grain bags and
Bales of hay
And
Then looked up and the next thing that I saw was
All the men in the room were coming at
Converging
And all the women and children were fleeing out the doors
And the men came up and said you better get yourself out of town right now
We are tar and feather you get on a plane and never come
They said those words to you
Absolutely and so the cast walked out
And at that point in time Richie was staying at our house
Richard and I sat on the sofa in my living room all weekend
Just about in tears
What's going to happen we had lost everything
How long did the
Boycott last
All weekend
And and I think it was maybe it was on Sunday afternoon or Monday the Baptist
Preacher
Call this together
And he negotiated a truce
And Richard apologized profusely I mean
He was practically down on his knees begging forgiveness
And that's quite a
Stretch for
Theater director
This project meant everything
But I just about lost
Every time I start to get annoyed with folks
I remember what I did that day
I just forgot
For I was with who I was
I got to go
It is
Saturday October 10th 1992 the premiere of swamp gravy
This is video first showing the lobby of the elementary
Preschool you can see
Is the fundraising quilt
There's somebody selling swamp gravy t-shirt
And then
We're in the auditorium
Places
So there was probably about 300 people
And but they were local people
You were where you where were you in the audience
Throwback I was stand front near front
The stage is dark
And when the lights come up there about 10 people in old timey Bonnets and overalls
In the entire room
Is silent
For just a moment
And what were you feeling
Just kind of been treated like what was going to happen
You know
How is this going to come out
The show starts with reflection on Chris
Columbus it was
Premiering on Columbus Day weekend after all
Columbus had an idea
Now there were those that held that the Earth was flat
And to be totally honest with you
This is
Pretty tough to watch
It doesn't seem like the crowd
Intuitive all
Comenity still awkward when is Columbus section
The new section begins
Icon from Tall Pines and short fuses
I found some Big Valley
Subaru hard to hear but every actor is saying I come from
And then like a line like I come from
Deep down in the sea
I come from all dressed up with no place to go all dressed up with no place to
And still it is really hard to tell if the body is
Is getting this
At all
And then
I come from a cannon with no stop lights
Hot girl from shut up and
Best first
Big laugh
And you can see the actors on stage break character and they start smiling
Kind of like
Okay thank God maybe this is going to work after
It's okay if I fast forward a little bit just kicked a couple places
Parts of highlights
There's a song about starting work at the
The crack of dawn
There was a sketch about caucus
Quotes famous berries
They are good for
Good for digestion
I heard it with liver trouble there was a story about
Two girls
Stealing a bottle of herbal Elixir from their mom and then getting very can
Lydia e Pinkham tonic
For ladies
Lady E Pinkham if you ever heard this
Story about
Women used
Did take it for anemia
But
The story was that there's a baby in every bottle
What what
What it means is the woman would get built up and she get pregnant again
I don't know but one of us is going to have this baby
But the Show Stoppers
Where the closing song
This is Annette Miller the ambulance
How she was Young Band
Weren't we all
You know Iris
Experience
But most people was what they had seen
Add a scoop
And you need to have them on this
States
Bombing
In such a
An almost
Professional way
And it was
Was so far beyond our wives
Expectation
They stood up and gave us a standing ovation
People with Blown Away
And it made it all worthwhile
Could you clap harder than you ever clapped in your life
Can you cry did you how did you react
Is cheering and beaming from ear-to-ear
Clapping very much
Let's Circle up you die.
It is now
25 years later and swamp gravy is still going
This is a rehearsal for this year's version of the show
Quiet place
So this is
Kenny and Noel
For the evening
Just don't worry about them
Not the school auditorium NE
This is cotton
Halt it is
A permanent venue built
For swamp grass
And it is
An old Cotton Warehouse
Has been converted into a
A giant state-of-the-art
Alright.
The director you're hearing is obviously not Richard
Richard is moved on and help loads of other places start things like swamp gravy and has the show mature
It has dealt with some of Colquitt stuffer realities
They tackled
Sexual abuse
Racism
They even had a sketch about murder
But it's still overall Maura celebration than it is
The director now is Kate Willis
Cook she's a 35 year old former theater major who moved
To Colquitt for this job
The show's writer is a local kid who grew up acting and swamp gravy
He moved to New York
He worked on Broadway and then he came back home because of swamp
So now we are not
Just here because swamp gravy is still going we are here because
Full right economic
Case studies
About swamp gravy and remember 25 years ago
This was the part of Richard Gere's
But even Joy Jinx was not so sure about
Joy told us she remembers the
The exact moment
She realized
This thing could have a monetary
After that first show was a
The success locally
They decided to put the show on again
It took a couple years but
New stories new songs
And somehow
Word traveled about this small town putting on a
Surprisingly great show
And into caucus Town Square
Play Massive
Charter bus
Southern coaches
Was the brand
It's a brand of the two of us
So you see that
And what do you think God really exciting must be happening in Congress
But it was your play
They were swamped
Eventually swamp gravy became profitable
And along the way swamp gravy has been invited to
Perform at the Kennedy Center in Washington
DC they got to perform at the freaking Olympics when they were held in Atlanta and every season there are about two dozen for 4
Performances of swamp gravy
Many of those fell out
And the vast majority of tickets are bought by people from out of town
Colquitt County Miller
Brought in
Roughly seven and a half million dollars
Indirect tourism
Some spending last year
A lot happens if we went on a little drive around town with
Localendar here in the car
Lest you forget what day it is while you're driving
You're very busy huh
Oh yeah what is drive we started to realize that
Because of swamp gravy there's something totally backwards about call
Yeah most cities you got developers and entrepreneurs whatever
Making money and then they are the ones that
Support the Arts
In Colquitt
It is completely
Flip last little ones
This playground were there bunch
Toddling about the project of the Arts
Cancel it's an early learning site daycare center and it keeps happening we drive past this charming
Old building called Market on the Square also is a project
Of the Arts
Is a retail incubator space owned and operated by the Arts
And the apartments above that space renovated owned and rent it out by the Arts Council
The one with the ghost miserly at one point
Owned and operated by the Arts count
Something I want to say that I've got
Dig out
StarTalk
Just start talking
I think
What his
Come to the full gram about swamp gravy
Is
Not only the economic benefit to the town
But I think the real basic thing that is
It's given this tan
Is the new a Feeling
We're somebody
We have arrived
We are important in the scheme of
Things
And that you cannot underestimate
Take for granted the idea that Arts
Play a role in helping a city
It's a pretty popular ID
Hazel Reid
About the creative class in the value of building a community around smart
Part of the reason swamp gravy has worked is that Colquitt figured all of this out
First
It got there first and now it gets to be Georgia's
Official Folklife play
And of course
There can only be one official Folklife play
I'm not going to say I just was
I never been scared to say what I think you will recall fire chief
Chief Craig Tully swamp gravy
Loudest critics lot of people just think it don't say it I'm going to tell you what to think even as the show group
As the tour bus
Just came to town
He still refused to see it he just did not want to go
And then one day
She gets a call that something is wrong down at cotton
Maybe someone smells
Smokey can't remember exact
But he had to go over
He gets there nothing actually is wrong
And the play is going on at
That's normal I stuck my head in there
And
You know you look and you see the people that you're know who are up there doing things that you didn't know they could do
Active
The lighting
The actors
The music
I think the music
County kind of caught me to
Chip Kelly wants to show us just how much he has come around
He walks me out of his office
Is Into the Fire
Are cheap now we're staring at the side of one of your fire trucks
He's pointing to the official crest
Abbey carpet fire
Fire on left side wrist
Do you want to ride
And in the center
We have a just
A painted fire helmet
Any we have home of swamp gravy as in
At the center of the fire logo are the words
Home of swamp
Which is
We're just letting people know we're proud to be the home of swamp gravy
It is this the best thing we got
Usopp future
Support for this podcast and the following message come from fidelity
As a Fidelity wealth management class
You get a dedicated advisor to help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes and make
Clear recommendations for your
Full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
I'm Linda Holmes there's more stuff to watch these days than you can ever get to
That's why we make pop
Culture happy hour twice a week we give you the lowdown on what's worth your time and what's 9
My pop culture happy hour on the NPR one app or wherever you get your podcast
Today Show was produced by Nick fountain or supervising producer is Alex goldmark and our editor is Bryant
First at we want to thank the ladies at The Terror in in Colquitt for their hospitality and a note about all of this one
DMV
Could not get
Tudor India
Episode some of the people who work
FootJoy Jynx to get the show off the ground
Kay and Don Chandler Charlotte Phillips and Kimbrel
And I've attached
If you got that about Today Show he can hit us up on Facebook we post a link to every episode and you can leave a comment there
We are at Planet Money on Facebook and Twitter and on Instagram
I'm Kenny Malone and I'm Noel cakes thanks for listening
Hey Noelle as you know I stayed in the
The Masala room
You did the ghost
I promise to like
Record just leave my record
Okay I'm about to go to bed
I mean I guess if Miss Holly has anything she wants to say
Say it
And dumb
Can I play for you like what I found on the roof
Is that real
Just getting up sketch
I can't look at it 7 hours it doesn't load
Oh