Julia Simon Kenny Malone
Last week you
Spend some time on Manhattan's Upper East Side I did because we had heard that there was there was like something
Weird going on in the art world in the Art Market
I went to Sotheby's I went to the sarlacc
And I get there
It's as big room there's jazz music playing
Ladies and gentlemen the sail is about
To begin if
You can take receipts
I was surrounded by men and fancy scarves women and black dresses
Everyone drinking champagne
They settled in
Good evening
Ladies and gentlemen
And welcome to Sotheby's my name is
David Pollack
I'll be your Auctioneer this
Art Market has been going nuts
And we
Begin with
Lot 1
There are about 70 pieces up for auction
Petition
A Van Dyke 42 is next Velasquez
Portrait
And a highly anticipated work
Fine artist named Nicholas longpre
An allegory of
An allegory of winter is the title of the pain
It's from the early 1700s it some women playing cards
A couple of guys there's one dude
Looks like he's man's waiting to the lady about her set of cards
$1000000.
Starting at $1000000 now
1 million 1 million
At one point five
Chico's at 1
2.2
It's in the front
Fair warning then a 2.2
Auction fees it came to 2.7 million.
Erect
For Nicholas longpre painting
And Records have been falling
Left and right in the art
Market maybe we can hurt about
The DaVinci Code
450 million
Dollars a record by a hundred million dollars
At an art auction
Salt 200
LOL
Thank you all very much indeed
As soon as the auction is over
They make me stop recording
Sotheby's doesn't want me wandering around with a recorder recording their high-end client
The art world is disc
They're always
But on my way out
As I was in line at coat check
Distemper British gentleman said something
You absolutely have to do the ACT
Open right now
He said
I have it on good authority
March of the sod
Came from Storage
And much of it will end up in storage
That is that is not bad
All that's to say
That some of this art
May never wind up on some
Wall it
May never even end up in a museum
The money pouring into art as an investment
It's causing some of the Worlds
Greatest treasures
To Venice
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Julia sign
And I'm Kenny Malone
Today on the show we take you into a
Shadowy world
Where investors are piling money in
Into the greatest visual works of our culture
And then hiding
We go on a mission to find out where they are
And why they're there
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence
Prince and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality
And mobiledit
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR
To save 10% off your first purchase
Have a website or domain
So we're on a mission
To figure out where all this artist
And again
It's very secretive
But I was told
There's a woman in Los an
Who knows the art world see
My name is Amber Noland
Is an artist yourself
Curatorship
Art school one of her sculptures was it at a female pirate
These days she works on the business
Decide treating art as a tangible asset
A way to store your money
People in the industry describe Amber as
The closer
To like what does it mean that you're the closer
It means that I will do anything
Find a solution to fix the situation
Okay so like anything
I mean that sound
A little dramatic be I don't knock anyone's needs out
Whatever actually does is
For the past 24 years she's managed art for wealthy collect
One day she'll be
Helping a client block off a major
Street and use a crane to install a roof on another day she's dealing with a heist
At a stoplight
Somebody lifted
The backend of the truck and took the art that was in there
Is about 4 pieces of work that we're really valuable
Never found again
Some days she's going into an ancient Library
Twins back to work
By Leonardo DaVinci
What was it
Chaos
That I can't tell
She can't tell me because then you could Google it and then you'd know who our client is
Amber is discrete because she works with billion
A nurse in a high-end art world you have a broker for your stocks
And you have Amber for your heart
I'm handling the actual
Physical aspect of
Their high-end
So they've got a 3 million-dollar painting and the overall collection is probably valued at
Anywhere from 500 million to a billion
What
Wow
Amber has run 40 full time
Client ensure many of them are art lovers
But some of them see art as a place to put their money like a better version of $1000000
Sure it's a place to invest a bunch of cash
But you can't move in apartment
Anywhere in the world
Whenever you want
So these investors they
By the art they want the art
But they don't necessarily want to
Run a museum they don't want to have to hire guards they don't want to have to worry about
Mold or
Temperature whatever
So it's not going anywhere it's not hanging up in anyone's house
It's not
Ready for the latest dinner party
So Amber explains
She tells her clients look
If you're really buying this artist and investment
You want to keep it safe
You don't care if it hangs on a wall
She tells her clients
There's this option
Something called a freak
A Freeport
It is
This weird kind of Zone where a lot of Art
Is headed east
Their enormous buildings are usually near airports where art
Just
Sits
And weights
And hopefully gets more valuable
And the strangest thing about these freeport's
Is that the sort of
Exists between worlds
So say I buy work of art in London
If I send it to a Freeport
Luxembourg
It has a really entered Luxembourg
Is between countries
It's in a sort of
Customs limbo
Amber says as
Art closer fixer whatever her job is
She has ended up placing about
300 million dollars worth
A client art in this
And there's one other big reason Ambersons all that are into
If reports
Taxes
Reports are used in the art world
To hold work
To delay
Taxation
So
The work can live there and be immune to any type
Of Taxation
Amber gave me an example of how this work
Sarah client bought a work of art from million dollars
Is that client buys art in York at Sotheby's
He has to pay the New York sales tax
8.875 /
That 88
Thousand
$50 but
Maybe he sends that
Work of art
Straight to Freeport
Maybe in Geneva or Singapore
She doesn't have to pay that tax
And that's a lot of money that's a lot of money
A lot of money
That you don't have to
Pay until you
You take that artwork
Out
Which could be
A long long time it could
Be forever
You might even be able to
To use that art
Stowed away
As a kind of cat
Taking a loan out against
It seems like a great deal for our donors
And a bad deal for government
So I called up the federal office which regulates these zones here in the US
And they didn't get back to me for an interview
But I did get in touch with Joshua Kaufman
A lawyer in Washington DC who specialize
And I asked you
What is the incentive for the
Increase
Trade in the porch
Anthony dustrial stimulus
People building those warehouses
They're paying real estate taxes
Facility
They're shipping cargo there
If we go because they're lost it says
You know there's economic
Benefits spin-off by having
Then sure maybe there is some economic spin-off by happy
But
It's also true that these reports have become one of the
The standoff
Places compete to have rich people do business there
If Geneva has a Freeport everyone will do their art business in Geneva
So Luxembourg has to have one too
And Singapore West saw this and thought they're getting on this too and so now there are
Freeport Indian
United States
But the other weird thing about Freeport is it they're not at all new
It's just that being an art tax Haven was not at all what they were intended
No they started in the mid-1800s in Switzerland but they were originally built for things like grain and tea
Green and T
You can't store it forever
Is short-term storage
And that's why the Swiss government said
Hay Merchant
You can store your goods here for now without
Taxes you can worry about taxes later on
When someone buys art
Overtime rich people started
Realized
There's this temporary layover we can
Twitter gold our wine into
Tax free
And no one seems to care that we're keeping it here
Long-term
In the last 50 years or so art collector started keep their art in Freeport
In the state of Texas pension
For as long as they want
And of course we were dying
To see the inside of
One of these places
The challenge
Is it there
Are not advertised they're not open
Open to the public they are sort of like
In time
After the break
We go to a Freeport
In America's favorite tax Haven
Delaware
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses
Is to design and build their own website
Using customizable layout
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop in online
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR
How to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
So I went down to Delaware with a guy named Fritz Dietl he's wearing glasses blue jean
Blue shirt blue coat I like Picasso's blue period
In Austria he became an apprentice as you do in Austria
His apprenticeship was an art Logistics and he loved it
He was transporting famous works of art
All over Europe
Art but
She was noticing
At rent some of his client in New York were sending their art back
These freeport's
In Europe
Everett he wanted it
She wanted to build his own Freeport
Just like a big white building
Why you like it like that
Well what's going on inside so we get out it's very
It's snowing Fritz rings the bell we need another Austrian the building manager
How are you you take me inside where I signed a visitor book so this might
Sound like a weird question but are we technically
Where are we now in America definitely still in America
We are at designated foreign trade zone Warehouse so for US Customs purposes
We have some property here that hasn't
Formally enter the United States
Puppy is still under US Customs control
Fritz takes me through loading dock
Lots of boxes
And then he takes me to the back of the warehouse where the building manager opens up
A huge metal gate
Cavernous
20 foot ceilings
And as far back
As far as I can see
Boxes so I'm looking down and I see wooden boxes
Wrapped up crates everything we only store artwork
I thought about something the former director of the Luxembourg Freeport one set
But he didn't want freeport's to become cemeteries for art
But what was I looking at
I was looking at a bunch of Art
In wooden boxes
Kind of look like coffins
Princeton let me look for long
I clearly wasn't going to be allowed among the Priceless artwork
You just turned off the light is do you keep it in darkness
Absolutely
Close the gate
So we went out to the front room and talk for a while with some boxes nearby
So this could be a sculpture or painting you can't tell me what's in Chinese
And I'll tell you what's inside
About the size of the water lilies
And this is the thing about free
Steak to make it so
Tempting if you are a narc
Poured money into this work
Is take that work of art
Box it up
Store it out of
So I called him Joshua Kaufman the attorney again
When I pressed him
Why are people okay with the system
System that makes it profitable to put great works of art in storage
You're not using yard this system encourages people
To put their art and warehouses
To invest in
Yeah I mean it's waves
Looking at it
I am
If I get anything else
People invest
Denart
St. Augustine real estate they just in all kinds of you know
Places
But you can see a building you can see real
You know of.
I guess you know that sitting in a Freeport
You and I
We can't see
Well I mean
Stop making that argue
Great extent about
But you know all great artists and private collection
Somebody what I don't want it on them
But those people do I guess I could go to my Freeport and sit in
My room and look at my art
I saw another piece near the loading dock as I was
It wasn't in a box it was wrapped in plastic
I found one piece of art
One Resort that I could see cuz there's a
Clear plastic over it
It's like a lot of white paint
Kind of sunglasses
Are smoothies that I can see
Later I figured out who would painted that one piece I did see
I tried to get in touch with her
I wanted to ask her what she thought about her art being in a warehouse
But you didn't want to talk
Sure cuz I mean I can imagine this is all pretty Bittersweet like on one hand
You sold a painting in the
Art Market
Is booming which is
Is great but
Arguably
All of this booming has
Contributed to more and more
Works of art
Being stored
Away
In these like anti-music
Yeah Kenny the two of us will be looking at art in books
The real art
Start itself
It might be sitting in darkness
Today's episode with produced by Jessica Jung are supervising
Producer is Alex goldmark urstadt is Planet Money editor
Thanks to Georgina Adam Christine Horry and Marcy Friedman
And if you're looking for another podcast
Don't miss today's episode of
It's been a minute with Sam Sanders
Because
Planet Money
He's very own
Stacey Vanek Smith
And Cardiff Garcia are the guests
They talked with Sam
About the wild
In the market
And why we should take
The Longview
Instead of digging into the ups and downs of every
Listen to
It's been a minute with Sam Sanders on NPR one or wherever you get your part
I'm counting on Julia Simon thanks for listening