Hey just a quick note Today Show is a rerun it originally ran in 2004
Robert the couple days ago you and I went to the grocery store in Brooklyn to
Do that thing
Yeah
Do we have a giant pile of watermelons is a classic seen in any grocery store
What are you looking for the chicken
Yeah we don't know
Sorry
Associate
Pickup on 101
Alright one more time
So we got
Cardboard box
Full of water. This is a classic summer scene where the watermelons come in
They will them in
The middle of the store
I don't give a s*** about the watermelon
Is the palette that there
Pallet
Those big wooden things that just about everything in the world
Get shipped on
Cutting watermelon
Including everything else you buy it
At the grocery store
Certain things in this world are hard to
You know the classic example.
Trap but we're talking about it and we were like the paper
The paperclip
Is 1 wire
Benton to
Paper clip shape it's so perfect the shape is named after the update
And the super sized version of this
Perfect object
The palette
It's 15 or so pieces of cheap Lumber nailed together
It's not an extra piece of wood or an extra nail in the whole thing
Keep stuff a few inches off the floor works with a forklift
Amazing
This perfect
Perfect system of moving stuff around a pallet has been around for a long time
Basically for 50 years
No one improve.
Until
Until they did hello about the planet money on Robertson
And I'm taking cold
Today on the show
Yes you can build a better Palace
It's not high tech
It's not computerized
But someone came up with a way to completely rethink an object
But no one
Even knew needed
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Which come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solution
Support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org
This is not going to come as a surprise to you but we are going to bring you deep inside
The pallet world
Because of course there's a
Right
Invisible
We only see the piles of old pallets
Out behind
Supermarket
Under the kitchen watermelon
But there are billions of
Pallets moving around the world
And there's old magazines
It's called modern Material Handling
Unfortunately they changed the original name which was
The Palatine
The palletiser I love it it sounds like some sort of
Logistics Uber
Superhero
I talked to the editor of this magazine Bob travel
Working Families palette
Was just out of college
My I guess my most notable a
She went with nailing a Runner 2
Ouch
Pallets are cheap
And easy to me
Anyone could do it
You could probably build a pallet
If a kind of classic thing that you know some Factory somewhere would put out
Million of them a day but
What tablets are actually
Unique
Object in that they are both cheap
But they are big
Mer bulky and there
Heavy and it doesn't make economic sense
The makeup palette in some central location and ship empty pallets all around the country
The truck says a pallet industry grew up as all these
Tiny
Little pouch
But you have a lot of two men and a dog
Piano guys who made pallets in their garage
After work
So you know Joe at the plant buy pallets from his buddy bill and his buddy Dave who built them in their garage
There are still a lot of shops like
My name is Steve Mazza we're at S&B pallet which is a local pallet recycling
I need the s in S & B L I N D S & S M okay
S&B pallet is in Plainfield
It is more than two guys and a dog
About 70
It's down the block from Geno's truck and Tire maintenance across the
The street from this neighborhood with houses in
Countries in Philly
It looks like it could be any town
Because
Physically there is something like this in almost every time
Parents are still this very local business
Don't you pull in here
Park in the dirt parking
And suddenly you're in this like
Grand Canyon
Where the walls are made of power
Stack
You ever even think I'm constantly thinking what if this mountain the palace next to a spell I might have your kids
Beef out to pretty stable when they're when they're stacked like that
That noise you hear in the background it's a band saw and
Coming from a big shot
Over in the corner of the yard
S&B doesn't do anything fancy with the pay
What what they do is just buying up used pallets for about $3 each
Fixing him up in that shop and then
Reselling them for about five bucks
And the pallets coming through this conveyor long and then what happened
I worked
The guys at work tables taking powered off and inspect
Stop and inspect the bottom for any broken boards loose
Or just there's debris and everything else that Palace repair to fix a broken board to the new Bora Bora.
This is
Clearly in low-tech operation
The guys working here using nail guns and just even regular ham
I can hear it I mean but of course it's low-tech
I mean
Poets write these guys are making basically the same thing
The people have been making for
For decades
Early part of the 20th century
I think you could have made it
5000 years ago
The only reason pallets weren't invented even earlier
Is xXx really need them
Until they had
Forklifts they sort of evolved together
Really just has
Two jobs
Old stuff off the ground
+ 2
Make it easy for forklifts to pick that stuff up
And so you know decade after decade
Things don't change that much
The standard pallet becomes an essential part of World Trade
American GI is dragging around the globe in World War II and Steve mother's all over the country are running their lip
Little pallet businesses all making basically the same kind of power
Now over the years
Lots of adventure
Try to make it better
Try different configurations
Materials
Pallet
How do you write this is how most products improve
New technology
But this did not work with
Because think about a better palate
Would be a more
Expensive
And companies don't want a more expensive palette
They want a cheap
Disposable thing that'll pull dare
Whatever case of the toilet
Yeah and we were talking at the pallet World in a more expensive
Pallet turns that whole world
On the 10th
Toss them in the back of the store right there expensive if you have two people to
To guard them you have to make sure no one throws pallets away definitely college kids don't steal your palette
Make the world's ugliest coffee table
Soap pallets
Hinder stay the same forever
Until the blue one
Yes the blue one
Back in the 1990's in yards and in the back of store
You would all the sudden see a bright
Blue palette
Most of us wouldn't notice this and if we did notice it we think I'll need
Painted a different color
But Steve Mazza
The pallet guy from New Jersey
Vividly remembers the first time
He saw the blue
He was in Memphis
For a meeting
With a meeting of the national wooden pallet and container assoc
And he went out to visit a local pallet yard
Because I guess
That is what you do when you're at a Palace Convention and you have a few hours off
I actually went to a pallet yard and I said hey that's one of those blue Palace
Can I have that and he said sure I took that blue palette knife
We were having a general session for an association meeting and I walked into that General Session I put a pallet of my head I slammed it down on the floor
Lauren I said you know what guy
Everybody better understand what that pallet over there is because it's not just a pallet
It's the end of our endless
These blue pallets were all coming from one cup
A company called check
Caahep
Chop and this company is coming it will change the American pallet Market forever
What's from Australia
Quick backstory here when the US Army left Australia after the end of World War II
Left behind
A lot of pallets
And the Australian government
Scoop those pallets up informed
The Commonwealth handling equipment pool
Cheap
Jeff
Chocolate private it got by the international
Conglomerate
And they were intent on turning this
Really local
Low-tech pallet business
Into a worldwide in
Chest loot Palace they're still made of wood they're still held together with nails
But they're put together in a different way
Okay this is going to get a bit
Nerdy but you are going to be able to impress your friends next time you go to supermarket by knowing
The different kinds
The palace
Standard pallet
Is known as a Stringer
The kind of Steve Mazza
You can look it up from the front or the back
But you can't we lift up a Stringer pallet from the side because
There's a vertical bordelon
The new palette
Called
A block
And it's open on all four sides
And that makes it much easier to move around a warehouse
Oreimo stomach
Stronger
It's basically better
But that doesn't mean it was an easy sell
David Lee help wants chips business in this country and
You told me about shopping this new palette around to manufacture
Well obviously the introduction of the block pallet was a major deal
For us there's a skeptical Industries saying well do I really have to handle
Multiple specifications of pallet
And you have to persuade them of the benefit
What we know
You know and love the string of palette
But but his
He's a better mousetrap
The black palette had actually been around for a long time
But it wasn't popular
Because it's really expensive
Quotes about
$20
Normal palate cause maybe half
How did Shep get customers to buy this luxury palette
They didn't
This this was actually chips real innovation
Chipset
We are not going to sell you the
We're going to rent the
Here's Bob trebilcock
Palette expert
Again
My first memory of cap is hearing people talk about this idea of
We're going to rent
The pallet that sounded a little crazy
Why would anybody want to run at
Running out of pallets seems like running out of paper
Bringing out an aluminum can
But here's how they sold
If you're saying a toothpaste company
And you want to get your toothpaste from your factory to the
Uphs
Say
V bucks
And they let you borrow one of them
Pallet
Then winter toothpaste gets to the grocery store check comes and picks up its pallet
Expect some real support and then rent it out again
Eventually this caught on
In what have been this Ultra local two guys and a dog pallet world
Suddenly there was something
Much bigger
We have something like 78 million circulating
And in the United States
78 million pallet
But of course now this means that chap
Has to keep
Track of 78 million power
This is a really hard logistical problem and David Lee says
This is why all the pallets
Are painted blue
So that you can see them from across the sea
We have a nice white logo on the side and a big sign that says
Probably of chat
On every single palette so so nobody in the US can say
But I don't know who owns a pallet
There is
There is even a phone number
Stenciled on the side
You can call if you find a blue pallet
That has escaped
Into the Wild
Yeah they Skype the fold
Escape the family
I think it's in our DNA that we do feel that way but the we all believe but yeah we have a personal responsibility to bring them back
Into the fold the company of contest for workers who find pallets out in in the wild
David Lee says
Give me totally found one helping to hold down a bouncy
County Fair near me
House and now that we have told you
About the blue pallets
I swear you will start to see these things everywhere I have started
To see them everywhere
Behind grocery stores holding up the produce in a supermarket and there is one place
One place where you are going to go see more pallets than just about any other store on Earth
Was that after the break
Support for this podcast
Cast in the following message come from the Annie E Casey
Sea Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is
Is available at aecf
. org
Ring Costco
Bling Brooklyn cast
Where in the diaper aisle
I'm just going to run down the line here and look at these Palace on this road
Blue blue blue blue blue blue blue blue
Here's back Costco looked at these chep pallets
And they actually they did the math that they look at how long it took them to unload a truck full of chep pallets
Versus how long it took him to unload a truck full of
Full of regular
And they realized
With the chep pallets they saved a little bit of
Of course if your Costco
And you can save a little bit of time on every truck you unload
That is a big deal
Costco issued this
They said
All of their suppliers
When you send us stuff
Whether it's diapers or
Peanut butter or whatever
It has to be on a chep pallet
Or at least on a pallet
Like a chapter
There are few exceptions but
If you walk into a Costco today
Look up at the palace
You are going to see a lot of blue
That is the thing that is put the fear of God into the paladins
The Palatine
All those guys building pallets with
Wood Hammer somewhere in your town
All the guys who go out and recycle old pallets
Guys like Steve Madden
Yes
S&B pallets
The New Jersey
Play mother knows this new chep pallet is a better pallet
Maybe not surprisingly
Steve Messer wants to get into the better pallet business
But there's this big barrier
Chip has turned what used to be a local business
Into a national
The complete C Maza would need
Lots
Of pallets
How many pallets would you have to build to get going at minute every minute
5 million to 10
Just for 5 million pallets you need a hundred million dollars
109th do you have a hundred-million-dollar don't have a hundred million dollars surprisingly not
But he is working on
He's teamed up with a bunch of other pallet
And they're launching this new company
It's called 9 block
Because
Extra geeky facts
There are 9 wood blocks in a box
And 9 black basically wants to be chapped
But with more like a local touch and all they need is a hundred million dollars
In the meantime
Monster in the other little guys are doing what lots of small companies in lots of Industry
Please do to compete against
Giant Global competitors
They're figuring out how to do things that the big guys don't do
First deposit that means making specialized pallets for local businesses that say
Ship really heavy things are really big things
Things that can't go on the standard blue chep pallet
Headed to chat
For creating this sort of
Excitement in the pallet industry after decades
When you change something so basic
So perfect like it kind of gives everyone this hope
Is there a new things to discover it makes guys in
Jersey and Ina yard an industrial neighborhood dream of hundred-million-dollar company
Maybe the booth how old is just the start
Baby
This is the new age of pallet innovation
Banks to Stuart Richardson
He wrote pallets a North American perspective and he talked to me for the story
I also want to mention that I got interested in pellets because I recently read a great article about
Pallet I was published yet cabinet magazine and will post a link to that on our blog
The block is at mpr.org money
We of course appreciate you listening to Planet money but if you're looking for something else to listen to
We'd like to recommend NPR pop culture happy hour you can find it on iTunes under podcast
Talk show today was produced by Thea Benin and Vietnam
I'm Jacob and I'm Robert Smith thanks for listening