This message comes from NPR sponsors snowfall
The only data warehouse
Built for the cloud
Unlock deep data in
Insights with the instantly scalable
Cloudbuilt data warehouse
Start your journey towards data-driven decision
It's snowflake. Com NPR
Hi Karen Duffin here
Today we are replaying a classic episode that was
Originally reported back in
In 2013 about wine in New Jersey
And believe it or not a lot has been happening in the New Jersey wine industry since we first reported this
So we will have an update for you at
The end of the show
Really this week Zoe and I
Hit the road for a tour of wine country
We drove most of the day we got The Vineyards
Right around sunset
Our first stop was
The alma theater cellar
It was pretty gorgeous
If you walk here you'll see
The owner Luciano Texas passed
100 year old farmhouse
And we drop out rows of Old Vine
But here's something that I put in the ground in 1976
Foods that this old world charm about him
You both kind of looks
Sounds like Marlon Brando
Have to have a feel for the next 30 Years After
Your baby is this what you're saying
Well more or less and I am hopeless Romantics and I'm starving
Realistic about the whole scene there
Looks like one of those etchings
But you'll see on the front of an old bottle of French wine you know with the vineyard in The Farmhouse
We are not in French
We are not even on the west
Inside Lou pulls out one of his bottle
Bottles that this Winery
The location we're standing in is in something called the outer coastal plain
This is so good this is
Fantastic
So good
Easy to forget where we really are
You like that one
Not bad for New Jersey right
New Jersey
Hello and welcome to Planet Money on Robertson
Today we traveled to the land of Tony's
Soprano Jon Bon Jovi New Jersey Turnpike
Rotella quintessential New Jersey
Story
Scrappy Underdog
Tries to show the snob that he is just as good as they are
Lukrecja low and his fellow New Jersey wine makers
Suffer from the classic problem
You aren't always judged by who you really are
The by your reputation
Where you come from
How do you get the haters
Change their mind
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Madewell
Where the model
Good days start with
Raging
How did they make them so great
Madewell starts with
Premium denim
Then offers men's and women's styles
4 seriously every
Also you can recycle any brand of jeans in a Madewell store
And they'll give you $20 off a
The new pair
They work with the blue jeans go green Pro
Turn old jeans
Did the Housing Act
4 communities in need
Terms apply
Ready to find your perfect fit
Stop by a Madewell store
Store or go to madewell.com
The dream that New Jersey could be like
France ligue Bordeaux this is not crazy this is happened before
There was once
Another Scrappy Underdog estate that was reviled
The butt of jokes widely mocked horrible reputation
Their wine got no respect and fancy wine drinkers wouldn't touch
In 1976 the reputation of California
Wines was
That it was only slightly better than Rock.
That's George Tabor
He's a White journalist
There were sweet
High alcohol wine
Such as Ripple
When its slogan was it has that ring a ding flavor and this guy George Tabor it was on the scene when California
It's coming out party it's
Debutante ball
In the 1970s
Heber was a writer for Time magazine in Paris and
He got this weird little press release one day inviting him
To cover an event called
The Judgment of
Paris in honor of the American Bicentennial
California wines out of the little-known be
Regions of Napa and Sonoma would go head-to-head with
French Chardonnay and Cabernet
So paper shows up
May 24th
1970s
He's the only journalist in the room
Preeminent French wine expert
He looks around
If he can immediately see something happening
The judges were becoming
Fused
They could not tell the difference
Between a California wine and French wine
Well there was one
Kind of freakish moment
When Raymond Oliveira who was the Julia Child in France
Set the time
And he had a glass of wine up
And he looked at it
And you swirl it around and he tasted and then he looked at it again he said
Allied
Back to friends
I looked out my scorecard I was the only
One of the rumor had a scorecard so I knew what they were drinking
And he just tasted a freemark Abbey wine from California
Sacre bleu the winning line was American the French word humiliated California was triumphant
The Judgment of
Paris put California on the map
Overnight
The next
Monday morning
The Time Magazine story
Came out
I found a baby wine shopping
Manhattan
They were swamped
With people coming in with their copies of Time Magazine saying
Can you have any of these wines
If you do can I buy him
You probably know what happened next
The price for California wine what up
Number of wineries in Napa
And Sonoma
Exploded
A star was born
And all around the world
Dreamed of making great wine said
People like Luke rocheleau in New Jersey
If the French had been taken down by anybody that meant to the new
World was going to open
If that was possible that means any region in the world with similar
Carmen the winemakers could do that
Even New Jersey
And solu Plantation
Is first vines in an old
Potato field that is family owned
Just off the Old Highway
Halfway between Philadelphia and Atlantic City
If 1976 was when the California wine industry arrived
The New Jersey fine wine industry was just
Beginning
The thing about wine is that everything takes
A long long time
Okay so
You want to taste the wine
Lou takes us through his old farmhouse
The food science
Best Buy training
And he did not cut any
Corners in his operation
It took him six years
Dejected
Great grapes
Alone right
Retainers after that to produce a bottle that he was proud enough to share
And eventually
Eventually the wind started
Taste the way he imagined
It started to taste
French
Who opens the door to the White's house
So
This is this looks
Like
Basically a cliche of European
Wine cellar
Hippie 1682 here
Exactly is little candles around and he's beautiful
Barrels
Attacked another cliche
This is a guy identical to the way it was going to 1750 nothing's different
Making the wind is hard but that's the fun Romance
Louis got a way bigger challenge
Getting other people to notice
That is wine is great
And that's an especially Big Challenge in
New Jersey
Not just because of all the things you think of when you think of New Jersey but because
New Jersey wine
Already has made a name for its
It's just not the name that you want
Where's New Jersey one
People have been making wine in New Jersey for 200 years
There are dozens of wineries
People like
Charlie tomasello
He's just down the road from Lou but
He is Worlds Away in his winemaking
King Style
BT pellets
Do you like
It has been described to me as
A little bit like grape jelly
Yes well I think that's it
Because concrete is used by
Welch's probably make
Grape jelly center
And it's very sweet I had to
Tell you that
Sweet
Smuckers
Concord grapes
Lose fat
French style
Why dump truck
But Charlie tomasello has been here way longer than Luke
Decorative migas traditional gravy wine it retails for about 10 bucks
His grandfather started the police after prohibition
History is it
A couple weeks after prohibition ended he ran to Washington in the snowstorm and got his license grandfather was pretty much
Not quite the first in line but almost the first one
Thomasville family have been very successful
Making me sweet wine
You can find them all over the country
And the tomasello winery and others
Bastille the world
What New Jersey style wine is
It's pretty
Sometimes it even made from raspberry
Cranberry
Especially people always talk about the New Jersey blueberry wine
I like it
I know I can picture almost like being poured over ice cream
It has that kind of like almost syrupy taste to it
It goes very well with cheesecake
Nothing wrong with cheesecake why
This is a very good example of the form
Even at $11 a bottle Charlie
Eats it when people assume fruit wines are low quality
There are 12 lb of raspberries in a gallon of tomasello Raspberry wine so it's a premium raspberry
It's just not the kind of wine you can charge
$100 a bottle for
What kind of wine that
Wine collectors around the world will fight to own
And your friend is not the
What kind of wine inspires people to travel a long way to spend gobs of money you know taking bicycle tours to the
Wine Country
A southern New Jersey
Writing out the New Jersey wine industry generates around 35 million dollars
Ciara
California wine is hundreds of times bigger
20 billion dollars a year
Lucre Chula and even some of the fruit winemaker's dreams
Stealing away some of that money
I think the Jersey land and the Jersey grapes are good enough
The problem is how to change people's expectations
Lou wants
Esl classic
European style dry wine
From a place
Where people
Expect you
Now would be really clear for a second
I'm here I am not a sophisticated wine
I'm not either we both thought that both wines were delicious so sweet and the dry
But the point we're making here is that in order to sell the dry
You can't be saddled with the reputation that all the wines that come out of your area or sweet
George Tabor that wine journalist
We spoke to a book about the Judgment of
Serious wine buyers will not look
Twice
Add a bottle with the name nude
Basically the wine industry
Wine business in the state
He's got to kick that reputation
And you don't kick it
By continuing to have
80% of the wines out on the
The market
Are those sweet ones
You can buy
Tomasello blueberry wine in bulk
Liquor store
It's out there their they're making it there
Obviously making a profit on it
They're just not making a reputation on
This is known as a collective action problem and it basically means this
Sometimes your success depends on how your competitors behave
People are judging you not
Just buy your product but
Buy the product that your rival down this
Street mix
You are all groups
Together in their mouth
Louis caracciolo and his french-inspired wine
What's the change the reputation of newt
He wants to make it a place where you can go for cabernets and have frogs
But I can't do it alone
He needs his competitors to up their game 2
So that when someone takes their very first New Jersey wine
That experience
The thing they're going to form all their opinions on
That experience has to be good
Lowest taking this on this
Is collective action problems he has a plan
First thing
Ditch the name New Jersey
Much better to
Slap on the official geological name for the area around Atlantic City
The outer coastal
The outer coastal plain when imin International
Show now
People pick that up and say
That's almost really isn't it but once and Australia
New Jersey
It sounds fancy
It's Market
When you get to work outer coastal plain you can almost
I smell the Salt Air the breeze coming off the water you picture this
Rolling Hills
Yeah it needs a little bit like that in South Jersey
But the name is actually
Legit
Luann from the other winemaker
Cuz they got South Jersey officially certified by the federal government
As a wine region
An American
Viticultural area
Lake Sonoma
Like the Russian River Valley
Like the Antelope Valley of the California high desert
That's Los Angeles County
Just north of La okay what are you got this trick from the front
It's how they dealt with their Collective action problem
Back in the 19th century
Back then some French wine was good
Other French wine
When was laozi
The fancy winemaker
Force the government to come up with a
Formal classification system
The premier wineries band they didn't have to worry about what their neighbors were doing
How to destroy the reputation
Wine regions in the US
Accomplish some of the same
Napa wines Pizza
Way in the Hope in New Jersey is
The outer coastal plain will acquire
Slowly the same sort of cachet
What's cheaper stuff
Call itself New Jersey
But a name is not enough
You also need a
Critical mass
Of wineries
Who uses the classic jersey example
It's very very similar to gambling
You're not you're not a gambling region Leicester
Reno casinos
So here the jewelry for wine drinkers are going to come down the region to spend a day or two
They got to be able to take University
Of the different ones and then
That that Rising tide lifts All Ships
And so Lou is on a mission
He visits the other wineries in New Jersey and give them the sales pitch
Sherp still sell the sweet wine make your money that way
Make your record
Keyshia Dior prestige on the phone
It's not the most
Easy pitch in the world
Making French
Or California style wine is in
Expensive proposition
Finicky grape vines that require constant
Pending and you can't release your wine right away you can't make your money back
Agent properly in Oak Barrel
B70
210 years before you can make
Any money selling the wine from those
New European Vines you plant
Some people are into it though Charlie Thomas Loc
He still makes the traditional New Jersey
Sweet wine
But he's also battling a
2010 Reserve Cabernet grape jelly
Fatheads
Nice kisses
Forward fruit in a little bit of leather and chocolate
Even the cork sounds fancy
And it is delicious
Called
Cameras
It sells for
$48 a bottle in the name New Jersey does not appear on the front of the bottle
It's all out of
If you want to know the name of the winery or where it's from
You have to check
Define print on the back
Lou and Charlie tomasello and the other New Jersey wine makers
Still waiting for the big
California MoMA
But it's tougher than it was in 1970
Sex back then
They were not too many states that we're making great why
But lose try to recreate the magic of
That's hot
Last year flu and ends Neighbors in Southern New Jersey
They're going to have their own blind test
Just like the one that happened in Paris the Judgment of Paris
The distance knobs
Would have to pick up a jersey wines
From a field of French heavy
George Tabor the guy who was in Paris in 1976
He came to Princeton
And they try to replicate it
Number 6
French Cabernet Sauvignon
In the competition
+ 4
From the United States
It's again just as it had been at Paris
Show picture
Quiet room
You're taking
I need little sips of wine
The experts have their pencils and their slips
The paper that writing everything down
The scores are being tallied
And then the moment
This was the time for New Jersey
To show the world what they were made of
And somewhere out on Highway 9
Springsteen holds his breath
And the winner among the whites
Is
A French wine
French wine
But
The second place
Was a New Jersey one
The state of New Jersey the Garden State
That wine would be made at Exit 8
I got it Exit 8 on the turnpike
Overall New Jersey wines did
Really well
Three of the top 4 white wines were from New Jersey
Garden State red
Place 3rd
Charlie tomasello Cabernet
Took 5th Place
But so far no mad rush to the wine shops Looking for Jersey wine
Quake of the
The judgement of Paris
You know if you listen if you put your ear to the ground
You can hear a rumble
Way out on the turnpike
Jersey is coming
Support for this podcast and the following message come from made
Where the motto is
Good days start with
Raging
How did they make them so great
Madewell
What starts with premium denim
Then offers men's and women's styles
4 seriously every
Also you can recycle any brand of jeans in a Madewell store
And they'll give you $20 off a new pair
They work with the blue jeans go green
Turn old jeans
The Housing Act
4 communities in need
Terms
Ready to find your perfect fit
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Karen Duffin again here in 2018 with a few updates
So I checked back in with Lou house wine in New Jersey
How about your business
Wow
Sale of New Jersey wine is up almost 38% since 2011 they now have four official
Billy designated wine growing regions
I'm also told people have gone from there's no way New Jersey has good wine to
I'm curious about how New Jersey wine taste
And they're about to get a little more help in selling people on New Jersey wine
The Garden State wine growers association just got a grant from the USDA to do a marketing campaign for
New Jersey wine
I have some ideas
Trying to hear my slogan ideas
Okay how about
Stop being a snob drink New Jersey wine
Work
Blue like the snot
Because if you can convert
Stop going around
Just found a winery that's the whole goal of being a snob is that you catch the thing before it becomes a thing
I see well I guess we don't need my second slogan idea then
Okay here we go
If it's good enough for Bon Jovi it's good enough for you
I am told it well
Bon Jovi is invested in wineries
He's not invested in New Jersey Winery
Blue says he can fix that
Okay alright so next step broker an introduction to Bon Jovi
Mr. Bon Jovi You officially have an invitation to lose wiring
Kuwait to every episode on Facebook
Twitter
Stats on Today Show leave comment on post
We gotta we are also on Insta
Instagram
Carl Lewis
At Planet Money
The show was originally reported by Joey Chase and Robert Smith
Aviva dekornfeld and Eliza is scarce they produce the rerun
I am Karen Duffin thanks for listening