How's it going where NPR reporters were doing a story on pepper you got a second
Yeah it's okay
How's it going where NPR reporters were doing a story
Rapper
You and I were out on the streets of Manhattan
We're talking to people who are walking by
And we've got with us two tins of
Did the pepper that you've seen all your life to standard pepper 10
We got two of them
Because about a year ago
McCormick machine
This classic
Pepper chicken that they sell in the grocery
So what we were doing is
We have the old one and we have been
We asked people to play to play game we asked him to Spot the Difference
Between the old and the new
Same color red and white primarily
Little blue and McCormick
It appears that the embassy are the same
Your ground black pepper
So that's what it say on the new one
Pure ground black pepper okay same font
It appears so it's an illusion
Not an illusion
Fin Fun
Other people
The tunes were slightly different size
Probably Merrill all right so you think it's a little bit thicker
Nine everywhere not thicker they are exactly the same size
The only difference between the tens is written right at the bottom of the small numbers that say how much pepper is in the
Different
Different amount
The old tin the One McCormick sold for years and years has
4 oz of pepper in it
The new one has three
Significantly less
Same size canvas significantly less or quarter less
Impressive right the how identical they are like everything else I think that's a little rip off a little
Misleading now
The tens used to be filled with pepper all the way to the top now there's some empty space right there where there used to be pepper
And what is west of it
Are
Why that
Who's going to take care of this meme
Do other countries what would happen here is some government Aid
MC Lyte say the FDA
Find the company or make them change what they're doing or maybe not I mean it does say right there on the front of it
Exactly how much pepper is inside they're telling the truth
In America we do not leave this up to the government
In America this whole pepper thing is the basis of a lawsuit
Actually lots of lawsuit
It's in California and Iowa and Pennsylvania in about a dozen states in all
What are going to spend countless hours on
Arguing for the judges if it gets that far in front of juries
Back and forth over this question of whether McCormick
Should have put more pepper
In the tent
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Jacob.
The pepper case is a class action
Thousands of these lawsuits grind their way through the court system every year
Today on the show we meet the man who helped
Create this class-action world we live in today
You did it partly in the backseat of a car on a manual typewriter
We asked him how he feels about this thing that he Unleashed
Also we do try to get to the bottom of the pepper
By the way we originally reported the show back in
In 26
We'll have a little update at the
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their own website
Using customizable layout
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobile added
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization to help you develop an online presence
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
The man who helps
Create the modern class action
His name is Arthur Miller
Not Arthur Miller the playwright Arthur Miller the lawyer
And he says the key work your happened in the 1960
I must check out I may be the last person alive
Who is in that room
Well I'm glad I'm glad we got you today then
Tomorrow who knows
Miller is a professor at NYU
He looks like my grandpa
They both have these amazing out of control eyebrow
But Miller is better dress
I have never thought
A class
Other than
In
A suit
The three piece suit
They don't really even make threesome
Piece suits any lawn
I wear them with a red tie
And a red pocket
That's a uniform
We went and visited Miller at his office
On spring break and there was nobody in the building but he was wearing that three piece suit
Class actions were not always about things like
Is there an app pepper in the
The roots of the modern class action
I'm going to say they were Noble
They go back to the Civil Rights Movement go back to this time when you had
Huge groups of people who are just being denied their basic legal right
A class-action is
When
You have a lot of pee
You can all fit into the courtroom
But you want to give them access
So 1 to 5
10 people come forward
And say we will sue on behalf of
Class actions have been around forever
But they weren't being used very much
That is really interesting reason
Yet the reason was a problem
With the rule
And I haven't really thought about the
Before but you know there's like these tutorial perilous
There's the laws that you think of the laws that congress
But then there's this other thing that is really important
And that is
The rules
For what happens in the courtroom
The rules for
Who can bring a case and when and what the judge can and can't do
They're called the federal rules of procedure
Nurses in the 60s
The rule for federal class actions was this
Total mess
You couldn't figure out what it was saying
The words were
We're short of an
Ambiguous they were vague they were amorphous
Hope Miller is working with this secret committee
And by secret I mean it's not at all
I just personally never heard of it before the Committees appointed by the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court
And their job was to
Update the rules
Specifically they were trying to change the rule for class action suit to make them more effective
Giving key
In particular
What they want to do is they want to make it clear
That if even just one person
Send files a class-action and wins
The Judgment applies to everyone who is in the same situation
Everyone who could have filed
When weekend Miller and a senior lawyer
The driving out to the country trying to figure out exactly how to fix this rule
I'm in the backseat
With a typewriter you would consider to be something out of the Stone Age
It's like on your lap on my lap on my lap
In the backseat
And we're playing with words
So they're looking at the rule and they're trying to figure out how to make it right
They're saying put this word over here or put the semicolon over there
Yeah and then they drive their car onto a ferry they're going out to an island
For the weekend
On the ferry with all these other
Miller still sitting there in the backseat
Clacking away on this on this manual type
A woman in the car next to us
Rolls down her window
Reaches out and Taps are window
And the woman says
Don't you hear the clock she said
Are we sinking
How do you say civil rights
Will change your life
He was right this rule was you it made it so anyone could go to court
Argue that their civil rights were violated and if they won
You change things for everybody who was in there you know in there same situation
Certainly every voter rights case you can think of
Came after this rule came in
Natchez voting rights
Dozens and dozens and dozens
Of community
Would be separate
Bigcommerce of the class action
You even see desegregation decisions in my old town of Boston
Where they desegregated
The school system
That was because of a class-action
That was the beginning of modern classic
But that for while some lawyers looked at this and said
You know we can file all all kinds of classes
What about those late fees on my cable bill
Yeah that was one of the first big one
Deborah Hensler is a political scientist at Stanford and she says
In that case
The plaintiffs won a big settlement
So I don't lawyers thinking fees monthly fees weight fees
Who else
You know
What other businesses are there
Where this might be an issue and so you then see a line of cases why
Like that
And here is where something that begin with big civil rights issue
Voting
Desegregation
What are the gender discrimination
Cures word Edge toward things like
Can you be more pepper in this
Enes Kanter pepper
Arthur Miller the guy who helped make all this happen
He was watching at the number of class actions exploded when do you realize the genie is a
Man created a monster
You can hear this voices by half
That they're a bad class actions of course there are bad
Class Act
Do you remember the first one that you like this is just silly
Yes
Two of them
Both happened in the 90
Okay sound honestly
When we born
I was born in 1989
Okay I'm going to be your 90s guy the first case Miller says you can describe into words
Milli Vanilli
Remember notionally honestly I barely remember
Here's what happened
They were two singers
They had this big debut album it was a hit
I think it was this song what was it
Girl you know it's
True
Yeah
I'mma tell you something
Not Milli Vanilli
What day was this candle day wear lip syncing came out they didn't actually sing on the album
And you know what comes next class action Class Act
Settlement
People who bought the CD got $3 back
Peabody Gazette
You got $2 back
Amazing
He was later there was another case that made Noah crazy and this time he got to see it unfold in real-time
Miller was watching this boxing match
On Pay-per-view
Even I've heard of
Mike Tyson versus
Evander Holyfield
And lo and behold
The third round
Bites off a piece
Atole fields
Here
They stopped the fight Tysons disqualified and right away Miller picks up the phone and calls A friend is who is also a lawyer
I see Mel you watching the fight
He says yeah I said
Is class-action here
There's a Class Act this is a Consumer Fraud people have paid to watch
$90 whatever it was
This is a classic
The two of us were laughing
The following morning three class actions
Defiled
And what were you thinking right then when you saw it in the newspaper
What did we create
I mean wide
People push the envelope
Beyond
Rationality
This this release oils at 4 everyday
I mean did you feel embarrassed
Slightly
Embarrassed for the profession
Come on
You paid you saw
There's certain things in life
You should just
Forget about
That's kind of what the judge said I got thrown out of court
So now we're to do that now we're to the world of Class Act
Actors that we live in
And you can kind of way this you know on the one hand
Now you have the solution
If there are a lot of
Weapon harm and some really small way
That would never be worth bringing a lawsuit on it
Now classics
They can band together and fight back
Amelia
Come
I mean like when we've been talking to her friends about the
The story that were doing
Weather keeps saying to us is like yeah
Of course class action
I got a check for 2 bucks and the lawyers get rich
And you know you do have lots of lawyers and federal judges dealing with these cases and warehouses full of vodka
I actually don't know are there still working my mind there still Warehouse
There was there was a lot of cost here
It's an expensive way to figure out how much pepper
Should be in the tent
You've been spending a lot of time with pepper lately
We have been spending a lot of time with pepper
Elizabeth Fagan is one of the lead lawyers for the plaintiff in the pepper
Like are you entering the tins into evidence you are
We're making sure they preserve them
Here's the story fake and tells about
She says McCormick started putting less pepper in it spins about a year ago
Just leaving empty space
This media because I'm Global markets the price of
Raw pepper
Commodity pepper whatever you call it the price was going through the
McCormick wouldn't talk to us for the story we ask
But they have argued in court filings
Hey look we put the correct amount of pepper right there on the label it
It's right there on the front of the tin for everyone to see we're not
Hiding anything
But fake and says they still broke the law
There's a law
That prohibits was called non-functional slack fill
Means making a large package but only feeling it with a small amount of Prada
They just I just wanted like
Delighted that phrase to say the phrase
Non-functional slack fill
Okay so non-functional I get that Slack
Phil what is slack fill
Slack fill is
Are
It's the fortune of a package that I
A manufacturer fills with nothing but air
Side note there is such a thing as functional slack filled are that's in the package for
That is allowed
If there's an FDA regulation that actually lift
Pacific reasons why flag still might be okay
Like if the product settles during shipping I'm pretty sure I've seen that on the side of the cereal
Bauxite product may have settled during shipping
And yes figen says
There's the potato chip rock
If you need a certain amount of air in a package to protect the product
For example
Potato chips are to protect
Potato chips from getting crushed
That is functional slack fill
Correct
Are because you don't want to put as much pepper in the can
Is not okay
Before Fagen was arguing about pepper in court she was handling other Class Act
Some of them had much higher Stakes one of those cases was over sexual harassment at a big real estate
Men were allowed to
View pornography
We're allowed to touch women in a way that women would not want to be touched in the workplace
You know it was a it was a very
Pratt house type environment
Company settled the case
Agreed to changes practices
Thousands of women
Thousands of dollars
Each
I don't know I don't know what kind what to ask
I get why you want the way the pepper in the 10 things me and doesn't seem that
It seems
Kind of silly
On a certain
Certainly relative to to this case where
Women were being systemically harassed at this rate
And maybe that's an unfair
Comparison but I don't know what what do you think just can you sort of put that together for me
I think if there are cases
The have more societal value than others
And there are cases with
Where people have more
Personal injuries
And others
I'm so there's a spectrum
Of cases that can be brought as class actions
But consumers have a right to recover
$4
Do the math
She says if you bought one of these tins
According to her argument that company should give you you know a couple bucks
Which team small
But
Millions of people have bought these pepperton
And that adds up
A lot of money
There is an FDA regulation about
This is how we called the FDA
They have not acted on this
I'm thinking so that's sort of the point of class
They're like this backup for When government Regulators don't act
Now there is this big backlash against this wave of class at you hear it all the time
Time right like
So many cases clogging up the courts
And businesses have started including these
Clauses in contracts that make it harder for people to sue
Urban challenges in court several weeks of going all the way to the Supreme Court the results there have been mix
So Jacob
We brought all this up with demand response
Arthur Miller
You got this long Arc now
50 years
If
I'll be the life of this rule you created
We're here where we are now how do you
How do you weigh
What you
Done
It's an impossible question
Because you were weighing
We're trying to
Things that are unquantifiable
That is a very clever answer
And true as far as it go
But you
Let's have some fun
How do you feel about
What class action
I believe that in the 50 years
We have had this
Rule
That there are certain class actions that never should have been brought
Admit
That we have burdened our judiciary
Yes
But we've had a lot of good stuff done
We really
Have
Miller says
2030 years ago
Lawyers from around the world used up pointed the US end
And laugh and Marcus
OUC over everything
There's so many class actions clogging up your system
Today he says
That has changed a lot
Dozens of countries around the world
Now have
Their own
Big Country
France
Australia
Taiwan
Brazil
They have all decided
Like we have
They don't want to leave regulation to the regular
They want to backup
They want class action
We'll have a little update on the pepper case
Right after the
This message comes from NPR sponsor Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimums that can be open from anywhere in 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Okay
We originally reported the story back in 2016
And this week
I called up Elizabeth Fagan
She remember is the lead lawyer in the paper case
And I want to know how things were going
So is it over everyone
We have not one we're waiting for the court to rule on a motion for class certification
To the side
Weather everyone who bought pepper
Burton's is a like
Whether they can sue.
What else are you working on in the meantime
We have a case involving Broiler chicken
Nationwide class action involving an an antitrust violations are conspiracy where the
Pictures of our chicken got together to
Reduce the amount of chicken at our stores and raise prices
Planet Money listeners will know the story very well
StayWell
We just did a show about chicken that is sort of the backstory of bacon
It's episode 840
And you're working on something else right
We are we are representing former actresses and actresses are other people in the entertainment industry
Dragons Harvey Weinstein then it's a truly horrific story and what some of these
Women have gone through and how it's affected their careers
I'm in fact really just derailed
I'm aware very promising acting careers
It's truly awful
Best thank you for the update
Thank you
You can email us at Planet Money on NPR. Org
I can attest people actually check it
I actually will appreciate that Nick
You're on Twitter at
Nick Fountain I'm on Twitter Jake Goldstein we all are on Twitter at Planet Money
Our episode today was produced by you make fountain
With help from tally ho
I'm the fountain and I'm Jacob Wilson
Thanks for listening
How's it going where NPR reporters were doing a story on McCormick black pepper
You're about one of those
Are you ready
This is this is like the classic pepperton are you guys from us
Okay
One more
How's it going we work at National Public Radio we're doing a story about pepper you ever bought one of these
Espanol okay
Pimienta
What is the movie similar
Are you middle
Look grandma
Easter dinner menu
Pamela Perez
4K
Paranoia