Support for NPR and the following message come from service now making the world of work
Work better for me
They're cloud-based
Platform and solutions
Deliver digital workflow
Spell create great experiences and unlock productivity for your whole company
More at servicenow.com
The world economic forum
Which takes place each
It's January in Davos Switzerland
Brings a lot of CEOs
And heads of state
Tiny Town in the Swiss Alps
You may have heard the President Trump
Game this year
It's the kind of place where you
You can be online to the bathroom and
Need a former ambassador
And if you just look at
The titles of the panel's it's a pretty
High-minded seeing all that cooperation making the world a better place
I went to a panel called the weaponization of culture
With that Swedish Minister and Yo-Yo Ma
It was another panel called we need to talk about privilege
I can get a ticket to that
But there is a whole other
Because
When deseos billionaire some diplomats
Go out of
The high security cover
Protect your Dome
And down to there
Private parties
And events in hotel shaped like wedding cake
They pass by a street called The Promenade
Mercedes-Benz Mercedes-Benz
Volkswagen
And down here at the Promenade the scene is very different
Your countries that have rented out storefronts
Trying to lure in the influential and Powerful attendees
My first app
Is India House
A lot of people who told us that they've come specifically to the lunches to eat the food
So it's being also a soft power kind of swords
Okay so they come for the food but they learn about the Ambassador
Since it's mutually beneficial in both ways down
This is
Aditya nagarajan
Key points of a series of giant number ones printed on the wall
We number one in global retail development index
Election about
How India means business
India India meet with Texas written on the door
But just pop up
A few doors down to a Timberland shop turned into you
Ukraine house
There instead of samosas and Dry Ginger they're serving Porsche what should you paying by the way
Don't trust Hollywood
Andre kovacic Epcot
His list of the things that
Ukraine is number one in
The pain is number one in your birthday
Quantity of certified IT specialist
Number one in Europe in the quantity of certified it special
That's right
India do they have more rights
Especially
If you want to go cheap you go for India because you're going to pay twice more
Fort Ukrainian programmers why
Pacific epic quotes
Steppin Out
Crane house
I go to the Indonesian Pavilion for some chicken soup and talk about Jakarta startups
And by this point I realize two things about that
First
You never have to pay for
Second
Steam at least in the billionaire bubble is about saving the world
What it really feels like down on the street is
Epcot Center for billionaire
Countries wooing investors by picking their favorites.
Then something odd have
I walk into the spot that Saudi Arabia is rented out
Ali-A Benetton clothing store now it's straight in green the color of the Saudi flag
I can at first it seems like the exact Same Song & Dance
There's Cardamom Coffee being served in the corner at jumbo TV screen with
All of Saudi Arabia's number 1
Registering properties in Saudi Arabia is extremely
Affordables actually 0-coast that attracts a lot of investment number one in that
Number one in access to electricity exactly under 1 and tax payments
Exactly
But then
This funny thing
This guy who's pitching me this list
Name some stamatina Madonna
Kwikset button on the Tempest
So let's look at the bottom line
Worst
CO2 emissions is something that we are very concerned about and so this is something whenever watch list
Diabetes prevalence is something the rankings here
It would Saudi Arabia gets most criticized for
Like having so few women in the workforce
Having lots of migraines
If you write
I think that's what I'm doing well
Well every other country on this devil street is
Showcasing their number one stats
Their best ranking
Saudi Arabia is coming to Davos with a different plan
It got
Database of 700 in
Indicators
In any
Chicken look up where they were
You have nothing to hide
Public data
We have not
Hello and welcome to Planet Money
Gregory Warner today on the show what is Saudi Arabia's endgame
And why asking that question
Actually let me on a totally different Quest
Back up the mountain to figure out
What happens when we see the world and ranks
And ratings
Not just your on the Swiss Alps
But everywhere
Support for NPR in the following message come from servicenow
Making the world of work work better for me
Their cloud-based platform
Form and solutions deliver digital workflow
Clothes that create great experiences for employees and unlock productivity for your whole company
Servicenow digitizes the work your people have to do
So they can do the work they wanted
Using technology
How to make people more productive and engage
Moret servicenow.
Essam Al madani
The guy I met from Saudi Arabia
Is 38 years old
Went to Harvard and
Is a self-described data upset
Fitbit is an example so I'm obsessed with those 10000 steps
Even though my weight doesn't show
He Traxxas steps he cracks asleep when I sleep I look at how many hours I slept and if it is
Set the number of hours in a field good
Attract the ratings of the beaches and restaurants he visits on vacation with his family
Says he can't help it technology in this generation
Is also
The 32 year-old
Crown Prince of Saudi Arabia
Mohammed bin Salman
The story really starts when that Prince was first appointed
In 2015
Any called Hassam into the palace
And I do my interview at 2 a.m.
With his Royal Highness
Which was a bit tonight and I wasn't prepared
When is Summers called in for this 2 a.m. meeting
He's already spent years working for aramco
The Saudi oil company
Can you speak job with tracking
Performance
Efficiency
Now the prince told them to build a similar performance Tracking Center
For the entire country
He wanted to know how the country is doing accurately And Timely
On second you wanted to know
How we are
Doing on the global map
How are we doing the global indicators
How we rank
How would we die
The Saudis build a controller
I said the name in Arabic and English
Call Martha. Which means the cockpit I can you just describe that room for me is a bunch of TV screens
NASA it's awesome show me pictures of the cockpit it totally looks like ground
Control Houston
Except instead of tracking
Rockets and satellites
They're tracking
Unemployment number
Home ownership and something the Saudis used to call the citizen satisfaction index
Citizen satisfaction index
That's what I used to be called now it's called
Beneficiary satisfaction
So investors
Residence
Citizens
This is something that is phenomenal and historical
Of course other countries do have a way to gauge their side effects
National dex
It's called an election
Perfect of course but
At least it is one way we have the voters
Can rate the job the governor
Do it
Saudi Arabia
Is not a democracy
It's World by
1 royal family
They're accountable to no one but themselves
And so they designed it
Launching an app that allows any citizen or investor to to immediately on the spot
Did the government service that they received
And the feedback comes immediately to our reporting cycle goes right to the cockpit
Address to the cockpit and also goes to the ministers themselves
The Crown Prince who hired a song for this job he's got big plans to diversify the economy
Make it less dependent on oil
And to pay for these schemes he plans to float an IPO in the largest oil company in the world
Sessoms former employer
Aramco
For the first time
Foreign investor
Stores will be able to buy stock
In a company
That means that Saudi Arabia has gone from being a country that didn't have to care what people
Suddenly seeking favor with lots of foreign investor
Foreign country
Saudi Arabia is open where open for business
We're open for Partnerships
We're open for learning
And we cannot embark on our transformation
Without being truly humble and interested to learn from others
Which brings us to why Saudi Arabia
I showed up
At Davos why they've rented out this Pentatonix
Presented this data to the globally
What song says is that he's going to be meeting with
Business tycoon
Global leaders
To basically ask everyone the same
Recognize the people in Dallas
Tell us how we can
Read this data diferencia light indicators.
Took off today's
Complex problems in the globe with all
Of these indicators and rankings out there
What should Saudi Arabia focus on
What is
Actually the most relevant
Tamil question
I would like it to be more clear about what relevant
Let's find out
They said goodbye. Song
Made plans with him to check back in at the end of the conference
The Friday find out what he's learned
And as I walk back out of the sliding glass doors onto the slushy sidewalks
I was struck by the odd predicament that sound Arabia and really
Lots of country singer
Need to find this out
We're on the one hand
Countries ranking
Candy
Really important
In terms of investment
Disney Corporation for example reportedly uses one index from the World Bank
World governance
Index
To help it decide which countries to put its factories
But those same countries
They can have very little say on what gets ranked or
How
I started talking about this with folks I was meeting on the Promenade
If your a devil
Over here I just heard
Is the
That's how I met Sandra Rodriguez
She's a sociologist and a fellow at MIT who's actually been thinking a lot about this
This very question who's making the calls
Because
Ranging also means who gets to choose
What are you ranking
What's the best
What are you looking for to rank
Who has
Person who has
Central Rivers actually the year she started thinking a lot about
It was 2006
She's going back and forth to Cameroon in West Africa from her home in Canada
Are laws in Canada made of that are cell phones were kind of
Crappy but not only that they were
Very expensive
And you would arrive in in Cameroon and suddenly you would have
LED under an umbrella with
7 cellphones and people would just pay $0.25 to use them
And it was really impressed by the use of cell phones
Think about this
This was
12 years ago
Before smartphone
Cell phones
They're pretty expensive
And yet the poorest cameroonian
Could rent
The phone for a moment to
Make a call or send a message
But I do know that the big debate was the ranking
Because suddenly you and ranking decided that for
Country to be digitally
Advanced
It didn't mean anymore to have access to
Digital technology but own it
Cassandra wasn't quite sure why these rankings changed
Weather maybe the cell phone companies were involved
But she says what happened next
African countries
Behind the rankings
To back down
Africa loses again
You know North American countries win
Tattoo School
Some people are happy of course most of the rest of the world
This kind of politics can make it into even the dryer sound
Prince's take the world things
Ease of doing business index
2 years ago the country Chile
Dropped hard in those rank
Leggings for round 35 in the world to run 50
And then this month
The chief Economist at the World Bank Paul Romer
Revealed that this slide downward wasn't
Because Chile suddenly became harder place to do
Do business
It was at the World Bank
Had tweaked
The methodology in a way that punish chili
And it punished it
Right after
The country elected as socialist
This was such a scandal that Paul Romer
Futon the whistle on this
Ended up resigning 6 days later that just goes to show
How hard it is to
Understand who
Race
In the first place the indexes that will be looked at
Do you think
One of them is
Here at devils
They're probably a lot of them here if you're looking for the Illuminati that's something else
If I couldn't find the Illuminati at least
Define some member of the indicator Elite
It will must be here at Devil's right
Except that turned out to be not
Easy to do I called the World Bank
Their senior staff were all booked up with meetings
Same thing with the UN
I almost gave up and then
I heard about
A professor
Pitch Perfect dabo's resume
She's a Rhodes scholarship
Advise the IMF
Herewith
The world economic forum and
15 dogs
Professor ngaire woods
Agreed to give me a little bit of time
Should and found a quiet corner and
I told her about this Quest
They had
To meet someone who makes the indicators
Are you them
No but
I know that that's not true I mean
I have been put into
Indicated
In fact she is in the middle of designing an important new indicator
Right now
What would a government
Effectiveness indicator look like the government Effectiveness indicator she's doing it with Oxford
She also consulted other things like
The UN human development index
Which have been involved with in the past
Social Progress Index
So so glad I choose some of my mission
And why you think that all this work fine-tuning the ranking of countries
It would make her more of a believer in the power of data
It's actually done the opposite
She is a total indicator skeptic
Countries by here at Davos to be
Tell me about that list you know I'm going to come top or I'm going to move up to point then
That shows that when I was minister of the economy I really did great things
But actually
Them reaching that indicated might just mean that they pass the law
It might not mean that the law is being implemented or that it's being enforced Reddit actually changing anything on the ground
Talking to Mary
I suddenly got this sinking feeling
Here I was
Up here on the mountain finally face-to-face with a member of the Davos Elite
Indicator maker or advisor whatever end
Well down there
In the rest of the world with countries
Cities were
Killing themselves to be first in the rankings
The rankings
She apparently doesn't trust
Then
The person I've met who helps measure the world
Healthiest
Is actually not about the measurement of these not about the measurable
At this point we were talking about how the United Nations has set all these
Ambitious goals
The Year 2030
Gold Spike
End Hunger in
In Copper
Now if they'd just on that everybody would have said it's all tyranny
So now they've done a deeper exercise of saying he will all the different things we should measure under each one
To measure progress to woodston
For the next decade or more till
The year 2030
Countries will be arguing about who ranks better in ending poverty in ending hunger and yeah
Those numbers will definitely be fudged
And they'll probably have politics in them
But she says that without the numbers without
Some kind of scorecard
It's hard to get us to collaborate on anything
So
Even if these rankings don't
Actually tell us a real score
They may at least
Encourage us to play the same
After the break
I bring that message
Search for the mountain
Down to the Promenade
Support for this podcast in the following message come from Madewell where the motto is good days start with
Straight jeans
How did they make them so great
Madewell starts with premium denim
Then offers men's and women's styles for seriously everyone
Also you can recycle any brand of jeans in a Madewell store
And they'll give you $20 off a new pair
They work with the blue jeans go green program
Return old jeans
Housing insulation for communities in need
Terms apply
Ready to find your perfect fit
Stop by a Madewell store or go to madewell.com
Friday morning
The final day of the conference
I came back down to the Promenade
Talk with someone from Saudi Arabia in storefront
I got to say
I was kind of nervous to
Tell him what I learned on the mountain
Because remember he and his team it's been all this time putting together an iPad app that
All these hundreds of indicators and exactly where every country ranked
He come to Davos to present this thing
And what I've heard from them
People on the mountain with the
They don't take these rankings all that seriously
It turned out that his son
I've been hearing that line all week
Spot on
And I'm very overwhelmed by this feedback
What indicates Northwest been hitting this as
They taste good indicators of fine but the discussions we can have
But when you say spot on
I'm so surprised that you say that
Because I thought you would take note to say that science
Data is data just
Established
The Daytona always have
Some bias is right
After all his meetings at Davos
One thing has I want to do is take this
IPad app
With all its thousands of graphs
Charts and rankings of countries
And add a comment
So you could actually
Criticize
What's the rank of the number you've been given
Literally turning
The number
The score
Into the beginning of a conversation
And that's a lot more messy
Ben
Is first version
About Clean Vines
But maybe
It's more the way the world
We'd love to hear what you think of the show send us an email where it's Planet Money at
Npr.org
Find us on Facebook
What Twitter
Will have a link to Saudi Arabia's measurement tool Kobe International performance hub
Find out where your country ranks
That's on our website NPR. Org / money
Today Show is produced by Sally Helm are senior producers Alex goldmark
And Bryant urstadt and the show
If you're looking for something else to listen to
I host a different podcast
Called rough translation
Work hard at work on her second season our first season is out in the world that haven't heard it
Go give it a listen it has stories about how the things that we are talking about here in the United States
How they're playing out somewhere else in the world
Rough translation
Fighted wherever you get
Podcast
I'm Gregory Warner
Thanks for let