Support for NPR comes from investor.gov
Presenting this mess
When it comes to investing
We all have Quest
And investor.gov has answers
If you're free resource for
Tools tips and information about investing
Before you invest
Investor.gov
Can you hear us yes hello hey we're up and running Catherine eckel runs a behavioral economics program it
Texas A&M University where she studies the many reasons people donate money
So
Suppose that you
Really like Planet money but Along Comes somebody who says
I'll just pay for planet
Can someone who only cares that planet money exists
Would reduce their giving
Does Planet Money doesn't need it as much anymore that's a rational thing to do at that point
But part of the motive for giving seems to be
I don't just care that Planet Money exist
People want to be the one who's doing the support
Okay and that's the Warm Glow
The Warm Glow
As in like how I feel like an actual thing they're getting
From giving
Actual utility
Okay
I'm going to I'm going to make like a little commercial
I'll just
Reminding people that warm glow exists they could have a piece of it to try it
What that feels like
A beating heart
Intuit
Thank you so much professor eichel
My pleasure
All right I've got a commercial to work on in the meantime
You can support Planet Money by donating to your local NPR station
Just go to donate. Npr.org
Planet Money
They will know you're giving because you listen
Again that's donate. Npr.org Planet Money
Kid drummer
Sally Helm you went on a trip to tell me about it a couple weeks ago I went to Branford High School in Branford
Connecticut
To watch a play
An adaptation of Charles Dickens
Christmas
I want to say
First things first
They treat you right in Brandon
The play's director of met me at the school door
The culinary arts class
Cook me dinner what you have
A ham
Scalloped potatoes
Green beans
Side salad
Before things got started I sat down with the star of the
My name is Adam Jackson and I am playing Ebenezer Scrooge
Scrooge
Is literature's most famous mice
And the plot of A Christmas Carol
Is basically these three ghosts
Spirit of Christmas Past
Spirit of Christmas present
Spirit of Christmas Yet to Come
Convincing Scrooge to be a better person
He starts off
And you have to play him completely meaning completely rude and completely evil sort of
But then by the end of the show he's everyone's best friend
About an hour after our interview the entire cast got together in the school's choir
Baba baba baba Sali I can see in your eyes that you recognize
I did High School theater
That is the sound of four dozen teenagers
Warming up their vocal cords before a show
Mi Mo mu alright repeat after me
Can I be
Adam and all the other kids are standing in the big circle buzzing with
Pre-show jitters
Everyone's wearing their butt
Frock coats and vest and old timey dresses
Boys tryouts
Country girls wearing top hats with their hair in ponytails
Play the boy parts
After the warm ups
The place director
The slight silver-haired retired teacher named Maria ogren
Is the Nook tablet
Last night
You proved
That you could do this today
And tonight
You're going to prove that last night
Was not an accident
Okay
You'll melt look
Part of my reason
Traveling all the way
From New York to Branford
It's just that I have this tremendous soft spot
For the earnestness of high school
Quiet quiet quiet
Close your eyes
Set her down
All right
We Are One
Have a great show
But there was another reason I was there the play they were doing that
A Christmas
It is so much more than just a story
About whether the Ghost of Christmas Past can convince Ebenezer Scrooge
To be a
Decent human being
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Keith Romer and I'm Sally helm
Today on the show The Secret War taking place in the pages of Akron
Carol
Yes the story is about saving time Tunes life and teaching screwed to the true meaning of Christmas
But it turns out
Charles Dickens is up to weigh more than just telling a ghost story with a happy in
A Christmas Carol
Is this knock-down-drag-out fight
Charles Dickens and some of the biggest names in the history of economic
This message comes from NPR sponsor game
The Bold way to steady growth
People often think annuities are too conservative
Too complex or only for retirees
But annuity
These can be a smart way to hedge Market
And earn guaranteed returns
Game Bridge aims to change the game
By offering simplified annuity
He's in a Sleek digital experience
That replaces fine print and phone.
With clear conditions and a direct
Loafy model
Learn more at gamebridge. Life
8 / NPR
Game Bridge
Which is not available in all states
All right
Just in case it has been a while since you read A Christmas Carol or watched The Muppets or Disney or
Creepy CGI Jim Carrey version
Here's where we start
It is 19th century London
The Industrial Revolution is in full swing
And we need to start of our story
Ebenezer Scrooge
Oh yes
Mystic
Have you come to make payments on your new
It comes to tomorrow
Fresa
We will need more time
No
Set
A contract is a contract
I would have my payment when it is due
Scrooge is somebody who has gotten very very rich
Presumably from the industrial
Ocean itself somehow
But he is not about
Least of all
Poor
Limitlessly cheerful
Employee
Bob
And a merry Christmas
Swiss Hall
God bless us
Bob Cratchit has an even more relentless
Bosun
Tiny Tim who hobbles around on his
Crutch
Everyone
On Christmas Eve Scrooge gets visited by a series of ghost
I'm the ghost of
Christmas pop
I am the ghost
Christmas present
Are you
The Ghost of Christmas Yet to Come
The ghost show him all these fish
Including one work
Tiny Tim dies
Presumably because Scrooge doesn't pay Bob Cratchit in
Divisions work
The ghost convince Scrooge to
Stop being a miser
In fact Scrooge become super generous
Give Bob Cratchit a raise
Titan lifts
A Christmas Carol
Is one of the iconic holidays.
It's basic message that we should all be nicer to the poor
It's part of how we think about Christmas
Itself now
But
When you sit down to read a Christmas
Miss Carol
You are actually diving right into the center of this massive argument that has
So little to do with Christmas
And so much to do
With economic
Surprised
In 1843 when it Christmas Carol was written
The big economic question was
What the hell is going on with this Industrial Revolution
Where is all this money coming
Why
Are there all these poor people leaving the countryside and coming to the cities
Is all of this change even a good thing
The decade of the 1840s in England
That was increasing
Mass
Poverty that's Michael Slater he wrote a biography of Charles Dickens title
Charles Dickens
Wages
What kept very very low in England and it was kind of rule capitalism if you like
Slater says
The inspiration for Christmas
Miss Carol Dickens red
Parliamentary report
About the terrible working conditions of
Poor children
We're talkin 8 year olds working
14 hour days in Coal Mines I just
Everybody be clear the position of NPR is that that is bad
And so
Was Charles dick
Dickens was horrified by
What he read yeah but
Charles Dickens
He's not just some random tender-hearted dude
He is a super
Famous
Tenderhearted
Back at the time that we're in 1843 there is no TV
What is instead yes
Correct
When Dickens go to America in 80
Thousands of people turned out to see him in every city
He is a huge deal
So
Super Famous Charles Dickens decide
He is going to use his Fame
To take a stand
And so he decided he would write a pamphlet
A cold in a few
On behalf of the poor man's child
To be fair that was a thing back then
Tablets
And for a while
Dickens is pretty fired up about his pamphlet
But then he remembers
No wait
Charles Dickens
You're in the freaking pamphlet
He had the very sudden inspiration
How to write a short book
In the form of
Almost like a kind of fairy story
And he said this would have him at his house and times more effect than any articles
But he could ride
Would you go sit there
Dickens write to a friend
Says his new story is going to
To hit with the force of a sledgehammer and you want to know what he is going to smash
With a sledgehammer
This new academic discipline called
Political economy
Balloon alcoholic
These political Economist they wanted to do for social sciences
What Isaac Newton had done for physics
But instead of discovering the laws that govern motion and
Forest
They wanted to discover the laws
That governs how human beings
Charles Dickens
Not a fan you just hated
Questions to do with Humanity being
Dealt with in a
Episode of
Coldly scientific mathematical sort of way
He was all for the heart rather than the head does it work
Okay so Dickens captain of
The heart team
Captain of the coldly scientific head team
Adam Smith
Adam father of economics
That's the one in 1776
He publishes his 900 something page book
An inquiry into the nature and causes of the wealth
Of Nations
They should be buddies Charles Dickens love creating 900-page books
Bleak House
Dorit depending on what you get David Copperfield
A mutual friend
I looked at it
Okay so there are a lot of ideas in the wealth of May
But for most readers
The big takeaway
Self-interest is
If everyone just looks out for themselves
Then the Invisible Hand of the market
Is going to do an amazing job
Of allocating capital and labor
And the economy is going to grow and it was going to be better
People are going crazy for
Fitness idea for Adams
Efficiency and self-interest
They're going to save us all
When you read A Christmas Carol you can almost hear Dickens muttering to himself is
Rights
Yeah take that exchange that we listened to before between
Scrooge and
Warminster Pembroke
This scene in the play doesn't actually occur in dickens's original but it is definitely true to the book's description of sky
Screwed as a quote
Merciless
Teresa
We will need more time
No
Set
A contract is a contract
I would have my payment 22
It's pretty hard to be more self-interested than Ebenezer Scrooge
Picture of
Business
Is business
Good day
Charles dickens's version of Adam Smith is
Such a jerk Adam Smith though
She is just the tip of the iceberg for
There's another scene
This one straight from the book
Where to people come by
Asking for donations
For a Christmas charity
We are raising a fun to buy the poison food and warmth that this time of year to be surprised to learn that Ebenezer Scrooge
Will not be donating this Christmas
But if you listen carefully
To the way he says no
You will hear Dickens taking shots
At a second
Bleckley County
Mai Tai
What about the prison
Who's in the workhouses
Those that badly off my stove
Forgot to die
In 1843
If you heard that last phrase
Surplus population
You would 100% no
Food Charleston
Was talking about
Is that terrible phrase about the Surplus population
That's a reference
To the Reverend Moses and mail
Tea
H u s
Okay nurullah podcasting that I'm making up for this show
When one scholar
Literally spells the name of a historical figure
You have to find another scholar to
Explain that historical figure
Sally Helm
I accept your terms
I'm broke Mayhew I am a professor of historical geography and intellectual history at the University of Bristol in
Indian ice kingdom Mayhew wrote a book about the Reverend Thomas Robert Malthus
Titled Malthus Malthus was a pioneering glitter Economist his main work
Walls a book Gold an essay on the principle of population which was published in 1798
He's most famous for arguing the population will inevitably outstrip
The results is it needs to survive on that folder that will be some form
Oh
Population collapse or crisis in our ability to sustain ourselves is a civilization said he's known as a
Prophets of Doom Isis
Malthus was not a big believer
In the possibility of economic
What he saw
When he looked at the history of the world
Was not progress
But instead this endless back and forth
Good Times
And bad.
In Good Times
Everybody would be like life is great I'm going to have a giant family
And then the bad guy
Wages would go down
Food prices would go up
And poor people would start
And now this
Quite understandably
Thought that this was terrible
But
He also thought that in economic terms
The root of the problem was that there were just too many
People
People who starved
They were the
Surplus
Population
Here's Michael Slater again
Being a romantic also loved most of his grades
Part of this is Dickens
Deep suspicion that in their quest to understand how markets work
Political Economist like mouth is
Had completely lost sight of the fact
That these were people
Not just numb
But because his real problem with Malthus wasn't
Like the form of his thinking
It was the Practical conclusion
That mouth is came to because of that thing
Conclusions about what Society should actually do
About the pool
Mai Tai
Just about the prisons and the White House
Those that badly off my stove
In 1843 there were a lot of people who were badly off
The Industrial Revolution was
Kind of economic
But it was not a miracle that everybody shared in
And if you were really poor
And you couldn't find work there was pretty much just one option
The workhouse
Workhouses had always been pretty horrible
Families would get broken up
Mint 1 Section women to another children to another
Everyone would get some terrible job
Breaking rocks or literally picking apart
Rope in individual strands
Exchange
You would be fat
You wouldn't starve
But earlier in the 1800's there started to be this concerned that some of the people trying to get poor relief from
The government
Could have found other ways.
To keep from starving if they really wanted to
So in 1834
Parliament passed what are called
The new poor law
The ancient SE full Polo is designed to make it work harnesses
Much less
I can type track to that's not the right word but to
More frightening as it were
And
One of the most famous proponents of these new harsher workhouses was
U guessed it
Thomas Malthus
There is this even darker Jabet mouth
Hidden in the Christmas
Amor Direct
About not caring enough about the children of the poor
In one of the visions that the Ghost of Christmas present shows.
Scrooge sees his clerk Bob Cratchit at home
Prepare ourselves
Finest Christmas dinner in all of London
May the Lord make us truly thankful
Gratiot is this wonderfully loving dad
But he is also a kind of stand in all the people who are being left behind by the industrial
While the scrooges of the world are getting rich
Bob Cratchit is taking home at very little in wages
And because he's so poor his son Tiny Tim
Tights
In a second vision
Scrooge watches
Bob
Gathered his family around Tiny Tim's unused little crutch
And tell them to never forget their
But when we remember how patient
Tell Michael he was even though he was a little child
We shall not easily quarrel among ourselves
What you doing so
Bob Cratchit is a good dude
But he's poor
And he has a big family is Tiny Tim apart of the Surplus population
I assume the tickets is main point
Is
The
In a cold
Utilitarian calculus Tiny Tim is Surplus population
At this point in the Bible cast I will blame
Basically no one
Who feels like they would much rather be on team Dickens
Venti mouth
Am I sensing
Are you on team melfes
I mean what
Is so Malthus is the scapegoat for a bunch of riders
Including maybe Dickens
Who never even read it
Strawman okay but part of it
Is that Malthus is this kind of tragic intellectual figure
Because he was kind of right
But he was just about to be totally wrong
Sally
I brought you a girl
My favorite oh my God
It's quite a graph
Okay it is
World GDP over the last two Millennia from the Year One
Bay City prison
Strong timeframe GDP gross domestic product
Basically every bushel of wheat
House every Christmas wreath that got made each year
4 mm
And it's basically flat flat flat and then at a certain point in
What we say
Old 1798 or so
It shoots up
World GDP just goes
Crazy
Goes into a base without a vertical line from them
Super almost 2000 years GDP growth is like
.3% is basically
Hasn't been invented yet malthus's right but then
The Industrial Revolution
Then he's wrong basically
The day he publishes
The economy shoots up
All of a sudden there's
Not just
Is plenty of food there's plenty of everything
This is that super steep growing part of the graph
Steam power factories
Mechanization
The economy the British economy especially takes off
Basically in the 45 years between mouth is putting on his book and 7th
98 n tickets publishing A Christmas Carol in 1843
No. Growth didn't get shared by everyone there were still
Plenty of Fish
But
Human beings show they could figure out how to grow the economy
The population could grow and there would still be enough food for everyone to eat
So basically history proved Malthus
Totally wrong
I just want to point out
History also kind of proves Dickens Rock
I'm for almost the exact same reason as what happened to Malthus Malthus misses the possibility that
Economic growth
Because economic growth has never happened
But Dickens completely misses this second
Huge economic shift
That is happening right under his feet
A shift by the way that political Economist like Adam Smith
Said was going to happen and then does
Right around 1843
Wage growth
Is weird growth of a sort
In
I have a sword Christmas.
Do the little number on screws into a different person
No no no no good.
I will honor Christmas in my heart and
New Leon miserly Ebenezer Scrooge
Give Bob Cratchit a raise
Wage growth a Merry Christmas Bob my good fellow
I told raise your salary
With your struggling family
Makeup app
It is not
Just
Scuttles of coal
Tiny Tim lives
Surplus population problem solved by the miracle of the Christmas spirit
Okay
I'm about to be dispersed
Go there
I know that the point of A Christmas Carol is that everyone should be kind and generous to the poor
Adobe clear
I am for that
But the secret to wage growth
Canopy
Ghost visiting Employers in the middle of the night and convincing them to be more generous
What happened
Right around the time that Dickens write a Christmas carol all of that Industrial Revolution wealth that the Bob cratchit's of the world weren't
Seeing any of it started sort of seeing some of it
And that was for tons and tons of
Productivity went up
More and more of those Factory owners had to
To compete for workers
Labor organizing help
We just started this long long rides that lifted a lot of Bob cratchit's of the world out of
Now look
Charles Dickens want his readers
To use their hair
Consider
Bob Cratchit and Tiny
Tim
Is real living breathing human being
Not as data points on a graph
Care about making their lives by
Okay
Political economist
Then and now
What's a
Look making that graph
Using numbers to describe the world as accurately as hell
Possible
Sometimes that is a necessary first step
Making people's lives better
There is something about those grass
That just does not sit right
I asked Ben Klaus who plays Bob Cratchit
Why he thinks Tiny Tim end up surviving
Second question
Construed
Save the day musically
And
Tiny Tim is the result of that he's alive he's well
He's doing okay
If I made the argument
That would really save Tiny Tim
Was the increasing productivity of the Industrial Revolution would you just say that I'm kind of a scrooge
Probably are
This is what I came here to learn
Crowne Plaza
This message comes from NPR sponsor game
The Bold way to steady growth
People often think of nobodies are too conservative
Too complex or only for retirees
But annuities
These can be a smart way to hedge Market
And earn guaranteed returns
Game Bridge aims to change the game
By offering simplified annuities
He's in a Sleek digital experience that replaces fine print and phone.
With clear conditions and a direct
Loafy model
Learn more at gamebridge. Life
8 / NPR
Game Bridge
Which is not available in all states
Alright warm gloves
Warm fuzzy feeling you can get
From supporting Planet Money
Here we go
It's raining outside but
You're inside next to the fire
Oh the water is ready for your hot cocoa in
Good news your best friend showed up
I brought you a music box
They pull you in for a big warm hug
Only one thing could feel better than this
Just go to donate.
Npr.org
Planet Money
Were you can support Planet Money by donating to your local NPR station
Enter there
Just bask in the warm glow of supporting planet
Donate. Npr.org
If you are in high school play that has a secret economic message we want to come send us
Does an email Planet Money at npr.org you can also reach out to us on Facebook
Twitter and Instagram special things today to Anthony Brundage for helping me understand the history of the poor laws
And to maria ågren chris lemieux
Jeff Strasburg everyone at Branford High School
The performers you heard throughout the show where Adam Jackson been Klaus
Lisa kroeber Alexa
Brown henna Bloomquist
Sofia Coppola
Rita miklus Abbey Boyle Dorian Hayes style Ramallah Heiser
Robert olearczyk
And in
Introducing as Tiny Tim
Alexis assault
Today Show was produced by Alexi Horowitz Ghazi
Alex goldmark Isleta bunny supervising producer Bryant
I'm finally home
And I'm Keith Romer thanks for listening
Is it Thomas is it Robert is a pastor what do I call
Is William Thomas Robert that he's known by his own family as robot
So
Take your pet credit
What About Bob
Occasionally unless he's bought but II as a rub it myself I didn't think so
Because you don't want to be called Bob he said he felt the most of most of the contemporary
Artist to him all to Toma Sol to rub it and if you know him a protocol in communicating about him
With him is probably Thomas
I really want to call Bob