Hey guys
Couple things
The show is a rerun we originally reported it into that
15th
Also it Future Sailors and
People who curse like sailor
Think of a delicious fish
And Marco Hagerty
Has caught
I've trolled for salmon
Avada Hearing fished up here and Dungeness
Crab
And
Halibut
I meant Maca on the pier in Homer Alaska
You got these great big bushy eyebrows
Albert Einstein hair tucked behind a Black Beret
Michael loves the
Competitive
Thrill
And Alaska used to be the most
Competitive place of all
Fishing season would open on a
Certain day
And it was a race
A race to get your boat out in the water
I get all the fish
The whole Harbor would just be a buzz
And there were a lot of people beating the docks looking for jobs in there were lot of boats participating in the fish
Shree and it was
Wide-open nobody was limited into how much they could
To catch they were only limited and how much time they could
Spend people made a good living which attracted more
And all together everyone is catching more and more fish
So in order to protect that fish population
This season got
Shorter and
And shorter in 1970
Season for halibut with 150 days long
Then it was shortened to 100 days
And by the early 1990s
It was 20
4 hours
4 Hour opening
It's just a few times a year
Just imagine how intense this
These fishermen are trying to earn their
Higher your salary
And a handful of
24-hour Sprint
It became known as the derby
An all-out race to fish
And back then you would see thousands and thousands of boats all going out to
Everything that's loaded wood now
Out in the right kind of shape and the wrong kind of shape
That was a open-access and people had
Everybody was involved in you'd have skips go out
We had the sinkings
But if you wanted to make money
You had to go
You went out if you were sick
You went out of sweater
Vici boat
You went out
Phoenix.
You know what you're doing
You went out there were dark clouds
Threatening on the rise
And even if the weather was good and the fishing was good
You overloaded your boats during the Derby Days
And that man
Your boat might sink
The 24-hour Derby made fishing in Alaska one of the most deadly jobs
In the country
Fisherman has higher death rates
Firefighters
Pilots
Police officers
Finally someone said
Have to figure out a better way to do
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm just checking the other show how fishing went from deadly to
Well saver
The solution was not about getting better gear or
Better Warning Systems
It was an economic fix
One that could help solve much bigger problem
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their own webs
Using customizable layout
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online presence
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
You the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
It's Lulu Miller and I am back with a new story for invisibilia
Is about the
Pleasures it's just electric and the dangers there should nothing more Gary of trying to live
Between Two Worlds
You can find invisibilia on NPR one or wherever you get your pot
So you have to ask
What kind of person
Would go out in a tiny little boat
In miserable dangerous weather
The catch fish for
For 24 hours
Everyone
Everyone in Homer Alaska
You can pretty much grab anyone on the fish.
And they would tell you these
Crazy stories about the Derby Days
Like I met Kurt Van Doren
He goes by the name
Carcass carcass
Cow looks like a carcass he's wiry thin with crazy hair
And he's a dick
He works on other people's boats
Has told me
The reason the Derby got so dangerous
It's because the government chose what day it was
Months in advance
Way beforehand
They didn't know the weather when they chose
The day and that meant the weather could be really bad and you would
Still go out
Chris remembers one
Really bad day
Well I was on watch
And I'm just sitting up there I think
Man this is a 1912 old wood boat
How nice the boat was taking these ways were in like 45 to 50 Footers
And when I mean you're huge and it's a little 52 football Tree in curlers you know
We're going home and all and I'm going out and taking a pretty nice
Feeling pretty good
He's doing so good because the fishing had been really really great
And that man
He was going to get his share of that cats and he thought
She could get about $15,000
He even picked out what
He's going to buy
A new truck
So that's what he's thinking but the next week
All of a sudden we took one and we're not coming back up
Real buried
Warriors all over jacket
Mark get up
Rebecca buried around we're not we're not
Bismarck was the skipper
It doesn't seem like we're coming back
The next wave hit us and we just leaned right over
And it's like
Martian get everybody the fox out we're going down
Perkis grab the crate with the life raft
And popped it open
And a big wave came up
Wash the liferaft overboard the brand new one
Laurel Market
Discovery we still got the old one is released when we pull the release
It's stuck in the crate
We're trying to break down a crate when you're off
Find polling we're all in water up to her waist
I mean we're talking big smokers
Big wave
The carcasses were 50 ft
Hi
The wind was blowing a hundred miles per hour
And they decide to jump
Swim for that Lifeboat
I was being Swept Away
They hauled themselves inside
And the first thing we hear is called
Louchem pig crossword
Umar has been together in form and route for four people in it
It's not very big
Now we here. Oncoming right away
Aroma going my God is good
So now we start locking our arms
Around each other
Showing their waves hit
When I don't
Bash into each other
Now we here
It's the Coast Guard airplane
And I'll tell you the most beautiful sound in the world is a C-130
That's when you really think you're going to
Carcass and the three other guys they all make it back
They all survived
They just don't have the fish anymore they don't have
The money and the carcass
Not getting any
But the crazy thing about carcasses
She goes back every year he told me he thinks five times
Five ships of God out under carpet
Still goes back
What cities do not go out with turkey
I will
You know I've been to Alaska
And
You talk to these guys
End of bravado really is
Stunning the ability to just
Keep going out and
Enemies has so many people and even old-time fisherman
Like Clem tillion
He's 90 years old and he fish for decades
She was looking at all these thinking
And just wondering
Why
Young man loves you
Axon the excitement it was going black Las Vegas you went roaring out of the storms and you caught all you can
Caption
The guy is a
Took the most risk
Chuck Bluff
1 a.m.
They went looking at anything else
Except
The fun of it
Klamathon the Fisheries Council
His job was to help
Suzhou population
24-hour Derby
Was in fact
Really good at protecting fish
Because the catch was limited
By the number of minutes of the day no one was overfishing
But he started to worry that the rules the government
Set up
We're basically encouraging all these young men
And there were real consequences
3000 fisherman that went out
We didn't make it back
It was a very stupid sister
It was
Murder By government you might say
Order by governor
Yes
And
A few of us were looking at other ways of doing it
There was an idea out there
A way to protect the fish
And make fishing safer
Instead of limiting the amount of time people
Limit the total amount of fish that
Could be caught
If you were fishermen
It's been having two fish
Any 24-hour Sprints is
Is crazy race
Clinton wanted a system where would be
Basically leisurely
Because each fishermen would be guaranteed
A certain amount of fish
The beginning of the season
It was this simple solution
But anytime you distribute something valuable you know people are going to fight
The cat should be distributed among boat owners
And Captain
Please remember basically halibut is
Money
If you live in Alaska. That's how you make your living
I thought that the cat should be distributed among
Boat owners in
And his thinking was
Those are the people who have invested a lot of money in
Monkey rental they should reap the reward
But when guys like carcass heard about this
Pissed
Carcass de novo
He was a deckhand
He worked on someone else's boat
Hauling in the fish
And risking his
And it was a real ridiculous thing to each one of us crew members
Shouldn't have got our share of it you know what it's like
The owners knew what was going on the owners
Kept it to themselves
You could see why they would be
You so upset under the old 24-hour Derby system
The fish what's the
People who worked
The heart
The people took the most chances
That's what the frontier mentality
But now the government was coming
And saying
You are winners
And your loser
Boat owners who the winners
The boaters were going to be
And the deckhands like carcass they weren't going to get
Anything
They're being left out of the system
They could fish and they could still work
But they weren't going to get a guaranteed share of the
The catch so you can understand why
The losers the deck hands
Basically confronted the fish react
They confronted Clem tillion
Mass demonstrations on sometime
My niece had her tires slashed in my kids got beat up in the playground I mean it was Island
Your kids got beat up
Yeah because the other way with two limbs kids you know
Amda
I was just
One of the things that happened
When people don't like something they can get
Pretty mad about it
Especially when it's their livelihood
And I was rearranging their whole livelihood
The Clement and the Fisheries council did look at other ways
That could be considered more
They are they looked at a lottery
System where everyone gets in
Equal chance
Or an auction
Where the permits went to the highest bidder
But no one wanted to pay for something that they had always gotten for
And so with no better option
Clam drafted the proposal
Guess what they're going to do
Fish scientist would estimate how many halibut there were in the sea
How many cookies
The cot
Then the Boat Owners would each get a share of the fish
More race
Derby
He went into effect in 1995
And when I visited Homer Harbor
You could see how different it was compared to those Derby Days
Will have that right after this break
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence
And run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial and when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
What does it take to start the something from nothing and what does it take to actually build it
Every week of how I built this
Speak with Founders behind some of the most
Inspiring companies in the world
Find it on NPR one or wherever you get your podcast
When I wanted to go out fishing
I didn't have to wake up
Super early
I didn't have to race
I just called up a boat owner and
She said I could come anytime
No rush
So this is about
As you can see this is a work boat
It's Nathan
Not just for show
No
This is Christy and David Frey they own the boat the realest
The realist as in
Fishing reel
Realistic
And they tell me they have 1700 pounds of halibut to fish
That's our quota for the whole year
Nf3 specific 1700 how they come up
The government looked at
How much fish the fries caught in those older
And they took an average and use that to calculate their share
Not easier to enforce
A time limit 24 hours then is to enforce over specific number like 17 lb of halibut
How do they enforce
David says they're BB's federal agents
From Noah
And they would police the dock
When they implemented this system
They just figured everybody was going to be
Criminal I guess
So that brought
So that mean had
Blackjack
Sonic
Gun lights
You know come down to my boat on my boat with a damaged gun
What Jagged lucky you didn't go in the water
You're damn lucky I was
Alaskans are bigger to their freedom and I'm sure at first this fishing quota
Do you like this
Like straight jacket on what they did on the whole
Freedom
Swashbuckling fishing thought
People were not into it at first
Hatsune fisherman saw the advantages
If the weather is bad they could just stay at home
Cigna at the Manor and going like
That there is no way
And it goes further than that if you don't want to fish all season
You can take a break and Lease out your quota
You can have someone else fishing
And Dave and Christy have basically double the amount of fish that they can catch
Buy leasing out other people share
That sounds like a good time
Start the Fry's Drive the boat out of the harbor Christie suits up put on this orange rain slicker
And she puts a few cans of Redbull in the cooler
David beats the Herring and salmon octopus.
I call it a salad
The gear goes into the water
And a few miles of line with hundreds of schools out to the Bottom of the Sea we're out for about 8 hours
And it's so cold
You don't see another
Commercial fishing boat
For the whole day
And that by the way is the whole point of the new sister
Now that people can trade or sell away their quotas
Temple donors have taken this
Easy money
They've given their fish to someone else
And have totally gotten out of the business
The number of fishing boats is only a third of what it was before
And the theory is
The only people left are the best and most efficient
Picture of it
Repeat that the club know they're like one big muscle trying to like
Get out of the boat
The Fighter
Christie puts a knife through the guilt
And then quickly remove the gut
She said in the past
During the Derby Days
Should have time to take care of the fish like this
Just threw all the fish on ice
And Hope
Everything stayed fresh
So it's better to get it on the boat it is so much better
She says it's more delicious
Okay so the Halibut quota system
Seems to be doing exactly what it's designed to do
Delicious
Preventing overfishing
And the death rate for fishermen United match of the top-of show has
And in some ways this is a beautiful model for managing any scarce
This is exactly what we're talking about when you came back from Alaska that
This model
Did they have for resources in Alaska is it
Pretty good model for something like
Climate change
Everything limit amount of
Pollution a limited amount of carbon that we should let out of the war
Every question really is
How do you allocate
Should we give pollution credits to
Factories in China or two
People are commuting in LA
It's essentially the same question as they faced in Alaska which is how do you take
Something that everyone wants
And
Divvy up
Go to Fairway in a way that doesn't make people
Terribly upset
The key question is
Fairness
And you can see from the Alaska case
It is really hard it took
20 years for the fisherman to get used to this system
And it was only a couple thousand of them and they still Grumble about how it All Shook out
Well they are fishermen and fishermen who grumble
For a living even the people who are winners under this scenario who got the
The fish allocation
Can go out 3
Long fishing rod
It's only the fish jump into the boat
I mean it still
At its core
I really
Call job
When I went out with Christy and David
They only caught 6 steps the whole day
The thing is now
They can go out tomorrow
I guess we'll see what happens eternal optimist
For the record just did bring back some smoked fish
It was delicious
You can see more of our stories on NPR. Org money or you can check out her Facebook page facebook.com
If you'd like to comment on Today Show
We would love to hear it when you tried Twitter
At Planet Money
Or if you want to get personal I'm at radius
And there are a couple of people I'd like to thank Billy Sullivan and he boiling Ivy and Speedy Shane Hawk
To the expiry
BBCOR
Our episode today was produced by Nick fountain
I'm Robert Smith
Lyme testing
Thanks for listening
What is coming up here
Hot Wheels are watching
GoNoodle
Tell the weight
Aesthetic bro