There's this rustic Little Beach town in northern Jamaica one reggae bar on the beach with a tin roof
When the tropical rain comes out of nowhere everyone runs into this bar
A self-described Rastaman is in there singing reggae calling everyone girlfriend
Very first time I bless my eyes on you girl
It's not the kind of Beach town that tourists watch
This is a local
Okay it's called
Silver Satin
And
It's because ex-wife
Glittering sand
Against
Blue Water
Sandra James love this letter
Live on the beach Hawaii
Louise
Calms you
Cassandra fields
Protective
Very specifically
Of that white
Glistening Sands
Because
Everyone seems to want it
It happens a lot in this area
Send
Sand
Fat
A lot in this area
You can hear the truck that Knights moving
Wit's end
In Jamaica sand is valuable
So valuable that a few years ago just down the road
An entire
Beach was
Stolen
Thieves showed up in dumb
Trucks and just
Check off
The whole thing
Hundreds of tons of powdery white Caribbean sand
It happened in 2008 and Vicente was
Huge and that just in Jamaica it was a warning sign to the world that Saint had become this
Bing worth
Dealing and smuggling hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm sad
Sarah Gonzales today on the show
There's not enough sand in the world for everyone and
We need that
Sand is a miracle material that is used in a whole bunch of things that we can't live without
You just
Looked around right now
The building that you are in or the sidewalk that you're on
It is made of sand
Because sand is a main ingredient in concrete
Also in class
So
Cell phones your windows
Beer you drank last night
All made out of sand
This episode involves a helicopter sand
Chase threat the Queen of England and teams of scientists who specialize
Insects and forensics
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solution
It support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org
There's a lawyer in
Michael Hilton real
Quiet talker
Born and raised in Jamaica claims to be the only person on the island who likes
Baseball he's a
Yankees fan
End
He's modest
And what's your title
Eternal unprivate
Mr Bob Marley
Lawyer
You are the lawyer for the Bob Marley family
Midas
I don't know because it's so.
Somebody has to do
Michael was running what is a
Essentially the justice department in
Jamaica and then he decided to go into private practice
And in 2008 he gets
Call a beach
Has been stolen
Taken
In the dead of the night
Hauled out
Inductor
So there were Witnesses who saw
Trucks in the mud
Boynton
But who could not say where the sun was beating
And Michael Hilton his job was to
Find this missing
Band
The challenge would be
Pool
Weird assignment who took it and who benefited from it
The Michael heads to the scene of the crime
Drive town of Rocky overgrown dirt road goes past herds of goats and
Hebrew
A mangrove
Forest
There's a crumbling medieval-looking Stone Castle on a hill and peeking out
Through the beautiful mango trees is that aqua blue Caribbean Sea
And then
He sees it
There were
Chords
That were
Probably
10 feet deep but there were holes
Weight benches
Deep trenches
Like if someone went down one of these
Probably would not be able to see the
Digging trenches like this
Would require some kind of excavator type of
Equipment
And was there is was there any way that you can like
Fill the whole leg just kind of move it around to fill the holes or
New Sun
They took almost
All the sand with them
So if you were in a boat you saw water
Rose of
Flaw doubts and trenches and then
Trees
Nobi
The amount that was stolen was not something that you could just
Hiding somewhere
It was way too much sand
So Michael thinks
There has to be at
Scrooged
Heil of sand somewhere on this
Silence there looking all over Jamaica but they don't find any big
Pile of sand
So Michael thinks
Descend
It must have been
Read outs
And where would sand be
Spread out and who has the money to buy a million dollars worth of
Stand
Beachfront Resort
They become Michaels primary suspects
Give me the points that was taken
It would almost certainly have gone
To do Beach building onto new Beach Building
Sometimes
Sand is also used
Orsat
Michael Sands one of the owners of the stolen Beach
Ace and scientists and a Justice of the Peace
Animation
Up on a helicopter
The justice of the peace is kind of like a notary who
Only job is to corroborate what happens on this helicopter and
Make sure no one tampers with the evidence
And this is
Scrappy eagle-eyed sand Squad
They noticed something
At two particular Hotel
These hotels look
Like they were built on beaches that had Brown
Sad
They kind of look like
White sand have been sprinkled over the Browns and
Vivian Ariel
We are
The sand was
Hi the brown or Spurs
And then suddenly
There was a very large stretch of new white expensive sun
Stolen white sand
I just need to
To prove it
The pilot lands the helicopter on the border of one of these
Pirate Resort
The saint scientist
Runs Out
Collect some sand samples and then runs back on to that
And while they were flying around in Helen
Copters
A guy from the United Nations
With wandering around the beaches
Hello can you hear us over there
Yes absolutely hello Sarah
This is Pascal
I'm Pascal Potosi
I'm from Switzerland
Pascal's with the environmental arm of the United
He happened to be in Jamaica at the time
Doing research for the UN talking to the locals
In one Village we people told us that's a some people came off of night
Yeah the guns
And trucks
And they stole $0.02 is sold at beachway of annoyed
And Pascal studies Coastal erosion so
Houston beaches disappearing but like over hundreds of
Years
And here they're telling him a beach vanished overnight
How could that happen
So he starts
Studying the Sandman
And he discovers that this Santa Fe in Jamaica is
Is just one tiny part of a
Huge and
Growing
Sand
Shortage and
A ton of money is at stake
How to say businesses b****
The very minimum 250 billion dollar per year
Legally
But humans are extracting sand
Faster than the Earth
Create space
Because it
Takes forever to me
And we don't recycle sign
1 sand is
Trapped into concrete it's trapped in there forever it doesn't come back as
Sad
This makes the sand industry a linear
Economy
So Pascal takes all of his research and he publishes a report
Closet
Stand
Rarer than one thinks
You even think likes and he's just he's coming material that we all know we week
Going to beach with a very familiar with that and we think it's just
Infinite
Eddie smokes
And where sand is running out
Things are getting
Violence
And 5 people have been killed in Mexico a ninja and probably many other areas
Just for Fen destruction
There is a ton of desert sand on the planet but nobody wants
That's sad
And that's because
Not all sand is created equal desert sand like from the Sahara it's too smooth and silky
Need to be used for construction
So when Dubai which is
Of course I play surrounded by desert
Sand was trying to build the tallest building in the world
I had to import the right kind
Sand from
Australia
They needed the grainy
Greedy kind of sand
The kind that comes from either River bottoms
Or Beach
That's the good
Stuff that's the stuff that can be used for construction
And Beach replenishment
And Pascal says the biggest
Sand importer in the world these days
Singapore
They have imported
Hundreds of millions of
Tons of sand
Singapore is in terms of landmass they don't have a whole lot where do they
Put their sand
08 they do see the Reclamation so that they take you take
Spend a Toy Story by placing Sam
Into the sea
Singapore dumps all of this and that it buys on TV
The edges of the cut
Treat to make
Singapore
Bigger
Since the 1970s Singapore has it
Expanded its territory by 20%
It has changed its countries
Borders you can see this
From satellite images
We can see that by satellite you use what used to be water is now temperature you is buildings on it
The water in some areas been replaced by buildings
And those bloody well build on sand
Singapore used to get all of its sand from
Vietnam
Thailand and Indonesia
But then
Vietnam Thailand and Indonesia started
Shrinking
They were literally
Selling their countries
To Singapore
The UN says around twenty-four Indonesian Islands
Disappeared
They no longer exist
Because all of their sand
Went to Singapore
Nope Pascal he did eventually leave Jamaica
Michael
He would be on the trail of the missing sand
4 years
After the break
We go back
To Jimmy
Support for this podcast and the following message come from fidelity
As a Fidelity Wealth Management
You get a dedicated advisor to help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes and make
Clear recommendations for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
Okay so Michael has suspect
Beachfront Resort
To all inclusive luxury resorts are at
Accused of buying the
The stolen sand
And no one thinks that these hotels actually went
To the beach in
Took off with all the sand
The hotel say we bought this and
Legally from a sand Mining Company
Michael Michael is like
You guys should have known that this was stolen
Property you were Reckless
And so
You should have to pay for the damage
First
Michael needs to prove that the
White sand grains they saw from the helicopter in
Snuck off with
Came from his b
Beach he hires
Sedimentologist and marine geologist to run forensics on these tiny white sangria
But it gets
Complicated because
These hotels are raking the sand in the middle of the night
The Rake The Sand
3 a.m. 4 a.m.
The wrecking the Stalin
Son of the beach
What does that mean like they just like
Smooth it out
So that it doesn't look like people walked on it
Why do they do that
Resort Hotels also
Yank out the grass from the bottom of the ocean so that luxury resort feet don't get grazed
To buy seagrass
At least her is who demand their unlocked on Sand with no grass they are messing up my
Forensic work
Because the old saying in the new sandroll mixing together
Send forensics
But luckily for Michael there are also
Pebble forensics
And while Michael is hanging out with
Pebble expert
The hotels at
Accused of buying the stolen sand are flying in their own X
To do their own saint
And forensic
And Jamaican police are also on the sand forensic be
They're knocking on these Hotel doors like
Excuse me we have a warrant
You collect some sand samples
There was a hole
Criminal
Who would have brought the criminal case
Crown
As in
Queen Elizabeth
Cuz she's a queen of Jamaica
Jamaica is part of the
The Commonwealth the old British colonies
And Nobody messes
Shoes with the monarchs
So this sand theft is so massive that it becomes of Interest
Not just to Jamaica but also to England
Because you don't still beaches
From parts of anybody's country
That's Mark Shields he was ahead of the national police force in Jamaica during this
Highspots Easter eggs in the US if you
Decided to go to the Grand Canyon and take a huge portion of the sand and rock from the Grand Canyon I think probably the Americans would have
Something to say about that
Bet you can't do that
It was just too much than to not have been noticed by a lot of pee
People throw
Mark is thinking
How many people were involved in this
End
How high did this crime go up
There were allegations that police
Were escorting these dump trucks helping them make
A clean getaway
Quite clearly the police would not
Under normal circumstances be escorting
Send
From one location to another
Years into this case
The crown says that their main witness starts getting
Death
Threats real and specific intimidation
And they said
The witness
No longer wants to
Dubai
And the crown is forced
Drop the charge
It was clearly
Quite a conspiracy
Panda
Some of the people to be involved in this will be quite influential
And on the Civil side the judge decided you know what
This would be a great time to retire
She retires in the middle of the
The case without giving a verdict
So in the end the hotels.
Just settled
Without admitting
Jamaica's
Great Sand Heist so big the evidence
A scene from a helicopter
Whoever did it
Got away with it
My disappointment in this case
Ace Hotel
There's a part of me that would prefer to block
Then the nethercutt net worth
It's not my favorite
Instance that theft and the UN report the problem has just gotten worse
In India alone
The UN is aware of
Thousands of illegal sand mining site
And you know we can't live in a world without sin
And it is to import
Soap Pascal says
We just have to be
Smarter about how we
Used San
He says we could just
Simply used less of it we could make our buildings with thinner concrete walls or
We could use
Different ingredients
What's in concrete like
Sawdust
And Ashes
You can actually add chemicals
To desert sand to make it sturdy enough to use for construction
These are all
Real alternatives
It's
Just a little bit more complicated to build this way
Luxury resorts are
Probably not going to
To start dumping Sawdust
And Ashes onto there be
Taurus will continue to demand their powdery White
Perfect fan
When I was in Jamaica I went to one of the Resort's that was a
Accused of buying that stolen sad
Pools and bars and rum
Everywhere
Are catamarans and
Tiki huts on stilts
In the middle of the water
And of course
Big
Expensive
White sand
And everyone I spoke to for the story told me the same thing
Wherever
Is Hotel got that white
Sam from all those years ago
That sound
Is long gone
I was
Probably standing on a new batch of whites and that they brought in from some other B
The thing about Saint
It comes and goes with the waves sand is always on the move
We love to hear what you think of this
The show email us Planet Money at mpr.org or find us on Facebook Twitter or Instagram we are at
At Planet Money are show today was produced by Elisa if that's it and Aviva dekornfeld our editor is bright
Bryant or Stephen and Alex goldmark is are supervising producer I'm Sarah Gonzales and I'm Karen Duffy
Thanks for listening