Stacey Vanek Smith
Carlos Garcia
We host Planet Money
Other podcast the daily podcast what other
The daily podcast the indicator
Stop bothering us and we just got back
I'm awake
In California if we did it while we were there
One day I tripped up a hill in Los Angeles
NPR business
This reporter in LA
Senoia where are we we're at the Baldwin Hills Overlook which is
You've likely seen this in a commercial
We're sort of in the middle of the LA basin
And it gives us this incredible View
So you can look almost 360 and see all away
Around
The Los Angeles Basin this is what the literary types of call a sweeping Vista I think
Where it where are the movie lights
Well one of the movie last words like very nearby that
Culver Studios
That's what Mel Brooks as office is where they filmed Gone with the Wind
Sony
Over there and
Century City
Obscurus
20th Century Fox or 21st Century Fox the movie studio
And the other movie studios you can't see cuz they're in the valley and Paramount is somewhere in Hollywood
Okay
And we've got you out here because when
When people think of LA
They think of some
Fairly obvious interest
Film
Entertainment
Hollywood
There's more to it than that
Yeah you think that 18 million people moved here
Because of Hollywood
It's a lot of people with dreams of Stardom Hollywood is very
Important clearly
But that's just one of the bubbles in a
Drawer pulls Lowe's
Particracy
And I'm Stacey Vanek Smith and we are the hosts of the indicator from Planet Money
California
Huge formidable upon
One of the largest economies in the country
Actually also one of the biggest economies in the world
California's economy part of is bigger than France
To take that
Pompous
Indicator
Costa California
We see we can learn from this
Powerhouse economy start a celery Farm
We head to a metro station
Part of the states housing prices
And we end up in one of the country
Biggest
You may not hear a ship horn
You definitely will
Support for this podcast and the following message
Come from mizzenandmain
Mizzen & Main dress shirts are made with performance Fabrics
Designed to look great all day with minimal man
There moisture Wick
Wrinkle resistant
And machine wash
So they don't require ironing
Or dry
Check out their gift guides for the guy on your lip
Who is always on the move
Had to visit in Maine.,
Mizzen & Main
Look great longer
Use code NPR at checkout
To receive $10 off your dress shirt
Hey I'm Kelly mcevers from embedded
Bill Spencer works at a Coal Mine in Kentucky
It when I start asking about a future without coal
You know what I'm going to say
So if gold goes out I'm done board.
Play NPR one app for wherever you get your
Dollar-for-dollar California is the
The biggest agricultural economy
Almonds oranges avocado spinach berries
They're all big
Step business
Is having big trouble
Each year
Tougher
Offer for Farmers to find workers
First harvest all there
It smells like celery on here
Yeah I know you don't forget that
It's kind of nice where we are today cuz we're really close to the ocean she get a combination of that
See are in a little bit of celery hands
So pretty nice spot to be
That pretty nice spot to be is a celery field in Ventura County
California we were there with Tom.
His family has owned farms in that area for a
About 8
It's like an ocean of celery
Yeah I know there's probably
80 acres of celery here in
Really
So that will
I'll get harvested
About
Two and a half weeks
In the middle of the ocean of celery
There is a crew of about
30 workers
They walk in a row in big straw hat
Hacking up celery
Restocks and tossing them
This motorized class
Stretches
The field and chugs Along by
They're so fast it's really cool they are it's a skilled physician that takes a lot of years of
Experience to be able to perform at this level and
Obviously you can see they've mastered it
On that moving platform another worker cleans up
The celery stalk and impacts
Fit into a box
Alex Martinez is the Harvest manager out here and he shows us his celery
It's a 12in
Dexter Stainless Steel machete
That is then
Cut about
4 inches from the top
Turned in re-welded back to it
Otis like a custom job
A lot of crops
Can be harvested by machine
Crops like wheat corn potatoes
The most fruits and vegetables are
Quite uniform enough
Harvested like
For the most part they have to be harvested by
It is really hard and dangerous
10 hour days
Swinging a knife
In the hot sun
And when the job market strong
Like it has been for the last few years
These workers have a lot of other options
They move into whether it's landscaping jobs construction jobs
Food service jobs Whenever there is
An increase in demand for
For the general economy
Workers generally migrate away from formwork into other areas
Tom deardorff
Just had to compete for work
He's raise their pay by Acts
Quite a lot
Back in 2006
Working the celery field paid about $8 and seventy
An hour
Now it pays more than $21
Pay
Has gone up by more than double
Wayfair
Campground in most of the
Now we are well aware of the criticism that
That's been around for a while that the app
Agriculture sector relies on underpriced labor and in particular on undocumented workers
Take very little money for back brake
Can work we couldn't speak to any of the workers on Tom's Farm but
Tom says his workers all are documented and the
Even doubling wage
Hasn't solved the labor
Yeah I don't think it's an economically should I think it's a political issue
I mean it is not sustainable under the current political environment that is true
Because we do not have a legitimate
Immigration policy that allows us access to workers
Tom says the agriculture visas that the country offers
Are not real
Sick for his business
They're too difficult to get their expensive and there's a
Just aren't enough of
Deirdre Farms used to hire more than
600 workers
Every year
But Tom says he can't make that happen anymore
More so he's had to make changes to his business
For example
He's changed
The crops that
We've shifted away from the most labor-intensive crops
So things like Vine ripe Tomatoes we no longer grow anymore you don't grow them at all cuz of Labor
Correct
They're just spit those. Program alone took about 400 workers
And so we just got to the point where we could no longer find the steady supply labor and
Decided that we just need to get out of that business
All together
Doodle Farms also got out of strawberries
It's that time has gotten into leafy green
Things like kale cilantro broccoli
Ancillary
They require fewer workers and can be at least partly automate
Where Tom used to hire about
600 people every year
Now he hires around 2
But you can find in 200 work
So I made another
We've also shifted large amount of our production down in the max
So you shifted
Production
A big chunk of what you do
Away from the United States and now it's
Being made
In Mexico
You couldn't find
Workers
Correct
Yeah I mean basically
The fact that matter is is it a
Foreign-born person is
Harvesting your fruits and vegetables
So the decision is do we want to do that within the United States with a guest-worker program or do we want to have that
Foreign-born workers stay in
Second Harvest
Fruit and vegetable sale
Based on what we've seen in the political environment over last 15 and 20 years we have decided to go down there and
How hard was it to make these kinds of
Decisions based on life
What you were
I mean if I was looking at spreadsheets all day long as a really simple decision and one we probably should have made five years before we made it
But I mean these are ranches it
My great-grandfather farmed and we'd rather keep them active but the economics in the politics
Debater suggesting
So Tom keeps doing what he
He can to attract workers
Including using that little motorized platform
Cuz it means that the workers don't have to
Security giant boxes
Celery across the
So this machine is like kind of one of the ways that you attract
The best people
Definitely yeah I know you're looking for a competitive advantage in the labor market and this is one way to do that
To provide a work
Environment it is
Is safer
It's more efficient and it's slightly easier than what may
Occur in somebody else's
He worried that one year you're just not going to be able to produce whatever it is that you're aiming to
Mapreduce because
Enough people just don't show up
Yeah we try and forecast at a little bit we reduce planting sizes and we spread things out a little bit and
Just based on what we
Feel the labor
Availability is going to be
And then we're constantly looking for Innovation to get us
The same
A production with less people
So we're we kind of attacking on two fronts
Tom says his business has become this
Constant calculator
How to harvest more wood
How to get more crops at
The ground was
Because in spite of everything the harvesting machines higher pay the different crops
His turnover rate
Keeps growing
Fewer and fewer
The same workers come back to his farm
Every year
When we were in California there was one very big
Snooze
State legislators killed a bill
Called Senate Bill 8
27 or just s
To 7
Yes spa27 was meant to address
Housing
In California
It's a shortage that has led to
Sky High
Of course that is not just
California issue it's a problem in California shares with a lot of Pi
Is it talk about California's housing problems and to discuss why bills like SBA
27 in particular struggle to get past
We called Pablo monkey
He's a professor public policy Norman
Planet UCLA
She said
You know what
Meet me at the
This one particular Metro Station
And I'll show you
This is all about the platform Edge we're sending the Westwood Ranch
Show Park Expo station one of the stations in the city of La new Transit infrastructure
Why did you choose to have us meet you at this Metro station is a good example of what's wrong
I was planning in California so we've had this massive public investment in a Metro System surrounded by
Single family homes as far as the eye can see most of them are one-story 1950s stock
Station surrounded by all these 1950s one story houses
Is new
And looks like not that many local residents are using it very skeptical that they do but even if they do
Did you know maximum 150 people from this neighborhood would be commuting to downtown Los Angeles
1/4 /
People who drive cars living in flat single family houses
As far as the eye can see
And you're the strain station there are no visible apartment,
Papa says that's too bad
Local zoning laws don't allow for certain kinds of buildings
Like apartment complex
Certain areas
And that limits the overall housing
Supply
And that means fewer people using public
Transit stops like this train station
And also it means that house prices stay
High and so does the rent if you look at zoning in Los Angeles 75% of residential land
Is zoned exclusively for low-density single-family homes
Those low-density single-family homes on average are 20% more expensive than houses in in multi-family build
So I think that
A logical housing policy would to be to legalize the less expensive kind of housing if in fact we want to make housing more
And Los Angeles can't do that why
Political opposition to change
River that housing Reform Bill SB
B82 7
It was defeated
Literally the day before I met Pavo
With that Metro
Literally
Literally not and not like the way the kids use literally or at least figuratively but actually like
Right and it still would have literally allowed more construction of apartment buildings close to busy public transit stops
Bus stops
Train stations
Any idea what was the building more apart
We need more
And that would mean cheaper rent
It was kind of amusing to see how many pallets
Lights with the bill was trying to
To do
But ended up
Opposing the bill itself
I do think we have a housing crisis in this state
But we also have to get it right
Unfortunately be supporting the bill today
It pains me a bit to to have to refrain from supporting the measure today
And I will continue to work with your bills doesn't get out of this committee
Today
And hopefully bill is supported at the Seawall
The reason spa27 was so controversial is it it would have overruled the zoning laws that were already put in place
By cities and towns
California
The laws determining where new construction is allowed
What kind of buildings are allowed Apartments
Prince's houses
How many stories high the build
Can be problem on Canon says there's a few reasons that neighbor
Like the one surrounding the train station where we met him
Don't often allow new building
One reason
Is it new building can go against
Stephen Ansell in
Of homeowners in the US weaved evolved land use controls to the local governments and often they respond
Find very much to Neighborhood associations
Interest
So
I think there are a lot of reasons that people opposed new housing near them
But one of the main ones that
Been out there for a long time is
Thinking about single-family home owners
As a kind of cartel
Where they get together include to prevent new Supply
In order that their assets
Increase in value
That's interesting cuz nobody really think so
Homeowners
Where's as a cartel at their thought of his like living the American dream
Yeah I mean I think and that's a problem with the way we think about housing in the United States right so we want housing to be affordable on the one hand
But if we own a house we might be happy when that house increases in value right and so I think people often
Their own minds don't realize what's happening
The second reason people opposed more building in their neighborhood
Is that they could simply be afraid of having their lives disrupted by the
Changes by the
Construction
People think that the city might come in and bulldoze their house and put up a public housing unit when in fact what would happen is
As people sell their houses
From year to year
Some people that want a single-family house might buy that in
Keep it the same
In some cases a developer might buy it
And tear it down and build a 4-story building or something
There are neighborhoods like this in LA and people like them they're not unpopular neighborhoods so I don't think that people
I kind of understand how the the change would affect the quality of life and I think it would be probably minimal
More legitimately publishes
A third reason is it people worried that there will be more traffic
More congestion
10 in their neighbor
Of course that worries someone addressed at the building takes place near public transit and also
Some neighborhood and
He is going to have
Set the traffic Pablo's point is it
The traffic would be more evenly distributed throughout the city
If more building were allowed in the wealthier neighbor
1/4 reason to some communities have opposed more building is it they just don't like developer
And also we have a recent paper we look at an experiment where we give people different reasons to oppose
Housing Development and we found that the one that elicits the most opposition to a hypothetical project is when we
We say that the developers going to make a lot of money
So this is the one reason that actually doesn't affect Peoples Neighborhood
But there's kind of this fairness
Repugnant
Idea where developer getting ripped off or something
I think it's connected to people seeing housing as kind of an important accessory for for human life
And then
Disliking people that profit off that
When often they themselves are profiting off
The fact
Did there's a scarce supply of housing
So people are complicated and often holds contradictory opinions and finally one of the effects of Provera
New building Pablo says
Is it a computer
City segregated by wealth and in some cases
Buy racing
Ethnicity people who live in apartments in pay rent on average make less money than people
Who own homes
But those apartments are not getting built in areas with a lot of single family
Mike Holmes
So final reason also the ugliest reason
Is it some communities
Want to exclude categories
The people from living in their neighbor
Now there's no simple solution
To the conflict between communities that feel they have the right to decide for themselves what their neighborhood
What you look like
Anthony from warehousing
But Papa said when housing costs remain unaffordable it doesn't just hurt people who were forced to leave
Thriving area B
They couldn't afford rent or people who couldn't
Afford to live there in the first place
It also affects future Generations
Papa said the paper from Economist Raj Chetty some of the County's where it's best you know for your life
Best prospects to be born to a low-income family
Are in the Bay Area or in LA
And so by preventing low-income households from from living here we're denying their children the chance to kind of had a better future
Critzer knows when making it impossible for low-income people to move to somebody's high growth areas
It also has an effect that reverberates down to the Next Generation or multiple Generations even
Yep that sucks California
After the break
We take to the Sea
We go to a port
And side note one of the best things about being a reporter is it
You can be a grown woman and still ask people to honk their horns for you
How long do you want it for
The first one
That's something that we're not supposed to do anymore we became adults I didn't know that
Support also comes from Fidelity invest
As a Fidelity wealth
You get a dedicated advisor
To help grow and
Protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of tax
And make clear recommendations
Thanks for your full Finance
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
I've got that
There is so much Politico
Is the follow these days
But you don't have to keep up
With all of it you just have to keep up with us
On the NPR politics
You can find us on the NPR one app or wherever you get to
In California everyone is talking about
Man actually still is talking about
Is possible trade war between the US and
China
Because California is among other things
Homes the biggest ports in the country
Port of Long Beach in
Port of Los Angeles ship nearly 390
Billion dollars worth
Worth of goods
So you can see this is the
The greater Harbor the state-of-the-art terminal be here will you see the screens movie
The Port of Long Beach is the
Long stretch of coast
Southern California giant white and red cranes
Hang out over the water in
Huge ships crawling along the bay
I'm here with Mario Cordero he's the executive director of
He points out this massive pile of lumber being loaded onto ships
Bound for Asia there's a big oil tanker on the horizon
And an enormous white ship called
Is launches a satellite to satellite
Oh my gosh Ecuador satellites down there
Wow
And then they're just like
Stacks and stacks and stacks
Stacks of shipping containers all different colors over there we moved over to the 375
5 million containers
Coming from and going to
China
You invite him as a president
Of the board of Harbor
Commission for the port of long
She loves
I think it's beautiful
I think it's a piece of art
I mean everything that everybody has their homes is touched by the Port of Long Beach and one way or the other
Is that true
I think so
I mean really about textiles and in electronics and furniture and
Clothing in
You know they're all good to come through the port
Glenn says more than 7 million teus
Please come to the Port of Long Beach
What's a teu
A total equivalent unit
What's the total equivalent units equivalent unit
Are those the big
The boxes
You just go like right onto the back of the truck right now
A teu is basically the back of a semi-truck
And the Port of Long Beach moved
Seven and a half million of them last year
The stuff in those
Use is going to retailers
Walmart and Target and Lowe's
In the port
Facilitates
The deals between shipping companies and these retail
Mario Cordero says that the poor business all about volume
Sport makes more money
When more ships
In and out
The last decade business has been on
Hair the economy's been growing us consumers have been buying more stuff
Has been expanding
And ships have been getting bigger and bigger to me
The Port of Long Beach has been investing
Billions of dollars
Accommodate
We've been dusted
The tuna for billion dollars over a 10-year. To increase our infrastructure here we're ready to
Receive here 20000 teu vessel
20000 t
You vessels that is a ship that can hold 20,000 semi trucks loaded up with
Like the Benjamin Franklin ship which came through the port last year
It made a big impression on
20 stories high
That can hold
91 million pair of shoes
This would be like if you tipped over the Empire State Building
And filled it with shoes
Shoes from China
In fact 70% of The Ships coming to and going from the Port of Long Beach
Are coming from
To China
So when the trade War talk started
Between China and the US
Luigi Mario Grand Hyatt
Do you remember when you heard about the tariffs
Do you remember like where you were when you heard that news
Yes I was glued to the TV like I've been glued to the TV for the last 18 months
When am I overweight
They were waiting for China and the US to release the list of things that would be
Text
And when those lips finally came out
Poured over
Right away
Demario sollozzo
Nuts
Fruit you also sell Steel
Aluminum
The Port of Long Beach ships all of this
The Mario says the list
It was actually kind of a relief
Because the Lion's Share of their business
Was not on the
Here at the Port of Long Beach are largest commodity that
It's important is in fact furniture
You know and that's at the tune of
25%
25% of what comes in here is like
Dressers in couches and beds
Furniture
Which is the reason
For The Targets in the lows in Nederland Walmart
Naddition number 2 is Footwear
So
Right now
Those bodies have not been talked about in terms of the Tariff discussion
Those items are on the Tariff list right now
What Donald Trump has talked a lot about rethinking
Betrayed and
Deals
He scrapped the transpacific
Partnership deal
Repeat early on in his presidency
And he's talked about throwing out NAFTA and
Of course there's the trade War talk with China that has been asked
And this is happening just as
The Port of Long Beach
Just finishing up
4 + 1/2
Billion dollar
Remodeling to accommodate bigger
I mean there is a possibility that at least for a little while for the foreseeable future
Free trade is going to move backwards in this country inn and the larger ships won't have
Maybe as
Much of a future as we
Thought it going backwards
Even in a temporary nature whatsoever
Really I'm cuz it does seem like
Maybe were in a moment's at least politically that we may be stepping back from free trade and and
You know I mean if if huge tears get put in place
There's nothing you could do
Let's 2018 not the night
1930s
That's true
Have you just think things are too interconnected and globalized to go
I think that the economy is so in
Integrated and Link anymore
Got to admire her optimism it's true
When points out the present
Trump got a lot of backlash
From Farmers over the China Terrace
And she also noted some reports that
The Trump Administration has been reconsidering entering the
PT. That's all still really uncertain
Raven shoulder and says they are covering their bases
See you tomorrow been exploring trade routes in
To South America and even Africa
And that's a tiny part of the port's business now
But she says they've got to be ready for
After all Luanne wants to keep ships moving in and out of the pool
In fact she says sometimes she just likes
To go out on the pier
I need to be able to see the terminals and the cranes and the ships moving in and out of the harbor
It's a it's a wonderful appreciation of this economic engine
That's the piece of art that's the artwork
We put every episode of Planet Money on Facebook so if you have thoughts of
About to show you the comment on the post
Indicators produced by Doris Rocky on 10th
Did by Patty Hearst
One quick note we have a new video out this week as part of our planet money shorts series
This one is about the rise of the Honeycrisp apple it's really good check it out and you can find all of our videos at end
Npr.org Planet Money shorts and lest we forget
Listen to the indicator
Every single day
We hosted
That it is the best
I'm part of Garcia and thanks for listening