Hey it's Alex
DUI hear that Russell
That is the sound of
One point
Billion dollars
Coming my way
A lottery
I pick those exact numbers
Because they are the same one
That were on the Planet Money Lottery Ticket almost 3 years ago
Thank you to everybody by the way messaging us about that episode asking
Replay
At the time we did that show
The Powerball pot was at 1.5 billion.
The biggest price of had been up
America had Lottery fever
And we got it too
We scrambled
Define the best stories we could about
Lottery
We found the oldest Lottery on
We talked to the man who beat the odds
Over and over again
And we crunched the numbers on whether or not it is a good deal
To buy a ticket
When the pot is as big as it is
And the numbers by the way back then
Pretty much the same as they are right now the outcomes
So we're leaving those calculations in the show
Only other thing I have to say is
What are producer Diane Woods has put in front of me and made me promise to read
I solemnly swear to split the pot with Planet Money
If we win with this lottery ticket
Even though I bought it with my own money
Okay with that
Here's the episode
All right we have just 24 hours to put this whole show together
And also I need to know
Who's in I'm in I'm definitely
In for sure
Yeah you're a dime into it we're both good and then
Stacy's never got it
Never got a ticket never know I'm super excited I don't even know how to do it
Who here has bought a lottery ticket before
I have bought a lottery ticket
Before the fact I have one right here
Drawings
I haven't
Are the to you
Bicycle
I feel like actually we could win
Like that is
Hello
I'm rich
Robert Smith
This week the Powerball lottery is up to
1.5
Billion dollars perhaps you heard
So like everyone else in the country we are getting no work. We're spending all of our time
We have the story of one of the very first lotteries
The main prize is amazing you won't believe it
And with the story of the one time it made absolute economic sense to play the lottery
And we talked to the guy who pulled it off
But first
Stacy you and I
We got to take care of some business
All right
Play The Marine
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Is reimagining Bank
I offering account
With no fees or minimum
Memes that can be open from anywhere in
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Since we have some time to kill before we
Quit our jobs
We thought we talked about
One of the very first times a lottery
Exist
And we have been kept mom and Stacey Vanek Smith here
Totality
Can give you the footnote this is the first state lottery that we have good records
Oh as always
As long as 1567 isn't England and they have
This problem like the harbors are falling apart they need money
Everybody hates
Taxes
So their finance minister
I had just been to the Netherlands he saw they were trying out lotteries there and it works well he decided
Let's do it in England
But this was brand-new in England and so they had to try to figure out how do you
Explain what a lottery was two people how to get people on board and most importantly
How to sell tickets
Laika a lottery ad campaign
You may be a winner
Exact
And we talked to David Dean he is a professor at Carleton University in Ottawa
And he told us
The lottery in England with something like this
So imagine it is 1560
D7 you walk into the public market on
On Saturday
And there was a man shouting
Buy Lottery
We know that they have a Trumpeter
Sometimes they put on a little play
How about you know I'm so far I'm so far I'm so far all my God have won the lottery hippie I'm happy ever after you know
That is basically what Lottery ads are
To this day which people going like I can't believe it I'm so lucky throwing money in the air
He said they're also in the Marquis would have seen this like big poster that had the official seal of the government saying you can trust it this
This is for Real
And in the middle of it there were these pictures of the prizes
Is this thing still exist and he described
The prices are really cool because they show jugs and plates and their all gold and silver but they also have monkeys holding
Bags of coin
And wait until you hear the grand prize
Whosoever shall win the greatest and most excellent price shall receive the value of 5
Thousand pounds sterling
That is to say three thousand pounds in ready money that's cash
700 lb worth of plate gold and white
And the rest
In Good Cafe
History and also a bunch of them and coffee as well
What is the gold plate is that in like a
Bar or what does that mean
No it would be plates
And jugs and calluses and
Yeah and you you would sell that to melt it down or you treasure it on your man so pretty
Good grand prize
I mean it would be riches
Beyond everyone
Dreams
You paid 10 Shillings
To get one Lottery
Ticket and
You would write
A poem
What was just something to uniquely identify yourself you know in case you want
God is mighty may I win or
Godspeed my Lots
Anderson Ferry
Scary ones like snakes mate
With garlic is good to eat
Why didn't people
Just leave their name
They don't have to ride in Ames that we have today
And there'd be a lot of confusion there a lot of Tom Smith's in the end
Robert Smithson that has so much more
Literary
Then ours I feel like it's so much classier they had like criers and everybody wrote
Poems
And now we have like
A guy with
Bunch of ping pong balls
In a vacuum on TV
They should absolutely do that
Like Daddy's like I want everyone if you have to do something a little player
The poem sing a song
What's your problem
I can't think of anything funny but
The Winner's clearly
Our planet
Nice that's pretty good
Play Mariah
It is unclear exactly how this works but
At one possibility is like
When they pulled out the winning ticket they would just read like the first half
And the person who could complete the poem that would prove it with them
But he said despite like the trumpet
And all that stuff there are not a lot of tickets out
The whole idea of a lottery
Is just new and people
Do not trust the gum
Let you know they're not sure they're going to
Get there golden
And another thing is the tickets were expensive
Tension
For a carpenter let's say in the city of London who's a pretty well paid person compared to Carpenters elsewhere
There any five Shillings a week so this should be a fortnite hacker month salary
How many people it would have been a president of a month's salary and a few or labor or Plowman or something you're talking about
Six months salary
So a lot of people ended up going in on a lottery ticket together
Exactly like we did
But they also had another idea to
To further entice people into buying tickets
They agreed to not arrest
People when they came in two by two
A lady was like you know if you lived out in the country or something maybe you done something wrong like you've stolen
A loaf of bread from somebody
Like don't worry you can come into town or you might normally be arrested
And we're not going to rescue you can buy it
Wow it's kind of like the embassy they have an overdue Library
Is one day only
Give us your money
And we want to rest
Does all ticket holders were promised freedom from arrest for all crimes other than murder felonies
Piracy or treason
That covers a lot
It does
It's covers that hit my day really really wanted people to come and buy tickets
So finally the big moment come
Right everyone gathers down
It's outside St Pauls gift
They're going to pick the winner
He says he thinks it was probably all the tick
Barrel and there's one official
Pulled out the winner
And you want to know who the winner is
We don't know
What's the trouble
We have no idea
Today's no media coverage of the winner
No media coverage in the newspapers of the day
This Lottery was a total failure they only sold about one-tenth the number of tickets they were supposed to sell
Any actually ended up
Heading back the prize
To 1/12 of what it had been
Grand prize got cut
By that much
Oh my gosh that's
I mean the one that's that's
And of course that just reinforce everybody sense that
Okay this is a failure and it's not working
Then we will never try it again
But they did try to
Well they did over a hundred years later
Sore people smarter back then
I mean even back then people went
I have no chance of winning
I asked if it was it that you know they're like this is a stupid investment why do I do this
He said no no
It was just
They didn't trust the government
And it was very good
I wonder if they like cut the plates
7/2 or something
Or are you at we get 1/12 of a golden plate
There's somebody out those plates right now
But that's basically how it started the trend has been toward bigger and bigger
Piles of
Money you know we had prepared the state lotteries and then
I would like all we can have a much bigger pot
And that's
As we have today that's the one
25 billion
Does not include gold
Becky David
NCC stick around cuz we got to do so
Okay my favorite subject
Okay because we're economics reporters
We have to sort of do the numbers here
And show you that this is a
Parable
Terrible terrible Financial investment
No matter
How excited we are about it
The numbers
Do not work in your favor
This very quickly back the envelope
The odds of winning
1 in 292 million it cost $2 for every ticket so if you wanted by every possible combination
That would be
Million-dollar
He's what we take
So with the pots over 600 million then it starts to be worth it
So it's like 1.5 billion is
What you would get over many years if you took the lump sum
They figure it would be about
930 million dollars
It's still pretty good
But then you have to take away
Taxes you have to pay the highest tax rate on your lottery winnings
So that would mean you'd be left without 561
Million dollars
After take my federal taxes but ofcourse
You & I in the Planet Money Team live in New York City tax
Estate tax
So basically
It would Whittle down to about
Five hundred million dollars
Would be
Are lottery winnings
Will plus we have to split that 8 ways
Yea or more
I think they can
Game the system and play the odds of the lottery is that you have no control over who else buys your number
We could win with our numbers and somebody else out there
Could get the exact same.
But what are the chances of someone peeking exactly the same numbers in exactly the same order
Well
You know in order to show this as an economic lesson
I think you something after you left the corner store that you did not hear so play that tape
Okay Stacy is left
So I would like to buy the exact same number again but this one's me personally I just want to get the same number again
Same number
Salem
Alright so one of these is mine and one of these is the rest
Farmers
Let's just say that if our numbers hit
What money of which I'm a member has to split it
With Robert Smith
The individual
Cutest
You just don't millions of dollars from us
The author not good
What fictional Milian's butt
What's the word I'm trying to demonstrate how
Difficult it is to consider the lottery a sane Financial invest
But
When we're doing research for the show we discovered
That there was one guy there was one guy who managed to figure out how to
To game this entire system
And with that story
Is
Planet Money senior producer
Hi Robert
So it's 1992 in Virginia and there is a big lottery jackpot for the time 27 million
Dollars numbers
Winner
Add it first there's nobody who comes forward
But there are reports that there was something that was maybe going on before the lottery drawing something suspicious
Starts to Dawn on them that something is up something is different about this
These reports
From around town
People have been going into different grocery stores buying 50,000 tickets at a time and different combinations
And they put it all together and they realize
That someone or some people
Have pulled off what is the dream
MO Lottery players
They took the luck out of Lottery they bought every single combination of numbers possible and guarantee themselves Irwin
And this is totally perplexing
To the people who run the lottery system like Ken Thorson head of the Virginia Lottery this is him on TV shortly after
I really never
Would have imagined that anybody would have ever wanted to try to buy it out if you never happened in the United States
But the very idea of spending over 7 million dollars
To buy all the shares in the lottery just seems
Preposterous
Because think of what it would take I mean you need investment of 7 million
Actually go and buy
That many lottery tickets are going to be buying ticket
Twenty-four hours a day need to fill out each different ticket you need to keep track of where each ticket went so that when you win
You can sign the winning ticket and get somebody pulled it off
Yes
His name is Stefan Mandel
I did a little research poke around and I found him
Living on a
Tropical island in the South Pacific for CSS in Vanuatu I made a phone call I got a cell phone and
And I rang him up
Hello
Hi is this Stefan Mandel
I told him I'm a reporter and then I'm doing a story that Lottery
Are you willing to talk to me about it
For the radio
Let's go he died a long time ago
As soon as I started asking him questions he just could not stop he lit up cuz he
How did he pull this off and he says
Listen Alex
That Virginia thing it took him decades and decades
Perfect his system
To get to that low
The story starts in Romania
In Romania
Yeah and in the late 1950s
And Stefan Mandel is working at some job he doesn't really like it and Industrial mining
Company
And he's got a wife young kids
And you just desperately wants out of the country
Money to do it and he starts looking at the lottery
That was the only way that I could get some
Quick
I mean
Show me Life360 lay a month
Which was the coolant
Good pair of shoes
But it doesn't just go out and buy random
He's a pretty natural math
He goes to the library and start reading math paper aftermath paper aftermath paper and he comes up with a formula for
Buying blocks of tickets
The he thinks
Should guarantee him a prize
Because he doesn't have money to buy
Every number
Not yet
Okay he pulls in three friends they take their money together they still don't have enough money to buy every combination
But they figure they can guarantee themselves
Second prize we17
50 mm
Which was
Alright Big Score that was on your first try
Be honest was that luck
Wechat lock
Okay
Because he was playing for second prize but he happened to win first prize
So he takes the money any
Leaves Romania finally brings his family and they end up in
In Australia
And this is where he takes his Lottery planet to the neck
Okay Define
More investors who raises more money
ASCII
This is what he saw
What is really the obstacle to this whole crazy scheme
Write normally when you want to pick out your own numbers for the lottery go to the corner store and he asked for that little form
With the numbers on it and you fill out each little form with the pencil it takes forever
Reese's
I'm not going to go
I'm going to order
Please set up a room
Filled with printers in it
Computer program is going to spit out
Those forms already filled out with every possible combination going to fill out the forms for him at high speed
Composition of the paper
Print it out
Scripps
Redis
With a combination sander
Legal to have a computer fill out
Just looked for you
It was legal when he did it and he turned Lottery winning into a business for a while
12 time
But I kind of got stuck up their noses
They changed a lot birthday passed a law that said
No one person can buy every combination lottery ticket it's just a literally do not do that again
And so then he broke it up into 50 different people who each bought 150 or the numbers
And so he keeps winning and eventually
They make enough sufficient laws
That prevent him from doing it again
But this turn up
Stefano.
No he started looking even bigger
He starts looking to
The US
He looks to a couple different states he starts doing the calculations again because you have to find a place where the jackpot is big enough to
Justify health is
Printing
Analucifer
Right so he finds Virginia
And in Virginia
There are 7.1 million combinations of lottery tickets and he has to wait until the jackpot is
He figures 25 million or above just make sure he turns a profit if there's a split pot
And then
He waits
He sets up his whole operation for when the time is
To print out the the numbers
Yeah
They printed out all 7.1 million tickets in Australia paid $60,000 to ship them to the US
Negotiated bulk buys with grocery stores all around Virginia
About how they could send cashier's check to buy
Tens of thousands of lottery tickets
I mean it's like a bank heist
How complicated is what
Event on the night
The Virginia Lottery I he did not have the same feeling that all of us have
Right now
Awaiting the numbers
To come out from
Powerball
Disguise
Knew he had in the back
Yeah but I asked him where you
Were you scared were you worried are you excited you're just like
I have all the time
I knew that would win one prescribed
Second prizes
Mind if I
27 million + saw those minor prizes
Electronic
There is a little dispute about whether or not he really bought all of these tickets or whether he came
Pretty close
Because there were a few stores
Who just said oh my God this is too much
You have to stop coming in with all these tickets
In the middle of his Vines
But he swears to me
That he found workarounds for all that he had Back-up Plan
And in the end he did buy all the
So did he have any advice for anyone who's thinking of doing this
On the scale of a
Powerball
Giant like
Billion dollar prices are coming at 9 cannot be done any
He says you cannot do it the number of combinations of grown too much you wouldn't be able to print the tickets he wouldn't be able to buy the
Xiamen time
And you probably couldn't even do the math right to figure it out without making a mistake
So he might be the last
Guy who is able
The corner the market
The great Lottery corner of 1992 will remains
Great Lottery corn
Alright Alex
See on the beach of Vanuatu
If I numbers come up
Definitely Robert
After the break
The lottery lawyer
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence and run your biz
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial and when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
So there is
There is one
Last thing that we wanted to do
Stacy and I
Called one man one man who is almost certain to profit
Off of this Powerball fee
So is this the lottery lawyer.com
Correct
What's your actual name
Jason Kurland Kurland
And how much did it cost to buy your url
I don't remember it wasn't much it wasn't much
People found you through that website
Oh yeah
It sounds like this is a much more wise investment
Find lottery lawyer.com than buying an actual lottery ticket
Almost any investment is better investment of vinyl everything
He's right
All this fun we've had a side
You really should not
Buy a lottery
The terrible path
Especially since we don't want to split the pot any more than we already have
Do not buy 1011 51/52 6280
We always love to hear what you think of the show send us an email Planet Money at npr.org
Or you can tweet us at Planet Money
Our show today was produced very quickly by Jess Jiang and Nick fountain
Robert Smith
And I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Thanks for listening
Okay Alex here from 2018
We are looking for two talented interns
One fourth planet money to show and one for our sister show
The indicator
From Planet Money
They're both great jobs past interns have gone on to work in the show
Great job
In NPR and elsewhere
Radio and economics journalism
So to apply go to our website npr.org money
Click on the link there
The deadline is Monday so get applying
We have to shut down Planet Money you know that
No we can take a huge
We could have like Planet Money is just going to listen to us
Caribbean disregard valid money we count all our money again how big is too big
Zachary
Support for this podcast and the following message come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children