Buehler
Envy
Venn diagram of
Iconic
Pop culture moments
And critically important economic history lessons
There is an overlap of
Roughly 40 sec
So first I guess I want to ask you do you do you know this
Scene from Ferris Bueller course
Doug Irwin Economist at Dartmouth
Can you do it without looking like you know it by heart I can do the first part
In 1930 the republican-controlled House of Representatives passed the
Everyone
Anyone
The Tariff bill
The Hollies
Smoot
Terrorist act which
Anyone raised or lowered
Raised
Paris
In an effort to collect more revenue for the federal government
Did it work
Anyone
Anyone know the effects
Anyone anyone know it did not work out well and the economy sank further into the Great Depression
Not bad almost word-for-word and by the way
Hawley-smoot smoot-hawley Duggar when says you can't
Either way and it went when it comes to
Smoot-hawley you are kind of like
The smoot-hawley
Guy
About right
There aren't many competitors like one way of putting it I mean I think everyone knows of them but no one is
Stun the Deep dive like I have I guess
Doug read a book about the smoot-hawley Tariff
Including an explanation of how it became the most infamously boring High School lesson in movie history
They passed the actor Ben Stein who's the son of a famous economist herb Stein
They want him to be a boring High School teacher but they didn't actually script what he's going to say
So they let him rip
I start talking about the smoot-hawley Tariff but why do you think it works as a punchline in that
April 1st was delivery mainly
Because I think you can make smoot-hawley excited
It's spring this conflagration the Great Depression
It's has a lot of drama has really funny name Smoot and Hawley interesting characters
Unintended consequences and I guess now it has a tremendous amount
The relevance to today
Yes hello and welcome
Planet Money I'm Kenny Malone and I'm finally home
And we all get passed on through the holidays because the story of the worst
Terrorist ever
Eerie parallels to what's happening in the white house right now
Today on the show
How this big old tariff bill with
With a silly name
Help tank the world economy
And why it means that today 90 years later
President Donald J Trump has the power
To start
What a lot of people fear
Is a trade
Support for this podcast
In the following message come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and community
To help ensure a brighter future for America's shield
More information is available at aecf. Org
Quick recap of where we are in the world of import
Tariffs
About a month ago President Trump walked up to a Podium and
Follow through on a big
Campaign
Promise
We will have a 25% tariff on foreign Steel
And a 10% tariff on foreign aluminum
He also put some tariffs on washing machines and
Solar panels
Details of these tariffs are changing
Pretty much every day some countries
Exemptions or maybe more products tax
Broad Strokes
This is a political move by the Trump Administration in part 2
Punish China for
What they say is a dirty tactics
Send the trade world
And it's also partly a protectionist
Tax to help people who are a big part of President Trump's building block
AKA manufacturing sectors left behind by globalization
Economist
Tend to not agree
On March but you would be hard-pressed to find one who
Who thinks these tariffs are good
And a big reason for that is
This kind of economics
Horse
Story scare young Economist around the campfire
The tale
Absolute
Holly we are thinking
The best place to start
Probably with the
Election in 1920
That's the perfect place to start again
Tuckerman
So in 1928 the US economy was doing
Exceptionally well
The stock market was booming and players were hiring the unemployment rate was very low there's no Great Depression
Play whatsoever
And so one question is what could the parties fight about
In that campaign
Try to win voters
And I
Turns out while the overall economy is doing well there's one second it was being left behind
And was not doing well and that was a Greek
Farmers were feeling forgotten
Desperate
Because
They're losing their
Jobs
The economy is Shifting away from them and towards a
Fancy newfangled tacky
Industry
The coastal Elites
In this case back then the hot
Tacky industry is
Manufacturing making things
Like
Cars
Sewing machine
So this became an election issue
Save the farmer
Save the people who are being left
And
The Republicans and their president
Super they win the election
Herbert Hoover president of the United States
Stood before the people
His platform had been prosperity for everyone
By the time Hoover was giving his inaugural address
Republicans
In Congress were already trying to make good on this
Protect the farmers promise
Most notably
Reed Smoot
And Willis hawley describe these men for Alyssa
So one of them sort of tall and lean
That would be
Reed Smoot
And the others little shorter little squatter little fatter in that would be Willis Holly
You know the Muppets
Yes
You know Statler and Waldorf
They're my favorite Muppets yes they're the guys the old guys in the balcony who are
Jeering at the act on stage
No they can improve all Chauvet just change the ending
What are closer to the beginning
Who's the one more
I want them giving us something other than second-rate entertainment
What's up
Third grade entertainment
Person is you
Reed Smoot was a senator from Utah Willett Ali was a wreck
The different Oregon
They were the heads of the Committees in the Senate and a house that were in charge of tariffs at the
That's why their names are on the bill
The two agricultural products that were facing
The most
Foreign competition at that time were wool
And sugar
Tok so you can imagine one version of
That's where the pilot
Just say sugar and
Okay let's just put a tariff on imported sugar
And wool
And then we know we could debate
The benefits of that
But that is not even have a debate when
At all
Partly because of something called
Logrolling
Which is basically
Vote Trading
So
Say you're a representative from
Corn
State like Iowa
Wait
Why would I go for your sugar and wool tariff
I am not supporting that unless you put a tariff on
Horn button the Representative for Ohio
Would be like wait
Why am I going to vote for your sugar and will end
Corn Terrace
If you don't protect
My goldfish producers
And everyone's like
Goldfish producer
Apparently there was someone firm in Ohio that raise goldfish
And they thought that imported goldfish were eating into their mark
Talking like a little goldfish in a bag and a
Fair
Bicycle Tour talking about
Like orange goldfish
For your
Fathead
Like a goldfish
Did they get a tariff 35%
Industry after industry with lining up asking for a tear
Asking for
Protection
The congressmen were over
They worked day and night
A lot of complaints of members of Congress saying how
It'll stay up so late listening to
People droning on about
Clothespins and oil drums
Certain types of chemicals
New York State grain and hay Dealers Association they made the Polly on behalf of the humble buckwheat industry
And just to be clear
Humble back with a quote from what actually happened then
I think that buckwheat Dennis Cruz portray itself as humble so they say we are the humble
We dentist
There were so many Industries asking for protection that
The Senate heard from more than one
Thousand Witnesses
Who gave more than
8000 pages of pasta
And it's worth noting
Unlike sugar and wool a lot of
These industries
Barely had any for in combat
It's unclear that the Tariff would even help
Once the flood gates were open
Be humble buckwheat Growers the
Close Pin makers
The goldfish
Growers I guess
They were like
Come on
Why not us too
Yeah why can't we get a little bit
Right and so instead of
This being a
Terrifying
Sugar and wolin baby
One or two other agricultural industry
The ultimate number of tariffs
Was
How many
I think over 800
Cooperate
100 right
Of course Congress has passed
Carrots before or since the beginning of the country
But this particular group of congressmen seems to be going pretty
Tariff
Crazy
There is one group watching from the sidelines
Thinking
What are you
The Economist
When politicians are talking about terrorist
Economist get very
Exasperated
Because tariffs
It might seem like they're solving one problem
But they can cause a million other problem
That is true even for the people that are supposed to
I think we want to sort of
Help people understand like why this
Was going to potentially backfire imagine Sally is a wolf armor from from then so
Sepia what are we
Wool producer sheep from Shepherd she's a shepherd
So she raised the Tariff on wall that's definitely going to help
Sheep farmers and wool producers
They definitely want that that's why they were fighting for it
But also raises the cost of all the manufacturers of Woolen Goods
Trying to reduce coats in in pants and others for consumers
This is known as a downstream
Until that is one
Problem a tariff
On wall may help
Sally the shape
But it has these unintended ripple effect for other
And smoot-hawley was not just a tax on wool so
Now whatever benefits Ali the shepherd's getting there probably cancelled out by the fact
The tons of other things you need
Games to buy
Those are going to cost more because Sally
Can't get these things at the global competitive
And another thing Economist hate about Terrace is that they can cause chain reactions
Around the globe
Like
You can't just put a tariff on something and expect other countries to sit back and let that happen
There will be counter Terrace
And this is yet another on antenna
Consequences
The lawmakers
Apparently had not thought through back in 1930
They didn't answer
State that they would be retaliation
I mean that's so crazy like why not why would they not see that coming
Well because this was considered domestic legislation pure and simple and there'd be no foreign ramifications and that was the way it was
You thought about it
What time so there's this really a few of the reasons that
Economist were screaming into their pillows about the smoot-hawley bill
And before the bill made of
Is the President's Day
The Economist
Tried
To explain all this
One more Thai
Very
Clearly
A group of more than a thousand Economist got together a thousand economy
Adjust for inflation that is like
Thousand Economist by today's economy. Easily 5002 days Economist and they wrote and signed a letter
Begging President Hoover or Congress to
Stop this smoot-hawley nonsense
We have a copy of that letter right here
It outlines all of the ways these tariffs will be a disaster for
For the Economy Inn
Beautiful passionate meticulously detailed language that would
Hoover the politicians they were like
Nah
These Ivory Tower Elites they've never worked a day in their lives
Hoover sign the tariffs into law
And virtually everything The Economist warned would go wrong
Went wrong
One of the most insane
Examples is
X
American egg producers
Theoretically got the benefit of one of the many smoot-hawley tariff
The terrifying eggs went from $0.08 to $0.10 a dozen
But Canada
They were so incensed they raised their Terror from $0.03 to $10
Whoa
So that was reciprocity they want the same Turf as we did
And here is the beautiful boneheaded Twist of smooth
American egg producers
We're exporting a
They were making a ton of money by sending their eggs
Canada
Or at least they were
Before Smooth
Or exports fell from almost a million doesn't the 13000 dozen eggs
Are the same. So our exports of eggs really got wack
We lost a lot of dozens
And Canada was not the only country that got pissed off at Smoot
And Holly and
This kicked off an unprecedented wave
Protectionism
Acrostic
Protectionism aimed specifically at the United
There were a bunch more counter terrorist countries formed
Trade blocks against the US
Global trade fell by
6% in the years after this
Because of Smoot Hawley
And the protectionism that followed it
But also because of a little thing
Called
The Great
Holly was in the works
Before the Great Depression but it didn't pass until things
Had already started to go south
It so probably the nicest thing anyone says about smoot-hawley
Well
He didn't
Cause the Great Depression
Economist generally agree you know a lot of things cause of
Great Depression monetary policy Etc
But then the passage of smoot-hawley
It sure as hell
Did not have
We've tried nothing some metaphors off Doug Irwin
So
The Great Depression caused
The US economy
Basically
Flail in the water drowning
And the passing of smoot-hawley was the equivalent of sort of
Throwing it a brick
Or align with nothing attached to the other end
That's like words
Cuz it and you're giving people hope but then you start pulling on it there's nothing there
And how did smoot-hawley work out for
The politicians involved
Anyone
Anyone that workout
It turns out both Holly and Smith were kicked out of Congress by their constituents ultimately
Play so it didn't work out for them
It took decades to truly undo the damage from
Smoot-hawley II
Untangle the tariffs
Panda counter-terrorist
Counter counter tariffs
Foley
We did
The world moved away from protectionism
Towards free trade
Agreements were made the World Trade Organization was set up as a kind of
Referee and then four years you could shut down
Conversation about terrorists by just saying
Raleigh
In fact in the 1990s
Al Gore was debating Ross Perot
Perot was against the North American Free Trade Agreement
Gore brought a photograph of Smoot and Hawley
Scotus last time
So you can put it on your wall if you want to thank you thank you
That is the sound of Ross Perot cut up
Slamming this photo face down.
And that's because smoot-hawley had become shorthand for
Remember the last time we tried this
Protectionism
Is a bad idea
Of course
Things have changed
We have
To protect and build our steel and aluminum
Industrious
After the break
Holly
Interim
Attorney that lost
Support also comes from Fidelity Investment
As a Fidelity wealth manager
You get a dedicated advisor
To help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes
And make clear recommendations for your full Financial
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
So couple of things you may have noticed about
Today's tariffs
Haitian for one
Where is Congress in all of this
There were no hearings there was no vote there was no goldfish hopping no it appears as though the president was able to
Just Terrace
Yeah he kind of was
A huge difference between the smoot-hawley days and the Trump days
Is that
The president now has a lot more power to set tariffs
And you don't Trump did actually have to follow a process here he had to come up with justification in in the case of the steel and
Aluminum tariffs it was National Security to jump through some other Hoops as well but clearly he was able to
Get the Terrace done
And
This fact
The fact that the president Canal of uterus
Doug Irwin says
That is part of the legacy of Smoot Hawley
Yeah after congress went tarriff crazy in 1930 they basically said
Maybe we should have our tear
Privileges
Congress delegated powers to the president to oversee the whole tariff system
So essentially congress-led look we made a mess of it just didn't work out so well they were like a bunch of children who'd been let loose in a
Candy store
And realize they couldn't be trusted to moderate their own intake
They overate they got sick and they said
They need some restraint on themselves from doing that again so they just
Delegate to another party
Overtime they delegated that power to the executive branch and the president
They decided that is the better sister
Inarguably we are now watching that better
When Congress dealt with terrorists
The game was stacked
Against narrow
You want to protect only wool and sugar well good luck buddy because it's snowballs
Today President Trump wants to
To protect steel and aluminum you can stop there if you wanted to
He doesn't have to trade votes to get it pass
And so we're not
Hundreds of
Terrace like in the days of smoot-hawley and separating these very targeted
Very political terrorists
It could be that way
But these terrorists
Still have Economist like screaming into their pillows again
Because even narrow Terrace
Are going to cause the same web
Problems
Downstream effects
Ultimately shooting ourselves in the foot
We asked Doug Irwin
Like
Do you think in 20 years someone is going to write
A movie scene about a boring High School
Teacher
Teaching the lessons of the Trump
Tariffs and he was like
Who knows probably not
But
If they do make Ferris Bueller 2
Doug Irwin
Will be ready
Do you want to give a shot at doing the benstein thing but with the news of the day with the Trump news I could give it a shot
Okay
In 2018 the Republican administration of
Donald J Trump
It stood higher tariffs on anyone anyone steel and aluminum
An effort to protect the jobs of steelworkers
Did it work
Anyone anyone it did not work and we lost jobs and downstream user Industries and it failed to revitalize the steel
That is so off the top of your head well done
Today Show was produced by Lena Richards and edited by Brian Hurst
That our supervising producer is Alex Goldberg
Also we have a new video out this week it's part of our new series from the NPR video team this one is a
About why the price of Coke
Stay the same for so long
And it's hilarious it is
Is seriously worth the watch
Find it at npr.org Planet Money shorts
Or you can follow us on Facebook we have post it there too
Protectionism
If you want more info on smoot-hawley it is be placed
I'm finally home and I'm Kenny Malone
Thanks for listening