There are two kinds of
People in this world
People who think about germs people who do not
Lisa resin movich
Her life
I am the director of infection prevention here at Hunterdon health
Think of Lisa at the hand-washing police at this County Hospital in New Jersey
I have been called worse but yes
Yes that is a nickname
Well
We don't go into it but
Lisa is a germ investigator
So
I'm potentially exposed to a lot of on different types of bacteria viruses
Different pathogens that make people say
Lisa's job is to prevent germs from
Spreading
If anybody at this hospital has a bad bug they have to alert Lisa
Anytime there's a positive lab they automatically fax over the results
What is an incident report
Nothing good comes from the fact
Machine
And one morning last spring
It comes to life
Spits out a sheet of paper
She walks over
Picks up the paper turns it over and she sees
E-coli
O15
7 H7
This is the worst
Combination of numbers in letters
Is this kind of E coli
Is the really bad
They release something called the sugar tax
You can shut down your kidneys that can kill you
And Lisa
Bed bug investigator her job is to run straight toward the danger
Straight
To a 66 year old grandma Louise
Frasier
Normally pretty feisty
Mine or Miss is to either walk 6 miles or I run
3 miles
So very energetic
Yeah but today everyone in the hospital is
Poking and probing her they are not going to let her kidney
Blood test
Everyday
I think they suck me like
20 times in the one arm
Doctors are forcing liquids into her kidneys
To keep them from shedding down
She's weak
Bloated from all the fluids and
She just wants to lay there
With her eyes closed
Louise doesn't remember a lot about this
It's all a blur
But she remembers
Some woman coming
Sitting down next to her
This was Lisa
Of course she said I'm going to sit with you for like an hour we need to go through and talk about everything
You ate in the last week to 10 days
This is where Lisa's detective work
Start
Lisa needed to know everything that Louise ate every sauce every night every fruit
Because if you're sick with e-coli
You probably pick it up from something you ate
And Lisa
She needed a list of potential culprits
So she pulls out a calendar to help Louise remember
And we just went back
Date by date
And then as she told me what she ate
You then have to ask
What was in it
What was on the pizza
Where do you buy the food from
What ShopRite what Costco what
Supermarket
What supermarket can think about what you had for lunch
Last Wednesday
I was
Working at home
I got something out of the fridge
I don't remember what what did you have for dinner let's see last Thursday
I can pretty much guarantee I had cheese
Cuz I eat a lot of cheese
But I don't know where I got it from us we breakfast I know Brett
Okay the point is this stuff is
Really difficult I honestly have
No idea how Louise
Remember every single thing that she
At least that she's right there with her going through the calendar Mondays breath
What about lunch
Jenny snacks
And Louise is like no no Lisa
I can save you the trouble I know what the problem
I had this huge meal the day before I started feeling
It was a fish fry for the local fire
I was eating fried clams
Pierogies I was eating french fries and then I topped it off by going to our local ice cream store and having ice cream
I'm thinking that's what made me sick
It was not the fish
The fire department did not accidentally poison Louis
Do not blame the firefighters but something did Poison
And it poisoned a bunch of other people too
Hello and welcome to Planet Money
I'm Sarah Gonzales
Louise is not the only one who's sick
At the same time all across the country hundreds of people are getting
And there's an army of investigators trying to figure out
Why
Today on the show we join the investigation
Go on the trail of a nasty micro all the way to a valley in the desert
Heads will
Roll
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Is reimagining Bank
I offering account
With no fees or
Animals that can be opened from anywhere in
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
There is a step by step method to solving a true food
And the very first piece of the puzzle is
Which
Food
This is why Lisa resume average SAT there with Louise Frazier in your hospital room
Going through those food memory
Deliciously shameful food memories
Monday I took my
Grandson to
The show
Great meal that day I had ice
I had a hot dog
Ice cream on my way home that was my that was my meals those days
We talked about bad habits
My kind of girl there were some healthy things to though a meal at a Panera restaurant
A Fuji apple chicken salad
My favorite there
And Lisa our infection fighter
She's back in your office typing
Fuji apple chicken salad into this
National early warning system
If microbes are launching a sneak attack
This is how the whole country finds out about it
So she's right there typing all this information in
And then the fax machine
Comes to life again
Another case of E coli
In her Hospital
Music does the same thing runs to the patient
Calendar survey and
Whoa
This patient
Also ate a salad at
Panera
At least a thing
I got to let the big bosses at the County Health Department know about this
So she calls Kathy jig
Whose job is to
Stay calm
So she called me that
There's something suspicious going on I have two cases of e-coli
At the same time
And Kathy's thinking Pinterest
I'll keep an eye on that
And then she gets another call
This time from the state
And they tell her to more people
In the next County over have also just tested positive for e-coli
I was shocked surprised and my adrenaline was flowing
And now Kathy has to find out what the
They hate
Because if they ate at a Panera that's more than a coincidence
That's a pattern
So she calls and she gets through to one of the page
Your husband was at the bedside
And the
Wife would answer the questions through him and he wouldn't answer my
They go through all her meals and
Yep
This patient also ate a salad from Panera
But we all ate at
Different Panera
And this is important because
It was the same restaurant
Chances are
The problem is at the restaurant maybe someone wasn't watching their hands right
But the fact that people are getting sick from food at different Panera's means this is bigger
This
Goes up the food chain
All these sick people
Had different
Salads
So investigators start looking at
The ingredients in the salad is it the tomatoes is it
The carrots is it the hearts of palm they all had one thing in
Lettuce
Well
Sure cuz
It's a salad
But specifically
It was romaine lettuce
But then people all over the country start getting
Sick dozens are hospitalized
People who never ate at a Panera
One guy pick up a Caesar salad at a Costco in Idaho
So at this point it becomes
Clear
Panera is not
The problem
It's
The Romaine
5 people died
And now
The feds are involved
The nation's top
Cop on the food infection beat
He is on the
Every moment
Is of the essence
This is Steve ostrow from the Food and Drug Administration
Before he was in the FDA he was an assistant Surgeon General
A rear Admiral people saluted him and he's like okay so we know it's the Romaine but which
Romaine from what farm exactly
Who is growing this
Contaminated lettuce
The more we can narrow in on this thing the better if we can find the
The store that selling it
The farm
Came from
The exact field we can shut it
Down order a recall
Save
Deep senses investigators to restaurants
Some grocery stores where sick people bought their lettuce
We say showers for records
Azteca
That romaine lettuce that you were
Serving
Or that you had sitting on the grocery store shelf on that day
And it is so hard to
To track a leaf of lettuce back to where it came from
Restaurants are telling Steve little army
We got this remain from a bunch of different processors and processors are like
We got it from a bunch of different farms and chopped it all up
Together
The investigators are getting
Nowhere
Naked berry
Prostrating the only thing they know is the most basic fact of lettuce geogra
Pretty much all the lettuce in the US comes from just to place
Sisters Yuma Arizona and the Salinas Valley in California
They sort of take turns
Yuma grows in the fall and winter
The Salinas Valley takes over in the
Spring and summer
Given the timing this contaminated lettuce mustard
Just come from Yuma
So the government pulls out their biggest bluntest will they tell the whole country
Any romaine lettuce from Yuma
Could
Kill you
And I remember this
Very distinct
I was texting my mom and my sister is like
Nobody by Romaine it is killing people that you were actually part of a big problem
Did the country the government was saying don't buy Romaine from Yuma Arizona
And what everybody heard was
Is just don't buy Romaine
Yeah that's what I heard
Even Lisa the infection fighter who got the
This whole thing rolling
She had two menacing heads of romaine lettuce in
I'm looking at them and I thought well
How do I know if the this is packaged in
Do you Marie I didn't go to Arizona and buy it from there I bought it from a supermarket around here
And at that time I had
Been in the supermarket
And they were too
If directed
Any romaine lettuce
To pull off the shelf
So everyone is just dumping all their Romaine in the trash
But here is the weird thing about
About this by the time people reacted to that warning most of the lettuce wasn't even coming from Arizona anymore it was coming
From California
So it was farmers in California took the hit
Nobody wanted to buy their romaine lettuce either
So California Farmers
Have no other choice
They had
To destroy their beautiful healthy Romaine
Ran over it
With these big machines that chopped up all these heads of lettuce and plowed them into the dirt they
They had to bury
Perfectly healthy lettuce
And then the sounds so sad to me
Dan
It's so hard to be a farmer
It is not just Public Health officials who are looking into this
There's a guy in Seattle
A lawyer he's watching this very careful
Kentucky's got his own investigation
His name is Bill Marler
You know I have a morbid curiosity to these things cuz I've been doing this for so long
If you get sick from food and you want the food companies to pay
Bill is the guy you call he sues food companies for a living
And he's serious
The last time salad was making a lot of people sick
Bill Marler got on a plane to California looking for info on how it
I camped out in Salinas and San Juan Bautista for a week
Hanging out in bars
Trying to find
Where the investigators were
Bill is now representing Louise Louise who is having fluids pumped into her kidneys
He's also representing about a hundred other
People who got sick during this
Romaine E coli outbreak
He's obsessively following every new Story related to this
Staying and
He comes across one that seems like a really big
Break
It came
From a prison
That's right a Prison Break
8 men in a prison in Nome Alaska of all place
Asus got sick from E coli
And because they were locked up investigators Newegg
Exactly what they did
But it wasn't chopped up salad mix
This time it was
Whole heads of lettuce
And the prison had invoices
Showing exactly where it
Paris Farm Show
It was a it was a pretty good
Little piece of evidence he thinks this is it we've got the corporate this one farm and
Everybody wants the contamination to lead back to just one
Farm
This is the best case scenario
For consumers for the FDA
Even for the farmers
Except for the farmer whose name is on the invoice
Ultimately there can be one person to blame and therefore you're blameless
You at least can avoid
You know direct responsibility
But here's the problem
Louise did not eat lettuce
That's grown on the same Farm as the prisoners
There wasn't one trail of contaminated lettuce
There were a lot
Trail
Leading to a bunch of different farms in Yuma
Miles apart
To something else happened in these
Fields
Something
Mysterious
After the break
We catch a flight to Yuma Arizona we are on the hunt for e-coli
O157 H7
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Capital One is reimagining Bank
I offering accounts with no fees or minimum
That can be opened from anywhere in
5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Na
All winter long
America's salad comes from a narrow Valley
5 miles wide and 50 Meandering miles long
It follows the Colorado River
When I was there it was Blazing
Oppressive
When the weather turns cooler this place is perfect for growing crops
Most of the farmers in Yuma did not really want to talk to me about ecola it is not a pleasant
Syntopicon
One farmer though he said come on over
Steve Alameda
Big lettuce grower
Co-owner of Top flavor Farms
I found it
How are you I'm good how are you
Places amazing he was bald got a plaid shirt and mudding issues he's super friendly and super proud of what he does
I say can you show me around
Usher
He chose me cotton field Hayfield some date
Trees and Acres of bare dirt that will turn into lettuce fields
7 another five months is a wallaby green I'll be green with veggie
You can grow anything here well it's
For a grower
Would what would I put the
We just be like being in the Silicon Valley I equated to that
I tell Steve that I am on the trail of E coli
And he's like yeah you and the whole FDA
He says there's a team of them
Poking around this Valley
Testing the water that
Farmers used
To water their crops
And Steve son Mike
She knows exactly where they are like right now
And he pulls up a map
So I'll drop a pin right here on that road
And and where's the canal
Right below it
If the E coli is out there I am going to find
Have a good day thank you you too
IHOP in my rental car
I head east
It takes a while but eventually I find
There's a van and a white Suburban
9 people are standing along a
Concrete lines
Ditch with water running long.
Most of them look like grads
Summer wearing blue latex gloves
They have cooler
Hi-Tech scientific
Every so often one of them reaches down and fills a bucket
With water
A broad-shouldered guy comes over to say hello
He's an FDA employee based in Yuma
He says they can't tell me much about what they're doing out here
Very sensitive
And a few hundred feet away there's another Canal filled with water this is a bigger one
A bunch of farmers use that water on their lettuce
And right next to this water
Cow
As far as the eye can see
Thousands of them
Just standing there quiet
Quietly
They won make any noise he wouldn't move for you know they're standing there on this
Bearger lined up alongside
Troughs filled with corn and hay
Eating
Not moving
Pooping
Cattle
The animals that most often carry E coli o157
This is where E coli comes from
Humans sometimes but it's usually
Animals
Deer
Wild pigs
Cow
This might be where the long search
For the source of the contamination
This might be where that search ends
Actually here goes a truck
Caring cattle manure out into the fields where it's composted
Driving right past this ditch
The FDA found e-coli
Invest
Water canal be exact genetic strain that got everyone sick
Their theory is that e-coli from the
Cow manure
Washed into this irrigation ditch or
Blue in
And then the contaminated water to
Flowed into
All the vegetable fields
Across
The valley
I talked to Steve about this day
He doesn't get his water from it but his lettuce farming friends
And they've actually been worried about these cows for a long time
Cuz they're just so close to the vegetables
You got like I say 100000 animals that the real culprit space
So you know what you be
You before not to not to have that pop in your head
Anyway I can say we're aware of it
And we were always
Checking for it looking in
Hoping that we can
Survive you know next to each other but which we've done four
60 years
And in
So did something change something happened that we that we
We need to know I need to know
The lettuce growing season in Yuma is supposed to start up again in just a couple of months
And Steven is friends want to grow lettuce again
But those cattle are still there
And the farmers
Don't know what to
To do the FDA hasn't announced any rules or
Even recommendations for what
The farmer should do differently and the thing that really scares the farmers
Is the possibility that the people who buy their lettuce
The big supermarket
Get some processors
Maybe they will say we don't trust lettuce from Yuma any
We won't buy it
Bill Marler the food safety lawyer says they should be worried
If there's another outbreak like this
A tough question for a Walmart or tough question for Costco is
Flydubai
You know product
From a place that you know is near
A feedlot that just had an outbreak last
That's a that's a very uncomfortable question
That a lawyer gets to ask
Steve and his fellow lettuce farmers are trying to figure this out one way they're talking about
Is to treat
Irrigation canal with chlorine
To kill any e-coli
But they've also been talking about something more drastic
Maybe those cows are now just too much of a
Threat to the lettuce and
Maybe the lettuce Farmers have to
The band together and buy the Feedly
Just to kick the cows out
Shut it down
4 century
Farmers of raised
Their animals
And their vegetables
Side by side
But farming has reached
Such a scale now
Maybe they can't annies
Maybe this Valley
Just ain't big enough for the both of them
Poor cows
You can send a story idea Planet Money at npr.org
We're also on Facebook Twitter and Instagram I'll put up some pictures from the trip
Today's show was produced by Elisa is garce and Alexi Horowitz.
Nick Fountain edited
And our big bosses are Alex goldmark and Brian Turner
Many thanks to China Rock Christina tan and Karen DeMarco for their help with this episode
I'm dance worlds