This is a bonus episode here in the Planet Money feet and it's for a special occasion
Other podcast
The indicator from Planet Money
Turned one-year-old this month
We have picked out one of our favorite episodes from the past year
To Mark the occasion
If you don't listen to the indicator it's like Planet Money
But it comes out every weekday
It's always 10 minutes or less
We think of it as a daily economics
Crash course on what's happening in the
So he was a favorite episode of the indicator from Planet Money
It ran back in June
The Venezuelan economy has
Years of Economic mismanagement and a worsening political crisis have led to a recession that has almost no parallel
In recent memory
Explaining just how bad things
I've gotten is also really hard because the normal economic indicator
There's that we used to measure countries
Economy
I started to sound so
Crazy so unfathomable
Did it feels impossible to get our heads around
Bridge Apple inflation in Venezuela right now is running it almost 20
G5
Thousand
Percent a year
And that one estimate almost nine out of ten piece
People are living
This was an upper middle-income country that has become
Super poor country
And so the numbers changed so dramatically that are the reality of people changes so dramatically
That babe
Is it
Is no longer
Can be captured by the traditional numbers
That's Ricardo hausmann
He is a Venezuelan Economist based
Harvard
And if we understand what's been happening in his native tongue
Country he's had to be inventive
If you had to construct an economic indicator that did not exist
One that communicates the full-scale.
Calamity in ways that makes
I'm Cardiff Garcia
And I'm Stacey Vanek
On The Chew today what Ricardo came up with
What is indicator reveals what conventional economic numbers sometimes missed when it country is rapidly
Collapsing
Support for this NPR Podcast in the following message come from policygenius.com
The easy way to compare and buy insurance online
With policygenius
You can compare quotes from top rated carriers
Get unbiased advice from licensed experts
And apply online in minutes
Whether you're shopping for Life disability Home Auto or renters insurance
If you care about it
They can cover it
Compare and save on insurance today at policygenius.com
Throughout the 2000s
The Venezuelan government borrowed at
Haunted money
To pay for social programs and other things
And the government felt safe borrowing the money because it's a
Economy produce a lot of oil and oil prices were really high
The government borrowed so much money that went oil prices fell a few years ago it didn't have enough money left over to pay both
Both of the programs and
To pay off a
Stats
In one of the government's
Responses within start printing money and raising wage
Bridge workers
That led to hyper
Not only that but the government had also taken over big parts of the economy from the private sector
And then mismanaged
Combination of hyperinflation and this mismanagement led to a big shortage
Even basic items like toilet paper became hard
Find and therefore incredibly expensive when people could buy them
Ricardo hausmann says that people in developed countries like relatively rich country such as
Does the US
Don't necessarily have a useful frame of reference for understanding just
How bad things have gotten
In Venezuela
For example the US has been traumatized by the Great Recession of 2008
A 2009 etcetera
Well that recession is probably
10th
The size of
What happened
In Venezuela
Wow how do you explain something that's 10 times bigger
Traditional metrics like inflation and unemployment don't really work when a country is in free
In the United States inflation is about 2% a year
That just means that the average price of the stuff that we America
5 goes about 2% every year
So what does it mean for a country to have almost 25000 percent in
Inflation like Venezuela
As for unemployment government simply stopped reporting that number more than 2 years ago
So I was trying to communicate in all the collapse in Livingston
Gender
It's it's
It's very hard
To make those numbers
Baby intelligible
Foreign economic catastrophe this severe
The figures for inflation or unemployment can feel like abstraction
Sara Carter got to work on an indicator that's not just
Concrete
Imprecise
But when it really gets the human toll
The crisis
Has been exact
He starts with a fact about the Venezuelan economy
It's both astonishing and depressing
And it's this
The minimum wage in Venezuela is also the median wage
This means that more than half of Venezuelan workers are in the minimum wage
So when the government
Increases the minimum wage most of the Venezuelan population gets away
Grace and keep up with Rising prices the government has been increasing the minimum wage a lot in the last cup
But two months ago for example the government raise it by a hundred
55%
Another
Crazy number
But how much more can a Venezuelan really Buy on that wage
Give me the price of everything is going up so fast
People's wages might be going up a lot but if prices are going up even more than living standards in the country are still getting worse
Just how much worse is the question Ricardo wanted to
And he wanted to explain it in simple.
So here's what he came up
So we decided to measure for example the income of people
In terms of the calories you can buy
Verde
So you know
How many calories can you buy if you were to spend 100% of your income at the cheapest available calories
Works Ricardo his team tractel prices
Different foods in Venezuela change from month to month
And each month you would find the food they gave you the most calories for each Boulevard
What is the Venezuelan
At the food cost
In other words he was looking for the cheapest
Food available
And since Venezuela has shortages of food the cheapest food available would sometimes change
Pasta or corn flour
But now even those food
Unaffordable so right now the cheapest food is the gecko
Take a typical Venezuelan worker
Someone who makes the minimum wage
If you spent every single Boulevard from his weight on that cheapest food available
How many calories could you buy in one day
Here is the incredible in French
Devastating ant
This a calculation that went from buying 57000 calories a day in 2012
Buying less than $900
Calories today 900
Calories
That's today's Planet money into
900 calories
All the calories
Set the minimum wage will get you in Venezuela after
You working an entire day
Which means I do know if a person normally spends over 2000 calories a day
It means that a worker
It cannot
Being himself
Let alone his family
And that's assuming he doesn't spend anything in clothing in France
Asportation
In
And medicines
And housing
It's so it just gives you a sense of how
Catastrophic
Maggie's doll collection
Put that 900 calories in context
In United States you can buy more than a hundred thousand calories in one day on the minimum wage
Venezuelan people are starving
Anacardo told us about it
A couple of other similar statistics that also tell the story
You'll see we we did as we measured it just an ex
How many eggs can you buy
Well before you know another you could buy several dozen eggs now you can buy two eggs
That's it
Who acts and that was important for us to calculate because
It's not just calories it's also protein
Hey that people need
And so you know right now people in Venezuela
If I 2X
A recently people have calculated what is the cost of a Big Mac how long does it take you to work
To make enough to buy a Big Mac and in Venezuela right now that's a month-and-a-half
2x a day
Order afford a Big Mac
The Venezuelan worker would have to save every single ball of our he earned
A month
And a half
The inevitable result of this has been that Venezuelans are losing a lot of
Survey from three universities in Venezuela founded
The average Venezuelan lost 24 pounds last year
Because they could not afford to
And hundreds of thousands of children are at risk of dying from starvation and malnutrition
This economic collapse has been accompanied by a
A societal collapse
In Law and Order
Braswell
And even though the government has stopped
Publishing the data on that there are credible estimates show in the Venezuela probably now has the highest murder rate
The world the situation has become so intolerable that a staggering number of Venezuelans are just leaving the car
Ricardo and his colleagues estimate that almost 10% of the Venezuelan population emigrated in the past year
That is almost 3 million people
If we were to try to analogize that to it happening in the United States for instance where there's
300 and something million that would be the equivalent
30 million Americans leaving the country
Every single year
This is astonishing and I'm wondering if there's any
Precedent
I mean
This is
A migration of Siri and proportion
A butt in Syria
People fleeing linode
Insecurity people fleeing the war
The people fearing
Imminent death
Am in Venezuela
It must be something as serious as
Fearing imminent death
Regenerate
Is that magnitude of enough
That was an episode of the indicator from Planet Money and it ran in June
Since then
Inflation in Venezuela has gone from 25000 percent
More than a million
To see how Venezuelans are doing better or worse
Put in calorie terms with our house Monroe earlier this month
That a day's work
The median wage but not by you
1.7
And to get a pound of cheese
It would take
8 days
The indicator from Planet Money is there help you make sense of the numbers that matter in the world
It's every weekday afternoon 10 minutes or less
Subscribe to the indicator from Planet Money wherever you listen to podcasts
Soarescue smart speaker
To play the indicator podcast
I'm Alex goldmark and thanks for listening to Planet Money