There are these videos you may have seen in December it felt like they were everywhere for a while there
Stop from cars driving down the 405 freeway in Los Angeles it's dark out
The cars drive through this Valley and they pass between two Hills that are completely
On fire it looks like the cars are driving
Straight down into hell
I grew up not far from those Hills
And I spent
A lot of time watching these videos as
Wildfires were spreading throughout Southern California
It was a really bad virus
I'm about to get on the 405
I went to Los Angeles in January because I really wanted
Stand on those Hills
I wanted to see
What do they look like now
Soap
I drove up there
I got out of my car and
Right away I saw a house that
Clearly
Burnt wow pasta house there was a trail leading up into the hills I can see the four
405 freeway down blow me twisted up trees
Oh my God there's like a shell of a car on the side of the Hill
Walking through a weird Wasteland it's really eerie
I don't know what exactly I'm looking at
Except that the fire was definitely
Here
But I called someone who would know what he
Hi are you Robert
Hello
Robert Rowe agree to meet me here because
He can look at a burnt up Hillside like this
And read it like a book
He's a former firefighter
And for more than a decade now he has had his own fire investigation
I design my own logo little little guy with a magnifying glass with a flat top and
Espiral Got Run
And your pirate
We start walking up the hill together
So when you walk
Up here
What do you notice first I mean to me it just looks like a sort of
Apocalyptic
Bland
So
As we're approaching a a shrub here
We're going to be looking at
Robert starts turning over
Rock climbing up trees that are burned almost
Despot that were in it's like
One chapter of the fire that burned here
What was called the skirball fire
A discoloration on
Reading this
See where the Flames were coming from
Were they traveling up the hill or down the hill or across the hill
When we got up to
Peak
He tells me that far traveler there's no question
Did you see that right when you walked on the scene
Well
Yeah pretty much when a wildfire breaks out
Pyro cops like Robert they show up at the scene and they have
Enormous
Power
Because
The spot the fire started and the reason it started
Those are going to have
Huge consequences
For a lot of people
You can identify the source of ignition down to fraction of an inch
And it becomes somebody's equipment
That either failed or somebody's action
Then
I'm going to go to jail
Or somebody's going to have a hefty recovery bill but they're going to have to pay
Billions
Billions of the bee
Hello and welcome to Planet Money on Sally home
And I'm Kenny Malone
Wildfires are not like other natural
World disasters because you can't pin an earthquake on a single Reckless teenager you can't
Teresa hurricane back to the first Gustav
But with a wildfire you can find your way back
To the first
Spark
You can find a reason this disaster happened
And sometimes
Someone has to pay
Today on the show
How to find a source of a deadly wildfire
How to find the line
Between a natural disaster and a human
Support for NPR in the following message come from servicenow
Making the world of work work better for
Their cloud-based Platte
Form and solutions deliver digital workflow
Clothes that create great experiences for employees
And unlock productivity
For your whole company
Servicenow digitizes the work your people have to
So they can do the work
They want to do
Using technology
How to make people more productive and engaged
Moritz servicenow.com
There's an official list of the
The top 10 most
Struct wildfires
And if you look at that list three of those fires happened in the last six
It is been a horrific fire scene
And next to each of those
Fires on this list
He's like a little note
Where the
The cause of the fire
All of these recent fire
It says
Under
It could take months
For those investigations to wrap up
And so
We're going to look back at a different fire
One of the biggest most destructive fires in California history
And we're going to tell the story of how that blank got filled in and
Presidents are getting worried that they must leave their homes immediately
Within just the first
Few hours at The Witch Creek fire burn
Starfire quadrupled in size and white now
On October 21st 2007 The Witch Creek fire started
Somehow
And then spread
Shockingly
It was unclear exactly how bad the damage would be but
One thing was
Clear The Witch Creek Fire was going to be one of the big one
I was on duty in Riverside unit as a fire captain specialist
This is Matt
He works for a state agency known as Cal Fire
Bass we got a phone call
Sending me to the witch fire
Media origin causes
When is the murder you
There's a fire
You send Matt Gill
Matt drives towards the area where the first reports came
From which means
Gives driving towards
The fire
Which is pretty intense
But Matt seems chill about it
Empire on both sides of the road
What was that like
Fairly typical for a job
Somax driving through
Two sided fire
And he can see which way the Flames are blowing in the wind
So he knows roughly
Where the fire is coming
He drive down to the edge of the burn Zone
There's still some smoke around black and grasses everywhere
This is where he starts
His investigation
The part where I was at was on top of a ridge
The wind was blowing to the point where I'm at at moments it was very difficult not very difficult
But you can definitely feel the winds blowing your progress is your wife
The format can figure out what started this
He needs to figure out exactly where this fire stick
And the fire leaves a lot of signs
It's been an investigator like Matt
Can follow back
He can see the direction that the fire burned across
A tree
It's like an arrow pointing him towards the
Same is true with
Charred rocks on the
Trash
Cans and bottles anything that's left on the ground
He walks and walks follow the fires Trail and whines up at what he is almost certain is
Is the spot the fire started
The sign
Pointing Towards the Sky
There's a dirt road winding through this
Rocky ranchland
You would not be surprised if he's a cowboy riding through the background
And this is the point where the process changes
Now that is looking for the actual cause
Fire
And it is sort of like the game Clue
Like he's figured out
That the crime was committed in the conserva
Satori
And
He doesn't just get to look down and see if there's a wrench or revolver lying there
He has to
Eliminate all of the
Weapon choices
And figure out what actually started
Yeah that's a process process of elimination it's a way to make sure he's being as
Thorough and scientific
Possible
And Matt has been like
Fire investigator school
You have a whole list of these potential fire causes in his head
Debris burning
Lightning
Spontaneous combustion
What is that
This is where I often times you will see you in
Like a mulch pile
Under the right conditions
Can Sophie and
Wow really
Yes
Petscop
Okay
Somat looks around
For mulch piles
You didn't see anything
You check the dirt for tire tracks
Because cars can start a fire
He looks berglas
Bottles apparently in rare circumstances sunlight can refract through a glass bottle
Start a wildfire
Matt doesn't see anything like that laying around
How about smoking ice out of here about you know
Don't flick a cigarette out your car window or whatever is that is that a real thing
It's
Not as common as one might think
All my partners and I carry a pack of cigarettes in the truck
And
We tried it and I have yet to
Mets sifting through dirt
Shearing under rocks checking
Weather report
He sees no cigarettes
No signs of arson no reports of lightning
Well at this point after all those
Right now we're looking at the power
The power lines
Really technical at this point in our conversation
He speaks carefully
I was able to observe damage to the power lines
Where it appeared to be small sections of the power line work
When you said small sections were missing he means that there
Little Nick's in the metal wire
Spots of
Visible damage
Do you sort of thing
Do you know what's going on at that point
At this point it's not a 100%
Determination
But
I've got something that bears further follow up
Here's the part of the story where we say the company that owned those power lines San Diego Gas & Electric
Never remember Matt starts this investigation on day one of the fire and within a day or two he is already zero
Zeroing in on a car
But he won't release information until he's done
Complete
Location and so he keeps on investigating
In the meantime all the public knows at this point is that the Witch Creek Fire is burning
And spreading and is very day
People actually did die in this fire
And other people are trying to escape
Some of them are recording videos as a cruiser homes thread
Is here
You can hear all the fire trucks in the distance
One person looking out his window seeing all of this
Is Terry single
In very short order
The sky
Wildfire was moving Dangerously
Close to Terry sing
So you were ready you were
Pretty much packed up
Stuff I really did not want to lose weight
50 years of photographs and that sort of thing
Cancel documents but that was it
Mostly photos
Yeah I think I also have my
Terry's able to laugh about this now
In part because the fire spared his house but
He's an attorney and he's part of this neat legal industry
Actually more like
2 Army
Did start lining up
When a wild fire starts to spread
Terry in the past as represented victims of wildfires just like this
And so
Carrie starts
Getting calls from people who are losing their homes
And they're saying
Terry
Is there going to be anything we can do about this and on the other side
Car companies
We're calling their attorneys and wonder
Are we going to get sued for this
And some of them may have called
Ready camp
Anything that can create a spark
Can anyone who can be responsible for creating that spark could be a client of mine someday
In 2007 Randy was a lawyer for a cable company and a tree trimming
That got sued
Over other big fires burning near which Creek
Randy has been a part of this Wildfire legal world for years
He says
When a fire starts spreading
You'll have all these opposing lawyers and
They hire private fire investigators
Insurance companies have lawyers and
Their own investigators
They're all showing up on the perimeter of these buyers
Sometimes
Literally
Upma
I'll go to places I was working a fire in Texas Nathaniel still burning I'm walking down this dirt road mystalk small town
Town in Texas I turn the corner
And there are five guys I know
It's like a traveling Road Show sometimes
So Randy hears about the fires in San Diego and
And he goes down there
Terry the lawyer for victims he's there to both of them are getting information
Turn from their
Gators word is going around that power lines may have been involved in one of the fires
And so these two legal armies are gearing up
But the official word on the cause
Is going to come
Forum at Gilbert
What he found
After the break
Support for this podcast and the following message
Did come from the this week in Google podcast
Cast at twit.tv
Every week
Leo Laporte
Jeff Jarvis and Stacey Higginbotham
Talk Tech media and privacy
The unapologetically question if Google Amazon Twitter Facebook and other Tech Giants are on the right
Attract subscribe to this week in Google
On your favorite podcast
Or it's wet. TV / twig
Matt Gilbert had Cena's damage power lines
The origin of the Witch
Witch Creek Fire but
To be sure about the cause he got in touch with
The first person to report the
It was a pilot
Who works with the same state agency is
Cal Fire
The pilot was in the air over which Creek and saw the fire when it was still small
Matt wants to know if he
He'd seen anything weird around that spot
And the pilot says
You know
Okay did see something
Power lines
Observe the line of
Bluish colored flashes
That works
Blowing With the Wind waves
To be as certain as possible Matt gets access to data from San Diego Gas & Electric about those very Powerline
Find sea salt the area of Orange
It's her technical data but
He reads it
And conclude
On the day of the fire just minutes before that fire was first reported
Something has
With the power lines
That very well may have
Caused
The first Spark
So at this point are you 100% sure
At this point I was comfortable
Releasing the official cause of the
Would you say 100%
Basically at this point when I
Based on all the available information I have
I think in that Gilbert speak that means he's Shore
He says in the scheme of fires he's investigating
This one was pretty clear
Enzyme that releases the official cause of the witch King
Greek fire
It was the power lines operated by
San Diego Gas
Electric
Lawyers had already launched into the legal battle
Lawsuit said Rd
Been filed
And now with an official cause
Even more Suits start time
How many cases were there about this fire
I think
That number includes the Witch Creek Fire and those two other fires that were burning nearby at the same time and it was actually Eva
Even more than two.
All told there were about
100 claims
Spawn by those fires
Loads of people sued San Diego Gas & Electric
San Diego Gas & Electric turned around and sued
Some other companies like
Randy's clients who are in charge of tree trimming for example victims Sue those companies as well
Kenny everybody is suing everybody
And
In the end
The companies
Do not admit fault or liability
But they do pay a lot of money in settlement
In total for all the fires plus legal fees
More than two
Billion dollars
That money got paid out by a number of entity
All told San Diego Gas & Electric
Themselves
Had to pay a reported
379 million dollars
The lawyers and
People who lost money or stuff
In the fires
This whole process this whole Witch Creek Fire industry
Actually
Isn't even wrapped up yet
There are still some lawsuits and loose ends getting sorted out and it's been more than
Years since that first start
Terry though the lawyer for the victims
He's settled all his case
I asked what it felt like when he settled the last one
Emotional experience
Going through that
You're supposed to be representing
And you
You try to protect
Terry says these big settlement payments do a couple things
They mean that
Victims get help rebuilding their lives
Money on top of any Wildfire insurance they may have
And the settlements also hold companies accountable
So they'll do all they can to prevent the next big wildfire
Get to prevent a disaster
But this raises an almost philosophical Quest
What is a natural
Disaster
And what is a disaster caused
Like if a deadly Wildfire is started by a light
Strike is it a natural disaster then
Probably
How about a bottle
Left there by human
Just the wrong way by sunlight
Is Hannibal the Foster
Maybe
And it started by a power line
Filter by humans
Who are supposed to be making sure that it doesn't cause a fire
Things like that could be a human disaster
But climate change maybe making it harder to say what is an act of God and what's an act
A man like
What if a spark comes from a power line and then it lands on super dry brush that is dry because of a historical
A long drought
Where does the natural disaster end
Human disaster
Begin
Back above the 405 freeway in Los Angeles I was
Heading home out of those Burnt Hills
And I stopped in front of that house
Oh my God you can see the the roofs caved in exposed pipes there's
Black and bean sticking up
Still don't know the source of many of the big fires that
California last year
But
Investigators actually did find the cause of this one
It was a cooking fire in a homeless encampment a little ways down the mountain
Any Spark
Can start a fire
But not all Sparks are financially
Sequel for the Spire there will be no huge settlement to help pay the price
Tell us what you think of the show you can email us Planet Money at NPR
R. O r g or find us on Facebook Twitter and Instagram Today show with produced by Nick Fountain Alec School
WorldMark is our senior producer Bryant first at a tattoo shop on Eldridge and Scott in the plane
Iran to Justice John Trotter and lawyer Kenroy also we are looking for an intern
North summer if you Loveland money and will help us make it and are in school or have graduated
Check it out it stayed I started out as a Planet Money interns great job you can find more info at NPR.
Shmoney
And if you're looking for something else to listen to embedded is back there doing some stories on
President Donald Trump and Russia it's really interesting listening check out embedded on NPR one
1 or whatever get your podcast I'm Kenny Malone