10 years ago in early September 2008
We still had no idea how bad it was
The housing crisis was picking up steam
But Lehman Brothers
Han collapse
The financial Panic hadn't spread through the banks
Through the whole world
And at that moment
That is when
Planet Money launched its first episode
We are going deep into the archives so deep that some of the podcast players don't even go back that far
We're going to revisit our very first episode
Summer will be covered back that has changed and in some interesting ways
But a lot of it
Hold up
Wait more than I expect
First episode sounds like an experiment
Because
It was
It's about the trade deficit with China
How exactly the dollars flow back and forth
Giant Loop changing what they pay for at each step
The end of today show will have an update on how the story is changed and about which predictions came true
Do you want to listen to other vintage episodes we've made a list of 10 of our favorites
It is at npr.org
Planet Money 10 numeral
Npr.org
Splash Planet Money 10
After the break our very first episode
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is
Good days start with
Straight jeans
How did they make them so great Madewell starts with
Premium denim
Then offers men's and women's styles for seriously every
Also you can recycle any brand of jeans in a Madewell store
And they'll give you $20 off a new pair
They work with the blue jeans go green program
Turn old jeans
The housing insulation for communities in need
Terms apply
Ready to find your perfect fit
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
I'm pretty sure you've heard this idea that China and the US are in a crazy kind of codependent relationship
We keep buying stuff from China with our dollars than China turns around and lends those dollars
Right back to us
So we can then buy some more stuff
China
They want some more money to us on and on
But
What you might not know and I didn't know until very recently is that Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac those to come
Chinese you heard a lot about lately
They are Central they are crucial
To that whole recycling of money process they make it happen or at least they helped make it happen
I'm going to explain in a second but first let me tell you I am Adam Davidson
International economics correspondent for national
Public Radio
And I'm
Just starting to run something new here at NPR we're calling it Planet Money
And our goal is to take the big complex global economic issues
The kind of thing I think most people feel like they really should know a lot about and understand but they don't then they get
Really confused
Our job here what we're trying to do is to make this all easier for you
We're working really hard and
We will succeed
At least most of the time to help you understand
How the world economy works
And how it affects your life
And right now this right here is our first ever
Podcast
Tantrum
Today I'm going to talk to Brad
Used to working at a treasury
Department
And you should be glad I'm talking to Brad because
He knows this financial entered the
Ending relationship
Between the US and China better than
Anyone I can think of
Over the years
He has really helped me understand how the US and China Financial system works and let me just give you the
The basic idea before we get to Brad
So you buy a DVD player t-shirt something made in China
You give your dollars to the store
They take those dollars and give them to some importer who brought the thing into the country
The Importer
Take some of that money and send a check to China to the factory that made whatever it is you bought
So think of it from the factory owners perspective he's in China he's getting all these dollars but he has
Employs his electric bills he is all this stuff in China so he doesn't want dollars he wants the Chinese currency
Renminbi
Owner does he takes those dollars and he brings them to his local bank
There are lots of banks in China
And he says here's a bunch of dollars I want Renminbi
Now the bank has dollars
But they don't
So every day this happens every day a business day
All the local banks in China and around
For 5 in the afternoon
They send a message
It's a call or email to Central Bank
People's Bank of China
And they say we've got a lot more dollars in today
And we don't want them
We want Renminbi
The Central Bank says alright that's fine give us your dollars and we'll send you some
Renminbi
So every day
The People's Bank of China gets
A huge pile of new dollars
But they have to do some
And Brad is going to tell us in a minute how many dollars it's a lot
So
People's Bank of China
Don't want to just hold on to
Dollars dollars don't earn interest they want some kind of investment
But they don't want any investment they don't want some
Speculative Tech stock or some hedge fund because there was Central Bank they need
To keep this money they need to know it's safe
The number one thing they want is US Government debt
Treasury bond
But believe it or not
However big our debt is and it is big
There aren't enough treasury bonds
Things to satisfy China's
Hunger
The People's Bank of China by the next best thing
Which it turns out is Fannie Mae
And Freddie Mac
Bond
Those bonds as it
Fan are made up of bundles of us home mortgages
Probably your mortgage Maybe
Put all together in a package and then sold as Bond
No China doesn't particularly care
That these were bonds backed by home mortgages
They just like the
These Bonds were considered really safe and that they gave some return
We love this process because what
Effectively is happening is every dollar we sent to China goes through this chain of people and then comes back to us
In the form of mortgages
Americans used
Houses home equity lines
The credit and they buy a lot more chinese-made stuff
You see how this Cycle Works
And hopefully now you see how Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac are Central
To this whole cycle
And the person who knows how all of this works better than anybody
Is Brad setser
Well
Probably did some guy in The People's Bank of China by that guy
I don't know who it is and what he
Probably wouldn't talk to us anyway so we're very happy to have Brad
I started out by asking him
How big is this whole thing how much money are we
We talkin about
I think it is reasonable to think
The Chinese vine
Over the boat's over the last 12 months
Roughly 400 billion dollars in US debt
That's
A lot
Over a year
So that's
I'm just doing the math is that for business-to-business
2 billion dollars
Sounds like a lot
It is a lot
Is ballpark
The same size as the US fiscal deficit
Is ballpark the same size
Import bill
It is a larger right now
Extended
Non-oil trade deficit
It is a phenomenal sum of money
I think of you
As the leading guy studying how much
Us
Money China has
Polite way of saying I've been obsessed
With this question for The Last 5 Years
It's the main thing you're right about you have
With a China
I reserved watch spend a lot of time trying to figure out just how much
How large is China's purchases of us Bonds were and are
Look it up somewhere
I've only the world for that simple
No you actually can't
There
Actually
Cell
The bond directly to China central.
The US government sells
A lot of bonds to
The broker-dealer community the primary dealers who buy up treasuries
Fixing big Banks
Thanks
Those big
Goldman Sachs
JP Morgan
You name it
Household names the really big
The core of the USA
Play Beautiful Audubon
And then they sell them to a bank in London
And in the bank in London sells the bond to china's central bank
The US contract
The amount of debt that it issues
And it can track the sale of bonds to foreigners
But in the first instance it thinks that it's old
The bond
A private financial institution in London
And has no way of knowing
Then
Where that bond is that
Financial institution then sells the bond to China central bank
Is that by Design
Pharmacist time zones
This
Is there a building for the guys or 4 for the guys in fishing or just on the phone to London all the time saying hey we need another
This is how someone explained it to me in
That at the end of every day
The reserve manager in
China institution great name
State administration of foreign exchange
Safe safe
The guy gets a call from other people's Bank of China says you have this today we
That we bought 2 billion dollars in the market
Anthonino's okay why have these Bonds mature expiring cuz I already hold you know 1.8 trillion
Reserves
There's a certain amount of that again
Come you only get paid on some of the loans and bonds
And sent at the end of the business day in China
The US is asleep
The natural thing to do is get on the phone and call London
So he gets on the phone and how many bonds can you sell me
I'm in that process
Goes on date
Saturday
After day
Another problem
It's hard to track it from the US Side by looking
Kathy USA.
Then you have to go to the Chinese
Chinese date
And try to figure out how much
China's foreign asset to Ghana
Well China central bank
It's actually really slow and releasing its Reserves
Most central banks release their reserves data at once a month
I only does it once a quarter
I sometimes you just publish how much
Publish on their website how much they hold
And I don't want to go into the details about how many obscure
Websites that you need to visit in order to try to get a good s
How much money does State Banks have
I don't speak Mandarin have a friend who dies and that's the only way you can
Impossibly
Find
Some reason might give you some basis for doing the estimate
What is that what you're doing all the time
Calling up a friend and begging them to go on the Mandarin language pboc's website
Yeah
So there's dozens of weird Chinese of the Chinese agricultural
The data on the foreign exchange Holdings of the state banking system
Which is just a little bit hard to find
Yeah central banks by player
But it's a hard part is you never quite know where the
Increase is going to show up
And what day does series and sometimes it changes around a little bit of guesting
Why are you so obsessed with
Why not
What what do you want to know so bad
Is it to me there's been a sort of a deep puzzle
About the global economy
For the past several years and you can think of that puzzle Dilaudid
One is that
A relatively poor country
Chinese dolls
A relatively poor country is financing a relatively rich country
You might normally think that
The money would follow the other way around
And historically that's
Countries or country's
Rich Banks fun for people exactly
If you want
Right
Citibank was
You know some guy named Frank
Who's funding Citibank
But it's also a very fast growing economy
Which is financing a slow-growing
She's also perhaps not
The way
Things normally work
I'm hearing this is an intellectual curiosity
You could do crossword puzzles instead you're trying to figure out
How much u.s. debt the Chinese government has its oh my God will my
Standard of living collapse and will the US economy fall apart its
This is really weird
I don't understand this
The initial
Motivation was also a little based on a concern
The concern was well maybe this can't go on forever
And then the more time you spend looking
And in your eye that actually written the paper saying that it couldn't go on forever
Make a public prediction that something
Is it going to go on forever
And it seems to keep going on long past
The point where you said it wouldn't
You kind of get interested in
It becomes you know the crossword puzzle that you want to solve on a daily basis
Can I go on forever
Tropicana
China cannot reduce the amount of financing that it provides the United States
Without inducing a Slowdown in the US economy
A slow down or fall and u.s. purchases of Chinese Goods
He were Chinese exports
And
I think that is a very
Important
Consideration that weighs very heavily
On Chinese policy-making
The China isn't providing all this Finance
The US
Just cuz
It loves United States
Do they want us to have to live beyond her means That explicit interest rates low in America
So that I spend more on my credit card and I buy more Chinese stuff
Now if you asked China's leaders
Do they want the us to live beyond its meaning
I think it was a no
China's building up dollars
Castle in those dollars out
I am if you were you need someone who needs to borrow and otherwise I need to be someone in the US is living beyond their means
In order to keep
Current demand for Chinese Goods going
So
In that sense
The
Indirect effect
Of China's policy
Has been
To encourage the US to live beyond its means
I think you can say that
Squats not the stated goal
You certainly the byproduct
And it's good for them
It's good for 12
Good for that other good for them are good for us there different interest inside challenge there different interest inside the US
It is good for the US Treasury
If China buys a ton of Treasury bonds and keeps interest rates low
It is bad for workers in Ohio
Producing Goods
They compete with Chinese good
If China's holding his currency down and taking market share away from USA
Same thing works in the opposite way
China is good for china's exporters
It's good for workers in the export sector
But it isn't good for China's taxpayers
Cuz I going to be taking a loss
The arguably isn't good for the workers who could be employed building schools in China
Which Heineken
Buy build more of
If it
Borrowed more money at the government level on Resident lending it to the US
And use that
Borrowing to buy
The Biltmore
School domestically
Choices
And those choices
Just have different effects on different groups within each economy
And it's very hard to set us a
One side wins the other side loses parts
Of the two economies are impacted in different ways
Tomorrow
He doesn't care about financial
I care about his own economy
Hell-bent on using whatever power he can
To destroy a mirror
Now
Is Robert Mugabe decided that
I think it's safe to assume Zimbabwe does not have
The ability to destroy the US
You know
Hugo Chavez
Could
Cuz I couldn't destroy it what what would China do let's just say they hired you said Brad can you destroy music on
Anime forest
I can't destroy the US economy
I can cause a lot of damaged
Wsvn
And I would say you have a very simple Ops
If you want to
Cause a great deal of disruption
To the US Financial system to the US Government Bond Market
And by implication to the US economy
You just have to stop buying a single new US government or u.s. agency Bond
If this stop
If the unsustainable
Is no longer sustained
China stops buying
US debt
Total collapse of capitalism
Great Depression
Late 70s kind of slowdown malaise
Early 2000s
Brief recession that doesn't hurt on that Continuum more late 70s
Then collapse of capitalism
What Great Depression
Unemployment goes up
Unemployment already going up
Unemployment goes up by a lot more
Mid america Fields pore
America has to live within its means we're used to living beyond our means
Borrow last housing prices go down
Our dollars don't buy as much
Broad it's your new cool things like iPods
Well I think it is not fewer new cool things
I get to buy
You get to buy fewer new things
And those cool new things cost a little bit more
Right that the iPod may not be manufactured in China
I mean not yours design in California manufacturer
China famous lake
Well maybe it'll be
Design in California manufactured house in Mexico and have some California and cost twice as much
How to exaggerate a little bit
So there will be
So some people will benefit
Certain kinds of jobs will grow in the
Absolute
I mean
As you said before the people who are hurt now
Will no longer be hurt in the people who win at 1
But
It's the shift between the two
Butt cheeks
Time
It takes effort
Olfactory doesn't just spring up
Magically
There's an interesting story about
He was in business week about it
An American inventor who thought they'd
Dad
Created
A better battery
For laptops and they wanted to finance new technology they want to find a manufacturer
In the US
To build
This new battery
Cuz I'm okay no shipping costs have gone way way way up
That strong a reason to have this
Inside
Hello cost
Manufacturing centers
Kind of language
Could be made
But there wasn't any contract manufacturer in the US with expert
He's building batteries
So it takes a while to build up
Skills
Where's in China
Wars in China there diamond
So it's the difficulty
Hetalia by contrast
We had specialist here in the US
Economy who could
Take a mortgage
Really complicated features
Reverse amortization
Variable
You name it
Package it with other mortgage
Just combined it into a bond
Combine that
Split that bond is different
Parts
Combine those parts into another Bond
And sell it
Optical
Work
Thin turnips replace broken
It was a set of skills which wouldn't be
Be present in China
The process
Changing the way
What an economy produces
Takes time
And it is also the effect of
Econo what have to stop running Upper Deck
And while that's probably good in a long time since
In a short time since it means that
Would be
Vial of the bus
So pretty crappy not
Absolute misery
Where were not on the lease
Total Doom and Gloom side of the spectrum
But at the same time
It is
I would much rather see it
A process
Spyware
There's a gradual reduction
In China's Reliance on the US and Europe
Ferdinand Forest Products
Much more
Reliance on
Internal forces
To keep China's economy growing
And a gradual process
Square
The US moves from a world where in order to
Keep
Running a large trade deficit
Yes keep borrowing
Marge Simpson by the government
To a world where
Trailer for the smaller
And that trade deficit can be financed by selling
Bonds
Private investor
But I want that process
Gradually
Suddenly
Cuz if it happens suddenly
Are you coming
Unpleasant
And it's not just
In Thompson's inefficient
Because
Economy can't shift
From manufacturer
Mortgages
Tell manufacturing laptop batteries
Overnight
You need to solder the process to occur on a
Slow basis of the
Investment in new factories
Other
Services
Can be sold abroad
Comes online
As the sectors that have benefited from
Strong Chinese demand for debt
All right
R r Trucking
Thank you for listening to the very first planet money podcast
We have a lot more information about Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac and China and
Everything that we
We talk about here on our website including some links to articles by Brad
That's npr.org
/ economy
Also please do send us your questions and your comments and your ideas
Future podcasts
Stories
2 global economy at npr.org
Economy at npr.org
One thing
Please do let me know how I did in this podcast
Did the did I make things clear did you understand it was
Interesting what could I have done better
I really want to make this work for
Are you
So I would
Genuinely love to know
Hopefully you'll be reasonably polite but you can give me
Real constructive criticism I hope
Global economy at npr.org NPR news
Alex heeren 2080
Those websites and their email address
They don't work anymore
But we do what your feedback just as much as back then
Npr.org money is the website
And Planet Money at npr.org is the email address
At the break
An update on what's changed since that first episode
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online press
And run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layouts
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase
Just have a website or domain
So here are a few things
That are the same since that episode 1
The US
Still run the trade deficit a trade deficit still works the same way
Have to be down somehow
Trade deficit still means an investment Surplus I'm going abroad buying US debt us bonds investing in the US
Also the same Brad setser
He still studying International economics
Still at the Council on Foreign Relations
So ask him what's changed
The thing that is changed
Is that China is
Start sweeping up
Dollars
At the end of every business day in the way it was in 2008
China is just not buying as much
US debt as it used
I need
For China's government
Step in
Mumbai dollars is largely gone away
It's gone away I think
Hurt to read
The first is that China is importing a lot more oil and a lot more
Iron and a whole host of other commodities
So what
The dollars
China earn
X1bus get sent
Well Expo
Then by us
That's good
And another one
Private
Chinese citizens now
AR
A bit less confident China
Currency China's economic course
And the more willing to hold
A portion of their wealth abroad
There isn't the same kind of imbalance in the Foreign Exchange Market
And the crisis he was worried about if China stopped buying US Government debt
Didn't exactly happen
A bigger Crisis happen
First win that week after the interview aired Lehman Brothers went bankrupt
You probably know that
Since it's our birthday to do something we don't usually do
I'm going to
Ask for birthday presents
The biggest way that you can help us out is to tell a friend to listen to the show that is how new people
Find Planet Money
You can even send them our list
10 favorite episodes for the past 2
Npr.org Planet Money 10
The numeral
Or you can rate and review it on your podcast
Right now the top review for us and apple podcast is from 2008
Network effect
How about we try to get a review from 2018 to be at
I think that if just 20 or so people go and find a recent review from 2018 and Market
Helpful
Then that will probably push it to the top
Alex goldmark thanks for listening
And thank you to the staff
Planet Money
Quiz work so hard on this podcast
Over the past 10 years
Can you just like maybe start the show play some music and welcome people
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Alex blumberg
Hannah joffe-walt Today's Show we're going to be making a t-shirt that tells the
Story of it
Fairy making
I'm just saying hello I'm later podcast celebrity Robert Smith and her Planet Money we come up with a miracle answer system
Simply
Get us your question and our team will do the Google
The reporting for you like to start off by saying hello and welcome to Planet Money can you say hello and welcome to Planet Money
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm so itchy head on Lisa child
Hi Marianne McCune boldly go where no podcast has gone
B4y hello I am Karen Duffin and I'm new
Here at Planet Money
Hello and welcome to Planet Money Karen Duffin really didn't say that to me but we really good to everybody
Milky Chance
I'm Sarah Gonzales
I'm Carlos Garcia