Support for NPR comes from investor.gov
Presenting this mess
When it comes to investing
We all have Quest
And investor.gov has answers
If you're free resource for tools
Tips and information about investing
Before you invest
Investor.gov
Douglas Bruce loves
The Constitution of the United States of America
If I could carry the little pocket version of it everywhere Side by Clarence Thomas
Define the way to work
Fusion into just about every conversation
The Constitution
Says an Article 28 and article 6 says I'm going to quote it verbatim
And that's guaranteed in Article 1
That's what special constitutional right did this the first time I met him and he even got choked up talking about
About the founding fathers
The Constitution Bruce left the most of the Bill of Rights that's the section about freedom
Speech religion right to speedy trial and Bruce likes it because to him it is the original
Limit on governor
It even begins with the words Congress shall make no law
First lives in Colorado Springs
He's a former lawyer and he owns a bunch of Real Estate
And he starts
Thinking hard about the Bill of Rights
The drafters of the Constitution were pretty smart guys but there is at least one limit on government that they didn't
They forgot to limit the right of government
To Levy taxes
On up on the people you can say you're free if the government can take away everything you have
What about your permit
Douglas Bruce decided he was going to
Fix this little oversight
He wrote up a sequel to the Constitution he called it the taxpayers Bill of Rights
Tabor for sure
And he said just like the people have a freedom of assembly right
Trial by jury
They should have a right
To vote
On their own tax
Everytime a government raises your taxes
They should have to ask your permission first
It was radick
It's incredibly difficult to plop concept
And then
The state of Colorado
Actually passed it
Planet Money I'm Robert Smith from Colorado Public Radio Rachel at herco reporters
At CPR
Then the minor and Ben Marcus I've just finished a podcast series called the taxman
It's about how a man who held no political office
Just an abscessed Outsider ended up changing the very relationship between the citizens of a state
And their government what happens when you take away the politicians main power the power to
Erase texts it ended up putting Colorado on the brink of disaster and for Douglas Bruce it cost him
Reputation and eventually
His freedom aren't very sooner or later they're going to figure out some way to put me in jail I have no.
And he was right
Support for this podcast in the following message come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing Solutions disa
Support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf
. org
Douglas Bruce sat down at his kitchen table
Colorado Springs in the 1980s
Old-fashioned typewriter sitting right in front of him
A bang out his version of this brand new law
The taxpayers
Bill
Rights
At the time Bruce had never served in government in any way
But he was something of a legal savant
Any real would look like a very simple law it said that whenever the state or local government in Colorado wants more
Our money wants to increase tax rate
It has to put the question on the ballot increased taxes for roads
Voters get to decide
You want better schools well that's
Your call.
Timber submitted this as a citizen initiative on Colorado ballot in 1988
Bruce thought it was a slam dunk people hate taxes and this measure would inevitably keep taxes down
What's not to love
They voted against it on Election night he Blaine
The voters
Basically said listen
You don't know what's good for you
And when the tax increases come
Don't bother calling me
For a reaction
I'll give you your Sound by
Right
Now
Listen carefully
I
Told
You
So
For lot of people this would have been The Bitter End
Tax revenue
Colorado
What does Bruce
Is not someone who gives
And he realized something about people in Thai
Everyone's right
But when push comes to shove
People don't want to have their parts in their libraries closed
At their core the sort of
Afraid to limit.
Afraid to limit tax
Clippers needed to sell this thing differently
I said
Well if
Change the bumper sticker
Instead of limit taxes were going to say vote on tax
Bruce essentially rebranded
The idea
Starving a government as
A fight for freedom
And that is not an exaggeration
He made his little pink index
Cards and toss them out on the
West Street
One guy in the campaign Fred Holden he still has one
What We Believe by Douglas Byrd believe in limited taxes not unlimited Got to Believe In the supreme power of the people not the special privileges
We believe in democracy not bureaucracy believe in individual
Responsibility not Collective guilt
It's time to send the politician a message
They won't forget it's time to stand up
For America
Big it felt like something the founding fathers would write
Douglas Brooks was here attacking the very Foundation of
A representative democracy
Do we trust the people we vote for to represent us
In the figure out the right amount of taxes
Which was not okay with everyone I mean Colorado's Governor at the time Roy Romer is it Democrat
He used an analogy where he called Bruce
Terrorist
Throwing a bomb into the Machinery of government I saw this man who had
A flame in his eye
I was passionate
He was over the top
Really I thought
And that's what would cause a terrorist comment has a weird sense of humor though
So this is what he did after the governor's comment
I got a business card that said
Karrueche Bruce Harris
He handed out a business card that said he was a terrorist amazing and this is
I feel like
Bruce was tapping into something that has obviously become more frequent today but was little more we're back then and now
Luckenbach
And belittle your political opponents
People eating up
People can't take her eyes off of him
He was always doing something out of the ordinary let's say like this one time he had a confrontation
With Colorado Secretary of
State Natalie Meyer
She got to approve
Tabor for the ballot so she was important here and
She had said that some of the signature is Bruce's side had collected to get it on the ballot
We're not valid
So he held a press conference in Denver just down the hall from the Secretary of State's office
The videotape
Tuesday it's amazing
The woman has obviously
Mental deficiency
You heard me
You heard me I thought you were leaving at this point Myers walking up the hallway towards Bruce and the reporters
And the TV Camera pivots to her and she is furious
Woman has obviously at what
As I was saying
Something
Dog got a little bit
I think you need to exam
Whether you're caught
That you are saying you represent is being hurt
By your verbiage
And you can't really continue this can you without being in court I feel like a secretary of state really stood up
To Douglas
Bruce here
And came off
You're looking pretty good in this competition but
But legally she didn't
Tri Nguyen it
Yeah she backed off and the signatures were approved
So come up to the election of 1992
Tabor had
It's big ideas about Freedom the little pink index
Cards and heavy attention-getting antics
Of Douglas Bruce switch
Was getting a lot of press
And then I got this
Lucky little break
From National policy
Remember it's 1992 you got the incumbent George HW Bush
Running against Bill Clinton
And an independent in the race from Texas
You got to take away Congress has right to raise taxes
Now there's a radical idea Ross Perot
Ross Perot he was a populist in a campaign that was all about the rough economy
He said voters alone should have the ability to raise taxes
Now that sounds kind of familiar in Colorado right it's the same message as Douglas Bruce
But whereas Bruce was screaming it
Restroom baby ideas seem like Down Home Logic that your Pappy might tell you on the front porch
Drinking too much
Got to take the bottle away from him for a while at least
That if I need more money
Not the owner of the country sign up
The frogs just tucking
Theoretically on the national
Colorado this was now a real option on the ballot
And protocol
A lot of ads nationally
And his words were echoing in voters ears
As they went to
On Election Day the pools
For Tabor were really tight
Neither side was sure what would happen
Douglas Bruce got to the party in downtown Denver at the Embassy Suites around 8:30
So when I got there
People started
Aquatic
And I haven't heard the
Results of the radio and they said you know
It's now
We're at 49%
Rachel is the first time I
Her Douglas Bruce
Express emotion
Yeah I mean he doesn't have kids he doesn't have a family he's not married like this is his baby
Sm81 on the more conservative parts
State added their results
And it was clear
Tabor
What the taxpayers Bill of Rights
Was not law in Colorado
And Douglas Bruce
Still remembers the first words of his victory speech
The Liars lost
The wires lost
The people
People
Kroger
We asked him what it felt like
Vindication
It was a
If I Die Tomorrow
We can't take it away from
I
Am I crazy
I'm crazy about Micah
I'm crazy enough to believe
All those things we were told
School
About the
Consent of the governed
We the People
People in this hotel Ballroom are rat
All eyes on Douglas Bruce
We have taken away their crowbar
And for once
It is the politician
You got nails
All the sudden every elected official in Colorado
Had to live by Bruce
Just rules
The taxpayers Bill of Rights
Was now part of the state
Despite politicians worst fears
The sky did not fall
The economy boomed during the Clinton years
And during good years more tax money Flows In without ever having to raise taxes
Bruce's law said that some of it had to be sent back to
Like the state of Colorado actually had to send refund checks
Everyone in the state
Even the TV reporters at the time seemed
How would you like
$54
What would you do with it
Buy some books
In park
Because Colorado's economy is booming
The state treasury is overflowing with money
You are mine
And it's coming back
Dream right everything seems sweet with the taxpayers Bill of Rights
Until April 14th 2018 Black Friday there
Dotcom Bubble Burst
Everything came crashing down not just in Colorado but across the country
It was the worst
Single-day Point loss ever for both exchanges Colorado
Tax revenues plug
And the state was about to discover how the taxpayers Bill of Rights was really designed to work
After the break
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Fidelity Investment
As a Fidelity wealth management client you get a dedicated advisor to help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes and make
Clear recommendations
It's for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
Supposed to
Tax revenues first state
Go up and down depending on the economy
What brings in more money and
Spend it
During recession the state brings in less
Shmoney and
Cut services
Goes up and down
Texas Bill of Rights
Is a sort of
One way
In Colorado if tax revenues go down one year
That becomes a new Baseline for the state
When the recession is over
And more money starts to come into Colorado
State is not allowed
Keep it
Close government shrunk during the recession
And now it was
Locked
In the shrunken
State
Douglas Bruce
I thought of everything
He said it was all by Design
There are no unintended
None
Zip zero
I knew what I was doing and
And I don't regret anything it's in there I wish I could have put in more but I had to make it calculated decision is but
What we get 51% of the vote
Colorado can always ask voters
Increase
But even that has been anticipated by Douglas Bruce you couldn't
Just go to voters and say
Hey everyone we really need
No
You actually
Start the ballot measure
With these precise words
Charles taxes
Be increased by
X millions of dollars
Or billions
I mean Douglas Bruce knew that that kind of language does not encourage pee
People to vote Yes
After the 2001 recession Colorado was
Chris Castilian was working in the Colorado governor's office and he says they were looking at having to Splash higher education
And health
Our budget director of the time Houston
How is
Command and say
You know we're at the point of basically kicking old people out of nursing homes and so what do you want to do in order for us to meet the
Requirements
What taper is imposing on
So they decided they had to change Tabor the taxpayers Bill of Rights
They had to go back to voters who
Passed it
And essentially
Beg for them to loosen some of the rules
Douglas Bruce of course was like wait wait wait a minute you can't just go and find some
Work around 4
Freedom
Colorado voters disagreed
They voted to loosen some of the restrictions that the taxpayers Bill of Rights
I put in
It was doing a fact but the state wouldn't have to kick old people out of nursing homes
Douglas Bruce
Was Furious he had all these ideas for new anti-tax measures
By this time people are starting to Tire of.
I was
Radioactive in certain circles young people say
Oh I hate Doug Bruce I love taper but I hate the group
Buster's had one
Last plan
He got himself temporarily appointed to a seat in the Colorado State ledge
He was going to take this anti-tax fight
All the way to the state capitol
And inside
Bruce is not a man who's built for politics
On one of his first days in office at the state capitol during the morning prayer
A bunch of photographers were gathered around him taking pictures like they're kneeling at a
And Bruce
Pushes one of them with his foot like he knocked the camera out of his hands
We're still maintains it was more of a nudge than a
Kik
Obviously this did not go over well just a sideshow he may be a freakshow self-righteous and
Arrogant the Colorado house called a vote to censure him
On the house floor
Douglas first give this rambling defense of himself
From 1939
It's called Mr Smith Goes to Washington
I think many of you have seen it
Even the other Republicans didn't buy it
Representing Bruce
You're not Jimmy Stewart
This is not a 1939 movie
This is today
Your actions were wrong
The center vote was 62
21 Couch Street became the first and so far only member of the state legislature to be censured
Something he said to this day that he is not embarrassed about
100 +
40 years
Yes
Really
Of course
I I considered it's a badge of honor because these people are so saturated with corrupt
They would do that both parties
Parties Republicans and Democrats
And eventually the Republicans ditched him they pick somebody else in the next primary
And like that
He was out of the legislature
Things got worse for
Remember that pocket Constitution that he always carries with him
Says I'm going to quote it verbatim
And that's guaranteed an article
One set up a charity
To among other things
Make sure the high school seniors
Had their very own tiny pocket-sized editions of the Constitution that they could carry with them to class
What is the state of Colorado
Bruce was using this charity
To avoid paint
In 2011
Colorado charge
The most famous
Tax cutter in State history
With tax
I ridiculed the government Siri calling it
Felony philanthropy
I still got forty thousand copies of pocket constitutions in my garage
Better
Interrupted in
Distributing
One Friday afternoon Bruce went to the post office in his hometown Colorado Springs
As he was leaving officers came up
And arrested him
Bruce talk to the reporter the courthouse on the David
But you could also do people like you with your activism there is nobody like
What kind of a question is that
This probably won't surprise you but Douglas Bruce
Used his trial to sort of
Rail against
The system to say everyone is out to get
But it backfire
The jury convicted.
Was Bruce Douglas Bruce ended up in the Delta Correctional Center in western Colorado
State Prison
Oprah's is locked up the state continue to try to chip away at the tok
Paris Bill of Rights
There's even a name for this
Call D bruising
One of the things that the state did was to raise
Fees instead of taxes
You don't need a vote to raise
Safi undertale
But the taxpayers Bill of Rights is still in effect
And it has
Real Empire
Funding for Colorado schools is among the lowest in the country despite a booming economy here
And Colorado has some of the worst roads in the country
In July 2016
Douglas Bruce wenzhou
The parole board and asked to be let out of
Except responsibility for all my actions
I deeply regret them
It will never happen and accept responsibility for all my actions
It will never happen again
Those are true statement
That doesn't mean that I did anything wrong
I regret the fact that they sent me to prison
Any
Intelligent person would regret that
Miss Abruzzo
I read your statement I've heard your statements
I've reviewed your file
You're doing well
Feel very good about the fact that we will never see you again
That concludes is here and good luck to you sir
Douglas Bruce went back to his home in Colorado Springs
He doesn't show up at the state capitol much anymore he doesn't have any big tax limit measures but
He does filing lawsuit
Against
Local governments in particular that
He thinks are violating the
Paris Bill of Rights he still fighting
To defend this law
In fact the voters of Colorado
They changed the rules
Sprint putting initiatives on the ballot they make sure that something big like a taxpayers Bill of Rights
Could never again be passed
Colorado
Dennis Bruce hasn't totally gone away though I mean you can still see him at his home town city council hearings when are
Never anything to do with taper comes up
Regular meeting
He's that guy at city council meeting
Waiting to speak two rows of chairs that are mostly empty
I've lived here for over 30 years
And what this council did with one dissenting vote
Last April 20th
Was probably the most flagrant
Violation of law that I've seen in my 30 years here and that's
Saying something
A flagrant violation of his law
Haber the taxpayers Bill of Rights
He handed out copies of it to every council member
In size 32 font
Let us know what you thought of
Today's show you can email is Planet Money at npr.org or you can find us on Facebook
In Twitter
Special Lake City to Rachel's Co reporters at Colorado Public Radio
Nathaniel minor
And Ben Marcus
If you download their podcast series called the taxman you can hear
More Amazing Stories
Of Douglas Bruce
And of the people who tried to stop and there's some great
Tails and there we didn't get a chance
Put up the show 18 Aaron Lewis
For his mixing and His Brilliant original music in the taxman series
The plant movie version was produced by Nick Fountain our senior producer is Alex goldmark and our editors bright
Now that you're finished
Listening
To our show and going to listen to the Pac-Man from Colorado Public Radio
May we suggest
The indicator in fact
They're doing a show today on that little Google selfie thing that compares your face to famous works of
Arch and why some states
Abandon
That's the indicator you can find it on NPR one or wherever you get your
I'm Robert Smith and I'm Rachel Estabrook thanks for listening