Hey just a quick note this episode originally aired in 2015
If you find yourself drug around Upstate New York you should stop by the farm of Rick
Minkus he grows
One hell of a night
If you're on the farm you can pull one
Write out the ground and take a bite
I mean I'm just going for it
I mean it's very oniony
That's what a fresh onion
For the record we made Keith do that as kind of Planet Money
No thanks thanks for that
Rick is one of the biggest onion farmers in Upstate New York
Stacy gross
End of millions of onions each year
Digress the onions but he is also a business
What is onions are harvested
They're just a commodity
He needs to find a market
And right now
The market for onion says
It's $9
450 lb bag
$9 is not great but $9 okay we're making money at $9 will start selling but we're not going to go
Crazy so you know when we have bills to pay I mean I have notes doing
I might have to get some cash flow
This is how it has always been
Performers
They're at the mercy of the weather and the soil and
Are plants during the growing season
And then after they harvest the crop
We're at the mercy of financial Market
The by the rug
Except for this one time
Another farmer from upstate New York broke all the rules and made himself the master of onions
And the master of markets
He was known as The Onion king of Pine Island
His farm is a little ways down the road from here
And to this day around these parts you don't want to bring up his name
Vince kasuga
Have you ever heard of a guy called Vincent kosuga
Skip
Does he have some reputation in this part of the world
Yay
He's had a reputation that you don't do business with him
Is it 1 Point
Vince kasuga held the entire onion World hostage
You made a fortune doing LOL
And I'm Keith Romer today on the show we will tell you just what it took for Vince kasuga to become the onion King
And why is Neighbours still resent it
A story about a scheme that got so out of hand eventually the Chicago River load not just with lock
America's Army
So many onions
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence
Sand run you're busy
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off
Off your first purchase of a website or domain
Vince kasuga started out as an onion farmer back in the 1930s
And he was pretty successful at
But onion farming was never quite enough RAM
Yeah after you finished working on his own crops he like to make
Big bats on other
People crops
He would pour His onion money
It was called the
Futures Trading
Basically the place where you can make a bat
That it's going to be a great year for a week
Or soybeans I swear to God are going to take a beating
He was just addicted to Trading
He would trade anything I mean know if it moves he would trade it I think he liked the action and I think he liked being right
This is Harvey path
He's a Commodities Trader in Chicago and the nephew of Vince kasuga
Performance Futures markets are way of taking some of the risk
Out of their business
Mybatis spring
Right you need money to buy seed
Attract
You know you can have a million pounds of onions to sell in 6
Six months in the fall
But you need the money now
So you agree to lock in a price
My dog's back
UFC sold contract to deliver the onion
In the future but you get the money now
Not only does this let Farmers plan their finances
It also let them sleep soundly.
If in the fall the price goes down to $6 a bag
Who cares they're locked in a $9
But you can trade Futures even if you're not
A farmer there's a whole Exchange in Chicago with
If you just know in your heart
The price of onions is going to go up
You can buy a future country
The price is low
You can talk when the price is high
You can make a fortune
Ford Blues one
Like Vince kasuga did early on
When he first started out
He was trading wheat
And got annihilated
I guess he had a mortgage part of his farm and
He swore on the Bible to my aunt that he would never trade
Wheat Futures again
But you notice he just told his wife
Wheat
It wasn't long before Vince must have realized
What do I know about wheat anyway
I'm an onion farmer
I know everything there is to know about onions
Victim self-hate
I know about onions I know about Futures Trading what if I use that knowledge
Pull off
The greatest onion tray that the world has ever seen his idea is kind of the fantasy of all Commodities trade
In 1955 he decides that he is going to
Corner The Onion
Corner
The mark
This is something you mainly hear about
In movies when you need some sort of motivation for the evil guy
You know I just cornered the market in Gold mist
List of Bond now you will do my bidding
When it's not in the movies this is really hard to do
Cornering the onion Market means that Vince kasuga needs to get his hands on virtually
All of the onions in America
And
Guess they figure out where to put them
So is evil plan starts in New York
With a little construction project
Well he was building
Was a big shed of corrugated aluminum I mean huge and he had a conveyor near neighbor
Filling it with onions
So he was stockpiling all the onions from his from his farm
And not just doing it on his own Farm
All Around The Country Vintner
Starts buying of onions
Millions of
He was doing this in New York
I understand he was doing it in Michigan taxes
And I think he had a partner to out in California so we're doing this
Throughout the United States
Warehouses
Is everywhere filling up with America
Is onions
There's a lot of onions
I could buy that
Sylveon tattoo do all of this completely in secret
Because if he doesn't and the market finds out what he's up to the price will go
Up and up and up before you
The chance to buy all the
And after start stockpiling onions that are already on it
Looks Francisco
What about those onions
That are growing right now and this
Is where's expertise as a traitor comes in
Because he is able
Dubai futuristic
Essentially saying to Farmers
As soon as I come out of the ground
I want to I want to buy
So Vince and his business partner Sam Siegel
Produce distributors
Is a traitor to they start buying up all of the available Futures contracts on onion
It is amazing by the time fall of 1955 rolls around
Vince kasuga
Has wrapped up the entire
Tire Mart
So you want all the lawns in the Futures Market
Any on wall unions in the United States basically
He cornered the market
He did it
And here's why cornering a market is such a big deal
Vince kasuga
Could set the price for onions
Whatever he wants
People have to pay
Otherwise
No onions on your burger
Escallion ring
So of course
Vince want the price to go up
He keeps the onions off the market
He creates an onion shortage
And then when the price is high enough
December 1955
Vince makes his move
Vincent Sam called a bunch of onion big
Growers Distributors ultimate meeting in Chicago
They say fellas
This can go one of two ways
You can buy a bunch
Are onions
We've got stored up at
The price that we demand
Or
We can just dump all these onions on the market all at once
We can destroy the price of onions for the rest of the year
It's your call
They don't really have a choice
They are in the onion business and Vince is threatening to blow the whole thing up
In the end they agreed to buy almost 9 million pounds
Onion
Is amazing and Ferb
Pretty much anyone who's ever courted a market this is as far as it goes
He bought all the onions low he drove the price up
And when it came time to sell he made a killing
Vince has stopped
Here
He would have been an absolute Legend
And maybe even a hero to his neighbors
The man who made onions worth a fortune
Kasuga
Did not stop there
He didn't just want to make a killing
He sees that he can make
Two killings
He has such a powerful hold on America
Is onion Supply
But there is this
Second opportunity to make
Money it's just
Waiting for him if he plays it right
If you control all of America shenyang
You can make the price go up when she did
But you can also make the price go down
Any thinks about this
And there is a way in the
Futures Market
But you can basically short tomorrow
You can make a big
That the price will go down and once again
Vince kasuga can make the price go down
So he starts to quietly make bets
Against the price of a
That the price will go down
Any bakeries that day after day after day and when March hits
Vince kasuga Springs
His second
Trap
He stabbed his fellow farmers in the back
Flood the market with onion
I will wait for the markets
We're not meaning this in this theoretical inside markets kind of way no he physically take
His onion
From his secret warehouses
He loads them up
And he basically says to all the other traders in Chicago
Surprise
What they didn't count on was him delivering the onions
To The Exchange
But wait a minute this
Does it mean there are
Physical
Trucks filled with onions driving into downtown Chicago
Correct
No
Yep
No where would you put them
I'll get to that
Trucks
Train cars
Vince casuga onions
Coming into Chicago and of course the onion Market goes Haywire
Normally if you are Futures Trader and because of your contract you get delivered a bunch of onions
You just sell them on to someone who wants them
Produce distribute
That's the way the market normally were
All these onions coming into Chicago
The price Falls
Floor onions are basically
Be worth with no one wants to get stuck
Bazookas onions
You can imagine all those traitors walking to work
The streets of Chicago every morning
Seeing these huge bags of onions piled on every loading dock
The train yards filled with onions
Everywhere
Onions
The mesh bag that you put 50 lb bag of onions in
The bag alone empty cost $0.20
A 50lb bag
Of onions they went to 10 cents a bag
As long as there been Futures Trading in onions
No one had ever seen a price that low
You couldn't sell it
You could not give them away
So what do you do with your onions you did they called orphanages they called Hospital schools whatever
They try to get rid of as many onions as I could and the rest of them they dumped in the Chicago River
And of course there was one man who had made a huge financial bat
The price of onions would drop to nothing
And that man was Ben kasuka
He made a fortune
Made 8 and 1/2 million dollars
It's a lot of money 1955
A lot of money now
And a lot of people took a beating on Svenska
Suga's onion
Other Commodities Traders
Farmers
Put Canada being able to sell their onions for a profit now we're growing
People went bankrupt because of kasuga
There were stories of suicide
Yeah I didn't really
Upset and in Michigan they affect called their congressman
A gentleman by the name of
Gerald Ford
President and they said
We have got to stop this craziness with the onion futures
What size shirt
He gets Congress to hold hearings
Talk to economist
The onion farmers
I talked to Uncle Vince
Bazookas lawyer tell them listen
No matter what you do
Do not perjure yourself
Tupac lie to Congress
He was on the stand
Raises hand and said your name is consumer he said yes
You said that you live in Pine Island New York yes you have a farm near yes
They should vents be understanding on 97% of the onions in the United States
He said that's incorrect
IO 98%
He corrected them so didn't perjure himself
That's what I can guessing was in his mind
But after all this outrage it was hard to really pin down the
Crime Vincent committed there laws against Market manipulation but they were super vague and hard to enforce and biscuits
He said if it's against the law to make money in the United States and I'm guilty of something
But of course it is not
How to make money
Indian kasuga had his training license suspended for 10 months and he had to pay a small fine
Like tens of thousands of dollars out of the eight and a half million he made on the trade
Now at this point Congress
Could have passed the law reforming parts of the onion trading world
Perhaps limiting the amount of the nation's onions that one man
Could own but onion farmers were pissed
Are always complained about Spectre
City Slickers using the Futures Market
How to get rich and ruin the little guy
And now they had proof that speculators
Could destroy an entire Market
Congress listen to the
The farmers and they chose the nuclear option
Coming up after the break
This message comes from NPR
Capital One
Is reimagining Bank
I offering account
With no fees or minimum
I can be open from anywhere in
5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Na
In 1958 Dwight Eisenhower signed
The onion Futures Act
Which makes it illegal
To trade onion futures
In America
And to this day to this date you cannot
Trade Futures in onions and it's the only Agricultural Product that's
Specifically outlawed light
Like that's the only one
You can trade in soybeans
Wheat corn no problem but onions
Forget it
It's so farmers theoretically should live happily ever after
No speculators to mess around their mark
Except for one thing
Not much
Change the Union Market
The price of onions with steel unexpectedly shootout
Crash down without warning
Just like it always did
Even without Vince kasuga onion farmer still face the prospect
I'm making a bunch of money one year
And losing it all the next
And without Futures there's this slow drip drip
Drip out of everybody's pockets
If a farmer can't sell is onions ahead of time
Just to pay the store.
Because Farmers money
It cost you money when you're buying onions
Maybe just a few sent an onion but it's money that Congress entry told us that we
Have to wait
Vince kasuga went back to farm
Then after his suspension was up after 10 months
He started trade Futures again
Just another Market
He traded potatoes
Pork belly
His nephew Harvey worked alongside him and said that he
He would tell
This onion story
And other Traders would just
Marvel at what are you called
Because you can't do that
You could not Corner the onion Market
Not because of what Congress
Not because of the law
But because there's so much more information in the market
Yeah she tried to buy up a ton of
Corn or soybeans first of all
Everyone would know you're out there by and secondly people would see you building the warehouse
We have just so much more information about the
The Futures Market you would see someone like Vince casuga coming a mile away
His title as the onion King
Is going to be safe for a long long time
We always love to hear what you
How to get a shower
You should email it
Planet Money NPR. Org
Rihanna spratlin money
Special thanks today to Andrew Gerda another onion farmer we spoke to
Did you try one of his
Woop woop woop
To Scott Irwin at the University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign and also to Emily Lambert the author of the book The Future
Which was a great help in putting together the show
The show today was produced by Jessie J
Robert Smith
And I'm Keith Romer
Thanks for listening