Support for NPR and the following message come from service now making the world of work
Work better for people
Their cloud-based platform and solutions deliver digital workflows that create great experiences and
Unlock productivity for your whole company
More at servicenow.com
We had this great idea for an episode
A few months back
Super clever way to deal with
This problem
Are corporate bosses that NPR decided that they were going to
Rehab R-Spec
Wreck everything down take everything out pull up the carpet it was extremely well
Oh no
Everything's gone to chairs the death
For a week
The Planet Money Team rented
The temporary office at a wework
This is one of those co-working spaces that feel like a
A cross between a boutique hotel
And a student center to call it
Is this
Lounge Funk playing everywhere
Not inside the offices but in all the common
IHeartRadio
Oh but there was free beer
Deck Party Jackson Bagel Time and we thought we might do an entire show on we work and the
I need to experience there
But then
Esquire magazine came out with their article
Ennui work
Entitled
And I'm so jealous of this title
Sriracha is for closers
It was essentially the same story that we wanted to tell about the people who inhabit this world of wework
But if I'm being honest with myself
It was better
Just listen to this line from the stories writer Eric konigsberg
What might Willy Loman
Who ventured door-to-door with nothing but a smile and a
Shoe shine
Have made if we works by an incubator program
With its build your own hash brown bar
Thank God it's Monday
Honey come on
As a journalist what do you supposed to do
When somebody kicks your butt like
Well hero Planet Money he writes up a valentine
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Robert Smith
K Michelle we bring you our annual Valentine's Day Ever
A yearly tradition where we express our love
And yes our jealousy
For the things that we wish we had thought of
Well if members the Planet Money Team come on and share their favorite Twitter account
TV shows articles
And even the Blissful sounds of nature
Support for this podcast and the following message come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities to help ensure a brighter future for America's Choice
Children more information is available at aecf. Org
The other day we're having our regular staff meeting
Here at Planet Money and
Noel King who is
Who's nobody pretty quiet
Halo out there Roberts
Noel was on
Fire
Talking about this article
That that you had read that you just love that I said like something just come on in here and just
Tell us about it for a valentine
Yeah it's called
Promethea Unbound and it was in the atavist magazine it was written by a man named Mike Mariani
I'mma tell you what I love about the story I'm going to keep it really short
It starts out in a way that you've seen a hundred other new story start out right it's this single mother
She's very poor she's living out of a van with her five-year-old daughter
They have no money they're sleeping in parking lots are washing their hair and Fountains at night
And the mom is trying to not let on to her five-year-old that this is not a normal way to live right this is like
Derek Durand Dire Straits
She's keeping her entertained for the kids not enrolled in school but she takes her to the park she takes her you don't like little educational things
And very early on the store you weren't at the mom is planning the surprise trip for her 5
You're old and she's pregnant
Just like driving the van and she don't know where that goes yeah yeah
And it turns out that they are driving to Stanford University
And then you learn that they're driving to Stanford University
Linear
Accelerator
Which is a top
Science lab and you're confused now cuz you're homeless mom and five-year-old daughter what is going on here
And in their there they're at Stanford to take
A tour of the linear accelerator
Any luck with your kids program know that or is it
College professor is a college student in people who really interested in like 5th
And into the finished
And the professor was leaving it says does anyone have any questions
The five-year-old girl raises her hand and she says
Just like really seriously adult
Question about particles colliding in why the accelerator doesn't overstay for like what is going on in the story
And then it unspools
This little girl this five-year-old girl is a genius
No I don't want to spoil the end of the story
But I wanted to ask you as someone who is
A reporter and tell stories for live
What is it about the structure of the story
Grabbed you
The basically makes you want to steal it for a future future podcast
Person who represents
Who's the Everyman who represents everybody
Especially
That's right what you have in this case is a character who is so
Singular
Almost seems like she must be made up she must be Fiction it's like
You're reading this story and you feel like you're reading a novel
Because the character
Is so far from a cut out
She is
So extraordinary
End
And I think if you can write a 39 page magazine article
It reads like a novel
Mike Mariani hatts off
The name of the story is Prometheus Unbound and you can find it at the enema status. Com
Thank you Robert
One of our newest
Reporters here Julia Simon has a secret
Nerdy
Passion
That's true reveal what it is
My Valentine goes out
To Samir madani
This guy who spends every night
Tweeting
Where oil tankers are around the world
Like tweeting out
The location of
Oil tank
It's like Trainspotting for oil tank
Exactly
He's made this group of people all around the world
Who are tweeting with
And they're called
The organization of oil trading tweeters
This is not an official organ
It is not an official organization it is modeled after an official organization OPEC
The organization of the
Petroleum exporting
But this hashtag in this group
Has transformed the world of oil
We should say that you have
Extensive experience
In in doing stories about oil so it's not just a random
Impressed it's not totally random but
I also just love the high seas
And they're Nazis they're the high seas
Why is that such a weird thing
I'm going to look at the hashtag OOTD
Xian Twitter
This is real thing
It is
I want the first one that comes up is
Standoff in the high seas as Cyprus says
Turkey block
Gas
Drillship
Hashtag
Yep this is the type of drama yeah
The sky Samira madani
Why does he do this is John know this isn't his job he's a technology executive
And every night he goes online and this is his entertainment
Uses satellites and Report
And he looks at anchors all around the world
And he sees some pretty crazy stuff
Shenanigans
Odyssey
Arrange things so Francis
Suntransfers
What happened in the clandestine manner do switch off their AIS trans
Finder
And a transfers oil bye-bye hoses
They're transferring oil using hoses from one ship to another
Yeah Odyssey
I mean you're watching the stuff on folding it's so excited
You really don't need Netflix
Senior Life
They should be paying me to watch this stuff
So we just did our planet money space Series where we talked to a lot of people who use
Satellite various other spy means to essentially do the same thing
Track ships around the world
Any ideas there are Commodities traders who can
Make a lot of money if they figure out that
There is a too much oil in this place and not enough oil in that place and there's oil headed between them
So I understand the green part of
I don't understand why would you just do this
For free
Yeah I mean
She just
He's an oil nerd
There are a lot of other oil nerds all around the world
They're sitting there they're totally lonely
Until summer
Comes around with this hashtag now they can talk to each other and share this information
The club it's a club
And in this club sometimes pirate show up
What about to go crazy
Thank you Julia thank you Robert
With us now
Is the editor
A Planet Money Bryant or Steph
We should say before you give your Valentine
Where did you grow up
I grew up in New York City on the Upper East Side
Yes you are city boy through and through
Yes
And your Valentine goes to
Farm Show magazine
Okay
The describe the thing to me because you have this little tiny tiny magazine
What the size of the palm of your hand called Farm Show magazine
So Farm Show magazine is printed on newsprint as you can smell
And farm show magazine Paisley rounds up tips and tricks from what they call farmshop Wizards
Or Farmers all over the country and they
Basically just right in and tell people what they've done often it's projects they spent months working on and off on that solving problems that bother
All kinds of farmers
So can you give me an example
Engine powered gopher killing machines
Okay
Mini electric fence keeps mice out of stored machines
Wait to tiny little electric fence there. You can see the other tiny little electric fence it runs around the perimeter
Okay
Texas ranch makes money raising butterflies
And my new favorite
Elevated bus makes great deer stand
No deer stand
For those of you who live in a city is
A place where you shoot deer
When you're hunting deer you
Basically waiting for them to show up and it can take a long time and a lot of people do it
On a little ladder in a tree
But this farmer has decided to do it in a school bus
Which he is mounted as you can see here
On a 28-foot high gas tank
Samantha the yellow school bus
Essentially up in the air what does it look like
10 20 feet up it looks like a flying school bus
Which is basically is
Eddie Murphy's baby inside
There's a little table in a little place we can sleep in a setting like a microwave oven so sure
Why you can never ever ever where you live now in Suburban Connecticut use any of these
Why do you read this
I sit at my desk all day
And I dream of
Solving
Problems that don't require a keyboard
And this magazine is just filled with people
Usually who are probably living
Living pretty far from one another who want to communicate with each other who actually have solved problems
And there probably is someone else out there
Wondering how exactly to get his school bus up on a 28-foot gas tank
Any instructions are inside
And I just want to be a part of that world even if it's only watching
Farm Show magazine
Out of Lakeville Minnesota
Make bread
Hello
I bring you my valentine
Stacey Vanek Smith visiting from the indicator how are you doing
So my Valentine is to a
Television show
Show that I
Call the Victoria is about Queen Victoria it is
Part of Master
Theater
Anyway though it's like I watched the show.
You don't get away from work it's a sort of
Lovely Escapist Robbins very well.
Incidentally
But I was watching it the other day and
There's there was this hole
Slotline
And
It reminded me of work so much I could not believe
The scene takes place in British Parliament
British Asian
When firming comes again
Find a polishing the toilet
The Corn Laws I can't believe it they're talking about one of the sort of
Fundamental historical moments in free
Yes exactly the Corn Laws were tariffs that were put in place to protect the threat of landowner Gentry
Reclass and they
Basically made it impossible
Really really really expense
Import grain from other
Which made food very expensive in UK were talking 18
Yes and this became a huge problem during the Irish
Potato famine
The Irish potato crops very famously failed
The Irish had
Nothing to eat
People were starving in record numbers it was horrible
Meanwhile these laws meant that importing
Green to send to the Irish people to save them from starving was almost
And so the prime minister at the
The time is man's Sir Robert
Give this big impassioned plea about
Repealing the Corn Laws essentially moving
Words
Free Trade Street for the workers of this country who may not have votes but
You deserve no molestes to buy untaxed food fix the speaker
I commend this bill to the house
Can we talk about free trade Planet Money all the time this is a big topic met in the presidential election
Tariffs free trade all this
Stop it
It was amazing to just
Watch it and see it in all of its drama they should
Starving Irish
Peasants
Initial people yelling at each other in Parliament and
The royal couple got in a little
Fight about the Corn Laws and it was just
Really wonderful to see
Free trades with dramatized in this really
Amazing way with such
Beautiful costumes and
End of the passions that it allows for instance I mean I hope this isn't a spoiler
There is this man who tried to assassinate Sir Robert peel right after the vote
Passes to repeal the Corn Laws
Because he's a landowner nice or he's going to lose his livelihood now that
Green will be able to be imported from
Answer the bigger spoiler alert that you can't get rid of the Corn Laws
Embraces what I David Ricardo the great Economist called comparative advantage which is that countries
Should do what they are good at which
At the time was
Making textiles and such
And it all
At least
As far as grade was concerned
Workout for the
Exact
Anyway it is
A grade
So I don't know if I should recommend it cuz
You don't have to later. Dramas with costumes but if you would like. Dramas with fussy costumes and like furtive glance
Oh my God
Victoria
Stacey Vanek Smith thank you anytime
After the break now that the voices of the Planet Money Team or echoing in your ears
We have a solution for how to get them out
Support also comes from fidelity
As a Fidelity Wealth Management
You get a dedicated advisor
To help grow and protect your wealth find ways to minimize the impact
Taxes and make clear recommendations for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
I make my valentine
Shorty goes out to the video.
Here
At NPR yes
NPR has
A video team and they've been spending the last 6 months working
Annie's amazing short videos based
On
Episodes
Of Planet Money
They're hilarious
The first one is about the chicken tax is how frozen chicken
Change the market for pickup trucks around the world
And you can find these videos at
Npr.org
Planet Money shorts
And finally one of our reporters Katie Malone
Did not suggest
A valentine
Although I noticed that he is always sitting in the corner
Listening to some
Yeah
I'm trying to block out the sound of all of my call
What do you listening
Before I tell you what I'm listening to I mean I think it's important for
For listeners to know that
The NPR New York office recently underwent some
You're already
Open concept
We became more open concept Wall came down more people are now in the space and say what you want to say
Robert Smith UF
Okay it's very Charming it's
The Planet Money staff as a whole and I'm part of this is
Is a we are excitable
Often a little bit loud and so in the open space sometimes it can be a little over
That would mean that you
For those of you listening
Here's an example of what are office
Town of Canton Ohio
There are no.
Stream
But that's because Define
The mammal with four legs a little beers
The moment the dog
Workwell Robert is saying what whatever that
If it's too hard to explain but it is not true about Canton
Let's move on
Okay
So
When you see me listening off in my corner with my headphones on I'm trying to concentrate
And
This is
What am I listening to
Is that water
Sound of relaxation
This is what you're listening to when I'm in my corner
With my headphones on
I'm listening to loons man
Aren't you just there aren't you like
Staring through Cattails looking out on a lake somewhere in the middle of Ontario
None of this is this is what I have on my phone I have
At least 3 hours worth of loon sounds
Two different albums worth
I tried to find it binaural so if any listeners have any suggestions for binaural loon sounds I'm open to that
Just let this one play at
And I'm just super super
So right now so
70 thoughts on the show email us or don't
I mean for Planet Money on NPR. Org G1 Facebook Twitter
Yeah she was pretty Today Show is produced today by Nick fountain
ARS
Senior producer in
Alex goldmark
He said
Idaho
Fighter stats
Indicator
Yeah this is other thing we do
It's called the indicator by Planet Money
Set timer no I'm sorry
The indicator
From Planet Money
Of Planet Money
You need something more fast-paced
Quicker
Baltimore md news
I'm coming alone
Robert Smith Young
Nice listening