Getting into Cody's car there is just a
Here is just a pistol hanging out
It was just a pistol hanging out in the passenger seat so I am going to
I'm just going to be careful
I'm going to hang on to this thing until he gets back in the car and says that it is not loaded
I'm holding it away from me
The gun belongs to Cody Wilson
Independence vs
Cody is either one of the most
Dangerous people in the world
Or he's a twenty-nine-year-old punk pulling a prank
Or he's a hero of the First Amendment
What's what's the status of the puppy here
This gun shoots the rotors
Being a danger to either one of us
What is a gun
Cody is hard to pin down
What I do know is that he doesn't like
Regulations or government or the state
She does like that
You don't remind this is a work of art
I mean I saw the way you held that you held it like
Well I quit a measure discussed but
No not discuss my dad always said hold it away from you so you don't shoot your damn self
You know what they're enough
Cody and I are going to Best of the West which is a shooting range outside of Austin Texas
We're running late in the sun's getting lower until we pull it in a rush
They're going to close in like a
Going to say something
So he goes to check us in and he gets our tactical baby book
And then he gives me orange ear plugs
Kodi does not look dangerous
He has dark hair and dark eyes and little dimple in his chin Babyface
He also makes eye contact like maybe someone has spoken to him about the importance of making eye contact
So anyway he lays the guns out on the table and these are mostly guns that he has made
This is a Glock
Just as an M1911 single stack 45
This is a
Standard military configured
Colt AR-15
If you know guns you know the AR-15
Teen and if you don't know guns this is the one you've seen a bunch on TV
AR-15 rifles and AR style rifles were used at the movie theater shooting in Colorado
And the concert shooting in Las Vegas
And others
Are you going to let me shoot the AR-15 or no
Absolutely
If you want to show you can shoot
I don't have any particular love for guns
As odds
I don't have any particular revulsion for them either unless they're used to kill or to hurt
My father owns guns
And I don't know if I want to shoot that AR
But at the same time I don't want Cody to think that I'm
Scared to shoot
Cell
You're leaning back if it just kind of get that before and come forward into it a bit
Find SQL
Well
Yeah I like that I like that put you on fire and you want it if you want it with your own thumb you can play
Just pull it down
You can fire
At will
Hells Bells
After only like three
Three rounds with a naturally
Maybe I'm just one of those people
Or do you think everyone's just one
I have a sneaking suspicion we're all one of those p
Yeah
Okay
Cody Wilson is a gun make
But he's never sold a gun and he's never killed anyone and as far as he knows
None of the countries made I've ever killed anyone so why do people think Cody Wilson is so dangerous
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Noel King and I'm Elizabeth collapse people think Cody Wilson
Is dangerous because he makes guns but because he's made a way for anyone to make their own
I mean that proves that he's made some start need to move from person to person in a store
Instead they're packed together using information that's free and easy to find on the internet
Guns that can go viral and potentially make gun control impossible
Support for this podcast in the following message come from the this week in Google podcast
At twit.tv
Every week
Leo Laporte
Jeff Jarvis and Stacey Higginbotham
Talk Tech media and privacy
The unapologetically question
Google Amazon Twitter Facebook and other Tech Giants are on the right track
Subscribe to this week in Google
On your favorite podcast
Or it's wet. TV / twig
Elizabeth
Noel I think we all know someone a little bit like Cody Wilson
She's the kind of person who takes a good idea
Like free speech
And then he runs with it
Any runs with it so far
Did it starts to make
People nervous
He really likes shocking p
And his main idea is
Freedom
Every decision in Cody's life comes down to
Does this make me more free
He's the kind of guy who reads meechy and he talks about Anarchy
And you're thinking
Have you thought this through because Anarchy actually seems kind of
Terrible
Cody calls himself a crypto Anarchy
It is not clear though if this group actually wants to claim him back
There's a reason why Cody wants to align
Name self with this
They have a lot in common
Crypto anarchist
Believe that the anonymity
The internet is going to bring about
It's a world that they want to see
Will that they think is inevitable
Where to point now Whittington allows you to evade
Censorship
X's and Louis
Why would anybody follow the rule
And you know a lot of these guys live in their heads and then they get out of
High school or college
And like they calm down you know they go off to Los
That is exactly what Cody Wilson did he went to law school
But then you realize
VA te Busco
I felt fully Superfluous in Moscow and I feel like a complete waste of my time
I was going to school with like Tradesmen more than
You know me choir is
Nothing Sultan of course
Of course
But Cody
Wanted to change the
He just have to figure out something
World-changing
So one dates on the phone with a college buddy thanks to spit pulled all the time about ways that they
Raise mischief
He's princess
What if we made
A gun
And it feels Cody's like
Well
Everybody likes guns
It's nothing special something new to do anything there you just be coming off
Dennis Francis
Listen
I just remember him saying what you know what about
3D printing a 3D printer gun
Wait wait hang on hang on
It was just like that I have no prior experience
I'm passing like maybe the other people has it
But it was that Loki hey
Kodi
We could 3D print a gun
It was about a couple minutes into that I'm like
If that is possible
That's what I most exciting things actually
That
Out of her car to me
In 2012 low cost 3D printers at taking off
Could you describe the 3D printer that you was going to use like an elevated hot glue gun
It takes to soften plastic and using digital blueprints if piles layer upon layer of plastic into whatever shape
3D printers aren't just getting cheaper they're also getting smaller
They have these ones that you can fit on your kitchen table
Two people are using them at home
And they're making simple solid objects
Play toys and figurines
But as far as Cody can tell no one's ever used a 3-D printer to make a gun
And then made the blueprints public
Going to a gun store and scanned it account at to buy a gun
Jupiter digital blueprint online for free
And then anyone can take it and improve on it
3D print their own gun
He does a little bit of research
Any figures that to lease a high grade 3D printer and to hire an engineer he needs about 20,000
$1
Restart the campaign on a crowdfunding site
He makes a video when he's sitting there in like a peach colored Church shirt look about 14 years old
And talking about his idea
For a Wiki weapon
The product is in the right position what we're interested in producing is
A digital file
The file itself
VShare
Let me explain saying here is
I'm not interested in making and selling
Actual
Physical
I'm interested in the free exchange of ideas
A lot of people watch the video but no one is really giving him any money
He gets a handful of calls
Is one dude from West Texas who gets in touch and says hey this is a great project I'd like to
Help me with a multi-millionaire in West Texas and he had a big oil company I checked out and checked it out and checked out General company
The guy that helped finance
Scientific stopping at all checked out I was at when I was rich
Curious
Anime
I'm a chat you know ice
Zwilling give a kid a chance to
Oh and he got me he was he was the first guy to get me I had never been
Catfish by the insane
This gentleman apparently really just wanted to talk
On the phone
Seven three weeks Cody had only raised a couple thousand dollars and the needle was stuck
And then the crowdfunding sites
They like
Hey
With a pipe bomb will you come to fundraise
Feel like
Smart tooth
Not a god
At the same time Cody gets a break
A reporter from fold magazine he's about what he's planning
Holding up
You for real
Call you like
I sure am
So you got the profile info
First line of the article
Cody Wilson
Has a simple
Cody Wilson has a simple dream and after that the money comes
It's pouring and it's just a handful of people but they are people who are really behind
Erase is almost $20,000 and he can finally lease
A 3D
A beautiful 3D
Print out by the way the delivery truck rolls up
I'm in the back door open
They listed it down on a pallet and I tore down off a pallet of beside my apartment complex so I can
West Campus
But then a couple days later he gets an email from the printer companies lawyer
An email says basically at Hey kid
We heard about you
You're trying to use our printer to make a gun
We will be picking it up from your apartment
Tomorrow
Well I had made a lot of progress I hadn't unboxed
Most of it in fact
I don't have it for a few days a couple days top Center
They came to my house they took the boxes out
They put them on the truck on a lift gate and
IWatch Tikka
So his printer is now gone
But rather than back down he gets
Defiant
Now he needs to do this
Because not doing it would be loose
He figures by now no one else is going to sell him only
But he has a back-up plan he knows a small 3D printing shop in Austin and Leona's
A game a couple of dudes in a machine shop in on st. Elmo in Austin Texas they want to have some fun
Cody just go back his Ambitions a little bit
He decides he doesn't need these guys to 3D printing and entire gun
The engineering part of this is actually really difficult
So he's just going to have them print
Single gun
Part
Because there was a gun parts as a single guy
Pot that had already been
Printed with
Another gunsmith at donut he put his blueprints online
It was a lower receiver of an AR-15 rifle
The lower receiver is the part that makes
The gun A gun
It's the foundation
It houses the magazine with the rounds
Firing mechanism
The receiver is also the part of the gun where you have the
Serial number
It's a part of the gun that you need a background check to buy
So if you can 3D print one of these things you're making a gun part
Without needing a background check
That has no serial number
And that can be turned into an untraceable gun
So Cody hands over the digital
Prince to the
Company and they call him the next one
Ushered me into the back room and said look it's ready it was finished for you
Hey listen
The printer had a Bay open
We took it out
Separated from the
From the plate and
It's beautiful I never see this
Is she not at this kind of
Material that needs to be removed from it
It's kind of like a
Call like the afterbirth items are just beautiful stuff that needs to be removed they cleaned it up for me
Literally like I have been born in
And they
I put in my gun case and we just had my heart
Shuffle purpose FL
So powerfully
Parts of my car and you after that
Put in the passenger seat of my car and he drove straight to the house of a machinist Inu outside of Oz
And when he got there the sun was setting
And they were all of these people all of these gun enthusiast
Good heard about what this kid was
Trying to pull off
Who takes the receiver out of the case and he passes it around
I was green it was fleshy with strange
You know the season guys for like without you knowing
Not comfortable too much
Benedict potluck dinner to celebrate
Curry slept on the floor that night
Next morning he The Machinist
Machinist shop
Fishing is together 3D printed lower receiver
At the other pods
End
Fate had today off
The question now was a
Do they have a working
So they drive out to the Hill Country
To find out and of course Cody takes a video of all this and puts it up online
I posted up on a steel Target
I have my glasses on
Anna
I squeezed a shot and I heard it hit I felt the gun kind of pulse
My shoulders when I look down
I need to survive
I don't know it was probably greatest day of my life
He done it
It worked
He had printed a gun pot a crucial gun pod
From blueprints that he could now
Share with anyone
Online
It wasn't Hogan
Which is what he wanted
But this was a big step forward
Remember Cody was
Still a lost
In about a month after he shot that video he was in a big lecture hall about to sit an exam and he's taking his stuff out of his bag and it's
Phone pings
And there is a text from Andy the reporter who profiled him in Forbes
Emma text says
Does this change your project does this change what you're going to do
I don't know what you mean
So it puts it out of his mind
Until the exam is over
And a couple hours later he gets out into the hallway
And he's making his way down a hill to his car
Randy sent me another text message Sammy said it just said Newtown Connecticut
So I Googled Newtown Connecticut and I found
I found exactly what it happen
And
I won't lie to you
I I thought
Okay
I'm ahead of us
That's what I thought
What do you mean I'm ahead of this
I knew immediately this was going to be
A big one
This was going to be the next
For five months are going to be about American gun control
And
The attempted bills bills in the house bills in the Senate the president's efforts you know we were going to start selling and campaigning on guitar just knew that
That engine was starting up
I knew it there are people who are going
Want to know why your first thought wasn't
A bunch of
Small children
I have been shot and killed in a school
I am trying to understand
A thought process
That goes directly to
I'm out in front of this instead of
Oh my God
The thing I like the thing that I cared about
Was that I had a project I had to do to Fidelity
Tell the truth
Love that product like I was going to make it happen
And
This in my my update
Up the ante but as well at VNC in the next in the next few days and weeks I began to see that people began to take a passionate
My project
Not
The school is a curious what a cool new tech idea people began to think
Intend to say
You must when you must do it they're going to take
The stuff away from us so we went from being kind of curiosity on the internet
The people
People needing us
Saying that they needed us
To win
Dance to this
It's about the pasta
First for me
I need to just
Jump it
NF
Do you have an emotional human response
To the death of children
Small children in a classroom
With a gun
I'm trying to understand
If you are feeling anything about that
I know this matter
Innocent, casual social casualty of of a climate of
Persistent
Yeah I like mass shootings and stuff I mean it's not
The first
Thought you have sadly
Is that okay yeah there's another shooting
Babies babies mark
I get that
Okay what do you feel it
I did it and feel it I understand that that
It is bad
But I'm already in a
In a place
An activist mentality
What is going to be done with
How is it going to be used
How's it going to be used against me
Look I mean that's
That's where I am
Okay I'll be asleep Cody and I were not going to see this the same way
But Elizabeth you heard what he was saying there he was saying
We were afraid that the government was going to come and take our guns away
He was not the only person thinking that
The truth is
We know that after mass shootings gun sales 10 to go up
But after Newtown their fears didn't really come true
This country didn't pass any really significant National gun control laws
But something else did happen here
Cimino's begin Cody's
The community that he'd belong to those make is the people playing around with 3D printed online
They turned on him
And people like
They started pulling off their websites
Anything that has to do with 3D printing weapons and guns
This infuriated
Kodi
He was like
DoubleDown make his own webs
He takes his Blueprints and digital files that are being dumped
I put them back online
Trees raising the stakes year
And then he raises them to a point where they
Can't get
Much higher
Remember she was still determined to 3D print an entire working gun
And after a couple months
He did it
This little pistol called The Liberator
It work
It was a real working 3D print
Gun
It takes a liberator Blueprints and puts them on his website
And in the next 2 days
100000 people from all over the world
Download them
24 hours after that
Cody gets a letter from the US state
And for something written in legalese it is very clear that he is an enormous.
The latest said Cody may be in violation of some
The international traffic
In regulation
Itar is a set of regulations that controls the export of Munitions weapons from the u.s. to any other
And there are lots of rules about which weapons
Can be sent outside
And and where they can
And the state department letter to Cody says
Look when you uploaded those blueprints to the internet
You exported weapons overseas
Each download
To form person was this was a violation
We're talking about a hundred thousand
A violation
Hundreds of thousands of violations
You personally responsible for it
It's basically like being a being a Gunrunner on the Internet or some
I mean his website didn't just have the blueprints for his 3D printed pistol
They were blueprints for other guns there were blueprints for an anti-aircraft Warhead
But he's letting sporting actual guns a weapon
Bryce this is where it gets complicated
Itar controls distribution of
Hardware software and Technical data
The state department is saying these digital blueprints count as technical data
I guess what he's doing really he's against us
I mean it really depends
The state department says look you didn't get a license to upload this
And that is the rule with x
Do you want to export something you need to prove
What he didn't ask for approval so okay
But if you follow the state Department's rules to the letter you can see that the
Very
Is Harry respect
I'm thinking basically classify anything they want as
Technical data
And yet at the same time
Legally I cannot be used to restrict free speech
Is legal precedent
And we have an example of just how tricky this can get
Elizabeth you are an Australian citizen you are okay and so let's say right here in studio I'm going to tell you how
How to make a very simple
Step 1 Step 2 Step 3
Bang
Pictures how you doing
Cooties lawyer who of course is on Cody side
He says if you interpret itarsi
Strictly I just exported a gun to Australia
Illegally
Missy League
Illegally I could get in trouble
And this is what Cody was
He could be in trouble
The thing is whether you like Cody or not you have to imagine a world where the government gets to decide that I can't tell you
What was it that certain things
Because that is technically exporting munition
I'm not feels a whole lot like restrict
Yes and it did to Cody to
She did take his website down
He was facing 20 years in prison and $1000000 fine for each
Foreign download
But the word got out
And there are a lot of lawyers out there who are really into
Interested in not restricting the First Amendment
And also a lot of lawyers who are interested in the complexities of it
Security hire some of them and he sues the state department
And his legal strategy is this
The stuff you put online the digital blueprint
That's not technical data
That is speech
Some of the top lawyers in the country are now working for Kodi
Escapism
Kicked around the lower courts in Texas
Dinosaurs actually tried to get the Supreme Court to hear it and recently found out that the Supreme Court will not
So it's going back to a lower court in
Peter Cody points out
Virginia is already out of this photo
350 guns Realty happening now and
In many ways it doesn't really matter what the governor
The whole conversation had been fixed since the late eighties
That one American gun control is always going to look like
How we were going to do gradualism kind of get to
Why don't some consensus place
An innocence that arguments or repeated everyday winner
How can this balance between what we got to control things and
You know this kind of person can buy guns
A person can't of course that's all exploded
In a world where you can just download whatever kind you want
At which is the world's you want
Fossil wallet made
After the break
How you take a dangerous idea
And make it even more Danger
This message comes from NPR sponsor Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimum
That can be open from anywhere in 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
I've been talking to Cody for a few weeks about what he's doing now
He is still taking good ideas like free speech and then taking them
Very very far
His latest project is a crowdfunding platform called
Heatran
It lets people donate money to personalities including whites
Supremacist like Andrew Anglin and Richard Spencer who have been
Kicked off other
He's giving them a home
And he is also in manufacturing now
So here's what he's doing
The government pulled them offline yes
So he started Manufacturing
Gun Mills
This is hardware computer-controlled Mill
Amil is a black
Steel box
She's very heavy it's about a foot by a foot inside of it is a drill a cutter that can move in three dimensions
It can make a AR-15 lower receivers with no serial number
Gun control Advocates call these ghost guns
So Cody is kind of a middle finger calls his male the ghost Gunner
It can also take a metal frame
What pistol frame and make it into a weapon with Cody actually showed me
It comes in a pistol frame and comes out
Illegal
Firearm
Cody's company has sold about 4500 of these
They go for around $1,700
And I think it's tempting to look at them and saying
Well that's not as big a deal is 3D printing right it's just a mill
But you never reported that Cody was talking about
Andy his name is Andy Greenberg and he's a writer for Wired mag
Now we called him up and he said
Don't be mistaken
These nails are really
Significant
They make it easy to make untraceable
Those pots are made of metal
And as an experiment and even tried to
To do this himself
Inside the sound
Like almost like an infomercial this is actually
Results of the experiment
Is it is works great usually it was
It was a piece of cake
Did greatest durable metal
Lower receiver for a semi-automatic rifle
I just remember that
Nobody
Except me
And I didn't wake up. Co
Sacrum of wired
Office in San Francisco
And he started writing about Cody
Assuming that lawmakers would
Freak out
When they heard about this guy
Legislation would be passed to ban ghost guns really believe that was good
California does have a bad in the books that will take effect later
Is he us
Korea got me attention of a handful of other lawmakers
But aside from that largely not
Has changed
Anyway
Cody and I stayed at the shooting range until just about Sunset and then this guy rolled up in a golf cart
I'm holding a weapon
I got two minutes left
2 minutes left
1735 Northeast fire thank you sir
So I asked her hey can I take your picture and he says he of course any
He picks up one of the rifles and I put my camera phone at him
And he like deliberately makes this
Really mean angry
You don't even look like Cody that I've come to know today you look like a gunman
You look like a gun when you look like an actual gunman
Yeah I'm the guy that helps you make the guns on the gun now
Elizabeth he was
Totally performing
And I wanted to say that I wanted to say you are
Performing
But I knew that he turning on me and he'd say will you know what your performing to and then you Cody being Cody would turn into this hole
Philosophical fight
And to be honest
The place was closing and I was tired
So I let it go
I helped him put the guns back in the car
And we left
Today Show is produced by Sally helm
And Kasia mihailovic supervising producer
Special thanks in today's episode to Matthew Goldstein he's an international trade lawyer specializing in itar
He also represents Cody Wilson
Steve Albanese is a gunsmith at BlueLine tactical in Elmsford New York Kip Bradford is a board member at nation of May
Makers Adam Skaggs Chief counsel for the Giffords Law Center
Thanks also to Andy Greenberg you heard any episode
He's now a senior writer for Wired Magazine he's been covering Cody 4 years starting at 4
If you want to know more about Cody check out and he's work online
And
Elizabeth you have an announcement to make
I do this is my last episode of Planet Money
As a producer exactly you are going out into the world to seek your fortune as a freelance reporter
Be back in here I have no doubt
I'm Elizabeth gulou and thanks for listening