Just a little note today's podcast include some bad words actually the same bad words said over again in Rapid City
Hi Jacob
Here's a photo
This is a surveillance photo we're pretty sure taken by the FBI
You want describe it yeah so it's
Two men and a parking
It looks like the picture was taken from across the
You see the men in profile
The man on the right is wearing sunglasses at a
Dark jacket
Handing an envelope to the man on the way
What I love about this photo is it captures the exact moment where the guy on the left
Actually taking me over the closing right over
We can tell you what's in that envelope because this whole thing ended up
It is stuffed with money
The envelopes filled with $100
This is a picture of
Insider trading
You care about insider trading in the news
Who is this abstracting
No here is a photo of it happening
Insider trading where one person tips a friend off about some
Merger
Or leak some
Information
They buy some stock
Can you make a ton of money
This one made for a particularly good
Insider trading feels like cheetah
Because
Because it is
And it strikes this nerve
For people who feel like
Markets are rigged
You know here is your proof
Right to men in the Starbucks parking lot exchanging an envelope
What welcome to Planet Money I'm David kestenbaum and I'm Jacob Goldstein today on the show we talked
That man in the photo taking the envelope full of trash in the Starbucks parking lot and he tells us everything
What he did
How we did it and why you did but I don't know why he's still kind of training
Author what is insider trading the law is not actually there isn't really a law
And we dig into this brain teaser the money that Insider traders made where exactly does that come from
Who are they stealing from Today Show is a rerun from 2050
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities to help ensure a brighter future for America
Is children more information is available at aecf. Org
Usually in these cases the person who commits the crime
If you call them out they will just not
Call you back
Where they say talk to my lawyer and then the lawyer will
This case is different
So
See the guy in the photo
I am the guy in the photo yeah
This is Scotland
I've been a while I was
CPA
A CPA a certified public
Accountant
That was an accountant working at one of the biggest accounting firms in the world
KPMG
And he was good at his job
You got promoted over the years to where he was overseeing 500 people spread across the whole region
And he says it was a kind of job you could feel good about
They were conducting audits
Hundreds of
Publicly traded
Making sure those companies weren't cooked
Books are making
Got all the big decisions ran through him
And in the course of
Doing that
What do you learn about a company
Everything
Hefei
After really everything
What's going on internationally what's going on with quiddity wise what's going on with future projections
I thought you would know as much as almost anybody inside the company about
The company
Yes
This was of course very valuable information
And Scott says it was super clear that it was supposed to
The whole point of the audits was to ensure fairness
In the market
They would check in
Improve the company
Financial statements
And then that information will be released to the world
Everyone would get it at
Level plane
That's if they had Essex training classes every year or so
Reminding people about the importance of keeping the information secret of keeping it confidential
As a boss
Scott says
She was often the one telling people to be careful not to even let anything be overheard accidentally and there were numerous occurrences
I swear
You know you're on the 30th floor of an office building you all head down as a group to lunch go get a bite to eat
And you're in the elevator and and you get you get on 437 gets off for 20
I had to
Discount
Put my finger up to my lips
Or do you like that the stop sign over your neck is that you don't hey stop stop talking that type of thing
Sometimes his friends would ask him you got any stock tips
And his answer was always
No I can't tell you anything
Sorry but it is hard not to talk about work
And Scott had this one
Name Brian Shaw
They belong to the same color
We went out for dinner and we play golf and we
Occasionally travel together
It went to concerts together it was one of those nice relationships that exist outside
Out of the family part of your life they weren't hanging out
Because their kids like
Whether they like
And Brian was in the wholesale jewelry
But sometimes seeing Scott talked about stocks
Erie Safeway
Until one day when Bryan when Scotsman
Makes this proposed
Eagles hey
I no way that we can both make a little bit of money
You give me information
I'm going to trade on it
I will split it three ways
I keep the third you keep a third and the government gets 1/3
What did you think when he said
My initial reaction was I was joking
I just yeah I said want you we can't do that
Definitely does not need the money he's making more than $500,000 a year
But he says
His friend Brian's jewelry business is doing really bad
Play this is right after the finance
And his friend says he need some help so Scott considered
I can just a little bit
What was going through your head at the time
You know it
A battle
The simple version of one side is that I knew it was wrong it was stupid
Alan the other side
Is
Alright well
He's a good friend
I trust him
You know
If you're your training and you know you're your
You're only going to make 10 or $15,000 who's going to know
Okay
I'll do it
And he stepped across that line that for years he's been telling people not
And here is how the insider trading
Scott agreed to pass Brian infirm
They did this about companies you may have heard of including Skechers the shoe company
Herbalife
That makes weight loss
For example just before Herbalife was about to release its earnings report to the pub
Public sayings
Whatever saying hey we had a really good quarter
Scott and Brian would talk on the phone
Scott would tell Brian what those results were going to be in advance
Before the public knew
Brian would buy the stock or
Place a bet that the stock was going to go up
Then the official announcement
About and the rest of the world
Play a little tape from CNBC
Brace yourself
Herbalife reported seeing Beauty Court
Stories coming in about 43 first-year Rose 28.5% you
Amazon
Do like this comes out the stock price goes up you can make thousands of dollars in a moment
In a minute just from having that little piece of information before everybody else
But here is something super weird
Where exactly did that money come from
Intimate
Support for NPR in the following message come from service now making the world of work work better for me
Their cloud-based platform and solutions deliver digital workflow
Clothes that create great experiences for employees and unlock productivity for your whole company
Servicenow digitizes the work your people have to do
So they can do the work they want to do
Using technology
To make people more productive and engaged
More it service now.
Who got robbed here
It's kind of a brain teaser think about Jacob you and I spent a long time trying to work this out with diagrams on
Drawing circles on paper and lines like okay here's the insider trading here's the money and wait who is the victim
Who's on the other end it's kind of tricky to think about because
Like if Brian buys stock
Right
He bought that stock
So you could say the person who sold that stock to him
That the person who got robbed
Because the stock went up
Yeah but that person wanted to sell that stock at that price if Brian hadn't bought it someone else would have
The seller that is not the Vic
We are not the only people who have struggled to figure this out there are a bunch of
Of academic
And here I think is vegan
Somebody was deaf
It's just really hard to know who
Think of it this way
For purposes of explanation imagine that Brian had bought
10 shares of herb
Okay
That is 10 shares that
Someone else
Doesn't own because Brian.
We don't know who would have owned it Brian didn't exist but somebody would
That somebody that unknowable somebody
Would have profited when the stock went
That unknowable somebody
That is the victor
That is the person who got
You're looking for someone who doesn't own the stock lots of people out there who don't
I think it's Brian have gone to Scott and said hey let's Rob someone's house
There's no way Scottwood
But this felt different
Scott says that was part of his thinking at the time
It felt like a victimless crime
God says he gave Brian inside information about about a dozen
And he says Brian paid him
For that information
In all these different way
What to give a watch Rolex
Another time but expensive
Tickets to a Bruce Springsteen concert sometimes
You just gave him
Usually they do the exchange indoors somewhere once the O'Brien called and asked
Meat in a Starbucks
He was going to be traveling he was going to be going someplace he actually wanted me to get this money in my hand
Is there anyway you can meet me
Like okay well I'm
At work
You know just a
Couple miles away
You know I can meet you there if you really want to it says yeah let's do that they meet at the parking lot
Nearby
There is a cow
Pants that photo that would later be all over the Press
Amscot taking me envelope
Stop Twitter
$5,000 in cash
In hundreds or what
$5,100 bill
What what do you do with
$5,100 bills
To be specific I put it in my underwear drawer ins in my closet
I always wonder where you should hide
Not long after that Scott remember the date because
What's his wife's birthday
He was home alone in the morning getting ready for work
And there's this knock on
Will the doors
Summit beveled glass all I could see was kind of just 2 images
The first reaction that I had
Was it was too guy to Jehovah's Witnesses
He opens the door and
Two men showing their FBI badge
And ask can we come in
And I said of course and they came in
It was probably a 30 step walk from
The front door
To the kitchen table where we sat
Nobody else was home
They showing that photo in the parking
Federal agent and his friend Brian
Right then
Escada sitting there
He sees all the Dominos
Was like okay was my wife going to say
What are my friends going to say
Oh s*** was KPMG going to say
Oh s*** I'm going to lose my job
Oh s*** I'm going to owe a lot of money oh s*** I'm going to go to prison
It got worse
Scott got a lawyer and one day they were on their way to court
In the lawyers car Scott's reading the news on his phone
And he sees this story about his case
It has something he says he didn't know
His friend Brian hadn't been just making small trades for
For a few thousand dollars
The story says
Brian has been placing much bigger
Says he made 1.27 million
And I almost threw up right there in the car
And I actually told my attorney he got pullover
He was driving but I just you know I was just
Fearful that I was just going to lose it right there
So I just I just couldn't believe it
And once I saw that I said
Holy
Holy hell this is
Yeah this is obviously going to be a lot worse
Got off to learn something
After his friend Brian had gotten caught
Brian helped the FBI
Set up a sting
Some of those last phone calls have been
Unrecorded
And that meeting in the Starbucks parking lot with the envelope
That was a setup
Is all spelled out in
Import document
Other course they were the TV Camera
Weather reporter standing up in front of the country
All started here seemingly innocent
Golfing friends and Buddies
The whole thing goes before
Are we get to another
I think frankly that I found surprising
When I started learning about this whole thing and that is the way the law
Insider trading
We talked to Sarah baumgaertel
She's worked as a defense attorney with fellow at Yale Law School
Something interesting about insider trading law in the United States
Is that there's actually
Nola again
Insider trading
So there is no law that says like
The insider trading law passed by Congress or
Or whatever
Correct there is no lie like that and in
In typical Congressional session they have
Increase the penalties for whatever insider trading is
With
And she said well everybody gets upset it inside her
Because you give someone an unfair
That is not the legal reason
Why it gets
The argument use these days in court for wife
Is that insider-trading amounts to stealing information
It's like that
And so for that reason proving that someone traded on Insider information that is not enough to convict
It's a financial document from some company blows out the window and you happen to find it sitting there on the sidewalk
Terraces
It's not insider trading for you to use that to make money in the stock
Because you didn't steal
One of the Box you got a check
The person providing the information
That person has to benefit
And in fact a bunch of
High-profile insider-trading cases were recently dropped
Because an appeals court ruled that that among other things the person providing the tip for adding the information
That person has to benefit in some substantial way
Who ran through Scott London's case with Sarah
To see if it met all the criteria
One did he give away information that he had a legal duty to
Yes absolutely
Did someone trade them in infamy
100% yes
Did Scott London benefit
We told Sarah about that photo of
Muscat getting cash
In a parking lot
That sounds bad
He agrees with
So so
Is he guilty of insider trading
Is this a trick it sounds like
Siri obviously guilty of insider trading
He pled guilty immediately immediately to identify
Scott confessed right away when the FBI came to
To his house
Ever since I got in talking to Scott is that he's one of those people
If you ask him a question he is just going to
You're Scott on the courthouse
TV reporter asked him a question about how much money he made from the insider trading
And he doesn't you know.
The question doesn't run
He gives this very complete
Accountant like answer just
Listing of each thing he got
Items that were
And the jewelry
The people back in the studio on TV after this they were talking about it like
Who missed their half a million-dollar a year job for $70,000
Scott says his friends asked him at 2 and he does not
Have a great answers
Can't say exactly why
I asked was it exciting
Thrill part of it
No wasn't exciting at all
Was he trying to get his friend to like him or what
Is that what it was
No ever
Master my mind
Got that he was kind of overworked and unhappy with
The job so
Everything felt a little lesson
Maybe that had something to do with it
He says crossing over that line was somehow just not as hard
As it should have been
Scott says what he did was just
Donkey says
But he's as well as best as he can figure out as best as he can
Reconstruct
He did it to help out his friend
And he says he didn't think they were going to get caught
Scott was sentenced to 14 months
Is given a window to turn himself in
Because of a mix-up he ended up spending a month in solitary confinement
But most of the time he was in a minimum-security
Spend a lot of time walking around the track they had listening to a small transistor radio telling other inmates
No I
Can't help you figure out that accounting issue with your marijuana
That was really a couple months early for good behavior
I think about what I did everyday
I think I let you know that
That. There's Downer days but for the most part no 80% of time I have
I have good days but I think about
How life would have been different
Were you able to go back to your your turn of your personal life
Yeah
Yes I committed a felony
There no doubt
I did something bad
But
You know I'm 53 years old and I've
And that
What I did there does not in my opinion does not define my
Personality of an
Who I am in a core
My friends understand that
They were
They'll say the right to my face
You're an idiot
I can't believe you did that
But I still love you
And I still would you know stand right behind you if I ever needed
Do you still belong to that Country Club
They kick me out
You ever see Brian Shaw
I have not seen him
Or spoken to him
Since the day he gave me that package in the Starbucks parking
Scott says they do live in the same
And they go to the same restaurant
So he knows he's going to run into a
And of course we asked him what do you think's going to happen when you do see
He said I'm not going to hit him so I can go to punch him
I just want to tell it
When the FBI caught you
You should have just come to me
I would have turned myself in we could have skipped all the drama
They never would have been that embarrassing photo in the Starbucks parking lot
One last thing I did call Brian Shaw when I was working on this story
He answered the phone I told him who I was and he said he was not interested in talking
You can send this email we are Planet Money on NPR. Org you could beat up at Planet Money
Arshad name is produced by Jess Chang special thanks to Bill Wong at the Hastings College of Law he was the one who
Finally definitively answered the question of who is harmed in insider trading