Support for this podcast
Send the following message
Sitcom from NCR who believes in small business
That's why they build NCR silver
Worthington point-of-sale NCR silver deliveries big Enterprise Manager
Tools built for small business
Visit ncr.com
There are some people in this world
Who do not take
Half-measures
Weather people is Asia press
Listen to all the Beatles albums
Because I like
The first one so I had to
To finish all of them
She also does this
Flip books
Red ocean comes novels
And short stories
And just last week
I feel completed something that to me sounds
A little alarming
She decided to listen to
Every
Single episode of Planet Money
Ever made
We occasionally hear from other people who have done this
For the record
No one on our team has
I guess my first question that I have to ask is like
Are you okay that's
So much Planet Money to listen to
You know six months ago I give up
And after doing that I so how many do I have left
Was
And I said to myself
I can do it and I will do it
Just about 900 episodes here at Planet Money and
Honestly
Sometimes it feels like there is nothing
Left
To make a show about
So I want to ask Asia
In all of that time
All of those episodes
What are some things that we have never talked about
I don't know I don't think it was in any episode about theme park
Theme park
Next we missed theme park
What about the cost of
Moving
Goodwin
Submarines and Marines so I guess there are still a few things left
Cover over something to cover Asia is right there is
Something left a cupboard and sometimes we ask you the listeners to help us find it
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Sally home today on the show
We take your questions
Your questions about Arby's
Airplane life vest
And
A whole different system for paying rent
Thelma femoris though
We're saving up for later
This message comes for men
NPR sponsor
Sergey Brin
The Bold way to steady growth
People often think annuities are too conservative
Too complex or only for retirees
But annuities can be a smart way to
Hedgemark
Risk and earn guaranteed
Returns
Gamebridge aims to change the game
By offering simplified annuity
Please in a Sleek digital Experian
That replaces
Spine printing
And phone tag
Nike with clear conditions
Ana Direct
Loafy model
Learn more at game Bridge.
Slash NPR
Cambridge
Is not available at all
All right Sarah Gonzalez
I had to bring you into the studio to imagine a world
That is
Kind of unimaginable
A world where everyone who wants a job
Has a job
Yes
We got a question about this from
Chris Jeffries on Twitter and he said hey
What would it be like
If we had
0%
Unemployment in the US for a few years
Sounds like a great world
It sounds good
Just know it's know there's
This
It's
It's not
I just can't even wrap my head around it
This is Heidi Schierholtz she's a labor Economist at the economic policy Institute in DC
And she used to be the chief Economist at the Department of Labor under
President Obama
So let's say hypothetically like hypothetically
If the United States did have 0% unemployment what
What will happen
The economy
That's hard to imagine that I can't can we do it more like if it went very low
I can't I can't even wrap my brain around
Cruzeiro
Impossible to even pay
If you got an unemployment rate
Anywhere near
0 /
Science
You're going to
Etsy
Dangerous effects of adjusted
An overheated economy
So right now the unemployment rate is 3.9%
If we got close to 0%
Here's what that would
The minute you wanted a job
You just had
No one would be unemployed that even for a little while
And if you're an employer and you need
To hire someone for a job opening that would make things
Complicated because
You have to lure away someone else is in
Employee
And in order to
Keep your own workers and lure someone else's
You'd have to increase
Priest wages
Which would be a good thing more money
But
If employers are
Constantly giving everyone in the country pay raises
That employer
They have to start increasing price
Cover the cost of those increase
Beijing wages
And those increases
Prices
If it happens on math
Can lead to
Accelerating inflation
Inflation Rising prices across the
And a little bit of inflation is okay
But in this world that were talking about it could be out of control
Right
Economist say we have to balance employment
And inflation
And the perfect Ideal Balance is called
Full employment
No one actually knows what the
The unemployment rate would be in that scenario
But Heidi says that full employment is when
Everyone who wants a job
Can find a job
But
You may be unemployed for a little bit of time
So there is some unemployment
But
The kind were okay with
So
Maybe we can talk Chris
But full employment is kind of like
Economist zero unemployment
And also that
Chris you should not want
The United States
To achieve
True 0% unemployment that would not be a good thing
For any of us
Don't do it Chris
Finxera Sally
Alright next up in the studio we have Kenny Malone
Drinking tea
I'm a little sick I'm so sorry for anyone
Listen to this but I think it will be worth your time
What do you have for
In the United States Ally you are aware
Two ways
Of getting housing you buy property
Or you rent it
Yelp
Better listener Richard Lee in ours was in South Korea recent
And was interested in a potential third up
A system known
As Chauncey
Shenzhen
That's right
So I can say can be translated as
Key money deposit
Yes he money deposit
This is Professor Jung Seung Kim was born in South Korea and is now an economics professor at Bryant University
In Rhode Island
He told me translate is
It's kind of like a giant
Security deposit
If I want to live in your house
I hand over some lumps out of money
I move in
Usually for 2 years
I don't pay you any monthly payments nothing
It's just that love Simon
Beginning
And then at the end of the two years
I'm about
And you give me my money back
Okay but what if I like
Lost your money well luckily I am
Living in
Collateral like I'm living in your house
Are there protections maybe there's insurance or a lien or worst case scenario maybe I get a cut
Of the sale of your house but hopefully you will not lose
Mighty money deposit
What ends up being like
An interest-free loan from you the renter to me the homeowner
With the house as the collateral
Exactly
And can be a lot
Money up front
Anywhere from 50% to 80% of the market value of the real estate
Almost
Buying
The apartment
Right but without buying the apartment she sounds a little ridiculous
Johnson says this system made a lot more sense in the
When home prices in South Korea with skyrocketing
And thanks we're really giving out mortgages
Translate development Middle Ground
Who couldn't afford to buy
But didn't want to throw their money away
Rent
And landlords Luvdisc
Because they could take this key money deposit
And then invested
There were these insanely High interest rate
25 to 30%
It's the perfect match between
The homeowners in the East End of the renters needs
One of the questions are listener had
Is whether or not this kind of a system would translate well into the United
I am a little sceptic
Because he says
For starters Americans just aren't familiar with
Probably be
Weird but if we could get over that
There's like where you going to put the money
If your a landlord where you going to get a
A good investment you can't go get those 25% interest rates
Anywhere
So
It's just too risky
Like it's better just to get the Sure Fire Red
And by the way this is
True in South Korea is
As well the chance a does not make nearly as much sense as it did in the
Sixties and Johnson suspect
That it is probably on its way out
Don't get to know about
Kenny Malone thank you you're welcome
Okay but
I actually need you to stay here in the studio
But I'm I know you but I need you because
We're going to do a lot of math
I know you were a math major
It's going to be good okay
We got a two-part question from Allison and Brian heitner
Have Airline life vest
Ever saved
Single life in the history of Aviation
And how much do they cost
OIC he's
Wants to know is it like worth it to be paying for these vests and then
Flying tomorrow
Oh yeah he told me that he thinks it's not worth it that's it
Listen to this for him
And I talked to this guy named Harrow renter
He runs a state database of plane crashes
And he sent me a list
Of
Times when passenger planes
Have had to land on water instead of can
Controlled way
Cold itching
And theoretically
That's when you left us could come in handy right because you might have some time
To grab it
So on this list there are 43 cases of this
In the last 50 years all kinds of plants like small ones only if
A few big commercial Jets
But Harrison life vests have almost
Certainly saved lives in at least
Some of these
If you're just talking about big commercial planes
More complicated but history of Aviation
Definitely yes
Okay okay
Now cost
This isn't this turned out to be very calm
Okay babe. I talked to one major airline who told me that they get their life vests
440 bucks a pop and they last for 10 years
Send it like a penny is a that's 100% worth it
There's some food lot more together
So I got in touch with
Robin riddle who's a partner McKinsey who is an airline expert
He was like you got to think about the
Fuel cost
Write the fuel cost because the more
Martial art uses
How much does a life vest
Point eight pounds roughly according to Robin
Including the density of jet fuel
And it comes out to about $0.04
Purvis
Per hour of flight
Okay
So then you multiply that by the average number of hours that a plane in the air per day which I got from it
And then you do that over 10 years
And you get
About
$133.59
$133
And $0.59
Is
The amount spent on
Fuel
Flying one pets around the world
Relic typically on average
Track my flight
Do some division
It comes out to about
$0.05
Purvis
Per day
$0.05
Five cents to have a
The vest on my flight there is like some labor costs associated with at 2 because flight attendants have a check then
Because apparently sometimes people steal them
That's preposterous I know
I'm so happy to be subsidizing
Even saving one life
In history and even if it were zero
I'm pretty happy to pay a nickel just to have the
Theoretical life-saving device
Listen to Ryan
During cost benefit analysis based on that but
This is no brainer for me
Yeah I guess
I don't know
It's pretty unlikely you're going to use it on a normal flight
There's a lot of planes out there
But I guess Sally five-set says it's comforting to have a life vest for $0.05
I think I think
That's probably right this is madness
Okay that was a lot of numbers
We need a break
Existential where
Is
The terror
Support for this party
And the following message
Come from State
Who's agent snow
That your car and home
Are more than just
Big purchases
They're a big part
Of your life
You put the time
I'm into making them your own
So now it's time to protect
With your own personal
State Farm agent
Not only
Play do they truly get you
But they'll be there for
For you when you need
And with over 19000
Neighborhoods across the US
There could be
Just around
Moritz statefarm.com
1 800 state
State Farm
Here to help life
Go right
Tariffs are something that we
Hikari on planet many many many times
But we have never
To my knowledge
Atera
And we got a question from listener Steve Whitworth the Bisley SS
When someone pays a tariff
Where does the money go
And that kind of thinking just like
Where
Is
The Terrace
In the most concrete possible way
And Stacey Vanek Smith
Is here with us by Sally whole host of the indicator Planet Money daily economic
What's podcast
I hear that you
Found the Terrace you touch them
This is true
I found them and I touch them
If you want to do this you go to Newark
New Jersey
To the US Customs and Border Protection
Protection building in Newark
And there
In this building
You will find
A massive
It is the harmonized
Tariff schedule of the United states
Wheel of the harmonized Tariff schedule it was all the terrorists with more than 3,000 pages
It has everything you could import
Yak United States
The woman who showed us all this information by the way was a woman named Linda Burke
And she took us through the Tariff book from moon rocks to purses to shoes
The works
Okay so you saw the Terrace
On paper
But
We wanted more than just
Paper we wanted to get closer
To the money
Where does the
Tariff happen
Like let's say there's like a 20% tariff on
Sandals from China
Who pays that when do they pay it like how does that even happen
After the merchandise is accepted into our Commerce
The
Broker has 10 days actually happened
Once items
Already arrived in the United
The people on the hook for tariffs
State government
Are American imp
Who often pay through it
A broker
And they get something that is
Kind of like
A credit card bill
Sofas like sandals Inc based in Tacoma
Send sandals ankle pays the import fee
Pratt
And then how do they
Who do they pay
They pay
National Finance Center CBP
Typically start electronically very
We see less and less checks
Every year
Cash is almost unheard of nowadays
But it still happen
Rarely if I would be surprised once or twice a year
Tariffs and cash man but it sounds like we didn't get to touch bags of cash
I costumes
There was no bags of cash that they let us see
But they did say that they are electronically bringing in a ton of money
After the IRS
Eccpp that
Customs and Border Protection is the country's biggest revenue-generating agent
It collected more than 40 billion dollars worth of Paris
That is a lot
To be fair at the IRS did bring in more than 3 trillion dollars but still a lot
And for the last part of Steve's quest
Where does the tariff money go
That is an excellent question
It could basically go anywhere
It just gets put into the US Treasury and because
Part of the money that the government uses to
To pay its bills
So anyway it's all around us
In a way
It's everywhere
Thank you Stacey
You're so welcome
And
Listen to hear more please listen it to the indicator
Daisy hosted with Cardiff Garcia it is
Excellent excellent excellent go check app
Now here with our last topic for the day we have Bryant or Stat our editor Bryant
Hello
So shoot what are you got on your mind
Meg Larson said it's an email about a drive sheet
Took through Minnesota
And on the way
She notices something there all these huge
Huge huge
RV recreational
Vehicle
Dealership
And she wants to know
Can there possibly be this many people buying RVs why are they so big
And it was something I've been wanting about to I have been driving by the same dealer in Massachusetts for literally decades
I've always been amazed at how enormous at Seaview Drive 4 miles is nothing and then there's just a
Filled filled with RV
Okay so massive RV dealerships
Across the country
What did you find out
Well it was pretty easy to find a person who knew the answer room I'm the director of media relations for the RV
Industry Association
There's always an association when you need one
And he said something that surprised
He said RV dealers really aren't that big
It says what Meg
Is experiencing
Is actually
Magic there's a little bit of a knob
Pollution effects
And the dealers
They're kind of David copperfield's
David Copperfield
Magician
David Copperfield was like a Dickens care
Calculator became a magician and had a huge television show in the 80s
Can the generations never talk to one another if we're talking now we're just not understanding each other
Anyway the Steelers there a bunch of David Copper
They put their biggest
Highest end
RVs
For the front of the lot
And so as your driving by it looks like there are a lot of fun
But there aren't Nessa
Sara Lee
As many as you think
So this is like the fake western town
And I'm in Hollywood a little bit and I Google that place in
It's ensure enough right there on satellite view on maps I could see it
There were not hundreds and hundreds of RVs as I thought but
Just like
Dozens
Strategically positioned so that from the road look like an endless field it's all a lie
It's mostly a lie
Thank you so much better that you're welcome Sally
Centos more questions
We are Planet Money at npr.org we are at Planet Money on Twitter and Facebook
I want to go follow us on Instagram from posting a lot of new stuff there it's looking really
Really good check it out
Play show with produced by Taylor Haney and Aviva dekornfeld
Our editor is Brian first. And Alex goldmark is are supervising producer on Sally home thanks for listening