Trade desk
Yes they can start in some pretty
Weird place
Take
Flavored
Tobacco
Flavored tobacco back what I graduated from high school it was a theater kids
And gosh
Smoking clove cigarettes everything smell like Christmas morning
I don't think clothes were a thing when I was in high school it was menthol
You know something I feel like every generation has
Their tobacco flavor that
Pools that into picking up a filthy filthy habit
I know I was one of the Phoenix
That's Barack Obama former Jones ER in Chief former president former cigarette addict
It's 2009 and here he is standing in the White House Rose Garden about to sign this big anti-smoking bill
Typically to crack down on those flavored cigarettes
The chocolate
Pineapple licorice
Coconut
Stop the kids like
They are
Offered products
With flavoring
The mask the taste of tobacco
And make it even more tempting
I want something to a desk
He's got the ceremonial pen thank you very much
On flavored cigarettes
Is
La you can't make them sell them or ship them
American kids are saved it is a happy ending who could possibly argue
The entire country of Indonesia
They've been sending the United States
Hundreds of millions of cigarettes
For decades
Clove-flavored cigarettes
And Indonesian there is something funny about this
La
The band includes
Strawberry flavors and Cherry in
Coffee
But there is
One flavor that is
Escaped the Spanish
Mint
MIT
Better known as
Cool refreshing menthol the law specifically exempts mint cigarettes
Which are mostly made here in the United States come in Indonesia is like wait a minute you can't ban
Our clove cigarettes and allow your mint
Cigarettes that's now
Fair
We as Indonesia save this is
In international trade violation under the World Trade Organization
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Sarah Gonzales the United States
Just about every country in the world
Decided
They were going to have a
A common set of rules about Trey
And if anyone broke those rules
They would have to immediately report to a lake
In Switzerland
Homo
The World Trade Organization
WTF
It's like the United Nations for trade
And like the United Nations
It's made some enemies
Including it seems our current
President
Today on the show we asked
Big question
Should the WTO be able to veto a decision made by the elected representatives of the American people
Does it have the power to stop a trade War
Is mint
A flavor
Is there a flavor
Is it
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Fidelity invest
As a Fidelity wealth management client
You get a dedicated advisor to help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes and make clear recommendations for your full Financial
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
Justice League
It's 2010
Geneva Switzerland
The headquarters of the WTO
If the speed
Classical looking office building right on the shore of Lake Geneva
Sun pours into his big windows
And a letter arrives
From the country of Indonesia
This is the first volley in the great dispute of Indonesia versus the United States
Loathe versus men
Savory versus refreshing
Don't listen to him kids don't smoke
The letter says we formerly called BS on this whole flavors
Cigarette ban
You have Des
Discriminated against our clove cigarettes in violation
Of article 2.1
The technical barriers
To trade agreement
It's part of the Marrakesh agreement
We all agreed on that remember all of us green
AmeriCash in America
The WTO is both in organized
Station and any idea if they have a building with employees they all call themselves The
Crateria twitch
It's just a fancy word for staff
Really it's much
Bigger than that
The WTO is a bunch of countries that
Promise to follow
Rule
They're about 60 agreement total but the main Prince
Boils down to
What is good for me
Has to be good
For you
We the countries to trade
Cannot screw each other over
And the WTO will help us enforce these rules against each other
Process of figuring out who screwed who can take
So what we can do right now is compressed
The whole drama
Clove vs. mint
Into just a few min
Step one in a trade dispute
The private
Meeting
The two disputing countries have
Tuck it out on their own any secure room works
It doesn't have to be in Geneva there just has to be a table
Actually
Pretty big table
They come with the lawyers and their brief
And if it already try that have racial yours in that pool that have a portal yours
That Pascal Lamy he's French during clothes
So I'm looking at this
Case between
2010 and 2014 about clove cigarettes
Do you remember this case
Of course I do
And he says the first meeting is like any negotiation
Except
Except they're quite productive the translation going on
The WTO
Works in
French
English
Fewest walks in and says
We're Banning flavored smoke
To protect
The kid
And I'm sure some countries would love to have a bunch of twelve-year-olds smoking the clove cigarettes Indonesia but we'd
And Indonesia is like
Oh really you
Care about the kids then why are you still allowing a candy cane flavored cigarettes
It's menthol
Edit palette
It's a flavor and kids in the US are smoking menthols to
No you're just protecting your own us tobacco companies and
Punishing the rest
To the world no no no no no this is not
About for inverse
Domestic product
We never mentioned
Any other country
Labor Day we are allowed to do that
Stalemate
Indonesian the United States they don't agree in that private
That's okay there's a bunch of steps next one step two
Bring in the air
Do usn Indonesia have to agree on 3 outside experts that usually diplomats
Former diplomats
And these three outside experts they are going to decide
Whether the US has violated in international trade
And the drama moves
To the headquarters of the WTO
I've been there before the whole place
She's kind of a trip it has all these
Old
Gorgeous murals
Workers on the wall and ornate ceilings and light fixtures but then it has all the
Funky modern European furniture in little
Little teacups
Everyone does have good coffee there
It is
Excellent coffee
Okay will bees experts they go into one of these fancy rooms with a good coffee and now even more lawyer show
This time with
Cartloads
Of paperwork
No it's just you know these people
You know that
Lawyers video by the timer
All by the page
Because a page is a Time
So the longer the bigger
The more money they make
And it's not just the United States and Indonesia in the room now now every other country that also stands to win or lose
Who is over the
US ban on flavored cigarettes their meeting with a panel to
Brazil they say we agree with Indonesia this Special Rule unjustifiably
Discriminates against imported cigarettes
And here are a bunch of past trade disputes to prove it
Turkey says
I don't know panel of experts first you have to tell us whether mint cigarettes
Are in fact the same product
S clips
And Guatemala is like
This distinction has too many ramifications for our country
We're not going to take
Take a side
But allow us to explain all the reasons why we think this case is so,
You can see why this process takes
So long
A year-and-a-half
Later the panel of experts releases
A 190 page
Report and there are many fine points in there the panel decides that the United States
She's right
About flavored sake
But they also say that the United States
Is giving special treatment to its
Menthol cigarettes it is
Discriminating against an Indonesian product
Fine
United States appeals the decision
Countries almost always appeal
So the final decision will be up to what is essentially the
Supreme Court
It's called the Appellate body
Body made up of
Actual
Changes although apparently they don't look like
Do you wear robes
No
Anor
Does your body work
James Backus is one of the original Seven judges at the World Trade Organization the way you are described to me
Was
As like
The grandfather of
The WTO appellate judges
Comforting father to grandfather talk to be brother Young
1995 Ford
Search up
Parole
Bacchus is American he was commuting from his home in Orlando Florida to
To Geneva
The judge job
Is a part-time
Becca says they all have to shed their nationalities at the door they represent the whole world
Now
And I can't talk
2NE1
We refrain from dinners cocktail parties or
Anything of that sort
How to descent we socialize we socialized among ourselves
For the first few years the judges don't even go to the WTO cafeteria
Feel like monks
Which they had to
The stakes are very high
Whatever these judges decide affect
Trillions of dollars of trade
The clovers mint case went before the judges
In 2012
It is not a trial
Lonely Robles judges meeting in a room
Going over all the oral and written testimony from the earlier expert
Propel
And they deliberate
The cigarette world is holding its breath
And the judges side with the original Three
Spurts the US
Loses
Time for puns
The WTO has what I call
The rule of the
The country hits its neighbor unfairly then that country is allowed to hit it back
The WTO gives countries permission to punish other countries we're talking money
Either cut us a check or
We get to slap rich
Retaliatory tariff
To hurt you as much as
You hurt us
Indonesia says the ban on flavors custom million
So they wanted 42 million dollars back
From the United States
Every year the law is in effect
And then
The whole thing just sort of fizzled out
Indonesian United States reach a secret settle
And US says
We're going to keep our ban on flavored C
Cigarettes and Indonesia at this point has found
I work around
Cigars
They start sending
Chinese
Cigarette looking clove cigars
That's why we all still smell cloves on the
I feel a little bit
Bad about this anticlimax
Ending to our big
Well
Welcome to the WTO anti-climactic is our motto this is how a lot of cases end
Everybody get that thanks for participating
Participation Trophy and then they go up
But this is the thing about the WTO no one country is willing to fight
To the death over this because
Countries
Want to resolve their trade disputes they want to
Trading with you
So in this case I mean even though the two sides fought like hell over
Flavored cigarette
In the long-term there are bigger issues out
United States wants to sell
Very expensive technology
Indonesia
Textile industry in Watts
To sell that to the United States
And so if you look in the long-term
It is in everyone's best interest
To compromise
Or at least it was
After the break what happens when the largest economy in the world besides
It's had enough of this whole
Compromising
This week on the indicator the Supreme Court just legalized sports betting and some people are worried about rampant
Game fixing
But it turns out
Legal bookmakers have a way of keeping people on it
Phenol
Watched people betting and they were able to trace it back to some players indicator from Planet Money shorts
Story about the economy
Every single day
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their own website
Using customizable layouts and features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online presence go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to launch you the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Donald Trump was elected
You may have heard
He does not see the subtlety and the beauty of the WTO like you
You do Sarah
Official sporange I just
Has ruled against
United States
He says quote
The WTO
Has been a disaster
To be clear free trade has actually benefited the United States and the United States has won most of the case
Is that it has brought
The WTO does not matter the Trump Administration decides not to
Fight back
These other countries on trade
It decides it's going to go after
The WTO
Itself
So we called up the guy running the WTO Roberto Azevedo
Ask him the most
Pressing question of our time
Director-general
Is mint
A flavor
Well
The first thing I should make clear is that as Direct
Dollar General
I cannot comment
On specific
Disputes you can't even say whether meant to the flavor or not
I can tell you my preferences
I love them in
Chewing gum for
Things like that
Okay I'll take it
Bruce Lee
If you are striking at the very heart of the w
Remember those judges
We talked about
The ones who are sitting alone in the cafeteria
Have to agree on who those judges are
And countries haven't always they vetoed the nominations
Guy just before said
This person let's start the whole process over and find a judge we can all agree on
But under the Trump Administration the US is preventing any new judges
From even being considered
What we see now is different
It's not about
Disagreeing with the outcome
It is about not allowing
The process to
That is impressive
And there's nothing the WTO can do about it
So we don't even begin to look at
Received the names of the Kennedy
The process was
Launched
Which have two handed
Can I see something pretty
Clever way
Just slow down the work of the WTO right now there are four judges
Two are on their way out
When it goes to two
Then at that point in time
The appeals process is
Play paralyzed
Are you concerned about that
Absolutely
It seems like a lot of the reason why countries
Play by the rules is just
Kind of like out of respect
For the Norms of the WTO
What happens if a country
Goes Rogue
Says you know we're not going to follow the rules that have historically been followed
So it will compromise the system
Pusher
If we don't all
Try
Observe the district
Placenta results
Dudes
And in the system.
Sum function
I think sometimes the WTO is
Portrayed
As this Boogeyman have all of this
Power
But it really it's a pretty fragile system that takes a lot of
Agreement among its members to get anything done
Like there's no enforcement it's really just countries promising to be nice to one another
We contacted the US trade representative
Office in the Trump Administration to ask about the news
And they said that they have some
Problem
With some of the technical ways in which the WTO is handling the judge situation
Those are resolved
They're not going to prove anymore
Okay but there's one thing I want to get him here
Yes
The US is making things difficult for the WTO there
Screaming at the referees on the soccer
The US
Is still on the field they are still
Playing against other countries
The United States itself
Bring in disputes
To the system even though
Demonstration
Soap
Why bring a dispute to the system if
You don't want to
To observe this is
Want the system at all
So you're saying
Under the Trump Administration the United States is coming to the WTO and making claims against other countries
I'm not saying that
What is a
I feel the same
WTO can't live with it
Cat Crusher trade opponents without it
Robert just a warning
I think we might have to do this whole process all over again
Food and Drug Administration under Trump
Steve just announced that
They're ready to start considering a ban on
All of the flavors including cigars and E-cigarettes
Even
Menthol
We are at Planet Money on Instagram
Twitter and Facebook or email is Planet Money
Npr.org
Special things to Michael McKean with the bertelsmann foundation
Today Show was produced by Megan tan and Nick bouncing or supervising producer
And our editor is Bragg
Robert Smith thanks for listening
I highly told breathing I thought they needed
PTY
Like disease
Lung
Okay wait
Do we promote cigarettes
I don't know I kind of feel like going to be today
You should we should play out one of those ads for
Yeah
Cuz I really
Cool lights
Smoking ain't cool ads