Support for this in
NPR podcasts
The following message
Come from the UPS
Offering services from shredding
To printing to mailbox
And instead of closing this Memorial Day we
May 24th and 20
The UPS Store
He's doing another thing
All together
Opening
The UPS Store
Everything for small business
And of course shipping
Brittany shammas
Hello you are a reporter at the Miami New Times
Where does the story start
So 4 to Paris the story starts
When he's on the floor and his living room reaching under his couch
I adopted a new puppy
Who happened to like tennis balls
And unfortunately all the balls were going under the bed the couch
The dresser this joyous guy he's got this great goatee he loves dogs obviously
Prettiest back problems in this new puppy was making them
Proceed goes to the store he gets a Singer sewing machine a bunch of fabric and some stuffing
Piso's
Best egg
Long
Tube
Any something under the couch
It was like a bumper
He rolled the ball towards the couch
And it didn't go under
When the ball row rolled
For the couch
It bounced out
And I was like oh my God
Look what I just did
You invented something
I meant something
He called it Teddy's ballie bumpers
Is your is the dog that was around when you had this event when you made this event is it still alive
He's right here with
With his with his back to me I would just be like in the future
Did you name the thing after him
I did Teddy's ballie bumpers
How do you want to talk to Nick
He's looking at the phone
He actually just yawned so I don't think
No he's not
Kanaka boy
A few days later Steve's watching TV and it had came up for World patent marketing
A telephone number
And so
I called it
They said this is World patent marketing how
Can we help you and I
Told them about that I had no idea
And they told me that
Before I
Explain my idea was
They wanted my email address
And they want to send me a privacy
Statement
That you know I wouldn't have to worry about
My idea getting out
That sounds legit
Brother they were already trying to
Yo make sure that normal
Steal my products so I felt wow that's
That's pretty good
Live didn't know it yet but I've walked right
Into a trap
Glenn Wilkins Planet Money I make Fountain Britney is a reporter for the Miami New Times and Brittany
You wrote this amazing mind-blowing article about the world that Steve was about to enter
Movie about inventors
Avengers are the most optimistic people out there
They imagine a better future and that's why they're so important also why this company
Preyed upon
Unless an empty handed and out of thousands or even hundreds of thousands of dollars
Maybe with the help
Are they acting us Attorney General
Bubble get there
Support for NPR in the following message
Come from servicenow
Making the world of work
Work better for
Their cloud-based platter
Form and solution
Deliver digital work
Clothes that create great experiences for employees and unlock productivity for your whole company
Servicenow digitizes the work your people have
So they can do the work
They want
Using technology
To make people more productive and engaged
Moret servicenow.com
Hibernate you've been reporting on world patent marketing for a while now right is this the craziest or you've ever worked
Pretty crazy but I've also written about you know cough syrup theft rings for purple drank
That's possibly involved Lil Wayne and
Chris Brown as customers so that was crazy too
Where does the story go down
Festive cats
A confidentiality agreement
He signs it he send it back in
Then he hears from a representative of world patent
If it's British guy who the New York
And you like wild
Fantastic
What a great idea really talking it up
And then the guy said the next step was that world patent marketing could do some research
He told me that for the price of 1995
They will be able to do an analysis
So Steve is told that the market analysis is going to tell him
Whether there any other products out there like his
And if so are they patented
It also is going to tell him
How marketable his product is
And how World patent marketing could Market it for him
And then it's six weeks I would get a pack a bag and it would tell me everything
Oh my God
For 1995 fl1995 you know
Mcmxcv Doppler
Werewolves
Sorry I thought you were talking
Like $20
No
Are you talkin $1,995 but
But as an investment
In your future
You know you got to be in it to win it and so that's what I did I went in at 2 with it
What I did
Perceive gave the company has credit card information
And then after that he just waited
Braided one week weight at 2 weeks
3 weeks 4 weeks 5 weeks
It's six and a half weeks
A package
Came Federal Express
From World patent marketing
Opened up the envelope
And there was a packet in there probably around
I would say 50 pages is a very very first who's sick it was very thick
It was very impressive
Inequalities
Drawings
He's like mock-ups and also
A market analysis supposedly done by Baylor universe
Airport said that Steve's product
Didn't have any Market company
There is nothing else like it that was patented Repose ballie bumpers
Like a viable product
Yes it was so
There was a section that gave you a score
My score was
Which was the top
79 to a hundred was a probable
High probable sale toolbox
Bed Bath & Beyond not so far away
Oh yeah oh yeah
All of them
Walmart all of them
I mean
The dream right then
In their became a reality
Also in the packet
4 steps on what he could do next
The Rock
Packages that world patent marketing offer
And Steve was pretty excited at the time
Started looking into the primo one
It was a universal patent
Protection package
I want that. This package
Are patents mentioned in 21 countries
Manufacturer
I never do all the marketing
Product
That was
$20,000
So that was
One of several options
Yeah and there are other options
2 but I figured that
Because my score came in as high as it did
I would want to protect myself
In other countries if you didn't want people ripping you off
Another country exactly
He went ahead and put a New York to meet with his financial advisor
To talk to him about this package
And his financial advisor
Thought the
Packet was legit and
They decided to go for it
Patent application paperwork for his patent
He was told that his product needed to be patent pending before he can move forward
Steve
Who is full of Creative Energy and like nervous because he wanted to get started on this
Couldn't go out and talk to manufacturers or Market
Did the Peter topping and
You know you're looking around and thinking old man old man
Got to come through it's got to come through
And
Sure enough
It it did
It did
Oh yeah I did get a
Is the receipt
That it had actually been filed
Okay and that all the paperwork was received by the US patent office and then my product was in Patton
Pending status
Perceive
This is huge
I was in a better I was
I was that person
Like the person who invented the the steel mills and
The only other
Crazy things that were invented
I was now part of that family and
You know it was just a thought of of being an Avenger that made me feel so wonderful
So after that
Steve hears
From the CEO
A world patent marketing himself a guy named Scott
He was definitely
A New Yorker someone who
I'm not taking anything away from New York all night
So was so was this guy SKy Cooper
Was he stoked about your products
He told me
He told me that this was going to be
The product
His company
He was going to I was going to be
Did the top inventor of
Roll patent
Well
Oh yeah
Oh oh oh yeah oh oh
It gets it gets a whole lot better
We should stay here we did try contacting Scott Cooper
Where to get his side of this
I didn't get back to
So Steve is pretty excited to be working with World patent marketing at this point
But things are going a little slow for amino
He's like I want to be in every Walmart yesterday
So he doesn't even wait for World patent marketing to find a manufacturer
He finds one for himself
And
We were go
Scott
Scott and World patent marketing we're not upset
That you
Dad found your own person
Oh no
It was the opposite
Cooper call them up and it's like
We need to do a market
What's we got to send out a press release across the country
Any sense of a draft of the release
I said Scott isn't the only thing is it says that
World patent marketing
Got me the manufacturer his ball doesn't really say that
It says that you don't we're sort of in on it
Acid
Got my manufacturers this was all worried about that
We want to get people motivated
And I said well
Okay his trust me
Trust me
So it's a few days later Steve is at a Christmas party in California he's standing by the pool
Scott Cooper
Inside it is depressed for
Saying that Steve Harris just received this incredible Christmas present
Of
A manufacturer
And so it went everywhere and I'm fact now I can go everywhere but it also went on his
Website
Haha
So you were like
You are a big success story
Actually
So I was
The success story that they did
Wait what
Thousands people
We meet someone who took the bait
She and Steve would end up taking this whole thing down
Support for this podcast
In the following message come from the Annie E Casey
Sea Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and community
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org
Okay we're going to pause Steve Harris's story for a second because we need to meet Crystal Carl
Britney tells about Chris
Crystal Carlson is
Amazing
Investigators she knows her way around public records she knows how to pull
Court documents she for many years had her own Plumbing business and I also homes
School
My children have seven kids
So that's like a full-time job and its own Crystal got involved with World patent marketing after Steve
She's living in Arizona
At the time she would see these reports on the local news about people leaving their kids
In hot cars
So she was worried about that
Casino seven kids
Crystal went from
Civilian to inventor one day when she was coming home from the grocery store with her family as we're bringing groceries in I've got to
Do that have to go potty and I'm trying to get down to the toilet and then the dog
Made an accident so that it's like this clean
And then I'm like asking my husband is everything out of the vehicle and he's just staring at me
I was like
Where's the baby
So Crystal invented
Pressure sensor that detected with a kid was still in the car or any other parent when they were walking away with the child still
Did you like
Work up a prototype
I did
What it look like
Horrible
I tore apart a bunch of items
Estelle
It was not very
It was like a real
American tinkerer invention
Yes Crystal knew she needed patent protection
So she went looking for someone to help her
And remember she really does her homework
I'm a very
Big research nutso
Haha I really poured into it and I found so many different companies and they had all these different
Things that they
Said that they didn't and when you try to research on them you couldn't even find any of their products out there so
It's really hard for me to feel
Like I could trust them she found this one
World patent marketing
It was super profession
The CEO of the company
Was supposed to be very involved with inventors and Crystal like that
And also
They had some success stories
Hi my name is Steve Harris
And so I decided I'm going to Google search
Kiss products
And lo and behold I came across his product manufacturer for sale in a website
Site
And every other company I can't find it
Single invention cell
That's promising
The world patent marketing
Write any
So crystals looking around and she finds this page
On the world patent marketing website touting its advisor
They just have this little thing that said meet our Advisory Board and they had all these images to the people who were on The Advisory Board
Impressive
Impressive because a lot of those people
Tide
Background
To them
That would make you feel that they were important
Government officials
Ex military officials one of these officials
Was Congressman Brian mast
Another one was Del daily a former State Department official
With Matthew G Whitaker
Whitaker was a former US
Attorney
For the southern district of Iowa was just tap to be the acting Attorney General
He is the most powerful law enforcement official in the US right now
Whitaker was paid for his role on The Advisory Board close to $10,000
According to court.
Give us a list of prominently and press releases about the company
Any recorded videos for them
There's one that we saw online where he's talking up this chair for a hot tub
It's a unique design is going to help
Lots of people
Manor
And here's another one of him describing dislike razor blade cover
Is a
Simple design but unique
We did reach out to the Attorney General's office and a spokesman told us that Matthew Whitaker
Had no knowledge of any fraud happening at World patent marketing
Roccat marketing is just the latest version in a long-running cotton that has been
Take advantage of inventors for
Decades now
But World patent marketing is unique
Because of how much money was able to get out of
People like
Crystal
World patent marketing
Mostly the same cell on crystal as they did to Steve
The confidentiality agreement and whatever
But there were a couple nutria
This time
They made her wait before they took her money
And I told her it's because I had another lady
What an idea just like hers
But you were more prepared than she was so they ultimately decided to move forward with you
Wow
Now I have this feeling of
Oh my goodness
There's another person out there
Trying to move forward
What the same thing as me
I'm in a race moving right right
Crystal's sold in old cars
Scrubs together
Some change and paid for the marketing study
And again it found
Her products was a winner
World patent marketing told her that she needed to pull together 36
Thousand dollars
For the global patent protection
This package
Was the work
They said it would get her patent protection everywhere it would get her copyrights trademarks
Ana license
They told her that to raise the money she could just go borrow from friends and family
Or maybe she can take out a second mortgage on her house
Or go get a personal loan I don't even know a person personally who could go out there and get a personal bank loan
$35,000 cash
Right
So
I can't do that so she turned and said to her friends and family
And she showed them
The packet that she had received from World patent marketing about the viability of her product
Crystal told her friends and family what her contact at World patent marketing told her
That
They would make their money back in 6
So
Her friends and family gave her the money
Incent World patent marketing
$1,000
Kriti sanon today
Crystal realized
Hennessy
A patent attorney kept making errors
She was having to correct them this is the part of the story where the dogmas of the inventor
Combines with suspicion
And becomes a powerful tool
Crystal start researching everything chic
Patent law licensing marketing
And she starts
Calling World patent marketing
Pretending like she doesn't know about these things
And drilling them
And won't they're stopped all the phone calls
Savannah Crystal started looking for other world patent marketing customers
To see if they were having similar issue
How'd you do that
Facebook
I mean I know it sounds crazy but
The first reason that Crystal tries to find
Is that guy from the videos
That's the guy whose product World patent marketing was bragging about
Again
On your knees or
Straining your back looking under the couch or bed for your pets toys or the remote control had to find him
And the way that she did was
Pretty clever and every single
Article they wrote it was Steve H you know so
Steve wise
Ddave so
I went through
All the way like 2 years back and then I found
This poly bumpers thing they were promoting and then I click to view who all likes it and I see this
Steve Harrison oh my God the Steve H cuz I was not the only one that was
Steve with hearing a lot from other people who are sending him messages
If I was a multi-millionaire
How do I get into the box stores really busy trying to get his products
Into stores he had had 500 Vale bumpers manufactured
With the manufacturer that he himself found
I need marketing the product on its own
Air inflation pump free
Order Chinese boy poppers today
Your dog
Never lose
His balls again
To Crystal messaged him it was like
How's your project going
And we start exchanging stories to realize that
We were being scammed
And then
Steve received a letter
From the US Patent off
And
I open the envelope
I
Pretty much hit the floor
Because the letter can
Contain information that my patent
When abandon
World patent marketing hadn't submitted his patent application
Improperly
And then when the patent office followed up with questions they hadn't responded
Steve dreams of being an inventor and His image of himself as an inventor
Was all coming crashing down around him one of the sons of the manufacturers
Texted me at
3 in the morning and woke me up
And said you better see this
And it was a commercial for
Product
That was just like mine
That was published
Five years prior
So
The Prado
It was
It was devastation
It was complete devastation
So you'd spend
3 years of your life
Roughly $110,000
Have you sold any
Read sold
Probably about
30 of them
And then
You haven't sold one since
I can't I be infringing on someone else's patent
How does that feel
I I I I can't
I can't go I can't go there
That that's a place I can't go
Meanwhile Crystal was reaching out
To everyone she could trying to warn them off
One of her biggest moments
Was when she found out about a police officer
Put already sent money with World patent marketing and was planning to spend thousands more
She called him and I told him what happened to me
And I told him what happened to Steve
At that point he said thank you
How did you feel right then
Really good
Yeah
You should feel good about that
I'm sorry I'm getting teary-eyed
It's fine
Personal experience
You know I borrow $236,000 from friends and family
It makes you feel horrible
When you're able you're not able
To give it back
I'm sorry
I haven't talked about it like
While
Did you ask them for your money back
I did
I sent a certified letter
Crystal Palace. Cooper give me my money back or I'm going to report you to that
Immediately she got an email back
He threatened me
That he was not doing these things that I claimed he was doing and
She's got all these
Powerful people part of the Obama Administration on his Advisory Board and why would any of
Of these people
Want anything to do with him
If he was doing the things that I claimed Crystal shut her computer and decided okay
We're doing this
Call the FDA
Call patent office
Started trying to reach out to anybody else I could and man we grew our numbers fast that's when we went
From 10 to 20 to 50 to 100
So this letter to him happened in April and by December we are filing a class-action lawsuit
By August
I was already talking to the FTC
In private
Because they were doing a soft investigation
So in 2017 the FTC comes in and they raid the offices of world time
Marketing
They got all the paperwork and the office
And they file a complaint accusing
Scott Cooper and World patent marketing of building thousands of people out of
Almost 26 million dollars
We reached out to that DC and they decline
But there were tons of documents
They submitted in court
And a lot of crazy stuff came out
The CEO Scott Cooper
At former Israeli military as security guards
You tell people they were trained in Krav Maga and use them to threaten
Another thing that came out where the script
Scripps that sales representatives would use when they were trying to persuade somebody to send them money
A lot of pictures of felt like their ideas are unusual
And being approved
But it turned out that they're all working off of us
Stetson Baptist he found no rejection
One more thing that came out in court was an email from Matthew G Whitaker
The now acting a
Attorney General
He was put in place last week after Jess session
Chance was fired
This email seems like it's a someone who's complaining about world patent marketing
It basically was telling this person
That they could face
Potential civil or criminal consequences
If they were doing
What sounded like from you know the context
The email
Reporting to
Better Business Bureau or
Marrying
The company online
We asked Chris about this
How do you feel about this
This guy who's now one of the most powerful people in America
Being involved with this company
My personal opinion is I do not know Mr
Whitaker personally
But as far as any involvement with World patent marketing
World patent marketing with
Stock Supra with a con man and he conned
Everyone
Focus on Steve
That if they can fall for it
So could anyone
Including a former US attorney
I called the court-appointed receiver this morning the guy who's trying to collect money for the
And he told me while other board members ever
Return the money they made
Whitaker has not
Scott Cooper the architect of this whole thing the CEO of world patent marketing
He settled with f
Without admitting or denying anything
Brittany
You actually been on the hunt
This week right yeah so he's going through some marital issues right now he was supposed to be in court for a
Sharing earlier this
Prudential
Okay wrap this up where is everyone now where are inventors
Stevens retired
He's not inventing stuff anymore he was never able to sell all the volleyball players that hit manufactured
Crystal is still tinkering away she's been really busy reaching out the car companies trying to sell them on her idea
Whitaker
Is the acting Attorney General
Of the United States of America
If you know of a scam is out there
Let us know
Will let other
Planet Money at npr.org also on Facebook and Twitter
And Brittany
Yuan breaking news
Left and right about
Where can people find that work
On Twitter at Brigham
Or at the Miami New Times website or you can find it on any Street Corner Miami
God bless all week long live all weekly
Britney's original story on this
Amazing you should go read it
Right now we spent five days on the story
She spent five weeks on hers
We have a link to it on our website
Today Show was produced by Sally Helm or editor is Brian Earth that or supervising producer is Alex goldmark
Editor's Tim elfrink and Chuck Strauss
Thanks Tim and Chuck
I'm Nick Fountain and I'm Brittany salmon