Hey I'm just leaving a voice memo for myself
I'm in the Shannon Airport
In Shannon Ireland
On my way back to the United States to New York
There is this
Picture wall
Giant pictures of all the famous people who come through here
Xenon headlights
John F Kennedy and his Fidel Castro and Boris Yeltsin
And there is one photo that was sort of amazing for the picture of the president of Ireland next to him is someone called doctor
Brendan Oregon any sort of out-of-focus you can see he's granddaddy suit
Just got an extra pocket square
And it says the Doctor Regan was the person responsible
For the skip work for basically developing Shannon International Airport and most importantly
He created the world's first
Airport
Duty-free shop
You know the duty-free shop at the perfume and the chocolate
And all the liquor
First one was here
And if I get a flight I just wanted to quickly over
And take a look at what was the world's first duty free
Alex scarves little jewelry
Where's the perfume
Is Jessie Baker
Folder durable my children on charge
I think duty free shops are
Supported on people who forgot to get gifts for the children
Chocolate
I got to go
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Robert Smith
Here with International jetsetter Informer duty-free addict
Turn.
This is true back in my corporate days I did spend a lot of time and money and duty-free shop
It seems like these days we're locked
Denis epic battle
Between those who want free trade across borders
And those who want to put up barriers
An early Skirmish in this economic War
Happened at airport along the banks of the Shannon River in
Today on the show we have the story of Brendon Urie
A former bartender turned entrepreneur who said let the world have its Courvoisier
Tax free
Am Lich the question I know that I have asked over and over again
Are we really saving any money
At the duty-free shop
Support also comes from Fidelity invest
As a Fidelity wealth
You get a dedicated advisor
To help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of tax
And make clear recommendations for your full Finance
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
Hey we want to tell you about planet money's video series called Planet Money shorts
Charming Mo make you laugh
You'll see the host and producers wearing fake mustaches and talk to him fake Australian accent you can find them on YouTube
Borat npr.org
Flash
Planet Money shorts
The story of Duty Free starts with a
Bit of Irish
In the 1940s when people were traveling from New York to London or Paris
There in these propeller plane
And to refuel they had to land in the first Runway they saw after crossing the Atlantic
And that was Western Ireland
County Clare
Along the Shannon River
Former mud flap
All of a sudden
Became the grand gateway to Europe
In the forties and fifties
Every famous person
Across the Atlantic
Almost certainly wound up going through Shannon
So movie stars
President
Prime minister
Kings Inn
Queen
They all land Edition
They all have to load to Shannon Airport
Ryan O'Connell was a bit
This man in the region
Is there any fish that everyone realized pretty quickly that they needed to upgrade the local amenities
For all these
Movie stars
In those days the airplane ride from United States
Long
Comfortable
And bumpy
Sometimes it was even in these
Flying boats basically planes that would land on water
You're probably tired you could be cold
Because obviously the
Brickley the flying boats flew
Cyclo
Atlanta compared with the play today so people
Where
Looking for a particular T to good food to go drink
This is when
Be free hero dr. Brendan O'Regan
The story don't let the doctor part fool you it is in
Honorary degree
Brendan O'Regan had been a bartender
Hotel clerk
Decatur
I want to Shannon Airport realize that all the movie stars were coming
They needed someone
They hired Brendan O'Regan to
He was a man who was very soft-spoken
Playas
Come
It was no nonsense about him
When the movie stars got their pictures taken
Could sometime Co Regan in the background
The Dapper man with Sandy hair slicked back
A region had this
Knack for promotion
From the very beginning
Rather than
Continental Cuisine with
Which is what they were serving at airports everywhere
He served
Irish
But you don't it up with all these place-names oh look this is
Carrie lehrman
Dublin prawns
Limerick butter
Wendy would serve Whiskey in the coffee
He topped it off with this
Thick layer
Local cream
And he named it the very first
Irish coffee
We over again created the very first Irish coffee is delicious Irish coffee is
They're at the Shannon
And here in this little
Kiosk
Next to
The restaurant and it was it was nothing really little mini bottles of whiskey
Trinkets and Chee
Cheap stuff
But the point here is that everything was always tax
Back in those days
Well not everything
Pizzeria noticed that there was this Loop
In the British Isles it had been a tradition that Sailors about to head off on their own
Voyage
Could bring on board rum and whiskey
Out paying Duty
Yep which I don't know why would they do that just to
Keep the crews happy I think that's right. That must have been an element amateur
Have some sleep off a lot of the time I don't know what that was a tradition that went way back
YouTube
Alex 17th century our way way way back hundreds of years
And strangely this loophole was still in effect in Oregon State
In 1950 he was on a trip to the United States
Any decide not to
Flyback
The Shannon but to take a cruise ship
The SS America
In a Rican notices when he's on board
That the alcohol the ship is whale Essex
Expensive stuff
He's been serving at the airport
Oldest alcohol and tobacco was good so Judy free
Because they were in international waters this is like the law of the high seas
So he said wait now we're competing with these guys
Fire
It's not fair
That I contact the same text about used to have
And this was the genius of Brendan O'Regan
He went to the Irish government he said
Essentially
What are airplanes
But votes
Of the sky kind of Truth and what are airline passengers
Modern-day Sailors of the
Cloud right also deserve their tax
Free rotten
And perfume
And Haribo brand gummy bears
His exact words are lost
The history but we do know
Did a lot of people the Irish government said
Latex free
Are you kidding me
Because every
The proper to put out every Customs people worldwide
Resist
Getting away tax revenue
Shredder for tickly of this paste Marley the idea who you who's benefiting out of this
Wealthy people who
Fly the Atlantic and plain semi that's only a tiny percentage
Population
Why should we do any good for them
The government stood to lose a lot of money if they went with this tax
Freeskiing because
In some cases
When you buy alcohol most of the price tag is
Actually tax
Steven taking today
If you buy a bottle of wine down the street here in the United States
There is a duty added to the
Lacoste
Of that wine if the wind comes from overseas
But even if the wine is made in United States there is a
Federal excise tax
An alcohol addict the price
And then each and every state add
Their own excise taxes
To the wine and this is all hidden in the price tag
Plus
Then when you bring the wine to the counter oven you have
To pay sales tax
And on the total
Brendan O'Regan said to the Irish cover
Yes
Yes you will lose some money in taxes
But in the long run
If we do this
Will attract people to come to shadow
If we attract people to come to Shannon
MCR let some of them might decide to
Don't visit the place
Will make people aware of
Irish Goods
Irish whiskey was not
Property of acids minuscule of the US compared with
Scotch whiskey
Will make money because I the franchisee of office government-owned
Airports and you're making
The prophets so I'll I'll make you a lot more profit some particular I'll make you a dollar profit
So
Ireland said
Alright let's try it
But
We are keeping you on a very short leash
Or we can open the first duty-free shop
In the Shannon Airport in 1951
Okay it was only for passenger
Ecodistricts you will recognize from today
It was located between the lounge and the restaurant
So you had to walk through it
To get to anything
I hate that no it's
Brilliant and just like he promised the government
He featured Local Foods and crafts
I saw an early photo
Hanging in the airport
There's a picture of Gene Kelly the the the old dance from the old days buying
Butter or cheese or something
At the duty-free other selling
What looks like
Ham
Bacon
Honey
Cheese
Jam and eggs
We was just like a farmer's market in the airport
I think the local stuff was kind of first show because honestly
From the beginning
This was all about cigarettes
And alcohol
Whiskey and smokes were Apparently one
Third the price you would pay outside the airport
It was so cheap
Irish government was paranoid
Irish gangs with try to smuggle alcohol
Out of the airport and you can make a fortune right
They required Oregon to take inventory
3 *
Add a new account for every single bottle
If he actually dropped or misplaced
Single bottle he would have to pay all the tax
And this was
Within just 6 months Oregon had to
Band the store
Because all of these other manufacturers wanted their products
In there too
I mean
This is a captive Market of
Rich people
On vacation
In came the Leica cameras and the Omega
Watches even relatively inexpensive products discovered that they could get some of that airport
Glamour
I just getting placed between the Chanel Number 5 and the cuckoo clocks
At least that's what mr. tobler of Switzerland thought
Mr tobler was there with a real person
Theodor tobler Theodor tobler
Coup
Create the chocolate bar
Not just any chocolate bar
The Toblerone
A triangular prism of delicious
It was sold in that very first Shannon Duty
Freeshop
Tom Armitage is an executive with Mondelez International which owns total
The word comes from the combination of alleles is
Sonic tobler with the Italian word
Which means
It's kind of like that
You got that loud
Golden Nugget
Duty-free with
Huge break for the chocolate bar
Pictures of odd
Because there aren't really heavy duties and taxes
Chocolate not like alcohol
But
It did fit the duty-free aesthetic
It was kind
Weird fancy looking
Get you could
Hyatt with leftover change in your pocket from what you do
Spend on that Swiss watch
It would take a few more years for Toblerone in the duty-free concept to spread worldwide
All these International delegations would visit Oregon shop
And they saw how much you
He was making and I thought
Wait a minute anyone could do this
Amsterdam open II duty-free shop in the world and their airport in night
57 in 90
A private company
DFS
Open the first duty-free shop in the United
Red States
Why
Come Armitage the Toblerone guy says
But the numbers just
Took off from there
Duty-free stores will do
Do 70 billion dollars
Worth of business
Justice
5 billion of that is candy
And Tom will give you the chocolate stats
All day long
Euphotic beauty4u to Country
It would be the 9th
Biggest
Chocolate Market
In the world
Wow
Okay the 9th biggest chocolate monkey
In the world
Effectively
Just
Just behind friends and just ahead of India
The more people buy chocolate in duty free
Send buy chocolate in India
By value
These days Toblerone make special chocolate bars specifically designed for.
Actually if you think about it
The perfect place for test marketing and data
It's the one kind of store will you know which customers will show up
When
So if the flight from Paris to New York JFK
Takes off at 1:28 p.m.
Then the duty-free store is filled with Americans
Right at noon
And you can test new products
IDOC
Chocolate Toblerone milk chocolate Toblerone
Crunchy almond Toblerone
Temple Run
Messaging for example on the Toblerone fleas
What is the message that I forgot to
To get you a gift in Paris at the airport
He would say for example I love you thinking of you
The duty-free store concert
The idea behind it became so big
So powerful in marketing
The people sort of forgot about that original duty-free shop
In the Shannon Airport
And once long-range passenger Jets were invented
Not as many people needed to stop over in rural Ireland
For an Irish coffee
And because Brendan O'Regan didn't try to own the concept
Sadly did not become a duty-free billionaire
But other businessmen would
But you know
O'Regan
Remained
Hero
Of Ireland
He helped set up Textra manufacturing Zone
He became obsessed with the way that trade could help
World Peace
Any set of all of these to a piece exchanges
It's between the Republic of Ireland
And Northern Ireland
The people say we're really instrumental in
Creating the peace process
Brian O'Connell has just published a new biography
City of Brandon over
And so
She's a little biased
IPad but
She believes that
First little store in
The airport
Change the world
If he hadn't.
There would be no airport duty free business of the world it wouldn't ever
Taking off in my opinion
Really Bianca Bethune doing favors for
Wealthy people are traveling
Would have been a big factor
When you put it that way
You have shops at airport
But did you see free industry
Would not have developed
It was o'regan's gift
To all of us trap
But exactly how generous a gift was it
Will have the answer
After the break
Support also comes from fidelity
As a Fidelity Wealth Management
You get a dedicated advisor
The help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact
Taxes and make clear recommendations for your full Financial
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
What does it take to start something from nothing and what does it take to actually
He killed it
Every week of how I built this
Speak with Founders behind some of the most
Hiring companies in the world
Find it on NPR one or wherever you get your podcast
That was the history of duty-free but now the psychology
Duty-free because
When I walk through these places in airport there's a strange feeling that comes over me
I feel like I'm part of this exclusive clock and I'm just paid hundreds of dollars for ticket
I presented my passport
People with guns Guardian
And I walkthrough
It's soap
It's filled with all these vices
Cigarette
Alcohol
So many scotches
So many statues and whiskey
And also
A little bored
So it's basically the classic setup to spend
Too much money
By Design
Play
We just tried to find a definitive study to find out how much of a break you're really getting a duty free
Yes there are no taxes
But
You have to pay for all this very expensive airport retail
So it's almost impossible to
Figure out the bottom line
Every duty free store has
Different prices
Different exchange rate
A tax break depends on how much tax
You usually pay back at home
So I try to get at least some anecdotal
I was traveling with my family through the Milan airport in Italy
And my daughter Elsa and I spent
An hour
Logging all the time
Here's a carton of Camel cigarettes
39.5 Euro
VSOP
48.5 Euro
Jameson for your deal
17 Euro 18.2 Euro
U-Save 7.8 Euro
And what was your verdict on duty free
It depends
I know that is not the answer you want to hear I will tell you that tax-free cigarettes
Are criminal cheap
Under $5 a pack and they're almost three times.
Here in York City
So
If you want cigarettes
Buy cigarettes in
Other deals
Are harder to find
My daughter Kelsey is a expert in makeup
Okay so
Giorgio Armani
Luminous silk Foundation
Natural silky lightweight fluid
Really expensive Foundation
That's still not that much it's so expensive
No that's just the display one this is the
When you buy I would never pay that much
But I checked your New York
And
Not the worst
Price for Giorgio Armani so not to buy
But when it comes to alcohol there is no log
American whiskeys in Milan
Are 2/3 the price of what you would pay here in the United States
Even though they ship it all the way to Milan. All the way back true
But Courvoisier
From France next door to Italy
What's more expensive in the duty-free
This is here in New York
And toblerones
I hate to disappoint you or almost double
The US price
If we aren't always getting a
Steel on products
And the governments are losing out on Tagged
Tax revenue then what's the point
What is my Siri
On this
If they let you know when
Ireland first started duty-free was this
True bargain
And Ireland got all these benefits from the ex
Detroit business
But then what happens is this race to the bottom every other airports starts to offer the exact same time
Brakes just to come
And then once everyone has a duty
Free shopping there's pressure just to make your Airport
Duty-free shop
Bigger brighter and fancier exactly everyone ends up with this one
Expensive shopping mall and somewhere in all of this the tax break concept
Just sort of gets
Lost
Prices start to stick back up because
Who can really tell
It's only the people making the money or not
The Travelers but the shop
Sups
Any airports
Which you'll notice are now redesigning themselves
To provide even more space for duty free
Okay cosmopolitan's if you spot a glitch in the international trade system
Hear about it
We are at Planet Money in the UK
Places and Planet Money
Npr.org on email are special to all of our Aussie listeners I will be heading out.
Audiocraft podcast Festival in Sydney Australia
June 2nd
And third they have a great lineup
Stop on by
And say hi Today Show was produced by Sally Helm and Megan tan
Our editor is Brian Hurst at
And Alex goldmark is our supervising producer
I'm turned up and I'm Robert Smith thanks for listening
Go to bring one of your friends next salami