Support for NPR and the following message
Which come from WWE
Publishers of people power and profit
Progressive capitalism or an age of discontent
By Nobel prize-winning economist
Joseph E stiglitz
Oliver below is a journalist
To write a lot about financial
Talk rhyme
How many years he worked in Eastern Europe
And in 2014 he was in Ukraine
And Ukraine was in bad shape
Ukraine music
Pomsky
You know it was in a mess of the roads were falling apart though
The government was terribly got to pay bribes to get anything done that
Children can get the medicines they needed and it was awful
It was awful but it was also interest
Oliver is fascinated by the countries that make up the former Soviet Union
Like Ukraine
Since the end of the Cold War Ukraine is always sort of had one foot in Europe and one foot in Russia
And then in 2013/2014 Ukraine's president a man named Viktor Yanukovych
Decided to move
Both feet
Toward Russia
His government suspended a plan to sign this
Trade deal with the European Union
Which would ideally have brought open markets and transparency he said no
We want more trade with Russia
And it's
Oligarchs
Incorruption
This is a small group of intellectuals
Will Furious
The other night and they wanted
Protested
The princess continued and then the government responded in very heavy-handed way
Tomorrow People cast
This expression of Rage
The presence of just have to run away
Paisley deep timor-leste went away and the clothes he was wearing
He did bring his hand luggage
But when Yanukovych got on his helicopter and bounced to Russia
Everyone including Oliver was able to get this rear window into how he been living
Because it's houses were just left open left there for anyone to see
So Oliver go see Anna Kovach is Palace on the outskirts of
Kiev I woke up to this fences it's an ordinary
Green fence right to green fence but
It could be around 2 I mean it simple dump or something
And I won't screw this
Gateway pics my card into the
A Wonderland
Unfinished wooden wreath
Ukrainian suburb what does potholes in the roads in the
And the tablet to run down and
Yeah the bus is a
Third-hand from Pingree
And suddenly
Through this gate in the fence of entertaining tale of the universe where everything is brilliant so that Golf Course ever
Enclosure for shooting animals
You're a wild goose people Stop & Shop
There was a ton of Spanish galleon
Biltong
The side of the river
Look up Pirates
Yeah like a pirate ship sort of thing we didn't have an actual Pirate Flag but that's what it looked like and then
That was his Palace
Log Cabin
But five stories high
The amount of money that have been spent on this
It was absolutely extraordinary
Yanukovych should go away in his helicopter in just had it off
And left it behind
It was magical
In a
Lumos elucidatory while peeing in a dream
The joy of Discovery post-revolution retirement it was no one to stop you doing this if you were curious
Then
You just carried on and you just looked and poked around and one side
It is Palace I kind of got the bug out of other places
Those other places were also in Ukraine and so Oliver start
Traveling around
And look at
And along the way he goes from marveling
At what he's seeing to be
Really
Really angry
Ukrainians are poor the country is a mess
And that is what's on his mind when Oliver and his friend Anton walking to yanukovych's
Everything was exactly how we left it near the heated massage table
Sooner a plunge pool
Everything that the loan to perfectly mode
Absolutely surreal
In the bathroom
Opposite the toilet sitting down heart was a really big television
So obviously you know if it'd been in bed watching a TV show and then needed to go to the Loo it
Turn if across and Just Dance continue watching it in the toilet and I've never seen anything
That was the moment that made me really realize how a pulling this man has been
And I said to Anton how did you not stop him
And I'm telling you is it polite guy but but you know passion about me some Splendid at me really
How do you say we didn't know we couldn't have known
Because if you look it up pick it up this Palace
It isn't even in Ukraine look it up it's in English
What are the three main and you look it up look it up
I went in and I did look it up on in the land registry
The area of Lima sewing by Ukrainian
I'm not Ukrainian company was owned by British
The British company was owned by another company and that was his company was owned by the foundation in Liechtenstein
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Noel King
Moneyland
Wife thieves and Crooks now rule the world and how to take it back
We see the world in terms of country
That makes sense trade happens between Sovereign countries
Soda trade Wars
Countries have their own currencies
All of this is obvious
But Oliver argues there's a kind of upside down
A shadow economy just under the surface
We're money
Stolen money dirty money
Is Vanishing into dark
No One taxes that money no one regulates it
No one can even count
Sometimes money from that Dark World bubbles up into our world
A 90 million-dollar Penthouse that no one is living in
Stupidly big yacht
And you can make fun of it but Oliver thinks it's dangerous
Is that dark economy gets bigger
It starts to erode
Countries
It starts to suck the life
A democracy
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Should come from mizanin
Mizzen & Main dress shirt
Guitar made with
Performance Fabrics
Designed to look great all day
With the minimum
There moisture
Wrinkle resist
And machine wash
So they don't require ironing
Or dry
Check out their gift
Where the guy on your lip
Who is always on the
Head to mizzen & Main.
Mizzen & Main
Look great
Longer use code nprha
How to receive $10
Where's off your dress shirt
So my first question to Oliver
Am I not likely to get to moneyland anytime soon know how much NPR pays its journalists
I suspect
Well I fear that that you're going to have to work on your kleptocracy skills
If you want
Up to it to gain citizenship of money
But Oliver decided standing there in that logic that he was going to try to get
Somaliland
And he got a lucky break
In Ukraine the door into money Land Act
Accidentally opened up just across
Because on his way out
Ukraine president Viktor Yanukovych
Made a really stupid
Viktor Yanukovych runs away in a hurry
Embarrassed
Huge volume of incriminating documentation which Show how he structured will his essay
And how he's hitting his money and money land
And so that will not panic
Yeah the revolutionaries are coming it's going to be awful
And I just hope that sink but
Some of dead but not enough of them
So when the revolutionaries turn out that this artist Larry floating Bits of Paper bank statements just
Floating in the water
And so they died in in fishdom left again and dry them they draw the Minnesota
And this
Episode
I did not say that they had this soda priceless
Inside a documentation to show them
How his
Asatru structure how the money flows what's you know who it's been paying off
And all that it yeah it was
It it was a it was helping Crack the Code of
You have been doing intensive how we lose it
To Country Oliver starts looking into how yanukovych's money is moving around the world and keeps remembering what he
His friend Anton told
You know this building is not in Ukraine
Leaving will then where is it
So he looks up the company that owns the land
And that the lodge sits on
Any fines in address
It is not in Ukraine
It's in London
29 Harley
It turned out Yanukovych run
It's two companies that use
That particular building as their address
And Oliver thinks
This is it
He has seen money land on paper
And now he's got a physical address but he can visit
It's just in central London it's very easy to get to
Just up from Oxford Street
The big shopping center
The house is a kind of pit at match that's okay to leave a goatee that separately built but they're very lovely
Imprinted on Holly Street it's good.
Stained wooden front doors cut like a kind of ballast right at the federal level and then up at the top and other one and I knocked on the door
I'm dumb young man opened it and looked at me so disapprovingly in and I'll shoot me into a conference room this is very boring
Conference room
Anime Young
Lady came out
I'm going to chat and she said I'm so you can have to email me the question
Because being a bit distrustful Journal
And that was the last I heard of her
That was it he was spoiled
But anyway he was able to go online and find out a little bit about this
It has an official name is
Cold formation
No more than 2,000 companies Bay seven in a relatively
1 houses small house
In that house
Was a company that creates
Companies
In the past 10 years hundreds of thousands of companies
Have been created out of this one house
It costs little is
20 lb to get a company started in the UK that's about $26
Viktor Yanukovych has two companies were called
Steward Partners in Blytheville
Let me ask you what do those companies actually do with anybody working for astute or 4
Why did they have employees did they have a
Add icy accountant or bookkeeper who is
Your funneling money like what
What were those company
Those companies did nothing
Nautilus companies just existed
To own property on his behalf
And it's not just company Mills in London
Entire countries are doing this
Remember those documents that were thrown in the lake and then dried out in the sauna
Throughout those documents there was one place that
Kept coming up
The island of Nevis
Tilt that was Oliver's next stop
Nevis island in the Caribbean
I'm which is a sort of jurisdiction size version of the
House of Harley Street
It exists to provide people with anonymity
The laws were written for it by a group of American lawyers
He wanted
Essentially
To make it easier for people who have been sued or who would divorcing that wives to 2
2 hydroxy
Oliver has some specific addresses on need
So he gets on the boat and go slow
I'm actually hard to find them
But they're all in an area about the size of a football pitch
I got off the Dyson the first
Hocus Pocus
Is directly opposite me
And then there's another one
I'm jealous. Wait another 100 yards in the other direction.
It's absolutely tiny
Reese real
Because
All of these dresses in my head were
Like cuddle mcmafia addresses
Hideout to the mafia and then.
Custody plan office block
Fox Weather with a couple of receptionist
I went all the way there
And essentially have to serve
Couple of hours wandering around all done old
Came that do intend to knocking on doors and I just ended up sitting in a bar on the beach and ghetto eating fly fishing
Drinking beer
When you were in Nevis
Did anyone tell you anything worthwhile
I had this extraordinary encounter with the regulator
Because he's essentially in charge of checking the Integrity of
The financial system
And
It was one of the most extraordinary interviews I've ever done in my life I mean
She just lost me
From beginning to end
I didn't mean that. You didn't see
Maybe he didn't see the humor in it but here's an argument in their favor
Maybe it was funny because he was acting like a detective on the trail of
Something that is
A normal totally legal way of doing business
It would be like if you went into a night
And you said
I travelled across the world
I took a boat to get here
Are you people really just openly selling furniture
They would laugh in your face
So from there he's kind of stuck no one in any of these places is going to give him any information
But even though the money in moneyland is hidden
Somebody's going to start
Bubbling up in various
Specifically
The really
Extraordinary thing is where the money gets spent is where ends up and where ends up is overwhelmingly and under the New York it's like the outside
I doubt he's losing
Into our world
You want to put your money somewhere weather
This lovely all calories great restaurants
Georgia Parkson
New York
So it's it's the desert of the really uncomfortable truth
At the Hop
This whole episode
Is the fact that we criticize you know
At the Marshall Islands
Juanita Solis revolve show me pom Fringe destinations for
Enabling fraud and Theft
Which they are enabling
Prudent
But it's where the money ends up it's important to the money ends up in in London New York Miami
Los Angeles
Expensify.
Annie's get some things that have been really hard to
Explain
Like how is he
Former presidential campaign chairman
Who's done some Consulting work in Ukraine
Able to buy millions of dollars of rug
Send suits and a townhouse in
I'm talking of course about Palmetto
I think the really interesting thing about Paul manafort
Is the fact that he did
Exactly the same tricks
As the ukrainians did
If you look at the indictment I love
Paul manafort indictment I practically have
You're stuck on my wall
It's so wonderfully
4 nut
The structures that he used
To move his money through we had companies in Cyprus you had company a company in the UK
Notification on Holly Street Priscilla company in the UK
He had a company's in the Caribbean is it
The Grenadines he had a whole string of LLCs in in the US
The tricks he was using what exactly the same tricks
Is being used by
Ukrainian
Cat scratch that yanukovych's Indiana Convention
Just friends
How do I think
What's really interesting about
Manifold is doing is it shows that this is not a crime of culture
This is a crime of opportunity
It an American
Youku
Essentially see his way to
Don't jinx greasy touching taxes
You're keeping money in the same way
Didn't I see you crying and it was doing it typically cut
Because he could
And that's just it it's that easy
And it is also easy to not think
Too much about this
But Oliver is
Obsessed
Because remember he spent years working in Eastern Europe
In Russia and you
Ukraine
And Kyrgyzstan and Azerbaijan and
Tajikistan
And he's learned that when a country's money is Vanishing down the drain
And I can't be
We found ortak
Store even counted
There is something very big at
Mistake we need to deal with this issue if democracy is to have a future
If some people cannot pronounce whole
That legislative and Taxation prices
And that is a threat
Democracy
Because otherwise you end up in a situation
What you doing Russia
Where
More than half of all the money in Russia resigned offshore it's in Manila
52 PSI
Of the household wealth
So it's 52
Send 52%. Money is essentially no longer subject to the to the decisions of the Russian government
Now you can understand why
If you were rushing the wealthy Russian you might not want your money to be subject to the decisions of the Russian
Yeah
Hopelessly you can put that's very bad for democracy or any chance of democratic transformation
It's important for democracy that money can be tax
Because that's how democracies found himself
Taxes are the price we pay for civilization
That figure by the way 52% of Russian money is offshore
That's an estimate from The Economist Gabriel zucman who studies tax Havens
So big
What are the
Well
I mean the real Ethiopia state
The thing that we will need to do
Is find a way to stop
I'm hiding
Dialysis
We need transparency Battleship so shall company doesn't work anymore
It's a very important principle because
Even the FBI
Find the product
Could find out who owns a company in Delaware
You left alone in the investigator
Authorities in inside out
And inside it makes it very easy just hide your identity behind a Delaware company and and you and your home free
You're that should stop
When Oliver was chasing this money he talked to fbih
Santa law enforcement officials who are working this be
And it is maddening
Trying to unpack that traded companies you have to go to every single one of those country
To find out who owns the company
And then once you found out that actually has just done somewhere else
You have to go to another country if I know who I am
Eventually you will end up possibly
Finding out who ends up but yes would have come by and by that sector I would have happily moved somewhere else with my soupy outside
Yeah it is
It's become incredibly easy
To steal money and hide
End
Then enjoy it
Suspended of course there is one big problem
A lot of people and a lot of places are making a good living catering to money land or being part of it
The problem is
How do you persuade Delaware
When the Delaware state budget is is heavily dependent on Incorporation
How do you persuade South Dakota
Did they should stop
Party pitabilities behind trusts
When is South Dakota trust Industries absolutely blooming
I mean not see that's the argument over
For this isn't it I mean
Is economy
Estates would say
Plenty of people who are not
Are starting
Funny people have legitimate reason
Thanks for wanting to
Keep their wealth
Are using RC
Services are setting up
And so what are you doing
But we need to say yes if you have a legitimate reason to own your property honestly that should be allowed for everyone
Illegitimate reason like
You live in a really unstable country
You don't want people to know how much money you have because somebody might kidnap your kids and hold them for ransom
In the courts are usually decide you pass a law that says you know these are the people who have the right to anonymity people who have a legitimate fear
Security and that you got you done
I'm very straightforward
But the problem is if you were to
Positive words that make sure you'll eventually gassing the state budget of evil
Jurisdictions in countries all over the world by satellite
It what do they do to make up the shortfall that which is the money that made from incorporating
Companies for people who want anonymity and what are you do
I'm it it's it difficult but we absolutely have
To do this because
This money is
Poisoning the world
We don't know an economist will cop to this
How much of this money there is
An educated estimate around 8
Percent of all the money in the world
Is in that upside down
No taxes being paid no names attached
Just waiting to come up to the surface and
Buy more stuff
Oliver tells this story
About walking around his neighborhood
Put in London
The shop where he buys his coffee every morning
That building is owned in the Bahama
The building where he gets his haircut
Is owned in Gibraltar
Is a building site he passes when he walks to the train
That is owned in the Isle of Man
Any wonders who owns those buildings
And he wonders if the money that bought them should be paying for roads or hospitals in some other country
But the odds are Oliver like the rest of us
Won't ever figure it out
Support for this podcast
In the following
Message come from mizzenandmain
Mizzen & Main dress
Shirts are made with performance Fabrics designed to look great all day
With minimal man
There moisture
Wrinkle resistant
And machine washable
So they don't require ironing
Or dry clean
Check out there gif
Lights for the guy on your list
Who is always on the move
Head to visit in Maine.
Mizzen & Main
Look great
Longer
Use code NPR a check
To receive
$10 off your dress shirt
Special thanks to Gabriel the book The Hidden Wealth of Nations
Today's episode was produced by Alexi Horowitz Ghazi or editor is Brian first at and are supervising producer
Greaser is Alex Goldman
Samuel King
Thanks for listening
Your book has not been published in the US
Will be next
Spring but you haven't published in the UK
You have fifteen Amazon reviews and all of them are five stars and all of them are people who wrote like
Relatively long reviews saying how much
They liked this book
Is that your friends and family
I'm actually no I'm one of them is
That's the guy who's married to
School for my wife
And I think you know I haven't looked in the mall like
You know I only opposed to Unlimited in in financial instruments.