Support for this podcast in the following message come from NCR who believes in small businesses
That's why they build NCR silver
Worthington point-of-sale NCR silver deliveries big Enterprise management tools built for small business owners
Visit ncr.com silver
Hey before we start Today's Show we have a quick favor to ask we've got a survey going right now
We want to know about
We want to know what you like about Planet Money what you want us to change
It should take about 10 minutes
And you can find it at the following link
Npr.org
Slash
Planet Money
Survey
Thanks
Monday around Thanksgiving of
Sil Turner noticed it
It seems like suddenly everybody was talking about
He thinks himself
I thought about that in Forever
I definitely used to have some of the
It's Amigos online
And holy crap
The price of Bitcoin
Was up to
Hen
Thousand
Dollars
Hey cell
Hey
It's 3 days later it's a Saturday still at his house outside of Atlanta and he's starting to get in
Because
The price of Bitcoin is now up to 11000
Dollars
Still wants to find his Bitcoin
And he says there's like a chance
Maybe they're in his attic
On an old hard drive
In-N-Out
Computer
But I'm 900 miles away I can't get there to search
Testing 3 2 1
Who lives closer to self and ask her can you please drive over there as soon as possible and hopefully
We can record the moment sill Turner
Find a fortune
There's nothing to do right now
So
You want me to just go straight up to the Attic
Yeah I mean I guess so kind of over here for right yeah
We'll go up the attic now
Tasneem sent me pictures of seal throughout this process and he's got to
A big bushy beard
He's wearing a black
T-shirt with a picture of a rainbow colored
Astronaut
Nestle can't remember exactly how many bit
Coins he has
Maybe one and a half
And they were worthless when he got them but
Today
They are worth tens of thousands of dollars
Alright so
Yeah are you in the Attic yeah we are in the Attic luckily it's not super hot
What kind of nervous for you man this is the biggest sum of money I've ever been hunting for a little nervous
I can't believe this
Having all right
So
Sing me a picture of seals attic
Hoarder
But there does appear to be about a waist-high layer
Of all kinds of stuff
So probably
So let's dig in let's do this
Yeah yeah we can start digging in
Think
All right there's like a broken fog machine baby
TVs that are identical Goldfish crackers box hello and welcome
Planet Money I'm Kenny Malone and we are in the midst of a Bitcoin Mania the digital currency that owned
Only used to be a big deal in small Circles of the perriand technophiles and Anarchist headaches
Exploded over the last year this has created the class of overnight Bitcoin millionaires
If you happen to know where your Bitcoin
Today on the show
How to lose a digital Fortune
And maybe
How to find
I mean there's a lot of empty boxes to stay on the line with you while you clean out your whole addict
This message comes from NPR sponsor game Bridge
The Bold way to steady growth
People often think of nobodies are too conservative to complex or only for retirees but annuities can
Ambius smart way to hedge Market risk and earn guaranteed returns
Game Bridge aims to change the game by offering simplified annuities in a Sleek digital experience that rep
Places fine print and phone tag
Lights with clear conditions and a direct
Loafy model
Learn more at gamebridge. Life / NPR
Cambridge is not available in all states
Stepped on something still digging through his Attic in Georgia
Frisbee
So is a software developer but like the rest of us he doesn't really understand how Bitcoin
You heard about it right when it launched in
In 2009
Figured I can't wait to have some of this stuff
It was worth pennies
He treated it like
Loose change
Never kept track didn't really know how many
She had and then eventually
Let it fall between the
Virtual couch
Or whatever all right so I think it's one of these computers inside of computer up
Is an old hard drive
With an old file
Call Bitcoin
Coin wallet
That would give him access to his bit
What you would then sell immediately
Make something like $25,000
And then probably put that in
College fund
For his one-year-old son
We start taking these computers
I think we should take a hard drive out of this one anyway just
In case but I don't think
Pretty sure that is not the right hard drive
Pride open the second computer
Okay go go there is a hard drive
Oh my goodness
Oh my God
Double chances are really
Did not expect to see hard drive
I'm here to be honest what did you think it happened
My thought was
I took the hard drive
Out of this one and I think I really do think it is this hard drive this one terabyte
Oh man I just actually really shocking to me
Because I actually did not think the
This hard drive is going to be in here I mean should we just checked should we just checked that one now
Yeah let's look at the
Seal head back downstairs with a hard drive
Baby wakes up hey buddy old hard drive
And so is worried that he erased this at some point and use it for video game
What
He's hoping
Searching for any sign of this wallet file
Alright so
I got to wear
I believe this
Would be
There is a Bitcoin
Directory
In here where it should be
Or if it's in there
There's stuff in here
There's a wallet
There's a wallet and there's blocked okay I don't know what this means but I'm going to copy this out to my hard drive
Seals pretty shirt
And find out how much Bitcoin is on there
He explains that he needs to wait
Well another piece of software downloads
The entire history
Of every single Bitcoin transaction
In the world
Onto his home computer
It is going to take
Hours
And unfortunately there's just no way to steam and Ike
Stick around for that
But how are you feeling right now like okay so what I'm feeling right now is my my hands are very sweaty
I'm just kind of I'm kind of
Amazing
They looking for the
Pennies in the couch cushions though that part of it I think I found it but it's encrusted with some kind of like I like I smell
Beer in the couch
I like this thing is kind of stuck there and I don't know how to get
Get it off without ruining it yet
So I think what we should do like when it's ready I think you and your wife should
Just record yourselves figuring out how much is in there okay is that sounds good idea
So while still is waiting to learn his bit
I started to get curious about how many sill Turner's are out there in the
And the first thing that comes up when you search
Locbit
Is the story
Of James Howells
It was the summer you were working through the stuff in your office and he found the hard drive why did you throw it out
I haven't used it for 3 years
This is a BBC interview with
James
She threw away a hard drive
With 7 and 1/2 million dollars worth of
In fact this interview
Is at the landfill where he
He thinks the hard drive may have wound.
Yesterday they basically told me that anything that goes into the household scrap bin is compressed on
And buried by the way this interview
It's from 2013 a lot has happened since
More legitimate vendors start accepting Bitcoin Big Time investors started trading at
And as more and more people saw Bitcoin as a way to make money
The price has Skyrocket
Those bitcoin's James Howells lost
Are now worth more than a hundred million
James I'm sure there's an awful lot of people feeling for you right now how do you feel sticky
Absolutely devastated as you can imagine
I just wish I could go back in time and
I'm not so that joy joy
Lost Bitcoin
Has been this legendary thing within the bit
Community
It's also been kind of anecdote
I wanted to get a sense of the actual scale of
And of course there were Economist already on this Quest
Are you outside I guess I didn't ask if you either do our individual Bitcoin
A very small amount of
I was writing a paper in 2012 I think on bitcoin I bought a couple
Also very small amount but
So is it my turn
Nor did I take it seriously at any point until
About three way
Weeks ago this is Kimberly grauer and Jonathan Levine
Kimberly is senior Economist of a company called chainalysis Jonathan is a co-founder
The company makes software that can
Can dissect Bitcoin transactions
Despot money laundering
Detect illicit Behavior but also just to learn about
Bitcoin
What what do people actually say Bitcoin Bitcoins you can have Bitcoins on bitcoin is by the currency in
Okay
To understand how the James Howells and the sill Turner's of the world
Can lose or nearly low
Whois Bitcoin
We need to clear up a common misconception that
I totally did not understand either
There are no big
Which I know. Digital.
Real but no
No no
There are not even digital things
Been traded back and forth
With unique serial numbers are
That is not how the system
Yeah yeah
So if I send you Bitcoins
I sent Bitcoin to your account on the Bitcoin blockchain
Blockchain
Big word sherbet
Here is very non-technical way of understanding what it
Imagine with me if you will
A massive
Auditorium
Filled
With Bitcoin book
That Jonathan wants to send me one bit
She walks on stage
In front of all these bookkeeper
Step Up 2
And he's like
Hello entire Bitcoin universe
Is all of your book show
I Jonathan
Have 3 Bitcoins
To my name of course it would
Not be named Olivia
Anonymize account number I would like everyone here to know
Did I am giving
1 Bitcoin
To Kenny after Jonathan says this all of these virtual Ledger keeper
Scribble this transaction down
Duct one Bitcoin from Jonathan's account increase Kenny's account by one
And that
Is a Bitcoin transaction
Nothing is really transferred
It's more like an instantaneous
Adjustment
Across a whole bunch
When people talk about the blockchain
They're talking about this system
Weather is no Central Booking
And here's we're losing Bitcoin
It's interesting because
Bitcoin never disappears
All of those computers keeping all of those books
All show that my account now has one Bitcoin the one that Jonathan gay
However
If I lose the key to that account
There is no customer service line
Call there's no
Bank I can plead
There's exactly one way into this virtual vault
And it is with
My private
What is a private key look like
I'm it's a string of letters and numbers that's pretty long a
Can you give me an example
B987 3D 7c 6870 c0
B6
Aa5778
Skip 64 randomly
Generated numbers and letters this
Is on for a while 33262
Virtually impossible to remember
And if you lose this key and never find again
The Bitcoins inside your virtual Vault will sit there for
So when
We talked about lost Bitcoin
Coin what we really mean is
Eternally Frozen
Bitcoin account
Okay so now we know how
When transactions are
I recorded we know about the private key and how you can lose Bitcoin
The next big question
Is how much Bitcoin
Is lost forever
Listen to up on my plate on my first day senior Economist at chainalysis
We are sitting around brainstorming some of the most interesting economic questions that we could tackle
And this was
Something that came up right away
Bitcoin is not
Like other currency
There's no
Government that is going to just print more of it
The system was created so that
For the rest of time there will be a
Finite amount
We even know this number it's about
21 million Bitcoin
And people are now buying and selling Bitcoin
Because it has this scarce Resource Property
But we don't know exactly how scarce
Because some of those 21 million Bitcoins are already lost
Forever
In a garbage dump
So that's why Kimberly
Analysis and really anyone even thinking about
Bitcoin is interested in this question
Kimberly was able to work some fancy Analytics
And identify millions and millions of Bitcoins no one has touched
In a long time
Baidu.com
There are two main reasons those may have gone on to
The first
Is it maybe
The owners of those coins are just
Really Savvy investors they
Why didn't early and they are still holding on waiting for the right time to sell
These are essentially if you're in the know in the Bitcoin Community they're called toddlers
Hodl
Earth it's an acronym for hold on for dear life hold on for dear life coins
That is an investment strategy where bottle is like
Early adopter
Going to believe the sky is the limit
Yes the coins you bought
For two cents are now worth $15,000 but
Hold on for dear life
Because remember
You believe they could be worth
50 or even $100,000
So some percentage of those out of circulation coins
The Kimberly identified
Are being
Hodl what is the other chunk then
Well I check if those are going to be lost
What do the name for those for those people
I don't have a name for those people I'm going to suggest
Loser
Losers. Bad meme
What about ogwen
Which stands for
Oh God
Where is my Bitcoin
Ogwen
Yeah it's not
That catchy of a word
Toddler is not
I like it okay
We're all in the same picture
Yeah I did
Kimberly was able to estimate
Of that finite chunk of Bitcoin
Remember to only ever be 21 million of them
There is a
Painful amount
Locked away forever
Soda Springs AR grand total 2
Between
2.7 and 3.7 million lost Bitcoins
I feel like we should just let that sit for a second
At current prices that's more than 40
Billion dollars
A forever sunken
In on one hand
It shows the most obvious problem
With a ruthlessly decentralize money
There's no kitty
There's no option if you lose your private key
You lose your Bitcoin
In a centralized system in if you had a sack of u.s. dollars and they caught fire
The US government has an office that will
Look at your case maybe even give you a new money we did a whole episode
On the other hand
All of this lost Bitcoin illustrates
Something like paradoxical almost about
Think of it as it's a femoral thing
That can just disappear
But it's there forever
And no one's making new Bitcoin is only going to be 21 million estimated Bitcoin in
The history of the stuff
All of this lost Bitcoin
Is reminder that
This
Is digital yes
And you could lose it easily yes
But it is truly
Is scarce
Digital
Resource
Whatever that mean
The other thing to note Kim says
Is it the vast majority of these lost coins were lost in the early years of Bitcoin
When the coins were essentially
Worthless
People going forward
Probably won't be losing at such a high rate probably most of the losing his
Already happened
Because
Who cares about letting
A penny fall through the couch cushions
But if you happen to know that it's a
Very rare very expensive penny worth $17,000 you're probably going to
Take better care of it
Exactly
Even if Bitcoin goes back down to pennies
I think people will be more care
About their keys
Because I know one day
It could be this
All right so I believe
This is probably done this is a recording seal Turner eventually sent
So we can see what
How much Bitcoin is in this wallet
My baby is crying, he and his wife Jackie or sitting next
Computer sales got his digital wallet he's got his private
Keep and for the first time in nearly a decade
He is able to open up his
Virtual Bitcoin fault
Sigalert
Excited
Leaving is going to be
Nothing
Alright let's see
Point
I think
Oh wait
I sent .02 from this
To where
I don't know
What is
Dawning on sale
Is it he is Bitcoin
Vault
Is
Not only is it empty
He can check the history and he can see
The dis is
Clearly the wrong
Account
She must have liked setup
A second account of test account
My friend must have transferred him a little bit coin and instill transferred it right back
I don't know how this works
This must be my other wallet
Oh man
She's continued
You know what to do now
Alright well
This is where we're at right now
After the break
We get porcile Turner
Some professional help
Support for this podcast
And the following message come from State Farm
Who's agents know that your car and home are more than just big purchases
They're a big part of your life
You put the time into making them your own
So now it's time to protect
With your own personal State Farm agent
Not only do they truly get you
But they'll be there for you when you need
And went over 19,000 agents in neighborhoods across that us there could be one just around the corner
Moritz statefarm.com
Are 1-800 State Farm
State Farm
Here to help life
Go right
Can you guys hear that
Xidan
This is Kimberly and Jonathan from chainalysis
I got on the phone with them
And we called still turn case still yeah I've got
Jonathan and Kim on the line
Doing good
So we have gathered here today
To try and resurrect
Seals lost Bitcoin
And
I know we should say here that the chainalysis company does not want you to
Call them about your life
But
They are very smart and they're very kind
And they agreed
To hear porcile Turner story
And see if there was anything that can
Alright so
Probably 2009 or 2010 summer
So we tell them the whole story how he's been back into his attic
And there is not another hard drive is not another private
Keep a keen nose
There is another account with Bitcoins in it
So that's where I'm at
Okay
Yeah boy it's a real shame to hear but it wasn't the right hard drive
Unfortunately
Well we need to find the needle in the haystack is even like
A little bit of the
Chucky
What Jonathan is saying is the Bitcoin private keys
Are designed to be unguessable
Even by the most powerful
Computers that we have right
It still happened to write down part of his key at some point
There companies that will use that information
To help still
Break into his own account
The charge him a fee or ask for some of his Bitcoin
Stellar Bitcoin Bounty Hunter
The Alba Madonna
Is out there
But
You have to have some
Peace
Of your product
And at this point
Man probably forever
Cell disease
Unfortunately unfortunately contacts Leah help you out
I don't know what kind of
What kind of things do you say to somebody in Sims position
People that have
Lost Debit coins I say
I know this is going to be like my deathbed
Regret them like I should have backed up that wallet
Have you lost something that you need help finding love
Let us know about it Planet Money at npr.org
Instagram
Today's Show with produced by Nick fountain or senior producer is Alex goldmark or editor is Bryant
Urstadt special thanks this week to test me in shama for this amazing audio of seal Turner's hard drive boot
Booting up
And also an apology this week to Jonathan Levine MD
Olive Britton really for
Myturbotax
If you are looking for something to listen to right now we have a new show it's
Call the indicator from Planet Money Planet Money quick take on the news 5 days a week
Today's Show is about the underrated numbers in today's job for 4
The numbers you don't hear so much about
The tell us a lot
About what's going on in the job market
That's the indicator from Planet Money you can find it wherever you find your part
I'm Kenny Malone thanks