All right it is that time of your candy canes mistletoe
Public radio and we heard that there are people outside of our house
The people or is it asked you to
Money
We figured that if anybody knows how to raise money at them so we're going to go get
Down at that corner
Chaoyang park
Why we can't record in the park
We need a permit
Okay we're leaving
But I think I see the people with words
3D printer stopping quickly ask them
Yesco quick hi how you doing
We work with national public radio across the street
We're getting kicked out
Alert to supervisor
On behalf
A Planet Money t-shirt
Thrown out of Bryant Park
By the New York City Police
We're willing to go to Great Lengths to get you stories yes please support our efforts by going to donate. Npr.org
Splash Planet Money and just get whatever you want
Big small
Big prefers
We prefer big
That is donated npr.org Planet Money
Who's this number
It's probably the most important number in the world
This number determines how many people in the US have
Have a job
It has the power to wipe out our
Wings account
This delicate fussy little number is the inflation rate
A bunch of what the Federal Reserve does all day is
Try to get this number just right
And for the longest time
The Fed
Didn't want us to know what number they were targeting
But on January 25th
But then Fed chair Ben Bernanke
Hold Us
The committee judges that inflation at the rate of
2%
Ben Bernanke said the FED had in it
Explicit goal of
Keeping busy
Powerful number at
2 /
This was a huge shift in American economics
And we've actually talked about this one planet money but
Google we didn't know at the time was that this big bombshell announcement
With the end of a mud
Longer story that starts
On a tiny Island full of
Kiwis and Hobbit
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Karen deafening Sarah Gonzales today on the show
The real
Secret history of 2%
We take you on a trip around the world to just about the farthest place from the United States
And we find the true origin story behind the most important number in the world
And when we get back
Find out that we might have just spent the last 22 years
Targeting the wrong number
This message comes from NPR sponsors
Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one Platte
How to build an online presence
And run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR
To save 10% off
Off your first purchase
Have a website or domain
The whole reason Ben Bernanke told us that the US was
Targeting inflation
Was because
One guy in New Zealand
Decades earlier
Proven that sharing your economic secrets
A good thing
His name
Is Arthur Grimes
Arthur completely reimagined the role of central bankers
Change the way whole countries
Keep their economies
Stable
He's one of the most
Important economist
In the world
How do you think New zealanders View you
Mayport Naval Academy
That's one
Are there used to be the chief Economist and New Zealand Central Bank he is a current professor of Welby
Weight flake well-being like we're happy
Disease children smiling in Prague
Economic well-being and he's a jazz musician
Saxophone player tenor saxophone
Yeah NHL going to do I called you awfully
You like that his neck
You got to go.
So what else would we
For most of Arthur's life New Zealand had massive inflation
Richmond prices were going up
And everyone's money was
Losing value
This can happen when there's too much money floating around an economy and everyone tries to
Suspended on not enough
Stuff
And the government had tried everything
Thing to lower it
For nearly two decades
There were
Harley
Days Days the government didn't let you drive your car to try to stop gas prices
I'm going up
There's a Time the government banned businesses from Raising
Prices for a year
I finally they turn to Arthur they say
You're a smart economist
You go find a way to fix
Let's go see what other country
And around 9
Five nights
6 they sent Arthur on a
A trip around the world
When you're in a small country that's on the other side of the world from visually everywhere
It's just natural for us to actually see what other people do
How do other people do these things with a bunch of smart people in the US
UK Germany Canada
We all have different methods for controlling info
Some central banks have a monetary Supply Target witch
Just means they're capping how much money is
Is printed every year
Others have it
Unemployment Target
The perfect amount of people with jobs for the healthiest economy
And some have an interest rate target
They're trying to pin down what's the right interest rate for loans
But all these targets
Were aimed at
Keeping inflation low
There are three things
Why not just cut to the chase
Fixed I get the ultimate goal which is inflation
Happytime inflation-targeting
Inflation targeting
Set an ideal level of inflation and drive the economy toward that
Central Bank three years to develop
This whole new system
The people had talked about inflation targeting before right
It was only after that after you seen it done it that
That Tim was actually invented
You invented inflation-targeting
So the government says okay Central Bank give us a number so we can hold you accountable
Inflation is at 9% right now
What should we do
Arthur says I'm not going to give you a number I will give you a ring
022 by 92
0 to 2% inflation by 1990
This was the
Here's the thinking behind this
Aside from it being
Catchy
If you have 0% inflation that is
True absolute
Price to build
The price of carrots sugar your rent
Never change
If you have 1% inflation that means that the price of carrots
Goes up by 1%
But you're not
Skipping meals over this you just buy turnips instead of tariffs now 1% inflation doesn't affect your wealth
So Economist in New Zealand considered
1% inflation kind of like neutral in place
And then Arthur sink
We need some wiggle room and so he says let's give ourselves
Plus or minus 1 /
So that's how they got
0 to 2
But
They knew that reaching this target
Would be
Much easier said
What was that experience
Tips and advice and we'd all be brought up with
Double-digit inflation
Minos was considered
Extremely difficult
Get stupid
New Zealand was going to dramatically forced inflation down from 9% to under 2
And having low inflation like 2% that's good
But the process of
Bringing it down
That hurts people
It is a painful process
And if they were going to meet their target they needed someone who could say
I don't care what happens to people while we
Deflate
We're doing this and we're not looking back they chose a guy
Appropriately named Don
Brash
I don't hear
This is Don brash
I had to portray myself as someone who didn't give a fig
You had to present yourself as someone who didn't give a
Fig
That's what I said
This is for the American expression which is
More than you want to include
Done
Job was to
To force the inflation rate
He did it by restricting how much money regular Banks
Had in their vault
Which affects how much money everyone has
That was the easy part he literally just had to
Snap to make it happen
But that
Easy thing
What causes
Huge spike in unemployment
At the time inflation was really high
So people needed Highway jinx
Reese's just a break
I'm done is telling people those wage increases you need
They're going to make unemployment
Last longer but you can help shorten this pay
If you just believe me
We have a little faith start acting like inflation is already at 2% and we will get to 2%
Pastor he was basically Newzealand Smokey the Bear
Only you
Can prevent long-term unemployment
So you're going around New Zealand telling workers
Listen
I know that inflation is almost
6% right now
But trust me
I'm going to bring it down so just don't ask for a 6
Percent
Wage increase in your salary
That's what you're doing
That that's roughly what I'm doing and then you're also going to businesses in
Something business is
If we know the inflation rate is almost 6%
But we're going to bring it down to just don't charge more for your good
That's right that's right
But nobody
Employees
Keep asking for highways
Because even though
I believe they don't need them any
And companies are continuing to give them
Because the employees are demanding
And so companies now
Cannot afford to pay everyone at such high
So
They label
People off
More people off
Unemployment goes up past
11% one in nine people who wanted to work
Couldn't
Well it didn't look good at all and I love you for that very bad and I was just concerned about
Is anybody else believe it or not
When you have to be hopeful miserable so-and-so not to care
And it wasn't all on
The government was also announcing all kinds of other reforms
At the same time like they were privatizing public company
So there were a bunch of
And if New Zealand had some old
Stop the running the central bank they might have been like
Wow this is
Is getting really bad maybe we should
Stop where
Creating a terrible recession
But not
John
Don is like
Too bad we can't back out now even if it means
Will Cipher
People like
Sue Radford
Sue
Glad and unemployed workers
And they decided to rush
Dance Central
But which obviously expecting us so it was pretty easy we just ran through
Chase Bank
But it does have security because
Yeah cuz it was a bank the doors locked behind them
Sue hung up banners across the windows and sat on the floor of the main room
Waiting for Dawn
Until police dragged her out and throw her in a cell
What was the charge
Remember
Artist to look at my record for children live with me
I have an expensive record for projections
The next day's sugata
A phone call from Don Brash adhesive
I hit you came to visit Asia
Yesterday and I said yes and he said well
Courtyard to come and find out why you were purchased and why you walk
Depart the bank
Intoeing Watertown
To come
To Oakland
We're up at Edward was
They just wanted to convince Diane to
Ease up
A little bit
I was a co-parent
African babies
Living on welfare and trying to get a job at 5 I so did anything change after
Don Brash met with you
Of course not done with supposed to get inflation between
0 +
When to buy 1992
And sure enough we retrieved learning by Naughty to we actually achieved it by naughty one
Which of the Lodi then then plan
And there were people who said look
But getting there early
You have subject
To the real economy to more pressure than you needed to do
And it was
How did people feel about you in New Zealand
Vary greatly depending on
Known people hated him
Even though inflation went down unemployment was still high
Estate High
Even today people still have issues
Baton
Impart also because he said some controversial things about the indigenous population in New
But he did
Lower inflation in this new way that no one ever had
Before
And yes there were still problems but a
Economist understood the logic behind inflation
Marketing
And the world's biggest economies
They start following in this tiny countries with step
They announce inflation Target
Of Their Own
Canada first
UK the
Australia they all chose different ranges
Is and they all
Told their status
Is just a done did
But here in the United States
It went a little
What happened was
Really rather strange
This is Sebastian mallaby
She is the person who uncovered
The bizarre way that the
The feds settled on 2%
It happened at this one Central Bankers meeting
And we have prepared a dramatic Recreation of this meeting
We have the transcripts
Which we have slightly sweet For Your Entertainment
It is the summer of 1996
The FED is considering whether they should Target in place
Like all the other cool countries have
And Janet Yellen
A central bank Governor at the time says
Bringing inflation down
20% sounds good
2% very likely is a good idea
Not surely
And men being men sometimes were like
Enter meeting moves on and then later one guy goes
Maybe someone else already suggested this but I
We have the best IDE
Why don't we have a
2% Target
This is the most progress we've made in over a decade
And like every woman at
It's a meeting in their life Janet Yellen is probably
Sitting there thinking
I said that
Earlier
And then Alan Greenspan the Fed chair
At the time it's like
Weight Janet
You say that
That is what I say
But you've all been talking
This whole time that was
That's about 30 seconds they do consider a
Different inflation Target
What about zero
Let's do 2
Is Zero's basically two
This is of course a major economic.
Decision but after that Greenspan just says
Quote can we leave it at that
Let us now move on
It's almost like
They didn't come up with it this is Sebastian mallaby
The one who
Surface the trance
They just kind of
Landed on it
By some Quirk of how the conversation
I'm flattered I thought that was the most extraordinary way made this
Epochal decision
This decision was
Huge
And Alan Greenspan started getting nervous
So the next day he
Came back into the room and he said
That big thing that we decided yesterday
How about what's not telling you
He said
I will tell you that if
2% inflation figure
Get out of this
Run
It is going to create more problems for us than I think any of you
Mercante
So the US has this
Ballistic Target to devalue our currency by 2% every year
And they weren't telling us
And there was a second When Alan Greenspan thought
Is this
Fraud against the saving public
He said
You know if we have 2% is out Target we're centrally taking 2% of people's savings away
Every year
And she made this might come and he said that
We just have to make out dollar bills smaller and smaller every year
To reflect the loss of purchasing power
Okay so he's being tongue-in-cheek there but the point is
The US is
Keeping this
Secret
And Sebastian says
Doesn't make any sense
Because remember what we learned from New Zealand
Telling people that you're going to force him
Inflation down is
Heart of how you
You achieve it
It's like that movie dr. Strangelove
Dr. Strangelove is a movie about a defense scientist
Laying out the logic of nuke
Nuclear deterrence
He says
The whole point of the Doomsday Machine
If not
If you keep it a secret
And of course what do you mean
Is that
If you want it the time
Your enemy from attacking you
You've got to tell them that you've dropped
Devastating weapon
To not announce your inflation Target undermines the whole
Queen airbed
But the reason the US Capitol
The secret was
So that they could
Change their mind
At any time
And they gave themselves no deadlines
To reach their target
So it was
Far less risk
Also the US was almost at 2% inflation already
It was not a shock
To our economy
So Sebastian says the main question this secret meeting raises is
Y2K
There's no
Magical logic
That justifies
2% more than 1% or 3%
And yet we made it kind of fetish for this 2% Target
Way I scherzo proportion
To the logic that was deployed at the time when
With fast brace
And by Logic he means lack of logic
Alan Greenspan never announced his
Secret inflation Target
It was Ben Bernanke who announced it in
And
It might not even be the right number
Valerie Wilson is an economist at the
Economic policy in
Institute and she says there's no reason our inflation Target
Should also be a number that we can
Never ever cross
You know a Target doesn't necessarily mean it has
To be a ceiling
The 2% Target
Should you could you
Just be staying average she thinks the US should have a ring
Not one explicit number of rain
Looks like New Zealand
Some Economist say 2% inflation that's just
Too low to get us out of a baddie
Economic situation like a recession
They say a three or 4% Target would give us more wiggle room
But Valerie says she
Does not think that it's likely the US will raise
Because
Keeping it low benefits
Some people
A higher inflation Target
Benefits
Borrowers who tend to be those with
Less income
On the other side of that those
With higher income and greater well 2
Are the lenders
Your would not necessarily
Want to raise the inflation Target the US
Has been targeting the egg
Exact same number since 1990s
And Valerie says
That doesn't make sense our economy and the world
Totally different now we should
Evolved other countries have New Zealand
Their original Target was 0 to 2 and they quickly raise it
And now the target is one to 3%
Remember Arthur Grimes
The jazz musician econ PhD who invented inflation-targeting
He likes
The original 2
2% Target
No I like on the 2% that's what we started after all
This is Arthur
Jazz Duo Planet Money listeners
Duopoly
He wants inflation rates just the way they are
The band also features the ukulele
And the electronic wind in
This message comes from NPR
Capital One
Is reimagining bad
I offering account
With no fees or min
I can be open from anywhere
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
And again it's fundraising season if you want to support Planet Money and NPR
The best way to do it is on this website
Donate. Npr.org
Splash Planet Money
Your support makes it possible for us to do our work that's donate. Npr.org
Planet Money podcast the indicator
Some of the stories we covered this week
Do they actually work
And the cost of higher education
Colleges are doing some extreme things to raise extra money now
That is on the indicator from Planet Money out
Every afternoon
10 minutes or less
Today Show was produced by Alexi Horowitz Ghazi
Special things to Sir Roger Douglas for helping us with fact-checking is a real Serrano
Kate helped us with
There were a lot of conflicting origin story so we have to think Charles goodhart David beckworth David
Wessel Jerry L Jordan and my friend in New Zealand Jeff Cooper they all helped us sort this out
Also
Super X
Extra special things to Planet Money Zone kiwi economist
Radio producer
Darien wood
He wanted the whole world to know that New Zealand is the reason the US has an inflation Target
And Darien knows Arthur Grimes
Thanks so much for coming at short notice
It's okay. How long you been over here where you guys know each other
How is Darian as an intern
We have to get rid of
Yeah that's right.
We always love to hear your questions ideas that's about the show we are on Twitter Instagram Facebook we are at
Planet Money
You're currently listening to a New Zealand band called Hans
You can check them out at Hans pocket. Bandcamp.com I'm Sarah Gonzales and I'm Karen Duffin thanks for the