College students may not know it but for the past few years they've had a secret Guardian at the Consumer Finance
Protection Bureau
The cfpb
Sethrak
His job has been to make sure students who
Take out student loans
Don't get ripped off
Financial companies
Debt collectors
Or even the Federal
His job has been
To be a whistleblower the whole cfpb is an agency of whistleblowers
But one day set says
He was told to
Just
Not send out a report
He was told to
Stop whistling
It was so clear to us at this was like
The first lock pulled out of that
Jenga game
Where you could just see that just you could like almost Envision it that day of watching how all of
The pieces were going to be pulled out until a kind of people down
Ceph started typing a letter that
When he wasn't sure he
You never send
You know the letter
That one that lives in our dress folder
You been it makes you feel better don't put an email in the address line so you don't accidentally
Send it
Yap Seth was writing
That letter
But one day
He realized
Oh I have to send
Send this letter
When you left for work that Monday morning
He told his daughter
I think I might be able to take you to the playground today
Like
He might get walked out of the office with his things in a box
What a centrally told her was
That there was a good chance I would be home early that day
Cuz I didn't know it was going to happen I didn't know if I was going to press send and just be
He told to go home
I didn't know I didn't know which way
Way2go
That's because in this letter
Seth told his boss
You have abandoned
Student Borrowers
You've used a federal agency
Serve the wishes
The most powerful Financial companies in America
Insecticides to send this letter
From his office
She walks into work
On August 27th
At 9:30 a m
Take a deep breath
And click Send
Escaping one week notice
Addressed
To his boss
And oh by the way
PCC.
Bunch of
US senators
Preventative
US Treasury secretary
MBA education sector
I was prepared
That
After I press send that I would
Be quickly leaving the bureau and be the last time that I step foot there and I had to make peace with that
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Sarah Gonzalez
PR and I've been investigating the student loan
Today on the show
A letter
You may not know it
But the federal government has
Become
Potentially one of the biggest banks in the country
The Department of Education has lent out over a trillion dollars to
Two students
A trillion dollars in student loans
NSF rapmon says
It's not clear who is overseeing this Bank
And young People's Credit is being totally
Ruined
Because the education department wasn't built
To be a bank
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Is reimagining bang
I offering account
With no fees or minute
That can be open from anywhere
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
To understand why sets
Letter matters
You have to understand
Why the cfpb exist
Why there is this whole
Unit dedicated to student loans
When we took out our feet
Federal student loan
We borrowed money from Big Financial,
Thanks
Yeah I'm
Still paying my student loans off those Banks
But we're paid by the government
To do this
To lend us money
But when the financial crisis
Isis hit
It slipped
This whole student loan industry on its head
President Obama said
He thinks we don't actually need you you're just the middleman
So we kick them out
Federal government took over a hundred billion dollars
An existing student loan
NSAID
From now on
We will ensue
Beatification to park
The
Bank of Education
But the department has never really been a bank before they're not built to be a banker and educator
Vision Department
They literally do not have the capacity to
Process the monthly payment
Of 44 million student Borrowers
That's how many there are it's more than 10% of the country
So President Obama was like
Middleman
We do still need
Someone needs to answer the phone mail the paperwork
Collect the money you know pink things
The government now
Paisley
Big Financial companies
To be
Glorified record Keepers in debt collector
Except
Really powerful glorified record Keepers in debt collectors who
Determine how much students pay each month and have the power to ding their credit
If they miss a payment
And student Borrowers
A Miss payment
A lot
Every 28 seconds a student borrower defaults
They can't pay their loans
Every
28 second
Student borrowers hold more Consumer Debt than anyone else
Except homeowners
And young people have never had this much debt before
And one law professor at Harvard
She saw all this coming
She asked
Who's looking out for borrower
There should be like
Whole new federal agency
For this and as the education department is
Coming this
Trillion-dollar bank that law professor at Harvard
Gets her shots
To build this new agency the cfpb
Our newest
Federal agent
That professor
Hi this is Sarah this is Sarah High Senator Warren
Now Senator Elizabeth Warren welcome back to Planet Money
Thank you it's good to be here
Her job was to hire everybody
She got a small office in the treasury Department
Just a desk and a coat rack
With one thing on it
An Old Fashioned
Police cap
Cop on the beach
Tim Geithner gave it to me the Secretary of Treasury
He said this is what you wanted
And
He handed me that you said you need to be dressed for this
Did you wear it
What's in a while only once in awhile
Elizabeth Warren
Created
Seth brought man's entire student loan unit other units too but this one
Was for college.
To give them some confidence
That when you sign a piece of paper on the student one if there's not something
Barry back on page
Disconnect
Blowed and
Choose your future
You are like the cop of
Fine print
I like that I like that
And her job was to recruit all the other cops of
Fine print
And starting a brand-new agency means
Holding your meetings
Out by the elevator
What's the biggest space we had
Would be a ding in the elevator door would open and
People would look at us like we're all crazy
The cfpb was the kind of place where employees would introduce themselves as
Steve employee number 7 and
Elizabeth
Warren employee number 1 I believe that I was
Like employee number 90
This is Seth frotman
The guy who CC Congress on his resignation letter
When you became a student loan Watchdog it cfpb 3 years
Before that he was looking out for military
And once he gets to the student loan unit
He realizes that
These companies the government contracts with the glorified record Keepers and debt collectors
They're making
Ton of mistakes
Violating laws
Example College.
Later joined the military and got
Disabled
They're supposed to get their loans completely forgiven
These companies
I didn't forgive them
And it destroyed their credit
There's a lawsuit about
The cfpb has actually returned
750 million dollars
Strong
Student Borrowers
Seth and the cfpb have been calling everyone out on a bunch of things
And all this is happening under the Obama Administration
These were not things that were necessarily warmly
Create it
By the Obama Administration
The cfpb is supposed to be apolitical
Their independence
They don't work for any president
Until
It kind of started feeling like they did
After the break
Everything Changes
This message comes from NPR sponsor squares
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online press
And run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layouts
Along with
Features including e-commerce functionality
3 + mobile app
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR
Car for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase
Just have a website or domain
After Donald Trump becomes president
Keypoint Mick Mulvaney to be Seth frotman boss
Stop Mulvaney is a former,
Who has
Does talked for years
About how much he hates
The cfpb
Harry is in a 2014 inter
It has
No accountability to anybody
Turns up
Being a joke and that's what the cfpb really has been in in a in a in a 6 and kind of way
A lot of conservatives feel this way
Washington doesn't need more bureaucracy
More regulation
Mulvaney says the cfpb has been over reaching all these years ignoring the letter of the law
And the changes start with something
Kind of small
Spending
Hundreds
Of hours
On things like
Changing the name
What do you mean spending
Hundreds of hours changing the name like the name of a report
Changing the name of
The bureau
One of Mick Mulvaney's first big moves in Consumer Financial Protection
Rename the age
So what is the name now
Why aren't you going to say it
Kurai Consumer Finance Protection Bureau OK Google Vini
Learns that the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau
Is actually served
Who is to have been called
The Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection according to the language in the statue
But poor Mick can't get anyone to call it by its new name
I can't get anybody to call the Bureau of Consumer this is Mick on CNBC
Because you have tried to change
The name of this you want to change the name
Well it's some other things as well but yeah that's a start
Set the guy who had the bags of all are
Disabled military student Borrowers
He is now
Sorting through anything that has
Cfpb written on it
And told
Wagon
We're going to have to change it to BCF
And that is like
Okay mental note this is weird
But he keeps going
Until that first log
Comes out of the gym
It's wobbling
And this
Is when Seth starts turning all those mental notes
What letter
American families need an independent
Consumer Bureau
To look out for them when lenders pull
Posh products and then one day stuff starts thinking
I might actually send this letter
He's just finished this big report
It's about Banks paying colleges millions of dollars
Words to push debit cards
Like students here by these get these credit cards
Graffiti shirt
Okay free t-shirt your first bankcard not necessarily a problem
But some of these cards have crazy fees
He's like you get multiple overdraft fees in one day and they're each
$35
Some of these Arrangements were
So
You can imagine what I'm going to say but where are the schools actually got
More money
The more in debt their students were
It also is likely illegal
Under current federal regulations
As on the books by the Department of Education
You said the word you were going to say was effed up
It's funny I was thinking predatory
That tells you a lot of hurt me and sicker
But when he hands the report Inn
He stole
Thanks
Yeah but we're not going to do
You had the report you showed it to all your people that you were supposed how did you find out that that report wasn't going to
Go out into the world
Was there a moment
I think we were just two
Curtis Mayfield
Burgess.
How like
Like what like in an email in Georgia
Part with gun
Okay to be fair
Debit Card issues might not
Technically be part of sex
Stop
He's the student loan guy
But the way set season the federal government is loaning students money to go to college
And then allowing Banks to suck
All that money away in debit card fee
Because he's thinking this is exactly my job
He adds one more line
After 10 months under your leadership
It has become
Clear that can be a good time for the cfpb
Stop going after violations because
There's a big problem Brewing
It's been brewing for
10 years
End
It's about to boil over
Loan forgiven
At the end of the Bush Administration
Congress ad
If you become a teacher
Aura firefly
Spider cop
Any public service job
We're going to forgive your loans
In 10 years
As long as you make your payments
That's our big thank you to you
Pretty wasn't the clearest thank you because
Beautification Department didn't actually tell p
People what path they needed to go down to
To get this great thank you money
And the companies that the government pays to manage these loans
I don't really have an incentive to help students sort through this
Complicated
Path to thank you money
You look at a dollar or two a month
Per-student
For $2 a month
I want to do a lot of paperwork or spend a lot of time on the phone
And obviously if the loan is Forgiven their pay goes down to $0 a month
So you can see why there's an incentive to keep students
Confused and pain
It's not a great system and by the way I've spent a lot of time and
Trying to get these services
To talk to me
But they don't really talk
I have though
Heard from a lot of students
Who thought they were going to get their loans forgiven
But they're not
Student like Sarah Cronin
Been in public service for 6 years and she's thinking
I'm only 4 years away from my thank you money
And then
One day
She called the education department
And someone there
Said
I'm really sorry I know your service
Hold you you qualify for Public service loan forgiveness
But you don't
She said yeah it really sucks
And I just hearing her say that
In a way was a relief I mean it wasn't
6 years worth of
But it was a little bit of
I need a confirmation that
This is not really the way things are
Post to be there were 29000a play
Applications for loan forgiveness in the past
And 99% of them
Were denied
99%
See that's actually a huge relief because I walk around with enormous
Amount of
Feeling silly
The education department
They say everybody who is eligible
Who is being approved
Still they say they will work on improving the process
Meanwhile
Set start
Realizing
You can either keep his job
Or she can help borrowers like Sarah
He's got to do it from the out
So he
Finishes his letter
The bureau has abandoned the very consumers it is passed by Congress
With protecting and he sends it
1700 G Street Northwest Washington DC
Hoping it will
Galvanized States
If there is any upside of what I did it's a recognition
Anyone who has any sort of power if your state legislature if you are a state attorney general
To look around and figure out how you could help a population of 44 million people that
Desperately needs it
15 Senators have told Seth's old Boston
That quashed report about Banks ripping off college students
If it exists
We need to see it
And states are telling the education department
If you're not going to protect our students
We will
They're suing these loan servicer
Even reliably conservative States like Montana Kansas and Texas
Are telling the government
Stop protecting these services
But the Trump Administration is saying leave our services alone we're policing them just fine
Besides syrup our employees
And we say they're exempt
From state laws and lawsuit
You can't
Sue them States
The federal government
Isn't only walking away from the fight
To help student loan borrowers they are actually are mean the other side
Here's where we're at
The education department is now a bank
1 + 1/2
Trillion-dollar
And this Bank wants to regulate it
No wheat
Seems a little off
Cuz
What other banks are allowed to regulate themselves and then there are the companies that work
For the Department states are saying they're making mistakes and they're breaking laws
Do something about it trumpet
Administration and they're being told
Stay out of it states
So
This is our new system
It kind of goes back to Senator Elizabeth Warren's cop hat
No one's really wearing it right now
And you could describe that as a
Truly free market or
Total chaos
By the way since you started listening to this episode
41 student borrowers have defaulted on their loans
We heard back from the cfpb they say that while they disagree with the assertion then sets letter they wish
I'm the best in securing his future employ
You can email us we're Planet Money at NPR. Org
We're also a plant money
Twitter Instagram editor is Brian thorstad and Alex goldmark is are supervising producer
Today Show was produced by Sally Helm also we're looking for a next internet
It's a great job
You can help with all of the parts of the show it's
Paid you can pay off your student loan
And while I've been talkin another student just defaulted on their loan
Get more information about the internship at NPR. Org
Splash money and you can also go there for a link to more information about student loans and the cfpb
Okay special thing Square you have like
Seconds for thank-yous before another student DeVos
Melissa Emery Eros Robert kelchen and Colleen Campbell
Thank you for listening