What's your name
Emily and you're out here raising money for charity on the street in Midtown Manhattan
I'm trying to get people to give the public radio right now by getting them to go to donate that npr.org Planet Money
Can you give me your top tips
You do the trick dislike you got to hook them at the beginning and you're like
Do you have a minute for dying seal to do that one
Will usually do something funny like are you as friendly as you are fashionable
Stuff like that
Oh so you are you put on the charm offensive
Yeah
Ilima smile
Cool so I'm if I'm trying to get people to go to donate that npr.org Planet Money
How should I do that
You should definitely get them the last first and then
I would say you have to be confident
I don't know tell him to go right on over there go check it out
Trisha was originally reported in 2015 we've got an update for you at the
All Fab
Start out the same way
With this feeling inside
You just got to have something
Did everyone else already has
Zach Hill
In 5th grade
That thing was a tiny plush animal filled with itty bitty Bean
The Beanie Boos in Garcia tie-dyed teddy bear
I was in the Hickory Ridge Mall in Memphis Tennessee
I think I was trying to impress a girl or something and I bought a Garcia
For like 7 box with some allowance money
Let them know that he was at the beginning of a beanie baby bubble
Because bubbles always seemed harmless
Just a simple fat
Then someone figures out
Make money by reselling that thing
I ran into my friend room
Andrew really wanted to Garcia he was swept up in the crazy like I was
He's like I want that I want that I want that I might do that you know they go to the store so goes to the store and they weren't selling it
Annie's just telling his mom and daddy wants it
And she says like hey like will you sell me that I was like
Yeah like 15 bucks
And she said yeah
And I just realized I made like a profit on that sounds like the soup probably not be
The last time that I do this
This was staged to
The Bible no matter how much you pay
There is some chump like
Drew's mom out there
Willing to pay more
Insults little Zach Hill 5th grader went into business
Buying up stuffed animals on the internet
Tabasco the bull
Swoopy the pterodactyl
And unloading them on desk
What school made from parents he says even did
A big business with teachers
Zach was a full-on specs
I made a lot of money is a 5th graders selling Beanie Babies on eBay
What did you
News like
40 $50,000
Are you kidding me
You know how the story ends
The way all bubbles app
Stage 3
Too many beanies
The market crash
I think I have like a tupperware tub in my attic with like
You know a few dozen or something
Exact like every other kid moved on to the next fad
He started getting into a card game called
Magic
Little piece of cardboard with pictures of dragons
Works
Fairies angels
Kids collecting magic cards
Trade magic cards
It was a stage 1 bubble all over
I never thought these cards were going to go the way of Beanie Baby
Stack them up in the attic
Except the folks who sold magic cards
How to plant
A plan to once and for all conquer the science of bubbles
And make a collectible
Make a lip scrub
Hello and welcome to Planet Money Robert Smith
So how company that makes little pieces of paper with nerdy illustration
Went to battle with the speculators intensified going for 22 years
This message comes from NPR sponsors
Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their own webs
Using customizable layout
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online presence
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR
How to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Do I have to admit something
I do not know a lot about the car
Card game
Magic I was vaguely aware of it
Back in the 1990
I was just starting and radio
And her Studios were
Actually right above
Card store
Specialize in selling
These Magic Car
And we went down there the place was very Dungeons & Dragons let's
Teenagers
Hanging out but it was definitely this big fat
NPR NPR back the time give it the full series
Americans by the millions are discovering a new card game
It's called Magic
The Gathering
It's one of the fastest-growing games in the country
Magic is played with elaborately Illustrated cards
A complicated set of rules
The I assume that this whole fat
Completely
Because I hadn't heard anything
But then one of my producers here in the office said to me
This game is
Alive and Kicking
There's so many people that
I'm a huge fan of myself
I'm actually going to play this Sunday
Mia group
Friends of mine
We're going to go out to a bar
And we can play
Cebu explain to me that
Basically these cards are like baseball cards
I like myself
And they have these creatures on them
MBA School statistics Reddit powerful
They are but unlike baseball cards you can actually
Do something
You can actually play a game
Yeah it's kind of actually really funny you're like you're like a wizard
And each one of these cards is a spell
In your deck
And the trick to this game is so you have to assemble enough spells
In the right combination so that you can beat your opponent
It's
Is supremely nerdy and I mean that in the best possible way
It was designed by math graduate students
For people who eventually might
B math graduate students
We tried that one of the early employees
Of magic
A math and physics grad student named skaff Elias
And he says from the beginning they suspected that these cards
Would be added
Every game you played was different
You know you immediately thought about wow if I could change my deck if I could take this out or I can put that in it would play a different way
Tennis game
It would come back to bite them
And this is the economic
They sold the cards in
You pay like $3 for a pack
I could get a bunch of random
Cart
But occasionally there would be a rare and Powerful something in the
Dragon angel
It was like a little Lottery
So that anticipation of did I get the best
One of those hundred we are cards
Is yeah that's a super exciting for
Steps right
Yo you go to the store you buy pack if your pack after pack
Looking for that rare card
And they expected this when they started
But what they didn't plan for was that once people got those rare cards
They would start to resell
For a lot of my
The rare dragons
Creatures and even rare flowers
Start to go for more and more money
Some of these cards that
Anomaly are $3 a piece cuz they're the one rare card that comes in a $3 pack
Eventually those become
$10 cards
And $15 cards and then hundred dollar cards and then $500 cards this all happened in the first year
This should start to sound familiar this is a stage
YouTube
Business perspective
It was a gold mine
Sign companies owned the magic card
Come pick up Wizards of the Coast
Was literally selling
Pieces of paper
Did some people thought
Where were the fortune
Speculators would buy cards by the
Hunt trying to find
Bsquare car
People at
The company a lot of them wanted to push that side of it
Produce more cars produced rare cards keep the print runs Limited
For many people the symbol of this craze
What's something called
The Blacklist
The black lotus
It wasn't a monster it's not a dragon
It's just a flower
But I gave you the special ability it let you have
Extra power sooner than anyone else
Which meant that if you had enough of
You could beat your opponent
Really fast
And
This card ended up being worth what
It was worth
Thousands of dollars
And show you how exciting
This card was
We're going to play a YouTube video going around of a man
Who is opening up a pack of
Random Magic
Flipping through them
Andy fine
A black lotus
And then the other one is
Cooley
Oh my gosh
Precisely
Baidu
Holy mackerel it's right there
Magic was well on its way to being the next Beanie Baby
What's gap and fellow designers
Saw a big problem
Because remember magic isn't just a collect
Nothing like a beanie baby you put on your shelf
It's also supposed to get game
It was me a fun game you play with your friends cheap fun game but all the sudden they were these where powerful
Shuffle cards
That you could buy if you had enough money
It would allow you to beat
Your friends
You know at first it doesn't sound so bad right
But imagine you're playing a high-stakes poker game
And you could go to the store and buy just
10 Aces
Nobody would play poker
Nobody would play that
This is what the magic folks
We're worried about
Sky Phantom the other math guys looked around and said you know this bubble is going to pop hard
This is going to be
Like Cabbage Patch Kid
Star Wars figurine for pods
Being a math guy and working with other math guy
They actually went out and grass
The life cycle of a fat that use Research into comic books and baseball cards
To figure out
How much time am I
The stuff we looked at had its its height like where it was sort of white-hot would be around a two-year
At some point you realize why I just spent $1,000 and there's only
$25 worth of comics here that I actually want to read
And that that that hit you like a ton of bricks and as soon as enough people believe that the momentum in the mark
Changes
And and then there's a big problem
Stop at his friends made an argument that
Sure you could make a lot of cash
In two years you can burn this whole thing out and walk away with millions of dollars
But he said perhaps
We should see if we can make
Magic City
Stainable
If we can make less money in the short-term
I keep it going for 5 years
Tenure
Perhaps he said we can
Wait this bubble
Without popping
So the first thing they had to do was bring back
The price of magic cards
2 normal level so that an average person
Could buy them again
Set a fire.
Compresses and
Basically princes sleuth new car
We just printed so many cards of the new sets coming out we warned people that were going to do that
What that meant immediately from the get-go was even though people could still make money in the secondary Market of the older cards
The speculators would no longer touch
A new set of cards
We had a pretty neat trick
To doing this they would basically print a bunch of cards
Then it would go out to the car shops
To see what the facts were selling for
And if they were selling for more than retail price
They would print some more
And some more and some more and eventually
Even the most stubborn speculators gave out
They were able to
The push the price of each pack
Down to what they really wanted to sell them at
About 3 bucks
The collectors were not play
We heard from so many people that we were
Throwing the game
And then 95
Over and over
Like it's this is the end
You guys
Have screwed everything up with much more colorful language
And they had just
Start it
Because they had a second problem all those old cars
Remember the black lotus
Black lotus
Rare dragon
They were so powerful that you couldn't
Just print a lot of those because that would
Still ruins
And they're worried about pissing off fans
Even more than they already work
You imagine
Kid who saved his allowance
It's for a year
Just to get a rare card
Didn't want to say like hahaha it's worth nothing
So we came up with another solution
They tried the band The Cars from play and that didn't work that didn't work at all because
Players want to play the way they learn how to
We came up with a really interesting fact
Patriot
Pro league
Professional magic cards
Yeah
The crowd is mug
Oh my God
And the police had an advantage
Work the company
Magic because
Magic could set the rules for the
Yeah that's right so they set a rule that said
You can only play with the most
Instead of card
No black lotuses
No super powerful monster car
Just the last
And so by setting those rules they basically say two players everywhere
Sure you could use the old cards
But if you want to
Do what the pros do
You should only use the new car
That's right
And the plan
Wart
Remember Zach Hill
5th grader who made $10,000 on Beanie Babies
You got into magic cards
As a fat but he got good at them
And he grew up to be a big name professional
Magic card player and eventually got offered a job at
Company to design magic cards and says
By the time he had gotten there
They had solved
All of those early problems they were not making
The same missed
We can't just keep printing
More and more and more and more powerful
Are more and more and more and more big and splashy
Ecards
That's why we don't make like
Our market research shows that people like
Swords Angels fire dragons wings and battles on cards right so we don't make
Take the like
Batwing Angel sword
Fiery Doom
I can see your eyes though you did that would be a pretty good card
I like it I'm not going to lie to you
Simply figured out how to keep the economy of the game stable
And talk to people involved in the game it's amazing
How much they talk as if they are sort of a central bank
Running economy they want
Stable prices
They want the game to grow
But they don't want to go too fast and I don't want to grow too slow there's this
Target
For growth
They managed to make a game
What is it now
22 years later
22 years
Bowie hits. Going to play this weekend in the fact
He dragged me down to a card store
The other night
Friday night
At midnight
What people were lined up
To get the latest data
Signed up
And paid for in a
Dance
Do the back of the line and we will take care of you at the end
All right who's excited
Gatherer fate reforged
And I had no
Idea
This exists
First of all that there was a store like this called
Twenty-sided store after
The dice
But the people were basically going to play this new set of cards
All night long
They're at least 50
They're all lined up to play this new deck of cards before anybody else and they were packed in there like
Ripping up in these packs
Like slapping other cards
Shuffling them and you can see how the company sort of
Has mailed this line
Between that the sort of rare Collectibles and
Play because there was actually a real card in the deck
It was called
The organ
It kind of looks like a blue dragon can a floating in space
Nobody could really explain to me
What the heck did what you could tell when somebody in the crowd open their pack
And pulled one out
Google is that cool
It's pretty cool
It's like 30 bucks right now
Alright I'm going to sell it
Maybe
Not the 2nd not the 2nd
This moment right here is exactly what the makers of magic cards wanted
This guy
Just got a rare card he was super excited
But rather than put it in a plastic case or frame rather than run to a dealer and try and sell it
He decides he's going to play with it
He decides he's going to go with the game
After the break
How much does Bugan Dragon cards are going for now
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence
And run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to launch use the offer code NPR
To save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
We were part of that original story back in 2002
And here are a couple
Quick updates
First there are still World Championships of magic with
Play by play announcers hopped up on adrenaline
Is your world champion
I know it seems like
The magic League are going to get even bigger just a few weeks ago
Wizards of the Coast the company behind Magic
Then out something called The Magic Pro League
With 32 players each getting a contract of $75,000
And they'll be 10 million dollars in prizes up
Big money makers
And
Guess it evident
They also had this Flash
Promo video with
Sir Mix-A-Lot the 90s rapper
Kid that Whispers feel that respect
Next update
On the value of the cars themselves the economic
That you can dragon card that everybody wanted at the store when Robert and Bowie went there
I just look it up online here in mm
18 and it is
Holding its value
Demon going up a little bit was
$30 back then
And now you can find it for $50 all the way up to $150.
Depending on the addition
To even with all that work at Wizards of the Coast is doing to
To keep the cards for playing and not collecting
Not totally working
Black lotus
That is still super valuable
So valuable that this past July 1 sold on eBay for
$87,000
If you like Planet Money
And you want to support us you can donate to a local NPR member station using this link
Donate. Npr.org Planet Money donate
Npr.org planet
We always love to hear what you think of the show and to get your ideas for future shows we are on all the social media places at
At Planet Money
Or you can email us
Planet Money at npr.org
This episode was originally reported by Robert Smith and quattrone Bowie this rerun was produced by internship
Thanks for listening