Support for this in
NPR Podcast
The following message
Come from the
UPS Store
Offering services from shredding
To printing to mailbox
And instead of closing
This Memorial Day we
May 24th and 20
The UPS Store
He's doing another thing
All together
Opening
The UPS Store
Everything for small business
And of course shipping
What's your name
Emily
Emily and you're out here raising money for charity on the street in Midtown Manhattan
Yes
I'm trying to get people to give the public radio right now
By getting them to go to donate that npr.org Planet Money
Can you give me your top tips
You do the trick dislike
You got a hook them at the beginning and you're like
Do you have a minute for dying seal to do that one
I don't do that one
Will usually do something funny like are you as friendly as you are fashionable
Stuff like that
Oh so you are you put on the charm event
Yeah
Ilima smile
Cool so I'm if I'm trying to get people to go to donate that npr.org Planet Money
How should I do that
You should definitely get them the last first and then
I would say
You got to be confident
I don't know tell him to go right on over there go check it out
Hey today's episode originally ran in 2014 and we've got a small update for you at the end
This week Zoe and I went
The New York
Would you like to ride in the Cherokee the Wrangler or the grand cherry
Will get it to anyone
We're getting a test drive since this is Manhattan
Can't really take it off
Road bike jeep has built a driving track
A bunch of fake Hills and bumps all set up right in the middle of the city
Welcome to Camp cheap because my name is Steven I'll be your operator
And we are going to slide around the track here in our 2014
Jeep Wrangler
This is the unlimited so it has the four-door and all this type of the Jeep takes off and we are going up this incline and
I swear
That's where the car is about to tip over
And then we whip around the corner we start bouncing up and down over bunch of stumps in the road
All right
Made it
Could you drive this Jeep off-road
Driving on dirt roads
Yeah absolutely that's what this
This particular kind of Jeep Grand Wrangler
Could you drive through a river
You can water poured with it that's one of the things that makes Jeep
A trail rig vehicle is waterboarding
So can you drive this thing anywhere
Babylon places you can't drive a Cadillac
But you cannot drive this car
Anywhere
Because he doesn't mention one
Very large place
It will not allow this car in their roads
Europe
This particular Jeep
Would be illegal in Paris
It would be illegal in Milan would be breaking the law in Berlin
Because of a technical
All the safety features on this Jeep
The airbag the bumper
They're built to us safety
And there is an entirely different set of standards in Europe
And so in order to sell this particular Jeep in Europe
Jeep will have to replace a bunch of parts redesign other parts in the Europeans have the same issue
Volkswagen Golf
You can see it driving the Autobahn in Berlin but it is not yet arrived in the United States
The German company has to sort of remanufactured the car for a completely different set of CC Radio
Right now it's actually the case that you developed a vehicle twice
Once for North America and once for Euro
Hello and welcome to Planet Money Zoe Chace
Today why can't you build a car that can be driven anywhere in the world
We go to the car show and we talked to designers and car company executive
But one of the biggest
Technical challenges that they face
Making all these different governments happy
In these subtle differences in safety regulations they end up making our cars cost more
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solution
Strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information
Is available at aecf. Org
You walk into a car show and it is like a brand explosion boom
Honda
Toyota
Acura BMW
Maserati
Porsche.
Jaguar XE Mercedes in Alfa Romeo and big vw's back there I can barely see
It's like being inside a glossy magazine all the cars are sparkly and new with
A special lights on them exactly how you sort of picture a car showed actually big raised up stages like lazy
Susan's rotating around and yes completely dressed women in high heels standing
And the police is
Filled with
He sort of Mad Men type
Just guys
In suits
Everywhere that look like Don Draper and Roger Sterling walking around
Winning at the cars Consulting with the
Each other
And chatting up the women I talked about in the high heel
Be jealous
Here it is
MX-5 Miata
25th Anniversary Edition
This whole show is a lot of
Fox
For something that is
But a car is a special kind of Pop
It is super complicated is a highly technical product
It's often the most
Expensive thing we own
And
It is one of those highly regulated products in the world
Which country developed
Their own regulator
They have their own laws their own testing standards and
Friends even the Expert Car Guys
Admittedly is not us even they cannot figure out some rationale for the
Standards being different
That's why we met up with Dave shepardson
He covers cars
Detroit news
And we met him at the Fiat section of the auto show end
What's this
Beautiful car I think anyway the Fiat 500
In order to bring this from Italy
Words you can drive it all over the place to America
Had to change a bunch of things
Including
The windshield wipers
American regulations
Require
That the windshield wiper
Capture a larger
Part of the windshield
Versus European ones
What is the logic behind
You know I I I
I guess
America's Best
Therefore they would be looking at a different part I mean I'm struggling here I agree with you to come up with a rationalization
Yeah some of the regulation seem totally arbitrary
Like the very fact that a rule exist at all for the things you've kind of crazy let alone that there are two
Rules in different countries
Like we found these
Two brand-new Porsches
On the show Floor One Porsche for the us and one for Europe
Did two different colored eyes
Turn signal
Visit Porsche Panamera
I'm looking the US version we had the Amber turn signal indicator or is here
On the German version we've got the clear
That is actually
A law that is a rule
We don't care if your car is worth $1000000 and his car is
Is worth $1000000
You have to have an Amber turn signal in America
And you have to swap out this little piece of plastic if you're in Europe
This may sound
Kind of silly but the rules go from the very small
To the very big
Because
A car can be a very big and very serious
Because cars can kill you
Which is why the government feels like they have a compelling interest to get all up in how you make your car until you what you
Can and cannot do
Cars are one of the leading causes of death in the sky
Different countries have
Different assumptions about
Exactly how these cars are going to kill you
Pek crash test
In Europe you have to put Crash Test Dummies into a car and you drive that car into a wall head-on
But the US also looks at what it'll be like if the crash happens at a slight angle
A small difference
But it
Big deal for designers
Because this presents them with a problem now
A car company
Design a car that will withstand both kinds
The car that would be legal in both United States and Europe and a lot of
Used super luxury cars
Do this
But it could be really expensive to make the flame that way until
What a lot of other car companies do is they do this or the second most expensive
They just redesign the car they say this one's for us this one's for Europe and they re crashing
A retest you might think I did
First Edge
Assume that Europe is just a C4
Ways to drive and in the US they are more left
Figured in Europe they're more strict
Soap in Europe they're probably
But this is not the case everyone tells us and studies back this up
The in general intake all the regulations with Europe in the US
Both places
Are pretty safe
They're just different
The US may require a certain test like this
Speed in Europe may require more kinds of tests but doesn't result in significant difference
In the number of death
Difference is almost
A philosophical one
What does it mean
To make a car say
There's one big philosophical
Sprint switches
Who are the rules designs
Protect
So in the US
Cars are tested
To make sure that
People inside the car are for
Did the driver in the
In Europe
Cars are also tested to see if they protect
Pedestrian
People walking in front of the car
Cities are denser they drive less so European Regulators want the front of their cars
Basically softer
The guy rep forces
The Hudson in Europe actually have to have it
Standard than in
What states have to be able to
For lack of better term absorb
Somebody's head hitting the hood of the car were to hit
A pedestrian
If if I'm walking around the car show and I'm hit like a car if I'm a pedestrian hit by a car
It's probably better to be hit by a car on the European standards and is willing American
UB
According to the standards you be safer
So if your us car company and you want to sell your car in Europe
You got to make sure the hood crumples and absorbs the impact of
Say in Italian
Also you have to smooth out the surfaces of the car because in Europe apparently their concern
Earned it someone's going to accidentally
Cut themselves or hurt themselves on the outside of a
And this is a test
Yep require
The baby head test
Do all the European cars have to meet this test
The baby head
Cast they don't use actual baby head
But they roll a ball about the size of a baby head
Oliver the car
Make sure there are no
Sharp edge
It's all done biking
So the cars look smoother than they used to
Maybe the baby head test mix
Sense in having smoother cars
Is C4 thinking
What is an Amber turn signal really better than a clear one or vice versa
The question is why haven't at this point all the regulators
Comment or room and sort of
Just voted
Look at all the data
Decided what works best what's the safest thing to do
And then just
And then enforce
The same set of Standards all over
The world that normally wouldn't encounter something like this a trade barrier
We look for the person who is
Pushing for it
It's usually some industry or some farmer wants to be protected and they go to the government and they demand or rule set
Regulations
It keeps out foreign car
Competition
But this is different than car regulations
It is hated by all of the car companies
Equally
We couldn't find anyone who want these differ
It protects no one in particular
And the car company say
It actually hurts them all
But it's not up to that
If it were we would have one simple list for everyone
That's what a global engineer Cadillac.
You think if all the companies in the auto show right now they're set together you guys could just come up with what the list would be
Everybody feels this way huh
We could know I absolutely would be would make life so much simpler
And I could use the same part around the world
Without all the unique testing and certification requirement in design
And it it gets to exhaust systems and it gets the seatbelts and it gets the glass and it
Guess the mirror
In tires and
It's Millions
Just not thousand
Kansas millions of dollars
Annually to make sure that our
Vehicles meet the requirements of the global market we sell Cadillacs in over 40 countries around the world
Just imagine wooley Cadillac off the production line in the US and just
Sending it out anywhere in the world
Testing it once
And then telling it to whoever wants to buy it
And that conceived
In the millions of dollars
Cars
Might be cheaper for us
Because complying with
Who set the rules gets
Baked into the
The price
Interview bigger select
Cars 2
Attacking the former CEO of Hyundai
And he said there are a lot of great
Cheap fuel-efficient cars on the road in Europe
The Never
Make it here
America
Because it would be
Basically too expensive to re-engineer the cars for our
Safety standards
If you have a cheap car
You want it to be cheap
All around the world and if you have to do different safety standards re-engineering
Look at the cheap anymore
And no one's going to want to buy
So who's in favor of
Who likes the two separate sets of rules
The rule-makers
The people who made the wrong
Each countries Regulators have their reasons and data to back up
The reason
That's why change is hard here
They've been trying for decades to come up with
The same set of regulations there are these working groups
Over in Switzerland that have been
Trying to do these things for decades
And the u.s. in the EU or right now working on this
Big free trade deal in the same conversation is happening again
Can we get
1 list
Standards
Everyone can
It was hard at first for us
Why do we
2 difference
Rules
System everyone at the car show
No one had a good amp
And when it came right down to it
It's language
We have the same human bodies
Baby heads on both sides of the Atlantic
And we couldn't quite figure it out until
This one moment
When we suddenly understood
We may all be physiologically
The same
Culturally
We're different
So
In American Europe we actually drive.
Take a very basic example
Seat belts
In every car
You required to wear them in Europe
You are required to wear them in the United States
Ring United States
Let's be honest
People do not always wear their seatbelt I
Do not always wear a c
Seat belt
You're pausing because
You want me to admit you there are times when I'm going a very short distance and it's a bad thing and you should wear your seatbelt
But their time for very short
I do not put on my
I just don't
Now
Try and run this by
A European
I found a German person
You wear your seatbelt
Yes of course
Every time
It's my safety
You don't get that feeling like I'm just don't really want to bother
No way
Never
Can you understand
Has some of us might feel that way
We have
I love Ruth and Germany in
It's kind of mentalities
Everybody puts on the
Seefeld and
The mentality has to follow the rules
Yes
Tilt Clannad who is one of the car cleaners here he just looked at us like
Wework rate
Now
Look at this
Through The Eyes of a Reiki
They see that Americans
Zoe the time don't wear their seatbelt
The Germans
Philip always where there's
So when they get together when the Germans get to
Designer Arab
Back they assume everyone's wearing a seatbelt
There are bags
Can be smaller more targeted they know where the head of a person is going to go in a crash because of German is wearing his seatbelt
In America
We assume that people will break the law and
We want those people to live as well so are airbags are bigger
Fort some idiot who is not wearing a seatbelt who goes flying around the car
What are guys from Volkswagen
Christian Bowman he he showed us this inside their new American mod
Of the golf r
The the Arabic
Made in
In a difference
Ways so it protects also the unbelted
Now
Volkswagen told us they want one set of regulations just as much
Ascp Cadillac
Because it will save them a lot of money
Clear just from talking to
German guy that Christian thinks is more efficient
Did you airbags the German Way
Natsu
American Way
The problem is
Will the unbelted person
You don't know at which point
The hits
Off the dummy
Hits the Epic
Where is
With the belted person
That is always identified and therefore it's in the ideal position
She can see the problem here
Right in theory all regulation should be the same
But
If you have two different kinds of people
And you have two different kinds of airbags that means the car manufacturers have to manufacture a different kind of dashboard for Europe in the US
At two different dashboards means
Essentially
Two different car
So it's a trade barrier but it's an emotional barrier which is
Possibly why it is taking
So long to straighten this out
After the break and update
Support for this podcast
Cast in the following message come from the Annie E Casey
Sea Foundation
Developing Solutions
It support strong families and community
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is
Is available at aecf
. org
Okay it's been 4 years since we are the story and we called up Dave shepardson he was the car reporter at the
The Detroit News who we talk to you about the Fiat
He now works at Reuters
And he summed up what has
Changed in the past 4 years
The US and the EU
Still have pretty different safety standards but Dave says there's a chance that that could change soon
But by and large the same issues are still here
And then as a result the EU and us still have very different safety standards
The US and the EU are said to begin trade talks
And Dave says those talks might lead to more safety standards being harmonized
Today Show was reported by Robert Smith and Zoe Chace Shane McKean and Darien would produce the rear
Email us at Planet Money at npr.org we're on Twitter and Facebook and Instagram
Or at Planet Money
And if you want to support our podcast
Go to donate got npr.org
Splash Planet Money and
Depart of local NPR station then we can stop sending me
Out onto the street looking for tip
I'm Sarah Gonzales
Thanks for the
What is the average weight of a podcast and radio show
Planet Money
Planet money bro apply for an intern
Would you guys like 2 years ago you faded me
I'm sorry I'm the one who
Awesome awesome
Alright well
What is your name
Connor
Since your Planet Money fan
What are the top tips on fundraising tips
They not
You not here to convince anybody of anything for suede anybody anything
Hit up remind them that they are a good person and give him a chance to prove it
Flex Hot 97 is Hot 97