This message comes from NPR sponsors snowfall
The only data warehouse
Built for the cloud
Unlock deep data in
Insights with the instantly scalable
Cloudbuilt data warehouse
Start your journey towards data-driven decision
It's snowflake. Com NPR
I'm at Chris at a park in Manhattan
Tell me what your nickname is
Free black
Blastoise shortness of
First and last name
Chris
Likes
Good bottled water
The Mets the Knicks and the Jets in that order
And
Chocolate while I was a Butterfinger when you
Approach
Chris has a daughter who just finished her second year of college
Carrier picture right on my phone went to
Is that her high school graduation robe valedictorian
Wow
He's been helping her out of bed putting some money in her pocket but
She treated him to lunch today
For the past eight years I think I've been paying her phone bill and my phone bill
And now she because I'm in this situation she actually paid the phone bill for us
NRA
I think I did a good job raising
Chris became homeless a month
And a week ago
Actually I was on a train
For two nights
Before I got before I
Got into the sea
That's not too bad
Cuz I didn't know about the hotels
The hotels
Chris check into a hotel in Manhattan a couple days ago
And all the rooms at this hotel
Are completely occupied by men
Who are homeless
Paid for by the city
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm finally home
And I'm Sarah Gonzales
Today on the show we look at how New York City ended up renting thousands of hotel rooms for the homeless
Also how solving homelessness might be
Surprisingly cheap
And how the first
Stop insulting it is
Learning how to count
This message comes from NPR sponsor E-Trade
Investing your money shouldn't require Moving Mount
No matter how much or how little experience you
E-Trade makes investing simple
Along with great value
They provide the tools and support you need to navigate the market
All to help your money work hard
For more information visit etrade.com NPR
E-Trade Securities LLC
Membership
It's 1965
White minister is murdered in Selma Alabama
But no one is held to account
More than 50 years later we return to the place where he
Call Ally Ally
And finally solved
White Lies
NPR
New episodes drop
Tuesdays
People in New York City have what's called a right
To shelter
That means New York City is legally obligated to find a bed for every person who needs one every
Single adult ever
Family ever
Couple every night of the year
If the shelters are full
People cannot be turned away
So the city rents
Blocks of hotel rooms entire floors entire hotels
Just for the homeless
Some sort of like a Shelter Hotel hybrid
Some are five star hotels with paying customers on some floors and homeless families on others
Hotel Chris is that doesn't allow him to have any busy
So I couldn't get in
I asked for a picture you want to see
So this is your windows overlooking apart
And that's my bet there and doesn't look
Like
A hotel bed
No no
Like it's not hotel furniture
Write up here's the headboard
Of what they had I guess I'll
Queen
King size
The headboard is still up there by
Everything else
Taken away so they can put these two cot that what I call him
Yeah they're cut
Twin bed on on metal
Oh so they removed the
The official hotel furniture
The hotel that Chris is staying at is a big
Hotel chain
You've heard of it
You've seen signs from the side of the freeway
But we're not going to be in the hotel
Because the city told us that in the past when
People have found out that
Certain commercial hotels are housing the homeless
Those hotels
Dump the homeless gas
Overnight
Leaving the city scrambling to find new hotel beds for them
All the hotel rooms the city uses are technically shelters
With the rules of a shelter
You have to be in by 10 p.m.
And you can't be in the hotel during the day
Yeah if you're not working you have to be out
Between hours of 95
As far as
Food and drink water and can't bring anything else in
There are ways you can sneak some candy bars in
They check your socks
But if you take the candy bar on put in the back of your side
At this hotel it's two strangers to a room
That you can get a locker for their stuff
Cuz they're strangers
And Chris says his roommate is a big snorer who keeps the room too cold
And his body roommate
Very close to each other
Does it feel like a hotel
Well actually it does
I'm you do get the
Free Service Tire
You get the linen
Veterans what that the inside is is is
Looks like a hotel
Last year the city spent 360
4 million dollars about a million dollars a day
Using hotels as shelters
And of course it spends even more money on
Traditional shelter
Never said he has to do this
By court order
Right to shelter has been around since 1979
A group called The Coalition for the Homeless was behind the right to shelter
But even they say that things have turned out kind of weird Giselle routhier with the Coalition says
I never thought it come to
Hotel Beds
It's far cheaper to provide housing and not only is it cheaper it's more Humane thing to
To do
It just makes logical financial and moral sense
Housing
It costs about $40,000 a year to
To shelter a single adult like Chris in New York City
And Giselle says that is so much more than what it would cost to help Chris rent in apartment
Basically
Double the cost of renting him in apartment
As a city
Is now spending a greater and greater share
Sheltering tens of thousands
The people
They need to be thinking about
Solutions to start housing people so that they can
Not be spending billions of dollars on shelter costs
In perpetuity
Cities all over the country
Spend huge amounts on temporary shelter
Even though housing is often cheaper than shelter
Not always working to get into some of the nuances in a minute
Either way
Chris says he wants out
I got to go
I can't stay
And I'll do everything I can to get out of the system
Christmases
Cooking in the kitchen
Not matter
Chef Ramsay but I like to cook my own me and my meals are 20 minutes or less
What do you what do you mix cookie
Spaghetti and tomato sauce
And the City
They get it they say you have these hotels are expensive
So they're phasing out Commercial Hotel use
But it'll still take 5 years
And they're investing more in permanent affordable housing
How should the country spend money to address
There was one study in the 1990s that really change the way people
Another next story
First a little context
Homelessness really comes on the scene as the crisis it is now in the 1970s and 80s
And at the time the President Ronald Reagan.
The market would solve homelessness
Is that the free market would
Create low-quality housing for the poorest
Soap the government shouldn't have to
Payforit shelters and housing
So Reagan
Cut funding
Substantially
But by the 1990s
Homelessness is getting worse
And Advocates are pointing out how expensive homelessness itself
Candy
30 Flyers all over the subway about this
You know the price of a jail cell $58,000
The price of a hospital bed
$140,000 the price of a shelter
$30,000
The price of an apartment
$11,000 ghetto professor of social policy at the University of Pennsylvania
Keystone research on homelessness
And he knows at the time that most
People experiencing homelessness
AR
People like Chris
People who will need a little bit of help for a little bit of time before they get back on their feet
And that is really just a small group of people who will be homeless
4 years maybe forever
People with addiction and mental health issues
Chronically homeless
People who are chronically homeless
Spend a lot of time bouncing around between shelters
Emergency rooms getting hospitalized
Getting arrested and going to jail
And that is wanted to find out
What cost more
Paying rent for the chronically homeless
Giving them housing assistance
Or
Keeping things how they are letting them stay home
He follows 10000 people who were chronically homeless over 8 years
So you wanted to see
How often are homeless
People
Using
Shelters going to the ER going to jail
If they live on the street compared to if they live in the house that is being paid for by the state of the city
That's exactly what we did and when he added up their jail and shelter and hospital stays
He found that those
Same dollars
Could have actually solved the problem could have gone toward
Paying their rent
And getting them off the
Street
And he found that if you have a house
You're actually less likely to cycle in and out of jails and hospitals and shelters
So give it all that it was almost a break even
$1,000 more per year to pay rent for this group of people but
Dennis also didn't look at a bunch of other cost
Associated
We did not include
The cost
Of
Emergency medical transport
Which turns out to be a very big number
And had we included that
We probably would have been better than break even there would have been a positive return on
Denison study has been replicated dozens of times and
Every time I find the same thing
It cost about as much to House people who are chronically homeless as it does to
Not
Were you surprised
I will be found surprised that we got so close
Drake even I am
Dennis is dead he looks specifically at a group of people who were considered the least possible and the least
Deserving of help
Single adults
Sometimes with addictions
And his finding was counterintuitive
That the thing that seems the most generous
Help them get a house
Is basically worth it
Financially
Now it's important to point out that this doesn't necessarily hold for
People who are not
Chronically homeless
Most people are just
Homeless
Temporarily
It doesn't always cost us less
But I think if you look at it over the larger population
It can be
Break even in many cases and even better than break even and in some cases as well
And Dennis is Teddy really change the tide on homelessness
Best policy
In a huge
Way
The Sun comes out in mm
And it convinces the president
George W bush
To make a goal of ending chronic homeless
Do you what do you remember when that happened
Oh yes I do quite clearly
It's very exciting I have to say
Bridgeport 500 million dollars into homeless services
After Ronald Reagan had cut
Almost all of them
All this extra funding worked
It brought homelessness down
To the point where
Genesis
An end was kind of insight
But in order for cities to get all of his money
They had to do this weird thing
Which brings us to our final story
Do you have head
Really no idea how many homeless
People there were on the street
So the Bush Administration told cities and counties
Find out
Every corner of America that wants to receive federal funding for homeless services
Has to physically count
Their homeless population
Like at night
With flashlights and clipboards
On a cold night in January every other year this incredible process
2 count
So homeless
All over the
Thousands of volunteers bannout
To physically count
Every homeless person they see
Call the point in time count
Pet
And every city and county does it a little differently
In Los Angeles it's a visual count more than 8000 volunteers cover every
Inch of the county all 4000 square miles
7 p.m. to midnight
Shining flashlights behind dumpsters going in
Every alley every
Public parking lot abandoned buildings
How's it going
Countdown across the street every single blue
Discounted the future is the park
The dried-out river beds
Volunteers get a map and a tally sheet
Chance
They just start Market
Somebody saying there
If you see an RV
Tally mark
Makeshift campsite
In actual person
2 individuals
All these communities
Send their totals to wash
Where is tabulated
And a quick 11 months later
They get the official number of how many people were experiencing homelessness
11 month
And these tally marks are supposed to help determine where funding and resources will do the most good
Cities do not get more funding for having more homeless
People that would create a
A perverse incentive to have more homeless people
It's more about how fast communities get
People out of shelters and into permanent housing things like that
One of the volunteer counters is a guy named Jake McGuire
Hebert's Addison Austin
I got two hours of training basically
You know
Here's how to get the tally sheet
Here's a map of the area you're going to go
Here's your partner
Jetta car
Try to be back by this time
Jake is now with a nonprofit called Community Solutions their whole thing is trying to end
Homelessness
We're like in our lifetime
Before we die like this
Have to happen this
How to be a problem that goes away and these new
Count
Help him realize that the problem wasn't actually that
Big in 2010 at the point in time count showed that there were 106
Thousand chronically homeless people in the US
Remember that's the worst form of homelessness people who are out on the streets
3 years
And Jake and Community Solutions were thinking a hundred thousand people that's actually
A small number relative to other social problems
There are more Librarians in the country than there are chronically homeless
So they launched a national campaign to
Pretty simple find homes for those hundred thousand people who are chronically homeless
And they chose this number base
On the point in time count
The tally marks
From that night in January
You're like okay this is the number this is how many people we have for chronically homeless
Right and then you find out how
The country arrived at that number
What do you think
I think okay I guess that's how we do it
Yeah I never I never questioned
Yeah
It took a couple years
For me to start to wonder
Is this number
Ridiculous
Because here's what happened to the 100000 homes campaign
All these communities came together and
Found 100000 homes
Actually $105,000
And we sat back and thought this is great
We just took care of
You know 90% of problem
That we're going to see a massive
Decline
Can chronic homelessness
But that didn't happen
The next point-in-time count showed
The Chronic homelessness only went down by
Not a hundred and five thousand
To take things
Okay
This point in time count is clearly missing the real
Maybe we can't just count the homeless with flashlight
Once every other year we need it
Current information
We needed information that was going to be up to date
In real time
In every community in the country this is how we attract other important things like
Unemployment and jobs
We want to know every month
How is the economy doing
Are we creating new jobs
Is the unemployment rate going up or down
Because our expectation is that if we start to see that number going in the wrong direction
There are people in the federal government and other places who could do so
Something in response to that information
If they have it in time
It's so important for those numbers to be meaningful that economist
Go back and revise them months later if they're a little off
Jake thinks the US
Could be tracking homelessness as often as unemployment and jobs
Or like the way we track crime and natural disaster
Stars in real time
So we know where to
Deploy resources to minimize the damage
So they set out to create a database
List of every single person experiencing homeless
Not a tally
A name
Ana survey
One that's updated at least twice
Real time
Homelessness
Data
And big cities with huge homeless population
It's like New York in LA
I like
Impossible
You couldn't possibly get that kind of data quality
In a place this big
Which I just think it's
Crazy like we track the flu in real time we tried polio around the world in real time
I mean
Of course you can get that
Most of the people in LA or extrinsic are known to somebody already
Like what we just take to get all that data in one place
End table discount people
They would talk to them
Ask them exactly what they say
I mean
Like how do you do that you knock on a tent
In the middle of the night
Yeah sometimes
You wake them up
Yeah yeah
Touch them
I call out to the
It's a man a man
Hi I'm sorry to bother you
If they're sick
They're veterans
And you ask
Like
Are you addicted to drugs
Very personal questions
It's it extremely sensitive yeah and they want to know this because a lot of communities have money
That's specifically earmarked to help people struggling with SEPTA
Since abuse or health problems or
If they're veterans
So if they know this
They can connect people better say okay
What do we know about this
What do they need what would it take to get them hell
What's the plan
Next week
Is that person out if not what do they still need okay what's
The plan did jaundice in 69
Communities
Bergen County New Jersey
Rockville Illinois
Chicago
Jacksonville
Phoenix and when Phoenix did this they find out that Phoenix had about four hundred homeless better
And that
They actually had all the federal and local housing subsidies they needed
To house all those homeless veteran
It was just about connecting the person
To the place
And this group was actually had more luck ending veteran homelessness than anything else
They worked with nine communities
To have salt butter and homeless
End
They got a lot of help from the federal government
The US spends a lot of money on veteran homeless
And for communities in the country have ended
Chronic homelessness overall
At least one without the help of this group and 3 with their help
They say these communities are at functional zero
Meaning
If your home is there
The community can find you a home
Within a month
Support for Planet Money and the following message
Sitcom from American Express
You want to build your
They can help build your business with financing solutions for eligible business cost
The powerful backing of American Express
Don't do business without it
Terms apply
Visit americanexpress.com business
If you need to be reminded
We're all more connected than we realize
Get the storycorps podcast and restore your faith in humanity
Uninterrupted conversation
What's between real people about the things that matter most
And this season in honor of the 50th anniversary of the Stonewall uprising
We're highlighting voices of lgbtq people across America
Stories from those who lived
Before Stonewall
Today
Episodes are available every Tuesday
Planet money has a new email newsletter it comes through in box once a week with a
An interesting economic Insight you can subscribe at npr.org Planet Money newsletter
Should do it
Npr.org Planet Money newsletter
Today Show was produced by Alexi Horowitz Ghazi and Liza Jaeger Brian or status to show an ounce gold
Mark is a supervising producer
Special thanks to Mary Cunningham she's a homeless and housing expert at the urban Institute and she taught us
If you want support kind of money one way to do it is televangelist your favorite episode or
Rate of energy bus on Apple podcast
I'm Sarah Gonzales and I'm finally home
Thanks for letting
What's your what's your go-to candy bar
Usually
Almond Joy
Almond Joy is not a common favorite chocolate bar
Since I was young
I love that
That's my mom's favorite
Coconut
Chocolate