Support for NPR and the following message
Did come from servicenow
Making the world of work
Work better for me
They're cloud-based
Platform and solutions
Deliver digital workflow
Spell create great experience
Frances and unlock productivity for your Holcomb
More at servicenow.com
From a seriously price Commodities in everyday life
Press 3
Your question will be answered in the order in which it was received
Your call may be recorded
Podcasting purpose
Thanks for calling plan of money this is Karen how can I help you
I was booking a flight
And one of the cheapest flights
British Airways and I clicked on it and
The entire flight cost $516 and they said that $514 were for taxes
And let the fear itself cost $2
And I immediately thought that this doesn't make any economic sense
Okay so
The question we got from our listener is basically how can you have
An airline flight that is
$516 and only two of it be for the flight and the rest
$514
Before taxes and fees
Which is why we have called in
Julia Furlan
I believe that you looked into this for us
Yep I took this question and I call the guy named Bob man
And he's an airline industry expert he knows a lot
He's been in the industry for like 40 years
The history of it is actually that it comes from a
Fuel star
Charge
In 2008
Fuel prices were really high
So Airlines
Put this like taxes
These thing into their fare breakdown
So there was a fuel surcharge
But then fuel prices
Has went down
And guess what the airlines didn't do
They didn't take away the taxes and fees that is not cool I know right
Pacific to British Airways either any Airline can break down their Fair kind of however they want and there is
Some amount of monitoring from the Department of Transportation but it's kind of random it's not good
All right that's one question down but there are a lot to go so let's dive in hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm
Karen Duffin and I'm Julia Furlan
We got tons of questions from listeners everyday and some of them turn into full episodes
But every once in awhile we tackle a whole bunch of them all at one
Your calls are very important to us so today on the show
Julia and I are stopping the Planet Money listener help.
Stay on the line will be back with you shortly with some answers
Support for NPR and the following message come from a luminary
The only place where you can listen to Trevor Noah's a new podcast
With his new show
The Daily Show host
Challenges himself and his listeners
To explore unfamiliar anger
And embrace different viewpoint
Listen to Trevor Noah's new pot
Along with other original shows only on luminair
Visit luminary. Ling
Mega / money for your first two months of luminaries premium content for free
Cancel anytime
Terms apply
Give us about 10 minutes
And up first gives you the biggest stories from NPR news
No need to stay glued to your phone or your TV
Up first has recovered
Start your day
And all it takes
Just 10 minutes listen to up first every morning from NPR news
Thank you for calling Planet Money help desk this is Julia Furlan speaking how many my name is Solis Barrow and
My question is why
Vanilla prices have gone up so dramatically over the left
Little while I went
Takako
It's been over a year but
I paid 599 for 16 oz of vanilla and then
I went back and it was
$32 for the same thing over the course of a year
Why is this happening
Okay so we sent this question over to our sweet tooth producer Alexi Horowitz Ghazi Alexi why did the price of vanilla rice
For the past couple of year
First I'll say that vanilla gets kind of a bad rap for being really bored
But
After a little bit of research
Kind of falling for vanilla
What turns up
A little bit mad
What did you find out
First thing I found out somehow I never knew this
Vanilla actually comes
From a beautiful orchid
Why they left
I didn't know that end in the 19th century the French transplanted vanilla to several of its colonies in East
Including
Madagascar
Which
Turns out has a great climate for growing vanilla
The only problem
The insects that pollinate vanilla orchids in their native habitats
Do not live in Madagascar
So they have to be hand pollinated
One by one with like a little toothpick stick
It's super time-consuming and labor-intensive
And
Vanilla flowers only bloom one day a year
What
So the timetable can get pretty crunched
Delicate price
That is so well I can't decide if this
Extremely dark or extremely miraculous
And because Madagascar has become the main source of the world's natural vanilla
Up to 80%
The rest of us can often feel the fluctuations
Intercrop
At the ice cream store when we buy beijing
King supplies
Right that makes
For decades that wasn't really that big of a problem because vanilla buyers could just supplement that Supply with
Synthetic
Vanillin
A much cheaper lab-produced version of the plants
Essential ingredient
But what happened recently that made the prices go up
Well a couple of
First public taste begin to shift
Closer to getting more and more into natural ingredients instead of artificial flavors
In 2015 Nestle and Hershey's and other companies
Announce that they're going to switch from synthetic
Back to all natural vanilla
Which of course contributes to this huge spike in demand
And the price is going up
I wasn't there also like a hurricane in Madagascar
Recently that
Like wiped out a lot of
Crop someone on a tropical Cyclone hit Madagascar in 2017
Damaged one of the main vanilla producing regions of the country
And that made prices go even higher
And that's why I shalisa
Pay more at the register at Costco
Yes along with all of the ice cream junkies and Candy freaks of the world
Thank you
And how many listener service this is Karen how can I help you
Hi Planet Money this is Justin Lee and I want to know what's the economics of those
We Buy Houses signs
I want to know who wins and who loses
Thanks so much
We turned this one over to Jake
Goldstein and
Disappeared for a couple of days and came back with this
Special Report
Jacob I am delighted
To take this question
Because
In just the past few years.
We Buy Houses
Has been
Wetransfer
Formed in a really in
It used to be
Largely local businesses posting their phone numbers on telephone poles by in a few fixer uppers from people who are in a
Today
It is billion dollar tech companies
Buying thousands of homes that are in perfectly good shape from people who are doing
I talked about this shift with Glenn kelman
He's the CEO of Redfin this big sort of hybrid tech company real estate broker
And he told me about the first time somebody suggested that his company Redfin
Should get into the We Buy Houses
And then you know what I said
I'm too chicken
I won't do it
Courses
You have to put you know
Hundreds of millions of dollars on the line
Betting that Redfin could buy houses
Turn around and quickly sell them for a small profit
This is legitimately terrifying
But when told me
That would you intimate Terror notwithstanding
There were these
Three big changes that finally persuaded him and a bunch of other companies to get into this
The first is that
People who sell houses through redis
Are having a time getting a money fast enough to buy their next place in other words you're selling your house
You want to buy a new house
But after the financial
Crisis it's a lot harder to get a mortgage for the new house
Before you sold your old house
So there is this new group of people who could afford to make a move
But they just can't make the timing work
That is change number one
Change number to is computers
Algorithms technology
Companies like Redfin are building these algorithms that are really good
Estimating home
And then change number three
Is investors all around the world
Start throwing gobs of money
At tech companies
It was so much money
And it seem so easy to get
That it even surprised Glenn kehlmann
The CEO of a tech
Redfin
Got a call
From somebody representing Saudi Arabian money or Kuwaiti money
And then he said I've got a problem
I have all this money
And I need
To deploy it
He just wanted to give it to us
And that's what I felt like something really deep
Fundamental
Was changing in the global economy
Soap companies that have build algorithms to estimate home
Are now
Flush with money
And can use that money to start buying houses from home sellers who need money
Finally Glenn tells his employees
It is time to do
I think the subject of the email with something like
Strap on the Viking helmet
Go forth and conquer
They're mostly buying moderately-priced home
In subdivisions with lots of identical house
Because that makes it easier to
So if you live in a house
Like that
You can go online
Enter some details about your house
And in a few hours or a day
Get a cash offer from Redfin or one of his camp
Fast and easy but there is a trade-off
You probably will wind up getting
A few percent less
Then if you sold your house the old fashioned
Several other companies are getting into this
As well
Zillow Keller Williams
The one buying the most houses
It's called open door they have raised billions of dollars in debt and equity and around 10
Housing houses
Last year
Glenn says he can imagine
That's something like
10% of people might someday sell their home
And that is
Enough to be a little bit scary
I think it's a new thing in the economy
And if I had to pick
People
Make
Prudent bats
At the casino tables
Hack people wouldn't
Be that I remind myself would not
I just remind myself every night
If you look at the history of subprime you see people making a ton of money in that
Space
And other players getting drawn into it one by one
And it proved to be their demise
Because
Yeah you chase
Prophets
You follow the customer
Over a cliff
And yeah we're trying to be the one to beat those odds
Please hold for the next procrastinating
Planet Money this is Julia
Print money
Hi
Hey I was wondering
Why a barrel of oil is 42 gallons
I'm not around number like 40 or 50
Chamberlain is that you
Kenny I recognize your voice come on let's get in the studio
ILearn
Make the phone call okay. Crime okay I great
Reporter Kenny Malone what is the thing that you absolutely must have
A barrel of oil
Is 42 gallons and that is a weird number
It's not 40
And it's not V
And I learned why it is 42
On a reporting trip
Earlier this year
Reporter Julia Simon
Went to Titusville
Is the middle of the winter
This is the sound of a snowball
At the birthplace of the modern oil industry
Titusville is where America's first commercial oil well was
And I was back in the 1800s
Now
There's an oil Museum
Which is where we met
A curator named Sue Bates
To Julia noticed was wearing earrings shaped like oil
Oh I did that sound like little silver oil derrick
All about oil here
Sasu did explain to us that
In the 1800 oil people
Did in fact want to send and receive
A nice round 40 gallons
Problem
Which of these barrels were going to have to be pulled by horses
On crappie
Rocky Roads
And so
It was cited
That they would build in an extra 2 gal
And that ensured that 40 gallons would arrive at the refinery
It allowed to gallons for leakage
Right
Yeah yeah apparently there's oil all over the roads in this area Splash and spilling out
Gross
It is also worth noting that
Barrel makers apparently
Used to this 42-gallon size they have been
Making booze in barrels the size for a long time
I may be also
Answer the question a modern barrel of oil is 42 gallons
Because
The 1800s Titusville size Barrel
Became the Indus
Weather we
Thank you so much Kenny you were welcome one of our reporters will be with you sure
Dollars
This message comes from NPR sponsor Microsoft
At the Carlsberg research laboratory
Scientists are using Microsoft AI to reinvent the way they produce beer
See how AI is empowering business innovators at microsoft.com AI
What would you do if you found out a story that have shaped your identity was a lie
NPR news podcast
White Lies investigates murder in Selma Alabama from 1965 and exposes the
Conspiracy the captain
Until now
White Lies start listening to
Thank you for calling
Please remember
No problem
Vitamin E
Juliusspeak
Play Planet Money this is Jacob and I'm curious
768 Cuban in a
Chin world
What's the cost of being tall
So what are the cost of being tall
To answer this question we turned
Greg mrozowski who is 5-11
For the record
Greg pours over all kinds
Studies constantly to put our newsletter together
Hi Greg hey Julia what you got for us
So I talked to Jacob and he
He told me all about the
The cost of being tall
First clothes cost more everything I own shoes
Socks pants shirts
Ties everything is special order this cost like food dye wood
Naturally assumed I ate more than in an average human and then there are costs that have nothing to do with money
A concert and I always have a bunch of really ticked off people behind me oh my God I am one of those people
You so much I'm five foot one
I feel like every time I go to a concert there's somebody who's like
11 ft tall with big head
That guy I know so turns out there's actually a lot of studies about
But they're not about the cost of being told they're all about the Ben
So study after study
Spell gnat like
Call people on average they are better educated or happier and beardmore
In fact an influential study a few years back found
4 in increasing height
Was associated with
Average earnings boost of about 9
9% 9
Why is that we're coming to be about like why there's
Earnings premium for 12
People
Influential study and they explained it basically by breaking down how tall
People get tall
There's the science like you know your jean Seabiscuit by Greg have.
Potential to become a certain height
C511 okay okay for the nurture kicks in
If you get good nutrition and vaccinations
Send good Medical Care growing up you'll probably hit that potential
Your total height growth
And here is the important part
Your brain also
People who reach their Highest Potential also tends to reach their brain potential
Great that's basically like the takeaway from the study and we should save these people who grow up in these nurturing environment
And get all these benefits
They also tend to be more at 4
It's just like us
Super Advantage Psych
They get better schools
Food
They get better High
They got better money
Exactly okay but as somebody who grew up with good
Schools but is51
Are you telling me that I am not operating at
Performance of this study
You can't just like take Jacob who's 6 a.m.
They therefore he's smarter than you
These are just averages like if you
You take all the tall people's earnings and average that they earn more
And besides you're clearly brilliant so you obviously
Reached her genetic
Thank you so much Gray
Sure
All of our reporters are assisting other listeners
Please leave your question after the tone and it will be Google
I mean answered in the order it was received
Hi my name is hello Wisner I'm from Albany New York
And I've been having problems
Focusing at work
And I was wondering
If Ethan's effect
Workplace productivity
So far our very last question Julia and I
Enlisted the help of our
Plastic intern Rachel Cohn
She's amazing hero of the fields I think so oh my God
This is like too much pressure
So the question is like
Do you work better in the
The summer or the winter
I think that's right I think they're wondering like
Especially now that it's spring
Am I being less
Productive
And there isn't a lot of research
On season
But I did find this one study
From researchers were at Harvard and UNC
Chapel Hill
And what they did is they look
At how weather affects
Productivity
Specifically they were studying the productivity
People who are doing
Data entry
So this might be different
For people who are in
Rita fields
What they did is they collected two years worth of data from a bank
Bank in Japan
And they looked at you know how long it took workers their day after day
To enter information into a
And what they found
Was that for every 1 inch of rain
People were 1.3%
Faster
I completed
So basically bad weather was good for Prada
I know right
And you don't 1.3% might not sound like a lot on an individual
Put across the whole Bank
That can make a big difference
I think about what that could mean when it
Sunny outside
Businesses might be losing 1 Point
3% of the productivity
All of their workers
The researchers in this study estimated that 1.3% loss in product
Would translate to a loss in Revenue
Of 9
$500 a year
Yo million bucks
That's not nothing just a million dollars
Okay simple what are you do like we can't
I can't personally
Control the weather I did speak to one of the researchers involved with the
Study
And she suggested that businesses
Put just let
People go home early on sunny days
You know an acknowledgement of the fact that were less productive and we'll make up for it when it's raining I love is I think
Study and I think that on behalf of NPR and our list
We should probably just
Animal science toilets
Planet Money email newsletter
Money newsletter Planet Money newsletter Today's show was produced by
Alexi Horowitz
Thank you for listening
If you still have burning questions