This episode is part 2 of
But I at least I'm calling
The antitrust
And so Jacob Goldstein
I want you to imagine the words were about to say
Read the text.
Crawls across the screen
At the beginning of Star Wars
A little more than a hundred years ago the US government broke up the standard welcome
That was this
Essential early moment when the government stepped into the free market
Because it's not a big company was doing things that were bad for company
In the decades after that
The government got more and more aggressive
It intervened in the free market more and more
Until eventually
There was a backlash
Today's episode is about that backlash
And the man who made it home
Ladies and gentlemen is my privilege denied my very great privilege
Introduce one of the great constitutionalists about day The Honorable Robert Bork
This is from a speech a judge named Robert Bork gated in 1980s
Thank you can I was a poor signature look with this sort of Shaggy 19th century Style
Before we started working on these shows about Aunt
The thing that I knew about Robert Bork
Was that he was nominated to the Supreme Court
And rejected because Democratic senators did not like his long history of
Very conservative
Opinions on subjects like abortion
And civil rights
And when he died in 2012
That is the subject that his obituaries were
But there is something else about 4
But you don't hear as much
All these Reflections are prompted by the history of antitrust law
When I first started at Yale
I really thought
The situation of the law was hopeless
Robert Bork completely transformed the way antitrust law Works in this
He changed the very definition of what's legal and illegal
For Big Comfy
To do I mean
It changed it so much
It is shocking it is still the same law
And it seems like even Bourque with surprise
Body impact
The fact is
I simply underestimated the power of ideas
Now that's a very natural error for a professor
If you sit in enough faculty meetings
You are very like it underestimate the power of thought
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm taking Colton and I'm Kenny Malone
Today on the show how Robert Bork won the fight over the very meaning of competition in America
How to pave the way for some of the biggest most
Powerful companies
We've ever seen
Support for this podcast
Send the following message come from fidelity
As a Fidelity wealth manager
Client you get a dedicated advisor to help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of Pacs
And make it clear recommendation
Thanks for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
So let's talk about bork I mean did you know him did you work with him doing well this is Eleanor Fox
Professor at NYU
Sister political views are significantly more liberal than Robert
Works opposite
Well if you like
Leslie Mann
Very very nice very cordial very witty
Eleanor Fox started practicing law in 1960
Right around the time Robert Bork started
Teaching at Yale
And you found your way to anti
Frustrate you became an antitrust
Yeah it sounds it sounds
Luckily it founded
Why was luckily
Cuz I love it
Why do you love antitrust
But I loved David against Goliath and David against Goliath which side did you root for
Oh David
David and Goliath
So
Take B classic
From the first episode of this series
Goliath was Standard Oil
The giant Oil Company controlled by one of the richest men in the
David
With a little startup refiners
Standard oil bottle
Or forced out of business in order to gain control of 90% of
Have the refining biz
We just did a whole show on
What was the antitrust worldview when you started practicing in the night
It was for the little guy without power
It was the suspicion that when big
Firms did
Anything that made life
Tough work
Editor
That was probably illegal and you can really see this in this moment the 19th 6
The Supreme Court
Pushing antitrust
Further and further
Case-by-case in 1960
T2 Brown Shoe Company versus the United States
Tennis shoe company buy up a chain of shoe store
Supreme Court was like
No
That shoe company would just kick the other shoe brands out of those chain stores no
Can't do it 1966
United States vs Vons grocery
Hand to local grocery store chains merge in Los
I don't know
Merger after the merger they'd only have seven and a half percent
The local market
Supreme Court was like
No you can't do it would be too hard on Mom and Pop shops
Okay 1967
Utop High versus Continental baking
Can big
National frozen pie companies sell really cheap pies in Utah
I need business top 40 local Pike
No way okay but what is the local Pie Company controls most of the local market and keeps making a profit through
Most of the price for
Still no show in case after case
The court kept
Ruling for the little guy kept ruling for team David
And expanding the definition of what was it legal what was bad for comfort
So there was
A kind of joke
At the time
That the Supreme Court was like the little boy who
13 News
How to spell banana but didn't know when to stop
But what I want to sleep
I'm trying to spell banana but didn't know where to stop so we kept going
Banana nano3
But finally I got
Right she was saying that it was appropriate for the Supreme Court to find for David to find for small businesses
In some cases
That's the banana
Banana
But the court didn't stop there
It kept intervening into
We probably should have just left the market alone
That's beat naanaanaa
And to be clear for Eleanor Fox
The basic antitrust worldview at the time
What's correct
It was just
Did the court went too far in a
But Robert Bork did not see it that way
At all
He's going to law school at the University of Chicago where he was
Profoundly influenced by this group of economist
And lawyers
Who are arguing in a very Broadway that in general the government was way too involved
When brake applied this
Chicago School logic 2
Antitrust
He didn't see just a
Few weird Supreme Court decision
Instead
She saw an entire worldview built on a fundamental misunderstanding of what
Competition bench
And what the point of antitrust was supposed to be
We set out to destroy that
Just reduce it to rubble and build a whole new world you in its place
He started writing and arguing
And in 1978
He published what was arguably the most important work on antitrust
Ida Tarbell took on John Deere a
Propeller and stand
It was a book
Call the antitrust
Paradox
Do you remember when that book came out
Was it a big deal
Yes
Did you see people reading it like was it did it have a moment
Would you be on the subway in Pokemon go
People I hate
You read
I don't know you were assumed to have
Jake and I both have copies of the
We both read it
And it's an important book that we're going to talk about for a little bit
Because in this book
Work goes through those cases from the 1960s
And many many more
It essentially says
If you look at these you can see clearly antitrust policy has gone
Way too far
For example the brown shoe
If a shoe company wants to buy a shoe store
Fine
If the shoe company forces out other brands and then consumers want those other brands
They will go to another store the shoe company will either start selling those other brands again or go out of business
Either way
The free market will sort it out the government
Did not need to intervene
Vons grocery store case that case work
Two stores wanted to merge into one
You know he looks at that University says yes
Sometimes mergers are bad
You know I say
Two firms merge and get 100% of the market
That's clearly definitely bad
And in fact you know he steps back any looks and he finds this threshold that's way below that
He says it may be reasonable to block murders where the new firm would have more than 40 per
Percent of the
Vons grocery store case in LA
Pause would have had seven and a half percent of the Los Angeles grocery store
You want to bet he says
That's not bad
Clearly we can let that
Also that you taught Pi case
Where the company said it was the victim of a price War but kept selling pies at a profit
Work looks back at that
And wrote
There is no economic theory
Worthy of the name they could find an injury to competition on the facts
Defendants were convicted
Not of injuring competition
But quite simply
Worx big argument in the book
The point of antitrust is
Just encourage
Everybody
But
Encouraging competition
Doesn't
Mean protecting David against Goliath
You know if Goliath comes along and make some more pleasant groceries
Restore ourselves a cheaper frozen pie
Then go I should win and David should lose that is what competition mean
The Supreme Court in bork's
The View was not encouraging competition it was
Protecting companies like
The Utah Pie Company
But didn't want to compete
The court was using antitrust law
To make competition itself
That is a pear
Antitrust
The law that is supposed to help competition
Was actually harming
Import in this book not only pointed out these problems
He also
Argued first
The chi said was to stop focusing on comp
Predators Andino David
The other David and Goliath
Instead work said
We should focus on protecting consumer
So you don't straight-up price-fixing what a bunch of companies get together and decide not to compete on price
That is definitely bad for consumers we should go after that
Also you know like those murders if a company
Buys up all the other companies in its business like Standard Oil did
Pretty clearly bad for consumers
Butt pork look back at lots of other things
The court found illegal
Price Wars manufacturers buying retailer
Small merge
And he says those are usually fine
If they lead to lower prices or better stuff
That's good for consumers
And if they don't
Consumers will shop somewhere else
We can leave this to the free market
You can almost boil the book down in
$0.01
That's in the final
Says
The only goal that should guide the interpretation of the antitrust laws
Is the welfare of consumer
Consumer welfare with is really pretty different goal for anti
Work was saying
When a business wants to do something we're not so sure about
We've been focusing on how this will affect
The other business
We should be focusing on how this will affect
The consumer
After the book came out consumer welfare became this viral phrase among conservative antitrust
Did you have a sense that it would be impactful when you read it
I think
Yes
But
I probably could not have imagined how impactful it would be
Say more about that
Oh cuz it became the Bible
In 1980
Ronald Reagan was elected
He was very much on board with this free market cost
His administration adopted new much more permissive
Very bourke's merger guidelines
Built around this idea of
Consumer welfare
And that idea also transform the way the Supreme Court itself thought about anti
The court cited the antitrust Paradox the year after it came out
And then for decades in one ruling after another after another
The court started reversing its earlier antitrust decision
And using the consumer welfare standard
To legalize more and more kinds of business
There was an argument going on in the seventies
And and
WorkOne
K1
Are we still living in in
Bourque's world
Yes
This consumer welfare stand
Now
Define
Antitrust law
You heard it just last year when
Another antitrust case came before The Supreme
Luke 16:14 54 Ohio at all versus American
American Express in this case was definitely the Goliath and
1 minute and 15 seconds into the oral arguments
Justice Neil Gorsuch
Broken with a
We're not here to protect
Competitors ripeness Murphy
Protecting consumers
Correct just like the ghost of Robert Bork was sitting there whispering and Justice Gorsuch
My question is do you have any evidence fit on a net basis consumers pay more and I don't believe you have
The court found in favor of American
Express
Some antitrust
Cases are
You know a bunch of
Companies collude to fix prices
That is obviously bad for competition obviously bad for consumers
The government should
Definitely stop it
Under the companies prevented from happening
But there are lots
And lots and lots of anti-drug
Face
When a manufacturer wants to buy a retailer
Or when a bunch of companies start engaging in a price War
When it is much harder to
Figure out whether the government should intervene
And what are the really striking things is
A lot of the time
The answer you get to
Is basically the result of where you start
If you start out thinking
You know the free market muesli work
New competitors can come in and take business away from the big established player
Then you will usually want to let the free market sorted
But if you think the free market just
Doesn't work that well if you think it's
Pretty easy for big companies to use their power to suppress competition
Then you will think yeah it a lot of those sort of hard call cases
The government should intervene in the free market in order to make free market competition
Eleanor Fox
Says she thinks of the bork Revolution
The Chicago School Revel
Into
The first part
What's a useful corrective
Some of the accessories of the 60
It really did sharpen thinking about the economics of
And what competition really me
But there was also this second
There was never explicit
But that second part she says
Was implicit in everything Robert Bork
The second part is about the
Presumption
That the market works really well that government intervention is
Really bad that government messes up when it comes in
That friends can take care of themselves and if they don't do right the market will catch them
So that second part is the ideological part the first part
We needed badly and we got and we adjusted to it
The second part we didn't need
Foxes that second part
The assumption that the free market is good government intervention is
Is bad
Has pushed the government and the court too far in the other direction
The government just doesn't bring antitrust cases as often as it used to
And when it does it's like the banana joke
He's back but
Instead of fighting for David ever
Now the court almost always rules in favor
As a result
In lots of Indus
Food production in
Banking
And Airlines and on and on and on
A smaller number of firm
Is controlling a
A bigger and bigger share of
This tends to feel beautiful pretty abstract to us
SF consumer
Just in the past few years
And even really just in the past
Year
This issue has suddenly come to feel much more
Much more real much more sort of visceral much more
And this is largely
Because of the
Incredibly fast rise of a few gargantuan
Basically Google Facebook
And Amazon
The world Robert were created was the world that made it possible for those companies to get so big
And so powerful
Next time on planet money has the board Revolution gone too far
Amore the point
What should we do about these giant death
Support for this podcast
Cast in the following message come from the Annie E Casey
Foundation
Developing solution system
Support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is
Is available at aecf
. org
We love to hear what you think about the show you can email us Planet Money at NPR. Or
Margie were also on Twitter and Instagram at Planet Money our editors Brian first that are supervising producer
Is Alex goldmark
Today Show was produced by Sally Helm and Alexi Horowitz Ghazi also thanks to our intern Rachel Cohn
We are now accepting applications of for a summer intern you should apply if you're interested you get to do lots of interests
Things you get paid
Are you can find out more about it at NPR. Org
Slash money
The Robert Bork audio you heard at the beginning of the episode comes from a 1987 speech he gave to the Philadelphia
Supreme Court tape you heard in this episode comes from the website oyez.org
I'm coming alone
And I'm Jacob Goldstein thanks for listening
By the way Jacob
I made something for
I would love for you to
More it comes on for 7 minutes
I want to hear every ma more
Yes no
Okay.