Support for NPR and the following message
Which come from WWE
Publishers of people power and profit
Progressive capitalism for an age of discontent
By Nobel prize-winning economist
Joseph E stiglitz
Everyone Stacy here
Today Show originally aired back in 2016 and we have an update for
At the very end
Last year on Valentine's Day Fred Ruckel was sitting on his couch at his house in Upstate New York
And his wife Natasha was playing the piano for
What are you playing
Something she made up
Sometimes I just sit there and let my fingers go and see what Tunes melodies
Come out and emigrate but Fred loves him
I love them
Actually paying that much attention to the music he was paying attention to this new little kitten that they've gotten
So who is this
But she can introduce yourself with this is Yoda
Hey Kitty we say something
At some point I'm going to have to get Yoda to meow
Got to get the sound of the cat radio when I want to try to meow
We'll get to that
Anyway friends playing with
The kitten and he takes a little toy mouse that Yoda has a
Throws it across the room and it slides across
The floor and they have a rug that's a little bit rumpled up and the mouse slides across the
Therefore right into one of the little rumbles in the rug
And the cat
Goes
Bananas
And she immediately attacked it just ran and started putting her paws underneath then playing with it and
Fred said nice out there we said we going to make the Ripple rug and I looked
What you mean what's the Ripple rug
Ripple rug
The Ripple rug
The Ripple rug is a cat
It is basically the size
Of a doormat
Robert in the show you
The Ripple rug this is it
This is
The rebel ride
I don't know how to describe describe it looks like someone's taking a carpet
They've cut holes into it so it looks like swiss cheese and then they have
Wadded-up
The carpet
Turn on the floor
Yeah that's essentially the report apparently Disneyland
A year later Natasha and Fred are selling
$60,000
Ripple rugs every month
Debutantes Today Show
They have set up a shop
Open Amazon Marketplace
Amazon Prime
And the Ripple rug was one of Amazon's best-selling pet toys
39 99
And then one day Fred gets the
Missed call from
My brother-in-law's like hey did you see it's on eBay cuz he's always looking at stuff on eBay
And I was like what
Fred was immediately to his
Computer logs
EBay I just typed in the Ripple rug and there was already for sellers selling the Ripple rug and then every single
All day there would be five more six more
10 more
How much were they charging
They were going as high as 5999
That's
$20 more than he was selling them for on Amazon
Beastly people were scalping Ripple
Buying and selling them on eBay at a market
All these people who read a Natasha never met
We're getting rich off of their invention
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Stacey Vanek Smith and Robert Smith
The internet was supposed to get rid
Of the middleman
What they told us consumers were supposed to buy directly from manufacturers no more going to people like
Travel agents having to pay fees
Internet was going to be about getting stuff from the source
For a wholesale price
It did not work out that way
Just ask the makers of
The Ripple rug
The internet has made it so that anyone can be a middleman
Or a middle person
Middle person doesn't sound as good as middle man
Screw
Today on the show a middleman or taking over the global economy
Support for NPR comes from LinkedIn learn
Proud to support the launch of life
NPR Sky to help you make better life decision
LinkedIn learning short video tutorials cover
For business tax
And creative skills employers look for at every level
All talk by X
Mu courses are added every week
+ LinkedIn learning
Personalized
Recommending courses based on your interest
And life
Kid listeners get a month of learning
Restart your free
Trial at LinkedIn learning.com NPR
Winford Rocco saw all of these people selling the Ripple rug on eBay
He went a little nuts
He started spending hours everyday checking eBay and trying to get in touch with
The people who are selling his cats
Did you ever try to contact any of the
Mittleman
I have reached out to many of them I've sent cease-and-desist orders to every single one of them
Well hello
One of them stop
The letters did not work and then Fred started tracking down their phone number
And personally calling them
I am Fred from snuggly cat the makers of the Ripple rug and calling you about you selling our product illegal alien
You know I'm not telling you
Well I mean
BB guitar probably right there's nothing illegal about buying something and reselling it there's even name for it we used to
Arbitrage arbitrage mean
You buy something cheap in one place
You sounded expensive in another
Yes but this is a
Twist on Arbitrage called drops
And it's kind of
Genius because there is
Basically no risk involved at all
These people never bought a ripple in their closet and then sold
They never actually
Touch the Ripple rug
They just
Wait until a customer buys
The Ripple rug from them
And then they buy it from the Amazon store
And ship it directly from Amazon
To the Past
And the customers
Have no idea where the River Run comes from all I know is they paid $60 instead of $40 and the Ripple rug
Showed up they thought it came from
Clevermade
Exactly and the dropshipper can just pocket the difference
Okay it is easy to resent
People who have found a way to make some easy money
This is good for Fred this is goodbye
For Fred and Natasha and for the Ripple rug
Because this
Lita
Middleman whoever they are there advertising
The product
And yeah they're adding money to an aggravated making a profit but they act
It's the sort of
We have sales
Out there pushing Ripple rug
Getting into people's hands
Yes they don't actually do any of the work
But they were making more sales
But Fred says there are a couple of problems
The first is that he is trying to build a brand
It's not just about selling one ripplerock it's about building the snuggle
Cat brand so part of
A luxury cat toys
Christ is a big part of
Branding and so he wants to control his Brandy wants to control the prices
What is product doesn't want people selling it for all kinds of different
But the real problem was if he says he was losing money
Because what was happening
These people were ordering this product on eBay
And the Box showing up at their doorstep was from Amazon
Two people get confused they would look up the product on Amazon and they would realize
They said they had paid $20 more
For the rubber rug needed to pay
And so they would think I'm just going to return it to eBay and
Order from Amazon
Let's say you feel cheated you say I want to return it cuz
It's 3999
Honey you know Amazon for real
I paid 5999 they're both free shipping and free returns
I'll return this one order from there
But you're not returning the product
To the middleman
To the people I mean by you're really Return of the product
Back to front
And that comes with a whole boatload of feasible
Apparently so Amazon charges fees all along the way they have a fever
For the purchase of
Before shipping it
Thank you for the return if
Restocking
And then when the customer reorders it from Amazon
There's another
Another
Sprint has a lot of times the rugs with comeback used
So he had to
Just right then he couldn't
Resell them
And just two months after
Fred noticed all these dropshippers on eBay
He said he had over 200
Which was over 10000 losses in
Just a couple of months
You lost $10,000 in 2 months into months
Meanwhile the eBay people
All the people who are charging $60 for this pocketing the extra $20 different
They get to keep the money yeah they're not paying any of the
The geniuses
Do you want me to go first you can go first back
Okay I'm first all right though hello my name is Nikki with a
Hello my name is Parrish Witherspoon
Nicki and parashar dropshippers I talked to them on Skype
And the city never sold the Ripple rug but they do sell tons of cat toys and household products in
Supplies and all kinds of things on eBay store
And with the make any of those things
They don't have possession of any of those things they just
Mark up the price
And send them on to
The customer that is what they do
America got started in this business when they were both living in Baghdad
In Iraq they were working for private contractors
And they were spending all of their time
Buying stuff online
You know groceries and household type stuff
Furniture
We bought a car online
We bought a house online we bought a dog online
Adam schitt
Dodging ships from Oklahoma to Iraq we sure did that wasn't
Nicky and Paris are very familiar with buying things online and they decide to give dropshipping
A try
The sign up for the company called
DS Domination PS4 Dropship
Exactly
And think it's software that helps them find these best selling products on Amazon
Copy the images from Amazon set up a little store on eBay and figure out how much to charge for these
These products if they're dropped
They start out selling mostly.
Toys and Novelty
See items and almost right away
She says she realizes
This is going to be
Be a big
I'll never forget it it was like an Angry Birds Star Wars set that we had got and it it took off in
In less than 48 hours
I mean you just kind of sit back and you're like
I just paid
$0.30 for this item and it
It's old were like 9 bucks
About 30 times today
You know
It was just an amazing feeling
An amazing profit
I'm just did that one day they made you know what
Twitter 60 bucks
Yeah nothing yeah
And after just a few months of this they were making enough money that they were both able to quit their jobs in a rock and
And moved back to the US
To Houston
And now they say they make more than a million dollars a year in sales
Steve
No they were selling like dumb little toys
Well they've expanded into a whole bunch of other thing
Think they're wholesaling now and
Doing private label stuff but
Nikki told me they will never stop doing the drop ship
It's just it's just too easy
Portsmouth. Some some tools in there that kind of automate everything
Really just a matter of pressing a button and your stores kind of ran for you
So you know what that that's profit that
You know if it's that easy to do why would we not keep it you know
Did you ever feel like
We're not actually doing anything we're just
We're just charging to post it you don't even like you're not adding anything to the product or anything like that
Did you feel weird about that
Not not really honestly
You know when you're actually doing it it does require some work you're having to do the tracking
You know I'm a say for instance if Amazon is is out of
Parts of a particular item
I'm get to go to a national retail location grab that item put in the Box make sure your customer gets it you're doing all the cuss
Customer service you're making sure that that customer is happy
There's no issues with it
And you know Caitlin control I mean if you're doing the whole thing
When you put it that way
They sound like a retail
They sound like a retail store that wants
Customers to return
And even though they don't make
The products are even really even ship the body to touch the products
They're the public face
Of the prompt
Yeah in a lot of ways retailers are
Just mittleman
But to Fred and Natasha the cat rug makers
Guys on the internet or just scalp
They were making the products a lot more expensive
Customers
They were not adding anything to it
Jason feifer is the editor-in-chief of Entrepreneur magazine
He wrote about the ruckles and dropshipping if there's a bad guy in this story
Really
It's us
What know it's us
Have you ever bought anything on eBay
Yes
Did you ever
Think where it came from
No seller
The Cellar right there yeah you don't know where it came from
That mentality
Create this opportunity
Still with our fault because
We aren't shopping around we cuz we're not searching for the original Ripple rug at the original $40
Exactly we don't want to look around on the internet
It's so the middle men are saving us a couple of keystroke
A few seconds here and there
Yeah and we are willing to
To pay for that $5 10 dollars $20 we are paying for that
All I have to do is go to another website
NC
The prices differ
And I don't
It's crazy like why am I not doing that
I mean as long as we are all willing to
Taken advantage of by
Different Market
Places even though we have all the information in front of us
It would literally Take 5 Seconds no time at all
And we don't do it
So if we're not going to do it
Why can't people take advantage of us
We are the problem
Like this gets to something
Because although economics treat us like economically rational beings always hunting for the best price
The truth is
We are all deeply lazy
Inside
And
There's always someone who will help us
Be a little bit lazier
For a profit
And I guess it's always with all that you know one-click shopping the internet has made us
Lazier
And it's simultaneously created all these opportunities for
For people to jump in and make things even easier but to take a little slice of the profit here
Exactly
Do you like save us a couple
Spooky strokes and Charters little more
Michael Munger is an economist at Duke
He has been studying the middleman for years
All you have to do is have a computer with a connection to the internet the ability to write code
And you can be a middleman it's the most competitive industry the world has ever known
Being a middleman
Being a middleman that's what people all over the world want to do
I want to write an app
That will sell and I'll make a lot of money but the app itself can't make any good or service all I can do is
Bring together
A buyer and a seller who otherwise wouldn't have met that's the essence of being a middleman
Think about it a lot of the hottest companies in the world right now are
Essentially just middlemen
Yeah and we don't even think of them as middleman right or I'm going to get an Uber
That's what I say I'm going to Uber so a car is going to show up Uber all over is a middleman between me
Add a driver they don't own any car
Cars they don't employ any drivers
They just take a slice of profit for connecting the two of us
Same with Airbnb
Kayak
EBay and Amazon Alibaba all just
Middleman
So
The future of the economy is really
Becoming more and more about
Middleman
Getting people
Much much much more efficiently
Goods and services you're not going far enough it's about almost nothing else
Is more middle name
Good
That's like asking is gravity good
We are comparing middlemen to gravity
I'm comparing the economic logic of selling reductions in transactions
Irresistible inevitable
So inevitable but even middlemen are worried
About middle
No
Yes
Nikki and Parrish Witherspoon the Amazon to eBay drops
Shippers would not even give me the name of their store on
Because they were worried that someone would go to their store copy all the items they were selling
Set up their own store
And sell them for a little bit less
People that are lazy will go in instead of doing the research like we did
We'll just go and take what you having
You start selling it
They're not going to have to do the work
But you did to go research the item
Dropshipping way I thought like
The whole is not the whole thing
Absolutely it
It is absolutely it that you don't find it's not for you to call
Copy other
Right right that's why I was
But their whole business is copying other people
Yes but they said that they know things they gotten
Really good at their business of theirs and they don't want somebody stealing their ideas
Middleman
Are like gravity there just inevitable
Call me if there's any little bit of profit left on the table somewhere
Someone is going to grab
There is one man who has decided to fight
To fight the middleman
Fred Ruckel
Are Ripple rug maker
He was spending hours a day
Trying to shut down
Dropshippers
First thing in the morning check for arbitrageurs last thing at night
Check for Arbitrage to send out any cease-and-desist before or after
It was taking up inordinate amount of time and it was a super stressful
A couple months ago Fred did something
Drastic
Keep hold the Ripple rug off of the Amazon Prime Market
No more free Prime shipping Amazon store
That is where the arbitrageur
We pulled out of the hole in Prime shipping thing in May
And at that point we were over 60000 a month in sales
And in a blink
60000 went down to
$25
Oh my gosh
That's a big price you paid
I would say it was a huge price
Is it worth it
Well we had put together
Really that's all I mean that's so much money that's like
Integrity is important
Stress Factory trust so we removed all the stress
Bread and Atasha started doing all of their own shipping
And they converted their garage into
A little pack
King facility
Gotten really good with those
Envelopes
And the night before I saw them they both been up until midnight
A video had gone up online with a couple of
Cat celebrities minor cat celebrities named Cole and marmalade playing on a ripple rug
An order
Had been pouring in
And so we spent two hours each packing last night and then this morning we spent another two hours each packing
That's 8 hours
For one person right there
Pimp so this isn't make you wish slightly that you were still
Using Amazon to do all the shipping
People would be arbitraging our products
I don't know if they see it seems like
Everybody's
Losing out of
This decision threatened to Tasha are losing money they're not selling it
Beat the dropshippers the arbitrageurs
They're not making as much money reselling these things
And their product
Which seems like a great product
Is harder to get cats everywhere are suffering because Fred and Natasha won't just suck it
Shut up and deal with the middleman
All of that is true
But there's an emotional component
And Fred and Natasha invented this
They felt a lot of ownership for it and to them
It felt like people were coming in
And taking like a bite out of
The Sting Main Event they were
Essentially sort of stealing their product
Acton Subway
And for frigid Ashley just wanted
Control back they didn't want to be up at night and up in the morning trying to
Polder products back from all of these differ
Forces
They just wanted total control vent and the loss of money they told me it was worth it today
Now for the Natasha are mostly selling Ripple rugs Direct
We from their website and they told me sales are starting to come back after
For the initial Bay
Big drop off
And they were very pleased to say in the last 4 months
They have only had
To return
Will you meow
Kitty kitty kitty
We reached out to both Amazon and eBay Amazon did not get back to us
EBay did respond saying that dropshipping
Is not against its rules
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Game Bridge
The Bold way to steady growth
People often think of nobodies are too conservative
Too complex or only for retirees
But annuity
These can be a smart way to Head Market risk
Can earn guaranteed returns
Cambridge aims to change the game
By offering simplified annuity
He's in a Sleek digital experience
That replaces fine print in
Phone tag with
Clear conditions and a direct loafy model
Learn more at gamebridge. Life
5 / NPR
Game Boy
Page is not available at Allstate
Everybody
It's Stacey it is now it 2019
Simpsons episode first aired Fred and Natasha say they have largely solved their Dropship
They have a new problem
Counterfeit
Of course Fred and Natasha Archer
Termans to fight the counter
They told us about this one group that was selling fake Ripple rugs
And the way that they tracked
This one down was
Pretty ingenious
I saw a TV commercial
Still advertising
Ripple rug
Knock off
So
They worked backwards
From that commercial
Because you know it looked like it had been shot in the studio
We were versus engineer their shoot for their video and knew what kind of environment and had to
To be filmed in
Then we looked
For casting calls we found how they cast
The cats for the commercial
They actually had a casting call for cats or kittens on Facebook
The casting call was looking for
Quote
Kittens born to be Stars
Using
The casting call and finding different people that responded on Facebook we were able to facially track the cats back to the owner
And that's how we originally busted this open
Now for the Natasha are helping other in
They set up a website
Site called as stolen on TV.
That's one word as stolen on tv.com
It is a service that helps you
People take on
Their own copycats
As always we like to hear what you think of the show email list
Planet Money at NPR. Org
Or tweet
WeChat us
We are at Planet Money
Our episode today was originally produced by Nick found
The rerun was produced by Darian woods and Rachel
A huge thanks to Jason Pfeiffer you should really check out
His article about Dropship
Entrepreneur magazine
And he also has a new podcast called
Pessimist archive
Apparently is a history of unfounded
Ears
Json is fearless
And we have a new route
Planet Money videos
For your viewing pleasure
Our first short video from the 2019 season is about vodka
Go to npr.org
Planet Money shorts
There you can see what Kenny Malone would look like in the 70s
80's 90's
Today that's npr.org
Planet Money shorts
I'm Stacey Vanek
And I'm Robert Smith thanks for listening
Wynfred Russell the Ripple rug
Wynfred Russell the Ripper
That
Wynfred Russell the guy
Wynfred Russell
Fred ruckel Ripple rug
Sounds like
Badboidavee
The people always Shout