This episode originally ran in 2016
At the end of the show will give you an update on this
On a hot day in the summer of 2012
Derek Walters drives
To the Rio Casino in Las Vegas
He's going there to play in the most famous poker tournament in the world
The World Series of Poker main event
What do you wear to these tournament
Personally I just try to
We're like comfortable clothes
Like a tracksuit
Not not attracted I try to like
Look presentable just like jeans
T-shirt hoodie
Sunglasses or no sunglasses
I don't wear sunglasses
Yeah it would just be weird
Timmy wearing them inside
Because in fact
It is weird to wear sunglasses inside
We're back in Las Vegas for the 43rd edition of poker's most prestigious tournament
Derek like everyone at the tournament has to pay
$10,000
To play
If you wins
First prizes
Eight and a half million.
Derek is a professional
And he figures he's got an itch there's always going to be
Simpro is at your table and there's going to be some recreational players
Usually kind of like split half and half
When you say recreational players or is that just a nice guy saying bad
Yes that's the yeah that's a PC weigh at one of the
The PC way to say no
Derek is going to pick off these recreational players
One by one
And make
The Killing that is the plan anyway
But that is not how things
On the very first day of the tournament Jericho's All In
And you lose
He's out
It's a pretty bad feeling
You lose loss of your chips what you put them over to the other player end
Just kind of collect your things and just like
Do the Walk of Shame out of the poker broom to your car
The hallways are so quiet
Just because like everyone's out their seats playing
The $10,000 Derek used to buy into the World Series of Poker
That is gone
And Derek
Is completely out of the tournament
Except
He isn't
In fact the 2012 main event is going to be the biggest payday of Derek Walters life
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm keep Rohmer and I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Today on the show The Secret World
Big money poker turn
What you see on TV that is just the surface of
There is a game
Behind the game
Support for this podcast
In the following message come from the Annie E Casey
Sea Foundation
Developing Solutions
It support strong families and community
To help ensure a brighter future for America's chilled
More information is available at aecf
. org
Stacy yes
I want you to get ready for some sweet ESPN poker.
All right bring it on before 6598 players compete for poker is most import
Morton title the tournament rooms are empty
No players
No dealers no Stories the only thing that fills the room
Is Hope
That is how you report on an empty room
Outside that empty remote there are some pretty great stories
One of those stories is about that player Derek you heard of the beginning
He's renting this house about five miles south of the Las Vegas Strip with some of his poker but
It's a nice house there's a pool table upstairs swimming pool in the back
The youngest guy in their group is just 21
He's a skinny guy with longest hair they were kind of
Swept across his forehead
His name is Jake Paul
He told us he didn't actually get his own room in this
Sleeping on the couch
There was a huge couch looks pretty nice actually
In terms of this group of guys that you're staying with
Were you kind of the low man on the totem pole
Unquestionably
Jake cannot afford to buy into the
It cost $10,000 and he's in college
What is friends with a bunch of the guys we come down for a visit
He figures he'll go home once the tournament
I no intention of playing it
You know you was a lot of money night
I didn't get them for asking that or anything you know
Tonight
My friend Max is having his birthday party that day
Actually literally packed up
Everything about the Vegas into my car
And I was going to leave in there like you to just hang out the other party for you to a couple hours I can drive home like anytime today is fine just the same
For a little bit
The party goes on for a while
People are drinking
And Derek and the other guys are like
Jake you got to do this you just turned 21 you can actually legally play in the tournament it's the World Series
Is the main event
I don't have any good mood.
But they're like oh you know many you got to find Amanda's to stay for the main won't buy a piece
The guy say look we will
Payforit we will pay the $10,000 so you can play who are these friends
I don't know I don't have friends
Actually they're not just
Giving him the money
His roommates are offering to stake him
That is the
And what it means is that they're going to be investing in jail
If someone ships in 10% of the buying back I will get 10% of whatever Jake
Kids sleeping on the couch
Did you pass a hat in
And people just be like I'll put in 1500 like how did that actually work
Really pretty much though so I don't know who first said it but one of them was like yeah you know I'll take like
10%
10 + 15
If I lost I lost but it's not to do tutorial
So if Jay Quinn
He would get to keep some of them
But most of it would go to his roommates
Like Derek
Terry puts in $1,500
And now he basically owns shares in
Jake is a stalker
MGK is not his only invest
Derek actually has to make it
Spreadsheet
To keep track of all the players he
Investing money
I see a lot of these
Are screen names is that okay
Yeah that's fine
Okay so
Acid night
5%
Chip soccer 5%
Zach vac
5%
Jumanji board 5%
Covino 5%
Skillz that killz 5%
Casewell
5%
9 ml 5%
John Kay 5% man-child 5%
Jake 15%
I think that's
I think that's it
Some of these guys Derek is friends
But some he says
He wouldn't recognize even if you ran into them at the tournament
They're just poker players that he finds online
So you just said
Five hundred bucks to a dude named chip tracker that you've never seen in your life
Yeah probably like half a
Deals I do like I never meet the person
Yeah
So this is part of the game behind the game
Poker tournaments are really expand
A lot of the players you see on TV they are not playing with their own money
Even really good players
Most the time I enter a tournament
They're going to lose
And even if they do win
Only a few people going to win the really big
Poker tournaments are
Sort of a recipe
Fever burning through a lot of
Being a professional poker player is like having a job where you get paid once
Every 10 years
And when you do get paid it's a lot of money it's
10 years worth of money
But there are a lot of
Meantime
Before that that's why poker players like Derek spread their risk around a lot
Instead of just making one giant bat on themselves
They make all these other little bits to
Buying shares in other players can get expensive
So there's another thing
The trade shares of the
Hotels with other players
Before the Tournament begins Derek does this to
It's a simple system
He finds a guy he wants
Trade with and they make a deal
I'll give him 5% of whatever I win
And he'll give me 5% of whatever he wins
For this tournament Derek made
5 swap
I swapped with
My friends chardin
Max
Jake RJ and
Indonesia
They're all Vipers
These are all handshake deals by the way
No contract
Normally yo-yo planet
Like a day in advance so disliked message your friends
Like make sure you guys are on the same page with
The swaps
But sometimes you'll just see you like a friend you haven't seen in awhile in the hallway and be like oh yeah
What's waffle bit
Deal just send a text message and say hey if you win $8000000 I'll get 5% of it right you're cool then I'm cool that like
That's it
Yep that's it
Derek says you only really want to swap percentages with someone who's as good as you
Has someone ever asked you to swapping your like I don't know I'm sorry I think
Not so good
At 1 move is like someone asks you to swap you don't really want to hear like real like swap 1/4
There's a lot of ways you could deal with
The situation
But you can just say oh sorry I'm swapped out I've already swapped
With so many people
You know and it's not a big deal
Derek is not the only one doing all this swapping a
And buying and selling by
He estimates that something like
Half of the players in this tournament have sold a percentage of
And even more than that or swapping p
I would say basically every professional is swapping
And this
Can we do some awkward situations
Like what if Derek and Chip Chuck
End up sitting next to me
Why would Derek Titanic ship Tracker out that hurts
Damn that's his invest
Did it ever happen to you end up
At at the same table with somebody to swap shares with are you you own shares of
Yeah that happens all the time
And
Yeah as long as you have liked
Small percentage of them it's not really a big deal
But I mean it's only like in the business world or in the professional world or
In the world
We would call this
A conflict of
Yeah it is definitely a conflict of interest and
You don't want to
You don't want to cheat the other players basically
I asked a lot of poker players about this
Anniversary outside
Yeah
This could be a problem
But this point the shares players have in each other
Pretend to be pretty small
And there's just not a way to help out the other guy without hurting your own chances
Either they get my chips or I get my check
You can't have it both ways
This is a tournament for everyone and everyone is here prose amateur
Dreamers
This is the scene when the tournament starts their three giant rooms in the Rio Casino poker tables as far as
As you can see there are six
How old in people playing in this term
Can hear the sound of the chips in the room
Derek is we mentioned got knocked out of the tournament on his first date but because of the game behind the game
He is not out
Between all of the swaps and chairs
He's got a piece of 15 players who are still in the turn
It is like this little army of Derek's out
All trying to win him
All right so what's 13 and 1/2 million chip pot they see the tray of space
Bev's on the river
The tournament keeps going
Day one day two day three
Derek's Army of players gets knocked out one after the other
By the middle of day for
Eric's only got four players left
Then ship tracker goes down
Batman child
141 pros and amateurs continue on day 5 then case
Swell gets knocked out
Derek is only got one chance
Left in this
One player he is now pinning all of
Hope sign
Jake
The 21 year old kids sleeping on the couch the one whose friends chipped in throat
Play the tournament
They won with defense
Becky went pretty well
And then from day 3 and on I was just like running very very good
Over the course of that week
I did the guy somehow start treating you any differently
They let me move into the master bedroom from the couch
Definitely moved up in the world
The guys who paid for Jake to play they decide they need to take better care of their vest
So get some ass
Master bedroom
And whatever else you want
Derek says
If Jake wanted something to drink at the poker table you like fancy juices
One of the guys would bring it to
I know definitely one of his request at the time was Naked Juice
We we did a lot of that
I'd like the green kind of the fruit kind yeah I'm not sure
And Jake just keeps winning
And hanging around
Now back to balsiger
Running deep in this 21 year olds first-ever main event he makes a 2 million straight
And hanging around
Turn on Jake Paul's I got the twenty-one-year-old coming off his junior year at Arizona State for the raise to a half million
Hanging around
And windows 6598
Players finally get window down
29 players
The final table of the tournament
You know who still wasn't knocked out
Getting to be one of the nine players at the final table
Table is a big deal
Poker players try their whole lives to get there
And Jake makes it the first year he's even legally allowed inside the casino
5 minutes
The literal best feeling there as you know like
During the entire time you're just on like complete Cloud 9
The final table is played in this theater with a thousand or two thousand seats
Jake is wearing the same blue plaid shirt he wore for everyday
It's really cool environment very high energy you know people like Siri
People are just getting Fairy like
John Kerry net sports game on me
At that table Jake looks really really young like they let this skinny teenager
Turn off the street
Behind him his whole crew is wearing the same blue plaid shirts that Jacob
Derek is there of course
Right in the front row on the rail when you're the rail and you have a piece of someone that's
Personally I get a lot more nervous than when I'm playing I'm just like sitting there and I have no control
So it's like you're gambling
Yeah exactly and I mean
Like when your guy like gets all in and you just like watching on the sidelines yet
Yeah it's really intense
The clock about the strike midnight on Jake wall stickers Fairy Tail all right now to turn Park
That's earring you can probably hear Derek in
After hours and hours of play the nine players get whittled down to four
And Jake
Skinny little Jake is still there holding his own
Jake gets all in against another player Russell Thomas
Ace King 4 Paws eres 9 off for Thomas and this could be the end of our evening
Jake wins the hand and takes Russell out of the tournament
Knockout
That's as far as our player Jake
And our investor Derek
Many many many hours later
Jay gets knocked out himself
He takes third
But you know what you get with third place
A lot of money
You're out in third place winning almost four million dollars
Not telling you on TV
Is that Jake is not taking home $4000000
He's taking home
Volundr 700000
The rest of it
Is going to his buddies who invested in him
After the tournament ends Jaguars his friends their share
For Derek
Jake Reitz
Personal check for $600,000
On a Hello Kitty check
Hello Kitty checkbook
I thought it was funny
With his share of the money
Jake
Goes
Big
The only two like
Possessions I remember buying
Where a bed frame from Ikea
Because I've been sleeping just like on the mattress on the floor
I bought
A hammock on Amazon for like
I want to pay $120
Derek investor who watched the whole tournament
From the sidelines
He took home almost as much as Jake
$600,000
Dad took that money
And reinvested
Derek still plays tournaments but more and more this is what he's doing
Buying up shares in a
Other players
Are you a better investor or better poker
Definitely
Better investor I think
There's a lot of
Really good poker players
But there's not that many people who do as much investing as me
Derek knows a lot about poke
How's the math he knows if you need an ace or a 10 to come on the last card you got a 17.4% chance
Knowing the odds is his job
And for him
The other best when he is betting on other people
Instead of playing himself
That was our story in mm
An update after the break
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solution
Strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information
It is available at aecf. Org
Hey it's Keith here in 2019
It's now been six and a half years
Jake won all that money at the World Series
And it turned out
He was not beginner's luck
Jake has gone on to become a
I'm a professional poker player P does not need his friends to buy him into tournaments anymore
Now he is one of the pros at folks like Derek
Are super eager to swap with
And Eric
Still invest
I called him up on Skype to find out what
Hey Keith how's it going
Derek reports he is still making good money as a poker investor
But now that he's got more money to invest
He started running into a problem
Last year it was to the point where
I can put in as much as I even wanted to
I could see you
A player whose
Really great in an amazing tournament but
He only has
Like 20% available for sale
Derek is learning
Poker investing is hard to scale-up Optimal strategy for me would to be like
Okay I want to put 5000 into that
What's that something that you could do with like
Stocks or
Real estate maybe but not poker
Don't feel too bad for Derek though he's still a poker player
And a really good one
Last February
He made the final table of this big tournament in Los an
It was $1000000 up top
And ended up getting third place in the end
For about
Jake decided not to play that
So the 5% swap they normally would have done
Didn't happen
That seems like I was a mistake on his part
Is very unlucky for Jake
I did
Offer to help Derek with his investing
Problem after all I've been having
All the success at the lowest
Is possible limits in Atlantic City
I have been
Brushing the ones who game at the Borgata
Is this the year that you're going to stake me for
Okay the one
Never been to Borgata so that could be outside of my scope
But that's a great start though
I feel like all you've done is update your at your way of refusing people that was a mistake
That's outside my scope that's nice
Like any good investor Derek still knows a bad deal when he sees one
So instead of finding worse and worst poker players to invest in without his ex
Extra money
He's Diversified
He's shifting some of his Focus
The startup
Special thanks today to Jesse Sylvia Sandeep Carol Klein Mike McDonald Ryan the plant
Ingenuous
We always love to hear what you think of the show
Email us Planet Money at npr.org or find us on Facebook
We are also at Planet Money on Twitter and Instagram
And if you are jonesing for another podcast about poker
May I suggest ESPN's 30 for 30 podcast
The show's fourth season
I reported an entire episode
Chris Moneymaker and the 2003 World Series
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
And I'm keep Rumer thanks for list