Support for this NPR Podcast
In the following message come from Better Health
Online counseling by license
Professional count
Specializing in issues in
Including depression stress and anxiety
Visit betterhelp.com money to learn more and get 10% off
If your first month
This is Planet Money
Nick Snyder is devoting his life
To this
1 elements
On the periodic table
Cute
And it's
Kind of like a tribute to his great-uncle
His name was Charles Conrad. I won't call him Pete
Charles Conrad and everyone called him Pete
Uncle P
Was an astronaut
Keep
Walked on the moon was the third person to walk on the
But he wasn't like
Serious nerdy astronaut think
Daredevil
Prankster asked
Yeah it is
Personal motto I think a bit tongue-in-cheek was if you can't be good be colorful
Like as Uncle Pete walk down the ladder
Toward the Moon
Key made
Another dramatic pronouncement
But a joke about being shorter than the other ask
Small step for Neil Armstrong
But a long one for me
Uncle Pete is walking on the moon just like Dum Dee Dum Dum Dum
This is
Actual audio
From the Moon
You did a lot of colorful things in his
NASA career
Quite a memorable character
Because of his Uncle Pete Nick grew up obsessed
With everything about outer space
And this is what brings us to Nick
Obsession with
Helium
You cannot send a rocket to space
Without
Helium
And a few years ago Nick heard
But the world
Is running short
On helium
And that is going to
Put at risk
Space exploration and access to space which
Certainly was something near and dear to my great uncle in my whole family
Helium is
Crucial for way more than space
If you need helium to run
MRI machine
Look for doctors to detect
Cancer and tumors
Unique helium to keep
Deep sea divers den
Electronic chips for our cell phones and computers
Made using helium
Soak the helium shortage threatens
All of that
Also birthday parties their entire birthday parties and proms
With droopy
Helium love balloons because
Some party stores are out
Epithelium
So when Nick hears about the helium shortage he thinks of his great-uncle.
And all this other important
Helium stuff
And he decides
He's going to go looking
4 more
Helium
Hello and welcome to Planet money from NPR I'm Sarah
Today on the show
The helium shortage
And how we got here
Helium is
So special and so rare
Does the US government once tried to buy a
All
The helium
Entitle
Before anyone else in the world new
Where human was or what it could
Also we go exploring
For new sources of helium with Nick
We've got our
Steel-toed boots on
Any drill
Made of diamond
Kinda
Support for this podcast in the following message come from E-Trade
With all the jargon
Investing can feel like a foreign language
E-Trade makes investing simp
By providing personalized support and guidance in terms you can understand
They let you get started in the market with as little as $500
And then help you learn as you go
You don't need to be a pro to invest a teacher
For more information
Visit etrade.com NPR
E-Trade Securities LLC
Members
DJ's Senator Elizabeth Warren is riding around Iowa in NRV campaigning
And I'm back we have a huge sign that says
Honk if you want big structural change
And according to Warren it is getting attention
We had Truckers coming by and they were they were really on the big air for
Play NPR politics podcast hit the road to ask Lauren about all that structural changes
She calling for
Subscribe to list
The story of helium is
Largely a story of the US government
It has
A massive stockpile
Aquila
And one of the people in charge of that stuff pile
Stamford
What are your thoughts on balloons
Party balloons
Yeah like helium used for
Graduations in party personally love
Party balloons
I think it's not a party without balloons right so
I'm a big fan of party balloon
And Sam
Love's
Helium
I like helium
If it's my element
It's an amazing material
I've spent my whole life working with it
I'm quite the helium geek
Sam says
Astronomers first identified helium in the Sun
In 1868
And as far as anybody knew there was almost none of it on Earth
Just design
But then in 1905
It was found
On accident
In Dexter Kansas
Mixed up in the natural gas bear
A couple of scientist discovered
Oh my gosh this is helium this is the same stuff that's on the Sun
This is the first time that anyone has found helium in any significant amount
Anywhere on Earth so scientist bottle it up to start test
And they learned that
Helium is
Really
Light
Like
So late
It can lift
Things
Like if you fill a balloon with helium it will
Lift and Float off
But at that point people already knew that hydrogen this other gas could
Lift things
These people were using hydrogen to lift blimps this was before airplanes are really a thing so blimps are real
Really big deal
People are flying around in giant blend
But hydrogen blimp
We're dangerous they were catching on fire because hydrogen is very
Very
Flammable
Helium
It's not
Helium will not catch on fire
The military found that application very very interesting
The US military thinks a lifting gas that doesn't burn
Wood
Transform Warfare in the air
Answer the government was like
Hey Dexter Kansas
We'd like to have him by your helium
Yeah
And it was actually top-secret work it was considered highly top-secret how we getting that that helium gas
The military saw so much potential in this helium
That they decide to
To keep it to themselves
And in fact of the German government approached the United States and requesting helium and because it was a
The defense minerals a strategic mineral
I said no we wouldn't give them our helium we would not give them our helium
And how we got it was considered very very very hush-hush Tussaud
How did Germany know that we had killed
Apparently somebody
That's where you getting it from well. He's got it
Government researchers are using all these
Code words for helium like
He is lost
Send more pups from the same litter
Batman
By the 1920s the government is sending helium to the Army and the Navy indeed
Big metal cylinders to
Fill up
The first ever
Super Save
Helium blimp
They could attach bombs to these blimps
Spy on enemies
From the air
But there's a problem
The helium kept leaking out of the cylinders
Lake
Slowly over time
Helium is an escape artists
If there's a whole helium will find it
Sneaky little element
It absolutely if there's a leak it'll it'll get out
Helium is one of the smallest
Lightest things
In the universe
It's so light
And floaties
That it's one of the only things that can
Escape Earth
Gravitational pull
It will just
Float
And out
Into the universe
Where helium
Is a bunting
So if you try to trap
Helium in a cylinder
It will find a way out
So you're just like use it real quick
Because if it disappears are closed off it to outer space
Yeah
But eventually
This problem
Helium leaks out of everything
Turned out to be really useful for the space program
It's the height of the Space Race and
We want to make sure that Uncle Pete's
Space suit and his Rockets don't have any leaks
Any leak in a rocket engine
And it could have
Explode
Dissolution
Cast of suits
Wiki Liam
If helium doesn't leak out
They're super sealed
And it's not just
Testing for leak
You need helium to launch a rocket like to push an astronaut
Into space
So the US starts to realize
We need helium
More than ever
It's a matter of National Security
And this
Kicked off
A series of government decisions and counter decisions and
Counter counter decision
That lead
To today's helium shortage
Okay we know helium is in natural gas
But a lot of it was just
Floating away
So in 1960 Congress passes a law
The set up a national helium
Stop by all the South pile where Sam works today
At the Bureau of Land
Congress says to the
Sam of 1960
Go to the US Treasury and borrow the money you need
To buy a
Hun
Of helium
Pay whatever you have to
So it's really a win-win it's it's to the to the Natural Gas producers helium is kind of a waste product
So of course natural gas company start
Capturing their helium and
Selling tons of it to the government
And now
America has to figure out
How to
Dora the
Sneaky gas that escapes from any container you put it in
And then
Someone goes
Okay hear me out
What if
We put the helium back in the container
It came from
Like
Underground
They find a huge chunk of underground rock near Amarillo
Texas it has
These holes in it that helium likes to
Float into
If used to have a bunch of helium
And in 1960 the US government starts injecting helium
Back into that rock
And they injected 32 billion cubic feet of helium that's an awful lot of helium that they put into the ground for future
Your use like how far down into the Earth are we talk
Skincare
It's 3000 3250
Down in the ground
Where did where the dinosaur bones
There's somewhere in there right
Yep
This is the only stockpile of helium
Anywhere in the world
Other countries have tried to trap helium
And failed
So this stockpile
Totally topsy
It was like cold war Cold War stuff
To protect
The field from
Prying eyes
The government was
Hiding the helium
In a field
Near Amarillo Texas
Imagine of a wide-open Texas Prairie
There is slightly Rolling Hills
Predominantly flat
Hershey to see a big open plain you slide back this metal cover and look down and there's a ladder that takes you down
Walking around the field like I was just a field just an empty field and then there's like a little door and you open it
There's a well solar there so
It really is
Important
Elements in the entire universe
Down here
There you go
By 1973 there was
So much helium under that rock
But the government stop injecting more
They thought they had enough
For like a hundred years
Bay
We're wrong
Buy 1996 two decades later if the helium world had totally changed
Yes Sam was still selling government helium to the military and NASA and
The weather people and science researchers
But now
There's this whole big
Private helium industry to like
Private companies
Selling helium to private company
Run MRI machines blow up party balloons whatever
So Congress is like
Why the hell is the US government in the helium business why are we maintaining this
Stop
This was a national security issue
It is no longer
And it cannot be justified as a jobs program either
It needs to be put to rest
Spire
They introduced a bill to
Casella
All the government here
Shutting down in any fishing facility
Which has outlived its need and can't compete
With a private sector
Congress votes to get out of the helium is
They tell Sam
Sell off
All the helium you've got
Not just to the government
To anyone who wants it sell it as fast as you can
It has nothing to do with the market nothing to do with how much
People are willing
To pay for it
What could go wrong
I would say that
We were doing it just for our own expenses
And with Sam and his colleagues
Didn't realize
Was that they were flooding the market with
Cheap
Helium
So cheap that it wasn't worth it for private companies
To try and find
New helium anymore
Their low prices
We're killing the private helium industry
And by 2013 Congress was like
Wait our plant turns ubm over to Private Industry
Didn't work
There is no real Private Industry
We messed it up
So they gave them New Order
Congress
Said
You need to raise those prices
Congress told team Sam at the helium stockpile
Increase
The price of helium
To encourage
Private Industry to go looking for new sources
So now
If people wanted to buy this
Rare precious gas
They were going to have to
The fight for it
Sam and his colleagues.
Auctioning
Helium off
To the highest bidder
The price of helium
Went up
It raised up fairly quickly
It raised up to in the in the 60 to $70 range during this time. I think we're in the air
80 $80 range the auctions it's it's up at the 219
Send Congress told teamsam
Start auctioning off of helium
The price has gone up from around
$55
Per thousand cubic feet
2 $119
Helium is more expensive than ever and
People are paying to get it
But the demand for helium is so high right now that Sam and the people at the helium stockpile
Literally cannot pull it out of the ground
Fast enough
We are delivering what we can as fast as we can
And sometimes it's not as much as they actually need
Well there's more in the ground but we can't give it more than what we can deliver it
So they're rationing helium everyone gets just
Some of what they actually mean
Which is why some birthday parties have droopy balloons
And why helium has become too expensive for some scientist to do their research
It's becoming scarce enough that some in the science Community say
The government should ban helium balloons
Save it for more important
Hatsune
It won't be up to the government at all anymore
The government has
To get out of the helium business
Entirely
By 2021 once and for all
That's what the last
Gilliam Law requires
And they're not just selling off the last of the helium trapped in the rock
At the highest price
They are like
Selling the field with the hidden door selling the building
To all the nuts and bolts in
Pipes
Yep Roc
Computers desk
It's all that stuff
September 30th of 2021
I going to take like a little bit of
Helium with you
We better not do that just a little bit
No
I better not do that
Now that Sam and the government are getting out
People like Nick Snyder
The guy who's great Uncle Pete walked on the moon
Are getting in
In 2013 the year Congress Ed helium
Has to get
More expensive
Nick started a company that year
He called it North American kill you
Means we drill holes in the ground looking for new sources of helium in North America
End
I invited myself along to Saskatchewan Canada this is what they call the Prairies right
Canada very much for a long time in both directions they find a lot of
Dinosaur fossils found here, Indiana Jones guys
Here's what you do step one
Find a place where there once was helium
And go back and see if there's more
Images going to drill holes
A mile and a half into the Earth
If you don't at least have some suspicions that there might be helium there
We have Bob
Specifically promised or investors that we are not going to do that
These people drilling for oil
Stumbled onto helium
And it's going to see if there's maybe any more left down there
Step 2
Get the rights to
Suck the helium out of the ground
Nick doesn't just get your own whatever you then he finds he has to go through the Canadian government
And his deal with them
Invest
Tens of millions of dollars
Cheap
All the helium you can find on 1.8 million Acres of Canadian Prairie
- release
Step 3
Rent-A-Wreck
Higher crew
Click the short
14 hours later
Yeah
When we get to this rig they give me some coveralls
Toggle tighten up my hard hat I've got my steel toe boots on feeling
Particularly powerful let's go punch some holes in the ground and look for the union and entire
Aircrew comes with me up on the rig we walk up some stairs to this metal platform
Dog House everybody hangs out in the doghouse basically a trailer up on the rig
Apparently that's where you want to be on a rig and the two guys on the floor running the wrenches to call
Who are the Roughnecks the Roughnecks
There's lots of cool names that's for sure
And this guy
He has the coolest name he is
The mud man official title it's honest trailer
Bruce schievelbein
Mudman
What mom told me years ago to stay quit playing in the mud and I never listen to her and still doing it
The Mudman is essential
First step
Drill a hole
There is a drill that slowly breaks into the Earth over several days
Through millions of years of rock it's like
A metal ball
Smaller than a volleyball
Drill holes into the Rock
How do you insure a mile this drill has these little knobs
Diamond
All over it
For strength
It wouldn't look good on your finger but
Oh my God I can't miss this
If you turn this
Small heavy Diamond Drill over there are these little Jets on the bottom that shootout
A special kind of mud that the mud man make
It's it looks like smooth and silky like it looks good
Very slippery
Probably good for your skin
The best cold
Slippery mud that shoots out of the
The drill as it smashing Through The Rock
It's like a pressure washer
And the mud send
Rock shavings
Shooting up to the surface
Every 15 minutes a geologist
Looks at those rocks
Those Rock
Crumbs will tell them
When they've hit the rock they're looking
For the rock with all the holes in it where helium likes to live
You do not want to drill past the rock you want because
Reeling is expensive Nikki spending $50,000 a day
Andre Lee
That's the cutting sample that you're very very old rock
I think there's like dinosaur fossils mixed into this
The farther back in time you go
They have drilled
We pass
Food recipe
Like
855 million years
Cast where the dinosaur fossils are
And after 11 days of drilling here
They hit what they were looking for saw the the zone of Interest we saw the rock properties that we were looking for
So you just saw like oh this this is the kind of rock Wii U like this this means there could be healed
That's correct that is Marlon McDougall he works with Nick
And the final step
It's a build a plant
To separate the helium from all the other things except
6th and West
They're doing that 2 hours away from here and they can Marlin take me to see it
Welcome to Battle Creek this will be the next producing helium plant in Saskatchewan
You're looking at it right there
What am I looking at
You're looking at a farmer's field right now but
That's for the plants going to start being built within a year
It's one man with a giant balloon
Don't forget you need a ride back
Yeah exactly
The only thing we can see is grass
But off in the distance
There's this
Little.
That's the thing
Helium will flow out of
You can see a little red
Yeah, Cabrera
Fiery red color
That's called the well
Faucet it looks like a faucet
Sure that works faucet
And so you turn on turn it on and it would flow helium right now
Likes
Much louder and much more much more Force like a jet engine
What it like shoot me out it would kill you
Good good to know
This plant will be ready to start selling helium in 2021
Just in time to
Steppin
Is the US government
Stepped out
This message comes from NPR sponsor Microsoft
Studying snow leopards helps us understand their ecosystem
Microsoft AI
I quickly analyzes thousands of remote camera
So researchers can understand these animals and their environment
Microsoft.com AI
Everyone is ophira Eisenberg and here I'm chatting with one of queer eye's Fab 5 Antoni porowski
Culinary deal-breaker for you
Ketchup on hotdogs makes me really uncomfortable
Listen to NPR's ask me another the answer to Life's funny or questions
If you want to see videos of us
Drilling for helium and
Pictures of
Billion-year-old rock that may or may not have pterodactyl bones in it
Good riddance
At Planet
Oh my God there's a Party City
Right by my hotel
Today Show was produced by Liza Jaeger and Cynthia bet you Baeza
Alex goldmark azar supervising producer and jacob goldstein edited the show
Party City
Do you guys have like a maple leaf balloon
Or anything that would be like extra Canadian
Oh there's a cavity balloon
Perfect
Thank you
1 Canada de Belen
I mean
I obviously have to do this
I'm Sarah Gonzales
This is NPR
Thanks for listening
Oh man
Galaxy