Support for this in
NPR podcasts
The following message
Come from the UPS
Offering services from shredding
To printing to mailbox
And instead of closing this Memorial Day we
May 24th and 20
The UPS Store
He's doing another thing
All together
Opening
The UPS Store
Everything for small business
And of course shipping
Lauren Neuwirth is a junior at
Purdue
She studies biological engineering and
Food processing sign
Is which means
She knows a lot about how Food Works
As a technical expert is there some artificial flavor that's just like where they just nailed it
I would say like banana bananas actually pretty cool from a chemical standpoint like a volatile account
Beastly is super pint
And she knew that Purdue was a good place to
Get into the food engineering industry
But you couldn't figure out how she was going to pay
Yeah it was
Extremely stressful like I was telling you before every time I go into financial aid I just start crying
Because
It's just so much money
And
Like I come from like a single-parent household
So it's hard to rationalize like
Asking my mom for like
Easter Bunny with Lauren went off.
Her mom gave her $30,000
That was her College
On top of that she was able to get some government back student loans
Niigata paid internships
In the summer
But all of those things combined are not nearly enough
To pay her way
So
I went to financial aid and I was like
All set to basically like joined the army because they said that they would pay for my school
Bruce Lee went in there and I was like okay I need some money or I'm calling Army recruiter back and I'm driving the Army B
Because I don't know what else to do in schools like 30 grand a year
And that was when someone at the financial aid office
Told her about a new way for students to pay for
It was so new
The even the person at the financial aid office
Didn't know all of it
Play sad like they didn't know a ton about it and that is kind of a new program and I should like go home and kind of looking
Duet
Anna and I did
Yeah I think this does sound better than the military
So I
Applied and I got approved and then that's how it's been like
Paying for my last
2 years of school
Purdue gave Lauren a bunch of
Tens of thousands of
It's not a scholarships not alone
There's no set amount of money that Lauren has to pay back
Instead
Lauren had to promise that she will give Purdue a chunk of her income
4 years after
She graduates
The more she makes
Amour perdu
Lawrence olds
Stock in herself
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm taking books
And I'm Kenny Malone
Today on the show
This idea of selling stock in yourself
Or something like it
Has been kicking around for decades
Now
Finally starting to have
This message comes from NPR sponsor snowfall
The only data warehouse built for the claw
Today organizations need the agility
What about rapid Data Insights brain
Want to stay a step ahead of
With snowflake
You can instantly and infinitely scale your data warehouse with the touch of a button
Delivering deep insights at any time for all use
Start your journey
Towards data-driven decision
Snowflake.com NPR
This thing Lauren Neuwirth
It is called an income share
It is a new way to help
College butt
It is based on
Pre old id
One of the people who helped kind of ReDiscover this
And dusted off
Is a man named
Miguel Palacios
Hello
Jacob High
Hey Miguel how are you
Good thank you how are you tell is a professor of Finance at the University
Calgary
He grew up in Columbia
It in the mid-1990s
He heard about this weird thing happening
In the news
Involving
David Bowie
You must have done so
David Bowie race capital
For himself
I'm at the special thing about this Capital racing was that he pledged his future earnings
This was in 1990s
And by this point David Bowie had been a rock
Rockstar for life
30 years
He had this huge catalog
Perpetual
Under pressure
Starman The Man Who Sold the World and every time somebody
He bought an album or played one of those songs on the radio
But we got a little
He got royalty
So what but we decided to do at this
What's instead of get a little money every year
He wanted a lot of money
Now
Joey said to invest
If you give me a lot of money now
I will give you a chunk of my royalties
For the next ten
And
It works
Investors gave Bowie 55 million dollars
And in return they got a nice steady stream of income for the next decade
When Miguel Palacios heard about this Bowie
He thought immediately
But this kind of deal would be great not just for rockstars
But for regular people
In particular
He thought a college
It all came from experiencing the
Fate of several classmates when I was an undergrad student who are doing okay but basically had to
To drop off
Because they couldn't
Survive financially
These people I knew they were highly capable they were very talented they were they were
Possibly much more talented than I was
And they were giving up
On a degree that it done in Colombia
Very very Valentine
So you heard about the Bowie bonds
And you thought about your your friends or classmates who
Had had to drop out because they didn't have enough money and I'm what did you think
I thought
They should be able to do something like what David Bowie
Not exactly
Like what David Bowie
Dead but Miguel wanted to give college students
Choice big companies that had 400
If your company
And you need money you basically have two options
Option number one
Debt
Get a loan sell Bond
If you do this you have to pay back everything you borrowed
Plus interest
Option 2
Equity
Sell stock to invest
If you do this investors
People
Give you money
And you get to keep
Is not alone
You don't have to
To pay it back
But the people who gave you the money who invested in you
Get a share of your future profit
The more money you make
The more money you have to give
Ordinary People don't have this
If your regular person
And you need money all you get is option one
You can borrow money if somebody is willing to lend it
If you don't want to borrow money
Or if there's nobody who is willing to lend you money
You're out of luck that is why Miguel's friends who couldn't get loans had to drop out of
Sao Miguel keep studying this idea
He goes off to grad school
And you learned that people have tried sort of similar things in the past but
But not really what Migo was thing
He also finds a couple people trying to get companies off the ground
90s butt
Nobody's getting very far
And at some point Miguel happens
To come across this chapter in a book by Milton
The famous icon
Randomly
So I was
Reading
Capitalism and freedom
And it was there right so there's this this chapter and there it is
It's light out
Very clearly
The whole idea of explain
Freeman just says it
We should have a way that you can give a student money
In exchange for a cut
Of his or her future
So you just happened to be reading this book at this moment
Yes
Serendipity
What did you think when you came upon this in the book
Cool things
On 100
I guess it's not an original idea
On the other hand
Milton Friedman also thought it was a good idea yeah yeah the big moment for Miguel
When you met a guy named Felipe Vergara
Also Colombian
Very entrepreneurial
And interested in education
Describe what I was
Writing about
I'm sure she thought it was
Very interesting
And but
This is worthy intrapreneurs different from the PhD
Student
I was thinking that I would spend several years studying and learning and then designing
I'm she said why don't we do it let's try to have the first contract by next month
That was the birth of Looney Looney is the company that Felipe and Miguel found
Wanted to do this thing Miguel have been dreaming of
To make income share agreements
For students
They did all pilot program in Chile Where Miguel at work when he was in
2606 students
$10,000
Well that was great
And that
West say the first the beginnings of a track record
That allowed them need to start raising more Capital to finance other students
That was in 2001
Today almost 20 years later
It operates in Colombia Peru Chile
Mexico to this point something of a 10000 student finance
Movies counter
In all they provided about 50 million dollars
500 in
And the investors who put money in they are getting paid
But
Lumi is not really
Cracked
The United States
A place where
Obviously
People have huge problems
Paying for college
After the break
Income share agreements
Support for NPR in the following message come from servicenow
Making the world of work work better for
They're cloud-based Platt
Form and solutions
Deliver digital workflow
That create great experiences for employees
And unlock productivity
For your whole company
Servicenow digitizes the work your people have to
So they can do the work
They want
Using technology
How to make people more productive and engaged
Moret servicenow.com
Alright one moment he saw the meeting right now one moment please
Media who were taking note
Purdue received a record number of applicants
Purdue University remember is the school that is using an income share agreement to fund part of the education of Lauryn or
The food engineer who we talk to
Whatever your Pursuit McDaniel McDaniels is the president
Highest chicken Goldstein at NPR
4-year University in the US
To try income share
And this happened because
In 2015
Mitch Daniels went to wash
In to testify at
At a congressional hearing on higher ed
You talk about a bunch of different issue
Use and just passing
He mentioned income share
I was almost a throwaway line but as soon as the
Hearing was over I was swarmed with the first of all reporters were curious about the
Concept
And then shortly thereafter I began to hear from people who had hoped that somewhere someone would try to get this
The concept airborne
Beachwood back to Purdue
And ask the team of
Figure out if
Could do this and if so
What students might be
Address to beat Super clear here
Step back for 1
College is ridiculously expensive
Income share agreements
Are not going to solve that
Also there are better ways to
The pay for college
If you can swing them
Government-backed student loans are better than income share agreements for most
Also
Grants and scholarships
Are obviously better for students than income share agreement
Play 4 lotto
Students like Lorde net worth
Grants and scholarships
Government-backed loans and summer jobs
All put together are not enough to pay for
For college
Those students often wind up taking out additional private loans
And for those students
Purdue decided
Income share agreements might be a good
All I know is there are millions of students
Who are taking very expensive loans who might be candidates for this and let who might
Find it to their advantage
Purdue launched its income share
MIT program in 2016
So far they funded about 500
And the details of how this program works
Are really into
We're just going to run through some of those details to explain how it actually works for students like
Say Lauren new
I like printed out all my forms that I signed and everything last night I was kind of like what you have
The school gave Lauren
$50,000
And she promised to pay roughly
The 15% of her in
For eight years after she
So the more you make
The more you have to pay
Yes
But also the less you make the less you have to pay
But I mean we're hoping to make a good amount of money what are the most interesting things about the program is that the percentage
Picture of income that students have to promise to
The pay depends on what their major
We talked about this with Mary Claire Cartwright who manages the
And we know that a chemical Engineers traditional salary
I'm out of school is going to be different than let's say an English major and then by different human way higher
Correct me for most people right
Right here is the thinking behind how
Mapreduce at this
They want everybody who participates
The ultimately pay back the same
Now English majors are probably going to earn
Unless
So if they want money now
They have to promise
A higher percentage of
On the other hand Engineers are probably going to earn more
So they are on the hook for a lower percentage
Did you verify
Feels like I don't know a little weird make a little judgy
Most schools for example don't charge different tuition rates for different
They just set one average for everybody
So why not do that
With income share
So you could you could decide to just take the average income of all
We're going to charge you based on that
That's an option
It is
But it would be one that might cause there to be more adverse selection into the cohort
You mean that if you if you ever doubt all the English Majors would say like sure that sounds like a sweet deal ready to chemical energy
You doing they just be like nothing
Right correct haha
That's interesting
Adverse selection is this General kind of problem that
Occurs when
Exactly the wrong kind of
People sign up
And one concerned with income share agreements
Is it even when you charge different Majors different rates
You could still have this adverse selection
Yeah like say I'm an English major
And I'm planning to go to Las
And get some high paying lawyer
I'm going to make a lot more than the average English me
So for me
An income share agreement is probably not a good deal right I'm going to be on the hook for a lot of money
On the other hand if I'm going to go say you know be a teacher get a
Get a good job but when where I don't make a ton of money
In that case on income share agreement may be a good deal for me
The Purdue doesn't have any
Control over what you do after you
They're not going to tell you
To take the higher-paying job over a lower-paying job
But there are some
Terms in the contract to catch
You know like super slacker
I mean if someone told me like
You're going to pay a percentage of your income
For the ten years after you graduate
I would initially be like great
So I'm going to Europe
For at least two of those years
Great
You know we want people to experience that and you pause the contract because you're not
You're not seeking employment pause the con
The students will do this
That's the students
Like Lauren
Debt income share
Are on the hook for 8 years after they grow
It's like there's this clock running down
But pretty will stop the clock if the students if they Lauren decides to know to bum around Europe or for that matter to go to
On the other hand
If Lauren gets fired and she's looking for a job
The clock keeps running
And since she doesn't have income
She doesn't have to pay
On the
Other
I guess other hand
If Lauren becomes
You know what some food
Text superstars who becomes
Banana in a billionaire
She does not have to kick back 15% of that huge windfall to
I predict she does not have to give them
Whatever a hundred million dollars
There is a cap
On what she and everybody in the program has two
And that captives
Two and a half times the amount that Purdue gave her in the
Lawrence KS
It's a hundred and twenty five thousand
After she graduates
She'll have to tell Purdue
Or the company that's running the
Yes program
Purdue
How much she is May
Edible oranges
Uses to pay
They can come after her and demanded that she pay
Two and a half times the amount
They gave her in the first
No matter how much she's making a
So those
Are some of the terms
The terms that
Lauren Neuwirth sign
How do you feel
All
I mean honestly not great
Because
Like no one wants money taken out of their check every month
But at the same time like maybe I don't make a lot coming out of college okay well then we're still doing fine I'm not going to like
Default on my loan
The first students in the program have already graduated
They're making payments
Seems to be going well
But really it is too early to say how this is going
Ghetto will students like Lauren feel good about it in the end will the people who put money into the program get their money back
How profitable
Will it be the kind of thing that draws in
Big money private investors or is it going to remain this kind of
Semi philanthropic niche
But for sure
Income share Agreements are a thing now
They're popular with vocational schools
Coding bootcamps
Colleges all over the country
Utah Colorado Pennsylvania in New York
Are all launching their own
Income share agreement
You can communicate with us via email or social media or on your standard Suite of social media
Yes Planet Money our email is Planet Money at npr.org
I am just like I am like a marionette that is propped up
By like all these different people here and it's
Just the craziest feeling that is Bryant urstadt
Planet money editor
The show is produced by Darian Woods
Are supervising producer is a lie
Thanks to Tony OD Sorrento of vemo education and Julie Margarita Morgan of the Roosevelt Inn
Planet Money videos are thing in the world they're fun they're short and you can see them at npr.org
Planet Money shorts
I'm Kenny Malone and I'm Jacob Goldstein thanks for listening
My first summer I did production and then my second summer I did quality
Does that mean you were like tasting the chocolate
Oh yeah there is always lots
Have you ever seen I Love Lucy
Yes and I know exactly what you're talking about because that's
It's literally what I did in French