Support for NPR and the following message come from State Farm
When it comes to home and auto insurance
They're here through the ups and downs
Go to statefarm.com
To be connect
It was one of the 19000 ages
In neighborhoods
Across the Nation
State Farm
Here to help life
Go right
This episode originally aired in 2014
I went to the gym the other morning a planet
Fitness
And if you've never been to a Planet Fitness
It's one of the cheapest gyms around
It's like $10 a month
While I was there by said the sky
He was sitting in a massage chair
Fitness has massage chairs
Jaquan voice
He and his friend had just finished working out
He told me they were working on their arms
How often do guys come
5 days a week.
Yeah
That's Monday to Friday cuz I work in a city
Flock of Seagulls
But to be honest while I was looking at him
Wasn't totally convinced that Jaquan actually comes to the gym 5 days a week
So I asked him
Do you mind if we run your card and see how I feel you've actually been
Really how long how long do you need
I don't want to take away your massage time
Couple minutes later I caught you one actually trying to sneak out of the gym
Or we could run his car
But I saw him out of the corner of my eye
Hey do you mind if we do you mind if we check your card
We went up to the front desk and the receptionist checked his membership card
When he swipes when he comes in
She picked a few different weeks and checked how often Jaquan actually goes to the gym
Turns out he's pretty consistent
The moment of truth
Play in a week
2 days a week
The receptionist tells me this rude awakening happens all the time
Do some people think they work out more than they do oh yeah
Pandora.com using massage chair
Rather than workout
The result of the self-deception is obvious
This Planet Fitness here in Manhattan one of them
Crowded places on Earth
Smack in the middle of High Gym season
And this gym is pretty much empty
The members of this gym may think they're working out a lot but they're not
And frankly this is the way gems like it
Customers who pay
But don't cost the business a dime
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Businesses would close their customers never showed up
An empty restaurant
Disaster
An empty store
Bankruptcy
Here among the mirrored walls rubber mats in elliptical trainers
Emptiness equals success
Today in the show The Mind Games that Jim's play with you
From design pricing to free Bagels
Jim's wannabe this product
Everyone dies
But no one actually use it today shows about gyms
Trainer from Planet Fitness
I'm going to be popping into the show to give you exercises to get in shape while you learn some economics
Shake It Out
And look at started
This message comes from NPR sponsor Microsoft
You might be surprised by the amount of Science and Technology that's inside a bottle of beer
At the Carlsberg research laboratory and coping
Brewers are using Microsoft AI to help them reinvent the way they make beer
AI enables them to analyze raw ingredients for unique flavor
So they can develop better beers faster
See how Microsoft AI is empowering business in Nevada
Bears at microsoft.com AI
A language was about to die
Once it gets wiped out that's it
We will have nothing
In our language to pass to our children and the people trying to save it
We're still learning how to
Speak it and we have to hurry up time was working against us we're like hundred years late you know
It's code switch
Viola Cole over
Listen And subscribe
Let's be honest here
Most people don't use their gym membership
Ivan Ben
And like 3 weeks
That's not that bad I haven't been in 6 months
And you know why Caitlin
It's this
All right everybody know we're going to go and do some push-ups
So the park
Feet slightly apart from each other
And
Down
Well I'm not alone here in Planet Fitness they tell me that half of their members never set foot inside of this gym
Half of their members
The whole gym system is built around his fat
How many people can work out in the gym at 1
I'm going to take a few hundred to be completely honest this is Chris antique she manages the Planet Fitness on the upper west side
The gym can hold 300 people
How many members does it have
Set 6000
Wow slider members
What would happen if they all came oh my goodness you have a very crowded gym
Thank goodness they all don't show up at one time
Because if every member came tomorrow they would need 20 times the space
The treadmills would be drenched in sweat the barbells would be broken
Bread lines
Elliptical trainer
And it would cost a fortune
People actually came to the gym
Planet Fitness would have to charge a lot more than $10 a month
Gyms need their members not to come
Lock the doors
I can't tell people not to show up
So they have to rely on
Consumer psychology
To get you excited enough that you sign up for a gym membership
That's so exciting
So you'll get up an hour early to do some crunches
For work
Grenadier Planet Money people
Princess
What if you plan on the ground
Meatspin
Of 1
Hold back down
First gym track
Attract the right kind of
Kind of customer
He thinks he's going to workout
But who
Customers
Like this guy
I personally like the gym that I can get a shake
Goodbye in Italian
Rudy Fabiano is in his early 50s
He lives in New Jersey
Especially buff
He doesn't belong to
Which m
Which is weird
Because he designs gym
For a living
We are Architects that specialize in fitness center design
Rudy says architecture and design can basically allow gyms to attract
The kind of customer they want
When he started 25 years ago the kind of customers Jim's wanted were bodybuild
Gyms were designed around sweat
No spaces were big Warehouse
Houses filled with equipment
New member to baggy pants
Everybody had and
A lot of clanging
And not a lot of it
Experience
Beyond the experience of just lifting weights
Does James Attractive people
Who came everyday
Memberships work Spencer
What gyms looked less like sweat Factory
What if they looked more like a fancy restaurant
Our hotel lobby
Maybe you could attract someone else
A more casual exercise
Either the first he says the gym owners
Didn't get it
I used to have these discussions with
What the gym owner has died
And the arguing will be with G I'm so proud of all this
Equipment
I want to show it off
So I'm going to put all my
You know 80 pieces of cardio
Right in front when you come in
You're impressed
Am i r u b I'm not in
I'm scared
Cuz I clicked on a Monday night and there's people sweating around me in the noise of all those treadmills and
The experiences
Is not
What we're trying to sell
To show me the experience
Is trying to sell Rudy took me to a gym he just finished designing in Manhattan
Okay Frank we're going to need something a little more mellow for this card
Alright listeners now we're going to jump into some like lifts
So this time you want to fit together
Heritage sites
To bring them down one
3D ground backup
So I was saying
Rudy took me to his newest gym
VFX
In Chelsea
We stand outside and it sort of looks like it could be a cocktail lounge
What we're looking at Clear doors and
Right across from us
Is the b f x logo
It's a laser cut in wood
Can see people sitting in the lounge down
Stairs
Not sure what they're doing
Right and then you walk in and it looks feels like a store doesn't feel like your traditional Health Club you really don't see
Any equipment
You know you're here obviously the music
In the van in is
You'll start seeing some more component
And of course here is the welcome desk
It's white marble and as a member of the out of shape public
Remind me of something
It looks like a like a bar almost is like the same dimensions as a box
We like bars and this place is designed to make you feel comfortable
You feel like you could hang out
This kind of design it gets you in the door
Suddenly you're imagining yourself sitting in those chairs chatting with a friend and before you know it
The shelling out money for yearly membership
Or some classes
Jason Caitlin going to start with some subject let's go one
Here is another subtle signal at VFX
Those intense weightlifter types the ones who come everyday and sweat everywhere and cost place
This is like this a lot of money
They want to see the weight room
Heavy equipment
And in most casual gym that's hidden
The gym part of bfx
Turns out that's down a set of stairs
Rua Lounge behind a wall
And as we approach it I can start to feel myself get a little
Nervous and intimidated
Rudy says that's
Pretty common most people because there's equipment in front of you that you may not know what to do it
And the barbell sister big
Yeah it just looks like stuff I could never do
Why I don't do those big barbells.
I mean
It seems like you're trying to make a gym that doesn't look like a gym
Is that right
That's correct
Rudy has designed over 500 gems
That don't look like gyms
All over the world
So what did the track did the Wright cut
Customer
The non sweaty bodybuilder type
It doesn't really matter if your customer never gets on the treadmill
It doesn't matter if they never use the gym
But you have to keep
The money flowing
And you know how this
Dreaded annual conf
Joining a gym is an interesting form of
What behavioral Economist called pre-commitment
Kevin bolts Texas Center for Health incentives and behavioral economics at Wharton
He says normally we hate
Lock us into doing things for certain period of time
Cell phone contracts
Gym memberships
Hulk says those are different
We actually want to be locked
They're picturing
The new me
Who's actually going to go to the gym 3 times a week can
Become a physical fitness machine we like the idea of locking ourselves then we think
Now that I'm paying money for a
A year I will make myself go
And then we do
And then we don't
And even if we think about cancelling our membership
Some of those contracts are notoriously difficult to get out of
This business model works so well that low price gems are growing like
Crazy
Turned out the selling stuff that nobody uses
Is a great
But there's one problem
Annual contract end
I want people realize they haven't been using the thing they've been paying for they haven't been going to the gym
They tend to drop out
After the break how gyms are scheming to get you to renew your annual membership
Support for this podcast and the following message come from odoo
Want to boost your business
Check out ododos new business game
Scale-up
It's fun it's smart and odoo offers it for free shipping included
Use promo code money
Odio o.com
Scale-up
Who plays of games everybody I hope your Eisenberg host of NPR's ask me another are you looking for
The answer to Life's funny or questions
Zamboni that is correct every week we blend comedy + a
Special celebrity interview
Rolls listen and tell your friends
Most gyms lose about half their customers every year and so they have to rely on one final trick
They have to make sure you got something valuable
Because let's be honest
Guitar apps
Jim's do all kinds of things
Things to make themselves seem value
Remember the massage chairs equanimous using Planet Fitness has rows of them
Along with an Aqua Massage bed
A lot of gems have mixers and other social events
Planet Fitness also has pizza nights
And free Bagels want some
And those are the gyms busiest time
Are you guys coming from the bagel
Breakfast at Planet Fitness
Oh yeah
Is that what you guys came
This is like the most miserable day
But
You still try to actually exercise
Definite keeper babe
Maybe next month
The Builder weird to eat a bagel right after you absolutely feel very weird that you just exercised and I or carbo-loading
Salmonella Bagel volume all time
The idea is that these folks will look back fondly on their Europe bagels and pizza and renew that annual contract
Once again
Or I got to work out those bagels at Brandon place now
Come on guys pick up the pace
Now all of this can seem like you're being manipulated because of course you are
But remember every person who signs up and doesn't go to the gym
Is basically subsidizing your gym membership
Making it cheaper for everyone
If you have willpower and everyone else doesn't
You could actually work out for a week
Ridiculously low price
And think about the alternative
Gyms were really about
Fit if they really wanted you to show up and pay for it
And all gyms would look like
It's not that nice in here there's nowhere to sit there's no mirrors in here
It's a really kind of barebone
Space
This is precision athlete
A tiny gym on the upper west side of Manhattan
An EVO is one of the owners and she is super fit
She has amazing leg muscle
From doing all these squats
Though says she has about a hundred
And 50 members here
And they all come
In fact
If you don't come
Or if you're not hardcore enough you will get
Kicked out of this Jam
Do you ever like
Reject people
Yeah
Yeah common thing that you'll hear is I'm too busy I have this and that
Like
Vladimir Putin works out everyday
I would argue that he's pretty busy
Are you busier than he is
No
You are not
This is the kind of place where everyone knows
Exactly how often they show up
Andrew Atia poop has been coming to Precision for a few
How often do you come
I come 6 days a week
Wow
Yeah
I totally believed him the whole time we're talking
He keeps looking away to stare longingly
At the exercise bike if he's coming to you
There's no mirrors
There's no disco music playing right now
There is no like slogans there's
This is
Really sincere place
Sincerity means
Neutrik
No annual membership
No massage chairs
Insincerity also means your membership isn't being subsidized by all the
Placards that don't show up
And so we can finally see what a gym that everyone uses would actually cost
Precision athlete
Starts at 500 bucks a month
CC here it is 2019 safety of today and we checked in with an EVO from Precision athlete
She left that small exclusive gym in 2016 and she's an independent personal trainer now
In the nearly five years since we talked and he says that that kind of intensive gym model has really taken off
And even the big gym chains have gotten on board
Now all the big gyms have an internal gym
Elevation cross-stitch of proliferation of Orangetheory
Sitting room townhouse everything you can think of so I think
At this point
You know everybody has a few Boutique gyms that they belong to
10 years ago when we first started
We are kind of the first
1 to offer that experience
Of course we have also seen the rise of
#fitspo
That is fitness inspiration on Instagram
At least it's inspiration
If you are inspired by watching people Flex in front of a mirror
But all this together we asked Annie
Does it actually inspire people to go to the gym more
I don't think they're actually still going to go
That is the problem right like where is the app that makes going to the gym less painful
We always love to hear what you think of the show
If you have any questions or comments send us an email Planet Money at npr.org
Where you can find us on social media we are at
Planet Money
Check out the newest video by the way our planet money shorts series
This time we sink our teeth into
Government cheese
Had to npr.org
Planet Money shorts
If you like this episode or if you like Planet Money In general please review us on Apple iTunes or where we get your podcast
And of course they could always tour amazing
Producer Jess Jiang the rerun was produced by Darian woods and Cynthia battle
I get with Kenny and I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
And I'm Frank Pena that was just your first set and I were wanting to podcastone into it all over again
This is NPR
Thanks for listening