A couple of weeks ago
Something
Very very strange happened in one of the most anticipated college basketball games
This is North Carolina versus
Duke archrival
Top 10
And Duke has a player named Zion Williamson who
Is probably the single most amazing college player I have ever seen
So we're 30 seconds into the game
Williamson has the ball
Driving spinning Zion Williamson
And as the announcers
Watching the replay of the
They start to realize
Did Zion Williamson
Fell and got hurt
Because his Nike shoe
Head split open
Like
The soldiers
Ripped away from the fabric and he slid to the floor
That's unbelievable you broke your shoe with his own foot
Zion Williamson sat out for the rest
With Annie in
Apparently because
Is Nike
Basketball shoe
Head blown out
The next day
Nike stock drop
Nike itself had to issue a statement saying this with quote
An isolated incident
But that the company would launch an investigation
And isn't watching all of this unfold
My first thought is of course about Zion Williamson
Luckily it looks like he
Define
But my second thought
Was holy crap
We did an entire episode that we never thought would be relevant
But suddenly
It was
So today we are going to replay that at
The story of
The last time
There was a major investigation into
And a national obsession with
The quality
A basketball City
Hey
Data package
Jeffy.
Adidas sneakers
Starz series
Hey there
Used
Yeah they're like Spider-Man
They're not sweating
Danny
Okay that's probably sweat
Hello and welcome to Planet Money
Anthony Malone that was my wife Hannah
And those sweaty eBay sneakers
That I'm wearing on my feet right now as I speak
They are one of the most extraordinary experiments
Basketball sneaker history
Today on the show we know that you can put a famous basketball players name on a pair of shoes and charge more money
But what happens when you put an NBA All-Stars name on a pair of shoes and charge less
Much much less but like
Okay don't wear any worse.
Support for this podcast
In the following message come from fidelity
As a Fidelity Wealth Management
You get a dedicated advisor to help
Grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes and make clear recommendations
Thanks for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
The Man Behind the sneakers that I'm wearing
Is an NBA All-Star named Stephen
Marbury
And he grew up during the basketball sneaker Revolution
You got your mom and you
You say I'm playing basketball I need
These sneakers
Important distinction here of course
Especially with my mother
Gwen Stefani was born in 1977 basketball shoes were essentially
Does a piece of sports equipment like knee pads for your feet
The most iconic brand for decades was a shoe called the Chuck Taylor All Star
Their basic affordable Shoes Canvas rubber nothing fancy
But what's the fun with 8 years old
The sneaker game
Change
In 1985 Nike release this commercial is Michael Jordan
Soaring in slow motion through the air
Air Jordan with the first Air Jordan sneaker and it was beautiful
Look like a sports car white and black leather with streaks of red
Stores couldn't keep these things in stock people were wearing them as shoes not just as basketball shoes
And they cost a lot
The Air Jordan 1 retail for $65
150 bucks in 2 days
And then the next year 1986 Air Jordan The Jordan 2 came out is all of the imaginary
Those hot even more $100
The Jordan 4s
Cost a hundred
10 to Jordan 5 cost $125
Stefan was 13 years old
When is Jordan 5s
I was living in Coney Island Brooklyn one of seven kids
His family didn't have a lot
And so
When Stefan asked his mom
For those shoes
She was not having it
I mean my mother asked my mother for a pair of shoes at that price the reply was
Boy those are groceries for the month
Why am I going to go spend that type of money
A pair of shoes
And you would say what cuz everybody else got them
Oh yeah you're not going to be the one that's going to have a pair
But it wasn't because she didn't want to buy them if it
Just because she couldn't
Stefan says this planted a seed
He always wondered when there be another option here
Is a famous players basketball shoe always have to be so expensive
Know a lot of kids might
Think this
But
Stephan got to do something about it
Because
I grew up you got very good at basketball
In 1996 he was drafted into the NBA
The Milwaukee Bucks
Select
Stephon Marbury the camera cuts to the whole Marberry family they are freaking out
Stephon Marbury is Banning by now it's brexit
This moment right here
That makes me love Stephon Marbury
Because on the first question was totally just sounds like an ice breaker
She just starts
I can't even
20 loan
The camera Cuts backstage and now Stefan's mother is dancing
Is this girl so good I could put a smile on my mother face
Define join the NBA
Became an NBA All-Star
Twice
And year after year famous player after famous player
Signed endorsement deals to sell shoes at ridiculously high
Stefan doesn't remember the exact moment but an idea started
And you can think of it this way
Sneaker is made up of foam and rubber and leather
By attaching a famous basketball players name
Can you get to charge more
And kids go crazy for
Could you use an endorsement
To do the exact opposite
Topeka same shoe of foam and rubber and leather
And attach a famous basketball players name
But charged
Less
And still have it
Be cool still get the kind of buzz
The Air Jordan
Stephan wanted to know
Could I make affordable sneakers
Cool
I can see my mom I can see my mom being able to do something for all of her kids
Does that is that who you
Picture winners
Of course
In 2005 after he been in the NBA for almost a decade
The phone finally met someone
You could help him make this
A guy named Howard Shack
Is always talked about there has to be a dick
Well
We were the different way
Howard works for a clothing company called
Steve & Barry's founded by a pair of long Islanders named Steve
Amberry
It was a relatively unknown chain that sold clothes at ridiculously low price
And they said they were able to do this
A couple of
For one they cut out the middleman
Manufacture Their Own Line of clothes in China
They took the smallest markup
But they could possibly
Afford
They basically had no advertising
Budget
And then they open stores in struggling malls where they would ask for
Discount
Free space
This was a business
But now
Steve & Barry's
Wanted to get in
2B Athletics
Howard personally had a vision for cheap basketball shoes
And he wanted to have a famous basketball player
People who told him that Stephon Marbury
Happened to be a famous basketball player
Looking
To make shoes cheaper
There was just like a light bulb went off and they said you know staff
Could be the perfect
Athlete
So where gets the stuff on that Steve & Barry's would like to me
And his first thought
Who and who
I didn't know I mean I learned of them before the meeting and I was like this is you know I got to see this for myself
Stephon took this meeting
And he remember Steven berries laying out their vision for the sneak
They're going to call at the star bear
That's been Stefan's nicknames in high school
And they have brought some prototype
Plus some clothes that would be part of the star berryline
They start showing me and you know
Stuff that we're making the quality is really good that is
I'm saying OK Google how much is all of that how much
It's like $15
You're going to make all of that stuff in $15
Damn
And then he
No we're going to sell all this stuff
All the stuff you see is going to be $15 or less
I said
T okay
Like I
And it was like no serious
For real
And I was like
Are you telling me you can make all of these different things and you can sell everything under $15
Let's do this deal
Another art
2 ways to think about Indore
The obvious one is that
You want to go out and find the most famous the biggest like the best person and attach them to your product
At this point in his
Career Stephon Marbury wasn't really any of those
But the other way of thinking of endorsements is it if you have the right product
In the right person
In a story is
Perfect
Then maybe you don't have to be the most famous person in the world
So yeah there's a place for the Air Jordan where you have the most
Famous basketball player matched up with the most expensive most
Shoe
But maybe there's also a place for the star berry
Where you have
Ellesse famous basketball player
Who has a great story about how he couldn't afford those shoes
But now
He's matched up with a $15
On August 17th
The shoe drop
The strawberry one went on sale
Exclusively
@stephen
Another basketball star is lending his name to a new sneaker unveils his line of high tops
At a low cost his starbury one basketball shoes that cost $14.98
Affordable for low-income families
The story was everywhere
And so is Stefan
Showing off
Strawberry one is a mostly white shoe it has dark veins and blue cutting across the upper that's the
The part that goes over the top of your foot
The sole of the shoe was New York Knicks orange the Team Stefan
Playing for time
People seemed
Excited to see it
But
Over and over
Same question
One question I might ask is
Are you cutting Corners at the production and cuz that's a sensitive issue everybody thought
If this cost $15
It cannot possibly
Be a good bass
I'm Good Morning America Diane Sawyer was worried about the bottom of the shoe
Basketball in here Jimmy Kimmel show a picture of Stephan holding up a shoe that look like someone had pulled it out of it.
But what do you want their $15 it was a price signaling
Problem
In the marketing and Retail World prices communicate so much information
Especially
In an aspirational market like athletic
So when you go out and you buy a new golf club for a little bit more money you're hoping
But that is going to buy you performance like maybe your drive will be 10 yards longer
And so pricing the star berry at $14.98
Had unintentionally signals that this sneaker
Is crap
The Fancy Shoes are ten times more money does that mean that they are 10 times better does that mean
That the star berry is 10 *
Worse
See Premier the shoe
I forgot to
Before we talked
I went on eBay
The price signaling problem
Dominated the starburys Khan
And what's the phone kept saying was
If people would just try these things out they would see that these are not 10 times
These shoes are 10 years old my bodies on eBay
They're my size
I'mma put you through the wringer man
I'm a play
Play games on it
Try to run a half marathon time prediction is that they're going to hold up
You going to run a half marathon
Try try having
I haven't trained for it you good
Okay on the good baby go for it
Go for it
She's kind of heavy don't breathe well but
Not the problem I am the problem 6 - 6.55
I did a half of a half an hour
Terrible idea she was hella fine
They also actually held up really well running and cutting on a basketball court
But listen these are not the exact same as $150 pair of
Many of the differences are just cosmetic
It looks very simple the laces aren't fancy
And I suspect the leather upper
Is actually pleather although I've never gotten
A straight answer on that
But there are things that seem more important like there's no match for breathing there's no air bubble in the
Nikhil
That said
It is way closer to an expensive shoe than I expect
And so when the shoe came out
The goal was to get people to try it and have the same experience I had
Stefan went on interview after interview
Trying to convince people just give it a chance
My favorite way that's dafont
Did this
Was he tried
I tried so hard
To just get someone to take a star berry
Had to take an expensive shoe
How to do an analysis
By chopping them both
If you take a $200 shoe and you take my shoe and you cut both of the shoes down
Got a motor with a chainsaw over and over
Cut both of them down the middle
And then finally someone actually took Stephan up on
Cut it down a half to do the same exact thing
Really
It was John Stossel on 20/20 actually took a pair of Jordans and a pair of starburys
Sneaker
Expert so we cut both shoes up
And he and others In The Biz
Concluded are constructed the same way
Are the Air Jordans do have this thing that looks like an air vent but
It's closed
I actually talked to the guy who is in charge of Designing Air Jordans at the time a sneaker Legend
Name Dewayne Edward
Oh yeah we bought a pair just to see cuz we were curious to like how they pull this off
Auntie Wayne said Yeah we actually chopped a pair of them open to
It was about the bare minimum you need to build a basketball shoe
He wouldn't go play in it
But that said
Is it better
Then you would expect a $15 sneaker
It was
It was honestly actually
People cutting a shoe open grate
But Howard Schecter from Steven berries
Says that both he and Stefan new
There's really only one
Test but ultimately
Can an NBA player
Where these $15 shoes
In a real
NBA game
It is very easy to record $50 anything
Thank ya
But if an NBA player
Kenan Trust
Their body
Tibby's
It's got to be good enough
It's got to be good
The shoe launched in the summer during the autopsy
People had months
To speculate
About whether the shoe could hold up or not
And then on November 1st
The day arrived
First game of the season
New York Knicks
Versus the Memphis Grizzlies
They're Stefan wearing the black version of the starberry the version he wore for away game
Howard sheckter remembers watching this
Enormous Pride every time they showed up and you saw that logo
We
Chilitos little company nobody ever heard of
We we made it we got this NBA star is wearing the sneaker we thought about on
Concord
The game was going great it was
What's the third quarter Stefan and the Knicks
We're leaving by 9
And then all of a sudden
I think staff tripped or something
Imma
I'm thinking it better not been the shoe whenever he's playing in those reduced
Price shoes
But the wind is knocked out of me
God forbid
The shoe ripped on court
Or it didn't hold the traction any any slipped in tours near something
You know it's done
Define goes over to the bench the game goes on without him and somebody rushes over to look at his foot
And everyone is like oh my god let's hope it wasn't the shoes fault like let like talking about
Probably Define was totally fine
And he got a kick in the shin or something
Came back into the game and honestly he doesn't even remember it
You know this is part of basketball
When the next game came Stefan for the $15 shoe again
And then the next game
And the next game
For the entire season Stephon Marbury
Wore a $15
Sneaker
Sales of the star berry
Tok off
Steve & Barry's expanded the line Beyond just the basketball sneaker and in total over the next year-and-a-half they sold
Around 4 million pairs
Starbury sneakers
Instaff on for his part
Kevin Durant 8 million dollars
In royalties off of clothes
And shoes
Duffy's Bar not Air Jordan numbers but remember they didn't have to
Because Stefan was making affordable shoes
Fat people wanted
And he was making money
The experiment
Was a success
It had worked
7 Plex a point to this one moment in particular
Thumbs this up
It's from one of his store appearances and is actually video
When is a little kid
He shopping with his mom
And he's picking out all of these clothes and then he just goes and he walks to the camera he said
I'm living in a dream mean
I'm in a dream
Veteran
It did not last forever
Because in 2008
The financial crisis
Howard schachter
Send it hit Steven berries
Particularly hard
Retailers that work on thin margin
Rely heavily on the credit markets
To give them a line of credit in which to go out and buy inventory
And then you saw that inventory and pay back the bank and
And keep going
But credit lines
Froze up
And Steven Berry's filed for bankruptcy
Without the store the $15 sneaker experiment
What's Done Steven berries was the exclusive provider of the sneaker and they were the ones
Handling the manufacturer
Those with their connect
Those were my connection
Other things were also going badly for Stefani
His father had died tragic
His basketball team was struggling and he was getting blame
Time for it
Plus he wanted young anymore
And so in 2009
He decided
It was time to
Stefan left the NBA
And you left the starbury sneakers experiment behind
But then
Stephon Marbury resurrected his career
In the one place
That might still give his sneaker dream
A chance
Rihanna
Washu ma bully
After the break
Stephon Marbury
China
What I ate youngboy what does it mean I love China
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to
Strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf
. org
In 2010 after Stephon Marbury had left the NBA
If you want to play professional basketball in China
After a couple years he landed on the Beijing ducks
A beloved perennial Underdog
They had never won a champion
So we go we went 13 games in a row out the gate
Stephon Marbury led the Beijing ducks to its first championship
And that another
And then another
He has since become one of the most
Famous basketball players
In Chinese basketball head
It's like a whole new life baby I can't tell you no lie
It's the truth
Statues Museum
Am I mistaken there was like a musical also did a musical
I did a play
From that moment
The Vice news organization actually went and recorded this play
Stefan is now very well connected in China
The global capital of sneaker Manufacturing
And of course basketball players are still putting a name
Amazon basketball sneakers and charging an absurd amount
And so Stefan
Has decided it is time
To bring back
The star berry
A solid
Affordable basketball shoe with his name
Is currently a limited run of starburys available online
They're ramping up production now
Instafont will still sell
A $15 basket
Can you still make and sell basketball sneakers for $15
That you could
Play basketball in
Yes you can
It's happening
It is happening
Exciting
I'm very excite
Cuz I want all the little kids to be happy when they plan on the court refresh Pig kicks
You understand that's what it's really about
This time around though
He's also going to be selling some higher-end
Although
What's the fun higher-end means
50 bucks
60 bucks
The shoes will mostly be sold online
But there is a plan to have a couple of flagships
One in Brooklyn possibly Coney Island
Neighborhood works
Stephon grew up
The other one
In Stefan's new home
Beijing
All right future can you hear with an update Scarborough
Curry shoes are still being sold today according to the website you can get a pair online or
ATS elect Citi Trends stores
Did you cost a little bit more than $15 an hour
The cheapest men's shoes go for 90
T90
As for Stephon Marbury he fully retired from basketball in 2008
And in the final seconds of his final professional game in China
Stefan pulled up for 3-point shot
Crowd hold its breath I sue my wasn't there but he drain the shot his team won he ended his career
Gonna make
This episode was originally produced by Sally come with an assist from Elizabeth Co
This update was produced by our intern Rachel Cohn
Planet money's editor is Bryant first at or supervising producer is Alex gold
Marking special thanks this week to eduard Saakashvili and to Chuck tatelbaum who helped me make sense of hundred
Creative pages of bankruptcy
If you would like to tell us about
I don't know if your sneaker
Blowing out or something you can let us know we are Planet Money at NPR. Org we are also pain
Instagram Twitter we are at Planet
I'm Kenny Malone
Thanks for listening