Tony Miranda is the kind of police officer
Who makes you want to follow the rules
More because you just don't want to disappoint him
Not so much because you're
Scared
Physically
I'm only like 5 6 and 1/2 5 7 out of the academy hours
Hundred
40 lb wet
So I was challenged on almost every stop every arrest and they're like okay
Officer take me to jail I like to see you do it to learn how to use
His wit
And he pretty quickly made a name for himself
About 20 years into his career
Tony caught the attention of a nearby
They wanted him to
To be the new police chief
In Irwindale California
Just east of LA
It's like a well-kept
Secret
There's only 14 and a residence
And a lot of them are second and third generation ruined aliens
They've just been there for
Ever
Apparently people who moved to Irwindale rarely
It's this town where everyone seems to know each other and it has lots of perks for a town that size
A modern Rec Center really nice parks
Their own little Library
And they are able to provide medical and
And benefits for the resident
Meaning like if you're a resident of Irwindale
The city gives you health insurance
It's not comprehensive but
It's something that's like a premier little cities are so there's a lot of civic pride in the little community
Lots of Pros to becoming the police chief in Irwindale
One big caveat
The city was known for the police department because it garnered the most news
I'm talking Front Page News
News at 6 News at 5:11
And
All negative
We're talking about some
Serious ugly
Heinous crimes
Like one officer had been accused of sexually assaulting a woman during an early-morning traffic
Stop another accused of
Embezzlement
And now there was a third officer
It was under investigation for having none
Sex with minors
So are you
And I'm not even talking dark cloudy
Cast of black cloud over the whole community
All of these scandals we're just taking an emoji
Emotional toll on this tight-knit little town they were taking a financial told
These candles cause Irwindale millions of dollars in legal fees
And it wasn't just the city footing the bill that
Is what turned this from the police reform story that you usually hear what about protest and activists
Into an entirely different one a version we had never heard before
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Karen Duffin and I'm Sarah Gonzales
Three on the show Tony Miranda goes to Irwindale
You guys pick the police department
And he has a powerful Ally out of
Is back this entire industry that puts a price tag
I'm police
Behavior a sort of Shadow regulator with the power
Change police
Insurance
This is the story of what happened
Winnie Police Department can no longer afford it
Bad behavior
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Which come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solution
It support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information
Is available at aecf. Org
Tony Miranda never thought that it
Easy to clean up the Irwindale police
Department
But as he walks into the building on his first day
He starts to really understand what he's in
4picture lowlights
A building that was built in about 1985
Bottom of the walls are cinder block they're all dark gray
And there's no
Art posters art
Anything on the walls
Like this is really sad it's depressing in here
There are a lot of basic things that most police departments should have
Like there are these things called mdt's they're these fancy
Computer screen type things that police have in their cars to track 911 calls
Tell them where to go what they respond
Antonis asking his guys
Why are there only
A few of these
And a bunch of them broke
And I said well if you're not
Using an NBT how do you get to call
And one of the patrolman's holds up his palm and he says like this
I look at his palm I'm going
That's unacceptable
Until I could see red
Can you call scratch it out Gondola calling scratch it out
He's riding the calls on his palm of his hand with his ink pen
Okay we are really starting from the bottom
And if we have any hope of fixing this this team will have to band together
Those really bad officers the ones wrapped up in the expense
Glass suits
They had either been fired or we're on leave while they were being invest
The Gated
But if Tony wants to prevent any new problems
He needs to fix
The culture
Administration and the officers just could not get along so
It was a lot of internal
Fairs in Ithaca
There were 30 employees and 14 Internal Affairs investigation
And these are not just people in the community complaining about bad cops
These were cops complaining against other cops and administrators complaining against
Cops it was just unreal never experienced anything like it
Tony quickly realizes that the same thing that makes this small-town great
Is also what has made it such a hard place to chain
Everyone knows each other
So when there's a fight in the police department the cop might just
Call is Uncle on the city council
The fights there are entrenched and there
Personal almost tribal
Saucony things
We need some new blood
He calls his leadership team together and tells them
I'm hiring a new number two
And
It's not going to be any of you
It was really quiet and and one Sergeant stand up and says you know what chief
Police Officers Association not going to stand for that
They're going to call 4 a.m.
Oh no confidence
Find me yeah the new guy
Right of the bat basically hey city council fire the
This guy so Tony is standing there at home if it's 5 foot 6 l
Looking straight at mu
And this may have been where the
The story ends
But
Tony had more than his width
Chino's
Change is
Coming whether they like it or not
Because of
Their insurance
Authority
In some situations Insurance have a lot of power over Apple
Police Department's most small or mid-sized police
East Apartments have some kind of insurance
In part because
Police Department's get sued all the time for all kinds of things
Justified or not
And insurance help
Cover the rest
Big cities like Los Angeles they get enough taxpayer money that they can
Basically self-insure like
Set aside some money for a rainy day or a lawsuit
But smaller cities like Irwindale they actually buy insurance
Through either a private insurer or something called a municipal risk pool a municipal risk pool is kind of like
Like a family car insurance
Irwindale is on the same insurance plan as a bunch of other please
Nice apartments in Calif
And if one of those Police Department's gets in a wreck
Everyone's premium can go up
They call them
And the worst part about this plan is that everyone knows it's your fault
Irwindale
You're the bad teenage driver in this family
So they needed to either
Get a handle on things or
Cancel their policy is that was that was it
What are the two options
Yes or you can you need to shop for another one
And you'll be paying some premium
That's if you can even find another insurer willing to take you on
If you can't
You might lose your Police Department altogether
Because one incident could race
Taxes are even bankrupt
Small town one run
Conviction one use of excess Force
And Tony wanted to make sure his rank-and-file understood the stakes were that high
So he brings them all together and says
Let me tell you guys a little story about Maywood California you know me what about
20 miles west of us
Their Police Department also had a lot of problems
And our risk for our family insurance plan
Got tired of footing the bill
First
Maywood God of War
They were told they needed to fix it
They didn't
And they lost
Insurance
They can no longer be police officer because of the motto of exposure they have
The whole Police Department
Shut down
The city of Maywood couldn't bear the risk
Of having police
Without the insurance Authority
Antoni tells his officers
I was there at the end
The day they shut down I remember it
Just before midnight
All of the Maywood Police Officers
Lineup in the parking lot
Dressed in their finest
Tell their standard
San Marino
Already 2825 years on
And they're about to lose their career in their jobs and I know this
And
It's like being at a funeral everybody's crying in the audience
And these
Grown men are standing here weeping
One by one
Each officer steps forward
Picks up the police radio
And what does
Chief does have them
Do one last radio transmission saying that they're going out of service
Charlie glass
These are recordings of those final Transmissions
When Charlene
And they had to do a final salute and then he takes their badge
And take their
They put their portable radio in a box
The last one to go is
The police chief
He salutes
And then he signs off for the last time
Cudahy Police Department
This will be our last
Transmission
David Feliz
Call Darrell b1070
End of Watch
God bless all of you
So I shared that story with them and I said
I've seen bigger stronger
Mendon yuan in this room
Broken down in tears
Don't think for a minute
Did it will not happen
I've seen it happen
Tony says this is the moment
After he told that story
Did he started to notice a ship
At the Irwindale police
Police Department
This is real this is
An exterior threat that could
Close Irwindale police department down
This was
Real
Irwindale censure had made it
Very
Clear Irwindale PD had to follow a
Performance Improvement plan
We had eight things to fix
And 18 months to fix them
The clock
Birthday cake
Support for this podcast
Send the following message come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solution
Support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information
Is available at aecf
. org
Quick note I did reach out to Irwindale ensure and other people in town and many of them were willing to talk
But said that
City official had told them not to speak
However we verified the story with some folks who just
Didn't want to be recorded
And with public
Okay back to the story
For a long time a lot of police departments weren't allowed to buy insurance
People that it would create moral hazard basically
If your risky behavior is covered by someone else
You might do more of it
But then in the 1960s there were a few Supreme Court rulings that gave police more rules
The right to remain silent anything you say can and will be used against you in a court of law
That's right
Shoutout Law & Order there
And all of this
Made it much easier to sue the police so
Moral hazard be damned
Smaller police departments felt like they had to get in
There's a hole
Big powerful well-financed industry
Daddy's trying to influence police
Behavior this is John Rappaport he's a law professor at the University of Chicago and he wrote one of the first paper
Looking at the influence of insurance on police
In the mix of a discussion that is often understandably heated and emotional
Insurers Look at police departments through the cold hard lens
Of an actuary
Does this police Behavior create risk
If yes
Let's reduce it
It's a business relationship
To say we're actually not
Protesters are activists we're not telling you you're bad
We're just telling you
That your numbers are worse than they were last
And we want to bring them back down to where they were
The goal of these insurers is not just to win lawsuit
It's to be so above board that nobody even brings a lawsuit
So often insurance issue guidelines that are more strict than the law
Chicks strip search
After the Supreme Court said police can strip search pretty much anyone for any arrest
This one insurance was like
Yeah we're going to give our police some restriction
And they added things like
You should have someone of the same gender
Conduct a strip search
And you should do it
In a sanitary setting
And those are things that
Actually aren't in
The Supreme Court's opinion
But it seemed time I think the
The insurer was you know
Using common sense
How would this look to a jury
And if you really want to make sure people are behaving the way they should
Sometimes
You got to be proactive
One insure
Said that they send
An insurance representative to hang out at cop bars
And listen to gossip
I mean if you do hear anything alarming they reported back to the
Vying for that job I'll go you know if you really need me to go drink in whatever.
And John says look they don't just leave cops out there hoping they don't match
They also try to help them out
In the most insurance way possible
Doing things like updating police manuals or giving them training
And if the department does get better there are rewards like lower premium
So back in Irwindale Tony has his to-do list
Ba things that his family insurance plan has said he has to change in 18 months
Antonio added a few things himself to help fix the culture
Calls all his people together
And he stepped up to the Whiteboard
And says alright
This is how we're going to
Why do we are going to treat this like a plane crash
A plane just crash in Irwindale
You're all paramedics
Let's
Triage this that start with the most essential
Equipment
Remember those monitors the ones that tell cops where to go when they're responding to a 911 call
Irwindale fix them up and bought some more
The stuff that would help reduce risk
You know
Going on a 911 call is pretty important that
You're sweaty Palm Desert
Turn the 9 into a
3 or 6
They fixed up their patrol car is fixed
The cameras in their cars got workplace harassment training and
More training community-based policing
Courses
Officer safety change was that Tony had to run almost everything he did buy the insurance Authority
Like if you wanted to discipline someone or fire someone
He needed their permission
We met every I think it was every Wednesday at 10 a.m.
Without I mean you cleared your calendar you're going to be there
Field have to run your
Things by Insurance Company
Well
It was not common practice ask
And
To a certain degree act out second-guess but at the end of the day
It just adds
More credibility
Because
It wasn't Justice outside Chief saying
This is what we're going to do
It's also our insurance company
Who can make us or break us
Tony says they didn't really overrule his decisions they just made him explain why he wanted some
Something and as long as it made sense they were cool with it was her appointment with you thought
This might
Work
I think it was in year two axle
In my second year on the 4th of July
It was Urban deals Independence Day party in all the cops
Time to work
So Tony brought a grill made everyone
Tacos
Somewhere in the middle of it Tony took
Picture
And
The day was over and I went home and I looked at that picture on my cell phone
And I looked at their faces and they were all smiling
And I hadn't seen that anywhere
No Irwindale is just one police department in one small town with a specific set of issues
If you step back though
And ask whether insurance is an effective way to improve Police Department
Overall
John Rappaport
That law professor says
Sometimes
The issues they care about most are the expensive
Things that might generate
Large payouts like
Excessive force
But the less legally expensive the issue
The less likely insurance is
Two addresses
Because insurers aren't making moral judgments for them police reform is a business
For Irwindale pressure from an insurance Authority seems to have helped
18 months after Tony showed up under that
Cloud the insurance authority to Clare. Irwindale new and improved
They could keep their coverage
They could stay a police depart
Antoni says he doesn't think they could have done it without that performance improved
Open plan that pet
I have to say
Without that pimp
The officers will continue to be aggressive than continue to fight absent of the pimp
I'm not sure if Irwindale would be here today
I'm really not sure
I'm I'm not sure
Tony decided
His work was done and he handed off the department
To a new job
I'm handing you the keys to a Cadillac
Please take care
These guys are good guys
And you're very lucky
You're lucky
Were you driving when you got there late
1972 Gremlins like a pinto on 2 cylinders it was bad
If you have a story idea of email s we're at Planet Money at NPR
Are. Org Today Show was produced by Nick Fountain Brian Earth that edits our show and Alex goldmark is our supervisor
Baby predictor
Special thanks to KPCC and KCRW also rate
Great story about this issue for the Atlantic Joanna Schwartz Tsubasa done some great research on this
And thanks to all the people who spoke with me on backgrounds
I'm Karen Duffin and I'm Sarah Gonzales thanks for this