Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Elsa Chang
When Donald Trump was a businessman
She brought a lot
Quite often
Common but
What are his businesses
Defaulted on a bunch of those dads
It became harder and
Harder for him to borrow from a lot of banks
But
It was one thing that did not run away
Leaned in
Netbank
Is Deutsche Bank
Right now house Democrats are trying to get a bunch of records from Deutsche that
Are connected
To Trump
It's a conflict that's been playing out in the news and I've been really confused about all the
Which is why
I was glad our friends at
Podcast
Trump Inc
From WNYC
Publica
I put together an excellent at
So what about the long relationship
The Trump family
Deutsche bank
So we decide to run an edited version of
Right here
It starts with Trump Inc Andrea Bernstein
Talking about some of Deutsche bank's
Troubles
Ladies and gentlemen
Very welcome
In January the head of Deutsche Bank
Christian setting did an interview with Uber huesers business editor at the German newspaper decide
The two were speaking at a reception at the world economic Forum in Davos Switzerland
Do you want it to be
Become a drone
Pierce user the newspaper man asking the banker
If you were a journalist
How would you report on Deutsche Bank today
What would you write
Did you eat your CEO was taking a bath
He fumbles for a moment
I would say Deutsche Bank is
The most
Self-help story
A few months earlier the German police have raided the Bank Frankfort headquarters
It's disappointing
Not disappointing you know personally
Being subject to investigations and Regulatory actions have become the new normal for Deutsche Bank
In recent years the bank has been fined billions of dollars for lack
Controls
On everything from laundering Russian money
Violating sanctions against Iran Libya and Sudan
Somehow you life is
Tainted by Deutsche Bank past
How do you live with the
The constant uncertainty
That's something that is my papa
You know I think that makes live really interesting
By that standard
Life has become
Burien
Fordite today
In a recent court filing
Congress reveal that has been asking for detailed records of
Family business interactions with Deutsche Bank
In the filing Congress Ed
Straight out
It's investigating the relationship
Four possible money laundering
Illicit Financial deals
Fraud and foreign influence in the 2016 election
Bates own admission Deutsche Bank has a history of serious compliance deficiency
When it comes to Global money laundering
In the very recent past
Now comes a new revelation from The New York Times
Scotiabank
Own anti-money-laundering
Flag multiple suspicious transaction
They were as recent as 2016
In 2017
And involved
Trump's business
And the one formerly run by his son-in-law
Jared Kushner
Among the transactions
One more money had moved from Kushner companies
Two Russian individuals
The times wrote that don't your bank's money-laundering experts were so concerned
They wanted to report these transactions to the US Treasury
But supervisors refused
To do so
Carrie McEwan Deutsche Bank spokeswoman said in a statement
Alert disposition
By investigators undergo a higher-level review by qualified staff
Transaction monitoring Castle wide neck
And not all alerts will result in escalation
She added we take our responsibility for compliance very serious
I'm at the bank has
Increase our anti Financial crime staff and enhanced is controls in recent years
A spokesperson for the Trump organization email the
The statement
This story is absolute nonsense
We have no knowledge
Launch of any flag
Transactions with Deutsche Bank
In fact
We have no operating accounts with Deutsche Bank
We sent questions to the Kushner company is the White House Trump's private Banker
And lawyers for the trumps and Jared Kushner
The White House did not have comment the others didn't respond
Meanwhile
The investigations
Those subpoenas were sent to multiple financial institutions including and Deutsche Bank the house intelligence and
Financial services companies are hoping to get information on loans the German Bank gave
A to the Trump and Trump organization and then
Friends calling harassment of the Trump family and their organization sued Deutsche Bank and Capital One to block subpoena
Penis into your bank and we are
Collecting a lot of the document that we have requested and we are reviewing them
I can only tell you that the investigation came about as a result of the testimony
Michael Cohen
Hello and welcome to Trump Inc podcast
WNYC and propublica that digs deep into the secrets of the Trump family business
Andrea Bernstein
Today on the show Trump
And his family's relationship with Deutsche Bank
A bank with a history of problems
They were laundering money
For wealthy Russians and people connected to Putin and the Kremlin
In a variety of ways
For almost the exact time. They were doing business with Donald
This is David enrich
The finance editor of the New York Times
And all of that money through Deutsche Bank was being channeled through the same exact legal entity
In the US
That was handling the Donald Trump
And there are a lot of coincidences here there's a lot of smoke
I have not found any fire
But unfortunately I do not possess subpoena power
We're going to walk you through all that smoke from Pink is an open investigation
So we're just going to say right now we're still not sure what this all adds up to
What we do now
Trump right now is about 350 million dollars to Deutsche Bank
More than he owes to any other financial institution and so much is happening regarding the bank
So fast but we decided to lay out what we have learned
By digging into Trump's Financial deals with the bank
And why his recent loans raise so many question
Questions raised by Congress
The New York attorney general
And the bank's own employees
Support for this podcast
In the following message come from ZipRecruiter
Hiring
Used to be hard
Multiple job site
Stacks of resume
But today
Hiring in Bez
And you only have to go to
One place to get it done
ZipRecruiter sends your job to over a hundred of the web
Leading job board
Vin ZipRecruiter scan thousands of resumes
Define people with the right experience
And invites them to apply to
To your job
Try it for free
Ziprecruiter.com Planet Money
James Reid was fatally beaten on Selma Street 1960
Is death
Galvanized
Put in a court room 9 months later a not guilty verdict
In episode 2
The trial and the birth of the conspiracy
Mmpr it's White Lies
Listen And subscribe now
So let's go back to the beginning of Trump's relationship with Deutsche Bahn
Hits 1998
His life
Is like the Destiny's Child song
No no no no no
Trump's companies have to
Declared for bankruptcy so many lenders that the Big Bang
Chase and Citibank
Well Trump was looking for a bank
Any bank would do
David and Rich of the times has upcoming book about Joy
Dark Tower the inside story of the world's most destructive Bank
He says
When Deutsche Bank First approached Trump in 1998
Both Trump and the bank needed each other
He was completely frozen out of financial
Defaulting on loans
And
Deutsche Bank in the late 1990s
Was
Very eager to make a name for it so
Self in the United States
So they really needed to go searching on the fringes
Define clients that were
They had a bunch of money but that their reputations were sufficiently scuffed-up
That they were not suitable clients for the big Elite
Wall Street investment
And Donald Trump fit that bill.
The bank lend him money for a downtown Manhattan skyscraper in the building across from the UN
And Trump's business came with
He would fly Bankers to Atlantic City for boxing matches take them to the US Open tennis tournament in Queens
Then
He asked the bank to sell
High risk
Bonds
Junk bonds
To keep his casinos going
Sandwiches reporting's on Georgia Bankers initially didn't want to but when Trump dangled the weekend at Mar-A-Lago
Assault
480 million dollars
Cinnabons
Everyone is really pleased with the outcome until a few months later
Donald Trump default
I'm looking for Hans with his guess what everyone had feared would happen in the first
So
There should have long-term reputational risk of selling junk bonds that are in default
Irrelevant
Well thank you everybody it is quite a crowded
Not too long after
Trump was once again bound up with Deutsche Bank
140 million dollars
Lights for a Trump Tower Chicago
Help get the loan he assured Bankers that his daughter Ivanka then a recent college grad would be in charge of the devel
Family was in it for the long haul very very happy with what's happened with respect to this building and
How fast can September 2008
Got this one bill and we're really
2 months later
Trump default
Did something unusual and on dacious after
Defaulting on the loan Trump sued his lender Deutsche Bank
The lawsuit began like this this action arises out of defendant Deutsche bank's attempt to derail the success
Well completion of one of the most acclaimed construction projects to be built in the United States in recent times
It went downhill from there complained he couldn't pay back the loan because the financial crisis
Was a force measure an act of God that Deutsche Bank was responsible for the crisis anyway
He asked for billions of dollars in Damages
Deutsche Bank suit and back
The trumps
Kept selling units in Chicago
In a real estate business the word luxury is terribly overused
It's lost
Ivanka Trump has by now become a key marketer
Action property
Fabulously luxurious
Trump International Hotel & Tower
Chicago's famous Skyline
Finally after a few years the two sides settle
He's on the hook
440 million dollars
Which he personally guaranteed
He needs to pay that back to Deutsche Bank
Where does he get the money
This is where they're already strained relationship
It's way stranger
Out of the blue the person who comes to his rescue is his new son-in-law
Jared Kushner
David enrich of the New York Times
And he had
Jared Kushner had struck up a relationship with a private Banker at
Band named Rosemary
Do we know how do we know how they met
We don't that is one of the world's greatest Mysteries if you occupy
My brain
What I know is that in probably around the summer of 2011
Jared arrange a meeting for his father-in-law
To go into Deutsche Bank
And meet with rosemary
Who at the time was one of the
The real shining stars
Deutsche Bank
Private Bank
And private banking is have a weird business than most people who do not
Obsess over the stuff
I probably never heard of in it
Part of the bank that caters to the world's richest
The job of a private Banker is usually to help rich people protect their wealth and grow it even more
To keep tax authorities away from their Investments
And companies
Private bankers
Do not usually loan money for a large commercial real estate developer
Rabbit did not respond to our questions for this story
As before Trump showers attention on all the right people
Bradley
What time is the Trump Tower gets treated like a friend
There's a favorable profile
In one of Jared kushner's newspapers
And Donald Trump that maybe
This arm of Deutsche Bank the private bank
Can strike up a fresh relationship with Donald Trump
And do what no other bank on Wall Street
What no other bank is willing to do is loan Trump
48 million dollars
Taipei off the door Jamaica Chicago loan
Because Trump has defaulted on his loan and Sue the bank for billions of dollars
But with the help of Rosemary vrablic
He's getting money from Deutsche Bank to pay off Deutsche Bank
No one is ever seen anything like
In fact a lot of the people I've talked to at the bank
Previously at the bank
Had
Initially insisted this just hadn't even happen
It's not the way work at all
And it is the way it works
And it just so extraordinary and unusual
That no one
Believed it to be possible
Deutsche Bank
Enrich their private wealth unit made money from truck
Because he opens personal accounts there
Brought them business
And yet this is
One of the clearest examples I've ever seen a bank that is so dysfunctional
And so careless about is risk management and so careless about the reputations of it
Clients
And so
Loose with
The protection of its own reputation that it would allow
A guy
Who has repeatedly defaulted in burn the bank and caused a huge public embarrassment
To borrow
Tens of millions of dollars from another arm of the bank
To repay the part of the bank
That
Vicki is engaged in litigation
It is it's
Really mine
It's not
Just Chicago
Around the time when Deutsche Bank is getting ready to pay off Deutsche Bank
Trump starts
Coveting
Bankrupt golf course near Miami
Doral
It has a history of Hosting major tournaments
MIT post financial crisis
It's not in great shape
And it's in the flight path of the Miami Airport
The property itself I was told by people involved in the bankruptcy was kind of a dog
This is Heather Vogel from propublica
She dug into the bankruptcy records and land Deeds for Doral
The sellers were going to go with Trump because
He was willing to
Close by with no Finance
Essentially
The bankruptcy filing showed that Trump agrees to pay $150 for the whole business
105 million is for the property in the buildings
Atlanta record show
And that's where it gets kind of interesting I think because
He does not buy the property for all-cash he does need financing and from what we can tell he needs a
A lot of fun
And for that money he again turns to Deutsche Bank
Trump flies Rosemary vrablic
The private bank
Down to Florida
And she helps him again
Deutsche Bank loans him 106
Million dollars
Remember the county records show that Trump paid 105 million for the land and buildings portion of the sale
And the sale in the loan are recorded the same week
To the Moon again
Is for more money that he pays for the property
And we are also after digging around found out it wasn't actually the only loan that they gave on this
Property is another Droid Turbo
Awesome
My Rosemary
This one
419 million dollars is also backed at least in part by the Doral Golf Course
So that means he's got 125 million dollars in loans on a property that was sold for 100
5 million
Which is certainly not the kind of thing that anybody who's bought a Homewood
Define believable
You can't just get a bank to give you all of the money for your house
There could be an explanation for this
An appraisal showing Doral was worth more or additional collateral
What we do know
What's in the public records raises the question
Of whether the loan was unusually high for the property
I think that there's a larger context here that's interesting because of Deutsche bank's involvement
Which has been accused of not doing enough due diligence in order to spot money laundering and to stop
You have Trump who has also been repeatedly accused of not doing due diligence with his Partners has been involved with p
Who have criminal connections for years people with connections to Russia and people with
Connection to illicit activity in Russia
You start had this Nexus of all these different
Actors
To have had problems in the past and you've got that the court would appears to be a business decision that doesn't make
Why would Deutsche Bank
Lenses much money
For this property
The trumps themselves
Spun out yet another story
Forbes wrote about it
How Ivanka Trump got the Doral Resort and the Blue Monster for a bargain-basement price
And had a baby at the same time
We got the Ral which is
A great deal of myself
2012 Ivanka Trump released a video touting some recent accomplishments
Celebrity
Trump organization was also tapped for another important detail for the family
At a time when the trumps were buying golf courses and thinking farming licensing deals
It was a development project
They really want it
Additionally
We were selected by the GSA effectively the government
Tom the preferred Developers for the old post office building in washing
Incredibly
To widespread criticism in alarm
Donald Trump's family business
Gets a 60-year lease
Quran what is now the Trump International Hotel in Washington
Another bidder files of protest
Claiming there's no way Trump can live up to his financial promises
His history of defaults and Company bankruptcies
Should disqualify
Ivanka does the negotiating and the tramps lineup an equity Park
Colony capital
Is that name sounds familiar
If the firm founded by Trump's friend
Tom Barrack
We recently did an episode on Barrack
He was Trump's inaugural planner know what we're doing is trying to oriented towards the the greatest tribute to America
Vera cleanse colonies name
Trump's bid for the Old Post Office
But then, he drops out
And Trump needs a new Financial partner
He gets another generous loan
This one 475 million dollars
Also through Rosemary vrablic
From Deutsche Bank
Ivanka Trump says the family is in it for the Long Haul
She wants her daughter Arabella to oversee the hotel someday
Trump now is going to bank nearly 350 million dollars
Weather Chicago
Two loans for Doral and one for the Old Post Office
Can you try to get another one to buy the Buffalo Bills but the deal never went through
The New York attorney general is looking at that one
Oh
There was one more loan
Coming up after the break
Deutsche Bank says no
To the trumps
Support for NPR in the following message come from Capital One business credit card
The spark cash
Offering Unlimited
2% cash back on everything you buy for your business
Capital One
What's in your way
Visit capitalone.com for more information
So how many candidates are running for president
22 maybe more to come if there's a lot to keep track of
Which is why the NPR politics podcast
Hitting the road
The introduce you to all the people running for president
Join us on the campaign Trail as we interview the candidate
To ask why they are the best pick for present
Follow along this spring and summer by
Subscribing to the NPR politics
All right we're going to pick up now with Andrea Bernstein
Podcast Trump
In May of 2015
Ivanka Trump's husband
Jared
Kushner's company
Buys the retail floors of the former New York Times building for just under three hundred million dollars
Then six
18 months later the kushners go to Deutsche Bank
To get an appraisal that says the property is worth two hundred million dollars more than they pay
Increase volume was because they were going to get more lucrative tenant
But anyway
They get a big loan from Deutsche Bank
It's for more than what they first paid for the building
They walk away
74 million dollars in cash
In 2016 someone is Georgia Bank finally decides to say no
Trump's running for president he asked for money for renovations at yet another Golf Course
This one's in Turnberry in Scotland
And this is the moment inside the bank
Where one senior executive after another realized
Just how deep
And
Long-standing the Donald Trump relationship was
And people are stun
And
They
Put a stop to David enrich
The loan was initially rejected
Buy a committee in the US that supposed to Veterans actions with an eye toward protecting
Reputation
And then Rosemary vrablic steam appeal that decision which is quite unusual
And this wind up
London Frankfurt where there's a big fight
At the top of the bank about whether or not to do this long and was eventually killed by the guy
Who is now the CEO the bay
Bank Preston 7
He's the guy we heard being interviewed
Beginning of the story by the German journalist
Are you sometimes mad at your predecessor
No
Ditto
I think
Also that you landed in sports you never look back
I mean this is setting it doubles again
He saying the bank is trying to turn a corner
Come clean
Make things right
You know what you just want to make this
Bang out again
A bank which lives up to
Descendants
And which has the record
Education which is used to have
And therefore I'm not looking back I'm not mad at three sisters
I just want to get my job right and at the end
You know what
We need to bring
Trifecta.
Today the bank faces an array of potential trap
For instance
If Trump
Bolts on his lungs
They have a choice
Seize the assets of the president of the United States
Or let alone slide
And given unimaginably large gift
To a sitting president
Trump's relationship with rosemary vrablic continues she was given VIP seats at the inaugural
And
This has not been previously reported
She was one of a select group of people who got to stay at Trump's hotel in the Old Post Office in Washington
During the inaugural
According to a person familiar with the arrangements that weekend
Other guests at the hotel included
Jared Kushner family
And key inaugural personnel
The Doral loans come due in 2023 the old post office and the Chicago loans
Karina possible
Second
Term
So house Democrats have said
Subpoenaed a bunch of records from Deutsche
And President Trump and his children Ivanka Don Jr and Eric
Absolute to prevent the release of those Wrecker
And in their complaint
They allege
Quote the subpoenas were issued
Rats
President Donald J Trump
To rummage through every aspect of his
Personal finances
Businesses and the private information of the president and his family
And
Interfered about for any material that might be used to
To cause him poop
Damage
And quote
Two congressional committees
Responded
They filed a
If opposing
Lawsuit and in it
They say
They have quote
Serious and Urgent questions concerning the safety of banking practices
Money laundering in the financial sector
Foreign influence in the political process
And the threat of foreign financial leverage including over the president
His family and
Just today at hearing a federal judge
Ruled against
Andrea Burnside was at that
Sharing and four more on that part of the story go listen to their version of this episode
On the Trump Inc podcast
You can find it at Trump Inc podcast. Org from WNYC and propublica
Subscribe for more stories just like this
The Trump Inc team includes make
Kramer
Sullivan Alice Wilder Bill Moss
Ilya marritz Charlie
Herman Eric manske Nick brushaber and Robin
Give me some music
Is my hand is brown
This planet money version was produced by Darren Woodson
Jager
And we always like to hear what you think of the show so send us an email at Planet Money on NPR. Org
Run Facebook Twitter and Instagram
At Planet Money
I'm off the chain