A few weeks ago reporter Sally Hershey
Steps decided to run an informal economic
So who Am I who am I talking to you introduce yourself in 10 years old
Estimator
10 years old
She was with her friend
I'm caffeine I'm 10 years old
Here we go Sally put a box on the table
It was
A cake
It wasn't intentionally a lab
There was like
A section with a pile of marshmallows another section with
Gummy bears
Another sex with a pile of Skittles
A pastry in the middle I know that it is a cannoli the cannoli
We have to figure out
How to fairly divide
Cake this is an actual academic
Problem there is a hole
Genre of literature dedicated to the
The cake cutting
Problem
This is a surprisingly complicated problem
The cake is all these different parts and the girls have
Really different taste
How do you both feel about the marshmallow marshmallow
But they do make different flavors if you combine them what we many mathematician
Thought about this for years
And there is
A solution
Called
Or if your kid it's called
I cut
U-Pick
One person cuts it and the other person decide who gets what
They could be equal
I think
That works
Too because I'm going to want to cut them equally so that then at least we at least
I don't get a tiny piece when she gets a big kid hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Kenny Malone
And today on the show we walk you through some of our favorite are division problems
And their Solutions we will tell you how to
Fairly split the rent between roommates how to take a movie when you're in a group of people with strong opinions and we go
Go to California
We're one of the most complicated Fair division problems we've ever seen
Exists
It is a mess
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses
Design and build their own website
Using customizable light
And features including e-commerce functionality
Leanne mobile app
Squarespace also offers
First built and search engine optimization
To help you develop an online price
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Okay problems of fair
You see examples of these
All the time
Take your morning commute
Maybe your Highway has an express lane
Yeah how do you decide which
Stripers get to use it
Should you only allow carpoolers or
People be allowed to
To pay to bypass traffic even think about a swimming pool
Should there be a special Adult Swim should some Lanes
Be dedicated just for swimming laps
One guy is always this guy in a little
Rubber
Beating top and those like
Blue plastic cargo rooting for everybody
Right
Anyway
These are all resources
With someone
Needs to cut and divide
In the whole reason we got interested in Fair division is
Is because of this mess we heard about
In Santa Barbara California
So I headed there to check it out
Is this refund mccrummen
Nick Cannon
Harbor operations
I'm at Santa Barbara Public Harbor and helps run things here he's the Harbormaster
Nick
Oh my God it's so beautiful no one told me California
So pretty and beautiful
We can ask
Look out at the water here
On one side mountains and palm trees on the other
Folks
Sailboat
Commercial fishing boat
Yacht
This big white boat over here Sally
What's a catamaran
Don't look super fancy
Is super big
Mixes that belongs to Warren Buffett's business partner Charlie Munger
Bethesda
The Crosby used to keep a boat here
Kevin Costner and Kathy Ireland husband still do and here is the problem Santa Barbara has run
Over the last 30 years it has become a destination for the rich
And Famous
Famous people love
Really big boats
Troup head so the harbor has run into this classic dilemma
It needs to parcel out these limited space
At the public Harbor
So that everyone
From a fisherman to a billionaire
Could have a shot at getting one of these spots
Very quickly
Demand for places to keep a boat
Got out of hand
The waiting list for a boat slip
Which is a parking space for a boat
Was so long
Get ready for it
You could be waiting to
100 years for a spot
However there was this one
Loophole
You could by somebody else
Boat
It is part of that transaction
They could transfer the rights
They're like boat
Parking Spot 2
And so
This Market Spring
You overpay for somebody's boat
You get their spot on the dock and you don't have to worry about that giant waiting
It's like buying somebody's crap
EPPICard to get there
And as soon as you have something increasing in value and a way to train it
You get speculators
Because back in the day back in 1999 or 2000
A lot of people they were buying boats and getting slip permits
As Investments
Except of course the city owns all those
Stock spots
So investors weren't buying real estate they were just
Paying for the right to park their boats there
And then hoping they could sell those rights
To make a profit
I just got so high people were
Grant but it was this one rule speculators had to abide by
You can just get it
Permit leave it empty and let its value
You had to have a boat there
Any boat
We're people just
Buying
Like some sort of
Crappy old boat
Parking
Yep
Yep to sit on to sit on the investor
Oh absolutely
Basically I wouldn't stick that was 60 feet long
A stick no basically
A log with some you know
I mean
I'm exaggerating but not by much
Just a
Yeah okay log marries a canoe
And and their offspring is what I'm talking of it was clear to mix
That his Harbors way of giving up these spots
Was not working
They just completely out of whack
This whole mess at the harbor is an example of
Fair division at its
Very worse
And this was how we got fascinated
With the world of fair division problem
We figured
Certainly there must be someone who
Studies all the different ways
Harbors or cities
Or cake loving people
Can split stuff up
And of course
There was
Should I start now
How to hire Constantino's
Said that's colitis and a professor of computer science at MIT
What are your colleagues call you
ICarly cast
Kostas is an expert in game
And he says of course not every Fair division problem
Is as simple as dividing a
Yeah like what about things you
You Can't Touch This
What happens when money gets
What about when there are more than
Will trying to share
Socastee is going to walk us through a range of fair division
Spring start
Which one of the most
Practically
Something called
The rental Harmony problem
And man I wish I knew about this one in my 20s
This is a solution for 8
Perplexing issue many of us face sometimes in our lives
How to fairly split the rent
Between roommates
Kirsty says imagine that you got an apartment
With two
One of those bedrooms
What is big
But it has no closet
The other is small but it does have that magical closet space
That's right and how you split the rent
I maybe you know I value a small room that has a closet but usually more a big room that because you like space
I'm taking the closet
Yeah I don't need the closet
I wear the same jeans everyday for 2 weeks in a row
So like you know who gets what what's the location but also how is the rent split
So what is the protocol
Cuz he says well
What's in the rent is
2000 bucks
First thing
Everybody needs to figure out what percentage of the rent
The stink
Each room
Me before you
Dudum Seroquel
The word for kidney
Big space is so much more valuable that he says looking I don't care about the clothes that I don't even have clothes okay
So what I can about this case
So at some point
Close
So the protocol that we use my roommate was the classical one
These are the two domains in a sealed envelope
Wright's what they consider to be the right split what would be the right values of the two rooms
She did that
We did.
If he also Affair division guy your roommate
Also a mathematician
Not going to get together and we opened doesn't
And when they open those envelopes
They found out
Hey Kristie says roommate
Thought the person with the big room should pay $1,400
And the person with the smaller room
With the closet
Should pay 600
The coasties
He valued both those rooms equally he was willing to pay $1,000
For either room and in case you haven't been following along with a calculator each roommates
Total bed for both rooms
Have to add up to
$2,000
Provided the big room
Morganite value
Yeah
Were there the highest
Be there
How much do we pay we pay the average tattoo prices
I'm so happy
Que said 1400 I said a thousand so he can get it but he placed 100
Circus copyright space
800 for the small room
And he's happy
Because he
He was willing to pay
Everybody's happy now
Live with mathematicians
Are you are you free tonight because I feel like next time my boyfriend and I decide
Who gets to pick what movie to watch I would like you to be part of it
And this gets to our next
Tear of
Classic Fair division
Problems
What's a year with a friend
It's Friday night
You cannot agree
What you should do
Kenny I know what you're going to say you want to bake a cake
I wish I could bake a cake what I actually would like to do
Is watch The Great British Bake Off have you seen that oh my God yes every
Single-season multiple times
I'm embarrassed to say how many
4 years behind on this
Kind of end
Sorry Kenny I really do really do not want to watch that again
What I would like to watch the
You asked is this awesome new nature series from David Attenborough and the BBC is called dynasties
Work Tennessee's if you're British and it
It's awesome I don't care how it's pronounced I want to watch baking
And here we are turning
Luckily Fair division has a solution for this
Random
Assignment
AKA
Coin flipping no course
We all know about coins
Nothing but
Christy says think about what this is actually
Only doing
You pull out a coin when you're dealing with something that can
Cannot be divided like
What movie to watch or what
What TV show to watch
Yap and flipping a coin gives to people
The same chance of getting
How to choose
Fair
Random assignment
And if you have more than two people
You can use a similar protocol
But it has a way
Way cooler sometimes
This house of the Eyrie name of random dictatorship
Random dictator
Oh I like that
Friends and you want to decide what to do tonight okay
The one way to be fair about the decisions to say I'm going to sleep 5 face you know
Daiso k
Yeah
And you know whoever is elected
Will decide the whole plant
We'll decide what restaurant to go to a movie to go to the party.
He has a name
Sounds bad random dictatorship
But you know automatically
Sounds good if you would
Christie says the random dictatorship
Is more common than you might
I think in fact it is a key part of our judicial system
Take
The jury
The Judy's random
So you have a random guys
Who will make a decision
So that's what I'm going to be
Is randomly take a subset of
Kenousa
Time to make a decision
How would we apply this
To the boat
I guess this was a small different people have different perspectives
What is fat in different situation
After the break we go back to the boats
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
When is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimum
That can be open from anywhere
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Our Fair division expert coasties says
It is not his job to Define
Fair that's a question for the philosopher
Superstore
In the case of the public Harbor
The city of Santa Fe
But he says let's go through some of the sea
Systems the harbor
Could put
Therapist
A lottery
As in
A full reset of the harbor
Cancel everybody's existing permits
Then reallocate those permits
Randomly
Does nothing bad with the lottery is inconvenience going to be inconvenient for people but ultimately
That is super 4310b buddy equally
Okay that makes sense if that is how the city wants to Define fair
Of course there would be
A lot of very angry boat owners who got their permit
Another solution coasties mentioned
Time sharing
When you have limited resources one way you can allow more people to use them is by letting people.
Take turns
But with boats that is
Not so practical
Because where exactly are boogers supposed to be
They're both when it's not there
Turn of course there is the money versions
You use money as a proxy
For who values these
If you want to perm it badly enough
And you can afford it
You can buy one
After the voters who
Can't afford a spotted
The doc
What the system is supposed to benefit them to
You know it depends on your definition of yesterday so like if if I can know if my Citi can extracting a million dollars
From the billionaire okay
And build a school next to the dark okay
You know or you know Builder
Kindergarteners or whatever next to the dogs that people food then go to
To cruise terminal leave their kids play in the kindergarten
The furnace is very complexed
Define Mathematica
Back at the Santa Barbara Harbor Nick Crompton the Harbormaster said
When he started his job
He was already
The investors had already begun sinking money into theirs
Counting on getting it back again
What a prophet
Nick says now yours later at the harbor change that system
They would say
And if the harbor made selling slip permits illegal
It wouldn't fix the problem either it would just
Create a whole other kind of
Because
This whole scene with Wunderground
In other words the underground economy
Has so many tens of millions if not hundreds of millions of dollars invested in it
It's not going away
There's no way it's going away what are you doing away with slip permit transfer
Fees or not
Or slip permit transfers
People will take out life insurance policies on each other those set up phony corporations
And functionally the whole thing will continue the way it does now
Without any oversight
For municipal control
If you open the waiting list today how many names do you think
Quit go on it
Thousand
Micset Nick decided
If this multimillion-dollar
Economy for
Public dock space
Was going to exist
Then the public should find a way to get its fair share
Somic started to make it more and more expensive
To sell your dog
Used to cost 25 bucks
Transfer your spot
Now they can go for as high as $500
So if you own a c
60 foot boat we are talking
Grant
Now this is not a solution that all boat owners rj
For sure it creates a situation where you need money
To get a boat
That is less fair for the Santa Barbara Inns
Who have boats
But not as much money
Arguably though
It is fairer
For all
The transfer fee
Goes into Waterfront apartment coffers if you will into our operating budget
And we use that to maintain the harbor
For the public for the public
To accommodate voting and make sure the facilities are kept up
Right we're walking on a wooden dock
All the planks of which have been replaced over the years you can see it
Is pressure treated you can even you can see where you know
It's a high-quality doctor I are full of splinters and what have you those people shouldn't be walking on
Wooden docks in their bare feet
Mixes this money also helps pay
Fire boats
Law enforcement
The First Responders
The Harbor Patrol gets a lot of medical calls
If someone has a
The heart attack or gets
Sick on the water
Mix at the other thing that they
These massive transfer fees do
Is make it less appealing to invest in a dock slip
Because when you sell your permit this
Giant chunk of money is going to
It cut into your profit
And sure enough when Nick and I still do the harbor the rusty canoes
They were almost all time
There were just a couple of exceptions that looked like they were
Floating placeholders
Protecting and invest
Spots the Santa Barbara.
Sorry to hear that
You said here's an example
What's the scribal we're looking at here that is
It's a mold ridden
Crepid
Loading
Thing that looks not used very much and maybe operable you know
Kayak tied to it it may be used for you know the kite kayaking nothing else
But the boat itself probably isn't worth I'm guessing more than 500 $750
Weekend those investment boats are rare
And mixes this solution seems to be working as best as possible
Most people are actually using the harbor for commercial fishing or recreational boating
And the public Harbor is now getting a
Pretty nice
Cut of a millions of dollars
Sloshing around
Let me ask you if you have a weird question which is
Do you think that this is
And I'm looking up perfect
World in a perfect Harbor
Is this the most
So your solution or is this the solution that had to be adapted given all of the history and the
Like if you were going to start again
And build a harbor from scratch
Would you do things the same way
No mixer
If you could start from scratch he take the money out of it
If I find a different way to define fairness
But this is the system he's stuck with
And that's something to keep in mind if you ever find yourself fairly dividing
Think hard about the system you pick
At the very beginning
The way you define fairness
Because you may be stuck without definition for a very very long time
Is there a fair division problem ruining your life
Definitely want to know about that
You can email us
Planet Money at npr.org
Brighter status Planet Money Alex Goldberg is supervising producer today's episode was produced by Alexi
For Wisconsin and
I note about elaborate
Take a picture of our
Skittles
Gummy bear marshmallow cannoli Fair division cake
We're going to post that on Instagram
We are at
Planet Money
I'm Kenny Malone and I'm Sally herships
Thanks for listening
Oh and you guys have any advice for grown-ups when they're trying
To share things and they're having a hard time figuring out how to do it fairly
Just leave it to us will eat the cake for them
Nice of you