Support for NPR and the following message come from service now making the world of work
Work better for me
They're cloud-based
Platform and solutions
Deliver digital workflow
Spell create great experiences and unlock productivity for your whole company
More at servicenow.com
People make predictions about the future all the time
The right iPad say going TV but get interviewed on podcasts
And a lot of times
These predictions have this kind of
Weaselly unfalsifiable vibe
You know people say
I wouldn't be surprised if we see a recession next
The next hurricane season could be worse than ever
What does that even mean
How do I even know if you're wrong or you're right when you talk that
Even when people do make predictions that will clearly be true or false
You know there's no way unemployment will fall below 5% in our lifetime
Whatever
Everybody forgets about those predictions by the time they're approved
Wrong
It does not have to be this way
There is a better way to live
When somebody makes a prediction
You can ask them a simple question
Want to bet
The thing I liked about bats and then someone's got to be wrong and at the end of the day they have to say they were
Yes and somebody gets to be right and if they end of the day they get to do the right dance
I'm I'm more way more interested in the concession speech that's the one you never get without the bet
So anyway kestenbaum back in January of 2014
Bitcoin was this relatively new thing that everybody who thinks about economics and Technology
What's making wild predict
And so
You know we were interested in the funeral so many question that alone
Don't we were interest
Didn't it but you know we definitely didn't want to have the weaselly
Non falsifiable prediction show
So we were thrilled when we found two really smart really thoughtful
Who are making
Very different predictions about
And who are willing to come on our show and makeup
They decided for 5 years and now today
Around today
Is today Ash it's been 5
The bet is up hello and welcome to Planet Money on Jake Goldstein
You and I co-hosted the original episode about this bed back in 2014
To send you can have to work at this American life but today
For a very special episode of Planet Money
I'm here get your back
Today on the show who won and who lost
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One Capital One
Is reimagining Bank
I offering account
With no fees or
Animals that can be opened from anywhere in
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
This is a better the future of money
Between two people
Red totally opposite
Each guy was completely convinced he was right on one side
Was Ben Horowitz
Who's Venture Capital firm Andreessen Horowitz have bet 50 million dollars
And so I said why don't we just
And you said that in public when then came on the show
5 years ago to make the bet it was a time when you still heard a lot about this sort of like
Political libertarian like we don't need the government for money kind of
Kind of talk around Bitcoin
But then
Practical
I thought you know it was clever as a technology and it just solved this really
Basic problem with e-commerce
And that is
Companies that sell stuff online have to pay a really high fee to accept credit card
Like two or 3% of every sale
Yours been back in 2004
Do you like at overstock.com which just started
Accepting Bitcoins
One of the interesting things about it as their margins are very low there yeah they're operating on like a 5-2
10% margins are two and a half percent
Is a
Choochongkol
The prophets are there Bitcoin
Transactions are significantly more profitable
Don't been thought Bitcoin was about to take off as a way for people to buy stuff online
The guy who bet against Ben was a finance journalist named Felix salmon
Being challenged with that by Ben Horowitz his
Kind of high point of my career
And so IND rates for axios in the host
Slate money podcast
5 years ago when he made the bet
The price of Bitcoin was skyrocketing
The Felix.
The rising price of Bitcoin was actually going to be
No problem because it was going to make it less likely
People would actually use
Bitcoin to buy
Because Bitcoin
Office the potential for so much
Prophet just by sitting on it
And because it's an inherently deflationary currency which means
The longer you don't spend it
The more you benefit
Then everyone has an incentive to not spend that Bitcoins and Yukon
Have an effective payments mechanism
If you know
Spending account
So the question was
Where lots of Americans about to start using Bitcoin device
Back in 2014 we propose to bed
Let's wait 5 years to see what happens
And then take a pole across the country
Find out if people are actually using Bitcoin
I like this I like this
Let's let's take a representative poll
People in
Awesomest question happy use Bitcoin to painting
Fur Goods in the past
Laughing
This good week is a week but that's a month
Because I want to be generous
What number been
What percentage of people are going to say yes
In five years time for that Quest
If 5 to 10% of the people who made payments to use Bitcoin
Like that's a lot of payments
What depends how much
They use it because if you only used it once a month
Temperature saying it's going to disappear
Eventually they settled on a number
If 10% of Americans or more
Said they bought something with Bitcoin in the past month
Ben Woodward
The number was lower
Felix Woodward
Mainstays of course would be
One person's right and one person is wrong
Hate to brag they decided they were going to get some
And they decided on
One of the first things you could buy with Bitcoin of game kind of famous for the
They decide to bet
Pair of alpaca socks
One last thing
Will you guys both agree to come back on our show
Hopefully graciously it and top of it
5 years from now in 2019
Absolutely
Five years pass
We got everybody back together
Hello
Market
How are you
Happy New Year
We're all here didn't pay Felix
Iban
Are you
Do you sound like you're the one I'm sure they'll fit
Step in Time
When they make the bed five years felt like a really long time and then as I was walking over
To the studio to do the interview with you
I was just looking around the world and being like has the world look different from five years ago and the only thing I saw
Woody's motorized skateboard
Basically the same
Yeah and Bitcoin it did not go away like Fela
In fact
The value of Bitcoin actually went you know when
Crazy write it when it was less than $1,000 when we first met.
It went all the way up to almost $20,000 it fell back down
Now it's around like $3,500
Which which three clear is way higher
Then it was when they made the
But the question was did people actually use Bitcoin to buy
I didn't know what the answer
And that is what we did the poll about
As promised we went out and got ipsos a real polling firm
To ask
900 some Americans
Representative sample of Americans
This question
Have you purchased anything
Using Bitcoin as your payment
In the last
The percentage of Americans who said yes
Now they did ask those people the people who said they had they said
At what merchants did you make the perch
And I have some of those answers and it suggests that the 3% is a little
If you go down this list somebody said Gaia ethnobotanical which I looked up
In fact does accept Bitcoin Subway I think some subways
Accept Bitcoin
But there's also a bunch of that say this one says Litecoin a few say coinbase which is a Bitcoin crypto crew
Currency exchange
So these people are are using
Bitcoin to buy other cryptocurrency
Walmart is on there
Your Walmart is on there does not accept Bitcoin
So I think the 3% we can take safely as a ceiling and and
I feel like that the real number is probably what
Well
Subhanallah
I did I did
And I actually would like to start the conversation by giving full credit to Felix and Felix please let me know you
Your sock size
I will I will accept any thoughts in this photo of you know 11 ish
Rain
Big all right all right those are on their way
Thank you very much
So I have been where you wrong
Yes
Can I say I wish I was kind of disappointed by benza
I was wrong cuz he just said I was wrong
Like a really hard time saying
I was wrong I usually say really fast
All right I was wrong but
He just said like I was wrong yes and not only did he come to be in wrong head like this whole analysis of why
It was actually an impressive way to be
And I was wrong in two dimensions
And let me kind of gun to that one with timing
The first way in which she said he was wrong
The classic
I just didn't have enough time
Log a longer-term that I would have eventually I am right
But the second mistake is is a little bit more complicated also it's much more interest
And this is
Ben thought Bitcoin would work like other
Big open source technology
What you see with those kind of
Project princess
Developers you know coders they just start solving one problem after another
So the projects just get better and better
That's the way the internet itself
Developed yesterday with no security but Lena like
We got security
Started out with no naming but we got that
There was no way to distribute addresses we got that feel like it just kept
Evolving a lawn
Because
It just met the needs
Of the user Community that's what Ben thought would happen with Bitcoin
He thought the code that powers Bitcoin would just get better and better and
Very quickly it would obviously be this safer faster and more private cheaper way for people to buy stuff on
That did not
No Bitcoin just became so valuable
That the people who worked on the system
Didn't want to make it any
Better they just wanted to lock everything down and keep it the way it was
I think that
What happened
With Bitcoin is that
There is kind of one very very
Strong need
Among the kind of investor / minors which is
That
The code in the meaning of
The code would not change
So basically
Felix was right the thing that he thought was going to happen happen
The fact of Bitcoins became so valuable method people
Didn't really want to use in the bicep they'd rather just hang on to them
But even be like this surprised by the way things actually turned out
I honestly I was looking back about I mean there were two things which
I
Expected
Would happen
What if I expected the
Price would probably
And it didn't
Way up into the
Right
And the other is that I expected that would actually be used
Over there
The following five
PS the even if
People when using it to buy stuff in
Stores and that was my
Excited
I imagined
Use permittance azure
Somewhere along the line it would have evolved if it especially if it
Grown to be worth thousands of dollars per Bitcoin
Then it would be used for
More valuable and less useful than you
Then if they didn't seem that like upset about losing her back
I have a theory about
Yes right so in the real world his firm invested tons of money in Bitcoin
And they seem to have done great
On those in
I think I've made a tremendous amount of money
Are we don't know exactly how they've done but one thing we do know is they were an early investor in this company coinbase which we mention
Recently coinbase was valued at 8 billion dollar
You were
Wrong about the bet
Alpaca socks
But right about the BET of
50 million.
Yes yes I'm ahead
Ben still investing in companies that work with crypto
Do you think
X number of years
You know whatever 5 years
From now
Lots of people will use some cryptocurrency to buy stuff on a regular basis
Oh yeah I definitely
I feel like this is like taking candy from a baby
I think I'll be a bear I think yes
Yes I think there will be a bearer instrument
On the internet
Okay repeat the exact same bat
For another five
Titan Bitcoins
Then today is less convinced that he used to be
That Bitcoin in particular will be there cryptocurrency that people actually used
So this time for this bad
He wanted to make it about
Cryptocurrency more General
Play with that and then there was one other change you wanted to make
And that was he wanted to move it outside of the US
Because he said
Yes Credit Card fees are high in the US but let's be honest
Credit cards work really well here
So there's not that much of an incentive for people to switch to some
They want anyone to do in some country
Credit card we're not so wide
And wear if there are some nuke Simple app on your phone you left
Apply for credit card UK
Pay instantly and easily
You know I might really take off
He said
What do the BET for Mexico
I'm perfectly happy to change
Planet Money
It's very rare that you went to bed and then you get to go swimming again
Ben what are the states
Texas timer
But whatever you like we'll do something serious will do it will do it for a hundred-year-old bottle of Madeira
Henry Cavill bottom freezer actually maintained its value
For over a century
Is
Find Portuguese fortified wine called Madera
And it gets better with age
And if you buy it you can drink it and nuts
And you're very happy person cuz it
It's delicious in if you don't drink it
You can keep it in your salad and it retains its value and
Let's go to a much better store of value
Van
Any cryptocurrency will ever be
So I will bet you
A hundred 100 year old bottle of Madeira
Do you
I will not be able to find 10%
Mexicans
Cryptocurrency
In 5 years time
Okay perfect
Custom you really wanted them also to include some kind of cryptocurrency in the back because that's what we know cryptic
Currencies are good for bedding
Eid
Bottle of wine in like some invisible
Like I did I did
So they did add a cryptocurrency they decided in addition to the bottle of Madeira
Tibet something called an ether which is one of the big cryptocurrencies that's popped up in the last year
Yeah what one bottle of Madeira and one
Just got more colorful
Okay
Right now just for the record
A bottle of hundred-year-old Madeira
Cost between 500 and $1,000
And an ether cost around $100
I may change by the time
Madeira Promenade
And pills could really win because
Is possible that no cryptocurrency is used in Mexico to buy
But still people are betting like crazy with ethernet switch
How you get the best of
Or you can lose
Can I see that's what kind of frustrating about this bed for me
It's very gentlemanly I want somebody to like to admit
Total and utter complete
Failure
You know
Yes well it's tough when the guy who lost the bet to millions of dollars
In fact in fact last year
Ben's fermentery Subaru actually bet much more fun crypto that they have a birthday lunch this new
300 million dollar fund to invest in crypto related company
So obviously
A slightly bigger bed than a bottle of Madeira and an ether and we will be
Tracking method
I think a few more Generations it's that it's going to be hard for them to make
2029 no way
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Is reimagining Bank
I offering account
With no fees or minimum
Thermostat can be open from anywhere in
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Na
I would love to do some more bet
Paste shows
If you have heard people making wild predictions about the future and you think we should have them on and make them commit to Abba
Please tell us
You can email us a planet money at npr.org or you can find us on Twitter or Facebook or Instagram at Planet Money
Today show with Reese by Sally Helm Alex goldmark is are supervising producer Brian first at
SM Pampanga coming back now no problem
Don't think so
Hello
Felix
Are you ready to open the package
I'm ready to open I have scissors in my hand
Okay open the package
All right
It fit
Okay
Here we go by Felix enjoy yourself
I got you an extra pair and Kacy where a hole-in-one during the victory.
Oh wow
Okay
Felix
Would you put the socks on your
Okay
Okay so they don't need to feel very soft
I have to say
The Cozy and they