This message comes from
NPR sponsor energy upgrade California
Statewide program
Encouraging Californians to use less energy whatever pops
Because it all adds up
Keep it golden
And learn more at energy upgrade California.
Professor Schierholtz can you hear me
And I'm going to just warn you I'm like on the
Very very Talent
I
I'm on the end of a cold
50 people with cold
Talking
Heidi Schierholtz was Chief Economist at the Department of Labor for a good chunk of the Obama in
She's with the think-tank now called
The economic policy
Is partially fronek policy
Is partially funded by labor
I wanted to talk to her about something that is happening in the job market
Right now
Has hit
3.6
Percent
Which means that
Of all the people who want to work
And are able to work in the United States
Just 3.6%
Do not have
That is the lowest unemployment rate
In almost 50
How do you says
Cause unemployment is so low
Workers are starting to find themselves
With this
Almost like
Superpower
The
Quit threat is good
Is that a real term
This is the kind of thing economist
Wood name
Yes it is
Oh yeah and I'm not
Sure what the hell
Actual
Name is
8 Cuda look it up and I'll get back to you
I did check and her colleagues agree this should be called the quit threat though there is not currently seem to be
But the general idea is
If I go to my boss
And I say
I might
Quit
That threat
Becomes more and more realistic
The lower unemployment
The chi
Logic of this
This is exactly what anyone on this
If your employer knows that you have
Decent outside.
They have to pay
Better wages to
Their workers at the pay better wages to get the workers that they need
And we know you know
The difference
9% unemployment rate in an 8% unemployment rate
Means a lot less
Two workers
As far as the economic leverage goes
The difference between a 4% unemployment rate under 3% unemployment rate so there is definitely some nonlinear
Moving towards
Full employment means for
Non-linearity etc etc this is
A beautiful mathaway
I'm saying
For the first time in decades
Kind of suddenly
Workers
Have
Power
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Kenny Malone
Today on the show what does Full Employment or near full employment
Actually look like in the real world
Our colleagues at NPR's businessdesk have spent the last few months all over the country reporting a series of stories
Json full employ
And today we are going to hear about three of those story
How bratwurst
Cheese and the quick bread or helping unions in Wisconsin
How some workers are still being left behind
And what happens when a city's unemployment rate
Hip 1.5%
As it has
Ames Iowa which is funnily enough my hometown wait get out of here
Nope yep I'm in Ames
This message comes from NPR sponsor Microsoft
Today artificial intelligence is helping us grow more food
While using fewer resources
It helps Architects bring our lost history back to life
It even helps us search for our next
Favorite beer
Across the globe
Innovators are using artificial intelligence
Ways to reinvent the way we work today
See how AI
Why is empowering business innovators at microsoft.com AI
Mitch McConnell
Become a champion for conservatives
But back in the day
He wants got support from groups like labor union
Mark it down as one of the worst things I've done my life
So you thought about over the years I still think about if I see a face
Mitch McConnell
New series from embedded
Subscribe now
All right before we get to the stories about what's happening in the United
States right now there is one sort of wonky but
Really interesting thing I talked about with Heidi she
And that is
What do economist
When they talk about full employment
It's pretty straightforward so
Full employment
Is the lowest level of unemployment you can get
Without sparking accelerating inflation
And that link between unemployment and inflation might not be totally clear to everyone to let me just
Yeah verify
If the unemployment rate is so low
That
For employers to be able to get and keep the workers that they need
They have to raise wages
Higher than they can reasonably absorb
So that they then have to raise
Prices higher and higher and higher
In order to cover those costs that's it
That's how low unemployment
Can lead to accelerating inflation
So we are currently at
3.6%
Unemployment
Is that full employment
Well this is the opened
Heidi Schierholtz for example says
What you know
Wages are starting to go up but
Inflation is not out of control so
She thinks there's still room to get unemployment down
Even further and
Wages up more safe
Some people think we are already at
This is kind of beside the point
Because what isn't controversial is that we are either at full employment or very
That puts us in a moment where power
Is shifting
From employers
Two workers
And here to tell us one story about that shift is
NPR's economics correspondent Scott Horsley Scott things
Scott I like to think of you yes and economics correspondent but
You are the person I think looks most like Anderson Cooper at the NPR
Oh I disagree
I
The story Scott
Is going to Palace actually starts a while ago
Back when unemployment was still really high
Scott went to Sheboygan Wisconsin
To visit the
The colder fat
They make a lot of
High-end kitchen fixtures bathroom fixtures are they there a big company that they also make things like lawn mower
They workers at color are represented by the United Auto Workers Union and there's a union hall
Where I met up with
The woman who is the
The star of our show Courtney Herring Heering I actually
All the finished products and faucets
In. Any unfinished brass
And I move them around to differ
And when she started out she was making she told me
Between 11 and 12 bucks an hour which
She thought was not a terrible picture gallery for that for that time
But as time went by
She found out that they were people
When doing very similar jobs to hers
We're making about twice that much you really did open my eyes
To see what was really happening and how much of an opportunity I was actually missing compared to what I actually thought I was gay
But once you knew was it a little bit
It was an eye-opener it was a huge eye-opener
It made me realize
Oh man this is a huge gap
So what is going on
Why is there that she
Yu-Gi-Oh opening
So couple years before Courtney started working
Color in the midst of the Great Recession
Kohler like a lot of
Employers
Had adopted what's known as a
Two tiered wage structure
A two-tiered wage
In an effort to save money
The company rather than cutting everyone's pay says okay we're going to leave your pay existing workers where it is
But anybody who's hired
From this day forward
Is going to get paid a lot less and maybe have worse benefits as well
Twitter something that we talk across the economy
When unemployment was higher when employers had more
More power
It wasn't Universal but it was it was common among some big industrial companies some of the
Most famous were the big three automakers
Crew sweater two-tiered weight scale during the recession Kohler did caterpillar did
Lots of
Unionized industrial companies adopted this so-called
Two tiered wage structure
Union membership in general
Has been on the decline
For decades
It's but
Even for the existing union members
Great Recession
And the resulting 10% unemployment
Gave employers Leverage
Over workers
Yeah I mean I talked to union members who were at Kohler in 2010 when the
Two-tier wage contract was adopted
They didn't like it at the time but they didn't feel like they had any power to
Negotiate
An alternative
Are they were afraid to go on strike unemployment with sky-high companies
We're closing their doors all around
People are getting laid off left and right and
They didn't let the workers who were there at the time didn't feel like this was
An opportunity for them to drive a hard bargain
Back in 2010 there was a lot of what Economist call Slack
In the labor
Market slack basically just means
It's easy for employers to go find someone else to
Dell course unemployment has been dropping for years now
And Scott says everyone's been looking
4 signs
Status Slack
Has gone away
Anything about slack is
If there's a little slack or a lot of Slack
It's kind of the same result I mean if you think about your your dog walking along on the leash
If if there's a foot of lease dragging on the ground or 3in of these dragon on the ground as long as there's a little bit of Slack
It it feels the same to you and the dog
Right
It kind of happens all at once
Like when your dog suddenly pulls tight on the leash
This is what it means that slack is nonla
When unemployment drops from say 9
To 8%
It's not like workers
Really have that much
More power like okay you want to raise there still 9000 job and you're
Probably still not going to go fine
Find a job
But a drop from
4% 2
3% now that
Is a tightening labour
Market approaching full in
Workers have
Actual
Quit threat power and that's what that supposition the Kohler found themselves in
Last year they had a lot of job openings they couldn't feel
They had existing workers who were defecting to
Neighboring factories like Sargento Cheese and the
Johnsonville Brats company
Yeah right nearby
It's A Feast for the senses
Can-Am I couldn't but
Those those companies we're hiring workers away and suddenly Kohler was in a less competitive
Position
It when it came to attracting and keeping good workers
The slack had suddenly evaporated and when the slack was gone the workers wouldn't wear a much stronger position to negotiate
The new contract
In mm
Teen the union got Kohler to
Close app
Pretty significant portion of that
Tier Gap
And then as the labor market tightened and tightened
Further
They were able to renegotiate again
In 2008
18 before the old contract was even up
And fully closed
The two-tier structure
And as a result you've now seen
The newer worker
Grayslake Courtney Herring get a nice
Bump in their pee
Courtney said it really made a difference in how she and her fellow workers felt about
What the work they were doing
I mean I was told don't go in a factory don't go on a factory you're not going to have a life there
It feels like I do and I'm getting somewhere
So I could see myself being here for my career
My family's been in it for
At least 40 plus years so
I like the kind of continue that tradition
That said Kenny
We have to acknowledge there are some counterexample
Pause I mean even in this tight labor market for example UPS just negotiated a new contract
That puts new drivers on a lower pay scale than older drivers
There is a locomotive plant in
Pennsylvania where the new owner is trying to impose
A two-tier wage scale on employees there
I that case
Still in mediation
So it's it's
Not a uniform picture across the country with Eric certainly caveats to it
But the broad outline is worker certainly have more bargaining power
To demand better pay and better benefit
What's today
Then they did
At the height of the recession
All right
Scott Horsley thank you very much
Alright and Anderson Cooper may have
Complained rink bring he can send them to me
Full employment or quasi folder
He's making things better for workers
We're just going to take a moment
To talk with my colleague Jasmine gar
About some of the problems
We still see
Jasmine thank you for be
Here to rain on your parade
The reality of the
We wanted to talk to Jasmine because for NPR's
Full employment series she had been looking into unemployment within the Hispanic
Hispanic
Is the term the Bureau of Labor
Did employment rate for Hispanics is 4 point
That's fairly close to the national average that seems
Distance good
It's at a historic low
Okay it is
Always good for there to be more
Jobs
But there's layers
So you have to peel off
And look a little deeper at
And Jasmine says what that picture shows is that wages
For Hispanic and Latino workers
Are still relatively
Weekly median earnings are about 75
Percent what they are
R4 white work
Annotating labor market hasn't
Medigap worse it hasn't
Made it better it just
Was and still is
Oh yeah I mean like look Hispanic Libra
It still comes in
Rated in low-wage
A lot of that has to do with it
Educational attainment
It there still
Alive even though it's been growing next
Financial aid
They're still alive
Done for immigrant communities a lot of it
What is language
Depending on
Status of immigration status you know if you
I have an irregular undocumented
Status in this country
It is going to be harder for you to go to Europe
Employer and say
I want a raise
And Jasmine says there's a similar point to be made when you look at
African American
It is
Very low by historical stand
But
It is still very high 6.7%
More than double the white
Again
The tightening labor market hasn't made that got worse but
It hasn't really made it
Better either
It just still is
Yeah my point with these two numbers is
. there good it's always good to have left
Unemployment
Are 4.2% for Hispanics
6.7% for African Americans
That's great in a hiss
Historical context
But it's also indicative of others
Systemic problem
The tighter labor market
Doesn't
Change
Discrimination it doesn't solve races
Jazmine Garcia
Thank you so much
Thank you
After the break
The city
With the lowest unemployment rate
In America
Support for this NPR pipe
And the following message come from ergotron
With a mission to design and build active working
Ergotron introduced
The sit stand desk
Over 10 years
It's full line of standing desks gives you and your team
Everything they know
Need for a comfortable and healthy office
Ergotron
A trusted partner
Fortune 100 company
To save 10% or more
Visit ergotron.com NPR
After James Reeb was murdered in 1965
There was a national outcry
The back of the scene of the crime in Selma Alabama
People responded different
What happened
And what did Justice look like all these years later
NPR's new podcast White Lies seeking answers
Listen And subscribe now
All right the US unemployment rate is
Is 3 point
6%
Extraordinarily low
But there is a city where the unemployment rate
Is 1 Point
5 /
What does that
Even
Look like
The answer that question here with me now is my colleague
Rollie who
Is a correspondent on the business desk and also
I had the unfortunate pleasure sitting next
To the Planet Money
Team we are very loud
This is my
Formal on Mike apology
This is New York so where you stay
Jimmy went and visited the city
The lowest unemployment rate
31.5
What city is
Well I went to the city of Ames
Iowa catches about 40 minutes north of Des Moines
Yes right right it's a small City maybe 60000 people
Why didn't new buildings there there's an older
Downtown Wichita
Very pretty very quaint
So Jim driving into Ames
Is it
Can you see
That there is 1.5% unemployment like are there signs that something is
Is different here
Well yeah you see signs all over the place saying Help Wanted
Three little girls absolutely yes yes I've been restaurants bowling alleys and bars
Everybody's looking for workers
Windows
So why Ames Iowa Welch Jim says
Cities with research universities like
Iowa State
Tended to recover better from the Great Recession
Ames is adding job
Good high paying jobs
Tech Healthcare in other growing fields
That's part of why
The other part
Is the Eames needs to attract people to fill those job
It is not San Francisco.
It is not
New York
Iowa has a relatively stagnant population
It is not attractive
People at the rate it needs
To feel those jaw
So that's it
Combination that's that causes
It means you have a I have a worker shortage and so sure this is affecting the higher-paying field
James is also seeing this
With in service industry like a rest
Oh yeah when you have I'll let you know when you have a lot of
Well paid
Jobs
That are filled by
Educated people
Who make good salaries
You know that tends to filter down through the economy as a whole it's worth stepping back here
2 Note
Did those workers in lower wage jobs
Are benefiting the most
When the labor market
Gets real
Because
If you're in some highly specialized
Rocket science
You already have a lot of
If you quit
Your employer is going to have a harder time finding
Another rocket
But
If your job is
Is bussing tables for example
Your boss can go and find a new employee
Train them up pretty quickly
And replace you
But it 1.5% unemployment
There isn't really a new person to go find and train up and so
Waiters and table bussers in this world
Have a lot more leverage
And Jim says
You can see this play out better than anywhere else
In Ames Iowa
In those
Help Wanted signs all over
So I said it was driving down the highway and I saw a lot of these signs and I stopped
At 1 restaurant
Which actually turns out to be sort of a venerable institution in the aims
Hickory
Hickory Park Restaurant company and we're off
Full-service Family Restaurant we serve a smoked food we also went in and I met with
One of the managers
Elizabeth kopetsky
They had a sign out
Front that said
Help wanted all chefs that sign we have never hung sign out in front of our building ever
Until the last 2 years
But that sign says help wanted all positions and in your saying that's been there for a little while
USB just kitchen
But now it's like all position
Everybody's in the same boat
Liam last your head
A call from a restaurant down the street
Asking if we had an extra staff that they could share that's how bad it's getting what did you tell them
We didn't have enough for ourselves
That's what I told them I was in another restaurant with another work
Worker and she was a manager but she was having to fill in at the dishwasher
Filling with the Castro
I wait tables drawing of somebody bouncing 18 different cups on like one finger
Brandon on the other hand I've got platters in a cash register
This is what
1.5% unemployment look
Yeah I mean if you are looking for work
In
A place like games
Especially if you have a good
Resume
IUD basic
We have your pic
Job
I mean I want went into one restaurant and I'm and I met a woman named Tanisha
Cortez you sort of an assistant manager there for a few days
I'm a manager at the other store so
She
Had lost her job
Last November
Because the restaurant where she worked
Add closed
And so she went she decided to know I'll look for another job that I put in applications for actually a few places in
Everyplace got back to her and offered her a job
Every place
So that's why I gave you
This must be what it's like
When you're LeBron James in your free agent
It's just every basketball team calls you and it is a nice position to be in
Especially after the past
10 years or so on what the workforce was like just remember in 2010 how terrible
Well
Those days are gone
Thanks for telling us about Ames
You're welcome
We could use your help with an upcoming episode our colleagues on the podcast rough translation or working on a story about
Confidence games and they would love to hear from you you can send them your story about getting conned
By emailing
Rough translation at NPR. Org just make sure you use the subject line con Co
Ons and it may end up in that
Episode
Today's episode was produced by Liza Yeager Darian woods and Rachel Cohn Alex gold Marquise Planet Money
Supervising producer Bryant urstadt edits
The show NPR business editor is pallavi gogoi and a very special thanks to her and
14 for pulling together disc fantastic full employment series you can hear more of that at NPR.
Archie if you'd like to support Planet Money the best way is to rate or review the podcast or even just share your
Favorite episode with a friend that would be wonderful
I'm Kenny Malone this is NPR
Thanks for listening