Support for this podcast and the following message
Should come from Amazon pay helping businesses deliver a fast familiar shopping experience for Amazon cast
By minimizing steps at checkout
Shoppers are more likely
Play to complete the park
Learn more at pay. Amazon.com NPR
One of the greatest American Economist who ever lived was Irving Fisher
He was a true visionary
How to turn a really big important insights into really big important things
Monetary policy behavioral economics
And yet
Today
Almost nobody remembers any of that
If people today remember anything at all about Irving
What they remember is this one thing he said in the fall of night
He said
Stock market hit quote
A permanently High plateau
Few weeks later
The market
Crashed
Irving Fisher state with sealed
He would forever be the
Permanently High
But now imagine a different scenario
Suppose some big famous economist said
I am freaking out something very bad is about to happen in the economy and soon
And then the economy
Kept growing
4 years
Just expanding and
Expanding adding jobs
The markets resuming happily ever upward
Would that person have been mocked forever as the you know
Eminem precipitous crash person
No no
No everybody would have just been like hey
Thank you for warning us about that
Things that didn't happen
And then if a bad thing had happened
The person would have been hailed as the genius who warned us about the bad thing
Okay so now it is June of the year
Here we are
Which means this month the economic recovery in the US turns 10 years old
Unemployment is at the very lowest in decades
Wages are finally climbing for most workers
And the incentives
For us
In This Moment
Could not be more
It is time for us to bravely.
Eclair
There are things we should be worried about
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm taking Golden Child
Mary you read about Finance
Forbearance that's true I write about worried people worrying about things for more worried people
What should we be worried about
It's not rhetorical we rounded up three legitimately very troubling answers
Actually we've rounded up a lot more than that but we narrowed it down to three so that you could ever sleep again
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence
And run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial and when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
I'm Karen Duffin this is rough translation from NPR and our next episode we continue the story of a hoss
Stitch rescue operation created this impromptu Rescue Team the team finds Newcleus you know exactly who
Louis
They sit down with Isis and they try to figure out who they can trust
We're almost at war with each other
Listen And subscribe this time on rough translation
Okay just a couple little bits of housekeeping before we
Get into the shower
Number one
There are lots of things we should be worried about that we are not going to talk about it
Nuclear war
Underrated I think underrated as a warrior
Probably
Climate change
Mass extinction related to climate change
Very big worries
Spit on Today Show we're going to focus more on that sort of short to medium-term ordinarily sort of
Financial
Thing number 2
Planet money has done a version of the show already what should we be worried about
4 years ago
So for a first call we wanted to follow up with someone
That show who was worried about the stock market
Hi this is Jacob Goldstein NPR New York
And this is Bob Shiller Robert Shiller won a Nobel prize in economics for telling us what to be worried about
He looked at the housing market in mm
At the Bible
Same thing with the stock market in the late 1990s
4 years ago we had Yuan
On our show on Planet Money
You brought up the cape ratio
The cape ratio is this thing Schiller came up with
It's a way of measuring stock price
If you know price-to-earnings ratio is a version of that
But basically when it's high it mean stocks are more expensive when it's low stocks Archie
And here I can actually just play a little moment from that here's what you said in 2000
Is high
The only times it's been higher
We're 1929
And
Mm
In 2007 was about tied
Spell trash can
Is that the only times it's been this High has been right before
Market crash
So I'm worried about that
So that was
2015 what happened after that
Stock market keep going up
Okay so I didn't say that it was going to crash eminently
What what do we what did you make of it were you too pessimistic
Pick 4 years ago
Oh I think I didn't see that stock prices would go up as much as they have
Today that number that he watches the
The cape ratio is even higher than it was four years ago
Chiller still thinks that the stock market will probably fall
Because that's what always have
This is more or less the same thing you said when we talked to in 2050
Survival
Probably fall
When
But this time when I talk to him
He got into this hole bigger picture way of thinking about the economy and and landed on this
Whole other for nothing to worry about
He says when he thinks about the future of the economy
When this fall will happen whether it be sudden or gradual what effect it might have
He doesn't think about like what the FED is going to do or like
Commodity prices or any other techniques
Google measure
He thinks about how people feel
About the economy
Right now
The stock market is perceived as high
I know that I've been surveying people
And also the housing market is perceived to be high
It's not gotten people worried yet
But if you talking about worst-case scenarios
They could suddenly get worried
Who is this I'm talking about everyone in America
And then so what happens if everyone in America gets worried
Well then they would become less
Excited about investing in the stock market
And about
And also in the housing market
Prices start
The fall
Those falling prices
Freak people out
They were
So they cut back their spending
They start saving more
Which means sales and profits for companies start falling
So then company start laying people off unemployment goes up the economy starts drinking
So you feel like we're all just sort of floating on this kind of
Cloud of
Optimism and the
Fear for you is not some technical change in the world but
Just some kind of
Femoral change in people's emotions
It suddenly will go from being
Hopeful to being scared and that that is
Itself will cause
Real economic
Yes
I hate you got it
That has happened before that is a very meta word
Well it's
I think that's
Yeah
But we have to worry about really worried number one is not about the stock market
It's worried about worry
Thank you for your time
My pleasure to call you again in 4 years
Take your head don't tell me I was wrong
So at Barons I write about corporate debt
Which means I spend all my time talking to this little group of people that lend money
And little island it's all the same people go to the same
Princess and right now everybody on that island is
I have to say when you started telling me about
Life on this island I actually got worried like
Like I really did you know I mean I haven't thought much about corporate debt
Before but
As we were reporting the story it became clear to me that in the you know
Relatively near few
Corporate debt could be a big deal not just for this little Universe of lenders and Borrowers
But for like millions of ordinary people who just
Go to work everyday and don't think anything else
Those people
Could be affected in a really big Way by what's going
One of my very favorite people to talk about this
This is Ann Walsh
I'm in Walsh on the chief investment officer for fixed-income for Guggenheim partners
Guggenheim Partners runs mutual funds manages money for big investors
Animals his job is basically lending investors money
To become
How much how much more less how much money do you manage
180 billion dollars from 80 billion dollars
It's a lot of money
I normally when you have a 180 billion dollars to lend
You get to make
The rules
Leonard Lake and make actual rules
People call them covenants and their huge deal on the
You can make a rule saying
Hey company we will lend you this money as long as you don't go out and borrow a bunch
More money
Were there rules that say
You can't sell your important
Stop
Or saying that if something bad happens you have to call me immediately and we will have a very strongly worded conversation about it
So this this Covenant these rules they used to be
Totally normal in the
But now that has changed
Those rules have largely gone away
So if you
If you went to a bar or now somebody wants to borrow money and they're a little bit of a you know
Do they have a little bit of a
Whiskey company
And you said to them I will lend you money
If you promise not to go out and borrow money
What would they say
They say we're going to go find somebody else to lend us this money
It's easy it's heard there's so much out there
What's happening today is that companies are able to borrow money with
With none of those protection
Built-in because more and more people and incest
Institutions
I got more and more money that they needed
Did you invest to let out
Pension funds and
Rich people Saudi Arabia they're all competing to lend enormous sums of money
So now
Borrowers
Have the power
So you
Have a hundred 80 billion dollars to lend
And yet you don't have
For the power in this relationship
That would be correct
That's extraordinary
I think about that corporate debt in America is now at the
Highest level ever and with the loosest terms
First of all time
So right now
Lenders are being the cool Mom they're letting companies run around willy-nilly spending all the money running up the credit card
With no curfew
So in the weird little corporate that world where I live this is what everyone
Worried about so what answer this is there is a Next Step
Pierre and that next step is why
Everybody else all the other people who don't live in your little corporate debt world
Everybody else should also be worried
All those companies borrowing all that money they do normal things like run retail shops
We're Ordinary People go to work everyday
So at some point
Some of those companies
Won't be able to pee
Their debts
Do you have companies that start to default
They can't refinance they can't operate their businesses they have to lay off employees than those employees
Have to go find another job
Right now that's not such a
A big deal right now it's okay to find a job
But if the economy slows if there's a recession
All that corporate borrowing with almost no rules
Could mean lots and lots of
I won't be able
And I'll have to leave
And that is a terrible time
To get laid off
In a recession
All of a sudden those excess Jobs go away and it becomes a lot harder to become re-employed
I mean that that is its own spiral then right because then there's more people without jobs in their spending less that's bad for
Companies
And that's the classic downward spiral
Exactly
So this is wearing number 2
Big lenders stop Lending
Companies that might have survived
If they hadn't borrowed so much and on such a
Easy terms just
After the break
One more thing to worry
Support for this podcast
In the following message come from TD Ameritrade
Offering
Free education for invest
Choose from articles videos webcast
And in-person events to take your trading knowledge to the next level
Visit tdameritrade.com education
Member sipc
When you're paying for college on your own there's a lot to Bala
Help you get through it all and scared life get talk to the real X
Student
Finding a side hustle that works for you and works for your schedule is
Usually beneficial
Find life gets new guide on how to pay for college in apple podcast
Or npr.org life
Last and final worry
Trade
For this chapter we caught up Chad Bown an economist at the Peterson
Who basically Specializes
Entry doors
What I actually focus on is the areas of
Friction
And trade is right where things
Kind of begin to
Fall Apart
So this is your moment
This is the Superbowl this is yeah that's my moment is my Superbowl this is what I have
Forbetterforworse been preparing my entire life
Like 4 so President Trump has imposed tariffs on about
200 billion dollars of
Chinese good
Has threatened additional tariffs on another
300 billion or
And what that means is American company
Import those goods
Have to pay tax
Of 25
And Chad is worried that the terrorists are going to hurt the economy
And anyways
I'm frankly that I find pretty interest
What he told us is
A lot of the taxes so far the ones that have already been put in
Ouran what Economist call intermediate Goods
Basically just
Stuff companies use
How to make others
So you think about Ford or GM for example
They make cars in Michigan
But a lot of the stuff they use to make those cars
So if you go down the Tariff list which I happen
But to have right here
You can see lots and lots of
Car and truck related things
Like electrical lighting equipment of a Kind used for Motor Vehicles or Cycles other than bites
Brakes and Servo brakes
And parts thereof
Fuel lubricating or cooling medium pumps for internal combustion piston engines
Not fitted with a measuring device could pump seems like the keyword there of a Kind used for persons in motive
Call Stacy
Sure
So there's actually more than a hundred
Car related
Things on this
Amazing list that has all kinds of
What that means is now Ford and GM
And every other company that makes cars in the US
Has to pay
A 25% tax to buy those parts
Or they could stop buying those parts
If they did that
They would probably have to pay more
Male part of President Trump's
Goal in all of this
Seems to be to want to
Bring American production
American manufacture
Back to the United
Some of these tariffs
May be successful in doing that
He may Force companies
Is that if you want to sell to American consumers you have to make it
Here
But the implications of that are
The prices to American consumers are going to be a lot higher and these American companies that are making here they're not going to be able to produce Pro
Products that are going to be
Commercially viable anywhere else in the world
You can sell them to American consumers
But 95% of the world's consumers don't live in America
Asia or Europe or elsewhere and they're just not be willing to pay these much higher price
So that's where we are now
It's harder for us companies to compete around the world
Okay but I still feel like I could be like
A little bit more worried
Shut down
So a really bad scenario
Would be President Trump
Following through
An imposing all of his tariffs on China
Andino
The full 500 in
Something billion dollars worth of imported
25%
Then President Trump getting upset that progress isn't happening with Mexico with the Border
And he decides to impose
Tariffs on imports from Mexico
Play further gets upset with Japan and Europe that don't do something that he wants perhaps on a NATO or cooperation somewhere else
Nelson imposes tariffs on
Cars coming in from those
Now all of a sudden if you're going out and buying a car car prices are going to be higher
For you
If you're going back to school shopping with your with your kids and trying to buy clothes or supplies
Prices are going to be higher for you
If you're an American company if you want to sell your product
In Europe or in Asia
You're not going to be able to compete anymore because your costs are so much higher
It took this attic really is the is the big concern
The effects on the US economy could be coming from a lot of different angles
I feel like after the last one the last time Planet money did it similar show
Like everything was fine but I feel Almost sure that not everything is fine
Now
I'm worried
Mission accomplished email at at Planet Money
Leatt npr.org or you can find us on social at at Planet Money
Special things today to the Center for Automotive Research
Robert Shiller has thought for a long time about why emotions are important to economic outcomes
For more of him on that
I'll check out a recent episode of our sister showed that indicator
I just last week they talk to Sheila about that the headline on that show is animal spirits and the name of the show is v in
Today Show was produced by Darren woods Alex goldmark is are supervising producer and Bryan tour stats
The show
If you like the show
And want to help us out please leave us a review online and actually help
Other listeners find Planet Money
You don't like us
You don't need to bother it's fine
I'm Jacob Goldstein
And I marry child
This is NPR thank you for listening
I get to
Bee clipart now
Everyone people will finally be listening to me
Isn't
I agree thank you