Support for NPR in the following message come from Pushkin and Des
Presenting the podcast against the rules
Michael Lewis explores the corrosion of fairness in America
And what it has done to our society mostly
Without our noticing
Listen to against the rules wherever you get your pot
Do you remember what the subject line was on
The email that you double clicked on
Exactly verbatim
But it had to do with
A document
For our record
This is Mavis Jesus
Supervisor at
Hair Company
And we're only using her first name in this story for read
Become very clear in a minute
And that email she got
That was from someone she actually knew
But it seems a little
Off
And I replied to the email and I said
Are you sure this was meant for me
And
Came back and said oh yes it's for you
And that's when I clicked on there
Email wow
What did it look like
It really
Had nothing to do with
The type of documents
That I deal with
So right away it was like oh
This is
You know I'd
And never really thought anything of it
Then a few days later Mavis was in her scent box
Looking for another email
And that
That's when she saw
Her computer all on its own
Sending out
Email
And you're just saying
Sin sin sin sin sin sin sin sin sin sin sin sin sin
And then right there was like
Crap
And not just because she realized she'd made a mistake
But because she knows breaking into her particular account
Is incredibly serious
She's not only a supervisor
She's a supervisor
Financial Services
I thought for sure I was going to get fired
Yeah no hands down Mavis new her account was a
A hacker's
A motherload of
Social Security numbers banking information
Retirement accounts
With bank statements and wiring instructions help
Polly attached and she was just thinking
Life made such a dumb mistake
And then you think of
The time in the money
They can't end up having to spend
It feels awful to be the person who did something like that
But all kinds of companies are going through this right now
Marriott Chinese hackers Target they are hacking into cash registers the Democratic National Committee
That one was also fishing there were so many hats so often
This point
It may feel like
There's no way to stop it
But there is a ray of Hope
It's a little old-fashioned and very low talk about as low-tech as you can get it's been around for hundreds of years
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Dina temple-raston and I'm here indefinite Dina is here with us
Today reporting the story but she is covered terrorism and technology for NPR and while we've all been searching for some fancy
High tech solution to all these hacks
Age old remedy has been sitting in the corner biting its time
Waiting for us to notice
Can a Dusty old Financial tools called one of the most modern problems in the world today on the show
We introduce you to a cyber SWAT team and tomatoes
And some friends in Nigeria
Urgently require your attention
Support also comes from Delta
Delta flies to 300 cities around the world that's 300 cities
It's where many people do the same things you do
That's 300 cities were people in those 300 cities think they're the only ones who know about that
That one place
And 300 cities where people miss him
One and one of Delta's other 299 citic
Delta isn't flying to 300 cities merely to bring people together
But to show that we're not that far apart in the first
Delta
Keep climbing
What meat is sweating over what she was afraid might have been a hack
Her boss Wendy was on a business
Blissfully unaware
How serious this all was
Until the dark
I got a phone call from a very important
Business partner of ours
And
No they're unhappy
The phone call was from one of the companies
Baked clams
And they told Wendy
We just got this really weird email for
From Mavis and they say we've been hacked
Using an email that
A lot like
Any chance you guys got hacked
Oh my
This is big
It made me shaken
Wendy had been preparing for this for years
She knew exactly what
To do turn to that old-fashioned tool we talked about something a lot more people have been doing lately she pulled a big black bee
Binder off the credenza in her office and started flipping through the pages
And she finds a phone number in big block letters and
Begins to dial
You have reached the data security event hotline provided by the law firm of ma
We get a call a day
But at least
Just Happening all the time that's Cristiano and he's a data privacy lawyer with melancholy
Anytime someone calls that hotline
He gets a text on his phone it just says
Somebody called and it's it's got the recording attached to it
The first responder to hacks like this for the very specific
Initial discussion will be protected by the attorney-client privilege
Thank you and someone from Mullen Coughlin will be in touch with you shortly attorney-client
Privilege with a lawyer on the line
You can admit to the most embarrassing parts of the hack
Without ever being worried it'll get out later
If you wind up in court
That's kind of Genius
Super Genius and Chris is part of Wendy's secret weapon that we mentioned
Because about a year ago as if she had foreseen poor Mavis
Clicking on that fateful email
When do you have purchased
Protection something fairly Cutting Edge
She bought
Cyber insurance
Now there's been insurance for computer businesses for a while back in the 1990's you could get insurance for
Errors in data processing
What the internet introduced
A ton of new threat
It got so bad
It was even a big turning
In 2003
The California security breach an information
Made it to
The company got hacked
They couldn't keep it secret anymore
They had to notify residents if their information was still
Which is how this started to get really X
Not just because having to admit to a hack might prefer
Lawsuits
PR problems
Also just the cost of telling everyone
Not to mention me be having to fund
Credit reports are some other remedy to make amends
Tunnel starts to add up which is where insurance comes in
It protects you against the unforeseen
WeatherTech home invasion health problems
Or even a hack
Pay a little now so you don't get stuck with a big
Delator
Cyber Insurance be
Become the new new thing
Cross the Country Insurance Brokers are now selling
Literally thousands of cyber policies every single day
And what companies get for their money
Are people like the
This lawyer Chris
And this
Navigate to emergency response teams for North America
Incidence
A response
Steven Seagal SWAT team
Prescriber
You certainly could think of it like that yes ma'am
He works at a private company called Kroll cyber risk
And he used to be an FBI agent
He was chasing hackers for the feds
Thnxcya side but inside a computer
To keep that sweet sweet attorney client privilege intact
Chris the lawyer
Conferences in Devon the former FBI guy with Wendy
Madison spas
Sounded like an emergency call an emergency call and that's the way that they treated
Devin goes to the crime scene
Gmail account
And he starts investigating and what we'd look for our kind of weed but I would equate to the fingerprints
Of the actor of the bad guy when they're in the account
Step one you can think of a essentially dusting for digital
Devon find a foreign IP address from Lagos Nigeria in mavis's account
We then realize
That we had unauthorized access we could
Firm on the account
Frittata.
4 days
A hacker in your account for 4 days
Is a really long time in a phishing attack
And this is what he could do with 4 luxurious days in her account
Rifle through it in search of
Gold
We did this in a very simple way
Just type into the search window at the top of the email account
Payment
Wiring a
Instructions
Wire train
And a host of other financially related search vim
He wrote them to a folder she never used called an RSS feed
Wait is this like a folder that all Outlook
They do if you look under your scent
It's right there
Oh I have one
Place wheel did no idea with nobody uses it
So he replied
Pretending to be Mavis
And he basically says
Are routing numbers changed
Please send it to this bank account instead
But lucky for Mavis no one
Feel like a for effort Nigerian hacker but you get zero cash
0 cash
On his way out the door though the hacker sent out of party gif
Actually they were a whole bunch of
The movie called burning of the account
Where they send out spam emails
And they move away from the account they don't come back
The scent scent scent scent thing that made us all when she realize what it happened
That was in the hacker coming in
That was him going out
Those thousands of emails to be sent on his way out the door where the hacker
Virtually inviting mavis's entire contact list
The click on a link
XOXO
Migas
Chase Suites
So this investigation is over
And insurance help them
Through that phase
Spray paint for people like Devin
The next step is preventing
The next
And this new Cyber Insurance helps them do that too but in a way that's not as obvious
Hackers going to hack We Can't Stop
But there are two sides to every relationship
Packers
And the maven
Wendy and her insurance policy can do is
Focus on the mavis's here's the lawyer Chris
Getting a shin insurance policy to cover cyber
Requires you to ask some hard questions about
Your data security knowledge
And that
Has to make you wanna
Change your behavior change your behavior
That's the other thing Insurance helps you do
I always thought insurance was just about
Risk pooling Actuarial tables
But it's really about
Behavior and changing it
Insurance sets up
Very simple mac
Mechanism
You want to take risks
Then you pay more
For your insurance you want a discount then you better shape up and they offer the most effective motivation known to man
I assume you're talking about a mother's love well know even more than that
Monday
Sorry Mom
If you want to get a lower cost on your homeowners policy
You have to install it home security
If you quit smoking great
Here's a discount on your health care
Motivation
It's all motive
I was with Wendy when she got a motivational email
From her insurance
I emailed her agent this morning cuz I just hadn't heard anything
Knowing that we are
AIG coded the renewal with limits
With a 66% increase
An increased the retention from 10000 to 25000
That's the deductible
Increasing your premium by 66
6% and more than doubling your deductible
What motivates change
No Wendy has her motivation time to pass it on to the employees she puts her whole company through a
A cyber workout
Her program may sound familiar it included the
Be reliable Stand By Me
Mandatory Workshop
No Bagels no Bagels
We
Bring our employees together and we talked about security it included the obvious this is what you look for check the
URL followed by the more obvious and if you aren't absolutely shirt
Absolutely don't click on it also basic office hygiene or death circline we don't leave data laying around and
And if all of that doesn't work
There's always
Fear in others
Consequences out there in and we know it
Do you think the behavior company-wide has changed you think if a phishing email got into their mailboxes they double-click
Our Behavior has changed internally because
People are more aware
They
They know that it can happen to anybody at any time
And they're more cautious
Wendy was able to convince a new insurance
Company that her new training program
Actually work
She got a new policy with more coverage
But for less money
Not to second-guess Wendy or her new insurance company but I couldn't help but Wonder
Have they really changed how they really sosina copena I am a little sin
So I decided to run
A kind of cyber fired
Essentially
Test the car
Test Wendy's employees
So I called up my old pal the investigator Devin to see if you could help me with a little
Fishing Expedition
Seven runs these kinds of tests for clients all the time
He artisanal ecraft emails with a
Pacific company in mind like if he was going to fish NPR it might say click here for free tote bags
For Wendy's company it was financed
Asian fact it looks a lot like the original email.
He wants the emails to look
Really close to something that you would actually get
I know that sometimes what happens
It's a slightly Miss
Spell the word like
Let's say one of my client
AIG Insurance
It'll be two eyes so it'll say aiig insurance is it something like that
What is this so Devin launch to sting offer
Hear Planet Money we are calling it operation Mavis ouch we told Wendy it was going to happen
But she didn't tell her employee
Hey Wendy it's Dina how are you
I'm good
Waiting to hear well I've got Devin on the line so that he can tell you himself
We fished your users
2 days
How many
We fished 109 users
And we had five users
Open phishing email
We had one of those 5 users
Click the link in the email
Continue to the fishing website in other words they put in their name and password
That is correct that's not good
So maybe things haven't changed as much as I thought
Then
When you surprised us
But I already know who it is
They self-reported MIA
Yep
I got an email in our human resources in box
With a copy of the email from the person
Saying
I should have done this
I clicked
I put in my info
So I called her it team and I had them scan my computer
One person
Now that might not sound like my
My progress book
But any hacker will
The difference between someone alerting it
Right away
Anime this is
Case waiting for days
Well that's an attorney
There's a huge difference between say calling 911 minutes after heart attack and calling 911 4 days later
So the training worked
And Wendy is paying less for
Her insurance
The impact of a cold hard insurance policy
Actually a very human
It creates a system in which what I do affects
You get Whispers
We're all in this together and in doing so it becomes
Powerful force
Pushing the world towards safety good
Cision maybe even fewer have
It is so valuable but yet
So unnoticed
You just got a little mushy about insurance active
It deserves it
It's a beautiful thing
And that's great
Nice work wind
But did Operation Mavis
Catch Mavis
No it was not
Good
It was not
People are getting smarter
There's a conscious decision that has to be made
You can have all kinds of these things that you put in place which we've done
But in the end it's the people that have to make those choices
And
We're relying on them to make good choices
Support also comes from Delta
Delta flies to 300 cities around the world
That's 300 cities where many people do the same things you do
That's 300 cities where people in those 300 cities think they're the only ones who know about that
That one place
And 300 cities where people miss someone
And one of Delta's other 299 cities
Delta isn't flying to 300 cities merely to bring people together
But to show that we're not that far apart in the first place
Delta
Keep climbing
If you have a fishing miss out to confess we are on Instagram Twitter Facebook we are at Planet Money or
Or you can email us at Planet Money at npr.org Today Show was produced by Darren woods and Sally helm
Our editor is brighter stat
Are supervising producer is
We would like to give a very big thanks to Dina for reporting this for us
I'm Dina temple-raston on Karen Duffin
Thanks for listen
We do all Outlook app
That's a dude you just don't notice that I really understand
Oh well wowzers
Wow
Support for this podcast and the following message come from The Economic Development Authority of Fairfax County Virginia
Square One in four jobs are in technology sectors
And we're nearly 60% of adults have college degrees