Hey Stacy here thank you for listening to plan it
Did you like the show and want to help us out have an easy way that you can do that
We want to better understand who is listening to the show and how you are using podcast
So we're asking you to complete a short Anonymous survey if you got time
Npr.org
Podcast survey
Less than 10 minutes
And it really helps support the show
That is npr.org podcasts
Now on Today Show
Today show with originally reported in 2007
But you know it is about taxes and what is more timeless
Ben taxes
Also we got an update for you at the
What are producers Kira Planet Money Elizabeth kulas had recently moved to the US from Australia
And she got this kind of
Interesting initiation into American Life
She did
Her taxes
At first she and her husband Matthew Harding tried to do it on their own
Then the taxes
And it took over their part
On our
Dining room table
We have a pile
WW2
V 1099
Animism other forms like a 1095-c
Elizabeth and Matthew realized they were going to need some
So they hired an account
It could easily be $500 a weekend to spend at the account
What did Mayweather you say to me the other day you would be happy if was less than $1,000 what she said
This is all kind of blowing their my
It's because there was nothing like
This in Australia
In Australia paying taxes is really fast and easy
In fact Elizabeth the math you couldn't even tell me when Australian tax day what
So is there an equivalent of
April 15th
In Australia
Really
I don't remember being such a thing
I think it's like February or March
It's October 31st actually but in most of the rest of the world
They don't know when tax day is either
All of the crazy stress around tax
24-hour hotlines
Software the accordion folders full of receipts the lines down the street at H&R Block
That is
Pretty much just a USA thing
So we have it the worst our taxes are the
Worst
I filing system is it worse
Like adjectives
Yeah objectively
Joseph bankman is a professor of tax law at
And he says collectively
We spend billions
Of dollars and billions of hours every year filing our tax
Not to mention the emotional
Juices it does not have to be this way
In most of the world it's not
And Joe
Knows exactly how to fix this
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Stacey Vanek Smith and with me today is Alex may I see
Play Stacey Joe Versus the Texas.
That's right it's a story of this lovable professor
I believe the paint taxes does not need to be so difficult
Because I'm a year-long quest
McFarland taxes easier for everyone
Can you wake someone during
Who would want to keep taxes complicated
Well I will tell you who
A multibillion-dollar corporation
And one of the most important power Brokers in Washington
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One Capital One
Is reimagining banking I offering account
With no fees or
Items that can be opened from anywhere in
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
So Alex jumping bean does not look like your
Typical
Warrior hero
What's the best way to describe
When Steven Spielberg inevitably directs a Blockbuster movie about taxes
Joe bankman will be
Who played by Tom Hanks
Mind you it's a Tom Hanks
Suspend teaching tax lot Sanford
Also average rest
Down Tom Hanks
Alex when we talked to Joe bankman at Stanford you were marked nobody was very dressed up
Joe and I are both pretty casual Alex is being very sweet but as I look at these Sarah slat
I noticed
There's a stain on one of them
An
The cops are afraid
Delete
I hate
Taxes
But you'll bankman
Love's tax
Joe loves taxes so much that he thinks about them in his spare time
In fact
He spent time when he's not in class or on campus
Helping the state of California wear contacts
Back in 2003 Joe is part of the
Little team that was working with the state to help take down Taxi
We are just done a bill to penalize a form of tax shelter
And it raised a lot of money for this day
And we're all out to lunch at a mediocre restaurant in Sacramento
Yeah we are celebrating
Joey his California tax
Neymar beating lunch
Can shop at the tell Joe they have the
And I did I think would save California
A bunch of money and time and help
Most people in California
Have really simatai
They get all of their income from a regular
And taxes are already withheld
When does Paychex
So their idea was why don't we start off
Giving them a tax return
That's already filled out with the income we know they have
And then they can make Corrections
That was their idea
Basically the government would send you a tax return that was already filled out
It would include all of the income that the state knew about all this
The taxes that had already been withheld from
And you would look it over and
Mail it in
Joni this was how taxes work in most country
That works in Europe parts
Asia Scandinavia Australia
And so he thought
Why not here
The way I think of it is
Imagine if the credit card
Acted like the IRS
Each month you get a Visa bill and be a blank piece of paper
And you'd have to write down all of your purchases and added up
And if you did it wrong you face a penalty
So the IRS could
Act like Visa
And paying taxes
Would be like
Paying a credit card
And we could be like Elizabeth and Matthew are first-time taxpayer
Not know when our tax day is
So now Joe and his team had this
But they still needed to
Make it real bad to figure out
What this
Form would be and what it would look like
And so Alex we haven't we haven't
In front of us
Do not look like a tax form
I've ever seen
Yeah you know it's it's just one page it looks pretty friendly it's not
A bunch of legalese you know it says
Easy as 1 2 3
Step 1 review return step to make any changes in step 3 send it back
That's it I know there's something so friendly about it at the time because
Filing your taxes just got easier
And then it has the name that Joe and his
Team gave to this form and enter this whole project
We called it a ready return
I like ready return it snappy
It's nappier isn't it
Now Joe and his California tax
Team have this form
Ready to spray friendly form
But I still need to see if ready return is actually going to work
If taxpayers
Use it if they would like it
So they did a pilot program in California
In the 2004 tax season isn't ready returns out to about 11,000 tax
Along with this
Little survey
So we ask people
Do you think you'd like to use this again next
And 99% of the people said yes
99% of people don't say yes to anything
90% is amazing
I talked to someone else who's involved in ready return and what he told me is
When you work in government nothing
That's reviews like that he's a
You don't get 99% satisfaction rate with the polio vaccine
True
And it wasn't just the survey either think it was actually the proudest over
The comments
The people had written in on their surveys
And he actually brought a stack of
Printed out comments into Taco Bell
What I do
Is a rifle through some of the pages
And then I asked people to tell me when to stop
Because I don't want to anybody think I'm cherry-picking so tell me here are Alex can see me
Tell me when to stop flipping through the pages and I will tell him to stop right now
Okay cuz on a random page on some random
And the first one thank you for allowing me to participate
Second this was very easy and convenient
3rd
No problems I loved it
So I said I loved it
I love that skiers one that says PS is the same service available for federal tax
Returns this is all cap
Add someone used all caps positive
Yes
There was one comment that really stuck
Finally governments doing something to make my life better
What did you think when you read that
I was really touched them and I was really moved I'm even moved as I think about it now
For someone like me that's your your dream right
You know if you think about filing taxes he
It's one of the most important interactions you've got with your government and how does it make you feel
It makes you piss
You can understand that you're anxious you're worried about screwing up
And
We make 160 million people go through this each year that's
That's really bad
Did you think that
We improve that did you think it would like help improve
People's relationship with the government
Absolutely
Joe thought his little
Ready return form
Mickey big
Difference
In the country
Of course the first ready return had to pass the California state legislature in
But you wasn't that worried I mean everyone who tried ready return head
I've loved it and California governor Arnold Schwarzenegger was also on board
So just started making the two hour car trip from Stanford to Sacramento every week
To talk with Legend
Well I thought
That if I just talked
Did Anders
I was kind of naive I thought well I get it
That
People are conservative or a liberal but
Since this is a nonpartisan issue
I'll just talk to all of our Representatives
In Sacramento and explain things to
I'm a talker I thought I could do that
Choza Taqueria
He is a talker and he he made a list of all the legislators would be voting on ready
Return any just started calling at their offices and asking for meeting
I wasn't getting enough meeting
Are people with put me off or they say we'll get back to you
When Joe did get a meeting
$10 go so well
Well one meeting
Somebody said I've been warned about you
That was sort of startup with what did they mean
They mad that the Intuit lobbyists it already been in
Intuit
Is the company that owns
TurboTax
TurboTax is of course
Be very popular tax preparation software it is a multi-billion Dollar business
A multibillion-dollar business that was now staring down the barrel of Jose ready return
And if you look at this from TurboTax is point of view
This is not good and ready which one is all about making taxes
Easier
And if your taxes are easier you're a whole lot less likely
To spend a hundred bucks on tax prep
Software
So just started hearing that into it
Was asking around about his
Is plan
Which of these little talks you know for legislators about ready return he given academic talk for students and professors
And he started noticing something odd
Whenever he gave a talk
He would always notice someone from Intuit
In the crowd
They would show up at talks I would give how would you know that it was them
I give a lot of talks
And I'm only going to get it like
10:30 people
And everybody looks like an academic but one woman comes in
I just kind of looking a little corporate
She's like dressed better than the rest
And so that's a tip off right away tax academics or not the best dressed people in the world
Intermittent want to talk to us for this piece but they sent us a statement
It said that they have long advocated
Tax simplification
But they're ready return quote minimizes taxpayer engaged
They think that's bad thing
You discovered the into it had been very busy in sacrum
Meeting with politicians getting money
Intuit gave a million dollars to a Pac that supported one of the
The key politicians on the ready return issue
This kind of thing happens all the time
We have a little group it is
Very invested in an issue that
It affects a lot of people
Give me the little group in this case TurboTax
Is willing to spend
Tons of time and tons of money making something happen
And a large group of people that might benefit a little bit or not willing to spend that time and money
Prince I would love it if filing my taxes were easier but I haven't called my congressman
I'm not really willing to spend a whole bunch of money to make that happen
Then again
I
I'm Nacho
So that's
The point where I decided to hire my own lobbyist
Someone hiring their own Lobby
It was really fun I really enjoyed hiring a lot
I hired a guy named Mike Robson
Coart smart as a whip
Really likeable
Kind of looks like a more svelte James Gandolfini
But that lobbyists
He didn't come cheap
How much did that cost
They gave me a deal
Because they thought it would be kind of fun
The work for this
Craze Professor working for you
Yeah
They're working for me and so
The normal price I think would have been a hundred
$40,000
Christy get Mike services
But he gave it to me for only
If I pay thirty five
Like of your own money
But my own money
Liquor savings
Yeah why did you spend the money that way
I know I felt lucky again to be able to do as a great cause
And everybody I think has some causes and think we're good causes and
This was a cause that was really good and nobody else was going to do it but me
Making that investment Iron Mike
Paid off
With microbes and everybody would talk
Why
Well they had relationships with him
Legislators
Kind of like that I was with Mike
Because they also kind of legitimated
They figure if you're with Mike you're probably sensible
You probably are going to get good information
If I have a question I can call your lobbyist if I can't get ahold of you
The meeting start to go a little better
Legislator start listening to Joe
Telling him
You got my vote
But Joe says
He noticed
It was hard to get Republicans to back Reddit
It wasn't just into it or campaign money
How to do
With a pledge
And privately I should say
A lot of Republicans told me what this just sounds like a no-brainer I just can't do it
Because Grover norquist is opposed it
Hello my name is Grover norquist
I am the President of Americans for tax reform we fight for taxpayers try to keep taxes low
Grover norquist is a famous anti-tax crusader
He heard about ready return
And sprang into action
So does a wave to raise taxes
A way to send people a bill for more taxes than they owe
And they're unlikely to contested people don't fight the IRS
Norquist.
Ready return is tantamount to attack
Because once the government has tax
Autopilot
Signing and sending
Bill start sneaking things in like the house cell phone
Company sneakers
Little charges and you look at them and sort of wonder about them but
Me and you just pay because it's easier
And norquist has this famous Platt
Republicans
All across the country.
Take it and the pledge basically says
I will not support any plan
That racist
And that was a problem
What happens if you break the pledge
When somebody breaks the pledge
Their opponents in the next election 10 to remind voters
They lied their way into office
I am depressed test
Focus on it
Northwest put out the word to California Republican
If you back ready return
You have broken the pledge
Joe bankman this tacswap
Professor and his loan lobbyist
Are now battling not only a multi-billion-dollar soccer
Also one of the biggest
Names in US policy
Joe kept telling everyone this won't race
It will just make it easier to pay them
I'll see if everyone time and money
But Joe says he talked to a lot of small government
And actually
They wanted
Paying taxes to
Their logic was
If paying taxes
It's difficult
People will hate tax
And vote against them
Joe and Mike kept
And they started getting ground
Little by little with Democrats and Republicans locking downvotes
And a couple weeks out
They needed just
One more vote
One more vote to make ready return happen in the entire state
California
And then
I found a Republican
That was going to support it
Joe convinced a republican legislator to back the
Ignore the pledge
Ignore the campaign money
After a year of taking on corporate lobbyists political power Brokers and so many talk
After spending $35,000 a piece
His own money
This was it
Ready return
Look like it was going to happen
Just before the vote
Joe had to drive back down to stamp
Videos of the politicians who supported ready return
To keep them up
The day of the boat
Joe remembers getting a call
I could tell by the time this voice
What the answer
What's before I said any
He said
So and so I've even forgotten the legislators name is not with us looks like we're going to be one vote short
Vote
Shorts
Republican and changed his mind
And Joe
Had lost
And all of the other states that I've been calling Joe asking how they could implement the plan like this
The kind of dropped away
It was it was a little bit crushing
Hot to lose like that
How much time have you invested in this
You don't know why it was a year of my life
It's a pretty big blow
SoJO
Joann back to teaching full time
But he kept pushing ready return
A version of it did survive in California
It's buried in the state's tax site but it's there
A few hundred thousand people use it every year
And ready returns had a pretty interesting Legacy
In 2016 Elizabeth Warren and Bernie Sanders introduced a bill that looked a lot like ready return the even
Reference Jose pilot program
It did not end up at
But Joe says we could getting close
Eventually
He thinks it's going to happen
My fantasy
Is that
At some point it just makes so much sense will join the rest of the world and all
Paul dillet
And I don't know how that's going to happen with our current political climate
Maybe some mid-level bureaucrat I'll just make the change herself
And it'll go through it'll kind of fly under the radar
That's what I think will happen sooner or later
Somehow
In the meantime people like Elizabeth and Matthew are first-time us
Taxpayers how to mention all the rest of us
Are stuck spending hundreds of dollars and
Many many hours
Filing Arts
Play it is not without its ups
I never would have even said so like accomplishment when we get through it
I think I was saying Sally like if we can do this like we can do anything this is probably the most daunting task
It would come across by tax return
Welcome to America we've got an update after the break
This message comes from NPR sponsors
Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their own webs
Using customizable layout
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online price
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Stacy here it is now 2019 and I got an update about the tax story
Our very own tax Rodeo bankman is still teaching
Stanford
He has not given up on trying to simplify our tax system
He has seen some changes he says but
Not exactly in the way he wanted
My thoughts are now less well-attended because into it doesn't send its Representatives anymore
Okay so Joe is not striking fear into the hearts of the tax lobby as much as he used to
He says he is still making progress little by little
Maybe one
Step forward and two steps back
The IRS is moving ahead with the plan to modernize data collection
And make
More of that data available in a timely manner
Do your tax preparer
So it would be easier for your accountant at least
Pepper regular people's would like to get their tax forms just all filled out automatically
Well that is not going to happen because of this one line that keeps getting added to the Appropriations
The industry is put a rider on a bill
That would make it illegal
The federal government to do the kind of return pre population
That is the basis for red returning the California still doing
Still
Joe remains Optimus
He says he's waiting to see if a new Congress or the next
Presidential election might Shake That writer off of the app
Hope Springs Eternal
Special things to Larry zelenak and to Alex may I see who originally brought us this
Today's rerun was produced by our intern Rachel
And we always love to hear what you think of the show we are on Twitter and Facebook and Instagram at Planet my
Money you can always send us an email
Planet Money at npr.org
If you like this episode of Black Planet Money In general please leave us a rating or review in your favorite podcast app
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
And this is NPR thanks for listening