David Goldstein lived
Politics for decades
Behind the scene
Working on this campaign or the ad campaign always for the Democrats his specialty was the digital stuff
Choosing which strategy to take online or using data to analyze which voters to focus
And after years of feeling like he had a handle on how campaigns work
2016 happy
Two outcomes most people predicted would never come true came true
First there was brexit in Europe and then
Donald Trump
In America
And when David tries to make sense of it
He realizes that some of the same people were behind both campaign
It is so rare
And so hard in politics to pull an upset
I they are few and far between maybe and your entire
34 tier political career you will be on the winning side of a single upset
They pulled off
2 upsets
In back-to-back
Here's specifically there was one company that worked on both
Cambridge analytica
And as we heard about a lot since then they got caught using personal data without permission
Some of it from Facebook
They're accused of breaking laws but they also claimed to have pulled off new
Legal tax
For finding especially personalized
Even intimate ways to persuade voters using online.
There's a lot that was simply
Anime that we hadn't thought of doing the
A big thing was
Yeah this kind of setting up your own
Personal like online ecosystem of content meant to persuade people to a certain action
Currently trying to fly into a web
They were claiming they could create profiles of people based on their online dating
And then use that against them
2 Chainz
Maybe without them even knowing it was happened
Maybe using missing from
And it just felt like playing dirty
He's thinking
This is not how democracy
Should work I'm not somebody who scares easily but I am legitimately scared
He's looking at this like an arms race
Race with the Democrats way behind sec
And he wants to sound in Allah
He sets up a bunch of meetings at places like Google Facebook
Twitter other big online cup
My Hope was
So there could be some kind of like
Cross-industry investigative body that could work with the government and Regulatory and Private Industry
And I was shot down very fast
I imagine the people that he talks with these big tech companies are like
Obviously you can Target people and persuade them
That is the point of RI plat
Parts to get the most persuasive ad in front of every person exactly in the way that persuades in the most that is why we get paid
Call Dad
Nicely though the same person who shot me down says the same time
If you want to see something happen on this
You have to do this yourself
You have to do it too
You have to become a Cambridge analytica yourself
Well that way yes
Without
Illegal arms hello and welcome to Planet Money
Group there's a threat to democracy
David decides
To mess with them
And maybe help his own party along the way
When he says he wants to prove there's a threat he needs proof like with a science
Experiment on actual voters
In an actual
With data statistics controls all of
Today on the show had a metal in an election
Step by step
This message comes from NPR sponsor Microsoft
You might be surprised by the amount of Science and Technology that's inside a bottle of beer
At the Carlsberg research laboratory in Copenhagen
Brewers are using Microsoft AI to help them reinvent the way they make beer
AI enables them to analyze raw ingredients for Unique flavors
So they can develop better beers faster
See how Microsoft AI is empowering business anime
Raiders at microsoft.com AI
James Reid was fatally beaten on Selma Street in 1965
Galvanized
Put in a court room 9 months later a not guilty verdict
In episode 2
The trial and the birth of the conspiracy theory
Mmpr it's White Lies
Listen And subscribe now
Sodus Point David living in New York
He and his main job it is not an apology
She's not working at a big corporate Ad Agency
The science experiment think he's hatching it's like a Cypress
Nights and weekends
And the first thing he needs to get it going as some money
It's recalls up some old contacts
And most of the donors
He goes to their like
Are you kidding me
You want me to find a plan for you to go Rogue and be a Cambridge analytica of the left with
Potentially ethically sketchy methods
Unreal Motors
In a real election
But you don't know which one yet
And David is like
Yes
Biggs
That is exactly why
Eventually he scares enough donors
And raises 85000
Chinese in business
It takes David about two weeks to get his whole team together
He's going to be the brains he comes up
Strategy
Text messaging and Designs what people will see when they click
He needs someone to Wrangle the data for him
Enemies people to design the ad
He'll be right you also check the whole plan over with an election lawyer because
He wants to stay
Legal so we had kind of formed our team
Right and we all resolves okay we're going to do this
But the thing was it was like summer 2017
The next big elections are more than a year away
And he needs a bigger
Because he's running a science experiment on voters need lots of Voters he needs a way to make two groups of Voters
Ideally
Demographically identical
Voting history
Turnout history partisan makeup all the things that he can measure as identical as possible
Into one control group and Winchester
After his campaign
And half dump
And then he's going to measure
Like a medical drug trial
But for politics
It was very tough
To figure out exactly how
We would cut up the potential electorates
In such a way that we could reliably say
We had an impact in the test condition because this did not happen in the control
And Alabama
Comes through
Senator there Jeff sessions
General
So there's an open seat
So
What happened is the Alabama senate election was called
It didn't seem winnable
For the Democrats at first
This is that election by the way that ended up with Roy Moore the Republican candidate getting accused of being a pedophile
Instead Jones the Democrat but David is assessing this race
Way before those are the final
And he knows it's been about 25 years since a Democrat won the senate seat in Alabama
What I plan to my team and what occurred to me was we don't have to win
It doesn't matter if we
We just have to show
In effect
I was like if if he loses
By 14 points
But we go back to our group that we hit and the only losses in that group by a point
We can show
Ss&b
Boss
If
Or hypothesis
Is right
I know how to set up
Pick 3 State Senate districts
Matches those against three
Three tests district3 control
And three of those
You
And given the ads and the other three
You don't get mad but you measure them like you did so you can
Yeah and with digital ads it's easy to pick who will see your ads
And who won't
Yeah and in fact
I think what's
Xidan surprising to a lot of people
Is this element of what we call negative Target
So if I don't want someone
To see my ads I can put their name into the system
And they will never see my advertising
He said he could even feed in the names of all the campaigns
The journalists covering the race
The Regulators to
And make sure that they never see his campaign for
If he were
But the people he does want to Target he can bombard them with whatever ads
She can afford
To pay for one of the one of the wonderful things
Are props awful things
I got this new age of digital advertising is the number of times
That we can touch you
Right
That sounds great
Anyway anyhow it's it's if it's referred to as yo
Essentially a touch like how often can I get
Am I content what I want you to see in front of you
With the old ways
Ways a candidate would flood local TV ad and be lucky to get it in front of a voter they wanted to reach Maybe
Twice a day
With the amount of time that people now spend
On their smartphones on their laptops and
Simplii online are 4 to 5 hours a day
I know I'm hundreds
Of opportunities in one single day
To hit you and possibly even thousands
He can show you one at and then another
Add another testing out different messages or designs on different websites you might check
Trying to figure out
What catches your eye
And when
Going after the same pull up Motors and hitting them over and over and over and over again
Until they figured out what would make them flick
And once the automated ad system
Hesitant
It learn
The next time the system tries to
Are you it goes
Right to the stuff in nose
Always test
Always learn
Very rap
And that's why this is so devastatingly effective
Because you can cut into people who are typically very sophisticated viewers people with higher education's
Are people who are very wealthy
But because you're continually exposing them until you find out what
Flips hair trigger and something always does
You're getting access into that person's mind that you never would have previously
And sometimes looking into that person's mind is relatively
A harmless
I mean it's just annoying when the internet wants you to buy that pair of sunglasses
It gets dangerous
When is trying to change the way you vote especially when the person behind all of this doesn't want you to notice they're even trying
And this isn't just
Facebook
He is trying to reach people
All over the web regular website
A system it's like any online ad
And for all this to work
Do you need to create a
Hon of different messages to test
Those messages need to lure voters
The best thing to do for me
Goodbye phrases
I want it
Nefarious
So basically
What you are going to click on in the future is what you were clicking on now
Reitman that were creatures of habit and makes us so I assumed if I went to right-wing websites and took a look
At what the advertisers were doing on those
That would help direct me
I'm to what
The brief should be
For my own content producers in a day
Cuz you had you had actually get inside the mind of
The Republican
Normally what you do
Right is that
It is a kind of obsessive study on the look in the Styles the theme
The freezing even
Very big on Words having to do with things like yeah
Anything that smokes like the flag us patriotism
Honor was very important concept that came out of my deep dive
As I was putting my ass together for them I was trying to tap into those themes
Hurry Elsa I want to show you something
Betrayal
Of Alabama's honor
And there's a dude in a cowboy hat
Alabama's great
It looks like 1990s
Is website
Level up
Animation
Like you did it at home
Noah paint It's Like A step above
But like looking stencil that you're behind
He says that it works
Like amateurs
Enough that I was actually curious why he did
That was on purpose
Absolutely unfair
That wasn't cuz you just had a small budget
What are the nice things about working in New York is your you have access to the best talent in the world
And yes it was tough for me to tell he's very very talented dark eyes
This is too nice
Make it simpler
Kenmore black
But those are the ads that fit in with the other ads on the websites that his Target
You're going to
That's what he gets
And now he's almost ready to
And then the election change
Roy Moore becomes the candidate on the Republican side and
He is now probably the worst candidate imaginable
Call for a general election
Because this is the time where he's getting barrage by all these allegations about how he's a pedophile
And there are no prominent Republicans saying Roy Moore is unfit for office
Suddenly David science experiment is happening in a nail-biter of a closer look
And maybe the science experiment can help his side win
Support for this podcast in the following message come from Google
From Connecticut to California
From Mississippi to Minnesota
Millions of businesses are using Google tools to grow online
Learn how Google is supporting businesses in your state at google.com economic MBA
So how many candidates are running for president
Maybe more to come it is a lot keep track of
Which is why the NPR politics podcast
Hitting the road
Introduce you to all the people running for president
Join us on the campaign Trail as we interview the candidates to ask why they are the best pick for president
Follow along this spring and summer by subscribing to the NPR politics podcast
So David has his Clique harvesting machine
The ecosystem drawing flies into a web
What is a klick
I mean where do you go when you click
What happens when they get the
The Click is they go to a website that I've set up just for that when this case different websites for different groups of Voters
David plan for Democrats is just a boost voter turnout
Tell when a democrat in Alabama clicks on an ad
They get sent to a website with videos and articles design
To boost their mood to uplift them and in the process make them feel like everything will come down to their one
With Republicans David's plan is a little savvier little sneakier
He wants them
To vote
This man for moderate Republicans is to make them want to write in Canada
It's other than Roy Moore
By making them think that that's what everyone else
So he sends them out at Republic
Looking to
A website that looks like a news site
It's filled with
True stories
About how other Republicans are planning to write in
Other candidate
Is playing for a conservative
What is to make them
Stay home
On the conservative website
I was just for the conservative alabamians
I filled it
With content
That was not written by me
Was written by other conservatives out somewhere anywhere on the web
Tor writing about how terrible
Roy Moore was
To not fake news this was
Not fake news I never once
Created
Article
Tweets
Nothing ever what does might look like is
A Breitbart or idrudge Style music
But if it has pieces linking to the local newspaper
Or maybe something a conservative writer posted on his blog and it just happens at all these posts on the site pain Troy MO
It is really bad
David is using a site to create a fake view of the
With real story
They're out of context
But they are still technically real
And the point is to dissuade vote
Sites are already
His research tells him he'll
I have the most impact
Closer to the election
In about a week and a half
Before election day
Everything
Goes like
Essentially what happens is the ad start get pushed out
Right and they start to appear in front of people
Time in Alabama
Either on their smartphones or on their laptops
And he waits
Automated system
About this point
It's easy to say
He'll come on this is over playing the power of at
Who really clicks on them
Or
I live through Upworthy
But that is not the
It doesn't really matter if you do it
It only matters
Someone
A sliver
The people history
You might be amazed
Right and the guy next to you might be another guy next to dead person might might be mean
But I only need to change 3% of people
In order to effect a given result
Then I can go 97 people down
And not having a fact but as long as I have an effect on one two three
An only on this one specific action
But all the rest of the time they're immune
But to me they're not
Then
I can literally change the world
I talk to digital campaign
Republicans and Democrats
Professors who study
Regular old ad buyers for non camp
And when I told them about Dave
They all kind of went
Yep that makes sense
Half of them told me other ways that he could have done it that are even more surface
But that yeah
In principle
This is what campaigning is
And when David checks is early data
The grand science experiment
To be working
Always say the biggest shock was the most engaged folks were they conservative
Republicans
They did the most
Clicking out of any of the groups they spent the most time in his ecosystem of website
To measure the voting
When he does eventually get the voter rolls
And he Compares his Control District with his
Experimental treatment group
To see
Which groups turned out to vote more
It looks like he has had a real
Democrats
Experimental group
Turn data off 4% higher level
And the Democrats in the control
4% so you think that your work
Cuz 4% higher turnout
Yes
In the places you try to
That's a lot
Most of that is more than the margin of victory
In a lot of Elections
Loads
Yeah
It's enough to flip an election
Absolute
And the Republicans did it work on them it did the experimental condition was two and a half percent lower
For the moderate Republicans
You believe you caused a two and a half percent lower turnout
For the moderate Republicans the fact that you targeted
Exactly and then for the conservative Republicans
Was 4.4%
Can I have a drop off
Which is which is also a lot to take out of someone's face
Exactly
Roy Moore loses the election to Doug Jones the Democrat
We just
1 + 1/2
This is a little over 20000 votes Statewide
So I asked David
What did he think that his science
Experiment
Had caused
I would say we could reasonably lay claim
About 89000
That sounds like a lot of vote
I'm serious I guess it's a big claim
Yes but
I'm fine sharing the
Yap shut the data with whoever wants to see the data
You know I would like to take a look at the data
I looked
And I wouldn't talk to professors who studied
Another campaign strategist on the roof
And I talked to David Quinn
And
It's pretty much impossible
To verify
They said there's too many variables are too little information
Like maybe Doug Jones held a bunch of big rallies in one of the testis
Or
Maybe a big influential pastor
Have a church in one of the tests District made a big show of writing in his vote against Roy Moore
Could be all kinds of
And even by his own numbers and his own calculations the impact that David had on Democratic turnout is up
Because you're like to percent change
When you factor in a few more
Most of the experts that I talked to we're skeptical of how big his numbers were
Given how little money
But
One of the campaigners
I talked to also told me that they've heard of other
Send other studies
Other campaign groups that are not ever going to be made public
And in a lot of ways
This isn't so far out of line
What's different here is the person who ran this campaign
What's this
Doing it pretty much on his own from an office in a city
Many states away
Make it look easy to build an algorithmic system that could sway thousands of votes
For less than $100,000
What do you do after you meddling in election
Intense term but I got it so you start showing it to other people who have to worry about
The next
Election themselves
After his experiment David showed his results to democratic
And you said
Hire me and I will show you how to do what I did
Or at least
Learn how to fight against what I did because anyone can do it or even worse
Is it
Just inevitable that that's going to keep happening as long as we have online ads
I mean I necessarily I think it was far easier to sway people with the TV ad in the early days of TV
Is a
Ways to do the radio ads and I think
Right now we're in a bit of a
Free and easy.
I think when it comes to digital
Online advertising but
You know I do have a belief that as we grow more
Sophisticated should make it more difficult
For folks like me
I'm not an empath
After I talked with him
I was thinking
This is just an arms race
And I wondered
If that ever let him do just want
A truce to go back to the
So I asked him if he ever brought that up with him
He wrote me an email back and he said he had
He said this makes it cheaper for campaigns to reach voters
Easier to get a message
Campaigns won't give that
Also he wrote
I don't know how to say
I'll stop if you do
In Russian
How do you subscribe to our newsletter do it is one
Planet Money style story designed to be read on your phone like
How would a welt
Tax work or are doctors
A cartel
Describe at npr.org Planet Money newsletter that's npr.org Planet Money news
What're you want to thank a ton Hirsch at Tufts Dan Christ at UNC Mark Stevenson at Red Oak strategic Michael P chat crossword
Green partners
Tamban you're at Target smart and everybody else
To talk to us for today's episode
And if you like today's episode we're going to keep covering out data and Technology are changing business and Society
And let us know what you wanted to cover get in touch at Planet Money at mpr.org if you want more Planet Money on campaign stripes
Set number 8 for 5 called
About how gerrymandering got so out of control this show is produced by Dearing Woods
Brainerd status her show
And if you like Planet Money the best way to show your support is to share it with a Friend helps grow
I'm out with Mike and I know that this is NPR thanks for listening