Here at Planet Money
NPR offices
We have this little Muse
With a bunch of memorabilia from different episodes across the years there's the planet
T-shirt
A Santa hat little vial of oil
Another little vial
Gold
And
This
It's a jar
Looks like it was once
A peanut butter jar
And on the side of it is this label
It says Planet Money investment fund
And there's a handful of building
A50
Every few years at Planet Money
We take this money
And we make
Investing
Some would say so much
Questionable in
What are my favorite experiments we did back in 20
We did a few shows on it
And the first one of those were going to be plated
Cured
Basically every penny I own
It's all a bet in One Direction's all bet that everything is going
Like I own a house
Right that is a bad thing
Real estate
And you're so crazy because you are a guy who is normally pretty cynical about
I look my entire retirement account right it's like stocks
Stocks are bet that a company is going to be worth
Bonded loan to some municipality that's going to build like a
Sewage treatment facility it's a bet that that's going to work out they're going to pay me back no one would call you little Mary sunshine and yet
You are doing what everyone else in America.
Switch is to
Bad things are just going to get better and historically like that is not the worst better than
No it's a totally fine but it just struck me as odd all the
Because
There is no other better
You can make right
You can bet in the opposite direction
You can make a bed
That will pay off
When things go badly
Hey perhaps you've heard us talk about this
Before it is called
A short
A short sell it so if you short Apple stock you're basically betting that Apple stock is going to be worth less than a month
32 months or a year
And the goes down everyone else is crying the very very sad
You have to celebrate
Their loss is your gain
And it's not actually that
Hard
Too Short something and you can do it online anywhere where you can buy stocks you can also short stocks and yet
The most part
Nobody
We decided we would we would short something we consulted a bunch of experts they told us not to do it
I said there are some very very good reasons people don't short
Run off the planet money I'm David kestenbaum
And I'm Robert Smith today on the show we ignore the advice of some very smart people and we short some
We're going to put our money down on a bat against something that everybody loves
If you haven't been reading Planet money's newsletter you're missing out on stories about
Hidden beaches and scooter Mania and plastic bag ban it's just the right amount of economics and
Analysis served up once a week
Subscribe at npr.org
Planet Money newsletter
Longtime listeners will know that we have a little bit of money set aside for a moment
I guess I could call the Planet Money investment fund also known as the world's least successful hedge fund
Back in 2010 I think it was we all put two hundred bucks
Can each total of $1,000
First we bought a toxic asset one of those
Mortgage things that I was brought down the global economy proxy
We lost half our money on that
The Jake but I took what was left we bought gold we actually bought a gold
Coin
We lost some more money that was like 3 years ago
I put whatever we had left
In a locked cabinet
And we basically forgot about
Until last week
Robert
Yes sir I see how much money we have left in the Planet Money investment fund
Oh yeah totally
Where is it in the locker
I'm surprised it's under lock and key
Thr
What is it like $6
I have a confession
A couple years ago I need to cash it didn't have time to go to an ATM
So I got the money out of the jar I did put a little note there but
Looking at it today like I don't know exactly what I meant by this note there two numbers there one is crossed out
I'm pretty sure we have
$406
Sixth Sense
What's left in the fun
Teacher are the worst
Good Ship Lollipop
All right man
Play money jar is back in effect
A little
This is it
See if we can
If we make it all back
There's no way we're making it
It is theoretically possible
The reason why we wanted to pick short against these really we have done podcast on shorting before and
Economist are always talking about this
Important part of the financial markets that
Help stocks from becoming too hyped
Keep bubbles from forming
I really had no idea how it really worked I certainly didn't know like
What we should short or had a
We went to consult
An expert one of the ex
This guy's name is Andrew
Used to write a newsletter
The title was
Stock lemon
Noah changed
Well
Stock lemon
Was very tongue-in-cheek
I thought I just needed more of a
A highbrow name
The new name
Citron research
And it's been at this for over a day
He's the guy that went CNBC needs to get a short seller on
They often grab
And he's great on the air because he's betting against things that other people love
You know those little cameras that if you go skiing you see everyone has his little cameras on top of their helmet GoPro a short GoPro
Is short Tesla another company a lot of people love and Green Mountain Coffee K-Cups that you
You put in the ass
Yeah yeah exactly
So he asked his advice
Suppose someone with almost no investment
And
And very little money
Came up to you and said
I want to try too short
No
Don't do it
Why
It's not it's a very skilled formers invest
It really is not for the average
Investor
It's dangerous
You can lose too much money doing it
The forces of Wall Street are against you
It's not worth it
Do something else
You know we went into this I sort of thought that shorting a stock was just the opposite
Buying us
Instead of betting that a stock is going to go up you're just betting that it's
What is we dug into it I realized it is not it is a completely different animal in just about every way
Yeah there's all these hurdles you have to go through I think both mentally and financially before you can short a stock I mean
The first one is the most
Basic thing
Which is okay
Most stocks seem to go up over time you have to find a company
It is
You have to find a company where you know something that no one else knows you have to find a company
You hope
Whoops lunging
You got to find something like this guy
My name is Sam and Randy on the chief messing up surf Kerrisdale capital
Sam is another famous short seller he is 33 years old
And 4033 year olds getting very large coin jar is hedge fund has over quarter billion.
Dollars under management
Is abscess where a few blocks away we went over to talk to him
Unfancy
Samsat down in this little conference
And he coached us on how to pick a stock to bedok
He told us this one
Perfect little story
Best case scenario
About this one company that
Sound too short this is back in 2010
I'm in Santa's poking around looking at
Certain Chinese cup
Chinese Dumplings
Starting to get listed on us stock exchanges any found
This one company that I had a business model like Princeton Review they basically
Coach Chinese students
On how to pass entrance exams for college
Company was called China educational
It was Opry Mills classes in selling these
Sample test online
And
Sam looked at the website looked okay to him
But he couldn't
Read Chinese
I got a guy who could read Chinese actually try it out
Any found something weird
And we came back with those
Cannot connect to purchase any product
Despite the fact that this business half of its sales
From selling testing on its website
It's test as website
Was completely non-functional
Wait they couldn't like
Order anything or put in their attic when you tried to go to the part of the website where you would put in your credit card
An error screen popped
Barry
Very suspicious
But you know the company did say that it taught classes in
Person soap
He decide to check on that
This is harder to check because the building where the classes
Frittata in this Northern
Province of China near the border with Russia
But some found a guy to go check it out
Like he found a freelancer through one of these websites are
Say I'll do God jobs
Some pay the guy $1,000 when she was
Very excited
And ask him to go check out the building
And we have to take a camera
So I went there and saw there was a
Completely vacant building
What do you want to eat in the forest with 6 floors there no chairs or no chalkboards
It was just a completely vacant building
So think about this for a moment
There's a company
Did everyone loves that everyone thinks is doing is gangbusters business
And some knows something unique
He knows that this company
Isn't doing anything
Something that the fraud
A perfect stock to Short
Someone deceased
Like if you find something
You think it's like this you have to be really careful you have to do your research
Because
What's about to happen next
Can be a total roller coaster
Though the actual Act of shorting a stock
Turns out to be very soon
Just a matter of pressing
The red button instead of the green button on your account
Was it really just a button the red button you press
It is a red button yeah I think it was a short
Remember how it felt pressing my button
Slightly dangerous
Your normal investing you biased
You can just sit back and wait for the company
Sexy right they have a PR team out there
The company itself is trying to make
The case that it's going to be great
But if you short a company
You got to go out there and make the case that it's overvalued
Simon bet against China
Education Alliance
But he was only going to make money at the stock price drops
Soap
He shouted it to the world he posted a video of the empty building online
And he and his team wrote this really detailed report
That they put out they're basically saying the company was a fraud nothing really sit on 10 a.m. on November 30th 2000
Ben 10
In within 2 hours of stock of the climb
He ended up making a bunch of ma
We have some you know how I feel and he was like good
Were you dancing did you pop champagne if you would just
Rocktown a company and made a fortune
And I really like 10 different times and I think basically he's a pretty even-keeled kind of guy but I also think
There's this other thing
On which is really another way in which the shorting is totally different from normal investing
Your profit
Is really everyone else's loss
There were lots of other people who had invested in this car
Hoping the stock prices going to go up
And now thanks to some
In collapse
I get that it felt weird to celebrate
Yeah they've been bad for a minute I think there's a lot of investors that
You don't picking become blind sighted when we put out these reports and
You guys don't like us for losing the money
Will Saginaw
Your investment company has committed fraud and they should be letting the manager instead of us but
Most guys blame us
There are so many reasons
Not to become a short seller I mean
We have to be ready to be hated by everyone David we have to have some sort of special secret knowledge that were 1%
Picture of you leaving out the best thing
Is there a practical point
Vanderlife
You can lose an infinite amount of money
Infinite I feel like we should pause on that infant
Support for this NPR Podcast in the following message come from Dino the Capital One assistant that catches things that my
Might look wrong with your credit card send you an alert and helps you fix them
Another way they're watching out for your money when you're not what's in your wallet
See capitalone.com for details
It has already been uneventful summer in Polish
Yeah between the 2020 debates
And the president's battle over immigration
There's alot going on
And when there's news you need to know about the NPR politics podcast is there to tell you what
Not to mention we're hitting the road so you can meet all of the 2020 contender
Crazy the NPR politics podcast
Subscribe
This is probably the major reason that people don't
Short because
What you say that you are an optimist that you're buying stock in a company that you hope will go up
And it goes down right what's the most you can lose if you buy $100 worth of stock
You could lose
$100
But if you short sell it is completely
When you short a stock what you're actually doing is
You borrow the stock then you sell it in the hopes
That you can buy back at lower price and return it
Got it
I know Jacob hate that we do this
Let's demonstrate
Robert you have an actual stop
Yeah and until I got this in the mail I didn't know that they still made my day anymore this is a paper
Stock certificate for a small Community Bank in Pennsylvania
It is a gift
To my daughters from their grandmother
Is there a supposed to pay for part of their education
So say I for whatever reason want to short this lovely little boy
Here's how
First I need to borrow a share from someone who has one
At the end it back to you at some
Oh yeah it's for Mike
So I take this borrowed stock
And I sell it
So say the price right now is 10 bucks a share
I pocket that 10
Now I got to give you a share of the bank stock
Back it's a
White denim stripe
So I wait
Hopefully the stock price drops
Then great I can buy one back cheap hopefully for like you know pennies
Any returns talk to you
And we're done
I made a profit
Almost home book
That's the rosy scenario
For you
No the Evangelist put a Beat
Infinite amount of money scenario
Start the same way
I sell it for ten bucks and I wait
But this time instead of a stock price dropping
Let's say it goes up
And let's say it goes
Way up like
The bank has an incredible year some big investor comes in wanted
To expand and say the stock price
Goes up to like 50
Now
You are screwed
David kestenbaum because you owe me that stock and you have to buy that stock
And it's a $50 you have lost
A ton of money or supposed
The stock
Temple
100 hours to buy that stock
To return it to me or $200 or $500 or $1,000
Siri
There is no
Limit to how much you can lose
You can lose an infinite amount of money
Infinite
And how much is in a jar
$6.06
That's life
Hi David let's get out the checklist of things that we need to short a stock number one
The stock we think will go down
At no check we don't have that
Big pile of money
Don't have them
And number three number three heard about this from several people
We need lawyer
Angela tells that he had been sued four times and he told us about this one episode
Where I see you got really really really mad at
And his wife noticed this black truck Park
Parked across the street
And she went out in the cell does Andrew Luck live here
And she said yes
Are they made comment we're friends off and they said the CEO's name they just sat up there
Outside Andrews house in that black truck
I called the CEO right there on the phone I'm like what do you think you're doing this is Wall Street this is business like what we're
World do you live in what do you think
What world do you live in
What did the guy say after you said that to him on the phone
Typical thuggery type stuff you don't know who I am
But what does that mean
I know you are you're the CEO of a publicly traded company
Just
Nonsense
Little David this is exactly the kind of drama
I was worried about
When we started this project
Because
I'm a journalist
Your journalist
How to get our DNA is to be neutral and the premise of this project
Is that we are going to bet against a company we're going to put our money on the line saying that some company is going to fail
Talk about it on the radio and they probably against the NPR ethics
So we spent a while in the office here talk
And we came up with a solution that I was actually really
Excited
Instead of shortening
Particular
We would short
Every
We short the entire stock
Which is not as complicated as it sounds there's a way to do this
Let you know how their index funds which include like a
Tiny piece of lots and lots of stocks
You can buy those turns out you can also sort them
You can bet that the entire stock market
Is Rick back and forth about this we realized
Did this
Is a perfect short because we weren't picking on some
Tiny little company where some CEO is going to call us up and try to bully us
We were picking on the biggest economic Target there is an entire world
The plan would be
Planet Money too short
America
We ran the idea by Sam
Yeah that's a terrible idea
Is very dangerous and it's a great way to lose lots of money
Basically going to the stock market as a reflection of
Aggregate
Prophets of all of
The nation's public company
And every year companies make more profit
I was rushing American companies because
You know I think 40% of Revenue come from outside of the US Siri essentially
Shorting
Global
Corporate profits
As long as populations are growing and there's Innovation companies going to make more money year and you're at
I'm shutting the whole planet
Yeah that's why I usually just work
Something have a name for what we are proposing
He called it
The Armageddon
We definitely had to do
Yeah I think he's trying to talk us out of it but Armageddon trade was perfect as you could picture
Some broker somewhere
Sing
Everything Great and Powerful does ever exist in the world
Eventually goes away
Ottoman Empire
Dawn
Roman Empire destroyed dinosaurs
Disappeared
Before the others
Go with me on this
No one thought
If they would fail
And they did
America
Can't last forever
Sound was not persuaded by the dinosaur on
I ran the idea also by Andrew
He was actually okay with
He said the stock market could go down
Time is right you guys could make
But he was not okay with the term
Shredding amera
You really didn't like it
Do we have problems of course
We have a lot of moving parts
Price for shorting America
I just don't I don't like the way that sounds
We are hands-down
The greatest country in the world to invest in
We've really done an amazing thing in this
Is there a pep talk from a guy who
Specializes in shorting
Get listen that's what part of the amazing part about this country
Is the ability to Short
I mean how great is that that we live in a country cuz you know what
Me to buy stock
You don't like to talk
Beauty short the stock
And that's what we did
ETrade Elite line services
Steven Pearson
I didn't do any Trading
Because shortened can potentially cost you so much I had to stick extra money
Not an infinite
2000 bucks of my own money
Justin Bieber
And we're ready to go
I want to short something
All right
I want to short the entire stock market
The entire stock market
Well
Stevenson I'm not sure we can sure the entire stock market we can come close he said there's this thing that tracks the S&P 500
Has a little slice
Of the 500 largest stock
Let's try that
Minute later
All right
I've got that trade place for you
America
Your bad news
Is now are good
Back by the end of the call the stock market gone down we made a little money how much $0.80
Start
The next show we're going to find out how Robert and David did
And they'll tell the story of what as far as we can tell
Was the very first short ever
It was a surprisingly long time ago
And it does not work out well for the guy trying to do it
Let's just say
He gets a mention on his gravestone
If you like today show and want to support us
Help us grow
Send a podcast to friend
If you have questions or complaints or whatever
We're at Planet Money at npr.org
Or we're on Twitter or Facebook or Instagram
I'm surprisingly good stuff on there
Today Show was produced by Jess Jiang originally
The rerun was produced by Rachel Cohn
Robert Smith
I'm guessing about
And I'm McFadden
This is NPR
Thanks for list