Maybe you've heard that this guy named James holtzhauer is absolutely dominating
You've become a celebrity now because
Of your accomplice
Restaurants on
Jeopardy
Going to be a lot of pressure on
Thank you I appreciate that
Is James's sort of a relic
13 years ago
His only sibling
Ian married my only sibling
And since then I have been
Keenly aware
The James
Is kind of a better version of me
We're the same age but James skipped a grade
We were both math Majors I still have nightmares about it but
James apparently didn't even need to go to class and made money playing online poker in them
Meantime
I went into public radio
James got really good at analyzing Sports data became a very successful Sports gambler
Retired at like 27
Travel the world
Climb Mount Fuji
In a type
And look
I can handle being left
But now
Their nieces and nephews in
Here you are
Usher wait is this recording for sure this is Jack and Scarlett
James and I are there only uncle
And it is irrationally important
That they think I'm the cooler on
And this recording was the moment
I was sure I had one
Jack and Scarlett were visiting me in New York
I let them play video games Zelda breath of
The wild
I had just taking them to the Harry Potter play on Broadway
And now I had gotten them into a real NPR Studio
You interviewed me first
Okay
Hello
So
Jack
Do you have any hobbies
I like playing Minecraft and watching Uncle bunny
Uncle Kenny play Zelda
Watching Uncle Kenny
Play Zelda
Of course 2 months later is when James shows up on Jeopardy
James holshouser is
Health power for 34 years I felt like this isn't going to
Like Kendall care about trivia it's boring to them right
Is Howard James is going to
Find a way to use this National platform to like send messages directly to jackets
Bartlett
Write the game was a runaway for our champion James
Let's see if you came up with the correct response
She had Madonna and happy birthday Scarlett pretty soon you're going to run out of birthday friends
Past month
Necrophilia Uncle War
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Kenny Malone and what makes Uncle Jamie so great at Jeffrey
No seriously
What makes James holzhauer so good at Jeff
Today on the show
I talked to all kinds
Of Jeopardy
To find out what they did to get so good at the show
And about how James Holt tower has
Completely reinvented the game by applying technique
Probability that you developed as a professional gambler
A math prodigy
And you know
The best
Support for this NPR Podcast in the following message come from TD Ameritrade
Investing lesson number one
Don't pay for lessons
TD Ameritrade education is free
So you can use your money for trading
Not learning to trade
No matter what your level
You'll be able to learn what you want
When you want it
Choose from articles videos web cats and in-person events everything you need to take your trading and
Investing knowledge to the next
Level start learning today at tdameritrade.com education
Member sipc
About 10 minutes
That is all we need to get to started every morning
The biggest news stories from politics to pop culture
With the analysis you need to understand what
Listen to up first weekdays
From NPR news
James holzhauer is Las Vegas PSA professional
Sports
April 4th
James episode number
What does that mean exactly this year I like the lightning
I don't really know I'm not look
James has unretired from Gam
Point out here
The Tampa Bay Lightning wound up getting
Crushed
One of the few things James would get wrong on Jeffrey
Play are the highest capital city
Watching this first episode we are all very nerve
The returning Champion is really quite good
It's clear right away
Alex is playing the traditional style
River Jeopardy's played on this giant
And Alex starts in the top row with the easiest least valuable
And finally you're an 11 don't tread on me meme
Alex
Car with highest capital city for 200
Kendra catmandu Kingston
Alex a new capital city for so you know Alex stays in the same category and then moves to the
The next clue slightly harder slightly more.
But as soon as James gets control of the board he does something totally different
James what is Addis Ababa
Yes
Ballpark Cuisine 1000 he goes right to the hardest
Most valuable clue
Game for the Diamondbacks
Yes you three 1000cc jumped to a whole new category again directly to the hardest
Clue and
I'm checking Twitter as this is on TV and parts of Jeopardy Twitter
He changed his style
Jarring it is hard
To play along at home to it
I will later learn
But this style
Isky
How James has been able to rack up unprecedented
So now the last clue
So this first episode is rapping
I Dreamed a Dream from this show
Alex
You're right and that takes you to 18,000 ordinarily that would be remarkable but James has 40
1412 The Runaway game it's a runaway game Alex
James has such a huge lead
But nobody can catch him in finals
Players here's your clue the Jordan bear and Weber Rivers deposit over a million tons of
Minerals into it
Annually
Much of that chloride and sodium
30 seconds good luck
I was aware that at some point James decided to get very good at
He banished other show called
The Chase & Dunn absurd
Believe well but
Cleveland Jeopardy
It is not just about trivia James is using
Some sort of
Strategy or tactic
The question I had was like
What is it actually mean to be good at Jeopardy
What specifically are you
You good at
That was a question I wanted to finance
After of course this episode
Games
I turn this game into a runaway
Did he get the correct response though
Apopse the Great Salt Lake on his
I most certainly did but Uncle Jamie
Has written a little extra
Happy birthday Jack alright
Is a version of Myra
And your wager will add 3268
March 26th
Jack's birthday
James and I share four
And happy birthday
Hate is an happy birthday we're down to
You get to each of them
At least ones happy birthday Scarlett again
You ready to go you want to roll I am
Recording now
I'm Ken Jennings
Ken Jennings is the greatest Jeopardy champion of all time
But to understand what made him great
You have to understand that he got on the show Eddie
Key moment in it
For the first 20 years of Jeopardy contestants will get bounced after winning five times
A car
And Sia
And there's a car
Drive Away literally get in the car and
We don't want to see you again
And they change their format to which is indefinite
After I tried out in 2003
Before I went on the show
Ken says anecdotally he heard the show was like because someone one I don't know
10 game
Kenwood win a lot more
And let's be clear
It's partly because he is better than an average
Contestant
At trivia
According to Ken himself that advantage
Marginal
Because by the time people get on Jeopardy they're very good most contestants know most of the
The answers
It's according to Ken
The biggest ant
Is the ability
To buzz in
Before everyone else
The deal with the Buzzard feathers not live until Alex finishes reading the question
For your brother
Girls like you actually lock yourself out
For a fraction of a second so the big mistake on the show is people who are all adrenalized
And are buzzing too quick
Some degree Jeopardy is kind of
A video game
Had a crappy video game where it's like light goes on press button
That's it is that true I do like to think of it as a beautiful art
And not a really crappy video game
When does the art comes in with internalizing the rhythm of Alex
Kangaroo up in South
Korea and he says the only english-language station there
Play Jeopardy right after
What's a young age
Like a second language almost
Scan Inc
Turtle eyes Dalek
Alex Trebek voice
How he reads
Clues what it sounds like when he's about to finish reading
So when can get on Jeopardy he is very good at the buzzer
He is getting in first
On 60% of the clues
And then the more he wins the more practice he gets on the buzzer
And the new contestants they are just like Lambs to the slaughter
After 48 win
The show steps in
And institutes more in-depth buzzer
And I really did make a difference as soon as they did that you could see the attitude Gap really lower and the market became a lot more competitive
Do they tell you that they're going to do this
Are you pissed
I don't think anyone ever said hey Ken were going to let the challengers practice more he did not anger me I was flattered
You know it's like
It's like the NBA adding different like Lane violations to stop Wilt Chamberlain from
Doing those tippens
Can wound up winning
2 point
$5000000
Over 74 straight Jeopardy
No one has come
You can close the next closest
Is James
Who's currently at 22 game
So arguably
The increase buzzer training has
Evened out the car
But Savvy players
Practice the buzzer be
Before they get on the show
They know
The Jeopardy
Is a trivia game second
And it kind of crappy video game
James episode number four
We need to talk about daily.
Professional Gambler who's used to betting large amounts
If he hits those Daily Doubles
Watch out Daily Doubles are the hidden clues that let a player wager as much of their money as
Three of these per game
And in this game
James found every
Single
Yes architecture 804 there for Daily Double this was not a
I've been watching James at this point for 4 episode
And he consistently found most of the Daily Doubles like
At a rate that seem statistically impossible
And then when he found them
He would wager enormous amount of his money
So this Daily Double for exam
This is late in the game
James has a huge
And lots of contested in this situation would wager like nothing
Preserve the lead
And keep that money it will turn into real money if you win
But in this case
James Betts so much
You can hear one of the audience members whistle in disbelief 25000
All right
Here's the clue
In Andalusia
Arabic
Calligraphy
Represents
This style
Name for medieval visitors from Africa
What is Moorish Moriches right
James did not miss a single Daily Double clue
Throughout this day
He had that huge
And as a result at the end of the first two rounds
Kewanee huge amount of my
James what is Austin you are right that's okay to 17600
Trebek says
The one-day record
Is 77 fast
Hahaha
Final Jeopardy coming up
Ironically
It's a metaphor meaning a huge step forward
But this to word process
Only occurs on a subatomic scale
30 seconds good luck
James is going to break this
But what will make headlines the next day
Is how brutally
Thoughtfully
James breaks the one-day record
70 mm
600 going into final for you James
We need to find Quantum Leap
We do happy birthday
Badger booger booger his nickname for his daughter
How much did you risk 38000 314 a new one day record 100
10914 and only had James destroyed the existing Jeopardy record
He wagered so that the new record
Would be his daughter's birthday
1109 40
November 9th
He's back tomorrow Jonas
How are you feeling about the about the record falling
I'm
You know I'm totally cool with the record falling I think it's
Great Rodger Craig won $77,000 in a single Jeopardy game
The record
The James obliterate
A lot of people texted me or called me or whatever and said
Condolences and they were really sad and I was like
I get to just say I've the highest scored other than James holzhauer so that's going to be my claim to fame there
Rodger will also always be famous as one of the first players to approach Jeopardy as a data probe
An approach that
Was impossible until
There was Data let's start with a
The Jeopardy archive
Sure the Jeopardy archive is it's an online website
Dad all these super fans God bless them created they have tapes of the show
And put all the questions and answers into a web page for each episode of Jeopardy
I'm going to pull it up here
Okay
Like episode oh my
It's laid out like a board and then if you mouse-over
The dollar amount of the clue it will reveal the answer
This is incredible
So I knew about it in
To either 2005 or
You know it's very soon after
Decided to scrape it
Download the website
Download every single
Clue yes there were two hundred thousand
250000 I think now it's up to
The 300,000 250000 that's right
Rodger has a PhD in
Computer science
And he was curious like
Now that I've downloaded
All of Jeopardy
What categories
Is the show
Julie ask
So the most frequently at a high level is history geography literature
Not not surprising probably I guess those those
3A that's the bread and butter
The show says you can vent dig down into those categories
Within history you need to know America
Then within that you need to know the president
Backwards and forwards
Equally important
This analysis showed Rodger that kind of stuff
That wouldn't be worth his time to stop
That's right so it's much more important to know
Abraham Lincoln
In Phantom of the Opera then it is to know all the cheeses that
They might ask
The Jeopardy archive is a huge Innovation it is allowed a whole new generation
Players
To hunt
Ferdie's exploitable parts of the game
So here's all my scraping code luckily I just ran it once it took like
Half an hour I was like I'm going to go
Wake make some dinner come back I think this will be done in just a half an hour
Send me the recipe
This is Monica to she won Jeopardy's 2012 college tournament
As a high schooler taking college classes
Per half-hour dish by the way
Cacio e Pepe
So what I'm going to do here
Should work
Twan
Well laptop
You can have it
Monica is showing
How she scraped
10 seasons of Jeopardy archive
How to look at Daily
Are they placed random
Is there a pattern
So should we go to do is look this top row to see
Deletable never comes up in the top row
Turned out Daily Doubles
Not randomly distributed at all actually you can see this same pattern top upset
Bro3 Andro400 most likely to have Daily Double
Daily Doubles are way more likely
To show up
In the row
With the second hardest Clues
And the rug with a third heart
And if you know this
You can go Daily Double hunting
Bouncing from category
The category in the second and third to last
Monica has used this strategy
Rodger Craig use this during his wreck
Game
Is also the key
Two James Holt hours
This
Is how he seems to find
A magical number
Up daily
Dope James episode number 80
Things are starting to get absurd
Alex Trebek Just Darts the show this way gentlemen and welcome everyone for the James
Holzhauer show
James episode number 19 he wins so profoundly that one of his opponents
Write this in finals
I will for delivery Woodshed 7400
Her response was
What is congratulations to gain yeah I know the feeling
Hey I started FaceTiming with my sister brother-in-law
The kids during
It is sincerely the best part of James is
Occasionally does just turn into Uncle Jamie is awesome
Today Concepts
Do teacher told a kid he should go on Jeopardy like
James guy
In a 3 year old weigh
What's her turn mean
Oh my God
It is hard to overstate just how dominant James
He is still on the show
It's just on break right now for the teachers
Cement butt
As of this writing
James has won 22 straight
+ 1.7 million
$10 he is averaging
Nearly $77,000 and episode
Nearly as much as Roger Craig
Old record the Louvre with it
What is Mona Lisa
Okay hold on my brother-in-law
We have this tradition where we pause the game right before finals
Maybe try and figure out
Whose birthday James will wager
Based on his lead and what he
He can safely bet
Yeah
I don't know why
After the break
We talk
To Uncle Jiang
Support for this podcast and the following message
Come from goo
From Connecticut to California
From Mississippi to Minnesota
Millions of businesses are using Google tools
Instagrow online
Learn how Google is supporting businesses in your state
Add google.com economic impact
What would you do if you found out a story that is shaped
Your identity
Was a lie
NPR news podcast
White Lies investigates murder in Selma Alabama
Nineteen
55in exposes the
Conspiracy the
Kept it on song
Until now
White Lies start listening to
You do remember I don't even remember what the how good your memory on White 2
The answer actually wasn't the first the first episode the answer was Great Salt Lake
Yeah and then you wrote
Arrow happy birthday Jack
I believe Alex Trebek was like and happy birthday Jack alright
And I was just like a like this is a whole new level of thing that I
I can't talk
I will tell you I went to go visit the kids the week before I was on Jeopardy and they still accidentally referred to me as Uncle Kenny a good 20
I think you're doing just okay
It's sweet of him to say of course all of that is
Before he was on
James has been trying to get on Jeopardy since 2011
He's taking the online test like 13 times
The culprit in person auditions once for Sports Jeopardy twice for real Jeopardy
And then finally
Last January he got the car
Congrats you have three weeks to prepare
2 Chainz with queue Up episodes of Jeopardy
Play along at home with a makeshift
Mechanical pencil buzzer
Wearing shorts but also
The dress shoes
He was going to wear on the show I think that was
Possibly more important preparation that actually learning any facts or figures the buzzer timing
I think making sure you're comfortable
In your elements and also I discovered I really needed dr. Scholl's insoles for my dress shoes so
Assuming at this point in your career you're not wearing dress shoes
The tremendous amount
No on game shows and maybe weddings
You didn't see them on TV that's the stupid jeans and tennis shoes
Comfortable but
They said no
When you talk to other Jeopardy champ
Beans about Jane
They will say that
He is the quintessential modern
He's great at the buzzer and getting better
Jane says Guitar Hero
Help with that
He's got an absurdly broad knowledge
Jane Says
He studies the kid books for
Only what he needs to know
Plus pictures
But the way James has broken Jeopardy
Is how he is using daily.
Because
To a gambler
A daily double
Is an absurdly good deal that would be irrational to bet smaller
This requires a bit of explanation
Patience
Remember the Daily Double allows James
To wager the money he's
For every dollar he bets
If you get the clue correct
She wins a dollar
Bet 10000
Win 10000
And that has like a name in
Gambling Harlan's right
Yeah we call it even money proposition when you get paid the same amounts for winning as you will lose for losing
Bet a dollar make a dollar at a casino
Is usually the payout for
Playing roulette and betting on
1 black
Just about half the time black is going to come up
About half
The time it won't
Even money payouts are four things that are like a coin toss
That's where you're going to be wrong about half
Sing about a daily double
It's paying out
Even money as if
The players going to get it wrong half
What's the time
That's definitely not true for most players and it is
Certainly not
For James
Add
You know what my career if I find any money proposition that wins 52% of the time I'm very happy
Where is jeopardy the average contestant gets
70% of their Daily Doubles right
You know I
Think that I have to be over 80% so if I found out personal life out of my work out as much at the Sportsbook with let me
You go borrow my me it's kind of thing you if you could borrow money to do it if you like this is probably
Exactly
Getting a daily double with no money
Is relatively useless
And this
Is why James does that
Kind of crazy thing at the beginning of every show
He intentionally avoids the rose wear Daily Doubles
Tend to be
But he does not start
With the easiest
Least valuable
What I do that's different than anyone came before me is I will try to build the pot first you know the
Daily Doubles actually don't come up that much in the thousand-dollar clues but those
Star where the big money is obviously in
Maybe the opponents are not ready
For this
Dance of the big money questions right away they don't feel comfortable with it
You know what's in my comfort zone
South Pasadena dad is there
Indian ideal game then James
This would work his way across the bottom thousand-dollar row
Rack up money while he's at
Opponents are still
Kind of in a daze
Then you find a daily double
And bet everything
Within 5 minutes
Play
He has opened up an insurmountable
And you can see James manage his risk
Based on how much game is
So early on he'll take
Huge shots because
The upside is that he can basically put the game away
The downside
Is yeti losing a lot
There is a ton of game left
He's very good
Probably catch up
Towards the end of the game though
James is more risk-averse
There's less time to recover from a bad
By the way
This is how you're supposed to manage your retirement
Riskier stocks when you're younger
Safer bonds when you're heading into
James
Sports gambler
Has a different amount
I get mad at
Football coaches who are afraid to call for a big play Early in the game you know because they they want to
Still be in the game at the end then it turns out they have no chance for the
Hail Mary or something similar to that at the end yeah they would have done better day
Do some more gambling earlier
For me it's about gambling earlier so I don't have to sweat Final Jeopardy so much
Yeah well look man I am I am
99.9% of the time just very happy for you look at it this way if I lose to Ken Jennings and their Deathmatch
That's maybe we'll both be second and third place to Uncle Ken after that
Family I just did
I think we'll just put together a concerted effort to stop that
We would love to hear how you or anybody else
Crack the difference
Game show UK
Email us we are Planet Money at npr.org
We are at Planet Money on Instagram and Twitter
Today's episode was produced by Darian woods Alex goldmark is Planet Money supervising producer Bryant
Headed to the show
Special thanks this week to Andy Saunders who runs the amazing website the Jeopardy fan, which is where I go
Buzz in statistics
And also to Matthew amster-burton
And I just want to say Ken Jennings has a new book out it is called
Planet
Funny
Not consciously
Inspired by planet
We got a new newsletter you cancer
Describe at npr.org Planet Money
I'm Kenny Malone
Thanks for listening
Hey sorry everybody
My apologies
Gyros
Like a knight
Can I ask a quick favor that I near me.
I can give you the long back story but my guy Roz
Ghost of a podcast called how I
This they put our shows together and put
Radio
So during this James
I was
Whining to my sister about being gay
Uncle
And she goes
At least you know guy Roz
Why do the kids care about guy Roz
Because
Kyroz
The kids podcast
Call wow in the world
Apparently the nieces and nephews
Loveloud
Love guy Roz perfect
Hey Scarlett is Guy Rozier
Birthday messages for every
Hey Pete is skyrise here from Wow in the world
And I
Just got out of the time machine
Only to do
Discover that it is your birthday
So happy birthday to you Mindy sends her regards and so does Reggie and Dennis and
Logang
I'm well in the world
Hey guy in that time machine who have you learned anything about
I don't know jeopardy or anything
Now and I haven't even heard of it