Support for Planet Money
And the following message come from Michigan Economic Development Corporation Cy Michigan is attracting top talent
And pop businesses by searching Michigan pure opportunity
Just a quick warning there's a little profanity
In today's show
In 1958
Jimmy Lai was 10 years old
He lived in southern China and he made money carrying suitcases at the local train
One day a guy garage
The train and told Jimmy he just come in from Hong Kong
Jimmy heard stories about Hong Kong before
It was supposed to be this magical unbelievably wealthy play
But you know Jimmy figured whatever people tell store
Jimmy was carrying the guys bags for the station that the guy started eating a chocolate
When they got to where they were going Jimmy put the guys bags down and the guy gave Jimmy the rest of the chalk
So I turned my back and tried it
And I said shut up
Wow what's this
He said chocolate
I said wow Hong Kong Must Be Heaven
You never tasted chocolate before
I never heard about
So I'd that moment not determined I'm going to escape
To Hong Kong
Escape to Hong Kong in the late 50s Hong Kong was not part of China it was a British colony
And this was a moment when China was closed off from the rest of the world
Chinese people were not allowed to set foot outside the country without special permission
From the governor
From the Chinese Communist Party
The party was radically remaking
They had Force Farmers to give up their land and work on Collective Farms
And partly as a result
At this moment when Jimmy Lai first taste of chocolate
China was in the middle of a famine that would kill tens of Millions
Soap to get out of China
Jimmy found a Smuggler
Who hit him in the bottom of a fishing boat
With a few dozen other people
They left around midnight and we're in Hong Kong the next after
He didn't have any money he had to go that night to start working at a glove Factory people like
12 and a half years
But the next morning
As he walked through the streets around the factory
So all these
Little food stamp
Ordinary People you know
Poor Factory workers like him
We're eating these big bowls of noodles and rice porridge
Food was just
Everywhere
Food everywhere and then the people sitting with you was
Cheerful
Such a beauty Norman on for me
That's when he realized that all the stories he heard about Hong Kong
They were true
I knew that moment
I'm in a different world
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Jacob Goldstein
Hong Kong is this sort of impossible play
It's this capital city with a free press and freedom of assembly and an independent judicial
Also
Hong Kong is part of China
A country with none of those
Jimmy Lai is an embodiment of all of that
He's one of the richest people in Hong Kong and also one of the loudest critics of the Chinese guy
Today on the show
The story of Jimmy Li is the story of Hong Kong
And the story of Hong Kong
Is the story of the 200-year relationship between China and the West
I mean
This message comes from NPR sponsor Microsoft
As an apex predator
The presence of snow leopards informs us about the health of their environment
That's why the snow leopard trust has turned to Microsoft AI to find and study these elusive at
Animals with AI
It only takes minutes to analyze thousand
Since I've remote camera images
And understand where these animals are
So researchers have more time to protect them and their ecosystem
See how
Ed microsoft.com AI
It has already been uneventful summer in politic
Yeah between the 2020 debate and the president's battle over immigration
There's alot going on
And when there's news you need to know about the NPR politics podcast is there to tell you what
Not to mention we're hitting the road so you can meet all of the 2020 contender
Ompl is going to drive me completely crazy
Dianping
Podcast subscribe
To really understand the story of Jimmy Li and of Hong Kong and China and the West
You have to go back to the 1830
At the time China was almost entirely closed
If you are a traitor from Europe
Orphan the US
It was only one place in China you are allowed to go
Town in southern China that westerners called
Canton
Actually foreigners weren't even really allowed Encanto
I talked about this with Stephen Platt
A historian at the University of Massachusetts
The foreigners had to make do with
A little tiny compound about 12 acres
Outside of the city down and serve a muddy spot by the river
So why would these traitors sale halfway around the world to stay in a muddy 12-acre compound down by the river
To get rich
It was an incredibly lucrative trade basically the world source of tea at that point in time
Time was entirely from China in Canton what's the only place you could buy it
12 acres was it was
The center of an engine for the world economy essentially
But these traders who are getting rich in their little 12-acre compound
Started to bump up against a problem
The world and especially Britain wanted all this
But China didn't want that much stuff from the world
For a while Traders were just paying for the tea with silver
So much so that all the silver just started flowing into China
Eventually the traitors did find a product that the Chinese really were
Opium
The British Traders became big-time International drug kingpin
Which then is now was a very profitable
They started ramping up opium production in India
I'm shipping it over it illegal to China where it was being sold off of the coast to wholesalers
And opium had become the largest for an import into China
End it
Had in fact undone the trade imbalance
To the point that the British were not only getting all the tea that they wanted but now they were starting to drain all the silver out of China
Opium was illegal in China but until this time
The government had sort of look the other way
Then as more and more people became opium addicts
And a silver started leaving the country
Deborah was like okay enough
He said one of his top advisors a guy named Lindsey shoot down to camp
Want to try and crack down on Oak
The British Traders opium is on ships
Dinner options
It's not there in the car
Linda Shu he got second on and what he did was
He walked up the British merchants
In that 12 acre compound
And he said
I'm not going to let you out and I'm not going to let you trade anything else
Until you give me all your oppa
There is a British
Admiral who is in charge of trade at
His name is Charles Elliott
And he wants to settle
So he says to the traitors
Okay
The British government will buy all of your open from you if you just turn it off
So they signed entire season Supply over to him
And then Admiral Elliott gave this mountain of opium to Lynn's issue
Who dumped it all in the
Who destroyed
We're gets back to London about what
But the British government does not send 2 million pounds to make good on Admiral Elliott
Instead
The British send warships to force China to pay for the confiscated
The fact that this was a war fought over
Illegal drug dealers was not at all
Holden started calling it
The Opium War
But by the time it ended
It was about way more than
By the time the war ends in 1842 it's turned into something much much bigger than what Elliott had believed
Britain had any kind of a right to
Turn into a wart a forced China open to British trade
In the treaty that ended the war
The British demanded not only their 2 million pound
They also made China let foreign Traders into a bunch of foreign
Canton and
Also Shanghai
And also a few others
And the British decided
We don't want to run the risk of some Chinese emperor locking up our trade
We need our own base of operations
We need a little British colony
So they made China give them this little rocky Island
Write off
The coast of Southern
Hong Kong
This is the beginning of what China calls its
Century of humiliation
Up until this time countries in the west had thought of China as this rich
Powerful Empire
Now they saved it can be pushed around
The Germans in the French get their own Colonial concessions from China
In 1898
Britain makes China give them a chunk of the land on the mainland of China
Across from Hong Kong
It's about 300 square miles
They call this piece the new tariff
And this particular land grab the British say is not forever
It's for 99 years
They say they will give the new territories back
In 1990s
When the British took over Hong Kong was this rural
2000 fishermen and farmers
But then
In the 1850s a civil war broke out on the mainland
And Hong Kong became a place people started fleeing to from China
There's a huge amount of fighting and it really vicious government Crackdown in South China
In a lot of wealthy Cantonese start moving to Hong Kong to be under the protection of the British
And it becomes a place where they can conduct their trade outside of the Civil War area
Tom and from there it really takes off
This really is the Hong Kong where Jimmy Lee climbs out of the bottom of that boat
In 19
This trading center
That is attached to Mainland China
That was created in the sort of
Original sin of the Opium War
That exists under the laws and Norms of the British Empire
And that has been populated mostly by people like Jimmy
People have fled China and the descendants of those
So you work in the factory
What making clothes is that what you're
Lithograph
Gloves making process
And you were like running a sewing machine or what are you doing
The first I was sweeping the floor all cleaning business
No umentary you know that
Betray me to be amateur so are you know I'm operating at the knitting machine
Yeah he works his way up and by 21 he's running a factor
Hong Kong by this point has become an International Financial
Place where lots of Western money flows on its way to a
And Jimmy start speculating in the Hong Kong stock
I need as well
He makes enough money to go in with a partner and buy a fact
Like a lot of factories in Hong Kong at the time
Is factory made clothes for foreign retailer
NECC spring companies
And selling it acute
Anythink
I should be the one selling at that
Joey decides to start a retail clothing
He doesn't know what to call it
Until he goes on a business trip to New Year
He's meeting with a clothing importer here in New York
And on the way out of the off
One of his friends at the company gives in this like
This little treat for the road
One of the importing company
Somebody
Supplication beer
Chocolate
Biscuit you know like cookie cookie cookie
Buy portable charger
Chocolate with
Some marijuana dick
So I thought I took it I was
So high I was so hungry after I ate it I never was that hungry
So I just went into
A piece of pie
Okay
A piece of paper
So you know what the napkin that I clean my mouth I just put it into my pocket
Tobacco
Went went
What's haidian Twilight
So this morning when I woke up I was at that time I was thinking about the name for for the retaining strap that I'm going to end
I'm going to stop
Giordano
The name of the pizza
I want that's great you know people would think that I'm a
Is that a true story
Yes that's if it seems too good to be true
I wanted to be
Yeah I Twilight
It's not too good to be true because when
Bright white was not very well at UK's a uniform meter thing about
A brand name is not easy
Sure Express 3
I think it's stupid idea to two
Do you sleep
Italian names and thinking that people will assume YouTube
Retarded friend
By that time you know
Okay what the hell do I know
Jimmy launches Giordano in 1981
Eventually there will be Giordano clothing stores in more than 30 countries around the world
Giordano will make Jimmy
Is Jimmy is building Giordano in the
There is like this Cloud hanging over his feet
In 1997 Britain is supposed to give the new territories in Hong Kong back to
But in China almost everything still belong to the government
Most of China
You just could not be a rich entrepreneur like Timmy
At the same time though the British Empire was basically over
Britain was like
Getting out of the business of being a colonialist
But they were governed as a straight-up colony
Run by a British Governor appointed by the Queen of England
Controlled by British law
An extraordinary thing is how well it's
Hong Kong had become like this essential node between Asia and the West
So that by the late 20th century
People in Hong Kong we're not only profoundly better off than people in mainland China
People in Hong Kong were richer on average
Then people in Great Britain
Soap in the early eighties
Is the British prime minister Margaret Thatcher and the Chinese leader Deng Xiaoping
Start needing to figure out what to do about hunk
Patrick told dumb
Of course will give you back the new territories like we promised
But we never said anything about Hong Kong Island
Tolchester what if we just
Hold on to that
Here is Thatcher years later describing dunks
Icon
I said yes
Dakota
There's nothing I can do to stop
But the eyes of the world
China was like
Everything would leave Hong Kong
Angel song
Lustrelux
Just to be clear this is Great Britain lecturing China about how it would look bad to take Hong Kong
Song by force
Deng Xiaoping was in some ways a practical
He was introducing capitalism in mainland China
And he knew that workers in capitalist Hong Kong were much more productive and had a much higher standard of living
Then workers on the Communist man
He didn't want to mess that up
So in 1984
Dumb and Thatcher met Daddy
Great Britain would agree to give all of Hong Kong back to China in 1990
And China would agree to basically let Hong Kong
Keep being its own special thing governed by its own special laws
For 50 years
Until two thousand forty seven
And then
At midnight on July 1st 1997
It happened
There was Prince Charles all the people of Hope
Phone call who have been such a stone
I'm special friends
I was so many generation
There was Chinese president jiang zemin
Junk drawer
Jungian CNN.
At midnight they lowered the British flag
They raised the Chinese flag
And that was it
155 years after the end of the Opium War
Hong Kong
A place as devoted as any on Earth
Capitalism and free trade
Was part of communist China
After the break
What the Handover meant
Virginia Lottery
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Capital One
Brought to you by the Capital One Venture Card
When you earn Unlimited
Two double miles on every purchase
Your next trip is closer than you think
What's in your wallet
Planet Money as a weekly email newsletter
If you subscribe now you will soon get an email from us telling you the story
How Leonardo DiCaprio
First helped and then hurt the economy
EBay small Beach town in title
You can subscribe
Npr.org
Planet Money newsletter
That's npr.org
Splash Planet Money news
By the time Britain handed Hong Kong back to China
Jimmy Lai was running a new kind of company
A kind of company that made this a dangerous moment
Few years earlier he'd been inspired by the tiananmen square Pro
Who wanted among other things more freedom of speech and less censorship in mainland China
And after the Chinese government
Declare martial law and killed hundreds of the protest
Testors Jimmy started a pro-democracy media company in Hong Kong
I said look
The best way to use my money is to go into the media
Because
To deliver
Information
Is actually delivering
Liberty
Let's go into the
Freedom Fest
When the Handover happened in 1997
Jimmy was running a Weekly Magazine and a major Daily newspaper in Hong Kong
Both of them were openly critical of the Chinese
Were you worried you're going to get arrested then
Next day
That never happened
I know it didn't happen but you didn't know the futuristic no I don't know the future but I just
I just
Lift My Life
Day by day
What was the day like for the first day when
Hong Kong is no longer a British colony and is now a special administrative region of
Nothing change
Venetucci
I'm sure people
People wear
Apprehensive about what's going to happen
Yeah okay but nothing changed and did you think still
You know I feel like the conventional wisdom in the West
At least at that time was
Well China is getting richer and we know that when countries get richer they become
More democratic and get civil freedoms
Is that what you thought that's what we for
But that'll cost
Do you happen
China has not allowed more freedom of speech
Publications can still be shut down for criticizing the cover
And yet China has gotten richer it started to develop its own Financial Center in Shanghai
Foreign money Canal flow into China without going through Hong Kong
So the Chinese Communist Party
Doesn't need Hong Kong as much as it used to
This has led to more and more tension
Between people in Hong Kong
And the Chinese Communist Party the Chinese
In 2014 there was a fight over how to choose the government official who runs Hong Kong
And a million people in Hong Kong took to the streets to protest
Just last month the government official who runs Hong Kong wanted to pass a new law that would allow people in Hong Kong to the x
Extradited to China to stand trial
The people in Hong Kong said
We don't trust your Mainland courts
2 million people protested in the streets
Including by the way Jimmy Li
Who is now in his seven
What was it like what was it like walking
When you see so many people
It is fighting
Emmolo issue
We don't have guns
We can have 10 we don't have anything
The only thing we have the Chinese government done is the model of 42 we have the moral courage we have
The moral Authority encourage you
Two weeks later on July 1st
On the anniversary of Hong Kong's return to Chinese rule
Protesters broke into the Hong Kong legislature building
Smashed glass walls
And spray-painted
Chinese leaders see these protesters
And Jimmy life for that matter as agents for foreign in
You know basically Latter-Day colonialist
His house has been firebombed and there was an assassination plot
Against him
I stop thinking about him
Just because I let the fear
Frighten me
I cannot go alone
You know because
With
What happened
I have
To substandard
I will be the last to leave
That is like a captain who cannot jump the ship
I mean you're you're rich
You could leave if you want
Yeah if I leave I'm rich but I'm an a******
What what what my kiss Roofing about
Being rich
You can be very poor
Go on
Play more because
If you only have money
You lost the meeting you lost addicted to you lost everything as a human being
What else do they have
In the end the big risk that Jimmy lie on the Hong Kong protesters posed to Beijing
It's not really about Hong Kong
Itself
Fat people on the mainland could look at Hong Kong
Hey
We're going to break some windows to
We're going to start protesting he
If that happens
Beijing could send in the tanks in Hong Kong
And shut down the protest
You can email us we're at Planet Money at
Npr.org on Facebook and Instagram and Twitter at Planet Money Today Show was produced by Darian Woods
Alex goldmark is our supervising producer
And Brian urstadt is our editor
Special thanks to Samuel Mark and some Chan and David Webb all of them spoke to me at length about
Stephen Platt the historian I talked to on the show wrote a book about the Opium War
It is called Imperial Twilight
The Opium War
The end of China's last golden age
I'm Jacob Goldstein this is NPR thanks for listen