Vanessa Hall Harper seems like one of those
People who are always in a hurry always
Rushing
She walks into the public library in North Tulsa Oklahoma caring this holder that is
Completely staffed with papers
Yep this is my Bible
In that folder is everything that Vanessa Hall Harper needed
To fight the fight of her life
So it's just everything
Totally unorganized
Vanessa is from North Tulsa and there's one issue that's been on her mind
4 years
North Tulsa
Does not have a gross
Got plenty of churches in
Liquor stores like most
You know disenfranchised communities
Vanessa works
In public health
And so she knows that people who live in North Tulsa
Die 12 years earlier than people who live in self
And food is apart of
She decides to run for City Council on a platform
Promising to
Bring a grocery store to North Tulsa
I started
Noticing
That anytime there was any development whatsoever
In my community it was a it was a discount.
And I'm trying to figure out what is going on
Dollar Store
They keep popping up in North
Literally within a few blocks of each
And they were just popping up popping up popping up
I'm saying this has to have an effect
On the ability of a grocery store
To come in
NBC
Successful because even though dollar stores are not grocery stores
They do sell groceries like pasta and cereal and yeah those things that are horrible for you
Diabetes and all those
Yes
Dollar stores don't usually sell fruit
Or vegetables or meat
That is not where the profit is
Grocery say they don't make the real money selling
Carrots and lettuce they make the real money selling twinkies and Cheetos in like
Paper towels
And dollar stores
They really only sell those
High-profit items
So at this point there are already
$10 stores in Vanessa's District
End in XI dollar store is asked
Sushi slike
Hold on
Let's not approve this just yet
I actually think this is going to make it
Harder for me to get a girl
Grocery store in here
That was a couple of councilors of like what there's no studies to show that what you're saying is is accurate
I don't need no damn study
Okay I have common sense hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Sarah Gonzales
Can I know Elle King
Today on the show
Should we hate
Dollar Store
This year a brand new dollar store will open up
Every six
Hours
They're more than $30,000 stores in the United
That's more than there are Walmart
McDonald's and CVS stores combined dollar stores are everywhere and they are sitting up in places that
No one else will go
Tiny towns urban areas
So are they feeling a need
Or is the Dollar Store take over destroying something more valuable
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Wix.com
With wix
You can create a professional website for your business
Choose a template design for your industry
Free and customize it to match your brand
With Ascend by Wix you can easily connect with your site visit
Capture leads and manage all of your customer relations from one place
Get started now and get the all-in-one Business Solution
Go to wix.com that's wilx.com money to get 10% off
When you're searching for a home to buy and you finally find one that's perfect it just feels amazing it's like
This is the house
But then is also the financial part of me is like
Can you forward this life cat is here to help we're going to Hold Your Hand
Beard guy to this home-buying journey
Check a life get an Apple podcast sword npr.org
Flashlight
Okay Vanessa Hall Harper has $10 stores in North Tulsa and she wants to consider preventing it
And 11th from coming
I didn't all of Tulsa just in her District
The Northside
But she needs the support
The whole city
Instead the local Chamber of Commerce calls her anti-business
And Vanessa's like I'm not anti-business I'm just saying we should have at least one other type of this
I was told this is illegal you can't do this
Daddy know I don't think it's possible I think this is illegal you know we're going to get sued and blah blah blah
And I don't care about getting sued as long as we won
And that's not necessarily the
The position of some
People and blue department and I get it you know they don't want to invite
Litigation
But
And my opinion is I told him that your job
You did this is called the legal department
It's your job to protect
Do you have a lot of friends in
City government
Yes I have a lot of friends a lot of free
Not
Cities don't like to just say no to new business
So they approve the 11th
Dollar Store the one that Vanessa was fighting
And her reaction is hilarious
She starts protesting outside telling people
Don't come to this Dollar Store
At least go to the one across
We never wanted
This one day even though she had lost the 11th Dollar Store battle
She was still fighting the dollar store
I said really
Software to do my research
There are three main dollar store chains
Dollar Tree sets up in the suburbs everything they sell cost exactly $1
And Family Dollar and Dollar General open up in urban and rural area
They sell everything from canned foods
Too close and
Toaster oven
Not all for a dollar but generally added it
They're like mini Walmarts for towns Walmart ignore
And dollar stores also employed
If you were p
If you don't need someone making sure the chicken didn't go bad or the tomatoes are not shriveled up
You can operate with
Much leaner staff
On average dollar stores employ nine people when local grocery stores employee 40
The dollar store that is growing the fastest
Is Dollar General
They have 15000 472 stores in this country that was as of March
March 1st
By comparison Walmart has about 5000
Dollar General turn down our request
For a recorded interview but they did tell us
That they know they're cuss
And that their customers are only willing to travel about three to five miles to shop
With them and that is why they open up stores so close to each other
And all of this could mean that the market is
People are shopping at Dollar Stores voting for what they want
With their dollars
But sometimes
People vote for what they want
With their votes
At The Ballot Box
And in North Tulsa they elected Vanessa Hall Harper
Specifically to bring a grocery
Vanessa keeps building her case that
Dollar stores keep grocery stores from surviving
And she finds out about a guy in the town of Haven Kansas
A couple hours now
Doug net
My title was president
Your table now
Funky
Clean up guy so
Doug is unlocking what's left of his grocery store
Wow I don't think I've ever seen it
Empty grocery store
The deceased to have a
Bananas
Onion remnants
Onion petals on the bottom
This was the only grocery store in town
Haven Kansas has about a thousand Reza
It's a Tiny Town surrounded by fields
And for Dollar General
It was a perfect Market
Most of their stores are in towns with less
Then 20,000 resume
They set up point
3 miles
From Doug store
The first day Dollar General open we lost
Almost 7
Hundred dollars in sales
Veterinary not advertise any
Beijing today
And Doug would go in and he would walk around the Dollar General he would check out the competition
I'd look at their prices I happen to notice one day that they were selling at 14 and a half ounce can of Campbell's chick
Chicken noodle soup Cambridge
Soup
$4
So I come back down here and I call
My warehouse caught this new guy and says this same can is costing me
From my supplier
Freight delivered
To the store here
About a dollar fifty
And mine is only 11 1/2 ounces
He called his Campbell Soup represent even asking
Why is this about we only make
Get for them
And we only make it in 14 1/2 ounce can
Specifically for Dollar General
Zip code for Dollar General
Dollar General Buys in bulk so Campbell's will make some things for them cheaper
Does cheaper products are great for regular shoppers
But they are not great for duck
People were still shopping at Doug's
The store though he had held on to 70% of his business
They were choosing to spend a lot of their grocery money
With Doug although to put it another way
He had lost about a third of his business
We just went down and it was nothing ever we never
Whenever
Popped up
He couldn't keep the lights on
Had to close
Pho always just hates Eclipse you tell me
I've stood I've said here for 972 days or whatever losing $700 a day
In sales
What do you want me to do what can I do
For Vanessa Hall Harper back in North Tulsa
This was the perfect
Dollar Store horse
But she needed hard evidence of a connection
And then
One big grocery store chain gave her the evidence
They were interested in coming to North Tulsa
But they actually told them
If you're just going to have dollar stores popping up constantly forever in this District it might not be worth it
They had written this letter and I'll read it
While we welcome healthy company
It is our opinion that a market oversaturated with small convenience
Type dollar stores would negatively affect honor capital
Ability
Shoe stores throughout Tulsa
Underserved
Coastway Community than this
I mean this was very instrumental this is a grocer
What they're saying is
The market is already crowded
So Vanessa is like
How can we legally
Keep it from getting worse
And you know who's really good at getting the businesses they want and keeping out the ones they don't want
Wealthy town
She learns about a city in Southern California
Coronado
That has what's called
Formula business
Formula businesses are chain
And in that Community they had a policy in place
That at no time will there ever be more than 10 national chain stores I don't care if it was a McDonald's burger king whatever
Any national brand no more than 10
It so that was the commitment
Visiting Coronado got sued
What they want
And now Vanessa has a real life example of a city restricting business
On the grounds that it is
Good for the city
And there are actually a bunch of cities I do this
Restricting chains in particular isn't what Vanessa wanted but it was
Similar
She still had to convince the zoning and legal
They held to public meetings in Vanessa's district and finally were like
Okay
People want this
Here's what they come up with
No Dollar Store can open up
Within a mile of an existing Dollar Store
Dollar Store Zone
We identified
Existing store
Input a one mile radius circle around it
There's no more room for any more disk
So there is no
Place in North Tulsa
Where a dollar store
Open up
That will be a mile away from another dollar store not in these boundaries
Is correct so this one mile
Marker is really the the loophole that you found
To prevent any new stores from coming cuz there is no space
Exactly because they proliferated so
I already
What Vanessa really wanted was for people to have access to
2 healthy food
Big picture so their proposal would also sweeten the deal for grocery stores
Normally they have to have a lot of parking spaces
This would cut the number of spaces
Also people with
Community garden
They would be able to
Sell any produce they grow
Right out of the garden no permit required
That's not allowed anywhere else
So the proposal comes up for a vote and the people of North Tulsa Pac into City Hall
I have to cut you off
Because this is
We're talking about the other side
And I know
It gets pretty contentious one person is like look the $11 store
Heard your protest they offer some fruits and such
Sports now
And we are choosing to shop there
In spite of it being
Boycott it
Protest
Is it against
The Northside residence
Is patronizing the same
Dollar General
Now the city councillors are listening to this their hearing everyone out
And they're also raising their own concern
One of them who has a background in economics is like
This sounds like fences this sounds like preventing busy
That's not good
Another city counselor thought the proposal just didn't have enough detail
From me the the hard part
Of this
His employee
Please don't start throwing
Tomatoes
If I got at me I don't have tomatoes it would have
Don't try throwing Cheetos
Packages of Twinkies
Okay okay okay
I can't vote
In favor of
Yes
Limiting dollar stores
Barely
5 divorce
In effect
No more dollar stores can open up in North
Tulsa
Of course the dollar stores don't give up that easily
Two new ones open up right on the edge of the restricted area in North
But this Dollar Store ban started to resonate all over the
Newark
North St Louis
Haskins Ohio the all called Vanessa Hall Harper saying
We have too many dollar stores to how can we do what you do
Mesquite City Texas just went ahead and pass the restrictions right away
And what North Tulsa did is make room in the market for a grocery
Restore they're trying to
Prop up a business that hasn't worked in the free market
But North Tulsa is still a market in order for a grocery store
To survive
It will have to be better than the $11 stores
Coming up after the break how one grocery store made one of the most Charming changes we've ever heard of
To compete
Support for NPR in the following message
To come from Capital one's business credit
The spark Cash Card
Offering unlimited 2% cash back on everything you buy
For your business
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Visit capitalone.com
For more information
Hey there it's Joshua Johnson the host of 1A on Fridays we make sense
The world
It's your chance to catch up on the week's top stories and
Prepare for what's next
Check out the Friday news Roundup in the 1A podcast
On the NPR one app or wherever you get your podcast
I went to a local grocery store in Conway Springs
Candice the wheat capital of the world
A place so quiet
You can hear the grass
In the Wind
It's a farming town with about a thousand resume
Jenny oxner and her husband Clint own the only grocery store in
Where
Homegrown that's what we liked
So high school sweetheart
Really
Are you a cheerleader
Maybe
Sweethearts built their store from the ground up
Ben Dollar General decided to open up
Right in front of their store
Like
Here we are
Your competition
Writing process
The Oscars
Saw their sales start to decline
And they decided to compete
Now they're open later and they work
Longer on Sunday
And all of this is good for consumers
I needed that because of the competition they extended your hours
Yeah we figured we needed to because they're ours weren't
What they should have been in the beginning
We know we should
She probably be open till 9 in the summer everyday but
We
Still like that little bit of family time that we have left
And they've tried to find a niche
Something they have that Dollar General
Doesn't
Like
The coldest refrigerator in town
Are milk coolers very cold it's very well refrigerated and so
Coldest milk in town coldest beer in town
We take pride in that cold is milk and
And sometimes it's whatever works right and that works
Express also have
Pretty intense
We do it
Boneless
Barbecued baby back ribs
Weave bone out Boston butts a lot of times
It just takes a little extra time
Bone out Boston butt
Yeah that's a butcher term I guess
And look there are examples of grocery stores surviving dollars
Just like they survive warmer
Which Jenny and Clinton
What dollar stores are differ
Walmart is cheap but dollar stores have this way of making us
Feel like they're way cheaper I means they're called dollar store is
But they're not always a good deal when you compare prices
Is pound-for-pound
Celtics
Back in North Tulsa
Vanessa's long battle to bring fruits and vegetables and meat to her neighborhood
It worked
You have a grocery store
Yes but you know who they are
Yes I just can't say it yet
But it's a done deal
When we breaking ground hopefully
Late summer
So yeah
They did also get some Federal grant money for their grocery
As Eva District that has $11 stores
Do you think
That that grocery store will be able to survive
When it has 11
Dollar types
Stores to compete with
Yes we are very hopeful that it will
Because I'm going to educate and work and encourage my constituents
Look if we don't support the
Restore we won't have it and you'll still be complaining about the same thing you've been complaining about for the last 10 years
That we don't have quality course
Community
Something's in the grocery store will be more expensive than the dollar type
Vape stores
But we as consumers regularly pay more for the things we want including low-income
Like
We might pay more for the coldest milk in town
And people in North Tulsa might be a couple cents more to have access
To the vegetables
They like mustard greens
That is what Vanessa really want
If you have a story idea we would love to hear from you you can email us
Planet Money at npr.org
Today Show was produced by Darian woods and Liza Yeager
Brian aurstat is our editor and Alex gold markets are supervising
Special things to Michael stavola with hutch news for putting us in touch with Doug neck
And things to Eldar shafir at Princeton University
I'm Sarah Gonzales and I'm Noel King thanks for listening
Norfolk bridge
Let's fly right out the Tulsa don't you know
Okay so maybe there are too many dollar stores but I grew up loving the one where everything cost
Exactly $1
People here were skeptical that you could find good quality stuff
Challenge accepted
Okay
I bought
Do you have things wrapped in newspaper
Like a wine glass tumbler
Wake high quality
Glade air freshener clean linen
What are the fat bomb on my God for a dollar in the shape of a mermaid tail Hallmark thank you cards 8 pack
I would actually
You can have them
This is the beauty of the receipts
24 items $25 and ninety
A dollar a dollar a dollar Cube answer something so satisfying about seeing a long receipt with only one
$1