Support for NPR in the following message come from graduate programs at the University of Colorado Boulder
Go further in your research and your career in Boulder
Ranked number one in the Bloomberg brain concentration index
More at colorado.edu grad programs
Just tell me your name at your job
Just so I don't forget that
Sure my name is Jordan Thomas I am the chair
Of The Whistleblower representation practice at laverton sushiro
And I'm based out of New York
Tell me about growing up
Well my mother a white former nun turned school teacher
Kind of instilled in me
A profound faith
And encouraged me to contact my life
Serving others
How my father was a black judge turn political fixer
Who
Taught me
The unwritten rules of power
He was a
Kind of incredibly smart
Charismatic
Man
Who believed that the American dream is a mess
Yeah
If I could come to
Distill
Answers of my father's face
It was that the world is rigged
The ends justify the means and
You're either pulling the strings or you're the puppet
And
For many years
I wanted to come in
Join the family business for black a better way of saying it
I wanted to be a power broker
A string puller
If you will
To be close to him
Not to earn his love
I was willing to do illegal and unethical things
Why I'm not proud of it
Ana spent the better part of my life trying to make amends
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Jacob Goldstein
Turn Thomas maybe the top lawyer in the country in his field
Representing people who seen some kind of financial wrongdoing and want to report it to the SEC
When I first called him that's all I expected to talk about
Working with Wall Street whistleblowers to bring cases against some of the biggest banks in the world
But as we talked
He also told me this to extraordinary story about how he grew up and what made him the person is today
So today show is both about the work Jordan Thomas does and the life that led him to it
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their own website
Using customizable layout
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online presence
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
You the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Mitch McConnell
And become a champion for conservatives
But back in the day he wants got support from groups like
Labor unions Market down as one of the worst things I've done my life
So you thought about over the years
I see a face Mitch McConnell
New series from embedded
Subscribe now
During and after the financial crisis
Jordan Thomas worked as a lawyer at the SEC the Securities and Exchange
That's one of the federal agencies that regulate wall
While he was there he helped create this new whistleblower program
What is the program people who see Banks or other companies breaking the rules
Can anonymously report it to the SEC
If the SEC follows
Tip and whines up collecting money from the bank
The Whistleblower is eligible for an award
It's like a bounty
After the program was up and running
Jordan went into private practice
Helping whistleblowers bring their cases to the SEC
In exchange if his clients get paid a bounty his firm gets a chunk of the money
He's become one of the preeminent lawyers in the field
The clients have provided tips that have helped the SEC
Collect hundreds of millions of dollars from some of the biggest banks in the world
He told me he thinks there are a few reasons for his success
One is we're very selective
We get in contact with all kinds of people
Whack jobs Washington security theories and Foxhole conference looking for get-out-of-jail-free
Our job is to come figure out who the good guys are
The real whistleblowers
The ones who know where the bodies are buried in the ones that can lead us to the
And
Pretty good at that
I think the
II
Thing is that were
John Hardin realest
We understand how things really work
And
Are willing to use non-traditional tactics
Grey the grey Arts if you will
Good example is csec
Is not permitted
Covertly record conversations
Well
IRS whistleblower Advocate working with my clients can
Covertly record conversations
In many states in the United States including New York
Cracked
And I'm sometimes joke that some of my clients must have been trained by Mossad because
They have enough recordings of of people that are good that are game changers
So in the past the SEC
Would have to build cases from the ground-up circumstantial
Now my clients are bringing them
You know countless recordings of senior people talking about wrong doing
It doesn't get much better than that
What can you tell me about specific clients of
Not much our clients tend to be a senior people with a lot to lose
And actually
The number one question that was a lower come to
What's a bar council with is
Will I lose my job
Will I be blacklisted in my career
And
Other than to see what's above program
You can report anonymously
And so
Yeah and many of our
Anonymous whistleblower cases
We will
Make arrangements for the SEC to speak to that the client
By phone
We will use voice change technology to change the gender
Timber of
The whistleblowers voice so the SEC itself can't even identify the voice of The Wiz
Whistleblower right
You said you can't talk about the clients
I know that
You mentioned a few cases are there instances where you can talk about the case
Now let me give you the example of
JP Morgan
JPMorgan was still was telling its clients
That they would
Objectively pek of the best funds
For their clients
When in fact they had a bias toward picking
Dietary products in which they made more money
And sometimes as products and work performance
Because they they were able to make greater fees
And our client along with another whistleblower not represented by us
We're able to provide evidence of that to the SEC and the SEC was able to confirm that
This is something that affected over a hundred thousand
JP Morgan clients
And was stopped because of our our client
And what happened to JP Morgan
What would they have to do as a result
And pay over 300 million
And Jordans client in that case got an award of 13 million dollars
Second whistleblower in that case represented by a different attorney
Got over 30 million.
Those awards were announced just a couple months ago and that was the third biggest case in the history of the SEC whistleblower program
The biggest award was last year in that taste Merrill Lynch got in trouble for misusing customer funds
And three whistleblowers all represented by Jordan Thomas
Rewarded a total of 83 million dollar
Even now does Merrill Lynch know who the whistleblowers were who your clients were
Now they don't
Wow
The same as JP Morgan if we do if we do our job well
Our clients can and do continue working
At
The organizations in which they reported
Even though they can buy an island some of them like working so they keep working
I mean not to be
Glib but there is that
There's like
Hey Bob
How to show up in a Lamborghini today
Yeah I know some some people don't don't show their money and
Machete I am calm secret Millionaire's and I'll people who won The Whistleblower award but choose to keep working
At the same firm
It does happen
People's relationship with their work is in some ways like family after a period of time
And breaking it off as hard
After the break
Family's secrets and how Jordan Thomas became Jordan Thomas
But what was your name before you were Jordan Thomas
Paul Thompson
Does anybody still call you Paul
No
Scorbutus NPR Podcast in the following message come from Salesforce Salesforce helps you deliver the end
Innovative personal experiences customers want learn how Salesforce brings customers and companies together at
Salesforce.com NPR
After James Reeb was murdered in 1965 there was a national outcry
The back of the scene of the crime in Selma Alabama
People responded different
What happened
And what did Justice look like all these years later
NPR's new podcast White Lies seeking answers
Listen And subscribe now
Tell tell me about your mom
Well
My mom is a former nun
I like a joke that my
My mother is a cross between Mary Poppins and Mother Teresa
Seems pretty good
Ya know she is
One of the most loving
People that I've ever known
But she's also not a worldly person
And
As a result I think that the world I wasn't hasn't always been kind to her
How did she and your father
Get get to
Together they sound like they were living in very different worlds
Well my mother
She was in a Convent in
Compton California
And my father was working in politics in Los Angeles
And she and another none
Went to
Hey public hearing to advocate for crosswalk near the the school if she worked for
And
Somehow struck up a conversation
A year or so later she
Left the convent
And
Began dating my father
Shortly thereafter
They had a surprise
And that was me
My parents weren't married long and she were married my stepfather
Who was regularly unemployed
And kind of saw me as an anime
At different times in my early life I was neglected
Abused and homeless
But I got glimpses of
More Glamorous Life
When I visit my father
What did he do what was his
Jabra weltmeister
My father was a rising star as a Young Man
He
I came from nothing
Went to Community College then went to a night law on unaccredited night law school and then ended up working for
The County Supervisors in Los Angeles
And then
Was
The first elected black judge in Southern California
And
Then
Abortion I got in a serious car accident
And
The car accident require them to take prescription
Painkillers and
Prescription painkillers affect your ability to
Affects your judgement
And so he was medically retired from the bench
And kind of all of his dreams
Future seem to fade away
So after
His
His path is career ended
Key
Confused of what he knew
To solve problems for
People if people wanted to
Be appointed to certain positions he would help them get a point into those positions if he wanted
To receive federal funds for something he would I use his
Political connections
Sure Builder
And I you wanted to build beyond the code
Music I you go to
He solve problems and help people kind of Leverage
The government
How did you think about your
Dad when you were a kid and how did that change as you were growing up
You know I idolized my father
He was everything that I hoped
To be
He know he knew famous people
Party with celebrities drove fancy cars lived on the beach or near the beach
How to farm in Hawaii
I mean it was so hot he was he
And cuz that was his existence
Now he ate every meal out
Flashy kind of a successful
For the person and
Turn up the alternate universe that I lived in was
How is my mother and stepfather
+ mobile home parks we didn't have a lot of money
I remember going regularly to the day old bread store
Scrape off the mold and you know eat them bread and
It was that it was stark contrast
The life we lived
And
I guess every son wants to be like his father but
For me
He was everything
My dream
Wants to be
I his number two
And my father's plan
Was for me to enter some form of politics
And then
Cop with that
Sort of
Station
Will power
And influence
It's interesting I mean
I could imagine
Going up to a different way if you
You know going to the day old bread store and Senior
Father go out to a restaurant at every meal wondering
Well why he isn't
Giving your mom money
Take care of you
Yeah I think that that is something that I didn't appreciate when I was younger
I'm by began to appreciate more later
As I Grew Older
In my teenage years
Turn my idealized image of my father
I began to crack
As a student at UCLA I was finally living close to him and began to
To see him at his worst
Dishonest with those close to him
Motivated by self-interest and
Dependent on prescription drugs
I saw him for who he actually was not who I wanted him to be
And during the start time
I became depressed and you're suicidal
When was that
When I was 19
Patrick close call
More drunk behind the wheel on a Steep Ravine and in the Malibu Hills almost died on
I'm driving
Anyway I need cat needed to break away
Entirely
Brokers my father
Shortly thereafter
And that point I decided to reinvent myself
Essentially
Putting myself into a witness protection program kind of
Of my own making
What's an interesting choice of phrase
What do you mean by that I didn't believe that if I stayed in Los Angeles
I could
Can't wait for my father and his info
And
I thought my best chance of
Having a new beginning
Was to
Get lost
And
I didn't know it at the time but it also was important for me to find myself
And so
I sold everything I could I couldn't backed up my old Volkswagen Bug and
Transferred across country to Paddington on the well-known modern dance school in Vermont
It was like the farthest away
From
Where I was
And I never been there and
Help make this transition I legally change my name to Jordan Thomas
My first name was Jordan because I I love Michael Jordan love playing basketball
Adam.
So I thought that would be a good first name and
My last name was Thomas at it because it had some
Titan
My
Old man Thompson
And my middle name have a good store to it I think
Insight eye related to kind of Michael Corleone's
Efforts to legitimize himself in The Godfather
I took Corleone's
Original name and Delaney as my middle name and
That point fully detached for my family friends and kind of former life
It didn't end well for Michael Corleone it didn't end well
I suppose I didn't think through that had as much as I should have but it has ended well for me
What was your name before you were Jordan Thomas
Paul Thompson
Does anybody still call you Paul
No
Do you think of yourself as as Paul Thompson at all
I don't
You know
Up until very recently
I couldn't remember anything
About my
My life prior to
Changing my name
4 million dollars on a gameshow I couldn't have told you
One name of a friend teacher coach girlfriend
Even today after
Going back and trying to remember
I don't remember much about
Call
I think that
Most of of
His life was was very difficult
It's amazing that you called
Can you use the word his
Rain-X like it's somebody else
It really is
You said until recently you didn't remember anything was there something that cause you to remember
There was
There was a New York Times story that came out
But that profiles me and alluded to some of
My past
And
It felt
Surprisingly
Made me feel lighter
But I felt like because of that feeling
I realize that I hadn't fully dealt with
My past
And
As a result
Have encouraged by
My clients and some of the readers of the profile
You told me that day that I inspired them
I decided to revisit and investigate my history
So what I did is I
Took time from working and travel
All the places that I once lived and
Sought out people who knew me then
Grand
Try to
Remember
What had happened
Attempt
Terrifying
It was
But
Necessary
Jordan gathered up old family photos and letters he kept stored away
He got on a plane to fly out to the West Coast to talk to people who knew him but he was Paul Thomas
And
For me that was a moment and I was at 35000 feet or something like that and I was reading
Old letters that I've written and looking at pictures and
All of a sudden
My memories started flooding back and
Literally the woman next to me said are you alright because I was just like
Clearly affected
And
That was the beginning of me beginning to see
What I hadn't been able to come
Revisit
Were there any particular moments on that trip
That that stand out specific conversations you had
Places you went
You know I
I had
I talked to you about the airplane experience night light
I also remember I had a different point
Meeting with my
Cousin near me
When I was a teenager
Hand
Her describing
An incident where
Chuze babysitting
And I
I wanted to make pancakes
Somehow
I made batter and then
Toaster
Honda
Obviously that didn't go well
And
She would calls talk talking to me about
My reaction
What was your reaction
Apparently I lost my mind and it was like
I'm not going to be tonight was going to be as soon as he was like the world's end it was like
There's just
Hide me
And
Some of these conversations help
Just to see that
Terrified child
And
Can grieve for
One of the things that I've kind of learned from my clients is that
Secrets are rarely empowering
So
Part of
My decision
Was
To no longer keep the secrets and that's why I'm speaking you today
Reflecting on
Where I am today
I know that
I wouldn't be doing the work I do
But for
Encouragement my mother
I wouldn't be as successful as I am and doing what I do
But for the training
Google dark arts
By my father
And
I would have had the courage
Two kind of
To take this unconventional path
But for the difficult
Times in my life and the need to recreate myself
So
I've been kind of holding on to
2 secrets
My nose have been the foundation
Of my life my success
Who I am
Today Show was produced by Alexi Horowitz Ghazi and Liza Yeager
Our editors Bryant urstadt and our senior producer is Alex goldmark
You can email us at Planet Money at npr.org or find us on Facebook
Twitter or Instagram if you're a fan of the show you can help us out by leaving a review and a rating wherever you listen to pod
If you want Planet Money in video form I've got good news for you that is available at NPR.
Splash Planet Money shorts
Short cheeky delightful videos on things like the invention of plastic and the economy of the tooth fairy
Those again are available at npr.org
Planet Money shorts
I'm Jacob Goldstein thanks for listening