Just a quick warning there is some bad language
Which in Today Show
A couple years ago
Alice Wu was an undergraduate at UC
The Berkeley
Studying economics
Monday at some of her friends told her hey
You should check out this thing we just found
It's called the economics job market rumors
Then you like I wanted to
To do a PhD in comics
I thought you told me they were half joking like
Future call eggs and stuff dolls with lecture fine
What's the website
Click through a few threads
I was just surprised or like really in shock when I saw those
Commons
Just kind of
Pointed directly to a very hostile environment
This forum had originally started as a place
Or PhD students to swap information about the job market
Who got an interview who got fired
People started using it to like
Argue about nerdy econ research things you know like coase's theorem is highly overrated
It's an anonymous online forum
Meaning but soon it became pretty much the worst
At least parts of it did
End
Alice
Stumbled into some of that stuff locker room talk
Of something
Or like a boys club
I like that
Took out very
Disgusting
Very quickly
No
Numbers-wise
Economics is a boys club
There's this
Stark gender gap in the profession
For example in the US in 2018 just 17% of full professors economics for women
At the undergrad level only about a third of all econ Majors for women
Even though more than half of undergraduates overall wear women
So far all is all of that is
Kind of just part of
And this nasty stuff she's reading on the Forum
Children really dwell on it
She gets out of the Forum pretty fast
Sounds like maybe this is one of the dark secret professions I didn't really think so
Too much about it
Until
A couple months later
She was in a meeting with her advisor else was in my office.
Chat a little bit about ideas for
Senior Theses this is David
Card he's a big-shot labor economist
First met Alice when she was a student in his advanced economies
So they're sitting there in his office Battleground ideas for her
FS1
The phone rang
David picked up
It was an old friend of mine whose it was actually the chairman at the
Princeton economics Department
Jack Curry
And
Janet was quite upset
Italian upset because
She had been reading that same forum
She was familiar with the place
And she was fed up with it
Because
There seems to be a very persistent pattern of basically there's a lot of negative stuff being said about female economist
She hung up the phone after I got off the phone I kind of mentioned this to Allison I said this is what we were just talking about
I've been sitting there a code you know about the akan job market rumors for him
Isaiah heard about it
I wouldn't have thought you would know about it it turns out I guess
People know more stuff than you
You think if they know
I was told me she thinks
Pretty much everyone in economics has been on this forum at one point or another
So she and David start talking about it just looks like a little
Pretty terrible situation
And I
I'm not exactly sure how we got to
To this point I think you say maybe could just write a small report really a 10-page report
What's going with the forearm is like
See just exactly what was the pattern was there any really
Difference in how people were talking about female versus male economist
This is the place where I think economist
Diverge from normal people
The most people here is How The Story Goes
Yule log on to an anonymous online forum
See a bunch of sexist garbage and say
It looks like people on this former being sexist
Case closed
But
A lot of economist
Don't see the world this way
They have in the words of one Economist I talk to a bias
Against bias
This deep-seated belief that often things that look a lot like discrimination
Can be explained in other ways
So what else will you set out to do
What do you use the tools of economic
How to test for bias on econjobrumors.
Because
As an economist
She couldn't be sure it was there until she wrote a rigorous replicable statistically sound quantitative economics
Teen debit card
Their data people it would be
Probably important
Just to establish the facts
It did turn out to be important
Alice Wu ended up writing her undergraduate senior thesis about this for him
And the paper
Which proved something so obvious that Alice herself almost blew it off
That paper became one of the most talked-about economic papers of the year
The New York Times wrote about it
One Economist called Alice the most important Economist for 2017
And some of the most famous people in the profession
Women who have been a condiments for decades
Say Alex is work is helping them to finally talk about big problems in economic
Hello and welcome to Planet Money
I'm finally home
Today on the show
A young economist
Holds a mirror up to the field
And her colleagues don't like what they see
This message comes from NPR sponsor squares
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence
Sense and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable Leo
Along with
Features including e-commerce functionality
The and mobile app
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase
Chase have a website or domain
Look up a child swim in a minute
But first
This idea in economics that sings
That look like discrimination might not actually be discrimination
Where does that come from
Can you hear me can you hear me
Yes I called up Beatrice Cherry a
She's a historian of economics
And
She told me that there was this one
Theory of discrimination that emerged in the 1950s
In later decades it became a dominant Theory and a lot of people are still into
It was applied to racial discrimination and
An Economist who believed this model
Think about discrimination in the labor market
Basically this way
In a perfectly competitive world
Discrimination is
Terrible form
You're a sexist manager you just don't like women
Some Economist would call this
MSU of animist
So you'll hire a less
Competent man rather than a more competent women
Gun
You'll fall behind your competitors
If your business you'll make less money has Department your reputation will suffer
Discrimination is an efficient
So because it's inefficient
A market dynamics are going to push these people who have a taste
Spoken for discrimination out of the market
So basically it's going to get competition to weigh
Yeah exactly so you don't need to do anything about discrimination
Because it's going to disappear
And it's say gender disparities don't disappear
Maybe that's okay
Maybe women don't want to enter the war
Women stay at home
Because it's irrational calculus its
Specialization within the house
So
Horizon from their preference
Did you know it's their choice
Back in the 1970s
A group of female economist
Sad
Our preference is to be economist
Reason for not getting the opportunities we should
Econ departments should actively encourage women grad students
Whether or not they're married or half
Some Economist didn't want to do that
Beatriz told me there are letters from this time we're Milton Friedman
One of the most famous economist in America
Was arguing against it
Is explicitly applying is
Thinking about the labor market how the labor market work
To the problem women in the comic
But around the same time the 1970
Economist are developing a new theory of discrimination
And this new theory is sort of about
Pizza connoisseur like
Maybe it's not
Animus
Maybe discrimination happens
Because employers are making bad assumptions
Based on imperfect information
So they look at the world
See that men are publishing more economics papers than women say
And then when they're hiring an economics professor they look at their job candidates and they're like
I guess I should hire a man because on average men published more
It's called
Statistical discrimination
Discrimination based
Not on cannabis
But on statistic
Economist can spend hours on the philosophy of how those two things are different I personally don't get it but I'm almost ready to retire
Everybody's talked about that forever so this is David card again the big shot labor Economist who was Alice Woo's advisor
You told me that
Both these models have a lot of cloud
And he has an affair
One reason economist
Care about the difference
Is because it might affect what you do about discrimination
Like in this statistical discrimination model
Maybe you can solve the problem by giving employers
More information
About how women are actually great
And if they don't have animus in their hearts
That information might convince them not to discriminate
Maybe we can do something about this
And yet
I was just
Surprise or like really in shock when I saw those
Commons
There are also places like econjobrumors. Com
In fact
Anyone who's ever been on the internet might think
Anime
Seems to be out there
Now
David card is part of a big group of Labor economist
Who say basically
We don't need to keep endlessly arguing about why
Discrimination is happen
Go out into the world and get data
Documents
Annapolis student Alice Wu
Set out to try
Remember she wanted to know if there was a difference
It's in the way men and women were being talked about on this forum a difference she could prove
Her first step was basically to write a computer program that would download the post
From The Forum
2217000
And 46 of them
So after scraping data is kind of just in very messy form so he's all like
Post after post
Now she has to figure out how to sort these posts into buck
1 bucket is post about men
1 bucket is post about women
And to sort of her first step is to pick out words that clearly refer to them
Most rare follower wise are pronouns like she or he
Her
That was so other general ones
Like female now women
Man I think I remember from your paper there was also bro and bruit
Is that right
Yes
Chelsea picked out names classified as those as male or female
And once you have this initial list of words
Some of the posts
Are super easy to classify
Like if a bird he appears 20 times in a post in the word she doesn't appear at all
It's probably a post talking about men
Echoes in the mailbox
Agitate
Those pills
The ones that are obviously talking about men or obviously talking about women
And she analyzes.
Using machine learning
And that's a list of
Other word
Words that come up
Disproportionately in post
About women or post
About men
Alice brother that list
My first impression was obviously the
Bad but if you
Are familiar with a forearm and look at those poses with him
Surprising
She went to an advising meeting with David card and
At some point she offhandedly showed him the list
I just showed him like oh hey this is a list of words and he was like
Can you show it to me
Do you have card immediately knew that this list
It wasn't just
Like preliminary data it was a finding in itself
Because
When Alice showed him this list
He didn't even want to read the words out loud while Alice
Student was sitting there in his office
You could imagine
A situation where a male older male Professor physics
Showing a list
Of words like that
Two younger female
Student and
I could lose my job
I wasn't that worried about it but
I was aware that you know
We're not going to say those words out loud
In my office
I pulled up the latest version of Elsa
The paper while we were talking
Can we look at the words
Oh yeah
Wow okay
Would you mind reading them to me
You don't have to if you don't want to that's okay but
Will you
Actually wood and Watson
So I read some of them pretty terrible let me see
Blonde
Unattractive
Gorgeous
Assaulted
There's also naked
Horror
Wow
Raped
Vagina
Ugly
I'm less offensive but still not great ones like pregnant and Mary
To be fair there are some disturbing words on the mail list
The top word most disproportionately associated with post about men is
Homo
The second is testosterone
Along the way there were also some words that were just confusing
Why is salmon one of the most malware
I don't ever talk about food
Why is mountains on there
I have no idea how Tallis the main distinction has to do with which of the words are professional
And which words are
Personal
Notably none of the words that were disproportionately associated with women have to
To do with economics
But words disproportionately associated with men included things like
Macroeconomics
Keynesian
Advisor
Nobel
This west end up becoming a big part of Alice's senior piece
And it's the part that people in the economics profession have really
Grabbed onto
No I should say that this study is narrow it has limitations
For one thing the posters are anonymous
So we don't know who is saying all this nasty
Stop or how many people are saying it
Remember this is about how it disproportionately these words come up in post about men and post about women
Not how frequently they come up
So
For example out of 400,000 post that Alice analyzed
The word ugly comes up
1046 X in posts about women
And 404 times in post
Batman
Did card has study discrimination
4 years
He says
One reason why Alice is paper is important is
Because it identified
Animus
So not
People just need a little more information and then they'll do the right thing
Dammit
Hostility
Meanest
This
Demonstration on econjobrumors says it is really something to adamhs
It's not that everybody has a pure mind
That is just
I really wish I could hire women but you know there's
Is not that good
This is like oh my God these guys are going out of their way to trash
Of course
Alice's paper does not prove that their hiring discrimination happening in economic
These posters could just be a tiny slice of Trolli PhD Bros who
Don't have any real cloud
End
It might have become just
A really good senior thesis that helped Alice Wu get into grad school
But that's not what happened
After the break
Alice's paper blows up
This message comes from NPR spawn
Capital One
Is reimagining Bank
I offering account
With no fees or minimum
I'm sticking be open from anywhere in
5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Na
So Alice
Finish your senior year of college
Second semester her thesis is done to sign into Harvard for grad school she can relax a little
Ashley
Discover my interest in beer
He says when the prize
And over the summer she gets an email
Economist Justin wolfers wants to write about her paper in the New York Times
Ultimately says okay
You know
She's nervous
It was real
Like a lot of pressure
First
Economics paper at Rio like
I don't know
But she agreed to do it
When the New York Times piece came out the reaction was
Huge
Economist spoke out
Online at conferences is an email to Alice
They were sharing personal experiences with sexism in the field
It will start talking about those you no more
I'm so I think that the form is definitely problematic but it reflects something much
Larger than the Forum itself is just basically reflect
The gender issues in
The profession one place where Alice's paper was big news was at this annual meeting of economist
The meeting of the American economic Association
Fate is a big deal
One thing this conference is where grad students interview for faculty jobs
It's where fancy new papers got presented
Alice spoke on a panel at the AAA conference in 2018
And around that time
She did something that made her a little anxious
She searched
Her own name
Anaphora
One thing you like I'll be presenting at this session there were just some really
Like we are common they're like oh we are going
Stalkers
Something that was really scary
It didn't turn out to be that way at all
Alice presented her paper alongside several other female Economist who studied women in the field
Are entangled Betsy Stephenson and Tatiana a Bulova when the New York Times word about this panel their head line began
Wielding data
Women force a reckoning over bias
And it seems like data
Has really convinced a lot of economist
Did they have a problem
Play I actually did a big survey this past year to get more and more comprehensive data about the culture in Act
Comics
Not about sexism they also asked about racism and about sexual harassment
And
The survey showed that racism and sexism and harassment are problem in the field
Predictably
It also showed that not all economist
See the problem in the same way
For example 52% of men who took the survey agreed that women are respected in the field
Only 16% of women agree
I wanted to talk to someone from The Forum who would read Allison paper and
See if it change their mind
So
I made an account on econjobrumors. Com
I searched Alice Wu
And I posted on one of the preds about the paper
Hey
I'm a reporter I told people to get in touch if they're willing to talk
When I hit this button
Suncoast
I didn't specify my gender by the way because I was nervous
Oh my God
We'll see what happens
Pretty soon I got the first response
It starts
Ball yeah right
The person didn't believe I was a real journalist
They went on to say
Let's face it
Lysol better than the truth
And even if by some miracle this person
Academy
Was concerned about the truth
We all know that this person Lacks
The technical knowledge to understand any of our explanations
Why the paper is wrong
There were a few other responses to some of the nicer but
Basically I was a paper didn't convince everyone
I crawled this idea that competition should help get rid of animus
Discrimination so
May we don't have to worry about it
What idea has been around a long time
Life of economist
Still believe it
At the big annual meeting of the AA this past year
People were confronting this head-on
Okay welcome everyone thank you for coming
Coming out
This is Betsy Stephenson an economist at the University of Michigan
She sitting on stage with a bunch of famous economist
All women
Economist
Swear to come to the field with a prior that there's no
Discrimination and they're only going to move their prior
When confronted with some sort of
Compelling evidence
My question to the panel is
How can we best
Address those who are the most skeptical that there's any kind of problem with discrimination
One of the economist on stage is Susan Athey
Stanford professor
People have this habit of making me statements
To me seems somewhat
Ridiculous like
Oh you know this can't be an issue to get some Peter to etcetera
And you know I don't really want to get in that argue
I might
I might get emotional I might lose my
My temper I might never think about that person the same way and so it's it's really very risky I feel
Still
Start these
Conversation
And since I want to make sure that when I answer I'm going to be answering in the economic way
Evidence
Data so thank you everyone who's giving me
Data
Uniqlo
It's very hard to tell so on stage
Janet Yellen
The only woman ever to chair the Federal Reserve
Which is arguably the most powerful Economic Policy job in the world
You know you uas busy
Why it's so difficult to convince man I think they
Regard themselves as rational in the field is being highly meritocratic
And it does
Requires some evidence
You know what evidence yellin was
Particularly impressed by
I think we got that evidence in the atlas wallpaper I think that was
A remarkably convincing
Appalling finding I haven't heard any mansao that's all
Finding it shows our field
Is functioning
Well when properly
Janet Yellen will take over as head of the AA next year
And
The ETA has started making some changes
Among other things they adopted a professional code of conduct
The first time I've done that
They plan to start new programs aimed at getting more women and people of color into economics
They've also started an alternative to econjobrumors.com their own forum
It's called econ Spark
I was told me that not that many people seem to be using it
Planet money has a great new newsletter
It's a way to keep up with what's happening on the show also get a dose of economics in your inbox
Topics include things like
Will a plastic bag ban actually end up hurting the environment
And is buying a house overrated
Subscribe at mpr.org
Planet Money newsletter
You can also get in touch with us at Planet Money at mpr.org Amber on Twitter Facebook and
Instagram
Today show with produced by the Jaeger it was edited by Brian Ernst. And Jacob Goldstein
Special thanks to Judy Chevalier
Heather sarson's
Sheila metcon and Donna cancer
Vonnegut there was The Economist use that phrase
Biased against bias
Thanks also to soumaya Keynes of The Economist magazine
Her reporting on gender in economics have been
It includes lots of great information about papers covering bias in economics
Willing to some of it on our website npr.org fast money I'm finally home thanks for listening