Today show with part 3 of what I have been
Been calling me Planet Money antitrust
The show will be much better if you
You go back and listen
The first two episodes
If you do not
Here is the
Text that Scrolls on the screen at
United States government used to use antitrust law a lot
To protect small companies against big companies in the name of competition
Then there was a back
Flash led by a judge named Robert
He wrote a book called The antitrust parody
Docks that argued antitrust enforcement had gotten out of hand
And the government needed tobacco
Now in the past couple years as a few tech companies have gotten very big
And very powerful
A backlash to the backlash has been
My name is Lina Khan and I'm an academic fellow a Columbia Law School and a senior fellow at the open market
Find your lawyer
I'm a lawyer when Lina Khan was in law school 2 years ago
She wrote a paper for the lottery
What was the title of the
Amazon's antitrust paradox
An allusion to that board
The antitrust paradox
Why did you choose that
I was interested in exploring how
Works approach to antitrust had enabled Amazon's rise
And
The Paradox with Amazon seems to me that
Here we had a company that was amassing dominance in various markets but our current approach to antitrust laws
Always really keeping us blinds
So that dominance
And so that to me seems like an interesting tension or current approach to Aunt
Worksop Road
Is known as consumer welfare
The basic idea is
Low prices
And lots of choices
Are good
If consumers are getting these things then there's no antitrust problem
End
Clearly Amazon has delivered low prices and lots of choices so it hasn't run into much trouble with an
Antitrust law in the United States
And yet Mina Khan argued in this paper there are things that Amazon has
I've been that
So her wonky article comes out
She heard from a few antitrust lawyers
Ben-Hur article gets mentioned in the New York Times
That's bird kind of a new wave of interest and so I just
Started receiving more and more email
What about this which I
Respect
The tremendous amount
Even though it's not good for our story
What she is not saying
Is the Des student law review article
Completely blew up
I mean I know you didn't go on Ellen
Or whatever
Lina Khan learned that the rise of a few Giant
Had made this very wonky thing
Antitrust
Suddenly feel urgent and important
Two lots of Ordinary People
Is it
Bad these companies are so big r
They assigned that the free market is failing us
And competition is this
Disappearing do we need to think about antitrust in a new
Congressman wanted to meet with her The Washington Post in the Atlantic wanted to profiler CNBC NPR
She joins me now to talk about how antitrust law
Handles Amazon
Lena thank you for being with us let me first say Amazon is among NPR's core
Corporate sponsors
Right we're going to have to talk about that hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Jacob
I'm Kenny Malone today on the show Amazon
One of our corporate sponsor
And Facebook
And Google
Spectra corporate Swanson
Okay but all of this is kind of a
These three companies are suddenly everywhere
They have an incredible amount of money
Empower
And leave his part of this new wave of thinkers were starting to say
Maybe the rise of these giant tech companies is a sign that antitrust is broken
And we need to fix it
Support for this podcast
Send the following message
Should come from the this week in Google podcast
Stat twit.tv
Every week
Leo Laporte
Jeff Jarvis and Stacey Higginbotham
Talk Tech
Media and privacy
They unapologetically questionnaire
Google Amazon Twitter Facebook and other Tech Giants are on the right track
Subscribe to this weekend
Google on your favorite podcast
Or it's wet. TV / twig
So the question for Today Show is
What if anything should we do about the big toe
I mean actually that's a ridiculously large question there's no way we could do that
And we're going to do a subset of that
Question right we're going to focus specifically
On competition and the free market and the role of the gutter
We're going to focus on anti
Took the question really is
Should we be using antitrust law in some way with respect to these big Petco
And the way we're going to do this
We're going to talk to two very smart
Lawyers who
Job is
To answer questions like
We're going to ask them to Big Quest
Are we thinking about antitrust
The right way
Does this consumer welfare standard still
10 question 2
If you had all the antitrust power in the world
What would you do
First step
Lina Khan
Do you want a title we're going to make you that
Ruler of antitrust in America
Nazi scientists article to the
Spirit of antitrust
So you where are you
Assertive respectfully decline an appointment
I'm happy to play along with the hive
Is there a reason in particular to focus on big technology
So the reason I've been focusing on big technology companies is because I think
Some of the blind spots of the car an antique
Best approach
Are most significant in the context of these tech companies
In part because in many instances are offering products or services that are nominally free or paying and data
So that complicates how antitrust
Starbucks at these issues
Think of Google and Facebook
You don't have to pay money to use those services
So the current antitrust
Consumer welfare standard
Which focuses largely on price
Just isn't going to work very well
Also she says this is fundamental nature of a few key text
They just tend to be winner-take-all
Everybody's going to tend to end up using one search engine one social network
Everybody who wants to buy or sell online
Is going to wind up at the one online store with the most buyers in
Can we talk about specific companies
Okay
What should we do about Amazon
I think first we need to have investigations into Amazon's conduct we have a very
Meagre understanding of how the different parts of
If it's business is actually Interlink and how it potentially uses data collected in World Market to Advantage itself in another Market in
And that sort of thing
And so I think as a first step more investigations more hearing
I'm just understand what's happening and that should then help inform what we should do
Okay what about as a second
Realizing things that are way more interesting frankly than investigation
Yeah I mean I think
It'll one problem that I've been focused on is the potential
Conflict of interest
It seems baked into some of these companies current
Businesses Amazon
Amazon is many
The main thing most people think of when they
I think of Amazon is
This Market
A store where anybody who wants to can
Sell almost anything they want
The millions and millions of potential
In the jargon this Marketplace is
A platform
And what we wound up mostly talking to Lina Khan about
Is what does it mean for competition when
One company wind-up controlling such a
A huge
I mean what so unique about platforms is that
Platforms end up dramatically reducing the cost of entry for all the third parties and what that means is
Platforms can be really
Good for competition
Because now there's this place where everybody in America who wants to buy say
Batteries
This is going to go to buy there
So if I want to get into the battery selling business that is great
Of course I have to compete against
All the other battery brands
Not only Duracell and Energizer but also Amazon's own private label batteries
Amazonbasics batteries
Amazon
As built out pretty extensive private label it has at least a hundred and twenty different labels where it's now actually Pro
Producing Amazon based
Good
You could argue
A lot of people do
But these Amazon store brands are good for combat
Amazon is one more competitor in the market
Pecan argues in the long run
Amazon selling Amazon brand stuff on Amazon
Maybe bad for company
So that I think can create a conflict of interest and so far is Amazon owns the platform it runs the platform and decide
I2 comes up where in the search rankings
But it's also competing with all the merchants that are now depending on the platform
So this problem I mean this seems like
A fundamental like a store brand problem
Bright light therapy
You know whatever Walmart is a bigger retailer than Amazon and they have store brands and they can you know
Put
Purina dog food on the bottom shelf in the
Boy or whatever their house dog food is on the top shelf and you could imagine the same problem they're right a giant retailer with all this
Power just said so look what we're going to have a store brand
Is that a similar competitive Prof
I think you have to really look
At the degree to which
The retailer or the distributor is
Playing a bottleneck roll
In a sector
So which retailer is a
It's absolutely true that they have private labels generally speaking there's much more competition and the retail Industries and there is
Prison online Commerce
And so I think that means that the stakes of discrimination are quite different
So you're saying I could shop at Walmart or I can shop at Kroger I could shop at cost
That level of competition that you're talking about
There's also the issue of how a risk gets assigned
The issue of who is taking
The riskier
The company developing a new product
Or
The company running the store where the product is going to be so
So what's a Jacob
That
You and I decide to go into
I'm going to sell
Hats for dog yes
Million-dollar idea
The way a lot of traditional stores
They buy the dog hats
From us in bulk
And then if the dog had sit on the shelves and don't sell
It's not really our problem at least not in the short
The retail store
Paid us money
For our hats we have the money
The store took the risk
That the hats my
Amazon does not work
Amazon is not going to buy the dog hat
That's from us we can post or dog hats
For sale on him
And if they don't sell
We go out of business
And it did not cost Amazon in
If the dog had to do self
Then we pay Amazon jungle Barbara
Dog hat sell like crazy
If the world suddenly Goes Bananas for dog hair
Then Amazon is free to start selling their own line
Amazonbasics
Is the bring all sorts of nice
Cut up shirt that are not guaranteed
Need to sell their
It's the third parties that are undertaking the original
Risk
To invest in a product and see hey is this going to succeed
What's troubling is that in some instances
When a product does start doing well
Amazon observes it and then takes that idea produces it itself
Knocks out the third party from the top search listings and so suddenly you know
Is Amazon that's reaping the rewards
Of the risks that somebody else took
Then what would you expect this sort of long-term consequence would be
I need the long-term consequence will be the third parties will be more reluctant to invest
Skin products to take risks to bring them to market the idea being that even if this product succeeds there's a
A good chance that Amazon will appropriate the value
Of that reward
And they'll just be left hanging other words if Amazon's just going to wait and see if our dog hats cell
And if they do sell it's going to start selling amazonbasics dog hat
Why should we get into the dog had business in the first place
Kant argues that lots of people will think
Why should I even start selling anything online
I'm just going to end up losing to Amazon
And in the long run she says
This will mean less,
You presented this as a problem or is a potential problem
What's the solution
I think one solution is
Separating the marketplace
From Amazon private label I think
If you're going to be a dominant Marketplace
Then
You perhaps you to be able to also sell on that Marketplace
Putting yourself in direct competition with all the merchants that art
Dependent relationship of dependents
It really want to drive home here
It is that you would say to Amazon
You can either sell Amazon stuff
Or you can be a Marketplace for all these third-party sellers
But you are not allowed to do
That's right
That's that's a big one
It's a big one not just because it would mean the government intervening in a big way in this giant pizza
Although obviously that is big
It's a big one because really we haven't seen antitrust enforcement on this scale in this country
For decades
And by the way we did reach out to Amazon
Spokesperson argued
Amazon making its own product
Means lower prices better product and more
He also noted that private label
Is a relatively tiny part of Amazon
After the break
We talked to her second emperor
And he tells us what he would do
About face
Support for this podcast in the following message come from the this week in Google podcast
Stat twit.tv
Every week
Leo Laporte Jeff Jarvis and Stacy Higginbotham
Talk Tech
Media and privacy
The unapologetically question
Google Amazon
Twitter Facebook and other Tech Giants
We are on the right
Subscribe to this week in Google on your favorite podcast
Twitch tv / twitch
The second person we're going to talk to
To today is Scott here
He's an NYU Law professor
He's teaching right now and antitrust course called
Big Tech and standard oil
Perfect for the series
Working on
And he did want us to mention that he's done some Consulting work for a firm
It has concerns about Ana
Temple is working antitrust for a long time
And for most of that time
Most people were just not very interested in
In talking about
Was there a moment that you
You realize other people were perking up and paying attention
Would have played a role in the last presidential campaign
It was it was a plank in the Democratic platform
And
Then-candidate Trump
From time to time raised concerns about
Possible targets for antitrust intervention
Was it like exciting
Sure it was exciting exciting
So like
What's it like working and you know being an antitrust expert now having the speaker feel that this
It's cool that people are excited about this
Is there a black bear
We worried that we'll get it wrong that we'll get too excited that will pass a new law that does more harm than good
That
People have unrealistic expectations for what
And I trust is about I would accomplish
Scott Hemphill describes his antitrust views as middle of the road
He doesn't think the system needs to change as much as leadec on things
The system needs
You're one difference between the two of us
Confidence the consumer welfare standard
Just fundamentally can't work any
Hemphill thinks it can
Remember consumer welfare is a lot about price
But companies like Google and Facebook give their product away to people
For free
So it seems like under the consumer welfare state
And it would be really hard to know what to do about
But
We say consumer welfare and antitrust is a short
Four situations where sometimes we don't mean
Consumers in the sense of individual
Consumers can also include companies
Step by step
Like say companies that buy ads on Google and Facebook
And if Google and Facebook use their Market power to jack up and prices
That can be a violation of antitrust law under the consumer welfare standard
Scott Hemphill says generally we are thinking about antitrust in the right way
We don't need to rethink the goal of an
Is still worried about big tech companies
And competition
Emperor of anti
Today
What would you
Two major things
Oh
1 is
Could I just want to point out as soon as you were annoyed and Emperor you fold your arms in a very
Assertive
One place to go is
Investigate
Now this may seem like small stuff
Of course you want to invest
Pretty weak
I'm I'm warming up here
The main thing I want to do is take a hard look
At Tech murders that have
Already been consummated where
There may have been an anti-competitive problem at the
What's the big idea for
Scott Hemphill
Mergers
That is the thing that worries him
Thinks about big Tech
And antitrust
And specifically what are some of those men
So that the
The one that jumps out to me is
Facebook
Instagram
In 2012 Facebook buttons
Instagram for 1 billion dollars
And handle says
Is antitrust emperor
She would try to figure out
Why Facebook
And why he says is important because
Murderers are not inherently on anti
Is that sometimes there's a totally legit reason for two firms to
The classic reason for murders is if you think
1 firm
Can
Help successfully grow promote develop
The technology of the other
So Facebook already has all this data and it has a great ad sales team or whatever things that will really benefit in
Instagram is just
Going to be a more efficient business
Can I grow better that's going to be good forever
That's a good news happy stories
And it might be right
Also you might be wrong
The Facebook Instagram Marjorie might be a bad news
Sad story
Companies already big
And then it starts getting bigger and bigger
By buying up other
That is a sign
But maybe the company is trying to suppress competition
You know what you just buy up its rival so it doesn't have to
Compete that is obviously
Bedford company
Temple says as antitrust emperor
He would try to figure out what Facebook was thinking
Why did it want to buy Instagram
Good news happy story
Or bad news set story
By the way I just want to bring Lee to come back for like 1
Second here because
She also mentioned the Facebook Instagram merger as a potential antitrust prob
This really interesting reason
Why it was bad for come
Let's just think about
Real example of witches
As Revelations about
Facebook Slack
Privacy and security
Protocols of
I'm coming clear you've heard more people say
I'm quitting Facebook I'm just
Is closing this down
At least I have my Instagram account
I think
Privacy is one good example of a
Dimension on which
Consumers should be able to choose and having more competition
By that
So this Facebook Instagram merger is one place where Lina Khan and Scott Hemphill
I'm pretty close on what they think we should do
It what I'm saying is that a transaction
Motivated at the time
Bye
Avoidance of competition
Is a good candidate for
Divestiture after the fact
Wait
Is that
Middle of the road
Consumer welfare is fine antitrust Emperor Scott Hemphill saying
After an investigation depending on the findings
The government should maybe break up
One of the biggest companies in the world that's what I'm that's why I'm thinking about you
Okay
OK Google
You're about to not be the emperor anymore you have any last wishes
No no it's
It's a heavy responsibility of the emperor heavy is the head
We did talk to people at Facebook about this whole in
Anime the case that both Facebook and Instagram benefited from them
They pointed out that
Instagram had infrastructure problems in just about
30 million users when they acquired the cup
6 years later there are 1 billion
They also noted that
Relevant Regulators so no reason to
To stop them
So we talked about Amazon with Leena Khan
In Facebook with Scott
Hemphill now
Let's talk about Google purchase
Google is a big one
We did a whole episode a couple years ago about Google and anti
Still online to find it just Google
Google is big is that bad
That was the headline
Since then there's been more antitrust news
About Google
Specifically
He's in the European Union that focused on Android on Google's operating system for smartphone
Which is by far the most popular mobile operating system in the world
Google had told phone maker
If you want to use Android
You also have to pre install the Google Search app and Google
Chrome browser on your
The EU looked into
And last year
Issued a decision
Quote
Google has use Android as a
Vehicle
To cement the dominance of its search
...
They have denied European consumers the benefits of effective competition
Any important mobile sphere
The European Union found this illegal
Under its
Antitrust rules and find Google
Billion
Google said in a statement afterwards
Quote Android has created more choice for everyone
Not less
The company is appealing
So okay we have done these three shows on an ant bite
And the first to wear these historical moments
When we went through really big changes
As a country in the way we think about
You know the free market and big business and competition and the role of the governor
And now you know this episode we have that the present moment the rise of the tech Drive
An end
You know the ending question has to be
Is this another moment when we need to once again sort of stop and rethink the way antitrust
Scott hemp
Pretty middle-of-the-road antitrust
Set no
Maybe we could
Forced
Current rules better but the rules themselves the worldview
Is basically working
And then there's Lina Khan
She is part of this other group of
Micros were saying
Antitrust is
You know what that what that
Tech Giants have Jonas's
There are these fundamental problems with
That the current antitrust world
You just he's not
And she sang
The government really needs to go
Back to that
Free Robert Bork era
He needs to intervene more often in the free market in order to make free market compass
We know we didn't talk about monopsony
Email us at Planet Money on NPR. Org you can also find us on Facebook Twitter and Instagram at Planet Money
Today Show was produced by Sally Helm and Darian Woods
Sally and Darien are both
Former Planet Money interns and we are look
Looking for our next intern
Interns have a lot of responsibility help out with all aspects of the show
And I get paid
Applications are due March 4th
Find out more at npr.org
I'm taking both today and I'm Kenny Malone thanks for listening