Support for this NPR Podcast
In the following message come from Better Health
Online counseling by license
Professional count
Specialized
Issues
Including depression stress and anxiety
Visit betterhelp.com money to learn more and get 10% off
If your first month
This is Planet Money
Okay Dina temple-raston
Yes I think we're going to just start with
A single-minded mission that you had in East Africa in Malawi
Define denote
To find an elephant and record it
In-person correct
Up close and personal with an elf
Okay so this is our first night and what they do is they say look we're going to
Go out on the river everybody please
In this River and people are very much in Romanian
Everywhere you look there are animals popping up
Dropping into the water and coming up
We're completely focused on these hippos
All of a sudden this
Elephants
Come off the hill
And start walking towards the water
And of course we were all
No tape
Okay idiot
But the truth is that if you want to be really close to an elephant you have to go online
We saw the fresh dung piles along the road and followed those found him in this clearing sure enough
Right in front of us is this
Steve normis elephant
And you think an elephant is so huge that you'd hear him walking all the time but what they say is the only time you here in LA
Washington's when he's coming any breaks a branch or when he's eating and all we got was an elephant eating
It was magical I was sewing
I found it so magical but to see them in the wild is magical
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Kenny Malone
Today on the show a quest to record the sounds of an elephant
Because
Elephants are being killed at such an alarming rate experts say they may be extinct in some countries in as few as ten
And years and recording elephant audio is a critical first step
In Saving the olive
We have a story about how researchers tried to pull off a kind of
Old school style house scheme
And to do that they had to steal a page from Silicon Valley and Wall Street
Hiding in trees secret recordings but also artificial intelligence and finally
We will have to understand
What a neural network actually does
Plus some of the most incredible audio recordings we've ever
Support for this NPR Podcast and the following message come from waste.com
A web platform for creating your own professional website
Join Over 125 million people already using wix
To tell their stories online
Gota wilx.com to create your website today
Greg
Yeah
What are you doing here again
I-Ready newsletter
What's next week's newsletter that
It's about a really uplifting subject it's about the stagnation of our economy
Where can people get that sweet sweet contact npr.org Planet Money newsletter that's why I can say that
That's what I can sign up yeah
Alright so I just want to try this thing
Okay
Turn your headphones down just a little bit OIC
Miss a long time
Is that you that's me
Okay it's me and it's the best
Animal impression I can do bad and when we think of elephants that's the sound we think of that trumpeting sound
But it's basically an elephant child
That's right by far the most frequent kind of vocalization we call a rumble
Which is very low frequency
Peter rig is an elephant scientist
Cornell University
And he's the director of something called The Elephant listening
It's a team of researchers that works in the rainforests of sin
We called Peter
I mean honestly a little bit because
We wanted to ask him every elephant
We ever had are elephants really scared of mice
Not at all that's a Disney thing that's all from the cartoons but also
We computer because
Just a few years ago
There was
Huge news
If you were an elf
A new study the great elephant census
Congestive failure to protect the world's largest land mammals the great elephant census was basically
The separate account every elephant Oliver after
Because that's the first step and knowing how fast they're being killed off
And where is specifically they're dying
There was a big copier
Did the study though the great elephant census
Depended very heavily on
Small aircraft
In the savanna you can fly over it and count
Herds of elephants
That is not possible to do in the rain
The great elephant census had to leave out the Forest elephant
The exact species of elephant
Peter specializes in
Yeah that's the Forest elephant is the smallest
Of the three species of elephants and their Ivory is the most
Apprised of any Ivory because it's denser than Savanna elephant Ivory and it has a pinkish tinge
So Peter and his team set out to see if there is a way to
Count this elusive foristell
In problem number 1
Is yet to see them from the air it is also hard to see for ourselves
Fence from the ground
Sometimes you see the let's say 15 meters away from you on the trail you're walking on
And they move 5m into the forest and you can't see them
Even though there are 3 ton animal that dance
It's tencent somehow they just disappear
Masters of camouflage
What's the elephant
That's right
Forest elephants are so hard
Account the best method they came up with was just walking around and Counting Forest elephant donkey
There is an estimate of how often does an elephant
Poop
And how long does a pile of done last in the rainy season or in the dryer
Is super time-consuming
And pretty Limited
2 Peter wanted a new way
Count these Alpha
Any thoughts
Can't see them
And we can't
Track them
What if we try to just
Listen
If we
Know how often an elephant call
Then we can spread recorders over a big area
And record their vocalisations and use those numbers to count
This was my dear that was floated a long time ago by a scientist named
Katie Payne
And the technology was reaching a point where maybe it was possible to conduct the kind of
Acoustic senses
Computers team decided
They were going to do
First Step was
To have 50 custom audio recorders
And they headed to the rainforest in central Africa
Every 5 square kilometer
They placed in audio
And where were the recorders
Just go like
Just put them on
Ground that gets stomped so we put
Recorders
7 to 10 m up in a tree hanging from a tree limb seven-and-a-half to do them
That's 21 to 30 feet up in a tree out of the reach of an elephant up on its hind feet
Because they actually eat that way they the elephant might accidentally
Eat your audio recorder they have done that
Baby in your audio recorder well babe
They tasted that
Stuck at us through them
Yeah
Peter and the team climbed
30 ft into the tree
And they strap these audio recorders in place and then
Peter could study these elephants long enough to know that
It could be days weeks even
Before an elephant would happen to wander By Any Given recorder and make that
Elephant Rumble
The team just walked away
From these recorders
And they waited
And after 3 months
They went back into the forest
Backup the trees and the grab the memory cards
Brought them out
The most important thing is you get back
The sound files
And listen to know that actually you have a recording
Did it actually record
Exactly
Did it record when the first dated came back from this Forest
There is a lot of excitement because every rainforest sounds different
Insects calling frogs calling
The pounding on a tree buttressed by chimpanzee
You have that on tape by accident so we have lots of them
But remember
Peter was listening for elephants
And specifically
For that different
Kind of elephant
So they're going through hours
And how hours and hours of audio
Just like we got it Jurassic Park sound
Act like you can't believe that it's a real sound of Sun
Y'all know that's very true and if you have a speaker that can generate power
Shake your whole body
As soon as I hear it I'm visualizing this 3-ton beautiful animal
Wondering what is it doing when it's doing
But I think the next thing was actually kind of apprehension
Because
50 recorders recording 24 hours a day for 3 months
Save-A-Lot
Stuff to get for
It's a hundred
Thousand hours of audio
Oh but Peter just have a computer do it I can
Can hear you thinking at home well
Listening to elephants is exactly
The kind of work that has been hard to Autumn
That's right it's a human labor story
After the break
Can we teach the robots
Listen for Alpha
Support for this podcast comes from the John S and James L Knight Foundation
Helping NPR Advance journalistic excellence in the digital age
Bitcoin is a huge amount of electricity to power to compute
And that is created some very unique money making opportunities in different parts of the world
It is also causing some government concern
Listen And subscribe to the indicator from NPR
I before we go on
We wanted to just take a quick
Door to knowledge that
A lot of elephants
Good stories are
Like a little over simple
I got a real sense of this when I went to Malawi to try to see now that we ask you can we talk I was getting to talk
For this relatively new fence on the edge of a one-day National
The park when we ran into this local
Ass my name is videos
Shenzhen
Close by
My house is 15 meters
Ephraim betta fish
Before the fence
Were there elephants that came
Around your house
Especially when they come through
A garden where there is food
We had problems
Problems because elephants are attracted to people's guard
Various is a school t
But like a lot of people on the edge of this park
He relies on his own garden and some nearby fields for his food
And if an elephant came to your garden
You could eat the entire Year's worth of crops
Just a couple of hours
Do you have an experience with an elephant
Fortunate that I'm not
Cured
Human-elephant
That's what they're called
And the Really Danger
Curious remember this one horrible day
Before there was a fence
When an entire herd of
Prince kind of stampeded to his village
I did Iroquois
7 people
7 people Wednesday
Yes elephants are magical and incredible when you're a turret
But if you lived
Next to a bunch of elephants
It's not really so incredible
And this dynamic
Contributes to the biggest threat facing
Elephants
Illegally killing elephants
Poaching
Are elephant research
Peter rig
Says that the Smugglers and the international cartels running the ivory
What they'll do
Is it often find a local Africa
Chicken farmer not various but somebody who just had their crops destroyed by an elephant
Dell approach that person
To do the actual elephant
If someone comes in and says hey I heard you lost everything
Go kill that elephant
And I'll give you enough money to buy the food for your family
I don't
I don't really blame that guy who went out and did it
Still
Peter is doing everything he can
How to stop
Poaching
That's what this
Acoustic sentence with all about in the first
Tennis team ever courted months and months of rainforest audio
Sing elephants in rainforest sounds but if they went through the recordings they also had gunshot
I don't think we have any where you hear any elephant call or Screaming after the shots
Possibly because
Elephants are actually kind of too far away for the rumble to be heard or maybe they were instantly killed with
I doubt
But you know
Burst from AK47
Peter's team was going to count elephant sounds for this
Acoustic Forest elephant Center
They're also going to count gun show
This is the best proxy they had four
Poaching attempt
Again
The problem was he had too much tape
50 recorders
Running for three straight
Months it would take a grad student
Listening to that 24 hours a day
6 years
To go through all of that audio
At Double speed
Peter needed a better man
You have I mean you can look at it with
The spectrograph
Spectrogram
This is where you turn sound into a
And if you've seen this it's like a ghostly picture of sound
If you looked at enough elephant sound
You could learn to recognize
So the first way to try to
The count elephant calls is to have a human being sitting for
Pewter
And then like I said of really weird flashcards
Apopka picture of like a minute of rainforest
And then another and then another
And that just flashes flashes flashes flashes and you're looking for that elephant call in there
So that's founder that's good it's faster but doing that with one day of sound
Takes about 20 or 25 minutes
Not
Super
Efficient
Ideally you train a computer to do this for you
And that's what Peters team tried to do
But this is exactly the kind of human labor it's been really hard to replace
Peter's team had to describe to a computer
What a picture of an elephant called
But each one is like a little different and sometimes there's a weird looking one that
You know human would be able to point out but then how do you
Tell computer to
Define those ones in
Two Peters team ended up with
With this like detector program
It had a really broad parameters
Of what it would look
So it's fine signals that aren't actually elephants and we have to sort through that
Time-consuming very time-consuming not an ideal
Luckily for pewter
Another animal researcher had run into this exact same
Let's get this party started
Let's do it
Matt McKeown
Started as a bird rio
As part of my PhD work I was collecting
A ton of recording acoustic recordings
You know sitting on mountain tops with tape recorders
And and then I started to
Text bar how I can collect more data
Just like Peter rig
That was pretty quickly swamped by the volume of recordings he created and to some degree this is like the modern
Problem Ark
Ability to record data
Of all kind
Has outpaced our ability to make sense of
This is what people mean when they talk about the era of Big Data
A huge part of the tech economy now
Are companies that are just trying to come up with ways to get through all the stuff that we can now collect digital
Somat started looking around for solution
He found
The buzziest of all Silicon Valley Buzz phrases
The neural net
Talk about neural networks
Explain what those are pretend I'm a 3rd grader
Well you know basically what it is it's its
A system that's kind of
Based loosely
On the connectivity patterns of neurons in the human brain
Right right so
There is
A lot of really complicated math
Going on inside oven door
So complicated
In fact the computers couldn't handle it until relatively recently
But
We're going to do our imperfect best right now to just give you a sense of what is actually going on inside of it
Let's say you want to show a computer
And how to tell you
Dog
Not.
That is
Really easy for a human being to do but it's really hard
To write a set of rules for a computer to identify a dog
Get to be like
You know it's like a dog I don't know it's like
List all user
It's fluffy
But but I mean not always I don't know it's it is just too much to have
So the idea behind a neural network is
It's a computer program where you don't have to explain everything
But in order to make that program work
You have to give your neural network
A bunch of pictures and say
This dog
This. Dog
Yes you're showing it pictures with a dog and without a dog and telling it which is which
What is happening each time this
Program looks at a picture
Is it you got this first layer of what people call neurons
These are metaphorical now
But each of these neurons is going to focus on some general facet
Of the doggy
So imagine there's one neuron
It's looking at these and thinking like
You know when there is a dog I'm seeing like a lot of
Round a lot of the time
Well I'm noticing a lot of Curves in these
Ignorant they start to learn you know like
I see Brown
Then they are going to light up
I'm in the later layers metaphorical neurons
Refine the analysis
Oh hey look
I got like a tail like a
The tale
Something over here next time these neuron see that stuff
They're also going to light up as well
And this whole process is
Cumulative the idea is that
Dogness
Become so decentralized
In this network
Work that no matter what
Picture you show it
If it's a dog you're going to get some combination of neurons
Lighting up
And being like yeah
This is a dog
Again
To train the network
You have to give it tons and tons of pictures and say
This dog
This not.
And with each new picture of dog
The program teaches
Is itself a little more about dogness
It starts to hone in on the TV
Tiny traits of dogness that are most important
To look for and the network is almost certainly going to
Find ways to identify a dog
That we humans
Wouldn't have even
Pot to tell the computer
Computer to look for in
In the first place
This is what people mean when they say machine
Learning this whole field is called Deep
Learning because of the Advent of modern computer technology
You can make these neural networks that have many many layers
Of neurons
And so you can start to recognize real fine scale patterns
Matt McKeown
Ended up starting a company
Need to help researchers like Peter Rabbit
Set up their own neural network
To dig through there
And his company is now working with Peter and the Elephant listening
Project
To deal
With all that rain
By the way this works is
Is the Peter Rags rainforest
Turned into those specs
Sound
And then Matt McKeown is training a neural network to go through every single rainforest sound and say
Elephant sound
Not elephants
So
50 recorders three-month Siege over a hundred thousand hours of audio
Matt says his neural network will be able to get through all of that
In Just 4 hours
Just 4 hours
Count up all of the
It sounds so Peter can finally know
How many Forest elephants are there and where are they
It may be hard to
Tell a computer exactly what to look for
A neural network and learn
To look
For this
That actually is
A fantastic example of
Two females who are
Performing what we call a greeting ceremony
Again
Peter Rag and he says
These Rumbles
These are a perfect example
Of elephant
Language
They've heard this pattern before when
Elephants have been separated for some time and then they come together to like
Wechat
I think it's very much like
If you run into a friend on the street you know that you haven't seen for a while
It's a back-and-forth 100 how are you and all I'm okay what about you though it's not so good I've lost my jaw
Oh my God
Who knows what they're really saying but it's that
Perhaps that kind of thing
Computer set out to do this audio sensors that neural network was still be
And today it's still being true
They're still showing at tons of elephant column
Yeah it takes a long time
So for the first round of data
Peter went ahead and use the old school method
Telling the computer what an elephant call looks like
And yes
What's precise
Or labor
But it worked
Any idea as a whole
Recording for a selfie
2 track for sale
Peter's team was able to find all those elephants
Play some on a map
Figure out what time it happened
And if you imagine like a TV weather map
Instead of rolling clouds
Esl
Is the kind of thing you need
To make anti-poaching teams is effective
You can say okay we know that elephants are not using this huge part of this park
For these 7 months
We don't need to send any other coaching teams they are because no poachers are going to find an elephant anyway
And you can see
Where the population of elephants
Does moving across the landscape at different times of year
Cool no one has ever known that for any elephant of any
Species anywhere
This has Peter excited
When is neural network
Really trains up
That's when the possibilities really get go
A neural network
Would move
Wayfast
Anyway morak
And you can imagine
Dish Network learning to hear
Kinds of elf
Like when it's a distress call
Maybe some other sign of
And
We have
Two gunshots here or we have AK-47
Gunshots here
If I can be fed out of the rainforest
In real time
Then the anti-poaching people nowhere to go to intercept that poacher that just killed in
Do you think that AI
It's going to save the
I actually do yes
Edina
I think we should play one last elephant called from Peter Rex recording
Okay let's do it
That is a real elephant trumpet and I just I want to say like I feel like my impression is very good art yours mine
And here's the real one that's good
It's good okay I got to tell you I was a little dubious from what I hear them side-by-side it's a lot better
Better than I thought it was
If you like this episode of Planet Money if it helps us if you just send it to somebody or did you leave it there
Rating in your podcasting app those are some of the best ways you can support OSHA
Special thanks this week to the elephant listening project into conservation metrics
And John Keefe John is part of the courts AI Studio
And he is in
Incredibly helpful
We always love to get your feedback we are on Facebook Twitter and Instagram at Planet Money or you can always send
What is an email
Planet Money at NPR. Or
And this episode that you just heard is
Is part of a larger project
Text Dina temple-raston
Is working on it is
Is about
Technologies that are watching us things like artificial
Intelligence data
Surveillance
How does things are changing The Way We Were
Explain a little bit more the project is called I'll be seeing you and it's coming to NPR in September
So I hope you'll keep in Europe
Today's episode was produced by Nick Fountain Darian woods and Michael May
Bryant urstadt editar show Alex goldmark is are supervising
This is planet money from NPR I'm Kenny Malone