He's a big deal now
The founder of Panera Bread but that's when he was in college he was just
Ron
Shake some team getting kicked out of stores
Twist out of a local convenience store where you got kicked out of a convenience store in college what did you do
They accused of shoplifting I did nothing
Are you sure I am positive
Okay Ron Shake
Vowed to never go back to this
Play Store
We open our own non-profit convenience store
If they don't appreciate our business
Let's let's do our own Ron was 19 years old when he
Restore honest college campus
What did you sell
We sold
Everything you might want on a college campus
I know crackers and snacks the beverages cleaning supplies
Ron
Was good at opening stores
He went on to build this little cafe called Au Bon Pain
Into a big chain
And out of that came another big chain called
Panera Bread
There more than 2000 Panera's now
And he runs a good guy is the kind of guy takes his kids to volunteer at food banks on the weekend
And while they are volunteering he starts thinking that
Food pantries are actually really
Inefficient
You might as well
Just write a check
And then one night he's watching the
It was actually a rerun
IBM PC
She said
And they have the story about this Cafe in Denver
Caught saying
Short for so all May
That allows customers to pay what they want
There's the menu with no prices
And the customer those with and those without
At same Cafe
It didn't matter if you had money to pay for your meal
Imran's thinking
The sounds great
I can do something like this
I said we open a cafe every two days
We have more equipment more resources more capabilities
This is this is something we could do
He thinks Panera can do this
Faster
Bigger
And better private sector official
And this is the moment he decides he'll open non-profit version
Panera's
They look and taste like any other
The customers can decide what they want
MyPay
I fundamentally believe that there were enough good people in the world
That they would do the right thing
But I particularly loved
Torturing the cynics
Who were arguing you know
Everybody we know Ruby lunch on Uncle Ron Ron was making a big
Bet
Not just on the business but on human nature
That wealthy people and poor people would want to sit side-by-side for lunch
And that people would be
So generous that
These restaurants would break
Even
And a professor who really knows consumers
Was watching all this
With a lot of it
What was your first impression of the idea
My first impression of the idea was this will never work
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Sarah Gonzales household name
They tell stories about how Brands affect our lives
Today on the show an experiment and charity that goes right to the heart of
Human Nature
The relationship between what we believe in
And
What we will actually spend money on
It's a story about homelessness
Broccoli cheddar soup
And the war between good and evil that rages within every consumer
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses
To design and build their own website
Using customizable layout
And features in
Including e-commerce functionality
3 + mobile app
Squarespace also offer
First built and search engine optimization
To help you develop an online
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR
How to save 10% off
Your first purchase of a website or domain
Panera's are kind of like
Fancy or fast
They're a little healthier and a little pricier
And when Ron said he was going to let customers
Pay whatever they wanted for Panera food
He decided Beast
Special cafes needed to be in areas where there were enough
Horror
People
Who could benefit from the generosity of enough
Welfare PA
Our whole idea here was not
Simply to create another
Homeless shelter another soup kitchen
It was actually the have
A real meal
And a real meal with dignity
So he creates a non-profit arm
Call Panera cares
Instead of cash registers
The cares cafes have donation bins
All the prices on the menu
I just suggested
Note to give customers
Some idea of how much food actually cost
And the whole idea and hope here
Is that enough wealthier customers will pay more than the suggested price
So the needy can eat
For Less
The first location opened in Clayton Missouri near st.
Saint Louis into
Ron actually step down as CEO to get it off the ground I can remember the first day we open the cap
I waited on customers
I waited behind the counter I worked 100 hours that next week into calf
Run then opens more nonprofit Panera's
Chicago Boston Portland
In Oregon
And Dearborn Michigan right outside
Detroit
I was a reporter in the area then
Remember thinking
Hunger such a big problem
Maybe this could actually
No big restaurant corporation had ever tried this
And there was one Professor who studies consumer behavior and consumer ethics who was thinking
What Ronnie's proposing goes against everything I know about how can see
Zoomers
What is the most depressing thing you've learned in
Studying consumer ethics
Oh my gosh
That's a wow there's a deep well to attitude to pull from
Tiana Eckhardt is a professor of marketing at Royal Holloway University of
Well
I'll answer that by telling you that the title of my most recent book on this
Topic which
Just called the myth of the ethical
Consumer
Yep
There are no ethical consumers
Gianna says how people feel about a social issue like
Hunger and how they behave in the marketplace
Are two totally different
Meaning like I
Can hate sweatshops but I might still buy a pair of
Tennis shoes
That
Turn the brand that uses Sweatshop labor
Exactly
So she's like I have to follow runs
Experiment she actually observed
These cafes for years
These Panera cares cafes got going
Soon they were serving 4000 people
And of course there were a few early problem
Like Ron had designed these
Big signs
Explain the model
The menu the mission
We put so much energy into building the sign to tell people
To do the right thing Pay What You Want
Pay-what-you-can
Pay it forward
Apparently people don't read signs
Everyone was confused like what do you mean
Suggested prices
So now they have to spend money to hire someone who could stand at the door and explain how this whole thing work
But whatever like they were serving the needy this is what run wanted
And you know there's a certain kind of person who's going to show up when you do something like this like this kid to take the whole
Bowl of Halloween candy
Yeah they showed up
I can literally remember
Couple of kids
Local
Oak kids walked into our store in in Clayton Missouri
And they
Walked up to the counter kind of laughing
And they said I'll have
3 smoothies and then
Roast beef sandwiches
And here's my Dad's credit card
Put three bucks on
I just wanted to jump over that counter and I wanted to grab the kid around the neck and Wacom
I just want to say don't you get it
Somebody else has got to pay
Ron had to
Keep battling
People's bad impulse
Even his own staff
They started judging
Profiling
People would walk in
And
We would
Assume
We knew
Either
Based on how they looked
Based on how they were
Dressed
Potentially Dredd based on the color of their skin
What they were going to do the staff would be like
Wait
How much did you put in the bin
You look like you could give a bit more
He ends up putting the staff through sensitivity training
But he's really happy with the experiment
About six months in reims as more than half of the customers were paying
The suggested price
About 20%
Extra
And the other 20%
Sometimes
They paid nothing at all
Hate free soup
Which overall sounds
Great
But what Gianna is singing
Sitting there on all her visit
Looks a little different
At the beginning
People who were homeless were bringing in every possession that they owned into the Panera which was typically
In like a shopping cart that's how they would keep their possessions and so you would see all of these shopping carts around
Which also smelled in addition to the people themselves
Set of the managers had to
Yeah come up with rules about the size of bags that you could bring in and things like that to
To manage that situation
It fell on employees in these cafes.
To deal with issues that they weren't really qualify
Like
Mental Health
Can drug issues
Sharon Davis work
Did the Portland
I was probably one of the oldest
People there
Stop this kind of like Grandma Sharon type of thing Grandma Sharon saw the best
And worse
People who was a customer sitting there and she comes up
Oh my God
These people are stink
I can't stand eating like this
Next to I'm really sorry
But they are entitled to a meal
You try to be very very dignus in a graceful about it
And the bathrooms in particular were a big
Try customers were doing things in there that Grandma Sharon should not
Be quite a few of them that were shooting up in there
When they come out the door you know they were loaded
And we'd open the door and look and there's blood everywhere
So then we have to close that bathroom
Sharon says they were trying to do their best
They would refer customers to rehab
Open shelters
Jobs
And things like that
But this experiment was really about food
And employees like Sharon told us the real problem was that these cafes
Worrying attracting enough generous people who wanted to pay more
So pretty early on Panera's cafe started telling customers that
If they didn't have money to pay
They could volunteer for an hour and it
Exchange for a meal you know
Clean under the counter
The first store was in business
For 8 years
But then it closed
Go to the ones in Dearborn Chicago in
Panera says it did not make Finance
Stan's two
Continue to operate Panera
They're no longer trying to
Food banks at their own
Panera is back
Tube donating to them
Writing check
Sharon said she had a month's notice
We poured our last coffee together out of the coffee machine and
Then we closed the door and we all just stood there and looked
New y'all gave each other hugs and so we'll be in touch
And
We left
The parking lot for the last time
And
Gianna our consumer expert says Ron was just kind of naive about the whole thing
He didn't understand how those with
And those without
Would behave next to
To each other what ended up happening is the people who
We're not food insecure
Did not want
To eat lunch with p
People who were food in
And Jenna says those who were food into
Secured didn't necessarily feel comfortable sitting next to those with more means
Either
But Ron is a belief
Even today
He says
The Cafe is closed
Because they're beasts
Rap in the rent
Skyrocket
Not because I didn't
At work what do you say to people
Who say maybe you didn't understand
Like human nature when you started
Wizard
Excuse me
Write this thing work
Usurped
Millions of people
Over many many
Years
And so the fact that at the end of five years or seven or eight we close the store
By no means means that this wasn't a success
Gianna says there are other models
I could have worked better
Like Panera could make people feel like they're getting
A gift
Gibbs
Make us feel
Guilty they make us feel like we have
To give back
Their pizza shops
Some coffee shops in the US that do this already
A lot of the ones that have been more successful than
Panera cares tend to be a pay-it-forward model rather than a pay-what-you-can model
So say it's like a coffee shop for example you're told
Someone who came here before you has paid for your coffee and your handed a free coffee
That's a
The good one
Yeah and then your ass would you like to pay for someone else's
Coffee
Of course
Yes and because this is framed as a gift
It tends to be quite powerful
So you think I've received a gift
From someone that I don't even know
And this summer
I should repay that gift is a very
A very strong Instinct inside people I think
Another thing that would work better
Take those suggested prices off the menu
If you see a price
Tiana says you think that's the amount you
You should pay with no price
People actually give more
The cafe in Denver the one that is
Inspired run that's what they do no prices
Yes soup salad and
That's what we serve every day
Brad Rivendell run Steam caffe
And it turns out they're actually
Pretty different from
Panera cares
They never wanted to come
Fleetly rely on the generosity of P
People they don't want to be self-sustaining they fundraise they have a big Gala every year
And Brad says that if more than half of their customers are paying
They're doing something wrong
It becomes a place where wealthy white people feel good about eating but it doesn't actually serve the mission
Brad says it's actually a terrible business model
If you're trying to break you
This was designed to be a charity
It runs like a non-profit
And it was actually designed to help the people it serves
Like there are cubby
So homeless people have a place
To leave their stuff
There are with a call
Introvert tables
The people can
Sit there and pee
Bistro hours
You know I'm a I'm a middle-class white guy
And so if I ever want to be left alone I go pay $5 for an overpriced coffee and no one's going to bother me but many of our guest there
They are carrying all of their
Belongings if they own are made to feel uncomfortable in
Even if they pay for a coffee I haven't thought about it like that but white men do love sitting by themselves
Coffee shops
And we're good at it
But there is one Panera cares left
After the break
We go
And we pay what we want
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
When is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or mini
That can be open from anywhere
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Dan and I are in the one remaining pay-what-you-want Panera cares it's embossed
And they take their bathrooms
Security very seriously
They change their bathroom codes multiple times
Today what's the code right now
Dakotaz 8053
29921 7
The ladies room
How do you remember that
Hahaha
I make a man I'm kind of a
This is Perry Como
The manager of Panera cares
Pretty much like any Panera with a few little differences like there is this wall of
Day old bread when you walk in
This bread walls for anybody else that's in need
You can come in we have been here you can add what you can
Grab a loaf of bread bring it to the cashiers and weed spices
Good for you
Donation
Right into the wind here is not allowed in there right now is at 4 bucks it's not for profit everything is suggested amount
I've actually never been to a Panera
So what should I order that sounds like they like gateway drugs
Panera
Okay let's order something
We see those
Clear donation bins
Plexiglass plastic
But you have to look really closely
See the tiny type
The top of the menu
It says the prices are just suggested donation
Okay I'm going to do the broccoli cheddar soup
Soup
You like me to Nation today
Meaning like I can donate 928 or I cannot donate 928
It's up to you to just place your value in the bin
Overmuch you wish to donate I got
So I'll do that
How much should you how much should you pay for a $10
She told me that I donated
30 what is that $0.32
The next person that I felt like
Yusuke like I should put more money
Yeah that is a little cheaper but you got to come on but I saw you like hold a water bills
Into the band and just hold it there for like a minute
It was like I was just trying to
Fit in the little slot so many bills cuz you're so generous
Right now this store
Loses
Barry says
They cover about 85
Percent of their cause
Panera makes up the rest
Think this place will be here in a year
I know it'd be here in a year
What makes you so sure
Cuz we run it right
We treat people respect
And it was actually really nice
Be like there were customers on laptop sitting next to you and talking to people in need people
Eating three loaves of unsliced bread out of the bag
There were people volunteering in exchange for food
And I have to say in the end I felt guilty about the $0.32 I donated
Dropped a few more bucks
Listen to the band on the way out
If you have a story idea send us an email Planet Money at npr.org
And check-out household name for more surprising stories about famous brands
Our second season starts right now
Today Show was produced by Darian Woods
With Sarah weinman
Amy Padula and Gianna Palmer and household name
Special thanks also to Susan dobscha
Bryant or sad edits our show and Alex goldmark is are supervising producer
I'm Sarah Gonzales
And I'm Damned about