Support for NPR in the following message
Did come from Pushkin and dust
Resetting the podcast
Broken record
Rick Rubin Malcolm Gladwell and Bruce Hedley
Sit down with the musicians you love
To talk about their lives work and the music
Listen to season 2
Wherever you get your podcasts
There is this one house on ursulines Avenue
And it stands out from the rest
It's in Treme a historically black neighborhood that is
Build a big old houses and a lot of them have
Seen better days
But this one it's
Perfectly cut
It's bright pink with white trim
Fresh paint
It's nicely landscape
Charlene Griffith live here
And when we walk up
She and her husband
I just gotten back from the Garden State
Would you pick up today
We got some got some pain
Hematocrit
Something that could bring some cheer
For the festivities that's to come
Purple yellow and green
UPR going to be in the front
Are those all of all of these except for these two here
Charlene is protect
She knows what she wants and she makes it happen
Even as a kid
When she was 7 years old sheet set up a table in front yard
I had a wet Norman's people call a huckabuck business
Which is Frozen car
With different varieties of flavors
They're like these homemade popsicles in plastic cup
She ran a talent show in her family's garage
Artemisia
She got older it was time for a real job
I don't have a degree I didn't
Complete College
Sounds like a lot of New Orleans
She wanted hospitality
Got a job at a Downtown hotel
You work your way up from
Phones
Cleaning lady
To manager and I can be pretty nasty work
Especially around Mardi Gras time
Housekeepers deal with a lot we have those
Famous
Hurricane drink
And we have a hand grenade drink stat
People tend to become projectile
Mardi Gras Hotel hazard
It's a she figures
Mardi Gras Hotel Hazard pay for the house key
Only seems fair
Soap she goes to the manager with her pet
This is beyond just general
Cleaning this is bio you know bodily fluids that's coming up and he was
Play Charlie we don't offer anything like that there
And I'm like okay well you should
She turns and walks away and her tidy work uniform shaking her head and an idea strikes her that's when
Bed and breakfast
Came to mind
So she quits her job at the hotel and she buys the gutted out house right next door to her for $15,000
Then she spent the next couple of years
Working to fix the place up
Drywall
Plumbing
Staircase
Painting and she did most of it with their own hands
Then Katrina
Ruthless
She had to fix the place up all over again
Are opening a real bed and breakfasts
It just still feels far away
Then one day on the radio
I heard about the Airbnb they had did a newscast and Mardi Gras was coming up
Airbnb
The website the company was coming to Newark
And it would be easy she wouldn't need a front desk her to cook breakfast for everyone
Just choose an enticing named and listed on the website historic
Three-bedroom two-story modern home all the things
We didn't have a lot of furniture is good
We had the boxspring and mattress
And the property was nice and clean
And she doubled her income nearly overnight
She went from making about two grand a month at the hotel to making
For on a Goodman
Changing her life
This is the kind of thing that
Politicians and Community groups at everybody
Wants to see happen
Somebody from
The city
Making good
Reinvesting in the neighborhood
Building
Being a African-American woman purchasing a property here in Treme
Which is the first African-American Community here in the city that's historical
All by myself
And I'm excited about it and I want to keep it
So
Why would her native City
Shut her business
Down
Hello and welcome to Planet Money
Reporter with wwno in New Orleans today on the show how New Orleans set out to help residents like Charlene build
Caldwell and it backfired
Airbnb let Charlene go from hotel worker to Hotel owner
But then everyone else got in on it to even big companies
So many homes
Turned into hotels
That whole block
Whole neighborhood
Change
They got fixed up and they look prettier but they lost the thing that makes New Orleans New Orleans
It's residence
Now Charlene is caught in the middle of the city big
Let it more money and become less interesting
Oriental residence like Charlene to shut down their businesses
Along with the big guys
Support also comes from fidelity
As a Fidelity Wealth Management
You get a dedicated advice
To help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact
Taxes and make clear recommendations for your full Financial
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
To understand why the city would shut Sharlene.
You just need to take a walk down the street
To the other side
Mardi Gras tradition
So imagine this it's Mardi Gras morning it's super early like 5 a.m.
And this tradition happens every year some say it's been going on for like 200 years
Off in the distance you hear it clanging bells and rattles and hand drums this
Walking parade
Waking up the whole neighborhood
And then you will see the skeletons walking
Industry
Yelling out
Bunganut sidebone game
We are going to know
Golden Ball Game
Will you come to remind you
Before you die
This is your heart is real
He is part of this calling
And I'm Mardi Gras morning he and his friends dress up as
Spirit they wear these
Bulbous
Skeleton mask
Where stilson
Horns on their head and they carry these big
Cow bones
Really freaky
And it's super loud
And the point
Is too scared
On Mardi Gras day this day of x
Just to scare them straight
And be like
I've just wondering
Not 10 that's how deliver
And people know this tradition they know with the spirits mean
You're supposed to play along and be afraid
The ultimate people
Big new
I mean we have grown people that with
Take flight when they see the bone game
But in the last couple of years the neighborhood has changed
There aren't as many black families as there used to be
Dohar finds more up smiling as he would say Anglo-Saxon
So we coming down the street
And you might see them
You know what their robes on
Peeping out the door
They drinking coffee and smoking a cigarette
And waving at you you know they don't really know
It's a little sad
He misses when people used to freak out and run away from a cup of coffee
They don't understand
They don't know anything about
Autobahn game
But the same Canadian
Swiss visitors
Visitors are Charlene's customers
It used to be in the city with j
This neighborhood over here
It's for Tori
It's a commercial
And that one over there it's residential no hotels
But Airbnb has blurred the law
Each new home that switches from home to hotel
Takes away a little bit from the old field
Zohar we take from the culture
But Charlene says
She's part of the culture too isn't she
And she sharing that culture with your guess
For them to become a part of the culture as well
Like the time she had a Halloween party
New Orleans
Turn Style which means she had to warn her gas it was
And it would be a little loud
We the owners would be loud
So it would be great if they could come and take part in it
So they came and they dressed up in their costume my husband was dressed as Spider-Man
I dressed up as a witch had my little broom and and
The guest came and she dressed as us
Seamoth lady in like this really flowy dress
We had a great time
Having touristy next door might change the neighborhood
But she sees it as a compromise worth
Some of them have even become a friend
Her first guess still text her every Fat Tuesday
We miss you guys we know what you guys are doing we are working on on this Tuesday 1
We know that you guys are partying out nor
So it just really delighted my heart
Separate like 5 or 6 years or so
Charlene is running this Airbnb
It's her business
She's hosting people from all over the world
And she's making some pretty significant income
With no problem
So she's pretty surprised to be driving along one day and she hears on the radio that the cities concerned about all these
Coffee drinking
Taurus
And there may be going to start cracking down and making it harder for them to come
This was about three years
Get up until then
Anybody could rent out anything on there be
It was technically illegal
But there was
No enforcement at all so it was a free-for-all no limits on
How many places you can rent out where you could rent out a house on there
And this radio spot comes
At the same time that cities around the country are crafting strict regulations about
New York and Seattle in Santa Monica
They're all doing something like that
The regulations
Are coming down
Some like okay well this this shouldn't be a problem you're not I think everything should have some regulations
Charlene Drive downtown to the meeting
Pinterest and goes on for hours
And that's when I realized this this is a big deal here
This is this is affecting
A lot of people in different ways
It was people down speaking the neighborhoods have changed there's no children in the neighborhood is running up and down
It's not the old lady that normally would be sitting on the stoop doing the lookout for the community
And after all that when the council votes they say
We're cool with Airbnb
And Council passes some rules that are
Maybe not quite a rubber stamp
But they essentially said Charlene you can keep doing your thing you can keep building your business
I have to do now is register for a small fee and pay a tiny little
Charlene
She keeps fixing up a place with nice furniture and less curtains
It keeps that paint job
The freshest on the Block
These new regulation
They opened up a boom. For people to buy places
The fix up and rent them out to
Having some
Light regular
Is like an even bigger invitation to invest and if there were none at all because it's
The city saying
We are behind this we made these rules
Clarity
Do your thing
Whole block start
Change it
It's easy to see when we walk from Charlene's block towards the
First people on porches
Is one cheat on a skateboards mother coming home from school and like a grandma hanging out
It's a little baby
And then
On-the-scene Avenue just a few blocks
The neighborhood starts
More and more of the homes that we
Pass has he
Digital keypad locks
Instead of regular key lock so people can check themselves in
510 minutes towards the French Quarter
Call Charlene
And the
Woman at the coffee shop just pointed out
Basically this whole block is Airbnb
And it feels kind of like wearing a hotel it's weirdly quiet for a week
Dino cars
People so we look up some of these addresses on a City website
These four homes are owned by one dude who owns upwards of
You know 20 Properties or more in the city
And he hires a bunch of people
You know
Clean the oven
You know check people in and check people out like this is his hotel
Annie's
He's running he's running a for home Hotel on the same street that it's just
Gianna Venice Hotel
Though not to the people
Richard Kendricks lived here for half his life and he's 83
Everything everything in the back and B&B
Everyday
He says the whole neighborhood needs to be filled with family
It's mostly black families with children
Predominantly
Temperature around here
Cuz you don't forget your signature and around your neck
They said he only knows two of his neighbors now
Lots of lox
Have been bought out by big out of town and
There's this
One company from San Francisco that bought like 200 houses
And then hired managers
Including staff
Running it like
Giant hotel
And making it more expensive for locals to buy houses
To live in Kristen Gilson Palmer was running a nonprofit for low-income homeowners at the time of this
I just started getting calls about Airbnb
What we started seeing
During that period was that
Out-of-town investors would come in
Mumbai property
Edumatch inflated
Cost right because they're looking at purchasing a house
Different than the way home owner purchases a house right
Soap shoes
Ran for city council partly on a platform to
Crackdown on Airbnb
But she's not mad about Charlene
But she wants to get rid of these
Is bigamist
And it worked she wins
The new slate of City councilors takes over
And they're looking to rein in Airbnb
So
The city does it all over again
Another big meeting
Tegan you were there
You are good morning and thank everybody for being here yeah there was a huge turnout there were people pissed off on
Both sides for and against an
A long line for these little yellow cards that you have
To fill out in order to get up to the podium
And speaking
The chambers were overflowing
It was
Tents heated
Suzhou they're running charities
Even the complainers at a city meeting in New Orleans have
And then it's Charlene's kind
My name is Charlene Griffin I live at the ursulines Avenue
I've been leaving here 50 years
And I'm here today is just a people need to wake up
There's so much blood
Short term rental has really Revitalize a lot of communities
And when the city council
Takes all of this in and votes on the new rules they totally flip
They go from about as
Lucent permissive as they can be to some of the strictest in the country it's almost a ban
And this happened last fall
The city put the rules into place but they also say
We're going to study
We're going to see how everything is working out
And essentially
They're saying we might
Change everything all over again this coming spring
But for now councilwoman Palmer has what she wants
The only short-term rentals that are allowed
Are the people who actually live on the property they're renting
An extra bedroom
So basically
You will not have whole house short-term rentals you can only have a short term rental
If you live in the property
The city also says that certain areas
They are goes on
Their commercial and they're fine for your
But other
Places residential neighbor
Like where Charlene live
Only very few situations
Are now allowed
So your favorite room yeah that's okay
Even if you have an extra apartment that is
Attached to your house where you live
That's also okay
But if you don't live in the house
Mike if you are a
A big out-of-town investor with
4 homes on one block
That's not okay.
Or
If you are a local
Hometown business
You bought and fixed up
The house next door
It is also not a
And that shuts a lot of
People down
Airbnb the company says they've never seen this
Before Stephen Shepherd
Says also not such a great idea
Is an economist at Williams College in Williamstown Massachusetts
And he's been studying Airbnb for the past
The problem about
Mucking around with these sorts of regulations is
You could if you don't balance it and
Get the balance right
You could end up
You know trying to keep housing affordable by
Choking off investment
One thing that Economist do know about short-term
Is that they increase overall profit
So Shepherd he did a study using data from you
He found that
When you double the number of Airbnb
It drives up property values by 6 to 13%
Which makes it more worthwhile to
Renovate brings in more money to the community which seems like you're
Should be a good thing for a place like New Orleans where
Mayors and government officials have just
Struggled so much
Since hurricane Katrina
Define anyway
To get people to
To fix up neighborhoods in fix the blade housing so
Airbnb seems to be
Doing that
How is it not a solute
Shepherd says there are of course winners and losers
And you have to weigh them against each other which he did you're saying
You can divide a city into two groups
People who use Airbnb
Add an event
Out there house or just stay there as tourists
And everybody else who doesn't use Airbnb and you're saying
The users they win
And the people who don't
Use Airbnb they lose
I think that's a fair characterization of my viewpoint yes
So I think it makes people who are seeking housing in the city
I bet you are not
Making their homes available
Condo short term rental market
I think it makes them
I worse off Airbnb is bringing more money into these neighborhood
But the other side of rising property values is
Rising rents
And so
It's pushing
People out
And their weirdness with
To the cities
Steppin in it
But these new regulations for not just kicking out the baked salmon
Francisco investors and getting rid of those blocks that have been turned into hotels
They're shutting people like Charlene down to
What the city is trying to do is balance distraida
Of prosperity
With preserving
Culture
In the city
Is making a bargain
It's it's
Just decided on the compromise
We want to stay
More of the same
More weird
Even if it means
We stay a little bit poor
And Charlene
Definitely a little poor lately
I'm trying to
Packages say
Steel claw my way
Call my way
Hold on hold on hold on and
Try to make some fun and because I don't want to dismantle
This whole house
When Charlene walks into an empty Airbnb now its
Christine
But like a museum
Empty
The staircase Cherry varnish
Gathering dust
The beds are perfectly made up for guests
With matching sheet
Only now
Wanda plaza
Sick rap
Normally wouldn't have this plastic on it it would
You know just be welcoming for guests to come in and
Take their leisure
But
That's what you do when a place is Sitting In Limbo
She's hoping that when the city council finishes up that studying
Spring that they'll make an exception for people like
Maybe grandmother her in
I'm still mine Bible baby cuz it's
Did flip flop made so much flip flop
Flip flop back and forth
Yes no yes no
Yes or no
But
No but it could be a yes
For now the money's not
But she's got a new gig
I spent a half of my day out ubering
Because that's what I'm doing to try to
Hold his property out into the city made
Make a decision of what they what they going to do
She says she likes getting to see all the houses around
Especially the ones that have been fixed up in
General Decker
Maybe by other are
Airbnb owner
Even if
The houses are empty now with no tourists or locals
Support for this podcast and the following message come from mizzen & Main
Mizzen & Main dress shirts are made with performance Fabrics designed to look great all day with minimal man
They're moisture-wicking
Wrinkle resistant
And machine washable
So they don't require ironing
Or dry
Check out their gift guide
Lights for the guy on your list
Who is always on the move
Head to mizzen & Main.
Missing in Maine
Look great long
Use code NPR at checkout to receive $10 off your dress shirt
Today's episode was produced by Alexi Horowitz Ghazi and
Megan tan
Planet Money zaditor is Brian Hurst at we are on
Twitter and Instagram at Planet Money
That's where you can see a picture of what Charlene
House looks like
And if you have something happening in your city that you think we should do a story.
Send an email we are Planet Money at NPR.
I know it's called bark and I'm taking Redlands from NPR member station wwno in New Orleans
Thanks for listening
See we also have to
Defend ourselves
You know you never know when
Someone
Get drunk
And and you don't want to run up on you
So we have to have
Some things that can
Warning offer
I mean you're holding a spear with a with that looks like a deer antler on the
Is also for balancing two
Stilt-walkers little tired you can find
Lean on
They did the stick
You know to keep him up
And then pokes a drunk
What's with the antler on the end if you need to
If need to
He also has a sword
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start with
Straight jeans
Madewell offers premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store or go to madewell.com to find your perfect pair