This is part two of our series on recycling part 1
Is the origin story of why we started recycling
He should go listen
In Boston
Alright let's just get this out of the way at the top here
The 3 R's
Reduce
Reuse and then
Recycle recycling is the last option
Although
It sometimes feels like it is the main option
And it is broke
In the United
And to see just how bad it has gotten
You just need to go to any waste and recycling
Except those waste and recycling centers don't really like to talk about how
Broken recycling is
But
We found one place that would
Nogales
Arizona
It's Thursday
Recycling day
And a City truck has gone to everyone's house picked up their recycling
And brought them to a place called Tucson Recycling and waste
Beer bottles
So water bottles milk jugs
Cardboard boxes
Always
Stuff tumbling out of the truck is
Carefully hand sorted and handprints
Soup cans and newspapers and
Peanut butter jars
Open the upstanding citizen
Sins of Nogales Arizona who have made the effort
To help save our planet and our ocean
And the guy overseeing all of this Delbert Gallego
Does that sorting and rinsing using fact
Critical recycling is a delicate process you need to do all that
You have to Triple rinse
The plastic
Eminem if you had the lids on it
That's considered contamination
No lids
Wow
Oh I've been doing that one wrong
So the city of Nogales when
Around to everyone's house this morning and picked up
They're recyclable
They brought them here
And where is all this going to go
It's dumped over here for right now
And went over here for
Trash
The recycling
Is going into the trash
I am watching Christine beer bottles and Juice cartons and cardboard boxes get smoke
Pushed into a pile of wet
Gooey dripping food waste
And Soggy diapers
Our wish would be there
To be able to recycle it but we know we can't we'll end up landfill in that way
This is Kurt wall he's delbert's boss and he says
Something has gone
Terribly wrong
In the world ever
And it's not just no goddess
Cities all over the United States
Are shoving their recyclables
Into the trash pile
Unfortunately
Recycling is is not
I'm not saying it's dead
But
Is it certainly
I wouldn't say life support but it's critical
And I don't want to be the person to burst their bubble
You will not be the one to Break people's bubble
I will burst their bubble
Me and a bunch of cold
Parted economist
I'm there and I'm Freddy Malone today the show recycling
He's on life support cities might be picking up your recyclables but there's a very good chance they are not
Being recycled and that
Might
Be a good thing
If you really care about the planet
Scorbutus NPR Podcast in the following message come from sales for
Salesforce helps you deliver the Innovative personal experiences customers want
Learn how Salesforce brings customers and companies together
At salesforce.com NPR
It has already been uneventful summer in Polish
Yeah between the 2020 debate
And the president's battle over immigration
There's alot going on
And when there's news you need to know about the NPR politics podcast
Is there to tell you what
Not to mention we're hitting the road so you can meet all of the 20/20 content
Olympia was going to drive me completely crazy
The NPR politics
Subscribe
To understand what went wrong in the world of recycling
We called economist
Bevan Ashton Miller at Occidental College
They're generally I teach in environmental economics I'm an environmental economist and environmental economics isn't pretty depressing
In class so I sometimes a teacher class called
Marriage money and motherhood I don't even want to know the findings of that
I have a really good friend who teaches in he's always like
I just love wage gaps they just make me so excited that I've liked on this end
Okay Bevan also knows a lot about the economics of recycling and
She says the first thing you need to know is that in economics
We have Goods
And we have bad
A good is something that you pay money to get that's why we called a good we're very simple people
Annabelle
Is something that you pay money for somebody to take it away
Every time you make a good like
A jar of peanut butter
You also make a bad
An empty jar of peanut
Something someone will need to dispose of
But back in the 1990's a few things happen that made all of our bags
Really attractive
To China
China was making all this
Stuff and shipping it to the US in these huge cargo ships
They
We're bringing a lot of tankers
Into the US that we're dropping off materials
And it doesn't make sense to bring a tanker back empty
Tell some smart person was like Walden
Why don't we just fill those cargo ships up with something useful then
Like
Empty water bottles
China was like we can turn those things into like
Polyester
Socks and sweaters what you're basically just woven out of really really really thin plastic bottles
And that's a market
4 Hour bad
Was born
Eventually
About half of the entire world
Junk plastic
Was being sent
The China much of that coming from the US
And when this woodworking
It is what
Reimagine recycling to be
My peanut butter jar turning into freaking socks I mean that is a modern miracle
But then
Just last year
Something change dramatic
China said
This isn't worth it for us anymore
Turning your peanut butter jar into stocks is creating too much pollution and
Frankly it's just too much work for us now
Because
You guys aren't as good at triple rinsing your plastic as you think you are and you're not even sorting it properly their army
Milk jugs in with the peanut butter jars lid still on
Peanut butter still in the jar
A total mess
And it used to be worth it
For China
To just go ahead and clean this stuff up and sort it out on their end
Because you know labor was
Cheap and so
Cleaning and then recycling our old plastic and aluminum
What's cheaper than creating new plastic and aluminum
Baidu
Drilling for oil and mining for bauxite in the ground which
How we get plaster
Can aluminum but then
China's economy evolved
Labor got more expensive
And China said
We don't want to be the world's garbage
Dump
An actual quote
And so China instituted
A new
Plan
Call Dean National
Sword their name for
Annie's plan
China said
We're only going to take recyclables
If they are absolutely spotless
And perfectly
Separated
Plus
We are going to stop taking
24 different kinds of
Including
Some kind of plastic mix paper
And certain metals
Vistana shocks throughout the entire recycling world
Seemingly overnight
The biggest recycling Market
Shriveled up
And you can see the impact
That this had
In Nogales Arizona
He would see a lot of your
Really wet
Nasty trash in there
Remember Kurt that guy who didn't want to burst AR recycle
Here is the position he's in now
Keep Collective
All these recyclable
But he still needs to do something
China used to buy recyclables
Kurt actually got paid for this stuff
But when China went away
There was no one to pay for it anymore
Now it is on Kurt to pay
If he wants this stuff to get rid of
Whenever you go from being paid for a product
What happened to pay theirs
Absolutely is staying in the
An Awakening
At that time so now
Kurt could either
Hey
$200
To get one ton of plastic recycled
Or he can pay
$30
Get that seem kind of plastic
Buried in LA
Obviously I'm not going to bring it there for $200 a ton
It just simply
Didn't make Financial sense to recycle anymore
And so he has started
Landfilling
And cities all over the US are in the same position
Summer just canceling
Parts of their recycling programs all together
Douglas County Oregon Franklin New Hampshire Deltona
Florida
Broadway Virginia
There are entire cities that are saying
We're not even going to bother to pick up your blue banana
There are no more blue bins
An entire town
Nogales Arizona they're a little more optimistic they're at least making sure people are going through the motion
We don't want to just discontinue we don't want to just do away with it because I think a it'll be harder
Retrain people to
To do what we think is right thing
And
We have the hopes
That
At some point it'll it'll
Start up again
It took Americans so long to pick up the habit of separating our paper and our plastic that if we stay
Stop doing it
Kurt worries
Residence won't pick to have it back up
Once there is a market for pasta
Again
And sometimes when Kurt is
All alone at night and he sees April
Killer Elite
Clean batch of cardboard boxes
His heart goes out to them
It doesn't make Financial sense but
These would make such great new boxes he opened up his wallet
And paste
For that stack of boxes
To get recycled
Because again I couldn't
Bear to see it just going into the land
I could just throw it in the trash wood
Would not feel good at all
But then eventually Kurt says
He couldn't even pay anyone
Is cardboard they wouldn't even take it
You wouldn't even take it because again they've got so much product
They had nowhere to go with it
There have been piles of paper and cardboard stacking up all over the country
Like actual warehouses full of water bottles and piles of paper
Just waiting for some buyer to come back on the scene
So we've got all these recycle
Piling up
What we're going to do about it
After the bridge
This message comes from NPR sponsor KPMG revolutionize your Enterprise with a i
KPMG can help you harness the power of AI to unlock its potential and deliver growth
More
Read. KPMG. Us
Flash NPR
Hell it's called Garcia co-host
Of the indicator podcast
This week on the show in the wake of the
Two huge earthquake in California
We look at how Los Angeles is
Preparing for the high magnitude earthquake
It's science
To say is long overdue and will hit
Directly
We also look at the jobs report
For June which
Confirm that yes
The labor market is slowing down creating
Fewer jobs
Each month that it was last year
And finally we also look
And what's been happening
Deutsche Bank
Disaster
Check out the indicator
Planet Money
Okay so we've got piles
Up recycling
Piling up
Or getting land
Because
China doesn't want our dirty poorly washed and sloppily sorted recycling
So we wanted to talk to some experts about
What are options are
At this point
It seems
The main issue is that like if we
Had perfectly clean
Recyclables then China would still buy
And so we could just
Clean it ourselves yeah but I'm not sure that would be I mean like there's a water question here
Right again Bevan Ashton Miller who teaches all the depressing classes
This is the argument that people are constantly having like do I spend all the water to clean my peanut butter container out
It takes so long to clean out a peanut butter container
An is an economically efficient for me to waste all that water cleaning out the stupid peanut butter
Everything so it can be recycled
Devin says in places like California where water is
Precious
No you should not waste water on this
And hot water
Heated by burning fossil fuels
Forget it
You will quickly undo the environmental benefits of reciting
It's okay maybe we should not clean extra carefully and then ship our recycling
The China butt
All these recyclable things
AR
Piling up all over the US so the US
Is now looking for another country
That maybe doesn't care as much
If our stuff is.
You know the way it used to be with China
So
You expected a time to be passed and it has been passed
This is Thomas Kinnaman and environmental economist at Bucknell univ
Indonesia
India Malaysia these countries will
Except some of the stuff and they have them
Ml go through the same process
Accepting it until they say okay nevermind it's sweeping
At some point it looks like plastic and it's some other plant starts looking like garbage
Is that like
As the saying goes I actually just made that up
Thomas is kind of The Economist when it comes to looking at all the financial and environmental cost
And benefits
Recycling
If you just landfill
Peanut butter jar obviously that has
Cost and Thomas cakes that into a cow
But he says
There are also costs
Do recycling like think about what it entails to recycle that peanut butter
A giant truck has to come to your home to
Pick up
Your peanut butter jar
And then drive it somewhere to get sorted and then drive it to a recycling center and then probably put it on a train which
Takes it to a boat which
Takes your jar Halfway Around the World
Their cost are there Financial cost
Paying the truck driver the boat driver this order and there are of course environmental cost
Like the pollution from
Trucks
And trucks
And trains and boats
And that's where you start wondering okay wait a minute
Is
Recycling worth it
And when you crunch the numbers, says
Moore recycling
Isn't always better
Sometimes
It is
Including in ways that you may not have thought of
You're sort of the untold story is that China's ban may may actually reduce the amount of plastic that ends up in
Neosens
China was not very careful about what got into their ocean for long period of time
And if some of the plastic
Tiles were just too corrupted they could
Do whatever they wanted with that dump them in the ocean
Okay we know that there is a big pile of plastic floating in the ocean and Thomas is like
How do you think you got there
One bottle at a time
Really you could Maginot that big
Pyle plastic in the ocean came from the odd bottle being blown off the dock
San Francisco Bay and it went out there and joined all of its friends and they're all hanging out there also
Off the coast of Hawaii
That's probably very tiny part of it
Countries
Historically dumped
Waste out in the ocean
Thomas is saying that our Valiant recycling efforts have been
Hurting
The ocean
In this cute sea turtles
You're given two options during the middle part of the country to the landfill about 50 miles away
Or put it on a boat to China and ask yourself
Which plastic bottles most likely end up in the ocean
I'll let you answer that stuff
And this gets us to the first
Of what it's going to be several controversial
Thomas Kinnaman
We're going to save you the Google and you can email us your complaints to Planet Money at NPR.
But here Thomas out okay he is an environmental economist he is interested
In helping the planet
So
I know it's hard to hear
But Thomas is saying that at the moment
It is better for the planet
If your
Plastic
Ends up in a landfill
Instead of on a boat
Ship docked
To be recycled
And it's not just about
Falling in the ocean this is about the overall environmental cost
Of that Journey
And actually is analysis finds that
This is also true
4 glass
It's better that ends up in
Paper though he finds it can go
Either way sometimes recycling is better sometimes
But good news everyone
You can still recycle something's
Certain materials
Definitely, says it is
Terrible if it ends up in a landfill
Like metal
Tin and aluminum
Soup can and
Cocaine
Thomas says mining for new aluminum in the ground is worse
For the environment than the environmental footprint that goes into recycling aluminum
Even if we do ship them around the world
Anytime and aluminum can ends up in the landfill is that
Is the problem so we should be should be
Targeting 100% for those materials
We should basically do everything we can to make sure aluminum and other metals do not ever
End up in Orlando
All this time we've been demonizing water bottles
And Lacroix cans have been
Open skating by
I'm going to watch you personally recycle that Sarah Gonzales
Here's the twist
Tin and aluminum
Are still being recycled by the us there is
Still a market
For metal
Give me the crack another bottle
Sarah
I brought back up and keep it in crack it properly
Moral of the story Thomas says
Sarah is going to need to recycle all these
Cans
And she should barrier plastic
Yeah put it on the landfill or or or burn it which is what's happening this Wells and parts the world
Hold on
It is
Better environmentally
To burn plastic
That is not going to go down well
Are some of our listeners I feel like absolutely will not go down well in the United States
You have to travel to our other developed countries in the world
So you are making the case for
Burning flask
It's going to be expensive
Actually the most expensive
Way to dispose of waste
But Thomas says it is surprisingly
The best for the environment
Better than shipping to recycling places all over the world and better than landfill
And Germany and Anna Netherlands and in Sweden if they've embraced a new form of NC
Generation
I refer to his consideration 2.0 consideration
2.0
Thomas's these newer
Fancier incinerators
Actually give off
You were dangerous emissions
That a backyard charcoal BBQ
He calls incineration
The Cadillac plan
Because
He says
Basically solve all of the problems
Incinerators
Generate electricity and hot water and the ashes
Are used for things like sidewalk tiles
It is
Very
Expensive but he says
Incineration 2.0
Is the future
That's a ridiculous that that's a ridiculous
Know that you're not being invited this is Eric Goldstein and attorney with the natural resources defense Council
And Eric is so not down with
Incineration 2.0
Well some people have said that
I guess. They don't say to me
Directly
They know that would be a mistake
Well we wanted to talk to Eric and the nrdc because
They represent another ideology
It's more absolute
Well we like recycling
They say
We owe it to the planet
To find a way
To make all kinds of recycling
Plastics are made from fossil fuels
If we continue to utilize every bit of
Coal and oil
Petroleum
That's buried under the ground
We're going to have a planet that is uninhabitable
Eric says the minute you burn or landfill a plastic jar instead of recycling it
You just took a resource from the Earth
The oil to make the jar
And you didn't even try to use it as much as possible you never gave that resource a second life
Not good and he says
Thomas's calculations
Are based on how things are today
Where we have to ship things around the world to recycle them
If
The US were to invest in more recycling plants
Domestically
The calculations would change
It could make
Sense to recycle
And
We also need to recognize that maybe it shouldn't all be left up to municipalities to solve this problem
And that manufacturers or the bear more of the burden
For figuring out how to deal with this ever-growing amount of waste that we're generating in the United States
Make less
And useless
Reddit
That is the best thing we can do
And our environmental economist
Thomas Kinnaman
Totally agree
It's just that right now a lot of things
Commonplace
Your shampoo your
Peanut butter
So what are we supposed to do
It's okay to
Put it in
The garbage pile
I didn't landfilling feel okay about it
Bad luck weekend
Putting a plastic
Container
Into your trash can
It is going to
Feel
You're going to want to pull it out
And put it in the recycling bin
Thomas knows this Earth
Very well
I recycle actually all my plastic even though my own data suggested is now they good to
You still recycle
Yeah I'll even send out a little bit before I
I put it into the container
If you have a story idea send an email Planet Money at npr.org
Yes I have a newsletter just the right amount of economics
Spare your inbox
You can subscribe but going to npr.org
Planet Money newsletter that is
Npr.org
Planet Money newsletter
Today show with Bruce by Alexi Horowitz Ghazi and Liza Yeager
Bryant or status or show
And Alex goldmark Hisar supervising producer
The wave Canyon we are still recycling
If you really want to be good to the environment you're just going to have to do a little research
Find out how your city is responding
I'm sorry
I'm Kenny Malone
We have to give a special things
To Lowell Harrelson of Mobile Alabama
He is basically
The reason why the United States started residential recycling
And his story was part one of our series
And we thank you for listening