This message comes from NPR sponsors snowfall
The only data warehouse
Built for the cloud
Unlock deep Data Insights with the instantly scalable
Cloudbuilt data warehouse
Start your journey towards data-driven decision
It's snowflake. Com NPR
Hey it's Allie helm
There was big news yesterday out of my home state of Calif
The giant utility company at Pacific Gas and Electric or PG&E
Filed for chapter 11
Bankruptcy
Action
PG&E is one of the nation's biggest utilities they serve about 16 million
People
And this news comes after
2 years of
Really bad wildfires
Across California
Investigators have said that PG&E equipment caused
Some of those fires
And the company is facing billions of dollars
Potential liability
Last year we did a story about wildfires and Fire and Ice
Navigation
And the questions we ask then are right at the center of what is happening with PG&E
So we're re-airing that story today
It originally ran it February 2018
They're these videos you may have seen a while back it felt like they were everywhere for a while they're shot
Cop from cars driving down the 405 freeway in Los Angeles it's dark out the car
Cars drive through this Valley and they pass between two Hills that aren't completely
On fire it looks like the cars are driving straight
Straight down into hell I grew up
Not far from those Hills and I spent a lot of time watching these videos
Wildfires
For spreading throughout Southern Calif
Fornia it was
A really bad viruses
I'm about to get on the 405
I went out to Los Angeles
Because I really wanted to
Stand on those Hills
I wanted to see
What do they look like now
So I drove up there
I got out of my car and right away I saw a house that has
Nearly burned wow pass the house there was a trail leading up into the Hills
I can see the 405 freeway down blow me
Trees oh my God there's like a shell of a car on the side of the Hill
It's like walking through a weird Wasteland it's really eerie
I don't know what exactly I'm looking at except that the fire was
Definitely
Here
But I cook someone who
Would know what he's looking at
Hi are you Robert
Hello Robert Rowe agree to meet me here because
He can look at a burnt up Hillside like this
And read it like a book
He's a former firefighter and for more than a decade now he has had his own fire investigation come
I design my own logo
What's your look up little guy with a magnifying glass with a flat top and
Espiral Got Run
And your Biro.
We start walking up the hill together
So when you walk
Up here
What do you notice
First I mean to me it just looks like a sort of
Apocalyptic
Bland
So as we're approaching a
A shrub year
We're going to be looking at Robert starts
Turning over rocks
Pointing out trees that are burned almost
Despot that were in it's like
One chapter of the fire that burned here was called the skirball fire
A discoloration on the
Reading this
To see where the Flames were coming from
Were they traveling up the hill or down the hill or across the hill
When we got up to the peak
He tells me that fire travel up there so there's no question
Did you see that right when you walked on the scene
Well
Yeah pretty much when a wildfire breaks out
Pyro cops like Robert
They show at the scene and they have enormous
Power
Because
The spot the fire started and the reason it started
Those are going to have huge
Consequences
For a lot of people
You can identify the source of ignition down to fraction of an inch
And it becomes somebody's equipment
That either failed or somebody's action
Then
Somebody can I go to jail
Or somebody's going to have a hefty recovery bill but they're going to have to pay
Billions
Hello and welcome to Planet Money on Sally home
And I'm Kenny Malone
Wildfires are not like other natural
Jaster's because you
Can't pin an earthquake on a single Reckless teenager you can't
Teresa hurricane back to the first gust
But with a wildfire
You can find your way back to the first
Spark
You can find a reason this disaster happened
And sometimes
Someone has to pay
Today on the show
How to find a source of a deadly wildfire
How to find the line between a natural disaster
And a human one
Support for this podcast and the following message come from fidelity
As a Fidelity wealth management client
You get a dedicated advisor to help grow and protect your way
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes
And make
Clear recommendations for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage services
LLC
There's an official list
Of the top 10 most
Destructive wildfires
In California
If you look at that list
Six of those fires happen
In the last
2 years
Which is to say
Between October 2017
And the end of 2000
It has been to
Horrific
Fire season
And next to each of those fires on this little list
Is like a note
Were the cause of the fire wood
Go
Pepper almost all of these recent fires
It just says
Under
It could take months for those investigations to wrap up
And so
We're going to look back at a different fire
One of the biggest most destructive fires in California history
And we're going to tell the story of
How that blank got filled in and
Residents are getting worried that they must leave their homes immediately within just the first few hours that the Witch Creek
Fire burn that fire quadrupled in size and right now
October 21st 2007 The Witch Creek fire started
Somehow
And then spread
Shockingly fast
It wasn't clear exactly how bad the damage would be but
One thing was clear
The Witch Creek Fire was going to be one
The big ones
I was on duty in Riverside unit as a fire captain specialist
This is Matt gay
He works for a state agency known as Cal Fire
Bass we got a phone call
Sending me to the wish fire
Lydia origin causes
When is the murder you attended
If when there's a fire
You send me
And soap Matt drive towards the area where the first reports
Which means
Gives driving towards
The fire
Which is pretty intense
But Matt seems
Is Chill about it
Fairly typical for a job
Yeah it was it was barely
Somax driving through two sided fire
And he can see which way the Flames are blowing in the wind
So he knows roughly where the fire is coming from
He drive down to the edge of the burn Zone
There's still some smoke around black and grasses everywhere
This is where he start
His investigation
The part where I was at was on top of a ridge
The wind was blowing to the point where that at moments it was very good
Difficult very difficult
But you can definitely feel the winds blowing your progress as your walk
The format can figure out what started
This fire he needs to figure out
Exactly where
Is Firestar
And the fire leaves a lot of signs
But an investigator like Matt can follow back
He can see the direction that the fire burned across a tree it's like an arrow pointing
Imports thesaurus
Same is true with
Charred rocks on the grill
Trash
Cans and bottles anything that's left on the ground
He walks and walks
Follow the fires Trail and whines up at what he is almost certain is
Vspot the fire started the signs are
Pointing towards the spa
There's a dirt road winding through this Rocky Ranch Land
You would not be surprised
Cowboy riding through the background
And this is the point where the process
Changes
Now that is looking for the actual
Cause
Fire and it is sort of like the game
Clue like he's figured out
That the crime was committed in the conservatory
And
He doesn't just get to look down and see if there's a wrench or revolver lying there
He has to eliminate all of the
Weapon choices
And figure out what actually started this
Yeah that's a process process of elimination
It's a way to make sure he
He's being as
Thorough and scientific
And Matt has been like
Fire investigator school he has a whole list of these potential fire causes in his head
Used debris burning
Lightning
Spontaneous combustion combustion
What is that
This is where I often times you will see you in
Like a mulch pile
Under the right conditions can
Sophie and
Yes
That's kind of insane
Okay
Somat looks around for mulch piles
You didn't see anything
You check the dirt for tire tracks because cars can start fire
He looks berglas
Bottles
Apparently in rare circumstances some light can refract
Through a glass bottle
Start a wildfire
Matt doesn't see anything like that laying around
How about smoking I don't care about you know
Don't smoke a cigarette out your car window or whatever is that is that a real thing
It's
Not as common as one might think
All my partners and I
Cherry pack of cigarettes in the truck
And
We tried it and I have yet to
Mets sifting through dirt
Shearing under rocks
Checking weather reports
He sees no cigarettes
No signs of arson no reports of light
Well at this point after all those
Right now we're looking at the power
The Powerline
Not really technical at this point in our conversation
He speaks carefully
I was able to observe damage to the power lines
Where it appeared to be small sections of the Powerline worms
When you said small sections were missing he means that there were Little Nick's in the metal wire
Are spots of visit
Do you sort of thing
Did you know what's going on at that point
At this point it's not a 100%
Determination
But
I've got something that bears further follow up
Here's the part of the story where we say the company that owned those power lines San Diego Gas & Electric
Declined to be interviewed
Never remember Matt starts this investigation on day one of the fire and within a day or two he is already
Zeroing in on a car
But
He won't release information until he's done
Complete investigate
And so he keeps on investigating
In the meantime
All the public knows at this point is that the Witch Creek Fire is burning
And spreading and is very day
People actually did die in this fire
And other people are trying to escape
Some of them are recording videos as a cruiser home thread
Chillax is here
You can hear all the fire trucks in the distance
One person looking out his window seeing all of this
Harry single
In very short order
The sky
Wildfire was moving dangerously close to Terry Cinco
So you were ready you were
Pretty much packed up
Stuff I really did not want to lose weight
50 years of photographs and that sort of thing
Cancel documents but that was
Mostly photos
Terry's able to laugh about this now
In part because the fire spared his house but
He's an attorney and
He's part of this Niche legal industry
Actually more like
Two armies
It start lining up when a wild fire starts to spread
Harry in the past has represented victims of wildfires just like this
And so
Terry starts
Getting calls from people who are losing their homes
And they're saying
Terry
Is there going to be anything we can do about this
And on the other side of the
Car companies
Who are calling their attorneys and wondering
Are we going to get sued for this
And some of them may have called
Randy Campbell
Anything that can create a spark
Can anyone who can be responsible for creating that spark could be a client of mine someday
In 2007 Randy was a lawyer for a cable company
And a tree trimmer
Moving company that got sued over other big fires burning near which cricket
Randy has been a part of this Wildfire legal world for
Years
He says
When a fire starts spreading you'll have all these opposing lawyers and
They hire private fire investigators
Insurance companies have lawyers and
Their own investigators
They're all showing up on the perimeter of these buyers
Sometimes
Literally
I'll go to places I was working a fire in Texas Nathaniel still burning I'm walking down this dirt road missed a small town
Town in Texas I turn a corner
And there are five guys I know
Sounds like a traveling Road Show sometimes
To Randy hears about the fires in San Diego and
And he goes down there
Terry the lawyer for victims
He's there to both of them are getting information
From their
Gators word is
Going around that power lines may have been involved in one of the fires
And so these two legal armies are gearing up
But the official word on the cause
Is going to come
From Matt Gilbert
What he found
After the break
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Should come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solution
Strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org
Matt Gilbert had Cena's damage power lines
The origin of the Witch Creek Fire but
To be sure about the cause he got in touch with the
The first person to report the
What's a pilot
Who works with the same state agency is
Cal Fire
The pilot was in the air over which
Creek and saw the fire when
Still small
Matt wants to know if he
He'd see anything weird around that spot
And the pilot says
You know
Okay did see something
Power lines
Observe the line of
Bluish colored flashes
That works
Blowing With the Wind waves
Power lines
To be as certain as possible Matt gets access to data from San Diego Gas & Electric about those very Powerline
Fine sea salt the area of origin
It's her technical data but
He reads it
And conclude
On the day of a fire
Just minutes before that fire was first reported
Something happy
With the power lines
That very well may have caused
The first Spark
So at this point are you 100% sure
At this point I was comfortable releasing the official causes of
Would you say 100% I mean
Basically at this point when I
Based on all the available information I have
I think in that Gilbert speak that means he's Shore
He says in the scheme of fires he's investigated
This one was pretty clear
Enzyme that releases the official cause of the witch Queen
Greek fire
It was the power lines operated by San Diego Gas
Electric
Lawyers had already launched into the legal battle lawsuits had already
You been filed
And now with an official cause
Even more Suits start come
How many cases were there about this far
I think
2000 kisses
That number includes the Witch Creek Fire and those two other fires that were burning nearby at the same time and it was actually Eva
Even more than 2000
All told there were about
100 claims
Van by those fires
Loads of people sued San Diego Gas & Electric
San Diego Gas & Electric
Turned around and sued
Some other companies like
Randy's clients who are in charge of tree trimming for example
Victims Sue those companies as well
Kenny everybody is suing everybody
And
In the end
The companies
Do not admit fault or liability
But they do pay a lot of money in settlements
In total for all the fires plus legal fees
More than 2 billion dollars
Got paid out
That money got paid out by a number of entity
All told San Diego Gas & Electric
Themselves
How to pay a reported 379 million dollars
The lawyers and two people
Who lost money or stuff
This whole process
Witch Creek Fire industry
It dried out
A
Long
As of 2018 there were still some lawsuits and loose ends getting sorted out
More than 10 years after that first
Terry though the lawyer for the victims
He's settled all his case
I asked what it felt like when he settled the last one
Emotional experience
Going through that
You're supposed to be representing
And you
Terry says these big settlement payments do a couple things
They mean that victims get help rebuilding Our Lives
Money on top of any Wildfire insurance they may have
And the settlements also hold companies accountable
So they'll do all they can to prevent the next big wildfire
Get to prevent a disaster
But this raises an almost philosophical Quest
What is a natural
Disaster
And what is it disaster caused
Like if a deadly Wildfire is started by a lightning
Strike is it a natural disaster then
Probably
How about a bottle
Left there by human
Just the wrong way by sunlight
Is Hannibal the Foster
Maybe
And it started by a power line
Filter by humans
Who are supposed to be making sure that it doesn't cause a fire
Seems like that could be a human disaster
But climate change maybe making it harder to say what is an act of God and what's an act
The man like
What if a spark comes from a power line and then it lands on super dry brush that is dry because of a historical
A long drought
Where does the natural disaster end
Human disaster
Begin
Back above the 405 freeway in Los Angeles I was
Heading home out of those Burnt Hills
And I stopped in front of that house
Oh my God you can see the the roofs caved in exposed pipes there's
Black and bean sticking up
We still don't know the source of many of the big fires that
California last year
But
Investigators actually did find the cause of this one
It was a cooking fire in a homeless encampment a little bit down the mountain
Any Spark
Can start a fire
But not all Sparks are financially
Sequel for the Spire there will be no huge settlement to help pay the price
Tell us what you think of the show you can email us Planet Money at NPR
LRG or find us on Facebook Twitter and Instagram Today show with produced by Nick Fountain Alex gold
WorldMark is our senior producer Brian Hurst at a tattoo shop and Scott McClain
Fire ant Justice John Trotter and lawyer Kenroy Malone and I'm finally home
Thanks for listening