This message comes from NPR sponsors snowfall
The only data warehouse
Built for the cloud
Unlock deep Data Insights with the instantly scalable Cloud build data warehouse
Start your journey towards data-driven decision
It's snowflake. Com NPR
In 2002
Tim Damaris noticed that
Sales at his
Company
We're slipping
And he couldn't figure out why
Tim was working for
Small company in Indiana called
They make things
That handy people keep in their garage epoxy glue spark plugs
Engine degreaser
And Tim's job was to travel the world going anywhere he could sell a broke
I was allowed to go as long as I could as long as we brought back business and
We felt like Buccaneers going to these Emerging Markets
Congo in the
And then in Russian
Ghana Cameroon
Maybe you've never heard of a bro
I certainly hadn't
That's because
None of the stuff that makes
Actually get sold in the US
But it's really popular
And a lot of other play
Places where made in America
Carrie's extra cash
Today when you refer to a roll of masking tape in Pakistan
They simply asked can you get me a roll of a bro
Big deal in Pakistan
Anyways
Tim couldn't figure this out
Why were his sales
Slipping
And then
He heard from a customer who had seen some counterfeit Abra Prada
China
Tim gets on a plane to investigate
Its first.
Is this trade show that everyone in his business ghost
Canton Trade Fair is one of the largest trade fairs in the world
His first day there Tim's walking around this massive exhibition
Hunting for Clues
And then suddenly
Freezes I peered around the corner hiding really behind a booth
And I looked around and I was literally
Shocked to see what I was in front of me
In front of Tim is a booth that
Looks to be
Inoperable
The thing is Hatboro never
G4 booth at this Fair
It's a same logo same colors and products same everything
Only
No one inside the booth
Actually
Worked at Abra
They were passing out a burl business cards
Abril catalogs with all our products in it
To my arrow customers that were visiting so it was total confusion oh my God they were telling people they were the
Abro subsidiary in
China Tim knows Arrow doesn't have a subsidiary in
So we go
Straight to the show officials
He provides documents showing a bro has a real trademark registration for a bro in China
The officials confirmed this with authorities in Beijing
And then boom
Favorite
They will raid
Get the fake aerobus
We had police Personnel
There were military personnel because the military guys in this Entourage strain
Absolutely absolutely because the military is part of
These trade shows in China because they
I want some of the companies
So I'm
Marching I've been leading my Army a men
I feel like a gentle going to battle I mean it was kind of scary but it's kind of exciting Tim gets to the booth
And get right up in the face of the man who seems to be in charge of the operation
I said
The party's over Mister Avril
Is here then the Chinese guy turns to him and says
Is very calmly
No
Your
He reaches into a briefcase and pulls out a set of documents
He says shows
She is the one
Who owns the Avro trademark
Mark in China
Everyone just sort of
Looks around at each other
Stunt
And the show official start backing off they don't know who to believe he
But Tim
To know something they don't know
He points to a four foot tall poster inside the booth it's a blown-up photograph of a woman who appears on every page
Package of a burl epoxy glue
I said the older who is that woman you have the photo
He said that just Western model
Have that phone
I lost
I just lost
I said that is not a western model that is my wife
And that time I just ripped out my wallet I pull out a picture
Tell my wife I be careful last 3 years
It's throw it on the table in front of the owner of the company
I said first you steal our corporate identity
I know you're stealing my wife
Elsa I've been playing this moment over and over in my head
It's like that moment
In Good Will Hunting where Matt Damon
Goes up to the guy and he's like
Yeah well I got her number how do you like them apples
The next day the
Fake eyebrow Booth is empty
With a sad piece of tarp
Flow rate over
So
Was that the end of the story
I wish it was but that was only the beginning of the story
Hello and welcome to Planet Money
I'm Nick. And I know
There's a story that's taken hold
About China
Little something like this
China is
Garbage at protecting intellectual property
But eyebrows story is
Yeah the reason I even know about
Because last year when the Trump Administration was collecting horror stories about American companies screwed over by
China
Abro raises hand
Instead
China is doing a great job
We were like
What
We want to hear that story
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
When is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimum
That can be open from anywhere
In 5 mins
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
So Tim gets back to the US and he's telling anyone who will listen about how he took down his chai
Chinese counterfeiters
With a picture of his wife
Yeah
About that
Few months later Tim is in Saudi Arabia
Walking through Market when he see something that looks
Like AB Rosa Parks
But you notice is there something different about the packaging
Right where that picture of his wife
Usually appears
The woman had an Asian face
They kept the same outfit my wife is wearing but just cut her head off and put the Asian face in there
Wait till it was your wife's body on the bottom with an a
At the jogger fit waist body
Asian face
Brake lever
It's just so petty
Fake eyebrow took Tim's
How do you like them apples moment
It said how do you like them apples right back
And that right there
Is the moment that Tim daoust
Himself
You guys down
My wife's picture is the face that launched a thousand lawsuits
But the for a broken bring any lawsuit
Against fake abro
We need to figure out who these imposter
Are they trace the counterfeit Goods to Hunan
Providence to a company called
Cunanan
Magic
The person at the top of Hunan Magic
Is a man named un homework
Tim realizes
He's actually method
He's the one Tim confronted
Inside the booth in China you're going to be hearing a lot about you and homeway and Hunan match
Taking this story and we wanted you to hear their side
But after a long back and forth they decided they didn't want to talk to us so
According to Tim
The next thing that happens
Is Avril filed a lawsuit
In Chinese court against
Hunan Magic
But it's slow going
In the whole time
The Apple brand
All around the world
Is taking a beating
Emily came out with circle
Other parks that we'd even have like a rat poison
They call it a burl rat poison
They were doing all kinds of wild
He said the product Hunan magic is selling Under The Apple brand they're horrible
Apple glue for example
Normally
Has a shelf life of one year minimum
Hunan Magic
Counterfeit glue would get hard in the tube within days
Whoever decides
It needs another
Rose Hunan magic could end up killing their business
It was time to bring in the
Professionals
Easy Pulp Fiction
Yeah
Okay so when they got the two dead bodies in the back of the car you call in the wall
We were kind of like that portrayed by
Bill Mansfield is a former private investigator who helps people with
Special trademark
When a lawsuit just isn't enough
He used to go undercover as
The counterfeiters
Usually a Russian for
For whatever reason
To collect Intel on badly behaving com
Bill will be the first to tell you though
He does not look the part of a typical badass
I'm perfectly round I'm A Perfect Circle if you saw me
You mean your
Your rotund
I am I am
I am a
Sphere
With legs and arms
And we'll head on
Wake mr. happy you know the book character
Yes okay yes
What is work though
She is not so mister
He tells a bro
The surest way to get these guys to stop
You got to make it hard
You got to make counterfeiting
So costly so painful that the counterfeiters will have no choice but the backup
And so far
That's just not happening in China Seville says
I didn't bring these guys on to home turf
He digs around and finds an obscure law in Louisiana
Which is incredibly harsh when it comes to
Counterfeiters
Like down there
You can get sentenced to
The hard labor
Counterfeit
Okay so you were looking at that and you're thinking I could get you in home way
On a chain gang
That is my goal
Yes
Because because the system
He was in
It wasn't tutoring him in any way but Tennille you at home way on this counterfeiting laws
Bill needs to get him on Louisiana soil
So the police can arrest him
Bill hatches a plan to set up a
Fake company in Livingston Parish that starts doing business
Suicune and magic and is fake company orders shipping containers full of counterfeit glue from Hunan Manor
Which will become the evidence they need for an arrest
The relationship going great and at one point and undercover guy at the
Fake Louisiana
Tells Hunan Magic
You should come over to Livingston Parish sometime for a visit
Teach us how to grow our business as your distributor
And they accept the invite
Bill has just two weeks to set up a
A sting operation
The plan is to give you and homeway
A tour of the fake company which bill needs to build
From scratch it had to look lived-in had to look real
It had to be so that you dug into it
You would find things I liked that didn't make you suspicious
But they confirm that this was a real living breathe
And that people walked out of it Friday at 5 p.m. and they walked back in
Monday at 8 a.m.
And there were things going on in the we had to
Fake storyline
Built into it
Like what the people
Do the people in the office were having an affair
And if you if you'd wish group
Well if you look through the trash you find crumpled-up little love notes between them
The day of the visit rules around Representatives
Magic
Show up
But not
Un homework
He's the one a brownie.
The one they wanted to arrest
So dummy
Peanuts farted
Bill sting operation was a bust
But then
Couple months later
Coonomagic
Unexpectedly calls of a bro
And makes acid
Surprising
Hi res space
What coonomagic
Become one of your manufacturers
We are making a bunch of your stuff already anyway
I was listening to this
Yes and thinking
Wait a minute
There is still an arrest warrant out
4 yuan hongwei in Louisiana
All we have to do
Is get him on us soil and he
He's finished
We love this idea y'all should come to Indiana
What's me
Ian Holloway is also not an idiot and said no I don't think so but
I will be in London in three way
Let's read
And that is when Bill Mansfield
Call from abroad
Your mission should you choose to accept it is to get you and hongwei arrested in London and then extradited to the US
Our chance to finally falling over
But it was very soon and it was
In another country
And it was my job to figure it out make it happen or to some extent all this might have been
Bill Spence three Sleepless weeks trying to organize the arrest
Chinese City
In London
Based on a warrant from Louisiana
And by the time he touched down in London at Heathrow Airport
His plane taxied left instead of right
Came to a stop
Please came on took him off in car
Jen homeway
Is behind bars for a while
And then right before his extradition hearing
He post bail
Annie's release
What he's told
You have to remain in
But instead
He disappears
After the break Abril finally figures out how to shut this whole thing
It does not include catching you and hug way that's just never going to happen
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
When is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimum
That can be open from anywhere
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
It's not like the US government
Wasn't doing anything
How to protect a bro
They had a guy in Beijing working the case
His name is Mark
Cohen when the state department created a new position at the embassy to deal with counterfeiting in China
Mark was the one who got the job
He was the
Perfect person for the gig
Not only was he an IP lawyer
He has this
Deep understanding of Chinese culture
Is Mandarin puts mine to shame
So
Could you recite
Say a Tang Dynasty poem for me right now Andre
You know that's the most famous part of the problem
Albert was having with Hunan match
Any words that a bro isn't the only company you at home ways knocking off
Mark Slade
I want to talk to this guy
Guy see if I can reason with him
But you went away
Is really hard to get in
He's a type of Conifer that we used to call
In Chinese record of Shanghai Mountain stronghold County
These guys who operate
Been kind of more remote harder to enforce places
Saumur travels down to Hunan Province himself
To see if he can meet face-to-face with you and homeway
But before he confronts MP decide
I better go talk to the local officials first
Sometimes they can be helpful in this matter
But when you get to their office
He sees something that makes him really nervous
I saw a
Window display
With a bunch of awards given to Hunan match
What were the awards for
Famous brands
Innovative company
High-tech company
And you could see the way you could see these awards today if you go to the one on Magic website
Under Chinese word says award
They're still bragging about these awful bright and the dates you will notice
R2000 to mm
3 mm
When they're counterfeiting products a little typical game you know
Pretend to be the most honorable company in the world to your own
Countryman
Knock off
Right then and there are two sides
It's just not worth it
Because all these Awards
Local officials
I probably going to pray
Protect Hunan
I decided it was
It would be unsafe
For me
To try to meet with local government officials
Azan physically
You at home way may have been pressed local
But they weren't there to protect him in London set in motion a series of events that make out
Counterfeiting
Chest
Painful and nausea
Conway
He was threatened with hard labor in Louisiana had to spend
Weeks in a year
4 in jail cell
And then had to secretly sleep
The China
Not the usual cost of doing business
For making knock-off clue
Even though Bill had lost you and homeway in London
Bill
Actually one
Because after London
Jen home
Stopped
Counterfeiting eyebrow products
The bills problems
With a burro counterfeiters
Didn't quite end there
Reading jinan Magic beating this major counterfeit
It was similar to how when we beat the Soviet Union
What do you mean
Well
After the Soviet Union fell there was a part of us that said a we won the Cold War
We don't have any more problems
What we just had were smaller and differ
Here's what was happening
Even though Hunan magic was out of the picture
It's temporary success at ripping off a bro had spawned copycat counterfeiters
Elsewhere
In
Gola Ecuador
And of course other places in China
What you meant ever had
A bigger and more complex problem
You couldn't just hire Bill
Go around the world planning
Expensive sting operations
An extradition
What do we do we have to stop the counterfeiters
But now we've got a bunch of them
And we have to do it in a way that still leaves a business profitable or what's the point right
But when it came to China bill
Remember loves and elaborate sting up
Operation discovered over time that the solution
What's an old EX
Complicated
More expensive
Instead it involve drinking a lot
Of teeth
It's very good what kind of end
Government T I'm not real clear
I'm not I don't have I have what's known as a
The gutter palette still has found that in China
Local authorities have a ton of power
So what he does now is set up lots of meetings
Meetings with the people who can launch investigate
These counterfeit products
An arrest counterfeit
I always prefer criminal a
An arrest is always what I'm looking
A tot
Sometime in jail
Is never worth selling counterfeit glue
If you ask Bill
This is how to stop
In China and Elsa
Lots and lots of meetings
He's been at it 11 years
He says
He traveled to 55 countries gotten at least a dozen
Convicted and millions of dollars of counterfeit go
Has destroyed
How do you reward these local authorities after a raid.
To take me out to dinner
I wore them with the the key currency all bureaucrats love
Which is
Thank you
And often a small plaque
A small Factory can put in their office
Is there a Sephora in black and it says you know that you helped us and I like to give him
I make sure they know who they help that they see pictures of people that way
Hang up in their office that's really why they're helping you
The people I'm working with you
The date they want to be people want to be appreciated for their work
You know I thought a lot of the time never bribed
PPL bill
No never
We ask Bill about bribery several more times
Anytime he swore
It never have
But I have to admit you symbol to me
The idea that the solution to protecting intellectual property in China is
Justice with local officials
How typical
Is eyebrow
We keep hearing stories about how the Chinese don't respect intellectual
Stories about trade secret theft
Patent infringement forced
Technology transfers
How can I beat that the solution to all that
Is just a sit-down with a lot of bureaucrats
Drink a lot of tea
And give out a lot of plaque
I went back and I talked to Mark Cohen about
And he was like
Publix Sumter
Pictures of what you got
China does protect some for an IP
He pointed me to cases involving vacuum
Water heater
What he said was important to look at
Is what China isn't
I believe
Based on the data.
NKC
Is that
In general if it's an area that's important to China
What's a Salmon Canned
Let's say the it sector
What's a farmer
That your chances of getting a fair Shake
I'm not nearly as
As
Something that is
Of less
Critical importance to China's Industrial
Like
Glue
Like Glue
So you think maybe that's why in the end I wrote found a way to make the system in China work for the company
Because they're just selling glue they're not selling semiconductor technology has not as far as I know have a five-year
Industrial plan on glue so yes China is able and willing to protect foreign glue
Circumstances semiconductors
A difference.
We're trying to do more reporting on China trip planner
So if you're there and you think you have a good story to tell or you know someone who's there and has a good story to tell
Let us know
Planet Money at NPR. Org
Special thanks to Agawam for interpreting and Leon de Jack change. Palmer Bill Alfred and William Way
Treatment for teaching me about China's IP system
Primary supervising producer is Alex goldmark and our editor is Brian Dorsett
I'm Nick Crompton and I know thanks for listening
One more thing
We have a new round of
Planet Money videos
They're just coming out
The first one
Is about the genius
Convince the world
To overpay for vote
He's played by Kenny Malone
You're going to want to see
You can buy the videos at npr.org
Slash Planet Money
That's npr.org
/ planet
Money