Okay so did you see it
Iceland
So what was it
It was a blanket with a message on
A blanket with a mess
And the blanket was hanging from a bridge
In the state of Guanajuato in Mexico
Do usually send messages like this
They right
Messages on blankets
Yes
And the hondaman cities with the very foul language
Terrible spelling
This is Manuel Milano he's an economist in Mexico with the Mexican Institute for competitiveness
This is
What are we usually call a narco Manta
Which has a blanket that hash
Some sort of warning medical Manta a drug trafficker
Blanket
Basically a billboard from the drug cartel
Journalism Mexico has stopped reporting on these blankets because
Didn't want to spread messages
The cartels
They are
Legitimately frightening
But this time the Fred is directly against the president of the are Republican.
What's the weather
Andres Manuel Lopez obrador
This was addressed
To the president
Of Mexico
And it was signed by a criminal called alma mater
The hammer
Technically instead Elsinore tomorrow which would mean
Mister
Hammer
The blanket said
President of
I demand you get your Navy
Army Air Force and federal police
Out of this
If not
I'm going to start killing
Innocent people
And then kind of like a PS it says
I've left you a little gift
At my refine
That little gift
Was an orange
Pickup truck
With what looked
Like a bomb inside
And the part of the message that says my Refinery he needs an oil refinery
Like we're gasoline
The refinery is owned by the Mexican governor
But the hammer is saying here no no no
That refinery
Is mine
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Sarah Gonzales
Play on the show the hammer and a lot of drug traffickers and cartels
Are diversifying
They're getting into the oil business
Killing billions of dollars of gasoline
Every year
The president of Mexico is taking radical even dangerous steps
To cut them off
This message comes from NPR
Capital One
Is reimagining Bank
I offering account
With no fees or minimum
That can be open from anywhere
5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Na
Just a quick warning this show includes audio from a deadly accident
It is disturbing
Okay the first thing you should know about gasoline in Mexico is that it
State-owned the national Oil Company petroleos Mexicanos is one of the largest oil companies
In the world
Everyone calls it
Baymax and pemex gasoline
Is really expensive for people in Mexico like you have to work almost
Full day at minimum wage
In order to afford
One gallon of gasoline
And as a result people have always stolen Sun gas in next
There's even a special name for stole
Everybody calls it what you got
But for a long time it was kind of a a manageable
Until a few years ago when drug cartels wanted to diversify beyond the drug business
Some turn to prostitution
Some started kidnapping
People for ransom
And some look at this little watch equal thing and we're like
We can make this a much
Bigger business
Billions of dollars of gasoline is
Flowing
Right at our
So they started tapping the gasoline pipelines and they are selling stolen gas into this
Giant
Global Market
It's hurt you talked about the global market with Ian Rowdy he works for the United Nations
His job is fighting Maritime fuel smuggling
Which
Basically means that he fights
Pirates he's a pirate by Pirates
Pirates Smugglers traffickers and thieves
Are you ever scared
Yeah I Meister fight about this interview
When you're talking about doing the benefits of criminal profit
People go to links to keep that invites crime that happened in the ocean
And he says that one of Mexico's most notorious cartels
Is that a full on
Fuel exporter they have fake export certificates
And in in Tiger
Fleet
Of ships in the sea
They have tankers they have Supply vessels their support vessels
And they can
Take fuel right from the refinery put into a tanker
With falsified documents and then
Tell it right in two
Somebody's pork and
Distributed as if it was a legitimate
Shipping vessels filled with fuel that is being sold all over the world stolen Mexican fuel sold all over the world
How can you sell
Stolen
Fuel smuggled out of Mexico to like Thailand
Well if you probably wouldn't sell it to Thailand because they're there their smuggling it in by fishing
Boats from Malaysia and then selling it and Coke bottles on the street
So Thailand's Got itself
Don't Dynamic that you would you could even tell it into Caribbean countries into other South American countries into
Parts of Europe in North America
What is this massive Global Indus
All of the supply chains going from country to Country
And the different ways people come up with the steel gasoline is just
Encryptstick Morocco and Algeria
Facebook closed border people are not allowed to
To walk across drive across people cannot cross the border
But
Donkeys can
Like
Trained
Unmanned
Donkeys
And as a result
Donkeys have been taking overnight
Jerry cans with Algerian fuel across the border into Morocco 4 years
And if you think that's just a small-scale think
Come to the total adds up to about 2 billion dollars a year
My donkey
Injury can
So there's this extraordinary Global Market in stolen gas
Once the cartels in Mexico discovered this
They just started stealing more and more
In 2016 spamax Mexico's Oil Company lost 1.5 billion dollars
2 stolen gas
Then 2.5 billion dollars the next year and 3.5 billion dollars
Last year that's 9 million dollars a day
Nginx stealing from a private company they're stealing from the Mexican Government
From the people of Mexico
Today's problems getting worse
And then on December 1st of last
You're just a few months ago
A new president was for
Andres Manuel Lopez obrador
Name is a handful so everybody calls
And Manuel The Economist says he's just a different kind of
I'm not traveled around Mexico without Secret Service
And to save the people money
He flies
Commercial like a regular
Diesel
Fearless man
I have to give him that he's really Fearless his first day as president he said he was going to sell all the play
Planes and all the helicopters that the quote
Corrupt
Politicians use
He came in
To change things up in Mexico
He has an idea power
Closer to that of Aztec Emperors on the IV thing
He projects that image that he's in control and
Can
Achieve
Absolutely anything
Just enough willpower and so on December 27th just a few weeks after he became president
Imma hold this Prescott
All about spelling
Combative
Oromo come on this is a multi-billion Dollar business
Of course people at pemex know this is going on
They know when someone has punched a hole in a pipeline and is
Siphoning gasoline
The people in the government know this is happening to obviously
They are letting it happen
The authorities
Are complicit
Go la complicidad this stolen gas this what you called is from the top
What you call
Federal
Does that leave ER
And then he says
Right now
We have to end this corrupt
Como esta Kuroshio
And then he does something that nobody has ever tried
Before something
Rap God
Amlo
Shut down the gasoline pipelines in
Turned off the valves
Dried out the pipes
No more gasoline flowing
So even if the cartels cut them
There be nothing in there
He was taking on the cartels
The only problem is
He shut off the valves
To the pipeline
Like the thing that brings gasoline to millions of
People in Mexico imagine you're living your life and then one day
I don't know where the president is like sorry
Turning up the supply of gasoline.
Fighting crime
Technically still gasoline in Mexico but now instead of flowing through pipes
Gasoline was moving in trucks and rail cars
Traveling by police
Escort well
Of course I'm an economist and I'm worried
The best way to move
Liquids used through a pipe
The cheapest way
It cost 14 times more to move gas by truck
Then by pipeline
According to the max
And also and more importantly in the short-term in Mexico
It is a much
Much slower way of getting gas
So after almost shut off the pipes
Guess just couldn't get the gas station fast
Millions of people who just wanted to let you know drive to work
Car pick up their kid at school had to wait
5 hours
8 hours
It's just a put gas in their car taxi drivers truck drivers farmers
They couldn't move their product
The price of fruit and meat and vegetables went out
And people stayed home
It was like a natural disaster
That hit Mexico
Eventually gas stations ran out in Thai
Even in Mexico City
In the capital
For more than a month
There were shortages
People started fighting with gasoline
So the president had cut his own people off from this essential resource
And yet
He was still really Poppy
90% of the country
Supported him
Turning off the pipes they wanted him to fight Gaston
And people started getting used to waiting in long lines for gasoline
And you know when there are a lot of Mexicans to
Just waiting hours and hours for one thing
We're going to we're going to turn it into a party
A few pipelines were still running
One ran through in Alfalfa field in a farm town called
And of course when so many pipes are dry
Gas thieves are going to find the one that's running
And on January 18th
Some Gatsby
This one and the gasoline started leaking
Forming some sort of pain.
Of gasoline
This is a very small Lepore rutile town
In N Central Mex
So people started flowing to these place
In order to get
5 l
Hundreds of people like 700 people women children grandparents
Showed up
Bucket
Monsters there
Scooping up
Spilled gasoline
And then some soldiers came
They trying to get everybody to me
How to get everybody to stop you
But they were outnumbered people just
At some point that day the leak turned into a gusher
Gas started shooting up into the air
50K
There videos of this online people are getting
Covered in gasoline
So
I mean this is the kind of happiness you would find in
American scenes of kids in a very hot summer
Gathering around the broken
Fireman
Connection
Riley kids
Around a fire hydrant
Yes
Event that happened in Mexico
No I don't think so
To secede from Americana apus
I mean that's how
Look up first nanny
Just became
Dnieper
Something cause a spark and everything burst into flames
16 from hell it's just something that
You cannot fathom you cannot imagine
Furious
Table counting and people running from one side to the other
In flames
People are in flames
Rolling around in the Alfalfa field trying to
Put out the fire
Taking off all their
Close their shoes
Begging
For help
Dozens of people were
Really badly burnt
Kids lost their limbs people's faces
Completely changed from the Burns
And more than 130 people
Workouts
That night
The president went to the scene of the Explorer
He offered his condolences to the victims and their families
And then a reporter asked him
Does this mean you're going to change the way your fighting gas
No he said no
Merchant
But to help with the shortages
I know spent almost a hundred million dollars on 571 new trucks
That he bought from the United
He has also turned most of the gas pipelines back on
But there are thousands of soldiers guarding the pie
Out there right now
So gasoline is getting two people again but at a really high cost
And guess that
Is down
Ian the pirate fighter and fuel theft expert says
It probably won't last
Criminals
Are incredibly creative remember Coke bottles and.
Oil or fuel
You're just going to see a change in the modalities of how it
Stolen
Shifting from pipelines to trucks just means that you're shifting from tapping pipelines to
Hijacking tanker trucks
Ultimately and says you don't solve
The problem by
Turning off the pipes or by moving oil
Out of pipes and ink
Trucks
You solve it by arresting people who
Stihl gasoline and resting corrupt officials who let them get away with it
Until you do that
People will keep stealing
Why wouldn't they
4 pemex officials have been arrested including the man who's in charge
One of the most important gas pipelines in Mexico he's accused of looking the other way when he knew criminals were Steel
This message comes from NPR sponsor squares
Squarespace allow small biz
Design and build their own website
Using customizable Leo
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobiledit
Squarespace also offers
Built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online press
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Special things to Maria Jose Sanchez
Oviedo who wrote us about the gas prices in Mexico
We read your emails we love getting them you can send them to Planet Money at npr.org
Thanks also to Duncan Woods believe in Mesa AZ Mohan and Luz Elena Martinez and an extra
Special thanks to our producer at the indicator Constance that guy got to go
Nnps Mexico correspondent
Today's Show is produced by Darian woods and Megan tan
Ryan or Stat edit our show Alex goldmark is are supervising producer of Jacob Goldstein
And I'm sorry but thanks for listening
We had somebody who actually came forward and said that they had the ultimate solution to all of this is very very serious terms
The ultimate solution yes which was
Stop using fossil fuels all together
Whatever energy Supply comes next
Somebody will love to feel that as well
People are going to win at
Bottle up the sign-in
Wind
Precisely
Real Steel off of solar fields
Bastille off of wind farms just get off of wave Farms
You know we already see people stealing off of
Off the Grid in the US