Is this is probably not your first Studio interview in your life is it
Or is it
The first one with disc
A white brothers equipment
Kenneth kid is a geneticist
At Yale
And in some circles he's a pretty big deal
For example
He was one of the first scientists
To persuade judges to accept DNA as evidence in American courtrooms
But the wake and got tangled up in the story we're going to be talking about today
Has to do with a project that he's been working on for decades
It's trying to understand human genetic variation
Around the world
The idea is
As if you draw someone's blood
Get their DNA and then look for the right markers inside that DNA
You can probably figure out what region or ethnic
A person comes from kind of like 23andMe but fancy
And four years can has been testing this idea this idea that
Certain markers in your DNA show where you come from and to test that idea
Do you need a DNA samples from people of all different ethnicities from all different parts of the world
But in 2010 there was still a big hole in the global genetic picture that he was trying to assemble
A place where he didn't have a lot of genetic samples
From yet
And that place
With China
There's like more than billion people there I imagine there's a lot of genetic diversity that's worth money
Yes
There is
What Ken says he didn't know what he couldn't know with how China would end up using his research
Any did you have any concerns at the outset
Not
At the outset
You see what Kenwood later find out was that his collaboration with Chinese scientist
Would end up helping Advance one of the biggest
Most invasive surveillance
Projects
Anywhere on Earth
Vulcan Planet Money
China is building a
Huge high-tech system for tracking targeting and cracking down on minority
And they're developing much of that technology on their own
But they're also relying on the work of American society
Today the show we're going to tell the stories of two men
YouTube
In very different ways
Got caught up in the scariest
Most dystopian police state
We turned up and I'm very long
One of them
A scientist
The other
Just a guy trying to have a summer vacation
Is there any part of it
Feel sorry for kind of
I absolutely do
I mean the thing is
He's extremely irresponsible and negligee
Start doing what he did
But
At the same time
Everyone makes mistakes right
This message comes from NPR sponsor E-Trade
Investing your money shouldn't require Moving Mountains
No matter how much or how little experience you have
E-Trade makes investing simple
Along with great value
They provide the tools and support you need to navigate the market
All to help your money work hard for you
For more information visit etrade.com NPR
E-Trade Securities LLC member sipc
No matter what you got planned you need a song of the summer
This week on NPR pop culture happy hour we are rounding up experts from NPR music we will play a ton of song
To lift your spirits
And you might even find your next favorite artist
That's NPR pop culture happy hour listen
Subscribe now
The part of China that we're going to be talking about today is
Pretty closed off
It's called sinkiang province
Nearly half of the people there are uyghurs a Muslim minority
And over the last several years the Chinese communist
Party has been ramping up its
Persecution
Have the wee course
Journalists don't get real access conditioning John they're often followed by government minders they
I only get to see what the government wants them to see
So today our guide into the police state that's being built there is a man who saw firsthand WhatsApp
Because he lived it
And is willing to talk to us about it
But we're going to take some steps to protect his identity asked us to use a different name
And the boys are about to hear
It's a boy voice actor
Voice actor who is reciting word-for-word from the interview with our source
Olam is a grad student in the US
He's uyghur and he grew up in sinkiang
And two summers ago he went on a trip home that helped him understand just how much everything there is
The trip started out like most of his summer break
Text Ed
On a long flight to China
He watched a couple movies nap
8-up pretty mediocre airplane Halal meal
And I'm on the plane landed
Flight attendant
And she was like
Oh they're asking for you
There might be something wrong with your Visa
And I was like
I don't need visa
I'm a citizen of this country he's like I come home every summer and nothing like this has ever happened before
And then she was like
Oh and I I don't know what's going on you should probably should go and see them
Police officers take him off the plane they searched him question him for 4 hours
And then I tell him he's under arrest
The charge
Disrupting the societal order
And then I started
Laughing
Coughing
Yeah
I a laugh
Hysterically
Because it sounded
Bizarre
To me like
Never in my wildest dreams did I imagine getting arrest
On had heard stories about uyghurs being detained by the Chinese government which has been cracking down on the group
Because they say uyghur
Suppose a terrorism
Almost nowhere near that were
In the US so
He was thinking this whole time
I'm just going home to see my family eat some good home cook Weaver food
But this trip with
Turn out nothing like that
The police bring a lamb to a hospital
And they say he needs to undergo a quote
Health check
They took me to
A room
To do ultrasound
An ultrasound of where
My
Belly
Of my organs
I guess
Belly like as if you were a pregnant woman exactly
Yeah
Didn't take him to a windowless room they started
Taking pictures of my face
From all kinds of different angles you mean they move the cameras
Almost 360 Degrees around your head to take it yes your head your face smell different
Vantage points yes
They did
And then
After that they started to tell me
Open my mouth
Event taking pictures of that
And then close my mouth and then taking pictures of that
Unlike
Reveal my teeth
Like kind of like
Smile and then taking pictures of that
It's as if
They're trying to
Gemini like
Take pictures of my facial expressions
At this point
Alarm starts to realize
The government is building a profile on
That is what they want on this date at 4
Did you ever feel like you could say no
No
That's that's not negotiable
I felt like if I
If I tried to resist
It was only look bad on me
And make me feel like
Make
Make them think
That I'm a criminal
So I cooperated with
Everything
To take his hand prints that take us
Is footprints
They sit him down and record his voice
They handed me this this
Passage in Hoover
And told me to read it in front of a very expensive-looking mic
Finally they take to tube
Types of olives black
And then an officer Blatz a little piece of paper with his
Labeled it with his name and national ID number
Places the paper in a box
As he was placing my sample
My blood sample
Into the box I could see
Easily hundreds of other samples
Because I could see people's
Names
That ID cards
Just like mine
Attached to that blood sample
Hundreds of other people's
Blood we're in that box
Yes
It's not just hundreds
It's million
Human rights groups say the Chinese government is forcing every person in sinkiang from the ages of 12
B5
To go through a health check
And that the government has thrown more than a million of these people into so-called
Haitian camps
That is where all them
And it up
After the tell check
She was sent to a detention center and he spent his days watching propaganda videos
Chanting slogans about how great the Chinese Communist party was
Reciting rules against extremism
And then
One day the police tell all them
You can leave
Just like that
The guard came to me
And then he was like
Pack your stuff
And then I was like I don't have any stuff
And then he was like
Come out
They take him to his family's apartment
And then for the first time in 28 days
He's free
And he's thinking
I can finally do what I come back for every summer I can go play soccer with my buds I can
Walk around my hometown
Eat a bunch of samsa's
Does it like
Uyghur
But as he starts going about his life
He starts to notice that
Things are really different
As soon as I get out of the building
I actually am
Notice cameras in the apartment complex
Witches
You know weird because there wasn't cameras last year and over the next few days he realizes it's
Not just new cameras that are everywhere
There are also these new police station like literally one on every block
They call them
Convenience police stations convenience police stations
Yeah that's supposed to create convenience for the people
They say you can
Charge your phone inside or you can use the restroom inside
But
Everyone knows the police station
There are these signs on them that say beware of three evil forces the three evil forces
Terrorism extremism and separatism
He says
It was weird
He was noticing all this stuff
The cameras.
Police stations a bunch of extra police
But no one was
Hawking
But once he was over at his uncle
And one of his family members starts talking about Ramadan
Which at this point had pretty much been outlawed in ching chong
And my uncle
Immediately stop the conversation
He was like no
Don't talk about this don't talk about anything that would get us into trouble
Because those Vehicles outside with the giant antennas
What do you think those are for
The listening to
They're listening to conversations that are happening in our homes
He says people weren't really talking about
Anything of substance
Because they didn't even know what they weren't supposed to be talking about
It's still
Kind of felt
Lake prison
I felt like I have no Freedom like even though I was
Technically free
And then all I'm even began to doubt if
She was
Technically
It started this one day
When he and his friend were just walking to the mall to have lunch and I was entering the small
And at the entrance
There's a security check
He said these checkpoints are all over the
The kind of looks like a cross between an airport metal detector and a Subway turn
Style
There's camera and a screen attached to it so you can see yourself being recorded yourself yeah yeah
Absolutely
His friend goes through first and his ID
Walkthrough
And then
It's all a
I scan my ID
Immediately
Orange alert came up
A bright orange light
And a police officer calls
And then it was like yeah yeah come in come into the station
Alan said that all he was thinking was
This is it
I'm going back into
Detention
Police officers
Hey follow me into the station just sit down
I just got to ask you some
And while he was filing that on his computer that I asked him
So is this a mistake or
What's going on
And then he was like
Oh they just updated the system today you probably shouldn't go anywhere
And then I was like
What do you mean
And then he was like you know I have every public place has this machine and they would flag you each time and
We don't want to you know do this filing every time you come back to the
Station Inn
You don't want to come back either I assume
So just stay home that means you're under house arrest basic but that's exactly what I was thinking
She goes back home having no idea really what his status
Whether there been some glitch in the system or if they ask
Had something on him
Or if you've been permanently flagged as a c
Security risk
But then one day he would have friend who works for the government who says
You want to know what your status is
I have this app
On my phone
I can look you up
He pulled out his phone open this app
And then I told him my ID card number
And then
Right after he press confirm
My picture and a lot of different information shows
And he said
There's an orange warning on your ID card
That's usually used for
Criminal
And he was shot
He said
You can't leave the city
Let alone China 2
Go back to school
So then when the end of the summer was approaching
Would you nervous that you would not be able to fly back to the US
Absolutely
What was that app
And what is all this technology that's being used to track all them
We'll find out more
After the break
Support for NPR comes from Newman's Own Foundation
Working for nourish the common good by donating all profits from Newman's Own food products to charitable
Stations that seek to make the world a better place more information is available at Newman's Own Foundation.
Got to work
What is video games can help you and your child Bond and learn important skills and here is life good for parenting it taking
On screen time when the big things were working on right now is a concept resiliency and not quitting when something is hard
He lives in lose and loose
Scraps of Life kit all guys Oliver epi
All in one place
And she John all them could see all the cameras
See all the security checkpoint
Police officers waiting on every block
What he couldn't see was the scale of the digital prison around him
One person has been trying to put together that bigger picture is Sophie Richard
Want to move the mic
Put together wherever it needs to go
So he's been trying to figure out as much as she can about the surveillance technology being used in sinkiang
She's a China director at Human Rights
Watch this spring she and her team got their hands on the app that police in sinkiang are using to track
Uyghur
Probably the same at that all it was
And her team reverse-engineer.
And what we were able to show
By unpacking the source code of this app that
Behavior ranging from
Suddenly socializing less with your neighbors
Got suspicious
Talking to family members overseas going out the back door instead of the front door putting gas in somebody else's car
All of these behaviors that are perfectly legal
Perfectly legal are now considered
Suspicious
And
The bad information can and will be used against you
And Toby's team isn't just looking at this app they're looking at everything
Like for example that security checkpoint that all-in-one through at the mall
It is way more advanced than he ever knew
Recognition software
You know they'll always walk literally The Way You Walk that's monitor
Correct and identifies you correct wow and all of that is linked to a central database about who you are and all this other
Correct
One other thing so he's been doing is she's been trying to track America
Who are helping China build these high-tech social
End
Quite frankly
Shaymin so they'll stop doing
She had some successes
But it's meant digging through stacks of obscure documents trying to understand complex science
Is this company based in Massachusetts
Thermo Fisher
They make these things called DNA soup
We actually found from looking at police tender documents
Thermo Fisher Scientific
Had sold DNA sequencers to the xinjiang public Security Bureau
So he called them out and they said they would stop
Selling fishing John
Her team also called out iflytek
Which is this Chinese company that collaborating with MIT
Iflytek has supplied a lot of voice recognition technology to shrink John
MIT says they agreed to the collaboration the
For the University came up with a whole new review process for
Elevated risk
International
But they're still collaborating that I fight
By the way
Voice recognition technology is why were using a voice actor for Gollum
Remember how police made him read out loud
A page of uyghur text in front of a fancy microphone
Well they have his voice
Forever
An engineer's that NPR told us
Even if we tried to distort his voice
It could be reverse engineer
Sophie says there is one particular American who worked with the Chinese police who stands out to her
She remembers when she first got a tip about him
I was sitting in the Brussels Airport
Reading
That packet of information and help
Physically
Lll
She was reading about a geneticist
At Yale
Names
Kenneth
Kit
The guy from the beginning of the show
Do you feel that you have done absolutely nothing
Wrong
I have done nothing wrong
Here's can story in short
In 2010 he got an invitation to travel to Beijing from the Chinese Ministry of
Security
Which is like the Chinese police says he collaborates with law enforcement all the time
He does DNA work
So can fly to China and meets one of the top
Scientist for the Chinese
And she says hey I'm also interested in this DNA ancestry marker stuff
Also thanks to my job I have access to DNA from all sorts of ethnicities from all over.
So she says
Do you want to work together
Can I come visit your lab
Ken says sure come on over to Yale University
And she spent a year inside that lab a pretty productive year
It's capped off with a paper that they co-author together
And one of the paper looks at
Is what differentiates the DNA of certain ethnic
Groups including groups that the Chinese government is targeting in shenyang like
Uyghur stodgy
Has aux-in kirghiz
We now know that this DNA was most likely not collected consent
McKenna says the scientists working for the Chinese police
She claimed it all her DNA samples including the weaker ones
Gathered with
Permission
She says
That
The samples were collected with signed informed consent
And you didn't question that
On what basis would I
Question
Penn says he followed accepted
And that there was no way he could have independently verified whether there was informed consent
But a lot of people including Sophie Richardson
Are outraged by his collaboration with the Chinese
Police
They're also disturbed by the fact that can not only use data drawn from DNA samples that the Chinese police provide
Lighted but that he also provided genetic samples from his own lab
To the Chinese
Police
And they say he allowed data based on uyghur DNA
To be included in a global database that he runs out of you
Knowing what you know now
About how the Chinese government
Has treated uyghurs
In-N-Out Ruth wiegers do you still believe that every genetic sample taken from a weaker
Referenced in your database or referenced in your research
But each one of those samples was
Definitely taken with informed consent you do you really believe that
It's impossible to believe that
Unequivocally
But
On the other hand
I have no way of knowing
One way
Or the other
Because critics say that by collaborating with the Chinese police
He helped give China
The tools to
Figure out
Whether someone is uyghur
Which helps China Advance the system that
Tracks
Targets and oppresses the uyghur
10 Tesla
This collaboration
This happened years ago
Before much of the world knew what was going on in Shanghai
I can't no
Everything that
Going to happen in the future
Ken says he stopped
Collaborating with the Chinese Ministry of public
Security
And that he's removing all that problematic weaker data from his big database
Have you asked scientists at the Chinese Ministry of public security to stop
Using the genetic samples you provided them
Yes
Did they say
They would stop
I've gotten no reply
We are stalling
About tennis
And he said he had heard about him
And even though there is no way that all of his blood sample was used by
Who says
He still a victim of a system that
Can help
Advance
As a human being I can
Relate to making a mistake
Car
Screwing up big time
Cuz everyone
Once in awhile
But
Just thinking about it
Makes me really angry
It's difficult for me to sympathize with him
Knowing the magnitudes of his research
And
The potential damage his research could do to my people
Alan has good reason
To be angry
It's been
2 years but he is still real
Laying in his head the nightmare
That summer break in shenyang
He waited out the rest of the summer counting down the days
Today's return flight
Back to the US
Trying to stay under the radar
Name of the summer was nearing its end he went to the airport
Not knowing if his orange alert would mean
He could never leave China
When he got to the airport the police questioned him for so long that he missed her
Is flight
Then they said
Come back tomorrow and try again
So we showed up the next day super early
And they questioned him again but this time they did let him go to the gate
I was still nervous I was like
I'm not out of the woods yet
They can get me
Anytime they want
What if they change their mind
He says the four hours he waited to get on the plane with the longest of his life
And when we finally boarded the plane
I was still anxious because they knew that they could stop the plane as long as we're on the ground
When we finally took off
Had a huge sigh of relief
And I knew that didn't exist this is it
Autumn is in the US now
But he sure the Chinese government is still tracking
So
He's being really careful
And he says
If authorities found out he was talking to journalists
Very bad things would happen to his family
We asked him are you planning to go back next summer
And he said
I don't think I'll ever go back
Hate we have this new cool thing
It's the Planet Money newsletter it's smart comes out once a week
You can find it at npr.org Planet Money newsletter
If you have any story ideas and burning questions about the world email us at Planet Money at npr.org
And if you like the show
Hit that share button
Send it to a friend
Today show with produced by The Dream Team Darian woods and Liza Yeager
Alex goldmark azar supervising producer and brian dorsett edits the show
Special thanks to Darren Byler who talked to me for hours about what's happening in sinkiang and Mark munster's Yelm
Who has been following Kenneth kids work and shared what he found with Human Rights Watch
Also thanks to Jim millward Maiwand Ryan thumb Sam Hoffman and of course our voice actor
Weger Abdullah
Yes that is actually his real name
Parents are weaker and he grew up in Australia
And your parents named you weaker
They were
Very imaginative
I'm off the chain and I'm Nick.
This is NPR thanks for listening