Good morning
The actor Kurt Russell
Does Square One Time
Who are you and
What are you arguing and why
Greg I'm going to Simpson I live in Hot Springs Village Arkansas small rule Community outside Hot Springs
And how are you
But
Big cities
Simply aren't worth the cost
I can continue but that's usually the kind of clip you use
Dennis Simpson clearly knows how a Planet Money episode works
He is a list
And he sent us an email
With an ARG
That stems from the fact that
His life in Hot Springs Village Ark
Chainsaw is apparently
Freaking
Great it is 26000 Acres of complete awesome
Golf courses
Lakes I'm looking across our Lake right now it's not the largest lake in the village but it's very nice
Over that hill and over the hill behind it is 1.7 million Acres of National Forest in the water
Mountain Valley Water is bottled about 6 miles from here we have some of the purest water in the United States
And it says Hot Springs Village
Is cheap
Especially when he
He Compares it to places like
New York
Or Sanford Zoo
We watch the realtor.com and we watch the Zillow actually got to link the other day
For a
Quarter acre lot
With a dead truck
A deadbolt
And a cinder block 800 square foot house that was 1.2 million dollars
In the Bay Area
And we joke about that that's a $30,000 redneck home to us that
You would never live in that
Temperature to boil down your argument
Cities are overrated
I think cities are overrated
I really do
They're overrated
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Kenny Malone and I'm Greg results
The conventional wisdom from Economist has been
If you want to Make It in America
Move to the city
But in the last few years
People have been leaving City
Cities like New York
In San Francisco and Miami
And Los Angeles
Today on the show
Are cities overrated
Is it time to rethink
Where to live
This message comes from NPR sponsor wix.com
With Wix you can create a professional website for your business
Choose a template design for your anus
History and customize it to match your brand
With Ascend by Wix you can easily connect with your site visit
Capture leads
Cheats and manage all of your customer relations from one place
Get started now
And get the all-in-one Business Solution
Go to wix.com
That's wilx.com money
To get 10% off
I'm Gregory Warner
Rough translation we follow a Rescue Mission in real time
After Nawrocki photojournalist goes missing on the front lines we don't believe it I don't believe it
Lisa's family and his friends
Try to say that when you said who is this what who are you they respond we are
Are the Islamic State
From NPR's rough translation
Listen And subscribe
Today we are going to talk
Due to the country's leading economy
To ask the question
How do cities become / 8
No they're not overrated
They do amazing things and they have been doing amazing things for thousands of years Ed Glazer is an economist at Harvard
And wrote a pretty popular book about City
These called Triumph
Of the city what was the subtitle of that trying for the city how our greatest invention makes us
Smarter healthier hold on let me get
Make sure I have to eat have the adjectives in order for you
There a lot of hair
Ed Glazer for decades has been
One of the
Biggest cheerleaders
Four cities
Trying for the city how I greatest invention makes us richer smarter Greener healthier and happier
Play circle up in Manhattan in the 1970s and 1980s
Which wasn't the most glamorous time for New York
Or really any of the country's major cities
Cities had been these manufacturer
Hap's pit
During that. The world
Kind of opened up
New York's garment industry went overseas for example
Detroit car business started shriveling up
The crime rates in cities skyrocketed
Cities became
A place where
Where scary things happen
And or at least that was the
New York the entire city
If you've ever seen the movie Escape From New York the scary plot is
It's the future
And the president has crashed in New York City
And must be rescue
You can win
Find a president bring them out in 24 hours
You're a free man
24 hours
Make a new one
Bulshit
Straight just like I said
This movie was part of like a whole genre
Of dystopian New York City movies
Came out in the 70s
It really felt as if the age of the city at
Come and gone was not going to come again
And that was really the back. That was the world that I grew up in
And from that perspective The Comeback of cities feels fairly
The reason cities came back is because
There was this whole wave jobs that came in the 90s in the 2000s
They're all part of what a condom is sometimes called knowledge
I think like Finance
Biotech coding
Instead of making a new physical object with your muscles
This is the kind of job where you give the world a new idea with your brain
These types of jobs
Ed Glazer says
Thrive
Live in dense urban area
Is old Urban Edge
Enabling Act
Get smart by being around other smart people that older bananas became more valuable
And it was on that
Advantage
Did cities found himself coming back
There is the stunning statistic in Blazers book about this modern economy
Please are found the Americans who live in big metropolitan areas are 50% more productive than their small
Mooretown equivale
Glaser along with a lot of economist
Best tips spent decades trying to figure out why this is like
What exactly is the magic
Of a city
And he says for sure some of it is this
Self-selection
Where you got high Achievers trying to make it in
Play Store says even when you take that into account
There's something about a city that seems to make workers better at their job
So the key point is that all of
Human creativity
Is based on the Bedrock of human interaction
Almost everything of what
I know I've learned from people around me
Physical proximity speeds the flow of ideas and city's been enabling
The collaborative change of creativity that are powered Humanity's greatest hits from
Athenian philosophy to Facebook
So these are fundamentally enablers of human creativity
And now it's not like every city in the country
Has rebounded from the 70s
Canady's the same
And this is why you'll hear Economist talk about
So-called Super Star City
The rare economic term
It sounds like it should be a song from the band
Superstar City
Are these
Places like San Francisco New York and Seattle
Places accounting for a disproportionate share of a country's economic growth
Over the last decade are biggest cities have accounted for over 70% of the nation's job growth
In other words the cities aren't just driving our economy
They are kind of becoming
Alright so are we are we ready to go
Yes okay this is David daughter
He's a labor economist
Mist at MIT
I'm also the
Co-director of the MIT
Work of the future task force
David told us another reason why cities
It's that when you look back through history
They have this incredible power to give opportunities to
Even workers who did not have specialized skills or College
Agree
For these types of workers David
Moving to the city would actually change the kind of work
You do as you
Went from rural areas to suburbs
Metro areas to City
There's a kind of an occupational escalator
The non-college workers rude
This is the classic
Start in the Mailroom and work your way up store
The data show that if you move to a city
The odds of this happening we're just way better
You leave a small town and step onto this big city career Escalade
And workers would benefit with
Or without a degree it would arguably be building more skills
And I developing a unit
Especializacion that would
Exit more productive that would cause her wages to be higher and it would give them more
Optical job security over
Hey look I'm from a small town in
This is exactly what I grew up assuming
To be true assuming
Bit the quickest path to Upward Mobility
Was packing my bags and moving to a big city
Actually I think most Economist assume that to that is the conventional bison
Is is that what you think
That's what I thought you know up until 6 months ago
After the break
What David daughter learn 6 months
NPR Podcast in the following message come from sales
Salesforce helps you deliver the Innovative personal experiences customers want
Learn how Salesforce brings customers and companies together
They're at salesforce.com NPR
Hey Sophie reisenberg from ask me another if you're craving nerdy trivia or celebrity interviews we've got you
Covered with house musician Jonathan Coulton and the sherpas Contessa
Canton Public Radio NPR hour of puzzles where games and trivia
Last year David daughter got an invitation
To give
What was probably one of the biggest speeches of his life
Every year the president of the American economic Association
This is the main Professional Organization
For us economist
He or she selects
A big-shot economist
Give
This lecture That's The Witcher TV lecture
And I Ben Bernanke who's the incoming president
Selected me invited me
Do it which is that a huge honor
Everything it was incredibly intivity Ben Bernanke is
Is the former chairman of
The Federal Reserve
He sent me an email he sent you an email
He's like I want you to give this prestigious lecture
Where does your mind go so you know the first place my mind went was
Can I delete this email and pretended it has never caught
Because this is going to be really hard
Hello everyone
I'm Ben Bernanke on the in
Course David Auto did not delete this
Email from Ben Bernanke I would like to do now is
Introduce red lecture
David otter
I was actually there for the speech it was in Atlanta it was a huge convention room full of hundreds
Economist
Diva daughter takes the same kind of nervously smiling
Thank you
It is a
Overwhelming honor
To be early starts talking about how we starting to rethink
The popular wisdom
Insidious
So when I started this project
That was my
Assumption
Cities are land of opportunity we are rising
That's where we should go why is everyone moving to
Remember moving to the city
Got you access to that career Escalade
Free speech
David did some new research
In the first big surprise
Was it this career escalator
It have been flattening out
For decades
Another word that was steeply upward sloping in the 1970s
1980s
Starting 1990s it starts to
Rotate downward
Further show in 2004 they're still so that by 2015 that escalator
Had complete
Fleetly
Leveled out
Moving to the city date
Is now more like one of those moving walkways at the airport
There is no moving up
Like I used to
And so the big question is
Why is
That's what changed
And the answer has to do with something at David and actually been looking at for a long
Our country's labor market has been splitting into two tiers
Number one
You got high paying knowledge-based jobs
Two number two
Low-paying service-sector
The stuff that used to be in the middle tier
That is the stuff that has proved
Easy to automate with
Technology or offshore with
You know free trade but this was just a general national tree
For this fancy speech in Atlanta
David decided he wanted to see how this was unfolding across America
Where exactly
In the country are these middle care jobs disappearing
Expected to see them.
Disappearing everywhere
Especially in rural areas and smaller declining cities
Like those in the Rust Belt
Places that were obviously sucks
David assumed the exception to this would be
In ARP Superstar cities
That's where
All the benefits of
Silicon Valley or Finance
Los Angeles her spilling over to everybody
You know just get there the cup runneth over and everyone is
Part of this
Concentrated prosperity
What would David had found
What is presenting
In his speech
What's the exact opposite
This job polarization
This division of the labor market into high-paying and low-paying tears is now happening more in Superstar cities
Been anywhere else in the country
This job polarization is urban phenomenon
Until about 72 hours
I have been telling you
People
We got to get everyone to move to cities cuz that's where the opportunity is
I'm less certain of that
Then I was
72 hours
This was pretty Bonkers to hear live
You know it wasn't like Ben Bernanke was spitting out his drink and the audience was sobbing uncontrollably
But deep Sauter was onstage challenging this decades-old economic truths
Go to the city
If you want to make
You were saying
That simply isn't true for a huge segment of the work
It was kind of
Jaja
I got your job was slightly on the floor mine was you know like I couldn't get off the floor for weeks at a time
So surprised
David Pink Floyd
Dark picture of what's going on in Superstar cities
You have this talk to your job is doing better and better
Then you have that lower-tier of jobs
Non-college workers are primarily there to
UC to the care and comfort and feeding and security of the more affluent
They have been
Shuffled
Into these jobs that use
Arguably
More generic skills
And that's why
It's hard for them to command High wages because the set of people can do many of those tasks
Is
Abandon
And since David daughter gave this
And revealed these fine
I think there has been a wave of follow-up
Most recently a group of economist
At Cleveland fed
Tried to calculate where you should go live
Depending on what you do
And what they found is that
If you do not have to be in a superstar City to do your job
Probably should not go
Do a superstar set
And so the question that started this entire up
How do cities become over rate
We put that directly to David daughter
Depends for whom
They're overrated for
Adults at college tours
They're probably not overrated
For how to get your
David says
That means cities are overrated
Protest about one in every three work
For about a third of the country
Cities are now
Allowed
But they're still the other 2/3
At the moment
There's a lot of opportunity for
You know skill specialized creative work
In dense urban areas that are just not yet nearly as available
In Hot Springs Arkansas although I'm sure Hot Springs Arkansas author Whoppers Mini
Wonderful things are not available in New York
9 golf courses 11 Lake water as
Charette
The driven snow will a 2 + 1
Dennis Simpson
To listen to We started this whole thing by claiming cities are overrated
We called him back
And we explained
Basically he was right
If you don't have a diploma or some specialized
In-demand skill set
Cities are not the place
I'm actually kind of living that process just a minute
Simpson though
Cities probably are not
Overrated
For him personally
Because what dentist does for a living
Is run a tech
In your line of business like
Will it come into the city make a lot of sense
When do you make a lot of money
Oh yeah yeah yeah no question I do I've never argued that point
Nm4
15 years I had like the third largest IT company in Little Rock
And my joke was I had 16 employees and 17 headache
I didn't miss
Any part of that
No part of that whatsoever do I miss
We cannot commit
You just doesn't like C
He wants something as he puts it holistic
Holistic is getting up in the morning
Walking outside and seeing the bald eagle in the tree literally 15 feet from my dick
There are bald eagle sightings in New York City
Although
We looked it up in the last story we could find about
A sighting was
Two thousand
Lowe's in Staten Island
When a bunny has a brand-new newsletter if you are not
And in fact Gregory goralski is the brains behind the newsletter Greg
Becomes what once a week comes once a week
It's usually about some big thing in the news or some big economic idea
You should totally subscribe npr.org
Slash Planet Money
Newsletter
Play show with Bruce by Sally Helm Alex goldmark is Planet Money supervising producer and Bryant order status
If you want to support Planet Money
One way is to leave us a rating or review in your podcast app
I'm Greg Rutkowski
And I'm alone
This is NPR
Thanks for listening